There we go.
Hello, everyone and welcome to handmade hero show.
Rico to complete game live on Twitch right before.
All of our very eyes, we are in the middle of doing sort of our own
renderer, which is kind of awesome.
We're basically implementing essentially what a GPU does.
We are implementing that ourselves so that we can see how it all
works.
And I think, one of the things that's been kind of surprising, is it?
Hasn't taken us very long.
Like, you know, it's kind of thinking the back of my head like, oh,
we're going to have to implement, this will render.
And, you know, I mean, I hadn't done much in the way of software
rasterizing in a long time and I was kind of like, wow.
All right, that's going to be a major undertaking.
It turns out like we just kind of blew through a bunch of it and it
was like you know, a couple days and we had all of the sort of
primitive stuff working and it was just weird.
So I hope it continues to go that way.
It was a little surprising but that's how it is.
So we're going to go ahead and continue with that today.
Before I begin, let me remind everyone.
That we are on day 95 today.
So if you are someone who has pre-ordered the game at handmade hero
dot-org and you would like to download the source code so that you'll
be where I am today.
Get that from the link that you got in your email and unpacked a 94
source code into a directory.
That is what I'm starting with today.
And so you will be right with me.
If you would like to be now where we left off, we just did a brief
aside yesterday on gamma correction at the behest of one Chun.
And so basically, what we did is we
He added some gamma correction to our little texture map, texture
mapping routine which allows us to draw a little rotated and scaled
versions of any of our Sprites that we want to.
And so, you know, we kind of wrap that up to some degree.
Now, someone was asking on the pre stream a little bit and I haven't
read, they were referring to something that they posted on the forums
to.
I haven't had a chance to read yet.
I will absolutely read it.
I pretty much read everything on there, you know, sometimes it takes
me to the weekend have time to do so but I always
Go through it all, and they were asking about how the gamma interacts
with premultiplied Alpha and if you take a look at the way that we
were doing things, right, where we did our srgb to linear stuff.
So rgb2 linear.
So it was sorry.
Srgb, 252 linear.
If you took a look at the way we were doing stuff, right?
What we were doing is we were kind of lofting hour.
Our values up and we were doing all of our math and making sure that
we did all of our math in s RGB 255, 255 space, and all these sorts of
stuff.
But there's one thing that we didn't talk about and it's a good thing
to mention, which is that, if you are doing premultiplied Alpha,
Then you kind of have this problem of when exactly do you pre multiply
the alpha, right?
Because this srgb to linear thing it seems like you probably want to
Multiply the alpha you know you want to make sure that when you when
you do your Alpha premultiplication you're doing that.
Presumably.
You want to do that in a linear space, right?
So that you have already converted things out of srgb.
When you're doing your Alpha pre-multiply, you do the pre multiply,
then you do the blend and then, you know, etc, etc.
So it's kind of one of those things where I believe and we didn't
meticulously inspect this.
But I believe we're essentially doing what I would consider to be.
The most correct thing right here.
I believe and it would be nice to have a real rendering Authority.
Take a look at this and verify that that's correct because I'm
certainly not that guy but I believe we're basically doing it as
correct as you might possibly be able to do it but when we kind of
move past what we're doing right now and try to optimize this a little
bit, one of the things that often comes up is how do you deal with?
Storing your your your Alpha values.
Sorry.
How do you deal with storing?
Your color values so that you can store them already pre multiplied,
you know, do you pre multiply first and then convert, you know, du du
pre multiply and linear space.
And then store, srgb and whatever.
And the reason for that is, you know, maybe we don't want to have to
do the alpha pre multiplication in here and so on and so forth.
So there's a bunch of issues in there and I'd rather just tackle those
when we get to them because right now I believe we're doing.
Things correctly.
Where, you know, I have to think about it.
But basically what we're doing right is we're sampling from a texture
which is not premultiplied Alpha.
So it's got the actual srgb values in there and the actual Alpha value
that was using Photoshop.
We're converting out to linear, right?
We are then blending in, you know, non P multiplied, space linearly
right?
And and then we are, we are doing the alpha composite after the fact
now.
The problem I guess now that I think about it, the problem with that
is this by linear blend might actually want to be in premultiplied
Alpha, right?
Because the I think the bi-linear blend like we were talking about
before when you're doing the larps doing larps want to have the
premium the alpha, pre multiplied into them already.
And so if we wanted to make this a little more correct, I suspect what
we would want.
Want to do is take the alpha out of these guys and pre multiply it in
right here after the gamma correction, if that makes sense.
So, it would be something along the lines of, you know, for each of
these textiles because, because we've kind of got it over.
Let's see where we're doing that here.
Let's see.
So, when we load this in, we've got color a times color are times
Texel are
Unless we just okay.
Is it this right here?
RSA know.
So this is did we remove something?
So, this might not be correct.
We may have forgotten something yesterday, because now that I'm
starting to go through it with a fine-tooth comb here.
I'm looking at this.
Where are we actually doing our Alpha multiplied, right?
Because I don't, I don't see it Texel a
I don't see our multiply right.
So I think we're I think it's missing.
Do you guys feel the same way?
I feel like we had it in here and I removed it accidentally.
When we were doing this, I feel like it should be multiplied in here,
right?
And let's take a look.
Let's see about the the the change in appearance that we get from
this.
Let me let me make our little.
We do have a little bit of a of an issue with our Arts tree being
Easy psychedelic right now, which is not going to be conducive for us,
testing some stuff and debugging.
So let's, let's put a little bit of a.
Let's calm down.
If you will this this sort of trippy psychedelic thing that's
happening here with our tree, so that we can concentrate on on.
Just what's happening with the actual renderer?
That seems like probably a good idea to say the least.
So, okay, so if we take a look at what's going on there,
See if we can perceive any difference here as well because again, this
will only really be in the edges for the most part.
So let's take a look.
So, if I come in here and I say, all right, at the very least, this,
we're not doing the pre multiply properly.
So we want, you know, our colors to be pre multiplied here.
We just see what happens there.
So, there we go.
That would be if we, if we actually multiply it in the alpha.
Now it's almost impossible to really see any difference there.
This is an again, this is why I say a lot of times unfortunately, a
lot of this stuff is kind of more about the thief.
Article correctness than actually seeing artifacts on the screen
because sometimes it's almost impossible to actually perceive that
difference.
But yes.
Oh, yeah, can I see that?
Not really.
Yeah, that's that's just not.
That's just not something you can really see.
I know you and if I can't see it, you guys definitely can't see it
because it's going to be kind of blurred out on, on the, on the
stream.
So, yeah, I would say, first of all, I feel like our textiles are not
pre multiply properly here because we are not storing them,
premultiplied was my understanding.
Now, maybe I'm wrong about that.
Let's go.
Let me go look to see.
Maybe we did actually do that.
Like I said,
Been a long time.
So maybe in are loaded bitmap routine.
We are storing them, premultiplied already in which case that is where
that's coming from.
So debug load bitmap.
Are we pre multiplying the alpha in here, right?
Okay, so we are so that's the answer.
The answer is that.
We are storing these guys pretty multiply it already and that's where
that goes.
So yeah if you think about what's happening there, then we are not
doing the most correct thing, right?
Because
Cuz what happens here and at least again, most correct thing.
I'm just saying this from my own personal opinion of the read on it,
you know, like I said you probably want to ask more of rendering
expert.
But what's Happening Here is we're turning our textiles from srgb to
linear but they've already been pre multiplied by the alpha out here.
Right?
And so technically we're not at the edges where we have partial Alpha.
We're not actually getting back the correct srgb values because we're
getting back the srgb values.
They've already been pre multiplied and they were pre multiplied in
srgb space which isn't necessarily what we want, right?
And so, one way that we could sort of, look at handling this, right?
If we wanted to be more correct, what we could do here is we could
say, all right, let's not do that.
So when we load our bitmaps, let's not pre multiply the alpha at.
All right?
Let's not do that.
So if I do that, now obviously we're going to ruin everything else on
the screen that's being blit.
Certainly
So that's a little bit of a problem but here we go.
We start that.
So everything but our tree will be wrong, which is, you know, not the
best thing.
But now in this case, when we are loading our bitmaps, they are
correctly, not pre multiply, right?
And if they're not be multiplied, then what I was saying, now becomes
the correct thing to do, which is to say that when we do these and we
load them and convert them into linear space, then we can do our our
Alpha multiplied.
So that's basically going to be like
The RGB of the guy is going to be multiplied times.
The a right, we convert all these guys from pre multiplied from, non P
multiplied, to pre multiplied.
So convert to premultiplied Alpha here, then the blend will happen
correctly because we are in pre-multiplied space, which is where we
want to do the Blends, so that happens properly.
And then we can do, I believe the rest of this the way that we would
want to do it now,
Now we do have, I guess one other problem, which is thinking about it,
when we output, we're going to want to Output our Alpha, our color
values, want to be not pre multiplied at this point.
So we've got kind of a little
Work to do there, but I believe that that would actually be the
correct thing to be doing there.
If I'm not very much an error, which I might actually be, but I think
that's correct.
Now again it's really you just can't see the difference to allow these
things.
There really isn't any thing to see there, but I believe that would be
more correct, right?
Because now we're converting from srgb to linear.
Then we're pre-multiplying then we're doing the lerp.
Then we're doing the blend.
And that is, I believe actually correct.
Now, the only thing that I was saying that we aren't quite thinking
about yet is what happens on repeated Blends.
So if I'm, you know, kind of repeatedly blending to the screen, like,
when we were producing our ground chunks, for example, where there's
lots of slats that are layered on top of each other.
I have to think about what happens there because I don't know, I don't
think there's anything in particular, we have to
Concerned about with that.
It seems like it'd be correct but the Final Ground Splat I guess it
doesn't really have the Final Ground spot doesn't really have any
transparent Parts but if the grep Final Ground spot had transparent
Parts.
One of the problems that I think we would have right, is the RGB
values in it?
Are we were, we were outputting them as if the whole thing was pre
multiplied.
So that means that the values are actually P multiplied by the
so, which is not what we would have wanted to have happen, right?
So we'd have to kind of think about that, right?
We'd have to kind of think through what that actually means.
So it seems like you're kind of in this nasty situation where you
really want your stuff to all be, premultiplied Alpha because you're
constantly you constantly be fighting this thing of like storing.
You know, incrementally storing to the three-month limit.
Let's I don't know.
Think it through on the white on the Blackboard because to be honest
with you I don't even know really what the correct answer there would
be right because that's pretty complicated and you don't actually do
this in Hardware.
You typically store the things already pre multiplied, that's just how
that works.
All right.
So let's think about this if we were going to do this right?
Then, you know, we've got srgb in a buffer, right?
And we've got a so those are coming in and you know, I don't know will
cause we'll call this color and Alpha or something like that, right?
So this is what comes from the artist.
Yeah.
Now we know that we can do everything properly here if we do it in
light linear space which we've already talked about this, what we
talked about yesterday.
So what we want to do is grab this C value, right?
And we want to take the C value and turn it.
Into linear, right?
So we can do that by, let's say this is C and srgb.
So then we have a c in in linear space, right?
So, the sea and linear space, we can now do anything we want with, but
we already know that our Alpha values don't actually work properly if
we use lerp right without pre multiplying them.
So we need to pre multiply it if we want to go through the lerp
function, right?
So, in order to do that, what we have to do is we have to do CL x a
right?
And we would then have that to work against, you know, some
Um destination.
So we would be producing CL times a and then eventually we would be
writing that you know into a buffer, right?
And that buffer now actually would have effectively premultiplied
Alpha in the buffer, right?
So if we wanted to, then use it in the same context as one of these
artists applied ones, we pretty much would have to multiply by the
inverse of the alpha value in order to
To restore this, right?
I mean because we're producing this because in order to go through
lerp we have to do that.
So if we wanted to put it back into this format, right, there's really
not much we could do about that.
Like, you know, we don't really have the option, I don't think of
doing anything else, they're right?
And that's the dicey proposition because multiplying by the, inverse
of the alpha, the alpha could be 0, right?
And so one over
Zero.
Right is not a value that you want to start having in your code
because then you have to like special case that do all sorts of
things.
So I feel like, we just probably don't want to go this route, right?
We want to store our values premultiplied if we can
So what we could potentially do, I have to think about this but what
we could do is say well what we want to have happen here is we maybe
want to have the linear value from our colors, right?
We want to say if we were to take the value as linear, then multiply
by the alpha, then project it back to srgb.
We'd store that value.
So that when we pull it out, it's linear again.
Right, it's the right thing.
It's the it's a times C linear, right?
Instead of a times c s projected to linear, right?
So we could, you know, if you believe what I just said there, which
you know, like I said, I'm not really rendering guy so I don't like
the state these things, very authoritatively.
Maybe, you know, we can only go by what we can determine on the
Whiteboard and like I said, a lot of these things.
It's hard to see the artifacts so we can't really guide
Can't really use what it looks like as a guide.
We'd have to start thinking about it more mathematically and actually
maybe we could write some little tests that would draw things and test
the values that come out versus some things, we think should happen,
you know, that sort of thing.
But we
It really make much in the way of decisions about whether it's
important for the game because they really just always look the same
some level.
So what we could do is say, alright, let's store the, the
premultiplied alpha values.
But instead of
Storing them the way we were where we multiplied by the alpha value.
Maybe what we do here is we do this sort of lofting where we do the
srgb to linear in here, right?
So we say, alright, let's let's go ahead and read in whatever this the
bitmaps Texel the Texel value is there, right?
Let's go ahead and read that in like, we were reading in the other
stuff and, and where we've got, you know, are red.
The top are green
so, and our blue here like so,
And Alpha, let's read that in and then let's Loft it up.
Just like we were doing before.
So you know, take that textile and turn it into, you know, a textile
that that's that's linear right?
And once we do that, then maybe we say all right, at that point we
take the textile and we multiply the textiles RGB right by it's a.
So we do the pre multiplication for Alpha and then before we store it.
We project it right?
Right on back, right?
We do the linear 12s RGB 255 in there, and then when we store it,
we're storing a value that we know when we pull out the value again,
it's going to give us the correct, premultiplied value in that linear
space, right?
Hopefully, that makes some sense.
I don't know if that made sense to you guys, but hopefully that makes
some sense.
And then we kill this premultiplied Alpha here because we just assume
that they're always in Primo.
It applied Alpha all the time.
Anyway, right.
RGB is not a member.
What
Serious.
Are you serious?
Well, you know it's true, it's not a member.
Well let's let's fix that, I guess.
So, here's our Union.
So I guess what we'd do is we'd say alright let's go ahead and have an
RGB in a relay in there.
Like so I guess although well this a and this, a will collide.
So I guess technically for pushing it a little bit here.
We do this, right?
It's a little gross, it's true but there we go.
So yeah, so that when we load now we should probably verify did a
bunch of stuff there but
That when we load now.
Well, it doesn't look like that.
Quite did what I was hoping.
After that, that looks like the background there is still.
So I guess the, the other thing that I have to think about there is
what that yeah.
So
Now, that I think about it.
That's fine for our routines that are actually gamma aware, but our
routines that aren't gamma where are going to cause a problem now,
right?
Because they don't actually do the conversion back afterwards.
So, you know, this is now going to be a value that produces a blend.
That's kind of a little bit unusual, right?
So we have to we'd have to go and and modify our other routines to be
aware of that which is fine because they're all, we're all going to
To doing all this stuff through that main path.
Anyway, so I suppose that's fine.
We could just say, all right in our drawbitmap call that we have that,
you know, this one right here, we could do that, that that conversion,
that handling as well, right?
That's not that big of a deal.
All we would really have to do is say, all right, when we load the
srgb is here, we could just we could just upconvert them, right?
So yeah.
So
Let's do that, that's not that huge of a deal, right?
And that way will at least be uniform in both past.
I guess the other thing we could do is just ignore it for now.
And until we actually have everything going through drawbitmap slowly,
which I guess is the other thing we could do.
Mmm-hmm.
I think I'm going to just poured it for now.
I think that's the easier thing to do.
So we don't have to get too ahead of ourselves.
So yeah, so alright, what we would do to me
Well we would need to do here is we need to again, load the textiles,
just the way that we have been doing it before, right?
So, we've got all of these guys here and that c Alpha is going to have
to happen down here somewhere, right?
So Texel RGB is going to have to multiply it by C Alpha outside there.
Now so if I go ahead and take this guy here, right, and I've got all
of these guys, real 52, that loops.
Do not real pretty too.
Like so that's their get.
My, our Mig might be and the a value here this.
So we've got all those in the Texel.
I do the srgb to linear of that Texel as always.
So the grab the textile out, we do the srgb to linear we multiply by
the alpha.
And we produce also the
The textile a here.
We don't need to do that / 255 because that's already baked into this
guy now.
um, and
when we, when we compute this, we gotta multiply the RSA by the clf as
well.
So that's fine.
We then go ahead and read out that destination.
The destination.
We would also like to up convert, right?
Because
We said we're doing the frame buffer, that way.
So are dest our desks here whatever we call that D.
That's going to be another one of these reads off we go.
so,
There's our Alpha goes at the end, so there's our g b and a, so, the
RGB and a values, grab those art out, we can then convert that text as
well.
So D equals srgb to linear D, so then we can do everything.
Like we were going to do with the blend.
We do we have checked that math, rarest course.
We're changing the math.
Now then we compute, what we would actually want to do in terms of
Of putting it back.
And in this case, what we really want to do is actually just make this
beep, sort of what we're going to write.
So this is our result right?
In our result, is going to be all these values when you put them in a
vector.
So I can on map them, there's our in.
So
Yeah.
Oops, got my equals and so that that should do it, right?
And then we can just take result and do linear to srgb on it before
writing it out.
And I think that converts that routine if I haven't made some
egregious errors in their into something that will actually write got
to actually use the values that we said we were going.
Hughes.
There's the text will read, text will read Texel.
Green Texel blue, and the RSA RDA.
Those sorts of guys are all good.
What is the problem here?
Oh, that's not dust.
It's Dee.
RDA is Undeclared RDA, in this case is just the destination, a right?
It doesn't have anything special happening to it.
RSA is that reversed?
RSA there.
I'm sorry.
RSA is just the the compounded one.
And then RDA did I do?
What did I do there?
RSA.
Okay that was a typo.
Sorry RSA.
So this should be D A and B should be ta and RSA stays what it was.
So
When we are doing this, we multiply all of these guys out.
So technically RSA, we can just actually do the full multiply here,
right?
Because these are both be multiplied by the same thing.
So we can actually just say textile x, c Alpha and then RSA, right is
is just the same value.
RSA is just Texel that a right.
So, I think that should pretty much do it.
And does that jive with what we're doing up here as well?
I guess we are.
Still doing it here for no apparent reason.
Yeah, no apparent reason whatsoever.
And so really, we can, we can collapse these to do the same stuff and
again, they will be the same eventually, we'll probably have all this
stuff collapse down.
Anyway but you know, for the time being I guess we will kind of avoid
doing that.
So in virus a will leave already a, we'll get rid of we'll just make
this desk dot a and we'll make this desk today and then that RSA is
again just going to be Texel dot, a tech, slow day.
Like so-and-so.
Textile dot a.
Now needs to actually have this done to it, but so does this color a
have happened to have to do the multiplication there.
So, we're just going to do again, that, that exact same thing.
So Texel X, the x equals x tilde
Right.
I'm sorry colored a day.
There we go.
So yeah, I believe that does the same thing on both paths right there.
We've got that c Alpha right looks about right?
The RSA has to be colored Ade.
Now RSA has to be color dot a, I'm sorry, textile dot a, that was a
steak there Texel daughter.
Yeah, so let's see.
See how that's looking whether that's a total nightmare or not.
We should probably stop generating the grant.
Oh dear.
Well, it did not go.
Well, we can say that obviously we're not quite
You gotta love it when you get a full blank screen, right?
You just, you just tweak a few things and all of a sudden, you've got
an entirely blank screen to contend with.
Oh, okay.
No, we're good.
Never mind.
It's just because now everything so much slower, because we have this
ridiculously slow path, it just takes forever to draw all the ground
chunks, so that's fine.
Yeah, no big deal.
And so now you can see we've restored everything back.
Our compositing of the background looks proper and our tree is still
our tree nothing particularly weird happening there.
But yeah.
So so alright I think we're getting a little closer just in terms of
stuff, but now we're super slow, because all of our stuff is
Really slow.
And so, you know, one thing we probably should have to start thinking
about this point is how we're going to make sure our software renderer
runs.
They quickly.
Now, of course, at this point, it may actually be true that that we
doing.
That if we actually asked for compiling with optimizations on, we
would get a pretty good boost here because we're not actually asking
for that at all.
So, let me see, I've got my Saudi there.
Let me let me switch it to 0-2 and see what the difference is.
Because now we've actually got routines that it matters how fast
they're like, wow, what a difference that is.
Look at how fast that runs with optimizations on, right versus how
fast it runs with optimizations off.
Okay, that's
That was on here is off.
But it's it's incredibly slower and and that's because we're actually
doing a bunch of intensive code there.
And so, if the optimizer actually, you know, does some, even just
basic things to, it's probably makes a huge difference.
I mean, look at this, it's not even up yet.
After all this time, kind of ridiculous, right?
And you can see the frame rate is atrocious.
And so, the difference between compiling and debug mode and compiling
an optimization mode.
When you have a situation like this, where
You're manually doing all of these operations to all the pixels on the
screen all the time, debug versus non debug makes a pretty tremendous
difference as you can see.
So you will have to take some steps, probably to make sure that we put
ourselves in a position where we can deal with that relatively.
Well, meaning, we'll have to start making some concessions that allow
us to compile some stuff in, in optimized land as opposed to
non-optimized land.
While not having to compile everything there.
So what we'll probably do is split our build into two files for the
handmade that sleepy.
One of the files will be the renderer pixel routines, which will get
optimizations turned on.
And the rest, won't have it turned on in our normal build so that we
can still have to bugging everywhere else.
If that makes sense, it's kind of annoying.
But unfortunately, the pragma optimize directives, don't seem to
usually give you what you need to turn on heavy optimization in just
one little chunk and so there's really not a lot of ways to deal with
that other than splitting out the optimize routines into one file.
But anyway,
So let's take a look at that.
Again just to just to sort of wrap that up.
So what we're doing here, right?
Is in our draw a rectangle slowly.
We're assuming now that we've stored, our values pre multiplied by the
alpha value, right?
But we've pretty multiplied it in linear space and then convert it
back to srgb.
So this conversion is converting a value that's already in,
premultiplied Alpha in.
That's been baked in srgb back into
Linear where we can do our lips with.
Premultiplied Alpha in there, right?
We then do all of our stuff and then we store it back still
premultiplied, right?
Although it looks like correct me if I'm wrong here but we took care
of know we did.
So that's fine.
The RGB still got to be multiplied there, right?
The color a, we took care of out here, but we didn't take care of the
rest of it, right?
So that's all people.
That's all fine.
That P multiplied is fine.
We could also save a little work here if you think about it, we
We really could just multiply have have pre multiplied color first and
then just done the Straight Ahead multiply, right?
That's something to think about.
Like, for example, this right here could just be
Best.
That would allow us to not have to do that extra multiply of the a
every time because what we would do is we just out here, we'd take
color and pre multiply it first, right?
So we do like pre multiply
Color.
Up front and so we just do.
That right.
And so,
Probably worth doing in my opinion because if you pre multiply the
color up front, then that means that you save One X, the alpha every
time because now you just multiply by the are, which already has color
a multiplied in and so you don't have to both X the A, and by the are
so that just sets us up for, you know, a better time when we actually
go to do the optimization there.
So that seems reasonable right.
Okay.
So yeah, that's all seems pretty good.
We have about 20 minutes left, I'm not sure I want to start doing the
thing that I was going to do.
Just because I took a bunch of time kind of going through that that
premultiplied Alpha stuff.
But yeah.
So let's just continue down here.
So we grabbed our values at which now are already pre multiplied.
When we do our conversion up, we do our lips which should work because
we're in premultiplied space.
Hopefully, that's the goal.
Anyway, we then multiply by our
Modulation color which is basically the color that we use to tint
things here.
Like r g b values that you know we went want to change and the alpha
value which allows us to trains change how transparent this thing is
as a whole we read out whatever is in the current destination and we
assume that that was in srgb as well because you know, we are going to
store it that way.
So we convert that up, we compute the inverse of the alpha.
That's now had both the textiles Alpha and the color is Alpha
multiplied together in there.
Are we do the blend in linear space, right?
We then convert from our linear space, premultiplied back into the
frame buffer.
And we output, right?
So
I believe that is a pretty correct math pipeline but I could be
missing something still, right?
So if there is somebody out there, who's a serious render fellow?
Who sees anything missing?
I would highly appreciate you taking the time to let us know, but
that's seems roughly, right?
Seems roughly, right?
And like I said, one of the big problems with stuff like this is, you
know, it would be nice if we could just run it and see when it was
wrong but we're not going to really have that.
You know, only really gross errors are often going to show up that
way.
And so what we could do down the line when we're kind of done with the
renderer stuff a little bit is we could make some tests if we can
think of any good test to do that would sort of try to suss out.
Any places where we may be doing our conversions wrong, that might be
something we could, we could look at.
All right.
All right, so let's just do a little bit of cleanup then since we have
15 minutes to go, I think probably rather than start something new
what I'd like to do is just clean up a few things.
So if you remember correctly, in our render group, right?
I had said remove the header and removing the header is a good idea.
I think removing the header is something we should probably do.
So, if you remember, we were doing this is we had a buffer where we
would put in all of the things that we wanted to send to the renderer
but each one of them had to have this render group entry header thing
and that's a little error-prone and there's really no reason to do it.
I just kind of did it because we were, you know, that was how it shook
out when we typed it.
But we don't really need that because what we can do instead is
You can just have our stream encode and decode here.
When we push things on to the firm, when we pull them off, we can just
have that know that it looks for a tight first, right?
Really, really straightforward.
So what I would suggest that we do,
Is again, just we go ahead and do that.
So we take a look in here where we're actually pushing stuff on.
First of all, when we push render elements on there and all we have to
do is say, whatever the size is that the person is trying to push on.
Let's just go ahead and increase that size by.
However big the header is right that way when we push it on there we
will sort of get the header right first and then we will also
Get space for for the rest of the thing, right?
And so we can go ahead and set the header and set its type in the
buffer and again, I'm just doing right.
I'm just saying, well, we've got sort of this this buffer here, right?
And what we were doing before is we were pushing something onto it,
right?
That's a took this much size and we knew that the first thing of it
was this header, right?
And so, we would return it and then the caller would go.
Okay, thanks for this.
This header piece, I'm going to set that.
In the thing, right?
It was looking at this guy and what I'm saying now is well, let's just
talk about it in terms of doing two sequential pushes.
So when we push it first, we push the header on and then we push the
data on and then the data people never have to care about the fact
that there was a header at.
All right?
So the header is just in, there is a little sort of thing that the
stream control uses to understand what the what the structure looks
like, right?
So here we go, we push on some, the size of what we of what the person
wanted plus the header.
We then say, okay, make sure we've got enough room for assuming we do.
Now, we find out where the header is by looking at where the push
lever base, is we go ahead and set that type and then we take the
result.
What we're going to return is just going to be the header plus 1,
right?
It's just going to be one like the the next bite after the header is
full-size.
Because remember, in See, it'll do the pointer arithmetic.
Check for us if we have a sized pointer.
So header plus, 1 is whatever.
The byte location is of header, plus the size of the header, right?
And so, you know, we end up again in that situation to make that a
little clearer though.
I could also alternatively write it this way.
So you can see right if I do this,
That's saying like, Okay, take whatever header is and move.
However, many bytes header is size-wise, right?
And off you go.
So then, the headers type is set correctly.
These guys all, get back the correct thing.
So all we would have to fix then I think is this part right here,
which is after we grab that header out, right?
What we want to do is instead of these guys then casting using that
header as a cast their which is not what we want to do, right?
What we'd rather do is
Have them just kind of look at the data which will prepare the pointer
for them to point to the correct place which is right after the
header.
Right?
And so what we'll do is we read the header out and then we say, okay
after the header we've also got a data pointer and that is literally
exactly the same thing that it was before, right?
Like so, so there's our data pointer.
There we go.
And what does this want to do?
Oh, this is returning.
A render group entry header that is not to return to return a void
star.
Because now, it is not turning the header, it's returning that data
corner and so we should probably step through that, make sure it
works, but we could just say, let's go for it now.
Okay, of course not.
So let's go ahead and and step through that and to take a look at how
that's actually working and, and debug it.
So,
I believe the first thing we typically push on as a clear, right?
So let's take a look at how the clear works.
So we come in here and we have the size that the the clear is actually
going to take, right?
This is the render entry clear, I guess structure which is 60 we want
to add
The size of the header, which is 4, bytes long.
So there we go.
We see if we can get that and we can.
So we then grab a pointer to the header, which is going to be the
first thing in the buffer.
We then set the type, which of course is still clear.
It happened to already be zero, so it didn't really change it there.
But then we want to make our result pointer.
We want our result pointer to be 4, bytes after the header.
So hopefully we should see that happen here, which is 5 C, right?
So that's, that's
that's what we wanted to see.
Because now we should be able to see care star results - Kara star.
Header should give us the size of the header right for B, which is
good.
Then we increment everything forward.
So that's all good.
And so I think that's probably working correctly.
What I suspect is not working correctly.
Now that I think about it is we didn't Advance the pointer properly.
I kind of forgot about that.
So when we do our Base address plus equal size of Entry.
Here, we forgot.
I didn't actually increment our Base address for having read the
header, right?
So the Base address here, just needs to be incremented to account for
the header size.
That's probably all that we did not do.
So that's probably it again that just cleans it up a little bit and
makes it.
So that all the code that uses that doesn't have to be aware of any of
that stuff which is nice.
And in man.
Yeah, we sure slow and slow down our bitmap drawing.
But you know what you going to do?
We will have to.
We'll have to take some steps to speed that up pretty soon or we can
start compiling it with optimizations on, but when you start complying
with that positions on it makes it a lot harder to debug stuff.
So that becomes a little bit of an issue.
So anyway, especially for a streamer.
I'm trying to show things we in the debugger, makes it pretty hard
because the instruction pointer tends to jump around and it's just a
little more confusing.
So,
That is in the entirety of that.
Trying to think if there's anything else in particular that I wanted
to clean up in here.
That's a small-scale thing.
That doesn't remove.
That doesn't introduce anything.
New know why we need that comment is kind of useless.
So I think, yeah, I think this is all fine here.
I don't see anything else that needs to happen.
We've got all of our debug code.
We've got this.
Yeah, yeah.
So that's all good.
So I think we're pretty good for right now.
Trying to think of what else.
I might be able to do that.
That wouldn't be, you know, sort of starting something that we can't
really get at all into
We don't really have much on the list here that isn't something that
we would have to start.
I guess what I could do.
Is start doing that.
Pull out so that we can compile those routines.
Like what I could do is say, all right there is handmade optimized dot
CPP or something like this.
You know something II.
Don't know where we are going to stick routines like this one.
Like so.
And we could do that, of course, it's kind of a little nasty because
it's hard for these guys to properly, see all the rest of the things
that we want them to see.
So typically, you don't really want to do this.
Pull out with the optimizations until you actually have these
optimized in sort of a, at anaesthetic more of an assembly level.
Because you run into the situation where, like, okay, if I want to
still use you,
Rebuild that I want to pull these out so that they get up my
separately.
You know, I have to start segregating my inline functions that they
might use right in other things like that which is just kind of
annoying and I don't really like to do it so maybe that's not the best
idea.
I'm not sure what to give you a little bit of perspective on why this
is a problem, right?
There is a way if I wanted to.
I guess this is probably what I could do with rest of the script
stream.
Let me let me not.
Not introduce that file just yet.
There we go.
Okay, let me delete handmade optimized before I go down that that
path.
So, the optimization pragma, right?
I'll show you a couple different things here.
So there is in Visual Studio.
I mean, starting visual C++ in the compiler, there is a way to bracket
things with some optimization directives, right?
So, you can say optimization list on and off and there's like, Global
optimizations shorter, fastest machine code, blah blah blah, right?
But I don't actually know if it will fully optimized stuff to the
We would want it to just by using these with on, I know with off.
You can shut off a lot of things.
I don't know if on will actually turn on all the stuff that we might
want, we could try, but I don't actually know, right?
And furthermore, I'm not sure how you can push, so I guess when you
use the so.
So if you take a look at what this even says here, it suggests that it
won't do that at all right?
When you use the on parameter, it resets the
The optimizations to those, you have specified with the / 0 compiler
option, right?
But oh well, okay, but that's only if the string is null.
So maybe this will work, maybe this will work.
If you can get away with it it would be nice.
Let's try it, who knows?
Because if we could do that, that'd be nice.
Then we wouldn't have to ever worry about splitting the stuff out.
Though we may eventually want to do that anyway but that's kind of a
kind of separate issue.
So let's see if we can get this to actually optimize by just telling
it to turn on everything, right?
So if I want to, I'm not optimistic.
I will tell you that but we'll give it a shot.
So if I tell it, I want to optimize
This routine and and we'll say Global optimizations on, I guess.
Do you have anything else?
There's 20, more of the funds.
So Global optimizations, I think is the only thing shorter fast
sequences machine code.
So I guess I want fast sequences machine code for now.
And yeah.
And so then after we're done with that, after draw a rectangle slowly,
I just want to put in a pragma that.
Also, you can well, I guess I want it sort of around both this and
drawbitmap.
So let me grab drawbitmap and stick that in there as well.
So it said that if I used it with nothing, it would just revert to the
the old optimization settings.
So, I don't know if that actually optimized.
I'm doubting it did, and it certainly doesn't look like it, right?
This is nowhere near.
This is nowhere near the speed that we were getting before.
So, yeah, that really does not seem to do what we needed to do, right?
As far as I can tell.
Anyway, we got pragma optimize GT on and it really didn't optimize our
drawbitmap into anything noteworthy.
I could check and double-check right.
Like turn on visual C Optimizer for just one function.
And and see if anybody has has any information about that.
Let's see here.
There's two optimization frequence, fishes.
To my station.
Decal, specs Now, sort of, let's pull this out a little bit, so we can
read it.
So, let's see on a function, as the ideal for those workers, are
Arabs, Christians when it conforms compiled with optimization, okay?
That's not what we really wanted to hear what we want to do is just
set one of them to be on for more.
Yeah let's see.
This does not.
This is not helpful.
Because most of the time they're thinking disabled optimizations, but
we want to do is enable optimizations.
I guess we could wrap everything else in in a pragma optimize off, but
that doesn't seem like such a good idea.
I don't know, but maybe we could try it.
This is something I've never done before.
So, I don't know.
Maybe, we'll try it.
Rapping just that in a pragma optimize on, doesn't work, maybe
wrapping everything else in a pragma, optimize off.
Would and so, maybe we do this, right?
So we say, pragma on pragma off, like so.
And then we literally in our handmade dot CPP at the very top of the
file.
Return all the optimizations off and then at the bottom of the file,
well, at the bottom file, we don't do anything.
What will that do?
I don't know.
So off the bat, it should do nothing because we don't have any
optimizations enabled so we're in slow mode and so that's fine.
But then if I go into our build and turn optimizations on, what
happens?
I have no idea.
Still totally unoptimized it would appear.
Right.
Like that's not at all, helping us.
Yeah.
Hmm.
I feel like that should have worked though, right?
So I wonder if there's more to it.
I wonder if it's because inline functions that, you know, like perhaps
inline functions can't be optimized if they're in the optimized off or
whatever.
I'm not sure, but for whatever reason, it looks like we're not going
to be able to do that.
So we'll give up.
It's not absolutely essential what it
This will have to maybe do some optimization earlier rather than later
so that we can still compile with optimizations off and be able to
step through code and sort of show, you know, do that illustrative
stuff.
Because the reason that I'm spending so much time differing about this
is because if I compile with optimizations on all the time, I just
want to show you what it looks like.
When you sort of start stepping through like you see what's happening
there to see how it's jumping around like that.
You know, it's it's basically because the optimizer has rearranged all
the code and so it's very hard for me to sort of teach on the stream
and show.
Oh, this happened on this happened.
Then, let's look at the values on the stuff.
If the IP is, you know, jumping all around like that to cook to
execute the function.
Right?
So, you know, normally you might just be fine with that, and that's
not really a problem.
So we just compiled with operations on and we'd be done, but
unfortunately, that's not probably realistic.
For handmade hero.
So we will have to do something to sort of make sure that that that
that works out.
And so maybe I will try to split those into two separate files and
compile.
One with the optimizations and we'll just pull out the sorts of stuff
that get needed into handmade optimizations dot h.
You know, like we'd have handmade optimizations optimized dot h, or
whatever.
And that would have the inline functions that we expect to have in
there and then we'd have the other one as well or something like that.
So you know, you can, you can Envision it working relatively cleanly,
so maybe we'll just go ahead and say that.
That's what we're going to have to do.
Maybe I'll do that tomorrow, for example, and, and that'll be our
thing.
All right, so let's take a look at the Q&A because we're about out of
time here.
So, so let's go ahead and go to the Q&A.
If you do have, if you do have questions, please prefix them with Q:
starting now, and I will take a look at them.
Yeah, I really wish there was a way for visual studio.
You can just say, optimize this function, extremely heavily just this
function because that would be all you really want here, right?
And I've encountered that on my own code base as well.
I prefer to compile in debug mode, most of the time because it just
makes it easier to view things in the debugger.
And so I would really like to be able to say, hey, this is a critical
function just just optimize this one.
Please, what?
Pretty awesome, right?
so,
Yeah.
So anyway, does anyone have any questions?
Arbs felled, why can't you compile opengl code to see to make a
software renderer?
I don't think I understand the question.
You are asking, what is opengl code, in this case.
Mr.
Fourth dimension, is it useful to be able to debug with optimizations
on?
Do you think you might be able to show how to do that at some point?
So the first thing you need to do is if you want to, if you want to
debug with optimizations on, you're never going to really get around
the fact that it jumps around like that.
That's just, that's just the nature of the beast.
But what you can do to make life a little easier on yourself is Visual
Studio,
Bug optimizations which I don't remember what the switch is.
It's in here, so it might be that guy right there.
Enhance optimized it bugging.
So I believe this is always off by default and and so I can try to
give an example of why this, this is something you probably would
want, will want to know.
So I'll just show what happens.
So in our build dot bat, right?
We've got that 02 in there.
So, this is an optimized build, it's getting optimized fairly heavily
by the compiler.
If I come in here and start to try and do stuff.
Like let's say, I try to see what Min X is right.
Well, Min X according to it is is undefined.
It has no idea what Min X is now.
It's right there, right?
But it has no idea what it is.
So the reason for that is because the way that the compiler chose to
optimize this code
There's no longer an easy way for it to look up what the value of Min
X is right.
So it just doesn't show it to you, it's like, I don't know, right?
I have no idea.
And so, if you wanted to know what my next was and you're in here,
you'd actually have to go in, and you'd have to go to the disassembly,
right?
And you'd have to actually look to see where it had put it like.
Okay, it's being called in from xmm.
It's putting it into ebx and then some
I'm in X-Men X, should still be there, it looks like.
So if I looked at where ebx was, which is here, this is what that is,
right?
Like, it's like, that's the process you'd be going through which is
really time and efficient and very error-prone, right?
So, one of the things that they added that was a nice feature.
I think in 2013,
Hard to like 2012 or something.
I don't know that they added at one point it was it was not something
you could really do before and they added it at one point.
If we instead go in here and add that zo switch right in theory that
creates a more extensive debug sort of annotation in the pdb file that
goes through your executable if you remember way back from the first
days when we were looking at that stuff, more expensive, annotations.
So sometimes now when you go through here,
Here, the the, the debugger can actually tell you.
Unfortunately, it looks like in this case still can't tell us, right?
So not particularly useful but at least at least it knows about it now
and it's going to tell us that it's not available but so sometimes you
will get more for that.
Like Source offset is probably one you would not have gotten for
example like you can see that you can see it now.
It's 83 I'm I'm going to go ahead and
A so let's say we can see that's 83 here, I'm going to go ahead and
say that probably that was one that if we took the zo out, you
probably wouldn't be able to see, right?
That's just my guess so you can see identify our source offset X is
undefined.
So you know, it gives you something, it allows you to see a bunch of
values that you wouldn't otherwise see, and that's very good.
So, minus z0 is something you probably want to add to the build.
We probably should add it way back in the
But just didn't think of it.
So that helps, but that doesn't change the jumpy around Miss.
And so there's nothing to tell.
I mean, there's nothing about the debugging.
It just means the code was rearranged for more optimal execution,
right?
But and, and, you know, or collapsed away or all are sorts of things
that might have happened during optimization.
So you just have to get used to that and understand.
That's what's that.
You're only getting an approximation.
And you have to kind of drop down to disassembly now and again, and
this is kind of annoying.
Yeah, but this is this is a thing where it's not sure which address
you're actually talking about for debugging, but you can usually do a
reasonable job.
I just stepping and then getting back to the place where you're at.
So you have to kind of look in here.
Sometimes figure out what's going on.
It's kind of annoying.
There's really no tricks to this.
That's just, it's just hard to debug in optimized land.
It's much harder to do that than in debug.
So what I recommend doing by far, is never debug in optimized mode, if
you can avoid it, right?
Always try to debug in debug mode when you can and only divided
optimized code when you have to.
So, you know, that's that's that's what I'd say about that.
But you know, when you are it, inevitably happens because you have a
bug, that only Repros, an optimized mode or it takes too long to run
and debug mode.
So you have to run an optimized mode.
Whatever then that minus z0 is a good thing to know.
Let's see.
Glsl.
Okay, so you were talking about compiling glsl code into a software to
make the software under.
So the answer is glsl has nothing to do with rendering at all.
Really glsl is shading computations.
So the actual entirety of the renderer is not, none of the renderer is
actually in GSL.
Only the shading computations are in there.
Now, granted shading computations have now grown to Encompass, a lot
of things that are render as
Right?
But the whole superstructure the whole part of the renderer that
decides what pixels get filled right and sort of the.
So I guess I should say is let's not use the word.
Renderer glsl is not a rasterizer, right?
It does not have anything to do with figuring out what pixels to
consider.
All it does, is it figures out?
What the inputs, the outputs are, and the inputs are two very
well-defined shading.
Pipelines that basically take buffers in and push but put buffers out,
but there's no pixels involved anywhere in there, right?
And so the superstructure around glsl, which you don't see that's all
implemented on the card or in the driver is the thing that actually
determines.
What pixels are actually getting considered to ever.
One, the glsl code on those pixels, right?
And so that's a very small part of our problem because shading code on
2-D game is very basic.
Usually, there's really just not that much.
Maybe you do some normal map lookups, you know for lighting or
something like this or some other little things in there.
But for the most part, all of software, rendering tends to be in the
rasterizer.
It's figuring out what pixels to fill.
That's the that's the most of the, the 2D rasterizer part.
Things.
Right?
And so glsl doesn't really help us at all right?
We don't really have any glsl is just not really a useful thing if we
wanted to and we for some reason had a bunch of glsl code that we'd
already written that talked about how we were going to do our Shader
computations and we didn't feel like rewriting it in intrinsics in the
compiler we could write a thing that read glsl and outputted
intrinsics that we could then compile that's certainly possible.
It's just it's not really much it.
Really, very little to do with the renderer for a 2-D game.
It's just a very uninteresting part of it, right?
Whereas, you know, maybe in a 3D game, there's a lot more of it
because maybe you've got tessellation shaders in there and geometry
shaders in there and vertex shaders in there, and then the pixel
shaders, which are much more complicated because we're doing all kinds
of crazy stuff in terms of approximating things, and post passes, and
all these sorts of things.
So maybe, you know, that makes some sense would make some sense if
you're doing a software rendered 3D game but even then, I just don't
know that it buys you anything.
Thing, because, who cares?
Glsl is just a programming language, like any other one, why not?
Just write it in the actual language.
They're really, there isn't any, you know, use use for that in some
sense.
Now, if we were going to have a lot of shaders, one reason you might
do that is because you don't want to have to rewrite all that code.
Again when you use when you do Hardware, when you implement in
Hardware, right?
And so it's definitely true that if I thought we were going to have a
ton of shaders then that would be a case where we might want to go.
Alright, let's make sure that we can do this you know have a Common
Language describes both but the way to do that might still not be to
actually look at glsl code as a as a source language and compile it
what you might want to do is just make a little macro language that
would expand to glsl or to your own code and just do it that way.
Like, reading glsl might not be worth your
While to do right?
So yeah so I would just say that that's just not a very interesting
part of this problem.
We're not going to be spending a ton of time running shaders because
they're just not that useful in the kind of game we're talking about
here which is about putting a lot of bitmaps on the screen.
We just won't probably have a ton of Shader code.
It's really the most the smallest part of the rendering process and
the rasterization is the big part.
should the load bitmap function also be optimized after making changes
today to do pre multiply
yeah, I mean probably not because that will probably just get rolled
To whatever prepares our assets.
So I'm thinking that that's probably not that useful.
We don't load very many bitmaps currently so it's probably not taking
hardly any time.
It's the ground chunk preparation and the screen bleeding.
I think that are probably taking all of our time at the moment.
How would something like a dynamic array and this memory system work?
Something that is persistent across frames, but able to change size
holes are not possible in the memory Arenas right now.
So the answer to that is usually like it depends on the circumstance.
If you want a dynamic array you can just do you just have to put a
well I put it this way.
If you end up wanting something that is totally Dynamic, like a
dynamic allocator, then you have to write a dynamic alligator.
Like, that's what Malik and new and all those things are doing under
the hood there, taking large, chunks of memory and a portion them up
and what they do there is if they produce holes, they then later, try
to fill those holes with other allocations that are similarly sized,
right?
So if you really do end up wanting something that's totally Dynamic,
the whole system ends up being cognitively Dynamic, you need a dynamic
allocator and you could write one of those.
They're not particularly hard, right?
But I usually say, why do you need the dynamic array?
Are you sure that that was the best idea, right?
Because most of the time, I find that Dynamic arrays are not such a
good idea.
Usually, you can, you can write it in a way, that's more predictable
because any Dynamic, array opens you up to the
You have memory fragmentation even if you have a dynamic allocator and
it also opens up to other possibilities that aren't so nice such as
unpredictability in terms of when allocations happen.
So I feel like I would I would say you know be sure first of all that
you really want dynamism in your memory allocation that way because
it's not always such a good thing.
Couldn't a compiler translate the opengl commands to see commands and
wrap them in a loop which iterates over the pixels?
Well, sure it can.
But take a look.
I mean, let me let me try to.
If you were not convinced by my explanation, let me get show.
You just literally the code that we wrote.
Here's draw a rectangle slowly which is most of what we've done so far
in terms of rendering, right?
Here is all the code.
To draw the texture map rectangle, right?
The part of it, that is the Shader.
Is right here.
So this is for multiplies that you would have implemented it in.
Our glsl pipeline to get.
The rest of this, this is the blend output, so that wouldn't be there,
right?
Because the blend Blends are not programmable in glsl at the moment.
Anyway, although I feel like someday, that's probably going to happen,
but right now the blend unit is not a fully programmable unit.
So this is not in glsl, right?
This is in the texture unit, so this is not in glsl, right?
I mean maybe if you were if you call there would be one glsl line
called texture or something that had to do and it would expand to all
This stuff right?
This entire part here, that's all in the texture unit.
It's not in glsl, right?
This is in the texture unit.
It is not in glsl.
All of this is the selecting the pixels not in glsl, right?
So, the code that would be in glsl is literally that like, that's the
part that you would be saving.
And it just I don't see why you would bother, right?
It just doesn't make any sense because this is the Shader for this
effect, which is just tinted thing.
And so, yeah, that will there be
Be a little bit more later.
Probably, they'll be like, a normal map thing or something in there.
Whatever.
Like we'll have a little bit more.
But it's just such a minut part.
Why would you complicate your code by introducing this whole other
language?
This whole other translation process?
Like why would you do that, right?
It's just a really bad decision until you know, you're going to have
tons and tons of code in glsl that you need to translate that way,
right?
And I just don't see that being logical.
Lucas parent.
Could you explain us how you free all the memory stack when closing
the game?
You don't?
Windows all modern operating systems discard 100% of your memory when
your clothes so you don't have to free any of it.
I have a hard time understanding, why srgb?
Conversions are required for the alpha Channel at all.
Well, so first of all, they're not happening in the alpha channel.
So, if you notice srgb, conversions are not happening in the alpha
Channel, we leave the alpha channel unconverted, it's linear.
And why your initial code was incorrect.
The alpha channel is being used to represent a proportion of photons
from one source and a proportion of photons from another source.
Wouldn't that be outside of the purview of color curves?
Because it doesn't technically have anything to do with brightness.
Yes.
Oh.
So you are correct in your intuition.
The alpha is not an srgb value in our current system, we are not
converting it.
You seem to be manipulating colors on a low level.
How are you pushing pixels?
Sorry, I'm kind of new.
You want to go back and take a look at the video archive.
So, on handmade hero dot-org.
Actually, if you go to the Forum site is probably the best part place
to go.
So if you go to forums, I have made here at or gup there.
What you can do is you can go to the episode guide.
And if you take a look at the episode guide, there's there's sound and
input on window.
Simple frame buffer on windows.
So week one, this is what you want to watch that.
That'll tell you.
Any reason you write Texel a plus desde - Texel a times desde instead
of this Envy that's tarde.
Este times Texel a, which would masturbate, you know.
No there isn't it's actually just because I worked out the math on the
Blackboard and this is what it worked out too if I remember correctly.
So yeah, we can do that if you take a look at what
What he was suggesting there.
So if I rearrange this, so I move this.
Oops, so just you can see, so curious Texel a right, if I move Texel a
to the end.
So keep the exact same equation.
Then, what I can do here is this is just one - Texel a times deste,
which is in virus a right.
So, you know, we could just write that much.
More concisely there.
I had just copied it down from the Blackboard but that's that is.
Yeah, definitely it makes perfect sense.
Why you would want to do that, it makes it much cleaner and more
definitely easier to read.
Right?
The other thing we could do is recognize that because we've gotten
this down to such a straightforward think.
Now, if we want to, we can also say, well, this is just in VAR, sa X
desk, plus Texel, right?
That's all I was.
So now it's just it's a little cleaner to read as well I suppose,
right?
So that's that's always good.
We can just keep on keep on keeping on, right?
Condense them condensed and condensed and so that's kind of fun.
This also is obviously the hadamard product so we could actually be
calling, you could actually call Texel equals hadamard.
Texel X color, right?
Oops, not plus equals hadamard times color, right?
And and that's the same.
I should double-check obviously that the
See.
Just double-check that are crazy.
Psychedelic thing work still.
There we go.
Lovely, isn't it?
So yeah, so so that can all be condensed quite a bit obviously.
Possibly should be.
Similarly, we could do this guy down here because it does exact same
code, right?
This is is, is the same we Arrangement, right?
So move the textile to the end, like so.
And then recognize that this is just one - textile, a times d a, which
is in virus a right and then that collapses its exact same operation.
So result is just getting Barse.
X d + Texel.
And that is, of course, the only place where, in virus a is used, so
you can substitute it in like, so,
So yeah, it just, you know, makes things a little bit cleaner.
Certainly
wasn't the alpha Channel authored with nonlinear colors.
So I don't think so because the alpha channel is typically authored by
Photoshop by writing the coverage value into each pixel when you paint
with the brush Strokes.
So I'm assuming and I don't know this definitively because I don't
have the source code to photoshop, but I'm assuming that the alpha is
not srgb encoded.
All right, so I think that's about it seems like no further questions,
so I will call it a day.
All right, ok, in that case, let's go ahead and close these guys and
save our Blackboard.
So, there we go.
All right.
Okay, that brings us to the end of another episode of handmade hero.
Thank you very much everyone for joining me today.
Pleasure coding with you, as always, if you would like to follow along
at home, you can pre-order the game on handmade hero dot-org, and it
comes with the source code that you can download every night, so that
you can turn to Tinker around with it and experiment with some of the
things that we're doing.
So that's a really good way to learn if you want to give that a shot.
We also have a patreon page.
If you want to support the video series, you can subscribe to that and
we have a forum site, which you can go to.
Where if you go to the Forum site, there's a bunch of cool stuff.
Episode guide, there's a Code discussion and there's a port to Mac and
Linux all kinds of good stuff there and there's a tweetbot that lets
you know the schedule I highly recommend checking out the Tweet bot,
if you are interested in catching the stream live because it always
tweets the schedule at you.
So you can always kind of know when it's going to be live so that's a
good way to do it too.
So tomorrow we'll sort of pick up I guess.
Maybe we'll start thinking about how we're going to keep things
optimized relatively.
Well, while we go forth, maybe separate some of that code out do
whatever needs to get done.
There.
And then we'll sort of push forward on a render.
Since I think we're in pretty good shape here.
Cleaned up some stuff today and we can maybe start adding some stuff
tomorrow, so that'll be good.
So yeah, hope to see you tomorrow.
Same time.
Same place tomorrow.
5:00 p.m.
Pacific Standard Time.
Right here on Twitch.
So, hopefully, we'll see you for that and have a good Wednesday until
then.
Take it easy, everyone.