Okay.
Hello everyone and welcome to handmade hero.
We are on day 39 here.
This is, of course, a full game and engine coated live on Twitch in C
and C++ using know libraries, no engines.
We are basically doing absolutely everything from scratch, largely
sort of as, as both an educational process and, and just for fun.
I think it's really good for, you know, on both on both ends really,
for the kite.
Type of person who actually enjoys programming than being able to
program.
Everything yourself is kind of a fun thing to do.
Especially nowadays when you don't get to do that, all that often.
And I've certainly been having fun doing it, and I think a lot of the
people out there have been to and also, it's a great thing for
educational purposes because a lot of people just don't have a chance,
a lot of times depending on sort of what their programming language
was to go through and do all kinds of interesting, low-level stuff and
build an entire game engine from the ground up and that sort of thing.
And so there's just a lot of cool stuff.
You can learn in there.
I think.
Anyway, I always feel like most all the most
I think stuff that I've ever learned in programming came from having
to tackle, you know, hard, low-level problems really honestly, even
the good high level programming stuff that I know is largely from
having to do sort of, you know, having to think about hard
constraints, and, that sort of stuff.
So, anyway, right now we are at the point where we sort of gotten,
we're sort of wrapping up the stuff that we can reasonably do before
we learn some math.
Basically is what, what I guess, how I would say it, we've wrapped up.
Up sort of the basic stuff of putting Sprites on the screen, you know,
loading, B Babs.
Doing some basic Alpha blending techniques, building a tile map and
moving around through the tile map, that sort of stuff.
But in order to start moving forwards in, you know, on the, on the
engine further, what we kind of need to do is we're probably going to
need to start doing some math very soon.
So I think today, what we're probably going to do is we're going to go
through and we're just going to kind of like do a pass over the stuff
that we've got so far and just kind of like clean things up.
And
To get things into place where we relatively happy with them.
So that we can start clearing the way for doing, really, maybe
starting to have a serious discussion about gay math and what sort of
math, we need to know and what all the different types of math are
that tend to come up in games.
And so, then starts go through some of the one, the most basic ones
that we will need in order to move forward with your basic 2D Vector
math and stuff like that, which we're going to need for just about
everything that we're going to do.
So if you went to him made here at Oregon, pre-ordered the game using
the little pre-order button,
And you should have gotten an email with a link that allows you to
download the source code and the test assets that we use as well.
There's two zips up there.
Make sure you grab both of those.
And inside the source code ZIP.
There's a bunch of different Zips resource codes from every different
day.
We're on day 39 right now.
So if you want to follow along at home, unzip day, 38 source, code
day, 38 source code is what we are starting with now, and if you unzip
that, you will be at the exact location that I am starting with today.
So you can follow along exactly the way that we are with exactly what
we're doing.
So, if you guys remember, we gotten to the point at the end of last
streamer, we were able to blit basically things on top of other
things, which allows us essentially to compose whatever we want in
terms of Graphics.
Now, we can, you know, layer Sprites on top of each other all day
long, but we had only just finished that so we didn't just we didn't
really do anything with it.
So I was thinking, maybe today, what we could do is just load in our,
our little hero Sprite and he's in three pieces.
As I think I showed when I was going through the different Sprites
that were in there.
He's in three different pieces.
So maybe we'll go in and load his three.
Pieces.
And we also have four facing directions for him.
So maybe we'll load in all of those and we'll sort of make a thing
where he can.
As we move, he faces the direction, you know, that we're moving or
something like that.
Just something basic to sort of clean up the bitmap loading, and the
bitmap display code into something that were relatively comfortable
with for the moment before we kind of move on to trying to do a little
bit, more serious stuff again and where we'd have to start talking
about math for reals for reals with a z.
So, okay, assuming that we're in that situation right now, we
We are loading all of our bitmaps.
We haven't talked really very much about Asset Management in terms of
how we're managing loading stuff in the code.
And that's actually deliberate.
It's not something that I think is really worth discussing at the
moment.
I think that's going to be something that comes into play.
Once we have a bit of the renderer sort of the real renderer.
Once we kind of have more of a real renderer, written is really the
more the appropriate time to start thinking about that.
So right now we just have the sort of the most basic thing you might
do in a game which is loading all the assets at startup not up.
Really useful thing to do if you're actually talking about a shipping
game.
Because like I said, in this game, we're going to be streaming our
Assets in so loading, everything at startup isn't really an option for
us.
But while we're just developing things that certainly fine.
So I'm going to have to load these different hero, things for four,
different directions.
So I'm just going to go ahead and make life a little easier on myself
for now and just say that we have sort of a hero bitmaps structure and
that will have basically the different pieces, the head of the cape
and the Torso each for, you know, the different facing directions of
the hero so that I can base their we have hero bitmaps.
And the here, a bit maps that we have.
Our for the for facing Direction.
So, we'll just stay here a bit maps and I guess I'll do.
I don't know.
We could do something like just a brackets for I guess.
Because we will essentially have to map into that somehow.
We'll think about that in a second.
But, anyway, if I want to load those in, I've already got code that
loads each of the each of the test pieces in here into the hero head.
I don't know what happened to our hero torso code.
I must have actually hit Ctrl K.
That's a mistake.
So
so we already have code that does that, which is this code right here,
but I need to load one of those for each of the facing directions.
Like test here are front, you know, the sort of the front back side
and all that sort of stuff.
So I'm going to go ahead and do this.
Responsible thing here just do hero bitmaps, and I'm going to
substitute in basically one of these like that for each of these ones
that we load like so.
And then I'm just going to go ahead and call that four times.
Nothing particularly exciting here.
And like I said, we'll think a little think harder about how we want
to do this stuff.
Once we actually think about asset loading and how we want to identify
bit Mass because in general, you know, you don't want to have to have
huge tables of strings in your code.
At least.
I don't.
And so,
So that's not something that I would encourage you to do when you're
actually doing the real code, but for now, it's exactly the right
thing to do because you do not want to be thinking about that while
you're trying to work on other pieces of the code.
So here is the set of files that we have.
We have front back left and right.
I'm not sure what the best way to map.
Those two zero one, two, and three are at the moment.
So I guess, maybe what I will say is let's go ahead and just do we'll
just do maybe
With with moving right in that 0 slot.
And then, you know, I'll go I'll basically do it almost like it was a
circle.
So then there's the, there's up is after that.
Like so and then this would be left.
Right?
And I guess it's not snot up.
It's actually that's that's looking at his back, right?
Like so and then and then front is down here, which we've already got.
And so that'll load all those bitmaps into memory for us and it'll
just go ahead and be using those for the entire run of the game.
At the moment.
If I go ahead and compile then we will not be able to find that when
we do the hero head but we should be able to do here a bitmap 0 dot
head.
And now we should basically be back to exactly where we were before.
Only now, he's, you know, the other facing direction, right, but I'm
going to need, actually to draw.
Well, you know what?
I don't know why I keep forgetting the fact that I can always leave
the code running.
We don't actually have to don't have to, I guess it's just from a lot
of the stuff that I work on data.
Today doesn't have this feature necessarily, so you kind of get in the
habit.
Unfortunately, oops, that's not right.
So if I have the head, I have the Torso and I have the cape.
I guess the cape comes over the Torso.
Basically, what I do is I want to draw these in reverse order because
remember, this is a lot like Photoshop things get layered on top of
each other.
So what I actually want is I want the Torso first since that's the
thing.
That's the lowest down in terms of what gets shown then the cape gets
laid on top of that, then the head on top of that and in theory, that
should reconstruct my hero.
If, if I'm not very much mistaken, and yes, there is, there's a little
hero fellow and he is facing in the, in the direction to the right,
which is what I expected.
Now.
I probably could also say here, you know, if I had a facing direction
for the little fellow right?
If I had facing Direction equals 0, let's say and I went in here and
said, you know, facing Direction like this.
I think then I would be able to also sort of flip them around.
I suppose as I go right, if I flip it to one, there.
He goes to nice facing that way.
Three nice facing towards us.
And so if I wanted him to basically face the direction that he's
actually moving in over 3000.
Okay, don't think 3000 is very good.
Things happen.
There.
If I wanted to face the wreck, she's moving.
I just need some way of specifying, what it was, whatever that last
erection was.
That is the direction in which he moved, right?
So, if I go in here, and I just say, all right, that facing Direction,
you know, hero facing direction is now a parameter.
And then out here.
I can go ahead and grab out the hero bitmaps thing that that is
appropriate based on that facing direction, right?
I can go ahead and do you know, gamestate hero bitmaps?
For game state hero, facing direction that would give me back that
bitmap that I actually want the whichever one, you know, it's actually
supposed to be.
And so then if I go in here and just go ahead and change these all to
sort of operate off of that, then I sort of made it so that we can
easily store in the game State structure.
What it actually is we want the hero facing direction to be.
So if I go ahead and go over to the code.
Where we actually move the guy around right with move up, move down,
move left and move, right?
It'd be pretty trivial for me, to sort of go and just set it to
whichever key down.
You pressed last, which is a totally reasonable thing to do for now,
since we don't really, again, we haven't done that Vector math, so we
can't really do much.
We haven't really written any real hero movement code yet.
And so, it's, you know, it's not really going to be something that we
can do anything fancy with yet, but for now, we can certainly set the
hero facing direction to whichever thing you
Actually push down last.
So if the hero, you know was was was moving upward, we can set it to
that moving up direction.
If the here was moving down here.
We can say to that moving down, you know, the left and and the right
like so and then if I go ahead and compile that what's these are
supposed to be address of the bitmap there?
Now, I should have a way to basically have my my dude change
direction.
Oops, and I've got I missed.
I missed typed at once there.
So I
I've inverted, my my two directions.
What did I do?
Let's see here.
So if we're moving left, yes, left is supposed to be to write is
supposed to be 0.
That's that's what I said when I made it, but I didn't actually do it.
And so now the hero actually does change for whatever Direction, he
moves in and I'd like to go ahead and Center him on his rectangle as
well.
You'll notice that basically the bitmap right now.
We do have something.
In fact, this is probably something worth talking about because we
haven't really addressed it.
And in the art assets yet.
We're not actually at the level of loading artists.
That's where this sort of stuff comes in.
But we'll need to do something as sort of a temporary temporary fix to
it.
If you consider the fact, if you consider what these bitmaps actually
are, right?
If we actually go and you can see, we're drawing the players bitmaps,
right?
All those three bitmaps.
We're drawing them with this upper left corner here.
This this is the point, the position that we are passing.
When we say, we want to draw those bitmaps.
There's a bunch of information, kind of, there's a bunch of sort of
assumed information.
That's all getting baked in there.
And it's why, for example, the hero is kind of nowhere near where our
rectangle thinks you should be.
This was our little test triangle rectangle that said, where we
thought the hero should be and that, so it's not at all.
Correct, right.
We'd expect the hero to kind of be standing up, you know, with this
feet roughly where the bottom of the rectangle, where was for example,
but that's not at all what's happening.
And so considering that situation, right?
What's
On their.
Well, if you look at what we've got in terms of assets.
If you go into the test directory and look at what these assets are,
let's say we open one of them up.
Well, obviously, I'll open up all three for a given facing direction
will open up the front facing ones for now inside gimp.
And what you can actually see if you take a look at these guys.
In fact, you know, what I can do to?
That was probably the wrong way to do.
It course that opens three different copies of gimp.
Therefore.
We thank you so much gimp.
What?
I'll actually do is I'll go ahead and we have the front torso loaded.
I'm going to load the head and the
Ape and so now they're all in there as a layer right there.
All on is there as layers and what you can see is basically the way
the art comes in because these are raw RSS.
There were loading.
We haven't processed ever done anything to them.
Basically.
They're just a giant empty space around the guy which is totally fine.
Like we want that.
That's what you want your artist to give you but then you need to do
work to kind of process those down into final art assets that you
would use and you would store all that empty space obviously.
And so on so forth, but the other important part of this is that
there's essentially an implicit
it hotspot defined here.
Often times what it's called.
It's often times called a hot spot on.
That's like the old school term for it.
It's sort of what the used to call like cursor locations and stuff
that you'd use for offsets.
It's, I don't actually know why the term is what it is, but there's an
implicit sort of alignment point you could think of which is basically
right down here, where the dude is standing is where we kind of want
to position him in the world, right?
We want to have this point.
Line with where we think the players position is like something like
that, right basically, right where he would be sort of standing where
he would be touching the ground.
Right?
And we don't actually have that information yet.
And so what we're going to have to do in our eventual, real art files
is, we will have to have those registration marks basically in there,
or we'll have to set the manually.
One of the other doesn't matter, but you have to do something along
those lines.
And so, if I look in there, I can actually see down in the bottom
here.
Right here, gimp will tell me what those pixel coordinates are like 72
180, 270, 2, comma 1 82, right?
You kind of see as I move.
Those are the X and Y positions, so we can go ahead and put that in
there.
We can say that at 72, roughly 72 182 for that particular facing
direction, right?
And that's that's the one where he's facing the front.
So in the one where he's facing the front, and in fact, I guess we
could sort of do it.
Here, so, it's oops.
It's a 72.
And 182 for the X and the Y, we could go ahead and make this a little
more concise here.
And basically say, well, okay, there's these hero bitmaps and we're
going to introduce another thing which is basically the aligned X and
a line, Y, right for this bitmap set.
So that we kind of know how to position them relative to the points
that we actually care about in the world.
That makes sense.
Okay.
So, what we want to do is we want to basically have those
registrations that will just hard code for now into this part
ourselves.
And then when we get to the point where we actually are talking about
putting large numbers of assets into the game, what we'll need to do
is we'll need to have a way of actually loading that data from
somewhere like that data will have to be produced in a more efficient
fashion.
We probably don't want to sit here and hand coded ourselves.
What we'd rather have is some way of just marking it in Photoshop or
whatever it is.
And then
Those are access get exporter will make sure they get exported to
something that we can read when we process our art assets.
So I'm going to go ahead here and just do something like this where we
can sort of have a nice.
Yeah, something like that.
In fact, I guess what I could do.
Yeah.
This is actually pretty easy.
You could actually do this and then I'll just do.
Bitmap Arrowhead equals, debug load like so and and
It map hero Cape so just clean things up a little bit here.
So there's not quite so verbose.
There we go.
And now I'll also do bitmap a line x equals something and bitmap a
line, Y equals something, and then I'll move on to the next bit map.
Right?
So this will just load our hero bitmaps as they were.
So I'm just going to go ahead and make that change everywhere.
I think I can probably, I don't know, you know, it's always dicey when
I do this.
But we're going to do it.
Anyway, I think, I think it's just, it's the right time to do it
people and you know, when it's the right time to do it, you know, and
when it's the right time, you kind of just got to go with it.
You kind of gotta go with the flow sometimes.
So there we go with that and then we'll put that here.
So let's go ahead and get that going on.
There we go.
It's clean that up.
And now we've got something a little more respectable in terms of
code.
We can use.
Okay, so I'm going to go ahead and just manually for now, do those
offsets.
But again, that's just something, you know, something definitely to
pay attention to, you know, if you didn't have me, sitting here,
telling you the sorts of things that will probably do.
Because I've done all this stuff like this before.
This would basically a place where you'd want to think in your head,
you know, I don't want to be sitting here manually.
I open up these bitmaps every time.
The artist change is something looking to see where that alignment
point is like, you can see that that's going to be something that's
going to take time.
And you might art, you know, you kind of want to think to yourself,
what could, what might we be able to do?
That could sort of speed that process up, right?
Like, how could we how could we make a better way of setting these
alignment points?
Right?
And there's a lot of different ways you could do it, but it's just
something to be aware of it.
Kind of like it raises that little red flag where you kind of got to
think to yourself.
Of what you know, what's the what's the end scheme here?
So it looks like actually, like, these are roughly the same.
I don't know.
Yong, Chi.
And may have already just kind of lined everything up for us, which is
kind of nice.
So, it looks like, they may all be roughly the same, so we won't have
to really do.
Yeah, I think she might have, although that one's a little different
than than the other ones probably, but we could probably use them all
at the
Moment as as being 72 182.
That's what that's what actually they almost all look like is roughly
about value.
So we'll leave it like that, but we can tweak them later.
Okay.
So now we've got these loaded.
There we go.
What, why are you?
Oh, whoops.
That's no good.
I didn't even realize I still had the game.
Loading, my bad.
Sorry guys.
Okay, so now we've got our little fellow there.
And what I want to do is like I said, I've
The information in there.
Now, where I could go ahead and correct for where he should be
relative to that relative to the alignment point.
And so what I need to do is I need to have some way of actually taking
that alignment into account.
So, in here where I do this drawbitmap, I want to basically be able to
change the player left in the player top based on that alignment
amount.
And so what I'm going to do is I'm going to introduce probably a new
function here, which is a drawbitmap aligned function.
Or there is a different thing I could do which is I can make these
basically be some kind of registered coordinates.
It's a little bit hard to say at the moment.
I think possibly in the interest of
It's so tough to say sometimes, you know.
I'm not sure how we want to do this yet.
So I think temporarily what I might do is
I might just pass these as optional parameters into this thing.
We're going to want to do something fancier than this later, but I
think we might just want to have it in there, right there for now and
we'll sort of when we have more of a renderer.
There's going to be more clearer places where those should go in my
opinion.
So I think for now we'll just leave it like that.
And we can go ahead and say that the the hero bitmaps align X and the
hero bitmaps.
Align, why can go ahead and get passed in.
They're all right.
So I'll go ahead and compile that and what I want to do now, right is
I want to actually use those alignment points to offset the place
where we would be drawing the guy.
And I think I actually have to try to remember what we actually did
for player.
We're passing player left, and Claire top, but that's not what we
actually want anymore.
We actually just want the players actual location, right?
So so we actually want to
Where the player actually is we want a player ground Point basically
and and we want that ground point in X and Y and we so so we don't
really, we're not so interested necessarily in these sort of like
adjustments for the players height in the players width and so on.
Right, that's not actually what we want to see what we want to see
here.
Is we want to see?
Let's see something more like that.
So that's going to be the player ground point x in the player.
Ground point Y and then
I'll go ahead and keep Computing the location for our rectangle as
well.
You might as well leave that drawing, but then in here, so what I want
to do is I want to pass those points that were aligning to, right.
So I'm going to pass those instead of the the left and top.
So player, ground Point, why there we go.
So now, we're passing the right things in and now that should make our
guy up here, even more off center.
Because we're now passing this point right here, which means it's
drawing like this.
So now we have to do is do that alignment to get him back up to the
right place.
So, if I go into that drawbitmap call, you can sort of see.
It's not going to be particularly difficult.
We've got our real X and are real.
Why that come in here.
Basically, all we have to do is subtract from those the values that we
have for our alignment, right?
All we need to do is say we want this a line X, and this aligned, why
to actually be sort of the, the alignment Point versus the point that
we've been passed in.
So, if you think about what happens, I'll go ahead and draw it out for
you here.
On our handy.
Dandy whiteboard.
I don't know why create a still is
Passing a hand for our cursor.
Nobody really knows.
We don't try to understand create, do we just accept the fact that it
does what it does?
And so what I'm doing here right is, we've got a blind routine and the
blind routine is going to draw a rectangle from like, an upper corner.
It's going to copy these rows in here, right?
But what we have is we have a registration Mark right in the world.
That's basically where the player.
Point is.
So this is the ground point, right?
And then we have a bitmap that also has a registration Mark in it,
right?
That's measured from that upper corner.
So what we want to do, if we are saying that these two registration
marks should line up, then we're relative to the ground point.
Where would we draw?
Write that this bitmap?
Well, the answer is we just invert right?
Whatever.
This was if for saying that the aligned X and the line y is how you
get from the upper corner?
To the alignment point, then getting back to the upper corner is just
going to be a matter of subtracting them.
Right?
And so that's all I'm going to actually do here is, I'm just going to
go ahead and subtract those aligned X and the line Y points, so that I
can offset my bitmap by the amount that we possible, that would be
necessary to move those alignment points into into coinciding, right?
And so, now, you can see our little hero fellow.
He actually is properly aligned with where we thought he should be,
and that's all good.
He's a little
Often though in the direction that I said, maybe he would be often,
which is the side ones.
I wasn't sure what we should set those alignments to, but he's for the
most part, pretty much fine.
And so that's a lot better than what we had in there before.
Now.
What I'd like to do is I'd like to get back to screen-based stuff
here, you know, we had our tile map and then we started doing
scrolling just as a test thing.
I'd like to get back to having things fixed on the screen where we
just walk in the end.
We walk around the screen instead of the screen scrolling around us.
So I'd like to go back and and and
And change things back to going that way for a while.
Until just because I that's sort of the way the game will mostly be
played.
And we don't kind of want this random stuff in here for now because
we're going to start working with the players actual move.
It code.
All right, so
Hopefully that was all very straightforward.
Nothing.
Particularly unusual going on there.
Let's see.
We got about 30 minutes left, which is quite some time.
Okay.
So what I want to do now is kind of figure out some way to keep our
camera centered so that we can have our tile Maps back.
Also.
I feel like we can probably at this point stop drawing the crazy
backdrop for now.
Well, I mean we could keep drawing that backed up.
I guess we could do a number of things.
I'd have to think about exactly what we should be doing.
It's a little bit difficult to say because again, trying to manage
stuff at this stage in the game.
We're kind of thinking about all the different places we could go.
There's so much.
There are so many different places that we can go obviously,
exploring.
Because we have every, every part of the system is still pretty much
up in the air.
But basically, I guess what I would say is, do we want to leave that
drawing the backdrop in there, you know, maybe we do at the very
least.
What I'd like to do is just leave the sort of the world fixed for now.
Yeah, so what I'd like to do is I'd like to change it so that instead
of drawing out from around the player, because you remember this,
right here, drew our tile maps are this.
Little debug thing for drawing.
What was filled in the tile map?
I think what I'm going to do is I'm going to change it so that we have
both a player P and a camera P, right.
So now, I have a place where the camera is looking, and I have a place
for the players looking and they're not going to be the same anymore.
So now the camera p is basically going to be
You know, the place around which we Center that Tha map rendering.
So all the same stuff we were doing here.
We're going to do it's just we're not going to do them from the player
P, right?
Instead of player pee in here.
We're going to do it from this perspective of the camera.
And so what we were doing.
Remember if you remember how we drew this town map, we are essentially
starting with whatever tile, the player was on.
We were saying that was going to be centered in the very middle of the
Green.
And then we were just going to walk out words from there to the 10
pick tiles on either side and I'm sorry 10 pixels up and down 10 tiles
up and down.
So 20 tiles total and 40 tiles across so negative negative, 20 to 20,
which is more than actually was on the screen.
We were kind of over drawing a little bit.
We were we were going a little bit further out.
So, what I want to do is just say, okay, we're going to do exactly the
same thing only instead of walking out from the players position.
We're going to walk out from the cameras position.
So everywhere that there was a player pee in here, right?
I'm going to change it to a camera P, right?
And so that's that's how that's going to work.
So now when we initialize that player position at the outset of the
game, we're going to initialize the camera position to be something
logical as well.
So we initialize the player position somewhere in here.
There it is.
So,
We're going to say that.
There's also a stage where we initialize the camera position and that
camera position should just be let's say on that very first map that
very first tile map down in the corner at that tile chunk.
I think we said basically our tile system was going to be roughly
something like 17 by 9 or something like that.
I think is what we were saying, so I'll do 17 divided by 2 and 9
divided by 24 what that was going to be gamestate camera p.
AB style y equals 9 divided by 2 and you know what?
It's interesting.
Well, I guess that's fine.
So, there we go, and we will go ahead and run that noun see where we
get.
So essentially.
Oh, right.
And now we actually have to do the work for doing player position as
well.
But now, our cameras going to be fixed.
And remember, we were cheating before we never actually computed where
to draw the player.
We just drew them at the middle of the screen.
So now we actually have to compute where he is.
Which means we're going to have to do a relative computation to see,
where is the player?
Relative to the camera because we know the camera is at the screen
center X and screen center.
Why?
We know that's where the camera is essentially going to be in sort of
the space.
Let me draw the screen because that's the definition of the center of
the screen is wherever the camera is telling us to look.
So, what we need to do is we need to add something to that.
Right?
We need to say, where is the player relative to the camera so that we
know where to draw them relative to the center of the screen, right?
And so, what we need to do is we need to have essentially a
subtraction operator and this kind of leads nicely into that mass Seth
I was talking about, so this is going to be good because you will sort
of it.
Sort of is a nice segue, if you will.
For talking about this tomorrow or Monday, whenever we decide to
transition over it to it, but we've got these tile map positions and
basically what we want to be able to do is we want to be able to
subtract, right?
We want to be able to say, what is, how do I get from one to another?
If I have the player and I have the camera, how would I get from the
camera to the player?
Because that's the distance that I want to give in, in sort of.
That's, that's what I want to add to the screen center to know where
the player is, right.
So so what I'm going to do is I'm just going to say, okay.
Let's actually pretend we have that.
Let's actually just say that we had something that could do a
subtraction right.
And it could subtract a tile map position from another time a position
and will give us back the real 32 answer, right?
So I'm just drawing a name for that at the moment.
I'm not suggesting.
This is actually going to be the name eventually but that, you know,
let's do that.
Subtraction.
Right?
Well, that subtraction is just going to be between the game, the, the,
the player P, right.
And the camera pee.
Oops, State camera P like.
So now, of course, we might, as well just do.
We don't really want to have multiple functions for this.
We might as well just do one.
That will actually give us back the whole answer.
And again, this is kind of setting up the mass.
So we're going to have to kind of do this in a bit of a janky way for
now, because we haven't introduced vectors yet.
So we're just going to kind of see it.
And then when we do our vectors, which I guess will be maybe tomorrow,
seems since it seems like, this is kind of the most pressing concern.
We can kind of see how it, how to clean this stuff up nicely.
So I could
Say there's a tile map difference function.
Let's say, and that's going to basically give us back the difference
in X Y and Z when we do that subtraction.
So if I do the subtraction I could do it like this.
I could say that we get back at I'll map difference.
Right?
And that, that difference is going to be the difference between the
player and the camera.
Once I have that difference.
It's pretty easy for me to go ahead and and add it in.
So I basically
basically now would have a way of getting to where I think the player
actually is.
So all I need to do is make something that could subtract these two
and produce one of those as a result.
So if I look at what has to happen to do that, right?
Well, part of it is really, really simple.
Right?
If I've got two of these.
Let me go ahead and set this up for a little more success here.
If I had
Tile go like so.
So we've got Tom app difference that we want to return, right?
And we want to basically compute a d x, d y and add easy out of that.
Now, what I'd like to do is I'd like to take into tile map positions
in a and Abby.
Like so.
And then I would like to say,
How do I subtract a 2 of these?
Well, I know how to subtract the offsets directly because the offsets
just are real 32.
So producing another floating-point offset by taking the distance.
The difference of these two is really, really easy.
It would look like this, right?
That's all I would have to do.
I would literally just subtract these offsets.
But what I need to do now is I need to account for these abs tiles,
right?
I don't have a way of accounting for the ABS Tiles at all.
Okay, so in order to do that.
I would, I want to be able to do a signed distance of some kind here.
So what I might do is say, alright, we could do the subtraction in
float for now.
I have to think about how I actually want to do this eventually, but
for now we could basically say all right, we've got the, the signed
distance which is the D Tile distance, right?
And that's going to be, you know, the ABS tile X.
From a - the ABS tile.
Why?
Like, so on, so we go, so I'm going to do that subtraction to get
these, these Delta's here detail x, d, Tau y, details Z, right and
then those are in tile.
So in order to change the distance in tiles, I would need to know that
tile side and M.
Right?
I need to know that tile map information.
So I'm going to have to take the tile map in order to do that
conversion.
Right.
I need to know for every one change.
When I do this.
How far are they in tiles?
I need to know how far that's actually going to be in the real M units
that we're using for everything else.
So the tile side and M, right?
That I'm going to have to go ahead and multiply in here, in order to,
in order to.
And I guess I could do that down here as well.
There we go.
So basically, I have my detail, X and D, Tau y, matte side, m d, Tau
y, x, 0, and tile side and M.
We don't really know yet.
What H RZ?
Really be.
In this case.
It's unclear that we ever want to actually have a DZ and this way, but
I'll put it to do in there to think about what we want to do about Z
because Z is really
Not a real dimension in our system, because since the way, Tom app
games work, you don't really have Z in the same way that you have X
and Y.
So, it's hard to say.
But anyway, after we compute these tile differences and then we
actually go ahead and do the math here, to add in the tile difference
amount.
Plus the offset amount.
Now, we've got a real d x d, y and easy, but of course, this is
actually all going to be in meters, but we need our M to pixels in
order to actually turn that into pixels on the screen.
Green and these are all in pixels from here.
This is all rendering units.
So there's our meters to pixels that gets added in there.
To convert that difference that we did.
And of course, we have to pass the tile map as well, which I think is
just gamestate to market.
So, there we go.
And so, I believe that is roughly all we need to do to get that guy
going.
And of course.
Oh, I gotta return the result of course.
And so, I think that should be roughly.
Correct.
And, of course it isn't classically.
You gotta love that.
I think that's just because I forgot that we have to flip things
around for our are kind of non.
We don't really have a render yet.
Like I said, so our coordinate systems are a little ad hoc here.
So, of course, yes, this is where we have to do.
Our flip always, which, you know, is kind of annoying at the moment,
but that will all get handled in our render for us.
So it's really, it's not as janky as it seems like it has to be the
fact that that the
The up-and-down doesn't quite work the way that we would like it to.
But anyway, so yes, what we would like to do here is we'd like to have
the player ideally go in the opposite direction.
Also, let me see here.
We should also make sure that we don't have a bug in our
in our offset X offset y stuff.
I don't think we do but we could double-check to make sure that we
don't.
So let's go ahead and double check everything here.
So we're going to take all of the tile cited M.
The dty, why is always going up?
It goes up in tiles as well as in as in r m units there, so that's
correct.
But yes, this this is this is wrong because obviously the guy is
supposed to go up, not the coordinates are inverted.
The renderer as from what they are in the game that didn't seem like
the bug.
We were having though, but I don't know.
Yes, we still get a weird.
We still get a little.
Yeah, I was going to say it didn't that was that was one bug that we
had but I'm like, there's that weird kind of we get that kind of
nasty.
Thing where the x is, the x is related to the why I must have had a
typo in that code.
Let me go back and look at it for a second though.
Fantastic.
Yes.
I have tons of typos.
Wow.
Those are amazing.
There we go.
All right.
So I think we are good to go.
Now.
Our dude is moving around to the camera is where it is supposed to be.
But we have a few other things that we would need to handle in order
to get everything working properly.
Also, I should note that we still have not finished our drawbitmap
routine.
So if we move to the top you'll notice I don't know if you can see
that.
That our guy doesn't actually he can't clip off the front, off the top
of the screen, we have a to do in there about that.
So those are the things that we have to finish.
So let's get him walking throughout the entire match.
For now, for example, when he comes off the top of the screen here,
you'll notice the camera will never change locations because we have
never actually program the camera to change locations.
So he is, and we and we also are drawing him, whether he's on the same
Z plane as the camera.
Not, so when Technically, when go upstairs will never actually see
that.
So we have a bunch of stuff that we need to fix.
So, let's go ahead and fix all those, we've got about 15 minutes left,
just so we can have things cleaned up and working relatively.
Well.
So we can start working on our math, having math.
With having real math is going to be a pretty nice thing.
Let me tell you, it's been a bit of a struggle to kind of go through
without ever having really vectors or anything like that.
But, you know, you got to pick an order to do things in, right?
And so it's always important to kind of, you know, not not go too far
too fast.
All right.
So, first things first, we always want to move the camera to wherever
the player is in Z, I would say, right?
So, no matter what happens.
I would say, the the camera P.
I'm just going to say that the ABS tile Z is always going to be the
same as the player State AB style Z.
Right?
So, so what if the player goes up, then the camera goes up.
If the player goes down, it goes down and and so I think
Yeah, there you go.
So now we can actually get up and so the only thing that now we have a
problem.
I was at the player moves off the screen, the camera doesn't ever
follow them.
Right?
And that's no good.
So what we want to do here is we want to then say alright, the other
thing we need to do is to see whether the player ever gets more tiles
to the left or to the right.
Then you should be relative to the player.
Now, what we could do if we're always locked, two screens.
There's a lot of different ways we could do this.
You know, it depends, whether we want to drop down our own manual
camera points and, and this would allow us to do different things like
having screens of different scale.
Sometimes.
There's there's just a ton of stuff we could do here.
I'm trying to keep it again relatively simple because one thing at a
time, but we basically have a problem with our tiles X and tiles.
Why were we want to do is at the player.
Moves one screen to the right or once we left we want the camera to
follow them.
They're right.
And so the simplest way we might do that is just basically say if
we rounded the players position to whatever the
Closest Center screen center point was we want the camera to always be
looking at that, right?
And that's one way we could do it.
I'm not sure if that's the smartest way to do it or not.
Yeah, it's really hard to say.
So one way, I mean, you know, let's let's let's put in something.
Let's put in something even simpler.
Let's say we've got this, diff this dysfunction here, right?
Like, so, oops.
In fact, I guess we don't even really need the diff function now that
I think about it.
Well, I guess we can tell, you know, kind of want it.
We can probably do want the diff function.
I don't know.
It's difficult to say, but I guess what we'll do for now is say,
alright, when the, when the we do the subtraction here.
Then basically what I'm going to do is say if the the Delta X is
greater than a certain amount, then I'm going to go ahead and move the
camera for words and if it's less than a certain amount, right?
I'm going to move the camera backwards.
Just going to see how that works out.
So basically how far is it?
Well, I'd say it's that 17 by 2 number again, right?
If the if he moves basically more than one screens worth away, then
he'll go ahead.
And do the change.
So I don't know.
Let's see what that number actually ends up.
Being if I have 17 tiles across.
As I think what we said, it was normally on the thing and so that's
eight.
Point five is the midpoint.
So eight tiles in the eighth tile, right?
We have seven tiles on one side, seven tiles on the other side and
then the middle tile, right?
So basically if you were to get, let's say nine tiles away.
If you were to get nine tiles.
Away from the camera on the X direction.
That would be too many and we'd want to flip to the next screen.
So what we could do is say, all right, let's take 9.0.
F is the number times the tile side and M.
Right?
And that is basically going to tell us aside and M.
That's going to say that the player move too far away from the camera,
right?
I'm just going to go ahead and do that.
Like so and let's just see what that gets us.
Again.
We got to go upstairs first because we can't get out of this room.
So we go out there and then we go here and do that.
That is not.
Oh, well that did exactly what I told her to do.
We're supposed to move the full 17 tiles, but for some reason I only
had it moved one tile which is not really going to help us.
Here to say the least.
Alright, let's try that again.
My bad.
That was that was that was not very bright.
So yes, if I go out here, now, we should see me come back on the other
side, which is exactly what happens.
And that's all good.
Again.
We still we have to go fix our problem so that this doesn't happen.
So that's the next thing to do.
And then we also have to fix up and down.
So, here we go.
I can walk out here and then I can kind of walk up Hoops up here.
And this is the place where we would like to go off the screen.
So again, hey, man, since we got Live code editing.
I don't have to walk all the way back there.
I can just go ahead and say let's duplicate this.
And so, since it's nine in the direction, I guess that would mean it
was for here is the tile side of M.
And so the d y is going to basically do this, right?
And that should give us some better motion up and down as well.
Right?
So when we walk off the end there, oh, okay, so it's actually sorry.
It's not for its five-star was happening there, but we were right it's
because we didn't Encompass that extra tile when we walked onto that
tile.
We were in neither as camera.
Space the camera.
I certainly would flip back and forth going.
Oh, I'm too far away.
So you actually have to do?
Yeah.
All the way to the end of that fifth tile or at least to the middle of
it in order to not have that sort of problem.
All right, so, I believe we can now walk all around the world with our
guy which is nice.
That's always good.
It's kind of a happy little fellow.
Well, he's determined you know, he's happy but he's determined, you
know, that's how he is.
So anyway, he's going to go out there.
Let's go up there.
See here.
Go through here.
Yeah, so everything's nice and happy.
Everything is good.
No complaints.
Alright, so basically all we really need to do now to keep to get
ourselves back to a place, that's pretty stable for him walking around
to where we can start to talk about wanting his movement code to be
better, is is, you know, I'm, I'm walking out there and I'm clipping
against the screen here.
We just need to make sure that we do the math, right for clipping off.
That edge of the screen.
I think we already do the
Right for clipping off the other edge of the screen, meaning that if I
was going to go down.
I think that works properly like so for example, going off the screen
this way just works, right?
So that's all fine.
But it's that, it's that it's that coming in off the Min that we
haven't done yet.
So let's go ahead and do that and draw a bitmap.
let's go ahead and
make sure that this function now properly, handles, that you notice
the to do here that we left in there, which is source for needs to be
changed based on clipping.
And so that's the problem.
So basically what happens is our rectangle that were that were
bleeding does properly get clipped.
So we don't overwrite memory or do anything bad like that.
But what we're not doing is advancing The Source row and the basically
that starting pointer for where we're copying the pixels.
We need to advance that by however much, we clipped the left and top
edges of this bitmap.
So basically this part right here, when we do this, we
Basically save an offset value.
We need to save us like a source offset X and we need to save a source
offset y to tell us why we should be fetching pixels further in
because we are not drawing, the ones that are off the screen, right?
And to make that a little clearer for folks who haven't done this sort
of thing before, when we're normally drawing, right?
What's happening, is if we're clipping off the other side of the
screen, we don't have to adjust the point where we copy from, right?
All we do is,
Copy less.
So when we copy a row, if we started here, all we have to know is will
stop copying before you know, before you would have otherwise which
would be all the way out here.
But if we were to clip off, the Min edges of the screen, right?
And the case like this, where we clipping off, both of the minimum
edges, then we can't start copying from here.
We actually need to start copying from here.
And so we weren't doing that.
And so obviously, we were going to have those graphical glitches
because what was going to happen is we were going to start copying
from here, but we were going to draw it to here.
Which basically gives a phantom translation of our bitmap down and to
the right and it makes it look like a stops early because this is
still the clipping for it.
So it's basically translated our guy this way and clipped him.
So he would just you'd see like his head like there.
When his head should be up here, off-screen and his body should be
here.
Right?
So, all we need to do is just advance that pointer pre advance that
pointer to the right location and that will totally fix the bug that
we have.
So all we need to do here is basically go.
All right.
Right, we have this which is our source row, but we could go ahead
right now and update it to say that whatever our set X is, will move
that many pixels in and whatever our offset Y is well, multiply that
by the bitmap with right and that will offset it by that number of
rows.
So that way we'll get, you know, the, the row offset and the column
offset.
We're all good there.
So all we need to do now is actually store them.
And of course, it's whatever it was, whatever this value was.
That this negative value is how is we want to offset by the off the
opposite of that?
Right?
So there we go, and now we should be copying this guy well, or we'll
just go ahead and just straight-up fucking crash.
Because it's amateur programming, our here on handmade hero.
Apparently, I don't know exactly what I did there.
Oh, right.
Because because I forgot that this bitmap is bottom up, right?
So basically we have to actually go down.
We have to actually subtract for each of the thesaurus offsets.
Yeah, not not, not the brightest move by Casey.
It's true.
But again, a lot of this stuff is just since this is test code.
You can't expect me to remember all that stuff when we actually are
doing the full render.
Coded lot of this will be more commented and more directly will have
bullet down more and then you can get mad at me.
So I'm not going to allow a shame that that was not an ALICE.
Shame moment, my opinion.
I'm going to give myself a by on that one.
All right.
So anyway, I think our dude.
Is pretty much.
Okay.
Now you can see how he Clips properly now off either edge of the
screen.
So that's all good.
We'll try it on up as well just to make sure that.
Yep, that's all good up and down seem to be good there.
No issues.
Yeah.
Yeah, everything is fine.
Okay, so he can go adventure around are very sparse, and not
particular, interesting world.
But at least everything is working the way that we think that it
should.
And so that's good.
That's all very nice and good.
The other thing that we probably should do it.
Some point here is check our frame rate because of course at the
current moment, you know, we have, we're doing this rendering code
without any optimizations.
It's not Cindy, it's not optimized at all.
It's crazy.
And so we should trouble trouble.
We verify that all this crazy stuff that we did without any thought to
the performance of it whatsoever.
And we're not again.
We're also not even using GPU.
So we're at a severe, disadvantage performance-wise here.
So we should actually just go and check because we still haven't had a
chance to do anything in terms of a heads up.
Display for ourselves.
I just want to take a quick second to look to see what our frame rate
actually is in practice.
So let's take a look at that.
And it looks like we're still, okay.
We are hearing that that 30 frames per second goal.
And so we are, we are in good shape.
All right, even with all of that pickiness, so I think that's about
everything that I wanted to do today.
I can't think if there's anything else that I thought that I needed to
do.
I don't think so.
So, maybe let's go ahead.
And go to the Q&A a little bit early.
I'm trying to think if there's anything else.
Oh, well, you know what?
There is one thing we could do that.
I wanted to mention, I mentioned this in the forums to people because
they were having trouble with it and I just hadn't had time to do it
myself.
We could just throw it at the end here.
And that is that since we're doing our Live code loading.
Sometimes the problem, a problem happens with Microsoft Visual Studio,
which is that when the compiler writes out the executable, it
sometimes writes this cutable first and the pdb.
Well, I think it always actually does that.
And and so the pdb actually finishes writing after the executable
finishes writing, in this case.
I should say dll because it's the dll that we actually care about.
So we write that dll out and then the pdb gets written out.
When our hot loader goes to load the executable in, it will load that
executable almost immediately because remember we're running it, you
know, 30 frames a second here.
So it's going to load it very, very soon and the pdb sometimes hasn't
finished writing.
So what will happen is Visual Studio, will fail to load the pdb, and
then we
Can't set our break points and stuff, right?
Because the pdb is still open for writing.
So what I want to do is to show a little trick that we can do here to
avoid that problem, people were having trouble with this on the forums
and I told them how to fix it.
But I figured people on the stream should know as well, and that's
basically just to create a lock file.
So, all we really have to do is just in, in the direction, the
directory, where we're going to put that dll, right.
All we really need to do is we just need to put a lock file in there
and so we can say waiting for pdb and we can
Put that out to like lock dot temp or something.
And then when we are done will delete that locked up temp file, right?
And that locked out temp file.
Basically just says don't load right now because whatever you're going
to load is going to be stale.
And so if we look at what happens, if I do that, when I'm doing this
compiled here, it's probably hard to see because you can't actually we
probably can't catch it in time.
Well, you know what I could do.
I might be able to.
Oops, I might be able to show it here.
I'm not sure if I will, or will or will not be able to catch it.
But essentially, if you think about it this way, where's my build up
that handmade?
Note that bat.
I know if you can see it show up there a tall boots.
That's not right.
Build that that
I don't know if you can see.
It.
Show up there.
Probably not.
Yeah, it never actually it never actually puts forth.
Does it?
Let's see if I can get it to go.
There.
It was lock it down.
And if you can see that pause the stream, anyway, there's a locked up
temp file, now that gets created there and that locked up temp file
will not get deleted.
Hopefully until after the pdb is loaded, because the compiler will
have returned entirely at that time.
So once we know that there is that lock file in place.
That's just a dummy file.
That's there to let us know when that thing started and ended right
what I can do.
Is I can go ahead and just test to see if the lock file is there and
assume that whatever compilation has to be going on?
No matter how complicated, this thing gets will always wait and we
won't delete the lock file until all the things that we need to have
happened before the hot loading occurs have occurred, right?
And so when we do that, sort of load game code thing and I mean,
remember where that is at this point.
It's a load game code.
What we'll do is we can actually say when we go to load that game
code.
I think this thing actually sets.
Let's see here.
Yeah, this thing gets the that dll.
Last right time.
So what we could do is when we actually go to load the game code, we
could check to make sure that the lock file is not there.
Right?
And we have two places, technically, we could do that.
We could do that really in either position and I don't know which one
we would like to do.
It's
Hard to say.
I think we probably just want to do it here.
So I think we want to do and why is this still there?
I believe we are getting the proper path.
I think we're doing both of those two dues.
We need to go check to make sure we have a lot of to do is lying
around there and have to be there.
So basically what we could do right here is just go ahead and and do
the if right here to see whether or not that lock file actually
exists.
And so I think the easiest way to do that
That is just to do like a maybe a get file attributes or something
like that.
Let me see what.
Easiest way is to do that in.
To see whether that that file exists, I think actually to file exists.
It's it get file attributes.
I don't actually know path exists.
Don't think that's a good.
I don't think that's actually the function that we want.
Windows 2000, professional.
Requires floppy.
Yeah, I don't actually know if we want.
That doesn't seem like a good thing.
Get file attributes, might be the easiest zip file, attribute CX.
Let's see about that guy.
I could also look, I don't think there's a file exists, functional
think there is.
Look at double check file exists, path exists copy file now.
So let's go ahead and use get file attribute CX and basically that
should return false if we can actually get it, right.
So we'll just call will literally just call this thing right?
Like so and if it actually if it actually was there, then we'll be
good to go this.
Okay, so,
We need to do here is we need to have that file name, whatever that
foul name actually has to be.
And so it's going to be sore stealing on the attempt telling him and
lock file name, right?
Like that.
And so, we'll go ahead and pass that lock file name.
Now, whatever.
We do went through to load code.
We need to do lock full path.
And or I guess it's a game code lock full path that Source game code
dll.
And so here I should just be able to do temp with lock.
There we go.
Lock full path.
And that's I think just called it.
Locked up temp and there we go.
So I think oops, I think that should be sufficient.
I'm not sure.
I think it is.
And so let's take a look.
So if I go in here.
Well, evidently not.
Oh.
I did it backwards again.
Get file attributes.
So it's basically, if not, it's supposed to be, if we don't see the
file, right, it should load.
And so I think that should be fine.
But let me just test to make sure that we still have our hot loading.
Um enabled.
So okay.
Let's go got this guy going.
I'll make a new frame.
Maybe.
Oh, the Hideous colors.
Maybe I won't make a new frame.
So I'll just move this guy down here.
I guess we could go ahead and and do a loop for now.
Let's go ahead and make him go up.
Here.
We okay.
And so, I don't know.
What do we want to do?
Let's see if our live coded.
We'll Live code, edit him to go backwards instead.
So I'll go in here to handmade dot CPP and go to the facing Direction
stuff.
And basically, I'll just say, oh, yeah, whenever he is going to the
right.
Let's actually make them face left and vice versa.
Yeah.
There we go.
So should be good.
Yeah.
All right.
I'm satisfied.
Okay, so
I believe we now do need to go back to our originally scheduled
program.
We're a little bit over now.
Three minutes over the Q&A.
Now that we have taken care of that, I think everything is is, is
kosher now with that.
Yes.
I believe it is.
So let us go ahead and go to the Q&A.
Now that we've finished that, if you would like to have me, answer
question, please, put Q: in front of it, so that I will see it.
I and that starts now anything that you've put
That's Q:.
I won't see.
It's anything that starts now and has a cute: front of it.
I will I will take a look at and please try to keep the questions.
Two things that happened on today's stream or previous streams.
So please try to save off, topic questions or things about what we're
going to do in the future for a pre streams.
I try to show up about 15 minutes, early to most streams.
I can't always make it but I try to and I answer off-topic questions
at that time.
So if you're interested in asking off-topic questions, that's totally
fine, but come before the stream to do those.
So, most of the time I try to be here before them, so yeah.
Let's see.
Genetic species.
Can you do that live code with a function call?
That could just be a poke.
Hmm.
I'm sorry.
I'm not sure what that means.
Can you do that live code with a function call.
Could you be more specific, perhaps?
Let's see.
Enumerations.
Am I correct to say you've not used them in handmade hero yet.
I'm guessing this is simply because it's too early to know.
What will eventually require a new enumerations and not some other
reason did we really never use an enum?
That may be true.
We may never.
Yeah, so we haven't ever.
I do use enums.
I'm not avoiding them for any particular reason.
We just haven't had like sets of types or anything.
Probably.
When we do like entities, you know, our entity types might be an
enumeration or something like that, you know, but yeah, I'm not
avoiding them.
We just
I guess I just hadn't come up yet.
Why not layer?
The individual body parts into a single bitmap that way you only have
to draw one image instead of three.
Well,
That's a very good question.
And hopefully this is a very good answer for you.
I want him to be very bouncy.
So I want him to kind of hop along and I want the three parts to kind
of do this sort of a thing, right?
So, I asked, young-shin to make sure that they were separate so that
he could kind of be like a little springy guy that Springs around.
And in addition to like, squashing and stretching the bitmaps.
I also want them to move relative to each other, if that makes sense
to really kind of give that sense of, you know, motion.
Are you wearing a blue Cape like the handmade hero today?
No, it's not a cape.
It's just a shirt.
I don't actually have a cape, a handmade hero Cape, but see, I just
want to point out.
There is a magnifying tool in windows that came with arrow.
Yes.
It's true.
Unfortunately, it's really hard to use.
At least.
I find it hard to use.
I like this other tool called zoom in which I just haven't gotten
around to finding, I don't know where it is.
I may have to copy it from.
Like an old version of Microsoft developer Studio or something, but it
was so much easier to use than the than the one that came with than
the one that they ship.
Now.
Let's see if they've got this zoom in.
I don't know if this is someone else's stupid zoom in.
I want the actual.
I want the actual zoom in that used to come with the dev tools.
So there used to be one and Microsoft.
UK tools.
Yeah.
I'll have to go hunt for it.
I'll have to go hunt hunt for it because that's the one.
I actually want.
I suppose I could use color Cup.
In fact, maybe I should just use color cop because color cops.
Pretty awesome.
Yeah.
But looks like it doesn't do real-time.
Oh well.
Yeah, I don't know.
I want to go get that zoom in tool because I don't like the one that
comes there and that's why I haven't been using it.
It's too hard to use in my opinion.
And he's SZ.
Don't you want to test the bugging?
You can't really.
We'll just have to see if we no longer hit the problem because there's
no way to tell whether or not we just got lucky you just you.
So you just have to do that the test.
It like, lots of times.
You can't write because it was only, sometimes that msec didn't
actually do the reload.
So I just wanted to test just that much and then we'll see as we go
forwards.
If we have, if we have the problem where it can set breakpoints.
Girl and a boom.
Oh, no, I swore, I didn't mean to swear.
Oh, that's the second time.
Oh my goodness.
I don't know.
Even what I said, that's how bad of a swear that was.
That's awful.
Okay.
I'm trying to keep this the language.
Okay?
For kids and
You know, normally I swear a lot.
I will tell you so it's been rather difficult.
Can you add a standard def include to handmade platform.sh?
Sure.
I can do that.
In fact, people have been asking for a few things in here.
One was to get standard def in there.
So that platforms could get some platforms.
Want that for size T, this guy right here?
And so that the other thing people were asking for is they were asking
if maybe the utility functions could be moved in there because they
were having trouble compiling.
Well, in fact, you can kind of see what they are.
Basically.
We're
Still using handmade .h in win32.
And so what I could do is I could I could force it to stop doing that
and just do handmade platform.sh, and that would tell us what our,
what our stuff is that we're missing.
Right?
And so we would need to move in basically all of this stuff for the
most part.
So we would need to move in to the platform layer all of this code, I
think.
Probably, let's see here in there.
I don't know what else and get controller.
So, get controller would have to be in there as well.
Whereas get controller.
So those are the things that the platform layer was currently calling.
And I don't know that I really want all of those in the platform.sh at
the end of the day.
Oops, move that down a little bit.
Yeah.
And so yeah, I don't know if I want all of those things.
Is in there that may not be the best idea.
But at least now we compile clean.
So people who are reporting to other platforms, can go ahead and do
that.
So hopefully that helps them out a little bit.
Just making sure that they see our win32 layer, just only includes
handmade platform.sh and that's a little more consistent and make it a
little easier for them.
Why does the guy have no feet?
Well?
I mean.
if you look,
That right there should tell you why he has no feet.
How do you know which compiler options like CLR and standard headers?
You want to use?
I'm not sure what you mean by that.
Exactly.
I mean, essentially, my general rule for for standard headers and
compilers is that you want to include everything in the platform layer
and you want to include as little as possible in the main code.
So you would, ideally, I feel like you wouldn't want any includes in
the in the stuff that gets actually included in the game, but the
bottom line is that's not actually physically possible, mostly.
time, because you need to get
Little bit of information.
I mean, you could duplicate what was basically happening in these
headers so you could do that.
But for the most part, what you're trying to do is minimize the stuff
that you're including to only be definitions of stuff that you
actually need in terms of types, but you don't want to include
anything else for the most part.
That's the way I usually like to do it because I like to make sure
that all of my code is in my code and I don't call out into the
library for anything so that I know absolutely everything that's going
on and I can guarantee that everything is portable and so on and so
forth.
But yeah, that's just me in terms of in general how you decide what
you want to do?
It's whatever you want to use.
Like, I mean if you want to use stuff, I mean basically the way too.
To know about size T is just that if you go to us, any kind of
reference on C++ or C, you can kind of see like what it gets what you
need to include to use it.
So for example, in C++, if you're using the standard size T it tells
you here, like that's the include that that comes with.
If you're looking at the C library, know where that would be.
Exactly.
I know who says where that is.
Here you go, there to find the header file standard def dot h, so you
kind of have to go hunting for them or you can search in your C,
compilers include directory, to try to find where they are, but it can
be a little hairy.
When you're like I want to use this language feature.
Where is it?
Right, so I don't know.
So I don't know if that's exactly what you're asking.
If you want to ask a more specifically, I can try to answer it.
Maybe perhaps a little bit better.
Changing the literal value of a variable is a peek and poke technique
poking a value into memory address 0.
I see what you're asking.
Okay.
Yes for the Live code.
It is not poke based for what you're saying.
It is full on Live code.
So for example, what we were doing there is when like, for example,
you're moving this guy around, we could actually, you know, change the
code to do anything.
We wanted.
We could, we could change it to do absolutely anything.
So, for example, we could just go into the actual code where the guy
was, was being drawn right in the drawbitmap.
Code and we could just fall on, you know, drum or heads, right?
I mean, if we wanted to, we could just, we could just do you know,
anything, and there's a second head on the guy.
Maybe we could, we could go in and say, we want to draw.
Lots of heads on the guy head, count or head index equals zero head,
index is less than 10, plus, plus head index.
And then, you know, you get into this kind of a situation where you
just have so many heads.
You don't really know.
Oops, it mean, header and head.
EXO, right, and this is still all running.
You know, totally fine and you can like I do the loop Live code
editing thing that I was doing before, where the, dude kind of does
whatever his thing is that he does.
And that can be running all the while if you want to write.
And so, I can switch up what I'm doing here.
I can I can remove that and just draw one of them, right, like that.
I could, I could do anything I wanted to.
So yeah, we've got, we've got pretty much as hardcore Live code
editing, as you can get in a reasonable amount.
Out of time.
I have some harder core stuff where you can actually change data
structure layouts that I've done in the past, but that's a huge thing
that would take many hours of explaining on the stream.
So I decided not to do that one, but we've basically got as hardcore,
as you can go without that.
So yeah, it's pretty awesome too.
We haven't had a lot of chance to use it yet because we're not tuning
stuff at this point, really, where this becomes really great and we'll
see this possibly next week or maybe the week.
After is, when you're trying to tune, like the feel of an animation,
like in that movement code, or whatever being able to do this, where
you can just see them walking around and tune it and tune it in tune.
It is pretty awesome.
So I'm looking forward to that.
What will happen if you have an item that is in front in one view, but
in the back on another since it seems you've hard-coded the order in
which they're drawn, what you reorder them based on The View or some
other rendering technique, so it depends largely.
I suspect that the way you're.
Okay.
So this is just some code that we put in here.
I feel like I say this a lot, but I guess it doesn't necessarily often
come through.
All of this is test code.
None of the code that we have written in anything.
In here.
We'll actually get used, right.
It's all spec'ing out our game engine.
So we will not be drawing the player.
Anything like this, in the shipping version of the game, right?
It will literally bear.
Absolutely, no resemblance to going on.
What's going on here?
All of the stuff.
We are learning and that I'm explaining while we go through, it will
absolutely be important because we every single last thing that we've
learned here will be crucial.
All in are making the engine good but none of this is how you would
actually do it.
So when I say that I'm just drawing a couple things in here so we can
put the hero in that's literally what I mean.
What we will actually be doing is we'll actually have a number of ways
in which things actually get sorted into the scene and you'll see that
once we actually get to the point where we have a renderer as opposed
to just some test code.
Thank sense.
Why don't you use the emacs calc?
The reason is actually cuz I have not bound to key to it yet.
I only just figured out that it was there like accidentally on the
Basically, Mac sakie Max has so much stuff in it that I only know,
like .5 percent of the things that are in there.
And so I need to remember to bind a key to it eventually so that I can
just quickly hid it in calc.
So I have to meta X quick Dash, calc blah blah blah takes too long.
But yeah, I'm going to bind a few to at some point.
Oh, someone is saying that maybe I can get zoom in at
sysinternals.com.
Is that true?
Salinas utilities.
Zoom it.
Zoom.
It is different than zoom in.
Hmm.
Interesting.
Huh?
Well, to be honest with you though.
I'm kind of curious about that.
And since I obviously love Mark russinovich.
I might be inclined to take a look at that guy.
I did kind of want zoom in but Zoom, it sounds like fun.
I will say.
So maybe we'll check that out.
Yeah.
All right.
Thank you for mentioning that that could, that could be useful.
Let's go ahead.
Close that down there.
When you pan off the Min edges, can you explain how the head was
redrawing over the body?
So,
Redrawing over the body.
I'm not sure what you mean by the head was redrawing over the body.
Well, I mean, I can sort of just quickly go through what was happening
there and hopefully answer the question as part of that.
So and just for the fellow who was asking about how extensive are Live
code editing was, I will go ahead and and introduce a bug in the code
while it's live.
There we go.
Um, all right, so I'm going to turn off the looped live coding here
and go ahead and and get us to a point where we could actually see
that that happening.
So this is what was happening, right?
You can see that bug now that I've commented out the line so the head
wasn't redrawing over the body.
That was not actually what's happening.
What's happening is once we hit the minimum edge of the screen, right?
So remember the bitmap is
bigger here because there's just a bunch of alpha empty Alpha around
that guy once we hit the edge of the screen and we keep going forward,
what we're essentially doing is we've, we are now clipping the blit
rectangle like the
Rectangle is like this big, right?
And in fact, you know, what, I could do to just to show this to you.
I could go ahead and write in here.
The, our Channel always on, for example, like I could do something
like this, right?
Oh, but I have to do it just for dudes just for the little dude there.
Hmm, how do I do that?
Well, the way I could do that is say if I was clipped I suppose.
So I could do I could I could do it this way.
If what did I call that variable?
Source offset, so if sores are set X or Source offset, y draw, the red
Channel.
Oops.
So what I've done is, I've made it so that you can see the entire area
of the blit.
Once it starts clipping, when it Clips off the minimum Edge, right?
So hopefully, you can see what happens.
I move up there and now my rectangle is flush against the side.
As I move further over our rectangle properly Clips to the size that
it should be.
It correctly sets, the size of the blind.
But it is not changing the offset in the bitmap where it's copying the
values from.
So it's always copying as if it were going to copy the whole thing,
but it just gets clipped out entirely right?
As that as the rectangle shrinks and shrinks its only copying less and
less.
So what we need to do to fix that problem is we need to copy from
further in at the bitmap.
As we fall off this edge of the screen.
We need to move in on the source.
The place for copying from.
We need to move in.
That he moves over even though he's only copying a little bit.
So it's copying this, you know, this part from the rightmost edge of
the bitmap basis.
You could think about it as doing that, right?
And so when that happens, right?
Go ahead and turn the bug off.
Now, what's going to happen is essentially, you can still see it's
only bleeding.
This this piece, right?
It's only bleeding that rectangle right there.
But what it's doing, is it skipping?
When it copies a row.
It's skipping the first n pixels where n is however, many however far
off the edge, we were right.
And so that allows them to move all the way off, right?
So does that make a little more sense?
Right.
We didn't have to do that.
When we were flipping on the other side of the screen because on the
other side of the screen, we know we're going from the left to the
right when we copy a row.
So all we had to do was stopped early.
So the this this for Loop that's going to a Max X.
When we clip the max X that just that just works that just solves the
problem.
Right there.
We set the max X right here.
Right here, right?
When the max X is greater than the buffer with.
So when the max X would be off this Edge, we go ahead and stop it and
we set it to that edge.
All we need to do because we just stop copying the road, right?
We just stop copying the road early.
That's it.
Right, but when we're oops, trying to move the guy by clicking the
keyboard when I'm focused in the other room window, but on the other
Edge, it's not that simple.
Because if we were to just stop copying the row early, we get what we
saw before, where the guy appears to stop.
I'll get clamp against that edge because it's still copying the
pixels.
From the beginning of the bitmap where we don't want to copy those
pixels, right?
So hopefully that makes more sense.
I'll go ahead and remove
of that there and there you go.
So now we're back to normal.
Can't wait to do better player movement code.
It's awful.
Trying to get through these doors.
Yeah, I'm just like every time I try to go through a drawing, like I
gotta fix that.
Do you ever write tests or does the average game?
Not have unit tests?
Well, so unit tests.
I've covered this a couple times before.
I'll just say quickly again.
Unit tests aren't very useful in games because not many things have
the kind of well-defined repeatability that you need to make unit,
testing successful, but sometimes you do.
And so for like the renderer, for example, where you that would
probably be a place where we do unit tests.
We will have some performance test which look a lot like unit tests.
They're not really testing correctness as much as they're testing
speed.
So we'll have some of that.
So you will see a little bit of that.
You just don't see as much of it as you could.
In other disciplines where the state space is much simpler games, have
huge State spaces that are that are very different from the kinds of
code, that is usefully tested by unit tests.
And so usually, if you were doing unit tests on a game, you're often
testing things that don't really that aren't really the hard part.
So,
You'd like your bulletproofing, your easy cases by writing unit tests
in most game code, and that doesn't really help you.
But there are places where you can use it and we will use it.
I suspect on the stream in a couple places.
We just haven't gotten anything.
We're still doing exploratory work on how we want the engine designed.
And so until we get to some code that we think we're going to ship.
There's really not much that much point in doing it test, right?
Because you just kind of wasting your time.
You're wasting your time, bulletproofing something that you're not
playing ship.
Does this form of live coding work with adding member variables to
structs in some cases?
Yes, in some cases.
No, like I said, there's the harder data data layout stuff is
something we didn't to do because it was going to be a very much more
involved process to do that.
It involves writing meta code and stuff.
And so, I didn't want to do that, but you can add to, like the end of
structs in certain situations, but you
Rearrange data members.
And the reason for that is because, well, I mean, you could, as long
as there weren't any of them in use yet, right, but assuming that
there are ones in use, they won't get remapped.
And so, what you need to do is you need to go in and remap all of the
ones that were different now.
And we.
Yeah, so we didn't Implement that.
How does this test code help at the future architecture?
Since it all gets dumped?
So basically what it does is it will Define exactly what we want our
engine to do.
I always say right?
The usage code first and I really, really, really mean that never
write an engine without knowing exactly how the game is going to use
that engine.
And that is what we're doing right now.
So we're basically just building a game, doing whatever it is that we
want to do first.
And then what we'll do is we'll just kind of pull out those pieces and
turn them into real.
Hidden components, as we go and we already did a little bit of that
with our tile map.
We have it done a whole lot.
But we've already made the tile map stuff, work.
Kind of that way, where we've defined what it needed to do, and we
just haven't, we haven't gone and done like full hardcore engine stuff
on it yet, but we did pull it out into a little system.
And so, that's the way things will work.
So don't think of it as dumping think of it as continually evolving,
but the point that I'm trying to make before, was that none of the
code that we wrote as written, will be what ships in the game.
So you don't really have to
Worried about it at that level.
You just have to look at it and go.
Okay.
What does this do right now?
And why do we want it to do that?
And what is, what do we need the engine to eventually do for us in
that case?
So, the question of the person asked about sorting is actually totally
fine to ask a little further down the road when we're trying to figure
out how we want to do things attached to guys so that they start right
and all those sorts of things.
But you know, that's not really where we're at at this at this point.
We're not really trying to solve those kind of problems right now.
Once we get to them we'll think about how we want them solved.
Will spec that for the engine.
Push it aside.
And off we go.
I'm not sure if this is true.
I'm assuming you are making the guy clip when leaving the screen but
why make it clip?
If you can just make it Follow the yellow box, which might clip the
guy itself again.
I really sorry.
I'm not sure.
I understand the question.
Yeah, I apologize.
I'm not sure.
I understand the question so I can't really add much to that.
If streaming assets will be required to display, all visual
information.
Will there be some type of manual limit placed on the procedural
generation to ensure that all assets will never be required for a
single room.
Well, that's kind of getting ahead again of where we are.
But the simple answer to that is it depends on what our asset plan is.
It depends whether our assets have a degradation path or not.
And of questions, right?
At the end of questions, how is that possible?
That is just too, that is a good omen people.
Well, ladies and gentlemen, thank you very much for joining me for
another episode of handmade hero.
This was a pretty fun one.
I'm kind of glad we have a little dude moving around.
Now, that's a little bit satisfying and it makes me want him to have a
nice sort of feel as he moves and a nice animation as he moves around.
And so I feel like that kind of
Answers, my question of what we should do next.
I think I definitely do want to go ahead and say let's animate the guy
next and make them have kind of a nice feel as you move them around
because that will basically let me start talking about the math and
let us get into some kind of really interesting stuff.
Yeah, I think that's, that's, that's what we want to do.
So, I think tomorrow what we'll do is we'll end off.
Well, I'll have I'll take a look at my sheet of stuff that we've
postponed.
Tomorrow will basically be our
Clean up day.
We'll just go through everything anything that we want done before
then, and then let's let's just go ahead and say unless there's some
major turnaround over the weekend or something.
Let's just go ahead and say that Monday is going to be our day to
start some serious math action because that's going to power us up a
lot and we're going to need that power for all the stuff that we're
going to want to do.
So, please consider joining us for that for that episode Monday.
8:00 p.m.
PST.
We will be back here.
But if you would like to catch us tomorrow, tomorrow is the stream for
our friends in Europe, obviously, on Fridays.
We always.
Go ahead and do a stream earlier in the morning.
So that people on the time zones, can catch those set of 8, p.m.
Tomorrow's will be 9 a.m.
Pacific Standard time in the morning.
So if you are interested in catching sort of the, the final, the final
step in our, in our current series of handmade hero stuff before we
start the math, please join us tomorrow at 9 a.m.
Pacific Standard Time.
It's a little bit early.
I will be groggy, so will everyone else?
But we'll get through it with a little bit of coffee.
Almond milk.
I suspect and I would love to see you there.
Again, if you are interested in following along at home and you have
not done, so you can always pre-order the game and that comes with the
full source code.
So you can always download every night after we finish programming.
You can always download the latest source code and follow along at
home.
It also comes with the test assets that were using here.
So you can, you know, use those as well and see you can you can kind
of play around with them?
Just like we're doing.
Similarly.
If you want to support the video series.
We have a patreon.
We also have a news or patreon.
I don't actually know you pronounce that I suppose patreon.
I'm not sure.
But you can subscribe to that if you want support the video series and
we have a news and Forum site.
You can go to which has a lot of great information on it.
It's got the schedule for the week posted.
It's got an episode guide with all the previous episodes and people
submit time-coded, sort of jump lists, and you can jump around in
them, which is kind of Handy.
There's a coding resources section, which has Port still there.
Forms are trying to follow along a Linux or Mac has some great
resources for you there.
And of course, there is a code discussion forum.
If you want to ask questions, so please check it out.
If you're trying to learn from the stream, that's a great place to go.
A lot of really helpful, people up there, and people have done some
really great stuff.
So, I highly recommend it.
All right.
Thank you, everyone for joining me and I hope to see you tomorrow and
Monday as well.
So, take it easy, everyone.