Go ahead and start the actual recording here.
Okay.
Hello everyone and welcome to the Thanksgiving Day stream of handmade
hero.
I am feeling a little bit better today.
I'm pleased to report.
I'm hoping that I am actually starting to recover from my illness not
entirely yet.
That's true.
But we're getting a little better.
So I'm hoping that maybe pretty soon here.
I will actually be able to stream to you completely illness free maybe
next week.
Who knows.
Anyway, we are going to be doing are finishing up our sound
programming today.
Just taking a look at the sound output code that we made and you know,
basically trying to go in there and inspect it and make sure that we
don't have bugs in there.
So the sound output code is kind of finicky, direct sounds a bit, a
bit finicky the way that you actually have to use it.
And so we want to kind of go through that and just Shore it up, make
sure that everything is working properly and the and then after that,
if we get done with that, we'll be looking at timers.
So if you're following along today, and you've pre-ordered The Source,
the pre-order, the game and want to follow, along with the source
code, you're going to want to go and get the the
07 zip that is yesterday's source code and you can follow along with
with us on the stream by using that source code here on day eight.
Okay.
So basically, we're just going to jump right back to where we were
yesterday.
I've got a couple of clean up things.
I wanted to talk about that, don't have anything to do with audio, but
we'll get to them later.
If we get to them, they're kind of, on my notebook of just things to
talk about that where I didn't get to yesterday when I was talking
about, because we went right up to the end with sound.
So, here we go.
Here we go.
Basically yesterday what we did is we learned how to basically lock,
our direct sound buffer, which basically asked direct sound to allow
us to write into it to update the contents of the sound, that's being
outputted by the sound card.
And then what we did is we wrote a square wave into it and then we
told directsound to unlock that, basically, saying we're done writing
into it.
You can continue playing now.
Now, the other thing we did, right.
End of the stream in the QA people were asking why there is a pause.
We waited until we actually filled the buffer once in order to play
the sound.
So that, that's why this thing down here was true, because before we
were starting it before, we had actually filled it at all, which
causes a delay and so on.
And so, basically, what we're doing is make sure we had it filled,
then we start kicking it off and we go from there.
So the thing that I want to do today, first of all, is a square.
Wave is a, rather harsh wave.
And so it's a little bit harder to hear if there are bugs in the sound
output.
One of the things, I'll tell you a little story here on the
Thanksgiving stream.
We are not particularly time constrain today, by the way, so we could
go a little longer if we wanted to I'll try not to but we could.
So one of the things that's actually kind of weird about audio and
that you kind of have to just decide to take it on faith when I tell
you this.
If you
Had this experience yourself, then it may sound a little hard to
believe but you're just gonna have to trust me.
It's true and I'll tell you a story so long time ago.
I don't know how many years it was now probably eight years something
like this.
Quite some time ago.
We used to do a thing called the indie game jam and the indie game Jam
was actually the very first game Jam that ever existed.
It was a thing that a bunch of us started.
The very first one was held at Chris Hecker and Sean.
Barrett actually organized it, out of a barn in in Oakland,
California.
And basically it was, it was a long time ago in a bunch of us were
sort of emailing about how computers had just gotten fast enough to
maybe do.
Maybe if we tried, they could maybe render.
I think it was 10,000, or was it a hundred thousand?
It was either 10,000 or 100,000 Sprites on the screen just Sprites
like old-school Sprites.
And so, what we were talking about is well, what kind of games could
you make with 100,000 guys?
And so out of that was born the idea of.
Why don't we just get all the game developers that we know, you know,
all of this kind of the friendly game developers who are all kind of
profession.
They were all.
Everyone was working on AAA games that time.
There was no such thing as an indie scene.
I don't know when this was
2099 something like this, probably the year.
Probably 2000 or 2001.
I would say.
So basically, we got everyone together and we said, all right.
Let's see if everyone comes down for a long weekend.
How many games we could make that just play with the idea of having a
hundred thousand guys?
And so I worked on the engine, for that jam.
I think I did like, a couple things like the camera code and the
loader that loaded, Doom wad files.
That's where we got the Sprites from, and then like,
Sean Barrett did like the renderer for it and stuff.
That would actually try to push 100,000 guys, at once and so on and so
that when everyone got there, there was basically this code that could
go ahead and actually render 100,000 guys and people could sort of
make games with it.
And that was the very first game Jam that there ever was.
And since since then, there's been lots of that, that idea of having a
game Jam or everyone just kind of packs in and makes a bunch of games
has kind of caught on and and there's been lots of game jams, but that
was the first
first one, I think that ever actually existed a concept of a game Jam.
But anyway, a couple years down the road, we had done multiple of
these game jams.
And we got two particular one, the fact, the last one that was ever
held.
I believe it was the last one.
I think it's the last one that was ever held was an audio game jam.
And the idea was games that use audio to basically, to capture the
gameplay.
So the gameplay was going to be or audio oriented and the guy.
Was doing the engine for that one because again, the pattern for the
game jams following that first one was always.
We built an engine before.
Hand.
So that's not part of the jam so that everyone they show up already
has a code base and they're just writing the game piece on top of that
basically.
So, you know, people would volunteer to kind of work on the engine and
that sort of stuff.
So basically what happened is, the person who is going to write the
engine for that one was actually ottman binstock who you may know.
Now.
He's like the Chief Architect at Oculus Rift.
He used to work for valve and then he left to go do Oculus stuff at
Oculus to do.
The 3D headsets.
Anyway, he was writing the sound engine and he was living in Japan at
the time and I had never been to Japan and I had always wanted to go.
So I went out to visit him shortly.
For the indie game.
Jam was supposed to be held and so he was showing me at a cafe in
Japan.
I don't know what's going on because I can't really speak Japanese and
all this stuff.
I'm just, I think it's awesome.
I love Japan.
It was like, probably one of my favorite trips.
If not my favorite trip of all time, go and go into Japan.
So where there were in a cafe in Japan and basically, we sit down and,
of course, since we're in a cafe, the only way to listen to sound is
on the
The the headphones, right?
That are plugged into Ottomans laptop and he's was just like showing
me the engine.
He's like, here's the stuff I built for the audio engine, you know,
got this go at that and he has some pair of headphones that are like
the standard 30 dollar headphones, you know, just random headphones
that you might buy, or that come with them and iPod or something like
that, and iPhone.
And I've got actually quite some time before I actually
I spent quite a bit of money.
I had bought some professional grade headphones when I was working on
sound quite some time ago.
I had actually asked some friends.
I think it was, it might have been John Blow who first recommended
them to me.
He basically said, you know these they're called a domotics there, a
headphone company.
They make these like, you know, headphones or whatever.
They're really, really good, but they're expensive.
So I had bought some and I have them and they are really great.
They're amazing headphones.
I've had the same pair for like a decade now.
And so, he's like, showing this to me and I'm, and he's like, okay,
listen to this and I plug my headphones into his, you know, laptop
Jack.
And I listened to it, and I go ottoman.
You've got a, you've got a bug.
Like you're not quite aligned right on the buffer or something.
You've got a bug, I can hear it.
I can hear.
There's a little click there.
And he like plugs his in because he's got his headphones and heat like
we unplug my earplugs because like I don't know what you're talking
about, the sounds right?
So I'm like, okay, here you go and I give him my headphones.
He puts them in.
He puts the thing into the Jack, he listens for a couple seconds and
goes.
I got to get a better set of headphones.
the moral of this story is,
Would be surprised at exactly how much variance there is in the sound
that comes out of both speakers and headphones.
When you plug them in.
There are different kinds of effects that happen to the sound on the
way out when you plug in a crappy headphones.
Crappy speakers or even good speakers that are going through a system.
Designed to make sound sound, better or smoother or warmer or whatever
you want to call it.
There's a bunch of essentially filtering.
There's a bunch of mutation to the sound that happens and that
mutation, while it may make the sound sound better, or make sound
sound worse, who knows?
Obscures the truth of what is actually getting put out of the lung,
putting put out the line by the computer.
So if you have very subtle bugs that result in very subtle artifacts
in the sound.
It's entirely possible that your sound setup.
May not even allow you to hear them.
That is, how finicky
That's this sort of stuff is small errors in how you feel the sound
buffer.
Small Gap, small differences, can produce frequencies that you can
actually hear on.
And artifacts.
You can actually here on very, very good frequency response, audio
output like, you know headphones speakers whatever.
But that you actually can't hear on Lower quality or smoothing stuff
stuff that that sort of munches with the sound.
And so one thing that's definitely
Certainly true is that if you really, really want to know, if you've
got sound bug Beyond being able to inspect the code and try to verify
things as much as you can.
But if you really want to debug sound code, strangely enough, you kind
of got to invest in a pair of headphones that have really really good
accurate frequency response.
That really accurately produce, the sound reproduce sound because you
may miss the bugs entirely.
Anyway,
Hoffman did fix the bug.
So it was gone by the time of the jam but only because of the
automatic headphones.
So you got to give them props for putting out a good product.
I guess.
Anyway, that's a little story for you, at the beginning of the Stream.
I hope you all enjoyed it.
I'm not much of a Storyteller.
So I'm sure it could have been done in a more exciting way possibly
with visuals.
But you know, what?
Can I say?
All right, so I'm going to go ahead and we'll open up emacs here.
Just so we have our source code at hand in the editor as well.
And then I'm basically going to take a second to talk about and think
about how I want to go about verifying that this code works.
So we've got a lot of moving parts.
R.
There's a lot of things that we have to think about.
First of all, when we come through it, the first time we fill the
entire buffer basically to give it something to play and and then
we're going to go ahead and and kick that off.
So that means as soon as we fill the buffer the first time,
This then we kick it off the playing here.
It starts, playing the sound, which means that that play cursor.
The thing that we're chasing essentially is going to start moving
through the buffer.
It's going to start moving through the buffer and direct sounds going
to be playing what's in that buffer as the play cursor, moves, and
basically our job then because we filled the entire buffer.
So basically our right position is back to zero.
Our job is basically to go look at where that play cursor went to and
then go ahead and and fill up to there.
Now there's some
Complexities and how we do this obviously.
And there's some things that I want to point out that maybe aren't
quite right.
I'll give you an example of something that we're doing here that may
be wrong.
And so maybe we start to clean this code up.
We start to think about these cases, starting to bug it and make sure
what's going on.
But like it was kind of a little hacky, you know, it's test code,
that's fine.
But you know, we're trying to actually pull this out and something
we're going to use eventually.
We got to start thinking about these things.
So one of the things that we're doing, for example, is we get the play
cursor, here.
We take a look at the play.
Cursor is equal to the bite.
Lock.
We assume that we're basically starting out.
Everything's at zero and we're just going to fill now.
Why might that be wrong, right?
Well, one reason, it might be wrong, is because the B to lock and the
play cursor.
Well, we know what B to lock will be.
After we're done, if we write the whole secondary, buffer size.
Then B to lock is basically going to be back at zero, right?
Because it's going to advance one whole buffer size worth, but we're
modding by the buffer size.
So every time we advance it one whole buffer size.
It's back to the exact same position was where it started, which in
this case would be zero.
So if the play cursor has not moved the, next time we get back to
through this Loop, if the play cursor.
Back where it was, we would refill the whole buffer again, which is
totally wrong because the buffer hasn't actually been played.
Does that make sense?
And that could very legitimately happen depending on the system?
Because let's say that we are on a system whose play cursor reporting
isn't particularly accurate.
You have to remember the play cursor is basically an estimate of where
the sound card is, in terms of playing out.
The sound on the speakers in some sense, but we don't actually know
how that's being computed, that
Has a lot to do with what the sound output chip is on your actual
computer.
What the drivers are doing, how frequently they update with direct
sound.
How direct sound in the kernel mixer?
Decide how they're going to report those values when they're going to
report those values, when they're going to service those values.
We have no idea what's going on here and certainly in the old days
that play cursor used to actually be updated very infrequently.
In fact, nowadays.
I suspect it's probably a lot more frequent, the updates that are
coming through it, but it's worth remembering that it could actually
happen that
Doesn't actually advance.
So that's kind of a bug waiting to happen in my opinion.
So this we need a more accurate.
Check van B to lock equals play cursor.
Basically, what we kind of want to do is maybe write something that's
a little more intelligent and looks to see wants to see that play
cursor advance of
It and know that it has actually been updated before we actually fill
it again.
Like one thing we could do trivially perhaps to increase the
reliability of this code would be to check to make sure that in two
times through the loop.
We have seen a different play cursor, like don't take any action until
we actually see that play cursor move because the play cursor hasn't
moved then.
We are in a situation where we really don't know what's going on and
we probably shouldn't be touching the buffer.
Excuse me.
Still sick getting better, but still sick.
It is true.
Okay, so that's something that we need to take a look at certainly
something to think about.
The other thing that I want to do.
And the first thing that I think we're going to do here, is that a
square wave is actually not a particularly good wave for hearing
errors.
And the reason it's a very harsh wave.
You can actually just tell just by looking at the square wave.
And for those of you here yesterday, you know what the square wave is
but I'll I'll just bring it up again just to refresh your memory.
A square wave is basically completely harsh cut.
It's full-on followed by full off, Paul by full-on, or I should say,
full positive, followed by full -.
And if you think about that, that basically introduces, this really
hard.
It's very unnatural.
That's not something that you're probably ever.
Actually going to see in the real world.
Right?
Sound is a lot smoother, normally.
And so that's just a bad thing to test against.
We don't really know what that should sound like intuitively.
We probably can't hear errors and it very well.
So, the first thing that I want to do and I didn't do this originally
because I didn't want to try to, I didn't want to complicate the
Well Nation by starting to talk about transcendentals and and things
like this is we're going to actually switch to a sine wave, a sine
wave.
Obviously is very familiar to most people and you've probably seen it.
If you've ever taken high school math, at least in the United States.
Typically everyone has to go through trigonometry, which means that
you'll have seen something like a sine wave.
A sine wave is basically a continuous periodic wave that just kind of
Loops up and down.
Very smooth, very continuous and it is up sounds to your ear like a
very pure tone.
Is like the most pure sounding tone that you can really hear.
It's like this.
Perfect.
Smooth.
No noise.
No you, no, harshness to it.
It's like a very warm pure tone.
And so what I'd like to do is basically just first switch over to a
sine wave because I think we'll have an easier time hearing the
errors.
If we switch over to a sine wave for, for our, for our
For our sound output.
So that's the first thing we're going to do.
And in order to do that.
We need to change the way that we're Computing our sample value.
Because remember, our sample value is currently being computed as a
square wave.
So we're going to go ahead and and change this Square wave period to
just wave period and a half Square.
Wave period to half wave period because now we're going to actually
not be talking about a square wave anymore.
We are going to be talking about a sine wave.
So if we actually go in here, the first thing that
Have to understand is basically we're going to be seeing
floating-point numbers for the first time.
And I'm not going to try to explain them fully here because we don't
really need to understand them fully to do this.
But there's something that's going to come up again in the Stream
actually fairly soon that we will have to start understanding in a
little more detail.
So this is just your first introduction to them.
Don't worry about them too much, but try to start getting acquainted.
Basically, what I like to do, like everything else is, I like to have
a typedef for them because I like to be able to specify the size.
Explicitly, basically, the types that I use for them are real 32.
And real 64.
Those are those are the two types that I use and basically, they
correspond to the two built-in types for C and C++, which are float
and double now, afloat is 32 bits wide and a double is 64 bits wide on
the machines that we're talking about here.
And basically, that is usually true across a lot of platforms because
there's a thing called the IEEE standard for floating point and it
actually specifies.
How that
At how the floats work and how they work in 32 bit.
So you can actually take a look here.
If you look this up, you can actually see.
There's, there's a whole spec for these sorts of things that you can
look at this.
It's it's not, it's basically it's, it's a very rigorously defined
thing.
I guess.
It's how I would say it.
So there's not a lot of flexibility across platforms with how the
actual math works out.
When you're operating on these values.
There's they're actually a very rigorous
This definition for how all the math has to be worked out.
There's reasons behind all of it will refer to some of it as we go
through the stream.
But a lot of the minutiae here, there's a lot of minutiae to floating
Point math.
There will probably never get to stuff that you only really care about
in scientific Computing or very delicate numerical algorithms, where
you care about stuff like, is something positive or negative zero.
And yes, ladies gentleman, there is such a thing as positive or
negative zero, and the IEEE, and there's good reasons for it to
reasons that.
That I don't necessarily pretend to understand very deeply because
some of the people who came up with this stuff.
We're really crazy good at thinking about computer math and all of the
ramifications of it for computing, actual math.
It's scary how much thought went into some of these things and if
you're into that sort of stuff, I highly recommend reading about the
history of it.
And so on it's it's actually very fascinating but we're not going to
go into that today or possibly ever.
We're only going to kind of touch on them a little bit.
Further out.
So we are going to go ahead and include math.h.
And this is just something again for test code in the actual code that
we actually right.
We are probably going to take the time to not use the C runtime
library for for floating Point operations that we're about to use the
C runtime library for here.
They're built in
Basically, if you want to call sign, if you want to call cosine, to
want to called tangent or anti tangent, these sorts of things, they
are actually built into the C runtime library and sometimes they are
built into the CPU.
But some of them aren't built into the CPU.
And one of the things that I was kept harping on on the stream over
and over is that we're not going to use any libraries.
And so even though some of these may be built in some of them may not
be built in etcetera, Etc.
What I want to do sort of
The stream proper after we get out of the platform layer because I
want to actually show you how to implement some of these things
yourself directly.
So for, at the moment because we're focusing on sound, we're going to
go ahead and allow ourselves to use that sign function for testing
purposes.
But when we actually go to implement the actual game, when we want to
sign a cosine, I'm going to show you a little bit more about how those
things are computed.
And the things that we should actually be aware of to implement them
ourselves.
I think that'd be a good idea.
I realize it's a little bit Overkill a lot of
People watching the stream or probably like, that's ridiculous.
But, you know, like I said, we're trying to use know libraries.
So we'll probably actually not use any libraries, but for test code,
you're allowed to call anything you want.
If you want to test code, is just basically about testing stuff as
efficiently as possible.
And so if you've got it, you can use it that is totally fine much.
Like here in the platform layer.
We use all courts sorts things like output debug string.
When you're on a particular platform, always feel free to use whatever
that platform gives you.
Get your test code up and running and that sort of stuff that is
always totally fine.
Obviously as well.
And in general like I've said sorry to harp on this but using
libraries and stuff is fine too.
Some people have been getting the impression that I say don't ever use
libraries and I think that that's not true.
The only reason we're not using any libraries on this stream is just
because I want to show you how everything is done.
Not because I think there's anything wrong with libraries there.
A couple libraries that I even like and I use Sean Barrett's libraries
the stb libraries I've used in code many times and I love them.
So yeah, there's nothing wrong with
Libraries, it's just we're going to be trying to make sure that we
really don't rely on any interactional game code because I just want
to show you how to build your own stuff.
Okay, so we want to compute a sample value, that's going to be a sine
wave.
So basically how this actually works is, we're going to have one of
our floating Point values here.
That's going to be the sine value that comes back, right?
We are going to have a signed value.
That's in floating point.
The reason that we're going to do that is because all of these
advanced math functions of transcendental, sine cosine, tangent, those
sorts of things.
They do not operate on integers by default because all of these
things, the mathematical definition for them is stuff like, you know,
sign returns a value between negative one and one that is just the
mathematical definition typically of how signed works you pass in an
angle, right?
If you remember your trigonometry you pass in an angle, the angle is
usually in radians, but you could also think of the angle is being in
degrees and then convert to radians computers work in radians, but
sometimes math classes teach things in degrees.
So six of one half dozen of the other.
Is convert between them.
A point being you pass in an angle in radians, and you get back.
From that a value between negative 1 and 1.
So obviously an integer would not be a very useful thing to return
this in because it only has negative 1 0 and 1 as values.
And you need all the values in between, you need all those fractional
values.
Now one thing they could have done is decided to multiply it out, so
that it actually returned like - 4 billion to positive, 4 billion or
sorry - 2 billion to positive 2 billion as the values and then, you
know, blah, blah, blah, but because if you're using sine and cosine,
you're almost.
Oh, he's
With very mathy code and mathy code is almost always written in
floating Point.
All of the math functions natively work in floating Point as well.
And we are mostly going to be doing our math and floating-point to
because modern processors have a lot, a lot of horsepower designed to
facilitate floating Point math, and we want to take advantage of that.
It used to be in the old days.
In fact, when I was growing up, my favorite computer to program on to
get.
This is a very Marie under extreme today.
That's by Design.
I apologize for boring people with my stories, but I'm going to
Tell him.
Anyway, sometimes it's the coffee.
I had some coffee.
This morning makes me very loquacious.
It's true.
I think coffee has a similar effect of alcohol.
Perhaps where you start to think your stories are really interesting
even though they're no more interesting than before you drank the
coffee.
But here's the thing.
I used to have an Amiga computer.
I said this on the stream before and I loved programming on that
thing, but one of the interesting things about computers that time
specially home, computers at that time.
They oftentimes didn't have any floating Point operations in the
actual Hardware, the 68000 CPU, which is what power the original Amiga
Amiga 500 Mega 2000, Mega 1000.
Those did not have
Have what's called a floating Point Unit and FPU.
They did not have one in there.
And so they actually could not natively compute.
Anything in floating Point, all of their computations were done with
integer.
And if you wanted floating Point operations, that meant it had to be
implemented.
Essentially, using integer arithmetic that simulated, the floating
Point math, which is obviously very expensive.
Much more expensive because you're doing a lot of operations to
simulate.
Essentially, one operation, you want to do a floating-point multiply
you got to do a bunch of integer work to make that happen.
You're basically doing
What the CPU would be doing internally.
So in the old days people used what was called fixed point.
And what fixed point is, is it's basically a way of dividing up your
integer into pieces.
And you know, what?
Because it's sort of worked.
And I'm not going to use the word so well, because so, well would be
kind of kind of overstating the case, but because it worked at all,
let's just use that phrase because it worked at all for our audio.
The other day, when I was drawing out to you, what we were doing.
I'm going to go ahead and go over here to the diagram and just kind of
draw out for you, what I mean, so that's a little clearer.
So if you imagine
And basically we've got I like drawing these little hash marks with
either side.
As you know, everything can be that this was a sound buffer yesterday
today.
This is going to be a 32-bit integer, right?
So basically what happens in a 32-bit integer, right?
And, you know, usually look at him.
This is going to be the 31st bit up here.
And this is going to be the zeroeth, bit down here, right?
That's where we're at.
And we've got, we can basically chunk this up into even parts that are
8 Bits, each.
This is B 0, right.
This is b, 1 b, 2, and B 3, right?
That's what we've got.
Basically.
These are B here, each one's 8 Bits.
So if you take a look at this, 32-bit integer, there's a number of
ways that we could imagine.
Ajan, that it was divided.
Right?
What we've been doing so far is we've either been assuming that it's
unsigned, which means that all of the bits just act together to give
you one value.
So there's the 0 B, the one, the sorry, there's the, the one bit that
there's the bit that if it is, set it equals 1, then the one that's
equal 2, then 4, then 8, then 16 32 64 128, 256, 512 etcetera,
etcetera, right?
And you add all those up together and that's your number.
So if you have the
Item, 3, B, set, you know that your actual value is the one plus, the
2 plus the for, right?
We went over this in the intro to see stream.
Hopefully, everyone's familiar with the binary encoding there.
That's how we been doing it.
And then sometimes we've used negative numbers and negative numbers
use, what's called two's complement.
And that's basically where you have the high bit is set, you know,
it's a negative number and then the rest of these are encoded in a way
that basically makes.
So, the mass still works out for negatives.
You interpret them say differently.
We didn't actually talk about to accomplish on the stream.
We should probably do a string about that at some point.
But it's not germane at the moment.
So we're just going to skip that bleeping.
That's all we've done though.
So far.
Now there's other things we could have done with our 32-bit integer.
Let's say that we actually wanted to store some fractional Precision
here.
Let's say that we wanted to do something like have a number, so we
have a number, right?
Like we would in math, but with a decimal point and then a fractional
part that comes after it, right?
Well, one thing that we could do, if we
To do that is we could imagine that we just separated up our bits into
this part, right and this part so we could say, we could just
arbitrarily say, okay.
Let's say the bottom eight bits, are the fraction, right?
And then the top 24 bits are the number, right?
So this is a number up here this 24-bit number, which means it can be
up to like 16 million, right?
So, we have zero to 16 million in the top part and then down here we
Of zero to 256.
And so we just assume that we have a well 255 I should say, right?
So we just assume that we have whatever this number is in the top, 20
for a b.
And then we have a fraction that is essentially whatever this number
is will call this.
Number F.
Let's say for fraction.
We have F over 256.
So our number is whatever.
Our number is in the top 24 bits, this thing, plus whatever.
This thing was divided by 256.
You see how we could we
Would encode it that way and you can see how that be pretty easy to
abstract a to extract as well.
If we wanted to just know what the top number is.
We could just shift this down, shift this down by eight.
Right?
So the whole number we'll call the entire number W.
Let's say, if the whole number was shifted down by eight bits, it
would knock out the fraction and leave us with just the actual number.
So we know our whole number very quickly, that's called truncation.
It gets rid of the fraction entirely, right?
It just gives us back the number.
We could also round the number if we wanted to, we could add right
half of this.
We could add 256 over 2 or whatever, right?
Actually, it's actually technically 255 over 2.
So P 127, right?
We could add 127 to the bottom, which would mean that if it was 128 or
higher, right?
It would wrap and add one into here, it would carry into their right
and that would increment our whole number by one.
If it
If it was less than that, then it wouldn't carry.
It would just stay in here.
When we did the ad, we could do that ad, then do the shift which would
have the effect of rounding, right?
So truncation would be this.
This is truncation right here, right?
That's truncation.
And rounding is just W.
Plus the fraction total over 2, then we shift it down by eight, right?
Hopefully, I'm, you know, I'm this is not a complete explanation
either.
Hopefully that kind of makes them.
Sense, right.
You see how that could kind of work and then we're basically doing a
bunch of math on numbers that are encoded this way.
There's some other stuff you have to do with multiplication.
You have to worry about the shifting because you've got an extra
decimal place and all this sort stuff.
I won't really cover that.
But basically, this is called fixed point, right?
Oops, fixed point.
Fixed Point math, and this was something that people did back in the
day in order to avoid doing really expensive, floating Point math,
when they didn't have a floating-point coprocessor, that is fixed
Point.
That's how that works.
It's called fixed point because you have set an arbitrary fixed place
where the decimal occurs in your number, that is how it works.
You can never have more than 256.
Levels of your fraction, no matter what the number is and you can
never have any more than 6 B 6 million here because you only had 24
bits.
So, wherever you pick, you could change that decision by moving this
around, but whatever the line is that you pick to write your math.
At you, basically are fixing the amount of fraction versus the size of
the number that you can have.
Does that make sense?
So what floating point is is floating point is a more powerful
representation that basically allows you more flexibility at the cost
of having the Precision of your operations vary depending on the
values involved.
And basically what it is is it's a different way of dividing up those
bits.
So, floating-point works completely differently.
It's actually completely different.
Conceptually then fixed Point.
Really how it works.
Is this divided up in a way that looks sort of like this.
We have a thing called the mantissa which goes down here and that is
back.
This is basically a number that tells us only a fraction of one.
So it's basically a number between 0 and 1.
That is, that is how that works.
Essentially, in here.
It's shouldn't say.
It's not sure how to
Explain this.
Well, it's not really a number between 0 and 1.
It's basically a value here.
Here's how you know, what, here's how say this is, this is this is
much clearer to what it actually is.
If you imagine a number, that's like one point something and there's a
decimal out here, right?
So we basically have one point, you know, two, three, five nine, four,
seven, eight, six, whatever, right?
Some some fraction out here.
We're the mantissa is a bunch of bits that stores.
This
It's the part that stores, the fraction.
The one is not stored.
It's just assumed to be there.
So it's just the fractional part.
That's the mantissa, a fraction of this one.
Okay, then so the mantissa is here and then we have the exponent up
here.
This is an exponent.
So basically this is if, you know like an exponent, if you have
something like x to the fourth power, that is an exponent, right?
It's something that raises something ^.
So, we have the exponent.
And then we have the sign bit.
The sign bit is either 0 or 1 depending if the thing is negative or
positive, right?
That's based.
That's all that.
That's all.
That means.
The exponent is a power of 2 that says how big this number is.
So essentially, whatever this exponent is here, whatever this,
whatever this value is.
It's basically saying, if, you know, if this is n, it's 2 to the N,
that's, that's what it is, right?
And then this is the actual, this is the actual fractional value.
What this allows you to do.
You, is it basically allows you to separate the degree of precision
you have, in specifying the number, which is always going to be,
however, big, the mantissa is from the scale of the value, which is
specified here in the exponent.
So, this tells you the magnitude of the number expressed as a power of
2, and this tells you the actual value of the number, which will
become bigger or smaller depending on,
On what this is.
So if this is high right, if the exponent is high.
Then basically the mantissa encodes a much lower amount of precision
for the value, right?
Because whatever the fraction is, however, much Precision.
The fraction has in here, you're basically moving it up to a place in
the number based on this end, right?
So let's say this n is like 50 or something, right?
That then you're taking two to the 50th, right?
That's a very Heart.
High number and you're multiplying this other value.
You buy that.
So even if it had a lot of fractional B even had a lot of even though
that fraction is very specific.
It's moving up into the whole number part because of this giant
multiplication on the other hand, right if this number is negative,
right?
Because this this, this exponent can be negative as well.
Right?
If this number is negative, then you're moving it down because again
to to like the negative n, right?
To to a negative number is basically creating the opposite.
It's making
Optional values it's making its dividing out because that's the way
exponents work.
And this is just a suit.
I'm assuming you basically no exponents here.
So what you're doing with that exponent is your sort of sliding this
decimal point around.
So what ends up happening with the floating Point representation is
you basically have a situation where you've got one point, you know,
2359 847, whatever you've got some fractional value here and you're
taking the point with that exponent.
This is this
Specified in the mantissa, right?
So this is just, this is just represented in the mantissa.
You're taking this point, and you're sliding it by that exponent.
However, many places the exponent is.
So if the exponent is negative, right, you're sliding it this way,
you're making it more of a fraction.
You're making it point zero zero zero zero zero, zero one or
something, right?
If the exponent is negative.
This is a negative exponent, and if the exponent is positive, you're
sliding it this way, right?
So you're making it bigger.
You're making it 1 million.
In something, blah, blah, blah, right, or whatever.
And that's why it's called floating point is because the decimal point
is essentially, floats.
It's no longer fixed.
It's not fixed Point anymore.
It's floating point.
And what that means is when you do math with floating Point, you're
basically always guaranteed the same amount of relative Precision.
No matter what your values are, right, you're always essentially
getting the same amount of significant figures.
If you will write, if you ever saw that term, you're sort of getting
That sort of equivalent of scientific significant figures in some
sense where you're saying, however, many bits of mantissa, the
floating Point format.
You're using happens to have.
And again, you can see there's, there's 32 bit floating point 64 bit
floating point.
So the size, the Precision varies, depending on how big, the total
thing was, basically you're getting a certain amount of significant
figures, which depends.
Let me test a size, a certain degree of scale, possibilities,
depending on how many bits are in the exponent, right?
And then you can do math at any, any scale allows.
Allowed by that exponent will have the same number of relatives and if
configures.
So, if it's a very high number, right, let's say, you know, it's some,
again, we have to 3598, 47, whatever, and this is some really big
number, right?
It's some number.
That's huge.
Like this.
We're still getting the same number of significant figures essentially
right here, as we would, if we encoded that in a in a different way.
That was very very small, right?
If we use the different exponent for it, right?
Here's the same.
Number.
But we slid it down quite a bit.
Right?
We have the exact same number of significant figures, no matter what
the scale is.
We're never getting any more than that.
We don't, once we get up to the scale.
We can't even encode.
What the values are that?
Go all the way, the decimal point.
There might be tons of zeros here and we have no idea what they should
have been because we can encode that and same as here.
We can't know what any of these things are because we've pushed it
down too far, but that's basically how that works.
Right now again, I'm drawing this.
All in decimal.
I'm writing .000 as if they're decimals and then these are all decimal
numbers.
Right, and that's not really the case because this is all binary.
So really these would be things like point 0, 0, 1 0 1 0 0, 1 0 1, you
know that sort of stuff but you get the idea.
It works exactly the same.
You're still moving a decimal point around that has to do with that.
So hopefully that makes some sense.
Oh, I'm sorry.
I just checked the stream.
I'm I guess I'm talking too loudly today.
I should I should quiet myself down perhaps.
Maybe.
I'm getting a little to cough it up.
Getting a little too caffeine and I'm clipping.
Sorry about that.
I'll try to calm down.
Make it much calmer tone.
Okay.
So basically that that is basically the the way that floating-point
works and we'll talk about this a little bit more as we go.
So I can kind of explain what's going on with the floating Point
numbers, and why you have
Understand some of these things because obviously this is all kind of
minutiae.
The processor is doing it for you now.
So basically, what we are able to do with modern processors, that we
couldn't do say on the Amiga, which didn't have an FPU.
They actually later added one in the 60, 80 30.
So if you bought like an Amiga 3000, which was a later version of the
Amigas, they had FB use that could do some floating Point math.
Nowadays.
Everything does floating Point math.
Your graphics card does floating Point math.
Your CPU can do floating Point math.
And in fact, most of the Computing horsepower in your computer is
often dedicated to doing floating Point math, because floating Point.
Math is where most calculations happen.
Now.
Certainly all 3D Graphics runs through floating Point math.
Almost every stage of the pipeline is very heavily.
Floating-point.
Now certainly all scientific Computing.
Almost always uses floating Point math.
Although, there are certain cases where integer math gets used and so
on.
So,
Any point, map is one of the most important features of a CPU now,
even though they couldn't do them the old days.
They now have tons of horsepower for horsepower for it.
So again, even though we're taking a very handmade approach to this
fixed Point even in that case is a very bad idea because really what
you want to be doing.
Now, if you're trying to be efficient and trying to be down to the to
the CPU level is you want to be using floating point because that is
where the horsepower exist at almost every level of computing.
Now, is that
Floating point.
We may we're going to encounter some some problems on the Raspberry
Pi.
I think because I know there's some Delicacies with floating point
there.
So that'll be a bit of a battle.
Certainly, but for the most part in, any modern thing that you would
ship a game on, there is a ton of floating-point horsepower.
Even mobile devices, have a ton of floating-point, floating-point
horsepower.
All right.
We're gonna going to end that their clothes are mspaint session and we
are going to go back to creating our sine wave.
Now, a sine wave is obviously very simple.
I showed you what it looked like, all we need to do to get our sine
value is, we just have to call sign and we have to call it with where
we were in in the period of the sine function.
Basically another's two versions of sign.
I can show you what they are.
There's sign and I sign f.
Hoping if I do sign FL come up with both of them.
Yeah, here we go.
Here's in the msdn documentation.
So you can see here.
Here's the sine functions, right?
There's basically a sign F, which takes a float and returns a float.
Those are 32.
That's a 32-bit sign.
And then there's a double sign which is a 64-bit version of the same
thing.
There's 64 bit floating point.
When you want more precision, and there's a 32-bit when you don't need
as much, we will probably never really use 64-bit Precision for most
stuff in the game, but it's worth noting that it's there.
It's slower.
Always pretty much there.
It's very rare that you can do 64.
Bit floating Point math, as fast as you can do, 32 bit floating Point
math.
Usually, that's true these days because basically of Cindy, we won't
get into that too much.
But basically, you can you tend to be able to do twice, as many
floating Point operations, as you can double operations, because of
the way the processors work nowadays, so, it's usually best not to go
double.
Unless you really know, you need that extra precision.
And in this case, we definitely don't and foremost, the game, we
aren't.
Going to need it.
So you probably want to stay away from that.
So we're going to call sign F, and we basically need to know where we
are.
We basically are in some position.
In the sine wave which typically in math is called T.
Usually T is the you know the value that's kind of the running time
value for your sign.
So we need to compute whatever that is.
But once we get our sine value back, remember our sine value is going
to be a number between 0 and negative 1 and 1, but we actually want a
value, that goes between tone volume and negative tone volume.
So, what we need to do is we basically need to cast to an inch 16, but
we first need to take our sine value and we need to multiply
Apply it by the volume so that it will take it from us negative one to
one version of our sine value.
And why is it doing that?
Why are you?
Why are my keyboard is overzealous today?
I don't know why that's very interesting.
Is that there we go a little bit better.
Okay.
So basically what we're trying to do is basically just scale R sine
wave from negative 1 to 1 up to the the tone volume so that it can be
mapped into the 16-bit space properly.
That makes sense.
Okay.
So basically what we want to do here is we want to say okay we're
going to do that.
We're going to let that go ahead and put that back into our sample
value.
We don't care about rounding at this point.
So we're going to ignore.
We're going to talk about that at the moment.
And basically we don't need this anymore, which is R square wave
generator and we'll go ahead and copy this down here.
After we're done.
We need to collapse these two Loops eventually Hazard to do.
That's our to do says.
So basically in our T.
We know that we already have running sample index, which
Keeps going up and up and up.
So that is essentially our T value.
But if we were to use that as the T value, the period of sine, right?
I believe is pie, right?
Let's let's let's take a look here.
So sign if you take a look at the actual scale of this thing, you can
see that the the, the period will the half period is pi, right?
So one cycle is pie, and two cycles is 2 pi.
So are half period.
I guess we don't have to
More about a half period, we can literally just go with our period.
Now since our period is going to be 2 pi, right?
Basically, what we want to do is say as this thing goes up to whatever
the whatever the actual period was going to be, which we computed
right.
Here's our wave period, whatever.
Our and we don't actually need this value anymore.
The halfway period just doesn't need to be used.
So whatever our wave period is basically we have to say the
The running sample index /.
The wave, period.
Right.
Gives going to map that into a number from 0 to 1, you know, as we go
through the wave, it'll be zero.
One, two, three, four, just like we did before the divide that tells
us where we are in the period.
But what we want to do here is we want to actually convert these two
floating Point first, so that now, we actually have smooth values that
run from 0 to 1 fractional as we go through, I may have to diagram.
It's out for you.
I realize this is a little complicated and we
Done stuff like this before.
So I'm going to actually, I'm going to do it to do.
Draw this out for people, so they can see it.
And then we need to multiply by the period.
We actually wanted, which was to pie.
Now.
We don't actually have a value for pi yet.
So the other thing we need to do is actually do a pound defined for
pie.
So here is our pi32 that's going to be some real 32 value.
And basically, what we need to do is get the digits of pi.
By and put them in there.
Now.
I don't know exactly how many digits we need for a floating-point pie.
I'm going to go ahead and see if that's enough.
Let's see here.
Why do I always reverse?
The order of things doesn't matter, compiler is catch to it.
So it's good.
So basically, what we're doing here is we're just transforming the
period of running sample index into the period of sine.
We're calling sign.
We're multiplying it by the tone volume, and that's our sample value.
Print should be pretty straightforward.
I don't think they'll be too much confusion.
Using there, but again, finicky code.
I make a lot of stupid errors when I write code like this, even when
I'm not streaming.
So we may have to do a little bit of debugging here.
Everyone brace, your ears.
It is time to listen to our sound, which could be totally messed up.
Let's see what it sounds like.
Why am I not hearing anything?
What did I do?
Did I do something?
Oh, yes.
We forgot to actually increment R value.
I should just leave that down there as we play with this.
There we go.
So I can hear immediately A scratchiness in that, right?
And that is, I mean, obviously we could have messed up our sine value,
certainly.
But assuming that, that is actually, assuming that that scratchiness
is actually in there without the fact that we've messed up the sine
value that is sort of revealing, the fact that there is clearly a bug
in our wave output, which is what I wanted to do because that's pretty
sure there was.
But you know, I wanted to actually make sure that we knew that.
So now we can actually go about starting to bug.
That's the first thing to do, is to verify that our sine wave makes
some sense.
Okay.
So one thing we could actually do if we wanted, to is actually draw
the sine wave out on the screen, which is probably what I would do in
a normal circumstance.
And I'm not sure if I want to do it now and because we'll have to sort
of explain a bunch of drawing things to get there.
But the other thing that we can do is we can kind of look at this
code, inspection wise, first of all, just step through it once.
Make sure that we understand what's going on.
The other thing we can do is not fill the buffer.
So basically, we know we had a one second buffer.
So the very first thing I'm going to do is just never fill it again.
So basically what I'm going to do here is this sound is playing this
thing that says if not sound is playing that sound is playing.
I'm just going to use that as a latch to only update the buffer once.
So basically what we do is here is say instead of calling get
competition.
I'm going to say if the sound is not playing and you are able to get
that cursor position, then go ahead and fill that buffer, right?
So basically I'm going to do this.
So what you can hear?
Now, please.
I hope you can hear this.
If you can hear it.
We hear only one skip to hear that.
Solid tone and Skip and how far is it?
Apart?
1, s 1 2 3 4 5 here that, right.
So when you hear that, what we now know what that has determined
right?
Is that we have a bug in how we fill the buffers, where the sign lines
up when we fill those buffers, right?
We know that our sine wave is actually outputting correctly because
our sine wave when we listen to it.
When we when we listen to the sine wave just filling the buffer.
Once it sounds like a pure tone, correct, and the only time it has a
skip
Is at the end of that one second buffer, which is where it Should
Skip.
Because the, we didn't do anything to make sure that the sine wave
wraps properly from the end of the buffer to the beginning.
So, there's a hard Gap there.
Right?
So, basically, we've now determined rather definitively that, at least
our sign out, put this code right here is working properly.
What's not working properly is either the way that these two things
are Gap together because remember, we're only testing one path.
In fact, we can sort of see that here when we come through and do this
the first time, right?
Right?
When we get this back, our region R2 region sizes.
Let's take a look at those here region.
One size region to size.
You can see that because we're locking the whole buffer that first
time through, because it's not playing yet, and we're just filling the
whole thing up.
You can see that we only do one region feel so we're only doing this
Phil.
So we could have a bug here as well.
That's entirely on the table.
We have not real that out.
But we know that we either have a bug there, or we have a bug in how
this stuff is.
Dating because we're basically saying when we start to actually fill
the buffer up incrementally afterwards, we're introducing a lot of
Skips.
That should not be there.
Right?
Does that make sense?
And so there's a bunch of things that could be wrong about that one.
Is that we could be doing this, Phil wrong one, is that we could be
incrementing, our sample index that wrong so that we're thinking we
should be when the place that we're actually writing into is not the
place that we should actually be.
According to where we are on the sine wave.
There's a lot of things.
Things we could be doing wrong.
And so now we have to kind of go figure out what those are.
Okay.
So, first thing we want to check is just let's go through the code and
just verify that we actually think we know what's going on here.
We know we have basically a buffer that's going to be 48,000 samples
long, which is going to be 48 thousand times for because in terms of
bytes, right?
That's the that's the bytes per sample.
So when we init.d sound were expecting to pass 48,000 here and
Forty-Eight thousand times for here.
So, let's go ahead and just
Ben and will kind of walk through the code will sort of analyze it
line by line to make sure that we understand what's going on.
Have to actually start it running again.
There we go.
So when we pass it in here, let's take a look.
That should be 48,000.
I'm going to switch out a hexadecimal display here.
Samples per second, should be 48,000.
It is secondary, buffer size should be four times that that looks
about right for X 48,000.
Yep.
That looks right.
That's what we expect.
So, our buffer is one second long, and it's playing at 48.
Which is what we wanted.
We come in here.
We process our messages and then we're going to go here to fill our
buffer.
The sound is not playing.
Yet we go in here to fill the buffer are running.
Sample index should be 0 and it is our bites per sample should be for.
Now.
Why is this not parenthetical though?
That bothers me a little bit because that should be, that should be a
parenthesis right there.
And that's, that is not, that is not how I would normally write that
code.
So II messed that up because the operator precedence, to be honest
with you.
I don't even remember what the operator.
Precedence is between these two operators.
I would never leave that be.
So let's double-check our operator precedence there since it came up.
Operator precedence.
See
And let's see if it's got it here.
Where is the mod?
Operator people?
Where is it?
It's right there.
So these are left to right.
So in theory, that's not a bug but it's so it would have been
operating properly but I don't like that at all.
I don't like to leave things like that to chance.
I don't like to be the kind of person who just memorizes the operator
precedence, and always embeds that in the code.
I think it's a lot easier for other people, as well as yourself to
read code.
That looks like that.
So, you know, unequivocally that's what they meant, and there's
Problem that don't worry about the five-minute warning today people
because like I said, this is going to be am kind of Meandering stream
on a holiday.
So we're going to go ahead and blow straight through that.
There will be a Q&A.
We will probably just take our the whole Q&A, right?
The Whole 30 minutes normally for you a to finish what we were doing
just kind of get comfortable and then we will have a Q&A after that as
well.
Alright, so basically we've got the bites to lock here.
That looks like a correct computation to me the b 2 lakh rather they
see what
Are doing is you're saying, whatever our sample index was times the
number of bytes per sample, modded by the entire buffer size should
be, where we are in the buffer.
That seems like a solid computation to me.
I feel like that that is relatively straightforward.
I'm going to go ahead and recompile that here and then I am going to
step back to here.
And I am actually, oh, you know, the thing I would do is I'm going to
remove our check there so that we actually can step through twice.
Because what I'd like to do is I'd like to verify
I that this wraps around 20 again the second time through.
So the first time through we compute that b to lock and it's 0 the
second time through, I would like to verify that it's zero again and
it is.
So that's good.
That's what I wanted to see and want to make sure that the sample
index would go up by 48k and it did and that all looks roughly,
correct.
Okay.
So let's move on to thinking about something else.
So I think that running sample index looks kind of okay to me so far.
You never do know if the bite to lock.
Equals the play cursor.
That should only happen that one time at the moment.
Like I said, it's a little iffy.
We've got the to do in there, but I'm going to go ahead and try to
verify that.
It only happens the one time.
Oh, no.
See, look at that.
We've already found a problem.
Why is that happening?
Why is the play cursor and the B to lock?
Always the same?
Oh, you know, huh?
Oh, that's funny.
That is very interesting.
So I think basically, what's happening is exactly what this to do,
said would happen.
Basically, we are writing.
Up to the play cursor and then we always find that the play cursor has
not Advanced.
By the time we get through the loop.
The second time.
That is what's happening.
I think so really.
We just have to make sure that the bite to lock is behind the play
cursor.
Always, if it is not, so if it's above the play cursor, that's okay.
That means the play cursor.
We have sort of wrapped around it.
But if we're equal to the play cursor, that's actually something that
maybe we're going to have to start, just not doing anything because
we're assuming that
We've already caught up and we're fine.
So really that should probably look like this.
So we're going to do a little bit of a hack here.
If sound is playing.
If sound is not playing, we're going to do that and I'm just going to
double-check what that sounds like real quick.
Okay, so that already eliminated, one of our problems.
You can tell that it's very different already.
We still got problems, but that was definitely wrong.
So, alright, so let's think about this for a second.
So what we should probably do is start pulling this out into a little
bit less hacky a little bit more correct code, so that we can do stuff
like fill our buffer control, how we're feeling our buffer, a little
more explicitly so we can call it in here.
So let's go ahead.
I'm just going to pull this out here.
I'm going to make a little struct.
Called struct and then 32 sound output.
And I'm just going to wrap these values up in there.
I'm going to pull them out of there, so that we can have a little more
granular control over what's going on.
So all of these sound values that we had, they're all going to come
out into here.
Right?
And I'm going to actually have those default set set outside.
So here we go.
And some code we got to set up our stuff here.
So if we make a win32 sound output, this is our sound output
structure.
T', we can go ahead and then output are sorry.
Set.
All the values to what we were setting them to like this.
Here we go.
Set the wave period, set the B 4 sample set, the buffer size.
There we go.
And these guys now have to be based on this.
So we're going to set all that stuff up.
So that's good.
And then we are going to go ahead and make this initialization code
happened down there.
So let's get
Of these because you can't actually do those.
You can't funnily enough.
You could actually leave those in.
I think now that I think they added the C++, 11 standard added, some
abilities to to specify default values like that.
So you could have you could have actually left that in there
technically.
So we're going to go ahead and move that down into here.
So, basically, we're going to create one of these and we're going to
fill it out like that.
So that's good.
We are going to now call win32 and it D sound with those values.
So now, we'll initialize them straight out of the sound output.
And that's fine.
And then what we'll do is, we're going to make our buffer fill stuff.
We're going to actually make that buffer fill stuff, be something that
we can call.
And we can give it a little bit more of guidance about what we
actually want to do.
So this buffer fill stuff right here.
Basically this part right here.
We are going to pull out into something that can kind of be called in
different ways at different times so that we can be a little more
explicit about it and see what's going on.
So, let's see when three to fill sound buffer, like this.
And that's going to take one of these sound outputs.
Like that, there we go.
And then it will take the two parameters that were passed here before
the B to lock and the B to, right?
It'll basically pass those in here, right?
See that?
So we're basically just extracting that code out again.
I like I said, I'm a big fan of just pulling things out when you need
them.
Instead of trying design step up front.
You just see what the patterns are that emerge and then you pull out.
It's a good way to keep yourself in a good state to the code.
So he's actually doing
Nothing useful and you're not wasting a lot of time with abstractions
that don't actually do anything for you.
So that's the way I like to do it.
Always pull out start with the code, pull it out.
Alright, so basically what we've got here is we've got a function now,
that'll do this fill for us, and we just need to basically reference
the sound output for all the parameters that we used to use.
So B for sample was one, we've got running sample, index.
That's one.
We've got our wave period.
That's one dark tone volume.
That's looks like bout it.
We've got that, we've got this and we've got that.
Okay, so that should basically give us what we had before.
Let's go ahead and compile that make sure that works that missed a
couple.
There's one, there's another and there we go.
Alright.
So now down in here, what we need to do is we need to actually call
this function, right?
We need to actually call our fill function.
Down in here and we will do that.
And there we go.
Now, we will call the sound output with that.
We will use our B to lock in place to write and now this should
basically give us the same code with the same bug.
It's just a all we did was pull it out into another function.
That's the only thing that we've done so far.
So there's our sound output.
Let's take a compiled here and just fix our compile errors.
Sound output.
Oops, sound output.
There we go.
That and that.
So let's go ahead and just get that indented properly and last, but
not least.
There we go.
So this should give us the same exact thing we had before same bug,
same everything.
Yes, and that is exactly what we get.
So that's fine.
All right.
So now what we can do is we can make this stuff a little bit cleaner.
What we can do is we can say, all right, the first time through after
we in it, let's go ahead and do a little bit of a fill.
So let's go down here.
And say, all right, we've got we've got our Wind Through to fill sound
buffer.
Let's go ahead and fill the sound buffer at startup, and then we can
also do our play at startup as well, so we can kick the sound buffer
off right here.
That gets rid of that.
Sound is playing variable, that's gone and we could just basically
kick it off right here.
So what we're going to do is we're going to fill our sound buffer.
Excuse me.
We're going to fill our sound buffer and we're basically to pass it
the first bite and we're going to pass it, I guess.
Guess, we'll just do for the B to write will do the entire, the entire
secondary buffer size.
So that'll fill the buffer.
Like we said before.
Now, what should happen here again is we should basically get exactly
the thing that we got before.
Let's do go ahead and do this.
We should get the same exact bug that we got before.
Hello.
Now, we are back to a pure tone, ladies and gentlemen.
In fact, a perfectly pure tone.
So basically that that check there was bogus.
Why was that the case?
That's very interesting.
Let's take a look.
Oh, even better.
That was just a national uninitialized variable.
That's all that was.
That was our entirety of our bug.
We forgot to do.
That.
That was it.
No other problem.
That was the entirety of our sound output problem.
Awesome.
So basically the only problem is when we went ahead, we had our
problem of not catching up to the play cursor.
So we had to fix that.
But when I did our test for that, we fail to we failed actually
initialize to zero again, one of the reasons to start pulling code out
and start making things cleaner cleaner, code has less stupid mistakes
in it, right?
And that's a very good way to kind of look at that and maybe we should
have actually finished licenses are here, but the same time.
Was actually gentleman bug.
One of the things that that's interesting about.
That is I think maybe this is this might be a case where we want to
start turning up our warning level as well.
We should probably look at that.
I'm going to write that down as maybe something to talk about next
dream getting the warning level up to something proper, because the
compiler should warn us about a lot of things, not necessarily that
one, but we're currently working without a lot of warnings turned on a
lot of usually, when I compile my code.
I have a lot of warnings turned on, so, something to think about.
But anyway, point being now all of our cases.
Has actually initialize the variable properly and hey, what a
surprise, our sound output works.
Works perfectly sounds lovely, doesn't it?
This isn't that pure tone.
Are you loving that?
I'm loving that but yeah, that's something that we want the power to
catch for us.
And so maybe I don't know, we're kind of I feel like we could still
make the stream, be limited to an hour because we've done what we
wanted to do today, which is to bug our sound output that has worked.
We're pretty happy about that.
And one of the interesting things is, if you look at the latency here,
our latency is now going to be the entire buffer.
Earth, right.
Our latency is going to be one whole buffers worth of sound because
we're always writing up to the play cursor.
What we could do in the future.
And what we probably will do is write less into the buffer.
Right?
Instead of being we're now one full second latent which would be very
bad for a game because we're writing a full buffers worth it, head of
that play cursor, but what we could do is basically say, let's not do
that.
Let's write up to someplace short of that basically, right?
Right.
Let's take a look at the play cursor.
Let's move only a certain amount ahead of it.
And let's write it to that.
So, we'll look at that a little bit later, too.
If that makes sense.
When it comes time to actually play sound effects.
That is something that will be looking at.
So what we'll do here is we'll say to do basically we want to change
this to using a lower latency offset from the play cursor.
When we actually start having sound effects, right?
This sort of thing would be fine for music streaming because it's not
particularly accurate in terms of latent.
But basically what we want to do is yeah, is change that before we get
to sound.
So I think we have actually accomplished what we want to do for the
day, even though it was a Meandering stream.
We actually did exactly what we wanted.
So that's pretty exciting.
The only thing I would do want to note is to do Implement sign
ourselves because that would be that would be nice.
If you notice if we go ahead and remove math.h here, you will notice
we get an undefined identifier error because there is no sign F
actually implemented.
So what I'd like to do is eventually Implement that ourselves, we can
Look to if we go in here to the sign code, where is it?
Let's see here.
Phil buffer.
If we go in here and take a look at what it does, we can step into the
Assembly Language, and actually take a look at what that's going to
do.
So if you take a look here, it literally does call a function called
sign F.
Right.
I don't know if you can see that there.
Let's, let's take a look.
Here.
I'll be a little bit more specific.
We just we just called that one.
Let's go back around the loop.
Whereas our jump jump people jump.
There it is.
So we jump back to top of the loop.
We come down here and you can see we call into this sign.
F function, here is the sign F function.
Oh well, now it's as them and I guess it's not going to show us the
sign F function because we don't have a source, but we can look at the
Ross assembly for it.
Let's take a look here.
Doing a compare doing load, doing a bunch of testing doing a bunch of
moles blah blah blah blah blah.
You can look at that.
That's a pretty expensive sign.
Actually.
It looks like I don't know if that's the most we may want to that.
We may be able to implement a more efficient sign because we know that
we only care about certain things as
Well, so that's, yeah, that's definitely something.
We probably don't want to just leave to chance.
So, we will probably do something with that ourselves.
All right.
Anyway, I think that is basically all we wanted to get done today.
We will do timers tomorrow.
And then finally, on next week.
We'll actually, I think we're in really good shape next week.
We should be out of Windows code.
We still will probably do a little bit with file loading in the
windows code and will be massaging the windows platform layer a bit.
Next week as we go through it, but I think I think that's it.
Tomorrow will do timers and then we are good to go.
Ladies and gentlemen, we have been remarkably on time with the stream
the first day or two.
Not the first day, the second day I think was the only day we really
didn't get to as much as we wanted to.
This has been amazing.
I don't know.
Give yourselves a pat on the back for our, for our punctuality.
I think that's about it.
So, let's go ahead.
Let's go ahead and go to the day 9 q a yeah.
Let's keep our keep our streak going here.
Let's take a look.
Uplink coder, indeed.
This bug could not have happened.
He always initialize variables.
Yes, and I actually try to do that myself as well.
A lot of times.
The only problem is sometimes, so what I like to do a lot of times and
and you know, I'm going to go ahead and point this out here.
Actually in our code, you'll notice what I like to do.
A lot of times is stuff like this.
I like to, I like to always just initialize to zero at the opening in
code.
That's not
Worms critical.
I like to just initialize to zero because I feel like it catches a lot
of bugs for you and you just always assumed that things are zero.
So you just, you don't even clear values that are going to be 0 and
you try to make as many values default to zero as possible.
A very good way to do things.
So I I like that.
I would probably like that aspect of D.
I have not program D myself, but I do think that's a good idea.
What would be nice is the something basically where you always assume
that values are initialized and then you ask for them not to be
initialized, would be the better way to go.
So that in the case, where you care about the performance and
don't want default values.
You just say that that's probably something that would be a good idea
and languages or at least give the programmer.
The ability to basically say with a struct here is I expect this to be
initialized to 0 all the time, unless the person ask not for it to be,
would be a nice keyword.
For example.
Now, the thing that I do want to emphasize here though is that this is
not really about catching a bug.
What I wanted the compiler to do, was not to initialize b 2, right?
Because we still had a bug in a sense.
Yes, zero happened to be the right value there.
So it seems like it would have been catching the bug.
But actually, what would have happened?
Is it would just been hiding the fact that our logic was buggy.
And so what I would rather have had happened there and what I think
the compiler would have done if we had turned our warning level up,
which is why I wrote that down is something to do very soon.
Maybe Monday will do that.
That is what I want that.
Is to tell me that there was a hole in the logic, tell me, not all
paths, initialize B to, right before it's used that would have
actually been what I want.
I don't want to silently initialize, the value and hide.
The fact that our logic was buggy because our logic was buggy.
We did this, right?
We did is sound playing or whatever something like this, right?
We did a thing where we typed in something here, but we didn't have an
else.
I want to tell me that else was missing.
That's what I actually wanted.
So,
So and I think the C compiler will actually do that most of the time
on a higher warning level which is kind of why I brought that up.
That's the thing.
We actually want the compiler to do for us, not silently, initialize
the value because this value doesn't have a default value.
It needs a specific value for every possible case and I want the
compiler to hold us to that and to say you've got a bug here, if you
didn't initialize it in every case.
That's what I actually want and that is why I didn't write this to
begin with.
Because I actually didn't want that.
So that's something to keep in mind there.
Let's take a look at what we've got in the Stream.
I'm going to blow my nose, apologize.
I'm still sick.
It is true.
Let's see.
Okay, doot doot.
Doot.
Do do.
Doot starting back at the beginning.
Pop up.
Let's see.
How do you know that b to lock is far enough ahead of the play cursor?
So we don't really know anything about it yet.
All we know is that we have a one-second, long buffer and we're
updating our buffer, every frame, which means that basically our game
would have to stall for an entire second.
In order for the play cursor to lupus.
So, we will never know.
And that is one of the bad parts of using direct sound that may be
fixed in later versions of the API.
But that was even fixed in wave out, which was actually the older API,
but you can't use because of, for various other reasons.
Basically, you do have a problem that if you did stall for one second,
you would know it.
Would, you know, if the buffer wrapped, if the play Chris are wrapped
around in the time, it took you to get around to another frame, you
would be.
You would be totally busted.
You would have no idea what went.
Not.
And so that is one argument to, you know, we could go up here and say,
you know, is is one second enough, right?
You know, should we actually say, you know, maybe make this like 10
seconds, you know, or 30 seconds.
How about 60 seconds?
Make it a minute, right?
Maybe make it so long that there's no conceivable way.
No matter what happened, the game could ever pause for that long, so
that we can always see.
Very clearly where that play cursor is, and that's something to think
about.
Could be forced multiple regions by setting a maximum buffer, lock
size to be a fraction of the sound buffer.
Sorry, I'm not sure.
I understand that question.
Let's see.
Sorry, just reading through everything.
Try W4 if it's not too much trouble, W3 will talk about that on
Monday.
I wanted to wait until the next plane, how warnings work and how you
turn them on and off and stuff.
So we'll get to that.
Let's see.
Where do I look for standard C function, documentation like printf or
size of?
Yeah.
And like, sign for example.
So typically you should actually be able to do msdn printf and you can
actually still use the msdn for that.
It's got them all in there.
You can also look in other places like when you just search for
printf, you will get a C++ reference that comes up.
Usually.
You can.
So you can see that there as well, but msdn is actually perfectly fine
for looking at stuff up as well.
If that makes sense.
Let's take a look.
I think you can now remove, if B lock equals play cursor, check.
It will be handled by the else case.
Let's take a look.
Yes, I believe that's correct as if they're.
Yes, you're right.
We could just do this because now, since we're Computing everything
we're doing the fill outside.
We should basically always be correct, like we were, that's how we
wrote it initially, but we added that thing in there.
It's kind of a hack to fill the buffer.
Let's listen very carefully.
Okay, I guess the other thing we could do is while we're on stream
here.
If I go to OBS settings.
I don't actually know if I can change these offhand, but basically is
there some way to change the volume?
That's of the game coming out.
We could test that on the stream.
Maybe we'll do that in a separate test stream.
I'll just write that down basically, like audio Valium.
And
Yes, that's something to think about because people are saying it's
too loud or whatever.
So we probably want to take care of that.
Especially when we're not working on sound code.
We don't want that blasting, every time we play something, so that's
something to think about.
Okay?
- that again.
Will be used.
Find the actual game.
No will be playing.
We probably will never use the sine value in the actual game.
It's autocomplete intellisense a bad idea for a programmer.
Un John do not seem to use it.
Well, I don't think intellisense is a bad thing.
I do use autocomplete.
So I use basically, you know, I do B to right hit tab or something II
do that right, a lot, which is sort of like intellisense.
But the reason that I don't like intellisense in Visual Studio is I
hate the way that the input actually works with that it locks up your
up and down arrow in a bad way.
So basically, I don't think that's necessarily a bad thing.
I would just say if you can and I've never looked into this, but if
you can and you're in Visual Studio, I would say look into rebinding
the keys, a little bit there.
If you can, I don't know if intellisense lets you do that.
But if you can rebind the key so that it's not locking up your arrow
keys if you could do something there, but I'll think it tells us
necessary bad.
I don't know that.
It's necessarily all that useful though either.
Let's see to to do to do.
I got to do a better job of keeping my place in the Stream.
I need like a little tool that lets me know where we were.
So so we just ask the you and John did not seem to use it one.
Where is that?
There it is?
Okay.
Let's see.
I don't think it had to do with uninitialized variable.
Wouldn't that mean you would do a huge right writing past the end of
the buffer is because you were overriding the region with the Lakers
in the right cursor.
So yes, I mean technically that is what was happening, but it was
because of the uninitialized variable.
What we wanted to do was write 0 B, in the case, where the play cursor
and the B to lock, where we're at the same place, because there's no
need to write any more.
We'd caught up.
But what we were doing instead was writing an undefined.
/ of B, right.
We were writing some whatever the value of B to write actually
happened to be garbage.
Right?
We were, we were writing that many essentially and, of course, it
didn't overwrite, the end of the buffer, because when we call lock,
direct sound will clip that number down to the buffer size, presumably
or something else will happen there.
So basically, we were getting a cascading failure from the fact that
this value was initialized and it was causing us to do a right.
When we didn't want to actually do one at all.
Our logic was supposed to say, don't do the right.
And that was the initial idea.
Has value variable, that was causing that problem.
Excuse me.
Still quite sick.
Unfortunately, hoping this will go away by tomorrow.
Maybe I was feeling a little bit better today.
So I was hoping it would would start to lessen up anyway.
Is it possible for B to spill over two variables in neighboring
variables?
When bit shifting ends or something?
Like, okay.
I see what you're saying.
The answer is no.
So the reason that that b cannot spill in when you're doing, when
you're doing shifts and stuff like that is because when you are doing
things like that, you have to remember that the Assembly Language is
doing very specific things.
So basically when we come in here, let's take let me type a little
example in here for you to answer your question more specifically.
So let's say you want to know if I have something like this and this
right?
You want to know if repeatedly shifting X will accidentally get into
why right?
So if I do something like this, right?
If I shift this up, one, how many times can I do that before it shifts
into why something like that?
Right?
That's what you're asking essentially, if that makes sense.
So what happens in this circumstance is you have to remember that
these things are on the stack.
Yes, and they are next to each other.
That's also true.
So if I look at these two things and I look at the address of X and
we'll get the address of Y.
You will note that they are, you know, sort of close to each other.
They're a little further apart.
You may have expected right there.
Not right right next to each other.
They're actually quite a bit apart.
If you look at that.
I don't know if that's some kind of a padding check or something like
that.
I'm not sure why, they're, so why they're as far apart there as they
are but point being they are still both on the stack, but they can
never write into each other with a shift because what actually
happens, if you look at the Assembly Language code, you have to
remember stuff doesn't get operated on in memory.
It gets operated on in a register.
So what happens here is
Order to shift, left X by one first, the processor loads wherever X
was, and it loads it into a register.
So, if you click on the registers window again, if you don't have your
register windows open, you can go to debug windows and then it's in
here, registers.
You can go into your registers and you can look eax.
Right?
Is this value here?
Basically, it's called our ax and said, well, I can also do all this.
Looks like we have initialized our register window.
You can right click in here and get all the actual stuff you might
want.
There you are.
Ax is basically the the 64-bit version of eax.
So when I load this, it's going to load into the low part.
E ax is the lower 32 bits of our ax.
So I do that and you can see, I load it in the value, right?
What's going to happen now is, I'm going to shift left the register.
So you're not shifting left, the memory location X, you're shifting
left the register.
So the register shifts up, right?
And it went to, to just like we would expect, right?
You can actually
do this in your watch window as well.
You can type in our ax, the actual thing or even eax.
I think.
Yeah, and you can see what eax is.
That's the low 32 bits of our ax, right?
You can do that and you can even do comma B if you want to because
this didn't work in the intro to see stream, the comma B didn't work
because we were using an older version of Visual Studio, but now that
we're using 2013, we can do comma B, which shows binary, which is
really helpful, especially for teaching purposes.
There's the binary 64-bit register.
And as we go through, you'll see.
It does the shift left right now.
It writes the value that's in the register.
It writes the low 32 bits of that, register out to X.
So, the address of X, you'll see still has one in it.
It did not get shifted yet, until we do this, move to write the
register about value back.
There it is, right?
You see that there.
So, now, the register value got written back to X.
Now.
And again, this is very unoptimized code.
The optimizer, would normally go to town on this.
This and it would just change it into a single shift in a right or
something like that.
Right?
But since this is unoptimized code, if you turn the optimizer off,
literally just outputs explicitly.
What you told it to do and what you told it to do was to load X into a
register shift, it left by one and then put it back out to the
register.
So now it's going to do the exact same thing.
Again load back in the value, which it did shift it, right?
It out, load shift, right?
Load shift, right, load shift, right?
And basically what that does is that just keep doing exactly that load
shift, right?
Keeps updating X and so on.
So forth.
When you get to the end of X, when you get to the end of the 64 bits
and shift it out the top.
Or in this case, when we get into 32 bits and shift it out the top
again.
It's just going to take the 32 bits of the register and write them
out.
So there was no way to shift it into some other memory.
This is in the register.
The only thing that can happen is when you shift, I think there's like
a carry flag that gets set in the processor that you could test.
So you do know whether you shifted a one-out.
I think there's a basically a thing.
In here, if you look in registers, there's a Flags thing down here,
right?
There's there's that gets set sometimes and stuff like that.
But you can't access those flags from see.
They're opaque to you.
They're not actually exposed.
So basically that's what happens.
So that's why you can never write values into other values like that.
The only time you would have an overwrite is, if you were writing to a
pointer and you wrote too many bits to the pointer, which you could
do, right?
You could, you could have a pointer and write 64 bits out to it, but
you are pointing at a 32-bit value, and then you would corrupt.
The thing next to that thing in memory, that makes sense.
Hopefully that clears that up a bit.
Let's see.
I don't think it had to do with uninitialized variable.
Wouldn't that mean you would be doing a huge right writing pass in the
buffer?
I think it's because we're right we did that is possibly spillover.
Will use the same audio buffer to have overlay?
Several sounds.
Yes.
We only need one output buffer and we can mix all the sounds
ourselves, which I'll show you how to do later on changed her.
It's on a button.
Press the bug will resurface.
Know that bug will not resurfaced.
What you're seeing.
There is the fact that you cannot instantaneously change the hurts
like that and expect to not have a sound clip there.
Is two reasons, you will get that sound clip one is that you are
harshly changing the, the frequency right away and that will cause an
artifact.
But the more serious artifact is, you'll notice basically, what we
have here.
Is is the well, you know what?
This is going to be a long stream today.
Anyway, I think because we've got extra time.
I'm just going to go ahead and show you because that's a very good
question.
That's a very good point that basically, that you brought up and I
think if we explore it, it may be educational.
So let's go ahead and explore it.
What the person writing instead is they want to change the pitch based
on what the controller was doing whether you push the a button for
example, so what he was saying is for example, he wants to do if a
button
Right, then.
Basically this tone Hertz is going to change its going to change up to
something else like double that let's say 512 or something, right?
So we're going to go in here and we're going to set that to 512.
So that makes sense.
I think this is what the person was saying.
And so we kind of push that button we do that, right.
Why am I not hearing that?
What did I do wrong?
That is the a button.
Is it not?
Did I type that properly tone hurts 512?
Well, that was, that was not as dramatic as I hoped.
It would be.
I feel like that should have done it.
Sound output tone hurt, though.
Well, duh.
We have to recompute our period as well.
Hmm.
So, how do I want to do that?
This is not a particularly good way to do that.
I don't want to have to recompute all the dependent values every time
we should make that into a function or something.
But let's let's do it again here.
So, I don't know if you could hear that.
I'll run it one more time, so that you can kind of hear it.
When I push down the a button, you can hear the click that happens
just on the changeover, right?
And I assume that's what the person meant when they said that the bug
or services.
But that's not a bug.
I mean, it is a bug, but it's not a bug in our in our code that we
wrote.
It's a bug in this idea.
This doesn't work.
The reason that it doesn't work.
It's because you have to remember we re compute where we are in the
sine wave every time.
So if you look at how this
Works up here.
Basically, what we're doing is we're using the running sample index
and we're dividing by the wave period, every time.
That means our sound will only be continuous.
If wave period was continuous if wave periods.
Suddenly changes to something else.
We will have a sound glitch right at the point where it changed.
So what you actually would want to do if you were trying to change the
pitch?
Continuously is instead of storing running sample index, you actually
need to store.
Where you are in the sine wave, you need to store T sign.
Basically up here in win32 sound output.
And then what you would do is instead of computing, this value a new
every time basically you just add at the end, you know, something else
to it.
So basically we'd say sound output, T sine plus equals.
However far we want to go and how far we want to go.
Is basically
One samples Worth, right?
It's basically one.
Samples worth over that.
That period.
So that way just the increment is now going to change by the way Ferry
it right?
That is what we would actually want to do if you wanted to avoid the
glitch.
So our code was totally correct.
You were just doing something that is not that is going to produce a
glitch with the way that we chose to represent our sine wave, but the
buffer code is still valid and now we should be able to basically get
something.
Whoops.
We need to actually say
Sound output T sign here because we are now outputting without that t.
So we do that, right?
There we go.
And now we should be able to hear that no glitch anymore.
Right?
And so I hope you guys understand what was happening there.
I don't know if you do or not again, since it's a long stream.
I feel like it can't hurt just to solidify that in your heads a little
bit with a lovely.
One of these Microsoft Paint diagrams.
I think everyone loves them.
I think everyone knows they love them.
So I'm going to go ahead and just put this out here.
Okay.
Let's take a look.
Here we go.
So, if you think about what was happening, we had a sine wave at a
certain period that is the worst sine wave.
Probably anyone's ever seen.
But this is Microsoft Paint.
What do you want from me people?
What do you want?
And so from Peak to Peak right there?
Basically, that is the value that we're looking at that is the period
of the sine wave.
And we had a period that we were saying was, well.
Yeah man, this is so bad.
I really want, I really want to solve this.
It's got to be something.
We do pretty soon.
I got to get a better diagramming situation here better.
I got to get a better story.
All right.
Anyway, point being we basically have them to me.
We basically have a period here of our sine wave and what we were
doing before is we were just taking the absolute index.
So basically we have a buffer and the buffer is actually only this
big, right?
But we essentially retreating it as a giant linear buffer because
running sample Index, right?
Running sample index was essentially incrementing ad infinitum.
It's just getting bigger and bigger and bigger.
Right?
And we were modding it by the buffer size to figure out where we were
in the buffer size.
But we were just using this value directly to compute where we were in
the sine wave.
So, our position in the sine wave was also equal to running some
sample index, and we were just using the period as a divisor to map us
into where we should be in the same way.
What that essentially does is it means we are just direct mapping.
Our sine wave into this buffer.
It's a direct mapping, right?
That just basically fills fills the sine wave as we go into our giant
sort of virtual linear buffer and we were just kind of mapping it
circulate, right?
So what happens if you were to suddenly change the divisor because
there's a divisor here.
Dividing by the period of the sine right to do this.
If you suddenly change that divisor, right?
We were here in the sound wave.
Let's say what you wanted to do.
What you were trying to do is change the sign to a different period.
Can I make for the love of God?
People?
Can we make a bigger eraser?
Oh God.
This program is this is not this is not a good drawing program.
I need to figure out how to get a real drunk room in here.
Alright.
Anyway, what you going to do?
So if you wanted what you wanted to do was
What you're trying to do and you push that a button to make a nice
continuous tone.
That doesn't have a skip, is you were trying to do this, right?
You were trying to just at that point start oscillating, more
frequency frequently, but what you actually did is you essentially
just you had because you just change the period right out from under
it.
You can imagine there was basically two sine waves, one with one
period, one with the other, you have the slow period sine wave, right?
And then you had a fast period sine wave, right?
And what you did.
Instead instead of starting where you were and just changing the
frequency of oscillation, which is what we wanted.
You were taking wherever you were in the Stream and jumping right to
wear.
This other sine wave would have been at that point if it had been the
only sine wave that you were ever playing, that means you would
discontinuously jump from here to here.
And then start oscillating, right?
That causes the skip.
That is the skip because now you've got a discontinuity in your sine
wave.
And discontinuities sign sound like when you hear them, it's basically
a very high frequency because you have to imagine what that actually
turns into is a very high frequency Spike one little tiny sine wave
that moved you up to their essentially it's a very high frequency
Spike.
So if you looked at it on a graphic equalizer, you know, you'd be
getting here is your normal tone that you were trying to get.
And there's this really high frequency Spike here, that just kind of
quickly jumped in to make you move and that's no good.
So you don't want that.
That's bad.
Bad, bad bad bad.
So that's what's happening there.
And that's why I said what you have to do is you have to track where
you were in the sine wave, because then you can just accelerate that
tracking and you'll always stay, you'll always know that you were
starting from the same position.
You can change the pitch, all you want basically and we could, you
know, we could go nuts with that obviously, right?
You could, you could map the pitch if you wanted to.
You could map the pitch to one of the sticks, right?
You could say, oh, you know, the
Which is something like the the stick X or something.
Let's say right or the stick, why, let's do stick, why?
So, you know, we could say, okay, there hurts is something like the
stick y, divided by whatever the stick.
Why can possibly be?
So that's, you know, 32,000 or something like this.
It's a it's 65536 divided by 2, but I'm just going to say stick /
30,000.
So there's a change.
Those two.
But as we do float math, to get basically a value between negative 1
and 1 here and will basically say that it's, it's 512 is the tone
hurts plus some value that more than that.
So we can we can do 256 up or down times that and then we'll cast it
back to an integer.
I think that's what it was.
I don't remember what that actual value was.
What was that value?
Let's take a look at what we actually Define it to be.
It was an integer.
So we'll know.
Look at that, back to ensure.
So we could do something like this and this will actually allow us to
go ahead and control it.
I believe with the stick.
Let's take a look here.
If that actually works.
Which stick that I do actually?
That's work.
What am I doing?
Oh, the a button has to be down.
If you don't actually want that.
Let's get let's just get rid of that a button check.
I don't want to have to hold that down while I do the stick thing.
Right, make sense.
So, the other thing that we might want to do now is we might want to
get that latency down because now we've actually attach something to
controller.
And so what we probably want to do is when we fill that buffer, when
we do the global fill buffer, we probably don't want to fill the sound
buffer, quite so far.
So what we would want to do here is we want to introduce another
variable.
That's basically saying where we would actually like to be relative to
that play cursor.
So basically what we can say is we can say basically our latency.
Sample count.
Let's say how many samples ahead of the play cursor.
We would like to be in general.
Right?
And what we can do is we can introduce that value in a way that makes
some sense to us.
We can say that the sound output latency sample count is basically
going to be equal to the samples per second.
Let's say divided by 60.
So 1/60 of a second is how far ahead we want want to be.
Let's say that's might be a little aggressive.
Let's do let's do a fifteenth of a second.
If
Ventually, we probably want that to be high much, much higher like a
60th of a second, so that we're constantly really good.
But then what we might get dropouts a week, so we're gonna have to do
a little more stuff when we actually get down to it and tighten the
ratchet on the sound code.
But let's let's do this now.
So that if you're running at 15 frames per second or higher, you
wouldn't get any dropouts.
So, then when we go in here and we actually compute those values, what
will actually do is say that the play cursor itself.
What we're trying the place that we're trying to write to is not going
to
Be that play cursor instead that value is going to be something else.
It's going to let's say B, you know, the target cursor or something
like that.
And that Target cursor is going to be the play cursor.
We want to we want to write to
At least the play cursor plus however much the the latency is going to
be.
So what would, what did we say?
That was that was sound.
That's a that's this here.
That is the latency sample count.
So base, we're going to take wherever it's playing.
We're going to say, we want to be a fifteenth of a second ahead of
where it's playing all the time.
That's our goal.
And then instead of play cursor.
We're just going to change that to Target cursor, right?
We're just going to.
We're just going to look at the Target cursor and say, that's what
we're writing to not the play Chris or anymore make sense.
Hopefully that makes some sense.
And then what we do when we initially kick off.
Our buffer is in, we kick off our buffer.
Instead of writing the whole buffer.
We will actually write the latency.
Count times the B first bites for sample again, will actually write
that many bytes ahead so that we start off head as well.
And we just try to stay ahead.
We're still getting a little.
Getting a little bit of a quip there.
You can see we're right on target now.
So, basically, I don't know if I introduced a bug by quickly doing
that or not, but it could also be that that's just not enough ahead of
the play cursor, to make it actually work.
Okay.
I'm not sure which one that is.
Let's make sure that this was sort of at least roughly.
Correct if that makes sense.
Do.
This is probably not the way to introduce that.
Code was to Blitz it out like that, but I felt like we
Kind of going that direction.
So we might as well.
So let's double check here.
Let's say that let's let's double check and make sure that if we just
say that, it's the latency sample count, is the samples per second.
We should be back to where we were before.
So there you go.
So, I did introduce a bug because basically, that that shouldn't
change anything, right?
Oh, duh.
Yeah.
I was even thinking this when I wrote it one of the problems again.
I say this a lot on the stream, I think about things but then my mind
is occupied with explaining and it forgets the things that supposed to
Do in fact, we had that just just yesterday with the unlock as well.
Remember, I said we've got to unlock that buffer.
And then I never remembered unlock the buffer.
So, so the problem here is the target cursor.
When we do that thing, it could wrap around.
So when we get to the end of the buffer, we tart crust will be past
the end of the buffer.
And we actually need to be back around.
So, basically all we need to do here is do that mod.
Again, we need to make sure that we're always in range of the buffer,
when we actually asked a lock that that's that's it.
That's the only pretty sure that's the only thing I've got.
That take this code, should not be too hard to add in and I don't
think it is.
So, basically, just need to do that.
That move it, move it out to where you think is going to be map it
back into the buffer and then treat that like the play cursor and now
it should, it should be correct.
Its I've gotten a semicolon there.
All right.
yeah, and so now we can go ahead and go back and drop that latency
back down to something aggressive like 15, and now we've got, you
know, not super low latency sound output, but it appears, you know,
like to me, for example, you can see
Right.
So there you go.
Now we've got about, you know, I figured this would be a two hour
stream.
We've still got 20 minutes.
Let me cover a couple of things.
Well, I'll double-check with the thing for see, if there's any
questions here.
Let's take a look here.
Hmm.
Let's see.
If we can live with a slightly less accurate sign, it can be
approximate with polynomials.
We don't actually need to do that.
Well, I mean, we do actually kind of need to do that.
You'll see what we'll end up doing is, will actually write something
that generates the sign using the sse2 instructions will be totally
fine.
And we will, we won't really be approximating.
It will actually be Computing it to floating Point Precision probably
most of the time.
Although we could do a less accurate one as well.
But because basically you have to remember approximating something
actually ends up being exact as far as
Computers concerned.
If you can do it out to the number of bits that are in the actual
floating point value.
Because, yeah, that's not exact.
But neither is the floating point value.
The floating point value can never represent even pie.
Right?
Pisan infinitely repeating.
It's got an infinite number of digits, right?
It just keeps going and so you can never accurately represent things
in floating point.
So we only have to when we actually compute sign, we only have to
compute it out to the number of points that the mantissa has in the
first place, which is only like 24, I think, 24 bits.
I don't know if that's actually true.
That might be more than 24 bits.
How many bits is the mantissa?
The 24 bits.
Some reason.
I think it's 24 bits.
Let's take a look.
Floating-point, 32-bit mantissa.
I think it's 24 bits.
Let's take a look.
Man, this a say what the spec spec should say, here it is.
Let's take a look internal representation.
Okay, so it looks like it's actually 23.
So it's not actually 24 bits.
Oh, but it's well as 24 because of the implicit one, I guess is what
they're saying.
I don't know.
So there you go.
There you go.
That's the table right there.
And in W.
Basically, you get you get double that right plus a little more little
more than double that because they assign less to the exponent
proportionally.
Anyway, yeah, not really important right now, but point but point
being
Let's see, okay.
What about lead time between play cursor?
And B to lock?
Sorry, not sure.
I understand that question.
Well, the art and audio for the game.
Be released into the public domain.
No, not for a while.
Anyway, do we get them for paying now while we are following along?
Yes, all of the art.
I mean, basically the game you'll get access to the full game if you
pre-order.
So basically you'll get all the art resources to play the game because
they're actually playable versions of the game released.
Once we actually have it up.
And running and those will come with the art.
So if you're following along at home with the code, you will also be
able to load the art from the game builds that ship because people
will start actually playing the game build to have.
You don't even necessarily follow with the code.
And so, yes, that aren't will come with that, but it will not be
released into the public domain.
If it does, it may eventually get release in the public domain, but it
won't necessarily be coincident with the code being released.
The code will definitely be released in the public domain and it will
be released, presumably sooner.
If the artwork to be later.
So that's it.
What is going on here?
Okay.
Alright.
Let's go back to the chat.
Okay.
Is it a good idea to use fixed Point math for games that require
deterministic simulation for multiplayer, or is it actually feasible
to get consistent results with floating Point math across different
systems.
It's a good question.
There's people who've done it.
I think Bungie actually did it that way.
Basically, what I would say is it is entirely possible to use floating
Point values to get determinism because floating point is very
rigorously defined and most processors have to do it specifically in a
particular way and all that.
But there's a really huge problem that you run into and that is the
optimizer floating Point operations won't come out to equal the same
values if the optimizer rearranges the code because let's say for
example, just to in this is not very realistic, but I'm just giving
you a very trivial example, let's say that I have, you know, a couple
of values and a couple operations between them, obviously math can be
rearranged in different ways.
I can do it.
First, I can do a divide s that sort of thing, depending on what's
happening on the platform.
You may end up in a circumstance where you get a different orders of
operations happening, which produce different results because of
rounding, the floating Point values have to get rounded.
Obviously, because when you do floating Point math, you end up with a
number that's more precise and you can shove back into the 32 bits.
So, you basically have to round that last bit, one way, or the other.
And so if you do the operation of the episode, you can get different
things.
There's also a thing called operator, whew,
Asian which is when like let's say one platform has a multiply add.
So a single instruction that is a multiply and add together.
And then another platform doesn't well up in.
It has a single multiply add could do it at higher Precision than one
that has to do a multiply round then.
Add.
Right because that's the store the value back.
It's got to do that round.
So it'll do multiply round and round instead of multiply add round.
And that's a problem too.
So this is a huge problem.
So could fix point B, and answer to that, it could
I don't know.
I mean.
It depends how you want to set up your multiplayer architecture.
I am not an expert at such things.
I think different people will have different arguments about how you
shouldn't shouldn't go about structuring code that way, but it's
something to be aware of certainly, it's a good question and it does
have ramifications is really the answer.
I can give you and different people choose to attack that problem,
different ways.
If someone is just Bull and Summer, She's rule 32.
Mostly.
I was because I was on the stream, really?
I don't ever want pool.
So basically, we can actually go in here and just replace Loops.
We can just replace Brule with rule.
32.
I don't ever really want fool.
If I don't, I don't ever use Blu in my own code.
I was doing that for a while because of the stream, but I never
actually do that in real life so we can we can just get rid of that
entirely.
You'll never see me type of pool again, unless I forget again that I'm
supposed to be doing code my way.
Now, not like the
Courtesy stream.
Let's see.
There is a red volume slider, right?
On the OBS main window.
Okay, cool.
I will, I will go investigate that after we're done.
Thank you.
Let's see.
Are you going to use ET W de la context which is for the game.
That is a funny joke.
No, because it's insane.
It's such an awful API.
Is this.
The audio API will be using in the final version of the game.
Yes.
We direct sound is perfectly usable to ship games.
It's pretty reliable and it runs on just everything you can run on
Windows XP.
It'll work.
So we probably will ship the game on this.
We don't really need anything else.
I don't think.
Giving directions actually.
Common interfaces.
Is it a safe thing to call in the interfaces without going through the
cam layer, especially without even initializing?
Calm?
Yes.
It's the direct sound create call does the initialization for you?
Try paint.net for drawing.
Okay.
I will let's see.
Target cursor, doesn't wrap the buffer size.
Yes.
Whoever Caboose 2311 you were right on target there.
Let's see.
I think that's everything.
Can we do an episode on emacs any techniques?
Yes, we will do that.
That's already on my list.
We will absolutely do that.
Alright, we've got 10 minutes left now.
So I am going to go ahead and talk about talk about basically.
Let's see here.
One more thing, two more things.
Two more things.
Yeah.
So 2/3, know we've got three more things that I want to talk about on
the stream real quick.
Just real quick, really simple stuff.
Should not take any time at all.
We've got 10 minutes left.
So I'm just going to go ahead and cover the
Those will get them in here and I can cross them off my list of things
to talk about.
So, apparently, our direct input.
I mean, our xinput stuff.
There's even another Library.
People were saying was, sometimes the only one that was on their
machine.
Basically, it was called X input.
What is it?
114?
I don't even remember what let's.
Let's go ahead and take this is ridiculous.
You'll see why it's ridiculous as X and put Library versions.
Let's see if we can get a thing here.
All right.
So there's xinput 1.4.
There's egg put 1.3, and there's also xinput 9.10.
I am not kidding.
You ladies and gentlemen, those are the versions of X input that they
shipped.
That is the way Windows goes nowadays.
It's absolutely ridiculous.
But that is how it works.
And basically some people said that only that one was available
sometimes on certain machines.
And so what we'd like to do here is just further explode.
Our set of checks and basically say well, okay, excuse me.
Let's try and load that one as well.
Now.
I'm not sure what the actual file name of that is.
So I'm going to attempt to look for it and see which one.
I don't know if it's on this machine, let's go ahead and go over here
to windows again and just do again.
That Dura, /s, X input star.
Let's just see what versions there are.
So it's got its on this machine.
We've got this one xinput 91.
So let's go ahead and see if we can load that one as well.
And that way, we've just covered.
Absolutely all our bases, no matter what Microsoft decided to poop out
into their Windows operating system.
We will hopefully have coverage there.
So, let's take a look at that and double check that that works in the
controller.
Still works.
If we load that library, because I've never actually tried lien that
library before.
Let's take a look load that library and it
Loaded and the controller Works a okay.
All right, so we're good there.
No issues with that.
So that's one thing off the list, not much, again.
Nothing to talk about their just had to make sure we covered all the
bases.
Let's thing I want to do is talk about the dead zone.
I realized I did something stupid.
This would not have been a problem when we actually went to handle
this stuff for real.
But the, but the joke code, I I typed in here was
Dumb and I didn't want to leave it in there without an explanation of
why it was done, just in case people internalize it and didn't think
about the dumbness.
Basically.
What I did is I shifted this down because I was just like, oh, I want
to kill the low.
I want to make it a very low value, so that when you push the side,
it's not scrolling by infinitely fast because this is a 16-bit value.
So it'll go between 32,000 - 32,000 something like that and we're
scrolling in pixels when we, when we do our X offset.
So we that's way too many.
I mean, our whole
So is only going to be like 1920, pixels wide at best and we were
right now using just only 1280 by 720.
So, scrolling by 30,000, which would wrap the screen tons of times in
one scroll.
So I try to scroll that down.
Now, the problem is this is perfectly valid shifting down by 12.
That's basically the same as dividing by 2 to the 12th, right?
There is a cash to catch occurs when there is a negative number by
default when you shift and see, I believe it does sign extension.
And what that means is, if the number was -, so if that high bit was
set and you shift it down, it continues to shift in the high bit that
leaves the number - if it was - before.
Now I wanted to I want to just show you what that means because I
realized a little complicated understand but we come in here.
First time through, right?
And we take a look at what goes on.
We have an X offset and a y offset, and you can see excuse me.
Ah, man.
The coughing, it never stops of zeros and we are going to add to those
zeros.
How much you want to offset by.
Now, stick offset, I'm sorry, X offset, and wife that are both zero,
like I said, so what we would expect to have happen here, right?
Is we would expect to see 2035 shifted down by 12, which is 0, right?
Because that's basically there's a, what's called a dead zone on the
controller.
The controller is basically kind of noisy.
The inputs aren't perfect.
And when the controller is back at zero, it may not be right at 0.
It may be anything from like
4,000 to positive four thousand or something.
There's like a huge range of what?
What centered might be in the controller.
So basically that shift by 12 should have totally killed that noise
because the two values that are on the controls.
Are you?
Notice are both zero, right?
But, when we actually go to compute these lines, you'll notice that's
not what we get.
We get negative 1 and zero, right?
Which is what causes that persistent scroll.
I was just saying, oh, this controller is broken because I thought the
controller was broken.
That's not the case.
Case that was just me being dumb.
Basically, What's Happening Here?
If You Look is if we see what actually happens when we do this.
Shift when we do this shift right here, right?
If we look at what actually happens there.
We will see the problem.
The problem is that that value?
When it gets shifted, there's my to bugger.
Where is my to bugger?
There?
It is that value when it gets shifted.
This is a binary value.
Right?
If we look at the binary value, that's a two's complement value.
The high bit is set at means it is - what's going to happen when it
shifts it is, it's going to shift in the sign bit.
The reason it has to
Shift in the sign bit that high bit, that's one that's going to be
one.
Anytime that the number is negative is because if it shifted in a 0,
the number would flip from negative to positive.
Right?
So what it does is it shifts in a - it shifts in that want the the -
to keep the number remaining - and that's just 2's complement which we
didn't really cover too much.
But that's what's going to actually happen.
When that happens.
You will notice that we basically end up producing a value.
That's all.
What, you know, when we shift it down, it's going to be all once
because we shifted it down enough to knock out.
We shifted down 12 places, right?
And this thing is only 16 bits long.
So basically we ended up with just these ones that were here and we
shift it in, once for the rest.
So, these ones are those ones, right?
They got went down there and we shift it in a 1 for everything else.
No matter how far down, we shift the negative value.
It'll never go to 0.
It only goes to negative one.
So it's not really the same.
Him as an integer divide at that point, that is a crucial thing to
remember.
And I just kind of, I didn't even think about it and I just kind of
crap that in there.
That was a bad idea.
So that's not good.
What we actually wanted to do, is we actually wanted to use a real
divide here.
We actually wanted to use something that was basically, you know, 2 to
the 12th.
Let's say something like that.
And that's going to be what 256 with, for more extra place.
So 265 1220 2048.
So it's going to be something like 2048.
Let's say, right now.
We're going to do that divide, something like that.
Maybe not sure what we actually want to be.
Maybe we want.
4096.
I think it's 4,000 is because there's actually one extra shift.
So this is actually a little more.
But that's to look totally fine value.
And I can feel that that's not quite all the dead zone.
You see how it sort of, it's got still a little bit, sometimes of a
bit that's happening there.
So I think the dead zone is probably somewhere around 4096 and I think
if we actually look, so I'm going to, I'm going to stick with the
higher number that whoops.
That's the wrong editor, tell immediately when you type into it 4096
4096 and that should handle the dead zone properly.
I suspect.
All right, looks good.
The only thing I wanted to check as well is whether or not what the
xinput, definition of The Dead Zone was because if I remember
correctly, they say with the dead zone isn't here and like I said,
we're going to handle the dead zone properly.
This is not proper, handling of the dead zone at all.
We're going to handle the prop, the The Dead Zone in later.
Editions more properly than this, but you can see actually the left
and right have much higher dead zones actually even than 4
As in 96, those are really high there.
So technically actually, we would want to kill any number, you know,
that was that was above those.
So keep that in mind.
We'll deal with that actually a little bit a little bit later.
Okay.
So basically that's just something to just something to keep in mind.
In fact, you what, I'll go ahead and put it to do in there.
So people can see it.
And know that it's okay.
And we're going to get to that later, note, or to do Casey.
We will do DeadZone handling prop later using X input Gamepad and
there we go.
Alright.
So basically we will, we will actually do that later.
You'll see that happen later on, and when we actually process this
joystick to shove it into our actual game properly.
Right.
So, that's the dead zone thing.
And then the final thing was just one bit of cleanup, which was the
deaf window.
Proc technically should have been deaf window.
Proc a, again.
This is just cleaning up things that for people who want to compile
and unicode, anytime.
You see one that I've missed.
We're just trying to make it so that if anyone does it compile, it
does compile it and unicode Mode.
Nothing breaks.
Basically, so, there we go.
All good.
I think we have come to the end of the stream.
I don't think we've got anything else.
Looks like, that's the end of the questions, too.
So, thank you.
Everyone for joining us for this special to our holiday Thanksgiving
holiday episode of handmade hero.
I am, I am delighted to see that.
So many people actually joined us.
I was figuring today, would be a not many people on the stream because
of the Thanksgiving holiday, but it looks like we still got quite a
few people.
So thank you so much for coming and hanging out with us while we got
our sound code working, and we did some other kind of fun stuff as
well.
Talked about floating point and all kinds of other good stuff.
If you would like,
Again, to preorder the game, you can get the full source code here and
that will come with art assets as well.
Like we talked about on the stream.
If you want that.
You can pre-order it here.
If you want to email a question.
You can email it here.
We're still working on the Forum.
So hopefully that will soon be a forums button.
You can actually go and talk to other members of the community as
well.
Again, the Twitter stream.
I usually post when the things are going to be as well so that you can
get updates on when the next stream is going to be.
And of course the YouTube video
So go to handmade, hero dot-org.
If you need anything.
We've probably tried to put most of stuff there that you need and and
the forums will be coming soon, which will have even more stuff.
So, that should be good.
Thank you.
Everyone for joining us.
Tomorrow will be 11 a.m.
Again, then Monday will be going back to 8 p.m.
So we'll be back on regular hours.
Friday's will probably always be sometime in the morning though, so
that people in Europe can join in.
So Friday's will be early in the mornings from now on basically, but
Monday through Thursday will be back at 8 p.m.
For next week.
Thank you everyone for joining us.
It was great to see you and I hope.
To see you again.
Tomorrow, have a Happy Thanksgiving, for those of you who celebrate
it.
And for those of you don't just have a good rest of your day.