Start recording.
Okay, hello everyone and welcome to handmade hero.
I know we are staring at the Emax ring.
That's a little bit weird.
Normally, we're not doing that on handmade here, it's because I was
explaining something in the freestream to somebody.
We had this little situation happening there, and so I'm going to go
ahead and close that down.
That was just a little, little pre stream, chat, little pre stream
chat.
We were chatting about some stuff and I wanted to demonstrate.
But here you go back to the standard where we normally start the
episode.
Welcome to handmade hero show.
Where we code a complete game.
Live on Twitch and, you know, yesterday we kind of just went.
I was surprised at how well yesterday went to be honest with you.
I didn't really know how it was going to go and we just straight-up
replaced.
Our other debugging system with one that basically goes all the same
stuff but captures the full information, including the timestamps and
everything, and that was pretty awesome.
And I'd like to go get back into that today because we haven't really
played with it.
Now that we have this extra information, we haven't done anything with
it.
Because we just finished up actually collecting it.
That's pretty cool.
Now, there is a slight issue with it, and it's an issue.
That honestly, I haven't had to solve recently in professional
programming, at Molly, because of the way that I do things, there's a
different way that I structure the code, that makes it, so that this
particular thing is not necessary, but I know that we're going to have
to solve it here and I'm a little rusty.
I'm sorry to say, I'm just rusty with the technique that we're going
to need to use.
Is or at least I assume that we're going to need to use unless the
correct solution is just to kind of switch over to the way that I do
it.
Molly which I don't know that it necessarily is I think that's a
little bit further down the rabbit hole than probably we would want to
go for the code that we're doing right now.
But
I'd like to get back to it.
I'd like to talk about some of the things, the shortcomings that we
still have in there.
Can we fix them?
And if and then which ones we can leave?
And then I'd like to go if we still have time after that which don't
know if we will.
I'd like to start going into like how to use the data a little bit
more.
And then for certain tomorrow and Friday I'd like to start a get into.
Okay, let's let's make some nice visits now that we've got this extra
information.
Let's let's fix the visualizations.
We were doing from a for to sort of have the information that now we
can provide such as know.
How much time a function took exclusive of its Children of the like of
the people that called, for example, right?
Or knowing how when things happened relative to each other that sort
of stuff and that sort of stuff that I would like to be able to see in
that part.
I like to have a really nice profile view there because, you know,
like, like you've seen so far.
It doesn't take that long to do this stuff, you know, in a couple
weeks of handmade hero time which is, you know, something like a few
days of full time.
Programming time, you can build yourself, a pretty nice inline
profiling system, and there's really nothing like that.
Having that nice in line profiling system.
Really allows you to kind of just always have a heads up kind of a
rough idea, you know, of what your
Is doing without having to go into some kind of mentality that like,
oh, I'm profiling, my code now.
And so you never have to worry about like, oh, launching up some
external profiling, tool of these sorts of things.
So having that in line, profiler, even if you do, end up using
external profiling tools because they have some features that you want
that, you don't have time, it'll matter whatever having an inline
profiling tools, usually, a really great idea because it's all about
keeping that situational awareness of your code, so that you always
know what's going on, all throughout the development, it really helps
you keep
In mind, it really helps.
You spot bugs, weird, things happening earlier rather than later and
it prevents you from getting into the situation where you suddenly
opened, up this sort of really you know, you're opening up the trunk
of the car and all this membered bodies are in there.
Sometime at the end of the project, that's not the best place to be
right.
You'd rather always know what's going on and kind of have this.
The sort of heads-up idea of like, where am I?
Where's my time being spent roughly, how many times does things get
called having that in in mind all the time helps you make,
Really good architectural decisions all along the way so that you're
not just slammed with it at the end and going, oh my God.
Like what do I do now have I painted myself into a bunch of Corners?
Like what do I do?
So having that information all the time I think is really good and
that's why I think spending this time is good and like you've seen, it
just doesn't take that much time.
We're talking about a few hours here, you know, 10 hours, 15 hours,
something like that.
To build a pretty good system from scratch is really a very small time
investment on any project and so I really highly recommend
And keeping that going if you can in your own projects and certainly
I'd like to do it here on handmade hero.
So anyway, I guess the price yet starts mentions day 182 if you have
pre-ordered the game handmade hero dot org and you would like to
follow along day, 181 source.
Code is what I'm starting with today here on day 182, if you want to
follow along unzip, that if you are using the GitHub, use the tag
Browse by tags and grab tag 181 and that's where we're at.
So, however, your however you're getting your source,
Of these days whoever your source code hookup.
Is there whether it's the Zips or the GitHub, go ahead and get that
day out and that's where I'm going to be starting at now.
If you remember what we did on the, on the last time we had just
finished up, making sure that we could we could run with sort of this
new system and that everything seemed to work realtively.
Well, it does.
And that's pretty cool.
It's a little slower than our old system, but I have a feeling, I
can't say for sure, but I have a feeling that a lot of
That has nothing to do with the insertion of the timing.
I think our timing code is probably still pretty darn efficient and I
suspect that pretty much the entirety of the of the additional time
spent on behalf of the system is in the collation phase and again,
that's totally fine.
If collation takes a long time and you know, that's a that's where all
the time is spent for this particular profile system.
It means that we can't really run the game at the full frame rate
while we're pro while reviewing the profile, right?
But we can certainly run it.
The full frame rate then pause and view the profile for example or any
other things like that, we can always sort of compensate for that
stuff.
So if it's just a collation phase, that's slow.
That's really not going to be a problem.
So as we dive a little bit deeper in the keep that in mind, the inline
profile slowing our game down is only a problem if it's slowing the
game down inside the actual code that we care about, if it's all stuff
that can be isolated into a into a post pass, which I believe it
already.
Is because I think we did a reasonable job on it, then we really don't
care because there's plenty of ways, we can get around that plenty,
plenty of ways, you can get around that, that that we can do, that
will make it.
So we don't really have to care and that won't affect our ability to
use it.
I don't think so.
Anyway, what I'd like to do now is go ahead and and talk about what we
are actually doing here in terms of how the buffers work and some
limitations of them, right?
Okay.
So first of limitations on
I don't think I'm going to fix and then I don't know that we really
ever would need to fix and that one I just want to get out of the way
so that we're all aware that it's there and I'll put it to do in just
to talk about it.
Here.
I will say to do Casey, no attempt is currently made.
To ensure that the final debug record.
Being written to the event array.
Actually complete their output prior to the rollover for the swap of
the event array Index, right?
So, what I mean by that is we have this Global debug event array and I
have two of them because as these events get streamed out into the
system and are recorded,
We want to be able to be doing that continuously from as many threads
as we want and we don't want to have to put any restrictions on it as
a result.
When somebody goes to actually gather the information, there is no way
for us to actually look at the data there, you know?
We can't, we can't sort of say, okay, the buffer is done, go start,
reusing it for the beginning, we can't do that until we've read, all
the data and reading all the data might take some time.
Meanwhile, some other threads want to be able to write to it.
And we don't want introduce a mutex.
And I think that's because the whole point of our timing blocks, as we
want them to be as fast as possible.
They're just like, right directly to the debug log and that's it.
So because we've done it that way.
It means we need sort of a double buffering system.
We need to make sure that we are writing to one while we're reading
from the other.
And then we just in one Atomic, call swap them so that we know that we
never have a conflict now, that's all fine.
But what it does mean is that if somehow and it's incredibly unlikely
but if some bizarre thing happened where a thread
Got its debug event, array, index back from the synchronous operation
had, not written to it yet and in that period of time, between when it
got the index back and literally like it just got preempted right
there and held on preemption for the entire time, it took the other
thread to swap, do the atomic swap to the new buffer and then parse
the whole debug buffer, all the way to the end where those missing
elements are and then read those missing elements before.
Or they were written.
It would get bogus information, right?
The chance of that happening are effectively zero.
I think I don't think there's probably anyway can happen.
It would be really crazy.
Maybe if there were a lot less debug events in the array, it might
happen once in a while, but we're talking about a debug array that has
potentially hundreds of thousands of entries in it.
Remember it had more than 64,000 entries in it already.
So we're talking about a massive log of chances of that happening.
I think are extremely slim, and if they were to happen, I think I'd be
okay with that.
So we'll just put it that way.
Now Famous Last Words, maybe that'll come back to bite us, but I'm
just not that concerned about.
So I'm going to let it be and I don't think the cost of fixing it to,
in terms of how that might affect the lightweightness of the ability
to time those blocks.
I just don't think it's worth it at that point.
Okay, so that's what's going on.
That's a limitation that I think we're just going to live with and be
okay.
With I don't foresee it causing us very many problems and I hope that
is true.
But
but now we've got some limitations that we do want to fix.
And those specifically are about, you know, this stuff that I didn't
do, right?
It's not like the system had a problem.
But if you take a look here, I don't know what core index I'm on.
I don't know what thread index.
I'm on, right.
And so that leaves me in a situation where I can't really do the work
that I actually want to do.
And the core index part is a nice to have.
It's just nice to know.
So
You can see if we want to what korres, our threads are running on how
they may get moved around that sort of stuff, that's just nice
information to have.
If we're doing profiling work,
no big deal, we could leave that one a zero forever and not really
care.
And I was kind of hoping to get that out of our dtsc P but maybe
that's too much to ask and so maybe we won't.
So maybe fixable in the future, maybe not, I don't know something.
I think about a little more but not that critical thread index is the
big, one threading index is absolutely crucial.
And the reason the thread index is crucial is because some of our
threads call the same function.
So for example, if we want to do profiling of our renderer, which is
something that we very may, you know, we've already done some
profiling, the render, it's a very time critical component, the
chances of us wanting to insert
Profile counters into the render very high.
But the problem that we have, there is many different threads are
using the exact same functions.
What that means is, we cannot assume that any given functions, begin
and end are happening on the same thread.
So, we may see a begin event for one of our blocks and then an end
event for one of our blocks, we don't know if that end event was from
some other thread, finishing that function, or from the thread at the
beginning was on.
So, we need some way right of being
Well, to determine how these things line up in a thread sense.
Now, since we know that threads always are sequential, meaning inside
a given thread, we're never going to have that happen.
Because threads it actually do things in order.
It's not like multi-threading where different things happen, different
times, right?
So, for a single thread, if we see begin, begin, begin and end.
We know that the first begin goes with the last end, and the second,
you know, we know that they line up, right, because a thread can only
enter a timing block and then leave it.
It and any entry that it did into another timing block would have to
happen, you know, as something sort of subordinate to that and it
would go in that order, right?
But if we have multiple threads of the mix, that's no longer true.
They can begin and end at arbitrary ties.
We don't have any way to pair those up unless we have some kind of a
unique identifier that tells us, which thread was weaving through
here, which was the one that allows us to pair up.
Those begins and ends as being the same, right?
Okay, so we have two options for solving this problem.
Option one.
Is we figure out a way to get a thread index, we figure out a way to
get some number that is unique to the thread that it's executing on
and we use that.
Now, the reason that I like that the most is because that allows us to
tell other information such as what threads were doing, what?
When so that we can have a picture of our threading, baked into the
log, as well, and that's extra information, extra information that I
would like to have now.
We're not crazy threaded in hand.
Here, you know, we have a few things that are threaded, it's not a
complete crazy thread thing.
We got like asset threads render threads and some background
compositing threads, right?
So we have threads
But we're not thread, crazy.
It's not.
Our game is not all about multi threading or anything like that, so if
we didn't want to do that, that wouldn't be the end of the world.
If we find that it's too onerous to do so that would necessarily be
the end of the world because the other thing we could do is since we
know that the begin and end blocks are paired.
What we could also do is introduce another counter, another u-32 that
just gets atomically incremented every time.
And instead of thread index, it would just be like unique ID and at
the top of the block, we would sink.
We would synchronously increment that counter put it in and then on
the end block, we would use the same that same value so we can pair
them up.
And since we know that
One of those will get a unique one.
All the way till four billion when the counter wraps, which let's be
honest is not going to happen inside the course of one frame because
this debug buffer.
First of all, whatever flow for starters.
But yeah, since that we know is not an issue, we could easily do it
that way and and get the base level functionality out of it right, we
can get the base, the basic idea out of it, which is very specifically
making sure that our beginning
A properly.
So very straightforward could Implement that immediately if we want to
do that, we could do that.
So, the only question is, can we get a number that corresponds to our
thread index in any easier way?
And so, what I'm going to do here is I'm going to first talk about in
win32, there is a way that we can get the thread ID with a function
call.
Now, remember function call not really something that we want to do in
the middle of a timer block.
So what I'm going to do is I want to look and see if I do get current
thread ID, I just want to see what that would do if I called it,
right?
So if in here, I have a thing where I'm going to do, get current
thread ID and I just go, you know, red ID like so and I guess I'll put
this in the winter to layer so we don't have to complicate things by
including Windows here or anything like that.
I just want to see what it is actually going to do.
And so that we can have some some opinion about that, right?
So here's when main right on the interest to win main, I'm going to
see about getting that current thread ID.
So I'm gonna pop over to bugger set a breakpoint win main.
Oops again set a breakpoint in Maine.
And here we go.
And what I want to do is I want to look at the assembly.
I want to see how expensive it is when it when it tries to get that
out, right.
And so you can see here here, we're in the assembly, right?
Here's the code B.
Here's the the parameters to the call, it's going to call out to this
function.
And so I want to do is I want to step in there and want to see what
it's actually going to do goes into assume.
This is like the the dynamic linking jump table.
So let's go ahead in there and see what it does.
So it looks like this is what I suspected, it looks like it's a really
straightforward thing in order to get that thread ID.
You can see that it's just referencing off the GS, which is segment.
It's sort of loading in, I can sort of see if I can get some
information here.
It's loading into our ax.
It's loading in this, this pointer here, I assume because you can see
that's about to use it as a dressing.
I assume that's our thread-local storage.
So that's basically a pointer to memory.
That's specific to our thread.
I assume that this is some segmented addressing, right?
Where the threads themselves have, each individual thread has a
different
Segment for addressing set.
So then we go ahead and move off of that address.
We move it into eax which is the return register.
So there we go.
So getting off our thread ID out for example is really a simple as a
dressing off of this, this GS right here.
So what that implies to me and you know, this this could be this could
be a little bit presumptuous of me but what that implies to me.
So, it's all I wanted to do was have a way of knowing what my thread
actually was, it shouldn't be too difficult, right?
It's just two instructions to access thread-local storage that the
local storage for this thread.
And again, we haven't really talked about that.
So maybe I should just say really quickly what that is, but I'll
postpone that for 45 seconds.
I just have to figure out where my thread-local storage is by using
this GS segment addressing and then I go ahead and address off of that
into a fixed location to get the thread ID.
But at some level, this is already a thread ID, right?
Because whatever the address of my thread-local storage is, if that's
unique to every thread, I could just use that.
So really just RX just this one keyword move out of the GS segment.
That one move is all I would need just one instruction and grab it.
Sup.
What I mean by thread-local storage?
All, I mean by thread-local storage is most operating systems these
days when a threads begins.
So you saw us, we had create thread right?
You remember this stuff?
Hopefully for those of you who watch handmade here are regularly,
we've got this function, create thread, we create the thread, we
obviously get one thread of the beginning.
When Windows calls are wind made, its calling it in a particular
thread, it's our main thread and then we create other threads give
them pointers to functions.
Windows will create a thread for us, whatever that means to Windows
and then
Start executing the code at the function that we gave it at that time.
On that thread.
Now, when it creates the thread, both for our initial startup thread,
and for the threads that we create, what it does, is it sets, aside,
some memory that it's like, this is memory, that's going to be unique
to this threat, right?
It's like a little section of memory that's like this is for this
thread and it sets up some known segment.
Addressing some like some predefined stuff in the memory table
basically.
That's in fact, I think we might, there we go.
It's actually right there in the actual registers you can see the GS
segment right there.
This is the value that it's actually.
Got it sets up this concept of a location that's in the CPU registers
in these extra segment registers right, which are again, things kind
of that used to be like they were kind of a holdover from the old
days.
When you always
has to do segmented addressing
Out as we think about us and it's always flat but there's no reason
you can't kind of consider there to be segments where you say oh I
want to address off of a particular segment register and say like okay
when I give you a value instead of you thinking, this is my normal
memory.
I want to tell you what segment, I'm going to go office.
So if you look at here this is this is an example of I'm taking some
address and I'm addressing 48, hex off of that address.
I'm going to load it.
That's just my normal standard addressing in sort of the default.
Default segment, if you will of my virtual memory.
This this GS segment is a way of saying, I want to address memory
slightly differently.
The address is based off of this other piece of information, right?
And the reason that they use that in this case is because what they do
is for every thread, when the operating system switches between
threads, obviously restores the register state of the CPU.
So like for example, if a thread is running, it gets preempted,
another thread runs during that changeover, obviously it has to
restore all the register State because whatever preamp something
that's got
See what the registers were because the code needs to be resumed at
some point and have all those registers come back.
One of the things that it restores are the segment registers.
So each thread can have a segment register set to a different value
that allows it to have effectively thread-local storage by saying any
time you want to access some information that I believe to be specific
to your thread.
I will use the GS segment instead of normal and resting so that I can
get you different information than what a different some
Other thread would have gotten, right?
And so something like that thread ID window.
Zoe stores.
It in exactly the same place for every thread in relative to the GS
segment but that GSA went is actually pointing to a different place in
memory for every thread, right?
And so that's how that sort of situation works and that's you know
that stuff is way before my time.
I don't know really anything about segment addressing.
I only know as much as I just said.
You know, so I unfortunately can't really tell you much else about
things like the GS segment or this, or these other segment registers
like I that's out way outside my area of Competency for sure, but it's
something that an old-school dust programmer would have known about a
lot because segments were a much bigger deal back then.
Because all memory addressing was all about segments all the time and
it wasn't like you had this concept that one particular method of
addressing was like the main way and then there were segments for
special times, it was more like a little more sort of segments
oriented than that.
So anyway, what I can see there is that that's that's something that
doesn't really require a function call at the end of the day.
So what I'm kind of wondering is, is there some kind of intrinsic?
I could use.
I mean, I was like I just really do that directly myself, but is there
some kind of intrinsic?
I could use to get that.
So for example, if I just want something like
Thread ID, intrinsic some way to make it.
Not have to drop.
Drop a function call
To do that every time and I don't know if it's likely this, this is
not looking particularly good.
This is this is talking about sort of other other sort of stuff and
what's kind of frustrating about that as we know it's possible, right?
It's just a simple mob.
So it's kind of unfortunate to to think about that.
But let's see in win32.
Let's see if there's any know, if there's any real way to do that
access to the ti be so you can see like there.
Using inline as in there to do it which is you know again not what I
would really like to do.
Here we go with using Microsoft intrinsics, so they've got to
underscore read DFS word there.
So, you know, maybe we can do something a little bit cranky here.
And again, since this is debug code, one of the benefits is even if
what we do is a little bit janky and doesn't work reliably on end user
system, it's okay because it's code will never run on an end user
system unless we make a mistake and ship it, but you know what, we
would fix that.
So the idea is,
No the profile blocks will get come we'll get compiled out and so we
don't have to worry if it only works sometimes or some in some places
or only on x 64 or stuff like that.
That's actually, okay, so let's take a look and see M SV C compiler,
intrinsics, I want to see if I just look
Sort of directly in there.
Can I find anything that's like talks about threads or anything like
that?
It doesn't look, doesn't look like it.
So let's look at moves there is that move DFS?
Word intrinsic there.
Let's just take a look and see if we've got it.
Move, move move.
Let's see.
Doesn't look good here.
Does not look good.
Let's see, access GS segment intrinsic or access GS intrinsic and it's
DC.
Let's see on Microsoft.
S are some details.
Let's see.
It just for should not relate to the stock at all an extra stretchy
part of the operating system data.
Instead of FS segment.
Descriptor, let's see FS.
+ G SI B and long mode.
Just are only available in kernel mode.
Oh, that's unfortunate.
You know, second area is just pointing to some kernel mode.
You won't need to the address person.
I don't know what these for these would be
Well, that'd be too bad.
That was true about this.
Read memory location from a location for Side by an officer.
Let's begin the GS segment.
Well what do you know that sounds like exactly what I want?
So it does look like that.
Read G.
GSD word would be sort of exactly what we would want.
So I don't know.
Like I said, not something that I've worked with before.
I'm just kind of winging it here.
So I'm going to go up, I'm gonna go up in here and I'm just going to
say you know what, folks, let's go ahead and read GSD word and I'm
also going to do, you know what I'm going to do too.
I'm going to go ahead and say that, maybe we just straight-up.
Look at exactly what that thing.
Is doing because remember, it was, oh, hello.
Nope, not cite.
Don't yet, stop it.
Stop, don't do not.
There we go.
So I'm just going to go ahead and step in there or not.
I'm going to go ahead and step in there.
I said, okay, I'm gonna go ahead and step in there after the jump.
Double jump, double jump.
Yep, the compiler Windows likes to double jump.
It found that Metroid upgrade.
So you can see we're accessing 30th off of that, right?
For starters and I assume that is our thread-local storage segment.
That's what I'm assuming.
Anyway, so you could imagine us reading a d word off of that segment,
like, so that's going to get us back a pointer.
Apparently, this is our thread-local storage.
I guess, again, totally just going by the disassembly here, I have no
idea what I'm doing.
Literally, I'm just reverse engineering pretty much exactly what I
think I need to do in order to not have to do a double system, a jump
into a system call and crap like this.
So I do that and then I get back that pointer
And then I'm going to go ahead and here and get that 48h off of the
pointer, right?
So that's going to be a reference off of there.
So, yeah, so when I do this well, you know what, it's reading, a
pointer.
So Daddy words, not going to do it.
Do I have the ability to read a quadword?
I do.
So I can read a quad word out there, right?
So, I'm going to assume that that's a pointer.
And again, it's reading a d word app.
It's a d word the next time around, right?
It's a d word, read.
I'm going to do is it's going to steam this points to a d word.
There it is.
I'm then going to go ahead and grab it.
This is our thread ID, number two and I'm just going to say okay so 48
hex.
Here's my thread-local storage although I guess technically I want
this as a you ate so I can address off of it as 48.
I thread-local storage plus 48.
If I treat that as a you 32 and then dereference it, I believe that
will give me the thing that I want.
Now that may be protected memory.
I don't know if I can even access that.
I didn't see a ring transition there.
So I don't know if that's true but I don't know if it
Show me that in the debugger.
Anyway, read gqd word is snot found did Ice.
Oh whoops, it's G.
St.
There we go.
Let's see.
Bat.
So I don't know.
This is going to do it all again, I'm totally just playing around here
to see what I can do.
There's the thread ID, so it's thinking it's hex.
1094 is the thread ID.
Here's my thread-local storage looks like looks like it gave it back
to me and it looks like it's the same value as I was getting before or
something similar, like it's up in that that range so that's good.
Grab that thread ID.
What do you know?
Look at that.
Look at that folks.
So now, if we take a look at what happens in the disassembly, right?
We can see that this is actually just totally perfect, right?
It's just one instruction even to get that GS pointer, which I know
has to be correct.
I can even ignore the thread-local storage part.
Probably, although I don't know necessarily, I don't know if I need a
second mauve.
But tit, in order to get the windows thread ID, doing one extra
instruction at this at every block start not a huge deal.
Might be worth it.
So that's kind of cool, right?
That is kind of cool.
I am pretty happy.
About that.
So let's just take a look at what it would take to go ahead and throw
that in there.
I'm going to jump into handmade debug here when we're doing reach
record, debug event.
If I wanted to make that happen it would be this, right?
And there's our thread ID.
And so if I then want to do, put that in thread index, I can do it
like that.
Now, we do have a problem, which I think our thread index is only you
16.
In fact, you can see right there that it is only.
It's only a you 16.
So there's that since we don't have
Have the core index yet?
I could just say, what the heck?
Make this be a 32?
So that way I don't have to worry when it comes back, but for now we
could just chop it.
We'll see how that goes.
Oops, I met you 16.
D, there we go.
And so there we go.
Now I feel like in general, that is just totally fine.
And if we go into handmade intrinsics inside compiler msv, see, I can
then sort of abstract this out because I don't know that that's
actually going to work anywhere else.
We probably mean to use a different technique on another platform.
so if we want to get back thread ID,
Like so then we need to do this on MSNBC or on Windows.
I should say however you want to think about that.
At the moment, they're the same.
We might have to differentiate more by platforms later, but there's
what that's what we would do, right?
We do that region.
Word the thread-local storage so on, so yeah, so that's pretty cool.
That's really all we would need to do and then we just return that
value and we are good to go at that point.
So in theory, we can replace this with get thread ID and now we're
still platform safe to a certain degree meaning that we can still run
our profiles on other platforms by implementing those functions once
we are actually on those other platforms.
So,
Are we go?
Okay, so that's, I believe.
Now gives us accurate thread, IDs, and Theory, as part of our profiler
does not involve any operating system nonsense and should not flows
down especially in an optimized build when that stuff gets in lined.
So if we go over here and we check like build up at if I switch this
to an optimized build, which is what we would be using for profiling
that in theory, I should be in pretty good shape.
I would think so.
There we go.
That's that's where we're at at the moment, and we've got a thread
ideas now.
So that should give us, plenty of ability to sort of be a little bit
more fancy and get a little bit more data in here.
So that went a lot more that went a lot easier than I thought it was
going to go.
I lucked out assuming that we're actually getting a reliable thread ID
out of that.
That was really smooth.
So yeah.
So we can go ahead and start right now.
Bring together a better debug view than this one.
Now that we have that more information and so what I'd like to do is
I'd like to start.
I think what I'd like to do is start having a concept if you will of
when blocks begin and end in this sort of stuff, I'd like to start
building more of a timeline view of things.
I'd like to turn this thing down here, because I really like these
kinds of displays.
I'd like to turn this thing down here into something a little more.
Well, that shows this kind of what's going on in terms of how our code
is, who's taking up the time in our code.
It's kind of like a pie chart, right?
Every one of these lines is showing us what's going on where and you
can already see how easy it is to tell.
If we added some ability to like figure out what functions these were
or whatever, you can already see very dramatically, who's taking the
time, right?
The giant blue bar is the problem.
Not the little tiny green bar, right?
And so I like having that ability because that's the kind of thing
that allows me to sort of get more information about what is
occurring.
So okay.
Since we have about 20 minutes left in the Stream.
Yeah.
I think, what I'll do is I'll sort of postponed improving the of is
itself till tomorrow, when we can start right at the beginning on
improving of is what I'd like to focus on today is getting rid of this
thing.
If I can so if you remember we pass this debug frame and input info
thing in here and the only reason I was doing that is because there's
no way to get these debug counters to to work at all on the platform
side of things.
But what I'd like to do is figure out a way that we can turn that
around.
I'd like to figure out a way that we could have the, debug counters
that.
We, I'd like to figure out a way that we could have it so that the
platform code,
Can be unified with our regular debug code such that we can use the
counters on both sides of the of the of the program, which is a little
tricky.
But I think we could do it.
There's I can't think of any reason why head why we can't do it just a
little bit tricky.
We have three compilation units.
It seems like we should be able to have three arrays and have it work
properly.
And in theory, they should all be able to write into the global debug
event array as well.
So really, the only thing that's a little bit tricky.
Is the handmade debug .h code has to be factored in such a way that
would allow me to expose the important parts of it.
The part that allows you to record a debug event.
For example, that has to be accessible from the actual handmade
platform.sh itself.
And so it kind of has to move over, right?
So I'm going to go ahead and do that.
See how much of it I can get done in 15 minutes?
Hopefully, most of it.
And so that way tomorrow we can focus on improving the visibility.
Is so I'm going to go ahead and start with that.
Again, we kind of you can, you can sort of see it happening here, how
record debug event work and how time block works here.
So, what I'm going to do is, I'm going to try to pull those out, put
them into the platform layer here, so that they actually are part of
this this system right here.
Okay, so let's do that, if I just go ahead and grab this out like so.
And then I take this stuff and do the same.
Then that's all the code that I actually need, right?
And handmade intrinsics.
These intrinsics, I guess the other thing is that atomic
The atomics that are used in here.
So we've got a couple of them, we would need the adieu 64, right?
That guy, Atomic add 64.
We've got two of those that are happening there.
Oh, wait.
No, we don't, this is, this is not necessary anymore, I guess, right?
So actually, a bunch of this stuff can be removed.
I'll leave that for.
Well, you know, I might as well as do it.
We don't need it right now.
Goodbye, so record, debug event on the start and the end is all we
really need there as far as this
This is concerned.
We need that counter in it, that's the needs to be there.
However, some of this other stuff does not necessarily need to be
there, we've got that hit count.
I don't think we need to store any of that stuff.
Looks like debug record star record.
Doesn't really need to be stored either.
So I think we're just looking at this if I'm not very much in error
about that, I would say that looks pretty much like what I need right
and to do record the hit count value here so that we can get those
sort of numerical counter
As vac potentially, we may want to add that a little bit later but
that's not really relevant to what we're doing right now at all.
It's something I wanted to mention.
So that's all the code that we need for the for that block record,
debug event.
Again needs the atomic ad.
And it needs the our dtsc, which we also don't really have our own
call for, which we should have our own call for, and then we have that
get thread ID.
So those intrinsics, I don't know, transics, they are not in here at
the moment, right?
So the intrinsics would have to get moved in here as well.
Not any of these other ones, these are all fine, but just these ones
specifically right here, the atomics would have to get moved in as
well.
So I've got to do that, really nothing I can do about it because I
need access to those so that's going to have to happen.
But first, let's talk about the more pressing.
That's, that's just a mess matter of, kind of cleaning this up a
little bit and just doing it, but the more pressing problem, right?
Is, how do we find the addresses to write to for these for these guys,
right?
How do we actually know the location of the rights?
For any of these things?
Like these debug events?
Right.
so,
That part is a little bit trickier and I got to think it through
because if you take a look at what happens here, this this right here
and this right here are both sort of Global's that need to be
available to the debug system.
So that whenever you come through here and you're going to use them,
you have to have a way of getting right.
You have to have a way of knowing what we're what those pointers are.
There's two
Pointers and both pointers need to be respected in some way.
So I don't necessarily know what the easiest way to do.
That would be
I feel like probably what we could do is make it so that they're
always stored.
They're always kind of stored on the platform's layer side, right?
I mean, we can make it so that those are declared and, and they live
on the platform of your side, when the dll is loaded, we can make it
so that
It is those global values are initialized at that startup time.
I don't think that would be particularly difficult to do.
I also don't know if we couldn't possibly just have it sink those
I feel like dll binding should actually allow us to do.
I haven't done this in a very long time, but I feel like, dll binding.
Should be able to patch the address of the global just fine.
so, I think
Deco, spec import data.
I think.
We can just make it just plain work.
So let's see if I see if you're outside.
The deal was guess it's a convenient that removes labor Direction.
When you import data from a dll you still have to go through the
import address table before Douglass Park dealer import, this menu.
I'd remember do next eleven direction, right?
Okay.
And access to that.
So the dll you do that when you marked as like deal Imports and
programmatic interested in the interaction table, the energy code for
you,
You no longer have to worry about the steps above as stated
previously.
Do not use things like deal import decoration on the data when
building the dll functions within the dll do not use the import
address table to access the data object, therefore, you will not have
the extra love in Direction present.
So.
Okay, so that's actually probably what we want.
Then, what that means is that we can leave it declared and operating
the way that it was before, where it's actually the data's actually in
the dll itself.
And then the platform layer.
Just grabs it.
We could do that.
But is that what we really want?
It's so tricky.
Here's what I'm going to do.
I'm going to go ahead and say that.
Yeah, I'm going to consolidate this a little bit.
So what I'm going to do first of all is I'm going to say that we have
some kind of a known way of addressing this thing so I'm going to
simplify this a little bit down.
So if I take a look at this here, you can see how we've got this all
set up and it's kind of got this this whole situation going where we
declare these things and
Different places and have different stuff that going on, I don't know
that we need some of the things that we were doing.
So, for example, in handmade the CPP I think it is or handmade debug
s.
So, we include handmade debug way down at the bottom, right.
You can kind of see the way that we did that.
Is we did, you know, we Define these things here.
We no longer really care.
How many of those things there were we don't iterate over the debug
record array ever, right?
That's not something that we actually care.
Well, I know that's not true.
That's not quite true.
Alright, so, but it doesn't really change my plan.
So what I'm thinking is, can I consolidate this into a thing that's a
little bit cleaner in terms of how you
Actually access it, right?
Can we do something where we say?
All right, the thing that we're actually talking about here is going
to be a struct, right?
And that struct is going to have a debug record, debug record array
thing in it and there's going to be three of them, because that's how
many translation units we have.
There's also going to be this stuff in it, right?
There's going to be the, you 64 for the defendant array index, debug
event thing.
Thing.
There's also going to be the debug event array pointers, right?
So these are the the two arrays that we've got there.
And so, furthermore, I think I could do this by going like that and
just actually having it there and, similarly, the debug record erase
stuff.
We could just say, you know what, you can't have any more than,
however, many counters there are.
So we, you know, we've got, we've got, Max, debug event and Max debug
event, or Max debug record count and you know, who cares what it is,
does not matter.
Something like this to find Max debug units and that's 3 or whatever
translation units like that.
Yeah.
And so then this struct right?
This struct has everything in it that we would need.
So this is like our debug table or something, right?
And yeah, like what I would then do is translate everything over to
working solely off of the global debug tables.
So there's the debug cable
Right.
And there we go.
That's what it is.
That's the whole thing.
That's all we've got.
I also might go ahead and say this was volatile.
I never really did do that.
The atomic should have done anyway but
It helps I like having it there, so I can just remember.
Oh, yeah.
anyway, so we got the the diva table and then we don't need
Any of these things, right?
So that's good.
Shove that in there, get rid of this.
And now, we don't really need to declare anything anywhere.
Really everyone just needs to be able to get at that debug table
somehow, right?
And they, when we actually do our build, instead of having the two
ways we were doing before of defining stuff instead, we're just going
to have just the debug record array index.
That's all we actually need.
Right?
And so now we can actually do this like so.
And so now the platform layer can be its own translation unit, we
could even make this a more formal thing like translucent translation
unit Index, right?
Like we could do something like this.
Right.
And so now, we just have a thing that we know we've got three
translation into units, so let's just go for it, right?
Okay.
So that seems reasonable to me.
Certainly and let's see if we can then go ahead and kind of, you know,
consolidate this stuff down into something a little bit cleaner.
So let's go ahead and look now at the places where this is ever
actually accessed.
So you can see that this stuff down here is really just about storing.
Some debug info doesn't really have anything to do with anything that
we care about.
So I'm going to go through here and see, you can see that some of the
stuff is getting declared.
Here.
I don't care about any of that anymore because I just want my debug
table, that's the whole thing just that right there like so call that
the global debug table.
There it is, this stuff now.
No longer has to be their global current event array index that can
also be moved into here.
For example, it does that one doesn't really have to be but I feel
like we might as well.
Why not right?
Then we've got the debug records optimized count.
That's I don't.
Think is, yeah, those things still kind of have to be declared
somewhere.
We just don't have to ever
Do this part of it anymore, right?
What we can do is just something like debug records count, you know,
or wherever we want the actual counts to happen, give a record count 0
is happening like this.
We'll have to think about you.
Almost you almost want something like this, right?
Debug records count.
And you kind of want them to have their different counter values in
here.
Right?
But that's not really something we can probably do directly.
So yeah, we kind of need these these.
We kind of need these extern cops kind of things.
Unfortunately, as far as I could tell,
Right?
We don't need the consignee.
More of though that can go away and these debug record optimized
declaration, these can all go away.
All we need to be able to do is say that we've got our debug records
main count now as well.
And that is going to be counter.
Right.
Then we've got that extern and that's one that we're gonna have to
pull in from the other file, the global debug table is declared there,
so that's all good.
And then we've got our handmade optimized over here.
That guy has got the debug records down here as well.
So there's it getting defined, we don't need it to do the, the records
anymore.
So that's all good.
And I think that's really all we would need from that.
So, let's continue down the road to success.
We hope lies ahead of us and not behind us.
But as we go, I'm going to go ahead and pull the debug table over here
because now we can go ahead and do this here.
And that is actually legitimate all the time.
I'm going to pull these time, Block B down there, so
Okay.
Oh, I did that exactly the wrong way.
This wants to be at the bottom of things, doesn't it?
There we go.
All right, so our debug table needs to be below their obviously, there
we go.
And now, we can just say the global debug table.
That's got the event array index.
So we can get rid of the debug parts of these things.
This is just the event array.
This is the record array.
Just call this event, some records.
Now, in fact, we could call this event array index, and event index.
In fact, event, array index, actually could just, yeah, I guess.
Well, now, you know that needs to do is and then we've got this is no
longer as we called go B, just current event array index so that all
is much nicer.
Certainly in here, we have our Global debug table access is now going
to be just accessing that I believe and we have our Atomic switch.
We have to move in.
I think I had about five minutes on the clock.
Not very much, but hopefully I can, I can finish up what I'm
Here.
So we have Global debug event array.
That's just going to be the global debug table.the events array.
And that is all she wrote for that.
We've got that.
Get thread ID, is not imported, yet debug record array index constant.
This is actually the translation unit now and we should probably go
ahead and rename that as well.
So in debug event instead of calling it d by record array, indexes of
just translation unit, right?
And that is something that we specify in the build translation unit
index.
We go Atomic, add get thread translation.
Unit index.
Undeclared identifier, what?
Translation unit index.
It's right there.
What are you complaining about?
Oh, in the test asset Builder.
Well, alright, I guess we got to tell it that in the end of the test
asset Builder as well, not that we'll ever use this in the test asset
Builder, but we need to be there.
So now it's there.
All right.
Got the atomic add.
We need to move in got thread ID.
That's fine.
Okay, so here we are in the debug record array.
So that's actually going to be Global debug table and then we have our
records
Excel.
See what else.
We've got the bug record array so that all looks fine.
Initializing cannot convert.
That is true because this now needs to use that translation unit
Index, right?
It wants that's that specific set.
So get thread ID, that's good Atomic, add get thread, ID talking head.
Okay, so let's go and fix this now before we import those, those
intrinsics cool ladybug records now has to know how many there are.
That's not really a problem.
Again, that's told to us right here.
So we have basically the oops, we have the the main count
Right, plus the debug records.
Optimize count.
account plus, you know, whatever debug records platform
And at the moment, we'll just make that be stubbed out since nothing's
coming from it.
But then we're going to want to clean that up in a second.
Well, probably tomorrow.
Okay.
So got to move those intrinsic sin.
Then what else we got?
Debug records main array County but it remained that's actually debug
workers main count.
Like so.
And then again, that's this guy is just going to be the counter array,
plus the main count.
And
Optimize count.
What else we got there?
Okay.
Oops, that's going to be 3.
This is going to be 3 and this is going to be 0 again for the moment.
All right.
So Undeclared, identifier, debug records main, that's true.
Because now, this is actually, in fact, we don't even need this
anymore because now, debug records translation unit can just be in the
global debug table, it can just look up directly in records because
we've set it up now to be working properly there.
Then we've
To debug record array index inside the event is actually just, again,
the translation unit I believe, right?
This is, this is looking we change what that means and so that's all
good.
Now we can come down here to the global current event.
That's just going to be the global debug table current event array
index.
So we're just again, just sort of cleaning up that naming scheme
there.
Nothing else happening here.
This is going to be the same thing.
Here's the global dubourg, table event array index.
Aunt, index.
And then in here, same thing, level debug table event array index.
Oops.
Is that current
I believe that's correct.
So now we've gotten rid of all the compiler errors and I'll just
quickly because I want to see where we're at.
In terms of having things work, I'm going to go ahead and take those
intrinsics out.
I'm going to go ahead and pull those into the platform layer.
Take it.
If compiler.
I believe we have that setup.
Here we do, right?
And there's our, if compiler, msec.
So we know that that's set by now.
So I'm going to go ahead and just drop those in here.
At the moment, we're going to have one.
Organize this file a little bit better.
It's getting a little bit unwieldy at this point where everything is
and if you kind of see it's just a little bit out of control.
So what I want to do here is I'm going to go ahead and grab these
atomics and and move them out.
So,
Let's grab all these guys here.
In fact, I guess I can just grab this whole block.
All right.
So I think we're all good now.
Lisa looks like anyway.
I also think I'm still building an O2, which I didn't mean to do.
So let's go back here and so I don't know where we're at now.
We'll find out in a second.
Looks like not fabulous.
So it looks like we've got a bug in there which is just in terms of
probably how we organized, our different translation unit stuff and
all that goodness.
Let's take a quick look to see what's going on there in handmade debug
Let's think this through just real quick again, not gonna try to debug
it too much but just want to do it just a double just just a quick
little check to see if I can immediately see what we did wrong.
Where's our collate, debug records?
So the counter Ray stuff that's doing translation unit I think
properly because main than optimized.
Yeah, that all seems roughly correct to me.
Let's take a look at handmade platform.sh.
Each and see what we see there as well.
When we are doing the stuff we put in that translation unit, the
translation of is but I think it is, right?
Yeah, it's 01 into.
That's what I would have wanted to be
So, we've got all that in their atomic.
To the event in the X.
Yeah.
Etcetera, Etc.
We've got the records array and the event array.
That all looks fine to me.
Yeah, what's, what is this guy saying here?
Current event rate.
Index equals not.
Whichever one is we're doing, we do the atomic exchange.
We set up the swap for the current event array index.
That's what I wanted.
And so that all looks good.
The event rate index, in the event, can't get pulled out of that.
That also looks good, we don't call ft by records anymore, and in fact
you can consider that not relevant anymore, Global debug event array.
Why is that even still here?
Global debug event array.
That is our problem right there.
That's not good.
Why are you here?
So that's our problem.
That should have been this.
What can you do?
All right, little vestigial remain there and now we're back.
Okay and so we're almost we have a one more thing to do which is just
passing a piece of information from the platform layer for words that
says, how many counters that has but we pretty much did it.
So this is great.
I'm really happy about that because now we'll just be able to use
those uniformly across the platform boundary, which is what I wanted
and I think will also be able to kind of put it in a way that now it
doesn't matter how many translation units we have.
That's kind of cool too.
So yeah.
We're good.
And I would be pleased, I would be very pleased at this moment.
In time to take your questions, I would be very pleased to take some
questions from the handmade, hero studio audience, let's take a look
and made tail.
See, Merit or eqa.
All right, all right.
What do you think is an effective way to get better at assembly?
Go over a book tutorial, read the code disassembly and vs.
Mike acting can look at a piece of code for a couple of seconds and
estimating how much Cycles it takes.
And what the assembly code for it is I'd like to reach that level one
day.
so,
I guess what I would say is,
There's a couple ways you can go about it and I think you probably
want to do them all simultaneously.
You definitely want to read this assemblies.
Like I do, when you see me drop the December like we did on today's
stream, you want to be doing that so that you have an idea of what the
compiler is generating.
And you can just sort of go, well, you know, I don't really know what
this means, but I'm starting to see it, right?
It's kind of like an immersion.
Like when they said, like, you know, I want to go learn French so I
can go to Paris or something, right?
And it's like, okay, I I start watching, you know, a French film or
something with no subtitles.
Start hearing it.
So you get used to like oh I noticed when the person comes home, they
say this right there like, you know, bonjour madame or whatever.
So I think that's definitely important.
Do it.
You know it's free when you're debugging stuff to just do.
Right click and do show disassembly do it, you know do that.
Another one is the Intel architecture manual explains that the
instruction formats how they work you know spend some time with it,
just look read some very sections just you know just reading
Reading about it, read agner fogs webpage, that sort of stuff, you
know, just just do, just do reading occasionally on it.
And then finally, you know, right some definitely like we did with the
intrinsics on the renderer start writing some stuff in intrinsic.
That's that's not even really a Assembly Language, right?
But it's much closer than just straight C and then you can start to
think a little bit more in terms of how that's working.
And you can your disassembly, will look a lot more like what you're
writing and you can sort of start to narrow that.
Cap and so that's a lot of a lot of those are sort of good steps to
take.
Students say three were actually a pre-recorded laugh track.
Yes.
Hey I made here is filmed in front of a live studio audience, cue
Applause.
How would you deal with switching between multiple apis in a single
application?
Like software Hardware renderer, would it be structured similar to the
platform layer?
That's really kind of a very open-ended question.
It depends a lot on the nature of what you were doing software or
Hardware renderer switching is very different than how you would
switch other things platform wise.
Potentially,
And so it's worth understanding the difference.
And the reason for that is because there's theirs
There's a difference between wanting to switch, apis purely because
you need to interface with two different apis, that do the same thing.
And that might be an example of like opengl versus direct3d.
It's like, they're basically exactly the same, right?
It's like, they're just
Current syntactic dressing on exactly the same thing.
It's even saying driver underneath in a lot of cases, right with just
a different set of like ways in which it sort of fumbles itself
together.
There's a difference between Matt and abstracting a renderer in a way
that like, oh, I've got a totally different renderer.
Basically, for the iPad where it's like an embedded tiled, renderer
versus like, on the PC for like SLI card Invidia.
You know, Crazy Town by endless graphics.
The way in which you will separate those out.
Changes pretty dramatically.
And the reason for that is because the logic for the control flow
The boundary about where that, where you draw the line.
For the control flow changes, based on how different the control flow
has to be across all of the targets.
So for example, in opengl versus direct3d, you may be able to put
almost all of the control flow logic in the platform nonspecific part
of your code and the only thing that you will actually need in the
platform's aesthetic, part is the specific opengl or direct3d ish
calls.
You need to do to accomplish this exact same thing.
We're trying to do in both cases.
that may be completely not true for the case where you're talking
about going from, you know, some from opengl with Nvidia extensions,
Two metal on the iPad.
They may be like completely different control flows, not related at
all.
And in that case you typically want the the line of who is doing the
control flow moved up significantly.
And so you have to be very aware of the appropriate places to put
those divisions.
And the reason for that is because where you put that division, the
closer that lines up with the actual variability of the problem.
The more time you save in development, right?
Because if the cost for putting it too low, meaning the control flow
is all on the shared side and none of it's on the Lower Side.
The cost for that is if the if the thing is
On the other side, but s the actual implementations.
They will have this problem where they have to work around the
limitations of the control flow if they're very disparate.
So if they are all very different from each other.
Now it gets very expensive to try and Implement one of them because
they're essentially fighting the control flow decisions that were made
based on one specific one of them at some time.
And now it's just this nightmare and you get poorer performance and
you get Harry code in there and all sorts of bad things like that.
the consequence of,
Moving it too high is the opposite of that.
It's that now the upper layer does very little work and expects all
the implementations to do.
Most of the work they can now all be very custom, very efficient, but
you got no code reuse.
So now if it turns out that all of those implementations are all
basically the same, you just wasted a ton of effort because you could
have had all that be shared and now you've got 10 different, you know,
substrate layers on there that all have 90% of the coding common.
And it's like, oh,
Okay, that's not so good.
So in some circumstances you will even end up in a situation where you
draw the line in more than one place where you actually have a single
API stack.
A full stack for those of you who are full stack developers, you will
have a single sort of slice of the API there that actually has
multiple Cuts.
It's got the platform nonspecific part.
It's got the platform specific part, but in between there may be
another layer, which is sometimes there and sometimes not, and that is
shared code, that is common between some of the platform layers and
not others.
And so you end up building a three-tier four-tier who knows, right?
It could get very complicated depending on what sort of sisters were
talking about.
That are based on trying to build up the correct set of cuts through
the API that allow you to have the correct implementation everywhere
but without rewriting code unnecessarily throughout all of them.
Nobody does any of that, right?
Hardly ever.
It's it's an example of something that's very poorly done.
It's why I say, API design is definitely a very important skill and
very few people have it.
Almost nobody who makes apis has it?
Most of them have no idea, and that is why most apis are awful.
But it's obviously, it's a very important thing for architecture for
apis to understand that stuff.
It's worth practicing.
It's worth getting to understanding how important it is, and how all
these things work out.
It's a very important piece.
It's a piece, that's not taught very well, it's a piece of snow,
Dressed hardly ever.
And it's a piece of lot of people take for granted and and you end up
with, you know, you end up with with
The kinds of os and SDK API is that we get these days that are pretty
awful.
K, why don't you Powers expose apis?
That give us information about our code, like access to the AST,
because when we write a top-down, parser writing, something that the
car already has.
That is an excellent question.
and the answer to that question is because the C++ standard committee
is again, some of the worst designers that have ever come together to
make a
All of that stuff should have built been built in.
There is zero question about it.
In my mind, I've never been sure of anything else in my life, then
that meta information should have been a part of the C++ Peck from the
very beginning, but what do you want?
And so the compiler vendors.
Don't have a lot of incentive to provide that because they know that
most people Target more than one platform if they provide this
information, it doesn't really do anyone any good because they're not
going to Target it because I don't exist in that compiler, right?
Furthermore, they'd have to design it all themselves and maintain it
all themselves.
And that's just not something the compiler vendors.
Tend to do.
That said it has happened.
It has already happened before.
The compiler called Montana.
It was written at IBM.
It was a wonderful idea for C++ compiler.
Unfortunately was trapped inside a product called visual age that
nobody wanted to nobody used in, which is now gone, but it was
visually age version 56.
I'd 11:13, I have no idea.
The code name for the Pirates, Montana, and it did exactly that it
actually was obviously a bunch of people who actually got it.
They actually knew what they were doing.
Unfortunately, they were not the people working at Microsoft or
working on, you know, compilers that still existed but what they did
with the compiler was great.
It required no header files.
It was an incremental compiler.
Just like John, Blow wrote for Jay.
I were you don't need to pre to declare anything.
It was a C++ compiler that just it incremental way front.
So no decorations necessary.
Thing, one thing two, it exposed that information that you're talking
about via plug-in API, so you could write your own hookups to it, that
did compilation passes modified stuff.
It basically had like an open architecture for hooking into it and
attaching to it and I don't mean like the kind like llvm where you
have to, then go like build the compiler to do it.
I mean like you could just build like a dll that would like interface
with them and it would work, right?
So it has been done before.
Unfortunately, for a lot of other reasons, it was never something that
was really available in a way that anyone could use.
It was trapped inside.
This, you know, big corporate weird product that you know, wasn't
really going to be relevant to anyone.
But it had it was tried and did work and unfortunately, that wasn't
the lineage for a number of other reasons that were left with today.
So we don't get to having those benefits.
Unfortunately.
Are you still using the software renderer?
Yes.
We render and suffer.
At what point is the perfect become a good programmer.
What do you think you became a good programmer?
I think I became a good programmer sometime around when I was 16.
I have been preparing since I was 7.
I think I got better at programming recently.
Good at 16, I then become became really bad at programming when I was
Teen.
That's because I was introduced to C++ and arbitrary to programming
and I thought, you know, I believe people, and they said it was good.
And then I was a really bad programmer for about four or five years.
And then I, when I went back to and realize that was all awful with,
with the help of some very good friends, Jeff Roberts, John Miles, the
folks at Red game tools, kind of like, not really telling me.
They weren't like, you got to stop this, but just kind of being there
and kind of constantly sort of being a good example.
Sample.
I kind of came around to us like, oh yeah, this stuff.
Is already pretty dumb?
Huh.
And then I think I've been a decent programmer.
Since then, again, it took me a while to come back.
I think I've been a previous Emperor since then.
How do you handle programmer burnout?
Depression, those days when you're just not in the mood to do
anything, not productive or do motivated?
You can barely do any coding you rather do anything else other than
what you should be doing.
I would say that I wouldn't worry about too much.
Everyone has that, that problem the thing to do is always right an
hour or two of code, a day during that time.
Anyway, I don't care what it is, whatever it is that you're working on
and that you're stuck on that you don't know how to do when you don't
want to do type something in.
I don't care how
How lousy it is.
I don't care how far it is from an actual usable solution to the
problem that you have.
I don't care how much you know, you're going to rewrite it later.
The number one, cure for programmer, burnout and depression is to
write code because invariably once you get a little further over the
hump pitcher on, you realize that it's all code you can do and you
start to focus on actually doing it and then you're out of the funk.
And so much like doing anything else, like writing a book, or anything
else.
It's when you get in a psychological state, where you've decided that
you're stuck or that you can't do it, or whatever.
That is, what's stopping you from going forwards.
Not the actual failure of knowledge because the truth is you just got
something you don't know how to do yet and that's fine.
The way you get over.
That is by experimentation typing stuff in running.
The compiler makes small goals for self whatever.
Are you need to do?
Do that, just keep the code going, and you will get out of it.
If you allow yourself to lock up entirely, then you won't, and you'll
go for days without having done anything, and that's really bad.
In the 30, do you really prefer to save to unconditional jumps to the
CPU pipeline?
Won't be flushed at any chance instead of compiler and platform
Independence, referring to get thread ID part.
So first of all,
there would be no platform Independence because the way you would do
that,
Those in the way you do it on links are probably different, right?
So you need to make a different function, call, presumably on Linux,
then you would on Windows, or say on Mac, so there's no platform
Independence.
It's only compiling dependence.
There's only one compiler for this platform and unsurprisingly.
There's only one compiler for the other platforms.
We are only ever going to pile up with msec on Windows probably and if
we switch to another compiler, we just switch that composite we
wouldn't still compiled with msv.
See we're only going to compile with llvm on Linux and we're only
going to compile with the llvm xcode branch on
Mac.
So why add two jumps to every counter when you get nothing for it,
right?
Seems like a really bad decision.
Let's see.
Why are you making an engine instead of a game?
Well, I'm making both right, I don't really think of those two things
as being all that separate, but in order to because I decided I want
to start from scratch so that everyone could see how to make
everything.
I have to implement all of the pieces of an engine first, but we've
done most of that.
So we don't have a whole lot left to do and then we can do game stuff
as well.
But as for why I would make that decision, there's a huge number of
reasons.
Number one is, I am an engine programmer.
That's what I do.
I am not here to show you how to make a game, you know, making a game
is a separate discipline.
I am here to show how you do engine programming.
And so it doesn't really make any sense for me to not make an engine.
Because the whole point of the stream is to show you how you make an
engine.
And we, we are making a game as well.
And so, to that extent, I will be showing how to make a game.
But that is because the engine in the game are very, you know, closely
related.
And obviously I if I just showed you how to make an engine, there's a
whole bunch of stuff that's
Difficult to teach and show because it's like, well, why are we doing
this without a game there to motivate why we wrote the code?
You know, if we don't need the bullet to collide with the Statue and
have the statue fracture, we don't know why we are writing this code
injection code and we don't know why we are writing the statue
crumbling stuff, right?
And so to that extent, you know,
the reason that it is a game and an engine together is because I feel
like that is the way to learn.
It shows you why everything gets written.
So that you don't have to wonder why I'm putting in, you know, this or
that feature or why?
I'm implementing something the way I'm implementing it.
I can always point out.
Oh, I'm writing this piece of code because we're trying to make it so
that the world can be extremely large.
So I need to store it's parsley or something, right?
If I don't have that in mind then, you know, if there's no game then
you wouldn't know.
Maybe you don't need that, maybe it, you know, if it's a game, that's
just takes place on one screen.
Why am I doing that feature?
Right, so, so I tried to pick a game as well, in a game design that
has all of the things I want to teach, so that it can constantly
motivate, you know, the code in that way.
Hopefully, that makes some sense to you.
Let's see.
Do you think of owning a red X matter is worth it, useful for
metaprogramming?
No II, don't do it.
I don't, I don't really like Rex's.
I never have, I don't, I don't, I don't care for them.
I think they're too simplistic.
I'll be want to seem to be pretty and happy to call you my server.
Do you think programmers were better in the past?
Is this all for you?
Produce always Flawless and Bug lists, as asking, seriously, just
trying to return your point more clearly.
No, I don't think anyone really ever produces software that's false
and Douglas.
I mean maybe once in a while you get really lucky and you hit some
sweet spot but yes programmers were much better in the past
significantly better than they are today.
The reason for that was because it was very hard just to do
Basic programming.
And so really the only people who were programming in the past for
people who could pass a certain level of quality in terms of what they
knew, how to do, and how good they were, in my opinion.
So, there was a natural selection process.
Nowadays, anyone can program, like, it's trivial.
You can just like, you know, load up some PHP script and start quote,
unquote programming.
So I don't think there are less great programmers today than there
were in the past.
There's just a lot more bad programmers.
So, you know, however many good
Programmers.
There are probably hasn't changed that much.
But the number of bad programmers, have skyrocketed.
As a result most software doesn't work at all.
Oftentimes on the stream, you even see that happen yesterday?
We had a particular, a singer.
I just wanted to play a movie the first movie player.
I tried crashed the second movie.
I play our went through all these different things.
It started asking me if I wanted to, like, install a storefront.
And then it couldn't play the video because it had the codec and
couldn't find it.
It was like, you know, and you just like, yep, that's that's - offer,
you know?
And so as far as saying, you know, is everything produced Flawless and
buglets.
No, absolutely not.
But what I will say
Is I try to have a certain quality bar that I get my software to and I
don't just, you know, sort of put out whatever the random thing is
that happens to work in some giant stack of garbage, that's super
slow, and buggy and all this other stuff.
I don't try to, I try not to shift that, right?
Where's a lot of people just shift that and they're fine with that and
they don't see a problem with it, you know, like, Facebook apparently
doesn't see a problem with shipping their Facebook app and that's
insane to me.
Like, I don't understand how you do that.
I don't understand how you can't look at the Facebook app on the
iPhone and go like, oh my God.
We need to completely change our engineering practices.
This is an epic disaster.
That's not what they say.
And they write blog post about like how good they did or stuff and
you're just like that that's like more my problem with things.
It's like if you put out the Facebook app and you were like wow we're
really awful.
We're sorry.
This is the best we could do.
We don't really know what we're doing.
We're all taking a voluntary.
Pay cut and we apologize.
That's different than we're great.
And here's our app that's absolutely ridiculously bad and huge and a
nightmare and like it's slow to use and everything else, right?
Right.
So yeah.
So I think there's definitely a thing there.
And what I will say as well is like, you know, I've definitely learned
my lesson to overtime, you know, I feel like if anything my Quality
Bar is actually lower than it should be like I don't I don't feel like
I'm that high actually, right?
And that's the other thing that troubles me,
I think of myself ranked against meticulousness on programmers.
I'm low compared to programmers that that I respect, right?
I am not like the guy who demands the most Flawless bug was code.
I'm far from that guy, right?
And so that's like another kind of troubling thing about it in my mind
is that I shouldn't be the one telling you your software is bad,
right?
I shouldn't I if, if you've crossed below my
Bar, you're really low, you're way below acceptable, because I'm not
that high on the like on that, on that side of things.
I'm okay.
Letting things slide like, you know, Jeff Roberts is performance bar
compared to mine.
It's night and day things that I think are totally, fine, performance
wise and I'm okay with them.
He thinks are not even close to where they need to be
performance-wise, right?
So so if you're below my bar,
I don't even know what to say to you, right.
I don't know how you get down there in the old days.
Yeah.
I guess I'd say it's, you know, when I got into programming when I
sort of got out of like high school and then started, you know,
programming professionally.
I was the bottom of the barrel on that those opinions, right?
And that hasn't changed.
All the guys that I was pregnant with that those times.
You know, they have higher performance standards than I do.
They know more about optimization than I do.
And that really hasn't changed.
What's changed is the industry has just is necrotic.
I mean, the number of people who accept absolutely awful levels of
reliability and performance is just staggeringly bad.
And, you know, if I could just sit, you know, if I could leave with
one, if I could sum that, in one thought it really is.
If you are below my quality and performance bar, you are in trouble
because I am not the high Watermark opinion.
Why?
Eyes by a drastic drastic.
Delta.
bye, you know, drastic
Let's see.
All right, I think most of the rest of the stuff.
I can't really address in a short amount of time.
So I'm going to wrap it up.
I'm going to go ahead and wrap it up.
Let's close it.
Close it down.
Pretty happy with where we ended up today, actually, because I think
that puts us in good shape tomorrow for having a pretty nice system
set up and kind of like
So anyway, thank you very much for joining me for another episode of
handmade hero.
It was a pleasure coding with you.
As always, if you would like to follow along at home,
you can always pre-order the game and it comes to the source code,
even just right now, if you would like to play around with it, you can
go ahead and do so and experiment, have some fun.
You could do that.
Just by clicking on the little pre order button.
We also have a patreon page if you want to support the video series,
that's the place to do it.
It's always very much appreciated.
We also have a forum site, the forum's is place to ask questions.
You can look at an antidepressant guide.
There's all kinds of good stuff there.
So if you're interested in following along the series that's good
place to check out.
We also have a tweet bot the tweetbot Tweet the schedule use.
If you're trying to catch the schedule live at any given time, you can
go there and see what's going to be for the weak, or that day, and
that sort of stuff.
After that schedule, I will be back.
Back here at 5:00 p.m.
Pacific Daylight time tomorrow.
So if you want to see us, go ahead and start collecting that deep,
that new debug info that we got, in a way that we can then use,
that'll kind of span across platform where let us really start to take
a look at things and see how our code Works, which I'm pretty excited
about.
Honestly, right back here 5 p.m.
tomorrow that's the place to be.
Hope to see you all there.
Until then, please have fun coding and I'll see you guys on the
internet.
Take these everyone