And jump right in to another episode of handmade hero.
Alright.
Hello everyone and welcome to what I believe if I'm not very much an
error.
It is day 12 of handmade here.
It's almost like the 12 Days of Christmas only.
It is not Christmas and I'm not sure how that works out.
Exactly.
But I think we all know that the 12 days of Christmas are a little
weird.
If you listen to the song, It's a bit bizarre.
And so I feel like we could easily say that handmade hero was on.
One of those days, maybe you get five handmade Heroes for the fifth
day.
I don't really know.
Either way.
Thank you so much for joining me here on day 12.
If you are someone who has pre-ordered the game and would like to
follow along with the source code.
You should have gotten a link in your email where you can download it.
And when you download it, you want to unpack day 11 for this episode,
because you always unpack the previous day's to start on the new day.
So unpack 11.
That is what we are going to be working with today.
Now, yesterday, I went over all of the basics of platform API design
and
Basically, what I mean by platform API design, there really isn't a
term for this explicitly.
I don't think.
But basically, what I'm talking about is the ability to abstract your
code away, sort of like, pull your code out of being tied to an
operating system.
And so you can write all of your code.
So that it's basically used across all the platforms that your game
ships on and then you just have a small piece of code.
That's basically, like a shim, a little platform layers, what I tend
to call them that basically allows
Game to run on whatever that platform is.
Now what how complicated that is and how efficient that is all boils
down to how good of a job.
You do defining the boundary between the platform-specific code in the
platform layer and the platform nonspecific code that comprises the
rest of your game.
And I talked about the philosophy of that yesterday, please be sure to
watch that video if you have not already because it really does lay
the foundation for everything that we're going to do for the rest of
the week here.
It's basically good.
The driving force between the decision behind the decisions as we make
them.
And so really what I'm going to do today is I'm going to sort of
continue to push a little further down the direction that I started at
the end of the last dream, when I talked about the platform philosophy
that I take in terms of separating things out.
Now, if you'll remember, basically, what I said is we want to divide
things up, into two sort of directions.
There are services that the platform layer asked the game for and that
stuff like what do you?
Want to render.
What do you want to play out?
The sound card?
Right?
What do you want to do for files?
Like, saving files, that sort of thing.
So file IO sorts of stuff.
And then there's stuff that goes the other direction, which is also
files because it depends on which who's asking for who and who depends
on who's doing what basically, you know, if the if the platform layer
is asking the game to save it state or something that could go One
Direction.
Whereas if the game is asking to load a
That might go the other direction.
So that's sort of a bi-directional thing, but also their stuff like,
you know, maybe the, the, the game needs to take some profiling
information.
It needs to look at the system clock or something like that, and
that's going to be different on different platforms.
So there's all sorts of things like that.
So, basically, we break it down into two types, their services, that
the platform layer provides for the game and services, that the game
provides the platform layer.
And what we did is we started last night after kind of going through
all the philosophy of it and the reasons behind the different
decisions, and we
Leslie said the first thing that we're going to do is just abstract
are simple gradient.
And so we left off.
Let me go ahead and open the debugger.
Here.
We left off at feature, parity, basically, where we were originally
feature, parity, but we'd pulled out one piece of code.
So we're back to where we used to be.
If I grab the little trusty Gamepad here.
I can still do this sort of stuff with it.
It's back to where it needs to be.
I can go ahead and do whatever I want to do with it.
It's all good, but
We have only abstracted one very small piece of code, which is that
gradient.
The render weird gradient thing is the only piece of code that we
abstracted and that's a problem.
Basically, because we've got a lot of other code that could be
platform.
Nonspecific that isn't the example, first of all, the storage of the
X, and Y, offsets that happen.
When you're moving the gradient around, there is the interpretation of
the control events, like what the, what the things on the controller.
What what, various operations with the controller.
And as far as the response of the gradient, there's the sine wave that
were outputting that supposed to basically just, you know, this is the
test sine wave that generation of sine wave is not platform-specific.
So we just have a lot of things that are still in our win32 layer.
And what we want to do is move all of that stuff out here so that we
can see how all of that stuff is going to flow back and forth because
we made everything in the win32 platform layer.
We made input, we made sound and we want to kind of move all that
stuff out here.
So we're going to start.
Art by getting sound out because you can see, we did it already with
the game on stream buffer.
We're going to also now, try to get sound out of there.
So sound is a little bit trickier.
And the reason sound is a little bit trickier is because sound is
actually temporal.
Now.
This is a little confusing to understand and it actually boils down to
a technicality that we may or may not choose to to explore on the
video side of things, but I'll explain it in detail after after a
little almond milk.
Basically, if you imagine what we are outputting we are outputting
sound and video.
At took basically comprised the audio visual feedback that the user is
going to get when playing the game.
And basically, that is what makes a video game.
The audio visuals are, what make a video game because really, if you
didn't have those, you would be bored gate.
That's kind of the difference between the two things.
So it's that it's that audio visual feedback that really kind of
defines to a large extent, the fact that we are video games.
It's
Important.
And it's one of the most important parts obviously to think.
Audio is mandatorily temporal, right?
Audio happens over time.
So when you are listening to the audio output of a game, it is not
optional how long it will be playing for.
It has to play continuously if I'm playing a piece of music and I
output say
A sixteenth of a seconds worth of music.
But I let that play for an eighth of a second, which is twice as long.
The user is going to hear garbage or silence.
Whatever was in the buffer at for the other eighth of a second right
for the for the other sixteenth of a second.
The first 16th.
It'll play the music but the other 16th, nothing will happen.
Contrast this with video if I play video on the screen, if I put up an
image I can hold that image on the screen for as long as I want in
some sense and really, what will be
See if I hold it too long.
Is that the frame rate starts to slow down but you really won't get
that same kind of glitching.
It's not like it, it disappears or something like this, right?
It's still just it's just lowering.
The sample rate is in some sense that I'm outputting to the person,
but they're their mind, does a good job of assembling those images.
So if I was displaying at 60 frames a second and then I miss one frame
and I end up displaying at 30 frames a second from then on because of
some system event or something.
So, I get slower.
It looks a little
Little less smooth, but it did not really appear to be a serious
glitch, right?
And so what I'm trying to impress upon you here is basically that the
video that gets output is a static snapshot in time.
That is held for some amount of time and you're bringing reassembles
those and considers them animation sound, doesn't really have that
option.
You basically have to Output a very large number of samples per
second.
I mean, if you look at it at the sample boundary, it kind of looks
that way maybe but really it's so temporal that you
The basically be outputting 48,000 things a second, and if you don't
keep out, putting all those samples to tell the sound card, what the
sound sounds like your brain immediately.
Here's the error.
It sounds harsh and unfortunate.
It doesn't just seem like you're slowing down the sound or anything
like that.
That's not what happens or that the sample rate of the sound dropped,
what actually sounds like is just a flat-out bug.
So, so what that basically means is that when we prepare a frame.
We don't really need to know how long that frame will be on the
screen.
It's a little weird to think about, but we really don't because we can
put that frame on the screen and let's say, our Target frame rate was
60 frames a second.
We can put that frame on the screen and if we miss 60, we just update
to the next frame when we're actually generating.
The next frame, we say something like.
Okay.
Let's make that frame.
Will advance the state of the world, a 30th of a second, and just flip
it later.
We'll just move it later on, right?
We could recover in theory.
Not necessary saying you
Really do all of this in game code.
I'm just pointing out to you the difference in the
Put.
So with that with rendering, you're basically just saying at a
particular instant.
In time.
I need the image for this instant in time.
Just please give it to me.
With sound, that's not true.
I have to say, I want the sound that starts at this particular point
in time and I need this much of it, right?
I need you to give me this much sound.
Hopefully, that makes some sense and if you misjudge and you get to
little sound and that play cursor, and direct sound catches up to you,
you will get a glitch.
That's just how that's going to work.
Now.
The reason I say that it's actually not quite true with video.
What I'm saying is because, technically, you could imagine if your
render was sophisticated enough to do, say, motion blur, you were
doing really accurate motion blur.
So that instead of a single, snapshot in time.
You were actually rendering sort of the
Motion of everything in the world over the time, step, right.
Over the entire time that you anticipate the frame to be on the
screen.
Well, now you've essentially got the same problem that you have with
sound now.
The renderer needs to know exactly how long you plan to have that
thing on the screen because it's actually going to do a blur between
the start and ending position of all the entities.
And if you were to hold it on screen for longer than you should, then
things will teleport from their end to their new position.
Actually, when you actually go to do the next frame, that's at the
wrong time.
Essentially.
I know that sounds fairly complicated will to kind of drill down to it
a little bit more.
But basically, my point here is that there's a lot of subtlety
involved in how you update.
This most games, do this.
Very poorly.
Most games Loop actually is very ignorant of what advancing time
actually means and what they're actually trying to achieve with it.
What they normally do is just measure how much time elapsed and they
like ask the you know, world to advance.
That much time, they don't think of it in terms of like what the
future is going to hold.
And that sort of stuff.
There are definitely our games that do that, but they tend to be
higher end.
So a lot of games just don't really aren't aware of all these sort of
temporal issues that are involved.
So anyway, what I'm going to do is I'm going to start out with a very
correct, but very simplistic model of this kind of a request for audio
and we can use it for video to if we want to.
And there are some reasons.
Is why we may not be able to get away with this?
Exactly, in the end due to the whole audio frame rate glitch, sort of
things where we if we're talking about trying to make sure that we can
be as robust as possible in the face of system, things that may like,
interrupt our frame rate or slow us down those sorts of things.
But my start out with something that is relatively correct in a sense
so that we can basically start there and loosen up to things that are
less correct, as we need to if necessary.
Ali that makes some sense.
So what I'm going to do is I'm going to look in here into the game
update and render and I'm basically going to think about the thing
that I
You said, and I'm going to State what I kind of want to have from the
platform layer.
And this is a very typical API design approach that I use.
And I say this, very stringently actually in lectures.
And so on, always write the usage code first.
If you can, when designing something like an API, I'm trying to design
Define here.
What the platform layer gives me, but it's a mistake to try and Define
that upfront.
What I'd much rather do is just write some code that uses the
Things that I think that I'm going to need look at it and go.
Okay.
The usage code is right now.
Now, let's go Define the API to basically do exactly that or, as close
to that, as we can.
So that's what I'm going to do here.
I'm basically going to say that well, I know that I need to do some
stuff.
I know that I need to, you know, update the sound right?
I need to Output the sound.
Let's let's call it output sound or output game sound, or something
like this, right?
I
That I need to Output the sound and what I'm going to need for.
That is like, well, whatever my game state is, and I don't have that
yet because we haven't actually made a game.
But then I'm going to need basically, how many samples worth of sound.
You want me to Output, right?
I need to know, essentially some kind of integer which is going to
tell me, you know, how many samples.
So the sample count to Output, right?
I need to know that then I'm going to need a sound buffer to put them
into and I'm probably going to
Just lock that format.
I'm going to probably just Define the format to be 16-bit interleave
stereo.
Like we were using in our regular buffer.
I don't see any need to make it be sort of like more flexible than
that the time.
So it's going to say that.
So it's going to need to know how many samples have put.
It's going to need to know where to put those samples.
And if we were really going to be, you know, sort of, if we were
really going to be flexible about this.
We would probably put in a way of saying, we're in the, we're in time,
we want those
Supposed to be so that we can if we want to we can skip.
If we if we get into a situation where we're kind of in trouble, we
can sort of skip forward.
And so what we'd like to do here is basically Define something that
allows us to sort of say.
All right.
I don't want you to really assume that every time I call you.
I'm just asking for the next set of samples.
That would be right abutted to the previous set.
You set, you sent me.
I might want you to, like, overwrite old.
Sample, so we'll Advance last or I might want you to kind of like,
give me samples that are further out.
That's a harder thing for the game to respond to.
But if we were really trying to be flexible, that's what we would do.
I'm going to not do that yet.
I'm going to put it to do here because it's harder for you to
understand, given the stuff that we've said so far is already a lot of
stuff in there that we kind of have to cover.
It's hard to understand at the moment and it is harder to implement.
So we'll start with the simple case, where we're always asking the
game to just give us continuous sample.
We say we want X number of samples.
We're just going to plop those down.
And then the next time we ask for X number of samples, we plop them
down right at the end.
They just kind of chain onto each other and we'll just assume that
that's the way it goes later.
We'll kind of look at a more advanced way of doing it, that can be,
because I could do better error recovery.
So, allow sample offsets here for more, robust platform options.
So, so we're going to call the game the games.
Sound output thing here, we're gonna pass it.
A sound buffer, and the number of samples that it should output.
There.
It will do that.
And for now, we're basically going to make that just be our sine wave.
Right.
And our sine wave.
Again, was basically a something we pulled out here.
It was this win32 fill sound buffer, and it was pretty
straightforward.
It basically looked like that, right?
That's what it looked like.
So this is roughly, what we're going to have for that code and I'll
tune that up in a second here.
So that's one thing we have.
Got to kind of keep it, keep that out of the way of the of my of my
talking head control L actually will do that for me.
So that's what I'm going to do for the game for outputting sound.
And then the other thing that I want to be able to do here is I want
to be able to do the render in the exact same way.
But basically what has to happen, there is we're going to have to
start outputting.
We're gonna have to start keeping State, and we're going to have to
start using a timer to really do anything more complicated here,
right?
Because you can see, we're pretty much platform-independent with the
rendering but
We're passing in this blue offset green offset.
So that's something that we're going to have to do once we actually
get it.
So we'll talk about that in one second.
Let's just focus on the sound thing here.
So if I want my game sound output thing to basically, you know, I
don't like the order of those parameters.
I tend to like things to look a little bit more like they have the
object first for some reason, like they have the, this truck that
holds the things if that makes sense.
So, this is going to be a game sound output buffer, and I'm not
thinking too hard about these names.
Well, I'm having
Typing troubles today.
There we go.
Sound buffer.
And then I'm going to say sample count output here.
Then we're going to go ahead and actually output those now.
The sound buffer is basically just going to be something that gives us
a pointer to the sound for now.
There's not going to be anything more fascinating about it than that.
And so really, what we should be able to do is essentially just use
this code, exactly, as it is, so we should be able to use this code
right here.
We should be able to say which sample index we are on.
We should be able to go up to the sample count entirely.
Lee and then we should be able to.
Let's see here.
Is there anything else we want to do?
Here?
We can produce our sine wave exactly as we are.
So we're going to need some where we are going to need to have our T
sine.
So for now, we'll just use, our will pass that in and save that.
All right, there we go.
And oh, you know what, the other thing we could do for it too.
And maybe this is easier for now.
Let's let's make this a local.
St.
Sign because we're going to move it out pretty much right away.
So there's our T sine so that way we can just use it directly in here.
When we have put the tea sign, we will go ahead and put our tone
volume in here as well.
Because these are all things that we are going to abstract out of the
platform layer very shortly.
So, we got our tone volume in here.
That doesn't actually have to be persisted because that can just be
essentially constant.
There it is.
So that's good.
We've got our tone volume and then we store our sample out.
So our sample out,
Out.
In this case is an in 16 and that's just going to be coming from the
sound buffer.
Basically, the sound buffer is going to store is going to sort of give
us the pointer to where we're going to Output it.
We're assuming the platform layer told us where we should dump our
samples if that makes sense.
So we do that, then we increment and I think running sample, index is
now Irrelevant for us in this code.
Yes.
So basically all I did here was the basic minimal transformation
essentially, nothing.
All I did was
I'm gonna get a pointer to a sound buffer, right?
I am going to take a number of samples to Output, right?
And then I am going to just dump the samples into whatever is in the
sound buffer.
That's it.
So it's much less complicated than the old version because we're sort
of simplifying things for the game and I'll talk about why I decided
to do it that way.
So let's see here.
We've got samples for 2nd overtone hurts.
So this is just, we're not even going to
Let's see.
So this is a good situation here actually and this kind of, this
actually underscores exactly what I was talking about.
So you'll notice here.
I got to a point.
I hadn't really been thinking about it much, but we want to know the
samples or per second here in order to calculate this, this tone hurts
thing.
So, the tone Hearts, we know what we wanted.
We know we wanted the tone hurts to be 256, but we don't know the
samples per second here in the platform-specific code.
A platform nonspecific code.
So that tells me right away because I want to know the wave period.
Right?
What is the wave period?
Let's see here.
Wave period yet Saint in still, so I want to know that value so that
tells me that basically just a huge clue that we want to store that
value in the sound buffer because people who are going to be using the
sound buffer from the platform are going to want to know how many
samples per second or playing.
So if they have things that are tone based they know how many output
so that was literally I mean, that's exactly what I'm talking about.
When I say things like, right?
The usage code.
First that just tells me what should be in that.
I just know.
Now I
Didn't have to guess.
I didn't have to presuppose.
I didn't have to think hard about it.
It just popped right on out.
Okay, hopefully that makes some sense.
I'm going to go ahead and start compiling here so we can start
knocking down our errors.
So I have this game sound output buffer.
I've got to Define it.
Obviously, I've got to come in here and actually make one of these.
And so, really, all this is is the sample out, right?
This is basically the, the
Sample buffer.
I don't know, we want to call this, they will just call it samples.
That seems like a totally reasonable thing to call it.
Because that is what it is.
It's the samples.
And then we know that we have essentially a well, you know, what we
could do to I like this.
I think I like this as well.
Yeah, I like this as well.
I think I might just roll this in here.
Right?
I might just say that there's a sample counting here and the sample
count says, how many output then there's the samples per second,
right?
And that tells you about the buffer itself.
And that to me actually looks even better because then you're just
passing.
One thing, you're saying here's a buffer.
Please, fill it?
You don't have to correspond that in its baked right in there, right?
Like that.
So that's pretty handy.
And it eliminates one whole thing.
That might happen down here.
Let's
Had to do that and that looks pretty good.
Yeah, I think that's pretty good.
Okay.
So basically all we have to really do is pass that and that's it.
And then we're going to have to talk about this T sign here and that's
good.
Because that's exactly what I did want to talk about immediately
thereafter.
Okay.
So we're going to have to pass this.
We pass our gret, our Graphics buffer here, but let's pass our sound
buffer as well.
So let's get that in there.
So now it's going into the game.
So we'll pass that and that way, it can pass and buffer on.
To the sound filling call.
Alright, so let's take a look.
Here.
I got missing semicolon.
That's always good, sign.
If so, which right, we're still in test code land.
So I want to actually I think I've said this before.
I want to actually Implement sign ourselves.
I've already got a to do in there.
So that should be fine for the test code, but I would like to go in
there and just we'd like to look and make sure that we're doing a good
Cindy, sign evaluation or something in there.
I don't want to, I don't want sign to be sneaking around, doing all
kinds of things behind my back.
You never know what it might be doing.
Behind your back, the compiler might do anything if you're not
careful.
Okay, so we've got a sound buffer now.
Okay, so our sound output, buffer has to get filled.
And now, you'll notice that what I've done is, I've implicitly made a
decision here, and this may not necessarily turn out to be a good one
or not.
But it's the decision that I wanted to make at the outset, which is
basically that sound is just not very big.
Okay, that's something that you have to understand.
Basically, if you take a look, let's say you are drawing.
Like I said, at 60 frames a second, 60 frames a
Well, we know we've got 40.
Oops.
Well, if your type right, we know we've got 48,000 samples per second
that we're playing.
We know that we divide that by 60 frames.
That means each framed.
We are outputting 800 samples.
Okay, we know that each one of them is 2, bytes long, that's 1600.
We know that there are two of them for stereo.
That is 3200 B, that we are writing.
3200.
B is like the most insignificant thing modern.
Processor has ever seen.
We are talking about processors that can move GB of data a second.
So 3200.
B is literally irrelevant.
So what I have elected to do here is suffer an extra buffer copy for
those through got 3,200 bytes per frame, that will be going out.
The wire.
Basically, I'm going to do an extra buffer copy there because I would
rather prevent present the game with a cleaner interface of just
writing into a single buffer rather than forcing it to inherit the
direct sound duel, right problem with the ring buffer.
Because
A complicated thing.
It's easier to get wrong.
And I don't want to pass it on to the game especially because there
are other platforms that don't have that janky ring, buffer nonsense
going on.
And in those cases it this will be just as fast because it can write
directly into the location.
It's supposed to go.
And so basically really I'm just saying, I don't think this is going
to be a performance problem.
So I don't want to pass this on to the application.
I just don't think it's going to matter and that's always a judgment
call.
There are plenty of times where you have an opportunity to do.
Nothing more efficiently, but you incur a bit of complexity and it
really is a judgment call which one of those you take.
And which one of those you don't in most cases.
I tend to prefer to do the cleaner thing, if I can, if I know that
it's not going to be too expensive and then later if it turns out to
be a performance problem when we are actually measuring it, then I
will go and introduce the added complexity at that time.
That usually is a smarter way to go especially because it means that
you already have the simpler case working correctly.
And so when you
Implement the more complex case you're just a bugging.
It versus the simple case.
Instead of writing, it completely fresh the first time.
So it tends to actually be a good way to develop.
Even if you weren't doing the methodology that I was talking about,
which is see, make sure it's actually performance bottleneck before
you incur the cost.
Okay.
So we've got our sound buffer here.
And what that basically means is that if we take a look at to me, if
we take a look at what's going to happen down here.
We basically need to first, get some memory that we're going to store
the this sound in.
Now, we don't even actually have to allocate any memory because we're
only actually going to be doing whatever our frame rate is and our
frame rate at the moment.
I think I'm leaning towards may be doubling that number instead of
eight hundred samples.
I'm going to, I'm not say that maybe we'll try to run at
Like, you know, something more like more like 30 frames a second
because since we're going to be doing software rendering, I think,
trying to hit 60 frames a second is not going to be realistic in a lot
of cases.
So, 30 frames a second, might be more we target.
So basically what I'm going to do is going to ask the game for a
buffer that is going to be 1/30 of a second worth of audio each time.
I ask it.
So basically, I'm going to go in here and say that the sound buffer,
right?
And I'm going to look, take a look groups.
That's not good.
I got to take a look at the actual stuff.
I got to put in here.
So the samples per second that we've already got.
That's fine.
The
For a sample count, that's going to be the samples per second divided
by 34.
Now again, this is all just sort of layering the code in.
This is not supposed to be final shipping code or anything like that.
I'm just showing you how we do these transformations in steps.
So I'm going to go up here and say, okay, we have the samples per
second, as well.
It was right here in our sound output routine.
So I'm going to go ahead and put that in here.
There we go.
And then the samples.
I'm just going to put these right on the stack.
I don't really need to allocate any.
Memory for them.
There's no sense in doing that.
So, basically, I know that I just want this many of those, which is,
which is pretty trivial for me to do.
I can basically say that I, you know, I just got in 16, sample, count
and soups samples.
And I will, actually just say that I have some of them and will
basically say, I don't know for now, we'll just say that we've got
this many of those samples.
So basically that is really all I wanted to do.
It's pretty straightforward.
Word.
And then this is going to get cleaned up in a second here to use
something.
That's a little more flexible because the problem with doing it right
on the stack, is that unless we use a function I have not talked about
yet.
You can't actually make anything that's on the stack, be parameterised
on something.
That isn't a constant.
Now I could, of course, actually introduce a constant for it, but I
don't see any reason to because I want to talk about how you do that
also separately.
All right.
So if we do that, when we call game update and render, I can pass the
sound buffer.
Now, into this.
Which I will do.
There we go.
And in theory, this will still run even though we've kind of just
doing some janky stuff.
Maybe not not, maybe not ladies and gentlemen, as I say that I'm
totally lying.
I did do the right number here, is that I not.
This is, this is literally just for janky as code.
I mean, yeah, I say it often times, but do not, you know, this is
never something that should be left in the shipping program.
I'm literally just trying to show you how to, how to push the platform
layer, kind of up there.
Just want to make sure I didn't type something.
There we go.
Okay, put the samples in there.
That's good.
I called the thing with the sound buffer.
I don't remember what we wrote so far in here.
Game output, sound got the sound buffer samples per second, the tone
her.
As we look at the samples there, the sample out, it's going to the
sample count.
Oh, this is right.
This is right value in their sample index goes through its at putting
two of them.
Yes.
Fantastic.
This is just dumb.
We are stereo, of course, so we need that.
There we go.
Okay.
Good to go.
So, one thing that's kind of nice about that and I'll talk about that
in a second.
As you notice when I forgot to multiply that, you'll notice that the
debug Library caught it for me.
So basically, what happened here, is they put some checking code to
see if you over rote memory somewhere, right?
And that's pretty helpful.
It's it doesn't happen that frequently, especially if you're not
trying to stream at the same time as your programming and you're
paying attention, but it
What happened?
And so one of the things that's nice is, if you do have things that
catch buffer overruns, it's something that helps take like a lot of
people are afraid of pointers and afraid of languages that have them
specifically because you can do stuff like this and you are afraid of
shipping.
Things that have this, these sorts of bugs in them and that's
legitimate.
But there's a lot of ways you can actually minimize those things and
we haven't gotten to any of that yet.
But this is already one that's even just built into msv.
See, basically, I didn't have to write that, right.
It just, it just caught that.
For me, I didn't do that work.
It just caught that buffer overrun for me.
And so then when I fix it, it doesn't happen anymore, right?
And that's pretty cool.
We're going to be looking at ways of doing things that are a little
more advanced than that to catch things that are possibly a little
harder to catch.
But for now, it's just worth mentioning, that that's kind of a nice
thing for people who are going to be a little more scared of pointers.
I'm never scared of them.
I just like, throw them around and then I'm like, okay, when it's time
to start tightening things down.
I bounced check my things and I just go through a set of things that
kind of, rigorously tightens things up.
So I don't really worry.
Out them.
It really doesn't end up being a problem.
But for people who are scared about things like that.
It's worth noting that there are a lot of tools that help you.
And that was one of them.
That just that just helped us.
Okay.
So right now, we're still getting a sine wave from this, from the
actual platform layer, right?
We've, we've given us a sound buffer to the game.
Right?
And the game is, is doing the sound, you know, it's generating sound
for the sound buffer, certainly, but we have a problem and that
problem.
It is that basically we are not using any of the stuff that comes
back.
We are still generating, the sound cook thing.
All the sound code ourselves ourselves in the platform layer with
win32, fill sound buffer.
So what we'd rather do now is we'd rather use that win32, fill sound
buffer code right to actually grab instead of the sine wave.
Grab out of our buffer.
So I can do that.
Pretty simply write.
I can just pass the sound.
Buffer itself over to this thing right into win32, fill sound buffer.
And now, instead of this.
Her actually Computing a sign, right?
It can instead just read from the buffer that we already had free
prepared for it in the platform nonspecific codes.
So I can say game sound output buffer.
It's basically Source samples.
Maybe, let's just call it source that Source buffer.
I don't know.
What have you guys want to call it, call it.
Whatever you like anything.
You like.
It's fine with me.
Okay.
So let's say we have the source buffer.
They're basically what we're going to do is we're just going to pull
from that sort of buffer instead of the sign.
Wave.
So we got an M16?
We've got sample.
We got - we'll call it Source sample, and maybe we'll call this desk
sample.
Right?
We'll just change the denominator here and that's going to be the same
Source buffer samples.
It's going to pull from.
So in here.
All we're really going to do is we're just going to copy, right?
We're just going to copy every every last thing.
So we're just going to do something like Source sample plus plus like
that.
Basically, this is all we're doing.
Just copying from one buffer to another.
We're just flat-out copying.
Nothing else is happening of any interest to anyone for any reason,
right?
Okay, so we're just, that's it.
That's all that's happening.
Star Source, sample plus plus, in fact, you know what?
I don't even need to do this.
I can just copy this one up here.
We don't need the sign stuff at all.
I still have draw this out for people.
I don't know if we drew it out or not.
We didn't draw it out and you want me to see a draw?
It now would be a good time to tell me.
So, we're basically doing
That copy.
We're doing it twice.
We can collapse these two Loops soon to actually, you can see there's
trying to get even more ridiculously simple and related to each other.
So that's really mostly.
All we need to do to change it from out, putting the stuff that comes
from one, from outputting stuff that comes from the other.
Now, what we do have to do is deal with our start up a little bit
differently because we initially filled the the sound buffer, with
stuff at the start to put a sine wave in there.
On a front loaded, but that's not really what we want to do.
Right?
We don't want to do that.
What we want to do instead is just basically clear it at the
beginning, right?
We just want to clear the whole buffer.
So what we really want is something another function here, which is
basically like win32 clear buffer, something like that.
And so what we want to say is like hey, why don't you why don't you
just take the entire buffer flush it with zeros, and then we'll start
writing sound into it at some appropriate point in time, right?
So assuming that we do that win32 clear buffer.
What we basically need here is something that goes ahead and does
that, clear, 32 clear buffer.
Let's take a look here.
So we're going to Global lock this thing like this.
Right?
Here we go.
And this is basically doing the exact same code.
Nothing really doesn't need B to lock or B to write really?
Because we know pretty much
That were locking the entire buffer, right?
Absolutely.
Everything is going to get, is going to get that treatment.
So the B to lock will be the entire size of the entire thing.
So we basically want to basically just pass everything.
Give me everything you have.
From the start, all the way to the end of the buffer.
So that'll lock that.
It'll give it back to us.
And then we just need to clear it basically, and we can use this same
code here.
We can basically say, well, we'll go ahead.
We'll take that.
Will take a look at the sample count.
Well, actually, we don't even need to be in samples anymore.
We can just be in B, so we can literally just take something that
looks like this.
You can say B index equals 0, B index less than that b index plus
plus, and we can basically say
This is going to be a un Tate like that.
We're just going to basically clear everything the entire buffer 20.
Does that make sense?
Hopefully that makes sense.
So we're basically just
Saying, all right.
Clear.
Everything, everything.
You've got every last bite in this buffer should be set to 0.
So there you go.
Now, I don't anticipate.
This actually ever happening because it should just give us back one
contiguous region since the thing isn't playing yet and we're locking
from zero to the secondary buffer size, but just in case something
wonky happens on might as well handle.
It will cease.
Okay, we got the dust samples.
We get sick region 1.
Go through all of region 1 we write zeros into it, same exact thing
here.
We're doing it by B naught by samples this time because we don't care,
this could also be.
If since we're not really trying to cause as little Library functions
possible, there are functions like memset built in the C standard
library, that would set memory to particular value and clear as well.
But we're just doing it manually ourselves.
Okay, so then we go ahead and we unlock the buffer after we're done
with it.
So there you go.
That'll lock.
You know, do the clear unlock right?
Nice and clean.
So hopefully that will clear a buffer.
Yep.
There we go, and now will actually sort of be playing our sine wave,
but there's a bunch of janking ass in here that we now we have to
clean up.
I think it will probably actually play the same way, but it's going to
be, it's going to be buggy if that makes sense.
Gotta finish this as well.
So,
Okay.
Yeah, sorry.
Forgot to forgot that we were in the middle of a second function there
as well.
All right.
So win32 Phil sound, buffer also has obviously has to work.
All right, so we're going through our samples.
We have our source buffer here.
We're doing interleaved, which is correct.
Oh, okay.
So the other thing that we, yeah, this is, this is just the thing that
I was about to say, I guess, I can't run it till I actually clean up
the thing I was about to say.
So I was going to say is so now, however, much we tell the game to
fill, right?
That is essentially going to be determined by that's going to be
determined by our frame rate if we're trying to actually hit the
framerate properly, but the problem is the thing that we were using
for our right cursor is just taking wherever the target cursor is and
looking at how far we would have to write to fill up to that point.
Right?
So what we actually have to do is we actually now have to think about
where in the sound buffer.
We actually need to start putting things and then we need to
just always make sure that we update the right, the right amount of
samples.
So there's two ways that we can actually do this and maybe I should do
the other way of doing it first, instead of saying, let's always
output the number of samples that will correspond with the frame that
we want.
What we could do instead is say, let's just use the way we were doing
it before and asked the game every time essentially to, to Output
enough to fill to the point that we want.
So basically, what we could say, right is we could do this here.
And basically say all right, you know if sound is valid like this doo
doo doo.
Like that.
Valid what we could do is do the computation that we were going to do
before.
So basically, assuming that the sound is valid, then we actually asked
for that many.
The reason that I wasn't doing that quite yet is because I wanted to
do it without having to show you guys how to allocate stuff on the
stack, but I guess we're going to have to because at the end of the
day we can't actually call this thing.
If it's not set up to work properly.
It's just going to crash on us.
We're going to have a huge problem there if I don't do it properly.
So, you know, what can you do?
I was trying for
Something I gotta Backtrack on it.
I gotta backtrack a little bit.
That's what you know, what can you do?
So anyway, if we take a look at these guys here and we basically say,
all right, we've got this stuff.
We're going to compute it.
So we're essentially going to compute all these things.
We're going to compute the B to luck.
We're going to compute the target cursor.
Damn, we're going to compute the B to, right?
And we're going to save them.
Right, oops.
It's not right.
There we go.
We're going to compute the B to write are going to save.
Those things are going to say that sound is valid.
Assuming that we were able to actually do that.
Assuming the sound is valid.
Then what we want to do here essentially is we want to go ahead and
ask the sound layer the game to Output the number of samples.
We actually want because we now know how many there are, right.
There's going to be b, b to right will basically be the thing we want.
And since we're asking for it in samples, we basically need to divide
that by our
Sample size, right?
However, big the bytes per sample is.
So basically what we're doing here is we're saying okay the sample
count that the game is supposed to write is going to be the B to write
/ r, b, / sample, right?
It's basically for dividing by 4, divided by stereo paired 16.
So the problem with that is this thing ain't going to hold that.
Now, I mean, I could be cheesy and do something like this, which would
be absolutely huge.
That's not what I want to do.
So we're not going to do that.
But at the moment we
We can probably do something.
What'd it sound output area.
So, let's see here.
All right, but first, maybe I'll just do it this way, just so we can
do bug this code.
I slammed a lot of code out there right now.
I appreciate that.
So we got to kind of debug it, get it working properly, step through
it.
Make sure everything's kosher.
And then we'll talk about this nonsense right here.
That seems like a reasonable thing to do.
All right, so hopefully, as you can see, we're back to basically
exactly what we wanted.
The only problem is
Is we've, we've kind of dropped our feature parity again, because we
no longer pass the tone hurts in the tone Hertz is not dependent on
the stick, which is what we wanted.
But we are actually generating our sine wave.
As you can see, sign f is no longer called in the platform layer at
all.
So, we know that basically, all of our sound is now coming from game
output sound, which is what we wanted.
However, we still got some really crusty stuff here, and I want to
step through that code.
Maybe what I'll do is I'll push it.
I've one more thing.
I maybe want to get to today.
Or maybe not.
Let's let's, I'm gonna push forward a little bit more.
I realize there's a lot of stuff in there, but in the Q&A, we'll go
over it again, just to let you know.
So let's let's yeah, let's let's take a take a look at maybe one other
thing first.
So, the other thing that I want to do, right?
Is I want to move that tone.
Like I want to move sort of the
You know what?
Now?
It's going to be tomorrow.
I'm sorry.
I'm thinking I'm kind of running ahead in my running forward in my
head and I'm just thinking about, I'm like it's going to be too
complicated for me to talk about all things.
I want to talk about for the next thing that we're going to do.
So instead what we're going to do is I'm basically just going to go
ahead and pass that tone hurts to get our feature, parity back.
And then tomorrow we will look at getting all of those values.
Basically that were passing here, right to game update render.
I'll look at extracting all of those back out again.
So tone hurts.
He's in here because the none of these should actually be being passed
from the platform layer at all.
None of that should be happening.
But I kind of tried do this in waves so that I don't overwhelm people
with too much reorganizing of the code at once.
Basically.
So the tone Hertz is now passed in.
We're good to go with that.
So, in theory, we should be back to feature parity yet.
That's what we wanted.
So that's all good.
So let's go through here now and take a look at all this crazy code, I
added.
It.
And then I guess the most important thing to talk about will be that
stack allocation.
So,
Okay.
I have choices here about where I want to store this sound stuff now
in the future, I don't really want it on the stack.
The stack is not probably where I want to actually put this stuff.
But like I said, while you are moving code around and doing stuff and
we're trying to get all the architecture in place, the way I want it.
I don't want to spend a lot of time, thinking about things like this,
you want to basically.
And and again, this is sort of the sort of thing, a lot of people talk
about garbage.
Collected languages and that sort of stuff and they're like, how can
you possibly deal with languages that don't have these things of, that
sort of stuff?
Well, the answer is actually I just don't worry about those sorts of
things till I'm ready to kind of tighten them down.
And in the interim, there's a lot of techniques you can use to not
really worry about memory to just kind of have it happen.
However, you want.
And you'll notice that we kind of haven't had any problem with that so
far.
We've basically never had to really think about memory at all.
We're just like, you know, most of them were thinking about memory.
We're talking about like writing things into buffers and stuff like
that, that you would have to think about.
Anyway, even if you were
Just filling them as a raise.
You can still do things like buffer, overruns and languages that don't
have pointers by just trying to right outside the bounds of an array
or something.
That's still a bug in your program.
You shouldn't have done it.
And so the fact that maybe the language doesn't crash as a result
isn't much of a is, it doesn't really help you because your programs
will just doesn't work.
So anyway, point being what I want to talk about here is if you just
are trying to get stuff working and you're just kind of screwing
around there, actually is a function.
Depending on the circumstances called a lucky and basically I don't
actually know to be honest with you whether they've standardized on an
actual name for it.
That always works or whether you have to choose whether it has an
underscore or not based on whether it's on a certain platform.
So I usually abstract this away.
It's actually in the platform include files.
I do it but it doesn't matter here because we're actually just calling
the windows version.
So we only care what
There's is and basically what this allows you to do.
You can basically say alakay and you can give it anything you want any
size.
So that's like a size that we want.
We want.
Let's say that many.
It's 16s, right?
That's how much we wanted.
And basically what that will do is that will just allocate on the
stack for you, that that much memory.
And the stack, if you think about, it is kind of a little like having
garbage collection, right?
If you don't care about something, you can throw it on the
stack and you know, that it will go away when the function is done.
So it's kind of automated in that sense.
If you're a C++ programmer and you like things like smart pointers or
things like that.
It's very similar, right?
There are things that are going to go out of scope at the end of a
function and just clean themselves up.
So you don't have to think about it.
I don't actually tend to use code that looks like this in shipping
code, very often because I prefer to do things slightly differently.
Once I have everything the way I want it, I tend to go in and do a
little picking this.
Hello, seediness that results in usually not having allocates happen
in code very often.
But when I'm just developing code, I will often throw and stuff like
that because hey, I just like, okay.
I know that that'll allocate the thing that I wanted, right?
And it'll be fine.
Where was the actual where was this guy to find?
It is in Malik .h ago, not H and I am going to go ahead and put that
down here.
There we go.
Put that standard eye out.
Okay, and then I should be able to compile now hopefully.
Oh, right.
And this returns a void star, of course, so I have to cast it to the
type that I wanted.
All right, so that's basically just a way to do that allocation or
not.
All right.
So I guess this is basically saying that I can't make something that
big on the stack is my guess due to do.
Maybe this is one good reason not to do it.
What to say.
Yes stack Overflow.
Okay.
So basically this is one of those things.
Where we looked at this before, if I want to start playing around with
alakay.
I'm going to have to actually deal with.
I would actually have to deal with having that stack size larger,
which, of course, we can do, if we just want to play with it.
But again, I just wanted to kind of show you that.
So I don't really know if that's worth doing.
Like I said, I almost never use Alec.
I only use it when I'm just playing around with stuff.
So if I'm going to allocate something that big it really wouldn't
matter much.
I don't know.
I don't know, we've got 10 minutes.
Minutes left.
So let me just go ahead and do it.
The real way to stack, Overflow is kind of like a message to us that
says we should actually just do it properly.
All right, so what would I want to do?
And I wanted to do this before.
It's basically we have our allocation up here, right?
We've got our virtual Alec right right here.
This was our virtual Alec the created, the bitmap that we actually
needed for our dip section.
Right?
And so if we wanted to do something trivial down here where we
actually just want memory for our buffer, the the easiest possible
thing to do the thing that
That's just the simplest is just to do this buffer once, right?
And I was trying to avoid actually going into this but I realize I got
plenty of time so I might as well just do it because it's the right
thing to do and it's what I wanted to do eventually.
So basically all I really have to do is I can just do this, right?
And I can actually virtual Alec the thing that I actually wanted
originally from Windows directly.
And basically, what I can do is I can say, why don't you give me
something?
That's the entire secondary buffer size, because I know that I can
never
I never will need to Output more sound than our entire buffer size and
that just gives me a backing store.
Now that I know will always be big enough to fit the thing that I
needed.
Right?
So basically, I'm doing this, you know, we're good to go.
I always have the memory.
I don't have to worry about alakay being to, you know, pick on the
stack.
I don't have to worry about any of that stuff.
This is just a memory that I wanted, right?
So that's pretty straightforward.
It's a very easy thing to do, but one of the things that I like to do
too, is I don't often like to necessarily have all these
Sewell Alex around.
So what we will probably do eventually and you'll see this very
shortly.
Actually is will pull these virtual Alex into a single virtual out
that just gets us are all the memory that we wanted and then we will
subdivide it out.
But for now that is really all we had to do.
Because if you think about it, we got this the memory for our bitmap
up here.
We've got the memory for our sound, buffer down here and basically
what's happening is we know that we never need more than that memory.
So it doesn't actually matter when we get down here.
It never actually.
Only matters how much we're going to ask the game for we could ask it
for a lot for a little.
We know that will always fit in that buffer that we got because that
buffer could have could hold if it needed to basically all the stuff
that was coming from the sound output right that there isn't any way
to play to direct sound more than the buffer size that we originally
had.
And so we can just allocate it this way, right?
It's really really straightforward.
I hope that makes some sense, but basically all we're doing.
I don't know why that always starts off.
That it's kind of weird.
I look, it's like for some reason, my Gamepad has this weird thing
where like it always starts off, not centered, or something, weird,
like that.
I'm not sure what is actually going on there.
It's weird or two.
I don't know if you can see this, but the GamePad itself isn't even
like initialized.
You can see that you notice how it lights up when I launch the app.
Yeah.
I haven't played much around with this game pad.
I suspect that.
Basically.
We just have to go in and tighten up that X input code a little bit,
which will do a little later on but it's kind of wonky anyway.
So that's really.
All that's going on here.
So, let's take a look at what's happening when we step through the
code, right?
Basically, what's happening.
Is that at startup time?
Here we go.
We opened our window.
We initialize, our sound output with D, sound and clear out that
buffer, right?
The buffer is gone.
It's cleared.
Now, what we do is we say, all right.
We need to allocate a backing store.
That's basically someplace that we can put the samples that the game
can stuff the samples that we can then copy out into the ring buffer
for a direct sound.
So it's that extra copy.
I said, it was a little inefficient it is but I didn't want to pass
that complexity on to the app.
So basically we get our
Will buffer.
There we go into our Loop and each time through our Loop.
Okay, after we're done processing messages and the controller,
obviously we go.
And we say, okay, where is the right cursor?
At the moment.
Tell me where it actually is and that will basically give us back how
Mitch we want to write into the sound buffer.
We will then create a faux little wrapper here that just says, here's
the samples per second.
We were using here is how many bytes I want you to write out / the
bikes for sample to give you a sample count to write.
This is basically telling the game how many to, right?
We're going to go ahead and set up the
Matt memory as well.
Like we did before, we then tell the game, we want the bitmap.
We want the sound.
It goes ahead and does it sound.
It looks at the samples.
It writes them into that buffer.
Using the sine wave, right?
Does the gradient like we did before?
Now, assuming that the sound the sound sort of request for the pointer
work before us?
That we know we're actually outputting sound properly.
We'll go ahead and fill that sound.
Buffer will come in here will copy out from the the samples that the
game stuck in the buffer will copy those out and we'll use the split
ring thing.
So we'll be so basically.
Turn it into the right thing for the ring buffer, if necessary, and
then we will unlock the buffer and it will play.
Right?
That is all we did very very straightforward.
Very, very simple.
Sorry.
That I sort of gave you a little red herring with the alakay there.
I thought it might be a good time to introduce allocate.
Wasn't because base, our stack just isn't big enough for something
that large.
That is a fair number of bytes because, you know, I was allocating the
entire seconds worth of samples.
If we were just allocating, just the 60th of a second or just the
30th.
That would probably work fine.
But when
Change to doing the whole thing.
That's, that's not going to fit.
We'd have to up our stack size and that seems stupid because I didn't
even really want that to happen.
And so it seemed like a bad idea to kind of go down the alligator out,
just because I started on it instead of switching to the correct
thing.
So basically what we're going to do this is going to get pulled pool
with bitmap virtual a lock and that's basically all we really need to
do there.
So,
That's mostly everything for sound output.
And so if you look at basically what we've done, we've got graphics
output moved over.
We've got sound output moved over.
So basically all we're going to do next time is look at, as look at
how to get input over there.
And then we've got all the platform Services over.
But we still have one more thing which is memory and we're going to
have to talk about that, probably the day after.
So unless the input goes extremely quickly, which I don't think it
will will do input tomorrow and then we'll do memory the day after and
then we should be in really good shape.
We're kind of in game land at that point.
Now, one thing that I wanted to talk about that's a little bit iffy
here, right?
Is this is still kind of janky?
Because if you think about what happens when we come to this code,
we've got five minutes left.
So I just want to kind of talk about it.
We're clearing the direct sound buffer.
So now it's all filled with zeros.
And then we're starting at playing.
So now Windows is just playing.
What I would like to do is say, well, the first time we start filling
it, we don't want to fill it basically from the beginning because that
doesn't make any sense.
There's no need to do that because we haven't actually done anything
yet.
What we want to
Do is start filling it somewhere in the buffer based on where direct
sound is at the time, right?
So what we want to do is basically in here, right?
When it figures out, this sort of stuff and it says, you know, where
the target Christians should be.
We want to always do the lock from like the right curse or something.
We'd want to, just put the sound out there, where it should be.
Now there's a problem that we run into as well, that's worth thinking
about which is when we look at this and we say, when did we call get
current position to get the right cursor?
Right?
Well, we know that we're going to call that we need to figure out how
much sound we want to write, if we're going to actually look at the
sound card to see how much we should do.
Well, the problem there is by the time we're then going to go through
when we do that we do that call.
Windows will tell us basically right here.
Where is the sound card?
Playing at that time, but then we're going to get down here.
And what's going to happen is we're going to call game update and
render and that's going to take a lot of time.
Game update and renders going to take like a 60th of a second.
So we can fully expect that.
This will will be like eight hundred samples out of date.
By the time we get down through this, right?
So we kind of have a mismatch there and we need to start accounting
for that.
That's sort of what I was saying is why we have to start getting more
advanced with these things because there's actually a lot of Fennekin,
Enos that happens there that we have to think about.
Now, one way to solve that problem obviously, is to always be very
latent to always be very far ahead.
So, for example, we could go in here and we could say that, you know,
we're always going to start.
We're going to try and be way ahead that latency sample count is going
to be like really fairly sizable or something like this.
But again, these are all things that we kind of have to look at a
little later when we start start to sort of tighten that down.
For now, we've gotten things working the same way that they did before
and that's fine.
But that's not going to cut it in the end.
So basically, I'm going to drop a little to do in here and that's
basically like Tighten Up Sound Logic so that we know where we should
be writing to and can anticipate the time spent in the game update.
Because that's going to be pretty important.
This is like I said, it's pretty janky right now.
It's not what we would want to do.
It's good for playing out a sound wave, but in terms of actually
robustly keeping the sound going, it's not going to be it's and and
there's
Basically, the code is structurally correct in, how it's getting the
data back from the game and how its feeling the sound buffer.
But it's essentially it's logistically incorrect.
Because it's asking, if the way that it's doing, it started
computation just isn't good.
It was, it was basically.
That's what we did to get things working in.
That's fine.
But we go, we gotta basically take that up a notch.
I'm not going to start doing that now because we're almost to the Q&A
but that's basically it for that.
So, let's take a look.
I can't bear if there's anything else we're supposed to.
To do today.
I don't think so.
Well, I guess at the very end of the stream here.
I might as well go ahead and do one thing that someone asked for, they
were asking to maybe have the this haven't if not exist.
Basically, in our build dot bat, you'll notice that it always says
this line and that was annoying.
Somebody that I guess they were stickler for for checking first.
So we can do a thing here.
I never do these.
Do you do?
Like this, I think that's how you do it.
So you just do if not exist the directory, then you give it the make
door and that works.
So, I'm pretty sure that works.
I guess I'll double check that it works because for all, I know it
might not.
So, inside that build directory, if I was to temporarily, say renamed
build to build Foo, would this guy?
Where is it?
Would it work?
Let's take a look.
It did.
Okay, so that's
Fine, let's go ahead and nuke that hoops.
And then we'll rename it back.
Okay, so hopefully that takes care of anyone who was was getting, sort
of forwarded by that or getting sort of annoyed by that coming in
there that that repeated attempt to make a directory when a directory
already existed.
Okay, so, we now have both sound and video happening out in here and
we basically our video is actually pretty okay.
There's some things that I want to change a just finish up about that.
As well, but we could write a whole renderer in here.
We'd be fine.
Our sound is still needs a little more tightening.
Whether we do that tomorrow or not.
I don't know.
I probably would rather get the input and everything over there and
then and then maybe do next week a little sound tightening.
Just go through and kind of have our Loop a little more laid out, but
we're pretty good.
We're in pretty good shape.
I don't think there's anything left dangling here.
I think it's pretty good.
So I'm relatively happy with that.
I think now is a pretty good time to go ahead and start the Q&A.
So let me see if anyone's got a Q&A out there to ask about.
Let's see.
Trying to figure out where the questions start.
You're allocating a new buffer every frame.
They don't get freed until the function exits.
Sorry.
I'm not sure that doesn't sound like a question, but that's okay.
Let's see.
This may be getting a little ahead of things.
But will we want to use allocated?
Do things like store pointers to game objects that are local to the
player?
No, so alakay is literally just a local variable.
So basically all it is.
I kind of I probably shouldn't have shown it today.
Like I said virtual Alec was really the right thing.
There and and more specifically pulling these Alex up ahead up above
is going to be the right thing eventually, so I probably should have
gone there first and you know, one of the things that's hard when I'm
in the Stream, I got to make split-second decisions about what I
decide to try to show you.
And I look for opportunities to show you things that might be
appropriate but I don't always know if they will be right?
Like I've never tried to allocate a 1 second sound buffer on the stack
before.
So for all I know that could have worked fine, although I guess we did
kind of check.
That I'm actually surprised that didn't fit.
It's probably should have, but it would have been just barely.
All right.
It doesn't really matter point.
Being what you have to remember alakay is basically goes away whenever
a local variable would have gone away.
So if I do an alligator here, let's say I do an in Star Foo equals
alakay, right?
And I say that I want, you know to allocate an inch.
This is basically, you know, this this is basically what's going to
happen will show you.
There we go.
So our food, let's say we wrote to Star Foo equals.
I have like that.
Right?
There we go.
So basically, what's going to happen is when I come in here, let's
take a look.
Hello, there we go.
Let us go to where I wrote that.
So it's basically going to happen is when I come in here and you can
actually see in the assembly here.
If I dump into it, right?
You can basically see that.
No actual allocation happens, right?
Nothing.
Nothing actually occurs.
What happens?
Is it just moves the stack?
It just expands the space in the stack just like it would be for a
local variable.
Right?
So it goes ahead and expand the stack.
And then basically what we end up with now is our food point.
Right.
That's the pointer to Foo, right?
Y offset is right, is right before it, right.
You can take a look at what the address of Y offset is.
They're right next to each other.
Right?
I mean, they're not a budding, but they're based on the same space.
So all that alakay does is just says the same place that I'm storing.
These local variables for the function.
I guess.
I need some memory that I don't know how much it is.
So I'm just going to pass you a number and I want you to give me that
much, right?
What that means is that literally at the at the soonest possible
instant, right?
So, this is the scope that we're in, we're in this scope.
So, if we go down here, right?
That's, that's here or whatever.
I can actually set a breakpoint there.
But, you know, you know what I mean?
That's like, that's like right down here as soon as the, the control
flow reaches the end of this.
Exit it.
It goes away that memory can go away.
The compiler might keep it around.
You know, it's at the compilers discretion basically exactly when it
cleans up the stack, but at the very least when the function exits
it's going to reuse that stack for the next function call.
So you cannot put anything at all in alakay that you want to keep.
Nothing that you want to keep.
You basically have to only use it for transient things, just like
local variables.
Now.
There are some exceptions to that.
Obviously, if you were to alakay in the middle of the main which never
exits, essentially, then you kind of have it forever.
But at that point it's also the only reason to really use alakay
instead of a regular Alec is because you expect it to go away.
I could have just called virtual Alec and got the memory and kept it
which is what I had to do.
Doing right?
So there is no real compelling reason to use alakay, unless you are
trying to use that stat clean up to get rid of the memory for you,
when you're done with it, right, too.
So it's really, it's a thing for temporary computation.
And that's really all it is.
You don't you can't use it for storing, anything permanent.
There we go.
Let's see.
If the DS buffer lock fails, you'll pass garbage, vars to the game
code update by the game output.
Buffer set up.
Yes.
That's, that's totally true and I can put it to do in there for you.
Like I said, this, this logic kind of needs to go away, but if it
makes you feel more comfortable, right?
You can do make sure this is guarded entirely, right?
Because yeah, we don't and we also don't know Zach.
What's going on?
I mean,
Suppose, I mean one thing I could do if it makes you feel better to is
like a do this, right?
And that would be fine as well.
Because then, if it does fail, this, you know, we'll get set to zero
here and that'll be fine.
But again, this is getting vaporized.
So I wouldn't worry too much about that because this computation is
not right.
It needs to get it, needs to get changed.
So we'll do that shortly.
When you say 60, FPS might not be feasible.
Do you mean for non-pc platforms or specifically?
So I mean for non Hardware acceleration or it might even be for
Hardware acceleration.
I mean, basically, we don't know going into a game.
What's going to be feasible, frame rate rise, because there's a
trade-off there, 60 frames a second means, you have worse looking
Graphics period.
I mean, that's, that's just by definition.
You have half as much time to generate the graph.
X.
So, basically, if you're at 60 frames a second, they will look half as
good as 30 frames a second and it's actually even worse than that
because some things are constant and don't scale depending on that.
And so, like there's at the risk of getting into something that's a
little bit too off.
Topic, what I mean, is basically, if you imagine, you have a post
process and a pre process that happened before doing the actual
Graphics, like, say a post-process filter on the screen.
Well, that filter is going to be the same amount of time.
I'm no matter whether you're doing it 30 frames a second or 60 frames
a second.
So basically if you expand to doing something at 30 frames a second it
takes up the post process takes up a lot less of a fraction of the
frame time than it did at 60th of a second.
So, the actual time you have to do, all your render stuff actually
goes up by more than a factor of two.
That's a little confusing.
It's probably bad explanation table that for much later when we talk
about rendering stuff but point being we may decide not to be 30
frames a second, even with Hardware acceleration if we want the
graphics to look better because for any given game, you have to make a
call about whether 60 frames per second is worth it or not.
Now, of course, it'll always be able to run at 60 frames a second.
Two years later when all the graphics cards are way better and stuff,
right?
But I mean at launch at the Target platform normal, you know person
does not own 50, SLI graphics cards and a giant water cooled case
machine.
Then maybe we'll decide 30 Hertz is better because we can make
prettier Graphics or something.
Let's see.
For a clean build blowing away build each time.
Would be nice.
But then the solution file is there are we not worried about clean
builds?
Yes.
We are not worried about clean builds at all because we rebuild
everything every time.
So build clean is something that you only have to do if you are doing
partial rebuild, right?
Since we build everything.
Every time we don't care at all.
We don't need a clean build.
We never will have that thing where the bill gets weirdly out-of-date.
It solves all those problems.
If you just build with a batch file that builds
Everything.
So we don't ever have to worry about a clean build.
So the fact that the sln is in there, doesn't matter to us because
we're never going to have to clean out that directory.
Now, you could move the sln somewhere else if you wanted to, that's
entirely up to you.
Yeah.
The allocating every frame was your bug with Alec, a you were calling
it in a loop, that's actually fine.
So basically, it doesn't matter if you call allocating the loop
because alakay goes away at the scope.
I believe, unless I'm wrong about that.
So for example, if I want to, but maybe that's not true.
Maybe I'm wrong about that.
I don't use Alec a very often.
Remember the last time I actually used alakay.
But but so I'm just going to go ahead and allocate something
relatively large here and see if that's actually true.
Just so I can't know, for sure.
Yeah, hmm.
Okay.
So, basically, that I think you're actually right about that, then
that does suggest, that that's true.
So, I was assuming that that would get cleaned up on the scope, but it
only gets cleaned up on the function.
I definitely have never called alakay in the loop before, that's
definitely true and I home hardly ever call alakay at all.
But it looks like okay.
Yeah.
So basically, I guess what?
That's a good catch.
So basically, let me take a look here.
Yeah, yeah.
Okay.
So what does it say that?
I know what it says.
Let's see.
Yeah.
Okay.
So basically it doesn't actually scope the alakay it only Scopes it to
the function.
So basically, okay.
So basically all that's going to mean is basically it's only going to
free when you leave so I should at.
Yes.
Oh, that makes sense.
So okay that that all makes good sense.
Now that was just mean, never.
I've never I've literally never called alakay in the loop before, so I
had no.
Idea what it would actually do in there.
So if we had done it right here, basically, this is not in a loop.
If we did it right here that suggests, it should have worked.
I just got dropped it in where it was logically, let's go ahead there.
So I should be able to instead do it this way.
Thank you, by the way.
Dyslexic.
Deity, or wait.
No, who was it?
Yes.
Dyslexic deity.
That catch.
Having more eyes on the stream is so good.
Like I probably would have just moved on and been, like, I would ever,
because I never use alakay, and I was just like, whatever.
But that's like, cool.
Like I learned something, right?
And that doesn't happen when you're just programming by yourself.
Yeah.
Okay, so he's so that's totally awesome.
So basically, we could have used alakay.
It was not a problem size.
Wise, we could have used alligator right here instead of virtual lock
and put it on the stack.
The problem was that I put it in a loop because I just assuming, oh,
the compiler, will clean it up when we exit that Loop, right?
When it comes down here.
It'll just grow.
The shocks think the shrink the stack to be honest.
I don't understand why it doesn't do that.
But I guess it's better that way because the compiler has more options
if it knows, it only has to clean it up later.
So that means you basically can't ever use it in a loop, but that's
okay.
Because we like I said, I've never actually used a loop before.
And in this case.
I didn't even want to use it in the loop.
I just had dropped it in where the loop was because I wasn't thinking
about it because we don't actually need it in the loop for any given
reason.
We just wanted to allocate the buffer.
One time so that's fine.
So that's actually totally fine.
You could use alakay there.
I'm not probably going to leave that in there because I want to use
Virtual Alec eventually, so I'll delete that.
But thank you very much just like Zod for pointing that out because
That is good to know for people who are going to use alakay.
That is you got to keep them out of the loop.
So you got to keep them only anything.
Yeah.
Well, you learn something new every day.
I guess I should have been using allocate a lot more.
Although I still don't really.
Yeah, like I said, I just I don't use it very often.
So it doesn't it's not that everything that comes up super much for
me.
Let's see.
Can you explain again?
Why our current sound buffer fills problematic?
Yes, let's do that.
So we'll bring up again paint brush, which is not the best paint
package in the world.
We admit that freely and let's see if I can draw something I can.
So basically here's what I was saying.
So we've got this situation.
We allocated our buffer and that's good.
And then what we did is we cleared it to 0.
So it's empty, right?
And then we started at playing.
So, now, direct sound is playing it through, and direct sound has a
play cursor, right?
Here's the play cursor and then it has a right cursor.
You know what?
I'm going to make this a little
Drew myself and just say p.
And then it's got a right cursor W, and it doesn't want us to write in
here, right?
Because this is the area that it's busy.
Possibly copying out to the sound card because, remember this is
constantly moving forwards, time.
Waits for no code, if you will, and then there's the right cursor.
So, ideally, what's happening is we have some place that we want to
write our sound too.
Right?
So we have some place we're writing our sound too.
Okay.
So at the start of the code, this is cleared to 0.
We start playing forwards.
It's playing silence.
Right now.
We query it and we say, where is the play cursor?
It says, well, the play cursor is here.
We're like, okay, we know we have a, you know, a 60th of a second
worth of frame time that we're going to wait for.
And then we've got some amount of latency you want.
So like ideally we'd like to write right here, right?
That's what we should be doing.
We should be saying ideally we'd like to write right here and then
we'd say ideally we'd like,
Right?
Right here and we'd like to fill two right here.
This is our optimal strategy, right?
And then the next time around, we query again for the second frame and
let's say we find out that the play, the play cursor ended up here,
right?
So it's been playing part of our thing.
Now, we don't have the freedom now, right?
To just write anywhere, we want, we have to write from where we left
off to continue our sine wave.
And then we say, well, if the play cursors here,
you know, our optimal fill is out to there or whatever, right?
So basically what I was trying to say before is although are
relatively janky code is doing that second part correctly.
It's saying, where is the play cursor?
Let's figure out where to write to and we'll fill from where we left
off up to there.
That's working correctly right now.
What's not working correctly?
Is that first time?
So the first time through
Basically, what we're doing is we're going to right from the beginning
of the buffer always which is guaranteed to be wrong and stupid
because basically, what it's going to do is to play cursor, is going
to be here.
We're going to look at it.
We're going to say, oh we'd like to fill to here.
Then it's going to fill this coal thing.
Including the region that direct sound told us specifically.
It didn't want us to fill.
Does that make sense?
So what we really want to do ideally is we want to make this logic a
little more sound and just do the first time through actually.
Realize that we don't have to continue from any particular location
and start it up at the right point, right?
Hopefully that makes some sense.
Let's see.
Didn't you say that?
We should write the sound far ahead of the graphic, so that it syncs
properly, wouldn't the current method of updated graphics and sound on
the same frame?
Cause some lag on the sound know.
So basically, what we're going to do is we'll have the frame, right?
And we'll know that the frame is going to be displayed here.
Right here is the frame of Graphics.
Yeah, like that.
So we know we're going to start displaying the frame here.
And so we know that we just fill in the audio right here, right?
And so we're Computing that somewhere back here, which is
Fine.
And then we just make sure that we output each at the correct time.
So, will predict when we're going to flip the frame.
We'll line up the sound there and then we'll go and again, like I
said, this is going to be kind of complicated code.
That's why I say, our current ones pretty janky because we're not
doing all the stuff we need to do to actually make any of this happen.
But like I said, I got to kind of walk us through it.
A wave at a time to avoid just throwing in a ton of code and then
being like, Oh, well, the reason this thing is doing this is because
it's other thing that we haven't talked about and that so I can't
quite
Do all of this at once.
So we're just starting with the basic one, which is just chasing the
play cursor properly, which is now working in so that we don't get any
skips.
And that's good but the startup is wrong and the alignment is wrong
because we're not actually trying to, we're not doing anything
intelligent right now to try and sink our audio with our video.
And we may not for a while because that's kind of advanced.
Since alakay is just a function call.
How does the compiler know when to free the memory?
It's not a function call.
So I think that's what I was trying to show before when we stepped in
It's actually an intrinsic to the compiler that tells it to do a
specific thing.
So it's kind of like our dtsc when we look at that before it's
basically telling it to do a specific set of CPU operations.
In this case.
The CPU operation is to expand large the stack so it's to move the
stack pointer or the stack, top basically.
So it knows that it is that that it's using that memory.
Let's see.
Will we split our game sound updates out of game update?
And render said it can be called from a callback or another thread.
Yeah, I think.
So.
That's why I was saying earlier.
I think I said in a previous stream that we may eventually have to
split it out, to fill it on a separate thread.
We may decide never
Do that.
There's plenty of game to ship that don't do that.
But if we want to do that, then we would have to put it up, but I'm
not going to put it up until we have to
So according to allocate, according to amnesty and Alec is deprecated.
Should we not use malloc?
I like it suggests.
I so as I have amply demonstrated.
I never use alakay really, it's just not something that I ever do and
so like, like I did not even know that it wouldn't cleaned up at
Loops.
I assume that it would, I don't know the difference between Malachi
and Alec a the fact that it's deprecated and it says, tells you not to
use it suggests that you should probably use malloc a, but I don't
actually
We know what the difference is.
You should check them out here.
If you actually care about that.
Like I said, I don't really want to use alakay.
I would rather use Virtual a lot for all of our memory including
Temporaries and probably will.
I tried to show some out gay stuff.
I probably just shouldn't have sorry to confuse people with that.
Like I said, it's not something I use and so I'm not really in a good
position to talk about it any further than just to point out what it
did and it seems like some people on the stream or pretty
knowledgeable about it.
They're the ones who corrected my bug.
So
Maybe on the forums.
Someone someone who is an alligator type person could speak to that.
But I don't know, I've never I don't even think I've ever shipped code
that had an Alec a in it.
I've used it a couple times for testing.
Like the thing that I was just about to do is something I would do in
testing.
I guess I just was never unfortunate enough to throw it in a loop, but
I never actually ship code that has allocated in it.
Because I almost always have a place that I want my memory to go by
the time, I'm actually done.
So
Yeah, I'm sorry.
I just don't have any experience with it so I can help.
Tom Forsythe says, Alec a scope versus function is probably a see
Legacy versus C++.
That's probably true.
C++ is more about cleaning things up in Scopes.
And so it might be old school.
See.
Let's see.
Can you provide a log of the chat on the website?
There are a lot of good questions here.
I don't really want to have to try and maintain that.
If someone wants to put up a site that the chat log, you can do it
pretty easily.
You can run something like hex chat that just records the log and then
you could post it so that you're more than welcome to do so, but
that's probably not something that I will do.
Okay.
So plain flavored who, I'm not sure why that is.
But says, Malachi decrements to stack at the size is less than 1 K or
calls Malik otherwise, okay.
So basically alakay that's interesting.
So basically what the person on the stream says, and I'm sorry.
Like I said, I don't know.
I'm not an Alec a person.
But I'll just say what he said in case this helps you understand it
and you can go read the documentation to check what he was saying.
Is basically Malachi.
Basically will actually do a real allocation.
If you're trying to allocate more than one k.
So and then it will automatically insert a free at the end.
So that's kind of Handy.
Actually, I guess.
I don't know seems reasonable.
I doesn't sound like a problem to me.
So I would say, yeah, that does sound kind of cool.
I don't know.
Like I said, I don't use them.
I'm not sure.
Can you talk a bit about how you can safely predict where the flip
happened so that you can write sound there?
Yeah.
So basically, what we're probably going to do and this this kind of
code is always pretty tough.
It's when we actually do it.
You'll see.
I will mess it up a few times.
I bet as I go to debug it because if I'm not like basically cheating
and looking at my existing code, it's complicated to do this
optimally, basically, here's what you need.
To do.
This is T equals zero.
Right.
This is when the program starts sound will start playing basically
immediately.
So off it goes, right?
And it will sort of Advance forward in time.
Now, these, right?
Ideally, our this is frame one, right?
So this is one, this is frame 0, this is frame to.
So we will be displaying nothing during this time.
Right?
We've just started up.
We haven't actually do anything.
So we're Computing frame one right here.
This is us.
Computing it, right?
And what we're going to try and do is flip it here so that it displays
right here and we're going to write sound here.
Right?
So the way we do that is we go.
How fast do we think?
Our frame rate will be right?
We compute the frame based on that expectation.
So if we're trying to run at 60 frames a second, we basically say,
okay, let's plan to do it at 1/60 of a second from now, right?
The audio into the buffer 1/60 ahead of when we started, right?
Right?
And assume that it won't catch up before then.
We will do the frame, get it ready.
And then we will either use the vertical blank to trigger it or we'll
just use the actual, our dtsc, or query performance counter.
Probably not ours to see.
Query performance counter to see how much time has elapsed.
And when a 60th of a second has elapsed, do the blind right there.
Right?
And we'll have to write some code, the janky code.
That's basically tries to make sure that if we end up in a situation
where we skip, where we
Miss a frame or something that a that the audio doesn't skip.
So we might have to write like two frames of audio and then overwrite
a frame of audio when we aren't skipping.
So, right ahead and then overwrite basically, and also to handle when
we miss a frame.
So that we're displaying at one frame for two frames that sort of
stuff.
It's really kind of janky.
It's not fun.
It's not fun at all.
So, let's see.
Yeah, so in answer to your question.
So how we predict where the flip happens.
We just use the query performance.
We use the timer in the system.
And we basically just try to try to use the timer to predict when
that's going to happen.
If we have vertical, refresh of e blank.
So a sink that we can sink to then that's good because basically,
there's a function that will wait for that vertical.
Retrace.
So we know that that's happening.
And also when we use opengl and direct3d it'll automatically, we can
set it to automatically, wait for that.
And we can see when that
As we can time, a few of them and see.
So, we've got some options, but it's really, it's awful.
And you'll see when we write it.
It's just, it's just awful.
It's what you, it's something you wish to operate system would do for
you because it's in a better position to do it.
We know that you can't really go below 30 frames per second, to give
the impression of smooth motion.
Is there similar standard rule of thumb for audio latency?
Well.
I don't know.
I think it varies per person and it depends on the type of game, you
know, if you're playing a game, where the audio is largely color.
It's just, it's like things that reinforce what's going on with the
graphics, but it's not integral to the great gameplay.
You can have pretty high audio latency, you know, you got if you have
like a hundred milliseconds of audio latency or something, which is
huge, you may get away with that, right?
Because the brain kind of does this weird thing where it sinks stuff
up, that doesn't happen at the same time.
It'll
Up, but two things if your gameplay is based on audio.
Like, you're playing Guitar Hero or something, or if you're just going
for that really tight, crisp feel then the lower the better really.
I mean if you can get it down, I don't think there's ever a time when
you don't feel better about lower latency audio.
I don't know.
It's tough to put your finger on.
I don't know if people have done sort of tests where they've seen how
the feel of the game is.
Improved by reducing the audio latency down.
But yeah, you'd like it to be 0.
You like there to be no separation between the frame display and when
the audio happens, so
Let's see.
AJ bunk husky says the reason allocate is deprecated is because it's
hard impossible to implement on some platforms.
Also.
It has to be a compiler built in which is clunky.
Lastly, things get tricky when you in line a function with an Alec a
or use inside a macro the Cincy, modern best practices to use
something like good new obstacle.
If you really want automatically free dynamic memory in C++.
You'd probably opt for Unique pointer shared point of these days.
Yeah.
and, like I said, I
Agree, I just don't use Alec a pretty much in shipping code.
So I don't actually know.
I can't really say if there's something else that you should use.
Yeah, if you're into shared pointer or basically I think that Dynamic
that a C++ class that dynamically freeze, the memory that it holds
when it exits, the scope, that's one totally valid solution.
Another thing that's nice about it is basically saying, well, you
know,
Can I get temporary memory in general in my system?
I don't know.
I will show you when we actually get into things.
When we I was the only reason allocate even came up today because I
thought I might mention it.
Since it's something that's worth knowing and I haven't gotten to
memory stuff yet.
So I'm not in a position to use the sorts of things that I normally
would use.
So I guess what I would say about it is yeah, just be aware that it's
there.
It allows you to use the stack in ways that that allow you to not have
to predict it.
But like the people on the stream said, it's kind of it's a tough.
It's a tough guy to ship.
It's a tough guy to rely on.
If you actually want it to always be there.
There's a really it's kind of unfortunate because it would be nice.
If there was a good way to treat the stack and memory, the same and
allocate Kai does allow you to do that.
But it's just in practice.
The main thing that killed, it always for me was the fact that there
was such a small limit typically, or you had to make the stack size
huge and there was all these sort of constraints on it.
That was always the thing that killed it for me.
But if I was like in charge of how see should have implemented, I
probably would have done things.
So that allocate could do huge allocations and you could have done it
so that the program stack was a giant memory stack and it worked a
different way.
Like so I would actually like to have a real alakay but allocate isn't
really that thing.
And so as a result, I've never actually used it in shipping code
because I never was comfortable with it.
Yeah.
And like you see
I didn't even really know.
I didn't even know when it was when its clean up rule was, I would
have thought that I didn't realize that I put it in a loop.
I wasn't thinking about at that time.
But even if I had, I would have thought that it would clean up at the
end of the loop because I would have figured that with the compiler
would do is entering the loop.
Push, the stack frame down on, exiting the loop, pop it up.
And to be honest.
I have no idea why you wouldn't just do that.
But I guess it makes things too complicated for the compiler because
it has to remember where it's basing things off.
The stack pointer is something I don't know.
It doesn't seem like it should be but you know, maybe.
It is.
Oh, and AJ Busca, I know you weren't picking out my style.
Like I said, I don't use alakay.
So it's not picking on my style at all.
The last thing I would do is recommend people use alakay because I
have no experience with it shipping code.
So I have no idea.
I was just saying I you know, it's there be aware of it allows you to
grow the stack size dynamically, and it looks like I guess from what
people are saying that.
Maybe you can't use it very effectively on their platform.
So that's maybe one good reason not to.
We won't be using it in the final in any of the final code of handmade
hero.
It's just not something I do.
But yeah, but I like I said, I try not to be ideological on the Stream
So I try not to say stuff, like don't use alakay because how should I
know right?
Especially things.
I don't have much experience with like Alec a or other sorts of
things.
I'm not in a position to tell you do use this, don't use this.
Usually all I can really do is say here's what I do.
Here's what works for me.
Here are some trade-offs about them.
Make your own decisions and for something like a like a.
Like I said, yeah, I couldn't say that.
So I do.
Wouldn't I don't you.
Is it?
But I wouldn't say don't use it.
I'd say go learn about it yourself.
Now that you kind of know about it and see what you think of it.
And like I said, there's a lot of people on the street who seem to
have more experience with than I do.
Maybe if they're on the forums, you guys could discuss it and they
could tell you a little bit about why they don't or do you use it and
you know, stuff like that.
How do you do two voices with sound waves in one buffer?
Well, we will be doing that.
Just you wait.
Let's see, when will be the first bright display in animation.
Who knows?
When we get to it, when we get to.
It depends how we, how long things take to explain?
Let's say.
I've heard the brain treats sounds with within 10 milliseconds is
happening at the same time.
I suspect audio to video think is the same.
No, I don't think that's true.
I think you can be way further off than 10 milliseconds in audio/video
sink, but I could be wrong about that.
Getting less than 10 millisecond.
Latency would be great and you would love to have that.
A lot of times.
I don't think you realistically get it, but that would be cool.
When you work with temporary memory, is there a risk of memory
overflow in memory leaks?
If so, how do you make sure these don't happen?
So yeah, I mean memory basically, anytime you're managing memory.
It is definitely something that you have to be aware of.
Typically, the way that I approach those problems and you'll see me do
this.
Like I said, I haven't gotten to the point where I've talked to you
about memory yet.
So we really haven't had a chance to do any of the things that I would
normally do, but we're getting there.
In fact, maybe Thursday that we do it.
the thing to understand is,
Managing memory actually, isn't that hard?
Once you build some tools?
We haven't built the tools yet.
So it's pretty.
It'd be pretty hard now.
So, but once you have some tools for it, you'll see it's actually not
that hard.
But, yes, you anytime you're doing low-level programming, even if it
has nothing to do with memory.
Let's say, you're just trying to fill it in a buffer.
That's that's, you know, you know, just some array, someone made.
If you don't, if you're not careful, you could write off the end right
off the beginning.
Who knows?
There are tricks for catching those sorts of things as well.
You saw
The compiler catch one of ours today, but there's another way you can
do it too.
And I'll be showing you that it's spacely with virtual Alec.
You can line things up.
So that if you write even a single bite off, the end of something,
you'll fault immediately and that's a good way to catch things, too.
But there's a lot of stuff that you have to do, basically, to make
sure that you could run and debug mode with that.
But then run in non debug mode without having all the overhead of
doing the lines up like that.
So we'll look, and we'll be getting to those things.
Let's see.
I'm a longtime rhythm game player and I can notice audio off sync as
little as 10 milliseconds earlier late getting it just right as both a
big deal and possible.
Yes, and I agree with that.
Like I said, the problem is you it's really not possible though.
Because even if you get it right on the output, which is what we'll
try to do your TV, May delay it and you're like you may plug it into
receiver and the audio plays on a delay that's different from the
video.
So it is very problematic getting
Getting below 10 milliseconds.
If you if you don't have some way to really calibrate your actual
setup so we can do stuff to try and get it so that we are outputting
things at the right time, but that doesn't really help the actual
real-world result.
Unfortunately.
Okay.
We're getting to the end of the stream here.
Last couple questions.
Let's see, any advice for a senior level CS student interested in game
development.
Not sorry.
If you want to ask those kind of questions.
Maybe we can do that on some kind of a stream that's not programming
oriented because basically those those questions are kind of general
and I'm not even a good person to answer them.
But in the pre stream before the stream starts, we will do questions
sometimes of that and I can answer them to the best of my ability, but
I don't know, I don't even really know answers to questions like that.
Let's see.
Think that's roughly it.
Do I see anything else on here?
I don't see anything else on here.
Let's see.
I think that's about it.
Alright, ladies and gentleman.
Thank you very much for joining us for another edition of handmade
hero.
I think everything besides our attempt to show allocated a, which was
kind of terrible, though the folks in the Stream, kind of saved it for
us.
So thank you very much for that.
Basically, that would have been that would have given people the wrong
impression of alakay.
Now, they've kind of got the right impression of, that's good, but,
basically, ignoring the allocating this today, I think we
Did a pretty good job of doing what we set out to do, which was
obstructing more of our platform layer.
We've now gotten to the point where we're all good with audio
happening on the other side.
So, we need to do some work on our platform layer, to make the audio
output actually synced more properly with the video, which is
something I want to do, but we'll hold off on that for a little while.
Tomorrow we're going to do input and then the day after that we'll do
memory and then we'll be in good shape for actually starting to write
some gain code or going in.
Hiding tightening down, a few of those platform things, which is,
maybe what we'll take some time to do.
Just so we can really solidify that platform layer and kind of be done
with it for a while, put it aside and move on to actually writing the
game code.
So thank you so much for joining us.
It has been a pleasure.
Thank you very much.
The people on the street who corrected the alakay stuff.
I could not do it without you guys because like I said, when I'm
program in the Stream It stuff up here.
It is definitely tough.
And especially when I'm working with some stuff and I want to point
out something that isn't something that I do frequently.
It really helps to have other experts on board.
Who can say, like, oh, you should know this or take a, look at that.
That's that's pretty helpful.
So, thank you guys for that.
And if you do have time to post on the forums, that would be great to
to fill in some of that knowledge.
If you go to handmade hero dot-org, there's this news and forums
button here.
You click on that, and you can get all the stuff you can get the
episode guide, which is pretty cool.
But you can also go to code discussion where we've got a bunch of
stuff there.
So thank you so much, everyone for joining me and I hope to see you
tomorrow at 8:00 p.m.
PST when we will tackle input.
And maybe memory.
I don't know if we'll get to it will do input in memory of the next
two days, but how much we get to tomorrow?
I can't say, so thank you very much for joining us and I will see you
tomorrow.