Still recording.
Hello everyone, and welcome to handmade hero.
The show we could complete game live on stream on Twitch and before we
get started today, I obviously want to mention for anyone who has not
already heard the news.
We are very, very excited to announce that we are going to be having
convention for handmade hero and you can actually find out more about
it.
You can, you can really just type handmade con dot-org into your
browser and hit return and it will take you directly to whatever the
latest post about it.
Is we just put up the very first post about it which is kind of like
our save the date post.
It lets you know when it is you can buy tickets if you want to at the
early bird kind of price, early, registration price and it tells you
kind of where it is and when it is in case you want to, you know, if
you know it something you're definitely going to want to attend.
You can plan your trip already and get everything all set and what
we'll be doing over the next month or the month of October is will be
posting.
At least two more blog posts.
I don't know if I think that might cover just about everything will
posting to more blog posts with quite a bit more information about it,
one will be the complete speaker list for handmade hero.
Con 2015, which the the sort of set up for the conference is going to
be very specifically.
It's going to be quite different from what a typical programming
conference consists of, instead of sort of a series of lectures where
someone gets up and go, you know, run through a PowerPoint
presentation, slide at a time.
It's going to be the opposite of that.
What we're going to do instead is we're going to essentially take the
the people who are going to be the speakers at it quote, unquote.
And I say that because it's a weird term when you say speakers like
obviously lots of people speak at a convention but basically the guest
of honor, let's say right?
And what we're going to do is I am going to sort of act as the person
who is going to talk to them about their past projects, their current
At their future projects, the programming involved with them, what,
you know, what were some of the most interesting problems they face?
How do they solve them?
That sort of thing and it's designed to recreate sort of the more sort
of what I would say.
The more intimate or interesting way that programming knowledge
actually gets shared.
When you go out to dinner with somebody who's, you know, you know, a
really great program or something else or you happen to meet them at a
conference you know, at the bar something like this and you strike up
a conversation and you actually get to talk to them.
About like it's sort of an interactive way the stuff they work on and
to ask questions.
Dynamically.
And so the whole thing is kind of like a more real more direct
experience.
It's not passing through this filter of somebody.
Spend a lot of time like thinking about slides and making bullet
points, and kind of like cramming sort of the way their brain
naturally works and naturally explains things into this sort of like
weird awkward format.
And so again, the goal is to really kind of
Have it be much more of a like kind of session where you can kind of
drill down into things and let you know, sort of the natural way that
people think about things and talk about things come out and my
reasoning for that is just because I've always found that it's so much
more useful and interesting for me when I have been able to talk to
Great developers that way.
And I always feel like there's a tremendous amount lost when I go,
listen to lectures by the same people.
Because it just doesn't have the fluidity and the speed and the
interesting sort of like directness when the person is just able to
talk about what it was that they did.
And have, you know, a an inquisitive person on the other end to direct
that towards like the really interesting Parts than the confusing
parts of it that they want to know more about, right?
So I've designed the cover that kind of around that and I'm really
excited about it because I've never really seen it.
That much before there are kind of models of this, a little bit.
There's some things that I've seen where people have done, sort of
like interview style, things like this.
But never quite in the way that I kind of had hoped and certainly
never for programming, but I've seen, so I'm pretty excited to try it.
I think it's going to be pretty interesting and the other thing that I
think that it does, which is is pretty important.
Is it also allows us to potentially talk to people who we wouldn't,
ordinarily be able to talk to you.
Because their schedules are too busy, you know, or, you know, a small
calm, like handmade con wouldn't be worth their time to it to do all
the prep for something like this, you know?
Because it's a small interactive thing where they just come and they
be themselves and you know, they talk or you know, people who don't
like public speaking, you know, or don't know how to prepare a
presentation, but our great programmers and people that we want to
hear from it, also allows us to to talk to people like that too.
Right?
So it means that now,
Like it can be.
It can be anybody who we think is like a great game developer or
something.
They can share their knowledge with us and they can share how they do
what they do.
And I think that that to me is a really important aspect of it too.
Because there's so much there's so much artifice in the normal way
that program and Conference has forced people to present and I don't
think it actually yields much like better content.
I think it often feels worse content.
And it greatly restricts, the number of people who are willing to do
it or have time to do it that year or who want to bother and all these
other things.
So, I'm really interested in this, and I'm pretty excited about doing
it this way.
And so, the people that I'm selecting who I, you know, I'm going out
and trying to say, you know, hey, do you want to do this and, and sort
of get them interested in the whole concept of, this are all people
who I want to have that dialogue with.
So I'm
Specifically picking, you know, programmers who it's like their stuff
that they're working on now or that they worked on in the past that I
think is really, really interesting that.
I don't super understand how they did it or like the way they did it.
And I want to have that conversation with them.
REM like, tell me about how you did this.
Tell me about how you solve this problem.
What was this development process?
Like, you know, I really I'm basically selecting it to be like stuff
that I really want to know because I feel
Feel like if I want to know it it must be something relatively rare,
right?
It's like it's not going to just be something that you would just know
if you're a game developer, it's going to be something kind of unique
and special and I feel like that's the really, the most interesting
thing that we could do with a conference is to kind of get some of
those things that that are really sort of interesting insightful.
Things that often times, you know, you have to the only way you're
ever going to get to know those things if you happen to have the Good
Fortune to know what.
These people personally and go out to dinner with them or talk with
them on a regular basis or something.
That so that's the whole point behind him icon and like I said, we
will be announcing this the the people who will be the guest of honor.
When we get that list completely nailed down, it will probably be.
I'm guessing it will be five people.
based on the way that I've looked at the times because basically we
have the venue from 10 in the morning until 6:00 at night,
And so assuming that people, you know, at some point have to break for
lunch that leaves us enough time.
I think to do to do five solid sessions of that with five different
people.
I could go up to six but I was looking at it.
And I was saying, well,
I'd rather do one less person and have a little more time with every
buddy else.
Then try to cram more people in there and not, you know, have to end
the sessions just when we were getting to something really
interesting.
We want to talk more about and all of the people that I've been
approaching are all people who I strongly suspect that even with an
hour, 15 an hour, 30 minutes between all the things that I want to ask
them.
And then we probably want to have, you know, as a little bit of time
for
Audience questions as well and stuff like that.
It's I really just don't think we're going to do probably more than
five.
So my plan is there will be five people who I really want to talk to.
And that will be the way that we do the conference and we'll talk to
them pretty in-depth.
Probably like I said for about our 15 hour 30 would be would be my
hope it may be that again we it has to be a little shorter again just
because of timing and and we'll see since it's the first year doing
this.
I do expect that there will be some bumps.
I'm not going to lie to you.
Like the chances that Me by myself, with very little resources, I'm
going to be able to run things complete without a hitch is probably
not realistic.
but again, like I
I tried to keep things very, very simple.
So the chances that we'll all be able to just show up, run a good con,
have a lot of fun and get a lot of really great information are pretty
high because the number of things that have to get done for that to
happen.
I've tried to keep them to an absolute minimum.
I've picked a good space for it.
It's a really nice place and it's really easy to get to its Central.
It's easy to find places to stay around it.
It's, you know, a notable landmark in Seattle.
So it's pretty easy to find as well.
So I'm thinking that probably we've got a really solid chance of even
though this is the first time we're doing it, I think we probably will
be able to keep it relatively smooth.
Like I said on the pre stream and like I said in the post, if you read
it,
One of the things that will probably not go smoothly, that's a
separate issue.
Is, I really don't know what will be able to do in terms of getting
the content streamed.
My goal for the conference because handmade hero is a online show,
that's that's performed live.
And the questions are taken live of the internet and all that stuff is
that I would like the conference to be streamed live as well I
approached, which about that several months ago.
They said they
What would do it?
But of course, you know, they're entitled to change their mind.
So I have told them now that we've got all the days now that was,
like, here's what it's going to be.
And I've asked them to please help a stream it if they're like, yes,
let's do.
You know, we can totally do that.
Then it'll happen.
But, you know, they might say, no, you know, we change their mind or
we don't have the resources for that right now, or something like
that.
That's totally within their purview right there under no obligation to
help with it.
And, you know,
They're doing it just to be nice.
Basically.
So you know, it's just a straight-up charitable thing for them to do
to help the community.
So I don't know what they'll say, I'll keep you posted on that but
that's what I've asked them to do.
And you know, they were definitely receptive to it and I think they're
going to try to make it happen but no promises because like I said
it's just a straight-up charity thing for them to do.
They might not have it in their budget.
They might not have the time to do it.
They may be overextended at that point, I don't know.
So fingers crossed that would be what happens.
But if that doesn't happen, we will probably not try to stream it live
ourselves because we just don't have the expertise for that.
I definitely don't know how to do that, if other people who think that
they do have the expertise for that, want to give it a shot.
I would certainly go ahead and give them a live stream key for that
day and they could give it a shot.
So you know, if people out there want to try and to do that, if twitch
is not able to help us then that could certainly happen as well.
But like I said that part I cannot guarantee.
So for people out there
You can't make the con, I can't promise that it will be able to be
viewed lied.
I just don't have the resources to make sure that I could really
actually guarantee that that will happen.
So I promise we'll try but I, you know, I just don't know, realistic
will happen.
Same thing with video.
I would very much like it to be recorded, so that people can view it.
After the fact on YouTube, especially if it cannot be streamed live in
which, you know.
So there would not be a way to watch it remotely.
So failing, the ability to, you know, to have it streamed live on
Twitch.
We would also then of course, try to do a permanent archival recording
of it again.
No promises there because it's just not my expertise.
We will try to ask some people to try and film it and hopefully that
goes smoothly.
And that the audio is okay, but again, I really just don't have any
control over that.
It's way beyond my
My thing that I ever do, I don't do AV for anything.
So, you know, that's that stuff is just not a guarantee will try, but
it's not a guarantee, everything else.
I think we'll probably be able to pull off just fine, but those two
things are ones that are very technological in nature.
Mostly about having the experience to know all the little things that
can go wrong when you do something like that.
And so you know if again, if twitch can do it, I think it'll be great
because they have the experience, I'd they would know how to do it.
They would know how to not screw it up.
And but if they don't, then we're just going to have to sort of wing
it.
And I don't really know if that how that will be.
But so that aside, I think everything else for Hamid.
Khan has been coming along quite well, and I'm pretty excited about
how it's going, and I think it's going to be really great.
So that is it for him?
Make on, I'll mention it a few more times on streams as we go for
people who may or may not be catching this dream.
Catching this one live.
I'll mention a few more days from now but now you've basically got all
the information about it and like I said, I
I will as soon as there is another post about speakers or about other
things about the conference.
I will mention them at the start of the stream so you can check them
out.
All right, all that said,
We have lunch of programming to do.
So we need to start doing it today is day 194 on a hero and we are in
the midst of doing some work with our debug viewing, where we're
adding features, so that we can, you know, have sort of a fairly
reasonable set of tools for inspecting, the behavior of our game.
As we go, I would like to sort of push a little harder on the UI
today.
And also I think I figured out a way.
He may be able to have our cake and eat it too.
As far as debug variables is concerned.
I'm not 100% sure, but I did think of a way to do that and don't know.
We want us really do that today.
But I did think I figured out a way of thinking about it, where we
could have the both the pluses of having ability to compile things in
and out entirely runtime as well as the ability to live update things
instantaneously.
So I was thinking that maybe there is a way to sort of do something
really wacky, there that might work.
Don't necessarily know, can't promise but we may try that as well.
For now though, I'd like to do a little bit more work on the u.
I so that's what we're going to do today.
194 if you would like to follow along at home, you will want to unzip
day 193 source code.
If you preorder the game on handmade here at org, that is the source
code that we were going to be starting with here.
And that is, you know, if you want to kind of follow along and with
the exact same code that I'm doing that is the source code that you
want to start with, all right?
So here's where we left off.
We had our handmade hero, right?
And we have, like, kind of a really for lack of better term, a very
ugly radial menu that we had implemented and it allows us to recompile
the game set switches and change the actual compilation of the game at
runtime, right?
So for example, right now, you can see that we're using the sort of
small render plate here as said of the full screen.
One and so if we want to, for example, then that's a compile time.
H, if we want to, we can actually go pick the, the debug option that
changes that trying to set this one right here, right?
Test, weird draw, buffer size, and if we toggle that, then you can see
that it.
You know, it actually did recompiled the game right there, Reloaded
The Game on the Fly and, and went, which is kind of awesome.
I mean, it's just, I don't know.
It's one of those things.
That's just so neat.
You know, you can be in the game.
You can go like this.
And now, you're you recompiled and the game like didn't even lose its
state, right?
That's the kind of thing again, that a lot of people turn to scripting
languages for because they want that kind of functionality and it's
kind of neat that we basically just totally got it here on handmade
here without ever having to leave C.
So we can totally do completely performance oriented code anytime we
want.
But anytime we don't want, right?
Like, anytime we want the convenience of a scripting language, we
actually get that for free now that we've done that work, which is
pretty great.
So that's pretty pretty, darn neat.
But like I said, this radial menu is like really super ugly.
Not very functional.
And it also doesn't really allow us to provide very many options here,
right?
Like, you know, you could imagine if we tried to scale this up to 100
debug options, Not only would it be a crazy radial menu to try and
pick from, but it would also have a pretty nasty problem of finding
where they were would be pretty darn tough, right?
So, at the very least, we're probably going to want to do something
the hierarchical.
Alright, even if we stuck with just a radial menu, you'd want
something where maybe you could pick a category and then pick
something from it or things like this.
And when I'm thinking personally about this right?
Is that in general?
I want sort of a clutch style thing.
Like I talked about before where I will just right click and some you
I will come up, I can do some stuff and then it goes away.
So that the debug stuff is always out of my way and I can just always
get to it this way.
And so when this comes up, what the really what I'm thinking of more
is I want this radial menu, the reason I put a radial menu in there is
I want a quick
Menu something that I can access quickly.
And I feel like the radial menu will do that for me, but that is just
for certain highly used things that I might want to turn on and off,
like profile information or something like that, right?
So I want to now create an additional piece of UI before we refine the
radial menu, at all before we go any further down that path because
that's sort of I mean it's already sort of functional.
I want to get some other things functional as well.
I want to create something that.
It will allow us to do a more sort of a more extensive user interface
for categorizing larger series of things.
So I'm thinking about something like a scrolling hierarchical, Tree
View, kind of a thing, you know, some kind of standard interface
thing, so that when I hit the right Mouse button and another thing too
is what I just hit the right Mouse button you know the it just kind of
blinks right now.
What I want to do is also change that so that like you can just click
the right Mouse button once and then the menu will stay up as I
interact with it.
And then if you hold down and then release the button with a gesture,
it will select from the radial menu so that we can have
Our speed cake and eat our functionality to if it coin a phrase, a
very bad phrase.
I always The Familiar is following me too.
I feel like I want to turn that off.
Familiar, follows hero.
All right, so now the familiar is not following the hero.
All right.
So yeah.
So that's what I would like to do is I would like to have some way,
you know, I suppose our ground chunks should probably also not be so
ridiculous, huh?
Where is that guy?
Chuck checkerboards.
Oh, and you know what?
We would also have to turn on the rebuild on on recompute ground
chunks, on XE change so that they will flush having to recompile on
the Fly code, is just so darn neat.
I'm sorry, that's just super cool.
Anyway.
So yeah, what I want to do here is I want to figure out some kind of
way that I'm thinking maybe, like, something where, you know, on the
side here.
Maybe I'm just throwing this out there.
So maybe something on the side here.
It's just going to be kind of a list, and the list could have some
hierarchical options in it, right?
So, like in the list, maybe, you know, we've got stuff like, you know,
rendering and simulation and whatever, right?
So that we can categorize things as to where they might belong in that
list.
You know.
And then we could find things easier and even if there's like
thousands of options they can be in some kind of nested sense.
So finding them is is easier because you can kind of Pare down what it
looks like at each time.
Right?
So that's what I'd like to do.
So I'm just going to go ahead in there and since like I said I have no
idea really what form that's going to take or what that's going to do
what I'd like to do is just go in there and
Make something much like we did the radial menu that just does that
something like that and so that we can start to investigate the code
and build something relatively reasonable.
So that's what I'd like to do and I'm going to start doing it so that
we can figure out how it should go.
Alright, so here we are in handmade debug.
And as you know, in handmade debug, right?
We have the thing that draws the, this debug main menu here.
It draws that radial thing, right?
And this is the thing that kind of Loops over, whatever we have listed
in our, we've got our debug variables array, right?
So, here is that debug variables Ray.
This lists all of the variables that we have in the debug system.
and those debug variables, obviously, all get sort of
Listed in the radial menu right now which is not at all something that
I actually want to have happen.
So we know that the radial menu will go to being something that Loops
over this array.
To being something that only Loops over some very specific, certain
ones of that, right?
Certain very specific, certain things.
And what I would point out here is this debug variable list is in?
No?
Does it in no way needs to be actually a flat flat array or anything
like that?
We saw with the debug counters, and those sorts of things.
We have time-sensitive macros that have to do stand that have to,
like, operator multiple threads and right into buffers and all this
other stuff.
So, the other dead debug stuff, kind of had to be careful.
They had to be these Global variables and they had to be written into
by threads and
Away and all this stuff.
There's all this sort of restrictions on how those could be but the
debug variable list fundamentally is nothing more than just a list of
debug variables that could be constructed in any way by anyone.
At any time, it's not edited by the code at all.
And in fact if we look at the config file, this config file is
actually the thing that the program reads and writes, right.
Those are the actual lb defines that actually get read and write by
the program.
So this while this file has to look like this because handmade hero
reads and writes it this part right here, I'm free to do whatever I
want with it.
So what I think we could pretty trivially do here is just instead of
constructing it and as this plate aside see unfortunately and C++ as
well.
Do a very bad job of allowing of alike to enter data.
It's one of the biggest snafus of c and C++ is the fact that they
didn't think through the
The fact that people would want to enter data in along with their
code, right?
And so, they only have the most sort of rudimentary unfortunate ways
of actually putting data in.
Basically, the only thing you can do is just make a big old flat.
Yes that's it.
And it's pretty hard to do anything else.
Actually you end up in kind of nasty situations if you want to do
anything such as like dynamically sized things where you have like a
pointer to an array or something.
They've always made it very difficult for you to Flap Define those in
convenient ways.
So what I like to do in circumstances especially like this where there
isn't any particular reason.
Why I have to make this be an actual data value constructed by the
compiler, is I like to go ahead and make it something that's just
constructed at startup by the actual runtime code.
And of course, we do know already that we have the ability to
initialize our debug code.
We've got some stuff right here, right.
It's got a Rena that it can do things with to create.
Of various sizes.
So if I wanted to right here, I could go ahead and create a dynamic
version of this.
That is actually created at startup.
And the reason I'd like to do that is to make it easier for me to
construct this as instead of a flat list of things.
Actually, a hierarchical list of things that will allow us to do
things like put, you know, put that sort of tree view or something
like that, you know, into place, right?
So, here's the way I would
I would like to do that, but I'd like to do is create like a little
place for me to put that, right?
So I'm going to create a function to hold this code will call that
debug create create variable hierarchy or something like this.
Debug create variables, debug.
Create something name is hard, brain doesn't know what name is
English.
So difficult, half a
In the words.
And so what we'll do here is we'll just pass in, you know, a memory
Arena that it can use to allocate the stuff and it'll just use the
debugger arena there.
And then what we could do is recreate this list instead of having in
handmade debug variables that H, or, you know, what, even we could
just even put it in handmade debug variables, that H, we could
actually just have it exist in here.
So that again, because again, my reasoning for
Doing this was because I wanted to make it so that it was kind of
confined to one place.
So that was easy to know where you went to add a debug variable.
So we could totally do that again, pretty trivial for us to do.
So, when we do our debug variable this thing here, what we would then
do is say Okay, instead of doing a list this way, right?
We'll just do a list this way.
So, exact same code, basically, in terms of what we're typing in.
But instead of the macro expanding to a fixed data definition, we're
just going to change that to actually call a function that creates the
variable, right?
So we'll just have like, debug add variable or something like that,
and it passes.
In the name, bowstring eyes and the actual value of that name regular,
right?
So, there you go.
So if I do that, then I will have the ability to start doing some
other things, right?
I would have the ability for example, to create groups of these, just
by using a little, you know, like, you know, begin group, something
like this.
You know, and then end group.
And so, what I could do there is say, like, okay, so you know, use
debug camera, use space, outlines, maybe.
And I'm just like, and I'm just making this up.
It's not really important.
We'll probably have a lot more opinions about this sort of thing.
You know, maybe use room based camera as well, that seems like the
kind of things, ground chunk outlines maybe.
Well, I don't know, maybe not that you can sort of see,
We might start to put these into groups, right?
There's ground checkout lines ground, chuck checkerboards, we've got
recompute ground chunks, that sort of starts to look like, you know, a
group of things that are based on crouch-jump things.
So, maybe we say, okay, this is a group.
It's called the ground chunks group, right?
And then here's particles, right?
And so maybe we have another group that's like particles.
You know, and then here, I've got some things that are like rendering
related.
and so maybe this is just called renderer
and this is may be called camera.
You space outlines is probably actually something that's more in out
in Sim for the moment and debug and variables group.
And you can see how now we're starting to break it up a little bit.
And so now we have some places that these things can go.
And now instead of looking at, you know, all of these options
together.
You know, if you're looking for something that affects the camera, you
would just click on camera first and then you would be able to get
down to, you know, the things that are affecting the camera or
something like this, right?
And then, similarly here, maybe we just don't know what these are.
So they're on categorize for now and they just go at the end.
I have no idea.
Again, we can sort of just make this up as we go.
Along and similarly, you know we might want to do something.
You know, I don't think this is necessarily how we would want to
organize it, but I just, you know, would sort of say we could sort of
do something like this.
Just so we can test the ability to have our groups be a little bit
more nested because we may want that in a future.
You know, I'm kind of conceptualizing
Is being able to fit a lot.
I'm going to want a lot of debug options so I would like to make sure
that it's not just one level of hierarchy.
We can have as many layers of the hierarchy going down as we want.
So that's you know, what?
I would like to do there.
And similarly I think this debug UI thing is fine and all, but it's
kind of annoying to always have it there.
So I think what I would rather do is probably do something like this,
right?
So this way, we don't have to say, debug you, I ever we just say it
like that and that way when we get the actual names of the things in
there,
You know, they're kind of a little bit more straightforward, or
readable or whatever, right?
Two ways to do that, right.
That's one way we could do.
It seems like a pretty good way.
I don't actually know, but that just seems like probably the most
reasonable thing but yeah, you know, maybe the better way to do it
would be to actually just put a second string after it.
That's different.
I don't know, we'll see how we like it.
It's not hard at this stage to change it, but before we add two,
These guys, before we have 200 of them we'd probably want to make sure
we kind of know, right?
So yeah, I'll put in these as a since we put those two dudes in there,
we'll leave those there.
I'm going to go ahead and make this kind of a local macro
You know, so it's only in there because it's the only place that
people really should be ever using that macro.
And so that is what I want to implement.
And so we've got begin variable group.
You got an enviable group.
And we have an add variable, the moment that's all we have.
And the add variable that takes the name of the variable and it takes
the value of the variable at the moment.
And in the future, I think one of the things about that is we're not
going to be when higher 100% certain, which kind of variable each, one
of these things is just by its type.
So we won't necessarily know if something's a Bool or
In it whereas we would probably know it's a floating point value or
not right because that's a little bit clearer potentially but that
again that's just something kind of to to keep in mind.
So yeah so we'll take it but for now we only have billions so we'll
kind of look at that will let that kind of come out as it as it comes.
We won't we won't try to do anything weird with that the moment but
here we go.
Okay, so the other thing that I'm going to want isn't
Going to want a little context thing here.
So that stuff can be you know, recorded a little more cleanly.
So inside debug create variable and all those sorts of things were
going to want the debug State.
I feel like you know, for these things and the debug state
Probably I maybe even want a little bit more so I probably want like a
debug variable definition context kind of a thing that's going to wrap
up my my debug state memory Arena.
Which is what I'm gonna need to implement it.
And then probably also something here like the, you know, debug
variable group or whatever, right.
I'm going to need to know that as these groups get sort of pushed and
popped.
That's something that I'm going to have to sort of be aware of, right.
And similarly, as they get pushed and popped, you know, we're lots of
create like some structure to store it.
So I'm just kind of like hypothetically saying I'm gonna need that
there so I don't know yet exactly what that will be, but it's kind of
obvious.
It's going to have to happen.
So anyway,
Here is the group name, right?
And the context this one, I guess.
We'll just again to take that context straight up.
And this would also take the context like so.
So we call into those and inside here, we know that we could always,
you know, pass that context like this and similarly, these guys could
always pass the context like this.
Oops.
Well, and that's starting to look, okay, right?
That's starting to look like it's basically got everything that it
needs.
Should be pretty easy to implement.
And that's that's yeah, that's about it.
So let's take a look at what it would take to implement something like
this again so that we can basically build the data structure which we
will then draw.
So what we would need here is we have the concept of a debug variable
defined right here.
You can see we've got like a type for it and we've got the debug
variable itself, that's all there.
So what we would want to do now is say that there's some way of
holding this
Things, right?
And so that would be where we would get this notion like of a debug
variable group, you know?
And the debug variable group would presumably have something like, I
don't know, whatever it's children are, you know, something like this
so I'm not really sure exactly what that did is structure should be.
But, I mean, I know that it has to hold more groups because like say I
could I already said I want multiple levels of hierarchy so I know I'm
going to have like a group and then each group
you can have multiple groups inside it.
I know that's going to happen and obviously I know it's going to have
a name, but then I also am going to have some kind of a situation.
Where I would have, you know, variables themselves, right?
So a debug variable, I guess, I would say is probably not the right
thing here.
Probably we're going to have is like, a debug variable group.
Maybe we'll just call this a debug group and a debug group member.
and a debug group member right, could either be a variable
Or something like this or, you know, maybe it could in addition to
being a variable, be another group.
And in fact, I guess there's not really much reason because debug
variables not really used in any other sense, so it could be that
maybe debug variable itself is is really just we could just use it.
Because I mean, like I said as debug code, there's really not that
much point in having it be any fancier than that.
We could just do something like this.
Right.
We're now we have a set of things.
Does things go in a group?
And then we can just say that it's always a debug variable group.
And sometimes a variable is just, some kind of a group itself.
It's seems like a totally fine thing.
So if we were to do that,
then I guess what we would need to do is say all right the names and
stuff like that are going to be in sort of these debug variables and
that's all fine.
But we need some way of maybe like chaining these things together so
that we can iterate over them or you know, who knows other things like
that.
And so if we were going to do that I guess the easiest way to do that
would be to say like every debug variable probably has like an
exporter in it so that we can kind of run through it.
And you know, we could have a child pointer to fit, you know, first
child or something like that in
Of a group that sort of thing for now, that seems like a pretty easy
way to go, right?
And so this v32 would actually be like the Boolean, right?
Or will 52.
And so, then this this would be if it's a group that's what it would
have.
Now, the group probably will want more information than that because
now, you know, if it's a hierarchical list group view or something
like that, then obviously like a debug variable group.
Artistry.
But debug group is now something that kind of exists inside here
because we're saying that these can be grouped.
So there's our debug group like that.
It's going to have a pointer to the first child.
But it would probably also it again just like saying I'm
hypothetically saying, it might also have a thing like, did you expand
it?
Because like, if it, you know, if the UI allows expanding and
collapsing these groups, then there's probably a notion of what's at
stake right now.
You know what I mean?
So, that's just an example of how, this sort of thing might go.
And if I want to build that, right?
That's just like, right, I wrote the code here.
This is the code.
I want to have happen.
I know that I need to get it into something.
This is the
Simple something I could see storing that thing.
And so now, I'm just going to, like, type in the code that translates
that to that, right?
That translates this into that.
So in order to begin a variable group, obviously I'm going to have to
push on to my Arena.
I'm going to have to push one of these things.
I'm always pushing a
But variable on there.
And, you know, because I'm always going to be pushing A debug variable
no matter what kind of variable I do, I think I probably want to do
something where that debug variable push
Or just you know debug add variable R, it adds a generic variable like
this is probably going to be sort of a root function.
I'm going to pass it.
Whatever the name is I'm going to pass it, whatever the type is and I
everybody's going to call through this right because I know that
everybody whether you're making a group or making a Boolean or making
any of the other floating Point whatever kind of values we may want to
have in the future, we know that you're going to call through this
right?
And so we want to do is have it so that you know you
You get too far out of the Arena, you initialize the values that we
know that all of them have you know I'm saying.
And then you go ahead and return that thing.
So then here we've got our our group in this case and so in order to
make the resulting group,
All we have to do there, I guess we'll call it group.
Oh, and you know what?
I just realized to when we do this, add this debug a variable that
should presumably add it to the group.
I'm also I'm going to do a little thing here.
If we only have a pointer to the first child then one of the things
that's very difficult.
If you have a singly linked list is you if you want your variables to
go in order which I do, I want them to kind of be in order.
We would have to reverse the order of them
Are because they're going to get pushed on like the the last person
who gets added to the list would be the first person who shows up in
the list because you always are adding them at the head end, right?
And since I would rather have it go.
The other way, I want a store.
I think, even though it's a singly linked list, I'm going to store the
first and last pointer because it's really pretty trivial to do that.
And then it means that, as I add, it will add, I can add at the end,
which is what I want.
You know.
All right, so if I do debug add variable then implicitly, what we want
to say is, in that case, is that when we add, we always add to
whatever the group is that we're working on right now, right?
So, whatever, the open group actually is that is the group to, which
this variable is, is added.
And so, we're going to say something like, you know, after we create
this variable, we now need to add it to the group.
So we're going to say, debug variable group equals context group,
If that group is a valid pointer meaning, if there is any open group
at all because maybe the very first one we add there, be no open
group, for example, not crowned, that's good.
Then what we want to do is say that group, it's got two cases, you
know, with a linked list, one case we have where there is something in
the list, right?
And another cases where there isn't something in the list.
So if there's nothing in a list, it's really trivial.
To add something to the list as you might expect.
Because in this case, all you have is the variable that all you have
is the variable.
The variable is the only thing that exists as we all know, it is the
everything.
So, basically going to just have a next pointer of zero, which would
be like the default thing.
Anyway,
you know, I like put that up above the union.
So you know, you've got an exporter of 0 and you've just got a list
that consists of nothing other than the very first person in the list.
That's the first and last person.
But assuming that there is something in the list, then what we would
want to do is make the last child, become the variable, right?
And the variables next pointer should point to the last child.
Because, oh, sorry, that's not true.
And the last child's next pointer should point to the variable, right?
So whoever was last is not last anymore.
We are last and we point to them.
And the last child is now up, we're moving that pointer forward to us,
so we're just changing out of the end and the way that I like to write
this to make it symmetric, I think it's kind of fun is to make it.
This is one of those like stupid programmer things.
I often like to write this this way for maximum pointless.
Tree.
I like to make it look like this.
It's just kind of pleasant.
You know, wouldn't you say?
I feel like it's true.
I don't know.
I don't know why.
You know, you can.
You can get even more ridiculous with it, if you want to, but, but I
feel like that's just kind of a pleasant kind of a pleasant way to do
it.
So there we go.
Now that we're all chained up, so we can just add variables all day
long and they'll come into a nice hard core structure.
And so, we have to do one of the thing.
I don't know like that there's any reason to do this.
I don't know that we really need it but it does mean that it would
simplify our sort of begin, very dependent variable group stuff.
So I'm just gonna stick it in there because again these are debug
variables we can literally compile the completely out if we want to.
So we really just don't care how much memory they take as long as
they're, you know, flexible and do what we need them to do.
We're totally fine.
And so in this case, it's really, really simple.
Right?
Yeah, so that's it.
In order to begin a group.
All we would do is we again, call add variable, we'd say that we want
it to make for us, one of these group types and there's the name of it
that would give us the group and we don't really have to do anything
with the group structure per se, other than initialize its variable.
So we'll assume that all groups start unexpanded for now.
We'll assume that their first child and their last child's are.
No, there's nothing in them.
Right.
And then by default when you begin a variable group,
Sleeve that becomes the new group, right?
But everything will be added in if you go to add a bully, mmm.
Then that's again, pretty simple.
We're just calling the exact same thing.
Again, we're adding a variable here.
Right, we're taking the context.
We're taking this type.
Oops.
And we're taking the name.
We are then going to set that variables Boule 32 value to the value
and that's it.
When we end a group what we will do is say that the context Group
which is was the current group, we will simply assert that it is not
equal to 0 because you can't end a group if there wasn't a group and
then we'll set the new group to be, whatever that groups parent was
because we're basically popping the group at that point, right?
so that
Is actually the entirety of the code necessary to create the entire
hard core structure of our debug system, right?
I mean, it's like, you know, it's like 30 lines of code or something
very, very, very simple.
And that's really all.
I think that we will need now, the debug variable definition context,
we need to create in order to get the process started, but that's
really all.
There is so here's our context, right?
We can go ahead and set the variables of the context there.
We can set the variables of them.
We've got the state, we've got the arena.
And so, I guess debug create variables would probably do something
like this, right?
Yeah.
And so, what we want to do for our very first group is that probably
just wants to call begin group, right?
So we're going to start with like a route group.
If that makes sense, we'll call it the route group because it just
makes our lives a little easier.
Because at some level if we just have a situation where we've got
All of this stuff set up for hierarchical things.
We might, as well as make the root of it.
Be go through the whole path that we have, right?
There's no real reason why we wouldn't do that.
It just seems like the obvious thing to do just saves a lot of typing.
So that's, that's it.
So in order to do these here, when we with this Arena, what I'd like
to do is I guess, say that, why do I keep wanting to do that?
There we go.
I just, I just say that we've got the debugger Arena.
So, whatever that is
Rena is right.
That's the one that we would use.
Like that and I think that's basically it.
So now inside a ham idea.
Bug when we are initialized when
Initially when we make our initial attempts to make the arena there,
immediately after that, I think would be fine time to create the
stuff, right?
So there's debug state.
And my my forget where we include this guy, to be honest with you, I
do okay.
There it is.
So if this is where this gets included, I'm not sure why and the debug
variable group was not it's because I called it debug group.
Which was not the name that we said, it was going to be, do I use
which one did I end up using?
So I never use that.
So let's try that again.
Let's just call it that instead.
Yeah.
So in this case, we don't really want to start doing very well group
pointers because basically everything is a debug variable anyway, so
that seems fine in this case when we have groups, we really want to
talk about group dot, you know, the actual group part of that since
it's in a union, right, which is pretty easy.
Again, same thing here.
So this is just basic cleaning up, compile errors, nothing
particularly going on.
Interesting here, pretty straightforward.
So when we return
These guys, we're gonna have to actually say what we made so that
people can edit them.
That's probably a good idea just in general because we may want people
to call in to Big special variables at some point or things like this.
So you might as well just get in the habit of returning, those things
out of the functions, easy enough.
And what is the problem that was supposed to be a semicolon?
But wasn't
and that was an errant quote, their real group that should have one on
either side.
And our debug variable index loop loop things here when we do our
right hand made config, now we will have to Traverse this thing as a
hierarchy and write it out.
So this is actually perfect because we have about eight minutes left
on the stream.
This will give us a perfect test of our construction code to see
whether or not it worked, right?
So let's go ahead and do that.
All we need to do to complete our
Structure is to have a way to get it right in order to get it.
All we need to do is say that well in here we just need to have some
way of getting to the debug variable.
That's like our route group, right?
Whatever our route group is that is the thing that will iterate over
so, well,
Assume that the route group has been set because this is the thing
that sets it and in fact, I guess what I can do here as well, is just
kind of say like, oh, hey, debug create variables, that will just
return, whatever that route is, right?
So that we can store it on the other side.
And so if we do that,
Well, you know, I don't even know if we want to return it because
maybe we'll set multiple things.
So, so let's not going to say that, let's just say that.
At the end of this, what it does is it takes the state and it sets
that route group equal to the context group.
So, it just, it writes it into the debug State itself.
Whoops,
Alright, so now we are in the position to Loop over it just fine.
And again this is just going to be a recursive sort of thing.
So all we have to do here is just say right hand made config recursive
and what that will do is it will just go ahead and sort of do this
exact process actually.
I guess I should make supper one of these something like that.
Right.
I guess you know what?
Since we have parent pointers I suppose I don't even really need to
make it be recursive, do I?
Let's try doing that recursive, why not?
So, if I wanted to, I can start with the root group, write debug
variable, you know, far.
And I can say, okay, we know that this is the route group
So the first thing we would do is we'd go to its first child
naturally.
And then we're going to iterate over that until we get to the last
one, right?
So while we still have our off, we will go and we would want to write
this out, right?
So we'd go ahead on while VAR and this, by the way, we're going to
have to deal with in a bit anyway.
Okay.
So you need a giant buffer here
We'll probably want to allocate that but that's not our problem for
the moment.
So what we would do is while we have a variable we will write out the
variable that were on and then we just need a way of getting to the
next variable, right?
So we would say okay the next thing we're going to write out
Is going to be dependent on what this thing was, right?
So what I'll say first is I'll say if the variables type
was a group.
Then I know that the we have to descend the level, the next thing I
want to write out is going to be like it's child or something, right?
So I want to do something like the next guy is going to be the vark
group first child.
So that's what I do next, right?
If it's not a group,
then I
Next pointer to be whatever it actually is, right.
So, whatever comes after
This guy if the guy alright up next.
However if there isn't one so if there's if there's nothing down there
so I got into the end of this list.
Then what I want to do is say okay if there wasn't anybody next then
go up one level of the tree, right?
So go you know the next pointer is going to be equal to the VAR parent
which I've gone up, one level.
And remember, I've already written out the parent.
Presumably
So at that point, I would want to advance one on the parent as well.
Right?
And presumably, yeah, I need to do this in sort of a while loop
fashion, right?
I need to sort of do it like this.
I need to say, while, you know, because I may have to pop up multiple
times, right?
So it's probably more like this.
the first thing would be to say, alright, let's start with
Something like this.
So I'd say start with the one we're on, while it's not valid, I'm
sorry while while I guess just I might even do a forever one here.
So like, just keep going and I'll have the break Criterion here, like
something like this, right?
So what I would do now is say, Okay, first try to go to the next one,
you know, if the next one is valid, you print that?
Because that's that's the guy we're going to go.
So break out a break out of here.
Continue the loop, you know, and so just leave our equals next.
End up, in fact, I guess, since we want varda be it.
At this point, I suppose, I could just do this all with vars.
Well, right.
So I could just make this all be with VAR, I don't even know that I
really need this next thing.
In fact, do I need that at all?
I don't think I do.
So I suppose it's just this I don't even know why I introduced that
variable.
Maybe there was a reason for it.
Not sure what it was.
So I think I want something else like this.
So I go to the next one.
If there is a next one, right?
So I just do it.
That's why I introduced it because of that milnes, but that was just
stupid.
I can just say if there is a next one, go to the next one.
That's much cleaner, right?
So if there is a next one, go to the next one.
If there isn't a next one, then I go to the parent, right?
I just say like, okay, you know, VAR VAR equals of our parent.
So I've gone up one
And then I guess this does actually become a while VAR and I'm, maybe
we're done.
Does that seem reasonable?
Right?
So I come in here, I say assuming of our is not null which I know it
isn't the first time through.
But I then say, okay, if there is a next one, we go to the next one
and we're done we print that one out.
You know, we Advanced up in that one, if there isn't the next one.
We go up to the parent and then we go backs up a loop.
If there isn't a parent, then we're by definition going to follow this
Loop and be done.
And we're going to fall out of this loop as well, right?
If there was a parent, then we're going to see if it has an X pointer.
If it did we advance to it and break out if it didn't go up to the
Down.
Don't know if it'll work seems reasonable.
All right, so that
Is about about all there is to that, right?
So, let's see what else we got here.
Okay, so values.
However, debug variable, that's true.
We're going to do, boo 32 here.
So we'll just do something like this.
Oops.
We'll do that and then we'll see here.
We're just going to turn off.
Let's turn off this menu.
That'll be our job for tomorrow.
There we go.
And now what I'd like to see is I'm just going to go ahead and call
right hand made config directly so that we can see what it actually
does.
So I'm going to again, set a breakpoint and we're just about out of
time.
Oops.
Hello.
There we go.
At right.
Hand made Peg.
Run it.
And I don't care about push that map.
So let's see what we get.
So we start off on on our group here, and I'm going to also take a
look as we're doing this.
I'm going to take a look at the string as well, right?
This is the string right here.
That we're actually trying to that we're actually sort of
accumulating.
So we come in here and the first thing is a group, so it doesn't print
anything out because we don't have anything for a group.
So we see that it's a group, we descend one child that.
Here we are on ground chunk outlines.
We then see that this is a Boolean so we printed out there it is very
good.
We then go to see that there is a next and so we go to the next one
and we print that out as well.
So now we've got two things in their ground checkout lines and ground.
Chunk, we go to the next variable.
Able there is an X variable so we print that out.
Let's see what that looks like.
Again, we've got the third one there.
That's exactly as intended unfortunate.
There isn't a next pointer there.
So now we Ascend one up and we try to go to the next one, on the
parents level.
We do get to the next one on the parents level, which is another group
we fall through here.
We see if, you know, if this is a printable thing, it's not a
printable thing.
So we go ahead and look at the the type.
It's a group.
So we descend down to the first child of that group and we see that
it's a Boolean we printed out blah blah blah blah blah, right we get
to the end.
We write out the file and let's take a look at the file that we wrote
out to see how it looks.
Looks perfect.
Everything is good.
Unfortunately, we did forget one thing, which is that, for whatever
reason, I totally spaced when we did this, and when we put the names
in there, obviously, we're going to want to reinsert debug UI in front
of it, because we've sort of stripped that out from our concept of the
names.
So I should probably go ahead and make it so that when we actually do
right?
The handmade config, which I'll go ahead and do now.
We re insert that, right?
So it's actually going to look like that.
Since we know our names are now for pretty printing.
They don't have the that particular thing in front of them.
Right?
Yeah.
And so that's right.
Yeah that's going to be that's going to complain but otherwise I think
we're all good again, really simple stuff.
Nothing too unusual but we've totally gotten now are because all of
our stuff organized in a much nicer fashion that we can.
Tough with.
All right, so let's skip ahead.
To after it's written.
All good.
And so now we are good to go.
I will pull this guy out.
From handmade debug.
And then we will go to the Q&A.
So yeah, you can kind of see here to kind of mention as an aside.
Just want to get rid of that.
You can kind of see what I did here on the handmade configure right
out.
So you know we could have done this recursively but it was just so
easy to write it in order that way you don't use a stack because you
know, when you're going to Traverse a tree
You need a stack to reverse a tree.
If the stack itself, doesn't have pointers back up the chain, right?
But the way that I chose to do this just because it was debug code in
there.
Wasn't any real reason not to use the space.
We have these parent pointers so we can always just walk without using
any storage.
We can always just walk through just knowing whoever we're on because
whenever we get to the end of something in there we just chased those
parent pointers back up and then know that we continue traversing that
Way.
So it just makes it, you know, pretty easy to do that.
Okay, so that's all there is for today tomorrow we will start writing
some code to print it out that way and allow ourselves to expand and
collapse our list but that's pretty good.
I think we're all set and yeah that puts us in a good position for
tomorrow with that I will go to the question and answers if you have a
About what we've done, please post it now with a q: in front of it so
that I can see it and hopefully answer answer it.
K.
Can we make it an option to toggle between optimized and debug builds
from the debug menu?
Not at the immediate moment because at the immediate moment, we don't
rewrite the build script at all, but yes, it would be easy for us to
do that.
We would just have to say well there's two ways we could do it either
a we switch back to doing single translation unit with pragma optimize
off, which I think is probably what we want to do.
Now that we know that
The reason it wasn't working before was because we have to also
include the pragma optimize stuff around inline functions.
So we could try that again.
That's probably the right thing to do and then at that point all we
would do is put debug brackets around the pragma optimize offs so that
if we turn off that Define it would it would run the code optimized so
that's probably the way we should do it.
But the other way we could do it without changing, how we're doing it
optimizations right now?
If we could just have a build include file essentially which just set
some environment variables and then we would write
That out in there.
And it one of the things that would set is like additional
command-line switches and those would either be - oh dear - 02, right?
So yeah.
So that's what I think we should probably change to the other.
I think we should probably switch to using the single translation unit
build again because that would be better for a number of reasons.
Let's see, can you run the tool to see how many lines of code we have?
Yes, I can.
Lock in the code.
13,000.
I guess.
Wouldn't it be pretty?
You're visually in our config files to be to be indented, according to
their group depth, that way, we know which variables belong to which
group IE variables.
In the route group, don't have any annotation group Death.
One will have a single level invitation.
I don't know that we care because I don't think we will ever use.
not like I don't will look like the game writes this so I don't know
that we
Will ever read it but if you want to obviously it's really trivial
right?
You just say the depth is zero or whatever right.
And each time you do this, you increment the depth and each time you
do this you decrement the depth
you know, and then in here you just do right like
Just really, really basic or indent indent less than depth.
toughest Indian and, you know,
Well, you don't have to do that.
You just do this.
Write something like that.
I guess I got a call this from somewhere so you can see if it worked.
But it would, it would ya.
Yeah.
Something like this.
I mean the other thing you'd probably want to do, I'm just guessing if
this is your if this is your jam like you're like I like I need this
in my life.
This is what makes me feel whole inside and and all that sort of thing
you would probably cuz we don't print out groups in there you know you
would probably want to add those as comments, right?
So you'd probably want to add something like you know,
You know, you'd be doing this, this sort of action, oops.
right, which we need to do anyway and so when you encountered a group,
you would also
Say what that group was.
So you do a thing where you were like oh yeah you know just say what
the group name is a comment.
Something like this.
and then when you ran it,
it would insert lines for groups even though they don't need to be
defined just so you can see where they are if that makes sense.
So it's a little, it's a little wonky because you might want to
control whether you print an indent or not based on whether anyone's
going to actually be doing it.
And so you kind of get in this weird situation where you're like okay
do I print it intent?
Don't I print it indent but you assume that if everyone
One always print something out, you know you would do you would do it
that way.
probably as well so that you can, you know,
have camera be indented.
You might also want this sort of thing, I guess.
So that it's a little easier to read your indents.
Right.
but that's
yeah.
Someone has posted a link to the forums.
Why?
Why have you posted a link to the forums?
But you have not told me what I, why am I going there?
I see.
So this is requests for changes.
All right, maybe we can do those because we've got some time to look
at questions for us but we could do some of those changes for people
who want to run on Linux.
Let me let me just go ahead and make sure that we take out the call to
this though.
I don't want to leave that in really
Do you have any add-ons that you are using with Emax?
Is it something like space?
Max, no II.
There are no e add-ons.
It's just vanilla emacs.
Off topic question, are you using your razor on stream?
Know my razor blade Pro laptop.
I'm not using it at the moment.
And my it's my it's my you know I use it for Dev so it's not here.
And this is my old Dusky board.
Three my Razor keyboard is actually it's plugged into the Razer Blade
laptop at the moment.
Just see gr not running the game today.
We were running the game.
We were on the games being a stream.
K was the intro.
Talk about him made con include as part of the main area of the
stream.
Yes, it is in them, it's in the recording, it will be in the YouTube
archive.
Switching between Dragon optimized mode, would not need a restart of
the whole game.
Nope, I probably wouldn't
I can't really think of any reason why it would
Like, off the top of my head.
A slim serious Zimmer Torre can we sometimes see you play a game on
Twitch just like John does just to chill out.
Stream would love to hear a pin on a different games.
You can there's this channel senior ettore.
I don't really have typically a ton of time to do it but I do do it
occasionally and I put the archival thing on.
So
what about a handmade certification for games?
A badge of honor could be placed in a splash screen or in the credits,
please use certifications.
Each of the Australian made could be organized the conference.
So I think that's that's not really something that I'm super
interested in.
I mean like I'm interested in people being excited about doing
handmade Dev stuff, the way that we do it, like I mention people
caring about code and caring about how their code works, but I don't
necessarily know that they need to have some kind of a certification,
you know.
So I don't know.
I mean, if other people did that, that's fine.
But I'm not, that's probably not something that I would do.
Because the important part is that people care about it and it's not
so much.
I don't even know what the certification process would be.
Like, what would you certify?
You know, because you have to have some way of saying, what you were
what were you even trying to certify?
That the programmer was interested in how their code came out, you
know?
I mean, how do you, how do you certify that?
Just have them say, they did, you know?
It's something really sure.
Piracy 9k.
Thanks to you.
I was able to implement Dynamic code reloading for my project to
saving me a time, that is awesome to hear.
Wait, there is an a Sir John has commented.
Why did I not see it?
They say right here.
Why do I have to stream?
I paid the micropayment.
I don't know, man.
Did you get did you buy enough coins to like to purchase the Stream?
Because it's like 100 coins.
You can get a gem and for every gem that you get, you have a chance of
being able to watch the stream.
And if you get like, at least eight gems of different colors, then you
are guaranteed to be able to watch the stream for a little while
anyway.
All right, so I'm going to somebody posted a link to the thing about
Linux stuff so I'm going to see if we can do that.
So here's what it says on the forums, these are people who ported the
game to Linux already.
SEL handmade doesn't does sorry SEO.
Handmade does run on Linux and OS X but require some small changes to
Casey's code.
We're looking for volunteers to bring these issues to Casey attention
during the stream currently.
The following methods need to be implemented in handmade platform.sh.
And so basically what they're doing is they're just sending in what
the things are that need to be implemented in order for the code to
Out on Linux because like I said, we wrote all the code to be basic
cross-platform.
So for the most part you can just compile it but there's a few
platform specific things we have to call in our code that need to
happen.
And so specifically like these atomics, for example, these atomics are
things that we need in to implement per platform because they're
different and so it looks like these have been posted.
So let's take a look here.
I'm going to go ahead and
I'm going to Ted I'm going to assume I guess that Atomic compare
exchange 2013 2 is correct.
So that these are the only ones like you see, we have not implemented
them yet because we don't compile on the next, but other people do.
So, try to be nice.
So it looks like what they've got here is that the code for this, just
requires us calling sink, lock test and set with just the value and
new.
That's it.
No casting necessary.
Atomic, add is sync, Fetch and add the value.
And the a dent and then the get thread, ID is, I guess different,
depending on, which platform you're compiling it for, even though it's
under llvm, it is not always the same, I guess.
So, the way this works is there's a thread ID, if defined Apple
LF find.
I 36.
Alif defined.
X86 64.
Else error unsupported architecture.
Okay.
And in order to get that thread ID on the Apple model, they say, you
have to do this.
That's some stuff right there.
Lovely.
So I guess you have to move this.
So the thread ID on Apple is the is right at the base of the GS
segment so you're just going to straight up grab that in.
Like so this is inline assembly, gasps, gasps style going to assembler
style which is some crazy stuff right there.
It's basically outputting one of those mob instructions, like we see,
and that's the GS segment and it's going to put the result in thread
ID.
This this % 0 here is kind of like printf.
It's saying take the this variable from the actual function and the
assembly that I want to admit will store this part of the GS.
Here.
And the crazy part about good new assembler.
Is it goes the other way round from Intel assembler.
So, although, you know, if you remember on stream, we always use.
See, like, when we go to the disassembly, we look at a move
instruction, the destination comes first in the source, comes second,
well in good new assemblers backwards.
So basically the source comes first, the destination comes s.
So this actually, even though it looks like it's moving in.
Did you guys actually moving out of GS which can wreak havoc on porous
and of a programmers, if you're used to it?
Got to like reverse.
All your thinking just kind of crazy.
Okay, so it looks like again, same exact thing on on i386 and on
Linux, they're all actually the same, it's just which segment and
we're uses dessert.
Just because of the calling Convention of the operating system, where
it ends up storing that particular piece of information.
But there you go.
Okay.
So that we have now done, what was requested of that and now we also
need casting for one thing
and Martin's Mosaic, oh, was also suggesting that the if defined Apple
Should actually be an if defined Apple.
I think and defined x86 64.
Because otherwise, apparently that will trigger on the iOS which is
not the correct, you don't want that to happen.
So you want it to hit an unsupported architecture are at that point.
M SV, C, 2013, as SM printing function, that is almost like sprintf.
So, instead of using ugly sprintf function, we could use this.
And then you sprintf in all places, then no one will have issues on
OS, X, Linux or even among wind W, also add security to deprecate
argument for cl to not generate dedication warning.
So they're basically saying SN printf would be better than the one we
were using and that does seem totally fine to me if we wanted to again
we're going to get
To that we're going to get rid of the C runtime Library entirely.
So would be fine for now.
If we use SN printf,
I guess.
Does that actually work?
Well, we'd have to actually pound include something, I guess for it to
work, but not sure what that would be, because doesn't look like it's
in here.
So I'm not sure about that.
We're going to leave that for now.
So we should probably also just remove that dependency soon so that it
doesn't bother anyone else.
So the last thing, they were saying in order to get us compiling
correctly, on Windows Linux and Mac, as well.
For people who are trying to do, those builds was that time function.
Needs to cast the function name.
That's what they were saying.
Oh, it's a Castaway, the concert there, but that sounds like it.
So I think we're good to go.
Stephen last does the idea for having your compile switch variable
switch speed cake involve compiling code out with is 0?
Yes it does.
It's pretty straightforward.
If you think it through I'm not going to do anything too weird.
But it's just like
Was the natural sort of thing that you would think to do.
So I was going to try it.
Naysayer.
88.
Why don't you use Lou?
Are you dumb?
So the reason that we don't use luau on the stream right now is
actually it's totally that obviously all games should be written
entirely in Lua because that way it's like really hard to debug and
it's slow and that's what you want, you know, ideally in a game.
As you want it to be both slow and partridges.
Ugh.
Because that really helps your productivity and also if possible you
want your language to not have a lot of features in it.
So you want to be like it'd be like hard to program in that language
and Lou also does that as well.
So we were pretty much gets the three points that you want, for
writing gaming.
So ideally, we'd write the whole game and Lula.
The only reason I didn't do that is because I was too dumb to get it
working.
So we tried to get it working and then just failed.
And we just gave up because we're like, we're way too dumb for this,
there's no way.
We're going to do it, but yes, smart people would just write the whole
game in Lua.
Registeration.
How do you handle multi-threading?
We have a bunch of you can go back and watch the episodes where we
Implement multi-threading, it's pretty simple.
We don't we don't do anything too crazy.
Run code use fight.
You've inspired me to forget about my years of commercial experience
writing RM.
Dewey's and to go Implement, I am doing for my game.
I love coding again.
Well, that's really good to hear.
I'm very happy to hear that.
K.
Someone asked a question about push truck on that day so I'm guessing
Casey might have introduced it.
Then okay.
I think that was just an answer to this question in sohbat.
That's out of the question UD handmade here.
How long have you been making games?
Well I mostly am.
I work on game Tech?
I don't really make games per se so most of my experiences just is
unproven game Tech stuff and that I've been doing for I guess
professionally 20 years.
A Nexus.
Why check unmatched parentheses in LF in thread ID extraction?
Where are you?
There we go.
Thank you.
Okay, there we go.
Cuba.
Caleb.
What registration do you streaming your development motivated?
You to do more or more consistently?
No, not really.
I'm only assuming the development for educational purposes.
I still work full-time on a different game during the day.
So this is, this is strictly for teaching is the reason that I'm
streaming this, it's not because it's not for any other reason.
Did you use SM printer for sprintf?
The defined thing, change SS, printf 2sn, printf,
Not sure what you mean.
SN printf did not seem to be available to us.
Right.
So it looks like we could use underscore S printf.
I don't know if that helps anyone else though.
I'm going to I'm just going to not deal with that right now, to be
honest, because I think we should just go ahead and replace that and
we can do that.
Maybe we'll do that next week.
It's not very much work.
Do you use any type of documentation or design for this project?
What types of documents have you produced planning to produce for this
project?
I guess I would say I don't really like using the term document to
refer to something game-related because it is often sounds like a
thing that I associate with really bad games.
So I have some notebooks that I used to plan things out in terms of
the game design stuff.
But I'm not really the type of person who's like going to make a
document.
I'm not a game designer so you know you that's really probably not my
Place to talk about, though.
All right, I think we've come to the end of the queue.
So I'm going to wrap it up, going to wrap it.
Up.
Close this.
Okay, thank you, everyone for joining me, for another episode of
handmade here.
It's been a pleasure working with you.
As always, if you would like to follow along at home, you can always
pre-order the game on handmade hero dot org.
If you preorder the game it comes to the source code.
You can always play around with it at home, learn from it and
experiment with it, which is a good way to go.
If you're trying to learn from the stream, we also have a patreon
page.
You can subscribe to you if you want to try and support the video
series, but
that is, of course, always appreciate in the video series is always
free.
Even if you don't we try to again, do things as Ultra, Ultra Stickley
as possible here.
So the video series is free and always will be.
And you can get it on the video archive, as well as on the Forum site,
where you can ask questions or view annotated episode guides that
people in the community.
You have made so you can go back and watch all the episodes and see
you like we're certain questions were asked or when I talked about a
certain topic that sort of thing.
It's really pretty awesome that's about it.
If you want to catch the show live will be back here again.
5 p.m.
Pacific Daylight time tomorrow same time.
Same place we will also if you if you're wondering when the streams
live in general we have a tweet bot, the tweets, the schedule you
which you can subscribe to you to get notifications or you can just
check it periodically to see when the shows going to be a post a full
schedule.
On the weekend or on Monday and then everyday it posts.
Reminder.
That just says, this is when the tree will be for this days, you can
always just go to the top post of the Tweet pot and it tells you, this
is what it seems to be.
So that's about it.
Hope to see you guys back here tomorrow, when we will Implement.
Now that we have a backing structure for our Haiku control will just
implement the hierarchy of control.
So that'll be pretty fun.
I think, and we'll be able to play with it so that'll be good.
Hope to see you here for that.
Until then have fun programming and I'll see you guys on the internet.
Take it easy.
One.