Start recording.
Hello everyone and welcome to handmade hero.
Sir.
We could a complete game live on Twitch.
Now we are at the precipice.
We are about to likes or off the precipice of having some good profile
inspection code so we can see where our time is being spent, I'm
fairly excited about it, we just barely got things working yesterday
stream but we had some bugs and we didn't have time to really look
into it.
At the end of last last night's dream.
So today I think will be the day that we finally get to see this
stuff.
Sort of come to fruition a little bit.
And we get to start working on some new stuff that I think will be a
lot of fun like putting in some interface stuff so that we can quickly
navigate around and like drill down on the / stuff and that's going to
be kind of fun.
That's sort of a new thing break from the actual debug data
collection, now that that's working properly.
So if we go ahead
Ed and get started on that.
I think there's not much to say about it.
It's just us to bugging our stuff from yesterday today, is they 186?
So if you unpacked a 185 source code into directory, that's what I'm
starting with.
So if you're, if you preorder the game, I had met here at org, that's
the source code that you want to work with now.
If I remember correctly, we sort of had some stuff drawing but it
wasn't correct.
So there was some, we knew there was some kind of problem with what we
had written but we didn't have any time to really
What was actually going on?
Like it was definitely not correct, but we weren't sure what was
incorrect about it.
And so like, for example on here you can kind of see, we've got sort
of the something that kind of starts to look like a correct series of
things, but then it rapidly Scrolls off.
And then we have, you know, essentially these should be all frames
that are being displayed in here.
Essentially, we've got just one, it looks like frame at the beginning
and then nothing else.
So, to me, that suggests that we've just got a bug in how we're
getting things into frames or something like this.
This and so that instead of having a full screens worth of frames were
not properly accounting for that and we're getting just like one
bucket with nothing in it or some weird situation is happening.
So we need to kind of dive in and figure out what's going on there.
So we can, we can figure out what's going wrong and solve it, right?
So let's go ahead and take a look at what we've got and and see what
the problem is.
So, let's just take a minute to refresh our memories, what's going on
here, and I'm
And I sort of take a look into the code.
So the way that we have things structured is we, you know, we maintain
sort of a little collation thing here.
Every frame we come through and we create a new sort of memory
scratchpad and we build up this information which is a a set of
frames.
That have in them up here.
Right with having them sort of the beginning and ending clock for that
frame.
And then a series of regions and the regions are essentially time
spans where something was happening.
So that's all we're trying to accomplish right now and we sort of
started to see that happening on the screen, but we should be seeing a
full screens worth of reach of frames with little colored regions and
we're not seeing that.
So the first question I have, you know, is is
is the debug frame stuff happening properly.
Are we actually seeing those debug frames?
Get getting built up properly.
And so what I'd like to do is take a look at that and find out what's
happening in there.
So there's a couple different things that I think could be happening
in there one way or the other.
So, the first thing that I was thinking is, well, you know, we have
potentially more debug frames, then we have event arrays, like I don't
actually know.
All that stuff is shaking out the moment.
So I'd like to do something where I just look at what the frame count
actually is.
So I want to just, you know, what, how many frames is it?
Think it got?
So, I'm going to just let this thing run a bit.
You can even see.
It's kind of, like, does this weird thing when it starts up or its
kind of sitting there, right?
And like these frames are not getting pushed off.
So these are like a presumably, the initial frames and then it looks
like once we hit a certain number, they start to scroll by right.
So it seems like the frames are kind of moving backwards way of their
expect.
So the weird part is that nothing seems to be moving in from the left
and from the right.
We should be seeing frames of data and instead we're just getting
nothing, it doesn't really make any sense.
And furthermore I don't know what that's doing there because how is
that thing?
Varying when we don't see those frames coming at and moving this way.
So I want to kind of start to
Can see, first of all, how many frames do we think we have and some
stuff like this?
I just want to get a feeling for what might be going wrong there.
Okay, so here we go.
Let's go ahead and and just stop basically right after that that
collation has happened.
I'm going to take a look at the debug State and here we go.
So we sit we think we have 63 frames and that seems
Like pretty much exactly the number.
I would have expected to see and if we take a look at those frames,
Well we can see you're kind of right off the bat with the problem is
we're really not getting any regions in there and I feel like that's
probably no matter what the case I don't feel like there should
probably only be two regions that seems really unusual.
And here we go.
We got two regions in one and then zeros in the rest.
So it seems pretty clear that we just have a pretty fundamental basic
In there because that just doesn't make any sense.
There's no way that could actually be what's happening.
I don't think with the data were collating.
So I'm going to go ahead and take a look.
We probably just have some kind of a basic problem with the way that
we're collating.
That's you know, Lille to yielding this problem.
So when we come through here, we are making sort of an array of frames
to store our frames and we're saying that we're just going to make
enough that we know that we won't overflow it.
We initialize all of our scale stuff and we decided not to play with
frame bar scale yet.
So we're just kind of setting that of the constant value so that won't
change as the as the graph progresses.
So then we come through our events and every time I guess, we go
through our
Ventura, you know, I should probably pre warm this up so that we're,
at the point where it's buggy, right?
Because we're getting some actual data here.
So that's actually looks kind of valid at the moment.
So let's let's let it kind of scroll off.
So that now that we know we're in a just known, totally bad position.
Now, let's kind of come through and see what happens there.
So, our Global debug table contains all of the data for the debugging,
right?
It contains all of the events that have been stored
Up.
So, if I take a look at the event count array, that is all of the
events that are happening here.
And you can see what the counts are.
The counts are massive.
There's there's plenty of events in there, so it seems unlikely that
we aren't getting at least a few top-level events everywhere.
And so looking at that it's like, okay it doesn't look like the
problem is that like we're not recording in any events because it
looks like
Definitely recording a ton of events, so that's fine.
So, if we grab out some of these events, here we can take a look at
how they're working.
We get frame marker.
as the very first thing,
That seems fine.
So we're going to assign a current frame to that.
And here it is.
We're then going to assign sort of like the clocks to it.
There's the beginning clock.
The end clock hasn't been recorded yet the region cast going to be 0
and it's going to have some kind of a nominal region count there.
now, we come through and we look
We are on frame 0.
We take a look at what the thread is that we're currently on.
That's thread 54 08.
That's the ID.
And what we should see in the debug state is now, there should be one
thread in the table of threads.
There it is, it's assigned Elaine index, which is what we want.
It remembers the ID.
It has no open block at the moment because that's exactly what we
would expect.
We take a look.
It's a begin block.
That's what we would think because you know it's the start of the
frame.
We're going to open up that
Block.
And of course, there isn't anything on the free store.
Because why would there be?
We have an allocated anything yet.
So we go ahead and allocate a new debug block.
We put which frame it's on here we take the opening event there and
And record it.
It's this one.
It's causing us to happen.
We remember what the parent block was, and then we set, which, of
course, is nothing.
Yet, we set it to be us from now on.
So anyone underneath us is going to be inside this block and then we,
you know, continue on.
And so now anyone under here, oh well, there's the end block.
So it looks like there was no timings inside that block.
In fact, you know, I wonder if we could even see if we could actually
see in there.
What the actual?
Well I guess we don't have a way.
I should have checked up here.
We could we could have seen who, which block was being opened.
But anyway, no big deal.
So we come through here and we say.
All right, we have a matching beginning and block that was.
What this does is ensures that that were matching when it matches we
see whether it's on the same frame.
It was we see whether or not the open block had a parent because we're
just taking the top level ones and we find that it did not.
So we just say
A.
Okay, let's record that into the current Lane for this thread and
using the sort of the clock base that we would expect.
So there's that begin clock of the frame.
We're just going to remember the timing of this relative to that begin
clock.
So we do that there and we say okay we're good to go.
Alright, so at that point now what we want to do is we want to mark
this block as being free.
So we go ahead and we dump it onto the the free list.
Is this, wait a minute.
What's going on here?
First open block next, free equals, debug State, first free.
Block, first open block.
Oh, that's just.
Because this is the thing, I probably should have used matching block
there.
That's a little, that's a little
Odd to look at.
But anyway, so we take whatever, the current free list is, we stick it
on to us, we then set whatever the free list head pointer is and we
set it pointing to us.
We then make sure that we move one up the parent.
So it should set the first open block for the thread to be equal to 0,
which it does and then we continue.
So now we're going to see, presumably another begin block.
There it is.
And of course, this debug block already has a.
There's already something on the free store.
So we just use the one that we'd already allocated, we set all of its
values.
So those all now get set properly, as far as I can tell, and let's
just double check that, I guess, do we have a good?
Have a good, debug block view here, you brought block
Smoothest a little bit.
So there it is set up so we set the parent equal to the parent, should
be, we cleared the next free and we set the two values to what they
should be.
So that's all good as well.
We can take a look at what opening event this is as well.
The The Source should be in here.
Do we ever grab the source?
We never grab the source unfortunately.
Oh well well here it is.
So this is input processing.
So again, exactly what we would think we would see.
So there we go.
Here we are for the end block for input processing.
And again, it works pretty much exactly as I would have expected it to
write.
And I don't again, I'm not seeing any, I'm not seeing any real
problems yet.
I'm not seeing anything.
Particularly odd Happening Here.
It looks pretty good.
So now let's see what happens.
When we get to something, I assume were going to get to the game first
that has children.
So let's see, game update.
So now this is going to have a bunch of children.
So this is the first time we're going to see a bunch of children here.
We create the open block and now we're going to probably see another
begin block right for the first time we're seeing that.
So what I'm going to do here is I'm just going to set a breakpoint for
the next time that we hit an end block and I'm also going to make sure
we don't see something like a frame marker before then just to make
sure
Things, you know, relatively kosher there.
So there we go.
We're hitting an end of block and presumably, that's going to line up,
right?
And it's going to remove it, it does and so that's fine.
We then come back around.
And now I'm going to check to see when the next time we hit.
One of these is right so the next time we close something that we're
actually going to record and again I'm going to I'm going to just set
a breakpoint to make sure up there that that we okay.
So
It looks like we have something bogus happening in terms of our block
pairing or something like this, right?
Because we should not have been able to get to the new frame without
having closed the game update.
The game update block.
Let me see win32 handmade.
because if you take a look at Hoops game update,
Well, big game timer block.
Can block.
Okay.
Ken Block in for processing.
Let's take a look at en Bloc, so we saw that one.
We've got begin block game update.
So then we've got en Bloc game update.
So we should have hit this and that should have closed out at the top
level.
It didn't, right?
We did not see that happen.
And so, what I'd like to do is I'd like to figure out some way of
stopping us at the point where that happened and so trying to think of
the best way to do that.
So inside the debug code, like I want to see what happened on that
frame where you know when we get to this what is the circumstance that
causes this to fail?
so, in order to do that inside here somewhere, when we, when we look
at this stuff,
I mean, one thing I could do right is I could I could complain here
about it I suppose.
Do we have any blocks?
I guess other threads we do.
So it's hard to say.
Traffic and how I want to approach this?
So On Any Given thread.
We're always looking at the first open, block, on the thread, so we
know that they closed in open and closed in order.
Mmm.
So I guess what I'd like to do is come in here and say well,
When we get to the end block event, I would like to know for this guy
here, I would like to know if it's this one, if it's, this particular,
end block event and so I know that the that game update will appear as
a string, right?
So what I could do is I could just just full-on, do some kind of a
string compare here where I just say if the source block name and this
equals zero, then that's the one I'm looking for, right?
Something like this which is just again, totally random.
I could just straight up do that.
Now, we haven't written a string compare.
We could use the one in C runtime library but they're so easy.
We might as well just write one ourselves again.
I don't know really, we don't have a utility function area yet but we
can just throw one in here there that simple, you know, it would be
something trivial.
Like, I just want, I want some way.
Of returning, you know, assigned difference value.
That's going to be positive or negative.
In fact, I guess I could even just do a Boolean one.
Now, so two strings are equal.
And just have a and I assume we haven't are done that things are
equal.
Maybe we have
We already did it, nevermind.
Never mind.
Strings are equal.
And if are not found, oh
Ha ha it was finding the one that I already wrote.
Okay.
So we didn't do it.
So, here we go.
We pass, we passed two things to our strings are equal.
We just want to know if these two things are the same or not and we're
going to return a value that's like true or false based on whether or
not they match, right?
So all I really need to do here is just do something like, you know,
why let a equal, you know, well star a plus plus equals star B plus
plus or something like this.
And we don't want to kind of go over so we probably want to do while
star a and star B and I and maybe I won't do that in here just to make
it a little clearer.
What's going on?
I'll put it inside, right?
So while everything is valid and the two things are equal, we can
advance one letter, you know, just a really very stupid string
compare.
So while we're not at the null Terminator of a, we're not at the null
Terminator of b and a equals B for the characters, whatever, the 22
will advance them by one character and then if at any time, these guys
are not equal to each other, it would stop the loop, the criteria for
Whether or not they were equal at the end should be that they both hit
their null Terminator, you know.
So the result is just going to be that star a equals star be you know
and star equals zero which is like you know, or I could you could
alternatively think if this way
If both of them are now pointing to null, then we've reached the end
of the string if they aren't then, you know, then we know there was a
difference.
So now I've got a string compare.
And I can do this.
So if strings are equal to, then we'll stop and I'll just put a thing
in here so I can set a breakpoint on it.
All right, so if we are to run it again,
off we go.
There we are.
And so as we sort of move, move forward, oh,
Well, that's particularly odd.
Access violation.
Writing location, zero.
So we out, we had more.
In that one than we normally do.
Which is a little weird.
I wonder why it doesn't really matter I suppose for now, but it's
weird that that didn't happen in previous runs.
You think we'd have roughly the same number or debug events.
So that was a little odd to say the least, but
No, big deal.
Not what I want to look at at the moment, say the least.
Okay, so this is kind of settled down to its bogus state.
So now, I want to kind of look at what is the reason why that this
game update never actually gets cleared.
So, this first time through we should be looking at the open block and
oh,
Oh wait, no.
Sorry that's the the end block.
Never mind.
Well let's try that one more time.
Alright so here we are on the end block for game.
Update.
Come through here.
What's in the thread?
Let's let's find out.
And so our thread, first open block, there it is.
So that's valid.
We then take a look at the stuff here, what the opening event was, and
let's take a look at these guys, so we've got the opening event.
And we've got our event.
Okay, so they're both on the same thread, which is what we expect
because that's I mean how things are being recorded and then we have a
deed of record index that does not match.
In fact, a translation unit does not match either so these are two
totally different events here.
So I'm not sure how that's actually happening that's that's obviously
what the problem is.
So if we take a look at debug,
For our thread.
If we take a look at our first open block, how far up, does it go,
right?
It's got one parent to parents, three parents for parents.
So it's super deep, right?
Look at this.
That's crazy how deep down it goes.
It feels to me.
Like there's like an unclosed block, right?
It feels like it feels like something in there isn't closed properly.
And I'm not sure.
Yeah.
Why that would be but I mean, look at this.
Look at how many there are here, right?
So I feel like the easiest thing to do would be to just look at what
are these opening events that are never getting closed.
And in fact, if you look,
These these opening events are all the same event, they're all the
zero.
They're all the zero event.
So there's just so there's some I think we just have a bug in the in
the record recording.
Right.
That's causing that to get pushed on there in Translation unit 0, the
first debug record index and so I guess, what I'll do is I'll just
say, well, which one was that?
You know, if I take a look at Global debug table, I should be able to
look at this records here.
Global, debug table records 00.
Should tell me I would think who that was Global debug table era.
and,
So let's see.
This is who it was.
Is it?
Is handmade render group dot CPP, it's draw a rectangle line number
39.
So let's take a look.
So our time function does not seem to be closing itself.
So maybe we just when we did our sort of our courting of this stuff
maybe we just didn't do it right.
Maybe end block with this counter is somehow not doing what it should
be doing.
I don't know.
Because that should be pretty straightforward.
So let's see time to underscore function is going to call timed Block,
it's going to call it with these parameters, right?
And we know that that's working because we saw those values in there.
So we know that this part is working.
We know that we're hitting the begin block, and the begin block itself
is I guess doing this, right?
So, it's getting one of these debug records, it's filling out, the
founding which we know is happening properly, then it's doing a
record, debug event of the counter.
Whichever counter were on and where it's using the begin block tag.
So we then do an end block with the counter, and that's doing a
record, debug event of the counter and the debug event and block.
And so that feels like that should be correct.
I don't see why we would having a problem there because here is where
we you know, we store that counter and it right into this integer we
use it in both places passing it.
Through the macro.
So it seems like that should be fine.
I guess what I'd like to do is, is just take a look at draw rectangle.
So I can see what's going on.
So here we are in draw a rectangle.
And here we are in timed block.
So, let's go ahead in their Global debug table.
And let's see here.
The counter is zero, which is what we'd expect begin Block.
It's going into record, debug event.
That is exactly what we'd expect to see.
We're getting an event index out of the pool.
We are oh and now week it time to block again but for probably
somebody else.
I would think all those draw a rectangle again.
I'm not sure exactly what happened.
There could be a different thread.
I'm not sure.
Let's find out.
3780.
Okay, so we get our core index.
Here we come on counter counter in it.
So again, I guess this is a different, a different one of them.
There's a translation unit or that could actually just be jumping
around because that may actually just be because this might be an
optimized function here, I'm not sure.
Anyway, I don't think we put it in the optimize section, though.
So, alright, we got our translation units.
We got everything recorded.
And that's all good.
And that feels correct.
Nothing in there looked weird to me.
Here we go.
You did, we is this?
How come this code appears to be optimized?
Oh, you know what?
Oh,
You know, it probably is optimized because it's getting called from
inside.
Something that was compiled with optimizations on.
I'm guessing or did we comply with optimizations on?
We're not compiling with optimizations on, are we?
Yeah, o.d.
and is optimized and made optimize the CPP.
It's only this one function, so I don't understand.
Why does this appear to have been compiled with optimizations on?
It's jumping all around, but it could just be, well, it could just be
that.
Yeah so it's just another thread.
There's another thread that's in draw rectangle so that's all we're
seeing.
It's not jumping around.
Is just multiple threads.
So that's fine.
Just want to make sure you can barely see that little guy on this
monitor.
But and as you can see that,
You see that right there?
That little thing, that's the little marker that says that the actual
thread you're looking at switched when between steps
So that's going to go ahead and do the fill, so I'm just going to go
ahead and hop down here.
I want to juggle check that I'm before the part, where things would be
closed out.
So you can see there's the call the ending call.
So I'm going to let's hop down there.
There we go, and step in here.
Here we go.
Into end block.
So we come down recruiting 0.
Thread ID is to 5508 but that's in the guy who doesn't?
I don't know why it's hopping around quite so much 3780, so it is it's
properly recording it and end event there, right?
So I'm not sure what the problem is.
It seems
Like, it's fine.
It seems like that should be fine to me.
You know.
We have multiple threads that are hitting that function.
but I don't feel like that should be causing us a problem because
We're expecting it may be our code for dealing with the multiple
threads stuff is wrong.
So I guess, let's take a quick look at that.
And see.
So what I'm going to do is I'm going to do the exact same thing.
I just did only instead of looking at the end of block, I'm going to
look at both.
So, I'm gonna just go ahead and check any time.
We have draw rectangle.
I want to I want to know about it, right?
So I you know I could actually just go ahead and do it here.
So before we start pressing anything, I just I want to see when we get
to that.
Okay.
So in the debug code,
I'm going to set a breakpoint there, so I'm going to let this guy go
for a little bit again, just to make sure that we're past any, like
frames that may happen to work by luck.
And that I know that we're into frames that are definitely busted, and
then I'm going to go ahead and set the break point.
So, here we go on the entry for this.
The first entry.
so, there is
Amusingly draw a rectangle.
The place that's probably being called mostly is in the debug code.
So we're probably causing this bug by drawing rectangles in the debug
code itself.
Which is kind of hilarious.
But anyway, so here we go.
We have an opening one.
So, we'll go ahead and take a look at that.
so, there's four thread, 60/40 opened one
and now thread 6040.
Open one again or closed one.
So this is just weird right thread.
60/40 should not be able to open this many draw rectangles without
closing them.
Right, that's just should not be possible.
That is not something that should be possible.
Are we reading past the end of the array.
Well, it's got a valid threat, ID set so I don't know.
Contradicts is 32.
Event count.
Valid range plus 1.
So that's fine.
We're looping through those guys.
Hmm.
Hmm, I say.
So I guess I'll try one more thing.
Which is I will go ahead and set inside.
Inside my render groups, I fear where we call that draw a rectangle
here is where we're doing that.
What I want to do is I want to look and see when we get here.
I want to look at the global debug table.
And I want to just get an opinion about where it's writing to and I
want to look at it.
So
I want to see what we're actually writing to it.
And when now that's controlled by this guy.
And so the top is the event array index.
So, if I shift this down by 32, I can see which it is.
And of course, I guess, I want to wait again.
I want to wait till we get to known bad behavior because these
actually look kind of correct, right?
So now let me go back there, set that break point.
So here's our event array index, you know, and I'm going to do the
same thing.
Oops.
I'm going to do the same thing to find out.
What the event index is that we do in the actual code just so 27:22 is
the code is that is location.
So I'm going to look at Global debug table and I want to look at
Global debug table, the events for array 8 and I want to see the 2762
if of them
Right, I guess I should do it probably like this.
Okay.
And I would like to see potentially more than just one of those but
yeah and so if all so let's take a look at while we're at it.
Let's just see what the global debug table event count is for array, 8
at the moment.
Yeah, so that's bogus the moment.
That's okay because it gets set at the end so that's fine.
We can double check if that actually works properly.
I suppose a little bit later, but so if we take a look at this, we're
about to write into this guy here.
So there's us writing into it or trying to
We wrote in 50 to 64.
There's one there, I'm going to look, I want to look at a few more of
these.
Can I look at like 16 of these potentially?
I guess not.
There we go.
So you can kind of see here is what we got.
I'm going to keep looking through here at these guys.
So you know, I mean if you just look at what's writing in there, I'm
not seeing that pattern that we see when we actually go to collate.
It there's 50 to 64.
There are six 116, there is 1628, they're all different thread ideas
that are coming through here.
54 52.
So where's the first one that there are six sixteen.
So, we're the first time we see that again is here.
So, let's see what happens here.
So, six do 116, what are we on?
We're on 2769, so 2769 and 62.
So we have written
They're so, but that does look.
like we wrote to in without closing it,
Yeah.
So, I don't understand like how did that happen?
How indeed?
That that's pretty troubling to me because that means we're just
writing bogus data in here.
Like with, it's like the actual debug log is wrong.
So, our collation routine isn't really wrong.
This this routine is or who knows, which routine is actually writing
the stuff out in properly and I don't know why.
So, again, all we're doing is calling that end block here.
So, I'm not sure how it's getting.
How it's getting?
Two opens without the clothes.
It doesn't really make much sense.
When we do record debug event, we're doing an atomic ad,
And so, it feels like we should not have that problem.
Now, I wonder if I guess there could be a thing where it's optimizing
it or not reloading it, although the atomic ad is supposed to always
treat it as
As volatile.
So that seems impossible basically because we're going through a known
compiler path there, we have 20 minutes left on the clock so we
actually have quite a bit past this.
So this is a bit of a Puzzler, right?
This is a bit odd.
This is all looks relatively innocent in terms of how we're addressing
this stuff.
So I'll go, I'll go ahead and step in here, one more time.
And see, see what else I can see.
So, the first frames, it seemed like it worked more properly to right?
So let's take a look here.
Here are our
Oops.
Here are our values.
So we're at array 0, our event index, that does not look like a proper
event index.
Does that look like a proper event index to you?
That just looks totally bogus, maybe that's because by the time we got
to draw a rectangle that actually was the case, but it does seem a bit
odd.
Right?
Possible that a bit odd.
I'm going to make sure that's correct as well.
So, let's step in here, game update and render.
all right, so when we step in here,
Our Global debug table.
Aventure re-index event index and event re-index event index.
Here are both zero.
That's what we would expect.
I'm going to run through one more time to the second frame.
And then I'm going to see what happens.
So 6118 is the current amount that seems like it could be plausible,
given that there are other threads that are running.
And we're on a re-index one.
That all seems relatively plausible, I can't believe it.
So this Frame is not a known bad frame necessarily but I'm now I want
to see.
I'm just going to go in here and take a look at this time function.
I want to see what actually happens here.
So inside the time function, I'm going to watch what it writes.
I'm just going to use again this ability to sort of view what it ends
up.
Writing out to the stream.
So, here we go.
so,
we should see some rights here to this location.
There we go.
Wow, look at that.
It's just it's just pure nonsense in here.
Like here, you've got 164.
Ending 164 ending again.
Here's 164 ending again.
Right?
Because the values for those guys,
Is 012.
So a 2 means it was an end block.
That's just full banana cakes.
There's like no way that should be happening.
So I'm not sure what to make of it.
And I mean, look at all that.
That's purely crazy.
So I guess one thing is is our get thread, ID, function, busted, you
know, like, did we did we Implement that wrong, right?
Is this guy wrong and we could test that, right?
We can try to figure out a way to test that since we would be.
I mean, kind of think of what the easiest way to do that would be, we
could probably try to do something here, where we used thread-local
storage or something like this directly.
I guess I don't really know we could do something like that, but you
know, it's possible that this thing is just reading a bogus value out.
And I'm not sure what else I could do, what else I could do to test
that, we don't have the ability to call Windows directly in here in
this part of the code.
So there's no way for me to
All actual get thread ID, I guess we could start linking with colonel
in this dll.
But like, I can't do this, you know, at the moment anyway.
That's not a known thing.
So, I don't know.
On the other hand, those look like valid thread things and so I guess
I could also, you know what, I could do to, I can test it where I do
create thread.
So here is create thread, create fed immediately calls.
Red frock.
With the new thread.
What I can do here is I can say oh, give me the thread ID.
You know.
And then assert the test thread ID equals get current thread ID,
right?
So that I'm sure that windows and I are getting the same value when we
do a thread ID test.
We'll just try that, just to see.
And so it looks like that's working just fine.
So it seems to think the thread idea is the same.
So we've got something stupid going on but we just don't know what it
is, right?
Something stupid is happening, but we don't know what it is.
And I guess, you know, it seems like it happens under stress meaning
when you have a function that multiple threads are calling at the same
time, apparently this seems to be a problem.
so, with the way this is working,
Perhaps something about how this Atomic is being accessed.
Perhaps something about the way that I'm doing it is
Not proper like in something is getting lost.
I'm not entirely sure.
But oh I'll double-check Atomic adieu.
64, we are marking it as volatile.
Right.
I don't know if one of these castes is, maybe a bad idea.
But I don't think so.
This is, I suppose a volatile as well, but
That shouldn't have any that that should really just that should, that
should not have any effect on anything that I can think of at all.
This is a stumper.
It's a bit of a stumper.
And it's especially Stumpy because you can see that it happens
correctly for a little while.
Like this is exactly what we would expect to see for the most part,
right?
That is like those those are for get them back here.
Those are our debug asynchronous, debug thread spinning up doing a
bunch of rendering and then coming back.
I would assume, right?
So this this is a totally plausible visual picture.
So the question is, just what happens?
Why did things go sour and why does it start to record?
These totally bogus things.
I obviously have some kind of a bug with how those things are getting
written out, but I don't know what it is.
I suppose I could look at the assembly might maybe illuminate
something, but that's sort of presuming that.
There's something subtle happening.
It's wrong.
Where's some kind of expecting?
It must be something blatant that we're doing wrong like something
that's just flat-out, totally wrong, you know.
because in order for it to write out, such ridiculous data, it has to
either be missing a particular piece of debug information or it must
like
get the event type wrong.
In some way.
And I'm totally not seeing it.
Record Loops record, debug event.
And I guess one thing we could do is we could sort of take this part
out of the equation a little bit too.
Just for fun.
We could do something like this since.
I don't have any immediate idea.
What the problem is, I could do something like, count, begin block,
draw a rectangle.
And Walk Tall rectangle.
And now it would be going through.
It wouldn't be using the Constructor Destructor paired one and it
would be using the more explicit path.
So it's still incorrect as far as I can tell, which is good, that
would be even scarier if somehow that wasn't the case.
But now, when I set a breakpoint here, I can look a little bit more
explicitly at when it's doing what, right?
So okay, so let me set a breakpoint there as well so you can see these
guys kind of coming down through here.
Right.
It's a whole bunch of people hitting this function at the same time,
they're doing whatever rectangle filling fund, they want to do.
And then eventually
I don't know why.
When I hit run, it still shows me things from other threads.
But then when we get down to end block for draw a rectangle, I want to
see what that records.
So we're on event array 3 at the moment and we're on 2271 is the
event.
And so let's see what happens here by step into this guy.
It's going to write to 2272 which should be like that guy.
Sorry 2271, it will write to that's the next value, so rights in
there.
I don't know why the thread ID.
Oh, it didn't update.
Just did change their so thread.
ID 68, what's the event?
Type event type is end block.
That's what I would expect to see.
So that's good, right?
Everything is still happening the way I want it to, so that's all
good.
And then, let's see.
Now, we come through here, somebody else has done their increment.
It looks like
I want you to keep want you to keep going, man.
It's Ron's 2774 now.
So it ended it for two of the different Frets here.
There we go.
I don't know.
I got to have to come up with a more creative way to debug this
because I don't see anything obviously weird happening here.
I don't see it, but by the time we sort of get out to here, it's
definitely having this weird thing where it's having a, I don't know
if it's a race condition or right problem or what, but it's eluding me
at the moment, really, just to the point of where I'm not even sure.
I don't have a really good hypothesis for like usually, I could think
of, like, oh, here's something, I suspect.
Be happening.
Let's go investigate it.
I don't really have one of those so I'm going to pause.
Here's the thing you can do.
I don't normally do this but I'm going to do it anyway.
You can kind of see, it's crazy.
All of these people hit draw.
A rectangle at the same time, right?
And so that, I guess that's what's kind of causing our problem is we
R, SF something that doesn't quite work there.
What I'm going to do is I'm going to go ahead and like freeze these
guys so that they can't Advance anymore, right?
I'm just going to freeze them.
So now, they should be unable to continue.
So I'll be able to look at just this one thread.
And I'm going to see what happens if I let each thread.
Do its thing.
So when we come in here, I'm going to get or I it was supposed to.
Why did, who unfroze you the main thread came in?
Freeze.
There we go.
All right.
Try it.
One more time.
So we come in here.
We're going to write event index 2764.
And we're looking at that here, 2764.
So here we go.
I'm going to take a look at what that writes a to here.
It is it's writing in the begin block For Thread 46:52 that's all
good.
Writes it all in there.
Here it goes.
And then we get down to the end block, all the other threads are
frozen.
So now we should see something right here, a 46:52
The end for that guy, right?
And I guess there was an interesting guy who snuck in there as well.
That's probably the begin block for the other guy for the one that for
the main for the second there.
So there is the two, there is the one, there's the to, right?
So, that's good.
Okay, so now let's unfreeze one more thread.
This guy was going, so I'll go ahead and freeze you.
And I'll unfreeze you.
Bah.
You can see what I'm doing here.
I'm just telling the threads, which thread can do.
What when
So, it kind of has this the sort of ability for me to watch more
carefully at what's actually happening.
So, here we go.
You start writing to it, you can see it writing in here.
There's the start.
58 84 writes, everything in as I would expect.
Gets down to the end of block.
I should write it out here and it does as a too.
So it kind of looks to me again.
It's I don't know.
It looks a lot like some kind of a race condition because when we
force these guys to serialize meaning, you know, when we, when we
prevent them from being able to hit the, the debug array, at the same
time, I'm not seeing the kind of ridiculousness.
I was seeing before where you were getting all of these opens and
closes with the wrong thread IDs.
So that seems suspicious.
But at the same time I don't know, like I don't have any idea why that
would be happening.
I don't see where
Would be having the race condition there.
So let's freeze this guy again.
I'll throw another one out.
So there's thread 912 coming through.
Right.
And there's thread 912, closing again, perfectly paired exactly what
we would have thought,
So it looks very suspicious right.
You know, it's not a Smoking Gun but it looks very suspicious because
why is it suddenly behaving so much better when we freeze the threads
There's got to be something.
It would seem in this.
That is incorrect.
That's not, it's not doing the right thing, right?
That's something that it's allowing it to, to misbehave.
And so, if I look here, you know,
These are all values that should not be changing.
The only value that we really use is this one.
We get that debug event in here, right?
So we've got get thread ID, get thread ID.
As far as I know is not doing anything weird.
Maybe there's some reason why get thread ID is itself, not thread
safe, like I don't know if read GSD word somehow doesn't work properly
under but I mean it shouldn't have any thread dependent dependence
whatsoever.
I mean it should be.
That should not really have any bearing on anything.
I wouldn't think although you know, maybe there's some reason why
that's that's a
We're not quite safe.
Because if the gut thread ID was was coming back bogus then that would
be something.
I suppose the other thing we don't really know, we could do something
where with get thread ID, we're getting back, a u-32 obviously forget
thread ID.
We should probably try to determine well, we already doing that.
We're already verifying
I guess that's not true.
We don't verify that it actually fits in a u16, right?
So the other thing we could do is we could do this.
Just to make sure that we're not truncating it in some bad way, but I
would not expect that to be true.
But I just double check again at this point I'm you know sort of
paranoid about it, right because I don't really know if I don't have a
good idea of who the culprit is, then I have to start to suspect every
last little thing.
So that's fine.
so,
I don't know.
I'd say this is probably the hardest, debugging problem we've seen on
handmade hero so far.
That doesn't necessarily mean it's the hardest bug, but it's
definitely the one that's caused me the most perplexing.
Which usually has to do with you, not guessing not being able to guess
in the right direction of what the problem is.
So Atomic, add you 64?
Is presumably not at fault here.
Because we would assume that we would have seen that in some other
way, right?
When we have
See here.
We have been using those atomics, you know, the windows atomics.
Pretty much for everything we've done and we haven't seen any problems
with them.
So if there's a problem with the way that we were calling, we would
have expected.
I would think to see it in the renderer somewhere, whatever.
Now, granted we never calling it as heavily as we're calling it here.
That is true.
So there is a little bit of that I suppose.
But himself, you know, it's doing in Deluxe.
Change at 64 bit.
Is it conceivable that it's not aligned?
Somehow that it like straddles, a cache line or something like this.
So it wouldn't be.
That seems just really like I'm grasping at straws personally, what it
kind of seems like but I mean all right you know let's let's make sure
just just because why not.
So let's make sure that the address of that guy and the bottom 64
bits, right?
So I want to, I guess I'm saying is I want to make sure
This guy isn't in some kind of a weird alignment, so that's aligned on
all every, every 64.
So, I want to make sure that the the
Excuse me.
The bottom six bits.
Well I guess 8 so the bottom three B should all be zero.
So I want you know something like you know I want to make sure that
that I don't have
First cast sister, you 64.
Whatever the address is of this thing, right?
I want to make sure that, you know, that would be aligned to every two
bites.
That would be aligned to every for B.
And I want this aligned to every
Every eight, right?
A brains kind of fried here.
I'm also.
Little slope.
So yeah.
I'm just going to see what that does.
Right.
Yeah.
So
Sorry, that's not quite right.
Yeah, my brain is totally fried.
Sorry, I'm too busy thinking about the bug.
And not busy.
I'm not actually thinking about what I'm trying to explain here, so
that would be two that.
If that equals 0 then your your your lobe it that tells you every
other B, right?
That tells me the next bit over but I need I need both I need to know
that the low bit and the next bit up is not set, right?
So that would be forever.
For.
And so then, you know I wrote it right the first time that I was
trying to explain it.
I kind of said it wrong and typed it wrong and so that has all three
bottom bit set.
So now we know that we're by twos, we're not by twos, we're not by 4
as they were not.
You know, we've got to be by AIDS.
Right.
So that we relied them on on a 64-bit or eight byte boundary.
So I'm just going to go ahead and run that.
That's a little bit odd.
Oh well that's all right.
I guess sometimes the block name in The Source is 0.
So we should add our we should allow our string routine to handle that
we can just say something like
These are two results is false.
If a and b.
Like that.
So now you can pass in a null pointers if you want.
And I'll just tell you, although, I suppose, we could also do
something like this.
You know, oops.
So essentially like if they were both know, it would be okay because
technically if you say strings are equal, zero comma zero, that
probably should be true because they are same string.
So that seems like a fair thing to do.
All right, so let's run that.
Yeah, so that's all aligned properly.
So there's nothing weird going.
On there.
So our Atomic Miss should be fine.
Yeah, and there's nothing.
Nothing peculiar there.
I don't know.
This is a stumper.
I could just if you think it maybe it would be fun.
I could end the stream and see if people want to try to bugging it.
See if they could figure it out.
We've pretty clearly stated what the problem is, right?
So you should have a very good idea of exactly what you're looking
for, but why it is happening, is anyone's guess we pretty much don't
have any idea.
We're pretty much don't know, right?
So yeah I'm going to end it.
We're going to sleep on it and we'll see and we'll think about
tomorrow how we want to reproach to bugging it because it looks like I
don't have any good ideas for it.
And I think we may have to like what I am leaning towards doing is
trying to Pare down pair of this down to the smallest possible Repro
case, so that I can debug it more in isolation rather than having to
do it kind of with a
Instead of debug events in in the running program, right?
So I think that's what I'll do.
Maybe someone already knows what it is, but I'm assuming that without
doing the debugging themselves, they might not be able to.
So let's go ahead and go to the Q&A.
and I will leave debugging that as an exercise for the reader
overnight, if anyone can find it and see,
This Isaac try running without timing.
Draw a rectangle.
I'm sure if you want to see if you just want to see if it's like only
this one routine which is a perfectly reasonable thing to want to do
just to get more information.
Like is there something weird about draw?
A rectangle specifically?
And it does not look like it, right.
It looks like it's just happens.
Eventually.
Regardless of what we time.
The other thing is I suppose, you know, there's the timing that's in
render group is the timing that's going to be multi-threaded.
So you know what we could do to is say here like
Inside render group, we could replace time function.
With the new word timed function.
Like so.
And then up here we just do pound find ignored time function.
And that would take out all of them.
And similarly, inside optimized.
We do the same thing.
And that would give you.
That would give you like one that presumably wasn't really doing any
heavy multi-threaded use.
And, you know, it does sort of reinforce the notion that the code was
was working properly.
When it does not have, excuse me, multi-thread contention there.
And so, you know, yet further evidence that it suggests that something
is wrong.
But still doesn't really tell us what the what the Smoking Gun is, you
know?
So
So, still a Puzzler.
In my opinion.
The msdn documentation for read, gsq word States, these intrinsics are
only available in kernel mode and the routines are only available as
intrinsics.
If this is the case, how are you able to use read gsq word to read out
of the thread ID?
I'm not really sure what the difference between kernel mode.
User mode is so I don't, I'm pretty sure that is a bogus claim on the
msdn documentation.
And the reason that I say that is because we took
Look at how get current thread ID worked.
We like looked at this assembly and it issued a Direct Read to the GS
segment.
So clearly you don't need to be in kernel mode to do it because
Microsoft's own code, does it not in kernel mode?
So, I don't know where that notion came from, but it doesn't seem to
be at all grounded in reality, as far as I can tell.
So, all we're doing right now is exactly the same code that would have
happened with get current thread ID.
As far as I know,
You said that it seems to work normally for a little while, then stops
working when it's under stress, maybe let the threads run wild for a
little while, then freeze them or is this not possible with the
debugger.
Well, that is what we did.
or, I mean,
Yeah, I mean I mean we can definitely do that.
so, in order to do that,
let's go ahead and
switch this back to Broken mode.
Oh well, you know what though?
Let's not.
Quite do that.
Let's just see if turning on the just draw.
A rectangle is sufficient to reproduce the problem.
That I would like to know.
Really.
If yes, if we got some weird bugs in here, like, what is going on
there?
How could turning off stuff end up with more regions, you know, it's
very strange.
I guess it's well it's probably because there's no parent.
That's probably why there's no parent to draw a rectangle.
So you're just going to see a ton of draw rectangle calls, right?
so yeah, I mean that I guess doesn't isn't really that surprising but
still
Man, I guess there's just a lot of draw rectangle calls.
This is going to be like an Infinity of draw rectangle calls, right?
Because it's every every time we call draw a rectangle, it would add
another region per frame, that makes sense, because the Region's
themselves are draw a rectangle calls.
So it's just this kind of infinite feedback loop sort of thing.
It's not an infinite feedback loop but but it's a bad situation.
So yeah, I'm not sure how we would really get by that because there's
going to be a ton of them.
Right.
Because the student, it's just going to keep adding more and more and
more.
More and more, and more of them.
Let's see here.
Events are there?
Current frame.
It's that first one that first frame has way more debug events than
everybody else, which is also a little bit odd.
I don't know why.
Exactly that would be maybe because it has to do a lot of
initialization of stuff which is causing word, you big events.
But this is a little weird, right?
I sort of a separate issue there.
like,
It's a bit odd.
Is it possible that the array index part somehow got swapped out
during the begin and end records?
Even if it did, that's fine.
We don't count on that, not happening.
Did you create your colors to be easy on the eyes?
If not, how did they come to be here talking about the grid ones, or
Didn't remove the end block call.
No, it's still there because it's sort of implicit.
If you take a look the time function, it includes it automatically
does the beginning and right.
That's that's its job.
It uses the Constructor Destructor pair trick to make sure there's one
at the beginning in the end.
So you know,
But yeah, I wanted to kind, I wanted to do to do that, I guess what I
can do.
So here's the way I can fix this problem because I don't want to have
to deal with this.
The way I can fix this problem.
Is in the render group.
I can just add put one more of these guys back in like the top level
guy that way it won't add a region for every rectangle call.
so, if we did that,
It just being here.
So now we wouldn't be pushing those regions on and then it'd be fine.
I should think or not.
Hmm.
Right, so this is kind of interesting as well.
Let's take a look at what happens here because I'm interested to know
why that's happening source.
So draw a rectangle should not be happening.
Without an enclosed person, right?
Who is calling draw.
A rectangle.
That's not underneath one of these two guys.
Looking where can draw a rectangle be cold.
So, it does get called directly just straight out of the gate.
So there is one place there.
Well, that's not.
That's if they're it out though.
So that wouldn't count Direction quickly doesn't count draw a
rectangle.
There's our time function director.
How slowly does not count, draw a rectangle and the render group.
This is inside render group to Output.
Surrender group to Output.
Oops.
Render group to Output.
Is pretty much only called.
inside the guys that I just said,
right.
There is render route output.
So I guess not so do tiled render work.
Doesn't actually count because it isn't under here, right?
All right.
We'll see.
Okay.
So now we don't have that problem.
Once.
It's once those guys are sort of, you know, stuck under there
Now, we are properly seeing the render kickoffs and everything else it
looks.
So having those draw rectangle calls, kind of wild.
It's kind of interesting.
I'm gonna go ahead and make ignored time function, the time function.
Again.
So my turn all these guys back on and let's see what happens.
So it still has a problem if you turn everybody on, if that makes
sense.
All right, let's try one of these at a time.
So, now, with everybody on except the optimized code, right?
If you've read Justice counting, the optimized code,
We are not hitting the case.
so again, yet one more piece of data there,
Let's see, Elvin, if the debug code is slower than the actual runtime
of the game.
How can we rely on the debug systems to give us accurate timing of how
long things are taking in the game since they naturally take more time
in debug mode?
Well, again, there's a lot of stuff that we're will kind of be looking
at to what degree to how much stuff we can do and still reasonably,
get good timings remember.
It doesn't matter how slow the game runs.
It only matters how slow the part that actually interferes with the
games.
Fang takes so that the the overall time when we actually draw it
separately, that part is not so critical.
Look, we don't care if that slows things down because that doesn't
really affect the code that its timing.
It's only the part that does the actual timing that can't be slow or
the can interfere too much.
Thanks, that's
so, you can kind of see to like,
This is already, I believe, showing us what's happening in the game,
pretty clearly.
I also, you know what, let's why is it?
I want to move it down a little bit further as well.
so, let's go ahead and
do this here.
So let's say, let's just say,
That at y here.
I'm going to give it another 300.
Just so I can see a little more clearly.
But you can kind of see, right?
You can see what's going on here.
I believe, if you look at what these actual frame, display things kind
of look like, you can see that you've got, you know, this is that
first kickoff.
This this is rendering the game.
This sort of first batch here.
Those are the threads that actually render the game.
And this batch up here are presumably the threads that render the
debug output, right?
You know what I mean?
So it's kind of interesting to see that.
And, you know, the other thing I could do, is when we render these, we
could render less of them so that they fit on the screen properly.
Again, will kind of get to all this stuff a little bit later but just
for sake of the argument.
So you know, if we did something like, well we've got, you know, n
frames.
We know that the most recent frames are the last frames.
So if we did something like like this, we could do something like,
okay, give me.
The frame.
That's the frame count - the frame index.
you know, or
Like that.
And then here, what we do is we'd say, well, I really just want to go
to to like the tenth one or whatever or something like this.
So it'd be something like, you, 32, Max frame equals debug frame
count.
If Max frame is greater than 10, Max Payne 2 equals 10.
Just throwing it out there for now.
And that way, you know, presumably, we would have less of these well,
although that's still drawing more than 10.
What did I do wrong in there?
Didn't use it Max.
So at least then yeah we kind of have a little bit.
So this is the most recent frame here and you can kind of see.
Now, a little more saying it's not spending so much time drawing
rectangles and stuff like this, right?
But you can kind of
Here.
Now we have a again, a better sort of picture of what's going on.
But even just before, we've even debugged the, this system, you can
now see a really clear picture, even just from this really, really
lousy visualization.
Since we haven't spent any time, actually with a vis stuff, you can
already see a really good eye picture of kind of what's happening the
game.
Here's the main thread, right?
And you can see it's broken up into like the game update is this?
This large solid part.
Here's the part where it's waiting for the frames to change.
Here's the beginning part where it was like, pressing input and stuff
and then you here, you can see the frames the threads getting kicked
off to do the rendering and here you can see the threads, get given to
the rendering a second time for the debug overlay.
So you can, you know, it again, people were sort of saying, why do we
spend time in the debug code?
It takes too long.
I mean, the stuff we're going to find out and be able to see from
just, a few weeks of work.
And don't forget if you, if, you know, if you weren't breaking this up
into chunks of had to be an hour, a night uses not very much work, you
know, you're talking about like full-time one week, maybe two weeks of
full-time work at most to write a decent debug system.
The stuff that you end up seeing in it, just pay off.
So huge already, this kind of validates, what I think is happening in
the code and it gives me a much, you know, as soon as we're going to
be able to drill down in there a little more, we're going to learn a
lot of stuff.
We probably didn't know.
And it's also kind of itching to see how much time is spent prior to
taking off those threads.
It's actually pretty significant more than I would have thought there.
So I feel like that's yeah I feel like it's really good idea to spend
time on this kind of code because I feel like you learned a lot of
things that you wouldn't know otherwise.
Remember Chris, another day you discard events at buffers are full.
Are you sure?
I'll buffers are big enough.
Well actually that wouldn't cause the problem though because the
problem that we're seeing is that we're getting to end events that
don't have corresponding bit.
Begin events.
If we were throwing out events when the buffers got full, we would
never see the end events either.
So throwing out events on the bumpers feels actually fine.
But, no, I don't think we're having that because we have an assertion
in there, actually.
The moment.
We actually have a surgeons in there, like this.
You know.
so,
So yeah, I'd also be interested to see just for a moment.
I'd be interested to see if we go into our build-up at
What the difference is.
if I was,
To run release mode.
So seriously, you can see that just like a lot less time spent there,
right?
Not sure what those kind.
Those are some interesting spikes there.
Like, I don't know what their spikes were from.
That would be something that I can read.
Want to go ahead and investigate.
Oh, you know what we missed?
That's missing the frame.
You can see that it.
Misses the frame turnover.
It looks like
So, I'll be adjusting to investigate as well.
Again, really pretty interesting stuff.
Besides it could it be threads running across a frame boundary.
I mean, yeah.
I mean, I obviously could I just don't know.
I mean since I don't know what it is, I don't know what it isn't,
right.
but, you know,
this code doesn't care if that happened.
It really doesn't care because let's say that the begin events had had
moved out, had fallen off the had fallen off the event.
Arrays.
So, you know, they happened on the last frame and the last frame fell
out.
So we're starting on the, the farthest back frame.
We're starting to process it.
We don't have any big events.
We see end events.
We just throw them away.
Right?
They wouldn't be causing a problem.
They wouldn't be causing the problem you're seeing, which is that the
open block array is filled with people who didn't have who never got
closed.
From then, on we're processing everybody on all frames.
So it doesn't matter if a person crosses a frame boundary we should
still pop them off properly, right?
We don't reset the frame stack.
When we do this, this doesn't reset the frame.
I'm sorry, it doesn't reset.
The thread open block stock.
So it shouldn't matter if they cross.
So yeah.
All right, I think that's about it.
We're going to, we're going to leave that one be well.
Do you know I'm going to restore it to to its non-working State
because I don't want to leave it in a state that's actually working.
so, I want to
Put it back.
Into a state.
Where it is broken.
So that we can work on it tomorrow.
So that was the broken version.
Yeah.
What has happened?
Oh no.
That's correct.
Because we're only seeing the last ten frames.
Yeah.
So yeah.
So we're back in the broken safe here.
So I'm going to leave it like that because I want a broken when we
start looking at it tomorrow.
So that's good.
Let me go ahead and close down the thread.
The string
Nobody says nothing scheduled.
There we go.
That's what should say, okay.
Thank you everyone for joining me for another episode of handmade
hero.
This is a bit of a stumper.
This is the first time I think we've had one on handmade hero, so I
feel like this is a kind of a tricky problem to debug and it'll be
interesting to see what we do tomorrow to try and track it down.
Yeah, we're going to have to, we're going to have to give it some
serious thought because there doesn't seem to be anything particularly
obvious to try.
If you've got ideas, you can always try hunting down the bug yourself.
See if you can find it.
Is a tricky one.
So if you're looking for some debugging practice, I would say it's
probably a good one to try because there was not it was not something
that was immediately obvious to me.
So I don't think it would be immediately obvious and it might give you
a good chance to try and play around with hunting a hunting down.
Some, that may even be a multi threading bug, which is a particularly
tough type of bug find verbally as well.
So anyway, if you want to check that out you and you can always do
that.
If you are someone who pre-order the game, again it comes to the
source code so you can download the source code.
I'll upload it now and you can download the latest version and then
see if you can find it.
If you do, I don't know if you want to do spoiler warnings or not, you
can post it on the forums and see, maybe we can see who gets it first.
I seen you guys could easily beat me to it if you started.
Now, my voice is about to go.
So I'll just sign off for now and say, thanks everyone for joining me.
I'll be back here tomorrow.
I think it's a, it's a late stream tomorrow.
So it'll actually be 8 p.m.
Pacific Daylight time tomorrow.
When I'll pick back up the bug hunt and see if I can't find out what's
wrong with that guy.
Until then have programming and I will see you guys on the internet.
Take it easy, everyone.