Hello everyone and welcome to handmade hero.
The show recode a complete game live on stream, you know, I just
wanted to take a quick second before, starting today's stream to point
out that the, the folks who provide the forums for handmade hero,
which is handmade Network who actually provide the forums for a lot of
projects that are hand coded.
They have finally added something that I know that they
You have been wind out for a while, but I think they wanted to make
sure that they had a good procedure in place for handling such things
before they opened it up.
But they decided to open up their project submissions for anyone who
was interested in having a project hosted there.
And you can see that if you go here to handmade Network / projects, or
you can just go to handmade Network and click on this projects button
and that page lists all the projects that they're
There are but previously you know, if you wanted to be part of their
project hosting you had to email someone involved with the site and
ask them to add you because they didn't again have it set up yet for
public submission but they've finished all the stuff they wanted to do
for public submissions.
So now you can do a really handy quick submission process.
If you haven't registered for the site yet which of course on this
browser, I haven't
I am registered on the site because there's our project right here, if
you haven't, you just register first to make a username and, you know,
you might already have one of those because you may participate in the
forums here.
But if you don't have one, you just register appear.
And then this register, or login, B will change to a submission
button.
You can click and then you can send the information about your project
and they will take a look.
So yeah, if you're interested in doing a handmade project and by
handmade project, I mean I think one of the interesting things about
handmade project is certainly I never attempted to Define what
handmade project meant and I don't know that anyone really knows what
it means because it wasn't supposed to be a name for anything.
It was just the name of this particular series, and now it carries a
lot of connotations I suppose where that that are different from
person to person.
But in general I think it you know, just kind of means if you are
Who's interested in programming and you know, learning about
programming and doing programming in a dedicated way where you
actually care about the results and you care about what's going on.
I feel like that probably slots in here and if you look at the kind of
projects that are in here, they're pretty varied.
They're not specific to games or anything.
So, for example, for coder is the editor we use on stream and that was
Handmade by Allen Webster handmade here obviously, is the show you're
watching motion box is a
New browser.
Only enough, which is kind of so like totally not game related, but
it's designed to just browse videos like, that's all it does, is
browse videos.
So, it's kind of like meant to be sort of, like, a new way of
thinking, about Television, right?
And a lot of people really like this.
I've heard a lot of positive things about it, so you know, again,
completely unrelated to video games or the original product in any
way.
But it's just like part of the sort of idea that, you know, building
things and caring about them is good.
And then there's papaya which is a image editor, right?
Like a painting program, there's a a game engine kind of thing like a
not a game engine necessarily meant for, like shipping commercial
games, but a game engine that's made to, so that you can learn how to
program video games.
It's like a teaching engine.
If you will, obviously, Sean Barrett's, fabulous collection of
libraries that a lot of people already use their now hosted on here
and, you know, the list kind of goes on and on here.
And
They've built up a pretty impressive list.
There's even people who are working on new debugging tools and that's
going to be kind of awesome because I've always wanted to switch away
from the debugging tools that I have.
Currently I don't love them.
And so you know much like we switch to for coder because I really
didn't love emacs and I'm much happier on for coder.
I think maybe you know the day might come when we get to switch from
Visual Studio on stream.
I've never really been a big fan of using
For debugging to one of the buggers that people are building here,
which you know, would probably be more focused towards kind of
debugging that we do.
Right?
Visual Studios is geared towards a very broad, you know, audience of
people that doesn't really necessarily have even program in C++,
right?
And so a lot of times the focus on that debugger is elsewhere and so
you know it might be that one of the debugger is made here will focus
more on the kinds of stuff that we do.
So there's all sorts of stuff here.
Of course.
10 is the paint program, we use on stream as well.
So that got written under the handmade Network Banner as well.
So there's just a lot of great projects on here.
And, you know, even if you're not thinking of starting a project, you
should probably check out the products that are on here because a lot
of them also provide source code so you can learn from them as well
and if a lot of them also accept either donations or our commercial so
you can purchase them.
So if it's a project that you want to support that would be a great
thing to do because obviously
the folks who are building these things could you know they've got to
eat too.
So yeah all this stuff is pretty cool I would definitely recommend
checking it out and if you do have a project that you think you would
like to be part of the community that they're working on at handmade
Network and the sort of stuff that they're doing, that's the news
right?
The the submit a project button is up and they are they're ready to
start looking at at folks who have projects who might want to host on
here.
So, give that a shot.
And made Network / projects and yeah, the folks on the chat Abner and
Abner coimbra and Andrew chronister and joroan.
That's let's see.
That's it's just Abner coin, brave for usernames, Chrono dragon and
and Colombian on the chat I believe do.
Most of the site works.
So if you have any questions about that and or you have any
Abel submitting your project because again this is a brand-new
feature, check them.
Check them out on chat.
They're oftentimes on during handmade hero so you can find them in the
twitch chat or on the handmade RC or you can also if you registered a
username you can go to the forums here and there's a site feedback you
just from the handmade Network main site.
You can just click on this forums button and that forms button will
bring you to like a place where you can post questions.
Or if you're having trouble with the site or this, just something
about the site that didn't work, the way you thought, that's a good
place to let them know so they can be aware of it as, you know, I'm
sure you're aware with web development.
A lot of times things are different on different browsers or different
things happen that are confusing.
And, you know, they might not know about the issue that you're seeing
or they may not be aware that there's some problem with a specific
configuration or whatever you're doing.
So if you're having any trouble that's the place to go as well.
And again, if for some reason, you can't even register because of
something in your area or whatever is happening, check them out on
chat and and they can help you out.
Alright, so that's about it, we are ready to get started here.
I don't know why this isn't showing I guess because it didn't get
reopened the other yesterday.
I pushed the clang compatibility.
Well push his father Edward I
Did the work on the clan compatibility stuff but I don't know why it's
not on here because I closed it but I thought it got reopened because
some folks did do the testing on it and there was one other thing that
we needed to fix when they tried to compile it.
Now I don't know why that's not on here.
That's a good question because these are sorted by date.
Are they not?
So it should have been right up here but I don't actually see it now.
Maybe it's because it didn't get recorded in here for some reason.
I'm not sure.
Or maybe the notifications page would tell me.
Here we go.
So why?
Why was that not?
I don't know.
Anyway, all I can say is we found it will just consider that a victory
there, a little, a little minor GitHub Victory and we'll just
With that.
So okay, here was the actual thing I want to talk about.
So this is the, the fellow who actually, I believe continues to
maintain an sdl port in the GitHub as well, you know, for handmade
hero.
So he compiles it on
On clang all the time and Martin's and and and him were the two people
who basically gave me all of the information I needed in order to fix
the build under clang.
So, he went ahead and tested it.
And apparently the problem now is confined to just the time function
macro and it has to do with the fact that the, the care that the
function is declared.
As const the the function string.
So we need to Cast Away the const so that we don't have a compiler
error there.
When you pass it to the time clock function, but the other thing is, I
guess we weren't properly passing the counter or something.
So I got to go take a look at that as well.
That may just been a mistake on my part.
I'm not sure why that didn't fail in our build, but there's probably a
good reason for it.
So we'll take a look at that as well.
And
It looks like there was some problem with GCC where the macro
expansion leaves a comma incorrectly, which I'm not sure why.
Because, I thought that double paste thing was supposed to be the way
that that gets fixed, but I don't even know if that.
Double Pace thing is standardized or not, that may have just been a
convention for not having
The comma or I don't really know.
But yeah, that is just a generic thing that I use when I end macros in
general to make sure that they can pass through more information if
necessary.
And that just to give some perspective on that, the reason I do that
is because then if the underlying function, that the macro calls adds
new optional parameters at the end, it'll still work without having to
change the macro.
So I typically just do it that way, but as Kim's pointing out,
Here, we don't actually use that.
We don't, we have never needed to pass additional arguments.
So at least for the time being, and probably for the foreseeable
future, because time function, I did never really envisioned it,
taking more parameters.
Anyway, that's just, like I said, more of a thing that I just do in
general when I make macros.
So there's really no reason, we can't eliminate it.
So the fact that there's that extra spurious comma getting inserted by
GCC.
We can work around that in exactly the way that chemists suggesting
here.
Basically that vet by removing that our VA aren't entirely, then we
won't have the problem.
So let's just go ahead and do that.
Again, it only
A few minutes to even do.
It's a very very simple change.
We did all the sort of actual work that it was necessary for this
yesterday.
So it's pretty easy.
If I just go and compile the the project here to make sure
everything's set up properly in if I jump back to the GitHub and look
here you can see it's just the time function thing, we know that
that's in debug interface and so we'll just jump down to it.
Here's time function.
And if you take a look at what's going on in time function, again, you
can see that it's just really something that's getting passed down to
the timed block, right?
You can see the time block here and here is that timed block function,
you can see the hit count in it, right?
Which is there, which is to record a single hit, and as you can see,
we're not using that anymore.
And so, this is what I saying about, you know, we don't really need
that that aspect of the matter,
Anymore.
So we can just get rid of it for now, if we find that we needed again,
well, we'll have to think about that and deal with it when the time
comes right.
For now, we might as well maintained GCC compatibility because that's
the only thing stopping us from getting that.
So if we take this out of the time function, right, and you can see us
passing this, this information here.
When we call the timed block, we're supposed to pass a grid, a name
and a number.
Now, I don't know why we were able to not pass that number here.
That's a really good question.
And I guess it's just because the number isn't getting used right.
You can kind of see that the number just isn't getting used, so it
looks like that number was actually getting past as the hit count,
which was just getting ignored.
So I think this is just Legacy code anyway.
So I suspect, what we can probably do is just say like, okay, timed
block really just takes a grid and a name and that's all it does,
right?
The counter is not necessary at all.
Neither are the variable arguments because they're all they're going
to do is end up getting past the time block, which we already know we
do need, right?
So, if you take a look at what's going on here, we could just say like
okay you know, if we just want to leave this as simple as possible,
which you might as well.
Do at the moment, we can always make it more complicated later, right?
No, no programmer ever was like, oh, I can't make that more
complicated for you.
So if we just go ahead and get rid of sort of the vestigial remains
there, then we're left with
Thing that will probably be able to compile properly on all the
platforms, right?
And so, I think, what we probably want to do is say well, okay, since
name just gets replicated multiple times here, probably when we do
timed block, we just pass a name and then we replicate it twice all
the other aspects that we use.
We're going to go ahead and use sort of the grid expansion version of
them here.
And then when we call a Time function by itself, for just going to
pass function and function as the name.
Right.
And you can imagine it's just calling timed block here with because it
would it with function as long as parameter.
But I'm not going to bother doing that because against
Trying to get this to compiler multi compilers and we have testing of
a current macro set.
I don't want to like poke The Hornet's Nest there, any more than is
absolutely necessary.
So I feel like just trimming that out, we should be in better shape
now, and, you know, here's here's everything running, I believe
properly, and if I go to the profile, you can kind of see that our
names are still good.
Right?
There's there's nothing weird happening there with our time function
blocks.
These are
All timed functions.
So it looks like we're all good, right?
Everything seems fine there and so I think that's a change that we can
keep.
Now, like I said, I don't understand why this didn't show up there,
but it looks like because it's not, they didn't, it looks like Kim
didn't reopen the issue, it might be because he can't I don't know
what the rules are in.
Good of, it may be that I accidentally closed it in a way that it may
be the only I have the authority.
Because it's my project to reopen the issue, I'm not sure.
But anyway, I'll just write it here so he could see it.
And then I do get email notifications when people reply to these
issues streams.
And so, in that way, right?
I can know if there was an additional problem with it, even though
it's not listed as a open issue anymore.
Just build that row its vestigial, isn't it?
Yes, it is.
So now we've at least try to make this stuff work your and hopefully
that will now bring us into full compliance with all the compilers
that people use, clang, GCC and an MSP see.
No way to know without testing, we will certainly find out and we will
let the folks who use clang on a regular basis.
Let us know if everything is now working correctly for them or whether
there are still issues out there.
Okay so today I guess I'm not exactly sure what we want to do today.
I was thinking the probably what I do is just kind of play with that
camera code a little bit and just maybe sort of like get that stuff to
a state that I'm happy with and then that way next week we can start
on 3D Fresh.
So from the start of the episode, we'll just do that and you can kind
of see that we've got some weirdness is now and stuff that we would
probably want to improve and address.
So there's a couple different things we might want.
I want to do here, right?
So let's just talk about those for a second and then, we'll sort of
talk about what we can do with them, or
Them.
So, at the end of yesterday's stream, we had gotten it to the point
where we now have all of these sort of rooms that can be different
sizes, right?
So we used to have it so that the rooms were always the same size and
now we have it so that the rooms are different sizes, right?
And you can sort of see that that's happening.
Both horizontally and vertically like we have rooms that are wider
rooms.
That are narrower rooms that are taller rooms that are shorter because
It's just getting a random variable there and making the room whatever
that random size is and the rooms are just stacked against each other
with a dual row of trees in between them.
That's, that's all we made, you know, we don't have really any World
Generation code right now, we just have really basic stuff.
So if you take a look at what's going on there, you can see that that
basically everything is working fine with the camera in terms of
picking out, which rumor in and everything's working fine with the
world Gen 2.
A certain extent there and that's all fine.
But
Also, I would point out, you can kind of see where all our time is
going here.
Remember our get closest reversible function is of course the function
where we don't have any acceleration.
It's N squared.
So the number of entities on the screen, it just goes up and up and
up, right?
And is it's currently the very biggest of piggy.
So we kind of have a nice.
We have a nice profile there for our future optimization because
that's a function.
We can very easily.
Down to very little cost anyway, but that's fine.
So if you take a look at what's going on here, everything's working
fine.
In terms of what we wrote, but obviously, it's not very good.
In terms of anything you would really want to ship in terms of a good
player experience.
The reason for that is like, you take a look in here and you know,
this this room is too big, you know, like for the player to even see
what's going on in the room and we don't make any attempt to like,
zoom out to see the whole room.
We also don't pay on the
The camera.
So if the room is too large you know then we get in these weird
situations where like the, you know, the camera just does really
strange things.
I mean, I guess they're not strange per se but they're not helpful.
Like if you were a player playing this game, like, you wouldn't be
happy with what was happening here in terms of how the camera was
moving around and we've never really done any real camera code here.
And so, what I think we probably want to do today is just going in and
finish up working on the camera code.
Like, okay, you can see all that is kind of nuts.
What's happening there, right?
We're gonna go in here and just make something that's a little more
sane for how we're doing our camera control.
And that way, when we have something more saying for doing our camera
control, we can just go ahead and
Jimmy, we can just go ahead and have our
Our gameplay systems, dictate what the camera is supposed to do and
then it will be relatively straightforward for those systems to pick
what they want.
And so for example, you know, you could imagine a circumstance where
we want to sort of, Zoom, the camera in and out to control how
particular like region work.
So for example, let's say that we turned on the debug camera here,
right?
Let's see.
There we go.
So, one thing that we might want to do, let's say we had a really tiny
room, right?
Let's say the room was only this big.
Then we might want to like, zoom in to that room and sort of have it
so that we were all, you know, close in, you know, maybe that's a
little too close, but all closed in on the room because it's supposed
to feel like we're just focusing on that room, right?
But then, if a room is too large, you know, maybe a rooms really big
like this.
We may not feel like gameplay-wise.
The right thing to do is to zoom out all the way to the full scope of
the room because maybe it just gets too tiny and too difficult to
play, you know, I don't know, we don't know those answers ahead of
time.
So the important thing to do here, I think is just to make it so that
the camera system can do whatever we want it to do and then we can
have it so that as we're doing gameplay, we can sort of make decisions
on a case-by-case basis.
So maybe we want like, you know, you go in to talk to the shopkeeper
or something like this.
I'm not saying that there's a shopkeeper.
Anything but you know, you can imagine in a game where they're, you
know, you're going to go buy something at the store if you imagine
something like that happening and maybe that room is for a tiny, maybe
we want to zoom in on that and that's the grammar for that.
So you zoom in zoom out on rooms of a certain size but maybe once
rooms get to a size that's larger you know that's that's too large.
That exceeds some threshold that we set maybe then the camera just
pans around to follow the player in the room as necessary, right?
It's really hard to say which of those were going to want.
So like I said, I think we just want to kind of focus on making a
camera system that will allow us to do whichever of those we want to
do.
Okay.
So yeah.
So basically we have a lot of easy options here in terms of actually
setting the camera, right?
And so for example just to illustrate how the system is currently
working especially for
You know, we bounced around a lot here and especially for beginners.
It's probably hard to keep all the what's going on in, you know, in
all the different pieces of code and how they work in your head
because you know, we bounce around and we change them and we talk
about different ones at different times which is, you know again very
in keeping with how game to go and actually works you know typically
you have to bring up systems kind of together and, you know, you're
not just focusing on doing one thing, finishing it completely and then
move.
To the next sometimes that's the right answer but other times when you
try to do architecture, the answer is to kind of be more broad but you
know that can be very daunting for people who haven't done a lot of
these systems because they're trying to learn how to do the sum of the
program, the system and then there's also all this other stuff going
on and we're moving around.
In that can be pretty challenging when you're, you know, sort of first
starting out.
And so just to kind of reinforce what's going on here?
When we go into when we start playing the game, right?
And we've got
The camera.
The camera can actually be set at any distance above the Playfield
already, right?
Our debug camera isn't the only way that can happen.
There is a camera offset variable and you can see that.
Here.
So here's the game camera, right?
That we keep, it's basically just a struct that has some information.
It says, which entity its following.
It says what it's two positions were the one from the last frame, the
one from this Frame and it's got an offset.
And the offset is basically how far away from the central, like tiled
chunk position, which is this world position here.
Right?
The camera is and that's a three dimensional variables.
So not only can It displaced laterally and vertically in the room or
in the world, basically.
But it can also displace up and down.
And so if we want the camera to be back further, if you wanted to be
up higher, all we would have to do is just set that variable to be up.
Right?
You know set that Z value to be a greater value and we would zoom out
or at least that's how it's supposed to work, right?
So what we could say in let's just like again, to sort of illustrate
the example.
Let's just say that, you know, we have these sort of room entity sorts
of things here if we wanted to
We can introduce a variable that was like, hey.
Let's say there's a thing called camera, height.
Right, let's just say that's what there is and what we're going to do
is whenever we go into update and render world's, we're going to call,
remember how this works.
We call stimulate, and then before we're done and we call update in
Winter Park systems before we're done.
We call a function called update camera for any movement, which sort
of decides where it's going to move the camera to, to follow the
entity that the cameras ostensibly supposed to follow.
Right.
So given that, that's what we want to do.
What I can do is say inside the the code for that function.
Which is update camera for entity movement.
What I would say is in this in this function I think we can just read
out because we know which entity is the entity defining the room that
we're in.
We can just read out of there, what the camera height should be and
then set the camera height to that.
And so I just want to show how that will pop the Heights in and out as
we move from room to room.
I am, right?
And again this isn't going to be a good thing yet.
It's not going to look nice.
But I'm just trying to illustrate how we would go about constructing
that that beginning of the process.
So just knowing what the height should be right?
So here's well, I guess we have in room which is getting set.
So all I really need to do in here is say okay, here's the camera
offset, right?
You can see there that the camera offset is getting set and you can
see here it's getting set to a bunch of random stuff based on what the
entity.
Situation is.
So then what I can say is oh in addition to that, right?
I can set the camera height.
I can I can offset whatever we were going to use for our camera height
by a greater height.
Based on.
Whatever the room were in says the camera height should be right.
And so most rooms, well, maybe just have that set at zero perhaps.
And then, you know, we've got kind of that exact situation, right?
Here's the camera height for this room, whatever.
Okay.
But what we can do now is say, well, okay, now when we're actually
creating these rooms.
So when we say add standard room, right?
You can see here, you can go in and say, well,
when we want to create one of these things and we, you know, you
remember, we added sort of a brain ID for these rooms where as my ads
standard room,
You can see when we added the room, entity itself, right?
Which is right here.
We have the opportunity to set something for it.
If we wanted to write here when it's created and that will get
remembered so later we can look at it.
So what we could do is say, well let's just see what the maximum width
and height settings are for this room and maybe set the height based
on that, right?
So here's our radius X and radius, why
What I could do is say, well let's make the camera height, be
proportional to their difference from the default or something like
that, right?
So what I can do is say all right let's suppose that we had a like
diff value here or something like that and that was going to be like a
clamped value.
Let's say where I'm going to say all right it's got to be the can't be
greater than it.
Can't be less than zero but it's got to be something greater than 0
where I take.
Take the these two values here radius X and radius y, right?
I'll say radius x - its default which is 84 now.
And then I'll say take the maximum of
Both of these.
Right, where you say.
Okay, I take the maximum of the two radii eyes differences from the
default.
I don't want a lower value ever.
So like if there, if it's a smaller room, I'm not going to zoom closer
in at the moment.
I'm only going to talk about
Hang out and to take that difference and I'm going to make that
difference, be the camera height at the moment.
So for every tile outward we go, I'm going to move one unit upward.
For the camera, right?
At least that's the theory.
And so now you can see it's already sort of working to a certain
extent.
Now that we're in this room, you can see that we get a
zoom out that features the entire room.
Here we go.
We got the, I think we're doing something wrong with our Collision
detection there, because there shouldn't be a middle area between the
rooms, but we're going to get to that in a second.
And so now, you know, we're zoomed out a little bit more so we can see
the whole room at once.
And there, you can see that that it was a discreet jump in the zoom
level.
Right.
Did you see that?
Because again, we're not interpolating that that value yet, we're just
jumping it.
So whenever we move from room to room we definitely have that that
jump, right?
But now you can sort of see that we fit the rooms much.
Nicely.
So, you know, we get into situations where we have a longer room or a
narrower room and we adjust.
Okay.
And that's kind of nice.
Because now for game design purposes, if we want to write, we can
basically make the Playfield be whatever, we want it to be.
Now, what you'll notice here, this is the first time that's happened
so far.
When we've walked through it, you can kind of see that when we went
into this room here, the camera that that value is a very rough value
like that, that was just that ad hoc value that I picked.
And so if we actually wanted to see the whole room, right?
It would have looked like this, but that's actually what we got,
right?
So, it's not really looking at the whole room, the way that we would
want it to look at the whole room and so,
oh, and I just remembered why we're not doing good injection properly.
It's because we don't set room, we don't create corrosion boundaries
for the room yet.
So we already know why that is happening.
I already knew that yesterday, but forgot it anyway.
So, what's the reason for that, right?
Well, the reason for that and we'll sort of talk about this on the, on
the Whiteboard, I think is probably the most important the most
appropriate way.
I feel like we have to
Yeah.
One of these days, I'm going to get a graphics card, that's less than
10 years old.
So I can actually run Milton on it.
Reliably, I'm still using.
I'm using an old version of built-in because I don't have a graphics
card that really it's it's a it's a six-year-old graphics card in this
machine.
It's old anyway.
So room.
Camera.
Fitting.
So let's just talk about this problem briefly and I don't know that we
want to bother solving it really at this point but at least so you can
be aware of what the problem actually is.
And so, you know, we probably would solve it at some point, I don't
know, I guess it depends on whether we decide that we're going to use
this in this way or not.
So, what ends up happening, with camera fitting, right?
Is you can imagine, we've got you, if you've been following handmade
hero, you know, exactly how this sort of stuff works.
We've got a camera and the camera is
Down on the world, right?
This is our camera.
And this is z, right?
And we've got this sort of
plane here that we're looking down on, right?
And this is the world.
So, you know, the world is, is down here and the world is in these,
these Z slices, right?
Because it's a 2-D game, but in some sense we think of it as 3D.
So we actually, we actually do consider things having volume and
whatever.
But, you know, when we view it, we're sort of viewing a slice, slice
of stacked on top of each other.
So what ends up happening is these slices have always been the same
size.
And so from the cameras perspective, if we were to look at it, right?
If this is a room, what we've been typically doing is we've just been
hard coding, whatever the cameras, distance up was, right.
Here's the that viewing area.
Right.
So this rectangle here maps to this rectangle here, right?
This is top down we just been moving the camera back manually to see
however much of the room, we wanted to see.
So if we wanted to sort of make you know I just kind of tuned it to a
value that I thought looked appropriate and that's what we left it as
and that's a perfectly valid thing to do and that's how you want to do
that.
But we introduced a problem when we then say,
We don't know how big the room is, right?
Because if the room is only this big then we would pick a very
different value from how for how far the camera zooms out.
You know, because as the camera moves closer, this this viewing area
gets smaller.
And as the camera moves upward that viewing area gets larger, right?
So if the room is bigger, we want to move the camera further back and
if the room is smaller, we want to move the camera down.
But the key fact here is we don't know how much.
Right.
We have no notion of how much to move the camera.
So in the current system I just picked an ad hoc value.
Of 1 meter, right?
Per tile in radius.
Right?
That's what I did.
So I basically said all right, here's the standard room size.
Okay, you know, it's it's radius is at the moment its radii at the
moment.
Is eight tiles this way and five tiles.
Sorry for tiles this way.
So all I did was say, okay for every room, if you go over eight tiles,
right?
So if you get more than eight tiles out for every tile, you go out add
a meter to the height of the camera.
So if you were going to be out here, you would add one me to the
height of the camera.
Similarly for everyone you go out here, add one more to the hi to the
camera.
Now, since these two things don't
Add together.
Meaning, if I'm already moving out this far, I don't need to also,
move out again to capture this because movement of the camera upwards
expands the horizontal and the vertical range.
So, what that means is that I just take the maximum, I just said,
whichever one of these two, right is going to be greater use that
difference.
And by the way, if you go inside here don't bother because you know we
didn't we don't get closer in on ones that are lower at the moment we
have a quart of a minimum Zoom range.
Right?
So the problem here is that's a totally ad-hoc thing, right?
And you know, don't get me wrong, you can absolutely.
Ship a game with ad hoc stuff like that.
It happens all the time.
Hand-tuned constants, when they work, they work and you're done,
right?
So you don't need to belabor Technical Solutions to problems.
You don't actually have and so if this is good enough for you, then
you should just use it but we may get into situations where it's not
good enough, right?
And so it begs the question, what could we do?
That would be better.
Well, as you know it's just math, right?
It's not like we couldn't figure out how big the cameras viewing area
is when you get down to this particular distance from the camera,
right?
Because if we were to look at this again from the side, let's say so
this is perfectly sidon.
Here's the the viewing axis of the camera.
Right.
Viewing side on.
And here are like sheets.
And you can imagine, like, as we go down further in the camera, like,
maybe this is like three meters away and maybe this is five meters
away and maybe this is 7 and you know, looks like a little more.
So I mean that's 10.
I don't know.
So whatever distance away we are here.
Each time we go down.
We're widening that area, right?
Now, at any given for any given room, we know both things.
We would need to know to reverse our calculations, right?
We know how big the room is okay, because we know how big a tile is
and we know that if we make a thing that's
12 tiles by eight tiles.
Let's say we know how big that actually is in meters, right?
So we know if we were looking at one of these things, we know like oh
okay, if this is how far away it is from the camera and and we know
how big the room is maybe it occupies this much space, right?
We could easily compute both of, you know, we know this value, we
could easily compute this value and say well we know the camera is
viewing this much distance
We know we want to view this much distance.
So there's a gap here and it's like, is that Gap?
You know, we probably would have some value for The Gap.
How much of a gap do we want?
Or are willing to have any?
That Gap is too big or too small you know maybe the room just over
blows the size entirely so we know it's totally just marketers.
No Gap at all we can solve for the distance.
We would have to move the camera like how far out it has to be in
order to be that size, right?
And doing this is not that hard because it's
All just very simple, high school geometry.
Right.
It's just a case, it will trigonometry.
Sorry, I think is the correct categorization here.
It's just a case of similar triangles, right?
We have a situation.
Where we've got the camera here.
It's looking down here.
We know we've got, you know, and you could imagine, there's just the
other side of the, the of it here.
But we're only gonna look at the right triangle part of it, because we
know that it's just 2.
X is the distance here.
so, we know that if we have a
A ratio that can produce, you know, we know we know how to compute
these triangles, which we do know how to do.
If you go back to how we're going to production, will go over it
again.
If we know how to compute, one of these triangles for some distance
here.
Right.
So we know for the distance away from the camera.
We know how long this leg of the triangle is right?
We know this is basically the viewing with right?
It's a half the viewing with right.
Let's say so if we know how to compute half of Ewing with from the
distance
Then we know how to compute the complete viewing with the distance.
So if you give us some other viewing with right, we know that it's
just going to be a straight ratio of that one that we want, right?
Which would be you know, half the distance half the viewing with we
wanted which would be here.
This is like our desired with right over to so half the desired width
versus this thing.
We don't know which is the like desired distance, right desired
distance.
I guess these are some pad pie, huh?
Have too many D's here.
Let me try that one more time.
Let's try that one more time.
So we've got the width of the view and the width of the desired versus
the desired View.
And the desired.
Distance.
Right.
So we know this and this right?
Our ratio that we already know because we set up the camera so we know
how to generate these triangles.
Right.
We already know what these are.
So since we're prescribing, one of these, all we have to do is solve
for one of these, right?
Because these things set up an obvious ratio since they are similar
triangles.
We can easily just say that DV / w v equals d d.
Over WD.
It's just a similar triangle ratio of the sides have to be in ratio to
each other.
So solving for one of these is a simple as multiplying out, right?
So you just have DV / WV X through WD equals your DD, right?
It's just like I said, really simple high school math.
Nothing to it.
So as long as we know that ratio as long as we know, how to compute
that ratios for similar triangles, for our camera, which we had to do
to make the projection equations in the
First place.
Then we know how to produce that and again, we have to do this though,
keep in mind that it's, it has to be done for both of our axes if we
were to look at this top down again, right?
So here's the camera, it's looking down on things.
We have to know this for both of our axes.
So we have to know it for our viewing with and for our viewing height.
So we're actually going to have two of these equations where we end up
with two different distances.
One is the distance where we would exactly fit, you know, that the
camera would have to be up to exactly fit the width that we asked for.
And one would be to exactly fit the height that we asked for, right?
Because again, the screen is not a square.
The screen is a
Tangle.
So the computation will be different for each.
So we feed it a rectangle and say, okay, tell me for this with of a
room that I want, what is the width of what is the distance for the
camera to match it for this height of the room?
What is the height off the ground of the camera to match it right in
both cases?
We got to have ground.
We're going to end up with two camera distances, right to Heights of
the camera off the ground.
And it's kind of hard to I'm using height in two different ways here.
So, I guess I should just say for a, you know, for an X range and a y
range, what is the Z displacement?
The camera off of that plane, that will give me what I want, right?
I'm going to end up with two different displacement values, right?
So I'm going to have two different cameras.
He's so all I need to do is say well, okay, what I'm trying to do is
fit the whole room.
So I just want to take whichever one is greater because whichever one
is greater will Encompass, the more difficult thing to Encompass,
right?
You can imagine a room that was like very oblong, right?
So this width is very small, and this height is very big, right?
Well, the distance for the camera to Encompass, this room is going to
be something like that, right?
So obviously the
Value that the get back from solving, this is going to say well to fit
the width, you don't have to be very high.
But to fit the height, you have to be very high.
Obviously, we want to fit the height.
In the case, where we want to fit the whole room now.
So that's Max, right?
That's we would take the maximum of the two, but we might also want to
take again for gameplay, purposes may be wanting the minimum of the
two because the other way we could look at this problem is by saying
if there's a room that's really hablo like that, what I want to do is
see a whole, I want to fill the screen with the room, right?
So what I want to do is take whichever Dimension.
Fits the tightest.
And take that, and that would be men.
And then that's if we wanted to do screen scrolling because then we
would know we'd fit one axis.
Exactly.
And we'd scroll the other axis, right?
So hopefully that makes some sense.
Okay.
So how would we actually do that if we want to do that?
And I guess we don't need the game running at the moment.
What would we actually do there?
Well, if you remember, go back to render group, you go down to the
bottom.
And if you remember, there's a bunch of stuff that we were doing here
that already sort of involved, all these things.
Right?
So you can see a bunch of this stuff down at the bottom of the
function here.
And we have, like, for example, this thing called on Project where you
give it an object transform and pixels x Y, which is basically like
the the
The pixel position of the thing that you want on Project, right?
And it undoes the projection pushes it Forward, right?
And so, what you can see here is if we have an orthographic transform.
Well, we don't care about that kind of thing because we're doing a
perspective transform for our geometry.
So, the orthographic transform is really not relevant.
That's for like you I and stuff.
But if you take a look at this other one here, you can see, okay?
So we kind of know how to unprotect stuff off the screen.
If we take a screen location and we subtract whatever the center of
the screen is right?
Then we multiply it by our m, 2 pixels to get it into World space.
So we're it's coming in and pixels and we want
Buy it.
Bye-bye.
We have M to pixels and we want pixels to M.
So we're inverting it.
Right?
Then we go ahead and take the distance above the target - however far
away.
The thing is, and we divide that by our focal length, we then multiply
by, we take that
ratio.
Which again, is that similar triangle ratio is just talking about and
we multiplied by a to get, which is the the pick M value.
We look at their to get where we would be in World space, right?
That pretty much tells us exactly the equations we were looking for
before, right?
So we, this right here, is that ratio right the transform distance
above Target - Ossipee?
That's the distance, right?
And then this focal length here that we divide by
that's the thing that actually,
To the ratio that tells us about the similar triangles, right?
So once we have a value that's in meters, it's pretty trivial for us
to get it back, right?
So,
if we want it to,
We could go ahead and say here, all right.
Let's create something.
That will tell us this information that we want to know if I am going
to pass in some kind of a rectangle, right?
So I this is exactly the function, I just talking about if I say I
want to, you know, get distances get you know, camera distance for
rectangle,
Or maybe like fit camera distance to rectangle or something like that.
so if we want to, we can pass in the dimensions of our rectangle and
then this information here,
So assuming that the object that we're talking about is that this
transform and it has this Dimension right?
What is the distance that the camera would have to be off of the plane
in order to give us what we want?
and so given that we pretty much know like I sang for
we know that the distance above the target, which is
okay, we know that this camera transform, right?
Which is set for our render group.
This camera transform is going to, give us the distance above the
Target that we're looking for and the object, transform offset, P .z.
That's going to give us.
That's going to give us the focal length.
That's that plus the focal length.
The transform is going to give us that ratio.
Now, you'll note, we don't really need the offset Z here, right?
It's really just, we could just use essentially the focal, length
input, the focal length and a z-value to
they're right, those, those could be
Those could be the pieces of information that we actually pass into
the routine.
But I'll keep it like this for now, just for a second and we'll get
see what we want to do in a minute, right?
So
if we compute that ratio right, what we've got here is this is
expanded out a little bit here, right?
This is our Z value.
In fact, I can actually even just name them what they were here if you
take a look at
No.
If we take a look at this here, right?
We've got our DV and rwv, right?
So those are
The focal length.
So it's kind of tough to describe focal length as well because it's
sort of a
It's sort of an odd concept, right, but the focal length of the lens.
We talked about before is if you imagine
This were an actual camera.
The the image plane of the camera is sort of back behind the camera
lens, right?
Here's the lens and the focal length is where that image.
The focal length of the lens is where it Focus how far back from the
lens.
It takes to sort of converge the the light, right?
I can get a better diagram for this.
I'm sure, here you go.
So when the lens, you know, when you have if you imagine a curve lens
here, right?
The focal length of the lens is from that lens shape.
It's how far it takes to converge the light to a point, right?
So I probably this is kind of a misleading way to draw this.
I mean, really, it's like,
That sort of thing, right?
Because the lens is an actual is not a point, right?
The lens is an actual shape.
So anyway, the focal length is, is that distance there, right?
And it's basically saying from the imaginary lens back to the point
where the light converges and then from that point, right?
The light and it's not like when I said I wanted a better diagram, I
guess this isn't really the diagram I wanted.
Because I wanted to show the light converging.
And then diverging again basically like the focal length is here and
then this sort of reversal of the light.
As it passes through, that one point, then has a an image plane or
something like the film of the camera or whatever.
The CCD of a digital camera, where the light is getting sort of
placed, right with the lights getting collected and we don't simulate
any of that in our pipeline.
Or anything like that.
Some Advanced 3D pipelines will try to simulate things for this,
right?
But for our purposes, right?
It's just this value here, right?
And so in order for us to know what we are, expecting this value to be
right here is the focal length.
So that's the focal length.
But this value right here, we don't actually know what that is, right?
We that's not in this equation here, right?
And you can kind of see that it's that it's not being, you know, it's
not represented here, right?
So what is that actual you know what is that actual value?
Well, we do have that value.
It's just not in its not stored in there for the camera, transform.
Where we have M to pixels screen center, focal length.
This is about Target and all that stuff, right?
What we actually needed was the monitor have Tim in meters, right?
The monitor half-demon m is the thing that tells us how wide the
screen actually is at that focal length, right?
So for that distance away, we know that the monitor half-demon m is
actually how big the monitor itself will be and that wasn't relevant
in our unprojected because nobody in the unprotect cares, how big the
monitor is, right?
That's just not relevant.
Because I mean, in some sense, they do, but it's baked into m 2
pixels, right?
M, 2 pixels, already captures that for the purposes of unprojected,
which doesn't care.
What the actual extents of the monitor are in any particular way,
right?
So now if we want to compute this ratio, we know we've got the focal
length, which is that distance and we know that we've got the monitor
half dim in meters.
Which is the either, the width or the height of modern painting on
which one we want, but it's half of it, right?
So at that point, we can easily just go.
Okay, we know we can, I don't know why I've got this as e here.
We know, we can compute exactly this triangle relation by using this
as the monitor half-demon.
M, this as the focal length, right?
And then we can solve for this using this input, which is the dim,
right?
Because it's only
One leg.
We don't know me.
All right.
So let's just continue down this road a little bit.
So when in fact what we could do here is safe it camera distance
instead of two rectangle.
I think what I might do is make two of these right fit camera distance
to
Two Dimension, right?
And what fit cameras in two Dimension would be.
We say, all right, for the monitor half dim in meters and a dimension
in meters.
And then the focal length.
For those three values.
All, that's all I need to know to compute this ratio.
So all I need to do is say, my result is going to be the focal length,
right?
Which again is, is this DV here, right?
And we solve the equation, there's the DV X.
Whatever that Dimension is, that I was looking for mentioning m.
/, whatever /, whatever that that monitor have Tim was
But this of course has to be halved as well because we're only looking
at half so we might as well just say half dimension in meters so that
way if that's what people happen to have they have it otherwise they
can multiply it by 2.
Right?
I mean I divide it by 2 or X .5
So that computes are similar triangle for one dimension, right?
And it gets us back.
You can see the conversion happening.
Pretty directly.
If you think about the dimensional analysis, right?
You've essentially got a focal length, you're trying to solve for
another focal length.
So you multiply the focal length by the dimension that you're actually
looking for and you divide it by the dimension that, you know, is the
screen dimension.
And that's the ratio right there that you're looking at, right?
You could you could view it, alternatively more.
This, if it because it makes a little more sense, perhaps, right?
Where you say, if I divide these two Dimensions by each other, because
those are two things that I know that are in the same space, then I
can multiply by the focal length to get out some other focal length.
That's essentially going to be the distance that I want the camera to
be at, right?
So,
Since this is all over the monitor half-demon M, that's good.
Because that way we're never going to divide by zero because we know
that the monitor cannot be zero.
We should not be getting to this point if it is, right?
So we could guard this, but I'm not going to.
That's if you like size the window, all the way down to zero.
I think we just don't want that to be allowed.
So, what we would do, if we allowed sizing of that nature, I think we
would just not, we would just not call the game render loop.
At all, if we detected the monitor size of zero,
So anyway, fit camera distance to rectangle that is going to now want
to do this twice.
So what that's going to do is say like okay, we've got a, you know, a
dimension or a result rather which is just two calls to this.
And that's going to call it with all of these same pieces of
information, right?
And when we do fit cameras, direct angle, I guess what I'd say is,
let's just go ahead and do it this way.
Speaker names.
Maybe something like that.
I don't know.
I'm not sure.
Is this a still half dim?
I guess they're both the same, really?
Honestly, they're the same.
so, if we go ahead and call this,
Halftime in all cases and then we just have two versions of it.
You know, one you can call with a veck to and one that you don't and
then we just pass it through.
So that is a way to just sort of say, okay?
You know, we're going to do an X and A Y version together here if you
want to.
That's the same equation, doesn't matter.
It's just giving.
It's just doing it with a vector, right?
So no big deal there.
And so once we have that function, now we should be able to compute
the values that we wanted to compute in order to get information about
the camera transform.
Now, one of the interesting things about the camera transform in this
case again, is this kind of ad hoc so.
You know, we're probably clean this up a little bit when we do the 3D
version of it, but you can see that it's got a distance above Target,
that's inside the camera transform.
And so what we kind of want to do here is
And that's going to get taken into account.
So, whatever value this gives us back is actually has to be compared
against the distance above Target because it's not like the value we
set for the camera.
Doesn't include that it does.
So if we take a look for example, at World mode, right?
And we go in here,
And here you can see us trying to do with the camera stuff.
Here's the distance above ground, it's just set to 11, right?
And so that distance above ground value is kind of baked into
everything and to be honest I guess I don't really know why.
It is set that way.
Sorry Justin Smoak Target.
Because really, that distance above Target value seems like the sort
of thing that should just be set off the camera off set directly,
right?
I mean, if you think about it, there's not a whole lot of reason why
you would not want that to just be all part of the camera offset,
right?
So the fact that that
Since above Target, is there at all, is kind of weird and doesn't make
a whole lot of sense to be honest.
Because it just seems like
You're just putting a lot of weird stuff.
In there for no reason, right?
I mean, here's the camera transform, right?
And this distance above Target is really the camera position in Z
essentially.
But what you'll notice about that is, it doesn't include any other
positional information for the camera, which is kind of bizarre,
right?
Like, if you were going to include an offset for the camera inside the
camera transform, which of course, makes plenty of sense, you would
expect it to be a veck 3 because you would expect it to be a thing
with says, hey, you know, here's
The displacement that you apply to everything before you transform it,
right?
But instead, we only have a z transform that we apply in there.
And why we do that?
I have no idea because you'll also notice that we ended up deciding to
do here is in the object transform.
Which is right here.
We bake in the camera position to that transfer, right?
So we're essentially doing that because we don't have any way to not
do that because the camera transform itself isn't allowing us to
specify an actual Veeck three, right?
Which doesn't make a whole lot of sense when you get right down to it.
And if you take a look at what's happening with that camera pz there,
right?
We're using that value out of the camera P, but really, it's more
appropriate.
That that should have been something that was in the camera,
transformed to begin with, because that's what that actually means.
We're now sort of having a pass to things all the time a camera
transform.
But then wait, no really.
The also, the camera transform, right.
And that's just kind of dumb.
It doesn't really make very much sense, so,
Maybe let's take the opportunity here.
Oops.
Maybe let's take the opportunity there to just correct that oversight
such as it is.
And so when we have this is above Target, I'm just going to say, let's
say that this is the camera.
P.
And so we'll set the camera position in World space in our camera
transform.
And then that will just apply everywhere, right?
And that seems better.
So if we just do that, then what we should be able to do is say okay
whenever we have like distance above Target here,
Whenever we're using that somewhere else, what we want to do is just
apply that transform completely, right?
It's going to get applied on top of
The all of the other piece of information that we have here, you can
see that all the rest of this stuff right?
Where we have rho, XY and all that stuff, and original p + object
transform and all that, you know, stuff.
So when we have our row XY, that's our p.
X y, that's coming in here and being done with the object transform
and all that stuff.
What we should be able to do is say, oh, all right.
Take the p.
X y and add the camera transforms.
X Y to it, right?
Well not add subtract right because wherever you move the camera,
everything going to center around it, so subtract that away, right?
And then when we want distance above Target, okay, we can just look at
that Z value that we have their right and then the rest of our stuff
just flows.
Normally there's there's nothing else that has to happen there, right?
Similarly when we want this piece of information here, right?
We have to do the same thing but we have to do it in reverse so we've
got our camera P here and we're going to do that again that same
subtraction so to find the distance from the difference from where the
camera is in that case to finish the on Project to me.
And then we also have to do the exact same thing when we then figure
out what the result is of our own projection or rather, when we
produce our world space piece of information.
Remember what we were doing is we're doing this displacement and then
we're projecting.
So now we need to unprotect and then do the displacement.
So we've done the on projection here, we then have to go ahead and
say, okay, whatever, our unprojected XY is, we have to then add the
camera transform back in.
So in this case, right, we could change this result.
Well, I guess because it's got the offset pay for the whole thing.
When we go ahead and do that on Project, X Y, we can just add into it.
The transform camera.
Peas, xy2, like restore that part of the transform, right?
So when we say, get camera rectangle, at Target, this is again just
doing the same sort of unprotect here.
And so when that place is distance, when that calls camera transform
can't above Target, we just want to
Say for the camera peas Z value, that's all that piece of information
is actually giving us in this case.
Now when we call the perspective transform what we're going to want to
do is say okay what we actually want to do is pass a whole camera P
here.
And similarly, although my head is in the way.
Let's just kind of scroll down there little bit.
When I say, distance from Target here, equals one point O we again,
can just say, well, alright, we have a camera p, and that can be equal
to.
That effectively what the same thing was.
So now whenever we call perspective and we want to say distance above
Target, the question is now just, where is the actual camera P?
Right?
And so, if you look at where the camera p is getting computed, let's
find out here in update and render worlds.
Should be getting called down here somewhere.
There it is.
Here is our world mode camera offset World transform offset P nonsense
right?
All of this stuff now hopefully we can sort of take away and make a
little bit cleaner right?
Second.
Okay, so let's see if we can do that.
So you can see in this case, when we call simulate, it's not relevant,
right?
Because simulate doesn't actually oh wait, no it is.
So here's our world mode camera offset that's getting past their
right?
And so the goal here is to sort of get rid of that world mode camera
offset, right?
We want this to look like that.
So the world mode camera offset is actually just part of that camera
P.
That's getting set up in the first place, right?
So the world mode camera offset.
I don't think it's actually touched anywhere in here.
It doesn't look like it is.
So I'm just going to go ahead and put it in here for now.
There you go.
And we'll see, we'll we'll give it a shot.
So here in simulate
just here, it's taking this camera all set.
I'm just gonna get rid of that and I'm going to get rid of everywhere,
we were passing it.
So I'm just I'm just getting rid of that pull chain of custody there,
right?
Where people were passing that down.
Which is good, right?
We want to simplify that and then we just need one in cure for the
this is for the
The layered scene rendering and you can see in here, we actually have
a camera offset value, which is what we were using here and that
camera offset value is probably getting applied all the time, right?
You can see it getting applied all in here, rather than rewrite that
code.
I'll just leave it the way it is at the moment, but you could imagine
making this simpler as well to do.
We could simplify this potentially in the future by changing the
camera situation here.
And so, then all we really have to do is take this entity stuff which
was taking into account before, and if we want to we can literally
just get it out of the render group because it's there.
And that should actually be all, I think we really need to do.
So let's double-check
Epically successful.
You always gotta love staring at a blank stream, blank screen.
So yeah, you'll notice, this is why I decided to do this first before
blanking, before, trying to do the other thing at the same time
because I had a feeling we were going to have to trace the thrill more
carefully.
And I suspect that that I suspect that that blank screen, indicates
that, that is correct assumption.
So you can see that we're just using the camera peas.
Z values here,
That's all.
That's really getting done.
And oh right.
And so this offset P now is already always going to take that into
effect, right?
So, the offset P of the entity transform.
No longer has to have that information in it and that is at least one
Improvement that was.
Yeah, that was going to cause problems.
But so the camera P getting used, let's see where this is going to be
used here.
So,
That camera P getting used to figure out these typical floor height
piece of information.
Again, that's something that we want to get rid of entirely
eventually.
So, yeah, we're going to have to do something about that, it at some
point.
But, you know, for now, I think that should have still been working,
right?
We should still have been able to use the camera P there, that
shouldn't have been causing us any problems.
I don't think.
Right?
So I'm guessing and I don't actually know, but all we really need to
do is just to restore to our offset system.
The concept that we had a basis of 11 meters before so this distance
above ground,
Lb is bright.
This is not in there anymore.
And so, I think if we just now say that our base camera offset,
because remember, we're setting the camera offset here in add standard
room.
I think all we have to do is say our standard camera offset.
Now just has to be taken into account when we are creating that camera
height piece of information.
So instead of just the diff what we actually want is that base value
of 11
Plus the death.
And I think that may be it Famous Last Words course, it's not, let me
just check something here.
So you can see that we do have the correct camera placement.
What we do not have is the correct camera distance which is I guess,
perhaps unsurprising, do not know where our rectangles wind so that's
always good, right?
This doesn't, this actually doesn't have the debug camera on.
And it's going, okay?
That's interesting.
Offset, just slightly.
Vertically.
All right, so we have a couple of problems here to address.
One is that we still got a little bit of bugging us going on there.
The other is of course, since our rooms are not the right size in when
we create that room Collision because the room Collision volumes are
always marked as the same size.
We have this problem that where we start, our entity is not actually
in a room, right?
And that's a bug.
So that's a problem obviously but you know, we can deal with that in a
second are more pressing problem is we don't seem to have that value,
correct.
And also are rectangles are not drawing correctly, which makes me
think that that we've done something incorrect with our the way our
rectangles are working and I'm not sure why that is the case.
So we'll have to kind of think about why that is, let's see here.
So that looks really to have Lee.
Okay, so let's let me just go ahead here and just double-check
something.
So here's me walking to the left.
You can see as soon as I get into the room.
Boundary, we end up centering ourselves horizontally correctly, but
but vertically, not which is, which is pretty interesting, right?
And I'm not sure exactly what the reasoning is for that because it
seems like that should not be the case and I'm not sure why, that is
the case.
So,
Since the camera p is getting applied here by the you know every time
something gets transformed we subtract away.
Whatever the camera is location.
Is there Jimmy?
We have to figure out sort of what, exactly, let's see.
We have to figure out what exactly is happening.
In terms of setting, that, that is bogus
So, I'm passing the offset from the world mode here and that camera
all set.
Again should just be
It shouldn't be anything special because it should be exactly the same
things that we were passing before with no real change there.
Because now we're passing a height.
That's a Delta off of the height that we were expecting and so that
seems totally reasonable.
I'm sorry.
Passing in height there that includes the the value that we were
previous setting to and the Delta.
So that should be the same.
So the only difference here is rather than baking that into our
drawing stuff.
I guess, what?
Oh, well, there's a couple of places here that
I suppose that we might have used this.
Suppose I should double-check with those are.
So if I look at camera dot offset p and where that's getting used.
Right.
Which is sorry camera.
Just camera done offset.
Yeah.
So it looks like I'm still doing that in a couple of places here that
that probably don't want to be done.
Now, this one for the world transform here, this is only done for
doing those outlines of like the world, rectangles that stuff so that
shouldn't have affected anything.
But at least that simplifies that code a little bit for updated
rendered particle systems.
The world mode camera offset.
Doesn't shouldn't actually need to be applied at all anymore.
So, if I take a look at the particle systems code in update and
render,
Ecosystems and we look at that camera p, in theory.
In theory, we should not have to do this anymore.
Now, floors e on the other hand, we would have to do and that's Again,
part of that sort of nastiness that we were trying to do, was to keep
everything sorted into layers and that sort of stuff.
But this offset P for the transform.
Now, is already, is, is getting remembered properly, so and pass
through properly in the camera itself, so I believe that part to be
unnecessary now.
So let's double check here.
Yeah, but we're not getting those particles properly.
So we still have something wrong.
You can see kind of there's like particles over there.
But those are incorrect and we're still not getting our floors
correctly.
And so I think most of this probably just has to do with the Z sorting
for floor information, right?
And to be completely honest with you, I don't super remember how we
did this weird floor stuff, one of the reasons I wanted to move to the
3D thing was specifically because the floor is e stuff is just really
weird, right?
So okay so you can see what's going on here.
It looks like the floor is easy stuff is gets combined with distance
above Target.
So basically now that the cameras e includes that piece of information
Yeah, not a smart way to do this, that's going to be wrong.
You know what I'm saying?
Because the floor is e is is not the correct piece of information.
It doesn't need to take this into account, right?
So the fact that that camera pz is getting used there at all, is
actually wrong as well, because that's getting accounted for again
after the transform.
So really, this doesn't need the camera P anymore.
Pretty much at all and let's just remove that entirely from the
pipeline.
There you go.
And so now in theory.
Yeah, there we go.
So now we have restored our particles back because we fixed that CC
displacement.
That was happening there.
And again, that's felt good because like a lot of that stuff was just
too hacky and it was, you know, it's stuff that's in there because we
were sort of trying to figure out how to handle the like sort of
pseudo having to render to 3D stuff in 2D thing that I never was
really happy with because it just creates all weird problems like
that.
We're like okay, these are weird coordinates and having to deal with
all this stuff, it just doesn't seem to make.
Whole lot of sense why I wanted to move away from him, okay?
So the particles are restored in, that's good.
Now let's take a look at the entities.
And again, let me see what we actually use that camera P4.
So when we're looking at camera, relative ground Z here, I think
that's still needs to take that into account, obviously, it does, but
if you take a look at what that was doing this again, doesn't include
that displacement.
Or I should say.
Previously, that was not including the displacement right of 11.
It was not including that.
Any of those displacements.
Right?
So I don't really know what to say about this because
You know, I think in some sense this is just totally wrong.
This has to be grounded.
This has to be a Delta value off of something, right?
Essentially, this has to be
That right, in order to get back the value we were doing, which is how
far away are we from our Baseline value, which is kind of nuts, right?
Which is again, why I say this is not a particularly good way to do
this.
and if you look at the camera, relatives ground Z I think
The same thing applies here, right?
If you were going to subtract this again, you have to remove that
default value because this code was written, assuming that it was just
a displacement from normal, which again, is is not correct, right?
So yeah, so not great.
And again, not really what we want to have happen there but there you
go.
Right.
So now things are at least getting a little more same but they're
still not as sane as they should be, right?
And I think again,
This is why I would like to move to 3D to sort of prevent having that,
that sort of constant annoyance of having that problem, but at least
getting back to a more saner approach.
Right.
And I don't know how far we need to go down that rabbit hole of of
actually cutting us out because I think what we really want to do is
just convert to a nice clean 3D version of it and then we don't have
to worry about any of these because they won't cost me won't cost
them.
But wait.
Okay, how do we want to handle floors versus this or whatever?
Right.
So yeah, so that's all pretty nasty and probably should get just we'll
just get cleaned out when we go to straight 3D.
Now, the problem here again, though is
We still have a couple other things even just for Baseline to make
this work correctly, that we would want to do.
So, for example, what we would want to do first is make sure that our
rooms actually have the sizes that are rooms, should have, that's
like, obviously something we would like to fix.
So let's go to add standard room here.
And just see what we can do about fixing.
That fact, so what we can do for now again because we don't really
have a strong opinion on this either way, since we haven't really done
World gen yet, what we can do for now is just create any Collision
volume groups as we go, right?
So instead of doing room Collision here, we can just make one of those
every time.
Yeah.
Where we make a simple grounded Collision volume for every room based
on how big the room actually is right.
So we knew here that we have how many tiles we have?
We know that information because we know the radius.
So it's just 2 times radius X Plus 1 and 2 times.
Radius y plus 1 and that gives us the information that we want.
So then we have the tile side in meters, which we don't actually know
at the moment but we could easily have someone tell us, right?
And in some set chunk position from tile chunk position from tile
position needs to know that as well.
So you know that's going to be in the world struct that we can grab
out, right?
So we can go ahead and say, all right, whatever the tile side is in
meters, there you go.
Wait.
Position from tile position position from tile position needs to know
that piece of information, right?
It's just fantastic.
I guess we just sort of said, well here's that value.
Pretty fancy, huh?
Yeah.
So that's pretty ugly.
So
We probably want to do there is to at least make this a value that we
know globally for the time being and probably we want since that's not
going to be constant, will probably want something a little more sane
pretty soon in the world creation stuff that makes that, you know,
less of a thing.
I would really like it if my head was not in the way.
So I think I'm going to move over here.
All right.
So, basically what we're substituting for at the moment is, you know,
we sort of have this hacky World Jerry stuff because we need some
World Gentoo test.
But what we really want, is some utilities for building worlds.
And when we're building those worlds in a local region, we're going to
presumably want to set a tile size for talking about tiles but our
game isn't hard coded to Tiles at all.
It can be nice and variable and we probably want to take advantage of
that.
So what we're going to need to do is sort of have ways of
constructing, okay, this area is a grid.
This area is not a grid, here's how to work it.
So we really are
Sort of compensating for that at the moment.
And so I don't think there's any need to try and look at that now.
So I just want that as a global.
So No One's Gonna even think about it or care about it and it doesn't
have to be something that anyone even is thinking about temporarily.
And then when we go to, actually make something a little more creative
there for the world stuff that's the that's the better part to start
addressing that, right?
So I'm going to go ahead and do it this way here.
Are we have a
We have one of these for room.
And that's got to be moved up.
Okay.
So think we're good and now at least our rooms correctly, have their
bounds and you can now kind of see that being placed in here properly.
Can see that the bound properly encompasses?
The actual room which previously it didn't, right?
And so now we get nice.
We get correct movement through and we don't have that weird like in
between Zone anymore, you're always either in a room or you're not and
that's, you know exactly what we wanted.
Now, one thing that you'll notice this is still happening bug Ali
though is this screen is kind of offset from the bottom, like a room
is not centered in the view.
It's it's
It's skewed in.
Why?
You see what I'm saying?
So, the offset of of our view in y is erroneous.
And so, I think what we want to do because we still have about 20
minutes left, or so, 25 minutes left on stream.
I'd like to just get to the bottom of that again.
Not because that code will actually stick around necessarily because
as we go through and do the cleaning up of the three, dienes of it
all, I feel like that will go away but
At least at the moment, I would just like to know where the source
that bug is just to make the code AS correct as possible going into
the 3D cleanup pass.
So we're not spending our time, tracking down bugs that might be in
something that had nothing to do with the change to 3D.
So I'd like to have that if that makes sense.
Even though the code is not super important at this point, right?
So let's go ahead and make that happen.
Let's first go ahead and ask ourselves the question of how are we
centering that camera?
Right?
What is that?
Actual piece of information that were using?
And I believe the way that that we're doing that currently if you go
ahead and look at some region is, you know, update camera for entity
movement is going to take whatever the in-room value is there.
And it's going to
It's going to use that.
To compute the room relative P so you can see here, we've got the room
relative p and the test Senate EP there, right?
So the room relative P that it computes for figuring out where it
thinks the player is, is going to be based off of that test data
teepee.
However, the test that a tea
The room campy, which is where we think the camera is for this room.
In general is the test entity P location as well.
If we take a look at what happens here, however, the camera offset
itself is not initialized to be the difference between the test and a
disposition and the actual
How should I phrase this?
So the offset of the camera because remember, everything's in local
space to our Sim region.
So everything's been mapped into a thing.
That's
On the same region origin.
But the same region origin is set arbitrarily, right?
I mean we know what it sets you because we can go look.
But in order for this code to be technically correct, it shouldn't
depend on what the same origin was set to the same origin.
Should be able to set to anything and this code should still set the
camera in the correct position.
So what we want to say here is the camera offset, right?
Where we believe the camera to be for purposes of rendering, that
should be based on the difference between wherever the camera.
There, simulation region is, which is where all the positions relative
to the camera should be recorded in that space, right?
So now rather than doing things that we were doing them before this
camera offset Z is not the only thing that should actually be getting
updated here, right?
What should actually be getting updated is
The entire entity, the cameras entire placement itself.
Right.
So whatever room were in we should center around that room.
That's where the camera should be if that makes sense.
So whenever we're yeah, whenever in a room, our camera Center should
always be wherever that room is now at the moment, our Sim region, I
believe anyway is always set up to have itself in centered around
there anyway.
So I don't think there's actually any
Difference between the code.
I just wrote executing now and the code that we as it was exiting
before, but
There's a little bit of flashing at that transition point.
I'm not sure why hold on one second.
Want to take a look at that.
Anyway, was going to say before was but I believe that's still more
correct, right?
So simulation that's what I want.
So it's just at the changeover point I'm assuming that has something
to do with the fact that it's not in any room at all.
Maybe.
So I'm not sure what happens in that one case because if we're not in
any room at all, then in theory we should not be modifying the camera
offset.
And so, I don't think there should actually be any changes here to
that.
Now that may not be true someone else.
Maybe setting that camera off set somewhere because, you know, there
was no rule in the code base about when you could set the camera off
set to something.
So I don't actually know that that's true but I, you know, I didn't
think that there was anything happening there in particular.
Let me take a quick look and see who actually touches this.
Just so I can eliminate that from the set of possibilities.
So that's nice and clean.
I mean, nobody touches that thing except these two routines, right?
So that's that's good.
I mean that's where we want to be but we still have the bug so we're
not out of the woods yet just because the code is getting cleaner.
So what I would like to do is I would like some information to try and
figure out whether or not the case that I'm seeing does coincide with
what I suspect.
So, all I want to do here is create an assertion.
In fact, I can create this assertion.
I guess without the if statement I can just say, I want to create an
assertion.
So it'll fire when we are not in a room, right?
And then I can see whether that assertion appears to fire at the exact
time when we were seeing the flash or whether it's not
And that will help me tell if those are correlated.
Okay.
It doesn't actually seem to be doing it right now which is odd.
Let me drop the time, step down.
So, I'm definitely seeing the flash there.
Hmm.
so, I guess what I would say is,
This may just be an artifact of the fact that this particular piece of
code here is just based on a room Delta, which doesn't really have
anything to do with anything, right.
Because if you take a look at what's happening here at the room, Delta
is just whatever the size of the room is, but that's not actually
correct because if the other room is a different size from this room
than the room, Delta isn't properly half what it should be.
Although if we only are going half way, then the other room should go
the other half way when we pan.
So to come
Give it, I don't know.
That's not actually a good enough reason to really it seems like
that's actually still should be some inaccurate.
So I don't know what the problem is here with this offset at that's
still a good question.
I guess.
What I would say is, maybe let's go ahead and just not do this offset.
Here's a thought for you.
So that changeover would coincide with the time when the Sim region
moves from one block to the next block because we're changing the
camera's base location here.
Right.
So what I could totally believe is happening, is this offset will be
used on the next pass.
Right?
So if we set it to the new room,
we are going to compute a camera P, which is erroneous.
Because it's going to be working off of the I'm sorry, we're going to
compute an offset that's erroneous because it's going to be working
off of the old.
Location of the Sim region rather than the new one.
Does that make sense?
So what we need to do here is when we detect that we've moved from one
room to the other or rather, whatever room that we're actually in.
rather than using,
A comparison with the room apron here.
What we actually need to do is first compute the
what we actually need to do here is
Is compute the offset that we would have had before we changed rooms
or not?
Touch it at all?
I think, because let's just go back over exactly how this is flowing
through the pipeline here.
Right?
Because here's update, candidate update and
Update camera for entity movement, right?
So here's update camera for any movement, it's going to call it at the
end and it's going to get called.
It's going to do this operation after.
Everything's already been drawn for this Frame.
So the next frame is going to use whatever.
It's like one frame behind, right?
Is one way to think about it which we may not like, right?
We may want this to try and be one frame.
To not be one from have to be synchronized but you know, for taking an
argument.
Okay let's just take a look at what's gonna happen in the current
case.
So we're going to come through here and we're going to compute a
offset and a location for the same region and those are going to be
used for next time, right?
So when we do this computation, we have to be careful that we're not
doing anything in a space that has to do with where the Sim region is
now because the offset is going to get used for a different location
of the same region, right?
So, I just want to verify, or I want to take a look to see to make
sure that we're never that we're not doing that at all, right?
So, for example, here's the camera offset and here's the in room P,
okay?
That in room p is wrong.
As far as the next Sim region is concerned, right?
Because the next Sim region is actually going to be the new location
of the origin.
So when the Sim region changes over, there is no way to avoid the fact
that this is going to actually be incorrect.
Sadly, right?
So in some sense, me trying to make this code better right?
By saying, oh, let's take the offset into account actually, made it
worse.
Like, this is probably what's causing that displacement because at
that.
Changeover point.
It's wrong.
If that makes sense.
So let me go do it one more time here.
And again, I'll slow that percentage way down so we can see it easily.
So there's that scroll
Crap.
And let's go ahead and put it back in.
What happened?
Huh.
ah,
I wonder when we did our update of the Grid's, if we forgot to do
because you notice our Loop Live code, editing had a problem when we
did our updated the quiz to handle the GCC compat, if we don't copy
them anymore,
If that makes sense.
Hold on a second.
I want to take a look at that.
So
so it looks like we do copy both of these four pieces of information
when we do get element from event here.
So I'm not sure that that should have introduced any particularly
Generous stuff.
We take a look at that.
And you can see that the bug is back, right?
So I think that we can say that this is in fact, the culprit
unfortunately it does look like that's a pretty transient bug because
I can't
Seem to get it to come back.
But yeah, so you can see that that, that problem would persist there.
So I guess we just kind of have to say that hey that camera offset
always has to be
Always has to be assumed to be the center of the same region.
So maybe I'll just document that and we'll leave it like that for now.
Okay.
So, I'm not sure.
That there's that, there's anything else look at here.
Other than that, displacement now and we know that the same region is
properly being created at the camera Center.
So I'm not super sure why we're getting that displacement.
Which looks like the centering is wrong for what the 0 0 value is, but
I'm not 100% sure.
So I just want to take a quick look at that to see what the status is
there.
So let's go ahead and zoom in here, right?
We got to have a better know why.
That's so unsafe.
Our Delta code is so unstable there.
It's like rounding error, basically, right?
That it flips between.
Anyway, if you take a look at where that zooming in on, it's
definitely, you know, it seems to be zooming in to the center point.
Just fine.
It just doesn't seem like the room is centered on that Center Point,
if that makes sense.
Or rather the camera is centered on the room Center Point.
And I'm not sure why that would be, that's a good question because if
everything is relative to those coordinates, you would think that it
would have to be the case that you would not have any kind of
displacement of a tile in that direction.
And since we know the bounds of the room are, what the bounds of the
room are, right?
We should know where the center of the room is as well and we should
know that it's that's in the correct location, right?
So I'm not 100% certain why we sort of are having that that particular
issue.
I think about what possible causes there could be for that.
And why we would not be getting that sort of centering.
You know, it probably is because the Sim region isn't sized to the
room.
That could be one reason.
So let's take a look here.
So when we grab a Sim region here, you can see the Sim bounds use, get
the standard room Dimension, right?
And so, what's going to happen?
There is, you know, it is going to be centered about the same place,
but it's going to be sized differently.
I don't know why that would cause any problems, though.
It doesn't seem like it should.
But maybe there's something subtle there that I'm not appreciating,
that is why that would be the case, right?
so, we have to think about that a little
I don't know why that's still there.
Because nobody uses it.
Just a red herring at this point.
So yeah, get standard camera programs.
We've got our screen bounds there.
And that's just setting the Z.
So it seems to me that since everything centered around the, the Sim
Region Center, the fat, really shouldn't cause a problem.
The fact that the simulation region is not sized to the room, may be
something that we want to fix for other reasons.
But I don't think it's a reason.
I don't think it has any particular effect on the centering that I can
think of at least, not at the moment.
and if we take a look at the
if we take a look at the frame to frame Delta here,
that's only affecting the particle system so that wouldn't have any
effect.
So yeah, I can't see a lot of reason why we would be getting a
displacement there.
And I would expect the center of the simulation region to be in the
center.
I guess the most logical thing to do.
Now would be to try to draw something.
That's where we think the Sim Center actually is right?
So if I went ahead and push direct outline on here, I'm going to
offset these a little bit screen, bounce inbounds.
And some region bounds there.
I'm not sure what the difference is between those two values at the
moment, actually, though, to be fair but let's take a look.
So, it's kind of as I expected there, like, you can see that the
simulation region is lined up in X with the screen but it's not lined
up in.
Why I went that was screen with the room.
And so, that's an interesting question.
As to why this is the center tile.
We would expect it to be in the center of this white rectangle.
And it isn't so my hunch as to what was happening is correct.
But, you know, I my hunch as to why it was happening is not only just
not correct but rather we would say non-existent I don't have a hunch
as to why that's happening and so I feel like we need to try to make a
determination about why the Sim region.
Ian.
why the, the
Why the Sim region doesn't seem to be centered in the way that we
would expect?
So, how do we compute the same region Center to begin with, right?
And let's just take a look at that.
So
When we create the Sim region.
Inside simulate I assume or other inside begins to him, we're using
the camera dot P for that, right?
And that camera dot p is going to be set inside, at least after the
first frame is going to be set inside here, and it's going to be set.
By mapping into chunks face, whatever.
The
Route camps position is relative what to whatever the origin position
is of the same region at that time.
So whatever the Sim region was
Which is this?
We're just going to say pretend we have an offset of that which is
whatever the entity thinks.
It's at map that into trunk space and that's going to be the position
that we're going to use as our Center.
And that seems pretty valid right?
That's going to come or should be Computing.
A point that has that information in it that information that we
expect and I don't know why we would get a problem with that unless we
are incorrectly applying that when we actually do our run map, right?
So let's take a look at how we're doing our own map.
So here's begin Sim where I guess begin World change rather.
So here's the world change.
And you can kind of see us doing our thing here when we go through and
try to compute where things are, we do subtractions of the chunk
position.
From the origin.
And as far as I know that chunk, Delta should include the origins
offset, right?
Which is whatever gets passed in here, which should include that the
micro offset not just for the chunk.
Let's make sure it does starters.
And it looks like it very, you know, clearly does, you can see it
using a offset and be offset there where it subtracts the two.
So that should be, you know, that should be correct for all intents
and purposes.
So that chunk Delta, that we get here, where we subtract the same
regions origin from the chunk position that should give us that
displacement out to that chunk.
And then when we're taking entities out, right?
We're just putting that that chunk Delta in there.
So that seems like that should.
it'd be correct and I'll take go ahead and
just,
We'll run a few times here and I'll go ahead and look just to just to
see what we're actually getting for those values.
So first of all, here's the same regions origin value.
And you can see that there is an offset in there.
And so, then we come through here and we do our
Let's take a look at the chunk.
That actually hasn't minute.
so there is our chunk Delta that, we've computed
Like so.
And what we should be able to see there.
I guess what I'd rather do is verify that it's actually using those
values, I guess.
So, here we go.
So let's take a look at our a and our B and you can see as you'd
expect the chunk part doesn't have enough set.
That's what we want.
And the other one does have an offset and they are getting respected,
so that computation appears to be correct.
So I dunno why the origin
It's not getting set properly in that regard, right?
That's a good question.
So let's take a look at how we're updating our camera.
So there it is and we come down here and we're taking a look at at the
end of these and we find whatever the room entity is and let's just
take a look at what the room entities position is its 0 as we would
have expected.
So the remedy is right in the middle, right?
Supposedly of this thing.
Now, that doesn't really make any sense because we're sort of saying
that, well, if it was right in the middle than we would have expected
the rooms boundaries to be centered with respect to the same region,
they should be roughly about the same, right?
But at the moment they aren't and you can see that just by looking at
the fact that that white rectangle is directly centered.
But the room rectangle, which is this yellow one here is not.
So, so that's a bit of issue.
I'll also point out that
That the screen bounds are not quite centered either, which also
doesn't make a whole lot of sense, right?
So I feel like we have a couple remaining issues there.
Let me go ahead and
Reduce the displacement that these are feeling.
So, there we go.
So that just turned out.
That was just an offset issue, so that's fine.
So, what's interesting about that because this is actually very
relevant.
So
when we offset things,
Z.
they get shifted upwards, it looks like
And that, of course, makes a fair bit of sense because I think that's
exactly what we said should happen, right?
We specifically said that things should get off set in why when they
get higher, right?
That was our whole thing with
With having the two transforms.
And so you can see that you know we displace the Y with the author
from Z hide off floor, right?
So I suspect, the reason we aren't getting the centering that we want
to get there.
It's because our height off floor computation, right is giving us.
A bogus value for that.
Because now the distance above Target for the floor Z, right?
This does is above Target value is including the whole displacement
rather than just the relative displacement and then you end up with
extra displacement there.
So I guess what I would say is I'm willing to say, okay, I'm not going
to fix that one, I'm going to leave it the way it is because I believe
when we go to 3D here that will take care of itself because then we
won't have this dual notion of things that happen will only just have
the 3D working as it should work, right?
And then I think we'll be more, okay?
So I'm going to go ahead and go to the Q and A on that note.
And and take any questions that people have.
Can you girls high for how long is this Bliss of weekend?
Episodes going to continue.
Got any news in the making for us?
Yeah I actually probably will just keep doing it this way.
II like the weekend streams.
And I don't have very much ability at the moment to fit weeknight
streams into my schedule.
So I think it will just be this way.
Probably indefinitely.
I'm glad you call it the Bliss of weekend episodes that makes it sound
like you like it which is good I'm sure for anystream time change.
There are some people for whom
It's better in some people for whom, it's worse, worse.
But yeah.
Oh, can you cause I did not realize you were asking if there were all
any additional news besides the weekend episodes?
No, I don't have any news at the moment.
No.
It's not a bit off topic, but why do you use your headphone mic rather
than the nice Studio mic?
You have the Jess and Casey show?
Well, actually there's a couple of reasons but one of the main ones is
just I don't really have a good way to put that mic in here somewhere.
Where I could talk into it.
That wouldn't pick up the machine noise like really dramatically
because it wouldn't be on a headset.
It be outcome sitting on the table where we get a lot of noise and
also I don't really
You know, I can't have it in some place that Mike is supposed to be
like, right?
Close to your head here.
If I was to try and put an aperture that would make that happen, I
wouldn't be able to really work that effectively.
So, you know, I probably could try to use a better microphone in that
way, but I would have to, like, buy a bunch of stuff to kind of try
and mount it in a way, that would still let me type and like, not
Yeah, it would be bad.
So let's go with the camera.
Doesn't need to be centered perfectly working as intended.
Yeah, that's what I was just talking about.
I don't know if you just maybe you just came to a stream but that's
what I was just saying, is the reason is because of the Y offset,
which we are going to remove.
So I'm not going to touch it at the moment.
And in terms of testing the theory by just removing that transform.
Yeah, we can do that, although it would probably have some other side
effects if we change the Y offset, that's that line of
There.
And then you can kind of see everything is centered properly, right?
So now we're now it's entered the way you would expect.
So it's just that that that y displacement which like I said, I
decided I'd I'm going to change the way that that works.
Sort of following the series on YouTube and have made it to episode
for loving it so far when I tried to build solution in Visual Studio,
I'm able to do so.
Unless I put the pound to find some type that into every file.
Is this a visual studio thing or am?
I doing it wrong?
Sorry, for going way back.
So you are not doing it wrong in the sense that there's something
wrong with what you're doing.
You're just not doing it the same way I did it.
And that's probably why you're getting that problem.
What happens is in visual studio.
So by default, if you use this solution Explorer thing and you add CPP
files to it, right?
And you let Visual Studio, do the build each CPP.
File is passed to the compiler separately.
Right.
And so, because each CPP file is past separately anything that might
be a dot h file or a DOT CPP file or anything that needs to be used
cross.
File has to be redefined.
That's why we have H files.
Technically, when going back to the old days, when that's how you
always did, it is passing everything separately.
That's why you had to have a child and you furthermore had to like
Define everything like every time you made a function, that would be
called.
But from
File to another file.
You had to into the H file, put that definition.
So the compiler would know that that that you know it was something it
was available to be called, right?
The reason we don't have to do any of that stuff on handmade hero is
because I don't use the IDE to build.
I use a batch file and this is the batch file and what it does.
Right.
Is it just builds the one file and all the files are included in that
file.
So if you look at handmade dot CPP you can
see that it includes all of the CPP files in it, right?
So what that does is it just makes one giant file.
That has all the code in it and it just compiles that one file.
Now, if you try to do that in Visual Studio, in the naive way, where
you just you've got this file handmade dot CPP in there.
But you also added all the other files in there because hey there the
files and you thought you would want them in there which makes sense.
Now, it's going to try to compile the handmade one which
Pile properly because it includes everything.
But it will also try to compile all the other files individually.
Even though it doesn't need to and isn't supposed to do that, because
it just thinks anything that you listed in here is supposed to
compiled as source code, right?
So what you have to do if you're going to compile inside Visual Studio
is either only add handmade dot CPP and win32 handmade dot CPP as two
separate projects with two separate CPP files and that's it.
So it will only try to build those.
So, or you can add everything you want, but then you have to customize
your build in Visual Studio using like the build stuff.
There's like, a whole I don't even know like this whole system thing.
If This Were a real project and not just an executable, it have a
whole bunch of settings.
Here, you'd have to set all those settings correctly and I believe
people have worked that out on the handmade Network forums.
You can go and see how people have done that and so, you know, you
don't have to try and figure that out yourself.
If you are new to visual studio and don't necessarily know how to, you
know, sort of massage it into the correct configuration to make that
work.
There are there's folks who have definitely
Miss on handmade Network.
I just don't actually know exactly where you to visual studio and
doesn't know.
It's me talking to me.
No just stop.
Okay, so if you search in here like Visual Studio, I think there's
probably
Let's see.
so, I think this is
Handle them here kind of, right?
You can sort of see
Yeah, you can kind of see people working it out.
I'm not sure which one of these is definitive because I don't use
Visual Studio in this manner so I don't even have an opinion about it
one way or the other, but that's kind of what's available for for
going down that route.
If you if you will, does that make sense?
And yet looks like,
You know, it looks like probably there's different ways to make things
work better and like, if you want livecode reloading to work, for
example, you probably do a lot more work setting up visual studio,
then if you just want it to build, right?
Because in order to get the live coding to work, you have to build the
dll and do the thing where we unlock the unlocked change the name of
the pdb.
And there's all this other stuff that we do to make the loop live
coding work in the batch file and and visual studio would have to be
set up to
to do the right stuff for that as well.
So, you know, there's probably
Degrees of compliance.
You can achieve with visual studio and there are probably different
amounts of work involved in them, but people have sort of posted that
there and so you can go ahead and use that as a resource if you're
having trouble.
Looks like that's it for questions, which is good because the stream
just ended.
All right, let's close things down.
All right, so before I close things down, again I just want to re
mention some stuff we talked about.
No, don't don't do it.
Okay, there we go.
I was almost going to have me talk to me again.
I just want to mention again, if you are interested in handmade
Network, which is sort of a separate.
It's, it's a it's not a handmade hero thing.
Actually, it's kind of like a place for projects that people
Are trying to do programming in sort of a similar, I guess I would
just say, like, attitude towards how we do it on handmade hero where
you're, you know, carrying about the code and trying to sort of focus
on learning how the computer works and these sorts of things.
So, if you're interested in that sort of stuff, you probably have been
to hand me a network before.
But previously, in order to get a project listed on handmade Network,
it was just sort of, you had to email the maintainers and that sort of
stuff because the site, you know, has only been around for actually a
fairly short period.
A of time.
And so they were still working on getting all the other features of it
going and, you know, cleaning it up and work on the layout and all the
sorts of things you have to do to run a website.
Obviously.
And so if you before, if you wanted to be one of the people who
maintained a product on there and use their product hosting services
and kind of be part of that Community, you had to email someone to
make that happen.
And you have to go dig to find two, who to email.
And, you know, it wasn't the kind of thing.
It was really set.
Up for public consumption, but they've now gotten all their stuff done
that.
They want to get done in terms of allowing product resubmitted
publicly.
And so, if you are interested in submitting a project to handmade
Network, and you'd like to be hosted on there and you can now do that
directly from the hand being Network site, which is just a made-up
Network, you just click on projects.
And now this submit a project button should be here, you
Have an account on handmade Network to do it but obviously that's free
and easy to do.
You just click register.
If you don't already have one and you can register.
And then this button this dialogue here, if you are a registered user,
which many of you probably already are, you can will just see a submit
button there.
And so then you can submit your project and they can take a look at
it.
And if it's the kind of thing that fits with what they're doing, they
can set you up for hosting the project on there, and there's a lot of
great products hosted on there already.
So I would highly recommend checking them out.
If you haven't, you can see there's an for entire pages of projects
here that are like all over the map in terms of what they cover.
So by no means.
Does it have to be something similar in scope or type of project to
handmade hero because most of the things on there are totally
different sorts of things, The Homebrew operating system, a remake of
Quake, you know, the drawing package.
We use a voxel engine, you know, everything.
You can imagine is already sort of on there.
And so there's no reason to limit yourself.
If you are doing a project like this, it doesn't have to be anything
like handmade hero.
It just has to be something where you're concerned about, you know,
making quality software and wanting to write things with an
understanding of how they execute on hardware and stuff like that.
Everything is welcome on there as far as I'm far as I'm aware.
So, I would check that out.
Check out the products that are on there if you haven't already and
then
if you are working on a project that you'd like to see be part of sort
of their umbrella, you can go ahead and submit it here.
And I believe that, that, that the backend that they have basically
includes like all the stuff you need for hosting, so you don't need to
maintain like a separate GitHub or anything like that.
I think they even have, like, all that stuff just built in.
So it's, it's completely like the forums.
Are there?
The GitHub sort of equivalent?
Is there like, all that stuff is just kind of there, which is pretty
cool.
Because then, you can just have all that.
Stuff taken care of and you don't have to, you know, have deforms in
one place your GitHub in other place and involve law.
So I think it'll probably be pretty useful for people who are
interested in maintaining projects in this fashion.
And even if you host the project, externally, obviously there's still
ways that you can use it as far as I can tell.
Because, for example, handmade hero already had all the stuff set up
with the GitHub and the and send owl and all that stuff.
And and it's still on here for the forums and everything right to, so,
You can also have that stuff taken care of how much do you pay for
health?
And please just don't twitch.
Really wants me to see some ads.
I guess so yeah, you can use it also.
If you're just interested in form of stuff, but you have a project
that fits well, you can still probably use it here.
And again, like these are kind of cool features, right?
Like as much as you probably don't want this to watch an advertising
here.
If you are a twitch user, actually anyone who's Amazon Prime will see
ads, right?
I'm just not.
And I wouldn't normally see ads on Twitch.
So if you're live, it'll show up.
When people are browsing a channel, which is a pretty awesome feature.
So there's just a lot of neat things that they're doing and because
they care about this from the perspective of people who are making
projects like these.
It's very likely that the sort of stuff that you're going to want, is
a sort of stuff that they're working on.
So it's also kind of nice in that respect because, you know, it's not
geared, just towards people who are doing stuff that may be very
different from the sorts of stuff you're doing.
It's geared more.
Or towards the sort of stuff that you probably are interested in.
If you're the kind of person who likes, what we do on handmade hero
because that's their Focus, right?
So check all that out whenever you get a chance.
And again that's who hosts the forums for handmade here.
Anyway.
So if you're on handmade here that org and you click on the forms
button, that's that's already where it's going, right?
And so that's just if you didn't already know, if you click on that
handmade Network part.
You get to the broader site which has a bunch of other
Objects that are in a similar vein.
And a lot of them also have learning resources associated with them,
just like handmade hero does.
So there's a, quite a few on there.
I think at least three or four that also have streams associated with
them, where you can watch and learn about how they were developed, or
how they're being developed.
And so, if you do like that sort of thing, it's also a good way to
find out what's going on there.
Some of them also don't necessarily have educational streams but do
have streams.
So, for example, when Sean Barrett does development on his voxel
engine, he does stream the development.
Now it's not necessarily an educational stream per se, because he
doesn't necessarily Translate
Teach you what he's doing, but he does record what he's doing.
So you can learn from how he's coding just by observing, right?
So if you want to see how he's approaching the code and how he's
running the code, you still can do all of that, right?
For that, for that voxel engine.
So in addition to the ones that have overtly educational streams,
which are designed to be more teaching oriented and have complete
explanations, and break things down for,
Or an intended audience of people who may not understand them.
At first glance, there are also streams that are happening on there,
which are, I guess, you might call them more expert streams, which are
to say that you could still learn from them.
You just have to be a little further along but as long as you can
follow along with what Sean's doing without too much detailed
explanation, you can sort of still see how he approaches code.
How he goes about like debugging, how he thinks about things and there
is commentary from him from time to time too.
So you
you do get also some of the, like the back process there.
So there's kind of a ray of streams as well that you could check out
on there, that might be useful.
And so, you know, I would recommend spending time exploring it if you
like handmade hero, there may be other things on there.
That would be really useful to complement it or to sort of take it
into areas that, you know, we don't
Really cover, you know.
So if you're looking for more materials I would highly recommend it
that's it for for today as always if you're just interested in
handmade hero, you can always pre-order the game when it comes to the
source code on.
Handmade hero dot-org, I uploaded every night.
So it's always fresh.
You can play around with it.
We also have that for him.
So I was talking about hosted by handmade Network which you can check
out and now is a good time to do it.
Like I was saying, it's kind of the sort of kicked up the
functionality on the site and Notch to a place where I think.
You probably going to be really happy checking out.
What they've got.
We also have a patreon page to want to support our video series a
schedule, but if you want to know when we're going to be live and an
episode guide maintained via the fabulous me blow, which has all of
our old episodes on it.
So you can go back and see what we did and when it's got nice time
coded entries so you can jump to things and all that sort of stuff
that's it for today.
I will be back here next weekend to do some more programming until
then have a good week and I'll see everyone.
On the internet.
Take it easy, everybody.