Alright, hello everyone.
And welcome to handmade here on the show.
We could have complete game live on Twitch.
No engine.
No, libraries, just us.
And right now, we're working on multi-threading which we just
introduced of the past two days.
And today, we're actually at the part where we get to actually do some
cool stuff with it because we had to cover all the basics, Monday, and
Tuesday, but now the bases are out of the way.
So yesterday we wrote, what is essentially an completely unsafe
version of a work queue that we would like to get working.
And so today we're going to do is use sort of the stuff that we
explained yet on Monday and Tuesday, to show how we can make that more
robust and make it so that it actually works properly with
multi-threading instead of not working properly with multi-threading,
which as I demonstrated yesterday, the naive code won't do.
So before I get started, if you do want to follow along,
Today, since we are gonna be doing some coding here day 124.
So what you want to do is if you preorder the game unpack day 123
source code and start with that, that is what I am starting with.
So you'll be right where I am today.
So let's jump right into it in the win32 code, right?
We've got our create thread here.
Let's create thread.
And if you remember where we left off yesterday, what we did is we had
a little work queue, essentially kind of a thing we could do.
We could push a little strings in there.
And then we had worker threads that were supposed to come along and
pick up whatever was in that queue and do it, right?
So it was supposed to pick up the strings.
We were pushing in there.
So it's a print them out to the debug port.
And we wrote this, I wrote it essentially in a way that doesn't use
any of the stuff that I talked about on Monday and Tuesday so that I
could show you what would happen if you.
pay attention to things that I said we would need to pay attention to
And what we can see if we actually run that is we get sort of bad
things start to happen and they can kind of happen randomly, you can
sort of see here.
We've got two different threads, both do work unit 0 for example.
And in fact, in this case, no thread did work unit to, it looks like
you can, you can sort of see that.
There's just very bad things happening here because what we would like
to see is we don't really care which threads do which work units, but
we want to see,
All of the work units done and we want to see all of the work units
done.
Exactly one time, that is sort of the very minimal criteria, that one
might want to have for a work queue to say, the very least, okay?
So let's take a look at why that's happening.
I put the to do sin.
So I talked about it yesterday, but let's take a look at these in
order.
So we can make sure that we actually have them.
Structured in a way, that will make sure that we don't have these
problems.
All right, so the first problem that we have is actually a problem.
I'm that doesn't really exist on the x64 processor if I remember
correctly.
So it's actually strictly a compiler problem but either way it is
still a problem and so I want to start talking about that now.
Basically, what we have here is in our push string, what I talked
about yesterday, the fact that the rights are not in order, you can
see that right here, what we do is we want to put something on our
work Cube.
So we have the code that actually writes it into the queue into the
data part of the queue.
But then the thing that increments this entry count here, right?
The thing that actually says, oh, there's a new entry in the work
queue that thing is happening, right?
It's happening at a time before we have actually written.
The stuff into into the into the queue.
What that means is anyone who's looking for stuff on the Q?
Might see this value.
Get incremented before we have a chance to write it because we
increment it and then write it, right?
So, what we would need to do in order to make sure that this is more
robust is first, we would need to make sure that we were going to
write the thing in before we do anything else.
And then we could come in here and we could go ahead and write the the
Entry count, make that increment it.
But even though I have rearranged these lines of code
This is still not.
Okay.
And the reason that it's not okay, is because although the processor,
again, this is why I say, I seem to remember this being true about
ecstasy for, although I seem to recall the processor actually
enforcing memory right order which was a thing that was like not true
on the powerpc but was true about x64.
If I remember correctly?
It was I saying like it's been a while.
Even though the processor might guarantee that if it sees writes in
an, in an order in instructions, that they will go out in order, you
have to remember that the compiler is under no obligation to keep our
rights in order.
So, at any time, an optimizing, compiler could come in here and decide
to move this, incrementing of Entry count up above, where it sets the
string, because it just finds that to be a more efficient, ordering
for the instructions.
Or for whatever reason, it doesn't even need.
Reason it could just do it that way.
This code would then be broken before it ever even got to the
processor.
And so at that point, it doesn't even matter.
If the processor has strong ordering of Rights in.
So, you know, your sort of your code is broken before it even hits the
processor.
So it doesn't matter what the processor actually guarantees in terms
of The Ordering of Rights, right.
And when I say ordering of Rights on the processor, what I mean is not
all processors guarantee that rights that come in in a certain order.
Go out in a certain order, right?
There's there's
Certainly processors that can do their rights out of out.
Order out of the order in which they come in.
And so that's worth being aware of because On Any Given platform you
kind of need to know that, right?
So let's talk about how to solve both of those problems.
Even though, like I said on ecstasy for, I don't think we actually
need to solve it.
Let's talk about how to solve it anyway.
So the first thing we need to do in here is we need to put in
something that will tell the compiler.
Never to move a right.
That comes after a particular point before, or right, that came before
this point, right?
So basically what we need to do here is we need to do something that
says like,
Pleat past rights before future.
Right.
We need to do something like this.
Okay?
And what we want to do presumably right.
Is we want to basically have this be some kind of a macro that on
whatever platform we happen to be on.
We can tweak it so that a will put in the correct thing for the
compiler, right?
Which on this platform there's going to be a reason.
Why?
It turns out we actually don't have to because we're going to change a
little something else but we'll keep that say that for a second.
But we can also do is in that macro.
If we are on a platform that does not support strong ordering of
Rights, we can put in whatever instructions we need to put in there
because there's usually there's things called memory fences on
processors, which allow you to sort of explicitly.
Tell the processor.
Hey I need you to serialize these things, right?
And we will get to one of those in a second because x64 does have some
other things we might care about.
All right?
So based on what we want to do here is is make sure that we have a
thing, which does this, right?
And actually for the compiler, the only thing we actually need to tell
it, I believe they've got these now in ecstasy for visual studio.
They actually have these more explicitly than they used to be.
Just go ahead and look it up here.
Here it is.
Here we go.
So basically what these things are these intrinsics, right?
These are these, the old ones, why is it telling me caution are all
deprecated.
All right, great, you show, you see how old I am.
The things that I normally use are now deprecated and they want me to
use Atomic thread fence and standard atomic.
I don't want to use these C++ features.
I don't want to use these people such as at all.
I do not trust C++.
I am still going to use these but you can follow this cautionary,
note, if you would like to write, so what I would like to do is I
would like to use these
What I want to do here is a right barrier.
I want to be able to say, hey, I would like to make sure that
essentially this thing the reason it's called a barrier.
This thing, this line prevents any rights that were below it from
being moved above it.
Right.
That's what that's what I would like to do.
And so let me go ahead and see if that will actually work.
I think it should.
There we go.
So I'm going to go ahead and do that.
And similarly, as you can see there, you could there was also a
version of those four reads, right?
You can see it here, it was read barrier, right?
So that would prevent reads from going through.
And you can see well actually, I don't know if they actually say much
are.
Here you go the right Barry intrinsically mystical power positions
that can remove or reorder memory access operations across the point
of the call, right?
So, basically, at the point where you do it, right?
It will prevent the rights from moving across this boundary in ways
that would would make things problematic.
Now, it's not actually a call, right?
It doesn't actually do anything.
This isn't actually a function call.
It's just a marker that the compiler uses to know that.
It shouldn't
Do that.
Okay, so that's what I want to do there.
Now, like I said on x64 and we'll double-check this later or someone
on the stream if they happen to know, can double-check it.
But on x64, I don't believe we actually ever need to tell the CPU to
enforce.
Right, right.
Ordering because I believe it retires rights in order.
Normally anyway
but,
If we did have to do that, we would put in a memory fence.
I see here and fence.
Where is the, where is the memory fence?
Wait on loads and stores.
That is not what I was expecting to see, we would put in a memory
fence here and we might actually do that in a little bit here.
When we get to reads, there should be an intrinsic for this and I
forget what it is at the moment, but there is normally a memory fence
fence, intrinsic groups in music.
Let's see here.
There we go.
Fence.
Oops.
C++ compiler, equivalent.
Underscore underscore M fence.
Yeah.
I'm feeling slow today.
I didn't get enough sleep last night, basically.
I feel like we should have this.
This should be here.
Why are why are we not getting?
Why is my M fence not showing up.
This is one of the problems when you build your own libraries and
stuff, you like I have long forgotten, what the actual members stuff
is for x64, so I have to like, reread it again for the first time.
I'm just like, I just want the thing, that tells the processor not to
reorder across here.
And I wanted to be able to memory
But for some reason, it doesn't seem to actually be showing up as a
thing, which I don't totally understand why, let's take a look here.
Well, you know what I'm going to do, just because, you know, I can I'm
gonna go ahead and go in here to program files.
I'm going to look to see.
I want to see Visual Studio.
There it is.
Visual Studio 12.
There we go.
I want to look in VC include and I just want to see is in Trend in
here.
Yeah.
So I just want to see where my fence at
You know, where are the fences.
So that is underscore underscore em fence.
There it is an M&M in Trend and there's assume that the load fence
there and there's the store fence.
So, it looks like you've got all the fences underscore underscore rmm.
Fence.
So there you go.
All right, so we've got those.
So if we did want to actually do that,
S fence, I believe would be the guy.
See sense.
Which is the processor fence for stores.
But like I said, I think in this particular case, I don't actually
think we would need to do that and so I'll go double check that for
now.
But it would look like this, right?
So if we, if we wanted to actually insert a processor barrier as well
as the compiler barrier, we can do that by putting in an actual, an
actual fence and into the instruction stream, right?
So what that does, this is strictly telling the compiler not to
reorder stores around that bit, that that point, and this is actually
inserting an actual thing into the instruction stream of the
processor.
Will see that says, I don't want you to reorder stores around this
point.
So anyway, so we'll check that that out in a bit.
In fact, I'll just put it to do in here to do a double check the right
ordering stuff on
The CPU because I'm pretty sure that you don't that this is not what
this is.
Like, I'm pretty sure that s fence is like a difficult thing but point
point being we'll leave that anyway.
so,
where do we go from here?
Assuming that we actually have this, right?
We still have another problem that we haven't addressed yet, which is
the compiler.
You know, now that we've put this in there, the compiler, actually
knows this right barrier thing but as you know I said we may not even
really have to do that because this other thing about to talk about in
a second I'm sorry there are so many crazy things to talk about this
is just yeah like I said see wasn't made with multi-threading in mind
so you got all these kind of weird things to talk about.
All right.
So, what actually happens here, and I mentioned this, I believe,
yesterday when we were writing, this is that the other threads here,
right?
When the compiler is looking at how to compile this code, it may look
at entry, count and go.
Oh, you know what?
Nobody modifies entry count in here.
So I why do I ever need to even do this?
Check, I know this check will always succeed or I'm going to predict
when this checklist your something like this why do I even need to
look at it anymore, right?
And so
It may do is it may like do stuff like load these guys into registers
or do you know, who knows what?
But point being it may not the compiler, may not feel at all compelled
to keep going out to memory to load in the the latest value of Entry
count, right?
Because it doesn't know that there's another thread out there that
might be changing entry count while we are executing, right?
So there's actually a keyword in C it's called volatile, right?
And what volatile is volatile is a key word that lets the compiler
know that, whatever the thing is that you happen to be talking about.
It may be changed without the compilers like implicit local knowledge,
right?
So when the compiler looks at a piece of code and thinks it can
determine that a particular thing.
Cannot be changed because it doesn't see like a function called could
possibly affect it or something like this.
Volatile is your way of telling the compiler?
No, no.
I actually want you to assume that somebody else in the system at any
time, might actually be changing it.
So any time you go to use it again, I need you to actually load it
back in and double check.
So that's what that does, right?
Volatile is kind of this way of saying, hey, don't don't optimize out
the actual loads of this thing.
Every time through the loop, I need you to actually do it.
It's just something you need to.
In there.
So, the reason that I was saying that sometimes you don't actually
have to do this is if we were to actually declare all of these
volatile, which I'm not sure we actually want to do, but if everything
here was volatile, I believe that the convention introduced in msv.
See as of I don't know the early 2000's Maybe
Is that effectively there is already a right barrier around rights to
volatile.
Register volatile variables.
So I believe it actually might insert the right barrier for us in
certain cases.
And you wouldn't actually have to do that because it already assumes
that a right to a volatile, is defensible Operation, right?
but,
unlike this guy, which we don't, presumably want to put unless we
absolutely
Have to because it's actually instruction this guy, we can kind of put
in extras of, right?
If we have a right barrier in there already was a right Barry there.
That's not really that big of a deal because we really just don't want
things to move across that boundary.
So saying it again, doesn't really matter, right?
It's not inserting instruction, it's not a function call, it's
nothing.
It's just a compiler requirement.
So that's probably fine.
Sorry, so once we have this, this routine is now more correct.
Now.
This routine when it goes to, put the string on will actually make
sure that it wrote the string before it increment that counter.
So that's a good thing.
So now let's move down to the thread proc, which had problems in it as
well, right?
So the first problem that we have is the fact that we did not use the
interlocked operations that I was talking about before.
So, what that means is essentially the exact case that I described
On the Blackboard yesterday where two threads could load in the value
of next entry to do.
They could both increment it separately.
So the each load in like a value of one, they both increment it and
mute get to and then write it back out and they both end up doing work
unit 1 because they didn't know that the other person was in the
middle of incrementing at the same time.
So this is where we need to use that interlocked operation concept and
we can do that here by do using the interlock increment.
Function, which is actually made exactly.
For this thing, which is the simplest possible version and all incur
interlocked increment.
Actually, does is it takes the value that we have there and it goes
ahead and adds one to it.
Now like I said I think we might want to just go ahead and use
interlock compare exchange for everything eventually.
Just to keep things a little simpler but because interlock compare
exchange is a little bit fancier.
I want to start out with interlocked increment just you can see how
that works because it's very simple to understand.
All you need to understand about it is it does a
Plus plus operation, basically, in a way that no two threads will
conflict with each other.
So they'll all each get back, a unique value when they are when they
are calling interlocked increment, even if they both happen to try and
do it at exactly the same time, okay.
So interlocked increment
Is really just an intrinsic that tells the the compiler to use the
correct instructions for doing the x64 locked increment behavior on
the actual processor, right?
And so, you can see the function prototype of a hero interlock
increment.
What it does is it takes a pointer to some volatile long, right?
And a long again, is just an in 32.
So we, you know, we don't actually care about that when it's actually
doing the increments incremental work the same either way, so we can
And totally just cast it to a to a long volatile Star, right?
So if we want to increment Next Century to do like so that will go
ahead and do that interlocked increment.
And then, as you can see here, it Returns the resulting incremented
value.
So actually it
I'm quite do what we wanted to do here.
We wanted the value before you increment it, so once we interlocked
increment it we're going to get back the incremented value.
It's like a you know, it's that not that, right?
So it's actually doing this Behavior, which means the entry index, we
actually wanted was whatever the value was before the increment.
So we need to subtract one from the value that we to get the one that
we actually want to use, right?
So now these are interlocked and so that gets
Gets rid of that to do.
And so now know two threads will see that same value come back.
So, that's a good thing, right?
And furthermore, we've we've gotten rid of this to do already because
I stuck the volatile in there to let it know that next entry to do an
entry count, our can both be changing without the compilers knowledge,
right?
So that's good too.
So finally, we get into another situation, which is that this right
here, right?
Is also a problem in terms of
In terms of doing reads an order, right?
Because what can happen here is we could be seeing, you know, to take
the absolute extreme case.
Imagine if the compiler decided to do this load up here somehow which,
you know, honestly I don't really know if it should ever be able to do
because if it was doing that what if it happened to be an out of
balance load?
So you know this is not a really a real one but I'm just pointing it
out.
You could get into a situation where
Okay, if the compiler was being really extreme and decided to move the
read up before, it had actually checked entry count, right?
Then you could see that situation happening.
That's actually not a problem here.
And I also want to point out another thing, which is that interlocked
increment
actually serves as a fence itself.
It's actually a processor fence, right?
And so, essentially, interlocked increment will do I believe all of
the fencing that we actually need to do, but if we really, really
wanted to be, absolutely sure that the process that the compiler was
not going to do anything weird.
We could put this in here to make sure that like before we ever read
from this, make sure everything had happened but it really, that's
probably redundant.
So okay.
Now that we've cleaned up those two dues.
If we run this again, let's take a look.
If we have actually produced good behavior again.
You can see that we've got, let's see zero one, two, three, four five.
There's our six seven, eight, nine.
So you can see we fix the problem.
Now already of the fact that this was doing the wrong sort of stuff,
So, that's good.
Let's try increasing that thread.
Count up to 8, which I guess is, how many threads will use in the end.
There we go.
And you can see, let's see, 01,
Is my to is all the way down there so 0 1 2 3 4 5 6 7 8 9, there we
go.
So we're getting better right.
Our Q is functioning a little bit better now.
But let's talk about a couple of things.
So, first of all, one thing that we want to think about here is the
thread count.
I guess people told me, even though this, this has this process, this
machine has 16 hyper cores right in it, and I cranked the thread count
up to 16, right?
We made 15 threads and then we've obviously got the one thread that's
actually running here.
You know, I done this and apparently that was way too much for this
machine because our process just hugged all of the CPU resources and
OBS, couldn't send out the video anymore.
So we're going to have to
Yeah, parse our thread usage at 8 here.
So, even after we go an inquiry, how many processors there are will
probably have to put in a little debug.
So, it just says on this particular machine only ever use 8 because we
don't want to take the streaming.
Which is, you know, obviously a problem.
So that might not be so bad later when these threads sleep as well as
the other thing I could think of but but either were, so if you look
at now what we've got, this is essentially a little nice little work
Cube.
We can actually use this work queue for basically anything that we
would want to do, but it's got some pretty obvious limitations.
It only sort of piles up things.
It doesn't function as a circular buffer right now.
So that's a little bit wonky.
But really, at the end of the day, it's not too bad and so
Really only one thing we would have to add to this to actually use it
to do the renderer because the render doesn't really need a circular
buffer.
What's going to do?
So if we wanted to start using this with the render, there's really
only one thing that we would have to do.
And what that thing is is right now.
The only thing that we actually know is how many jobs have been
started, right?
If you think about it, next entry to do tells us how many jobs have
been started.
And if next entry to do equals entry count, we know that all of the
jobs have been started, but what we don't know is we don't know how
many of the jobs have actually finished, right?
And that's a problem, because if we don't know how many jobs have
finished, we don't know when we can actually like, if this was the
renderer we don't
When we can actually consider the rendering done.
Like we don't know when the bitmaps ready to go back and be related to
the screen, right?
So in addition to not knowing how many jobs have been taken, we need
to also know how many jobs that are finished.
Now, there's a couple different ways we can do that.
I'm going to do the simplest one right now because for the renderer
one thing that you have to understand,
is, there's a difference between needing to know how many jobs have
finished and which
Have finished because those are actually two different things, right?
If I need to know, if I need to get alerted specifically.
When a certain set of jobs has finished, that's a different problem
from, just knowing how many jobs have finished in terms of how you
have to code it, right?
If all I want to do is make some code that tells me entry completion
count basically like how many have been completed
All I really have to do there is I just have to have it so that every
time one of these guys finishes it does another one of those
interlocked increments on that value, the completion count, right?
Entry station count and now I know that as soon as entry completion
count, actually, equals entry count.
All of the jobs must have been completed, right?
And so, what's kind of interesting about this?
We can go ahead and do this, right?
You saw this over here.
Before we have that thing where thread to was kind of off in the
middle of nowhere there, I don't know if we're still unfortunately
that that's not super reliable that that happens I guess I was hoping
kind of was 0.
1 2 3 4 5 6 7 8 9 I was kind of hoping that it would always do that.
Weird it with thread to or at least sometimes there it is with thread
0 there, right?
So what I wanted to show curious if we wanted to make sure that we
printed all these guys out before we went on to do anything else.
Now we actually have a way to do that.
Right what we can do is we can go.
Okay, let's actually wait until entry completion.
Count is equal to the entry count and then we would know we were done
right?
So we could do.
While entry count is not equal to entry completion count and we could
just go right?
It's just full-on spin, lock, on that, right?
so,
Now we should always have this, this Behavior, it should always print
out our 10 values and it should never actually do anything, like
allowing them, you know, below the sort of load line there, we start,
loading things up.
So yeah, so that's basically it now.
I think I'm going to go ahead and move this into the renderer although
well let's maybe we should tackle this one other thing that we're
going to need first which is that what we don't really want to do
because yeah, you know, I think about it.
I mean we've got two ways, we can go, we can go put this into the
renderer and then we can come back and talk about how to make it so
that we're not burning up CPU, right?
Because all of these threads are sitting here, literally melting the
CPU just you know, never allowing it to go into a low-power state.
Now, this would have been fine way back in the day, when CPUs
Have a little power State and nobody cared.
But nowadays, you don't want all of the cores to be doing crazy stuff
like this when they don't need to be.
And furthermore, this is a multitasking operating system, which means
that if we are sitting here, doing all of these Loops, just checking
this over and over again.
Checking checking checking checking checking, never letting the
processor.
Go do something else.
We are making multitasking harder for Windows, right?
We are constantly looking we're appearing to the system as if we need
all of this processing power but really we didn't need any processing
power.
We could have been put totally to sleep own and just have our threads
woken up again.
Essentially once work actually does exist for them do, right?
So what we could talk about now instead of going to have the renderer
start multi-threading itself,
Or I should say we should start mother turning at what we could talk
about instead is what do we actually, how do we have to actually
structure this?
So that when there is not work to do?
And also during the times when we want to wait for work to finish, we
can tell the operating system that in some way that doesn't totally,
you know, melt the CPU down and make it difficult for us to actually,
Coexist peacefully in a multi-threaded environment, right?
And this Parts, a little janky, unfortunately.
There's really not much you can say about it.
Other than that.
But the reason it's janky is because, you know, windows and so on are
not real time.
Operating systems, they're not even soft real-time operating systems.
So sometimes you have to start a fuss with it a little bit but they do
provide the correct Primitives for doing this work.
It's just you don't have any hard knowledge of how long those
Primitives might take to complete or things like this.
So you'll see in a bit but we'll talk about that.
So, what I would like to do here is I have thread procs, right?
And what I would like to do with these thread products is, I would
like to check to see if there is something to do in my cue now, I
don't care what that check is.
Like I said, right now, our queue is pretty remedial.
That's fine.
But point being no matter how complex it does get, we will always have
some piece of code that looks something like this at the head, end
figuring out whether or not there is work in the queue for us to do.
And the problem that we have right now is in the case where there is
not work for us to do in the queue, we would like to have an else
clause, which will put this thread to sleep in some way so that the
thread doesn't waste a bunch of CPU Cycles.
So what we need to do here is we need to figure out how to put this
thread to sleep, right to do.
How do I put this thread to sleep?
And sleep is really a term that I'm using here.
I shouldn't really say that that that's really not what we're talking
about.
Sleep is probably the wrong word.
What we're talking about here is we simply want to announce to the
operating system.
Hey mr.
Operating system scheduler, we are done doing work right now.
You can go ahead and suspend us as a thread and we will do something
later that will let you know when it's time for us to come back to
resume, right?
So, we need to put the be able to put the thread to sleep here, right?
And if the threads are asleep, then we need when we do these push
strings, right?
We also need some way to wake them up again, right?
So when we go ahead and do push string, we need in here some way.
To Casey some way to wake up our threads, right?
So that's what we need.
We effectively need some way to put threads to sleep and we need some
way to wake them back up again.
Now, there's some subtleties here.
And the specific subtleties all revolve around the fact that all of
this is timing sensitive.
The reason I say it is timing sensitive is because you can imagine a
lot of circumstances for example, where something goes to sleep and
something else is supposed to wake it up, but the thing that was
supposed to wake it up happened, like before the Sleep happened.
So the wake up, doesn't wake.
The thing up and the thing stays asleep forever.
Or something like this, right?
So there's a bunch of problems that you can have that have to do with
this, right?
So the thing that we're going to start with tear, it is a primitive
called a semaphore.
And windows implements these.
Here's a hopefully, the correct description of them semaphore objects
and you can read about this.
If you would like to read about it, I'm not going to actually read
this out loud because there's a lot of text here, but essentially what
a semaphore is he's a semaphore is a countable, wait primitive.
It's basically something that in addition to allowing you to do these
sort of operation, I'm talking about here where I like, I want to kind
of put things too.
Even wake them up again.
It keeps track of account to try and help you avoid the kind of
circumstances that I was just talking about where you might have a
timing mismatch and accidentally leave things asleep or whatever which
is what might happen if you were just using some kind of a global
signal or something like this, right?
And I guess I mean, I don't know.
It's I'm kind of torn on this.
I'm not sure.
I don't have a strong opinion about it.
Like maybe I should show you how to use just a regular signal first,
No, but point being, let's take a look at this, this is the first
thing I thought of maybe to show.
So I think it's just going to show.
So let's go ahead and take a look.
Create some before.
Here we have create something for e^x.
And again, we've got those security attributes, which we don't have to
care about in our particular circumstance.
But, you know, point being there there.
And when you can see us, we have two counts on the semaphore, right?
We've got an initial and a maximum, okay?
And so what I'd like to do is basically set that maximum to be the
maximum number of threads that could be awake, right?
And I'd like the, you know, the initial count to essentially be, you
know, the the
That are awake at startup or something like this, right?
So I want to basically set the semaphore up so that it's going to be
counting more or less like what threads do.
We actually have a wake at any given time, right?
And then what we have once we have what he's semaphores, we have a
handle that comes back, a generic handle and we can start to use that
handle with a variety of these synchronization functions here that
Windows provides now.
There's a lot of them and I'm kind of not
going to talk about all of them because honestly, I don't even know
all of them.
There's bunches that have been added recently and all sorts of other
things.
There's are interlocked guys.
These are all those interlock guys that we were just talking about.
You can see, there's a ton of those as well but what I want to start
with
First of all, is just this wait for single object concept, right?
So here is wait for single object x.
What wait for single object X does, is it takes a handle?
Like the kind.
We would get back with our semaphore.
It takes a number of milliseconds to wait for which can be infinite,
so it can just go forever.
And then there's an alert about a thing which we don't actually care
about here.
This is a, this is a separate its additional things that don't
actually come into play for what we want to do.
So if I go ahead and and put the
In here, right?
I can show you how this works.
So here is, let's bestows.
Suppose we have our semaphore handle here.
Oops, that's the bad spelling.
There's our summer for handle, right?
And our MS is going to be infinite here.
And I'm just going to pass Falls to this because I don't actually care
about the alert about bit.
See what's our d word return.
So when we return, we should always basically get the fact that it
signals.
So we don't really care about this.
So this this stuff we don't really care about but if you lets you
might want to check this return value.
If you were setting a time out here, a maximum amount of time to wait,
if you were setting that you might want to know.
For example, was it.
The thing that I was waiting on did that actually trigger me or was it
the time out?
That triggered me.
Write stuff like this anyway.
Ignore that for now.
Being what this function does, is exactly what we wanted the function
to do, putting the thread to sleep, right?
What this does is if I call this off, thread that
First to the operating system says, okay go ahead and suspend me
suspend me for this much time.
And since I'm passing the special constant infinite, it means
indefinitely, just suspend me.
And don't wake me up until whatever it is.
I passed in here as a handle triggers, right?
Until it gets signaled and the reason those terms are very generic is
because as you might imagine, if you start to do lots of stuff with
multi-threaded coding, especially in operating system context, there's
Lots of things you might want to wait for.
And so this is a generic function that can wait for lots of different
things.
It can wait for semaphores, but it can also wait for a bunch of other
types of Handles in the system.
And so that's why it's very generic.
It's like signaled it's like whatever the object thing is you passed
me when it does.
Its thing that says go that's when, right?
So this wait for a single object d x is just going to wait for the
semaphore.
Be signaled.
And of course what does that mean?
We haven't talked about that yet but that's okay.
This is all we really need to know for now for this routine because
this gives this routine, basically all it it really needed which is
something that will sit there and wait giving the time back to the
operator, some so other people can use it or if there's no one to use
it, it just will allow the processor to go into a lower power State
and say power, say battery life, save whatever.
Until there's actually some signaling happening
Okay.
so,
We need to create the semaphore.
Right.
So we need to create this semaphore and like I said, we need to call a
create semaphore EX4, that right?
So here's our create some of 4X call that will get us our seventh
floor, so Sears our semaphore handle
Like, so we're going to create a summit for.
We don't need security attributes.
Yeah.
We don't need the help.
I've seen the string value.
Here is purely optional, right?
I assume we don't need to name our summer for us.
I believe if you named semaphores, you can query them by name if this,
that makes it easier for you.
But since we will always have the handle, we don't actually care about
any of that.
So I'm pretty sure I can just pass zero here.
We don't actually need a name.
So let's do our initial count here.
And our maximum count.
So, so here's our thread info.
I'm going to go ahead and say that we've got a thread count here and
that's going to be the array count for thread info.
Like so, and I'm going to go ahead and put the thread count in there,
like the.
So let's take a look at the flags.
Well, it's reserved in must be zero.
So I guess that's, that's going to be 0.
And then we've also,
Got the desired access here and these are just going to be we want we
want just regular semaphore access right?
All possible access rights for a semaphore object.
So we want we we're not trying to do any sort of fancy security stuff.
Here, we just want regular oxidized soon that should work.
Been a while since I created one of these.
So we should be able to get a semaphore handle.
And then what I'll do is I'll just go ahead and snuggle that in here
so that each thread gets the summer for handle from its thread info
and it's going to wait on it there right now?
Remember, we haven't actually implemented anything with this yet, so
really what will happen is these guys will all do.
Wait for single object X and they'll wait on the semaphore handle and
they'll never wake back up again.
So that's not a particularly good thing, but we'll fix it, you know?
Don't worry, we'll fix it.
We're getting there.
One thing at a time.
Create this summer for handle.
We're going to go ahead.
I'm going to, I'm going to say the initial count is 0 for now.
Well, I'll do it this way, so you can actually see what's there.
So many zeros in this function, I feel like it's a good idea probably
to name them.
They're like so on.
So, here we go.
We create all our threads.
When we create the info struct, I will now put that handle in there.
So here's the semaphore handle actually getting created, right?
And
Oops, put you two in there and now what will happen is well you know
if we if we were to run this maybe we'll print out some strings but
hopefully you can sort of if you're starting I don't know.
If you're starting to think about multi-threading stuff at all or not,
I know it's hard to think about, believe me, everyone has trouble with
it.
It doesn't matter how good the program or they are multi-threading is
intricate and complicated, so don't worry about that.
But if you start to think this through a little bit, you should be
able to sort of think about what will happen here.
Because now our threads are going to sleep when they don't find
anything in the work queue.
That means that they may print out some of these strings or they may
not, it entirely depends on sort of the race between whether this main
thread gets to one of these pushes before the operating system
actually kicks off one of these guys, but before the up, the operating
system going to kick off all these threads, if all of these threads
make it to the wait for single object d x, before we push a string.
Nothing will be printed but if some of them don't then, you know, we
may see a string printed or two, but, but hopefully, you can kind of
see what's going to happen here, right?
R RQ, will now be broken.
It won't actually necessarily work and so you can actually see this is
kind of fascinating multi-threaded.
Coating is always this way, right?
So you can see what actually happened here.
If we reverse engineer it essentially, it's kind of cool because this
is actually.
So,
I kind of let that mother threatening usually isn't so perfect, but
you can kind of see exactly what happened to your right, how many
threads that we create, we create threads, right?
And so you see back in here, what's happening?
This main thread can't get to start pushing the strings, until it
creates all of these threads.
So it goes through to create thread, 0 creates thread one creates to
create stress three.
Meanwhile, those threads are starting to get kicked off.
Since this thread is busy doing all this before, it gets to the push
strings.
All those threads 0 through 6, all come into their start routine and
hit the weight before there's ever anything in the queue but thread
seven.
Not so the last thread that gets
Has created through here in this.
Create thread this routine, manages to make it to the push string
right before thread, seven starts up.
So thread seven doesn't get to here until this is already gotten to
here.
And by the time this guy has done its interlocked increment and its
output debug string.
It's had time to push the next string as well and the next thing in
the next ring, right is goes.
And so now this guy actually is able to beat him all the way through
to number 9 but what that?
Just he's always print out in exact order, right?
Because there's only one thread that's actually able to dequeue them.
Make sense.
Now, we could, you know, just to underscore what's happening here.
If all of these threads had to wait a little while, before they were
actually able to go, we'd be right back to our functioning Q because
none of them would go to sleep, right?
They'd all have a chance to actually do work before going to sleep,
right?
But that's not that's just an accidental thing and then they would
they would go to sleep in the queue would now no longer work anymore.
So we want to get this working properly, right?
What we want to do now, is say, okay, we've got this stuff for object.
How do we actually use it to wake these guys up in a way that's
relatively safe, so that we don't introduce a bunch of bugs.
Like, I was saying, where the push string is going to be a problem
there, right?
Okay, so if we come through here, right?
Oops.
If we come through here and we take a look at how we've kind of gotten
away from our semaphores, where our semaphore is create semaphore
exo-k.
So we've created our semaphore and I want to actually look.
Now if I always forget what they are, there's the signal, it's like
there's the signal semaphore thingy, there's the signal object.
Where are you?
This thing that you actually used to Signal the
Guys, and I forget what the function actually is.
Here we go.
Okay, this is our function, I believe.
Increases the count of the specified semaphore object by a specified
amount, right?
So, basically, what this does, this function actually goes ahead and,
and changes whatever that count is.
So, whatever the count is, whatever the some of our current count is,
will go up by this amount and it will return to us, whatever the
previous count actually was right.
So, every time we pushed a string,
For example, right?
If we wanted to make sure that some thread would potentially wake up
to process that string or something similar, we could do something
like that.
Like, we could say, like, release 74 here and if the threads were
asleep, this would potentially wake them up, right?
So we could do release some before.
There's a caveat here.
All threads about to sleep.
Etc.
So there's a caveat here but I'll I'll talk about how I probably will
solve that in a second by incrementing.
A number by one that seems a little weird but up, we'll get to that in
a second.
So anyway, ignore that, ignore that for a moment but so if I want to
do release semaphore here, I can so I can pass that summer for in.
I have to actually know what it is.
So I have to have this semaphore here.
So here's some for handle and what I can do is say, all right, I want
to make sure that I'm going to.
I'm going to do this cat.
So I want to release at least one because you know, I want to I'm
pushing one string on.
I want to make sure at least one thread is going to be awake to
process that and I can pass in the previous Kappa.
I don't actually care what the previous count is.
I just want to know that it's going to go up by one, right?
So that's good.
Oops man.
I'm bad at spelling Summa for
All right.
And so these all have to take the semaphore handle and off we go.
All right, there we go.
For our, okay.
All right, and so each time we put the string on here.
What's actually going to happen is these these guys here are going to
Increment, the semaphore.
and then I believe, if I'm not mistaken, the whole point of a
semaphore,
Is what you then happen.
Is it wait for single object?
X.
Whenever one of these guys wakes up that will decrement the count of
the semaphore, right.
So basically like waiting on the guy I just let me let me actually see
if this is actually true before I say it, but I believe that that what
should happen is it should increment and decrement it, okay?
Let's see.
Did you do?
It's great for into initial count me, through its release, because of
some of our signal State, the counter.
This number has decreased by one yet.
So each time away thread is released because of the semaphore signal
State.
The count of the semaphore is decreased by 1, right?
So basically, the way these semaphores are going to work for us, is
anybody who's waiting on them?
If they wake up, they will decrease the semaphore account by that one.
By one by one, it will decrement it, right?
So that provides a nice symmetry to this.
Every time we push the string, we're going to increment the value of
the semaphore and every time we wake up to process a string, we will
decrement that, right?
Which is exactly what we wanted to have happen.
And it gets us out of the business of having to worry about signaling
things in a particular order because we now know that it's just
counted, right?
So it'll count how many strings happen to be pushed on there.
And then, it will wake up as many threads as it has, in order to do
that as the semaphore.
Decrements, when it comes down to zero, it will stop waking up
threads, which is exactly what we wanted, right?
But the other thing that I couldn't remember is when you wait for
single object,
I can't remember whether wait for single object automatically
increments the count or not.
I don't think it does right, it shouldn't.
So I don't think wait for single object.
Does anything to the semaphore account, right?
I was consumed, it doesn't for now.
Yeah, let's just assume temporarily that wait for single object
doesn't do anything.
The semaphore count on Entry.
It only does it on wake up, that's what I'm expecting, but will double
check that later.
Okay, so what we need to do now,
Right.
When we have this initial count here we don't.
The reason that I'm passing in zero for the initial account is because
at first, we haven't pushed any strings on here.
So there's no reason for these threads to get signaled.
There's no reason for them to wake up or anything like that.
Right.
And so technically what we even could do is we could do it a little
bit differently here and actually just do it at the head end and say,
okay always decrement the semaphore.
But really, you know,
Should be sufficient and we want to if there's work in the queue,
always just do it without calling the operating system.
So I'm going to leave that there for now.
Right now, here is the problem that I was.
Well, you know, I think the caveat here is actually fine.
I think we're okay pretty much in all cases, right?
Because our semaphore is always going to go up.
When we do our push string here and the wait for single object.
You X is always going to go ahead and decrement that guy.
Yeah.
So I think it's fine.
Now, there's a couple ways we could have used a semaphore, we can use
the semaphore to actually indicate how much work is actually in the
queue, right?
But I don't actually want that to happen.
So as far as I'm concerned, wait, for semaphore is just going to be
how many threads are open at this particular time.
So I don't care if it ever gets above the number of thread count,
right?
So we're not going to try and track it specifically.
We're just using it as a general mechanism to put these threads to
sleep, okay?
So they go ahead and run this now and go back.
Appear.
What we should see.
Hopefully is everyone's working properly.
0 1, 2, 3, 4 5, 6, 7, 8, 9 lovely, right?
And they're all being processed on different threats and things which
is all good.
But what I want to demonstrate now is the difference between doing
this waiting and not doing this waiting.
So let's say, I do not do the waiting, here we go.
And we run the program, right?
And what we can see.
Now, if we take a look at performance, even though we're not really
doing anything,
Thing with those threads at, all right.
You can see that our processor load has spiked to 70% because many of
the cores are actually now having to do real work.
Sitting there spinning on these values, loading them in and seeing
that there's no work to do and then just going back and re checking
and rechecking and re checking and rechecking, they're all locked in
those Loops, right, and that's not good.
That is not good for battery life and it's not good for multitasking.
So we really don't want to do that if we want to actually only use the
processor when there's actual work to be done and so with
Our wait for single object.
We should be in a position where we can avoid that.
And so now you can see how much work we're doing is now commensurate
with the work that actually has to be done which is again down, sort
of where the actual renderer work was happening before.
Again, we can take a look at that here and you can see we're still at
only 6 percent, which is what we wanted to be at in terms of if we
were only using one CPU, right?
So that's good.
So our semaphore has worked, it did what we want to do, but let's do
one more.
Test here which is I'm going to make another set of these guys that
happens basically after a long sleep so I can ensure that all of them
have actually gone to sleep.
I'm going to go ahead and do that with a sleep 5000.
Then I'm going to push all these strings on here just to have sort of
like a, a and b set of strings, right?
And just to make sure there are threads wake up again when they're
supposed to wake up again, right?
So here we go.
So our threads go to sleep, we print out all the A's but then our
threads go to sleep.
And now after the timeout, when I know that the all the threats have
gone to sleep, we can make sure that we print out our be.
So all of our threads woke up again, which is great.
So that's a good thing, B, 0 b 1, d 2 3 4 5 6 7 8 9, right?
So that's good.
So we're getting there.
We now basically have a work queue that we can actually
Use it may not be the world's best work you, but we have a
successfully gotten to the point where we can put work into the queue
and have it be retired properly.
In a way that is you know that that is not susceptible to a bunch of
immediate race conditions or anything like this and which allows us to
return time back the operating system when we're not using it.
So that to me is sufficient I think for a start to the multi-threading
stuff.
So tomorrow I think what we can then now do is just go ahead and
translate this
Something that can actually call the renderer and then we'll be in
good position to actually start using all of those extra resources
that we could be using on the CPU to do our rendering for now though,
I'd like to go to the Q&A, right?
And answer any questions.
And so, also, while you I'm waiting for questions, hopefully, you can
see why I decided to do semaphore.
First semaphore is kind of a really convenient thing for work queues
where you have some number of threads, but need to potentially wake up
and do work because it allows you to make sure that you don't have
kind of the signaling interplay between the going to sleep and the
signaling.
So what you can kind of Imagine is just like if I was to do a signal
here,
I don't necessarily want to wake up all my threads, but I want to make
sure at least the number of threads wake up as there have been pushed
Rings, right?
As there are things in the queue.
And so the sum of four just gives me a really easy way to do that,
right?
Do you Seven Samurai says in the visual studio debugger you can
right-click in the output window and deselect some of the stuff.
You know, I'll be honest with you, I never have tried that.
That's kind of Handy.
Huh.
That is pretty darn handy.
Why thank you D Seven Samurai.
That is excellent.
Yeah, that's good.
I like that a lot.
Now, we just see our program output for now.
Pretty cool.
Yeah.
Cooper.
Caleb why does it have to be so complicated?
Well you know it's not that complicated, you know it's more error
prone than complicated.
I mean there's not that much to it.
Like you kind of saw how it worked.
Once you write one of these cues you can just use the Q mostly and as
long as you're careful about stuff you'll be fine.
So it's not it's not that bad.
It only gets bad if you're if you're trying to do a lot of really
interesting.
It kind of interlocking things which you know it's best to try and
avoid any way if you can because they always got bugs in them.
Why did you put the memory barrier in a macro when it's
platform-specific code?
Because this won't always be platform-specific.
These will these are going to have to get moved out into the renderer,
which will be platform-agnostic.
Actually.
So we these these will, we will have to Define these per platform and
a header file and use them.
Kind of like will be doing for the
Intrinsics.
After the sleep, some threads, did push several strings leaving out
some other of the threads.
Why is that?
Well, so one of the things you have to remember,
is the operating system is at its Leisure, going to wake up threads
based on a semaphore and who gets a chance to do what with them is
entirely up to how the operating system, scheduler ends up deciding to
do it, right?
So whoever wakes up first will process, the most entries in the queue
probably because it'll have them, you know, it'll have the Head Start
and whatever.
And it may be that like by the time, one of the guys wakes up there
isn't anything to do, right?
so, you know, it's hard to say
would sleep zero in your spinlock help anything which spin Locker
talking about this one?
Yeah, I mean, essentially, so we didn't quite get to it here but now
we actually know
we can actually do some stuff.
In fact, I guess I should have probably really have time today but
let's turn this into something way, double
Right.
This we won't have to spend lock on anymore, right?
Because now we will actually have a way of knowing what is going on.
Because so if you think about it, right, what do we know?
We know that once these guys are going to sleep, once all these guys
have gone to sleep, our semaphore will be 0, right?
So we should be able to at that point, actually, go ahead and know
Or do something creative to know that nobody is, is we should be able
to wait on that summer for ourselves essentially in some way.
Off to think about exactly how we want to do it.
But we should be able to wait on that in some way that makes it so
that we don't have to spend lock on it.
So yeah.
So sleep, putting a sleep 0 in here would not be a good idea.
We can do better than that, and we just have to think it through.
We'll make sure we do that tomorrow.
I am gooey has been trending.
Sorry if you get asked this more than you'd like to.
Yeah.
I, I don't think we'll probably do very much with.
I am gooey in this game.
No, because there won't really be much gooey in the game.
So somebody asked when you initially started this project, what were
the first five things you coated in?
Why the answer is if you would like to see go back and watch the
original videos, you can see exactly what the first, five things I
coded were.
And I will explain exactly why.
As for the person who said I missed most of tonight.
What does the volatile keyword mean?
This will be obviously on YouTube immediately thereafter after this.
And you can also watch it on the twitch broadcast so you can see me
explain volatile in the Stream.
Basically.
All
Means is mr.
Compiler, please do not optimize out loads of this variable.
Please always do the loads because this variable may change because
other threads are writing to it.
How do you plan to maintain cache line?
Coherency?
Between processors can physical CPU.
Share a castle.
I'm oh well.
Yeah, so if you couldn't tell from yesterday stream, I'm a bit
Antiquated in my knowledge of how these things work.
Fabien was actually saying that system bus locks, don't even ever
happen anymore.
Everything goes through messy, which I'll explain in a moment.
And so that is why lock free stuff actually is sort of technically
lock-free now, because I'm exiting for a processors, you don't need a
lock to do an interlocked increment.
Kind of a tidbit thing there but since you brought it up and it's a
very good question.
I will do my best to explain what you would have to go.
Learn to understand this part but I cannot really explain it to you
because it is not something I have ever studied or even really
understand it, any level beyond the very, very Basics.
But I will, I'll just give you the part that you need to know to go
learn it.
so okay so when you say how do you plan to maintain cache line,
coherency between processors
You're you're sort of presupposing that I am the person who is going
to do that but that is not true.
Actually the person who does that is the Intel chipset and it is
designed specifically to ensure cache line, coherence between
processors and cores.
So the way that they do this is through a thing called mes I which I
believe stands for like modified.
Exclusive.
Shared.
Invalid.
Right.
So this is like an acronym.
Okay.
And like I said, again, please take this.
Explanation with a very big grain of salt.
I'm just trying to tell you roughly what you should go read about this
is not something I have ever studied.
And it is not something that I know how they actually do it on the
chip at all.
I just know that it does happen.
so what essentially you have to imagine occurring,
Is you've got on your system.
Let's say that I've got some beef, daddy machine, it's a for CPU.
Each with 4 cores, right?
So I've got something like this going on here, right?
Of course, heroic or one core to core three or four or five course six
core 7 Loops seven core.
Eight core nine Core, 10 core 11, core, 12, or 13, core 14 cor 15,
right?
So I've got 16 cores in this processor spread across four logical
processors, right?
We know about this is that the cache is, we've talked about this
multiplies of handmade hero.
The cash is maybe set up in a number of configurations.
There may be an L3 cache which is out here that shared by all the
processors or that's shared just by a processor.
So each processor has its own L3 for example, or something like this,
right?
But then each core may have its own l0 or L1.
I'm sorry.
L1 or L2 or something like this, right?
Or stuff like this.
So,
The cash is L1, L2 and L3 are all they can be in various different
configurations depending on what the CPU architecture is right.
And as you correctly, sort of surmise and asking this question since
Sometimes some of the caches such as let's say, the L1 cache might be
specific to this core or to this processor.
How does it mean Tain coherence between the different processors?
Right.
And what coherence means.
For those of you who don't know, is, if I am in executing some coding
core 0 here, that changes some memory location and that memory
location is only existing currently in this cash, right?
Because let's say I've got some memory location out here, right?
This is memory location.
2500 x.25.
No, it's not.
That's a ridiculous number.
This is memory location.
0, x 100.
Let's say and it holds the value for, right?
Now.
Well, if I'm going to do something in a very naive system, that didn't
have any of this stuff happening in it that I'm about to say, then
what would happen is, I would go ahead and I would execute some code
that wants to load and change this value.
It would bring that value into the L1 cache of the processor.
Here, it would then modify the value.
And then sometime later it would get flushed out and have the new
value, like 5, or whatever.
But once it gets brought in here.
Some other core might also bring it in here, change it to a different
value.
Say six.
And then what would happen again in the naive system is whichever one
of these two cores happened to evict it from the cache.
Last, that is what the value would be, right?
So if this guy happened to finish last, this would get written as a 6.
If this guy happened to get finished last, it would get written as a
5, right?
And so coherency.
Here means that is not good, right?
We want to have some actual understanding of who is writing to which
memory locations and when so that when two people do a load,
They know that if someone else had already written to that location in
memory, when you do the load, you get the actual value.
So, what we want to actually see happen, is this guy loads the for he
changed it to a five, this guy does the load, he gets the five is what
we want now again remember this is not talking about coherency of the
program because loads into registers are not handled in any particular
way for you so that you have to worry about yourself.
So once the thing gets loaded into the CPU,
Stirs all bets are off and that's where that interlocked increment and
stuff like that, come in, but in terms of cache coherency where we
just have to worry about.
Oh somebody did some work on some memory?
Someone else later who we know is happening afterwards, right?
We did some kind of synchronization to make sure he's happening
afterwards is about to do some stuff on that memory.
Making sure that he gets the values that are actually in this guy's
cash and that haven't been written to memory yet, that part is the
coherency part, right?
Well, this is the way they do that, it's called the messy protocol.
And basically what there is is, there's a thing called a snooper.
I'm not making this up.
They really call it snooping right.
And what happens is, when somebody goes to load a value inside each of
these caches the cache lines are marked with these flags modified
exclusive shared or invalid.
And what these things mean is
What should happen when you go to load that cache line, right?
So when you go to issue a load or something like this, and this this
core wants to actually access the the stuff that's in this particular
location, right?
It's cash actually knows whether or not some other part of the cash,
previously did a right that would create a modified State on that
cache line, right?
Because basically what happens is when somebody goes to write to a
cache line, I believe what happens is it
It transitions that cache line to modify in itself and forces the
other people's caches by notifying them that they have to become
invalid.
Because the value that they have in, there is no longer
Good.
Right.
Something like this happens.
So what will happen from then?
On when this guy goes to do the load knows that what it's got is old
data.
So when it actually goes to do that load, it will actually Snoop
quote-unquote, the contents of this other guys cash and get that back.
Instead of the value that's actually out in memory.
That's the snooping part.
Is it actually Snoop someone else's cash, right?
So, the way these transitions works are actually important, if you
care about learning about this, go read about it, they'll tell you, it
has something to do with, like, okay, when two people read from the
same cache line, they transition to Shared.
So they know that two people are looking at it, if it's in shared,
then when you want to go modify, you have to do a like read for
ownership to turn it into exclusive where you can then modify it
because you know that no one else is modifying.
And they all transition from shared to invalid and blah blah blah.
Right.
So it's they've worked this whole thing out that allows them to make
it so that everything is coherent in here and off you go, the long and
short of this is you don't have to worry about it on x64 because the
exit before chipset is actually really darn good and will maintain the
cache coherency entirely on its own with no help from you whatsoever.
The only thing you have to make sure you do is you don't go working on
things in red.
Stirs thinking that you're updating them out in memory somewhere and
expecting everyone can see them and then having two people over,
right?
The same value because that the processor can't protect against at
all.
And that is why we have the things like interlocked increment which
are saying oh wait a minute.
Like okay hold on a second that sort of read modify write cycle,
right?
That thing where we pull something into the to this, to the register,
We operate on it in the register and then we put it back out to the
cash that thing.
We have to be responsible enough to make sure that we are never doing
that in a way that isn't properly interlocked, but as long as that's
okay, right?
The cash part we never have to worry about because the Ecstasy for
chip is actually really good.
Was volatile added in c99.
I don't know, I don't know when volatile was added.
I feel like volatile has been there a long time.
I feel like volatile was in there before I see 99.
Abner Cohen, Bray wait.
So transactional memory wants to simplify concurrent programming by
allowing a chunk of load and store instructions to execute in execute
in atomically.
Have you messed with this?
I'm not mess with this.
I don't even know.
Are there chips right now that have it in it that aren't broken.
I thought the desktop tips had it broken.
So they disabled it or
This, I don't know.
But yeah.
Okay.
So again, this is not something I've ever used.
It's coming down the pipe.
I don't know if it's actually in there working yet.
It's definitely in there in modern processors.
I just don't, it was broken in some of the chips.
So they disabled it.
And so I don't know which ones have it enabled or disabled.
It's probably enabled and fixed by now.
I have no idea.
But what this is, there's a thing called transactional, memory.
And what transactional memory is, is basically a way of doing a thing,
they typically call La Collision.
And lock Collision is a fancy word for like not doing the lock.
So, okay, so suppose I gotta update a bunch of stuff, right?
Suppose, I've got a whole, you know, I've got some struct, right?
And it's not just one value that I can do a locked increment on, and
it's got all these things in it and I want to update the whole thing,
right?
Well basically what this transactional memory is is it's basically an
interlocked compare exchange.
Remember we talked about interlock compare Exchange,
Which is basically saying, okay, I want to replace the value.
That's out of memory location.
So long as the value that's in there right now, is this one that I
expect it to be right?
Well, transactional, memory is basically like a giant one of these
around, a whole block of memory.
Basically, what it does is it says, like, begin transaction,
And I'm going to begin this transaction.
I'm going to touch some cash lines, right?
So I'm going to go ahead and touch this struct right on a right, all
into it, and just do all kinds of crazy garbage, right?
Blah, blah, blah.
So that's happening in here and then at the end I'm going to say, end
transaction, right?
And what's going to happen is the processor is going to look to see
whether anyone else ever took ownership of the cache lines for writing
During the period where I was taking ownership of them for writing,
right?
And if they were it's just going to not ever commit any of that stuff.
Makes sense.
So it's basically a way of doing a bunch of work as if you were single
threaded and then going hey, did anyone else touch it?
If the answer is no great committed.
If not, then I will have to actually do some work that actually
involves taking a lock so that I can actually do the work or something
like this, right?
So they call that alighting the lock.
I don't know why.
Like I said this is not something I tend to work with and basically
what you're saying is okay, if it just so happens that no other thread
was going to do anything at this time.
Then I can avoid doing any sorts of locks by using the transactional
memory.
That's, that's just how that goes.
And so, yeah, I'm not the person to explain that to you.
I have never used it before.
I do not even know what the Primitives are that they introduced and
x64 for this or exactly how they work.
But it's something along these lines.
We're basically because they already have all of this cash control in
there and happening.
I guess it just made good sense for them to expose it, so that you can
Implement transactional memory on it where you could basically say,
Hey, you already know whether anyone
Did did any operations on these cache lines?
While I was trying to do what I wanted to do to them.
So hey, could you go ahead and just tell me if they did?
And that way, I don't have to do a lock if it turns out nobody did.
And Abner Cumbre said transaction members often Advocate as an easier
to use replacement for locks that avoid any possibility of a deadlock.
So I wanted your thoughts and so yeah, transactional memory is, you
know, supposedly more efficient at the limit than taking locks and
stuff like that.
But what, you know what, I hope to show on handmade hero is for a lot
of the stuff that we want to do in games you don't ever need to take a
look anyway.
So you know like a heart, a real lock
Has to be taken.
And so what you want to do first and foremost is just do all your code
as much as possible to never really use to never, require something
like transactional memory.
But then, if you do get into a circumstance where you find that you
really need transactional memory for some reason.
Then you know, then you do.
So if you really have to, if you really have to use it you can use it.
Now, keep in mind that transactional memory doesn't have to be
transactional.
Memory is a concept, not a processor feature.
There are features in x64 which now allow you to implement
transactional, memory more efficiently but you can actually Implement
transactional style stuff Yourself by just having ways that you check
to see whether other people have done things.
So for example, one thing we could do that would be a
Actual memory style operation is, you know, our Sim regions are Sim
regions when they go to commit their results.
Back to the main store, could check to see if anyone else had already
written to some of the entities that they were going to touch.
And if so abort the simulation right?
That would be a way we could use transactional memory.
That has nothing to do with what's in the processor.
It's simply using the concept of transactional memory, and that is
something that may we may well do.
Who knows?
We'll see when we get there.
If we want to start multi-threading our simulations and
And we find that that's something that's important for us to do.
We could do it, right.
Plain flavored.
Why are we building a generic work distribution system when the tiled
renderer is designed to cleanly split up the work anyways?
Well, the answer is because again, we do need some kind of a queue.
Like, I've explained this yesterday, I don't know if you caught it,
but I explained this yesterday right here.
Basically, the tiled render is just designed to break up the screen
into tiles.
But we don't know how long each of those tiles will take to process.
It could be that some of those tiles take a long time and others the
tiles take hardly any time because some of them may have like complex
particle systems happening in them and other than may have nothing but
like a single tree sitting there, right?
So we want to basically take all the tiles and put them into a work
queue and then have our threads, grab those things off the work queue,
so that if one thread gets unlucky and happens to grab a 10
millisecond, chunk out of 10 millisecond tile out of the work queue.
It's not going to hold up the entire rendering because we have to wait
for it to finish that and then finish all of its other tiles that were
supposed to do.
We want all the other tiles to be handled by the other thread so that
by the time that 10 millisecond chunk is done the whole things done,
right?
So we still need a work queue even though we've broken our things up
into tiles.
A work queue is important and we don't need a super fancy work Q.
So we haven't built a fancy work queue but we need a work queue and so
we built a work queue and that is what we will use.
We seem to have run out of questions.
Well, that's handy because we have also run out of time.
So,
Now would be a good time to wrap things up.
There we go.
Let's go ahead and close things down.
Okay, thank you everyone for joining me for another episode of
handmade hero.
We have been doing multi-threading this week and now we have gotten to
the point where we've more or less finished the basics of
multi-threading in terms of how to build a work queue.
And at this point really all we have left to do is actually use that
work you to call our renderer so that's what we'll be doing tomorrow
and go that's not entirely true we got one more thing.
We have to do tomorrow.
First thing we'll do on the stream is actually to show how to have the
Same thread not have to busy wait or maybe we won't do that.
First thing America's at the end of the day we can't have that main
thread busy wait that's not the end of the world but we should
probably do that for completeness so we'll do that and then we'll go
ahead and actually get it calling the renderer which will involve a
couple things basically evolved abstraction that code out into a way
that we can call it cross platform in a nice way.
So let's do a little bit of work there and then the other thing we'll
have to do is we have to clean up a couple things in the renderer that
currently don't let us run multi-threaded?
we hopefully will see those as
Bug.
So you don't have to just take my word for it that they could happen
but, you know, maybe not, maybe we'll just have to sort of fix them
preemptively and say, trust me, this will be a bug.
So that's what we'll do tomorrow and I hope you'll join me for that
same time, same place, 5 p.m.
Pacific Daylight time tomorrow right here on Twitch, until then, if
you would like to follow along with the source code, you can always
pre-order the game on handmade hero dot-org and it comes with a source
code, so you can go ahead and download it every night after we're done
with it and play around with it to your heart's content.
If you have questions, please ask them on our forums.
They are pretty handy.
You can also check out the ante depe sewed, guide, that members of the
community have working on that helps fill up with past videos stuff.
Like, that's pretty cool.
There's also ports of mac and Linux and things like this up there.
The community members have done, that might help you if you're trying
to follow along on those platforms.
If you just want to support the video series, we very much do
appreciate that fact.
And we have a patreon page for that.
If you would like to subscribe to it, we also have a tweetbot, the
tweets, the schedule it.
You, so if you want to check out the schedule and keep up to date on
when the streams going to be live desk,
Do it.
And finally, we've got a little Live Now, button that button will tell
you the countdown, till the next live stream.
If you are wondering when it is, you can always visit.
He made here at org and see it.
That's about it for today.
Thank you, everyone for joining me and I hope to see you back here,
tomorrow, until then have fun programming, and I will see you on the
internet.