We will deal with that later.
Alright, hello, everyone?
And thank you for joining me for another episode of handmade hero.
The show where we code a complete game from scratch using nothing.
No libraries.
No engines, just right on top of the OS as low as we can possibly go.
And again, this is just an educational program.
We're basically trying to do everything that's involved in the actual
execution of a game, so that people can understand the complete
technology behind them with no kind of hidden aspects.
Misunderstandings like, really getting down into, absolutely
everything that makes a game tick because not only do I think that's
important because hey the next generation of engine programmers, and
are going to have to be able to do all that stuff.
But also because even if you always intend on using engines or
libraries understanding how everything works, in the full stack of a
game, really allows you to make better decisions.
It allows you to debug things better and it allows you to drop down
and do low-level stuff in the
Is where you actually need to in order to make new things for your
game.
In the cases where existing things just don't work.
Right?
Or don't support the kind of things that you need.
So pretty much there's never really a bad time to learn more about low
level stuff because it can only really make you more powerful in
everything that you do no matter what level you do it at.
And so with that with that stated, we're going to do some stuff today
that we to pick up on where we left off yesterday where we were trying
to basically put C into a position.
To be as easy to use as a scripting language in terms of turnaround
time.
So instead of having to go through a compile, debug Run Cycle every
time you want to change something and see where you have to restart
the app.
We made something yesterday where we could just change the C code and
it would automatically update in the game without having to close the
game.
And so we're going to do is kind of we're going to work on that a
little bit more today and perfect it to getting to the point where we
can just Live code C and have the game change, right?
It's at a nice lie, as we change the C code, so if you are following
Along at home.
If you have pre-ordered, the game, you should have gotten an email
with a link in it that link always allows you to download the latest
source code.
It is one big zip file that has separate steps in it for every day.
And as you can see here, Friday handy dandy counter, we are on day 22.
So if you would like to follow along with us unzip day 21 and you will
have the exact same Source set up as I have right now.
So with that said, here we go.
Now a couple things happened yesterday.
Basically, we were having trouble with
I was having trouble figuring out how to tell the compiler.
No, really.
We don't want an exit.
We just want to deal L, but it turned out, the only reason for that
was because I was compiling in the build-up bet.
I was compiling trying to pass the / dll to the Linker, but it in
turns out, if you're actually calling CL and not the Linker, you have
to pass this /ld switch.
So it's just a compiler, switch change that you have to do.
So we did that yesterday.
But what that means is that a couple of things that we did to try and
get things to Output a dll are not actually necessary.
So for
People at the bottom of handmade dot CPP.
I had inserted this dll main, which is basically the place where when
a dll is loaded Windows calls that back just to see if it needs do
anything.
We don't need to do anything.
But I check to see if we had to put that in there.
I don't think we actually need that anymore.
So I'm just going to verify that we actually don't and it looks like
we don't.
So then we have in our build directory.
We still should be producing a dll and we are not Annex C.
So basically just want to get rid of that code because didn't need to
be there.
So there's no need for it.
Other than that.
We were in a
Pretty good position.
Yesterday.
I'm going to recap sort of where we were.
Just so you have a good understanding of what we're going to do in a
second here.
But basically where we gotten to is if we go into the build directory
and we ran our game, right?
And here is the game.
We were now in a position where we could.
If we wanted to go into good new emacs, or whatever, editor, you
happen to be using at home, if I want to kind of make it so that I can
see a little bit better.
I'll make a little kind of short shorter and Squad easier, if you
will.
Oops,
Windows for correcting that, of course, that's what I wanted you to
do, was to make it the, the whole window size.
So if I go in here, now while the game is running, we had actually
gotten it to a point where I could go and change what it was doing and
it would update on the fly.
So for example, if I wanted to change this from using green, to
putting green in the green slot, to putting green in the red slot, I
can do that.
I can hit save and then the game will periodically reload, Oscar.
I got to build it first, so I build the game.
Mmmmm, when it actually finishes building the game will then pick it
up and change the color.
But you'll notice there's a fair bit of lag there right?
When I get it and I redo it.
There's a fair bit of lag there.
And the reason that there's lag is that our game is only actually
checking to see if it needs to reload every so often.
It's only checking about once every two seconds.
So that's something.
We could fix and get it a little bit better.
The other thing that we would like to fix at a bare minimum is that if
we were running in the debugger, oops, that's no good.
I keep forgetting.
That the in fact I should
Let's go ahead and close that.
Get that out of there.
I was thinking the witness earlier today and don't want that getting
getting a snuck in here.
This is not a witness coding session.
This is a, this is a handmade hero coding section session.
So basically, if I was to run this in the debugger, right, so I run
this, this the same thing that we were running, but I run it under the
debugger.
If I was to go, try to recompile.
We ran into a problem, which is that Visual Studio when I try to
compile when the game is running it,
Aunt actually compile.
Because Visual Studio has locked the debug information file.
And so the compiler is unable to actually do anything about that.
It can't out put a new one because it's trying to write it over to the
same place.
And this is pretty bad because I would like to always be able to run
into the Bugger.
I don't want to have to stop using the debugger when we want to use
our Live code loading.
So what I'd like to do is also figure out a way to get around that.
So the first thing we're going to do is see, I don't actually know
this.
This didn't used to be
Visual Studio like many, Microsoft products gets worse with every
revision.
And this is one of the ways that it got worse before, when you would
unload a dll, it would actually unload the pdb, as well.
And so, I assumed that it would do that, and that all we'd have to do
today is make sure that we actually do that, like, in the game, we
would unload, the dll it would unload, the pdb, windows Visual Studio
would stop locking, the pdb, for Access, so we could write to it and
then we would reload it and everything would be fine, but from
looking.
On the web today because I wanted to check to see if that was true.
Still, it turns out that it does not look like it is true.
It looks like visual studio now continues to lock the pdb even after
you unload a dll even though it doesn't need the pdb anymore.
It's just keeps it locked.
So, we could go verify that that's true.
Or what we could do is try to change what we do a little bit to see if
we can work around it.
So, one thing that I was thinking of people were saying, basically,
you have the timestamp, the dll and stuff like that, but I'm not sure
if that's actually true, we can change using a compiler option.
We can change the name of the pdb that we're going to use.
We can force it to Output the pdb to a different file if we want to.
I'm going to go ahead and look up that here.
So if I Google for msv cset name of pdb, there should be a thing which
basically tells us a Linker flag.
Well, actually it looks like a compiler flag.
Sorry, a compiler flag that basically allows us to pass the name that
we want for that pdb.
And so it's a /f d.
So if I go in here and I say /f d in theory, I should be able to.
I don't know why you / has all of a sudden when I usually use dashes.
Basically, I should be able to pass something else.
So let's say I go ahead and pass some other thing here.
Like, you know, food out, pdb.
I should be able now to make it build a different pdb into the build
directory.
Let's see if that actually works.
So I do not see a food pdb.
Why do I not see a food up?
Pdb?
That does not look like it worked.
People does not look like it worked at all.
Am I wrong?
I did not think I'm wrong.
Let's delete all the pdp's.
Just double-check.
There we go.
Yeah, so it's still going to handmade .pd be as far as I can tell,
which looks like R.
Minus FD does not seem to have stuck.
So I know this is yet another situation where names default to vo.
Well, this is not, Hmm.
This is that secondary pdb, which is not the pdb that I actually
wanted to rename.
Is there another one that I can do that changes the other?
Because remember, we actually stopped it from outputting that vcp DB1,
the other type of PD.
Be we actually stopped it from doing that.
So I don't know.
Can the Linker does the Linker have a way that we
Put the pdb and maybe change it there because there should be a way to
do that.
So let's take a look here out / pdb, alt path.
I don't know if that's good, an alternate location for the program
database file in a compiled, binary file.
Normally the Linker records location PDF file in the binary.
Is that it produces?
You can use this option for a different path and file name for the pdb
file.
The information provided in pdb all past and that change location
actual pdb file.
But what does pdb path?
Is that right?
Let's take a look here.
Come on.
Msdn.
You can load it up.
P path.
Will search your computer along with the file passes Burger search
for, pdb know.
So I don't know.
Let's see, does anyone around the stream know which is a, which is a
way, I can tell it to do that because last time I spent too long
looking for compiler symbols.
And to be honest with you.
This is a lot of my life.
Whenever I'm on Windows is searching the Arcane documentation to try
and find out how to just do something.
Really simple, which is like set.
Where are you?
This pdb goes and a lot of times something like what I just did like
exactly what just happened.
Is what happens to me.
A lot of the time I will go in.
I'll find documentation that says, here is how you set where the pdb
goes.
I'll do it and then it doesn't work.
And of course, there's really no way that you can actually go in and
do anything about that.
Because you have like nothing to go on.
Like you have no idea why it's deciding not to use the switch that you
have specified.
So, again,
Excuse me.
I'm not sure.
So I'm going to see if I can just go ahead and set it in here on the
Linker.
I don't know if this will work /, pdb.
No / pdb.
Actually supports arguments, but I'm going to go ahead and try it
there.
Because like I said, I just want to see if I can.
I can put it to a different file name and have that help us here.
Let's see.
So, pdb: file name, looks like that should do it.
So I'll specify it here, instead of there and see if that helps at
all.
I don't know.
Maybe, I need to specify in both places.
Let's find out that looked like it work.
So apparently specifying it to the Linker works.
But specifying to the compiler does not work.
Is that true?
So I deleted the pdbs.
Let's compile it again.
And let's see what it does.
So, that looks good.
All right.
So now we've just got the two pdbs, one for our win32, which is fine,
because that never closes and one for the game code, which goes into
food out, pdb.
So, now, what I'm going to do is I'm going to see if we can just
generate a different name for the pdb every time.
So basically, we'll do handmade underscore.
I don't know.
Like there's probably, isn't there a date.
Predefined thing for date or something like this.
Let me see in Windows and think there is date.
Yeah, so there's a pretty
Defined thing for date.
So let me see if there's something that we can do here that would
allow us to set the date, to something that would be convenient to
insert.
Because those slashes would not be a good thing, obviously to put into
a file name.
But it would seem oops, that that would be fine.
In fact, that would actually probably be fine.
You know, we could just do something like handmade underscore time Dot
pdb, and I don't know if that'll work, but it probably will.
Let's take a look.
No, that did not work program to are writing profile.
So it doesn't like that name because the colons.
Yeah, so the cohens won't work.
So is there any way that I can actually make this?
Do something that will be a good name.
So let's take a look here, bat file a pen time to name.
Let's see.
Let's take a look here.
Stack Overflow.
I don't think has redeemed itself.
It's his entire time.
So this could be its big chance.
All right, so there they've got a little syntax here.
That looks like they there is a Syntax for the time command.
So that would suggest to me that we can do.
MS-DOS time variable syntax.
Is there a thing that would tell us what that was?
And then we could take a look.
Let's take a look date and time.
Let's see here.
Let's see.
Yeah, so it looks like we can do some stuff that has to do with all
this doesn't look like a very concise way of doing that.
So, all right.
Maybe we'll just do what it says in here.
Alright.
So basically we could use Blau this is look at that.
That is some crazy stuff.
I didn't even know there.
A lot of I don't even know how to do a lot of this stuff in batch
files.
That looks like some crazy stuff.
I don't even know.
Look at look at this.
That's crazy town.
It's a little bit more crazy than I was hoping for.
Wow.
Yeah, I don't know.
But let's take a look.
So if we actually use this line here, right?
Let's see what that?
What that actually equals when you Echo it and if that's something
that we could use.
I don't know if it is or not.
That doesn't look promising.
I wonder if we have to have command extensions in able to actually use
these things.
I'm not actually sure.
I am not actually sure.
So again, this is all just really simple stuff.
Like I am not an MS-DOS batch junkie or anything like that.
But really all I want to do is make one of these that sanitized so
that I can so that I don't have to do anything fancier to get em SVC
to stop locking our file.
So I'm just going to make it output to a different pdb every time and
hope that that fixes it.
So if I want to do that, I just need a way of format the date in a way
that isn't
Totally crazy.
So let's see.
Replace.
I guess the other thing I should check is to see whether this works in
a batch file instead of it's possible that the thing does work in a
batch file and or does work under the set command and doesn't work in
other things.
So let's try this as well.
Then see what test is set to now.
So it doesn't work there either.
So I don't know.
That could be, I'm not sure why they have that.
And I'm not sure why they are able to do this or think that that works
and we can't write, but it could be.
Well, it looks like maybe it was just a typo in the previous one.
All right, so that's fine for our purposes.
Actually.
That is totally fine.
All we need is some unique Stream.
So if that works, that's totally fine.
There we go.
And we don't care at all about this code.
This is literally just working around the craziness in visual studio.
So, let's see if that allows us to do it.
Okay, so that's
Total Crazy Town don't even know what that does.
Like.
I literally have no idea.
This would be interesting.
This actually kind of has me interested.
I will probably go read about this later.
I didn't know that you could do these Tilda things.
Like normally, you know you in a thing you can put in some kind of a
variable in, it'll fill it in inside, parentheses inside a batch file.
I had no idea there was this: tilde crazy replacement syntax.
It looks like it's giving you character offsets.
- 44 - 10 to like, look at all that.
It was like you're extracting.
It.
Looks like you can basically say put in give me the value of this
variable and then extract this range from it, which is pretty kind of
cool.
I mean, MS-DOS batch files are so underwhelming in terms of what they
can do.
It's kind of cool when you find something where you're like, oh that I
could actually use that.
So, basically, all I want to do here is I want to just delete the pdbs
that currently exist, right?
I want them to go away.
And then I want to rebuild them, and I'm going to make a different
name every time.
And so really, all I did is I say, okay, delete all the PD bees and
then use this crazy.
Awesome string from stack Overflow.
That's amazing.
And and is absolutely nuts to just stick a thing on that's based on
the time and that way every time I recompile my pdb will have a
different name.
And so what I'm hoping is now when I run visual studio, right?
It's going to load that pdb file for the dll and if it keeps
Locked.
I'm hoping that that's okay.
Because, basically, now when I go in here, right?
And I asked this to recompile, it will actually just recompile to a
different pdb altogether, right?
So when I come in here and I do this, I'm assuming that it won't touch
that one.
It'll just use a completely different one and then it can re pick up
the old dll and there it goes.
So I'm hoping that that is the simplest possible solution to this
problem.
You don't have to do any trickery.
We don't have to change our DNA.
LOLs name.
The dll can always be built to the same place.
But basically we just keep making new pdb.
He's making new pdb.
He's making new pdbs.
And you can see that they start stacking up here, right?
Every time I make a change will end up with a new pdb in there because
M SV c will keep them all.
Locked in its infinite testable.
Wisdom.
I have no idea why it's doing that, but we don't really have to care.
It just means there's a little more space used on our drive for these
pdbs right there.
They all are stacking up.
But as soon as I end this program and we get out of here, then they
will no longer be locked.
So when I go to do my build again, you can see there's all the pdbs
there.
But when I go to do my build again, it should delete them all.
And there they go.
Now it's kind of annoying to have that deletion thing.
Show up, so, I'm wondering if I can just do something to tell it to be
quiet.
So like, don't, you know, don't tell me all the time when you can't
delete things.
So there is a minus q, but I don't know if that actually do it.
So, let's find out.
Let's see if there's a way to tell delete to be just a little quieter
because again, I'm just trying to figure out how to get rid of this.
Access is denied.
Access is denied nonsense, right?
So in here, I'm going to go ahead and see there's the pdbs.
I do Del startup PDP it.
Access is denied.
If I do / Q still says.
So I don't know if there is a way to make it quiet down.
Prompts for confirmation for still eating green, only files.
Delete specified files from all sub directories.
Yeah.
I don't know.
It doesn't seem to be any way to do that.
Now.
I have RM installed but I don't really want to do that because I don't
know if that's I don't think that's installed on most.
People systems, unfortunately, so I don't know.
We may have to live with that.
I'm not sure if there's a way we could, what we could do is pipe it to
something that we don't care about.
So, one of the things that you can do obviously in a command shell,
right?
Is if I do Del startup pdb, it prints its stuff to the to the thing.
If I want to I can pipe it to like Foo dot txt.
Right?
And I think you can even pipe even the error stream as well.
I don't know if you can do that in thing.
Not sure.
Yeah.
I don't know if you can pipe the error stream.
But basically what you can do is you can pipe the output of it to a
file.
So I can at least put some I can at least send it somewhere and I
could send it somewhere that we don't care about like Unix you pipe to
a thing called Dev know which is basically just a place that eats
everything I could do something like that.
But for now, I guess I'm not sure what I want to do with that.
So let's just leave that for now.
And we'll think about it.
We'll think about that a little bit later because I don't even
remember the Syntax for piping basically.
Commands from the console have two different streams and we didn't
cover this because we're not making a console app, but there's
basically two different streams that console apps can write to
standard out and standard error and they can be redirected separately.
So, by default any time tries to write text to something called
standard out.
It shows the console any time, it tries to write something called
standard error.
It shows up in the console.
But if you do something like I did where I use that little pipe
syntax, so I did start up.
And then I try to pipe it to a text file like this, this little arrow.
Here says, send the output of this thing to food out text.
When I do that, right?
It sends only what's called standard out, only the output which
doesn't include standard error, which is usually what things right to
when they have an error message like, access denied.
So you can see, we got rid of some of the printing, but not all of it.
Now, what the command is to pipe standard error.
I don't even remember.
I do not remember what it is.
Let's see.
Let's check the stream and see if anyone knows on there.
So they say /, null / to null.
So they were saying potentially you could do this sort of thing,
right?
I don't know if that actually works.
Doesn't look like it though, which is the 2 comes with four.
So it's this way.
Okay.
So there we go.
So there is a way to Output to pipe the different stream.
So what we could do is do something like this and you could can
actually do them to basically a null destination, which says just eat
it entirely.
I don't really want to go down too far to oops.
I don't really want to.
Okay.
Thank you.
I don't really want to go too far down that path necessarily, but this
looks like a relatively solid thing.
We can do that just as
Get rid of that input because we don't ever care about it.
But like I said, I don't want to cover batch file programming because
a, I don't know it and be it's really only applicable to Windows.
So let's go ahead and put that on the end here.
So that's basically saying get rid of all those messages and there we
go.
Now we have a much cleaner thing and it just keeps on going.
I wish this thing would not tell us about the Performing full link
because I thought that I had turn incremental off.
I'm here.
But maybe I did that wrong.
It's supposed to be off or, no.
I'm not sure exactly why.
I can't seem to get it.
Not to do, not to do that stuff.
I'm going to change these to my supposed to do that.
So I'm not sure if I could get it to stop complaining about that
necessarily.
Where are the common Linker switches.
Did I forget them?
That's probably the problem.
My common Linker Flags.
So it's not on there.
Right?
This one's not, I'm not actually using the common Linker Flags because
all of this stuff is not actually on there.
So, okay.
So basically, I should change this.
I should probably change the structure of these, but we'll deal with
that, a little later.
So, let's see what happens if I turn off, incremental linking, and
there we go, so that's, that's better.
That's a much more concise one certainly.
So I can live with that that seems pretty good.
And now we are able to reload in the debugger which solves one of my
problems, right?
So that's that's better.
We're getting better.
We're getting closer to good but we're still not great yet.
What I'd like to do a couple more things.
Like a really simple one is I'd like to make it so it's much more
instantaneous.
So again right now if I'm running it here, basically I
Over here in and I want to edit something.
I'm in handmade dot CPP.
I want to change.
Make this change.
I want it.
So that as soon as I hit that em when I see it complete, I want it to
change right away.
I don't want to wait around for some number of seconds for that to
happen.
So what I'd like to do is change our platform code, a little bit to
make it so that we don't have that delay and it's pretty easy to do
that actually.
Because if you think about it, all we really need to know is whether
that file changed and checking if that file changed is actually
pretty.
Simple because what I can do, is, I can look at the date stamp on the
file.
Because if you look, basically all files have a date stamp, it shown,
right here, right?
You can see all the files and when they were when they were last
touched, what I can do is I can just look at that date stamp and
periodically, check it.
Checking the date stamps really quick.
So we could check the date stamp like every frame and not really can
not really have any kind of Real Performance penalty associated with
that.
Just check in the date stamp a one file.
So I could do is, I could check the date stamp of just the deal.
If the date stamp has changed, reload it, if it hasn't don't and then
we would get down to just one frame of latency.
Basically, like we wouldn't even be able to see it.
So I think that's the safest thing to do.
So basically what I was doing here may not even need to be necessary
anymore, either we could think about whether it is or not.
But if you remember at the end of last dream, what I did is since the
I needed to rebuild the dll what I do.
Every time before I load, it is like copy it to a temp and I load the
temp.
Now, we wouldn't necessarily have to do that.
I don't think but I think I'm going to keep that in there just just
because it works.
Actively well, so I think we want to I think I want to keep that in
there.
Okay.
So we're going to do this first to do here.
We're going to do automatic determination of when updates are
necessary.
So the first thing I'm going to do is I'm just going to Define this
name here because this handmade dll.
So I'm going to I'm going to actually store what the name is so that I
don't use it multiple times.
So basically we're going to have the source dll name and that's going
to be this, right?
And then we're going to have the temp, dll name and that's going to be
this.
And that way we just don't
We don't spam strings all over the place.
So we've got the source dll name that's here.
We copy the source to the temp.
Dll name and then we load the temp.
Dll name, right?
Real simple.
Nothing.
Nothing particularly crazy going on there, pretty basic.
So what I want to do now is I want to extend this code to basically
say, all right, let's also whenever we do this load, let's snap a
reference.
Let's snap a the file date.
Let's just just get a quick handle on.
How old the file is so that later we can check against that and see if
we need to reload.
So I want to do win32, get filed date and we want them basically the
msdn documentation for this.
So here you go.
You can see it's really pretty basic.
It's some of the windows 32.
Hope you guys are actually pretty straightforward and good.
Basically, all we have to do is just pass it the handle to a file and
it'll give us back the different the creation time the access time and
the right time.
Now my question is, I don't necessarily want to have to open the file.
So I'm wondering if there's perhaps an easier way to do it than that
happen to do it.
That way I could call this, right?
But you notice it takes a handle, not a path.
And I don't actually want to open the file for any particular reason.
So I'm
Worried that might incur a little bit of extra cost.
So I'm thinking I might use a different API.
Let's take a look.
Here.
There's a thing called Fine first file, which is used for searching
files on a drive, basically.
And I'm wondering if that may not be a faster way to do it.
It's hard to tell but basically the way this works is you call fine,
first file and you give it a file name and that found them could be a
wild card.
But in this case, we wouldn't pass a wild-card.
We just passed the actual file name.
And then I'm wondering if perhaps this fine data, but the data that it
passes back.
Wouldn't have what we need.
Because you can see in here.
It's kind of embedded in there.
Right?
It's got the creation time access time and right time, now, I don't
know which one of these would be faster.
I really don't.
I just think, maybe not opening a file handle, might be a better idea.
So if I call this, so we'll just try this first.
And maybe if it's a problem will actually check, but, you know, we'll
just try this first.
We'll call fine first file.
Excuse me, as a way to get that date.
So basically what happens is this opens up a find handle right?
Instead of a file handle, which is the thing that I was thinking might
be a little might be a little faster.
If I was to open on the source, dll name and then pass, one of these
win for you to find data structures.
Find data to it.
Will fill it out for me.
And then I do a fine clothes.
This is something, this actually like does produce a handle, which is
unfortunate.
Again.
I wish I could do something that didn't produce any handle at.
But I don't know if there actually is anything that will get oops,
that will actually get a files date without doing some kind of an
open.
There might be somewhere, but I don't actually know.
Let's take a look at any of these.
Other guys will do it.
I don't think so.
I don't think there is think you actually got to get the name.
Well, I don't know.
It does not look so does not look so but anyway, so I'm going to do a
fine clothes on the handle to get rid of it by the handle.
Oh, there we go.
And so that should give us back the actual stuff that we wanted, the
actual data that we actually need.
And that is something that we can kind of wrap up here into into a
call that we can use to get the the date of that file like every
frame.
So I'm going to go ahead and here and go to the this fine.
First thing.
I'm going to take a look at that win32 find data and basically what we
want is this last right?
Time the last time.
The thing was written to write.
So we want, we want to
Grab that out of the result.
So basically that
Data dot last, right time is going to be one of these file time,
things, and that file time thing is going to be the last right time of
the file.
So I can pull this out now and I can make this a little thing, a
little function that returns a file time.
That's called get five last right, time like this and then I can go
ahead and put it in there.
Whatever the file name is that we're going to load.
It will do that.
And then that will allow me in theory to just
Go ahead and get the filed every frame, if I want to.
I think that should work.
Now, of course that find handle this, this could fail.
In other words.
It's not, it's not a given that it can find a file.
If the file doesn't exist or something like that.
Then it wouldn't work.
So there's a question of what we do on failure and I think it's
probably safe for us to just go ahead and return a 0 handle.
If that was the case, like to just basically say, all right, if this
file handle,
It's not equal to invalid handle value.
Then we will go ahead and do the actual work.
If not, then we will just leave the last right time to 0.
Because that means, you know, when I'm thinking about how this is
going to work, when I asked to the last right time, let's say the file
doesn't exist yet.
So we haven't built the game code.
Well, all I need to do is make sure that the last right time is
something that when the game code does exist.
It will not compare equal to it, because that will trigger us to
reload it, right?
So I think just passing as
Zero back here, should be completely sufficient.
So let's let's assume that that's true.
Now.
The other thing I don't know is whether or not assuming that this
returns invalid handle value.
I don't think I have to find close it.
So that should be it for that and then we go ahead and get the time
out of it.
Well, I guess this is a little cleaner if I actually do it this way,
so that should basically be all I really need to do.
And then I'm going to go ahead and say that will also pass the file
name in here.
All right.
So let's go down to our with 32 load game code function which is right
here.
Let's let's go ahead and pass the source, dll to that.
And when we are going to load it, basically whenever we load it, I'm
going to snap that file date into into the into the struct that we
return.
So this results direct right here, where we restore everything about
the game that we loaded.
I'm also going to store that file time.
That's like the last right.
Time for the dll.
Let's see, dll last right.
Time SEC.
Okay.
So I'm going to update that in here.
I'm going to say OK when we go ahead and do this load Library,
whenever we do that.
I am going to go ahead and snap a copy to that.
It won't be perfectly accurate because in theory, it could change in
between these two, but that's okay.
This is not code.
That's Mission critical or anything.
This is just for our own debugging purposes.
So we should be fine.
I will ask for the last right, time?
Right here.
Just using the same code that we already did.
Actually, I should.
Should we use the same name here?
So like that and let's go ahead and compile that in theory.
Let's see Source.
Dll name.
We should now have something that works exactly the way that we did
before.
This should actually be no change when we're actually doing it.
We should still be able to do our changes, but they still should be
latent.
So, everything should still be working, there shouldn't be any
bizarreness there.
There we go, but we still got that latency.
So now we're in a good position to fix.
latency, so,
Now in win32 handmade, we don't have to do, is this load counter
anymore?
Basically, we have a way to unload and load the game code.
So all we really need to do is to figure out, whether it needs to be
unloaded, and we've put ourselves in a great position to do that.
Right?
I can go to load game code here.
I can use this last right time thing like this.
I can say, okay.
The file time is going to absorb the dll.
We're going to get that every time through the loop like this.
So this is the New Deal, alright, time that and basically I can just
do if the new deal, right time.
And I can't quite do a, not equals.
But essentially what I'm going to do is, do a not equals here where I
use whatever the the last right time was.
What was, you know, I'm going to move to go ahead and move that
struct.
I like to keep my structs out in the H file so I can see them easier.
So I'm going to go do it, go ahead and and check that that deal.
Alright, time.
So this is basically what I want to do.
I want to do a not.
Will's here.
But if I actually compile, you'll see that I can't do that.
And the reason for that is because file time is actually a compound
structure and you can't test for not equals in a compound structure.
Now.
I don't know if Microsoft actually in, has a built-in function, for
comparing file times.
It doesn't really matter because we could do it ourselves, but let's
take a look here compare file time.
Okay.
So they, they've written something already that compares.
The foul times for us, so we can just go ahead and use that, and it
works on Windows XP.
We're all good.
So all we really need to do is say that it there, this function will
Zero if they're equal, right?
So basically, whatever happens if compared file time like this, if we
just pass it, the two times that we want to compare that, assuming
that it is not equal to 0, then it's time to unload and reload the
code, right?
Because basically what we do every time as we get the new, whatever
the the current dll is, we look at that date.
And we see if that date on that date stamp on the file is different
than the one.
That was the last time we load it.
And if it was, then we go ahead and reload it, right.
That's all we really need to do.
We can make this a little more efficient in a second here and
actually, probably possibly eliminate a bug if we want to know if we
will or not.
Okay.
So now when we're running it in theory, it should be.
Checking course.
We don't know if our codes buggy.
It might be.
So let's go ahead and take a look.
We go in here again doing the same green, red switch that we did
before I go ahead and hit build.
and boom, instant
Is exactly what we wanted.
Right?
There we go.
So now we're at a position to really have that nice kind of smooth
feedback of every time we edit.
It's just bam, right?
So that's pretty good.
No, real problems there.
I think we've taken care of that to do pretty handily.
So now we basically have to just deal with a couple other random
issues before we can move onto to something slightly related, but
that's that's slightly different.
I know if lot of time in the Stream or not.
We have a couple
minutes left.
We've got what do we got?
We got 22 minutes left.
I don't know if that's going to be enough or not, but we'll see.
So hopefully you can see how that's working.
That's really pretty straightforward.
We didn't do anything spectacular.
Interesting there.
All we were doing was just getting that time.
And so one of the things we could do here is avoid doing multiple of
these get times because that way we won't miss a right to the dll was
the only thing I was thinking, excuse me.
So, basically, what I was thinking there is in that unload load game
code.
If I just take load game code and I have load game code, take the file
time, you know, take this this thing right here.
We already know that.
We have it anytime that we actually do that load.
So we could just pass it in here and set it, right?
We could just do that and not do it.
And so I don't know if maybe that's a little bit better.
I don't think it really is.
I think it just adds a little
Because we still could sneak a right in between so I think I think
it's probably fine.
So, basically, the problem that we have now that we have to address as
if you remember, what I did yesterday is I set this directory to be
the build directory.
And the reason I did that was because it needs to load the dll and the
dlls go in the build directory.
So what I wanted to do is I wanted to leave it to where we had it
before, where it's in the data directory, where our assets going to
be, where they need to actually load that stuff.
So,
So I, if I ran it now in theory, we shouldn't well, okay, that was
rather surprising.
Oh, no.
That that actually, is that actually is probably what you would
expect.
Okay.
So basically what happens here, is Windows knows to use the search
path for our executable to find the dll when we called load Library.
So load Library succeeds, but what I would assume happen is our file
date.
Check fails, because that can actually find the file.
I'm not actually sure if that's true.
But let's
Go ahead and see if it is.
So when 32 load game code.
Oops.
Introduce load game code, set a breakpoint and run in there.
So, here we are on load, gain cut.
I just want to see what happens here.
So basically, what happens what I was suggesting happens, is load
library, and we talked about this when we first started talking about
load Library, load Library, a there is a search path.
Complicit in, where it's going to look to find that dll.
And one of the places going to look to find a dll is it's going to
look in the same directory as our executable.
So when it looks in the same directory as our executable will,
Find the dll which means that load Library will succeed.
What I'm worried about.
However is that this will not right.
So when I come in here and take a look at it, it does Define first
file.
You can see it fails to find the file and the reason is because it's
looking only in the current directory, which is set to whatever we set
it to in here.
Let me, I want to actually close this.
Please that'll actually do that those please.
Okay, it's whatever we set it to in the solution Explorer.
So
so basically, this thing
Is what our current directory is.
And that's where all files will be looked for except dlls, which have
that magic search path.
So what we need to do is make it so that we can actually find the dll
ourselves.
No matter what our actual path is so long as the dll is in the same
directory as executable.
So what I want to be able to do is I want to be able to ask, where is
the executable?
Like, where is our exit actual executable, so that we can look for the
dll in that path specifically.
And furthermore, when we do this copy, we want to actually put the
Puppy in the same place as the dll was.
So if I go in here, right?
You can I think you should probably be able to see that it actually.
Well.
No, it didn't do that.
That's weird.
I thought it would have done the copy to the wrong place.
Oh, you know what?
The copy probably just flat-out failed because it probably couldn't
find it.
So actually that's probably what happened.
This copy probably failed as well because it could never find the
source tool.
Oh, I'm so yeah, so both of these things don't work unless we actually
have the path.
Proper, so that's basically what we're going to have to do.
We have to get that that path to be proper.
So what I'm going to do here is I'm basically just going to try and
ask Windows where the executable is.
And I think probably the easiest way to do that is to use get module
file name because I believe we can just just flat out, ask it where it
actually is.
So, let me just double check to see what the look.
The EX version of that is.
I'm not sure what the two different ones are.
So one takes a process and a module.
One takes a model.
So yeah, so we can just use this one.
So basically what this does is remember those module handles, I said,
but occasionally you actually need them.
We only used it like twice, I think.
Well, here's another time we can use it.
Basically.
The module handle allows us to identify some piece of executable code,
that was loaded and windows.
We know what ours is because it's passed in.
I don't know if you guys remember in win main.
We actually get this H instance, which is a module handle.
I know it's a little deceptive, but it actually is a module handle, do
not, that's kind of antiquated, weird Windows type stuff, but that
that is what we could use for the module handle.
And so basically, when we call this, what we
Be able to do is oh and you know what?
It looks like.
We wouldn't even have to pass it in because know if we just pass a
zero there, it'll just default to using our current executable.
So we don't even need to pass it.
It will just do what we want it to do if we don't pass anything at
all.
So we need to do is we need
Figure out how big that actually is going to be.
So if we take a look,
if the buffer is too small to hold the module name, the string is
truncated to n size characters and function if the function returns in
size and the function sets last are, so it looks like if we call this
function with a buffer size, that's too small.
It would tell us it would basically tell us how big we need the buffer
to be.
That's what it seems like it's saying.
So, I believe if we say here, get module handle with zero and I pass
it.
Let's say I have a buffer.
That we know is too small.
So I just pass it.
Well, I don't even have to pass it above her right eye.
Could pass it.
Well, so, I have a buffer here, I could pass it the buffer pointer and
just pass it zero as a size, right?
Like that d word, size of file name.
Let's take a look.
So oops.
What is the problem function does not take three arguments about get
module handle?
That's good.
It's get module clown.
There we go.
So if I actually call that, what I want to see is if this will just
tell us if we call it with no buffer essentially will it then return
us how big the buffer supposed to be so that we can just make a
buffer?
That's the right size, if that makes sense.
So let's go ahead and check in our wind main here when we come in.
Let's see what it actually does.
Because I want to see if that's, that's correct size of filename.
Nope, that is not useful to us at all.
So that is unhelpful.
That is very unhelpful.
Say, the very least because that does not allow us to actually tell
what something is now.
I suppose, I could do something like this and cheese out a little bit.
But what I would have liked to do is how to tell me how big it was so
that we could have done it.
William Lee.
Yeah, well, I don't know what to say there.
I would say, since this is debug code again, not something that we're
ever going to actually need to use in practice.
I would say this is probably fine.
But basically, what I had to use is, there's a, there's a Define in
Windows called Max path.
Right?
And if you take a look at what it is, it's basically a thing that
tells you what the maximum number of characters is for a path in
Windows for a file name, right?
And I don't know if they
They document that in here somewhere.
Oops, Max path.
Yeah, here you go.
So it's defined to be two hundred and sixty characters and so on and
the reason that I don't like it is because it's totally wrong, like
it's not actually the max path anymore.
Like you can see here.
There's extended pass in certain circumstances and all this other
stuff.
And so really like Max path is just is not right.
So, you know, I'm just going to say
A never use max path in code.
That is user-facing because it
Can be dangerous and lead to bad results right now.
It's not going to produce a buffer overrun or anything here, because
we're still passing the size of the buffer, but it would mean that
we'd get the wrong.
We get a truncated file path back.
Potentially, in the case, where the size was larger than what we
passed in.
So I feel like it's just a good idea to not use it.
If you can, I don't want to go through some kind of long process of
trying to coax Windows into giving me the name by calling this
repeatedly with
Sure, buffer sizes or anything like that.
So I think this is for debug code.
This is probably the safest thing to do is to just actually do it this
way, but it would have been nice.
If Windows API had just allowed us to say, how big is the buffer need
to be and then we will give you that size buffer.
But what can you do?
So there you go to do it that way and now I'll get back a buffer and
that buffer should have the name of our executable.
Now, the thing that I want to check is does it actually have the path
baked in there?
I don't know if it does, so I'm going to look to see if that gives us
back the path.
It does look like, gives us back the path.
You can see
It's got the full path in there.
So what I need to do now is I just need to truncate that path so that
I basically have a way to build new paths with a change in the
filename part.
So all I'm going to do here is I'm going to do a real simple sort of
truncation where I basically go, give me wherever the last / is in
this in this name.
So I'm just going to do a really stupid, absolutely stupid Searcher.
I'm going to say
This right, as long as okay.
So I know this is null terminated because Windows is supposed to
return me a null terminated string.
So I can start scanning the buffer.
I go through the buffer looking for an alternator is and I stopped
when I get to the alternator and then what I'm going to say is there's
a last /.
The last lash is by default going to be equal to whatever the the
actual last character that Windows said was there.
I'm going to actually say that that is where that actually is and
we'll pretend that that's the last laugh.
That's where we would start actually writing stuff.
I guess, technically, we want one past the last lash in the file name.
And so then what I'll do is I'll go through here.
And if the character that IC is equal to a backslash, then I will say
One path, / / equals scan plus 1, right?
So I'm just I just basically just, you know, kind of quick and dirty
really simple thing to truncate, the file name.
I don't know if Windows actually provides one of
Those but it might.
So anyway, we look at one pass last / here and take a look at where it
is.
You can see that.
Basically all I did was I wrote something that just starts here.
It scans through and it looks to see whether it sounds the last /
where it found the last lash and it gives me a pointer right to there.
So if I wanted to just keep the path part, I now know I can overwrite
that part with the, you know, with the new thing.
All right, if you want to see that in action, we can step into it just
so you can see if you've never
And stuff like that before.
It's really simple.
Basically, what I did is this gives me back a length.
So I started off by saying, well, if there's no slashes.
I'm just going to assume that.
It's basically, the null Terminator is where the last lashes.
Although now that I think about it, that would be wrong.
That's not quite right.
Really the one if for this purpose is if there was no slashes than
there is no path is just a file name.
So I guess we would just be just be the beginning of the buffer,
right?
We'd overwrite the whole thing.
So, yeah, because there is no path.
So that's that's basically it.
So that's actually that's actually
more correct for our purposes.
So we go in here, we start off and we say that one pass last laugh is
just the beginning of the buffer and we've got scan and scan is
pointing to at the outset, the beginning of the buffer we go through
and we just go through each character.
Literally you can see em SVC is incredibly long, lag time for updating
its watch window, which has gotten worse with every version.
Speaking of things to get worse and msec with every version.
It used to be instantaneous when you hit F10, now, it takes like a
second to update the watch window.
Yes, I just like to remind you ladies and gentlemen, vet this machine,
which has this many virtual processors, at least in it.
This many cores.
I should say, is taking and, you know, Monster amount of memory, the
the people who wrote Visual Studio, could not figure out how to update
this watch window in any faster time than that.
Okay.
So, basically, what I want to do here is, like I said, I'm just going
through here.
And any time I get, a /i update one pass / / to point to that.
At location, so you can see it updated here, because it hit a / the
scanners hit a /.
So it updated it.
So, now we write through again.
We're gonna be scanning through.
You can see I'm eating characters using characters eating characters.
I get to a slash and now it's time to update one pass /.
/ 2.2.
Just after that.
There it is.
And that's the last time it will update because it won't hit any more
slashes.
So it eats the rest of the string when we finish, we are pointing to
exactly what we wanted.
So now, we know that the path part of our string is between buffer and
one pass last stress.
So if you wanted to build new ones we could which means, you know, I
should I should put this.
XZ, filename shouldn't be called, buffer.
Buffer is not a particularly good name for something certainly.
So there we go.
That's a little bit cleaner for that.
So we get the exif file name and now we have that dll name that
Source, dll name.
So what we can do now is we can actually start to play with this a
little bit and say, okay.
Well if we want to we can use Windows to construct new strings for us.
That actually happy.
So we can say WS printf which again you seem to use before which is
just the window.
As call for doing sort of formatted.
I 0, I can go ahead and say, all right.
What I'd like to do is print that path that we had, and then I'd like
to print handmade dot DL.
I like just append and made that deal to it.
And so, that's pretty straightforward.
Right?
All I have to do now is create something.
That's got the actual eggs e founding
You know what?
Maybe I should write this.
I mean, this is handmade hero.
Maybe I should write it ourselves.
Should we write the stream processing code ourselves?
Let's write the string Crossing code ourselves.
It doesn't look like I'm going to get to the other thing.
We were going to get to tonight.
Anyway, so we might as well write the string processing code
ourselves.
So let's do a concatenation function, basically, right?
Let's just do something that concatenate these two strings together.
So I'm going to do something that's like concatenate or or you know,
cat strings or something like this, right?
And so it's going to take Source a
I'm Source a count.
That's what I want to do.
And then a source, be count and a source B, and then a desk count and
a dest, right?
And I'm basically it's going to write something that does the string
can cat- myself, because why not?
And so then what I'm going to do is I'm going to call Cat strings to
produce the new string.
So let's say I've got something I want to do that Source, dll name,
and then I want to do that temp DL name, those two things, right?
I want both of those to be there.
So if I want to produce those strings, again, this is like the this is
the grossest way you could possibly do string processing.
If you were doing a lot of string processing, you would.
Absolutely not do this way.
You'd actually write a little string library for your use and then you
would kind of be in something, a little more convenient, you know,
like you would imagine seeing in python or something like that, but
for now since we really this is the only processing we have to do.
I'm just going to write it this way and not go right?
A huge, big library, or something to do with it.
But basically what I'm going to do here is I want to basically say,
all right.
So one past lash / - XE file name, gives me how long that that path
is, right.
And then I want to copy XE founding from there.
And then I want to also do that handmade.
So I've got this handmade dll file name, right?
Or I should say game code, dll.
Um, I don't know what you want to call it.
Just the file part of that.
So maybe maybe Source URL, full path and or I should say, let's say
game code.
Dll full path and game code.
Dll file name, we could do it like that, like that.
Basically, this will equal just the handmade dll part, right?
And similarly.
I can do a thing where, basically, the temp, dll gets the same one.
So there's the temp and
Milk should be called.
I don't know.
So called a source game code and temp.
There we go.
Something like that.
That should be relatively clear.
Right?
I feel like it should be.
So, anyway, and this was I guess, I think this is called underscore
temp.
I don't actually know what we called it, but doesn't matter.
So we do the cat strings here.
Then we want to do the size of this guy and source code, dll.
File name like that.
And then we want to put it in here.
So just past that.
And there we go.
This that's really all we need to do.
I think nothing particularly odd there.
So we want to do source with temp, their replace that and I think
that's the correct calls this double check.
What did I do wrong there?
Argument conversion from N64 to n 0.
So the size of its leader actually 64-bit since this is
Nicly a 64-bit OS.
We don't really need them too because we're never going to have 64-bit
wide strings.
Okay.
So then for win32 load game code, we are now going to pass both of
those things to it, game code.
We need to pass both the The Source deal name and the temp name.
So those go out of their Source kilo name and temp.
Dll name that?
And that should be about it.
Oh, of course, these were not named that anymore.
I made the super long crazy explanatory names for them.
So we got the full path here.
Full path.
And then we've got the full path here and there we go.
So, there we go.
And right in the
This guy has to also ask for that.
So I think that's it.
Just a couple more places load game code needs to take both of these
again 10.
So, there we go.
So now all I need to do is actually write this function because as you
can see, it doesn't actually do anything quite yet.
So that's no good.
So basically, all we have to do is we just have to copy these in
there.
So I'm going to do probably the worst possible implementation of this
because we don't care how fast it is.
I'm just going to go ahead and write the first thing that comes to
mind.
Actually, what we need to do is, we need to do a loop over Source, a
count and copied into discount.
Right?
So I need to do something that basically does tubing.
The basically does, you know, 4nt a index or should just say index,
equals Source, a count, right?
Zero index less than Swiss account index.
I'm do a loop over that guy.
And while we're in there we do desk plus equals.
I guess I should say well we'll do that in a second.
Sorry desk equals Source a plus plus this.
So we just basically move dust along copying and Source a and then we
need to copy and Source be like this Source be.
There we go.
Nothing particularly useful there.
We just do that.
And then,
That is the end of it.
But the at the very end we have to do something that looks like that
to insert the null Terminator, right?
Because all strings in C and in a null Terminator.
So we have to insert that null there.
And so that should be basically it.
Now, the question is, of course whether the null Terminator already
exists in these, when we get the size of, I think it does.
So technically this guy,
This this guy right here has to be a minus 1 because we don't want to
copy the null Terminator.
We could we, you know, if we wanted to copy meal Terminator, we would
but we got to get rid of that.
So we can just copy not the null Terminator part of these so that they
will can cat together and I guess, technically, we could have if you
wanted to be kind of weird and Sly, I actually could do this.
I don't think this is a particularly good idea, but you could just let
it copy, the null Terminator out of this one.
So that that would end it.
It's a
So creepy and I don't think that's particularly good idea.
So I'm going to say let's just not copy null Terminator.
No wouldn't matter.
We could add we'd end up a tune all Terminators and that'd be fine.
So the only thing this doesn't do now right now is doesn't actually
check for overflow in desk.
But I think it's actually borrowing a stupid mistakes, which usually
one does make in these particular circumstances.
Let's take a look here.
Let's run in there real quick.
So inside our first call here.
We've got Source a and we've got Source be.
There we go Source.
A
Out Source, be count, looks fine to me.
And then we've got our discount and are dest, looks fine.
So we start copying in.
There we go through these two copies, or say, go through these Copy
Source, be do the null termination and out become we then have our
temp game, code DOL, full path.
Oops, we didn't do that one yet Source, its source game code, dll,
full path.
And Hey, look, it's the path that we wanted.
We do the same thing again, and it is the temp game code.
Dll full path as well.
And that is correct.
So now in theory this actually will work.
I think, let's take a look now and see if it did the right thing.
So we are running it in the original location.
And now if I go into the build directory, let's take a look and see if
it actually did it.
So, it did create produce the handmade temp or at least we think it
did.
Let's see if that's the right time 859.
Yes, that is the right time.
And so now I should be able to do the stuff that we were doing before
I go in here and I change us back to our green like this.
Do the build and let's see.
And it is great again.
So I think we are totally good to go now.
Not not.
Really particularly hard, but I got to drop it to do in here because
we ran out of time before we did dest bounds checking.
And again, we don't need to check the bounds because this is debug
code, but we might as well implemented properly.
Alright, that is the end of that.
Now I have a new system for doing questions today that I hope will
work.
I don't know if it will work properly or not.
I just I just I'm hoping
Will work properly.
Let me see here.
I got to get something.
I have to just for a second quickly.
Switch over to this machine because I forgot to set it up before I
actually came on the stream here.
Alright, so let's go and set this up.
What I tried to make something.
I was having trouble, keeping track of questions.
So I tried to make something that would be a little bit easier for
that.
Okay.
So you saw what we did.
All we were doing today.
Is basically cleaning up our code from yesterday to make it so that
it's instantaneous now and that it works in no matter what directory,
we start our game in, we accomplished both of those.
There's still one more thing I want to do for doing this sort of Live
code editing thing, but we are in really good shape.
Now, I'm pretty actually excited about this because this is going to
be probably one of the first times I've ever had this working on a
game as I was developing before the last time I did a game was before
I had really thought to do this.
For some reason, it was a long time ago was like in 2005.
So it's like 10 years ago.
And since then I hadn't really ever thought to do it.
And so in a game where you're tweaking lot of stuff, I think this is
going to be pretty awesome.
It seems to be working pretty well, but there's a couple of things
that I want to do to it.
That we can do that, we'll do tomorrow, but I think we're in pretty
good shape.
Now, everything seems to be working relatively.
Well, so let's go ahead and go to the questions.
Please put Senior ettore in the question somewhere, so I can see it.
And please keep the questions, two things that happened on to
Add a stream or in previous streams.
Nothing about future streams because we will get there when we get
there.
So let's take a look here.
Let's take a look.
Okay, so case basically what I've learned is that my question thing is
still not quite right.
I forgot to do one part of it.
Terrible.
All right, well,
Next time tomorrow.
I will remember the thing.
I forgot to write in my question thing.
You didn't see it.
But there is a shame Al going on on my other computer.
Ladies and gentlemen, that is unfortunate.
All right, questions.
Let's see.
How do you manage to time your coding so perfectly?
I don't I just stop coding.
When we run out of time at whatever the thing.
We're on.
We've always got more things.
We could do.
You mentioned yesterday.
You have something you want to address from previous day's but you
never did.
Yes.
I've got a notebook full of things when we're done.
I want to do this because it was fun.
We got some other to dues to finish up when we are done with this.
So after tomorrow, we'll go back and do some of the things that are on
the notebook.
Just clean up stuff, you know, Thursday and Friday will basically just
be cleaning up stuff in preparation for Monday of next week.
I'm officially calling it done on the win32 platform layer.
I just, you know, like I said, what?
I just want to do something fun instead of moving right on to the game
code and and pretending when 32 never existed which will be fun.
But I wanted to do some fun stuff with win32 first so that people
didn't think it was all bad.
It is annoying to program platform layers.
It's true.
Once you do it you don't do it again, right?
You do it once and you kind of like have it and you use it, but
I want to show you that there are some cool things you can do with it.
Let's see here.
Will this capability be in the shipping game?
Or will it only be for debugging?
Well, we'll leave it in the shipping game.
Probably, as an option like we can leave it as like a - switch what
you could say, you know, go ahead and do it, but I don't know.
There's really no point in leaving it in the in the in the shipping
game because in order to use it you have to be able to build from the
source code and if you're building from the source code, then you
could just turn it on yourself in the bill that you use.
So we really don't need to ship the commercial.
Executable doesn't need to be built with it on because if you were
going
Play with it.
You would already be building your own dll so I don't know.
I don't think we need to ship it in the executable will leave it in
the source code though.
So anyone who starts playing around with the source code can do it?
Does the reload of the dll?
Reset the game entirely?
No, it doesn't reset it at all.
In fact, you saw you can see that.
It's already true.
Right?
I mean watch this thing right?
Watch it run.
You can see that it's got progress, right?
It's going in there.
And when we do this, when we rebuild, it does not miss a beat, right?
It's oops.
I got it.
Yes.
It does not miss a beat.
It stays exactly where it was.
There's no reset whatsoever.
Right?
So, the game,
Get reset in any way.
It's totally fine.
I can, if I was to do something like this, so, change the state.
Like that's are really all our game state that we have right now.
You'll notice when I, when I do that, it's exactly where it was.
So there's no resetting whatsoever.
We're totally live and it just works, right?
Let's see how much time have you spent planning this game prior to,
even starting day, one planning the game, not a whole lot.
I mean, I kind of thought through what I wanted to do for the game
that I thought would be a game that would allow us to focus on
learning to program games.
Well, so I picked a game that would have a lot of complexity in the
game code.
And that was the primary part of the planning that I did.
I did no planning for the code and I will never do anything.
Waiting for the code.
The most I will do is if I think something takes a long time like
those compiler switches and stuff.
When I did the day of compiler switches.
I knew that it would just be me looking at MSD and the entire time.
Sometimes I will go look at my old code and write down what the
compiler switches are.
Just so I don't have to spend as much time doing msdn, but I try very
hard to basically never do any planning for the stream.
So it's exactly as if
Sat down to program that day and had to figure this stuff out, right
then.
So I try not to do pre pro work because I feel like if I did pre pro
work, it wouldn't show you the real way.
I have to write the code.
It would show you a rehearsed fake way and I don't want this dream to
be that.
I want the stream to always be me doing it.
Straight out of my head without having the benefit of the pre pre warm
up.
Let's see.
So are you building the game into wait?
Are you building the gaming to sort of sections?
One being core, C++ section, and the other being a platform serves
section.
Yes, if you've been following along, you've seen us do that.
Basically, we're just about done with the platform section.
That's for win32.
As far as prototyping is concerned.
We basically finish that.
And so next week, we're moving on to the game core, which will still
touch the win32 layer.
Occasionally, if we want to change stuff that it does, like we're
like, oh we really want it to have passed this blonde.
It doesn't pass this.
We'll go change it, but we won't be really doing any more serious.
Win32 work.
Will always be doing game work from then on.
Since dlls aren't on OS X Linux.
How would we handle these in those environments?
They are actually, they're not called dlls, but both Linux and Mac OS,
X, have Dynamic libraries.
All major operating systems have Dynamic link libraries, so you can
just do it.
Beep.
Oh, did you list your qualifications in a previous stream?
If not, what are they?
I do not know what qualifications are as far as I know qualifications
for programming.
Is that you program?
Well,
And I think by watching the stream, you can tell whether I can or
can't in your opinion.
So, I don't know if there's any qualifications, certainly, there's a
lot of people who have done a lot of programming and are still bad at
it.
And there's people who haven't done a lot of programming in are good
at it.
So, I'm not sure what qualifications means as far as this is
concerned.
Why don't you use Dynamic buffer?
Allocation?
I'm not sure what that means.
We do Dynamic buffer allocation.
We have Dynamic buffer, allocation.
Basically in oops, that was not what I intended to do right there.
Basically if we go back to here and I do virtual a lock it's in win32
handmade so you can see here is where we allocate our our memory.
So that this is this asks for memory.
So we have to allocate
Patients currently in our code actually got more than that because we
do the bitmap as well and this read entire file.
So there's a couple places in the code where we dude.
Use dynamic allocations.
You said you were going to show us how to make a game.
Well, what are your qualifications for saying that you are making a
good game?
Code wise?
Well, I mean, I guess what I should say is, I do not know of any
absolute qualities of how to make how to certify that a game was
coded.
Well, so I can only give you what I consider to be game code that is
architected.
Cleanly, hopefully, as we go, you will.
See that there is good stuff.
Like we've already kind of done some things that I would say
illustrate that even though, we haven't even started the game
architecture yet.
You can also see that there's been good decisions that are made and
we'll see some more of that tomorrow actually, but for example, how
easy it was to do the dynamic code loading, a lot of that was because
I already did the game architecture correctly.
Like I showed you how to make the game architecture, just in the place
where interfaces the platform layer to be correct and in so doing.
Oh, doing it was trivial for us to make the code low.
Dynamically.
We didn't have to do a lot of crazy stuff to connect it up and back
and because we did the memory properly unloading and loading it just
works there as well.
So we're going to see tomorrow.
There's a bunch of other decisions.
I baked in here that I'm going to talk about because I basically can't
talk about decisions that I make until I show you why they're
important.
So I talked about decisions at the time when I can actually show you
the reasons why they were good.
And so hopefully it's very self evident as
Go why a lot of these decisions are important and why they're correct.
But if they're not obvious to you, you can always feel to ask.
You can always feel free to ask questions and I will try to explain
why it was a proper decision to make or why it was at least a good
decision.
Some decisions are not about right or wrong there about whether or not
you're prioritizing certain things.
And so I'll always try to be very clear to you about whether something
was a decision.
That's a six of one half-dozen of the other or whether
it was a decision.
That was like, you really should do it this way because we do it the
other way.
It's going to be bad.
Could you explain your method of compressed programming somewhere in
writing on the Forum?
Maybe, Yes, actually, I could so looks like someone already posted the
link.
So there's an entire blog post about that.
If you go to Mali rocket.com /, KC, my blog is on here and there's
this long series of working on the witness articles where I talk about
all the stuff that I was working on on the witness.
You know, like this one was the first one was a pretty popular one
where I talk about bullet, try doing some stuff to test the the
movement code.
I've got more of those articles that are men coming out.
Probably hopefully, early next year that are talking about
Final Collision system that I did on the witness, which I think is
actually pretty cool, but it's very odd.
Anyway, on here.
I believe there's a series that starts.
I think it's on 11.
Yeah.
So basically this this work on the witness part 11 from here on is all
about that.
That programming style that semantic impression programming style
where you kind of go through and you can see there's a bunch of
articles on it.
They go all the way through 15.
Sixteen Seventeen eighteen and even post a source code to it.
So yeah, you can go through those if you want to read about that style
of programming, so that's good.
When find first file is called, does Windows actually read anything
from the disk or is file system.
Meta stuff.
Kept in.
Ram.
Usually it's kept in Ram.
So it shouldn't have to actually hit the disc to answer that.
Maybe the first time it does like on Startup if that was cold, but it
should be after that.
It's cash, so it should be fine and it shouldn't cost anything.
One way to abuse.
The fact the game code is in a different dll is to do a Doom 3 star
release, where the dll part is open for modders and modding tools.
Well just to point out though.
This game comes with a full source code.
So modding isn't really a concern that we have because basically
people will be able to shift their own executables.
Right?
So basically you'll be able to just like, here's a new executable
will.
I'll try to do something when we actually ship the game.
But it basically says the game and its content are
Rated but anyone who buys the game, has the right to send executables
or post executables for the game, just the executable or something
like that.
So that people can trade their own executables, if they want to.
So, we'll figure something out.
I don't know.
What will, how will do it, but we'll figure something out.
So that basically the same sort of stuff is possible with the modding.
Let's see, one common theme in these videos is that you shouldn't
clean up OS objects or memory on shutdown, but OS objects will
presumably need to be cleaned up on dll reload, correct?
No, so basically our dll doesn't talk to the operating system.
And that's a crucial thing to understand.
The dll is our game code.
So it does not have the ability to nor will we ever give it the
ability?
T to handle operating system objects, so there will be no clean up on
on clothes and reload.
If that makes sense.
Not seeing any other questions.
Are there.
Any questions that I missed?
I don't things think.
So.
I wish you had a subscriber button.
This is awesome.
Are we?
In Q&A time right now?
We're still coding.
We are in Q&A time.
I do have.
So I talked to Twitch about being coming a partner.
And unfortunately, I can't sign the contract that they have.
Because their contract says that content has to be exclusive to Twitch
for 24 hours.
And I upload the videos to YouTube immediately.
So people can follow along with them.
So I couldn't sign the partner contract, just because of the weight,
which does things.
So I couldn't, I can't put a subscriber button.
So I apologize for people who want us to Cairo and I can't do that.
But I did.
There is, if you go to handmade here to, or if you just want to
contribute to the series.
There is a patreon link a lot of PPL at were asking for this.
If you go there, there's a way that you can sign up to just, you know,
pledge something for every month that I output the video series.
So if you're looking for a way to support the series, you still can do
it to subscribe to the series.
Basically you still can do it.
But I'm sorry.
I apologize to people who want the subscription button.
I can't do that because
Basically, I want the videos, the videos have to be in a permanent
location.
So they can't just exist on Twitch because twitch clears them after 60
days or something like that.
So I have to have a permanent location where people can go to get the
videos.
And so that the the episode guide which works off of YouTube can and
often from a location can be there and I don't want to delay posting
the YouTube for a day because there's a lot of people who work on it
like within just a couple hours of being posted.
So I just
has made the Judgment call that I felt like, you know, I mean, it's
not I don't I don't think to which generates a lot of revenue for a
stream like this one could or anything anyway, so I felt like it was
just like it didn't really matter that much and I'd rather give people
the files as soon as possible that just seemed like a senior decision.
So again, I apologize people who wanted to subscribe button.
I just I felt like it was easier to just do it this way and have a
separate place where you could donate.
So that's what that's what ended up happening.
Let's see.
Firefly says, are we going to see the process of Designing the game to
as in the game concept rather than the code?
No, and the reason for that is not because I don't want to show it but
it's actually just because I am not really a game designer.
So the process of Designing the game, I don't feel like
I don't want to present the game designing part of this series as
being an educational thing because I don't really want people to learn
their game design skills from me.
I think you want to learn your game design skills from like John, or
someone else who's like, a really great game designer, who's designed,
a lot of great games.
I am specifically selecting the game design for this game to be about
what we can do.
That creates a lot of code complexity.
And so I want the game to be driven by how do we add that complexity
in that forces us to do good work in the code.
And that is really the direction that we're going with that because
that's something that I feel qualified to do.
Whereas, if this game, if this stream were about designing a game, I
feel like you would want someone.
I mean, I have 30 years of experience programming.
I have hardly any experience.
Shining games, right?
So I feel like it would just be a bad idea to go.
The point of this stream is to design a great game and let's focus on
designing the game because I just don't feel like I have the kind of
experience necessary to do that.
I may look into it or I may be able to design a good game here, just
because I have a lot of experience with games.
And the game design is not crazy.
Far out there.
It's not like we're designing, some new kind of genre or whatever.
So,
The game design may go well and I hope it goes well, but even if it
does, I'm able to explain code coherently, I think because I have so
much experience.
I wouldn't be able to explain design in that same way because I'm not
a great game designer.
I don't have that background.
And so a lot of what I would say might be wrong, like even if the game
design is good.
I may not explain it in a way that allows you to do good game design,
right?
And so, I really feel like this.
I'm used to not be about that.
The scream is strictly about programming and hopefully someday, maybe
maybe if this series proves to be popular, which it has been so far,
you know, maybe someday there can be another type of stream.
That's by somebody else, who is a great game designer who will do the
equivalent of handmade hero.
But for design, right?
I can only hope that that's true.
I think I would learn a lot from that stream.
And so so I don't know.
So yeah, so all I can say is we aren't for this game.
I'm intentionally picking something that is not like a genre,
redefining kind of game design so that it can be relatively
straightforward in its core.
And then I'm just driving the design off of trying to make the world
and the items in the world and the monsters in the world and how you
interact with them very complicated, in terms of the possibilities of
what can happen.
That we will have to really do a good job, improving, and improving
our game, core to support all that.
So that is where the game design comes from.
Can you give some examples of some types of code changes to the game?
Dll?
That won't work?
Well with hot reloading.
Yes.
So changes to the code will always work.
Changes to the data layout will not.
So basically if we change a struct to reorder the parameters, it won't
work anymore.
Right?
Because the memory is static.
We load new code.
It's looking for the members of the struct in a new play, in different
places and it will fail because we'll get totally garbage.
There are things we can do that will improve that ability to make it
so that it could work across those changes in certain circumstances
depending on how much of a change you make.
But I don't know that we care about that.
So I may not.
I may not do those things.
I don't know how much we will care.
Will have to drive that decision based on what we see happening.
If it turns out that it proves to be a problem in a lot of times, we
would like to be able to have more flexibility there.
We can go.
It's actually a fairly heavy weight thing that has to happen in order
to make that work.
Okay.
So basically we could we could think about that and we could then at
that point say, all right, we're going to spend a month of time
because that's probably how long it would take given that I only get
an hour a night and I have to explain everything.
Probably take a while.
It's probably a week's worth of work.
Normally let's say
So it would take a long time for me to do that on stream.
So I'd rather not do it if we don't have to.
But if it turns out that that something that really looks like it
needs to happen and then it can happen.
Let's see.
Let's see what else we got on here.
Can I scroll back?
I can't scroll back.
Don't got no, don't got no mouse.
I got to plug in a mouse to this laptop so I can scroll back.
Any other questions.
Do we have any other questions?
We have about five minutes left for Q&A.
Do you have any opinion on Louis such as using it for configuration or
more comprehensive scripting?
So I guess what I would say is, as I talked about last night, I don't
understand what the value added of Lua is you can dine in a
dynamically load, C and C is way more powerful than Lua and it has
that you can use the same debugger integrated.
All together II, don't know why anyone uses Lua.
I mean, I'm not trying to say that.
It's a bad idea to use Lua.
I'm just saying I don't understand this issue.
In the decision seems very
Odd to me because I don't understand what you perceive to be getting
by using glue.
It seems like all you did was make the language that you write your
game code in be worse than it was before.
It's like it's like a downgrade switching to Lua.
So, yeah, so I don't want a flat out, say, don't use Lua because I
don't know, maybe there's something that people are getting from it
that they like, but from my perspective, hot loading, C is superior to
Lou in all possible ways.
And if, for some reason, you thought there was something you needed a
loo.
I would say really, think about whether that's true.
And whether you can really say, for sure that it's true because like I
said, even if you wanted to make it so that you were, you could hop
load, see across data layout changes, you can do that.
And if this were a game where I was programming at full speed 40 hours
a week, I just do them.
They take a, like I said a couple, didn't you?
Maybe a week to do, it's not a big deal and then you're just done.
Do you think this method of hot reloading can be useful for developing
other types of software, besides a game?
Like, for example, a mobile app or business system?
Well.
May I don't know I don't just develop mobile apps or Business Systems.
It depends.
Basically, it depends on how long it takes you to get from starting
the app to the thing you want to tweak.
That's what this really does, is it cuts down that iteration time?
Because now you can just edit the code live.
If if you're spending a lot of time like shutting down, restarting the
app at every time you make a code change, then yes, this could help
you if you're not then it's just it doesn't really do anything for
you.
So, I don't know.
It's
Case-by-case basis.
You have to look and see if you thought that was true.
Do you think there's a case for dsls in some cases instead of using C
for the code?
Like for a I not really because I think there's domain-specific
languages.
Are only useful, if they're more powerful and expressive than C.
And so what I would say is why don't you just make your CB that
expressive, like, right?
The stuff that you're doing and see if he may be that expressive.
Now.
There are a bunch of things that I wish see would improve on, right?
There's tons of things I would do.
That would improve.
See and John blow right now is working on his new version.
That doesn't like he's doing that, right?
And so what I would say is if you were going to do a domain specific
language for your AI system,
Why think about it that way?
Think about what's wrong with see that?
You don't think you can write your AI in it and just improve see to
have those things, right?
Because all that time, that you spend just make a c preprocessor that
output C because then now you can use it for everything.
Like, why don't you want that power everywhere?
And so I don't think domain-specific languages are typically very
good.
I think you should just focus on.
What are the things you can't do in your language?
And if you're going to spend time making a new language, just make
that be the thing you actually program in, you know.
Panic says, one benefit of Lou is that you don't have to recompile it
all but neither do we really like I mean, I hit all M.
And it changes.
So it's basically like I could just bind the save key to also
recompile and we wouldn't know the difference between that, right.
I'm guess.
I'm people whose compile times are really huge.
Then that's true, but
Will the game engine?
Be mostly generic or tailored for this game?
Well, tailored for this game, obviously.
Yeah, it will be it'll support all the things that you need to support
for this game.
It's not going to be like trying to be like Unity or something.
That's like kind of an everything engine.
Let's see.
Any more on topic questions?
I don't think there are any more on topic questions, so I might switch
to off topic questions.
So, people are asking about larabee and Xenon, fee or Phi.
I don't know how you pronounce that.
So they're the same thing.
Obviously, Larrabee project is what turned into the Xenon fee, or Phi.
However, you want to say that.
So basically, I can't, I don't think I'm really allowed to talk too
much about that project because I was on that project so I probably
shouldn't talk about larabee and Xenon feet.
All I will say is I would have preferred it.
If that is the way graphics cards had gone permanently.
I would have preferred it.
If graphics cards were just programmable CPUs, that just had a lot of
in order cores on them.
So,
do I recommend C over C?
Plus plus?
No, I recommend using a few features of C++.
Basically.
I don't like most of the features of C++.
But there are a couple that I like, like, operator overloading and
function overloading.
So I feel like it's worth it usually to use C++ and just use it
lightly because basically, when I you know, a lot of times I will or
other people who are
It specifically kind of program in the way that I people who
programming the same style that I do often are disparaging a C++.
What were, what were disparaging of when we say C++ is bad, is really
that the way people use it is bad.
And the way people use it as bad and the language committee, the
changes that they make to see the way that they've made.
Improvements to the language.
Have been poorly thought-out and poorly executed.
Right?
So we're not trying to say that c is better than C++ because C is
really, mostly a subset of C plus plus, so it's usually better to use
C++ and then just not use a lot of its poorly thought-out features
just ignore them because you can still use the ones that do work.
Right?
And so usually the reason that we're so disparaging of C++ is because
we wish that the people who designs of us had had a clue because if
If people had had a clue, we would have had 30 years of great
modifications to C and C would be an amazing language today.
Instead.
What we got is mostly very poorly thought-out, oftentimes, almost
unusable a bad feature additions.
And as a result, most C++ programs are a mess because people try to
use those features in the way.
They
Intended, and they end up with code that's worse that if they've never
used that, they had never used the features at all.
What's worse is most people don't realize.
This is true.
They think that they've made progress but really their code compiles
slower.
Run slower is harder to read, has more bugs, is more lines of code.
Like everything is worse about it than if they just done the
equivalent without the C C++ feature.
And so, that's really that we're all the anger.
And the vitriol comes from.
I think I could speaking for myself.
I don't know if I can speak for other people.
Who don't like, see both laugh, that's really where it comes from.
Is this the mist potential?
We basically had a lot of people who didn't know how to do.
Good language design, iterating on.
See that's what produced C++ instead.
We had had great language designers who had done C++ instead of C.
We would have had an amazing language today.
And again, that's the thing that John Blow is trying to rectify right
now.
I highly recommend watching his stream naysayer 88.
He is like the one person right now who's actually working on trying
to build a better see
And I really hope that he succeeds because we could really use it.
And I think already, he's already his language is better than C++ has
even though C++ had 30 years of improvements.
So, yeah, I'm pretty hopeful.
Let's see.
As a beginning programmer, is Unity a good?
Start to develop some basic games.
I don't know.
I've never used Unity.
Probably.
I mean if you just want to make games and you don't care about
programming then like yeah, you know, maybe just Unity or unreal for
or one of those other game maker.
There's a lot of tools out there that you can use to just play around
with making a game.
If you care about programming and learning to program, I don't know
how useful those tools are because they opted to skate the programming
and what actually happens to a large extent and they may not be so
good for that.
So depends on what your goals are as what I would say.
You complain a lot about the windows API but clearly other platforms
aren't any better.
That is true.
I do not think other platforms are better.
What would your ideal, general purpose platform look like that's too
big of a topic and there's just so much to discuss there.
Sorry, it's a good question.
I just, it's too big.
We're there any personal products that you had done prior to
graduating high school college that came in handy, when looking for a
job.
How did you come to work at rad?
You can actually all of that is on.
If you go to the video archive, and you want to know the answer that
question.
If you go to the video archive on videos, all the way back.
Well, actually, you know, what?
Don't do that.
Don't do what I just said, instead click on news and forums.
I should probably update that video archive.
The go to episode guide, and on episode guide, click on this.
I think it's introducion Windows day 5 because this is the thing with
that.
Has the time jumps in it.
I'm pretty sure it was in here.
Was it in here?
Oh, no, you know, what was in the Q&A?
So the Q&A
Day 5, I think.
Is that it?
Let's see if it's down here.
Yeah.
Okay.
So if you scroll down here, you can see that.
They've actually the awesome people who do the handmade here episode
guide.
You can, you can go, which, by the way, if you go to this, thanks
page.
You can read a bunch of the people responsible for all this awesome
stuff.
Anyway, if you go on here, you can jump to basically, what's your life
story.
How did you learn programming?
And there's just honestly, it's like seriously a 30-minute thing.
That just tells you
Everything about that.
So, if you want to see that, it's recorded on there.
And it basically says what happened to me.
Do you think games can make use of concurrency?
And parallelism were than it is right now?
Well, yes and no, I mean a lot of game engines.
Now are getting pretty parallel.
So I don't know.
It depends on which it, depends on what specific game, you mean,
right?
Like some games, don't use it at all and some games, use it to a large
extent.
So, you know, six of one half dozen of the other.
Where can I find the song used in the YouTube trailer?
Well, I don't know if you can.
Basically it's a, it's a piece of music.
I licensed music for the game, and it's a piece of music that comes
with the license library that I did.
And so, I don't know.
I don't think, I don't know if you can get the song as just a song
that you buy.
I don't think it's like on iTunes or anything.
So, I'm sorry.
I don't know that.
There's anything you can do there.
Can you show how to set key bindings in emacs?
Sure, if you go in, well, I'm going to load mine.
But wherever yours is mines in the Miss directory.
Here.
If you go in there, there's basically like a bunch of lines.
You can see that look like this Define key, global map thing and
basically what you do is you put the key binding in here and then the
function you want to call in here and wacky that like back / e, just
means alt.
So if you want to do all you put that you can also see like if you
If you scan through here, you can see the syntax and other places like
backslash uppercase C is like for the for the control and for control
key and stuff.
There's also, this is an alternate syntax where you do bracket C Dash
a thing.
I don't know.
I don't, I don't know emacs.
That's but also, this is just like what worked for me to be able to
bind the file, you know, I don't even know if that's a good way to do
it and you can see, I have some keys Bound in C++ mode and other Keys
Bound in the global mode.
So, you can set them what you put in here for global map or C++ map is
just telling you like.
Oh, this is when that keyboard key binding Works, whether it's always
or just in C++.
What do I think of Blizzard is a game development company?
I've no idea.
I've never worked for blizzard.
Never work for blizzard.
Never even visited the offices.
I know some people who work.
But they work their long time ago.
Like Pat, Wyatt's a friend of mine?
Great guy started.
Arenanet same with Jeff strain.
I know those guys, they're great guys.
If the rest of blizzards like them, that's probably great.
I don't know.
Yeah, they went on to do like arenanet and then they did Undead Labs,
which is also here in Seattle, or we Nets across the water in
Bellevue, but basically, those guys are great and they're really good
at what they do.
And so I don't
Know if the rest of blizzards like them or you know, they were the
good people at blizzard and they left and now it's not I don't know.
But my only experience really with blizzard people was was knowing
them from way back when and and they're awesome people.
So, I don't know.
Yeah, if the rest of Brothers like them and it'd be awesome.
If it's not, then I don't know.
Perhaps this question is better suited for the forum's.
What guidance can you provide for newbie game?
Developers looking to find artists for their game projects.
Make money first.
As far as I know, like finding good artists involves paying for them.
I if you happen to look out in your friends, with someone who's a
really good artist and you want to go work on a game together.
That's great.
But if you want good, if you just want to like work with a good artist
you need to pay them.
So
You've got to have money, get funding is the really the way to do it.
And if not, then you're going to, you're going to have to befriend
someone for.
So It's Tricky.
You mentioned on stream, meta programming in c.
What does that look like been dying to know?
Well, this is this is since we're in off-topic land.
I mean, I can, it's really simple all meta.
Programming.
In c means is that you write a c program that right to see program.
So, you know, if you wanted to do it, you know, you open up
metaprogramming dot CPP, right?
And you have something that looks you know like this or whatever.
And you just output C code, you're like, hey, you know, I don't know.
This is my C file and I do enough open and it's like out dot CPP,
right?
And I do, right?
And then I do, you know, fprintf C file.
Int main.
N targe.
Seek a star star.
Argh be backslash, n right.
You know what I'm saying to you?
This this is all I'm talking about.
That's metaprogramming, metaprogramming is just writing a program that
outputs a program and that's it.
That's all I'm talking about.
So the way that I do things nowadays is I most of my code gets
outputted.
Well, not most but a fair degree of code, let's say,
Percent something like that gets outputted by a program that outputs
programs.
And the reason I do that is because C is just doesn't have a lot of
features that I need.
And so, what I do is I Implement those features in the meta program so
they can output C code and IU C code.
Sort of is like my output language.
That's, that's, that's all it is.
That's all I'm talking about.
And so basically, now once you have your program out being output by
another program, you can use control flow and do all the stuff you
want to do.
And obviously, it doesn't end up looking like this.
You've got helper functions that output functions and all that sort of
stuff.
But basically this is all I'm talking about, right?
So sweet that file.
That's it.
There's no magic to it.
You just write a program that spits out a program.
They compiled that program and run it.
Ambiguous Panda.
You mentioned that you don't think you will make much of a profit from
becoming a twitch partner, but you get 7x more viewers than some of
the full-time streamers.
So, the reason is because the streams just not on that long and also
I'm not going to put, I'm not going to put ads in the Stream.
This is supposed to be educational and I'm doing this to teach people.
I'm not going to start like triggering ads every 15 minutes or
something.
Right?
And so the way that it works and which has a TV station basically.
And so the way that it works just like everything else is
No, they get you get paid by when people watch ads and then if people
subscribe, you get something.
I don't know.
You get fifty percent of that or something like this.
But I mean how many subscribers you know, are you probably going to
get?
So it just economically speaking.
I don't think that it's something that's worth compromising.
The uploading of the videos, which it has a real tangible, educational
value to people who are trying to keep up with the Stream.
So, I just didn't feel like the money was worth.
It, you know, if they were like you can have a hundred million dollars
and if you just don't upload the videos for 24 hours, I'd be like,
okay, because we can probably do some really good stuff with a hundred
million dollars, but on the whole, I just didn't feel like the stream
was going to generate that kind of Revenue that would make it.
So that the good stuff we did with it would outweigh the bad of having
to hold the files.
Just a judgment call.
Like I said, I just I prioritize people having a stable location for
archive files.
That's up right away.
I prioritize that over, whatever the incremental Revenue would be up
from the twitch stream.
That's the best way to say it.
And I also I don't want to, I don't want this to be a slight on Twitch
in any way.
Their contracts are their contracts and they're trying to run a
business.
So I'm not trying to say that this is bad.
I just couldn't sign their contract.
And so, you know, that was that was just how it went.
I mean obviously Twitches a good service.
You've been watching the show on it for many nights now and it has
never gone down.
In the one time.
We had a problem was because my internet service provider died, so
So Telegraph Cable says, sorry if I missed it, but did you fix that
expected B until flipbook in the autocode know?
Like I said, I've got a notebook of couple things we got to clean up.
So we haven't done any cleanup of the code.
We've just been implementing this new kind of dynamic reload thing.
So we're done with the dynamic reload will clean up that and there's a
couple other things I have written down my notebook that are I don't
know if that may be the only bug but there's other things that I'd
written down that should be cleaned up and so we'll clean this up.
Couple days.
Can you make a lot of money by C programming?
Yes.
I make made all of my money by C programming.
I've supported myself for since I was maybe 19 20.
I supported myself through C programming and it pays very well at
least currently, so,
Yeah, I mean I have never felt that.
I couldn't earn a very good salary, C programming.
It is always been true.
And the other thing that I would mention is if you know, low-level
programming like the kind that we're sort of going towards on this
stream.
There's hardly anyone in your job market, like you are alone.
Like basically, you can go work at any company, any high-end company
you want to, if you know how to do a little level game programming,
because there are so few people who actually know how to do it.
Like, most people only know how to do like the high level programming.
So, like, at any given time, tons of companies out there, big name
companies.
Wish they had more developers who know, new really good, low level C
code code or kinds of people.
So I've never seen a case where a great engine programmer was out of
work.
That's just I've never even heard of it.
Maybe it happens.
But I've never heard of that, usually the times, when people are out
of work programming wisest because they don't have those special
skills.
They're just a generic high-level programmer.
And those are actually very easy to find, it's very easy to go find a
person who could program in a high-level simple language to do, you
know, basic kinds of programming stuff, but people who can write their
own rasterizer.
I just don't know, of a time when people who can do those kinds of
things,
Things can't go get a job.
So and maybe that's changing.
I don't know me.
That's not true anymore.
But that's been the case in my life.
Anyway.
Let's see.
Do you use hot reloading in any of your non-game projects?
Yes, but I can't talk about those yet because they're not announced.
Why do you think so few people?
Learn this stuff?
Well, two reasons, one.
I'm trying to fix with handmade hero, which is that I think people
don't know how to get to the point where they can work on low-level
code.
Like, I don't think they have a good intro.
And so the idea behind handmade hero is that if you can
You're an hour or two a night for a year, like like you would if you
were going to a college course, then you will be able to see the
entire process of how to do that low-level code.
And I feel like I'm trying to solve that one part of it.
The second part of it is a motivational issue.
I think what happens is people go.
Oh, I can just go download unity and start making a game.
Right?
And it's a lot faster to make a game in unity, because so much code
has already been written for you.
And so using code that's already written for you is always faster.
To get started, then writing code from scratch.
Now what's kind of odd is?
Sometimes it actually turns out to not actually be faster overall
because you have to fight that already written code all the time when
it doesn't do what you want.
So depending on whether you happen to do a unity game, that's exactly
like some other unity game that already works and didn't in kind of
had Unity built around it or whether you're doing something totally
new and you have to write a lot of code.
Yourself may make that determination.
But either way in general having a game, engine means a lot of code
was already written for you and just using it's a lot.
Fleur.
So, people often don't want to invest the time to learn how to do the
little level code.
So what that means is, basically, you will get, I think in the future.
A lot of people who can work within the confines of an existing
engine, but cannot extend that engine effectively.
That's a bummer.
Because I think game engines have a long way to go before they're
really great.
So I think we need a lot more engine programmers than we have.
I think we need a lot more unit.
He's like, I don't want Unity to be the only game engine, you know, I
don't want.
Unreal for to be the only game in.
We need a lot of good game engines and we need them to be competing so
that we can have a lot of progress in what a game engine is how it
works.
What it's capable of because I think we've only just scratched the
surface really so I think we need that but there's another there's
another side to that coin which is and I'm you know, I can say this
definitively because I do play a ton of Indie Games built in unity.
I play a ton of them because I do judging for Indie Mega boost.
And I just like, I'm interested in indie games.
I like indie games and I like, like, as much as I want people to be
lower programmers.
I like the fact that Unity allows people who maybe would never invest
the time to become a game programmer at a low level and build their
own engine.
I like the fact that it allows them to make games because maybe there
are people who will be great game designers don't have, maybe the what
it takes to be a low-level game designer, but do you have what it
takes to be a great game designer, for example.
So Unity empowers.
Those people to do that game design and so on.
So I think Unity actually does a really good Public Service in some
sense by and makes a good business out of it.
Certainly by filling that Gap but there's a real big downside there.
And that is that a lot of games.
I see Unity games.
I see the controls are awful, like you play a platformer and it just
plays terribly.
And the reason for that is because the person who made the game just
doesn't
No enough about game code to make a really great feeling.
Well, jump or a really great feeling rocket boost or that impact, or
what a gun should feel like the fire or what it should feel like to do
X, right?
And so programming and understanding like how to program your own
physics stuff, and how to program like is really very important.
Even if you're using someone else's engine, because we haven't gotten
to the point yet where the engines, make it foolproof for you to make
a good feeling game time.
Maybe someday, we will and that's like a very important Avenue of game
engine development and I'm sure that's the kind of thing that Unity
people are probably working on.
And, you know, I hope they succeed and making thing tools that make it
easier for you to do those things.
But for now, I feel like, even people who use an engine or existing
libraries need to know their stuff, and they don't need to know, all
the stuff that I'm learning on that.
I'm trying to teach on this dream about like how to like concatenate
your own strings and how to rasterize your own Sprites, but they do
need.
To learn some of this stuff.
And so, you know, I hope that their becomes more of a trend of people
sort of showing how to do that kind of programming.
So that games don't end up being bad for the reason that the probe,
the people making them didn't know how to write the code, right?
I mean, I literally cannot tell you how many Unity based Platformers I
have played that feel awful.
It is dozens.
Right?
And if those Platformers may have been great, like the platformer may
have actually been a good design that was interesting to play but you
just don't want to play it because it feels awful and the jump feels
awful.
Like that happens all the time.
And so there are consequences to people not knowing how to do some of
this coding.
And so I feel like there's a sort of Flip Side to it, too.
All right.
So any more questions, I think my horse my horse.
My voice is just about shot.
So
I know some of your friends went to reinvent but I can't stress how
much Guild Wars 2.
Feels awful that they didn't do Guild Wars 2, they left so the friends
of mine who is talking about they found it.
Arenanet made gills, Guild Wars 1 and then left because of political
reasons when the company got acquired.
So, do not worry.
You are not insulting them.
By saying, Guild Wars 2 is bad.
All right.
I think I'm going to call it here because I need to save some voice
because again, would be programming tomorrow.
Thank you, everyone for joining us for another episode of handmade
hero.
I'm going to go ahead and close everything down here.
Basically, if you enjoyed tonight's episode and you
Like to support the series, you have ways of doing that on handmade
hero dot-org.
There is a patreon.
You can click on if you'd like to just support the video series.
But also if you'd like to pre-order the game, you can do that right
here and that comes with some benefits.
You can download the source code every night and you will actually be
able to get builds of the game as well.
Once we have the full game running.
So this is like a basically complete access to everything and you can
download every night.
After I finish the stream, you can download the source code and it has
all of the source code from the previous day's as well.
So, if you go back and do other things, you can do that.
So, yeah, you like sports series, you've got ways of doing it, and I
appreciate that.
Also, we put up a site.
If you click on that news and forums link, if you click on this link,
right here, we put up a site that basically has like a forum.
You can click on code discussion and there's a forum in here that
people can can discuss things.
Help each other out, talk about things.
They've done with handmade hero.
There's also, if you just click on the main link to handmade hero
Centrelink, it's got the the schedule for each week if you want to
know ahead of time.
And also,
Got this great episode guide thing.
Well actually two great things.
This episode guide thing is basically a thing that community members
have put together where you can, where I showed it a little bit in the
Stream today where you can go click on things in there's like time
markers.
You can jump to anything that you want to learn about if you want to
go back and reference it.
So that's pretty awesome.
And this coding Resource page has some awesome stuff on it to people
have ported.
Handmade hero are ready to Mac OS X and sdl.
There's a bunch of stuff like that on here.
We've also people have talked about how to use other editors.
And we've got weekly Illustrated summaries.
These are pretty cool.
Like or murga does these ones where he does little illustrations of
what happens every week.
So there's just a ton of stuff here that you can check out and there's
also a thanks page where all the people have made this possible.
They come on here, so you can thank them if you see them online, so
that's that's all the the stuff for handmade hero.
I hope to see you here tomorrow at 8 p.m.
Pacific Standard time.
And then Thursday, and Friday will be on holiday hours because we're
getting close to Christmas.
Seriously, Thursday and Friday, we will be 11:00 a.m.
We'll be in the morning.
So some of you might not be able to make it but some of you from
Europe may be able to make it.
So hopefully we'll see some new faces.
They're on the twitch stream as well.
Thank you very much for joining me.
It has been a pleasure coding with you as always and I hope to see you
tomorrow.
Thanks, everyone.