String begins now is to begin the stream.
I think we can all agree on that.
All right, everyone.
Thank you so much for joining us.
Again.
This is handmade hero day, 13.
Where we are making an entire professional quality game from scratch,
right before your very eyes.
We are in the middle of a process where we are basically taking our
Windows code, which is what we did the first two weeks and we are
turning that into platform independent code.
Just a little Windows layer and that'll set us up for Success.
Kind of going forwards, where we can have this run on lots of
platforms.
And we won't have to touch any of the code that is in the mainline
game.
So we left off yesterday.
We had just moved sound output over from being platform, specific to
being platform nonspecific.
And so today we actually have to do the same thing for input.
So basically what we're going to try and do is we're going to try and
end the day with having input being processed on the other side.
Now, there's one little thing.
He made cheese out today because I want to talk about it in depth
tomorrow, but we're going to do most of the work for the input today.
So loading up win32 handmade.
This is our win32 code here and then loading up handmade .h.
+ dot CPP over here, which is our platform non specific code.
Basically.
What you can see what we've already done is we're already passing some
generic structures that just are the off-screen, the graphics buffer
and the sound buffer to the game and then the game feels those in.
But what you can see here, obviously,
Cecily, is that we're still having to pass in things like blue offset
and green offset, which are essentially, they are allowing the
platform layer to process the input from the GamePad, or the keyboard
or whatever, do whatever it's going to do and then pass that
information to the game so that it can render the the off-screen
buffer.
But Peru, you know what this is kind of interesting here.
Let me finish that gonna say but then I want to show you something
else.
Something a little fun, but
What we're not doing is we're not actually passing the input across
and letting the game.
Do that processing.
So all of the actual results of the input processing are still sitting
in our win32 code and we don't want to do that.
We want to have all of the logic for processing, the input, on the
platform independent side, and we just want the win32 code to do the
work necessary to sort of like process it out of win32 format into
some convenient, generic format, that all platforms.
Can provide hand that over.
The game and then go from there.
So that's we're going to do.
I want to say one thing.
Now, you'll notice, if I cut and paste this here.
We didn't notice this.
No one on the stream.
Notice it either see anything going on here.
The deaf the definition for our function is here, but the Declaration,
the forward declaration up here is missing this.
It doesn't have in tone, right?
So how did that work?
What happened there?
Right?
Shouldn't we have gotten some kind of error?
Well, the answer is
That actually in C++ anyway, when which is what the mode we're
compiling.
And we're compiling.
Mostly, what is C code, but we are compiling and C++ mode.
So we can use C++ features when we want to.
If we want to one of the things we get in C++ mode is function
overloading.
And what that means is you're allowed to Define multiple functions
with the same name that take different inputs.
So, for example, I could Define many different functions, Each of
which took a different set of parameters.
Ders, you can see what I'm talking about here.
For example, each of those is different.
I can compile this and it is totally legal.
I can each make each of these, be its own function, and there's no
problem with that totally legal.
No warnings.
No errors.
No nothing.
It is.
It is flat-out, completely legal, get that up there above my window so
I can see it.
There we go.
And so you may ask yourself.
Well, in this one actually is a duplicate because
Well, okay, you know what?
It's good that I did that.
I could tell you why it's to put, basically, you may ask.
How does it know which one to call when you go to call one?
The answer is it just matches the parameters and sees which one
matches.
So, if I go down to win32 handmade where this is called game update
and render, you'll notice that I'm passing one, two, three, four, five
parameters.
So, it's just going to look and say, oh, okay, all of these, there's
only one.
Right?
That actually takes that many parameters.
Sorry.
That's a five.
That's that's that's what 12345.
Yes.
That's right.
And this is 1 2 3 4.
Which doesn't count.
This is 3.
This is 2.
So the only one that counts is this one with five parameters.
So it's just going to go.
Oh, it's the five parameter one and try to call that.
Now thing is can get a little more complicated if we have ones that
have the same number of parameters.
So let's say we had five parameters in both of them, but I have this
one, be a float like that, it still would work.
In theory, let me get rid of this guy because I'm not gonna talk about
me.
It still would work because most of the time, the compiler will be
able to tell that you were trying to pass an integer.
Not a floating-point.
So it's going to call the integer 1 whereas if you pass the floating
point, it would pass the other one.
So you can see that basically it's going to do its best to kind of
match those up.
But sometimes it doesn't know what to do and then you will get an
error.
And that's that one that I deleted here.
So let's say I have ENT green offset and it blew off set and that's
the only difference.
It's between these two functions.
Well, which one does it call?
If I pass it, you know, a buffer, an integer and then the sound
buffer, the answer is, it has no idea.
It does not know how to differentiate between those two because they
both take an integer.
And so that is an error.
You would have to change one of these or rename one of these in some
way in order to differentiate them.
In a way the compiler understands.
That's the, you know, the simple capsule overview of function
overloading basically, I don't use function overloading a whole lot
but I do.
Having access to it.
It's one of the reasons.
I like compiling with CPP files.
I don't know if c99 let you start doing function overloading or not.
I've never really looked at the c99 spec, but C++ let you do it.
And it's one of the things that I like as compared to see one of the
reasons I like it is because it allows me to basically have a few
different ways to call the same function without having to have
different names for them and it just makes things a little more
convenient and easier to read in a lot of cases.
So I don't go Hog Wild with it, but I do like it.
It and I think it's a useful feature something to be aware of there.
So anyway, what was happening here is we just had a completely
erroneous declaration.
This is not a function that ever existed, and I just forgot to update
here.
We don't need to actually put this here.
It is.
Strictly sort of for legibility.
I like kind of sticking things together so I can quickly look at what
the definition of definition is of my platform layer, but basically
like we don't even need this here.
We could have it be completely not defined at all because since
handmade dot CPP gets included.
We're win32 handmade dot CPP.
We are totally fine.
It'll pick up the actual definition here in, doesn't need a forward
declaration at all.
So I hope that basically works and and Jagger 27.
I know my face hides the code, but I can't see that code either.
I can't see it now.
It's blocked for me as well.
So I promise you.
It will never hide code.
That I can see.
It'll only hide code that I can't see either.
All right, so moving.
On basically what we've got here is we have a situation where we need
to extend this so that it starts taking input.
So the first thing I'm going to do is I'm going to basically pull out
these guys into Statics because I don't want to get to memory yet.
Like I said, that's going to be the topic of tomorrow's entire thing.
Unless we somehow speed, through input tonight, which I don't expect,
we will, I expect there's plenty of explanation to do there.
So, all I'm going to do is, I'm basically going to pull these out here
and I'm going to
I'm going to basically make them be equal to whatever they were by
default.
So the X offset y offset here that were equal to zero before.
I guess we'll just leave them is 0.
Now.
That's what they would have been initialized to anyway, but no big
deal.
Tone hurts here was 256.
So we'll go ahead and make that 256.
I'm gonna go ahead and nuke that from this, as well as the tone
volume, because those are should not be used anymore in the platform,
code, tone hurts and tone volume are gone.
I don't know if we use running sample index.
I
Leave we still do out here.
Correct to figure out where to lock yet.
So think that's basically everything that needs to be removed from
that struct.
Let me go ahead and pull that struck out up to the top as well.
I tend to like to have these up here.
In fact, what I usually like to do as well as they usually like to
have an h-file even if I don't need one.
And I like to kind of put that stuff in there, so I can quickly, see
it quickly flip between it.
So I may just go ahead and and and straight up do that right like
that, that makes sense.
So basically the wave period.
That's also should be gone.
So, let's get rid of that.
What else do we need to ice these two.
Not going to happen.
Now, we're going to have to do those ourselves tone hurts.
That's not going to happen.
I got to get rid of that.
And the wave period.
Also, they all that stuff's going to have to be dealt with differently
and we're not going to pass them anymore.
So we're basically just down to this and now we get to a situation
where we've done a little bit of feature regression there.
We have removed all of the ability to control what's going on.
And we're going to have to start moving that into the platform layer.
So there we are, things still working, but we cannot use our joystick
anymore.
Basically, if I go ahead and and pull out our lovely pink joystick
here.
This guy there is no, does not matter what I do.
I can Mash on that all day long and we're not getting anything from
our game.
So now what we need to do is we need to decide basically what we're
going to pass the game and this is a little bit complicated because we
have not written the game.
Yet.
And so one of the things that's very important.
Like I've said many times on the string is, you always want to write
the usage code first and we are at a bit of a disadvantage because
since we don't have the game, we don't actually know exactly how we're
going to be using the user input.
If the game was done and someone handed it to us and said, hey here,
make a platform layer that supports this game.
Well, we could very easily see what the optimal way to pass that input
to the game would be, we don't have that and so we know going into
this and it's important to know these things.
We know going
NG into this that what we're doing here is a first pass.
This is a first pass attempt on the interface time for some almond
milk.
Bit of a long Swig there.
If you are drinking along at home wasn't your own almond milk, I
highly recommend taking a pretty strong hit.
Sometimes it helps especially when you have a cold.
Alright, so basically what I'm trying to get across the areas API
design and platform layer design and just code in general.
You always need to have a little bit of Consciousness.
You have a little bit of a voice in the back of your head that lets,
you know, exactly what it is.
You're doing at any given time because the type of code that you're
going to type in, is going to be different depending on the
circumstance and the circumstance.
In this case is, we are iterating towards the API that we want, which
is not the same as typing in the exact final API.
The reason this is important is because it means, you have to let
there be a little slop in there.
It means that you have to not spend a lot of time on a lot of the
code.
Now, you'll notice that our win32 code is pretty darn janky.
That is not because we're being lazy.
That is because we're trying to save ourselves work.
We know we're going to rewrite a lot of that stuff when we go to
tighten it down for shipping and the time that we would spend
tightening it down now with just be wasting because it would all be
deleted.
So, we need to remember, what kind of code were writing.
We need to know what kind of
Anders that code has to be up to.
We need to know, what kind of future that codes going to have.
And all of those things in the back of our head, informing us with how
we should proceed are very important because they'll save us work
doing too much analysis and too much work on code too.
Early in the process is bad.
There's the old adage.
Premature optimization is the root of all evil and a lot of people
take that to mean that the optimization is making code fast.
Well, that may be true doing that at the head end might
Be bad, you might spend a lot of time doing optimization on code that
didn't need to be optimized or that you optimize in the wrong way.
Because later, you change it, you have to undo it all and do different
optimizations.
That's all true.
But what's also true is that optimization really, in this case, for
purposes of the adage can refer also to the design of the code itself.
Premature design is one of the most and I repeat most destructive
forces in Computing today.
It is the thing that cost the most time it.
The thing that results in the most problems in shipping code,
premature design is awful.
You have to remember what you are doing at any given time.
So right now, we are at the beginning of the design phase for this API
and we need to understand that these are experiments and we need to
use them as such and guide our code up to the point where we can start
to do final API work on it.
And that is the time to start tightening down those those, although it
crossing the eyes and dotting the T's, or crossing the t's and
dotting, the
Why's depending on which language you happen to be using that, that is
the time for that?
Okay.
So basically, what I want to do here is I want to start to imagine
what would be useful for my game in terms of input, coming from the
platform layer.
Now, I know that this game is not really going to care too much about
which controller you're using keyboard or joystick.
It needs to be able to work with keyboard and Gamepad.
That's true.
But I do at least want to know.
For purposes of tuning whether the user is Using a Gamepad or they're
using a keyboard because at least for movement, where one of them
might be analog and one of them might not be, I kind of want to know
this.
So I feel like I'm gonna at least want there to be something, you
know, like the input dot is analog or something.
I'm going to want to be able to do some checking on something like
that.
Right?
And I'm going to want to be able to do things in here.
They're like
Use analog movement tuning and in here, I'm going to want to do use
digital movement tuning, right?
And so I'm gonna, I'm gonna expect there to be differences in how I
might want to tune the motion of the character based on which one it
is now for the buttons.
I don't expect that to be true for the buttons.
You push a button on a keyboard, you push a button on the GamePad for
the purpose of this game.
I think those are going to be roughly the same, so you won't need to
tell the game about that.
But for the stick, I'm going to want that.
So again, just Pie in the Sky.
I was just saying, I want that.
It's got to be in there.
Whatever this thing is going to be.
It's going to have to tell me that piece of information.
So we've got that.
Now.
I'm also going to want to basically be able to look at that at that
motion of the stick.
And now when I've got to think about here, and maybe I'll bring up the
diagram for a second, the awesome, Microsoft Paint, one of the most
powerful paint packages in the world.
Certainly, the one that most game art is made on.
Microsoft Paint.
Everyone knows that professional paint artists love their Microsoft
Paint.
So, in in here, basically, you've, you know, the ubiquitous Arrow
diagram that I draw every time.
This is time here.
T going forwards and we've got frames right?
We've got frames worth of processing.
So in here, this is frame one that we're processing or actually, let's
call it frame 0.
Let's start at 0, like a good programmer would and going forwards.
Now what we have to remember is the yu-er user is viewing, a
Mmmmm, basically, after we compute it.
So, if this is, if this is which frame, we're Computing, right?
If we're Computing frame 0 in this time, it's actually going to get
displayed here and they're going to view frame 0 here, right?
And then they're going to view frame one here, and they're going to
view frame to here.
So, it's always, it's always kind of going like this, right?
Hoops made that Arrow.
Go a little too far.
There we go.
Can't blame Microsoft Paint for that people.
Alright.
So basically what happens is, if we are Computing during this period,
let's say our will actually use it.
We're sort of up here.
So we're just playing frame 0 and during the time when the user is
looking at frame 0, right.
They are moving the joystick around right there, moving the joystick
left and up, and who knows?
Maybe they rolled it around now, they've only got a 30th or a 60th of
a second.
They don't have that much time, but they still could be doing some
small amount of motion on the stick in that time, right?
They might slightly move it, you know, from from you know, if the
stick is one of these things and it's over here, right?
You could imagine
In a 60th of a second.
Second, if you were really wailing on it, you could whale it down a
little bit in a sixtieth of a second.
And especially for going at 30 frames a second, and we've got a 30th
of a second to do that.
Well, they might be able to move it twice as far.
They move it even further.
Right?
So the user is moving their, their joystick in response to what they
saw on the screen.
We're not going to get this input until after we've already computed
frame 1.
So the next frame they're going to see is not going to incorporate any
of the input they were doing when
They actually saw frame 0.
This is one of the reasons that having a high frame rate is good
because basically, you have to act on the input that you got last
frame to compute this Frame, which means you're always essentially one
frame behind.
If you do your input stupidly, you can even be two frames behind but
no matter what you do.
It's not instantaneous the response, It's Always bucketed by that
frame rate and you're going to be one sixtieth of a second behind
possibly more depending on the circumstances.
So we have some decisions to make here.
Now.
We got another thing which is
Let's say they push the a button, right?
They push the a button down then they let up on the a button, then
they push the a button.
Again.
Probably pretty hard to do that in a 30th of a second.
But who knows maybe there really wailing on it?
Maybe they got magic fingers.
I don't know.
Maybe they hooked up one of those old turbo joysticks that does the
automatic repeat fire.
I don't know, who knows what could happen but point being.
If we imagine this Frame to be impossibly long.
Let's say we were running at one frame a second, then you can
certainly
Imagine the user pushing the button a couple times during that one
second.
And of course, that is something to be aware of as well.
And so, what we need to do now as a game is, we need to decide what
about this series of operations that is happening in here.
Do we want to actually record?
So like, what do we save, right?
And of course, we have some restrictions on what we can save because
the joystick itself is only pulling.
There was its own state for a
/ of times a second.
So we actually just get snapshots.
You know what, we get.
If we look across this, depending on the polling frequency is we just
get a series of little positions of the stick.
Right?
We don't actually know what happened in between there.
We don't know what happens in between the polling frequency.
So no matter what it is.
It's kind of a discrete approximation of the actual motion that
happened on the stick.
Same thing with the button.
If somehow the user could press the button twice fast enough that the
joystick itself wasn't pulling fast enough to catch that you
Could imagine a circumstance where a button pressed was completely
missed, right?
So there are limitations of what we can do.
But certainly what we do want to do at a minimum isn't sure that
anything that's important for our game to have happen that we don't
miss.
So for example, if the user happens to let up on the a button here,
press down on it and then let up on it again.
That's a button press.
We don't want to miss it.
We never want to miss a button press because then the user press the
button and didn't shoot or didn't do whatever it is.
The game's going to do.
When you push that button in, that feels awful to the player, so we
want to respect those things as much as possible.
Okay?
So what we need to decide now is how we're going to collect this
information and how we're going to pass it on to the user because we
can always decide to pull those devices more frequently.
If the operating system lets us do that or try to get, you know,
access to lower level data.
We can always try to improve how we get the data, but no matter how
much of the data we get.
And how
Accurate.
It is we still are always going to have sell a problem of how do we
encode it properly so that when we pass it to the game, it has the
easiest time understanding it.
Okay, so
What I like to do in general.
is I like to think about what the possibilities are for the various
things in the game, and on the
On the, on the joystick.
And the first one I'm going to talk about is basically looking at sort
of what people will often do.
And then I'm going to say why I often don't do that thing, sort of as
a compare and contrast.
So what people will often do is, they'll often do something like this.
They'll well, you know what?
I can write it, encodes you, so you don't have to look at like an
interface.
You can actually see what the code would look like when they write it,
they often do something.
That's that looks something like this.
You've got a for Loop, and it's going to do something like, let's
I'd say event index equals 0 that is, if I can type tonight, which who
knows event, count plus event index like this and then they'll go
through and they'll have something that's like an event array and
they'll look into the event or a and they'll do like switch event or a
you know, what type of event this is.
Oh it's, you know, event a button or something like that, you know,
that sort of thing.
So they'll have like a type of event or the events will just be
A state of the joystick.
So basically it'll just be like, okay, there's an event index and
we've got the stick X in here, right?
Stick Y in here, that sort of thing, you know, whatever a button is
either up or down that sort of stuff and basically what happens is
again, it's a very minimal amount of processing that the that the
platform layer does.
And the platform layer, basically goes ahead and and takes its
information.
Does the minimal amount of processing on it?
And
Hands it over to the game and says here you go.
You look at the series of pulling results and you figure out what's
going on.
Now.
The thing that I don't like about this is that it has an inherent kind
of limitation in it, that forces us to think about something and that
limitation is you've got to have somewhere to store these events.
And the number of them that you choose to store it determines exactly
how many times the buttons can be pressed inside a given frame.
Now that may not sound like much and it isn't because memory is really
cheap nowadays.
You could just have 10 megabytes of button store and go to town on
your little party and then no matter what the user was doing or no
matter how long, the frame took you will not be able to generate
enough events.
Even if you're pulling it some you know, if it took one second long
and you were pulling it, you know, 1,000 Hertz.
Well,
Events is not going to be a really huge deal.
But in my mind, I still tend to think of it.
As you know, why would I
Incur the downsides of having a variable-length set of storage if I
don't need to.
And so what I ask when I see stuff like this is, do we really care
about that?
And for this particular game, I don't know that I actually do.
And so what I like to do is I like to do something more, like having
the input.
Just say something.
Like let's say a button started down.
Right?
A button ended down or something like that and number of transitions
or something, right?
Because what I can do is I can essentially turn any one of these
buttons right into something.
Let's say the button.
Let's let's say that we have over time.
If this was a diagram of our a button, this is is this is a up and
this is down for a button if over the course.
First of the frame, it started up press it down.
Went up again.
They left it up.
They pressed it down again and it went up, they press it down.
Right then.
Basically, I know that I can encode this signal.
Right this like, up, down, up, down up down, kind of a signal, right.
I know that I can encode the signal by just saying, how many of the
transitions I went through, right?
I can just say, how many times it went from up to down, or down to up.
I can just treat that I can treat that as one or transition.
Or I can count half.
Transitions, right?
I can count down to up and up to down, I can count that.
So it'd be a basically two transitions or two, half transitions per
press, right?
Half Transitions.
And if I encode it as half transitions, I can basically say, well all
I need to really know is what state the button is at the end.
And then I know the number of half, transitions tells me what the
state was the beginning.
So basically I have two things I need which is is the button down now
and how many Taff transitions did it go through for the course of this
Frame, right?
So what I want to know here is basically, okay.
Do I ever actually care about subframe resolution for the button being
held down?
Right?
Because what I lose by encoding it this way.
What I lose in this encoding is if the user was able to differentiate
between say a hundred and twentieth of a second press, That's this
long.
And one that's like a 240th of a s press which is like that long or
something.
Right?
I don't know.
I'm drawing, this poorly.
This diagram has gotten out of control, but you basically know what I
mean.
If I, if this was our, if this was our time here, right?
And I've got this is 1/60 of a
Can't right here, right?
Then as I go through this, if I was to look at the the button press
going from up.
So if the button is up and then it goes down for a whole 1/20 of a
second.
This region right here.
Do I want to differentiate between that and something that just looks
like this right?
Where it sits down for only half that time.
And my answer to that is I don't think any player can even do that,
right?
Players can't really distinguish between a press.
That's a 60th of a second.
And a 30th of a second.
Maybe they couldn't a 15th of a second, but intentionally, that's not
really the case when we're talking about the difference between a
button hold and not, we're talking about a hold across many frames.
I think.
So, I'll hold is going to be, you know.
A quarter of a second or something like this or an eighth of a second
and that's going to be across many frames.
So at that point, I tend to kind of think of it as well.
I don't really think I want to try and track that and I don't know if
most operating systems are even going to give me anything at an
accuracy, that would even let me see that.
So I think it's probably just a waste of time to encode it.
Okay.
So what I'm going to say is, I basically just want to try something
that's basically like the a button started down, you know?
And and the a button half transition count and that's all I'm going to
do per button.
So we had four buttons we have for those, right?
So I'm just going to go through those and we don't actually use the
button right now, for anything.
We'll have to invent something for it to do.
But basically I guess what we'll do is we can do something like a know
and I wanted ended down not started down basically for now.
What I'll do is since we don't have anything else to do right now.
I'll basically just say that if the a button ended down, I will, I
will make on any frame where your swear.
You're still holding it.
I'll make the green offset, kind of increment by 1 or something like
that.
Let's say, just for now.
It's not a good example of doing anything useful.
Once we get some like projectiles or something.
We can start doing some real code.
In there.
We look at the half transition count and launched as many as we
should, and things like that, but for now, we're not going to do that.
Alright, so we did that, right?
We've got the a button-down and a half.
Encount.
That's what I'd like to do four buttons.
Now the stick and the stick is a little more complicated because it
depends what we're going to want to do with it.
If we had a d-pad and be a little clearer.
I think if we knew that we were going to be on a machine that had a
good d-pad.
I might want to do stuff like allow you to do that.
Old Dash thing that people used to be able to do.
Do you know, the one I'm talking about where they basically could like
double click this thing in a direction and you dodge.
You know, I'd love to have that.
I'm worried that that is too difficult to do.
Basically I'm worried that's a little bit too difficult to do with an
analogue stick.
I don't know what I do know is analog sticks are so clumsy that no
one's probably going to be able to do much in a 60th of a second with
that.
But the reason that I mention it is because I'm a little worried about
how to capture that motion.
If we were going to do quick dodges.
Oh and the reason I say that is basically because if you think about
what we're trying to do here, let's say we were pulling fairly
frequently.
We got a 60th of a second here.
Right?
We've got this 60th a second and basically let's say we were pulling
it, some kind of a thing like a 1,000 samples, a second.
Right?
So basically we're talking about we're talking about having a thousand
samples of s and we've got 60 buckets into which those can fall.
All.
So there's actually 16 samples like this, right?
That that that that dot dot dot da.
Okay.
There's our samples.
123456789 Loops 1 2 3 4 5 6 7 8 9 10 11 12, 13 14 15 16.
So they each go one sample in each of these buckets, right?
We got a stick position in each of these buckets.
So let's say that we were pulling at some ungodly frequency because
we're trying to be mr.
Amazing action game.
And we've got some crazy.
You know the dude spent eight thousand dollars on his razor massive
joystick thing that pulls perfectly and for Street Fighter.
He's playing at Evo.
God knows what's going on.
We're trying to do that and we basically want to look at this and say
well, okay.
So what happened here was he started wailing the stick right here.
So basically the stick at this point and so from this point to this
point went from neutral, right to basically wailed all the way over.
He just full-on slut.
And it and he's got magic fingers.
So it went really quick then he released the stick and it returned 20
here, right?
Well, the problem with this is, if I'm trying to text it, if I average
the stick value over this time or something to pass to the game.
I'm going to get an average that's like somewhere, you know, in the
middle of that range, right?
And this could happen even in a wonky way across frames, you know, you
could imagine something where, like, I've got a situation like this,
where the stick was held this way, across two frames, but here it's
dead.
And here it's dead, right?
This
And the average of these is going to be something that never shows,
the stick fully wailed, right?
It's always going to be halfway old.
And in know, who cares about half wailing.
Nobody half, Wales the stick, that's not even a phrase.
No one's ever said.
I have failed my name pad.
That's not a thing.
Hmm.
Got that kind of caught your kind of caught a little bit.
You see that, you got to hold it back.
You got it.
This is how you do it.
If you got one of these bottles, you got to hold that back.
And then you, you know what?
I'm
Saying those of you have these know what I'm talking about.
Otherwise it gets up in their gets all up in your face.
And there's nothing you can do about, it's too late.
That point is no recovery possible.
All right.
So basically, what I, what I'm worried about here, if we were, if we
were just doing, you know, a lot tip, my hand too much here.
But let's just say that Legend of Zelda or Binding of Isaac, were in
the realm of things.
We were trying to do here, and we want to move a little character
around the environment in like, a
Top down any kind of way if all we were doing was cloning those sorts
of games.
Exactly.
I would say, does not matter, that kind of stick move.
It does not matter.
We'll just pass the average stick and we will be fine.
But because like I said, not tipping, my hand too much.
I'm not really doing exactly that.
Or at least I'm not planning on doing exactly that kind of a thing.
We have a little bit more to worry about because I might want to try
to get some stuff working that involves these kind of tap motions at a
quick Tap.
Maybe not a double tap it at least that one quick tap, so.
What am I going to do?
And the answer is, I think for purposes of this.
I'm going to go with a stick interval and this may be a bad idea.
It may be that I should just shove 16 samples down the thing at a
time.
It may be that I should switch to an event thing.
Like I said, but I don't know.
I'm not sure.
I think I might just want to go with some kind of stick interval.
So you can kind of see how far the stick move that kind of a thing.
So like
Min max sort of a thing if that makes sense.
And so what I think I'm going to do is I'm just going to go with an
input kind of thing where it's like we've got a Min X and like and
like a Min y kind of a thing and they'll have Max as well for the
stick that kind of a thing, right?
So that I can basically see where the Min and the max was and then
maybe where you ended on, right?
And so the same as before, you know, end X, right?
And I could even do a scar decks as well.
Well, so we can basically see where it started, where it was in the
Middle, where it ended, right?
That kind of a thing.
I do know, like I said, experimenting totally being experimental here.
Not saying this is the right way to make a game.
Not even saying this is the right way to make this game.
I'm just saying that's what I'm going to try and we're going to see
how it works.
So, how does that work in practice here?
I want to write the usage code.
First.
I want to basically take our tone hurts, right?
I'm going to take our tone hurts here.
I want to update.
That.
So I'm basically going to take the tone hurts and say that the the
tone Hertz is going to be plus it, plus some small amount of Wiggle.
Basically, that's going to be it's going to be on there, right?
I'm going to do this in floating point because as you'll see, we're
going to actually start moving, almost everything to floating-point
pretty soon, but we're still an integer here.
So I'm just casting back to it for a sake of our tone hurts again.
One thing at a time, always one thing time, and I'm just going to go
ahead and say that, whatever it ended.
Adan again, because that's the easiest thing for me to do at all times
and we can trivially test to make sure our thing is working at all by
like sort of going there, right by getting that to work.
So I'm gonna make our town hurts, be that, and then I'm going to make
our blue offset B plus equal to, let's say whatever the intent is of,
I don't know.
Let's say up to 4 pixels at a time, maybe times whatever that that
stick is.
What is that?
Stick going to be that?
It is going to be and why location, right?
And that is what I think I'm going to want.
That should basically work for the most part.
I think except for the fact that I don't actually have anything to
find yet, but it looks good to me.
I'm gonna go ahead and say game input is here.
And basically what I want to do is I want to blow this out a little
bit because I feel like we're going to have a situation where well,
you know, what if we want to support multiple players, right?
What if I want more than one player time?
Basically, what I want to do is say well this input thing whatever the
input thing is the input equals like, you know, the player one input,
right?
I want to be able to get just play.
ER one, let's say for now later, we'd have a way to like join in know
who was joining, but we kind of want Player, 1 input, probably, and
then we just kind of go and say, well, whatever player.
One input actually is then then we'll do that.
So, maybe input is like a game controller input, and we get that back.
We some, we take the random thing, we say, input, and we say input, I
guess we should say zero.
So player input 0, something like that.
I'll just, you know, grab out of an array of inputs.
That will say, well, how are you?
Players, we support may be 0 may be one and then I'll say we know that
that's accurate.
Right?
There we go.
We know that that's going to work.
So I don't really have to test anything.
Then this is going to be a pointer input 0.
I want to know if it's analog or not.
I'm not really doing anything with that yet, though.
Well, there is one thing I could do, which we could we could play
around with which is which one of these were going to do.
So, for the moment, we could say that, you know, will use is analog
there.
Let's do that.
That'll be good.
And then
I will also do our button thing that happens.
Whether it's analog or not.
We'll do the digital movement there and just try to think through, if
there's anything else we needed, that's fine.
A button into down that all looks pretty good to me.
So I'm going to say, let's go with that for now.
Let's just see how that works.
Make sure that there's nothing particularly surprising going on in
there.
We'll just see how that works.
So, I'm going to say, we've got this game controller input thing, the
game controller input is going to have the things that I talked about.
I also probably want something
Like this game button state that will have the half transition count
and the ended down flag.
That's actually going to be a Boolean for now.
So I've got some button States.
I know that I wanted I think I said that I wanted six buttons on this
thing, the two shoulders, and the a xyb.
Now, I don't know how I want those to be right now.
I am not sure so I'm just going to call these up down left.
Left, right.
Let's see.
And then left shoulder and right Loops, right?
Shoulder like that.
I'm just going to say that.
That's what those are for.
Now.
We might want to put them in an array later.
If we decide to, if we decide we want to, if it makes things easier, I
could also make a union out of these, I could do something fancy.
For example, I could do this if I was mr.
Crazy town and wanted them to be accessible in both ways.
I could.
Do something like this?
I don't know if that makes any sense to you.
When you take a look at it.
Maybe I'll do it just so you can see how that's going assuming that I
type that in, right?
We'll see you in a second.
The game input will just have a bunch of these controllers because we
might want to have some controllers.
Let's just say the thieves are the I guess we should call them
controllers not players because they're not really mapped two players
will say that we support for controllers coming in.
We're going to maybe need to do some work on that in the future to
make that a little more robust.
Being on the circumstances, but we'll just say that's good.
And then we'll just do controllers there.
Right?
And so that's sort of what I'm thinking, then we obviously have some
floating Point values here.
The floating Point values, are the stick X and stick.
Why there's some stuff that I probably want to do with that in the
future, but I'm going to leave those as x + y, is right now because we
haven't really talked about vectors and don't want to jump right in
with vectors if we're not ready for them yet min.
X Min y but those of you who know know what vectors are you pretty
much know.
You can see it coming.
I think when you look at that right there, you're pretty much going to
know what I'm talking about when I say the vectors are coming.
Alright, so Hoops for a little semicolon there.
I gotta actually pass this stuff to the actual thing.
So going to need to pass my game in.
Input and we'll just go ahead and send that in this way nice and clean
and we will delete those extraneous erroneous parameters.
We now have that going for us put that in there.
Lovely lovely, lovely.
Like one of those cooking shows when they put in like the basil and
they're like, you know, starting to smell delicious.
You can.
You could almost just feel the aroma of the fresh pasta and they say
all these things right?
And you get really excited about it and you're like, wow.
And I'm not going to eat that at the end.
That's one of the things we have ladies and gentlemen, over a cooking
show.
If you think about it, you are going to get to play the game.
The actual game at the end.
You even get to have the source code at the end.
You it's like the cooking show reaches out and hands you the pasta.
How cool is that?
I mean, yes.
Okay, I charge $15 for it.
I apologize.
It is actually a commercial product but that you can't you can't like
pay $15 and get the food in the cooking show.
Which by the way, I would probably do.
If you could do that just kind of came to you guys like a download
link and you could like get the pasta.
It'd be like, I want to buy that when they have replicators of Star
Trek, works in the future and you just like, have like Gordon Ramsay,
cook some stuff and you push the button and like it charges, you 15
bucks, but you get this whole meal like that's like going to be
totally crazy.
Right, like how awesome is that going to be?
Of course, it make it harder to make cooking shows because the stuff
comes out and tastes lousy everyone at home knows.
Now, they can just lie basically, right?
And be like, oh, it tastes delicious.
Maybe it tastes terrible, right?
And you don't know.
But anyway, so that's this.
All, we're just.
That's where like one step ahead of the Food Network here on Twitch.
Okay, that's that's where we're at.
So, this is some good stuff.
This is, this is this is the future that isn't gentleman's the future.
It's the future of food in a roundabout way.
Alright, so basically where we're at is we're just going to have to
now do the porting work necessary to shove this stuff down to the game
from the platform layer, which shouldn't be too hard for got one of
the things I wanted which was analog.
So each controller is going to have a Boolean up on top, which is
analog.
There we go.
Go.
That's fine.
What is the problem?
Not a member of controller input.
What are you talking about?
Did I mess that up is analog.
Oh nice.
Then put the is in front of it.
That's not going to help anyone.
Okay, and so this is ended down.
So we've basically got whatever the a button is the button that points
down.
So that's the down button on our controller.
In game update and render now seems to take one of these.
Okay.
So this is going to be a real straightforward thing here.
This is not going to be particularly difficult.
Basically.
The only thing that we're going to have to do is for keyboard inputs.
Going to be a little janky and I'll show you why in a second.
But basically, what we can do here for the most part is we can just go
ahead and take this game button State.
I mean, I'm sorry game input, stay thing here and we can just cheese
out.
Cheese out entirely.
And go up here and say, all right, when we go to actually do, you know
our message or whatever?
Here's our input State, everything gets initialized to 0.
Why not?
For now, we're going to go with that later and basically in here we
can sort of do all the stuff that we said we were going to do now.
We only get we are only taking one sample per frame right now.
So it's trivial to set up the things that we want to set up like
really really trivial.
That almond milk.
All right.
I need to get some kind of endorsement for almond milk.
I like it so much.
I don't know how you drink the store brand.
That's a proud.
No one's ever gonna give you your.
Not going to get this week deals, right?
You're not going to get the NASCAR stuff where you got like the
emblems on you for the store brand, right?
Like nobody that, that doesn't happen.
And I just drink the store brand.
So that's yeah.
What are you gonna do?
You got to sell out sometimes people.
That's the thing.
You got to sell out sometimes.
Alright.
So basically, we've got the d-pad up down left, right?
That's
Our stick situation.
So we basically going to have to handle these four are stick and and
take a look at those.
We have some stuff.
We need to think about in terms of how we're going to handle that, but
we'll think about that in a second namely, what the analog, how we
want to answer analog for something that could be using both the
analog or not analog hard to say, so we'll take a look at that in a
second.
We will also go here and do the button so the button should be pretty
easy.
Basically, we can just do something.
Like this.
So we can say for our input.
We have our button State and our button State just has this.
So the we have a half transition count and we have whether it ended
down.
This is our button.
Here are buttons direct.
There we go button.
Okay.
So basically what we need to do here is if the button ended down
really all we need to know is was it down before?
And if it was down before then there was a half transition.
If it wasn't down before then it wasn't
Really not a whole lot to it.
So basically all we actually need to do is say something like was it
down previously?
Right?
Like we don't know if it was down previously than the half transition.
Count is 1.
If it wasn't down previously, then it's 0 or I should say more
specifically if was it down?
Previously equals whether it's down now, right?
Something like that, right, make some sense.
Hopefully, that's pretty clear.
So, basically if the button was down,
SLI.
And now it's not that's a transition.
If it wasn't down previously, and now it is, that's a transition.
And then whether or not it ended down is just the state of the button.
So that's just going to be something that looks like that, right.
So what we can do we've got a lot of buttons here.
What I'd like to do is basically generalize that out so I don't have
to type it that many times.
So basically, what I'm going to do is I'm going to say something like
this.
I'm going to go up here and say, well, I've got an internal function
and that function is, you know, in
Maybe let's say, process process digital button or process xinput
digital button.
Let's say because that will basically.
Yeah, there we go.
So that will be our call here and it will take the information that we
need to do this press thing, and then we'll just call it for each one.
So this guy right here, I believe is the d word normally.
So this is the button bit that we've got button bit.
There we go.
We've got the button itself.
Which is this thing?
All right, this is the thing we're going to call this new state.
That's the result that we want to compute.
And then we're going to have to pass it.
The Old State as well because it needs to know whether it was down and
what's going on there, right?
That's going to have to happen.
So the half transition.
Count is basically going to be if the Old State ended down, right?
Let's just say and the new state ended down are not the same.
Then there was a transition, 1/2 transition up to down.
We're not pulling frequently enough to make that happen any
differently.
So in the future if we do up the polling rate, that's where we'll put
it and we can probably do that on a separate thread.
If we wanted to, I've never really tried that with xinput.
I'm not sure how effective it is, but maybe we can play with that and
see I don't know if you can turn on Buffer it in put in some of the
later versions of the xinput library, but
Like I said, I'm want to leave the platform layer.
A lot of room to get us better data if it can so that
Forms that do support higher polling rates will get that data.
So that's something I just want to make sure that we're future-proof
essentially down the road.
So the game can get that information.
All right.
So if it ended down is just whether or not this right here equals the
button bit, right?
Basically, that's that's all we're saying.
If the if that button bit was high, we are good to go.
I think that's about all we need.
That is, that is looking pretty straightforward to me.
So, this is New State and down new state half transition count, old
state looks good.
So now we've got this digital button thing here.
Oh, that's right.
And we need, we need the actual button state.
So X input button State.
We need to actually look at that as well.
So that's X input and state.
So, that's all we need.
I think, then we come down here and we actually go ahead and process
all these buttons.
So we've basically got a call here.
It's going to be passing the button bit that's appropriate for it and
the button state which is pad W buttons, right like that.
So we're going to do that.
Then we need to take our input.
So this is our controller and this is going to be a particular.
This is old controller, I guess, and it's state.
And then we're going to do a new controller and it's state and there
we go.
Go and then the button bit, right?
So then I just blow this out for everyone that we need.
Not particularly tough.
Basically.
I've got the a button there.
What else?
We got the B button as soon as I like over pronouncing the word button
button, right?
It's very satisfying, button button.
It says button, when you kind of swallow it, it doesn't sound as
proper, right?
It doesn't sound like, you really mean it.
You didn't really care about the button.
But you cared about the button, right?
You know what I'm talking about.
Anyway, so basically all I did here was I just cut and pasted that
code there so that we can basically crack things out.
Now.
I'm not actually tracking the start in the back button because I'm not
sure if we actually care about those.
So we're just going to leave those blank for now, nothing particular
happening there and then we got to do our Dead Zone processing up here
as well, which will do.
So basically what I need now is I need to get these things that I was
talking about here.
So
Old controller.
The state for the button is going to be each one of these.
We said that a button points downward on the controller.
Yes, it does.
So that's a, that's an old controller down.
Then we've got the Y button, which is the up button.
So that is this one, right?
Then we've got the x button, which is left, that's left, and we've got
the B button, which is right.
So there we go.
Now, we just basically craft those out and basically, all
Done.
Here is just made a reusable piece of code that we can call so left
shoulder as well.
That we can call to crack all our buttons for us.
So we don't have to keep cutting pasting the code, we can basically
just make this is like a table base with that goes through each one
for us and we're all good to go.
Right?
So that should be fine.
We just now need to get the controller State.
Now, fortunately, we know that basically this user X User maxed out
here.
What we want to do here is say controller Max controller count.
Oops, controller, count, equals X User Max count, right?
And I just
I want to make sure that if someday they add more controllers, so if
the mass controller count is actually higher than the number that are
in this right here then input, uh controllers recounts.
I will tell you how to write that function in.
Just one second.
If it's greater than that, then I want to basically make it be equal
to that.
This is just basically capping that, let's say, the X User Max count
was 12.
I don't want to get into a situation where I'm filling out right off
the end of this array.
By reading into the 5th, 6th 7th 8th and 9th, elements, and so on.
So I'm just going to try and cap it here and say it's the maximum
value is either the max count of X input or if that's too high for our
for our input will make a smaller one.
All right, so I'm going to tell you about how to write this array
count thing in a second here because actually see doesn't do that for
you.
It doesn't tell you how many elements there are in a static array and
not static array, but in an array that's fixed size.
It doesn't have a way to actually tell you that.
So you gotta write that yourself and I'll show you how in a
And it's real easy doesn't?
It's not hard and it can be done at compile time.
So anyway, we're going to do that.
We're going to go through the mask mask controller count.
We're going to go over each one of those and at the top of this, we're
basically going to say, well, alright, we've essentially got the game.
Controller input is the input that we're going to be looking at here
is the old controller is going to be old input, which will have to
save old input controllers, that and we'll do a new controller State.
There we go.
Is new input.
So I should actually also make this be whatever the one we're riding
into like that.
Let's do it that way.
New and put controllers, and we're going to take the controller index.
We're going to grab those out of there.
Right?
So we're going to get those and we're going to write into them.
There we go.
So that should give us what we wanted to do.
And then at the end of it, the end of it.
All, when we're done.
We're just going to swap those two.
So at the very end here, when we're done, we're going to want to swap
our input.
So we're going to want to do something like games swap, you know, swap
pointers or something like that.
Well, I don't know if I really want to do that and we'll make it a
macro for now.
This is the place where I really wish I had metaprogramming.
This is the place.
People often use templates.
I don't really like to use templates.
My metaprogramming sort of fellow, but if you have templates, you'd
use them right here.
I'll just write it myself for now and we'll think about what we want
to do for stuff like that, a little bit later on.
I'll put that actually up in here.
I was put it to do.
To do.
Swap min-max, macros.
Oh, yeah.
Alright.
So in here, we're just going to do the game controller input thing.
This game input temp, equals new input, new input, equals old input
old, input equals new input, and we will leave it at that.
Now, whether we need to clear these, I don't know to do Casey's.
Should I clear these here?
Possibly, we should.
And will think about that in a second.
But basically what I want to do now, like I said, is, I basically
They just want to have to input buffers and so I can look at whatever
the last one was because that's something that I wanted for button up
button down.
So basically what I'm going to do is I'm going to go look at that
input that game input thing and I'm basically just going to Define two
inputs right structures for the game input.
And I'm going to say that my new input one, right?
Equals input zero.
And I'm going to say that my old input equals input one like that.
And that way, I can just swap.
Op the the pointers to them later and it'll be fine.
Excuse your, max count.
Oh, did I accidentally delete something important from that?
Let me take a look at the xinput documentation.
Oh, well, you know what?
I could actually do, I could guess.
I guess correctly.
I'm gonna show you how to write that one in a second.
What is the problem here?
Can I state to button States star?
Okay, right.
These just need to pass the address of it because they are taking a
look at the address.
I could not, I could not bother to pass the address of the first one
for not writing into it.
But who cares?
All right, got that one game update and render is going to take the
new input always and then the array count.
All right, so I think
We are one second.
My screen has blanked out here, that will make it hard for me to read
the questions.
Let's see.
There we go.
Okay.
So for swapping.
That is that was, that's not, that's always good.
All right, for swapping.
I'm just doing a swamp here.
Basically, this is just we should have a function that does this.
What I wrote at the bottom here was I wanted to basically just ping
pong between two buffers.
I wanted to use one buffer and leave the old one around switch to
using the other buffer so that it would leave the previous one around.
So
We always have access to the last buffer.
We used in the previous frame.
So all I did was I can't, I can't say, you know, new input equals old
input because now when I say, I can't say there's nothing left it
over.
Wrote what the value of new the pointer to new input.
I have no pointer to it anymore.
Right?
So that that's a bummer right if that makes sense.
So basically what I had to do is I had the first snap a pointer to the
what new input was so that when I overwrite the pointer new input with
the pointer old input, I have the temp back.
Right.
Does that make sense?
Yeah, really?
What I wanted to do was say
New input old input, but I wanted to kind of wait till we actually
write a swap function to do that.
So I'm just doing that temporarily.
So now we have to go and take a look at this.
Okay.
What is the problem here?
Missing?
Semicolon.
Yes, it did.
Okay.
So now I just got to teach you how to write this guy, and then we have
the start of our input.
We might have to go a little long tonight.
Looks like we're a little behind schedule from where I would like to
be.
All right.
So basically defining this, this guy array count and it takes an
array.
Oops, takes an array.
All this does is it basically just ask for the size of the array,
whatever the array is.
That's the total size of the array.
And then we're going to divide by the size of the zeroth element of
that array because that tells us how many there are, right?
The total number of bytes used by an array divided.
By the number of bytes used for a single element that gives us how
Elements.
There were so that's all I'm going to do.
That's that's it.
I don't know if I can bracket this.
I'd like to bracket it.
I don't know if I can, I can so that's good.
Basically.
I didn't know, I didn't want to make sure I wanted to make sure that
everything bracketed because basically in a macro this thing is going
to get inserted into here.
And so if it was something like an expression that I didn't want the
02 like, you know, if it was if they passed in something like if I had
this and they pass in something like food plus bar, right?
I didn't want that to expand to Food Plus bar because
then the zeros only on the bar.
I wanted it to be expand to something like that.
So you kind of have to be careful in macros to always pair, you know,
put parentheses around more things than you would ever have had to in
another case.
All right.
So let's see where we're at here.
That was a lot of code very quickly, but it actually works just fine
and pushing the a button and it's going up there.
All right, so that works just fine.
So really the only problem that we've got right now is our stick and
so we've got to get our stick in there.
Now the stick has a thing called a dead zone and I guess I'm going to
have to defer that processing to later because we don't have time.
So we're still going to say to do.
And basically what I'm going to do is I'm just going to turn this
stick value directly into the input value that we're saying.
So basically the start X Min x max x and x thing.
I'm basically going to do those directly here real quick just so we
can be working.
And I guess we don't do we don't need any of these right now.
These are the d-pad.
So I'm going to say to do
D-pad and see what we want to do with that.
But basically the thumb this thing right here, I'm going to turn that
into a float.
I'm turn that into a float and I'm going to divide by well, so this is
a question.
I don't actually know what the min/max values are allowed to be for
this thing.
I'm going to assume it's 3655.
36 divided by 2.
I don't actually know.
Let's take a look and make sure we know what that actually is.
So we're going to go a little long here.
It's the end.
This will make up for it in Q&A.
Let's take a look.
I just want to pass.
Stick but I don't actually know what the values are.
So here they are this.
This is what the documentation claims and values are.
So it is the maximum range people of a short.
It looks like to me.
So basically, this is what we're what we've got.
Now, we have an interesting problem.
We have an interesting problem.
We want to normalize this value.
We want to normalize this value, so which do we divided by?
And the answer is, we actually want to do it accurately, be kind of
have to divide by different value, depending on which is positive or
negative because the range of - is greater than the Nate range of the
positive.
So technically right we should do something like
X equals whatever the value is like that /.
This.
If and only if if this is less than 0, right?
Like that, technically, that's what I want to do something like that.
Otherwise, if it's not, I actually want to do the same value, divided
by that, right?
So that right there.
What I'm trying to do is I'm trying to turn this integer value which
isn't particularly meaningful and is hard to use mathematically
because it's just some arbitrary range that just has to do with how
many bits are in a short, which is irrelevant.
I'm trying to change it into a number between negative 1 and 1.
And the reason that I want to do that that's called a normalized.
Number normalized is when you divide something to produce something of
unit length will be talking about these things.
A lot.
When we start talking about vectors.
Basically I want to do that because that way, it's always
Easy to take some other quantity, like the maximum movement, speed of
my guy, and multiply it, by the number between negative 1 and 1 and
get out how fast he should be moving.
Right?
So it's a nice normalized value.
It takes away the size of the thing on one side so that you only have
to be concerned with the size of it on the other side.
So I just want to normalize this value like that, right?
I want to do this to it.
Okay.
That's what I want to do.
And so then I'm just going to stuff a new controller for now.
I'm going to say that new controllers.
Start x equals old controllers and X.
That's pretty straightforward.
Same with this, right?
Like that.
And then I'm also going to say new controller, Min x, equals new
controller, Max x equals something, excuse me, equals and x.
And this is not exactly correct, but
You with that, to do min max macros, because we're going to need those
here.
And then that's actually all going to be equal to that x value that.
We just computed basically right here like that.
So, there's our x value.
And which one did I use in here in handmade?
I used ndex in NY.
I think I actually want these reversed.
I want that.
The blue offset to be on end X and I want the tone to be on end.
Why?
All right, so, I can change that to y41.
We're going to have to abstract those coalesce.
Those two Loops can't read it because it's underneath my lovely
talking head.
There we go.
All right, so that I hastily put that in there.
I didn't really check it.
So it might be kind of busted.
So I'm not actually sure if that's going to do anything at all.
In fact, it does not appear to do anything at all.
So that's not that good.
So let's double check.
What did I mess up?
Our let's see, put all those in there and X Y and Y, and that should
have done something.
But I'm going to go ahead and step through that just so I can see like
I said, when I kind of hastily bang something out like that,
especially when I'm talking, there's a high probability of messing up.
So I just want to take a look at what's going.
Going on in here.
So X and Y, are both the values that I think they should be actually.
So let's take a look at new controller.
There we go.
New controller.
Oh, duh.
We didn't set it to analog.
So obviously we also have to set it to analog in order to use the
analog path.
That was our only problem.
Probably I'm guessing.
So let's take a look.
Now if we've got something a little more reasonable.
There we go.
Yeah.
All right.
One last thing I messed up is of course, we got to preserve the - in
there.
So basically we got to have got to get rid of that negative, that
would dividing by a negative, would flip the sign.
And we didn't want to flip the sign.
We still want the sign to be - if we didn't.
That's what we should have done.
All right.
There we go.
And we are back.
We are back.
Lovely.
So that's it.
That's all I wanted to do.
Just get that stuff working.
We want to do min max macros and tomorrow we'll have to also do dead
zone processing.
Finally.
Oh, actually, I guess I've already got this.
So let's say that we actually want to do those tomorrow because we're
going to need them.
We can't put it off any longer because we're asking to be using this
input for real stuff and we have to do the min/max macro.
So we'll do those tomorrow.
Otherwise, I think
Are good for the day.
Ladies and gentlemen, we have successfully gotten to the point where
we are almost almost.
At a reasonable platform layer.
We're pretty close.
By next week.
I'm going to say.
We will actually be game programming.
I think next week.
I want to take some time to kind of go tighten stuff down.
Fix some stuff that we kind of left kind of hanging for a while.
But that is pretty darn good.
13 days in tomorrow.
We will have memory as well.
So that will be 14 days in and, and that is just not a lot of
programming.
When you consider how much talking I've been doing and explaining a
stuff, I mean,
Are talking about something on the order of two hours of code.
Total to write the entire abstraction layer for a win32 prototyping
thing.
That is pretty darn good.
Do not let anyone ever tell you that it takes too long to make this
stuff from scratch.
That was just not that much.
I mean, it just isn't that much really when you when you factor in all
the stuff and how quickly this has gone even with explanations.
It's kind of crazy.
But anyway, thank you.
Very
Very much, of course for joining us.
It is time.
Now for the Q&A.
We didn't really even go over that much.
We got 5 x 5 extra minutes.
We took that's not much.
So let's do a good 25 minutes of Q&A now or what we'll go five minutes
long in the Q&A.
If we need to to remember to put see Mira Tori somewhere in your
question because I have a thing that just shows that so that people
can talk on the stream without me having to see it as and get confused
about where the questions are.
So question time is now
Let's see.
When normalizing the thumbstick value is it worse to just add 32 768
then multiply it by 2 over 65535 then subtract 1.
I don't like the necessary if statement personally.
I want to say,
So, the re the aunt, the full answer is I don't know because I've
never thought about that before.
I want to say.
If you do that, please make sure it doesn't offset your zero value.
A fractional amount in One Direction.
If fractional amount down, do you know what I'm saying?
Because because your range doesn't have a mid point.
Exactly.
And you really care that 0 maps to 0.
So so I don't know that there's anything wrong with what you're
suggesting.
But if you could, please first check.
If you don't want to do what I did.
If you could please check or you know, what I should do here to, I
should say to do collapse to single function, please double check that
it leaves 0 where it should be.
That's the
That sort of thing.
Or or don't care about zero and let the dead zone.
Do The Dead Zone after you do the thing you were talking about, do the
dead zone afterwards to suck up to make the 0 value, really big, and
then, it wouldn't matter that.
You had a slight bias in One Direction, right?
Gasps blizzard nitpick, but is it a bit misleading that the half
transition count is 0 or 1 rather than an actual count.
I'm sorry.
I'm not sure what you mean by that.
We are only pulling once a frame, so we can't actually count yet.
In order to count, this more accurately.
We would have to have a higher polling rate.
So until we increase the polling rate, we I don't I'm not sure what
you mean.
Let's see.
Will you completely ignoring platform code for most of the rest of the
series?
Yes, there there will be a couple times when we'll do more platform
work.
Basically when we do our resource system, that'll be platforming.
And then when we do our rendering stuff, that'll be platforming, our
Hardware rendering, but other than that we won't be doing platform
stuff anymore.
And yes, obviously for Mac, Linux ports, and Raspberry Pi.
That's all platform stuff, but that's way down the road.
Can you describe the struct inside of the Union in more detail?
Yeah, that's a good point.
I totally just, I was thinking, oh, I'll explain this later and then I
never explain it later.
So let's explain it.
So basically what happens is anytime you want, right?
You can create a struct and we've been doing this all the time, right?
We can create a struct and we can just shove some stuff in it, right?
So, I can create this struct called Foo, and I can create this struct
called bar, right?
That's totally good to go.
And we both were
No, we were kind of comforting with these.
Now.
We've used them through the whole series.
I hope most people would know what happened there, right?
but,
Let's say that I wanted to now include the stuff from this struct in
this struct here, but I didn't actually want to have to use.
So, okay.
So I'll give you a concrete example.
I could do this right now.
All of the stuff that's in a foo is also in a bar, but to access it.
I have to do my bar dot my fuu DOT the thing, right?
It's I gotta use the foo every time so it's that, you know, it's
It's down its left.
Right?
But what I can do as well is if I actually have it declared inside,
right?
This is what that would look like declared inside.
If I actually have it declared inside, I can opt to just drop all of
the Declarations from it, entirely like this and then, it's
essentially just a pass-through, just whatever was in.
There is just up at the at the higher up in the higher one.
So now I could just do barred up.
Bar dot down bar dot left.
Now that doesn't really matter much because you just say well, why
wouldn't you just do this?
Right?
And the answer is because of unions.
So what a union does is a union allows you to put two things in the
same place, right?
That's a union.
It basically, says, I only want 32 bits and I'm going to access X or
Y, depending on which one.
So this is like integer.
It's probably say, integer X or float X.
I'm going to access whichever one I wanted and you have to really know
what you're doing here.
If you do stuff like this because they're the same memory.
So if you write a float to float X and then try to read it as an
integer, it's going to be the, the bits of the float in an integer,
which is not the number.
It's some other thing, right, but that's what a union loves you do it,
lets you to use the same memory for multiple things.
So all I did was use the anonymous struct inside.
A union to, basically, let these names all exist in the same places,
this array.
So we could alternatively, we could basically say button.
Zero.
And that would be the same memory as up, right?
And buttons, one is in the same memory as down, so it just gives me
two ways of accessing and code the thing.
So if I want something that just Loops over all the buttons, I can do
that trivially or if I want something that accesses the buttons by
name, I can do that as well.
Furthermore.
I use the exact same trick again on the union because normally the
union would have a name, but I just did decided not to name it either.
So that all this stuff is just in up in the outer game controller.
And you can just say, you know, controller dot up instead of having to
do controller dot, some Union name dot up some struck name, right?
That would be way more verbose and not actually meaningful because I
don't care.
Hopefully, that makes some sense.
Let's see.
um,
Does it give any problems with capturing inputs over time?
When due to some circumstances from Windows?
The game lags and the frame time base expands?
I'm not sure exactly what your question is.
But what I can say is like Windows is not a real time.
Operating system is not by any stretch.
It's not even a soft real-time operating system.
Let alone a hard real-time operating system.
And what that means is that, yeah, it's actually not that great of an
operating system for games, because sure stuff can happen all the time
in Windows, that causes our game to lag out.
And if that point
All bets are off, you know, who knows?
What was when the display got updated.
And when we don't know how to sink when this play gets updated with
when the input samples are even if we were sampling the input.
There's a lot of bad stuff that can happen.
There can be USB latency on the USB bus or stuff like this.
All sorts of things can happen, the system as a whole is not set up
for us to be really accurate and that's just the facts of life.
When we're on the Raspberry Pi, I think we may be able to use the gpio
pins and the outboard I/O.
Board to make a real joystick that actually works that we can pull at
a high frequency and it's super exact.
So I'm kind of interested in those sorts of things.
But until we get on a platform that we control entirely, there's you
just going to have to live with the fact that it's a little sloppy and
there's nothing you can do about it.
I mean, well, there's something could do you cannot make it worse
base?
We're going to try.
Like I said to kind capture all the nuances of the input as much as
possible.
And maybe we'll pull a little, will try not to make it worse.
But I guess what I'm saying is, there's a minimum bar there and
windows sets that minimum bar pretty sloppy.
So you're never no matter what you do, you're never going to get too
far through that slop because there's always, you know, someone runs
Adobe Acrobat in the background doesn't realize it and it's sucking
down 25% of the CPU and randomly inserting spikes this like, who knows
what could happen, right?
It's banana cakes.
Let's see.
I can't find all the questions.
There's so many of them.
Them.
I got, I got nothing.
There's so many questions.
A lot of them aren't about the code.
Let's see.
To Vault, eval Amo.
Your normalizing code has an error.
They both divided by positive.
You should normalize thusly.
I don't know that.
I do have an error.
This is correct.
As far as I know.
So if the value is negative, we divided by the maximum negative value
and we want the thing to be -1 at maximum.
So this is negative.
So a negative divided by a positive is a negative.
That's right.
This is the positive Branch.
So a positive divided by a positive is also positive.
So it's also correct.
So basically this is the most correct way to normalize as far as
I don't think you can normalize any more correctly than this.
I think the slightly less correct way.
Potentially would be the way that misc Annex or mechanics, or whatever
had suggested.
I think that way would be possibly a little faster due to the
branchless.
I'm not sure.
And so, if I was going to be concerned with speed, I would probably do
it the other way, but then again, this is, I mean, even caring about
the optimization of this is crazy.
There is, it doesn't matter the memory.
Us here are going to be all that you care about the nothing.
This computation is so minor in a relevant that even thinking about
the performance, doesn't make any sense to me.
So yeah, so I think this is the most correct way you could do it.
I'm not sure if there is a more correct way.
But if there is someone else could say, it's certainly I don't think
the one you're talking about though.
Let's see.
So many questions to read through what happens if there's a name
conflict between struct scope and a non Nest instruct as far as I know
it.
An error and I can try that for you.
I don't think I've ever actually caught in this error myself.
But yeah, so if I do a struct foo or a union Foo as what we were doing
before, and I do in X and then I do struct float X, I pretty much
think you just get an error.
Yeah.
Basically you just you just can't do that and you don't have to worry
about it because the compiler will just, it'll just catch it for you.
It's not an area that will ever show up in your, in your compiled
code.
It's
totally caught at compile time.
Do you plan on abstracting the input more?
For example, instead of having a player respond to a button, press
have them respond to an action.
That is bound to a button or stick.
No, I don't think we're going to do re bindable controls.
In other words.
I don't think I'm going to let the person bind like a to the thing
that used to be bound to the Y button, I think.
And and that's that's not because I think that you shouldn't do that
or that like I have that you that there's a coding reason not to do it
if you want.
Ahead and extend handmade here at everybody will controls be my guest.
But the reason I don't want to do it is I don't like games where I
boot them up and there's all these options.
I'd much rather prefer to just reboot the game and it's the game and
there's no options.
The options are set to the way they should be set and off you go.
Because otherwise what happens is if there's an option screen, I go
start thinking about how to refine the controls.
And I don't really want to think about Brandon controls, and I want
the controls to be so simple, that people wouldn't have to remind the
controls.
Like it's just like, yeah,
There's four buttons and the 4-way stick and the buttons.
Do something that's in a direction or something.
So, there's like, there's no way you'd ever remind them different
differently.
I like that better.
So I'm going to try and be more on that side of the philosophical
fence, where the controls are dead simple, and you'd never have to
rebuy them rather than let's do a whole system for a binding, the
controls and make a pretty interface with people, don't mind the fact
that they have to rebuy in the controls and whatever.
Why is game update and render internal when they designed to be called
for the pipe?
Where all our functions are internal?
They are all internal because we only have one translation unit.
So everything has static in front of it effectively because that's
just faster for the compiler because it knows it's never going to have
to do any external linking for anything because everything is all
pound included into one file.
We're just compiling as one big file.
So everything is internal.
Let's see.
So left-handed people can't play with a Gamepad though.
They'd never be able to push the buttons.
I mean, maybe if you say you want to do re bindable keys for
left-handed, people on a keyboard then maybe that makes some sense.
But on a joystick, there's no I mean like I'm holding a Gamepad.
There's no way there's no buttons on the left side of this thing.
So there'd be no way to actually play it.
In a left-handed way.
And if that makes any sense.
Let's see.
When we decide to actually remove, all to dues in your code, so we'll
probably never remove all the two dudes in the code.
They'll probably keep sort of piling up.
And then we'll do kind of ways where we cut them down next week.
I want to do a pass on some of the to dues that are in there.
And so next week, probably will do a cleanup week where we go through
and tighten everything down.
I want to go through and get the audio sync, proper and stuff like
that.
So, next week, we'll probably will get rid of some
See.
Let's see.
And by the way, like I said, I'm not saying there's anything wrong
with her binding Keys.
It's just it's my game and I don't really want to go down that road.
Right?
Like re bindable keys are decision that.
The designer makes that they put in the game and you can also have a
way to rebind Keys, external to the game like with a text file or you
can run utilities that ribeye the case and that's fine.
But putting them in the game is just something I just don't want to
do.
I don't like that and so I'm not going to do that.
And if anything, what I would do is if there was a left, right?
Russell that had to happen for left-handedness, which I don't even
know if there is because I don't think of when I think of the kind of
game, this is I don't think of there being a bonus to one hand of the
other you need to use both hands effectively.
So I don't think there's any way that a left-handed person can can get
a disadvantage or an advantage.
It's like you need both hands.
So basically what I would say is that I if I was gonna do something
that I put it in game more so that like when I said like move the guy
around whichever thing they tapped, that's what I'll make be movement
or
Like this, but yet.
How is the old controller persisted across frames?
So that was actually just like I said, it was just kind of cheese.
I didn't do anything.
I just put it outside the game Loop.
So we come in here.
We open the window.
We allocate space on the stack by just like saying, I want to inputs
and then I pointed one pointer at the first one and one pointer at the
second one.
Then, inside the loop.
We just write to one of them.
We write two new input and we look at old input, right?
And then at the end, we swap the two pointers so that we're pointing
new input at the old input and open at the new input.
So that the new input effectively becomes the old input that we would
compare against in the next Loop through.
So, the way it persists is just because it's declared outside the
loop.
It's on the stack before we enter the loop and just stays on the
stack.
Do do, do do.
Will the windows callbacks for keyboard inputs required?
Great deal of extra work for you to implement.
No, and I would like to get to that tomorrow.
Pretty simply like basically.
All we're going to do here is inside these.
We're going to set the think the same things that we were going to set
before we could even probably do that very quickly.
The problem is assigning controllers to it.
So I'm probably just going to let it be controller zero right now as
well.
So both of them go to the same.
Roller for testing purposes.
The problem is the is analog thing.
Like I'm not sure how to set that.
Exactly.
So we'll have to sort of think about how we get the keyboard input in
there.
Maybe I'll just put it on controller, one, always and only sample the
first controller here or something like that.
I don't know.
We got to think about how we're going to sign controllers.
It's real easy on a console when you know that there's four slots and
the controllers go into those slots, but on a computer it's kind of
wonky.
Like if there's four controllers plugged into the computer which there
could be and there's a keyboard.
Which controllers are, which is the first one you hit, like it's kind
of confusing how you want to do that.
In terms of ux.
It's not hard to program once you've decided what should happen, but
it is kind of hard to decide what should happen.
So something like that.
What about people who only have left arms?
Will you can actually play the game if you only have left arms because
it requires two hands to play.
Unfortunately, that's just the way the game works.
Let's see.
I do not have any more questions that I'm seeing, will we eventually
be using a timer to pull the controller input or just a thread?
So we can't really use a timer depending on what you mean by that
because well,
So, I don't know of maybe you could use a timer.
I don't know of any timer in Windows, that's accurate enough for that.
So, I would say we would have to use a thread on Windows on other
operating systems.
There may be timers that are accurate Enough by don't know if Windows,
especially Windows XP, which will be our minimum Target.
I don't know if there would actually be a tart a way to do that.
We would probably do something with a separate thread hard to say, we
may also be able to do some
Good stuff with xinput.
I don't know.
We'll see what I don't know yet.
That's that's to be determined.
Time to compare One Way Ticket.
One millisecond resolution.
Yeah, so timer begin period.
One might ticket one millisecond resolution, but it might not.
Like I said, it's it means that you might be able to do a one sec Ms.
Sleep.
It doesn't guarantee that you will.
It could put you to sleep for far.
Longer than that, so it's hard to say if you really wanted to be mr.
Doesn't care about the CPU.
You just spin lock on the pole.
But yeah, I don't know what.
We'll look into that.
I think we basically got all the questions trying to see if I missed
anything.
I think we've got all the questions.
Got three minutes left.
Someone asks have I done much physics?
Coding?
Does that say have I done much finished cutting related to games or
otherwise?
Yes.
I have done a ton of physics coding.
In fact, I worked on one of the first game physics engines for
definition six.
Unfortunately, it never shipped in an actual product.
But yes, I did a ton of physics coding back then.
It is the only reason I really no real physics code instead of like
sort of wrong game physics code.
Not that.
We really need real physics code for this game, but it's why.
I know, for example, I would know how to program angular momentum,
which almost no game physics ever has, unless it uses a real game
physics engine, but that's the only reason I knew that because Chris
Hecker was really into it at the time and so I learned a bunch of that
stuff at the time.
Would you be fine with people using the platform as a base for making
their own games with attribution?
No, not until it's released.
That that's actually answered in here.
You can see on the handmade hero thing.
There's the source code.
It says right here.
How will the source code will be licensed?
You can go read that if you want to.
And so basically all the source code.
You still have to get a license from us.
If you want to use it until two years after the game is done, or the
game is released after that.
It becomes public domain and you
Do whatever you want with it, including use it without attribution.
So you will not even have to give attribution to it after that
two-year time period.
But up until then you will have to get a license from us.
That does not mean we wouldn't give you a license.
If you ask her when it just means you have to talk with us.
And we will have to agree that your project is something we're okay
with before.
You could do that.
But yet, obviously this is a learning project.
So the goal is at some point and it will be at least two year.
It will be at least before that two-year clock.
The to your clock is the maximum that time it will all be released in
the public domain.
So, at that point, after we've basically been able to recoup the money
on the game.
Hopefully, if we're lucky, then, you know, we'll release in the public
domain.
So, everyone could just party on it, and you can do whatever you want.
You can make commercial games with it.
You don't have to credit us, you have to do anything against go to
town.
How much will you need to explore other platforms for and doing what
the abstraction API will look like?
I won't have to explore them at all.
Pretty much because I've done so much cross-platform programming.
So I just know the stuff we're doing.
I work mostly.
But yeah, if you were doing this yourself and you had no experience,
what you'd want to do is not what we're doing.
You wouldn't want to do one platform and then make the game, you'd
want to do a bunch of platforms with a Prototype game and get, you
know, all the platform stuff, straightened out.
And then be like, okay, we're good to go and go forwards.
That's what you want to do.
I think we're basically out of time.
The stream has ended according to the clock.
Let's see if there's anything else.
What kinds of numerical methods are used in game physics.
How is that a question related to today's code?
How you had to know when you type that in, that was not related to
today's code because we haven't done any physics in today's code.
There was no physics in there.
There.
We aren't even passing the time.
You don't even passing t t by definite physics is by definition, the
computation of what happens to objects in the game.
Game over a Time.
Step T.
And we're not even passing a tea.
How could we have physics questions?
How
What can you do to people?
What can you do?
All right.
Let's see.
So think we are done with all the questions.
I think we will are done with everything.
I don't see anything left.
So I am going to call that done ladies and gentlemen, if you would
like a copy of the source code for now and forever more, you can
pre-order here.
Like I said, the license is described down here.
It's also in the actual game proper.
And yeah, for people who didn't know about this or didn't read this.
It is true.
The source code will eventually be released in the public domain.
So if you are thinking of taking the final stuff and basing your own
game on it, that will
The thing that is possible, you can contact us and get a license to it
earlier if you really need one, but you can also just know that that
it will be in the public domain two years after.
So you could start building things on it.
And by the time your game was done, you'd be okay with it probably.
But anyway, if you want a copy source code to follow it, home, that
comes with any pre-order of the game.
Just gets the source code.
You could do that here.
If you need to discuss things ask questions, or just generally want to
chat with other people about handmade hero.
The news and forums buttons will let you do that.
That.
And of course, the video archived on YouTube is also there.
There's also a great resource put up by some people from the community
who do an awesome job at it called the episode guide which has older
episodes annotated so you can go in there and get them annotated.
That's really great.
Take a look at these guys up here who have done all the hard work to
their you can say thanks to them on Twitter, which would be very nice
because they put together some really amazing stuff.
So anyway, thank you all for joining us for another episode of
handmade Hero.
Please come back.
Tomorrow, 8:00 p.m.
Pacific Standard time when we will be finishing up our input code and
moving on to memory and perhaps,
We'll pass the time down as well.
So that should all be tomorrow.
If not, it will spill over a little bit into Friday, but that should
be basically it for abstraction layer, and then we can move on next
week, to cleaning things up.
Before we start coding, the game, which is pretty exciting.
So hope to see you all here tomorrow.
Thank you very much for joining us and have a fantastic rest of your
Thursday.
Sorry, your Wednesday night and your Thursday day.
Thanks, everyone.