He looks like the stream begins now or so says the little timer and I
think we know from experience.
The timer is never wrong.
So, welcome back everyone to handmade here.
I hope you have had a good weekend this week, in our quest to build a
complete game from scratch.
We are going to be getting some user input and getting sound output
working.
If all goes according to plan, now that there is much of a plan.
But if all goes according to what we would like to get done, let's put
it that way.
So if you are following along with today's lesson and you have
pre-ordered the game on handmade hirota, or you can go to your zip
file and unpack the day 5 source code.
That is what we are starting with here on day 6.
Now.
The thing that I want to talk about today is basically how we are
going to get input.
Basically from a Gamepad, if that makes sense.
And also how to get it from the keyboard.
So, if we take a look here, I'm going to search for something called X
input.
So, you can see what I'm talking about.
X input is basically,
The current way that you have to use to get the kind of gamepads that
almost, everyone actually uses with games now, which are like Xbox 360
controllers.
Microsoft for whatever reason, they introduced their own sort of
interface layer for getting controller.
Input was called direct input and then they turned right around a
couple of years later and decided that they were just going to ignore
that entirely and make them to a whole new one called X input.
And and so that is what you use now.
And they're not really, they're not even really compatible ux input
control.
Ours will show up in direct input, but I guess you can't send Rumble
messages out to them potentially and also, you can't get the audio
handle for outputting, audio to the controller's plug, these sorts of
things.
So if you want to support gamepads properly, you pretty much have to
use x and because that's what everyone has you can go Implement direct
input.
If you want to be able to support kind of Legacy controllers that
maybe don't have an X input driver, but on the whole you're you're
pretty much going to have to support xinput at a minimum.
And now what x is
It looks like thankfully.
It is actually one of the simplest apis to use on Windows.
It is very, very simple.
You can actually see, I don't know which one of these has in the msdn
has a good introduction, but I think basically any of these probably
has a good.
Yeah, here you go.
So basically, all you really have to do is code that looks like this.
You Loop over the number of controllers that there are you go ahead
and you get the state of each controller.
And the state of the controller is basically a big old structure that
just has
All the stuff that you might want to know about the GamePad.
And so, it is, it is really absolutely trivial to do, and we will be
doing it today.
Hopefully, we won't hit any snap poop snafus, but that is basically,
it.
Now in the old days.
If I remember correctly.
You couldn't actually include an X input header file.
That's, that's what I want to say.
I want to say that was true.
But I guess I'm going to assume that maybe that is not true anymore
and that we'll be able to, to sort of directly include it, but I'm not
actually sure.
So I'm going to go ahead.
Fire up the Max and we're going to see basically what what our what
our situation is here in the modern world of programming.
So I'm going to go into handmade.
I'm going to launch the trustee emacs that that is, you know, so he's
our trusty editor on every platform a little bit slow a little bit
aging, but it gets the job done, most of the time.
And I'm just going to see straight up.
If I can include, I believe it was X input dot h, because I don't even
know if that exists on platforms and it does.
So basically, X input dot h,
Holds the definitions of all of the stuff that we actually want to use
to get our to get our input.
So what we're going to do is we're going to go down here.
Now, if you remember we have a game loop, it's really kind of a very
beginning of the game loop.
I mean it barely does anything, but we have.
When nonetheless, we go through here and we process our Windows
messages, then we do our rendering and then we go ahead and lift that
rendering to the screen.
So what we're going to do is right here after we get our messages
because these are messages that are going to come in to do keyboard as
well.
A keyboard will
Through here, the X input is a polling based API, which basically
means that it only gives us back the state of the keyboard Sarah, the
state of the, the, the controller when we actually asked for it.
So we have to ask for it at some point, and that some point is going
to be here right after we do this.
Now, something that we should note and I'm going to put in a little to
do about this because we may decide that we want to do this later.
Should we pull this more frequently, so what you have to
And about input devices is there's two methods of getting input from
input devices.
Often times.
There's interrupt and pulling sort of a vague way to think about them
basically, but an interrupt based input scheme is one where whenever
the controller itself, whenever the thing that you're actually getting
input from the device, the external device.
Whenever that device actually needs to tell you that something
happened, like something changed a button, got pressed.
The state of the stick, wiggled, something like that.
It will actually send you the data.
Right.
So basically, it's controlling in some sense when you need to wake up
and process it.
Now that sort of thing doesn't really happen very much anymore.
But in the old days, I'd actually used to be literally true.
There used to be actual interrupts that would happen on the CPU.
That would actually say, hey, this device has something something to
say.
Well, that doesn't really happen very much anymore.
For the most part, what happens is things are either pulled or they're
kind of a network.
He's sort of thing where they kind of send packets to you and those
packets kind of get buffered up, or those sorts of things.
So, in some sense, it's sort of like an interrupt, but it instead of
actually interrupting you.
You're reading,
Really just reading a stream.
Either way since this API involves us actually pulling the MPX input
controller and asking for it State.
We may get into a circumstance where we want to pull it more
frequently than every frame now.
I don't know that that's necessarily true.
60 frames a second worth of polling.
May be plenty or it may not be.
And the only real way to know is by sort of playing with it and
testing, there is some stuff we can do inside xinput to actually kind
of get a feel for how frequently we're pulling it, relatively to how
frequently it would like to be pulled and things like that.
That, but we'll get to that later because right now, we're certainly
not gonna care about that tour.
Actually tuning doing the like real, real, serious final stuff for the
windows layer, which we won't do up front.
Those will be things.
We do kind of more towards the end of handmade hero.
So, inside the documentation here, you can see I've got the different
functions.
You can see that X input is a pretty small API, and that's a pretty
good thing.
Basically, that is that is what you want.
So looking at it basically XM
Put get state is primarily what we need?
Get xinput.
Get state is the thing that actually Returns the state to us.
So, all we really have to do is we just have to call this, but we have
to call it with this thing called DW user index, which if you look at
the documentation here, it says the index of the users controller.
So, as you know, Xbox controller is only allow for controllers.
They've got those little sort of quadrants, but they fill in, so
there's only four that are allowed to be there.
But if I remember correctly, there actually is somewhere in here.
Are there is a pound of find Define that says, how many there are?
I want to say that.
That is true, but I don't see it listed here.
It just says a value from 0 to 3, which is kind of unfortunate other.
It is X User Max count.
So that documentation was just a little stale, you can see that this
is basically the loop that you want.
Here you go over each of the controllers and in case they ever
increment, the number of controllers that are necessary.
We know that we would get them all.
By doing this.
So we can just basically use that power to find right there that lets
us.
No.
No, I don't really love I necessarily.
So I'm just going to go ahead and say that this is the controller
index.
Just so we know we're talking about here, and then I'm going to go
ahead and expand this out.
So, there we go.
Now, we are looping over all the controllers that we might possibly
have.
And now, we are going to pass that controller index, and we are going
to ask it to give it back the state of our controller.
So this is the state right here and we pass an address of that thing
and it will fill out that address for us.
So they're, there we go.
That's basically, that's basically xinput.
Now.
It's going to return to us a piece of information.
That's whether or not the controller existed.
I believe.
If
Not very much an error.
So let's take a look at controllers, not connected.
So basically, if it equals error success, you got to love things like
error success.
If it equals error success, then that means this controller is plugged
in.
And if it doesn't equal that if it equals any other error message,
then that means that the controller is not available now, maybe that
could be an error, maybe that could be that it's just not plugged in,
but basically, what happens,
Is we can't actually do anything with controller here?
So that is actually information that we need.
For example, we may want to show in the user interface that a
controller has been unplugged.
We may want to take action on that.
So this is not necessarily just an error.
This is actually a case that we want to handle in the future right
now.
We don't need to because we don't have any logic but in the future, we
may want to we want to handle that.
Okay.
So all we're going to do here is we're going to actually look at this
controller state, right?
We're going to take a look at the sort of things that we can get in
it.
And if we go in here, I guess.
Let's see if I've got a good.
Where's a good?
There?
It is.
X, x input, get state.
So you can see what it's got here.
It basically has a packet number.
And again, remember when I was saying just just a few minutes ago.
I said that basically, there is a concept of the device, sending you
pieces of information, perhaps or being pulled at a certain frequency
and that sort of stuff.
Well, this packet number is basically sort of increments every time we
know about the state of the joystick changing.
Now, I don't really know since, I don't know the internals of how
expert input works.
I don't know whether it's the driver, that's thinking about that.
So that the driver
Internally as pulling it more frequently and incrementing that or
whether the controller itself actually manages that, I suspect.
It might be the controller.
I'm not really sure doesn't matter.
Either way point being when we pull the state, we get back a number
that basically says, what where we are in the series of State changes,
for this particular controller.
So if we missed a bunch if, if, you know, if we pull it and it says
50, we pull it again and it says 30, we know that there's a bunch of
states.
The controller went through, baby buttons, that got pushed or the
stick got twiddled, that we never actually saw and that would be an
indication that we might be pulling it too.
Infrequently.
Now, it doesn't necessarily mean that because it may be that it just
gets sample that is really high rate.
And we don't actually care about that because the user can't actually
press and unpressed the button at a rate that that that's that faster
things like this.
So we don't actually know but at least it'll give us a little bit of
an information, you know, sort of an informational boost, right?
So basically all we're going to do here is we're going to say, okay.
Roller, you know when we when we get back we're going to get that
thing.
So in the future, maybe we'll take a look at that.
I'm going to I'm going to say that DW packet number.
I'm going to actually write that in here as a thing to maybe look at
see if packet number increments to rapidly and then we're going to
look at basically this Gamepad piece.
So I'm going to snap a pointer off of this thing.
So we don't have to keep talking about controllers, state DOT Gamepad.
I'm going to actually grab xinput gamepad.
Add star pad equals the address of that, and that's just just
syntactic convenient.
So we can just talk about it like this.
So the X input Gamepad is the only structure we've got to find
currently.
As you can see.
It's got a bunch of fields that correspond to the things on an Xbox
Gamepad, shocking.
I know.
But that is all that happens.
So w buttons is basically a bit field, you know, those bit Fields
again.
I think it's funny because people in the intro to CS stream or asking
how often you do bit manipulation and I'm like, we do it all the time.
And man, we have
Done it a lot and all we're doing is implementing the windows layer,
right?
We've already done a ton so that W buttons filled.
It's basically ordered an order to
Version of these field.
Feels right here.
Now.
It's a word, which means 16-bit.
That's windows for 16-bit Value.
B.
8-bit value 8-bit value, short 16-bit signed, right?
So we've got the buttons and the buttons include the d-pad.
Those are considered buttons actually, since they can either, you
know, I'm actually know whether buttons because they're mutually
exclusive, you can't really press the d-pad like left and right
buttons at the same time.
But there you go.
That's how they work.
We've got the start back, the thumb buttons.
Like when you press them down the shoulder buttons,
And you got the, a b x and y and then you've also got on these things,
the triggers are analog.
So, you know, how far the user press them down.
So those are actually B that range from 0, to T 5, depending how press
they are.
And then you've also got to xy's for the to thumbsticks the left and
right thumbstick.
So, you know, it's real self explanatory.
There's almost nothing that you that you really need to learn here.
I mean, it should be real self explanatory.
I'm gonna take a little almond milk it and then we're going to take a
look at these.
Okay.
So basically what we're going to do here is we just want these things,
you know, out and the question of what sort of stuff.
I actually want to get for this game.
You know, this game is kind of an old school game.
So I suspect that mostly what we're going to be looking at is those
four buttons?
As I really don't know that we're going to want to do much of them,
the four buttons and maybe the two shoulders.
Yeah, like the two shoulders, these buttons.
Maybe the start and end.
I don't know the d-pad.
And I'm thinking, most of the stuff you wanted here.
Triggers is probably not going to be very useful for an old-school
game.
I don't, I don't suspect because, you know, if you're playing an old
person as game or something like that, you probably didn't have a lot
of like first person shooting and that sort of stuff.
So I don't know that those will be very useful in these.
Well, I don't know depends on whether we want to the reason to support
these guys, even though we're probably, you know, not going to want
them as much for an old school game.
Is that?
Well, I think we all know the Xbox 360 game.
Pads d-pad was not that great.
So if you're talking about,
The Xbox one you could probably play on the d-pad and be very happy,
but we may need to support the thumbsticks just because that d-pad on
the 360 was so bad.
So it looks like most of the stuff we're actually going to want.
We don't actually need to do anything with it yet because we don't
have much to find.
But basically what we're going to do is we're just going to go in here
and sort of Mark out the stuff that we actually care about.
So we care about these things, we care about basically whether this is
down, so I'm just going to kind of line these up here and then we'll
we'll take a look at them.
As we go.
So let's just take a, let's just take all the things that we need.
So we want d-pad up.
We want down, we want left.
We want right?
We kind of want to see these things.
We want.
Start and back, that's good.
We're going to want left thumb and right thumb left thumb and right
thumb.
And we are going to want a b X and Y.
I think.
Oh no.
But we're going to want shoulder.
We don't actually want thumb and I think we want thumb is always hard
to press for me a b x y.
There we go.
Okay.
So we've got up down left, right?
Start back shoulder, left shoulder, right?
Shoulder a b, X and Y.
So, yes, we'll call these a button.
Just to be clear about what that is.
There we go.
So that would basically decrypt into boolean's, right?
All the things we might want.
I don't think we want those triggers, but we are going to want that
left thumb.
I think we're going to want that left, thumbstick.
So we're also going to want, hear something.
That's basically a in 16 of the, I guess, the stick left, which I say,
stick horizontal.
I guess would be it or stick ax.
Maybe let's call it and stick.
Why are the two things that we are going to want?
So we're going to want to grab those out of the PAD as well as thumb.
And ask them why.
Now the question of whether we want the right thumbstick or not.
I think we're going to need those buttons.
So no one's really gonna be able to use it so we can just leave it
there.
So that is basically as far as I know.
I'm trying to remember if there's anything else that we actually need.
What did I do?
Oops, that d-pads not supposed to be there.
Trying to think if there's anything else we need.
I didn't bother to delete the d-pad part of this, which is kind of a
mistake.
There we go.
I'll try the others, anything we actually need.
Need.
But I don't think there really is, that's probably all we need to get
out of these and we're going to get him for each of the four
controllers and I will have to decide whether we actually need
multiple controllers in the future, but that's basically what we're
doing there.
And the thing that you have to notice now is it xinput?
Get state is again.
Something that we have to link with.
Now there's a little bit of a complication here.
And I was trying to decide whether I wanted to handle this today or
handle this in the future.
And I think, based on the time that we've got here.
I think I probably want to handle it today.
That's my thought, because we've got a lot of time and it's not that
much work to get that xinput get state.
So you'll note that we've got what we had many times before here,
unresolved, external symbol X input.
KET State referendum function when main right.
And so basically that's exactly what we were talking about before.
And as you know, I
Taught you what to do in this circumstance, you basically just need to
look at the function wherever that function is.
And inside that function.
It's going to have a thing down at the bottom of the msdn
documentation, that will tell you what you need to link with.
So you can see it here and it's got it right.
Now.
The problem that you will see is, you know, it's got it here.
It's got some stuff listed, right?
What's the deal?
Ello?
Its 1.4 or something blah blah blah, right?
The problem that we
We have.
Is that this, this platform requirements line is a little bit sketchy,
right?
It's like, okay.
It requires Windows 8 potentially which we know that most people don't
have because nobody wanted it.
Right, so that's not happening.
DirectX xdk.
Well, we don't really know what that means, what version of it do.
They mean, and, you know, does the user have that installed?
I don't know.
We haven't actually used anything from the DirectX SDK, but when we
do, we'll probably use one from a very early version of the DirectX
SDK basically.
So we can't really guarantee that that's going to be on there and
Windows Vista.
Well, what if the person was running Windows XP?
I don't know.
I don't know why.
Windows 7 isn't listed here, presumably, it was in Vista.
It would work on seven, but I don't know.
So you can see that it makes me a little nervous.
So what I would rather not
Do is I'd rather not linked directly to xinput lib, because if we link
directly to xinput lib, then what's going to happen is if it can't
find one of these dlls on the system, then our game just won't load
just flat-out won't load.
And that's kind of annoying because you don't need a Gamepad to play
this game.
We're going to allow you to play it with the keyboard at a very
minimum.
And so it would kind of be bad if you couldn't launch the game due to
direct input into the xinput.
When you, otherwise could have totally easily played it with a
keyboard in the circumstance where there wasn't an X input Library.
So what do we do?
How do we resolve this external symbol problem?
Well, what I want to introduce you to was the concept of basically
loading Windows functions.
Yourself essentially, basically getting the code into your executable,
for a Windows binding and looking up the function pointer so that you
can actually call directly into it without using an import library.
And this
Actually, a really simple process and especially in a circumstance
where we have such a small number of functions that we actually need
to deal with.
In this case.
Probably possibly only two that we might need to deal with total.
I'm looking here.
Let's see.
What is X input, enable.
Do we need to call this?
Let's see response to get input state, state will be registering not
sent to the device.
I don't know if we need that one, but pretty much.
We're going to need, get get State and set state is probably mostly
all we're going to need.
Need to set state allows us to send vibration out and we may want to
vibrate the controller and response, the things that kind of adds a
little bit of fun to a game.
So we may want set State as well.
But that's really all we're going to need is is X input set State and
xinput, get state.
So what I want to do is basically I want to kind of come in here and I
don't know if I don't actually know how good the browsing is.
Oops, gotta open up Dev m.
Get back to our program in the debugger.
I don't actually know how good this is.
Can this do a Open document and jump us to it.
Let's take a look.
Hello, Windows.
There.
It is.
Good job.
Okay.
So basically we're looking at this and
Looks like it wants xinput 1.4, a DOT DL and that's fine.
You can see it defines those here for us if we want to know them.
And then you got all the defines in this, in this Windows include
header file, the base.
They're all the things we were looking at, right?
It's got this one.
It's got that.
And then this is the part we actually care about here.
It has the defines for these two things, right?
These are the two functions we actually care about.
And so, what I'm going to do.
Is I'm going to say that we're just going to flat out, get these
ourselves.
We're going to load them ourselves from that dll without actually
asking Windows executable loader to do any of it.
So what I'm gonna do is I'm going to cut and paste the definitions in
here.
Right?
And I'm going to strip out those little in and out, annotations,
right?
Because those are just for the static code analyzer.
And we don't actually need those.
I'm going to get rid of all this stuff so that we just have the
function signature and that's it.
Right?
You can kind of see it just got the function signature, nothing else
in there.
Going to get the function signature for this one as well, right?
Like that, and go in here and make sure I've got the vibration one
there as well.
There you go.
So now I've got the two function signatures.
Now, what I'm going to do as you know, if I just put the function
signatures in like that, then basically what that's just telling
Windows is hey, by the way, there is an external function somewhere
called this.
In case you didn't know.
And now if I call it you can bind to it in the Linker stage, right?
So that doesn't help us because that was already in X and put dot h,
so that does absolutely nothing for us, but
What I can do is instead of actually treating it like this.
I can change this into EPS, didn't mean to hit that.
I can change this into a typedef.
I can basically say I am going to do a typedef, that tells the
compiler, there is a function of this type, and I want to actually
start declaring variables that are Pointers to it, basically, right?
So, this is actually saying, I just want to type called xinput, get
state, right?
This is the name.
I want to type.
That basically is a function.
That's the type of this thing.
So, you know how you say typedef, Gant Foo.
And now, Foo is basically a synonym for in.
So if I do Foo X, I've got an end.
Well, if I do this, now if I have X input State as my type by say x
input State Foo.
Well, that doesn't really help me because you can't Define actual
objects that are functions in C.
So that's not going to fly.
But what does fly is if I wanted a pointer to one of those functions,
I can do this.
I can basically
There a pointer to a function that has this signature and that's
totally legal and that's exactly what we want.
So,
What I'm actually going to do, is I'm going to go ahead and say that
this is a global variable, since there's only going to be one of them.
We are going to have X input, get State, and X input, set State, X
input yet State and xinput set State like that.
And the problem now is we're going to conflicting.
With this Windows header file.
If we call them the same thing as you can see here, right?
They've defined these or not macros or anything.
We can't really undefined them.
I could not, I could not pound include this file, but then I would
lose all of these to find that they did for me.
I have to cut and paste them in.
That might be something that I might want to do.
But for now, I don't think I want to do that.
So we're just going to go ahead and say well, alright, let's call this
may be dynamic or something like that.
I don't know.
I'm not
Sure, what the right was?
Let's see why we'll just fix it with d y.
So, we know this is our dynamically loaded one.
And and that is what it will be from now on, in fact, you know, what
we could do, we could do something even clever.
This may be a little bit too clever for our own good.
I don't know if that's actually true or not, sometimes, but let's find
out what we could do is, we could say, okay, let's take an underscore
after them.
Just so we know.
And then we'll actually just go ahead and change what the meaning is
right here.
We could do that might actually work.
I don't know.
Let's see.
Let's get wild on a Monday.
This basically says all right from now on anytime.
You see this, change it into this.
That way, we can still use the real name, but it will always actually
remap to our fake pointer.
Yeah, makes sense.
Hopefully that's clear enough.
I'm just making that a little bit more easy because I don't want
somebody typing xinput, get state in here and calling the windows
function because we're not linking with that course, they would get a
link time error, but I don't know.
I'd like to try and prevent people from accidentally doing that.
So maybe we just do this and that's good enough.
Okay, so let's recompile that
Off we go.
And so now what will happen is you'll notice that we still have, we
have a call to xinput get State and it's down here, right?
That is now defined to actually be this.
So it's going to call it's going to actually call the function pointed
to by our pointer, but our pointer is uninitialized, right?
It's zero.
It's not initialized zero because it's one of those static Global
variables.
It's zero.
So basically what will happen is if we run this program, we will just
flat-out crash.
At least.
I assume we will.
Let's verify that yes, we will just flat-out crash in the kind of
After will have is basically a in execution violation.
So you remember,
we've seen what happens when we try to read and write from invalid
memory.
We get an access violation.
Well, you also get the same kind of access violation.
If you try to execute memory that isn't valid and that is Zach.
What's going on here?
Basically, what's going on here is we declared a pointer to a
function.
We did not point it at anything and then we went ahead and tried to
call that function.
Well, unsurprisingly that jumped 20 000 000 as you as you might expect
and there isn't anything there, so it immediately faulted.
And stopped our application.
So that's fine.
But we do need to do is we do need to basically figure out some way of
actually pointing this to something useful.
So, how are we going to do that?
Well, the way we're going to do that is twofold.
First of all, and, you know, I mean
We kind of have two choices here.
I'm going to show you how to do one of them and I'll briefly mention
the other.
But the first thing
Do is I want to go ahead and stop this thing from crashing in the
case, where we don't have these pointers.
So, I'm going to take it one.
I'm going to take the Ridiculousness up, one more level and basically,
Define a macro.
This is how I normally do things.
This is how I normally do them.
I know it's particularly odd, but basically I'm going to define a
macro that defines a function of this form.
So basically, it looks like this, right?
It is a macro that just outputs
It's that and Hoops.
I don't know why I keep hitting the insert button today.
So basically if you run this macro and you pass it, a parameter, it
will basically Define for you a function with that name.
That is all it's going to do and then I can replace and well, you
know, I can do the other one as well while we're at it, right?
Why input?
Oops not line but X input set state name.
There we go.
That's the other one right there.
Right?
Looks good.
Oops, Got the d word.
Didn't we do that?
There we go.
Got everything in there and looks right.
Okay.
So basically what we're going to do is we're going to Define these two
macros, the basically Define the functions for us.
We are then going to Define our typedef in terms of the macro.
So we're basically say, well, that's just this, right?
That.
You can see that will just this line will now produce this line so we
can get rid of it.
Right.
Same thing again for the set State 1.
We want to produce this line.
So we'll just do X input sets, a tips G, their necks and put set
stink, that will produce this line for us.
And then the global variables can stay as they are those totally work
and now you may wonder and then we've got our remapping down there.
Now, you may wonder, why did I bother doing that?
Why did I bother break it up into lines?
Well, it's because
I want to make functions of this form as stubs basically, right?
So we've defined the types, but I want to actually do an X input get
State stub, which is a function with the same signature.
But the does absolutely nothing just return 0, that's it and the same
for set State, there it goes.
Now.
I'm going to say x input, get States tub and X input set State sub.
To stop.
There we go.
Let's compile that make sure everything's cool.
And it is.
So I hope you can see what I did there.
Basically, this is, this is very efficient way of defining the
function prototype once for the thing you want.
Defining a type of that so that you can use it from now on as a
pointer and we want to be able to do that, defining a stub with it as
well.
And now if we need to change this print this, this function signature
at any time, it will change it everywhere.
Right?
So it's kind of nice and compressed in that way.
Now the stubs and I might go ahead and do them like this, right?
In fact, I might even go a little bit further and say, just group
these all together.
By set state or get state.
So there's that one and there's this one, right?
Yeah, makes sense.
So basically, these are our definitions.
Now this is is our support for xinput.
Get state.
And this is our support for xinput set state.
Right.
And all I've done is, I've made it so that now, our function pointers
point to a default function right off the bat.
So, in theory, now when we run, we will not crash, we'll just do what
we used to do.
And what will happen is, and we'll see here if I run to it.
Basically, what will happen is this function pointer is just pointing
at the sub function.
So when we jump into it, we just jump to our sub function, right?
No harm done.
So basically that's a good way to initialize your function pointer.
So just point to a stub.
So that if you don't initialize them ever again, or fail to
Able to load the thing, you're going to load.
Well, it's no big deal.
So.
Yeah, so let's go ahead and call that done for now.
And now we got to see how to actually load the windows versions of
those right?
Pretty straightforward.
So just reorganize that a little bit here.
So I had to make a function up here just because I want to be able to
keep this close at hand.
I want to be close to these definitions so I can just see it easier to
be honest.
We're going to call internal here and I've got these the I got
internal right, good?
Why?
Why isn't these?
These should all be called internal?
I don't know why they're not.
So I'm going to go ahead and do that just to make sure.
Yeah, you should all be internal and they are.
Okay.
Okay, in fact wait, but isn't this one can't this one be internal to?
Is that elapsed?
The internal make complaints there?
Now?
It's not because it's a
yeah, okay.
Okay.
Good.
Sorry about that.
Just a quick.
When I see something in the code.
Sometimes I'm obsessively going to have to go touch it.
That's just the way it goes sometimes.
All right, so I'm going to go ahead and Define the new function here
called load X input.
And I guess we'll prefix it with win32.
Since that's what we've been doing.
Load X input is just going to be a thing which tries to get X input.
If it can, if it can't, it can't.
No big deal.
Not a problem.
All right.
So what we're going to do is we're going to essentially do the steps
that the Windows loader does.
It loads our program.
so,
We are going to use a function called load Library, which loads
basically the dll the backing part of the thing that Windows uses,
basically to give us functions, which I may be and we're going to have
time in this dream.
I think we're going pretty good or I might actually draw some diagrams
for this one.
So you can kind of see what it is.
We're going to use that to load the dll that we actually wanted.
So we're going to call load library with a file name.
The file name is going to go in here, right?
And that's going to give us back a module, which is basically a
Handle to some code, right?
A handle to a loaded piece of code, kind of like our H instance was in
Wind main, if you remember that, it's that sort of thing.
So what we're going to do is get the xinput library.
We're going to load it and assume.
We get back a valid Library.
We're then going to load the functions out of it.
So xinput, get State.
Our function here, get state is going to be equal to something that we
load of that library.
And our, why do I keep, I always want to type y.
If I type back set, state is also going to be one.
Now, the function that we need for that is called get proc address and
we'll see how that works in a second.
So load Library.
We need a file name to load.
And remember, I was mentioning it before inside that xinput .h, they
actually were nice enough to Define for us.
For this version of the header file that we're using which one it is.
But to be honest with you, I would rather use the earlier version
because that'll give us a little more compatibility.
Now.
I happen to know that xinput 1.3 tends to be available on a lot of
machines.
So I'm going to go ahead and just verify that that guy is there.
So, let's take a look.
Let's go ahead and change over here to Windows and let's do a derp /s.
I don't even know if this command works anymore.
Best.
But let's take.
Whoops.
That's not good.
Dot DL.
L.
I just want to see if it has one of these still there.
Sure does.
Yep.
Does it have a four?
I don't know.
Let's find out.
Let's take a look.
What dlls dll?
Bingo, ladies and gentlemen.
What dlls do we have?
Definitely got xinput.
1.3., We got two copies of them because you can always do with a few
more copies.
I think one of them is a 64-bit and ones with 32-bit.
Maybe I don't know.
You can see these in while 32 and this isn't system.
32, which I think means this is the 64-bit one and this is the 32-bit
one.
Paradoxically perhaps or yeah.
Okay.
So if we were to try and load X input, 1 point 4, we would not even
run on this machine probably.
So,
Actually, this just kind of gets back to what I was saying about why
you kind of want to take this sort of thing into your own hands.
Potentially.
Let's we, if we were to actually let it load for us.
It probably wouldn't would have failed.
So I'm going to try and load X input, 1 Point 3 instead of 1 point 4,
because that's going to be on more machines and that'll mean, you
don't have to install a bunch of stuff to actually have our game work.
So assuming we get that back.
I don't know if you have to check for invalid handle value.
What is it is null.
So that's fine.
So basically we're going to load it that dll up its going to map.
It into our process virtual address space.
We are then going to pass that handle to a function called get proc
address and what get proc address does f.
What it says it gets the address of a procedure or function.
So if we look at that basically, all we have to do is pass the module
and then pass the name of the thing that we're trying to load.
So we are trying to load xinput, get State, and xinput set State.
Now, you will notice since it does not know, get proc address does not
know.
What the function signature is, this loading?
It can load anything.
Any kind of function.
It's just going to return.
What is basically a void star.
So, we are going to have to cast The Return of this to the type that
we actually want.
Otherwise, see, will immediately complain and we know the kind that we
want.
So that's pretty easy.
We just do it like this, get input set State star and that is that.
So, we're gonna go ahead and compile that and we're going to go ahead
and see if that worked by stepping into it.
And taking a look at sort of what actually occurs, whether we get
valid function, pointers back from those groups.
Of course that will only work.
If we call the function, if we never call the function, we're not
going to get much help I suppose.
So that's kind of initialization stuff.
So I'm going to put that right here.
First thing we do, we're going to try and load it.
If we can, we can, if we can't, we can't.
So, let's go ahead and see, can we load it?
Loaded just fine.
Looks like, so we go in here, we call get proc address.
Did we get an address for that?
Let's see.
X input, get State, what happened there?
Oh, right.
It's an underscore.
Sorry, and xinput set State.
We use that macro trick makes things a little more complicated than a
bugger.
It's true.
So, it looks like we got both of them and you can kind of see.
Now, if you look in the
Watch window.
It's kind of interesting.
The watch window is actually smart enough to tell us that these are
now pointers into the xinput 1.3, dll portion of our memory space,
right?
Which is kind of cool.
So we've got them now.
Let's see if we could run with them, we can.
And so in theory, now, we are actually getting back from Windows, the
actual state of the controller, which means, if we wanted to, for
example, we could make it so that something was predicated on that we
could make it.
So, for example, that, you know, we do this little thing here, like we
Add y offset, maybe we will only add y offset.
If one of these is downright, since this is just our little thing that
we play with.
Anyway, maybe we'll go in here and say.
Well, you know, if the a button is down, right, let's add to that.
Right?
And there we go.
Now for running we should see no actual why motion and that's true.
And if we had a Gamepad here, what you know what, I don't see any
reason not to run into the other room and get a Gamepad and test this
out.
I don't really think there's almost any chance that
There's anything wrong or such a simple API, but you know what?
Give me one second.
I'm gonna go grab one plugged in my TV.
Seems worth it.
I don't know, only took a couple seconds.
You can see I've even got the one that that was sort of the video and
I actually don't think that's true.
The one I recorded in the trailer is actually at work.
Got two of these pink ones.
I bought them one time.
I bought two pink ones and like a green.
When they were all.
They had left at at the Target downtown.
We were trying to play a game called Gang Beasts and we wanted extra
controllers.
So let's take a look and see, I don't know if this is going to work
here.
It doesn't look too promising because it's not actually lighting up
for me, which does not fill me with much with much.
Hope for the fact that it's actually working properly.
But what are you going to do?
Let me try.
Plug it into the actual PC down here.
There we go.
That that had a little light flash on it.
I don't know that might indicate something good.
Not actually sure well.
Yeah, well, I don't know.
I tried.
We'll see if we can get this Gamepad working.
This is this doesn't seem like it's going to be much to do with.
Oh, no that actually does.
There we go.
Okay, totally good.
I guess you just have to, I don't know.
I don't know why the light you can see the light just came on.
I don't know why the light wasn't actually on originally.
I thought that it would just be on when I plugged it in, but maybe you
actually, it might be that you have to actually load X input for it to
actually go on or something sometimes.
An older versions.
I don't know.
Normally when you just plug it in just works.
I guess because this machine perhaps doesn't actually have the little
X input helper, the little X Box controller app, or whatever.
Maybe it doesn't.
But that's pretty good.
That was it for controller support.
I mean, you saw that, that was like, hardly any code, right?
And we did it the hard way.
We did it, loading it ourselves, but you can see, I don't know if you
can see there.
When I push the button, it totally works.
So we're basically done.
I mean, that's the controller input.
There is nothing else to it.
We can go ahead and send Rumble back to it.
So I guess we might as well.
I
I don't know what else to say about it.
Other than hey, that when you actually make a good API ladies and
gentlemen, which xinput actually isn't that bad.
It's got a few things that are kind of annoying, but on the whole,
it's pretty easy.
Look at how easy this will be able to program.
You know, it's a good thing.
So, I guess what I could do here is just call get x and x input set
State just to verify that it sort of worked.
I could go ahead and just send that to the 0th controller.
Yeah, and we'll just, we'll just send some some rumble level out to it
just to verify that.
It's actually working.
Then we'll save that a for some other time later when we actually have
some really coherent thing that we want to do with it.
So I'm going to go ahead and look up X input set State here.
Just so I can see what the parameters are of that structure.
You got to fill out that it passes to it, xinput set state.
So it's called an X input vibration.
Let's take a look here, xinput vibration and it is just left motor
speed and right motor speed.
That is it.
All right.
Well, that should be easy enough.
So let's take a look vibration.
.W left motor speed equals something.
What is?
It's a word.
All right.
Well if it's a word, I mean, clearly if it's a word, we're going to
want something close to the highest value because we want some
serious.
On here, right?
That seems to me like, a good thing.
Maybe not quite the highest not 65536, but we're up there and let's
take a look and see what happens here.
When I run that.
Look at that vibrating nicely.
I don't know if you can even see it, vibrating but it is definitely
vibrating.
All right.
Well, there we go.
That was the adventure of xinput.
Not a whole lot.
To do and good for a day's work.
So while we have time, we might as well add keyboard input to just so
we can see how to get that.
So that when the time comes and we want to wire this up to our actual
game code, we will be ready because I'd like to have keyboard input as
well not just joystick input.
So I'm going to kind of go up here and show you how to do that.
It's real simple.
Basically for the kind of basic keyboard input that we're looking for.
There's a kind there's a more advanced kind will do when we when we do
like the shipping version of the win32 platform layer, which is way
down the line.
Basically, there's a thing called raw input, that we would use, to be
able to handle multiple keyboards that are mapped to different
players, which almost nobody supports.
But if you can actually, you can do it.
And we might as well do it.
But in for the mean in the meantime, there's basically ciske downs and
ciske UPS.
Let's see.
Sis key up and there's keydown and keyup.
I think that's basically it and I'm not sure.
I don't remember these adults.
So we're going to look at them.
I don't even get input this way anymore.
Like I said, I use
Use the kind that's it's it's significantly a lot more complicated.
I would say but you get a little bit more from it.
So it's something we'll kind of cover more in the future, but you
definitely don't want to start with it because it's a bunch of
complexity that you don't need for anything other than if you actually
want to handle multiple keyboards.
So, let's take a look here.
So, in ciske down the W / am is the virtual key code.
And the virtual key code is basically the thing we want.
So what win is going to do is what is going to call us back with these
messages, whenever anything happens on the
Keyboard.
Now you don't need to register anything.
It just happens.
Windows will always send these to you.
And normally what was happening before is they were going into here.
They were they were just getting eaten up by the deaf window.
Proximal.
All we're going to do is start actually looking for that's it.
So basically the W / am is the virtual key code.
The W / am is the thing that comes in here.
It's just a Anonymous parameter.
That's depends on what message you have.
So the virtual key code is, is this?
So let's let's go ahead and Mark that off.
Is that true?
As well in ciske up.
Let's see.
Ciske up.
Yep, it is.
Let's look at Key down.
And key down message.
Let's take a look at that.
The virtual code of the non-system key.
Yeah.
So basically it always is going to come in with the V code K code
there.
So, that is exactly what we wanted.
We want our VK code.
Now, tell you what a VK code is in a minute, but for now suffice to
say, it's just a thing, which tell you which key it was.
But there's also this other thing, which is the L, / am and the L /,
am basically tells you some additional things about the, the, you
know, what went down basically.
And so there's the previous Key State which is B 30, right?
So if you shift one up by 30, you get B 30.
If we take a look at L per annum and it with that.
That tells us whether the key was down before, the message was sent or
up before the message was sent.
And so I don't know why you would receive receive key down messages,
if the key was already down, but it may be because of key repeat, if
that makes sense.
Like, you know, you hold down a key.
Hold on a key like this and it keeps going.
I think that might be the case and will double check that.
But for now, let's go ahead and just say okay no matter what happens.
We're going to get basically a VK code out of it.
We're going to see what the VP.
What the wpm is that that tells us what key actually went down and
we're just going to look for the keys that we actually want.
That's all we're going to do.
We're going to take a look for those individual keys and the keys that
I actually want.
Basically our VK.
I think these are the way that they are listed.
I'm going to see if there's actually a VK code listing somewhere.
Let's see VK code listing because I don't remember what they all
actually are because they have
Different names, sometimes you can see.
All right.
So here you go and msdn.
There's a listing of all of the VK codes and the VK codes are
basically all of the codes that don't have direct antsy mappings.
So, basically, you remember the ants e.keycode stuff.
We talked about, in the intro to C3.
Well, basically, all of the ANSI Keys actually map to their actual
like antsy equivalence, right?
So if you actually in see, if we want to, let's say test for the W
button, you could
They just do that and it would work.
At least I believe it is.
Always the capital.
Yeah, it maps to the capital if I'm correct.
If I remember correctly.
Yeah, that is the W key and you know will double check this to make
sure it wasn't the lowercase and I'm totally wrong.
Well, you know we can just do it right now.
I'll put debug string a w, very exciting.
Alright now let's go ahead and run this and get this window over the
side there.
Whereas our output.
There's our output W.
There it is.
You can kind of see it, wa out there always good.
So that's all we really needed for any of those.
So if we want W ASDF, basically what we're looking at is just
something like this really?
Really trivial code here, nothing particularly interesting.
So if we want the full complement, let's say w,a,s,d and of course
The ubiquitous q&e, you always need those special options.
That is basically that nothing particularly interesting there.
Then we just need to know stuff like say the arrow keys, maybe the
spacebar and then probably like Escape.
That's that's kind of the stuff that we would expect to get back in a
game situation.
I think that probably be pretty good for now.
So we've got q and E and then we go in here.
We're going to need VK up.
VK left?
VK down VK, right?
VK Escape.
Is it is?
Escape or just ask.
I wonder, I don't actually know.
Let's take a look here.
You can see these left up right down.
There's home in end and all these other, good things VK Escape.
So it is escape fully typed out.
And then what else did I say?
Spacebar is a typical one is the spacebar mapped to just space or does
it have an actual space in it?
VK space?
There we go.
So that's it.
That's basically all there is and those are all the key codes that we
might want to handle.
Now.
What we're going to do with those is going to be determined once we
actually get our game stuff working and we have a place to wire input
up to but I just want to show you.
So there is no confusion.
Basically what was going down going on and so we can also get some
more information here.
Like I said, this is going to be basically a was down which is
basically saying, oh, okay.
Was the key down beforehand.
So that's that's like if this is not equal to 0 then the key was down.
I'm basically just turning that into a guaranteed Boolean, this this
Bears, a little explanation.
Again.
We this has been a pretty good stream in terms of having plenty of
time to talk about stuff.
So I'm just going to say what I'm doing here.
So basically this L program is a bit field, that's got a bunch of bits
set.
It said that the 30th bit tells us whether or not the key used to be
down or used to be up before this message before the before, whatever.
Event triggered this message.
Well, if I just add those together, then what I'm going to get is, I'm
not going to get 0 or 1.
I'm going to get 0 or B 30 being set, which is way not one.
And since I wanted to sanitize it into a 0 in one potentially, since I
was going to put it in a pool.
I don't know.
I don't really have to put it in the pool for any particular reason.
We'll talk about that kind of a little later on.
Maybe maybe we can talk about that tonight.
If we got extra time.
I just said not equal to 0 that comparison.
If you remember from the in produce interest East room, we're talking
about it.
And I think I was actually even a little unsure about it at the time,
which is kind of odd considering the fact that I would have known that
this happened.
But what you gonna do sometimes in your on stream, your little crazy.
Basically what happens is if you ask see to do a comparison for you,
it will produce 0 or 1.
So if we do not equal to 0 that will actually produce a 0 or 1
depending on whether it was 0 or the B 30, so that's basically just
turning, it's basically turning you know, this we got back either this
40, right?
We got either that or this but we wanted was this or that right?
We wanted we wanted this one to turn into one and this one to turn
into zero and so the not equal to 0 just basically forces that to
happen, right?
That's about it.
All right, so that's a was down and then I also want an is down
meaning.
What actually was this message trying to tell us?
And so let's take a look at back to the WM key down message.
And what does that actually stay?
Okay, the transition state.
What is the transition state defined to be always 0 for a key down
message.
So what is the key up message?
Is it always that as well always one.
Alright, so the transition state.
So basically the other bit will tell us what actually is now.
So basically if that bit is set, am I correct for a key up message?
It's always one.
So we want it to be equal to zero if it's down now.
Now, is that correct?
Because Kiev?
So let's take a look.
Basically.
I'll go ahead and test this with say the Escape key.
So when we put that I'll do an output debug string and I'll just do a
test on is down.
Alright, let's see, do it this way and was down, right?
So we'll do output, debug string, escape and then we'll say is down.
Was down.
Excuse me.
I'm still sick.
Ladies and gentleman.
This true.
I did not recover much over the weekend.
Unfortunately, then when I run this I should be able to kind of go in
here.
Take a, look at that output stream and do my Escape key.
Well, that did not work particularly well to say the least.
Why is my Escape key?
Not working.
Oh, that looks like it didn't compile.
What happened there?
Why it how did that happen?
I thought I compiled it and yet it was still printing out W, which we
deleted.
So I guess I didn't compile.
I don't know what happened there.
That clearly looks like I compiled.
Maybe, I maybe I did something else wrong.
There it goes.
Yeah, I don't know, ladies and gentleman programming so he's a little
wonky.
Okay, so I hold it down is down and it was down.
That's correct.
So I am getting key.
Repeat messages.
So I get them repeatedly.
Then when I let go, I get just was down and that's correct.
Yeah.
Perfect.
So looks like that's all good.
Basically, we have everything we need here.
We don't need those key repeat messages.
So, one thing that we could do if we wanted to is, we could just kind
of get rid of them.
We could basically say that if was down equals 2 is down.
This is not an interesting message for us.
If that makes sense.
We could just flat out, say that.
And then when we run in here, we will basically be
Those key repeats, right?
Let's see.
There we go.
He's down was down.
No poop.
So I do that.
The wrong way again.
Yeah, awesome.
I do that all the time.
People all the time.
What I wanted to do was say if if they're not equal.
I want it.
If it wasn't down and now it is or if it is and if it was and then now
it isn't.
So I want them to be not equal.
I basically filtered for the case.
We don't want that's brilliant.
That'll help a ton way to go.
Good job.
So there we go.
That's what we wanted.
Yeah, exactly.
Perfect.
So that's really all we want and that is pretty much the
Ready of key input as well.
That's it.
So we've got input.
Now.
We just need a game to funnel it to and like I said, we don't want
this.
I mean, this is not good code, that's going to do anything useful for
us.
I just want to put in there so you can show how to get it.
Everything once we actually have something to fill out.
What we'll be doing, is in here.
We'll just go ahead and say, okay, let's pass.
Let's let's fill out the stuff that we're going to pass through the
game by using these things.
So that's all we're going to do.
Well, here we are at the five minute warning.
We have already accomplished, everything that I want to accomplish on
that stream.
Let me think if there's other things that I might want to do real
quick.
One thing I want to do is I got email from people over the weekend.
This was supposed to be a win Class.
A.
Remember, I was in trying specifically to make everything be a is
where they should be.
And so load library is also an a kind of a thing.
So I'm going to try and go in here and just pass a to everything so
that we know that we're not using Unicode for the benefit of people at
home.
Just make it a little easier for them if they're compiling in Unicode
mode, since we are not.
If they are for some reason, trying
Do that then.
Then this will make it a little easier on them.
Just if we have most of them, correct?
Okay, I guess I guess.
Get proc address.
Only has a Nancy version.
There is no Unicode version of that.
So that's good.
All right, that's all set.
Let's take a look and see if there's anything else here that I wanted
to take a look at ya.
Yes.
Oh, there is one more.
One of the things I was thinking about over the weekend as I did and I
asked some friends about it too, just to be sure.
I decided I don't really like this passing by value.
I mentioned it real quickly.
I was talking about passing win32 off-screen buffer by valuing, really
passing something by valued in the hopes that's going to optimize
stuff when it's that big, but it's something that large which is that
is a fairly large.
Dropped.
It's more than, you know, it's not like a tiny little struct.
It's fairly sizable.
I think.
In general, you're counting on inlining, you're counting on on the
optimizer inlining this before.
It's really going to get a win out of that.
And if it doesn't in line at then it's going to be a problem because
it's going to force copies stuff like that.
So I want to actually go back to the way I normally code.
I kind of did that for the benefit benefit of the people watching but
you know, honestly, it's not something I would actually do.
So I'm just going to go ahead and change it to the way that I actually
do do things and not try to be overly clever.
Over on the stream.
I think that was a mistake.
And so I'm just going to actually kind of rearrange a code here and
just make it a little bit.
More like what I would normally do.
And just because I think that's the right thing to stick to, I mean I
should stick to how I code and if I want to mention something that
other people do and say you could try to do this or investigate on
your own.
I think that's good, but I shouldn't try to do things that aren't the
sort of things.
I normally do just because they might be better, or maybe they're
newer ways of doing things because at the end of the day, I have no
guarantee that they are actually correct and I may just be leading you
astray.
So I'm going to go ahead and just clean that code up a little bit and
make
That look a little bit more.
Like what I would have expected.
Okay, so we are almost done with that.
There we go.
And now we are compiling again.
And I think that is it.
We are still in good shape here.
We've got three minutes.
I don't know what else we should try to throw in here in the three
minutes.
I guess.
One thing we could do is we could go take a look at the set cursor
situation since we're
Not saying the cursor, we could try to throw full screen there.
Two minutes out of know, that two minutes.
Maybe we just go to Q&A early.
Maybe we just say that was a good day.
We got everything done that we wanted to get done.
We've got input in and so we'll have the rest of the week to work on
sound which is really the only thing.
Well, you got two things really sound and file I/O.
So if we can get through sound and three days, we could do file I/O on
Friday, and then we would pretty much be ready to get going on the
game.
Proper the following week, which would be great, two weeks.
On Windows, it's not very much to spend.
I mean, that is longer often times.
I'm sorry that is shorter often times and it takes to figure out why
your CSS isn't working on when you're trying to make a web page.
So I think that's probably pretty good.
All right, I will go ahead and go to the stream now to see what is
going on over there.
Let's take a look.
To do.
Can you write a driver to make it work piece?
Okay, L.
/ m, 30 is always one for WM key up.
Yes, that is should be true.
But that's okay.
We don't care.
I'm not sure why that would matter that.
We don't we don't actually care if that's true.
Right?
Because as long we just want to make sure that we're turning whatever
these four messages, these four separate ways.
That wind is going to tell us about key events.
We just want to make sure that we turn them into something reliable
and whether it was down, whether it is down or usually pretty reliable
things in my mind because it kind of lets, you know, which direction
your go.
It kind of makes it so that no matter what the message was, you end up
with a stable state that you can record in here.
So it was just kind of a way of decrypting that into something easier.
Okay.
Not a Christmas tree.
And why uppercase variable names, really?
It's something that I got in the habit of doing it.
My very first thing which is was partnering with Chris Tucker.
Actually, there is no reason for it.
It's just how things were done.
And that's what stuck with me.
I don't, I don't think there's a right or wrong way to capitalize your
variables or anything else.
Okay.
Can you explain your macro and referencing the X input functions?
Again?
I certainly can.
Let's see here.
so,
In here.
What I did was I said, well, this is the function prototype that
Windows made for xinput.
Get state, right?
This is this is what it looks like in the windows header file.
So what I did is I replace the name xinput, get state with basically a
macro parameter.
So that allows us to make as many functions of this signature.
As we want, just by using this macro, right?
This macro will basically generate the
Signature and swapping.
Whatever name.
We give it.
So to define a type that is that signature, right?
The type is this function signature.
I just do typedef that I let the macro expand this thing out with the
name that I want my typedef to have, right?
Then I do the exact same thing to generate.
It again only this time with a different name and that generates the
function, the actual header, for my function, which I then have return
0.
Finally, I make a global variable that points to it.
And then I I define basically xinput, get state from now on to, to use
my new pointer that I declared because I can't undefined the one that
Windows had.
So I just renamed basically everything from here, on out to use this
one.
There's really nothing magic going on here.
It's I guess it is something that only I do because I posted an or
maybe other people do it, but I've never heard.
It it's basically something that I posted in a one of my windows Dev
blog entries and I got email from people going.
Like I never seen that before.
That's pretty cool or something like that.
So I guess it's not that common but I it's the only way I ever do it.
So the way I the only way I ever do function pointers is I pound
Define a thing that generates the signature.
I type def using that macro using the pound to find.
I make the type def to the type.
I
Fine.
The pointer by using that new typedef, right?
And I Define the stubs by using the macro.
Just works really well because especially it works, especially well,
you'll see later on when we want to do dispatch tables or something
like that, and you've got a lot of functions that all have the same
signature and you want to be able to change them trivially, having
them all go through.
This macro means you can just change one line and have all your
functions.
Function signatures.
It's pretty cool.
Let's see.
What's the size?
We're copying?
Becomes problematic for a struct?
I don't know.
You'd have to time it.
It probably depends on the platform.
But in certain cases, like, for wrecked, for example, we still were
passing that one by value for a while.
And earlier.
We're not doing anymore cuz you don't pass the rectangle thing, but
something like rekt where it's 3:30 for 32-bit values or something
like that.
I don't know.
Let's take a look.
I don't actually remember.
I think it's for 32-bit values in a wrecked, right?
Yeah, so if you have something like for 32-bit values that seems like
something you probably want to just pass by value because you know, I
mean you wouldn't you wouldn't bat an eyelash right at having a
function where you were going to do something like, you know, in Star
a in Star be right, but in 64-bit code, that right there is 128 bits,
which is the size of the wreck struct.
So it's really not a big deal with something small like that.
But once it gets big enough,
Yeah, I would say, you know, you don't risk it, pass a pointer.
Now, the problem is, how do you know where that breaking point is?
And the thing that I want to emphasize, this is something that I
actually wrote down here that I want to talk about.
And I'm glad it came up because I was going to kind of force the issue
here in the Q&A, if it didn't, but
Basically something that I want to get across that, I didn't do a good
job of getting cross.
In fact, I probably exacerbated the situation last week is don't think
about optimization at a low level until you actually are optimizing it
a low level.
Because if you're constantly thinking about how to optimize your code
to the low level, you're probably just wasting your time because low
level optimization is very difficult and very specific.
And a lot of times if you're like, oh I'm typing along and I decide to
pass this thing by value because it'll be
Faster, you don't know if it's faster and you're not going to spend
the time right now to check, right?
And there's so many things that are interdependent in low-level
optimization that you're just likely to be wrong all the time.
So, what I'd like to emphasize is program in a way that doesn't create
obviously bad things.
Like don't do anything that's going to be disastrously bad.
But other than that, try not to constantly focus on anything low-level
optimization wise because you're probably just wasting your time
thinking about that.
Might be actually making things worse by doing things assuming that
they're helping in their actually hurting and so on.
So, I would say you want to write your code in ways that are nice and
clean and simple because that is what will be easy to optimize later.
So you should always be thinking about that, but don't spend too much
time thinking about how to do like crazy little optimizations.
For example, in fact, someone just just said, this, they were saying
instead of writing it this way.
Why not write it this way, right?
And then not have to do that thing.
And the answer is because that's just, that's way more obtuse, right
at some level.
It's just more confusing to look at that.
Really?
What you probably should do in this code, is something more like this.
You should say, like,
W like like he message was down bit, right?
Like this, you know, or something like that.
And just so that you actually are actually testing against things that
make some sense.
If you know what I mean, this is probably an even better way to write
this because the compiler is not dumb and it's probably going to be
able to generate the right code out of this either way.
So, you know, that's just, that's just a cleaner way to do it in my
opinion.
Yeah, I don't know.
But either way, I don't really care again.
Like, you should write those sorts of things.
However, you want to write them.
Whatever.
Makes it cleanest and easiest for you, to understand.
And remember because this is the kind of thing that really just
doesn't want to be done at this stage in the code.
If you are thinking about how to write this more optimally, you are
totally wasting your time because a, the compiler will probably do the
right thing.
No matter what you write on that line, because it's so simple and be.
If the compiler is
Doing the right thing rather than guessing, what will be the right
thing for to make the compiler.
Do you actually should if you're like, I got to optimize this.
Now, you should look at the assembly.
See what's generated, verify the thing that your writing is faster and
then, you know, and so I really want to make sure that people aren't
getting hung up on this.
I'm talking about low-level programming because that's I like the
control.
And I like to be able to do the optimal things and we will be getting
to those sorts of things, but I don't want to create some kind of a
thing where people are thinking they always have to be thinking
About exactly what the compiler is going to do and how to make it the
most optimal because that's actually going to cross into unproductive.
So you need to know what your code is doing.
You need to know what you're telling the CPU to do, but between you
and the CPU there is that compiler and it will do inefficient things
and you don't have to always worry about wrestling with it.
The time will come when we start to wrestle with it.
But until that comes, you know, maybe just try not to fixate too much
on it.
Let's see.
Let's see here.
How does that Dynamic Linker?
Find the X input Library installed on the user's machine.
Is it allowed to link xinput?
A compile time or distribute the X input?
Dll alongside Excel to ensure that a lamp Dynamic can find it?
Okay.
That is a good question.
So basically what happens is, when we call load Library, it is going
to look in a number of places.
And in fact, I believe and I don't know if this is true anymore, but I
believe you should be able to actually read it out of the
documentation here because I think they actually document the series
of steps.
It goes through to find the
File.
Now, let's take a look if that's actually true.
Maybe I am totally wrong about that.
Okay, the tumor.
Here we go.
The first direct research is the directory.
Containing the image file used to create the calling process.
So first, it will look where our executable is.
Right?
Our wherever we installed our eggs e, it'll look there.
So basically what we could do is we could dump an X input dll that we
wanted to use into that directory, for example, and then it would
always load that one.
Okay, so that's fine.
Let's take a look here.
The search paths can be altered by set dll.
Directory, if a path is specified and there's redirection.
Yeah.
Okay, path.
Ruble.
To load a model for a relative path without switching their path.
Get full path.
Name here.
It is.
Dynamic link Library, search order.
Factors that affect searching.
Okay.
So this is the page you want.
This is what you want to read.
If you want to know everywhere that it goes through.
I'm not going to try and read all this because oh my God, right?
Like look at all that.
Suffice to say, We'll look wherever executable is.
Then it will look and like the Windows system directories and stuff
which is where stuff gets installed when it's system-wide.
So,
If we wanted to ensure that X input X input was redistributed with our
game, we could do that and we could put it, just we can just put X
input in our directory, but it's unclear.
Whether we actually need to do that.
Because usually, if the person has an X input controller, they will
have gotten the little redistributable thing that comes with it or
install, the little helper function, that will install it, or they're
using Windows 7, which has it installed by default and so on.
So we probably don't need to do that.
But if you really wanted to when you did redistribution, yes, you
could go.
In fact,
Might even have one.
These are typically called redistributable 's and you can look for
xinput redistributable.
And there might be a thing which basically says how to do that and
let's take a look.
Okay.
So basically it says here that that there is a redistributable as part
of the SDK.
So you may be able to go into the windows SDK and get a little
redistribute redistributable, but they have
made for you that you can just run that will install it on the user's
machine if you want to.
I don't know.
I usually try not to do that when I ship stuff, I try to make it so
that it just works on the user's machine.
So what I usually do is I load Library the earliest version of the dll
that I can find.
That I know will work which in this case is this one.
And so then I know that almost everyone will just already be on their
machine and work and if they don't have it, then they don't have it.
They can always choose to install the X input app thing.
And then
they will magically get it so they can always, you know, I can always
have in the web page if you would like to use a joystick with this and
and you
Don't have and you have an older version of Windows, like, Windows XP.
Just go ahead.
Go on Microsoft site.
That, you know, here's the link, download the xinput application and
install it and then you will magically be able to use the X input with
your game.
I tended like to do that a little bit better just because I find that
most things you can get are already on the Wind persons machine as
long as you use old backwards compatible stuff and don't force to have
the like the newest like that's why I didn't put xinput 1.4 here,
right?
I find that that's better because then the
User isn't like.
Oh I'm running in order to install this game.
It just installed this crap on my machine and I don't even know what
half of it was and now there's the DC library and all this other
stuff.
You know, I just don't, I don't like that.
So I try to keep that as minimal as possible for the benefit of the
user.
Let's see.
You had a second part of that question, is it allowed to link xinput
at compile time?
So, no, it can't really link it at compile time.
That's not really an option.
It has the thing that it's linking.
Compile time is just an import library that itself calls like this.
This basically is more or less, what actually happens when your
program is loaded in Windows, right?
It's going to go ahead and it's gonna look at the things that were in
your import libraries.
It's going to get their
This is much like this and then the only difference is instead of it
like instead of it being pointers that we manually dealt with like we
did here.
It's just going to patch them in.
It's going to patch those pointers into direct memory locations in
your executable, but it's basically the exact same process.
So that's just what's going to happen.
If we didn't do this Windows, just doing it for us.
And that's how Windows is, you know, Windows is already doing that for
a bunch of functions for us, like, get client wrecked and so on,
that's what's happening there.
It's getting its the loader is doing that.
Let's see.
There was a question earlier about why you chose an if-else Cascade
for key input instead of a switch statement.
It's up for grabs.
Okay.
So basically the reason I chose this is that I wasn't really trying to
write any real code here.
So basically this is just going to sit here until we actually have
thing to pipe to and we may well switch it to a switch statement.
That would be totally fine.
In fact, we can, you know, you're you're welcome to basically recode
it like this.
If you
Prefer, it does not matter at all.
Like, like I said, this isn't real code right now.
Just showing you how to get it out.
I just want it to be there so that later when I go, okay, it's time to
add input now and we add it in the game.
I can just go out here.
I have to explain anything.
I can just hook it up and we're done.
So this is just showing I was just trying to show people what comes in
and how so yeah.
This is not a choice.
It's not a smart choice or a dumb choice or anything.
It's not even a choice.
It was just saying.
Hey, this is how that would work.
I break the giant header off of the main.cpp fell.
So you're talking about, I assume this stuff.
Basically, I'm assuming probably next week, I guess.
How do you know the xinput, stub, things work without testing it, on
an XP computer without expectations, input installed?
I love that question.
It's like you read my mind.
You know, it was going to be a secret but because the question was so
good.
I'm just going to say
I don't know if anyone noticed this guy sitting right here.
Well, once we are all done with the window stuff, I was going to show
you guys that exact thing.
You see this guy right here, x Windows XP.
I I did it.
You didn't believe I do it, I bet.
But I did I install a Windows XP virtual machine.
I actually have a bunch of Windows XP licenses.
So used to have essentially render farm and that totally is
decommission now, so I've got like a stack of winxp licenses.
So I took one of those installed it on here and now I've basically
Got Windows XP, a fully legitimate, actual fully licensed one.
So we can run it for as long as we wants not even one of those, like,
30 day trial about, to undo itself, kind of a Windows xp's.
It's like a full-on version of Windows XP Pro that we can launch and
test on.
And that was, I was gonna do that as going to be like at the end.
It was gonna be this big climactic moment of like how do we really
know?
And then we're going to run it on there and all that stuff.
But you beat me to it, but with such a good question, I felt like I
had to had to let the cat out of the bag.
Now.
What I will tell you is as of right now, there's absolutely no way
that we run on Windows XP.
I bet.
And the reason for that is because I think you even need to pass
special Flags to the Linker right now to make that happen because by
default, Microsoft's compiler.
Like doesn't even output stuff that runs on Windows XP.
That's how bad the default setup for the compiler is really, it's
Sad.
That's just the way it is.
So I can pretty much tell you definitively.
Yeah, that that we don't run on Windows XP.
And so what we're going to do is we're going to run it on there.
I'm going to show you that it doesn't run out on your show.
You the flags.
We need to set to make it run and then we will also be able to verify
that we're not calling anything inappropriately that causes us not to
run on there and that's so that's a great question.
And the answer is the only way to do it is to test.
So I highly recommend.
You always have a virtual machine or actual machines with the platform
different platforms that you want to ship on on their the minimum one,
especially so that you can
You can figure that out.
Is it a waste of time to check if get progress proc address return 0?
So
You know, I get, I don't know.
I mean that's a good question.
If you wanted to be really, really stringent about it.
You could, you could reassign to the stub here and actually in my
actual real code, I do it.
We do that, I do a thing.
We're actually after these, I basically do, you know, if not get input
State X input State, equals x input States tub.
I actually do do that normally just to make sure that I don't get a
bad one, but
You know, is it a waste of time?
Yeah, probably because you are so far.
You're basically guarding against something that's kind of
meaningless.
Like if you loaded this dll and somehow someone had modified the dll
to not have the functions in it that it normally has.
Then you know who's to say that the function is even work at all, but
like guarding against it, not finding them is like the least of your
worries.
At that point.
You're probably about to jump into some real crazy stuff if someone
gave you
Dll that bogus, you know, so do I think that's worth it.
Not really, you know, I don't, I don't think that's particularly good.
Yeah, you know, not my I wouldn't I wouldn't say that.
That's a particularly good thing to do.
We'll do it.
Just because you asked, but yeah, I wouldn't say so, you know what,
while I'm here.
I feel like this kind of has to happen, right?
I feel like we kind of need to do this.
Excuse me.
Me.
Something like this.
That's do plus equals stick X stick why you know, that sort of thing
and those are probably going to be pretty heavy weight.
So we're going to we're going to match.
That's probably still too heavy weight.
Let's do that.
All right.
Oh, no, no, no.
No.
Ahh, what's going on?
That's no good.
Well 08.
That's double what I meant was like, shift down by it.
I was I was trying to make the much The Dead Zone alone will be no
heat that up.
See.
All right, so here is my controller.
At still way too much.
That is still way too much.
Let's set that down a bit.
So we basically want something like that.
I guess a very very, very little back from controller.
Yeah, oops, that's why offset.
Okay, there we go.
And now we can control our scrolling.
So that's always good this.
So that is interesting to this guy is always a little bit left, isn't
he?
You know, I thought this Gamepad was busted.
I was playing with it.
This guy, you know, if you can see that now we're actually getting
stick in there, which is I don't know.
It felt like it kind of have to happen.
I thought this Gamepad was busted.
We've been playing a bunch of games with it.
Doug was over the other day and we were playing a bunch of games with
it.
And it was like, I thought that it was always
Going the other direction, and I don't know.
I think it's like got a messed up dead zone or something, because it
shouldn't be that there's no way it should be.
It should be registering that much all the time.
I think this is just basically a faulty controller.
I'm gonna have to buy a new controller, ladies and gentlemen, maybe
this will be an excuse to order an Xbox One controller.
I don't know if those work with xinput yet.
I assume they do.
Yeah, well, that's just that's just lame.
But anyway, that needed to happen.
I think we all know need to happen.
Let's see.
Do do do.
All right, we're kind of out of question.
So I think we mostly got.
I think we've mostly got everything.
Open up.
We got a little bit more.
Let's see here.
Rai has no impact on performance.
I would disagree with that.
I would say that are aii, does have a large impact on performance.
That is one of the main reasons that I don't use it.
So, we'll, maybe we can get to that some other time.
Probably not a good time to do it.
But yeah, so I'd say, let's see, where do the W / a man L / am.
Come from?
Well, basically what happens is Windows calls us back here.
Right?
So if we were to set in fact we can just go ahead and do that.
So if we were to set a breakpoint here like this, we get into win32
main window, call back.
Basically what happens is whoever was above us in the call stack is
the person who's supplying this stuff and that stuff comes from user
32 dll.
So this is some windows code.
The windows code basically, you know, it's the thing, right?
It's the thing that's calling us back and telling us what window, what
message and what wpml / am, what they are.
Now.
The reason they're called W Prime and L Prime is because it wants to
call us back at just a single function.
But it has all these different messages that it wants to give us.
And each message has different parameters.
So, it can't actually put the actual types in here.
It can't say like, in t
W pram and void star L / am or something or you know wrecked or
something wrecked star L per annum, because each message uses a
different type.
So basically, what's forcing you to do is use this message to go into
a switch or some other thing and test Where You Are.
Once you figure out what message you're you're at, it's incumbent upon
you to basically decrypt.
Those wpml prams cast them to the right thing or do bit operations on
them to get out the values, you need, whatever.
That's basically what's happening there.
And so the W Prime until parameter just basically Anonymous parameters
to.
I think they're 64-bit.
I don't know if the 64-bit or 32-bit.
Let's find.
Size of w.
/ am
They are both 64-bit.
So they're basically just to 64-bit values that take on whatever
meaning they need to take on for the message in question.
Let's take a look.
Why did Ms.
Choose to use a link and import Library approach, like this rather
than true dynamic loading.
I'm not sure what you mean, Dynamic loading on Windows works.
He is no less Dynamic than Linux Unix Drive platforms.
I'm not sure.
I understand that question.
Sorry.
Let's see.
Will the game State be cleared once per frame so I don't know exactly
what that means.
Resetting Mouse positions clearing boolean's.
I mean some stuff will be cleared per frame.
If it's something that is only true for the frame.
I'm not sure.
Sorry.
I don't understand that question as well either maybe wait till we
actually get there and then you can ask it more specifically at the
time and it will be clear.
Will you implement procedural generation?
Yes.
When are we going to get a naysayer and Senior ettore combination
game?
I do not know.
But I, you know, the witness has both of our code in it.
I mean there's that I think braid even has some of my codon.
I think maybe the rounded rectangle intersection code is in there.
I don't know.
You'd have to ask John if that's still in there.
I remember it was in there at one point.
I wrote some rounded rectangle intersection testing code.
I mean it's like 60 lines of code and what's probably you know tens or
hundreds of thousands of lines of code for the game.
But if you really, if all you care about is that you had a game by
Jonathan Blow that also had some code from me in it.
You already have one that you can play.
What sound do PR, we're going to use.
Direct sound is what we're going to use?
Will the OS free all Heap objects on program exit.
Yes, you do not need a free.
Everything yourself.
It will free everything.
Let's see.
On Unix, you don't need to link to a DOT lib file at all to use a.so
file.
Where, as an MS platforms.
You needed that lib file.
I don't think that's true.
That is not been my experience on my, in my experience on both
platforms.
You can either use an import library and have it.
Do the binding for you or not use one and not, I mean, yes, you have
to.
Okay, so maybe that's what you're talking about.
Maybe you're talking about the fact that you can directly say, I'm
using this library and you don't need a separate.
Dot lib.
That tells you what the import library is, but that's really a
compiler thing, doesn't have anything to do with Windows.
That's just a, the way the compiler is decided to Output the
Stuff.
You wouldn't have to do that.
I don't think if you didn't want to the compiler, could have just done
it directly.
I think it's just designed to save time.
Maybe even because the compiler could just read the dll and output the
code to bind to the dll correctly, just like it does on Unix.
Oh, yeah.
I don't think there's much of a difference as you think there is.
I guess that's what I would say, but either way, I'm not sure it
matters.
Like it's really not a thing that affects anyone as far as I know.
In the far, future will use direct X or opengl or what?
Well, we'll probably use one of the two of them to do, are bleeding
for a 4-speed purposes, but I'm not sure which one we will probably
use opengl if it seems viable at the time.
Otherwise, we'll use DirectX on Windows and opengl only on other
platforms because sometimes, opengl and windows doesn't work as well.
And so on.
Let's see.
We will be drawing the whole screen every frame probably.
I mean, not exactly true.
But we will there's some things that will be sort of redirected, but
we will be drawing the whole screen.
Are we going to use the width and height in the paint variable again?
No, I don't think we are.
You're talking about in here if you notice they're already gone,
right?
Is that what you're talking about?
I'm not sure exactly what you're talking about.
But in here we passed the window within the window height only so we
don't ya I'm not sure exactly what you're talking about.
But I think we already got rid of them is my understanding but you
know.
Let's see.
Why does valgrind make it look so scary when you don't free?
Well, because they don't have anything else they can do, right?
I mean, it's an external utility.
It doesn't know whether that thing was a leak or something.
You actually meant the OS to clean up, right?
Because let's say I allocate at the beginning of the program.
I allocate a buffer that we use for stuff and then I don't free it.
I left the operating system clean that up that's totally valid in that
works.
But let's say I allocate something every frame.
I'll get a new one every frame.
I never cleaned that up.
Well, that's a memory leak valgrind where valgrind I believe is how
it's pronounced.
Valgrind doesn't know the difference between those, it doesn't know
what your intention was, right?
So it kind of has to report them all and you will have to kind of let
it know.
I guess, which ones are you have to know which ones are legitimate and
not would be my guess.
Let's see.
It looks like wp-admin.
El primer 32-bit on XP.
Yes.
Well, it's not really about XP or not.
It's about whether you're compiling in 64-bit mode, or not.
So I suspect if you were using XP 64 which
And you were loading in the 64-bit mode.
They would probably be 64 bit if that's it's really just whether your
32-bit or 64-bit is whether they're bigger or smaller.
We're compiling in 64-bit mode.
So they're 64-bit.
And we are basically at the end of the questions, it is pup.
Is it possible to keep your frame rate consistent while dragging the
window around doing repaint on WM move is slow.
So here's what I'd say about that.
I have noticed.
A lot of people I've been doing some crazy stuff with the handmade
hero Source, like trying to time the frames per second and stuff like
that.
I would highly recommend not doing that.
We are just setting ourselves up so we can learn how to write a
renderer and we'll be timing the code in the renderer because we want
to make that fast.
But we're not like right now we're just using a Windows call.
That's probably on the slow path to blip things to the window.
So don't time it.
It's going to be way slower than it should be.
Like like this is not we're not trying to get a fastball, it going
here.
We're just trying to get something reasonable to the screen bleeding
in an easy way that allows us to do our own bitmap rendering.
And then when we are done with all of that stuff, then we can start to
look at.
Okay, how do we get that stuff to the screen fastest?
Because that's a whole separate thing and I don't want
Want to put the cart before the horse.
That is way down the line because you get you we haven't even seen how
to like draw a game yet.
And so you don't want to try to draw game fast before, you know, how
to draw a game at all.
So hold off on that.
Don't go nuts timing.
This code is totally pointless because we probably won't even call
stretched B when we're done stretch.
Tibbets when we're done.
Okay, everyone.
I think that is the end of the stream.
So thank you very much.
Everyone for tuning in.
It has been a pleasure as always.
A stream went so, well, we basically had more time than we even need
it.
So that's good.
Let's hope that continues tomorrow.
We will pick up, where we left off with doing basically direct sound
so that we've got our input will start doing our sound.
So hope to see you all again.
We are also trying to get the forums and stuff up and running.
So maybe by tomorrow.
We'll have that too.
If not, hopefully by the end of the week, so thanks everyone for
joining us.
I hope to see you here again, tomorrow at 8:00 p.m.
Pacific Standard time, that will be the last eight pm cast for this
week because we're going to have
Holiday hours for Thanksgiving Wednesday, Thursday, Friday will
actually be at 11 a.m.
In the morning because everyone's going to have Thanksgiving things in
the day and parties and all that stuff.
So we're going to try and put it in the morning where people might be
able to catch it and then next week.
We will go back to our regular schedule after that.
So thank you very much for joining us.
I hope to see you here for the rest of the week when we add direct
sound and yeah, that's it.
Thanks for tuning in.