Hello everybody and welcome to handmade hero.
The show we could have complete game live on stream today.
I think, I guess, I don't really know what we should be doing today
necessarily but I think today we will do is we will go hunt down some
bugs and possibly play a little bit with how we're submitting
Primitives because I don't necessarily want to start today on.
Sort of the shaders multi sample buffer, sort of stuff.
We're going to have to upgrade the opengl part for right now.
I was only using, you know, slightly extended opengl to the old-school
one that's you know that you can just link to on Windows and run.
We only query a handful of extended functions and those were both
basically only for using srgb.
Instead of you know
To basically to have light linear color operation.
And so, we were doing that very specifically because I didn't want to
teach a bunch of open shell minutiae if we weren't necessarily going
to use it, but we probably are at this point.
So it's a good time to go.
Alright, let's take a look at how you initialize open.
Jill in a more modern way.
Where, you know, we're going to load a Vertex Shader in a pixel
Shader, at least,
Possibly not, we could even use more shaders at the head end, like
geometry, shaders, and stuff like this in order to produce our Sprite
since that, you know, send down more compact information for our
Sprites.
For example, we could do that
I don't know that we will or should but we'll sort of do that work.
And we also need to because we are actually using the Z buffer.
Now, we need to go ahead and use some slightly more advanced features
like multi sample, anti-aliasing, and Alpha 2 coverage.
Just to make sure that we can do the least amount of on CPU work, to
get our Sprites sorting properly.
And again, a lot of this stuff is just to eliminate visual artifacts
of compositing.
Alpha Blended 2D Sprites week, you can see them how it how it is.
At the moment, you can see a lot of this stuff here with the Z buffer
and the fringing and that sort of stuff, that is what I'm talking
about.
We need to eliminate those for visual quality purposes.
Everything else is fine for our purposes in terms of Z, buffer wise.
And, you know, the only other thing that I thought were going to have
to do is because, you know, our Sprites are stacked on top of each
other.
Other at such an oblique angle.
I guess steep angle, I don't know what you want to call that at, such
a steal.
Angle.
We're going to have to potentially fudge the Z coordinate, so that
things rise up out of the plane faster than they would in Geometry
terms when they're accessing the z-buffer.
So that's basically like the last set of stuff we have to do to move
over to 3D and to get visual quality and you know get rid of like the
flickery B and the fringing.
That's that's really what we have to do there.
And what we can do is
Is will will try to coincide that with updating to the new art as
well.
Basically the holdup on that as I have to go process it out of
Photoshop and put it into like our format and stuff like that, which
is kind of a bit of work for me on the side.
But that's really what we have to do for that as well.
So that's really all we are looking at here that will not be
particularly difficult work at all.
It's just time consuming because any time you're working with sort of
a black box in, like, we are with opengl where we can't step directly
into the code.
We are at a severe disadvantage for obvious reasons.
We aren't able to easily track down bugs.
We might have because we can't watch what happens to things.
We send down the pipeline.
So, you know, if you take a look at something like, multi sample
anti-aliasing, you know, we can go through the special magic Mojo.
Of turning it on and resolving our buffers and whatever.
And you know maybe it works, maybe it doesn't work if it doesn't work.
How do you solve it?
Right?
And so you have to kind of go through this process of like sending
down structured art and looking at what happens to it and making sure
that it verifies and that sort of stuff in order to really be able to
get well working programs here.
So we may also at that point have to switch to a different computer.
The reason
In for that is just that one of the things that aids debugging greatly
with something like opengl is having the ability to use one of the
inspection tools like nsight or one of the other tools that allows you
to look at what your opengl instruction stream is doing.
And I don't, I mean, we could try on this machine to do it, but I'm
not optimistic.
Like that, we will get any of them to work.
We certainly can't use n site because it's got an AMD card in it.
But I don't know that we'd even be able to use.
I never remember the name of there's a public, there's a non
vendor-specific one whose name I always forget but that would work on
AMD cards but we can't probably use that one either just because the
graphics card on this machine is so old that I would be surprised if
the
if the tools can really,
Work on it, effectively.
Because it's a graphics card from seven years ago.
And I just don't know that anyone's bothering to keep anything up to
date on that.
So if I knew what it was called, I would mention it.
But I'm assuming that if we tried that, it wouldn't work and
fundamentally speaking.
It's not generally a great idea to do development work on Old
Hardware.
Anyway, just because again, you're making life a little harder for
yourself.
The time took play around
With older Hardware, is when you're getting closer to shipping and
just want to do compatibility work, not, when you're trying to get
stuff working and you're fighting the hardware, in addition to working
on the new code.
So,
all that being said, we pretty much finished the Cube stuff.
We don't have any textures to put on the cube.
So I'm going to go ahead and just start some debugging and start some
refinement of this and next week because I'm assuming we'll have
enough work to do today.
I just kind of going through that stuff that we won't have to start
with you'll stuff, but maybe we could do the multi sample buffer.
In fact, I guess one thing we could do.
If we wanted to was tried to turn on Multi sample anti-aliasing today,
because that would be separate from loading any shaders or anything
like that.
So we could try that as well.
In fact, maybe that's what we should try.
We could try that an alpha 2 coverage.
So
Maybe let's do that.
I'm going to go ahead and turn off the the textures.
Let's go ahead and do that here.
Since we don't have a texture for the cubes there, and it's going to
be a little distracting to have that that sort of nonsense in there.
So I'm going to go ahead into open, Jill the renderer portion of the
opengl renderer portion of the code.
And I'm going to go ahead and take out the texturing.
So all I'm doing is I'm placing a disabled at the top and an enable at
the bottom.
And again, since this still is using the fixed function pipeline at
least until next week we can still monkey around like that.
So this is the cubes being drawn just with a white color.
Obviously what I'd like to do here is again since we're just talking
something in so that we can see it, okay?
And we will kind of deal with this when we get to the new art we can.
We can fuss a little bit more.
How we want to specify our cubes.
What I'm going to do here, is something a little bit bizarre.
You can see where I've got this, this P0 P1 P2 P3 stuff.
Here, we created this to talk about our Cube.
We can see that there's these negative Z points, the four, five, six,
seven,
All points with the lower Z value.
The 0 1, 2 3 are all the points with the higher Z value.
I'm going to go ahead and just do a couple kind of bizarre things
here.
So and this is just to get something visually reasonable that we can
use and I'll complain a little bit about what it is.
I just want to set it up first and you can see it and it's just a way
of sort of getting something that you can look at that, will be sort
of a little bit more of a proper Q prepper visual cue.
So if you take a look at what's going on,
Here we know that everything that's a p 0 through 3 is the top face of
the cube.
Right?
And so you can see here this GL quad.
This is the top quad because it's p.
0 1, 2 3.
And those are all ones that have positive Z.
So we know they're the top faces that the highest of faces.
So what I want to do is I just want to make the top of the cube, I'm
going to just change this.
So that instead of it being colored by these sort of random colors I
put on here.
I'm going to
Make that be this thing called top color, right?
And then, what I'm going to do is I'm going to assign the rest of
these.
So we know the bottom one is, well, we know, right?
It's 4 5 6 7 so we can see here.
4 5, 6 7, this is the bottom Cube, we could have a bottom color of our
cubes as well.
Although it for our present purposes anyway, we can't see that.
So the bottom color is largely Irrelevant for all of our you know,
actual purpose.
Is here.
So I'm going to set the top color to the premultiplied color, the
bottom color did nothing just black and no Alpha I guess.
Well you know what?
I'll make it actually solid black.
So I will give it Alpha and then we'll have that Prima color.
And then what I'm going to do here is I'm going to make a gradient on
the other sides of the cube.
Now again, I'm just going to make these instead of like this c0 C1 C2
C3.
I'm just
Make two of those like so.
And what I'm going to do here is I'm going to say, all right for the
c-01, I'm basically what I'm going to want a color wash that whatever
the top Colour of the cube is I'm going to have that be the brightest
version.
So when the person specifies that they want to keep a certain color,
they're going to get that on top of the cube, then on the sides of the
cube.
I want a dimmer color and I want that color to get dimmer.
The lower it goes.
So it'll start out a little dimmer than the top.
And then by the time you get to the bottom, it'll be much dimmer,
okay?
And so what I'd like to do there is I'd like to say okay whatever the
top colors RGB was right.
I want a dim that down a little bit and I'm going to keep the top
colors Alpha value, I guess I should do it this way, so that we so
that you can specify transparent cubes if you really want to.
So, basically, I'm just going to take a gradient here by saying, I
want whatever the top color was.
I want 75% of that, so, just make it a little darker at the top, and
then 25% of it at the bottom, so much darker and I'll use the CT and
CP for that.
And then I'm just going to look through here and say, all right, so I
know, 0, 1, 2 3, are the points that are at the top, so I'm going to
call that color top and I'm going to call the other ones, color
bottom, right.
So basically four and five, which we know are like Down Below on the
bottom of the cube, they get the bottom color.
And so, you know, to is Top, This is bottom, bottom top, top bottom,
bottom top bottom top, sorry bottom top top.
And then now, we've essentially got a procedural assignment of colors
to the cubes.
Okay, now, what you can see hopefully
When I did that right is now we've got a way of looking at these cubes
that's just visually easy to parse right.
It may not be useful for our final game but we don't care about that
at the moment.
What it does is it cues the eye in visually to what's going on in a
reasonable way.
Like we can read that landscape pretty well and so if we want these to
be grass, wish, just for the current time and again, this is not final
art.
This is a
All, it's just because we're going to put whatever the art work says
we should put on there.
When we create these guys and we add a piece on here, we can just
specify like, okay, we want some color value here, you know.
That's going to be some kind of a green.
I don't know what that should be exactly.
But, you know, there's a green that's an awful green.
That's probably the worst idea ever.
Let's, let's try to maybe make that more of a pure green.
I don't know why I did that.
That way.
That's that's like to Green, you know what, why don't I just use color
cop?
Five color cop on this machine.
I love color cop killer cops, my favorite little color utility.
So let's see what color green I want here.
The guy want sort of a brownish green.
All right.
So color cups, great.
Because the thing that I like about it is you can specify the mode and
you can say RGB float, for example.
And it'll just like, give you the the correct values to paste into the
program, which is like, it's just a nice thing of for a Color Picker
to have, you know, I'm saying?
So there we go.
There is a color that will least be somewhat reasonable.
Oh, but you know what those are.
Not those are not Alpha, those are not srgb corrected.
So in order to do that, I do have to
I do have to convert them so because these are linear colors.
I believe.
Yeah.
Oh yeah.
But that also converts to 255 mmm-hmm well
I guess this'll do.
We should probably make a function for this because since we have to
specify colors in linear space here, not srgb space.
We should probably make a way of inputting them properly in srgb
space.
Still feel like that should be
Just still feels a little too light.
I want to see though if we've got that right, come back to me.
Killer cop.
But we did get that right so that was just it was we just need the
that srgb conversion there.
And you'll notice I didn't really do us for to be conversion.
I just did squaring it.
Because in the app right now, we don't actually do a real srgb curve.
We probably should now that we're using opengl in our software.
Renderer, we decided it was too expensive to use real srgb.
So we just used the squared curve, which is, you know, close enough
good enough for government work as they say.
But not, it's not right?
Because the grand, the graphics Hardware can actually do a more
accurate
Version.
Let's try this.
just a darker, maybe even darker still
I don't know.
And let's go ahead and make that.
that math function to
so in this case, we want
we want to basically make a
result value here.
That's just going to square the values and give us our srgb
approximation at approximation of on srg being the srgb inputs.
We would get from a program like color cop.
So, we just want something like that.
So I can say, you know, srgb linearize and maybe we do one for extra
added convenience, right?
I could also say here.
Well.
The reason we'd be using this in most cases is for a hand coded value.
So maybe we make an srgb, linearize that takes in our g b and a and
Returns the V4.
And so then we can just do you know the input equals rgba?
The result equals srgb lunar eyes of the input and then return that
result.
And so that is also kind of handy because then we can sort of say well
if we were going to be doing this, we can now just do this instead.
And pass in hand coded values essentially.
So let's go ahead and and run that.
There we go.
And that's not particularly attractive, but that is what I want
roughly for being able to see what's going on, right?
And so I said, I would explain what I was doing here.
And why?
So the reason that this ends up being an easier thing to see, right?
Is because it sort of does a very simple approximation to what will
often be, how things will look in the real world without actually
taking the time to figure them out.
So let me give you just a little bit of an explanation of what was
going on there and
That produces a more visually parsable result here on day.
367.
So, on day 367, we are dealing with fake.
Cube.
Lighting.
I think my Milton has gone into it.
Can't read the pen mode, one second here.
Where is Martin?
There it is.
There we go.
so, we've got
Something that looks like this.
Right.
And what I was doing was saying, well, alright, I know that these
things are going to be stacked on top of each other a lot or right
next to each other, right?
So we're going to have a lot of situations where, you know, we've got
things that look like this or whatever.
And, and stuff like that, if we were to draw all of these at the same
color, right?
If they're all green or whatever, the exact same green, then we just
get one big, solid mass of color and you can't see anything, right?
That's when I did it.
When I first, did it with white, it was just a mass of white and you
can't to see anything.
So it doesn't give you any information visually.
You can't tell what you're looking at it all.
Now, in the real world, if everything was flat white like that, you
would still be able to tell exactly what was going on.
And the reason is, of course, because of this, it's because of
lighting light strikes, these services.
So even if they were all the same material, the same white material
and had no defects on them, whatever and they're all exactly the same
uniform tone, you would still be able to see it because the lighting
would change so much across the scene.
And so, what did I do to try to approximate that given that we didn't
actually do any
Lighting in the answer is if we assume that there's something up in
the sky, like the sun, shining down on us roughly, then what we know
is the amount of light reaching this surface is going to be quite
high, right?
The top is going to get most of this sun.
Rays are going to hit it and are going to bounce off.
Favorably, towards us, right?
Because if we assume a fairly typical surface, you know, if you look
at the surface from the side, for example, and you've
Got sort of light coming in in this direction then it tends to bounce
out, you know, fairly uniformly.
It bounces maybe a little more up here and a little less towards the
sides.
Let's say a little stronger at the you know, it bounces little
stronger at the exact reflection angles depending on the surface and
stuff like this.
But generally speaking you know you're the more light, you're getting
in the more you're bouncing out for a fairly diffuse kind of surface.
And then if you think about what
On the sides.
Well the sides aren't getting as much of that sun, right?
Because the sun's high up in the sky and the amount of light that's
hitting these Services is less.
So the sides you know should be darker and if we were being even
snootier.
Mr.
Snoot with this new dating and we were actually talking about the
real, like, lighting from the sun.
We would pick kind of, we would have sides that were brighter than
other sides because the Sun
Is directional in that sense.
Right?
But what I did is, I did more like a sky lighting, which is to say,
hey yeah.
The Sun in the sky is obviously a very strong point, light source but
there's also overcast days, right?
And then it's kind of more uniform where the lights coming from but
the light is still coming from the top, right?
So anything that's facing upward and is exposed to the top is going to
get most of the light from a big hemisphere of the sky, right?
Meanwhile, the sides are going to get less because any given side it.
Only see one part of that hemisphere right if you imagine looking at
the cube like this.
And here's my hemisphere radiating light down onto it, my sky, right?
Well this top surface can see the whole sky, right?
It can see everything but this can only see one little portion of the
sky.
Right.
You know maybe maybe like that and so it's going to be correspondingly
darker than the top surface.
Does that make sense?
So making the top a brighter color and the sides are darker.
Color is a good way to start.
Approximating a skylight uniform like sort of in radiant gray, sky
light like an overcast day.
And then what I did furthermore is I made them get darker as they went
down.
So I started with a value.
That was a little bit dimmer up here but then when we got down to here
it was a lot dimmer.
And why they do that well again
There's other things at play here.
These are cubes that are stacked next to each other and when cubes are
stuck next to each other, they start to reduce the light visible to
each other as they get deeper down.
Typically, right?
So if I have something like this, where there's a valley here, as I
get further down here, this will be occluding more of the sky from me.
So it's just a guess that oftentimes those things get lower, there's
more stuff blocking them, right?
None of this
Is accurate to any kind of simulation of our scene.
I have done, no actual lighting, but what I did is baked in the way
that lighting normally would react in an average circumstance, right?
Something that sort of does add visual effect like that and we get
something that's easy to, parse visually, would you want this to be
your final lighting?
Absolutely not.
And why not?
Well, you want it to be more accurate?
To what's actually going on, right?
What we'd like to do is have our lighting take into account.
The fact that, you know, here is a big tall Edge next to a lower Edge.
There's probably some light getting removed in this area right from
this blocker.
So you know, that things should get dimmer in here.
And you know, maybe we want some of that directional sunlight as well,
right?
You know, to give it some kind of more color.
So there's, you know, if we wanted to do real lighting even even hacky
real lighting, there's a lot of hacking we
Could do there that would produce better results.
So this is by no means how you would want to do lighting it a real
game.
But in terms of just a quick way to get something you can visually
understand, which is exactly what I needed in this case.
We're you know, that is a really good way to do it, right?
Okay, so now we need to move on too.
The main event which was the multi sample anti-aliasing.
This is one of those things that you do like once and you forget about
it often times unless you're wondering guy.
So this is one of those ones where we're going to have to crawl
through the documentation to find, how to turn it on in the first
place.
But, you know, I can explain the basic idea.
Because that's not so hard to understand going and finding the right
magical, incantation, sauces, and opengl, and so on, might be a little
bit harder.
All right, so let's talk about Ms.
Oops.
Msaa.
And multi sample.
I've lost pressure control again.
I don't know.
I feel like Milton when you switch away from it.
Oftentimes, this is pressure control but I'm not sure why.
Did it?
No, it didn't.
Oh, and I switched back and it came back.
Interesting.
Huh.
I feel like there's a easy to resolve bug there.
But if you could just watch what was happening, it would be easier to
find because that it was just off and then it came back, which is kind
of interesting.
All right.
Anyway, so multi sample and saying, oh and I got so distracted.
By that, I wrote the wrong thing and alpha-2 coverage.
All right, so what do these terms mean?
Why do we care msaa?
You may even if you have never programmed with it before and have no
idea what it would mean in the graphical context.
Necessarily you may actually also already know what it means because
it gets too stuck discussed, very frequently in terms of gaming and
graphics cards and stuff like that.
So you may actually have already learned it and know what it means
anyway, even though you never dealt with it in a programming context,
Alpha to coverage, probably not.
that you probably only heard of if you've dealt one apartment complex,
but
Mother sample anti-aliasing.
Obviously the term anti-aliasing is something that we've talked about
on handmade hero before aliasing is a general term.
It comes from signal processing, I believe, right.
And aliasing is basically, when you are getting sort of like an error,
In discretization.
and maybe I'll
An apparent error.
And so, what this basically means is, you know, if you imagine let's
say an audio is a very common example of it.
If you imagine, you have a sound wave or whatever and you're trying to
represent this sound wave, that's an actual continuous thing in the
real world.
Let's say, well, continuous is hard to say given that we have
molecular and Quantum things and whatever, but, you know, at the
degree to, which humans can perceive it, there is no aliasing.
Let's say,
And so, we're talking about something that we're introducing as an
artifact, if we are to sample this at regular intervals, right?
Then when it ends up happening, is at those regular intervals, you may
end up producing a curve that is nothing like the existing curve,
right?
And so what ends up happening is, when you take something continuous
and you turn it into something discreet, like, we have to in
Computing, usually, you end up with the possibility of creating
artifacts, you know, and apparent errors that are apparent to the
person who's using, whatever it is trying to listen to the
Audio or view the graphics.
You end up introducing error that has nothing to do with any that has
nothing to do with how you're actually simulating anything internally.
You may be doing everything, right?
It's just when you actually get to the point where you need to display
it somehow or put it out, the audio speakers, you only have a limited
number of sample points to work with and when you produce those sample
points, you end up with this error even though they're accurate,
right?
Like, even though we're talking when I sample this curve, I didn't
sample it wrong, I sampled
Exactly where it should be, but it just isn't enough information.
I needed like all these other points in here to capture the Peaks and
troughs and I just didn't have a high enough sample rate, right?
This is called temporal aliasing, by the way, which is when you have
an aliasing artifact in time, right?
Because here's time.
Here's amplitude.
Right?
My sound wave.
The same sorts of things happens in graphics.
And it happens in graphics when we discretize to the pixel grid,
right?
We've got these pixels.
And I want to draw a triangle.
Well, the triangle is just like our audio waveform over here.
The triangle has infinitely precise edges, we can describe in.
Mathematical terms.
That is what we're actually trying to draw.
However, when we go to convert those infinitely, precise edges into
actual discrete pixels.
A number of discretization steps occur.
First of all, we only have floating point which is not infinitely
precise, that's not that big of a deal.
It is still precise enough these days floating point.
Is plenty accurate for our purposes.
In the old days when it was fixed point.
This was something that was much.
Trickier obviously, but so when we're using floating point, we know
that we're going to get a very accurate location in terms of pixels.
So no real harm there.
But then when we actually go to rasterize at every given pixel, you
know, if we only wanted to produce that much of a triangle but we have
to make a decision as to whether to fill this whole pixel or not you
can see how we get the same kind of aliasing artifacts, maybe we
decide to fill this one right.
But we don't decide to fill this one and then we do decide to
To fill this one.
You get these like, stair-steppy little like crispy pixel patterns on
the edges and nobody likes that, right?
That is not a sexy thing to see these crispy little, you know, sort of
hard pixel edges as you go.
So that's the aliasing that we're talking about, in terms of msaa.
So anti-aliasing obviously are techniques designed to combat the
objectionable visual artifacts that are produced from this process of
discretizing, to whatever it could be, you know, audio or the Grid or
whatever.
But anything where the the
Regular sampling destroys or just sampling in general, sampling of a
signal with more Precision than the sampling produces objection.
All artifacts to the viewer or listener whatever.
So anti-aliasing obviously yet techniques designed to prevent these
aliasing problems from being a parent.
Obviously we can't increase the pixel resolution we only have whatever
resolution the monitor has but we can maybe do things to help improve
it.
Now what we've done in handmade hero so far,
Is to do our anti-aliasing.
What we do is, we say, okay, let's just say that in the alpha channel,
right?
We're going to encode RGB a
In the alpha Channel.
Let's go ahead and code rather than just an RGB value.
That says, what the color should be when we're dealing with stuff.
Let's also encode a value that says how much of the pixel we were
trying to cover and the way that we did that is we said let's have a
Sprite and the Sprites going to have the graphics in it and all around
the edge of the Sprite.
The alpha values will indicate.
How much was covered there?
This way, when we draw the Sprite to the screen we can blend in just
just that amount of color that sort of simulates, a pixel being shared
between the Sprite and what was underneath the Sprite, right?
And that's
We got those nice soft edges.
Right.
But now we can't do that same technique anymore.
Why?
Because that requires us to sort.
In order to do that technique properly, we would have to sort our
Sprites and the whole point is we don't want to sort them.
We don't want to know what order we draw our Sprites and we just want
them to work.
Okay, so what we'd like to
Do is have a technique that allows us to draw in Sprites.
We're we're saying that we only cover a piece of a pixel sometimes but
have that still work, right?
Well it turns out the 3D graphics cards have to handle, not
necessarily this case as their primary case but a different case
that's related and the case that they have to handle is exactly this
one, right?
Most of the time when we talk about
Multi sample anti-aliasing.
As we'll see you in a second.
What 3D graphics cards are trying to solve is they're trying to solve
the problem of drawing actual triangles.
Because remember, we are drawing Sprites but 3D, graphic cards are
more about drawing shapes, right?
And yes they cover those shapes with actual textures and stuff like
that, but a lot of times they don't have Alpha necessarily they are
solid in terms of the texturing on them and
Part that gives them form is the fact that there's you know, millions
of triangles making up the actual shape of the thing, but somebody
modeled in mud brush or whatever, right?
But brush, that's good.
I combined mudbox and zbrush into one tool called Mud brush.
That doesn't exist.
Sorry.
The someone modeled in mudbox or is he brush?
Or mud brush the new tool for modeling.
3D.
All right.
Anyway, so what they have to do is they have to try and figure out how
to get rid of those crispy edges of the triangles themselves, what
that means is they need, and again, they have exactly, they're dealing
with exactly the same problem.
We are in terms of the aliasing, just not with Sprites.
They've got the same problem of the edges.
And they also don't want to sort, right?
They don't want to try and sort triangles in sort of the gpus that
that handle anti-icing this way they want to draw the triangles in,
whatever order they came in and then still get a reasonable result for
a pixel where a triangle only covered part of it.
And more specifically, perhaps, where many triangles crossed, right?
Like maybe I've got
Multiple triangles coming through a single Pixel and each one only is
covering a certain place, right?
And I still want something reasonable to happen here, right?
So the way that the graphics cards handle this is, well, there's been
multiple techniques of the years but msaa is the current technique
that is mostly used its multi sample anti-aliasing, what it means, as
its name implies is rather than only
We tracking one Z value Z buffer, and color value.
depth, buffer, and color value for a
Let's distribute some samples in a pixel and track them.
All right.
And this is when you see 4X msaa, 16x msaa, you've seen these terms,
probably the term, the number plus the X.
What that's telling you is, how many samples were talking about.
So if I'm doing 4X msaa, it means that for every pixel I've got for
you, no points.
It's in that pixel.
I'm actually tracking.
What that means is that when I have something like this case,
Now I know.
Okay this triangle here that passed through it, it colored this pixel
and this sample and only this sample.
So this sample was actually filled right here by this triangle.
A let's say right?
This triangle.
Be hit this one right and this triangle see hit these
Now, A and B, A also hit this one and be also hit this one, right?
So we still have the same problem at our samples, and whichever one
had a z-buffer value.
That was higher, will be the one that wrote in to this location.
So, it's not like it does the blending properly at the samples, it
does the same problematic non blend.
It doesn't do.
Order independent blending at the samples, but now we don't
necessarily care because now we can produce a blended value that, we
know should be 1/4 a 1/4, be and 2/4 or 1/2 C, right?
At this pixel because we only have two output a single color for the
pixel.
And so now we've sort of reconstituted, a proper order independent
blend out of
Dependent samples, right?
So that gets you out of the Sorting business.
So long as the number of samples you need is not too high.
Now remember, in order to produce the exact same output as a blend
would produce, we would need 256 samples.
Why?
Because there are 256 levels of color in our output
Now that's getting even worse.
Uh, D or well, I don't remember what they call them, but the new
displays that are HDR High dynamic range, and can support, you know,
10 B, 16 bit color.
Any of these sort of higher color depths then, even 256 is not enough,
you know, this would have to be 65 thousand samples, right to
reconstitute a value like that.
But chances are, if we're only talking about just the edges of things.
This amount of blending for samples are probably 16 if we if we're
going hog-wild 16 times over sampling is definitely going to be
sufficient to produce just a reasonable soft blend at the edge, right?
Because we don't need the full 256.
You know, we don't need that precise of alpha Bunny at just the edges.
Other things might need it like smoothly, fading in and out stuff,
wouldn't work because you'd have only
sixteen steps of fade.
So it would have to be a fade that occurred over at a speed where 60
frames a second.
It would have to be
So at 60 frames a second and 16 of these, it would have to be
something that covered 256 in only 16 steps.
So it would have to do.
It would have to be fading at 16 color values per second, right?
Which I pers per frame, right?
And so at 60 frames a second, that would be what
960 a second.
So something that went from zero to one color wise in in
a quarter of a second roughly, right?
And so something fading, extremely fast would work, okay?
Because you wouldn't be able to perceive the difference there, but in
general, something that was supposed to be smoothly, fading in and
out, it was not, you know, going to handle it.
You're going to see that step pattern as you get, you know, multiple
frames and they all resolved to the same value because you only got 16
values to resolve to, and then it would stop down and stop down again.
All right, so multi sample into a listing, all that's all it is.
That's it.
And so, all we have to do, you know, is is basically Wade through the
opengl mumbo jumbo to turn it on, but that's all we really need to
know about in terms of sampling, it's that simple.
So what typically happens, the way that this is set up in terms of
GPU, apis is what you do is you say okay, you know, create a Target
With MSA, a right to render to, then you render to that Target.
And what it does, is it renders all of the samples.
So, it's a lot more expensive.
It's 16 times more expensive in terms of number of pieces of
information has to fill.
It's not 16 times more expensive throughout the entire pipeline
because a bunch of stuff doesn't change.
Like the triangle set up phase like vertex, shaders, don't have to
change.
This is only a pixel operation, but it
Makes your pixel operations, a lot more expensive potentially right?
And there's things you can do to mitigate that in our case.
Like, we don't have complicated shaders.
You know, maybe we will eventually have to think about this more.
We don't have complicated shaders right now, so we don't have to worry
about our pixel cost as much, but you can imagine if you have very
expensive shaders, this is where stuff like deferred shading, right
starts to become even more important.
Because now you're talking about 16 times more pixel Shader
evaluations that are happening there.
And so, oftentimes what you want to do is make sure that you're only
actually executing those for the final Z.
People so easy prepass or deferred shading, these things that get more
important as you start cranking up that pixel count.
But anyway, so then you render to that Target and that renders, you
know, 16x more pixels basically more pixels.
But the reason that we don't call them pixels is now should become a
parent to finally because we've often use the term fragment and it's
like why are they called fragments?
Well, oftentimes, they're not actually pixels that are rendering.
Right, in this case, now you can really see.
They are actually these little samples.
So the phrase fragment is just the what opengl uses to say, hey,
depending on how you've got your rendering setup, we don't know that
this has anything to do with pixel.
So calling this a pixel Shader is not right?
It's a fragment Shader, it produces basically Point sampled color
values but we don't know how those are going to be used.
They might be, they might be output to pixels.
They might be output to samples.
There could be it.
You know, so it really is this sort of other idea and it's sort of a
stage of the output that we don't know exactly what what it's and use
is going to be when we're talking about it, we it could be any number
of things you want to do with it.
Hence, they invent the term fragment to, you know, refer to that more
specifically
Anyway, so we create a chart with most a thing we render that Target,
and then there's a thing called a resolved.
And the resolve pass is just a pass that says, all right, at some
point, I have to take these multiple samples.
I have to crunch them down into an actual pixel value.
So I need to go from 16 samples to one sample.
How am I going to do that?
And the answer is with the resolve, the resolve will take that Target
and it resolves.
The target to the, you know, to the output buffer to the actual like
display buffer.
And you have some control there, right?
You can do because you might want to do different things with the, you
might want to depending on what kind of rendering algorithms are
using.
You might want to do different things with the multi samples, the
multiple samples that you have.
We don't because we want to do just straightforward anti-aliasing,
like all were doing, is trying to do the very basic anti-aliasing, but
you can imagine whenever you introduce features, like, multi, sample,
testing, and other things like this, the people out there who are
trying to do the photo realistic renderers, you know, like, you know,
or like the new
Doom engine or, you know, the latest version of unreal or whatever.
You're constantly trying to use these features to do all sorts of
advanced graphical things.
So, you know, you don't want to pre, tell them how they have to
resolve their samples because if you allow them a little control
there, they can get more mileage out of their algorithms and do more
stuff with these than, you know, just simple anti-aliasing.
So, you know, msaa, we're using it for literally.
The way it was designed just take multiple samples, blend them
together, outputting the screen, get us some basic Edge anti-aliasing.
And in an order independent way, that's all we're trying to do.
Not super complicated but you can understand why that
Why?
That sort of thing is a little bit more programmable in certain cases
where you want to have more control, dare to do more advanced
rendering things potentially.
So this is all we have to do for multi sample and hissing, but as
those of you as the sharp independently, motivated viewer will have
already noticed.
I'm sure if you actually take a look at our pipeline, we did not
address a very important aspect.
Act, which is where are we getting the coverage information?
Because this is how they're getting the coverage information in the
case of triangles.
And so, if you take a look at what was happening here, and I gave this
diagram of having four samples on a pixel and some triangles come
through, and you can see which triangles cover which samples.
And so, that makes very good sense, how you would render these.
We don't have any such information, we are not drawing.
Any triangles we are drawing Sprites that have, you know, big areas of
coverage.
And it's inside the Primitive itself deep inside the Primitive itself,
potentially where the value actually is, and it's that Alpha channel,
right?
It's the alpha Channel, that's telling us where that's coming from
where the coverage is coming from.
And so, that's where this other technique comes in, which is called
Alpha 2 coverage.
What Alpha 2 coverage does is
The cover it says, let's read the alpha value and pretend the alpha
value says, Which percentage of these samples are covered.
So if I see an alpha value of one, I know that all of them are
covered, but if I see an alpha value of 0.5, I know that only half of
them are covered.
And so I'll fill in that number.
Now, at this point, we get to a sort of finesse element of this
technique.
There's a tremendous amount of subtlety.
In knowing, where are the samples?
because if I take a pixel right and I say this is 4X msaa,
It's like well, okay, if it's 4X msaa, I could just make it be like a
sub grid of pixels, right?
I could just just divide this pixel into four pieces.
One, two, three, four.
There's my sample right?
Or I could randomly distribute them around right in, maybe like a blue
noises found a fashion, I could do more of a white noise fashion, or
whatever.
Any of these all of this still easily comports with the notion.
That I've got four samples inside a pixel somewhere, but it's not at
all clear.
You know, how to distribute them?
Furthermore, if I've got two pixels next to each other,
There's nothing to say that I couldn't distribute these pixels in ways
that are designed.
So that when I compute the value for this pixel, maybe I use a bigger
region than the pixel itself, maybe I reach into neighboring pixels
for part of the values, right?
I mean, this is anti-aliasing after all.
So there's a tremendous amount of finesse that goes into understanding
how to get the most bang for the buck out of how the samples are
distributed and it may sound very difficult to pick arbitrary
locations for how you put your samples in.
Right.
You know when we had pixels and they're rectilinear, it's like oh it's
very easy to see how triangle fills them.
How do I deal with it?
If it's like in these weird offset positions, how do I even do that?
Well, remember, this is one of the big reasons that the sort of
implicit surface rasterization version of triangle filling is very
useful.
Remember how we wrote hours where we actually just took a rectangular
region and we used the edge functions of the triangle, to determine
what was filled.
Right.
Do you remember this?
Well, that's the same technique you can use.
Use here.
So when you actually write the rasterizer you don't have to really do
any more work you just have.
I mean you do tiny little bit for your samples, you just have an
offset that you know, you apply to the X and Y for that pixel.
And then you just everything else in the routine operates.
Exactly the same, right?
You just go ahead and, and offset those values to the Jitter whatever
it is.
It could be a regular Jitter could be an odd, you know, sort of spread
out Jitter or
Whatever.
And then you just evaluate the edge functions just like you would and
that tells you whether you're inside or outside at that point,
Because of that sort of implicit rasterization structure.
It means that it's really very easy to provide this additional feature
on top.
Whereas, if it was more of a pixel marching algorithm, that would be
very difficult, right?
To make that be efficient.
What that means, is that in a lot of cases.
It's not hard to even allow the user to prescribe what this is.
If you wanted it to right now, that's not necessarily super useful but
you can imagine just setting up tables yourself.
However, it's important to note that often times you want a pattern
that changes from Pixel to pixel because if you don't do that, you can
get aliasing again when things line up with however, you've jittered
your samples, right?
And this gets into a lot of sampling theory that I don't really want
to try to dive into it this point.
But basically, you can think of it sort of as
any regular pattern.
That you use in your sampling.
There will be primitive structures but you will push down to try to
render that will expose that pattern and show visual artifacts.
So what you're trying to do when you design, something like multi
sample anti-aliasing, is you're trying to place your samples in ways
that have no obvious visual artifacts in that way.
This is where blue noise comes in blue noises.
The most favorable pattern for placing samples in all cases.
So,
You know, a lot of times when you're looking at something like trying
to produce the best sampling for multi sample and saying, what you're
trying to do is get as close to Blue noise as you can without having
to actually do the complete work of blue noise.
We'll leave that for a different day.
all right, so
given all of that, Alpha 2 coverage.
What that does is that says, all right, I need to fill these samples
and I've got some Alpha value, right?
And then Alpha value, in this case would be like one point seven five
point five and .25, right?
As I get up from 02 to 0.25, maybe I don't cover anything from point
for to add 5x over 1.5 275.
You know what's actually probably more like buckets like that.
Or something you know?
Who knows how you do it but point being, you figure out how many
you're going to fill based on how many samples there are in with the
alpha value is and you fill those in, but which samples
Right.
And the answer is, I have absolutely no idea at all.
I have literally never looked I would my blind guess is that it would
use some kind of a function of the X and Y
Location of the, well, it couldn't use the Alexa, why location the
pixel because then everyone would choose the same ones for the same
Alpha value.
But it could, it could use the X & Y, location of the pixel, plus the
alpha value itself to determine, which one's it was going to fill in
but I don't really know.
So, I am curious.
This is the first time I've ever really be using Alpha to coverage in
any way where I care about it dramatically.
And so I'm kind of curious where the opengl extension is for it.
To see if it even specifies because it might not.
Okay.
Let's see.
The built in Israel.
Same physician contains the position of the current sample, right?
If I'm practicing straighter outputs, the built-in integer rage,
you'll see a mass can be used to change the sample coverage for
fragment from within the shooter.
Number of us in the raised seal sr3 to where s is the maximum personal
supported by the invitation.
So this looks like we would have to Output it ourself though, so I
guess there's no fixed function way to turn it on.
So it does have sample Alpha to coverage.
But which extension actually introduce that value?
Because it wasn't this one.
It probably was this one.
Yeah, fragment coverage to color.
so, we want the
Opposite of that is the only thing.
Come on, guys.
Someone must have this in here.
Well somewhere, somebody must have first proposed it and when they did
they had to specify either how it worked or that everyone could do it
differently and I just want to find wherever the first one was, but
unfortunately, well, okay.
We're attributes sampled.
That's probably not going to help us.
This is not giving me the answer that I want.
I just, I just want.
I just want someone to show me the extension for this.
I feel like
That shouldn't be that hard to find.
Right.
I mean, shouldn't that be pretty easy?
I feel like that should be pretty.
Z.
Well.
Maybe we'll just have to let it not be known until next week because I
don't really feel like spending too much stream time trying to find it
but point being somewhere.
Somebody at some point will have had to have said how it determines
which samples to cover, and I'm not sure what that, if that is
specified in a rid, like, rigid way, like if you're implementing
Opengl you have to do this or whether it's, you know, more ad hoc
where they're like anything, anybody who wants to invent something
that does something reasonable can.
So it's just a the ideas.
It just has to cover this many samples.
It doesn't matter which of the samples are covered.
So that's I don't know.
You can see why it would matter because if you have two Sprites that
are covering the same square and they both have an alpha value of
something, you want to know what happens.
So, it's important, it's not an irrelevant.
A situation.
So I don't really know why there isn't, I was expecting to find.
I guess it might have been because it's in maybe because it's in
Opengl 1.3, maybe it was introduced as the part of the spec itself and
was never an extension or maybe not.
But if it was an extension, I can't find it.
Unfortunately.
But oh well.
So anyway that's that's the entirety of it.
Notwithstanding the fact that I don't know where to find a definition
of exactly how it chooses, how to fill.
That is what will happen.
So for our purposes we need to be able to do all of those things.
Right?
Some are easier than others, obviously, GL sample coverage and
enabling that is the easier of the two.
So it looks like we don't have to use a Shader for that.
We can use the older version.
I wasn't sure if there was an old version of alpha to coverage.
I thought there was but I never used it myself.
So I didn't know if it, you know, if it was something that was only
possible for
Schrader.
Looks like that's not.
So when we are in here, we certainly can Jill enable this and turn on.
Exactly those values, we have to get them obviously, but we should be
okay.
So, if we take a look at GL sample, Alfred coverage, we should be able
to find docs for it.
Even if we can't find,
Anything else here.
This is not exactly what I want but multi-sample above, I actually
just want
The set of enables for this.
When most of those LGL enabled, with argument Geo, multi sample, a
fragment mask Expedia for each pregnant, that's fine.
If Rusev is mass is enabled.
After coverage, fragment alcohol is used to generate a temporary
modification Mass which is and it with fragrant mask.
Again, that's the part that I was trying to find the definition of
because we would like to know what that model if there are rules for
that modification mask or not and you know, off we go after your
version of alpha values to
Specimen values is enabled the the fragments Alpha is set to the
maximum allowable value.
That's right.
Get that part after conversion of alpha values to masks.
If replacement of Alphas is enabled, she'll enabled with argument GL
sample Alpha.
21 the fragments Alpha is set to the maximum allowable value, okay,
don't think we actually need that.
Finally, if fragment Mass modification is enabled GL, sample coverage
defines an additional modification mask.
Oh, no, we do want that, I see what that's saying because we don't
actually want blending to occur here, right?
We're trying to not actually do blending anymore.
So that this that takes the samples Alpha value, and Jack's it to 1 so
that it won't do any blending.
It's only using the alpha for the coverage.
So we probably want all of those, right?
So we want GL sample, Alpha to coverage.
We want Jill sampe Alpha sample, Alpha 2 1.
And we want Geo, multi sample as well.
I think we want all of those enabled because they're all useful for
us.
So the only one we don't need is DL sample coverage.
G else ample coverage would have us specifically The Mask more
directly.
So that would allow us
Say, hey, we're trying to fuss with the mass for this drawing pass in
some way globally and we don't need to do that.
So I think that's it.
For what we would need.
I'm assuming these values are not present at the moment, but I could
be wrong, I am not wrong.
So we need to be able to get those.
We can get those out of the GL Corps, our food,
Here is all of these guys.
I'll just grab them out and drop them in here, so that's all we need
in terms of enabling those this again allows us to turn this stuff on.
So I believe that's all we really have to do to get Alpha 2 coverage
and multi sample working in terms of telling the render, like the
actual rasterization phase to do it but that will not actually
Enable multi sampling in our case, due to the fact that we haven't set
up a multi sample buffer yet.
So you know, when we when we render this we're not going to get none
of those effects even though we're calling Jian able on them.
None of those effects are actually going to work because we don't
actually have anything creating the buffer, the backing buffer for
them.
But hopefully that makes some sense there.
What I did want to say real quickly,
Is, I believe we had a question about screen door.
Transparency.
And I just wanted to point out that screen door transparency and this
are basically the same technique right Alpha to coverage is screened
or transparency.
It's just screened or transparency being done at a resolution higher
than the screen resolution so that you don't see it as screen door
transparency.
You see it as Blended color values right because screen dark pants.
Transparency is basically saying well all right, you know, I'll fill
every other pixel with this render.
When I'm rendering guy, one when Brendan guy to I'll fill the opposite
mask and then I'll get some transparency in there because you'll be
able to see both of them, but you'll see it as kind of a stippling
pattern.
Well, if I do this, but then blend these two together right now, I
don't see that simple powder anymore.
I might see some art of some discoloration that indicates this Tuple
pattern, if I don't use enough samples or the samples are two regular.
But again it's basically just doing screen door, transparency at a
resolution.
I'm higher than the screen resolution and then down sampling it,
right?
That's really all Alpha to coverage does.
Alright, so we have to set up a Geo multi sample buffer.
Or I should say a buffer that's suitable for multi sampling.
And again this is one of those things like I said, I haven't done it
in a really long time so I'm going to have to blindly search for
Stuff.
To, to find our multi sample.
So I think
there's two ways we can go with it.
One way you can go with it is you can set up your main render Target
as a multi sample.
Render Target the other way you can go with.
It is just render into textures that are multi, sample textures, and
then leave your output buffer regular.
I think we want to do the, the texture version.
So I believe what we want to do is something like this.
So you can see here if you remember when we were because we already
did some render Target stuff.
We didn't do it for multi sampling.
But we you know, essentially wanted to render to something that we
could then use as a texture later and you can see here me doing it.
I find a frame buffer and then I called Yellow Frame buffer texture 2D
and I pass a texture handle and say this is what we're going to render
to, right?
So what you can imagine is if we wanted to create, if we want to do
the same thing, but we wanted that to be multi sample.
Well, where do we create this texture handle, right?
We call opengl allocate texture which is routine.
We wrote and you can see right here.
What we do is we call GL text image, 2D to specify a texture with some
data and that data just happens to be 0, right?
So we just don't give it any data so it knows.
Well, we're not trying to nationalize this to anything but here's what
it is.
so, in our case,
What we want to do here is we want to set up a multi sample version of
that.
And so you can see that the way that we do that is we call GL text,
image, 2D multi sample and in this case we have exactly the same
information, but instead of it being similar to a texture creation
call, it can optionally pass data, it can no longer be past data,
right?
All right, so let's take a look at this call.
We have the target, which is obviously just going to be the Multiverse
the 2D multi sample.
We've got the
The sample count, right?
We've got the internal format which is going to be the same thing as
it was.
We've got the width and the height, and we've got the fixed sample
locations, and the fixed sample locations is just saying whether or
not whether the whether the sample locations are dependent on where
the image on where in the image you are right.
so,
I'm assuming that there's nothing specifically weird to this.
I can't remember anything about it in particular, but I believe that's
all we would really have to do there and then we should be able to use
it as part of the frame buffer.
So I believe
I'll leave this page up.
I believe.
That we can still just use the same call.
Just making sure there's no other ones that I need to do.
So I believe, when we do buying frame buffer texture,
Let's load up opengl three there.
I believe when we do G 0, by in framework for texture, we can use a
multi, sample Target their right type of texture in Texas.
Barbecue Master face be attached.
So I believe, in this case, we should be able to do.
Gosh, there's a lot of stuff in here.
Temperatures are too short for cubemetricks visits.
The face is to be attached.
So I believe, in this case, we can just specify the multi sample one
and we'd be fine, right?
I don't think there's anything particularly bizarre about that, so I
think that's pretty much all.
We would have to do to start turning on the multi sample Miss of it
all
But again, like I said, it's been a long time.
I can't quite remember.
So I don't really know if that's true.
All right, so we also need to turn off our Alpha clipping for this.
We were previously doing a thing that we wouldn't draw if it was
greater than 0, I guess.
Well, you know what, that can stay in because that's an alpha Funk.
That basically only kills areas, we shouldn't be working with at all,
so that can stay in.
It was this one that would have been bad.
So we have to, we have to stick with this one now for reals.
All right.
So when
Doing Ermac render Target thing and recalling opengl allocate texture
here.
What we're going to have to do now is change this to something that
allocates a multi sample.
Buffer basically, right.
And what I'm not sure about to is when we want to actually do our
final bake down.
I'm not sure exactly how to set up the that resolved if in jail
multi-sample texture resolved.
Because again, when we've got
When you've got this situation where we have our texture, which is the
multi sample texture and we rendered to it.
So now it has multiple samples in it.
We have to be able to then render from that texture into a non multi
sampled frame buffer and have that work properly, right?
Let me see.
What the Press is here.
Let's see.
Christmas is linear blit of that is not lace effects as a mulch.
A resolved, I just want some good at data here.
Let me see if I can get anything lit frame buffer.
Probably would be sufficient but what if we want to read from them as
textures?
Do we have to resolve them first entirely?
I guess I'll take a look at this first.
There we go.
Yeah, that shouldn't be necessary.
I want to read from visas textures and I feel like I should be able to
do that, or at least resolve them without having to two round-trip
through there.
So, that doesn't seem
Like what I wanted at all.
So let's take a look at this as a better.
So this is exactly what I wanted.
And this is exactly what I just said.
So this all comports nicely with what we were talking about there.
Once you've rendered your scenes, must use can spray the entire
episodes here by putting your mother sampling frame buffer object to
the back buffer, using giblet frame buffer.
So that is, if we just want to splay it but what if I want to use it
for rendering, surely there is a way to resolve it into a texture
know.
So I guess I don't know.
I guess we'll try it this way first and see.
I mean one thing that is true is so if GL blipped frame buffer is the
only path that can resolve a multi sample buffer, we still could
generate textures with that because since we are binding, both frame
buffers, right?
if we're binding, both frame buffers, then we should be able to
when we bind,
When we bind the read frame, buffer will bind our custom frame buffer
that has a texture loaded.
When we bind our draw frame buffer instead of binding the the default
frame buffer, we could just bind another custom frame buffer that had
our texture as a Target, right?
So we can do the resolve that way.
Maybe that's the way they want us to resolve from a texture to another
texture but I don't really know.
Like I said don't really recall but that is certainly possible, Right?
That would give us the ability to specify that, that's what we wanted
to have happen.
What I would point out here is that since we're going to be going down
this route, this also gives us the opportunity to get rid of some of
the srgb stuff potentially because if we can get GL blit frame buffer
to do the srgb conversion there.
That would mean that we do good, we don't actually need to do to get
an srgb back before.
Buffer from Windows, which would eliminate some of the code on that
side and would be nice, right?
So there's that.
So let's see here.
Default it should be window system.
Frame buffer is non blorp Hardware lost book.
Serrations used to pass feel blah, blah blah.
No I know what I want.
so basically, what I want to know is Will blit frame buffer do an srgb
conversion if the two buffers are set up,
As such, I don't know if that makes sense.
What I'm saying?
But
An application which has is nonlinear Vector data.
And by the way, you can kind of see
I mentioned at the outset of this episode that there's a bunch of
black box next to it, and I guess I'll just sort of drive that point
home here.
So, again, this is one of the reasons that I find GPU programming.
So, and satisfying to, is that
Of times really mostly?
What you're doing is just spec jockeying.
Like it's not like, I don't know what I would go right to write the
rasterizer that did this multi sample result.
And I would know whether I was going to put srgb in that resolve or
not.
It's very straightforward, right?
But because it's this crazy non-orthogonal hodgepodge of like, mush
together stuff and all the graphs apis are different and all the gpus
are different.
They're not really programmable Hardware in the traditional sense.
They're like spot programmable, right?
You end up in this weird case of like all the you have to just hunt
down all these special features all the time.
It's really annoying because it's like
It spends a ton of time not doing anything that involves solving a
problem.
Like it's not like, I don't know where the srgb conversion should
happen, I would like it to happen there, and if I wrote that code, I
could just go put it in.
But instead I'm constantly having to go like, oh, can it do it here
Willie?
I don't know.
Let me look at the speck.
Okay, well that work on most Hardware are there bugs there?
Okay, maybe I shouldn't put it.
Their mission put it somewhere else.
Can I put it somewhere else?
Can I even put it here?
I don't know yet.
If what, if if I enable frame buffer
Srgb or not.
Will that is that going to take into account here and it's just like
it's just a basically, a complete waste of programmer time, right?
That at no point.
Are you actually dealing with the problem?
The problem is Trivial.
We already know what it is and it's simple to understand and solve so
it's really it's this really nasty like it's not, it makes me always
whenever I deal with it really appreciate x86.
And x64 as architectures where it's just like look.
Here's the instructions said, here's what it does right out, whatever
you want.
Go nuts, right?
And it's very easy understand.
It's very well specified.
I know exactly what's going on in a given time and it's really nice
whereas with the GPU stuff, it is nothing like that.
It's like most of your time is just spent figuring out the magic
incantation to do something whether that will work on the machine
you're working on at all right.
Now, whether it will work on the end users machines,
Whether there's some other way of doing it that would have been more
efficient but you didn't know about it, you know, and it's just very
unsatisfying.
I find this whole thing to be very unsatisfying and I definitely long
for the day when gpus kind of go away is a thing and it's just another
programmable piece but we're still not there.
Maybe someday maybe before I'm dead.
Although I'm getting pretty old.
So anyway, if we want to get started on this anyway that the blind
here with the srgb, I'm not sure what it will do.
So we'll have to take a look at that, a little more carefully.
But for starters, we can certainly create GL, text 2D multi-sample
And also we've got here on the opengl wiki.
We've got an example of at least what the opengl wiki, people think to
be the right way to do it, and it is showing exactly what we were
expecting here in this case.
Now for creating our drawable,
Textures here.
I'm going to stop calling opengl allocate texture and start.
Putting this in line.
Because in this case,
I think we've got hoops.
in this case, I think we want to start treating this very differently
from our normal texture allocation case because since it's going to be
a 2d multi sample buffer, it's going to be very different
in this case here, where we're taking the multiple samples, I feel
like
That's interesting.
Why are we?
Why are we not passing srgb there?
I don't like the fact that my head is in the way I'm going to switch
over to the side.
like,
We've got this opengl default, internal texture format.
Oh, okay.
Whoo.
Alright I got nervous there for a second.
I looked at this and thought that, that was that I forgot that there's
the internal texture format and the submission texture format, which
are different.
So that's fine.
Okay, sorry, I got got real nervous there so I believe we can just
pass srgb.
Multi sample format and then it will still do the linear to srgb
conversion for us.
We know what the width and height are
And we don't want regular sampling.
We want irregular sampling because that'll give us less artifacts.
Like I was talking about before.
So I believe here we want a GL false value and for number of samples,
I guess for at the moment, we'll go hog-wild and say 16.
But I don't know whether this card support 16 multi sampling to be
honest.
In fact, I guess we should probably call a GL get to determine
How many samples of can actually do, or what it's, what its best
sample type is.
Because I'm assuming that there is a Max sample.
Here we go.
So let's see.
Do do do do.
So I believe it would be g l samples.
I don't know if that's actually true or not, but I'm going to go ahead
and try to get g l samples and just see what it is.
So we can have an idea.
I believe this is an integer.
And I don't know that we've ever really done a Jill get before.
Have we?
Yeah, we've never really done one before.
You've never checked a cap.
So opengl has a bunch of these
Jill, get calls.
And so you can kind of see how they work here, right?
You say what kind of a thing you're trying to retrieve?
So in this case we're trying to get an integer, right?
And the V is just because it's taking a pointer.
So it might be numerous it depending on which one you pass or you
might get back more than one.
So I'm going to go ahead and say, you know, Max sample count and I'm
going to see what it tells me.
Right.
Get rid of all this.
And so I'm going to say that we'll just ask for the mass sample count
at the moment, but maybe not if it's, we might clamp it.
So I might be like, if Mac sample count is greater than 16, max ammo,
count equal 16, because it don't want to go above that, certainly,
And so let's try to get this path working with a step through it.
So, in this case, we also need the GL texture, 2D mother sample,
Define everything else.
I think we're good with.
So in this case we've got our texture handle coming back here.
Expand this detector handle.
Like so and we're using get with draw region.
Get height for our region as the size of these.
So I'll paste those in here.
There we go.
And so now all we need is to get the actual API stuff that we need for
multi sample and put it in here, right?
And to do that, we're going to have to get the specification for
these.
And again, usually what I do for that is just grab them from the ARB.
No oops.
I think I closed.
Yeah.
So I usually just go to the core our header file.
and we need,
Multi sample.
Texture, what was it called?
Texture 2D multi sample.
So, we really just need only this one.
and then we do need the
function as well.
Oops.
So here is GL text image, Trudy multi sample.
If we take a look at that sausage gentlemen, we then need someplace to
oops.
Some place to put that.
What usually goes in here, although it looks like, do we not?
Do we not have any opengl extension functions yet?
Besides wiggle?
Is that really true?
Huh.
We were pretty.
We were pretty clean.
That's interesting.
But here's our wiggle.
Get proc address calls.
And so yeah, I guess that was all.
We actually did.
Hm.
Interesting.
Well, either way, I'm going to start making some here that are in the
opengl area because in general, we're going to want them on all the
platforms, not just windows.
So, the typedef for these guys, which, you know, is the same kind that
kind of comes out here.
You can see, I'm going to go ahead and
Start a place for these to get to fine.
And we'll call this g l text image, 2D multi sample as the type and
then we'll put in, you know, all of these things as they are.
And then down here, we'll just say, okay, we've got one of those.
That is this function.
Variable.
And now we can call it.
Of course, it'll be set to zero at the moment, which obviously is not
the best thing to have it be set to.
So we need to enter win32.
We need to go ahead and grab the multi sample.
so, I think
That should get us initialized so that we can actually create the
buffer that were that we need.
But of course, we haven't actually done anything with that buffer yet
so we do have more work to do as you'll see in a second.
I'm going to go ahead and set a breakpoint in there though because I
would like to before we go any further.
Take a look at that sample value that's coming back and just see
whether or not that function works at all.
So I'm going to set a breakpoint here.
oh, and I guess we have to before I do that I'm going to have
Force it.
I thought we were still creating one extra sample, one extra layer but
I guess because there's nothing because we got rid of that stacking
stuff.
There's nothing happening there at the moment.
All right, so
if that's the case that I'm going to have to force it.
I want this to happen with the max render Target stuff.
I want that to happen for the render targets.
I need to create, even the first one has to create a render Target,
right?
Which means that use render targets kind of has to work if that makes
sense.
So we probably want to do here that says
Error dialog in platform layer.
If use render targets.
Can't happen.
Because we're going to need that now.
Because if our entire pipeline is going to be based on Multi sample,
we need to be able to create a render Target at least one render
Target.
That's the multi sample render Target, right?
I suppose, I could try to get a multi sample.
Render Target from Windows as the default one, but I'm pretty sure
there's no such thing as Hardware that supports multi sample
anti-aliasing.
This method that doesn't also support render to texture.
I could be wrong about that though.
So anyway, if we want to do is render targets, we use, we can just say
that has to happen when we use max render Target index.
We can now make that sort of forcibly happen.
Although I think, in this case, we don't really need multiple render
targets at the moment anymore.
Anyway, but where is global frame before count?
So, our Global frame of account situation, now needs to allocate the
first frame buffer.
Like it would allocate any of the other frame buffers as well, right?
And so, basically, all of our frame buffers would be the same in this
case and Global frame.
Buffer count would start off at zero.
When we find these frame buffers as we sort of go through them, we
would no longer do sort of a differing set of
We would always essentially do.
That in all cases.
And then only when we actually, you know, sort of draw the final frame
buffer.
Would we call the final GL viewport to the drum in drum acts, right?
So basically at the end of this,
What we would have to do is this is where we would sort of do our, our
final draw down.
And this is where we would do our GL, put frame buffer call.
All right, so assuming that we're going to do that now, we should get
forced into here because even just having it a zero with frame buffer
where we have one frame buffer is is sufficient to trigger it in here
where I go get integer vgl samples so oh man does this card not have
multi sampling that can't be true.
Hmm.
this might not be the maximum sample, count, this might just be how
many are currently
Currently bound, if that makes sense.
Let me I'm actually interested to know.
if I move this over here,
does this do anything?
Although, that's not going to actually bind it.
So let's see here.
First trans exception, status equals frame buffer in complete so we
don't get a free complete frame buffer.
After we have bound this we did get a texture back but that's going to
happen.
Regardless when we called this, we don't know whether this actually
worked or not, right?
This might have worked or it might not have worked.
so, when we
when we do Global frame, buffer handles,
We presumably got one and we did.
So all of this looks like it's working properly but the validation
step does not actually work.
Right?
And the validation step, not actually working is probably because I
tried to do the multi sample.
Bind.
Oh well, not necessarily the GL frame buffer called cure.
We forgot to update it with 2D multi sample and that's required as
well.
So, let's see how we do here.
Not so good.
Let's see what that status actually is.
No.
360 55.
Well, looks like we're going to need and hacks, my friends.
Eight cd7.
Incomplete missing attachment.
Hmm.
So I don't know if that's actually true.
Oops.
Because we shouldn't need another attachment than that should we?
But if our, if we can't actually create a 16 x multi sample, that
might be sufficient to have that happen, right?
Let's double-check
that there's nothing else.
Particularly odd going on here.
So you can see here is the G Elgin texture call.
Here's the bind texture call and the text 2D multi-sample, right?
And that's exactly what we're doing here.
I don't think we're doing anything weird there.
At least hopefully not with the generating, the frame buffers.
That already got done up here, right?
And so we're just going through and specifying them and we're
specifying them pretty much exactly the same way that it's find them
here.
So I don't expect there's anything particularly worried about that.
So the only question is really whether or not there's no way to create
multi sample on this particular Beast.
I'm not sure I suppose we can check to see if it supports multi
sampling at all, but it pretty much we know it has to because if it
didn't support multi sample,
Then she'll text image 2D multi sample would not actually exist,
right?
Presumably wouldn't let us call GL text image, 2D multi sample on a
card that didn't support any multi sampling.
I wouldn't think it wouldn't have found that
function, right?
And if we take a look at our g l extension string, I'm just imagining.
We could also
verify that, that was there.
so if I go ahead and cut and paste this over and scratch buffer,
So, GL are multi.
Sample is in theory supported.
so, I feel like
Nope, that's not what I wanted.
I feel like this should be okay.
Right.
Don't see the actual extension here, unfortunately.
G l, Max samples, that looks what I was looking for.
Do we have g l?
Max samples.
Is that in core ARB.
GM Max, that's what I wanted.
So it looks like I just queried the wrong value but this doesn't help
us determine why we were having the bug.
I just really wanted to know what that value actually was because I
have no idea on this car.
It's a really old card.
I have no idea what it can and can't do.
I'm totally
Totally no idea.
So, let's go ahead and put this back in.
Max sample count.
and it's saying that it has to be Max samples - 1
is that implying that I need to bind a different texture for each.
Sampler, something.
Because that's that can't be true but it says sample specifies.
The number of samples in the image and must be in the range.
0 2, gee, L Max samples.
So that sounds less like a sample count and more like a Max sample
number, right?
Because if it was a count 0 wouldn't make any sense.
Like, you can't have a buffer that has no samples in it, right?
So that's a bit weird.
I don't really know what to make of that.
But we'll take them at their word for now since we're almost out of
time anyway.
And will maybe take a look at this in a little more detail later.
So I'm going to go ahead and take a look and see what happens at the
max sample count.
Query here and see if we can't actually get a value now.
Let's go just back out of X.
So here it seems that we'd have 8X multi sampling, right?
So our sample count is going to be 8.
In this case, we're going to pass seven to their, I guess is what
we're going to get.
I don't know if that'll actually do anything.
Like I said, we have no way of really knowing if that worked.
And then here we get a status that we don't have the, we have
insufficient attachments.
But again, I'm not sure why?
Because we created a multi sample,
Buffer, just like before.
And I don't see anything particularly unusual about that, right?
That all looks pretty straightforward.
And it is in the color attachment and there shouldn't be any
requirement for us to put.
We're going to have to put a depth texture in here because we do use
the depth buffer now, but there shouldn't have been any requirement
for us to do that in order just to get a complete frame buffer, right?
That is not something we should have had to do.
So, I'm not really sure what the deal is with that.
So, a little bit of stumper there.
But I guess it's time to go to the Q&A anyway.
So I'm going to have to leave it there and we will have to
we'll have to pick it up next week.
What?
What would happen if I pass zero here?
so any any call to jail, text image, 2D multi, sample is a bug as far
as its concerned
Can I replace that?
With a regular text image call.
And get something reasonable.
Oops.
So it's only if I call GL texture, 2D multi sample that it is grumpy
about.
I guess here's a question for you.
And again this is just not remembering very well.
I wonder if what we have to do here is when we actually bind the
texture, we have to bind the texture to the multi sample slot.
Right.
Nope.
Not so much.
Although I am curious about that because it would seem like you should
do that.
Did they do that in the example?
Yeah, they do.
So I'm going to leave it that way.
So if I do slot and I'm just going to abstract slot away to hear,
right?
so, if I essentially make this code path work in both directions,
Then that would allow me in theory.
Anyway, to switch between the two past pretty easily, right?
So I can do GL texture.
2D
Or multi sample now, and I just want to make sure that I can actually
do that, right?
So there's that path which works properly and here's the multi sample
path, which does not work properly.
and we're not sure what it's actually grumpy about in this particular
case, but
at least now we've got both path so we can easily check them against
each other.
So I feel like this is the appropriate call structure.
It looks like now that I'm binding to the correct place by and
textures Jen and bind, I don't assume you need because again they
don't seem to suggest on the opengl wiki and current US anyway.
They don't seem to suggest that there is anything in particular.
You would have to do to generate one of them because it's just a
regular texture.
Like everything else.
You do bind it differently, right?
But everything else is pretty much the same and yeah, I don't, I don't
really see any other.
I see any other fussiness there.
It looks pretty straightforward to me, unless there's something wrong
with calling these texts parameter things.
One thing I could ask as well.
It's, I could do a GL.
Get error.
Just to verify what?
Was actually happening here.
Jill get her will tell me whether there's an error.
Not so I can do G, will get error.
In multiple places like this.
And then what I can do is just say like, hey, why don't you tell me
when the first time is that you saw the error if there was one at all
and we'll go from there.
What did you say?
Oh,
Just to see if there are any.
And so this is kind of what I would expect.
You can see that we don't have an error so I can actually bracket the
error exactly and say because I was guessing that the problem is
Margie, I'll text image to the multi sample fails
So you can see right here.
There is no, opengl are at this point, but when we get to hear there
is so we know that this call failed, right rgl text image, shooting
multifamily sample failed.
Now, we believe we've got it, okay?
Because we're using a slot that's Jill, texture, you much
multi-sample, we're passing what we believe to be reasonable values,
but hey, we don't really know.
And, and so, you know, it's, I guess it's a potentially open.
The default internal texture format.
You know, we could try not asking for srgb.
If somehow srgb is messing it up we can use exactly the syntax used in
here rather than using srgb and I don't know if that's, I wouldn't
assume that that would have anything to do with it but you never know.
Oops.
What did I just do?
First chance exception access violation.
What is the access violation?
Opengl render commands.
So we're calling into this pointer and it's got an access violation in
ati's driver.
How is that?
We're not calling anything.
We're not passing anything.
Right, I mean, all we're doing is calling text image, 2D multi sample.
Wow.
so basically, we can crash amd's driver by specifying a sample count
within the parameters that it gave us
Weird.
So if I specify anything other than 0 here,
nope, I can specify one.
How about two?
Two's.
Okay, but three is not on the table, my friends.
Three is just not on the table.
So the instant we call GL text image multi sample with three.
We are we are toasted.
We are we are access violating, presumably, anything above 3.
Also fails.
No, so for is okay.
Five is not.
So, let's see if Max sample count without the minus one, which is what
I would have expected to pass in the first place is actually, okay,
and it is.
So I think those docks are just probably a little misleading.
It looks like because they said it had to be max ammo, count minus 1.
It looks like it actually has to be Max sample count, unless a tti's
driver is busted, which could also be true.
I suppose, I'm guessing that that means that specify
Srgb as the internal format is not acceptable because it seems like
trying to specify that is just not working.
I don't know what that means for us because that means we can't have
an srgb back buffer.
In this case,
I guess, I don't know.
But anyway, I guess I will go to the Q&A now because we're over time
already, at least now we know how this works.
I don't know what is going on with that driver though, because that
seems real weird.
That seems real weird to me, I don't know what you guys think about
that, but that does not.
That does not seem like proper behavior.
I mean far be it from me, I'm not an opengl expert or anything but
that just does not make a lot of sense.
Can you check if the status is changed after updating blind texture,
which bind texture, do you mean
This one.
Or do you mean the actual bind?
I'm not sure what you mean by the buying texture.
Did you remember to prefix your GL text image?
Multi sample to D with a win API AKA Center called prefix.
I thought I did but I might not have
Yeah, I did.
Also, I don't think that would do anything because this is x64.
I suppose this, in this case, I also
I also sort of have this problem of the renderer stuff here, kind of I
guess needs to be here because that win API is a platform specific
situation.
So I suppose I actually need that to be here.
Oh so now we've got so there's GL Vine frame buffer, where is that
getting getting gotten?
Win32 in it, opengl.
So, I put that other guy in the wrong place.
That's probably not that, that could be part of it.
I felt like something had to be up there.
So, that was wrong because we were calling that on the wrong.
We were calling that in the wrong way.
We were getting it before we had made the right context current, so I
don't know if that might have been part of our problem.
Let's take a look.
Can we do this now?
Probably not.
But
yeah.
Oh well thought it was worth a shot.
Mansfield out your text parameter.
I needs to use Jill texture slot between most of our yes, good.
That's a very good point.
I don't think that'll probably have anything to do with our current
bugs butt.
It would cause problems in the future.
These all always need to be slot.
That should work the same as it was.
Whoa.
Although it didn't there is an error there, I guess.
Oh, you know, you probably can't set the filtering.
To linear.
Multi sample buffers, I bet.
Hmm.
Or maybe you just can't set these at all.
Yes, it might be that you can't set these at all.
Now, there it is.
So I would paint a Target on a texture.
Jill, 2D.
All their sample.
So, I feel like we should have been able to specify those.
But we are not able to.
so, I'm not sure why that is
Is there a way to debug or have a visual example of the multi sampling
process?
I mean you can sort of hack one together that draws like different
parts of it to try and figure out what's going on but not not the way
you might want.
Not really no.
You kind of have to construct it.
Maybe we should use GL, debug message, call back and Jill and able GL,
debug, synchronous some time.
Then we can ascertain the Callback and were able to just see where the
GL are, is the debugger.
Yeah, I agree with that and probably we should now that we're going to
be doing more opengl stuff.
I didn't bother doing that before because we weren't doing much with
opengl.
But now that we are we probably should
Yeah, you can't set sample state so I guess even we just can't set
them at all.
So we probably can set the clamping, only or maybe we can't set the
clamping even.
So if we can't set any of those, then it doesn't even matter.
I suppose in that case,
But yeah, that's kind of weird.
I don't know why we can't set srgb there.
That's very strange.
But yeah.
Storing tortoise.
You mentioned in a previous episode that one of the reasons for moving
to 3D was due to Performance research with a sorting.
Would it have been a viable alternative to keep the Sorting results in
permanent storage and then each frame only re sort the entities that
have moved.
Just considering that many entities like trees and to Russell's don't
move.
I don't think it would be.
And the reason for that is that I wasn't changing to Z buffer because
I was afraid about the number of Sprites we have on the screen.
Currently, I was changing because I was afraid about how I would deal.
The number of spread screen, I wanted eventually and some of those
things are like particle systems, right?
Like if I want to have like thousands of particles on the screen or
tens of thousands of particles on the screen, I don't want to sort all
those and those are all moving.
Right?
So I don't think it's a very viable technique to use the Sorting.
I just don't think it's viable.
I think there's a reason we don't sort things in 3D and unless we
absolutely have to and the reason is because it just doesn't
Divided enough performance.
And it's very inflexible, right?
Having to sort a primitive doesn't handle the case where you know
painters algorithm style break it, you know, cycles and stuff like
this.
It doesn't really handle that properly because it can't split
Primitives either.
So I think it's just it's not just like the performance that we were
getting was a problem because it wasn't, we were running fast enough
as we were.
It's just there so many red flags there.
For me, I felt like
that I didn't want to do it.
So yeah, I'm confused as to why we cannot request an srgb internal
format for Gia.
Text image, 2D multi sample and that is problematic.
It could just be because this card is ancient.
So, I will probably have to order a new graphics card to plug into
this machine.
One that, you know, is somewhat more modern, but
Michelle.
This is Casey, I have started working on handmade Vulcan Port earlier
today is that okay?
Well, you know, whatever your whatever back-end you want to use,
I mean, look, we don't have a whole lot of use of the graphics API and
handmade hear us.
So presumably wouldn't be too hard.
But you're going to have to do a bunch of stuff to manage like getting
the rectangle data down there because you're going to have to like,
actually deal with buffers and when they are used and stuff like that,
which we don't have to do because we're going through open Jill's sort
of more straightforward does stuff for you pipeline.
So, yeah, I don't know.
I'm curious.
I'm really curious, though.
If there's some other thing magic thing we're missing there, that's
the reason why.
So at least somebody else reports this having the same problem.
but,
Yeah.
That's the other so Alpha to coverage does order independent
transparency, just like that.
Any serious limitations?
You can think of yet?
Well it's again it's not really.
High resolution enough, right?
So, you know if you want to turn on 16x multi-sample anti-aliasing
then, you know, first of all, you're taking a big hit for that, right?
And on handmade hero, we can probably afford it because we're not
trying to do a bunch of complex 3D geometry stuff.
We're just layering some Sprites on the screen and, you know, probably
we could turn on something like 16 x.
But, you know, that's usually very expensive to turn on.
So first of all, you get that and then even if you turn that on the
transparency, only has a resolution of 16 steps, right at best
probably less because, you know, the you'll get collisions of the sort
of dithering pattern basically
So, it's not really a substitute for sorting yet, right?
It has to would have to have a lot higher resolution to really be a
substitute for sorting, so it's more fourth, it's more for handling,
the edges of things.
Where, you know, that the number of alpha value steps is pretty low
anyway and you're trying to just get like a reasonable sort of pattern
on the edge.
That's not going to be a harsh Edge it.
I don't you know
I don't think we could lean on it to do stuff like actually
transparent Sprites and stuff like that, you know, where we're trying
to have like colored transparency and stuff like that Regional levels
that fade in and out or something that I don't think it's going to be
able to do.
Stuff to that level of fidelity.
But yeah, otherwise it does you know for for the limited case, it does
handle it order independent.
But again, it does have some real limitations.
It's not an instant saw, it doesn't, it doesn't solve everything.
Snoring tortoise.
For those of us who are very interested in engine development.
What are some of the more advanced platform features that you would
recommend?
Can you be a little more specific there?
I'm not sure what that means.
Alright, doesn't look like there's any other questions coming in.
So I'm going to go ahead and close these down.
I really wish we had some idea about whether this was correct or
incorrect.
That it doesn't allow multi-sample buffers in srgb because that's real
weird, my opinion.
I'm really not sure to make what to make of that.
And the fact that we wouldn't be able to use srgb, there would be
pretty annoying.
I mean we don't really need srgb to be fair.
The only reason we ever did it is because Juan insisted that we do it.
so, I guess I would say
I'm just not sure if it's unreliable to be able to set a multi sample
buffer.
That's also srgb.
I'm not sure where that leaves us.
And I how I don't even know how that could be unreliable because all
major games have to be able to do that, everyone uses multi sampling
and they definitely use srgb.
So,
I'm kind of confused as to what's going on there.
It could just because this card is too old and maybe that's the
reason, but it's just kind of weird.
Snoring tortoises on the platform side, like any debugging features.
You mentioned a while ago, that 1935 was light years ahead, in that it
is far more advanced.
Yeah.
Well so
I mean, basically, like the the thing to think about in terms of
engine stuff is just
Platform layer wise, we do on handmade hero the stuff that we have to
do, right?
So basically we implement the features that we need to the extent that
we need them, but it basically means that any time.
If we were going to do something more something different we would
have to extend or change that how we were doing things, right?
So you know, if we wanted to write
Some code in the handmade hero, you know, using the handmade hero
platform layer for example that did something like iterate over a
directory tree somewhere and do a bunch of processing on the files
there and stuff like that.
It just doesn't really have that you know it has a very limited way to
just get what our art asset files are and that's like all I can do,
right?
So a lot of the time savings that we get on handmade hero for being
able to implement stuff from scratch is because we do what we need to
do and not a complete implementation of things that would handle a
wide variety of cases.
So if you want to create a platform for creating arbitrary stuff, you
have more and more work that you have to do.
So I wouldn't say there's anything in particular that like jumps out,
that's like oh, you know, the platform layer that were used at Molly
now is, you know, has this specific feature and this is something
that's important to look at it's more.
The difference between the two is the one that we use at Molly.
Now is designed to basically be the platform on which we build
everything, you know, editing, tools, tools for press.
Sing the art assets is designed to handle, you know, pretty much
anything that you throw at it.
So you can basically write everything to this platform layer and it
always will work.
And you know,
It handles Unicode and it handles, you know, there's no hard limits on
path sizes.
There's no, you know, so it's basically just like doing the
engineering properly for anything, just ends up being a pretty big
difference in terms of what it can handle and what it can't.
But I would not, I would not say there's any particular one feature or
another.
It's like the thing that makes a difference between an advanced
platform layer and it not advanced level or it's more about
completeness and lack of limitations if that makes sense.
hi like PEB cack
problem exists between Kronos and Casey.
I wouldn't say that it's not that I don't like KRON us, it's that I
don't I just don't agree with a lot of the design philosophies all
All right, let's go ahead and close everything down.
Thank you everyone for joining me, for another episode of handmade
here.
It's been a pleasure coding with you.
As always, if you would like to follow along at home, you can always
pre-order the game on handmade here at Oregon.
Come to the source code.
We also have a forum site, you can go to if you want to ask questions
a patreon page, go to.
If you want to support the video series, a schedule bot, you can use
if you want to find out where we're going to be live in an episode
guide for trying to catch up on past stuff.
We, I guess technically we did get the
Other sample working in theory with the caveat that it doesn't support
srgb.
So, I suppose next weekend when we're back, I will be able to actually
do the resolved and start actually using the alpha to coverage.
In theory, but again, like everything else when you're programming on
Graphics apis.
It's just a complete crap.
Shoot and it's always unstable.
It's always very buggy.
It's always unpredictable it often times doesn't work on multiple
machines the same way and it's so he's really unsatisfying, which is
why I don't like it, but we will try it anyway next weekend.
So I hope to see you here for that where we'll see if we can actually
use the multi sample stuff that in theory, we now do have working
properly, although again, we can't see,
To see any reason why the srgb doesn't work, can only suspect that
it's an AMD driver issue, although it maybe have something to do with
the card being too old.
So maybe I'll try to order a more modern car to stick in there so we
can check it out.
Alright, that's about it.
I hope to see you back here next week for that until then have fun
programming everyone.
And I will see you on the internet.
Take it easy, everybody.