Alright.
Hello everyone.
Welcome to handmade hero.
The show.
We could have complete game live on stream before we get started
today.
I wanted to mention something that only just got brought to my
attention, like, literally when I got home from work today.
So I have not had a time had time to even address it myself at all.
But one of the fellows Matt Massacre, I don't even know how to
pronounce his name.
Honestly, because on the he actually on the chat goes by me blow and
am I
Llo, so you've probably never seen this name before on the chat
because it would not have come across as that.
But me, blow whose real name is Matt bhaskaran Haas.
I don't know how you say, it started a patreon because he well, he
needed the money and he does a lot of work on the handmade Hero
episode guide.
Just as a volunteer, he just like goes on there and makes them
If you don't know what that is, if you've never seen it, it's pretty
amazing.
Actually, for people who are trying to follow the series.
If you go on here, you can go to the episode guide and it's got all
the episodes on here.
And then when you go to stuff like this, it's got this crazy.
Like thing on the side that's like all the stuff that happened to that
episode, you can like access it, right.
And this is kind of amazingly good because when you're trying to watch
episodes you know you might not know like oh I think there was a thing
in this episode about blah.
And it's like, oh yeah, now I know exactly just you can just click on
it, go to it.
So he's one of the main people who does those things.
He's done a ton of it and so if that's something that you appreciate
having this episode guide, he's one of the people who makes that
happen and he put up a patreon and so you know, he definitely he
already does way more than $50 a month worth work worth of work on the
episode guide.
No question.
I will be logging on immediately after the show, to make a pledge to
this patreon from the handmade hero patreon, because that is exactly
the kind of thing that the handmade hero patreon should be for
supporting people who are doing this.
And if you are someone who appreciates Us episode guides and would
like to contribute to this patreon, like I said, he already does way
more work than this a month on those episode guide.
So, I would highly recommend kicking a few dollars his way.
I know he could use it and would really appreciate it and
I said he's one of people who makes those episodes guys happen, they
don't just happen by accident, someone's got to sit there and actually
look at the video and categorize everything we do in to into those
times and that's just a lot of work.
So, check it out.
It's pretty easy to get to I think if you want to type it into your
computer, you can actually yeah.
You don't have to use whatever that is.
So it's literally just patreon.com, slash me.
Blow will get you there.
I think you can just, you can just do that and then we'll get you
there.
So check that out.
Out and yeah, check that.
And consider supporting it.
All right.
Let's go ahead and start the episode.
So I'd Hammer here right now we're doing some user interface coding.
We were doing some user interface coding because I thought would be a
good time to show how to do that.
Kind of code.
That's something people are often very curious about how you do it.
So I showing how to do it.
And the reason I'm doing it in the place, we're doing it right now, is
because there's not a lot of reason to do user interface code for
handmade hero because it's not really, you know, it's not a 4X game.
There's not a lot of toolbars and a lot of dialog boxes or things like
that.
And handmade here, it's an action game.
So what I'm doing is I'm taking the opportunity to do some user
interface code while we were doing our debug viewers.
So basically like our thing that views debug information that is the
thing that I'm sort of working on there and we've gotten relatively
far with it.
We're at the point where we can do some pretty cool stuff with it but
there's more to do.
And so I want to kind of jump back in there to it today is day 20 for
again, this is all coding today so if you want to follow along at home
and you have pre-ordered the game on handmade hero dot org, you can
Follow along by unpacking day two or three source code into a
directory.
That's the source code that I'm starting with right now.
So if you want to follow along home, you start with that as your
basis, okay?
So let's take a look here.
Where we are at.
So here is
Our debug system and here is it running.
And when we left it last we kind of have this little thing in here
where we, you know, we sort of had our little, a little test stuff.
And we what we recently did is add the ability to have sort of
multiple versions of a hierarchy and track the state of them
separately so that we can kind of, you know, have have more than one
state of the hierarchy.
So, you know, if we want to have just the render, a
Out here whatever all of these are tracked as independent states.
So when we are accessing them if we want it closed or you know on some
and open on others, that's totally allowed and and isn't at all a
problem for our system.
So basically what we did with the system was make it so that you know
we decouple the concept of the state of the hierarchy from the actual
hierarchy itself so that you know we don't have to worry about kind of
like coupling this the the sort of interaction.
With the thing that's being interacted with and that's just something
that I thought would be interesting to do so we did it.
Now what I'd like to do today is I'd like to start because we're
getting relatively close here.
I feel like on our debug sort of hierarchy View.
What I'd like to do is I'd like to start looking at the actual
representation of the debug variables themselves because what I'd like
to do is kind of make one more leap with the infrastructure with a
debug infrastructure to a place, I think is pretty important right
now.
What we're doing is these hierarchies the underlying
Data for these hierarchies is explicitly constructed and explicitly
exists all the time, right?
When I mean by that, is that, if you are to look in the code, right,
where we've got, we've got these sort of, debug variable types and all
that sort of thing.
If you are to look in the code, you can actually see us construct
right here, the actual, you know, version of this hierarchy.
We've constructed it and it exists in memory, right?
And what that means is that anything that we want to edit right now
has to actually exist in memory as a real debug hierarchy, right?
That's explicitly constructed as as a thing as a real, you know,
living entity.
And one of the problems with that is it makes it kind of annoying
potentially and there's different ways that we can look about.
Look at this, but it makes it kind of annoying potentially for code
that wants to use this to quickly expose debug
Goes to the system because now it's kind of a retained mode thing,
where anyone who wants to expose debug variables, has to kind of go
through the trouble of actually creating them and putting them
somewhere.
Now, that's not a big deal for Global's because for Global's, it's the
same.
It's six of one half dozen of the other because things like whether or
not the ground shook out lines are used is just a global switch that
turns on and off.
It doesn't really matter how we expose that because all it means is
that whatever that Boolean is or however it's defined.
We're just going to make one of these things eventually and then
forget about it and it's something that the debug system could always
use from then on and there's really no mystery to it.
But what I'm a little more interested in is the more complex problem
of things where the game has to fit wants to expose and it doesn't
necessarily want to do the work of creating an actual
Explicit debug tree for something.
When it, you know, that thing maybe kind of inconvenient, we don't
want to look inject, the, you know, we don't want to force it to kind
of have to store things or manage things.
We want to just kind of work.
And so, what I'd like to do now, is take a kind of a brief
Sort of look at what we could do in terms of making that sort of thing
work a little bit better, right?
And so the thing that we probably most want to be able to do in the
game is we'd like to be able to do something like inspect and entity,
right.
It would be nice to be able to inspect like what the values of an
entity are, for example, because that's something that can be
relatively difficult to do in the debugger because we don't really
know what entity is what and it's kind of hard to let go.
Oh, I see, you know, there's any that's misbehaving over there.
I don't know why I like, how do I see what the state of it?
Is that something that might be kind of a nice thing to add to our
system, right?
So I'd like to do today is start down that path and I'm going to
forget entirely about the debug code.
We've already written.
And instead, what I'm going to do is I'm going to go do what I want to
do.
To the editi code, to make it possible to inspect those variables,
right?
And then I'm going to go back to the debug system and make and unify
those two, right?
So this is again, a very standard programming technique.
For me, it's something I do very often which is if I know that there
is a particular sort of operation or tasks that I want a system to do.
I will go, right, the usage code for that task.
The thing that's going to use that system.
I'll write that before writing the system and then let that sort of
How the system works, right?
And in this case, we've already done some of that because we did like
kind of what we wanted for pound defines, but like I said, we've never
really looked at this other use case.
So I want to write that use case and then let that drive.
How I upgrade this system to support it rather than sort of changing
the system in hopes that it will support that well and then going and
using it and finding out that I was wrong, right?
You might as well if you know what you want to do.
Do go do it and let that inform how the system is written.
It's a much more efficient way to make that work.
Okay.
So if we were going to do something like that, let's go over to
handmade same region.
That's where we deal with our entities, a lot.
So I'm just going to kind of look in here and see how we're doing
that.
And so you can kind of see as I go through this this stuff when we
we've got kind of, our begins intense em situation.
And when we do begin Sim, we Loop through all of the entities that are
in the sauce.
The region that we're working on and we add them to the simulation.
Right, you can see that happening here.
And so if we do something like this where we go through and we add any
of these to the simulation, it's sort of an interesting question of,
you know, maybe is that the right place for us to announce an entity
or not, you know, it's kind of hard to say but what I do know is that
after we've added all these entities to the Sim, we have sort of an
easy way potentially now to pick them.
And so, what I'd like to do is do something where I can
Ask the same region, you know, using the mouse or something, I can go
like click on it, empty or something like that and pick that entity.
So now we know you know that you know what that entity actually is in
terms of like, you know, it's entity ID or whatever.
Right?
So this we know who it is.
So that's what we're going to do.
Today is the ability to like pick that Andy and take a look at how
that might work.
So inside the begin Sim when we do all this sort of stuff when we add
things to the Sim you can see that what we do here is we kind of put
them in like this and then we have a SIM entity Collision volume group
and that Collision volume group tells us like the bounds of that
entity, right?
And that's really all we know about the boundaries of that entity for
the most part.
At least I remember correctly.
I think that's all we know.
We might have an extra thing in there which is like some kind of a
radius.
But I don't actually remember.
I think all we really have is the Collision stuff, and in fact, when
we do like move entity, right, I'm pretty sure when we do move entity
that inserts things into the set, right?
Something like that.
Here, that kind of inserts things into the set specifically by using
that Collision volume, I believe, right.
Right, because when we write when we insert things oh no.
I guess that's not true.
When we insert things we don't actually care about their bounds.
We just use their position and put them in that way.
I think, right?
I think that's actually the case.
But we do know that least for most entities we will have that
Collision volume so we could start with something like that and say
that we'll just use the Collision volume.
We could also do something where we use just the position itself and
use the position.
I had to pick you know so we could click near the position into it I'm
not sure which of those would be the best way to go but you know
either way
Either way, we have some options, let's put it that way.
So if I wanted deal with something like that, the first thing that I'd
like to do is draw those collisions volume, so that we can see them.
Because so far as for like, you know, if you take a look at what we've
got drawn on here, right?
I'm going to turn off the debug camera for now.
If you look at what we've got drawn on here, we've kind of have this.
This situation where, you know what I guess I've got room based camera
as well.
There we go.
So we can have the situation where we don't actually see, you know,
we've got any of these and they have collisions like I can't walk
through, you know, this dude or whatever but we don't actually ever
see what those Collision volumes are right.
Like those Collision volumes aren't actually drawn in any way.
So what I'd like to do is just have some way of drawing.
Those Collision volumes onto the screen in a way that I can actually
perceive that, you know, that I'd actually be able to
To see and look at.
And in order to do that I think we may have to introduce, you know we
might introduce something even like a line primitive or something,
because I'm not sure that there's really a lot of good ways to do it.
I suppose we could do it with our rectangle but it's a little bit
tricky to even know how to do it.
Exactly what the rectangle even because well both of the points of the
rectangle would have to be projected and blah blah blah.
So I'm not entirely sure but let's take a look.
So in the sentiment of the Collision fighting group, you can see we've
got Collision volumes.
And basically what they are is there's like an offset.
And a dim, right?
So it's basically like a cure is, you know, here's my, my positioning
my placement, for it relative, the entities position, and then I've
got sort of a dimension.
The says how big it is, right?
And so if I kind of go into the renderer, we don't really have
anything that can do a rendering like that.
You know, we've got a bility to push a rectangle and we can push a
rectangle out of 3D offset, but when we specify the dimension, the
dimension
Is not specified in 3D and that way, it's specified in 2D, right?
So we wouldn't actually even see what that that rectangular really
was.
And so what we might want to do you know, one thing we can consider
doing certainly
Is doing something where we actually have a rectangle call.
That makes a rectangle that takes like two points in 3D and then fills
the rectangle like around those points, or something like that, right?
Or something that takes yet basically, something that would allow us
to more easily, draw those things and push wrecked outline, might be
the better one for it too.
Because push wrecked outline is we probably don't want to do solid
blocks for our Collision or tails.
Probably just drawing the boundary.
Maybe it's a little bit more.
Interesting, right, so let's just start off with something really
easy.
Let's start off with something where when we do the same entities and
that's tough.
Let's go into
Hand me dot CPP.
I think we've got a render Loop here, where you can see the render
Loop working its way through here.
And so, as we're going through these renderings, I feel like what we
could do is at the end of this, right?
If we wanted to after everything, we're we're doing all these sort of
push Rex what I could do at the very end of it is I could go through
the Collision volumes.
In fact, right here, you can even see us having done this before,
right?
What I could do is say all right, let's take this code for drawing.
Outlines of things, and let's just do that for all the entities right
that there are.
So Eve, No Matter What entity it was, I'll just come down here and
I'll draw that that wrecked outline, right?
So, this should work for any of it.
I think, for the most part, oops, know how that happened.
How did that get in there?
When did that get in there?
I don't even know.
So yeah, point being, let's go grab that their Collision.
Where did you go?
Do you like you, I use face outline.
So, all I really want to do now is make one of these.
That's like, you know, in our config file.
For example, I want to do something where it's like, you know, draw
entity outlines
But I like that.
And I don't know where that'll go, but we're going to put it in there.
Let's take a look.
I'm going to find that as one and I'm going to go into our debug
variables that H.
I'm going to put that.
Where is that going to go?
We don't really have anything.
I guess we'll just have what a new group.
I don't know.
And these something like that.
And then we'll do fine one of them.
Did my favorite list thing?
Raw energy.
Outlines.
Compile.
So there are, you know, some of the outlines for the different Eddie's
and you can kind of see that it's roughly.
Correct, right.
And we're just using that that same
Code for it that we were using before.
It's a little thick, I feel like and I'm not sure it's the dim XY,
it's just ignoring the Z bounds.
So that's how we were drawing it before.
And, you know, that's probably fine at the end of the day.
You know, that's that's probably good enough for our purposes and all
that, I wish it was a little less thick.
I do Wonder.
Perhaps if maybe our push wrecked outline, does that actually support
the ability to to do a thickness?
It doesn't seem too.
So we might want to do something where we, you know, allowed that to
sort of get passed in like this.
So that when we do a push wrecked outline and we're showing these
things that we're looking at here, we could also say, oh, you know
what could you just if you could just make that a little thinner?
That'd be great, right?
And so, there's those lovely.
They are really pretty beautiful.
There's a nice magenta outline there, right?
All good.
It's pretty good.
Pretty good.
So now we can kind of see those boundaries on the screen and so now
what I want to do is make it so that we can actually pick with the
mouse one of those boundaries.
So that when we're moving the mouse on the screen around like we can
click on one and say I want to highlight this entity, right?
Like this is the entity that I want to select if that makes sense,
right?
All right, so if I wanted to pick one of those guys, if I wanted to,
like, make sure that I could, you know, could do that.
Really?
All I need to do is be able to see whether my mouse cursor is inside.
One of those rectangles just like we were doing before, right?
We could we could easily do that.
The problem is, remember we have a transform on our view here.
We like I mean right just to put a fine point to put not too fine, a
point on it.
As I might say I can
Change.
Like, for example, this to use the debug camera and everything like
shrinks down, right?
So obviously there is not just some canonical like coordinate system
that this is all in at render time.
It's actually taking the world and it's like taking where the camera
is and it's producing where all of the entities are through a
projection like we talked about.
So in order for my mouse to know what it is over, in order for me to
figure out what the mouse is over.
Over in the in the actual game world, we need to basically do an
inversion, right?
We need to reverse the process that the renderer is going through.
That's taking things from the world and putting it on the screen
because the mouse is on the screen and we need to reverse it to put it
into the world.
Does that make sense?
And we didn't have to do that for hit testing for our debug UI because
the debug UI is not in the game world, right?
When we scale the game world, there's no transform on the debug you.
I, it's just 121 pixels, right?
So the pixels, the mouse cursor, where the mouse cursor is in pixels
and where these things are in pixels is the same thing.
Right?
So it's all in the same space and just works.
But if we wanted to hit test these things on the screen, because
they're going through that camera transform, which again is something
we can set and control and change.
Then we're going to have to have some way of reversing it, right?
And I think I almost want to say, I don't remember if this is if this
is the case or not, I want to say we sort of started this process for
a different reason.
I think, yeah, right here, right.
So we have unprojected, let's see here.
Want to see where that's being called, so we have on Project and we're
using that.
Well,
We're not using it at all.
So we have one project which is just a way of taking something that's
in the
I guess it's not really a 2d location.
No, we are using it.
Okay, there it is.
Get camera rectangle at distance, right?
So what we're doing there is essentially, we're saying okay, we would
like to take whatever our monitor is right, whatever, we know the
monitor Dimension is, we want to unprojected that so that we know how
what the camera can see, right?
So that we did have a good reason for it so we already have the
ability to unprojected something.
So if we
What we could run this projected X Y function on our Mouse coordinates
and in theory will get back right what that position in the world
would be now as you know or I shouldn't even necessarily say as you
know.
But I'll draw it out you just in case, it's not clear.
if I was to talk about,
The position of the mouse on the screen and let's just draw this
again.
So here's here's the focal point.
And you know, we're talking about something out in the world here.
Like here's the tree, right?
And this is the monitor.
And as you know, when we do our projections, like we take some point
on the tree, we project it onto the screen, right?
And this this tree, the whole tree point at a time, gets kind of
projected onto their.
If you think about it that way, thought about all the points on the
tree, they all have sort of lines that intersect the monitor that's
where we're sort of talking about them being.
Now if we want to do
Verse of this, if we have a point here and we go, where in the world
is it?
Well, what you could immediately see is, there isn't a single point in
the world that corresponds to a single point.
On the screen, it's actually a family of points along a line, right?
Anything along this line from the focal point to the point on the
screen and out into the world.
Anything along that line is going to map to the same point on the
screen.
Right.
So that's why we need one additional value, which is the distance from
the camera that we want it to be.
So if the cameras here, right?
And that's where we're sort of looking along, and this is the point on
the screen.
What we need to know is What's the total distance?
This way, like What's the total distance along that line, right?
In that along that line, I shouldn't say What's the total distance
like for this plane, if this
He was to be pushed back, right?
What's the total distance from the camera to the actual plane we're
talking about and then it will find that piece, right?
And we know what that is, we know what that is because that's the
camera.
That's that's what the actual.
Ground like distance is.
So when we're picking we could we could just use how far away that is,
but
It does get a little more complicated than that, in some sense if we
want to think about it, think it through a little bit more deeply,
right?
So, the other thing we could think about the other way to sort of
conceptualize, this is when we are picking something, we don't
necessarily know what plane we might want to be picking, right?
Because when we look at things, you know, if we had some things
stacked on top of each other.
So back here, there's me no more trees in the distance or something.
So it draws like an there, we might want to have it so that as we are
looking through these entities we are taking like whichever ones close
to the camera or maybe want to know all of the entities that intersect
it and select all the things that are under the mouse cursor because
they're going to be more than one, right?
And so another way to think of it would be to say, Well when we're
picking, we're really just talking about maybe like this line we're
talking about, we want to know what the entities are, the intersect
this line, right?
And that's a slightly more
Answer way to think about it.
And it's a way that's a little bit more complicated a program because
then what you have to do is when you look through entities, you kind
of have to go like would they, you know, where are they relative to
the camera, do the intersection and then go, okay, is would that
intersection have been the closest one, or whatever?
But it's still not particularly onerous for us to do so, I think
that's probably what I will.
Just go ahead and Implement, right.
And so, our goal for today is to make it so that as I move this mouse,
Surround, I want to basically like change this color, right?
This color here, I want to
Just color to, let's say yellow.
Whenever I am over an entity so that I can see that I'm like, picking
them correctly.
That makes sense.
So, in order to do that, I should be able to do something fairly
straightforward, like, doing unprojected.
We'll try this first.
So I'm going to go here and say, you know, is highlighted
equals false or maybe I'll just even go the for outline color.
Right, equals that lovely magenta and then I'll say like if some stuff
is true will have outline color equal to like a lovely yellow instead.
So what I want to do here is I'm going to unprotect the mouse.
And I'm going to unprotect the mouse for the render group that we're
using.
And I'm going to take whatever the mouse key is here, right?
And then I'm and we got to make sure that that's in our reasonable
coordinate system, obviously.
So we're going to take a look at that.
Sort of in a second.
But anyway, we've got a mouse P there and then we've got distance from
camera.
And what we want to do for distance of camera is we want to take
however far the entity is away.
So we're going to look at how far it is on its plane of existence,
right?
So I'm going to take a look at, like the entities total position in
space, right?
And again, that's going to be relative to the camera already.
Because everything in this, in this case is going is represented
relative.
Camera.
Now, the only problem is something I don't
Actually, remember, about the way we were doing this is I don't
actually remember.
What we set up for the camera Point per se.
But you can see here that if this is what we're actually passing that
we must have set up the camera correctly originally
We're sending the ground Point here.
So I'm just going to take whatever we're doing there that offset P.
I'm going to assume that that's the picking plane that we want to be
in for now, right?
So, I'm just going to say this, oops.
The Z of this.
Is what we want.
Okay.
And so then I'm going to say well okay after I unprojected this thing,
this is my like local Mouse P or whatever.
Then I can just sort of say, well, whatever I was going to draw right
for my, for my
Collision volume here.
Right.
I've got some some 2D volume that I'm sort of projecting here for my
push worked out line.
I should be able to take whatever that rectangle is and and and see
whether I collide with it, right?
So if I take this dim x y and I assume this dim XY is centered around
the Collision volume and I could do this per Collision value, in fact,
Could do this whole thing per Collision volume, if I wanted to, I
guess, I could say, I could do it in here like this.
And I should probably actually make sure I use that outline color.
Right.
So you can see here I've got the volume offset P so I could just use
that volume offset p and say, okay for the particular volume, whatever
its Z is at.
I'm going to run project that
And then I'm going to see whether this thing is inside the rectangle,
sort of defined by this Dimension, right?
And I guess actually I could also do it just by checking the well, I'm
not going to bother
Yeah, if that's the local Mass P.
That's the one that's like you know, in the same space as our entity
basically.
So what I should be able to do their say, you know, I've got the
volumes Dimension.
So I could just say, okay, if the local Mouse pee,
The volumes Dimension, you know, X and the volume is offset.
P.
You know what?
I can even make this little simpler after unprojected it.
I could even just make it relative to the offset P, right?
So basically what I'm doing here is saying, okay, let's find out
relative to the center of this this Collision volume, where is the
local Mouse, once I know where that is, I can just say, okay if the
local Mouse peas X is greater than like the negative dimension.
She now that I think about it.
How are we drawing this?
This is like a centre-half damn thing.
Right.
Pretty sure.
Yeah.
So if it's if it's, you know, greater than half the dimension,
And less than half a dimension.
right, and then I do the same thing with why
like so I now know,
Exactly.
What's you know whether or not this thing is inside or outside that 2D
volume and this is not a full 3d test against the volume but that's
probably okay for our purposes.
Like I said if we want to be a little more ridiculous about it, we
could do ray intersects 3D cube a 3D you know, right.
Rectangular prism but there's really no need for that for the debug
picking certainly.
So probably seems like that would be a bit of a waste of time to say
the least but
So let's go ahead and Loops gotta dereference that above where I use
it certainly.
So let's go ahead and see if we can make our Mouse P here.
Look at that.
We still controlling the Music Volume.
That's probably not what we want for now.
So we've got the input Mouse X and the input Mouse.
Why?
but,
Those again are sort of what the what the system tells us.
The mouse X where the mouse is and so on.
And so since, you know, rather than try to always remember exactly
where the system thinks the mouse is what I'd like to do.
Also, start is I'd like to do a push wrecked of the mouse's location
so we can see what we think it actually is.
Right.
And so what I can do there is temporarily, you know, again without
actually actually having to do anything too fancy.
Here I should be able to take some of the places where
During stuff, which is after the controller stuff happens.
So, when we start doing this here, like this stuff here, right?
We've got this perspective transform after I unprojected the mouse, I
could show words.
I'd like to show prior to projecting as well where it is.
So I'd have to think, I guess I'd have to make an orthographic
projection first, but that's not really a big, big deal, right?
So what I could do is right here where we've got this sort of stuff.
What I could do is do an orthographic beforehand, just to draw the
mouse right?
Because in here, you know, we
Did did that, right?
We did this.
So if I wanted to, I could do do one of these
Don't actually remember what this 1.0 thing is, if that's just the
scale factor, right?
So if I did that, now I could actually draw wherever the mouse is so I
can just say, okay there's a mouse P, right?
That's the input.
How sex the input Mouse, why?
And once I have that, I can do a push wrecked outline if I want to.
Now, again, I should probably also move the clear up a bit, right?
The clear should happen before all this, but I don't actually the
clear.
I don't remember if that clears the whole surface, or just this part
of it.
But yeah, I guess I can do it this way.
That's probably fine.
so when I clear this thing after I do the input mousex mess, why I can
then push a rectangle on here and if I do push wrecked outline
There we go.
I should be able to see where the mouse actually is before we do
anything with it, right?
So if we just go ahead and make one of these guys and then we have the
dimension of it.
I don't know, which will just be like a two-by-two thing.
Fashion show us.
Where are we?
We think the mouse cursor is before we try to do anything more fancy
than that.
All right.
Well you know what I probably need to draw that after because I saw it
there it actually worked but going to have to do that afterwards.
So this should probably as
Be kind of doubt the bottom after we do everything else so we can
actually see it.
All right, Mouse pee.
First Mouse be itself.
Can certainly be something that we do early.
That's all fine.
Okay.
So let's see if this works now, Mouse pee.
And, you know, the other thing that I have to do is reset the render
transform the offset p
This guy render group transform and I don't remember if we have some
way of setting the dredger transform to the identity.
I don't actually remember, if that's something we did.
Let's take a look.
I feel like that's something we would want, certainly.
Perspective or the graphic.
And you can see that those like don't get set right, like the offset P
doesn't get set here and I wonder if they probably should clear it?
You would think I feel like they kind of should because if you look at
what is in the transform, it's got the offset p in the scale and those
don't get touched by these.
But I kind of feel like they should
Right?
I feel like that's something where you kind of want.
Those to be set.
Maybe I'm wrong about that.
It's kind of feels like what it should be to me.
Yeah.
So anyway, you can see our little mouse is there now.
So now I've at least verified that it's accurate, which is what I
wanted, right.
But I think that also I don't actually know like I say in the
orthographic mode, I don't actually know that.
I'm interpreting that Mouse, right?
In a way that, you know, I don't know if that's actually in the
projective space secure and I'm not sure.
So I want to take a look at that those values.
So for example, when it's up here, right?
I'd like to know what it actually is, like, what's the actual value
when it's up here?
So, like right now, for example, what I might do is just break into
the code somewhere doesn't matter where game update and render.
And I want to see what mouse p is set to, right?
I just want to see what, what it whoops, what it ends up being, and I
want to actually search for it.
If possible, find earned quick, find mouse pee.
We go.
And so, what's the value?
so the x value is negative 9 34 and the Y value is 511, so it looks
like they the the coordinate system for the mouse is in
The screen coordinate system, right?
So that seems to me to be totally reasonable, right?
So now, what I'd like to do is step it up one notch.
I'd like to go ahead and say that when we are doing these debug and of
the outlines, I'd like to now also draw sort of the local P, right?
I'd like to
That actually save.
Hey, I hate it.
When Visual Studio saved my file, I wish you can turn Visual Studio to
never save anything.
To just only be in debugger, not an editor would be nice.
So when I Loop over these volumes that I do, this, look a mouse p&i
unprojected thing back into the world.
What I want to do now is I want to be able to draw that Mouse p as
well.
So we're whatever that local version is you know I'm saying.
So I want to basically say, like, okay, once I've been projected it, I
should be able to
Draw it again, after I compute.
Where it is, I should be able to say.
Okay, I've got the local Mouse pee
And if I were to turn that into a 3D thing using again, the sort of
the Z value.
So, you know, something like local Z.
That's my local Z value.
Assuming that I was to draw it.
Where would it be?
And I'm going to draw that as a bigger one here.
I'm going to draw that as, you know, something that I can can tell
what it is, so maybe like, 1.0 or 0000, just nice cyan there,
something like that.
And then I want to look and see if I can see that.
And if I can see that like, where it even is right, and I'm not seeing
it anywhere.
No.
That should have been, that should be happening for like every entity,
right?
And I'm not seeing it at all.
So,
Obviously thinking about this slightly wrong, I'm not, I'm not
properly doing what I should be doing here.
You know what I'm saying?
So something's amiss and I'm not sure what I'm looping through the
volumes, I'm using whatever the volume Z is as the reverse projector,
I'm taking, whatever the X and Y is of the volume and I'm subtracting
it away.
So this should be local to the entities like
Roughly local to the entities P.
It's not quite because it's the volumes fee, but even so, it should be
pretty close and so I should see something nearby to the cursor when
I'm over an entity.
And that is definitely not happening.
So I would like to know why that's not happening.
We take another quick, look down here.
Just so I make sure I know what I'm actually debugging.
So the way that we worked that out is we take the distance from
camera.
We divide the
by the focal length and we multiply that by the projected x y
By that value.
and so in theory yet, that would make it
so that I think,
Just thinking that through a little bit.
Right, that I think actually doesn't go to pixels is our problem.
Right.
like if we look at what actually happens there,
That's not going to actually get us to pixels, looking at our get
entity or basis P.
Right?
Looking at get render entity basis B, when we do our transform here,
you can sort of see
But after we do that projection, which you can see us doing right
here.
After we do our projected X Y, we do a transform of m, 2 pixels.
And so I feel like that, m 2 pixels is the problem.
You can see uh Sun projecting monitor half, demand M here.
So we would first need to, when we do this on a project, we would
first need to unprojected it like using the beaters to pixel value,
right?
So, I mean, I just for right now, I mean, I could sort of do that
directly.
We have this mouse P, the
He's already in M, the mouse p is not.
So we have M to pixels, right?
So what we could do is take pixels to M and multiply it.
And then we could go ahead and oops.
And then we'd be, we'd be going ahead and doing the the conversion
there.
Now looks like m 2 pixels.
It looks like we never actually did that one.
We only have M to pixels.
Not pixels to meters, but that's okay.
I can divide by it as well.
That's totally fine.
Or I should say multiply it by the inverse.
L, 2 pixels.
It's not, so it's a property of the transform.
Sorry.
My bad.
Okay.
Oh my
I can't say I know what's going on there.
Push wrecked line.
Local Mouse pee.
Is that oh, that's actually these.
All right.
Well,
Yeah, I forgot about the fact that this would actually get Scaled up.
That's my bad.
Yeah.
So probably want to cut that down quite a bit.
Yeah, because that's now in.
That's a m.
Yeah.
Okay.
Well we're getting there though.
We are getting there.
And looks like
Oddly enough were kind of either all in or all out on some of these so
that we're kind of, we're still a little bit janky but we're getting
there, right?
Like, you can see that no matter what the mouse is.
I'm sort of not actually these are not actually offsetting relative to
each other, their offsetting relative to their BC, all the same
offset, but it should be different per individual bounding element,
but we're getting closer.
So now that I've corrected for the pixels to M and I'm looking at on
projecting that Mouse P there after I do the unprojected, and then I
Center it around this particular Collision volume.
Ah, and there's yet another problem.
So when I am doing the, the offset p .x y, right?
And the offset P .z these are
Not actually where the thing is, right?
It's it's actually going to be relative to The Entity itself as well,
right?
So first we would have to put the mouse relative to The Entity.
Before going any further.
So this, right.
And we can do this first, right?
We can do something like this where we've got you know like M Mouse
pee.
Right, when we've got Mouse in meters, we then want to do is make it
relative to The Entity here.
So M Mouse pee.
We want all the rest of this stuff to happen, relative to The Entity.
So when we do this on Project, this local Z is actually not the
correct local Z, right.
It's because this m Mouse P that local Z needs to actually include
whatever the entities P was as well and of course on Project since it
uses the transform, which has been set for this entity that will
actually work because it gets included.
It in there, right?
But this subtract, which is not going through there.
Won't and it's a little bit subtle but just so I'll just reinforce it.
One project uses the transform and the transform here was already set
up to be relative to The Entity.
So anything that we draw or call the render system for is already
entity relative, right?
But this piece of math is not in any relative.
This is using the volumes offset P but it what it really should be
doing is being using the enemies P, right?
It needs to take into account this thing right here.
This entity any ground point.
It needs to know that, right?
Because that's what's actually
Used.
So it needs the volumes be and it also needs it also needs the
entities transforms.
Well, so it needs both of those things to take into account both of
those things, right?
Then it will actually local look relative to it and I think, actually
that might have been most of the bug entirely possible.
Anyway,
Getting a little closer.
So those are still those are now much too conservative.
So it's see here.
We've got our M Mouse P, which was converted from meters to pixels,
which is what we wanted because that would be multiplying by pixels to
M which is exactly what we want to do.
We unprotect it which is what we want, using the Z that's relative.
Mmm.
that all looks fine to me, we then subtract
Whatever the transforms offset was plus the volumes offset and we go
ahead and draw that on there.
That seems pretty reasonable to me I guess.
since it is a perspective projection though, technically we're not
really doing this in the correct order there because then
After we do that back projection.
Well, now that's should actually I think that should actually be okay.
That's still, that seems like it should actually be correct.
But anyway, you can see why I am already thinking it's not correct
though, right?
Is because as I'm moving these, all these things were drawing our
where the thinks the mouse is relative to some entity.
And so what we should be seeing, right is we should always be seeing
those guys line up with the mouse cursor, right?
They should always be lined up with the mouse cursor.
Sir and if they're not then it's just erroneous, right?
so,
You know, the other thing I can do is I could do something like this
as well.
This right here since I have an entity index, I could just pick one
entity, right?
Like so.
Not sure.
Which one do we want?
But we'll figure that out in a second here.
So, if I run this will pick an entity, maybe get one of them trees.
Do you see it?
There it is.
So now we're drawing.
Where we think the mouse is relative to this guy and you can just see
that that's like totally like that.
This is very nonsensical, right?
It's not at all in the correct place.
Now, it's not even the correct scale so like I said we've got kind of
a couple things that are there still something a little bit amiss, if
you will about how this is happening.
But like I said, I kind of want to do.
This is a fairly standard debugging thing, right?
I kind of wanted to reduce the number of cases, I'm looking at here,
just so I can get a little bit better idea what's going on.
So just by dropping it down to a single entity.
I don't have to sort of think about everything at once that's being
drawn on the screen.
So here we are.
We've got M Mouse p and after I unprojected that I'm kind of
interested to know after unprojected, right?
I'm kind of interested to know if I just on Project.
It what does it look like?
Then if I don't do the subtract I kind of want to know.
I'm just for educational purposes.
I want to see what it looks like.
If I don't correct it.
Right.
And so there you can kind of see not correcting, it surprisingly makes
it in there in the right place and I'm wondering does unprojected,
take into account this.
It doesn't see em project never takes into account where things are.
So, I'm a little weirded out of why I don't have to do this subtract.
This subtract should have to happen.
Very peculiar.
Very, very peculiar.
I guess that makes some sense though because if you think about it,
it's always gonna draw a relative to The Entity because that's what
it's programmed to do, right?
It's using that as its transform, so that's not that surprising.
And so anything that you moved around the center of the screen, you
know, it was but but even so
Okay.
Now so there it is.
So is around the center of screen, okay.
So that's totally
I'm just watching its motion, right?
So if I Circle it like this I should see it kind of move you know,
relative to the square towards the mouse cursor and I'm not seeing
that.
So that's what I want to be able to do right.
Yeah, that seems a little bit more like it.
I was going to say,
You should have to do that.
So when I do this on project and I take it back to the with the local
Z like that, I feel like that distance from camera so I feel like if I
look at what's going on here I feel like maybe our unprojected just
kind of fundamentally busted because if you look at what it's doing
it's never taking into account the actual offset P, it's as if the
offset P doesn't exist, right?
So really,
This local Z really should actually contain the entirety of this
transform, right?
It should actually have this in it, which is kind of dumb.
I feel like that's not so good.
The way that works because you feel like unproductive on Project
should probably take that into account.
But anyway, so that's probably more correct.
I think when we do that it should have that transform that offset p z
in there and then you know, both of those have that the locals.
He has that right?
So I'm pretty sure that's, that's more correct.
So the a distance from camera again,
Yeah, I just I mean that seems pretty clear to me.
So the at distance from camera
should include the full Z of the object, whatever that is.
And then the
I'm pretty certain that should give us the correct scaling.
And so I'm not sure the thing that that's kind of weird is why it's
not giving us the correct scaling I guess.
So after we do this this, unprojected local Z, that's the tricky part,
is this push wrecked will actually use that.
So it's actually only the volume Z.
This is just nasty that you would use their.
This is why I think our unprojected needs to be more symmetric
Just it's simply a little too crazy at that point.
Yeah, but that's still not scaled properly and I'm not sure why,
right?
Because I feel like it should be scaled, it should be moving with the
mouse properly.
So unless I'm doing something wrong with the m Mouse P here, where I'm
doing something incorrect where I'm not properly preparing it with m 2
pixels and I can double-check like we're just trying to do the inverse
remember of our
Get entity basis p.
That makes sense.
Render is the speed was good, but the function called there it is.
So yeah, you can kind of see what's basically going on here, right?
So we're just trying to undo this.
So we multiply m 2 pixels times.
The projected X Y to get the location of it.
We can ignore these probably this result scoffs Lizzie that's like the
Y offset for Z, but you can see here, we've got sort of the screen
Center.
And then we've got that projected, why?
Now that should be it, right?
I mean, that should be pretty much the whole thing.
You can see this projected X Y, distance 2pz thing that
This is the p.
Z is just the distance above Target.
So yeah, that that all seems.
Really reasonable.
That all seems pretty reasonable to me.
So you can see here, write the transfer m 2 pixels, the projected XYZ
there, right?
Whatever the Z is that Z value is what the scale would be.
That's how much the mouse should be moving.
So again, I feel like 1 over m, 2 pixels should have done it and I'm
not sure why.
It doesn't?
I feel like we're probably going to run out of time here.
I don't know when I started was probably like six ten.
I feel like this requires a little more careful consideration.
So I feel like like I said, I feel like we want this function to be
more.
Symmetric, I feel like we want it.
Exactly undo, this transform and we're not quite doing that at the
moment, right?
Because if you were to take a look at what this is doing,
if you just look at just this
Like so.
We're talking about this equation.
And so if we got transformed m, 2 pixels, projected XY, like so we
want to undo this operation and this is right.
That.
So if what we want to do is we want to get raw XY out of here, that's
what we're trying to do.
We you know, because we want to do the inverse, we've got this, you
know, we've got projected, we've got we've got result.
Bright and we want to get this solving this equation, right is going
to do, you're going to divide by this to get that out of there, right?
Oops, that was not a very good cut and paste.
All right, so get that out of there.
And then you just left with this.
Yeah, and then I just actually just get rid of these two guys.
and then,
We want to solve for rho, x y.
So we would move this guy over, right?
So, we'd also be dividing by this.
Which I think means this guy to the top, right?
Yeah.
And then the focal length again also oops.
Focal length is also going to get divided out so it's something like
that.
So, it's just itchin to pz X result over the focal length.
And I'm pretty sure that's basically exactly what we had.
The only difference is we left out the m 2 pixels, right?
So there's that distance to pz.
Right.
Yeah, so there's that.
Distance 2pz on the top.
There's the focal length on the bottom.
There's a result so that that is exactly what we do.
The only difference is we left out m 2 pixels.
So in theory, it just feels like if you get that back and you divide
by m 2 pixels that should have done the inverse.
So there's obviously something I said stupid that I'm just not picking
up on because that does look like the inverse and although I don't
like the symmetry of it, I'd rather just a bug this as it stands.
Before making that modification.
But you know, again dividing, that m 2 pixels, I guess.
The thing is you do the divided by m 2 pixels, kind of, at the end of
that, it shouldn't matter when you do it because it's linear.
So I don't feel like that should matter at all.
So that should be the the right thing I think.
But obviously, it's not because if it was this would be working.
And it is not working and so yeah.
We'll have to test it more thoroughly tomorrow, I guess.
Very strange.
Don't really want to stop debugging this.
I want to kind of go actually finish it because I feel like I never
like not knowing why something is doing what it's doing.
And these kinds of this kind of code is always very finicky because
you can't see it very effectively while the reasons I kind of want
debug diagramming in our system as well.
But yeah, it's just one of those things where it's like, there's
something simple going on here.
That's not clear about what exactly is not being reversible.
And I don't like leaving something like that, because it ends up
bugging me.
But I can't think of anything in the shorthand, so I feel like I'm
just going to have to because otherwise, yeah, I mean, we could we
could be here for another hour of me looking at it and going through
each individual part and verifying it and so on.
So it's probably deserve something better done for tomorrow.
So let me see.
So let's think here offset, p- the dim Z
Volume Jim, XY, outline color.
So that's just kind of that all assumes the centering around so that
that all looks like again look exactly like what I would expect.
The M.
Mouse P looks exactly what I would expect, right?
Divides by the m, 2 pixels for the transform.
Which seems totally reasonable.
And
The local Z.
I guess, one thing I don't know is if distance from camera is supposed
to be positive or negative there.
But that wouldn't expect affect the scale, it would only affect the
direction of movement, it would be flipped, right?
And if I unprojected Intergroup that I'm on now, I passed the M Mouse
p and the locals.
Eat that should give me a point in the world.
That is where that mouse was
Relatively speaking.
Yeah, I don't know.
There's something scale.
Scale wrong.
Scaling wise about what we're doing.
But I don't know what it is.
Are we sure we don't know?
on what order is the actual
lack of scale.
Like how far away from being correct?
Is that like for starters?
It's it's not centered around the correct thing, right?
But the scale itself being wrong is kind of interesting.
So let me try something here.
I'm just going to try something a little bit a little bit crazy,
right?
So in here, when we're always offsetting around the ground and the
point like we were doing before, right?
I'm going to I'm going to just see what happens.
If instead of doing that we were to just go ahead and like
You know like say okay the Rena group transform offset p is going to
be set back to zero.
So now all of the drawing is going to happen relative to just the
regular old world.
And so when I do this stuff here,
In fact, what I could do is I can draw the mouse, I could even stop
doing this.
I could just a bug that Mouse transformed by itself, right?
I could just say, oh okay, I'm going to do exactly what I was doing
before where I take a look on Mouse.
Be I do and I'm project.
But I'm just going to make up a z-value, whatever it is.
It's 10 meters away from the mouse.
Let's say so at 10 meters away from the mouse and again we can also do
this the same
Right?
So we clear off that transform.
We say 10 meters away from the mouse.
Where would it be?
And then we just draw that we draw that world must be at 10 meters off
out and that should again if we reproject it using the same local Z,
we should
We should see it right on top of our cursor and we're assuming that
our transformed function is broken.
So we won't see it.
Yeah.
And we don't
right, I'm going to set the debug camera out a little bit just to see
Where that draws.
Sam.
Even see that at all.
How's that possible?
Why am I not seeing anything?
But that makes it pretty easy.
We can just step in and see what's going on here.
Right.
I guess we should also set the scale to one just to be sure.
But, I mean that should not affect it, right?
All right, so let's see what's going on here we do m 2 pixels.
We do the unprojected with 10 meters as the distance.
I suppose.
I don't see anything for their so it's not some weird thing about it
being behind the camera.
So let's figure out why this is not working.
Well.
That would probably do do it a little bit.
Okay, so there we go.
so, looking at that,
You can kind of see that, it's okay, but not great, it's not really
tracking the mouse.
It's sort of where the mouse is but not really so something's wrong
with that.
And let's see what happens if I change the local z21.
Yeah, so it's really just totally wrong because what should be
happening when we do that on Project, is it should be scale-invariant.
No matter what, local Z, whatever Z we pass here, as long as we pass
the same Z here, the unprojected and the reproject should put it back
in the same place.
And the fact that that's not happening means it's obviously wrong,
like, that's just, that's just flat-out bad, right?
So that local Z
That local Z no matter what.
We said it to, we should get the same results and we're not.
So let's look at it, one more time and see what what am I doing wrong
there?
That's causing that problem, because that is definitely not correct,
right?
So we've got transform distance above Target.
And then we're saying the distance to pz is a distance above Target -
whatever the Z value is.
So, that alone.
That alone could be our problem.
We are not accounting for that at, all right?
So the distance from camera in that unprojected
Is not really.
That was a little too purpose-built that looks like almost the
entirety of the problem to me.
Yeah.
That's the problem.
So when we're passing this Z, right that Z value.
Yeah.
Okay.
So this Z value actually first, and you can see that there is that
there we had, it just render entity basis P.
The fact that Z actually looks like that distance above Target,
- pz that is actually probably our problem, right?
It's happening here but it's not going to happen in on project.
So really what we would need to do is after we unprojected this thing,
we would need to take that value.
That we get back.
Right?
And we need to local Z instead of being 1.0.
When we actually pass this in, it would actually, you know, the local
see that we're talking about would actually have to be like the
reverse of that.
So it would have to be, it would have to take transform distance above
targets.
Right?
And it would have to like have it be, you know, would it have to put
that in there?
Like, like this, if I'm not mistaken, right?
It would need to be, it would need to have this be subtracted out.
Oh, and I guess more like that because it's going to automatically
subtract out.
This is from Target and just be left with Peezy.
I think that's correct.
But yeah.
That's just something we're going to have to.
We're going to have to re-architect the way that works a little bit
because that's just complete garbage.
We want are two things to be symmetric there, right?
And so I'm not even sure exactly.
We have to get it to undo so that once it is pushed through here it's
going to equal the total distance to be that local Z is so basically
we have to make this equation come out to be local Z right?
So
We need to make, you know, whatever Foo is.
Like this we need to make sure that distance above Target.
This this whole thing comes out to be local Z is what we actually
need, right?
So food should be equal to local z+.
Nope, I take it back.
It's a - distance above Target.
Right?
And so then you that's the - Foo.
So the positive food would be just as about Target - local Z.
so, this is actually
I guess what?
The thing would be to correctly.
Reverse that transform.
If I'm not mistaken.
I think.
but actually, compile
Yes.
Okay, so I think that should have done it, although it doesn't look
again, still, not quite right.
But that's definitely like that's that's definitely a big part of our
issue there in the sense that there's no.
Yeah.
So I think what we really want to do is just actually reverse this
transform properly, and of course, we do have a slight problem where
we're going to have to think about what that means for.
Actually, the way we were using on project before, but basically I
want to take this whole thing, right?
And make this a little bit more specific, right?
So if we were to do a complete unprojected, so let's say, I went down
here and we've got a eject as it currently stands.
If we were to do
a complete unprojected, we need to do one.
That actually takes into account all of these things, right?
so, the first thing would be
We would probably want to do this, if Transformer, if the graphic
thing honestly, right, we'd probably want to do these so that we can
do both branches, right?
We don't want to use the debug camera ever, because we probably want
that to keep it sort of its thing going on.
I will though, we could actually, we could, maybe, I don't know, I
don't know, which depends on which kind of, unprojected, we wanted to
be doing.
But so anyway, so what we would want
Do curious a alright, the distance of p z greater than your clip
playing test.
We'll start inside there.
Here's the result P.
We don't care about the scale because that doesn't actually happen.
So, this right here is our final pee.
And this is what we did to it, right?
So I'm going to undo, ignore this one part of it, because I feel like
this part, we haven't settled on yet.
So I'm going to leave that out for now.
And then we're going to just do this part of it.
So again, what we're trying to solve for here, we're going to try and
solve for what the
What this input p is this guy right here, right?
So I'm just going to kind try and do these things roughly backwards,
right?
So if I want to do these things roughly backwards, then what I would
need to do is say, okay, if we start out with this
And what I'm getting passed in, is this final P?
Then, in order to do this step, I would want to get this projected, XY
back.
So, the first thing I would do is subtract the screen center like that
and then what the next thing I would do after that.
if I divide by m 2 pixels,
And then I would have my projected x y.
Right?
So that's my projected X.
Y is y XY.
Then I guess what I would do is say, Okay offset Z.
That's not actually thing that we're using anymore.
Like I said, we kind of got rid of that.
We've got the distance above Target, that stays exactly as it was.
We've got the distance to 2pz.
The p .z is what we're actually solving for, right?
In this case,
And so we need to do that for our next step, which is this thing.
So in order to back cell for this, we have the projected xyy here and
we need to force them back through this thing, right?
So this is like, sort of the next
The next step of it.
This is like the
I guess what we should call, this is like decentered, it's like the
decentered or scaled, I don't know and it will call this will just
call this a DOT XY, right?
And then here, when we get back to get back, projected, x y and write.
That was something where we had this this raw XY, that was getting
passed in here, which was the original key, right?
We want to solve for that row.
X Y.
So what we want to do is again, we want to move this stuff over.
So we've got our projected XY here, right?
Which is going to be that that ax?
Why we want to take this 1 over distance 2pz.
We want to move that to the other side.
So we want to divide by that, right?
And dividing by a divided is going to be multiplied.
And then we've got the focal length here.
That's going to be a divide
so there's that familiar part again, but we already had and then
here's the raw x y
Let me get past in, right?
so basically,
Don't need to know the near clipping plane.
We do need to know this.
Solving for the X Y there.
Yeah.
That just gives us the pxy that we actually wanted.
So this is our results, x y.
Again, that's exactly what we had before.
But the tricky part here, is this distance to pz.
So, our distance to pz.
And I suppose, this part here, the final P.
This is our, this is our input value, right?
The distance to pz in that equation is distance of a park.
It - peasy, right?
So, this thing gets inserted in here and we know that p z, that's a
given wheeler transferred Target, that's given.
So this is actually entirety of it and I feel like that should do it
right.
Like that.
Feels like it should be the long and short of it.
At the end of it, after all that.
I feel like all we have to do is inverse that sort of offset people.
Part of it as well.
So, whatever the result is,
That would actually get transformed by the offset p.
and I feel like that that should have been it, but if I take a look at
what that actually does,
You know, the actual things that that does, are the things that we
already were doing.
Right, we divided by m 2 pixels as a tech you know in our test code.
Right.
We set the thing that we were passing in to be the distance above
Target - the local PC.
And we have the offset and scale set to 0 and 1.
So they're not in play.
So, I do not understand why that.
Right there did not successfully lineup.
Right.
Like why does that not successfully do sort of a symmetric lie?
Reversed operation, you know I'm saying?
Because I've kind of verified the logic to my satisfaction now.
And so I think that like again like I said there's something much more
complicated that we're just not accounting for.
All right.
Well, I think based on that.
I would say.
I saw some residual peanut butter here, leftover from the free stream.
I would say that I'm not pleased with how janky that stuff is in there
and I feel like I don't want to be in a situation where I'm going to
have to constantly be like, looking through that stuff.
So I feel like we would definitely want to go ahead and spend some
time, cleaning up, what's happening in that projection and just do
some tests where we can figure out like okay we can all we have some
like well defined spaces, here's like screen space.
Here's you know World space and the transfer between them should work.
Like no.
Vast like that shouldn't be a thing that we have to think about
anymore.
We should be able to debug that once and have it good and it seemed
like we sort of had something like that for doing the camera bounds.
And, and I guess for some reason,
Whatever that reason is, it's something is, is amiss with how we're
doing that calculation, and it doesn't line up with the forward
transform, that makes sense.
So I'm not sure again, what that is?
It's going to bug me, but we'll have to do that tomorrow.
If that makes sense.
So let's see.
We will do a little Q&A anyways, even though we're sort of out of
time, that's not really a big deal.
So we can see if anyone had questions on that, maybe people already
figured it out, but I don't know if they did or didn't.
And, yeah, there's always is, it does always seem like there's a lot
of lag between when, when, when I see things.
and and when people on the track and hear them,
Cam locks, how will the focal length factor in will you have fov
stuff?
Well, we already do.
So, you know, we did basically like when you do this sort of thing,
when you go kind of up up and down the focal length determines like
sort of how that transform happens, right?
Because the focal length of the camera, determines what the Z, what
the foreshortening actually is like
Rapidly that happens.
so,
So yeah.
I feel like that's just it's so annoying.
I hate having a bug.
I don't know so I don't like leaving it but something pretty basic
pretty simple like it's going to be very simple in just the way that
we're thinking this through is incorrect.
And so, yeah.
I do feel like if in sohbat had really gotten its deep learning on, it
would just have known the answer, it would be like oh hey guys the bug
is blah.
So my related, what do you think about using different types for
points and vectors?
I don't find it to be very useful.
I find it to actually be kind of more of a pain because fundamentally
speaking Point versus Vector is not about storage.
It's about usage.
It's about like conceptualization.
And there are plenty of times when you may want to conceptualize
something as two different things depending on the circumstance.
And now you're in this thing, we got to like cast or convert and it's
just annoying, you know?
Does the screen center need to be involved?
It was using complete a projected.
So as far as I know, the mouse is already centered around.
That's why I check that before.
Worse, the mouse already is centered around the center of the screen
so that part didn't really need to happen.
Sorry pancakes is part of the problem that the code isn't normalizing.
The motion between the mass and the entity relative to the screen
dimensions in World coordinates at different levels.
So this transform in on Project.
Is completely linear.
Right?
It's just a series of multiplies.
So it should not matter when we transform the mouse from pixels to
meters, we should be able to do it before or after the on project and
there should be no change.
Right?
And I guess you know, since we're in bug land we might as well verify
this fact.
I mean that's what it looks like now.
And if I was to change it to doing it after the fact, right?
Where we did a transform first and then did the m 2 pixels, I should
get the exact same result.
Right?
And I do so.
Hey math still works, so that's something, but yeah, for whatever
reason.
We still have a problem in terms of how we're doing that.
Now, one thing I should look for that, we didn't look for as well,
right?
Is in push wrecked.
We do get render into basis P.
I'm assuming we use it directly.
Yeah, we do.
So we do use it directly.
And then when I actually render it render to rectangle, draw a
rectangle PP entry dim.
So it actually gets used very well.
Make sure there wasn't any other transforms happening in there.
America Embraces we have run out of questions.
Well, I haven't run out of questions because I still have a question,
which is what is the problem with this unprojected?
Right?
And that's a pretty good question.
I feel like
I feel like that's the kind of question I would like to have somebody
answer.
And I don't really know.
I don't really know what the problem is.
because that
this the dis is my project - pz, so that's just going to end up being
Local Z, right?
And so it's going to use one over local Z times the focal length.
X whatever we pump through what we're asking it to do.
Right.
And so,
yeah.
No, the questions.
yes, it the problem is
I think we should probably pick it up tomorrow because it's unbounded,
right?
It's like nobody has any idea what the bug actually is.
So we have to kind of go through and and step through it and be kind
of relatively meticulous about what we're doing so we can see what the
situation is.
So, you know, I don't really know.
Unfortunately, I don't really know any any simpler way to deal with it
than that?
if we just do that quickly,
let's see here.
if I just do that quickly,
and, you know,
I should sort of make a meta Point here because I feel like it's
probably warranted.
So this is the kind of bug that costs you time typically right.
We've kind of talked about some sort of programming
like I don't know attitude or whatever like the you know the
programming sort of like the Viewpoint of programming on handmade hero
and you know this is this is kind of a disconnect.
The fundamental disconnect I tend to
Of with most software engineering stuff.
It's like when you talk about languages or tools for programming, this
is what cost me time.
A lot of times in terms of bugs, I don't tend to have a lot of bugs
that are about me, forgetting to free some memory or something, right?
So like when people say oh we made this language and it's garbage
collected, it's great or whatever, right?
It's like okay, you know, maybe that's save some time occasionally,
IE, it would probably save some time on handmade hero because I'm
programming with no libraries at all.
So I don't even have my own stuff that does like allocation anything.
So I have to write, you know, a linked list or whatever on him, a
hero.
But in practice like, who cares that stuff?
I write it like once and it's fine, right?
But stuff like this because typically, you know, you write a lot of
code like this.
And even if you were using something like let's say, you, you know,
you didn't have to worry about unprojected in particular because you
use somebody else's 3D engine or whatever.
So, you know, you've you can maybe take care of that with a library or
however you we're doing it in your programming methodology.
You didn't work with that.
You still have the problem of you're going to write stuff like this in
game code like you've got some things and you're trying to you know,
compute something between them and it's just it comes out wrong.
And you're like, what
Ben Wright.
The kind of stuff that I want in programming to make life easier is
stuff.
That makes the bugging things like this easier.
Like I don't need something that makes debugging memory stuff easier
because that doesn't ever happen.
Like, that's like such a rare occurrence.
Something this happens to me all the time and so like you could
imagine like if a visual studio could just be like, draw this out,
like draw, these vectors like show them to me, right?
So I can see them and I can see the steps of the equation and how it's
going, it would probably be.
We'd probably all instantly know what the problem was.
But now instead when I got to step through this, we're just looking at
a bag of numbers that we can't even tell what they are or what they're
doing or why, right?
And so that's really the thing that's kind of frustrating is people
always seem to be.
They seem to work on these development tools.
That actually are four problems that I just don't have or problems
that I can solve in a very short amount of time with, not very much
effort and very low stress.
Right.
But then problems like this that are actually hard get completely
neglected and you typically have no tools for them at all.
And so the only thing that you can possibly hope for is if someone
already wrote the code for something like this that you could then use
but assuming that you are trying to develop the code yourself, which
is what you do if you're a programmer.
So no matter what Libras unit, you're going to write something
yourself, whatever that something is, will have bugs like this, and
they're hard to find, right?
And so that's really the thing where it's like you want this, you
know, you want things that make this sort of stuff.
You know, trivial like that you wouldn't really think you wouldn't,
you know, just like, oh yeah, I immediately could see what the bug was
and we were done, right.
So yeah.
But anyway, if we just take a quick look at this, here's our Mass P.
You know, that's what it is.
I want to be able to save this here, of course, there's like no way to
do notes and visual studio in your debugging, because why would you be
able to do that?
So I got a copy it into an actual text buffer.
So there's the mouse P that's we're starting with, right?
There it is.
And so we convert it to meters Mouse pee.
Which is obviously, much smaller value.
And there it is.
And that seems sane, right?
We were in this upper quadrant, I think so.
That makes some sense, right?
We then take the local Z which you already noticed.
A fixed constant of 1 and we're going to unprotect it, right?
So we come in here we're at a fixed distance of 1.
So this is really just going to be 1 over the focal length.
The focal length is .6.
There's a projected X Y.
So here is when we do that first on Project step, right?
Here's what we got.
Okay.
That comes back.
I've now got my world Mouse p and what I'm going to do is I'm going to
go into push wrecked and I'm going to see what happens when we
actually try to use this thing.
Well.
Step into pushback.
Please God.
Such okay.
So inside push wrecked.
The first thing we're going to do is make an offset here of this X Y
value.
And that's because we're drawing something of a dimension.
I supposed to make this a little bit easier on ourselves, we probably
should have made this Dimension, be 0.
And I guess in fact, in this case, I probably can just do exactly that
I can just reach in here and actually change these values.
So that when we're doing this computation P Remains the Same, right?
So when we do that computation, we end up actually.
And this value, right?
So now, our input value is exactly the same so that we're not even
drawing a rectangle at all.
We're just doing this.
Okay, and we're passing in that Z, equals 8 value and that's because
we're trying to account for the distance from Target thing.
And so if I take a look to at the transform itself, the distance will
Target was 8 and of course our Z was one.
So I'm sorry it's nice and it was one so that be equals 8, which is
what we would expect there.
ah,
I meant to step into that.
Let's try that one more time.
Okay, so here we are.
Here is our original P that's coming in.
Which is what we expected it to be.
We're going to transform it, presumably not at all.
So it should be exactly the same and it is, we're not in orthographic
transform.
Our distance above Target is 9.
So our distance to pz.
What?
Okay.
oh,
oh my God.
How many times are we going to forget about this people?
We took out.
We took out Z movement.
Relative to the basis B.
We took that out.
Remember we decided we didn't want that and we took that out.
So this whole thing was probably working this fine.
They're like never probably was a bug, get it at all.
Oh my God.
So basically like all we really actually had to do.
Is this?
Hey, look at that.
It's in exactly the right place.
Well, at least it's good to have found it.
Oh my God.
Well, I hope you also had happened there.
That was like by Design.
That was like closed by Design with that bug report came in.
We would have been like, nope, that's how it's supposed to work.
Because remember, what we decided is, we didn't want to do anything.
Since this is a stupid two and a half D nonsense again.
Were you like don't use the offsets?
Man, I think we should just go ahead and yeah we gotta like we got to
figure out a better way to do the Z.
That's so annoying but we tried and we couldn't figure out like a good
way to do sort of like the two and a half D offset thing but that was
all was we don't use the Z.
So you pass in a z, doesn't matter what it is.
It's not going to work.
Lame.
That is lame, dude, that is super lame.
That is lame, lame.
Lame stuff.
To say, the very least.
Alright.
Chat did everyone understand that?
What happened there?
Hopefully everyone understood that.
So, yeah.
Unsurprisingly the bug was somewhere that we weren't expecting it,
which is?
Yeah, I mean, if I had looked closer, I would have seen back but I
never looked at that, that right there is the thing.
And again, like I said, it was actually a feature that we implemented
but I forgot that's how we did it, that's how we run to do it.
Sorry, I don't know.
Yeah, that's that's that's interesting.
I think that's the first time on handmade hero.
I can remember getting bitten by a feature.
Where we were like, oh yeah.
That's how it's supposed to work.
Mmm.
This two and a half D.
Nonsense is so annoying.
But, I'm really not sure what's a better option.
Right.
I mean it's just
That's just kind of the way it is.
Just kind of how that stuff goes man, you know.
All right, well, so surprised there was no bug but we were too dumb to
know that and so the bug was was us.
We were the bug.
What you going to do?
Well tomorrow.
We'll go ahead and finish.
What Iraq's?
Well I guess not tomorrow because we're off tomorrow but Thursday we
will go ahead and finish that.
What should have been relatively simple?
And what probably would have worked if we had remembered how our
actual renderer Works which we don't but that's fine.
All right, folks.
The bug was us.
I will see you guys on Thursday for some more handmade hero when we
will go ahead and finish what I actually wanted to do.
And yeah and there you have it.
So someone on the stream is asking if this bug would happen if you use
a library.
The answer is yes.
Apparently because if the library was spec to work the way our stuff
worked, we would have the exact same problem because we would not have
known that.
That's how they did things because we forgot apparently, even if
Read the documentation and read about it, and then we would have made
the same mistake.
Oops.
It happens sometimes, at least we found it.
That's the important part.
But it would be nice to maybe figure out some way to make it a little
more intuitive.
How those things work?
Because in two and a half d, right?
It's like
I just wonder if there's some way of more cleanly, specifying two and
a half D things in a way that we could.
You know, that we wouldn't really forget the go be very clear from
like a structure of it.
What it meant, I don't know.
But anyway, if you'd like to play around with this sort of stuff at
home, you can certainly go to handmade here, a.org the source, code
comes with the game.
If you preorder it, so you can check that out if you want to.
If you want to try finding some of these features on your own, you can
certainly do that.
But otherwise, that's all for today.
You can as always support us on patreon.
If you'd like to, you can go to the forums, ask questions.
If you would like to you can also look at the annotated episode guide.
You can check out the tweetbot which treats the schedule and yeah I
think that's just about it until next time, which I guess.
Will this this week will be Thursday at 5 p.m.
Pacific Daylight time.
Have fun programming guys and I will see you on the internet.
Take it easy.