Hello, everyone, and welcome to handmade hero.
The sure we code a complete game live on stream.
We finished our sort of our foray into showing how to do memory
management stuff over the past couple episodes where I showed, how to
take the same sort of techniques we were using with flat allocations
in handmade hero, and switch them to Dynamic applications if you
wanted them to be that way.
And so now we can kind of do either one.
We have the opportunity now to basically pick and choose.
And there's really very little almost no game code that really has to
change for that.
Pretty much all of the game code that we wrote originally can just run
on either system, it doesn't really matter as long as everything.
Kind of thinks of itself is operating through an arena.
There's not a lot of other stuff that we have to do there, and so we
could probably pretty Flex Flex.
Flex, ssibly switch between the two kind of models pre allocation and
dynamic allocation without really having.
Thing to think too hard about how our code is working, which is nice
because it means that that's not a decision.
We really have to care about too hard, right?
When, you know, that you can sort of have something to be pretty
fungible and not have to change very much code.
It means that you no longer really have to worry too much about that
during your development process because it's not really infecting
other parts of the code with that decision, in a way that makes it
hard to change.
So, the best kinds of systems in terms
of that flexibility are the ones where you know that your choice is
really just kind of free to change and you don't really have to worry
too hard about it because then you know when it comes time to ship you
can play around with the options then and see what suits your fancy
and you don't have to sort of have this latent fear in your head gets
kind of like well if we made the wrong decision early on it's going to
affect all of these other things in the project and then so we better
make sure we get it right because if we didn't get it right, then it's
going to be this huge cost.
Her to try and undo that mistake.
So, yeah.
Hopefully I've shown that that really doesn't matter.
As long as you kind of stick to the principles that we originally
established for dealing with Arena allocations that you can pretty
much then choose to treat the underlying system however you want.
And you can pretty freely switch between dynamically.
Grobel Arenas which allow you to use as much memory as you want or
pre-allocated Arenas, where you're going to guarantee that you've
tested your game and you know that it you know, if you
Pick a one gig footprint for it or something that it can stay within
that footprint and and leave it at that.
So you have options there, and hopefully I've given you a sort of a
good understanding of how both of them work and so that you can choose
which ones you want.
But now that brings us to a point in handmade hero where I don't
really know.
What we're doing because we don't have a specific to do, let's see
here.
So we've got maybe maybe the best things to do.
Now, would be to kind of go do some of the cleanup that we postponed?
Like I said, I normally don't like to leave bugs lying around in the
code base on handmade hero.
I sometimes have to because we're trying to kind of break things up as
much as possible into chunks that are like easy for people to sort of
Watch.
A continuous through line of the coding.
So we tend to sort of put things off a little bit, maybe that we would
have investigated a little sooner.
So we've got a couple things on here that are that way.
And so we've got the fact that our cutscenes were malfunctioning.
We've got the fact that the traversable stuff when we changed over
when we did a little bit of clean up on our stem region, things aren't
set up quite properly.
And then we also had sort of this a little bit of work to do on the
arena front.
Are now that we have the ability to switch between Dynamic and static
sort of allocated Arenas.
There is sort of one past we should sort of do over the code, which is
just to maybe make it a little bit clearer.
How Arenas aligned with each other, and how they are cleaned up.
So that we know that all of our Arenas we've thought through what's in
them now.
And maybe done a little bit more work on making sure that they're
reasonable and logical, how they work.
And, who's responsible for what?
Because it's good to just lock that down at some point.
I think we have enough understanding of how our system works at this
point that we should be able to, you know,
Clean that up a little bit more from where it was for how it kind of
randomly grew now that we sort of know exactly what all of the parts
are.
So I think that that that seems like a good thing to do is just to
start in on this maybe for the next couple days and just kind of
finish that stuff up and I'd like to kind of get to the point.
You know, we're we're we're we're maybe going to tackle this part here
because I do think I want to maybe upgrade things to be a more
traditional 3D.
Path as the last thing we do in our engine stuff and you know, I think
that based on my experience in ruminating on it which I've kind of
discussed a little bit.
I just really don't like the pure 2D path.
I'm glad we tried it.
It was my first time ever trying a 2d path.
I've always written 3D games before.
I've really never written a 2-D game.
I mean, I sort of maybe did one one time, but it was that an indie
game Jam where I was kind of using a prebuilt code base where
everything you know was already.
Done.
So I didn't I didn't really write much myself and it didn't have any
depth.
It was like a fully flat 2D game not like a handmade hero is where
there's like this sort of you know, orthographic View.
So, I'm really pretty heavily leaning towards.
Doing that.
So I think what I'd like to do is just over the next couple days get
us to that point and then do the graphics upgrade and we'll sort of do
a transition to the real artwork with the graphics up way upgrade kind
of in tandem there so that we can like get absolutely final stuff on
all of that.
We're we're sure that all of our coordinate systems are exactly the
way that we want them, because that's the only thing that I really
feel.
Like it's still kind of up in the air a little bit in terms of stuff
that I'm not comfortable writing large.
Each amounts of game code on top of because I just don't, like the way
it felt and that, that 2D stuff with the heavy sorting back end.
I really just don't like it.
And I think that probably going to a more traditional 3D pipeline
there, as much as it would be nice to not have to do for various
reasons like such as targeting lower end, things for fun like older
raspberry pies or something like that.
Maybe I really just think it's probably not going to work in terms of
Of what I would want to do with the game long term and you know,
particle effects.
Also it just it feels like that sorting is just too heavy weight and
there's really no other way to do it other than to go Z buffer.
And so I feel like what I want to do is just make that call and say.
All right, we'll go z-buffer and, and leave it at that because, you
know, there's nothing wrong with using a z-buffer, right?
That's what graphics cards are set up to do.
So, at some level, it's just like, I don't fight it.
I think it's just cleaner to go that
Way.
And we'll let the GPU do its thing and will Implement a z-buffer in
our software rasterizer and off we'll go, right?
So
I think that's the game plan.
At least that's my feeling about it.
I'm Jimmy
And at that point I feel like we'll have done a pretty good tour here
and I don't know what it'll be about, 400 Days of just about
everything, you might want to look at inside a game engine.
I mean, we've done so many.
It's kind of crazy to think back on how many different things that
we've shown how to do on this series.
It's been like, we've built so many things from scratch.
It's crazy.
So yeah, I think that that's a pretty good stopping point there, where
it'll be like all right, you know, we've covered
You know, we've given a taste of how to do just about everything that
you might be doing in a game engine, because now they'll be some 3D in
there as well.
And hopefully that's a really good solid base, you know, 400 hours
worth of materials that you can jump around in and then we can just go
from there.
We'll write the game code.
And, you know, the part that I like least
But I can't put it off forever.
Eventually, you have to write the game code.
If you don't have an another person who does that for you, that's what
you, you know, if you had a designer programmer, they would be doing
that.
And that's really a nice thing if you can find one.
But unfortunately, designers gamed good game designers are, there's
almost
Of them out there in the world.
Most game designers aren't aren't very good.
So you don't usually have the luxury of just having someone around.
Who happens to be a good programmer and a very good designer who you
can just be like, hey how about you do that game, code stuff.
So, you know, like it or not.
I am going to have to do that part of it.
And yeah, maybe we'll ask some game designers for help.
If we have any problems that were like, yeah, this is you
No, this is a design game design.
Think you're not really what I do.
So, if you want to maybe chime in on some design things, maybe we'll
ask John or Daniel or somebody to step in and and give us some advice,
but either way that seems like the game plan.
So I'm going to go ahead and just start taking a look at some of these
bugs here.
I don't know if we have any GitHub bugs.
Are I haven't looked in a while.
It looks like maybe we've got one which would be this one.
Obviously this is not really a bug.
This is just an important thing we have to do, right?
Not sure what this has to do with anything, but not really a bug per
se and so this I think is our only bug and so maybe and that would be
take care of when we do the graphics update.
I think so.
I think we're pretty good to go here.
So I think
Really, just looking at the bugs that we have here and I'll start
taking a look at those now.
So if I build the game, I believe what we found was that before when
we did the cutscene stuff, you know?
I when I ran the the cutscene stuff you hit Escape that jumps out to
the cutscene this again.
The pink screen is a placeholder for our title screen which is not
supposed to be there because no one's done in the artwork for it.
But then here, when we switch to this,
Screen here that we're looking at.
This should have been showing a, you know, the the orphanage shot and
all that stuff.
And it's not.
So what I'd like to know is what's going on there, you know, why are
we getting this?
This weird black screen, what's happening there.
So let's go ahead and take a look at the cutscene stuff and just just
get a quick, you know, feel make sure that, you know, the basic things
are happening and that we, when we were doing our reorganization,
And isolation.
We didn't make some really stupid mistake.
That's why this isn't rendering before we dive in any further and take
a look.
So you can see at least we're calling it, right?
We're coming through here.
We call render cutscene at time, so that's good.
We're taking a look at the shots and you can see here, we got
It's I guess it's on shot to at the moment or well shot one, but, you
know, the second shot.
So that's good.
That seems like what we would expect.
So we know that we're actually calling render render layered scene,
which is good.
And here on render layered scene, when we're kind of coming through
here.
We do our little, we do our little camera stuff here and going through
doing doing our push bitmaps, so that all looks good.
And so the only question here is
Like, well, you know, we did change the transform stuff recently and I
do wonder if when we train change the transform stuff, we may not have
really done what we needed to do in terms of setting up the this stuff
properly, right?
I don't really know, you know.
We haven't really looked much at this but I don't really know if we
thought through What would
To our cutscene code when we did some of those transform changes.
And if I remember correctly, there's kind of like, you know, in the
sort group stuff inside this transform thing.
There's a bunch of stuff here.
Like, what the floor is each chunk.
See stuff is right.
And so now a days when we pass in an update Z and in fact, now that
I'm saying this out loud, I feel like this is almost certainly what it
is.
When we pass in one of these things it was really the the this Z is
just becomes a y offset.
If you remember correctly and the Z that we actually use for
displacement is the floor Z.
Displacement stuff, right?
And so we probably it's just a case of where we were setting the Z
values before you can see that the p z value here, getting set where
we were, setting the Z, those Z values before.
Probably we just have to Now set a different Z value, to make it flow
through the transform pass, a little bit more cleanly.
So yeah, when we do,
Do entity basis.
See here.
Basis.
When we do this, right?
We then we change this thing to have the distance to PCB to pzb
distance of of Target - Flora, see, right?
And Flora Z is the value.
We pass in and distance above Target, right is just that that
stationary value.
So it's really just this part that's controlling that distance.
And so in general I think if we want our cutscene to be restored to
To working the way that it used to, then it's really not that anymore
in terms of what controls.
It's really the floor Z so it's really you know, oops, it's really
that.
I think that is what we would need.
And oops.
And that is probably most of our problem there.
Let's take a quick look.
I should probably set it up to start in cut scene modes.
We don't have to wait for the are quote, unquote title screen.
But again, I think that's part of it because, you know, we weren't
properly setting that value at all before, let's take a quick look at
what's going on there.
Alright, so inside, here are transform offset, P has a z value of
zero, which is what I want.
I don't want it to be offset there.
And now, we do have a floor Z offset of - 200.
Let's take a quick look here at what's going to happen when I flew
through the transform just so I can get a feel for what else gets used
here.
Right, hold on a second.
So here's my push bitmap call and and
Somewhere here.
We should.
Be getting the basis.
Tim that basis.
So get bitmap Tim automatically, does that?
Never mind, never mind.
But let's take a look at what it returned.
Anyway.
So let's see here, scale 3.77.
So I guess what I'd say is it looks like to let's just take a quick
look here.
You know here we've got our pz - camera off set C so that's clearly
talking about, you know, that that distance.
They're if we if we look and see what our Z values are, right?
Our Z values are actually kind of getting further away the Z value
kind of goes up right?
That's the opposite sense that it used to be though.
So really this value is supposed to be flipped around because the
floor is he goes up towards the screen, whereas our cutscenes were
going the other way.
So that's another bug in there in addition.
So yeah, so I've got
At least those two, those should both be fixed.
Now, trying to think if there's other things, that might be tricky
inside the transform.
Let's see how we're doing here.
If we were able to fix any of that.
Let's see.
There we go.
Why did that?
Let me see here.
Why did that not trigger right away?
And I know why.
Anyway, so, here we are on the floor Z, which I think now is
Well, that's still going the wrong way.
I thought when I looked at this before, I guess it wasn't going the
wrong way.
Let me just let me just double check because I want this to be going
upward.
Like I want the floor Z value to get negative as it gets further away
and I just want to make sure that that's actually what we're doing
here.
Because I know those e values in there, I just looked at the ones that
the cutscene they were actually going.
They were increasing as they got further away.
Why is that not trigger this?
By the way?
I guess.
There's just a pause a quick black screen in there or something like
this.
So anyway here we are with the camera off set Z and the peasy.
So I guess this is already negated.
We must already negate it when it comes in.
I guess, right?
And I'm not really sure why that is, but that's apparently how we do
it.
So, where do we get that from the layer?
The layer p-value here it is, is already pre negated, so why does that
happen?
How is that happening?
Because these are not negative here, so those must be negated in some
other way, right, I guess.
I mean, I don't know what else is happening there per se.
Let's see.
let's see here, intro cutscene
layers P.
So interestingly enough the layers in that actually do have - zzz
Oh, okay.
So that's just the scale.
I was looking at, I'm just an idiot.
I'm looking at the wrong value.
So they are - inside here.
I was for some reason looking at this, I don't know why brain fart.
I looked at the last value going over the last 50.
It's not Z, there's my ex, there's my why there's my Z so that all
makes sense.
So, there's that 200
- 200 so that that's actually good.
It's going - is going backwards into the screen which is what I
wanted.
So that's fine.
So when we compute this value, here is our computation.
This value comes out - which is what I want.
So I didn't have to worry.
That was fine.
It's assigned to the floor z.
Now I want to actually not mess up.
My stepping here, I want to step to see what the transform is that
happens there.
So here, we are in pushed.
Map.
I'm going to step in here and I'm going to look at the get render
entity basis P here so I can take a look at what happens.
So, here's my p-value, right?
And I'm going to put that in the watch window so I can see it a little
bit easier.
Here's my X and my Y and those are reasonable because those are the
upper corner.
So that, you know, that seems okay.
And let's take a look at object, transform offset key as well.
Just to make sure that that's not so
It's not changing the Z value at all, but it's got the X and Y in
there, and that's fine.
all right, so we're
Darth the graphic, we have distance above Target is set to what it's
set to nothing, so that's fine.
And then we come through here and we say, all right, whatever the
floor is e is then the distance away is going to be sort of the
negative of that, which is fine, which is 200.
There we go, the near clipping plane.
We don't have to worry about because we're certainly not that close to
it.
Height off.
A floor is 200 and oh-oh.
Ah, okay, so the Z value is still an absolute coordinates there.
So we have to then say because we're using that for y displacement, we
have to then also say that whatever the Z value is that we pass down,
which I guess we can pass.
The way we were passing is actually also going to be equal to that so
that they're set equivalently, right?
Both things.
Let's take a look at what we got there.
We have to step through that one more time, just to see what happens
after that one.
Meow, meow, meow, meow, meow meow meow meow, meow, meow meow.
Meow
Okay, so now the cutscene has been restored and that looks roughly
correct to me.
So I think we're good.
Let me go ahead and just speed us up a little bit here so that we can
see what are.what are cutscene.
Looks like later, we really need to work on our debug you.
I hear this is not in a very efficient way to to speed things up takes
forever.
So, all of these look like they used to look to me for the most part,
everything seems pretty.
Okay.
Now, I don't see a lot of issues here.
Yeah, so I think that's it.
It was just that fact that we added the weird floor stuff and the
cutscenes have to run through it again.
Probably another good reason to switch to a more traditional 3D path.
I mean this stuff is so hacky the the sort of Two and a Half D where
displacement thing just gets very happy and you know the nice part
about the 3D stuff is it's been so well kind of hammered on that you
kind of know the right way to do things.
Maybe again it's just that because I'm more
Instant 3D that it feels that way to me.
I don't know.
But 2D always just feels very happy to me in that way.
And I did it.
It's kind of frustrating anyway.
So that bug is done.
Let's take a look now at the traversals.
Again.
If you remember what this bug was, it's
That when I run the game, you can see that.
There's a problem with initial traversals.
First of all, those snakes are not supposed to start off on the main
character.
That's a total bug.
The there's there's not supposed to be any way to hop through those
trees, right?
Those traversals are supposed to be occupied by the trees.
They're not being occupied by the tree is currently.
So there's something about the initial creation phase, which we were
sort of working on a little bit that made it so that the traversable
is didn't get set.
Early and so that's like something that we definitely want to fix.
It's the only bug I noticed that got introduced when we did that sort
of change over.
And so we want to kind of go through there and figure out why that's
happening like what our problem is there because I don't actually know
what what's causing that and we want to just fix that one.
So let me go ahead and do that.
Cure is
The way that is happening at the moment.
So the Sim region.
I think we sort of Switched the packing so that now like world doesn't
do.
Oops.
World doesn't do the packing, right?
What we do is we just have ways to, to say, I want to put something
into a chunk, or remove something from a chunk, which is this, you
know, kind of code here that just in charge of like, bucketing up the
world, right?
Excuse me.
And that stuff is now entirely.
Just it's just what the same region uses to basically stream in and
stream out entities from the permanent World storage.
Now.
The thing is
We then when we want to create entities we have a SIM region that's
open that we use to create the things that we want to create in the
world.
But what we found is, although most of the things are working
properly, that sort of traversable placement stuff, isn't working
properly.
And so what I need to do is take a look at say, for example, why trees
are not being able to occupy their proper traversable points.
Now, if we look at when that
Happening.
I believe it's this code right here, you can see what happens when you
call add wall.
You pass it a reference to one of those traversable which is just like
okay like I'm talking about this place over here and that that's
reversible reference is just where the tree is supposed to be placed.
And what I don't know is why this code basically isn't working, right?
This entity occupying
Going to standing on code isn't working and we kind of want to look at
why that is.
So one thing I want to do first is I want to also ask the question of
what's Happening
Those traversable references.
Exactly, let me take a quick look at how those are working.
Let's see, traversable reference.
So you can see that it's got an entity reference there and an index.
And so it's just saying like, hey, here's the entity.
I'm talking about, here's the index of the entity as well for packing
purposes.
So let's take a look at just what it, what it set to in that call,
just so I can have a sense of what's even getting past in here.
So here I am in that call when one of those trees is getting passed on
to the system and it looks like.
All right, so there's no editi pointer but there isn't any value, The
Entity value is 7.
And so one of the interesting things about that is at this point, we
do have a SIM region.
So really that entity pointer should be valid.
And the fact that that entity pointer isn't valid is probably 100
percent of the
Well, um, actually, so inside the play World call.
When we're actually adding this wall, when we look up into the rooms
information, we're not getting back, the kind of traversable that I'm
looking for.
So what I'd like to do is I'd like to go ahead and find out why we're
getting why we're not having any pointers in there.
And that's probably all we really need to do so inside.
Handmade World mode.
When I have ADD standard room here and add standard room.
What I'm doing is, I'm getting back, right, these?
These traversable 's from that call.
So it's this.
It's this guy right here, that's malfunctioning.
He set up to zero as you can see.
So let's see what happens.
So this is probably our entire problem here.
We're setting just only the entity standing on index and we're not
sending the pointer really what we want to do is probably the
Rest of that.
Now, right?
We want to set the pointer.
So this is probably just some, you know, you know, this code is
hacking.
This is The Pact World gencode, which we haven't spent much time
thinking about.
So the fact that pointer wasn't set is probably most of the problem
it's might yet.
In fact, it looks like it was all the problem.
So we just weren't setting that pointer and we wanted to set that
pointer because that's when you have a SIM region.
That pointer is the thing that's actually being used.
We were probably just hacking the index ID there, back in the day,
when we didn't have a SIM region open.
So, we were just,
Old setting the values as you know, prior to packing.
So I think that's really all there is to that and now you know,
everyone is properly.
You can see that the trees have the highlighted orange debug thing
beneath them.
That lets us know that they're actually standing on that point, which
is what we want.
There's nothing over there obviously.
And so that's all well and good.
Everyone's happy, everyone's smiling, it's like Christmas morning.
It's like the most perfect little Christmas morning when
Krampus comes.
He actually comes before that, but that's beside the point.
All right.
So that was that bug and now that bug is gone and that's all good.
Well, and good.
It's 5:30 right now.
According to the clock, which means that we have 30 minutes to take a
look at something.
So maybe cleaning up this Arena stuff is the best way to do that at
the moment.
I'm not 100% sure how I want to go about that.
But probably what I want to do is put in something that forces us to
explicitly like initialize Arenas just so that we can kind of have
some kind of attribution as to what arena is what like right now we're
using zero initialization for Arenas which means that an arena can
just be set to zero it can just be cleared to zero and it will
magically stop start working.
I do like that in a in general.
That is how I
For a code to work in general, but in certain cases, there are reasons
why that's not so useful.
In this particular case, one of the reasons why that's not so useful
is that zero clearing the Arena's means that there's really no way for
me to put information in there about which arena is which right?
I can't set like any debug information on those arenas for example
because I'm not ever calling anything to initialize them, right?
So I literally have no idea what Arenas what and I can't do some kind
of trick like store the file and line number of the initializer.
The arena.
So that when I look through later and go, oh, let's see, who's using
what memory?
I can just go.
Oh, that's the arena that start, you know, from from this part of the
code and this is the arena from the other part of the code.
Now we can just to be clear, we can still gather that data and we have
other ways of gathering that data, the way that we have to gather that
data is to do it by Arena pointer.
And use sort of the debug collation system to pick up when people are
using various Arenas and storing the data that way.
So that is also another option, but it's definitely a more involved
option than Simply Having the Rios be initialized.
So there's that the other thing that's true about initializing Arenas,
is I kind of want there to be some attribution of Arenas to parent
Arenas basically.
Like I'd like to sort of have a Rena's.
Be at aggregated up so that you say you know, this arena is a
submarine of this other Arena so that if this Arena gets cleaned up
that Arena gets cleaned up, right?
Because typically, if even if you want to separate arenas for
allocations, oftentimes they can both be sort of thought of as getting
cleaned up at the same time and it just reduces bugs if I have to if I
have it so that an
Time I just kind of say cure the things it exactly the same as an
arena makes memory allocation simpler because you don't have to worry
about smart pointers or explicitly freeing things or Garbage
Collection or any of this stuff you can just say I have an arena.
All the stuff for this part of the code goes in it.
I know that if I want to just free at all, I just say, get rid of the
arena and I don't have to think too hard about it, right?
Kai does everything for me and it's nice and fast.
It doesn't take any time, right?
Well, the same thing is sort of true of attributing.
The Arena's, this is basically like saying hey Arenas sort of have the
equivalent of something like a smart pointer, which is to say that an
arena can be in charge of freeing a sub Arena, right?
And this is just a way of putting that sort of aggregation at a level
that I think makes more sense than doing something like individual
smart pointers.
Because the problem I've been asked about smart pointers before and
why don't use them there?
And I don't use them is because they're very inefficient.
They do a lot of work.
That doesn't actually need to be done and cause a lot of code
complexity to be introduced that that isn't actually doing anything
and that is tends to be stuff that I just don't, like, I would rather
have my code, only do things when it needs to do things as possible
and you know, to a certain extent C and C++ make it kind of difficult
to do that sometimes because they're not the best languages in terms
of high level constructs to be sure but Arenas are
Example of one relatively easy way, you can Implement something that
gets you out of the business of having all of the like all of that
crazy smartpoint Earnest and other things like that that I don't
really feel like are very useful but that isn't to say that the
concept of automatic cleanup is somehow bad automatic, cleanup is
great.
If you can figure out a way to implement it such that it doesn't do
any surgery work.
And with Arenas, I feel like you can kind of get a nice sweet spot
there where it's like, alright Arenas are all going to agriculture.
Up all of their allocations.
So you're not going to have a lot of, you know, hundreds of little
smart pointer deletion calls ruining your day, but you can sort of get
that same behavior of like, I don't have to remember to free the World
Arena.
When I free the game mode Arena, I can just know that those two are
linked so that when I close down this mode, the Arena's involved in
that mode, will clean themselves up correctly, right?
So you can kind of get
get a nice Best of Both Worlds scenario there where you can have the
automation, but you don't have to have any sort of
You know, you don't have to worry about that other like the, the sort
of pervasive waste that something like a smart pointer inserts into
your code base.
Right?
So yeah, so I just wanted to take a quick look at that.
One thing that we can do first is just take a look at everywhere.
We're actually
Using these things and just kind of get an idea for that for for how
that's working.
And you know, essentially we've got a lot of people who are getting it
passed into them potentially but in terms of people who are actually
doing it actually have one themselves.
Let's see here.
So we have one in the world.
What's going on here?
Why am I not able to?
I don't know why I'm not able to do that.
Oh right.
This I'm using a version of for coder.
That's a little bit old.
I probably should upgrade my for coder.
I was like, why can't I go next and previous in this buffer?
And it's like because that was implemented in 4.0 12 or something like
this for a part of 11, which I don't have installed, but I should all
right.
Anyway, no real issue there.
We can still take a look at this fairly cleanly.
So we've got one in handmade worlds.
That that I least I thought that
So when there, where was it inside?
Hamid world.
Yeah, right there, we've got one in handmade world.
And then we've got some in handmade hero, you can see them sitting
there, we've got like the audio, one runs the transient Arena, the
game mode Arena, and then we've got the asset Arena, the debugger
Arenas, and that's it.
So, there aren't very many of these.
There's actually very few of them and yeah, I guess so, one of the
things that we
And do.
Now, if we want to is, we could pretty easily start thinking in terms
of having the the arenas for like modes and stuff like that living
inside the mode, which might be a little bit better than it is right
now.
And the reason that's a little bit better than what we were doing
before, our is just because at the moment we couldn't keep multiple
modes around, if that makes sense.
Like
we could actually create sort of a more robust type of like mode
Moodle system if we want to.
I don't know that we really, really do want to though, to be, to be
completely honest with you.
So, yeah.
So there's that.
Let me take a look at the World Arena stuff.
Is there actually?
Is it actually using its own?
I guess it's not I guess the World Arena is just using whoever it's
passed in as so I'll be honest.
Maybe there really isn't anything to do here.
It doesn't really look like there's there's all that much to do.
Where's the search that?
I just performed.
There it is.
There's really not very much to do here.
It's pretty straightforward.
Gosh.
So, so maybe maybe we just don't need to do anything here.
We've kept our memories usage, pretty clean.
And I could pull that out but I guess I don't really know that we need
to
I could just leave it like it is for now.
Yeah.
Yeah, I don't know.
I guess I'm going to have to say I do not really know.
Yeah.
Like what what to do about that?
It looks like maybe this is just kind of the way it should be.
Let's let's at least verify that we're not like leaking memory here.
Though.
You can see kind of our memory block situation where we've got, you
know, our footprint up there.
It's, that includes debug.
So a lot of that memory is also
We're going to be from the debug system and so on.
Let's just make sure that when we switch in and out of these modes
that we don't that we aren't hemorrhaging any memory here.
Like here, for example, we have seventy six blocks allocated and you
can kind of see it.
It's stable at 76, is the cutscene playing?
If I was to switch back into the game here I've suspected of the game.
I've got seventy seven blocks allocated here, let's switch back out,
or back down to 76 Back in 77.
So, you know, we've got a nice stable.
Footprint.
I just want to make sure that was the case.
So yeah, I guess I won't touch this anymore.
Then I think that's fine, just the way it is.
And I don't know that I really want to do this either.
I think that that's probably fine the way that it is.
So, yeah, we're kind of just down to this, which I've got about 20
minutes left, and I don't know that I'm going to make much Headway out
of here, but in terms of multiple SIM regions for frame.
Yeah, this was kind of
This was kind of just a problem with overlapping where we couldn't
really figure out how we were going to deal with the overlap problem.
And I talked about this a bunch and I don't remember any put real
solutions to it.
Unfortunately if me see if I've got a oh, I haven't rebooted the
machine yet, have I I need to, I need to put like a sticky note on
this machine to reboot it.
So that the because the walk em dry
Ivers are no longer working.
Remember they died for some reason.
I think when we, when we had that time, when we allocated so much
memory, we like trash the machine.
When we just like allocated, we were allocating without freeing and if
you remember that.
Yeah, but I gotta remember to do that because otherwise I won't get
the proper tracking.
But oh well, so the problem here on day 3 48, we go.
This is like overlaps overlapping.
Simulation, the problem with that was just that we can pretty easily
do multiple simulations per frame.
So, if you think about
The game world looking kind of like this.
And let's say this is how big a screen is so very tiny.
And maybe there's another screen all the way over here.
And like, yeah, there's like, you know, who knows tons of stuff in
between here but you can like walk between it and whatever.
So I could go all the way from here to here and it's like quite a few
rooms away.
Well, maybe I want to be simulating something here.
And I want to be simulating something here because maybe up here.
There's, you know, some NPC who's doing something important.
Like maybe this, let's say, there's an NPC who's like looking for the
hero and it's maybe going to find the hero eventually.
So the NPC is like, walking along this path maybe and eventually going
to get to the room that the heroes in.
So here's the the NPC, you know, it's the simulation region would kind
of be moving along this path.
Moving moving, moving.
And then eventually the the simulation regions would overlap.
And you'd be left in a situation, where like, if this is a simulation
region, here's the screen.
And here's a simulation.
One region for the hero.
Right there would be an equivalent situation where maybe it would look
like this for the NPC.
And so their simulation regions, share a common boundary here and the
problem with that is just that there's no way to reconcile this
problem as far as I can think of in my head.
Essentially, the only thing you can do that doesn't create.
Some kind of weird.
Buggy behavior is to merge the region so that your sim region now
looks like this.
Right.
So that's actually fine, right?
There's nothing particularly onerous about that and if it was just the
case of, you know, in a typical game, there's what NPC and one Kuro
that need their region simulated, that's probably fine, right?
That that would just be fine.
but the problem is, if you have multiple NPCs and the hero
Hmm.
you can end up in some
Upstate where you've got lots of NPCs close to each other.
And close to the hero.
You end up with a giant Sim region that can't be subdivided and your
frame rate would just tank, right?
So I don't really have a solution for this problem.
I don't know what you do to prevent that from becoming a serious
problem.
Other than just not allowing there to be enough NPCs that you would
ever get into a situation where that could occur like, you know, you'd
Force NPCs to only live in
Our various regions.
And, you know, NPC's can't free roam to some degree, right?
So we know that, you know, maybe there's one or two NPCs that can free
roam and we'll end up near the hero together and maybe that's fine.
But then the rest of the NPC's who might be simulated stay within
predefined areas and won't meet up with each other to create, you
know, that kind of bad chaining effect.
so, that's
Alls I'm talking about, right?
I hope that makes some sense there.
Yeah.
But
Other than that, everything else that we do right now?
As far as I know, is would just work like our multi simulating,
multiple regions per frame would just work.
I don't know that there's any problems with it and so then we could
have like, all kinds of interesting NPC Behavior going on and stuff
like that.
So, one thing that might be interesting to know and I don't really
know what it is at the moment.
So I'm just going to take a quick Gander here is
Without, you know, even though it means nothing because we're not
really doing anything at the moment, I just want to get a ballpark
estimate for if we were running in 02 mode, even just what we've got
right now?
What are we seeing in terms of a profile hit for, you know, the
simulation step, right?
So here's update and render entities, right?
And here's the clocks for that.
What?
I guess.
I don't know.
Is what's that looking like in here?
So, cures, debug collation.
Here's the game update.
Here's game update and render inside game update and render.
We have update and render world's update rid of particle systems and N
Sim, where's begins him?
Is that an update and render worlds?
Yeah, begin Sim.
Execute brains update and render entities.
So these are just really cheap at the moment.
I guess is is one thing, so that's kind of nice.
maybe I shouldn't worry about them too much, but, you know, yeah, if
we were to get back to go back to the
Here.
You know, if that if that merge four or five times, it can get pretty
big.
I don't know maybe.
Yeah, but maybe that's just not a problem.
I guess I just don't have enough information to really make any kind
of decision about this.
I guess, maybe what I should do is just cross my fingers and go.
All right.
Well, you know,
Until we actually have real world scenarios running.
There's no way to make some kind of a priority, determination of like,
what's going to happen here.
So maybe the best thing to do is to just say, let's go ahead and you
know, let's thread this thing and see if we just do multi-threaded
World update across multiple threads like we do with our render or
whatever.
Let's just try that out and see.
If we have that happen, make sure that that's all working fine and
then we'll call it a day.
What?
I don't know, at the moment is how we would really debug that sort of
stuff necessarily let's
Zoom out here.
Because we're probably going to need some kind of a debug view, right?
I mean, like, you know, we can get, we could use like a View, kind of
like this one where we can see more stuff.
Unfortunately, our current renderer is not really set up.
It's only set up to render.
Things relative to a particular camera.
I guess what we could do is just force, the other SIM regions to
render as well.
Like, in debug mode, we could force them to render out so that we
could have sort of more things going.
I don't know.
Let's play around with this for just one quick second here.
I'm going to go ahead and see what I can do in terms of
Creating more entities.
We probably need something.
We probably need some way of dealing, with, with creating worlds.
We don't really have a way to create big worlds, right now, we can
store them and process them, just fine.
We just don't have a way to really create them at the moment.
So, that's a bit of a problem.
But, here we go.
Let's just see what happens if I create a tiny world, but that just
happens to be bigger.
So, if I go ahead and
take a look here at the
world.
So yeah, if I go out here,
Error.
This is just a really long world, right?
This world just keeps going
and going, right?
So what I kind of need to do and let me, maybe let me re-enable that
make sure that we can actually make our game kind of go around a
little bit, little bit more than that.
There we go.
So yeah, so you know, I guess what I'm saying is at the moment, we
have a way to do a debug camera of that form, but we don't have a way
to do a debug camera of like this form where it's like super wide out
and instead of just showing what's in a simulation region, which is
what we're showing right here.
I would want to do something where we've got a little bit more, you
know, information on the screen.
Like so if we had multiple stim Regents, we'd see all of them.
Yeah.
Let's just try that.
Let's just see what that would entail.
I've got eight minutes left.
Let's see what happens if I just play with that a little bit.
So in World mode, Let's see what happens here.
We sort of have this this idea that, you know, we start the Sim here.
We are looking for controller input.
Here, we update the brains here.
We render things and then we finish, right?
So,
If we wanted to talk about a single unit of that, right?
Like a single one of those I could I should be able to pull that out
into a more coherent like thing.
So we do update and render world, I should be able to do something
here.
Where I've kind of got another one of those
Function here.
That's going to be a little bit more concise so you know, let's say
we've got this, begin Sim call.
Let's see where the Sim regions actually used and you can sort of see
the same region bounds getting used there in the wrecked outline stuff
and then this getting used here.
So let me just pull it at the Sim region part Sim Region 2 SIM region.
Right?
So
Where we do sort of the temporary memory block.
In fact, where is the memory itself?
It's right here.
So yeah, let's do this.
So here is a Sim step.
This is like, you know, simulate something like this.
Or this is like do some region, I don't know.
So here's update and render Sim region.
And this thing, you know, does all the stuff that we would normally do
now,
Essentially, what I want to do is kind of predicate this.
I'd like to say, you know, are we accepting controller input, you
know, or aren't we?
And I don't know if the best way to do that is to do that here or if
that is something that we should sort of have this be in stages that
happen, I'm not sure.
But let's just make it be an if at the moment.
so like if Flags, you know, allow controller
Or allow, like, spawning don't know, something like that.
There's the brains happening update and render entities, and update,
and render particle systems and then we end, right?
So, we've got all that stuff.
And I guess part of the problem,
You know, at the five-minute warning, I'm probably not going to want
to do much of this.
So I probably would just leave this where it is at the moment because
what I realized too is we have some stuff baked in there that we don't
want baked in there.
Like if we go back, if we go to n Sim I think we've got some stuff in
here that we don't really want, like we've got the camera following
entity stuff, I guess that's okay.
Because if I render somewhere else that into they wouldn't be on
there, but I think we need to be more careful about that, sort of
stuff, if that makes sense.
All right.
So, let's see frame to frame camera, Delta p and all that stuff needs
to get.
So let me let me just see what we need in here.
So we need camera bounds and M, the Simba and stuff.
This stuff I think can actually Sim bounds expansion.
I think that stuff can actually be kind of over here still or maybe
put inside the Sim stuff itself.
Let me just take a quick look in here and say let's put that there.
There.
So here's the Train Arena stuff for beginning temporary memory.
So let's say that we pass, do we need the trance state for anything
else?
No.
The update and render entities, does need it.
I guess so guess we need the trance state in there.
We're going to want to pull some of the stuff apart.
I can totally tell but their books World mode.
And world is just.
Off of world mode, I believe.
So we don't really need to pass that in symbols.
Should probably be passed in, right?
And input.
So this is one way we could do it.
We could just say, if you pass this, an input, then we'll process
input.
Otherwise we won't
Let's see.
Rectangle 3, my bad.
So then we need to render group screen bounds.
And game state.
I feel like we're going to have to and maybe this would be good too.
I think this would be nice if we could spend a little time cleaning
the stuff, we've got too many struct.
Some of stuff that probably, we could consolidate and be a little bit
more judicious about those things would probably be good.
Let's see, Mouse pee.
Scott too many.
We've just put all the stuff into this code.
It does it in one pass and that's fine.
But it just feels like now is a good time that it's complicated
enough, we're going to want to, you know, sort of extricate, pull some
of those or exfiltrate, perhaps, some of that stuff out.
So that it's not in there when we're just trying to do like basics,
Some stuff that makes sense.
So really screen bounds is not something.
We have to draw in here.
I don't think but you know we might need that for other reasons so I
guess I'll pass it for the moment, tangle free screen bounds.
We do need the render group.
There we go and background color, I don't know what background color
is, therefore Oak for Farrar Fade Out effect, right?
Yeah.
Draw buffer.
what are we using the draw buffer for
I'm curious to know.
Like, what is the drug before do inside?
Entity update, render entities?
Radha.
I can't see because it's behind my head.
Let's try that again.
Draw buffer.
so it's just for putting the alpha floor, clip, rect and
So really, the only reason that we have to do that at all is just
because the width and the height are required to do the push wrecked
in the case, where we're not even trying to push a cliprect, we just
wanted to have a way of saying, hey we've got that Alpha floor, render
Target that we wanted to Target, and we needed the to do that.
So that one's like definitely the case to where it's like, you know,
you can see how there's too much stuff that needs to be kind of
Peace, you know, peace depart there.
So yeah.
I definitely think that this is good thing to do tomorrow to get into
some of this, get into some of this stuff.
All right.
So I'm just going to leave it just to leave ourselves in a functioning
state.
I'm going to leave it like it is here and right after we do sort of
our sin bounced up, I'll call that function.
But yeah.
I think that's just, that's too much and so pulling some of that stuff
out and like, separating out the responsibilities there.
So we have more control over who needs.
What and when we'll just allow us to have
Of a little bit better division of labor in there.
So let's go ahead and go to the Q&A for now.
If anyone has any questions, Now's the Time to ask them.
Happens.
If you jump on this.
That's awesome.
It like tried to jump but couldn't move the head through.
It's trying to jump to the other one member because this was for
jumping up and down, floors.
That's hilarious.
It can't move the head through the trees, though.
Hysterical.
So I wonder if we moved it down one if it would be able to write.
Like if we were to say
in a standard room, there is thing that's like
Yeah, Auto booster.
Whatever it is the offset.
Why I like
if that was moved down on the left hole,
Oh, come on.
Get out of my way, guys, uncool.
Here we go.
So the problem is that one.
Still up at the top there, so we need to, like, we need to get that.
That one down.
All right, seriously.
Get off the thing.
Lame.
There we go.
I kind of like these boots squares.
I think I'm going to put these boost squares to good use.
Like when we actually do some real rendering here of like some
artwork, I think it would be funny if you could jump on things and
have them kind of boost you around like that.
I don't know.
It's looking really cool.
I'm going to, I'm going to keep that in there.
Will the switch to 3d effect the arc work for him a hero?
I know we're will keep the artwork basically the same.
yes, you can ask and ask have a question generally, what I do is I
give precedence to any questions that are on topic, but if there
aren't any
On topic questions than I just use the time to answer off-topic
questions.
Lori says, hi I'm way behind you in the series but you talked about
Mixon.
I don't know if you did this yet, but can you please explain it?
So one of the problems with that term, of course, is that different
people use it for different things so I'm not even sure if you look it
up, whether it's used.
It's kind of an observation term that is not maybe as clear as it
needs to be.
But here you go.
And essentially what it's trying to talk about is just the fact that
you can you know, sort of
Consider making something that's just a bunch of different things
combined together, rather than the sort of higher the sort of C++, the
early C++ idea of object-oriented programming, which is kind of
broken, which is like things inherit from other things, which is not
usually a very good way to build things.
And other object-oriented language is don't have that problem.
Like, that's not endemic to all object-oriented, programming languages
more.
Object-oriented programming languages in C++ don't think of ab
training programming in that way.
But essentially, all a mix in is, is a mixing is just saying, well, I
want to be able to create especially in like, a game like setting.
I often want to be able to create objects that just have a bunch of
properties that I want them to have.
And I don't want to have to, really think about
How that's constructed, right?
I don't want to have to think about like, oh, you know, this creature
inherits from Human so that it can have like bipedal locomotion
Ocean and it and then, you know, I but then I kind of wanted to have
mandibles like a spider, but I can't inherit from spider because I can
only inherit from either human or spider because human and spider,
both defined Locomotion.
You can only have one or the other, you know, blah, blah blah.
So mixing is just the concept that like K.
You just grab what you need from where you need it.
And so, for example, you could grab The Locomotion from Human, you
know, bipedal locomotion is a thing that you can grab
ab and then mandibles, the thing you can grab.
And it's just kind of like, you know, this this sort of piece together
parts to make the thing that you were trying to make.
So that's all a mixin is, is just that concept and C++ kind of, really
sort of sort of poops, the bed, you know, kind of, kind of Browns, the
bed a lot when it comes to being able to support mix-ins, they do a
really poor job of
Because there's a bunch of stuff at can't do, like, referring to Outer
Scopes.
And there's, there's all these reasons.
Why mix-ins don't really work correctly and C++ that are not
inherently problems with the concept of object-oriented mix in there
just problems with C++.
You know, what else is new?
And so typically what ends up happening is if you want to actually
Implement Mixon in C++ for something that you're doing, typically, you
end up kind of writing the system yourself, which is what we did as
well, right?
We have the idea of a, like sort of giant mush entity model thing
that's designed to give us certain benefits of mixing like stuff.
And you know, that's typically what almost every game engine does like
almost new.
Game engines that I know of of any prominence try to use C++ like
features to do mix-ins because really all C++ that you do, there is
either multiple inheritance which doesn't really work very well for a
number of reasons or you just have you know a class that includes has
members of the things that you want and that also doesn't work very
well because you can iterate over them properly and there's all these
other problems with it, right?
So typically
Ali what almost every game engine does is they end up implementing
their own mix in right and either exporting it to a scripting language
or just using it inside C++ their own system.
Somehow of doing that either with like lists attached to the entities
or whatever else to basically compensate for that fundamentally flawed
C++ problem, right?
And still there are you working on any of the interaction student like
fire weapons versus ice?
Monster poisonous arrows and stuff like that?
Probably not, I wouldn't think so.
Tiny construct.
Very have topic.
Can you think of the last time you took a dynamic programming approach
to a problem?
EG shortest, edit distance, opulent bsts, Etc.
DP algorithms are allegedly a common interview topic despite how silly
that seems
So I guess I can't say that I've used one recently.
I mean.
so, depending on your view of what you would consider a proper dynamic
programming approach, there are definitely
There are definitely types of things that programmers often write
without thinking about them as being dynamic programming problems that
do have, the structure of memoize dynamic programming, right?
And
Hopefully, this is a term, yeah.
so,
To give an example.
First of all, let me just say what's on our program is.
So because I'm sorry I can't really think of what I've done in the
past couple months.
Let's say, so what dynamic programming is, is dynamic, programming is
usually about a bottom-up approach to a problem.
So, for example, you know, most of the time, you think about things
where, you know, you'll think about sort of divide and conquer,
Oops.
Or something like this, you know as kind of a programming strategy or
whatever where you might think about constructing things like you
know, a binary tree or something.
And so the idea is you know you have some top down approach to
something where you're trying to divide stuff up into more manageable
pieces, right?
And so you tend to think about coming at things from this perspective,
where you know, we've divided stuff up and we're kind of like the way
that we're sort of optimizing this algorithm is by participating.
Learning what it's working on Endo way so that it only works on the
things that it actually needs to work on, right?
So, you know, a lot of stuff that we talked about falls into this
category, but dynamic programming is sort of about doing, you know, a
slightly different way of thinking about that sort of thing rather
than thinking about it in this way.
It's like thinking about it in terms of, let's start with all of the
stuff that we have and just
Working with it and then what we'll do is we'll build up from there.
So you know, we'll do some stuff on these three elements.
But then we'll remember that we did that and then we'll build some
stuff on these three elements and remember that we did that and then
later, when we need to do stuff on all six of these elements will just
reuse the stuff that we did from those pieces, right?
and so sort of if you want to think of dynamic programming as just the
act of
Saving work that you've already done to reuse it later in a way that
builds upon that work.
That is the sort of thing that programmers can often write without
thinking that they were doing anything dynamic programming.
Like, they may, not even know the term dynamic programming, but that's
still kind of dynamic programming.
And so the thing that came to mind was, you know, let's say that
you're storing stuff out to disk write and like,
Oh wait, no, we did.
We did one.
I was like God.
It seems like we should don't want him here.
We did do one.
The graph, sorting the graph sorting in, in handmade here.
Oh, it does does do this, right.
So here is sir, I was like, gotta, it seems like we should have used
something that was deceptively dynamic programming.
So, yeah.
Remember our sorting stuff, right?
Where we did sort entries.
So, remember how this thing worked, we did a thing where we'd say,
okay, like we built a Sprite graph,
And then we did a recursive front-to-back sorting, right.
And the way we did that is we would go through and we'd sort things.
But when we sorted them, we would mark them as having been visited,
right?
So later when we were sorting things, that contained, that part of the
graph, we wouldn't re sort that part of the graph, we just know that
we'd already sorted that part and could just point into it, right?
That's sort of dynamic programming, right?
We didn't.
Partition.
This ahead of time into into connected sub graphs, which we could have
done and then sort the subgraphs we instead just sorted.
We just started sorting and we remembered every time we did sort.
So that if somebody else was coming in, who also needed to insert
themselves into that sort, they just could.
Does that make sense?
Tiny construct.
Does that help at all?
Because that's sort of like, a more, you know, a fairly light, but but
traditional concept from dynamic programming, right?
Is just
Hey, we start sorting this graph.
We remember that we sort parts of it.
Well, we don't really remember that.
We start parts, we just have ways of knowing if we sorted parts of it,
and then it's like, hey, don't start that again.
We already sorted it rather than keeping the graph in some structure
that we know which parts are which
Midlow asks, how about movable boosters that you can set up to chain
boost you?
Yeah, I mean we support it, right?
All right, so yeah.
So, anyway, ton of contract.
I hope that answers the question a little bit in terms of like more
traditional like named, you know, traditionally named dynamic
programming algorithms.
I don't know that, we've definitely not used them on handmade hero and
I don't know that I've used one recently.
You know, I am implementing some compression stuff right now and it's
not entirely out of the question that some dynamic programming might
happen on the 1935 codebase in the next couple weeks.
But it depends like some of the stuff with like, you know, forwards
optimal parsing and stuff like this sort of stuff.
It's entirely possible that I might use something that from dynamic
programming in, in a compression, in a dictionary compression stuff,
kind of thing.
But
SDS gimenez.
So part of the dynamic, programming question, mentioned the coding
interview?
Do you do one for new hires?
Well, we don't really hire any programmers at Molly rocket.
I'm the only programmer.
We pretty much only hire artists and no, we don't ask them about
dynamic programming.
I guess what I would say is I never asked
so, I've said this before, and
I'll say it again, just briefly in my mind.
Any interview that involves an interview, question of that nature is
not a good interview and will not produce good results.
So
so, my reasoning for that, is that
I have not known.
Really any programmers ever.
Where their ability to answer a question that they were unfamiliar
with had anything to do.
Whether they were someone that I wanted to program with or that I
would trust to write a good program.
It is literally unrelated pretty much every even the very greatest
programmers that I've known their good answers to questions.
Come only after they have had a chance to think about those questions
and internalize them on their own time, right?
And I think this is true of pretty much everybody.
Like, you know, if I walk into it, someone's office at Rad or
something and start talking to them about a problem.
There's only two reasons that I'm doing that.
Well, I guess technically there might be three one is because I think
they know more about this already than I do, right?
Like maybe I
On a walk into Charles blooms office and talk to him about
compression.
I'm not doing that because I think he's so smart that he's just going
to suddenly, no compression really well.
And have some great things to tell me about the problem I was working
on.
I just know he's a compression expert.
So I know he's already spent tons of time thinking about these things
and that's where his smarts right, you know, like he's a very smart
person who spent a lot of time thinking about that.
So that's why I want to have a white board discussion with him about
compression.
It's not
because I think he's just instantly going to know answers that other
people didn't know, or something like that, right?
So that's 12 might be if I just want to talk it through myself.
So I've been thinking about this problem a lot and it's about
compression and maybe I'm talking to someone who doesn't know anything
about compression, but that's okay because I know they're smart and
we'll just ask questions of prompt me and it's really about me,
thinking it through, not about them, thinking it through, right or
third.
It's if I want that person to think about it over time.
So like, okay, I'm going to go into the office.
It just talking about say, hey think about this, let me know, you
know, after you know, we'll talk about it again tomorrow or some of
that, right?
I have literally never thought.
Let me go into this office of this person who doesn't know anything
about this subject matter.
And I'm going to ask them this question.
And I'm
Them to have any any insight into it at, all right.
Then that just, that's not a thing.
I don't care about it.
I don't care how well, they can do it.
It makes no difference to me what someone can think about in 30
minutes.
I'm it's irrelevant right?
So the fact that this exists encoding interviews, boggles my mind, it
makes no sense.
I think it has nothing to do with whether you're a good programmer.
I think it has nothing to do with whether you'll be a good employee.
I think it has nothing to do with whether you'll be successful at that
job, no matter what that job is.
Because the thing that you are doing in that moment is literally 100%
unrelated to any job function, you will ever have in that capacity.
Full stop.
So I think the much more intelligent way to run a tech interview.
And I've said this many times on stream is the way Chris, Hecker
taught me how to do it.
And unfortunately, he's still never written this up.
I've asked many times to do it.
He has not, but I've explained it before and that is a properly.
Run.
Tech interview is you read the person's past work history?
And You Begin by asking them a series of get to know project questions
about something in that history.
So for example, let's say that going back to the compression example,
let's say that the person says on their resume, that they did a bunch
of work on compression in school or at their previous employer.
So I'm going to say, oh, tell me a little bit about what you do with
compression.
Okay.
What was the most interesting parts of that for you tell me like, give
me some background so that I can get to know the candidates project
like
They were doing on something that they said they did a bunch on,
right?
Then you pick some specific thing that they've mentioned there and you
drill down on it, to generate a proper interview, sort of problem, out
of what they have given you.
So, you find their core competency like what they are comfortable
with, and what they said they've worked on.
Then you build the thought problem out of that, it's like, oh we get
down there and it turns out that they like weird started mentioning LZ
compression.
Be like oh, okay.
So LZ, compressions, kind of interesting, right?
Like tell me about how
You coded your, you know, LZ.
You know, when you were outputting the symbols, you know, what did you
use for a back end.
Oh yeah, why did you choose that?
Oh, so what do you think about arithmetic and coders?
Like, did you try one of those like why did you choose Huffman?
Oh, it was for Speed purposes.
So what kind of architecture was this like that you were doing it on
and like, you know, blah blah.
So you want to, you want to build out and find out how well does this
person.
Think through the problems that they've actually worked on how well
did they retain that knowledge?
Can they explain it to you?
Are they able to answer good questions about trade-offs that they you
know, should have thought of that?
Time has any of these things ever occurred to them bubble.
That's how you do it.
And I find that that correlates very highly with whether somebody is a
good has a, is it capable of doing good programming?
The one thing that it does not screen for and I have no idea how you
actually screened for this.
It's the one thing that I have no idea what, how you can actually
determine the one thing it does not screen for.
Or is productivity.
So this interview technique much like the brain, teaser one like it.
As far as I know.
This interview technique has no downsides that other interview
techniques.
Don't also have and it has none of the other downsides that those
interview techniques do have except for one which they all share which
is that, you can have someone who's just a very smart, very capable
programmer who just never is capable of sitting in front of the
computer and
Actually programming.
Right.
So they may be somebody who gets almost no programming done in every
day not because their brain doesn't totally capable of thinking it
through and being smart about it and understanding it and writing good
code and all of those things they just never do it.
They like to talk all day or go to coffee or who knows what else,
right?
And this is a huge problem.
So I don't know how you figure that part out.
I have no idea.
Maybe you, look at the person's track record, or maybe you just
contact them for six months and see if they actually are doing work.
I don't know.
But what I can tell you is that as in terms of screening whether the
person is capable of writing good code and capable of understanding
things that is that that Chris hackers interview is the right
interview process.
I'm
Pretty positive that that is the way you go interviews that it revolve
around a prefab.
Question, our are awful.
They are just a bad idea.
I have no idea why they are popular.
I can I can pretty much guarantee you.
They just do not produce good, reliable results.
I think they end up.
Biasing you towards candidates who happen to have seen questions like
that before, which is not an indicator of their ability to solve,
interesting.
New problems, they bias.
You against people who are nervous or aren't fast on their feet.
Some of the best programmers you will come across.
Do are not comfortable interacting socially that way with people,
especially in a situation where they may feel intimidated, right?
I think it's it's just a it's an and I think that's true pretty much
across all demographics.
Like like I think that that no matter who you're looking at,
There's a high degree of chance that you might get somebody who would
be a very good programmer, but they will feel intimidated or
threatened or just plain nervous in this scenario.
And even if they would be capable on their own time of doing an
excellent job on the thing, you're asked to do it.
They just won't be able to in this situation and again, not a job
skill, right?
Like having someone respond, well under Fire, not a job skill of a
A a programmer sits in relative quiet with no threatening Persona or
intimidating.
Watchful eye hovering over them with their job, on the line every day.
That that is not at all the environment in which a programmer should
be working.
And if that is the environment that your company has set up, you've
got problems, right?
So Insurance Lee, what you're sort of screening for in in addition in
that interview
This is not only is this person familiar with this arbitrary subject
matter that we pulled out of a hat.
Like maybe they just never done dynamic programming before.
Who cares?
You can learn dynamic programming in a week less than that.
If you don't need to learn like a ton of different ton of different
variants on it, right?
So, who cares if they've ever seen that?
It's irrelevant, right?
But if someone's never seen dynamic programming before, they're
probably not going to be comfortable working on a dynamic programming
problem.
It's going to be very new to them and they're going to need a day or
two for it to sink into their brain.
Like what it means and how they might apply it, and that sort of
stuff.
So, why are you asking that question?
That's just dumb, right?
It doesn't make any sense and it doesn't give the interview, the
interview candidate, a chance to demonstrate whether they're a good
programmer or not, right?
So you need
Make them comfortable.
You need to put them on their own turf and and ask them questions
about things.
They have become familiar with to see how familiar.
Did they become with them?
They had plenty of time to do this thing at their previous employment
or in school.
What did they do, right?
And how did they do it?
You can find that out from them.
You don't need to make some stupid question.
Like, you know, can you prove that there are two places in the world
on opposite sides of the globe that have the same temperature or
Something else stupid like this.
Let's see here.
So I really should probably get going soon.
We're way over time here but I'm just looking to see what there's a
lot of questions, all of a sudden.
Is there any time you've talked about deep learning?
No, I have not.
I'm also not super knowledgeable about about learning based algorithms
and I have like limited experience with some of them but definitely
not.
Anyone like that.
That is probably the the current kind you might see.
Like neural networks.
I've never done a neural network algorithm
speaking of past jobs, would you rather see a job at a Java shop
versus a local colleges faculty for high performance Computing?
Again, I don't care.
I'm not the one to ask because I don't really hire people, right?
Like, if we ever hired people at Molly rocket, they'll be probably
very few people and they're probably people, I know already, right?
So you know my opinion on how to hire is not that relevant in terms of
people seeking employment.
I feel like the advice I have
To give on that.
It's just more like if you're trying to hire people, you know, and
don't do the things that Google does.
For example, I think they just have a really bad hiring process and
not to be too glib about it but I think it kind of shows in the
quality of their software to but that's a separate issue anyway.
Like I feel like you kind of need to to think that through in terms of
hiring but in terms of getting a job, you know, I don't I don't have
much to say because I'm not
Not the kind of person who's hiring for most of the available
positions out there.
It's more like the type of people who are hiring are more like the
kinds of people who tend to think that it's cool to ask a stupid
question in an interview about some puzzly weird thing, right?
As for if you're just asking out of curiosity, what I'd rather see, I
don't care what's on a resume as long as there's something on it.
I can ask about that will allow me to tell whether this person is a
good program or not, right?
So, you know, if the thing is, like, just, I don't know.
I like, did, like, JavaScript programming, for websites, or something.
Maybe it's going to be hard for me to drill down to anything.
Interesting enough.
To really find out.
But, you know, most other things that probably, there are like,
certainly, a high performance Computing lab.
I could easily ask questions.
That would tell me how, well, you can think through these problems
has, what kind of experience, you've had, what you, you know, how you
applied yourself there, certainly that would have it and at a random
Java shop, you know, again it depends what you were working on, but
probably there are things in whatever that job was that I could you
know ask about to find out how you are at
and,
M, and learning that new things and flexibility and all that sort of
stuff, right?
Gimenez, great interview.
It's the only issue I've had with that is candidates, who have no
products.
They're proud enough to really talk about and I feel like I'm judging
them unfairly for not having the same interest for programming outside
of work or class.
Well, I don't think that should be the case though, because if they've
had enough experience to be applying for the job at all, like they
have to have written a lot of code.
Like, if you haven't written enough code, then that's just like,
you're not going to be a good programmer, right?
So you might as well send the interview there, right?
Having written.
Enough code that there's something in your past we can talk about is
kind of a requirement.
You don't have to be proud of it, you just have to have done it,
right?
So there has to be something there.
And if there isn't then that's just probably a no higher because you
kind of need like there are no good programmers who haven't done a ton
of programming.
So, you know, even entry level people, I would expect them to have
done a lot of programming and that's cool.
It doesn't have to be outside of their assignments, but they had to
have done all their assignments at least, right?
And you know, wherever they were working, they had to be doing stuff
at work, right?
So
What are some things that can cause a smart individual who has a good
understanding of programming, not to be productive and what can be
done to eliminate these causes?
I don't know, I have no idea.
you know, I pretty much always program for 4 hours a day, every day at
a minimum,
like, even my slowest, you know, it's real rare for me to go a day
without four hours of programming in it, right?
I'm talking about a work day and, you know, most good programmers.
I know.
Have something like that.
And I don't know why they they are that way, right?
I definitely know programmers, who I'd say.
These people are very smart, they're not necessarily good programmers
because they just don't get it done.
Right?
And and writing code is not the only thing you'd be doing, right?
Like, for example, Fabien has famously said that, you know, sometimes
he like work stuff out in notebooks and just reads things for, you
know, several days at a time and then just writes the code and it's
done and it's great or whatever, right.
So, it's not necessarily typing in code, but it's doing actual
productive work for, you know, for hours a day I think is kind of what
you would expect a program doing.
And there's some people who just don't do that.
And I don't know why.
I just, I just have no idea why.
I don't know if it's like brain chemistry, or if it's like, bad habits
or something, but not being a manager.
I don't really have to worry about that.
At Molly, we pretty much only hire people who, you know, are going to
do, basically the same thing for art, we do exactly the same.
It's like, we want people who we know, are working no less than four
hours a day, you know, at a bare minimum because we know that if
everyone's doing at least that much work, every day you get a fair bit
of work, done every week, right?
Whereas people who just talk all the time or you know, surf the web or
whatever else you just, that's just not useful.
You know, it's not work.
It's that's like playing around or whatever.
Rome 0, 0, 0, 1 0 0, 1 1.
But people do come with big claims on their resume.
You got to at least ask about Pointer math, if you're hiring a see
expert.
No, I mean, this is, the point is drill down questions, get to all
that stuff, right?
Like you you would be shocked how fast you can figure out that someone
has no idea what they're talking about when you drill down on
something in their resume, right?
Like it comes across out quickly, you know what I mean?
and so, it's like,
It's really not.
You don't have to ask reverse a linked list, kind of questions.
It's really obvious when you drill down into something that they can't
can or can't do this stuff because, you know, when I say drill down
you go all the way down to, like the code eventually, you will be
coding on a whiteboard.
When you do that style interview, right?
You're like, okay, like the LZ question, like, how your coding this
thing?
All right, so how did you, you know, what was the cash, you know,
Of that thing or whatever.
You know, you get all the way down to those things and it's really
obvious.
If somebody doesn't know, you know what a pointer is or something.
By the time, you're dealing down at those at the specifics, you know?
Chochmah who wouldn't know how to reverse a linked list.
You can do that on the spot.
Well again like two things about that one is I don't know.
Who knows why you couldn't reverse a linked list on the spot.
Maybe you're flustered or confused or something, right?
Like maybe you're bad at taking interviews, who cares, right?
Reversing a linked list is something you.
Almost never do that.
I can't even think of the last time I ever made code to reverse a
linked list.
It's like
I mean, of all the things that I type in many times and programming
reversing a linked list.
I've maybe done once if even that it's just really, it doesn't make
any sense.
Like why would that be the kind of thing you would ask when it's just
not relevant to programming most of the time and the only thing you're
going to learn from it is whether this person is not flustered that's
by, by having a thing thrown at them.
That they either have never done before, or if they've done it, it's
only because it was
Toy problem Bay chose to work on, right?
It just doesn't make any sense.
It's it's either zero information or wrong information is the only two
things are going to learn from that question.
So drill down on something that matters.
What has the person done get them to recreate.
Some of that code that they've already done on the Whiteboard for you.
That is way more useful and way more telling about the person and
their qualities as a programmer than throwing an interview.
Question, at them that they
Probably have never seen before unless they practiced for it.
On stupid questions, like reverse a linked list.
I mean, that's just
When was the last time you wrote code to reverse a linked list?
Like why did you do it?
What were you doing?
What code were you writing to reverse a linked list?
I mean, why did you build the linked list in reverse order in the
first place?
Like seems inefficient to me, maybe I should ask you, why you're
asking me to reverse a linked list does?
Like if an interviewer asked me to reverse a linked list, maybe I
would tell them.
Hey,
Why did you build the list backwards now?
You're touching all of those potentially unrelated cache lines?
That sounds like a horrible idea.
Often I have a hard time digging into people's past projects because
they throw out tons of acronyms jargon Frameworks etcetera that I'm
not familiar with maybe they've worked in a completely different
industry like medical or defense and their work context is totally
unfamiliar to me.
How do you handle that?
So the way that I handle that is make them, teach you that
Perfect.
If you go like, oh yeah.
Like so it says, here on your resume that you made like a mailing list
subscription thing like how, you know, tell me about that.
What's the deal with that?
Is like, oh yeah, for our website, we need to thing where you could
type in the mailing list and address it was described as like, okay.
So how did you implement, you know, the thing that stores the mailing
list, like, what was that and then they're like, oh, that was, you
know, Pro sequel.
I'm making up something that well, actually, that probably exists, but
let's say that.
Pro sequel doesn't exist for the sake of the argument.
Oh yeah, we use like a pro sequel.
Back end or something like that.
And be like oh what's Pro Sequel?
And the like oh it's you know, database variant by such and such a
company or there's like, okay, so how tell me about the deployment of
that system?
Like what does that system look like like.
Okay, tell me about the queries for that system.
How did the queries where it's like, you know, blah, blah blah blah.
Like make them go all the way down to like the actual code they wrote.
And if you don't know, the acronyms so much, the better force them to
Explain all the way down to the actual code.
One thing that they did, and if you don't know the acronyms, it
doesn't matter because that's even better.
That means they're going to have to explain all of that to you and if
they can't explain to you what they did, they obviously don't
understand it very well, right?
Like being able to explain what you programmed is a core job function
because if you're going to work with anyone else, you need to be able
to explain to them what's going on.
So if they can't tell you what it is, they did, that's a great.
You know, situation.
John McGrath I like this interview methodology maybe in a chat stream
one day you could mock interview someone as a demonstration.
Yeah I was just having that thought.
In fact I was going to say is anyone on stream right now that I can
just like conference in and I'll just interview them the way that I
think you're supposed to do this interview so that you can see
and you can't call this the case in your ettore enhanced interview
techniques because Chris Hacker is the person who invented it.
As far as I know.
I mean I maybe he got it from somewhere but I don't think he did.
I think he just came up with it because he was at Microsoft and he did
a bunch of interviewing and Microsoft was kind of the pioneer as far
as I know of the stupid interview question technique and Chris like
specifically did not think that was a good idea much to his credit and
came up with this as an alternate way to interview people and
It's very good.
All right, Sean.
Yeah.
I'll definitely I'd totally do the interview.
That sounds great.
Some other time, we'll do it.
and you can, you can stream
You can stream from your computer, your with the Whiteboard on, so
that when you comes time to actually scratch things out that I'm
asking, you can draw them on there.
Super jerk on this is actually already how I do interviews.
The problem is people tend to be totally blindsided by being asked
about their own experience yet.
One of the problems now is like people buy these books like how to
prepare for an interview and of course they're all to prepare you for
these look really crappy Google style, interview processes and so
they're all like practicing these stupid questions like that.
You know, is not at all.
Like if you actually end up getting a good interviewer viewer the can
It is now totally surprised because they're like, Oh I thought you
were going to ask me a dumb brain teaser question or something, right?
So you know like unfortunately one problem is that people aren't
coming prepared for a good interview.
They're coming prepared for a bad interview which yeah, it does make
it a little harder, but I still think it's like, hey, you know, if you
can't talk about your past experience after five or six minutes of
just like getting more comfortable with me, I mean that's going to be
a problem, right?
And that's another thing that I would point out is true about this
interview process is it's impervious to hacking, right?
Like one of the problems with with
The the random brain teaser question problem is that there's only so
many of those that people tend to give out and now they just got books
with a minute.
And so now people can just practice and maybe the only thing they know
about programming is how to answer that question, right?
But if you do the drill down method then the person has no idea what
where you're going to go with that drill down, right?
Because typically what you do and this is like sort of the the again
the Chris Hacker style.
Is he generally does the sort of Venn diagram approach to it, where he
takes something as the drill down proceeds, he finally gets to some
part in the drill down where he has a kind of area he wants.
Explore.
That's right nearby and he makes the candidate go there, right?
So it kind of like builds off of the candidates comfort and just out
into a little bit enough knew that the candidate has to kind of do a
little inventing.
And since there's no way to really know what that's going to be, you
can't really practice for it, right?
You know, the only thing you can really do to practice for it is to be
a good program.
And know what you did.
It's like be comfortable with the things that you've done and be
prepared to provide Insight in those areas to somebody, which is
exactly what you actually is.
Exactly the experience, we are hiring you for, right?
So it's the only way you could hack it is by being better.
At the actual thing, we actually wanted you to be right?
Because nobody expects you to come to a job with experience.
You didn't say you had right and nobody expects you to
Come to a job, being able to solve random brain teasers.
So, you know, the the other things, that the things that are
encouraged by the other interview process are basic.
Just burning the candidates time on stuff.
We don't actually care if you can do when you actually show up here to
work if we hire you.
Whereas anything you might do that would get you better at
interviewing on Chris's process is actually just making you a better
programmer and making you more experienced at the things that you
actually claimed.
You were on your resume.
Which is all win-win for the most part.
So,
All right.
Now I really got to go.
It's almost 7:00.
Okay, and I got to reboot the machine.
So I'm going to close this stuff down and we're going to reboot so I
can get, I can get some better.
It's like the Wacom tablet back online.
All right.
Thank you, everyone for joining me.
For those sort of handmade he rots in a pleasure coding with you.
As always, if you would like to follow along at home, you can always
pre-order the game on handmade hero dot-org.
It comes to the source code, so you can do your own experiments with
it and learn from it.
We also have forms that you can go to ask questions, we have a patreon
page and go to if you want support the video series, there's a
schedule bot that tweets the schedule at you and episode guide you can
use to catch up on old episodes and of course a little button that
tells you the next time we're going to be live.
If you refresh the page it'll just
Get down to the next showing.
That is about it for today.
I will be back here tomorrow for the last dream of the week.
Until then have fun programming everyone.
And I will see you guys on the internet.
Take it easy.