Hello everyone and welcome to handmade here on the show.
We could have complete game live on stream.
We are in the middle here of doing a conversion of our opengl fixed
function pipeline code, to sort of the more modern core opengl
pipeline.
Now that we have everything working and last week we have started last
week yesterday, we stopped right at the point where we had sort of
moved over to
We sort of began the move over to more of a streaming triangle system
from something that was more logical based.
And today we're just going to try and finish up that move or at least
the first part of that move, which is what we, what will put us in a
good position to do sort of a cleaner and more modern opengl pipeline.
So that's all we're doing right now.
If you followed yesterday then you kind of know what we're doing
because we stopped at a point where we're like all right here's you
know the this working with just one batch and now we're going to try
to make it so that it's sort of buffers up a large number of triangles
rather than just one set of single set of a single quad per batch.
So that's all we're really doing here.
So let's go ahead and dive in today is a 371.
So if you want to follow along at home, you want start with a 370
source code.
Let's go ahead and
Ben.
The project.
All right.
alrighty, so
if I go ahead and
Right?
You can see that we've got everything working relatively correctly
here.
However, as you know, each of these sort of Sprites that you see on
the screen is drawn with a separate in our render, is it putting a
separate entry in for each one of those but the whole point of what we
did yesterday was to make it so that we no longer have to do that, at
least on the submission side.
So what we did is we added this thing here called render entry text
Quads.
Those textured quads is just a number which says, how many quads are
going to be and then an offset into a giant buffer, fill of vertices,
where the vertices for the quads get pushed along side, that is a
parallel array of bitmap pointers.
Each bitmap pointer corresponds to one of the quads.
So for every quad, we can say, here's the bitmap that we want to draw
with that quad.
Right?
So that's all we want to do here.
And if we bounce back over to the opengl code, we can see that.
Actually, we're all ready.
We're ready to support that quad cab, you know, quad count being
anything.
It wants to be it Loops over the quad count and just draws whatever it
finds there.
It's still submitting it fire, the opengl fixed function pipeline.
So like I said, well,
Quite a mean it's switching to its own program but the vertex
submission is via the opengl fixed function pipeline.
What we want to do is switch this over to be a more modern version,
that doesn't use the fixed function pipeline, which we, or at least
I should say we don't want to use immediate mode submission so that
will be a little bit more modern immediate but its mission is kind of
old at this point.
So in order to get to that point though, what I want to do first is
just make it so that rather than sending these down one at a time and
because all of our entries right now have a quad count of one and you
know so it's just 1 1 quad /.
What I want to do is get to the point where we're sending down a large
batch of them at the same time, right?
So many many, many quads like I said,
We'll still have a problem with the bitmap part of things and we'll
talk about that a little bit later.
But for right now we're just trying to get all of our vertices in into
a more sane submission way.
My nose is very runny, so you're going to hear a lot of NOS blowing on
today's show you.
It's not gonna be pretty.
I'm not sick, it's just allergy season.
The weather is getting warmer and it's always a always rough when the
weather gets warmer in Seattle, right?
So here we go.
What we want to do is essentially take all of these calls inside, our
are handmade render group.
And right now, what we're doing is, every time we push a bitmap on,
you can see this, this is the call for pushing it back up here.
Every time we push a bitmap on, you can see us doing this
Process where we actually create a new entry render entry, textured
quads every time.
Right?
And so, what we want to do instead is just if we already have a render
entry textured quads lying around, then we will just add to it right?
That's all we really want to do.
So what we want to do here is basically say something like, okay,
inside the render group itself.
F.
What I want to do is say at the end and you can see I stuck it here at
the end of the thing.
I'm just going to have a notion of the last render entry textured
quads.
We pushed on there and every time we get a new one,
What I want to do is just append it, right?
I just want to append that that the new data to the old textured quad
struct, okay?
So what I want to do when we come in here to push bitmap is say,
alright, there's an entry for this thing right?
And the entry is going to be the red, the current quads, oops.
Right to the answer is going to be the current quads for you.
Whatever this, this render group is.
And, as I go with this current quads here, I will basically, I'll know
when I, when I look at it, if it's not there, right?
If, if it was set to zero so current quads doesn't currently have
anything in it, then I'll push a new one.
Right?
And I'm not going to use this plus size of loaded bitmap here.
We'll see why in a second.
So I'm just going to push the new render entry textured quads struct
on.
If I don't have one right, that's what I'm going to do here and then
assuming that I got it.
Now if there's an error case and we ran on the memory, then this will
fail this.
If will fail, but assuming that I got it, then also what I'll do is
I'm going to save it, right?
So in some sense, I could also do it this way I suppose.
This might be a little better.
Right.
So basically if that, you know, if that member isn't set to something,
let's fill it in.
Okay?
Then we grab it out and we go from there.
And then for that point, the only way this would be 0 is if we ran out
of memory for our stuff, right?
Okay, so the other thing we can do here is move our assertion up to
make this more robust as well.
We could say.
Alright, the other thing we need to probably know
Is that however, many vertices we have so far that if we were to push
four of them on, we would not exceed our maximum vertex count, right?
So we'll also clip that off there and then there's one other thing.
We're going to have to check and you'll see what that is in a second.
So once we push this on, you can see that we could just go from here
because the vertex array stream is is all fine and dandy, but we end
up in a another sort of problem where we've got these loaded bitmaps.
And the loaded bitmaps are in the same sort of
They have the same situation as the vertices, right.
We're sort of pushing them on one at a time.
We need a place for them to go and so it seems like probably what we
want to do here and it's hard to say but it seems like probably what
we want to do here is just have that be also part of the stream, we
could put it as part of the the the memory that we're using to as the
push buffer.
In this case.
But I'm not sure there's any real point to doing it that because we
know that we've got to fix vertex size buffer, we might as well have a
buffer of pointers as well, right?
And so I think what we want to do here is say, hey, just drive this
off of the vertex count, since we know the vertex count corresponds
one to one with the loaded bitmaps.
Let's just use that at least for now if that changes, then we can do
something different obviously but so
All we need to do here is say, alright, let's get rid of the bitmap
array concept and Winstead will say, is the commands.
Bitmaps or quad bitmaps.
I don't know, we'll call it.
I guess we'll call it quad boot camps.
So we have our quad bitmaps and we just want to set like we were
setting here.
We just want to use whatever the the vertex, count, basically divided
by 4, right?
So we're basically just shifting down by to the the value of this
thing and saying, whatever that, you know, whatever the vertex count
is, we know that we want one bitmap for every four vertices.
And so off we go, right?
And like I said, we can play around with that a little bit more.
If we get fancier later.
But for now,
That would be all we would need.
And so that will just work except for one slight problem, which we can
talk about in a second.
But what we do know is that if we want that to work, we will need in
our platform layer to supply.
Also the buffer of pointers here.
So if we come up in here and we wanted to put a loaded bitmap struct
in here, we would say this is quad bitmaps and that would have to be
initialized to the same size.
All right so moving on oops I forgot a pointer in there.
This is pointers to bitmaps not bitmaps themselves.
So in the platform layer,
That means that has to be.
Allocated as well.
So what we want to do here, probably is say.
We've got a block that's just a Max vertex count times, loaded bitmap
star, and then that's going to be loaded bitmap star star bitmap
array.
And inside our platform initializer, when we do render command struct
with that vertex array, there, we also want to put the bitmap Arabian.
And so, when we go ahead and specify that will just push it on here.
And now, the platform layer sends those buffers down and it's Off to
the Races.
Oops.
So now we should have exactly what we expect to have.
A fact I can if we want to have this happen every time where we just
say let's allocate one each time we go and and this should still work,
right?
Oh except for the fact that we forgot to have the reader do the same
thing.
So let's quickly just do that as well.
So on these, let's go ahead and get rid of this bitmap right here.
All right.
So since we have the vertex array offset in there, again the vertex
array offset divided by four is all we would need to know where to
load the bitmap from.
So in terms of the bitmap at all, we really want to do is just say, in
fact, bitmap at doesn't really need to.
Yeah.
So all we need to do here is say well, we're going to grab the the
quad bitmaps and we're going to offset by the vertex array offset.
But again, we just want to divide that by 4
So, we just want to say like, all right, you know, use the same offset
into a separate array, but just get one, every four instead of one
every time, right?
And so, that's all we need to do.
Furthermore we no longer need to do this offsetting here.
Because now, we're back to just adding the size that that the actual
struct is, we don't have to advance anything else, right?
And so here we are to where we were before and all we have to do.
To finish this transition.
Now is just make it so that when we're inside the render group, we
actually push this on in some kind of coherent way.
So if you take a look at what's happening here, if we have a current
quad structure, when we come through here, this quad count, right?
Is going to be something that could be, you know.
Already set, right?
It might be 0 in the case of if, this is the first one.
Oops.
So if this is the first time anyone's pushed went on, so if we hit
this path, then this would be 0.
But if we didn't hit this path then it wouldn't be right?
And same is true here where we're going to only set that vertex offset
the first time, right?
So those get set the first time and then every time thereafter when we
look at the quad count, what we're really doing is just incrementing
it, right?
We're saying okay we're going to add another trying, another quad two
triangles right on to the end.
And so as we go through here, you can see all the rest of this stuff,
should stay essentially the same except this bit right here where
we're looking at the vertex count.
Now has to be a little bit smarter, right?
It has to use the vertex array offset for the vertex count, and it
needs to add the quad count times for to that, right?
So, in here, we've got sort of the vertex count, which is a separate
thing now,
Well actually you know what?
No we don't why am I saying that this this will still increment
properly.
So actually all that's I guess just fine.
So I think this all just works as it is and this will append to the
current quads as it goes, right?
So now the only question becomes well, when do we have to stop using
current quads?
Right?
If the answer is any time, someone does a push, right?
Any time someone does a push that might affect what we are doing.
Then we need to because these things get retired in order, right?
Any time someone does a push.
That's not one of these quads technically if we want to preserve the
order then we have to it.
So for example if we put too much quads into a clearer than push bunt
squads we have to rescue the the clear in between those two if we want
to preserve the order that people sent them down and now the things
that we are setting again, most of these will go away so bitmap Cube.
Rectangle, all go away.
So the only thing is will be pushing our clip.
Rex blend targets and textured quads.
And so obviously, if we pushed say a new clip, rect we need to respect
that cliprect as we move forward.
And so, you know, change the transform change stuff like that.
Actually is important when we're pushing quads.
So, any time we do a push of that nature, we're going to have to clear
it out, right?
So what we need, here is something that essentially says all
right, every time you push a render and element,
We need to clear the current quads and I think that should be
sufficient for.
Now, we may have to be a little bit smarter about that later depending
on the sorts of stuff that we push at the end, but I think that is
sufficient and there you go.
So now, we are submitting everything.
As part of this sort of quad batches.
We can take a quick break point into the open gel layer to see how big
those quad batches end up being, which is kind of just something to be
aware of, for our own sort of Sanity check here.
So, let's take a look at how big the quad count is when we go through
a couple different cases here.
So not great.
And I'm assuming that part of the reason for this, let's see if this
is true, is do we push?
I don't know what we do.
Inside the entities.
Do we push a transform every time on the entities?
Yeah, we do.
Or do we?
I'm going to set a breakpoint inside push render on it might just
because we push cubes and other and entities interchangeably and we
move to cubes, it'll be fine.
But let me just double check here.
Because again, I want to make sure we don't have any funny business
going on there.
Alright, so here we are in push render elements, this is pushing a set
up, so we don't care about that one.
Here we are.
Drawing hip points that draws a rectangle rectangle rectangle.
Draw a bunch of rectangles.
Okay, there's a push with Map.
There's a push Cube.
So, you can see their kind of sandwich in there.
Why is this feeling so sluggish?
There we go.
You can actually see what's going on.
So a lot of these are push Cube calls.
So, maybe the best thing to do would just be to switch to a push to
the push Cube.
All right, so let's take a look at something here.
Let me just go ahead and and really quickly move the push cube in
there too, because there's no reason we can't do the push cube in
there as well.
Because right now,
We can't a great much because push Cube gets called a lot.
All right, so if we come up through here and take a look at render
group entry render type enter Cube, let's just grab that out and make
that work in the other way.
Now, we do a disabled of GL texture 2D here and so I'll replicate that
behavior temporarily just because we don't have any textures to slap
on here, but eventually, that would go away, right?
So in here, where we do the buying texture call, right?
What I'll do is I'll just do if bitmap.
Else.
And I don't know.
So here's a question, I'm not really sure what will happen if I bind
no texture.
Let me just see what happens.
If I don't bind a texture.
I'm curious.
If we draw white or, if it's all black
It's all black.
So I do have to disable what I could do is make a texture.
That's the untextured texture, which is probably the better thing to
do.
But like I said, temporarily, since this is not really a case that I
care about, I'm probably not going to bother
All right, so in here let's just go ahead and say that in this case.
We do a disabled.
Okay, so we do a disabled if we have 240 and then we come and
re-enable it again at the end.
Like so and that will allow us to just do the cubes way.
We are doing them now as well, just for debugging purposes, so when
someone does push a cube on again, all I'm going to do here is I'm
just going to grab the render entry Cube code exactly as it is.
And I'm pretty much just going to translate it into something that
pushes the vertices on as they are.
And rather than
Pushing just that description of the cube.
It'll just push the vertices on and off.
We will go.
And so the same we could do the exact same thing for the rectangles
to, but one thing at a time.
So let's get rid of rendering for cube here.
And in fact, I'll actually just get rid of render entry Cube at a like
in its entirety.
And now I just need to actually convert this stuff.
So instead of pushing render entry Cube instead, what we're going to
do here is I'm going to do the same thing that we did for getting the
rendering tree quads.
So what I want here is I want a little utility function that will just
do a section centrally this right here.
So this this code,
At will basically get the current quads out.
Like so and when you call me, just put that into it.
Yeah.
When I call this function, it'll check to make sure that we actually
have some, if we don't have some, it'll make some and then give it
back.
So then whenever we do this, I can just say, get current quads and
pass the group and then anyone who wants to do this, can just take a
look, right.
The other thing I can do is make this be more of a sort of automated
function here.
So what I can do is in here, check the if
To see whether or not the thing that's going to be put in there will
fit and if the thing that's going to put in there won't fit will
pretend that we didn't get one, right?
So, basically in here, will say, what's the, you know, number of quads
that you intend to push like so and then what we can do is say, well,
alright, if the current vertex X, the quad count.
Sorry, plus the quad count times 4 is going to be
Greater than or equal to I'm sorry or just greater than the max vertex
count.
Then.
To do to do to do.
Then we'd be in trouble.
I guess we could also just since we know that the, the amounts the
same, well, no, I guess that's all.
We need to check because we know that the other that the bitmap array
is also exactly in line.
So we could just say that four times the quad cap plus the max vertex
count.
That's that's really all we need to know, right?
So
when I call this, I know that this is only going to push one quad on
and
In fact, I guess we could also increment this.
And let's leave that in case the other person wants to do it, all
right.
So there's our quad count for push Cube.
We want to do the same thing, so I want to have a render entry
textured quads.
I want to get that entry.
I don't know why I just deleted that.
And so I'm going to do get current quads here.
And I'm going to pass the group.
And I'm also going to say how many I want to push.
Obviously, I need 14 quad for every face of the cube, which is going
to be six faces total for six squads.
And then, when I come through here, I need to now
You know place the stuff in that.
I need to record, right?
All right.
So looking at all this, most of this code can stay the same, right?
Most of this code, you can see here.
We've just got a Primo color on there.
Otherwise we just have bitmap p, height, and radius are actually all
directly stored.
So all of this stuff should work, instead of cube P.
We should just be able to use p.
And instead of like Cube Arrow, we can use that radius and height for
everything.
And then these peas, ER, 123.
Those all stay the same.
All these computations will all stay the same as well.
Everything here should be roughly.
Correct.
And then we don't need any of these sorts of things, but we do need to
record the bitmap texture handle in this case, right?
But it's just going to be bitmap for our purposes.
So we need to record this.
I'll do that one second.
And then we need to actually make these quads into vertex pushes right
now, what you can see here is we sort of have a notion in GL land that
it would be easier if we could just say, hey here's you know,
Here's a quad.
So what what I probably want to do is just say, you know, push quad
and have a way to push the quad on to the entry directly.
Right?
That seems pretty much like the way I would want to do this because
that way, I don't have to write code separately to push these every
time.
And similarly, the code for
Or the bitmap pushing could do basically the same thing, right?
There's no reason we can't just
Use this in both cases.
Now, in terms of the top color, but color thing, obviously at this
point, we want to turn these hoops.
We want to turn all these things into a 32-bit ones.
We could because we could pack these ahead of time.
I'm going to not do that at the moment.
I'm going to let that happen in here, but let's because we'll just
that's an optimization.
We probably don't need to think about too much at this point.
So here's push quad.
Compiler might even just do it for us.
So assuming we have a rendered render entry, textured quads
We're just going to go ahead and increment that quad count here.
And then I'm going to grab this stuff for.
We've got the quad bitmaps, you know, we got the bitmap here and and
all the output here we go.
so, I'm just going to go ahead and make this
Function, do the logical thing.
So, we need a bitmap
And we also need we're going to need to pass the game render commands
here.
I guess we'll pass the render group.
And in fact we could if we want to just get this out of the group as
well.
All right.
So when we pet, when we push the squad, we'd need the group.
We need the bitmap that corresponds to the squad.
We will push the quad on here.
I guess.
This is kind of a little more stain to do this way.
Probably, huh?
We'll push the the quad bitmaps will push that bitmap that we got
specified.
Will take a Vertex from the vertex array at the location.
We expect will add 4 to it so that we know that we've recorded four of
them and then in here, where we've got the vertex stuff, we just need
to basically allow these to be passed directly.
So we just have, you know, one for each of these like so,
Let's go ahead and clear these out.
And these are just numeric, right?
We're going to push one piece of data for every vertex here and we're
going to pass that data in.
So here's the P0.
Here's the UV 0.
Here's the C 0 and we just want four of those.
Right.
So that's what we need to do to do the push quad.
And so what we can do here is say oh, all right, if we're going to
A push quad.
We can just now wrap all this up as well.
So we can say, okay, we need to pass the render group.
We need to pass the bitmap, and then we need to pass each of these
things.
So there's the P.
There's the UV.
There's the color.
Oops.
And again this is just making it a little easier to push these on.
So the codes a little more concise and we're not repeating ourselves
over and over again.
Oops.
Clipped off a, why there accidentally?
There we go.
And so we've got our push Squad working in both places now and so this
these should basically both be the same.
Now, the only difference is we have one that is if you have pre-packed
colors, which is this one.
And so, all I want to do is is also have one if you don't have
pre-packed colors just to make it a little easier.
And so, all I'm going to do here is say, well, if you want one, that
doesn't that will pack the colors for you.
We can do that as well.
And all that's going to be is if we just do our GBA Pac 4 by 8, we're
just going to do that pack this call right here, basically the 255
times, the color value, right?
And again, that's just to make it a little easier for anyone.
Who wants to call it, who doesn't already have them that way?
Was, there's no sense in not just having utility for it.
So there's just another push quad, that will happen.
That will automatically do that.
Push that will do that conversion.
So, now, this code should be relatively correct.
The only thing we have to do is actually push the bitmap in here
because this code wasn't set up for that kind of work.
and instead of the entry,
this is a group.
Right.
So inserting that in here, we end up with that.
And I think that's basically it, right?
That we also have to come back up in here and say, well, we don't need
to me, we don't need to do this anymore.
Because that's already taken care of inside, the push quad call.
And now in theory, both of these are correct.
All right, so the we got to grab that commands array out here.
I also don't know.
Does this do that anymore?
No, it doesn't.
So this actually doesn't need the commands or anymore.
So that's strictly happening inside here.
And here?
All right, so the Primo color for the top tube is the top layer is
just this.
And so we've got that down and then push bottom of the okay, can't
cover it.
All the argument types.
What have we got?
V 4 V to V for?
I thought we had that one.
Do we not?
Render group little bit map, before V2, before before.
V2.
Before before V2.
V4,
That's this one.
These are v3's.
Well.
That certainly easier to rectify.
So, none of these need, is he bias on them?
So these can all be set to a z bias of zero.
And then I think that's all we need.
Yeah, so in theory are cubes, should now be going down and they almost
are, it's just I forgot we had the bitmap set, so they're still
getting a bitmap on them for now.
We want to set that off.
That should be.
Turning off the texturing.
Oh hmm.
All right, so that's actually not true.
Now that I think about it, this is one place where we can't lean on
the fixed function pipeline anymore.
It's going to force us to actually not do anymore.
So once we do use program, we're not going to be able to turn off
texturing.
I totally forgot about that as one of the things that's definitely
going to be the case.
so, once we do a used program here,
We won't be able to disable GL texture.
2D so pretty much
This, this to do is going to have to get handled immediately.
Because we always have to bind.
Something, the reason for that is once you switch to use program, the
parts of the fixed function pipeline, that would have affected, that
would have been about compiling the program.
No longer have effect.
So if you take a look down here,
What you can see is, we do this text sample equals texture texture,
sampler, fragmovie, call, I believe that we'll just always fetch from
the texture.
So we have to have some kind of texture bound to it the sampler
because the sampler will sample something.
Now we can bind just a straight white texture to it if we want to but
we have to find something.
And that's just going to be the way it is.
So yeah.
We will have to make a pure white texture or something like this for
now, it's okay.
We can just leave it like this.
I don't mind because we got to switch to having some something else in
there, anyway.
But as you can see, now all of our stuff is going through that
pipeline as as evidenced by the bug, we just had which is great,
right?
That's what we wanted it.
So now that more stuff is going through there.
Let's just, let's just get rid of the vestigial remains here.
Actually, you know what, let's do one more first.
Let's go ahead and put push wrecked in there and I guess that'll Force
us to do sort of the white texture thing that we were just talking
about.
So,
Trying to think about what the most efficient way is for us to to do
this.
What we'd really like to do is have had a sort of a pure white bitmap
that gets created as a texture that's sort of just sits around and
then still have a bitmap handle.
We can use to talk about that, right?
And so I'm not sure what the best way to do that would be, but it
probably looks a little bit like
Probably looks a little bit like okay.
Like that.
So if we just have a loaded bitmap pointer that's basically just like
the Pure White texture, we could do it like that, it might be better
to have the asset system do it.
I'm just not sure.
I have to go back and see exactly how we would do that because the
asset system
I don't know to what extent it really has support for doing something
like that.
Like, solid car bitmaps now we could add it.
I just don't know if it's worth adding it because I'm not sure if that
there's really much point to it.
When we do the load asset work directly stuff here you can see we have
a finalized bitmap call.
I mean really what we want is just for our asset pack to have a one of
these in there so you actually just ask for it.
And the other thing is I feel like if we put it through the asset
system it can get paged out, right?
I mean like technically so it's not really that kind of asset.
It's kind of something that just wants to be resident permanently and
so I kind of feel like it's something that wants a special path.
That's just how I feel.
That's my gut feeling about it, you know.
So, yeah, I don't know.
I think that should probably look this way.
Something like this.
and So then whenever we're doing something like, for example, if we
are doing the cubes
There we go.
So we have a thing here that's like get bitmap and we pass down the
ID.
I guess mostly what we want to do there is if that bitmap ID was like,
the, you know, that bitmap idea, we want it to be able to return that
white bitmap.
You take a look?
Yeah, I don't know.
It's a tough call.
I feel like it's that's the best way to do it.
Let's just take a look at what that would look like.
Inside the win32 side of things.
So if I'm in here and I've got this initialization code going on, at
this point, opengl has been initialized, right?
It's going on right here and we've gotten back in opengl RC.
So I think you know what I probably want here is just to say like okay
we've also got a loaded bitmap that's like white bitmap.
Right?
And when we're setting up that white bitmap, we need to say like okay,
that white bitmap is going to come from the opengl layer.
So it would be like
It has to come I guess from whichever layer.
It has to come from whichever layer is, the current is doing the
current rendering.
Now I guess that's not technically true because it can be both
It could actually just be a white bitmap that's actually in memory as
well.
but it just has to be one that corresponds to
Yeah, so I guess it's fine.
So what we would basically say is okay, you know, opengl
White bitmap or something like this and I guess we don't even need to
do that.
We could just do it when we do the render commands.
Like so.
And so then what we'd say is okay, inside of the opengl layer when we
initialize, we know that inside opengl.
We're going to have a jie Lun.
That's the white bit of a deep.
Well actually guess we'll just have a loaded bitmap.
It's the white bitmap like so.
And an initialization in here, what we do is we make one of those
textures for the white bitmap.
So inside we've got where's that opengl allocate texture like so
we would have that in here.
Oops and are loaded bitmap in this case would need a place to store.
It's pixel which can be right there.
And I think this would actually technically need to be aligned though
for the software.
Renderer, I don't know if we actually know, it doesn't because their
texture fetches, so that's not true.
So when we do an opengl allocate texture, in this case, we're just
going to do a one and a one.
And the data is going to be that white value.
The opengl white bitmap.
We now need in our
We now need to fill these out.
so, the white bitmap memory equals,
This.
The aligned percentage.
Let's just say it's centered.
Why not the with over height?
Is one because it's the same as Square.
The width.
Is one height is 1.
The pitch is 4.
And the texture handle.
I assume up Angelica texture will return this to us by, don't
remember?
That is true.
It looks like loaded bitmap isn't defined yet when we are here which
should not really be the case.
Where was that defined?
It's in a render group.
So I'm going to go ahead and move that to render.
Because it needs it should have those, right?
Why does it not have?
When is this actually included?
Because open, gel .h should have a bunch of that stuff.
Let me take a look here.
So we went through to your handmade
Surrendered on, aah.
Is.
Included.
It's not included before this I guess.
So it needs to be up here.
There we go.
I can't see but I'm sure I know what to do.
So I think that's mostly it now.
All we need to do is inside the platform layer.
We need to make sure that we're actually going to have a way to push
that on there.
So this is the white bitmap like so.
And now what we do is inside handmade render group it what we need to
do is make a version of push Cube that takes the the pointer directly.
So this is just a case of having a double call.
Like we have in the other case, where if your
The bitmap ID, it'll do the get bitmap for you.
And Paul called push Cube redundantly like so.
Or rather as a thunk.
With the actual bitmap.
So that way you can call either one and it allows you to pass the
white bitmap directly if that's what you're trying to so.
Similarly push bitmap in either case here again, we'll do the exact
same thing and I think that's all good.
There we are.
and,
Head is in the way.
There we go.
So, this should just work.
Now, if we want to start using that, I really have to update my
keyboard bindings to the same ones I was at work.
So don't keep trying to hit 62 indent.
So now all we have to do, if we want to change something to a white
bitmap is when we actually call, whatever that something is
for example, in this case, what we can do in this in now is if we want
to get the white bitmap, we can just say, you know what, use the white
bitmap
from the render group, and that should be a solid color and at least
in theory.
So,
Guess the only thing left, the reason that we don't see anything at
this point is we haven't actually initialize that to anything.
So the opengl white color, just needs to be basically all ones.
So it's just 225, 225 225 225 and then it should be a texture.
We can bind, that's just solid.
Whoo, my goodness, that's not what I expected at all.
I'm not sure how we manage that one does.
It think this texture is bigger than it actually is?
Or did we set the Border type to not be clamp or something?
That's fascinating.
You have to admit, that was pretty cool.
Now, one thing we probably will have to do is that white texture if
it's ever used is going to have to have some padding because our
software renderer, I think had some padding requirements as well, but
that sort of here.
So we've got clamp on the S&T,
I am really not sure.
What the deal is with that and there's no srgb involved here because
everything is 255.
So it's you know,
That is pretty fancy.
I don't know what to make of that.
so, it looks like
it looks like for whatever reason.
We're getting a lot of alpha in there, but I don't know why.
That's a Puzzler.
We have a white bitmap with a texture handle, be allocated from
opengl.
We're sending it down, just a basic White.
Pixel a single white pixel.
I'm pretty sure the submission format is just RGB, right?
Like
Here's like a texture.
We're going to get a texture.
We're going to buy in the texture.
We're going to send it down.
Its be gra, it's a width and height of one.
It's got a linear minification in magnification filter, but no mitt
maps have been specified so it wouldn't matter.
Anyway.
Presumably
And it's supposed to clamp at the border.
Let's see what happens when we step in there, I guess.
Maybe there's something weird going on.
That's not what I would assume.
That's definitely the value.
We would expect we generate a handle this handle to we're going to
send down the texture here.
Unsigned, B, with the one height of one.
Photo texture parameters.
Stop binding.
It put the handle back in and that's all there is.
ah,
Well well I can't say why that would be a problem in this case, that's
definitely a bug that I'll fix.
So since we're using this as something that sticks around now opengl
in it would have to basically be a destination based thing like so
Um wait no, it doesn't what am I talking about?
Open jail isn't?
That's the just the info structure.
Don't know why?
We're returning the info structure either?
When it's getting passed in here.
In fact, why are we doing that?
Let's get rid of that.
There we go.
That's a global.
So since that's a since open, jails are Global, that's that what I was
thinking would be a problem with definitely not a problem.
So that was just, that was just a I saw that return thing there and
it's like, oh, we're turning by value, but we're not actually doing
that.
So, this is should be fine.
So, I don't know what's going on there.
I'm curious.
Now, I wonder what happens if we just make this be something else,
just so I can see what's going on.
Do you have a set call?
So I just want to see what happens if I actually give this bitmap some
size.
I thought it might help me understand what open gels drawing.
Let's take a look here.
so, it looks like maybe
Let's, let's be a little bit more aggressive here with our test art.
So it looks like it is definitely using the color value, but it looks
like maybe it's the vertices of the cube that are broken.
And a not our texture.
Is I guess what I would say there?
So, let's see if that's true.
Let's go ahead over to render group and see what the problem is there.
so,
Is there some reason that the vertices of the cube would be broken
compared to see our bitmaps?
So we are using a different call.
We're using the RGB aipac 4x8 call.
Right.
where is the other one is doing the pack and then calling
Meaning, the push bitmap which is as far as we know, working properly
isn't using that path.
So but I don't think that should have much to do with it.
I mean, in this case, let's let's step in and find out I guess.
So here's our two colors.
We've got one that's sort of a got the green in it, and one that's got
nothing, right?
But they both have an alpha value of one.
So, you know, we would expect no Alpha here.
So, let's go ahead and step into push quad and see what we end up
with.
All right.
So, all of the alpha values for these colors are all full Alpha,
right?
So I would expect to see.
Let's see what the movies are, as well.
so I would have expected to see
No Alpha.
Right?
Because the alpha value is one, exactly?
Like I would have expected it to be.
So yeah, I'm still really not sure what I'm looking at there.
It seems like a Vertex problem, but at the same time, I'm not sure how
it could be a Vertex problem, if it doesn't look like that.
When we
Switch to a different texture, right?
So for example, if I go back to entity and switch it
Like so.
This doesn't look that way.
Right.
This texture looks correct.
So, it really does look like something texture related.
because only when we set it to the other texture,
are we having that problem?
That's a real Puzzler.
I don't think I have a good idea about what would be happening there.
I really don't.
We are using multi sample and we do have Alpha R.
Alpha 2 coverage on so that explains the banding because obviously the
coverage values make it so that because that cube is setting its Alpha
value.
The alpha is going into the coverage and the coverage.
Therefore is saying hey, you know, you've only got eight steps of
brightness here.
Right.
You can kind of see those 12345.
Kind of gets a little hazy in their six seven eight.
So you can kind of see that the alpha to coverage is doing that, but I
just really don't have any idea why I would be getting that pattern
when I should be sending down a full Alpha everywhere.
I don't know where the alpha how the alpha is getting set to
something.
Yeah, to something else.
So let's try a couple other things here just to provoke.
Sometimes you
To provoke when we allocate this texture, you know, normally when we
do allocate texture, we get the linear filtering if we were to turn
linear filtering off.
So just temporarily, I'm going to add a thing here that just does
nearest.
So no filtering, you're just going to take whatever sample you think
is closest.
So it's only the filter that's grabbing black somehow or at least
something with an alpha value of zero.
It's almost like it's disobeying, rgl clamp.
Call.
You know, I'm saying it's almost like a thinks there's a texture
border.
And it's fetching into the texture border.
I'm just curious.
So if rap smt,
Are set to GL clamp.
Let's just take a look at what those are now.
Maybe I need to set something slightly different joining us that clamp
to Edge instead.
Let's just try clamp to Edge.
I didn't think there was a difference between those two things.
I didn't even know there was such, as I thought clamp was clamped
Edge.
Maybe it's not as if I clamped Edge.
Huh.
so,
Is the difference between clamp to Edge and clamp?
Somebody tell me.
Obviously, I don't know the difference between these two things.
So for those of you who don't know, texture wrap is basically just the
way in which texture coordinates are processed if they're outside the
zero to one range.
So obviously as you would expect if you have something like GL repeat
on, you can go zero to one.
Then when you go from 1 to 2, it will repeat the range of 0 to 1.
So just like, repeat, it'll tie all the texture, right?
Clamp is supposed to just clamp it to the value that it gets to the
edge, but
Guess that's not exactly what it does.
I would like a list of these somewhere.
Let's take a look at the opengl.
Latest spec, and just see what it says in terms of GL clamp, because I
guess, obviously, I despite having used that for a long time, have
never understood what it actually means.
Can we search for geo clamp?
Oops, it probably would just be called, clamp, wouldn't it?
in the GL docks, they leave off the GL in the spec, they leave off the
G.
L prefixes.
So they're starting to talk about it here.
but I'm looking really more for a
So looks like just regular clamp is actually gone now.
So, I guess the answer is clamped has been removed, and maybe that's
why I don't know this.
So This document won't tell us what the original clamp was defined to
do opengl 2.0 spec.
All right.
Jill, normally clamps.
If the texture which are limited to exactly the range zero to one, one
touch recording is clamped his out of the texture.
Sampling filter straddles, the edge of texture image, taking half a
single values position and the other half from the texture border.
It is sometimes desirable to clamp a texture without requiring a
border and without using the constant border color, a new texture,
kind of ground, clamp to Edge, clamps texture coordinates at all meant
map levels, which is
Your filter never samples a border Texel, the color returned.
When clamping is derived only from deck to the edge of the cards.
So I guess clamp actually was sampling.
The texture border.
I didn't realize that at all.
All right.
You learn something new everyday.
Well, so that's fine.
That just means we were setting that value wrong for everything.
It just didn't matter because we always had an apron around the
textures.
Anyway,
So I guess that's all fine.
Yeah.
All right.
Well, there you go.
Okay, so let's see here.
I guess that's all.
We are now drawing what we expect to draw.
I think.
And so I think everything is going through there except for push wreck
now.
So let's go ahead and get pushed going through there so that we can
have everything going through that path.
And then we can talk about what the next steps are.
Now that we have that digression into learning the GL, clamp to Edge
is actually the proper thing to clamp.
Okay, we've also got so the store color there is now going through
srgb properly as well which means the entity for our push Cube.
Color.
when we call srgb linearize on this, that's turning one of our colors
into srgb,
And then we run srg being it.
so, the question there is
Are we properly preserving srgb through this path or not?
So when we do our push Cube here,
We do the store color.
This is this is not going to be nicer to be conversions.
So in the Shader in opengl, when we're working with these, and those
colors come in,
You can see in here, right?
If if the Shader, if srgb is not supported.
I guess it doesn't matter whether srgb is supported or not the colors
that we pass down, are no longer going to get srgb converted by opengl
anymore which is actually a good thing.
So what we want to do here is stop passing down srgb.
We don't want to pass anything down.
Srgb.
We want to pass everything down in light linear space, which I thought
we were actually doing, but let's verify that.
So when we pass down here, we pass down a color.
That color goes through unadulterated, right, not modified in any way
and so when we do the multiplication by it here again, none of that's
srgb.
If we have to when we actually go later to operate on that color, when
we write it out we have to simulate the srgb reverse conversion.
So that's what the square root is doing there.
But I think everything else should be fine.
We don't have to srgb convert the incoming colors frag color.
Like we do the texture because we're submitting it in srgb ahead of
time, right?
So I want to look at what store color does though.
So store color just does the pre multiplication that's the only thing
it does so that should be fine.
and,
Yeah.
So inside World mode.
When we do srgb, linearize for the push queue for the push Cube.
I want to take a look at what happens or srgb linearize.
that just squares everything so that takes it from srgb and puts it
into
That that takes srgb and puts it into linear space, which is what we
want to do.
However, I'm just
Thinking about that.
I feel like we're getting colors that are too bright, right?
This is what we're passing down for srgb, linearize, and if you look
at what we're getting here, that's just that's very bright by
comparison to what I would expect.
And if I, if I take a look at the values that are actually being
passed down, let me look at them in color, cop just to make sure
31 4932, right?
Let me see if that's the right color.
Well, now that does look like the right color, doesn't it?
I guess.
It just happens to be very bright.
Yeah.
All right.
I take it back.
So I guess we don't have any issues there, at least not that I can
perceive at the moment.
So, our srgb appears to be working roughly properly.
Again, srgb is in quotes because we're using squaring at this point
because we don't have real srgb conversion in on this card because it
can't do it.
At least during the right phase.
But we still got one more thing to do here.
So let's go ahead and do that thing.
Now that I've confirmed there wasn't a funny business going on there.
Let's remove bitmap and let's remove rectangle and so now we're just
down to texture quads and cliprect that means we're going to have to
get rid of push wrecked as well.
So push wrecked is going to have to conform to the same procedure that
everyone else is doing now.
Which is to say it's going to have to get the current quads render
entry stuff and
Who's that?
So in here, when we do this push render element, actually we're going
to do is get current quads, right?
And then when we do the get current quads, we're going to have to
adhere to do something that pushes on a rectangle, that conforms to
the specification that we were talking about before now.
In order to do that, I'm just going to jump over to opengl.
And when you use again, exactly the same process as before we knew we
were drawing a rectangle, right?
This was the code for drawing the rectangle.
It's going to come out.
Here it is.
So as you can see, all we were doing is just calling opengl rectangle
with those parameters.
So let's go ahead and go to opengl rectangle.
And grab that.
And that is what we are actually trying to do.
Right.
So we know we've got a couple different things here, we know we've got
the Min p and the max P.
So let's go ahead and make them in p and a Max p.
And those were first
What we call our entry p.
And then, our entry p+ are dim, right?
And you can see what those ended up being a peer.
So, the entropy was just the basis p.
And the gym was just the scale dim.
So really, what we need to do here is just say, alright will state the
basis p and then we'll do the Min P.
Plus the V4 scaled in.
Like so.
And I think that creates exactly what we wanted to create.
We have our pre multiplied color here again like before.
But really, we can just go ahead and say you through to color equals
rgba pack.
And get rid of all these cuz that's really all we needed, right?
So now when we come through here and we want to start recording
vertices,
we want to do these push quads again, and so we're going to pass the
group, The bitmap in this case,
It's just going to be since there's no textures on these rectangles,
it's just going to be that white bitmap.
And we've got the P0 u v 0, c 1 situation.
What we want to do here is just use exactly what we've got in this
case.
So this becomes V 2, I guess these didn't have to be v4s because I
guess we're not using them that way.
Right.
There we go.
So really we can just turn these into v4s again.
There's no Z bias in this case,
And again, we're just basically simulating.
We're basically doing exactly what the opengl pipeline was doing 4S
with a six function before, which is taking a series of calls and
turning them into just flat data that can be sent down to the card for
use, right?
So we're basically doing exactly that in preparation for doing exactly
that.
So then we just need to do this push quad which each of these.
And in this case we've since
Have a lower trying to Upper triangle.
That was getting used for the rectangles here.
We don't have to do that anymore so we can just go ahead and use our
final vertex as the final purchase the quad and just use for, right?
So okay, so off we go and now we just need to put the colors in there
as well.
So in addition to these at each step, we're going to have to send down
the color.
Now the color happens to be constant, so we're just passing the same
color each time.
So each of the vertices will have the same color
All right.
Oops, don't still want that in there.
So the menu, V-Max you V in this case, I guess also is kind of
irrelevant but we'll put one in there anyway.
Just in case, we someday want to have the
Have textures on it, I suppose.
Oh, and I got a reverse, the order of these, I was pushing them in the
opengl order, which is not what I wanted.
You need to be an hour order where position comes first.
Yeah.
All right.
And so now we still have the software renderer here which we are not
going to update right now, but we need to at least have it not cost us
compile errors.
So since we aren't,
Supporting this anymore.
Oh wait no.
Sorry.
This is the opengl render.
Yeah, we got to delete all this.
All right.
So now, everything is going through that path as you can hopefully
see.
And so that's all good, right?
And now, if I set a breakpoint in there, we should hopefully see more
aggregation than we were seeing before.
Because now most things are going to that path.
So hopefully most things should get be able to get pushed into like
they should be able to Clump together and so when we get one of these
entries we should see more quads in it then.
We're seeing before.
So let's take a look at the entry quad count each time through.
So here's a batch with 121 in it.
3,400, 181 3400.
So basically just drawing in two batches.
Now as you can see, and that's great right now.
Why is that great, like, why did I bother?
Why do I care about this?
Well, first of all, one thing that you'll notice there's a couple
reasons why this is an improvement and we'll go through them.
In order here.
So the first reason is we're sort of getting closer to a simpler
format for the render layer, right?
And that's pretty great because if you can force everything through
the same set of Primitives and make those Primitives, very simple.
It makes it a lot easier to optimize and make portable that render
back and layer, right?
So now if, you know, even when we go back to do the software, renderer
things are get a lot easier because it's got less things to worry
about, right?
It only asked to draw one type of primitive and that's a textured
quad, right?
And it all comes through in one batch and says, hey, here's the whole
set of textured quads for you to do just do
In order, right?
So, we simplify that back end by removing cases, write the number of
cases, get smaller and smaller and that's just better and better for
us, right?
So, you know, that's all fantastic.
Now, the other thing, that's the important part about it and the
reason why I want to do it now is because as we move away, from the
fixed function pipeline, which is what I wanted to do, wanted to move
us into, just basically the core profile, which is the more modern way
of using opengl.
Is we want to start talking in terms of batches of stuff.
We can hand over to the GPU without very much hand holding from us.
And previously, what happened with those GL vertex calls, right?
If you look at what's happening here, where we've got these things
like the old school way like this where it's 2x squared vertex.
X cord vertex x squared vertex.
These are calls into the driver every time and you know, if I go ahead
and set a breakpoint open jar
Which I don't.
I don't know if it gets called anymore, so we'll probably have to
force a call to it.
Let me just go ahead and force the call there.
Dude.
So, if I call opengl rectangle here, as you can see, I'm just going to
force the call to it.
It's a completely meaningless call, but that's fine.
So, here we are an open jar rectangle.
Take a look at what happens if I go into the disassembly here, right?
So what you can see is that this all we're doing here is outputting a
few vertices, right?
All we're doing is outputting six vertices.
When I come through here, I'm doing all the work to copy the vertices.
You can see, you know, I'm setting up the vertices here.
That's what I would want to do, right?
What I would want to do is just move this into some place where it's
going to get used.
But then I have to
Take the other step of calling into some completely other function in
the driver, right.
And you can see it's a double jump so it has a jump through an
indirection.
Here is the code.
It has to go through to do that.
It's got another call, right?
Here's another caller inside, okay.
I mean, there's just a tremendous amount of work.
Look at all this work that's going on here, right?
That was just for the color call.
Just this one call, right?
And so as you can imagine, that's just lumping this huge amount.
Optimizer can't do anything with this because the call has to occur,
right?
It can't this is a driver specific call.
That's happening here potentially, right?
You know, who knows what has to happen.
AMD versus Nvidia versus whatever we have no idea.
So the optimizer can't even reach in there.
And look at what that is or inline.
It, it can't really be inlined in any way because it doesn't even know
what the code is doing.
It has its never seen it at compile time.
So you end up in a really bad situation where there's a tremendous
amount of work being done per vertex on the CPU side for no reason
because fundamentally all we want to do is just hand it over to the
card, right?
and so what I've done now is I put us into a situation where we have a
much cleaner way of working with this, where, instead of that,
We pretty much have everything.
As you can see from here, we pretty much have everything in one big
array which if we wanted to.
Now, if we had some way of just telling the graphics card, hey
graphics card, take this whole array from us.
We would be all set, right?
And that's exactly what we can do, as we move away from the fixed
function pipeline.
So, instead of having to make this call every time where we go through
here each
I'm and say, okay, here's a Vertex here as a Vertex.
Here is a vertex here as a Vertex.
Here's a Vertex, here's a Vertex.
Here's a vertex and doing a tremendous amount of work, each time
calling into the driver three separate times for every vertex, right?
Because we have to set the color than the cord, then the vertex
location.
Instead of doing that, tremendous amount of work, we can now
drastically simplify that by just saying, here's all the vertices and
I'm just going to tell you what to do with those vertices in bulk
right now.
If we were fully bind lists, we could do this in bulk completely.
So if we wanted to use like Nvidia extensions, for example, we could
actually do one call that would draw everything.
We would
Basically say, I mean, I shouldn't say one call, it's three calls we
would say.
Here's a pointer that says all the textures to use that star bitmap
array.
Here's a pointer that says all the vertices to use and here's that's
the vertex array.
And then we just say draw quads, right?
Basically, it's what we would do, it's not quite grow cause would be
like draw, try strips of the restart, but that's a separate thing and
it would just go through and draw them all.
And that would be it.
Right?
So at the limit, if you're programming a heavily programmable hardware
and you're willing to use extensions or you're on like a console or
something and so you know that you just have all the capabilities of
the card at your fingertips.
You don't have to worry about like, Intel integrated Graphics parts,
are these sorts of things, which might not have the
You need, you can actually take all of the load off, and this is what
a CDO is approaching zero driver overhead.
The idea that you basically make almost no calls to the driver and you
just give it huge sets of data and then it just interprets the data so
that the driver and you don't have any need to communicate and there's
no overhead and translation.
It's basically just shoveling things to the card.
So once you put things in just some flat arrays that can be used off
you go.
Go.
Now we can't get that good and the reason that we can't get that good
is because we are still using rectangular bitmaps are not packed in
any particular way.
So we need to tell opengl for every quad.
What the bitmap is that it's supposed to use or in this case since
it's been sent out a textures which texture handle to use and using
setting, the texture handle is something that requires a call.
Again.
if you don't have an extension,
there and like I said, if you are willing to use specific extensions
for specific Hardware, that's not true anymore, because plenty of
Hardware does have the ability to switch textures / primitive
potentially based on input data because, yeah, because depending on
how the hardware setup, if that is a generic operation, meaning when
it goes to sample a texture, if it really just needs a location of the
texture information, you can just apply that as data other,
Cards.
Certainly older cards but also I think still modern until cards at
least up to a certain point.
I don't know about the very latest, they actually still required the
concept of texture units and those units being bound.
And so their Hardware actually still had the limitation that when it
was sampling for a texture.
It had to be a textured unit, not a texture address and at that point
it meant that every time you went through a new texture you had to do
that actual swap.
So to the best of my knowledge, there is no way to get around that
part yet everywhere.
It'd be really nice if it was because like I said, most high-end
Cards can just do this.
And so you're kind of in this very bad lowest, common denominator land
where the only reason you have these apis have all this ridiculous
stupid texture State associated with them is pretty much just because
we still have Legacy or less capable Hardware that we have to support.
Otherwise, we could have moved to something much better a long time
ago where texture data was just part of the regular data that fed down
and you didn't have this sort of overwhelming like state.
Eight sort of management that is associated with switching a texture.
Because, again, a lot of things like texture atlases and stuff like
that, you know, they don't necessarily need to be
Used in a lot of cases if it isn't for the fact that you just have to
worry about those texture State changes.
And so it forces people to do stuff in certain cases, that they really
wouldn't need to do because the hardware doesn't really care as much
as the API makes it seem like it does.
But the reason that the apis look that way is because of older or less
capable Hardware.
Not because the most fancy like modern and video part actually has
those
limitations because it probably doesn't, is I guess the way I would
say it.
But all that is neither here nor there because we still have to deal
with those cards when we ship on the PC.
So unfortunately, we're still in a situation where we will have to set
the texture a lot of times.
However just because we have to set the texture, a lot of times
doesn't mean that we have to live with the rest of the sort of
inefficient stuff that's going on.
So we can do some stuff now to sort of help move towards something.
That's that's not going to
This is not going to have to at least send down vertices piecemeal
because we've done the work of that.
And that is a nice simple change to make simple in theory.
Not so simple because the opengl API is absolutely disgusting.
When it comes to this sort of stuff.
Nobody really properly, ever updated.
It uses just the most heinous syntax which is going to just be you're
going to see.
It's just it's I mean it's just awful but once we actually get
Through the torture of the actual set of calls we have to do.
Hopefully, we don't get too many things along the way, where I don't
remember the exact magic Ridiculousness that we specify.
Hopefully, eventually we'll be able to
Get it working though because once it works, it's it's fine either
way, right?
So anyway, there's a, there's a bunch of stuff in here.
It's not client.
It's let's see.
It's not a real element.
Let's see.
Jill, draw a raise.
Let's, let's
Let's start here.
All right.
And like I said, it's just it's a question of me, remembering all of
these things.
So basically what happens is.
All right, so we have calls like this GL drawer raised.
For example, you can see what it, what it looks like, you give it a
mode and so you can see what the modes are here.
Points line stripline Loop lines adjacency blah, blah blah.
So you pass, basically what you're trying to draw in our case we want
to draw quads, but of course
We can't quite draw quads.
So we're going to try to draw a GL triangle strips and we'll use a
restart.
I'll kind of talk about what that is in a second, but that's putting
the cart a little bit before the horse in this case.
Okay, so you call this g l drawer.
He's right.
You've got the first
Says, hey, I'm guess there's some erase somewhere, right?
Which element did you want?
Start with?
And then we got count, which is like, okay.
You're drawing a raise.
What, you know, is the number that you want to do, right?
And so you can see here, this is the indexed version.
So, in this case, you
I believe there's this the in this version know, this might not be the
index version, so this might be the regular business on indexed so you
can see what happens.
Here is in the example code and this is exactly what we're going to
have to do.
Here's the deal drawer raised, it's going to draw a Vertex count here.
And what you can see is it first goes through a bunch of enable calls
and those enable calls.
Say, here are the
Here are the arrays that are going to be active at this point, right?
Then we say hey in those arrays, here are Pointers to where the data
is going to come from, right?
So it's basically saying, alright, in this array I'm telling you that
there's two packed floating Point values.
They're not normalized.
This is what that I believe usually means they here is the the pointer
to where they're at.
And here's
The base of it and we'll look at that call separately.
Then we do GL draw arrays and then we disable all those.
Right?
So it's sort of a case of saying hey here's all the the places to get
the data that I'm going to use.
Here's where they are in those arrays, do it, draw them, and then end,
right?
Okay, like I said, it's going to be real messy.
So here we go.
In jail vertex of trip pointer.
This is the call that we need to be able to specify where the stuff
is.
This is the pointer to the to the data.
And you can see, you need these indices in here to tell you sort of
where things are right?
And it's basically saying which array you're talking about because you
can have multiple Rays bound at any time, right?
So we're going to need these two calls.
We're gonna have to basically do what this says.
And then we've got yet another
Other thing that's a problem, because the other asset we have of this
is that this is what happens if you're using with the fixed function
pipeline.
But we also have the problem of we're using a Vertex Shader.
So in order to specify these things to the vertex Shader, we also need
a way of saying, hey, here's how you get the various values that the
vertex Shader is trying to read, right?
So if we come back in here, you can see we've got this sort of vertex
Shader here, and you'll notice we've got a bunch of output variables,
but we have no input variables, right?
And that's kind of messed up the reason for that is because we were
trying to use the fixed function pipeline.
So, we had this like GL vertex stuff going on here that is like a
built-in variable that was getting passed down to us.
Same is true of the techs coordinates
Don't want to do that anymore.
We want to convert away from the fixed function pipeline.
So, in addition, once we make that change, we're also going to need
two way of saying, how the vertex Shader binds name wise to the array
elements that were passing down, right?
So we got to do all of this crap.
Again, it's complete.
Busywork the API is absolutely horrid like it's just awful but that's
just the way it goes.
One of the things.
You have to remember out opengl one of the reasons has been around so
long.
Is they have a process for like a creating things together and moving
the thing forward?
They don't really have a process for stopping and going.
Wait, we've gone too far down this this road and it's all been
bootstrapped off of the old way.
The API was set up.
That doesn't make sense anymore.
We need to wipe the Slate clean and do a new thing.
That that makes more sense with how people are using it.
Now that doesn't really exist, they tried to do it once or twice in
its history.
It doesn't really work.
Super well, it's also designed by committee is rough when you get to
stuff like this.
It's a kind of thing where you end up just having just too many cooks
spoil the broth and that sort of stuff.
So, you know, you got to take it for what it is but it's an awful API
at this point for doing this sort of stuff.
There's just no two ways about it.
But hopefully you can appreciate why the API is the way it is.
And, you know, you can't really it's hard to have something that lasts
for this long.
Not get into a circumstance like this.
I guess one thing you might say is it's surprising it's not worse than
it is, right?
So if you look at what's Happening Here of the things we care about,
we don't care about normals because we're not sending down any normals
because we're not doing any directional lighting at this point.
So we don't need those.
So, really what we're looking at Kara's, we need to do enable vertex
of trib array and vertex, a trip pointer.
That's really all we need to do in this case.
So we need to set up these arrays and then we need to specify that
they're being used in a particular way, we don't really need to
disable them so much.
But we probably should just because we might want to mix other opengl
calls in here at some point I suppose.
So we're looking at something that's going to look a little bit like
this, but we need to do here is say, okay, let's, let's first start
with getting our vertex specification down.
Now, what you can see about vertex at your pointer and let's go ahead
and here and and see how this is.
So we're going to ignore index for now because we're not going to look
at that part of it.
So let's take a look at
The size, right?
So the size here, in this case is telling us how many elements were
specifying.
So in our case, when we're stressing text, chords were specifying to,
we're supposed to be
Colors were actually specifying four not three because we have an
alpha component and in position.
We're also specifying for because we have that extra Z bias component.
So it's not what opengl.
It's not what the people who are doing an example expecting which is
just 3D positions.
We've actually got three positions, plus one piece of information
So then we've got a type parameter here.
That says, what we're going to sending down, that's actually correct.
We are specifying floating-point texture coordinates unsigned B for
verdicts for colors and floats for vertex coordinates.
Then we've got normalized which is whether or not.
The things should be normalized from the values set that's in 2021
range obviously for floating-point values, that's not necessary, but
for these unsigned B, it is necessary because we basically want them
to take a value that's going to go from
55 and change it to one's going 0 to 1.
That's the normalization that it's referring to there.
So we want stuff that to true in that case stride.
In our case we have don't have separated vertex arrays.
We have one array of vertex data, right?
And so because we have one array of vertex data what that means is we
want to actually set this up so that all of our vertices are basically
moving as you would expect, right?
All of our arrays are pointing into the same array but they're moving
one full vertex at a time.
So what this means is sort of the the the distance that it has to go
is the size of our textured vertex primitive, right?
Hopefully that makes some sense.
So you can kind of see, all right, we're going to have these arrays
multiple arrays, supposedly of the data coming in, but really we just
have one array.
So we need all the arrays to pointing to the same place.
And every time they want to go to their next value, they're just going
to go Advanced by the size of a whole vertex.
Right?
And then similarly, when we come in here, we know that everything is
effectively pointing to the same location, right?
Everybody is going to be pointing into that commands vertex, array.
Right, so everyone is effectively.
Looking at it like this.
But each one of them is going to be offset by the address of whatever
the member is that they particularly care about, right?
So what we want to do here is basically say vertex base or something
like this.
And we want to take this and cast it to a you ate, so that we can do
offsets on it.
And then what we do is say vertex base plus, you know, offset from
offset of do we have, what do we got here platform?
see offset offset of
So, we want to do here is say, hey, we've got the textured vertex.
We want the offset of the one that corresponds to it.
So we want for our text chords, we want the offset of the UV inside it
and for the vertex base,
We want the offset of the color, sorry for the color array.
And for the position array.
We want the offset of the position, right?
And so just to underscore what's happening here, where is the pain?
There's the pain pain is in my hand.
so, basically, what we're going to do here is just say, okay, we've
got a Vertex array
And that vertex array is packed, right?
So we have position UV color position.
UV color position, UV color position, UV color.that that, right?
And opengl wants one array for each.
So we have one array, but it wants three.
So all we're doing is saying, okay.
Well if you want a position array, what we're going to do
Is point right here and we're going to tell you the stride is this
much is one whole vertex you want to you via Ray.
Okay, where we're going to point right here at the start of the UV.
So all from the beginning of our array by however much the UVS are and
again that same stride so it's going to skip over the other two
elements in the array, get to the next one and grab that, right?
And then finally, same thing color points to hear and skips over so
it's basically we're just setting up three array pointers to pointers
Point into the same array.
We're offsetting them slightly so that they point to the right
starting member as if they were array of just UVS or whatever.
But then we set the stride to be much larger than a UV would be.
So that every time it reads, 1uv, it will skip the interceding color
and position values, and get to the next actual UV value, right?
So now we've told opengl basically how to get these out.
And, you know, you could imagine a setting this stuff up like, so with
the vertex of him pointers and and all this other sorts of nonsense,
but
You can imagine we have some indices like this.
Our problem at this point is still that we don't know what these
indexes should actually be right.
And so in some sense I mean actually changes something that we can
talk about here.
There we go.
So that's a Glu in so position, array.
so I guess I'll say
P array UV ray and C array.
Yeah.
All right.
so,
it looks like we still use some a little bit here.
We do the budget, we still use an opengl rectangle call.
So until that's out of there, I guess.
Technically, what I'll have to do is move these down into the actual
batch call, which is fine again.
Like I said, it's it's called so infrequently.
Now, because there's only two of these per frame, that that's okay.
We can do as much set up as we want in there and it's really not an
issue.
Alright, so here we have all of our enable/disable stuff, we're going
to have to get some of those functions.
I don't think they were in opengl that early on.
He can see that they're going to have to be things that we get.
But we have some problems here, which is
What is the problem?
We still have a problem here which is, we really just don't know what
these values should be.
And so that's the primary thing that we're going to have to deal with
here.
Is this color?
Yeah.
And so the primary thing that we need to know now for the
documentation is where to get these.
Now one interesting thing about this is I suspect that if we want to
try to stick with the fixed function pipeline again and just stick
with it, as long as we can at each stage so we can only do the change
necessary to move one step closer.
We could try to find out what the values are for the original opengl
fixed function pipeline.
Arrays.
And so I don't actually know
I don't actually know if that how possible that is.
Well.
Yeah, I don't know.
Let's go ahead and just assume that we won't be able to do that hard
that it would take too long to do that and we'll do the will get oops.
I didn't mean that will go a long with
Well, we'll just skip that part of the fixed function pipeline
entirely and move forward and maybe it takes longer to debug as a
result.
But oh well.
Okay, so here we are with GL, get a trip location.
What is GL?
Get a triple location.
Well, gee L, get a trip location is the thing that I was talking about
before, that's when we're looking at the, this Shader code, what we
did before, right?
As we have these things called uniforms and we were saying, okay,
these things
Things called uniforms are the same for every invocation of the Shader
in a batch.
That's why they're called uniform, they don't vary.
And so when we're doing something like vertices and we're doing a
bunch of vertices in a batch then, obviously it's something like the
transfer Matrix that they're all using is going to be the same for
many vertices in a row.
Hence it's a uniform in order to set that we use the thing called GL,
get uniform location.
I think we passed the program and the name of the uniform and it goes
into the Shader.
And says, where is that name?
What's the off?
Of that name that I need to set the like writes Shader information for
it or whatever.
And that's what we used to talk about wear.
The uniform was right?
And you remember, we did that right here, you can see get uniform
location, get uniform location.
Right.
So now what we need to do is essentially do that same thing but for
inputs.
So instead of relying on opengl to give us the vertex position and the
vertex coordinate of the and the UV coordinates, right?
And the color, what we want to do is we want to specify those, right?
So we want to say that we're going to get a veck for.
That's the
Vert, you know, position or whatever.
We want to get a victim too.
That's the vert UV and we want to get a veck for that's the color.
Right?
So we want these as inputs to our Shader.
And then instead of using something like GL vertex, we're going to
just use like vert P.
So we're no longer asking the fixed function pipeline for anything.
We're going entirely our own programmable route, right?
So now, the fixed function pipeline is not referenced anywhere.
The only thing that we do is the GL position is being used here.
Because again, that is a part that remains fixed function, even in the
most modern graphics cards, you can possibly by rasterization is just
simply not programmable yet, so that is still fixed function, the
blend unit and rasterization are still fixed function.
And probably will remain.
So, for a while, I imagine maybe rasterization not but
Ending, you know is is rough.
Anyway, there's a bunch of reasons why blending is kind of special,
it's because of the multi-threaded synchronization necessary to make
it all work.
Fast is, it's a bit dicey to make it programmable anyway.
So
if we go ahead and say and I shouldn't say that program will
Make it.
Eventually, it probably could be more programmable but it would still
have to be very fixed function.
It would have to look like shaders where they're kind of like
interleaved and understand what that things aren't.
That doesn't matter.
Your honor anyway.
So what we want to do here is say let's take these attributes and get
their locations, just like we did with the texture, sampler ID, the
transfer Mighty that sort of stuff.
So what we want to do is say
PID.
A triplication hoping.
She'll basic see bias program.
Burpee.
and then so we know we have vert UV invert, see
Brick color in this case.
And once we get those, then we will be able to talk about those inputs
specifically in the vertex Shader and feed them, right?
And so then when we do our enable vertex at Rib array, that sort of
stuff, I think.
I can't remember.
Do we need to do the enable or not?
I don't remember whether we need to do the enable or not but I think
we do.
So I'm just going to I'm sorry this is like I said, it's just it's
very weird the way this opengl stuff works.
Oh well, you know what?
I can just assign them to the variables.
I've already got
Okay, and so now you can sort of see what's happening here.
What we're doing is we're saying, all right, we know that this Shader
is expecting a bunch of inputs.
We're going to get those inputs by asking the Shader compiler.
Essentially.
Where did you put them?
Like, how did you assign them right?
And then we're telling opengl, here's the pointers.
We want you to grab for those, right?
Okay, so now we just need to actually get these functions, right?
You can see well I guess I have to Define these as well.
But we just need these functions that were actually using here and
those functions have to exist.
We also will have to do one other thing, which is that.
If you take a look at what's going on here, we're still drawing using
the fixed function pipeline, which is not what we want to do again.
Instead of this
What we actually want to do here?
Is we want to do one of those deal dry erase calls.
And in order to do that again, we need.
So now that we specified our vertex base here, we need to basically
say, well.
Alright, what vertex would we be drawing?
And I guess this, I can also sort of put inside here.
That would be right there.
So, that is doing the vertices piece mail.
In this case, we just need to specify sort of an index.
In fact, I guess what I could do is turn this into.
Let's do this.
In fact, these could both be the same.
Let me do one more transform on this first.
Let's do an if one here.
And I'm going to F0 out these guys.
Because I want both these past to work.
So,
Go and run that.
Oh dear.
oh,
Right.
I can't run both pass because I changed the name in the Shader.
All right so yeah can't test that never mind I wanted to but can't
That's right.
We can just do it.
Blind.
all right, so
the other transformation I want to do at it.
Here was just say, alright?
So we're going to do quad index here.
And so in order to do this quite a next thing, what I actually wanted
to say was what if we just said, we know what the max vertex count is
or rather?
I should say, we know what the starting vertex is because it's the
vertex array offset, right?
So what I was thinking is we could just say, hey,
Hey, what if instead of quad index we just did vert index.
Here, we started at the vertex array offset because that is exactly
what that is.
And then we ended at the vertex array offset.
Plus 4 times the quad count.
Right?
Then we get rid of these two.
And in here where we want to get the bitmap, we just we're just
accident directly, right?
So, it's just whatever the vertex index is shifted down by two.
And this one is whatever the vertex index is.
So basically those two just come out directly and they don't have to
be fussed with at all.
Okay, so this stuff can now get put into this vert at.
Doesn't need to be updated.
So this stuff can now just go inside the the quads version.
It's in case we ever want to try to put that case back together and
then we now have the drawer raised version can be much simpler.
It can just say you know GL quads which again I don't know if we can
actually support properly.
I don't know if it'll support our quiet, it's so far.
It's been
Happy to do quads for us so I assume we can but I don't actually know
but then we've got the offset which is just going to be that vert
index and then I think the Primitive count is all we need.
Oh no.
Sorry is the actually the number of indices.
Did you do?
Yeah, so I'm pretty sure all we need to do here is then just say when
we do our GL draw risk, all we know we're just submitting one quad at
a time and so we just called yellow draw are raised for the GL quads,
right?
And I think that's basically it.
Now we just have to get those opengl calls.
And also I was a little overzealous there.
The bitmap still needs to be accessed regardless.
We are.
And now we just need to get the opengl calls that we need, for this,
which is enabled.
Disabled, actor, pointer and a trip location.
So I will go ahead and get the core ARB header out.
And B bump over to the win32 side of things.
Yeah, and I'll just put these guys in there.
So, let's see.
Get active uniform and of this, that's not what we want.
We want to Sable vertex that River, Ray, get a trip location.
And attrib pointer.
There it is.
All right.
So I do also think maybe based on how many of these we have.
I feel like I could have saved myself, probably a lot of time at the,
you know, at the very least by not using the complete.
by not using the, like,
Complete lower lower case of occasion, for lack of a better term.
right, because it's probably just easier to do something like
That just saves a lot of typing and similarly when you've got stuff
like this, you know, you can you could automate it a little bit more
so I might sort of switch over to that.
Breakers.
Let's say we did this.
Something like this and then we just have the name of it.
We know what the format of that would be it's just going to be Global
variable.
Type underscore the name and then the pointer.
Name like so that seems like a lot better, right?
so if we were to do something like this, then what we can do is just
say
Oh, Geo Global function.
I might as well have opened a little that?
And you could even go a little bit more ridiculous with this, right?
You could use a pound include.
You could use it include file that had these listed and do some macro
tricks to make it even fancier if you wanted to add I'm not inclined
to go that far but you know we could.
So if we have something like this right?
Then what we can do is
same thing can be true down here, so we could do a pound to find like
three to get opengl function name and when we've got one of these, we
would just say, like okay, the name equals type name
Get proc address string eyes name.
And off you go and so you can just do win32 open, get up and she'll
function and just put the names in.
So I probably should have done that to begin with I just always
thought like, oh, we're just doing a couple of these.
I won't think too hard about it, but, you know, eventually we ended up
deciding to use the full opengl pipeline stuff.
And so at that point, it becomes a bunch of typing.
If you don't actually take a second to save yourself, some of it.
So, you know, maybe we can convert those over at some point into it,
just to be a little bit more consistent.
Anyway, let's go ahead and start to bugging this.
Well, that's just lovely.
I think everyone can agree.
See that, that looks fantastic.
Amusingly it's sort of works, which that's not.
I usually expect.
When I do a change like that, more of like it's a black screen or
something, right?
But in this case, it's not.
So anyway, let's see what we've got here.
We probably just have a few mistakes in terms of how we're setting up
our specification.
So let's go ahead and take a look.
I'm going to flip this around so I can read the part.
I actually care about at the top instead of at the bottom.
There we go.
So we have our vertex index here and we're starting with index 0 and
we're going to whatever the, you know, four times the quad count
number of vertices.
Oh, that's supposed to be going up by 4's.
Hey look, that was a lot better than I thought.
We're not getting any texture coordinates or textures, but we're
getting close.
All right, so let's see what else we've got here.
Maybe our UV array is messed up or something like this.
We are pointing to the correct offset.
It looks like in this case.
We've got the UV rays to floats.
It's not normalized.
It's the right size so that all looks pretty good.
When we're binding the texture here,
Here, we're presuming.
Finding the right texture.
It's the vertex index shifted down by two, which I think is exactly
what we'd expect it to because that's where it would have to be.
I don't see any way that could not be right unless I'm missing
something.
So let me take a quick look to make sure we are enabling it to right.
Yeah let's make a quick check here.
We've got vert, you VI D is getting very VI D out of the basic.
Z bias program.
Let's see what's going on there.
That's the problem.
The ID was on the end, shouldn't have been.
Okay, so now we're in a good place here.
Now we're actually using pretty much none of the fixed function
pipeline along that path, which is nice and we're drawing everything
that we want to draw.
So now we're drawing using the GL arrays call, and that's a better
again, stepping stone to getting us completely off of the fixed
function pipeline.
So, if you take a look at what's happening.
Now, in here, again, the number of calls to opengl has been
drastically reduced,
Used, even though we're still not at the point where we're hands-free
or anything, it's much closer.
So you can see.
Now we make just a few calls here.
We make about nine calls, like one here.
Here, here, here, here, here.
And then here, here here, right?
So, make those nine calls to set things up, and we make three calls to
shut down.
I'm sorry for calls to shut down, which we could probably save some of
those we wanted to amortize.
But yeah, and then remember like our numbers in here whereas 121 and
then 3000.
So these calls
Are very minimal they hardly ever happened.
They only happened twice per frame so we don't even really care about
those.
So, all we care about is really inside this Loop.
And so we went from calling opengl
1 2 3 4 5 6 7 8 9 10 11 12, 13 14, 15 times per quod to calling it
twice for quad once with the texture and once for the instruction to
render one quad, right?
And so, what you can see, is we've gotten down to a really good place
for us by comparison.
But like I said, we would like to do much better than this, right?
Like what we would like to do is be able to just set those set in a
those two arrays, all the vertices and all because we know that
they're all quads.
All the vertices in that one buffer, all the texture for another we'd
like to just say go, but like I said, I don't think we can really do
that in this case.
And the reason for that is just because there's no way to use like
multiple bitmap pointers in a way that works across all cards.
But now that we've done that, we can also just sort of get rid of this
stuff here.
Tire.
This is no longer necessary.
And this becomes a pretty nice little function, right?
And like I said this, it would just be nice if we could get rid of
this Loop, but we can't really get rid of that Loop without a bunch of
without without using some kind of extended opengl.
All right, let's go for to a brief Q&A now.
Oops.
There we go.
Kim Jorgensen.
Would it be better to expose an opengl?
Get proc address method in the platform layer and do the lookups in
the handmade opengl layer.
So it depends on what you mean by better.
Unfortunately.
I guess what I would say is unfortunately the term better in this case
is depends on what you're aiming to do.
If you're trying to be more cross-platform than no, it's not better.
And the reason for that is some platforms already have a bunch of
these things built in and don't allow you to do a get proc address
call to get them.
Right.
And so on those platforms, it would all break.
I however you could use a macro and that might be okay because then
that macro would just just do it like at equal like this function
pointer equals itself kind of a thing.
So I would say, yeah, probably not exposing the get proc address call
but you could expose a macro and have that be included and then it
would probably be better because then the platform layers don't have
to duplicate it for ones that do have to do the get proc address, that
makes sense.
Val bus, we will use, I guess.
We'll, we use vertex buffer objects at index 0 for objects, in that
case.
Do you prefer using GL buffer data to send the data into the buffer or
using map before unmapped buffer to send the data?
So it the answer that question is, it depends at this point?
No, there's no point in US using vertex buffer, objects or index,
buffer objects.
First of all index, buffer objects we definitely don't need and would
never need as far as I know, because our vertex data is unique per
quod.
So we save Nothing by using index, a indices.
If we had shared vertex data ever then, an index tougher, makes a lot
of sense, obviously.
So index, buffers, not not something.
We need vertex buffers on the other hand would be something we needed.
If we weren't still having to make one call per quod, since we're at
the point right now, where we have to make one call per quad, which is
not good at all, right?
You do not want to do that.
Going to something like vertex, buffer objects in order to save some
additional performance time in terms of how things are specified down
to the card.
Just doesn't make a whole lot of sense because we're already too.
We're already way too slow.
Because of this stuff here, probably to care about something.
Like when the copy happens of the vertex data but
If we wanted to do a path at some point that actually took advantage
of by endless textures, for example, then absolutely vertex buffers
would be the way to go because we just put everything in the vertex
buffer.
And then have the drift dispatch call, go and we'd never have really
any driver stuff happening at all, which would be great.
To answer your question about Matt buffer unmapped buffer versus GL,
buffer data, the answer.
There is it depends entirely on your circumstance.
You need to test the two and find out which one's faster in some
circumstances map unmapped buffer should be faster because it can
avoid an additional copy in other cases map on Matt buffer will not be
as fast because the driver has to synchronize at that point to give
you memory that it can use.
And so it depends a lot on how you're doing it now, keep in mind that
there are new apis, in a zdo that allow you to map a buffer and leave
the buffer mapped,
And that is probably going to be the fastest thing eventually but the
extent to which drivers support it and it works well.
I don't know yet.
I do use it on our code at Molly rocket right now, but I haven't like
shift that platform layer out to anyone but myself, so I don't really
know if it's something you can trust on.
Robbie we use for a coder in full Window mode for Ed minus F in the
future.
I don't think I knew that there was a full Window mode.
But it sounds like something I would like.
Is this, you know what?
I'm on 4010 here though, is that something that got added?
Is there a command line reference?
I don't know.
There is I may have to
82, latest version of for coder.
Hold that thought.
Let's do that by moving, the construction of the vertex array to the
render group.
We kind of missed the opportunity of writing.
The quads directly into driver owned memory.
Is that statement correct?
If so?
Is that a problem?
No, that statement is not correct.
That is in fact, what you're getting out there is exactly why I
structured it.
The way that I did.
So what you'll notice here is, I was very careful when we did that
part of the code.
Platform layer to enable that kind of optimization if one, we're so
inclined.
I don't know that we will be so inclined.
But here, you can see the game render commands.
And as you can see, the textured vertex, array is a pointer in the
game render commands.
All we do in render group is right into this address, right?
So you can see that, you know, all we care about inside the render
actual code, that's in the platform Independence.
Side is that we have that pointer and we're writing into that pointer.
Okay?
That pointer comes from the the win32 side, right?
So in here we've got
This code at startup creates that buffer that's being used.
So, if we want to in the future, right directly into a hardware back
buffer, all we have to do is make this code right here.
Call opengl to get us the buffer, that's it.
all the rest of our render code is already set up, to do exactly what
you're talking about which is right directly in to the
coding question, right?
Kim Jorgensen couldn't opengl.
Get proc address.
Just return the method directly on some platforms using string look
up.
Yeah, it could.
But then now you haven't saved yourself, any typing right now, you
have to type in all of the strings somehow and all of their mappings
which is a function, which is exactly what you were trying to avoid,
right?
So, you know, the idea of the only reason to do what you're talking
about is to save yourself typing.
So you have to make sure you do it in a way that doesn't create the
typing summer.
Else.
And I think doing a macro does do that, right?
So you could just say that while okay, the platform layer before it
includes opengl dot, CPP has two pound Define, like, function.
Look up as a macro and then the opengl layer.
Just does that and maybe that macro just Returns the same name.
It's passed directly.
So basically just like function pointer equals function.
Or it.
Expands it to we're going to get proc address parentheses open, quote,
blah, blah blah, right?
So we could absolutely do that, but I think that's the way to do it
because if you did it any other way, I think you'd end up in a
situation where some platforms just have to duplicate all the typing
that you were trying to get rid of in the first place.
Justin Myer.
Why not build one massive vertex, buffer and just draw that once,
that's exactly what we are doing.
We just build one massive vertex buffer, but the problem is, we have
no way in without being specific, as far as I know, anyway, without
being specific to certain graphics cards, that we can actually
dispatch the entire drawn one call, the reason for that is every quad
has a different texture.
So we need to set a different texture per quod, right?
So what you can do, if you really
They care about this and like I said, we would have to first find that
we actually had performance concerns that we needed to address before
we would do this.
But what you can do this is where texture Atlas is or Texture arrays
are things like that come into play where you start to do things like
packing things into a single texture so that you don't have to change
textures.
Inside primitive dispatch.
And again the it's stupid because a lot of cards don't need that.
A lot of cards don't need you to specify vertices to specify textures
outside of the batch.
They can specify textures inside the batch because it's just a piece
of data that's used during the texture.
Look up, which can just as easily come in as all the rest of the data,
but because that's just not true on all Hardware.
You end up in these six are some cases where the programmer has to do
a lot of extra work to get that.
Such as packing things into an atlas or a texture array because
atlases and texture arrays are not different textures right there, one
texture with the way of indexing into them.
And one case is the UVS, in case of the atlas, and the other case is
an index in case of the texture array, which allow you to basically
essentially specify a different texture / primitive by using something
that the cards can do for indexing.
That all cards can do
Jesse Mayer.
I see!
Thanks any chance!
We can see a render call stack from Insight or render doc just to see
what the driver has to work through.
Don't know if we can actually.
Get that working on this card.
I need to replace the graphics card in this machine.
It's very old.
It's not what I want.
I don't know if we can because it probably just won't work but we can
try.
Let's see.
If it works awesome but I just don't know if it will because this
graphics card is really old and I just don't know it.
You know, if these sorts of things can be finicky, if it works, that's
going to be awesome.
But I just don't know because it's great for debugging to which we've
been fortunate.
We've been careful and we haven't run into anything.
That was really hard to debug but you know, how do I get to the
downloads?
There we go.
But you know, that's just because well and we're you know, we're not
doing anything really complicated in the shaders or anything, right?
So
All right, so I usually use Insight.
I pretty much never have used render dock at all, but let's see here.
if I open it up,
See, if it does anything.
Thinking about it.
Alright, let's see here executable path.
Is w and made.
Oh wait, w build.
32, handmade the working directory is handmade data.
We don't need a command-line arguments.
So let's see what happens if we tell it to go.
Only opengl 3.2 plus contacts are supported.
That might be a problem since we don't create one of those, but we
could.
So if we came in here and change it to an opengl 3.2 context,
Probably could.
So, let's try that.
So maybe this is working, don't know.
Not seeing a lot here.
So yeah, I don't know, just to conclude that it's probably not going
to happen or what.
Let's see.
Oh, you press F12 to capture?
Okay, because I've never used this before, so I only ever use n site.
Oh, crash my program.
Where did it crash the program?
Okay.
Not sure what's going on here, folks.
There we go.
So we crash inside render doc render, Doc is jumping to null, so it's
trying to call.
You can see we get pretty deep down here, drilling for oil and then we
hit the zero.
And so this, this sausage gentleman right here, dispatch 2000.
So I don't know what that implies exactly.
That could be because again if this card doesn't support certain calls
that it needs or something, but there you go.
so the answer is no I guess you can't you can't see a driver call
stack but
Yeah.
That's the other.
Does the debug you?
I still work is.
So how does one actually we haven't done that yet?
No, it basically.
It's pretty much we'll just work but we have to go do the orthographic
transforms stuff.
but after that, we it will work
Jimbo have you set a version Target for the pipeline?
Will you go full embedded systems bananas opengl es?
Well, no, we probably won't really support anything other than a Pat
from your typical game on.
But that would include, you know, opengl es on Android or something.
Probably.
All right, I got to close it down because I got to get going here.
It's getting late.
All right, I am pretty pleased with how that all worked out though.
I mean, we're basically running through shaders now and our own data
set set up the game looks good to me.
I think it really just now needs artwork to be dropped in there so
we're getting close next week.
I feel like I am going to be away for the weekend so don't do anything
next week but the week after that, when I come back we should be able
to sort of clean up the
The remaining stuff that we might want to clean up on in certain terms
of like, eliminating anything fixed function and probably we could
then switch over to just the core profile and have the core profile be
entirely all we use and then we're pretty fully modernized.
Like I said, the only step, I don't know that I'm going to take is
trying to texture Atlas our assets or anything and the reason for
That is just because I don't know I think it's some diminishing
returns there.
I don't know that we have the kind of performance profile that's going
to really care about the texture swaps.
We may just have to do one thing which is add one.
Other primitive type which is a bunch of things that are rendered with
the same texture and use use that for particles when we get particles
in there.
I think that might be all we really need to do so I think that's
probably the approach.
I will take, I won't try to go the Atlas Route, but we could also play
around a little with some Nvidia extensions.
And just for fun, do a version that does all the things in one draw
batch by using buying this textures because that would be just kind of
fun and it's eminently possible.
So yeah, that's about it.
I'm going to wrap it up now.
Thanks so much for joining me for another episode of handmade here.
It's been a pleasure coding with you.
As always, if you would like to follow along at home, you can always
pre-order the game on handmade here a.org.
It comes with a source code so you can play around with it.
There's also forms that you can go to if you'd like to support the
video series a patreon page, you can go to, I'm sorry, splits, those
forms that you go to, you want to ask questions a patreon page and
judgments fourth video series.
Schedule about you can use to know when we're going to be live and an
episode guide.
You can go to if you want to catch up on old episodes, that's about it
for this week.
I will be off next week.
I'm not going to be around, so I expect to not have a handmade hero
stream next weekend, but we'll be back the weekend after that to close
out.
Our opengl modernization pass because I think we've basically done all
the stuff I wanted to do and so we've kind of got a that stuff.
Nicely cleaned up, that's about it.
Thanks for joining me.
Have fun programming next weekend without me.
But I'll see you guys the weekend.
After take it easy everyone.