Start, there we go.
Okay.
Hello everyone and welcome to handmade hero day.
46.
This is, of course, the show where we code complete game from scratch
live on the internet's using nothing.
But our own little typing finger is no engines.
No.
Libraries basically as an educational process project and as sort of a
just a fun project, because there's something pretty fun about kind of
learning how absolutely everything works and being able to have
control over thing, you know, through the entire pipeline.
That's very satisfying and kind of all those things.
I think everyone should do at least once.
So anyway, without further Ado, we have we kind of left off on Friday,
implementing some Collision detection stuff and I want to get back to
that.
But before I do, I should point out that if you pre-ordered the source
code on handmade hero dot-org.
I'm sorry.
If you pre-ordered the game on him a hero, org, you have full access
to the source code.
So you should have got the link in your email in that link.
There will be a zip file and that zip file has Zips for every day.
So we're on day 46.
So you want to unzip day 45 source code from inside that zip file.
I'll so that you can be exactly where we are as we start coding right
now, because that'll put you exactly where I am.
If you want to follow along at home, which I highly recommend you do
because that's the best way to learn is kind of being able to follow
along and play around with things yourself and, you know, keep on
going after the show ends to kind of, see if you can play around with
stuff and make sure you really understand everything that we did.
So that's said, let's take a look at where we were so if you remember
correctly.
We were at the point where we were trying to fix basically are
sticking problem, which is that right there because we didn't really,
we didn't really have a really good Collision Loop and we need to
start working on that because we started to do our character motion
and it was getting a little bit of a better feel to it.
But we need to start working on that Collision problem.
So before we do that, we have to address something, which is actually
pretty hilarious that nobody noticed except for one person on the
forums, and I didn't even notice it because I actually
Thought I mean it was something that we were going to get to
eventually, but I didn't think we need to quite get to it yet because
I actually thought something was happening that was not happening.
So this will be pretty interesting and I'll show you, I'll give you
the full walk down here.
So if you remember correctly, we basically have a our little, our code
here, that processes controller input.
And basically, it does controller is analog, it would do some stuff.
And if it's not then it uses digital movement, right?
And I was under the impression that, oh, yeah, right.
We're only going to call this once rolling.
It.
This Branch once because as we Loop over all the controllers, there's
only one digital controller at the moment, right?
There's only one digital controller, which is the keyboard, right?
So I don't have to worry about the fact that this would happen
multiple times if you had multiple digital controllers in their blah,
blah, blah, but what actually happens at least or so sayeth, the
forums, and I believe them because I hadn't looked at it yet.
Whereas my, let's see.
Let's see.
Let's go to.
Handmade dot CPP.
There we go.
So I believe what actually happens is, that's not how they're actually
set at the moment.
So when we come in here, right, I'm going to set a breakpoint and take
a look at what happens in this Loop.
If we look at controller index, I'll go ahead and add controller index
to the watch window here.
Controller index.
Let's take a look at what happens.
So, we're on controller index 0.
We're going to go through here and do the player movement code, which
is what we want to have happen, because that's the keyboard.
And then
Unfortunately, we still have on the on the analog sticks.
They are not have not been set to controller is analog.
And so actually, we're going to do this player movement code, five
times.
Now, that would be fine.
If it wasn't for the fact that that basically means the player, the
the little guy will move five times.
This the distance he supposed to move and it will not be using the
controller input properly.
So really, we did not want to be doing this at all.
Like, that's totally bogus and not at all, right?
And somehow, we all missed it.
Myself included.
And like I said, that was just a pure on pure sort of oversight on my
part because I just assumed, oh, right?
We were setting, the is analog.
But now that I think about it, I believe what was actually happening
in our win32 layer is we only actually set is analog, once they
actually use that stick at all.
And if they don't ever use the stick, it'll just be default to be not
in log, which is totally fine.
It just means that this is not okay at all.
So at this point, we have to sort of think about what we
Actually want to do here and it's something that I didn't really want
to have to deal with quite yet.
But at the same time it's not really any there's no reason we can't
deal with it right now.
It just doesn't fit in our Collision detection, sort of stuff.
But so I kind of want to just think out loud a little bit about how we
want to handle this going forward.
Because here's the thing that we actually want to be able to do and to
some extent, we don't really know whether we actually will ever need
this in handmade hero, but we should think about it regardless of
whether we need it or not because it just it's it's it's something
that can be done as far as an abstract abstract thought experiment.
So basically there's some number of controllers attached to the
machine, right?
There's, you know, a keyboard there might be an Xbox controller or a
PlayStation controller or something like this that are attached to the
machine and even if there's only one player, you kind of have to think
about which of those controllers maps to that player, right?
One school of thought would be all of the controllers always map to
the player.
If it's only one player, right?
So, it's like, it doesn't matter what controller you pick up, you can
switch between the keyboard and the and the controller freely.
And
Just kind of always takes the input from whichever ones are doing
something and that's what it does.
Right?
And we can Implement that pretty easily and maybe that's something
that we should do but a wrench starts to get thrown into this if
Start saying what if we support two players on one machine like,
suppose, we want to be able to and we find that the game can support
having the main hero character.
Get joined by a second character.
For example, if you want to plug in a second controller and you both
play or one person plays on keyboard, when participating the
controller, then you actually have a problem.
And that problem is you don't know which controllers map to which
people
If there's two characters on the screen and there's three controllers,
the keyboard and to gamepads let's say which one maps to the hero and
which ones map to the sidekick right now with game pads themselves.
There's a little bit of a hint, we could make it so that you push
start on a Gamepad to join in on that Gamepad, right?
And that's a fairly common and easily understood thing to have happen.
And so, you know,
Could barely very transparently, sort of implement that in the game,
but there's still a catch and the catch is what happens with the
keyboard because the keyboard doesn't really have a predefined start
key.
And a player who is perhaps unfamiliar with convention or anything.
Like that doesn't necessarily know what to do when they're presented
with one of, you know, with a keyboard and said, you know, when you
want to start the game, what exactly do you hit?
And so, you kind of need to introduce.
If you want to go the start button route, you need to introduce some
concept of what is
The start button on a keyboard and it's not as simple as just saying.
Okay, maybe we, you know, have the keyboard, any any key you press on
the keyboard joins as a keyboard player because what if the person was
trying to, you know, get back to the main menu and they didn't
necessarily know what to hit and they just hit a key and now they're
playing and they just, you know, there's a bunch of things that could
go wrong there.
And so it's really a very touchy problem.
It's a problem that I kind of wish, you know, again people like
Microsoft, if they actually thought things through ever which they
pretty much don't
You know, they would have had some convention for setting up
controllers in Windows such that this was not something that each game
had to deal with in an ad hoc fashion.
And that players would have to learn separately for every game.
You just have a concept of what the controllers are in your system.
And which ones you wanted to use that you could remap per game if you
wanted to or all those are just up, really?
The operating system is the right place to do that, because it allows,
you know, players to configure things once for the most part and only
really mess with that configuration on a per game basis, if they
really need to for some specific.
Game, instead of having to do all of this configuration worker, all of
this learning in every single game they play.
But what are you going to do?
You know, we have not had a Good Shepherd of the operating system for
gaming, pretty much ever.
And so we're just in a position where we have to compensate for
ourselves.
And so, what I want to do is I want to have something in handmade hero
that is very easy, and transparent for people to use.
So they're not going to be very confused by how they have to do
things.
But I may also wish to support having
Four controllers.
so,
I would say what I think we should probably do for now is say, let's
assume that the way that the game works is that at any time, you can
push, whatever the start button is in your controller and will Define
where ourselves for the keyboard and you will join the game, right?
And I don't think that there really should be anything more
complicated than that at the moment.
So we'll just simply say that every controller.
That pushes a start button basically joins in and any controller that
pushes the start button again comes back out, right?
So it's basically just free to join free to leave and we'll see how
far that gets us because it's very very simple and easy to understand
and if we find that, we need to start introducing something more
complicated than we can do.
So later since we don't really know whether we're going to have two
players or not, it the final game whether the final
I'm will really support two different players the same time or not.
I don't want to overthink it too much now, but I want to do something
somewhat reasonable.
So what we need to do then is we need to move our controller code such
that.
When we process controllers.
We have an idea of which controller maps to which character, right?
And I just kind of said how I basically want that to happen.
I want to basically use the start button as the thing that determines
that feature.
So what I'm going to do is I'm going to pull this movement code out
entirely basically,
I'm going to put that in a separate place where we will execute it per
player basically, so I'm going to pull that up temporarily just to get
it out of the way.
While I do some surgery on this particular piece of the code.
So I'm just going to make a little holder here for it.
And I'm going to go ahead and say that basically everything, that
happens from this player speed stuff down.
Like all of this, basically is all going to be code.
That's in the player movement stuff now, right?
So, here's the player movement stuff.
It's gets out of the way and then, let's go ahead and take a look.
At what happens with these controller indexes.
So, for each controller when we go through and and do what we're going
to do with it.
We now essentially need to figure out
How we're going to map controllers to players.
And so what I want to do for that is I would like to go ahead and say,
OK, let's for now.
Let's just say, since we don't have the concept of entities, yet.
Let's at least say that we have.
Well, I'll just call it an entity for.
Now.
Let's say that we're going to take this, this player, stuff here, this
player P, and D player P.
Right?
Let's take those two and let's go ahead and say let's pull them out.
Out into this structure so that we can have multiple players if we
want to.
And we don't have to
Just have one, right?
Because this is all the state that we were using for the hero, right?
That was all, we actually needed.
So, if we want to, we could now have more of them, right?
So, if we wanted to have one per controller, we could certainly do
something like this, where we basically said, okay, there can be an
entity per controller.
And I guess I'll just call these players for.
Now.
We can have as many as we wanted there and I guess I need to actually
be able to check what that array count actually is.
Hold on a second.
Don't actually remember, what, what we call that a rake out there.
That's not it.
It's handmade platform at H.
So, where is that?
There it is, game, controller input.
So, what I want to do basically is just see what the
The bat is so I can basically say all right, I want to do the array
count of, you know, essentially one of these things like so I don't
know if this is kosher but I'm going to try it anyway, basically, say
the array count of one of those, whatever it is that is that legal.
Are you okay with that?
Oops?
Mister compiler.
See here.
that now,
And right, we will have to deal with this as well.
But it looks like it passed just fine.
So that's just fine.
So, we now know that we've got as many players as there are
controllers for now.
And so that's totally fine.
And then the other thing that I might do for now is I'll just say,
okay, let's go ahead and assume that we have some kind of a player
count here, so that we know when we've got any of them, right?
And so all I'm going to do is now all the stuff that we used to do for
individual players.
I will
Do that for each player that currently exists, right?
And so, this was the initialization for the player.
And so we want to do that initialization any time.
There's a new player, right?
So, instead of initializing, it just at startup, just for that first
player.
I'll go ahead and say, let's let's initialize.
Those will basically have a thing here, which will say, you know, add
player or something like this.
Seems like a totally reasonable thing.
So we'll do an ad player up here and what we'll do with that player.
ER is we'll just assert temporarily that that we've got.
You know what?
I don't even think that's.
I don't even know if I wanna do that.
I'm gonna do it actually this way.
And I'm just going to say that we've got the, the players here, and
then we've got however, many controllers.
There are actually.
I'm going to say that we have player index for controller like so and
we'll do that.
And I'm actually going to say that we've got sort of a generic entity
right here.
I'm going to I'm going to back off.
I want I said previously and I don't know how many of these were going
to have.
I'm not going to do anything specific there for now.
I'm just going to say we've got a bunch of them.
So what I would like to do then is say well we've got entities and the
entities themselves are going to basically have some kind of concept
of whether or not they are actually existing.
Maybe we'll call this exists, right at the moment and then I'm going
to say, all right, we've got we've got a notion that for any into get
individual player, any individual controller.
We have a player index that's sort of assigned to that controller, you
know, for the time being
And so if I go ahead and do that, I could then say whenever I do add
player basically what it would actually be is just an initialized
player and initialized player would say whichever entity index you
wanted to initialize.
So based, if I had an entity like this, then I'm just going to do
whatever that that code was.
That I was doing to initialize the single one that we had.
Right.
And instead of this being player P.
Obviously, this is now just p and this is just d p.
So that's basically the time that position and
The velocity right?
And so I'll go ahead and change that stuff here.
And of course, we may be reusing an entity at this point.
So what I'd also like to do is I'd also like to initialize it to zero
to clear out the entity structure, 20 anything that wasn't actually
there before and then I will set its exist.
True.
So now we've got an empty, whatever you want.
Initialize a player we can initialize it like so.
So again, not thinking too hard about this, just want to start to pull
it out a little bit.
Not
Doing anything particularly Fancy with the entities at all?
Right.
Now.
I just want to be able to have more than one of them.
So if I do that, then at the outset, of course, all of the entities
will not exist.
So that's fine.
When we go to actually draw them.
What is what?
What is?
Right?
Boyd, we go when we go to actually draw them here and I guess this old
player P is similarly going to be moved up to
Here we go.
Let's do that.
And this should also be moved as well because I might want to move
that other one to keep the think about where I want to process the
camera code basically, but what I'm doing here is just moving all the
code out that used to be best based on player movement.
Now that I know that I'm going to do it multiple times.
Okay.
So now, when I need to do is say, all right, we have a notion of the
camera.
Right.
And the camera has to follow the players around, but for our
particular game, we won't probably allow split screen or anything
because I don't really want to start shrinking the game world into
corners of the screen or stuff like this.
At least.
I don't think
maybe I do.
I've never seen a game do that this type of game.
Do that before.
I've never seen a zelda-like game have a split screen mode, but
Now that I think about it.
Is there really any reason not to do that?
That's something to think about.
All right, I you know, I mean I'm going to have to, I'm gonna put it
to do in there, how to put it to do in here and say, should we allow
split screen?
I don't know.
Maybe we should.
If this ends up being two player.
Maybe we should allow split screen.
That's a good question, two players.
Something.
I haven't thought at all about.
I'm thinking about this, mostly as a one player game for all the
design stuff I've done and but, you know, I like playing games with
friends.
So, you know, at some level, if it turns out to be interesting to have
more than one player, you know, maybe
Maybe that is something we should do.
I'm not sure.
I think it's maybe more interesting, if we don't because it keeps the
game play together and keeps people working together.
And that's usually a little more interesting, but I don't know.
Who knows.
So, what will say for now though is, we won't allow split screen and
so we need to do for camera.
P is Will basically say, all right.
We have a camera following entity index.
So basically just say the cameras going to follow whatever entity this
is set to, right.
And so if that is set to something that's not zero, right?
If that's basically, I'm going to say that if the camera flowing into
the index is not equal to 0.
Basically, so if it's valid, just based on what this is, then let's go
ahead and grab that entity.
Whatever that entity is.
Right.
Get entity.
And in fact, I guess I could do this a little more cleanly even.
So let's call camera following entity like that will say, let's get
entity.
And here's the entity that we want.
I'll pass it, the game state.
And then we'll say if that's actually a valid identity.
Then we will just use that entities P following tile the app Styles
eat, right.
And that seems pretty sane again, really nothing particularly
interesting going on here.
I'm literally just doing this most straightforward simple mechanical
work of pulling out some of this code.
Like I said that I like to do.
I like to wait till I've actually got some code and then I always pull
it out into things that are cleaner as
I sort of go further.
So when I do this, this allows me, why did I put this function here?
It just allows me to do range, checking or any other kind of checking
that I want to do.
I'd also like to reserve slot zero to basically means zero.
So, basically, what I will do here is say, if index is greater than
zero and index is less than game State, whatever the entity count is.
And so for now, that's just a ray count of a lot to think about what
we want to do with that little later on.
and,
Yeah, and so what I want to do here is say also probably well.
I don't really need to assert that.
So then we'll just do this and we'll say that if it's within that
those bounds, then the entity is just going to be equal to the
entities that
At that index in the array, right?
So that'll get the entity for us.
We now have a way to initialize the player as well.
And so now, what we can do is say, alright, let's go ahead and take
the stuff where we were going to.
Let's see what is going on here.
Okay, so that if the cameras following entity, then we also need to do
this stuff.
And all of this stuff that we do here, that used to be on the player.
P is actually going to be on the camera following entity, right?
So that's basically going to be this.
And, and yeah, that's really all we need to do.
And what that diff is that diff.
I don't know if that actually happens again.
Yes, it does.
So that's going to be used for drawing here.
So basically what we need to do is say if there is this will probably
have to do again because we were sort of reusing it here and that's
not going to work because we're going to actually have to have a loop
here where we draw all the entities like all of the heroes that are
Basically, right?
So if I go ahead and do that here, it's I've got to have to do the
difficuit so we might as well just put it there.
All right, so I believe the D.
The diff is a V2.
Is that right?
Now?
It's Tom app difference.
So let's go ahead and grab that.
Tom app difference.
What was Tom app difference?
Handmade tell .h, tilemap difference.
So tell map difference is basically just a vector, we can replace this
entire thing with a 3D Vector eventually.
So replace this.
This with a V3 once we get to B3 which by the way, is what I wanted to
do this week.
So hopefully we'll get there.
So anyway, all right, all well and good.
We'll take one of these tilemap differences for now, but eventually
will change those into V3.
It's because there's really no need for this class anymore.
So now we've done that.
And basically all I'm going to do here is I'm going to Loop over all
the entities that we are simulating for.
Now, again, dumbest way possible.
So, this is not supposed to be code that you're thinking about right
now.
If you are thinking,
About this.
That is bad.
You want to be doing, just the most straightforward thing.
So basically, we're going to go ahead and say, entity index, equals
zero into the index is less than array count entities, you know, I
don't really love doing a re-count entities.
So I think I'm going to do, enter the account like so.
So I'm going to say game state, entered account, and then we just go
ahead and do that.
Now, I don't actually know if I want store entities, an array like
that.
Exactly.
Yeah, but for now, I think that's actually totally fine because
there's nothing there's nothing particularly odd going out.
Its this is going to March through them in order.
I'm just going to go ahead and say that this is going to be a straight
ahead Loop.
So basically say that this is entities like that and each time through
the loop.
I know why that just turned green.
We will go ahead and increment The Entity pointer as well.
So this is just going to go through all the entities, if a particular
entity.
Exists, then we will just go ahead and draw and right now we only have
hero bitmap.
So we're going to draw it as a hero, but in the future, we would start
to do stuff where we look at, see, what kind of entity was and draw in
a different way.
So what I need here is a need the entity P to figure out where it is
and then everything else, I believe should be just about fine.
Now.
We've got this hero facing Direction, which will have to put in the
entity for now, but I'm not sure how we want to actually deal with
that long term.
So we'll just call this facing Direction.
And then we'll go ahead and say entity Arrow facing Direction here.
And that may be just about it for the stuff that we need to do.
Okay, so in here, this actually is probably better done, not where it
is right.
Now.
This is really what direction they were pushing which is not really
what we've quite want it to do.
So, I think what we'd rather do is when we process the actual
movement.
For the character and figure out what is velocity actually is.
I think maybe then what we'll do is say okay, take a look at that at
that movement and say, you know, if if maybe if DD player why you
know, trying to think of how to do it.
If basically we want to basically take, we want to take D&D player and
use the direction because remember D&D player was basically
Ali, the velocity of the player.
So we have D&D player is pointing in some direction and that's the way
that is going.
And what you want to do now is you want to say, which quadrant is this
Vector in, right?
So we want to see which of these quadrants he actually falls in most
heavily.
And so, you know, essentially what we could do is say, well, you know,
if if his why, you know, if is y direction, if the magnitude, if is y
is greater than the magnitude of his ex, right?
Then he's going up or down and if the magnitude of his X is greater
than the Y, then he's going left or right and then we just check it
sign.
So I feel like that's probably the simplest way to do that now, but so
I think I'll probably just do that.
So what I'll say is, you know, if absolute value
Which is an intrinsic that will also have to Define.
But if the absolute value of D&D player, Y is greater than that of X.
I think I might actually do less than so.
I will check X first because I'd like it if they're equal.
I'd like him to use his.
Why facing Direction.
Just, I think that's a little more sensible.
All right.
So if the absolute value of the x is greater than the absolute value
of the Y, then I'm going to say,
So the hero is up or down in this case, right?
That's a, this is up.
So if the D&D player Y is greater than 0, then it'll be, it'll be
and we'll say greater than or well say greater than zero and then if
Right, if the if the, where is that, if the heroes moving down, then
we'll do this.
There we go, and then I could do the same thing here.
So and so if he's moving left, which is that case and if he's moving
right, which is that case, I believe that should do it.
So that will determine is facing direction from his velocity.
And in the case, where his velocity drops to zero, he'll just point in
the direction down now, I guess, you know what we could actually do we
could do something a little fancier to we could say well will only set
it.
In the case, where he it actually isn't zero, right?
So if they're actually zero, we'll just leave it the same if we can't
tell which direction he's going.
So it's whatever it last was that might be a little singer.
And so, we could say something like, you know, if D&D player.
Yeah.
If well, yeah, you know, if they're both zero so I don't know.
That's just do it.
Sure.
Let's say that that's what it is and then we'll go from there.
So we'll do that for now.
And of course, we'll have to go test that.
I just kind of
That in there, but that means we need an absolute value intrinsic
which is basically say, what is the magnitude of this value without
the sign bit?
Right?
And that again, is something that the compiler will actually generate
for us.
I believe absolute value is just F ABS normally, and and that should
give us the absolute value directly.
And it should not actually have to call any C library functions.
It should be a direct copy thing, where it outputs direct to.
To the code stream.
We'll check that later.
All right.
What is the right that supposed to be a real friend to we go?
So, let's take a look here.
So now when we do our this stuff we can get rid of this.
And we haven't wired anything up yet.
So really what we should expect to see is nothing on the screen by
this.
Want to get all this stuff compiling.
First.
We've got camera following entity.
That should be happy there.
There we go.
And the entity that we go needs a parenthesis.
And so now I think if I go ahead and restart this guy, we should have
nothing which is exactly what I would expect.
Yes.
So now we have to actually add an entity.
And so what we're going to do here is we're going to say, all right?
For a given controller.
If that controller maps to an actual player, then we will route the
control to the player.
And if it does not, then we will just sit there waiting for it to hit
the start button, right?
So but will say is, we'll say controller start ended down, right if
they
Touchdown.
On the start button, I believe that's what are our definition Hoops
platform.
There we go.
Start button.
Yeah.
So if the start button went down then we will go ahead and and create
a new player right initialise player.
But if not, then we will just assume that.
Well, I guess I like I said, I gotta check it will soon that.
We don't have to do anything.
And then if we actually are mapped to a player, then what we will do
is actually do the player movement and what
We can kind of do here is say well if we got this DVD player stuff now
we could also start handling is analog.
What we could do is say we've got DVD player, which is the sort of the
movement direction for the player.
Like so we could just now say if the controller is analog, then let's
go ahead and actually use that stick average X, stick average y, if
that makes sense.
Okay, so stick average X.
Stick average.
Why D&D player equals that.
There we go, and so in theory, that should get us.
Oops.
See, I don't want to do that yet.
Yeah, legal mess without asking.
Okay, so we're all good there.
So what we now need to do, is we need to re-enable, the player
movement code by calling it, but first, let's actually do the thing
that actually initializes the player.
If this ends down, then what we'll do is say, okay, what we need to do
is basically get
That controller index.
So, where is that controller index?
That's not where it is.
Handmade that H.
So, we've got this array right here, which is what I'm going to do in
this array is store for every controller.
What player it maps to, right?
So what I want to do is say what I guess I want to do is just say
entity controller, entity, or controlling entity, and then I want to
say, get entity.
Player impex for controller of whatever controller.
This is, right.
So, there's a controller index.
There we go.
When I get the entity based on that, if I get one back then I know I
guess I should actually have this, this a little bit inverted to make
it a little cleaner controlling entity.
If I get one back.
Then I know that I just need to control the entity that I already
have.
If I don't, then I need to wait for the start button and potentially,
if it went down, I need to actually go ahead and create that new
entity right, which I can totally do like, so actually don't know if
that needs to pass anything, but the entity at the moment.
Yeah, I guess it doesn't.
Need that.
So really all it needs is for me to do that.
Like so and then player in this for controller.
It's always there.
And then in theory that should allow us to create a new player by
pressing the start button on any controller that we want to.
Now, in theory.
We already mapped start to
An arbitrary thing for the keyboard, but I don't actually know what it
was.
And of course we never actually rotate this down because we haven't
actually made like a little screen.
Says press spacebar, press anything.
So let's take a look.
It's Escape is the start button.
That's not useful.
I think Escape should be the back button.
Don't you doesn't really make any sense.
Not sure why I picked that I suspect, I wanted them this way.
So you'd push back to do a sitting back is like, Escape that go
backward yet.
I don't know.
Doesn't matter not important right now.
These are all decisions will make quite a quite a bit further down the
road anyway, so if I hit the spacebar, well, we should just you know,
I mean obviously what you should do at that point is Crash because you
definitely want to crash immediately upon hitting spacebar.
So what did I do here?
Oh duck.
Yeah.
That's that's totally.
Yeah, again.
Not particularly good on a Monday people.
It is not.
It is not it's not going smoothly here on our Monday.
So, when we initialize the player I need to actually, that means, you
know, if there was no index, the player means I need to make a new
index for the player, right?
I need to like, add an entity.
That's kind of obvious.
I don't know why I didn't think of that.
But anyway, so what we need to do here is actually say add entity,
right?
So that we can actually get a new one that we can.
Flats because it's coming back.
Null to say that there wasn't one assigned.
I can't just go ahead and call it that way.
So let's go ahead and do that like this.
And for now, this is not actually how I really want to do it
eventually but like I said, we don't have to super careful now because
we're not really trying to do the entity system at this point.
We're just trying to put something in so we can start to be a little
more realistic about what's going on there.
So when I add identity here, all I really have to do is just increment
The Entity count right, entity count.
And say that whatever the game State entity slot is that's next.
We will go ahead and grab it, right.
So that's basically that and maybe what I can do is say, you know, I
don't know.
Maybe I don't want to clear this.
I think, you know, I could clear it in a density.
Maybe that's the best place to do it.
I don't know.
We'll see.
Maybe, you know, maybe I want to do this.
Something like that.
Yeah.
Yeah, yeah.
Well, anyway, so there was another bug that I just saw two, which is
that that I think this was like that originally.
I don't know, maybe it wasn't, which would mean that this would set
that to zero and then we'd immediately right to a null pointer.
So that's no good.
But that's beside the point for now.
So let's go ahead and see what's going on here.
We're going to get that guy out there, which is good.
I want to assert here that we're not out of entities which would be
good.
So I want to start the end of the count is less than
the array count of the
The array please.
So we go and the yeah, that's actually not called entity.
It's called entities.
So there is our entities array and let's take a look.
If we maybe crash a little less than we used to, there's our guy, so
that's good.
And now we just need to actually hook him up so that we can, you know,
Control him again.
So then we've got a thing here, which is move player, right?
Or something like this, or move here.
Oh, I don't know what we want to call that.
Exactly.
Let's call it move player.
So for move player, all we need to do is take whatever the entity is
that this player that we're actually trying to move and then we take
the the acceleration that he's supposed to have, right?
And so I guess we'll call this accelerate player.
Something like this.
Now, I guess it's really moved player because you're passing in
whatever you want the acceleration to be this Frame.
And so really, it's going to do the movement as well.
It's going to actually do that work there.
So we want to do here, is say, alright, that entity p is now going to
be the thing that we're working on.
And so let's go ahead and go through here and see where we're at.
Yeah controller.
Okay, so that's just that right.
There is just actually a speed modifier will have to think about how
we want to do, that will get rid of that for now.
Got the Deep layer P.
So that's also in the entity now, which is fine.
So just use the entity that we are on new player P.
So, let's see.
This, you could just do together, the old player.
P equals entity p, and the new player P.
Just equals the same thing look.
So not sure why we need to do that.
Let's think about why we're even doing that.
And then, of course, we need the time step.
We need that DT as well, because that's what we need to.
Control everything.
So, however, much time we want to advance will do.
It's like so we'll take that derivative from The Entity structure
instead of from the game State.
Again.
Again, this is really just there is, there is nothing really all that
interesting about what's going on.
Here.
It is straight forward transformation just to basically pull the stuff
out.
Now that we know that we're going to have multiple.
So we need to basically ya know exactly what we're doing as far as
that's concerned.
So now we're going to need that tile map as well.
The tile map that it's moving on, which I guess is, it's not
necessarily.
So we've got the game state, which we could pass directly, which I
think we probably just want to pass the game State, and let it get the
tile map out of the game state that seems like a more sensible thing
to do.
So, basically, out of the game state will get the world down.
Maybe we don't need the game State per se.
It's
All that we could do just past the world and have things just use the
world, but I'm not sure about that yet and it doesn't really matter at
this particular point in time.
So
Let's take a look.
Here.
We've got our player with player height stuff, which is how we were
drawing him before.
And technically, that's really a property of the player at this point.
It's not necessarily one that we're going to keep, but I'm going to go
ahead and move that out because really stuff like what the size of the
Collision is for the player will be part of the entity eventually will
not necessarily the empty, but part of the entities type at the very
least, depending on how we choose to implement that.
And so player with the heights should get moved out as well.
They should not really be things that are
And here, right?
They should be things that are actually assigned in initialize player.
So you can have players that are different sizes, seems like a pretty
reasonable thing that you might want to do.
So let's go ahead and do that.
So we'll say with the height for now.
So, and there we go.
So then inside the entity, we need to put those width and height that
there we go.
And now everybody who uses those basically has two
To Pasta.
Now, use the entities within the entity site.
So player width is now entity with like so and hey, look at, we need
to do it there too.
So that's fine.
Oops.
That's not what I wanted.
And then we'll also do player.
Height will go entity height.
So now we've pulled that out.
Like, so.
Okay.
Let's keep going almost there.
Let's see here.
We need to do these.
It's
Entity P.
So I guess we should just pull so place.
This game State player P becomes empty P, that it's a bunch of those,
what's get all of those guys.
And then, deep layer P.
Same thing, gamestate deep layer.
P becomes empty DP.
There we go.
And here are facing direction is now entity facing Direction.
And now again, you know, I say there's nothing special about what's
going on here.
But you'll notice, there is sort of something a little special going
on here, which is just that, we're not overcomplicating things.
This is why I don't like doing any stuff, you know, pre design, or
pre-audit orientation, or any of that stuff.
I just like things to get created as they go.
Because you'll notice all the all of the code is basically telling us
what we need to do.
I'm not having to think real hard about this stuff.
We're just waiting till we get to the point where it's clear that we
need something to happen and then we do it right.
Right.
And so, you know, it's like, okay, we at the point where we're I
started want to think about the fact there was controllers and
entities be controllers and players that were map together.
So I just need to have those now.
So we just made them.
And if he's each step of the way, you just keep it simple like that.
The code and the needs of the code will always guide you.
And really, the only way you can go wrong is By ignoring what the
needs of the code are and like trying to keep shoehorning stuff
together when it's clear that you need a new abstraction or something
like that.
But you know, like I said, it is really
If you can, if you can always try to code this way where you always
get, let yourself get in a situation where you need something before
you write it rather than pulling things out.
And so now we're, at least, pretty sure that we've got entities that
have stuff in it.
That is actually what we need.
Okay.
So the last thing we need to do is we don't actually have a call.
This the move the movement code.
And so, we want to do that.
What we want to do is for each of those controller from each of those
controller index guys.
What we do want to do is if a controller is ever controlling an
entity.
We do want to actually move them.
I don't know that.
That's where we're going to necessarily, do that move right now, but
eventually, we'll think about how where we want to wear.
We want to do that.
But for now, this is totally fine.
We'll pass that Duty player that we computed will pass the controlling
entity.
That's supposed to be controlled and there we go.
So now we should actually be able to control our guy again by hitting
the spacebar.
He should come in and then we should be able to control him.
However, I do not seem to be able to control him.
Why do I not seem to be able to control them?
Clearly?
I have forgotten something, go ahead and and stop us here.
Well, you know what?
Let's stop us actually here.
There we go.
So I come in and I push down and we're not actually getting that
passed to us.
Why am I not ever seen?
That initialize player.
Oh, yeah, we forgot one more thing.
We actually have to remember when we initialize the player.
We need to actually set What entity it actually was so that's a that's
a good point right there.
So let's let's go ahead and do that as well.
I'm not sure how.
Hmm, I'm not sure.
I'm not sure what I want to do about this.
Exactly.
I'm not sure about this.
I want these pointers right now.
I don't think I really do.
Mmm-hmm.
We'll see.
So, what I'm going to do here is just say that, that Ed entity
function would have, you know, it's going to have to return the index
of the entity and I'm not sure how if I want to introduce like entity
handles or anything like that, at this point yet.
So I'm just going to kind of do something pretty basic here.
And this is something that I definitely want to think about a little
later on.
But anyway, there's the entity index like so it'll clear it out.
Like that and we'll kind of leave it, leave it as such.
So the controlling entity goes ahead and does the identity call.
Now it has to actually do a get entity.
So what we'll do is, we'll say entity index, so and then we'll do
this, get entity and game State, and to index.
And there's a, there's a bunch of things.
I don't quite like about this, but that's okay for the moment.
And then what we need to do is just kind of store back.
That that in that player initial controller because the reason that I
couldn't control the guy is we never actually stored back.
What entity it ended up initialising for him, right?
So now that we've actually added him, we can actually start
controlling him because we won't have this problem where we add them.
And then we never, mark the fact that the controller is linked to him.
So there what happened there, break.
Let's see here.
Oh, yep, got one more bug boy.
It's been a buggy Monday.
I don't know if anyone else feels that way, just been a stupid Monday.
So the other thing that
That we do have to do too.
Is I said, I wanted to reserve entity slot 0 as like a null entity
slot.
And the reason I like to do that is I just like 02 mean uninitialized.
So if someone has a handle to an entity and the end of the handle is
zero or something, it should mean that there's no entity there.
But if you'll notice, we're actually not, reserving, entity slot 0.
So what we really want to do is we really want to do something like
this, when the game actually starts up the first time as soon as it
starts up.
What we want to do is say, Okay, Reserve, entity slot, 0, basically
for the nullity, right?
And so this is the null entity Index, right?
Empty index and it's not actually used.
So I'm just going to say no Casey Reserve entity slot zero for the no
entity which will just be an entity that you should never really right
to or get.
All right, so, that's fine.
And now I'm hoping that will actually be able to control this fellow.
Let's see, where is what?
I was trying to do.
Okay, so we set up.
Wow.
The typos today.
Maybe if I don't have my almond milk, it seems like that's entirely
plausible.
I don't know.
Maybe it's not, but you see that typo?
Don't know if you guys saw it to you.
Probably already did on the on the thing.
Why can't I find it?
Controlling entity?
There it is.
I still didn't actually assign the value, I cut and pasted the thing.
And I didn't actually sign it.
All right.
So finally, we hopefully will be able to control it.
And of course, I still can't control it.
Wow, just
You know, some days you have to fire yourself, you know, if it's just
like what's going on people.
So yes, we're still not getting any control input there.
What is the problem here?
Let's find out.
So I come in here and I am actually doing this.
So why do I never see a
Down control.
What's go?
Why do I never actually, why do I never hit any of these cases, if I
actually did create the entity and am actually now calling that code?
What's what's going on with that?
That's very strange.
What I'm going to do here is I am going to go ahead and follow through
the pipeline, get controller controller.
So yeah, let's see what happens here, get controller.
Interesting.
So it wasn't controller zero that which I thought was the keyboard
that actually got initialized.
Man, it's like all these typos on one line.
How is that even possible?
How you know, it's just, I guess that I'd like to talk to that up to
the fact that I'm streaming but that may just be because I'm just dumb
today.
I don't know if you can really chalk that up to streaming.
You know, with that many typos.
I feel like at some point that ain't the stream.
That's just your brain.
Not not actually operating.
So I think we've finished our typo, our Festival of typos.
And now hopefully we will actually have our dude and so now I think
we're actually working properly and of course, our guys movements
going to be a lot more swimming because he's only having his routine
one, once run.
Once instead of five times.
I'm see that's a little
Oh, you know what to when we're now doing that facing Direction
calculation.
I realized we're using the acceleration for that, and we really want
that to be his his velocity now, right?
And so, let's see here.
There we go.
Deep layer.
And so we really want that to be as velocity possible.
So we're going to go ahead and do that.
And oops, and that's just a DP now, so I should also probably change
that.
D player to just be DDP.
So DVD player is DDP that and there we go.
So now we've got all of that stuff.
Worked out.
Okay.
Now if I go in and I create my dude, see how the facing Direction
works.
Still busted.
What did I do?
And I do so DP.
Let's see.
Oops.
Still got it in here.
Ya gotta do this guy.
Let's go.
And now I think the facing direction should be correct.
Hopefully, yes, it does appear so and
There we go.
I don't know if I actually want it to be based on the velocity like
that.
I think, well, we're going to do an animation controller for him and
that'll probably have more an opinion about that.
But anyway, our constants now need to be retuned certainly because
that's just a little too swimming to say the least.
So I'm going to go ahead and crank those values up a little higher
than what they were before.
Our acceleration so on.
So let's go ahead and make our you know, sort of faux drag here quite
a bit higher and we'll make this quite a bit higher and we'll just see
how that is.
Oops.
See how that is.
He's a little too fast now.
So let's turn that down a bit.
Let's see.
That feels a bit better, but I'm going to I'm going to stiffen him up
just a little bit.
Yeah, yeah.
Think we're getting somewhere.
I think we're getting somewhere.
Yeah.
That's much better.
Okay.
All right.
Now we're feeling pretty good and are sticking problem.
Should be much exacerbated.
Now it, I'm a thinking that now that we've gotten rid of the fact that
we were calling the loop five times, which would have helped are
sticking problem quite considerably, because it meant that only the
first time would actually try to move into it.
And then the other four times it would try to move directly down and
imagine we should stick.
Yeah.
Like right away.
Okay, so that's what I would have expected.
That's what I would have expected to see the first time and now it all
makes sense.
I wasn't seeing because that's what you should have been seeing.
You should have been seeing crazy sticking Behavior.
And the fact that we weren't was kind of actually bizarre to me.
I was like, it didn't feel right.
And so that's the reason why.
And so now we fixed it.
So that's good.
So now tomorrow, we can get back to doing our player moving stuff, and
now, we can also have multiple players in the game.
So, that's kind of fun.
We could, I suppose if we wanted to, also, do something strange where
we actually use different colors for the, for the different players or
something like this.
I don't know.
Haven't thought about that.
Much, but anyway point being now, we've actually got that straightened
away.
That's that's just 11 bug.
That.
That is out of our way for later and we are just about out of time.
So I'm glad that that was like right on time.
So maybe it was good that we had those typos in there because
otherwise we would have finished much too early and had to start
something new and then not been able to finish it.
So we lined up quite good.
And so now we've got multiple layers.
I probably should have brought a Gamepad in here, so I could actually
test multiple players, but I guess we'll save that for tomorrow,
although, how much time do I have two minutes?
That's long.
Enough to get controller.
I'll be right back.
Probably should just leave a controller in here.
Let's see here.
Okay, mr.
Controller.
I guess, we'll just plug that right in here.
Let's see.
Actually, no air.
Hey, look, it's all good and the d-pad works.
So does the analog stick?
How about that?
All right.
We're in good shape people which reminds me at some point.
We need to get back to do our Dead Zone work, because there's some
stuff that we never actually do with the dead zone.
Yeah, a multiple, handmade Heroes.
They're pretty cute.
Look at how cute they are.
They're like twins.
All right, with that, we have gotten to the Q&A ladies and gentlemen,
so if you could, please prefix your questions with Q: so I can see
them and try to keep it to things.
We've done on today's stream or on a previous stream.
If you want to ask off-topic questions, that's totally fine for before
the stream.
But please do come about 15 minutes early to the to before when the
stream supposed to start.
If you want to ask those off topic questions, I will answer them all
then.
But if for the
For the official qas.
Please try to keep it on topic because these are the ones that are
recorded.
On multiple players.
Split screen.
What kind of screen resolution are you going to be working with, for
each one?
You may not have enough available on all platforms.
Well, I don't know if we're going to do split screen.
That was just I mean, I think I was like I've never seen as lde
split-screen game before.
I don't know if I want to do that or not.
That's just total conjecture.
We'll cross that bridge much, much, much further down the line.
When we actually start thinking about, if we actually want any
multiplayer gameplay in here or not.
Look at the game.
May just not make sense that way, or it may make a lot of sense.
That way when we actually go to play it.
So you can actually see something else happening here that we'll talk
about later, which is you notice.
He should be in front of the guy but he's behind the guy and that's
because we're just drawing them in whatever order the entities are.
And so that's kind of interesting thing like to think about because
obviously, when we're doing the renderer, you know, this is a little
teaser almost for like, well, we have to have a solution for that.
Right?
So what are we going to do?
And, you know, and so we'll be looking at some stuff about how we want
to do that sort of thing in terms of sorting and all that sort of
stuff.
You once said that visualizing problems is never weird wasted thing.
So wouldn't it be very helpful to run to the question section for
better?
Understanding of what actually happens?
Yes, but we haven't gotten to the point where we can really do
visualizations because we don't have any rendering code.
So basically we're kind of in a, in a state where we're just going to
do basic versions of things.
And then once we actually Implement our full Collision detection, or
we will do all of that work after we have the render in place, which
can do things like text on the screen and lines and stuff which is
What we would need for for actual visualization.
Randy is just four players was going to handle all game objects.
Well, it'll handle all game objects eventually, but right now, it's
only
As because we actually haven't gotten to the point where we're
thinking about entities for real.
We're just right now thinking about we're just thinking about having
guys that move around.
So we don't don't think about objects at the moment.
We haven't gotten anywhere near objects right now.
How will input be handled when two players trigger an action at the
same time?
Well, I don't think we're really going to have much problem with that
because it's not a versus game.
So it should be relatively fine if they both trigger the same time.
It's just whichever entity is the, the main is probably, the hero
entity will probably take precedence.
Who is the camera following with multiple players?
If you leave the screen without and then follow with the other, will
it work as expected?
So I'm thinking, I mean, like I said, these are questions that don't
really make any sense to ask right now because they would depend on
the game.
So we have to decide what we want for these sorts of things right now.
I think we just want the camera to follow an entity.
And in fact, what I probably should do since we set it up to do this,
but we never actually used it.
Is we
I have the camera following entity thing, right?
We should probably set that to whatever player gets added first.
So when we do initialise player, what we should probably do is say
something, like, if, if there isn't a following entity right, then
then, you know, there is now right?
Or something like, if get empty, right?
If there isn't a valid entity that the cameras following, then the
camera should follow this entity, right?
And yeah, and so again, we kind of want this to be.
We want this to be this, and actually pass a game, State game state.
So, right, and entity
Entity.
Yeah, so let's let's just do that because now that way the camera will
follow, whoever joins the game first.
It's, you know, probably the easiest thing to make sure that we still
have our camera actually working to some degree.
So, there we go.
Oops.
So let's check that.
Make sure that works.
Let's say I come in here and I go off the screen.
Now.
I'm on the second screen and I go off the edge and I go here.
Now this guy, if we have another entity who comes in, he should still
be back at the start, right?
If he
They're okay.
That's pretty funny.
But why are we still drawing him?
Why is why are we drawing him?
Still on that Z?
That's pretty odd, don't you think?
Oh, because we don't actually check.
That's why that's pretty interesting.
You'll notice that right here, when we draw entities.
We don't check to see if they're on the same.
Z is the camera.
We just draw all the entities, who would be in that zone.
We just we would just draw them.
Yeah, so we actually need, we want to do a check here.
I mean,
It is basically calling, right?
So you want to do to do culling of entities.
Based on Z camera view, right?
Because otherwise, yeah, that's pretty funny.
When you decide to have multiple players you decide to make these
entities.
Why didn't you just call it character or player will just be used on
other things as well.
Yeah, I mean, I just don't know what I want to do with that yet.
Because the reason I didn't call a player's was because I don't even
know when I did that.
If the players are all playing the same kind of thing.
Because like I said, I've only really been thinking about this as a
single player game.
So I don't know if the entities are all controlled even if the all the
players are all controlling the same kind of thing.
So I just decided it's entities.
It's
They're controlling and I don't even want to know what it actually is
at this point.
I know one of them's the hero but I don't know what the other ones
are.
So I just called it entities, just I didn't have to think about it.
Let's see.
Where did all the doors, go?
They're all still there, aren't they?
I was walking in and out of them.
How do you make the characters not to run through the trees?
Well, we haven't really talked about Collision detection.
Much those that stuff back there isn't actually isn't actually part of
the game.
That's just a bitmap that we had.
Put back up there.
It's this test background bitmap, which is not even really supposed to
be in there.
Right?
And so really, we've got instead of this, this drawbitmap.
We had a thing in here that would clear it.
We were just using that to basically clear our screen.
And so, if you take a look at it here and I come on, right?
We were just using that as a backdrop to clear the area where the
player, what the player was standing on but actually the tile map is
only is only the actual white and sort of black areas.
I can show you if we get rid of this, right?
This is actually what we actually have drawn and so, you know, we've
only really got a tilemap here.
That's got some.
You know, it doesn't have any, any sort of other things to collide
with.
It's just, you know, pretty basic.
And so once we actually get to doing our world generation, those trees
will actually represented in the map.
And so, yeah, it's, it's just a, it's those, those trees are not there
right now.
Is I guess what I would say, they're not, they were just a pretty
backdrop to leave on there.
Well, we had it on, it was, it's prettier with it than without it.
So that's why it's there, but that's not actually part of it.
So yeah, let me go ahead and I like having a bitmap there.
It's just kind of pleasant.
So I'm going to leave that in for now.
Why are we doing physical base movement?
Controlling the players with forces instead of just controlling the
velocity.
Doesn't this add unwanted lag in the player controls?
It adds wanted lag in the player controls.
I like to the player to have a little startup.
I don't like it.
If the thing to starts moving at full velocity right away and I feel
like there's a lot of precedents for that.
Like, I feel like a lot of games that feel good.
Have a bit of that slop in them, that you don't just go full speed
when you immediately start.
And so that's why we have in there because it actually feels much
better when it's in there.
It just feels a lot more natural and it's more enjoyable.
We will be doing any image manipulation with code.
Yes, we will be doing lots of image manipulation with code.
Any reason to catch failing to load art assets?
Yes, eventually we will be fail.
Well, we will be doing that very specifically.
That was kind of a weird.
I didn't wait a minute.
That was kind of a little weird.
I want to make sure I've got these ifs, right.
Sorry, I got distracted by the movement of the guy.
That looks correct.
If DPX, it's not quite correct though.
Is it because they could be equal and just not zero.
So, what we actually wanted to do was do this, right if entity DP x
equals 0,
and,
At the entity DP, y equals 0.
Then we don't set it, right.
so note, Casey
Oops, leave facing Direction, whatever it was.
Otherwise, then we go ahead and enter.
At it based on the other two because otherwise, if you're moving
diagonally, wouldn't set it, which is not at all what I wanted.
All right.
So now we're good.
Yeah, much better.
Okay.
But anyway, any reason to catch feeling to let artists, it's yes,
later on.
We will be doing a lot more of that because will sort of be showing
how to do more of an asset loading pipeline.
That's not really just a load bitmap call, right?
And at that point, we'll have a lot of stuff where we may have written
things in code that haven't been drawn yet.
And so it won't even be failing to load our deficit so much as the RS
don't even exist at all.
And so we need to handle that because we need to be able to develop
without having art assets yet for particular things.
So we'll want to have like fallback art assets and stuff like that,
even.
So we'll be talking a lot more about that when the time comes.
Is the notion of having all the entities in the same array.
Just a simplification for an hour, that actually sign that will stick
for long.
The way we're adding and referring to entities, probably won't stay
around for long, but the concept of having a big block of entity or
entities in an array, probably will be possibly even what we ship
with.
Why do I not use an auto compiler?
Well, it's a little bit tough to do an auto compiler because if we did
Otto assume you mean that it compiles.
Any time I save or whatever, it may actually run the code in a state
that I don't want to and break are currently running game.
So, I don't know that, I necessarily want that, but it's not
necessary.
A bad idea.
I just don't know if I want it.
How would this connector controllers mid-game be gracefully handled?
Well, really?
I don't think we have to do much to gracefully handle them because
it's a controller gets disconnected.
They can just plug it in again.
Right?
So all we would really have to do is just put something up on screen
saying, please reconnect controller, right?
We're not doing anything right now.
That would cause any kind of breakage if a controller was
disconnected.
I guess the controller ran on the batteries.
You might need a way to.
Uhn stop, using that controller and start using the keyboard, but what
we could do is just anytime, a controller gets disconnected, then that
player is just in kind of limbo for a bit and anyone who pushes start
could like, take them over.
For example, there's a lot of ways we could handle it will see.
Again, when the game is up.
We don't really know.
When comparing a float 20.
Shouldn't you be checking your within a tolerance instead?
No, because we don't actually care if
These values aren't exactly zero, then we can just actually use
whatever the small velocity is to determine the facing Direction.
But if they happen to be exactly 0, then we literally can't determine
the facing Direction because that's the only time that the hero isn't
facing some direction.
And so, at that point, we have to kind of just leave it alone.
Will there be diagonal movement Sprites for the hero doubtful?
I do not expect so.
Not very many questions tonight seem to be question free.
And if that's a good thing or a bad thing.
Probably a good thing.
Maybe that means we can end early.
Everyone could go to bed for a sleepy.
Monday, can go to bed early tonight.
I'll stay up for I'll say on stream for a couple more minutes.
So just to see
if there's any more questions.
Let's see.
Now, that looks like it.
That looks like the end of the queue and a up.
No, let's see.
Since small velocities were brought up.
Are we going to account for small inputs IE controller, dead zones.
Well, you actually already do clip to the controller.
Dead Zone a little bit.
So in win32, handmade, when we actually prepare the input to send to
the game, you'll notice that we actually do.
We actually do DeadZone processing.
Right here, right here with the win32 process process.
X input.
stick value, you can see that we basically have here a thing that
Clips values to The Dead Zone and
some people were kind of grumpy because they were like The Dead Zone
should be circular but I actually thought about this quite a bit and
I'm 99% positive that you definitely don't want the dead zone to be
circular in this game.
So I'm pretty sure we actually do want a square Dead Zone, but it's
also on my list to write some Dead Zone, visualization stuff on stream
so you can kind of see and that will explain a little bit, maybe more
why I think that the dead zone should definitely be square, but I'm
pretty sure not only that the dead zone is actually physically Square,
meaning that it's Square on the
Stroller.
And that's the part that will visualize but even if it's not, I think
even if the dead zone is physically, circular, I still think we
probably want it to be handled Square.
About storing entities in an array.
Again.
It seems like there are possibilities for easily having massive
operations on all the entities.
Will this be exploited?
I don't think that probably will be able to be exploited.
I mean it might be but I'm not thinking probably that it would be.
And the reason for that is I suspect that most of our work will
actually revolve around.
Not processing all entities every frame because, you know, if we have
10,000 entities in the world or something.
You don't want to be processing all of them.
Reframe if they're not on the screen.
And so we're going to have a bunch of stuff to do there.
And I don't think that, I don't think that will end up optimizing for
bulk updating of lots of entities.
I think will optimize for updating entities in different time
intervals, based on what they need to be doing at that time.
Let's see.
Caught up quick with the YouTube archives.
A couple of things that weren't completely clear the indirection for
function calls.
Can you be more specific on that though?
I'm not sure what you mean by that and why we didn't use the bitmap
masks directly.
Well, I'm not sure how we could use the bitmap masks directly.
I'm not sure what you mean by that because the problem with the bitmap
masks is that they don't tell us how to get things into the location
that we actually need them to
A right.
So the bitmap mask does, in fact, tell us what we would mask to get
the value.
But doesn't tell us how to shift it, to get it to where we need it.
So we need to call finally significant set bit to do that.
Right?
And then once we have that since there's no such thing as a rotate in
C.
We have to shift it down and then shift it back up again.
Anyway, so we don't actually need the masks at that point because it's
free for us to just do the
The Mask after we shifted it down, I'm not sure if everyone followed
that originally, but I'll just say it again.
So what we need to do is we need to shift the value from where it is
to where it should be, but we don't know because we don't know what
the values are here.
Red green, blue Mass.
We had to solve for, we had to ask for them by doing finally
significant bit.
We don't really have any idea.
Whether the redshift will be up or down, from where the red is.
So we don't know whether to shift left or shift, right?
So what we need to do is we need to shift it all the way down first
and then shift it all the way back up doing a left.
Stand a right shift.
Basically, because we have to do a left and a right shift already.
I'm sorry.
Well, right shift first, and then a left shift, right?
If we had a rotate.
So we could just, say shift, either positive or negative Direction.
Then then we would just, then we'd be able to use the mass directly.
We use the mask.
Then shift the difference between where we, where it is and where it
needed to be.
But since we don't have one, it's free for us to just use 0xff, which
allows us to mass directly with the same value every time and not have
to use any of this stuff right over that make sense.
Are there any games that you have personally developed that are
available to the public.
Are you talking about games that I like designed and made myself know,
there are thousands of games with my code in them that are available
to the public.
If you if you want to find them you can go take a look at for example.
Here.
Is some?
Relatively, I don't actually know if there's a comprehensive list, but
this is all of the games.
That are on this page.
Anyway, well, use my code in them because they use the animation
system that I wrote.
But yeah, but I don't generally, I do not design games for a living.
I'm not a game designer.
I'm a game programmer.
So you're not likely or even really.
It would not be possible to find any game out there.
That I have designed only games that have my code in them.
Oh, and also, I guess there's a lot more now that I think about it,
too.
It's I did a bunch of work on big to, I don't know.
I don't just I wouldn't count this as much because I was more like
just the person who did a bunch of like, Tech research for Jeff on it.
But I also let's see.
I don't know if this list is segregated by Bink.
One in big too.
Because a lot of these would be big one games.
So but yeah, anything that uses this for video also has obviously my
code in it to at this point.
Although I think wouldn't actually have a lot my code in it per se
because I suspect that.
Well, I don't know, maybe it would, I'm not sure.
I'm not sure since I did a bunch of research work on this.
I'm not sure how much actual code is still in big to that.
I wrote, Because, as they refine it over time, I'm assuming that they
replaced stuff that
Did with with more optimized stuff, but I'm not sure.
But I did do a bunch of work on this product and defining how it work.
And also, I wrote the tools, the, The Village tools that they still
use internally to develop it.
So there's that.
Okay, so clarification on what the person is asking for indirection
for function calls.
So you're talking about why we use the macros here.
So the reason that I do these macros is because I like to make it so
that I don't have to change.
I always do this for function, pointers because that means that anyone
who defines a thing of that type,
Always gets the same function signature.
That's why you the macros.
It's not particularly necessary here.
If you didn't want to do it here and be totally fine because there
just aren't that many.
It's a you know, it's a one-off sort of thing.
So it's not a big deal.
But when we do stuff where there's going to be potentially a lot more
functions that have to have the same signature, then it becomes a lot
more important so you don't have to do it.
It's but it's how I write that code.
Well, I'll be waiting for John to complete his presentation tomorrow.
I set the start time for handmade hero to 8:30 tomorrow to give him an
hour and a half of time instead of an hour to complete.
But no will be starting at 8:30.
So I won't hold it over after that, but I did try to move it so that
both that hopefully we won't conflict too much if we do.
Can you explain what you mean by Dead Zone on the controller?
Yes.
So basically what happens is these controller guys here, these analog
sticks the way that they actually work is there's a thing in there
called a potentiometer that I don't really, since I don't understand
Hardware hardly at all.
Like, I'm not a hardware guy at all.
Like, if you handed me a soldering iron, I'd probably just burned
myself with it.
But basically there's some things in there.
I guess called a potentiometers.
Which are designed to read off where the analog stick is and obviously
there are Springs in there as well that are designed to pull the
analog.
Stick back to the center.
When you let go of it.
Now, apparently neither of these processes is quite perfect.
As you might expect the spring make Springs, maybe don't quite pull.
The stick back to an exact center position every time.
I mean, it's physical, you know, maybe it can't be made to be that
good or that accurate and also the potentiometers may have drift and
they may not be calibrated.
It calibrated properly or all sorts of other things.
Right?
And so what ends up happening is in order to
Herman, whether the stick is actually been moved away from the center
because remember, the six of the center, we don't want to do anything.
We only want to move the character when the stick moves away from the
center in order to determine whether sick has been moved away from the
center.
We can't just say, well, if it's not equal to zero, then it must not
be in the center.
We have to actually use a range of values from negative, something to
positive, something, basically that all are considered being in the
center and that's what's called the Dead.
It's basically a Zone that's considered effectively that the stick is
not moving.
Even though the stick is returning values that are not zero.
And if you want to see a demonstration of this, actually you can see
this probably pretty clearly.
If we go ahead and say set a breakpoint inside win32 handmade and we
Okay, let's go ahead and see what though the value is.
I'm not even touching the controller sitting on the table.
Right?
So let's go in there and take a look at what the actual controller
values are.
I'll just set a breakpoint.
Right?
So in here, will say, go ahead and set the break point and see what
this actually are.
So the value that came back from Windows when we said, give us the
state of the controller, right?
Was this pad thing and
and what did actually had is it actually has these these values here?
Well, actually those those are pretty good.
That's all actual zeros.
That seems crazy.
Is that actually true?
I don't know if I believe that.
That seems kind of hard to believe, doesn't it?
Which controller are we looking at here?
Is it just me or is that kind of hard to believe?
So I guess you can't have a demonstration of it because this
controller is like dead on which is pretty awesome.
Let's see, if that's let's just verify, that's true.
I'm going to hold it over to the side here.
Stop it.
Yeah, that's pretty good.
And then I Let Go.
Well, okay.
So there you go.
Now, you can actually see it in action.
So I have I'm putting the controller down the table and you can see
that value is for the left, thumbstick, sex position, right?
If you actually look at what it is, it's 420, but I'm not actually
moving the stick.
So, you know, that's what you're trying to guard against there and you
can see that it kind of drifts around actually.
It's it's unreliable.
What that number is?
Yeah, so that's that's what we're trying to do when we when we talked
about the dead zone.
We're trying to make sure that that isn't a problem.
Do controllers have an outside dead zone?
I don't think so.
I mean, well, you know, they, well.
You know, for certain types of games, it may be true that controllers
with the values that they returned around the circle is not perfectly
circular and you might want to try and deal with that for our
purposes.
We don't really care super much about that.
But yeah, I mean we once we actually go to do the, The Dead Zone,
visualization stuff.
It's definitely something that we can look at just to see to make sure
that what we're getting is relatively clean, but I
Another will have to really do much about that.
That's typically less of a problem than the center stick dead zone.
Try.
Rimmer of Rufus or trireme Rufus is asking you and with the 32-bit
value, then use what you get.
So, okay, he's still talking about the bitmap loading code question,
where I was trying to explain it.
I'm not sure how to explain it other than how I already did.
So,
Try to imagine right?
What happens here.
We load this bitmap file.
Now.
We know that we need to output something that looks like this.
This is actually the this is what we have to do.
Right?
So we load this and we get back, a red mask, that is some random
value.
If we and with the red mask, right?
So we've got the, you know, we got the bitmap color and it with the
red mask is what you're saying, right?
We now know that we have just the 8 Bits of red that works.
Just fine.
But how do we get it to be right here?
How do we move it to this location?
Right, how would you do it?
You can't shift it, left to move it to that location, because you
don't know that it's actually to the left of where it is in the bitmap
color and you can't shift it, right?
Because you don't actually know if it's to the right, where the bitmap
color is.
So there is no actual way to write this code.
Such that, you just did the the and, and then to shift, unless you had
a shift that could go by positive or negative.
Which we don't have or rotate, right?
We don't have that.
So what we have to do is the mask is not important.
The mass doesn't matter at all.
No one cares about the mask.
What matters is the shift and what we have to do, in order to make
sure we shift to the right place is shift down so that we align it all
the way at the bottom.
So that we know that it's been shifted all the way to the bottom,
which we can do by just using whatever the least significant set B, is
that we find in the mask and then we can shift it back up to its
actual location since we're already doing that.
We might, as well just use unknown mask because we can't it's free for
us to do it and it, avoids us having to, even bother doing anything
with these guys.
They can be reused, they don't have to stay in registers.
They can just be reused, right?
So just be less efficient frankly to use these masks at that point.
Can you ever talk about the code?
You made that shipped 2000 plus X.
Sure.
So it's just, it's a, it's an animation.
It's a runtime animation package.
And it's basically like, you know.
You can actually see up here.
They've got a bunch of random marketing stuff.
Right?
Like it's just, it's a runtime animation system and a thing that
export stuff.
Of Maxima and stuff like that.
So basically like, you know, I wrote like all this stuff for our
pipeline.
So basically like pull data out of Max and Maya and like condition it
and then play it back at runtime and provide access to it and that
sort of stuff, and, you know, do, animation blending, and that sort of
stuff.
So that's that's basically that's what it is.
Pink is a video playback engine and I worked on the second version of
it.
I was basically the second programmer on it for for Jeff because he
just had a lot of work to do on it.
So I
What sort of doing a bunch of the code gen stuff and just stuff that
need to be done on the project.
So,
What about stun hamsters?
Yeah, there is stunning upstairs there.
Stun, hamsters, and there's also the owl flying game, but those are
not like actual released games.
Those were game Jam games.
Will we use a component system mapping smaller, Focus trucks, like
collision and Graphics entities to allow looping over more of each per
frame.
Yeah, but I would say let's wait wait till we get there.
There's a bunch of stuff.
We have to talk about with entities and that's like the least of our
concerns.
Anticipation for when gooeys will appear?
Well, I'm not sure what you mean by that.
Exactly.
We won't have any gooeys in this game.
It's strictly going to be an action game.
There's not going to be like menus and stuff.
Mamizou Zuko or MMOs Echo.
So those rotate instructions that you're talking about.
He was posting that, you do have rotate instructions and you're
supposed to like them unless I'm very much mistaken.
Those are only 16 bit rotates, so they don't help you, but I'll
double-check.
Oops, typed it in wrong.
But maybe not.
We'll see.
Do these actually work.
Wait, is this a 64 bit rotate?
When did that happen?
Does it actually work?
Has anyone actually tried this?
I did not know that you could do a 64 bit rotate.
Where is this documented rotates B.
Like, what is it supported on it?
Is it not say?
It's just like, you get to guess what it supported on, because yes, we
could totally use a rotating.
If we had a rotate but I didn't know you could rotate more than 16
because I know that they've got the wrote the old rotate instructions
on x86.
But in x64, I didn't know if they had ever actually put any of them in
there.
So that would be kind of cool.
Does this work?
Or like I just don't want to find out.
This is only itanium or something.
Do you know what I'm talking about?
Why don't you give me any any useful things here?
So let's
oh wait, but these are serious.
These aren't intrinsics.
Though.
So these are just these might not actually be instructions, right?
So, I don't know, this is actually useful but we'll check it out.
So let's let's find out.
Let's let's find out.
We'll see.
if I want to call this,
what was that one actually called their underscore?
Raphael?
Unsigned in value and inch shift.
So I guess what I have to do is redshift so and then the value is just
whatever.
Who cares?
If the value is, let's say that it's the green mask for some reason.
Okay.
So oops.
So what I want to do here is I want to say, alright, I get a Unit 32
back, which is my result.
Let's see what happens there.
Cannot convert argument to from B, go, right?
I got to do redshift index.
So let's see what that actually ends up doing.
And then we'll have to check.
We may have to turn on the optimizer, to actually get it to do what it
would actually do for real.
So this may not be a fair test.
But I just want to see what it ends up doing here with that with that.
And with that guy.
Let's see there.
All right.
So let's open up the disassembly.
See what's what's going down.
There we go.
So, does this actually work?
Well, that's a full-on rol instruction.
Does that actually work?
This is going to be pretty darn exciting at this works.
Whoa.
Yeah, I did not know that you had those in x64.
I mean, I don't I guess I hadn't had an occasion to go find out but
that's pretty awesome.
If that's actually true because yes, then if we have the rotate then
we can totally do it.
Because basically all we need to do if we have the rotate is we can
just make sure that we know whatever the difference is between these
two.
Yeah, and and then we wouldn't have to do two shifts, right?
We can do a single shift.
So let's try that.
So what we want to do here is if we have a rotate.
Then, let's see.
We have our red shift and the red shift, is where the red is
currently.
And we know where we want the red to be.
And so, what we could do is say alright, we want to take where we want
the red to be, which is 16 up.
Right?
And we want to subtract from that, whatever that index is what's, what
is our B can result here.
Let's see, handmade intrinsic study, H.
What is our B can result?
So, our B can result.
Finally significant set B comes back with that index.
They're okay.
And so what we'll do is, we'll say all right, whatever that index is,
we will subtract that index from 16.
And if it's more than 16, it'll just basically be.
It'll basically be a
rotate in the other direction.
So it'll be rotate right now.
I want to make sure this is signed.
So I'm going to go ahead and make sure that signs like that and will
basically say that okay, we can rotate left now.
Whatever that value actually is.
So this is actually going to be our, our red shift is actually going
to be something else that this is this is like the redshift search if
you will, so this is the redshift or I guess we'll call this red scan.
So we'll do red, scan, read, scan.
That's can look so on and then that way we can still assert that they
actually were found and then we can just do redshift equals this so
right that and that way we now have all of the values that we have red
green, blue, and Alpha.
We will actually have the shifts where we want them to go.
Right?
And then,
If I'm not misunderstanding how this function is meant to work, then
we could actually use those rotates and that'd be pretty cool because
that's the only reason that we weren't using the masks before.
So now we actually can use the masks and we can say.
Alright, let's do our our same calculation here.
But instead of doing it this way, right?
We'll do it.
using a rotation, so
Let's see.
I need to do rotate left.
And I guess I purely arbitrarily picking rotate left, but we'll do
red.
Gift.
And I want to do see is the value.
So I'm going to do see and red mask like so on.
So basically, that's all I have to do.
So, yeah, I think that's it, right.
I think that's really all we need to do.
We do see and green mask, blue mask, Alpha mask, and then we shift
them by the different shifts.
And then all we have to do is actually put those intrinsics in
somewhere.
So in here, we need to actually put in the rotate rotate left.
And that'll take a value and a amount and it will return that rattle.
There we go.
And for good measure we might as well.
Do a rotate, right?
You know I'm saying.
All right.
So will this actually do what we want?
I have actually no idea.
Because like I said, I didn't even know those were in ecstasy for they
are, which is pretty great.
So let's go ahead and make sure that I'm actually doing any of this,
right?
so,
Red shift, green shift, blue shift.
Alpha shift.
So, let's see if I agree with what it computed for those first blue
mask, Alpha mask.
So please hexadecimal me.
There we go.
So the red mask is there needs to be there.
That is a negative 8 shift.
So is that so is that?
And that one is a 24?
So yeah, I agree with all of those.
Those are exactly what I would expect them to be, and let's go see
what it actually generated here.
Inside raw tell.
Salt and value.
Yeah, this is pretty cool.
I'm pretty excited about.
Whoa.
Thank you.
Visual Studio know what you were talking about there, but that's fine.
All right, so hey awesome.
So that answers to questions than answers.
My question about whether you can rotate and x64 turns out you can.
And that answer is trireme.
Rufus is question about why we weren't using the mask.
Well, we weren't using the mass because I didn't know that we could
rotate.
And so I didn't think I had that option, but we can rotate.
So now we're all good.
So that's totally great.
And thank you Mo Z Co, I don't know.
Bounce that but for pointing those out because I totally, I think I
even searched for them at one point and didn't find them.
So that's pretty cool that those are there.
All right.
I think I think
Think we could just say that's done.
Let's just let's just call it.
There we go.
Cool.
All right, okay.
I think that's it for questions.
Let's take a look.
Okay, so Matt D says that the rotate will work but it's micro coated
so don't use it when you need performance.
So maybe that wasn't such a good idea after all.
Who knows though.
It depends on whether the microcode version is faster than the shift
than doing, two shifts, which it might be.
I don't really know.
Doesn't the rotate mess with XP compatible thing, you're watching.
No, not really.
Because the the XV compatibility for x86 code, it should still work,
but it would just be like a slower version or something like that.
I would think, because it looks like the 30, the 32-bit.
No, actually, the 32-bit version is available in x86.
I'm pretty sure.
So that should be fine.
It was only x64 that I wasn't sure about.
Yeah, I don't know.
So it's a good question, though.
Just how fast it is.
If it's my coated, I wonder what the actual speeds are.
And one interesting thing to look at would be like, I wonder, if
If the agner fog tables talk about what the actual speed is roughly
like what you could, what you would expect it to be in general and I
don't really know.
So
What what?
I don't want to be on this.
Yeah, so
that's it.
And wanted to show me more.
I want I want I want to look.
Down at more modern one of the more modern processors.
I guess I'll just do it.
That'll work.
so,
how bad?
Does it get?
It's basically the question?
Don't want to know about the Nano 3000, always have such trouble using
these tables.
I want them to be organized a little bit easier.
Maybe just like a search or something that tells you like.
Okay, here's here's the instructor.
I want them like B all the processors listed next to the instruction,
which is
Just easier said than done.
Someone needs to make the Uber agner.
Fog, tables or whatever.
I wonder if the if that other site has any of the information like
that on it.
I don't think it does but it's something we could check real quick.
Oops, now, that's not going to have it.
That doesn't help.
Yeah.
I don't know.
I'd be interested to know across like a couple processors, how bad it
was because it might be that rotate still better than doing two
shifts.
You know, I mean, I don't know.
I don't know the timings of it.
So be interesting to see.
Yeah.
It did look fast to me, pseudonym 73.
It looked like it was going to be fast to me as well.
So I think it's probably something you actually would want to do if
you have to rotate like if you're going to actually do something
that's a rotate operation.
I suspect the microcode rotate would be faster than you doing.
Two shifts.
Because otherwise why wouldn't it just microcode to two shifts?
Right, but I don't know, maybe not I guess because it wouldn't maybe
be able to quite figured that out.
I don't know, hard to say but
All right.
Anyway, I think we have well and truly overstayed our welcome, this
evening.
It is getting rather late.
So let us call it a day.
Tomorrow.
We can resume our Collision detection stuff since we're kind of we're
getting to the point where things are going to things are going to be
starting to be a little bit more pressing in terms of us.
Figuring out exactly what our
Attack plans going to be like I was saying today, we really at this
point need to start sort of consolidating and and figuring out how we
want to do rendering stuff because we're getting to the point where we
want to start having debug visualizations and let stuff like that.
So we're going to have to kind of go.
All right, what are the things that we actually need to figure out
here?
Let's go figure them out.
So we can start to make the render a proper and kind of Leverage from
there and
We've got our player movement thing kind of under control.
We want to do the Collision detection and then the other big thing
that I want to take a look at before we start to talk about the
renderer though is seeing compositing.
And so I feel like that's really something that I still want to do
with, before we tackle, before we start, tackling the renderer or
finalizing on sort of how, we're going about approaching things in the
design.
And so yeah, so I think for the rest of the week, I suspect that we
will probably work on the character movement code, getting some
animation in there and seeing how we want to
Do animation of the character and, and what we want from the render in
terms of that because I think that will be very important to know and
how will want that to line up.
And then the thing that I think will want to move onto after that is,
how did you see in composition?
So let's start actually taking tile Maps, building actual scenes, out
of them, and seeing what we want in terms of that scene, composition
stuff.
And then that I think will probably put us into a pretty good place
where we can sort of say.
Alright now we can go build the renderer and
The the final like sort of world store and stuff and get that working
to a good place.
And then that'll that'll kind of tie up all of our engineer start
stuff that we need to do.
We want to do sound at some point to.
But again, this game doesn't have a lot of demands in terms of sound.
So those will probably be a lot simpler than the stuff that we're
doing here because, you know, we're just going to be doing basic
stuff.
You music, playback and sound effects.
We don't have a whole lot of stuff that we need to sort of think about
there.
So that'll be a little bit easier than the graphics to say the least,
but that's basically,
Ali where we're at, so, we're feeling pretty good about it.
Again, we're only just now we're about five hours.
We're not even off of Monday on our second week of coding, If This
Were mapped to the weekday, so we've made quite a bit of progress for
how short of a time.
We've actually been programmed for us.
So, that's pretty cool.
Anyway, I will be back here tomorrow at 8:30 p.m.
To start work on the clothes and texture.
8:30, not 8, Pacific Standard time because John Blow is doing his next
compiler, Presentation tomorrow, and I would like to watch it.
So
Me, come on the stream at the normal time, but I will just have John
on my desktop and I will be watching him because I want to see what he
has to present.
So if you want to join me for that, that's cool too, but I won't be
actually starting handmade hero until 8:30.
So so that will be a slight difference tomorrow, but then we'll be
back to 8:00 the following night.
So I would love it.
If you would join me.
I hope to see you here tomorrow.
If you would like to preorder the game and get access to the source
code.
You can as always.
Do that at handmade hero dot-org.
That is the site that has to handle People Order button on it.
And if you want to do that, you will be able to follow along with
source code because I upload it every night after we finished
programming together.
If you want Sports video series.
We also have a patreon that you can go to and of course, for more
educational resources.
There's always the news and Forum site, which is great place to go.
I highly recommend it.
It's got the schedule for the week always posted on.
It's got an episode guide so you can catch up on past videos.
It's got coding resources where people have ported stuff to other
platforms.
Already, even though we haven't they have so if you're looking to get
it running on Mac or Linux or something, that's great, place to go and
there's a Code discussion board where you can go and ask programming
questions, and if you want to discuss the series in more detail,
that's a great place to do it.
So I highly recommend it for people traveling for the series is great.
Place to go.
Definitely check it out.
All right.
Thank you everyone for joining me.
And it has been a pleasure coding with you.
As always.
I hope to see you back here, tomorrow, at 8:30, until then.
Have a good one.