Recording.
And there we go.
Hello everybody and welcome to what is I guess day 7 of handmade here.
It is hard to believe that we have already gone through seven days,
but we have got a lot done.
We now have our own window rendering and we actually have our input
working even on gamepads.
There is before I get the sound.
Today.
We're going to we're going to try and get sound working today,
probably take today.
And tomorrow.
I'm guessing to get sound working, but we're going to give it a shot
before we go to that.
I had a couple of Corrections I wanted to make from
Emails that came in.
There were some good points that were brought up and a couple things I
just wanted to show real quickly, based on the email.
I think everyone should see.
It's great getting email from everyone.
Actually.
It's it's really satisfying because, you know, having more eyes on the
code.
Is almost always good because people see you'll catch much things and
people are trying different things and all that sort of stuff.
So, first thing I want to point out, someone notice that in, this is a
good idea is basically that when I wrote These, I was kind of.
I was, I was a little absent-minded when I wrote.
The stub functions here.
The stub functions for our fake xinput calls.
So when X input isn't actually found on the machine and you want to,
you know, have those sub calls in place so that you don't crash.
What we probably want to do.
Here is actually return the error code that says that the devices
aren't connected, because right now we're returning zero.
And that's normally in my world, 0 means, you know, the call failed,
but in Windows world because they do the whole thing where the error
codes are actually sort of
A series of different integers that can get returned 0.
I is actually defined as error success, I believe.
So, you know what we what we want to avoid doing is returning a value
that would make the caller to the stub code think that it actually had
one.
You can see right here Eric success error success is actually 0.
So what we'd rather do is take a look at xinput, get State and see
what we can return that will make whoever's calling the sub function
think that there is no controller.
Has.
Hey, at the library is not loaded effectively.
There isn't so error device not connected is a better thing for us to
return here.
That'll result in us working a little more.
Similarly, in seamlessly, in the case where the stub function gets
called.
Hopefully that makes good sense based that was just me being
absent-minded forgetting that zeros, my kind of error code to return,
not Windows, Windows.
0 means success, in that particular case.
It doesn't always.
But in that case it does often times.
It doesn't, you know, different parts of Windows written by different
people.
So it's not a lot of consistency there.
All right.
So the other thing I wanted to talk about was right.
Here, someone was saying, and I didn't actually know this, this was
completely news to me.
I've never, I don't really have any experience with Windows 8, because
I haven't shift a game in modern times, when Windows 8 was around,
last time I was involved in looking at code that was shipping.
It was Windows 7, and so, basically, this call will actually fail on
Windows 8 because it does not have X input 1.3.
It has X input one plate for only.
So, basically seven is likely to only have one point three.
Is likely to only have one point for.
So what I'm going to do here is basically put in a to do that says,
you know, test this on Windows 8 at some point when I can.
But also what I'm going to do is I'm going to go ahead and do a
layered approach here where I'm going to ask for 1.4 first because we
can use 1.4 and then after that assuming that we cannot actually load
that because it can't find it then we will try to load one point
three.
So basically I'm just going to make it so we try.
Or we try one point four, which is the more recent version.
We try one point three and then assuming that we get either one of
those this, this will evaluate to true and then we'll be able to get
the functions that we want for pulling the X input device.
Now, there's two other things.
I wanted to mention and these are not things.
We're actually going to fix right now because we're going to get to
them a little later.
But thing we should mention ciske up and down.
Those are actually where the alt f4 for closing the window comes in.
So if you were upset about the fact that your window now low no longer
closes when he'd have, felt if for it.
You have to go and use the actual close button.
You can actually come in here and well I said I was going to fix it.
But you know what, I could totally fix it.
Let's say you want to come in here and make alt f4.
Still close the window while since we are now handling that ciske up
down.
We are the people who are going to have to choose to handle alt f4.
So if we decide that the that the VK code, equals V, K, F 4.
Then what we're going to do is we're going to set that Global running
equal to false to kill our application, but we also need to do one
other check here.
Right?
Because we need to make sure that the ALT key was downright.
We need some way of figuring out whether the all key was down.
So what we're going to do is we're going to take a quick look over at
the actual documentation here, because I believe the ALT key is just
in the codes that get passed for this actual message.
And so we won't really have to do much work.
We'll just be able to look at one of the bits, I believe and see it.
So let's take a look here indicates whether the keys an extended key
reserves, not use the context code.
The value is one of the ALT key.
Is down 0, if it is not.
Let's see.
I think that's right.
I don't know.
Let's find out.
That's a little weird, the way they have phrase that there, but let's
give it a shot.
So that is actually in the L /.
Am so the L Purim is going to have is going to have that bit set.
Basically if if the ALT key is down.
So I'm just going to check to see if that bit is set.
And if that bit actually is set then we
Going to see if that if that BK.
Oops, that's not good white boy off to a good start to get today.
People.
I don't even know what I'm looking at here.
Let's try that again, you know, some days on the stream, you get a
little absent-minded.
I tell you.
It's hard to always keep in Focus.
So let's make sure that's right, 29, that's good.
So we're just going to check.
If that bit is down.
And if that bit is down, we are good to go.
And I'm going to do this guy again, just so we don't get a performance
warning on the pool, which we would if we were pulling another mode,
save that story for a different day.
All right.
So let's go over to Deb em and take a look at what happens when we hit
F4.
Just to make sure that we're actually feeling it properly.
Let's take a look here.
Off we go.
So the first thing I'm going to do is I'm going to hit F4, just to
make sure note that did not work at all.
What's going on here?
ALT key was down, is set to true.
That's so that's not.
That is not what we wanted at all.
What am I missing there?
I feel like that should not have happened.
Am I misinterpreting the documentation?
The value is one of the
ALT key is down when the key is pressed so it should have not been
one.
That's a little bit weird.
Let's double-check just make sure we're not going.
Crazy.
Here could be the that documentation is wrong, could be again, but I'm
out to lunch on this stream.
It's going to happen.
If it doesn't happen today.
It's going to happen eventually.
So let's take a look.
You know, we want to see what the W Prime is.
We're taking a look at the 29th bit.
So let's see here.
So that's not actually said, what did I do wrong?
I did something.
Oh,
Let's see here.
I must have done this wrong.
Shift it up 120.
Awesome.
Yep.
We are out to lunch today.
Ladies and gentlemen, so that was interesting.
Let's, let's make sure that's the problem.
First is I'm going to explain that because that's actually a good
thing to explain.
You may run into that yourself when you're coding.
Yeah, much better.
So basically what happened there.
I'm sure that was going to be easy to miss.
So I'm going to go over a little bit more slowly because that's a
that's a bit of a snafu that you're going to.
You're going to fall in tune out again.
It's easy to do sometimes.
So basically we take a look here at all.
Key was down, what I
I actually had written again because of the out to lunch.
Notice that we talked about.
I had actually written it, missing one of the parentheses that I had
intended to put.
So I wrote it like that.
Now in C and C++.
There's a thing called operator precedence, which means that certain
operators, get evaluated, first and certain operators, get evaluated
second.
And so on third, fourth, fifth.
Now we talked about this the intro to see stream and I pointed out the
fact that multiplication will happen before addition.
Well, the same is true of any other operators.
So like this not equal.
Here and this shift, and this end, they all have precedence to now.
We properly wrapped our shift in parentheses.
So there's no ambiguity.
No matter what the operator precedence is, that's going to get done
first.
So that's fine.
But once we get out here, once this is evaluated, so, that's, that's
equal to something right.
Once that's evaluated, see, is going to look at this and it's going to
go, the compiler is going to say, well, I've got two operators here
and, and I've got not equal to.
I'm going to evaluate whichever one has higher precedence now,
In our case, this ended up having the higher precedence.
That's just how it's defined.
And so that ended up meaning that it would do this operation eval not
equal to 0 then it was going to end that with the L.
/.
Am I guess is what ended up happening and of course since eval not
equal to 0 will equal 0 or 1, the L frame, probably had the low bits
set.
I don't know if that's likely or not.
Let's take a look, the repeat cap for the message which so it was
probably one, which is exactly what we would have expected on the
second time through that Loop.
For example, the peak can't would.
Ben one.
So that will evaluate to true.
So all we had to do to fix it was to actually wrap the thing in the
parentheses that I was trying to type in before and totally failed to
do.
So, we make that extra parentheses say we got to do this and first and
then we check for the not equal to 0 which again turns it into a 0 or
1.
And that's something that actually I don't often do that extra not
equal to 01.
Maybe now's a good time to talk about that too.
Just while we're on this first little Preamble.
So usually what I do is I don't use Bool.
I don't usually use
Pool because Bool is defined in C++ to have some kind of odd
semantics.
Basically.
It's defined to have to kind of be either 0 or 1, in some sense.
The reason that I say this is because if you notice when we've got
statements, that are like this, when we do, the pool was down.
If I were to get rid of this, and I don't know, if this still happens,
this is something that at least happened in the old days.
I'll show you what happens when we try to compile our code with
optimizations on basically, so let me load up that
At build up that file whereas our build bat file code.
Build that bat.
So if I want to do optimizations, I don't know.
If 02 does optimizations.
It's been a long time since I've done that.
Maybe not.
Maybe W.
All does that.
Let's see if we've got it here to do.
Here you go.
So this is the warning that you will get basically.
It says forcing value Bool to true or false performance warning.
So basically what that means is if you take a look at what would
happen in the case that I wrote here, if you take a look at what would
happen here.
What it's going to do is it's going to end the value of L per annum
with one shifted up by 30, so the 30th bit.
So the result of this is either going to be 0 or the value of the 30th
bit being set.
It's not going to be 0 or 1.
So, if you assign this to a Bool, C++ has to generate code that
basically checks to see whether the value is 0 or not.
And if it's not zero, change it from that 30th bit being set to just
being one.
Now.
The kicker is we didn't care.
We were going to do this.
This comparison here.
Right?
Well, I guess.
So in this case.
No, okay.
I don't feel so bad about this one.
I don't feel that we were going to actually do it because we're going
to do a not equals here.
So, in this case, we actually did care what it actually was in,
because we want to be able to compare the two, but in a lot of cases,
we don't care.
So for in this case, for example, we don't actually care week.
This just has to be something that's nonzero.
So we're actually wasting some time by actually doing it that way.
So typically, what I'll do is
Will actually just Define my own type there.
I'll define basically a Bool.
That's that's actually an integer and to Bool.
So, you know, I will do something that looks like this type def in 32,
rule 32 and basically, so the only thing I'm doing there is I'm
saying, hey, by the way, whoever's programming this, I intend this
just to be a zero or nonzero value.
I don't want to care necessarily about what the value is, but I
Optical power to keep shoving it into this 0 or 1 state.
So I will often do that and then I'll just omit this.
That's what I will typically do.
So maybe we should start doing that because that's what I normally do.
So maybe I'll just put that here just so you can see it.
That's something that I typically do.
There's another thing that I typically do.
I don't know if I'm going to do on this stream because it doesn't seem
like it's necessarily such a good idea.
So I'm going to leave.
I'm going to say that that's probably all we really need to do for
now.
Have that extra Boule in there and then we'll go forward from there.
All right, we're going to
Turn off that wall because man looks like you really can't compile
with wall and include those windows header files.
Those windows header files are just filled with warnings.
Look at all that.
I don't know.
Maybe you got to turn on something else to get that to go away.
I'm not sure that looks new used to be able to compile with what w
all.
I thought maybe not.
Anyway, Windows header files, causing a little problem.
There.
Not much we can do about it.
But in the future, maybe we'll just get rid of Windows of H and solve
that problem.
Okay, so we are now at the point where we should be handling.
I believe our alt f4 a properly.
So F4 does not exit.
Alt f4.
Does that is what we wanted?
So I said I wasn't going to show how to handle it.
But I did it.
Anyway, there you go.
So the reason we had to do that again was just because basically
Windows is only going to send you that ciske down message because it
doesn't actually know if you maybe had something in particular, you
want to do with the alt +, F4 keys, and so on.
So he doesn't want to be presumptuous.
So it's actually
The deaf window prop.
It's this thing that actually picks up the alt f4, closes the window
for you.
So once you start handling, WS W, M6 key up and ciske down.
Then you have to do that stuff.
That deaf window proc was doing for you.
Now, you could just called if window prop but we don't really want it
to do any other Sisk.
He's probably.
So I say it's better to just handle it ourselves and leave it at that
especially because we may not want a cold exit on this.
We may want to do something here.
Who knows?
So that's probably the best way to do it in my opinion.
So that's what we should do.
Do last point of clarification.
Down in here.
Someone brought those up and their right to bring it up, but it's just
something we weren't going to get to yet.
So I want to wait and hold off on talking about it till we get to it.
We're just so, if anyone's else is concerned, there is a bug in xinput
a really bad performance bug and actually, as far as I know, I'm the
first person who actually complained about it.
There is a post on Molly rocket from a long, long time ago where I was
like.
Did anyone else notice the fact that this goes
Basically, what happens is when you call get xinput, get state.
If you do not get back in a controller.
Like if there was no control.
Remember we're going through all four controllers here and pulling
them if no controller is plugged in for that particular index.
So, if there's no controller 3, there's no controller for xinput, at
least on certain versions of X input will stall.
And it'll stall for several milliseconds or something.
It's a really bad stall, it eats up a lot of CPU time.
I'm and so you really don't want to actually do this when we actually
do our perf.
We are going to have to get rid of this call.
Every time we only want to pull the ones that are actually connected.
Now, the documentation suggests doing something that is actually not
what I would suggest which is pulling every so often, but that just
leads to a spiky frame rate.
You don't want to do that.
In my opinion.
The better way to do it is usually to use the actual hid notifications
that come in when devices are plugged in unplugged because there you
can actually see exactly when a device is connected or disconnected.
Didn't want to go into that yet, which is why you can cover it, but we
will be covering it.
So don't you worry about that.
When we get to Performance, we will get to all these things and they
will get ironed out.
But just in case you were worried.
Don't worry about that.
Leave it for now.
You may get those stalls.
They're fine.
Again.
We are not trying to be on the fast path right now.
We're just trying to get everything running, so I can show you how to
build everything.
And then we will start to be concerned about the speed of the various
things that I, you know, I already kind of know, we will have to
improve when we get there.
It's usually best to not crank the, you know, turn that optimization.
Ratchet though, until you've got everything working because your
optimization is a very precise, very serious thing that takes a lot of
attention and you don't want to be going at it willy-nilly and you
don't want to be doing it in code that you don't absolutely.
No.
You're going to keep because you're going to waste a lot of time if
you do that.
Alright, that is the end of the clarification.
So it is almond milk time.
I think pretty much without a doubt.
Almond milk time.
And then we will get started on Direct sound.
Heaven, Help Us.
Okay, a little bit trippy there.
That was not the cleanest almond milk.
Take I'm going to admit that, you know, sometimes this kind of like I
didn't type in those parentheses correctly.
Sometimes the almond milk, gets a little away from you.
That's what happens.
All right.
So basically what we need to do is first and this is why I say, it's
gonna be a little rough.
First.
I'm even going to do a little sketching here.
The sketching is brought to you, of course, and by, you know what, I
even think I still have his name written down.
This is brought to you by Kurt Car to let cartel.
Teppei.
In fact, the person who actually sent an email and told
How to fix OBS so that I could actually run at a reasonable frame rate
with tooltip still capturing.
And so I think I can actually draw somewhat speedily enough to
actually do a diagram here.
Yeah, that's pretty bad.
I don't know, it's not great.
But I'm going to drive draw anyway, it's better than it was.
So that's something.
All right.
So what I'm going to do here is just give you a little bit of insight
in how we're actually going to be, outputting sound because it's a
little bit wonky.
We're going to be using direct sound.
So that will have reasonable compatibility with older systems.
Like I said, I kind of wanted to show you how to get things running on
Windows XP as well.
Just to show you how to give you a little practice with kind of
reaching back and doing backwards compatibility.
Does that mean you actually have to charge it Windows XP when you're
actually shipping a game?
Probably not.
I think the user numbers are down to something like seven percent.
So it's really not that big of a concern, but I'm trying to keep it
that way because there's not a lot of cost to us to actually do that.
At least for the majority of the code.
So we're doing it anyway, so I'm going to use direct sound, which is
an older age.
I there are newer audio apis.
I don't think any of them are particularly good.
Anyway, they're probably all six of one half-dozen the other but you
might get slightly better latency and things like that with going with
the newer one.
I'm not sure point being the way the direct sound output works in the
way that we're going to be doing it.
It's basically you allocate a buffer of sound, this is my buffer.
This is, you know, the zeroth bite of the buffer and this is, you
know, some some number and out of there.
Wow.
This is really slow.
Thought it was going to be good, but it wasn't good.
And basically this this buffer is,
Circular, so, what's going to happen?
Is basically direct sound, you know, we'll play along and it'll play
along, and I'll play the sound and, you know, essentially, the
hardware, whatever your sound, however, it is playing the song, and
when it gets to the end, it just comes right back around to the
beginning again.
So it's just going to be constantly looping, this buffer.
So we're basically going to allocate a buffer.
That's maybe, you know, it's pretty long, you know, maybe it's like
two seconds long.
Let's say a nice, big buffer that's like two seconds long.
And, you know, audio D's days of you can see on most things is like 48
khz, right.
Oh gosh.
What is that?
What is happening?
This is just, this is awful.
All right, there we go.
Audio is basically 48 khz these days which is 48,000 samples per
second.
Right?
So basically we're going to have either 48 kilohertz, either 48,000
samples in this buffer.
If we do one second or we're going to have what is that does night.
96,000 in there.
Basically, we're going to have some some large number of samples.
And of course, what we're doing is, we're going to be running this
game at 30 frames a second or 60 frames a second depending on the CPU.
You and all sorts of other system, things the resolution running, at
that sort of stuff.
So we're looking at outputting, you know, something like I don't want
to, I want to say like 800 or something like this.
I don't know.
We're basically going to be outputting once, you know, forty eight,
thousand divided by 60.
In fact, you know what, I could actually just do that if I really
wanted to, I suppose, if I was being was being diligent here 48,000,
/, 6800 or I guess I didn't need to do it.
We're going to be outputting about eight hundred samples per frame.
To line up with the video, right?
Because the video is showing for 1/60 of a second.
Let's say, and we're going to Output 800 samples for that.
That is roughly what we're going to be doing.
But we cannot obviously, wherever direct sound is playing, you know,
wherever direct sound happens to be.
Lets say direct sounds that though.
I shouldn't say Direction on the hardware is at a particular location.
Let's say, right?
Let's say the hardware.
Is there something like this?
Well, if the hardware is there, we can't actually write directly into
their, because if we write wrote directly into their
We would basically have a problem where this would the where it was
playing would get past where we were trying to write before we finish
writing into it.
Right?
Because there's a bunch of latency and just the writing as well.
So what we actually need to do is we need to write a little bit ahead
of wherever it actually is, right.
So we're basically going to have direct sound is going to be playing
in the harbor.
Is going to be playing somewhere and we're going to be writing
somewhere ahead of it.
We're going to write in our new samples that go along with the frames
that were outputting and then when, you know, actually as direct sound
Is up.
It'll just play through those and off we go.
So, we're always a little bit ahead right now.
When we talk about the game Loop, when we actually go back and do the,
the full-on gameloop stuff.
Probably starting next week, maybe the week after that.
There's a little more subtlety here because it deals with how you
structure thing.
Things their stuff to think about like, where you're actually going to
do the page flip, right?
Because you can imagine if you're viewing some frame.
Let's say that you're viewing a particular frame that got flipped
somewhere around here.
So the user is viewing, a frame.
Of the video.
Got this drawing is so amazingly awful.
I gotta have to tune this sometime.
Maybe we'll do a practice room sometime where I try to get the setting
so they can actually draw.
So if we're viewing a frame and we're going to view this Frame, let's
say this is 1/60 of a second here.
So this is 1/60 of a second, right?
That's what's going, you know, and it's even Windows, that's ruining
my stream.
It's this stupid.
It's that thing.
I don't want that thing.
That's all I got turned off pan and put I guess maybe we'll just go
right to the mouse and just do it this way.
There we go.
So this is 1/60 of a second in here.
Let's say right the user is going to be staring at this picture for
that full 1/60 of a second.
And so what we're going to do is we're going to be building the next
frame like in here in this time.
This is where we're calculating the next picture, right?
We're doing the rendering and the game updating and all that stuff to
generate this picture.
So we would also want to Output this piece of sound.
So we want to Output a p, this picture and this sound together.
And ideally, we would be
Writing into the location of the buffer that lines up with where we
expect to page flip, right?
The problem with this.
It's actually really hard to do that because the page flipping happens
usually on the V blank in the old days, but could actually happen
anytime now with like in videos crazy sinking stuff and there's a deep
pipeline sometimes involved.
So we actually don't know where these are going to be shown.
There's all this kind of stuff that gets in there.
That makes it a more complicated than that, but it's just something to
be aware of like, trying to think about the audio sync on any given
frame.
Are Computing the picture that it's going to get flipped at some
point, going to start being shown in the audio that's going to play
behind it?
Ideally, and that's kind of the way to think about it.
So basically, what we're going to try to do today is just open a
handle to direct sound and get this buffer up.
This thing where and and have direct sound just kind of do this
infinite loop on it, where it just plays it over and over and over
again.
That's where we're going for.
I don't know if we'll get it today, but that's where we're going for.
So, hopefully that makes some sense.
It's pretty straightforward.
And again, it's just memory that we're just writing into just like the
bitmap, its exact same.
Same thing we did with the bitmap or just open up a buffer that we can
write our own sound into.
And then that sound, we'll just play out the speakers, which is what
we want.
I'm just going to close this awful gimp because that was horrible.
I got to figure out what's wrong with that before someone email me to
remind me if you think about it.
Just man to fix that because that drawing was horrid, okay.
So, what we need to do here, if I remember.
And we'll have to look at the Docks.
But if I remember correctly, you can't really get your direct sound
going.
I think until you have a window.
So basically we don't want to do it up here.
We can load X input we can load it anytime.
So that was a good good time to do that, but we can't actually do that
with directs.
I think we want to do that a little later.
So basically down in here after we actually know that we do have a
window in the window is actually open.
Then we're going to do a win32.
I guess we're going to call it Lodi sound because we got a load it.
And then we also got to open it as well.
So we'll basically call it that.
Maybe I'll call it a win32 in it D sound because to some degree,
that's a little more accurate since we're doing more than than just
loading it.
So, anyway, we're going to have this here.
Maybe it'll return something eventually, but base, we're gonna have a
little function here to initialize direct sound.
And what that's going to have to do is it's going to have to do a
couple things.
So, the first thing that we're going to have to do is we're going to
have to actually load the library, which is what we did before, right?
We're going to actually load D sound.
Because again, you know, if for some reason D sound wasn't installed
on the machine.
It's unlikely but let's say it wasn't there's no reason to not be able
to play the game.
You have to play the game without sound but at least the game will
still run.
So we don't want to say that.
You have to absolutely have D sound.
So, we're gonna have to do that.
Then we're going to have to get a direct sound object because
basically direct sound is object oriented.
That is the way they chose to implement it.
Unfortunately.
It's kind of a calm.
It's this thing, the component object model.
It's a whole thing in Windows, that I'd rather not actually have to
have to go into if we can avoid it.
So, it's just a nightmare.
It's basically a thing that they decided to do.
That was about trying to sort of have an object oriented model for how
things are called.
Windows and where you can ask about what interfaces thing support and
all this kind of jazz.
It was a complete train wreck awful, just absolutely awful bad idea.
But unfortunately, that is the way that these apis were exposed at the
time.
That's just how they wrote them.
They were not clean, like the xinput one where you just get a couple
calls and it works.
This is a lot Messier.
So we're gonna have to get a direct sound object.
We are going to have to essentially create a primary buffer, which is
basically
Sort of it's holdover from the original version of direct sound where
you wrote directly to the sound card in some sense.
They don't really let you do that anymore, but you still have to
create a primary buffer, which was supposed to be think those on the
sound card so that you can set the mode of that in the old school, way
of doing things, and then we're going to create a secondary buffer,
which is the thing.
We're actually going to write to if that makes sense.
And then after that, we will just start it playing.
Then we should be good to go.
That should actually give us sound on Windows in theory.
If I'm not if I'm not forgetting a step.
And in here, there's a couple things like there's a there's a
Cooperative mode that
To set that.
It's kind of tells it what you're doing and these sorts of other
things.
All right.
So first of all, we need to load the library.
We already know how to do that for basically, doing that exactly the
same way that we did it for X input.
When you look up here, right?
We're doing that exact same thing.
So we're just going to load Library, D sound dll.
If I'm not very much mistaken.
We're just going to go ahead and load that up and then assuming that
we actually find the library, then we're going to do these additional
steps here.
So in order to get a direct sound object, I
We have to get proc address on Direct sound create.
So, basically, this this thing right here, that we were doing this
sort of situation from before we got to do that.
And I think it's called direct sound create.
I'm going to take a look and make sure that's actually true because I
don't remember a lot of these things by heart.
I got to got to be honest with you.
So, direct Sam create much like I was doing before I basically want to
verify all this with the with the actual.
Yeah.
This is this is it.
With the actual documentation.
Unfortunately, this isn't the actual documentation.
This is someone asking about the actual documentation.
That's direct sound create a Twitch.
I didn't actually want because we don't want to require a.
We have absolutely no reason to require it but it doesn't look like
I've got a lot of other reference here.
This does actually look right.
But I'd rather read the actual documentation.
That's a little unfortunate.
Well, what are you going to do?
I guess we'll muddle through this the old-fashioned way.
Like I said it was going to be rough.
We're using an older version.
The API which means you kind of end up in some sticky situations
sometimes.
So let's go ahead and include D sound .h here, I guess and make sure
that we actually have it and we do.
So that's good.
And then I'm going to go up here and I'm going to just go right ahead
and open that up.
We'll just say, let's see what it's got in it because that'll help us
out.
So let's take a look at direct sound create.
Here we go.
This is the actual call that we wanted.
Looks like so I'm going to cut and paste that out of
Here.
And I'm going to go ahead and do our standard get proc address
maneuver exactly the way that we did these guys.
So, I'm going to say pound Define H result when a twin API and then
we're going to do a name here.
And this is basically our direct sound creates.
And so we give it a name and that will initialize it right there.
It's going to take one of those.
It's going to take one of those and it is going to take one of those
now.
One of the things you may ask me to do and I don't blame you is to
explain to you what these extra things are like pyung kaotar.
And I am, perhaps disappointed, perhaps pleased to say have absolutely
no idea.
I know it has something to do with the cam, interface thing that weird
old thing that used to do, but I have never actually had to use those
things.
I have never had to use that pointer for anything and so I'm happy to
say.
I have just always left at zero.
I'm sure it has an explanation.
I'm sure the documentation will tell you if you're curious, but I
can't tell you.
The the grid device on the other hand is pretty straightforward.
That's just what sound card you were trying to open.
We're actually in the past 0 for both of those.
But anyway, so here we go.
This is the thing.
We actually need to get that back.
So we're going to call Direct sound create, and then we're going to do
exactly the same things that we did here.
We made our macro.
We're going to make a pointer to it.
Basically, direct sound creates.
We are going to make, well, we don't actually need to stub call,
actually, because this isn't going to get called from anywhere.
We don't even
It to be Global.
Actually, we just need to type def because what we're going to do is
we're just going to use it to create it just that one time.
So we actually only need the pointer in here.
We're never going to call that create.
Again.
I don't think now, if we change our mind we can always move it out to
be a universal function that's called.
But since we don't need it, universally yet.
I'm not going to bother putting a universal because that will only
lead to maybe people calling it accidentally or who knows what else.
So if we get the library will go ahead and do the direct sound, create
call and we'll make sure we actually get that back.
Assuming we get that back.
And then we will actually try to call it like this.
I guess we'll just go ahead and call it right in here.
If we don't get it back, this would might be a good place to just give
a give a quick Diagnostic and I'm going to just put these in here
because will eventually have a logging system where will log arrows
and so I might just add those in there.
So we know and I'm going to put them up here as well.
Just so we kind of know, this might be a good place for a diagnostic
as well.
Just so you know, which version of xinput was running in case.
There's stuff, you know, we might print out kind of which version we
loaded, that sort of stuff.
You know, these these might be good that sort of thing.
So just just kind of put some to dues in there so that when we come
Through here.
When we do have a logging system.
We can add them in a code will still work.
Just fine.
Even though we don't have Diagnostics.
Those are just for error-checking later when we're trying to do
compatibility testing.
Sometimes it helps to have some way of looking at a log and seeing
what went wrong.
Okay, so I got to set the Co-operative level here.
I'm pretty sure that's what we do.
Direct sound create.
We don't care which device it is.
We need to create one of those.
Basically, the way that it works is we call Direct sound.
Wait, and it's going to give us it's going to give us back or turn
code that we're going to have to check here.
And and then we're going to do is we're actually not going to it's not
going to return to us that direct sound handle.
What it's actually going to do is it's going to to give us back the
pointer in an out parameter this this thing right here.
This LP direct sound.
So basically what we're going to have is we're going to have a direct
sound object, right?
We're going to have a direct sound object pointer.
So basically this is direct sound, right?
Like that.
We're going to have this.
Direct sound pointer and we are going to pass it, the address of that
pointer and it's going to fill in the address assuming it was
successful.
Then it's going to return this H result.
And because of the way they decided to do this in DirectX.
You have to use this macro this Mac.
Succeeded to see whether the thing actually worked.
It's absolutely ludicrous.
It makes no sense whatsoever.
They were just making things worse as they went.
But that's that's what happened.
And you can actually see what it is here in the actual things.
I think it should be defined.
All those probably actually defined outside of here.
I don't know where I don't know how to actually show you where, it's
too fine because it's it's going to be up in some kind of other API
definition, but basically, all it's doing, is it's checking the return
code of this for a specific value.
Like the kind that we were doing before when we said we had to check
for for that device.
Not connected kind of a thing, this sort of a thing and error success.
Remember that it's doing that kind of just it's doing that kind of
check basically, but I think they managed to make it even more
complicated than that.
Perhaps.
Potentially, if you're curious go go look it up.
Do a grep in the files.
But basically that's all it's doing is figuring out where the direct
sound create call actually worked or not.
So assuming that we actually do get one back.
We gotta set the Co-operative level and so set cooperatively.
We can also guess get right out of here, set Cooperative level.
So there it is.
This is the methods.
In fact, you can see here.
This is the interface.
This is the, I direct sound interface.
Actually, that's it right there.
So actually, that's interesting.
I wonder if this is it.
Does this actually compile properly?
No, it doesn't.
So, what is the actual?
What is the actual?
Let's take a look here, type that we should be using it.
Just I direct sound, I direct sound.
And eight I'm not entirely certain level P.
Direct sound is any direct sound.
But what is this actually defined to be is this just always defined to
be 8.
Hmm?
I'm just trying to figure out which type of object, we're defining
here.
So there's an eye direct sound, and then there's a, yeah, I'm not
certain.
I am not certain about that.
Hmm.
So I guess we'll just use their actual definition.
I'm trying to decide what would be basically.
What I want to know here is what's the most proper way to actually do
this.
LP direct sound is a pointer to a direct sound but I was wondering
what direct sound is to find 2.2 exactly.
If it's if it's designed to point to a specific one.
Or if it's design.
Yeah, I was a little hazy on that like it's been a long time since
I've heard anything like this.
We should be fine because we don't actually call anything specific.
We're just calling the very generic directsound stuff.
So I guess the probably the best thing to do is just to use the type
that they originally defined, which is LP direct sound, which is just
saying a pointer to a direct sound object and we're passing address to
that.
And if the header happens to Define that to only be eight, that should
be fine for our purposes because eight ships on Windows XP, I believe.
So we should be good to go with everything.
I don't know if we need for some reason, directsound 7, but I'm not
sure.
It's something we'll check.
So maybe we'll slap it to do in here and say double check.
That this works on XP directsound 847 because we're not actually sure.
And I think it you know, we're going to want to actually test it.
So it will no conjecture is not going to is not going to
For a lot of these things Windows compatibility is always a lot of
fun.
All right.
So anyway, if we're going to go do the we don't do that.
We need to do the set.
The compatibility mode thing that I think set Cooperative level.
So set Cooperative level.
I don't think there's anything special that we have to say.
We're just going to set the normal level, but I think you have to do
it.
If I remember correctly.
I don't I don't know if that's actually true anymore.
But I'm pretty sure you have to actually say this and say which one
you're going to do.
And so we don't actually need anything in particular.
Oh, you know, okay so we actually
Do so if you look here normal is what I was saying.
Oh, maybe we just do normal, but I don't think we actually do that.
What we want to do is do priority probably so that we can actually set
the sound output format to be equal to the format that all of our
sounds are in.
Like I said, we want to do 48 khz probably and we want to do like
stereo 48 khz up like that.
So we want to be able to set the sound card to be outputting in that.
Now in the old days, that matter don't know if that matters so much
anymore because it may be that all the stuff just goes to the colonel
mixer.
Anyway, and they all get smudged and all that stuff is fine, but
We're at least going to do it in a way.
That was correct at the time.
So we're going to go ahead and pass.
We're going to go ahead and pass that priority as well.
So as you can see here, like I was saying there's actually a
Oops, that was not the right thing to copy its the window.
So we're going to need the window handle here.
If you remember, I was saying, we actually need to to have a window up
before we do the things that we want to do.
So, that's exactly why, right?
We've got to tell it what window handle we are so that when we tell it
we want priority, I guess it ties That to the window had also that
when our window is active I'm assuming basically what it does is when
our window is active.
It'll make sure that the sound card is playing in that format and so
on.
So we're going to do that.
I don't think we're going to actually check that return code.
Because honestly, if they're if it can't set it, there's not really
much we're going to be able to do about it.
So what we could do is we could go here and say and say, you know, if
it didn't succeed, if it didn't do it, succeeded thing then.
Well, our guests will do if it succeeded in else, will put a
diagnostic here.
Just so we can say, oh, hey, by the way, we weren't able to set the
the buffer format, but we're still going to continue with the rest of
the stuff we were going to do.
So if we want to set the buffer format, I think that's where we have
to do this primary buffer thing.
So I'm going to go read the docs here because
I said, don't remember this stuff that well, but but yeah, so we're
going to, we're going to take a look at how you actually do the creep
over here.
Let's sink this.
I'm assuming we can sink this for, I direct sound correct, sound 8,
and we should be able to get all the calls that we actually have to
call.
So, basically, I think what I want is just create sound buffer here.
I think that's all we really need.
And that's basically another one of these kind of semis.
Eric calls.
It's going to pass a buffer description.
It's going to give us back.
It's exactly analogous to this call right here.
We pass it in a pointer and I'm not sure if I need to create the
primary buffer if we can't set the format.
So I'm gonna do it in here for now, but then we'll take a look so
base.
So we're going to try and create this buffer.
We're going to have a pointer to a direct.
By far, this is the primary buffer.
We're going to pass that in and it's going to give us back the pointer
again.
We don't need that Unk outer.
That's calm, more of that calm nonsense.
We don't actually need but we probably do need the buffer description.
That's something that we actually do need to do.
So we're going to have to Define this buffer description here and
we're going to have to give that a bunch of attention because I think
it's got a number of members in it.
So assuming that that we can create this and I believe this is another
succeeded if I'm not very much an error then we'll be able to set its
Or Matt.
So in the DS, buffer desk structure, it's got a few things.
It's got the size.
So Prime about 4.3, but every size and the size is basically just
equal to.
Well.
You know what?
When I do it in here, that's the wrong place.
I'm probably going to use a little trickier, I think so, I think if
I'm not very much mistaken, let's take a look.
I think they often tell you, you got a zero these things before you
actually use them.
I'm not sure if that's true.
But I feel like they often.
Do yes application?
No.
Well.
No, that's not it.
Let's see.
Let's see here.
I'm gonna, I'm gonna look at them, the web at large.
So let's take a look at create sound buffer and zero struct.
I feel like or whatever, zero memory.
I think it's called take a look here.
I believe that this is the convention that you always have to actually
do.
Yeah, it does so.
So I don't know why they didn't say this in the Docks, but they almost
always force you to do this.
They force you to clear the thing, 20 before you actually pass it.
They always say to do this and they do it in all their docks.
I don't actually really know why I think it's so that if they extend
the structure later, your code won't break.
You'll be able to recompile it and it'll just work and clear the extra
things, 20.
I'm not really sure.
But basically, I'm going to cheat and do a little shorthand here.
Since the sides is the first member always of the structure.
I'm just going to go ahead and do this because basically what that'll
do is, that'll stick the size of the thing in there, and then it'll
clear the rest of
20 off we go.
Lovely, isn't it?
Kind of a bit weird but might as well do it.
All right.
So then we got the flags.
Let's see if there's any flags that.
We think we need to set in here.
Let's see.
3D.
We don't need frequency control.
We don't actually need effects processing.
We don't need, we don't need pan.
We don't need volume.
We don't need position notification.
We don't need Global Focus.
Let's see.
See, no not.
Well, I mean, I don't know.
Do we want Global Focus.
We want the thing to keep playing, probably not.
I don't really know.
We'll get think about that one.
I'll put it to do in there to take a look at that one.
I don't actually know.
I don't recall ever using that one, but maybe I did, I'm not sure.
See if we want that one lakh, defer to her resource that plate, the
buffer can be assigned to her, or when this is called.
I'm not sure about that one.
We don't care about these whether their Hardware or software.
I'm not sure why we would actually have to call those.
Primary buffer that one we do need to call because this is the primary
buffer.
So that's one of our flags, for sure.
And let's see.
We don't know whether it's on board.
Sticky Focus still audible exertion of direction of the buffers muted
true play position to return the birds.
True play position only valid in Windows Vista.
All right.
I don't know.
It's a bit of a crap shoot here with these flags.
We may have to play around with a little bit.
Not a lot of great documentation there.
Anyway, the size of the buffer, invites, again, pretty straightforward
that is again, like I kind of explained in the in the diagram that was
Extremely slowly, because of gimp.
Basically, what I want to do here is I want to allocate about two
seconds worth of audio.
So what I'll do just to be a little bit more flexible is whoever
actually calls this can decide what that's going to be.
Now.
My only question though is I don't know whether I need to do it on the
primary, but for the secondary buffer, I think you want to do that in
the secondary buffer.
So I think the primary buffer is actually going to be set to 0 would
be my guess.
Let's double check that and see if
If that's actually true for the primary buffer, okay, the deerflies
member contains the same Flags used by the buff.
For the only difference is I just got structure blah, blah, blah,
according to location of the buffer.
These flags are optional used to force the either Hardware.
Okay.
Yeah, so we don't, we don't need any of those things.
What about this guy here?
What does this guy say when creating private option at the buffer, B
member 20?
Okay.
That's what I wanted confirmation on.
So, basically, on this guy that's still going to be 0.
That's going to be something that later when we create our secondary
buffer.
The secondary buffer will set this equal to the the buffer size
basically.
So we're going to pass that in someone else can tell us what our
buffer size is.
So basically, we don't have to worry about that at all.
So in the buffer desk back here on the buffer desk, let's take a look.
We have a reserved, a format, an address of a waveform, a TX for
specifying, the format for the buffer, this buffer must this.
Okay?
Must be null for
Re buffers.
Alright, so again all know so it looks kind of like basically.
The only thing we're setting here is the size and the primary buffer
caps.
That's a bit odd.
I don't know.
I'm also thinking maybe I want to do this.
This is not how I normally do it, but I'm thinking maybe I want to do
it like this just to be a little more careful.
Just because that way if they move the Dow size for a someday, we'll
be in good shape for that as well.
If I just stick it in here, then maybe they could rearrange the
struct.
I don't think they ever would but just in case they do, maybe it's a
bad.
Habit show people.
So let's just leave that like that.
Okay, so I think that's all we actually needed to fill out according
to documentation, seems a little sparse.
But who knows?
I guess we can see whether we got it or not.
Again, we're only creating this primary buffer so that we can set the
format on it.
Once we actually create it.
I believe we can call.
The function.
There's a literally a function called set format and it's on the
actual buffer.
So when we get back this buffer, which is me, I think there's just a
call that allows us to set the format that it is playing in.
That's get format.
That is set format.
There we go.
And so if I want to call set format, there's the primary buffer will
call set format on waveform at X is the thing that it wants.
So we got to fill this out here.
So there we go.
Wait for Matty.
X waveform at that.
Again.
We're going to go ahead and utilize that to zero because that seems to
be what they want us to do to everything.
Can't hurt.
This is not performance code at all clearing things.
20 can only help us avoid bugs.
So you might as well do it when you don't care about the Cycles.
So there we go, and then we will call set format with that.
And, and there we go.
Alright, so w format tag, that is the format, basically.
Only support one.
It looks like for our purposes, which is the PCM format there, which
is basically just the straight.
Straight ahead.
Audio one or two channel PCM.
That's what we've got.
I assume that's true.
I assume.
That's what we're going to go with for now.
Again, like I said, it's going to be rough with audio so many things
to set for such a simple thing channels.
I think we want stereo sound at the very least.
We want to play our music and stereo, but we're probably also one or
sound effects to kind of maybe
A little bit that sort of thing samples per second again.
We're going to let that be passed in probably just in case it wants to
be configurable.
No sense and enforcing that when we can make it parametric just in
case we want to change it average, B for second.
That seems like it's just going to be however, big.
Yeah, however, big, the buffer is in that many in.
However, May samples per second times.
The number of seconds seems like that would be well in times the size
of the thing.
So, let's take a look at your B.
Let's finish this out bits per sample is the number equal to 8 or 16.
So, basically per sample, we can decide whether we want 8-bit audio or
16 bit audio, and we're going to use 16-bit audio and that's what a CD
is, Right.
Everything is
16 bits in audio and we'll kind of I don't really want to get too much
into How Sound is recorded yet because we're going to talk about that
when we actually write our mixer which is where we're going to be
dealing with sound samples, a lot more.
So, suffice to say, just like a CD, we're going to use 16-bit audio.
Not 8-bit audio because why not might as well get the extra
resolution, it'll sound nicer.
The block of alignment is the Minnetonka of data for the W format, tag
format type block might equal to the product of n channels, and bits
per sample, divided by 8.
So it's basically just the number of channels.
We have per sample, right?
Which is to left and right channels per sample.
They're kind of packed in there times, the bits per sample.
So that is how many bits there are four a
But one for each channel, so be 32 bits and then we're going to divide
basically by the number of bits in a byte.
So that's the that's the calculation it wants to do.
So just to be more explicit about that.
Basically what we're doing is we're creating some memory and we're
going to write samples into it.
We're going to write in 16 samples in 16-bit samples for our audio and
those samples are basically the wave form their how high the waveform
is at that point of the sound, right?
So just like it's basically we're making a little graph of the
waveform.
And so basically we're going to write in 16, so we're going to write
them in like
Left right, left, right left, right like interleaved like that.
We're not going to have two separate buffers.
Once the Left Channel, 14 the right channel.
It looks like we're just going to, you know, there's nothing wrong
with that as well.
But looks like, this is the way they want to specify in here.
So this way, we're going to do it.
So, basically, what they're doing is, they're basically asking us to
do the computation of how many bytes per sample there are, and the
number of bytes per sample is the number of bit.
I'm sorry how many bytes per single unit,
Of the channel, so including the left and the right.
So basically in this thing where we were like, left right, left, right
left, right?
They wanted us to say, how big is this in B, right?
And so, if this one's 16 bits in this one's 16 bits, you add those
together, you get 32 bits, and then they want it in B, so we got
divided by eight, right, which is going to basically be equal to 4.
So all that is going to boil down to 4.
Then what they want to do is they want the end block aligned times the
samples per second for the average bytes per second, right?
However, many samples per second.
There are times basically the size of one whole sample.
Yeah, although the other thing about that is they're kind of mixing
words there if that's actually true.
Because if they're calling a sample in here, they're saying there's a
16 bits per sample, but really, they mean, 16 bits per half, a sample
in that sense because they're only talking about half the channel, but
I'm pretty sure what they definitely set it.
At least of the documentation.
They said, n channels and bits per sample, divided by 8.
So that's, that's kind of missing the words.
They're in some
Sense, I would think I don't know about that.
I don't know about that.
It's a little bit hazy.
I don't love it.
I don't love it people, but that's the documentation.
Say, we have no extra information at appended to the end of this.
We don't have an extension ratings for get rid of that.
So basically, we have one problem, if we fill out the structure and
Order, of course, Microsoft do us the favor of basically making a bug
if we actually fill out the sample the
Structure in the order that they told us to fill it out in.
Well, we've got a problem.
We're referencing block aligned before we actually write it.
So we got to flip that around in order to make it.
So that block lines actually filled out.
By the time, we actually need it to compute the average bytes per
second.
Okay.
So then we're going to set the format there.
We're going to set the format on the primary buffer and I believe that
that's all we actually have to call is just that give it the pointer
and that's going to do succeeded as well.
So there we go.
We're going to basically have
Diagnostics.
Here.
Because there's so many things that could fail.
That is one of the things that you absolutely don't want in.
Apis is tons and tons of failure points, but Microsoft has that in
Spades, unfortunately, and we are left to deal with it.
Basically, every game programmers left to deal with it.
What can you do?
Okay, so, in here, now, we have finally set the format's of the
primary buffer.
So that's a good thing, and we will be leaving that, and then we are
going
NG to and I should actually put in the comment.
That was said we're going to do that is up here, create the primary
buffer then we are going to go ahead and create the secondary buffer
which is the buffer will actually play in.
So really again, the only reason for all of this stuff was literally
just to make it so that we could set that format of.
So that wouldn't be doing any upsampling or down sampling.
Now again, I think the colonel makes her just does that stuff
nowadays?
So I'm not sure that's actually helping on anything other than older
machines.
It's probably not actually.
Doing much on newer machines, but what can you do?
All right, so to create the secondary buffer, it's the exact same
thing.
Nothing, particularly odd.
I think.
Since we basically want the exact same format in both cases.
I'm going to go ahead and promote this guy basically, out to here so
that we actually have the same thing when we go to create this buffer.
Now, I don't know.
The other thing that I'm wondering is, if you can just duplicate the
primary buffer because you'll notice there was actually a
Duplication call here that basically basically allows you to say, hey,
I want a copy duplicate sound buffer.
So I think we might actually just be able to call that.
Let's take a look.
What does it say?
The two pockets on both.
America's a new secondary bar, that shares, the original buffers
memory now, right?
So that we can't do.
That's no good.
That is not useful.
All right, so we're just going to have to create a new.
It looks like.
That's not a problem.
It just means we're going to have to use a different buffer
description here.
So, here in the second.
Buffer, we're going to have to pass different buffer description, that
buffer description will presume.
We have more things filled out in it.
So then we're going to go ahead and, and go ahead and pass that, get
that going to the succeeded.
Oops.
It's no good to the succeeded and then the set format.
Well, we want to set format this time because I think we can just pass
it in the buffer description because remember the reason we didn't do
that before was basically just that we don't, you think.
Just that we couldn't actually say to the primary buffer, that we
actually wanted it that we had to use the set format call.
It's just the way it was defined for no, no apparent reason.
All right, so in here, if we can create our sound buffer, I'm going to
actually start it playing as well, which will be kind of amusing.
It'll just be complete silence because we'll probably clear the memory
as well.
Oh, no, you know what?
We won't have locked it yet.
So we'll probably want to do will probably actually want to have a
second call to start it playing.
So I'm actually not going to do that.
I'm going to hold off of starting playing.
I'm going to put that somewhere else.
So I'm gonna go here and just finish our secondary buffer description.
I'm going to take a look at that buffer desk again and see which
values we want in the secondary buffer because obviously, there's a
bunch up.
That's, that's not it at all.
Buffer desk.
Why are you nuts?
Why are you not getting found buffer desk?
Where are you?
You are not there.
All right.
Well, that's fine.
I'll just look at create sound buffer and then we'll get
Get off of that because that's easy enough to do.
Alright, so here we go.
DS, buffer desk.
No, that's why, because I've named it wrong.
I, that was my fault.
That was entirely my fault.
Those should be DS, buffer, desk.
Looks like looks like to me.
Okay.
So basically what I'm going to do here is I'm just going to double
check to see what values we need because we are not the primary
buffer.
So we have to set the flags.
Get this is the size and the wave format.
So it looks like
Yeah, see what I said.
I knew we wouldn't quite get it all done today.
We're pretty close, though.
We'll probably get it done tomorrow.
Depending on whether we hit some bugs or not.
You never know when those bugs will happen.
All right, so we got a buffer description in there.
And basically we just gotta set these flags to something.
That's useful.
That seems like the primary thing that we're going to have to do.
So the Caps, let's see in the flags.
We don't want 3D or frequency.
We didn't want any of these things.
We didn't want any of that.
We don't curb Global Focus.
Maybe, I don't know if we want a global Focus or not.
We still don't know, lock Taffer.
Don't need any of that stuff.
Static don't know if we want any of that sticky Focus that we I don't
know that we want any of these.
It doesn't really look like anything we care about but freeze the new
behaviors.
Like her sir in the first version direct sound up liquor.
So it's significantly ahead of the actual playing sound on emulated
sound cards is directly behind the right cursor.
Now if
Flag is Justified.
We don't care because we really only need that right cursor.
Probably.
Yeah.
All right.
Well, I don't know, we could take think about about using that for
potentially some accuracy purposes.
So we'll just drop that in there.
But it looks like we don't really need much in the way of flags.
We might not need anything.
So, let's take a look.
All right, so create sound buffer up.
I just forgot that's actually off of the direct sound object.
That's that's a, that's a method call.
So we got to call it off of there.
DS buffer desk, let's see cannot convert it to oh, that's great.
That's not the right thing.
I meant waveform at.
There we go.
Again.
Static typing catches, a lot of bugs for you.
We have to pass the window handle here.
And then it's the that is not what I wanted to do.
We don't have an h-file for that yet.
Then I want to go double check.
Let's see.
What is that went through to in it direct D sound.
I want to pass a samples per second, which we said for now will be
48,000 and the buffer size which
We'll also be, let's see that times the size of an inch 16 times 2, so
we'll just we'll just ask for that.
Now, we'll kind of deal with how we want to do audio, start up farther
in the future when we actually know what's going on.
But there we go.
Will actually try the in it.
And, and before the before our time is up, we can at least run it and
see if we crash a horrible death.
See if any of these calls actually work.
And so, will kind of know what, what kind of shape are in for
tomorrow.
Well, we got the library.
That was good.
We got a candle directs and create.
It.
Looks like we actually got the direct sound create as well.
The Co-operative mode was set properly, we succeeded in creating the
primary buffer.
Well, I should have put something in here so we could actually see if
that succeeded.
Unfortunately, we may be out of register now, so I don't even know but
fill this out and that one.
All right, so the only thing I'm going to do just before we before we
run out of time completely.
We only have about three minutes left side.
It's going to print out a diagnostic directly to debug just to see
50s actually worked.
So output, debug string, a primary buffer format was set.
And then here also, we will say secondary buffer, created successfully
spelling.
All right.
There we go.
And let's see how we did if those both actually worked.
Let's take a look here.
No, I do not see, I do not see anything there.
Ladies and gentlemen, I don't know about you.
I did not see anything.
So that does not fill me with confidence.
We may have still went so well, they're at first, didn't actually
work.
All right, let's take a look here.
So we went in here, that's exceeded that succeeded, but that did not.
Succeed.
So, set format did not actually succeed and maybe I'm totally wrong.
That you can even do that and that did not succeed either.
So we were unable to create that buffer format.
So we still have some problems.
Basically, what I'm going to go ahead and do then, is I'm going to
print out what the error code is just so we can see it.
And then again, like I said, well kind of know what shape were in.
I'm sure we just have a couple things set wrong.
There was a lot of stuff we had to fill out.
So as you can imagine there's there's a lot of accidental things.
We probably set wrong.
Maybe some of you even caught them on the stream and in which case,
it'll be easier for us to debug later.
But basically, if you didn't, it's okay, we will be debugging it
tomorrow.
And I think we will have plenty of time to make that work.
So I'm just going to pull this out here so we can actually give me see
what those error messages are again.
So that we will maybe give us a little bit of a hint as to what we did
wrong among the Myriad of things.
We might have done.
Yeah, so, that fails.
So basically looking at that.
Oops,
It's no good looking at that error code.
What is that error code?
The error code is invalid.
Argh one or more out.
Comments are invalid.
All right, great.
That's awfully specific.
That doesn't really help us at all.
How much you want to bet.
The next one is the same and it is.
So basically, all we know is we filled out something in this
structures incorrectly.
That's about all we get.
And we're not going to have a lot more to go on now.
Hopefully, it's just something real simple.
So, you know, again, like I said, it's been a long time since I've
done this.
I will go like double check my own code.
It's probably just something really simple, so we should have no
problem getting
Sound up and running tomorrow.
That's the good news because this is basically all the work there was
once we get this loading properly, then you can go ahead and use the
lock command to just write the sound buffer and sound will play.
And that's, that's most of it right there.
Again.
Not a great API, it is true.
But the thing I want to keep emphasizing is meant, you know, it's that
many lines of code, you know, a lot of people, they always say it's so
complicated.
And why would you write it yourself?
But at the same time, it's like man.
How long does it take to just write that function?
I mean, that is just not that long.
We'll have it to bugged and running by tomorrow.
And you know, I don't know if I wasn't explaining things on the
stream.
For example, how much a time investing, is that 30 minutes an hour?
You got to debug it the first time, maybe.
So maybe figure, even even a day, but then you've got
Forever.
You never have to use 8,000 different libraries and all that sort of
stuff.
So, there's just, you know, I just want people to understand I guess
and I try to keep hammering home.
Well, there's while it's always fine to use engines and libraries and
you should do, whatever makes you the most efficient when you're
programming.
I also think that people need to be more realistic about actually how
little work there is in doing some of these things.
You don't really need to be that afraid of writing your own platform
code.
It's a couple of weeks of work per platform, a lot of times.
It's really just not that big a deal and once you do it once,
Once you're in a very good position to maintain that going forwards,
you know, sometimes they'll come along and they'll do something like
Windows 8, that really screws you up, but a lot of times it's fine,
and you can just keep on rolling and nobody plays games on Windows 8
anyway, so you didn't have to care when stuff like, that happens lot
of time.
So that's a benefit as well.
So anyway, that is it for handmade hero today.
We are going to do some Q&A now, that is all the code that we will
have time to, to get in there.
But I think it went pretty well.
There wasn't a lot of confusion there.
And actually we had very few errors.
In the actual class.
I think we'll be able to bug them really quickly tomorrow.
So be sure to join us again.
Tomorrow is going to be since today was was Tuesday.
Tomorrow is Wednesday, Thursday, Friday are basically the Thanksgiving
holiday here in in the United States.
So, we are going to be streaming at 11 a.m.
For the next three days.
There's got to be a morning stream.
So hopefully some people in some other time zones can catch up with
using our holiday hours.
They can actually come to the live stream, which is, you know, if this
was airing in the middle, the night where you are you couldn't you
didn't have the
That so hopefully we'll see some new faces to a little bit in the
morning stream.
And the other thing that I wanted to point out is that we should have
hopefully sometime soon at handmade hero dot-org.
If you go there, obviously, you can still do the standard stuff.
If you want to get that the source code you can pre-order.
If you want to get to like the Twitter accounts or that any of the
stuff, quick links are.
All right here, but soon very soon.
Hopefully, maybe later tonight, maybe tomorrow, this email a question
button.
Should hopefully turn into a forums button.
We are trying to get that working.
We are wrangling some some ornery Joomla and other nonsense to get
sort of a forums, Wiki thing up and running.
It'll be a little janky but
At least they'll be a place for people to go and congregate because I
know a lot of people be asking about that and asking for places where
they could sort of store all the information and make a nice way that
it could all be linked and worked on.
So we're working on that.
Hopefully we'll have that up sometime soon.
Hopefully to buy it by tomorrow.
So thank you everyone for joining us.
And now let's take questions.
Please be sure to put at senior ettore in the question somewhere so
that I will see it because I have a little filter that only shows
those for the question for the Q&A part of things.
Let's take a look.
Oh, yes.
Okay, you guys totally caught this?
Thank you much.
Like I said, we had to rearrange these Microsoft again, did them in
exactly the wrong order.
So you're liable to make that mistake.
I don't know why we didn't get a warning.
Oh, because we initialize it to 0, I guess.
One thing that might have been smart to do was that first because if
we had done that first, even though we want to clear it to 0, it would
have told us that, that was uninitialized.
And we could have moved it up here.
So that probably would a little bit been a little bit smarter.
Come to think about it.
I don't know.
Was that was that the only bug we had?
That would be amusing?
Holy cow, dude.
That was it.
So just me.
Miss placing.
The structure thing.
That was that was it and the stream caught it.
How awesome is that?
But I tell you programming with the stream behind you is pretty
awesome.
You make a little error like that and you might have to go hunt for it
for a few minutes and be like, what happened?
And I
Depth through, and look at it like tomorrow when we step through.
I would have to go through every line looking like, oh, right.
It's wrong here.
You just go to the stream, Just Nails it.
So this again, just to underscore this when you're making an API,
don't do stuff like that.
You're just, you know, setting yourself up for failure.
You want to initialize the variables in the order.
They appear in the structure?
Don't stick variables, you know, down somewhere and then tell the user
to use them in a line that happens before that member
Just asking for bugs.
I mean, you know, help help the users out, right?
Like, you know, help them succeed.
If you can don't set them up for failure.
It's a simple bug.
It's only going to take a few minutes to fix.
It's not a huge deal.
But why would you do it?
You know, I mean, why?
Yeah, it doesn't really make much sense.
But that's pretty awesome.
Thank you stream for catching that.
It looks like now we're initialized properly.
So that's pretty awesome.
That was the only but we have that whole thing.
That was great.
Awesome.
Let's see.
Do do, do do.
Do you think data structures while making a game like linked list?
Binary trees?
Sure.
We will be using data structures all over the place, but wait till we
get there.
Let's see, trying to look at questions on the code as we did it.
What keyboard do we use Das Keyboard for?
You?
Can have to put up a fact on the keyboard.
I get so many questions about that as well as these.
There are many active risk braces.
I don't know if they still sell them.
Can you explain again?
Why you need two buffers instead of just doing everything in one?
Yeah, I can't.
Well, okay.
I can't really explain it.
I can say the words again.
But really the explanation is because Windows is weird.
That's kind of more the real answer.
but,
The explanation is because one of them is creating a buffer.
The other one is really just getting a handle to the actual sound card
in some sense.
That's really what in theory is more like happening.
So basically, this right here where we create a sound buffer, the
second quote, unquote s a bar that's actually our sound buffer.
That is the buffer into which we will actually write things.
Okay, so that's really, that's the thing that creates, the buffer.
This thing up here is a strictly optional perhaps entirely
anachronistic.
At this point thing that you used to have to do in order to make sure
that this buffer actually played out the sound card without getting
resampled.
So in the old days the sound card used to be playing at a certain
sample rate.
So basically the sound card might be set to 44.1 khz, or it might be
set to 48 khz and if
We're trying to play your sounds at 48, khz while the sound card was
set at 44.1 khz.
It would always go through a resampling, which makes it sound worse
and it's waste time right now.
A lot of that stuff isn't true anymore.
I don't even know these days.
What the typical sound chips.
Do.
I've never even seen anyone discuss it.
I'm not sure, but basically, for back in those days, so the way that
you actually told windows.
I need you to set the sound card into this.
Format that I'm going to using a place sound was to call this create
sound buffer, call a skit for the primary buffer.
So it's essentially returning you a handle, the primary output device.
Then you just call set form on it to say.
Hey, I'm setting.
The format of this primary buffer to the waveform at that.
I know I'm going to be playing that's all this buffer is.
It's not actually a sound but we're never going to touch it.
We're never going to ask it a question.
We're never going to send data at all.
It's strictly getting that handle so that we can call.
All set format.
That's it.
So really, it's the secondary buffer down here is the is
The only buffer and you'll see that's the only thing we'll ever call
tomorrow.
When we actually output some sound will just be calling lock on that
buffer writing into it and then letting go that's it.
Let's see.
What's the command to compile on your emacs configuration all t'aime?
Are there any case where we would want more than two channels for this
game?
No, because it's a 2-D game.
So I praten.
And I don't have a full-time sound guy or anything.
So we're mostly going to be having stereo sound 2-D game, but you
could imagine if you were doing a more 3D game, like a not just 3D but
immersive 3D.
So, you know, you are in the world looking around like first person or
something.
Then you may want to Output more Channel sound because for people who
have those crazy setups, like the Dolby 7.1 or 5.1 like those sorts of
things where there's much, lots of speakers all around.
You can actually output stuff to all the different speakers.
I believe.
Like so, you know, I for example, when like, when you use the mouse
sound system for like the rad game tools product for that.
They've done have a bunch of stuff in there for like, you know, oh
targeting 7.1 sound and that sort of stuff and this.
Particularly useful for a 2-D game but it could be for like immersive
game where you're trying to play sounds that are like surrounding the
user in a meaningful way so they can hear.
Oh, The Gunshot happened behind me.
I got to turn around or that sort of stuff, if that makes sense.
So you do want more than two channels sometimes for us.
We're not going to really have any data that we can actually make use
of it.
But, you know, there's there's nothing that says that too, is the
right number 7 might be the right number for, you know, for whatever
purposes or eight.
Eight.
Let's see.
Um,
if the frame rate, whatever drop can there, be audio dropouts?
Yes, so here's two things about that.
I snuck it in there and I didn't really just describe it.
Let's go back to.
Well.
I can't cuz I close the Gimp diagram.
So you remember, when I draw the awful, give diagram that, hopefully
I'll fix.
Well, I don't know how we're going to do it maybe after the stream and
today we'll just leave the stream on and I'll play with the settings
will start stream stops to start the shooting stops until we actually
figure out how to get drawing properly.
But basically, the reason I was saying we're going to make a big
buffer, you know, as I said, a big buffer.
I said two seconds.
Well, why would you want the buffer to be two seconds?
Doesn't make any sense, right?
Well, the reason is because audio dropouts, there's two ways that you
can kind of approach them.
Right?
One way you can approach them is writing way ahead of where the game
is.
But then you've got a lot of latency or you've got a lot of over
writing that's going to happen.
One of the other.
The other thing you can do is set yourself up so that in general, you
only write maybe one additional frame ahead.
So if you miss one frame, you're fine, but if you missed a lot, you'd,
you know, you'd skip.
But instead of it doing what normally happens.
Where is the audio dropout, that you here, where you hear the like,
it's going like that.
Then it hit that that, like, that, that thing that you can really hear
that it when it Loops really quickly.
Lee.
That's because they had too narrow of a buffer.
So it was playing the same like 800 samples or 600 samples over and
over again, which is immediately audible to the ear as a bad sound.
You're like, oh it dropped out.
If you have a two second buffer, you can actually just full-on, stop
sending samples.
And the stuff that's in the buffer, is whatever happened for the past
two seconds, and you'll get a little bit.
You can sometimes notice if there was like a big thing, like a
splosion happening or something that happened right there.
Maybe you'll hear.
Jump in suddenly, but you won't actually hear any objection or things.
It'll actually stay smooth and just sound like you were still playing
from before until you come back.
And so one of the things that I found is very effective.
He's always have a giant buffer because then even if your game gets
just hammered for some reason, there's a disasterous, the CD-ROM drive
opens and windows halt, your process, and whatever else you'll still
actually be fine.
It'll sound fine.
It can play Forever on that to Second buffer on there will only be one
skip point and it won't really be
At noticeable, so it's just a little trick and something that we did.
You'll see it later.
Let's see.
The real silliness is a 10-block a line in average by per second or
redundant.
Yes.
That is true info.
That's John.
Hello.
John, John says the end block, aligning and average b/s are redundant.
And that is true.
Basically, you know it, you have to kind of Wonder a little bit.
If this is something that the documentation basically told you to
compute, why don't they just compute it themselves?
And I don't know.
That's a good question.
I assume that it is there primarily because they wanted to support
extended sound formats where this wouldn't necessarily be true.
But again, maybe they should just let us.
They should just let us pass zero in that case.
Maybe they do but it wasn't documented.
So they can just let us pass zero.
And then we wouldn't have to do all this Ridiculousness, to be honest.
This like I don't even know why this is here.
I mean, it knows the channels.
It knows the bits per sample.
It's none of this stuff should have to be filled out.
You should be able to set it all 20, so I don't know.
Maybe you can maybe you can't but that's just dumb.
Well, we kind of know you can't because we accidentally sent 120 and
it didn't work.
So it should have just let us do that.
It is just dumb and John is correct.
Let's see.
Let's see on Linux will be doing.
Sir, or higher level like pulseaudio Jack.
So I don't know probably just all set because that works on the most
platforms.
And all we need is one output stream, but we'll see when we get there.
I'm not a line X Linux platform expert.
So probably I will consult some Linux platform experts and I will get
their opinion, and we'll just have to go with that because I am not
shipped games on Linux.
I mostly have running on Linux for my own development purposes.
That's why I usually run on Linux.
And so I feel like my
My ability to really judge that would not be that good.
So I will probably defer to some people who have had a lot of
experience with that.
I'll probably ask some of the valve guys who did steam Linux who are
friends of mine to basically, you know, give me what's going to be the
steam the what's going to be the same length path.
That's probably what we'll do on Linux in the hopes that that sort of
initiative will kind of get some momentum next year and maybe get some
more links gaining gaming happening.
That be my preference, just do whatever steam Linux wants done.
What newer?
Assad API would you recommend a set of old direct sound?
I don't know.
I still direct sound is totally fine for my purposes.
I like to do all my sound mixing myself.
I don't know.
So, I I've heard people say x audios the thing that people use now,
but I don't know.
Yeah, I feel like feel like X audios, probably it but I'm not sure.
I don't do any programming in the newer sound API.
So I'm not really in a position to say whether they're good or bad
ideas.
It may be that they're just more work than to do.
And why bother.
But it may be that you get better latency and that sort of stuff and
then it's worth it.
I'm not sure.
Let's see.
What is a?
The two second buffer doesn't sound acceptable.
Not know.
So if you're playing music, I found that it did I found that was very
most people did not notice at least on Sushi.
It worked pretty well.
It's not again.
It's not what you want to have happen.
Like you wouldn't choose to have your audio dropout ever, but compared
to the repeating sound which is Harsh and awful.
It's much better to have it do this way, and I found that it was
actually very difficult, especially while they're playing in that
thing's super close attention to things necessarily.
Let's see.
Have or do you work in the industry?
Yes, I do.
Work in the industry.
I've worked in the industry since I was nine since I was see, 1995.
So since I was 18, and I've been in the game history ever since.
Don't know that I necessarily recommend it.
But but I was let's see to do how I thought about guess programmers
tagging to teach things like Linux or whatever topics their expertise.
I
I have thought about that and I do like that idea.
The only problem is, I don't know how practical it actually is at the
very, very least.
We will certainly get expert opinions on things as much as I can for
areas where I would prefer someone who's more experienced at it.
At that particular thing.
We will certainly get that before we do whatever we're going to do
whether or not someone else will actually stream.
I don't know.
But but, you know, definitely something about
Let's see.
I think that is it.
So there's one other thing.
I want to talk about that.
I've got good at the beginning of the stream.
Since there doesn't seem to be any more questions.
I'm going to go ahead and actually look here at the thing that I
wanted to double-check.
So someone pointed out that this mem commit here in the virtual Alec.
Someone pointed out that this actually probably should be both a
reserve and the commit.
So if you pass mem commit to Virtual, Alec will reserve and commit the
memory for you at the same time, but technically apparently, that's
not really correct.
Like it does it and it works.
But you're technically supposed to do Reserve as well.
And apparently, there is a post by Raymond Chen that said that this
was the thing.
And so if Raymond Chen says it, it's
Probably true.
I mean, the dude knows Windows better than probably anybody else in
the world.
So I'm going to say that's probably true.
So we probably want to do that.
If that is the more correct way.
Like I said, it doesn't actually change the behavior as far as I know,
but it's worth noting that that is probably a little more correct than
just saying them commit and having Windows do the right thing.
Anyway, I thought you only had to pass commit, but I guess you
actually more technically should tell it to do reserve it commits,
explicitly.
Okay, so just something to think about.
That was basically a question from the previous stream and someone
wrote in.
And it was basically saying, I don't think so.
And here's a Raymond Chen thing, and if Raymond Chen says it, it's
probably right.
So, I would stick with that.
Like I said, don't think it'll actually make a difference, but just
you might as well be more correct.
If you can be just in case there's some edge cases where it actually
does matter.
Let's see.
Looking through here.
Why wouldn't you recommend game programming as a career field?
I'm not saying I wouldn't recommend it as a career field.
I'm just saying, you know, it's like anything else.
It has its pluses and minuses.
I do like a lot of aspects of game development.
But at the same time it makes you a lot.
Less able to play and enjoy games like anything else.
The more you see how something is made and the more you become
critical of various aspects of it the harder time.
You have enjoying a game.
I mean if I think about the games that
Enjoyed when I was 16.
And I think about how much I would say that they sucked today.
I think a lot of that has to do with having been in the industry and
thinking, critically about games for a long time, and their
implementation and all this other sort of stuff.
I feel like that's just something that happens when you get into it.
So, if you're someone who really enjoys games, the answer is not
always.
Well, if I really enjoy games, I should go make them.
That's not necessarily always true.
Right?
I mean, if you really enjoy chocolate, it doesn't mean you should be a
chocolatier.
You
it just be someone who really likes chocolate and you should go, do
whatever you find that you enjoy doing for money and then buy
chocolate.
But you know, like I said, it depends if you really like technical
things like what I'm doing here and you like the sorts of things that
we're doing on the stream, then you probably would like game growing
quite a bit and then you should be in the game industry.
And if you like this sort of things we're doing in the Stream, you'll
probably very good at it because these are the sorts of things that
basically, only detail-oriented people are going to like, and people
who enjoy,
Electoral curiosity.
Only those sorts of people are going to like the things that we're
doing on the Stream.
So if you find yourself gravitating toward it and thinking it's cool.
If you thought it was cool, that we drew our own buffer before you are
probably someone, who would enjoy a game programming.
It's one of the few programming Fields left where people actually care
about that sort of stuff.
And we're actually does make a difference in the quality of the game.
If you know how to do Advanced things and get better performance and
so on, you will be very valuable to an engine team somewhere.
If you know these sorts of things and that is not true in a lot of
other disciplines.
Open to other disciplines are very lacks, in terms of performance.
A very lacks in terms of resource consumption now compared to games
and truth be told the reason that it's that way in games.
It just because games have to perform at 30 or 60 frames a second.
They can't be latched those things.
They have to fit in limited memory on consoles.
They have to do these things and since they have to they do and so
that's just the way it goes.
Let's see.
Will we show how to use bone animations or will we use Sprite sheets,
so bone animations and Sprite seats are not mutually exclusive that.
That is a slight that is that is that is a question that presupposes,
an answer that isn't actually necessary.
You can have a Sprite sheet that has a bunch of pictures on it.
And then you can assign bones to those things that will manipulate the
Sprites in the spreadsheet.
If you mean, will we use bones to animate things?
Other than strictly using direct copies.
I have not 100% decided yet.
We will probably support some sort of bending, depending on how we end
up doing the renderer.
It's really a about the renderer there, whether or not we support
that.
So it's it remains to be seen, but we the answer is probably going to
be yes.
Willie preload, all the audio files are stream from disk.
We will stream from disk.
Do I count between taking drinks?
That seems to be on a certain timing?
No, I do not.
It would be interesting if it was a time.
You just when I get thirsty.
speaking of which,
Is there a name to the double buffer technique?
I still don't understand the concept and want to do further reading
the double buffer technique.
Are you talking about the primary secondary buffer thing?
If so, I just want to emphasize again.
It is not double buffering.
We are not creating two buffers.
All this buffer call is doing is getting a handle to the primary sound
device so that we can set its format which puts the sound card into a
mode that allows it to play in the format.
We want.
That's it.
This is
Not a buffer, not a buffer do not think of this as a buffer, think it
was like a handle to the sound card.
It's purely old in.
Can't have stuff that we're doing here.
Just telling Windows.
This is the sound format.
We want to play.
That's all we're doing.
There are not two buffers.
This buffer is not really a buffer.
We will never use it as a buffer.
Let's see.
Are we going to get into concurrent programming?
Yes.
Do we think we'll use any of the kinds of metaprogramming stuff?
I do these days for this project.
Probably not.
I don't think we will have time to really get into that sort of thing.
Maybe we will a little bit but I don't know.
Let's see.
How much do optimizations matter in game programming.
Is it mainly about, making the game work or to game partner was also
worried about optimizing the game for the hardware during the
development?
Not sure, I understand the second part, but optimization matters a
ton.
Basically, like either you optimize your game or you wrote on top of
an engine, which was optimized, and does a bunch of work to optimize
for you but optimization matters a lot.
I mean, you know, try to run the original Binding of Isaac on a laptop
and the thing is like super slow, right, or whatever.
And that's an example of what happens when you build something on top
of something that
A game system that wasn't optimized to do what games do rights Flash?
Those sorts of things, you know, you get this all the time where
something is not fast enough and totally should be.
Computers are very fast these days.
They're certainly fast enough to run any 2D game.
We probably might want to write.
And so, you really do have to care about optimization in a lot of
cases.
Now, there's some code that doesn't have to be optimal.
Well, none of the cars gonna be op old.
There's some code that doesn't have to be optimized because it just
doesn't execute it enough to actually warrant it.
But a lot of the codes, certainly, the renderer
Probably some of the sound stuff in certain depending on the
circumstances and and probably some of the entity updating stuff in
physics and that sort of things depending on how many entities.
Have do need to get a do need to have some serious optimizations on
them often times.
And again, sometimes that can be the engine can help you with that.
It's not perfect.
Like, you know, a lot of times you'll actually have a situation where
scripting is taking a ton of the time in a game and the engine can't
do that much about it.
There's actually a lot of initiatives I think with unity and with
unreal like unreal just switch to compiled scripts and things like
this.
Like to actually, you know, I think they actually compile and see now
instead of having a scripting language, something like this.
I don't follow that stuff.
But point being
You do actually get in circumstances.
Where actually the game code is the problem that the higher level game
called.
It's just saying what entities do and that's our stuff actually is
causing performance problems.
So, at all levels, you kind of do have to think about that before
mites games at by their very nature are about responsiveness,
low-latency these sorts of things.
And so you just can't have piggy code sitting around because it'll
bite you sooner or later.
Why don't we use the second buffer to grab the handle instead of
create something?
Just to grab the handle.
It's because of this flag right here.
Basically Windows either returns, you a buffer, you can use, which is
what we do down here or it returns you the magical special handle the
primary buffer if you pass this, so we need to set the format on the
primary effort to tell the sound card.
What format it should play in.
So that is what this is doing is saying, hey Windows, give us back the
special secret, awesome buffer so that we can set the format on it.
It says, okay.
Here it is.
We set the format.
We're done with that buffer.
Then we say, okay now give us back a handle, do an actual buffer.
We can actually use that has nothing to do with the primary buffer.
And then that's the one we can actually write into.
There's no Rhyme or Reason to this.
It's just Legacy in some sense because basically you used to actually
write into the primary, but for the first version of direct sound you
wrote directly to the sound card.
So there only was a primary buffer and secondary buffers were for
doing things.
Like sounds that the primary buffer would use to stream in there.
There.
There was actually a little more logic to it.
It now, it's completely banana cakes.
Really?
All you should have is a call on Direct sound to set the format.
That would make a lot more sense.
So this is just kind of busted but it's still the way it works.
And I know it's a little hard to understand because it doesn't make a
lot of logical sense.
That's just the way it works.
Is there some way of figuring out how many CPU operations we have
available per frame and optimizing the game code based on that number?
Yes, and that is exactly what we will do but wait till we get there.
Let's see.
Isn't this learning how to carve Stone using a chisel over using
Modern Machinery?
No, because basically, right now, we don't have Modern Machinery.
One of the things I said in one of the other stream, someone said, why
reinvent the wheel?
My argument is we don't have any Wheels right now.
I don't think engines game engines today are very good.
I'm not trying to spare the people who work on them.
I think they probably do an excellent job for what they are trying to
do, but we just don't have the technology right now to actually write
the kinds of things that we want to write for building game.
Games, so I think we have a long way to go to actually build the
tools.
We need to make games.
So that there isn't any reason to ever do this low-level code again.
So basically what I'm trying to with this series is sort of show a new
set of programmers, how to do this low-level programming because
without more low-level programmers, doing this kind of programming, we
will never build the actual tools.
We actually need like, we are so far from being done building Modern
Machinery, as a two term you use.
Like, for example, just to just to put it in complete analogy terms to
what you said.
It's like you told me when you
up the horse and buggy that you're like, why are you teaching people
to study how to build like axles and like gearing's and stuff.
We have a horse-drawn carriage.
It's perfect.
You're like, dude, we need like airplanes.
Okay, we need race cars.
We need trains.
We need Rockets.
Like we're not anywhere near there.
So don't pick up a game engine and think you are using a rocket, you
are using a horse-drawn carriage.
And what we need to get to over time.
Is we
To get to the rocket.
We need to get to the race car.
We need to get to those things so someday.
Yes, that will be an okay mentality to have why reinvent the wheel?
Why not use Modern Machinery?
Someday?
We are nowhere near that day.
We are not even 10 years from that day.
We are like 50 years from that day, if we're lucky.
So I think it's imperative that we get a whole new generation of
programmers, working at the low level stuff so that they will be
writing their own.
Our own tools.
They were writing their own engines.
They will create the next unities.
They will create the next on reels.
They will correct.
The next Source engines and we will keep building better and better
things.
So that the people who don't know how to do this stuff, can use them.
And so that someday we can put this to rest.
Finally, and say, we pretty much got this under control.
We're done.
So that is the end of the stream.
I think that's about it.
We are at 9:30, and that is the end.
Thank you.
So,
For joining me.
Hope to see you here.
Tomorrow bright and early in the morning 11:00 a.m.
I hope some of you will be up for that and maybe we'll be getting some
people from different time zone.
So we'll see some fresh faces in here.
That'll be great.
Again, as always, you can go to handmade here.com.
If you want the source code you can pre-order.
If you want to ask question.
You can use the email a question button and hopefully that'll be for
him sometime very soon.
Obviously.
There's a Twitter feed, you could subscribe to if you want to see the
schedule.
I usually tweet several hours before the schedule and one hour before.
Oh the schedule just as notifications and you can click on the live
button, but you're already there watching on Twitch.
Presumably you can click on that like button if you want to follow on
Twitch so that you'll get email notifications when the stream goes
live.
Thank you so much for joining me.
Everybody.
It has been a pleasure as always and I will see you tomorrow morning
when we will actually start playing some sounds out of our sound
buffer.