Welcome to handmade hero.
Show, we code a complete game live on stream.
We are right in the middle of doing our cutscene sequence, so I'd like
to go into that.
We kind of stopped to cut sheets, cutscenes short of the finale
yesterday, and we want to go ahead and do those today.
So, if you are programming along at home today, stay 223.
So, if you would like to join me, please unpack day, 222 source code.
If you preorder the game on handmade hirota org unpacked a
two 22s.
That's what I'm starting with today.
Just to refresh your memory if you choose me.
Don't remember?
This is where we were at yesterday.
We basically made a series of cutscenes here and we've got them all
lined up in one file and we just kind of can pick in the code which
one we want to use.
We had a file called handmade cutscene, right?
And it's just got, you know, basically the simple little Logic for
each of our cutscenes here and we can go ahead and jump down to the
last one we did which was shot nine.
You can kind of see, it's just kind of zooming in on the little kid
who's going off to his room.
And yeah, so looking at all that I need to now make a shot 10 and a
shot 11 and that's it.
That'll be the end of it once we do that.
So I'll go ahead and paste that in here.
Shot 10 and we'll start off with only one layer of that shot.
You can kind of see that this one and again I should probably go to
what we were doing before.
Just make one one little window because, you know, we've got the Live
code editing stuff going.
I can just kind of tweak the parameters here, so I'm just going to go
ahead and load that up.
Here's can made cutscene.
So there's our first layer.
Now you can see that's kind of a sky layer, right?
So that one probably should be one of those layers.
It's like really far away or whatever in the background and let's go
ahead and move it back there.
I don't know how big we want it yet, but that's definitely going to
feature that flag where we have the scene layer flag, add infinity so
that it doesn't move at.
All right.
So just kind of stationary.
Let's go ahead and add it and how big we want that yet?
Let's go ahead and add another one.
So there it is.
I'm going to
This one, I don't know what motion the cameras going to have I suppose
is going to zoom a little bit I suspect so I'm just going to leave
that zoom in there probably it's probably not going to be that much to
me but so let's go ahead and make that happen.
All right, so let's see what we want.
The size of that to be, we presumably want this to be, maybe about 10
meters away, something like that.
Something kind of back in the distance, probably needs to be a little
larger.
Maybe not quite that large.
See
See here, maybe something like that.
I don't know.
We'll see you in a second.
Okay, so that's looking out the window and you can see that the sky is
a little bit janky there as well, so I'm going to try moving that
over.
I'd probably need to move it over quite a bit.
Several meters to line it up.
With the window, which is what we want, something like that.
And I'll have to move it up at two teeny bit as well.
Let's go ahead and get that going.
Let's see, there we are.
So that looks probably about right, I don't know, maybe not, I'm not
entirely sure what's going on there.
So we'll find out in a second when we when we kind of put some more
layers in here.
So there is a little hero, dude, standing on is little his little
You know, she's a little step stool, right?
And I'm going to go ahead and move him kind of over a little bit
because he's too far over.
See that looks more correct?
Maybe a little more Center than that, not sure.
But we'll find out in a second but otherwise that's about right?
That's pretty good.
I don't know if you actually know, I think about it.
He may need to be back a little further, so,
I'm not sure maybe he should be more like negative 5.
Oops sorry more like negative 3.
That seems pretty good.
Yeah, no, I don't really know.
So we'll drop another layer in there and we'll find out.
So here's the doors and I don't mean the band for those of you that
are into like sort of hard rock sorts of stuff, right?
So let's see here.
Let's let's get that going.
So there is the doors.
And so, what I want to do is I want to make sure those doors are kind
of
Lock blocking out.
You know that they should be big like the screen is right.
So I got a I got a size those up so that they don't ever have any
gapping, I'm going to go ahead and do the same trick that I was doing
before where I just kind of lock it to the initial shot so I can size
that properly.
So let's let's just make that get a little bigger.
There we go and so that's how that should look.
And so now the kid is obviously too small at that point.
So this is good this little sort of let me figure.
Her out how big he needs to be which is what I would like to do.
So let's make him a little larger, something like that.
That's probably a reasonable.
Maybe let's see here.
Yeah.
Something like that.
I'm not totally sure exactly what should be there but we'll see how it
looks.
Pretty good, looks pretty good so far.
Okay, so we're going to go ahead and add layer 5.
To the mix.
So this is all of his hat, his hat collection, right?
Because he spends a lot of time on Steam so he has a lot of hats but
he's purchased, you know,
Very important part adding customer value via hats.
So there we go, get those hats in there.
And those I want to size again, kind of, so that they're just about
the size of the screen.
I think something like that.
So I'm going to move those down like so.
Here we go.
And yeah.
So and then we've got one more layer to add in here.
I believe there's one more.
Yeah, and so there's that final layer so that's gotta be placed and
scaled up as well.
Let's get that in there.
I think that once entered.
So there we go and it's a little smaller than that, probably in
actuality.
I'm guessing maybe not entirely sure, not entirely sure.
But that's probably good.
Yeah, that's, that's about right.
Okay, so let's see how that looks.
Let's try and get the zoom right now.
So there's there's sort of the more Parallax bit happening.
I feel like maybe there wants to be a little more depth to that as the
zoom kind of happens.
So I feel like maybe that we're not we're just not separated enough in
terms of our sort of spatial placement of these guys.
And so I kind of feel like maybe we want this to be a more exaggerated
fall off.
So I feel like we maybe want something, you know more, wait a minute,
what's going?
They're okay.
Those are both at three.
Okay, so we want maybe like something like that.
Sort of a thing.
And I'm just trying to think about if that'll be enough of a
difference in what happens?
I feel like that will probably be enough.
Kind of hard to say.
I would like there to be a reasonable different, so maybe I really
just need to make this guy be like closer and so that because I want
there to be a lot of motion.
And, you know, at the current way that it is, it wouldn't probably be
all that much.
Let's see here.
So if this guy were even closer, so let's say this guy starts at 0.5,
right?
This guy starts at 1 and these guys are at to something like that and
then I just kind of resize them down.
To be wherever.
Let's see her to normal 20.
Let's see.
So if that's the case and I want these guys to be sized, okay, we
could cut that guy down and that's a little bit more like it.
You can cut that guy down as well and that's a little more like it and
we've got to reduce that a little bit.
Something like this might be a little too much.
There we go.
And those doors, those doors can't
No more.
So those are going to have to be a little bit more as well.
So that's maybe like that.
So let's see if that's any good.
Let's just get that go.
All right, that's feeling better to me, that's definitely feeling
better and I feel like maybe the kid, the kid in the door, just I
don't know, maybe the kid in the door should be slightly separated as
well, just slightly so instead of them both being at the same, like
maybe they're more like this.
We're like maybe the kids actually a little bit closer than the door
even I don't know.
I'm not sure.
Something like that.
Hmm, I don't know.
Like I could.
I could do it.
The problem is, of course, these will get drawn in the wrong order
which is not fabulous because I had them sorted the other way because
I was figuring it would be in front but I don't know.
I mean I could also do it the this way around.
So the doors are there in the kids further back, right?
And that's another again.
Just another way of getting depth into it.
So, I don't know, we'll see.
All right, so that's where we're at so far and I feel like that's
pretty good.
We do need to scale up the background a bit as a result.
It's not going to be enough the way it is because it's got its
actually got to go out to the bleed there.
So that's got to be a little bit.
It's got to be a little bit larger which means that this one does as
well, right?
Something like that.
So let's see.
How's that looking so far.
It feels a little bit better.
Yeah.
Yeah, I'm pretty pleased with that.
All right, so if we go ahead and just make this now, dive a little bit
more like the camera dive a little bit more reasonably towards the
kid, right?
Because we want it to sort of be zooming in on him.
He's the, the point of Interest are.
So yeah, if we kind of make it Zoom a little bit more towards him than
it's a little more reasonable now.
Unfortunately, we get that one thing that moves towards the near
clipping plane.
I don't know if you saw that, so it sort of disappears.
So we probably need to
Sure.
That's that's up a little more than it is right now, that's that
closed layer needs to make.
We need to make sure that's off the screen by the time it hits.
Because otherwise we're going to have that sort of disk discontinuous
sort of jump, right?
But otherwise I think that's looking pretty good so far.
Yeah.
Yeah, and I don't know, I think the kid may be nice to be just a
little bit larger potentially, just, it just a teats.
Oops, that's the wrong one.
There we go.
Maybe we need a little bit of upward motion.
I will look less.
All right, so I'm pretty happy with that.
That seems pretty reasonable to me.
Yeah, not really much else to say about that.
Seems pretty good.
Yeah.
It's got kind of a nice feeling of depth to it.
I think it's pretty good.
It looks like we're still may be getting a little bit too much of a
gap on that background layer.
So I'm just going to make that just a little bit bigger so just to
make sure that it doesn't bleed at all and I'm pretty happy with that.
All right.
Okay.
So now we just need our very last one, which is shot 11.
And so then we can assemble these all after we get shot 11 and we can
assemble these all into a single cutscene, which is pretty cool.
That's what we want.
And I'm going to go ahead and straighten this out again, just to get
us back to sort of a nominal level.
So, yeah, this is again, the same.
This is a, this sort of this shot is basically the same
As the opening shot, kind of a shot, it's like a layered Hillside kind
of a thing looking look at thing.
So, again, the background is going to be placed at Infinity.
So I'm just going to go ahead and again, the Z value doesn't really
matter because the things placed at Infinity but I set it at - 100
just so that we it doesn't, you know, I guess I don't really need set
at.
I don't even know why I said 900.
There was no point probably if the renderer ever sorted things by Z,
which we might
You in the future, we want them to sort properly.
So it needs to have a value that will be behind everyone else.
That's, that's really the only requirement, okay?
So let's go ahead and set up the layer 4:30 to.
So there's another one.
And I'm going to go ahead and turn off the zoom for a second just so
we can kind of lock it down.
So I'm going to go ahead and scale that back so I can see what it
looks like.
So this is just Hills with kind of like the spooky Forest light in the
back there and so I'm going to scale that up maybe a bit more like so.
And you can kind of see that's clipped off the top, which means that
this thing has to kind of be up a bit unfortunately.
Oops, not that one.
It would be nice if all these layers had were complete but some of
them are obviously.
So there's that part of it.
Next, I'm going to have to load in another one here.
So that I don't know what we probably want that to be at, I'm guessing
that should actually probably pretty far away.
I don't know how far away, exactly.
But probably pretty far away if that makes sense.
Maybe like that for now and so maybe this one, is it - 40 or
something?
I don't know.
So let's go ahead and spread that new layer in here.
So there's another layer that one will kind of put up to its normal
size there again.
There it is, and yeah, that needs to be just a tad bigger.
So something like that.
And it needs to be moved up a
As well.
So something like
something like that.
All right.
And so there's the next layer of Hills.
Now we have, you know, yet another layer coming in of hills
There we go.
And you can see that this is sort of a more.
It's off to the the other side, right?
Oops.
Try and get that in there.
So I don't know exactly how big that one should be.
But that is yeah, that's what we're going for.
So it needs to be kind of lifted up to the top of the screen,
obviously, and also probably moved over a bit.
So that it touched its, the, this like kind of sitting on the right,
the right side, right?
And yet now let's just take a quick look.
Oops.
Let's just take a quick look at what that looks like Zoom wise, right.
So we're not getting very much Parallax there at all.
There's hardly any difference between those.
Now we could make ourselves move more, right?
We can, we can crank up the motion to kind of see it a little bit more
pronounced, but you can kind of see that there's really just not that
much difference there.
So I wonder if we want to try when we're sort of setting these up.
I wonder if you want to do more like a half, a half a half kind of a
thing.
Let's see how many layers we've actually got here.
What's when do we get to one?
That's
Actually pretty close.
I don't know.
So there's that.
See what 6 looks like.
so, I think that must be the
Foreground most one guessing and let's take a look at what the seven
players up that is up kid.
Yeah, okay.
So we kind of know how much there are here.
We know that this is the kid but we know that these are all the layers
that we have to have.
And so I'm going to kind of I'm going to try just doing it.
Where will maybe do sort of like a doubling and so maybe this one is
like, you know, five meters away.
Oops.
Maybe this one is like five meters away since 10:00.
This is one, this is 20.
This is 40.
This is 80 something more like that and maybe we'll try to do it a
little closer to will do 2 to 5 to 10 to 20 to 40 and we'll see how
that goes.
And so if we were going to do that let's start over just on the back
there.
That seems like it's moving a reasonable amount for a distant plane.
So let's just assume that that's going to be good enough for now.
And I'm going to shrink that down.
Right.
I don't know how far down that should be.
She probably also stopped.
The motion.
Okay.
How big is it really is?
Is it roughly 40?
Yes, it's roughly 40.
And then 10.
There we go.
All right.
So let's put the next one in.
And that's going to be.
Much smaller.
It was certainly 25 before, so it looks like it's about 24.
Okay, and that I don't know how high that is 52.
Three.
So that's about 3.5.
All right.
And so how does that look, the zoom?
So that's looking better.
Zoom lies to me, right?
That's definitely giving that's that's got a little bit more of that
motion now, the background.
So you can start a start to see the the depth of the theme coming
through a little bit more, so I think that's good.
Okay, so let's add another layer in there.
Okay, so the other layer is now that's 20.
So this was going to be at 10 right thought I just yeah, I turn that
off.
So let's start that guy, back in the center and I don't know how big
you can probably be, maybe something like that.
That's probably too big, maybe the more like that.
Kind of a thing probably possibly maybe.
Don't know, can't tell.
So that's going to be like 1.5 and it's going to be like .5 /.
Probably be a little more.
475.
And so that's up against the corner now.
And so let's take a look at how that moves when it moves.
So, that's looking good.
Now, you can really kind of see those layers starting to separate,
which is what I want.
So, that's kind of good.
And now, let's get that last layer in there before the, for the little
kid.
Oops.
So, there is layer 5 in the foreground, and layer 5 is offset already.
So let me turn that off and get this scale down to something
reasonable.
There we go.
So it's kind of on the left, right?
So let's go ahead and make that be like a little bigger maybe than it
was and let's move it up a bit.
Wait.
This is not the last layer.
This is the second to last layer.
My bad.
I misspoke.
And I said this was the last layer.
That was just plain, erupt.
That was erroneous, it was an erroneous statement.
All right.
Perfect, perfect.
Okay, so that's good.
And now last last the actual last layer, before the kid instead of the
fake Last layer where it wasn't really the last layer.
But I said that it was because I was just plain wrong.
So there we go.
So that's the actual last layer.
And so now we just need to make sure that sized properly, which I
think is probably something like this.
Yeah, and then we got to move it up slightly.
Now of course we have a problem which is that I guess we can't really
move it up slightly.
So actually just has to be straight up, scaled more, looks like it's
not really the right size which is unfortunate but as far as I can
tell like that's just yeah that's just not going to that's not going
to work.
It would have to it has to be a little bit higher, a little bit
bigger.
Yeah.
After we check to make sure you can export something wrong there and
let's move it up.
So just a tease.
Yeah.
Just a smidge.
Okay.
Alright, so that's about it.
Now, we just need to put the little kid in there, right?
And the kid is just going to be, I guess, maybe it like - 14.
You know, -.5 something like that?
Pretty close up.
I think you would want them to be
Do wrong.
So, it's probably not that big.
All right, so maybe .5 was correct.
Maybe a little bit bigger than that.
And then he just needs to be moved over to sort of, you know, the
shot.
You can clearly see the shots framed with him, kind of looking to, you
know, from the left to the right.
So we probably want to obey that line-of-sight.
Certainly
So, let's see.
There he is and maybe just even just a hair more.
All right, so let's see, let's see what happens if we let this animate
now.
So that looks pretty good.
Although word clearly not moving towards the center of interest there.
So I'm going to go ahead and move the camera over so that it spanning
towards the center of Interest more directly like.
So see how that goes.
Probably a little too much of a lift there.
So we'll keep that down a little bit more.
Probably also want to knock that down a little bit that feels about
right.
Maybe a bit less.
So I think that's roughly what we would want the pan to be the kid.
Maybe comes out of the picture a little too quick.
So let's go ahead and put him at one instead.
We got some separation of those layers.
Unfortunately to their cement to scale, one of them up.
Yeah, so that looks pretty good.
It's just that that that mid-layer this one right here.
Looks like it needs to be scaled up a bit.
Unfortunate.
Because you can see it starts to separate right there at that, that
bottom piece.
Oh, so I can't move it up a bit, right?
I have to put it down a bit, oops, that's 11.
Got to leave it down.
But then, it's will separate that one.
Yeah, this is why I always ask for aprons on stuff, but it's tough.
If you're not, if you're not, someone who's used to making Parallax
shots, it can be kind of tough to remember how they're going to
actually work in practice.
So, you know, that's kind of, it's just a thing that happens.
But I can just knock some of these guys down a little bit and then
we'll probably be.
Okay.
I can't see because my my
fortunately, my
Head is in the way I need to see kind of that corner.
So you see that the corner there is got a problem.
So I need to be able to see that as well.
So I'm going to go ahead and and do this.
Well, I tune these so I can see that corner opening up and fix it.
So I'm going to move that back layer down.
I got to make that back layer a little bit bigger.
So that's that's this one, right?
Yeah.
So I'm gonna have to make that probably a little bit bigger than it is
just to cover again.
That that range.
And I'm going to go ahead and slide it over a bit too.
Let's see.
Okay, so now let's see how that goes.
Seems okay.
Yeah, it's still a little bit there.
Darn it.
All right.
Duh, so just a teeny little bit there.
So now there won't be any bit there, but I don't know about the start,
whether there's any fringing on the start.
I think that's about it, but hopefully, they're, you know, we're going
to have to check.
Okay, so that's fine.
All right, so let's see if I can see any other problems at the moment.
So the kid needs to be the kid at the start is a little bit off, so
we'll fix him in a second.
Is there any gapping on this guy?
Yes, there's a little gap down back guy.
So he needs to be moved down just a little bit as well.
Is it this one?
All right, so
I don't see any Gap problems with this one, really.
So I think we're really just talking about moving the kid down and
moving that other layer down just a hair.
So, it's not that one.
It's this one.
The kid has to be moved down slightly.
There it goes.
And now let's go back to
the motion.
and see if there's any other bugs that we
Fix.
Good, pretty good so far.
That one's still needs to be down, just a little bit, just a hair.
So this guy right here, probably needs to be more like that.
I'm reasonably happy with that.
Yep, all good.
There's a little bit of that back one.
I feel like there's just a bit of this guy.
So I feel like he needs to be maybe move down just a hair.
See if that would do it.
Now, I need to be down a little more than that.
And so, I don't know if that up clip him off the top at all.
I think that's about it.
That's looking good though.
That's looking pretty good.
Any clipping problems.
Nope.
So that looks okay.
All right, I'm reasonably happy with that.
Okay, so there's our set of cutscenes.
I think I can I can say that that's a pretty reasonable first attempt
at getting all of our cutscenes lined up, so there they are.
As you can see, it takes a little while to tune them.
Again, if you really had to do ton of these, you're going to do like a
hundred cutscenes or something.
You'd want to make a little tool for tweaking the values or something.
You know, you could write an importer for some tool or something.
But as a whole, I'm pretty happy with how that goes and so now but we
need to do, right?
Because we've
Make some way of playing these in a series, so that each cutscene
plays, you know, back to back.
So you can kind of see the whole thing, right?
You can see the whole thing happen.
And in order to do that, what I would like to do is say, Okay, since
this is clearly very data-driven at this point, right?
You can kind of see the data just living right there.
I should be able to just wrap those up into into, you know,
no, an array of layered scenes and just run it that way, right?
So I should be able to do something like, you know, layered scene.
You know, intro cutscene like that, right?
And then just literally grabbed everything here and dump it in there.
You know, and so now we can just go ahead and convert these into just
just literally, just some data.
So we know that we've got, you know, that kind of thing or there's the
asset type
There's the shot index.
There's the layer count.
Here's the layers.
In fact, what I could do as well, is just something like this.
Where I say the layer count is like the array count.
Layers one or intro layers.
One, something like that.
And then intro there is one so I could do something like that.
There we go.
Right?
And that would just let me do like, okay, here's intro layers one.
However, many it has in it.
That's how many we do, right?
And so, that'd be pretty straightforward.
I could even do something, you know, I could do something even a
little bit more ridiculous.
This could, this isn't a turtle Global by the way, right?
Or Global variable rather,
I could even do something a little bit weirder.
We're actually making macro like intro, like intro scene and then a
number.
Right?
And that would just be this stuff.
It would just be like that.
If that makes any sense, I don't know if that's a good idea, it might
be a stupid idea, but we certainly could do it because the index
appears like multiple times there, right?
So we could do interesting index like that, and
And do this.
I don't know, like I said, don't know if that's a good idea but we
could do it under way.
What Undeclared identifier it gets passed in.
Oh duh.
Okay so we could do something like that where we just kind of data
drive it a little bit more straightforwardly.
And that way we can kind of just
Drop these out here.
This is this is kind of convenient actually.
Now that I'm looking at it, that seems kind of nice, right?
Yeah.
Yeah, I like that.
So I'm going to go ahead and just do the munging to put all these in
that format and that should be that should be about it.
So this is actually intro shot, I suppose.
All right and just shot a shot.
And that compresses down pretty nice.
So I'm going to go ahead and grab out all the layers like so,
And that should be just about all there is to it.
There we go.
And several of these to do here.
Control errors.
Five.
And this is where I should probably use more than one window and
ping-pong back and forth.
But, you know,
Coulda Shoulda Woulda.
There we go.
I could also done a crazy Macro for this.
You know how I do like me and you know, some emacs macro action now it
again.
Let's see, so yeah, looks good fact, I could do this.
If I wasn't dumb I just do it this way with my
There we go.
So now, I've gotten all of those layers out, and I'm put them up here
as existing arrays, and then I should be able to just kind of change
these quickly into format.
We're using in the magnet
All right, so that seems good and that's all of our stuff there.
So now these guys are really pretty trivial.
This is just going to be like a sort of gathering up the camera, pan
information and putting it into into place, right?
So we're basically just going to grab those and put them in here.
3 4, 5 6 7 8 9 10 11 and so all I need now is just like these guys,
right?
And the fact that I feel like I am kind of tired typing at this point.
So I do kind of feel like maybe now.
Oops would be a good time to bust that one of those ridiculous macros.
So let's just try it.
Let's just try it and see what happens.
Because it's going to be crazy and weird so let's do it.
So here's what I'm going to do.
This macro in Ridiculousness and this is a macro purely purely for my
own Amusement.
I'm just going to go ahead and set up this guy here and this guy here.
So what I'm going to do is I'm going to record the macro starting in
this window.
I'm going to switch to the other window.
I'm going to search for camera start.
I'm going to cut
Out the actual value Switchback paste it.
Hit the comma switch again search for camera and right again, cut out
the value Switchback paste, right?
And then I'm going to search for the location of the next one.
And end the macro.
And so there will just suck them out, one at a time and done.
Ridiculous, I know.
Like I said, kind of absurd.
And so now the only thing that I think is left is the shot change time
thing.
And so the shot change time was always 0.5 at the moment.
So what I should be able to do here because I should be able to go
into the people who were using the shot change time and for now I
should be able to put it to just point five so and we can always.
Oops we can always fuss with that.
A little later on.
If we want.
All right, so that's all good.
Now, we've got all of our stuff wrapped up in there and we now have to
render our scene.
Somehow we should be able to just if we just want to test it right.
We should be able to say you know intro cutscene and pick one of them
right.
Whatever it is and we should now be able to just like cycle through
our cutscenes really easily.
You know what I mean?
So that's, that's pretty good.
And so we need to now figure out
Some way of dealing with this.
We now need to figure out some way that we can play all of these in a
sequence, right?
And so we want to introduce first of all I assume is for any one of
these shots we're going to want to have a another parameter which
allows us to say how long it's going to last.
But we talked about this yesterday
because not every shot you know will be necessarily on the screen for
the same amount of time.
So before we talk about like the camera start and end, maybe what
we'll talk about is the duration of the shot.
And so if I talk about the duration of the shot,
Then for each one of these guys here, right before it, we would put
the duration is.
And so, you know, we had a duration of 20 for each of these shots.
So I'll go ahead and just put that in here.
Like so, so that's all good.
And then you can see when we're doing this map to range thing here,
that map to range was that was taking the input value for the cutscene
and mapping it into R 0 to 1.
Now, unfortunately, it's only going to range from 0 to 20 because we
like hard-coded that in the art and the outside code and we don't
really want that to be the case, probably.
So I think what we'd rather do here is we'd rather just do something,
you know, maybe I'll even do something like this where we just pass in
the tea cutscene for now.
So we don't have to think about it.
And so when this thing calls out,
And passes that cutscene information will, just go ahead and pass the
address.
So that way, it can wrap it if it needs to or do whatever else it
wants to do, right.
so what I'll do here is I'll say, okay, let's start by looking at
This input value.
And we know we're going to have a fairly low number of cutscenes,
right?
Shots in the cutscene, it's only 11:00 in this one.
And if we do like a, I haven't decided whether there's like a game,
like a conclusion cutscene or something.
But, you know, if there's a conclusion cutscene, it's probably going
to be even less than that.
Like the intro is probably the one that has the most in it, right?
And so we know that there's just going to be very few, so I can just
linearly search to see where this value Falls, right?
So I'm gonna get a t-value
And I have a series of durations, right?
And so I can initialize T, start and T or rather TTC base.
Let's say right?
I guess I tease base to say the first, whatever.
The first shot is it's going to start at zero, right?
And then I can just Loop through here and I can say well for whatever
shot index, I'm on
Looping through the shots is just going to be however, many there are
in that intro cutscene array, right?
And for each one of those, right?
I can grab out, whatever the scene is for that particular shot by just
saying, whatever the intro cutscenes are.
I'm going to grab out whatever shot index that is so on that
particular scene, I now have a duration variable, right?
We added this concept of adoration so the durations there,
So what I know is the start of this scene is going to be equal to T
base.
The duration of the scene is going is specified, so the end is just a
start plus that.
And then so then the t-base afterwards, like the next one would just
be equal to.
Well it would just be equal to the end, right?
The start of the next scene is the end of this scene.
So what I can do there is say, okay, if you know if T cutscene is
greater than or equal to the start,
And see, cutscene is less than the end.
I've got an idea or two, but we'll talk about that later, and it's
less than the end.
Then, I know that we are in this particular shot.
So this is the shot that we're talking about.
So it's the one that I want to render, right?
And after I render it, I can also end if I'd like to because I know
that we're only going to render one scene.
If we had multiple overlapping scenes, we could not do that, but we
don't, so that's fine.
And so then what I want to do is map the map T normal into that range.
So I'm just going to go ahead and say OK, map it but
Tween.
I should make these T.
Start map that between t star and T end and and that's what I'll do.
The other thing I can do is make sure that if we flow off the
beginning or the off the end, I could also make it so we're under
saying, but we don't really need to think about that quite yet we're
probably fine without worrying about that too much.
Okay.
And so then what I'd like to do is say all right at the end of this if
T cutscene is greater than or equal
Equal to T base.
That means we've gone past the end and so I'll just set the cutscene
back to zero for now.
But probably what we'd want to do is signal to the outside.
At that point that hey man, there's nothing there's no more cutscenes
or render the actual game like stop playing the cutscene right?
And that seems pretty straightforward.
So, there we go, that's the code.
And I think now we probably in theory, anyway, should be able to get
this whole thing going.
So let's see.
So that's how that works.
Do you know, we'll pack up direct clamp to range should just work
although I don't see anything which suggests to me, that it doesn't
work, right?
I mean, I should be seeing somebody moving or somebody doing something
but I see.
Absolutely nothing.
So we, yeah.
What's wrong with this picture?
Intro cutscene was taught.
See, I should step into the debugger, I suppose T.
Star T equals T base Tian is to start plus seen duration, which is 20.
So it's going to be whatever that is, if the cutscene is greater than
equal to that start value and less than the end value.
Then we map it in between the two to forty normal, which we pass.
Oh, that's not so good.
That should be shot index, obviously, but that doesn't explain where
RT normal value is not changing.
Artie.
Normal value for clamp map to range between to start T end is is
janky, right?
Does not seem to be correct.
All right, so I'm going to step into that and just see what's wrong.
Probably do something stupid.
I'm a little bit tired today.
I'll admit it.
So, yeah.
Normally that's not code that she should have any bugs in when you
write it.
It's not particularly complicated.
But yeah, so here is our scene and there's a there's all the
information for the scene.
It's shot index 0 right for the first one.
And so let's see what the to start.
T end is and what is our key cutscene
Oops.
There we go.
So that definitely is in between 0 and 20, no question about that but
coming here, but Artie, normal should not be 0, right?
Because we're mapping between 0 and 20 and T cutscene is not quite
that.
So let's take a look at what that actually is.
We map it.
That's good.
So off we go, we break out of that and
Ah, that's the problem.
Yeah, that's kind of stupid.
If we break out, we'll never know what the end actually is.
So that was a dumb way to do that.
Ladies and gentlemen.
Pretty stupid.
That was pretty stupid.
So we might do want to do something more like this, where we do, you
know,
That's all.
and if you're not pretty stupid, then you reset the cutscene
That's a little better.
And so now we should actually see more of our cutscene happening and
and yeah, we should when we're finished our zoom on the home for
limbless children, we should then be in a yeah, in better shape for we
should we should see, you know, the the little kid at the window,
there he is.
And then after the little kid at the window, we should see, you know,
the looking
Very shoulder at the toys, right?
Which we still like this is kind of our most problematic scene doesn't
look that good.
So we may have to kind of work on that one.
Maybe change the art of it, I don't know.
And then we have Santa Claus of being his usual useless self and
giving the kid get another hat for Christmas you know what can you do
then we've got Krampus of course, bursting through the door and there
is an all his majesty.
It comes to find little Timmy, take a little Timmy away, there's a
little Timmy in The foreground running, you know, trying to get out
certainly as fast as you can.
Can't escape Krampus, but thankfully for Timmy and Timmy doesn't know
how lucky he is.
But thanks to her Timmy, the little hero stops Krampus.
Right.
And he's like dude, you are not going to do that to Timmy and then
Krampus is so impressed by the bravado that he's like hey man, you
know I
I'm going to give you your own hand fine.
I'm going to give you a hand, you can use.
And so the kid is like, so psyched about this, obviously,
Goes back to his room and he's like, I'm going to pick up one of these
hats.
That's an has always been giving me that I can never use and I can
like put it on now and I can go on an adventure which is what I've
always wanted to do if I'd only had a hand.
And now I have one and so he grabs you know hat and goes off now of
course you are allowed to pick the hat so we don't know which hat it's
going to be exactly but you know you get the idea.
All right, so that's in pretty good shape, I think.
And, and now we're playing all the cutscenes together and we can
change the duration of the cutscenes so that pretty much makes it so
that we're all set, I think.
You know for a first pass we're going to obviously want to tune that
stuff and when we get some voice acting in their, we're going to want
to again adjust the timing.
But for the most part, we've succeeded in what we wanted to do which
was just have all of our cut scenes, stuff, a good first pass of all
of our cut scenes working pretty straightforward,
word, since we wrote a renderer,
we are done all the heavy lifting.
It was really pretty easy for us to do and hey look at that.
We're just in time for the Q&A.
So let's go ahead.
and go to said q, a
Let's see.
What is in Q&A?
Yvonne, will there be hat DLC?
No, probably not.
I'm going to Cranberry wait for more questions.
I will do you prefer opengl or DirectX?
I prefer opengl because you can sort of Leverage that on multiple
platforms.
Like you can run on Linux and Mac instead of DirectX only allows you
to run on Windows which is kind of annoying.
Who draws the pictures, you anxiously draws the pictures, all that the
hmh bot, take care of that one.
I think there is still a tiny Gap at the bottom at the top of the
window and shot to towards the very end of the shot.
That may be true shot too.
Whoops, that that's shot index.
Is actually one.
She probably pad that out.
She'd probably do this, just so we don't get super confused, right?
Because otherwise it'll total be like what's going on.
All right, try again.
Yeah, you're right.
Wait.
Yeah.
All right, so that means in shot too.
The hero entry have to be a little bigger than they are, right?
So now I think we're good.
Seems like the cutscene is nearly finished for a first pass.
Are we returning to debugging next?
Yes, probably, I don't know.
We'll see what happens.
I'm not sure who knows, whatever we decide to do next, will do next.
Yuffie is how do you compile so fast?
Just don't use a bunch of libraries and templates, and crappy things
and you compile quite fast actually.
So I suppose the kid will there be sound effects in the intro scene,
IE door opening sound effects with this be separate or part of the
voiceover.
Yeah.
If there's any side effects, they'll probably be baked in like
normally in the game will be playing sound effects based on, like
what's happening but in the in the intro would probably just be all
part of the intro audio.
The last trip time starting out game development.
Know a good portion of C++ but trying to learn opengl or Advanced
Graphics rendering libs are feeling too tedious to me any
recommendations.
Not, not really tedious.
If learning opengl sounds tedious, that's probably not a good sign,
opengl slick, pretty easy compared to like if you had to write it
yourself, for example, you know, so I'm not sure.
Maybe you mean something other than tedious, you just mean difficult.
If it's difficult than yeah.
I mean part of it is opengl.
There is not a lot of good documentation on it anymore because it's
changed so much the old like tutorials and stuff just aren't really
that relevant compared to what you know.
And so there's very few like really good tutorial to point people to
if they want to use like opengl for, you know.
And so yeah, it's, it's a bit of a problem.
And unfortunately, there's not much I can recommend there.
Well, the hat be in the cutscene after its chosen.
Yeah I think so.
I mean I think what we try to do is just pick that layer dynamically
based on which hat you picked, but if we can't do that then we could
just you know, we could just cheese it.
We may just have to like put a random hat on him because now I think
about it.
That's if that plays in like attract mode you know then you wouldn't
have picked a hat yet.
So that my yeah, I don't know.
If you can't excited for Vulcan no I am not excited for Vulcan.
I don't like the design of Vulcan.
I don't agree with it may blow.
Could we just watch the cutscene on Loop while we do Q&A sure?
Let's go ahead and do that.
Know, any good opengl tutorials are the arc synthesis ones, which you
mentioned before and like, on stream way back when and which are, I
believe link to on the forums somewhere.
Those are the only ones that are any good.
They got taken down but somebody like saved, a PDF of them or
something.
I don't know.
Those were okay.
But yeah.
It's there just aren't that.
Many is what guy saying that?
There's, there's someone should probably write some good opengl
tutorials at some point.
For that over-the-shoulder seen what if you could give the boy a
velocity as well?
So that it partially exaggerated or counter the camera movement,
giving him some actual Movement.
We could we could also slow his movement down.
I don't know like like I haven't thought about it too much.
I got to think about what the right thing to do is there.
I don't really know.
What do you have to say to the anti Global variable zealots?
Who would complain about, all those Global's in the cutscene code?
I would tell them that it's if that's data, first of all.
So if they think of that as a global variable, then they have to think
of all of the data that's loaded out of like file out of data, files
is also
Bad.
In which case I would ask them how they plan on building a game with
no data.
I think the last shot still has clipping at the end, the heroes head.
Yeah.
I think we clip through the near clipping plane.
I don't know why the near clipping plane is set where it is because it
doesn't seem like it would have to.
But yeah, it does disappear a little too early.
Why, what is the setting for the near clipping plane?
Is there a reason for that?
Do we know?
I don't really know.
I'm very curious to know if we set the near clipping plane to anything
for any particular reason.
I suppose we could go back and watch the bod.
What's your favorite header file to include?
The ones you will advance for your project.
I don't pound include anything that I didn't write.
So, I think the answer would be somewhat meaningless.
if I were to actually answer it,
My project, our main game does not use any lb includes that are
external.
At all, literally zero.
Let's see.
When do you mention the banding on the streamer lives and said it
would be really easy to fix.
How would you fix it?
So yeah.
Basically like this is just this, this extremely lame.
The thing that does that is just this little app.
I wrote a long time ago for a totally different purpose, so it doesn't
really do anything.
Correct graphically.
And so it, the the gradient is very banded.
You can't really see it on in this case because there's so much color
information underneath it.
But if you put it against just like a regular flat background, you can
see that there's banding
And so to fix that, it's really simple.
All you have to do is just get through it.
That's it and so you can get through it any real way that you want.
You know, if you're going to be super hardcore, you'd use blue noise
but you know you don't really have to be that hard core.
You could just use anything just a standard ordered even just a really
basic death or would be fine.
Who is your ideal voice of Krampus?
I don't think Krampus is going to have any speaking Parts in this.
Growing Doubloon.
Do the hats, mr.
Magical powers upon you.
They might
I asked this during the priest reading, but sure, but not sure your
credit still catching the series but have you written it better hash
after the same region episodes.
No, there's been no, there's no touching of the hash.
And remember, we have to shift this this game with at least one.
Comment / / to do better hash function so that might be the one but
you never know as long as there's one.
Captain craft off-topic, how much planning for a large longer than one
year?
Software project.
Do you do before us to start the project?
How do you estimate the time?
It takes to get the work done.
Yeah I don't really know that that's an answer.
You can give without knowing more about the project, right?
And usually the it's also worth knowing that it's very difficult to
predict those sorts of things.
If the product is interesting at all, because chances are
Going to be, if there's any research involved or anything
unpredictable.
There, then really, it's you have to you rather than a schedule or a
plant which are usually making is sort of like a series of decision
points where you look a right to try this and see what happens in the
based on.
That will do one of two things and that sort of stuff.
When?
Up and coming out?
Why do you not like Vulcan?
I don't know when Vulcan is coming out and I don't like it because I
didn't like the design of it.
Curling champ.
Are you familiar with free, glut?
Thoughts on that?
Specifically, I have never seen free.
Glad I do not know what it is.
See.
I'm trying to go as independent as I can.
And my code base is, well, one thing that I'm not sure how to replace
this glue, how to load the opengl functions, myself mention of your
library for that.
Any tips?
Advice on the right where to begin?
You can just use wiggle, get proc address wgl.
Get proc address will allow you to load any opengl function.
So, so, you know, once you once you load library and get a, the
address of will get proc address, which I believe is in gdr 32 lib.
So dull it GTA 3, 2.2 L.
So once you dynamically load GDI, which doesn't actually have to die
in fluid.
You jack is already mapped in.
But once you get the coroner GTI using load library, then you go ahead
and get wiggle proc address and use local property.
Just get the rest of the opengl addresses.
What did Krampus do with the other children after he gifted that hand
to our hero.
What was the purpose of his visit?
Well you have to wait for the voice acting.
I think maybe to find out some of those specifics.
Huber, Caleb do you least include Windows?
No, I do not include windows.
I'm in my purse hover, there's a glitch in the graphic near the
Cockroaches antenna in the hats put on the hats playing.
Actually there's a lot of glitches.
Unfortunately, I don't know how many of these we want to clean up.
Like it depends how much stuff I want to send back to Yankton for
like, clean up stuff.
There's a lot of places where the alpha isn't fully one as well so you
can see like Krampus is hand.
Like even in that shot kind of shows through a little bit so there's a
bunch of stuff for clean up there and I don't know how you know
picking we want to get about that stuff.
I want to be very picky about the programming by, don't know that this
is a game where we want to be super picky about the art.
This is not really a product that's about art Direction.
It's a project.
That's a
Programming.
So I don't know what I want to do about that or not, but there's a
bunch of those this quite a few of them.
I have a feeling the clip plane might have been introduced when we
were doing the multiple ground layers.
Yeah, and it was definitely introduce.
I just don't know why it was set to what it was set at probably just
random my guess it may not have been a reason for it at all.
if I may be under a 10-7, feedings you layers, okay,
So, yeah, maybe we'll check.
I don't know.
We probably just picked it.
Randomly would be my guess because we just need a near clipping plane
because we can't not have one or we might draw something at zero,
which would cause a divide by zero or something, right?
K.
Krampus sounds.
So cool.
How did you come up with the name?
I didn't Krampus.
Is a real Krampus has a real thing.
You can look him up.
He like this is actually based on a true story, right?
True story.
Real Krampus, you know, real Santa Claus real Krampus.
And you know, I mean was there really an orphanage for a limbless
children?
I mean, you know,
But obviously, Krampus and Santa Claus are real.
So,
You know that that part is not is not open to question at all
certainly.
That's just science fact.
Does Krampus Return to Zero?
I don't know what that means.
Return To Zero what
So no more real questions of looks like I think we're done with
questions for the day, maybe.
Maybe.
Amoco Embrace.
Thank you, case.
You are welcome Abner.
All right.
Well, that seems like it's about it.
So you be doing the lutein character.
This weekend.
How many times I'm going to answer this question.
I don't do game jams anymore.
No no no, no.
I think personally unless you're trying to practice I don't feel like
we really need jams anymore.
There's so many games getting made right now that the problem is
usually attention to detail and taking your time to do stuff, right?
Not that things are taking too long game, jams are more appropriate
back when people were only making Giant games that took three years to
make, but that's not the case anymore.
If anything right now, people need the take a long time and do a good.
Job on the game Jam.
Not make a game in a weekend, which just we just don't really need
like.
That's, I don't see that as you feeling of particularly useful space.
So really the only time I think people should really be doing game
jams.
These days is if they're trying to practice programming or whatever.
You know, just trying to practice programming fast.
So, all right, I'm a close it down.
I'm going to close it down.
Killer co uk sometimes the transition from scene to scene is not
perfect.
Are you going to fix that?
Yes.
So we haven't talked about that yet, but what that actually is and you
know, if you think about it and you've been following the series, if
you think about it you should be you should actually know what that
is, right?
And what it is, is, when the scenes switch, that's the first time that
our system is getting asked for those resources, the bitmaps that are
involved in that stream, right?
And because we've got I don't remember how much we got.
Like half a gigabyte of bitmaps in this cutscene, but we only gave the
system like 256.
To work with or something like that, right?
So what that means is if you play through the entire set of cutscenes,
by the time, you go back and loop around to the beginning of the
cutscenes, again, all of the cut, all of it has fallen out of our of
our asset cash, right?
Because the rolling asset cash.
So on that first frame,
It does.
The system goes oh, who.
Oh, I don't have any of the bitmaps.
I need to draw this Frame.
Darn.
Right.
And so it doesn't dry anything and maybe you don't.
Maybe it has time to load one of them or something.
I don't know.
But it's basically just can't do anything right.
And so what you're seeing is that that period of paging in the
bitmaps, right?
So what we want to do is and this is what we'll do tomorrow is what we
want to do is make it so that we look ahead at what will come in the
next slice of time and prefetch the bitmaps.
And if we've never done this before,
For, but you'll notice that I kind of set us up for it right here.
That's that's exactly what we want.
And we've done the prefetching for sounds when we're playing streaming
audio, but we never did this one.
And that's exactly what it's for.
What we want to do is like I said, we should playing time to us
tomorrow.
What we want to do is in that cutscene
In addition, to rendering whatever our current T is we want to look
forward, say you know, I don't know, a tenth of a second, a half a
second or whatever we want to look forward a half of a second and ask
for the prefetch of all the bitmaps that we see then, right?
So, that's, that's what that's gonna, that's what that's going to do
and that's what would fix.
I think, what you were
I'm assuming to assuming that you're talking about,
that makes sense.
But yeah.
But this is kind of cool too.
I guess if you look at it,
This might be kind of amusing, although I guess we can't really, I
don't know if we actually can see this.
Because we're we still have the weird.
Like, you know, we've got the loop Live code editing weird stuff, but
we've never really gone an optimized properly.
But in theory, we should be able to see that actually happen.
So you can see right here when the scene changes.
It loads new stuff in, but we also generally don't ever change our
memory usage, so that's working exactly.
As we designed it, remember, we designed it to use a certain amount of
space.
For stuff and then never use anymore.
So, even though we now have more art resources than we actually can
fit in our working set, it doesn't matter.
It just works right?
Which is kind of cool.
So yeah.
Let's see, anything else here.
Yes, I guess that's about it.
I guess that's about it.
and then the thing too is you can kind of see
CPU is here.
The reason that we're not like we could peg this out.
We could use a hundred percent since it's a software renderer, right?
Since we render everything ourselves, you know, you might wonder why
we aren't just going for a higher frame rate and pegging all this out.
If you remember, we set the number of threads that do the rendering to
a lower number than the number that was in the machine because it was
interfering with OBS streaming,
So, actually, if I switch, and I probably should do this at some point
if I switch to streaming.
From like a graphics capture thing and we can just Peg the CPU.
If we just pegged the CPU, we get this.
This would we can totally use 100% right to just, we can basically
just like increase.
The number of CPUs we use to get higher and higher frame rates that's
just, you know, that's just the nature of a software renderer, right,
because the CPU however, much CPU, we use determines what our frame
rate is just.
And, and so, yeah.
So that's about it.
Now, the other thing too is
one thing that we can do if we wanted to for fun is we're really
wasting a lot of time to on these because if you, if you think about
what's actually happening with the way our render or works, we
actually spend time drawing all of this stuff multiply call the
overdraw.
Actually happens, meaning like even places where we're not drawing
anything.
We're still spending time like doing texture sampling, they're
determining, there's nothing there and whatever and we draw like from
back to front so we actually waste time drawing stuff.
Behind all the pieces that are moving, you know what I mean?
And so there's a bunch of optimizations.
We could choose to do to accelerate that now because computers are so
darn fast.
This is still rendering at a great frame rate even though we're not
even using the GPU, which is just crazy when you think about because
this is like very many layered depth scenes being composite in
real-time with with no actual optimization of the depth complexity of
the scene.
It's kind of crazy how fast this is running, but I just want to point
out that we could make it even faster.
In fact, dramatically Faster by optimizing, that depth complexity.
And so, you know, maybe someday if we wanted to, we could play around
that because it'd be kind of fun.
Let me step in here and help you guys out who are trying to answer
curling champ.
So, here's the thing.
Basically, if you're going to program a GPU, you should know how to
write a render yourself without one.
If you don't, then you probably won't really understand how the GPU is
actually working and you're kind of just throwing random stuff at it
and not really understanding exactly how it works.
So we wrote our own stuff.
Renderer, which actually does exactly what the GPU does for the most
part so that you can actually understand how the GPU works.
And that's pretty critical, especially for going to optimize GPU
performance.
It's pretty critical to understand the works and very few people
actually do, right?
So that was a very important exercise that we were going to do now.
Originally, I was just going to do that as a exercise to show, like,
here's how it is.
And then, of course, that's too slow because everyone knows that gpus
or for
X and CPU is not fast enough or whatever.
So, it's just going to be an exercise, but then we it turned out that
our, when we optimized our software renderer, it was so fast that it's
actually just can run the game straight up, like it runs a game at,
like, 60 frames a second, which is crazy.
And so I decided the best thing to do would be to actually do the rest
of the product that way, so that we actually have a complete software
rendered version of the game that we can actually play, which is kind
of Awesome.
And then later, you know, as an academic exercise certainly we can
just sort of hook it up to a GPU, but it's kind of awesome that we
don't even really have to do that if we don't want to, it's pretty
darn cool.
The Cockroach confirmed for familiar DLC.
Clearly, we need a cockroach familiar.
That's obviously true.
Is there some interface to use for using the GPU?
Yeah, like opengl and DirectX.
That's what, that's what those are.
That's, that's what they're made for to access the GPU.
It's the most in-depth game, you've created, I cut scenes, game
engine, and so on.
No,
Most of the things I've worked on in the past that are probably more
complicated.
Let's see your company 7108 perspective.
Projection awesome.
Good to know.
Isn't glsl and the DirectX Shader language.
Good for this.
Good for what?
I'm not sure what you mean by good for this.
Would it be possible to access DP without a driver?
Not really.
I mean, if you are running code in kernel mode, then in theory, you
could basically write your own graphics driver.
But you'd have to have all the documentation for the river which isn't
available for things like NVIDIA drivers, for example, because they
won't release it.
So, you know, let's say you were using maybe an Intel GPU then maybe
you could do something because that's fully documented.
Maybe you could do something where like okay, you wrote your own, you
know, kernel-mode specialty driver code, that writes directly the
graphics card, then you can do stuff like that but in the general
case, no, because Graphics vendors don't necessarily document their
card and won't let you program to it directly.
And so if you want to access say an Nvidia card, you pretty much have
to go through one of their apis either opengl or DirectX or something
similar.
Curling Champion made here, a moving graphics on screen.
Get the CPU to do other calculations.
So at the risk of being dismissive, curling champ like I understand
how to program computers.
I'm not confused about the fact that you use the CPU and the GPU in
tandem to produce Graphics.
This is something that I do every day at work and made here is an
educational series.
It's supposed to show you how things work.
So we don't do it that way because
Is writing everything from scratch.
Yourself is a pretty important part of this process a GPU is just a
very restricted processing unit that you can offload, certain
computations to, and knowing what those computations actually.
Are is a critical part of learning to program, right?
And so, it's really kind of obvious to everyone.
Hopefully that if we wanted to run this to the GPU, we could
It ain't hard, right?
So it's not super helpful for you to keep talking about that because
everyone already knows that and you can go back to the streams where
I've talked about this at length, they're all on the video on demand.
And just to be clear, we are not bit bleeding, these are not bit
Blitz.
These are actually full sub-pixel accurate by linearly sampled with
rotation and scaling support.
So this is nothing like a bit blit.
This actually implements the actual full texture sampling that you
would do just like a graphics card does.
That's why this in fact also is really nice and smooth and doesn't
have any of those annoying pixel like jumpy pixel artifacts that you
get.
If you look at like, even hilariously oftentimes, you'll look at games
that do use a GPU but they don't understand how any of it works.
So they still have like jumps pixel, to pixel as it moves and you're
like, what are you doing, right?
That's true.
We do do gamma correction as well, but we don't do full gamma
correction.
We only
Power of 2 gamma correction.
We don't do like full srgb because I really don't see the point of it.
Still have a little bit, still there, still a little bit of
Schmutz.
We gotta like align our layers a little bit better, but
does bilinear filtering hold up in 3D?
Yeah bilinear filtering is what most 3D runs on sometimes, you know,
You can do better filtering like there's trilinear, there's an
isotropic and those are usually for like filtering across MIT maps and
stuff, but gpus generally do bilinear filtering, that's what they do.
They don't do really much in the way of more advanced filtering for
textures.
So
All right, so I think we're all good here.
I think we're all good here.
Handmade cut and me, cutscene screen sir for Christmas.
It could happen.
It could happen, we could ship one.
Let me blow ya.
As far as I can tell you set the clip playing your company pre-round.
You okay?
Yeah just making sure.
All right, I'm going to call it a day.
Let's see here.
Let's see.
All right, thank you for joining me for another episode of handmade
hero.
It's been a pleasure coding with you.
As always, if you want to follow the series, you can always pre-order
the game comes to the source code so that you can play around with
like what we did on stream and also the our packs up there as well.
So if you want to play around with the cutscene art to sort of
practice, doing some of that stuff that we were showing, you can do
that as well.
We also have a forum if you want site if you want to go ask questions.
We have a patreon page.
If you would like to support the video series, you can always
subscribe.
If they're we have a tweetbot the tweets is scheduled to you except
when they reboot my server and then it doesn't I'm going to have to
restart him.
The poor little guy he got killed but when he's actually allowed to
run he tweets the schedule at you.
And speaking of the schedule, I'll be back here.
5 p.m.
I believe Pacific Standard time tomorrow.
You know what?
I got to look to make sure that's true because I forget sometimes what
the schedule is, I think so, yeah, that is correct.
So back here 5 p.m.
Pacific Standard time tomorrow and yeah that's that's the place to be.
If you would like to see how we're going to make sure that we always
prefetch our bitmaps that's we're going to do tomorrow to that make
sure that those transitions from cutscene to cutscene always roll
smoothly until then have fun programming and I'll see you guys on the
internet.
Take it easy, everyone.