Hello, everyone and welcome to handmade.
Here are the show.
We code a complete game live on stream.
We are kind of coming to the end of our debug code stuff here.
It's kind of been a long road.
We started it a long time ago and then in the middle we sort of took a
break and did some Hardware rendering stuff.
We we added a hardware rendering path in addition to our software
rendering path.
And then we came back and kind of like solidified things.
And we've got some pretty cool debug features in our engine now which
is nice but we're kind of coming to a good stopping point.
You know we can always come back to the debug system and add new
things as we need them later.
If we find that, there's some things that it should be doing or could
be doing that it's not doing for us and we'd like it to, we can
certainly do that but I think at this point we're mostly we're, you
know, we're mostly ready to sort of to move on.
So I'm just going to kind of be thinking
Here on day 268 and the subsequent streams this week.
Just like, what are some things that we probably want to tidy up?
What some UI stuff that's not, you know, maybe the nicest what can we
do to kind of like consolidate these things so that you can wind it
down to a point where we're like, pretty sure that things are working
in a way that's useful to us as we move off.
So, all right and you know that might involve adding some features as
well, you know, who's to say who's to say?
Okay.
So today is day what 268 I said.
So if you would like to follow along with source code at home and
you're one of the folks who has pre-order the game on handmade here at
work.
You want to unzip day 267.
That's the code that I'm starting with today.
So let's go ahead and load.
Let's load up here.
Let's get that going and get Ms.
Dev going and here is the game as it stands here.
Is our profiling system, which is kind of swanky at this point and we
can use it to kind of go through and see all the information that we
wanted to see.
We had a clipping yesterday so we can even get some nice.
Everything stays contained inside, our little display window, which is
also good.
And all that good stuff.
So I would say a couple things on the profile front one thing that we
might want to try to do is is come up with some kind of memory
profiling, which we could do.
And I think that might be something to maybe say for next week because
one of the things that I was thinking of doing for finally stuff,
before we go into the gameplay code, is I wanted to show people how
like, you know, we've kind of built this Arena allocation system
that's relatively primitive.
But that does work.
Very effective for what we need.
One of things I was going to show people is how you can trivial extend
it to be arbitrarily growing so that you don't have to pre decide
ahead of time.
How much space you're going to use?
Because one of the questions that I get asked because like the way
that we do it currently, as we, you know, reserve a certain amount
space and the arena allocates that space, But A lot of people like
confused about that and don't understand what they would do or how
they would use it.
If they didn't know ahead of time that they wanted to run with this,
For their size, there's really no difference.
You can trivially extend an arena class to grow on demand.
And so, I thought, one thing we might do is go back and sort of maybe
finalized that Arena class a little bit.
And I'll make it so that it can grow on demand.
So that's like a feature that you could enable because it's really
easy and then you know, while we're doing that, I'll add the also the
ability to track the allocations so that they can show up here in the
debug View and those are probably two things that might be nice.
That would be a good thing to do next week as sort of a little
exercise that I think people would probably benefit from.
So I think I want to stick with not that for this week.
I think I want to stick with sort of more, you know, kind of basic
stuff here.
And one of the things that's
That's currently true about the system is nothing works when debug is
paused and I think that might be fine.
Like, I'm not sure I actually care about that but you'll notice like,
you know, I can it's if I want to.
For example, I can I could actually toggle this this thing and have
it, have it actually happened.
Meaning it's actually make the change.
But the the change itself doesn't really ever actually show up in the
UI and the reason for that.
As if we're not recording debug information, none of our state
actually shows up here, right?
We just throw out data so it's always going to be wrong.
That's something that I might consider fixing.
If This Were A system that I was gonna, you know, like I said ship
commercial or something but I think that's just fine.
Like I don't think that's going to bother me at all.
I don't think it's worth spending time on it so I'm just going to
leave that be our system for cloning stuff at the moment is also not
particularly great.
There's some things that I don't
I love about the way the system works.
So, for example, at the moment we always have a little bit of space
here at the beginning and we get, you know, this kind of weird like
dot out here, that's how you move the thing around and there's just
some it's not the world's nicest situation.
I think maybe that might be something to turn our attention to
improving that system, just making these windows work, a little bit
better and maybe making better controls from the application side of
things that allow me to kind.
Ben code where I want certain things to appear and what sorts of
things I want in terms of Windows.
And I think that might be a good thing.
That's probably number one on the list today.
I think that might be a good one.
And the other thing I think would just be to tidy up the UI of this
system.
Where we like, maybe draw these thread things a little bit better,
maybe make it a little easier to click or to zoom on something in
particular.
So just cleaning up that a little bit.
Other than that, I can't think of a whole lot.
That would really need to be modified at the moment.
It seems like things are working well enough that we can probably rely
on them being good enough for us to use again, like I said, we have to
ship the game, not the debug system.
So while it's nice to have a good one at some level you can just make
arbitrary decisions of this is done enough and we don't need to you
know polish it to any particular extent necessarily, right?
So yes so I think what I'll do is I'll focus on sort of this this over
all drawing aspect of it and that's what I think I'd like to start on.
So I'm going to go ahead in and, and play around with that a little
bit.
Now, if we open up the debug code, you'll remember that this is in a
thing that we called Draw main menu and draw me menu is kind of like a
really weird situation.
I you know, it's called main menu but really it draws all the menus so
it's really just called it's really just the thing that draws
everything, right?
It's really just debug draw is what it is and you can see where it
gets called.
If I go down and search for that, you can see that essentially the way
our UI system actually works for all intents and purposes.
In fact, this all this stuff, you're our debug counter stuff, this was
all old code, right?
That was putting out statistics before we started working with them in
the profiler.
So really all of this stuff is just vestigial remains that we don't
really need although I guess, you know, now that I think about it, I
should probably look real quick and just see what's actually there
because maybe now that I think about it.
Do we want to resurrect any of this and copy it out somewhere?
Where can be used as suppose that's possible to.
You can see here.
We've got it looks like it looks like here.
We've got maybe some bar stuff getting drawn.
So this stuff, this this debug statistic hit counter stuff, looks
pretty irrelevant, but this stuff here looks like it's sort of a
that's like is our frame bar graph.
So it looks like all of this
We've kind of already got something of, you know, like all that stuff
is already there, right?
If that makes sense.
So I don't think we really need any more of that.
Let's see scope to record.
This is all old stuff as well.
We now have the ability to analyze any performance stuff.
That was really old things that are not really at all relevant
anymore.
And so I think scope to record can go away entirely.
And so, then we owe.
For a coder has died.
Poor for coder.
For coder has died.
That's a rarity.
We have not had many for crashes.
I believe this is the same for coder crash that I saw before on my own
work.
And if I remember correctly it's kind of a nice crash as crashes go
because it doesn't kill anything like if it crashes when I save data
so you don't actually lose any fact, if I build here, oops,
You're J.
If I build here I think we're all good.
Yeah.
I'm not sure what it is, exactly.
It's something about when you run a make, there's some very specific
chance that you'll crash.
So yeah, this one.
Looks like it didn't save.
I'm not sure why.
So, it's a little bit different than mine because mine actually did
say, but I definitely deleted this, right?
So I'm not sure.
I do not know what it actually is, that causes it at some point.
I'll have to debug it, but yeah.
Or Alan will.
All right, so let's see here.
What do I want to do?
I want to get rid of the scope to record and now scope to record is
gone, so that's good.
Let's see what else we've got.
We've got it complaining about the fact that I initialize it.
That's true.
But goodbye.
So anyway, debug draw me menu, which I think we could just call like,
sort of draw HUD or something, which is a much better name for it
because it's drawing all of the trees we could escalate draw trees or
something like this.
I think that's better than debug draw me menu to say the least.
So I'm going to call that draw trees.
And then I'm going to compile that function is an old function that I
think we must have been trying to show how to walk something without
using recursion.
I don't know why we did it this way, it doesn't make a whole lot of
sense to me why it was done this way and so I think maybe we're doing
that are trying to keep from having to pass down a stack thing.
I don't even know.
But point being I don't think it's particularly interesting and so I
want to change it into a recursive function because I think it'll be
clearer for everyone to read and easier for them to understand.
If I do it in that fashion because we don't need these debug variable
iterators or any of this stuff.
So, debug variable iterator
Is this utility that we were using?
I don't actually know where it is.
Do you but variable iterator this thing?
Yeah.
And it's just like, I don't really want to have to deal with that.
I don't want that in the system.
I don't think we need it.
So what I'm going to do is, I'm just going to change this over to
being a standard recursive call.
Like it probably should have been, but I'm sure we had a reason why we
didn't do it that way.
Anyway, so once we get one of these groups, I guess what I could do is
call this Draught regroup or something, and then I can come in here
and say, let's grab this code that's actually used for drawing the
tree.
And I'll put it in here.
Okay, and let's see.
This stuff is just sort of the end code.
I don't know what the if one here is for I'm not sure why we wanted
that to be potentially turned off, but I guess that's something in
case we wanted to make it so that we don't always draw the interactor.
But we'll get to that in a second anyway.
So I'm just going to go ahead and sort of make that make that do its
thing.
And
And I'm going to say, yeah, debug State at why.
I'm not sure what that really is supposed to be doing at this point.
So I'm gonna add a little to do.
Casey, do we still want this at all?
In fact, I might just do a quick check to see if I can determine it
immediately and I can.
So that's just a useless.
Now, that we have the layout stuff happening, that's just a useless
variable and it can be trimmed.
Aimed.
So here we are in Draught regroup.
And what I need to do is I need to make Draught regroup, be sort of a
recursive function that will allow us to do it in two different ways.
So you can kind of see how this works if the link does not have any
children.
We'll be in this else case and in that case it's just going to execute
the element draw.
So that's kind of the bottoming out of the recursive function
automatically.
So we're already in a state where that would be fine.
So the only thing we really have to worry about is this case here,
where we draw the actual header for this option and then we look to
see whether or not we need to draw the children.
So I'm going to say, okay, we've got view collapsible
Fan it always.
I'm going to say.
All right, if we're doing that, expanded always call, then what I'm
going to do is I'm going to call myself recursively.
So I'm going to draw a tree group again and I'm going to well I should
probably have saved exactly what these two things are just so I don't
mess it up, although we probably could have figured it out.
If we look here you can see this link, chill children, Sentinel next
and
And linked to the central, that's the list of things that we would
want to Loop through, right?
So those are the those are the things we want to Loop through if I
want to.
In fact, I could just make that Loop happen here.
Even in fact, I think I probably will.
So
I'll just say this is like, maybe I'll just call this something more
generic, like draw tree link or something like that.
And then inside here I'll call Draught relink recursively with
whatever the status is.
So I know that this Loop itself would be a debug variable link, and I
know this is like a sub link of me.
It's like a child of mine.
Sweet.
Child of Mine.
Okay.
Little concert roses for you, they're not
Really good Guns and Roses there.
So, you know, your mileage may vary.
But you know, I'm just saying Guns and Roses.
So assuming that the sub link is not equal to the Sentinel
Hello, there we go.
Assuming that the subject is not an essential.
I want to keep chasing its next pointer.
Like so, and and drawing tree links as I go, so I need to pass them
stuff to this.
Obviously, when we're drawing things we need like the rendering Group,
Well actually do we need to read the rendering groups just known all
the time.
Right.
I mean, do we even ever pass this?
No, we don't.
So we don't really need the render group.
That's a farce.
That's a lie, a ruse, a falsehood if ever, there was one
So I'm actually going to say no to that and put this here.
And then, I'm going to go ahead and say that we pass that layout.
Right?
Because it's going to open a layout and we're going to need that
layout to lay out the items as we go.
So, you can see, this is a very standard sort of pattern that I often
have, in the code.
You've seen it many times, I'll just call it out here because we never
call it out.
It's basically like a three-part method of function calling, right?
There's the sort of contextual there's the global contextual state,
which is just anything.
That's effectively a global variable.
For all intents and purposes but it's a global variable.
That's only relevant to a particular section or thread or whatever.
So you don't actually want them to be Global's.
You want them to be more narrowly scoped than that.
But in on the whole that's what this is.
This is a pointer to essentially or Global variables.
Then you have a pointer to what are effectively your local variables.
So for this option, for this pass through things, we're laying out
stuff.
That second parameter is, essentially all of the information that's
tracked for the laying out of things.
And then finally,
Do you have the actual element that you're operating on whatever that
is?
Which in this case, is that debug link, right?
And so you can kind of see that's the idea.
Hopefully, that makes some sense to you.
Like I said, you see that a lot in code that I right I think you
probably see it a lot in code that other people are, right?
It's just kind of the way that you naturally tend to tend to be three.
Groups that you're looking at any given time, the immediate item the
context for the operation, and then the whole state for the system
that's relevant to this portion of the program.
So anyway, I'm going to go through here and call myself recursively.
Like I said, I'm also going to sweat profusely because it is really
hot in Seattle and I'm with the door closed in a room that is not very
well ventilated.
So, I'm going to go ahead and drop Draught relink recursively again, I
passed the layout.
I make sure the layout gets
Incremented on either side here because I want to sort of increase
that depth as I go through, but then I don't want that depth increase
to persist.
So of course, this layout is now a layout pointer.
And so anywhere, where the layout actually got used such as here is
going to be a pointer now instead, so actually these things have to be
changed a little bit round but otherwise most of this code can
probably remain the same.
So in addition,
I'm going to need this tree information because as I passed down this
tree, I sort of have two things that I'm operating on.
So it's going to be a little bit more complicated, right?
I sort of have two things.
Again, this is the operation context here.
This is the main context and then these are things.
I'm not bringing.
This tree is actually something that I'm passing separate as well.
Now it is effectively part of this.
So, really, I could, if I wanted to move the tree into the layout as a
thing that was known,
Because it doesn't vary, but I don't really think that's necessary.
So I'm happy to pass these two, right?
There's no penalty for me.
Passing them as, like, more stuff.
That's on that line.
It's just sometimes sometimes you'll see me collapse it down.
So, it's literally just one for this.
And the reason for that is I just get tired of having to have people
call through when there's just one recursive function.
You won't see me, do it that much because it's not a big deal to
maintain.
But when there's lots of functions that all take them then, like I
would start to get
Annoyed about the fact that I passed the layout and the tree when I
could have just snuggled the tree in, with the layout.
So, anyway, just a little thought process there.
So, okay, moving on.
Again, the only things that I'm really doing.
Here are just cleaning this stuff up.
We've got the frame ordinal.
Now something that we're also going to want to put up here which one
reviewing.
So we'll get that going.
We got the render group here.
That's going to come from the debug State, and so I'm just going to go
ahead and pull that out.
Out as well.
So here's sorry, render group render group.
Like so, and that's probably an and we've got that at.
Why that doesn't have to happen anymore.
Draw trees, doesn't take the render group and so we can delete it and
then we're back to where we started.
All right, so let's see what we've got.
Step in here.
Handmade debug handmade.
Debug.
Where is my draw, treat?
Well, actually, you know what?
I could just call Raw tree link.
Wait, wait.
What?
Is it not called Joshua link?
It is called draw tree link.
Oh,
I can't step into something that doesn't get called.
You're going to have to admit that, right?
So draw tree link, got to take the debug State.
It's got to take the layout which we have, it's got to take the tree
and then it's got to take that route Group, whatever it is.
So a, debug variable group.
In this case, I guess that what does that actually have in it that
actually has one of these guys.
So we're actually starting out with one of these.
If we're starting out with one of those, then it might be better for
us too.
Well, I guess it doesn't really matter to be honest.
It's pretty easy for me to just do this and, and it's fine.
And it's a little Annoying to have that happen but it's okay.
So here's our group.
And here's our group, we go and let's see.
So, okay.
So here is all of our stuff and it appears to be rendering correctly
pretty much exactly as it was before with all of the fanciness.
You'll notice that already has fixed one bug that we sort of had,
that's been there for a long time, which is that the depth was
incremented on the first time through, so that
Even though this is, this is supposed to be left flush.
Like it is, it was always indented over and so, that's good.
So we fixed that which is one thing that is obviously nice to fix.
So okay, we're getting there.
We're getting there.
So, yeah.
So that's a, that's all well and good.
What I'd like to do now.
Potentially is is maybe get some kind of a notion of like, you know.
Well, I'm trying to think of like how we might want this stuff to
work.
Like, now that I've got this drawing in a more saying way, I'm trying
to think of is how I want this.
This
Some to behave in terms of editing it now, one thing I could do,
right?
It's I could go the wimp style and I could make these like little
windows that you move around, but I don't really like having things
work that way.
I don't really like having sort of, with
Style stuff.
And the reason that I don't like that is because it's really nice to
be able to win.
I'm not, you know, like I mean think about what the window that
encloses.
This is right.
I like not drawing crap over the game because a lot of times, you
know, we're trying to look at the game like we're looking at the game
and maybe we've got some stuff up and we want to be able to see as
much of the game as possible.
Right.
I mean, like think about the situation where we're just trying to view
this, this thing here, you know maybe I want
To sort of get rid of as much of this as possible and just have this
this thing up and that's it, right?
And so I really don't want to make like a bunch of business that's
like window.chrome that's like preventing me from seeing stuff.
So I like the fact that these things are not are not like sort of
heavy in that sense.
So what I'd like to do is I'd like to sort of think about that for a
second and and make a system that allows me to do
You a little bit more with with sort of arranging these things when I
want to or how I want to, I'd like to make something that allows me to
do that a little bit better and doesn't require any sort of more kind
of ridiculous stuff.
The other thing that's a little bit and this was mentioned before the
other thing that that might be true is you know, if I arrange some of
these things,
I don't know why that.
So, it's drawing behind I got to make sure those things draw on top.
Another thing that's true is, you know, if we create something here,
that's kind of the layout for the interface that we, you know, that is
how we want it.
To go.
One thing that's kind of a little confusing is well, you know,
Do we want to save that somehow, you know, is that something we want
to be able to save and that's kind of another open question.
Thinking the answer is probably, no, but we'll see.
So yeah, so in general, I'm just trying to think about that and how I
might want to do that.
And similarly, if you kind of look at the way this works, I feel like
it's a little bit broken to in that.
You always kind of get when I tear off something, or when I'm talking
about one of these things, it indents, the things inside it, which
would make sense
If it wasn't the root of the window, but since it is, the root of the
window, it makes me think that.
Really, when we do that tear off, we probably shouldn't bother cloning
that root element at all.
And these should really just be the things that you tear off, because
this is not a relevant piece of of UI anymore for this thing, right.
So, let me think about that for a second.
So here is the tear value bit.
And when you do the chair value, but you can see that we do at Riyadh
and we pass it.
A route group and the route group presumably is cloned off of the
particular variable.
Yeah, you can see, it's whatever this link is but we're assuming that
that link is either itself, a group or like I guess what we're saying
is if that link is itself, a group, we really want to clone probably
Just the stuff inside it.
So I'm going to go ahead and take a look at what we do including
variable group.
Oops.
Variable group.
so, curious clone variable group, and
Pretty much what it does, is it clones the children if it's got them.
Right.
And so it kind of doesn't do what we would want it to do.
It, actually, there is no way to say just clone the children of this
thing and input them into like a rude group here.
And so,
when we create this route group,
I guess, one thing that I'm not really sure about.
Is why it's still getting drawn either?
because riddle me this when we do draw tree link,
Remember, we did it sort of two different ways when we Loop over the
trees, we don't draw the name of this group.
So that, that top group, the group of the tree should never have its
name drawn.
So actually, what I just said, I wanted to have happen, should
actually be what's happening and I'm not really sure why it isn't
happening.
So I feel like we need to investigate and find out what the deal is
there because I'm not sure that I understand what that is.
I'm so I'm going to just jump in here for a second and I want to see
when we come to this code.
I want to see what's going on.
So, I'm going to open this up like I did before.
And I'm going to clone the Senate this entity over here and I'll leave
it open.
And then I'm going to come in here.
I'm just going to say.
Alright, let's take a look at what's going on.
So, here's the tree.
Here is its group.
Here is the name.
Cloned so it looks like, okay?
So when we do that clone
Their value.
When we do this clone, are we doing something?
That is the call, right?
There's only one call.
Yeah.
Interesting, interesting.
So we create a variable group.
And then we owe.
So where does creating a synthetic variable group for?
Absolutely no reason whatsoever.
So that makes very little sense to me.
I think what we actually wanted to do here was say that if this vist
thing already was a group, then we wouldn't do this, right?
So, I think what we really wanted to say was debug variable group
result.
And then we would say, if Source children, in fact, I guess we would
just say this here is the result, right?
All right.
I guess I shouldn't say the result.
The thing that we want to clone like this is the Clone me clone
Source.
We want to clone this Source children thing, right?
If the Clone Source or maybe, maybe I think I had to say this.
I don't want to create a new group if I don't need to write.
So instead of doing is create for a loop, this clone variable link
which returns a very building to me that will actually produce the
variable group that I wanted.
When I do the Clone write it.
Let me, let me show you what I'm talking about here.
So, here is the variable link situation, right?
And here is the variable group.
Now, why these two things are separate?
I don't really know because probably we could just convince them.
I mean, what it's the say for sake of one extra pointer it.
In fact, like I don't even know why those two things are different.
you know, there really is, absolutely no reason why those two things
would be different
I think I might just collapse them.
There's really no reason for that because all we really need to say
is, well, okay, we've got a debug variable link and here's here it is.
There's the children, right?
We don't need to look at that child porn or we could just use the
Sentinel, right?
That's that's really, that's it.
And there's really no need for this at all.
I don't think at least I don't see why there would be and then, you
know, if we want a separate
Here we can put one and then just not use it.
It's like like I said, it's one extra pointer.
It doesn't really seem like a big deal and we're just adding
complexity for no reason.
So if you look at these here right then instead of you know groups
these would just be anywhere you see group you would just substitute
a link.
Right?
And that should do it.
Now, it's going to take a little bit of love.
A fussing.
Ah, but I can't do that, right?
That is the real reason.
It's I just wanted to use the trick of having a doubly linked list.
Sentinel.
Well I can still do that and not have the added complexity.
All I have to do at that point.
I suppose is it continued and doing here?
Where was I?
There you go.
I guess all I really have to do is make sure that these are
That.
Is annoying.
You can see what the problem is, right?
I don't want this to be a separate thing, because there's no reason
for to be a separate thing.
But because I'm using the convenience of this being a doubly linked
list, you just make the Sentinel by including one of these in the
group.
But
That's just kind of annoying and it's just an implementation detail,
right?
It's a thing.
That's like, I don't really, it's just makes it a little bit easier.
To be able to do that.
So what I would rather do you know what I'd rather do, is this and
this would be, you know this is the kind of thing that you wish to
language did for you but it doesn't what you want to do is this and
just actually point when you initialize at the Sentinel, you want to
point it at this at this point are here, right?
Kind of nasty but that's what you would do.
And
I'm going to do it because I don't like having these being multiple
things.
I don't think there's any reason for it so I'm going to get rid of it.
So anyway,
Let's go ahead and change it.
So, in this case, for example, instead of
Anything where we would do sentinel next, right?
Actually, what we would do and in fact, what I can do as well to make
this a little clearer, I can make a thing that's like debug variable
link.
Sentinel.
And I can make this do the the Ridiculousness that would make it
appear as if it's a sentinel.
So, here's my from field.
This is my debug variable ink that I'm talking about and I'm just
going to say well, whatever the first whatever this guy is right here,
right?
That's essentially where I actually want to pretend the pointer is
Right.
So basically I've got this pair and I want to pretend that this pair
is essentially this pair.
Does that make sense?
I'll move this guy down here so you can see it a little better.
So yeah, it's not really a debug variable link, it's a fake one that
just exists right here.
For the purposes of, you know, making are doubly linked list work.
Yeah.
So, let's go ahead and make that happen.
All of these remain the same basically, debug variable group, just
changes to debug variable link pretty much everywhere it's used.
So, and then in here, same thing, really?
Start with all of these are going to be links.
Okay?
And then everywhere that we were using a sentinel before we can, if we
want to literally just turn them into a get Sentinel call or what did
I call it?
Let's call it.
Get Sentinel.
And that's really it.
So we can just use the get Sentinel call and get the Sentinel same
thing in this case here get Sentinel.
Very good.
Yeah, Sentinel and
Song.
What is it complaining about?
Get Sentinel.
Cannot convert.
Oh right I don't actually need that because that's going to
automatically done for me.
So inside here want to assert that this link does not have children.
So that's just saying that the link first equals get Sentinel.
So it's, it's empty.
There's all that's trying to say.
And you know what I could do to?
I could make that be a thing as well.
so, if the link first is not equal to
The.
Sentinel.
and yeah, so I can just say if this guy has children do your thing,
Groups, don't want semicolon there, and that's about it.
So, let's see.
This is the Draught relink.
So, if we're going to get the text out of the sky, then we can
actually just use this name directly and that's fine.
In here again, we want the get Sentinel actually, I guess we don't
even need that.
If we don't want to do, we can start using these directly when we know
what we're doing.
So like this link is first.
And you know what, I might call these first child and last child
As well, just to make it a little clearer, what we're talking about.
Okay, and let's see.
So this is get Sentinel.
And yeah, that's really just what that is.
in this case, we've got
Again another group we're just going to want the first child, and then
here, we're going to get the Sentinel again.
With the group actually makes this most of that iteration code
actually look much nicer.
So, here is the get Sentinel on the parent.
initializing the children part of things, this part we're going to
have to kind of actually do now, because this is a little bit more
specific
Add element to group will be done here.
The link that we add needs to have its children initialized.
I guess, although I suppose I suppose this push struct here.
Well, I guess it is a push truck so that element to group is actually
initializes it so cure.
When we do this, we would set first child equal to last child, which
is all equal to the get Sentinel on the link.
We then have ad group to group.
This is doing essentially the same thing when we're adding group.
Again, we're just adding one of these things.
We now long no longer really have to talk about adding groups to
things though for the most part, because basically anything that you
ad,
Excuse me, is going to be a link, so this is really as creates a link.
This doesn't need to create a link because it already is a link.
So this one is kind of a little bit on a little bit nonsensical.
So I mean really, this is just going to, this doesn't have to do a
push trucker any of those things.
This is just going to do this now and it's going to use that insert
and it's not going to do any of these things, right?
And it doesn't really need to return a link either.
So this is just like, add link to group and get you know, it's just
doing that.
So what to think about whether that even needs to be there anymore?
But anyway, create variable group, this is going to do exactly what we
would have expected it to do, and when it creates one of these, again,
it kind of wants to do what this thing is doing up here.
So, it's basically doing the exact same stuff.
It's going to do going to do this bit here.
When the group comes back, it's going to slice the child thing and
yeah that should do it.
Now again these things, I feel like this kind of wants to be
Or regular eyes.
Now I don't know what free variable group says, it's not implemented.
So I'm just going to go ahead and assume that we're going to will
Implement that some other time if we actually care about it.
I also don't know what ad region still doing there.
We haven't used that in years, so I'm just going to keep going here.
So we've got out element to group and and we've got a link to group
they both.
I'm sorry.
And we've got create variable group.
They both need to create one of these things.
Things.
And so, it's just a question of whether it's creating one or adding
one is an element.
So, I think, what I want to do is, is kind of make this guy be a
little more Primal where we just have create variable link, it's just
one thing now, it takes the name if you want it to have one and then
maybe it would take the debug element as well, if you wanted it to
store a debug element, all of these, if you want, can be,
Set to null, right?
You can pass 04 everything in there and that would be fine.
So I can even do an if name length on here, otherwise,
In fact, I guess I could do this.
And I don't know that might already do that.
I'm not actually sure.
In fact, let's take a look because I guess there's no sense in
duplicating code.
Here is handmade .h.
Oops, that's not right and made .h.
And me.
Yeah, push and I'll terminate you can see in here, what it's doing, it
pushes the size with the length and everything.
So push it it will terminate actually is always going to do that push.
So I think I am going to going to if it here.
So I'm going to say, okay, if there's name length of push it,
otherwise I won't, I have to initialize the other parts here, which is
the next in the previous, but that's where we're going to get handled
for me.
I guess delisted it does that does the first and last so I guess I
don't need that part.
I guess, I just say that.
Yeah, so I just say, okay.
Whatever my new link is initialize it please which does set the
pointer to point to itself.
The link itself does have the next and previous Parts which at the
moment, it's not going anywhere.
So I think we want the next the previous this 2.0 and then we want the
name to be with the name is.
So that's how we would create a variable link.
When we add this to a group, this one here we've got the parent and
the element and all that stuff.
I think all we want to do now is say, Okay, create variable link,
here's the debug state.
There's no name for it.
It does have an element, please make it for me.
And we can also make that link element come out and I'm trying to
decide whether I actually want that, maybe, you know, maybe we'll just
even do this.
And we'll just set that in here, right?
So that seems all good.
And then when we get to the rest of these, they just are always
calling that, right?
So, add element to group, does its thing.
All of these guys, basically, do its thing when we create one of
these, again, I think we would just call create variable link.
Instead of doing anything, fancier, it doesn't have a name.
This one doesn't.
So it doesn't have to do any of this.
And then we set the name ourselves.
It looks like
So we wouldn't want to clone it, which seems good.
And then we do our thing.
All right.
So that seems reasonable.
We're getting down to it, almost there.
Of course we've got some debugging to do to be sure, but you know what
you gonna do, Somebody's gotta bite the bullet.
So create variable link does not take four arguments.
I agree with you.
I got rid of one of them and get Sentinel of whatever our parent is.
There we go.
And this is, if the thing had children, I guess.
So, and let's see.
So in this case, we don't actually need to call this, I guess, because
we've already done Ed element to group and element group will create
the link for us that we need to add ourselves to.
So actually, none of this is necessary.
We can just say, well, whatever the thing is that we did if we had
children we just want to clone those children, right?
So really this is kind of academic.
We would just say we do the Clone and then we say if the source said
children we clone the children that's really all there is to it so
that should be simpler.
That's actually much easier than it is than than we were kind of
making it out to be same with that.
Let's see here.
When we do get a create group with name.
In this case, this is essentially the same situation.
This, basically, this actually seems to clean up the code, quite
nicely, in my opinion.
So far, I've liked everything.
All of the changes that have gone on.
Thanks to this collapsing of these two types down into one type.
So that's kind of nice.
Let's see if, if this has children was I guess what we were checking.
I'm not sure why we were checking it because I guess we,
Well, I guess you want to make sure that it wasn't a link with that
name that didn't have children.
I think we don't want that.
I think we just want to compare it.
Yeah, because we want to.
Yeah, I think so.
And so then we're going to say, well, here is the group.
If it matched then we're going to do a creeper oh group if it didn't
match and create an attitude to its parent.
So this is really great for the link again.
And add group to group and if are not found so ad group to group is
just add link to group, right?
That's the link to group.
Yeah.
So let me go ahead and change that.
I'd like to group.
Create variable group declare but not defined create variable group.
Where was that declared?
Was it up here?
And actually, no.
I'm in the wrong function, I mean the wrong file.
So here is our create variable group in our clone variable group free
declarations.
I hate pre decorations with a passion.
I was very glad to see that John did an incremental compiler so they
would not have this problem in j.i.
so we've got clone variable linked as one of our things we can do and
we've got what is it?
Create variable link.
I am.
So now we just want to fix those up.
So here is create variable link.
I'm sorry, clone variable link, it does not take two arguments.
What pray tell arguments does it take?
So it takes a desk group and a source.
so, I guess there was there's one that doesn't take
Yeah.
Actually two versions.
Clever and one is the one that we want to change that's kind of spur
and this whole situation for words, all right?
Keep on keeping on.
All right, so let's see here.
I don't realize the code was still running.
Let's get a fresh build of this and see where we're at.
okay, so to bug time,
our link name is no which is not fabulous.
so this is just because we're supposed to be, these are
This is yeah, we should just check the name there, that's actually
totally fine.
We're allowed to have no names there so really we just want this to
check.
I'm kind of surprised.
I feel like our strings are equal should actually take care of that
though.
I don't love that.
So I actually think what I would rather do is have our strings are
equal.
Handle that don't actually know where that is really got to implement
search in all files.
I have not had the chance to do that yet, but it's makes it really
hard.
I had that in emacs.
I haven't written it for for credit even though be pretty simple.
Just have had time.
So anyway, strings are equal.
I could actually just run fine sir if I wanted to just like the old
style, but I, since I can Implement directly in foreclosure, I felt
like it should probably be done that way, because it'd be better.
So I need to find our strings are equal but I'm not sure where it is.
and that means,
And where did I put that?
There it is.
So what I'd like to do in strings are equal when we pass these, what
I'd like to do is make sure that they handle like, for example in this
one, you can see that it handles the case where there's the word,
something's know, right?
So in this case, I would never be touching yet.
This, this function is basically really crappy.
This is not a good function because B can be null.
And it doesn't actually ever check for that, right?
So what we probably want to do is say something like, okay, we still
want the same strings are equal function like this one, but we want to
make sure that we're not yet.
I mean, I guess the way I could do this most easily would just be like
you know if if B then we do it the way we were doing it, right?
Not know why that's indenting the way.
It's indenting.
The Mysteries.
Okay, let's see.
The result.
Is false.
So we can do that the way we were doing it.
This could probably simplify it a bit, but just for the sake of making
this work at the moment.
If B is not valid, then we would just say the result equals a length
equal zero.
Cuz if there's no B, then that means that a is length had better, be
none, right?
That seems better to me because I would rather write I would rather
have that.
Do its thing.
That way.
Okay, so we have successfully made that change.
Our cloning is working again.
So that's all good.
Again, pretty simple change.
I just wanted to collapses down.
So now what I'd like to do since we're basically out of time, got
about 23 minutes left, I just want to go ahead and make that change
where I said.
So, like when I pull one of these things off, it actually just pulls
the group off, as its separate thing without leaving the header.
And so, in order to do that now,
Sorry, I kind of went off on a tangent there but I just want to clean
that code up in order to do that.
Now what I want to do is during the Clone operation you can see right
here, why we're having the problem when I say that I want to clone a
debug variable.
What I want to do is not ever have this happen.
I don't ever want to actually do any of this.
What I want to do instead is just do the direct clone and return it.
So I just want to do literally clone the
Course.
And now I can do that because they're all the same and we don't care
which one it's going to be right.
Whoops.
We allow this to be 0, right?
If I say add element to group,
Oh no.
We don't
So I could make that I'm trying to think of this should just be
untangled a little bit.
I want to be able to clone this thing and not actually pass it.
Anything for the desk Group which I could do a little slightly by just
making this support zero as the parent, but really,
These are sort of the same in that sense, if that makes sense.
I feel like this wants to be on Taylor and more.
I'll skip it for just a moment but then I think we should probably
untangle a little bit anyway.
So if we did add an element to group, you can see this is the part
that actually deals with the parent.
So I can just say, if I want to if parent here and this will just
work, but I feel like this needs to be untangled just a tad.
Now that we know what it looks like.
So now if I do something like pull off the the the profile now it's a
little more sane.
Now like the profile is just like a free-floating thing that doesn't
have an actual separate piece here and I think that's more what I
would like because now we always can actually draw the other part if
we want to, but we don't have to.
And I didn't like the fact that I had to write.
so similarly in here, if I'm like doing one of these things I should
be able to select one of these and
No, I can't.
Select these guys.
Yeah.
Oh, because we don't have precedence for those.
Yeah, that's never mind.
I do know why.
So, let's see if I can also clone of these.
Yeah, cool.
All right.
So, I'm going to call it there.
Gary Johansen.
I feel like I kind of lost the forecast or Forest.
I assume is what that was pretty autocorrect for the trees in this
episode.
Would you mind recapping
Sure.
So, here's what we did.
Two things I'll do miniverse order thing.
We most recently did is we had a struct that worked like this.
We had a previous pointer.
And we had a next pointer.
And the way that those worked is exactly the way you might expect.
They form essentially a ring.
So, you know, they point to each other.
Like this.
And they're looped such that this one points back to this one.
And this one points forward to this one.
So it's a ring.
And the way we were doing that is it's much easier to always have
something in the list so that you don't ever have a special case.
So what you typically do is you insert something called a sentinel and
in this case we had a sentinel
Which is just a dummy element.
That's the same as all the rest of them.
It's but it never gets removed and at the outset it just points to
itself.
So at the outset, right?
You have the Sentinel
Oops.
And it just points to itself.
So it's like this and this
and then when you come in here and you add a new item, right?
It happens to all just work because what happens is, you say, well,
okay.
I need to add a new item.
The rule for adding a new item is I just say, whoever the Sentinel is
make my previous pointer point to them right, which would do that.
Make my next pointer point to whoever his next pointer pointed to,
which is also him
Right because he's pointing to himself, then just follow my pointers
and fix them up.
So go to my
Yes, which is here, and make that next pointer point to me done, go to
my next and make that previous pointer point to me done.
And now we have a proper circular linked list again, right?
So in the startup case, it works and of course in every subsequent
case, it would also work.
And so adding, and removing from these lists is Trivial, because you
can just run the same stupid simple for line piece of code, every time
and it always just works when you have the
Oil in there.
You don't need to check to see if the list is empty and handle that
specially or any of the other things like that.
Okay?
But what this means is, you need to include the Sentinel itself in the
structure that's holding this thing.
So, typically what you do is you say, well, oh, I've got like a group
structure, you know, and I've got a link structure.
The link is the thing that stores, the preview, the next, and the
data, and the group is the thing that's like, you know, has whatever
the
Ms and Foo and bar, and whatever.
There's so much stuff in here and then finally, it just contains one
link and that link is the Sentinel.
So, there's one of these embedded in here.
And the data part is just ignored, that's how you normally do it.
But what if I now look at my code and I say, oh, hey gosh, these two
types are really just in the way I want them to all be the same.
There's no reason to have them be separate.
Well, you can't exactly do that because if you make these two types of
same, this type can't include
Food itself.
There's no way to have a group include a group, right?
But remember the only part of the link you actually need to make this
scheme.
Work is the previous and next pointers that's the only part that will
ever be touched out of the Sentinel.
Because remember all of these people, they all had data right.
There was always data in here.
And when you're talking about a valid link, like this one that data is
actually important but when you're talking about the Sentinel it never
gets referenced the sentence.
The definition of pointing to null essentially we always check right
in those Loops for you know link equal Sentinel or link equals first
child first, the link is not equal to the Sentinel do some stuff.
So we're always we're never going to operate on the central.
We're never going to look at this, which means the technically all we
need is that top two pieces.
So what I did is, I just lied and I casted a previous and next pointer
that I have in here, right?
I lied and I casted those to say that they were linked struct even
though the rest of the links truck isn't there,
Makes sense.
And so that's that code that you saw
up here.
See it.
So here is the next and previous pointer exactly as I drew them.
Here's the Sentinel for the links so each link can have its own list
inside inside of it.
These are what we would want to include.
We would have wanted to just type this
but we can't because it can include itself.
So, all I did is just said, well, these two things are the same as
these two things.
It's it creates essentially, the top, the header right there.
And then all I do is just lie and say, hey, that part right here is
one of those links went for purposes of the Sentinel, right?
so what this ends up creating
is something that looks like this.
Well.
You know, I'm gonna do, I'm gonna draw a little smaller.
It has of creating something that looks like this.
Here's my previous, here's my next.
Here's my first.
Here's my last.
And actually, you know what?
These are in the wrong.
Now that I draw this out, it's really should be last and first,
Oh no.
It's not.
It's correct.
It's because we had next and previous because it's whichever way these
go fits next.
Previous going to be first last, right?
So.
Sorry, let me, let me actually take a second to draw it, the way that
I actually wrote it down, so next previous first, last okay.
And then, of course,
The payload, oops.
Here's the data.
Okay, so what I did is, here is the struct and it's part essentially
of two rings, there's the Ring of its siblings.
So the things that are the same level of it in like this tree, right?
So I'm talking about like, these guys here.
Here we go.
Here are its siblings.
Here's the data first.
Last next previous, here's a it's pretty.
Its prior sibling one that came before it.
Data.
Next previous first.
Last okay.
And it is Chained like this.
There's that next pointer.
Here is the previous pointer here is the next pointer previous
To go somewhere, we don't know.
Here's the previous pointer pointing back to this one.
Okay and here's the next pointer pointing somewhere.
We don't know.
Okay.
Makes sense.
Now it's also part of another ring which is the ring of its children,
here is a children.
So this is its prior sibling.
This is its next sibling.
Guess I should say previous.
Previous.
And here is its last child.
And here is its first child, okay?
And watch carefully.
The first pointer points to the head of this guy, just like the next
pointer pointed to the Head.
Okay.
So here's the next pointer, here's the previous pointer, here's its
first child and its last child and its data.
Here is next preview.
First last data like so
And here this points, the last again points to the top of these guys,
okay?
But here's the trick.
These guys do not point to the top of this guy, if they did, it would
create one unified ring of all the siblings in the children.
Instead, they point to here, they point to the middle of the struct as
if it was the header but it's not.
Okay?
And that's how this thing works.
Make sense.
So it's kind of complicated to think about.
I guess it's the kind of thing since I do this sort of code all the
time that is Justin on thing to be like I just like yep.
That's how we'll make that pointer happen and off we go.
It's also the kind of thing that I get incredibly frustrated about
when people like make compilers that break this sort of thing, or when
they C++, language lawyer re or object-oriented stuff Miss and say
that don't do these sorts of things.
I hate that because it's like this is how CPUs work.
They don't know what a struct is.
A struct is just a thing that lets me create stuff, the CPU does and
this is cooler than whatever it was.
You were going to do.
This is cooler.
And I like it.
And it's not my fault.
If your language makes things like this harder to do that, just means
you designed it wrong.
You designed.
A crappy.
Language.
Not my fault.
Anyway, so yeah.
So anyway, point being that is how this works and so all I was doing
was just collapsing it down.
So I wouldn't have to think about two types anymore.
Everyone could just talk about a variable link and a variable link can
either have children or not and nobody care.
Like, I don't have to have a separate secondary pointer for no reason
to point off to nothing, right?
Last thing, so I guess was what were we doing first?
The thing that I did first today was I wanted to we were previously
doing a non recursive walk of this tree.
So we have a thing that's like Foo, you know.
Whatever.
So we have this tree and the tree has children, it's like a little,
it's a, you know, it's like a standard little list View, and you can
expand and collapse them, right?
And you've seen me play with this thing all the time on the stream.
It's this thing up here, right?
Where I can open it up and do whatever it is.
I'm going to do.
So, all that stuff is there, right?
And before we were doing this with what amounted to to me,
Our own stack so we just had like a for Loop you know.
I think it was actually a while loop not that it matters but you know
we just had a while loop and we had a stack here that we stored some
data with and we would like walk through this using our own local
stack and I was like I don't think there's any point in doing that I
don't know why we did that is directly.
I think we're just to show that you could or I don't know what we were
doing and I it just
I felt it would be easier to read and more easy to understand and
maintain because the stack is automatically managed for you by the
compiler.
If you just use the actual stack.
So recursion lets you use that stack and it because the compiler is
set up to more cleanly deal with that.
It's easier to read the code.
So what I did is I said, okay, forget the while loop instead, what
we'll do is use a recursive function.
So instead of before drawing everything inside the loop, what we do
now is we just have, like a thing that's like, draw a tree link.
All right, and we call it on one of these guys and it will Loop over
all of its children calling draw tree link on each of those.
So, if one of them happens to be we have children.
It will draw those recursively.
To make sense.
Dude and basement one thoughts on linked list and cash friendliness.
I found that a simple array and just hoping I'm assuming copying, when
it changes length was way faster.
So, I guess the things I would say about that is
I don't really like arrays and the reason I don't really like arrays
is because they are not or durable very well.
Like if I want to change the order of things in Array, I have to copy
the whole thing.
If I want to add something up to copy the whole thing and blah blah
blah.
And I just don't like that sort of movement of call of that.
Like, unreliability of the cost.
Like, I don't like having
Operations that are free.
Sometimes it really expensive, other times.
I just don't like it.
So if I'm actually performance, evaluating some code and I want to
know if this particular code is, you know, I want to try and find the
most efficient way to write this particular code.
Then I might try array vs.
Linked list and see
A lot of people say, the phrase to me, I have found that simple arrays
are much faster than click this or whatever.
I've actually, very rarely found that to be true.
In fact, when I was doing performance optimization on the witness, I
found that there is actually no difference between using arrays and
using linked lists at all.
And so, what I think might be sort of true there is, I don't know if
people are always comparing apples to oranges in that case, because I
think mostly mostly the cash friendliness of a linked list versus an
array.
There's no difference between the cash from this of the two unless
you're bigger than the size of the array of the, the cash.
And the reason for that is because let's say I have a link, right?
And the link has a next pointer.
Right?
Or I have an array and here's my raised like Link Link, Link Link.
Well however, much of this fits in the cache versus however, many of
these fish in the cache is going to be the same modulo however much
this cost you, right?
So if the answer is that this didn't that this didn't put you over
some
Ash limit for the size of the algorithm.
You're doing is, there's no difference between these two things,
right?
The difference that I think people see, is that unlike me?
I, you know, do push struct style stuff.
So all my links are all in the same place.
Anyway, right?
So if links are smaller than a cache line or something like this, they
all stack up right next to each other and are all on the same page,
right?
Because the links get pushed right on top of each other, all in a row.
So they're basically already an array.
What other people do is every time as they call New and who knows
where this puts the link.
So the links are probably scattered throughout memory in every which
way, right?
So, at that point, that means that, however, big the link is right?
If the link structure is however many bites well, now whatever the
amount of the cache line.
So it's you know, 64 bytes is the cache line size, right?
So however big the thing is
I'm divided by 64, bytes.
And then, the overhang that amount here is always polluting the cash,
which could be significant.
Like, let's say you make a 68 B structure, right?
Now, you're polluting the cash by 62 B.
Every time, right?
Which is a lot of extra cash flow, whereas I am polluting it by 8 B.
Every time, you know, maybe 16
And so I feel like when people say linked lists are way, worse
performance.
I don't know if they're really talking about it, right?
Maybe they are.
And maybe they were talking about a situation where it was really
super high performance critical.
Obviously you want to not have any anything extra.
So at that point you may decide that if you know how big the array
should be and you know that you're not doing a lot of shuffling that's
going to be better.
No question about that.
And I would never tell somebody you should use a linked list for
performance, right?
Those were
Aren't going to probably come out of my mouth.
Unless there's a lot of shuffling going on.
That makes it so that an array is somehow prohibited.
But you know again unlikely
But I do often questioned the people who seem to think that a razor so
much more performance than linked lists.
Because I've actually never found that to be the case.
Are they faster know, are they slower sometimes but often not by much
and so at that point, I would rather just have the consistency of
knowing that there's no expensive operations, they're all the same and
I have no memory bound weirdness, right?
So, I know that like I don't suddenly have to guess about how much
memory am allocating or where this thing is going to go.
That's kind of nice too.
So I tend to yeah I tend to not have problems with linked lists other
people maybe do maybe I just don't tend to use them in performance
critical situations so it doesn't matter.
And I'm just kind of like living off of the slop and don't care.
I'm not sure, but I just rarely find it to be that big of a deal if
that makes sense.
And pseudonym 73, second currency also matters.
Linked list can be better if you need multiple threads work on the
same time.
Absolutely 100% agree with that.
Arrays are real bad.
In that sense because now you've got a situation where like I got a
lock down the array.
Any time I add something to it because I got to do this whole copy and
I got to wait for everyone to clear out of it as well.
There's all kinds of stuff that goes on there.
Whereas linked list, you just do one quick interlock to get off
something and that's it.
You know, you touch it for maybe a cycle or two.
Cuba.
Caleb, how do you feel about object?
Pools is a sort of Middle Ground between linked lists and arrays.
I don't have a strong opinion about this stuff and like I said, you
know, I'm not trying to tell people to use linked list, like don't
take this as like some kind of Link this advocacy.
I'm just saying that like the hype of like, always use a raise or
whatever better like this.
I don't know that that's really true.
And I haven't seen the definitive analysis of anyone that suggests,
that linked lists are somehow not a good tool to use and that they're
somehow
Add.
So I feel like, you know,
if you care about performance, you need to time it, you need to see
what your operations are.
You need to think about it in time, it that's just true.
And whether linked lists are arrays or or come out on top or whether
the it doesn't seem to matter much.
The only way to know is to do that in the case, where you don't really
care that much.
What the performance of this thing is, it's not really a critical
thing.
Then I just have not found linked list to be problematic.
Like I haven't had that situation where I'm like oh my God, these
linked list cause my program to be so slow.
And there was like nothing I could do about it, or like the whole
thing is ruined, right?
I haven't really had that.
And similarly, it tends to be pretty easy to go.
Oh, these were linked lists.
I want to change them to a raise, okay?
Like usually, you can just do that.
It takes a day or two to of deciding how you want to arrange it, or
whatever, and do the work and Port the code.
If it's used in tons of places, maybe, but that's it.
I mean, you do it in son so I usually don't find it makes much sense
to even think about.
So I usually write the one that's easier for me to use.
At the time.
If that makes sense.
And a lot of times this stuff, I met a generate anyway.
So at that point, it's less about me, thinking of this.
I might just pick.
Oh, this should be this.
This should be that.
And I don't think about it much when I'm hand coding stuff.
A lot of times, our razor, more of a pain to encode.
I find and the pointers into them aren't stable which I also find
being to be bad, you know, if I delete something from an array, all
the pointers change and that kind of stuff.
And so there's just there's a lot of things.
I don't like about a raise.
I think.
As a data structure, I don't really like a raise for.
Editable or mute or changing stuff.
And so I usually prefer linked list unless I can really point to a
case and go.
I care about the performance here, though.
The array is clearly Superior.
I'm going to use it, right?
Because it just adds all this fuss.
That I don't like
Alright, I'm at a time.
Wait, there are
All right.
Thank you everyone for joining me, for another set of handmade here.
It's a pleasure coding with you.
As always, if you would like to follow along the series on your own at
home, you can always pre-order the game at hand made here at or get
comes with the source code so you can play around with it.
We also have a forum site, you can use to ask questions to patreon
page.
If you want support the video series at week, Bob the tweets the
schedule.
And I went this weekend, this is how much I love you.
Handmade hero audience, I even went this weekend and
And which Linux distribution was running on the server, so I could add
the tweetbot to the boot scripts.
So the tweetbot should be like, indestructible now because the tree,
but as far as I know, has never gone down, but it was never in the
startup sequence.
So, anytime they rebooted my server, it killed the tweetbot because it
wouldn't come back up.
I would have to log in and restart the Tweet, but because I didn't
know where the startup scripts were, on this particular version of
Linux.
Now that I know I put
Um, in there and I tested that this weekend.
So now both the GitHub authenticator and the Tweet bot, which again,
literally I know of not a single time they have ever gone down.
Well, now actually appear as reliable as they should have appeared,
which is to say never going down.
Because when they reboot my server for reasons, I have no idea.
Power failure, I guess, I have no idea, they will come back up without
me having to manually log back in and restart them.
How's that for 95s, reliability for you?
That's about it.
I will be back here tomorrow at 5 p.m.
Pacific Daylight time.
If you would like some more programming action, sweet, programming
action, until then have fun programming and I'll see you guys on the
internet.
Take it.