Hello, everyone, and welcome to handmade hero.
The show, we go to complete game live on stream on Twitch.
No engines, no, libraries, just us, and our typing fingers, right now,
we are in the middle of converting our game from using just loading
bitmap and wav files off disk to using a asset file like a pack file
of our own creation.
And we are about halfway through writing a test version of that.
And so today, what we're going to do is finish the piece of test
It writes out an asset file that we can then start loading in to the
game.
So yeah, not a lot to talk about because we've already talked about
all the concept involves.
So really we just need to finish coding.
It it's day 149.
So if you would like to follow along at home, you are going to want to
follow along with day 148 source code, unpacked into directory and
you'll be exactly where I am at right now.
So if I go ahead and pull back up the code here that we were using
test asset.
Elder we step through it yesterday and got it to the point where it
was essentially writing out most of the asset file header, except for
the asset array itself.
And what we wanted to do now was actually write out the asset array.
And in addition to the asset array, we also want to basically, you
know, include the assets themselves in here to write, obviously that,
you know, make some reasonable sense, right?
so,
What we would like to do here is we would like to have something that
spins through the assets.
And writes them out and actually puts in the asset array that also
tells where they are and if you remember the way we did this asset
array in the file, this is not what I wanted at all.
I want this asset file formats, right?
The way that we decided to do that is we have this hhas hhas at here
and that ha asset is going to be written to the file in a way that
tells us where the data for the thing is where the tags for it are and
how many that there are right.
And inside there is either going to be the definition of the bitmap
that we need, which would be the dimension and the alignment.
Or if it's a sound, it's going to tell us
Well, you know what, we really don't need first, sample index.
I don't know what that's doing there.
There's just a number of samples.
And whether this is changed with another, you know, some other sound
in the system, right?
So that's really all we actually need, it's really pretty
straightforward.
And so what we need to do now is just actually write this stuff out,
we're essentially writing out all the other things, we're just not
reading out this and so what I'd like to do is actually
You write it out.
Now, if you look at the way that we wrote out the other arrays, what
we did is we had them in memory exactly.
As they would be in
I'll and remember files and memory are like the same thing, right?
A file is just a permanently stored version of memory there.
They're just B.
There's nothing magical going on there, right?
There's just a bunch of cruft involved in actually like getting them
out to a solid state drive, or hard drive or whatever.
But in the end we're just talking about storing binary data, just like
the kind that we've been deploying memory.
There's no magic to it.
So, when we do a write like this, right?
We're just saying, take this block of memory, put it to the drive and
later on, you know, in the game.
I'm going to want to put
Get back in as it is right?
And so the thing is, these were just written out as big fat blocks
because we happen to have the race exactly as we want them to be in
this case as I go through the assets, I haven't actually prepared an
asset array yet because I haven't gone through all the assets and
figured out where they will be stored.
Because remember when we when we're looking at where each asset will
go in the file, you know, it's this big long linear series of bytes.
I have
Put each asset like after one another.
So if I write out the first bitmap and the second pick up the third
bitmap, the third bit maps, location is going to be dependent on how
big the first and second bitmap in the file were right.
And so, I don't really know what the data offsets are till after I
write the other thing.
So, there's two ways we could choose to handle this and I think I'm
going to handle it in a simpler way.
There's two ways you can choose to handle it one way we could choose
to handle.
It is write all the assets out.
But leave space in the file for the asset header.
Sorry, the asset array and then go back and write the asset array out
as a chunk.
I don't think I'm gonna bother doing that.
What I might do is just do the simple thing of writing out the asset
array as individual pieces as we go and write the actual Assets in
because we know where the assets will start, right.
We already figured out where the assets will start, because it's
whatever this location is, plus the size of the asset array is the
Free available B in the file.
Right?
So what I'm going to do is I think I'm just going to go ahead and loop
manually over the asset set, right?
So I'm going to start with asset index 0.
I'm going to go through the number of assets that we have, and I'm
going to do using a Sikh and this is very this is you know kind of
inefficient way to do this, but again, we don't, this is not code that
we care at all about.
It's never going to run on the end users machine.
This is just well, first of all, it's test code.
Even
For us but it's our asset file creation stuff which only happens on
our machine and we don't care at all unless it becomes some kind of a
production problem how slow it is, right?
So we don't really have to care about how efficient or inefficient
this.
Maybe we don't care at all.
So what we need to do here is we basically need to do our own kind of
streaming, right?
We need to do our own location tracking.
Because what we want to do here is we want to jump to the part of the
file where this particular asset goes.
Whichever one it is.
We want to write out the data there for the actual asset.
So the bitmap
Pixels, if it's a bitmap or the sound samples at the sound and then we
want to like jump back right to the asset array and put it in there.
You know what?
Now that I think about it, it's not actually any easier doing it that
way.
Really?
If we just do one F seek to put ourselves past where the acid areas, I
think the thing I said first is actually better, right?
Because then what we would do is we just fseek stream out all the
Assets in in order, right?
And then jump back to where the asset array is and write it out there.
That seems actually totally fine.
So there we go.
All right, I changed my mind in the middle of describing.
Even what I was going to do.
So there you go.
All right.
So, what we want to do here is we've done enough, right?
And we could almost even, you can see what we're essentially doing is
instead of f writing out the asset array here.
We just because, like I said, these, we can't give it the position to
write at it's going to write wherever at the end of wherever the last
right was?
That's just how the C API works.
Even though that has nothing to do with how hard drives work at all,
that is how they chose to implement it, probably, because they were
thinking of tape, drives or terminal streaming or something.
Like
Back in 1970 or whatever, but point being that is not.
We wanted also what we wanted to be able to do is say let's just skip
the place for the asset or a is we could just write out what garbage
there and then come back and write it later.
But we might as well not tell the operating system to do work.
It doesn't have to do.
So we want to do is be able to do this thing fseek, right?
And what fseek does is fseek allows you to move the file position that
c is thinking about
In its standard library to a different location without actually
writing anything.
And you can see it allows you to specify sort of the way in which you
want it to move.
And you can see it's definition here, right?
So you pass that file handle that we're talking about.
So, knows, which stream it's talking about, you pass a value that sort
of the, the amount you want to move, but that amount doesn't actually
mean anything.
Until you look at the third parameter, which says how you want that to
be?
It, and there's three ways you can do it.
You can say, Seek set.
And if you say Seek set, it will seek to that absolute B in the file.
So, if you say 5, you're talking about the 5th, B, in the file total,
you can say Seeker which is like saying, oh, let's go ahead and say
wherever I am right now, add this many bytes to it or subtract in the
case of a negative number, right?
And then finally see Ken says, start at the end of the file wherever
the last bite was written to the file in its history.
I want to start there and move from there.
So if I want to like back up a bit from the end of the file, I can do
that.
Right?
And so what I'm going to do is I'm going to basically just say I know
the asset array size.
Is this big, right?
I know that's how big the asset array size is.
So I'm just going to say from the current
Mission.
Right?
I would like you to skip however many that was and get to the next
location in the location.
The file that would start immediately after that, right?
Then I'm going to spin through the asset arrays.
I'm going to write out each individual asset, right?
And then when I get to the end, I want to seek back to this location,
right?
So now I want to be able to say you know what?
Go go seek back to asset array location.
And it just so happens that I already know that as well, because we
store that in the header, right?
The place where the asset array was, we already sort of Saved because
we had computed where we wanted everything to be laid out, right?
So, that's all good.
So this is going to be pretty straightforward.
There's not a whole lot to it.
It's all good.
There's only one caveat.
And you the compiler will complain about it.
Presumably actually for us and that is that we are using 64-bit file
offsets and a fortune.
Unfortunately, the C API doesn't actually support 64-bit file sets.
So in this case, we don't care.
Because in this case, we happen to know that this is not going to be
outside, the 4 GB range that the beginning of the file.
So in this case, we can just do that if we want to write.
But if you wanted to be able to handle seeking,
Very large files, you have to kind of go off book a little bit and
there are various things like L seek and sort of these other things
that take larger offsets for 64-bit files.
I'm going to leave that as an exercise to the reader because like I
said this is only test code and when we're actually, when we are
actually doing our reads from this file, we will not be using the C
runtime Library will be going straight through windows and doing IO
completion.
Port overlapped i0 which
Has no bearing whatsoever on any of this stuff.
So in this case, this is totally fine but just so you know, there are
actually sort of newer more recently introduced things that are I
don't even know if they ever actually became see standards but they
are kind of de facto standards.
Like you, there are ways that you can use the C runtime library to
handle 64-bit offsets if you really care to do.
So we will not be doing that on him made here.
So all right.
Now we've got this this, this asset array, right?
We've kind of got a problem here, which is that this asset array, that
we're writing out the asset array is a different array than this one.
Because this this asset set we made here is actually just a record of
like the files.
We wanted to read from.
Right but it's not it's not actually the asset array that we really in
fact actually want it.
And so what I might do just to make it a little bit more
straightforward is I think I'm going to go ahead and bifurcate this
and say that we have the at the hhaa asset set, right?
And these are the assets that are in the file and this is like the so
we have like assets.
This is an asset data or something like that, right?
And so our actual asset that we store in here is just probably, you
know, we don't all of this stuff will actually be well, I guess it's
these right.
The only things that we might have right.
Is, is this right?
We have something like this.
These are the pieces of information that we might need.
In addition to what we had.
And you know the other thing we might need is asset type and it would
be like oh you know this and I guess we could even just do well I'll
do it this way you know asset type sound and asset type bitmap because
since the game already knows what they are but we don't actually know
in this asset processor except when we actually announced them we
might need something like this so that's all the additional data that
we need right.
That's only used for processing and is not
Saved in the file.
So that way we can just fill out our asset sources, right?
We could say assets or something like that.
We can just fill out our asset sources and our asset data together.
We write out the asset data and we never bother writing out the asset
sources because that's just markup, right?
And so that's that's what we're talking about, right?
So we would say, here asset data, right?
And we would write that out.
And then in here, we would go ahead and grab these things hhas set.
Let's see HHA, right?
This will be like Source dust maybe even you could say.
So we've got these guys and I'm just going to grab out the pointers
from from the actual assets that just so we can talk about them a
little bit more easily in this code, right?
Alright, so here we go, you've got these guys ready.
And what I'm going to do now before I actually implement this, as I'm
going to fix the compile errors, that will be generated from from this
change that I made where I say that.
I want these two things to be split.
And so what I'm going to do is I'm going to I think I want to kind of
make this a little bit less.
A little bit less pointer oriented if you will.
So I want to kind of see how these guys are getting used.
I want to say that this debug asset also, I guess we don't really need
to do that, but this is going to be essentially a asset index.
Now, write something like this, and I'm going to go ahead and clean up
these compile errors so that that all works.
All right?
So what we want to do here is say that our what did we actually call
these our asset data?
Maybe I'll leave
leave that as asset so it can still be used in most places.
So what I want to do here is I want to change these routines to work
in sort of the split format.
So I've got, you know, my assets source and I've got my
Asset.
And those two things are different, right?
And these things here, I guess all can stay roughly the same.
That's all similar.
Don't think there's anything there groups.
And I got to have a differentiating name for these guys.
So, I'm going to call these source and desk for the moment as well.
Because I just don't know if that's the way I'm thinking of them.
All right, so well, maybe we'll do it this way.
Maybe I'll do it that way.
I think that's a little
it clear.
All right, so in the HSN, the AHA, we've got it looking like this,
right?
I think all of that stuff is, is correct, and when we do the sounds,
The Sounds would be similar, right?
We come through here and we've got the HH, a version set up this way
and we're going to go ahead and pull out the parts now that
Our that are in only the source.
So there is the source for a bitmap is just the file name.
That's all there actually is.
And then we've got the type, right?
I said we were going to have the type is asset type bitmap.
And then down here, we've got that file name.
And for a sample Index, right?
Those are both.
Those are both part of just the source like so.
And then we again we want to set that type.
Two asset type sound.
Okay?
And this is Jay's well this should be debug asset.
So this right here is just a assets asset index equals results dot
value, right?
And we're going to track that.
So in both cases so
and guys up,
Left of value and sound next ID to play is just that now.
Alright?
So we want to assert that debug.
That the asset Index right is not equal to 0.
So we do we do actually still want to do this assertion because that's
the null asset.
So we want to still check that.
And then here, what we would need to do is the asset itself would have
to be sort of grabbed out of that.
In order to do the increment, here, we have to actually have the
assets or so.
This would be h a asset asset guess we'll call it h.
A to be a little more consistent HHA equals assets.
Asset sources plus asset index.
Yeah, and the oops not assets horses, just assets.
yeah, and so
That's all good.
And just gotta clean up couple other things here.
Nothing particularly unusual going on.
All pretty.
Basic this is actually dot value.
And there we go.
Asset source.
And I think that's it.
Thank, that's it.
So yeah, that is pretty much it I think and that will in theory write
out everything correctly.
If in here we actually did asset processing which we're not doing yet
but that's what we're about to do.
So I'm going to go and run that and see make sure there's no
particularly odd things going on there.
And then I'm also going to Der are handmade data directory to kind of
see what is happening there.
There is our test dot h.
A, i don't know if that's the right size or not.
I would have to think about whether it is or not, we don't have that
many things in it, so it seems semi plausible will have to check to
see if that all makes sense.
So anyway, let's go ahead and finish implementing this stuff and so
inside our handmade asset now is the time when we would be moving out
like that.
Bitmap code, right?
So we have handmade asset dot CPP and you can see we've got like the
bitmap header and the wave header, and all this stuff, right?
So I'm not going to delete it from the game yet, but it's going to get
deleted from the game, right?
Like that's eventually going to go away.
So for now, what we're going to do is we're going to do is top down
the line.
We're is that actually it's not even used anymore, right?
We could we could just delete that and we.
Yeah.
So what I'm going to do is just copy
Be in this code that we had that we were using and then it once I am
confident, that everything is all set up properly.
I am going to delete it from the handmade asset because we're not
going to load things from BMP files anymore after that.
Okay.
So here's that code.
And you know what?
This could even go down in here.
Now, there we are.
So, yeah, I'm going to compile that and see what we're missing in
terms of, you know, whatever we have we might be missing.
So we've got our line percentage and is that just simply getting
stored in here.
It never actually gets used.
So I'm that's not necessary.
And I'm just going to go ahead and get rid of that anyway, and let's
see and loaded bitmap like
Stuff, I guess we could just, we could still use, we could still be
used loaded bitmap.
I think that's in the
Right.
Lodi bitmap.
So I can put that in here.
Now, we don't actually want the aligned percentage with over-height.
We do need, but we can reverse calculate that when we load it in, that
should be fine.
So, we're actually totally fine with with just this, I think in terms
of what's getting loaded, right?
So we need debug platform, read entire file, we need to implement
that, we don't have that yet and we need that to return some kind of a
thing that
It will just put one of those in here will assume that we have that
and that'll be fine and that it has it returns exactly the same stuff.
A contents in a condom size in a contents, right?
So will basically have a read file result or I guess we could just say
you can just call the entire file, write an entire file would have a
size and it would have a contents, right?
so yeah, we'd call read entire file read entire file would return an
entire file
And it would just take whatever the file name is, it's going to be
loaded and it would return one of these guys, right?
So it's going to do something here results.
So when it goes ahead and loads that in, it's going to look at this
and see I guess content size is what gets used their content size and
this is going to be entire file.
So we're going to load that in oops, tar file.
And then, we're going to go ahead and do this stuff.
Now, we've got these bits cans here which I guess means, we're going
to need those intrinsic switch.
We could.
I suppose also just cold, use.
I don't think there's any reason.
Not too right?
Does it?
Or yeah.
So that's totally fine.
We do have a V4 that we're using here and we need our srgb mapping
stuff.
So we are going to kind of need a little bit more, that's kind of
making me think.
Like, it was maybe a mistake to say no math, because it looks like
we're going to need the math, right?
If that makes sense.
So, we're going to want these guys.
RGB 255 to linear 1 and S and linear 12s RGB 255, right?
And those I think we had in here, I feel like what we're probably
going to want to do, there is just make these lofty, these up into the
mass of that they can be used by everyone, right?
So that should be fine.
So that's everything for that.
And now I feel kind of stupid for not just including the math thing
originally.
Right?
Because now we could just have the things feed V2s but whatever, you
know, live and learn, it's probably not worth changing it back now.
And so, what I want to do is I want to go to the sounds and do the
same thing, right?
I want to have loaded.
Be able to operate in here and I want it to, you know, do whatever it
is that it was going to do same way, right?
So we have entire file and we do read entire file, same thing and now
we are compiling.
So now we can do the same loading that we were doing in the game and
and you know, know that we're loading stuff exactly the same and
prepping it in exactly the same way that we had wanted.
It to be prepped if that makes sense.
So, if we do that,
What I can now do down here is I can just say well what you know, I
guess I don't even use switch.
There's only two things I can just say, okay.
Well, what type of asset actually is this thing that I'm pressing
right now, if it's a sound will load it, otherwise it will process the
bitmap, I'll assert that it is a bitmap and that it's not some other
magical type right.
But yeah so in in here what I would do is I guess I don't need these
things.
To be debug anymore.
It's just load wave and load bitmap so I can go ahead and do my load
wave there.
Let me or waves.
I like to call it drives Jeff nuts when I say that.
So here we go.
Here is our loaded sound.
I'm going to load it in, right?
And
Let's see.
Jimmy.
So I'm going to go this way file in, so I need the file name which I
have right?
I need the first sample index, which I also have and I need the
section sample count, which I guess.
I guess what exactly were we doing with that?
If this was going to be 0.
So this what I actually need to do is set use the desks one there
because that's where that actually exists, right?
That's actually in the hahhaa because it actually gets stored out,
right?
So we're talking about this value right here.
But the first sample index is the one that's that's pulled, right?
So, this would load our wave wave in, and then we could choose to
With it what we wanted.
And the same could be true for our bitmap, right?
If we do load bitmap we would pass the source file name and we would
get back the bitmap right and that seemed it is not 0 it's not quite
correct.
There we go, load bitmap.
Is it lubed BMP?
What did I call that?
It, slowed BMP.
Let the MP.
So, now, we'd be loading all of the Assets in, right?
But of course, the problem is, if we had a lot of assets, this would
get ugly quickly because they never actually free the memory that they
would be using here.
So what I want to do is something like this, right?
What I want to do is something where I just go like, okay, you know,
when I'm done with these guys, maybe I do something like this, right?
So I can load it in.
I can write it out and then I can free it, right?
Something something very straightforward like that would be nice.
So once we load this stuff in then we have to actually go ahead and
and feel in any data that we were getting from the file itself.
So from the wave file, like for example, the sample count may not have
been specified, like sometimes we just 50 is a sample count and we
then would get it from the file.
I don't know if you remember, when we wrote that code, right?
If you look at the original code, when we were doing debug load wave /
wave, when we were loading this, you can see that.
We did some stuff down here where we're like, oh okay, you know, the
sample count, right?
When the section sample count, we would actually do stuff with the
section sample count, if it was non zero, right?
But in the cases where it it was 0, we wouldn't change it.
So the sample count that we end up using would be dependent on whether
we'd specified one, and we might just use the sample count from the
file.
If we had specified, a section sample, count,
M0.
So we want to preserve that behavior.
That was important to how our loading code work.
Because that was, what was, you know, kind of getting chunks of things
out.
So what we want to do is go back through the file format and make sure
that we're writing out all the stuff that we might need, right?
So next ID to play would already be set so we don't need to set that.
But sample count would not necessarily be set.
So what we want to do is is grab that out, right?
That's something we want to grab out.
Yeah.
Now something that it strikes me as not also, as also not being here
though, is channel count?
Because technically we were supporting multiple channels so I'd also
like to put that in there and that would be something that would come
from the handmade asset loader, right?
It's this channel count value right here, right?
So I also think, I want to go ahead and copy that into the file.
That's going to be written.
So once I've copied those two things into the array that we will
eventually right out over here, right?
I then want to be able to, you know, just go ahead and take all the
sample data and block write that out, right?
So that's the actual data that's going to get written to the file,
right?
I'm going to write out, you know, very specifically the entire the
entire wave, right?
I'm going to say the samples.
Zero.
Which is that first channel I guess what I'm going to do here is this
is actually what I'm gonna do.
I'm gonna put this in a for a loop so they can support as many
channels as if we ever added more channels, right?
I'm going to say,
The wave we look at what the channel count is.
And we write out each individual Channel and we know how big that's
going to be.
We know how big that's going to be, because we know the sample count,
right times.
The size of an individual sample is going to give us that, right?
So we know that that's how big that is.
So we write out the one or two channels of sound data and that's the
entire data for this thing.
And now we need to tell it where that is, right?
We until we're in the file, we actually are
And as far as I know, there's no I don't know if there's a portable
way to do an F, tell that 64-bit.
So the same caveat applies here.
When we do an F tell it's not necessarily going to be 64-bit
compliant.
So, you know, caveat to anyone who actually is going to write these.
You would need to potentially worry about actually being able to get
past the 4 gigabyte boundary by using an F tell that was actually
64-bit, and you can see, like,
You can see that they've got these sort of Visual Studio ones and
whatever and I don't even know which ones you know you would use.
Like I said, I never use these.
I always go through windows or Linux directly but yeah, so you can
kind of see like there's these other options available for 64-bit
style offsets and that sort of stuff and your mileage may vary in
terms of which one the platform that your programming on actually has.
But here's the like,
Tell one that returns a 64-bit integer, for example, right?
So I'm just pointing that out.
Just just let you know, giving you what the idea is there?
So we have the F right to me.
But we want to do is make sure that before we start doing these
rights, we figure out where in the file we are so that the
destinations offset data, right?
I guess this is actually that the data offset that we store it in the
file.
Needs to know that you know, needs to point to where we actually start
writing.
So what I want to do is use the F, tell there again, I'm just going to
use the regular one, right?
Because we know that we're not writing out for GB for this test case,
I'm going to go ahead and say, all right, the data-offset let's do the
F.
Tell to get the 64, the 32-bit value back, and we'll just treat that
as good for now.
So, when we do the F tell of out, it'll tell us where we are.
We will then write the stuff out and then we will free the memory that
we used to hold the the contents temporarily while we wrote it right.
Exact.
Same thing happens with the bitmap, right?
If we look at what the bitmap actually has in, it is just got the
dimensions in the aligned percentage.
This we know this,
Comes from the file.
So we're going to do essentially the exact same thing.
In.
Are we are going to say, like dest bitmapped dim, 0, equals.
Whatever.
The file said, the dimension of the bitmap was same with this one, and
I don't know.
I don't we have to think for a second about how we want to handle
pitch.
So let's let's just do this part first and then we'll can talk a
little bit more about that so I don't remember what loaded bitmap had
in it.
Where's the renderer code?
They're loaded bitmap had just width and height and that's what we
actually want.
So we want with we want height like so and then what we want to do is
do the exact same thing.
We did here to write out the data, right?
We just want to do an F.
Tell to say, this is where the data is actually.
B.
And in some sense, I guess we could have just done that.
We can just share that.
That's going to be the same right between each piece of code.
It's just wherever we are in the file at this point, that's where this
thing is, right?
So we don't have to do that in both branches, we only have to do the
part that's specific to either Branch, right?
So that's fine.
So if we do that, excuse me.
In fact, we could even be a little bit more snarky here.
If we wanted to, I'm not going to be, I'm not going to be so.
Anyway, we go ahead here and we pull out that data for the dimension
in there.
And then what we want to do is we want to do the same thing with your,
for the sound.
But instead of writing out, like, the samples, right?
We have to write out the bitmap, b b.
So, if I go ahead and oops, do memory, what we need to know is how big
this is, and we know this going to be right, the width times the
height times for, Right?
Four bytes per pixel.
That's that's what we are always going to keep our bitmaps to be
formatted as at the moment, anyway, right?
So the problem here is that if the sot, we could actually just assert
it, I suppose that the stride in the width are equal, right?
That the bitmap right, the bitmap pitch is going to be equal to the
width, x 4.
So that everything is nicely packed.
And so, what we would want to do is you know, if we have bitmaps that
Don't conform to this format where there's no extra, you know, there's
no padding basically on the rose.
If we have ones that had padding on the roads, we would want to write
a little code here, just rip that out because we don't want the load
time.
Code of the game to have to deal with multiple pitches.
We want them all to be fixed.
I think, or if we always wanted the padded to a particular thing, we
would want to use the code here, that does that particular Paddock,
right?
So that's, that's that.
So,
That is that.
But now we have to go actually Implement these these guys, from to
load, actual pointers, to froebel memory.
So let's take a look.
Here we have
The sample count, the loaded web of apparently doesn't have the sample
County in it.
Why is that
What did I do?
Wrong there groups voted sound so it is okay.
Oh, is it this one that we're actually complaining about?
Let me double-check at what the file format says, it has in its HHA.
Sound, its sound, dot sample.
Count.
What is it complaining about cannot convert from loaded sound too.
Loaded sound star.
That's fine.
We're going to fix.
That s is not a member of hhas.
Set.
Oh it's the one down here.
Oops.
My bad jump to a conclusion there.
Let's see.
Cannot convert argument for to file star.
Oh, of course, I mixed up the order as I often do with f.
Right.
There we go.
So, here we are, load, BMP.
Can't that's fine too.
And this guy office is going to be the wrong order as well.
So it is flipped Loops put that around
Okay, so now and memory as we missed the accidentally, got it dash out
there.
So now we've got all that stuff set up.
We just need to actually make these guys return a chunk, that can be
freed if that makes sense.
And we need to implement this, this read entire file thing to
actually, you know, to actually read an entire file if that makes
sense.
I'm trying to think if I don't know if I actually you know what, I
don't really even need to do it that way.
I'm just I'm just going to do this, right?
Something like this, let's see.
Avoid memory or void star, free must and do it that way.
That's a little bit easier than than doing anything more complicated
with it.
So, that point these can actually just look like this free web 33
bitmap got three.
all right, so
Think that's all good and I just have to make sure that these pointers
here.
Change two dots.
The curse of see no one knows why they did.
That makes no sense but that's just the way I did.
What are you gonna do?
These are also wrong.
So, we're these
So is that Loops that?
Okay, so now what I have to do is actually implement this loaded web
this this bit here, right?
And so, I have to do the load by having a little bit map, I have to
implement the read entire file function, right?
Because it's not actually doing anything right now and once it reads
it, when it does the result thing here, I'm just going to say oh by
the way, you know, if you could just
Free that memory, you know, from the contents and the same is true for
for the load web, right?
So read result.
Oops, result that 3, it's going to read results, contents.
And so that just freeze the memory, we don't not like we care.
I mean, it's just a suppressor, but if you imagine a huge number of
assets, you might blow out memory.
If you were never freeing it or something like this, so just seems
like a reasonable thing to do.
So anyway,
In read entire file.
What I want to do is Malik, you know, the file size, right?
I want to F read which is the opposite of the about F, right?
Right.
I want to F read the file size in as like, one big chunk, and into
like, basically the the result that contents, right?
In fact, I guess you could say, you want to do this, right?
We want to, we want to do content size.
So we want to read in the whole thing after
Take a chunk that fits it, right?
So that's really the entirety of what we're talking about here.
It's not out.
I guess it's in at this point, right?
So what this is going to look like is really very simple.
We're just going to define a new file handle.
We're going to say that the input file right?
Is going to be read as a binary file off to ask again.
It's the same F open, we're using before.
It doesn't really matter.
If you know these things, these are just the C runtime, libraries ways
of loading files.
Like I said, not going to be used in handmade here at all.
It's only in this asset processor so assuming that we got, it will do
that.
Otherwise we'll we'll just print a little lame little error message
here, printf, right error cannot open file, whatever the file name is,
right?
And so then what we would do,
Here.
Is we just need to know how big the how big this thing is once we know
how big the file is.
We can read the whole thing.
We can allocate space for it, read the whole thing in, right, and then
then close it and that's all we would need to do.
So we just need to know how big the file actually is and what we can
do for that.
Right, is you've already seen this FC?
Remember when I said, well, F CK allows you to do seek end.
And specify a number of bytes, from the end to seek.
So what I can do is just seek to the end of the file seek back to the
beginning of the file like this, right?
So seek to the end seek to the getting when I seek to the end, the F,
tell result the file position that it would report to me is going to
be the size of the file, right?
Because I've gone all the way to the end, so, it's just a little
hacky, but I don't know if there's a cleaner way to do it in the C
runtime Library.
So, yeah, that works in a pinch.
Excuse me.
So content size, misspelled.
There, it's actually contents size.
So that's basically it.
And if I'm not mistaken, we've more or less finished the code, we
actually want.
Let's take a look though at what it's doing because I kind of just
slammed that in there somewhat willy-nilly.
So you know, we F tell the data-offset that's where it thinks we're
going to write to.
We're going to load a WAV file in here.
Oops, looks like we
Looks like we did not load the file.
Oh, the fucked up.
Well, there is one thing that we will have to do which I didn't think
of the first asset in all of our stuff is intentionally left blank,
right?
So in this file we can't just assume that we can actually load the
file name.
The file name May intentionally have been low, no on that first value.
So what I could
Do I guess is just start after the first index, because all the rest
of the ones should be non-null, right?
And that should be fine.
I would think, let's find out.
So if I come in here and load a BMP,
What happens?
Oh, dear.
That doesn't look good at all.
I wonder if this if this code is not let's let's step in here and see
if I'm doing this correctly at all step in there.
I want to open, what am I opening test hero, Shadow?
So we're able to do that.
Let's see how big it thinks it is 125 130.
Let's see if that's commensurate with the actual data just you know
because we're trying to make sure we did this, right.
Let's
I went.
Yeah, that's looks correct.
We seek back to the beginning.
Oh, nah typo.
We did not seek back to the beginning.
We select know.
Where do you see that supposed to be seek set?
I want to set it back to the 20 to the beginning.
Seeks out his relatives beginning of the file.
Well, that would that would do it.
Let's try that one more time so I want to come in here.
Do the read entire file is this now a little more.
Yeah.
So now we've
The values that look more correct.
We come through here.
We do our bit scans and all our other good stuff.
Let's step out.
See what we get here.
What's our desk to look like dest?
So at the data offsets their, its first tag is one.
It didn't have any tags because it's one pass last is also one.
We have the pit map itself.
It's dimensions are 144 about 217.
Looks right.
It's a line percentage is 5 and point one five, six, six, eight, two,
zero to nine.
Well, maybe that's correct but maybe it's not.
Nope, that's fine.
What do you know?
That's what we wanted.
So, okay, we're going to assert that.
It's aligned properly for our purposes, and then we're going to go
ahead and free it and then we're going to come back through.
So that's going to write a bunch of bitmaps out.
And so, you know, we can come back in here and do our load wave.
See if the load wave also works, right?
Those guys out free it.
So yeah, off we go.
There's their asset processor, quote, unquote, and you can see that we
now have a 17 megabyte file.
That is are bundled asset file now, I don't know if that's actually
the size that it should be because we haven't really done any
validation of anything yet.
But I suspect that that is probably correct.
Maybe because half of this guy, right?
We're 11 Channel of the music test, which I think is all we keep now,
right?
I think we're only doing one channel, right?
Is going to be like 15 megabytes and then all of these guys are very
tiny.
So they could easily only add up to 2 MB, that seems plausible.
So we don't know that our code is working at all yet.
It would be very premature to suggest any such thing but what we do
know is that we are not totally implausible and so if that worked
properly, what we have done is replaced.
All of these tests files in here with one file that's just test that
ha which includes all of the data for the game, right?
so now,
That we've done that.
The next question is could we use that for our actual game and have it
run at all?
We've only got 10 minutes so that might be a little bit too much to
bite off at the moment but we can certainly start.
And we're going to need to start validating the file anyway.
So you know, we might as well go ahead and do that.
Now, if we take a look at what's happening in here,
Where I set the structure up, what I can do I'm going to verify that
we're running the way that we thought.
You know what?
Oops that's the asset Builder.
Don't need to run that again.
Let's go back to win32 handmade dot s Ln and run it.
So we're running that we should probably also just for good measure
because, you know, it's a little odd should probably take out that
piece of test code, that's in the audio.
Mixer, that forces all sounds to play.
Be fast, right?
Like that is, you know, I don't believe that, that is what we wanted.
So 1.9, get rid of that 1.9.
So now we're playing properly, right?
And you can see all the Assets in the game are working properly and
all that sort of stuff.
So, what we want to do now is see if we can just switch over
To using that pack file.
So let's start.
So the first thing that we're going to do to do this is figure out
what the stuff is that we actually wanted to initialize correctly,
right?
That that is, that is actually being initialized here.
And what stuff?
We just don't care about, right?
So, the debug stuff can all go away for the most part, right?
Like, the debug stuff here, can all get removed like so.
And so we would really only have
These left over, right, we would then get rid of like, almost all of
this stuff, right?
Almost all of this would go away.
So we dif zero this out.
And yeah, it looks like all of that is all going to go away, right?
So all that would go away as well as would pretty much all of
This stuff right would go away as well.
So, all of that stuff would go away.
And what we would have to do now is we would have to sort of we're
going to have to kind of do this into two tranches because first I
want to use our existing debug file load routine, to load the whole
file into memory and just use it that way.
And then, after that, we will go and you add a path to our Windows
platform layer that will actually do proper overlap Tayo for us.
so let's go ahead and if zero out the rest of this,
Like so and so really what we've got is now these these sort of load
these guys here, right is what's actually happening.
So what I'd like to do I think what I'd like to do, there's a there's
a pretty good way.
I think that we could stub these out.
I think there's a pretty good way that I can.
I can I should just say first of all, when you're doing a big
co-chairs like this you've seen me do it many times.
I don't know if I've ever explicitly set it.
I like to schedule the work out in my brain in
Branches, right?
I like to be able to go, let's make one change and validate that it's
working.
Make another change of attitude.
I don't just try to do the whole thing at once.
Unless I figured in my head that really that would be very efficient
to do.
I like to kind of do it in steps, so that I'm not taking too big of a
leap of faith, so I can see how it's working out and potentially save
myself.
Some trouble if I go, no, not quite so and similarly with debugging.
If I, if I replace only one thing at a time, it's easier to debug
because I know where the bug might be, whereas, if I replace
everything, I have no idea where the bug is, right?
It could be in any of it and it's harder.
It takes longer to kind of isolate it down.
So that's you know, just to be a little bit more explicit, sort of
philosophically.
Conceptually about what's going on there.
That's that's sort of where I'm at.
So what I'm going to do is I'm going to take the debug load bitmap,
the to debug ones, right?
The load wave.
Debug load.
Wave, I'm going to stub those out.
Like this and just do like a cert.
No no no no right.
And then I'm going to do result equals some other thing and return,
right?
And similarly for debug load BMP, I'm going to do groups have it.
I am going to do debug
Wow.
I'm going to do the exact same thing for it.
Start SS.
Mmm, no loaded bitmap result, equals blah return results, right?
So now we compile, first, I have to actually put these in the correct
order shift those up here.
So now, you know, we just wouldn't run because immediately when an
asset was needed, it would assert and it would just say, no, you know,
you don't have that that asset, although for some or it wouldn't,
that's a bit odd, oh, right?
Because this is the good as any assets.
That's a kind of cool.
It's kind of cool how that works right when your whole asset system is
based on queries.
Like this you can just remove all the Assets in the game doesn't like
crash or anything.
It just it tries to build bitmaps and it says though there weren't any
in it, just keeps on going about it today.
That's kind of cool.
All right.
Well anyway.
So now what I'd like to do is try to restore those assets by using
debug read entire file to read in the entire that entire HHA, that we
wrote out
Right?
So what I want to do here is I want to say okay read this thing, read
this whole thing in and we're going to read in that what was the name
of that guy?
Test dot h, AI guess whatever it was right.
When I read the whole that whole test dot h.
A thing in, we're going to then go through all the Assets in it and
basically we're just going to let kind of plug our stuff to sort of
reference into the
Memory.
So we loaded the whole file into memory and I'm just going to flat out
romp straight over the other stuff in here with pointers directly into
that file.
Right?
So so I'm going to say that we overwrite all of these guys, the asset
count, right?
The assets themselves.
All of that stuff is going to get overwritten by the stuff that's in
there, right?
Okay, so the tag array is pretty darn.
I guess.
I kind of
I kind of do have to now that I think about it, do it a little bit
more.
I want to actually do the changeover processing.
So I dig it back.
I'm not going to quite do it directly that way.
Perhaps.
So what I'll I will actually do this, right?
I'll actually do the asset count equals, like, you know, whatever the
hhhh, a headers asset count was, right.
Because we'll know what that is now.
And then I'll push the right number on there and the same will be true
for
Tag count, right?
Like so and so then we'll have the arrays and then I'll just Loop over
them all.
And an actually set them up, right?
And we've got three things to Loop over the tag array.
At the asset type array and then the asset array itself.
So here is the tags.
And right now we're not actually doing today so we may just flat load
the tags, the tags could just be pointed to directly.
In fact, we could yeah, I don't know how we want.
We'll want to do is I'm going to Loop through them for now but we
could just turn them into flat loading.
And I'm going to say this is a to do for next time, right?
Decide what will be flat loaded?
What won't be?
Right.
But for now I'm just going to actually interpret all the data which is
just, it's not going to be.
There's no reason for us to do that.
So we'll eliminate some of this in the next pass, I think so.
You know what we would do here is say that we have again a source on a
desk to centrally.
We have an h.h., a tag, which is the source this time because that's
where we're pulling from in the file.
So we would have basically the HHA tags.
That one.
And then he's off for now and then we have our asset tag.
That's the things we actually use and that's the best and that's going
to be the assets tags array.
And for each of those, we're literally just going to copy the two
values that are in there, right?
It's just ID and value.
So it's like dest ideal Source, ID desk, value, equals Source value.
Right?
So really all we need to do here is now actually get at that data.
Now what we know is, what we loaded is an aha
Header.
Right?
We know if we look at the file format, that's what we wrote out as the
first thing in the file.
So if we literally just straight up, cast the read result, contents
like the file data, if we Straight Up cast on the Y tilde, K HH, a
header and it could just be header.
It's not like as another header, the HHA header is just the first
passage to the first byte of the file, right?
And we can assert that the header
that we wrote out has the magic value that we expect.
So we know that we actually, you know, are reading one of our files at
the moment, you know.
So while we're devoting it here we know that we're not crazy and we
can do this H A version as well to double-check those.
And then from there we can just use the asset count in the the tag
count and so on.
But then we also need to figure out like where like the hahha tags are
and stuff like that, right?
So we have h a tag like that, that's just going to be
Again, casting to an ha tag.
The read result, contents.
But this time we need to move forward a bit, right?
We're going to start at where the kind of started, but we're going to
move to the location the file that we wrote out to tell ourselves
where it would be, right?
So we know that this is where the tags are, right?
So we're just going to go ahead and say all right, you know wherever
the header says the tags are that's for the tags are right?
So it looks like I didn't include this stuff in our handmade .h, so
I'm going to now
We did not include the file formats in our list of stuff.
So I'm going to go ahead and do include and made file formats .h.
So, I'm going to go and put that in there and then, oh, right.
And I forgot to add this guy, I meant to add this guy.
I like I said, I've been playing around with what I like those types
to be named and I've been debating on whether I like the 08 or the
regular 8, and some people online were saying, it shouldn't use 08 and
I tend to agree with them.
I don't know.
I've been, I like it to line up, but then sometimes I don't.
It's just, you know, you know, it is.
So anyway, let's take a look and see how that actually goes.
But we're a little bit over time, but you know, that's how it goes
sometimes.
So, let's go through here.
If we load this thing out, let's see, let's see, first of all, if we
step in here, here's the header that the magic value is what we
expected to be.
The version is to the tag count looks right, right?
We got the 17 different asset types.
We have 51 assets in there.
We've got 44 tags, right?
And RHA tags are a
Right, let's just look at a few of them.
Looks exactly right.
Right.
So we've loaded the data in.
It looks like we've loaded in the data properly for the most part,
right?
So I would say that's that's pretty good.
So I think we stopped there for
And what we will do tomorrow is will just finish lining and stuff up
in the file, like, pulling that stuff out of the file and verify that
everything works properly.
And then from there, we can just move on to loading it out piecemeal,
right?
So yeah, so that's all good.
Let's go ahead and go to the Q&A for people who have questions on what
we did today.
Hopefully that was all pretty clear we basically just wrote that stuff
out to the file
And now we're just loading in the stuff from the file and picking out
the pieces of it that we know, are the data that we actually want if
that makes sense.
All right.
So go and head and if you have questions on what we were doing, go
ahead and please preface them with Q: so I can see them and I will go
ahead and answer them.
And I see people talking about how long it's been going for.
Yes, it has been going for 149 days but we only code one hour a day so
it's basically like a hundred forty nine hours.
But once in a while, we've done a long stream so it's you know it's
probably more like figure 160 hours or something like that.
So if you divide that by 40 hour work week, you're talking for weeks.
Gaston 5 asks, what does flat loaded mean?
I guess I don't know why that term is what it is but I can tell you
what I mean by it.
And what I tend to hear people mean by it, right?
So flat loaded.
Continuously mean one of two things.
The first thing is here is the file
Right here is some data.
And here is the memory in use in the game.
The actual memory is going to be used by the game flat.
Loaded means you literally just load the thing straight away as a
block into memory and the game just runs straight off it.
I believe it's flat loaded because you know, you're not relocating it
or you're not allocating pieces, right?
So by comparison, a parsed
Way or a piecemeal right way of loading.
A file is sort of what I kind of implemented there, where it's like,
okay, whether or not I load the thing in as a chunk, is not really
that relevant to this part of this question.
But it's, it's whether I run out of it directly, right?
So, if I load this thing in, and then I start looking at it and go,
oh, here's a thing that says, there were five tags.
So, I allocate some tags here, and then here's one of the tags.
So, I put that in here, right?
That is the up like that.
That's the nut.
That's not this, right?
That's the other way of doing it and it's kind of the more it's clunky
and cumbersome and you don't want to do this, right?
You're wasting a bunch of time in your load, if you can figure out a
way to not do it, right?
So typically that is what flat loading means.
Usually and probably even in handmade hero will want to be doing
basically that but there's usually another step.
So usually what happens is, we decompress, right.
So we want to do something where yeah, we load in a block, we
decompress it and then we slam it into the data and use it directly is
basically what we're going to want which
Pretty close to Flat loaded but not exactly.
Because there is this step of blowing out the data, right?
Someone during the stream asked about the benefit of keeping all
assets in one file as opposed to making different asset files,
dedicated to each type of asset.
Hmm.
I want to make sure I want to make sure that I actually understand.
The question that you're asking is I'm not sure if I do
Are you asking why I have one big file as opposed to one file per
asset?
Like one file per bitmap or something?
Or are you asking why have one file instead of two files, one for
sounds and all the sounds are in it and one for bitmaps and all the
bitmaps are in it because those are two different questions and I want
to make sure I'm answering the proper thing if that makes sense.
Tt, b GM.
Should there be are asserts if there are no assets that match a query?
I don't know.
Maybe maybe not.
I don't think so probably not in assert.
What we might want to do is have a way that it gets logged or
something.
Eventually I'd say, take a wait-and-see approach and see if we
actually ever run into cases where we need that.
Could you ever make games to make profit off?
Yes, I bet.
It's what I do.
Normally, in my day job.
Let's see.
The ladder about the assets.
Okay?
So I'm going to try and answer this question then.
So the person who was asking that question was asking the question
right now, this is what we have our file look like basically, right?
Right.
This is what it looks like and if we wanted to be more explicit,
right?
It kind of looks, you know, in more detail like this, there's the
header portion here.
Right is actually broken up into like a preamble, right?
That really doesn't have anything in it.
Magic value.
That's right, stuff in some counts, right?
And then some addresses of things, and then it's got some arrays,
right?
It's got tags, you know, asset types and assets, or something like
this.
I don't remember.
The order could be the other way around.
And these things point, this this array points into here, right?
And it says where the various each element of this array points into
where the various things are and we've got, you know, right now they
would pretty much be in order because we Define them in order.
So be like bitmaps would be coming first and then eventually it
switches to sounds, right?
But we could interleave them.
There's no, they just happen to be written out in the order in which
the assets are defined.
And we happen to the final AR B.
Massive Arsenal are sound s, but we could Define them in terms.
Even they would still work.
So this is not really part of the fact that they happen to be built up
this way is not really part of file format.
So what they what the person was asking was well why not do it so that
you have this essentially a file, one file that is this, right?
And then another file that is this part with another one of these on
top, right?
So basically have you know, two files where we have header data.
And then one is just bitmaps.
And one is just sounds, right?
And these are the two files so it'd be like the BMP resource and the
wave resource whatever.
And not to ask not to answer a question with a question or anything.
But my first
Thing that comes to mind as to why not to do this would be, why would
you do this right?
Like what's the reason why you would want to have more files on the
drive than necessary, right?
Like,
It's just one more thing to worry about, right?
If I only have one file and that file has all the data in it, that I
know that when I opened that file that's the only error I had check.
It's like I go.
Okay, can I open my resource file?
Yes, then I know I can get all my resources and the only thing I ever
have to worry about is if one time I go read from this file handle and
the OS says it's gone or something.
I have to go.
Hey, mister user just so, you know, your machine is broken basically,
right?
Or something like this.
If I have to, then that just doubles the amount of work I have to do
when I start up, right, I've got a.
Now I have to have one path for parsing.
The bitmaps one, Parish 1:04 path for pressing the waist.
Just adds more stuff that can go wrong and more code, right?
So the main reason just why bother right like, why not?
Just collapse it down into something simpler when they're what, what
would be the actual benefit?
And since I can't think of a benefit to having them separate.
That is why I say let's keep them in one, right?
So it doesn't look like we have many on-topic questions.
So, I guess I'll take a couple off-topic ones before winding winding
down.
Where did I learn to code?
I learned to code when I was little, my dad taught me to program when
I was seven and since then I, you know, I'm self-taught.
How long have you been coding for 30 years?
Is this what you do full time?
Do you work for company?
Yes, I run my own game.
Research company here in Seattle.
And that is what I that is.
What I do full time, not this.
This is a sort of pseudo.
Spare time to some degree activity, but I make, you know, two hours
for it every day to make sure that we do it.
And it's basically I'm trying to kind of do it.
Programming education project, if that makes sense.
Will the game be multiplayer or single-player?
And will you be able to code your character kind of like code spells
like the name handmade here?
Which suggests?
No, it is not like code spells and it is single player.
Although
The game as it ships will be single player.
Unless we see some way to make the design, not be a problem that way.
But so the game has it ships with a but we support multiplayer for for
the purposes of me.
Showing how to program it, right?
So even right now in the game when you when you hit the spacebar, you
you add your hero and you can walk around or whatever even right now
in the engine test code, if you were to plug in a Xbox controller and
push a button on it,
As hero.
So we're pretty much making sure the code always, the code allows
multiplayer but the design is not supposed to be multiplayer.
So the game will not really be multiplayer, but the code is throughout
the entire development process, we will leave the code in a state that
allows multiple people to play the same time even though I don't think
we want to ship it that way, because it won't be a fun.
It's not designed to be a fun multiplayer game.
It's gonna be a fun single player game.
So there's that.
Off-topic.
Why is your bio webpage?
Not for you but without JavaScript, that's because my webpage.
I don't I hate the web just pretty much period and everything about
it.
I hate HTML and CSS.
JavaScript.
I think they're all awful.
So I've done some experiments in my web page, was one of them with
ways of making websites that don't involve them in the source.
So the way my webpage works is actually that it's C program that does
lay out and it just spits out JavaScript as like a back-end like a
compiler sort of thing that produces the layout that I made in see.
you know it was a fair time thing I did it's not particularly good but
it's just kind of what I was interested in trying and I learned some
things from it and actually I went back and forth with the dude from
Firefox figuring out how to make it really fast because there's
actually a bunch of things that that won't work because JavaScript is
so slow and JavaScript and HTML are so incredibly slow that even doing
really basic layout is almost impossible if you
If you don't know, some very specific tricks, if that makes sense.
What is a bitmap?
A bitmap is just a it's it's really a misnomer.
So, in the earlier days, it was a little bit more accurate.
So the phrase bit map used to sort of mean, if you imagine in binary,
right?
You've got ones and zeros, right?
That's what a computer thinks in terms of, right?
And so in the old days, a bitmap was literally a real thing.
It really was a map.
B it was like oh I want to draw something, right.
So I've got these zeros and ones, right?
That oops, the actually represent where the data where, you know, what
you should color in and what you should not color in.
So if I wanted to make an H, right?
Oops, this is how I might store the graphics for an H, in a
quote-unquote bitmap, in the real sense of the term.
Right?
So you can see that it makes an H with the ones and the zeros are
where the H is not right?
And that would be a traditional bitmap, it is B that form a map a
two-dimensional image, right?
But over time obviously displays, you know, when displays were
monochrome a0 and A1 would tell you all you need to know if it's just
black and white.
That's all you would need to know to make an image but over time as
we've added color, it's not sufficient.
So what we've done instead is replace this concept
with sort of what you might call more appropriately, like a b map or a
multibyte map,
because what we actually store at each location in the H is a full
Rgba color set where there's 8 Bits used to represent each of these.
So you can have between 0 and 255 levels of alpha blue, green and red,
right?
So the term bitmap is now used to mean.
I mean it's still all stored as B, right?
I mean everything in the computer is in terms of bit so it's not a
complete misnomer, anything but where the term originally arose, I
think probably if you went Doug back into history they were probably
Talking about actual bits per pixel, like every pixel on the screen
was one bit on or off.
That was probably what a bitmap more traditionally meant.
Now, that's not true anymore because we've got color and it can even
be, you know, full of color in.
This could be 16 bits per gun and all, you know, and so on.
So,
Have you been doing this all your life?
Yes.
What is the Windows 10?
Release date?
I don't know.
Sometime this month.
I think, right?
What is your day job and do enjoy it?
My day job is making games and the, yes I do enjoy it.
How many years of experience do you have?
I already answered that one.
Okay, let's see what we got here.
What is overlapped?
I overlapped IO is just the name of the system in Windows.
That allows you to issue a synchronous reads to the hard drive.
I will be covering it in great detail in the next couple days as I
show how to use it to do asset loading.
Siesta 32:14.
In that case.
Why do other developers break up their Assets in separate files?
Do again.
Uh, same question.
Do you mean why you developers break up their assets into one file for
sound and one file for bitmap or into individual files?
One for each asset?
And if the, if it's the former, I actually don't know any developers
who break up their assets into all the bitmaps, go one place and all
the sounds going to another.
I don't actually know if people who do that doesn't mean they don't I
just personally don't know.
I couldn't say why they do because I've never actually seen anyone do
that, if you're asking, why a lot of developers just leave it as a
bunch of files on the drive where there's one file per asset?
I don't know.
I have I probably cuz it just never have written pack files before and
don't know how or don't want to be bothered with them.
I don't know.
Would having separate files assist with modding or patching?
Not really, because the way we expect our asset files as you can have
as many of them as you want still.
So you can always add more.
So, I would say that actually
It probably doesn't matter patching maybe because patching, you know,
we'd have to think a little bit about how we might want to do patching
if we wanted to do patching in it in a way that knocks out existing
assets, right?
although, I think we will actually just get that for free, but
So yeah, I don't even know that to be honest.
I think all that might just work.
It's my Cactus data or to design a different than compression oriented
programming.
Yeah.
So, Mike Acton's data oriented design stuff is sort of talking about
it.
They're, they're sort of different parts of the procedure really
compression or your partner is kind of how you do architecture, right?
It's about taking code that you've written and sort of pulling it out
into things that are reusable or that you know, have more leverage or
whatever.
Right?
What Mike actions use talk about with the data oriented design is
talking about the first step like a
Very pretty.
It's kind of like the Second Step he's talked about the first step.
He's saying the first thing that you should do.
When you write the actual code, is you write the thing that actually
transforms the data in the way that it's supposed to work, right?
You have data, and you're trying to move it from one place to another
and change it.
Like, that's what cook, that's just what code does, right or leave it
in place and change it.
But that's that's all CPUs could do period.
So we know that that's the entirety of the problem that you're solving
is a way of mutating data either in place or in route to some place.
So he's saying Orient the code around that and that is totally
correct.
And that's basically what we do.
Unhand me here all the time, right?
That is exactly how you want to do that.
But data aren't you die?
Doesn't really speak to what happens when you want to try to start
leveraging, some kind of high level structure and that's what
compression or any program is, it's about saying taking things, you
see that are similar pulling them out and making sure that they still
stay true to the data oriented design that you have.
So, you don't want to modify what it's doing.
You want to let it do you want?
Make sure the thing that does is the same
But you're trying to get it into a place where you can reuse it in
more than one way.
One reason to split files is to get around the FAT32.
4 gigabyte limit.
Another reason might be if your pipeline allows audio days to upload
to update their pack file for the game without needing or messing with
other parts of the game.
Well, that's a separate thing though because that's during Dev, right?
There's a difference between during Dev and how you shift the game.
So yeah, that's that's sort of a separate thing.
I would say in some sense, the FAT32 part, I don't know.
Like, do is there really a lot of FAT32 going on?
Still like, do you really have?
I guess if you're trying to transfer things on a thumb drive, maybe
you would see the old 4 GB FAT32.
I don't know.
It's hard to say.
Where can we read about the actual plan for the game?
That is not released yet?
Are using any C++ plug-ins for Emax?
No, it's just the standard vanilla.
The standard C++ mode that ships with the max by default.
Well, the game have to wait until all the assets have been to compress
before the game can start.
No.
So the way that we would do that, right is in here.
Where we have these bitmaps, right?
We would just compress each one individually.
So when we go to fetch a particular bitmap, we only decompress like
the bitmap that we want, we wouldn't, like, compress this whole block
as a single block and so that we'd have to, like decompress all the
bitmaps access one of them.
So we would set up the compression.
That we would do to allow that random access, right?
Why are using Windows?
Instead of Linux, that is answered on the page.
You are looking at right now.
In fact, that's answered on the twitch page, but the answer is just
that because nobody buys any games on Linux, you know, you can sort of
see this answer for yourself.
Actually if, if you go to the steam Hardware survey.
So you know, you're a game developer, you have to make money to stay
in business, that's just the rules of the game.
So you have to sell
Copies of your game.
And so, if you take a look and you go to the OS version, right?
And you take a look at where you going to sell those games on Steam,
95.7, seven percent of the people.
You can sell your game to are running Windows.
3.22 percent of them are running OS, X and Linux is essentially
nobody.
So while it's, you know, it's nice to support OS X and Linux for a
couple reasons which I'll talk about it.
Second.
If you are a game programmer, Windows must be your primary platform of
knowledge because the vast majority, the vast majority of people who
will play your game as an indie game developer.
If it's on PC is Windows.
Nobody believed thing on OS X and nobody believed thing on Linux in
terms of the numbers that actually, the actual fan base that you will
be reaching
so,
that is why I made hero is on Windows first.
It's because that is the platform.
You must know.
And is the platform you must get?
Right.
If you do not get Windows, right?
Your game will be a massive disaster when you release it, because
everyone will complain on your forums that it's not working on their
machine and blah, blah blah.
All right.
And you'll just have a disaster hands because 95% basically every
single person who bought your game was running it on Windows
Right.
You know, out of every hundred people that bought your game, only four
of them were running it on something other than Windows ninety, six of
them ran it on Windows, right?
So at that point, you may ask well, why bother porting to OS X and
Linux at.
All right, because and on handmade hero.
Once we finish the windows version, I will be showing how to Port it
to us, X and Linux, and there's two separate.
It's for that one reason for that is simply to make sure writing
portable code is a good skill to have and it's good to learn because
you don't know that windows will be the 96% case forever and you also
don't know if you might want to run on a console maybe you want to
ship on PS4, maybe you got a deal with Sony to ship it out, your game
on ps4.
You need to have the experience of how to write code properly to ship
on more than one platform because in game development, you will often
be expected to ship on at least two.
Two platforms that have to work well and so that's, you know, one
reason.
So porting a game to other platforms, you just a good experience and I
want to show how to do it.
So there's that and it will be something you'll actually have to do.
It may not be OS X and Linux that you will be pressed into shipping
because of actual Market concerns.
But it might be like widows in PS4 let's say, right?
So is that but the other reason is just that.
Well, I mean, let's be honest, Microsoft is really antagonistic to
game developers.
Right?
They are absolutely awful to us.
They basically do everything they can to make our lives miserable.
And this is like across the board, right?
They won't backport their Graphics Library.
So if you want to Target, d3d, 12, you can't run on Windows 8 or
Windows 7, you have to Target Windows 10.
Which means if you're going to Target multiple things, if you use D12,
you have to write a d3d, 11 back-end to run on the older platform,
right?
So, and they don't care because what they want to do is
They want to make sure people buy new windows versions of Windows,
right?
And they don't want to do the extra engineering work or whatever to
support the mobile platforms, or who knows what?
Right?
So they don't have your best interest in mind.
They have their best answer mind.
They want to promote the Windows store.
So they don't allow you to write in the desktop stuff anymore.
You've got to go right in in the Windows RT layer.
If you want to do stuff like show a lock screen notification, right?
Because they have an agenda, they want to push their Windows store,
they want to take 20% of your money or I guess 30% your money now or
whatever it is they have all these agendas right.
Right?
They don't care about you at all.
Unless you have some kind of monetary thing or cloud or maybe you'll
complain to a lot of it.
Like they don't care about you, right?
They care about them and making money and they have never historically
been nice to game developers all the way back to like stay when they
introduce games for Windows Live and wanted to charge players an
online subscription fee and like try to get people to go through this
like archaic weird, bad service that was lousy and then they
discontinued it.
So all the games are on it.
Sorry.
They just their pattern of behavior is extraordinarily antagonistic to
game developers and especially to indie game developers because indie
game developers, don't have any muscle, right?
If you're, you know, let's say you're the people who make Call of
Duty, right?
Your Activision, you have a lot of muscle and you could throw some
weight around and get what you want, probably right?
You know, we don't have that as an example a, there's nothing I'm
going to ever say to Microsoft that's ever going to make them.
Do anything for me or help out.
In some, you know, thing like that that's antagonistic to handmade
hero.
That's just not going to happen because it doesn't have any clout,
right?
And so in my mind they are a very dangerous thing that we are reliant
on in a very heavy way.
This, that's this number right here, right?
They are very dangerous and very troubling to me, it bothers me a lot.
That the ninety-six percent ownership of games on Windows is a company
that is openly hostile to us in many ways.
And has often proven, that they are totally happy taking that stance.
So why Porter game to Linux at all?
Because I'll be honest at some point, we have to figure out a way to
solve the situation and keeping all of our games portable and shipping
games on Linux.
Even though, you know, you will not even make back the money, it cost
you to Port.
It is still something that maybe makes sense to do because who knows
what could happen?
Maybe steam Linux, start succeeding.
And the only way steam Linux is going to start succeeding is if there
are games there to be played on it, we can help make that be true by
stripping his legs once that starts
Succeeding.
Now you have two competitors in that sort of PC gaming landscape,
steam, Linux and windows.
And it seemed like starts gaining traction.
And this number goes up,
Now, Microsoft can't be so antagonistic because there's this other
place we can go right.
And so you know if there's one thing we've learned from history is
that Microsoft is openly antagonistic to game developers at every
possible opportunity and there is no way that just counting on them to
do the right thing for us will happen.
But if we have Alternatives and we have competitors that are
essentially going to force them to do the right thing and force them
to be nicer.
They will write because they have to or they just go away and we don't
care, they're either right?
Because Linux is open and always will be so we don't have to worry
about that part, right?
So in some sense, the reason that I would say even though it, you know
how many Heroes on Windows first and if you are game developer, you
kind of have to be Windows first.
At this point, it's true.
It doesn't mean don't ship on Linux because there are very important,
very real reasons why you might why it's important for our industry,
to have some back up there, right?
And and actually, if you look to on handmade hero,
I gave a lecture recently, that's about this, if you're concerned
about that, kind of stuff and the
Fact that there's a lot of indications that that the platforms that
Indies rely on are kind of in a little bit of overhanging Jeopardy.
The Terminator Gene, which is the lecture I did, it's on the handmade
hero videos a stream.
You can watch it, it's 30 minutes, it's kind of entertaining.
It's something that kind of talks about the real risks involved in and
the ways that we as an industry, need to kind of think about starting,
starting to sort of a Shore up our
Our, our platform.
So that we aren't so beholden to an openly hostile single platform,
right?
so,
We're about over time.
So I'll kind of end it now.
Can you say something on stream to get Reddit angry?
They're already complaining about your Loop statement.
I kind of feel like Reddit is always angry so I feel like we don't
really need to say anything to make them angry.
They just will be angry.
so,
all right, looks like that's it.
Simple in pleat says, but you can code on Linux or Windows very easy,
right?
Not really, no.
I mean, you can run through wine, right?
And do your development emulated there, but that's not a very reliable
way to test, right?
Because you need to test actual Windows because wine is completely
different from actual windows and so you don't really want to be
testing your primary platform through emulation.
That's not a good way to go.
You want to test your primary platform.
With the actual platform.
So, yeah, I wouldn't recommend that.
You could try it and maybe then, just when you go to do your testing
test on actual windows in a number of skus but you're gonna have to do
anyway.
So you could do it that way.
It's not how I would choose to do it and I also don't like developing
on Linux because the their debunkers are really bad by comparison to
visual studio.
Which I know it's scary because it's not like Visual Studio is amazing
at the bugging your anything but but the Linux 2, burgers are pretty
bad so and
That's been shredded.
We've talked about that in the forum's many times and so I've kind of
pointed out the reasons for that if you're want to know what they are.
But you know, that's why I tend to stay away from using Linux as my
primary Dev platform at the moment.
so,
all right, I think we are about done for the day.
Let me go ahead and close these up.
All right.
Thank you.
And for joining me for another episode of handmade hero.
It's been a pleasure coding with you.
As always, if you want to follow along at home, you can always
pre-order the game on Hammer here a.org and it comes with a source
code.
So if you want to play around with the sort of stuff we're doing, you
can download the source code every night and, you know, sort of Tinker
with it experiment with it.
And it's a good way to learn if you're trying to follow the series as
an educational thing, that's pretty handy.
If you want to ask questions or take a look at past episodes on
anti-deficit guide that the community members,
I've done or look at ports to Mac or Linux that community members have
done in advance of us doing them.
We have a forum site, you can go to for that.
We also have a patreon page, you can subscribe to, if you just want to
support the video series and we have a tweetbot, you subscribe to.
If you want to know when the stream will be live, it shows you when
it's gonna be live for the week and then gives you a little reminders
every day.
What the stream will be that day.
So you if you want, try and catch it.
You've got plenty of notice.
That's about it tomorrow.
We will I guess check to see if
Our asset writing worked, we know that it sort of did because we
loaded a little bit of it.
So tomorrow we'll just load the rest of it in and we'll see how it
goes and from there.
Hopefully that will be relatively easy to verify the best working and
so from there we'll just switch from doing that single block load to
actually just reading piece mail out of the asset file and then that's
it for our asset file stuff.
From there we are just left with the memory management part of our
asset scheme and we will be pretty much done.
With our entire asset pipeline start to finish, which is great.
So it's pretty cool.
That'll be a pretty big to-do item checked off our list and one step
closer to having our engine pretty much ready to go.
So, thank you everyone for joining me.
I will see you tomorrow for that same time, same place, 5 p.m.
Pacific Daylight day, like time here on Twitch.
So I hope to see you all then, until then have fun coding and I'll see
you on the internet.