Alright, hello everyone and welcome to handmade here of the show.
We could complete game live on stream today.
We are going to talk about shaders because we need to put shaders into
the game for possibly some some effects reasons.
Obviously we might want to do some things with Lighting in the future
that would require us to have a Shader in there.
But the more pressing need in the reason that we're doing them, at the
immediate moment is just because we have to do some modification of
the
You values that are used for z-buffering in the game and I am pretty
sure that the most efficient way to support that rather than monkeying
with vertices when they are output at runtime is actually instead to
in the Shader taken additional coordinate that will tell the Shader to
go ahead and tweak the resulting Z values after the transform that I
think will be the most efficient thing for us to do.
We will see in a second if that's actually true,
not, but I'm pretty sure it is.
So in order to get there though, I've got to explain a bunch of stuff,
so hopefully we can get through that in a relatively short amount of
time.
And then we can move on to actually trying to get one of the shaders
working in game two.
Basically, just replicate the pipeline.
We have now with shaders.
And then we don't have to get all the way to the fixing the Z part
because that we can do the following week if we want to, but let's go.
Ahead and open up Milton here.
All right, so today is day 3.
feels like my tablet is not pressure recognized for some reason.
Where is it?
There it is.
Yeah.
All right, so let's see Jay.
369.
so,
Let's talk about.
Shaders.
I've mentioned these in the past and we should go ahead and give to
sort of a brief recap in order to understand shaders.
The very most important thing is that you understand how renderers
work in general.
And so the number one thing you should do.
If you aren't comfortable with it or didn't watch, it is go back and
watch the implementation of the software, renderer both the
implementation of the rotation part and
Imitation of the optimization part because that is crucial to
understanding how shaders work that.
100%, what you need to know, to know, understand how shaders work.
If you don't understand that stuff very well, go back there.
First, don't even bother watching this episode because that is the
crucial thing to understand first.
So I'm going to briefly say why that is just so you can map the
knowledge on and then we'll talk about the Shader specific stuff.
So the way Hardware in most cases,
On the PC does pixel processing is that the pixels themselves are
treated as a block.
So if you recall the way our software renderer worked is we took four
pixels in a row that were packed rgba.
So it was, you know, rgba rgba rgba or I think it our case.
We actually, because of the windows format, we were doing BG
RAB gra, right?
But point being.
We had four packed pixels.
Each of which had eight bytes per channel of RGB and a, which is 32
bits.
So we had four 32-bit pixels or 4 by 32 here which is 128 bits, right?
For 32-bit slots, if you will.
So if you imagine what that looks like, you can imagine those pixels
here, here's pixel.
0, 1, 2 3.
And there you go.
Right now in graphics Hardware.
There is obviously no particular.
So if you imagine what a typical Graphics primitive, looks like a
triangle or something, like this, that we're going to want to treat
individually to rasterize.
Right to produce the pixels for particular triangle.
Obviously there's no particular.
- towards them looking like long and slivery like that, right?
Or like this typically triangles are more like this shape right there.
More like reasonably sized.
In most cases if typically, artwork is trying to, if it can distribute
the triangle load evenly over the artwork, so that gets good coverage.
So, typically, they are more reasonable in terms of their area, their
more even in terms of their area,
And not extremely long and eccentric.
So what I would say is, if you look at these pixels in a row here, the
fact that we were treating our pixels in a row like this sort of
suggests this style of triangle, right?
A more sensible way.
Potentially, if you could control everything about it would be instead
to have arranged are pixels like this.
Right?
Because now we maximize the chance for a triangle that all of the
pixels fall inside.
Whereas in this case
Right?
We are sort of maximizing the chances that they don't, because we're
creating the longest possible run in one dimension, right?
Which isn't very good at keeping things inside, uniform, size shapes
now.
the reason we did that was just because in terms of how we load in
memory,
and because we are required to Output things in a certain way to
Windows that just made the most sense we needed to use Cindy, right,
which is Cindy single instruction, multiple data, right?
We needed to use the SSE.
Streaming simply extensions on the Intel architecture to do fast
processing of pixels and that is 4 wide at a minimum, right?
The, the version we were targeting as for wide, it does operations on
four things at once in floating point.
And so we wanted to be able to load something that was 128 bits.
Blow it out into channels and do for why Tops on them.
And of course, when you're doing the operations, you're doing
operations specifically,
Red Channel, green Channel blue channel.
So you want for Red's for greens for blues and for Alphas right?
In order to fill your entire CMD with right now, all of that stuff, if
that sounds unfamiliar to you have to go back and watch those.
I'm not going to explain that again here.
You have to know that stuff.
So go back and make sure you've got your fundamentals of software
rendering first.
So that you'll understand what we're talking about with shaders.
Okay, so yes this rectangle I'm sorry the square much better pattern
for keeping things on average inside uniformly shaped things.
So the way that graphics cards actually prices things is they do
process them in squares.
Now, it depends on the card itself necessarily, right?
It's not always the same, but basically, what you get is you get a
extension of the size of things being processed into.
Thing more like this.
And this is not exact, like I said, every graphics card can be
different depending on the architecture.
AMD versus a video.
How wide it is?
This sorts of things?
But this is an example of what it might be 16 pixels at a time, right?
And so what it does is it creates a square.
It still does load for a pixels in a row, but it also loads basically
four rows of that.
So it's 4 by 4 again in a square pattern especially when you get to
this size, you can imagine if we did 16 pixels across there's almost
be no chance that most of those would fall inside the same triangle.
So they tend to try to put it into more.
Metrically reasonable spaces, right?
So it's going to load 16 pixels at a time.
Let's say some I think only load eight.
I don't know the exact breakdowns of which cards do
How that goes, you'd have to talk to more of a GPU expert for those
sorts of nitty-gritty details.
There's also things like pixel packing, which try to gather pixels in
and there's all sorts of shenanigans that happen on gpus.
So this is again just the high-level overview and I'm not trying to
say this is exactly how a GPU is going to function because it's not.
So you have to imagine when you start thinking about shaders that when
I'm going to start filling pixels, I'm going to do them in exactly the
same way we did in our software rasterizer.
Only I'm probably going to do it much wider.
So instead of a 4 wide 70 think 8 wide or 16 wide Cindy so much wider
which means we want to gather up a good chunk of pixels either 8 or 16
to do all our operations on and we're gonna do those operations just
like our system.
They are masked.
So if the triangle passed through in this way, then you're going to
get a mask which says, well, all of these pixels are filled.
But these two weren't, right?
And that mask is going to say how to write back the results.
So it won't affect even though computed 3 and 12, it won't affect 3
and 12, right?
This is also sometimes colloquially called a warp in Nvidia.
Parlance, when you're looking at like Cooter, something they talked
about the number of things being processed together.
I just think of it as Cindy.
Again, I just think it is the register with or the operation with but
the things that travel together like this, where we're pressing all
the pixels together, they call a warp for some reason.
I don't know why they probably have a reason but I don't know what it
is.
That might come, I don't know.
Work might come from some multi-processing literature like earlier on,
I'm not sure.
Anyway so fundamentally speaking, when we are talking about writing a
pixel Shader, what we are writing even though it doesn't look like it.
When we write it, what we are writing is 100% just the exact exact
same kind of code.
That
Were writing.
When we wrote the software rasterizer, when you are writing a Shader,
it is literally the exact same process.
You should be thinking exactly the same way as you are.
Thinking, when you write SMD software rasterizer, which is why having
done that, you're in much better position to understand how to write a
Shader and if you haven't done that, you're going to be kind of
confused.
So why do I say that?
Well when you write a Shader, what you're going to see in the Shader
is you're going to see code.
That looks a lot like C code and it won't look very much.
Like some decode in the Shader you'll see things like, okay, I have a
veck for and the Veeck for is, maybe like the texture sample, right?
And I will call something like texture 2D and I will pass it, you
know, some UV coordinates, well I'll pass it.
You know, the texture to sample and the u and v or something like
this, right?
So you'll see code.
That looks a lot like this.
It will have built-in types.
And those built-in types will be types that are defined by the opengl
Shader compiler.
So Vic for is basically equivalent to our V4, right?
It's a bundle of, for floating Point values, you declare variables
their variables.
Just like you would think of them and see which are like text sample
or whatever, you give them a name and they correspond.
They have a type, you will see assignment and you'll see built-in
functions.
So this is a function specified by opengl that does texture.
Rambling, you pass it some parameters so it knows what it's going to
do this texture.
This you and this V will have to get from somewhere, right?
And the textures are usually abstract, they're not pointers directly a
lot of the times because we don't have access to the pointers at that
kind of a level so you can use extensions and actually do some stuff
like that with like a video instead extensions and stuff.
But we're not going to talk too much about that because that's a
little that hasn't really made into the mainstream as much yet
although the 4.5 ARB stuff.
I think actually,
Does let you do that?
Not I don't think all the bio stuff there that's a rat hole.
We can talk about at some future date after we get the basics down,
not important right now.
Anyway, this is the sort of code, you will see
But the important thing to understand it when we're writing this is
that any time that we're seeing things that are happening here, all of
these things are time 16.
So even though we aren't going to write anything other than what
happens for a single Pixel.
So this is like an example of instruction that would happen for a
single Pixel, right?
Here's the texture, here is the UV, we're sampling a texture, we're
getting back an RGB Vector for that says, here's what the color is,
right?
So we're looking
At it, and we're typing it in and it seems like it's a single Pixel.
It's not.
It's 16 pixels or some number of pixels that are having this happen,
right?
So you have to understand that basically all of these things that
you're writing in are effectively as if you were doing the wide
version.
So then when you then say text sample, right?
Down here and you're like, oh, I want a x equal that by 4.0 to like,
you know, I don't know, make it be and I don't think you put F Saint
anything and shaders until later they added the ability to that.
But regionally, you didn't do that.
If you do text sample, x equals 4.0 to multiply all of the members of
that by for, let's say, this is actually the equivalent of doing
something like what we were doing before, where we have the mmm,
right.
Mole, PS stuff.
And we said, okay, we've
Out the oops think that's just underscore mou PS we write something
like that and we just say okay we've got the text sample.
And the mm set one PS4 Point O.
So if you remember how we wrote that code this is basically equivalent
to that.
So every time in a Shader you write a basic operation.
That looks like a scalar operation in.
See it's actually expanding it out to a Cyndi operation.
That's going to operate on many things at once.
You don't know how many because the graphics card is free to choose
Like some graphics cards are 16:8 wide, whatever they could be 32
wide, who knows?
Whatever the manufacturer wanted.
So you have to understand that that's what's happening.
Now, the reason it's important to understand, why understand that and
to understand the fact that these things are getting blown out to the
width,
is because what that means is, when you think about the peak
throughput of the sampler, when you think about how much performance
it's going to get, it's going to be based entirely on how much of this
number, you can leverage right if you are constantly filling all 16
pixels and using them
And all of the instructions for all 16 pixels are getting used, then
you are going to get close to doing the number of gigaflops that that
card is capable of doing.
You're going to be using the floating-point capabilities of that card
to the fullest extent that you can.
However, if you don't do that, then you could go anywhere from slight
degradation in performance to drastic degradations and performance.
As much as like, 1/16 the
So who knows even less, right?
And how that happens is if you write Shader code unaware of what is
actually going to happen under the hood, this is pretty harmless.
This will only get next on the 16 when the triangle itself doesn't
cover enough pixels, right?
So when you're doing something like this and you've got 60 in there
and only these fraction of them are in, then you're not going to get
that 16, right?
And so there's always some loss and that loss, you know, it could even
be half, you know, who knows how much it is.
But there's always going to be some loss, just due to the fact that
you can't always get enough pixels actually relevant into the Shader,
right?
And that's the fault of the geometry and that's something you do have
to be aware of when you're thinking about how to make sure your
geometry is nicely is nicely even and does reasonable filling and that
sort of stuff right?
And remember this gets better.
Once you start,
About msaa.
Right.
Because with multi sample anti-aliasing, this 16 wide.
Well, if you did 16 x over sampling, like let's say you did 16x msaa.
Then this 16 wide is all inside, a single Pixel.
Right.
So, you know, it gets better with the more multi sample and aliasing,
you have because then you're less, and less likely to have triangles
missing things.
So there's there's that as well.
But anyway, so you start off and you assume you've got some losses due
to coverage which you can't really control as much.
The more amount of sample.
Anything you have probably the less of that you have to worry about
because you have less and less pixels per per warp and just you know a
lot of those are samples that are inside the same pixel.
So
Good.
But
you and again, even those samples though, our can still be outside I
guess if there were think of it too, right?
So if you're right on the edge of the triangle, then you can sell the
samples outside.
Just like, you have pixels outside, but I guess what I'm trying to say
is multi sample and feeling kind of it increases your effective
resolution by up to 4 by 4, right?
At which point, you're just much more likely to have a triangles of
the same size, cover more of your samples, right?
That that's all.
It's just like increasing the resolution increases or decreases the
sizes of the 4 by 4.
If the triangle stay the same size, they're going to cover more of
them, right?
So anyway, when we go through this, we have some losses due to
Geometry.
That's understandable, and that's not your fault.
In the fragment Shader, maybe your fault for how you set up the
geometry, but that's separate issue.
Once you get into the Shader prepper, you can lose a lot of that
parallelism by not
Thinking through what things cost.
So, for example, in a Shader you can write an if I could say, for
example, if the text samples, right, and the Veeck fours work, very
similar to how we wrote them in our C code.
So you can say for example dot R to get the red Channel out of a veck
for.
So I say if a text sample read for, you know, is not equal to 0.
Let's say, then I'm going to do some code here and then I'll do an
else branch and
Well, if it was equal to 0, I'll do something else, right.
So, you can write these sorts of things in a Shader.
Similarly, you can write for I Loops or something right.
I could write a for Loop here.
I could say, you know, for I don't know or a while loop like while,
you know, text sample.
R is greater than zero and we just go through here.
And at the end of this, I do like our, you know, text sample.
R- equals 0 .1, right?
so shaders, let you write complex flow control, just like you
Right, and see you can call functions.
You can do if statements, you can do while Loops.
But like I said, it's crucial to understand if you just look at that
and you don't understand how Cindy code Works, you're going to be very
confused as to why your performance is what it is.
So what happens when you write these things is just like we wrote
them.
For our masks, for our right masks, in the Shader, the in the software
rasterizer code.
That we wrote,
Just like that.
All the branches of a lip of a loop and all I'm sorry.
All the branches of an if and all of the iterations of the loop have
to happen for everybody.
Always because remember there's just one Processing Unit responsible
for executing this code for all 16 pixels at a time or 16 samples at a
time.
Right?
There are multiple cores on a GPU but in terms of one set of 16 pixels
flowing through that pipe or 8 or however many ever wide, it is just
like Cindy is only one core doing it so you can't branch.
Uniquely per sample, you have to Branch one way for all 16 samples.
So what ends up happening is when you do an, if and you look at text
sample, dot R is not equal to 0.
It's going to do the same kind of early out that we might do in the
software rasterizer, they might do a check to say are all of the
texture.
Sample .rs, not equal to 0.
If they are, then it will just execute this branch and not this one if
they definitely are not.
If they all are not, it could execute just this branch and not this
one, right?
But most of the time probably and again this is just one you need to
be aware of if you know that that's the case.
Like it's always all zeros or it's always all not zeros.
Then you're probably fine performance wise here because you haven't
introduced a problem but assuming it can be a mixture.
Then you are going to execute both branches, both branches will always
be executed, right?
And what will happen is it will create a mask.
This instruction will actually do a comparison and take the mask and
it'll leave that mask in a register.
It will then execute all of these instructions and all of these
instructions and then it will combine them using the mask into the
result.
So, all of the pixels in the warp that had the red
It'll not equal to 0.
Will get these results fused in to their slots, and all of the ones
that didn't.
We'll have it fused in, will have what happened?
He refused in, right?
So this produces one, result, whatever it is.
This reduces another and then they get masks together, right into the
result.
So again.
Understanding the Shader, just knowing what it does.
You can read this just like scalar code and yes, that's fine.
But understanding a how it performs and works.
It's crucial for you to understand that depending on the architecture
of the GPU, there can be very serious performance, concerns to things
like if statements or Loops, if you don't understand what you're
actually asking the processor to do.
If you think that you're just asking to do one or the other you're
wrong.
That's not actually what it often times will have to do.
Do so that's just worth understanding and again this multiplier is Big
getting 16 times the performance out of something from Cindy is no
laughing matter.
Right?
Take how fast your graphics card is divided it by 16, right.
That means if it's Max frame, rate was 60 frames a second, you're
talking about dividing it by 16.
You're going down to something that you wouldn't that wouldn't even be
playable, right?
You're going down to Something in the like, 23 frames a second,
something like that, right?
So you have to
And that every time you start losing, you start shaving off some of
that performance.
You're hurting yourself, in terms of getting what you need out of the
graphics card.
So you can't just willy-nilly right things that'll like do things to
just one or two pixels all the time and they'd all get fused together
in this giant Shader it'll cost you right.
The same is true for loops loops are just ifs and jumps right?
That's all they are.
They're just like I'm going to do a comparison and say if this thing
is
You know, true or not, true.
I'm going to jump one way or the other depending on it either.
I'm going to not, you know, I'm gonna let it fall out a blueprint to
jump back to the top of it.
So the same thing happens here.
However, many times through this while loop, the longest pixel goes,
that's how many everyone goes.
So even if you're on average, all of your pixels like only take one or
two Loops, let's say, right?
But in every war / 16, there happens to be one that goes like
100 Loops then every time it will be doing 300 Loops right now.
It's probably not going to happen that way.
It's probably going to be that only a few you know of those Works will
have the 300 Loop case.
But again every time you hit the 300 Loop case you're doing that 300
Loop for all 16 samples, not just that one.
So you lose the performance on everyone in the warp when that happens
and that's very important to understand, right?
so,
That's the thing to keep in your mind when you're writing shaders is
that you are wide and everything, you do is going to be interpreted as
Sim dstyle instructions.
So just keep that in mind as we're writing it and you'll be much much
better off in terms of understanding the performance on handmade hero.
We don't have a lot of complex things that we need to do in the Shader
so we probably won't have to keep this in mind for ourselves very
much.
We will not be pushing the graphics cards Shader capabilities in the
real way.
So I won't have a chance to really show you this in action.
But when you are doing more complicated engine work, where you're
trying to do photorealistic rendering or who knows what else you're
doing, gather indirect lighting, who knows that sort of stuff.
This is the sort of thing that you have to understand.
It's going to be important for you to get it right.
Okay.
So, now, the only other thing that we need to talk about before we can
go write some Shader stuff, is that there's two parts to this traitor
pipeline, one of which we haven't really mentioned yet and the other
is the the part that we just talked about.
So that part I just talked about in opengl parlance is called the
fragment Shader.
Right.
There we go.
Let's try that one more time.
Fragment.
But we also need a thing called a Vertex Shader.
And what a Vertex Shader does is a vertex Shader is basically the
transform stuff that we have done in our Graphics pipeline to do that
perspective, transform and you know anything else that you want to do,
that happens per vertex.
So
In up in jail, right?
We're sending down these vertices x y, z w.
You know, x y z.
W etcetera, right?
We're sending down these vertices to the graphics card and then we
just talked about.
Okay?
Then somewhere over here, the graphics card is going to have this warp
of pixels and it's going to fill or samples you know pixels in our
case.
Now it's samples because we're doing msaa.
So it's going to have this work of samples.
Those samples are going to be
Are going to be computed.
And so obviously somehow we got from here to here and that's where the
vertex Shader part comes in.
There's also other things called tessellation and geometry shaders,
which can happen before the vertex Shader stage, if you want to do
more complex work on these vertices.
This is essentially the, like, one in one out pipeline, right?
You put in say, three vertices for a triangle, you get out three
vertices that get
Drives into a triangle for fragment shading, but there's other ways
you can do say, if you want to just put in one vertex and have that
blow out to hundreds of vertices that got interpreted as triangles or
something like that.
So for amplification, that sort of thing.
If you want to do stuff like that, there are shaders that can do those
sorts of things as well, they happen before they happen back here
right there.
Having a lot of Milton problems here.
What's going on?
Here we go.
So there's stuff that happens to the left of this diagram, that we
don't need to worry about right now.
But for our purposes, we do need to know about these two.
So a Vertex Shader is exactly the same kind of code.
As a pixel Shader, there's almost no difference between the two of
them.
The only difference is instead of working on say 16 warp, a 16 size,
warp of fragments are samples or pixels.
Instead we're going to do a 16 x warp of vertices.
So instead of taking in fragments, we're just going to take in like
16, x, 16, y, 16, V 16 W is into our vertex Shader and we're going to
operate on them.
Right?
All the same stuff.
I just said, applies.
In fact, it does not.
You don't even have to think in either Shader about anything different
at all really.
They're both pretty much exactly the same in almost all respects.
Except for some things like fragment discard and stuff that will kind
of touch on a little bit, maybe later, but basically exactly the same,
it's just taking a big old batch of scalar values.
16 x16 by 16 z6w 16.
Anything else, color 16, movies for your texture 16.
Whatever's right transforming those and preparing them to be output to
the fragment Shader.
So what we will do is we will say when we declare these and you'll see
me do it will say what travels across this boundary, you know,
probably the positions for the vertices of the triangles that are
going to be rasterized, probably the texture coordinates that are
going to be used to look at the textures, probably a color value for
doing that modulation, right?
So we're going to declare the stuff that goes across and we'll
Make them line up.
But basically that all that's going to happen in here, there's nothing
special at all.
It's just doing a bulk, the bulk work of taking in rough, vertices
from the app streams that are we Define and sending them over to the
fragment Shader processed so that it can start doing rasterization on
them.
Right now, again, there actually is a rasterizer in here, right?
That we don't see and that's the thing that
Takes an actual triangle and generates the pixels that are actual
samples that are actually used in the fragment Shader, that is not
programmable.
So the vertex Shader outputs, the vertices that will be used to
rasterize the triangles.
The, the fragment Shader takes in the fragments that that triangle
covers, right?
But in between there, there is the rasterization step and you don't
see that.
So you don't get to see how triangles rasterize or
Change it that may change in the future but for right now it's not.
That's just what it is.
Okay, so
Is the end of that.
Let's go ahead now and actually do some work with these so that we can
see how this works in practice.
Now that you get the idea about how they work and again this is day
39.
So start with day 368 source code and that's what I'm me starting with
now.
So here's on the opengl side of things.
if you remember correctly, we started with our
Let's see here.
Here we go.
First thing I want to do is actually correct.
Something that Martin's pointed out, one of the problems with
programming opengl on stream is I don't have time to really read the
docs much and opengl.
I don't tend to know by heart just because I don't tend to really love
Graphics, apis, if you couldn't tell.
So I usually just make my own and then I kind of just write a little
binding layer and read the docs for a few weeks to get the right
stuff.
But I tend to not think in terms of opengl or anything.
That.
So I sometimes make errors in the minutiae and in this case Martin's
pointed out that validate looking at the validate status to get
compile errors isn't necessary and perhaps not wanted because
validation what it does is it checks the entire state of a program
including whether or not things like the arrays that are bound at the
time to take vertices are compliant with that vertex Shader and stuff
like that.
We didn't want any of that sort of thing.
We didn't want a full validation.
Ian.
So really all we need to do here when we check the status is we really
just wanted the Lincoln compiled status so we can get the link status
and compiled status like so.
And so what we can do is say you know link validated
Compiled validated.
LinkedIn compiled.
And then we've got a way to check, like, okay, if we linked and
compile their, if we didn't.
So I'm just going to go ahead and grab those in just to make that.
Because that's, I don't want to leave that in sort of a, not quite the
right way to do it state.
So let me just go ahead and get core are about here.
Oops.
And I'm going to grab those guys.
All right, and we'll leave out its ass in there because we may want to
do validation later on so we probably want to keep that going.
All right, so now in theory, if we run this we should be able to still
get compile errors on it which is what we wanted.
Here's that that Shader validation failed and if we look
Get we get the logs that we wanted which is what we which is what
we're doing before.
So what we want to do now is we want to actually start doing some of
these shaders, we want to try to compile the Shader.
Martin's also pointed out that that
In 20 in, in visual studio 2013, which is the version we are using on
handmade hero, you can use the multi-line strings.
It does have that support as in 2013, apparently, I've never tried it
but he said you can.
And what that means is that we could do something that allowed well,
here I'll bring it up.
Do we have a?
So this one right here is the one we're talking about.
I don't know if the here doc stuff.
yeah, you can ignore the rest of this for now, but
You can see here how this stuff works where you can say.
Okay you've got this are prefix where you're basically saying, hey,
this is going to be a string because I don't know if you remember, if
I don't remember forever.
Did wide strings?
I don't know that we ever actually did that but in C++, you can prefix
for example, a string with an l and the L prefix means that it's going
to be a 16, a utf-16 string, right?
Um and you can see some other things in here where they've got some
other prefixes, right?
But basically what this is is something that pre that comes before the
quote that will tell you, this is a that will tell the C compiler.
This is a special kind of string and this kind of string is basically
a way of saying, hey I'm going to put a delimiter in here.
That's going to tell you when you can end.
And so there's going to be a delimiter, followed by an open
parenthesis and the closed parenthesis, and then another delimiter.
And I'm going to
Guarantee to you that that delimiter will never appear anywhere in
here.
So basically, I'm going to give you the way of telling when you've got
to the end and that again, is we talked about, this is the here docs
for it.
I didn't think that that was in 2013 yet, but Martin says it is, so
that's good.
If we can do it because at that means we could make our shaders pretty
conveniently, right?
That means we could do something like this.
And then close it like this.
And then we don't actually have to do anything bizarre.
In theory anyway.
If it worked.
Now, I don't know if it will but that's the.
Yep.
And it does.
So I guess we can actually use those, those hear Doc's, which is
awesome.
It also means we can write our shaders and include them in line if
we'd like to.
So, we could write them as separate files if we want them to be
separate files, but we can sort of cross that bridge when we get a
little further down the road.
So, let's go ahead and try this here.
Oops.
I don't know when they added this but it's nice that they did.
I wonder if it's in 2012.
I don't know when it's, when I don't know when it made it in there
anyway.
Hmm.
Let Stoops don't need that.
So you know, if we take a look at how that works,
I guess there's really probably not a lot of.
You know, I'm a I'm assuming that pound includes in here would not be
parsed so we would still if even if we wanted to write a file that had
the Shader and it would probably still have to put the r: in front of
it.
I would guess.
But, you know, that's probably okay.
So, still not quite ideal for our purposes, I guess.
But nothing you can do about it, all right.
So here we go.
Here is our header code, here's our vertex code and here's our
fragment code.
And essentially what we need to do now is we need to sort of learn the
structural syntax of these shaders so that you can do useful stuff
with them.
And one of the things that typically helps, if you can find it and
we'll have to talk about the versioning a little bit here.
But if you can find, it is a, this Shader is fast.
This Shader language is called.
Sell right, the GL shading language.
And if you use that glsl search term and look for a glsl like version,
you know, like one point three quick reference card.
Hopefully, you can find one.
Here we go.
I think 130 is the version number for whatever reason on opengl
shading, Shader language 3.2.
I think, maybe I can't quite remember what the version numbering is
the version numbering on.
These is really weird.
That's the reason I typed in 1.3, you don't put pound 320 to do a
Shader.
In this one, you do pound.
You'll see that in a second, if it sounds like I'm babbling about it.
Let me take a look here.
So, version directive.
So it's this thing.
Basically what happens here is you can kind of take a look and see
like okay so if I want the you know to select a Shader version that's
going to be backwards compatible to sort of older things you know you
can go back to say opengl 3.0 or 3.2 and pick out one of the version
numbers and unfortunately the version numbers don't correspond with
the opengl versions because reasons.
So typically what ends up happening is the pound is
You have to pick a version of the language to say what your Shader
because the Shader does get the Shader versions are not backwards
compatible with each other.
So you have to pick a version that you're going to use.
And once you pick that version, the first thing you have to do inside
the Shader code is say what version it is that you think you're
actually trying to use so that you can guarantee that the compiler
will know what you were looking for, right?
So in our case, we can probably get away since we're doing, we're not
really doing much of anything in the Shader at this point.
We can probably get away with just using Shader 3.0.
Let's say so a pound 130 version would be fine.
And so what we can do here is just say, all right give us Shader
version 130.
Okay.
And in theory that should work just fine.
Oops don't need to put that in all of them.
I can just put that in the shared header.
So in theory that should be fine if I
This code, I would assume that we will not get any complaints about
that and I am correct about this.
There is no problems there, right?
So,
Once we have that and we know what version were in having the quick
reference card up is nice because the quick reference card will tell
you everything you need to know about what exists in this version of
opengl Shader language which is not always easy to remember.
Because even once, you know what those are, you may not remember which
ones go with which versions.
Now this looks to me like the API.
So here's okay.
Here we go.
Opengl shading language 150, quick reference card.
Here you go.
Although I gotta be honest, this doesn't look like the one I actually
wanted.
Okay, here's the guy, there's more of it.
Yeah, here we go.
I was like, I wanted more than that.
So right here is where it starts.
Okay, so the reason I think it's good to have one of these up.
Like I said is it's hard to remember all the stuff that's in there
even after you kind of are more familiar with it.
So I like to have one of these so second to remember oh wait is there
a function that lets me sample a texture at a particular level of
detail?
You know, an integer position or whatever?
Blah, blah blah.
And you're like, oh yeah, okay it does or doesn't have that.
It's easy to kind of look through here and see whether that's in there
rather than trying to learn it and remember it all.
So that's kind of nice.
But anyway, what you can see in terms of how this breaks down, you can
see in here, this is the version directive stuff.
And like I said, we're not going to use full of 150 because I don't
think we need it.
So there might be some things in here.
We can't access, but most of the things, we should be able to access
just fine.
You can see on here that a lot of the stuff is very self-explanatory,
right?
Like you can see all the types that exist in glsl.
They're all types that we have that we have written ourselves, sort of
In handmade hero, which is like you know, Vic to vector v of X.
For all very familiar to you, you've got vectors of Boolean factors of
integers, just like we did.
Sometimes we would create, you know, other things.
You've got the matrices for 2x2 3x3 for my for, right?
And you've got ones that are abnormally size as well like a 2, by 3
Matrix.
So all that stuff is very familiar.
Some of the other stuff is probably not so familiar.
You've got floating points a types.
This is things that sample from textures.
It is just a types.
Also, Sam from textures, you got implicit conversions, that will tell
you how their conversions work.
You can see here, they've got good Vistaprint.
Just like just like in C you can create a raised structures and blocks
just like you can see blocks are special.
They're not something that you've seen in.
See.
It block is basically just a structure style thing that lets, you
know, that something corresponds to a piece of code, you're going to
talk about in your
In line.
Because one of the things that you'll see us have to do, as we get a
little further down, is figure out how to get data into these shaders
from the outside, from our code, all the operators are the same pretty
much is what you've expectancy with some subtle differences so mostly
you can use your intuition here.
You know, you've got assignments and bitwise operators, logical,
operators shifting multiplication, all that stuff.
Most of the things you're used to having our their parentheses all
that.
Duff is exactly as expect.
For Vector components is exactly like see where you do the bracketed
initialize list.
So the people who made these shade languages, we're see.
See
People, they made it look like sea.
And so most of the stuff that you expect to be there is there.
You also have tons of built-in functions.
So you get a math library that comes with this.
That's built in either to the car door to the shading compiler.
One of the other you don't necessarily know which at any given time
but you they're guaranteed generally to be reasonably performant for
whatever the operation is what you could expect.
So things like sine cosine, tangent, taking the max to the minimum,
doing a mod, a ceiling a
The floor rounding all that sort of stuff.
I guess.
Florida, they don't have in there.
Yes, I guess you'd have to use you use frak that I don't see floor in
here.
Oh no, there it is.
That's what they should be there.
Flora truncation taking the sign.
Absolute value Powers logs blah, blah, blah, blah blah.
So you've got a full math library in there as well.
Linear interpolation is here, they call it mix.
So it also a smooth step function which is like a little like cubic
curve.
So to like
Then he's out of stuff.
So there's a lot of things you can do here, dot products, cross
products, take the distance, all the things we implemented in our math
library and handmade hero are here and probably some that aren't.
So they've got a lot of stuff to work with and then you've got a bunch
of built-in functions for doing things like getting information from
textures getting gradients which are things that we'll talk about.
Potentially if we ever get to them, we don't know.
We will noise values that sort of thing.
So there you go, right.
And
So understanding how to program the opengl shading, language is pretty
straightforward.
You'll see, once we get going you have a lot of stuff at your
disposal.
It's all standardized.
So you can just use everything that's here.
And the compiler will make that into efficient GPU code, and you can
just rely on it.
Usually, there aren't a lot of surprises there.
Okay, so now the way that this works is there is for whatever reason,
a Mane.
Did actually call it main.
So we I don't think that's specified anywhere on here.
So I guess you just kind of have to know, at least, I don't see it
anywhere, maybe it's defined.
Woohoo.
Maybe it's defined on here somewhere.
I'm not entirely certain, but you start off in a main just like you do
at a sea program.
And then one of the things that obviously is a little confusing is
well, okay, so I've got two main.
This thing is supposed to operate on 16 pixels or 16 vertices of the
time.
How do I say, what the result is like, how do I get information in?
And how do I put information back?
And the answer is, it's all done by global variables.
And so let me show you how that happens.
all right, so let's say, we're going to write some vertex code, for
example, what we have to do in the vertex code, and I'll show you this
in just a quick second here, but
For starters, we have to have some kind of input.
So we're going to have some kind of an input vertices here.
So like input vertices
Input vertex, right?
We're going to have some kind of input predicts that we have to
operate on and we're going to have to Define that as something, right?
We're going to have a main here and we're going to have to Define that
function.
But essentially what we're going to do is also have after that and
output vertex and we're going to have to write some code that does
something along the lines of oops.
Output vertex equals input vertex.
And obviously, probably we're going to want something like our
transform here.
And so fundamentally speaking a Shader basically looks like this it's
going to Define some Global variable called an input vertex and
somehow and we're going to get to that later somehow that will get
correspondent later on in our code with the vertices coming from our C
code.
So, our actual code for handmade hero in the game, will be setting
some things so that the opengl subsystem knows what should go into
input.
We're going to define something that's an output for a text here and
it won't actually probably called output vertex because you'll see in
a second.
It's got a special name but we're going to basically a sign that
output vertex to whatever we do to our input vertices and then we're
going to have some information, we're going to need like this
transform.
That's going to have to again come from handmade hero, that's going to
do the transform and basically this is what a Shader is going to look
like the main is essentially, in your head is going to be called for
For every input vertex.
So, every input vertex will go through whatever we write in here, and
this can be as complicated as we want.
This going to be many lines, we can call function, can have loops can
have ifs, but at some point, we have to assign something to the output
for a text and whatever ends up being assigned to the output per text.
At the end is what will actually be output of the Shader.
Okay.
And again this even though it's input vertex output vertex and
transform, it looks like it's only doing one thing.
It's doing this for like 16 pixels at a time or more, right?
I'm sorry 16.
She's a time from work.
Okay, so let's start with output vertex because that's the easiest
instead of us defining, a global variable for this.
What actually happens is opengl has already defined a global variable
for this and I believe those are in here.
Somewhere.
Here you go.
So you can see here is built in inputs outputs and constants.
You can see here, all of them are specified for what we care about
here is the vertex language.
Here's what's coming in.
We've got GL color, secondary color, and normal vertex multitec,
scored and fog cord, right?
That's I believe.
If you're using the fixed function pipeline, those will be
Again, otherwise you'll see there, you can Define your own and which
is probably what we'll do a little bit later on but then in the
outputs for this you end up having a glp position somewhere.
There it is.
A GL position which is going to be no, that's not trailer.
Where is it?
There should be an output to this summer.
There it is.
GL position this GL position.
Is the actual output in clip coordinates it that's going to be the
thing that we're actually using right that that the that the Shader
will actually output.
So this is automatically defined by opengl.
As are these other ones clip vertex trip distance and point size we
can output to if we want to override those things.
We have no need to have any of those values be set to anything.
We only care about the position because that's all we're using in the
pipeline.
So, this output vertex is actually just this
And it's already defined for us as a vector for.
So, effectively.
Opengl had this defined for us at the top of the program, but we're
not going to touch it because it's a special variable that it knows is
the output from the Shader.
So then we have what our inputs and our transform our.
And in this case, we have, I believe GL underscore vertex.
If we use the fixed function pipeline, I've never tried to use the
fixed function parameters.
Let's give it a shot.
I don't know if it'll work or not, probably won't and we can go ahead
and go to the, the primary way to do it, which is what we want to get
to anyway, but we'll put it in there for now.
So effectively, there's this being defined as well, which is the input
vertex in this case.
So we can do this.
Oops,
And so this is just saying the output is equal to the transform of the
input vertex vertex coordinates.
So the x y z w here is going to get multiplied by transforming it's
going to Output 2 GL position that is all we need if we had this
transform.
Now we know that this is a 4 by 4 Matrix, right?
And you can see in here, you got Matt, and we could do Matt for or we
can type it in Matt 4x4.
Either one will work.
I'd like Matt 4x4.
It's a little clearer so maybe I'll leave it that way.
We we know we want to map 4x4 transform here but what we don't know is
where this would come from, right?
Because remember this is going to get called from our code in our
code.
This this is going to be executed on the GPU when we try to dispatch a
batch of criminals right when we try to do some rendering like a GL,
begin GL end that batch of vertices is going to have to go through
this Shader.
Where does the transform come from right?
How is it going to get there because it needs to get past effectively.
We from our C code in handmade hero to the code operating on the GPU.
And how is that going to happen?
Well, the way that happens is this thing called a uniform, which when
you declare something as a uniform, what that's trying to say is this
is something that doesn't vary per vertex.
That's where the term uniform comes from, right?
It doesn't vary depending on the thing.
I'm operating on it's going to be set by somebody and then all of the
vertices that come down in a set, are going to use it.
So what that means is we can set these uniforms before.
Execute a Shader and those uniforms will then be able to be
communicated from our C code, right?
So how that works?
Is, if you come up here and you can see render group entry render
entry bitmap, right?
This is the code that we want to have happen.
What we would do is in this code, we would have a called here and
we'll have to look up.
What that call is, right?
It's GL uniform, but, you know, I want to show it to you in, whatever
they'll be a call, which will say, all right, I want you to bind and
it won't quite work this way because we'll have to look it up first.
In fact, it's more like this sort of thing.
What we will effectively have to do is take the transform that we want
to be used here and that transform again.
We actually do know what it is because we load it right here right we
do this load Matrix M for my for proj transpose this sort of thing.
What we can do is just say oh
okay, let's just
let's just keep this project around, right?
Every time we come through and we generate the four, by four Matrix, I
can now specify that, I want that Matrix to be the Matrix that gets
used every time that you're going to do one of these things, right?
So when we do this,
Specification here, what we can do is say we need to know what the
ideas of this transform, and then we need to set that transform to be
this value, right?
And so what this will do is this will tell opengl, hey, this line will
say, go look at the Shader
Figure out what your you know, what is the ID?
You know?
Basically.
What do you what do you use to talk about the location where this
string?
This strings name goes right?
In other words.
I should explain this.
So,
We've got something that says uniform.
Matt.
Four by four transform.
And then blah blah blah blah Shader, right?
Here's my shooter code.
So, you know, all right, I've got uniform at forward for a transform.
I've got some Shader stuff here and I need to be able to set this,
right?
So what's going to happen when opengl compiles this down, right?
This is going to go through the compiler.
Is it's going to go through a compiler specific to the GPU.
So on this machine it's AMD so it's going to go through amd's compiler
and it's going to Output a bunch of AMD right machine code.
So this is stuff that's going to be run on the AMD core, right?
So all of our Shader instructions are going to get compiled down just
like they would have got compiled down.
If it was regular C code to exit x64, they're going to get compiled
down to MD machine code.
That AMD machine code is going to be referencing a specific location
in memory where it expects this transform to be.
It's going to expect 16 floats.
Right to be somewhere in memory and it will have picked where that is.
So it will have an address that it knows it's going to grab.
When it goes to execute this Shader, this machine code will be looking
at that address.
Now that address is relative to the core because obviously it's
working on a particular batch at that time.
So it's not like it's necessarily a fixed address in the GPS memory
for all time but it has some idea of for a particular execution.
There's some
Will memory for this execution and where that is in here.
It knows, right?
So it's got, you know, we'll call it an offset address, where that's
supposed to be.
What we need to do is tell opengl.
Hey, we're going to give you that 16 floats.
Okay, here they are.
I need you to copy that down to the card and I need it to go into the
location where it needs to go for this Shader execution, right?
So what we're doing here is were saying, hey go look at when you
compile
All this Shader.
Tell me where this variable ended up, right?
Give me back a cookie.
Basically that I can use to talk to you about that location because I
don't need to know what it is, right?
I just need to tell you to put something there and here's me telling
you this is what I want to put there and then it will go down there,
right?
And then for this execution, the Shader for the GL, begins UGL, and
pair here, it will take that.
And use it, right?
It'll use that as the as the value of that variable.
So that's affected what we need to do.
Obviously we don't need to do this every time the like look up for the
name and that could be expensive for all we know.
So what we really want to do is have in here
Something like this, right?
Where our opengl that were using.
We can just say that it's a global because it's never going to change.
So when we do our initialization and we do create program, we're going
to want to do that, call down here.
Right?
So that it snapped and saved.
Okay, so that's how the vertex Shader code will work.
And we need to work out what those calls are obviously.
But other than that,
We are now okay to move forward.
So we have our GL position.
We're doing our transform there, and we've got our, our fragment code
now that we need to to create as well.
Same exact thing applies here.
We're going to have to define a main, and we're going to have to do
something with what's going on.
Oops, in terms of our inputs and outputs.
Now what you'll see here for the first time is we
Now, have a way that this needs to get communicated things have
communicated from the vertex Shader to the fragment Shader, which we
haven't had to do yet because remember this GL position is a special
variable that outputs the position.
The reason there's a special variable that I've put the position is
because it has to go into this piece that we don't control.
Oops.
Remember I said there's this rasterizer in between so we do some
stuff.
The vertex Shader, there's a rasterizer that rasterizes the triangles
then we get the French Quarter, this guy needs to know the positions
because it needs to know the corners of those vertices in order to
rasterize the triangle.
So GL position is defined as that communication, right?
GL position is the value.
You need to give the rasterizer for those vertices.
So we didn't have to Define that because it's already something that's
built in because the rasterizer has to know it.
So it has to be known to the glsl.
It has to be something that
Understands natively, it can't be a variable we Define.
However, we now get to something, we're in our fragment code, we
actually do need to know something, because we have to know what
texture we are going to be sampling from and we're right.
So we're going to have to have a texture coordinate that gets passed
down here, right?
We're going to have to have some way of getting texture coordinates in
and some way of outputting texture coordinates to the fragment Shader.
Now, I think about it though.
We can probably hold off on that for a second.
So hold that thought, actually, because we should probably get this
working with without textures first.
Alright, so in the fragment code, the same thing is true.
As in the vertex Shader code.
If you take a look at these vertex language built-in outputs and
constants, right?
You can see what all the them were there.
And then we've got the same is true for the fragment language so you
can see all the in values.
It, you've got the fragment coordinate the whether it was front facing
the clip distance, the point coordinates which are if you were doing a
the points right stuff.
That's same.
As the point size thing here it's again, not.
So when we care about what the Primitive ID was again, not something
we care about and the fragment death.
So you can see here, we've got some
We've got some inputs, none of which we really care about and we have
an output which we sort of care about potentially, right?
This is the depth value which we might care about, but you'll notice
the color actually, isn't there?
And the reason that the color isn't there, if I remember correctly, is
that actually for reasons?
I do not completely understand and really couldn't say what the reason
was instead of there being a predefined
Output for that.
You can actually just Define your own if I remember correctly.
Now, I thought that you could also use GL frag color and I feel like
that might be something that comes in a later.
Shader language version.
Meaning when they went up, in fact, let me just look to see if I'm
right about this because I'm just curious now
Yeah, okay so let's see.
No it's still not there so I guess maybe I'm just hallucinating about
that.
But anyway, what I was going to say beforehand before I kind of got
sidetracked on wondering whether or not that was true, is my
recollection, is that just whatever you define as an output variable
ends up being?
If the first one is,
The output color and if you define more than there are more output
colors that go to more buffers or something weird like this.
All right, so let's look at that for a second.
So as you can see here in the pre declared variable declarations, you
can see there's these ins and these outs those are not in C, right?
We never use in and out declarations and see because little variables
are just Global variables in shaders.
Since there are these pieces of code that kind of get welded together
with known things on either side.
Like the
Mance rayder has inputs from the vertex Shader and outputs pixel
values.
The vertex Shader has inputs from the tessellation of geometry
shaders, or the opengl pipeline itself.
And then has outputs that go to the fragment Shader, there's this
notion of in and out Global's because they're the things that the
context in which the Shader was being executed.
What comes in, what goes out, we can use those to say.
Okay, there's a now.
Variable here, it's going to be a vector for and it's going to be the
fragment color.
And then all we would do is say well, okay, whatever that is, let's
say the result color is effect for that's just read.
Right.
It's just red.
Okay.
And so again, this would in theory, be a completely usable pipeline,
if this transform value, we're set it would work, right?
It would be something that takes in vertex, coordinates transforms
them out to positions the positions get rasterized in between these
two then it calls the fragment code for each pixel or sample that got
rasterized.
It has to produce an output color so at least one output Vector for
has to be declared for the
What color the result color is going to always be set to read but in
the future, we'll set something more complicated.
And that's the end of it.
Now we have to go up here and actually put in this this code that I
was talking about before and since we have a quick reference card up
we might as well use it.
We actually have in here all of the stuff that you can use for
shaders.
You can see the uniform calls being talked about here.
This is all we really need.
You can see it here.
We've got uniform Matrix, f v.
There's the ENT location, the size, I count the Boolean transpose and
the consulate value that is exactly what we want, right?
We're trying to specify a uniform Matrix.
And again, we want it to be a 4 by 4 Matrix, which
They don't support.
Oh, I guess they don't support a 4 by 4.
So, you just put for, at the end of it.
All right?
So, whatever.
So that's effectively this, but they don't have it.
So, it's gonna be like, that would be bizarre.
I've done this many times, and I don't remember that.
I guess it's just they didn't bother giving the 4 by 4, this is only
for odd sizes for non-square sizes.
So there's that location.
Like I said that, we have to query, we then have a count.
We only want to specify 1 Matrix, it allows you to specify a bunch of
matrices in bulk.
There's a transpose.
Now, one of the nice things about that is the transpose part.
Like I said, before we can now, we were doing that transpose manually
ourselves.
And remember when we did that, I said when we get to shaders, we won't
have to do that anymore.
Well that is 100% the case.
Now we can if we want to just stop doing this
Entirely.
And instead say that proj just equals clip proj.
And it will work, so that's pretty cool.
For now, since I want to see if I can maintain these two pipes, just
for a second.
As we transition them over, this may be a complete disaster to try and
do but we'll try it anyway.
We're just going to say okay for now we won't transpose though.
So again location count transpose and value.
And so then there's that value which is just the main two floats of
that Matrix, right?
So that's what we need to do there.
And of course I actually have to well, you know what?
That's fine.
So we're going to have to load that variable certainly.
But then while we're at it we might as well grab the other one we need
to which is that when we're doing this transfer my D stuff, we've got
to have a way of getting it and what you can see is we want to get
this location ID.
We need a place to get that from and you can see here with Universe,
you've got this get uniform location, right?
And that's exactly what we want to be able to do.
We want to be able to get uniform location for a program and a name,
right?
So that's the function that we
Need.
And so, this opengl basic Z bias program that we get back, that's
actually what we want to get our transform back.
Right?
So we need get uniform location and we need the ability to load the
uniform.
But in addition to that, what you'll notice here is that no point,
have we ever specified how to actually say that we're trying to run
that program, right?
So at no time that we actually
Told opengl that we want this program to be run.
So we need some way of specifying that, right?
And we can do that by using the called GL use program.
So what Jill use program does is it says, I'm going to tell you the
program now that I want you to actually operate on and so that program
is that one that we compiled, right?
It's the basic see bias program.
And again, I've never tried to use the fixed function pipeline like
this before, and I'm pretty nervous that it's not going to work.
So we might have to first pour everything over to the program version
before we get it working.
That's not a lot of work.
So it's not a big deal but just fair warning, that may happen.
So, so be advised.
All right, so that's all we need at the moment.
So we just have to get those two uniform Matrix and get uniform
location.
We just need those, too.
Functions.
And then we should be good to go.
So,
See, let's just go ahead and grab that get uniform location.
And then we also want basically all of this stuff.
You know.
We might want any number of these but probably none of these were
probably always going to load in bulk.
So I would say we probably only really need, you know, this one and
this one we probably won't use much more than that.
Oops.
Okay.
So these are the new functions we will need again.
There's nothing mysterious hear about these.
So I'm just going to go ahead and do exactly what we always do with
them.
Know how I did the those before.
I guess I do it that way.
And then these get lower case of fide.
So, there you go.
And so now I just have to actually get these
Like so.
And last but not least, paste the name.
I suppose.
There we go.
So now we're effectively doing everything that probably would be
necessary to bind things together here.
But again, we may have to kind of push a little bit further before we
can actually get things running.
I'm going to go ahead and run first and see what's going on with our
shaders here because we may have errors and stuff.
So, oh yeah, that's a good point.
We never actually put in the main
I just left that in there.
So the glsl Declaration for main, I don't even remember.
What it looks like.
So, that's a good question.
So it looks like it's just void main void.
Which is fine.
Although, it seems to be complaining about our vertex shaders having
one, which is odd.
Oh, no, I only put that in the fragment Shader.
There we go.
So, you know what?
I guess now that I think about it is that even when I did that compile
status there, I may have done that slightly wrong.
When I put that in there pile status, let's take a look.
because compiled status may not be something that's
Find in the program Ivy, let me go ahead and just grab out because
we're now compiling properly, but we're getting an error, and I'm
probably just asking that for the wrong thing.
So let's double check here, dot DL.
Let's take a look.
Yeah, so you can see compiled status is not actually on here.
So compiled status must be only for get Shader.
So, I should be able to just say, get link status is probably all I
really need would be my guess because the link status would fail.
Presumably if the
like presumably, I can just do
This.
All right, so hey, I guess that actually worked, which I wasn't
expecting it to because like I said, I wasn't expecting it to actually
be able to mix with the function fixed function placement, so
smoothly.
I mean, I know it's supposed to but, you know, that's not a path that
anyone cares about in opengl because nobody uses it right.
But hey, there you go.
So there's that red that our Shader is doing, right?
And remember this stretch to Infinity is because our
You coordinate is set completely nuts.
So hey, let's see if our Shader really is working.
Let's go ahead and take that W coordinate and correct it.
Right, let's go ahead and say that GL vertex.
I'm going to find a veck for here, which is input for at x equals g l
vertex, right?
And then let's take our input vertex and let's set the W coordinate
equal to 1.
Right.
So that now we're not having that cause remember we were using the w,
we modify the pipeline to specify in the W, coordinate, r, z bias
value, which ruined the W coordinate which is what caused everything
to stretch into Infinity when we did it.
Now in our vertex Shader, let's take that out.
and he look,
Now, we're all correct.
So now you can actually see our vertex Shader is running, and it's
actually doing something useful.
Now, it's not particularly great because we're just drawing red,
rectangles, but that's pretty close to two working, right?
I mean, that's, that's roughly what we wanted.
So that's great.
And now all we have to do is say, alright, let's start taking this a
little bit further.
So, first of all, what we could do is say, well, you can kind of see
here where we create our GL position.
This GL position is going to have the x y&z w on it, right?
So what be pretty interesting to do here is say well okay, what if we
just use that Z bias value that, we have our GL vertex, W is the Z
bias value that we have.
We could if we wanted to offset the Z,
That we use for z-buffering by that value, right now, that value has
to be set to something reasonable obviously, because if we don't set
it to something reasonable, it has to be reasonable based on what
we're actually doing to our values here, right?
So after the transform and things are mapped into the Z space, that Z
space is negative 1 to 1, that bias value has to in some way,
correspond to this, right?
But if we want to be kind of lazy which I kind of do it right now
because I don't want to go work out any math that I don't have to yet,
you can imagine saying well we have a z bias value, let's just
transfer them to points and then we'll set the Z value to be whatever
the biased one Z value is.
And and and that's how we'll do it, right?
So we can say Veeck for
Z transform.
And what that'll be is, that'll be times the input vertex, Susie
vertex.
What we'll do is we'll just take the input vertex and we'll take the Z
coordinate of it, right?
And we'll add to that Z coordinate, whatever the Z bias value was,
which is coming through in the W coordinate, right?
Will transform it.
And then after we get the z-transform, version will take our GL
position.
The output that we're going to have there and we'll just over, right?
Oops, we'll just overwrite the GL positions Z coordinate with this.
He transforms Z coordinate.
Right.
So now what you can actually see is we are getting the biasing that we
wanted.
We're no longer clipping through the cubes right now.
We haven't set up texturing yet so we're kind of just sitting there
looking pretty dumb, but because we're just all red bread values, but
you will notice that these things.
These, these Sprites are still clipping straight through the cubes, we
just never see it because they're Z bias is always taking care of it.
So did you see how I did that?
All I did was I just wrote in the Shader code I was like, all right, I
have an input for Texas coming in.
I know that the W coordinate is secretly the Z bias, right?
So I'm going to overwrite the in the Z value that I'm going to
actually use, I'm going to overwrite that with one because that's what
I actually want to use for my transform, right?
Then I'm going to create another vertex which is the same as the input
vertex, but instead of having its normal Z value going to offset it C
value by that Z bias, right?
And you can think of it this way.
Right.
Another way to think of it might be.
Think you can do this.
We're going to find out.
So do you think it might be, okay?
The input vertex is actually whatever the GL vertex is
XYZ.
But then it's w coordinates going to be 1, right?
Then the Z bias is actually coming out of the W coordinate of the
input vertex, right?
So we're using the x y z in the W for two separate purposes.
Then we're going to create this synthetic vertex, that's the same as
our input vertex, but with the Z coordinate offset by whatever this
bias is right there.
We're going to transform them both.
And in fact, I can make this clearer by going.
Transform the input vertex, transform the output vertex, right?
I transfer the input for text transform.
The the one with the biased, right?
Then when we want to do our output, the output is just going to be.
And off you go.
So hopefully that's a little clearer now, right?
So we take the inputs, we bias, we created a secondary Point, that's
biased, right?
That's up further, we transform them both.
And then we just use the Z of the transformed one.
So it's as if it had been raised up in terms of its depth values, but
in terms of where it actually shows up on the screen, it uses the same
thing.
Now this may look really inefficient, right?
But actually it's a lot less inefficient than you might think.
The way that these Shader compilers work is they basically do, you
know, single static assignment kind of style form, where they
basically take a look at the thread that produces an output.
So it knows that the only thing it needs is GL position so it knows
that the only values it needs are these for so it
Was that the only thing that's going to use a zMAX transform is this,
so it knows that it doesn't accept to do this entire transform, it can
just do the Z part of the transform and it won't ever bother doing the
rest.
So it does have an Optimizer that is going to do relatively reasonable
stuff.
In terms of only Computing things that needs
That is true now, it's not an amazing Optimizer.
So don't get too excited, but it's definitely going to be able to do
some basic stuff for you.
So, you don't have to worry too much about that kind of code
structure.
It's not going to be literally executing the stuff that you wrote In.
All right, so in order to get ourselves back up to actually working,
here we need to put our textures back in because right now we don't
have any way of sampling from textures and we need to sample from
textures.
So inside our fragment code here we need to be able to get a texture
coordinate and so this is where we need to start having the idea of
colors and textures getting passed through.
So what happens here is we've got remember uniform
Like I said, uniform, is something to get specified once for a whole
batch, and then just gets used.
So it's coming from the C code that distinguishes itself, for sewing,
that's per vertex like this GL position output, or this GL vertex
input, which are per vertex in order to get texture coordinates in.
We want another thing that's per vertex.
So what you typically use?
They use the thing called varying, for example, to distinguish it from
uniform.
I don't know what this version of the shaders.
Actually uses.
So let's double check real quick because it changed actually.
Remember it changing
Used to be varying, or used to not be varying in, then it was, or I
don't even remember it was all big fun stuff.
Anyway, you can see here, we got qualifiers storage cars in centroid
in out uniform.
So it looks like there's no need to specify varying, so if we simply
don't say, uniform, it is assumed to be per vertex, is how this
version of the shariat straighter goes as far as I can tell.
So let's go ahead and make that happen.
So, we know we have
In in very value here, we know it's going to be a vector to, it's
going to be the UV coordinates, right?
And we'll call this input u v and then we also know that we want a
veck for for color.
maybe I won't type input, I'll just type in
Right.
So now if you look at that, you're like, well, okay, I've specified
things that come in, they must come from somewhere, I don't know where
they come from and it's like, okay, we don't really know where those
come from.
But then in terms of output, we have to do the same thing.
Because remember the place we actually want this, eventually is in the
fragment code.
So in here, we want the same thing.
It will call this frag UV and fried color, right?
Or maybe.
UV invert color.
I don't know what you want to call this interpolated color.
We this is basically, when we get down to the fragment Shader, you
know, each vertex had a UV coordinate in a in a color and we're
interpolating that along the, the line inside the triangle
barycentric.
Lie.
I don't know what we want to call this, but this is, this is, you
know, the I mean, I guess frag is probably this thing for now.
So here, we're going to need this and this, and we need to declare
these in the fragment Shader.
In addition, we need one more piece of information, usually.
And you can see it here which is smooth flat or non perspective.
Now, what's interesting about this is this is something that you can't
really appreciate and handmade hero because it doesn't really come up
super much in what we were doing.
But it's important to understand.
So I'll kind of go over it just really briefly here.
Was it no perspective.
All right, so three choices for variables that are in the fragment
Shader.
And why do we need these?
Well, okay, inside a Vertex Shader, remember, we've just got vertices
right x.
Y z w.
These are basically coming directly from the app.
So I'm specifying these in C, and the vertex Shader is just munching
on them and outputting stuff for the rasterizer, right?
So it's outputting these xy's and depth values right for the
rasterizer.
At no time, there wasn't anything here, that needed to interpolate any
values that it got.
But once these come to the rasterizer, right?
It's going to line up these as a triangle.
It's going to go like, oh, here's this guy, here's this guy.
And here's this guy, right?
Here's my Triangle.
Well I now need to shade some stuff that's in here.
How do I know what to pass for these values?
If all of a sudden I start augmenting this with like u and v, right?
How do I know what the UV is in here?
Because I know what the UV is out here.
I don't know what it is in here.
And the answer is, it has to do a very eccentric interpolation.
Just like we did a member go back to the software rasterizer.
If you aren't comfortable these things because we did them all, we
need to figure out what the UV is.
Using in some kind of a very eccentric interpolation between these
three points.
But there's multiple ways you could do it.
One way, is called Flat in opengl.
That's if it's always just stays the same, right?
So, that would mean, that, whatever like the first vertex is ones, are
the whole triangle gets it.
So, there's no interpolation at all.
It just doesn't interpolate
Next kind is called No perspective.
That's what we did in the software rasterizer that just says, I don't
need to do anything fancy.
Just go ahead and use whatever the barycentric interpolation would
give you at this point in screens face smooth.
On the other hand is for normal 3D games, which we are not really, but
if we were, and this will actually just would actually be the case
with our cubes when we use, when we do our cubes because they do have
things that slice downward and Z.
What that says is hey, let's say we
We're looking at something head-on like the wall of a dungeon or
something, right?
This doesn't interpolate evenly across its surface because it's going
backwards and Z.
So things that are close together.
Back here are actually much further apart than things that are close
together up here, right?
Just just perspective, things are closer together get bigger.
So when we interpolate the texture coordinates, we want to interpolate
them with respect to perspective.
So emotion up here should be moved.
This should move
UV coordinates more than motion back here.
Should write.
If that makes sense.
That's the bad way to say it.
But point being what we're trying to do is simulate the fact that we
actually did a perspective transform on the texture rather than just
warped it right.
And this is like if you remember looking at the PS1 Graphics, I think
we mentioned this before like PlayStation 1 was all kind of War P.
That is exactly what happens when you don't do perspective.
Correct or Ultima underworlds walls right that sort of stuff.
So smooth is what you would pretty much always do by default unless
you really wanted something specific because that's the one that does.
Correct.
3D interpolation, you only would specify the other ones if you had
some special thing reason that you wanted them.
So you'll know you'd know if you wanted them if you don't really
aren't thinking about it.
You want smooth pretty much.
So, let's suppose we get these in here, right?
It's not supposed to be back for
Right.
So let's suppose we get these in here.
Then we will do some things like say if we want to do modulation,
right?
There's a module 8.
We can just multiply now they don't use hadamard product in their
stuff, they just do.
Multiplication is is a hadamard.
So X is the hadamard product.
Then they use Dot and cross the words Dot and cross to specify dot
product and cross product.
So those are the four, the three Vector multiplications, they support.
So we can do modulation by the fragment color.
Just like we do in the software rasterizer.
Or just like opengl was doing before and then we can also do this
fragmovie.
We can we can look up a texture, right?
So instead of this red, right?
Like, here's our Vector for
I've read.
So instead of doing the texture sample, as just pretending, we have
pure red as a texture.
We can go in here and say, okay, let's take this UV and let's get a
texture sample.
So how do we get texture sample?
Well, like I said, there's a whole bunch of things built in for doing
that.
Where are you?
There you go.
Texture grad offset.
Here we go texture look up.
So here's texture.
You can see that there's all these different things.
Sampler 12 to the array by blah blah.
What we want is just the basic.
These are for things like cubemap sampling or Texture or a sampling
whatever.
What we want is we want something that's a g of x 4 that's going to
give us back a full sample.
We want a 2d sampler.
Right.
So we probably want something looks like this where we pass in a UV
here and the sampler that were sampling from and it gives us back the
color.
So that's the one that we want.
So we want texture.
We need to text your sampler.
And then we need just that that UV which is right there.
Okay.
So the only other thing we need now is a way to get this texture.
Sampler.
And again this is like a thing that is much like this Matt 4x4 up
here.
This is something that's uniform.
It's set one time right by the batch.
And this is the texture that we're going to use, and it's got to be
set from the C code.
So it's something that we have to tell the GPU to communicate down to
us, right?
Same exact thing as the transform was up here.
So we need
Say that we wipe have a sampler, too.
Because it's a 2d texture, right?
And that's all we need to say that.
It's a floating Point, Texas, a uniform, sampler to texture sampler.
Then it will go ahead and say, all right, assuming that someone bound
something to this at some point and we'll have to get to that later,
then we can, you know, make that happen.
All right, so what should happen now and let's just go ahead and I'll
show you the error first and then we'll show you show you the solution
to it as we should get compiler.
We do and the compiler errors should be that we don't actually have
the inputs that we wanted.
Right?
Oh well actually I've got a different one to hear.
Internal are unexpected qualifier texture.
Sampler parse error.
Did I specify something wrong?
Oh,
That's a it's not ass a to it's a 2d, right?
Yeah.
There we go.
Whoops.
Well, that wasn't what I was expecting to have happen.
So I was expecting it, an error there and I'll tell you, whether there
was I was expecting but I guess it's not an error for whatever reason.
So you notice, we've got these inputs here and these inputs, I guess
it just defaults them to 0.
These inputs aren't specified.
Right?
Was the point that I was trying to get to
And so, what we need is a way for our vertex code to Output, what
these values should be per vertex so that they can get interpolated by
the rasterizer.
So what we need to do here is we just need to specify these as as
output variables.
That line up with what we expect to come in.
So, our output names here, just have to line up with our input names
here.
And then when these two programs are linked together, they will line
them.
They will, the Shader compiler will understand that.
It's supposed to Output stuff from, you know, stuff that gets written
to here, gets red for in in here, right?
That it just needs to be able to make that sort of that binding,
right?
So what we want to do is we just
Want to pass through.
We want to Output a frag UV.
That's whatever the UV that was inputted.
And we want to Output a frog color.
That's whatever was inputted.
So basically, we're assuming these come from the vertex dream somehow
here and we'll talk about how to get that in a second and then we're
out putting them like this.
Now, I think, again, fixed function pipeline wise, we may be able to
cheat here and not quite start doing the array specification stuff
that we would need to do to find our own vertex dreams yet because I
believe, yeah,
We've got GL multitec, scored and GL color, so we can actually just
for go these for the moment and actually just say GL multitec scored 0
+ GL color, those are the fixed function versions.
And so in theory, those can get bound and output to the fragment
Shader, right?
Oops.
I need a jail mate.
Texas Court.
Did I
Did I spell that wrong or is that not supported in this version
multitec scored zero?
Because that is the value.
Is it not?
Geo multi Tax Court.
Vertex Shader was fine.
Fragment Shader was fine.
Frog, color interpolate modes.
Do not match in two stages.
Ah yes sorry.
The smooth.
Needs to be replicated in both places.
I don't know why.
But it does.
all right, so
we need some way of getting the texture sampler and the texture
coordinates set up here.
I don't know why I can't access multitec scored.
It may be because that isn't actually in this version of the Shader
language.
Let me take a quick look to see what the deal is with that again, I'm
trying to do something here that just as the transition that we really
are on kind of off the beat, we're off the beaten path, which is using
the fixed function Pipeline with shaders.
Normally, you just use one of the other
You don't mix and match like I am some pushing it a little bit here
but we got this far.
I might as well do it because like I said, it's been nice being able
to show you the individual steps not having to do the whole thing in
one big kerplunk.
So yeah, so let's take a look and see what the deal is.
Is there Shader wise?
Let's see.
Jill multitec scored just want to know what the Shader version is for
that.
Is there a maybe in this Shader version?
There was just a GL Tech.
Scored?
Was that a thing?
So maybe this just isn't allowed anymore, I don't know.
I'm confused as to why I'm not.
Also just try this because I'm just curious.
okay, so that
That looks like that was correct.
So so it looks like it's just a version mismatch.
So GL Tax Court is the thing, and so we only want the first two values
of it because we're only outputting to were not end texture,
coordinates are actually defined as full four dimensional coordinates
on input.
So we can just use just the U and the V part which is all we wanted
and then we should be good to go potentially I guess.
Can I apply dot operator to an array?
Oh, so it was actually just named differently, but it is still GL Tech
scored.
It is still a multi-textured array, I guess.
All right.
Fair enough.
So I believe we are now passing down everything that we need to pass
down.
The only problem is we are not actually, we don't actually have a
Sampler set up.
So we don't actually have a way of accessing the texture, right?
We are the we just name this Phantom texture sample and we're like,
hey, there should be technically.
I don't know if we can access the fixed function pipeline there, but I
guess I'll try again.
Just to continue with just doing it one step at a time there.
Let me take a look at the quick reference guide and see if that is
actually true fragment language.
It doesn't look like it.
Right?
So it doesn't look like those are defaulted to the Samplers are
defaulted in any way.
It looks like you have to specify a texture.
Sampler.
unless I'm very much mistaken and about that about that, that
Yeah, it looks like it.
All right, so the last thing we have to do then is just to get this
texture, sampler bound as well, right?
So again, this is exactly analogous to the transform thing.
This is something that per batch we want to set a texture sample.
So, we wanted to set a texture for the sampler just like we set a
transform for the vertex Shader.
So what we need to do in our opengl call calls, are we have to
actually have a thing here, which is the texture sampler ID and that's
going to get out of that program.
Extra sampler right now that'll work just fine.
The only problem is we don't do anything with it, so we're going to
have to have lips.
So, we're going to have to actually do something with it at some
point.
So what we need is you know, when we're doing our GL uniform Matrix up
here, we bind it.
We kind of need another deal uniform here which is going to specify
that we want our texture, sampler to line up with some kind of a
texture that we have bound to something, right?
So we essentially need to do a GL uniform, and in this case, I think I
misspoke before actually.
Now I think about it, I guess we do need a GL uniform.
I, in this case
Because we need to set the texture sampler up and we're going to have
to specify an integer, right?
So basically what we're going to do is we're going to set the uniform.
We're going to set it to be which texture slot.
It's in.
Oops, sorry.
Open Jill.
Yeah, and it also occurs to me that this should probably have this
going on here, right?
I'm pretty sure you have to bind the program to set these uniforms.
I don't know why that worked before, but I guess it did.
Anyway, we're going to have to specify a uniform here and the uniform
is going.
To bind the sampler ID to something right now this Parts a little
confusing.
Again, all of this binding stuff is really, it's a really messy part
of the API.
It's not done particularly well, it never really gets done,
particularly well, unless you scale all the way up to nvidia's by
endless.
Extensions are the only time that I've ever seen any done properly and
any API really for this sort of stuff.
So there's that.
But what we need to do here is we need to basically say,
For this uniform location.
We need to sort of correspond it to something texture related in
opengl.
And the way they chose to do that was basically with the concept sort
of texture units in the sense that like okay we're going to treat the
texture.
Sampler as if it's basically just an index.
So we're going to specify what index of the texture unit.
We're going to which texture unit index.
We want it to use.
So we'll say.
OK, bind to texture sampler, Z bind, the text.
Sampler for this ID, bind it to unit 0, or bind it to unit, one or
bias unit 2 and then we still text talk to it.
Exactly the way we talk to this stuff, right?
That's how this actually works.
So yeah, we don't have time to probably get this working, but let me
just go ahead and grab that function.
I can at least do that much.
But I thought, yeah, I thought that buying program was necessary to
use those uniforms, but we didn't do that.
I don't know why we didn't do that.
Hold on a second.
Let me just take a look.
What is the value?
Beautiful, very jewelry friendly.
Bubba, blah, blah, blah, blah, blah, blah.
None of this is what I want the commands by assuming uniform vote, a
blah blah.
Yes.
It's real uniform.
I and Jillian for IV of the only 200 meters is uniform.
Fails to find a sampler types.
Long-established function right.
But I don't know where it says.
The program has to be bound.
Well, doesn't matter.
Anyway, point being, let's move finish up what we're doing.
We can take a look at that again.
So let's go ahead and do Jill uniform.
Ivy.
Should be here somewhere.
No.
There it is.
so in this case, we just want Jill uniform, one eye
And same thing here.
So buying program, let's see here.
Texture texture or like that.
So buying program I guess we should also grab because I'm pretty sure
you needed.
I guess.
I just couldn't find any positive confirmation that we actually did,
but I felt like that should probably be there.
Is it just is just use program.
So is it just the use program is sets it in and of itself?
I don't have to bind it I guess not.
No, I guess not.
All right.
Okay, cool.
So I don't need that good.
Okay, so I think that's about it for this week.
We'll have to wait to do the rest of the texture stuff until next
week, but we're almost there.
So we're close close.
But no cigar
We will have to, like I said, play around with this a little bit more.
I'll leave this in the opengl code.
I'll leave the texture.
Sampler, so we can see things.
I'll I'll leave the alpha value at one just for fun.
So that we can actually see where things are.
But other than that, we'll go ahead and go to the Q&A, and we'll do
the texturing next week when we can both do the texturing and make
sure that we're handling Alpha correctly and stuff like that in there
because we will want to put in an alpha discard and stuff like this.
So we have a couple more things that we're going to want to do but
we're pretty close.
How is?
Wait seriously.
How is that possible?
Because I don't have any hotkeys set.
None controlled W.
Are you nuts?
How did that get set?
That has never been set before.
That must have got set for some other reason.
Well, that's terrible.
Yeah, I guess I don't hit control very often.
It's probably why we never noticed it before.
That must have gotten set during some stream.
We did for some other reason, I'm glad we now know what that is
because that would have plagued us for a while.
All right, let's verify that.
That won't happen again.
Well w.
That do anything.
No good.
That's still doing it.
I have cleared the hotkey, but it's still doing it.
How do I make it stop?
OBS seems to really want that hockey.
So those hot keys are still there, even though I've cleared them out,
I'm not sure how to make it not do that.
Hmm.
Well.
I can try like restarting obs.
Check your global settings.
Please.
I don't think there are any
Well yeah that's that's really problematic.
I mean I'm definitely gonna have that accidentally happen again if I
can't get rid of that because that's real bad.
Thank you OBS, for that wonderful feature.
well, can I set it to something like Ctrl, alt shift, semicolon,
Nope.
Boy, this this hotkey, sure is interesting.
Yeah, that's a good idea.
If I just deleted, these wouldn't be able to switch.
Let's do that.
Remove.
All right.
That's what we want.
Let's just leave it that.
So it's less risky.
Brooke tag now that we've gone up in jail, do you still think the
Raspberry Pi option is still on the list?
Actually, the only way we were ever going to do a Raspberry Pi is if
we did open jail because or some 3D Hardware something, because
unfortunately, the Raspberry Pi is a lot of the power on the Raspberry
Pi is in the graphics GPU.
So if we're ever do a Raspberry Pi version, we're going to have to do
it with the grant with the GPU.
It's not it doesn't have enough CPU performance to run a game.
I don't think software rendered
Would you?
What's the code for what you have done in the last two to four
minutes?
Yes.
Let's, let's go ahead and just go over what I ended up doing.
Just so it's clear.
Let me make sure this open Jill.
I mean, this thing is kind of, okay, so that seems to work.
Okay, all right, so all I did was I said, well, okay.
We're going to need to do the same thing with the texture sampler that
we did with the transform.
So it's a uniform value.
It's going to be this thing called a sampling.
Sure.
And what a Samplers is just a way of getting texture Samplers, right?
Texture samples.
We don't know anything about it, meaning the gravis card doesn't tell
us how it's doing that.
We just know that at some point we can call texture and give it a UV
coordinate and one of these Samplers and it will go get us, the
corresponding sample from the texture, and that sample will do,
whatever the thing is set up to do in the open gel texture unit.
So if it's set up to do bi linear interpolation, it'll do bi linear
interpolation.
It's not set up to do by their traditional won't.
There's also ways of trying to tell it inside the shooter, what you
want to do, whether you want to do by linear whether you want to do
this or that, right?
So it's going to do that, that sample.
It's going to get us back to texture sample.
Then we're going to use the texture sample to do, whatever texturing
we want to do.
That all is just very straightforward.
However, this thing at some point just like the transform has to get
passed down, right?
So we need some way of the C code being able to tell the Shader code,
This is what you're supposed to use for texture.
Sampling, right.
Which texture unit you're supposed to use.
So what we had to do to do that was to add.
Well, first of all, we had to add
Texture sampler ID, which is the same as the transform, just getting
the location out.
So it's basically tell us what uniform location we're supposed to use
right to talk about this value.
So we did that.
And then the other thing that we have to do is when we actually go to
call that we have to wear as it where we do use program.
Here you go, where we do use program.
We then have to say okay?
Just like we set up the Matrix we have to tell you what texture
sampler where you
At the moment, we haven't done anything to get that working.
So like I said, that's not really going to do anything.
I just am sending it to zero at the moment so you can see that it's
just this nothing particularly, it's not actually working yet, but
that's that's all I did.
That, was it?
It was just just to get away of now specifying.
Some piece of information that goes with that texture, sampler.
Oh, okay.
So
we got a little help here from wgg 25 on the Geotech score thing
because this was the part that I wasn't sure about before.
Like I said, I'm not sure where that's coming from.
He was saying that it's actually specified like that and the GL text
word one is an output 1 for fixed function pipeline.
So if that's the case, then that would be nice because I was just
trying to figure out how to get the fixed function input which again
like I said, normally you don't do
But let's see if that works.
Okay, there we go.
So that was, the only problem was that we weren't getting the right
fixed function, input there.
Thank you very much.
In this case, I can remove the, the setting it to 1.0 there.
There we go.
So now we're getting what we expect to get.
Pretty much in all cases, actually.
Now, we've were basically restored to what we want.
You can see, this is what we're actually outputting these sort of
flattened Sprites, right?
But it looks correct.
Now, when we look at them, right?
You can see the trees look like what they should look like and
everything.
But we still do have one problem.
One that we probably can't fix on this particular card.
As far as I know,
Because we don't have.
Well, I mean we could fix it I guess by trying to work around it in
the Shader but we don't actually do.
We don't actually have the GL srgb flag set still and if you remember
but when we create our multi, sample buffers here, for whatever
reason, even though it's supposed to, this card is not allowing us to
set the internal texture format to srgb, which is very bizarre, right?
So I'm not sure yeah we don't have a lot, we can do to work around
that although we could do it directly in the shaders ourselves which
but seems like a bad idea because we want to use the hardware for it
directly.
Yeah.
Midler.
I don't generally, I have to say, I have to go to both q&a's and type
in pound Q&A, so it doesn't automatically replicate anymore.
I think the handmade bought used to do it but it doesn't or in.
So about you said, do it, but doesn't anymore.
Sometimes I forget to put it in both.
Tag, you mentioned the new assets will not be rectangular like the
current assets.
Do we need to update the asset pipeline know the new assets are
rectangular
Every sure are we completely dropping support for the sufferer?
Now, no, we will definitely make the software renderer work as well.
I don't know when we'll do that.
You know, we might choose to do that much later on because we don't
need it for anything, but I would like to have them both running
eventually.
Ty says, I mean the hero head versus body versus
Cape are all the same shape.
Oh, yeah.
Yes, the we will have to do some changes to the code when we update
the artwork.
Certainly, but that'll be true in a lot of ways.
Can you explain what a little?
More detail.
How the Z bias thing works?
I'm not sure I understand it.
Yes, I can.
so, our situation as we had, it was
That we've got the camera looking down at a very steep angle, right?
And so we've got the right cards that are necessarily parallel to it
so that they can appear, you know, like Sprite cards on the screen.
But of course, if they are laying down that flat, they get intersected
here by other geometry that they really should be in front of.
We want them to look more like they're standing up straight like that.
But that would make them warp with the perspective projection.
So we want to leave them so that their face onto the camera.
So we have two choices here.
One is that we could actually have them stand up straight and then
adjust the, you know, if you took this is looking at it from the side,
if you looked at it, sort of more head on right here is those two
cubes and we've got the Sprite card that looks like this.
Flat one is to say well, okay.
We're gonna go ahead and widen or Shrink part of this.
So, we'll go ahead and, you know, move this up to here, but will
shrink it like that.
So, that the perspective that, you know, projection that fans, it out
will make it still appear to be a rectangle, right?
Because as it gets closer as it gets closer to the camera, it's going
to get you know bigger.
So if we don't have it in exactly.
And one,
Should I should back up and say anything in an XY plane relative to
the camera where the Z values don't change.
That's going to be a perfect rectangle on the screen with all four
corners.
Right?
Angled.
Right.
But anytime we make it come out of that plane, it's going to change
the apparent size of the top or the bottom right.
It's going to shrink or expand and you're going to end up with
something that on the screen looks like that or like this.
Right?
So what do we do?
It is to just
Just a pre is to make the opposite parallelogram in 3D that will undo
that projection so it's still projects to a rectangle even though it's
not the other way to do it is to leave it in the plane and in because
the only thing remember that makes the determines who shows up is the
Z.
Buffer is to just pass the Z buffer values from this but past the
actual coordinates from this, right?
And so, that's all we're doing.
What I do is I say okay, every
Text now has an x y z z bias, right?
So the W coordinate is actually Z bias in the Shader.
I
First that value to one point zero, so that the transform still
happens as if it's x y z 1, right?
So that just works, but then what I do is I take what this value was
and I transform a second Point that's x y z plus Z bias, right?
That gives me what the Z coordinate would be at this point.
And then I just say that that is the new point x.
Y.
And what if, what if that transform ends up being?
Being right.
So, you can see that happening in the code here.
The input vertex comes in.
I take just the XYZ and I slam this W 12:45.
So then I, I know that I'm going to transform it just like it normally
would be if we didn't have the Z bias at, all right?
Then, that transform happens, right here, right?
Zoom in transform is transferred in vertex.
I use that for the X Y and W values.
So the only thing I want to do now is change the Z values.
Member the Z value is only going to get used for z-buffering.
Write the W values.
What?
We'll do the divide and we're
The W value from the original vertex so it's unchanged so project to
the right place in screen space but to compute the Z coordinate.
What I do instead is I say all right let's make a new vertex that's
the same as the input vertex but now takes that Z bias and apply it to
move it in.
Z, do that transform and it will pass.
That is the Z.
So, effectively transforming two points, one, that's the original
point.
And one does the Original Point with a z offset and then we're using
the Z buffer value from that one, that allows us to pass the Z bias.
Skin per vertex, so that the two base vertices which are, you know,
the bottom of the Sprite will get nosy biasing and the two top ones
will get whatever we want.
Does that make more sense?
All right, think that's basically it.
Are we going to implement some for my Z before in Cipher?
Yes, we'll just exactly implement the z-buffer in software.
Yeah.
And so the key part of that, yeah like like Mansfield was saying just
to underscore it.
Is that effectively what we're doing is we're just transforming the
point as it normally would have been if we just specified it normally
without the weird Z bias then we just transform another one and Wii U
with the Z bias in and we use that result as the way that the Z buffer
will be used the W is, what does the does, the divided?
So as long as we use the
From our original default transform with 1.0 going through the
pipeline will get the right screen space physician and this Z will not
affect because this Z is not involved in the Divide at all.
Remember Z we don't divide by Z.
We divided by w.
All right, I'm going to go ahead and close it down.
See here, where are we at?
So, really our main problem at the moment is not being able to use the
srgb because it means all the colors are wrong, right?
Everything is too dark, because we can't specify srgb.
So I think we just need to actually move to a graphic card that isn't
seven years old which I maybe I'll have to try and do at some point
here to make things work a little bit more sanely.
So, yeah.
that's that's what we'll have to do but everything else seems to be
working relatively sanely here
We just need to get those colors fixed so that they're not all messed
up.
All right.
Alrighty.
Thanks everyone for joining me, for this of it, handmade here.
It's been a pleasure cooking with you.
As always, if you would like to follow along the series at home, you
can always pre-order the game on handmade hero dot-org.
It comes with a source code so you can play around with it.
We also have a forum site, you can go to.
If you want to ask questions a patreon page for on Sports video
series, a schedule bot that tweet the schedule at you.
If you would like to know when we're going to be live and an episode
guide for catching up on old episodes, that's about it for this week.
I will be back next week when we will.
Well, I'm not sure what we'll be doing next week actually, because
that's pretty much what we needed to do in terms of Z by saying, I
think we will probably want to maybe just take
And clean up and stop using the fixed function pipeline.
Probably, because we're probably on thin ice there in terms of
compatibility.
We're lucky that that worked.
So just finish transitioning away from that was probably the best
idea.
So we'll probably take a look at that next weekend, and that is about
that.
All right, thanks everyone.
Until next time, have fun programming and I'll see you on the
internet.
Take it easy, everybody.