Hello everybody and welcome to handmade her.
Sure we could complete game live on stream.
I left some windows up from the pre stream.
I don't really know why.
I, don't even know why this was up here, probably just because I was
showing some window stuff and so we need to launch the game.
I want to start out but in the pre stream, Kim Jorgensen and I
apologize.
I impress their, I might be jørgensen, I'm always wishing that.
I got a pronunciation guide with everyone's name so I could.
So I could get the
Right?
One of the downsides of the internet, like I feel like Twitter and
twitch and stuff should have a little, a little, what's it called?
Like, a little one of those little speaker icons on there, where you
could just click on it and it would have them pronouncing their name
how they wanted.
It said, so that that would be a nice addition.
But anyway, he's asking for Linux change.
There's a he said there's a small compilation error with clang that
says extra tokens at the
End of the end if in handmade import dot CPP.
This is probably something that, that windows that we compiled with
Microsoft compiler normally, on handmade hero, because we started with
that, clang, couldn't really compile stuff for Windows when we started
it, can now.
So we actually could use clang, we maybe should add a clang.
Step two, just compiled to make sure it compiles properly.
But point being, it probably is something that the Microsoft compiler
should also be complaining about
Doesn't because it's a little bit more permissive.
It's probably not supposed to be there.
So I'm just going to go down and get rid of that for people who are
compiling it.
Oh yeah, you can see, oh wait, no I can't see.
Oh, there it is.
Yeah.
So I don't know what that's doing there.
I'm going to get rid of that and then I think we're good to go.
I suspect that was the one.
I hope that's what.
Is that the right one can just give it to me, thumbs up or thumbs
down.
Was that the only one we needed to remove for the for the?
Yes?
Okay.
So I just want to get rid of that at the at the outset of today's
stream just so I try to keep it, the codebase Fairly clean so that
people who are trying to compile on Linux or
Her other platforms don't have too much trouble.
Since we don't do those on stream.
If someone wants to follow along on those, it helps to just clean up
whatever we're working on to make sure that it behaves properly.
And under the circumstances,
all right, so at the end of the the previous stream, I wanted to start
working on some entity storage stuff that would try to be a larger
study, larger set of information for entities that were sort of in the
important set that would then go away afterward but that still
persisted frame to frame and so I want to do that but while I was
doing it I was like I'd really like to show
The memory usage here so that we can be cognizant of it and also just
so I can point out why there's some reasons why we want to consider
doing this or why it's important for us to do this.
And so just looking at how we had our stuff set up, there was really
no way to track memory allocations because we didn't really.
Yeah, we really just didn't have a way of saying hey, cures the stuff
that's currently allocated.
And so, if you take a look at our memory system here, I upgraded it.
So that now every time you call Push size, which is are pretty much,
our only thing that allocates memory in our system.
There are a couple of the things in the platform layer that will
occasionally, do it.
But in terms of the actual running game, more or less everything we do
goes through, this push size, call,
so every memory allocation we care about looking at
it goes through that and inside the push sighs, call, where you've
got, internal memory per am here.
What we're doing is we're saying when we compile and handmade internal
mode, what we're going to do is pass a file name in line number 2, the
push sighs call.
So we know on whose behalf the size was requested that amount of
memory.
Now the question is so at this point thanks to yesterday's stream.
We have it so that that is happening right now.
We're getting all of that information, but once we get into the push
size, we don't do anything with it, right?
So we don't actually have any way of using the information that were
actually getting and that creates a problem for us because now when we
want to go print it out we you know, putting it out at the time we do
the allocation doesn't really help us.
We want to be able to print it out at a specific time when we go to
say draw
The information about what's in this Arena and so there's a couple
different ways that we could really do this but what I'm assuming the
most efficient way for us to do it would be is to just sort of have
this information gets stacked up inside the debug system somehow and
so I'm going to just make a system for doing that explicitly and then
we'll kind of figure out how we want to massage that later.
Now we have one issue which is that our memory Arenas themselves
probably when you actually create one of these Arenas?
So, you know, you can see in here where we actually do a like, all
right, if there's a current block or not, current block, these sorts
of things.
When we actually go through and use these Arenas, I don't think you
actually have to do anything to make them actually work, right?
So if you just have an arena, that's just got nothing in it.
just zeros then what will happen is when you first go to use it, it'll
just start allocating some memory for you right there, because here's
the call, for example, that allocates a block for the
You need to start using.
If you just pass an arena that's just garbage like zero.
It's completely zero doubt, it just starts working.
So that's it's one of those zero is initialization patterns that I
like and so we want to preserve that what that means is that when we
actually record these allocations, we do sort of have an issue, which
is we don't necessarily know how to talk about what the arena is.
We can use the pointer so we can
Say that like this Arena pointer?
Is the thing that we are associating these with.
And I think unless I'm mistaken, that's probably the best call.
Because if we don't do that I'm not sure how else we would really
identify them.
We don't ever have a place where we specifically named Arenas and I
don't really know that we necessarily want to either, right.
I think what we want to do is just say look this is the pointer to the
arena.
And here's all the allocations that it had.
Now, one of the problems that we're definitely going to run into is
that those pointers as memory to pointers may not be stable, right?
And what I mean by that is that obviously Arenas come and go so we
can't really count on that Arena pointer pointing to anything
specific.
I think that's probably okay, as long as we track arenas by pointer,
we should still be able to record what happened to them and show it
later just by association.
As if the pointer was a name and since Arenas have to be properly, 32
otherwise it's leaking memory anyway, which is something we would want
to see.
We shouldn't really have to care about whether that Arena pointer is a
still valid or be getting reused, right?
Because you should have had to have called things, like, free all
memory or whatever, right?
Clear, right.
We should have had to call things.
Like clear to get rid of the memory before we reuse the thing.
Anyway.
A or before we get rid of it.
And so, you know, we don't really have to worry about use after free
of the pointer.
I'm sorry reuse of the same memory location but for a different Arena
because we can actually just think of that as the same Arena that just
got cleared.
So there's no real downside to using the pointer out thing.
So mostly what I would like to do here, is just say, okay let's just
say that what we're going to do is create this allocation here.
And what we're going to do is we're going to say that when we get to
the end of it, we're going to say like debug record allocation or
something like that, right?
We're going to have some call that we make.
And that's what we're going to pass.
We've got that file name and line number that again are coming in
here.
and we need to give it some
About what actually happened.
So you can see here, that these are probably the two things we need.
This is the amount of size we allocated, and this is where we
allocated it.
But the other thing that we probably want to do is we may want to
record how much size was actually used because again because of
alignments we may be allocating from the arena more memory than we
actually needed and that may be something that we want to.
Do as well.
So an allocated size.
And then the amount that we used those, two things are probably
important as well, just to make sure that we can see that waste that
is essentially waste.
And so it's nice to have that in any given block.
You know, how many bytes did we waste?
It won't matter for a large blocks.
Those who cares?
If he waits a few bites but for small blocks, it could matter if we're
looking and we're seeing in and thing.
That's like, wow, there's a lot of like wasted space there.
Maybe that's important, I don't know.
So if we then look at how this thing would work we'd say, alright, we
got the file name, we got the line number, we've got the allocations
how much they were, how much we used.
And so what we want to do is we probably want to give it the necessary
information to do a good job tracking.
This, the arena pointer, like I said, I think would be good, but the
other thing that might also be good it, since we know that we're
allocating out of the thing called the current block, and that current
block has a base pointer, what
Might want to do is say also in addition, here is the base pointer,
right?
So we're basically saying, look, here's the pointer.
If in case you want to associate things together as parts of
individual chunks, we could say here is the the base pointer.
In fact, we could even give it the whole block structure if we go.
Oops.
If we go and look at the memory Arena here, you can see that this this
platform memory block is going to give a lot of that information will
be could say is like, look, maybe we give it the entire thing so that
the debug system can look at that that block and know all of the stuff
that's that's involved in it, right?
So, if we recorded all of these information, all of this information,
we'd be in pretty good shape, but we also need one more piece of
information which is that that will only tell us when things are
allocated.
It will not tell us when things are D allocated.
And I think what's important to realize is that we can do a good job
of tracking this through the debug system by recognizing anytime we
free things in an arena we are freeing.
In one of two ways either we are rewinding a blocks used pointer or we
are getting rid of the block entirely.
And so if we take a look here we could do
This.
That tells us that this entire block got removed and similarly, in
anywhere we rewind, which I'm pretty sure there's only one place we
wind which is in and temporary memory.
Any place where we rewind.
It's literally just a question of backing up the pointer.
And so, in that case, we could say, debug record block, I guess,
rewind
Or truncate.
And again no real need to do anything fancy here.
If we just pass that block,
we should be good to go.
So yeah, I think that's all.
We really need with those three functions.
We have told the debug system everything about what's happening inside
of these memory Arenas so that it can keep its own lists and it keep
its own track of what it may need to draw or record as far as Arenas
are concerned.
And so the only other thing I think we really need is
To go look at the arena part of things and I think what was that
called?
Like debug no.
Okay.
It's in here somewhere.
Actually.
I'll just go to the code because I don't really remember what it's
called.
Yeah, I just have no idea what it's called.
Casey doesn't remember what it's called.
Oh, is that it right there?
Yeah.
So you can see here, we've got this debug value and you pass these
Arenas and I thinking that I don't really necessarily know that I want
to do it that way.
What you can see here is we've got this debug data block memory in the
old days.
I think we kind of needed this because we were placing these like,
Arenas in there as something we wanted to view.
I think we just want to show all arenas that have been tracked in kind
of like a scrolling list and and do that, which we can do.
And so what I think we want to do here more is just associate names
with Arenas.
So in other words, what I would like to do is something like this.
Where we say, look, you're going to hear about a bunch of these
Arenas.
I'm going to tell you how to display them in like, a human friendly
way, right?
Because it's just going to get these pointers and it doesn't know
like, it doesn't know what those Arenas would be called to a human.
It just knows that there.
You know, something that's out getting memory and in those whose
allocating the memory but it doesn't know anything else, right?
So I think what I'd like to do is something along these lines.
We pass these pointers down, right?
Like so and we just say, look I'm going to tell you what the names of
these are.
There's a game mode memory, there's an audio memory or audio playback,
right?
There's a frame.
Temporary.
Okay.
There's a little bit stalling for you and then there's like an asset
store.
And so I think like, you know, this this is probably the best way to
do this.
Anytime soon as allocated or freed, we just pass a pointer and say,
Here's the arena that was associated with.
I don't know anything other than that, just deal with it.
And then later we can announce in a central place.
Anytime there's a particular Arena pointer.
We want to attach a name to that pointer.
We just can, and it will basically use that as like, sort of a hash
where it just says, look, I'm going to look up what the name of this
pointer is.
And display it.
If I've got one if I don't, I'm just going to say unnamed Arena and
let you figure it out by who's allocating it, right?
Who's allocating in it you know I'm saying.
So I think that's what we want and I think that would make it a little
bit nicer just so we can understand what we're looking at in there.
So if we look at the debug system I don't think this is actually that
hard to implement.
It's just a bit of typing I think the debugger Rena is therefore our
ability to sit to
Or permanent things.
And so really all I need to do is develop a little storage for the
things.
I just said, so we can eat here.
Say, look, there's a debug Arena
And or debug memory.
I don't know how we wanted.
I don't know what I want to call this one, the call T bug arena for
now.
Inside the debugger Weena, I know that I want a name for this thing,
right?
And that's if I associate it like this.
So I want to definitely have a name for the thing in the debug Arena,
and that's going to allow me to associate the pointer with it.
I also need the like Arena pointer because I want to store when I do.
Like
Cash comparisons or something.
I want to be able to kind of store that information.
For matching.
And so if I've got the debugger Arena and I've got these things, I'm
just going to create what amounts to a for lack of a better term, a
mirror of what I'm being told by the arena system.
On the debug side.
And so in here I've got like the file name and the line number that
I'm actually, you know, working with in terms of the each allocation,
I know that I want the size allocated and the size used so that we
have those two pieces of information that we can print out.
So we know like who allocated it, where how much they asked for and
how much was used and then each of those can just be chained
Right?
And oh, and sorry.
Maybe the offset from the block.
Right.
And so in each allocation, we sort of have this information and then
what we want to do is inside the arena block, we just want to say you
know first allocation and here we want to know.
Okay.
What's the like memory address?
Right?
Like where was this thing?
And similarly I want to be able to say what the next block was.
So that allows me to basically store all my applications in in the
block to which they, you know, were associated.
There is no real need to name blocks for a particular reason.
So I think it just looks like this.
Right?
And this just lets us create a mirrored structure inside the debug
system.
So it's not ruining the run time of our game and we can compile it out
trivially and it's you know you might ask and it's a toy legitimate
question, why not just make the arena store these things right with
the memory and the reason for that is we want to be able to compile it
out because it's unnecessary for runtime.
So I wanna be able to compile it out and I don't want it to affect how
the actual
The is being laid out because I want to see how that memory is
actually going to be laid out when we actually run the game with a
compiled out, right?
So that's why this stuff is going to be a mirror rather than just
placed in line, which would be easier, right?
Or or injected in, right?
And so anyway, when we've got this, we've got this backing structure
that will allow me to display it and update it as a story, as we get
information from the running game in, through the debug system.
I think this is mostly all we would need
I don't really think we need anything else, do we
I mean, I think that's everything.
Yeah.
And again I want to see like yeah I wasn't really that pleased with
how the debug system and
Up working, I think, someday, I'd like to go back and clean it up.
This is more how it should look.
We should have just built purpose-built things for what we wanted,
rather than trying to make everything be, you know.
Rather than trying to make everything go through something generic
that was just dumb.
But, you know, I like every other programmer make plenty of mistakes
and that's merely one of them.
But anyway, this way, we can just record the stuff directly, and off
we go.
Now, we do have an issue, which is to say that when we do this stuff,
we may want to be handling multiple.
So this memory could be coming from lots of different places and
different threads we have to
Red aware because we use threads in handmade hero but also because in,
you know, computers really, don't get that much faster these days
single-threaded they tend to get faster by being parallelized out to
multiple threads.
And so we really don't want to create systems that will prevent us
from using threading or that fall apart the instant we need to analyze
something that's threaded.
That's especially true, debug systems.
And the reason for that is because debug systems are
often times most needed with multi-threaded code because
multi-threaded code is the hardest kind of code.
There's way more happening once in way more possible errors than
single threaded code.
And so usually, you want to try to avoid scenarios, that would create
difficult code multi-threaded code sections, that then cannot be
analyzed with your debug tools because then you're putting yourself at
like a double disadvantage.
The code is more.
Complicated than the single threaded code.
You were trying to debug and you cannot use your debug tools to
analyze it.
And so you want to try and get as much as you can.
I know it's difficult to make sure that your debug systems handle
multi-threading and don't require like locking and things that would
intrude on the multi-threading and change the behavior of it.
When they attempt to be, you know, do you don't want to Heisenberg it
out in that way?
You want to be as
as transparent as you can be.
In that sense it's never perfect.
Any time you're analyzing something it will change but you want to try
and avoid anything major.
And so, what I want to do here is when we look at these calls that we
have, and we go to the debug interface system, I'm going to add them
in here so we can make them
What I want to be able to do here is say, alright for like these
things, that I said, we were going to start recording.
I want them to go into the debug stream, first right?
This is very important.
I want them to go into the regular debug string, first not directly
into the debug system.
And the reason for that is I don't
Tulloch.
Anything I want them to just go into this, to the stream of events and
then I'll pull them out later from that stream and create stuff from
them that way, because that will allow me to do the allow this to all
run multi-threaded perfectly without having any locking or contention
or anything like that happening.
It's just people dumping into an array while there's still some
potential but it's better, right?
So these are the calls.
We actually need
It's not immediately clear to me, whether this call needs to occur or
not.
One could argue that debug break, debug record block truncate is
sufficient and we should just call it.
Also does anyone know why record block truncate?
We were supposed to, oh, because it's got the used.
Okay, I'm like, why didn't we pass the amount there?
Because we don't need to.
All right, so we've got the block filename line number the size.
So this is the allocated sighs.
This is the used size and this right here is the result.
It's because we want offsets inside the block.
I may make it easier on myself here and just pass that directly.
I don't have.
Auntie You could argue.
It's a little bit better to not do it that way, I don't know, but if
you look here, you can see when we compute.
This result, we're already doing an offset into the block.
So I may just say look we know what that is.
We're all friends here.
I don't trust this system and I'm just going to go ahead and pass that
down.
So that way we don't have to do any point arithmetic there that could
be slightly wrong or something weird happening.
I don't know.
And so we're just going to record what the actual offset and block is
And off we go.
And so, I think that should be mostly all I need at the moment.
I'm relatively happy with that.
So, here's the stuff.
We actually have.
I'm going to go ahead and put those in here as dummies.
That's so that when we compile this out, these calls do nothing.
And again, this is why I wanted to go with a mirroring based system.
Like I said before, both in both cases, I just want to be as
unobtrusive as possible.
So in the case where you compile it out, it's not there at all, it
just completely goes away.
Even the file name and line number information goes away completely
from the whole system.
And I wanted that to be sort of a requirement of the implementation
Okay, so now we've got these things, we need some way of recording
these events.
Thankfully we have a fairly flexible system that allows us to do that.
You can see it here.
This is how we've been doing everything.
We got these record, debug events and so if
I add these in here where I can just say, let's record these events.
Some of them will be pretty easy.
Some of them will be harder what we know is, they'll probably look
like this.
Right.
This is
actually, I don't know why.
It's why is it passing unknown?
And then setting it to set Hood?
Is that, is that some is that because record debug event would
complain if you passed it, something that it didn't understand.
It's been a while since I used this.
Let me just see what's happening there.
So here's record debug event, here's the event type that's getting
passed into their this is it setting the event type here.
I'll be honest I don't see a lot of reason for that.
So I feel like you could just pass that down.
Actually the grit in it, I don't think we want anything, they're
really the name in it.
We could use ourselves probably.
So I think that's all good.
I'm going to go look at that event structure.
And what you can see here is we've got this sort of Union of
information.
Here's a stirring that memory Arena P information there.
These events are already 1V for long.
That's quite large actually.
That's for values.
So we should be able to stick a memory.
A piece of memory information in here that should allow us to do
whatever we need to do.
So given this record debug event call.
I also don't know for the grid stuff.
What are we doing for that?
Just debug name.
For the grid.
So I don't actually know what we would want to do there.
I don't know if we need those squids for anything in particular.
That's a tough one.
You know, just looking at how we're doing that.
You know, you can see here like we've got this sort of a grid, I may
just do that because that seems like the most logical thing to me.
So inside here we do debug arena name.
I may just do something like this, which is just like, you know, set
arena name and I'm going to put this in oops.
Like that.
And so, one of the things with set arena name is, I think it's kind of
doesn't need anything special because the name could just come in as
the name parameter and that's all good.
Once we get two things here like block, free and record allocation,
we're going to need a little bit more.
Nation, probably.
So here we've got, you know,
Arena block free and maybe I'll call this.
Arena set name.
So these all just start with Arena.
The name parameter here again, we don't really have a name for it, so
it's hard to pass anything there.
So we'll just say nothing for.
Now what we need to be able to do here is pass some kind of block
pointer at, right?
And so we know we've got a platform memory block yet.
And I don't know what memory Arena p is there.
Is there a reason we needed that to be specific?
I'm guessing it's because of the way we did the debug HUD thing.
So I'm thinking that maybe that is not super necessary for debug type
memory nappy.
It's probably was just for auto detection.
So I think we could probably do memory Arena
Debug type.
So actually that block needs to things.
So I'm going to actually say maybe we could call this
Maybe we could call this something slightly different.
So maybe we should say here.
All right.
This debug type.
Actually is like memory.
Hop or something and this is just memory up.
Mmmm up and this thing is like, you know, I'm saying to you.
I guess this should just be in keeping with the spirit.
And so, in here, what I want is I want the pointer to the arena that
we're talking about.
I want the platform memory block that we're talking about.
The filename in line number could actually go up into the grid.
That's probably what we should do with that now that I think about it.
So we'll make that work.
There's a little bit of gyrations, we should do for debug record
allocation and we can make that be nice and clean.
So we don't have to we can parse those out after the fact.
So I think all we need here is just the two pieces of actual
allocation information.
So there's allocated size used size and offset.
So we need
Allocated size used size.
And offset in Block.
But what you can see here is this is like gonna blow it out a little
bit, too big.
You look at something like a rectangle, 3, that's 6 parameters.
I don't really want to blow it too much more than that.
So if you look you've got
This will probably the biggest thing in here.
If you look at it like it's bigger than a rectangle 3, right?
And so I kind of feel like these things should probably have been you
know I mean I guess we could compress them though.
We could only output the size.
We actually need.
I don't actually know for doing that at the moment.
Probably not
We take a look.
Yeah, we're not.
We just it's just a giant array of these.
So it's a little bit annoying in that sense, right?
Where we've got the debug memory up coming into the stream here and
we're sort of just it's a little bit too big, right?
And so I feel like this this is just to blow T at that point and I
would like some way of making it less bad.
I would assume that probably the easiest way to do that.
Right?
If these were not, if we just didn't track,
Is that were too large, so we just marked them as such that would keep
this down to a more manageable size, right?
We do something like this.
So this is 1 2 3 4 5 6 7 8.
So that's 8 long looking at something like this.
That's six.
So you know it's still it's still just too big it's just too large
right.
And if you did that, I suppose that would we would do it, right?
But you kind of you're missing the overhang part of this a little bit.
So you don't really know how much you actually used here, which is a
little annoying but hey, we can sort of work with that.
For now, I do think we can solve all this by just having the having
this.
We could look record two events, right?
You could just anytime you need.
You think bigger like we should do that for rectangles as well.
Anytime you need more than one event, just record more than one event,
right?
Just like take forwards.
And just record like a sequence, you know what I mean?
So you could just say, hey every time you see one of these, you need
to see one of these after it, right?
And you just specify the same grid for both of them or something like
this, right?
We could do something like that.
I'm not going to go down that road right now because I just don't want
to deal with that.
Actually, we don't super need it but it's worth noting that like
there's better stuff we probably could do if we put our minds to it
here.
Alright, so looking at this stuff here.
So we've got the arena block and so on, in these debug types, I want
to be able to set.
I want to be able to set the type differently and have it.
You know it probably shouldn't come through here, she'd probably be
something like this, right?
And I don't think I want to make different ones for each of these.
I think they can all be that, right?
So I'm going to call it like, hey,
there's,
Arena set name.
There's Arena block free.
There's
Arena block truncate and there's Arena allocate, right?
Um,
I think that's everything.
And so in here, when we're doing our record debug event and all this
fun stuff, second it's out there.
So in here we want to say Arena block truncate and in here we want to
say Arena block allocate.
Oops, sorry allocated.
And I think because these don't take anything in particular.
I'm just calling them what their event is.
But in this case, I want this place here to take the grid explicitly.
So what I'm going to change is this is actually going to be the grid.
And that's going to get passed through and we'll go from there.
So in these, where we have like allocated size, use size, all set in
Block.
Like I said, that stuff is unfortunately not really that useful to us
at the moment because we can't quite store it exactly that way.
So, what I'm going to do here is, I'm just going to say alright, let's
go ahead and record what we can out of it, and then we'll see if it
ever causes us.
A problem, a little later down the line.
So, if we look down in here,
Here, we've got this, like value Diogo, debug memory up kind of thing.
So in all of these were going to want to set certain parameters of
these, and we have Arena block allocated size of offset and block to
be recorded.
So in here, we want to say, all right, here's the arena.
Here's the block.
Here's the allocated size.
Here's the offset.
Yeah.
And what we're going to do here is just literally do like these
things.
Truncated to you 32s, right?
And we're just going to hope for the best
and then someday we'll maybe try to do better.
All right, so that's hard to read.
Tell you what?
How about that?
All right, so for the other parts of this, we're still going to
basically do the same thing, but we don't have any other information
to record, right?
So we're literally just recording the arena in the block and off, we
go.
In this case.
We don't even have a block, we're just doing the arena, but we still
need to say what the arena pointer was.
Otherwise it would have no idea what it was when it went to actually
set the name which is this, right?
So I think that all would work just fine and yeah.
I think that gives us everything that we needed.
Okay.
So debug record allocation is now wrong.
These are apparently not known, so just get rid of that.
I have no idea what this is.
Oh, that's for event data.
We don't need that.
What are you complaining about?
Trailing return type is not allowed after wait.
What?
um,
I guess, I'm not sure what that is trying to say to me.
Trailing return type is not allowed after I nonfunction declarer.
So, my guess is that, that's just because we haven't adjusted this to
take the grid yet.
We were using it.
Don't quote me on that.
But so if you take a look at how we're using file in line here,
essentially, what I want to say is this probably needs to look more
like this.
Right.
And so what we want to do with the file and line numbers, there is
when we create those we want to create those as grids basically,
right?
And so you where we kind of munge, it Munch all the information
together into one thing and sort of store it away, right?
And so if you look at how we're doing that, like debug name that the
function, for example is probably the easiest way to do it but we
could also have some other name there where we we could put in like
who, which one of these people was was responsible for it or something
like that would be another way that we could have that happen.
So I don't know which one exactly what I do.
But basically just going to do a debug name and so that way it'll
create the grid this way, right?
Where it like builds the name up out of the
Is a piece of information and as far as I know, it looks like to me
the name part is never used anymore.
Anyway, right.
You can see it's just ignored because I think we couldn't figure out
how to correctly, make it.
Well, Don in certain situations, so kind of unfortunate, but that's
just how it works right now.
So what I think I'm going to do is just use this debug name here and
say, all right, everywhere that we were doing a file in line, I'm just
going to do debug name and I'm going to like put the name of the thing
that caused it to happen.
Right.
So like in this case, it's, you know, debug name.
Push array and that won't come through right now.
But if we ever sort of like modified or debug system to work around
that, we got rid of it because of some Linux nonsense, clang was being
stupid and there was really no way to fix it.
So we had to kind of get rid of it.
But that's just you know that's how that goes.
It's not really clanks.
Well, I think with GCC who actually set the precedent of having
certain things not be correctly.
And I, you know, I want to say that even got a adopted by the
standards committee.
You know, in their infinite, decimal wisdom, things not being created
as spring constants.
It's a long story, but you can go back and look at the archives for
why.
We had a Nerf that bit works.
Just fine, on Microsoft's compiler, but it doesn't work correctly.
On sort of the Linux origin compilers.
All right, so once we've got those in there now we should be passing
grids properly.
As soon as I actually changed this.
Okay, so I think that's correct now, unfortunately, that had nothing
to do with the error, but that is something we needed to fix
regardless.
All right, so let's see.
I have no idea what this is complaining about.
Event seems fine.
Is it just the fact that this comment is annoying you?
I doubt it.
So, what did I do wrong there?
Allocated size?
Equals allocated size, which is getting passed in, which should just
be fine, right?
I mean, I don't know why it wouldn't be.
I've since this is a macro, I should technically do this, but it
doesn't matter because it's not being used that way.
Do not like this.
What do you not like that's a very cryptic error message
And it's only on those two.
So, is there some of the thing?
When we're actually calling debug record allocation
We're passing Arena Arena current block.
We're passing the grid.
I should probably could be safe.
Also do this?
Nothing.
You should never be doing anything that would have caused this to be
happening, but just principle of least surprise, for on for the
caller.
I'll just, you know,
These getting past should just work.
I really don't know what that are is about.
And if I could quickly, just double-check that, I'm not insane.
I mean that just looks really straightforward, right?
Except wait.
Why is that working at all?
These should have been dots the entire time.
How did it?
How do you think these were correct?
What's going on here?
Something very strange is happening.
Like, how did it actually allow?
What's oh, there's one space after our that was just a preprocessor
error.
Oh, my god.
There was just a space after that ate the macaroni pasta.
They couldn't have fixed it.
30 years.
They couldn't fix it.
40 years.
These are all supposed to be dots.
Don't ask me why I wrote them as arrows.
It's not a pointer.
So let's see here name is an Undeclared identifier, that's probably
true because I don't remember.
Anything about that.
Yeah, don't ask me what that's doing there.
So I'm not sure what we want to put for the name in this case.
What do people normally do?
It looks like they just put the string of the thing that they were
taking.
In our case I don't know that we really have anything like that.
So I guess I will just say like you know
I could pass the grid twice, I suppose.
Other than that, I'm not sure what to see, what we end up doing with
that and then we'll go from there, I guess.
So, let's see.
Size is not a member.
Oh, right?
This won't work.
so,
Let's just make that work.
That way.
Um and sure.
Free is not a member again with the same problem.
Just name conflicts.
Let's see.
Screw this.
And leave it like that.
Do you put buck truncates?
Who is having a problem?
Run Kate.
and that's just a case of
still passing this down for no reason.
And we've got an unexpected.
Yes, that is true.
This is like I accidentally deleted.
The closing parenthesis.
All right, so just a lot of fussing there.
Unresolved external symbol Global symbol cubics up, so because these
events are getting recorded.
Now, it looks like
Our.
Artest PNG doesn't have any way to record that sort of information.
So I think what we want to do there is just make sure that we turn
this stuff off right for the memory subsystem.
So I would say that's probably just something that when we're doing
tests P&G itself, we probably want to do like that for the test PNG.
Just so that's not actually happening.
Probably do this, actually,
And we should probably do that for yeah, for everybody.
We could add the debug system to them but it's just not worth it,
right?
There's no point in having that
Okay, so looks like this is actually not.
This is itself is a pointer already and I guess that makes sense with
how it's actually being used.
So I guess I'll just go ahead and pass it directly.
Other than that, I think we're good.
Right?
What else we got?
Oh, it's not supposed to be a
Colon.
All right, so I think we're good.
The only thing now is this doesn't want to be done the way it's being
done here at all.
We kind of want now, our own way of displaying these things, and we
probably want to display them, sort of the way that we're displaying
like this other stuff.
For example, the thread interval, glass, graph, top clocks list this
stuff, right?
I think, what we want to do is this stuff should probably be.
What's displayed?
We want the same thing.
So we want to kind of get rid of this since it's never supposed to
happen now and we just want Arena occupancy itself to be the thing
that's there.
This will be Rewritten.
So I think we're fine to just do that.
And then I think we can go from there.
I think that's what we need.
Yeah, so I'm assuming, and I don't know, but I think we've laid the
groundwork.
Now, I'm assuming if we ran it, we should now get an assertion that we
don't handle the debug stream that comes in during collation.
Because now in the code where we are going to process it, we're like
coaling all of our events which we haven't touched in years, right?
But here Co like debug records.
Stuff.
We've got debug pin, lock and block data block clothes blocks that
HUD, blah, blah, blah, right in here.
I guess we maybe, I guess we wouldn't actually have.
It would just flow through here and not do what we want, which is
recorded as specific memory events.
So what I want to do now is I want to take those memory events and
make sure they get handled by specific code, designed to do the right
thing to record what's happening with our memory.
And in this case, it should be pretty straightforward.
Because these things have exactly purpose.
We designed them purposely to have exactly what we need to create a
backing store.
Of exactly the information about who allocated.
What?
And when so inside here, those will now flow through and just get
ignored, but we can soon break them out and something that actually
records the correct information.
And so if I now Run the game, I just want to make sure that everything
still flowing properly and that nothing bad happens.
Looking at our debug, it can kind of see here.
We've got everything, but the memory is now available.
This is all working properly, right?
And so I think we're pretty good to go here.
So now what we want to do is from the
From the debug events themselves.
We want to translate these debug events that are in the debug buffer
into calls that will actually create the mirror structure that I typed
in just a few moments ago.
So each of these calls should essentially create a an operation to
This stuff right here, right?
We want to now start creating these, these three things, right?
So the first one is pretty easy, right?
What we would do here is we would say something like get Arena by
pointer, you know what I mean?
And we would pass here.
Well, all of these are going to use effectively, some kind of a cast
down of the actual event.
So in here, where we actually
Get the event in question which I assume is this right here, we're
going to want to do something where we say, like, hey, debugging
memory up and maybe it should have been called memory event.
But who knows?
I'm just going to say look, give me just that part of this thing.
Right?
So we're just getting out the, the mop part of this.
And then we're going to use that to figure out what's going on.
So what I want to do here is I want to do like a debug get Arena by
pointer.
I want to pass the arena that
Recorded.
That should give me back one of these, right?
And then I can go ahead and set its name.
So that allows me to just record what Arenas are called for pretty
printing basically.
And so now what I need to do is I need to manage the actual allocation
stack in there, so we can kind of see what actually what's actually
available now in the future?
What we probably want to do as we sort of get a little fancier here is
and I'm going to put these two dudes in there.
I should probably, you know I'll say this to use for later I'll
explain a little bit later because I'll put them in the actual
functions.
But anyway, where we have
And maybe I should make this.
Do that too.
Yeah, let's do that.
So up here, we'll just have our calls and we'll just Funk out to them
immediately, right?
So, this will be Arena right, Arena set name, this will be Arena
lock-free.
This will be Arena.
From Kate and this will be.
Alakay.
So each of these, I think what we want to do is just pass the debug
event down and we'll take it from there.
and so,
I'm going to put this up in here and that way, you know, these things
are just pulled out too.
I do that because I think I might want to just I just want to kind of
be able to see them as the for Ops and make them do what I want them
to do.
All right, so here's allocate.
Here's block.
Truncate and cures block free.
These will want the up but the also want the event.
That's why I passed the event itself.
That's just necessary because the event has information like the name
and stuff like that in it.
So I'm going to go ahead and grab this in each case.
And then I'm going to go ahead and do the actual work.
Right.
So in here, what we're going to go ahead and do is say that, all
right, when we do an arena set name, right?
We're going to get the arena.
We're going to set the name to whatever the name says, it is in the
rest of these, right?
We're going to need the same thing.
So this is kind of always going to happen.
Probably this is probably just, you know, the first two things of each
of these
Is that?
And but then each of us can do something a little bit different.
So when we do Arena block free in this case, now, we need to do is we
need to scan the list of blocks in the arena and we need to get rid of
the one that it asks us to.
Now at the moment we happen to know that block freeze will always go
in reverse order.
So we may be able to just do an assertion and just take the easy route
here and actually write something even dumber than that, which is to
say that when we look at the Block,
Pointer, we may be able to verify what it actually that that block
pointer.
Is the top one.
So I might just do an assert Arena, first block memory address.
Equals whatever this block address was.
Do we have?
Hold, please.
I want to look at what our conversion is.
I know we've got some
so it looks like we don't have a way of casting between these, so I'm
going to actually do this
Although actually that should probably not be necessary.
That should just work.
All right, so I'm going to do here.
I'm going to say I want to um em from this pointer, which is
The Block in question and it's going to assert that these are the same
and then I'm going to go ahead and remove the first one.
So I have the bug memory block or something like that.
The big arena block.
Why am I calling it an arena block?
I don't know.
Who knows?
We don't even call these Arenas but we sort of do home.
Mary is I guess, Hannah, who cares, anyway?
I'm gonna go ahead and get this free block out of here.
In fact, I could do this which is just to say that.
Let's assert that.
This just all works and then I'm going to say, all right, the arena
first block is going to be whatever the next block was.
And then we're just going to take this block and all of its
allocations and we're going to move them to the free store.
So we're going to take and have you know, in our main system here,
we're going to need.
Well, we're going to need a couple things, right?
We're going to need.
A hash here.
For our debugger Enos because we need to be able to look them up by
pointer, not sure where that should go but maybe it just goes here.
So in our Arenas we've got, you know, look up, that's too many for
this.
It doesn't even matter.
I don't even know that we need a hash.
We could just linearly search.
There's only going to be like 10 of them or something, right?
I mean, how many Arenas even are there but, you know, we've got Arenas
that we're looking up here.
And the Arenas are never going to get freed.
So we always remember every Arena that we've seen, I think, to be
fair, I guess we kind of
need to get rid of them though.
So I guess we
Yeah, so maybe I don't want to Hash them.
Maybe I just want this.
I think that might be fine and then we want blocks and allocations.
So that's I think all we really need their and so what I'm going to do
is just put it onto that list when we free the block.
And what I need to do here is when we actually free the last block, we
need to free the arena as well.
Does that make sense?
So we can do debug, get Arena by pointer because we do want that.
But we are going to just now, literally search that list instead,
because there aren't that many Arenas, and I guess I just think it's a
waste of time to do something more complicated for fetching them.
Yeah, super things like block truncate block.
Truncate just gets rid of allocations that are after it.
So what we're basically doing is moving things off of the the list and
into the into the free list.
Our particular block and then debugger and allocate will just be
putting things on to those blocks, right?
And if there's a new block, we actually use the new block, okay?
So let's just Implement all of those and then I think we're good to go
and then we can go work on, rendering them in some way that we can
inspect
So we're going to do here is say, alright, when we free a block
entirely, what we do is we take the first block and we assert that
that's got to be the one referring because we don't allow freaking out
from inside Arenas at the moment.
And so we're going to go ahead and Advance it to the next one.
And then we're going to insert this block onto our linked list.
So basically the debug States,
First free Block, right?
The the free Block itself is going to point to that thing.
And then it's going to point to the three blocks.
So we're just pushing that on, right?
So that's basically going to take it off of here, right?
It's going to remove it.
So in fact, I'll just note it for you.
We're adding it back.
So the only other thing we need to do here is have a while loop that
gets rid of all of the stuff that's actually on the, all of the
allocations that are actually on here.
Those need to go to the free list right now.
There's two ways we could do it.
One is we can do a while loop here and the other is, we could actually
keep a tail pointer and then just move the whole thing in one.
Go, I like tail pointers, call me crazy.
So I think I may just do it that way.
But some and so what we're going to do here is just say look, since we
know there's a tail pointer, we're good to go if the arena.
Oops?
Sorry if the free Block.
If that free Block, whatever the free Block is.
Happens to have any allocations on it.
Then I'm going to go ahead and move all of those allocations over to
the free list.
So to do that, it's pretty straightforward.
We just say that the free Block last allocation, whatever that one was
its next pointer is going to point to whatever the first free
allocation was, right?
So, we're just saying, Shane it.
So we have one big long list of free box.
And then the big debug State first free, allocation becomes whatever.
Our first application was
So now we have a big long list just chained up there, so that just
loves to move them all at the same time, right?
So that's pretty straightforward.
And again is can just be done in constant time if we do track a tail
pointer and since we're already in that cache line tracking the tail
pointer should be effectively free.
That's so I think it's a better trade off than spending through all
that memory for no reason.
So in here, we've got the set named function should just work.
We've got the debug block free that looks like everything that needs
to happen.
There, we've got the block truncate block truncate, just needs to move
things to the free list sequentially.
And so, I'm going to do the same thing.
In fact, I may just do this.
I'm think I'm just going to do that.
And that way in here, we can call this function, debug move to free
list with both of them.
So the first free allocation and the last reallocation
Sorry.
I'm at first allocation last location.
We can move all those to the free list this way.
And reuse that.
Right.
So I think all that's good.
We could also assert that the last pointer is bad because if you have
a first pointer, you know, you should have both or neither, right?
So we could just make sure that that's true.
So that allows us to move all these to the free list.
What we would do for truncate is basically the same thing.
We would just say, look, we're going to go through here and we're
going to look for all of the allocations.
That we would be precluded by this retraction in the size of the
block.
So for this for this Arenas first, you know, it's top block, we want
to I mean I guess we want to do the exact same thing we're doing here.
We want to say, take that top block assume that it's the correct
block, because we should only be truncating.
The final block of the Arena, the most recently allocated one at any
given time.
Then we want to do is just step through that block and see if we ever
We want to see.
How many of its allocations would be invalidated by the rewind that
has happened because of the truncation.
so, what we want to do is say, let's start with
In fact, we could do this.
So we want to do here.
Say alright, let's start with the first allocation.
Let's push this pointer all the way in fact.
What's called first valid that that makes more sense.
Okay, so let's take first valid.
And let's push that all the way to the first allocation in this block.
That will still remain after the rewind.
So what we want to do is say okay you know I guess just while first
valid if the first valid thing is correctly break otherwise we do
first valid equals first valid Max right.
So inside each of these memory blocks we know that we have
We know that we have an offset From the Block boundary and what we
want to do is see did we rewind past that allocation, right?
And so, if the offset From the Block is now higher than the size that
the block actually is, which you know what?
We didn't record.
And we need to.
So that's something we need to fix.
So in here where we have the interface, we need to fix that.
Yeah.
So in here, where we do the offset in Block, we need to record that so
that needs to actually be specified here.
So when we do that call, which is
Here.
So when we do a block free or the arena name, those are both fine
because they're storing information.
We can use to reconstruct what happened this one.
Well I'm so is the same with occasion.
This one does not.
We need to in addition here record one more piece of information which
is off of the block pointer.
We need to know what the used size is now, right?
So when we do the record truncate there, you have to make sure that
we're calling it.
The appropriate time.
So that would be right here.
Yeah.
So you can see me.
Doing it here.
This is where that needs to happen, right?
And so I think what we want to say is yeah keep this in the like
allocated size or whatever it is and and do that, right?
So I think that's where we're at.
Yeah.
Okay.
Okay, let's see here.
First reblock must, we must be using that for something else.
What does it say yes, this other kind of block here, so I guess we
need first free Arena block.
Okay, so let's see where we are at.
It looks like for some reason.
My mom is not a member, right?
I think we called it the actual name it is which is memory write
debug.
so, that's actually supposed to be that
I just forgot we named it consistent with the other things in that
list, even though we don't really need it to be.
We did anyway.
Okay.
Here we go.
So, going back to where we were at.
I want to finish up.
We were doing here.
So, when we actually go to use these things, like I said, this will
move it to the free list.
This has to be Arena.
Block like I said, because we already have something called block
there, but let's get back to truncation.
So in truncation, we start at the first link and we go, every time
we're going to do this, we want to see whether the offset From the
Block is
Higher than the or equal to I guess the the used the allocated size
value, right?
So if the offset in the block is higher than what the allocated sizes,
then we know that this thing is now no longer valid.
And so, I guess the, the way we would do it as this way, we stopped at
that point, right?
So we want to advance this to the place.
That's the first valid thing that will remain.
if the first valid just doesn't exist anymore, meaning if we rewound
all the way back,
Then we're moving the whole thing, so that's effectively going to do
this, right?
That makes sense.
Otherwise
we want to move a subset.
We want to move all the way to First valid and not any further, right?
So in order to do that, the problem is this is not a one passed last
kind of a scenario.
We actually to pass the last one we're actually moving.
What that means is we really sort of need the one prior to the one we
stopped on.
Something like this.
And so each time through here we sort of need to do that.
And that's the one we actually wanted to send down
Like so.
So I think in this case, also the interesting thing about that is that
means we don't have to do this anymore.
I think you can literally just do the if
If weave.
If we haven't Advanced meaning, if we didn't go anywhere, then we
don't want to create free, anything that really probably shouldn't
ever happen but just in case it does.
And then what we want to do is free everything else up to that point,
right?
So I think that's correct.
We'll see, we should still get this call.
So I don't think we need to free the Block in the case where
everything Gottfried I think we're okay.
But we do want to do in either cases.
If we update this, we need to change what the pointers actually.
Now are.
So the first the last allocation would still be valid sometimes but
the first allocation will always need to change in the case of last
allocation.
What we want to do there.
I guess is just see whether or not we freed everything.
So we're gonna have to do a little bit of an if there but for the
first allocation we know that first valid is the the correct thing
there, right?
And for the last allocation we just need to say if
We are freeing the entire list.
Another way to say this.
That might be clear, would be if the free Block last allocation equals
the last free.
Then that means we freed everything, so it's gone, right?
So that allows us to get rid of any allocations that have now been
rewound.
When we do our allocate, this is actually the easiest possible case in
this one we just need to create a block if there wasn't one and place
the memory in it, right?
So in this case, what we want to do is say, alright, this is really
the only place that we're allocating blocks or allocations, but we
need to do block
Haitian.
And so in this case, we need to do is say look at the top lock of the
Arena.
If the top lock of the Arena happens to have the particular
characteristic, we want then we use it, otherwise we create a new one,
right?
So I believe this should just look like this.
Like that.
And we have to check whether the block is valid here because the first
time you allocate something in arena, there will be no block at all.
And so we do need to say, look, let's look at that first block.
If we assume that, it's, if it's invalid, or it doesn't match what
we're trying to do, we make a new one, right?
And we could scan but you know we could assert if we want to later
that there isn't already blocked somewhere else with that address, but
that's sort of a separate check.
I don't know that we really need it.
So anyway, we're going to take the first block if we didn't get one
that we need to allocate one.
So then we're going to just say, all right, push struct.
Debug Arena block and that's going to come from the debug State you
big arena set.
That's things called.
Yeah.
So we're going to do that but
We can get it from the free list as well.
And so assuming that, you know, we assuming that we could
But assuming that we can't we just make a new one.
So we really don't ever.
We don't ever say, oh, we gotta stop retake with their fists of the
can.
Otherwise we make a new one in the D Block itself.
We don't really have to do anything other than add it to the list of
blocked for this Arena.
And then track with the allocation actually is, we know the first
allocation is 0.
We know the last allocation is 0 when we first create a block, we know
the memory address is just whatever the memory address is.
We already found it up here when we looked, we're looking to see which
one we were doing, so that should be a simple matter.
And so, the only other thing we need to do is just create that next
pointer.
The next pointer should be whatever would chain it onto the arena
itself.
And so that's the entirety of constructing that, you know, stable
stable state in memory, finally, we do the same thing for the
allocations themselves.
We know that there can't be
An existing application.
So, we always need a new one.
So what we're doing is we're saying like first free, allocation is
what we want.
If there wasn't one, we need to do some work, right?
So if there was one, then the next pointer, right is going to be
Used to sort of maintain the free list, but otherwise we need to
create a new one from Whole cloth.
So that's maintains now and finally, we just fill out the information
that goes in there for any given allocation.
Just this I guess filename in line number are probably the wrong
things to be tracking.
Now instead what we do is we track these good things, right?
So we just want to put the Grid in there and that comes down just as
the event.
Like, that's all.
I think that is that actually is and so we just need to record this
other information.
We've got the offset From the Block.
We've got the size, allocated
And we've got the size used unfortunately.
We can't really fill these out properly yet because we're not, we
don't send them all down.
And so for now they just have to be sort of from, did you know?
So you know, one of the things that we could do to is we, you know, we
maybe don't really need the size used anyway.
In fact, I think I'm going to delete that because what I realize is
That'll just show up when you look, you'll see the gaps so I guess we
don't really need that like when they get drawn you'll just see the
gaps in between them.
You're like well that's the memory we're wasting.
There it is, right.
That actually seems fine.
We may also want inside the block to store the total size.
So that we just know how big it is.
And so I think I may want to do this.
And that would come from the debug memory up in this case, has that
size allocated field and I think that's where I would want it.
so if you look up here, we can just place that
To, you know, these two things are capable of recording that for us
actually.
So I think if we just went down to the place where we actually do the
oh wait, no, I take it back.
We don't know that because we don't ever actually record a block
allocation, as its own step.
Maybe we should.
I think maybe we should because since we know when blocks are
allocated, we should probably record it.
Because it would literally just look like this.
Used is not what we want here.
So, the platform memory block in this case,
Oops.
We actually want the total size here.
The
Hmm.
The memory itself.
Why that's not supposed to be used?
That's supposed to be total used.
Right.
So how did that fly?
Shouldn't we be getting an error on that?
I'm just going to assume that we would have been, so that should be
total used and this should be total size, right.
So, I'm just going to say that that would have been an error and
without actually looking because we got too much other stuff to bother
with right now.
But total use is not a member of platform memory block.
Isn't it though?
Oh, that's stats.
Okay, nevermind.
Sorry, I take it all back.
It is used in size, sorry everybody.
Sorry about that.
Okay.
Minor diversion.
All right, so moving along here.
So if I want to do that, then what that means is, when I do my
collation, of debug events in here.
I just have one more to worry about, right?
I just want to say Arena block allocate.
and,
I call it here.
That's really all that has to happen and then we move in here because
I had I guess I have that now block allocation there.
I need
This one too.
Make sure that it goes away when necessary, all I need to do is just
call this block allocation.
Anytime I actually produce one of these blocks and I believe that the
only time that that happens is inside here.
So when this occurs right, you can see me getting the new block right
here.
I should be able to just go.
All right.
Here's the arena.
Here's the current block, and we're done, right?
Because there's nowhere else that actually ever allocation blocks.
As far as I know,
It's completely isolated which is exactly what we want in is good.
So when I actually do that here and we have the allocate, all I'm
going to do is pull out the code that I was just doing implicitly
there.
So this part right here where we're sort of
Allocating that block at the.
Outset that right here we're going to just change this back to one of
those assertions.
Like it was before.
So this stuff will come up here and we will deal with that.
Right?
But we're going to change to just assuming the top block is accurate.
So in here, any time you push an allocation, we're like it better be
on the current block.
Otherwise something guys, think, and we need to fix the code.
The debug code is obviously like, you know,
Misbehaving.
So when you tell me to allocate a block, then what I can do is avoid
this sort of nonsense all together and just say, okay, we know we need
a new block so we're not sort of doing this kind of test anymore.
What we're doing instead is going directly, right?
We're going to say we know, we need to allocate a new block off of
this Arena.
I should probably put these in there though.
So you know we're going to get a new one assuming we did, we unchain
it?
If we didn't, we create a new one, then we need to fill out all of the
information on their this.
Has to go there but otherwise we just fill everything out.
Doesn't have any allocations to start with.
This is the address that actually has.
Here's how much space.
It got reserved for the block and then we change it together when we
go to the arena allocate.
Now,
We just say they did better be off of the main block, then we do the
same thing, get ourselves, something to use to record it.
And then we need to actually put it on to the block and question where
it's supposed to go.
And so to remember, to fill out all the rest of these, we just say,
okay, we've got the grid, we've got the awesome bucket size allocated.
The next pointer is always going to be zero because we're changing
these onto a linked list in the order in which they're actually
allocated.
Although we still want them in reverse order.
So no actually we're not, that's not true.
So the next pointer is because we want these to push on like a stack
so because we want the most recent allocation to be first.
So what we're going to say is all right, the next one is for whatever
block we ended up using its first allocation is going to be the next
one here.
And then the block first allocation
It's going to be.
The one we're on, right?
And now what we have to do because we decided we wanted to keep a next
pointer, is the next pointer has to get updated.
I've started a last pointer has to be updated as well.
And the way that we update that is the last allocation
always stays the same unless it's zero, right?
Because the first time we allocate something in the list, everything
else comes on before that thing, right?
And so that last pointer just stays pointing to the element of 22, no
matter how much stuff you put on it.
And so, the only thing we want to do here is say, look, if there was
no last pointer at all, then, we are also the last
Her right.
But otherwise we never touch it.
So that first allocation is the only thing we're updating each time.
We're pushing that backwards.
The next pointer is, you know, sort of going to the the allocation
that happened prior in time, if that makes sense, like it's the
previous allocation that happened or something,
All right, so we need to get Arena by pointer.
For one more collating.
I'm going to leave this out for now.
Like so, and I just want to take care of all of our compile errors
before we get to that.
So what is the problem here?
I don't know.
It's probably there, look at that in a second.
These all just kind of need the capacity bug state may, go ahead and
make sure that's happening.
and then we'll address it the second
Okay, this is actually event name so that's why that was wrong with
the opt itself.
It doesn't have the name.
It's in the outer debug structure, so let's see here.
This is just block memory address not free Block.
In fact, I don't know why free Block was ever used there.
We're not actually freeing the block.
Block.
Remains untouched actually.
This is off of the op, not the event.
In this case, this is the first block, not the first free Block.
Well, actually no, it is butts off of the debug State.
There we go.
Same here.
What else we got?
So, the debug Arena block first free black.
We made that mistake before.
Mina block.
and,
Just need an address of.
Sighs.
Allocated seems like that should just work.
What's the complaint for the?
Those with have a size allocated.
Oops.
But does this?
Allocated size.
All right.
Good consistent.
Naming their Casey.
Um, yeah, let's see what we got here.
So again, that's up to debug State, not the arena, this needs to
allocate here.
And this is don't tell me.
Allocated size.
so in this case, the allocates the offset from block
Let me go ahead and jump directly to that.
So in the debug memory up, we called that offset.
In Block.
Yeah, this is this is not a good naming day.
Wow, to is exact same thing and I didn't manage to call it.
The same thing always good.
So we've got Arena block allocate here.
Oops, Got Arena block allocate here.
We need to add that in.
I guess I'll do it like that and when we actually go into the debug
interface, we need to make sure we're passing that properly.
So we got the block allocation.
I'm going to move that down to the applications, both parts together.
This is going to be a block allocate.
So
And then, I think we're pretty close.
So in here, we've got Hoops in here, we've got debug Arena.
Results.
I guess I could just call it result.
I'm going to return the result.
What I want to do here is say find it for me.
By looping through everything.
In this case, like I said, I just decided it's not worth it to try to
accelerate these as probably just going to spend more time than it
actually saves because there's only going to be like 20 of these
things, right?
And so linear search, you know, you really don't want to start putting
in kinds of weird acceleration structures for things.
When there's not enough of them to act, like the amount of time.
You spend handling, those acceleration structures just ends up being
slower than if you just checked to begin with,
So in this keep occurring debugger Arena.
I'm just going to test to see if we found the one that we're actually
talking about here and go from there.
This doesn't need to be avoid.
I'm not sure why did that?
It could just be an actual point of the arena and I should note.
So I just want to make sure people know they're not that you shouldn't
be doing anything with it.
It's just there to let you know.
So maybe that, you know, maybe you would argue that, that should be
that way, just so people don't get the wrong idea.
So all I want to do here is say, look is the arena pointer the same as
the one that I'm that I'm asked to find.
If it is, then I'm going to say that that's done and off you go.
If we couldn't find it, then I need to allocate a new one.
So at that point I'm just going to say
Let's go ahead and create a new one.
Let's fill it out.
Although, you know, I could name it with the first person who used it.
I don't know that.
I want to do that though.
I don't want to do that.
And so then I think that's it.
So we're done now.
And now we have to actually get all this working, the debug state.
First Arena here, just needs to be updated to make sure this is all
changed together.
But other than that I think we're fine.
What else we got?
Okay, so now we just have to debug this, but it should now be
recording everything that happens in there.
And once we've debunked it, we should be good to go, right?
I would hope let me switch to debug mode so it makes it easier on us.
While we're bugging, we don't have to worry about any kinds of crazy
nonsense that the optimized for me.
I've done.
And we can see our errors better.
So off we go we're running now.
We're collating a frame and it looks like we're getting a Arena
allocate call on something that didn't have its block allocation at
the top, right?
And so we got to figure out why you know what happened.
And let's start by looking at the arena itself.
So looking at the arena you can
That it just didn't register a blackout cake call.
That's, that's the entirety of the reason.
And so that suggests to me that there's something wrong with the way
that we're actually calling block allocate because we shouldn't have
had that happen.
So when this occurs up here, it should have pushed that on there.
Specifically, this piece of code right here should have been called.
I'm going to go ahead and set a breakpoint there and see I just want
to see what happens right before that events.
So you can see that this is working properly for a little while, but
then it fails at a at some specific point, right?
So it's not that we never created the correct setup for an arena.
It's that at some point.
We did an incorrect somehow, this got got much with right.
So, let's take a quick look and see if that particular Arena was.
Implicated or not.
So I'm going to go ahead and do this.
So here's one Arena that we call the block, Al Catan, wish I could
cut, and paste this value.
And then we come down here, you can see, we're using the same Arena.
Come back up here.
Same Arena.
Different Arena now.
Although you know what actually am I being stupid?
Maybe?
Maybe remedy being is better than Visual Studio in this way and I
should just use it.
Let's find out.
We come in here and we get this Arena, so I lock that value.
No, it did not work.
Although this one didn't update.
I don't understand that was weird.
Did it work or didn't?
It may pay?
Close attention.
Be coming here, we've got 1.
V.
1 4 3 F.
1C 1D 0, right?
I lock it.
I run and that one updated, but this one didn't.
Oh that.
Okay.
So that probably locks.
That locks it to look at that stack location probably.
Is there any way in remedy to lock the current pointer like just this
thing?
I want to know.
I guess not.
Georgina out there today is he probably not, I think he's on vacation
actually.
I think he said he was on vacation.
so I feel like this would be a really good feature potentially, which
is like
And and maybe we can send it to George, send the recording to George
if someone can mark this for me.
What I want to be able to do is come through here and I want to say
like okay I hit this thing and Arena was this let me like and in fact
the best possible version would be looks like this and I like right
click or something and there's the menu which is like remembered this
like keep showing this and it would add effectively this, right?
it would just add like,
It would have that automatically so that when I run I still have this
one always right.
And when every time it changes I just right click and save it again.
So I've got them all, you know what I'm saying?
Like something that makes that really quick and painless.
So you can just do it anytime you want, or maybe you can even set up
things, like, save every time there's a new one of these, you know
what I mean?
Because that would be so handy, right?
Oops, I screwed up.
I think I'm supposed to type f8 there.
I did it wrong.
I copied this one.
all right, so
so, if we look at these,
These two properly have first blocks as we would expect.
I'm going to set a breakpoint in the block.
Clear.
As well.
That we should get a block.
Does who are we on now?
We're on 360.
That's fine.
C8.
So there's we just we're just great and plenty of different Arenas
here.
And we're allocating off the one we just did.
And so, it's actually.
That that one we never allocated.
So we never saw a block allocate call for that one.
Good way.
Let's verify that's the case.
So we get for that, we do and the fifth one screws up.
One, two.
34.
Five.
Six.
Seven, eight, nine.
10:00.
So that's five that were correct.
And six fails.
That one more time.
Okay.
So b0 twice, f8.
60 twice, C 8.
And it is 30 guy, we just never saw.
So, is there some way that an arena gets a block?
Allocated?
That wouldn't go through the path that I'm talking about?
Right.
so, in order to do that, you would need to have
Gotten here.
Well, okay, so here's a question.
What if you allocated zero?
Maybe I just need to special case that.
Did it allocate 0?
So, here's the event.
Right.
Who is the person involved here?
It's handmade win32 at 1298.
hmm, I wonder if this is because
this is a
win32 layer problem.
Who is doing that?
1298.
So it's the file group memory in particular.
When does that?
Well, I guess it would be fine, right?
I mean it's just created as a zero doubt thing.
and,
In theory, when it first enters that push struct.
It should just allocate a block.
Right.
so, I'm not sure why we would be seeing the allocation prior,
I'm just not sure why we be seeing the application prior to when it
was actually
Or why we wouldn't see the block allocation prior to, when the
allocation is used, the fact that it's the wintry to makes me worry.
That this is because these are two different modules recording events.
And so, are they doing?
Is there some kind of out of order problem that happens there?
I don't see why there would be though.
So, I don't know, these should happen in the same order.
So, what I'm going to do is, I'm going to take a look at push size and
I'm going to see stack wise when does this stuff happen?
So here's a push sighs, it's happening on.
Probably the game, right?
Don't know.
It's here.
So, it's doing a bootstrap.
It's actually the very first thing that it does right for the getting
the file types.
I suppose another way to do that, with just be to go like this.
Access violation.
What?
I miss something.
How did that caused an access violation?
Because that us again, I'm just concerned that has something to do
with something.
We don't really remember.
How those two are partitioned.
Alright, let's take a look.
So, there's the arena.
Yes, I mean that's just clearly somehow it skipped right over this.
Hit it just never called it right.
So why did that happen?
Why didn't it call?
Let's try and set it to this.
Just make sure that happens again.
So first time through we record a block allocation on Arena, it's like
he ate right.
Then we allocate on E8, then we switch to 40 and we never saw 40 never
hit here, right?
So, how is that possible?
Like how is this able to?
with 325 group memory now is like a
Oh no.
Hmm, the plot thickens.
Doesn't it?
Oh this, this is Saucy, indeed.
So, do you guys see what happened there?
The problem is that the memory arena is actually just a thing.
You can move around.
It doesn't.
All that matters is that this chain
Is correct.
And so, when you do a bootstrap, you use a different Arena.
It's temporary for the initial allocation.
And then it relocates itself to inside the place it allocated.
So, while we don't, while we can still track the memory, just fine.
We wouldn't have any way of naming, the Arena's the way that we wanted
to.
Because of the ability you have to do that sort of squirrelly little
maneuver.
so, I really don't know what else we could do here other than
When you first make a memory Arena, we mark it.
I think that's the only thing we'll really be able to do.
I mean, I really just can't think of any other way to do it.
We would need to put something in here effectively, right?
We're inside the memory Arena, we add a debug tag that only exists at
debug time, right?
And we could work around this specific problem by because bootstrap
Arena happens to know that you moved the arena.
We could simply add a debug call that says the arena moved.
But the problem is, I don't know that like anyone could still do that
on their own, like anyone can still do this.
On their own this copy.
And so we would I mean we could just enforce it by discipline and say
don't do that or make this call when you do, right?
And I guess that's fine.
That's the only other way I can think to do it.
In other words, you would do, you would have to do this.
You know, I'm saying to you.
So effectively you would not really be allowed to copy an arena
manually.
You'd have to copy it yourself, which I hate that kind of crap.
So I don't love this but maybe it's the best compromise.
because the only other thing I can think of is,
Is you have to mark them?
It's not where that goes.
Right.
Like I just don't know.
I don't know how I would track it and so if we want to be able to name
them, that's the way we would have to do it.
Let me think.
Is that really true?
Did I just?
Did I just say something stupid?
No.
I am being stupid.
I think I can actually pull this off without that.
And I'm going to try.
I'm going to argue that if we just let this be the way it was before,
without a move Arena call, there is a way we can do it and we just
have to change our thinking a little bit
right.
so,
Inside the debug system.
We're looking at marinas by pointer, right?
But what we know is that a rinas are just strings of blocks.
So if instead we just did this, oops,
and said,
Arena's are just a name String of blocks.
In theory, I think that would always work.
Meaning, when we go to get an arena, if we just knew what the top
block pointer was at the time,
That should be sufficient for us to maintain the chain.
The problem of course is that the blocks themselves were it requires
us to record what those blocks actually are.
Which in some cases is Trivial.
In this case, it's just works.
In this case, it just works.
And in this case, it just works.
The only one that's complicated is this one?
And so when we allocate a block,
We just have to pass the old block that we were using.
You with me on this.
This is some seriously nutso stuff.
So if we were to say
That.
Or.
I think it works.
And then you always look it up by this block.
so,
when we do debug get Arena.
By look up block.
We're just always going to do this here.
And I'm going to argue that that will actually work because as long as
we always pass, which one would have needed for that.
I think you can just maintain chains without ever actually thinking
about an arena at all.
And then you just need to know which chain you're talking about, which
is always correctly identifiable by whatever the top block, was at the
time, right?
Because that's just how the arena is working itself.
So I think if we do that, oops,
Then this whole thing just kind of works.
in here, we just say,
Whatever the first block is it should look at that.
Look that right.
And I think that's all there is to it.
Oh, but it's not first block.
It's that.
Right.
I think that's correct.
And so then what would happen is whenever the final block got removed
At that point.
You would have to record.
That the arena went away.
Entirely.
Right.
I think that's the only thing that becomes sort of complicated.
So when we're doing that, look up, you have to go back and say
yeah, you have to actually be able to clean those out, which I think
we would have had to do anyway now the think about it.
So that's actually no different than before.
So I think we just have to track that fact that whenever you clear an
arena down to zero, we have to remove it from the list.
So in the case, where you do a block free on the last block, right?
this case right here, you have to do a thing that basically says if
the arena first block
Is nothing.
Then this has to be scheduled for removal.
And so I think that's okay and we can schedule when we want those
Arenas to be cleaned up so that we don't have to remove ones.
Until later if we want to for at the moment I guess I would say we
probably can just remove them now but in the future if you want them
to persist so we can inspect them.
We may want to do something like just marking blocks as being free,
you know, and cleaning these out as sort of a separate path.
So we can watch what happened for now.
I guess.
I'll say look, we just remove this Arena, right?
And I think that's fine.
All right, so this is pretty pretty tricky, right?
It's pretty nuts.
When you think about it, but I guess I think that all just works and
the only thing that you need to do is normally, yeah, you would just
pass the same block there, but in the case of one of them, you have to
do a little bit extra.
So in all of these cases where you're sitting the array, this thing,
it's actually Arena.
Look up block now.
And what's going to happen is, it's just whatever current block is,
right.
I have to get set.
So in here, where we do
Arena set name, or any of this stuff really Arena set name.
I think could technically occur in a case where there wasn't top block
at all.
And so I feel like that one makes it a little bit harder.
To work with.
So, in this case, we would, I think, have to say that if we didn't
have a top block, we couldn't name this Arena yet, so it probably
looks something like
It probably looks something like this.
You know, I'm saying, but otherwise, yeah, I think it's always just
this.
Oops.
And so looking at these in a little more detail, I think we can then
go ahead and be a little bit more specific about how these things are
working.
If we come in here, we can sort of see that like the record.
This is just passing the arena current block anyway.
So I think we could just say, all right, on record allocation, we're
really just doing
We're just passing the same block twice, right?
And so I wonder if maybe it makes more sense to say in that case we
just passed this so it's just blbl.
Right.
For truncation.
Let me grab that.
For truncation, it's the same thing.
So I think again that's not changing which block is up there and
neither is this.
So I think these are all just this.
And you don't need that Arena anymore and you can sort of see where
I'm going with this.
Hopefully, this is again, pretty complicated, but I think it works.
So we can do the lookup book here.
Many are confused to this is the BL and so all that's good.
The only one we have to do here.
This is the weird one.
It's this requires a previous block.
so when we actually go to record a block allocation,
We need to know which one was when we actually did that black,
allocation.
So, when we do debug record block, allocation, we need to know what
the one was that was before us in order to do that.
I think what we want to do there is we need and in fact now I think
about it,
I guess we kind of always know which one that is because you can see
We have the arena preview here.
So actually if we just do this, we can actually just do this.
So I think that's all good.
And furthermore, because this this actually shakes out to be much more
interesting, it means that because we've got an extra
Field here, we can actually get a little bit more ridiculous if we
want to.
So, if we go to debug memory up now, and we look at what's actually
happening, it means that this could actually be more explicit, so if
we have,
if we have block,
Allocate.
Right.
We've got something like this and then we've got the allocated size.
In this case, all of these don't need another one.
So that means we can get what we wanted, which is these to be fully
These can have the complete memory size so they don't have to be
truncated anymore, right?
Without making this any larger than our previously previously size,
debug event.
So that seems good.
And so I think, what we want to do is this
So, we can always use the block there, and then only this particular,
one uses, two of them.
And so, it's going to use
Its own special version because it's got this bad changing Behavior.
We have to handle, right.
I think that's the only place where that actually has to happen.
So that way, we could do this and never have any truncation at all.
Everything would always be full full width, which is much better than
what
Before.
So I like that a lot.
And then when we actually correlate, those inside the debug system,
Everything should just work the only differences.
Now, the block allocate has this sort of other weird situation going.
So we've got the arena look up book there.
The rest of these can just use the block as is and be flying with
that, right?
Okay, let's see.
So let's try to make sure we've got everything going correctly here.
We've got to do the arena removal, and then we got to fix all of our
errors.
All right, so in debug record block, allocation here.
Also, I'm gonna make sure that I made those macros correctly.
Yeah, this should just do that.
What is the question BL?
We have a capital B lb, use their summer.
Not sure, I see where that's coming from.
Am I missing something?
It says Capital BL.
I mean, number 196.
In debug record block, allocation there it is.
So don't the wrong one.
Okay, so let's make all these things work properly.
So in the arena, look up block here where we get one of these things.
I think what we actually want to do.
Here.
Let's see.
So when we're actually looking these up we just want to use a block
address.
And the block address has to be the address of the first block, right?
So meaning we're going to be looking this up by this.
and so, we have to say, like, if test first block, and test first
block,
Memory, address equals look up.
Address right.
And so the look up address.
Is just whatever the block pointer was that we were asked to find
assuming that we did find it.
We go ahead and and return it.
If we don't find it, we create a new one, right?
That should always work except in this one case where we're not
allowed to do it because we're not going to fill in a block.
And if we're not going to fill out in Block, we're kind of screwed
because we need to look it up by that, right?
So in here, we get Block free food, free list that should all just
work, right think all this code should be fine.
What's wrong with this?
But you just be block
And that should just be blocks.
Well fact, I should be true everywhere.
So
That's correct.
That's all correct.
So, I think we're good.
And we just now need to build you to do the removal.
Get Arena by pointer, is not what this is called anymore.
And so then I think the only thing we need is is this code.
And so this needs to take a debug state.
In the arena to remove and all we're going to do here is look to see
when we find it.
So basically, we're going to say that we're going to look at the debug
State's first Arena.
We're going to look to see if we can find this particular one.
So we're going to say, oops.
so while we have one that's valid, we are going to
We're going to kind of move through each one grabbing the pointer.
If we find this particular one then we just skip it, right?
I guess I could write this in a simpler way.
That doesn't require so much fancy footwork.
I could just say this if the first Arena equals the arena, hmm.
Then debug state.
Skips it, right?
Otherwise, we stand.
And this is just a little easier to read it was the first one skip it.
If it's any other one, just do the same thing and check.
Right.
I was going to write them as one because you can you can do it by just
using the address the pointer.
But I decided not to just for making it easier to read.
So if the next pointer would have pointed to us, we just say that it
points past this right?
And then we're done.
So that gets it out of the list and then we can just put pop it on the
free store, right?
And so the only thing I want to do here is is again.
Just try to get it.
From a free store.
So we try to get it here and I guess I can just do it like this.
so, if we get it,
And if we don't, we make a new one.
I think that's all I really needed.
and,
I need to put that someplace actually store that in here.
Oh I already did.
So hopefully, now we can actually debug this for real and make sure
that we're actually getting the proper order of events here.
That was what I was worried about before so I'm just trying to make
that work.
Now let's see what the the bugs.
We actually hit our first before I go tracking down Jimmy.
So it looks like we've got a tracking problem with our first and last
pointers here.
You can see that the these don't match.
I was just an assertion designed to catch the fact that we're not
tracking the last pointer properly.
Let me go take a look at who's responsible for that.
You can see that we're asking to remove all of the allocations in our
block here, so it looks like our reblock in question is actually the
thing that's wrong.
so, looking at when that's getting updated,
There's two people who can be responsible for that one is when we're
allocating.
Well I guess you're three people actually technically.
So when we actually create a block itself where's our block out kit
called?
Yeah.
And here we set them both to 0 and then when we allocate a block I'm
sorry.
We at we do an allocation
We need to update the pointers here and you can actually see, it's
just a not, it's missing the not in that case.
So the debug Arena allocate just needs.
To update it when it's not set.
That was just a
Stupid type of, right?
Okay, so yeah, I don't want to quite do breakpoints just yet.
I want to let this thing run and see what happens.
That's bad.
Okay, so now we're at a place where we actually get.
Okay.
So we found an arena by a block, but there's no blocks in the arena.
That's actually not allowed.
So again, another bug case here that we actually want to fix in fact,
the so yeah.
The arena itself did come back, correct?
So first block should never really be allowed to be set to 0.
So in the case, where we do a
One of these get Arena by look up block.
I think what I may want to do, there is actually disallow creation
except on a very specific type of call.
So that we can have this error occur earlier in the process and and
debug it, right?
So in here we're we're doing this.
Maybe I guess what I'll do is like assert.
Allow creation or results, right?
Either we got one or you're going to let me create one but not both.
In fact I could also do it this way assert allow creation.
So that way when we do this we're just going to say most of the time
you can't make one of these.
In fact the only time that you're actually allowed to make one of
these
Is Jimmy when we're getting it here.
Right, and so this I'm hoping we'll catch problems with the way that
were processed.
This because it'll tell me like somebody tried to look up a block that
they shouldn't have been able to look up, right?
So, let's see.
It's in an allocation call and it's trying to create a block.
for whatever this is right and we haven't actually gotten that block
through here or it cleared out all of its memory
Well, no, it would have had to have called the free.
So so we don't really know, right?
We don't know why it's at why we're getting this event without that
information, but we want to know, right?
So we want to know like what's going on here.
Now, the question is, how many of these have we gone through before we
hit the problem and I don't know.
So let's find out.
Quite a few.
So we're like processing all of this stuff, right?
And this is all not causing a problem.
So we get to quite a few allocations and before we actually hit this
issue, right?
That's unfortunate.
It makes it a lot harder for subtract down.
But, you know, let's start by just going.
What's the actual location?
Who's causing the problem?
Maybe that'll give us a clip.
So the queen is coming from handmade memory, .h 388, right.
So it's another bootstrap, right?
It's a bootstrap, that's causing the problem and it's specifically the
first bootstrap that's causing the problem.
I should say the first allocation in the bootstrap is really what I
mean.
so somehow, this first bootstrap push size,
this one here.
Somehow that push size is using a block pointer.
They did not previously call.
The block allocate.
Now, why would that be
Tell me more.
It's the very first allocation in a bootstrap it did allocate 32 bytes
of memory.
And somehow.
It did not hit or this did not properly work.
This part of the code.
So, why is the question?
Why would that?
Be the case.
Let's ask another question.
So here we've got, in fact, I could even look at these a little more
closely.
So, since it's only the one bootstrap one, I'm interested to know how
often are we bootstrapping, and which ones of those are having the
problem, right?
So, if inside the bootstrapper here, if I just like, say, let's go
here.
First one, two,
Buck.
So I know there's only two of these that actually happen.
I can step through them, write down what they did and see why we're
getting an error.
The first one attempts to record a block allocation here, the arena
setup is as follows, you can see that the current block would be
whatever I just recorded here so it's, you know, to see 1476 f00.
Zero right.
So that's the block allocation.
That should be entered into the list right now as going with the, you
know, this operation here.
And
It will record the previous block as well, so it will the one that it
will use for look up.
Is actually zero.
Which should still work.
Okay, oddly enough.
We'll get to that in a second, I then come through and I'm going to go
ahead and do a debug credit allocation here.
I look at the current block and the current block does correctly
mirror this.
So there should be two events in the debug stream back-to-back.
And honestly, I think I can even verify that because if I look at the
global debug stream,
Where is that?
If I look at this.
This is going to be kind of tricky.
Search 82, which means I should be able to just do this.
Right.
So this is the first one, this would be like the next one that we
would actually record.
So we actually want to look at the one just before that, and the one
just before that.
So number 80, in this case, right?
Here's the block allocation and let's see what it said.
It said the lookup block was zero and the block was, you know, F 0,
which is exactly what we'd expect.
Let's see what the next one says.
In this case,
and in that case, we have got
That block as record to correctly as well, right?
There's the f00 other, so those are both recorded properly.
Let's see what happens.
The next time through on the push, block, the precise for the
bootstrap.
Let's see.
We got the arena current block to d d 0 0, 0 0, right?
So that's the second one.
That's that one.
And so what we want to do here is say let's just remember which of the
this was the first this is the second that we hit and there's only two
so then we go into record the allocation
We're going to use the current block, its, it is correct.
So again, those should be correct, 1661 should show us that as well,
right?
So that should be the block a lock looking at that, we get a zero and
a DD there, which is exactly what we want.
And then if we run it and record the other event, I should be able to
get opes.
Be nice.
If cursor positioning worked in.
What is it?
Here I am gooey or whatever it's called.
So yeah looking at the memory up here gd0.
So so these are totally correct as far as I can tell.
So it looks to me like we just have a bug with how we're processing
the events because the events look like they should work.
So the give me one second here.
I just want to look into the debugs systems handling of these.
So inside luck allocate, this is going to get passed a 0 which should
hopefully mean that it does actually allocate one.
It will then go ahead and
Nick, the new block like so.
Either way, it'll say there's no locations in it.
It'll take.
The block that was passed as the new one that's going to be there set
the memory rest of that, which is what it should do.
And then record that that Arenas.
First block is this one, right?
And again, when we're scanning for these, that's what we're using,
right?
We look through the Arenas and we look for the first block and
assuming that there is one we test to make sure that the memory
address is whatever address you asked us to look up.
And then when we add it in here, we just say, yeah, like take the
first free one.
And use it.
That all seems fine to me.
Oh, hi.
That's pretty stupid.
In the case where we used one, we never actually bothered to set it
State.
You think that could have something to do with it?
Yeah, probably.
All right, but it does seem to be working.
Okay, so far so let's see.
Now that tracks it properly.
And we can sort of see how owners it is.
Later.
Alright, so now we seem to be going okay.
If I go ahead and switch this to release build, we can see whether we
have any horrible memory runaway Happening Here.
Seems reasonable.
But it looks like we are sort of maybe leaking a bit there or doing
something that great like watch you can if you can almost feel it when
it happens.
Yeah, I mean just look at what's happening.
Right, so we're not quite processing that correctly but we're close.
Okay.
So let's try to
Let's try to just isolate our memory are here and then I think we're
good to go and this was pretty tricky to get right to try and track
all this without actually intruding at all into the thing we were
tracking but I think we did it unless there's a gotcha here that I
didn't anticipate.
But yeah so if we look oh.um
Yeah, we're probably we're properly calling all this out.
All right, so if we look at what's happening on all of these, let's
just double-check our process.
And then we'll make one pass.
One more, pass that a burger and see if we can get it properly.
Okay.
So, first things first.
Here's where we manage the Arenas.
So in here we say okay you know look through all of our Arenas see
whether or not we've got one here.
This actually should never be allowed to be zero.
So in a sense we could just do this.
Probably for starters, let's let's do that.
And just make sure that's true because you're not really ever allowed
to do that.
You're not allowed to leave somebody in here after the initial ad who
doesn't get their block pointer set.
So that's, you know, should just be the case when we come through here
we say, look, are there any free ones of these that we can grab?
If there are great, use it.
So we advance the, you know, pop it off the free list, basically,
otherwise just add a new one on here.
Either way we set the name initialize.
The fact, there's no blocks in it and then we change it on by
Hang the first arena points to it, and I'm sorry that it's next
pointer points to the first Arena and the first arena points to it as
a standard linked list addition, right?
For setting the name.
We don't do anything.
We just look up to see whether or not there's a block.
Pointer that's valid and if there is we just set its name and that's
all we do.
So we shouldn't really be able to do anything there that would cause
any memory to have exchanges to happen at all.
And since we're not even allowed to allocate here, we would get an
assert if it did moving stuff to the free list here.
This is probably a place where we could be having some serious
problems because we need to make sure we do this very carefully.
So, if we have a list where we've got a first and a last year, and
what we're doing is we're saying, okay, if there is a first point,
Order.
Then we need to do some work.
Otherwise we don't, but we want to make sure that there's no last four
in that case.
So assuming there's a first and a last Point, what we do is say the
next.
So From First to Last is a block of chunk of these links.
The next pointer will point to whatever the currently first free,
allocation is on the free list, and then we will point to the head of
this using debug State first reallocation, right?
That seems correct to me.
I don't see anything weird happening there.
So, that all seems fine when we go to remove an arena, pretty
straightforward process.
If it's the first Arena, then we just move the first pointer to
whatever was after it, right?
Otherwise we start by looking at the first Arena and we go as far as
we can go.
Yeah, we just look and see if it was the next pointer.
We then hop over it exactly the same way that we would have done here
and stop.
We then set its next pointer to point to whatever the whole chain of
fruit currently free reasons were.
So we do that.
We then say that the debug first free arena points to the arena,
right?
To the arena itself.
Maintaining the free train in debug Arena, block free.
This is taking one of these blocks and getting rid of the whole thing.
so what we want to do here is move everything to it, which is what we
do right at the outset and
We're just asserting here that this is that it is the top block on its
back.
So we do this, of course, that would have to be true.
So this is sort of kind of pointless, but, you know, whatever.
In order to remove the free block from the arena after we move all of
its allocations off of it, we say that the first block on the arena is
whatever the next block after it would have been.
That seems fine.
We then add the old block to the free list.
We do that by saying, it's next corner is whatever the arena block
free list, previously was, and then the free Block points to us, we
Say if that would have been the last block, then get rid of the Arena
entirely.
Now, for truncation.
So, this is quite possibly where we would have problems.
So, here we say, alright, get the arena by the block, assert that it's
the block we want.
We're going to start by looking at the first allocation, and if the
first allocations offset From the Block is less than the total size,
then we know that this is a valid allocation, right?
And the question is, is that actually is that shot going to work?
If we're always pushing allegations on in the reverse order.
So like, allocations come on and they get added to the front, right?
Which we did, you know that we did?
Make it so that every time you allocate its the first thing.
Nope, it's the first thing on here, right?
So they should go in ascending order.
So, if this block is less than the allocated size, then none of the
ones after it should be either, right?
We could add some assertions, if we want to double up on that, right?
But anyway, what we're trying to do here is say, oh, right?
So assuming that that that was the case, we just stopped and that's
the end.
But if it's not then what we do is say well we could free this one, so
Advanced the pointer and remember that we could have freed this one
if we get to the end of this and we find that the first allocation in
the block is not the one that we ended that iteration on.
Then we know that there is a range, we could free, we move everything
from the first application and it up to and including whatever the
last 31 was we move those to the free list.
We then make the first allocation whatever this first valid part was
here
And then we say if the last allocation was the one that we would have
freed there, then we now have no allocations left in the block
whatsoever, we don't actually deallocate the block because we assume
that it will tell us to do that in a call to block deallocate or block
free rather.
We assumed it would have called this, right?
Again seems pretty solid Arena block allocates that actually has to
make a new one of these.
It first says, can we get a free one if we can just Advance the
pointer for the free list.
So we get a different next time, otherwise I'll get a new one,
initialize its stuff.
Put it onto the Arena's first block.
Here.
And we know that must at least be working because otherwise we would
get assertions when people were trying to use the memory address
there, right?
So finally, we're down to allocate, we get whatever the block is that
we're supposed to be putting this one on it inside the arena.
First block part here.
What we want to do is say yeah make sure we're on the one.
We think we should be on then look to see if we have a free
allocation.
If we do then move the free list up one.
If we don't then make a new one record, the allocation by
Being that the grid from for this allocation is the grid from the
event that the offset is the offset.
The size of the size, the next pointer is going to be whatever was
previously on the the blocks list the blocks first, allocation,
I think, I just realized.
What the problem is, I don't actually think there is a memory leak.
So we use memory Arenas inside the debug system.
Right.
so,
this will always create an infinite Loop of allocations, because every
time you allocate you record an event which has to allocate
another record to store it, which will create an event, which will
create another allocation, right?
So we can't do this for things that are in the debug system, right?
If we do, we can never record them all because the act of recording
creates an event right.
So we need a way of telling the system.
When were allocating these, please don't remember that.
Um,
hahaha.
So yeah.
That makes it a little trishy.
That's awesome.
That's so cool.
So, probably what we would need to do.
There is this
everybody when we do the get a real look up,
If I look up block, I think what we have to do there is essentially
put in sort of a suppression operations.
So when you query this thing, you might not get one back even though
you know that doesn't make any sense.
Well, it does because we're going to have to suppress any calls that
came from the debug system in the first place, right?
In fact, I guess there's maybe one other way we could do this now,
that I think about it.
Which is when we actually go to dispatch the event.
Right.
We could look to see whether this event came from the debug system or
not.
And if it did we just throw it out.
If it's a Memory op that came from the debug debug system itself,
right?
And the way to do that, I think I hope
alone on saying that.
Yeah, if the debug system calls something that's outside the debug
system that would work.
So I take it back.
I do think you want this right?
You want something which basically guards all of the calls on if
Arena, right?
and then, in here, where we actually
Find this stuff, right?
What we would do here is say, you know, if results.
Suppress.
Then it's zero, right?
And so what we would need here is we need the ability to set an event
that basically says this Arena cannot ever.
Look, don't ever let this thing do anything, right?
And so when we get this event here and we get the name back, we want
to do is probably also be able to set a suppression event here.
Don't ask me why I spelled that wrong.
Something like that.
So if we set that secret flag in there or something, then it will, you
know, allow us to suppress this Arena and stop recording the events on
it because
That's sort of hilarious.
I was like, wait a minute.
Even if we don't have any bugs in this system, it will still fail.
There is no way to record the recording system for memory because just
the act of recording it required the memory, right?
And so yeah.
So anyway,
I think that should be fine.
And then what we want to do is when we initially create the debug
Arena, we just need that Arena to be suppressed.
So, both fat, and the per frame Arena will always be suppressed.
And since there's only two of those, I don't actually know where the
per frame Arena comes into play here.
But we want to suppress that one too.
Even the that one technically is okay because since we don't allocate
from that one, we could still like track it.
I just don't want to because it's like where
That's in-store event there.
Yeah.
So so the per frame Arena.
I don't know where we.
We have to wipe that one out there to don't we like
how is that one?
Being used, exactly.
Shouldn't there be a place where we clear that.
Oh no.
So we don't really do that.
It looks like
So it looks like more.
What we do there is we do allocate from it with a store event but we
We just recycle.
So is there a reason why?
That's
Is there a reason why we even have that anymore?
Interesting.
So, we don't really need these two Arenas.
We only need one now, right?
I want to say,
can we just do this?
Because I think so.
Yeah, I mean I don't I think we can just get rid of it.
So let's just do that too.
While we're at it that just simplifies things, we only have to
suppress one Arena.
I'm a nobody cares.
I think.
I hope so.
Now we just need that suppression call.
And that seems pretty simple because it's basically the same call as
the name call.
And so, I think all we have to do here is just say Arena suppress.
And then this just needs to set the little secret Special Sauce.
Oops.
Right?
So, I think that would allow us to suppress those messages so that
nothing would actually happen there.
I hope.
Yeah, and so I think we're good.
Now those will all get named and then that one debug one would get
properly suppressed.
I think what's going on here?
Hold on a second.
Looks like we've got somebody who's doing.
Allocate their, that shouldn't be.
Who is it?
So I guess.
Yeah.
You know what though?
I guess the problem there is we still do have to sort of track them.
A little bit, we can't detract them entirely.
So we hat.
We do unfortunately.
Actually have to remember how many blocks there are because otherwise
we don't actually know.
Yeah, like we don't actually know who to suppress without tracking the
blocks, so I guess we do have to do a thing which basically says if
Arena suppress here and then everybody else actually still needs to do
all the same work that they were doing.
Right.
I think.
Block, allocate block truncate.
Not so much.
But everybody else, yeah.
Man, this is crazy.
If this ends up working out to be pretty psyched because this was a
nut.
So thing to try and do but you know, sometimes it's fun.
So that's all good.
So we just don't track the allocations, but we do track the blocks.
And the suppression should stop anybody from going crazy with that.
And you can see us now being stable here it looks like which is good,
right?
I'll see if it climbs to.
Hi there.
It should go for a little while and then level out.
once the debug system starts, recycling events,
and that's just climbing too slowly for me to even really tell.
So I'm going to go ahead and crank it in two,
02, and just so I can see if
What I remember is feeling is there.
Wait, where?
Where are we?
How come we're not showing up in here?
What the hay?
There we go.
It's a now.
We're nice and stable.
And in theory tracking all the memory.
So now we know exactly where all of our memory is and who allocated
it, right?
And so in theory, I want to say that then we can just go ahead and
take the profile.
Information.
Like we were doing here where we created like a profile group.
I feel like we can then just put, you know, like
Debug state memory group like this.
And so in the like profile Group by just say, like all right, make one
of these things where we're going to have a memory display that just
hangs around and does whatever it does.
And I like how we were, we actually didn't even have the macro for
that.
It's this system needs a cleanup someday.
It's close to being good.
Actually, it's not that far.
Just a few bad decisions that if you just undid them, it would be
pretty sweet.
So I think that we just need to
you know, be able to add to the
you're this this route Profile Event bit here.
I'm just not sure.
I know how you set that up because I don't remember how we were doing
it.
I'm going to look and see who actually mux with that and how they
could figure like what it's going to show, you know.
Look, I don't really know.
Like how do you tell that thing that you want to see like the frame
displaying stuff?
You know what I mean?
I have no idea.
It's all just as very unnecessarily complicated.
Cuz you know, like I want to be able to do that for the memory group
and I just don't actually know.
Like how did it know that here's the route group?
Here's the function group.
Here's the profile group, right?
The profile group is, what you would.
Viewing.
And somehow that thing knows.
What it should do.
But how did it know that?
Does it get somewhere?
Apparently not.
Yeah, so I just don't know how that ends up getting set because, like,
just to sort of explain what?
I'm not remembering about how we did this stuff.
I thought you needed to set a thing like this demo profiling thing,
right?
That's what this is.
What it sets when you want to.
Look at that.
when you want to look at that using the debug system, you know, it
just sets it here and then
That's what it.
That's what the the thing uses to determine what it should display.
Right?
That's how this thing works.
At least I thought, but maybe that's not true.
I guess I could look at debug mode profiling here and see what it
actually does.
But
So I guess this is how we did it.
Okay, so I guess if we want something here we would say like here's
the memory of you.
I guess.
and then here we could say,
I don't know what this.
Means.
Either.
Probably just a name.
I guess.
So I don't really know if this will work because this is weird.
And kind of stupid.
Yeah.
So what I want to do here, right?
Is I want to now have a way of viewing, what these are rinas, actually
are showing right?
What they're tracking.
and there's a lot of different ways that I can do that, but
I want to do first is just do a simple summary of you.
So if you look at what happens here, right, we've got like,
Top clocks list.
I don't know what debug memory info is.
So it's that element that just prints like, the basic information,
right?
Like if you look at the profile view, here's what we kind of stacked
up on their right.
And so those
Calls.
Create this thing.
That's the frame.
Slider.
That's the last frame info.
Probably here.
Although, I don't know what last framing for is because I don't know
which one that this is, if his last frame in, for a debug memory info.
I'm not sure.
And then the top clocks list is this thing right with these buttons on
it, that kind of shows us what the profile looks like.
And so, what we want to do is probably something similar to that for
our Arenas, right?
And so I think we can just yeah, the name came through there.
So I guess we want to see like,
Should I call this like I used memory or something?
I don't even know.
But what I should be able to do now is kind of just copy the thing
that list.
So like inside the debug system where we actually draw the top clocks
list or back on stuff, right?
um, so in draw top clocks list you can see
Where were sort of, you know, placing these pieces of information?
Like here, is all that stuff and the top clock list itself, we can see
here.
We create some buttons that allow us to like switch, what's actually
going on.
And we probably want that to be the case with the memory system as
well.
So I'm just going to go ahead and say that we probably do something
like this.
Right.
And I guess the graph.
There's the debug view profile.
Graph thing here.
We've already got one for Arenas so we should probably use it.
I don't know what we're going to store in there but probably
something, right.
And
So when we do this, debug memory, if you encounter this, we probably
want to put the stuff we want to have here.
So we can say like, you know, Arenas or like, you know, totals Arenas
frames or totals or something like that.
I don't know.
And then, in here, when we've got these debug types, instead of memory
info, we would do is say, like which ones we actually wanted.
So, where we say,
People type two big memory, info.
That's actually going to have like a couple different things.
So like this would be like debug type Arenas, debug type
Arenas like, maybe arenas by frame arenas, by Arena, right, or like,
memory by Arena memory, by frame memory by total,
By size.
Um, something like that and so that we could just have those work the
same way.
The other stuff works.
So in here, like get rid of that and just say, give me these sets
here.
and that way, we print this out, we would say like memory by Arena
by frame.
and by size,
You know what I mean?
All right and so we probably won't even those I'm already way over
time because I got kind of a little too into it but that's basically
all I want to do.
So here we would say like the memory by size or something like that,
probably maybe.
Ends up.
We'll just do a really basic one.
Now to see if we're if this thing's working at all and then next
weekend, we'll do it more fun version.
So let's go ahead and say that, I don't know what this is going to do
right now.
That's probably going to look at what arena were actually talking
about here.
So I'm going to leave that.
That route button out.
We probably will use it eventually.
But for right now, I'm not going to bother
and what we should see now is that if
Actually, look at the memory graph.
Well, that didn't actually
Do you even remotely what I was expecting?
How did it even draw that?
Who is calling draw Arena occupancy in the first place because nobody
should be.
Oops.
Okay, so, Arena occupancy.
Oh wait, did I do something stupid here?
I don't think I did.
That was actually different type.
So, that was actually something that was in here and just not used.
Right.
Which is nuts.
But okay.
So basically this
In the profile.
I totally just because there actually wasn't one of those Arena
occupancy needs to go away.
It's not a thing.
Yeah, so this whole thing needs to be saved for later is I guess what
I'm saying, right?
But that is kind of what I wanted.
So, I want this to sort of be what we would base the codon, right?
So we want to save it, I don't want it to go away.
There we go.
And so yeah.
We do actually want this stuff to do something eventually, right?
So now if I run it, I should get in the profile.
It should just be what it was before, which it does look like in the
memory subsystem.
I should just have these which I can pick now.
Unfortunately, that's actually switching me to a totally different
type because I didn't actually correctly make these.
So I want to actually have these set to memory by Arena.
Everybody frame.
Remember by size and then I do want this stuff to happen as well.
So,
Basically like this.
Still pretty much wants to happen.
I don't know what this value wants to do with its life, but probably
not much.
But these are going to be the things where we actually call out to
some function that visualizes the memory somehow.
And then yeah, I don't know what this is supposed to be.
Yeah and this stuff didn't mean anything anymore.
That's why we got rid of it.
Okay, I see.
All right, so that's just done.
So I think this is everything we need now.
So we've done all of the infrastructure we have all the information,
and we just need to do the visualizations now and we can totally see
what's going on with the memory.
In theory.
And so we can much like the one we did before we should be able to
like you know do it just like the profile where it comes up on their
right.
And so if we wanted to do memory by size top, clocks list is
basically, you know, it's basically what we want.
And so I feel like we should be able to do something where we kind of
know where we just use.
The same process.
Probably.
So like if I was to literally just just clone the sky, right?
and I don't know where the memory stuff was at the moment, but
so if here, I just said like okay,
Go ahead and do a truck, an equivalent, right?
Of this.
Sort of if I wanted to do the same thing.
I feel like I probably just could so we know how many Arenas there are
by doing the exact same thing we're doing here, right?
So we could say either Garena equals Arena you know give your state
first girl.
Arena Arena, ankles Arena next, right?
I mean, that counts, the arenas.
Same thing, but we can create the Sorting situation here.
We can walk through these.
We can do the Radix.
Sort exactly the same way as we were doing it before.
In theory, I think.
Yeah, and then I think we literally can just spin through these and
write it down.
So for every one of these arenas,
in fact, you know, this is literally exactly the same.
Bright for every one of these Arenas.
As we go, we just need to track the index here.
So for every single one of these, I think we just do the same thing.
We just say that we have a total amount of memory.
I don't know that the are 60/40 is to happen over the statistics.
It does though so
I think we just do the same thing.
We just say total memory equal zero.
Don't ask me what the f doing on there because it's a double.
But for each one of these, we just say like okay whatever the entry
element is that's probably this.
And then we just do the stats from there.
So the entry arena is just the arena with talking about.
We won't need this that all works.
We then say the debug memory lock
Or sorry, either.
Arena block.
And we don't really need to know.
I mean, we could sort on two different metrics here, I guess.
we can sort on the total amount of used memory versus the total amount
of
Allocated memory.
And so I guess the statistic here isn't necessarily all that useful.
For us.
I want to look at this.
Actually, no, that seems very useful.
So I'm going to use it.
So what we do here is we say, okay?
We're going to accumulate our debug statistic here.
For the min max sum average count situation, right?
I could keep two of them, one for used and 14 total.
I don't know which one I want to do or if I want to do both, but maybe
I'll do both.
So if I came through here and I said, what we're going to allocate
this, we're going to use for each block.
I know the total that's been allocated because I can just say that
the debug information keeps that explicitly, right?
It's the size allocated inside the block.
So I just
I just cute allocated and used as my to stats.
like so I think
that seems right to me.
Yeah, and so for each of these, I just need to do the actual
accumulation.
And so for the allocated one, it's just the size that was allocated,
which we always know.
And so here, we just have that for this one.
We actually need to do an interior Loop, right?
We need to say Arena, allocation
And in here, we just say go ahead and accumulate whatever that
allocated size was.
And I think that's all we need.
The total amount of memory allocated.
And the total amount.
Can also be tracked through the process by just doing it here, right?
so, the total allocated
and the total used can just be
Summed up, we probably shouldn't use two levels of statistics for
that.
I'm not sure why we don't, but we don't for the sort key.
What we want to do here is just take whoever is largest.
So
I guess it's goes in negative Direction so I guess we do want this.
We probably want allocated but we may want to do used as well for
later.
I don't know what you do.
The Radix sort.
I guess this is kind of doing printouts here.
Not sure exactly how that wants to work.
If the total time, it's 1 over the total time.
So this would just be like the total allocated, right?
But that's like the percentage so that's the percentage total
allocated percentage.
Clocks probably what it meant should be Pa, probably, now if we were
being pedantic about it.
So once we come through here, we should be able to do like
Like allocated mused.
Like so.
And we know the arena cuz we kept that information.
Again, the running sum, I don't know which one you want to do.
It's that's why it's a little confusing but we could use allocated for
now.
We then want to go ahead and put a, you know, sort of a way of
printing out, whatever this information is, which I don't really know
exactly how we want to do that.
But in terms of what we've got to show, we pretty much know, we know
like how many blocks there were which is I guess another thing we
should have probably counted.
In fact let's count that.
Oh wait, we do know that.
so, in here, the
Once on the debug statistic for allocated would tell us that.
So basically, what we would want to do, there is just say
Yeah.
Like you know even know how we want to show this it's kind of
complicated so we've got the arena name which you know may or may not
be something human-readable.
We hope it is certainly and then we've got a bunch of information we
can print out here.
How many blocks there are, all that kind of stuff.
So I don't know what we want to do with this.
Number four percent 10, you see why there or whatever?
But probably we just wanted to like the MB of the thing.
so we would say something like MB there and so we would say like the
allocated some you know, / MB
Oops.
That casted would give us a megabyte number it probably doesn't need
to be 10 long because how would you allocate that many megabytes?
So what we want to do with that is probably printed out in something
that's like you know nothing's going to be more than a couple GB even
in the most ridiculous scenarios.
So we're probably talking about something like a percent for their
right.
so then we've got our actual floating-point number, which is going to
tell us now,
What percentage of the allocations total in the system?
This was taking up, right?
And then we've got information, like, how many allocations there were
and how many blocks there were and stuff like that.
So we could do for those.
Like, we could say, the allocated count and the used counts,
I don't know.
I'm going to get rid of this for now.
But we probably do want to hover tooltip on that at some point.
That's off the block, my bad.
So the Radix sort needs Arena counts.
Same here.
And the PC PA.
All right, so let's just see.
Now if we've got anything resembling anything here, I don't know what
temp name is for but it was probably
For constructing the name of the thing which we don't actually use, we
just have the name now.
So if we go and let's take a look at what that actually displays.
Okay, well, displaying nothing was not what I was hoping for in case
anyone was wondering, but to be fair to me, if you want something to
draw, you have to actually call it.
And so, one of the things that
You'll learn about CPUs as if you never tell them to Branch somewhere,
it turns out.
They usually won't know, sometimes they still will, but usually they
won't.
So, let's try that one more time and actually try calling her
function.
This time, the debug element root elements is not actually something
we need.
So that should probably go away.
We do want the rest of this stuff, though, to be occurring.
So, yeah, we want that to happen.
If I go look, I want to see how we're calling top clocks list to make
sure basically the same way because we want this to be effectively the
same thing.
So, when we call Tops clocks list, we're calling it with the debug
State, the debug ID here, the layout elements boundary,
And the mouse pee from the layout and that's it.
If I go back here I'm just going to get rid of that root element
because that shouldn't be used.
We have the Arenas in a separate storage location.
I am so now let's see if we got anything.
We've got a problem with our print out.
Oh, and yeah, we sure do.
So I forgot to I said, present for but I didn't actually say
what it should print it as
where is that guy?
So that wants to be an unsigned value there.
One more time.
All right.
Mmm.
So looking at this stuff here, we should probably name the suppressed
one and we've got to that that didn't get names.
We might want to try to figure out how to associate the names of them,
but you can kind of see now more or less, probably exactly what you
would have expected, right?
You can see that the debug system tracks, like a lot of stuff so it's
eating up a ton of memory.
We don't care about that as long as it doesn't crash or sister or
something because
it's just debug the game itself is running.
In sixty nine megabytes of memory right now.
There's a frame.
There's a frame temporary storage.
That's sitting at two megabytes, but it's important to remember that.
This, we probably need some additional additional statistics tracking,
to actually know some of that information because by the time we come
back around, we met because it's constantly getting like used a little
and shrunk, back potentially, the two megabytes is
Is like what it ends on before it gets flushed for the next frame, but
it could have like used quite a bit more than that.
But anyway, so you can now see exactly what those memory layouts are,
and who's using, what memory and for what?
And this is exactly what we want to see.
We want to see basically.
We don't care about this buddy, but when we want to see, like
everything in asset storage, because the best possible scenario for
our game, is we just use
As much memory the machine as we can to store our assets and nothing
gets used for anything else, right?
No, Pig leanness anywhere else and so so there's our memory sort of
analysis there, right?
And so if we want to draw the Arena's, that would be more similar to
the thing where we're drawing like the frame layout and that would
show like who was doing what in each of those Arenas doing that.
I don't know.
How hard that would be?
I'll take a flying leap at it now.
So I going to say oh let me add to that suppress called the actual
name.
And so when we have in the debug interface
When we suppress the arena, I'm going to go ahead and give it a name
as well.
So in here, we do debug arena name.
I'm gonna do that, right?
And that way, we can properly, mark it as the debugger Arena and
that'll be good, right?
So let's see here.
Where the other Arenas are coming from that are still persisting.
I'm guessing maybe they're ones that are coming from like,
Maybe the platform layer.
I don't know, we'll have to go see who they're coming from, but it
should be pretty obvious eventually.
All right, so now we should see is like the debug one is properly
marked as debug which is fine.
And we may want to remove that one as well.
So,
We may want to have a toggle here that says, whether you want to see
that one or not and so that way you can look at your percentages
without debug sitting in their car like sort of crumpling.
Crunking it up.
Let's say, so what I want to do now is just take a flying leap at
putting in the occupancy version, just to see how it looks.
If we take a look at the profile version of this, so we've got the top
men.
Plus version, this doesn't need to be here, does it anymore?
No.
So if we look at how this one's working, we've got the thread
interval.
Graph is really the one we want to look at there.
And so I want to do the same thing as doing here and do like draw
Arena interval graph, or something.
And so, at draw top men list in here, I want to do the same thing that
I was doing there.
Only now it's called this and not that.
And then what I want to do is I want to go to that draw profile in
thing and I want to do the same thing, right?
So I want to
Take one of these profile bars things and like figure out how to get
these two working.
There we go.
So
if we're going to do this, we need to know how many lanes there are,
but the number of lanes there are is just the number of Arenas there
are right.
And so we could just make a thing that's like, how many Arenas are
there.
And the number of Arenas is this.
And we could even cash that value if we felt like it.
So for some reason we didn't want to Loop over them.
But so few of them doesn't matter.
and so this way we can just ask how many there are
and when we then go through and draw these, we've got the link out in
the lane height stuff, that would be bad base to the same.
So we could have said, get Arena count for the jig's debug State.
That'll produce the lane height for us the frame stuff.
so really what we would need this for is if you wanted to like zoom in
on blocks,
Or something.
And and honestly, that just doesn't seem particularly
Plausible to me.
I'm just trying to think of how you actually do this, because the way
that this works is you want to be able to like see the blocks and see
where the allocations are inside the blocks, showing just the blocks
at first, and then you click on a block and it shows you the block,
maybe that makes sense.
So I think maybe maybe that's what I should do.
I'll be honest.
That doesn't really make any sense to me anyway, because why would you
care about seeing the blocks?
The blocks are just a list of blocks like, who cares about that at
all.
So you really just only need to see the individual things.
And so I think what you want more is just to be able to pick a
particular Arena and then just see it's layout.
I mean, that's really all you need.
And so I think like honestly, we don't really need a drum memory bars
call here.
I can just go ahead and get this out in its entirety.
I think I want to say,
And then I'm going to dump that in here and we're going to take a look
at it.
So I think yeah.
Like we just want to know which Arena you're trying to view and maybe
we just draw those as a little like bars.
You can then click on assuming that you click on one we then see which
one it actually is, I guess.
That seems like the best thing.
Maybe, I don't know.
So maybe what I'll do first is, I won't even do that, right?
Maybe I'll just do a thing that's like look.
Maybe I'll do is I'll just draw like all the allocations as a bar.
In here and we'll just call it a day, right?
And we'll kind of figure out what we want to do after that.
So if we actually do this stuff in here, this is mostly all we need.
I think we don't need a depth.
Thing we just do that all of this goes away, I think.
And so really, we're just mainly talking about this stuff, right?
We're going to pull this, swell know, we kind of want this.
So what I want to do is for each Arena, I want to go through each
block.
Oops.
And then I want to go through each allocation.
then what I want to do is I just need a way of creating whatever the
rectangle is going to be for that, allocation
And if I just divided it up on Long, the screen, right?
I would have a bar and each chunk would be one of these allocations.
The problem is, I don't know how many allegations we have.
You know, if there's thousands of them, they're going to be too small
for you to actually get into one and pick.
But, you know, I could just have there be a zoom factor that you could
use to zoom in and out on them and maybe that's sufficient to solve
that
Problem.
But the other way to do it would be to actually use the full 2D space
and like actually sort of just stripe them in there.
And you draw like multiple rectangles if you would fill more than one
row or that kind of thing, right?
And so you know that does seem like something good.
Probably, I don't know.
using the color table here also would be good, but would probably just
do that by which,
In next we are on the actual allocations.
Probably.
Just guess.
So this would probably be something like this.
this part is the part, we don't really know exactly how
We're going to do it.
The lien index is just going to be whatever Arena you're in though for
now.
Right.
And then most of this stuff could closely can pretty much closely
resemble what we're actually doing here.
We don't need the getname bit.
I don't think.
I think you just want to see that grid because it's constructed for
just the name by itself.
So my assumption is you don't need that but I could be wrong.
So
yeah, so I think we don't need this.
We just need that.
That's what you wanted to know and you want to know what the allocated
size was.
Right?
So you want to know for this application, what were you actually
looking at here in terms of B?
So you want to know like exactly how many bytes there were in this
particular.
Allocation, we don't need that to be formatted out.
That way it can look like this.
so, assuming that we print that out,
I don't think there's any way to zoom on these
so, I think that's just a non-issue
So I think we're literally just looking at that.
And then for each of these, what we really just need to do is for out
where the heck, this thing goes right?
And so for each block, what we could do is just say, well maybe the
block, since we know the total size of the block, we just draw the
block and then draw the things inside the block.
Proportional to where they were.
Cuz that is the information that we needed, right?
And so we don't really know is how big the block should be.
I could count the number of blocks and do it that way or I could just
keep stacking blocks.
Until we run out of room, I don't really know.
That's a
That's a kind of weird situation.
I don't know the answer to maybe what we'll do is is that is exactly
that though.
So, will basically start the blocks off at like, 00 or something,
right?
And relative to the profile wrecked.
I mean in fact I suppose I should actually just do it that way, right?
So the profile wrecked Min EX
Profile.
Rekt.
Max.
Why is where this thing starts?
And each time we record a new block, we just like go to the next
Go to the next thing I could on here also say like which Arena it is
so we could say like arena name something like that.
So I can use a double string there, so we'd have like a reading name
and then the grid that it was and how many bytes was allocated for
that thing.
And then we just need to know like, for each block and I guess that
gets rid of the lane thing too.
So we wouldn't really be using Lanes.
We'd just be showing blocks, right?
And so, this whole thing would go away for the most part and we don't
care about that.
We just do this so we need to know like what the
Dimension is so we need to know like how big is a block.
And I'm guessing that that needs to be fairly wide, but not
particularly high, right?
So maybe we say, like we want the profile wrecked, like maybe we want
to get the width of the profile.
Rex
And then here we want to say something that's more like a fixed size,
right?
So you know I don't know what this is but maybe it's like you know,
just 20 high or something like that.
And so the get with here where we do Jimmy hmm.
Where we get the profile wrecked.
We just say look, we want to fit like you know, some number of blocks
across.
So we just divide by that number and that's the block Dimension.
So when we want to know how big a block is, we do it here.
We also know that since it's four wide, every for we could reset.
So I guess what we'd want to do with that is like block index, as
well.
And I suppose that means we also could just do it this way.
So when we do a block, we know where it is, we just say the block
can be constructed from a wrecked and Max effect.
We could just do it this way.
Here is the block.
That's the block wrecked on here.
We say we want to know like
we know what the dim is so we could really
Say wrecked.
We want recommending.
Damn?
Really?
Yeah, there it is.
So what we would do is we'd pass the dimension, which is this and the
upper side of it is just going to be whatever our current, why is and
then the block index.
Time's the dimension.
Right.
So that's how we would stack blocks up.
And we can make that a little bit better in the future.
We'll do some dressing on that as well but that way we have the block
wrecked and all we really need to do on the why is say like lock why
and that's going to start out with the profile wrecked Max, why right?
Um, so yeah, actually, sorry - blocked in y.
So it's, you know, the first row of blocks starting at the top.
Each time.
The block index goes up over for, though.
We now need to advance it.
In fact, I guess I'll do that the bottom.
I'll just say like, you know, Block Plus
Parking decks if block and x equals 4 block and x equals 0.
And then we do block, why reset right?
So we just move it down a row each time.
So then we would need for each allocation to figure out where it is
inside that block.
But after that, we're good, right?
So we really just need to be able to create a barycentric rectangle
out of this larger rectangle, right?
And we know what the proportions are because well first of all we know
that we're going to use the full height of the thing so that makes
that easy.
But in terms of what the percentage is like where we are inside that
rectangle, we know we've got like a sort of a
You mean in a team, Max, right?
And what those are is inside our allocation structure, we were already
storing.
What we need to know where in the block we are, we're storing the
offset From the Block and restoring the size allocated, right?
So we know that if we add these two together here, we have the max,
right.
And if we look at this one, we have the position.
And so all we really need to do is we need to have a scaling value
that's sort of the
Inverse of the size of the block will, he know what that is?
Because each block itself has its size allocated on it, right?
So, whatever that size allocated is, we could just say like in size
allocated,
And we can say, if the block Rex has any size allocated, which pretty
much always should we just go ahead and take the inverse of that,
right?
So then, every time we want to compute one of these, we just say all
right, convert it to an F32 and then actually just compute the ratio.
This tells us we're inside the rectangle, we are for this particular
thing.
We know the upper and lower bounds.
Those are obvious.
So we really just need very eccentric.
That makes me grumpy.
So hmm what do I want to do with this?
I don't really want to lose what I was typing in here because there
was a fair bit of it although I suppose what I could do is take a
screenshot of that.
The easiest way to do that.
Yeah.
That works.
I don't know how much I had there.
Can we show me where?
that was it should be errors there now,
So what is this function?
Draw Arena interval.
This is still here for no good reason.
All right, so we've got this stuff is still there but we lost our we
lost this guy, right?
So I should be able to type this guy back in here and go from there.
Toggle fullscreen.
There we go.
So, let's see.
Inside, toggle are sorry inside, Rupp Arena, interval, or drop-top,
man.
Members, I guess is where I'm starting there.
So draw Arena interval.
Debug state32 luck state that by DeGraff ID rectangle to profile Rex.
And the mouse pee.
All right.
And so do I actually need Alec index?
I do because I need to know what color it's going to be for Block.
Tim I need the with the profile wrecked.
I need the block index and I need the block.
Why?
Then I need to Loop over the arena.
And track the block.
Why?
That seems fine.
We may not have a get with on that.
I think it's just get dim.
Right.
Yeah, alright, so we create the block wrecked with got the in size
allocated.
Oops.
Do we have?
We have a safe ratio, right?
So it's really just that
So in this case, what we want to do is say well whatever the block
size allocated is that's what we're trying to do, right?
So that seems fine.
And then I just want to Loop through the allocations debug Arena
allocations.
And then the color.
The color table.
Like so our team in, we know what that is.
Arcamax, we know what that is.
And then this stuff we did do like this is nonsense code.
So we do need to do this part, but we need to compute the rectangle
first.
So we don't know what region wrecked is yet.
The base is e part.
Also, I don't think we need to do for this because we're not stuck in
things on top of each other at the moment.
The color in this case is probably, well, I can just grab this from
the existing code because that's how that worked.
Let me actually delete this temporarily and just in here, do a, if is
in rectangle region, Rex mouse key.
And then here, we'll just do a tooltip buffer text buffer, equals
wine,
And then we'll do the format string text Data, arena name.
This is actually the Alec would and the size allocated, okay?
So the I need to go and cut and paste the the region or at the park
there.
Right?
Also, this means of termination from that.
So in the drop profile in or bars or whatever the part where it's
doing this, we need to capture this part here.
The base is e is just stupid stuff.
I don't think we actually need that.
So I'm pretty sure that you can just get rid of this for now would be
my assumption like the way that other people are drawing stuff, right?
They don't need to do that.
And so, I'm pretty sure that that part is not so important, right?
Yeah, I mean I just I don't think you need any of this.
I'm not sure.
But I don't think you need it.
So I'm just going to get rid of it for now.
And then if we have to change that, I will change that.
So how are we doing here?
If we push these rectangles on and have a little party,
Is everything going to be?
Okay.
What else do we need to know?
So, render group region wrecked.
You.
I so those things we need to get out of the debug State I assume
Yeah, so this stuff has to come out of the debug State.
What else?
We need?
So then I think we're down to just the barycentric version and so I
think yeah, it looks like we did this already.
So the barycentric version is good because it means we can just sort
of get the Min and the max is that we actually need
so, what we should be able to do here is say, hey,
Give me.
The rectangle min-max.
Let me go ahead and get those out here.
So let's get them in.
And Max like this.
So we have this block wrecked.
And what I want to do is get the Bary Centric location inside that
rectangle.
And the way I want to do that is
you know what, I guess I don't even really need to put these there.
I could just do this.
Right.
So the first things first from getting the minimum the X minimum is
going to be the team in the Y minimum is just going to be zero.
The maximum is going to be the max we computed and 1.0 so because we
want the full height of the thing, right?
And so at that point, I think that gives us our region Rex which is
what we actually want and then we're good, right?
All right, so, I don't know if this will actually work or what, we
probably won't be very good, visualization.
And but we can make better one next week so inside Arena, and of
course, I should remember to call.
I did remember to call it before, but then we crashed.
And so now I have to remember again.
So I think we want to just call draw Rena interval there and then, you
know, we don't have the frame version of this yet but that's okay.
Not reassuring.
Say the least.
So I'm not sure what the air is there.
It could just be that we're not placing these things correctly or
something similar to that, right?
When we're actually creating these like blocks, it could be also that
we are going.
I don't know which way our stuff goes as things to send.
I was assuming that y was going up but maybe why is going down?
I don't remember how we wrote this system, so that's one of those
things that could easily do.
Let me just take a look here.
You know, it's you can see it here, it's going down like that.
So I think when we get the dimensions of the profile wreck and we do a
y IO but that is not correct.
It's the maximum that we actually want.
Right.
Oh no, no.
I'm that's supposed to be the X.
First of all the block, why is the max?
Why - the black team that seems right?
The block index here is getting incremented, isn't it?
No, it's not so that would also be a problem.
How about that part?
So I think that's all good.
We should probably also draw the block itself here.
Just has like a gray like backdrop thing, maybe like this.
Um,
And then I messed up into this and just see why it's failing to
produce any actual trouble regions.
Okay, so kind of a little wonky.
What's going on there?
But the block wrecked at least is drawing that looks like it's drawing
itself now.
So I wonder if there's just something stupid that I'm doing here.
We've got a recommend dim and a strong.
It's going to draw this.
It should be a quarter of the size of the profile wrecked.
It didn't seem to be changing size.
So that seems bad.
Something seems a little bit busted there and I don't know what.
So we have to step in there and see.
we could make sure that we're passing the right size there, but
But it looks like we are, right?
So there's the layout elements bounds, so that feels like that should
be fine.
So I'm not sure why we're getting that kind of weird Behavior.
So let's step in there and take a look.
Just get a feel for like, what's actually being drawn.
This is turning out to be a totally Marathon session.
So inside, I want to bring this up first so we can take a look at it.
And I'm just going to go ahead and look at the Arenas.
So, if I now set a breakpoint inside drawer an interval there.
What's going on, right?
So as we come through here, let's just look at what our all our
variables are.
Just we know whether we're in complete nutso town or not.
That seems reasonable so long as our center.
It's almost the middle of the screen is 0 0, which maybe it is, you
know I don't remember how we set up the coordinate system that seems
fine that doesn't seem totally bizarre anything.
How big should each of our blocks me?
Again seems totally fine.
Okay.
So first of all, yeah, this is wrong because we're not we're not
offsetting by the profile wrecked corner.
So that's definitely wrong.
Let's see.
What else is wrong?
That's probably the only thing that's wrong though.
So the so let's see the block wrecked.
I mean, the rest seems that all seems pretty reasonable, right?
The Serene apparently has no allocations in it whatsoever.
That seems bad.
How are none of these having any allocations in them?
What?
We must have some kind of a bug in there.
Which arena is this pain away?
Oh well, I take it back.
The debugger Arena that is what you expect to see because the blocks
can't have any actual data in them because it's suppressed.
We should also not draw them.
I was going to say that's nuts.
We did something wrong, but we didn't do something wrong.
That's what's supposed to happen.
Let me also while I'm recompiling there, let me add the profile
recommend mm corner.
I just said we're off set properly out, that's going to help, but
It'll at least Center the thing properly.
For now, I want to actually see what's being drawn before I start to
building.
all right, so
Now we're at least properly sizing but by properly, I mean, it doesn't
seem like we're ever actually advancing the block though.
So that's a little bit weird, right?
But this block index should be moving the rectangle along.
And it does not actually appear to be.
But I'm not sure why that would be.
Yeah, I don't see it.
So, let's step through there, see why we're only drawing, what appears
to be a single rectangle and it's the wrong size, right?
So it's supposed to be a quarter of the size of the profile wrecked,
but it's like a half the size.
Although we could be drunk two, rectangles only and then not drawing a
third, which would produce what would amount to the same result.
What I could do is outline these as well, which I probably should do.
Something like this so that they have a little bit of an outline
around them just so we can see whether or not that's happening.
I don't know, we'll find out.
Just make sure that's built.
All right, so now we've got
So, were there's two of them that are being drawn.
And then we don't know why, we don't know what else is happening.
So we want to go now set that break point and see why.
So, if I come in here, we start out with block index 0
We suppress this entire thing.
So I guess I probably have to do this to get to the first unsuppressed
one.
We've produced a block rectangle for this entire block.
Looks pretty reasonable.
The Z on this is wrong.
So should probably make these so they can draw over these.
But that's a separate issue.
We haven't addressed yet.
So, this is not good at all.
This recommend Max.
Oh, wait a minute, wait a minute, wait a minute, wait a minute.
So get Bary Centric, does the opposite thing that I thought it did.
So get barycentric.
Actually computes the barycentric coordinates
I guess we don't have one that gives them back to us.
Like, when we put one in, we get back with the location, would have
been using that.
That's okay.
Again, the problem still is that our block works or wrong.
So I'm not so concerned about this part of it yet, but for what it's
worth, it's a pretty trivial fix.
We just want to do a linear interpolation here.
We want to take the block wrecked Min X, our team, in the Brock
wrecked, Max X, and then the Min, why?
And maybe I'll still do this.
Just to make it a little easier to read.
So that is the correct way to actually still hanging around.
That's what we were trying to do.
I wanted to sort of do a bilinear but I guess we don't really have
that.
So we kind of just have to make do right?
So I think we're fine otherwise.
I feel like I could have used that.
We do have a V2 version of this so I suppose I could have done that
but who cares?
I'm so, finally, I think that that was probably, our problem is why we
weren't getting actual memory ranges drawn in there.
But the problem again that we're going to have is that we're still
like the block reaches themselves.
The throng.
And so we have to step through and find out what's going on there.
I don't know what's happening there so when we step through here, we
should now have region rex that correspond more probably.
Yeah, exactly.
So that's much better.
And then what we need to know is
is when we
When we actually get down here, right?
And we increment that we should now.
See that block index.
Changing right.
How many of the virus?
So many of those suppressed.
Did you see that?
What's going on there?
Hold on a second.
How the heck is suppress set to 1 on the game mode?
I must have done something stupid somewhere else, too.
I bet you I bet that's just garbage right because we didn't fill it
out so that that was also about that was getting set to suppress.
Because we don't want to clear things in the debug system.
We wanted to be as fast as possible, so that was probably what was
happening there.
Alright, let's check it.
Check it one more time.
All right.
This is kind of nonsense.
I don't know what this is supposed to be.
Or actually that's kind of correct.
Those would all be fixed size, drunks.
So now that's looking mostly correct.
Actually I'm going to go ahead and change this back to regular build.
I think we're pretty close.
I'm going to probably call it a day now because we've done a ton of
work but I think we're at the point where we can now visualize our
memory allocations correctly.
Interesting.
You know, this is going to be pretty cool once we kind of get it, more
dialed.
Anyway, let me show you the thing.
I was actually trying to show you
so, here's the
Out of the world's with the extra bloating in it right those are all
the world chunks and what started us down this whole Rat Hole
yesterday where I was like I want to visualize the memory was inside
the entity struck time.
Like we want to start paying attention to this stuff and I was just
trying to make a point.
I was like I don't have any way to visualize it so this ground cover
here.
Let's say we don't have ground cover in there.
Right.
So there's no storage for ground cover and then I run this thing and I
look at the memory visualization, right?
Look at how big the block of memory is taken up by our entire world
is, right.
Remember that?
What is it?
1 2 3 4 5 6 7 8, 9 10 rows, 11, rows long, right?
I come in here and I add the ground cover in to these entities.
and now,
It's massive.
Right.
It's like twice that size.
1 2 3 4 5 6, 8 9 10 11 12 that right, furthermore, we could just look
at this number, right?
It's sixty nine megabytes.
And then we look in here.
And it's 47, right?
So just that one member is just way ridiculous in terms of its impact
on our footprint.
And that only goes up because every entity we added the world would do
it.
And so, I just wanted just to be able to show that what that kind of a
difference was.
Tyler founder, but there you go.
We will fix
that visualization to be better.
Later.
Hey, the mouse is working on Linux today.
That's a first
All right, let's go to extremely brief Q&A because I my throat is
tired this point, but now we've got the memory of is in there and we
can make it better.
Because right now, it's not really proportional.
So we kind of want that to be fixed.
On top of it all.
But could you just say hi to my friend, Thomas Grimm, who was a
fervent follower of yours?
so Thomas Grimm is a very, I feel like that is the kind of name that
You want to be an author of gruesome, children's books, right?
I mean that's what you always think of, when you think of Grimm, like
Grimm fairy tales.
Do you write children's literature would be my very first question.
And is it sort of somewhat gruesome?
All right.
No questions is good because we've been on here for a while.
So, I'm going to go ahead and close it down.
All right, thank you for joining me for an episode of handmade hero,
very long episode of Hannah here.
It's my pleasure coding with you, as always, if you'd like to follow
this with the series at home, you always pre-order game on hand.
Me here at org comes to the source code.
You could go make it better memory.
Visualizer we've done all the groundwork now, so that might be kind of
a fun little challenge if you're interested because like, the one that
we just threw in there, it's not even proportional to the size
correctly.
So like although it divides the
Upper block, it doesn't divide.
Stuff up for the total amount of memory being used and so we're going
to make a better one than that to be sure.
And you could be this to it, you have all week to make some better
memory visualizers in there using the data that's in there, do
something cool I'll be back next week to do some myself and and we'll
see what happens.
Until then have fun programming and I'll see everyone on the internet.
Take it easy, everybody.