Hello, everyone, and welcome to handmade hero.
The show where we code a complete game live on stream.
No engines, no, libraries.
And a lot of people ask me, they say, Casey how are you able to talk
while you are programming?
I find it's really hard to do that and the answer is that actually
it's really easy to talk while you're programming if you
Up all the programming.
So today we have our friend, the owl of Shame here to tell us a little
something about multi-threading that Casey totally didn't do yesterday
and which we absolutely have to do if we don't want to have kind of an
ugly situation arise in our code,
I knew you were going to get me one of these days.
I'll I see you looking at me over there all the time.
Anyway, let's let's take a look at this at this particular piece of
Shame here.
This is I think the first really legitimate L is shame.
The al-sham doesn't appear that often but he appears once in a while
but this one is like I think absolutely like it's an incontrovertible
Al of Shame, whatever that means.
Like if ever there was a time like no one, I think we'll ever argue
that.
This is not it.
Appropriate time for the Isle of Shame.
So here we are in the thread code, right here, we are in the Superfund
thread code.
And what we see right here is that I check to see whether or not the
entry count is less than xn fee to do.
And if it is, then I go, I'm sorry, I check to see if they actually do
is less than the entry count.
Meaning, is there anything in the Q?
And if there is, I take something off the queue.
I never actually check to see whether there's another thread that may
have come in here.
And stolen something off the queue.
I wrote this.
And this is actually literally, what I was thinking.
The entire time to I wrote this as if it was single producer, single
consumer, but this is single producer multiple consumer which means
multiple people could be doing this interlocked increment, which means
this code is totally bogus.
Right.
So that is a definite out of Shame.
And it's kind of a double Olive shame because the very first thing I
said, when we talked about multi-threaded coding, I set it on the
stream.
I was like what we should do is we should use interlocked compare
exchange because it lets you do the right thing easily.
Instead of trying to be clever, I said that.
And then later I was like oh I'll just show how to use interlocked
increment here and use that instead.
Well, guess what?
That was.
Totally not acceptable because interlocked increment is not going to
work in this fashion.
Because two threads could get here at the same time both who have
already done this check and then both who increment and now one person
finds that they have a number which is actually outside the bounds of
the queue already right and how does that work?
Now the whole scheme is borked.
So, we do not want to do that.
That is totally not.
Okay, right, instead?
What we would much rather do is we much rather use an interlock
compare exchange, right?
Because that will prevent us from making this error.
And we don't even have to think hard about it.
Like, we don't have to be clever and that would keep us from being in
bad shape, right?
So, interlocked compare exchange, here it is, we talked about it
already, you give it a destination, right?
And you give it a thing that you want to put in that destination.
And you give it this extra thing called compare and write or
comprehend.
I don't know you pronounce that.
The thing you're comparing two is what it means, right?
And as you can see here by the description, it's like
Paris.
The destination about the compare end, if the destination value is
equal to the comparing value, The Exchange value is stored in the
address specified.
Otherwise, no operation is is performed, right?
And so the long here, right, it returns, whatever the value was that
was there at the time.
So what we can do if we want to is we can do this check and say o is
the Q.
You know, what's up with the cue is it, is there anything in the
queue?
And then we could do interlock compare exchange, right?
Same exact code where we just say, Okay, do an interlocked compare
exchange that will actually return us the index that we should use
right?
And then what we want to actually pass in, there is whatever next
entry to do was before, right?
So this is like original next entry to do right here we go.
So assuming that that is less than the Q count.
We do the interlock compare exchange.
We want to put in there, right?
We want to put in their original, like why could I not?
Why did that not indent indent emacs indent
There we go.
I had an extra parentheses in there so you do not compare exchange.
We say Okay I want to take this memory address.
I want to replace what is there by incrementing the value by 1, right.
And then what I want to do is I want you to make sure that the value
that's actually there is the one that I thought should be there.
So I know that nobody else came in here and incremented it right?
Then I just go.
Oh okay, if I happen to be,
The situation where the index that I got back, right, equals the one
that I thought it should be then, I know, we're okay, right?
But if I get back a different index, then I know that another thread
has beaten me to the increment and I should not do anything, right?
I should not do anything.
So that's what we actually want to do.
And I would set result is valid equal to false there.
Right now, we've got a little bit of extra work to do when we do this
because that means now there's a case where we could fail even when
there actually is work to do, right?
So, what we could do here, I think this will simplify out a little
bit.
I think this will actually simplify things more, but we actually do
need to do as well.
Write is, we need to basically Loop over this.
If we want to maintain how this particular,
Function actually worked right, but we don't actually have to do that
because hold on a second.
I want to grab out the render group.
We change the API at the end of last last stream and we actually don't
want it to work.
The way that I had factored it quite yet.
I was kind of sort of pulling things out into a platform nonspecific
way, but then we decided to just do it this way.
We decided that what we wanted was just an add entry and a complete
all work, right?
That's
We actually wanted to have happen.
so what I'd like to do,
Is go ahead and pull, you know, basically restructure things to make
them into this structure so that they're working off of this, which
they almost are at the moment.
But just get it restructured and then go and worry about actually
cleaning this up.
But hopefully everyone understands my shame Al situation there.
Right basically I was counting on the fact that I was only having one
thread that was D queuing.
Which coincidentally, the reason I was thinking about that is because
The thing I was thinking of, in my head was a time when I wrote an
asset loader, which had a background thread, and it would just sit
there waiting for stuff to be told to do.
And in that case, interlock increment Works quite nicely because you
have to worry about that, right?
But when you have multiple people who are all looking at the same
queue, interlock compare exchange is way better because it allows you
to very simply without having to really do anything more fancy.
It allows you to very simply go.
Okay, just here's what I think the value was and I did.
All my preparations assuming that this was the value.
And now we're going to go for it.
But if that value is not what's in there, then, just don't do it,
right?
So you don't have to worry about the fact that no matter what you, you
don't have to worry about the fact that the operation that you're
about to do is always going to complete.
You can abort it, basically, which is kind of nice.
It's a little bit like that.
Transactional, memory stuff in a sense, it's like transactional,
memory for one single, for one single value, right?
Rhonda almond milk today and it's pretty delicious.
All right.
Okay, so let's see if we can wrap this up here, because I'd like to
try running the renderer today if possible.
So let me see if I can go ahead and wrap this up so that we've got the
renderer working in the way that that I suggest that I wanted to work
when I kind of wrote out this API here, right?
So what
To do here is we're going to say that there's a call to the platform
layer, that allows it to add an entry to Q, right?
And so we're going to go ahead and say that, you know, you pass a work
queue in here, here's the queue.
And then you pass in.
There's a, some kind of a function and the function signature, I
guess.
Just looks like this.
Maybe it also gets the queue that it was working on Just for
completeness sake and then it takes some kind of a pointer and that
pointer is
That pointer is whatever the program, whatever.
The program wanted it to be for like data, whatever the thing should
be using, basically.
So that's what we're looking at.
Here are so we essentially have a typedef, right?
We've got a function signature called do work queue or work queue.
Callback something like that.
Which is something where you can kind of register and say, okay, come
give me, give me slices off of a thread or something like this, right?
And what I want to do is say, okay, we'll take that call back as part
of the work queue Edition, and we'll take the data that we're going to
pass to it and that will be how we add entries to the list, right?
And a work queue entry storage.
Therefore will just be whoever should have been called back, right?
Like the Callback and whatever the data pointer should have been,
right?
So it's just going to store those two things.
That's all it's going to do.
So, when we want to add entry, right?
It's going to be just exactly this code that we already wrote.
So that's all good.
We've got this at entry here.
It's going to do all of the same stuff and remember, only one person
at the moment can write to it.
If we wanted to, I guess it would be possible to make it so multiple
people could write to it all, we would really have to do.
There is again, use an interlocked compare exchange on the entry
count, so I'll add it to do here.
basically, like switch to interlock compare exchange eventually so
that any thread can add
Because maybe we want to just try that out and see if that works,
okay?
Because if it does then you know we could just allow people to add
work cues from any thread that they want to.
Maybe that's a little too crazy but you know we could try it if it
gets crazy and we get bugs, and it's crashy and weird or whatever,
you're not to do it, you know, he's back up anyway.
So this adds the entry in Here and Now what we need to do is we need
to make sure again that we write all of that entry information before
we
And the entry count.
So what I want to do here is I want to grab out that work, you entry.
I go and grab the work queue entry.
That is the the one in question.
I, then set its data member to the one that was passed in.
and it's call back member this
Have to be here anymore.
And it's callback member to the one that was passed in as well.
So we're really just copying those two in there.
So, there we go.
So we copy those in there.
We make sure that they're written out.
We then increment and technically, I guess we don't really need this
anymore because we have read that Visual Studio will treat the S fence
as a right barrier, but I'll even both in there because it can't hurt
so, okay, we've got the queue entry count.
We're going to increment it, then we increment the semaphore.
That should be all we need to really do.
For add entry now.
I guess, this stuff right here is going to start giving us errors, if
I don't start piping it through.
So let me go ahead and actually pipe it through.
Let's see here.
So we got a platform work you render queue.
So let's go to handmade platform.
And when we pass in the game memory here, I guess, maybe what I'll do
is, I'll stick some work cues in here.
So we'll basically have a platform work queue the platform work.
You will just have the render queue for now and we'll leave that like
so.
And when we compile this, then we will actually need to I guess have
that definition.
Of course, we're not going to Define this is going to be blind.
So I guess I'll just go ahead and do struct Platform.
Work you like so or not.
That's right.
We're going to have to have a pointer there mmm-hmm because I have
this thing where I'm calling off of it.
Well, that's okay, that's no big deal.
Because we have to find a way we want to be able to
Get this function essentially because we're calling back the platform
layer and we want to have some way of being able to know what that
call is.
Now, I suppose we could make that some kind of a thing that just gets
assigned, like a global variable kind of a situation and really, we
could do that for anything that we want everyone to be able to call.
Because it would be nicer if we could just do this, right?
And that way, this is completely blind thing that the operating system
can the platform America defined.
However, it wants, which I think I prefer.
So, I think I may leave it that way for now, like so.
So, will basically have a platform at entry
And platform complete all work.
And we'll just have those be some things that are globally defined in
handmade .h, right?
So, in handmade .h, essentially, everyone will able to use them.
They're just Global because there's only one possible, one, they can
never call and it'll just be set by the game layer.
So that seems fine to me.
I don't have problems.
So this is a global variable.
It's going to be platform at entry.
It's a pointer to that function.
We also have platform complete all work.
Like so.
And so, we'll get those pointers.
Will get those pointers from the handmade platform.
So again, anything that calls back, right?
Anything that calls into our platform layer, we need to actually pass
into the game because that's just how we structured things basically
all of the platform Services get passed in at startup time.
We don't have any implicit finding stuff that happens with the
operating system or anything like that.
So we're going to go ahead and do these two here which means I need to
type
If these two guys, right?
Like so.
There we go.
And really, it looks like these only take some very rudimentary stuff.
It takes a platform work queue.
It takes a one of those functions.
Let's take a look at put that in here, but I got to hoist that out.
There we go.
So this is a platform work.
You call back.
So platform, add entry takes a platform work, you call back.
And it takes a void star.
There we go.
People were saying that was a good ship named.
It was actually a company named.
There is a company called void star.
I don't know if anyone knows that it's true.
So, all right, so we've got our type dips here for operating on the
work cues and that's really all we need.
I think that's basically it.
So over here, we got the platform work to call back.
We've got platform call back, there we go.
And I think we typically have a prefix these things with win32 so we
know which ones we're dealing with.
So we've kind of got a win32 add entry in a win32.
Well this is going to have to be a win32 complete all work I guess.
Like so.
So yeah, so I don't really know.
I mean, this is the tricky part, right?
I think we probably want to work cues like maybe like a high priority
queue and a low priority queue or something like that.
I don't really know, right?
So I think maybe what I'll do here is say that this is the like high
priority queue or something so it's like everything comes off.
This is like high priority stuff and then we'd have like another
That we would use maybe in the future for lower priority work.
I don't know.
I'm that's totally speculative, but I
I want to make sure I don't want to like fences in or anything.
So I just kind of want to make sure that we have the ability to do
that.
So I'm going to make sure that these always talk about a specific Q
all the time.
Just so the platform layer knows which Q you're talking about.
I think I feel a little more comfortable with that happening.
All right, so we've got 13 to complete all work and that's got to
basically be
You know, this, this is actually not what this is.
We're gonna we're gonna have to refactor some of this stuff a little
bit.
It's going to massage it around a little bit.
So what we need to do here is we need to kind of take this stuff that
we had like, the thread proc, right?
We need to take all this stuff and we need to factor it out so that we
can make it work with the API that we had.
Right, that we want, because we figured out how everything needs to
work, but we need to make sure that that we, that we can actually do
it, right?
And we can actually do it in the way we want.
So, when 32,
We all work.
I don't know why work queue entry completed that I didn't mean to do
that state.
This is just a void, right?
Yes.
So I'm going to go ahead and down here, I'm going to say that this
code right here, right, which we were used to be doing which waits to
see to it, you know which basically does the sort of like do work from
the queue until all of the work has been done, right?
I'm going to say that that is when three to complete all work, right?
Because that's essentially what that is.
So when three to complete all work right with that has to do, is that
us to sit there and do this check right?
Which just go ahead and
I'll make it right in line again because we only pulled that out
because I was thinking like, oh, maybe the platform layer will call it
but in this case we don't have that problem anymore.
So I'm just going to let that be inlined and remove this.
So while you know, while the intricate is not equal to the completion
count, meaning while there's still work to do right then we can can do
that.
Do that work.
And what I want to do here is I want to structure this so that the
other call that we have basically this win32 complete all work, just
like it was doing before, can share the do worker work stuff with the
with the thread proc, right?
So whatever the thread proc does will be the same.
Okay.
So in other words, these two functions here want to be able to do
exactly the same thing.
So this guy wants to be able to figure out if there's an entry in the
queue to do and if it is he does it otherwise.
Well, I guess he just keeps spinning actually, right?
So really we want to do here.
It's like do next work queue entry.
I think that's really all we have to do.
I don't think we have to break it out anymore.
So we can just do do next work.
You entry while the entry count is
Correct.
It will do it, right?
Because this is the live thread.
The one that's just going to keep going.
And then all the other threads, what they're going to do is they're
going to say oh okay.
I want to do the same thing.
Do the next work queue entry and if do next work queue entry returns.
Let's say just returns true, then we go to sleep.
So basically, it will tell us whether to go to sleep or not, right?
That makes sense.
So that's it.
And that's really it.
So we could
We could get rid of this as well.
There we go.
And so I think that's again, much cleaner now, right?
So win32 do the next work.
Queue entry win32 - no next,
Oops.
Q entry.
Yeah, the red info cute.
And then in the future, you know, we can make this so that it tries to
do work from either Q, right?
Right, you could imagine.
Us doing something where we did win three to do next work queue entry.
And if that and went through to, you know, other Q, right?
We could pull from multiple queues here and we always pull from this
one first blah blah blah.
So we could we could extend that to work with the multiple threads
pretty easily, I think.
So okay.
With three to do next.
Work queue entry, all that stuff.
Seems reasonable to me.
So what I'm going to do now is I'm just going to write this function
out of the pieces that we have before, which is actually pretty close
to what we originally had to do.
So we're kind of back to where we started, which is good.
I find that I do that a lot.
Sometimes I go on a little diversion and I learned something or I see
this not quite what I wanted, and I pull back and it's good.
So yeah.
Don't ever be worried about that sort of thing.
That's kind of the essence of programming.
It's very hard to foresee things.
So you want to kind of play with them, until you can see it coalesce.
And then you're like, okay, yes, I'm sure this is good now.
And again, you could kind of see how I did that.
I went over to write the usage code and that really educated me,
right?
It was like, oh right, this really could be done, very simply on this
side by just doing this so, you know, maybe that's what we should do.
And it turns out that I think that's going to be good.
So again, the usage code is always a great guide, it's always
something you should look to when you're like, I don't know what the
design is here.
Here, let me see what the usage code is.
Almost always the right decision.
All right, so in do next entry here, obviously, we don't have to do
this completed as valid interlocked increment thing anymore.
We can actually do that down in here, right?
So we don't have, we don't have to worry about any of this stuff.
We don't have to worry about this guy anymore, which is nice as well.
And we could actually now name this actually work queue entry which is
actually kind of nice.
So this is
Merc Q platform work.
Queue entry.
Like some on platform.
Work queue entry.
There we go.
So yeah, platform work queue entry.
Starting to look okay, I should probably go fix this stuff first house
so I can actually compile.
All right, so in here, where we at, where are we at platform?
Work queue platform were cute.
Rick you call back are both defined.
Are they not what we need a little void in.
There we go.
What is the problem?
Why are you complaining?
What are you complaining about?
Typedef void platform work.
You call back and that is correct.
Typedef.
Void platform, add entry.
oh,
so good spelling.
There we go.
So platform add entry cannot convert argument to, from odor load
function platform.
Work you call back.
Is that really true?
What is the problem here?
Let's see and handmade out H.
We have added platform, add entry and platform complete all work, so
that's good.
In handmade H, we have platform at entry, should take a cue, it should
take a call back and it should take some data.
Oh, it's because this guy is not thing.
So, here is where I would like to use the macro again.
People don't really like the macro version.
So I wasn't going to do them for these two guys, but you can kind of
see why this is Handy if we're going to start to have these.
So I want to do this.
Least for this guy platform work, you call back and you give it a name
and then it does.
This guy look so right.
And that way I can do it much more succinctly here.
I can say typedef platform work.
You call back and do it like that.
So, I've got my typedef in there.
and now I can make sure that everyone always does this stuff properly
now,
I probably want to do internal here.
All right?
Like so
There we go.
All right, so I think this can now go away, right?
That disappears.
Go.
And now, we just have to make sure that we actually pass this render
crew Q through and so infill, ground chunk.
It would need to take the cue to use right for this.
And we can totally just store that in our game state or anything else
that we want to in our transient state so we can just use the
translate for that.
For example, we can just do trance State render queue look so on and I
can also do that in the exact same way over here.
No, not there.
There we go.
And state render queue.
And then in the transient State, I'll just go ahead and stick that in
there.
Render queue.
Oops, platform.
Work here.
Render queue.
Compilations process is running.
Kill it.
Yes, I don't know why.
That was asking me that okay.
So now I just have to kind of avoid some of these guys out here.
I shouldn't say hoist them out, but actually, like copy them out.
So when we come in right, if we're not initialized, we want to do a
couple things here.
First of all, if we're not alishan initialized, we want to take
platform, add entry.
And we want that to be equal to memory platform.
At entry, we want to do Platform, finish all work.
We want that to be copied out as well.
And then finally, in the trance State, when we initialize the
transfer, transient state,
Right?
We want to make that have the render queue be in there.
Trance, State render, Q, equals memory, lender Q, right?
I think it was hype called high priority queue.
So, there we go.
So now we just have to finish porting out this stuff.
So we have to do Platform work queue here and make sure all of this
stuff is that way.
It is boiling hot.
In here, by the way, this room gets hot with the computers in the
summer.
It is going to be a sweating Casey.
All right, so
Now we just have win32 do next work queue entry.
Like I was saying before we do our interlocked, compare exchange, we
figure out what index we want to do, assuming that there was one that
we wanted to do now with three to do next.
Work entry, we are now counting on this guy to basically return true
if we should sleep, right?
So we should sleep is going to be false and we're going to return.
We should sleep like, so on.
And the only time that we know that we should sleep
Is if we actually saw these things being equal, right?
We're just like, okay,
if we saw these things being equal, then we should sleep.
Otherwise, we should not sleep because either we did some work, right?
Or we week like tried to do work with somebody else narked us.
And we don't actually know what the state of the queue is.
So we should try again, right?
So we want to make sure that we only sleep when we absolutely are
positive, right?
That we absolutely super double plus know for sure what's going on.
All right, so I'm gonna go ahead and dequeue this entry here, right?
I'm going to say, grab out the entry.
That's in the queue at that location.
you know, the one that was that we were on, we're going to go ahead
and actually dispatch there
So, when I do the dispatch, I should probably actually do a read write
barrier here.
And mmm fence.
And the reason that I say this is because the code that's operating in
here.
Probably, we want to make sure had the opportunity to finish all of
its rights before we keep going.
So I suspect we probably want that.
I could put it to do in here.
This is a double check, this isn't problematic performance wise but
I'm pretty sure there's no way it could be.
Oh no, you know what?
I don't have to do that because interlocked increment.
Does that fence for me, right?
So never mind, interlocked increment, does the fence that we need,
okay?
So we're fine, we're already automatically fencing, so it won't
matter.
So what I want to do now is I got to do the call back, I gotta do the
Callback, passive, the queue, and pass it, the data that it wanted,
right?
And that's basically all I think that we needed to do.
Now, we just have to go make sure that we can fix all the rest of the
stuff that was like our test code and whatever.
So here we go, platform work queue.
There's the queue nothing.
Weird happening their platform.
Go, we don't need that.
More.
All right.
Let's see when 32 thread info platform work.
You, that's looks all fine.
Work.
You entry do worker work.
So, do work.
Our work is now going to take a void Star, right?
Data will actually I'll just use the this use the macro that I made.
So here's our do worker work, which is just our little test function.
Internal.
And that is just going to print out whatever we have.
We don't know the logical thread index anymore.
Unfortunately, although we could actually have that passed in
In fact, why not?
I guess there's really no reason not to well, let's, let's
Let's let's chill on that for a second.
Well you know what?
For our test code we totally could do it this way.
In fact.
And for our test code, let's go ahead and do this.
Get current Red ID.
So, get current thread ID will at least give us a thread to print.
It will not be the kind of thread number we were using before because
it will be whatever the operating system assigned, right?
But that will tell us something we can see here to see which threads
we're doing what?
So that's fine.
So here's our data, we can do that, right?
But debug string, everything looks fine here, push string, no longer
needs to be that we can just
Wait up call, win32, add entry, right?
Because that's, that's all we're actually talking about here.
So push string becomes 13 to add entry.
And let's see.
Work queue is now platform work queue.
And win32 add entry now, has to take the Callback as well.
So that's a take do worker work, right?
So I'm going to go ahead and replace this with do worker work.
Oops.
That's kind of amazing.
I missed the I accidentally forgot to leave the thing and it made this
nice striped pattern without the quote.
About the double quote.
There we go.
Okay, so went through to complete.
All work takes the cue.
Okay, so let's see where we're at.
Here, we should probably step through this because we made a ton of
money modifications to it.
We also need to make a quick trip into the initialization code here
because the initialization code before it calls, anything needs to
properly set these values, right?
So what we need to do here is when we set up game memory, right?
And we set those debug calls.
Now we actually have to do like the the different things that we said
we were going to set these guys have to all be in there so we need to
provide a high priority queue.
We need to provide platform at entry platform complete all work right.
Like so.
That's win32.
Add entry went through to complete all work.
And then this right here can literally just be this Q so we can
actually call it Q.
So that's, we can even use that one, right?
And the only problem that we have so far is that now we don't actually
RQ.
Never resets, right?
So for the time being
And this is not the way that I actually want to do it eventually but
for the time, being whenever work is completed, so all the work in the
queue has been completed.
I will go ahead and at that time, reset the queue
Right.
So right then I'll just do queue entry, count completion, count.
Q next entry to do you area, right?
So that's it for the moment, nothing else going on their platform
work.
You, here we go.
So yeah, so I'll just run it, just for fun, but we kind of need to
step through its now and make sure that we're doing anything,
resembling anything really?
So, okay.
So, here we go.
We've got our threads, their printing stuff out.
Looks like we actually did work.
One, two, three, four.
Yeah, it looks looks good and we have a bunch of different Fred's
doing their thing so that's all fine.
And hey you know, surprisingly enough the game actually worked which
is weird.
There we go.
I was expecting something to go poorly there, right?
I'm expecting this thing to kind of died.
A horrible death, but, but
For some reason.
It wasn't.
Yeah.
And I don't know why it's not dying.
A horrible death.
There we go.
I was going to say, it should die.
A horrible death.
It is not dying.
I don't know why.
Oh my goodness pixel is like totally garbage.
So that's always fun.
Anyway, so we've got work to do to clean this up but already, we're
actually at least working.
So this is running through the threads which is nice, right?
So so we're not we're not totally broken, we're just, we're just not
really good, one might say so.
Okay, so let's take a look here.
I guess one thing so I already know is wrong.
I mean we'll just start taking taking a look at things.
So before I do any debugging here, what I would also like to do is I
would probably liked.
I would like to probably convert this guy.
Like what?
Here's what I'm thinking?
Instead of stepping through this and validating that all works, and
then changing it to a circular buffer and introducing more bugs and
then debugging that, I'm wondering, if I shouldn't just change it to
the circular buffer first.
And then start to
Hang it so that we're only debugging one thing which seems a little
bit.
More sane.
Also, this isn't thread safe right now so you know, because this
hasn't guaranteed that people have gone to sleep, for example, right?
So so what I would like to do is I'd like to do that first.
So I mean that even,
Is a cause of a bug that we could have, right?
So anyway,
so let's see what we can do to make this into a circular buffer,
right?
So what we want to do for a circular buffer is we want to have
essentially two, we want to sort of change the nomenclature a little
bit here to just say, we have, you know, a place where writing to a
place where reading from and then we have a completion that's in
between their right and we want these to be able to kind of wrap
around potentially into into the buffer, right?
so, one thing I could do in theory,
Like the cheesy way to do this would be to just change this to a un 64
and always just mod into the entry table, right?
That would always work, just fine.
But since we are already doing an interlocked compare exchange, I
think and I can't think of any reason why this wouldn't be true.
I think, if we just use interlock compare Exchange in both cases, we
should be able to just handle the wrapping and it shouldn't be a big
deal.
Lisa seems that way.
So let's let's take a look.
Let's just take a look at doing it that way, so that we don't have to
worry about Q rapping, being an issue.
So here's what I'm going to change these to be called, right?
I'm going to call entry completion.
Count will actually be like something like probably next entry to
complete.
Right or, or first, uncompleted entry about that, right?
Then we're going to have next entry to use or something, or to fill to
write and next entry to read
Something like this.
And so I just want these guys to constantly go through the buffer and
wrap around, right?
So when we do win32, add entry,
What I actually want to do here is I want to assert that the next
entry to write is not equal to.
I want to basically assert that if I was going to write something, if
I was going to write something into the buffer,
That we haven't like wrapped around, right?
So, in order to do that, what I would need to do is say that.
If the next if by writing into this entry,
I would overwrite an entry that's already there.
Then that would be a problem, right?
I'm trying to think of what the easiest way to do that would be, I
mean because it seems a little bit ugly to try and do that.
I'm trying to think of what the easiest way to do that would be for
not leaving space in between the two of them, right?
It's been a long day, it has been a long day circular buffers at the
end of a long day.
It's a little rough.
I'm going to pop over to the Blackboard so that I can think this
through.
so, circular
Fifo here.
so,
Here we go.
We've got this dude, right.
He's got a bunch of entries in him.
And what we want to do is we want to say, you know, if I have to read
and, you know, if this is the read location, right?
I need something that sort of says, where I'm reading.
I need something that says like, where the the you know where I'm
where I'm writing to, right, so I keep adding entries.
That point in moving, this forward and the read.
All the other threads are pulling things off of this buffer.
So the Reed is moving forwards, right?
And what I wanted to figure out is, well, when these guys are wrapped
around, right?
Like when the right, if the right corner comes around here, I just
wanted to be able to assert that.
It doesn't go past the read pointer, you know what I'm saying?
And so I guess I will just leave a space and say if the right pointer
Moving the right pointer would collide with the read pointer you can't
write like that's you've overflowed the Q right?
So I think that's just what I want to say.
I think I want to say if the next entry to write plus 1, right?
Madhvi the entry count.
so,
If moving one forward, would make me equal to whatever the next entry
is to read.
Then I'm going to just consider that.
That's that's bogus, you've put yourself in a bad condition.
I've technically you still, you still could run in that configuration,
right?
You it's the one after that that would be bogus but I don't want to it
puts the
To an invalid state in because the pointers are now pointing to the
same place simply that.
So I'll just leave it that way.
So assuming that that's okay, then the one that we're going to get is
the next entry to, right?
We're going to write into it then we're going to increment the next
entry to right and we're going to release a semaphore, right?
But when we increment the next entry to right, now what we would like
to do is say if the cues next entry to write equals the the array
count, we want it to jump back to zero, right?
So in some sense, what we want to say is this
IQ extension to write plus 1 mod array, count entries.
Right, which is the thing we wrote above.
So I think what I'll probably do is just say, oh okay, new next entry,
right?
I'll just say this is what it's going to be right, that's what we're
going to do.
And so I'll say, make sure that the new next entry to write isn't
equal to the next entry to read.
Because if it is, that would be bad news, right?
So that seems okay, right?
I know.
I don't see anything problematic there that seems fine.
Yeah, that seems totally fine.
So now, this guy is a little bit trickier, right?
First, uncompleted entry is a little bit trickier.
I'm fact, I think first uncompleted entry might not be like when we
start making this Q, be able to have more people in it.
We're going to have to actually have these things be able to external.
So this is I think this is still going to be like completion, count
like a different thing and we're going to have completion, count be
something that actually does reset in that way.
Right.
So okay.
So, if we do all of that, then we because we're going to have to do is
have multiple completion counts.
So everyone who has a job will have to have a separate completion
counter, everyone who has like a set of jobs that they need to wait on
will have to have like a separate, completion counter basically right,
if they're in the same queue.
So, anyway, now we can do the exact same thing.
We were doing here, which is to say original index entry to do.
Q next entry to do, right?
And that's the one that it's going to read from.
So it still does exactly the same thing but instead, it does new next
entry to do and it's really an extension to read now, right next entry
to read.
We go original next entry to read.
Your next entry to read and the news.
Century to read.
Is just the same as the same as this complication up here, right?
We're just doing this.
Next entry to read + 1 and remaining by the entries.
So we do that.
We do the original next entry to read, we do next Century to read like
so,
we check to make sure that the original next entry to read is not
equal to
Q next entry to write so that it has not caught up to the right
cursor.
We then go ahead and do that exchange new next entry to read with
original next entry to read like so and then assuming that the one
that came back was the original next entry to read.
We go ahead and we do it.
And we think the completion can't, right?
And so that now, I think should be a little bit more in line with,
with doing the circular buffer stuff.
So this is hoops.
This is q and trees.
Look so
Next entry to write new next entry to write that's a typo next entry
to do.
Next entry to read.
and,
Q, did you count?
He's like to entry completion.
Count.
Ah.
So again like I said, these are going to have to be a little more
General.
So what we want to do here is have some way of knowing when a batch of
jobs has completed.
So what we really want is something that's sort of, you know, it's
like we've got a completion.
You know, goal and a completion Target basically.
So we've got like our completion goal.
Every time we add an entry, right?
We need that to increase.
So, you know, every time through here, right?
We would want to Ink the completion goal and later they'd be different
completion goals.
And then every time in here, we the completion count.
We then just want to see, while the completion goal is not equal to
the completion count.
Right.
So I think that's roughly correct.
But yeah, we're going to have to test.
That does not look good.
It does not look good ladies and gentlemen, but I think that's roughly
correct.
So let's go ahead and take a look at it.
Oh, but this part work, just fine.
Which is a little bit odd.
I wasn't expecting one of them to work properly in the other one, not
two, but I guess that just means are wrapping
Not working properly, right?
So what I'd like to do is to test the rapping, I would like to set
this down to a level where the wrapping is going to happen more
frequently, right?
So I want to do something where we'll guarantee that we will wrap and
then, you know, in our test code.
So what I'm going to do is I'm just going to make it so that we will
definitely wrap, right, I'll make it so we only had like ten entries
in here or something like this.
And then you know, when I run it in theory that
Make whatever is going to happen, happen, like right away, right?
If that makes sense, least that's the Hope.
Anyway.
Well.
I guess not because that's in the renderer so the wrapping actually
didn't fail there.
Which is kind of annoying but okay.
Anyway, what you gonna do?
I'm gonna step through the code so that I can see what's wrong with
it.
I was kind of hoping that we would be able to make the bug happen
right there.
But I guess the answer is when you start the day off with an owl, the
shame you don't deserve things to go your way.
Potentially could be one way to think of it.
All right, so let's take a look inside win32.
Add entry.
Is our cue.
There it is.
It only has a few entries here.
So we come through and we push the first thing on their there is the
first thing that we picked.
We now have a completion goal of one, because there's one thing in the
queue that needs to get done.
We update the next entry to write moving it forward.
So we also kick off a thread, right?
So that's fine.
Let's jump back in here.
Take another, look at the queue.
You can see we've already read what entry so that already got done
that entry already happened.
So we come through here, we push on.
Pull back, we do the fence.
We take a look at the new next entry to right, and that's going to
update, so that's looking fine.
I'm going to go ahead and jump ahead here to the part where we get to
the wrapping boundary.
So we come in here, right?
And we now have an extension to write of 9.
So the new next entry to write should be 0 and it is, we come through
here?
We set that next integer, right?
Is 0, completion, goal got increment.
It again as it should have.
So now we're going to do that sleep 1000, all of these threads printed
out all the strings that we have there.
So our completion goal and our account, or both 10, which is what we
would expect, we're on the zeroeth guy.
So that's we wrapped around the Q which is what we would also expect.
So yeah, we've added in each one of these guys goes ahead and adds in
Exactly as we would expect and wraps around again the completion goal
finishes up and off.
We go.
So how many of these did we get?
1 2 3 4 5 6 7 8.
9 10 1 2 3 4 5 6 7 8 9 10.
Yeah so
that all looks good.
Which is kind of bizarre.
So, yeah.
Yeah.
We've got something sudden more subtle.
That is wrong, I guess.
But I don't know what it is.
So I guess the other thing I can test is just to see if there's any
chance we can make it more be clearly about the wrapping or not is
make it very large.
So this just doesn't seem to be about the wrapping at all.
We're just full on not completing right?
So that seems like it's about.
It's more about our that seems like it's more about our completion
code not about are our actual wrapping code which is not what I would
have expected.
Okay?
So let's see here, we are in the main thread.
We're inside complete.
All work.
At the completion goal is 16 to completion.
Counties 17.
Ha ha.
So we still got a race condition in here.
So, okay, so this is good.
We've pared it down.
We now know what are, you know what our Target is?
The completion goal code that I just sloppily added.
There is not correct.
Well, the completion goal code is correct or has no indication that
it's wrong.
Yet.
This is the problem.
Our completion count is not is not operating correctly.
So, let's take a look at what's happening there.
So we know that when we come into this guy, this is the guy who does
all the adding, this is the producer or comes in here.
So we know that completion goal kind of has to be set correctly by
that point, right.
Because we said it,
And then completion count when we're checking against him and doing
operations, somehow, either in the threads or elsewhere.
This actually increment to the value One X, one more time than it
should have been allowed to do.
So, how does that happen?
We have an interlock compare exchange.
We are trying to exchange the entry to read with this new one, which
is incremented by 1, right?
We are
Are giving it the original one that we saw that was in there, right?
The one that we think is there,
And then only if that was the value, that was still in there.
Are we going to actually do the work?
Batch right.
So, how does that end up?
Incrementing too many times.
How does it happen original next entry to read equals Q next entry to
read?
If they're not equal.
We're going to try the interlock compare exchange.
We're going to try it with the next entry that we computed.
So that will replace these two.
It will return us whatever was there, right?
And this is what we're expecting to see there.
And as long as that's true.
Ah, man, you know
Multi-threading.
Hard to do on stream, it turns out.
So once I read that once I can't I have to make sure I read the
correct one obviously.
Yeah.
So I don't actually know that was the bug but that was a bug because I
was reading this value twice, and I need to only read this value.
Once I need to look at it once and the new, all my computation based
on it because if I look at it multiple times, I could get different
values.
Is each time and then the whole thing comes comes falling down, right?
So I need to read that once and then never again, right?
So let me actually verify that, I never read it again.
In fact, right groups
So let's take a look at everything that reads from Q.
Here we read from next entry to read once next entry to write once,
and then we target Next Century to read.
That is how that should be okay?
And hey, that turns out that actually was the bug.
Bizarre.
So hey, you know, this is actually pretty cool because we are now
rendering multi-threaded.
I don't know if you noticed that but it's totally true.
We are totally rendering multi-threaded people.
That is awesome.
Now, how much of the processor we're actually using.
We've actually Rex using quite a bit more than we were before, which
is kind of cool.
We are not maxing it out and that's by Design, but we have roughly
tripled how much we're using.
I suspect at this point though.
We couldn't actually go any faster because we're not doing enough of a
workload at this point, right?
Meaning, we're only going to render at 30 frames a second because we
actually wait for the vertical blank and all that other.
We actually do is the sleep in there, right?
So we're never going to go faster than that.
So I think that means we're rendering at 30 frames.
Second.
We'll have to do some friends X and see how we're doing.
Start timing.
The overall thing, but we're getting there.
People, we are rendering multi-threaded, it's true, it's actually
true.
Now, you have a couple of things we got to work on, we got to set up
this tile stuff properly and we have a problem with how we're handling
the edges of things as well.
Now that we're multi-threaded, that wasn't a problem before we
multi-threaded.
So we got that.
Look at that.
But next week, it looks like we can tidy this up and
we've got a pretty pretty cool thing going on here.
I feel like I'm pretty excited about this.
Can we create can we crank our resolution to 1920 by 1080 at this
point?
You kind of It kind of asks if you can I don't know that that's a good
idea in general but
I don't know.
I mean, you might as well try it, right?
It's not quite as fast but it's still running and boy it looks pretty
good too, huh?
Let's see what happens if we just use.
Just I know you guys don't want me to use more threads because you
know, it ruins the stream, but I just really just, let me just put it
up, 2213 threads or 11.
Okay, 12 threads.
Okay, that's want to see how we do.
That's pretty darn good.
I mean that's kind of crazy when you think about it, 1920 by 1080,
that's pretty darn.
Cool.
I mean can you imagine how slow this was?
I mean we weren't even running we were running at some ungodly.
Like one frame is second on the quarter-sized and here's the full-size
running in like a totally playable framerate.
That is some really cool stuff right there.
And we're not even finished yet, right?
That is super cool.
That is just awesome.
That is so cool.
All right.
I'll turn it back down.
Yeah, yeah, yeah.
All right.
Let's go to Q&A here.
And remember this machine is from 2010 as well.
This machine is an old machine.
This machine is 5 years old.
It was a good machine at the time, though, but it was old.
What's, since the?
Clothes don't complete in order.
What if one workload takes very long while the other threads wrap
around in the Q, such that a new workload over rights, the slot with
the one that is still running.
So that's definitely a problem.
And essentially,
What we need to do and there's a lot of different ways you can choose
to approach this, but the way that I usually try to approach it is I
just make it so that I shouldn't be chewing up that much work
basically, right?
So, for example, in the circumstance that we have here, the renderer
we know, it's just going to kick off a fixed number of tiles and then
it needs to have all those tiles completed before it moves on.
So we can very easily just construct one high priority queue that we
know always has enough space and it to store a full render set of
tiles and that's never going to be a problem, right?
For out of order for like, background loading and stuff like that.
We can have a separate queue and we can just make sure that we always,
we don't try to launch new asset loads.
If the Q looks like it's getting filled, right?
That's not too hard to do.
And so what we can do and what I'll probably do is make a win32 add
entry, kind of a thing.
I'll make this return a Bool and it will just fail to do the ad.
And, and you'll then know the calling color know I'm like, okay, the
cues
full, I won't try to like launch any more background asset loads or
something, right?
So that's probably how we'll handle that.
Now that we're multi-threaded could be compiled in debug mode and have
the game run at a reasonable frame rate.
Oh my god dude.
Do you know what?
That was the debug build.
I want to turn it on optimization.
Dude.
With only eight, with only eight of the threads, we are running in
real time in 1920 by 1080 right now.
And that's doing full Blitz to we're not filling the ground chunks
right now because I turned that off, but it's actually bleeding, the
whole screen to and then playing the trees on top of it and then the
characters on top of that.
So it's not that different.
Like, we're gonna have to add a lot more complexity in there.
So I mean, it's not like we can send like, oh my God.
The the 1920 by 1080 software rendering is totally going to work for
handmade hero, because we've got a lot of complexity that we're going
to throw at it.
And I don't know that it's ready for that, right?
But dude,
dude, and it's sub-pixel accurate everywhere.
And it does scaling and rotation.
We've got some serious stuff going on here.
Not to mention, we're not even clipping the bitmaps.
Yet.
The bitmaps themselves are actually putting bigger than they need to
be too.
I'm going to turn on the ground chunks.
Because, why not?
Dude, this is awesome.
This is just so stupid, cool.
Machines, our computers are so darn fast.
Like this is literally not using the graphics card as anything other
than a dumb frame buffer and we're totally running this game in real
time.
This is going to be so darn.
Cool.
Doesn't this just get too excited though because now it's like when
you see stuff like this to, it's like it feels like
there's so much just more ownership of it to like,
It feels so good to succeed at something, even if it's not like, I
mean we didn't do anything round breaking, right?
We just did the basic stuff that we have to do, but like the fact that
we work through it all and then it's working.
So, nicely is just so satisfying because now like it's, we're
intimately connected with that speed.
It's not like, we just, like, brought up an engine, and we're like,
oh, hey, it runs as fast it runs.
I don't know, whatever.
Now it's like, no, no, man.
Like we did all that and it's a different
It's a different feeling it's just it is just different than if you
just took someone's code and ran it and like cross your fingers right
and so you know I don't know, I think it's something people should
experience.
It's why I do this project is because it's that feeling that you don't
get from just buying someone's thing and using it.
Right?
And again there's nothing wrong with doing that.
It's a fine way to make a game.
But you lose something.
When you do it, you lose that feeling of like holy cow.
Like this is so cool.
That all that worked.
It's just kind of neat and again it didn't take that long.
I mean, how many hours did we spend 30 hours 40 hours?
I don't know how long we spent on the optimized renderer.
Not even that probably 40 hours.
That's only one week that's not long to spend to get such a cool
experience, right?
I feel like it's, it's worth it.
You know, if you care about,
You know, kind of your own happiness as opposed to just how fast can I
get this thing done at a bare minimum or whatever, right?
That is darn cool.
Can we tell how much faster it is?
Now that is multi-threaded, we can I whole kind of hoped I would have
been done a little sooner today, so that I could time this
But you know, I was going to put in a little, a little query
performance, counter framerate.
We could we could probably I think we have an old one in there that I
could turn on me.
Turn the ground chunks off so that those aren't taking up some random
spurious time, but yeah.
So win32 add entry.
All this stuff.
We probably should clean up a little bit of some of that stuff, but,
let's take a look here at the frame time.
I think, I don't know if I can re-enable, this maybe I can.
Let's find out.
So there we go.
33 milliseconds of frame to remove.
All right.
Yeah, and we've got Cycles here.
This is actually also telling us the whole cycle count to, but yeah,
we are totally running at 33 milliseconds per frame, which is kind of
insane.
If I turn off, I just want to I'm just going to see what happens at
1920 by 1080 if I turn off multi-threading.
What happens, right?
Because it's really easy for me to do that.
I can just I can do that.
Right?
So instead of queuing these, we just do them.
So, I passed the render queue.
I passed detailed work and I passed the work and I just call this
thing directly, right?
Like that.
It doesn't, you're right.
Doesn't
So this is without multi-threading on so you can see it's kind of
poke, right?
It's actually pretty good though it's not terrible you know I mean it
isn't awful so we weren't actually that bad at 1920 by 1080 anyway so
we don't again because we do you know what I could take out that sleep
That's another thing I could do.
So and went through two, handmade, I could take out the sleep.
So you know,
On the wall clock, if I was to crank this up.
So I basically said something like, you know,
what's the target frames per second target game, update hurts Macho,
refresh rate.
So let's say, I went ahead and crank it up to 60, right?
So we just said, whatever the monitor refresh rate is, that's what
we're going to do.
What happened?
We go.
So if I crank it up to 60 right now, maybe we'll be able to see a
little bit better.
So here we go.
Now, we're running the dude, run at 60, but we're only hitting 50, I'm
sorry.
We're only, we're 50 milliseconds, not 16 milliseconds.
So we're at 50 milliseconds.
Now, if I turn on multi-threading, do we hit 60?
Again, really what we should be doing is just timing.
How long everything?
Take.
So I should add that in but I don't have time to do that right now in
the Q&A.
Holy cow, dude, I think we're actually just hitting 60 frames per
second at 1920 by 1080 in the software renderer sub-pixel.
Dude, we totally are.
That is crazy.
Computers are so fast.
That's unbelievable.
How fast they go.
And we haven't even like, I mean we just did a rudimentary version of
an optimized renderer, right?
Like we didn't spend five months sitting here playing with pit so
Compares we haven't even looked at the cash yet.
Man.
Robot chocolate Dino, instead of asserting that the Q doesn't
overflow.
In adding an entry would be better to just wait for an entry to be
red.
If there is no space to write, I don't really like to do that.
If I can avoid it, because it means that it could just stall the game
in the middle of a frame or something, right?
And so, I like to just have a constant time insertion as much as
possible.
Would you call this a thread pool?
I don't know, you know, I don't think I've ever read what people
actually call a thread pool.
It is sort of that way I guess.
When stepping through multi-threaded code, all the other thread stop
as well.
I take it.
So I think you can actually set that
To be honest with you, I feel like that's actually something that is
in here.
Okay, so no, it's it's processes that that you can control, which
one's break.
So yeah.
So I guess they all always will stop.
I think.
To be so I guess, I don't let me put this way, I don't know, there
might be an option to make that happen.
What I do know is that you can freeze and unfreeze threads.
So once you are broke into the debugger, right?
And you have multiple threads, you can go in here and like freeze and
thaw Fred's to stop them from from going or to continue whether you
can let some run while you're doing other stuff.
Maybe that's not possible.
I don't know.
It might be that processes as a
Whole might just stop and you can't stop an individual thread.
I'm not sure.
Can you make the number of threads and in-game configuration option?
We, I don't know that will do that, but we will make it dependent on
the number of threads in your processor.
How long until the render is sorted?
I don't know.
I don't I just don't care about the Sorting very much.
I want everything else to be done for us but it's so much more
important but we could we could play with the Sorting sometime soon.
Oh, man, did I swear?
I didn't mean to I just got carried away.
Is the we should sleep still right after you change the, if condition
around, I don't know.
Let's check it.
Check it out.
Because yeah, just one of the things like, you know, you might expect
me to say, no.
Obviously, it's correct because the code is running multi-threaded
code can have bugs in it that hide for a long time, right?
So, just because our code is working, doesn't actually mean that it's
a bug-free q because there's so many fancy little bizarre things that
can happen in multi-threading, when the multiple things are doing
things, and different times it's very unpredictable.
So, it's always best to.
If someone has a question or if you think there might be something
wrong, it's always best to go.
Read the code.
And because they're made to be a bug in it that just just did you
know?
It just hasn't shown up yet but it's there, you know and it's just
waiting for the right combination of thread things to happen before it
strikes.
So yes, we should sleep.
Does look correct to me.
Basically, what happens is we set, we should sleep to false because
the default is we're just going to always try to keep doing stuff.
We look to see whether or not the next entry that we're going to read
is equal to an extension of, right.
If they are equal.
That means we sleep cuz there's nothing in the queue.
If they're not, then we try to dequeue something.
If we can't dequeue something, we don't want to sleep.
Because the reason that we didn't DQ it is because some other thread
got there first.
So that
That means we really don't have any idea whether or not there's more
in the Q.
So we should re-enter this thing and do it again, right?
So what will happen is, we'll just let it pop back out and this and
either do this check or do this check.
Well, this does this one doesn't do a check, it'll either do this
check if it's this guy to see whether it should end the whole deal, or
it'll come through here and redo it again.
Why do you use pound if 0 instead of slashed a source said?
Comments, because we can turn them on and off, you know.
So, we can turn them on and on, and off is the reason.
Because, if you take a look like, for example, the stuff that I just
did in render group, you know, now, we've got one here that we can
just do like, you know, note Casey, this is the multi-threaded path,
this is the single threaded path, right?
And I can just with changing one character, I can do that, right?
And the other benefit to it is.
That they nest properly comments, don't always Nest properly.
So if you do like this and I want to take out some code that already
has it.
Like so, you know, if this was commented out, right?
And then I want to comment this out.
It actually ends up being bogus, right?
It doesn't, comment these out, you know, I'm saying it's an error.
So you want something that Nest properly and and the ifs Nest
properly,
Can you show for K?
Of course not I only have a 1920 by 1080 monitor here and I don't have
any way to broadcast that twitch doesnt even do for our K.
Does it?
I don't know.
Maybe it does.
Oh good.
Okay, so I didn't swear.
I was hoping I didn't swear but I don't know.
Is multi-threaded code less reliable than single threaded code.
Yes!
Yes, yes, yes.
And yes, that is why most good programmers that I know.
We'll try to come up with good systems that make it so that you only
do the multi threading in a very tightly controlled way, because if
you just go Hog Wild with multi-threading and let it just proliferate,
it can be bad news, right?
I really just don't know.
Programmers, who are so darn good that they just can write
multi-threaded code.
That's tons of threads happening all over the place and doing whatever
in it.
It just works.
Like that's usually not the case.
So is the circular buffer recycling, threads after they are done
processing a tile.
I wasn't clear on why a circular buffer was chosen.
So the circular buffer has nothing to do with the threads.
The circular buffer is just the Q and the reason I did that is so that
you can just keep stuffing things in the queue ad infinitum, and
they'll always just keep getting done.
Okay.
So in theory,
We're back.
Accidentally bumped.
The power cord.
It's a problem.
The power cord is right next to where the microphone plugs in, so, and
I have this little tiny microphone cable, so it's pretty tough.
It's not a good situation.
Anyway, I just wanted to see if the code got ruined at all, just so we
can know whether we have to repair anything that didn't say, I suspect
it probably did save but
Let's see.
Yeah, so we're totally good.
So we didn't really lose anything.
I don't think.
I think we're good to go.
So yeah.
So let's just double check
To make sure that we're still running.
Well,
Flog them hamsters flog them.
So, this is the thing, right?
That
Like did you see how long it took like when I click on file?
It's like an eternity and then it eventually popped up the window or
whatever.
That's one of the what you kind of saw today is one of the reasons I
think I'm always so grumpy, like, look at this.
Like what was that?
We were just rendering 1920 by 1080 software rendered, 60 frames.
A second sub pixel accurate with full transforms on this processor.
Using only 8 of the 16 cores that it has
And like the people who wrote this couldn't figure out a way to just
have it load up right away.
That was like they had no idea like what was going to happen there,
they were like I don't know but I don't see how we could load a text
file and display it in that period time.
It's an unfathomable to me, you know, how would that happen?
I don't even know how that would happen that you're talking about
future technology.
But hey, yeah, so that's looking really darn sweet.
I think we are probably gated by Windows now actually, because again,
we're using kind of a janky way to put this stuff to the screen.
So I think we're probably if we if we switch to going through say
direct3d and opengl to do our blit just giving just doing all still
doing our render ourselves, but to do our Blythe that way, we'd
probably be fine.
I don't even know what to do now.
Did does that.
We set the target for the software enter to be 1920 by 1080 60.
I feel like we can't because once we get more stuff on here it's not
going to work right?
I don't know what to say.
I'm just going to leave it like that till it gets slow and then we'll
drop it down.
All right, back to questions.
Sorry.
So so is the circular buffer recycling threads after they were done
processing.
I wasn't clear on why a circular buffer was chosen.
Okay, so the reason that I wanted to choose a circularbuffer, let's go
ahead and open up Blackboard.
The reason I wanted to choose a circular buffer is because I didn't
want people to think.
We did lose a little bit of our drawing.
I didn't want people to in the code.
I don't want them to have to think too hard about what's going on,
right?
So the reason I chose a circular buffer is basically what we need
here, right?
Is, we need something where we're going to put stuff into it that
needs to be done, right?
And then stuff is going to come out of it asynchronously, right?
So we're putting stuff in and then we're grabbing stuff out, right?
So we like putting a, we grab out a, we put in B we grab out B and so
on, right?
And what happens is these things we want to be able to happen over a
long period of time.
Potentially like let's say we want to use this for background
decompress or like filling those ground buffer chunks.
We want that to happen in the background.
So if we have a queue where we don't know how long things take,
there's never a point where we're going to complete them all in the
render queue.
We did stuff where we just like, queued up a bunch of stuff and then
said, go and everything gets cleared out.
If that were the case, we wouldn't
We need the circular buffer but since we have things that we want to
just take arbitrary amounts of time and we just kind of have a ruling
Q of stuff that needs to happen.
We don't ever have a single point in time where we're going to clear
everything.
We're constantly adding new things in as we're pulling old things off,
and it just goes forever.
And so, in that, I want to be able to, you know, the circular buffer
is so that I can just keep having that rolling window of things that
threads are supposed to take, when we go to use this queue for stuff
like background art.
And stuff like that.
I just saw you where you're sleeping threads if there was no work, are
you still using semaphore is to block and wake up threads or did you
switch to sleeping threads?
So sleeping is a bad term.
We're not using any sleeps in on the threads, they're actually waiting
on a signal so I should say wait.
See if there's any more questions.
Is the archive, in a saved correctly.
We can get it from twitch, if it doesn't, but we would hopefully it
did, but I don't know.
Would it be easier to implement the queue as a linked list?
So it has no maximum size.
Since we never need to Traverse the list, it should still be fast.
Well, it mean linked list has a maximum size, right?
It's the size of memory.
And if you allocate the memory every time, then you're incurring a
bunch of costs to in queueing things so you don't really gain
anything.
Like unless you actually want to have unbounded cues.
It's strictly a lose to switch to a system that doesn't enforce a
maximum size, right?
Because everything is worse in that system.
The only thing you gain is no maximum size, so we have to ask
ourselves, do we ever want an unbounded Lee growing Q?
What were the circumstances be under, which that occurred?
And why would we want to allow it to occur?
And as far as I can think of there's never a case where we actually
want that to happen.
So it seems better to me just to not allow it and let everything else
be better.
In the ruling buffer, you check the entry to be filled before writing
a new one in and otherwise skip to the next slot know, right now, we
actually just it's a hard error, it's considered an error to right
into the queue if you in that circumstance.
So right now it's just an error.
Totally in error.
so,
All right.
Looks like we're done with questions.
I will now start the process of figuring out if the video is good or
not, who knows.
It might be, might not be.
We'll find out.
And to answer the question of why I have to do it this way, it's
because people complained, that the audio quality had clicking in it
and they were correct when I plugged the microphone into the front
Port of the computer because apparently the
Port produces that clicking sound, although it doesn't actually
produce a look inside.
It's only when OBS is capturing that Port that it produces the
clicking sound.
So it's like something with OBS in that Port.
So I have to plug into the back, which means I have to plug into the
power cable, which means I can pump the power cable.
If I have to tighten it and it's a disaster.
Modern Computing.
Yes, these are unsolved problems.
Why is this ever a problem?
Why doesn't the front port on the computer work?
I have no idea because that's Computing these days.
Anyway,
That is confusing these days.
But there are small things that are always fun and reassuring like
having your software renderer run at 1920 by 1080 by 60 hertz, which
is pretty darn cool.
So there's, at least something awesome happening.
Anyway,
I'm going to wrap that up for today.
Yes, I know Chrome didn't shut down properly.
That's because the power went out on the computer, but thank you very
much for joining me for another episode of handmade hero.
We were able to wrap up our multi-threading of the renderer today,
which is awesome and it worked really well.
So, next week, what we're going to do is we're going to go through and
do a Polish pass on some of this stuff where we'll actually do some
timings and we have to go in and make it so that our tiles are well.
Lines that we don't have to do all the nonsense with the clipping them
and and the stuff that we're kind of doing in there right now.
So we got some clean up stuff to do.
So, next week, I'll definitely be clean up week on that one.
Will try to polish everything up and make it nice and pretty, but it's
running darn fast right now.
So I'm pretty psyched about that.
That is pretty pretty, darn cool people.
So I hope you're happy about that.
I know I am I hope but see you back here next week when we can kind of
play around with things and get everything tidied up.
Because I think it's
A pretty sweet renderer now actually all things considered.
So yeah, come back on Monday, we'll do it.
We'll get it, we'll get it going.
In the meantime, if you would like to follow along with a source code
at home, you can pre-order the game and it comes with a source code.
You can download it every night after I'm done working on it and play
around with it.
Just, you know, it's a good way to learn.
We also have a forum site, you can go to ask questions.
We've got a patreon page.
If you want to support the video series, we've got a tweetbot that we
Schedule.
And of course we've got a little button that tells you when the next
one's coming and of course, I don't up this update schedule, till
usually Sunday.
So the next button doesn't really help you till then but then it will
tell you every day of the week when the next handmade hero will be.
So that's pretty handy to thanks very much for joining me and don't
forget one of your esteemed, moderators Abner Cohen.
Bray is giving a lecture on Twitch on Sunday, 5:00 p.m.
Eastern Standard time.
So that's actually
Ali, to p.m.
our time I believe.
And that's it, that's a twitch.tv slash Abner, Cumbre, a be any RC o
IM bre but you can always check the handmade hero.
Twitter.
I'll retweet it if he tweets it out.
All right.
Thanks everyone.
Take it easy.