Hello everyone and welcome to handmade here.
Are the sure we could a complete game live on stream and I never have
a cord that's long enough to actually let me keep my head where I want
it to be because I don't know why.
Because set some point I just don't like spending a lot of money on
stuff and so I can't quite actually get a longer cord.
That's just the way things are sometimes.
And I guess the fact that this is not a dozen help, you know, maybe I
could fix that, that would probably be a good start as well.
Let's see if that helps.
It's a little better but actually is a little bit better.
So anyway, welcome to handmade hero today.
We are as the as the Romans used to say having our lunch and eating it
too, where we are going to try and get our debug system into a state,
where it both works for sort of like, everything, everything dumps
into a log on the game side of things.
So there's no actual Interruption of the game running, no matter what
kind of debug stuff you're doing or on the
Oxide.
It's just all sort of pulled up and collated and put it into a format.
That's easy to sort of like View and do all these other sorts of
things.
It's sort of like the, it's sort of like, the all you can eat lunch,
buffet of debug information and like any lunch buffet, you end up in a
situation where, you know, sometimes the sneeze Shield doesn't go down
all the way and, you know, some of the the those little troughs get
contaminated and everyone in the restaurant.
It's sick other times.
It's great and they have the chicken tikka masala or whatever that you
really like.
And it's you can just have a much of it as you want.
And so we don't really know which kind of a lunch buffet, our debug
system is going to be yet.
We're hoping that it's going to be the kind with the tikka masala and
not the one where somebody sneezed into the the saag paneer, it's
pretty hard to tell in saag paneer, whether or not someone has in fact
sneeze into it because it kind of has that sort of Green + yellow.
Look to it already and
Even if they were really, really sick and sort of had a fair bit of
bacteria in their mucus, you wouldn't necessarily be able to, you
know, kind of see it.
So I guess what I would say is, that's where we're at.
And that's kind of a gross thought now that I'm thinking of it, I kind
of wish I hadn't brought that up, but you know, whatever.
What can you do?
So we're going to jump back into it.
Pretty much same thing we were doing yesterday just trying to like
wrap up some of the code there.
This of course is day to 18.
So if you want to follow along at home, you want to unpack day, 217
source code into a directory and that is what I'm starting with today.
So here we go.
With the handmade heroing.
So I'm just going to go ahead and build.
Your and if I remember correctly, we turned off the debug system.
Just so people wouldn't have any trouble running it and so on.
So we don't have it on at the moment and everything's, wow, look at
that.
Guy's if around there, okay, go back from that.
But what we need to do, if we actually want the debug system to run,
as we need to change our pan to find a turn debugging back on.
And so now, we're back to where we were yesterday, which is, we were
kind of in the middle of making changes and so, let's go right back
into it.
Like, I do.
Always say.
If you don't like what you have for lunch, the best thing to do is to
just eat it as quickly as you can, there will always be a better lunch
tomorrow.
So let's let's take a look and see where we're at here.
We are with our grid stuff.
We just did this yesterday, what we wanted to do was sort of make it,
so that no matter where we were in the debug recording process, any
event that got recorded would basically have a grid associated with
it.
So that we knew that a particular
Station in the file, could be uniquely identified so that all of the
events that came from that location could sort of be grouped together
and looked at as a whole.
Now, of course, what we didn't do is we didn't actually change up in
here, the definition of a debug event.
So that's kind of thing.
And, you know what, we've actually got a lot to do in here which we
can get rid of because we got rid of the line number.
And now we've just got grid.
We still have block name, which is a different thing and I don't know
if we want to keep block name or get rid of block named, we may be
able to
To get rid of block named as well in the future.
Let's just say to do Casey, should we remove block name, altogether?
And I don't know whether we should or not, but, you know, we'll find
out.
So, let's see here.
We also I think maybe missed backslash at some point, we might have
now.
I guess we've got it in there.
So we just need a semicolon that's about it and then I think we're
good.
Now, what we also have to do here because this is one of those things
that
happens, especially in a situation where
it's kind of like, you know, we're making a fair bit of changes.
It's like, I always say when you're trying to serve lunch, if you
know, all the place settings are sort of shifted around that everyone
sits down and they don't know where to eat, right?
And so one of the things that you do as a programmer is, when you're
serving lunch, if you want to do something, where you shift the place
settings, you got to tell every got to go through until all the people
who are coming to the lunch party that they need to kind of move over
from their normal positions.
And that's exactly what we have to do now, right?
Because these people, when we do like these initializations at all,
That stuff we need to sort of go in here and incorrect.
The stuff that was expecting there to be founding block name.
Etc and now there's going to be that with thing.
So in here, we pass in the file name and all that sort of stuff.
I number.
So we want to do here is actually just be passing
Weird instead and we're going to have to, you know make that work
right, here we go.
And of course the way we get the grid is is we do this thing so we can
just anywhere that we were doing that before.
We should be able to make that work.
I'm wondering as well if I could do something like like this sort of
I'm wondering if this will work.
I'm wondering if something like that would be would be plausible.
So that basically
Lee.
This would just you know, would just look like that and I don't really
know but I'm going to try it anyway.
So okay, if we do this, then anytime we call debug initialize value.
Obviously, it's going to be incorrect.
Oops, we go, it's going to be incorrect now.
So we're going to have to make sure that works and you can see there.
We're getting those areas.
So, debug initialize value, let's go ahead and find that.
I guess it's only in these two places, so that's actually pretty
straightforward.
And you can see here, we've got file line path, sort of stuff getting
past.
So we want to do is get rid of these here file online.
Want to keep path because that's the name.
But now in place where the grid was going to be, we want to do that
unique file counter string like so and and hopefully that'll work.
I don't know if it will work.
Like I said, with macros, it's always kind of a little bit of an
adventure because I never remember exactly how the macro browser Works
other than the fact that I always remember that.
It's a giant steaming pile of lunch as I always like to call it.
So
here we are in add variable to group.
So now we've kind of that suggests to me that we've sort of corrected
the errors that we had from the grid situation and we're back to sort
of dealing now with the actual stuff.
The actual structural stuff of the, the debug system that now has to
change because of the stuff that we did yesterday.
In deciding how it was going to work.
And so let's go ahead and push forward.
Oh,
and that reminds me of something that I wanted to do as well, which I
thought of this in the shower this morning, I was sort of, you know, I
as I often do my brain just randomly thinks about something that I had
been working on program lies or whatever.
And, you know, it's kind of like one of those things when you're at
the lunch table and you're, you know, you're just eating your lunch
and your brain just kind of drifts off to think about memory,
allocation, what I remembered is that when we were doing this code, we
actually didn't quite do it, right?
We don't know this yet, because we haven't actually gotten to the part
where we're relying on it, but when we do this Arena has room for a
thing, this actually this code is actually
He not really correct.
The reason it's not correct is because we are never actually planning
to free any memory.
We're just planning to recycle
So the Arena's never going to have no more room, no matter how many
times we for your frame.
So really push size with the allocation was the wrong way to write
this.
Well, we actually wanted to do was have our allocator thing which
allocates event stuff.
We want to just that to like look and see if there is an old one to
use.
And if there isn't
Allocate memory or rather free frames until it can.
So, this was actually wrong.
This is actually two totally wrong and needs to be different.
That's just kind of a lunch sort of thing that we need to do.
Not, it's like less of a dinner.
It's not really a dinner or breakfast thing.
It's more of a lunch thing.
Kind of like, you know, you know sandwiches like no one eats a
sandwich for breakfast or for dinner, they eat it for lunch, it's that
kind of thing.
Right.
So moving on.
Let's get back to business here because that's the memory stuff we
can.
We can do later once everything is structurally back and repaired.
So what I want to do here again is I want to get this working so that
we're keeping everything in the element hash.
So that anything that comes in any time, we see a particular location
coming through, we want to sort of have the co-leader, put it into
basically a location based on where it came from in the code.
So this what that good thing is for, we're just going to use that grid
to just do it.
We're doing a basic string hash here, where we're just going to take
whatever we see there and put it in.
Now, when I say string hash, I don't really mean it because one of the
nice things about this,
Just to be really clear on what I'm doing here.
You can kind of see what I did for the quids right in this unique file
counter string thing.
What it does is it creates a concatenated string and that concatenated
string has been created at compile time.
So when it gets created, it's going to be put into the string table of
the executable and because it is a unique string, that means that
every single one of those will get a unique pointer in our program,
which means that I don't actually have to Hash the string, which would
be relatively slow, because I'd have to go through
All of the elements of the string and add them together or and you
know with some kind of a hash function and put it to do better hash
function in there whatever.
But because I happen to be doing it this way where I know that they'll
all be put into a string table and have unique pointers.
It means that really what I can use for the hash table is just a
pointer to the string and I know that, no two strings that were
generated this way we'll ever collapse into the same pointer because
they each are a different string so that's kind of Handy.
So really what I want to do is when we do kill ladybug record, we go
through these events and what we can do is every time we get seeing
event, we can use the grid from the event to create the element hash.
So we can basically say like, all right, there is going to be
On the corresponds to this and we want to do a get element from event
kind of a thing, what we would do is pass the event and it would use
the Grid in the event to determine which one it was and return us the
proper debug element, right?
So that's really straightforward, right?
It just looks like this, we have our debug stay here.
Oops, and we've got our debug events like so.
And all we want to do now is we want to just grab out of this element
hash the correct element for our for our event.
Now our event has that grid, right?
So we have the you know we almost could just use sort of the you at 30
Tunas of it all.
Right.
In fact, I guess we should do memory index and this is a little bit,
this is a little bit dainty, it's a little bit sort of weird.
So if we create, if we take this thing which is a pointer and we
create it to a memory index, the problem is we don't really know how
big that is right.
If we're compiling a 32-bit mode which we may want to do some day.
We're not compiling a 32A right now but there's no real reason why we
can't
It could be a 32-bit value because the players will be 32 bit if it's
a 64-bit compiled, then it's going to be 64-bit value.
And so we don't really know what we would do with our hash function
here because we'd want to mix the top into it if it was 64
potentially.
But what I'm going to do instead is I'm just going to treat it as a
32-bit value.
Because what I want to, what I want to do is say, all right.
Chances are the string table is going to all be in one relatively
confined location.
So, it's probably the case that the top part of the string pointers
are not going to be relevant, right?
That's just my assumption.
Now, I don't actually know if that's true.
That might be totally wrong, but that's just what I'm assuming.
So hopefully that's the case.
So what I want to do is just use 32 bits but I also
No.
The in general it's probably going to be true that the pointers are
not going to be unaligned.
Like they're probably not going to give me pointers that are on like B
boundaries.
I'm just guessing.
That's true.
I don't know, it's true but I'm guessing.
So what I want to do instead is I want to do something where I cast
this down to either 64 or 32, don't care.
I want to shift out some of those low bits because I don't think
they're going to be relevant and then I'll make that be my hash value,
right?
So here is my hash value.
Like so.
Okay.
So then what I do is I say, all right, the hash value.
And I'm going to go ahead and mod it, by whatever.
The array count is of the thing we're going into.
And I would like, by the way, to De to verify, I'm just going to put
it here to do Casey verify this turns into.
And
And not a mod.
So we may do that as well.
So this is the index right into the hash table.
So we get the hash value back.
We find out where we would put this thing and after that we then say,
all right, that means that the debug element that we're supposed to be
looking at here.
Or rather the chain I should guess.
I should say is going to be the element.
Hash
With that index.
So now all we're doing is we're just going to look through to see if
we can find it.
And so for any given one here, if the chain grid equals the grid that
we're looking for and again you'll notice here, I'm not comparing the
strings and the reason I'm not comparing, the strings is exactly the
same reason.
I just said we know that the pointers to the strings are unique so
it'd just be a complete waste of my time to actually compare them with
a string comparison of some kind.
Right.
It's like you don't eat lunch if you're already full right.
That's like first rule of programming, you don't eat lunch if you're
already full and so, you know, in this case, we're already full by
just checking the Grid's, there's no sense in eating.
Some extremely elaborate lunch at that point, when all you're going to
do is to get up afterwards, so we go through the chain here.
We see if we find one if we have found one then we can just
immediately know that we found our answer, right?
And here's our debug element, we know we found our answer.
So everyone's happy and we can return a result here.
We could return out from the middle of this.
I don't tend to love sort of returns out of the middle there.
I just don't, I like sort of my functions to have a clean ending point
that I know they always go to.
So, unless I really feel like I need to, I tend not to do that.
So here, I'm just going to go ahead and say that.
Okay, we
Grab that result and we go here will check to see if we did not get a
result.
We will then go ahead and put one in.
Right?
So if we did not get a result and then we know we need to do a
allocation to actually allocate a new debug element, which I will go
ahead and do so we'll just do push struct debug State, you big arena
and now you'll notice that I'm
I'm not using our other are sort of our allocation are special.
One that's supposed to be for anything because I realize, like I said
that that was actually stupid so we don't need to worry about that for
the immediate moment.
But anyway, so I'm going to do a push truck.
I push truck the debug element here, so now I have a new one and then
I just need to put it into the hash table.
It's really pretty basic, right?
So that's the location of It.
Whatever the next in hash is of this guy will point to whatever was
there before which
Might be 0, might not be.
We don't know and then we'll chain ourselves in.
Now, once we've created a new
Obviously we also probably want to initialize it at that point.
So whatever the debug element is here,
That we're talking about, you can see, it's kind of got some stuff.
So we set up the next in hash and that's good but we probably also
want to set up like oldest event and most recent event, 2.2 nothing,
right?
And then, we also need, like I said in cure, we kind of need these to
have a grid as well.
So we have to have in here is essentially just it's just a caressed
are, right?
That's the grid.
And so in here, will say, well, whatever the quit is, the quid is
whatever came in on that.
That event like so I'm also going to put in assertion in here just to
remind myself that all everything needs to have a grid.
So that way if we kind of have some stuff lying around that never sets
that grid when it does thing will go and fix it.
Because I want everything to have that.
Okay, because remember this, since we never, we never touched the
string here.
So again, this is not just a redundant, assertion, it's not a sorting,
something that's just going to crash a little bit later.
This assertion is important, because if I didn't assert that, a grade
of zero would just work, this whole function would just go ahead and
go, right?
So I really wanted to make sure that we don't ever have a grid of 0
because I want everything they have a unique with.
So I just want to make sure that it's never going to do that.
And that that's
Yeah, in fact I could just say that so that's all that is and here you
can see me getting that element now.
So now I can compile that and hopefully everything is fine.
In fact, I guess I didn't really look to see where we were at in the
compiled structure there, where is that stuff?
So to that all just compiled first time, wow, that is like that's like
getting lunch delivered.
There is what that is, that's pretty great.
All right.
Right.
Anyway.
We don't know that it worked so it's kind of like getting lunch
delivered but you don't know if you like it you know.
It's kind of like getting lunch from a restaurant, you've never been
to before and so it's kind of cool that got delivered because you
don't have to do any work but it may be something really awful, right?
Like it could be like a salisbury steak or one of those things that's
kind of in that like mucilaginous kind of gelatinous goo.
And, you know, do you really want that even if it is delivered, you
know, maybe if you're really hungry,
You know, you'll eat that, you know, Beggars, can't be choosers,
that's what I say.
But at, you know, at the end of the day, if you are someone who maybe
maybe you could can cook or can afford to get a better lunch than the
Salisbury steak, then maybe you would write, maybe you would elect to
make that decision.
So all right, we have a little bit more work to do here.
Like I said to kind of like cleanup what's going on here.
This this stuff here with creating variable groups
that again is not really relevant.
At the moment I'm wondering if maybe we just if zero it out for the
time being even because really this stuff is not relevant at the
immediate moment.
What's actually going to happen now, right?
Is in here, right?
Where we do this hashman, adverb group, this stuff right?
Add variable to group.
What we're actually going to do is take, whatever this event thing
that was, that came in, and we're actually, just going to put it on to
wear.
It's hashes like event stream, right?
Right.
So whatever it The Element was that it would correspond with which
we've already found, right?
Because we already did the work right here to get it right.
So all we're really going to do is say when we get one of these, we're
going to go ahead and dump that into whatever the element is that's
currently open.
Right?
And that's and that's all that is.
So yeah I mean this again starting to sort of coalesce a little bit
here.
There's still just a lot of work to do but
Your name.
It's all good.
So we have a debug start event and this is really, the only thing,
this is kind of thing.
I was talking about before where I was like, I kind of was just being
dumb when we did that stuff to make everybody go through the
allocation call.
That was a stupid, not very bright.
So, what we want to do, here is okay.
We need a new steward event.
This is the only thing that's actually going to get recycled because
everything else is a standing structure that persists, but stored
events just kind of
Pile up until we run out of space for storing sort events and then we
free old sort of events.
So what we really wanted to do is we wanted to make that be the way.
This thing worked.
So what we really want to do is do like an allocate start event right?
Or get or like store just maybe the store event, right?
And so what we do when we do store event
Pass the debug state that will take care of that allocation thing for
us.
And then we'll say okay, whatever the stored event is, we know that
we've got some stuff to initialize here, right?
We've got the next, we've got the frame index and we've got the event.
Now the event is the easy part, because the event is obviously just
coming directly in, so we can like quite literally just copy, whatever
the data is there and be done with it, right?
That's super simple, but the other stuff is a little bit more
complicated for the framing decks.
We have to know what frame were on right now.
And so, fortunately we know that, if we're in here, we do know that
piece of information, right?
So we know that whatever framework collating that's got an index, so
we will just go ahead and stuff that in there and that's pretty great.
you know, easy peasy lemon squeezy like they say when you're about to
I know if you guys take tea at lunch, but if you're the kind of people
who duty at lunch, it's just customary for everyone to kind of go
around the table and take a lemon slice and go easy peasy.
Lemon squeezy and then you squeeze it into the tea.
Obviously, you don't do that if you drink tea with milk because it
will curdle.
So you know, I mean why would you do that?
That's just dumb.
You know.
It's like haven't you ever drink tea before?
I don't even know what to say.
But point being
The only thing we have left then is the next and the next is part of
the sort of chaining thing here that we're doing where we want the
debug elements to just sort of be able to stack up events inside them.
And so to do that, what we would say is alright the next element is
always going to be zero because we're training this onto the end,
which means that it's really just the element itself pointers that
have to get updated the oldest event and the most recent event
Oops, would become distorted vent in the case.
Where, where are they?
Sorry where there are zero.
Right.
So if we don't have anything on the on this debug element yet, which
means that, you know, both of these things are 0, then we're just
going to go ahead and put the stored event as the only thing in the
list, right?
It's both the oldest and the most recent.
So it's the entirety of the list, right?
But if there was one then whatever, the that most recent one is its
next pointer is now going to point to us.
And then the most recent frame is going to
It's for event, right?
And I always liked this kind of weird, like, cheesy way of doing this,
which is that, it's kind of fun, right?
I don't know.
You know if you guys are down with that
maybe you are, maybe you aren't
It's not really my problem.
At the end of the day, it's like everyone should eat lunch where they
want and everyone should have the lunch that they want, you know,
don't let other people tell you how to eat your lunch because that's
sort of that's lunch despotism, and it's not, okay.
So let's push forwards a little bit here.
Really know if we care about this stuff just quite yet.
I'm going to take a look at some of these other things first.
So all right I'm pretty sure we don't really want the region stuff to
be happening at the moment.
So I'm going to take a quick sort of Gander at this and say that that
soups that we don't want those for the time being.
I'm also going to say that we don't want that.
And that's how that goes sometimes.
Excuse me for Mark debug value.
In this case, again with the, with the add variable to group in this
So I think we still want this to be essentially doing what this is
doing here.
And so, what I want to do probably is make it so that there's the
concept, the store event thing we could probably do as a sort of a
sort of a utility function so I could I could maybe even do it just
like this, right?
So I want to do a store event and and that'll like, do this whole
thing for me and that way I can call it in more than one place if I
want to.
And go from there.
Okay, so here we go.
Internal void.
Here is my store event and I guess that's not so void after all.
So there's my store event, there's debug State, there's the debug
element, there's debug event.
And now, all I have to do is just make this thing.
Well, I guess I really don't have to do much.
I think about it.
I don't know why add very little group is still there.
I think that's pretty much all I would need.
I just now need a way to get the actual stored event, right?
And this should be stored event by the way.
Right.
And so what I need to do here is just have a way of getting this and
that's the thing that we don't know at the moment, so that's fine.
But
Now, what we can do and what is, what are you complainant?
Lets you stream is not a member of debug element.
Is that really true?
Are you, are you?
Are you just joshing?
I just messing with me, man.
Are you messing with me?
Where is my debug element?
Oldest event.
Oh, most recent frame.
It's not most recent frame.
Most recent event.
Duh, there we go.
So let's see here.
Okay, so we've got ad region, this is still doing that, that region
stuff.
So we're going to take that out for the moment.
There we go.
Oops, got a little bit zealous with my hot keys.
There ended up creating two versions of the compiled.
Always good to see them in mirrored.
So, let's see here, create variable group.
Again, this is not particularly relevant.
So I think at this point, I don't actually care link children to
behave like group.
I don't care about this at all, at the moment.
Matching Block events match.
Do you like it?
Open?
Debug.
That's all fine.
And then here is our store event.
Like that takes care of that and here up at the.
Where are you?
Yes, Mark Cuban value.
That also stores the event.
Now I suspect
I suspect that we probably will be able to clean up a bunch of this
code as well.
After things start to collapse down a little bit, at least that's my
assumption, but we'll leave that for later.
Okay.
So we don't care about the values group anymore.
We don't care about the ad tree anymore and we don't care about that.
Okay, so we're back to just now.
We're almost to the point where we can start to pull things back
together again.
Like I said this push sighs.
It's yellow.
Is something that was just a very bad idea.
That was my bad.
I apologize.
I hate it made a faux pas there.
It was a paw that was made of Pho.
Kind of like, you know, the programming equivalent of when you you
know you go to lunch and your sit at the wrong seat and everyone's
embarrassed and it's just kind of this, you know this horrible thing.
You just kind of run screaming and crying from the restaurant and it's
scarred you for life.
So anyway, let's let's just pretend this this stuff never happened
because this was just like bad and and we don't want it to happen.
So really, I'm just going to I'm just going to vaporize
That it's gone.
Like we're going to pretend that never happened and I mean that like
really literally, like we're just going to pretend it never happened
ever.
And then we're just going to say that these are all going to be back
to the way they were, right?
We're like I said, it was just a, it was just a mistake.
I admit that.
And we're just gonna, you know, like don't harp on it, man.
Right?
I already said it was a mistake.
Why you gotta why?
You got to keep bringing it up, you know, let's just move past it.
We need to move past it, you know.
Don't don't let your whole life.
We defined by the one-time.
Bad lunch.
You ate, you know.
So anyway, let's
Let's go in here, open debug block.
Yes, that's gotta be this way again, just, this is just putting it
back to the way that it was write.
Debug push structs.
Oops.
Okay.
So now in theory, we're totally set.
Now for what we wanted except for the one thing, which is the stored
event situation.
And so now we have to do
Is we have to just have a way of again, doing what we wanted to do
with the debug Arena stuff.
We wanted to do.
Frames and the stored.
We wanted those to work.
So that as frames come in and sort events come in, we will free frames
as necessary to make sure that we can store the new events that we
get, right?
And so, essentially we just have two things we've got new frame and
we've got store event, and those two things both want to like, get a
new piece of memory, right?
They want to get a new chunk.
And so what happens here is we want to, we want to have some way of
saying, if I can't get the memory that I need free of frames so that I
will be able to get the memory that I need.
And so again it's the same code that we wrote before, I just it's not
part of the Arena now.
It doesn't need to talk to the arena at all.
It just has to do something like, okay.
And in fact, this stuff looks like it can be simplified.
Now that to do looks like it can be fine.
So let's see.
That's just this, right?
Yeah.
So that's all good.
yeah, I think so, although I would note
That this is this should just be using our should be using our macros,
right?
This should use free list, deallocate or free lift allocate.
Right?
I would think.
Yeah.
So like this should just be this should just be free of us to
allocate, really sure.
Although I guess neither of these things could really use that now
because these are going to have to sort of do the recycling bit,
right?
Okay.
Alright, so let's write this then
I'm going to get rid of this thing.
And I'm going to say, okay.
This is essentially what we have and I don't know that I need 20
structure because we initialize everything.
So I think this will just look like that and we'll be good to go.
Yeah.
So what I need to do now is I need to be able to get these guys off of
the free list, right?
So if you remember, we have a source for these, right?
We have a source, not there.
we have a source for these guys, which is like these,
This is like our per frame storage.
So, these guys are the two things that come in every frame.
We get frame pointers, right?
And then we get stored events that kind of, you know, accumulate.
And so when we go to allocate either of these, obviously, the first
thing we're going to do is say, okay, just assume.
First of all, that we can get it from.
The actual store there.
And so then we have two cases if we actually got it.
Then we just say that whatever the first free frame is
is going to be equal to the next one.
Right.
So we're popping something off the free list there and off we go, but
if we can't and in fact, I think this, we might, we might want to just
say that this is effectively a while loop, right?
This is essentially like while not results.
we would say, okay, the debug state
We try to see if we can get the first free frame if we can then then
we're good to go.
Otherwise we will try to do a free frame.
And in this case again the frame that we are freeing we would need to.
Yeah.
It looks like we don't actually really pop that off either.
So we want to do free.
Oldest frame.
And so free.
All this Frame is pretty basic.
All free old is frame.
Does is go.
We have the oldest Frank here.
We say if there is such a thing as the oldest frame, then the oldest
frame is going to be the one that gets freed.
Frame.
And we might say here that we might even assert this because in
general, if we got into a situation where there was no more frames to
free, we shouldn't be calling for you all this Frame.
I don't know.
Well, I guess you don't really need to start.
We'll see.
So anyway, hmm.
You know maybe we would say here we'd say you know assert that there
is a framed for your something like that.
Anyway you go free, all this Frame.
We say okay the oldest frame, if there is one we grab it.
We do a free frame of it.
But first we also Advanced the pointer forward.
So we say, you know, the debug all this Frame.
Equals frame next.
And if debug State most recent frame,
Equals the frame, we were on the debug State.
Most recent frame equals zero.
Right.
So that's it.
That's just all we need to do to free the oldest frame and so when we
get a new frame, we're just going to do something like this where we
try to get it.
Can't we free it?
And we keep going right store event will do exactly the same thing
like so all that's going to happen.
Here is this going to be scored event instead?
And I guess I could change that to result.
and so,
Again, the only difference here is instead of first free frame, its
first restored event, right?
And that's really all there is not really much else to it.
So I think which is compiled that free frame doesn't take.
That's true.
It doesn't.
And let's just take a look and make sure all the rest of our stuff is
doing something relatively reasonable here.
Okay.
And the other thing I want to do is make sure that the free frame does
something recently.
Yes, it does.
Okay.
So I think we're in good shape there.
And so now we just need to kind of go through and do a little bit of
cleanup.
Here is me and get everything sort of into a happy State.
All right, so, let's see where our bugs are first.
I probably can step through this because we wrote a lot of code, we
don't really know what it's doing or rather, we think we know what
it's doing, but we don't actually know
But let's double-check.
So okay.
Oh, right.
That code was a little short-sighted now that I think about it.
This part where it has two free of frame is actually only necessary if
we're out of memory, right?
So if we have some memory, we could use.
Then we wouldn't actually need to do that.
So what we want to do here is actually this is the part that would do
you know do we have enough room to store this thing and then if not do
it
okay, so that would do essentially if Arena has room for
Then we allocate otherwise we don't write.
And I don't like, you know, I look at this and I again this looks like
something that I would like to be able to abstract as well, which I
probably could.
If I wanted to, I could probably make this an arena sort of thing that
it can do.
And I don't know if I should, maybe I should actually
I don't know though.
We'll find out.
So anyway inside this guy where we've got the new frame and we do
Arena has room for we're just saying, like, Okay, if we have room for
another debug frame in the debug State, and this is going to be the
like per frame Arena.
If our Arena has room for one of these things, then we will simply
allocate it.
Otherwise we won't write and so that's again.
Doing the exact same thing here.
And so that basically says well, however, much memory we're going to
set aside for storing per Frame data and just letting it pile up,
right?
We will use up to that amount and if we run out, we will then just
start freeing stuff.
Right.
And that'll be that so pretty straightforward, right?
And if I go down to where we actually set up our debug Arena,
Which is somewhere in here.
There it is initialize Arena.
What I can do is do a submarine out of that guy which for however much
we want to handle, right?
So we could just say, okay?
We're going to do a sub arena there and the sub arena for this guy.
Rena.
The Submariner for this guy is going to be our per frame Arena, the
arena that it comes from is going to be this one.
The memory index of the size is going to be.
I don't really know how much we want it to be.
I guess we could say that there is a total size memory size.
And this would be some fraction of the total memory size probably
three-quarters of it or I don't even know how much you want to donate
dedicate to it, right?
Something like this.
And that will just write, that will just allow it to sort of work in
there.
Now, that means that, in addition to debug Arena, we do need a
perfumery name here.
And off we go.
so,
Arena has room for.
I don't actually remember how we implemented that guy.
I assume we just passed the size of, yes, we do.
Oops, has room for
Yes, eyes in it.
So that's just size of keep up frame.
Oops.
And debug stored events.
Same thing.
Okay, and so let's see.
Allocate rent.
Wait what
oh,
I guess I didn't leave enough room.
I don't actually remember to be honest with you.
How much saw how much room is thing?
Actually has 64?
So yeah so I guess we would need maybe to take maybe only half.
Let's say
And leave the rest.
we probably should allocate a lot more, debug memory than that, but
you know,
You can change that.
Change that later.
All right, so in theory, we are now actually.
Oh, and you can notice our debug UI stuff is still working, which is
kind of nice.
So, in theory, we are now storing all of our debug data and restoring
it all based on the location that it came from.
So now, all we actually need to do is go through and start to actually
use that now to sort of populate our hierarchical views.
Then we should be back to roughly where we want to be, but without any
of the limitations that we had before, in theory, at least that's the
goal.
Now unfortunately how much time we got left, that's not going to tell
me.
Yes, we got 13 minutes so I'm trying to think of exactly what part of
this I want to start with.
First of all I would like to know why our frame?
Let's just maybe do this.
Why is our last frame time wrong?
Right, that's weird when you say.
Most recent frame wall seconds elapsed.
So where do we set the wall seconds elapsed?
So it's every time we do a frame marker, it's whatever the value R32
is.
So let's just see
What's actually happening there.
So in handmade,
Debug interface.
So we have frame marker, s elapsed in it.
So it looks like it's it mean that looks like it is correctly writing
it down.
So I'm wondering why we're never getting the right value there.
Now, one thing, I guess, one thing that I haven't really thought
through yet is when we're looking at the most recent frame, I'm not
sure exactly when things get put on the most recent frame list.
So let's see here.
Frame marker, a certification frame, put the stuff on there.
Finish the collation frame out re the frame of her paws for not.
Paused put it on the list, so it seems to me like that should be
working.
So, I'm going to go ahead and take a look and see why we're not
getting that, right?
I'm going to go into
That frame marker place and I'm going to see what's going on there,
right?
So, let's take a look right marker.
All right, so a program is running and now we've hit a frame marker.
Let's take a look at what's going on here.
So we've got our Coalition frame, the frame that's currently being
worked on which is right there and it's all seconds left are set to 0
which is exactly what we would expect.
We're going to come through here and set our
That's that looks like the right value.
And then we add it to the list.
So the most recent frame wall seconds, elapsed is wrong.
so,
this is wrong.
This is totally wrong.
That would explain it.
So right here.
This should also be setting the most recent frame, right?
Wait.
What did that say handmade debug to see if he changed on disk?
Visual Studio.
Did you change?
Did you write my file?
I know you did not write my file.
You better not have written my file.
Did you write my file?
I hate the fact that this thing rights to files.
I wish you could set it into a mode where it didn't touch your files,
like debug only mode.
Yes, I want to edit the buffer.
Yes,
Visual Studio.
Okay.
So
What I want to do here is set the most recent frame as well, that was
the part that was not actually happening the way it was supposed to.
So now in theory, oops, we should be back to having a correct frame
time.
And hey, there it is.
So that's what I would have expected and that's nice.
That means we're kind of getting our frames there.
I also kind of interested at this point in doing a little bit of
Statistics, the sort of a thing here I would like to know with are
stored events.
I'm kind of interested to know how many
You have them, we have stored, and what's going on there.
So, what I'm going to do is, I'm going to go here and, and basically,
print out the size that's being used of that Arena.
So, when we do last frame time, I all I want to do like a thing, which
which also prints out.
The per frame Arena used.
And this is just like how much B you know.
I just I just want to know like the basic byte count, right?
Of maybe like KB let's say something like that that's getting used of
that of that buffer.
And so that's I don't actually remember if we put that in here like
get Arena size remaining.
I guess is the opposite of it so we could just print that out.
That's fine.
I don't really care so we could do it.
going to size remaining and
so I want to take that feedback State per frame Arena and I want to
buy is the alignment
Oh, I get it.
It's how much would be left if we assumed an alignment of four so we
actually want to assume an alignment of one.
Just tell me the actual size.
Basically it
All right.
Anyway so we want to ask how much there is left in this per frame
Arena, let you know, space remaining or something like that, I don't
know.
And then we want to print that out and kilobytes.
So we're just going to divide by 1024 so that we have the thing in KB
and that's it.
Actually, that's all I actually wanted to print out and so let's see
what happens.
Get her inside is remaining connector over and want to marry me.
And that's a good point.
I need to pass the address there.
So, let's see.
Okay, so that's not really going to test our memory thing.
Anytime soon, as you can see, we are going to take forever to run out
of memory for our events.
Because right now, we're not pushing enough events through it, which
is, so I guess not particularly surprising given the fact that we
don't actually do anything except that one little test piece, I
suppose.
All right, so maybe that's not such a good idea.
I could do to sort of accelerate that process obviously is when we do
some Arena and and do this I could instead you know, just give it some
laughably, small thing like
You know, maybe like 32k or 128k of memory, something like that and so
it would run out right away.
Least that be the goal and so that's what we want to have happen,
right?
That's exactly what we wanted.
We wanted to go down and hit zero and now it's just like recycling
that memory.
So assuming that things are working properly in there.
That's exactly right.
And we're happy, at least I'm happy.
I'm going to go ahead and just
Through that just to make sure that it's still working properly and
let's see here.
Looks like that's the case.
Let's let's see if we ever hit this case.
We do
Yeah, so I mean we haven't really checked it very thoroughly, but it
does look like it's working the way we expect it to work.
And we could do something like this.
So I think we've got our cells in good shape now.
So I think I'm going to call it there and then the next thing because
the next thing we want to do is to then go like re-enable the UI stuff
and start playing around with the fact that now we have this sort of
centralized stuff.
So I kind of want to start smashing those things back together.
So that's pretty good and I think thats yeah that's I think that's a
good stuff.
Point.
I don't think we want to do anything else.
They're all right, so I think that's a pretty you don't.
One of the things I say a lot of times when we talk about programming
is it's just like you don't want to eat more lunch than you can
reasonably digest.
Right?
So, you know, a lot of times people go into something and their eyes
are too big for their stomach and they'll just wait over eat the
lunch.
And so what I'm trying to do here is just keep lunch to a reasonable
amount of food so that we don't get too fat.
But we do get enough food to to keep ourselves going good.
And so then we could also there's always again like I always say
there's always lunch tomorrow and so that's, you know, tomorrow's
lunch will be a you know, will be just as tasty as today's lunch and
you know we can we can eat some of those other foods that we didn't
eat today at that time.
So with that I'd like to go ahead and go to the Q&A.
Oops, if I type it correctly.
So if anyone has any questions about where we're at, please prefix
them with q: and ask me and and I will answer them.
Oo, when we come to do the AI system, do you think would be reasonable
to give the dudes, a gather lunch behavior?
Well, you know, if there's lunch, I don't know that the game has much.
Lunch Concepts in it.
But, you know, we could try insofar as what did you have for lunch?
I had campfire barbecue for lunch, which is the best barbecue in
Seattle.
It's very, very good.
It's only available on Thursdays and Fridays or if you're live in,
Georgetown on Saturdays but I don't so it's only on Thursdays and
Fridays and it's a fantastic fantastic.
Barbecue.
Anyone who's in Seattle is doing themselves a disservice.
If they do not go to campfire, Barbecue on Thursdays and Fridays.
So you should do that.
Doritos Ranger.
Imagine that you're young again and you're eating your lunch and you
can choose between a c and Java, like language in what you can work
with memory and much see like way.
But that language would say how you, how to implement, some ideas like
a python is about line offsets, which is not good.
I think, what would you choose then?
And why
I so don't understand that question at all.
Basically, I think C is a perfectly fine language, right up until the
part where you try to do.
More higher, more higher level organization and generation of code.
And so, see I think is good and I don't have a lot of complaints with.
See there's some minor things I would tweak but it's pretty good job
has just garbage.
I have no use for it whatsoever.
So I would say I pretty much always would pitch pixie and then I would
want you know, basically to add like the new features to it, that I
would want but but Java definitely, there's I don't feel like Java has
any redeeming social value whatsoever?
I don't, I don't
I don't think Java has a reason for existing it's it is not useful
thing.
Ever during hmh Khan, will there be an organized lunch at the
campfire?
Barbecue?
No, because handmade Khan is on Saturday and you cannot get campfire,
Barbecue downtown on Saturday.
as far as I know, anyway, they're they're usually in Georgetown and
that's very difficult to get to
does emacs offer more syntax support than what I am seeing at the
moment.
Do you mean to me and sentox highlighting support?
And if you mean seeing as how your support the answer is, yes, there's
a lot of weird syntax highlighting support in there but I don't use a
lot of it.
Let's see.
Any other questions about the code?
Is there anything that could be considered a free lunch in low-level
optimization?
Sure when Intel comes out with like a new chip, that happens to run
your code faster, and you didn't actually do anything.
That's definitely a free lunch.
Kubrick Caleb fair warning.
The optimizer might store the strings in the same place which will
break the whole grid thing.
No it can't.
You know, there's no way for
Or there's no way for it to store two strings in the same place, if
they're different.
Right.
So unless you're thinking of something, I'm not thinking of that's not
actually possible.
BTN games, do you suggest programming should be snacked upon
throughout the day as an alternative to a three-course code feast?
In general, I would say that that you want to do.
At least two blocks of two hours worth of coding everyday at a bare
minimum.
And preferably three.
And I mean, actual coding like not Facebook is open, not, I'm code,
reviewing something.
I'm really talking about, like, making code in the computer, you
should be spending, you know, preferably three, two hour blocks and
then, yeah, you're not probably going to get eight hours of
programming every day because realistically, you got a lot of other
stuff to do if, you know,
In the course of actually making a game.
There's lots of things to do.
I know I often times, nowadays, actually some days.
I don't get any time to program because I have tons of this stuff have
to do.
I have to do 3D block outs after you left things.
So I like, have to manage my, my, my time blocks and, like, some days
I get to do programming.
Sometimes, I don't, and that sort of thing.
But yeah, assuming that your job is programming and you're not having
to substitute and make art or do other things with it.
Then you should be doing, hopefully, three two, hour blocks a day of
solid coating.
If you can get for awesome.
I these days tend to get 3 plus the one from handmade hero.
So I do tend to do for roughly 42, H E blocks of things.
And I sometimes get five, because I'll get another like, you know, are
or to block of, you know, maybe I got to work on stuff at night, like
the witness or whatever.
But
But never let yourself go below to if you go below to something's
wrong.
Insofar.
As why do you think there have been no good new languages since see
are all the languages irons out to lunch these days.
Yes, they are.
The reason that I think is because see was like the last time we're
great programmers made a language.
and as far as I know, like pretty much every language that was made
since then was made by people who actually aren't great production
like commercial
Shipping programmers.
I mean, the people who made see like made eunuchs, right?
Like they knew what they were doing, and they knew how to like ship
actual code like actual software.
And and I think that that's part of it, it's one of the reasons, our
students excited about j.
I is because Jay I like what Jonathan blows languages.
It's the first time a programmer who actually really knows what
they're doing.
He is making a language and has shipped multiple very complicated,
very Advanced things by themselves in some cases, right?
I just don't know very many other times in that never happened and so
I think that that tends to be one of the big reasons that there are so
many languages nowadays.
But most of them just really aren't very good at at actually achieving
high quality software is just because the people who made them work,
Experts in making high quality software, they were either academic or
they were, you know, trying to make, you know, low quality software
quickly or things like that.
And so, the goals are the knowledge, we're not there.
One of the other
cookies, Revenge, do you feel there's a perfect balance between test
based coding so more or more efficiency optimization or do you prefer
one over the other
I'm not sure, I understand the question.
I feel like test based coding is a totally reason, totally reasonable
thing to do.
As long as you're not spending more time total in Development, I've
said this many times, basically development should be looked at as a
sort of global optimization problem.
But you're trying to do is you're trying to take the least amount of
time to make the best possible code right for the thing you're doing.
And so if if test base coat, you know, if test-driven development is
actually going to, if the amount of time it takes to make the tests.
Is less than the amount of time it would take you to debug problems.
Later, on that the test would have caught, then it's a good trade-off.
If not, then you're just wasting your time, right?
And look, a lot of people are dogmatic about those sorts of things,
but you can't don't be right.
There's only one thing that is actually true, and that is what made
the best code in the shortest possible time.
Like, that's what you actually wanted.
And so only do something like, test-driven Dylan or whatever to the
It's that it actually leads to the same quality product in less time
if it's not doing that, then it's a waste of time and it's hurting
your development process.
And so I don't think there's anything as like like, you're asking a
perfect bounce, whatever, it's more just like you need to know these
things.
You need to learn enough and get used to the way you program enough to
know when it's appropriate to do tests based because you know the
thing that you're working on is difficult to get right?
You know that if you spend
Time to make the test.
Now, you'll save a lot.
Time to bugging later and you you know your ship a less buggy product,
you should know those things.
And you furthermore should know the kinds of bugs you make so that,
you know, your test-driven development might not be the same as
someone else's because the kinds of tests you might need to make, are
different than the kinds.
I might need to make because maybe I don't ever make a mistake of kind
X, but I do make kind Y.
And you are the opposite.
You never make mistake, why, but you always make us take X.
Well, our tests should be geared towards that my test.
Should test for the kinds of mistakes.
I make right?
Etc, etc.
What are your thoughts on clang?
The sort like trying to build it in the source tree like that.
The source code is a mess.
It's a nightmare.
It's way too object-oriented.
And it's just like it takes thousands of lines of code and clang to do
something that you should be able to do in like, you know, one line of
code or something, right?
So I don't like that aspect of it, but in terms of the actual quality
of the product relative to say visual Studios compiler, it's actually
quite good.
So, you know, I think they did a nice job.
Even I don't, I feel like the coding practice isn't playing.
Make it a very hard sorcery to work with and probably a lot less
efficient, and probably a lot less easy to modify than it should be.
But even that said, compared to the competition, it's quite good.
The Maxis, I think he meant string literals like the OG flag.
I think not sure what that refers to.
What do you think about Unity, Etc?
I don't I don't have much of a thought about Unity.
Any any licensable tool you can really always evaluate it the same
way, does it do what you needed to do and if so then you could use it
if not then you can't.
I think the biggest problem that I see or the thing that I think the
mistake of popular make is They Don't Really account for all of the
problems with something like Unity or Unreal Engine or whatever.
And so you know I think
People don't really appreciate what actually goes into making a
quality game, even with unity.
Because a lot of times people will use Unity, but then the thing that
they ship is like really low quality, right?
And so, just using a license will engine, doesn't give you a
high-quality thing.
You still have to do a tremendous amount of work to make a
high-quality thing engines.
Aren't at the point where you can just like magically just be a
designer and not have to know anything about programming and expected
to come out.
Good.
Could the only time that really works if you're making something like
exactly like what the engines demo cook does or something, right?
Like if you happen to be making Gears of War, or maybe exactly you
probably can just use the Unreal Engine, right?
Or something like this.
But so I don't have much thoughts about those sort of things.
Personally, I have a very low tolerance for a lot of the design
decisions in a lot of those things, they aren't designed the way I
would design them and they don't work the way I want them to work.
So I tend to not like, to use most of that stuff.
I also don't like to be beholden to somebody else for my core
technology and that's just, you know, part of building a company and
so on.
So I have plenty of extra reasons why I wouldn't use something like
Unity but that's doesn't necessarily mean that you shouldn't so.
Yeah.
What's the biggest hurdle you've had to overcome so far on this
endeavor?
I don't think we've
Really had hurdles to overcome.
I mean, we're just we're just doing programming, you know?
Killer for 3,000.
What do you suggest for people who are in the first year of C++?
Newest projects for coding throughout the day.
Feel free to skip a few answers before.
I'm not sure what you mean by coding throughout the day, but, you
know, if you're just starting out, I've said this many times, I think
asteroids, is the best thing to make because it's the simplest,
really?
It's the most simple game you can do and it, but it still features.
All of the basic components.
I always say, start making asteroid game.
Because we can't make an asteroid game.
Then you're not ready to do any of these more advanced things, right?
So you should focus on like understanding how to make an asteroid game
first and then you move forwards.
Right hand made sure I was like, way more complicated than an asteroid
game.
Right?
And so, like, you someday when I do, like the intro to see e part
thing or whatever we do, I do.
Like, here's how you make.
Just asteroids, it's like a little ship, it can shoot like a missile
and there's a little asteroid on the screen and it can hit it, right?
Just doing that and that's a good way to learn because it's so basic.
It's so simple that you can really just focus on.
Can you can you just do the just very basic aspects of programming?
And so that's, you know, that's a good one.
I think.
Jesse Meyer.
Have you seen John Cleese this?
Talk and creativity.
If so, what are your thoughts on it?
Yes, I have.
I liked it.
Maybe that's a question to ask in the freestream.
We can talk more about it.
It's a first, how many more features will the debug system get it
already.
Eats most other engines lunch.
Well it's not really there yet.
Like I said we're we're still kind of had to do our organization and
get these things, right.
So we still need to now go in and put in the interface and like kind
of get that data working in a better sort of flow so we can see stuff
and then and then I'll be pretty happy with it.
So it's not really that.
Get lots of features per se but we just need to clean everything up
and make it actually work well, because we haven't gotten to that
point yet.
So I don't know.
That will necessarily add more features.
We might add some diagramming support, but that's about it.
Lexington to feel that taken Calculus 1 2 is need to become a good
programmer.
Probably not.
If you if you are never doing any simulation code, you could probably
get away with not taking Calculus.
If you're however, if you're going to do any, simulation, simulation
and my simulation, I mean, really any simulation?
So rendering would be including there because that's simulation of
light.
Sound would be, including there, because simulation of vibration
propagation, certainly
Physics certainly any even even fake physics.
All that stuff you need calculus.
So if you're if you're planning on doing like game, programming is no
question.
You need calculus.
If you're planning on doing a web server,
Probably don't need calculus.
That'd be my guess.
Thanks miss.
It was actually a GF flag for the MSP C compiler, enable, string
pooling lumping all string literals into a read-only portion of
memory.
So it only stores one of each different string.
Yeah.
I guess what I'm trying to say is, I don't know why that was brought
up though, because we don't care if it pulls strings.
It can't pool.
Two strings that are different.
Strings string, pooling only pools.
Two strings that are the same string, right?
And since we created a different string for each grid, it think they
won't ever collapse, right?
Does that make sense?
So it's like, we don't care what the compiler does, whatever it did to
produce strings that were all the strings.
We told to produce, they're going to be at different locations in
memory because they're actually Different Strings.
It can only pull strings if we generate the same string for two grids,
but in that case, we would want them to collapse.
Because that means the grid is the same.
And our definition, the system is if the grid the same, then it's the
same, right?
Let's see, I'm just roids.
Do you think there really hasn't been a good language in C period?
Yes, I would probably say that.
Although to be fair I don't know, like all languages, right?
I mean there are so many languages out there that to really say that
definitively you'd have to be someone who just studies languages all
the time.
What I should perhaps what I could perhaps take more definitively is I
don't know of another good language that's been made since see.
And and to be fair, you know, I don't even, I would soften outside
late, I don't know of another language that's been developed since see
that isn't just basically see with a few minor additions or something.
Because there have been things like d for example or something.
Which maybe, you know, I haven't really spent any time with it but
maybe is like, as good as C4, what you're doing, but doesn't really
appreciably Advanced Beyond it, right?
And so that's probably more of the right way to say it.
So yeah.
Insofar as what if it doesn't pull strings.
And to same string, literals get different addresses with the system
lose its lunch.
No, because again, that's fine each.
One of our debug locations is intending intentionally.
Generates a different string so that each location gets a different
quick.
So we don't actually want it to pull the strings for any particular
reason, but we also don't care if it does because since they're all
different, they won't pool.
And Signum 73.
I actually don't believe that good language is relative to what you're
doing.
That's kind of the place where I sort of depart from that.
I always prefer to program in C pretty much period.
So if I wanted to do something prologue, like I would want to
implement whatever the part of prologue is that I wanted in see
because what invariably I find is that lets say, I
Did actually go use prologue to do it a, whatever the prologue, like
compiler or interpreter.
I used to do that, I probably can't run it on all the machines.
I might want to run it on and then I end up in the situation where
like, my code doesn't work anymore or whatever or it's too slow and I
can't optimize it because it's like someone else's like crappy old
prologue whatever.
So I actually
Actually, literally no longer write anything that isn't in.
See, like, the handmade hero GitHub.
Validator, I actually wrote myself in C, right?
And the reason that I did that
Was just because every time I've ever done something like, oh, it's
just a little web thing, I'll just write it in PHP or whatever.
I always regret it.
It always crashes.
They change like the the PHP to a different version and now doesn't
run anymore or like, I try to like move it from one machine to the
other, but like, oh, it required like my sequel to store the thing and
that's not running.
And it goes right.
Whereas here, I just know, nope, it's here's the C code.
I recompiled it, it never crashes, never goes down.
It can handle like a massive amount.
Of throughput.
So I don't have to worry about like, my machine being slow or
something like that and like, hey guess what they have me here at
GitHub valladares, been running for, like, God knows how long never
had a problem with it.
It's trivial for me to just move to another machine.
You just copy to files and you're done.
So yeah, like no, I am.
So not okay with the concept that like, oh, I'll just use this other
language.
I've never had that work.
Never not even once.
So yeah.
So I use see even when I'm just going to do like a little
You know, a little thing that's not meant to be whatever.
And so one of the reasons that I really want, like I said us a real
strong successor to see is because like right now, Eileen very heavily
on metaprogramming to do stuff.
And also, I can't really take advantage of a lot of people's, like,
libraries and stuff because people don't tend to write libraries for
see anymore, right?
They tend to write libraries for like C, sharp or Java or something.
And so, I would really like there to be a successor to see you.
Comes along so that the world would start using that and so there'd be
a lot more of that happening and a lot less of these other languages
which I think are pretty much universally bad and literally should
never be used.
All right, I'm going to go ahead and wind down here.
Thank you everyone for joining me, for another episode of handmade
here.
It's been a pleasure coding with you.
As always, if you would like to follow along at home with the source
code, you can always do.
So, by pre-ordering the game which comes to the source code in every
night, you can download it after I finish here, I uploaded to the
server so that you can stay up to date.
If you want to do that, 10 made hero dot-org, you can also find links
there to other useful things such as our Forum site which has an
antidepressant guide ports to Mac and Linux.
Those sorts of things a patreon where you can support our video series
if you like what you see and want to donate.
And
So we have a tweet bot, which treats the schedule at you.
So if you would like to know when we are going to be live, that is the
place to go.
It is always kept up to date, at least.
If I don't forget to upload the schedule that's about it.
I will be back tomorrow for the final stream of this week, 5 p.m.
Pacific Standard Time and of course we will be streaming next week the
lead-up to handmade hero con, which is coming our conference.
I don't know if there are any tickets left, I think there are
There were like 25 left when I checked last time, but if you go to
handmade conduct org, you can find some information about our
conference.
There were having on December 5th.
It's got a great lineup, actually, if you are planning on coming to
that.
Where are we here?
Hey, Mike on 2015 schedule, we've got Tommy referenced, Mike, actin,
Pat Wyatt, Jonathan Blow and Ron Gilbert which is kind of a crazy
lineup of people.
Base of the program was responsible for some of the, you know, most
famous games of all time, back to back.
So it's pretty cool.
We're working on finalizing sort of the AV set up.
Now we're hoping to be able to stream it here on handmade here as
well, but I don't know if we're gonna be able to do that because it's
not something that we technically specialize in.
So we're going to do the best we can.
But anyway point being we'd love to see you there like I said there
are still a few tickets left so if you want to go to that check it
out.
That's about it for today until
Tomorrow have fun programming and I'll see you guys on the internet.
And, you know, don't forget to eat lunch, right?
Most important meal of the day.
Thank you.
He's everyone.