Start recording.
Hello everyone and welcome to handmade hero.
The show where we Cody complete game live on stream.
We are well I think it is probably time to definitively handle our Z
situation because we've kind of we've only got a few things left to
deal with.
I think before I'm comfortable saying, let's let's move to mostly game
code and we've worked out a lot.
Energy System stuff.
I wanted to work out and that'll kind of grow over time, but we, you
know, that's been looking kind of nice.
But we really have got sort of this, this vestigial remain, where we
played around with Zia Bunch.
We never really came to a conclusion about exactly how they should
work in a 2.5 D, sort of environment.
And now I think we have a better idea of what we need from Z.
And so I think maybe this week, what I might try to do is just kind of
tackle that issue and try to get the renderer to the
A point where I'm comfortable with it saying that, you know, this
could be a reasonable shipping version of the interface and like we
won't have to tear out or redo a bunch of code later on because of a
bunch of choices that we made now, right?
Because yeah.
Like you know, at some point in development, you're going to go into,
you know, any particular piece of code you're going to go into a stage
where you're going to be.
Really heavily using that piece of code to, to do lots of stuff.
And so, you know, usually I try to do enough due diligence with
experimenting with that piece of code in real as real as scenarios as
I can before, I start leaning on it really heavily just because I
don't want to write you know a ton of code based around this one
concept and then find out that that concept is wrong, right?
So sometimes you don't have to worry about that because the number of
people who are depending on those decisions,
Is is low, right?
And if that's the case, then it's really not a big deal to change your
mind.
A lot even late in the project.
It's not a big deal.
But when you think about something as critical as how does Z work,
well, if we spend a lot of time tuning, how things are positioned on
the screen or how they look, or how they're sorted based on a certain
set of rules and then all of a sudden we upend all those rules we met
through have been throwing out all of that work.
And so I typically don't want to do.
I don't want to have those sorts of things happen if I can avoid them,
sometimes you can't.
But sometimes, you know, you
You can and you want to make sure you can as much as possible.
I because we were happy to be posting handmade Con 2015, videos.
All this week on the Molly rocket blog, I would also point out that
actually Mike act and if you go back to his post here,
This is news 35 here.
His post his video from handmade con.
He actually talked about something similar in here.
If I recall correctly, he was talking about the fact that some
decisions even game design, decisions can be extremely costly to
change later on.
And his example, for that was how fast does the character move in a 3D
environment because if you can look out over the world and you know,
you're moving,
Being a certain distance per second in that world that combined with
the streaming speed of the media, like the hard drive that you're
streaming off of, or the Blu-ray disc, or whatever it happens to be
those two things together.
Combined to determine exactly how much visual Fidelity you can put in
that world, right?
If I'm going you know at a certain rate through the world, the hard
drive can only Supply data so quickly know and you know I can compress
it a certain amount but there's only so much I can compress it and
The data that's coming in, can only be a certain density as I'm moving
at that rate.
Because if I can't keep up, then eventually, you know, the player
would that would stall or, you know, it would there wouldn't be
anything there or something bad would happen, right?
And so if you pick that speed to high, all of your game assets will be
modeled at too low a Fidelity because they didn't think they had that
kind of a budget because the streaming couldn't have pulled the data
in quickly enough.
Similarly, if you pick that speed
too slow, all of your assets will be to finally modeled.
So then later on, we decide oh the player really needs to move twice
as fast as this.
Well now you have to go back and decimate.
All of your art assets down to a lower level of detail to meet that
new streaming, requirement and all sorts of things like this.
Now sometimes you have automated system in place to take care of this.
Sometimes there's you know blah blah blah blah.
But you get the idea, some decisions have consequences that are very
significant in terms of the amount of time that you've spent doing
things depended on them and other
Don't.
And I think that Z and positioning in the world is definitely one of
those things that has a lot of dependencies on it.
And so it's something that I want to make sure that we have correct.
Now, as we go into writing, a bunch of code that depends on it and you
can already see, just in our test code, it's all hacked with Z.
It's all kind of hacky and weird and so now is a good time.
I think to go through and make that stuff work correctly and and you
know, just kind of
Get the Z situation figured out.
And so one of the things that I want to do there, well, a couple
things I want to do one is I want to make sure that Z4 hover works
correctly because I want to basically be able to say that entities
always have an XYZ position and that XYZ position tells you where they
are in the game, you know, on the screen game screen.
But then I also want to
To have a secondary.
Z that is a slice through the 2D world and that's just for stacking
rooms on top of each other and that Z will actually do prospective
scaling.
So basically we will not prospectively scale anything in an individual
game room because the art assets are all 2D, orthogonal, it wouldn't
make any sense for them to scale.
It just looks weird.
We tested that out a little bit.
It doesn't really look right and so we're not going to do that.
But we are going to do is when a room is on top of another
other room and we like move up to that room or down to a room.
We want to have that do that perspective scaling because it was really
nice effect and that doesn't fight the art assets really in any
particular way.
So that's what I want to do.
I want to start tackling that issue and figure out how to make that
clean and efficient for all of the rendering that the entity rendering
code and all that stuff.
So that when we're putting in all these values as we
To liked weak entities and how they're supposed to behave.
We don't have to go back and redo it all later.
When we decide that we have a better way to do Z or whatever.
I want to get that better way now.
And like I said, I think we've played around enough and seen enough to
make an educated decision here about what we can go with and then
stick with it.
Now, a reminder today is a 295.
So if you're trying to follow along at home day, 294 is the day you
will want to unpack for source code to start with.
That's what I'm starting with.
Now, let's go ahead and just refresh our memory as to where we left
off.
Although again, it's not particularly important.
In some sense because we are sort of starting a new run here, but we
had gotten to the point where we had a number of creatures working, we
have the ability to attack and various directions with our little
stand in sort of, we put a little plate rock that we had in there.
And so we've got most of these things working.
And you can see, we don't need a regular grid.
Anymore as well.
And so the things that we had sort of, you know, on the table where we
were like we got to work on these.
The two things that we had to do, where we had to sort of get RZ
situation straightened out, and we had to get our Collision detection
finished because we only have kind of rudimentary protection there
right now.
So those are definitely things that we will do, but right now I'm
going to focus on the Z.
So in order to focus on that Z, the first thing that I'd like to do is
I'd like to build a case for us.
You can see that there's there's one situation where
Are we are sort of using that Z.
You can see right here is I go from room to room.
You can see that it sort of goes up and it goes you know, pulls out a
little and comes back, but that's really the only case that we're
using the perspective Z at the current right at the moment, right?
And so that yeah, that's basically all we're doing.
As far as prospective Z right.
Now, what I'd like to do is construct a room here, where we could go
up and down between
Different rooms and so what I'm going to do is I'm going to create
sort of a stairwell, kind of a pattern that is designed to get us from
one room to another.
And we'll sort of try to figure out exactly how you would go up
between two rooms in the first place.
And I'm guessing that it'll be something like, you know, we'll put
well actually put some of these these hobble points in here, right?
Well, sort of make it so that we can, you know, hop up up up up and
and off we go, these familiars are
Early kind of annoying, aren't they?
They just keep following me around.
Well, I guess that's just what familiars do.
We, of course, do have a way to turn them off, I suppose.
I think that was in here somewhere.
Did we we don't obey that anymore.
Oh well well so much for that.
Anyway.
So what I'm going to do is I'm just going to start by heading over to
the world generator and I'm going to go ahead and say that that that
standard room
Which is really kind of a stupid concept.
I don't know why we have a this.
It's just, you know, because World Jen will be sort of the first thing
that we start with probably as we're working on the game code proper.
I just haven't decided to really make this any fancier but yeah.
Inside the world gencode I'm going to hack something in here which
will basically.
Yeah, it'll make sort of a floor Collision that kind of goes upward as
as, as you kind of walk up it.
And so in order to do that,
I think what I'll do is say all right, here's you know, the normal
code, right?
And what I'm going to do is say that, you know, we've got these
offsets being plus or minus these random bilaterals.
I'm going to turn that off for now.
So this looks more like a standard room.
And then what I'm going to do is I'm going to come down here and say
well or actually I guess I don't really need to come down anywhere to
say it.
I guess I'm going to say all right if the offset X I don't know what
it would be.
Lets say the offset X is 10.
Okay.
If the offset X is 10 and I'm going to bound the offset Y for the
length of my stairwell.
I don't know exactly what it'll be but let's say that it's greater
than 4 and
Less than or equal to 8.
So it's between four and eight, four, five, six, seven, eight will be
the stairwell.
We're 5 6 7, maybe, maybe, just for hops, would be enough.
I don't know.
So we'll do something like this.
And then what I'd like to say is okay, the P dot offset Z, I'm going
to go ahead and make that be equal to, you know, I don't know a
quarter, step /, / offset why
So basically offset y, minus 4.
If we do.
So now our Z offset should kind of go up as as we go there and, you
know, probably that's actually now I think about the wrong way to do
it.
I should probably do it backwards so I should probably do it something
more.
Like it's a trying to think of how to say this, right?
If I do it this way, offset y.
Oh well that's okay.
Why goes up
I always forget, y, goes up in our world, my goes up, so it's fine.
So now if you take a look at what happened here, right?
I don't know which one we said that was we said us at y equals 10,
right?
So I figure one, two, three, four, five, six, seven, eight, nine, ten.
It's this one right here in theory, right?
But you'll notice that it doesn't look like it's anywhere different
than it was already.
And there's a very good reason for that.
And that is because we even if this works even if that
Room code works properly.
We don't offset things by their Z value in the first place right now.
At least I don't recall us doing that.
Maybe we do, maybe we don't, but I don't think so.
I don't know.
That's a good question.
Do we?
Maybe we still do?
I don't know.
Well, let's find out because I don't actually know.
I was thinking that we
I was thinking that we don't anymore, but then we also kind of had
that dude who like was you could get on him and he would move up and
down.
And I don't really remember now, so I'm thinking that maybe we
actually should see this offset Z coming into effect because this is
not a displacement Z.
It was an off suit.
I think that was still the one that did get displaced.
So, never mind.
I think we should have seen that.
So let's just double check in there and step in to make sure that
that's all good.
Because again the fact even the fact that I can't ever remember how
she is supposed to work.
Is another good example of just how not settled it is, right?
Like that's the kind of thing.
We don't want to have to be second-guessing all the time and so that's
just yet another reason why I want that settled definitively.
So let's see if we ever get in here we never did it.
All right so that's always great.
So what's the problem here offset?
Ah, I see.
Offset X is actually, these are relative ranges.
I was thinking they were at the kind of absolute ranges we were using
in the other set.
All right so that's obviously wrong.
So ought to say, we'll do three and we'll do it between 0 and m 3.
All right.
Well, I'm glad I looked at that.
Okay.
All right.
So there they still they are still there, right?
You can see that the Z does actually.
All set properly.
And so I can actually kind of climb up it, it's not as much as I
needed to be and also that offset why that offset does look like it's
going.
Down, which is interesting.
Right.
Because, why is supposed to go upward in our system?
So, as y increases.
Oh, and I guess, well, this is probably why.
We don't need the - for anymore.
There we go.
Much better.
So here I can kind of climb up here and unfortunately, that's still
not quite high enough.
I also want to say this is this offset why we probably want it to be
maybe something more like between negative 2 & 2, something like that.
And I mail make that a little bit steeper.
Alright, so here we go.
As we go up and you can kind of see like if I if I get up in there,
you can kind of see that I'm like, sort of hopping up to the next
level effectively, if I hop on that chain, where it's from on the
other chain, I don't, right?
So, there I go, hopping up, and now, I'm on sort of the next level.
So now what I need to do is just put a room on top, so I can see the
room, like, above me, basically, instead of having rooms, that kind of
go off to the side, which are not
Full at all at the moment.
So what I want to do is say okay I've got, you know,
Two rooms and I'm always going to have the door go up.
So you know I would say instead of doing random Choice Series 2 here,
I'm going to say that we're going to do a random choice where we're
going door up.
So yeah, what is door direction?
For door up?
It looks like to
And so that way there's always a door up and we should be good.
Let's see.
All right, that is a bit hard to read.
I don't mind telling you, not the easiest thing in the world to read.
I can sort of still see it.
But you know, I think that the top layer is not getting faded out at
the moment, so it's a little bit crazy and that's not great.
Not great, not great Bob.
Okay, so let's see here, if I can and I also have these familiars, I'm
going to turn those off because they're driving me nuts.
The moment familiar.
Too many familiars.
all right, so let's
Up up here.
So there's one hop, two hop, three hop for hop.
And you can see the new room coming to view their and I should be able
to kind of be up in that room now, right?
And so now I'm actually in that top room.
And that's all fine.
Of course it's extremely hard to see.
So this is again, we're going to have to pay probably start drawing in
some floor tiles there.
So what I might do here is I might start to expand those.
I'm going to try expanding those sort of, you know, Stan, double
markers so that they're kind of more tile shaped.
Just so I can, you know, until we have tile Graphics in there that we
want to
You specifically, I can have sort of a clearer idea of what's actually
going on.
So I'm going to come in here while we're sort of standing up on this
thing and I'm going to try to move that.
I'm going to try to expand that stand about Point thing so that it's
considerably larger than it was.
So here's a traversable 's and here is the size that they are
currently.
I'm going to expand them out.
2.4, I'm just going to see what that looks like.
Hmm, I might go even larger than that.
I'm going to go out to maybe.
How big is 99?
I could go.
I could go even further.
So I could go to like 1.2 or something and still have space between
them.
Yeah.
Yeah, so that's not that's not too hard so it's actually pretty easy
to justify.
All right.
And so you can see
You can see that, I guess our Alpha is at the moment turned off
because that bottom layer is not really faded out at all, which is not
great.
And
I suppose that's not really the end of the world, what I could do.
What I could do is, and what if we fix the Z?
Sorting remember these guys don't see, sort properly right now because
there's these are all set to particularly hacked values as well.
But what I was going to say, is these
These things could also I supposed to be outlined to make them a
little clearer to see as well.
So I could do something like, I don't know why I closed the game just
then, but I could do something like, pushing your wrecked outline as
well as a sort of a wrecked thing on here.
So we've got, you know, the traversable
T.
And here I've got my V to appoint.
You a half half and
I guess this would just be black, probably just something to Edge it,
you know, something to Edge it out.
So yeah.
All right.
So
First things first, like that's actually much clearer.
If we were sort of doing the proper, if we were actually Alpha, fading
it out.
It would actually be quite clear what was going on.
So, I think we're actually to a point where we can start to use this,
right?
So I would say this is exactly what I want being able to come up and
down these stairs.
As I do, hopping wise is exactly what I wanted.
So, I think I just would say that our goal is to take this, which is
all
dated in properly and not fading out properly and all that other stuff
and just go through the renderer and clean out that input specs for
it.
So that all this stuff works the way it should work.
And why isn't it?
Do we know did I turn fading off or something?
Do we know why fading isn't fading?
Is that?
Anyone know, anyone, just anyone know anything.
So it faded out, so it looks like it's just not fitting out the
rectangles.
Actually.
Looks like everything else faded out.
Why is that the case?
So when we do a push wrecked outline, the global Alpha did the global
Alpha get reset or something.
Or as the global Alpha, not obeyed.
If the global Alpha is not a bay, that's a pretty simple fix, that's
just because we didn't obey it, right?
So Global Alpha,
Hey, look.
It's not obeyed.
So that's pretty simple.
If we want the global Alpha to be applied there.
We can just say, well, when we push the wrecked on here, we'll take
the global Alpha and and multiply it in, right?
So, that's much better.
All right.
So now we're in pretty good shape actually already.
And you can see that mostly what we're left with now since the global
Alpha actually was working just fine is, we're just left with an
inability to actually see some of the people whose have hacked Z
values because they're sorting below the ground tiles, which should
actually support, which should be below them, but are actually above
them, right?
There's also some interesting stuff here.
Like once we have the stairwell, it's very obvious to me.
That some things that shouldn't happen are happening.
Like, for example, we don't really disallow jumps to arbitrary
Heights.
So like, you know, certain things can happen that probably shouldn't
happen.
Like, I can go from here and because there's no other tile to my left.
I can jump all the way down to that one, which is probably not what
should happen, right?
But you know that is what's happening?
Oh well, so
Oh yeah.
I think that's about it.
So let's go ahead and tackle that Z stuff.
I don't know what we want to do in terms of
Drawing that lower layer.
I think, you know, my, my suspicions anyway.
Is that drawing that lower, that layer below us.
I feel like we don't really want to fade that out because we may have
a hole in the ground where we would want to see down to that layer.
So I'm actually I think I'm going to actually add exactly that so that
we can make sure that is clear.
So handmade world's most dot CPP.
I want to do an ad standard room on a, do like a knockout.
Out so that basically nothing gets created, you know, if offset X is
equal or is greater than equal to negative.
Five, let's say and offset X is less than or equal to negative 3 and I
may be accidentally removing the floor out from under somebody who
needs to stand there and I apologize.
For that.
You know what?
I'll probably do.
Well, I don't know what I'll do.
I don't know, I just don't know.
So if it's in there and the offset Y is greater than equal to, you
know, -3 and offset Y is less than or equal to negative.
To note hole down to floor below.
and then all of this stuff can happen, otherwise,
Right?
And so part of the problem here is that the standing on is going to be
null in those cases.
Have someone was trying not going to try to play something there that
would go poorly and we may have a bug about that.
So, yep.
And that is exactly what I was saying was the problem.
Add snake, peace, segment thingy.
So my turn off the snake.
And we'll check the monstar as well, but I think we're good.
Okay, so there's the whole right.
And I may need to move that whole a little bit, just to for optimal
viewing, but there you can kind of see I'm looking down through the
hole.
And I'm seeing the world below me and I'm going to make one more.
I'm going to move the whole a little bit up.
I think where is the monstar added room 34?
So we'll move, let's move that.
A little bit in why?
Can we move that up to like six potentially?
Just want to get the monster out of the way, so he's not in the hole
and where does the snake snake is X2?
So we could then re-enable, the snake as well, if I move that whole
up, I think.
So if I come through here, and I say well, alright, my offset why I'm
going to make that be much higher up.
So I'm going to make that be like, you know, maybe 02 - one sort of
I'm at one, that's it - one.
I think that is all I really wanted.
And so now I'm also going to need in addition, I'm going to need a
right.
That was not what I want to do additional for.
So I need one more floor above this floor, right?
Because you can kind of see, I want to see it Fade Out below below
here.
So, when I do a standard room,
In here as I go through and I add my room.
So I'm going to add a third room and I think, I don't know, I don't
know how the door creation stuff here works, this is not the Z.
Door thing is not met.
Yeah, this is not super relevant.
I don't think at the moment, this may get in our way because we had
some weird logic here.
That was
Doing all kinds of crazy stuff.
So I'm not sure what will happen here but we'll see.
Hopefully we can climb up to the next level as well.
Oops.
You can see it makes it annoying to play as well.
If we don't get that, like I really want to make it so that you can't
hop off those stairwells as you're going up, so that it won't
accidentally pick the wrong thing.
so there we can now see kind of down to another layer below us and I'd
like that to fade out and at the moment, it's not, right, so as I come
through there,
I definitely want that to fade out.
And I also our cameras e interpret is a little bit odd and that's
probably due to the motion of the head as well.
So, we'll have to see what's going on there.
Oh man, the snake is going up the stick snake.
Did you just?
The whole snake, just went up the stairs.
All right.
Well, good job snake.
I guess that's the problem with creating rich simulations is just even
when you're just getting started, stuff does all these weird things
and the snake just left.
It went up the stairs.
Okay, well, alright.
So anyway, we should we could probably also at this point, D,
obnoxious eyes are tiles because let's be honest, they're pretty
obnoxious right now.
So maybe I'll also just go ahead and fix that.
You got to admit that orange color.
When we're talking about a big old bright, huge Square, na easiest on
the eyes, not the easiest thing on those eyes.
So let's make that the I'm standing on you color, because it sure is
easy to see.
And then, let's go ahead and change this here out to something, a
little more Placid like 50% gray.
That sounds better, maybe not because of gamma.
All right.
So maybe something a little more like that and maybe just because
we're in a forest, maybe we'll tinted green, you know what I'm saying?
Just a little bit, just a nice little, let's just fire, a few little
green things in there, you know, some of the little green happy
things.
Alright, so now we're getting there and yeah and like I said, we've
got some work to do a bunch of stuff that this kind of reveals for us.
It's nice that we can work on.
For example, I can do this.
Probably I'm guessing.
Oh, no, I can't cool.
That's below the tolerance.
I guess, 45.
I was like, I thought I could probably hop down there as like.
We definitely don't want that to happen, but it didn't happen, so
that's good.
But yeah, you can kind of see.
We've got some work to do here.
Obviously, we want to fix that fading out.
And we want to start working on getting that Z spec, correct.
So let's see here in this situation that I feel like I want that to
fade out.
I feel like we were maybe a little bit.
Overzealous because I don't want to have it go down too far.
I don't want well.
The problem with having a go down that far is that means we have to
simulate all the people that are down there but at the same time I
don't know.
That could be kind of cool.
I mean it's kind of neat to look, you know, if you imagine you're
typically going the other direction, right?
I'm typically going down and so, if you kind of imagine, you know, I'm
going down to the dungeon and I see down there.
There's like a magical sword thing that I want to get.
That's two levels down, right?
That's kind of cool.
So I'm guessing that probably what we would want to do is instead of
fading it that way, you know, we might want to say that the global
Alpha does go out but not 20.
So you know it's more like
Fade bottom start Z is, you know, much earlier in, so it's like that
or whatever, but it doesn't go out till a long time down.
You know, so it's kind of just hazy and foggy down there and we could
make that go to Black in dungeons.
Like it's like lit, you know, more poorly or who knows what?
But that actually seems kind of cool.
And you know what?
I'm going to take that even further and just say, let's see what
happens if I'm to add a few more rooms because that just seems pretty
pretty great.
Well, you know, let's just add 6 stacked on top of each other.
So this is just a giant stack of room.
Alms for no reason at all.
Okay, so I'm going to go ahead and and head up here.
I also I wonder I wanted to see who is the slow people who is slow.
So begin Sim update and render world.
It's weird.
These guys are the slow guys in this sort of situation.
I feel like we should go find out exactly who's slow there and speed
them up so that we don't have to worry because in real in retail mode,
you know, in release filled, we're lightening fast even at this point
and so there's something kind of stupid happening possibly some
clearing to 0 or, you know, other things that are just convenience
things that if we got rid of them in this case, they would fix the
speed issue there.
And we should probably do those so that we don't have.
Slow, debug builds because I don't really like having to build and
release.
A lot of people just build and release all the time but I'm not really
into that.
I like having a debug build.
So anyway,
So, that's kind of cool, right?
Like
I think that's staying in the game.
I mean that's just really cool and I don't, I don't I don't think
that's really something I want to get rid of.
So I'm going to say that that fade bottom can just keep on moving out,
right?
And and we'll just work on the actual effect that's down there but I
think that's pretty cool and I think that's worth keeping in there.
All right so let's kind of come up here.
Let me see what's going on.
So I'm going to come up up up up.
Oops, I always there now.
Is this the last floor?
Now we, this is one more floor, so I should be able to come up here,
right?
Am I right about that?
I don't know if I am or not.
Snake.
Get out.
Get out of the way.
All right.
And one more guess.
Yeah.
Alright, so you can see the transition here, pretty clearly, right?
You can see it kind of fading out there.
In the distance.
And so you know in you can see like I just I think that's pretty cool
and I think we're going to want to keep that around because you can
see what's kind of happening.
There is I'm looking all the way down through this hole in the floor.
And I'm seeing, you know, here's my level of the dungeon, here's the
next level down here is the next level down here is the next level
down from that.
And I'm even seeing a dude, like moving around down there, doing some
Off which I just think is kind of cool gameplay wise.
So I think for like pits like that I think we're going to want that
because that's just too neat and I never see that in games so I feel
like that's a cool thing to have in a 2-D game because mostly that's
something 2D games just don't do.
So I'd like to keep that in there because I think that's kind of
interesting and I just haven't seen it explored much.
All right.
So yeah so that feels pretty good to me.
Can you see that there's the snake going down there?
All right, so that's all good.
And I think what I might do, what have I got, I've got about 5, I got
20 minutes left, so I think what I'm going to do.
Besides blow my nose because it's allergy time.
Here in Seattle.
I think what I'm going to do.
Is I want to just quickly check to see if I can make it.
So this isn't too slow because I don't want to have to use the the
release builds all the time and their way faster.
Right?
So like for example, if I go
Into the build-up at.
If I change it to release my build, we're 60 frames a second all of
sudden, right?
And 60 frames a second, using almost no time, right?
Because this Frame display here, I think that's the, that's the time
that we're like, waiting for the operating system to do stuff.
So,
Literally like we're taking almost no time of the sixtieth of a second
whereas in the other one, we can't even hit 60 frames a second.
So, the difference there is pretty huge and it means that something
we're doing in debug mode is very expensive, and I just want to go
figure out what that is because we can probably just have an optimized
version of just one thing and then be able to run at this speed in
debug mode, right?
And I'd like to do that and then we'll we basically left ourselves set
up with all of the problems on screen that we have to solve this week.
And so, that'll be perfect.
I think for what we want to do
So yeah, and you can kind of see.
Yeah.
Right.
Like we're totally 60 frames a second right now, so I'm not sure.
Now, if we switch the software renderer, we would not be because the
poorest offer render.
I want it to want to see how bad it is with that.
Where is this offer render again?
There we go.
The poor software renderer cannot render that many over drawers of the
screen at all, right?
And we could, you know, we could make it happen because what we do is
we'd start culling we do box culling on the tiles and we could toad
will, you know, probably someday.
We'll go back and as a fun stream after the game is all done, get the
software renderer running at 60 frames a second again because it's
just, it's fun.
But yeah, when you draw that many things on top of each other, it's
too much for it.
So, yeah.
But anyway, oh, and you know what?
You know what?
That's actually not true either.
I guess we don't know.
We never optimize the rectangle fill.
So the rectangle Phil isn't even running through the optimized path.
So we don't even know how slow this off Runners point being.
It probably wouldn't have been nearly that slow, but it still would
have been too slow because it can't software.
Renderer probably can't do that many layers.
At least I would be surprised to learn that it could.
So anyway what I want to do is I just want to kind of figure out what
we're doing there.
That's so onerous.
And so if you remember correctly, it begins.
Sam was a big time waster, right?
So you come in here, too, what was it?
Let's see, you come in here and you're like frame display.
So that is waiting for the operating system, right?
I believe, is that correct?
Yeah.
So that's that's waiting for the OS as far as I know and or well not
entirely true so that's not that frame display.
Also counts.
Also counts, the renderer starting time.
So we probably want to be more granular with that.
I think because we don't really know.
What's going on there.
So let's find out
So win32 display buffer and window.
What I'd like to do here, is just say, okay, let's let's take a look.
This is the case we care most about here.
So I'm going to do a thing where we just do begin block and block.
You can block.
And block.
So here I can say well how long does swap?
I first take, how long does opengl renderer commands take and now I
can actually see for real what's going on there?
Which is much more useful, right?
Okay, so pausing again.
Let's take a look here.
I should probably also that's in the platform layer, so I guess now I
think about it.
I have to rebuild and restore completely to see those guys show up.
Okay, so there we go.
So, looking through here, we've got opengl, renderer commands is
taking 30% of the time, get closer to where she was taking 14% of the
time, begins Tim's taking close to 20 and update and render world is
taking like 25, right?
So let's try to break again, some of these down into a little bit
finer, grained pieces, so that we can maybe hope to have a better idea
of exactly who is taking the time in there, right?
And so update, and
World, I would like to take a look at here World mode.
Just EVP.
So update and render world.
It's like a giant time function right now.
And so, what I would say here is well maybe let's figure out how long
it takes to execute the brains so I'll say begin block.
Execute grains.
And block.
And then in here where we do some little entities, I'll do like
simulate.
Please.
And so that way we've got some idea of what's happening in these
things.
And I can move this out to functions to maybe I will.
So, let's take a look.
So looking here, we've got begin simulate entities.
So what we learned from that, right?
Right off the bat is that brains are not the problem, which is good.
I mean, one less thing to worry about, but you can see, you know, we
don't have anything like the brains are down here in the noise, right.
Basically, what we're looking at to speed up, this program is pretty
much we're looking at stuff that's above here.
Now, debug and there's nothing we can do.
Is these guys are slow, always a debug collation and the debug and
There's not much we can do about those guys because they're big
expensive heavyweight sorts of operations.
It's true.
But these guys are all at the top of the list.
And so all of these guys together, you can.
Kind of account for something like seventy percent of the executable
time.
You know what would be kind of cool.
By the way with this
In fact, let's just do it.
I mean, why not right?
So if I come down here into the debug code,
Instead of saying, hey guys wouldn't it be cool to do this thing?
Why just do the thing?
So where we display that in the, let's see here in the Cycles.
Here's our draw top clocks list, right?
And what I would saying is, well why don't we just take this
percentage that were printing out?
And as we go down, do if you were to get, you know, if you were to
look at the percentage of time in the program taken total up to that
point,
In the list.
How much would it be?
So it's like the cumulative percentage to that point that makes sense.
So I don't know exactly how we want to put that but let's assume
You put that like this.
So we've got, you know, the Cycles we've got.
The, what's the PC?
Percentage total time 100% over total time, right?
So all we have to do here is in addition to its percentage the running
total percentage would just be like running.
Some
Right.
And what we do there is say well, okay, so running some is just a
value that starts at 0 and every time through here, we take, whatever
the stats, some was and we fold it in, right?
And so, then if we look, you can kind of see, like as you go, it's 21%
of the program, you know, up to this point.
Now, it's 41 percent for everything up to this point, it's 57 percent
up to this point, right?
And as we go down, we're we're sort of getting up to there and in
fact, you know what I could do so that it's maybe not so owners and
What kind of always, I don't know what you want to call it up and up.
Doing something bad.
That is not good.
I know we had a feature here that allowed us to kind of like Place
text that, you know, hover text if that makes sense.
And so, I just would go and look, and, and say that must be her
summer.
Yeah, you can see, right is in rectangle.
And then we did,
An ad tooltip thing.
And so I'm just going to go and make that the tooltip.
Right.
So I can say well alright if we're in the rectangle whatever the
rectangle this thing is which I believe text out returns, right?
Doesn't text out return a rectangle to you.
I feel like it does.
Maybe it doesn't, let's find out.
But I think we can just say like, you know, rectangle.
Text wrecked or something.
And I can just say, well if you're in the text wrecked,
And maybe that's maybe I want the whole bar wrecked, I don't know, but
we're just going to do this for now, we'll say, okay, if you're in
that rectangle, then we're going to do a printf here and we're going
to take this thing that we were Printing.
And we're going to say, all right, cumulative to this point is that
much time.
Right.
Easy peasy, lemon squeezy.
I gotta remember to update for coder.
Has fixed these indentation bugs already, but I haven't updated the
for coder that I'm using on stream and I should really do that soon.
I haven't had a chance to do that though.
So text out at does not do that.
Why not?
Why don't you do it?
Show me the texts out?
What is wrong with you?
Why are you not doing it?
I know you should because I've programmed for so many years now that I
just know that's what that function would do, if it knew what it was
doing.
And now it does.
All right, so for running here, I should be able to hover.
I'm not able to hover which is crap.
So let's figure out what's going on there.
If the mouse speed, we have a mouse P.
We got a mouse p.
The mouthpiece in the rectangle.
We add the tool tip and so that should work.
I would think because the techstop gives us the rectangle.
Yes techstop to book State we go ahead and output the text and then we
we return a rectangle.
Yeah.
Yeah, we Union it in.
So we have all the glyphs producer rectangle.
So that's
Should work.
But it doesn't work.
And I'm not sure why.
Methinks.
We will have 20.
I wonder.
There isn't a transform being applied here is there.
I don't actually know if this stuff applies properly to.
Yeah, well, no, I don't think it would be a problem.
All right.
Well, I'm not sure why that's happening.
So I'm going to go ahead and step in.
I don't have a good guess I got no good guess.
So I'm going to go take a look at this function.
What is it called?
Drop clocks list.
All right.
I don't care about that.
I care about this.
All right, so clearly our rectangle is not ever testing positive,
right?
Because if it was, we would come in here.
So let's take a stop here and see, what does that text record look
like, oh, dear.
That is not, that's not valid.
Not a valid rectangle, which may be fine as long as somebody
eventually because, like, people who are clipped off, maybe don't get
the but yeah.
That's, that's not looking good now.
Look, not great.
Not great.
So let's go ahead in there and see what happened.
Okay, so we have a rectangle to result here.
We're going to call a tech top.
We call a text app, we initialize it to the inverted Infinity
rectangle, which is this.
We come on through here and
Start to look at our code points and we print some spaces.
Apparently we print only spaces.
For a long, long, long time.
Then we come in here, I see.
So for some reason, we decide not to get the sizes of these or not to
perform the union inning when we draw.
even though I see, so this is kind of
Stupid.
Because it means that pushed bitmap would have been getting the bitmap
anyway and we could just have recorded it there.
Alright, alright, well, I guess I'm not as dumb as I thought I was.
Which is unfortunate.
Or rather, I guess I am as dumb as I thought I was because really that
information would have been free when it comes through here, but we
wanted to use the same render call.
and the reason that push bitmap doesn't return the bitmap to you, I
guess is because you don't have
And I guess that is doing extra work here, which I'm not sure why it
really is.
I guess, just because of the deferring, is mostly why.
All right.
That's fine.
Maybe I'm not stupid.
Maybe I am.
I feel like there may be a little stupidity there but we're going to
Pretend that it's not that stupid so that we can feel better about
ourselves which of course is the Modern Way in our American education
system.
So it's all good.
Just tell yourself that you're a winner and move on and that's that's
just what we're going to do.
We're just going to tell ourselves that we're that we are winner.
Good job winner.
You really did great on that one.
Nice work.
So
Let's see here, get text size.
Does not take three things, that's probably true because it doesn't
probably need to actually issue.
Let's take a look to debug you either it only takes a debug straight
and a string, it doesn't care where it's at because of course the size
is always going to be the same.
So once we get text size here, we would have to offset the rectangle
by that though.
And in fact you know what, if we don't already have utility function
for that, I feel like we should
Because right, we would want that to be something we could do.
Sort of anytime we wanted and it looks like we're already handling
that displacement.
So it seems silly to throw it away to throw away.
That math work that we already had.
All right, let's see here.
Any better.
Much better.
Okay yeah, so now we can kind of see where are splitting point is our
tool tips.
Could really use a little bit of backing on them.
I would think so.
You know, we could also say, well, we're the tooltip at where the
tooltip code at.
Let's see here.
yeah, so this code, when we do our text text text out,
That would be basically the same so the text bounds.
It looks like we get the dimension of the text bounds but we don't
ever draw the actual look we don't actually push a rectangle.
On there, for whatever reason right?
We don't we don't ever put like a backing rectangle on it.
I don't know why we just don't.
Let's see here.
Like, this is what we want.
You know what I mean?
So it feels like, yeah, we should come in here and say, hey, I would
like to
I would like to draw One of These Fine fellows here for the element
bands, that whatever it is that we're doing.
And then I would like to have that be you know,
Some kind of medium Alpha.
It's not really dark enough.
And I think that probably needs to be further forward as well.
So I would say that should probably be.
Where is this guy at in Z?
What's his transform?
I'm not actually sure.
Z sorting wise.
Speaking of things that could stand to have their Z, sorting worked
out.
Because I feel like this stuff was never particularly good either.
You kind of had to make these tooltip transform and all this other
stuff when it's really we just kind of, wanted to say, like, okay,
generally the stuff appears above this other stuff and it was just a
little bit too formal.
So, the tooltips would always be above everything else.
Certainly.
There we go.
And I guess this just had the sort bias baked into it directly.
For whatever reason, not sure, exactly how that was meant to work.
Yeah.
Alright, let's take a look at that.
Okay.
That's a little easier to read.
We probably need a little more region.
Needs to be probably a little bit darker but that's fine.
Okay, so let's make this sky where we do the push back to them and
bounce.
Let's do an ad radius to on that guy and just you know do like a nice
sort of wider gap of that element bands, push wrecked.
So it takes a V2.
Sorry.
So now we got kind of a, just a, just a bigger region and we can read
that tooltip a lot better as well as these tooltips a lot better too.
So now we can kind of scan through here and just see like where our
break point is and you can kind of see that like, well by the time we
get up to debug and anyway, which is something we can't do much about
80% of our program time is spent up in here, right?
So it's a pretty fat optimization Target and, you know, so we probably
don't have to worry too much about the fact that the debug code slows
us down.
Plus the fact that a lot of that code goes away when we close this
stuff, right?
You can see the difference in time when we're not processing the debug
information.
Like for profiling information and stuff.
You can see that this time goes down so that that becomes less
impactful when we're not viewing it as well, which is nice.
So yeah, we can see that simulate entities is a big problem and so we
should probably look at ways of fixing the code in simulate entities
to make it.
Not take so long, get closest reversible we know exactly how to fix
that's a spatial query and we can accelerate.
The spatial query is quite considerably.
Opengl renderer commands.
I'm not sure how speed up a bowl that is in debug mode, but possibly a
little bit, just because again, it's doing a bunch of stuff that
It's like walking through and possibly doing sorts and stuff like
that.
We could we could go see to what degree that can be improved certainly
and really the one that's most curious is the big begins him because I
guess what's taking the time there would be the copying but I don't
know.
And so what's interesting about that one is that, you know, I'm
curious to know if Sim region in terms of that copying is
Really, what the problem is or is the problem, actually something
else.
So if I go to begin, same here.
I kind of want to know what is actually taking the time in here that
mysteriously goes away completely when we compile in in a non debug
mode, right?
And so is, you know, is it just one of these copies like is it this or
is it you know something that I'm not thinking of is hausknecht entity
pointers.
Is that a problem?
You wouldn't think?
So I can certainly make that and known
Lock here.
But what I can do to start with is like a, do you know in here?
I can certainly say, timed block.
Sim unpack here and just get another sample Point.
Basically, I'm going to restart so don't have any spurious timing
still in there.
And so, looking at this, like the answer appears to be no, like the
copy is just irrelevant.
So begin Sim is sticking 16 percent of the time to do nothing.
So that might just be like a clear or something like that.
Like, for example, this right here, maybe it's just this clear because
it's pushing a tremendous amount of stuff on the stack, I've been onto
our arena there and it may be that that clear is is too much.
All right, so let's take a quick look just a real quick.
Look at what would happen if we didn't do that.
Right.
So if instead here where we've got entity hash brain hash, right,
those are pretty big and we've got all this stuff, let's just manually
initialize.
So, in here, I can say no clear, I believe that.
Correct.
Right.
And then I just have to make sure if I'm not leaning on that code.
I need to make sure that everything else gets specified.
So I'm just going to kind of go through here slowly and make sure that
everything is initialized because now it's not going to clear it.
So there's World.
Here's Max entity radius and Max velocity.
Those are getting updated and you can see I'm just putting in the same
order they occur.
So I can easily check to make sure they're all there.
So here is the bounds and updatable Bounds.
Here's the max entity, Cathy and Abby, count the entities.
X brain, count the brain count, and the entities.
And so these are raised as well.
In addition to the hash, these should be no clear, I think to write
like so.
Because we're currently initializing them completely on pack out and
then we've got the brains and that's it.
So that's pretty much everything.
So if we remove that clear, let's just see what happens there.
If I do that.
Interesting.
So
ah, so that's true.
We can't not clear.
We can't not clear the hashes.
So actually, it's only the arrays that we could avoid clearing, right.
The hashes have to be clear.
We can't use them for lookups so let's see how we're doing now.
All right, so that took begins him from being like 10% of the time or
15th, whatever it was before all the way down to zero point eight four
percent of the time.
So obviously clearing those arrays is a bad idea.
A debug mode especially
I guess not, I guess the optimized clear that the compiler was
generating, is like way better than the one that it wasn't General,
that it was generating without that, right?
So that's good to know.
And now we're up.
I guess when we close everything, we're up to 30 frames a second.
No problem.
But we're still not at 60, right?
So the question is, who's next?
We've got simulated entities, and debug collation is now a pretty
high.
And that's a little bit unfortunate, but I don't know.
We can always turn off debug collation, I guess, or have a way of
saying we don't want evacuation at the moment.
I'm not sure what to do about that.
Exactly, but point being simulate entities, still taking a ton of
time.
Let's just take a quick look at that one and then we'll be done for
the evening.
Here's World mood.
So here in simulate entities, you kept me cuts on this movement code,
and then we've got move entity getting called, and we've got a bunch
of push bitmap calls, and we've got some of this debug code happening
here.
So let's go ahead and start to block these off a little bit.
So let's say that this is the entity render code and I'm just going to
go ahead and say and you know what?
It could very well be get best bet.
Get best match.
Bitmap from or something similar.
I don't know.
Those might be taken out of the equation, but
So, here's entity rendering.
We'll see about that part.
Here's entity physics.
And now we can just take a look and see what the what the basic
breakdown is.
Oops.
So it's open up that profile again.
Submit, take a quick pause here.
Alright.
So you can see that entity rendering is taking a lot of time there.
The Lion's Share of that time and the rest of the stuff in simulate
entities is kind of a little bit more evenly scattered.
It looks like, right?
So we kind of end up with with stuff like the physics down here.
Not really particularly relevant.
And that sort of the other sort of sim style stuff that we're doing,
instantly entities, not being hugely important.
So it's really just that entity rendering code that's that's sort.
Being doggy, right?
And so what I would say to that is well first of all also I want to
come back to some region and get rid of this granular stuff here.
Just a I don't really want inside inner Loops like that.
I don't usually like to have timing blocks sitting around for no
reason.
But anyway,
Yeah.
So you can see here, we've got okay or entity rendering is taking up a
huge amount of time and of course get closest reversible, which is not
something we can really regret address at the time.
Being so why is entity rendering?
Taking up so much time.
Let's take a look.
I am.
So we're clearing out these vectors and doing a bunch of matching
every time and I do wonder if that is perhaps a little bit too slow.
We can break this block up into two blocks to verify that certainly we
could for example also time these I don't know in the asset system get
best match bitmap from.
So get best match asset from is actually a Time function.
So if we
Look, we should actually be able to see how much time is being spent
in that it's already a Time function.
So if I bring this guy out a bit, we should be able to see get best
match acid from.
So what's interesting about that is recalling 366 calls to get best
match asset from, right?
And yet somehow that doesn't take any time, even that's got a loop
through all the Assets in a system and stuff, if that's that's a slow,
highly a mop unoptimized thing.
NG yet entity rendering which hardly does that much Beyond.
It is taking a lot more time which suggests to me that somewhere in
here?
Something stupid is happening.
I don't necessarily know what it is, but we should try to find out.
So I'm going to go ahead and move this block down and I'm just going
to go just take a look at just the Piece list and remove that from the
equation.
So we can see if that's a particularly problematic, if that's the loop
that's causing us the problems, meaning it would basically be that
pushed
Map call or if it's something else, right?
Okay.
So taking a look at here at what we've got entity rendering is still a
huge amount of time and peace rendering takes nothing.
So okay.
So basically what we're saying is all of this stuff is not
problematic, I don't know.
So what's going on here is that this rectangle are these rectangle
calls?
I don't know.
Let's keep isolating further.
And you can see what I'm doing here.
All I'm doing is I'm just coming in and I'm just
Isolating stuff until I can find out who the offender happens to be
right?
So I'm going to go ahead and and just block off each of these parts.
So this is Vector clear.
This is a piece rendering Collision, rendering and hit point rendering
alright, so now we're running and we can see our profile
and it looks like Collision rendering takes all the time, right?
Like that is basically the hog.
So now we know who our culprit is and and we can start to address it,
right?
So something is seriously out of whack here.
I don't know what it is, but let's try to figure it out.
So let's just go ahead and say that we will take a look at the
Names.
Which shouldn't ever even be drawing anything at this point.
Oh, well no, I guess.
The trees Maybe.
Volume rendering and traversable run.
And so now we can see which of these two is the expensive one and
perhaps hope to figure out why
So there we go.
So traversable is is all of it that is by far the most expensive that
could just because there's a lot of them certainly, but it means we
don't care about this.
So this is what we care about.
We're going through the traversals.
We're getting each of these out really.
All we're doing is calling to push rectangle calls and so it must be,
you know, in our render group
We're basically looking at push wrecked and push wrecked outline,
right?
So it's probably all these calls to push wrecked and push fact,
outline where we've got push wrecked entity basis P.
You know, it's doing all of this computation here and then pushing the
render elements on and all that other stuff push render element.
What exactly is that doing?
So, this is very straightforward code, but it's definitely the kind of
code that gets a lot faster when you run the optimizer on it.
So I could see why that would be the case.
Certainly, what I will say is this basically quintuple is the number
of calls to push wrecked.
So I could imagine giving this up, temporarily
And seeing how fast we get there.
Okay, so simulate entities is still just very expensive.
Unfortunately, the traversable rendering has gone down considerably,
but this is still up a little bit higher than I would have liked, but
we're getting closer, certainly right?
We're almost back to 60
Let's go ahead and close this.
Yeah.
yeah, so the other option we have
That we could certainly try is turning on the optimizer only for that,
for, for that code or taking that code, and blowing it out into a more
explicit format so that it doesn't take as much time.
Although I will say that similar entities was still taking a little
bit more than I think it should have.
So we'll probably have to do a bit more.
Anyway, we're out of time, but I think we're good.
I just feel like we want to do a little bit more in terms of making
sure that that performance is okay.
I also don't know how much any of this stuff is necessary, but that
sort of separate issue.
Alright.
So we'll do a little Q&A now.
Even though we're over time.
I see, you know, questions.
Maybe I'll ask info about if he has a question.
In turbot.
Do you have a question for me?
And it's about you said, dude it's about as the best.
Sergio says, how much longer does it take to build handmade here with
release optimizations?
The optimizer typically takes quite a bit longer, it's certainly not.
That isn't the reason I don't build with optimizations on.
We could afford it, like it's not owners.
So you can see there's the sea time.
Right at one point to 48.
And with the 02, you can see that it's going up to two point seven,
seven, seven.
So two point seven, seven, seven verses 1 Point 2.
So it's over half, it's very slow, it's takes over twice as long.
but,
The problem there is that is not that like that's not like I don't
leave it on the reason why I don't leave it on is because even if
you've got the special magic switch that allows a debugging in release
mode often times, it's still a lot clumsier.
So for example, like I optimize this is the optimized build.
You know, when I'll come in here and I'll say, oh, you know, show me
what entry is.
And it's like, it doesn't know, right?
It's like, I have no idea where that pointer is man.
I know I had that pointer somewhere, dude.
Oh man.
Like sorry, dude.
Like I was just building this debugger and like, I don't know where
the pointer went, and it's just like, okay, great dude.
Like you know, I know it's legal in Washington state now, but you do
not
Have to give me the surfer routine.
So whereas if I have, you know, a debug build it's like clear that
when I stop somewhere, I'm always going to get the actual debug values
that I want.
And there's I thought we added it.
The switch actually but you know I don't see it here.
There's a switch that attempts to make the debug information better
for release build, so that you can actually inspect values, but it's
doesn't really work that.
Well, it's still pretty busted, so it's not good enough, but there is
a way to get it a little bit better.
I thought than what we had here, unless it is Alexis - zo.
I don't know if that's what I don't remember, what that switches, the
rest of the 90, and they're not that.
So,
That particular problem is the one.
Why not use it?
Because a I don't like that because I like to be able to inspect all
of the values correctly as far as what the compiler thinks they should
be at that point.
And I could do that in debug mode and I like that.
So just for my own sake, I tend not to want that, but also for an
educational stream, it's doubly awful.
Because then when I try to show you guys something in the debugger,
you're not gonna be able to see anything because it's just going to
say.
I don't know where that is man.
Right?
And then you're going to be watching me do this nonsense all the time
because like right the pointer is there just to be clear.
It's just the debug information doesn't store enough information for
the debugger to go get it right?
So you can go get it because you could figure it out, right?
You can see right here.
You're like, oh, okay.
This thing where we do end entry Arrow, pointer equals Death, stand
entry Arrow, index equals ID and all this stuff right there in the
registers are the information that we actually needed, right?
So it's not like we can't walk back up here and find out what they
are.
It just takes forever because you have to do this every time
Right.
And so, you know, I want to find out what the entry is, and so, it's
like, oh, okay.
So if entry pointer equals dest.
So, in this case, Desto, most assuredly is an R8, right?
And that was probably one that even, it can get right, so you can see
it appears to be able to find that one just fine I guess.
Right?
But it can't find entry.
It has no idea where entry is and probably that's because it's just a
stack variable and it's only
Been used.
It's only used it in registers, right?
So it's probably just saying like, well, okay, so entry the pointer
part right now is definitely going to be where our nine is and the
index part, right?
Is definitely our 9 plus 8.
So if you're looking at that and you're me and you're like, well, this
is one thing and this is eight away from that thing.
It looks pretty clearly, like entry is just what's in our nine, right?
So I should be able to say, OK.
The Entity has
Hash.
Of our nine is probably what it is, right?
And hey look, I was right.
so,
It's just because the compiler doesn't output good, debug information
that any of this matters but unfortunately it doesn't and so there you
are, so it's too bad, but that's that's the thing.
So hopefully, that gives you some perspective on you know what what
that is
Hubert Keller says that zo is in fact the switch.
So yeah, I guess we're even getting the supposedly good stuff now.
That's a meat.
Like I mean that was awful, right?
Like you saw how bad that was?
It was super obvious.
Where that thing was, it was right in a register.
It didn't have to do any arithmetic to get it and it didn't even know
where it was right.
It was like, it's right in that register on that line.
It's right there.
So it literally was the simplest possible case for any advanced
debugging information feature, and it couldn't do that.
So you,
Only imagine how bad it probably is if you had to do some pointer
arithmetic to go get the value, you actually wanted, you know, forget
it.
I miss the optimization due to buffering but I caught some stuff about
the clear being bloated but I didn't catch what the fix was.
Oh well, we just stopped clearing.
The Entity and brain arrays.
That was it in the same region?
We just said, don't clear them, so we passed the no clear flag to the
Alec to the array.
Allocation
Far away.
Floor string transparent doesn't look quite right since you can see
through them.
Yeah.
Well keep in mind that that part we will we will have plenty of time
to play with meaning.
We don't have to make it be a global Alpha value.
We can just make it be a global color modulation.
For example, once we actually put our stuff into the Z layers, which
is what we're doing this week, we can play with how that gets rendered
and do whatever we want.
It looks like long bullion was suggesting exactly that when peering
down the hole at the more transparent layers, you can see characters
through those ground layers.
My guess is, you would want to mix with a fog color instead of just
making the tiles from parent.
And yeah, basically like all we have to do is just modulate the color
with a fog color or we can do.
I mean, honestly, we wouldn't even have to really do that.
We can we could just never really fade things out if we wanted to.
But yeah.
Because I mean, I think well, I don't know, we'll see what happens
when we get to it, but yet we can just go with the fog color and that
seems like a reasonable thing to do.
Would llvm work on Windows, handmade hero.
I know it doesn't yet.
At least the last time which was about a month ago that I tried to use
llvm for Windows build, it can't handle, mmm, 128.
All of the like specification for that is different.
So I think we could compile with llvm if we changed how those were
declared or used a different include file to define the mm 128, then
we would be okay, but as it is, that won't work on the Windows build,
at least.
That's what happened to me when I tried to use it.
I was looking at it on our, on 1935 actually and that was a big
problem.
And the other thing is, I don't know if they've got a Linker yet.
So last time I checked, you still had to use, Microsoft's Linker to
produce the executable.
So you could only, you can only use the compiler, you can't use the,
you can't replace the Linker so you still have to use visual C++.
In addition to llvm.
So it's basically like it's kind of not very attractive at this point,
because you're like, if you can ditch visual, if you can ditch,
Microsoft's toolchain all together.
That's fantastic, right?
I will be so on that.
But at the moment you kind of would have to use both and now that
means you have two problems instead of one, right?
You've got to Tool change, you have to maintain,
That's no good at all.
So hopefully at some point you'll be able to move to lvm exclusively
and just get rid of Visual Studio which would be far preferable,
certainly.
What editor is most similar to for coder.
And how long did it take to pick it up?
Well, I guess it.
I don't know because for a coder is very programmable.
So it really depends on what what your configuration is.
I guess emacs kanui Max is the closest probably because for coder has
the mark Point kind of thing built into it.
Like, for example, for cutter, doesn't work like this, like, you don't
drag selected regions and stuff like that, you mark points, and you
cut between them like emacs and so that's kind of the way that is at
the moment.
So, maybe I would say it's a little emacs E4 or emacs or VI, depending
on which one, you want, you made your customizations kind of patterned
after,
It'd be one or the other but it is so be maybe more like a Unix editor
and less like a Windows or Mac editor as I guess the way that I would
put it.
Having many levels of rooms and having entities, in each levels Act of
executing, wouldn't that be heavy or expensive?
Or have you think in a performance solution or a level imitation?
Well, it doesn't seem to be is I guess what I would say like like that
just doesn't seem to be a problem in release mode.
We're still running at 60 frames a second and we haven't really seen
any real boundaries that were hitting up against yet.
So I would say until I start seeing the Performance Edge.
And until I start actively tackling it to and having an opinion about,
you know, how realistic it is for me to optimize the stuff we've got
in there.
I'm not going to limit the game design around that yet because it sure
seems like we're going to have a lot of horsepower there.
Is there a way to tell the compiler to optimize just a particular
section of the code?
If not, how would you work around it?
Hilariously.
The answer is no.
There is no way to tell the compiler to optimize just a particular
section of the code there is however a way to tell the compiler not to
optimize a particular section of the code.
So what you can do and we kind of, we kind of talked about this
earlier on handmade hero and
if there's a caveat to it is you can turn on the optimizer and then
use pragmas to turn off the optimizer on the entire program and then
just in the places you want to optimize
Have the pragmas again to flip it back on that.
You can do wonderful, right.
Unfortunately, there is a huge caveat to this and that caveat is that
it won't inline any functions who themselves weren't inside the
pragma.
Which sucks like what the thing you want to Mark, is you want to say
optimize this function and pulling any other inline functions that
would have been required to optimize this function, fully.
That's what you want, right?
And you want that to just be a decal spec, like, you just want to
thing that just like optimize the snot out of this program out of this
function right here.
It's just like Deco spec, fully optimized, and then it should pull in
every last in line, do everything it possibly can to make that
function fast.
Leave the rest of us alone, that's what you would want.
But that's not what we've got.
So
Clang plus plus is worse, honestly?
Why can't the pdb?
Just say hey you are at this instruction, okay, the value is in this
register address or whatever.
I don't know why it can.
There's two reasons, there are two factors, which determine it.
One is the degree to, which the compiler is smart enough to track
where programmer named entities are through its entire
Station pipeline.
Right.
And you can see why that might not happen because it's the person
who's writing the optimizer is just thinking, I'm just trying to write
optimized code and doesn't have in their head.
Oh, I should track everything.
So that as I do, all these optimizations, I have all these breadcrumbs
that, that can lead back to what the source meaning of each of these
things was then you're totally out of luck, right?
And now you've got this huge reverse engineering job to go back in
there and make that work.
If you're someone who wants to add that back to clang if that's not
how it was working to begin with, right?
And the other limiting factor is the size and complexity of the debug
information format.
So, you know, you can imagine how many lines of source code.
There are a lot of programs.
If there's a hundred thousand lines of code in a program, which, you
know, I mean, even at Molly, we're at around there, right?
Like, so, you know, even one person team if that programmers
relatively prolific and writes a lot of code, you know, you're talking
about a hundred thousand, two hundred thousand lines of code.
At that point you're talking about.
Well, every single line of that of that code has to talk about.
We're all full of the scoped variables are because each of them can
have moved around at this point.
And so you're kind of having to do all these bracketing operations of
like between here and here.
It's here and between here, it's there and whatever, right?
In.
So if you don't do a good job, specking that debug format.
You can see why that could get nasty, right?
That's a pretty you gotta be on your toes about that.
And knowing pdb /, dwarf stuff, from what other people have said about
it, I'm kind of guessing that they're probably not Spectra very well,
right?
So that's another
Sort of COG wrench in the, in the cogs.
I think, probably.
But I've never looked at it explicitly, so I can't tell you.
The exact reason why it isn't that way.
All right, I'm going to wind it down.
All right, thank you, everyone for joining me for another episode of
handmade here.
It's been a pleasure coding with you.
As always, if you would like to follow along at home, you can always
pre-order the game on handmade hero dot-org.
It comes with a source code so you can play around with it at home.
Even as we develop it, there's also a forum site.
If you want to ask questions about the programming, we do on the
series, there is a patreon page.
You can go to.
If you would like to support the videos that we do here, there's a
schedule bot that tweets, the schedule every weekend every day.
So, you always know in the street,
Lives.
You want to catch it and there is an episode guide for those of you
who want to catch up on episodes, you may have missed.
That's it for today.
I will be back here.
Same time, same place tomorrow.
8:00 p.m.
Pacific, Daylight time and I hope to see you all here when we will
start to work on our Z layering, that's it for today.
I'll see you guys tomorrow.
Take it easy, everyone.