Okay.
Hello everyone.
Welcome to handmade.
Here are the show that we werewe code a complete game from scratch
live on Twitch know, libraries.
No, engine we write absolutely everything ourselves here.
It's like a fine handcrafted piece of furniture from Artisan
Woodworkers somewhere in the, the depths of I don't know.
Europe.
Anyway point being we are in the middle of doing some cleanup and so
I'd like to get back to doing that today we
We sort of did 11 Passover, render clean up yesterday?
We've got a little bit more stuff that we want to do.
We kind of made a little bit of list, so I'd like to get right into
that, but before I begin, I do want to mention that.
If you have pre-ordered, the game today is day, 10 5.
So if you'd like to follow along, you can unzip a day 10 for source
code from the zip file, the source zip file, and that is exactly where
we are starting today.
So, if you want to follow along at home, that's the one to use.
Let's go ahead and see where we are at here.
Yesterday, we went ahead and switched our coordinate system.
We had some crafty things in our coordinate system.
For the most part, our world coordinates were all fine.
There were m + y, is up X is to the right kind of a thing.
But we had had our screen.
Coordinates were flipped from that and we decided that we wanted to
fix that to have all of our screen.
Coordinates be going in a particular direction which we did that.
Also fixed our test reflection code here, which is, what's that?
That's kind of creepy sphere.
It's kind of creepy because it kind of just moves along with you.
Anything that moves along with you.
Like that is you gotta admit, it's a little bit creepy, right?
I mean, it's just a little bit creepy.
Anyway so we did all that stuff and that worked well, but we've got a
few more render clean up things that we want to do.
For example, one of them is we'd like to go ahead and clean up houses
handled and we'd also like to start making it clear what things are in
meters and what things are in pixels.
Because although the vast majority of
Of our coordinate systems all function properly in meters and that
sort of stuff.
We do have some things like bitmap alignment which are currently
operating in pixels.
And we probably since it's about bitmap alignment, we probably do want
those things to operate in pixels but we don't want to do is have that
be ad hoc?
We want to have very clear specifications, you know, that's in the
code.
That's clear.
So that when people are using the renderer obviously, when we're
talking about people, we're really just mean me.
you know, anyone who sits down to use it,
Including ourselves in the future.
Shouldn't have to wonder.
What am I passing this thing?
You know what direction does?
Why go?
Is this in pixels?
Is this whatever?
So what we want to do is make it so that it's very rigorously defined,
how all of that stuff works so that we can take a look at the overall
API of the render and know that we've, you know, made something easy
to understand and easy to work with in the future.
So that were not constantly,
Every time we go to write something renderer related having to deal
with this uncertainty of wait, how do we write that code, right?
So that kind of stuff, that's kind of fine, we're just getting stuff
working, where we kind of throw things together, is totally fine for
that stage, but we've kind of gotten stage.
Now, we want to start thinking about how to solidify stuff so that's
basically what we want to be doing.
Today.
And while we're doing that, we kind of one of the one of the big
things that was happening in there as well that you may remember is we
also had z-- H, z-- coordinate was totally ad.
Hoc handled like we really didn't have any sort of real concept of
houses should be handled.
And so while we're in there kind of making, you know, going through
and solidifying some of the stuff we want to come up with some way
that we can make z a little more coherent as
If possible, that would be, that would be nice.
All right, so let's go ahead and
Come back here to our code and you can see we've got some notes here,
right?
And we did one, which is everywhere.
Outside, the renderer y0 is upper decks to the right and that was
true.
All bitmaps, including the render Target are assumed to be bottom up.
Meaning that the first row points pointer points to the bottom of this
row, if you don't screen, we did that as well.
So we did those two.
And then this is kind of what we're on today.
This number three, unless otherwise specified all
Put to the render are in World, coordinate, m not pixels, anything
that is in pixel values will be explicitly marked as such and that is
really the thing that we need to start working on today.
And what I'm going to do here, I'm going to do something that I
sometimes like to do.
When we start to solidify something, which is I'm going to start to
pull things out into this h-file, not because it actually is going to
matter at all, that we have things in the H file, but more just
because I want to start.
Art, having an easy place to look that sort of like an API reference.
So I can start to see if everything makes sense to me.
It's kind of in one place and, you know, I could do that.
There's ways you can do that in the editor, I can do.
I don't know if I remove these, I guess I did.
There's like a collapse view in emacs, I'll just help.
Oops, that's not what I want to do.
Help collapse.
No, I can't remember what exactly it's called.
It's called like
I don't think it's called outline mode but I don't know.
It might be selective display set selective display.
I think that is actually what it was.
So there's some stuff, any Mexican do set select a display that will
like collapse down to just using the functions and and visual studio
kind of has this sort of stuff as well, right?
Like, it's that
Sort of a thing, you know.
But that's really just super inefficient.
And it's super fussy.
And also it's problematic because it doesn't pull out the functions
that I want pulled out.
It pulls out all the functions, right?
And so, what I want to do here is just kind of make a little section
that's sort of like you know, renderer API or something like this and
I want to pull out the stuff that we have.
So we can start to look at it a little more closely, right?
So we have this, we have pushed piece, right?
Which is something that we were using
We have pushed bitmap, which is another thing we were using.
Their, we have Push wrecked.
It was our way of drawing sort of debug rectangles.
We don't really use it for anything real at the moment other than
debugging and same with the outlines.
They may never be things that actually get called for real, but they
are for debugging.
We've got our clear call, right?
I'm going to leave meleave saturation out for a moment.
I don't, I don't think.
Yeah, I don't know about the saturation thing I'm going to, I'm going
to go ahead and pull that out of here.
That was something.
Someone asked me to add there, at the end of a stream.
I'm going to, I'm going to go ahead and pull that up.
We'll leave the weird code that was in there to do it, but and then we
have our coordinates and thing, but that was just a test for the
moment.
All right, so let's start taking a look at these.
When we're rendering stuff, this is currently what we have to work
with.
So we can go ahead and push a piece on and a piece is basically a
bitmap that has some information on it and honestly at this point I
don't really see what the difference between push piece and push
bitmap even is I would like to know because I forgotten at this point
and I suspect that we probably don't even really need both of them.
And in fact, you can even see here that we don't if you take a look at
pushed
Versus fish bitmap, they're really just shorthand for each other.
Push bitmap, it looks like is always just going to pass instead of any
kind of Dimensions.
I guess it just passes 00 there.
That's what it looks like.
Anyway, I'd be interested to know.
So let's see.
Offset Z, alignment and dimension.
So yeah, it just passes, 004 Dimension, and then lets the piece get
pushed on here.
Now, what's interesting about
About that, it looks like Dimension.
Never gets used.
So this, this looks like just stuff.
It was kind of as we condensed our stuff into a renderer slowly over
time.
We just haven't fully removed all of the cruft that's in here.
I'm also going to sort of keep get that out for a second, so I feel
like that can just go away, right?
I mean, am I missing something there, right?
If that's, that's just not even doing anything.
In fact, I can just
had I leave this running to make sure he doesn't reduce any problems
but you know that's just kind of not
Not doing anything so it should go away.
It looks like push bitmap takes just an alpha value instead of a
color.
But other than that, it's exactly the same as push piece.
So I think we could probably do now is just go ahead and say that
instead of push peace.
We're just going to have pushed bitmap.
I mean, it just does not seem to make any sense and our render entry
that we were putting in there was already bitmap, right?
And so it just yet.
It just seems like it makes more sense to go ahead and and switch this
up, right?
So let's do this like this.
Let's have this, be our color value here and our entity zc can still
be there.
And we'll just get rid of push, peace entirely.
And then we'll go Port any of those calls that used to be doing.
That used to be doing that, that old style, right?
And so, let's see here, we've got pushed bitmap and make sure I want
to make sure that I met
Respecting everything properly here.
So you've got the bitmap.
We've got the offset and the offset Z.
We've got the alignment and then we have the color.
We can make the color, a default parameter because it looks like
that's something people when they were doing push bitmap might have
wanted right?
Just a pure white, it doesn't actually do anything there so we can do
that.
And then anything that has an alpha value now has to get expanded out
into a thing.
And you know what?
We should probably do here now.
Think about it.
There's one other thing we probably want to do which is we want to
State something about the alpha.
So all color values specified to the renderer as v4s are in non
premultiplied Alpha because I think that's probably what we're going
to want to do there.
Just from personal experience.
I tend to prefer that.
And so, what I want to say there is basically that like
The renderer will be responsible for pre multiplying the alpha.
So basically, if we have some color that looks like that, right?
That comes into the renderer, you know, we're going to expect the
renderer to turn that into this, right?
The user is not expected to pre multiply the alpha across before
handing the color value in.
And the reason that I want to do it that way is because usually the
users thinking users of the render, I thinking of a color plus an
alpha value and they would just have to keep doing that merge together
all the time.
I'm and so I think that's the way I would like to do that.
And if you know, if we find that that doesn't end up being the right
way to do it, we can change it later on but that's the way we will
have that work for now.
Okay?
So, the color value that comes in here, we'll just be that default
value.
Let me go ahead and check this out here.
And so, the shadow Alpha, if that's going to be passed in, just gets
passed in.
As of the for, right?
Same thing here.
Oops.
And
One more.
Is that?
That's just another.
That's just a more complicated Alpha value that we've got there.
Yeah.
And let's see push bitmap pushed bit mad.
It looks like we'd already gotten rid of all the push piece calls.
So they were push-based, essentially already was gone from the code
base.
We just never actually got rid of the push piece function so that's
good.
That simplifies things a little bit more, right?
You gotta push bitmap to got push wrecked.
We've got the push wrecked outline and and then we're down to clear.
Okay.
So, what we want to do here is take a look at what the parameters are
there coming in.
And the alignment value that we've actually got here.
What we can see is the alignment value is in pixels, like I was
saying, but it is not marked as such and so that's kind of the place.
So I guess like I was saying, where I want to go ahead and fix that.
Now, one thing that's a little bit interesting here and I don't know
if we want to do this or not.
It's a little bit tricky to say,
I'm just not sure, which is basically that bitmaps themselves could
have, an alignment value baked into them, because basically, every
bitmap sort of could have, you know, what amounts to a hot spot.
Right.
A place that's like this is when we say we want to draw the bitmap at
a location, we're not talking about putting its upper corner there,
we're putting it, we're talking about, putting It's Hot Spot there,
whatever that is and that's what we've been doing so far with the
alignment stuff, but we haven't Associated them directly with the
bitmaps themselves.
And I
Oh no.
That might be something that we want to do so that when you pass in a
bitmap here you don't actually passing any alignment, the alignments
actually just something that got specified with the bitmap probably
when it got loaded and I'm trying to think if there's any reason why
we don't want to do that.
I can't really think of a reason not to do that because I can't think
of a case where we're going to have bitmaps that will have a lot of
different alignments to them.
And even if we did we could make multiple sort of pointers through to
it that you would access differently.
So it kind of feels to me like we would want to just have those
alignment points be in the bitmap.
Yeah, so I think that's what I'm going to do.
I'm going to go ahead and say that so that we don't even have to pass
anything so that we won't be passing any pixel values into the render
for the most part.
Anyway, what I'd like to do is just say the loaded bitmap itself.
It.
The loaded bitmap, which I guess is up here, we'll just have the
alignment baked into it, right?
So that'll have like a line X align.
Why baked in, let's say and that way we can just assume that whenever
we're dealing with the bitmap.
When you pass it in, you don't have to pass in any alignment.
The alignment will just be something that's can be determined from the
bitmap itself.
So basically the bitmaps Align X and the bitmaps alive.
Why are going to be?
Handled for you.
That seems pretty reasonable.
I don't see a lot of reason not to do that, that seems pretty fair.
So if we go ahead and sort of massage this around a little bit, just
move that around.
So keep those colors down there.
Keep the wrecked I guess we'll also make default same defaults.
Yeah.
Yeah, so all I need to do now is go back and actually change.
When we actually do these pushpin my calls I'm going to need to now
make it so that we actually have, you know, those the when we load the
bitmap, we actually do something intelligent with those alignments.
Right?
So first of all, the line X and the line Y there, the line X
Where did that go under group?
The Align X in the Align.
Why?
I'm going to start off.
Assuming that they are set to the upper side and the lower left
corner, right?
But we'll assume that eventually, when we load things, those that'll
be specified in the art itself somehow.
And for now, we've been specifying those things manually, and we can
go ahead and actually just for
Hero bitmaps, we have a utility function at already sets that so what
we can do, pretty easily with that is actually just record that in all
the bitmaps, right?
And so instead now of having that hero bitmaps, which has the
alignment in it, in other words, this thing right here, it won't need
that anymore.
It'll actually just have that directly in sort of the the head Cape
torso thing, right?
So it'd be something like this, Ed
Cape and torso.
And those will be set to be aligned.
X, the line line.
Now unfortunately we don't have an integer style Vector.
We've never made one and I don't know that we really want to.
So we're just going to go ahead and do it this way even though that's
kind of just stupid since we are converting, something from integer to
a float and back, which doesn't really make much sense.
But that's just how that's just the easiest way to write this.
This point.
So, that's fine.
Anyway, so I think really, that's mostly all we needed to do for
those.
But there are a few other people who have alignments that are
specified in their drawing code directly.
And we want to kind of reverse that Trend.
So like for example this guy, it's just zero zero.
So we don't care, here's another 100 so we don't care.
Oops.
What's wrong here?
No operand, that's a good point.
Those should be dots.
Not arrows.
So there we go and push bitmap.
This is passing an alignment there.
It's passing an alignment.
That's right in the middle, right?
And so that's actually something that that we can just specify in that
bitmap struct, right?
And that's something that we probably would want to to bake in there.
Trying to think of.
Yeah, never mind.
I had I have thought it passed.
All right, so anyway we want to go ahead and bake that in that for now
we can probably that's something we could save permanently and then we
don't we really don't need to set it every time.
But again, that will kind of get pushed up once we do a little bit
more formalizing of that ground system so that should be fine there.
Let's take a look at this.
So Kira bitmaps.
Align, this stuff doesn't have to be passed at all anymore because
that's just implicit.
So again sort of eliminating some of these things.
Here that we don't need anymore.
Let's see the alignment the top down the line, that's four walls.
So we need to do is put this back up where we loaded the wall, right
groups, where did we load the wall?
Where did we load the wall?
Let's see game state.
So our wall was a tree, right?
And so, what we want to do is make that game state tree.
We want to do, we want?
Want that to to be aligned.
So I guess set top down a line will make one of those for bitmaps as
well as Heroes and that way we can pass that in there so that when we
make the tree we can set the alignment of the tree as well.
You know, the other thing we could do actually is we could just have
something where we just straight up pass it.
When we do debug load bitmap, we could pass the alignment in like that
which seems pretty reasonable, right?
I mean that seems like a pretty pretty
Thing to do, if we have our debug load bitmap function, right, it
could just take a line X and a line Y and then just Pat set those in
here.
So we could just go ahead and say, okay, we know that we need to flip
this.
Assuming that the the bitmap itself is flipped because these are
top-down alignments, right?
And in some sense.
I almost want to name them that so that we don't get confused, right?
I mean this is the top down a line Y right which means that in here
we're going to go ahead and flip that right?
So that's just kind of one of those things where I just want to make
it extra clear to whoever's using it.
What's actually going on there, right?
So I don't want to have to actually specify that for all of these guys
at the moment.
So I'm also going to make these just default to not being any offset
at all.
Which is fine.
So again can get rid of the alignment here, no need and then oops.
And then we've got that alignment which is for the sword.
So when we load the sword as well, we can go ahead and set the
alignment for that look so that's probably that's just looking much
cleaner.
Now, that's definitely was a good idea.
All right so we can get rid of these, you can get rid of this right?
Just getting rid of all these things and kind of just feels nice even
just to do it.
Alright so there we go and of course we've
Change the size of things.
So, everything looks fine except for our shadow, which I guess was
using some alignment that we did not fix everything else appears to be
fine, but the Shadows, definitely not fine, that's kind of bizarre.
So, what's going on with our shadow there?
And if you guys saw that, I guess that's because we were using the
Cure alignment for the Shadow and I didn't actually specify any for
the shadow.
So,
Is our shadow.
Where is our shadow actually loaded?
It's right here.
So I assume that what we want to do is again use the same alignment
that we were using for the hero on the Shadow bitmaps.
And that's where it came from in the first place.
So let's go ahead and put that adjustment in there.
There we go.
Now, our shadows are back where our shadows belong and I think that's
mostly everything that we needed to do for that.
Okay, so that's pretty good.
Because now we've actually gotten pixels out of the spec entirely for
the renderer so far, which is kind of Handy, right?
And now we've just got that one push bitmap call which was doing all
the book met bitmap stuff that we wanted.
And so that's also handy.
So taking a look at this here, it's taking the render Group, which is
good, it's taking the bitmap, which is good obviously necessary.
Then it's taking an offset and an offset z, a color and an entity SEC.
Now, those things are kind of janky to me, right?
I just don't.
That specification like why is you know if I have an offset and offset
Z shouldn't that be a three-dimensional coordinate anyway and and I
don't even know what some of that stuff means the edit easy.
See was kind of that hacked, z-height thing.
So I think we want to drill down into push bitmap, a little bit more
to get the Z position except correct color.
And the color stuff is fine, I think and obviously the Pitmaster
stations easy but the other stuff is a little bit weird.
What I want to do first, however because
I've got stuff that doesn't really well.
No, these guys have entities EC as well.
So let's let I think, basically, what I want to do is to get this down
one more level of tightness.
Exactly.
I just want to go through and figure out what's going on with our Z
positioning so that that can be a little bit more solid.
So let's think about that for a second right now, we've got this kind
of in our render group.
We have this thing that's a render entity based.
This right?
And the render entity basis has like a pointer to a basis and it's got
an offset here and an offset the all these sorts of things, right?
So that when you do, when you render a bitmap, it actually goes ahead
and it specifies this and points to some basis, which was basically
just a point of positioning point that we were using to say.
Okay, once we build an entity, we want to build it around this point.
It'll all be kind of be coherent, right?
And so what?
I'm not sure at the moment.
He's, I'm not sure this is the cleanest, I'm not sure.
This is the best construction mechanism for this sort of stuff.
Like I'm not sure.
And you can kind of see, we've got these weird things like the end of
these zc and the offset.
See, it's just, it's just a little over specified in weird.
So what I kind of want to do at this point is I want to go through and
take a look at how we're specifying this stuff a little bit more
specifically and try to try to kind of condense that down and make it
a little more.
Saying the base is stuff.
I mean originally we had the basic stuff for a reasonable reason which
is we want to be able to do single pass stuff, where we would sort of
we would build, we would be able to say what the entity should look
like.
Without having actually done his update Loop yet, I believe that was
sort of the reasoning behind that and you know I don't know if that's
such a good reason to keep it that way.
So I guess what I'd say is we just have a bunch of stuff here.
That's making me a little uncomfortable and I kind of want to just go
clean it out fairly thoroughly and for our rectangle stuff, you'll
notice our rectangle stuff also has this this sort of zc things in it.
It also uses the end of the coordinate system and I guess that makes
some sense because essentially, you know, it's not really in any
coordinate system anymore, it's just a coordinate system and so we
wanted to do stuff like put the little hitpoints and stuff under the
Of tests that sort of thing.
It made sense.
Why Jimmy
Why we would be passing the same sorts of stuff to the rect function
as the bitmap function?
But again, I kind of want that to be more solidified and and just have
a better handle for what's going on there.
So we make sure that, you know, direct angles really need this stuff.
What's the difference between offset Z and it easy?
See, that sort of stuff.
So, let's see.
So what are we doing at the moment?
Look, what are we actually doing here?
We have some code.
That's, that's doing those bases.
That's like, getting the EnV render base.
As you can see it here, what does it actually do?
So, we start at wherever the the coordinate system said to start,
We then have a z value which takes whatever the offset Z is.
And the base coordinates z.
Now I don't actually know what the base coordinate.
Oh, yes, I do.
I remember what that was?
You base coordinate Z.
Oh wait, no never mind never mind.
That's just the Z coordinate from our basis.
So that's yeah.
That's totally fine.
So that's just whatever was specified in thing originally.
So then we add the offset Z which is the thing that was the sort of
the extra specified thing when the entity was actually was actually
specified.
It was this this offset parameter, we add that in there.
So we're basically adding whatever the initial Z was for when the The
Entity was you know, sort of the entity group was started and then
we're adding whatever.
A particular piece of the entity had as its offset.
See we sort of move upwards by that on the Z fudge right now why this
is 1.0.
I guess it's because we're multiplying.
It's a scale factor.
So we're starting at one point.
Oh, I remember I think I threw this in, at the very end of like a Q&A
or something once.
Yeah, we have not thought any of this through.
So this is kind of
Yeah, it's good.
Good definitely.
Good thing for us to come through and, and clean this up before we go
any further.
So, we were basically trying to come up with a multiplier that would
multiply whatever the enemy's x,y was so that things would kind of
scale out this way, right?
That's what we were actually doing and you can see that happening here
is we are taking the center of the screen.
And we were saying whatever that Z fudge value was which is basically
the higher something gets in Z.
The more it would kind of blow out that way.
We were then taking the edit easy to be whatever.
Wait a minute.
So that's how we set the ground point, then we're ascending the
entities Z.
We were also using just the base Z which is like what was initially
specified as part of the transform.
Just the base is e.
We're turning that.
We're multiplying that by m 2 pixels so that they're now both in World
space.
I'm sorry the both in a pixel space and then at the end, we are
multiplying those two together.
I don't even that doesn't make much sense to me.
This is basically.
So I guess we wanted a coefficient I guess that's what empties
eco-efficient.
It's like code archaeology on some code we wrote that was really bad.
Well wasn't bad.
I mean it's just crazy.
So we're we've got a coefficient on the Z value which is yeah, I
don't.
So let's go see how we were why we wanted that?
Do we really need that?
Is that really necessary?
It's just super janky.
It's just yeah, I don't know.
I don't love it.
Let's go ahead and take a look here.
So, let's take a look at, like the hero who's the most complex shape
we have so far.
Right.
And here is here, is our hero value, right?
And our hero?
Okay.
So our hero doesn't even use this at, all right?
It's got a shadow, it computes, the shadow Alpha itself, it doesn't
use Z offsets in any way, right?
The Z.
Has not even touched anywhere in here.
There's really.
There's there's literally no nosy change whatsoever.
No, offset nosy change.
All right, so that's pretty boring.
So what happens when the hero jumps?
He's just setting his actual
Oh wow.
Yeah, this code is awful.
This code is awful.
So, all right, so here's what was happening.
This is just so this is I guess just stuff that we were hacking in
there.
Yeah.
So we want to do now that we're working on the renderer, we want to
stop this, this madness.
This is ridiculous.
So here's what that was doing, man.
What that was doing.
Was it was saying, well, okay, I have a Kuro location, right?
And my hero can do stuff like jump, right?
And when the hero jumps the way that it was working, I don't know if
you can, if you remember the hero was actually jumping, its actual,
the actual point where the hero was he was he was jumping, right?
And so for example this part right,
Here.
Get into the ground Point basis P.
That, that part right there, the hero is actually jumping the whole
thing, right?
And so, the re the way we made his shadow, stay on the ground.
Because like, as the hero jumps, right.
This is the basis point.
So all the things everything
It's rendered in the heroes.
Coordinate system gets rendered based on that position, right.
Everything that we put there, including the hit points, everything,
the shadow should be rendered right there as a result, but we wanted
to render the shadow on the ground.
So, what we introduced was a coefficient that would multiply the Z
offset so that instead of using that Z offset, it just could be
knocked out 20 and be down at the bottom.
Right.
And so let's just just to give an example of how absolutely stupid.
This is as a thing that should never have happened.
Suppose we got rid of it and go back and look at what happens in the
game, right?
You can see that the shadow moves up and down with the guy, right?
So that is like not at all.
Okay.
That is not the way that you want the shadow to work.
That is just a really, really bad idea.
Yeah.
And that was just something that we hacked in there.
So as far as I'm concerned that is getting pulled that is getting
pulled immediately.
So entities zc no longer allowed goodbye you are all gone.
We are going to have to come up with a better way of handling that
scenario so that's just that's not that is not happening in the
renderer sorry folks.
If just not so okay that's going away, let's go down to push bitmap
here just get rid of these entities EC get rid of this and a zzc
concept entirely goodbye man.
That's good to get rid of that because that's just yeah, that's just
nonsense.
That's been hanging on in there way too long.
Basically, you know, we since we didn't have a renderer, we were just
doing weird, anything, anything goes basically is what was happening
there.
Is not at all what we wanted.
So let's get rid of all these goodbye and CZ C and D zc is gone,
right?
So that's good and we don't store it anymore.
So now, hopefully, we can just get rid of all of this nonsense.
That was kind of cluttering up the code anyway, and again, one more.
We're nice, clean up pass.
It's just nice.
Deleting things is always good, pretty much.
It always feels nice with a get rid of stuff.
Okay, so
now entities EC is gone and that's good.
So we don't have a way to keep our shadow on the ground and we don't
have a way to keep our hit points on the ground, which we want to do,
but that is going to be a task for another day, and that's actually
going to be something that is not the responsibility of the renderer.
That's going to be responsible to calling code, to figure out where
the ground is, and just draw the things on the ground instead of
drawing them in the heroes reference frame.
And then having some crazy way that they get three projected back onto
the ground in the middle of the renderer, which shouldn't even know
what the ground is honestly for the most part.
So, yeah.
So that's just, that's just bad.
So, all right, so, that's good.
That we've got rid of that.
Now, let's go take a closer look at some of our
At some of our other code for that Z stuff.
Because we're not quite there yet.
I guess, one thing we could do, pretty pretty easily here is switch
from using sort of Offset.
You know, an offset Z because that was I think before we have three
dimensional vectors that we were using.
So we could now switch to actually just having an offset, which is a
V3.
So maybe I'll just go ahead and do that as the next pass because that
just seems like a same thing to do, which is to say that, you know,
there's really no reason.
We can't have those be stored sort of specifically like that, so let's
see, empty basis offset that's going to be the X Y there.
Plus that be two entities Z, so that's fine.
Let's go ahead and make sure that these are all passed as V3 is now.
Like so and that offset now is.
Yeah, is just going to be done exactly the way that it's done?
M, 2 pixels.
So if we're if we're going to convert to meters to pixels, we should
convert to meters pixels once in my opinion.
So if we go, if we go.
That is the basis thing again, right?
It looks like we were multiplying m.
2 pixels are offset.
Z here.
How are we doing that?
So, here is an example of multiplying that m 2 pixels for the basis P.
We've got the X Y be multiplied to be news to pixels.
So we never actually multiply the Z by m 2.
Cil's, it looks like.
Which is kind of weird to me.
I don't really like the way that's going.
So I think that really at this point, we should kind of have our Z in
the same space as our X and our y.
If we've moved everything into pixels we should leave it in pixels
right?
And we should just adjust whatever we need to adjust to make that
work, right?
So I feel like what we actually want here is to say, okay.
Let's convert everything to from 2, m, 2 pixels and and maybe I can do
that in two passes so that maybe we're not as worried about it, right?
So we'll do it this way, right?
How's this look?
So I look good to everyone.
Shoot me.
So push.
Is also working that way.
It looks like.
Let's go ahead and fix some of this stuff.
So that'll be an X Y as well.
And then we'll have the offset Z get set as offset.
Z we go.
Okay and our push wrecked calls.
So now everybody here when we're taking these in again this will just
be a V3 offset instead and so that is really just all going to be the
threes now but they're v3's with nothing in the last coordinate and
similar that offset Z just goes away.
Goodbye mr.
Offset Z or go.
And now all of these things we can kind of
We can kind of v3f I if that makes sense.
So this will be a V3.
There we go.
And I feel like someone was mentioning this actually on the other the
other day we actually had V3.
There was a version of it, that takes a V2 as the first parameter in
the Z and then later on I did 2 V 3, which is the way I tend to do it.
Normally, I don't know which one we should have.
So maybe we'll do it this.
This way, I don't know.
It's hard to say it's hard to say, so we'll do it that way for now and
we'll just, you know we'll we'll take two V4 and make it just be the
four.
How's that sound?
Good enough?
All right.
All right, so we've got our P here.
This is another case where we want to go ahead and and upconvert same
here up convert and looks like this one and actually doesn't need to
up convert it's already a Delta that's got everything in it so we just
want to do that.
Let's take a look at.
These are just zeros everywhere so this just gets extended basically
wrap everything in to be 3.
Let's see what we've got here.
V2.
Oops, those aren't V2s.
Same thing.
Let's see here.
And again same exact thing.
So these are really pretty straightforward, like I said, we just kind
of yeah, just kind of got to go through the code and and make sure
that everywhere that we
A previously passing in separate framers.
We just bundle them together.
Now,
Very, very simple.
and,
Let's see.
Last one that's offset.
P.
X y.
So what's its Z value?
I guess if we're saying, we want to render it at Z 0, always, I wonder
why we want to do that while we don't want to render it.
I'm not.
I want to see to be honest with you, I want to see if if we can just
just do it with its normal value.
So I'm going to, I'm going to actually take a look and see if we can
do that in a second here.
All right, see, so that all looks fine.
No, worries there.
And the Space drawing again, is those blue lines which were showing us
kind of where we had defined sort of rooms that you could walk around
in.
All right.
Well, that's all fine.
So let's take a look.
Then if that's the case, I want to know when we render spaces, right?
Which is right here.
Is there a reason that we were getting rid of this of the of the Z
coordinate because as those kind of go up, I feel like we would just
want to handle that problem.
Probably, that would be my guess although I guess the thing is
We don't really.
I guess we don't want there to be a z offset to it necessarily.
I don't know this.
This really feels like it wants to be just the offset P so I'm going
to leave it that way and will when we come back and are working more
at the volumes will see.
But I'm expecting that these were all were already 0 anyway which
looks like they were.
And so really it's just giving us that that sort of height, D Delta
off of it, which seems fine.
So I don't know.
Maybe that's not what we wanted.
I'm not sure trying to think if there's
A reason for that, Jimmy.
I guess one reason is that if we want to maybe draw it at its at its
lowest level, so we might want to do legitimately though is say we
want to subtract half the half the Y value right since we're drawing
like an outline, we may want to do something like this so that way
it's not floating in sort of halfway up, right?
And so that's more pegged to the ground, right?
I don't know if that makes sense but basically the, you know, the
volumes are basically.
A center and dimension.
And this is essentially the center of that of that volume.
So I was just saying, well, let me put it at the base of the volume
instead, which seems a little scene.
All right, so now we've got that.
Let's go ahead and try to handle our Z in a more sane way here.
We'll go up to the
The.
My voice is like, totally gone.
I don't know why.
Alright, so here we are in our get entity basis.
What I was saying before, is the m, 2 pixel thing, I would like to go
ahead and figure out how to get M to pixels to happen.
Only in one place and maybe I don't know exactly where I want that
place to be just yet.
But you know at at the very least, I want the renderer to have some
notion of who is doing that, right?
And so since that's happening in here at the moment, what I'd like to
do is change this up so that m 2 pixels is happening with the zika.
In it as well.
So it essentially we're doing this and we're taking that offset value
and we're just multiplying that by m 2 pixels like so.
And then we just when we do our alignment, we do the alignment like
so.
Does that make sense?
So that seems reasonable to me to do that.
So that will just
Sort of have a coherent m 2 pixels, which means that Z is going to be
a lot bigger now than it was, right?
So when we come in here, so stuff like this, that's working with the Z
values.
And that actually reminds me, the entity base is p, who was
transforming that from meters to pixels.
I guess that was just always being done in here.
Essentially, it's a little bit weird, right?
It's kind of strange.
So the other thing that's true too is like M to pixels is getting
multiplied.
For that half.
Tim we could just not do m 2 pixels there as well.
Right?
Could do that.
And just do that 1 m 2 pixels conversion right there, if that makes
sense.
So that seems that seems kind of reasonable to me something like that.
Yeah.
So that seems that seems pretty saying for the most part.
So now the Z stuff is going to go nuts.
In theory, I would think you can kind of see how crazy.
That guy's is going at the moment but all of these guys, the rest of
the stuff has z80 anyway so it's not really a problem so let's keep
going with that.
So when this gets pushed on now are m 2, pixels is always happening in
the same same place.
So that's all good.
This all looks totally reasonable to me.
Nothing odd happening here so that's all good.
So let's just go over to that get render enter.
D basis and think through what we want to do here now.
So let's see.
We have the entity base P which is something that's still in M, right?
And then I'm going to isolate what?
I'm going to try to do here is start to isolate these terms a little
bit are entities.
Z is taking the base p and bringing it m 2 pixels.
So here's the problem is our Z fudge, right?
Is is getting re x m 2 pixels which really doesn't need to because
it's already in m, 2 pixels.
If only this guy was a m, 2 pixels basically.
So yeah, it's a little bit strange.
So entity based P, right?
80 base fee gets used here and gets the m, 2 pixels converted and it's
here and gets m 2 pixel converted.
So what I really want to do is just convert that it with m 2 pixels
right off the bat, right?
So I'll take that out of the equation there entirely.
Okay, so that m 2 pixels is gone and that way M to pixels can just be
we can actually get rid of these either that
That that happens this way as well.
Okay, so let's take a closer look at some of this stuff now that it's
a little more condensed.
So the base P gets the basis.
P gets converted into pixel space which it is here.
The Z fudge uses that Z and the offset Z which are both in pixel
space, which is fine, which means this value should probably this,
this coefficient should go down here because now, the Z is much larger
than you used to be.
The ground point is just going to be whatever the center of screen is
plus that X Y offset.
But now we're using the Z fudge.
Like we're saying before the Z fudge is sort of thing that multiplies
those together to sort of give us a little bit of a scaling effect.
And then the actual Center gets is that is that basis point plus
whatever the offset is plus the Z coordinate.
Translated to, why?
So let's think here, first of all, why isn't the Z coordinate of the
offset of the entity being used?
There was it never used there because it was being used in the Z fudge
but not in the offset unless I accidentally deleted or something,
right?
But it feels like, I mean correct me if I'm wrong.
But doesn't it feel like this should look like that, right?
Shouldn't the offset?
Shouldn't the Z?
Offset.
Basically always be handled.
The same like, you know, total Z, right should be a thing, right?
I feel like that's just kind of a given.
Make sense and so it feels like we should have something relatively
sane there.
Oops, there we go.
Let's listen.
That does.
I'm going to see what that does.
So our guy goes up and down properly, our little dude is going nuts
down, there are, and so it looks like the entity basis Z is fine, but
but the Z offset is doing wonky things.
I'm not exactly sure why it's doing this wonky things.
So, yeah, which two should take a look at what's going on with that
with our little head dude.
But
Makes more sense to me.
So we've got our entity base P.
It does this, m, 2 pixels stuff.
We only ever use these things in totals.
Anyway, right?
Like, for example, any ground Point could just have this being here.
So we are always using
Well, that's kind of interesting so I guess we're not so easy.
We were Z fudging the XY of the base point of the entity so that thing
is scaled up and down where they were but the actual stuff themselves
didn't ever do that scaling.
So that makes some sense depending on how we want to think of it,
right?
So the way that we were, the way that that's being conceptualized,
Is that we've got sort of the concept of Z scaling on the screen so
that, you know, if you're a lower down, if this was like further away,
like a further level and this one was closer, right?
The same point would be scaled upward.
So like you know, if this were on screen, If This Were the screen
size, right?
Then this same point that's further away would actually be closer to
the center of the screen than the than on this closer one but when the
guy got drawn, he would still be drawn.
But the same relative offsets.
So he he doesn't actually get displaced less far when he scales that
Doesn't seem, I don't know.
So basically what that means is he doesn't come out word like that,
right?
He doesn't lean, he would never lean out in perspective.
That seems kind of write to me because we're not going to skew our
trees and stuff.
Like our trees will always stand upright.
They won't start to lean over, right?
When they're kind of towards the edge of the screen.
So I guess that, I guess that actually wants to stay basically the
same base of the same as it was II couldn't buy that.
That seems totally fair.
So, yeah, so really all we've got here.
Is that
Z5.
Value that's doing the scaling.
I think that suggests to me that you only want to use the entity base
p-value to do that scaling and you don't want to use the total Z right
for it.
You want to use the total Z only down here where we're actually doing
the offset by y to give it the appearance of height, right?
So that's like a little more correct if that makes sense and then we
still have to set that value down a bit but that seems about right to
me.
Yeah, and of course now our little dude has stopped freaking out which
is nice.
Yeah.
So that's all good.
I like the way this is going.
I like where this is going.
So that's all that.
All seems pretty sane to me.
I'd like to maybe just kind of document this a little bit here.
What I, what I do need now is something that actually comes the
position of the thing actually comes out in Z more.
So so that we actually see the action of that Z fudge happening.
It feels like when the guy jumps, the that should be seeing some Z
fudge, but of course, he's always at the center of the screen.
So, you can kind of see it happen here when he does his jump there.
Mmm-hmm.
What we really probably want at this point, is maybe to make to do
some shrinking of the just to move the camera in and out or something
like that so that we can see what's going on as far as that's
concerned.
Yeah, and you can kind of see as you move.
The guy, you can see that that change is kind of how he looks jumping.
Hmm.
But ruddiness of it always so busy and the Q&A bills now.
Well, alright, that's fine.
That's a totally reasonable stopping point.
I don't see any reason we need to push past that, so that's totally
fine.
We can totally go to the Q&A.
Let's go ahead and do that.
So I'd say we've made decent progress, cleaning up that stuff.
We've got a little bit more.
I think we want to do.
I think we probably should do tomorrow.
I'm guessing is we should probably put in some cameras.
Off so that we can kind of so we can get a better idea of exactly how
we want that Z to feel, when it kind of moves up and down because
now's that we can even hook up since we have it.
Our texture map were in there.
We can actually scale up the bitmaps like from the ground and stuff to
sort of see what happens when we zoom in and out and stuff like that.
So, that's probably what we should do tomorrow.
So let's see.
But for now, either way we should go to the Q&A.
So let's cut this out here.
Why are using a line X and a line Y instead of a V2 in the bitmap.
So the reason is hmm.
The reason that I was using it in into there is because it is an
actual integer and pixel coordinates that we were doing.
But to be honest, it doesn't super matter.
Like, I'd be fine with it, with it being a V2.
There's and, you know, I mean, it's conceivable that someone might
want to specify fractional coordinates, right?
So we could totally, we could totally do it that way.
That'd be fine with me.
We can
I can do that.
If it, if you like,
So, just be this right at the line.
And then align equals.
What was that set-top?
down the line that
yeah.
So that's just top-down a line.
Result.
Down the line Y, right?
I think that's right.
Oops.
And in here, obviously, we just do we just do.
This and yeah I mean that's that's totally fine.
I mean I guess that's probably I think I like that better just because
technically someone might want to specify a fractional a fractional
alignment.
I mean there's no I don't know that we ever would but there's no
reason why you couldn't specify a fraction alignment.
Because our renderer like, you know, the we're handling sub-pixel in
it, right?
So there's really no reason you can't do that.
So,
So, there you go.
So that's all good.
Shouldn't the shadow moves, somewhat up when he jumps because of the
angled view Port, know the shadow should stay on the ground.
I mean, the shadow should be in the same Shadows don't move when when,
you know, when, when, when people move, unless the light source is
coming from an angle, right?
So, you know, if this is top down, when the guy jumps, it should be
still below him, right?
If the shadow were angled in
Flying the light source was coming from somewhere else then when he
jumped it should move, right?
But the angle of the view Port really has nothing to do with it, if
the angle of the light source that would control that
Could you make the circle reflect a bitmap like a tree if you wanted?
It is reflecting a bitmap actually that's it's reflecting this, this
bitmap, these are bitmaps.
That's like, the whole point of those there bitmaps into which we're
going to draw out the lighting information so that we can sample from
them if you wanted to just prove that to yourself.
I mean, I don't know that this is really
Worth doing.
But you know, here's an environment map, right?
If we wanted to do, so we could just go ahead and and like, take the
drawbitmap call, right?
And and just say, like, okay, after we're done making this stuff, I'm
just going to pull on Splat a game state tree, you know.
Oops in
One of these environment Maps, right?
And Maps 00 or something.
Let's say, right?
So if I do that and I just say, stick it at, I don't know.
100 100 I don't even know where it should go.
And Alpha 1, we can just call the drawbitmap, call that would like
draw the tree in there, right?
In theory.
And and now the tree is in there.
And if the sphere got to the point where the tree was that you could
just see it there, I'll move it over a little bit.
It's not quite in view yet, right?
I don't know which I don't know where that we actually are on the
thing here.
So I'm not sure where to move the tree but you can you see it in
there?
You see the tree?
Right, passing by, it's going to come through again.
There's the tree.
So you know I mean it's just it's just reflecting the bitmap, it's not
It's not doing it the checkerboard in it, kind of specific way.
Can you let the orb sample from the ground or is that some time away?
It's not some time away, we could it would probably be you know in a
week or two when we formalize exactly when the ground layer happens so
that we then capture it out to the environment map.
But so yeah I mean if you wanted to do that now you just you could
draw some ground in there, you know.
Obviously you could you could take those ground chunks right now if
Just want to see what it looks like.
You could take those ground chunks right now and and draw those in
there.
So, like I could go grab, you know, ground buffers.
and ground buffers c0, let's say,
Buffer and just take the dot bitmap off of that.
Or maybe not.
I wonder if our graph because it's ground buffer zero.
Maybe isn't having in it.
I don't know.
Know why we're not getting our ground buffer.
There should be a ground buffer.
What am I missing here?
Oops.
How many ground buffers do we have?
Round buffer, count and state ground.
Buffer count.
- one do the last one.
There it is.
So that's what it would look like if it was reflecting from the
ground, right?
But again, reflecting from the ground is not quite the right thing,
yet.
The right term because at the moment we also we postponed finishing up
doing how all of our lighting stuff because we, you know, we wanted to
fix our coordinate thing coordinate system stuff.
So we're not quite done with this thing yet, so I would caution
against playing around with it a little too much because, you know,
it's not quite done yet, right?
Is all but yeah, that's that's what that would look like, right.
Let me see if I can get this a little more centered.
There you go.
So that's roughly what it would look like, right?
If it's reflecting from the ground and again, this is supposed to be
an additive thing.
So you're not really, this is not really supposed to, we're not even
designing this to
Reflective spheres.
This is supposed to be for lighting.
So what normally is you'd have the bitmap here?
And you'd be adding in this lighting as ground bounce, right?
So if we were trying to do something, whose only purpose was to
reflect the ground, we'd probably do it a little bit differently,
right?
Least?
That'd be my guess.
Although for the most, I guess you could mostly.
It's mostly doing that already.
But there's just a few things you might do a little differently.
How much zooming will the game support?
I'm not sure what you mean by that.
Obviously, you can the renderer allows you to zoom as far in as you
want.
But eventually the art is going to look stupid if you zoom in till the
pixel, if the pixels are too big, right?
So we don't want to zoom in too far.
I keep hearing you say entity but I take it.
You don't mean entity in the entity component system, sense.
Is that correct?
I think it is safe to say that I will never say anything on the stream
that I ever mean in The Entity component system sentence.
So, you can take that as a given.
You were going to add a comment to your Z.
Fudge code to say yxy was used, only not Z to avoid skewing trees
character Etc.
Yeah, I'm not sure I'm still not sure what we really want to do there
though, I'm not sure that I want to add a comment because I think we
need to do next stream, first.
I think we just really wanted to do here, which is like figure out
exactly how Z based X, Y, displacement will.
Work.
all right, because I don't really know because we've got some
some to dienes there to worry about.
I think I missed the day, but the bitmap is being texturized, using a
normal function into the sphere.
Yes, that is correct.
When are we going to scale the hero down?
Probably.
Right before we do animation, I would say.
Is that it for questions?
I'll wait a little bit just to make sure there are no further
questions before we finish up.
I feel like there's a bug with our edges as well on
We'll have to take a look at.
We go back to the normal stuff.
There's the edges are not anti aliased properly, which they should be.
So we've got also some Alpha stuff to look at there.
Would you implement a lamp in a dark room effect with Shadow mapping?
So are you asking about if we would Implement a lamp in a dark room in
handmade hero with Shadow mapping?
Because if so then the answer is no.
Because since we don't have actual depth information Shadow mapping
doesn't actually help us, right?
If you're asking, if in a 3D geometry game, you would Implement a lamp
in a dark room, affect your Shadow mapping.
The answer is yes, that is a way you could Implement a lamp in a dark
room.
Shadow mapping.
I mean if for people who don't know what shadow mapping is, it's very
simple.
It's just the idea that you essentially render the scene from the
perspective of the light source that you're trying to simulate.
And you remember what essentially, what surfaces you saw.
So that when you render the surface from the cameras point of view,
you can look to see did the light source.
See this thing that I'm about to render if it
If the light source didn't see it then I know it's not lit by that
light source, right?
Hence, it's in Shadow.
It's very, very simple concept.
Will there be emitters of some kind like Sparks from a fire?
Yes, that is why we're doing this lighting stuff is because I want to
have emitters.
So that's why we're playing around with, that's, that's the whole
point of doing the normal mapping.
So that we can do that.
How would you implement a lamp in a dark room effect in 2D game?
Well, we're going to have lamps in dark rooms so I would say stay
tuned and find out.
Really, it's this this guy right here is the dude that we're going to
this green texter figuring how to sample from that.
Green texture is going to be how we're going to do lamps in dark rooms
and like anything else.
It's kind of a hack because in 2D you can't really compute things like
Shadows.
Exactly.
Because the art is flat right there.
Art doesn't have volume.
So what we're going to be trying to do with that middle, that green
texture map is basically figure out a way to do some approximation of
light near field light so that we can have stuff like like lamps in a
dark room.
I don't know that we're going to have lamps per se but we don't like
torches potentially or fireballs and things like that.
Is it common in game development to use normal function for
texturising?
Is it performant?
Or is it much more common to break in texturising?
Trial Services, I'm not sure.
I understand the question, but basically, like every game in
existence, that's 3D uses normal mapping nowadays.
Like that's just a given normal maps are used for lighting in like
every game.
2D games often times don't
But that's mostly just because I think 2D games tend not to be
programmed by hardcore graphics people, so they're not trying to do
weird stuff like that.
But I feel like 2D games that are programmed by hard work, hard, core
Graphics, these sorts of people do 10 would do stuff like, have normal
app Sprites, right?
Like it that just be something you do, right?
And so, I think that mostly the reason you don't see more of that
stuff is probably
Oui.
That 2D games tend to be more.
Don't tend to usually have like people who like to spend a lot of
times on Graphics, don't, those don't tend to be the people who
program them, but when you do get that happening, I think it would be
a very straightforward thing, certainly.
So we're doing this in software right now unoptimized.
So this is an optimized software renderer that's rendering this, this
reflective sphere.
When we optimized it, I think it will be quite fast, but it's already
running at a frame rate.
You could play, right?
And so if we were to use the hardware, if we use the GPU, there's no
question.
This is performing enough, right?
I mean, the GPU would laugh at this Scene, It would have no trouble
rendering this, right?
If we could do it on the CPU at frame rate on optimize the graphics
card is not gonna have any trouble.
So there's certainly no performance concern there.
Insofar as well.
The entities have projected.
Shadows are just blobs, Shadows like the head has currently everything
will be Blobby Shadows because I do not like projected Shadows
largely, because they're not right, like the world.
Never really has projected Shadows, unless you're in strong sunlight.
Usually Shadows are very soft and very have a lot of complexity to
them.
So we will probably stay since we have to pick some approximation,
lighting wise.
We will
Probably always do soft Shadows everywhere.
Now we might do, we could do some things where we skew the direction,
the shadow grows in based on the lighting but we're never going to
have like hard Shadows falling because I really don't think they look
good in their almost never right.
Either.
Because most of the time that's not what the light would actually do.
Unless you're literally in
a room with like one very bright light and no reflective surfaces
behind you is to pick up that light, you know,
So there are seven but optimized don't you have o to on?
Yeah, I mean so it's kind of interesting I this is happening many
times on the stream so far.
Turning on O2 does not mean you have optimized your code that just
means the compiler will no longer be doing stupid.
Things like writing variables to and from the stack on every
operation, when they could have just stayed in registers, that's all
oh to does 02, does not optimize your code.
Your code is still lousy, just if you turn on O2, it's still
unoptimized code.
It's just code where the compiler isn't doing stupid things.
That's what O2 is, right?
So when I say the code is unoptimized, what I mean is we have not
actually done any work to actually make sure the code runs, he's is
written to perform quickly and so yeah we don't have debug on so we're
not like writing stuff back and forth to cycle time but that in no way
makes this optimized code.
This code is extremely slow right now and just not having a compiler.
Add more slowness to it does not make it optimized code.
Will the shadow be reflected in the normal map?
Well, anything that we put into our light field will be reflected in
the normal map, so if you put Shadows into it, then it would be if you
don't, then it.
Wouldn't that make sense?
Will the particle effects system interact with the normal map
certainly in for emitters.
I don't know about for other things whether we'd want to or not,
But yeah for anything that was like a particle emitter like fire or
stuff than that.
Obviously that's the whole point of doing this system was for the
lighting so we'd want that to to do to do it right.
Anything else?
Looks like that's about it.
All right.
Let me go ahead and close things down for the day, then save.
Mischief has been saved.
All right.
Well, it is time once again to wrap up handmade here for the day.
Thank you, everyone for joining me.
It's been a pleasure coding with you, as always, we are.
Yeah, I think we're making good progress towards solidifying.
Our renderer,
We've got a little bit more work.
I want to do with the Z stuff so I think tomorrow might be the day
where we start drawing some things that some a couple floors that kind
of where you can see down to you know from one floor to another floor
or something like that so we can kind of get a feel for how that's
going to work.
I think that's what we're going to need to do to start solidifying,
our Z stuff, but we're getting really close here.
I'm feeling pretty good about this.
So, yeah, it's exciting should be a fun.
Couple of weeks of just doing fun render stuff here and kind of
getting our gaming too.
Place where we're comfortable with how it looks and how it runs.
So, that's cool.
So I hope you will join me tomorrow for the next step in that again,
five PM, same placed which hope to see you there.
In the meantime, if you do want to play around with the source code,
you can always pre-order the game on handmade here at up org and it
comes with a source code.
I updated every night.
So if you want to play around stuff you saw on today's stream, that's
an easy way to do it.
We also have a patreon page if you want to support the video series,
you subscribe to that.
So he's very appreciated.
We have a
I'm site where you can catch up on old videos, there's an annotated
Video Guide to the previous episodes.
There's also ports to Mac and Linux.
If you try to follow along on a platform it's not Windows and you
don't want to have to do that.
Porting work yourself.
There's stuff on there that shows you how to do that and there's also
a place to ask questions so if you have questions that you don't get a
chance to ask them on the Q&A or you don't watch this live and you
want to ask questions, that's great place to do it.
There's also a tweetbot the tweets, the schedule.
So if you're trying to catch the stream live, just go ahead and check
out that tweetbot.
It tweets a schedule every week.
Weekend and also in the mornings and at nights it'll tweet when the
stream is going to be for that day.
So it's a great thing to check out if you're trying to catch it live
once again.
Thanks everyone for joining me and I hope to see you guys tomorrow.
Have a good day until then.
Take it easy, everyone.