Let us get things under control.
Okay, this up.
Hello everyone and welcome to handmade hero.
The only show that you can even conceive of watching.
Really?
Like, if you really just had to in your mind's eye.
I'm sure you could Envision no other show that could ever even
possibly exist across.
All of humanity, where people code an entire game from scratch with no
engine and no libraries, It seems impossible.
How do they even do it?
And
It night after night.
It is getting done with, just me and a thousand of my closest friends.
How long will we able to keep this up?
It's anyone's guess it's really.
You never do know that surprises around every corner here at handmade
hero, but that is certainly not going to stop us.
We are going to continue until we have our own very little happy
shining game that we can say we understood every last little bit of.
And honestly, I think it's going pretty good so far.
So why delay?
The inevitable?
Let's just dive right into it.
If you have pre-ordered, the game, you should have gotten a link in
your email with a zip file Download Sort of thingy from send owl.
You can download the source code every night from that.
You can also download the test assets if you download the source, it's
a zip file that has a ton of zip files in it.
One for each day.
We are on day 52.
So unzip day 51 and you put that in a directory and you will be where
I am.
So you will be like able to totally just scoot in the kind.
One of those bicyclists that drafts off another bicyclist, you can
just totally go for it.
No headwind.
It's great.
All right.
So, let's see.
I was right.
I was rudely interrupted by the timer last time who told me that it
was the end of the stream?
Because I was right in the middle of making some major changes to the
code base.
And so what I want to do is go ahead and get back to those changes so
that we can emerge from the other side of our change tunnel in a
wonderful, you know, where the bright light is shining and the and the
unicorns Run free.
He and the Rainbows are, you know, gluten-free and everything else,
that happens.
All right.
So what I was doing is, I was changing it.
I was starting to play around with changing things over.
So that we would have entities divided up into pieces, where we have
ones that were sort of in the active, in the close range around the
player, one, or two screens away from the player.
Those entities would be stored in sort of a high form and it read that
exists because we replace that yesterday.
With this.
Non-existent flag will be stored in this.
Hi Anthony.
And then we'd have low entity which are entities, that are being
stimulated, but are further away from you and are getting updated.
Perhaps a lower resolution and then we have dormant entities which
didn't get updated at all.
And so, we were just kind of thinking of that through.
Now, this is not set in stone by any means.
These probably won't be laid out like this in the in the final version
or anything like that, but I'm starting to play around because I want
this basic structure.
this basic concept anyway, the things get
Opt in and out of sort of the working set around the player.
And when they get mapped out, they're not, they're not totally dormant
automatically.
They could still be in sort of a low-frequency update pattern, and
that's where this would be.
So,
Let's see what's going on here.
I think we were sort of, in the process of we just it we were like
sort of in the process of making the change and we had to F0 a bunch
of stuff out.
So we have right now that move player.
I'm going to go ahead and start working on some of this code that we
have zero doubt.
So when we do our move player code now, we really don't have to think
about the tile map anymore for the most part.
In fact, I really just don't even know if we're going to have to do
anything with this tile map anymore.
Because really what we would have is we just we just have all of the
The tiles.
Just be moved into that set as well.
So, when we come in, I feel like all of those tiles would essentially
be sort of active entities.
And the reason I say that is because I don't know that we really want
tiles per se ever at all.
We just kind of want stuff that's following the tile map.
So, you know, if we have trees we probably just want the trees to be
in there and we want the player to collide against the trees and stuff
like that.
So,
I'm going to assume that we're actually just go ahead and I'm going to
just make that change while we're at it as well.
And so thinking about that.
I guess what I would say is our entity structures will also.
Let's say, why not?
Let's just say their energy structures will also contain the actual
tiles in them as well.
And so, if I wanted to do that, I'd have to start thinking about how I
would do my Collision detection, right?
Because if I want to have
T on entity Collision detection, which obviously, we're going to have
to have, we would need some way of bending them.
So we do some kind of like spatial subdivision to keep things
obviously from getting too hectic.
And so that would start to be sort of a retiling of things as well.
And so that's kind of something to think about.
It's like it's kind of weird that we have all of these sort of
different structures and it does seem weird to have stuff like, oh,
well, you know, why do we have sort of these different levels of how
things get done?
But again, it all tends to shake out in the end and you have to kind
of go
Oh, through a number of different iterations of how you structure,
things until you get something that you're very happy with.
And so it's all just it, you know, don't worry about it too much.
It's all just kind of the way things.
Go on the road to getting something that feels good and it's all about
kind of seeing how that goes.
So, I think what we'll do first is just assume will test every enemy
against every other entity, which is N squared, and really bad.
So that won't be able to be used in the final version, but we'll just
assume that's going to happen for now.
And so we'll assume that what we would say.
Actually do is just have entities for all of those tiles.
And so, in the high entity struct, that would be kind of a good
argument against the way, the storm.
Intensity thing was working where we had it backed where we had them
in parallel arrays because we would want to basically have it so that
they the high entities could be brought.
In from other places, so I don't know exactly how I want to.
I don't know exactly how I want to do that for right now, but
mmm.
Yeah, I'm just going to go ahead and do it.
We'll see what happens.
So if we were going to do that, right, then we no longer have to
figure out where we are in this space anymore.
We will have to do something like that.
When we actually want to do, we will have to do something where we
have some kind of spatial partition.
But for now, I'm going to ignore that.
I'm going to say, let's just ignore this this stuff for now.
Let's get rid of that there and the fact will get rid of this as well,
like.
So and I'm just going to go ahead and say, all right, for every
entity.
So we have, you know, an entity index or something.
Every entity in the world, right?
I am going to go ahead and check to see what's going on with with it
versus this other guy.
Okay.
Let's see here.
Oh, and you know what, really that's something that happens in inside
here.
So this this is actually the iteration right there that we're looking
at.
So we've got, let's see.
There we go.
So I've got that there and then instead
Ed of actually having any of the tile stuff, we're just going to get
rid of all that, let's see there.
And then we're going to take a look here and we're going to see what
this does in here.
So basically what I'm doing is I'm changing this into an iteration
over the tile map.
I'm changing into iteration over the entities that are active in the
region, right?
So what I want to do is say okay, we still have this iteration.
We've got to go over some for each iteration.
We've got to see what entities we're going to collide with for right
now.
We're going to assume that we can collide with any of them to get.
Like I said, it's really an efficient so we don't really want to do
that but
We'll deal with that when we when we go through the second path.
And since all the entities are defined to always be in the same space.
Now we can kind of get rid of all of this stuff entirely.
That's just gone.
And now we are basically talking about just having to compute.
So, the diameter, the diameter width and height is basically going to
be pulled off of that other entity, right?
So, do we pass in?
We passed in the entity that we're using?
So now we just need to go ahead and get whatever the other entity is.
So essentially we want,
Get the entity here.
So we've got an entity test entity and that's going to go ahead and
grab whatever.
Whatever entity we're on.
And so when I grab that test annatee, then I'm going to be able to
test against its width and height, right?
And so that's going to be the dormant version.
Like so of that of our entity and it's going to be the dormant version
of the test entity as well.
Right?
So again, we're just taking, we're doing exactly the same test that we
were doing before only now, instead of doing against the tile, we're
doing it again.
The.
Against the other entities.
So before we were looping over each tile.
Now, We're looping over each entity.
And again, we have with some Heights for the entities.
So we'll just use them.
That seems pretty easy.
And so then all we really need to do now is we need to come up with
what we were using before or relative.
Basically a relative position relative to, we got them in.
Quartermaster owner.
We have to have the relative position between the the tests entity and
our entity and that's obviously very easy to do.
That's just the high
And the test energy.
High P are the two positions.
So if I subtract those two, I'm going to get the relative position of
the player, right?
So I can just directly do that basically, right?
So that's the difference between those two and that is pretty much all
I need to do.
There will think that left again.
All this stuff is a little sloppy will come back through here and I
just want to kind of get everything laid out and think about it a
little bit as we go.
So again, looping over all the entities for each iteration of our
Collision solve and we're seeing what if we hit any of them?
And if we do then we just go ahead and and process the Collision like
we were doing before.
Okay, so when we come out of this, we should have a team in just like
we had before, we will update that team in by basically saying okay
The Entity position is going to have added to it.
Whatever that offset was the the velocity will obviously be clipped
like we wanted it to be so that it will no longer have any component.
If there was a wall that it hit, right?
And then the player Delta, which is the thing that we're updating.
By will also get clipped by it, and we will continue our Loop.
So that's about all that really needed to happen there.
The rest of this stuff can kind of work the same as it was before this
stuff is for going up and down, right?
And so I believe what we want to do here is say, okay when we're doing
our Collision, checking, obviously inside here.
We may find, we basically need now to have some concept,
of what our collisions actually do whether or not those collisions are
are things that actually stop the player or whether their collisions
that cause something to happen if that makes sense, so,
While we are iterating here, right?
Every time we hit an entity, it would be nice to remember which
entity.
It was that we hit, right?
So if I have, for example, entity, or a hit entity Index, right?
And remember, zero is the null entity.
In fact, I can always start all of my entities iterations, that one I
always forget that we have a null in today.
So if I have my hit into the index
Assuming that I have a hit entity.
It does kind of mean now that we could do something like okay if hit
entity Index, right if it's going, if something is going to happen
here, we could go ahead and see whether or not whatever that entity
was had something that was supposed to happen when we collide with it,
right?
And I'm not sure exactly what we'd want to do for that.
But you know, if we were talking about something that was like a
doorway.
A or whatever, we could easily put something in here.
Right?
That says, you know, 32d ABS tiles, e, right again, and this is kind
of what I'm doing.
Basically is sticking all of the things that I want Into The Entity
structure for now.
And then we'll sort of see how we want start peeling those off a
little bit later.
Right?
So like this is for stairs.
And I guess we should put stairs in quotes because we don't really
know what we want to do for stairs or rather.
What they're actually, what they'll actually look like in the game.
We don't know if they're actually the stairs.
It's all right.
So, what we could do is say, all right, if we hit, if we hit identity
index, then is that entity index something that we need to process,
you know, does it, do Collision response or does it do some other
magical effect?
Right?
And so what we could do is say another thing we could say here, right?
For example, is
Collides right or collides with, you know, I don't know.
We'll just call it collides for now.
Right?
And so what we could say is well if the test entity, if it collides,
right?
Then we're going to do some testing, but if it doesn't Collide, then
we won't, right?
And so once we do the hit, enter the index, we know that it is
something that does Collide.
And then we can go ahead and here and say, well, this is where we
would process our Collision response and and we can sort of save a
little bit work here because we know that if we didn't hit any
entities, then we know that these things are not in play, right?
So we could go ahead and say that, you know, that we only do this in
the case where we actually hit an entity and otherwise we just
Break out of our Collision Loop all together, right immediately.
So we could do that.
I don't know if we want to do that, but we could do it.
So we might as well.
All right.
And so if we hit an entity index, then it might be nice to go ahead.
And after we update the player position, see what it actually is that
we want to do when we hit this particular entity, right?
So when we hit this particular entity, right, we're going to go ahead
and get it.
So I've got a hit empty here.
And then I'm going to say, well.
Alright now we don't need to know, you know, we don't need to know
most of this other stuff so we can just go ahead and do whatever that
that tile stuff was up in here.
We don't really have to care about this stuff.
Let's get rid of that and then this stuff is updating the facing
directly.
Sharon and this I think we want to change this to be using the
acceleration vector, but we'll just make a note.
We'll worry about that when we get to animation.
All right, so if I'm doing this and I go ahead and get that hit
entity, right?
And then I should be able to say, all right.
Well the entity P ABS tile Z.
So that's going to be in this dormant state, right?
His absolute tile Z is going to have to change now.
And if I change the entities, the position of the guy the camera will
have to change as well, but that's actually fine.
So I think we would move his, I think we would move his abs tiles e
up.
And the only question I have here is, how do we want to deal with that
with the high entity versus the dormant entity.
So I think the problem here if I may is really that these
It's, I want to really be kind of three-dimensional if that makes
sense.
So, I really want these guys to be 3D since they aren't right now.
I'll go ahead and say that the ABS tile Z is actually in here so that
I can update the high one.
But eventually what we're going to do is we're going to extend these
2.
V 3 is which may happen that may have to happen relatively soon.
I definitely want to happen before we get to animation but
That's something we'll have to deal with in a moment.
Okay, so I'm going to go ahead and say, all right.
The high into the ABS tells e is going to get plus equal to whatever.
This D.
AB style Z is here and that's the entity dormant dlz, obviously.
Oops, wrong way there.
And that's how we Implement stairs.
Now again, you can sort of start to see.
I mean, you can, you can vaguely sort of start to see what we're going
to be doing.
Eventually here.
You can sort of a sort of get to feel for it.
After we start piling enough stuff up in here, it would be, it'll be
like, all of the things you ever want to do on collision response.
Would all be in here.
Right?
So you can already see that.
This is a place that we're going to want to start to focus, our
attention in terms of starting to support multiple types, of entities
and that sort of thing.
So that we don't have every single possible thing that could possibly
be in an entity getting stored and getting processed and all that
stuff.
Right?
So you can sort of see how things will our will sort of start to
indicate to us how we need to start to break down the
But at this point, obviously, it's totally fine.
But you can just you can kind of see it already starting.
This is where we'll have a bunch of data and will want to start a
start to Marshall that data sort of keep it under control and in
different ways.
And so that'll be very interesting when we get to that as well, but
we're not there yet.
So, anyway, that's right.
I forgot.
We have to pass.
At least at the moment.
We're passing, what kind of entity resolution we want four things.
So for now, we're doing it this way, but we're going to have to do
some other
other will do some other interesting things.
We might even get to that today.
We'll see.
So,
See here, we have our entity and that's obviously supposed to be that
in the high P.
All of these are empty High data.
There we go.
Entity.
Hi, right and so on and that all looks good.
Oops, that doesn't look good.
And this also has to have that same guy you obviously want to get the
entity at high resolution.
Although actually, we only really need them at dormant now that I
think about it because we're not actually
Doing.
Oh, no, we were doing.
We were doing the EM.
Now.
We're just doing the yeah, we were just doing the, we're just doing
it, the doorman access so we can just get them at dormant little.
All right.
So let's see what else happens here.
These are just ones that have to be changed to emptied.
Hi again, right?
Oops, entity with going to see got high.
So that's just changing like that.
Okay, and there we go.
Oh, well, that compiled the whole thing.
I
Expecting more of a fuss than that, I guess not.
Okay.
So we have a ton of work to do still because we haven't really done
all the stuff that we need to do sort.
For example, Change in city, residents has not been implemented yet.
Right?
And so you can see, we were trying to initialize the player and bring
him in there.
We haven't done that.
We haven't actually put any of the walls into the entity list.
So yes, the stuffs a little bit in a cakes right now, and not in a
particularly good setup, whatsoever.
So, what we need to do first is say, alright, when we
Do change, entity residents?
We have to take a look and see what is going on with the entity.
Right now, we actually only have one thing that we really need to
handle.
Or I should say, 2, to State transitions.
We need to handle, which is basically if, if the residents equals
high, right?
Then we need to guarantee.
We need to move him from dormant too high.
If you was currently dormant or rather just not in high else.
If the residents equals entity residents low, that means removing them
out, right?
That's really all we
You to do.
So, what we can do here is say, alright, if the entity residence
equals entity.
Hi are sorry.
It's not equal to M TT.
Hi, then we know that we have to do the move.
Otherwise, we don't have to do anything because it's already resident
in the place that we wanted to be and if the residents here is not
equal to low, then the same is true, but or I shouldn't say low.
It's actually dormant that we care about here and then I guess we'll
say well, I guess that's really it's really if it's equal.
Well, to anything else at the moment we'd have to think about what
would happen with the when we start to have something actually in low,
but at the moment, everything is actually in the dormant and I wonder
if maybe low entities, maybe just wouldn't have hardly anything else
in them.
So it may look, it may look more.
Like if the residents.
Either it's high and it wasn't high.
So as to move to high or it is anything and was going to be to be high
previously, right?
So it was, you know, it was anything if the residents was was was
already equal to.
Hi.
I guess we could say so if it's high and it wasn't High, then we need
to make it High by translating it up into the camera space.
So
Map The Entity into camera space.
And if it was something other than high and we want and it was if it
was high and we want to be something other than high, then we need to
map it, the entity back into tile space like so, right.
So yeah, so that's really all we need to do.
They're pretty straightforward.
Okay.
And I can already think about some I'm already thinking of some things
that I want to do that.
We released that we're going to have think about that.
I don't quite have captured here.
Like the example, the thing that I'm thinking about it, my head is
what if you want, you almost want it so that you can ask for either
one of these and it's almost more like a caching system if that makes
sense.
Like, I'm thinking about it.
I'm going, like, I don't really want to have to worry about what state
it's in so much as I want to just
Able to ask for one of these types of data.
So if I was Computing in tilemap space, I could ask for the doorman
entity and guarantee that that would be a valid position for him.
Even if he was currently High because it would do the reverse mapping
at the time that I asked if it was stale, you know what I mean?
So, it's
It's a little confusing.
So I got to think that through or I might just do it so that I always
map them back immediately.
After like another thing we could do right is that when we do the move
player at the end, we always just do the reverse mapping just at the
end of that move player.
So we could always just update it up here.
So every time we move somebody we update them just at the end so that
way it's all in float, but you always write back a valid tile position
at the end, you know, that could be kind of interesting too.
Always right back a ballad tile position, right?
Because then everyone who wants to act to execute slowly on dormant or
low?
And it he's can and anyone who wants to go on high as could as well.
It's kind of compelling.
Kind of compelling.
You know what I'm saying to you.
So it basically just be we would have no more concept of re
canonicalize either.
We just have a thing that flat-out maps by doing it directly.
Yeah.
I think that that sounds really good to me.
Right?
Because you can see how that works.
Basically, everything happens on high entities and they just get
pushed down to the doorman entities.
Right?
And then you know that the dormant entities are also always valid.
So you have to worry about the fact that something is wouldn't have a
p that was valid.
So I think that's yeah.
Yeah.
I like that.
I like that a lot.
And so, basically what that means to me as well, is like the change
entity residents, right is only
We going to is only going to really do this case, right?
It never has to map it out.
At all, that'll this will mostly this change.
Entity residents will become mostly about just managing the actual
lists of entities, and it won't really be very much about doing those
mappings.
All the only time it will do a mapping for us is when it needs to
generate the high entity out of the dormant one, right?
So that's kind of cool.
I like where this is going.
I'm already liking this and again, I just want to kind of point this
out.
I've said it a million times.
I'm just gonna say it again.
That's a reason why I code this way.
Is because I never would have thought of all of these things
correctly, right?
I just never would have, I need to go through them and see how they
work, and then come up with them.
And so, I try very hard to structure my programming technique around,
being able to iterate on a number of little design ideas like this.
And then when I know that I've got one, that's good.
Then I blow that out into the full design, right?
And that just saves a tremendous amount of time over trying to
pre-design everything up front, where I will always be wrong.
And I kind of feel like everyone I've ever seen do.
It is also wrong.
I don't think it's like, just me and so, just trying it first and
doing it.
That way is much better, because remember, it doesn't take that long.
We only spent a few hours doing this sort of stuff.
If you count up the timer amount of time, we spend doing it on the
sprit stream.
Any given thing that we're prototyping is usually only 23 hours at
Max, right?
And and so, if you think about how little time, that is to invest
towards exploring and figuring out what truck
Should be, it's so easy.
I mean, you know, people spend that long just draw and diagrams,
right.
That are that are not useful and so,
Playing around with code, is just a really good idea.
I think for figuring out how something should be designed.
So I guess what I want to do here is I want to calculate P.
So what I want to do is I want to say that the entity dormant P equals
map, you know, map into tile space or something like this, right?
And then, what I do is, I would pass the camera that we're using
currently and so that's, that's
This guy right here, right?
So this is, this is the base point.
So, yeah, so game Space camera P.
So that's the base point.
And then my entity.
Hi,
P is my current point.
And I'll just trust that will always generate, you know, a valid sort
of position there.
Right?
And that way, I know that those will always be valid as well, and that
will be pretty free to do.
It's like, you know, to divides or something like that per entity and
we're already doing so much work.
Obviously to update entities that I don't think that'll be
particularly relevant.
Okay.
So if we go ahead and do that, may I really want to I really like
typing doormat.
By the way?
So now we've gotten rid of re canonicalized, right?
It's gone and are we canonicalize function is just going to be that.
That
Mapping function, right?
So in fact, we can even just kind of lean on the one we have already.
So map into tile space write.
This function is now just going to be this, right.
So we pass, we're going to have to pass that tile map.
Oops, town that that's just gonna be map into tile space, right Hoops.
Not that one.
Map into tile space, and all we really have to do is say, okay.
We've got that base position and then we've got an offset, right?
And that's really easy because we already essentially wrote this
function.
All we really have to do is just we don't even have to do the work.
Right.
All we really have to do is just that I think, right.
So basically we take that base position, we treat it as if we had
updated it and then we go in here.
And by the way, I think these were busted, right?
Remember, we didn't really need those.
Um, if I remember correctly, that was just a garbage thing that we've
done because we had forgot to call reconnect lives or something like
this.
I don't know.
They were sent there was something that's going on there.
So we're gonna get rid of that for now as well.
Alright, so let's go ahead and see if we've got this correctly.
Not a member of tilemap writes, the offset their and reconnect lies
position.
We don't care about this anymore.
See, and that is it.
Aunt isn't, it's right.
It's not world, we go.
So let's do that.
And let's that's Point as well.
Alright, so that is that.
Now, what should happen I guess at the moment is we should okay.
We still have one more thing to implement and that is the change
entity residents function that has to go ahead and actually map
things.
Into entity space into the camera space.
So wherever that camera p is right, what we need to do is say we need
to do that difference.
That tile difference that we were doing before, right?
Here we go.
Let's see.
Tom app difference, we need to do this guy.
So we got to take that difference.
Where is that function?
It is subtract.
And so we are going
Subtract the entity position.
And that's the dormant position from wherever the camera is at the
moment.
And that is going to be where the entity now resides.
All right, so I would that needs the tile map.
So let's see.
We just did a ton of stuff.
I feel the need at the moment to kind of Step through here and kind of
get our bearings a little bit.
These are addresses.
So that diff now needs to have our entity High has to get initialized.
So what have we got here?
Well, oops.
Well, our enemy, hi now has two.
Have a key which is just going to be that div a right.
So that's the X Y, our entity High.
D p is going to be nothing will just assume.
He has no velocity at start which may be something.
We want to change in the future, but we're not sure it's ABS tile.
Z is just going to be whatever it's Z actually was, right.
So that's going to be AB style Z there and it's facing Direction.
Is just going to be 0.
I guess.
We'll assume that gets updated some point.
What was the actual name for that?
D?
X,y.
So, all right.
So let's see what's going on now because we've made so many changes at
this point groups.
Then MS.
Death was the old name.
They change it to Dev.
MF.
Don't ask me why, nobody knows.
So let's take a look at what's going on here because who has any idea
at this point?
What?
Going on.
So what we would want to start with is we want to start with the point
where a player actually becomes active.
Right?
So I hit the spacebar and we're going to add an entity we go through
here.
It's going to be entity one, which is correct.
That's what we want.
I would like to turn hexadecimal off, please.
Yeah.
And that's going to go ahead and clear all of the stuff out which is
fine and we're going to send it to dormant and that's about it.
Then we're going to initialize the player.
So we're going to go ahead and get that entity and let's see here.
We got all of the versions of it, even though it's technically still
dormant.
That's okay.
Because we're not actually doing any kind of compression with that
yet.
We're going to set where we think that it is and you know, we haven't
actually set.
Do we actually, I guess we did set the
Camera position as well.
So then we're going to call change entity residents.
So we come up here.
We say if the residents equals High, which it does in this case, but
it wasn't equal to high before, then we need to do our initialization
at the high entity.
So let's take a look.
Where is that?
It's - 9 - 1.
Those are relatively reasonable values.
I would think and we're going to
That ABS tile to where it was facing Direction.
So we've done that.
And since there was nothing else.
We're going to set the camera to follow and we're going to have to go.
We have to go update that camera fellow codes, don't think we ever
actually did that.
Alright, so that's all we did there and then we should be able to kind
of will step through it a little bit more and see.
All right.
So we're doing this railroad rail column nonsense now, so this stuff
is going to go away as well.
I think in a second here.
We'll find out.
So let me skip it.
Skip through here, anything that's entity residents High which is the
first one in the second one.
Neither of them were.
Oh, did we forget?
You know what?
I think we forgot to actually ever set the residence change and see
residents.
So we need to do at the end of this is say entity residents equals
So otherwise it'll never get marked as high which is not what we want.
Okay, so let's try that one more time.
See what happens.
So, we want to go down here to there, and let's see what happens here.
So, if we do this and I hit the spacebar.
I am still not even triggering your breakpoints.
So why is that the case did we, or did we not add an entity?
I guess we did not have an entities somehow.
So let's find out.
Let's open right?
Oh, that was funny.
That was funny.
If that doesn't change the end of the residence, that's just a note of
what the residence is.
We actually need to do it here, right?
That's actually where we need to change the actual entity.
Residence.
So I'm guessing that really what we want to do for that is that that
should probably be.
We would put that in the dormant part after I suspect, because there's
really no need for having an extra one here since we always have to
have the
The Entity data, but yeah, I don't know.
I don't know.
Yeah, well, there's a couple things we need to do.
So, let's do them both.
So, first of all, let's change this so that when we do the change,
entity residents will actually just do this.
In fact, you know, what, we don't even really need change.
Entity residents to do that.
Really, right.
This is actually going to be here, and this could actually be
something that's just taking the you into
32 of the end of the index.
So this is going to go ahead and say that entity residents like so is
Empty index equals the residents, right?
And then this entity.
Hi, it's only going to probably ever have to.
Well, now I guess it needs to do the rest of it too.
But that's just going to go ahead and do these two.
So in the case where these are here, we have the high entity equals
game State, high entities, and 50 index.
Go and the doorman entity.
T is game, state government entities, and 50 index.
All right, so we've got those, that's all.
Happy change this that that?
Okay, so that'll do that.
And I'm just going to have get entity.
Say, if the residents that you requested is less than
The residents are sorry is a greater than the residents that the
entity currently is, right, then it'll do that change.
So the first thing it will do is say, okay.
Here.
Yeah, because this is, this is garbage.
In fact, what this is doing.
This is not actually what it should be doing.
Right?
Because this was just filling in, whatever the residents was, we
really want to do is say if what we were currently residing at, right?
If the current residents like so if the current place that we are
residing is not where we want to reside, right?
So if it's less than, then we need to do that change entity residents
right to make sure that it's not anymore.
And
We can know that it is, so we could assert here that it was right,
that these are equal after the fact.
And or I shouldn't say equal The Entity residents is at least greater
than, or equal to, because really, we could allow that function that
change residents to change.
You at its discretion to a higher level of residence.
We just don't want you to change you to a lower level of residents.
So that's what that does, right?
Okay.
So, all we really need to do now.
Is figure out where is that residents again?
That residence is here.
So what we need to say is if the entity residents as it exists is not
equal to high.
Then there we go.
And let's see, change it to your residence.
This takes an empty index now and this is stuff.
I don't like about that too.
Many indexes versus struck thing.
So we have to look at that a little bit more, but does it really
matter at the moment?
Okay, so that should be now, I think changing it.
That we actually have an entity.
Okay, we do and let's take a look at what the entity actually looks
like high entity, low, entity dormant entity, right?
Here.
They are.
So there's the offset of the
Guy is facing Direction.
Let's see.
What happens here.
There.
He is.
He's moving around now.
He should be able to walk straight through walls, which is true,
because, of course, we're not doing, we're not adding those entities
yet, right now.
If I add another guy, I feel like maybe they would Collide now
potentially.
Maybe not know.
So I would like to double.
I'd like to go see why?
That isn't because of that, I think should be working.
So let's let's debug that because that is the one Collision that I do.
Think should probably work.
So, let's take a look.
So, what should be happening is when we do our Collision iterations
here, right?
We should be testing with the oh, you know, what else?
We kind of need to do is well, we need to make sure we don't collide
with our self.
Let me do that first as well.
Why do I keep closing the app?
I have to remember to stop closing the app.
I never need to close the app.
I need to fix the thing that was working out at work so that it has
the hot reloading as well.
So I just get used to never having to close apps anymore.
You should never really have to close them.
All right.
So what I want to do is say, don't use the index that we are, right?
So, you know, and that's pretty easy.
I could just test the pointer as well.
So I could just say all right.
No.
Basically, if test entity, .hi is not equal to Unity.
Hi, something like this, right?
That'd be pretty trivial, way to avoid testing against oneself.
Alright, so off we go and keep going there.
Let's move this guy over here.
Right?
And this is a search should be colliding, It Isn't.
So, I think that's just a bunch.
Right, so I want to see and make sure that we're actually okay.
So the first time through, we wouldn't try to collide with that guy
because it's us the next time through.
There we go.
It is not set to collide.
That would be it.
So when we add a player we want to say Clyde's, is true, right?
And now, maybe they will collide.
I don't know, hard to say very hard to say.
In fact, if we go, there we go.
And so we'll move this guy in here and see what happens if they
Collide they do.
In fact Collide.
Yes, although it doesn't quite skate properly.
So we still have some bugs in there.
Again.
The Collision Vector is pretty bad at this point.
So it's really not that big of a deal, but that should not be
happening.
Don't believe so.
We should go.
Double-check, what's going on in there?
I think that might just be again with the, I don't know if that's more
with the Epsilon issues.
On because like we haven't really done a good job.
Making our Coalition detector, do anything that you would want it to
normally do to keep things robust or good.
We only did like the very bare minimum.
So, you know, if this was something a little more conservative here, I
wonder if that would also keep us out of the woods until we actually
go ahead and make a real Collision sector but let's see.
Yeah.
So the sticking is definitely not is definitely not right.
At least you don't get Epsilon trapped anymore.
Yeah.
So what's going on with our sticking?
What is the problem?
Did I inadvertently muck up the code when I came in here.
So assuming that I hit an entity, if I didn't hit an entity.
Oh.
Do I ever actually set that?
Of course, not?
Duh, all right.
So that's our only problem entity index has to be equal to whatever
the enemy index was right that we, that we actually hit.
So, there we go.
That's really all we needed.
We weren't actually ever processing that case.
So yeah, of course, this is actually stuck in the guy now, that's
pretty funny.
Well, that's actually not that big of a deal to fix, right?
I can just do
I can just do this.
Right.
Initial stress is constant.
I know, well, if entity index equals zero, there we go.
Now I can get out, right?
And then I may have to fix the Collision detector.
It's bugging me enough that it's not robust enough yet that it's
already bugging me a little but okay, at least now gliding is working
properly.
So we can at least get that roughly.
Okay.
I hate leaving things broken, but sometimes I know that it's better to
leave them broken.
When you're not trying to actually ship them, your, you may just be
wasting time and so it's good to not do that sometimes and I can
appreciate that.
Anyway.
That's good.
That guys colliding properly, so that's nice.
And so now let's think about what else we need to do.
So we've done our mapping and everything is now happening in float
space, which is good.
That's all very nice.
But we also.
Now, let's start to look at what we have to do for the world itself
and also for moving the camera.
So like, let's try to put doors in there.
Let's try it with fire, but stairs and the walls, and that sort of
stuff, right?
Because you haven't done that yet.
So, assuming that, whatever the camera following entity is has,
That's the that's one we should.
We should look at right to be sure.
So.
What we want to do here.
Is make this work in Thailand camera space like our to do said, so we
want to do is say all right.
Well, we already know the stuff.
We were Computing with that diffe before we already know where the guy
is relative, the camera because his high position is now exactly that,
right.
So all we really need to say is okay, if the camera following entity
High position
Right?
If the camera following entity High position is if that is greater
than however far, we allow him to walk, then we know we need to move.
The same is true.
Right?
For the other directions.
These are all exactly the same checks as they were, right.
No big deal, py and so on.
So when we do these checks, we now will move the ABS tile.
X, the app style.
Why?
We'll move all those in the right direction.
So what we need to do is we just need to take whatever that difference
is.
However, far the camera moved.
So, this is the original camera P, right?
Or the old camera pee.
We'll do whatever updating we need to do to follow the guy and then
we'll take a look and see whatever his whatever that cameras position
is.
Now.
We need to update all the end of these by that.
Right?
So we basically need to say, okay.
Let's take a look at what that tilemap diff was, again.
See, what is that called?
Tile, Tom app difference.
So we need to do tile map difference and we will go ahead and say from
the current right to the camera P will subtract away.
Whatever.
The old camera P was.
Right?
And that gives us how far we have to move everything.
That's right.
That's how far the old the camera moved from, its current location to
its new location, right?
So
If that's the direction that the camera moved.
Then what we want to do is we want to move everyone else by the
opposite of that, right?
In other words.
This is this is the D camera p.
And what we want to do is have like the object offset, right?
So the offset they're going to apply to all of the entities.
So the entity offset is going to be the opposite of that, right?
To give you some perspective.
What I'm talking about here.
We have the screen.
We know that the camera was here and then we did something and we're
going to say, okay the camera goes here.
So entities that were here, right?
When the camera moves, if we were to apply the same translation, they
would move with us, but that's not what we want.
We're moving away from them.
So they should be the opposite direction.
Right?
So we want to basically move them the other direction so that when we
render them, they'll appear to have slid, if that makes sense.
So we want to move them count.
To the motion of the camera.
So this is basically D camera P DX y, right.
That's what we're going to do there.
And then we just Loop over all the entities and we Loop over the all
the entities and apply that.
And what we could do if we wanted to actually is we can roll that in.
We can just straight-up role that in to our to our update Loop.
Actually, you know, we could just do this.
We could eat, we could just do this Sophie to entity Offset, you know,
for frame equals nothing.
And then we compute it in that case, right?
And then, when we're in here, when we grab that high entity.
The first thing we do is just say, okay.
Hi, entity P, plus equals entity all set for frame.
Make sense seems pretty reasonable.
He's got to be addresses, of course, and that has to be an arrow.
So I think that's all that has to happen for updating.
Those guys will drop it in a tea down there.
And then we'll drop another one in here.
Help me out.
They get they spawn in each other.
Then they can't leave because the wall prevents the Collision.
So lame, I gotta I gotta fix that.
I mean, not that you should ever spawn inside someone but obviously
just just the way the conductor works just a little wonky there.
So yeah, so now that's that's correct, I believe.
And so we need to do now is
Oh, we wrapped which we don't allow by the way.
What's that Tyrell?
Times greater than.
Yeah, so we don't, since we don't support rapping.
We can't walk off the bottom side of the screen yet, right?
Or the left side.
That's a, that's a massive faux pas.
I suppose, we'll have to go ahead and move ourselves to the center.
That'll be a good thing that we can do as well for getting us into the
position that we that we want to be in for storing stuff sparsely.
So yeah, that's all good.
So now we really just kind of need to I guess.
One thing we could do is we'll start.
We'll start by making doors.
These guys work again.
The stairwells also should we be able to find some other part of the
world here that had stuff in it?
When we came back downstairs.
There should have been a place where we came back downstairs, right?
Yeah.
Here it is.
Of course, I don't know where it comes back again.
I'm lost.
It really would help if we had more backgrounds.
There we go.
Yeah, so yeah, I guess what I'll do is since we're at the five-minute
warning, I won't try and do that today, but that's basically, I guess
what we'll do tomorrow is Will.
Art by starting to deal with.
Putting the walls in the door, putting the walls in the stairs.
I should say in there, that seems like the most logical next thing to
do.
And then at that point, we should have ourselves in position to kind
of take a step back and look at what's going on with the entities and,
and with everything else so that we can maybe turn the crank one more
time on that and do a little more stuff.
Like, you know, like I said, maybe, let's put some monsters in here.
Let's put some hip points in here.
Let's put
You know, some gaming stuff in there.
So we can start to see how that entity structure shapes up and maybe
play around a little bit with how we want to structure that.
But yeah, so and we'll, we'll try spamming out.
A lot of entities and having the dormant array and then on door opener
a look, we'll just let us try all that stuff a little bit just to kind
of get us to the point where were relatively certain that we've got
things should you know shook out as much as they need to be.
I suspect I want to do a couple more things to that high dormant low
structure.
Once I have some people simulating out, like, in the world that's not
on camera and so on.
Yeah, so what we need to do now, let me just put in some to dues for
tomorrow, so we know what we're doing.
So basically what we need is, we're going to need some functions here,
right?
We're going to need like, when the camera moves so in the, in the
case, for the camera moves like there to do Casey map.
New entities in and old entities out.
Whoa, I forgot.
I got that.
Zoom feature.
And these out.
And we also want to do some stuff with mapping tiles and stairs into
the empty set and then we'll be good.
So I think that's yet.
I think that's about right and that is what we will do tomorrow.
Okay, we're a little early, but that's okay.
I don't want to start something else now because it's going to be a
relatively major something.
So, let's go ahead and go to the Q&A.
Please prefix, your questions.
Q:.
So, I will see them and please keep them to be stuff that we did on
today streamer that we did in a previous stream so that we don't get
off topic.
If you want to do off-topic questions, come about 15 minutes before
the stream starts, and we will, we will talk about them then.
Let's see.
Do we have any questions?
That's the real question.
The real question is, do we have any questions?
Why can't infrequent entity updates happen in the entities update
logic?
So that's kind of a slightly odd question because what we're talking
about here is really when the entities update logic gets called, if
that makes sense.
So, the reason that I don't want to have to, so, you know, if you're
thinking about it like
If you're thinking about it, like something like this, you know, the
sort of the, the old-school object-oriented way where you've got
something like this, you know, happening, any logic that you put in
here is inherently pretty problematic.
Right?
And the reason it's problematic is because frequency update logic that
goes in here, you have to call them all.
So if I wanted to scale the number of entities to a very large number,
like, let's say I wanted to scale to 100,000 in it.
Or something like that, right?
Well, now I have to make 100,000 virtual function calls just to find
out whether or not the entity should get updated.
Right?
And that's just very inefficient.
And, you know, you can pick the number, whatever the number is that
you want depending on how fast the machine is.
Obviously your you're just, you're not going to scale properly.
So what you want to do is you want to make it so that you have some
kind of a concept.
Outside from the entity of which entities need what, when?
Right.
And so by breaking it into the do, at least two tiers.
I don't know if we'll have three in the end.
But at least two tiers high frequency and low frequency, right?
We know that we can always scale up the number of entities and not
have have to worry about performance CPU performance.
Now, Memory footprint.
Another question, right?
How much storage we have?
Four entities is separate issue, right, but we want to worry about
performance because we
Always scale up the number of entities by updating them less
frequently, right?
So we are free to make that trade-off with the virtual function call
method.
You can't make that trade-off.
You've completely given up the ability to make that trade-off, right?
Because just the act of looping over them and issuing.
The virtual function call is too slow at some breaking point.
Where as well.
We won't have that problem, right?
We can scale up almost ad infinitum and you just won't pay for it, you
know, as long as you set that tick frequency to be low enough.
It'll
I'll work, it'll just get less accurate, right?
And that's a much better place to be.
Why do you want to use a 3D Vector for?
When the Z value is always going to be an integer.
So I don't think it's gonna always be even sure.
That's the reason why I agree that if it was always going to be
integer, it would be kind of dumb but I don't think it is going to be.
So here's what I think, what I think is we're going to have a problem.
Well, we already have the problem, but we're going to have to solve
the problem.
Let me put it that way.
And basically that is, we've got dudes, right, you know, we've got our
hero or whatever and you know, he's walking around.
And and if you think about the way that he is structured, and the way
that other things, the world is structured like, you know, tree or
whatever.
We want to be able to do stuff like have him jump right or bounce.
So he might be off the ground, right?
So if this is the shadow of the guys, right?
And here we go.
Right, and so now he's got are right.
He's jumping up and down or whatever, right?
So think about all of this and think about how this works.
We're going to have to render him so that everything occludes
properly, right?
We're going to have to render him so that if there's a tree and he's
in front of the tree, right?
If he's in front of the tree, then we don't want anywhere where he is.
We don't want the tree to be obscuring him.
We want him to be in front of the tree, right?
You know, we want, I don't know if this eraser Works, let's find out.
No, of course, the Eraser doesn't work.
Why would the eraser work?
It's only 2015.
There's no reason why a drawing program would be able to have the
eraser work on the pan.
so anyway,
so we want him to be able to occlude the tree so that you don't see
what's behind him.
Right?
So if you think about it, how are we going to do that?
You know, what's our, what's our cue?
How does the engine even know what's in front of what and the answer,
you know, one pretty trivial answer is.
Well, the y coordinate tells us something about where things are
right?
Because things that are higher up on the screen, right?
Our first are back further away from the camera in our mental model,
right?
In other words, when we when we're doing this, right?
And we have this guy here and we you know, we move this guy in front
of him.
That looks right?
But that looks wrong already.
You know what I mean?
So we know that things with a higher.
Why we're going to have to start drawing them behind things with a
lower y.
So the lower the why is the closer the camera?
It is basically right?
Does that make sense?
Hopefully, I'm not saying anything here, that's totally ridiculous.
And this all makes a fairly reasonable sense to you.
So what happens now when we start talking about jumping, well, if this
guy jumped such that his wife, I was up further, you know, here or
whatever.
Or something like that.
We don't want to draw behind the tree because he's still in front of
the tree.
He's just jumping.
So the y-coordinate alone is not sufficient.
Right?
What we really want to know is that there's a wide base point and that
base point you sorted, but then there's also a z which essentially
translates the why upward and gives it a higher Y without actually
changing its or
So I think we're going to have x,y positions for people plus a z
position for you know for Sprites and whatever and the same would go
for flying entities like, you know, if there's a dude with wings and
he's flying around, right?
That that to me is is what I think would probably happen.
And so what I want to do is switch to using x y z and then the Z
values will just work like everything else.
They'll be some height.
Where if you go
Above that height.
You have walked on to the next tile map slice, and it'll just work.
Uniformly, with the X and Y.
That's my hope.
We'll see what actually happens.
Dustin kalsi.
Kaur infection have to be axis.
Aligned know we implemented a very simple algorithm.
A very simple version of the minkowski closure sector.
Like I said, it's not very good, will be doing much better stuff.
As we go further in the Stream.
I just want to do something to get a collision Vector in there,
because I don't think we need much of a conductor right now to
prototype stuff, but later, the one that we
I assume anyways, I don't know till we actually get there, but I
assume the one will do later on the stream will actually handle
rotation.
Probably just fine.
I don't know if we'll actually use it for rotation, will probably use
it more for shape variance, so that we can have circles and that kind
of stuff, but you could have used the same technique would work for
rotation.
Just not animated rotation.
Okay, no more questions.
That is it for questions.
Well.
Very well.
I guess.
I guess we will end early tonight.
Seems like it.
I'll wait a couple seconds more just to see whether anyone has one.
Didn't you just Implement a bare-bones?
Relational database?
How do you think that's a good mental model?
For understanding today's code?
Well.
That's a interesting question.
So, I did, I have implemented an entire game engine before.
By writing a relational database at the bottom at the that was like at
the bottom of it.
and what I would say is,
It is.
Relational databases in general.
Isn't really much of a statement like a relational database implies,
usually a bunch of additional stuff.
If you say it to most people like their thinking sequel, they're
thinking query-based stuff.
And a lot of that isn't necessarily relevant to what we're doing here.
But if you're literally just talking about the cost of relational
database, where you have a key.
And you can pull things on a key and, you know, you can gather from
multiple tables.
Then.
Yeah, I mean that is a, that is a very good mental model for things.
Unfortunately.
If you think about it too much, in terms of the way that they're often
implemented or exposed to the programmer in today's world.
It becomes not such a good model.
And the reason for that is because a lot of things that you want to
just be able to do with pointers and graphs and
Of are really not representable in query languages like Sequel and so,
you know, you end up with all these ridiculous things like stored
procedures and just all this garbage happening that you just don't
want.
And so,
I guess what I would say about relational databases is that if you're
thinking of it literally, just as may be learning some of the first
principles of relational database storage might be useful way of
thinking about it.
But if you're thinking about it, like sequel, that's not such a good
way, right?
Because sequels, just kind of not good.
But I mean, hardcore, relational, database, people don't think
sequels, good either, you know, well, I shouldn't say that there are.
There definitely are, hardcore, relational.
Database people who think that sequel is a very good either.
So, you know, that's hardly a surprise, right?
I noticed your character do not collide with each other.
I thought you changed.
No, it does Collide.
It's just we're only at the moment.
We kind of we're trying to decide how big the players footprint is.
And right now it's just those those rectangles.
So it's just a little rectangles that Collide and you can see that
they do actually Collide at the moment.
Right?
Does that make sense?
So those are what Collide?
Now, we will allow the player to walk through like for example, that
is a totally valid configuration for entities even in the final game,
right?
You don't want to prevent them.
I'm from Staten.
You don't want to make it so that it collides when it gets to here.
That doesn't make any sense.
Right?
Because in, since these things kind of overlap, you want them to be
able to get overlapping in in why like that, if that makes sense.
So I think this is basically what we want.
The only thing that I was pointing out that we need to do is the the
we need to start.
When we do our renderer.
We need to do that sort of sorting by y, so that we can make sure that
we draw.
When you go behind something, you draw behind it instead of in front
of it right now.
It's just drawing.
Whatever order to the entities come in, right and that's not very
useful.
But the Collision is working properly.
How good is this addressing scheme for the cash?
It's not very good right now.
Well, I mean, I don't know how good is right now because I haven't
tested it, but it's not very good right now.
It's not good for the cash or for CMD operations.
So, I don't, like I said, I don't expect.
We will store things exactly this way, when we kind of get to the end
of the, of the tunnel, if you will, when we would actually do some of
those operations.
I don't know.
But like right now, if you're looking
For cash friendliness.
This is not going to be your friend at the moment, but you but also
right now, we don't really want to be optimal in cash - because we
don't even really know exactly how all of our operations work.
So until we do, we can't really think about the cash very well.
When jumping you just need XYZ coordinates to make it happen.
Question mark.
Yeah.
I mean, jumping is just.
Like we don't have a z coordinate for our guy.
Well, I mean you can
Yeah, I mean, I'm trying to think of what the easiest way.
Like, so jumping is just is just someone who gets some upward velocity
and then and has gravity, right?
I mean, if we had 3D vectors, which I don't really want to throw in
right now, but you could do it.
I mean, one way to think about it would just be, you know, if you
wanted to do jumping you just say, okay.
There's there's like a z value here, right in high-end stereo or
something like that.
And when you draw the guy,
The place that you're going to draw him, like the player ground point
or whatever.
You just go ahead and say we're going to offset it by whatever the
high end, it easy value.
Right, and so if I do that, let me see here.
If I do that right, then I should get exactly the same thing I had
before, right?
But now if I go ahead and actually jump it, although you know, what,
let me, let me, let me do it in a slightly different place to let me
do it actually here just like that, right?
Okay.
So now if you take a look at this, right?
If we were to change that high entity Z.
So let's say we took High entity Z and made it equal to, you know, to
We're for something like this.
Right?
And we still need I guess I should also point out, we need to do.
We need to do Z equals.
High entity.
See,
Like so, and we need to change that m 2 pics.
So there we go.
So we got our high into d z, so I'm going to make that a z.
So we're going to offset the bitmaps Y by Z.
Okay, and I can't remember.
So we're actually doing our flip here and then the drawbitmap expects,
the calls pre flipped.
Is that correct?
Yeah, that's correct.
So really the Z value is also negated, right?
Because it's going upwards for positive Z.
So, now you can see the guys like offset.
Maury should be right.
And he's like a meter above or two meters above Race, should be or
something.
Right?
So, there's there's where he is.
So, if we wanted to now, we could totally make the dude Jump by just
having right of velocity in Z.
That's all we would need to do and hopefully it's clear like how that
would work.
Right?
It would work by going, you know, for each entity.
The high entity Z, we have the, you know, remember the equations of
motion.
So the equations of motion that we had up here, right?
To remember these guys.
They're exactly the same if we wanted to do Z, right.
So you would just do exactly this.
You'd basically have whatever the Delta Z is.
So this is the Delta Z.
It's going to be the square of the time step and then it's going to be
whatever the Z velocity is times that like so on and the ddz, right?
So this is the acceleration.
This is the velocity and then we've got that Delta Z.
So and to update this, we just have to take again that and
T.
What's up, right?
So that would be read up.
You update the Z exactly the same way as we were updating everything
else.
That's why I say we could we should just use three-dimensional
coordinates really but you know, you'd update the jump Z exactly that
way and then what you do is
Okay, you know the high the this is the Delta Z.
There we go.
We don't want the high entities, easy to ever be less than zero or
whatever.
The ground height is will stay at zero for now.
So off we go and then we need, whatever the acceleration is in Z and
of course the acceleration in Z is negative 9.8 meters per second
squared, right?
Because that's the speed of gravity and the DT is going to be
Whatever that what our game input is rdt for frame, right?
There is our GT per frame.
DT for fraying.
Let's see.
It is a frame.
To, here we go.
So the DZ is the high entity DC.
So there we go.
And so I think that should now give us our dude.
Okay, so he doesn't have any Z velocity right now.
And so all we really need to do is give him some Z velocity.
So if we went into our code here when we, when we do our controller
check, if we, you know, went and said, all right.
If if action up and down then we'll just say that whatever entity this
is controlling entity High DZ equals.
He's got some, you know, he's just got some velocity right that
upward.
Right, and that's probably a bit too high of a jump to say, the very
least.
So there we go.
That's probably too little of a jump.
So, there we go.
Right.
And off you go.
So that's, that's really all.
It's literally the same equations of motion for last time just with
gravity in there.
And if you don't like, you know, obviously the speed of gravity,
that's fine too.
You know, I didn't actually check to see very carefully whether I had
done it properly, but I think everything should be correct here,
right?
Whatever the square of the time.
Step is blah, blah blah, right.
And
Yeah, and we're adding in.
Now, the question of like, depending on the perspective.
This is, this is not really a correct.
This is not really correct here.
It's really hard to say.
But yeah, you can then tweak these values if you wanted us, you know,
a stronger jump value.
So he jumps quicker or not as fast or whatever, right?
But that's, that's it.
I mean, that's all jumping is and so hopefully, you can see how that
worked.
It's exactly the same stuff we did from,
Or this is just the equations of motion.
Here's the update to the position.
In fact, we don't really need Delta Z in there at all.
You could just look at it this way, right?
So the new p is just equal to, right is equal to one half.
Ay t squared plus T times V.
Right?
So there's the acceleration, there's the 1/2, there's the squared
time.
Just like we did equations of motion.
Here's the T times the velocity because there's the velocity, right?
And here's the original position, P Prime.
And then the update to the velocity is just
Just okay, whatever the velocity, whatever the acceleration was times
the time, step, plus, whatever the velocity was before, and then this
just prevents them from falling through the ground, right?
So that's the equations of motion for jumping and there really isn't
anything else to it.
I mean, that's, that's that's all there is and that again, if you want
to tweak those constants at fine, but that'll give him the parabolic
arc as well.
Now I can double jump or triple jump, right?
Because we haven't done anything to prevent that.
So I can kind of fly him quite quite a ways away from where he should
be.
But you know, what did I do?
So yeah, I don't know that we I guess we can leave that in there for
now.
We'll pull it out later, but that's jumping.
Will be switched to some kind of sparse storage, for example, for the
high-res entities.
Yes, that's my plan.
So my plan is basically to have like a small array of high-res
entities and a large array of doorman entities.
And I don't know if we'll have like a low.
If I have a separate storage for low or whether the low will just be
stuff that is operating on the dormant.
We'll have to see.
So I'm not sure.
How would you handle jumping on a ledge or Surface to adopt a new base
height?
Well, I mean, you know, it depends on what you're trying to do.
In this particular case, if I, you know, if I was going to do
If I was going to pack it in here, it would look very different than
if I was trying to do something where I was really making a
platformer.
Like this is not a game where people jump like he will not really jump
in the game.
He just going to bounce around as part of his animation.
So he's not he's never going to jump in gameplay terms.
He's only jumping visibly, right?
Just kind of just a little hop.
So, I'm not really thinking about that too much, but you could imagine
making it so that, you know, tiles, the different entities had
Heights.
And if he was above that height, then you would go ahead and set his
base Z like you would basically say, what am I standing on?
What's its Z and that's my base Z value.
I mean,
That's one way you could do it, but I'd have to it would be dependent
largely on what the game was and what I was trying to do.
So, I'm not sure I can really give a very good answer.
This is kind of funny.
Yeah.
What do you think about physics for character or mob movement in a
platformer game meaning that I press, right, but it start to
accelerate instead of just move.
So I like that feeling, that's the way I'm doing it here.
You'll notice that the guy has some startup time and some slow down
time, and I like that feel.
I don't like instantaneous on instantaneous off.
It doesn't feel good to me.
But that is a preference thing, right?
That's, that's what do you like your game?
I feel like kind of a thing and it also is a design decision, like
some games.
Want a little more swimmy, feel in the controls and some want more
Precision.
So, I would say you can have to think about if you know, you'd have to
think about what you want.
Now make him jump through the ceiling into the next floor.
Really?
I don't really want to do that.
I cuz we're not set up.
This is not the appropriate place to be doing that kind of thing.
I mean, we'd have to say how high the thing should be.
Yeah, I don't want to do that right now.
Why is he so huge?
Well, because we haven't really scaled him down to how big we want to
me, but it doesn't matter because we don't, you know, we're not really
at this age where we care about that.
So I kind of like him giant.
But yeah, he'll be a bit smaller.
I suppose he's really giant if we do this, but yeah, we will.
It's kind of funny when he jumps.
Anyway.
Will the floor area of the zones be flat or will it have slopes and 3D
zones?
A Cahill's?
Flat always the reason that I decided I wanted to always be flat is
because I don't like the way Hills work in 2D games.
Really?
They always annoy me.
I'm just always found them really, really annoying like either.
They don't work the way you expect them to, and it's annoying or they
do work the way you expect them to.
And
Are annoying.
Like both cases are annoying.
One way is like.
I'm at the top of the hill and I'm trying to shoot down at someone and
I can't because like, the shot hits the ground or one of the other
end.
Like it's annoying or like it doesn't do that.
And so I think the enemy can't shoot me from there, but he can, like,
I don't know.
I just, I'm never satisfied with hills.
They just don't seem to work into, like, in 3D, they work fine.
Because it's all kind of in a consistent environment.
But in 2D because you have this sort of hybrid of like, well, things
are sort of drawn in 3D, but but, you know, we it's not real.
A prospective and it's not really transformed.
You get you just get these conditions that I don't like and so I just
I flat out said there's no Hills.
I think yangshin would prefer that there were Hills but there's not
gonna be any Hills.
There will be over hanging stuff.
So there will be a clue ders like like arches and stuff that you go
through and stuff like that.
I think there will be those, but there will not be Hills.
Can you change the yellow tile beneath his feet quickly and easily to
be grayish and round.
So, it looks like a jumping Shadow, completely not required, but why
not?
Yeah, I mean obviously you could do that.
So, what you would want to do for that?
So we've got the draw rectangle call.
Right.
And really probably what you'd want to do is call drawbitmap instead.
So like what you would do did we put a shadow already in the data
directory, though?
So there's already a shadow, right?
So we could do is just say instead of drawing.
If you don't like that rectangle, you could just go ahead and close it
out and say that you wanted to draw game State Shadow and
And that just be, that just be fine.
Yeah.
So yeah, you get the idea.
So you would basically say that there's a shadow here, and then when
we load the backdrop, right?
We'd just do
Something like this, right?
Test here.
Oh shit.
And see.
Do that, right?
All right.
There you go.
So there's the shadow, right?
And, oh, right.
I forgot that doesn't move.
So the shadow should not move.
The shadow should just be there, right?
So then he's jumping right, but what you really you want that we don't
have scaling in our rendering yet.
So you would want that to shrink that shadow to shrink and so we could
approximate that that affect by multiplying through by the alpha.
And we're really getting off topic here people, but you know,
Why not?
So if we add a c Alpha in here, right?
So we basically multiply our Alpha value by some other value when we
come through here and we pick up the a value, right?
We can go ahead and say that a x equals the C Alpha if we if we did
that, then you can notice nothing changes.
But if we then go in here and make that proportional to r z value,
right?
So when we draw the shadow will pass
That c Alpha value through here.
And then what we do is we say that the C Alpha value equals, you know,
1.0 f- whatever the entities Z is so that when he gets higher the
alpha value gets less, right?
And then a c Alpha.
We just make sure that if that's greater than I'm sorry, if that's
less than 0, we clamp it, right.
So it doesn't get less than zero and then you can kind of see
Right, it feels a little more, right?
You know, this this is this is pretty, we're playing it pretty fast
and loose here, but you can kind of, you know, gives a little bit
better feel, but we'd want to scale it down as well as what we're
doing here.
So so there you go.
That's there's a shadow for you.
If you wanted to Shadow, you got a shadow.
If you add walls in the middle of rooms, would they be handled as
entities to the perfect of collision detection or separately?
So what we're going to do I think and like I said, this is just me
playing around but I'm pretty sure we're going to do and this is what
I'm trying.
That's what we do tomorrow is everything's going to be entities in the
active play field.
So all the trees will be entities.
The walls will be entities.
Everything will be entities.
And when you move off the screen, they'll get moved back to the city
of town map.
Let's see.
She's too fast.
What is too fast?
The, the, the the fading out too fast.
I should just quickly say what I did there for in case you meant to
faster the explanation.
So the person wanted to Shadow, right?
So all I did was I just loaded a shadow bitmap that we had and I put
it down there, right?
And so instead of drawing a rectangle.
I draw through the shadow bitmap, but when he gets further away from
the ground,
You know, a shadow is caused by the Light that's coming in is getting
blocked by the person who's standing there.
And so it can't hit the ground, but as he jumps, there's he's when
he's further away from the ground, more light is able to get in at
that ground patch that he is, you know, so that he's no longer really
including that area.
Right?
And so as he jumped higher, I was just saying, oh, well, you know, the
shadow area should get smaller and we don't really have
The ability to scaling right now, but we do did have the ability to do
right, is our drawbitmap function does alpha blending.
So we already know that we have the ability to make things essentially
translucent, right?
I mean we could make things translucent by just only blending, right?
Half the value, right?
You can see that happening right here, right?
If that makes sense.
So because we have Alpha blending.
That means we have the ability to change how much of our source gets
written into the destination.
Because we were already doing this Alpha blend right here.
We, this was the alpha blend.
That takes the source and the destination and blends them using the
linear.
Again, that linear blend equation that I said would be underpinning,
everything and always is that linear.
Blend equation is blending between our source and our destination.
So it's blending between the guy and the trees, the forest bitmap in
the back.
On there, right?
So all I did is said, well, okay.
We were reading that Alpha out of the guys Alpha Channel and that's
what we were using to determine whether or not, you know, each pixel.
How how much each pixel would be there.
So that that way where the guy isn't we weren't writing any pixel data
and where he is we were and at the edges we were writing a, you know,
proportion of, right.
It's the thing that, you know, if I zoom in here, I don't know if the
zooming work still, yeah.
Can you how much can you zoom in?
Can you, there we go.
You can zoom in a lot.
That's kind of handy.
So you can kind of see right there like all around the edges of them
to write that.
The alpha blending is what's giving us that feathered Edge as well.
Right?
We wouldn't be able to feather the edge with the background without
the alpha blending.
So I just thought quick and I was like, oh, well if I want the shadow
to kind of diminish as he jumps, well, that's the one thing I have to
work with is the alpha blending.
So I said, well, let's go ahead and just pass in a coefficient for the
alpha here that I can pass from 0 to 1.
And that will multiply whatever the incoming Alpha is.
And when it multiplies, whatever the incoming Alpha is, if I set it to
like .5, then everything would be half Blended path is as opaque.
.25 would be a quarter is a pig, right?
As it should be.
And so that lets us very the translucency of things.
Right programmatically.
And again, we like I said, we already wrote all the code for that.
All I did was just passing the coefficient.
That's all I did.
And that was just to go ahead and get the shadow, too.
Do that little dimming effect.
That's it.
Hopefully, that makes sense.
How much has changing the rectangle to a bitmap is set of a rectangle
impacted your player on player Collision calculation.
It doesn't the player Collision clack.
Calculation will always be done on something other than bitmaps,
basically.
So the bitmaps are purely what we draw.
how many zombie DLC is, will there be well, I mean,
I don't know that we want to do zombies DLCs.
Because obviously, the most important thing in gaming is monetizing
the player.
Like, you don't want to think about stuff, like whether the players
having a good time, or whether the game is fun or whether you had an
artistic statement to make that you wanted to make, or whether you
loved it or any of those things which you want to think about is how
to maximize profits.
And so zombie DLCs.
I don't think we're going to be able to squeeze the whales with that,
right?
I think what we really need here.
We need a bigger Harpoon, right?
We need a harpoon, the whales of something bigger.
So I'm thinking, like, zombie DLC.
I'm sorry, zombie.
Microtransactions is what I'm thinking.
So, basically, what we do is we charge 99 cents per zombie.
And since we know zombies come in hordes, if the player wants to have
any fun at all, they'll have to buy like a ton of them.
And then handmade here I will just be like astronomically profitable.
Um, and that's the real important thing obviously.
Shouldn't you be doing this blending in a linear Colour space?
Yes, and that is something we will talk about Gamma.
In fact, you want to see something that I have when we talked about
Gamma before?
And I was lamenting that I couldn't find anything.
Well, guess, what?
My monitor actually came with its tested gamma curve.
You can actually see.
It's Candelas per meter squared here on the graph, right?
And if you can see that, can you see that?
So, yeah, I, when we get there, we actually have the monitor gamma
curve on a piece of paper, which is kind of fun.
But yeah, that's that's up to talk about in the render.
We're not there yet.
We're not at linear versus srgb color spaces or any of that stuff.
So we're not thinking about that yet.
Let's see.
When does the core mechanics of The Game come into play earlier, later
in the day of cycle?
So
On handmade hero.
It is coming later in the dev cycle than it would ordinarily come.
Because this is a very educational project and so I'm focusing on
teaching different parts different times.
Normally I would put the card game mechanics in right away.
They already would have been in right, but that is not really the
primary goal of this game.
The primary goal of this game is not game designed its game
programming.
And so, we will be going through a number of things before we start
talking about core game mechanics because we're not
Iterate on core game mechanics are trying to iterate on game code
which is different.
And so yeah, I'm making concessions to the fact that it's trying to be
more education about programming if that makes sense.
So, basically game mechanics will come in.
After we finish, the renderer probably.
Our rough road map is finish the rough version of everything is what
we're doing right now, which isn't that long, maybe a couple more
weeks after that we will go do Collision detection rendering and audio
output, right sound effects and music and so the game will then be
looking and and sounding properly, but there will be no game to play.
And then
We will switch over to the game mechanics and we'll just go
continuously with game mechanics from then on out because we got a lot
of them.
We got to do World Generation.
We have to do like entity systems and like interactions and ton of
objects and all that sort of stuff.
So yeah.
Well, basically, you know, will spend a few months on engine stuff and
then we'll switch over game mechanics and just I planted that's just
stay on game, mechanics lien the entire time from then on.
Is there an easy way to translate from Circle to ellipse Collision
detection by?
I'm not sure what that means Mankowski.
Will let you do a lips Collision detection.
Just fine.
It's a little bit more work than Circle, but not much.
So, I'm sorry.
I'm not sure.
I totally understand the question, though.
Did you ever learn to make a game engine rather than using engines
like Unity or unreal for people new to game development?
Well, it depends on what you want to do.
You want to be a game programmer?
Yes, I do.
If you want to just be a game designer, then it probably isn't
necessary.
Although I would recommend gaining some familiarity with it.
Meaning like, you know, watching this series or something and just
kind of seeing what goes on and maybe not having to learn everything,
but just understanding sort of the things that are going on underneath
the hood are very good to know, even as someone.
Who's primarily a game design programmer, rather than a game engine
programmer?
But, you know, you certainly wouldn't need to learn how to write a
render yourself, but it would probably be good for you to understand
how a renderer works, right?
And so, what I would say is, it's it's all stuff that everyone should
know, but it it's a it's a matter of what degree, you need to know it,
right?
You know how much of each section do you just have a vague
understanding of how render works or do you know how to write one
yourself?
If you're always going to be focusing on mostly doing game, design
programming, and you're never going to write your own game engine,
then you probably don't really need to be able to make an engine, make
a renderer.
Right?
But it would help you to know how one works and what's involved,
because you're constantly involved with those systems when you're
doing game design, and they constantly imply important.
Structions and opportunities for you in your design and not having any
idea what's going on is constantly a hindrance.
So, yeah, so what I would say is it's all good information for
everybody who's involved in games, but the degree to which you really
need to under internalized, it varies, widely, depending on what you
plan to do.
The rectangle box, which you have Alpha assigned?
Is that the same box you would assign hit points to in case the
character is injured by enemies or obstacles.
I don't know.
So, like some games, like, Legend of Zelda.
I believe is just sprite-based Collision detection.
So it's just whether the Sprite gets hit.
Whereas I think Binding of Isaac is actually sort of positional.
So so it's very 3D like like basically if a shot, you know, past
Kind you like that?
It wouldn't, you know, or I guess I could do it with the properly
included version here.
If a shot past behind you, it wouldn't hit you here.
Whereas in Zelda.
It would I don't know which one of those is better.
This one is more realistic, but it's not necessarily more
understandable for the player because then they have to kind of do
this Fuzzy Math of like, looking at the where the shadow is.
And so, I don't know, like,
for this game.
I really think I'm just going to have to try both of them and see
which one feels better once the game is actually running and were
playing.
Game, I think we'll have to feel it just and see.
How common are practical is pixel by pixel Collision.
Check versus overall shapes going to check, which one is more
interesting to you?
So pixel by pixel is totally doable.
We could do it.
The problem is it doesn't handle swept volumes very well.
So things can tunnel with pixel by pixel clothes and checks in ways
that you don't necessarily want them to.
So that's the impracticality part of it.
So what I would typically say is Go polygonal and use a fairly tight
polygon because that's almost indistinguishable from Pixel by pixel
and can do swept volumes.
That's what I would say.
What are your thoughts on the Allegro Library?
I have never heard of or seen such light said Library.
So I cannot comment.
All right, I think we are done.
This dream has ended if I'm not very much an error.
Let's go ahead and close this all down.
Well, yes, we are a little over time, but we're still, you know, it's
so it all kind of fits together.
It's fluid, what time we end and what time we start.
Thank you everyone for joining me for another episode of
Make sure it has been a pleasure programming with you.
As always, basically.
If you are the sort of person who likes to follow along with the
source code at home.
You can pre-order the game at handmade here a.org and it comes with
the source code.
You can just go ahead and download it, and then you can play around
with it yourself, change the jumping speed.
For example, if you want a faster jump or a slower jumper a higher
jump, even you could do that among other things.
So, if you want to do that, handmade here at or
look, this is the handy, dandy period of button and you'll be able to
download the source every night and of course the test assets as well.
And it'll obviously get you the the game when it's when it's ready.
If you want to support the video series.
We have a patreon.
You can subscribe to that's over here and we have a news and Forum
site, which is pretty sweet.
I highly recommend you check it out.
It's got the schedule for the week posted.
It's got an episode guy that has all the past episodes with like time
markers and good stuff.
It's really much easier to follow on there.
If you're trying to catch up.
We have a coding resources page and the coding resources page has
ports to Linux and Mac already, that other people have done.
So, if you're trying to run on a different system, besides Windows,
that's your that's your go-to place.
They've got it all up there.
And finally, there's a Code discussion forum where you can ask
questions about the game, the game code as it stands, or if you find
problems or trying to get things compiling and you can't or whatever.
That's the place to go.
A lot of helpful people and I answer questions on there, too.
So, thank you very much for joining me.
I hope to see you back here tomorrow night, 8.
P.m.
Pacific Standard time.
Again, we will have a delightful time and we will start looking at
pushing this a little further and getting our walls and stuff and
maybe we'll start trying to trees.
I don't know.
We have a lot of things we could do and they're all cool.
So I hope to see you back here as the game starts to take shape.
I'm pretty excited.
I think for a start we're getting closer to that cusp.
Yeah, do the render.
That's a big one.
So obviously it'll take us a few weeks to do a render.
I'm sure.
But that's one of the last big things before we start, start being an
in-game town for real.
So I'm pretty excited.
Thank you so much for joining me.
I hope to see you tomorrow and have a wonderful Wednesday whether I do
or
Or not.
Thanks, everyone.