Start recording.
Okay.
Hello, everybody.
Welcome to day 4 of handmade hero.
This is sort of day, two of my sickness stream.
So I apologize for my scatterbrain Miss.
Although let's be honest.
I'm kind of scatterbrained normally.
Last night was a bit of a defeat for us because we were just about to
draw stuff to the screen and we didn't quite get to it.
I elected to not push into the Q&A and take time away from that.
I said, go to the Q&A as we normally do but tonight we are definitely
the start drawing stuff, but we are going to start with a very
important correction.
And I am very happy that that Chris Hecker tweeted at me because this
is a this is a good thing.
I'm going to go ahead and launch our editor here and
Hang up our source code that we were working on.
Because after Chris treated at me.
I realized what my confusion was yesterday because I was a little
confused and I think you could tell in the Stream.
I was a little hesitant when I came in here to write win32 update
window.
I said something like, should I use stretched Tibbets or shouldn't I
use stretch Tibbets.
I was kind of hemming and hawing what?
I didn't actually fully explain at that time.
Is the thing that I was actually thinking of using, instead of stretch
debits and what that was was bit blit.
And bit blit is the function that I normally use.
I never actually used stretch to B.
I mean I'm aware of it and I know what it does but I never actually
use it.
I normally use bit blit.
And so the thing that was causing the problem yesterday and this is a
bit of a bummer that I just didn't think of it.
Was that actually, that is why there was the confusion about whether
we needed to create a compatible DC.
I remember s Silvan wrote in very helpfully to point out the fact that
since stretched a b takes a pointer to the B.
Why do we even have to have Windows do this allocations?
For us.
And I was like, gosh, I don't know.
And in my mind I was thinking well, I'm pretty sure you need to do it
for performance reasons.
But why was I thinking that?
Because I don't normally call stretch to bits by just thought that
that was true and blah blah blah.
Well, the reason is actually because this is what I normally use bit
blit is what I normally use.
And if you notice bit plate, does not take a pointer to the B.
It has to go device context to device contact.
So, what I was thinking in my head, as I was thinking about the stuff
you had to do to use bit bullet which involves creating a DC that you
leave around that has the bitmap in it.
It and that you always do the bit bit from that DC to the screen to
the window DC that you're actually drawing to, that's what has to
happen.
So you have to do all this stuff because you can't pass a pointer to
the bit.
But if you call stretch TI B, which I never do, you can actually just
point pass a bit pointer, which means you don't even need a DC or a
bitmap.
So the question is,
Why do I always use bit blit?
Well, the reason and this is why Chris is tweet jog my memory because
he actually is, he's a pro at this stuff.
I mean, he knows this stuff better than anyone probably in the world
because he wrote wind G, which was actually the first way that you
could do this sort of stuff on Windows.
It was under win 3-1.
Rin 351 or when windows for workgroups, whatever it was went 3-1.
You could actually do these Blitz to make games actually run on
Windows way back before they could.
And so he knew all about bleeding on Windows and he kind of he just
knows that cold.
And what he pointed out was stretched.
GI B used to be the slow path.
It was slower than bit blit because bit blit since Windows could do
the allocation of the memory and have the bitmap already selected.
It was a faster path than going through stretch GI B, which is why
I've always anachronistically used bit blit.
But since this is supposed to be for us to learn to write a renderer
and that performance difference, may not even exist anymore.
This was back when things weren't going through a 3D card under the
hood, and all these sorts of things.
There's probably no reason for me to ever use, bit put stretch, but it
is probably gonna be fine for us because eventually, what we'll do
when we optimize things will want to create an opengl context.
And actually write directly to a texture with overlap downloads, and
these sorts of things.
So when we get to like the sort of okay, we wrote everything
ourselves.
And now we're going to start doing Hardware things or whatever.
We're going to launch.
Think different anyway, so really we can just use stress GI B and I do
not have to worry about the thing.
I was worried about which s Silvan or also was pointing out.
We shouldn't need to do and he's right.
I don't think we do need to do that.
So with that correction in place.
We can actually simplify things quite a bit.
What that means is we don't actually need to store any of the stuff
anymore.
The H bitmap in the HDC, that Windows was going to create for us.
We don't actually need those anymore.
Right?
We don't need the bitmap handle.
We don't need the device context.
So, all we actually need to do, is have this bitmap info header filled
out that has the width and the height, correct, right?
And then, we can allocate the memory by ourselves.
We can just allocate our own memory.
However, we want to and as long.
It is the right size and works.
Okay, windows will go ahead and do the right thing.
So that makes it a lot easier for us.
And that's what we're going to do is we're going to keep our bitmap
memory here.
But we're going to do instead is we're going to go ahead and say note.
Thank you to Chris pecker of spy party, Fame for clarifying, the deal
with stretch gibbets and bit blit know.
More DC for us.
So this is awesome.
So basically what we'll be able to do here is we're basically just say
we need some memory Windows.
We need some memory for our bitmap.
And the first question is, how much memory do we need?
Well, we have asked for 32 bits per pixel, 8 Bits, red, 8, Bits green.
It's B Lu and I am going to leave a padding bit in there.
Sorry, padding bytes in there.
So eight bits of pad and the reason that I'm going to do that is
because in General on the x86 architecture.
Oftentimes
Is there is a penalty for doing what's called unaligned accessing?
So basically,
If you are trying to operate on a value, that's say 8-bit 16-bit
32-bit 64-bit, this sort of thing.
If you're operating on, like 32-bit values, 32-bit.
Use should be aligned on 32-bit boundaries, meaning they should be on
like the zeroth B, the fourth B, the eighth B and so on, they should
not start.
Unlike the second bite.
They should always if they're four bytes long.
They should be at multiples of 4 in memory.
And that's just the way the CPU is set up to deal with them.
And so, what I want to do is I want to make sure that whenever we
touch a pixel just for now, especially to simplify things and to keep,
make sure we're not incurring any penalties unnecessarily here just to
simplify things.
I want to make sure that
That we're always touching a pixel on an exact 8, 4 byte boundary
there.
So if we were to ask for the bits that we actually need for r g and B,
that would be 8, B 8, B 8, Bits, or 24, bits, and 24 bits is three B,
which is in no way.
Aligned with for you basically have to go out 3 times 4 or 12 to get
back to the right boundary, right?
So that's not going to do it.
So I'm asking for eight extra bits that I need, and those extra bits
are just going to be padding.
They don't actually
Anything and they were actually be used, but we're just going to do
that.
So that we know that our pixels are always aligned on 4 byte boundary.
So if that is the case, then I know I have a pixel size of 4, bytes,
right?
That is how big that's going to be.
So I need a enough of these for B pixels to have the width times the
height worth of pixels, right?
Because this is sort of elementary math if you have a rectangle and
you want the area of that rectangle,
You multiply the width times the height, right?
And so what we want to know, is, how many pixels do we have?
Well, we have width times height pixels, right?
But each pixel is for.
So, if I was to make this a little more explicit, I might say, bytes
per pixel, equals 4, and say that we have width times height times B
per pixel, right?
So, this is the size of our bitmap memory, right?
And if we want to allocate it, we say the bitmap memory equals.
Something that allocates bitmap memory size.
Earth now, in Windows, how can we allocate something?
Well, I like to use Virtual a lock for a couple reasons we could also
use.
He palak either way.
We are probably going to stick with virtual Alec mostly so I might as
well go and introduce it here.
Basically what this does is it goes ahead and allocates a certain
number of memory pages.
And basically what happens is when you allocate memory directly from
the system.
It is generally allocated in pages and pages are a certain size in
Windows.
They are often.
Six bites, sometimes they are 64k.
It depends whether they're large.
Pages, are small pages, that sort of an operating system thing that
we'll talk about a little bit later potentially, but basically there's
two ways we could allocate memory.
We could allocate it with Heap, a lock, like I mentioned and he palak
is basically asking the system to sort of sub allocate out of the
pages for you.
So you can pass any size you want here and you will get back a point
of that.
Whereas virtual Alec is a little more raw.
A virtual Alec must give you back pages.
So you can't for example, ask for something that is
Less than 4096 bytes and expect it to give it back back to you.
What it actually will do is it will give you back the whole 4096 spice
and the rest will just be wasted.
I want to get you used to allocating memory from this because we are
going to be doing almost all of our own.
We're going to be doing our memory allocation almost entirely
ourselves in this project.
So I just want to get started with this virtual elk right away.
So you're used to calling it and it does not frighten you.
So I'm going to call virtual Alec, and I'm going to look at the things
here.
We are going to Virtual luck, our bitmap.
And we are going to take a look at.
It says it wants to starting address of the region.
Now.
This would be good if we actually wanted to place our because,
remember we have a virtual memory space for those of you who watch the
intro stream, know, every process in Windows, has a virtual memory
space its own addressing scheme for memory and that gets, you know,
moved out to physical memory depending on the how the operating system
chooses to map it.
But we are always looking at basically a nice big flat 64-bit address
space.
That appears to all be our own even though Windows behind the scenes,
the sort of swapping that in and out of physical memory.
Are you putting it to disc, doing whatever it needs to do to make it
appear that way to us.
But as far as we're concerned, we have a nice big flat address space
and as long as we don't use too much memory, we can kind of assume
that we'll all be actually put in physical memory.
So we won't have to incur any kind of weird performance penalty.
So
all we have to do here is say we don't actually care where the memory
is because we don't we don't have any real restriction on where it is.
We have to say the size and this is the size, the region in B.
Basically, if the address parameter is null, the value is rounded up
to the, why is this?
Why is this scrolling?
There we go.
Round up to the next page boundary.
So since we did pass in the lp address, as no, it means that even if
we pass something that is less than an, even multiple of the page size
of the system, it will just
It up for us, which is exactly what we want it to do.
So that's totally fine.
Then excuse me.
We have the allocation type and that is going to tell a Windows what?
We actually want it to do to this memory range.
And that the interesting thing about this is there's two actual things
it can do.
There's commit and reserved.
And what's interesting about that is basically, since it is a virtual
memory space, what that means is you start off with 64 bits of address
space, but basically all of it is essentially vacant.
It's not actually memory yet.
And you basically have to say, okay.
I'm announcing that these pages.
Are actually now going to be used by me so windows can do.
Okay.
He's actually going to use some of this memory face.
I have to start tracking it and working with it.
Putting it in physical memory, doing whatever I need to do with it.
And it has a little page table based on that.
It keeps it says, which Pages for each process are actually being
used.
Now, what that means is when we go through virtual, Alec.
There's two ways we can ask.
Remember, you can ask it to actually start tracking the memory and
we're actually gonna start using that memory, which is, that's what
commit actually is but Reserve is a separate thing we can do.
If we just want to make sure
Sure, that memory is available for us and kind of tell you.
Okay, we're going to be using this memory, but you don't actually need
to start tracking it yet because we don't actually need it yet.
So why don't you actually just wait till I actually need it.
To actually start using it if that makes any sense.
So, basically we're going to use mem commit because we actually want
the memory right now.
So I'm going to go ahead and do mem commit.
And, and then we could talk a little bit more about that later.
Now.
I don't think we actually need any of these other ones.
We don't need to ask for a large.
Paid support for any particular reason.
We don't need that.
It's windy extensions or anything like this.
These are all things you do not have to worry about and I don't think
we'll have to worry about either.
And then protection basically says what we want our access privileges
to be.
Now we do
Not need to execute code out of this memory.
So we do not need the execute bit to be set.
That is basically a bit that says, whether or not of the CPU can run
code that is residing in that memory.
This is basically for security purposes.
I believe well could be for forking purposes to don't get hung up on
that.
Don't really matter point.
Being we want full read and write access.
We just don't need execute.
So we are going to ask for read and write access to this memory which
means that our process can both look at the contents of that memory
and store things to that memory, which we
Going to be using both up.
So we are going to ask virtual out to give that back and in theory, it
will return to us.
As you can see, from the documentation here.
It will return to us a void pointer member LP long portrait avoid that
is a void star.
It is going to return us avoid start, which is what we wanted, which
is the memory that we needed.
Now, if we should have to resize, our dip section and bitmap memory
was already allocated.
We want to just make sure that quickly before we do this, we go ahead
and free that memory because that is the only time that we actually
want to do that.
This memory is supposed to always be available.
Available to us so we only want to free it.
If we think we're going to allocate it again right away.
So basically what we're going to do here is going to use the opposite,
which is virtual free, what you can do down here in the see also is
they'll usually put things that are related.
So if you want to know how to free something, usually go down here,
sometimes I'll tell you in here as well.
Sometimes they won't hear it is virtual free can can can free the
memory.
So what we're going to do here is we are going to go ahead and do mem
release to actually get rid of the memory entirely, but I'm going to
talk about mem D, commit, just briefly, just to let you know how
Works because we may use that in the future.
Probably not here, but we will probably use it for other things on
occasion.
Alright, so we are going to free the bitmap memory.
We need to pass it, the address to free.
We need to pass it, the size that it was and that's the bitmap memory
size.
We allocated before.
So, it looks like we're going to have to store that since I assume we
cannot pass a no.
Oh, no, we can't actually pass a note.
That's good.
So we'll just free.
The, it'll actually just free.
The it remembers.
How basically, how we allocated and it will free it.
So that's perfect.
So we don't even have
To store the actual size, it will do that for us.
And then we just have to say that we want to release the memory back
to the operating system and it can reclaim those pages, use them for
something else.
Give them to another process, do whatever.
It's going to do, doesn't have to worry about, keeping them back in
physical memory, on the hard drive, any more now.
When we do this virtual free, I said memory, Lisa would get rid of
Pages.
There's another thing we could have done, we could have done.
Ma'am, D commit.
What is MD commit.
Now?
You notice we did commit over here, which basically said I want you to
actually make these actual Pages, release, mix them, D, commit like
stop being committed.
And it actually frees them as well.
But instead we could D commit them but leave the pages reserved.
So if for some reason, we said, look, you don't have to pay attention
to these anymore.
But we're gonna ask Ali, probably want them back later.
So don't what bother tracking them, but don't get rid of this memory
range, that could be something that we might want to do.
Probably not.
I don't really know the thing that we're more likely to do.
I'll mention really quickly.
Because for some reason, I'm spazzing out tonight.
I'm just kind of in one of those zones where I'm just talking at you
and talking at you and talking at you.
And I see no reason to stop virtual protect is a way of basically
taking something that we did with virtual Alec and changing the
protection of that page.
So, one thing we could do instead of freeing, the memory is, we could
choose to leak this memory and debug mode.
Meaning, we will not forget.
It'll just stay around and instead of freeing it.
We will actually virtual protect it.
We will virtual protect it with no actual access.
So we
We'll go in there and we will change the memory protection context,
contents, memory protection, constants of the page to be page.
No access, no execution.
No writing.
No reading.
So that way we can't use the page anymore.
Even though it is still allocated.
Now, why would we want to do that?
The reason we want to do that is to make sure nobody has a stale
pointer to the page because if someone kept a pointer to the page
somewhere and they were going to try to write to it, that would be a
use after free bug which are very hard to track down sometimes and so
this is one way that you can catch those.
Those bugs, you can go ahead and protect the memory, make it so that
you can't touch it.
And then later when that buggy code, tries to go and touch it instead
of perhaps exceeding touching it because it's still memory, that's
allocated by the operating system that got used for something else
later.
It will now fault, right on the line of code that try to do it, great
way to catch bugs like that.
We will probably do something like that in the future to try to keep
ourselves from from making mistakes like that.
Right now don't see much of a need to do that.
I think we'll probably be okay.
There's other tricks you can do with Mary protect.
We'll get into those later.
But that's all I want to do right now.
I'm going to step through this and make sure that we are doing the
right thing.
So I'm going to go ahead and type Dev em to bring up our project and I
will step into the win32 resize dib section.
So here we go.
Let's make sure the first time we try to resize our dip section.
We expect our bitmap memory to be 0, which is, which means we will not
attempt to free it.
That is exactly what
We wanted, we will fill out that header.
We know, that's right.
We check that yesterday, four bytes per pixel, which is how many we
expected.
We will then ask for a certain amount of memory here, bitmap memory
size.
That is this, which looks about right.
14:24 by 729.
Should be about that.
And then when we multiply, by the size of the picture pits, which for.
Yep.
We all good.
There looks good.
And now we will allocate our memory.
And did we get it back?
We did get it back.
All is good.
We are ready to rock.
So now all we have to do.
Do is pass that memory to stretch the.
I b to put it to the display and that will will solve our problem for
us.
Now.
What we're going to do here is I think we're actually going to start.
Remember we specially do what's called a dirty rectangle?
Update here.
We passed win 30 up to update window the region.
Of our window that Windows asked us to repaint, but we could introduce
some bugs here and make a stuff harder for us to debug by actually
using this dirty rectangle first time out.
So instead of doing that, I'm going to have stress gibus, just fill
the whole window.
First.
I'm going to have it drawn to the whole window.
We make sure everything is working properly and then we'll worry about
doing a sub-region that Windows wants us to do.
So, instead of doing it this way.
I'm going to go ahead and look up that that call right there.
Just a figure like this will simplify our to Buggy Bill.
Always start, start simple and then get more.
Complicated.
So basically pass, the device comes for painting to, we passed the
destination.
And so the destination.
This is it's no longer going to be this at all.
This is not what it's going to be.
So the destination is going to be 0, 0, always.
And then we are always going to do our full width and height, the full
width and height of the bit map instead of the repaint region.
We are going to pass that and then we will pass.
I guess we should name this.
So, this is, this is actually the bitmap with, and the bitmap height.
And then we will do use the window width and the window height to make
sure that we blit our whole bitmap to the whole window.
Now, in order to do that.
I need to actually know what size that is.
So temporarily.
I'm going to go ahead here and I am going to pass the actual window
size.
Might have not actually be temporarily.
We may just want to always know this.
I think we do.
So I am going to ask here for a window wrecked to be passed in that
will tell us basically how big the the window is.
And then I will save
The the to the width and height of our backing buffer here again,
these are Global variables.
Not because D should actually be Global Bears there because we're just
kind of working on getting the code working.
Right now.
These will not be Global variables eventually.
I do not remember like this is not a good thing to leave these Global
variables and we won't.
So, don't be thinking that you should put these things out there
permanently.
You should only put things as Global variables.
When you're first getting things working and see where everything has
to be and then immediately after you kind of know exactly how things
should go.
You want to clean that up and make sure that only things that actually
should be Global are Global.
And that is what
We'll do a little bit later.
So there we go.
We have our Global variables and when we come through here and we
resize things, we are going to go ahead and set the bitmap with equal
to the width and the bitmap height equal to the height and then we
will go ahead and set using those from then on.
So these will basically just be set there and then we will just use
those from then on.
Okay, there we go.
So that will be how will do that.
We.
Then just need to get the window with.
And the window width, of course, is going to be to thee.
The window wreck see there.
I passed a pointer to it because I didn't want to pass the whole
rectangle on the stack.
Didn't think that was necessary.
The window rex that will be the right - the left to get us the width
of it and we will do the window.
Height will be window wrecked.
Bottom - window wrecked top.
There we go.
And that should basically give us everything that we need to know.
We have our bitmap memory pointer.
But the one thing that I do want to know, is what
Are so stretched a b.
I'm giving it a pointer.
I don't know how it's going to read that pointer.
How is it going to access that memory?
Is it going to go?
Is it going to subtract?
So how should I say this?
So basically it's going to look at that memory.
It's going to interpret that memory as a bunch of pixels basically,
right.
And let's go ahead and do a drawing here so I can so I can kind of get
across to you.
This is a bit of a visual point.
I think it might help to have a diagram.
So I'm going to go ahead and draw one using gimp with my magical
drawing skills.
I think we all agree that.
At my drawing skills are kind of unparalleled.
So let's see.
Oh my god.
Wow!
Drawing with OBS is difficult.
Oh my Lord.
Okay, maybe this won't work.
This is why I got to get a video capture card.
Ladies and gentlemen, that's almost impossible.
That's almost impossible to do.
All right.
So that's a non-starter.
There's no way we're going to draw that diagram.
I will have to get a video capture card before I can actually draw
diagrams.
Oh, that's awful.
Well, I'm glad we tried because when it becomes more important, I'm
going to need to be able to draw stuff.
So we'll skip that for now.
Basically, I'll
A skew diagram for you.
All.
We're trying to do here is say well, we've got a 2d thing, right?
Which is a this bitmap, but we have a 1D representation of it because
memory is just a series of bytes, as a giant series of bytes.
So what we need to do is come up with a convention for storing,
something 2D inside, something 3D.
So basically the X, you know, a row of pixels.
It's pretty easy to understand.
Because if I just give you a pointer to a bite, you can assume that
you just start reading the B, and they are a row of pixels, but when
you get to the end of the row,
row, what's what happens?
Right?
Do you just store the next row down on the image?
And they put that there.
Do you start the next row up on the image?
Do you back up?
You know, do do some Porter math, you know, what's going to happen
there?
You need to know what happens at the end of the row.
Where the next rows bits are because basically, you've got a series of
1D slices in memory.
You've got to reassemble into something to D.
Normally, when I do things, I just tack them on.
So it's just one row, the next row, the next row, the next row going,
usually top down.
But we need to know what Windows is going to do.
That thing is called a pitch or a stride.
Typically the value is basically, when you move a pointer, when you're
going from row to row, typically something called a, I think usually
called a pitch, the value that we would add to a pointer to the first
row to move it to the next row is called the pitch.
Usually.
And a stride is the, the number you would add to a pointer to the end
of a row to move it to the next row, I believe that's true.
Really how those two terms are used but doesn't matter point.
Being there is some notion of what you do and we need to know which
one of those stretch bullet uses.
Sorry, stretch the I bet you use it.
So let's take a look at their remarks and see the origin of a
bottom-up dip is the lower left corner.
So we're talking about something there.
It starts down in the lower left corner.
The origin of a top-down dib is the upper left corner.
Now, I don't actually know which one those are, but I suspect that it
has to do with whether we set the bi height.
Parameter to negative or positive.
So I'm going to go ahead and see if I'm right about that guests.
Let's take a look bi height.
Let's see, the height of the bitmap it pixels.
If B is positive.
The bitmap is a bottom-up dib.
Wow, little but the brain circuitry is still sort of working, just
barely folks.
Just barely the bitmap is a bottom-up tube and it's origin is in the
lower left corner.
If you hide it - the bitmap is top-down dip and its Origins the upper
left corner.
So, you know what I prefer top-down.
I don't know if it's a performance penalty will see but we're
To go ahead and say that we're going to make this negative so that we
can ask the rose to go sequentially from the top down because I think
that's a little clearer.
That's usually the way people expect them to go.
And so let's do that for now.
But also lines better with old school.
Programming old-school, frame buffer start at the top and went down.
And maybe you could argue that this isn't as good for thinking about
new things in 3D where opengl want some going the other way and you
know, we'll take a look at all that stuff later.
Don't worry too much about it.
Now, but Point thing I'm gonna go ahead and do that now.
Just to make things a little bit clearer for people out of the gate,
especially since Windows coordinate system is all top down, right?
X is low, X is lower left to X starts on the left.
At zero goes positive towards the right side of
The screen and Y is zero at the top and gets bigger when it goes to
the bottom.
That's a top-down displace.
It's kind of weird to flip them around.
Alright, so back to stretch GI B.
We now know, we have a top-down window.
So let's see what else is says here.
If the parameters differ, they have different signs, going to mirror
image.
We don't want to do that.
We're gonna use the same sign screw top down image for divots - so
that's what we did.
The function allows Spa blah, but it doesn't really say what the
stride is.
It does not seem to say what
Stride is here.
Does the bitmap info say the stride?
I don't think it does.
So I guess we are just going to have to experiment ladies and
gentlemen and see what the striped actually is.
So we're going to pass that bitmap memory.
We are going to go ahead and see what windows does.
Now, we have not put anything in it yet.
So we are.
Oh, this is something I should note actually.
One of the things that's problematic is basically when you do a
compile inside emacs, or, from the command line.
Sometimes msv.
See doesn't give you the full path to the file name and I would like
it to give a full path to the file name.
So basically when you hit CL, right if I hit question mark slash
question mark CL slash question mark you can see that it gives me all
the compiler options and one of these options is basically to to get
full paths.
And so I am going to go ahead and see if I can't get that to happen.
I think I've got less installed on this machine, do I?
I do.
So I'm going to go ahead and search for full.
Let's see, useful past name / FC.
Okay.
There we go.
So FC is what we want in our build bat, and let's see if I can go
ahead and load that up.
So, let's get a minus FC in there.
See if that works.
And it does look at that full path name.
So what's a nice thing about that is now I can just
Turn on that and emacs and we'll jump right to the line or I can hit
alt M.
Sorry alt n, which is my go-to next error, which makes it a little
easier to find these bugs.
So we change the definition of win32 update window.
We certainly did.
And so we have to go back and take a look here and call it the correct
way.
It needs to take the device context.
It doesn't stick window rack, which we have not passed it.
So I'm going to go ahead and take the same code here.
This that just got the client rectangle and I'm going to pass that for
now.
You may want to clean that up a little bit, but that should be
sufficient.
That is the rectangle that we wanted the same way.
On that we were using to resize our bitmap.
So off we go.
Let's run the code.
We have not put anything in there.
So basically what we're looking here is to make sure we don't crash
because we don't know what stress GI B is going to do.
We want to make sure we're passing it.
Something at least semi valid, we seem to be.
So that is a good start.
Now, let's go ahead and actually draw those pixels.
This is what I wanted to do tonight and we are already there.
I don't know if you can contain your excitement.
You probably can't up.
Didn't your ettore for a syntax again said, I wouldn't do it on the
screen and I did, we are going to go row by row through this bitmap,
ladies and gentlemen, so we are
To start with a for Loop that goes over the bitmap height.
And we are going to look at each individual row.
And for each individual row.
We are going to go ahead and go over each pixel in that row, and for
each one of those did it again.
Her old habits are hard to break using the stream to try and break
that habit.
I know it's not useful anymore.
What can I say old dog?
New tricks.
Sometimes takes.
Well.
Alright, so we have our bitmap memory.
It is a big old chunk of memory reserved by windows for us
specifically for the purpose of writing pixels into it.
But we have a problem.
It is a void pointer and a void pointer.
As you know is a pointer to something that c does not understand.
So in order to start writing to it.
We have to change it into a pointer.
It does understand.
Now, what I want to do is I want actual explicit control over the
pointer and how it's going to move.
So I want to tell see first of all, basically that it is
Going to treat it as a pointer to just bytes in memory.
So I'm going to cast this to a care star.
Now.
I usually use like to use unsigned care Star right and these get sort
of a knowing the type.
So one thing that we're going to do and I'm going to start doing it
now because why not is I like to type def, some convenient.
Typedefs hear something that's a little easier to type and that means
what what I actually want it to me because I really don't care about
unsigned care.
What I care is that this is an unsigned 8-bit integer.
So I like to use you ate for that and basically what
you used to do in the old days is what I'm typing in right now, right.
You used to do bitmap memory.
There you go.
You should do that.
But recently, in C, and I forget exactly where these are defined think
it's in standard type study.
Is that a thing?
Let's find out.
No, it is not.
Is it a standard?
Lib?
I don't know where it is.
Who knows where it is?
Basically.
There are new types that actually have the thing that you actually
want, but I don't actually know where they are normally defined
anymore.
That is not correct, but I know you've
got these.
So I'm gonna go ahead and search for where they are.
They only just introduce them recently.
Well, recently in my, you know, I'm old so recently, it's probably
like five years, right?
But but I always had to do these myself back in the day standard ant.
That's what it is, but they've recently added these and that's kind of
cool.
Basically, there are now types which are actually set up to be the
correct size for your platform because platforms used to differ in
terms of what sizes things were.
So if you said in unsigned, that could have been 16 bits, right?
And that's no good.
If you actually needed the thing to be a precise size.
So now that you can actually do that.
I'd like to actually do that.
These are the
Types that I used to use and coincidentally, see who's the type, which
is almost the same but I like to Define it to be my own way just
because I am Persnickety that way you could just as well, use you n8t.
Anyway, that's something to think about.
We are going to basically cast this to an unsigned 8-bit integer, and
only reason I'm doing that is because I'm going to be doing pointer
arithmetic.
And as we know from the interest-free many time, I add or subtract
something for a pointer to move it around in memory.
See will silently multiply that Movement by the size of the thing
being pointed to.
So if I were to change this to a 16-bit, it would move.
I to every time and I don't want to do that.
I want to make sure I can do the arithmetic explicitly.
Now.
That's just something I tend to do in pixel operations.
The reason for that is because sometimes you'll see later on, they
tend to have strides that aren't necessarily aligned, on Pixel
boundaries for various reasons, stuff like that.
It's just a better way to write these Loops.
You'll have to take my word on it for now.
That's just kind of a better way to do it.
But once we get in here we can cast it to what we're actually looking
at and that is a 32-bit integer for going pixel.
By pixel.
So basically, what I will do is it's cast my row pointer here to that.
And then, at the end of each of these iterations, I will increment the
row pointer by that pitch which is the amount we're going to do to
move it.
And of course, the pitch is the difference between the the row, a row
and the next row that is basically just going to be the width times
the size of the, of the pixel, right?
That is how big each individual row is a row, is with pixels wide.
And each one of them is by 4 pixels long.
So that's how big it is.
So,
From row to row, that is the size.
That is the the pitch.
And then each row.
I'm going to access here.
Now again, this is maybe a strange way to write a loop.
It's just a good way that I find a right pixel Loops because
oftentimes, this pitch value, you know, you might say looking at this
it's totally valid and you're totally right to look at this and go.
Hey, wait a second, this pixel.
I bet you're just going to do this in their right.
You're going to go ahead and increment this pixel every time right
through the loop to write to the different pixels on the road.
By the time you get to the end.
It will already be right where this thing is going.
Owing to be.
Why are you doing?
That's inefficient.
You're correct.
The reason I'm doing it is because typically when we do these things,
the pitch is actually not going to line up with this.
And so it's usually easier to write them in this way for various
reasons, most of the time, but the other way we could do it is to just
take pixel and add the stride here.
Six of one half-dozen of the other.
Some, they have performance concerns.
Those are all things.
We look at much later.
So don't worry about it too much right now.
That's just a good way to write those Loops, typically before you're
going to actually go in and start doing any kind of Performance
Tuning.
Now, I went ahead and added you in 32 because we had to find that yet.
You know what we could go bananas.
Here, folks and just finish off our typeset entirely and get all the
different types that we might use.
Well, not all of them.
But you know, most of them just get them in there.
We will be moving these to a platform independent, header, at some
point because that's pretty good.
So, there we go.
We've kind of defined our various sizes, good to have on hand.
All right, inside here.
I'm going to use the dereference operator to write to this pixel.
Basically, that says, I am trying to access a memory pointed to, by
this pointer, which should be pointing to each individual pixel.
And I need something to write in here.
Now.
What am I going to write in here?
Well.
Each of these pixels is essentially packed in memory.
This is the structure of the pixel pixel in memory, right?
We basically have location 0 and that's going to be 8 Bits.
So we basically have in hexadecimal that is two of those things.
This is the first one.
This is the second one.
This is the third one.
This is the fourth one.
Now.
The question is, we know, we have to write r g and B, which one do we
write it 2?
And this is the pixel and memory.
So this is basically the location 0 from the, from the thing.
This is 1 by 10.
This is 2, bytes in, this is three bites in from the pointer.
So,
Basically pixel plus zero, right pixel?
Plus 1 pixel plus 2.
Well, they're not really.
It's the only if that was it's only if this was a un8 right?
Like I said, is that so this is this is pixel + 0 b, + + 1, B and so
on from that pixel pointer.
We are going in memories, right?
So this is this is what that is.
Now the question is which one of those is red?
Which one of those is green, which one of those is blue.
Now, if you were going in memory order, you would probably think.
Well, let's put to the 8 Bits of red there.
Let's put the 8 Bits of green there.
Let's put the 8 Bits of be there, and let's leave this as the
Ting B that you said you're going to have but what happens if we do
that, well, you know what?
I'm just going to do that and I'm going to let you see what happens.
And in fact, you know what I could do just you know, why confuse the
matter.
Let's just start doing it this way, so I can show you full explicitly.
This is will actually be that way.
So we'll just actually do each individual.
One will basically do the first one, so this will be pixel and will
then we'll increment each time will do.
Will do this will actually do it fully explicitly, right?
So we write each byte in memory.
Why not seems like a good idea just to show basically what's
happening.
So let's say we were to write the red first.
So, you know structured art is always a good idea to get things to
bug.
We want to see if we're writing to this thing properly.
So we're going to just write to the red Channel and we'll leave the
green and blue channels black for now so that we can isolate the red
Channel and make sure that we know how to write to it.
Alright, so we're going to write 0 into what we think is green.
What we think is blue.
And then what we think is the pad will also leave zero and then we'll
just write the maximum value for an unsigned character which is 255
into the red Channel or what we think is the red.
No, and then we'll compile that and see how it goes.
We will now go ahead and run this program.
And first of all, we have to see do we get anything on the screen at
all?
And you will see we do get something on the screen, but ladies and
gentlemen, it is blue.
Why is it blue?
does anyone know why it's blue welder experts out there who know why
it's blue, but I'm talking about people who took like the intro to
seek or
I'm not talking about the grizzled veterans.
You know why?
It's blue.
You get it yet, It's Tricky.
But we did cover it in the intro to see course.
We did.
Cover it.
The reason is because this is a little endian architecture.
Ladies and gentlemen, which means, as I specified in the intro stream
when B, our load out of memory load it out of memory to form a bigger
value.
So, if I wanted to load for B and produce a Unit, 32 out of them, the
processor will actually put the first byte in the lowest part.
Of those 32 bits.
The second byte will go in the next part and then the next part, and
the highest will be the fourth B.
/.
So basically what happens is, if these are the pixels in memory, if
you were to load them into a un 32, you would load them are first into
the low.
I'm going to use the hexadecimal notation.
We learned.
Here are our heroes are 32-bit value in a register, 32 bits.
Now, it's one big value, right?
The first two are and our go down here.
Here the next to GG.
Go in here.
The next to BB go in here, the next 2, XX, go right there.
And look at that.
It is backwards now BGR.
Well, the person people who wrote Windows didn't like that very much.
They were on a little endian architecture and when they loaded a
32-bit value and thought of it as a pixel, they wanted it to look like
it was in the right order when they were looking at it in the register
of the CPU.
So what they did is they Define the memory order to be backwards.
So it would look like
That which means that it is swapped in the memory of the machine.
So all windows bitmaps actually have the blue b first, the green B.
Next, the red bite after that and then the pad at the end that is
basically how that works.
And well there's really no other explanation for it than that.
So what that means is, if we actually want our red shirt to show up as
red, we need to move it to the third pixel.
Sorry the third bite and then we run it.
And now we've got a red bitmap blazing.
Gentleman, isn't that beautiful?
And I argue that it is in fact, beautiful, a very beautiful thing.
Now what we might want to do is start to make this a little bit
prettier as we go.
Let's see if we can do something a little bit cooler.
How about we go ahead and assign just the x-coordinate, cast it down.
So truncated, basically chopped off if you will just take the lower
bits of that value and we'll go ahead and assign green into the why
Channel and then I don't know what will
Will sign to Blue.
I guess we'll just leave blue black or sorry.
Even I'm messed up.
Now.
This is actually blue, not red.
So this is the red channel that will be will be empty.
So this way, we can, at least get a little amusing gradient going on.
There you go, as you can see much more attractive than what we were
drawing before if still not a game, at least something kind of fun.
Looks like it is all working correctly.
And now you can see what I did there pretty straightforward.
I just said, whatever our Exposition is.
I'm going to take the low bits of that, and I'm going to shove it
directly in the blue Channel.
Going to take the low bits of the, why the road that we're on shove
that in.
And so you basically get exactly that.
Look, you get 256 pixels of increasing blue and then it dropped back
to zero to hundred more 206, more of increasing blue drops, back down
to 0, because that is just the 8 Bits of the y-value going up, and up,
and up.
I hope that is pretty clear to people what's going on.
There, won't belabor that point.
A point, but we can go over it in the Q&A.
If it is somehow mysterious to you.
Now, ladies and gentlemen, we have done.
Something that is is rather remarkable.
If you will, we have gotten ourselves back to 1980.
That is what we have done.
I could not be happier.
But what just happened right before your very eyes, as we have turned
this modern awesome.
Beastly computer running a hugely complicated and difficult to wield
operating system into something where we just basically have a bitmap
that we can draw two and get back to the joy of coding because there
is no stopping us.
Now, we can draw anything.
We wanted that but there is something we could still do.
We have 20 minutes left in the Stream and 20 minutes is just enough to
start to do some damage on something else we might want to do.
So I say we go ahead.
And do it.
I am feeling good tonight.
Ladies and Gentlemen, even though I am sick, that is usually means
since Pride cometh before the fall that something terrible will happen
to me in the next 20 minutes.
But what can you do?
I can't stop that.
It was going to happen was going to happen.
Anyway, might as well enjoy the last 20 minutes that you get, if
you're about to get hit by a bus or whatever it is.
That's going to happen to you.
I say we move the rendering code for our bitmap.
Up here into a separate function that basically says, what's this
function to be called?
I don't know what it's going to be called.
Maybe we will call it render weird gradient because honestly, that is
what it is doing and the render reared gradient call.
We'll go ahead and take some kind of an integer that will be the X
offset and the Y offset.
And all I'm going to do there is when we stuff our values in, we will
add those offsets so that we can animate our gradient around the
Name makes sense.
I think it makes sense seems like a good idea to me.
And like I said, we got 20 minutes left.
So how wrong can we really go?
Now?
If we want to reproduce the probe, the behavior of our own program, we
can certainly just do that by calling a render weird gradient right
there and we can pass 00 to verify that we did not mess anything up.
Of course.
It needs to know how big those are, but we save those.
So that's fine because the width and the height are actually Global
variables currently, so we can go ahead and use those right there.
Let's go ahead and call in with the bitmap with then.
We will call in height, the bitmap height and then we are good to go.
O b, 4 pixel.
That is actually a constant.
We will hoist that out for now.
All of these things are things.
We're going to have to wrap up.
I'd kind of had I have a plan for this, by the way.
I'm not going willy-nilly.
I do have a plan for how I want to do this, but we will talk about it
in the Q&A if I don't forget, but I probably will forget so maybe
someone remind me.
Hey Casey, you said you're going to do something and you didn't do it.
Let's verify that we reproduced our program when we abstracted that
function out and we did, we pull it out.
All right, good.
Give ourselves a pat on the back.
Now.
Let's make sure that we can use our offset prep.
I'm going to go ahead and offset it, halfway on, just the x axis X
ass.
Yeah, X.
Axis talking.
Ladies and gentlemen, it is difficult.
You've done it all your life, but it is harder than you think when you
are programming live on Twitch.
Okay, there we go.
It is offset properly just like we want it to be.
So now we have every reason to believe that this function will work.
But we need to do something if we want to actually make that animate,
which is what I want to do.
We need to go down here and not, wait for Windows.
We do not want to wait around while Windows stuffs and our message
queue because you remember, I told you about get message a and one of
the problems with get message a is that it will block.
So once
We run out of messages.
We will block right there.
Windows will shut us down and it will wait for another message to come
to our cue.
It'll go do other things.
Whatever.
The other things need to be switched.
To another process, use that CPU time, effectively.
We don't want to do that.
We want to use that CPU time, all for ourselves.
So really what we want to do here is we want to change this to a
message Loop.
That processes messages when there are messages.
But if there aren't messages, we keep running, right?
That's what I want to do.
So we're going to go ahead and do that.
At why not?
We're going to go ahead and switch our message Loop by the seat of our
pants.
Ladies and gentlemen, to a peak message Loop, instead of a get message
Loop.
Here is our Peak message Loop.
And basically, what a peak message Loop does is the exact same thing
as get message, but when there is no message, it will allow us to just
keep on running instead of blocking.
So we are going to go ahead and call that you can see that it takes
substantially the same things.
It takes the address of a message.
It takes the window handle and the filters just like we filled out
before Dawn.
Any of those and then it has one additional flag that we need to know
what to do.
Basically, it's just something that says whether it should pull things
out of the queue or just look at them in the queue and tell you what
they were.
Well, we actually want to process our cue.
So we're going to pull them right on out of there, and that is p.m.
Or remove messages are removed from the queue.
After processing, by Peak message.
Go ahead and copy that out of there.
Here we go.
There we go.
Not bad Peak message.
Now, that's going to return a Bool and we need to know what that Bool
is.
I assume the Boule is whether or not there was a message, but
Let's go ahead and verify that it's been a long time.
Since I've actually written one of these Loops.
I always have the same Loop.
I've been using for years to be honest with you, cut and paste or use.
That's the way to do it.
Okay, so pick message if no message is available return.
Not okay.
Nonzero.
If a message is available, if no message available return 0, so all we
need to do is say if we got a peak message.
Then we are going to have to process it.
Now.
One of the things that we need to probably do is we don't want to
repaint all the time because we had lots of messages in our queue.
We want to process them.
Also, really, probably what we want to do is we want to say, while
people?
I said returns true translate and dispatch all the message just to
flush out our Cube because we're kind of obligated to process that Q.
We can't not process that Q or app.
Will start being badly behaved.
Maybe we want a gate limit that sometime just in case.
There's a flood of messages but I don't know really.
There's nothing you can do.
You got to process your Q.
That's pretty much just something you got to do.
So, we're probably just going to have to be stuck doing that.
So let's do it.
So this will flush out our cue as long as there are messages the Q.
It will process them.
But now we will no longer get our PR are quick message.
Oh, but that's okay.
We don't have to worry about that because
We are now using the running thing, but we should probably double
check our message to make sure that we're not getting a quick message
from Windows from some other for some other reasons.
So I'm going to go ahead and double-check that MSG structure.
Let's see here.
Dot message.
So dot message.
I'm going to say that if Dot message is equal to W M.
Quit.
I am going to make sure that running equals false so that we just
quit, anytime we get that W and quit message just to make sure that
we're handling this case that we use to handle down here.
Okay.
So basically, that will still do the exact same thing as before we
should have absolutely no difference now.
Oops, we need deleted the definition of the thing that pulls the
message.
That's no good.
Now, as we go in theory, everything is now exactly the same as it was
before.
But we are, we are now able to retain our bitmap as often as we want.
So, what we could do is we could say, x offset equals 0 and down here,
we can go ahead and say render weird gradient.
Right in our Loop.
So after we're done processing our message queue, we are started
turning to get behind the at which window there ladies and gentleman.
So I'm going to go ahead and switch back to this window here.
So so we are not obscured by the by the little picture of me talking
because who doesn't want to see me talking.
I am sure that it's everyone's favorite thing to do is to watch my
head.
Alright, here we go.
We are going to call render rid gradient with the X offset and the Y
offset.
And we are just not even going to bother initializing it in here.
Not at all, not going to do that because we don't actually care will
probably want to do in here.
I'll put it to do, probably want to clear this to Black, probably
clear, this to black, but we don't need to do that right now.
We're about that right now because we'll be thinking about those sorts
of things later.
And what we will do is every time through the loop.
We will take X offset and we will add 1 to it.
Just go ahead and commit that using the shorthand for plus 1.
Let's see.
What happens now.
Oops, that doesn't look good.
What's going on here?
Well, that was that was not what we wanted at.
All.
What happened?
Why did my render weird?
Oh, duh.
Well, there's one thing we.
Oh man.
I was little too excited there.
Forgot something obvious.
We need to still put it to the screen.
We'd actually update the window, right?
Because we were only updating the window inside.
WM paint.
Write this thing that actually does the strategy a bit.
I never called it.
So, of course, we're not going to see the results.
Sure.
We rendered to our bitmap but our bitmaps not on the screen.
We need to actually blit it to the screen.
So let's go ahead.
Head and have that blind to the screen.
Now, we're going to need the vice consul.
Next, we're going to need that window, rectangle.
And we are going to need the dimensions of the blit, which will
basically just be 00 and our window wrecked, our window width and
height.
So I'll go ahead and program those in there.
Sorry.
For the for the little hiccup there.
Ladies and gentlemen, I don't think that was a big one.
That was just a well.
I got a little excited and was hoping I could do a little less work
than what I actually had to do, but you know, no harm, no foul.
So window wreck at this point.
This is
Thing.
Now just I'm just calling this out.
I'm not doing it right now because we're just kind of messing with
things at this moment.
But you've seen me write this code a couple times with the.
In fact, I'm just going to actually cut and paste it from here.
You see me writing this code a couple times.
So right about now if this were actual code that I wasn't just kind of
fudging with and was going to rewrite in a second anyway, as we as we
start to clean things up, which is what we'll do tomorrow.
I would be pulling this out into a function and keeping the stuff.
I would actually have a function basically that does this because we
have done it enough times.
Now that it's clear, it's something we want to do and I don't want to
be cutting pasting it all over the
So I would definitely be doing that right about now, we're not going
to because I know that we're going to kind of fun, and we're going to
do something a little bit different.
But basically, you know, just just so, you're aware right about now is
when, that's why you sense will be tingling.
And so, if this were code, that we were going to keep it would it
would be a it would be pulled out.
So we're going to go ahead and get the device context of the window,
which again is something we need to draw and we are going to go ahead
and release that.
There's a kind of a getting release thing that has to happen here.
And by the way, for people who are into resource,
Acquisition is initialization, which remember I said, I don't like
very much.
They're a couple places where I would be okay with it.
I wouldn't fight you for it.
If you want to do something like this, and have a little thing that's
like a DC getter releaser.
Pair to make sure you don't forget the release.
If it's something that helps you out and you want to use Rai for that
you could pull this off into a class with a Constructor and do you
structure?
I would not get mad at you for that or disparage you at all.
It's totally fine.
Something, you kind of have to do some time.
So like I said, every programming thing has a place where you may use
it.
It's really the Dogma that gets you try not to get into the Dogma
because every
You practice probably has a you somewhere.
It's just usually not something you want to do all the time.
You need to know when to use things in a lot of times when people get
into something and they start to assign names to things and do those
art stuff.
They get carried away and carried away is almost always bad.
So for the raii people out there, throw you a bone.
It is true.
I would think that would be a perfectly fine thing for you to do.
Now.
We need to get the window handle.
So we have the window handle here.
I'm going to change this to window honestly, because I don't know why
I called it window handled again with we're not going to have anything
else that's called window.
So we're just going to go ahead and do that.
We have a client wrecked here.
So yes, I should call.
In fact.
I'm just going to replace that everywhere.
It really should have been client wrecked everywhere.
So we're going to change window wreck to client wreck.
We're going to go ahead and Loops change that.
So window wrecked, should be client wrecked.
There we go, just to be a little more concise and then we we actually
use it correctly there.
Get rid of that.
We actually have one.
It's not a
Are so we got to change those two dots.
The most useless thing you ever do in C and C++ and C compiler, should
just know John already fixed this.
In this language, I believe.
And then we need to pass a pointer to that.
So, cleaned up our compile errors and we should be good to go.
Now.
We are actually rendering the gradient and bleeding the gradient.
I'm hoping to see something on the screen now, but I don't know if we
actually will.
So let's take a look and see.
Is that animating it all?
Ladies and gentlemen, it does not appear to be.
Why are we sad?
Why are you sad Panda?
What's going on here?
I must have done something wrong.
Wrong, let's find out if we not bleeding properly or we not doing.
What are we not doing?
Do you do that stretch?
But I think is supposed to do it.
I don't know if I have to force it to repaint or not.
I'll double-check that in a second, but I'm pretty sure we are
changing up.
Awesome.
It is just a, you know, you get excited and you make a bunch of
mistakes.
So these are getting reset to zero every time what a surprise, gotta
put those outside the loop.
Casey, if you want them to keep increasing think that should be pretty
obvious.
There we go.
There is are animating.
So we are pretty much in shaped.
How to animate whatever we want.
Now what I would normally do at this point and in this is definitely
something that that is is high on the list of priorities for us to do
is to figure out how fast that stretch Blitz that stretch call is now
also, we should test this to make sure we can make it huge and we can,
we can also make a tiny.
There you go.
And now one of the things that I want to note, is basically goes a lot
faster when it's tiny than when it's large.
And that's because basically the cost of filling those pixels and
stuff like that, but the thing that I actually
want to test is how fast we can actually update the screen using the
sort of old-school way of updating that we're going to use so that we
can write the render ourselves.
But the problem is I can't really do that.
This speed is not representative of what it would actually be first of
all, because our gradient code is super crappy right now.
So that's going to slow things down a little but also just the
stretch, puts the stretch GI B call.
It is not a fair measure because open open broadcasting system or
whatever.
The OBS thing I'm using a stream right now because I have it set to
desktop capture.
Which is what I need to use in order to kind of go through here and
and show you all the stuff that I'm doing.
It.
Makes the machine have like a zero framerate.
Like basically anything I run.
It's just it's super slow.
So I can't actually figure out.
This might be running really fast right now.
For all I know and just is getting slowed down by OBS.
So basically what I have to do sometime very soon and I just haven't
quite had time to do the research to figure out what one to order is.
I need to order a video capture card so we can stop OBS from doing
that so we can actually profile the app on this machine.
And get somewhat reliable results because we're going to need to do
that for a lot of other reasons.
So that's homeless, the things to do.
But that is why we can't even tell how performant this technique is
even going to be.
In fact, you can see when I move the mouse, it slows it down, which
would never really happen.
If this was actually happening without OBS, but moving, the mouse
causes it to do some kind of thing in OBS and, and so on.
So that's a bit of a problem.
We are in good shape today.
People.
We have an animating window on the screen ladies and gentlemen, that
was less than three hours of programming including explanations
because Monday, we don't forget was
Setting up our Dev environment.
So three hours of fully explanatory programming, that's like, 20
minutes.
Probably of actual programming to get an animated window on the screen
using only our own code on win32, where we can now, write everything
we want.
I don't know.
People say it takes a lot of work.
Get something running on Windows.
I don't think that was a lot of work.
It's a lot of knowledge.
Yes, but once you have the knowledge, that's pretty quickly.
We are inside the five-minute warning.
So I'm going to do one more thing just to show you how this would work
writing, 32 bits is faster than running eight bits.
Ladies and gentlemen.
Although the compiler could probably do this for us.
Let's go ahead and change this to a 32-bit right instead of an 8-bit.
Right?
So we're going to change our pixel to be a 32-bit pointer, and we are
just going to go ahead and write to it once like that.
In a nice little shorthand.
We're going to write to it.
And then remember, this is the post increment operator, which means it
increments pixel after we have already used it dereference which gives
us the pixel that it actually was a little cleverness.
There.
It is true.
But then I'm going to go ahead and I am going to actually build this
out of B.
So we have three values that we
Actually wanted to use here.
There is our five minute warning.
We have the X Plus X offset.
We had the Y, plus y offset, and I guess we didn't actually have
another channel, right?
We didn't actually have another channel.
So we need to basically shift these values up and, or them together to
produce a single value that we can write out.
So what that's going to be is remember the farthest up.
The highest order is our pad, then we have 24, bits up.
Basically, those eight bits from 20.
Sorry, 16 bits up from 16 from bits.
16-bit 24.
That is our red Channel and we were leaving the red blank if I
remember correctly.
So we don't have to worry about that.
The green channel is bits 8 through 16.
So we're going to take that green Channel, which I believe was the Y
and I believe X was the blue, right?
We're going to take that green Channel and we are going to shift that
up by 8.
Then we are going to or it with the blue Channel which doesn't need to
be shifted up at all.
It just sits where it was and then we are going to call that are
32-bit value that whoops.
Well, in a way that Cassie still there.
That out of there.
Did not want that.
There we go.
We are going to call that done and see if we wrote out a 32-bit value.
Properly y offset is NOT capitalized.
Their poop.
Well, that was didn't mean to kill my buffer.
Well, you know, sometimes you accidentally hit okay, and that kills
the buffer.
So let's see if that reproduces it properly.
There it is.
So we've just changed to using a 32-bit, right?
And if you didn't catch what I did there, we still got four minutes
left.
So I'm going to go ahead and explain that in a little more detail.
Basically, what we want to do is we have
a thing, you know, that we wanted to write, we wanted to write out for
our pixel, which is 32 bits right in memory.
Here is the memory here is the register.
Okay, in memory, right?
We have blue comes first, then green.
Then red then pad.
So when I wrote that out when I did pixel, I wrote the blue pixel
first.
The they rotate bits of blue.
I rotate bits of G.
I wrote nothing to wrote 0, to 8, Bits of 0 to the RNA pits of 02 that
right.
So you saw me right blue.
In red, in the old one, but now in the register these things come in
and they get loaded and they get loaded flipped around, right?
Because of the little endian again, so, they're loaded like that.
So basically what that means is, if I want to find where I'm going to
put my blue, it just goes right in the bottom.
It's the bottom eight bits and then, I'm ordering that together again.
Ordering just Composites, two things together, if either of them are
set, then it sets it.
So I'm going to or those bits of blue with the bits of green but I
need to move them up to where they would be and they are 8 Bits up
right there after the blue.
So I shifted them up by 8 and then I ordered them together and output
in my pixel.
So, there we go.
That is that, and we are good to go.
That is the end of what I wanted to accomplish tonight.
I didn't even know if we get to animation, ladies gentlemen, but we
did and pretty much after we get input in here.
That means you can move the character around the screen.
If you really want to, we'll be seeing how to do all of that next
week.
Tomorrow.
What I want to do on the stream actually, is I want to go through and
really look at all this code.
I'm going to pull some things out.
Clean it up a little bit and discuss.
Each individual thing does show it to you in the debar groans more
detail just to kind of solidify things.
So probably, that's what we'll do most.
The time on Fridays is go through and do that solidifying work talk
about things that that were confusing people talk about other stuff
like that.
But that is a great stopping point for now.
So we've got two minutes until the Q&A starts.
I think I will drink the last of my almond milk and then we will go to
the questions.
So good, isn't it?
You know, I like almonds too, but I don't really like him that much.
So it's interesting that I love almond milk so much.
It's kind of confusing.
Alright, let's go ahead and take questions because I think that's all
I wanted accomplish today.
Certainly not gonna start something new and I can't think of anything
that we really wanted to fix.
Let me go ahead.
And I guess, one thing I can do is verify that we did not leak any
handles with Windows, or do anything, untoward in that sense.
Let me see here.
I will go ahead and bring up the task manager.
Or try to anyway, there it is.
Mr.
Task manager.
Please.
Tell me if my handmade Hero has caused problems.
Where is when 3D or handmade?
There it is.
So there is win32, handmade.
Ladies and gentlemen, it is using about 10 megabytes of memory, which
is pretty much all the stuff that Windows allocated.
I guess, since we didn't do any of that and do, do, do, do do, and
that is staying nice and stable.
It's just freeing.
And reallocating that virtual.
Look, which is totally fine.
So that is good.
No problems there.
And we will have more sophisticated ways of keeping ourselves from
doing anything untoward.
Oh man.
Look at OBS.
What is going on?
Oh man.
Whoa!
OBS is not cool.
I really gotta get that capturecard.
Ladies and gentlemen, I got to order that because this is not good.
Oh my gosh, what is happening?
Everything is going, everything is going haywire on my machine.
I don't know if you can see this right now.
I don't know what you're actually seeing on the screen, but
It is a bit of a disaster.
Ladies and gentlemen, all of my windows have gone away.
Oh my Lord, OBS, poor OBS.
Trying to capture all the windows.
It is the pop-up.
I believe that is it is ruining things.
Maybe we will have to end the stream and restart it.
I don't know if it's going to be able to to come back from this.
Yes, the Q&A begins.
Now, thank you for showing us that unfortunately, you have destroyed
the entire desktop in the process.
Us poor OBS.
I feel for you.
I really do.
I know Windows wasn't set up for this.
Come on.
Can we?
Can we just kill?
Can we kill our app?
Maybe kill our app, please get things back to normal.
Do something.
Somebody save us.
Yeah, this is not really OBS as fault.
Ladies and gentlemen, this is just what happens.
I think, when you are trying to stream a bunch of stuff on Windows 7,
which I don't think has a good way for OBS to really capture the
desktop.
Come on, stop our app.
Stop our app.
Stop the app, please.
Please.
There we go.
That work.
No, it didn't work.
Oh.
Well, I'll just go to the questions and hopefully we can answer some
questions that don't actually require this because apparently we are
not going to get our desktop back anytime soon.
Let's take a look at the actual questions and see if we can get
anywhere.
Well, this thing is trying to figure out how to get out of its own
way.
Oh, there it is.
We're back.
Hey, well, alright.
Well, that's just push the capture card up to a very, very high
priority for me.
Ladies and gentlemen, one of the things you should do, if you are an
expert on streaming and I mean a real expert and you know, some
things, please send me an email using the handmade hero email address.
If you could go to handmade hero Dot,
Whenever you would like to do, so, go to handmade here.com and
emailing a question.
And instead of a question.
Tell me what capture card I should get because that is the only thing
holding me up right now.
Thanks to the generosity of people who have pre-ordered.
The stream.
There is money in the count for handmade hero that I can use to buy a
card and I will do so.
So, all right.
Let's go.
Q&A session.
Is there a reason you prefer using zero instead of null?
Yes.
I find that.
I like less defines.
The less defines the better.
So, since 0 always is what null is on.
Every platform that I ever program on in modern times.
I just go ahead and use zero.
There used to be times when that was not true.
I think potentially or other things like this or I don't know.
In fact, Sean.
Barrett is still on.
I don't know, I think he is right now running a procedural Opera
generator, but he is the kind of person who likes know and knows those
sorts of things.
So he may have a good reason why you might occasionally want to use.
No, but I do not
I would love to learn how to script but I just don't get it.
Can, maybe you help?
No.
I don't know anything about scripting.
I don't really write any Scripts.
Clips to the rectangle.
Anyway, so I don't know what that means standard in t.
Yes, standard in s Silvan.
That is what we use to just took me a while to find it.
See, maybe I'm reading too far back here.
How come you don't like pound to find but typedef all of the student?
Oh, I like, I like pound to find.
I'm sorry.
I didn't mean to.
I didn't mean to give you the impression.
I don't like pound to find what I meant is I just like to not Define
things if they already exist, but the reason that I do, the reason
that I do the standard type thing.
Oh, my alt-tab doesn't even work anymore.
That's pretty awesome.
All right.
Let me see if I can.
There we go.
Okay.
Wow.
All right, ladies and gentlemen, I really need that capture card.
This can't happen again.
All right.
The reason that I did this is basically that in the old days, these
types didn't exist.
This is brand-new.
So I got in the habit of always using my own types because previously,
you actually needed to Define them all because you might be on
platforms where you needed to switch this.
So you might do something like, you know, if on 16-bit architecture,
you know, and then there was
In fact, this was this sort of thing would happen a lot, right?
You see something like this.
Make sense.
You have to do stuff like this.
So you always wanted to use this because you actually had to change
which type you're using.
So these are not Superfluous.
These are actually there because you have to use them and that's why I
still do it.
You could I be, you know, like I said, if you're starting your coding
practices, now, I might just say stick with the underscore T types
because they are what you want and there's no sense in redefining
them.
But the other thing that's true is I would argue that this isn't
really all that much of a savings anyway, because you still have to
include standard, ioh.
I wish they were just built in the language, which maybe they are in
some part of the spec that I do.
Senior Tori.
What would happen if you call.
Malachi said a virtual Alec, you would basically go through a crap ton
of C runtime Library code and then you would call keep Alec, which
eventually would call virtual lock.
So basically, you are just going through a lot of unnecessary code to
get the memory.
Everyone has to basically allocate memory as Pages down at the lower
level.
So really we're just going to allocate a bunch of pages with virtual
Alec and we're going to do all of our memory manager out of that
instead of calling the C runtime Library.
To avoid bothering, using whatever it is that they're doing, which is
just unnecessary stuff, basically.
What's their speed Malik new and he palak?
Not much.
I believe he palak is keep out because basically the system's
allocator that allocates from the Heap and Malik and new are the C
runtime, libraries way of allocating from that same Heap.
And so I believe all that.
Malkin new do is they basically introduced another level of
indirection, which I think is usually designed to optimize small
allocations and like large numbers of allocations.
Whereas he palak,
Since it's a system call, can't do a really fast return to you.
Potentially.
I don't really know.
I don't use those calls.
So I'm not really in a position to speak about what they actually do.
But if you want to know, you can probably step into mallik and just
look at the code.
Like we were doing the other day where you just call malloc and hit
f11 when you get to that line.
You can watch what it does.
I went really fast today.
Do you think you could go as slow as you did previously days in the
future?
Probably not will probably have to go relatively fast.
But what we'll do on Fridays is what kind of do our slow day on
Friday, where we go through all the code that we wrote over the week
and kind of dive into it more detail.
So what I would say is come back tomorrow and take a look there and
see if that clears it up for you, but no we can't go too slowly
because otherwise we would really never get anything done.
So we kind of have to go and say, well, alright you can go back and
watch the stream again.
Look at individual things.
You can ask
Questions and then drill down and it, but you're going to kind of have
to meet me halfway there.
If we ever want to actually make any progress.
I have to go fast.
Say everything that's happening as I go, but you may not understand it
all.
And then you'll have to kind of go back to the stream.
Think about it, go back and correlate with like the intro to see
course or things.
We've said earlier, when you don't understand something, you'll have
to ask me questions.
Or ask the community questions.
We're looking right now, try and set up a forum for that.
But that'll kind of be the way that it has to happen, because
otherwise, we'll never going to get a game done.
Are we going to use Val grind later on possibly?
But we may just use our own homegrown stuff.
Since we may not need something as heavy weight as valgrind.
Let's see.
Is the product going to take two years?
Are you planning on streaming for two years?
Yeah, we probably will be streaming for like two years.
What about null pointer?
I've never used null pointer.
So I don't have any thing to say about that.
Let's see.
Sorry, I'm still sick.
I'm sorry about the coughing.
Really need a cough drop, but there in the other room.
Can you explain what why we are using the user through you to live in
the GTI, 32 live in the build-up.
That I already explained that please go.
Look at the other stream.
Basically, what happened was?
We need those because those are the import libraries that tell Windows
where we, where to get things, like, stretch TI B, which is in GDI,
32.
Lib, so that is, that is basically the way that we get our, we import
our function calls to Windows.
I talked about that in the Stream will talk about that later.
When we when we probably, when we get rid of windows on each,
With there, be a significant performance increase if you allocate the
memory for the bitmap on the stack instead of the Heap well
performance increase.
So first of all, there's no performance increase just because you
allocate memory in one place rather than another
Only reason there would be a performance increases if that memory was
already hot for some reason, like it was already in the cache.
But memory is memory.
So only matters, whether that memory was touched recently whether or
not it's for some reason going to be more efficient.
So, so I don't think the question really makes a whole lot of sense in
that in that way.
But the more important thing is, we can't allocated on the stack
because anything that we allocate on the stack will go away after we
return from that function, right?
So when we come in to like win, 30 32 resized image section.
The stack is
At a certain Watermark, right?
All of the local variables, like bitmap memory size, right?
Get pushed onto that stack and our parameters, width and height there
on the stack.
But then as soon as we exit that's those get the stack goes back above
it, and that stuff is used for other things.
So if we were to allocate this on the stack, as soon as we returned it
would go away and then we don't have a bitmap anymore.
Right?
It's in memory that will get reused as we kind of move move through
there.
So you cannot allocate stuff on the stack that needs to be permanent.
The whole point of allocation is to allocate things that work across
Multiple functions like that across different Stacks, across different
levels of the stack.
Did I restart the stream for Q&A?
No, we are no longer doing that.
We're just doing one from now on.
Let's see.
I am scanning for questions.
Do you know what the page?
Right copy men.
Protect flag does.
Yes, I do.
Well.
That is one of those fun questions to answer on the Q&A.
So basically in I'm going to give you what I believe is the
hypothetical reason for it and you will have to go try to check this
perhaps on the interwebs or maybe as Silvan can.
Tell us somebody else for Microsoft.
Could maybe tell us but basically the reason that you have right copy
as a thing, which is basically what right copy is is it means we're
going to take a piece of memory.
And we're going to make that memory be essentially the same as another
piece of memory.
So we're going to put some data in it and we're going to have that
memory sort of mirror.
Whatever is in there.
But we want to do is when you touch the page when you actually go to
write something to that page.
We want to instead of actually writing to the memory underneath it.
We want to silently, move it to a new place in memory, a new, a new
page, and write to that instead.
And I believe that is the flag that your ass.
Going about.
Let me double-check to make sure.
I don't give you a completely bogus explanation here.
But, you know, I'm pretty sure I'm thinking of the right thing when
you say that.
So, let's go ahead and take a look here.
I need this to be a little.
Oops.
Didn't mean to grab my emacs window.
Get back over there.
I need this to be a little bit wider.
So it's no scrollbar.
Okay.
There we go.
So, I'm going to go over there and look at the memory protection
constants, and you said, right?
Be enables exit read-only and copy on write access to a map value and
attempt to write to a committed copy-on-write page results in a
private copy of the page being made for the process yet.
So so basically, the reason that this is in there and again, this is
just me hypothesizing, but I'm just going to tell you why I think it's
in there.
And someone from Microsoft and confirm this, it's basically in Unix.
There is a thing called fork.
And what Fork does is it basically says, I have a running executable.
I want to make a second copy of that running executable, right, but I
want the second copy to
Be able to have it's completely to basically they I want to be able to
then diverge.
So any of the things that this guy does to the processes memory after
the fork and anything that this guy does happen separately.
So it's sort of like just cloning the process entirely.
And as far as they are each concerned, they now are completely
separate copies.
So, if this guy changes memory, it's not seen by this guy.
And if this guy changed memory, it's not seen by this guy.
They're completely separate but cloned, right?
It's just like a cloning machine in order to do this efficiently and
that was a very important thing on.
It's for a while.
It's not so important anymore.
I don't think.
But basically that was the main way that you got multi-processing in
Unix.
The way that that's implemented is basically processor started
speeding this up by having their virtual memory units, go.
Okay, when I clone a process, all this map, all the exact same
physical memory into the virtual memory spaces of each process.
So there really isn't a second copy of the memory.
It's basically just one copy and then the virtual memory unit has a
flag that basically says whenever somebody writes to this, right?
I'm going to raise an exception.
It's basically
The the it's basically marking, the pages, read only, but what will
the operating system will do, is when that exception gets raised, when
the right triggers, it'll go.
Ok.
You actually tried to write to this cloned copy of the memory, which
we don't want to have happen because you each need your own copy
right?
Then I will basically then clone in the page table.
Make a new entry for you and then actually physically copy the bits
over to it.
So that now you actually do have your own copy so that your rights
won't be seen by the other process.
So I believe that the reason that this
In Windows.
Is because when they went to implement Implement posix compliance, and
they probably had Implement Fork, which meant they probably had to
implement this.
That's my guess.
You should verify it.
The download link from Sundial keeps bundling all the zip files
together.
That is what it's supposed to do.
Your base supposed to guess the basically get all the days together,
so that you can pick which one you want.
You wanted to say something about size in bytes, reminder.
You know what?
I probably did size in bytes reminder.
But you know what?
My mind since I had Focus so much on explanations.
My mind is just a blank as to what I said during the stream.
It's really hard to actually program.
At the same time.
I'm going to ask with you.
It's pretty difficult.
Size in bytes.
What was I even talking about?
When I said that?
Does anyone remember?
Because I would love to answer that question, but I do not remember.
Deflated.
I'm sorry.
I do not remember if someone can jog my memory.
That would be great.
Let's see.
Let's see, doo-doo-doo-doo.
Mive God, I'm having trouble finding questions here that actually
pertain to the code that we wrote.
A lot of these are questions about other stuff, which I don't want to
do on the end of streams.
Usually, because we got to concentrate on the actual code.
So if you could, if you could limit questions on these streams, well,
maybe we'll do some long stream sometimes when we do other ones pitch
and stride, so I said size and B and talked about pitch in stride.
Okay.
Well, let's see if I can jog.
I remember it all here pitch and stride.
So, basically in here.
Yeah, I don't know.
I'm sorry.
I cannot remember was going to say, maybe I'll be Rush this dream
later.
Basically.
What I was talking about here is is pretty basic stuff.
Basically, you know, we have a block of memory.
Let's go to her again, and to say the things about it.
In case, one of them was the thing.
I was going to say, we want to render to a block of memory, allocated
a block of memory and basically that memory looks kind of like this,
right?
It looks like
In memory, we have a pointer and that point pointer is bitmap memory
and it is pointing to right the pixels.
And they are basically the blue, the G blue, green, red X ax, blue
green, red x, x, blue, green, red, x, x, that is the memory for a row,
right?
One row of the image.
And so, we basically have width of these, right?
We have width of these going this way, right?
Starting from the from from exactly where the pointer
Is all the way to the pointer plus width times the number of bytes per
pixel, which is for, right?
So, you know, we're basically going from bitmap memory zero right to
to an offset of width x b per pixel.
All the way at the end which is, which is the end of it off, which is
like right at the end.
It's a pointer to like the first thing of the next row.
So at the end of every row, if we want to move to the next row,
Row.
We would actually be right there already because of the way that we've
packed these in memory, but if the pitch was something else so that
basically there, if it let's say there was padding, at the end of the
row like unused stuff at the end of the row for some alignment reason
which often times there can be in graphics.
Basically, what we do is we take this pointer and we add the pitch to
it to get the next row, right?
So this right here is rho 0, right?
0, 0.
And then Row 1 is going to be the next set of these, right?
And each time advancing this pointer is is like, you know bitmap
memory plus the pitch right to get to the next one.
Right?
Don't know if that makes any sense.
So we do bitmap memory, plus pitch plus pitch pitch, pitch moves us to
the next row.
So that's exactly what we did here.
Right?
We just said, here's the bitmap memory.
We're going to start right at the beginning of it.
And then each time through, we're going to add pitch to it, to move to
the next row.
Then this basically fills in the row of pixels.
So we take a copy of that pointer a pointer to the beginning of the
row.
We go through each pixel.
The road and me, write it now.
If we wanted to, you can kind of see what this does, right?
It does this if we wanted to, we actually could just Boop.
We actually could just use because pixel is basically getting an
advanced by 32 bits.
Every time it's getting Advanced through these things, right 4.
Bytes, at a time goes through there.
And so if we wanted to, we could actually not bother keeping a
separate pointer.
Because at the end pixel is actually pointing at the beginning of the,
of the row because the roads are tightly packed together.
So after it goes through all the pictures of one row, it's pointing at
the first pixel of the next row.
So we could just do, you know, basically say, okay, just use the
pointer that you were on.
That's that's the next pointer, right?
And that should just
Right?
So we could just do this entirely with one.
Does that make sense?
Hopefully that makes some sense, but I chose to write it in a way that
was a little more explicit.
Just so you could kind of think about that concept of pitch a little
bit because it usually comes in relatively often and I want you to be
aware of it.
Let's see.
You mentioned, oh, XXX BB grr.
Because of little endian.
Why was the blue Channel set in this case and not the padding?
So, the answer is just because of what the windows devs decided to do.
So again, the way this is in memory order, right?
Or rather.
I should say the way that it would be in memory order.
If you just started typing, it probably is you store the red.
This is memory order.
You store the read first, then you store the green, then you store the
blue, then you store the pad that's probably how you would do it.
Right?
Because red green blue pad.
It's logical because we usually think of
Read first green, second blue.
Third, when this gets loaded in right, load it in, on the little
endian machine, you get the exact opposite.
The red comes in first.
The green comes in, then the blue comes in, then that comes in right.
That is what would happen.
You get the gr like that.
So, the windows devs decided that they didn't like that.
They wanted to see.
They decided they wanted right?
To have it.
Look like this.
Now, you'll notice what they wanted.
Was just a swap.
The are in the are in the be they apparently didn't care that the pad
was still at the top.
That was okay.
They just wanted r g and
To be in the same order.
That's all they were trying to do there.
Right?
So the pad never got swapped in their brain.
So when they actually made windows and decided what the memory order
was, they just swapped the are and the G and left the pad where it
was, that is why.
So little endian was the impetus for them to change because they
wanted to read it this way instead of this way, but they didn't
actually care where the pad was.
They just left the pad where it was.
Could the padding B be used as at the alpha channel here?
Yes, it absolutely could be if we were using what was called what is
called a layered window, which tells the compositor that we want an
alpha Channel.
We could actually use this as an alpha Channel.
Yes, since we don't want our game to have the backdrop the background
show through, we did not do that.
But that is something you could do.
Yes.
And in that case, it looks like it looks like this.
Right.
So the alpha Channel goes in those patent bit.
Why are we having a wait symbol on the window?
The answer is because we have not set our cursor yet.
So if you are wondering why that is happening, that is because we have
not set a cursor.
And so what we actually want to do is we basically want to do a way
you would do that.
I believe is this way.
And now, we don't have a cursor in the window at all, which is what
we're going to want for the game.
Right?
And so, the reason that I haven't gotten that yet.
It seems there's a little bit of other.
You don't just want to do that.
That's not the only thing you want to do.
So I'm leaving that to a little bit later.
Could we explain the offset to X and Y?
Absolutely.
So basically all I want to do is get something animated.
So we're still writing the exact same pixels, but we're basically just
changing.
In fact, I should maybe rename these.
In fact, let's go ahead and rename these a little bit.
What this really is is blue offset and green offset.
We're just artificially offsetting the colors that we write.
So it appears to scroll, right?
We're just, that's all we're doing.
We're just adding an increment that's constantly incrementing
overtime, right?
That's all we're doing.
So yeah, those aren't really incrementing the X and the Y.
We're still writing the actual places in X and Y.
We're just using those to offset the color.
So it appears to slide now right now.
We're not passing.
Y offset at all.
We're just passing 04 it all the time, right?
Because y offset never gets incremented, but we could write and we
could, we could maybe do something.
We're actually, we could, we could offset it, may be twice as fast.
And then, as you can see, now we would get to
two ways of panning.
You're talking about wrapping your Global's.
I made a note in theriot.
I did internal versus global variable explain.
Oh, well, you know what?
Maybe I'll call I'll do this now make in case.
This was the thing.
I was referring to, I'll go ahead and do this now.
So, okay.
So the global variables, some people were a little confused by these.
So let me just use the last 5 minutes of our Q&A here to talk about
this potentially.
So Global variables, the reason that I call this a global variable is
because for us really is going to be Global and you're going to see
why in a second here, but assuming that I didn't do these pound
defines up here, internal local per system.
Global variable.
Right?
What you would have seen here was you would have seen like static in,
you know, Fuqua something static into blah, equal something.
And those would have been how we would do ours or or maybe they didn't
get initialized to the just be 0 or whatever.
This is what I would have been writing.
Their wouldn't been Global variables be static.
Right?
And basically what static does is static does two things.
The first is, it says that this name cannot be used outside of this
translation unit, which usually means file in our case.
It won't, which is why I say things going to be different from us,
which we'll see later on in the Stream.
I don't want to get into it now, but for translation unit, so usually
it means like the file.
But technically translation unit means like the file and all files
included by this file.
Like the whole thing.
NG.
So basically when we have includes the stuff like that, it's all one,
big translation unit.
So it's not just the file.
It's the file and all the things included in that file.
Static means that the name cannot be used outside of the of the
translation unit.
And it means it is going to be initialized to 0 means both of those
things.
We could.
Instead have declared a global variable like that.
And what that means is that the name can be used outside.
In fact, anyone can use it by just saying extern infu and
Hey, there's a food somewhere, you know, in their file somewhere, some
other files.
So this is included in file.
I say extern Foo and then I can just, you know, mess with food and
it'll work.
And it'll go find this food that we declared in here.
This Global variable Foo in here and it will modify it.
Right.
You can't do that.
With static other files can't reach in and touch your static
variables, right?
Other translation units.
So that's that's what static does, right?
And then the other thing that's
static does is if you put it in front of a function, which is why I
declared internal if I do.
Static void sum function.
Basically, it doesn't change anything about the function.
It just applies that naming part again.
It says nobody outside.
This file can use the name some function to call this function.
Now, it doesn't actually mean that other people outside.
This translation unit.
Can't call the function.
They can still call the function.
They just can't call it by name.
So if we wanted to
In some other code, like, let's say in renderware, gradient, which is
in the same translation unit.
I could take some function as a pointer and I could pass it to some
function outside.
This translation unit.
I could pass the address to it like that and then that could call into
it.
So it can still be called by anyone.
It just can't be referred to by name in other translation units.
That's the other thing that static does.
They're now what we're going to do, as you'll see later in the Stream
is we are only ever going to have one or maybe two translation units
total.
So for us static means completely Global variable.
So that is why I defined it to be called Global variable.
Some people got nervous about that.
Who knows?
C plus c and C++.
There were like, you kind of explain that wrong.
I'm like, well, yeah, I agree.
I probably should have explained it the standard way.
So, people know which now I hopefully have done.
But for us it's actually completely Global variable.
It's not even restricted to the translation unit because there's only
one translation unit.
So all of our code will be able to touch this variable this variable.
So it really is truly Global.
Hopefully that cleared some things up.
Select does not give you zero initialization.
You get that by virtue of it being a global.
Is that actually true?
I don't know if that is actually true.
Are we sure about that?
If you're sure about that then that's cool.
I would like to get confirmation about that because I don't actually
know our extern variables initialized to 0.
Let's find out, stack Overflow is a little bit untrustworthy.
I was kind of hoping that I can maybe get something a little bit.
A little bit better than that.
Hoping maybe someone who reference the spec.
Well, let's see if anyone references the spec.
Let's see.
This is useless as always.
Oh, maybe that guy reference.
The spec.
Did he
Well in C++ here, it says that.
Well, I don't know.
I don't know.
Basically, I would like someone.
I'm not really, I don't really care about that.
I never Define anything extern for the most part.
So I'm not sure I'm not going to trust track overflow on that.
I would like someone to check the spec.
But if you absolutely are I would like someone to actually check this
back and be absolutely sure that is true.
Before we say that on the stream because for some reason I remember
that not always being true, so, I don't know.
Do I consider overflowing numbers?
A good coding practice?
If you know if you meant to do it, I guess it's what I would say
basically.
Like anything is a good coding practice.
If you understand what you're doing and you believe that it is a
proper usage of the CPU.
And since the CPU can do wrapping.
With my tech very easily, especially on an 8-bit integer like that.
It's no problem.
I mean, it can do it on 32-bit integer just as well.
So you should absolutely use that if there's a reason to do.
So we are just about out of time.
So last question here.
Let's see.
Yeah, misc.
Annex says it goes in data as DB.
So it's very likely to be 0 but only because Windows zeros page for.
Yeah, I believe that the person who said that it gets initialized to
zero is wrong.
Actually.
I believe that only Statics are guaranteed to be initialized to 0 so
I'm really nervous about that.
But if someone checks the spec and says that it absolutely is zero
then maybe you can rely on that.
I don't know.
Okay.
Someone someone says they have is this is this actually I don't know
if this is actually someone someone sending a link here.
Maybe this is a link to the spa.
I don't actually know.
Let's find out, copy link address.
Let's see here, because I would like to know the answer.
I don't ever use it, but let's see.
Let's see.
Static.
If anonymous.
If an object that has automatic storage durations on its values in
determinant.
Yes, if an object has static storage duration, it is not initially
explicit initially, especially then gets cleared to zero.
As we thought.
Let's see what happens with an extern though.
Yes, it looks like it's not initialized to 0.
I don't know.
Someone should go do a careful reading of the spec, but I believe I
believe Dusty gozongas.
I believe that is not correct.
Static is the thing that gets you 0 initialization.
It being Global does not help you.
You actually I think do needed to be Global.
Now granted you could just do you know like this or something and that
would then cause it to be initialized to 0, but if you just declare it
with
Nothing, it will not be initialized to zero, like a static.
All right, I think that is about it.
Please save all the questions for tomorrow when we will be going over
this code with a little more of a fine-tooth comb and I'll explain
everything in very deep detail and we will clean up a few things and
talk about how we want to do that cleanup because the code is a little
bit messy right now.
So I had an excellent time coding with you this evening.
I'm pretty psyched that we have an animating bitmap now that we can do
whatever we want with and we will have about I think one more
Of Windows coding.
Next week will be a Windows coding week as well because I got to get
sound working.
I don't want to start the game without sound.
So we're gonna get sound working and just do a little bit of work with
input so we can have a Gamepad and stuff like that.
So I think we'll have one more week of window stuff, but then we will
be in game territory in time for the month of Christmas, which is
exciting.
Eating for me because I'm pretty psyched to start working on this
game.
I hope you are too.
So thank you so much everyone for joining me.
It has been a real pleasure.
I hope to see you.
All tomorrow.
We're going to do 8 p.m.
I think tomorrow again.
And then from then on we'll move the Friday streams to an early stream
so that people in other time zones can follow along.
But tomorrow we'll do a p.m.
Again.
I believe watch the Twitter to find out what the time is and I'll try
to get a live schedule up at some point.
So people know when the stream is up, so they know when to come
Again, thank you so much for joining me.
I hope to see you back here.
Tomorrow when we'll go over.
This code, will clean it up.
We'll talk about anything.
Well, you know, we'll sort of tighten down the learning screws on it
so that everyone kind of comfortable with where we're at because we
went really fast this week.
That was the goal will kind of try to do those like basically fast
through the first four days and then take a day of just like relaxing
and talking about the code and making sure we're all comfortable that
before I move on.
That's probably how will do things.
And I hope to see you all here tomorrow with your question.
So, thanks everyone for tuning in and I will catch you tomorrow.