Hello everyone, and welcome to handmade hero show.
Rico to complete game live on stream before we get started today.
I just wanted to put in a brief little aside on LZ versus run length,
encoding compression.
The, the fine fellow who's responsible for the past episodes.
This this past episode guide that we use on handmade hero is currently
working on a run length and coder.
And I was just he was mentioning it in the pre stream and I was just
mentioning that.
Hey, if you make a run length, encoding, it's not that much of a jump
to making an LZ encoder.
The decompressor is actually basically the same and it's only the
compressor actually gets a little more complicated, but I
And to diagram that for folks, because there's a really interesting
thing that happens with LZ compression and run length, encoding that I
thought would be interesting for beginners here.
So let me just go ahead and sort of diagram that out.
So let me just talk about rle versus LZ.
Alright, so, for those of you who don't know very much about these
sorts of things, which by the way is also me, I'm not a compression
expert as I think I mentioned it this this recent handmade con.
One of the reasons I asked the folks that Rod to come and talk about
it is because they are compression experts.
I'm a waitress a, they are the compression experts.
As like, the him, the people who currently have, like the world's
reigning smallest size, fastest speed, compressor, or whatever it is.
But, you know, just some basic things here because compression is kind
of just interesting and encoders are interesting in the general case
and there's some simple things you can start to look at about them.
So, what what are these things?
Well, you know, if you imagine that
You're sending something and you or encoding something that you want
to make smaller, right?
There's a number of ways that you might go about doing this.
And, you know, every way that you might try to compress something is,
is basically about figuring out what special properties of the data
are that you're working with, and exploiting those special properties.
Because in general, you know, I like I said, I'm not a compression
expert.
But the general consensus among people in terms of the math on this,
Is the information Theory wise in terms of what we've been able to
determine about how information really works, it's kind of provable
that there is no way to generally compress things.
Meaning you know if you wanted to make something that can fit stuff in
a smaller space, always it's not really possible.
All you can do is make things that fit things in smaller spaces for
certain classes of information, right?
And and again like that's you know, math, as we
no, it seems to indicate very strongly that this is the
Ace and you know I mean who knows maybe someday we'll come up with
weird things that sort of change the way we think about the world or
something, but assuming that the math we currently have is is, you
know, as infallible as it as we currently think it is.
Then there's nothing you can really do to make a thing that
generically makes information smaller that doesn't happen.
But with any piece of information, usually you're transmitting it in a
context, right?
Like, for example, maybe I'm
Making an image compressor.
Well, well, that means that I kind of fundamentally.
No, I'm transmitting images as opposed to other data, so that already
puts me in like a class of sort of information or storing them or
whatever.
I'm going to do, right?
And similarly, maybe I know these are photographs.
So there's even more restricted, the kinds of sort of information that
might be in here and the way that it looks and so typically what we're
doing with a compressor,
Is there saying well for the particular category of stuff that we're
working with what we're going to do is say we know that the the type
of information.
We're compressing has certain fundamental properties that are often
true and by exploiting the fact that those things are more often true
than not.
We can encode the information in a smaller space because we are
effectively giving up the ability to encode other pieces of
information that are not relevant to our interest.
In this case, those
Would get bigger.
Right?
So if you imagine this playing out in a scenario, like, like I said
with image compression, let's say we're trying to losslessly compress
an image.
Well, we kind of know, the sorts of images humans, tend to make and
transmit or store.
Again, we also know photographs versus like line art or that sort of
thing.
These all have very surprised to them.
It's very unusual that someone would make an image that's just like
white noise, right?
Or an image.
That's just like a very specific weird pattern of alternating Dot
Or whatever those are very unusual images.
So by saying that we don't care how big those images are to encode, we
can make a bunch of sort of assumptions about how our image data is
going to look that will allow us to encode.
Other the images, we work frequently care about in smaller space,
right?
So that's generally what we're talking about when we talk about
compression.
It's this sort of selecting a sort of an area of information that we
care about storing, and we're pre saying we're only going to work well
on those
Of things.
And then we start to make a bunch of concessions to that type of data.
That means that other types of data would get bigger and we'd actually
have an inflator not a compressor if we ran it on those but since we
never care about running on those it's okay.
And that's basically what compression is about.
It's about baking those assumptions in to a piece of code that then
allows you to store and transmit a certain class of information, often
much more efficiently because you have sort of given up on these
others on the other
Classes of information that you don't care about and so rle or run
length.
Encoding is usually
First kind of compression that anyone comes across and it's the kind
that you used to use way way back in the day before, sort of more
extensive compressors were really common.
But all it is is it's called run length.
Encoding.
And what it is is rle, schemes are a family of schemes that all work,
you know, very similarly but the specific way that you might pick how
to encode them might change a little bit but the idea is simply that,
well, if I'm coding, a piece of data, you know, that has some data, as
you know, maybe it's got, you know, an a b, a c and e, g, and H, and
then an a again, and then it'd be and whatever it comes to here, and
that's my message.
But then, it does something like.
Well, now, there's just a bunch
Of bees in a row, right?
And you can imagine this sort of thing is a little bit more popular.
Perhaps, in pixel art, where you've got, you know, maybe big Phil's of
of the same color or something like this, right?
Well what run length encoding does is it says all right, if I'm going
to encode this message well and the unencoded version of this message,
right?
How many are there here?
1 2 3 4 5 6 7 8 9 10 11 12 13 14 15 16.
Right?
So there's 16 sort of pieces of information are symbols if you
In this, you know, this piece of information that I'm trying to
encode.
But one, two, three, four, five, six, seven, eight of them, right?
Are actually sort of information that I, that I would have to encode,
perhaps individually.
Right.
But then there's this big long set, that's just duplicated.
So, what I might be able to do is put a number first, for example, you
know, right before here.
If I've got these, I'm going to
Stop it right here and say I've got these seven, right?
One, two, three, four, five, six, seven.
If I first encoded a seven and then said a b c EG h, a right, well,
I've expanded my message by one.
I've inserted one symbol here.
Alright, so it got a little bit bigger, but then what I could do is
I've got one, two, three, four, five, six, seven, eight, nine,
repeated B's.
I could just say nine and then, Abby, right?
And so if you look at what happens here, all I would need to do now is
encode some way of saying the seven is how many things I have in a row
that I care about, right?
And the 9 is, is the thing that encodes the thing that comes after?
It is just duplicated a bunch of times.
Instead of looking for New pieces of information that come after it
and often times the way that this works in early, it says, well, I
won't even bother spending any extra information to communicate that
all I'll say is that we just go in.
A I send a number of literals as they're called, you know, basically
things I'm going to encode directly.
And then a run literals run, literals run.
So I just do how many pieces of new information do I have?
I put them in there.
How many pieces of replicated information?
Do I have?
I put them in there, right?
And then the next one, it would be a literal count again.
And if I didn't have a run and I was at the maximum size that I could
fit in here, like let's say, these are B.
So maybe the maximum number of literals, I can have, is 255 for the
run, I just encode a zero and then it would be like, okay, there's
nothing.
There are no repeated values here and then the next thing would be
another count of literals, right?
So hopefully you can see how that run cutting very, very simple.
It's basically just a number of how many new piece of information.
I have been a number of how many replications I want to do of the next
bite.
Right?
So it's just like new B and then the B run count and then the B to
repeat new B and the B run count the run to repeat, right.
So hopefully that makes a fair bit of sense, right?
It's very, very simple encoding.
And, you know, for those of you who ever were back in the day, if you
ever heard of like the old-school formats, like maybe you're like me,
you grew up.
You had an Amiga in the household to me, computer.
Electronic Arts, I believe is the company who introduced this format.
It was called The Interchange file format, her iff, and it had the
interleave bitmap format was a sub format of it.
That could be put in there.
Ifm was kind of a container format, that can hold multiple formats.
It was our iff related.
I don't remember what our iife even stands for, but riff chunks are a
standard thing and I, I'm sorry, I can't remember what it stands for.
But anyway, this file format actually had run length, encoding in it.
So if you ever remember how bitmaps are sorted on the Amiga, I believe
our Ellie was in there.
Again, back in the day.
I believe there's also like maybe PCX.
I'm sorry my memory is kind of fading here but there's some old-school
formats that Graphics formats that that use this.
It's not really something that's used very commonly anymore, but it's,
you know, it's and it was, it was not so uncommon back in the day and
why was it not so uncommon?
Well, if you think about it, it's really, really simple, right?
You know, this can be coated in a few lines of code, it's just
Read read one byte you know, copy the number of bytes from the input
stream to the output stream that you just read read one, byte and a
replication, B, and just do a for Loop to Output that bite that many
times, right?
That's it.
So it's very, very, very simple.
You know, there's its it takes almost no code and can run very
quickly, right?
So the point that I want to make about early versus L, see here that
came from the pre stream is LZ.
Compression is a sort of
Much more heavy-duty form of compression.
You might say, and why do I say that?
Because, you know, at the outset I sort of said, well, you know,
compression is a no-win scenario, right?
It's like, it's just about selecting, certain sets of information that
you can encode and you can't really ever make something that makes
everything smaller.
So why am I saying that this is like more heavyweight.
What does that even mean?
Certainly it should just be that no matter what.
Encoding you choose.
Some things are much better than others.
And Bubba Bubba Bubba right.
Well
Oh, I really mean to say by this is this is a much more commonly
applied compression technique.
So if nothing else, we could probably say that our experience.
So far has shown that LZ as a technique tends to encode, human-style
messages much more interestingly than rle does for in terms of getting
good compression out of it.
So, you know, even though compression is a zero-sum game, it doesn't
mean there aren't better.
And worse compressors for the kind of information that we typically
care about.
And Elsie compression is something that's used in.
Basically everything that you use today whether it's 7-Zip or pkzip or
you know any of the sort of zip based utilities that you use or in a
PNG file.
For example, anywhere that you're doing lossless encoding.
You're going to see a lot of LZ related techniques and it's been
around for a very long time.
It's been around since the 70s and it's just something that hasn't
really been beaten.
It's, I guess, for whatever reason, it really hits a sweet spot in
terms of efficiency of coding versus ability to, actually get
compression out of the types of messages humans, typically send or
care about storing.
So, l z is a very, very popular compression format but, you know,
maybe it's a little bit more daunting to understand than our Ali or
something like this or maybe, you know, you think that it's like, oh,
it's kind of lure out there.
And I just wanted to make the point when, because we're talking about
on the
I'm that LZ in our earlier base are almost identical.
LZ is just a tiny, tiny, little bit more than are at least.
So if you feel comfortable programming run-length, encoding, you also
trust me will feel very comfortable programming LZ, which stands for
lempel ziv.
It's named after the people, it's not like run-length encoding where
it's named after kind of what it does.
So this is very easy, especially the decoder.
Now, the encoders are a little more complicated, not that much more
complicated because you don't have to take it to the nth degree.
One of the things about encoding that I'll talk about in a second.
Is that the reason that a gnarly encoder is more is more
straightforward than an LZ encoder.
Although, you know, one of the reasons is you'll see in a second is
this because there's a little more bookkeeping to do just to make
pills of encoder.
Then there is our Ally but with a limp L7 coder, there are choices
about what's the best thing to encode.
So, there's options, there's not just one right way to do a lempel ziv
in code, in terms of what the code looks at it, whereas with rle,
that's not true rle.
There's only one way to encode, the data for any given scheme.
So it's just instant, pretty much how it works, you know, I guess.
Well, you know,
Maybe that's not exactly true.
I mean, I could see for summarily schemes, like the one I laid out
here.
Maybe there are a couple of choices you could make.
So I, you know, maybe I wouldn't even go that far, I guess, maybe the
better way to say it would be with something like lempel, ziv, your
encoder couldn't get perhaps significantly more compression by making
different choices often times whereas with our Ali, maybe that's not
the case as often.
So I don't know minimalists often that a little bit but either way,
you could ignore all that.
All I really wanted to show was about the decompression.
Then how simple LZ really is, so that you can feel like it.
Maybe it's a little bit more accessible to you, then it would be.
So again, they feel comfortable with our Ali, you should feel very
comfortable with LZ.
And here's why
So, all an LZ encoder does, is basically exactly the same thing that
we talked about.
But instead of encoding runs the Run Part, right?
So the literal part is almost exactly the same in LZ.
There's really no difference at some.
There's going to be some way in a lempel ziv scheme to encode.
The fact that we've got a bunch of new B coming and then we encode the
B that part stays basically the same.
The part that changes is the Run Part instead of talking about runs in
a generic sense.
And right where we're saying oh hey, by the way, when I say something
is a run, I'm just going to give you a bite and you replicate that
bite.
So, rather than encoding runs that way.
Instead, what I'm going to say is in addition to just account, I'm
also going to give you an offset, okay?
And the offset is going to be some look back into.
What I've
Already sent you and then you're going to take that many, whatever.
I said, the Run was, you're going to copy that many things from the
previous information.
So, for example, if I had something like a b, c, d, e, f, g, h i j b,
GH, ABCD, right.
And one way that I might encode, this is say, well, okay, if my
encoder notices that we have an
Edie and an ABCD in both places, right?
Then it might choose to.
And there's the, you know, you can notice that this a be here.
I'll talk about that in a second.
And these GH is right.
We'll talk about those in a second.
But I see these ABCDs here in the encoder and I say, oh okay, so maybe
I say 1, 2, 3 4 5 6 7 8 9, 10 11, maybe I encode my 11 and then I
encode this, right?
And those are all new B.
So these are literals
Right.
Then I look at the ABCD and I say, oh back here I already sent an
ABCD.
So instead what I'll say is just 0 go back 1 2 3, 4 5 6 7 8 9 10, 11
B, right and then copy for B so you know the run like this is for the
distance is 11 and that's all I needed to encode.
So instead of having to write for things into the input stream I only
had to write to
Right.
Okay so hopefully that makes some sense and you know again there's
some subtlety here because when you encode things like this you still
have the problem of.
How do I encode?
What thing I'm doing?
Like if I say that I have an 11:00 here or a for how do I know what
that means and like one answer like it was in the early case is to
just say that they're alternating so the decompressor always knows it
does.
And then the other one, the other one than the other.
It doesn't have to spare any extra bits.
Other things might have individual bits on there that are like, codes
that say, oh, you do this or you do that.
So, you know, you can trade off information, in various ways.
That's again, getting into sort of the minutiae compression, which I
wasn't sort of going to try to do, but I just want to point that out.
So, if you feel comfortable coding, this, you probably feel Comfort
coding.
This, I mean, how simple is this?
You compressor I just read a number, right?
I then copy that number of bytes, then I
I read a number and a second number.
I use the second number to figure out how many bytes to go backwards
for Mike.
I just look my pointer backwards that many bytes and then I copy them
this many bytes to the input stream, right?
Okay, so again, hopefully anyone watching who's at all comfortable
with anything we do in handmade hero is going to be very comfortable
with that.
Because I mean, how simple is that?
Right?
Very, very simple.
It's certainly only the tiniest bit different than this.
So it's just it's very very
Like to write an LZ decode decoder in that sense, right?
So,
The thing that I wanted to show you in addition, this was the part
that originally made me want to go say this because I first of all
wanted to say, hey me blow, if you feel comfortable, darlie, you
probably would feel very comfortable this and I think, hopefully, I'm
right.
But here's the really cool part about LZ and I rarely see this sort of
thing mentioned probably because it's so by the time someone becomes a
compression expert, this is so not interesting to them that they
probably don't think it's as cool as like I
It is.
I recently implemented my first actual like compressor that will
probably ship in something, because I never do compression.
But for, for 1935, for the game that I'm working on.
Now, I did my own compressor because I basically wanted almost, you
know, essentially all the code in the game to be code that I wrote.
And so, I had to write a compressor for it and I kind of had to learn
like roughly how to do some of these things.
And I thought this was just
Cool.
When you have an LZ compressor, based on what I just told you at first
and again, so, you know, I'm assuming that you're like me, those of
you out there compression experts already know this.
But if you're like me and have kind of saw this stuff for the first
time, right?
Going through it, you're like, okay, well, if I come from a gnarly
compressor and I go to LZ compressor that allows me to like exploit
these patterns really cleanly, but I've lost the ability to do.
Big runs of the same thing, right?
Because now, you know, naively you might think well, now if I wanted
to encode a big long run of these bees like this it's like well how do
I do it?
Well, you know, I guess I in code maybe for bees or something or some
reasonable number of them.
And then I encode a replication that says to replicate those for bees
and then you know I encode a replication that says, replicate those
eight bees or something, you know, like,
You build up by doing squared every time like I replicate, I put two
bees in.
I replicate the to bees and I left the Four B's everybody pees, right,
and build it up and it seems like I'm taking a lot more space to
encode.
Just a big long run of like, you know a hundred bees or something like
this.
But the reality is as long as your LZ, decoder is operating sort of in
just in a buffer and you're just kind of writing to the buffer, you
can actually get an orally in coding.
Basically, for free in your LZ encoder.
Because of the fact that there is no reason you can't, replicate
symbols in the middle of the same run.
And let me show you how this works because this is the thing that I
thought was so cool.
I was like, oh wait, I when I realized this I'm kind of like working
on it and I'm like, oh well.
Oh cool, right?
So what happens here is, let's say that I have that exact scenario
that I'm talking about.
So I've got a b c d d, d, d d and it just goes on forever.
Right.
So there's just an Infinity of Dee's that come after this and I want
to encode them all.
How do I do it, right?
And so, like I said, the naive way to do this would be to say, oh
okay, you know, maybe I put out my first literal, you know, and I just
try to get that far in, right?
So I say, like, oh my first one is one, two, three, four, five, six,
seven, right?
So I said, okay, seven.
And then I encode my a,b,c,d DD d, right?
Then I go, we'll all replicate.
I go back for right.
So I say my
Distance to look back is for something like this and then my
replication is for, right?
So I just take this and then that'll output at dddd, right?
And then I saying like Okay the next thing I want to do is replicate
this whole thing.
So I would do like oh my look back is 8 and I want to replicate 8 and
then I've got 16 and then I got right and you can see why I'm saying
that that looks really bad because like, hey, that's so much worse.
The rle version of this would have just said, oh, I've got, you know,
however, many I've got 100 and then
And that's all I would have had to have sent and there's all the D's,
right?
So it looks like this is way worse, but what you have to remember is
that if the decoder is just writing it into a buffer, you can actually
just do the rle part for free.
When I get here, I go.
Oh, I've got all of these deals that come here.
So then all I do is say well, okay, in code for ABCD right now, I want
to replicate this D.
Well, all I have to do is encode the one which basically says,
Look Backwards, one for the start of my run which is here.
And then I just say how many I want, right?
I want you know, 99 more D's right?
And look what happens the decoder goes.
Oh okay take a deep from the input stream right because it's starting
here and it's going to copy and where does it write it?
Well, it writes it right here because that's the output point.
Now it goes forward to try and continue reading the run and it looks
and finds the D that it just wrote like the decoder just wrote
The D, but it's there in the buffer, right?
So then it reads that D and goes, okay, and right, sit here, right?
So essentially, an LZ, decoder can self-replicate what it just wrote,
which means that it is no less efficient really, to encode those rods.
It's a slightly less efficient because like I said, you have to
include encode the look-back potentially, so it might not be quite as
efficient, you know, in terms of 107 the bits, but in terms of
Derrek, Lee.
Speaking, how hard is it to encode a run?
It's actually really hard to really easy to encode a run because it
just self replicates out.
And what's more important is that unlike rle which has to talk about a
specific pattern potentially.
Like, you know, if I wanted to look at my early encoder, well, if I
wanted to encode a run of something more complicated than just one
symbol.
Let's say I wanted to encode biddy, biddy biddy or something like this
I would need an additional
Channel symbol in here.
In addition to the run count, I need how long the sub piece of the Run
was so that the decoder would know how many of these symbols to pick
out and replicate right.
Not so, with LZ with LZ the look-back, count is basically the same as
the duplication count, right?
It's if I wanted to replicate CD many times, I just encode a to here
and then I would have 99 copies of CD because it would write a see
here.
Addy here, right?
It's going because it's like
It's reading from here, it moves to here reads from here and it wrote
here and here then it moves to hear and read C and D again and then it
keeps so it just keeps self-replicating its own pattern and on and on
and on right?
So essentially an LZ, decoder has a run length and coder built into it
for free.
And you know, free is not really probably the correct term here but
almost free.
so that's just a really, really cool aspect of l z and it kind of just
shows why it's such an interesting algorithm to
it's got so much versatility there because not only
Can it do that?
Nice grabbing patterns that I've seen before but it can also go ahead
and duplicate just like a gnarly is in big long runs.
What's more is that?
It only takes two steps to do, a duplication from anywhere in the
street.
Because if you think about it, what was the requirement for me being
able to dupe here?
Well, the requirement for me being able to do peer was that I am able
to put the piece, the thing I want to do at the end of the stream,
right?
Because it needs to be able
BCD, right?
And if I want to do is like C&D, C&D, C&D, right?
Well, if I wanted to do this duplication, the requirement is just that
I have to send it.
And then the last thing in the buffer, right?
Has to be the thing that I want to do because I'm going to encode a
look back, right?
And then I'm going to encode, the duplication count, whatever it is,
and it's going to replicate replicate replicate, I couldn't encode a
bigger.
Look back.
Like if I encoded for here
because I wanted to replicate a be like, you know, I'm just doing an
example.
Let's say it's a b, c, d, A.B, A.B A.B.
I couldn't do this one and the reason that I couldn't do this one is
because if I looked back to hear, you know, and I'm right here, if I
look back to here and start copying, I'm going to have to copy the CD.
So it's going.
Because if if you know, if I say 99 and I look back is for it's going
to go like ABCD when it reads the a be.
Yeah, it'll put the a be here.
It'll write the, a low right to be but then it'll write a see in a
In the here before it gets to the, a be again, right?
So, I'll end up with ABCD.
ABCD ABCD so the LZ can can can wrap that last thing in the buffer,
but it can't rep an arbitrary, pull out, but with two steps it can
because obviously any point in l z if I've got some big wrong run
here, let's say,
Let's say this is the thing that I want to do it.
This is going to replicate many many times.
I've got abcdefgh is a big long string, you know.
However, long it is and then I've got, you know, ijk or oops.
I J K here.
And then I've got the dupe, abcdefgh, abcdefgh, dot, dot, dot, dot
dot, audit on, and on and on.
So I encode this big long thing as a literal and then I get to hear
and I'm like, oh, I want to do it like an infinite dupe base.
Do you like many?
Maybe this replicates many 99 times like the other one.
What are does or whatever?
Or a hundred times.
I want to sort of grab this part, and I want to replicate it, but I
can't do that because not the end of the buffer.
Well, that's okay.
It only takes me two steps, right?
I just encode the look back here.
One, two, three, four, five, six, seven, eight, nine, ten, eleven,
right?
So I say, oh, the look back is 11.
And then I say one, two, three, four, five, six, seven eight is, is
the thing to copy, right?
So I go ahead and put that forward.
That will write the first one in and then I just encode immediately
after that.
That my look back is just another eight.
And then my replication count, which is 8 times 100.
However, many I wanted their.
It's 800 or something like that right now.
Granted that's greater than 255.
So I'd probably do this in pieces but you can see how I can just move
it to the end.
And by the way, guess I should, I kind of miss poker when I said the
replication are 99.
What I really mean is 99 times to, right?
I mean times the the length of the thing that I'm replicating, right?
So that
That was just a, that was a typo there or a mental slip.
So hopefully, you can kind of see how it's really very versatile
because the encoder can do lots of things, right?
The encoder can encode just chunks that it wants to replicate, but it
can also move chunks to the front and then dupe them or just dupe.
The last thing that it's saw for the entire size of the rep count it
can do, right?
So it kind of gets you just a lot of Versatility there and that's one
of the reasons why l z is such a popular.
Awesome because it's very very versatile and gets you know gets a lot
of bang for the buck there.
Again, if you assume you're sending see a lot of signal.
If you assume that the information you're dealing with, has a lot of
self-replication or ceph self regularity to it, which again, is
generally true of the sorts of things that humans tend to do.
Like we tend to have a lot of regularity in our information, hence l z
works very well.
If we were a species, whose information typically included a lot of
white noise, this would be useless because
Data would look all completely random and there wouldn't be pieces
that you want to copy and the kinds of techniques we would use to
compress.
Things like white noise would be very different, right?
It wouldn't be this kind of thing where our information we tend to
Value information.
That's highly ordered.
That's the kind of information that humans traffic in probably for
good reasons, but I won't try to suss out any philosophical
underpinnings there.
I'll simply say that, you know it we tend to have how you order data
and so things that can exploit the order in the data like that tend to
be very useful for human style information.
And that is exactly what we care about when we are doing compression.
For things like games that are made up entirely of human created
assets, you know, there you go.
So that's LZ now, if you want to write an LCD compressor, hopefully,
it's just immediately obvious how to do so, from what I've just said,
right?
There's no mystery to it.
It's literally like read a number of bytes to Output output.
Those bytes read a number of bytes to replicate plus a number that
tells you where to look back into the stream and do the replication.
Now, one of the things that I baked into here,
That I didn't really mention is well, why is it encoded that way
because you couldn't coat it in a lot of different ways, right?
And the reason that typically elzy schemes tend to be about looking
From where you are is because most of the time.
Again, this is sort of like a prejudgment, right?
If you will, you know, I hate to use the term Prejudice because that
sounds - we're not really trying to be negative about it.
It's just that's what it tends to be.
It's a, it's a premade sort of idea about how this data is going to
look that.
We don't really know that it's going to be true.
But most of the time we hope that it is, we're going to pre say that
we expect most of the time when we see patterns,
Those patterns are more localized than globalized.
So, if I have some very long message, you know, and I've got, you
know, maybe this is a novel or something.
And I've got all these pages of my novel, right, you know, and here's
page, 1 and page 2 and page 3, and Page 4.
And then I'm up to page like 927 because, you know, maybe this is by
missioner, so it's really, really long.
And it just goes on forever.
Well you know you could imagine I'm trying to encode these things.
Again, remember everything that you encode has a cost.
If I want to encode the distance to look back for example or what, you
know, where I'm going.
The let's let's make it more generic if I'm going to encode the
location of the data that I'm trying to grab with some number of bits.
Well, however, many bits, I choose is going to affect how good of a
compression I get.
Get in various ways.
If I say that I'm going to use 8 Bits to encode, where to look, well,
that means that I can only specify 255 different positions to look in,
right?
If I said that, I was going to use 32 bits will, now I can do four
gigabytes worth of location but every time I encode one it's four
times larger than this to encode that position, right?
So I'm losing compression by gaining the ability to perhaps get some
work in.
Action by being more specific about where to look.
So there's this kind of trade-off there about how many bits I'm using,
right?
This gets a little bit more complicated.
When you talk about back ends, right?
And entropy encoding and I'll kind of leave that.
I'll say a final word about that, if I remember afterwards.
But so, you kind of do you have to remember that in a lot of encoders?
There's a step after l z which is like Huffman encoding arithmetic,
encoding, Rands encoding, these sorts of things that is designed to
more.
Only deal with the bit count, but the point still stands that,
however, many bits you actually use.
It makes a difference, even if you're using one of those back ends
because it's the all those back ends do for lack of a better term, is
they make it so that you're only paying for B you actually use and not
for B you don't use.
So for example this 32-bits it may be that the high for bits are very
rarely used, you know, once in a while they are but very rarely
instead of paying for them, every time you pay
Channel to how often you use them, right?
That is what those other sort of back ends, help you do so.
It's not, it's not.
Clean as saying it's four times bigger to like do this encoding or
something like that, there's more to it than that.
So I was going to.
But for purposes of thinking about it, it's not really that different
than saying this.
Let's assume that you're actually using the B you're allocating.
It is four times bigger, right?
Okay.
So this has a cost there.
So it has a cost to say that I'm going to allow my compressor to
encode the signal in a way or the information rather by reaching
further.
In back or by you know, picking a particular position in the Stream.
So if we were to say that we're going to use 32 bits, it might be fine
to use an absolute position like we could just start at the beginning
and say, where the thing was that we're replicating, right?
But that would require that we have enough bits to, you know, sort of
Encompass the whole message because otherwise, when we start getting
eventually, we'd only have the first few pages, right?
So let's say that's what we did and we said eight bits.
Well, eight bits is only going to get us.
Maybe the first page of our novel.
That would mean that if it was an absolute encoding scheme, right?
Where we just said, we start at the first character of the entire
stream we've done and we just go to and 5205 bites into it.
That's only like the first page of our novel.
It means that the only signal we can reference to duplicate the only
pieces of information.
We can duplicate are from that first page.
Well, if all of the words that we tend to use frequently all occurred
on the first page, great.
But what's the chances of that?
Probably, there are new characters who were introduced into the thing,
new location names.
New, manners of speaking depending on which chapter maybe some said
first-person sums in third person, you know how a novel is right?
So it doesn't make a lot of sense to encode.
The nine hundred and twenty seventh page of our book.
Using the same information is encoded the first page of our book.
And that's why encoders like this tend to use relative positioning
because the chances of finding a match for what we're
Where we're at right now tend to be much higher if we're talking about
the most recently seen 255 characters, rather than talking about the
very first 255 characters that we may have encountered.
So that's why typically no matter how many bits you tend to allocate
an LZ scheme, you oftentimes want to make them relative to the output
position because that allows you to more likely capture the
information, that's going to replicate it.
Because again, one of the assumptions that we make about this,
Data that we're trying to compress based on just the way humans, tend
to do it in the kinds of things that we tend to value.
In terms of information, the types of things we tend to produce.
Usually when we say something or do something or make a color in a
picture, the things nearby tend to be more similar than the things
further apart.
It doesn't have to be true.
And that's why you could always construct things, where it would have
been better if you did it the other way.
But for the most part, it tends to be this way, right?
Hopefully, that makes some sense.
Okay.
So, I'll say two more things about this LZ encoding.
So LZ decoder, like I said super simple, right?
It's just a question of coming up with exactly how you want those
bytes to work.
But you know if you just want to do it for as a programming, exercise,
you don't maybe have to worry so much about.
Are you getting good compression?
You can just sort of think about is let me just make something that
works and like I said we've talked about a very simple scheme that
could work.
Read a number of bytes to new bytes that are going to come in the
Stream.
So you write the number new B, then the B and then you just write a
number of bytes you want to copy and the look-back amount, right?
And then one more number you.
Go back meeting one more number.
That's how many B Nu B are coming.
The new B, right?
And just go on forever.
It's exactly like a gnarly encoder.
But now it's an LZ encoder.
I'm sorry decoder at that point, right?
Very, very, very simple.
Hopefully everyone who's watching would feel very comfortable doing
that if you made it this far, and handmade hero.
This is that's not very hard at all right.
Well, LZ encoding.
On the other hand, it's a little bit harder and, you know, even just
to do, even a basic one, is a little bit harder than something like a
gnarly encoder, which is very straightforward.
A gnarly encoder, basically, just involves looking ahead, a few
symbols, to CMI replicating.
Something, if I am and code it that way, otherwise don't, that's
really all you have to do for an early encoder, right?
If I just want something that captures this idea, right?
The only thing they are really encoder.
The basic kind of Arlene.
Cutter can do is just just capture this run, thats all it can do.
So all you do is you just look ahead one symbol at a time and say is
it the same as the symbol I'm on?
If it's not I just keep stacking up my literals.
If it is the same then I just keep a little count of how many there
are when I get to the end of that when I see the first differing
symbol, which would be here, right?
I go.
How many did I have?
I've got five.
Okay, encoder run five in the number, right?
So the encoder is very easy.
It's just all it is is just
Looking ahead, a few symbols to see how long any individual run is.
And when you see it, you out, put it, right?
So very, very simple encoder.
Not a lot of decision-making.
They have there are places you could imagine making some decisions
about that but you know, they're very, very simplistic.
It's there's not a lot of complexity there in terms of getting the
compression you would expect to get out of our leaders.
Just did not a lot there but for llz encoding it's more difficult.
The reason it's more difficult is because now you got this whole back
catalog, right?
Let's say we are doing b, b, b base.
So let's say we have a, you know, an 8-bit look back, right?
That's 255 positions in the output stream starting from where I am
right now, that could be selected as a place to copy from.
And now I have to make a decision about those 255 locations, right?
I have to have an opinion.
Which of those two 55 should I encode?
At all because I also could just encode a literal.
I could say here's new B, right?
So, if we think about this, the question is, how do I figure out which
of those to do?
Well, the brute force method, right?
You can think about, it's actually pretty easy.
If I literally wanted to make an incredibly slow LZ encoder, I could
just say, alright, you know, for you know, all 255, right?
I just literally from 0 to 255, right?
For each of those do a like while matches.
You know, run plus plus and keep the best, right?
So you can imagine what this kind of thing does, right?
It's like the brute force method which is very very slow.
It's like all right.
You know I'm here in the input stream, go all the way back to however
far back.
I can go.
If it's 255 symbols is my maximum then go back all the way to there,
right?
Start there and now I know I've got some symbols here, right?
X y z w whatever they are right my new symbols are here and you know
maybe there is an actual run so maybe the
One is c, d, d d, right?
So maybe there is the new symbols that are coming due.
Match something they match right there, right?
All right, so go way back all the way the beginning.
See from this symbol.
How many symbols in the input coming next, do I match?
Well, this is an A, and that's a see.
So none is the answer, right?
Then I, you know, this is this four part of the for I Loop here, I
come.
Now I go to be right.
Be okay, let's see how many matches I get.
This, is this part of the loop here while matches.
Okay, B and C, none.
Right.
So, again, nothing matches.
All right.
I come to the Sea and I say, all right, the see matches.
Oh cool.
Do the you know, increment this
Count I go di di di.
All right.
So I actually got all the way here and maybe this is an e so this
doesn't match.
Oh, so I got a 4.
Well, that's the best run.
I've seen so far.
So save this location as my best run so far.
I keep going, right, I checked this location, right?
I don't start here.
I still check this location because maybe the Run counts or whatever.
And again, because this is Brute Force, you could actually know that
that wasn't true by doing some of the things, but this
Beside the point.
So I go through all of these and I do all of that and I find my best
run is for and it's here.
So that's what I encode, right?
So that's a Brute Force, very simple, l z encoder.
Now you can imagine that this gets pretty bad especially if you
imagine, let's say you wanted to do a 16-bit look back.
Well, now you've got 65535
different positions to look at this becomes, you know, sort of this
very bad N squared thing.
Maybe my run count is 16 bit as well.
Now, I've got this much work to do, potentially to do my checking, you
know, it's not that bad because they won't all match but, you know,
it's pretty bad.
So you can imagine this getting extremely slow.
So typically what people do here instead of this is they try to keep
like a hash table as you the window slides through of like location.
And what the first three symbols of that location.
Let's say our so you do a hash on BCD on d d d and so on and you have
entries into a hash table so that when you CC DD you only look up into
the hash table and you only consider positions that started with CD,
right?
To keep your sort of match checking down.
And typically, the other things you have to do is, you know, you'll
often times get runs of just a bunch of things.
Like, if we have that thing where we've got all these dee dee dee dee
dee dee dee dee dee Dee Dee's.
Well, each one of these is going to Hash right?
Each of these dedede's just going to Hash into the same slot and
you're going to end up with this big old hash Collision, which is not
helping you cut it down at.
All right?
So the other thing you need to do oftentimes is keep sort of
information about overlapping run.
So you're like, okay, I know
This DD D, this 'run and this run, right?
I know that if I started, you know, if I checked this run and I got
into this run somehow, then I don't need to check this run at all
because there's no way that like, you know, once I get once I run like
overlaps, I know that I would have kept going at that point if I could
have and I didn't.
So starting here is not going to help being a surly or whatever,
right.
You can imagine like,
I'm passing a run at that point means that you only needed to check
one of those runs if that makes sense.
So yeah, anyway, I'm not stating that very well.
What I'm trying to say here is, if you got into a run at the same
place from two different locations, you can stop checking the run
because you've already gone as far as you were going to go.
And the other one would have been longer because it started earlier
because I guess what I'm saying?
So yeah, there you go.
All right, so my final note on this is just talking about the entropy
encoding backend situation, right?
LZ is basically a technique that says let me use sort of these
pointers back into, you know, sort of references relative references
back into the data that I've already seen.
As a way of pulling out common things that occur that we've already
seen
So that, you know, very straightforward.
Hopefully you can kind of see how that works.
Now that I've gone over it.
But like I said, a lot of compressors don't just use LZ, it's possible
that just using LZ, is your best bet that can be true.
Right there.
Certainly a class of classes of information, we're just using LZ,
directly is the best thing to do.
And off you go.
But it's also possible that using LZ alone is not as efficient as
using LZ with something called an entropy encoder on the back end.
And what this is, is these are techniques like I was saying before,
like Huffman
Arithmetic.
and our ins, or Tas things like these
And what these are these are techniques that allow you to take a look
at this, the actual information, you're encoding per symbol.
Remember Like These Guys, these symbols here, we've kind of broken it
up.
Maybe that's like b or the symbol or whatever or you know maybe it's
an 8-bit symbol per symbol or 16 bits per symbol.
taking a look at those and saying, okay,
After I do my l z compression.
Maybe my output my result, right?
So my result again, keep in mind.
My result is the the actual encoding of, like, you know, for literals
and here they are.
Then our look back of to, and a rep count of eight, you know, these
sorts of things.
So for ABCD, 28, then some simple, you know, blah, blah, that's my
actual thing that I'm talking about when I say my, my result,
Not the message.
I actually encoded or the information, encoded not that, but it's
compressed representation.
So the post LZ, you know, it's run through the LZ encoder and is now
whatever that bit pattern is.
So after I do that right after I encode my post LZ encoding
Take a look at that and say, well I know that each one of the things
in here is, you know, 8 Bits, or maybe some are 8 Bits and some are 16
bits, whatever.
However, it's broken up, I know that it's broken up into these chunks
that I understand.
It's got the literal count and then the literals encoded then it's got
the rep count and the distance count, you know, I know what it looks
like.
And I know there are these chunks and I know how many bits I allocated
to each one, but here's the thing, it may be that if you look at
these, they are not using
All of the bits equally for the same purposes and the same ways,
right?
It may be that if I looked at a histogram, let's say, right, so like
took a chart
And I said, what's the frequency of seeing a particular value, right?
And here is all my values, right?
So remember in 8 Bits, I let's say, I have 8 Bits.
I could have 255 different values, right?
And then the frequency is like, okay, how long is the message, right?
Maybe the message is, is 50 bytes long, right?
So that means the maximum frequency, I can see it's 50 if I just saw
the same thing 50 times, if I saw the same value 50 times at the most,
you could be and I have to 155 values.
Here is my 0
Right.
And here's 255 and here is 128.
Those are the values that could have been coding in a bite, right?
Yeah, I could look at this and if it's just flat right?
Which it can't be.
Lets you know what?
I should make this at least more.
Let's say that it's five, you know, 12 or something.
Write something like that.
So right, if every symbol appeared exactly twice, then it would just
be a flat histogram.
Looks like this, right?
Every symbol is equally likely to occur.
Okay, in that case, l z was great LZ.
We're done.
Right?
It out.
Put it a stream that has completely uniform, probability, that every
type of value, in a bite was equally represented
But what if it's more lumpy to borrow a phrase from Jeff Roberts that
he used at handmade cond.
What if it's more lumpy what if 0 for some reason appeared many more
times than everything else.
So maybe zero and let's it may be, you know, zero and maybe something
over here, appeared a couple times, but everything else was like very,
very low and there were these two spikes.
So I'm much much more likely to encode a zero for some reason because
of the nature of the data.
Let's say
And I was much more likely to incur, you know, encode a 97 for some
reason.
Right.
Well, now if you think about it, I'm not really using all eight bits.
Every time I output a bite because I'm much more likely to be talking
about zero and 97 which would only require, you know, two values.
So it would only take me one bit to encode a message that was all you
know, zeros or 97's.
But I'm writing 8 Bits every time and yeah I do still need
Eight bits of data because I do occasionally throw in a for and I do
in Cajun Ali, throwing a 237, right?
So it's not that I could have actually used one bit, but it's that
most of the time I could have used one bit.
Right?
Well, that's where these entropy encoders come in.
These entropy encoders are ways of saying, oh, what if, we actually
just use bits to encode the data.
And we used a number of bits for each symbol.
That was proportional to how many times it actually shows up.
How might we do this?
Well, let's take a simple example from Huffman because arithmetic and
Rands are much more.
Kids understand but they all do the same thing, they just do it to
better efficacy, Huffman it gets less efficiency, it's takes its
larger.
Huffman is the best you can do at a bit granularity but arithmetic and
Rands allow you to do SUB B granularity.
So, like arithmetic, and Rands allow you to do stuff.
Like, use one point five bits to encode things.
I know.
It sounds like magic.
It's not.
I'd encourage you to read about it, if you care about it.
But, you know again, that's
That's, that's why these are a lot more complicated to understand, is
because it, it seems like a little bit of magic, but something like
Hoffman's, very easy, to understand.
Let's say that we wanted to do this exact thing that we talked about.
I want zero in 97 to be very
To encode.
But I want all the rest of the values to take more space because they
almost never occur, right?
So all I have to do is say like, all right, let's just say that we
read the input stream, one bit at a time instead of one bite at a
time.
So I'm going to grab a bite of the input stream and I'm literally
going to go through the bits in it.
One by one to actually make sense of it.
Rather than saying I always operate on one bite.
So what do I do?
Well, I read the first bit in the input stream.
Okay, so here's the first bit, here's B 0, and I say well, is it a
zero or is it a one which one's it going to be right?
And whichever one is going to be, I'm going to make a decision if it's
a zero, I'm going to say, oh, okay, if it's a zero, then I know that
I'm in my high frequency thing, maybe I'm in the, the 512 versus 97
thing where they're both really highly likely.
So then when I get,
You know, and let me, let me draw this maybe a little bit differently.
We do this way.
Okay, then I'm a bit one here and I'm a bit one here, right?
So I read a 0 and then I say, okay, read the next bit, if I'm at a 0
and whatever that b is right, if that b is 0, I'm going to Output a
zero.
If that bit is a 1, I'm going to Output a 97.
Okay.
Now, it's taken me exactly two bits, right to encode a zero or a 97.
If the bit is a 1.
Then, you know, that first bit was a one
And I have the rest of my tree and maybe that rest of my tree, if
these really were uniform probability, the rest of that tree is just
okay, put 7 B after it or 8 Bits after it to say what the actual value
was right.
Does that make sense?
So basically, you can think about in this is like a muffin style way
to encode things.
So, basically, if you think about it, all this is is using bit
encoding to say, well, you know what, almost always what I encode is
some is one of these two values.
Use, let's make it only two bits to encode one of those values and
then I'll make it so that everything else takes 9.
B, write a 0 bit.
I'm sorry, A 1 B, followed by the actual 8 Bits of data.
But if it's a 0 bit instead, then I'm just shorthand for 097.
Now, what I've done, if I really did have this scenario where almost
everything is either a 0 or a 97.
Now, what I've done is, I've gone
From a message that used to take 8 bits per cell per symbol.
So if it was 512 long, it's 512 times one byte per symbol right?
Or, you know, we'll use b, x 8 bits per symbol.
So I've gone from a message that took eight times 512, bytes to one.
I'm 512 bits to 1 that takes 512 times to bits most of the time,
right?
Because there's only a couple
All times when I actually need to encode these other guys.
Right?
So at that point it's like hey great.
This is a 1024-bit message now roughly, whereas this one right here
was what a 4,096-bit message.
That's a great savings.
I've just saved, you know for it it's four times smaller, right?
So that's all these things do they basically say they basically take a
histogram of the data, a frequency count of the data and they try to
allocate the bits of the output.
So that it matches that histogram.
And what you can sort of see here to further understand why these
other two, and there's probably a lot more than he's out.
Again, I'm not a compression person.
So I can't tell you all the ways in which you might back in to encode
something.
There's certainly probably a lot more than
Resting here.
But again, I'm not familiar with with that branch of programming.
So, if you take a look at these, right, what you see there is, it's
like, okay, Huffman arithmetic Rands and tans for example, Huffman
because it looks like one of these, you know, there's tons of ways you
might organize how your Huffman trees were working and all these other
sorts of trade-offs, who knows, again, not a compression expert,
couldn't talk about them intelligently.
But if you're organizing it on a bit tree here, where you say, like,
okay, there's a bit, that's a one, or a zero.
And I go in a direction based on that down the tree and the tree.
Is designed to be balanced out so that the tree is shortest, where the
symbols are most frequent and longest, where they're not, that's
Huffman it has a quantization problem, right?
It has the problem that whatever these frequencies were, they probably
weren't binary frequencies because that's what this tree will give me
a path to a symbol on Huffman is going to be an integer number of
steps.
It's two bits.
It's to get down to here.
It's two bits to get down to here.
Whatever, this is down here is 4 bits to get to or whatever, right?
So I can only encode integer multiple frequencies exactly in my
Huffman tree.
So if I actually have something where there's which almost all
histograms will not fall into that category, most histograms.
If I say well the total length is 512 and the number of times I saw
you know this particular symbol is 7.
Dean.
Well, that's not going to divide out to anything that approaches an
integer, right?
That is not an integer, but that's how many bits I wanted.
You know, that's how or not, how many bits, that's how, What,
proportion of the output bits?
I wanted that symbol to take, right?
That is not going to be in codable in an integer step tree like this.
And so what these other techniques do is, they devise more clever way.
Ways of encoding that.
Allow you to know.
Oh, okay.
I want to produce a fractional number of bits to encode this thing.
And again, I really am not comfortable enough with the math at this
point to try and offer an explanation.
Huffman is very easy for a programmer to understand.
I would say, who did I just lose?
I just lost smoothing there.
That's interesting.
Is that because there's something else that was like, right when this
right when it switched this thing came up, I lost smoothing, I wonder
if that's information for Sergio because he was wondering why he lost
smoothing and it seems like that's a pretty interesting.
A Prius and coincidence anyway doesn't matter.
So point being that that is what these sort of additional techniques
do and you know basically like arithmetic versus Rands or Tans or
whatever.
The reason that people as far as I know Huffman is never what you
actually want to use in terms of
Sighs.
I could be wrong about this.
so, please take it with a very big grain of salt, because
I'm not a compression person, but my understanding is that Huffman for
example is a is like a very inefficient way to store the data compared
to arithmetic.
For example.
It's not like there's a trade-off.
It's just worse and very inefficient, probably wrong.
It is inefficient right compared to arithmetic because arithmetic can
match the histogram.
Exactly.
Whereas, Huffman can only
Approximate it by an integer match of histogram, right?
So that's my understanding of it is that you would never use a Huffman
encoder instead of an arithmetic encoder.
If what you cared about was space, my understanding is arithmetic, is
always better.
That's just my understanding.
I don't know if that's true.
Meaning, it's not like, oh Huffman works better for these signals and
arithmetic, works better thesis.
I thought that arithmetic was always preferable, but arithmetic was a
lot slower.
It involves integer divides or crazy table, lookups, and all these
sorts of things.
And supposedly, you know, again, the people I know who do compression
what I gleaned from their discussions on it.
And again, please take it with a grain of salt or even a cube of salt,
like, a salt lick.
The size of the kind of give to a horse is that Huffman encoders are
encoders, where you're doing them?
Because it's faster.
You can Implement them more quickly than you can't arithmetic and
coders.
Because arithmetic, encoders, involve things like integer divides.
Or things like this where as Huffman and coders did not and they can
be done directly with bit manipulation.
That's much faster.
That's my understanding of why you see Huffman and coders because they
are the very fastest back-end encoders, that still do a reasonable job
of histogram compression, but if you had unlimited time, you would not
use.
This was my understanding.
There's no sighs wind for it.
It's always a loss in terms of size or or it's always equivalent to
arithmetic or worse.
But these are a nsta ns encoders are like a new thing.
The ANS thing with something that was I guess invented by or
discovered recently in terms of the mathematics behind it.
And I don't know if the the folks at rad were the first people to
actually figure out why it was useful.
I think they might have been actually, I think Charles may have been
the first person I do.
I don't want to accidentally give credit to the wrong people or
something like this, but I think that's actually what happened you
should.
I don't know.
Maybe check the history books for this.
I'm not sure if anyone keeps history books on this, but it turns out
that by using the mathematics of these a NS things, which I don't
really understand at this point.
So I can't give you any kind of insight into how they actually work,
but you could read Fabi and Fabien posted some articles on it and you
could read some of his write-ups, if you're interested.
I don't know if Charles posted probably on his
Lockheed has posted some too, but basically the way that these things
work is they get arithmetic compression.
They get, they get sub, they get fractional bit Precision on the
histogram just like arithmetic coding, but they can be implemented.
In ways that gets you significant speed improvements to arithmetic
encoding.
And because of that, right?
You can approach Huffman speed while still getting the
Smallest possible size for your entropy.
My understanding is they are still able to win with Huffman.
So, my understanding is like a Trad, the very fastest codex, they
have, which are like very close to look a mem copy as how fast they
are.
Now is that Huffman is still the one that they use on the very fastest
codex but unlike just slightly slower they have our ins or Tas and
coders.
I'm not sure exactly how they work.
Like I say that's that's for the experts to know and me to wonder
about
the very fastest ones are still Huffman but only slightly slower now
are these ones that are based on the ANS math and those are like
extremely fast and get arithmetic size
Which is kind of crazy if you think about it because a lot of I think
for a long time people didn't think that was possible until you know,
some some Saucy gentleman.
I don't know the specifics, but came up with the ANS stuff and then
either the red
Folks are somebody figured out that there was ways to exploit the
properties of that ANS style, alphabets to to beat arithmetic
encoding.
So that's pretty cool, right?
That's a, yeah, that's just one of those things.
That's like awesome.
Like, how did that happen at this point?
I feel like we're kind of off.
Like this has been an almost an entirely compression oriented stream,
so, I don't know at this.
The point.
It just seems natural that we should just just do it, right?
We should just like, keep it going, why stop there?
So, you know, I mean, let's just say that, you know, we want to do one
of these, right?
Let's, let's take a look.
So right now you can, you can kind of see here.
We are in
In our handmade hero director.
You know, I'll just, I'll just load up some code.
Well, you know, let me not load up quite cold just yet.
Let's just take a look at something that I'll just show an example of
how you might approach.
So, I think, let's say you just wanted to play around with compression
little bit, right?
Like I said, not a compression experts.
I'm not going to throw out any kind of great wisdom here.
I'm just just giving you a like, a little tiny foothold, you know,
here's our, here's our art files and we know that our art files are
not compressed at.
All right.
We know that these are the files that
Got all we did was just we just dumped B into the file and we didn't
compress them at all.
They're just raw data, okay?
And so here we are in here.
And maybe the first thing that we're thinking is like, well, you know,
you should we apply compression?
What kind of compression should we apply?
How much would be saved if we did compress our data, you know, we
don't know, answers to any of this, right?
Well, one thing we could do is obviously, you know, if we wanted to
know how much compression we might get out of something like testing
layer 0 0 dot BMP.
You know, one thing that we might do is say, well, if we wanted to
use, lossless compression on it, how
Small, could it get one very obvious?
Way to do that, right?
Is to say, let's use someone's existing compression.
So let's say, I go and I open this up with a program like gimp for
example, or which is freely available program that you can download to
play with with with files, right?
So, one thing I could do is say, well, alright, let's suppose that I
just saved the file as a PNG which I know does have compression,
right?
And it has lost less compression.
Let's just save it as a PNG and see what we got.
So there we go.
Now I can compare these two file sizes and go.
Oh look at that.
Like, wow compression would save me so much space.
This is right now.
A 2 megabyte file that we're using in handmade hero, but if we wanted
to, it would have only been 86 K, right?
So, a massive difference.
Okay?
Now,
I don't know very much about the PNG format, but I do believe it's
basically like an LZ with transforms kind of a thing.
And we just kind of talked about LZ, so it's like, okay, well, what if
I just compress it directly with an LZ, something that didn't even
know.
It was getting an image, but I just wanted, I just wanted it to to
test just a straightforward LZ style compressor.
Now, lz7, zippers, one, we use here, use this thing called lzma.
A which is sort of like a very Advanced LZ.
Encoder does a bunch of very specific things.
It's got different back-end.
I don't even want to go into it.
It's got a lot of extra stuff but let's see how that does on it and
that does even better, right?
7-Zip is actually better than paying a compressing this particular
file.
But here you can see like, okay,
we're not going to replicate 7z or ping necessarily our first time
out, because we don't know anything about compression and whatever,
but odds are pretty good.
That an LZ compressor, something very basic would probably still be
pretty darn good here.
Look at how good we can get with these.
So again one typical thing that you'll do if you're just going to
start down the compression path of things, right?
It's say oh well what you know, what could a different compressor jet?
You know what could what could compress are written by experts.
What could that?
Now, I've got a sort of a bound on it, where I know, well, if I just
reimplemented, if I literally just went and learned how 7-Zip worked
around on it, that's what I can get if I went and read about PNG, how
that works is a public forum at?
I could certainly do that, that's what I might be able to get right,
so that gives me a good Target to shoot for, you know, and that's
really handy, right?
Because otherwise, we might not know, otherwise we might not have
anything to shoot for.
We would have no idea if our compressor was any good or not, or
Or what it's sort of bound.
You know what to Aspire to, if we wrote a good compressor, that was
based on 7-Zip.
There's based on LZ, what would it look like right?
But this is great because this gives us something to shoot for it.
Gives us an idea.
Hey, that's how good it could be.
Let's let's take a look, right.
Okay, so let's say that we want to do something along those lines,
right?
Let's say that we would like to make something that does a little bit
of compression there.
Well, okay, so let me go ahead and open up our project here and I'll
go ahead and build it and, you know, make sure that we get the build
loaded here as well.
There's our build up at and so, you know, we've got our simple
preprocessor here, right?
This was like, our little thing that we did.
That kind of
It was a little command-line utility could use.
Let's go ahead and just make another one of those, right?
So here it is.
Here's our simple preprocessor thing.
Let's do our, like simple compressor instead, right?
And we'll do a little CL here, and we'll say, okay, we'll call the
simple compressor, and we'll go ahead and Link it the way we were
doing, and we don't need to run it or anything.
Here.
But we've got a simple compressor at that.
Now, we'll compile right?
And so if I go ahead and do this build, obviously it's going to give
us an error.
It's going to say that simple.
Compressor is not found in, there's a very good reason for that.
We didn't actually make it yet, right?
But I can go ahead and let me just copy the simple preprocessor in
here and call it simple compressor.
And you know, will
We'll stop that.
So let's go ahead and load simple compressor, here a simple
compressor.
We don't actually want pretty much most of this stuff, right?
We don't want the meta struct and we don't want the tokenizer or the
parsing, or any of these sorts of things, right?
So we'll get rid of those, but we do want to keep probably read entire
file into memory and will terminate.
We don't care about the null terminate so much.
But the read entire file into memory would probably be a good idea.
All that would involve is getting rid of the file size plus 1 bit.
And the null Terminator.
But everything else here is exactly what we might want for this
purpose, right?
Pretty pretty straightforward.
So now we get rid of this stuff here and we can do our file contents,
reading to our file into memory.
And you know, here is our file and that we're going to do.
Let's say we're going to do this.
Basic compression idea, okay.
And so what I can do here is you know, we can even make this be like a
compressor or an actual little command line compressor that would
actually do something, right?
We can we can we can certainly do that.
Let's just say that we want our
You know, three arguments and again you know the way that's see works
is the course it passes.
The command name as the first argument.
So we're looking for arguments here.
So let's just say, you know, we're going to make a little command line
utility, we're going to print out to the standard error output.
If we don't get the arguments we expected and will just say okay the
usage of this thing is that you have to give me the command and then
you have to say like compress or like maybe.
Us or decompress like that and then like input and output.
Right.
so basically you just you pass compress or decompress or you know,
maybe we could do
this.
Maybe something like that.
Not very good documentation there.
I appreciate the fact that that is not good documentation but what?
You know, this is a little tiny utility, you know, what's the worst?
Possibly happen.
Famous Last Words anyway.
So in this case, I'm just going to pass that original argument there,
right?
And then we're going to go ahead and and and go from there.
All right?
So now we should actually have a thing called Simple compressor that
Run it.
Well I guess if I'm in the build directory, we can run it right.
There it is.
And whenever I run simple compressor, I'm going to get that.
That message that says, oh by the way you gotta use it like this,
right?
Some question or compress or decompress and off you go.
Okay.
So that's stuck what I wanted.
Now what we have to do here is we just have to do a string comparison
to see which of the modes that we're in, right?
And we can now that we know that we have the four arguments, we can
classify them as to what they are.
You know what?
I'm gonna switch over to this side so that my head's not in the way of
anything.
It just use a little bit easier for people to see.
Oops, let's go here, right?
So what I can say here is like, all right.
I've got an in file name.
I've got an out file name and then, of course, I've got a command,
very, very basic, right?
So my command is, the first thing.
My in file name is the second thing in my output file.
Name is the third thing.
I can then go ahead and do my string comparison.
I can say, you know, well if the loops if the command is compressed,
then I'm going to do compression if the command is decompress.
Oops, wow.
If they compress them into decompression and otherwise, I'm going to
have to print out the usage again, or or rather that I don't
understand the command, right?
And so I'll just say, you know, something here, it's like,
Unrecognized command.
And whatever the command was, we don't understand, right?
So that should be it.
And again, I'm going to have to actually include some of these spaces
C, standard Library here.
There we go.
And again, I'm using the C standard library, for this one.
Unlike on handmade hero, where we don't really use it.
So this should be something you can compile on any Aunt CC thing.
We're not going to, we're not going to try and be Windows.
Call directly into Windows there.
Anything like that.
All right, so now if I call Simple compressor like so on, right?
I could do compress, and it should work in theory.
Ooh,
Oh right, I would have to do compressed Fubar and it should work.
In theory course we have an employee anything so it doesn't I should
be able to call it decompress Fubar and it would work.
But then if I was to call something like blah Fubar, it should say
that it doesn't recognize those commands, Okay?
Now what we would do is on compress and decompress.
Now we just need to actually make these things do something.
So let's go ahead and try to make them actually do something.
let's see here, if we read file to our file into memory, this will be
in
I'll and you know what?
I just realized this.
I want this to actually be a little bit better than it is right.
File Contents.
I want to know that sighs.
Whatever that size is there.
So I feel like I also feel like this
Wouldn't work for anything.
That's greater than 4 gigabytes here because I feel like f tell
doesn't actually.
Give me a size T.
Is that true?
Let me, let me see here.
I feel like f.
Tell doesn't give you a size.
T, it gives you an ant, right?
I wish it gave you a size T, but you know, it doesn't.
So I don't think it's 64 bit.
That's all right, it's not the end of the world, but, you know,
Oh, the Aging, C++ Library.
Anyway, so we'll have the file size here, and we'll have the contents
here, like, so and so, you know, and maybe I'll do them Care on sign
here.
And I might even just to make life a little bit easier on myself, I
might go ahead and say that Karen signed is going to be, uh, so I
don't have to keep typing it.
All right, so there's my you ate and there's my file contents.
And so what I'm going to do is say, okay, you know, we'll get back a
file contents here.
Rather than just a raw pointer.
And that way, when I come through here, and I say, oh, what's the
result?
Well, I can say, oh the resulting file size is blah and the resulting
contents is is this see there.
And that way, it's all kind of bundled together and off we go, right?
So hopefully,
That's all we need.
Okay, so real contents result, file size?
Oops,
And just replacing that everywhere.
And then
I will read the in file here, right?
Let's see.
The file name is in file name, I forget, okay.
And the other thing that I need to do is I need to open the output
file as well.
And so, let's go ahead and do file out, file equals.
Well, actually, I guess do.
I really need to do that yet?
I guess.
I don't want to do that.
I think I left the other guy.
The other ones do that.
So, off we go.
So from here I would also like to probably put a
Hey.
Error message out.
If you can't believe the file, you know, why not been able to read
file % s and there's the file name, right?
So at least know that there was some kind of problem there and off we
go.
So now we just need something that does compress and decompress and
then we've actually got a compressor.
So we've got like a little infrastructure here for it and off we go.
So let's actually say that we've got that and and then figure out how
we're going to do it.
If we want to do compression.
We're just going to have a thing called.
Yes, let's say we'll pass it.
The in file file size of the in file contents.
And then we want to look an output buffer here, right?
And so the question would be how big does the output buffer need to be
right?
We need, we want to compress maybe from one piece of memory to another
piece of memory.
Let's say it's in memory compressor.
So, we want to compress this way, where we taken an input file, and
then we took an output file, we need an out buffer here.
And so we need some way of knowing how big the
Output, buffer is going to have to be right?
So when we do our Malik, we need some maximum size here.
And usually the way compressors do this is they have some idea of how
much they might inflate the thing to write how big it would happen.
It might become when they're processing it, right?
And so, you know, will also pass maybe the out buffer size as well
here, but we'll just say, Okay, so we've got an out buffer size and
then up over sizes, get maximum output side.
as for whatever this input size is,
Right?
So we're just going to say hey, one of the properties of our
compressor is getting the maximum output size.
Yeah, it's getting the maximum output size and maybe I could, like I
said, get compressed output size for some given input size.
So the input size and the output size.
We're just going to say we can, this compressor can tell you ahead of
time, this is what's going to happen.
And so what we could do is say, well, you know, maybe the the maximum
it could ever be is like twice as big or something, right?
And we'll be able to know what that actually is.
Once we write the compressor in a second here, but we'd basically said
like, oh yeah, it can't ever be, you know, more than that, or
something right to do.
Actually figure out the equation for our compressor.
But that's really all we're talking about here is just like hey you
know output size, we need something right?
So we'll say okay whatever the output whatever the compressor says the
maximum size is thing could be will actually do that and if we do so
then will now lock the out buffer size and you know off we go.
So at that point we've got the at buffer and we're ready to compress.
And here we go.
Similarly, in this case, we would have when we go to do our
decompress, right?
We need to do the opposite thing.
So we would have something here that's like decompress and that's
again going to be the in file size and file contents.
And then the out buffer size out by over again.
The problem is, what is
Maximum output size and again, in this case, let's just say that.
All right.
Whatever the Apple precise is here, is get output size or get
decompressed output size, and what we'll do is, we'll just say, oh,
hey compressor.
I'm assuming that you put something into the stream that lets you know
how big this thing expands to because that's just the property of the
thing that we want, for example.
And so, you know, you go ahead and you
Tell me how big this thing should be now I don't always actually like
that.
In fact you know to be honest maybe I don't really like that at all.
So what I might do is say let's do that slightly differently.
Let's say that's a property of the out the the sort of the, the outer
layer.
So maybe what we'd say here is like, okay yeah let's just say that we
this this file contents here.
Let's just say that the five the input the output content.
So he's
A size baked into it, right?
So, you know, since we can only do 32-bit wide things in here anyway,
because of RF teller, whatever.
Let's just say that in the in the outer area of the code, we remember
that particular piece of information.
So what we do is we say like, okay,
We know in here that we want to Malik the output buffer size, + 4 B.
And when we do the output buffer, we tell it to compress 24 bytes in.
That means at the end, right?
When we get our size T, like compressed size here, what we can do is
just store the compressed size into the output buffer.
So here is the output buffer, let's just say that the first pointer to
it.
Is an intern signed first thing there.
So I'm just going to write the compressed size in there.
Okay so what that means here is we can also say, all right, let's
assume that the file size here is greater than than 4 bytes, right?
Or it's got to be at least that if it's not that then it probably
wasn't our file because we know that we always output the size first
invalid.
Input file something like this.
Right?
And so we take a look and we say, hey this thing's got to be greater
than 4 B.
If it's not, then we should warn the user that, hey, this is probably
not a file that we output.
We don't output 3, B, long files.
So, you know, we take a look at the file size and we say, okay, the
output buffer size in this case is just, you know, whatever the in
file contents say that it is right because we out, you know, we're
just reading this we wrote out this 30
Two bit value here.
And now we're reading this 32
All you back in that we wrote out and then we say that's how big the
output buffer is that we wanted off, we go.
So we out, we allocate, we allocate that for our output buffer size
and there you can see that happening.
And when we come in here, we say well.
Alright, now when we pass in the contents, we just want to skip that
for B value that we had there, right?
And off we go.
So that's all we need to do, then we can decompress.
And of course, when we actually do the decompress,
Yes, we want in both these cases to actually write to the output file
as well.
And so, what we can do here is we could actually say if we wanted to
we could have a thing here that's like output.
Final output size and I guess that actually could be right here and
output buffer.
And so in this case, we just say, all right, our final output size is
whatever the compressed size is plus the 4, right?
Right?
Because we allocate the maximum, we would need plus the space for the
number.
But then after it's compressed, we only actually now need the
compressed size plus the 4, right?
We don't need to write out the whole buffer.
So our final output size is just a compressed size, plus our header
size, and we're done, right?
And our final output,
Buffer in this case is just the app up.
Same.
Exact thing is true.
In this case we know exactly what the output buffer size is it's going
to be this.
It's not going to have any adjustment to it and the output buffer is
here and that's it.
I think.
All right so now we've just got a case of like.
Alright let's go ahead and finish the scaffolding.
So we've got a thing that's like compress.
We've got a thing that's like decompress.
And now we just need to actually fill these in with some actual logic.
So we have the in size and the n, and then we have the outside eyes,
you know, and the out.
And then for the decompress, we've got same thing.
Okay, so obviously if we wanted to, we could just start by making this
an on compressor, something that literally is worse than a compressor
because it actually stores the size as well.
But just for our own testing purposes, make sure that our scaffolding
works, okay?
Let's just go ahead and say that we copy the in size from the into the
out and then we just return that size, right?
So, in both
both cases here and I guess our
Professor, you know, doesn't need to store anything because it's just
already again it, right?
So you know, this is now our the entirety of our
right.
We just want to do something very simple here where we do a copy.
So, if that's the entirety of our compressor, right?
It's not doing anything.
It's literally, you know, just a direct copy.
So, in this case, again, we are sort of saying we're limited to two
kind of files that are smaller than we might like care.
But that's because of the C runtime Library.
We can't actually get a 64-bit size out of everything.
So what you going to do, that's just just the way it goes, but anyway,
At this point, we should be able to now just use that final output to
actually write the output file and then we should be done.
So assuming that we got to here, right?
We could say if there's a final output size or rather buffer, then
what we can do is say, all right, let's try to open the out file
again, we'll just you know, do a standard, you know what I should
mention when we read this.
We want to read and binary, we don't want to read an ASCII otherwise
we'll get it'll the see runtime Library will do weird like translation
to the data.
So we're trying to read raw data here so we can press binary files.
Not just ask if I'll certainly.
So what I want to do here is open an output file for writing.
Hopefully we can load that output file.
And then I just want to do one giant F right to the output file where
we write that output buffer.
So the final output buffer.
I never remember which of these
Is the one we actually want because there's it has two parameters
rights and considers writing in chunks.
So it's like this, this times, this is the actual size and it doesn't
really matter which one you put in which position, but it has to do
with how it reports, the right, if there was an error which we don't
care about the moment.
But like I said, it's always a little bit weird.
Anyway, so when we do the fprintf here, we just want to say like
unable to open output file this.
And we just say,
Oh, that's out.
File name, okay?
So in theory, that's a complete simple compressor, right?
And so here's our simple compressor that we can run now and it doesn't
actually do any compression yet.
So let's go back to our data directory here.
I'm going to say oh well you know, we could do actually well, you
know.
No.
I'll go ahead and just copy something from the handmade.
Dana directory, the I don't know.
Let's see test 1 .hh a for example and will copy it here, right?
So there is test one that ha it's 1.5 MB long and so if I do simple
compressor on it and I say a want to compress just one .hh a test one.
Like simple compressor, I don't know.
Compressor.
Something like that.
Oops and I've got a command.
There we go.
Compress in theory now it should write out a file for this and that
file should be exactly 4 B longer and hey take a look, that's exactly
what it is, right?
Because remember we suck the length on the beginning and then we wrote
out the data exactly as it occurred.
Now, I should also be able to do a decompress on that from test-1 SCP
to test one, like let's say out right.
And now I should get back the exact same file size and I do and we
should verify as well that I can actually have.
Like, any kind of Dipping utility on here by any chance Beyond Compare
their, it is so beyond.
Compare should be on here.
I guess wind if I would prefer wind if I don't think it's on here so
it is.
There we go because this one is freely available.
It's in the wind.
It's from the windows SDK.
If you want to try and get it, although it gets increasingly harder to
Get these things.
They move them around and I don't know where they are anymore, a lot
of times, but let's take a look and see if there.
I think this can do binary files.
We can't we'll use Beyond Compare.
But anyway we want to make sure that these two files are the same.
So we want to do test 12th a and then test one doubt and we can see
that the files are identical and that's what we wanted, right?
So good.
So now we know that our compressor can do a round trip.
Now, the question is, can we actually add some some compression,
right?
And we've got some time here, right?
I think you know what?
I don't, I don't know when we started 30.
We got we got a few minutes here.
I'm do very simple compressing.
So let's say, here in our compressor, let's say that we want to do
like a gnarly compressor, right?
And what I can do here is actually make a couple of different kinds of
Of compression, even if I wanted to, I could do something here where
we said, like, which kind of compression we were using, which maybe I
should have put in a little bit more of a concession to that at the
outset.
But let's just say we're going to do our early compression for now.
So what we'll do is we'll say static, I'm just going to copy this
thing.
Really compress and Charlie decompress.
So we've got these two now and what I'll say is like okay we're just
going to forward these for now, or we can press in size and outsize
out and rle decompress in.
Skin that's eyes out.
And that way when we actually do this compression, we can actually
have something that sort of does you know, different kinds, what we
can try by just swapping out and probably I should put a little format
code in there that says oh here's what the compression is and so we
can pick between them or something, we'll do that later.
All right, so if I do our Ally compress here, this is the thing that
may blow is working on
For example, let's see how we might do that.
Okay, so what I want to do here is say, okay, I'm going to go through
my stream and I'm just going to write this the simplest possible way,
right?
Nothing fancy at all.
And I'm just going to say, like, okay, I've got my my string pointer,
so, you know, this is, this is my where I'm at in the Stream and I
want to iterate through all of the characters in the Stream.
Let's say,
And for every character in the Stream, I want to see how long of a
run, I have for a particular value, right?
So I want to early compress this.
I'm just going to say like, okay, I'm then going to say, you know,
size T offset or something like this and start at zero.
And then my offset is going to be less than whatever.
The inside is - the at.
So, I'm going to basically say, like,
You know, let's run through every character and for every character
I'm going to run from that character all the way to the end of the
stream.
Now, I'm not actually going to do that, right?
I'm just going to sort of say, hey, let's set up the loops to do that.
I'm going to break out early, so it's not actually a problem if you
will.
And then the other thing I'm going to do is say, well, this plus plus
at I probably need to work with that a little bit more specifically,
some it was going to move that down here for the moment, right?
Okay.
So I'm going to go through these streams here.
And what I'm going to do is
Really what I sort of said before, I'm just going to look to see how
many of the same value I have in a row, right?
So let's say I'm at this particular location, okay.
So I've got my value, you know, my starting value let's say, that's
whatever is in the input at this location.
Right.
That's all it is.
Whatever is at the input in this location, I'm going to go through
here and I'm just going to say, I want to count up how many of these
things there actually are.
So I want to say something like and I probably you know, let's let's
say we do something here.
In fact, we could just make this run and then just say while you know,
the offset is less than this.
And the starting value.
Sorry, just for organizing this here.
So,
Offset is within range.
So I haven't exceeded the end of the buffer or anything like that, and
whatever I'm at right now.
So, at plus offset, while it equals the starting value.
So, meaning I'm still seeing the same value that I was singing, then I
want to increase my run, right?
And and I can just make run be the variable here if you will, right.
Okay, so I start with a particular value.
That's whatever at the input stream at this point I say I'm going to
see how much of a run.
I could encode here if I want to encode a run.
I say while I haven't hit the end of the buffer, let's just see how
many times I see the starting value.
And I increment my run count right now, when I get to the end here,
now I know how long my run is and I could say, all right,
This includes the Run of zero.
So basically my run, I know my run has to be at least one, right?
In fact, I could just do this, right?
I could just say, hey, I know the first time it's going to be equal,
right?
I mean, duh, you know, and so all I really want to know.
Here is, how long, you know, how many can I go beyond just the one and
so then what I could do here is say like, okay, let's see what
happens.
Whenever
Is greater.
Then some value will think about that what that should be in a second
but let's say as long as it's greater than 1 will just encode every
run.
Let's say as long as the run is greater than one.
Then I want to you know encode a run otherwise I want to encode
literals right.
Okay, so let's think about what has to happen here, right?
Because we're going to start, we're going to kind of work this Loop
through a little bit.
So if I was going to encode a run,
Or if I was going to encode literals, I kind of have a little bit of a
problem here.
I need to know a little bit more about what I need to know a little
bit more about how I'm going to actually buffer these literals up
because if you think about it, if I encode a run, well, I could just
output a run right here, I'd say here's the run value, which I know.
And here is the value that I'm trying to encode, which I also know, no
problem, but if I'm trying to encode, literals, I need to
Buffer them up, right?
Because I need to like know that I'm putting literals into the stream
here.
So what I need to do if I'm encoding, literals is I need like a
buffer, I need something that's like my literals buffer, right?
And my literals buffer needs to have room to store as many literals.
As I might total, you know, be able to store
something like this.
Right?
Because the number of literals, that I might have is however many I
might have, and I might be able to store like 255.
Literals are coming.
I need to be able to write 205 literals into my buffer here, right?
So I need to have something like
That's where I just have.
Okay.
Here's the literal count and here's the buffer for the literals,
right?
And I could end up this.
Okay, so if I want to do something like that, then it's like, okay if
I wanted to encode a literal then all I would do is say all right when
I want to encode a literal I would say hey let's go ahead and put that
into the literal buffer.
Otherwise, I need to encode a run.
Right.
And we'll see how I have to go to run in a second.
All right, so that's really all we have to do there and I guess I need
another thing here.
Seems like out at
Maybe outsize.
Okay, so if I need to do this now, I need to start acting about the
encoding.
I need to Define how I'm going to encode this, right?
And for starters, let's use the simple encoding that I was talking
about before.
So let's pop over the decompressor for a second and just write it
because that will be the definition of how our output stream works.
Right?
And so what I'll do there is just say, okay, I know that I'm going to
continue going, see you
At zero.
As long as I haven't consumed into the entirety of the input.
I'm going to keep going, right?
So then all I need to do is say, all right, I want to take a look at
the value that comes in, whatever that value is.
So I'm going to say that the thing coming in is the literal count
Let's say so I'm going to read a value.
That's how many new b 1 code.
I'm going to go ahead and run that literal countdown.
I'm going to say for every literal that I was supposed to do.
I'm going to put something into the output stream.
So this is the copy right for every literal.
I'm going to copy from the input stream into the output screen.
Then I'm going to read a replication count.
Right?
And then I also need a replication value.
Write the value meant to replicate and then again, just going to run
that down.
Okay.
And there's an early to compressor, right?
That's that's the stupidest possible.
Early decompressor, could have all we're doing right.
Is in fact, I can even make this even simpler.
We don't even need in at at all right.
I could just say that the the end of the input is just the start of
the input, plus the size you told me and then I can just say keep
reading until in, you know, in as long as in
In is less than in end then we're still reading.
Right?
And assuming this was a well form stream, we're not really doing.
anything, we're not being, you know,
We're not being robust here.
So this is easy code to crash certainly by feeding it that data.
But you know, let's just start anyway for our own purposes at the end
that we actually consumed the right amount of input, right?
But there is our decompressor, right?
Very very simple read.
In how many things to copy copy that many read in how many things to
replicate replicate and then if we haven't hit the end of the data,
keep going.
Right.
Okay so off we go.
So every time we get a sort of a run or anything like this or literals
or anything like that, we always have to encode a pair, right?
So we're always in coding, a pair of literals and we're always
encoding some number of Liberty literals and some number of cop of
replications, right?
That's just how we've defined this and I'm not even saying that's a
good way to do it.
Right?
I'm not saying this is a good are LED compressor.
I'm just saying here's a gnarly compressor, right?
Because another way to do it would be to have these be B coated.
So, like, for example, we use one bit in the, in this value to say,
whether it's a run or a copy or whatever, right?
We're not gonna do that.
So, what we do is we say, all right values, come in.
We see how many there are.
If what we're on is a run.
Then we need to encode the Run.
Otherwise, we just buffer the literals, right?
And so, all I'm going to do here is actually have this be the encode
flush.
Basically, I'm just is going to be the thing that actually does the
encoding.
So what I need to do is I need to match whatever I was doing in this
output, right?
So I need to do a thing that basically says, alright, the output
Is going to literally be exactly this thing.
So, I need to
Maybe I'll do a little index.
I need to go over my buffer and I need to Output it, right?
So what I would do is I'd say let's output the literal account,
however, many literal literals there were and then I need to
I'll put the literals, I know once I've done that, my literal count
will be 0 because there's nothing left in the buffer, and then I need
to Output my run.
So then I say, okay, whatever the Run length is, is the run.
And the starting value, I know, is whatever the starting value is
right here, right?
Right.
So that's it.
That's all I have to do there and then encoding literals, I just kind
of go ahead.
Little scent.
Now there's one more thing we have to deal with here but yeah that's
basically the way it goes.
Okay, so let's go ahead and deal with are at handling here are at
handling like kind of.
As we're going through our in buffer, basically, when we look at these
runs
When we're kind of looking at how how far we've gone, run wise, all we
want to do there is say, well, okay, if we encoded a run, then we
obviously moved that far in the input.
If we encoded a literal, we only moved one right.
Does that make sense?
So we want to kind of Advance the input differently depending on which
one we did here.
Okay, so there's one more thing we have to take care of here and that
is that we don't have unlimited size, right?
When we go tear or two,
Encode a literal.
We can only actually encode a literal if there's room left in the
literal buffer.
So when we're going to encode a run,
really, what we mean here is, we need to out, we need to flush the
literal buffer.
Both in the case, where we want to encode a run.
And in the case, we have no space left even if there is no run, right?
So, what we want to do here is say more like, well, if the run is
greater than whatever, our run length value is or the literal count is
equal to the max literal count, because we couldn't put a single more,
one more, we couldn't fit anymore in the buffer, we have to flush,
then off again.
Hopefully, that makes some sense.
I'll cannot go over it one more time in case it doesn't.
But anyway,
So, in this case, again, we have to Output the little cap.
What we want to do here is probably a cert if the literal counts, I
guess we could say.
Like, literal count, eight equals, uh, literal count and then just
assert that literal count, eight equals literal count, like meaning
guarantee that we can fit it in the space.
We're actually trying to fit it, right.
We go and then the same thing would be true for the Run length, right?
Same thing here.
Drooping around length.
Run 8, equals U 8.
Run assert, run eight.
Let's run.
Right.
I guess it's just a buffer.
Literals
All right, so last thing we have to do again.
So this this part right here is designed to make sure that hey, we can
only store a value from 0 to 255 for how many literals are, so we
can't go above that number and similarly, exact.
Same thing is true for a run, so if you take a look at what happens
here, we've got this run is less than in sighs - at that's assuming we
can get to the end of the buffer, but we can't necessarily get to the
in the buffer because we could only encode a run of 255 at maximum.
So we can, we can adjust this value.
I'm going to be lazy and not even bother adjusting that value.
I'm just going to say and the run is less than Max run count, right?
Which again, is exactly the same Max, run, count to five and on this
is a less than or equal to their, right?
Because we could actually encode 255.
So then we'll come in here and just undef those two next one.
Okay, so there you go.
And that's just again to
Make it so that we don't end up with a value.
That's too big for us, right?
So hey yeah, I did I type that in extremely quickly.
Yes, I did.
So, you know probably got some bugs in there somewhere but let's just
go ahead and sort of take a look at how that's working in the
debugger.
So I'm going to open up Ms, Dev on simple compressor, .exe.
Give it a second because as we know Visual Studio takes many years to
load, it has to do all kinds of wonderful things.
I'm sure they're really important.
So let's go ahead and open up the properties for simple compressor.
Here, the X computer the executable, we need to pass it.
That information that we were passing it before, right?
We need to give it a valid compression rule, whereas that not
decompress.
I want compress, there we go.
Okay.
And so paste those in there.
So you want to pass compress and these two values, we want to be in
the bill directory.
That's where we were doing this.
So that's fine too.
So let's go ahead and step into this, right.
Let's go ahead and see how this works.
So it's exactly all this stuff is kind of wrote.
You've seen it many times before so we're going to go through.
We say, okay, what's the command the command in this case is compress,
right?
So let's load everything in.
I didn't mean to go that far.
Don't mean to go that far.
Stop meant to jump in here.
So here we go.
We start out in the compressor.
And now we have to go ahead and it looks like we had a bug there.
So I know we're going to get to debug this thing, but I just want to
kind of Step through it.
First wants to kind of see how we were doing with it, right?
Yeah, this one could actually also be done exactly the same way to
decompress with the fact.
I might go ahead and just do that because might as well have them look
a little bit more symmetric.
That's basically like this sort of thing.
So that's basically just again like we just always want to read from
that particular location.
So in this case, we can sort of, we can take our rats there and we can
just use just the actual
Station without having to do this, right?
So we can basically just say like, all right, the starting value is
always going to be, you know, wherever we are within, right?
So this is in 0, and then here, we're just going to be looking ahead,
run, you know, run numbers of things.
And and then when we actually increment will just increment the actual
in pointer, right?
So that seems reasonable
Okay.
And so then again this also becomes just a subtraction where it's
like, hey make sure we're not looking at the end of the buffer.
What are you complaining about, which one are you complaining about
signed, unsigned mismatch, okay, is that because size?
T is unsigned.
I guess it's okay because we know these things should never invert.
But yes, all right, so let's go ahead and go in here.
So here we go.
And let's just take a look at where we are in value.
So, here's some information.
So it just so happens that the first bite happens to be replicated,
right?
Because HAF, that's actually the data in our HHA file.
Remember, that was, I guess, what was actually there.
And then there were some zeros.
Let's take a look in memory actually, so we can actually see what this
is.
There you go.
So you can see the HF and then there's some zeros and other
information.
This is the
Stuff for actually compressing.
So hey it looks like the first thing.
There is actually a run count of two.
Now we break out of here because the next thing is an A so we could we
could encode the H as a run of 2 but we cant encode the a as a run so
that would have to switch to a literal, right?
Alright, so off we go, we look in here and right now we're in coding
runs of any length, right just as a test and we'll talk about that
later.
But you know, if you think about it, a run of too long might not be
worth.
With encoding because it requires a flush of the literal buffer.
And you didn't save any space because you had to encode the count for
the run as well.
So, you know that number might be more like for, let's say to actually
talk about more optimal encoding.
But anyway, ignoring that for a second, here we come in.
We take a look at the literal count,
And we see that it's zero.
So we store that 0 as the output right and then we don't actually
encode any literals because hey there was nothing in the buffer.
We then say hey there's a run count of two so we output that run count
of 2 and then we output the value.
We're actually trying to do, which is the H we then move forward by
two things in the input because we consume those.
So, now we're on the, the AF, right?
And then we go back to the beginning.
Again, in this case, there's no run.
It's just an A, so,
we buffer up the A and we say in our literal buffer and we can see
that getting an extra thing here you can see the a there it adds that
a to the literal buffer and
Got a literal count of one.
Now.
Right?
We advance the input by one because now we've consumed that literal
and we start again right there, we buffer another one and and we just
keep going.
Now there's some zeros right there was a bunch of zeros.
40's we say oh okay let's take a look at the literal Count, Their the
literal count.
In this case is 4.
So
Wait.
Oh no.
Oh wait.
No, that's fine.
That's a literal count.
Never mind.
I was like what's going on now?
The little count, that's fine.
So we encode the to then we encode the two literals, right?
There's the first one, there's the second one, and then we reset the
little counter 0, so that's what we want.
We then look at the run count, which is for we encode that run count
of four and we would encode the starting value.
Of 0, right?
Because it's just a 0 that were copied.
We then Advance the input to skip all the zeros and we get to the next
thing and off we go.
Right?
So now let's see where we were getting the problem.
We hit an assertion, I'm assuming it's this one, but it could be
another one of these in here.
Let's see which one it is.
We provided to bug.
What is this?
Where are we in the call stack?
Early compress
So it looks like we ended up with a run value of 256 so oh, that's
good.
Yeah, that was a mistake.
That's just a really simple mistake.
So this run count here, you can see, I did a less than or equal to
maximum count and I was dumb, it wasn't letting you go because we're
about to increment the value and we can't increment the value once it
hits 255, right?
So that's actually wrong.
That's good.
Thank you mr.
Assertion for catching that for us.
There we go.
Let's try that one more time.
And so here's our output size 0, right?
And our output size we need to actually compute that
Again, this is best done with pointers.
So what we can do here is we can say oh let's just remember where we
start, and we'll just do our output so that the end we can say instead
of like tracking the output size, which we don't want to have to keep
an extra thing around.
Let's just say, okay, we'll take the output size of the output size
will be equal to the out, wherever we were in the output - the out
base.
And then, we'll also assert that the
Is less than or equal to the max that size.
So, we didn't overrun the buffer because that just means we have a
bug, right?
All right.
So let's go ahead and run it.
We ran it.
And that's actually doing our compression.
So here you can see the actual results of the compression, right?
And it looks like, wait, there's no way that could be right.
It couldn't possibly have.
Hold on a second, couldn't possibly have outputted the exact same size
with a totally different compressor.
Could it have?
Are we not using the output size accidentally compressed size, plus 4?
Looks like we are, is that really true?
Let's take a look what happened there.
Compressed size.
How is that?
Okay, am I am I nuts?
I must have done something stupid.
It seems impossible couldn't happen to end up at exactly the same.
That's that's insane.
There's just no way.
This is one of those like hey I'm on stream so I'm not paying close
enough attention.
Kind of things got to be right.
So there's the output size right out - out base.
So let's see here in size out sighs.
So the in size and the outside eyes are like, no, we're closed, right?
They're not even remotely, similar to each other, right?
Okay.
So we're going to return that value.
Right.
Yeah, when I did my forwarding I forgot to actually
Use the value.
Okay, now we're a little bit better there.
All right, so okay.
Now if I actually run this
We have our compressed output.
You can see now that it's much much smaller, right?
It's about a tenth the size so that's great.
And now the question is well did it work?
Right.
And so let me delete test one that out here.
So there's our HHA again it's one point five mags, we went down 2.2
mags, little less than so that's great.
But one point.
Well, you can see the numbers yourself.
I wouldn't
Right to English, translate them.
So if we go ahead and write simple compressor, and we do decompress,
right?
Then I take my test one that SCP and my test one doubt.
And now it does the decompression and oh, and good.
And my decompressor doesn't work at all.
So that's always good.
So maybe now's a good time to switch over to actually to bug the
decompressor.
Hold on for a second.
So let me go ahead and switch to the decompressor.
So let's do decompress test one that is CP to test one.
Got out.
There we go, right.
Let's step in there and let's go ahead and take a look here.
So we step over to the file size with a look at the output buffer
size.
That's not right at all.
Ah,
That's another bug.
You can always find bugs when you step through your code.
So I said I was going to store the output size in here but I didn't do
that, right?
So I need to store.
This is I stored how big the file was when we don't need to store how
big the file was.
We already know how big the file was.
I need to store how big the original file was, so that's supposed to
look.
Oh, sorry about that.
I need to store this piece of information.
I need to store how big we're going to produce, not how big we ended
up being.
So that's just a compressor bug or rather, the wrapper for the
compressor was just wrong.
All right, so let's try a simple compressor.
Test one that ha to test the CP will do compress.
There we go, and then we'll do simple.
Presser decompress test one that is CP test1 dot out and we're still
not good.
Okay, let's try this one more time out, buffer size.
Now the app, buffer size weight, that's still wrong.
Did I did I not come?
We compile that
what just happened?
Well, I thought we wrote to the out buffer.
Oh god, wow.
How many you know the type of situation here is is interesting.
Supposed to be file size.
I need to pay closer attention here.
Let's try this one more time.
Okay, so I'm going to step in here and see what actually happened.
Okay, so we go ahead and we do our compressor, we produce the
compressed size which is this, we have the in file file size which is
that and I'm trying to write to the output buffer which is what I'm
going to Output here.
Is my output buffer.
Right.
And let's just see what the size is that we actually stuck in there.
So there's what's in the output buffer right now?
Which I believe it should just be garbage, right?
Because we didn't actually write anything to it, yet.
We right in there and there's our actual value, 1.5 MB, which is what
we want.
And we basically say that the output
Is what, you know what we used plus the four byte header bit there and
then we say the output buffer is the is the out buffer, right?
So here we come into final output buffer and we're going to write this
thing.
So we should be able to verify that the exact same thing as in there.
So here's final output buffer, right there it is and then we go ahead
and do our F, right?
I should I should have probably check that return value but it didn't.
So that's fine.
We're get.
You can see.
We actually did return it there.
Or x to the F right.
Looks like it's seated.
And so, then we're done, right?
And that should have written to our our output file, right?
Then if I step in here for the
The decompress.
Right?
Which I should be able to do.
Let's go ahead and, you know, I should have a decompressed.
I should have something that does decompression and compression so I
don't have to keep doing it.
I have to type keep typing these things in
but,
So, we do, if I step into the decompress and now I do like all right,
if anybody can press the, the content should show me here and there it
is.
All right, so I don't know why that was working before.
I guess I must not have actually compiled or something like this, but
I must not have actually run it properly, but, alright, so there we
go.
And now our decompressor works just fine.
That we actually pass it.
The correct size and then we have our output buffer and we write it,
okay?
All right so don't know what I did wrong there but
It's something wrong in terms of running the program, not in, not the
program itself.
And so, let's see what we got.
So here's our test 10th, a, here's our test of one dot out and now I
should be able to do our wind if no.
I don't know why I can't run wind, if it's not in the path, I guess.
So, let's just take a look at where it actually is, okay.
So it's in
This longest path here.
There we go.
So let me go ahead and copy that and then I will go ahead and paste
it.
And here.
And so now I should be able to do test one, two, Aha and test1.ogv out
and see if the same, right?
And it looks like
The fact that it was loaded would suggest that it wasn't the same, but
let's see.
Oh no, they are identical, right?
Okay.
Hey, so congratulations.
We have a compressor now, right?
It's not a very good compressor, but you can see it gets a lot of
compression on that file.
Let's see how it does with the whole HHA, right?
So, that's our simple compressor.
Let's say we went over and copied out of handmade hero.
The intro art.
That ha.
So that's a much bigger file right into our th a, that's about half a
gigabyte.
And so let's do simple compressor.
Compress intro, art HHA, intro art SCP, right?
And this, you know, probably in, you know, if we were actually trying
to make something real, we'd want to print out a little, like percent
on indicator, but there we go.
So we take a look at it and we see like, okay, the intro art, even
with are really, you know, are super simple, very basic, not
particularly distinct compressor.
You can see the intro, art, aha intro art, SCP intro, artists,
SCP got much better.
We saved you know entire hundred what hundred and forty megabytes
there, right?
A hundred and forty megabytes just by rle compressing this thing right
which is you know extremely stupid.
We didn't even do anything really to make our Ally compressor, be
particularly well tuned in any way but hey, that's really great,
right?
So, 100 extra MB, awesome.
And we could probably do much better than this, like I said, by doing
something better.
So maybe tomorrow, I'll show you how to do l z which would should
again save us even more space but you know, it it's still not really.
The kind of thing we would necessarily use on this but all right, so
Let's go ahead and go to the Q&A and like I said, this is just that's
like the dumbest possible compressor we could make right.
It's like it's it's not we have done nothing right?
But it just so happens that this data that we have here is very very
easy to compress because hey it had a lots of empty space right?
Like why is this compressor what?
You know I say it's a bad compressor but you see look at how much it
compresses file.
Well keep in mind.
That's because this file probably had hardly anything in it of
consequence, right?
So, you know, it's a bad compressor because you take a look at
Where was that?
Test 19th.
A let's see what happens if a real compressor comes in here, right?
And we add it to 7z and you can see like okay you know 7-Zip took our
output and it like made it twice it.
Then did another 2x on top of that, right?
So we'd only took out the low-hanging fruit but you can still do a lot
better and similarly on anything that wasn't so regular 7-Zip would
crush us, right?
Like we're only happening to benefit here and
You know what, we could probably demonstrate that because here's our
output file.
I bet.
If we compress, even this one with 7-Zip, it'll probably crush us.
Right?
So here we go.
Well let 7-Zip do it here and we'll see how big 7-Zip manage this to
get this file with the same thing.
And it'll it should just annihilate us, right?
It should just absolutely trance us.
Or it's questions here.
Midlow says, awesome stuff.
I hadn't been making the distinction between literals and runs in my
thing.
My test stuff has just been zeros and ones mine.
So I was just storing the first token and then the counter values.
Ah, okay, yeah.
So that's that's an interesting point.
So yeah, basically, this kind of our Li is the kind that I grew up
with again.
So that's why I did it first.
But yeah.
Either we could do it is just or account, and then a value account and
in value, and accountant value.
And in that case, your literal, your literals become, just a one.
And then the value, a 1 and then a value of 1 and the value.
The problem with that is a lot of times you have a group of values
that you want that are all different and you keep inserting all these
ones you like double the size of that, right?
So what this allows you to do is kind of take advantage of the fact
that typically, if you see new values that aren't runs, they
Be a bunch together, right?
And so that just, it just helps, it tends to be a little bit better.
Like I said, the other ways you can do this are you could have a one
bit in the Run encoding says whether it's literals or regular, so then
you can only do 127 of them right?
You divide your number in half and then but but you can say for each
one which kind it is, literals are runs.
Oh Magic.
603 what I was saying is tomorrow.
I will show you how to do simple l z instead of
Instead of rle.
So just just a different type of compression.
So, did 7-Zip finished yet.
So take a look here, you can see, here's the aha, that's our data file
for the intro cutscenes.
Here's the SCP file, which is what we did with our.
This is a gnarly encoded version, right?
And here is intro, art dot 7-Zip, intro art dot 7-Zip.
Look at how much smaller that is right, then hours.
You know what I'm saying?
It's like it's way better.
Better.
It's only a team eggs, whereas we're
20 Meg's from an original of foreign 262 Meg's, right?
So 7-Zip just absolutely crushed us.
Right?
So, you know, I just wanted to make that point because it made it look
test one that ha has so much giant blocks of zeros, and it probably
that it made our compressor.
Look are bad, compressor.
Look a lot better than it should have.
This looks amazing.
When you look at it, you're like, oh my God and 7-Zip.
Can only SS from there.
It's like, no, no.
Most data 7-Zip is way better than double, right?
What we would do with in our Ellie
so,
Tt b, JM, R, Hardware, image, D compressors.
Still a thing.
So I guess, I'm not sure.
I understand.
What you're asking though?
I guess I don't understand the question.
So the first thing I'll say is most 3D games anyway,
In 2D games may not for various reasons.
But for most 3D games because you're using Textures in a way that
tends to end up being like filtered and it's with lots of shaders
layered on top of it and all this stuff you tend to not need lossless
compression.
You can be a little bit lossy.
So most games nowadays that are in 3D and some that are into D,
depending on, again, the circumstances do use very simple texture
compression that is implemented in the hardware, which is essentially
a way of encoding, usually 4 by 4 pixel blocks, but that's not the
only kind but usually including 4 by 4 pixel blocks, by encoding them.
As something along the lines of let's say,
Two base colors.
And then each pixel just says somewhere between one and the other base
colors in like increments of like 25% or something like this, those
sorts of things.
And hey, if the value can't be encoded that way, then it just is
wrong.
It's lossy, it's totally lossy.
You're absolutely in no way guaranteed to get anything close to the
original image back.
But it's just like, you know, it's an approximation, right?
It's a way of storing taking.
It's a way of putting textures into a smaller space that is reliably.
Codable on a GPU that tends to have not to objection will artifacts
when the textures are being used in 3D for.
multiple Shooters layering, and that sort of stuff, there's enough
other things on top of that, you don't tend to notice the artifacts,
Right.
So if that's what you mean by Harvard Hardware, image D compressors
then.
Yes, if what you're talking about is more like jpeg or something like
this, with a discrete cosine, transform and stuff like that, then the
answer is more like, yes, and no.
Games.
Generally speaking aren't doing anything like that.
Games aren't speaking aren't compressing their textures with like DCT
that gets decompress and Hardware something like that.
That's not really a thing.
And the reason that that's not really a thing is because games,
typically don't care.
So much about how much space textures take up in main memory, they
tear care to.
They tend to care more about how
How much they take up on graphics card memory and since the graphics
card needs the textures to not be DCT encoded in order to use them,
you tend to not care, right?
So you tend to have to store the textures on the card in the format,
the card can read, which it can't do DCT in real time yet.
Meaning in at the speed, it needs to do it to texture from that.
Now I guess I don't know how true that really is because I don't know
if there's maybe some cards that are made of that sort of thing now.
But
Uno in general.
So, you know, if you were storing, those as 8x8 DCT blocks or
something like that, in main memory, you could just have the DCT done
by the CPU in the background before uploading the textures or stuff
like that.
Stuff like that might be happening.
But typically speaking, you don't store, you don't send down the
things as DCT and then have the hardware.
Do the undies ET typically?
Again, not to say you couldn't write, it may be that a game at some
point, and I don't know, I'm not up to date on what, you know, maybe
Battlefield one or some of, you know, Advanced engines these days are
doing.
But you could imagine implementing something like a DCT with a compute
Shader and then having doing your uploads in, like something like a
JPEG format and having the card, do the undie CT into the dxt format.
But that involves all sorts of other things and blah, blah, blah,
blah, blah, blah, right.
So there's a bunch of things you could imagine doing there, which one
is he?
Pilar in aren't doing, I'm not comfortable with saying, so that's the
know, part of the answer.
The, yes, part of the answer is for a bunch of stuff like video, where
you're just talking about one thing that's being round-trip, decoded
or encoded.
So like mpeg-4,
Or thing is like this, there still is a bunch of stuff in hardware for
that.
Oftentimes right?
So certain parts of the
The decompress for things like the mpeg-4 like you know the DCT or the
mo comp or whatever.
Depending whether you're compressing or decompressing, blah, blah,
blah, that sort of thing, maybe being done in hardware for video
depending on again, the circumstances.
And I'm not again up to date on what everyone's doing everywhere.
So I'm not comfortable saying who is and isn't using that and when and
when it isn't being used and blah, blah blah, but it's definitely the
case.
That that sort of thing is still happening in Hardware, depending on
the circumstances.
Has so.
Absolutely.
And so, depending on what you mean by Hardware image decompressor, the
answer is yes or no to varying degrees and it depends on who you're
talking about.
And so on so forth but keep in mind that basically there's a wide
spectrum there and I think pretty much everywhere on the Spectrum
there's probably someone somewhere doing something right and you know
To, to what extent that fits, what you were mentally thinking of when
you said, Hardware image decompressor the answer may be yes or no.
Right?
Because there's different.
You know, when someone says that they may be thinking of something
more or less Advanced or more and less less complex, or you know
what's happening there.
So
I don't know if anything, that was it for our questions, right?
Alright, I think that's it for questions.
So I'm going to go ahead and conclude
Or try to.
Okay, there we go.
All right, thank you, everyone for joining me for another episode of
handmade here.
It's been a pleasure coding with you.
As always, if you would like to follow along with the series at home,
you can always pre-order the game on handmade here at org and it comes
to the source code.
So you can follow along and play around with it.
We also have Forum site.
Go to ask question a patreon page.
You can go to file export the video series, a schedule bot, which on
the moment is needs to be upgraded because it used to be weekday.
Other weekend stream.
So soon, that will be back to telling you what the schedule is.
But at the moment, it's a little bit, not upgraded yet.
And we have a past episodes guide, you can use to catch up on older
episodes that you may have missed.
That's about it for today.
I will be back tomorrow and I'll just show you how to put an LZ
compressor in there.
So we'll kind of
Take our little compression framework and we'll just put an LZ
compressor in there and then you can kind of see like, okay, so now
you kind of get the basics of the really simple part of compression.
And then how kind of leave it up to, to you, folks, to figure out how
to do more compression stuff on your own by reading and stuff like
that.
Because I'm not going to go too much into it because like I said, I'm
not a compression person, so I'm kind of the wrong person to teach
anything beyond the very, very basic parts of it.
I really don't feel qualified in sort of
Going down any sort of deeper paths into compression.
So that's about it.
I hope everyone has a great Saturday until tomorrow, take it easy and
I'll see y'all on the internet.
Take it easy, everybody.