Okay, hello everyone, and welcome to handmade hero.
Although today we're actually doing handmade here.
We're doing handmade Ray because this is another test stream
yesterday.
We think everything went fine with our 1080p test stream.
We're not 100% sure those, some people thought there were some pauses
in it but we weren't sure if those were pauses because of the capture
or pauses because of twitch and rather than having to scrub through
the entire video and find out what we wanted to do today, was just go
ahead and actually have people write down what time they get pauses if
they get any pauses.
So we're starting here at 3:15 PST, 316 PST, right around there.
If you could just write down what time and time zone, you saw the
pause.
We can back figure that out.
Look at the video and make sure that it was entirely clear.
And after that, I think we can be relatively certain that we've gotten
everything else working.
So here's one more handmade Ray day today where we will finish, what
we did yesterday.
And hopefully, at the end of this, we will not only have a finished
Cindy, Ray Tracer, that's ready to have some more
Of light propagation algorithm is put into it for example and we will
also know that our video is working or not working definitively.
One way or the other.
So if everyone could help me with that, I'd really appreciate it and
off we go.
So if you remember where we left off yesterday, we had done the work,
which is the majority of the sort of structural work to make sure that
are handmade.
Oops, I want to go to the river a project that we go to make sure that
our handmade re-program was compiling in.
Essentially a structure that admitted itself to Cindy optimization the
way we did.
This was when we were casting raise per pixel, what we did is we
changed all of our variables to things that were could be custom
structures that could be cleared wide.
And then we took any if statements that we had in the code because
week since we're doing multiple things at a time, we can't actually
ever execute a real branch.
And what we did is we turn this into a conditional assignments.
So that we would only ever modify our state variables.
If we actually got hits in the correct Lanes, those Lanes of the state
variables would be the ones that get modified, and you can see that
we've got it working here.
And this is using no actual Cindy.
This is just using the SIM dstyle code, which can be, which could be
implanted, 70, but currently turned.
So that it's still using scalar.
You can see here is we have a lane with
Find the limit is defined as 1, and then we've got some pound gifts
here that are going to put in different pieces of code, depending on
whether we want assumed Elaine with of Oneness, in dealing, with the
four or simulations of a simulated.
If the one is just the neutral running without any actual.
MD stimulating with the four is SSE instructions.
Those are instructions that can do for floats.
In a single vector and single operation.
And then we've got eight wide which is the we didn't put a 16 wide in
here because I don't have a machine that can do 16 wide 16.
Why does avx-512 this machine can do 8 wide which is a v x 2 and so on
I believe that's all going to work on the core i7 just fine so we can
actually do 1/8 wide as well.
We just can't do a 16 wide because that's avx-512 it's only available
on zeon's and core I nines and apparently Koreans can't
Run it anyway.
So you're better off, just still using 8 wide on those.
It sounds like so, but in the future, in the future, in a few years,
for example, when AMD start shipping it, and when Intel gets it,
working better on the desktop cores, then we all you could imagine
upgrading this program quite simply to have a lane width of 16 and
that would be the goal, right?
So that's all we're really doing here.
All right, this is my little coffee.
I made some espresso this morning.
Alright so here we go.
We're going to ignore the lane with the vase for now or we're just
going to go straight to the Lane with the for and we're just going to
implement it directly.
There's not going to be a lot of magic to it.
Pretty much everything you need to know you seen on handmade hero.
So here you can kind of see us doing a bunch of operations on things
that are lean and before these were defined as scalar, right?
When we do Lane width equals 1, these are all scalars.
So it
An ex or that scalar, it does a shift with scalar Etc.
We need to now change these into things that do the equivalent
operations but that do them to all of the lanes.
And so the way we're going to do that again is to use as I always say.
There's only a few features of C++ that I actually use an operator
overloading is one of them, we're going to use operator overloading to
make it so that you can write this, it equation in a nice concise easy
to read form, like it is right now that everyone could understand, but
such that it can work on Lanes or not, depending on which way that
Pound Define and goes.
And so you can see us starting out with this here.
What we need to do is we need to grab this equation, we need to bring
it over into our lane definition here, where we've got our four wide
Ops and we need to start taking a look at which ones we have so you
can see here.
We've got two of them, right?
We've got an Annex or equals and we have a left shift at.
These are both ones that we can Define ourselves.
So if we have a lane youth or YouTube,
That we want to do our shift to we can just take in whatever the
actual Lane is that we're going to do and then we take in an immediate
here right?
Which is the shift amount, right?
And I can put a u-32 in here, actually, let me go ahead and switch
this over to the other side.
I can put a u-32.
Actually because shifts are not allowed to be - at least in x64.
As far as I remember, you always have to shift by an immediate and
that immediate have to be positive.
So if you wanted to shift the other direction, you have to specify a
positive shift in the other direction, not a negative shift in this
Direction.
That's just the way this chip is defined to work and how its
instructions work.
So we would be looking at an operator.
That looks something like this.
Where we now need to perform this shift amount on this Lane variable
and you can see that we have this Lane variable here is designed such
that.
It has an M 128, i in it.
And what we need to do is produce a result here, right?
A result one of these.
So we can say that the result value is going to equal the input value
and, you know, something is going to happen here, but we don't know
what.
So, what we need to do again, is now start.
As you remember Pope,
From handmade here.
Up start.
Going back to our old friend, the Intel intrinsics guide.
Because these men monix, you may remember.
Some, like, I happen to remember the one for this.
Like, I remember SLI and srl, I and these sorts of things, but if you
don't happen to remember, that's okay.
You don't need to remember any of these.
The Intel in terms of God is like a very good piece of documentation
until I don't know who was responsible for this but they did a very
good job on it.
So whoever put this up, thank you very much and until I should send
Kim.
After a note saying, whoever put this up was a very good person and
hopefully they got a promotion.
So anyway, what you want to do on this intentions, got again, if you
have if you don't remember from handmade Heroes, you've got the
Technologies on the side, these Technologies, they correspond to
revisions of the instruction set for x86 and x64.
And what we tend to Target is right in this area here, you could
probably these days go all the way up to here even, but you probably,
We wouldn't go past that.
So when you start to require things like a VX or avx2 or heaven
forbid, avx-512, you start to really limit the number of CPUs that
something can be run on.
That's out in the wild.
Anything that's MX2 sse2.
Pretty much anything.
You're going to ship to a game.
A gamer audience, which is what we focus on and made here are right
people who play games on a PC or are using a console like a
PlayStation 4 or an Xbox One.
This is exactly what they've got in there, right?
It's these, contests, these instructions.
Once you go up here, you're still targeting any modern machine.
Once you go up here, SSE 4.2 is certainly like an Xbox One or a pay
station for have basically, you know, support for this kind of
struction set, just fine.
But you start to limit the number of PCS, there are some older PCS
that won't have these instructions in them, so you're making a little
bit more limited.
Still not that much, you're talking with 10 20 % of PCS or not.
You out there that?
Probably playing games on once you get up into here.
It's nice here, right?
A lot of people who might play your games or might use your ray
Tracer.
In this case, they might not have these.
So we're going to stay away from these in the lane for stuff.
I think I'm going to stick have the lane for Stuff.
Honestly, I'm just going to pick sse2 is the break point there.
The reason for that is because we're going to do a lane 8 version the
lane eight versions going to be the really, you know, the, the 8 wide
one that will correct x 2.
So I think we can safely say
Say look if you're using the link for version, that's sort of the more
Legacy path, that's only going to go up to us to see, to something to
run on, just about any machine that still kicking, and then the avx2
path, that does the the 8 wide.
There's the one that will use all the instructions we've got at the
moment and then some day in the future, we can even do the avx-512 on
which would be yet.
Another sort of bleeding edge 1.
If I had a z on machine, we could even do that now.
But I'm, you know, I don't
Okay.
So that's what we're doing here and let me just go ahead and sort of
show you how this works.
So I want to be able to shift this, you can actually just search for
shift and it actually finds it in the description which is really
nice.
So if you didn't know what these instructions were going to be, you
can start to see what they all are.
We've got an M1 28i and we want to shift it by account SLL, right?
And if you didn't know what these where you could just look in here.
And it says you what it says to you, what it's going to be
So, that's actually pretty easy, but just, I'll explain them here.
These slls are a, it's a so on these are shift left, logical shift,
right?
Logical and shift, right arithmetic.
And the reason that you have these sort of different
for lack of a better term mnemonics for them is the shifting left is
an unambiguous operation when you shift something left.
There's only one thing that could possibly be meant by that, and that
is to fill the other side with zeros really.
There's no other possible thing.
You might mean, however, when you shift, right?
You're shifting down the B towards the lower end, right?
You're shifting.
Hi B towards low bits, right?
And if a number is negative,
It's going to be in two's complement which means the high B going to
be set.
If you were trying to emulate a mathematical operation by this shift.
For example, if you are trying to divide by a power of 2, you would
want to keep the - so what shift writes often have is they have a
arithmetic and a logical version.
The lot, The Logical version just moves the bits and put 0 in the end.
So that would fill the top of zeros, the arithmetic version shifts.
And
Puts ones in the end and that keeps the sign of the value as it shifts
across, right?
We don't have any such concerns here.
We are talking about a purely logical operation and this is on you 32.
So
Unsigned values.
So for us, we don't care about that distinction but just so, you know,
that's what's going on there.
So we need to do two different kinds, there's our shift left, I
believe we need to shift right as well.
That's going to come up in a second here because there it is.
So we really have two of these, right.
We've got we've got two of these so we have to do a shift left in a
shift, right?
And in this case, what we want to do here is use those intrinsic.
So here's the one that actually the I stands for immediate, so you can
see
Here, this takes a parameter for the count.
This takes the immediate, the epi32 is the 32-bit value, sort of
moniker.
So it knows you're shifting four lanes of 32 bits, right?
The epi16 would be eight Lanes of, of, of 16 bits.
So, here is that intrinsic you want?
It's MMS lli.
Right?
Epi32.
And that shift left logical immediate here is the value.
We're shifting by which is the value were shifting which is a.
And here is the amount we're shifting by which is the shift there and
here's that immediate that's being taken.
Now it's taking a sign to mediate even though assigned immediate
doesn't actually work as far as I know.
So I think I don't know why they just decided to make it an instead of
an unsigned that was just their choice.
I couldn't tell you why.
But anyway, that's all that's happening there.
And the same exact thing will work here.
So very, very simple.
It's just rough shift, right?
Logical immediate.
And again, you don't even have to look that up because now, you know,
how those mnemonics work, you can just know, oh, right?
It's going to be shift, right?
Logical immediate, and off you go and epi32.
Again is saying, for 32-bit Lanes of of integers, so that's all we
really need to do to implement those operator X or equals.
We're going to need something else for it.
That's the xor.
And so we need something.
Here, that will actually do an xor.
And you can see here, there's a little it's a little bit different and
you may be wondering why it's a little bit different.
Again, if you don't remember, the hand of my hero episodes, this might
be throwing you for a little bit of a loop here.
What's going on?
We were doing these.
Epi instructions for the 32-bit Lanes.
We're still trying to operate on 32-bit Lanes, if you want to do next
or equals and yet we've sort of got this weird.
This this wonky situation here, where there is no epi32.
There's only an si128, what's going on with that?
Well, the
And for that is that unlike most operations that happen inside these
Lanes in the processor and xor is bitwise.
So, you know, adds subtracts, divides, multiplies shifts, all of these
operations, they deal with more than one bit, right?
A shift takes a bunch of bits and moves them to a whole nother set.
So, you know, the bit in Lane 0 moves to the bit in Lane 3 or
something like this, right?
I should say Lane.
The b in slot 0 in B 0 moves to B 3.
Right.
Whatever the value is.
And all of those have to be clamped to the lanes, right?
They have to be clamped to the area in which the lane is supposed to
operate, because if you were trying to shift a 32-bit value that's
packed in for, you know, for why'd you don't want one of the four wide
Lanes shifting into the other Lane, right?
You don't want that cross-contamination.
So, you need to tell the processor by which instruction, you choose,
you know, how to gasket up, is it 8:16 wide things and that's how
we're, you know, clipping it.
Is it 4:30 to why things?
Is it to 64y things, but in bitwise operations xor, and or those sorts
of things not, it's just doing an operation to every bit.
So, the result would be the same.
Whether you had 8-bit Lane, 16-bit lengths, 32-bit Lane 64-bit lanes,
128-bit lanes, 256-bit lanes, 512-bit lanes.
So basically, when you operate on a register type, using one of these
operations.
It's bitwise.
You just operate the whole register at
It doesn't need to know how you're trying to slice it up, because
there is no difference.
It would be the same no matter how you did it, so they just provide a
single instruction to do it.
Now, you may ask, why do they have these other ones here?
And the answer is just because they did the stupid thing of having
types.
Having types in these sorts of things.
The stupid, the processor doesn't have a difference, there's only one
X or, but because they introduced M 128 D, which is the the the 64-bit
ones.
And 128, which is the 32-bit floats and m-28.
I which is the integer registers they had to have different ones.
So you didn't have to keep casting its really frustrating.
So these should have all just been em 128 and they should have just
had an MX or that's how the process actually works.
But, you know, people love their crazy C++ typing going nuts, and
someone told them that was a good idea once when they were in
kindergarten and they never forgot.
So anyway, here we go.
We're going to use this X or here and we need to do an
Operator x r equals my C++ days are long behind me.
I don't ever do them anymore, and so one of the problems that I often
have is I forget exactly how to declare an out of line, operator
equals.
I think you can do it.
I just can't remember.
I may be wrong about that but point being, we may have to make this a
member function.
That's the part that I don't remember whether they allow you to do it
as a non-member function.
Not if I were in charge, of course, you'll be able to but you know, I
don't know.
So anyway, what we need to do here is again
Then exactly that same thing we were doing before.
We're we're just going to take and this time instead of declaring the
result was going to do it in place because again it's an xor equals.
So what we want to do here is to an M xor of the si128, right?
The whole register.
And we're going to take the two values that we got past XR them
together and overwrite the previous value of a with that because it's
an operator equals.
Now I'm going to compare that because I don't remember if you can
actually do that, but I think you can and it does look like you in
fact, can so that's really all
All were doing today.
This is all we have to do is just go through and it's a little bit
laborious.
But as you can see, once you do this, once you could reread could
reuse this as a library, right?
You don't have to write it.
Every time, once you get one of these, that works the way you want and
that you're comfortable with, you can use these lean, F32 Lane, you
three, Tulane v3's anywhere you want.
Just like we use our vectors and stuff like V3 is regularly.
You can reuse these.
So that's one of the nice things about this is.
Yeah, it's kind of some busy work here to write this but
But once you've got one that you like, you don't have to fuss with it
ever again.
If you can find someone's out there on the internet that you like as
well, then you could just use that and be fine as long as you know how
it works and you're happy with it and it's not doing anything
deleterious.
So let's keep going here.
We've got Lane F32 from you 32.
And what that is is you can see is we're going to be taking some
things here where we've got integer values and we want to load them
in, right?
So in this case we want to return Elaine F32 but we're getting a lame,
you 32.
Right?
And we need to convert them.
So here we want an egg-laying, F32 result value, and that result value
is going to have to in
Should I put it?
It's got a load right?
It's got its got to do a conversion, right?
And in this case it's go ahead and and show you another thing to do
here.
In this case, it's kind of note hard to know what to search for a
right?
Like convert.
Maybe would be one of them, but it's kind of a little bit, you know,
maybe you don't know here.
So if you're kind of confused about where these sorts of things would
be the other nice thing about the intrinsic guide, right?
Is you can find them in here and they're categorized under things so
you can actually
Kind of see what's available for various different kinds of things,
right?
So if you just want conversion instructions, you can look at
conversion instructions here.
And the other thing you could do is scan really quickly.
You know that the epi32 is the 32-bit wide integers and PS is 32-bit
wide floats, right pack scalars with that.
Stands for epi32 is packed.
Integer 32.
I don't know what the key is though.
Extended.
What does the E stand for?
You know, I don't really know.
I I don't know.
Yeah, I'm sure it says somewhere.
But I do remember.
So anyway, what we want to do here is we want to convert
We want to be able to convert in between these pack integers and
packed.
We won't be able to convert between packagers and packed floats and
probably vice versa as well.
Right?
Look, we want both of those two things.
So what we're looking for here is something like it's going to return
an M1 28 and take it in 128 I and vice versa, right?
That's just what we want.
So you can see here convert epi32 PS, that takes an integer in and
returns.
Load out, right?
And that's exactly what we wanted here.
And you can see that the name is exactly what respect to the PS.
It returns a floating packed packed scalars, it takes epi32 convert
those to pack scalars, right?
So you can kind of see that the name actually says it as well.
Anyway, and remember this is different than casting.
We're not casting were actually converting here.
We're not, we're not changing the interpretation of the bits into
floating point from integer.
It's got a cast.
Its
Actual conversion.
So it's actually taking integers converting them to floating quick
format and putting them in the register.
So you know, that's important to remember.
Those are two different operations.
There one is take an existing pattern of bits.
Start interpreting it as an integer or certain touring is a quote in
this interaction talk about take the integer and create the float.
That means the same thing as this integer by putting that into the
mantissa and setting the exponent correctly and whatever, right?
So we need to do convert a pi32 PS here.
And by the way, I don't remember most of these intrinsics when I'm not
actively programming, they kind of flush out.
And I look them up like this every time as well.
Sometimes I remember some of them and sometimes, I don't when I'm
actively doing a bunch of work with them, they tend to stick in my
head but after that not so much.
So anyway, that's what we want to do here.
And that will convert this for us.
So we can take our lane u-32 here and convert it to our land F32.
And that's
really all we need to do cannot convert.
What does it say?
Can I cover argument?
One from you 3D to Tulane.
You 32.
Here it is right here.
So this is something that we probably want to be able to do for
shorthand.
You can see here that I've done laying after you to from you 30 and I
just put a constant in here.
We probably want to support that, right?
We want to support that because sometimes we're going to just want to
replicate a constant across all the lanes.
And so that's exactly what I've done here, right?
So here's like a replication value and if I want to create one of
these, there's actually a function specifically for that.
It's called Step 1.
And if I pass it a single value there, you can see in the intrinsics
guide, let me go ahead and do M&M's at once you can see it.
You can see set one epi32 that would take an integer and replicate the
integer across all four lanes set one.
PSL take a floating-point fire up that it again against I all four
lanes.
And so that's all I'm trying to do is take this constant and Loft it
up into four wide.
So there's a copy of it everywhere.
Because again, we have for actual values that are being exercised
here, we want to divide all of them by the same value.
That's a scalar.
And so that's what that's happening here.
Right now, we could do something else.
There, we could just try to do
Thing else if we didn't want to do that kind of upconversion, we could
also make that up conversion, sort of semi implicit.
Let's go ahead and do that.
Now, just for fun.
If we actually just said
Something like this.
Like we would normally do cast this to a floating point value and then
divided we could also just have that are out on.
We don't
What is what?
What are you saying?
Mmm.
Oh whoops.
This has to have the actual casting it.
Yeah, we would just get an error that would tell us that we didn't
have a operator divided.
And so, all we have to do then is produce that operator divided,
right?
So much, like we did the operator shift, here we would just make one
of these for F32 s like so that takes a divided value.
What's up in order to do this again?
All we need to do is have an instruction that's going to do this,
right?
So we it it happens to be that all of the the floating Point numbers
are pretty easy to understand.
They're just mmv operation name and then PS.
So like div Mall add sub, right?
I'll bring them up here just so you can see them.
Here's GPS, right?
Just takes one thing.
Divides by another thing.
And what you can see here is, this has to be a wide value, right?
So, it's a lane F, 32 divided by another Lane F32, right?
But in this case, we know that we don't have one.
That's okay.
Because again, just like we were doing here, we can just do a set 1,
PS to get that value, Loft it up and then do the divide and it's that
simple, right?
Not much to it.
Okay.
Now what's worth noting here is in some cases, these things can come
out to be duplicated.
So if you look at what we've got the set 1, PS in this case is
duplicated in two places, right?
We've got it here and here and this divided you know you can see this
being a thing that would happen again, right?
If we had a divided here we had an A and A B and we wanted to do a
wide divide.
So each lane divided separately, what we would write.
And we probably want to have this, right?
So that we can
Divides, it would do a and b.
Like this, right?
We would divide in the exact way that it's written here, and
everything would be fine.
What that means is.
If you look at this operator here, this operator /.
It's actually very redundant because what we could have written
instead is we could have written a v divided by laying F32 from u-32
divisor.
Right?
Because we know that both of these two things are defined.
We don't actually need to ever know what we're working with here.
Why do I point this out?
Well, I point this out because we could move this down to the bottom.
like so and basically any time we don't have a scalar Lane so
basically if the lane width is not equal to 1,
Right.
So we know we're dealing with some kind of Ops, then we can just put
all of our generic things in here and now that we know that these will
both happen in person went to the
Clean things up here.
It means that we don't have to worry anymore about.
Did I just
that's right.
I was looking for.
I think it means that we don't have to worry about implementing this
divided for each of our lane, with 416 8 and 4.
It can always be just this one function because it's basically using
the two functions that were defined in those Lane with, right.
So that will cut down on the amount of duplication that we have to do
so that we won't have to do as many things.
The same thing can happen with some of these operations here.
Let's say we took this and said, okay, here's the operator xor.
And the operator X or is just going to do the lanyard that you 32
result.
It's going to be result V MMX or si128 a.vb .v return result.
Right?
If I do that, I can then take this operator, this stuff here, right?
Where I'm doing the the xor equals.
I can just change that to be.
Well if I want to do x 4 equals, I know I can just do a VX or BV like
so and
It will go find the right thing that takes this out of the knowledge,
having to have the knowledge of which one is working with.
So again, it can come down here and be kind of generic relative to
those definitions.
Right?
So all of our functions that work that way can happen basically like
this.
You can imagine, it's just doing them all here, right?
So you could do a plus equals, right?
- equals.
X equals.
Divide equals and all of those.
Now, we'll just work.
Same with these guys, right?
We could do and equals or equals, right?
Any of the things that we might need?
I think we've got all the equals is that we've every would use
Divide Ranch, I mean I guess the shifts but we don't really need
those.
so,
Excuse me.
So that's really all there is to that, right?
And similarly, you know, these things can be reversed.
As well.
So if we wanted to put
Something like this in there.
And you know, I maybe should just keep it the correct naming scheme
here.
Right.
So if we want to, we can also flip the orientation.
So we can do a divide in either direction.
By a scalar, like a scalar /, a multi-lane and a multi-lane divided by
a scalar, both of those would work.
And again, we don't have to write any new.
Pearline with.
So we can just Define all of these here once and then they multiply
they sort of distribute over all of those.
Again, same thing with with basically all of our operators, if we want
to do an operator plus the same way, again, it's pretty much the same
thing.
Nothing weird happening here, right?
It's just pluses and then same thing with minuses
Right.
And finally times.
And so all of those things again with just kind of worked as fine and
in this case it looks like these are these are F32 so we can get rid
of this part as well, right?
The if everything's an F32, then it nope.
Sorry, that's not what I meant to do.
We just need to Loft up an F32 instead of a u-32.
So we just need some equivalent of that.
You 32 1?
For loading things that are F instead of instead of you, right?
Yeah.
So that's it, right?
That's really all we need to do and we have both of these
I'm in the wrong set of functions here.
Yeah, sorry, I lost it there for a second.
There it is.
Should I put these into different files?
So in this case right we've got one that casts this way when the cast
that way we just need one here.
That's going to I shouldn't say cast converts one that converts this
way.
Like so, and I think that's everything we really needed.
Now in this case.
Oops, got to take actual F32 there.
In this case, we still have a bunch of operations.
We haven't actually defined though, like, plus and minus, and divide
in those sorts of things.
So, we just need to find those operations.
Just like, we defined everything else.
So, like, we've got our operator / here.
Let me just make one of those for each of our operations for add,
right?
We just have an ad for sub.
We've got a sub and again, you can
Please let me introduce this guy, but they're really just exactly what
you expect floating-point versions of add subtract multiply and
divide, right?
And that's it.
So, let's see what else we got here.
No operator.
Which takes a left hand?
Oh, right?
These all want to stay as their types.
They don't want to actually pull out the V anymore.
That's my bad.
Sorry.
Here we go.
There we go.
And so no particular right-hand Lane F32 there should be.
Now an operator + 4.
That's all we really need there, right?
Yeah.
Again got to get rid of these.
In fact, I could just make this
redirect now,
if these a lot cleaner,
there we go.
And this is one case also, where a lot of people on Hammer hero, ask
me all the time about unit testing.
I don't know why everyone asked me about unit testing all the time.
It's one of like the least relevant things in programming and relative
to the number of questions I get.
But this would be a case where if you were planning, if you're making
one of these and you want to use it.
A lot unit, testing is not a bad idea, right?
Because, you know, you're going to
Right this Library once and you're going to use it for everything.
You could write a series of math tests.
That verify that it's doing something reasonable, right?
You know, exactly what the inputs are supposed to be.
It's math, it's floating point.
It's rigorously defined, you can easily write a sort of unit test.
That make sure that what you're doing makes sense, right?
And so, you know, that's just something to think about there, all
right?
So
Way.
Let's take a look at which ones I defined here.
So we yeah.
We've got a bunch of sort of Ops here, the integer Ops.
I don't think we really care about that much.
So, really, honestly, these should be
These should really be defined for the f30 twos.
Because we're not going to be dividing integers and stuff.
So I think I really want these to only BF3 Jews
All right, so and that means they return if ages.
So all we're going to do now is just go through and fill out all of
the ones of these that we needed.
Did I accidentally do it for carrot?
Where is carrot?
Here we go.
Specifically, those little like clumsy areas like the one I just
corrected there where you know it was missing the 14 karat was labeled
and or whatever else right that's exactly what you would.
Hopefully catch in a in a situation where you wrote some unit testing
right you just and it's worth doing because you know you're going to
reuse this a bunch of times and so presumably it's all good.
Okay?
Like you're not wasting your time.
Looking for bugs that aren't really hard to find or whatever, and it's
good to be able to trust your math Library.
So putting some extra testing, they're usually a good idea anyway.
So let me go ahead and Define the rest of these binary operators as
well.
Let's get an and let's get an or right.
These are literally the exact thing you would think.
And that's really about it.
So now we just have to go ahead and finish up the rest of this stuff
and make sure it works properly.
It looks like random bilateral supposed to return an F32 and never
did.
And that just in the scalar version worked because they were defined
to be the same in here.
We've got, we've, we're initializing these with values that come from
single scalars.
I think if I'm not mistaken, we can add some ways to automatically
convert those together.
I don't know if operator equals will actually work.
Here, I'm going to try it again.
This is my haven't programmed to C++ but much in a long time, so it's
a little bit tough for me, to remember, Sometimes some of these
things, but I think we can just do something like this.
and I think during construction it will pick that up but you may not
be able to use operate equals during construction like this, it may be
that you have to do an actual Constructor again, these sorts of
things, very
okay, so in this case, we know we've got an A
I think we can just do a thing where we do a equals lane from you,
three to be returned a.
And if that works, I don't know if it is, no, it doesn't.
Operator equals must be a non-static member.
Why though?
Why must it be?
Can you tell me?
Yeah.
That's a little bit weird though because
Why can we do?
Operator x equals that way.
It doesn't have a problem with that, but we can't do operator equals
that way, right?
It seems a little odd, doesn't it?
We go through this in handmade hero, too.
I thought we did.
But anyway, what I was going to say is assuming that you could Define
it, that way, if you could Define operator goes that way, you could do
it down here because it wouldn't actually depend on anything else
either write, it would be able to use the function.
We've already defined and we wouldn't have to do it per Lane with
right.
So I really just don't know how to convince it to let us do that.
I feel like we went over this before.
Hold on one second.
Let's take a look.
So, it looks like we did not do that ever.
Well, that's that's poop sauce if you ask me.
It's just plain poop sauce.
That's all right, we can make it, you know, if that's, it's really for
some reason.
We've got to make it that way.
I have no idea why that would be the case but if we have to, we have
to because I assume that it wouldn't matter if we got rid of that.
Yeah, so if we have to make it that way, then I guess we have to make
it that way but that's okay.
It's not the end of the world.
So in this case we would just say, all right, if it's if
Got an operator equals here.
We can just say star this, right?
Whatever the thing is here, equals that
Equals the Lincoln version.
And then we just make sure that everybody who defines one of these
here.
Who do you know, who each one of the lane things that defines one of
these just has to stick a lane F32.
Definition in here so that the compiler knows is coming, right?
So long enough for you to operator equals, F 32, right?
And as much as that's dumb, I mean, it's okay, right?
I don't think there's anything particularly bad about it, right?
So that should work.
This has to be in Acts go and presumably this will work for floats as
well.
Just fine.
So, here we go.
And that's it.
So yeah, I think that's mostly all we need.
No operator found, which takes a right hand side of Lane F32.
That's correct.
So, we actually need the other kind here, which is lofting up just a
straight u-32 because we want to be able to
You 32s from you 32s, so that's fine.
And the way that we would do that again is exactly the way we were
doing it before.
So we've got a lane f82 from you 32 Elaine after you to from F32.
And so we just need Lane you 32 from you 32.
And again that's just a set one.
Exactly the same thing but we just need to do a set one from an Epi 32
instead, right?
Where we're going to be instead of casting it to a float.
We're just going to set it as as it is and we're going to replicate it
to
All the links, right?
All right.
So let's see.
It.
Cannot convert u-32 two-lane.
You 3D to
Yeah, so I this is the part that I was worried about before.
Apparently, during construction, you can't do that.
So let's see if this works, for example.
Yeah.
So for whatever reason, see and it's infinitesimal wisdom forces you
to have a Constructor, I guess declared to do the equals here, which
is super, super duper lame.
It's like so incredibly lame because you know why, right?
There's no reason why that would be the case, but you would have to
write it like that if you wanted to do it or and we don't want to
create an
Operator, B Construction operate or anything like that because we just
want these things to be flat types.
So what I can do here again is just two lane, you 32 from you 32,
right?
So I can do that and then that'll work just fine but it's just kind of
stupid that I have to do that.
But that's the plus plus for you, right?
Like they would then go like, oh yeah, but you know what you should do
is Define a Constructor for every type that's going to take and then a
default Constructor is like, it's like no just make your programming
language actually work for the programmer instead of making the
programmer work for your language, you know.
But they've you know they've
Ed fastly.
Refuse that they're always like oh but no, you don't understand.
If you just type these extra hundred thousand lines of code,
everything works cleanly and you're like, you don't really understand
programming, do you.
So anyway, let's just finish this up.
We are forced to have these conversion types, and that's just
unfortunate, but that's the way it is.
And that is that.
Now, we're going to have to do the lane V3 ones as well.
Oops are these are F 32s.
We're loading here.
These are all actual floating Point values, right?
Yeah.
Okay, so what we want to do here is, what can I convert argument f30?
Those are f30.
Two's though.
Aren't they?
What was that?
What was the complaint here?
Cannot groups cannot convert.
Argument one from Lane after 2:00.
So these already are laying in Futures.
So these are fine because, right, because film dubbed film State, film
X and state film.
Y, plus half x with these are F32 is already, so they will up convert
the film X automatically, so that's cool.
All right, we need to add that function that function doesn't exist
yet.
And so off we go.
Okay, so in here, now, I want to inside the four wide float.
I want to do a lane V3, that's Lane V3 from B3, and it takes the thing
to replicate right?
So here's my result.
And I think I can't say for sure, but just I feel like this should
just work right?
What I should be able to do here is say if we just do this again
completely blind in theory, this should work for all the different
widths, right?
So this should work for 4 8 and 16 so it should be something that can
just come down.
And work here furthermore I think and I could be wrong about that.
But if you take a look at this, if we just said that each of these was
a lane F32, I think we might just be able to not pass it eclair.
This type month multiple times either, right?
Because in theory it can just lean on the F32 and work that way,
right?
So I think we can just do this and then off we go, right?
So I'm going to try that as well.
All right, so again, this is just going to be a lane you through to,
from you 32, where we lost that up.
Here, we've got a divided, raise per pixel, / Lane width.
That's a you 32 divided by another 32.
In this case, I don't want to use the lofted version, so I'm just
going to go ahead and do it like this.
So it's still in scalar because we're just trying to compute a scalar
on the way out, right?
For the contribute value, we've got the race for Pixel again that
contribute value can also remain a scalar for the most part.
So I'm going to use this part of the raise per pixel.
Again, right, and let me see here.
If we've got a phrase, per pixel is never used wide.
It's never used white anyway, so actually we can just do this.
Let's take a look at Max.
Bounce count.
That's never used by either.
So, these were really a little bit premature there.
I just kind of got carried away when I was converting them, so we
don't really need those to work like that, right?
We can just have
He's stay like this for now and we can anything else we want to do?
We can do later.
So, one thing that we're counting on here, which we should probably,
also assert is that the lane re-count times, the lane with is going to
equal the raise per pixel afterwards, if Lane width and raised for
Pixel, we're not, if rates per pixel was not an even multiple of Lane
with, we would be cheating here and not doing all the Rays.
So we probably want to do an assertion here just to make sure that we
don't get into that scenario.
All right, so let's go ahead and take a look here.
What else?
We've got now, we've got a x operator.
That's taking a left hand, type of laying F32.
So we've got like, probably this is RV.
Yeah.
So this is, we need to start implementing our lane V3 stuff, right?
So let's go ahead and start implementing your lane V3 stuff because we
have a bunch of things we want to do there.
So four lane v3's, we need to do a operator Plus
so, we need to open, I guess I should probably
So these are basically to be the exact same operations as our normal,
handmade math operations, right?
In fact.
T', I'm wondering if we can just use this stuff directly.
Because all of these are just going to be correct.
I think for the most part, pretty much all of this stuff so we can
actually take Ray math and just turn it into Ray Lane here.
I mean, really all this stuff, you know, I hate to cut and paste it.
Exactly.
Because I mean, can we get away with just having the lane version?
The only problem about that is anywhere in the code that just wants to
be scalar.
Couldn't really be.
But at the same time, I don't know.
Because you can always just use the bottom part, right?
You could always just do it in lanes and then just not use all of it.
I'm kind of tempted to do that.
So I think what we could do here is just not have any Lane stuff in
here at all, right?
Just leave this out.
Then anything that was a V3.
We could just get rid of the V3 type entirely, I think and just use
the lane V3 type, I think.
Let's try it.
And let's just see how it how we do.
yeah, I mean, I'm just looking at this code and I'm thinking
I think that just works.
I mean, there's because really
all of this stuff.
Doesn't really care if there's a couple things like the normalizer
zero, this needs to be done with the conditional.
But other than that, it doesn't really seem to be a problem, right?
So I don't know.
Do we use v4s anywhere?
The only place we use, it is in this bitmap color, right?
That's it.
So, I'm getting rid of that as well.
And I'm going to get rid of all the V for stuff to just simplify
things down.
So okay.
So in order to do the stuff that we need here, I got to see how our
dependency order is stacking up here.
So is there anything that's actually happening?
I don't think there is
So I think what we can do is just reverse this order.
Here we go.
And so lean V3 from V3.
Now would no longer exist because there is no such thing as a V3.
And then we just have to implement the lean operations that we don't
have.
So right now, if we don't have a way to do a unary minus yet and so we
need that right?
We need a unary minus on here now, I don't know.
I don't think there's a way to do a unary minus in SSE.
I think you just have to do some PS with zero.
Don't quote me on that.
Someone can check me on the stream who wants to double check, but I
that just, I don't think you can.
I don't remember, but I just don't think you can.
So the
Ra - operation here.
Where I'm going to go ahead and take a value and make us negative
value.
I think the only way that you do that in as a see that are the most
expedient way to do it is to load a 0 and subtract maybe you would xor
with a pattern but I think sub would be the same speed.
I don't know there's because obviously it's a floating point value.
So you can just twiddle the sign bit and that would work as well but
I'm not sure which way would be faster or whether there is a fast,
whether either of them is faster or not.
I couldn't say so anyway so what we want to do here is we just want to
take that a value and we want to do a lane F32 from F32, we want to
just load 0 and then we want to subtract a from from that because that
will negate it right?
So pretty straightforward.
The result is just that
And that's the negation.
So let's keep going.
So we've got the inner product here and the inner product of Lane v3s
is going to have to be a lane F32 obviously because, you know, we're
going to need to take the scalars here and they're going to get added
together and all that stuff.
So we're not going to end up with a straight up 32 anymore.
Let's see what else we've got here.
Same thing with the length squared, right?
And then when we
The third Square rooting these things Square rooting.
These things is again going to produce something here.
That's going to be in a lane form form and in order for us to be able
to do that, we need some kind of square root operation.
Fortunately for us, we have a square root operation.
It's actually provided directly.
It's called em em squirt.
Yes.
And there's actually two different ways that you can do this and it
depends on which one you want.
Now you can kind of see there's some
Weird anomalies with this.
And what you can see here is, there's a pretty high latency on square
root operations, but actually a very high throughput on them.
So what's weird is that you can do a square root, if you're doing
them, they actually pipeline very well and you can do lots of them at
once.
If you want to there's only a 3 cycle through put on them.
I so that's actually kind of insane on sky, like right.
But either or the cycle counts on, this are actually pretty low, but
there's certainly nothing compared to some of the other operations
such as mul PS, which is, you know, if you see how much lower these
are three cycle latency on some and a half cycle, throughput, right?
Lots of multiplies in this thing.
So there's another thing you can do which is called reciprocal square
root and this one has a much better performance profile.
You can see it here and what that does is that approximate it doesn't
give you a very good.
Good answer.
It doesn't approximation to the square root.
And does one over the approximation it's made specifically for
normalizing things.
We're not going to use this yet but be aware that it is here because
if we find that we're spine spending too much time in our square
roots, this is a way to speed them up.
So it's good to know that they're there.
If you want approximate Sprite it's especially good for normalization
where you have something that looks like this, which is 1 over the
square root.
This is specifically designed to calculate that.
And if you don't care about the exact answer, that might be something.
For you.
Okay, so what we need to do is Define a square root in the side of our
array Lane stuff and that is going to be dependent on which one of
them we have, because there's actually going to be two different kinds
depending on whether it's for wider, 8 wide.
So if we go to the square root operation here.
So we take a an input Lane and we want to produce an output Lane.
Then what we're going.
Do is we're going to say result dot V equals a top V here.
Result.
And we're just going to do this work.
We're going to do the full one.
So that's it, right?
And now this will vary work properly and off we go.
So, now we have to take a look here, we've got our, our lane V3 here
is getting multiplied by 1 over the length of a.
That should give us back another Lane F32.
So, this would be a lane V3 x, a lane F32, right?
and,
I think we need to define those specially, right?
Because we don't have I think we don't have any of those.
I don't think we have anything like that at the moment, right?
So oops.
So, what I want to do here is I want to start defining those as well.
I think those are ones that can be defined out here, right?
So a lane F32
Operation set for Lane V3 s.
So this is would just be X and divide really.
That would be supported I guess by this.
So you would be saying both versions of this
We would need both the, the scalar on both sides of this, and then the
divided on one side of this, I guess.
But so anyway, so the multiply here, what we'd want to do is say well
result dot X, you know, time equals a job x times x beat up V.
Right.
And this is just the standard multiplied.
We want to support that on either side and we could to support this on
either side if we don't want to write this twice, we can also just do
it like this.
So this will just call back into that and you know, off we go, let's
take a look here.
Oops, we've made a lowercase V.
I don't know why I want you.
That probably because we did lowercase x y z.
Let's see, and I meant to do that.
All right, so let's make sure we got the sense of that.
Correct.
So we have a lien V3.
It's got an x y and a z in it, and it's actually three different ones
of these.
And we have three different.
I'm sorry.
It's actually four different ones of these pack together and we have
four different floats back together and we want to do a multiply where
each lane multiplies, each lane.
So that that looks like the sense is correct there as well.
Alright, so let's take a look here.
Normalizer 0 is going to be the same way here where we have to set
something to 0 in the case, where we're trying to normalize it.
I think what we want to do is again, do that conditional assignment
here.
So this right here is going to produce a mask
Right?
Where we are taking a length squared value, that's coming back to the
Lane.
32, we want to compare it against a squared value here, whatever that
comes out to be, which can be locked to Lane as well.
And then, we're going to go ahead and say, let's do a conditional
assignments where we take results and conditionally assign it based on
the mask too.
To this value here.
So it'll be set to 0 by default and anything that isn't set to zero.
We something that past the mask, right?
And off we go.
So now we should get to the part where we don't have comparison
operators because we don't have comparison operators yet.
So we need to go ahead and put those comparison operators in again,
that's not too bad and and then we're sort of, you know, we're getting
we're getting closer.
And again, if it seems like a lot of work, it's really not.
As you can see, it's pretty easy work to do.
But the other important thing to remember is again, you really only
have to do this.
Once you can do one of these and make a nice little Library, once the
library is done, you can just use it and library is a strong term.
The H file, you can include this h-file anywhere you want.
And then once you have this h-file, you can just do scalar operations
on what looked like scalar operations in your code and have them be
actual Cindy operations.
And you really don't have to think about it ever again.
So anyway, so what I want to do now is put those comparison operators
in here again, those are going to be special operators because they
They are specific to the Lane width because they're going to call
different intrinsic, depending on what that lane with is.
So we've basically got, you know, a set of things here that look like
this right lane, F 32 x, right?
This is gonna produce a mask.
We played 32 result result is going to equal something.
With these two things.
And we're going to have just a series of something happening here.
So let's take a look at what that what has to happen here.
When we look at the these These are comparison structions again if you
did not know what you were looking for.
Again, you can come through here and click the compare button.
You can see you got all your comparison instructions.
Listen here.
There's quite a few of them.
A lot of them have some confusing mnemonics, but we'll go over what
that means.
Now, again, the last part of the mnemonic telling you, specifically
what's working on 16-bit Lanes, 32-bit Lanes, 8-bit Lanes,
64-bit doubles 32-bit floats.
So that ending is always pretty consistent.
Includes you into what?
It's actually operating on.
Again, you can also use sort of this to give you a clue, is whether
it's integer or not, because L have the eye or not in the parameters.
So we are trying to compare float.
So, you know, we're looking at things like this instruction here, copy
QPS.
As you might have guessed, EQ is equal to.
And if you look at what else, we've got, g e is greater than or equal
to GT is greater than not.
Greater than equal to, right?
Ellie is less than or equal to l t is less than any Q is not equal to
0 and N GE is not greater than not.
I'm sorry not not greater than equal to naught greater than a lot of
these are actually just mnemonics that all come out to the same in
actual instruction.
You can see here, for example, you end up with things where like
you've got, you know, not greater or equal to write, for example.
Is doing comp ss.
But so is this doing Compass s right?
I'm sorry.
Cop.
P.s.
I clicked on the SS one accidentally there whereas it's right there,
right comp PS and comp PS.
There's similar instructions that are doing basically the same things
and they take immediate to say which one of the comparisons they're
doing, and they just make mnemonics that are easy for you to pick out
which one you wanted.
So that you don't have to remember what the immediate tsar and all
these sorts of things.
So in this case, we've got a pretty simple and straightforward thing.
We want to do, what we're going to do here is say well it's a less
than.
So we want to be able to do
A comp operation.
I do.
Compare less than these two values.
And what we're going to get back is we're going to get back an actual
unfortunately.
Right?
If we do, mmm, less than we're actually going to get back a float
value, right?
We're going to get that complex than PS and generally speaking.
We were sort of, treating our, our masks as you 32s, maybe we
shouldn't do that, maybe we should treat our masks.
As lean F32 is, I don't really know.
We're gonna have to do a conversion here if we don't, right?
Because generally, it's not a conversion, it's a cast.
But generally speaking, these are not like
as clean as we would want them to because they yeah I don't think so.
If you take a look at these, there's actual or versions of the PS ones
as well as the Epi other si128, we could instead choose to do is
mostly Lane F32 s and use you 32s only sparingly for very specific
things.
I had thought about that.
We were originally doing this.
Let me see where we actually have Lain 32s here.
In most cases.
In most cases, we are all of our masking could just if we wanted to it
could actually stay as you 32 as F32.
Um,
I'm not going to do that yet.
I'm going to let these always phase you 32s.
And so what I'm going to do here is just do a cast instruction.
So what you can see here is, if I do a cast, you can convert one of
these to the other without changing the bit values.
So, for example, if I do a cast, si128 PSI can take an integer in and
return a float out.
Or in the case, we're talking about here, I can do a cast PSS.
I went to me and do the opposite, right?
And what that'll do is, that'll just take the B directly, right?
So it'll take a was a PS and turn it into an SI, which is what I want,
right?
So I'm going to do that because I just want to keep these as laying
you 32s for now, that may be a dumb decision but that's what I'm going
to do for now.
Just because it's clearer and we are not super focused on weird
performance things yet or anything where we might actually care one
way or the other.
So I'm going to go ahead and and spam these out here so that we can
have a couple different ones of these.
You can see that I'm just doing the exact function multiple times.
And all I'm doing is taking, you know, these and saying, well we've
got greater than is greater than equal to is equal to, you know, not
equal to is
Not equal to less than is less than and so on.
And you know that's that's it and we can do
these versions as well, without
Much Ado.
There we go.
So I think that's it.
Let's take a look here.
What are we talking about?
There were times takes right hand.
Yeah and so these right here are just ones that want to take a scalar
on either side so that you can automatically do the upconvert there.
And again, that's something that we don't have to do per Lane so we
can put that down in here.
So if we want to, we can have a lane u-32 operator and we can make
each of these.
Where we take Elaine F32.
on one side and a scalar on the other side Hoops be
What?
Why did we?
Yeah.
Well I guess it doesn't really matter.
This should really be a be right?
And this should be say yeah, for being for being salty about it.
So anyway, in this case these are all just, you know, wrote sort of
conversions, where we take the result and we say, well, we know that
we wanted to up convert one of them, so we'll just say a greater than
Lane if they to from
32 of B and then we return the result, right?
So this is just a little quick thing to make sure that it will
automatically take that one and convert it.
In this case.
Now, there's other ways we could do stuff like this, we could have
implicit conversion that would do.
It implicit conversion up to Elaine you 32.
I don't always like to do that unless I really have to the reason for
that is just because I don't love having surprise conversions, so I'd
rather have it.
Only do the conversion for operators that I've actually thought about
before.
Before if that makes sense.
Oops, so sometimes I like to just deal with the fact that c is kind of
annoying and makes you go through all these hoops.
But just deal with that fact and type it in once and then have it and
I know that it's only going to do the exact things that I specified,
right?
So that's just one thing to think about.
But, you know, that's the choice that you can make yourself.
If you would rather just put in some implicit conversions there, you
can to find implicit conversions in the type itself.
That would always be able to compute convert an F32.
You to Elena 42 like every time, right?
All right.
So now I'm just going to spam these out for each version, right?
Let me just make sure that I've got this compelling properly here.
There's an extra parentheses that you don't need there with that one.
And so now I'm just going to go ahead and did I get sling squared
greater than equal to square cannot convert Lane through?
F32.
Yes.
So this mask should really do that and then we've just got to make
that actual conditional assignment.
We know that we have a conditional assign operator there.
This actually needs an and in front of as well.
So now we actually have to implement that conditional sign and that
conditional.
The sign is not
Is not particularly difficult to implement either, so we can actually
write it.
I think we might actually be able to write it out here.
So for conditional assign.
We've got a lane, F32 d'Este, a lane u-32 mask, and Elaine, F32
Source, like so.
And in this case, what we want to do here is we want to actually
doesn't produce results.
All right?
Overwrites the destination, right?
So what we want to do here is we want to say that whatever the
destination is it's going to be equal to you know, itself anded with
the inverse of the Mask.
In fact, you know, we
We already sort of wrote it here, right?
You can see what we ended up with.
And you can see how we wrote it, right.
It's a little bit different in the scalar version because the masks
get computed wrong in the scalar version compared to what we want.
But otherwise, it's basically the same.
And the other thing that's interesting about it is we can take the
vector version again and that can be the same for all of them.
This this will work in all cases, right?
But the point is, the conditional assign that we wrote above, which is
this one here.
This is actually exactly what we want, right there is nothing more to
it.
As long as we've defined all of these operators, we're good to go.
Now, one of the things that's a little bit odd is that we could have
actually done this one a little bit more, a little bit more Saucy.
The reason that I say that is because if you look there's an and not
here so there's an and not PS and that allows us to do an and with a
mask that we haven't actually
Phrases.
So, in see, there's no such thing as like that.
Operator, you can't do an and with a knotted, whoa, there's something.
And, and with a knotted version of the operand, but in the intrinsic,
in the SSE instruction set, we can so, rather than first knotting,
something and then ending it together, what we can do is roll that
into one, and we do want to do that because we don't want to sit here
wasting time.
Hi, so if you see in psss completely bitwise, not of packs, a 20-foot,
putting those in a and then and with b and store the results invest.
So you can see that that first one is going to get knotted, which is
exactly what we want in this case.
Um, and off it goes.
So what we really want to do is introduce an and not operation here,
right?
And that and not operation is going to be
what we do on this side and then the regular and operation is what we
do on the source side.
And like I said, one nice thing about this is this will actually work.
Regardless of which one of these we happen to be using, right?
It can work for both both Lane versions.
This actually to I guess and I think about this guy can be outside
because this works for scalar.
It this works for everything, right?
And and so does this, I guess right?
In fact.
Why were these necessary?
Why weren't these already in the math?
Library.
Oh, because those were scalars that were happening there and these are
at the Jews.
That's fine.
All right, anyway, we'll get to that later.
All right, so in conditional assignment.
We've got these two versions here, both of which we want to have work.
So what we can do, if we want to is we can go to find this and not
operation and then that will give us the extra thing that we actually
needed.
So I'm going to go ahead up here and put that in.
So right where we've got this sort of and between two different
things.
I'm going to go ahead and take that and and I'm going to make a and
not and the and not is just going to look like that, right?
And that's that's all it's going to do.
Now, the other thing that I need to be able to do is I need to be able
to have these operations work even if it was an F32 that was there
instead, right?
So I need to be able to do it.
Where if I, if I
I'm going to perform one of these functions the and or the and not and
the or actually all three of those have to work.
Whether if there's an F32 on the other side of it as well, just see
what's going to happen here is we're going to get into a situation
where we need the the and not to take an F32 as well.
Now we could cast these here.
And that might be the easier way to go.
So we could we could do is introduce a Cast Operation that cast, the
the mask from a youth of you to an F32 directly and you know, that
seems like that might be the right way to go, probably a little
simpler than introducing, or is between all of them.
So, maybe I would just introduce one thing here, which would be like,
cast.
F 30.
Sorry, cast u-32 to F32.
Like that.
Something like this where we would then only have to do the do those
operations.
Where the types were equivalent.
I don't really know so you can do it either way.
It's again just kind of.
This is why I generally don't love having this idea in the first
place.
Like I generally, don't love saying oh, you know, sometimes we've got
a lane f42 sometimes got linear 32.
In fact, the way that I've done these in the past is I've actually
made it so that they're the same type and you're just a union of the
two and you know honestly I tend to like that better so maybe I should
have done that here but you know
The lake now.
Anyway, so if you take a look at that, we would need to have a cast
temperature.
And we'd also need to have the and operation here or we could just say
that the
I mean the other thing we could do is just say this could be a
specific operation that we only code that we hand code per one, we
could make the conditional assignment, just be hand coded, right?
I don't know the u-32 one will just work because that one is just the
same all throughout.
So maybe the right thing to do is just have the float conditional sign
because it is a little wonky.
Maybe that one we just code specially.
So we don't because we really don't need the rest of that stuff too
much in here anyway.
So if we were going to code that when specially right then it's just
Mmm.
And not PS.
Mmm, convert epi32.
PS.
Stardust.
Mmm.
4ps
And PS.
and I guess right here we would also say like, okay so there's an M&M
128 that's you know, the mask converted
So on.
Right, sweetie, or the and not in the and together and off we go now
it's worth noting that this is a very common operation and it's kind
of weird that they didn't put it in there to begin with but I think
it's because it would have to be ternary and some weird way probably
and they don't always love that.
but once they added turnery Ops, I believe,
That got in here.
Don't remember what it's called.
Because I've never actually used it because I always do it manually
because I don't have access to the instruction normally on things that
I ship.
I'm pretty sure got outed.
It's not extract.
I don't know what it's called.
I'm trying to look for it now but
The point is this operation right here where you do an or of the Ann's
not in the and is basically selecting Lanes, based on a mask that is
an actual operation that is, you know, is widely used and eventually
became part of the instruction set, if I remember correctly.
All right.
okay, so, back to our program,
So clamp 01 is something that we can Implement actually much more
efficiently now than we used to.
So if you take a look at what clamps are one was doing back here in
the old days, you can see how it was operating in scalar form here,
right?
And it's not very good involves sumifs and and garbage like this and
we can do much better than that now that we've got sort of a better
instruction set.
So, for example,
if you come in here and Implement Elaine F32 clamp like so
What we can do.
Is say, well, if you want to clamp something between 0 and 1, really
all that is is that saying, well, we want to take the, we want to do a
Min and a Max pass, right?
We first want to take the maximum value, right between whatever the
the
It is and 0, right?
And then we want to take a Min value.
I'll clamp it on here between that and one, right?
I mean, that's that's really all we're doing, right?
And so, one of the things is that if we write it like that, we can
then leverage the fact that those instructions unlike x64 in the
actual SSE instructions, those actually exist.
So we can actually do
Min and Max instructions directly.
And so if we actually Implement those, this becomes much simpler,
right?
So we can take
These two here and now we would have an actual Min and Max, right?
And you can see
And here very fast just as a quick selection where it picks whichever
the minimum or maximum value values.
Are at that point, we can Implement a nice clamp.
That's actually just two instructions long that does exactly what we
want, right?
And again, that's something that we can use irrespective of the lane
with because as long as we Implement a minute, Max function, we can
get our clamps for free and they're quite fast.
They're going to be better than the clamps we were using before.
We'll get four clamps done in less time than it would have taken
before for us to do the ifs.
Unless the compiler was smart.
And turn them into min-max, has like that itself.
okay, so let's go ahead and
keep going here.
Yep.
So these are just plain from convert these values up here.
There we go.
What was the problem?
Can I convert argument one?
That's a good point.
Sorry about that.
Okay, so now we've got these V4 operations which I don't actually
wants.
I don't want any V4 is in the program now because I just don't want to
deal with them, right?
So we're going to get rid of all these.
And then we're just going to implement the, the srgb stuff.
We're going to take that and put that in its own, sort of special
thing that we're going to do separately, right?
Okay.
All right.
So now in these cases where we've got sort of things in here that
we're still sort of using V3 is in some way.
I'm just going to Loft those up to be v3s, just by default.
And what that will mean is that when we load them, we can load them
directly and we don't have to replicate them anymore.
That might not be the greatest thing cache size wise when we start to
blow these things out into bigger things, but the other thing that's
interesting about that is, we could in the future.
we can in the future, just have these, the three floating Point values
that we then you know,
That we then deal with slightly differently or something right?
But for the moment I'm going to go ahead and make those people own out
just because why not, right?
And we'll go from there.
All right, so we don't actually need to do this anymore because these
are going to be
Well you know what I could do actually I didn't take that.
I'm gonna take that back just for a second for a quick second.
What we could do is Define that as a storage only thing.
Right.
I could see that being the case.
So we could do something like a V3.
Is for storage only.
And we never do anything else with it, right?
So I'd be okay with that potentially.
And it looks like, oh, sorry, that guess that has to be.
Taste.
And that seems okay.
Alright, so in this case we still can implement this function and
that's totally fine.
And we've sort of going to have to re backport it for the for the
I feel scalar version which will do but all this is going to do is
just load one of these from the storage format, right?
Stick with my ninja convention there.
All right.
And so that's just going to replicate the values across which is all
we really needed them to do anyway.
And there's not a lot more to it than that we will need to Define
that.
Up with the lanes stuff.
And that's just going to be defined right here because everyone uses
the same one, no matter what you're doing.
Okay, so this is Elena 3242 shows this.
So is this just lofting?
Plus equals is not implemented for the you 32s.
And we do want to, because we need to do this for statistics tracking.
That's really the only place that we use such a thing, but we do want
it to be there.
So let's go ahead and grab that.
So for you 32s?
Just going to look like this, and I'm going to grab the operator +
appear.
So we don't have one, right?
You can see us doing the plus operator.
Therefore, playing F 32 plus looking at food to.
We're going to need one of those for laying you 32 as well.
And again, that's really simple.
It's the same exact destruction just for integers.
It's epi32 instead of PS.
Exactly as you would expect.
So nothing, weird going on there, right?
What are you saying?
And yes, that's true.
It's going to return a u-32.
Now, I'm at 42.
Cannot convert from Lane u-32.
Same, same is true here, got to change the return type.
And so here again, we're loading.
Elaine V3 from a regular V3.
And here, we're loading a lane at 3:57.
My 32 and I really wish you didn't have to type that I don't
understand why you can't tell it.
To use, operator equals there, it's just C++ being stupid as it always
is.
There's probably some ridiculous Incarnation, you can do to make it
work and then if you do that, a bunch of other stuff in your program
will break because that's C++.
So I'm just not going to bother right now but so we've got
Logical or and a logical end here.
And I think in this case, since we know that these masks produce the
correct values we should be able to use a binary and an or again
because we know that these less than and greater than will produce
zeros or one masks.
Predictably, the only thing I don't know is whether the scalar version
will still work.
Properly.
Because I'm not sure what C is required to do in the case where you do
something less.
Something else.
Let me see.
Just what one of them does.
This is not what I wanted at all.
I wanted what the values have to be.
What are the values, please?
So, it looks like they have to be 1 and 0.
Right.
So in that case, in these two circumstances, we should be able to do
that.
Right.
Which is good because we don't want to have to have logical operators
as well.
If we can avoid it because they would involve doing extra conditioning
work on the values themselves to make sure that they conform and we
would rather not have to do that extra work.
We want we want to, you know, do it as efficiently as possible when
we're inside this part of the thing.
So yeah.
Same here.
And I think that should be okay.
So no blood upward, okay?
So now we've gotten to the place where we actually have to do the
loads here.
And these are annoying because obviously we have to load each
individual one of these separately, right?
So what we're going to do is we have a lane V3 here
Right and an F32.
I don't know why that's not a lane F32.
So these have to be lofted up from slices so that that material index
is going to load out of out of a couple different places, right?
So we need to actually do a scattered load here and that's actually
kind of tricky to do.
I'm not sure how we want to write this, exactly.
So that it works on all the platforms,
Scalar, as well as a separate.
And there are no instructions that you do scattered loads.
So probably what we'd want to do here is a load V3 and a load F32 that
take sort of a stride and an index.
Of a thing.
And I think that's the only way.
We're going to really be able to do it.
So I'm going to do a thing here called gather V3, which is just going
to take a pointer.
The thing to load and then the offset of the thing, right?
So what I'm the way I'm actually going to do that is I'm actually
going to sort of do it a little bit so it's just slightly differently
which is I'm going to sort of say
That the the part of it that you're loading is actually just
specified, like the member that's being loaded as specified at the end
and the so it's the pointer, then the member at the end.
So this admit killer has to be has to return zero on Lane mask.
So I think that what that means is in here, we would want to mask this
this off.
So when we return this mat emit color, and we put that we made sure,
we put that note in there that has to get masked off, right?
I guess what that means is in here, we would have to actually do the
mask, right?
So we'd have to do laying mask and to make sure that we wouldn't we
wouldn't ever load an Omission in a case where array was dead, right?
But I think that's all we would have to do their.
There's our ref color and here's our gather F32 World materials,
Hitman Index, right?
And so, what this does is The Gather operation is the thing that we
need to do.
That will basically load in
You know, it will load in each of the value sets that we need by
grabbing from multiple indices and pulling them in.
This is one of the worst operations you can do, it's really good that
we only do it.
After all of the work has been done basically So that's its infrequent
and it's basically the the it's the thing that that group gpus do the
best that CPUs do the worst right now, which is gpus have great gather
they.
Oh, do texture fetches and all these other sorts things and they have
special purpose Hardware to gather it right where you've got.
You know, if you've got a 4x4 grid of 16 pixels in each, one of them
used to fetch or different texture thing, they can just do that.
The CPUs have horrible options for this and it's basically all manual
and really slow.
This is a nasty part and it is generally a nasty part, it's not just
nasty for us, it's nasty period.
In x64 land, neon has some scattered stuff, satyr gather stuff and
avx-512 I think may have some scatter gather stuff although I don't
know if that's even implemented yet.
It's sort of been the spec.
I don't remember if it ever got in to the latest tips or not, there's
those word, caps bits of crap, like that.
So I don't know.
Anyway,
So here comes our nway load.
We need these gather instructions, so let's go ahead and put them in.
First of all, gather V3 is again something that I think we can write.
I don't know why these are in lines.
I didn't accidentally just cut and paste it.
I think I typed in line for no reason.
So for example, The Gather V3 should be something that we can do
automatically in terms of The Gather F32, right?
So it's really only The Gather F32 that we're going to have to write
and we want to write these in terms of the macro why we want them
right between the macro because we want the title.
To be known to us so that we can figure out what the strides going to
be, right.
So, we're going to have the base pointer.
Right?
That's the materials array.
We're going to have the index, which is packed for a wide and we're
going to have the number right, which we're going to add, which are
going to address off of that's going to, then call our actual
function, which will pass the base pointer as just a raw pointer.
It will pass the size of whatever the base pointer is pointing to, so
that will let us know how wide The Stride is.
It will pass the offset of
The that member.
So basically I guess I don't have to do it that way.
What I could do is say, all right, so the base pointer member
Here, I just want to know how far I have to go to get the base pointer
member.
In fact, I guess, you know what, I don't even have to do that, take it
back.
I'll just Advance the base pointer.
To that member and take the address.
Now, we know are pointing directly at that member and we know what the
stride is, as well, right.
And then, all I have to do is specify what that again with that index
is that we're loading from?
So then our actual function after the macro has kind of cracked out
those values for it.
For us is going to take the bait.
The, the base pointer the stride
This is actually just a, do we have a memory size value here?
You 64, I guess would be fine.
it's going to take the stride, it would really it should really and we
can we can do it, you 32 doesn't have to be, we know that these
Just can't be that big and then it's going to take a lane, you 32 for
the index in the Seas, right?
And then what we want this to do is we want to have, you know, I'll
make both of these and we'll cut paste the other one up above, but we
want to have both of these, right?
So our gather F32 is going to do the exact same thing.
In fact, both of these can be defined sort of outside, right?
These are going to be the same no matter what in either case.
Everything's no matter who's doing, what those are going to be the
same.
So that's all fine.
And as I believe all we have to do here is we'll have to implement the
gather F50 21, but the gather v31 can just be implemented in terms of
the F32 one, right?
So here, we got our lane V3 that we're going to gather.
Result X, the result?
Why?
And there's a z.
And in this case, right?
We know that the thing that we're pointing at is itself and x, y, z
value.
So we know that we just have to take our base pointer, whatever that
base pointer is and turn it into a floating point value, right?
And then, we can just Advance it one floating point value for every
time we wanted to do a gather and we're done.
Now this is not the most efficient way we could gather these.
We could do a load and then do some bit operations to gather them.
So I'm just going to put to do here.
We could do better than this by special casing it for each lane with.
But at the moment, we're not going to do that.
Alright, so now I'm going to do an F32 load.
I'm going to an F32 load.
Using these indices here and so what we have is we've got a base
pointer Jimmy.
And we've got sorry.
This is Lena 32 and we've got you three, two indices here at that are
four different indices that we want to load from.
Right?
And so what we can do here is we could just say, all right you know
what here is a pointer to the indices, right?
We know that if we just targeted this this part of it, right?
That we
I would look at each one individually.
So maybe that's just what we're going to do.
So here is our V pointer.
We can now look at each of the UN 32s they're there and we can grab
off of the base pointer exactly what we actually want here.
So let's put together a lane F32
That is the result.
We're going to do an M&M set PS.
I think we want to set our PS because I like to do it in the other
order I normally like
Me show you I'm saying here, and I think, Fabian for pointing out the
fact that they already have one of these.
You can see that there's like a least significant value to most.
This goes in the order you normally see them going in.
So, I find that much more intuitive than set PS, which goes in the
opposite order, right?
I believe set PS.
Actually sets them in.
Yeah, you can see wait.
What's going on there?
These are not
Okay, I take it back.
That's right.
So set RPS, puts the first one.
He's just weird that they named them III.
In this case, it puts the least significant one first.
So if you think in terms of memory order, right rgba for example, this
one goes in the least significant, it just looks weird because of the
way it's written here, but it's actually easy row is what it actually
is.
It's just called III.
It's getting a little confused there.
So depending on, which one you want to do it, we can do it that way.
So if I want to do 0 1, 2 3, which is what I want to do, or you do set
RPS, because you want the least insignificant one to go in, to be
specified first, and the most going to be specified last.
So, if I set this to you eight, star base pointer, I add 0 times, the
stride, because we're right at the value right now,
I'm sorry, now's your time to strive indices 0 times.
The stride right then I'm going to get the value that I actually
expected here and I need to cast that to the thing that I'm expecting
it to be, which is of course an F32, right?
So there you go.
It's kind of a cryptic sequence but it's pretty straightforward, was
doing I'm saying I've got these four packed.
Indices, I want the first index times the strides, which is however,
far I have to go for each index.
I want to add that to whatever the base pointer was and then and I
want to do that in actual bytes.
Then I want to say that, whatever I'm pointing at take that F32 and
load it, right?
I want to do this four times once for every index.
Then I've done a striated load, right?
I've gathered from a couple different places.
Again this really should be an instruction.
It's an instruction that kind of completes the set.
The fact that there is no strided gather basically means that you
can't do array offsetting and Gathering and stuff like that in the
instruction set and you always have to downshift.
It's rough but that's just the way it is unfortunately.
So you know what you gonna do anyway?
So
I'm not sure why it says I didn't phrase not find for Gather F32, did
I put it in the wrong place?
I did.
Basically, up more, and one thing we could do is break these out into
separate files, that might be a nice thing to do, so that we don't
keep getting confused between them multiple ones of these.
Right?
Which I am occasionally want to do, so that might be fun to do as
well.
Maybe we could do that a little bit later on.
So, anyway, off we go.
We got the set RPS.
I don't know why.
I've got an extra parentheses there.
Oh wait.
No.
I do need that.
That's the parentheses on this.
So each one of those there you go.
So that's correct.
Cannot convert em 128.
Oh that's okay too.
Actually
And so this here is no longer going to happen, right?
That goes away.
And the lane mask.
Here again, is sort of doing a mask operation on on this gather V3.
We don't, that's something that we don't quite have yet.
So, yeah.
If we take a look at the emit color here, it's just getting used there
in the hadamard.
What I could do is say
Yeah, I think we just want to implement that actual and operation.
Right.
I think that's something we actually want to do there so let's just go
ahead and do that.
All right.
So in re Lane how we doing on time here, we're not doing too bad on
time.
So in re Lane, I've got the
I've got to do one thing here which is that and operation operator and
we need to be able to do an operator and between two of these that are
you know I want if I want to be able to mask one of the F32 s by, you
know I want to be able to do like an F32 mask in this in this order,
right?
Then what I want to do here is say like, okay I'm going to do an end
PS, and I'm going to just do a conversion of the Mask variable.
And now that I think about it, I think.
Well, alright, I'll leave it this way for now.
So again I want to do a Cat cast.
Epi32.
Don't we have one of these.
I want.
Well, I want to do the other way around, right?
I want to do a cask si128 PS kind of thing, right?
I want to do a
I want to do with that.
Before I do my end there, right?
Yes, I went to meet ups.
That's what I want.
All right?
And so four-lane.
V3's.
Now that I've got one of those.
I can just do that.
Operation defined for the lean be 3.
Put that down at the bottom here, so an and operation for a lane V3
like so.
Where I'm going to take one of these and mask it off, it's just going
to be like you would expect it's just going to be an x equals b and a
tedx kind of a thing.
It's going to be this I guess I should do a D and B and it just
replicates across the various parts of it update.
So, it looks like we don't have a not equals to, for our hit mask, for
our, for our comparison operators there.
And I'm not sure why we skipped that one.
Looks like we've got a not equals 2 but only for f 32s and it looks
like we need one for you 32s as well.
That looks about about it right.
So again, just using the exact same thing here.
I don't know what the correct thing is.
So not equals to 4 epi32.
Do we have that comp equal to
so, it looks like
Looks like I'm gonna have to take a quick look at what they've got for
comparisons.
Let's restrict are set to stuff.
We actually do so it looks like we've got comp equal to
But not comp not equal to.
And the reason for that is probably just that they want us to just not
it after we're done, right?
They probably didn't want to provide a separate one for for integers
at that point.
So we have to probably use a cop equal to epi32, which would be this
one here and then do a not but that's okay, right?
I assume you've got an operation.
Maybe we don't.
Whoops, we have only compared selected.
So in order to do a not, we would have to do a next door with a mask.
It looks like, man, this is annoying.
I wonder is there a faster way to do it than what I'm thinking of?
Because if we do a cam PQ epi32, we say they're equal.
We then need to flip the mask, right?
And in order to flip the mask, we would want a not operation but a not
operation.
Is an available to us.
There's an and not operation.
But that doesn't really help us in this case.
So I'm going to do the stupid thing here, but it might be, I have to
think about that a little bit, there might be a smarter way to do that
without having to load a constant, right?
But if we just said, like, if we wanted to flip it, right?
We could do an xor with, you know, with zero or something, right?
Because then if it was, if it was a 0, it is 0.
It would become a 1.
If it was a one and a zero become a zero, right?
So we could just do something like this.
I don't know if they have an mm0, they have an M 0, PS, but I don't
know if they have any mm0.
Set zero.
Yeah, they do set zero si128 so they have a like a built-in for
saying, I want to use zero.
So I think
Operand actually Nursery too late and you're through to write six
left-hand, operand of type laying new 32, but there should be now
right hit Matt index.
Is itself.
Letting you through to right hit met index.
So Lane you 32.
And I guess this is just blamed YouTube from YouTube.
Hilarious not equal to 0 is actually we could just say yeah that that
would have been a simpler thing if you'd actually special case of
that.
But we don't really I don't think we want to go that far.
Alright so we've got our Max here again.
I'll just do Lane F32 from F32 to load that to up to a thing.
And now we've got ya, we've got a random bilateral, we're
In to pack those into a lane V3.
So, what I want to do here is probably just have a way to assign a
lane V3, from three independent components, right?
So, that's something that we could do outside, always, you know, we
can have, in fact, I guess we already have that.
It's
we really should probably just have that in here, where we've got
One of these, these themselves should probably just support Elaine V3
version.
But I'll I think what I'll probably do is just say, okay, let's make
the special one.
So we know when we're doing it, specifically, that just seems a little
bit nicer and in this case, that should just work, right?
In lerp here, it looks like we need one that takes a lane V3 as well,
and that's also fine, just put that in here.
Against exact same code, and that's all good.
The plus operator here.
What's that trying to add?
Is it trying to add a it's just Lane V3 on either side and we don't
have one of those yet.
So again that's something that we could put in here.
I'm not sure why there.
Shouldn't we have had an operator Plus in here somewhere.
yeah, so there's the lane V3 so it must be because it's
I don't quite understand where, okay, it's because I know why, it's
because these are not
This needs to come after the math stuff, right?
So these actually have to kind of come after the math.
Stuff has been defined so that's fine as well.
You know, that's that's a reasonable place to put them.
I'm fine with that.
Okay.
Now we have a few other things here.
We've got horizontal ad and mask is zero.
Let me see what else we've got here.
Yeah, so most of this other stuff we're basically done now.
So that's good because we're out of time but we're basically done with
our conversion and our implementation.
So let's go ahead and and just finish up a few more of these.
So in here, we've kind of got a couple other things.
We've got masked is zeroed this guy is actually I think this is
Is going to be something that has to be implemented per Lane, mask is
zero.
Horizontal add will have to be for will happen.
That will have to be done for the F32 s / Lane, but not for V3, is
because that's just again going to multiply out.
So if we take something like this, it's going to have to produce an
F32.
I'm sorry, this is a you through to that actually does this here,
right?
but the lien b31, which would just take an actual V3 in this case,
Yeah, that final color.
Yeah, but actually comes out as a V3, that's going to be totally fine,
right?
So, yeah.
So
if we go ahead here and say we have a result, the result X is going to
be equal to
The horizontal ad of a DOT x value.
Right.
And that just at sums up the components of it.
And so in this case where we've got these guys here, these are all
going to have to be done pearline.
So these are additional values that have to be additional functions.
Have to be implemented in the actual Lane stuff itself.
But again, no big deal.
These are pretty.
Oops, these are pretty easy functions.
Let's go ahead up and write them.
Right here.
So mask is zeroed, in this case, we've actually got
I think it's called mask.
Move, something like this.
Let's see here.
Conditionally start 8-bit integer elements from a into memory using
masks elements are not stored when the highest bit is not set in the
court.
No, it's not that
I don't actually need to move anything, so it's
Is it extract mess?
It's move.
Mask move mask, right?
Yeah, this is what we're talking about.
So yeah, I think we want something like this, create a mass from the
most significant bit of each 8-bit element and store the result in
dest, right?
So what we should be able to do here is just say, mmm, move, mass,
epi8 of this value and it will give us back.
A mask.
We can just say if the mask is zero, then nothing was there, right?
So that's very simple, right?
This this thing just takes those High bits and puts them into a value.
The processor can actually use as a general purpose register, which is
exactly what we want to do.
Our testing horizontal ads here, in this case we again want to do sort
of the extraction process which is unsavory but you know you have to
do it at the end.
You want to avoid how many times you're doing something like this,
where you're pulling stuff out of a register because it becomes it's
slow, right?
And there are sometimes instructs that faster ways to do this.
But this is only done at the end of all of our stuff so we don't have
to worry too much about it.
You could do it in a generic way here.
So here I have taken a pointer to the the values and I'm just going to
do the result.
What I could do here is return this as a you 64 as well.
Potentially because in this case, we could sum up more values.
So we could say like, cast this to you 64.
The 0 plus Q, 64 be 1, plus u 64, V2, plus you 64 B3.
And that way, we know we can't overflow it even if those values were
all very high.
We know that we can overflow.
If, you know, for whatever values that we had.
If there was an overflow, it happen beforehand, right?
Same thing is true for this horizontal.
Add only in this case we're still returning an F32 specifically and
that's because floats don't really overflow in that way.
They just get less precise.
And in this case we don't really care too much about that because
we're just using these four color values don't have to be any more
precise than, you know, sort of a vague 0 to 255, kind of gun value at
this point.
Although in the future, we make care more about that.
So anyway, here we go doing that horizontal add and then we just
return the value.
All right.
So yeah, the horizontal add here.
That should be a tedx.
That should be F32.
Coming back.
What is the problem here?
Cannot convert argument Wonder from Lena, 322 Lane V3.
I put these in the wrong place again.
Yes, I did.
This is why I think I need to put them into different files.
All right.
So, I think now really all we have to do here is just when we're
actually setting up some of this stuff.
We now need to deal with the fact that we've kind of got rid of some
of the V3 stuff.
And I don't really want to kind of carry around to math.
Libraries here, one for the unwind and one for the wide.
So what I want to do is try to make this stuff work relatively well
without that.
Now, what you can see here is, most of the stuff is fine.
The really, the only part here, we have to implement
The packing stuff, the V4 packing stuff.
This can just be done directly in here because the only place we do
it.
So I'm actually fine with that.
And I don't really need this to be extracted out a final color either.
So even that part of V3 is, doesn't really have to happen.
We can really just do exactly this but we don't have to pack it into
one of these either we can just say F 32 rf3, 2G F 32b.
And now we've got those
RGB values and we only have to implement this BGR.
A Pack 4 by 8.
We can go into the math library and find that BGR Pack 4 by 8.
And we can see that this is all that it does, right?
And so the unpacked ARG bees, those can just be put in specifically
actually leave the a in there in case we actually want to have a value
come out at some point.
Which is going to be, which would be some kind of a, like a
translucent value.
So I think, you know, if we just do this then the empty value.
Now, we don't need any of these anymore at all.
I don't think so.
I think we can kind of get rid of all this stuff.
We just need the one extract, linear to srgb, right?
I don't know where that went extract extract.
Where is that?
What's going on extract linear?
It's right.
Here is an extract.
Oh, exact.
That was funny, you have to admit.
That was funny.
Exactly near the srgb is already implemented in here.
So that part we don't care about at all.
We can go into this stuff and now I think we can just nuke all of
these.
Don't think we care about them.
At all.
Okay, so let's see here.
Now we just have a couple of these guys.
I think are just all V3 related, right?
So we just need to sort of finish this stuff off.
And so, yeah, I think if we just kind of clean up our doing our
initialization of some of these here, we should be fine.
So, the way that I would suggest doing this because
Have operations doing these Lane Wise is just have a way to smoosh
them down after the fact.
So, for example, if I just didn't, if I did exactly all of these
operations here, the way that they were being done.
All of this stuff should now work I believe.
And so then the only question is, how do we get them out here, which
should be a relatively simple matter?
And so down here, what we could do is then say all right, these are
just going to be taken directly from their counterparts.
So we'll just say like, you know, get or, you know, slice zero or
something like this.
So we can just extract the slices zero or like, you know, extract.
Something like that.
So this we can do all our computations in V3 regular v3s and then just
extract the 0l the 0 with one of them.
and that would just be something that inside the
inside the lane versions, We have a way to turn a lane V3 into a lane.
Or I should say a regular B 3.
So in this case, where we have this extract 0 here, we know that we've
got sort of sliced versions of all these and we only want the first
one of each of them.
So we've got a result here, the result X y&z.
We're just going to take an F32 pointer to the to the X here and and
look at the very first one of it, right?
That's really it.
And and that would pull out the first Vector in the set.
So, let's take a look here, we've got film centers that camera p- film
to start State camera Z.
This is again, I guess the same sort of situation.
Although, wait, what is the film distance is 1 point 0?
Is this just a case of us not having the F32 version here?
It seems like we are kind of missing the, our operators are laying
operators, right?
For operator times like some of those operators are not in the
Like these guys.
All right.
But that should have been there because Steve, oh, I see never mind.
Nope, I'm dumb.
The problem is, we just can't use the state ones because they are not
actually correct.
So we want we want to do.
Here, is do extract, zero Film Center.
And just do this up here.
All right.
So these are just have to be x y and z now because we don't have our G
and Beyond those anymore and that's fine.
And yeah, these guys are all just packing these V3 downs and these
are, this is sort of a
This is sort of an acronym stick.
Like what we really want to do here is probably have something that
fills out an actual material for us and similarly, for spirits and
that sort of stuff.
But what we could do as well is just make these be actual initializer
lists.
That seems the easiest thing to do for now.
So I'm going to do is just go to material, right?
Where we've got sort of
Scatter value.
I'm going to put that last and then I'm just going to come through
here and say like, okay, we've got, you know, and admit color, don't
give up.
Now me, open it first
Let's do scatter.
Graph, color emit color.
Just for now.
Okay, so then we've got our rough color here.
Rough color again.
Ruff color again, down to size is a bit cooler.
Rough color and Scatter.
Victor slightly prettier.
Yeah.
So we've got
0 1, 2 3 4, a 5.
Here's six.
And that is about it.
There we go, for planes.
Same deal.
We've only got one so it's just n.
D.
And the material spheres.
Got a bunch.
But then, that's it.
So, there's the pr and the mat index.
P.
R.
Madden decks.
He?
Are not index.
And pee.
R.
At index.
So now we are down to the very ends of the end here.
And if we want to have this entropy stuff work properly here, we have
to double-check how we're actually loading.
And using this, I think we want each of these to be its own separate
piece of entropic information.
So I would expect that what we actually need to do here when we're
loading up one of these entropy values.
It's since the seed value is going to be a couple different.
You 32s.
What I'd like to do here is take that
The entropy value and say, Lane you 32 from you 32.
And in this case, I'm going to make one of these.
That actually takes four values and loads all four values, right?
So we have like, one of these for each, and this is also the place
where we could do our dear and intrinsic.
We could have the processor.
Give us that information.
I don't know if
She has one of those for our dear and probably does, I don't think
I've ever used it.
So here's our dear and so we could actually use this as well at the
moment.
I don't really know how widely supported that is though.
So I'm not going to do it at the at the moment but
I always seem to start with to
When I'm typing in a quote-unquote random number.
All right, so these is these are just kind of dies at the moment and
that's fine.
But let's go in here and add our actual Lane U2 u3 to from you 32.
So all I want to do here is make it so that if I wanted to initialize
one of these with separate values like could.
So basically something like this.
And then what I would do is just use one of these.
Ought to succeed it with each individual value, right?
All right, so we now have the ability to run this sort of in theory as
a bunch of slices, we don't actually yeah like you can see that's not
a very good result there we don't want to actually start debugging it
like this though.
We want to flip back now that we've done all these changes, we want to
flip back to doing these in a in a sort of more about this.
We want to flip back to doing this in scalar form and we want to be
able to yeah we want to do a bunch of stuff, right?
So let's start by fixing a couple obvious things and going from there,
first of all, when we print out what we're printing out, we want to
do, we want to specify a couple things like what the lane with was so
that we can remember that when we're sort of playing with it.
So you can see here we say like eight cores with 240 slices blah blah
blah.
So we can put in what the lane with this here.
That way when we print, when we do one of these we can say four wide
Lanes.
So we know that we're doing bundles of for when we sort of push
through our nonsense here, right?
So let's go ahead and start by flipping the lien with back so that we
can kind of see what's going on here.
Let's flip it, back to 1 and let's make sure that we have the sort of
stuff that we need to hear where we can.
Where we can compile and scalar mode as well.
I don't know where the horizontal add four-lane V3 would have been at
the moment so it looks like we do have one of those.
So I guess that should be gone.
Yeah.
We've got the lerp already having a body that's because in this case
yeah these are all going to be the same so I guess yeah that's
something that really should only be done.
We don't ever want this to actually occur in any sort of situation.
Nations where we already defined the lerp for having a single scalar
there.
Yeah, I'm not sure how to really get around that problem.
Let's take a look at that a little bit later.
I'm going to Define these guys first.
So when we have a lane width of of exactly one, we need to have some
of these other values specified.
And this is kind of a dummy function.
Again, it's just to make it work, Lane, V3 from V3, same thing.
And I think that actually should just work everywhere though.
I don't think this needs to be specified uniquely.
I think that can just be something that's the same for everybody would
be my assumption.
Lane you 32 from u-32 as well.
Again, that's just going to be a dummy function.
See here.
So this is going to be laying F32 from you, 32 Lane, you 32 from you
32.
And then we've got sort of the gather and expect zero stuff extract
zero.
I feel like that is also one that will just work.
I don't think there's any magic to that one.
That should be fine.
We need the The Pact one of those.
So in this case, one of the things that's confusing about this guy is
that we'd be throwing away information here in this case.
I think that's probably fine, though.
This is really, the only case where we're doing something.
In the reason we're doing it this way, is because it is a random
Number.
So I think that's probably fine.
It's kind of hard to say right, but I think that's probably fine.
So I'll let that slide and I like I said, I think that's okay.
But yeah, if that comes back to bite us, well, you know, who to blame,
it was me.
So yeah, in this case, we'll just use the lower one and that should be
fine.
So now we just need sort of the gather and lerp stuff.
The Gather stuff is
Is actually pretty straightforward, right?
It's really just not going to do any Gathering.
It's just going to do a single, it's going to do a single grab.
So if we take a look at gather F32, which I think is the primary one
we need here, when the lane width equals 1, we still have to do that,
right?
And so it's going to give us the same things, really?
All that's happening.
Here is
This right here, this Lane you 32 is obviously only one thing so it's
really just Index, right?
And it's so it's just index time stride with base pointer and that's
you know, equal directly to the result.
So you're really just talking about doing one of the multi lookups
that's in there.
If that makes sense.
Lerp gather V3.
So does V3.
Can that be generalized gathered B3?
I think it can.
So I think that one as well, just should have been written outside.
All right.
No Globe operator found, which takes type.
Blaine V3.
so, last one here,
So yes, this can this just be moved out?
Right after and has Type F32.
So, I guess that one can't really be done that way because of the, and
So that kind of needs to be done.
Yeah, we allow that that operator there.
I don't, we're not allowed to overload, operators between primary
types like that.
I don't think so we're not allowed to add the correct type in there
for our situations which is unfortunate.
So what I would say is that probably has to be something that's done
special case in this case, right?
Oops, nope, not that.
so this right here where we're doing the sands,
I'm not really sure.
Yeah.
How to deal with that since we're doing that.
Okay.
So the way we'll do that is operator and
We'll just go ahead and make one of those in the actual Lane with one,
and we'll just make it do the cast appropriately, right?
So what we'll do here is we'll say, all right, do the and operation
with this as if it were you 32, right?
So in this case, right to the end with it, as if it were, you 32,
please.
And then you know, when you're done with that,
Give me back a value, which I can then.
You know, make equal to a float.
And it's just, you know, why can't you do an end of the float?
I don't know, like you the processor can so I don't know why you
can't.
But you know oh well that's just the way it goes sometimes.
All right, so now we've got our parlor problem and this is really just
an order of deck, order of like, where these are declared for now.
I'm going to put to do here.
and just say, if the lane width is not equal to 1,
Because we can't, we can only have that in the case, for the lane
width is not equal to 1, right?
So now, we've got this running scalar wise, exactly.
With, with all the same stuff that would be running in the wide case,
so we can freely switch between them.
And so, what I'd like to do is just take a minute, see if we can debug
the
Debug the scalar version first and get that producing a reasonable
image.
And then, once we've got that going, then switch back over to the wide
version and yeah, try to make that produce a reasonable image as well,
right?
Of course, the other problem is here is, I don't know if we're
actually getting stuck in like this, this could just be slow because
of the changes that we made.
I also don't know if this is just, we should probably
Yeah, so you can see that we've got a bug here, right?
The scalar version, no longer works correctly.
So in all those changes that we did, we do have some sort of problem,
which is fine, we were kind of expecting that.
So, let's go ahead and take a look.
At what's going on in the code.
Sue.
Start by coming through here and checking out what our values actually
are.
And okay, that's doesn't look like a a no decompile to me.
was that actually, you know, decompile because it sure didn't seem
like one
Oh sorry we're still threaded.
Let's go ahead and stop that.
Okay.
And now we can jump in.
So, here is US getting all of our values out.
And I'm going to take a look at what they all are.
So the Rays per pixel.
Let's go ahead and switch out of hex.
The raise per pixel is 1024.
That's what we expect.
The bounce count is eight also expect the film width and height look
pretty reasonable to me, certainly nothing too out of the ordinary
there.
Same with the pixel stuff, and the film location and the center looks
okay.
All of that stuff.
Looks pretty reasonable Acts.
Why?
Z and position.
The random series looks fine.
That's computed is initialized to 0.
Final color is all zeros as we expect the lane with is now set to 1
the line.
Ray count is 1024, which is correct and we are verifying that it
multiplies back out the contribution for Pixel is 1 over 10 24, right?
Which is exactly right.
And then we start looping through.
We produce our offsets here, those look pretty good.
We go through our way origin redirection and we know that the hit
stuff seems to work.
Okay.
So it's really the emission stuff that's probably wrong.
We'll go because that's exactly the bug we had before, where the
emitter wasn't going such that masking operation looks wrong.
we started out, but I'm just
I'm through discussing.
We made a lot of changes.
Let's let's make sure that everything is roughly coherently.
Mass looks good going through these and introducing the initial
startup setup looks good.
There, the lane increment looks good, that's the computer.
Got incremented properly.
We're pulling out the various clean informations, and those look
pretty good.
Distance, hit mask.
That looks pretty good.
Looks pretty good to me.
So that looks like that operated properly sphere index.
Looks pretty good.
That looks less good.
Oh, but that's okay because those can be Nan's because they're
actually not the mask is not going to let them assign.
So that's actually fine.
No worries there.
So those look pretty good.
Now let's see what happens when we do our gather.
We know that the material index that we hit was one.
And so let's take a look at what we gather out for are three values.
Are emission color is 0.
Our rough color is grey.
Our scatter is zero is that similar to what we would have expected?
Yes, it is.
So that's good.
At least that gather worked properly.
We're going to add our, you know, whatever week.
Here.
We're going to add that in the lane masking should have masked this
off to zero if it was out, but it's in.
So it wouldn't have done anything there.
So we go ahead and add this emit color which is already zero in.
We then mask off, anywhere the hit Jimmy.
We then mask off from the lane mask anywhere, where we didn't hit.
Now we did.
So we keep going.
And that's fine.
We compute our stuff and our next bounce here looks pretty reasonable
normalizer 0.
Everything seems fine.
We are not zero.
So we keep going.
Jimmy, Here Comes our bounce.
So the lane increment is still one our bounces.
Computed.
We've now, computed the second bounce.
We're taking a look here.
We do not hit here so we should expect you to stay at its current
value.
What
Is happening here.
It's because the yeah, the denominator probably didn't.
This isn't going to hit right?
Yeah.
Okay so it's not gonna hit, that's fine.
So now we're going to go through here, we're going to find a hit
probably right hit mask zero.
Actually, we may not be finding it remade, just hit the sky.
Right.
Oops.
That crap.
I went too fast.
Well, so the metal color here that we loaded is just garbage.
So, it looks like our gather is not working properly, either that or a
mask is not working properly, right?
So it looks like when we went to grab this, that's our culprit.
Now I may be able to just go back up here.
And do a sit next statement.
I don't know if that'll actually work or not.
It may very well not but let's take a quick look here and see if we
can see if that actually would work or not.
So the base pointer in this case we are expecting it to be pointing to
a material right but we're spending to be pointing to a particular
index off of particular material.
So right, if we go back to the Lane stuff where we do like a gathering
Are the base pointer, we're taking the address of a particular member
of the base pointer.
So, where we do our gather V3 in here.
We're looking at World materials Arrow emit color, right?
and if we take a look at,
Where am it color is?
It's the bottom of this guy, right?
We also are going to look at what the stride is.
Let me see.
So base pointer should be pointing to the emit color.
If I do this,
I should see the color there 345 of whatever the material, the first
material is.
So let's verify that I'm actually seeing that first right.
So inside, right out, CPP, where we set those colors 3, 4 5 is
actually exactly what it is.
So that's all fine.
You got the floating-point rounding error there that's which is fine.
It just can't represent exact exactly 3, for example.
That's right.
Exactly.
Point 3.
So looking at that, that looks okay.
What does the stride equal?
And let's take a look at the material here is 28 and
Indices.
In this case.
He just sees zero.
All right, um so yeah in this case that all looks pretty good.
And I'm not sure why the result would be borked, but let's keep going.
So maybe the bug is in gather F32.
So let's taste step in and take a look.
We know that this should gather a three for us.
So let's see.
So we're going to take the base pointer.
We're going to add the index times, a stride, which should just add
nothing.
We're going to use that as an F32, and we're going to get a result
out, right?
So, there's that result of 3, which is what we expected.
There's the result of three
The result of Y for result of x 5.
So back we come to here.
Let's step into the lane mask.
Oh, so it looks like this is where we messed up perhaps.
So here we go.
We have a lien V3.
We're trying to mask off or trying to mask it by a.
We treat the X y&z as ah, I know what the problem is here.
Yeah, this is again, the same problem that we were having before with
masks is that the processor just produced that unitary mask.
So, we actually already faced this problem before, right?
It's this guy right here,
So we need to convert The Mask first before we use it into something
that's proper, right?
So we need to do like a equals a like that so that when the masking
happens that happens in the way we would expect, right?
So, that's a little bit trickier because again, it's sort of cheating
on what the operators supposed to do and I don't actually love it.
So, yeah, so that looks better now, and that may have been the only
problem we were having with that.
So, let's, let's just see for a second.
Let me see what happens if we actually run this now, so I can get a
sense for what's going on.
Off we go and men were so much slower.
Now I don't know exactly what we did.
That was so much slower.
It'd be interesting to go see, but something that we did with when we
were going to wider things.
Facts.
You know what I could do to is I could change the re Camp something we
did was real bad, right?
I'm not sure it's the what he was, but something we did was real bad.
So let's go ahead and go back to the re-cap here.
Oh, you know what it was?
We turned off the CPU.
Multiplier never mind.
Yeah, so still a lot slower than it used to be obviously, but not
nearly as slow as all that.
So because I would expect to slow down again.
I expect a slow down from running scalar with code, that can't take
advantage of any of the scale Earnest of it.
Because again, it's just, you know, it's now it's doing all these
sorts of operations that are because it has to be Lane wide.
And you know, that's that's not what scalar code wants to do scalar
code.
Doesn't, you know, can do use real ifs and avoid Computing things, and
all those other sorts of things.
Whereas we can't, you know, we can't get away with that once we sort
of have to do it generically that works across any Lane with, right?
So off we go and now we can see whether that produced and it's not
that much lower.
I mean it's significant because you know, we were getting nine mil
point, you know, we were getting we're getting .002 more milliseconds,
more per bounce, right?
So it's definitely bad.
But it's, you know, it's four times slower three times, slower
something like that in scalar form, which we probably could figure out
how to improve, but at least when we look at it now we're getting the
correct results, right?
So that's good.
So now if we go ahead and set the lane with up, we at least hear that
the structure is correct, but we probably have bugs in our lane
implementation and so, we have to go now.
Figure out what those bugs are, because when we run it in length mode,
it's still wrong, actually, but we just run it this way, I suppose.
So, here it is in Lane mode.
And off it goes and it's doing its thing.
And
Yeah, and there we go.
So with doing these, you know, we don't really get a speed-up, which
is kind of weird.
So something's kind of odd in there and we're gonna have to go look at
this.
In more detail, we get a quite a speed up over the bad scalar version.
But remember our good scalar version was around this feed.
So it was all a wash.
If we don't get any more speed Improvement, then that, but before we
can look into that at all, we have to first figure out why we're not
working properly.
Because that's kind of a separate problem altogether, right?
So you can see here.
We're getting some really bizarre.
It's kind of interesting what we're seeing.
Honestly I am not 100% sure how to
what that pattern represents but you know, interested to find out.
So anyway, let me go ahead and compile that.
Let's go back to the
Sort of slow mode.
And just take a look at what's going on in the, in the wide version of
the code.
So in the wide version of the code, let's step in here.
And first, verify that any of these values or even correct.
I assume that most of them are because that image is kind of starting
to be close to correct, right?
Like things were sort of in the right place, the sky was in the right
place so it would be weird if any of these values.
We're super odd.
In terms of what they represented and so you can see 1000 is the
x-axis.
That's what we expect 0.065.
I'll be honest with you.
That's not what I would have expected for the Y value.
Wait was I oh I wasn't on the Y value.
That's why.
Now I was that that doesn't look like a right.
Y value to me though.
What happened here?
that, that doesn't
look like the Y value we had before.
What's, what's going on there?
That's obviously correct.
I, I don't.
I think that's right, though.
so, I'm just looking at this value and, you know,
These are all represented across, right?
So we're looking at the vector is coming down this way and that just
doesn't look like that would sum to 1 when squared, right?
I mean,
Those aren't sufficiently High values to some 21.
So I feel like this normalizer 0 cure is not doing the right thing.
So I'm going to kind of come in here and see what's going on.
So, let's see.
We've got
length squared of this vector and that's just going to be well, you
know what, let's just step right into it, actually,
So let's check a look at the.
Let's check a look at the inner product here and so this is just going
to do sort of those small pieces like multiples of those small pieces,
right?
So if you look at A and B and results, these are all actually just
replicated across so I should see if I look at these Lane, be threes,
I should see the inner product being just whatever it would be in
this.
And that's exactly what we see.
It's this squared plus this squared plus that squared.
Yep.
So that that looks right to me.
No worries there so that length Square looks.
Looks correct.
This mask value.
That's going to be a greater than comparison with the square here.
So let's take a look at that obviously a times a in this case, right?
That is whatever that is.
So
That's just going to produce a 1 or a 0 in this Lane.
You 32 should write.
It should just produce the mask that we want.
All apps are not all laughs, right?
So let's take a look here at like the, you three, two versions and
they're all positive.
Right, so that's good.
So then we go into the conditional assignment here.
Here is the result value that we actually wanted.
Oh, that's
No, that's right.
That's right.
So that result value should be all set to zeros.
We've got a mass but it's all set to ones and then we have a value
coming in here that's going to be whatever.
The a value is x 1 over the square root.
Let's see how that actually gets computed.
Here's the script PS of a so that that should be about 10 right?
Should be what we end up with.
In this case.
And that's exactly what we get.
So that's good.
That's all working properly.
So now we're going to invert that and get point one, right?
And that's again.
Looking right.
We then multiply by a, which was itself what did we say that was that
was oh, that's a vector of 010, whatever rights that's going to
normalize it down.
So let's take a look at what that is.
This should be our normalized Vector now.
There's the zero.
There's the one and that's looking great.
Right now, we go into conditional assign conditional, assign is going
to do the conditional assignment on each of these separately.
So it's going to use the source X, The Source, Y and the source is
easy, and it's going to use the desk decks dust.
Why invest Z with the masking value here we come into
She was assigned.
The first thing we're going to do is take that mass value and convert
it to a PS value, right?
And so if we take a look at the M 128 and we look at it as if it were
a youth or youth or D2.
That's our problem.
This is not right.
This is supposed to be a cast for some reason I did a convert and it's
supposed to be a cast.
So that's that's probably a huge source of a lot of bugs right there.
Remember convert actually takes the value.
That's of the integer and turns it into a floating point.
Value that has that same value.
That's not what we want here.
We want it to just pretend it was
I the exact B just stuff them in and call them afloat, whatever they
are, right?
And that's not what we were getting there.
So let's try that one more time.
Let's jump back here to the conditional assignment.
Whoops.
Well, that was not what I wanted to do.
How come we didn't break point here, someone's calling this, right?
Some point.
There we go.
So this should be called on that normalizer 0.
We should be an exact same place because the first one.
So, let's take a look at what we're passing here.
So the source,
And the dest in this case, doesn't matter.
Let's take a look at that.
Massive value.
Is it should be all ones, it is.
So now we're going to do with the and not and the and of the mask with
the to Source values.
Let's double check that we get what we expect.
So cures are dest excerpts, Test X desc, why dust
Z and we're going to step through it, and we should see these get
assigned to the right values now and they are okay.
So that's much better.
And now these values are going to probably look more sane to me.
Yep.
Okay, so let's try running this one more time so that I can see what
the image looks like.
And that will guide my debugging, probably as I look through for the
next set of Errors.
So I'm going to change this to 0-2.
And I'm going to return it to allowing it to use the full core count
so that we can quickly just run the image test.
Right?
So often goes doing its images, whatever stuff it's doing and hey we
got a little bit faster pronounce to so that was something but you
know, whatever.
So now here's our test bitmap and you can see we got better, right?
We definitely got better, but we still have a problem with that
Omission masking, right?
So we're not quite there yet.
We're now kind of more towards where we were when we first ran the
other one, right?
And I'll make sure that there were not seeing something deleterious
there.
We'll just run it again and it should produce exact same image.
But so now we knew there's something strange going on.
We're not really sure what it is, but there's something strange going
on here with the emission, tracking again, because we're clearly
getting the right hits on
On the first time through.
But then, as we Trace, those subsequent, raise Something That We're
caring for words is getting borked, right?
And so we need to go step through there and see there's two ways.
That could be going wrong again.
One of them is The Gather could be wrong, obviously.
So we could have a bug in the gather.
The other thing that could be wrong is we could have a bug in the the
masking or however that emission stuff is getting carried forward.
Let's take a really quick look at the gathered here.
Right here is our gather F32 which is really all we actually use.
and this gather,
F32 here.
just want to make sure that these two things are commensurate
or not, commensurate, but are sort of equivalent.
So these are the two gather functions we have.
We have the base pointer version which goes like baseball nurse.
Tried indices, right?
And then we have the the one that just does.
The Straight Ahead index here.
And it looks like these are basically the same, right?
I there's nothing.
I don't see anything too.
Wonky going on here.
Looks
Looks reasonable, right?
So it's Jimmy, we got a decent base pointer there, we should be able
to track extract those indices exactly.
As it's being shown there and I don't see any really particular reason
why.
I don't see anything in particular, that, that should be causing us a
problem with that gather.
So I'm going to go ahead and say, let's step through the code here.
Let me convert it back down.
I think we're almost there.
So, let me go ahead and convert this to an o.d.
and, and go back to One Core account there.
Like so.
and so, what I'm going to do here is say, let's assume that most of
this
I was working correctly for now and let's just Target our debugging
first at sort of that ending.
Part, where do we go here?
Right here, where we're actually trying to gather stuff up.
So, let's take a look at the mat emit color.
And let's take a look to see what we actually gathered there.
Madam it color, matte ref color and Matt scatter.
So here are what we gathered for these.
In this case.
And let's also take a look at what the index was supposed to be.
So hit, Matt Index, right?
All right, so our hit Matt index.
In this case, here are the what we think we hit so in this bundle of
rays we think we always hit sort of that ground plane I think so we're
probably focusing on just a little section down in the corner right
where there's nothing else to hit.
So all of our raise that went out through the pixel.
They all hit the same thing and that's probably going to be true most
of the time like because we're sampling a single Pixel.
Probably the first hit is going to be all
Same material, right?
That's just probably going to be true for most of the time now, right
on the edges, it won't be true but, you know, so we'll take a look
here.
We see that we're getting all ones.
So we should be gathering up the same values for the rest of the
stuff.
The scatter.
Where we look at what the scatter value is.
It should be all the same.
When we look at what the reflection color is that again.
Should also be all the same.
Right?
Here's its .5.
There should be 0.5 is here and it should be 0.5 is here because
that's that ground plane.
I think it's just a great reflected.
Plain, the emission color should be all zeros which you know, it is.
And that's all fine.
So that's all good, right?
So that seems pretty straightforward.
It looks like that gather maybe work properly.
It's a little artichokes, the all at the same things.
That could be that The Gather doesn't quite work right when you have
different indices.
So, that's sort of still leaves a little bit of, you know.
Well, maybe this could still be wrong happening there.
So, we've got the sample that we're summing.
Summing up here for like the Reds greens, blues, and so on the magnet
colors.
Nothing.
The attenuation is 1.
So in this case, we should just see that this sample didn't change at.
All right.
That's you know what?
We are going to see the lean mask.
On the other hand, all the hits were valid, so the lane mask should
stay the same right.
And let's verify that.
That's the case because that may be wrong.
And so it didn't, this is the kind of thing I was suspicious of.
You can see the hit Matt index here, not equal to 0 that was that is
not working and I don't know why.
So that's the thing that we next kind of need to to investigate
So let's step into that Ling mask.
Here we are.
Replicating this value out.
Let's see.
Oh,
So, see here.
So V, what is the value representing?
The really representing is 0.
So in this case we should end up with all zeros and in this case we do
so that looks right.
We've got a not equals operator.
Oh, and this was some nonsense that I sort of put in here.
So maybe I kind of did this stupidly, you know that could be.
That could be the problem.
So we've got an A and A B, right?
And we want to know if they're equal to each other.
So here's our a value in our B value, and if we're doing this as an
Epi, you can see that 1 is 1 and 1 is 0.
So what I expect to get here is the not equal to each other, should
actually return true.
And so let's see what it actually does return.
It returns false.
So this was just me being a bit of a dingus here, and it looks like
that is just a, not smart way to do it.
Now let's think this through, so when we do a comparison for equals,
this should have come back 0, right?
And so if I were to do a next-door of 0 with 0, I would have thought
that I would have gotten ones because it's exclusive or so, it should
be.
Oh no.
It's exclusive, or it has to be ones to flip it.
One slip zeros leaves the same.
Yeah, that's just, that's just a mental mental, fart right there.
So let's go back to that.
That's that's the problem.
Case you were wondering.
Let's see here.
Copy Q.
Yeah, so that was just me kind of being lost in the shuffle here,
doing something dumb.
That's not going to work at all because the exclusive art it has to be
exclusively.
Or if it's zeros I wanted to put the ones if it's ones on to put the
zeros which means I would have to put ones in there.
This would have to be right.
Set, one epi32
Of that right now.
Again, I don't think this is probably the best way to do this because
there's probably a smarter way.
We could get that to happen.
What we want to do here is we want to flip those bits and so I'm
trying to think of the thing that loads the least information
And I just don't know exactly what this going to be.
So I'm going to go ahead and put it to do here.
Because it's probably something that I thought about it for a few
seconds, I be like, oh yeah, it's this.
But you know on stream sometimes it's kind of confusing.
When you're talking things out, you make some dumb mistakes.
Anyway, and it's hard to think through little things like that, I
could do it on the Blackboard, probably is where we should do it.
So let's get back in there now and let's take a look at what happens
in that code.
So now we should be getting a result.
That's that's equal to one and we do.
So that's just that was again just being kind of dumb there.
Okay, so now Arlene mask should be set properly and it is and let's
see if that fixes our problem because I think that was a would have
been a big part of it, right?
Because then our lanes would get masked off in properly.
Let's go back here and we need a quick way to switch the build between
these two things.
I wonder if what we could do.
It's like a pragma optimize off kind of a thing.
I wonder if we could do a thing here where we just do well we'll look
at that in a second.
I guess.
Yeah.
Alright, so let's go ahead and try running that.
So off it goes.
And so again we've haven't proved our time but we haven't improved it
that much, which is kind of disappointing.
So even if this is correct we still a lot of work to do looking at
these two images.
It looks like we're still a little bit wrong here, right.
Here's our test bitmap and here's our
Here's our test-fit map and here's our reference bitmap.
It looks honestly almost like we've got some kind of like, we're not
using the scatter value at all, like the scatter values getting load
wrong loaded wrong or it was set wrong, one of the other, right?
Because it looks like these are getting set to sort of a more
reflective surfaces or something's weird.
So we're not quite out of the woods yet but we're a lot closer than we
were certainly
Right.
Okay.
So
Again looking here we're Computing roughly the same total number of
bounces as before we're a little bit faster than we were but we would
have expected to maybe get more more significantly faster like 2X or
something.
Hopefully out of this and we didn't.
So we're going to have to look into how how and why we're getting slow
down.
It could be that a lot of time is spent doing extra work, maybe those
those widths, the maybe we're not able to fill all for as often as we
would have liked to or something like
It's and we're just wasting a lot of time.
Loading up materials that don't actually exist or something like this.
You know, who knows?
So yeah, what I would say here is we need to kind of think this
through a little bit more and now we need to kind of also think about
where, you know, we've got some bug.
Math somewhere and we need to figure out exactly where that is.
So this can be a little bit difficult to do.
And one of the things that we would probably like to do at this point
is run these two things through sort of some kind of a set of test
that verifies whether they're all working properly with respect to the
scalar version.
So something that was is going to compare like a pixel to a pixel as
you kind of Step through it and see that they're getting the same.
It's in both cases, right?
And that is something we can actually sort of do.
We can compile this both ways and run them versus each other.
Unfortunately, this is harder to do than it.
Should be what you really want to be able to do is the have the
debugger understand this and allow you to run two versions at the same
time and show you the results from both of them because, you know,
that you'd see there as soon as they diverge, you know, you'd be like,
Oh, okay, that's where the bug is, right?
But what I'm going to do before that just in case we can do it quickly
and the stream early without to go too much into that stuff, is I want
to look really quickly at what we've got here in our four wide
version.
And just see if there's anything obviously stupid that we're doing.
So for R, less than operator.
We are doing a comp less than for a less than or equal to.
We are doing a less than or equal to write for greater than we are
doing greater than so that's nice.
A greater than equal to.
We are doing greater than or equal to
Four equals.
We've got equals 4, not equals B, but not equals and for nought equals
with you 32s.
We are doing this sort of weird thing that I messed up the first time,
but that it's working this time.
All right, for xor operator.
We've got
The xor operator properly, right done for our.
And we have an and for and with you 32s we have one that casts not
converts but casts the, a up to a PS and then does it returns a PS?
Which is what we want for and not we have an end not for or we have an
or for shift, we have a shift left immediately.
It and it's a logical shift that's going to kind of shift up there is,
and that looks proper for a shift right?
We have a shift, right, logical?
Which again, is also what I believe is supposed to happen there.
Now, I don't know that that's actually true.
It could be that they want a shift with right arithmetic.
Forex or shift and so I should double-check that.
Well.
Okay.
That's, I guess not what I wanted to know, but I guess what I would
say is presumably unsigned versus signed would say, which one it would
do in C.
And since we took a look at the Wikipedia code in C, if that code was
correct then and of course, we're just trying to match the other code.
Anyway then all of these were done as you 32s so it should be a
logical shift.
Left.
Right.
And so that is what it is and that's good.
So Arlene F.
32 ad is an ad Arlene.
F32 adieu 32 is a DPI right?
That looks good.
Our subtract and our mole or both exactly what we would expect.
There's a sub.
There's the mole right are divided is again exactly what we would
expect.
Our conversion is a conversion.
I r.
Set reverse is a set reverse.
This one doesn't matter really the order because it's just random it,
only loads Randomness anyway, are set one here, which replicates both
cases.
The replication looks right to me set 1, PS or set one epi depending
what you're reloading.
Yeah.
So that all looks good to me.
The square root is an M squared, which is exactly what we want it to
be the conditional, assign.
We checked and isn't and not, and with the cast we had messed that up
originally, but we fixed it.
The Min and the max, so Min is properly calling Min and Max is
properly calling Max.
So I think that should be fine.
We've got to gather F32 here that we checked and we think is working
properly.
The mask is zeroed.
It does the mauve mask that looked proper.
We could test it, we didn't test it, horizontal add, we don't have
much reason to suspect being wrong but you know, if it was.
So let's take a look here at the clamp
01.
So this we really could translate out.
Again, we could keep translating some of these out again, even more so
than they already are.
But if we take a look here at this, clamp 01, this is these are all
these in here are special as well.
So we probably need to verify those really quickly in addition, right?
Sue.
Yeah.
Why do we only Define struct Lane V?
Three lane with not equal to 1.
I guess because they happen to be the same but they don't really need
to do that anymore.
Can't we do this?
I'm sorry.
Can't we just do this universally now?
I guess I don't need to do it now but we should to do.
So in here, we've got internally an F32, and we've got operator + A
and B.
We are lofting the beat up by replicating and doing the ad, that's
what we would expect to do, I think, in either case.
So that seems fine to me in both cases.
Plus this plus minus is minus it all looks good.
Times this times, in both cases, divide is divided.
Plus equals does exactly what you'd expect.
For both, you 32s and F 32s.
- does what you expect x equals does as well.
Divide equals does to and equals
As well X or equals as well.
Or equals as well.
Operator equals.
Looks solid.
The negation operator, we had to implement manually, but that looks
reasonably, right?
If we want to negate something we can simply subtract it from zero,
and that will produce the negative value.
So that seems fine.
The multiplication operator on V3, s is just the multiplication
operator times, whatever the line value is there that seems
reasonable.
The operator star again the same
so, greater than is greater than
less than is less than
and, and is, and X, Y, and Z, XY & Z conditional assignment for you
32s.
Just uses the and not.
And the clamp 01 uses.
The Min and Max of the values of the maximum, whichever one of
Is higher and whichever one of these is lower.
That looks right too.
So most everything in there, looks the same to me.
So I'm not 100% sure why we're getting the difference and just to sort
of put some
There's the lane for version.
and if I go ahead and set the lane width,
Oops.
21.
I should now be able to run this and yeah, and get
Get a respective version of what it looks like when it's running
scalar and I thought the scalar version returned the correct result.
If we're lucky, this scalar version, only looks like a train the
crocodile and they actually return the same results so that we're
actually wrong in both paths, but I think the scalar version return
the right result.
I can't quite remember
So, there we go.
Let's take a look now at the two images and so you can see the scalar
version is definitely correct.
and the
The sliced one is not.
So there's Lane 4 and this is Lane one.
So you can see that there's just when we switch between those, it just
looks like for some reason we're getting like, you know, honestly, the
most looks like the normal is like sheared or something.
I'm not sure quite what to make of it.
It's pretty hard to guess.
Exactly what that is.
It just looks like maybe the scattering is not really doing much.
Maybe.
That's what I'm going to do here, just to see.
I'm just curious.
I want to see if my hunch is correct.
So I'm going to take a look at the scatter and, you know, the way the
scatter works right, is we take the scatter and we go from, you know I
got to say we picked a really unfortunate name for that because
scatter it really should be the other way around, instead of scatter.
It should have been called, it should have gone from.
If scatter was Zero, it should have gone from a pure bounce.
So these these two terms,
It should be inverted, right?
In my opinion.
And I kind of want to fix that, right?
We could call it something other than scatter.
So for example,
If zero is pure to fuse.
Right.
Like why did we do it that way?
Why is it called scatter?
Instead of specular?
I don't know, right?
Yeah, that's that's just I.
Yeah, I have no idea.
Okay.
So what I want to do here is say well, what would happen if we
forestall the specular values 21 anyway, right, is that what that
roughly looked like?
I mean, it doesn't seem like it because,
It doesn't seem like that's exactly what happened.
Right?
Because some of these things aren't reflective.
Like that doesn't look reflective, but it definitely looks like these
things are getting more reflective, right?
and I guess the other thing though, too, is, they're getting
reflected, but they're also getting shifted a little
Right?
Like so I want to see what the difference is there.
Let me, let me just see.
So when the mat specular comes back, what I want to do here is I'm
going to go into re dot CPP, and I want to go ahead and take a look.
In the materials, if I was to just set a bunch of these artificially
to be more scattery, right?
So our more specular, right?
So if I just set these up quite a bit,
so let's say, I just set everything to be real reflective, right?
And maybe that's a little too high, you know?
Maybe it shouldn't be one, but I'm just curious what I get out.
And again, this is here, I'm running the actual, the scalar version.
So this is the one that we believe to be correct.
For our purposes and you know we don't actually know if it's all that
correct.
I mean there could have been bugs the original, but we know this is at
least producing the same results as what we were getting before.
And so we'd like to get the other one producing these results and I
want to see what it thinks a more specular version looks like again
just trying to get a feel for what the bug might be in this case.
And so let's just go ahead and let that do its thing.
What's the kind of curious?
How much CPU usage?
Do we end up using?
So that's what we want to see, right?
Like we want to see our CPU, usage.
Maxed
So that's kind of nice and, you know, it doesn't mean we're doing a
good job, we might be wasting a lot of the Cycles, which of course we
are for not using 70 for example, but at least we know we're not
leaving anything in machine idle.
So let's take a look at what that looks like.
So here's that bitmap, right?
And yeah, I think you can really see that.
It's definitely skewing, right?
It's not, it's not just specular.
It's skewing.
So, I wonder if that just means our bounce computation is borked right
in some way because the specular, the specular does not shift like
that.
It just makes it clearer.
So that's good information for us, right?
I alright, so that tells me that I kind of want to take a look at how
that Loops at how
that bounce computation is is being done.
So you can see here, we've got the random by lateral stuff happening
here.
That we then convert to Elaine V3, where we take the next normal, and
we add it and we normalize it.
So, what I want to know here is are these random bilaterals being
computed properly.
A are the
are there is the normalizer 0 actually working properly be and then
the lerp is also
Suspect in this case, right because both lerp random.
Bilateral, and normalizer zero are not very heavily.
Used solar power, for example is used nowhere else.
Right random
Lateral is used only in one other place, which is in a place that we
wouldn't notice Badness in it very much.
Especially, because remember, that's just picking off sets within a
pixel.
And then normalizer 0 is only used in the startup code in the
redirection.
And to be fair, I think in the right direction, it wouldn't even
really matter very much in a lot of cases.
So we definitely are dealing with some highly suspect code there.
We want to verify each of these pieces of code.
Let's take a look at what they're doing so we can maybe get a better
feel for what's happening in them, right?
So I'm going to take a look at where lerp exists and one of the.
Again, one of the things here is that because lerp exist in multiple
places that's also a bit of a warning sign, in this case, I think,
Because it's it's also making me a little bit worried that maybe like
the scalar version since it doesn't have to use this particular
version of it.
Maybe this particular version of it is just kind of busted, right?
So in this case we're doing a 1 point 0 minus t times a plus T times
B.
That's the standard lerp that you would normally expect to see.
Let's just find out what that does.
Right?
Let's go take a look at what that does.
In this case.
So, let's go ahead and return ourselves to a lane width.
Oops.
A for and let's go ahead and take off the 02 and we'll put the core
count back to one.
Okay, so now I'm going to go ahead and take a look at that lerp
function.
I'm going to run to the lerp function in here, it is.
So I've got an a vector and a b Vector.
These two vectors are wide, right?
So they have four elements each and you know, maybe we can.
Oops.
maybe we can kind of get
a little more space in here.
Actually see these.
So you can see here that I've got four different values in my X, and
my Y in my Z.
Each of these is a different vowel, is a different normal Direction.
And so I've got two different possible answers.
One of these represents the bounce, one of these represents the
scatter.
And so, what I want to do here is say all right, I want to do 1, minus
ta + TB,
Let's step into the parts of that separately.
So here is the first operator times, it's going to be a times b.
A in this case, if we come back out, I think we're doing this.
Part right here.
So the T value, if we look at what T actually is T is just 0
everywhere so we should get none of be at, all right?
It should just be a, in fact, we can just quickly verify that is true.
So in this case, the result should just, it should be equivalent to a
exactly.
And if it's not, we've got an issue.
So, there we go.
That's exactly right.
No problem there, right.
Let's take a look again and see if we can get another T value in here.
Let's see if we can find a t-value where the T value is equal to
something else.
Not doing great.
It's run for a little while.
And stop again.
Run for a while.
So anytime the scatter value I'm sorry the specular value is 0, it's
going to be at equal zero there.
So it's going to take us a while to get to something that we actually
want to see.
You probably be doing this with something less than 1024 race per
pixel if I was smart, but apparently I'm not.
Let's try that.
Oops.
That's just going to do one bundle, right?
So let's stop here.
Hopefully we can eventually get a t value to something else.
There we go.
So with the T value of one, that's another good test value.
That is exactly what we would want to see for result to equal.
Be precisely so let's make sure that that works.
Okay 5 -1 + 4 so that looks relatively convincing to be honest.
So that doesn't seem like particularly suspect to me.
Both the min/max worked properly so I'm not so sure there's anything
going on wrong there.
Which is too bad.
Anyway, the redirection itself.
Let's see how we do in terms of normalizing.
That's
doesn't look too bad.
You know, we can spot check some of these
So if we were to take say, you know, point four times two point four
plus 0.9 times point nine plus 0.05 times 0.05 we do get something
very close to 1.
So the normalized version of this seems good and plus that's actually
point six and so I assume that if that was actually being done to full
Precision.
Yeah.
So those look like they are plausibly.
Normalized values.
You know, I could believe that, right?
So the other question here is well random bilateral, you know what's
going on in there.
I'm not really sure.
Let's step into this.
And see, here's our X or shift.
So we come through here and we get out one of these X values.
There's our x value.
Let's actually grab out the part.
We care about which is x dot V.
Dot M 128 I underscore u-32 really easy to remember.
And here's what those values actually look like those look like what
we want which is a bunch of random bits.
And we're going to shuffle them around here.
There's our Shuffle and now we return to our regularly scheduled
program.
So that seems like a reasonable job.
When we actually do one of these, we divide by the you 32, Max there.
So,
Wait, what?
Oh no.
But that's enough 32.
So that's correct.
So we had Lain 32 from you through to the converts up.
Both of those
So that's all good.
Our convert Epi PS should produce, basically floating Point values
that look like these values, right?
That are the same, roughly, the same.
so the fact that these are all exactly the same scale,
Seems bad.
Mmm-hmm, I didn't want this to be opened.
Nope, don't don't do that.
So that seems a bit odd to
So, here's our A.V.
Here are those values.
Here's what they actually are, right?
And now, if I look at the result, that the
And we look at what those are as F 32s.
That just isn't right.
Oh, crud poopies.
I know what's going on here.
So this is because there is no way to load a u-32.
It only loads signed values.
So, it's thinking that these values are signed and the hi B happen to
be set on some of them.
So there's slight.
Yeah.
Is that what it's doing?
I think that's what it's doing here.
So this is really not what we wanted.
So in the lane F32 functions here, we do lean F32 from u-32.
So anywhere we're doing a CVT Pi.
We need it to think this is an integer, I guess is the way I would put
it, right?
And
so when it loaded that in,
It loaded it.
It would be loading it incorrectly.
So, I'm not really sure what to do about that.
I guess we need like, is this all we really need to do so.
So if I were to just do pretend this as an integer,
Would that be sufficient?
Not sure.
So I want to take a look at this here.
So, when I call into random unilateral, I want to know, like, what my
result values are going to be now, are they going to be better?
yeah, that looks
Much better.
All right, all right, all right, all right.
So I think what was happening there is like when we were trying to
load up, say you 32 Max
Or I should say when we were trying to load up the x or shift values
originally?
Well no, that's not right either.
Okay, wait a minute.
I'm getting too far ahead of myself.
Let's bring this back.
There we go.
And I want to take a look at this function.
So it looks like that.
So I may have misspoke there.
That's actually not going to be a problem because it looks like we'd
already loaded those in.
So we were always even though we were converting, it wouldn't matter
presumably because it would treat it as a negative number.
Anyway.
Presumably
I may still be right.
I'll complain why.
I think I might be right in the future, but let's just double check
here.
Do you see how this is never able to produce a value?
Like, let's just verify that, I'm right if I'm right about what's
happening.
Then this will never random unilateral will never be able to produce a
value.
That is
Greater than 0.5 ish.
Let's say 0.6 just to be safe, right?
So if I were to say result dot V Dot Oh Heaven, Help Us, what is that
ridiculous?
Well, you know what here?
So assert that that floating point value.
Is less than 0.6 F.
Let's say if I'm right, we're probably not able to produce values
higher than that.
And hey guess what?
I'm right.
So what I think is happening here is we are loading in a u-32 Max
As a floating Point number.
But when we're loading in these X or shift values, it's thinking of
them as signed values.
So when it's converting from the signed value to the F32, it's only
ever going to be able to produce a short range of negative to positive
which is like negative point five, two point five or something.
Or all the negative numbers because the high positive numbers will be
converted to negative numbers, right?
So what I really need this thing to do is I need this thing to load
the floating Point values as unsigned values, right?
And I don't know if there's a CPU, like what I need?
There is a
Vert epu and I don't know if we actually have that.
We don't.
So we can do multiplication of unsigned values.
We can do ads of unsigned values.
But we cannot unfortunately do a convert of unsigned values, until it
looks like we can.
Well, no, we can never be, can never really do that.
Right, so that's just unfortunately not on the table.
That's what I say about that.
So we have a problem.
And that is our problem.
And how we fix that problem?
I don't know.
We
have these extra shift values.
They're going to be values that range from 0 to 0xffff, right?
And we want to divide them in floating Point by ffffff as well.
It seems like the sanest thing to do at this point is shift off the
sign bit of both of them.
Because if I shift off the sign bit of both of them, then we don't
care.
Since I have no idea what else to do, that seems like the easiest
thing to do and shift off.
I never did what I could and off
Wright could do either of those two things.
That seems like the smartest thing to do.
So for example, let's suppose that I just said well I'm going to shift
down the you 32 Max by one and then in here where I do my ex or shift
I'm going to take that value before.
I actually try to convert it and shift that down by one as well.
Clearing out the top bit.
And crossing my fingers.
Now, if I run it, I should get an assertion almost immediate and I do.
So now we've corrected that bias that was in that part of the code and
hopefully now we could actually run this and get you know, a
reasonable result.
Now why it's running this fast with only one core?
I don't know but I guess.
Yeah.
Well anyway,
So, let's see what we ended up.
Here's our test bitmap oh right because we set, that's right.
We set the ray count down a lot and that's already looking a lot
better.
So let's go ahead and now return to our regularly scheduled program
That was a tricky bug, right?
That was, you know, you kind of had to be pretty Eagle Eye to find
that one.
I gotta say and it's because it was coming from an entropic Source,
it's hard to test, right?
So the only way you could really find that.
So, let's say you had done the unit testing route, like are saying you
would need to have the unit test verify that it returns.
Good distributions on either side.
So you need a really strong unit test.
Do you couldn't you couldn't cheese that one out because it came from
the entropic source which is the harder thing to test because it's in
Bu knows what supposed to return, right?
But yeah.
So there that's you know, if we had done the thing, where we compare
it against the scalar version, which I think would have been a good
thing to do as well, we would have found it.
So that would have been a test that could have found that one as well.
Of course, I found it by hand which is also a good way to find things.
Assuming you find them quick enough which in this case we did.
Alright?
So let's go ahead and see what image we produce if we run for real.
Now, with the full thing
Oops.
So Off to the Races for doing our little rate off, to the ray, says
right.
Well pump, well pump for you there.
So let's see what we get now.
How do we get an image?
That's more?
Sane.
I don't know.
Let's find out, so that looks real good, right?
So now, if we compare say this and this together,
Go ahead and open both of those.
There's one.
There's the other
I do too.
Those look pretty much indistinguishable to me.
All right, all right.
So I think then we can kind of get rid of these other images that we
had in here.
And just slip between these two.
And those look really similar to me again.
They're not going to be exact because they're getting computed,
actually in slightly different ways, but they're pretty close.
So that's pretty good and we managed to get our speed up a little bit.
But I think our speed compared to what I think we would want it to be
is still not great and so it seems like maybe we aren't doing as well
as we should be doing.
There's probably still we probably did some things that aren't great
and they might have to do with say for example this way we're doing
The Gather here, we may have to improve that
I there's a bunch of things we have to do.
I'm going to set a breakpoint on this, I want to know if we ever
actually hit this break.
I going to have to compile and debug mode to do it because the
optimized version is probably going to move stuff around so much that
we would be able to really Target exactly.
But I'm curious to know whether we ever actually zero out, Escape out
properly.
It looks like we do.
So that's good news, right?
Yeah, okay.
So yeah, the last thing I want to do is try doing a significantly less
raise per pixel with this version, just to see what it what it
produces.
And here.
In this case, we can also save off this, this bitmap as our as our
final bitmap to for the day
Right.
It is day three.
Yeah.
So we can we can turn to get that finished up.
and yeah, I think
Well, I want to do was verify that if I drop the race per pixel down
to something lower, I should get a Greenie image.
I want to make sure we're not over counting here, you know because
that's a thing as well.
So that's still pretty smooth.
It's not as smooth.
Hold on a second.
so, it looks like, though we're doing the right thing, looks like,
looks like
Yeah, I just want to make sure we weren't accidentally overcasting,
but it looks like, you know, it's correct.
So we are actually casting the number of rays that we said we would
Yeah, okay.
So I guess now we should probably wrap it up because that concludes
the symbolization of this of this code.
And now we would have to start in on some harder work of figuring out
what slow about it and how we can make it less low.
Right.
And so that's, you know, going to be a lot of sort of tricky working
here.
I am curious to know how much of it is.
From the N way loading because that's some ugly stuff that's happening
right now and I don't know.
To what extent that is is downshifting us.
I'm kind of curious.
So I may just before we stop here,
I may go ahead and take a look at just what the disassembly looks
like.
So, I can see if it's saying or if there's some obviously, really
weird stuff happening.
Inside the loop.
So, let's go ahead and just go to disassembly here.
and,
Just looking around.
You know, all that stuff.
Looks pretty good, just moles and ads.
Here, we are with our bounce count.
Are these all look pretty saying, right?
I mean, they're just Loops through doing tests.
So this actually doesn't look too bad.
It's not great but it's not too bad.
So I guess I'll check one more thing.
What I kind of want to see.
Here is just a measure of the waist so since we have to track the lien
mask anyway what I'd like to do is in addition to bounces computed
here.
What I'd like to track is just how many of these Loops we did as well.
So bounces computed and like, I don't know what we would call this
Loops.
Computed something like this.
Right?
And we'll just increment.
Value?
Computed and Luke's complete computable.
Be computed.
Every million current, every time.
This one only be computed,
This one will only increment per Lane when we're actually doing work
on that lane.
So when we get to the end and we do bounces computed, we can also do
loops computed.
And
Some that in, right?
So in that bounces, computed value, that comes out.
Wait what?
Okay, never mind.
Yeah, that's fine.
When this value comes out, we'll take the loops, computed, and we'll
sort of AD will track that value with a locked increment as well,
right?
So our bats is computed,
Our Loops, computed Loops, computed will will track all that stuff.
Like so.
And then, at the end,
In all the places that we were using that, right?
That's is computed.
Where we do state Loops computed equals 0 and we add it here.
Then we get down to the bottom and we're going to print it out, will
say total bounces, right?
Total loops.
And that way, we know how many Loops we know how much wastage we had,
right.
so, like
Wasted bounces.
Something like this would be like LL U.
LL U % or something like that, right?
Or
2.0 or 0.02 F %, right?
And so then we can do, alright?
We know that we wasted out of the bounces.
This is how many we actually got or I guess we say wasted Lanes or
wasted compute, I don't know what to call this.
What is I'll leave it as that.
So we know we did this many bounces, but we know we did this many
Loops computed, right?
And that should be times the lane with.
So when we're incrementing the superior where we do Loop computed,
right?
This should be actually plus equals the full length with because
that's how many were actually doing, right?
And so once we get this value back, we know that in fact we could
compute this value here which is like wasted bounces we could do like
this.
We might even say it like this.
Here's what we say used bounces is this total bounces, is this wasted
bounces is this and the wasted bounces versus total bounces.
Is the value we're actually looking for here, right?
So 100.0, f, f 32 ft to just make a little percentage out of that,
right?
And off we go.
So that seems fine.
total bounces, we could rename these
used bounces.
Turtle bounces.
Those total - used.
And that should give us an idea of how much waste we actually have in
there, right?
And we can sort of go from there.
So, here we go.
Why am I doing it out there?
I have no idea.
So now hopefully this will track both values and this will give us an
idea of how much Cindy Lane utilisation.
We're actually getting, because one thing that could be happening is
maybe most of the time we end up having one, Ray that bounces in a
bunch of them that don't inside it, inside one wide thing.
And maybe that's why we're not getting speed up, but it looks like
that's not true, right?
We're only wasting 10% of our bounces.
That's just not very many.
So I'm not sure why we don't see more of a speed up when we go to when
we go to Cindy.
So something's wrong with that Loop.
I'm think I'm done for the day.
It's been a long episode already.
So I'm done for the day.
Looking at that will have to be an exercise for next time.
And Folks at home, who want to play around with it, can can do so as
well, so let me go ahead and go to a brief Q&A.
So all right, hold on a second here.
We have a bunch of queues.
So, first of all, some of us saying, didn't replace and equals with
the correct method.
Let's, let's go take a look there and equals
I assume that was old.
That's why old I think I already fixed that.
Is your peer?
Take it grew pretty fast.
No, it's a real beard.
Oh yeah.
Colombian suggested we rename the file properly.
That's right.
What is today 1119.
Pirates, have City for samples of, very smooth.
Could you compare 64 samples with 4y to 64 samples, one might they're
the same.
They still do 64 samples.
In either case because we divide the number of samples by the width.
So 64 samples, one wide or use talk about the speed.
Pregnant stripper, just about speed.
Because this is Judith, floating-point, Precision.
Is there a significant difference between generating a random Float by
dividing, 32 random bits by the max 32-bit integer, but or dividing
24-hour random bits by the maximum 24 bit integer.
I don't think there would be.
That's why I was okay.
Shifting it down, there are things including Point called D, normal
numbers and things like this, but we're not using those and hopefully
those are turned off.
Hopefully, do you know where flush 20?
And so you can actually get in a straightforward IEEE to spec value,
you actually can get more Precision than 24 bits by using a d normal
number.
But I I don't, we're not doing that, so I'm pretty sure that as long
as you have 24 bits /, 24, bits, 25 B, divided by 20 is because you
have that the sign bit as well.
I suppose in there if you wanted to, if you wanted to do it, if you
actually wanted to do the full thing may be but we're not doing that
either, right?
We're adding the sign back in later basically.
So I would say, yeah, 24 by 24 should be fine, but
Don't quote me, I have not really thought too much about that.
So don't quote me on that.
The Lira bulk coach me, I said in a much larger screen that using
operator overloads, 470 could confuse compiler preferring to use
macros, why the change actually?
The I think I explained this yesterday, the reason I didn't do it that
way on this one is because we're still in flux.
So you don't want to do Cindy optimizations on a routine that, you
know, you're going to heavily modify which we are going to sew.
So that's why I have this sort of interim approach, so we can still
get some speed out of it.
I thought it would be more of a speed Improvement.
I have to look at, why?
It's not, but that's basically why it's because I want to be able to
change all these computations in here that when we go through and add
some better lighting calculations.
So that's the same thing.
I didn't handmade hero, I did overloaded operators on handmade hero in
the particle system because we want to be able to fuss with it.
And I didn't do it in the renderer because we knew that route
Was just what that routine was.
Pragma scripts to the reason that I did, that comparison, where I
looked at 122 6512 1024 is I was looking to see whether it does more
samples, but it doesn't look like it does.
So it looks like it does the same number of samples in both cases.
But yeah, if you want to try that, we certainly can.
So if we do raise for Pixel here,
if I was to set this to 64 and recompile,
this is the version with the with the, the lane with
set 24 and that produces this image.
and then if I go through and set the lane with back down,
21.
Here's that.
but,
So something kind of weird about that.
No, that's okay.
Never mind.
That's that's roughly, correct?
Yeah, that seems just occurred to me.
Alright, so here's the two versions.
And they look pretty similar.
Like, I would say the noise level looks comparable to me.
I would like to snap off the Run of this guy there too, as well.
Oops.
What's smaller packing?
Potentially be better, is the packing taking too much time.
So I don't think so, but we haven't profile that yet.
So the next thing we have to do is really profile this thing and find
out where we're spending the time, right?
And so the thing that's kind of troubling about it, right?
Is, if you take a look at at what's going on with the timings, we are
almost four times faster compared to this scalar version.
That's doing the same operations as we are right.
If you look at these two in any in any case, that's what's happening.
We're not faster.
If you compare this version to the scalar version that doesn't have to
do that stuff.
So what it looks to me like is the branching actually is important.
I think I mean you know so we could try here's one thing we could try.
For example is to see to what extent that's true.
Let's say we go back into re dot CPP and we come up here and we say,
all right, let's suppose the early outs were actually really
important.
Well, where were those early outs before, right?
So one of them was, you know, we knew we were going to divide by this
denominator, right?
So we don't really need any of this information at all.
Other than just the, the initial like we don't need the mat index, or
any of that stuff, right?
We don't need to do any of this stuff, if all of the Nam, denominators
are wrong, right?
So, if there's no way that denominator could ever actually do its
thing, right, then we know that that's, that's simply not feasible.
So let's say, we took this and we said we compute the denominator, we
then look at the denominator mask.
If, you know, if mask is zeroed
Just say if not mask is zeroed, right?
Then we're going to do the rest of this stuff.
I could do the same thing again down here with the hit mask, right?
Or the team asked, right?
So we compute the T, well, the team asked, I guess the team asked is
just the thing that says, which of the T values we actually use
No, no.
The team asked, that's true of the team s.
So we add these two together.
We don't have to do any of these assignments.
For example, if the hit mask is then 0, right?
So we could also do this one.
If not mask is zeroed,
Right.
And it looks like the Mad index here also doesn't have to be loaded
till inside of there as well, right?
So you could do that.
Same is true for the planes.
So when we go through testing the planes, we could say, I mean that's
the Spheres same exact thing.
So if you take a look at all the masks terms, we have, we've got the
root mask term.
And we know that.
We can check that one.
We also know, we've got the hit mask just like before, right?
This is wrong.
Yeah.
So, you know, maybe this branch is important.
Look, maybe that work that we were doing, we would just really like to
save, right?
So now we can reorganize these into two, which ones we actually need.
We know that the team asked and the hit mask, don't need to get
updated until we know that the root mask actually works.
The pick mask, this one only has to get updated inside as well,
because that's conditioning, the T value.
Same with the T equals t p.
here, the root term needs to
well no.
So these guys here, right can be inside as well because we don't need
to compute any of this stuff.
If the root mask is 0, right?
So it only needs the root term.
To start with and not the denominator.
So it needs B and A and C to compute the root term and it needs to do
the mask but that's all it really needs to do.
Then we come down here, we need to pick which T value, we're going to
use and we need to Sauce it there.
So this all needs to happen like that but otherwise we're fine.
The same is true of the mat index here.
That doesn't have to get pulled out until later because we don't need
to grab that.
If we, if we're not actually ever going to have,
Right, the compiler should have done that probably though.
All right.
So, I don't know if that's any faster I guess.
Probably not.
But you know that was something that the other code was able to do
that.
Our code that are other code wasn't able to do, right?
And hey I
That's a pretty big speed and that's like twice as fast.
Almost, right.
We were at .09.
We were at 09 down here, right?
And now we're at 05 for the same number of bounces in the same quality
image, right?
So now that Ray casting time has dropped pretty dramatically.
If we compare the two,
To where we started.
That's actually quite good.
This one is not really.
We should have saved the one that we did.
That was a more optimized version.
I should have saved an interim because it was .09 4.
For the single core, but that means we've at least sped up to X, right
relative to where we were at before.
And that's, that's a decent speed up.
And, you know, I'll take it right, I still think there's probably more
to be done here.
There's probably some other things that we're doing that are dumb.
I guess.
One thing that I would say is if we look at the loads here the loads
are pretty expensive.
We could choose to move the loads below.
sort of the
we could choose to keep well.
We could choose to not do loads on ones that haven't hit, right?
So if we imagine changing the way, the gather works so that we only
gather things that are nonzero.
That, that would be an example of a way to optimize this, probably
further.
But yeah.
So the other thing I would say is if in the mask is zeroed case here,
where we're going to break out, I assume the compiler was smart enough
to do it, but I'll also just go ahead and do it for it.
We don't need to compute any more things through the, through the
loop.
We do need to update anything besides the lane mask, and the sample in
the case, where we're not actually going to do anything else.
So I'm assuming the compiler was smart enough to move.
These things into an else Clause basically.
So it, you know it looks like this where if the mask is zero, you
know, they won't
If the mass is real breakout otherwise we'll do this.
I'm assuming it was smart to do that.
So don't anticipate this would make any difference.
But that's another example of something that, you know, we can do
based on checking to see whether anything is getting used.
But all right.
No, I guess it wasn't smart enough to do that.
So there you go.
So that's another one to and there's probably lots of other little
things like that in here that we can get.
So, we're getting pretty good here now.
Like that's that's producing an image in a pretty reasonable amount of
time.
Course, our image is also fairly simple, so you know nothing to
necessarily write home about.
But at least we're like in the ballpark of Sanity now and we can do a
pretty detailed image in a pretty quick amount of time.
Right?
That only took 7 Seconds.
That's plenty, good.
Turnaround for a simple or a caster.
If you wanted to play with it and plus it produces reasonable results
at lower raise per pixel which go much faster as well.
We also don't know how long this would be take if we went even wider,
right?
So that part I'm not sure about, I don't know how long it would take
to do that.
Maybe I'll you know, I'm kind of into it right now I have to say so I
kind of just wanted to keep going but
In here, if we look at the way these re Lane things are set up, you
know, I might be inclined to say if we did a re laying for x or
something like that and in there, we took the ray Lane stuff that was
44 wide, and we just kind of grabbed all that out.
Like so.
and,
I feel like that's sort of
just a nicer thing to look at.
So in here, we would just say, you know, pounding group include
railing, train for x.h.
like so and if we want to make an 8X wide run one, we would do
That and basically that's just a copy right of this stuff and railing
8X that H goes in here.
and these are just
256 has
Right.
And I don't know, exactly all the rest of the stuff I would have to do
to make this work properly but it's more or less fat with changing the
mnemonics, right?
So if we wanted to, you know, here's the four wide version.
Again we can pilot want to comply this one you can see that like all
of these mnemonics are wrong now so you know, I don't know.
Can I just do this?
I've never had the luxury, this is the first machine I've ever had.
That had eight wide on it in the first place, so I don't even know.
But let's, let's let's take a look, so comp ltps, right?
Is is
Right anymore.
So, what are the intrinsics for avx2?
Any of the X4 comp belty?
Like how do you compare two values with with the wider instruction
set?
I don't even know.
Right.
Am I missing something?
So here it is.
It's just
Mmm 256 comp PS.
Looks like what it is and you pass in immediate value.
The immediate value is the type of comparison to use put out know what
those media values would necessarily be.
Unfortunately,
Let me look it up.
That's there it is.
Blend V blend V.
That's the one that does the select.
Like I was talking about, I'm like, I know it's in there is can't
remember tonight.
So there's a predicate, the predicate is in IMM, intron .h, so I don't
know where I am.
Intron dot h is
It's in there.
What, what a sensible path to an include file, you know?
Just just like the old days you could have backslash R, sorry /usr
forward slash include or you can have C colon backslash program, space
files faceprint open parentheses x, 86 close parentheses, backslash
Microsoft, based visual space, Studio backslash, 2017, back-sass
Community backs, SVC box size, tools backs, SMS, VC, back size, 14,
at 11.2, 5503 backslash include
Please Microsoft died in a fire.
Alright, so let's go ahead and open that.
Monstrosity up.
And see what that file says.
Sure.
So in theory, the cops are, oh, and here, they're right at the top.
So here are all the comps that we might want.
We've got something else interesting like signaling versions, and so
on.
That's cool, compare products for scale impact compared and transfer
functions.
So equal ordered non signaling.
So you have all these different kinds of things.
I'm not even familiar with these so I guess you can choose whether or
not it's signaling or not.
I assume that's signaling.
If the value was like and a man or something and we don't need to do
that so we can do non signaling ordered.
I'm not quite sure what they mean by that.
So I would like
Someone to tell me what that means, this will be educational for me.
Do they have documentation here somewhere?
I kind of just want the architecture manual.
Probably for this.
Because I would like to know what they mean by ordered, in that sense.
Hmm.
My say.
I really just want you to tell me.
Thank you.
Oq.
Open up, there we go.
Does this sort of?
Elaborate at all.
Okay, is this to comply with three of the DirectX 10, specification,
okay.
When either a both operates, our Nanny returns, false comparisons know
the sine of 0 comparison.
Any ear was earn a return.
True comparisons of non-invasive.
The correct result do Norms are flush before comparison.
Okay?
Infinity values of either, sign are considered ordered values.
Okay, so basically, this is just talking about whether or not Infinity
Works signed or not.
I guess.
Is that what he's talking about?
I'm not really sure right, that's not really clear on that.
So I'm not sure which one of those we would want
That's pretty confusing to me.
I'm gonna have to go with the architecture mail because I've never
seen that terminology for.
I'm sure it means something obvious, right?
But I've never seen it before because I've never programmed this
instruction set.
So anyway.
So what we want here is a is a 256, right?
We want AV we want this to be less than, right?
So we don't want signaling.
So we just want
Wyatt, we don't need it to Signal not that it would matter.
It could if it wanted to, we don't give it any of those.
I don't think.
Oh well, we might because we're doing masking stuff like that.
So we want it to be to be quiet.
So for example, in this case we've got a list an operation so I think
we want compelte oq, right.
Oops.
Throughout less than ordered quiet.
And the only thing I don't know is whether we want ordered or
unordered because I don't really understand the difference between
those two things, I would like someone to explain to me what that
means and
Yeah I just I just don't know so we may want oqs.
We won't meet.
Want you ques?
I'm not sure.
So that's kind of yeah up in the air.
So again, this would be the same, this is a less than or equal to
So it's probably just going to be that right less than or equal to.
This one's going to be a comp greater than 0 Q.
And this one's going to be a comp greater than or equal to 0 Q.
this was going to be comp equal to
And this one's going to be a comp not equal to Q.
And all of these are going to have to become just comp PS.
Okay.
So I think we did that, right?
But I don't really know.
So now we need one of these.
I assume
But yep.
And so this, I'm just going by how the in transition named I'm just
guessing that's probably that to do the conversion and hey, good for
them, for being consistent as weird as the nominee nature is at least
worked and I didn't have to look it up.
So there's those conversions.
And that's pretty good.
Now for you 32s, I don't know what we've got here.
They may have a comp for that.
We may not have to do the weird foofy miss anymore.
So let's just double check.
So is there a
Mmm tuna fish comfort for 32-bit wide or not.
Comparisons.
So there's a copy Q&A comp greater than but that's it.
So I guess that means that you don't, you can't do other kinds of
comparisons, you have to like negate the values and compare them that
way or something.
There's only two.
Right?
Because you you can imagine constructing the other values, right?
For example, if you want to know greater than or equal to you could or
together a greater than and equal to comparisons,
And if you want to do a less than you can just do a greater than with
the operands reversed and an EQ or whatever, right.
So you could imagine these going that way and that I guess what they
want you to do, here it looks like right.
So that's probably what's going on there.
So let's go ahead and do that to me.
Well, in this case, we don't really care because that's actually the
only one, we really needed, right.
Is that right?
Yeah, we only really need that one anyway, so never mind.
So in this case, I guess it's just, it's just this
Probably.
Yeah, I assume X or just translates directly across.
I assume that and translates directly across.
But I don't know.
Looks like this is like really easy, right?
We don't know.
It's gonna work, could just completely die on us here, but so far so
good.
Like some of it's a little different but the rest of it isn't, right?
A lot of its just doing this.
So yeah, this is when you've got to actually provide the right numbers
of values.
So yeah, I guess this has to take like as wide as the lane width could
possibly be he's worth of random stuff.
Right?
We almost want to call this like initialize to random or something.
Let's finish the rest of these first because it's a little bit harder.
So here's that mask, here's the cast operation.
Here are the ends and Knots and oars and that's really it.
These Min and Max should presumably just work there.
The same exact operations just on a wider width.
And then this stuff just has to gather 8 wide now.
Right before, 56.
Seven, but that's it and MOB mask.
Now, is going to do a bigger mouth mask, but that's it.
And
I think.
The only thing we have to fix is the way that this entropy thing
works.
So again, this function is kind of dumb
So I guess we just have to make this thing.
Take a bunch of these, right?
I always type 2.
Always what's going on there.
It's just where my fingers hit.
No entropy, I got no entropy in my fingers.
All right.
One, two, three.
Four.
Five, six, seven, eight.
So I don't know what this is going to do.
Maybe it'll just blue screen.
My machine, I don't know, probably not going to lose but you know,
let's let's try it.
There we go.
Immediate crashes.
What's the problem?
Render tile.
Image with wait, what?
No, let's compile and debug mode.
First people.
What?
so, it compiles in debug mode, but not
What am I missing?
So, it compiles in debug mode, but not in release mode doesn't work.
We sure about that.
What's going on here?
Tell me what's going on.
First of all, who faulted, are we sure?
We know who faulted is this one of those things where you're showing
me the wrong thread?
Folks.
I don't want this to be one of those things where you throw me the
wrong thread.
So, we're on.
Which instruction around here.
I am an exception at seven of a three, four, five, six.
So it's this one right here.
Illegal instruction.
So, V unpack, LPS.
Okay.
So V unpack, LPS.
Well, okay, so here's the thing.
About that.
Does this need to be aligned?
Is my own my only question.
What's rcx?
and,
All right.
So that's not aligned, right?
so, I wonder if it doesn't like the fact that this V unpack
I wonder if it doesn't like the fact that that's on the line.
Yeah, I'm saying to you.
What?
Take a look in here.
This stuff is all fine.
So is it something unaligned stack wise in here?
Who are we writing too?
Because of all of these things should be aligned.
Where's casts?
Take a state hasn't.
Doesn't have any of them.
So that, yeah, I do wonder whether that's an alignment issue, right?
I don't know.
Because it's not aligned.
It is aligned to 16, but it's not aligned to 32 and I just don't know
if that instruction has to be aligned.
Let's find out.
This is probably what we want here.
I want the architecture manual.
Load it up.
Load it.
Thank you.
How come I can't jump to anything.
What is going on?
Fine, I'll go there myself.
Do do, do, do, do, do, do do.
Unpack LPS, okay.
Evie, exfiltration exceptions, Type e, 4, and F.
And what do we know of K?
So which which ones are these?
These are evx and coded.
These are just Vex encoded.
Yeah, right.
Now, no, no.
It's using this broadcast here.
It might be that the broadcast because that's an e VX and V ve X and
coded instruction, and we might not be allowed to use those.
So I wonder I may need to tell
Visual Studio, not to do a broadcast.
because I don't know whether that's allowed right Visual Studio
architecture targets, which
So, I'm just curious.
No, that's not God.
Visual Studio CPU architecture targets which
command line.
This one.
So I want Arch x64 obviously, but I need it to do.
I mean, I think so.
It should already be doing this though.
So I don't know if mmm.
I'm not sure about why it's doing that, right?
Let me just see what happens if I smoosh this in there a little bit,
right?
So, here's the build line.
I'm going to go ahead and stick this in here.
I don't know if you want to be x-ray, Vic's, to, in this case.
So maybe that was all it took.
Maybe it thought it could use harder core stuff.
And telling it not to with the arch command is sufficient.
Because hey guess what, it's not using that broadcast anymore.
Right.
Here is the unpack LPS and it's not using broadcast anymore.
So that might be it.
All right, so 48 wide Lanes.
So eight wide Lanes is awful.
We actually get slower using 8 wide lanes and 60% of our calculations
are wasted course.
Let's make sure we actually got an image.
It looks darker to be mess up a summation value 0.
Our horizontal ad is wrong.
So 8 wide is not good.
We don't gain anything from 8 wide, right?
Let's go to Lane 8.
X horizontal ad.
Just go ahead and get that in here.
So yeah, this is not quite right yet.
4 5 6 7 oops.
Same here.
So, three, four, five Loops five, six.
Seven.
Yeah, and that's just not good at all.
Right.
Oh
So I guess that was just a summation that was busted.
Never mind.
So actually, that's exactly what we would expect.
Got twice as fast.
Never mind.
Is that, right?
So let's let me just check that here.
Where's the lane with?
Is aligned with the four and this thing's got to throw out those
values.
Also.
So it's not quite twice as fast, right?
It's not it's a little less than that and I guess we kind of sort of
have one culprit here a little bit which is that the waist advances
number is going up a little bit so it's not really as bad as I thought
it was right.
So hey, that's kind of nice.
We've got day 24x.
Here.
Oops.
Sorry, day, 3, for X.
I guess it's the same, in either case, I guess, but will will do both.
Here we go.
So there's our eight core with four wide Lanes.
Oh, where's the worst?
The additional data here?
I won't do that again.
All right, so let's try this again.
If I do build dot rate a test
Now, we should have this one should?
Yeah, there we go.
This is our 4 wide Lanes.
Right, and now I should be able to do the 8 wide lens.
It has to be equivalent to me.
That's good.
There's r8x.
Done.
So there's the Forex version, there's the 8 X version.
And again, not bad.
Getting it down to pretty low / bounce.
Plenty of room left there, probably for improvement but you know it's
not awful.
And the raycasting time continues to go down.
We're down from eight seconds.
25 seconds.
I think before we were at something like 17 seconds
so that's pretty good.
That's pretty good.
I'm happy with that.
Alright, that's about it for today.
I'm pretty happy with that.
That's a fun little raytracer there and I feel like we're in good
shape to next time.
We end up doing a handmade re playing around with the light transport
and building some better illumination stuff, right?
Like just making a nicer scene to play with and try to bounce the
light around in a more realistic fashion using
Some actual surface functions that aren't completely wrong.
So that's about it.
I'm going to go ahead and close this up.
Like so.
And and but why not?
I can't do zvx titled now because this chip doesn't support it.
This chip doesn't support it.
I wish if x 512 have been out I wish you'd been out a long time ago.
I wish you did had scattered gather.
I wish a lot of things about the Intel instruction set, but you know,
what?
Whistling ain't silicon.
So you can't make silicon out of wishes.
I guess is the rule.
So, you know until we actually get desktop Hardware that has a Vicks
512 reliably which even I9 doesn't apparently have.
Off we go.
So that's it for today.
Thanks everyone for joining me for this episode of handmade hero.
That was handmade re-up.
So technically I'm going to close down asking you on the stream if
they had any pauses or stuff that they noticed next week will resume
regular handmade hero until then.
Please have fun programming and I'll see everyone on the internet.
Take it easy, everybody.