Hello, everyone, and welcome to handmade hero.
The show we could have complete game live on stream yesterday.
We talked a lot about the fundamentals of depth buffering.
And why we wanted to switch to a depth buffer on handmade hero.
And today, we're going to go ahead and take a look at some of the code
that's going to be involved in doing that.
And again the code that's going to be involved in.
This is really not that extensive and most of what you're going to see
as we try to do this, switch over to someone
3D oriented stuff in the pipeline is actually that a lot of the work
is just in the 3D API Miss of it all.
As soon as you move from the CPU to the GPU, you're in a really
uncomfortable space where unlike before where we were able to step
seamlessly through all of our codes, see what it was doing and like
with our software renderer we could see how each individual pixel is
filled.
And so if a particular effect was not occurring correctly on screen,
it was very easy for us to determine what was
going on because we could step through our 100% of our code all the
way down to like how that pixel was selected, who was trying to fill
it.
What they were trying to fill it with and why it wasn't getting filled
with the correct color or correct texture or anything else, right?
And hopefully you always kind of saw how easy it was for us to kind of
work with that code and just understand what was going on.
And we never really had a lot of problems.
Sort of sitting around.
Banging our heads going, I have no idea what could possibly be wrong
with this for like a day.
Or whatever, you know.
And, and so, one of the big problems that you get into with.
Once you start using code in a GPU sense, is that that a lot of that
ability kind of goes away and you can get some of that ability back by
using a aftermarket debugging system that allows you to sort of do bug
GPU side of things to a greater extent and these tools can actually be
very valuable and I
And we are going to have to install one of those at some point if we
go far enough down the rabbit hole of 3D stuff because otherwise you
just have very little visibility in it and it's really a kind of this
really nasty black box to fucking problem.
That takes a lot longer.
When things don't go the way, you think they should because you make
some slight error somewhere in how you set something up and figuring
out where that slight era was, because you can't step through anything
becomes very difficult.
And so there are tools for this.
The insight to bugger is one of the Nvidia ships.
There's I can never remember the name of it, there's a third party one
that's freely available that works on both AMD and Nvidia chips.
That's available.
I would have already installed one for use on this machine.
The only thing is I don't know two things yet.
I'm going to have to find out both those things.
One is whether or not this machines graphics card is simply too old to
be supported by that tool.
It's an AMD
Obviously, nsight won't work, but the I can't remember the name of the
other debugger, but I don't know why the name could totally escapes
me, but it works on, am d as well.
We can try that one, but I don't know if it will work on this card, so
we may have to update the graphics card in this machine, put a
different crafts center or switch to a different machine for handmade
here or something.
That has a grass.
Carp, we can use for debugging because it's very important to have
that.
Otherwise you're just wasting time and
And again to be clear.
You it's not like you can't.
I mean, you absolutely can still to bug them that way, and that's the
way we used to do it all the time.
It's just that much, like debugging without a debugger takes more time
to bugging GPU code without a GPU, debugger takes more time and so you
don't generally want to do it if you don't have to because you are
literally just wasting your programming time.
That could be better.
Spent doing something more productive like adding a feature to your
game.
Similarly speaking, I do not know how running.
Something like a graphical.
Debugger will affect our ability to stream?
I don't know if that will create problems for OBS and so, we'll have
to do a test stream at some point to figure out these things.
Just so I can see whether or not we can get to bugging working, and be
able to step through GPU code.
Now.
Just to be clear.
This is still even when you get this working, not nearly as good as
when you have your actual own code running on the CPU in terms of
visibility.
And the reason for that is when I say step, you can step through GPU
code.
I don't really mean it.
What I mean to say is that it gives you an approximation of being able
to step through GPU code without actually being able to step through
GPU code.
So what it actually does is it does a bunch of shenanigans
To allow you to inspect the state of things in the middle of shaders
that you might write.
And it does a bunch of shenanigans to try and get you information
about the intermediate state of things before and after say,
transforms and stuff like that.
So it's more of a data dumping utility.
It's more of a thing that allows you to see data through the pipeline,
like the watch window in a debugger does.
But the stepping is not really stepping through everything.
The way that stepping on the CPU is stepping through everything.
And the reason for that is that there's no way that is exposed, at
least, you know, 2 and user on gpus to step through stuff.
Like the dependency graph walking dispatch system that determines when
batches of Primitives are dispatched, right?
And so,
You're never going to get, you don't get to see the whole pipeline
occur in any way, shape, or form.
You get to see snapshots at different points of the data flow.
And when you're in a Shader you get a pretty good approximation of a
debugger because that you can every line see the state of various
variables and stuff like that.
So Shader debugging is pretty good pipeline.
Stepping you basically don't get it all but you can see like data
snapshots and places and stuff like that.
But you know, again even with that which is way better than what we
have right now.
For example, which is nothing.
You're still kind of not nearly as close to the actual operation as
you are with a regular debugger.
So that's just the nature of the beast.
That's that's just the way gpus are these days.
They are not exposing their internal workings in that way.
And they don't have the same debug interrupts exposed that modern
system does.
And again, I think that's probably
We just because they don't really want you to know all of the details
of how they do their processing and dispatching on that stuff.
I'm guessing I don't really know like to be honest I don't know why it
could just be also because they don't want to implement the Silicon
necessary to have stuff like a breakpoint.
You know like an M3 in the middle of that dispatcher, it may just be a
hardwired thing that doesn't ever want to be step through.
You know I have no idea.
So that's the current status of it as far as I've ever seen it.
And so, you know, keep in mind, that that's something that we have to
address for today's episode.
I don't think we're going to need that too much because we're just
going to get you know barely get started on doing the changeover from
the current way that the code is working to a more 3D Centric way for
the back end.
And so given that that's the case, I don't think we're going to have
to do.
Lot of debugging of any sort of subtle things that are so subtle, that
we have that problem.
Like, even if we end up with just a black screen, at the end of this
episode, we probably won't have time to really de bug.
Why we aren't seeing The Primitives, we think we're seeing or
whatever, right?
So I don't think we're gonna get far enough to really need the
debugger today anyway so I'm not going to try and get that stuff set
up our tested today instead.
I'm just going to go ahead and do sort of some of the basic stuff that
we have to do and
And explain the things that I will need to explain along the way, in
order to get us started on that.
So let's go ahead and get things going here.
I'm going to go ahead and load up by the way to today is day 359.
So you want to start with the source code from day 358.
Let's go ahead and open up the code.
Here we are.
We Run the game.
We can see our 2D pipeline running, but we do like have Hardware
rendering enabled.
So remember this is a 2d pipeline back end.
But it is running on the GPU.
So, technically, we already have all the work done of setting up the
GPU, right?
Creating a frame buffer and rendering, you know, uploading textures to
it.
So we do have the basics ver.
So, really, all that's not happening right now is we're not really
doing any work regarding the three dienes of these objects as far as
the GPU is concerned.
By the time, any of this gets to the GPU, we have already.
On all of the necessary work like we've done the projection of the
coordinates and everything, and we're just handing the GPU things that
are already in screen space.
Okay, so given that.
What we're going to try and do now is take out that screen, space
transform.
Okay.
so,
let's take a look at where that was happening.
If you take a look at get render entity basis P, you can see that what
we're doing here is we are performing our own transforms, right?
And you can see this very clearly, so we have get render entity basis
P.
You can see in here, we've got this whole set of code and it's doing a
bunch of stuff to do, our sort of fake, you know, our isometric, sort
of transform.
And then, we also do a regular projection transform for first.
Going.
And so you can kind of see that this right here.
This code is the code that is doing our projection from World
coordinates, which is this original P here and I shouldn't really say
World coordinates because we have an object transform.
So we actually, oftentimes are giving the original p in terms of some
local coordinates and then the object transform transforms them into
some sort of the world courts working with and then that's the camera
transformed.
That's telling us stuff like how to
How to you know what?
The focal length of the camera is done like that how to transform
those World coordinates into screen coordinates, right?
But what you can see here is that we ended up with a projected x y and
the projected XY, then goes through some transforms for the screen and
then we end up with just a thing that says okay.
Now we've got exactly what we want for our screen coordinates and here
we have out put them right and so all of our rendering code goes
through this piece of code.
Code.
And what that means for us is that once we get to the actual render,
like the actual Hardware rendering back end or in our case a software
rendering back-end as well, they no longer have any 3D information.
At all actually.
And so what we were doing is, we were augmenting.
What we were writing their, we were augmenting it with sorting
information, which is all of this stuff that was happening in here,
right?
Like all these sort Kista.
We would push sort of some of the 3D information that we needed to do
sorting into this separate set of sort of like information chunks,
right?
And those would get used to do the Sorting because there is no 3D
information left over after we do our transform, it just has
rectangles that it knows, it needs to draw and that's a perfectly
reasonable thing to do with the 2D thing because there's no reason for
the render back-end to know anything other than how to sort things and
how to draw things.
So it doesn't really need, that's the information but now we need to
make a switch and we need to start giving it that information.
So if we pop over here to the opengl back end, which is what I'll work
on first,
Because we're going to have to write a bunch of routines in our
software renderer if we want to support the full 3d transform stuff.
So we'll kind of have to tackle that as a separate project at some
point.
So if we just look at, how do we're going to, we'd have to feed the
hardware.
One of the things that we can see about this is when we do
I'm going to go ahead and show you the little biggest thing when we do
our opengl set screen space, you can kind of see here how we're
working this out, right?
When we do opengl set screen space which I believe is the only thing
that we actually call here.
You can see when we do open gol.
It's, that's not the one I want there is when you come in here, and
we're about to do all our rendering, here's our opengl renderer
commands call
Before we do all our rendering, we set up a matrix and we talked about
kind of what that does roughly but we need to talk about it.
A little bit more in detail now because we're going to have to get
much more familiar with these things.
So we're going to go over that and very excruciating detail.
In a moment, you can see we got our opengl set screen space here and
the opengl set screen space called just past the width and height of
the screen.
Then what we do in that opengl set screen, space routine, is we
generate this Matrix, which as you can see is kind of an identity
Matrix to a certain degree.
It's almost just a non transform, right?
An identity Matrix would just be 1s down the diagonal and zeros
everywhere else, but it has for specific values that have been changed
from that identity.
And those are the scaling coefficients on the X and Y, right?
And to sort of negative ones here in the homogeneous coordinates,
right?
Okay.
now, this is really the super
This is the part that's super annoying.
We're using the fixed function Pipeline and so we have to deal with
this for a minute.
When we switch to shaders, we won't have to worry about
Apart anymore, actually, which is kind of nice.
But for the moment, I'm just going to go ahead and start out with the
very, very basic stuff here.
Again, just to refresh your memory and also to get a little bit more
detail, right?
Stocks touch yells at.
Yeah, there it is because it's going to be a lot more important to
have this stuff.
Understood very cleanly now,
So let me just say, one more time, you can see that there's a really
unfortunate thing that happens here.
It has to do with column Major versus row major storage, and all this
sort of stuff.
I just want to explain it one more time.
I think we went over it before when we did this but we need to go over
it again and you really need to understand what's happening here
because otherwise you will be a very unhappy camper when you start to
do 3D programming and try to interface with the GPU because yeah stuff
goes stuff.
Stuff goes poorly if
Get this part wrong and you'll always be scratching your head as to
why.
All right.
So let's go ahead.
and talk about,
The projection Matrix here.
Okay?
So what I want you to do is kind of look at how this is defined here.
You can see, I've got our three to project.
I've got, you know, a 0 0, 0 0, B 0 0 0 0, 1 0 negative, 1 negative 1
0 1, right now in mathematical notation, it's fairly standard.
How matrices our are written.
Okay, if you open up a generic math, textbook like an introduction to
linear algebra, textbook.
Whatever it is.
You would then think
That the Matrix that you see there, right?
Is this Matrix?
Right, because there it is in the code, it looks pretty obvious,
right?
And here, it is in in math, notation, right?
And now it's like real easy for me to say, oh, here's the code, and
here's the math, notation.
And so, when I'm working on the code, I know, whatever I worked out in
my math notebook, you know?
I just type it in and I'm good to go or I loaded up Mathematica or
Matlab or some computer-aided algebra system.
And I saw the Matrix, it looked like this and
Now I've got it right, but unfortunately at least it with opengl es
default the way that it does Geo load Matrix.
If you just call GL load Matrix, F to load a matrix.
This is actually not true.
That is not the Matrix.
You get the Matrix that you will actually get.
Is this Matrix?
Okay, and what you can see here is the matrices are identical, except
for the fact that they've been transposed.
Now, you
Number that the transpose operator, right?
On a matrix written typically with a superscript t above the Matrix.
All that does is it flips, The Matrix about its diagonal, right?
So we had a b11 down the diagonal, we have a B-1 one, down the
diagonal again, but all of these other things sort of flip around
there.
So this guy goes over to here, right?
This guy goes over to hear this guy to hear that kind of their right?
Everyone kind of goes to their flipped.
Occasion.
So another way to think of that would be, you know if I'm thinking
about the index this way, right?
Like let's say that I've got a matrix and I want to talk about the
element of it, you know, if this is a matrix, a and I want to talk
about the element IJ.
Maybe I is my is going across.
So I is like which one of these I am, right?
And Jay is going down.
So maybe I say A you know, 21 right.
Well a 21 is 21.
It's right here.
Well basically what we're saying here is we would just flip it around
to one is now at 12, right?
And so you could say that a transpose means that a oops, I went behind
my head there.
Hey, i j gets swapped right with AJ.
I right, you just you just switch which you know which indices you
have, the, the column and row of your index gets switched.
And that's where your new location is, right.
So why does that happen?
Well, it's just historical, there's really no reason for it.
It's just a historical thing that that occurred back when SGI was
first defining these sorts of things.
Column-major is what it's called versus row major.
What that means is in memory order, right?
Because remember, when we Define an array,
In C or C++, when we list the elements they get put in memory in that
order.
So, a comes at the first position in memory zero in the next 1000 B 0
0, 0 0, 1 0 negative 1 negative 1 0 1, right.
So in memory order right there basically, we're just doing this, you
know, I put in that indentation to evoke the structure of the Matrix
but really it's just a piece of memory.
That's got that in it, right?
I mean that's
What we're talking about here.
And so given that that's the case since it's just a line of digits,
it's obviously up to the programmer when you're when you're creating
things that operate on matrices, you know what the math has to do.
But you don't know, just when you have just a set of 60 numbers,
there's nothing that magically says which one has to correspond to
which position in The Matrix?
I mean we could make it be any rule we wanted really, we don't even
have to make it be anything logical, we could have it.
So that the 13th
It is actually in the first position of in the 11 position of the
Matrix, right?
I mean we could because it's just whatever the math.
Teens wherever they pull from to do their multiplication, that
determines the structure of the Matrix and so what the programmers
decided when they first did this was that it would actually go in
column order.
So a000, those first four positions in memory were considered to be
defining Down The Columns of the Matrix, so that when we get to the
next four elements, we're going down the next column and so much more
sensible thing.
It would have been nice wood.
I've been to go across because then A and C or any other language
where the arrays are written out in in this order, it's much easier to
read the math.
The standard math, textbook versus the code, but just the
circumstances being what they were at The Times.
They did not make that decision.
I do not know why I wasn't there.
I've heard various rumors but I have no idea how accurate they are.
Anyway, it's probably it's, it's similar to the fact that they're
still left handed coordinate systems.
In a lot of the early stuff like direct3d is a left handed coordinate
system.
For example, whereas like there's I don't think there's any common
math textbooks that ever use left-handed coordinate systems, they
always use right-handed coordinate systems.
So you know, I don't know why there was such a Divergence in the early
computer Graphics Community, but what I do know is that subsequently
most of the computer graphics people were much more closely wedded to
the traditional math and so they kind of undid all that and nowadays,
usually, you don't have any of that sort of thing happening, right?
They typically try to make things as close to math notation as they
can to avoid any kind of ambiguity anyway.
So basically, what happens here is this is the actual Matrix that we
are currently defining for our projection Matrix, and it may look a
little bit weird to you because what it actually equals, if we go up
here and read what A and B are, are some very unusual values right at
they don't make a lot of sense.
If you look at them, you know, if you just kind of like take a look at
them quickly and go, what is this supposed to be doing?
It's a rather confusing, right?
You might say
And this is, this is really a, I think, the thing that confuses people
a lot about projection, matrices as well, but you know what, kind of
get to that in general.
So this is the projection Matrix that were currently using in the just
to sort of start to get more comfortable with these with these kind of
matrices and what they're trying to do.
The first thing, I just want to point out is like, okay, looking at
this projection Matrix?
Why were we doing this?
What's the point of this?
You know, can we figure out what we were doing here?
Here.
And what I would encourage you to do.
Obviously as always is just to take a look at a point that's coming in
here, that's going to be transformed by this Matrix and take a look at
what
You get out of it, right?
Because that's always a good way.
You know, I this is a simple enough Matrix and I work with matrices
often enough that I just kind of can read it straight off and know
exactly what it's doing, but up until you build that sort of
intuition.
And especially even, if you have intuition, when you start to look at
matrices that are much more complicated than this one, it helps a lot
to just do the multiplication out.
Now, you'll notice what I chose to X was an incoming point in three,
dimensions X Y & Z.
And I wrote a one in here right now, why did did I write a 1 in here?
Here.
Well, the reason that I wrote a one in here is because this is a four
by four Matrix, right?
And a 4 by 4 Matrix, and computer Graphics parlance is often called a
homogeneous Matrix.
And do not ask me why they pick that that term.
That's another one of those historical things where it's like I feel
like it doesn't convey a lot of the meaning I believe the reason that
they call it a homogeneous Matrix.
That's something to do at the fact that they want to consider
translation to be treated the same as everything else.
And that makes it a monetary thing.
It's a very strange thing because it's not really yeah, I don't know.
So I have no idea if that's why they call it - it might be that
there's a really good math reason to call it homogeneous and I
suspected of student him, 73 is still with us.
Don't think he is, he could step in and perhaps give some people a
little bit more background on may be why the word homogeneous if it
predates the computer, Graphics usage and mean something better in
mathematics why that was there.
So that's kind of left an exercise to the reader because I don't know
and I don't pretend to but I can tell you exactly why they were used
in graphics and why they still get used to a limited extent today.
So what happens here is if you imagine the types of equations that you
typically look at, and I think we may have covered this before, but
again I'm just going to cover it again because it's all very
important.
And you now need to be really, really comfortable with it.
What does a matrix multiply do, right?
Well, as you can kind of see from what we're looking at here.
If you remember, how your matrix-matrix multiply works, you go column
by
Oh and you multiply the column of the input by the row here, right?
And in this case we only have a vector.
So we only have one column to multiply with.
So we're just going to multiply this one column by each row in turn
and that will give us our result, which will just be a vector if we
had a matrix, we'd have more columns and we do every row by every
column and produce several elements per row and produce another
Matrix.
Right?
We know ideas, we've done it many times before.
So let's go ahead and multiply here.
We've got our two over W Times X, right?
We've got zeros in the other two.
So we're not going to have any more terms here.
And then in the final one, we've gotten one times negative one.
So, we just got a negative one there, right?
Furthermore, we do the same thing again this time, there's only a
coefficient for the Y, so it's going to be 2 over h y.
And again, the one just multiplies.
We then have nothing else to multiply for the Z, right?
Oops.
Sorry
Nothing else, X, the Z other than unit coefficient.
So we just get the Z copied directly.
It doesn't change at all.
And then our final Road just multiplies, the one.
And so here is our resulting Vector its to over w.
X minus 12 over h y, minus 1/2 and 1, right?
And so now just to get back to what I was trying to explain their, why
do we have the 4x4 Des of it?
Well, you can kind of see why we need that for by foreigners.
Even just looking at this very very simple Matrix here.
The
It is because if the author of The Matrix who is trying to create a
transform for the incoming data.
If you have a 3D coordinate system, you know, that your inputs will
consist of xy's and Z's.
That's a three Vector, right?
And that means,
That if you were to only use a 3 by 3 Matrix, this part up here, then
every single thing you could do with the Matrix, right?
The only mathematical things you could produce with the Matrix in the
results, here would be equations that were coefficients of the input X
Y & Z because that's exactly what happens, right?
If I have a matrix that looks like this,
And I'm inputting an XYZ.
Well then the only things I'm ever going to be able to produce on the
other side are things that look like this.
Right.
There's no way for me to get another term in here.
I can't just add some additional value that's going to be on
multiplied by the input, right?
So effectively what it means is that operations like the one we are,
in fact, doing right now, where we just want to offset the value by a
constant that we Supply become impossible.
They will not work, right?
Because anything that you might put in The Matrix will always be
multiplied by something in the input.
And so if your goal was to produce an effect that was unmultiplied and
is irrelevant, what the input is?
It will still produce the same effect.
You cannot do it, right?
And so that's why you extend one beyond the number of coordinates that
you have and you augment the vectors.
By a third, I'm sorry, fourth value?
Or I guess, an N, plus 1 value, whatever your end Dimension is, right
for 2D you'd have a 3D Matrix for 3D of a 40 Matrix.
If you had 70, you detonate D Matrix, right?
You augment it with a 1 so that you just say, hey, don't modify at all
that final value.
Just keep it as it is and allow
But to be an offset for what I'm doing, right?
And so, the reason that the big motivation for this originally was for
doing stuff like translation, right?
Because you can do things like rotation which involve just
coefficients of the inputs, those can all happen in the upper 3x3 but
as soon as you want your Matrix to be able to represent a movement,
well, a movement isn't dependent on the input, a movement that goes
five units to.
The left is about subtracting 5 from your thing whether or not that
value is 10 or 50 or a
Thousand or a billion or - 325, right?
And so being able to support a offset just a raw offset value was
crucial.
And that's why they wanted this to be augmented.
Now, the other thing to remember here is that this value is not always
meaningless.
The input can actually use this value to confer some meaning, on the
input, right?
And what I mean by that, is if you think about what's going on here,
this X Y & Z value is saying how the upper 3x3 is going to work,
right?
The upper 3x3 of the Matrix is going to modify this and this portion
of
Matrix, right?
Is going to be controlled by this, right?
This negative 1 and negative 1 is going to be still controlled by
this.
We're setting it to one so it will just happen immediately but if we
wanted to we could also set it to zero and that would knock out these
terms and cause them to not have any effect, right?
And so that's why you will sometimes see if you've ever seen something
like this happen and maybe didn't know exactly why.
You can sort of see why people will sometimes say, well x, y z one,
that's a point.
Where is x?
Y z 0, right.
Oops.
Right.
That's a vector.
Sometimes people will say something like that.
I believe this is sort of a more rigorous way of defining these
things.
And what do we mean by this?
Well, the reason we would say x y z 1 is a point in x y z.
0 is a vector, is because x y z, 1 allows the input variable to pick
up those translation changes, right?
So, it's a point in space, that will be moved by The Matrix, right?
When the Matrix says, to move the point moves,
A vector on the other hand is technically, just a direction in space.
We tend to use Vector to mean this thing, right?
But in Geometry, you might sometimes mathematically.
They use these things to talk about them being different in that way,
right?
And so a direction in space doesn't move, right?
A Direction, Just points in a direction and
The Matrix is trying to move it.
It shouldn't move at all.
If you're still just point in that direction.
So this is the type of object that, you know, this is the type of life
that moves things is this, the type of object that only rotates with
it, right?
It only spins around and scales and shears, and does those other sorts
of operations that are encoded in here?
But it will never actually displace itself, right?
It will never move away from the origin any further than it already is
based on the translation.
It can move further away from the origin based on scaling, obviously.
But that's, you know, again, not a displacement, right?
So this this value actually isn't meaningless.
Either, it just isn't a coordinate of the kind that we're used to
talking about when we talk about things in the actual world and
picking points in three dimensional space because we don't talk about
there being this fourth coordinate ever.
But it does have a practical usage that can be used to.
Certain effect when you are providing values to multiply by a matrix,
right?
Okay.
So let's take a look at our projection Matrix now with all of that
understanding here is our projection Matrix.
And for starters, you know, I'm going to put projection in quotes here
because even though it's being loaded into opengl as projection Matrix
lat, is it doing any projection?
Not really
And you'll see what I mean by that in the feud in the future.
But just so you're, you know, as you already kind of know, we do the
projection ourselves in that, get empty basis.
P things, the actual projection, with the perspective, foreshortening
and all that stuff.
And so really, the projections already happened.
This Matrix essentially is saying, don't do any projection, it's
really what it's saying.
It just does some scaling and manipulation of the coordinates, right?
Because we don't want opengl to do another projection.
We want open G.
Just use the one we already.
Computed.
So what is this thing doing?
Well, you can see how these these equations are kind of coming down.
Let me go ahead and make that a clearer Z there.
You can see how these equations are sort of working out.
You can see we have two over W.
Times x 2 over H times y now.
Why are we Computing?
Those terms?
Well, remember we've already done.
By the time we get here.
We've already
he done.
This work.
Okay.
We've already taken our m, 2 pixels transform and multiplied that by
whatever.
Our
Whatever our projection result was and we've already offset by the
screen center.
So we've already put our values into screen space.
This does is undo that work.
Right?
If x came in, as let's say it was all the way to this end of the
screen, right?
So it was W, right?
So we were talking about a pixel that was over here and we input a w.
What would this do?
Well, the W's would cancel out.
We would get 2 minus 1 which is 1, which just makes one be.
This, you know, this side of the screen is equal to 1 in the output.
What if
We were to input 0, right?
So all the way over on this side of the screen in our parlance well to
over W Times 0 is just 0 and we're left with just negative 1.
So negative, 1 is over on this ice cream, same with this, right?
So you can see what we're doing here with that Matrix is we've created
a matrix, which takes coordinate system that write this in the right
place, that looks like this.
Right?
And it transforms it to one.
That looks oops, that's great.
That looks like this.
Okay, so you can see exactly what we're doing with that.
With that projection Matrix, we've outputted things that look like
this and the reason we output those because we have a software
renderer and that's what we wanted to draw with.
Is just locations in the frame buffer, but clearly opengl wanted this.
And so we needed to create a matrix that would produce this coordinate
system for opengl.
And that is exactly what I wanted to talk about today because it's
crucial for us to understand why all
Because that's the obvious.
Next question, right?
Is why does it want that, right?
Why does it want - 121?
What's going on here?
Okay,
and again, like I was saying, I really think this is crucial to
understand when you're working on 3D stuff because it can be so
confusing to people to look at projection matrices because they just
have no idea what's going on in them and a lot of the reason they have
no idea what's going on in them is because they don't fundamentally
know about the - 121 space because if you think about what you were
doing with the projection Matrix in our world and what we wanted,
With it.
We're producing a very different looking thing, right?
And so, if you're accidentally still in this mindset, and you look at
matrices, at do this, or you try to make matrices that do something,
you're going to make something totally wrong, because it's not doing
even remotely the same thing as what opengl wants you to do, okay?
So let's talk about what's actually happening here.
Okay what's actually happening here is opengl has to sort of have a
bunch of processing that occurs in order to do the 3D pipeline
correctly and robots late.
Okay, and one of those things is clipping
Clipping is extremely important.
It needs to be done.
Exactly correctly, or you'll get all kinds of visual artifacts which
means that this sort of math had to be worth out.
Exactly.
And the people who implemented in Hardware have to get it.
Exactly right.
There is no room for error and needs to be perfect.
Okay?
And the reason for that, is that, if you think about what happens,
you've got to systems that need to line up perfectly.
And here's what those two systems are.
If I have a triangle
And I say for this triangle, you know, I am mapping my little smiley
face on to it or whatever there's my texture map, right?
I Define the texture, mapping, all of the routines that do that.
All of the, you know, basically the pixel Shader, the fragments all of
the pixels Center, picking all that stuff, I Define everything such
that when this triangle is on the screen, I know I get this exact
beautiful try, you know perfectly rendered triangle and it looks like
a nice modern GPU rendered triangle, right?
It does not look for example like, you know, a PlayStation 1.
I do
If you've ever seen for example, a PlayStation 1 but well, you know
what, maybe we can just grab some graphics from the PlayStation 1 or
something like this, and I don't mean to pick on the PlayStation 1
uniquely.
I'm just picking something from that era, right?
So let's see here, PlayStation 1.
Let's see.
How do I get a game?
What's a good example?
May be Final Fantasy or something, I don't know.
What would be a good?
That's got too much pre-rendered stuff.
I need something that's going to be more.
Well, you know what?
It might be fine.
Let's find out.
There we go.
I'm trying to think if this will just the frame rates kind of bad to.
So, it's kind of hard to see some of this PS1 like maybe
Maybe this would be better.
Some of these would give exactly what I want, I suppose.
Still not really probably good enough for what I really want to
illustrate, but you can kind of see something happening here.
This is somebody who's hot.
The emulator I desk to use so you can kind of see what's happening
there.
Right?
I don't know if I can make this thing so is some higher res.
I guess not.
I wish I had a better example of this.
Well that's actually pretty good there.
Let's see if we can take a look at that.
I'm going to see if I can get a good high risk play of this because I
just want you to kind of take a look and see stop.
Exactly.
That's all I wanted to get in there.
All right, so if you take a look at something like that, right?
I'm not talking about that sort of thing because that's sort of back
when they didn't have all the math or exactly where they couldn't
afford the Silicon to do all the math worked out, right?
And obviously I don't mean they don't have the math right out like the
industry, obviously the industry had it worked out in the PS1 are just
the people who made the PS1, I don't know.
If the reason the PS1 has those problems is is because they didn't
know about how to do it, exactly right?
Or because they didn't have the Silicon to do it.
Exactly right, or what?
Right, I'm
Sure because St I was doing it right at that time in the higher end
Hardware.
So anyway, assuming that you don't want that like wobbly stuff, and
whatever you've very precisely specified exactly how to fill pixels
what you know they should be how they should be doing the math
interpolation to know the right texture and support from so that you
don't have all of this shifting.
Because you've maybe major Mass sloppy and it's rounding weirdly or
arbitrarily or snapping two integers.
Is arbitrarily and not taking that stuff into account, right?
So, sub-pixel accurate rendering like that, where you're doing all of
the math, just?
Right is very important for a solid looking image and they've done all
that.
But now consider what happens when that same triangle is slowly moving
and it slides off screen, right?
Well, during this slide off screen, you are seeing lots of steps of
actually filling other triangles.
Right?
You've got, you know, actually this triangle that you're filling once
it gets to that part of the screen, you're only feeling that triangle
once you get to that part of the screen, right?
So you're not even giving it the same coordinates in terms of like
distance from each other or even same structure.
You may even have to split some
Rules.
For example, if you imagine something like a triangle that was off the
screen like this.
Now, you've
Actually two triangles that you're filling for this one triangle,
right?
If it was moving down this way, right?
Some big triangle here and so, if you think about, you have to get all
of this math, correct?
And so it's incredibly important to the pipeline respect very
carefully.
That it be spect.
Such that you can have enough Precision everywhere to do the right
thing that you will not see any errors and that the clip triangles
will look exactly the same as unclip.
Triangles as they move off the screen to avoid getting any of these
other artifacts right perspective.
Incorrect interpolation is
Totally separate thing.
We kind of mentioned that before but I'm not even talking about that
right now.
I'm literally just talking even about just the basic getting the
subpixel fill and the correct texture coordinate picking correct.
Even just that stuff.
You have to make sure that all this stuff goes correctly and there's a
lot of different things that go on in this.
Sometimes there's a thing called guard band, which does some stuff and
that's a separate issue as well.
And gpus have all these other things that they do, we don't have to
care about any of that right now.
Now we just have to understand the fact that this is real work and
real math.
That had to be worked out and gotten just right and it's non-trivial,
okay?
I mean, like anything else is Trivial once you actually just know it
but it was not in Trivial that to everyone had to actually sit down
and do all this work and get it just right in.
This was a, you know, this was real real stuff.
So, in order to do that clipping process and to do it accurately the
way that opengl handles its coordinates system, is the input
coordinate system, right?
That's the X Y Z's that you pass, right?
Are they go through the projection Matrix?
Right and they come out in what is called a unit cube sometimes even
though it's really like a bilateral unit cube right.
But what this thing is is it's essentially a space where you've got
going to draw in some kind of crude.
There we go.
Here's an X.
And A Y Epps, that's no good.
Here we go, an x, a y, and the Z, right?
And it's negative 2 1 negative 1 to 1 on all the axes.
So this cube is, you know, along the Z axis negative 1 to 1 along the
y-axis, its negative one to one as well.
And I guess maybe I could write those on the actual axis.
If I was cool.
Right.
So the boundaries of this Cube, this imaginary Cube are negative 1 to
1.
And what it's going to do is it's going to clip the entire world,
everything that gets input to it is going to get clipped against this
Cube.
So anything that extends past negative 1 or 1,
Any direction on any access will get clipped if it's completely
outside.
So there's a triangle floating out here, it just gets discarded
entirely, if it happens to pierce it, right?
Then it will produce only the part of the triangle, that is going to
be actually inside the cube.
Okay.
So, that is actually how it does.
Its clipping in this uniform, I think this is typically called clip
space.
I'm not sure if that's what the open.
Jill spec, actually calls.
It's been a long time.
I should probably go.
I probably should have gone and reread that before talking about this
today, so I could have used right terms but as is the rule on handmade
hero I never get to do any preparation.
It's not allowed.
So that's just my vague recollection.
As I think this is called clip space.
So you have the input here, it goes through a matrix multiply
And that Matrix, multiply puts everything into is responsible for
putting everything into Cliffs face.
Now, you write this Matrix.
What that means is when we created our projection Matrix, that is our
job, our job was to put a, our input coordinate system, which was this
into Clips face, which looks like this.
Now we didn't have to worry about Z because we don't have it.
These are all 0, right?
So since ours, these are all 0, we didn't have to do any work in this
part of the Matrix at all to deal with Z.
We would have had to do the exact same thing and that's what we're
going to see.
That's what I'm building up to here.
We're going to have to do the exact same thing with Z.
Once we start handling Z in the back part of the pipeline here,
because what we're going to have to do, is make sure that our Z - 1 2
1,
Also does that exact same work?
So it takes the boundaries of what we are trying to render in our
world and Maps those from negative 1 to 1, okay?
So as you might imagine, once you sort of get this, this once you,
once you have this, it's there's not a whole lot more that needs to
happen in order to in order to get your screen coordinates.
It's just a matter of rendering what's in here, but it still does go
through a little bit of extra tough in terms of determining where
things actually are on the screen.
And the reason for that
Is obviously that, at some point, it really does have to do the
transform to pixels.
And of course, the way that it transforms to pixels is now it does is
essentially the reverse of this, right?
It now has to go from Clips face to I believe what they call Window
space.
In opengl.
And that is again a really straightforward transform that just
involves multiplying out again by the width and then offsetting,
right?
So that's just taking a negative 1 to 1 range on each of the axes and
producing a 02 width range 0 to height range, right?
Exactly like what we had to undo because they need to get pixels
eventually as well.
So they end up producing window Space by doing this.
Transform.
And I believe this is documented very clearly if I'm not mistaken in
GL viewport, I think so.
Let me go ahead and load that up here or try to load it up.
There it is.
And here you go.
Right.
And you can see it's the exact inverse of what we were doing.
I'm right, you can.
Yeah, you can.
You can see that it does exactly what we were doing.
This is the precise inverse of what we did to take our screen
coordinates and put them into clip space because hey, that's the do
the exact opposite to put them out.
And then of course it has an offset because remember GL viewport
doesn't have to draw to the whole screen.
You can draw two like a subset of the screen.
So it needs to also have like a displacement in there to allow you to
draw two just a sub rectangle, right?
And so that equation is going to happen after the things are in clip
space.
Let me just see, I don't know if I can get like a better.
Because these aren't there.
I don't know if any of the things we'll have the those those terms.
Oh, right gluperspective, that's what it's called.
There is a thing that I don't think many people use anymore, but there
is a utility library that came with opengl.
That you could use that had stuff like an automatic thing for
generating a perspective.
Matrix.
I didn't know if any of these would have quick documentation that
would talk about the window Space versus screen space the best place
to look for this stuff.
And I guess I mean I should just bring it up but the GL spec is is
pretty good about keeping all this stuff.
It's less.
So nowadays that it's focused on all of the
craziness in Modern Hardware used to be a much more manageable you
like, for example, if you go back to like, Geo spec as of like to, I
don't know if that's
I don't know how how
How easy that would be for me to get.
Okay, here you go.
So if you go back to like earlier versions of the Geo spec, it's a
If that's much more focused on just like the fixed function Pipeline
and while that's not so relevant anymore.
Because like I said, most of the time you end up do using shaders and
stuff like that.
If you're doing anything significant with Graphics program, these
days, it's a much more manageable spec, if you just want to read stuff
and find out like what the terms are.
And so, this is kind of a handy document to potentially peruse,
because you can take a look at stuff in an easier way.
So, so like here's here's an example, coordinate transforms, right?
And this kind,
Comes through and talks entirely about.
Yeah, here you go right.
This talks about all the terms and here is the other one that I wanted
to.
Let's see here.
So window coordinates, so window space is not quite correct.
Let's talk about.
Window coordinates.
We go and it looks like normalized device.
Coordinates is is the phrase of the negative 1 to 1.
It looks like clip coordinates subdivision car down and clip
coordinates to yield.
No choice coordinates in the final few of our transformation is
converters courts into window coordinates, okay?
So, that's interesting.
I may have misspoken on this then, as well.
So maybe the clip happens before the prospective divide which would
mean that you're not quite here yet.
So let me try and again I'm going to try and use this is unusual for
me.
I don't try to usually get these right but I'm gonna try to analyzed
coordinates
Is that?
There we go.
And maybe.
Also normalized.
Device coordinates.
Now, it I've got to have to take a look at the speck, Mark carefully
to see if they actually say exactly where the clipping happens, but
the part that we need to talk about in here now, I suppose it doesn't
really matter per se where the clip happens for our purposes because
we don't really need to know where the clip happens because we don't
do anything at that point if this makes sense.
But it would be nice to know it sounds like just the fact that they
talk about clip coordinates being
The protective I'd which I'll talk about in a second.
Suggest to me that my statement just there that they clip in the
negative one to one space is not actually true.
They clip just before it becomes in that space potentially, I'm not
sure, but let's see.
In fact, we might be able to tell because again, like I said, this is
a really good spec for this sort of thing.
I'm just assuming that the fact that they call it clip coordinates is,
is means that they clip there, but they're not coming out in quite
Saying, which because, and they might not want to say because maybe
they don't want the implementation have to know.
So, I don't know.
Yeah.
If you maybe take a look and see if you can find on your own, I don't
want to waste too much stream time on it, but you can see they've got
exactly basically the thing that we drew here with one exception which
is the part that we probably should start talking about.
Now I don't know if it's too early for it I so it's not I still got a
reasonable amount of time so maybe I'll give it a shot.
All right, so I think we've got our terminology correct here window,
coordinates and normalized device coordinates, and it looks like
actually clip coordinates are not these.
It looks like clip coordinates are actually a little bit before.
So I'm just going to go ahead and say, since it sounds like it from
the spec that the GPU may actually do the clipping before it actually
produces the cube just before.
And so let's talk about what happens in here.
All right,
So here's the part that I haven't talked about yet because our Matrix
doesn't do it basically and the reason that our Matrix doesn't do it
is because we're not actually performing any kind of work with Z.
So we don't actually try to produce, we don't try to be careful about
producing any particular results with the Z coordinate.
Like, we're literally not doing anything with our Z coordinates.
So there's nothing there's really no.
Modification that's going on.
Now it's tempting to take a look at this and say oh okay so you know I
know I've got my XYZ one that comes in here and I've got you know,
that I've got my XYZ one that comes in here and I've got an output
that also has an x y z 1 in it, right?
And so if we were going to talk about what would happen in terms of
projection and stuff like that, we would think about the Z coordinate
as being this coordinate, it turns out that's not
Entirely going to be the case.
So let me quickly give a brief refresher on what the perspective part
of perspective, projection, or the projection part I should say of
projection.
But the prospectus part in particular is going to have to accomplish
because we've already done it previously in handmade here, but we're
going to have to kind of remember again, and like be careful about
what that actually means.
So remember what we are trying to do with perspective projection?
And just to say this one more time because there's so much stuff in
here and I apologize for there being so much stuff in here, but you
kind of have to have a little bit of all of it in order to understand
what's going on.
In here, we were doing all of the work for the perspective.
Projection.
Would we want in perspective?
Now, we had two branches, one was orthographic and orthographic is a
transform that doesn't do perspective projection, right?
It doesn't have things getting smaller as they get further away from
the viewer.
It's just a direct.
You know, sort of projection onto the screen that doesn't change size
based on distance, but when we weren't trying to do that and that's
usually used for like you I or something is why we were doing that,
right?
But when we're not doing that, when we're trying to do things that are
sort of more realistic in the world and they get smaller the further.
They get away from the viewer.
When we are doing something like that, then we need to have some way
of shrinking things as they get further away and if you remember
correctly, the way we did, that was with a relationship of similar.
Triangles.
Right?
What we did was say, well okay, if we're looking from here, here is
our eyeball, right?
And we know we've got some flat screen here.
That we want to project onto, and you remember me, drawing this
diagram.
Hopefully then if we have a point out in the world, somewhere we can
find where it is on the screen, right?
We can find its coordinates on the screen by crew constructing to try
and similar triangles right to similar.
Right triangles, here's one.
Here's the other one and we know since we've got both the distance to
the screen, right?
We've got the distance to the screen and we
Half the distance to the point, right?
And another way to look at, that would be those would be the Z
coordinates, right?
This would be the Z of the screen, right?
And this would be the Z of the point, right?
Maybe the better way to do that would be screen Z.
Point Z, right, since we've got both of those.
And we know this, which is say the y, coordinate of the point or
whatever.
If we want to find the screen, why it's just a straight relationship,
similar, triangle relationship, just like, high school geometry class,
right?
So, all we have to do is just set up the really simple relationship
that s.
Why is 2py exactly as SZ is 2pz.
And then when you solve this equation, which again is Trivial to solve
And Y equals screen.
Z x, py / peasy right?
Just multiply this through, you've got a trivial way of computing that
relationship, right?
And so we basically worked out how we were going to do our math based
on based on this, right?
And it's very straightforward.
So that's what we have here, but
Implicit in all this, right?
Is is sort of this activity, that, that that relationship has a
divided, right?
We had to divide by something in order to make that ratio work and you
can see that divided operating right here and this is the crucial part
of it.
That's the thing that
The perspective right there, right?
The the correct visual appearance of things shrinking into the
distance is a 1 over distance relationship and so that must appear in
the final equations of your graphics, you know, of what you're
producing.
If someone over distance relationship doesn't appear in there, you
will not have something that looks like a human style perspective.
Spective, right.
So
That crucial part when we come back and look here, you can see where
is it going to come from right?
There is no way in matrix, multiplication to produce a divided, right?
I have an input and I need to divide some other things in my input, by
this, right, I need to like, get the Z in a denominator down here.
There is no way in a matrix to take something from the input and
divide
It by something else in the input, matrices, don't have that ability,
right?
So what happens in opengl is there sort of a secret additional
procedure?
It's not secret because like I said, it's very clearly spelled out how
it works.
But in order to produce prospective results, which we obviously want,
There is a divide that's baked in.
So, implicit in the process, although you set this entire Matrix
herself and provide all the values for the Matrix.
So it's a generic Matrix multiply, there is a baked divide that
happens in here.
That is like expect to happen.
It's just like after we do the projection Matrix like we would
normally do with the Matrix.
We are going to perform a divided and the reason that we're going to
perform perform a divide is because there is no other way to get
perspective results out of this thing.
So although we love
To make it so that you just specify a matrix and that's the whole
operation.
We can't.
Okay.
And so how do they do that?
Well what they typically do is they say well, okay, what we're going
to do is we're going to provide for one divided operation and that
divided operation is going to be to normalize.
Whatever is in the vector at the End by its W coordinate, right?
So instead of w coming out as one right, w-we're telling you, whoever
authors this Matrix, you can make W come out to be whatever you want
it to be.
So set up these Matrix values to be whatever you want.
Put anything you want into the resulting W.
And then what I will do when I am going to
The final coordinates is I will take all of these other coordinates
here, right?
And W itself although it's kind of somewhat meaningless, I guess and I
will divide them conceptually by the value of w.
So it's actually
You know, this is sort of what you have been thinking of it.
You know, we've got a matrix a projection Matrix here, right?
And we're going to multiply our Point by this projection Matrix and
get a new Matrix.
I think I get a new Point conceptually that's sort of what we're
thinking of but really what's actually happening and we just weren't
using it because we were setting W equal to 1.
So it was never actually performing any actual operation for us what's
actually happening here.
Is this?
Right?
Well that so we're actually taking whatever the resulting MP is using
its W value to divide, the whole result of our Matrix transform.
Right?
So what that will produce is essentially whatever the x coordinates
computed, you know whatever the new x coordinate is over the W Nu W
coordinate whatever.
The y-coordinate is over the new W coordinate, whatever the Z
coordinate is over the new W coordinate and then one
Right, would be the output.
So, hopefully, that makes some sense.
It's purely a convention in some sense, right?
Meaning, there's many mathematical ways that maybe they could have
gone about saying how we wait get a perspective dividing here, but
this is the cleanest and maybe there are deeper math reasons.
Why they felt like this was a good idea.
I don't know.
I don't pretend to know I wasn't there, but that's how they chose to
do it.
So what this means is, if
You want to implement your own perspective, projection inside an
opengl Matrix?
What you are fundamentally trying to do
Is move the information about what is supposed to get divided out into
the W coordinate, which means fiddling with these values here, right?
Which are what control the W coordinate.
Okay.
In order to put information in there, so we're not going to be doing
this anymore.
00:01 is not going to be what we're doing at all because we don't want
a 1 in here at all.
Instead what we're going to do is something more like a 0010
Right to move our Z coordinate into our W, so that it will divide
through, right?
That's exactly.
We're going to be doing because we need the W, coordinate to be
something more fancy than that.
But you get the idea, right?
So
At that point you may also ask well okay what is this here for?
Right?
Because if these are the coordinates,
if these are the coordinates that we're going to draw on the screen,
this is the thing that we're going to divide them by, right?
So we're going to do you know / W these so that's the perspective,
right?
So we're producing our XY coordinates here is the perspective part
that's going to produce our - 121 space over here and then we're going
to apply a viewport transform to get it into pixel space.
Well what is the Z?
Why are we even what's this even here for?
Why are we even Computing a z value?
And that's where we come full circle.
And the answer is because it goes into Z buffer.
That's what the z-buffer actually is.
Its, we need to now produce a value that will go into the Z buffer and
part, and parcel with that.
It's what needs to be used for clipping.
Right.
Because again, we need to have a range from negative 1 to 1 that we
can use for clipping.
Right?
So again, I want to just make sure I understand.
I'm going to go back and double-check the spec, to make sure that I'm
right about where the clipping happens, because I still don't know
where the clipping happens.
So saying there's a big divide here, may be the wrong thing to say, I
want to just make it clear that like, yeah, I want to see them say
specifically where they have this happen.
And I can't, I just can't seem to see them say it explicitly, so it
may be that they just don't, but you can see very clearly what they
call the stuff.
Right?
The vertex coordinates are presented, the GL are termed object
coordinates, right?
And so this right here,
Is this and this is what we're giving it right.
The modelview Matrix is applied is going to yield, I coordinates and
another Mage called objection are supplied to.
I course we equip born.
It's that part is not so true, really?
That's a very conceptual thing in opengl.
That's actually gone now, anyway, in the modern versions of it.
So that's kind of an acronym stick to 2.0 and the old fixed function
pipeline stuff, model view and projection Matrix.
We're just a convenience really, those are specified together, right?
And so really, you can
Think about this is just, there is a matrix, right?
And it can do whatever it wants, but it has to, at least do the
production of the screen coordinates, but member matrices can be
multiplied together.
So you can have whatever your object transform World, transfer, case
transforms.
All your other transferred can all be baked into one and then they
just have to be multiplied with the projection Matrix at the end to
produce one Matrix does all the work.
So even though they talk about model view and projection here really,
there's just one Matrix and even though opengl lets you set two
matrices,
He's in the old school way.
In the old fixed function,
Pipeline, those are just multiplied together.
Anyway, when they're actually used by the GPU, nobody actually does
the to, I think, the only reason they kept them separate was because
there was some old-school lighting stuff that they would do.
I don't even remember.
It was just nonsense stuff.
So anyway, so really in practice, we only need that one Matrix for the
full transform, when we're actually producing our screen coordinates
and so when we multiply by The Matrix, we get the clip coordinates,
right?
The perspective divisions carried out on.
Up towards do.
You'll normalized device coordinates which are these guys here, right?
And so I'm just assuming that the clip happens in here somewhere and I
just yeah, I'm assuming it happens in clip coordinates cuz that's what
they call it.
But again, I just don't know enough about the history there to know
why specifically, that's the best way to do it.
Like, I don't know.
I guess, here's one thing I will say and again, takes the grain of
salt because I'm not an expert on these sorts of things.
So I don't want to pretend to tell you the right answer.
But you know, in order to get the clipping correct, you can never
divide by 0, right.
So you imagine there's a divide that's going on in here, right?
I'm going to divide by w.
Right?
It could be that W is 0 if I divide by zero, all bets are off, right?
And as I get closer to 0 things, get more and more unstable in that
sense, right?
They start to go towards infinity and all sorts of stuff like that
before they hit undefined.
So in that sense you might imagine.
Well, okay, I can't divide first before I've clipped, because part of
clipping is, you know, if I imagine I've got my view
Here's my view.
Frustum right.
I'm looking down things this way, if I imagine, I've got some triangle
that comes back behind the viewer.
It goes out in front of the viewer and back behind the viewer.
It will pass.
You know, if this is where the viewer is standing, it will pass by Z
equals 0, like, this triangle Mae Pierce, Z equals zero effect.
Maybe I could draw it from the side for as, for better.
I think I drove the other way last time.
So you imagine, I'm trying to do this operation here.
Right?
Here's a, you know, a point and I'm doing the projection onto the
screen.
Well, what if this point is part of a triangle and the other point is
over here, right?
Here's my triangle, right at Z equals 0.
You know I'm saying.
Well, I still need to draw this triangle so I still need to produce
this clipped Point, that's like wherever it is right?
Wherever this triangle, intersects the screen I still need to produce
it and I still need to draw that, right?
That's crucial.
But I can't do the Divide first because this point becomes undefined
if I do the Divide right.
So I assume that basically what's happening there is the reason that
they have to perform the clipping before they go into this space is
just because, or at least conceptually perform at their, I don't know,
you know exactly how they do it is, you know, up to them obviously.
But I'm assuming that the reason they have to do it is because if they
don't get the near clipping plane, clipping done first, then they
would it would explode, right?
They wouldn't be able to do the clipping anymore.
So I suspect that that's basically what has to happen, right?
At that at that point, right?
The clipping has to do that clipping and now that I think about it
since I have done
Sort of software versions of this before.
That is exactly what you have to do.
You have to, I've never done it.
I did it before I knew about the opengl pipeline and so I never really
had anything as fancy as normalized device coordinates at all.
Those were totally A New Concept to me when I learned opengl but you
you can't do your perspective divide before doing your clipping
otherwise?
Yeah you get when things get close and pass through the near clip play
and you get explosions.
You get.
Yeah, yeah.
Your triangles go nuts because they get close to that undefined
divided.
So yeah so that actually makes perfect sense to me so I can talk to
you that.
So you go through the projection, you do the clip and then you do that
big divide to finally give you your complete - 121 space which is
where everything is fully defined.
Okay, but that's all we really need to know about it.
For now, in a sense, there's a lot there but that's really all we need
to know about it again, we don't really have to understand how the GPU
does clipping.
I just kind of wanted to give you a little sense of what was going on
there.
We don't actually have to know because we don't have to deal with that
clipping in any particular way, we just have to make sure that we're
out putting coordinates that make sense in this final space.
So our big focus is on this cube right here, because
Thing that we produce in our projection Matrix has to produce that
Cube correctly.
We have to make sure that everything that we want to see in our world
is fitting directly into that Cube.
So you can imagine our entire view space like what we are viewing.
That whole frustum, right?
The whole view, frustum.
I don't know how to draw this very well, maybe this that, maybe this
is the right way to draw it.
Just from the side again.
So I guess I'll do the dotted line.
There we go.
So, looking for the sign anyway.
I didn't want to try to draw a frustum in 3D.
It's kind of hard.
My sketching skills aren't up to it.
So looking from the side, our job is to take this whole part of the
world that we can see, right?
Here's the eye.
We're looking this way and we're trying to take this whole part of the
world that we can see and map it into that, you know, negative 1 to 1
cube.
Right.
That's what we're trying to do.
And so these are World coordinates, you know, and we and and we need
to map them into this this normalized device coordinates and that
involves a bunch of stuff.
First of all, it involves centering everything around the camera.
So actually technically, like even in this diagram, these aren't even
really
You know, they aren't sent around the camera yet, it's everything is
going to be in World space or wherever it is, right?
And then we have to transform it.
So it's centered around the camera, we have to, then transfer it.
So it's between the the front near in front clip, planes map - 121 in
Z.
We have to transform it so the extents of the screen map to negative 1
to 1 going out after the protected divided in blah, blah blah, blah
blah, right?
So we have a ton of work to do to make sure that our Matrix does all
the work necessary to take this frustum shape and
It you know, after the prospective divided into that clean negative 1
to 1 Cube, that's what we have to do.
So that is our goal.
And if we think about what's happening with our Z coordinate, right?
The Z coordinate is programmed when it's going to be using the Z
buffer.
Again to range between negative 1 and 1.
Now there are extensions to Z buffer is like w buffering and these
other sorts of things that we're not going to talk about right now.
But assuming we're just using a straightforward z-buffer for our depth
buffer, which is what we're going to do first, at least, when we are
producing our Z value.
Then what we are trying to do here effectively in that Z position is
we're trying to map the near clipping plane, right?
And I don't know if we've ever talked about the concept of a near and
far clipping plane.
We may not have but
a whole reason we have these things is specifically for that reason,
we want to be able to produce some consistent value for negative, one
in z,
and some consistent value of 1 in Z.
So we need to Define bounds on our world.
Where we know, like, we understand what we are actually mapping them
to, right?
Because we need those normalized device coordinates to map out
correctly, right?
And so we create an ear clip plane, which is this.
And if our clip plane, which is this, and that's what determines our Z
range right now.
There's a lot of things that have done.
There's
Lot of Z buffers, methodologies that aren't this.
There's a thing called an infinite, far clipping plane, which is by,
you can do a trick by putting Z into a denominators, so that you never
have a far clipping plane.
It just gets less and less precise.
The further out you get I believe is the thing which can just use a
floating Point.
Direct.
See buffer, where it just allows it to be greater than 1 and you use,
you just start floating Point values, which is basically the same
thing.
It just gets less and less accurate, as you get further out, so,
So by no means, do you have to end your understanding of Z buffer is
just with the understanding that you map Things, We negative 1 to 1
and that's the values that get mapped into the z-buffer somehow that
are used for the types of stuff that we talked about yesterday.
But for the purposes of our first implementation here and possibly
what, we will just stay with because handmade hero doesn't reach him.
A hero does kind of know a very tight bound on what it's trying to
display depth wise.
So it's it's highly unlikely that we will really need anything more
advanced than a base.
Z buffer approach but just understand that there's more out there than
just the basic z-buffer approach and if so if that's something that
you're interested in, you can look those up again.
You can look up W buffer you can look up infinite.
For our clip plane, you can look up.
Like, there's probably like no far clipping plane or, like, disable
far clipping plane.
I don't know.
I'm not sure what all the methods even are at this point, but there's
a lot of there's a lot more out there than just than just this one way
that we're looking at, but we just don't have any need to go into
them.
So, be sure to take a look at those.
If you're doing an other types of games, if you're playing around, you
know, with a more sort of traditional 3D style thing, where you're
standing in a world and looking out over the horizon or something in
it.
And, you know,
X, an outdoor scene.
For example, where you got these really Long View distances, there are
other ways you can try to approach these problems that don't
necessarily involve creating a far, clipping plane.
It's, I don't know if there's any way to get away with not having an
ear clip plane.
I have never really thought about that.
That's kind of interesting.
But yeah, that's usually less of a concern because typically, you
don't want stuff like right in the face of the player like that
anyway, so it's not.
Not as big of a concern but you know at the very least the far
clipping plane is often something.
When you're dealing with very large world's at view distances.
The far clipping plane is something that you do care about potentially
not having or at least not seeing its effects.
And so, that's something to be aware of.
So, anyway, if we come back here, let's talk about our projection
Matrix and how we might get sort of the effects that we want to get
out of it.
So let's take a look at how we were sort of doing this stuff.
To begin with.
And I think we did this on his.
Made hero before, when we were talking about how to produce the X and
Y coordinates.
But let's just kind of go back through here and see how we might want
to to do this.
So let's pretend we're having x, y, z and Z is come in.
Now that are essentially in our, you know, camera space.
Let's call it.
And what I mean by camera space is just I'm not going to talk about
the process right now of centering the world around the camera.
So let's just assume that the camera as you
No, at 000 or something.
We've already done that work.
So the world is just centered around the camera and that the cameras,
like, looking down the Z axis, so that the Z axis is like pointing
back up at the camera.
Right?
So we've done that, we've taken where the camera is out of the
equation and we're just talking about producing the perspective part.
And the reason that it's free for us to do is because again, matrices
can be multiplied together at any time to produce a composite result.
So if I
Something like this.
Two matrices, I can produce a matrix that does the effect of two
matrices just by multiple took multiplying together.
So if I want to, I can consider my projection Matrix, as a separate
Matrix, I can consider my camera Matrix as a separate Matrix, and this
one can be responsible for putting.
Well, actually these are in the wrong order, right now.
Order matters.
So let's try that again.
Here's my camera Matrix.
Here's my projection Matrix.
I can take a thing where I want to, you know, do a camera transform on
the points to put them relative to the camera and then I can do
another transform that does the projection that opengl wants me to do
and then I can combine those together and get the same effect on a
point by doing just a single Matrix, right?
And so, it's free for me to consider steps of these previous process
individually and not worry about any inefficiency because all I have
to do is before I get started with my world, rendering just just
Quick Matrix multiply to smush them together or even do it offline.
I can even do it in something like Mathematica or something like that.
If I want to, if I have matrices with constants in them that I've
considered separately, I can just do that ahead of time and produce
the result and then use that or whatever.
Right?
So there's really no consequence for considering matrices separately
because you can always multiply them either in code or symbolically
ahead of time to get a composite result that will do the combination
of them.
So, I'm going to consider just
The projection now.
And we're going to take a quick look at that.
So
Okay, so let's talk a little bit about what the sorts of things are
that we're going to have to do here, right?
And if we take a look at what's going on, you'll notice there's some
there's a very interesting occur.
Happening here and I just want to make sure that we sort of have all
of it.
Let me sort of go through what we were doing before us.
You can kind of appreciate all the stuff because it's been a while
since we've looked at this part of the code.
And it's, you know, understandable that you probably haven't, you
know, it's been paged out all the stuff that we were doing.
So let's take a look at how this transform is working here.
You can kind of see we have a
We have a pretty basic transformed here at the back of our transform.
This just doing essentially exactly what open jails going to do, in
terms of transforming, like things that the pixel space, right?
We don't really have to worry too much about about that part of it
because open jails are automatically going to do the transform out
into the screen.
But one of the things that you can see here is that nowhere in any
Of our equations, are we taking account of the different aspect ratio
of the screen?
Right?
And think about this and just just make sure that we appreciate all
the different parts of it.
When we are talking about coordinates, when we draw to the screen,
there are more pixels and X than there are in y.
Right?
Most of the time when we're talking about display, it's going to be
like a 1080p display or something, like this.
It's going to be like 16 by 9 aspect ratio.
And so part of the stuff that happens.
In this process, right, and you can see it happening.
Well, let's go back down here.
Part of what is kind of interesting about this.
If you think about this normalized device coordinates face, where
everything's negative 1 to 1, well, the negative 1 to 1 in X is
actually representing a wider swath of world space than the negative 1
to 1 in y.
And the reason for that is it's about to get blown back.
Out to a larger width.
And so, when we produce our negative 1 to 1 in X and our negative, 1
to 1, and why we didn't have to care about that here.
And the reason that we didn't have to care about that here was because
we were never producing normalized.
Device coordinates, we never squished our world into a negative 1 to 1
Cube like opengl demands that we do, right?
So what happened and how we were compensating for this and opengl is
We're dividing by the with the head of time and the height ahead of
time in our Matrix.
So that when opens yell multiplied it again on the other side, it
undid it.
Right.
So, we were effectively fighting opengl to prevent its it's
multiplication by
Width and height from producing an aspect ratio Warp.
And just to hammer this point home, let's say we haven't done that,
right?
Let's say that they were both done by the width.
Well, here is what we'd get, right?
So you can hopefully you can appreciate their that what we're
essentially doing was fighting the normalized device coordinates to
make sure that the normalized device coordinates wouldn't produce a
warped aspect ratio when our image was displayed to the screen.
So we need to be aware of that.
Now when we when we construct our projection Matrix because we need to
take into account that exact same thing, right?
So where did our, where did we go here?
I don't even know where I was.
I'm too.
There we go.
Here it is.
So we need to be aware of that aspect ratio problem and we've got too
much stuff going on right now because some of our stuff, just all
multiplies out.
If you think about what's actually happening because we're sort of
doing things that we don't need to be doing because we're doing them
than undoing them.
So opengl can redo them and all that sort of stuff, right?
So let's start very simply and let's try to move some of these things
that we're doing over to the open GL projection Matrix just very
carefully, right?
So let's see here is our P coordinates that are coming out, right?
And you can see we have our camera, transform screen Center,
That's being adjusted in.
Now, what I want to do is see, can we remove the camera, transform
screen center, right?
Can I just get rid of that entirely, right?
And so what would happen if I just get rid of the camera, transform
scream center, right?
And then I multiply, and then I run the game.
Well, as you can see, you know, I don't really get any ill effects
other than just the fact that it isn't the center of the world right
now.
The center of the camera view, anyway, is now at
Zero instead of the center of the screen because I'm not doing that
offset, right.
But the only reason I had to do that offset in the opengl path was
because I had, you know, that's how we were doing it for the software
renderer and now in the opengl path, we've got the -1 -1 to compensate
so it was doing that offset again, right?
So, if I just play with these values, right?
I can produce a version of that transform, that doesn't have that
problem, right?
That reproduces.
What we had before.
Now I, of course, since we don't have, I'm going to have to go ahead
and say I don't have any idea why we're getting that Ridiculousness
there?
Oh, probably because our sorting is still using those values as well.
So yeah, until we turn on the z-buffer.
Are sorting is going to be nuts, but anyway, you can see that our
transform anyway is still correct.
I apologize, mr.
Sorter, you're getting complete nonsense now.
So we're going to be flickering like crazy until we turn on.
Just a z-buffer for that.
But what do you do?
In fact, what I could do is just turn the sort off entirely I suppose
because it's not really going to do anything anymore.
But anyway, so you can see right there that that simplified what we
were doing for starters.
Because right there we've kind of got this.
We've got a solution there which means that our transfer Matrix no
longer has to be fighting a thing.
We were doing in our project, in our sort of offline, projection part
here or not offline production, I should say our render group
projection stuff.
As opposed to the open GL, projection stuff, right?
So that's kind of nice.
Let's take a look now.
A little more deeply here at what we're doing in terms of outputting
the result P.
So we're going to have to start producing 3D coordinates obviously.
If we ever want our perspective, divide and stuff to happen.
And, you know, we're gonna have to look at what's going on with scale
and all these are the sorts of things.
So, we're going to take this very slowly but at least we got rid of
one of those things there.
So now let's take a look at the m.
2 pixels part of this nanometers to pixels is something that's telling
us about the size of the world, relative to the size of the display.
Right?
And what you can see here is that m 2 pixels is actually getting, its
is actually doing work.
Because this within this height here,
That were dividing by those are getting sort of undone, if you will by
opengl later.
So, this with and this height are basically nullified by opengl as
multiplication by the width and the height later, right?
However, one thing that we could look at here is to realize that the
number of pixels that were using in this case is represented,
obviously by opengl
Who is open jails multiplication by the width.
So we can probably unwind our knowledge of pixels out of this routine,
potentially entirely by just taking advantage of the fact that opengl
has to be multiplied by the number of pixels at the end anyway.
So although we have to know something about the scale of our world in
general, we don't really have to know anything about its relationship
to pixels because the multiplication by pixels is going to happen at
the end.
Right anyway.
So if we were to remove the width and the height from here and just
talk about the difference between the width and the height to correct
for the aspect ratio, then we would be able to create something where
the pixels wasn't considered in here at all.
Right?
So let's take a little bit of a look at what I mean by that.
So
Where are we specifying or m, 2 pixels value?
I believe that gets passed in and so let me just take a look here.
M, 2 pixels.
That is not in there.
Where is that?
I don't know where we specify this.
Oops, here you go.
So you can see what we're doing here.
We've got width in pixels / with the monitor, right?
And we call that in get standard camera params and we're passing the
width in pixels.
So let's just quickly just math wise and I think you'll see what I
mean.
As soon as I read out this equation, it should be relatively obvious.
Let's just see math wise, what that's doing.
So we have M to pixels that's width in pixels over with the monitor.
So that's with of pixels over with of mom.
Right?
That's what we're talking about here.
So that's m 2 pixels in the actual case where we're out putting our
coordinates here.
Here's our result P.
We've got me restrictions time, projected, X Y, we are multiplying by
that m, 2 pixels value.
Okay?
So the P that we are putting down to opengl is, is starting off being
multiplied by this coefficient, right?
So, whatever the point is, this is, well, I can just write it right
there, this is multiplying that point.
Then inside our opengl path.
What do we turn around?
I multiply it by.
Well, we multiply it by two over the with, right?
So we multiply it by 2 over the width in pixels
Look anything jump out at you there, right?
It's like, hey, that actually cancels out.
Right.
I mean, that's what's happening, right?
Opengl will then later X, the width of pixels again to put it back in,
right?
So even though we were sort of thinking of it as canceling, this
because we wanted to keep this really, we could think of it as these
two canceling and opengl doing that work.
So that would allow us to simplify things further and cancel these
out.
But there is a caveat and the caveat is, we haven't thought about the
fact that both the X and the Y are here.
And this is
I was trying to get to.
So here's the X.
And here is the why?
It doesn't cancel any more at this point, right?
So our x coordinate totally cancels our y coordinate does not.
It is left with the residual term and that residual term is the width
of the monitor over the height of the monitor, right?
And that is the ass.
Horatio correction.
That is the thing that when we were shrinking down into those
normalized - 121 coordinates, does the correct warp to ensure that we
are encompassing.
A wider swath in X then we are encompassing in y and you can see what
I mean by wider swath because wpx right in this case and wpy are the
things that are
I'm I'm at a loss for words here, because wpx is is bigger, let then
wpy, this will mean that this will produce a what a bigger
multiplication effect on the why.
Right now again intuitively, you would think well, a bigger
multiplication effect in why produces a wider swath, and why, it
doesn't.
And the reason is because remember the negative 1 to 1 bounds, are
what determines, what we'll see on the screen, so if
Multiply y out bigger, we will select a smaller slice from it to be
viewed.
And so this is why I say it's very important to understand why I
wanted to talk about those normalized device coordinates so badly that
negative 1 to 1 Cube there.
And again, yeah, I wish I knew more about the origins of the 3D
Pipeline and why you did things certain ways.
I if we just had one of like the old SGI if like critically or
somebody or one of the old SGI guys was around, who wanted to talk to
us about it.
They could explain why they chose all these things.
Exactly.
The way they did, I'm sure they had very good reasons.
I don't know why they thought it was so important to put them into
normalized device coordinates.
But just because that that is how the 3D.
Works now in Hardware, you have to always be aware that your intuition
when you writing a prospective Matrix might be to think about creating
the screen coordinates, because that's what a software, rendering
person might have thought of, and you saw how it naturally came about,
that way, when we just wrote Our software renderer without thinking
about it too hard, right?
But that's not what happens in 3D pipeline, three pipelines about
compressing things into this Cube and so as a result, the exact
operation you would think to
Mix things.
Wider makes things smaller.
Okay but now let's take a look.
Can we just make this much?
Much simpler at that point, right?
Can we just simplify this out entirely?
So let's go ahead and take M to pixels and change that into some other
thing that isn't have nothing to do with that.
That is maybe a little bit more straightforward, right?
So maybe what we can say is, okay.
With the monitor is all we're going to have here, right?
M 2 pixels is not going to be involved at all and we'll just have
we'll just have with the monitor in here as the
The thing and then all we have to do over here.
Since we have the width and height are ready.
All we have to do over here is we just have to make sure that we
account for our aspect ratio adjustment, right?
And that's all we would have to do.
So let's go ahead and try that and see if we can make that work.
So accounting for that again.
We know that in here are safe ratio, one now would just be, there's
nothing to /.
That's just that's just not there anymore.
But in the case of where we've got that, the height again, we need to
actually perform the ratio W, PX / WP Y, in order to get the result
back again that we wanted to.
And so that would have to be, I believe the width divided by the
height in order to produce that Rio.
Wait.
but this is in the bottom of safe ratio, so it should actually be
There because this is a divided already.
So we want the with on top and we want the height on bottom to
reproduce this equation that we're looking at here and then I think we
would be okay.
That right?
And so now we have to do is make our m 2 pixels.
Actually not represent m, 2 pixels anymore and we don't remember
exactly where we were setting that.
Again pixels, I had it just a moment ago.
I was just looking at this.
There it is.
And so now you just have to have our m, 2 pixels, no longer take that
into account.
So if I was to go ahead and do that, where I no longer take with them
pixels into account, we can see whether we get what we would expect
and we do, right?
And notice that we are not warped at all at this point either we do
not have any sort of sort of weird, you know, contraction of the
screen or anything like that.
Okay.
So again that's kind of really nice because we're still simplifying
this down.
That we now have our meters to pixels is really just all we have.
There is now a transform, that talks about the width of the monitor,
so that we can sort of get a little bit of an idea of what's going on
there.
And that's just a constant multiplication that we're doing there in
order to
try and produce a reasonable effect there, right?
Okay.
So really, all we've got now is just a simple scale factor.
That's being applied that in no way.
Has any like that?
No longer has any bearing on any kind of input, right?
So when we call get standard camera, parameters, really?
All we're importing now is the focal length and this is really just a
scale factor that we determined in terms of what we thought was a
reasonable view on the world.
And so in some sense with the monitor, I don't even
If that gets used anywhere.
It doesn't right and so we can sort of stopped even talking about that
outside of outside of this context, right?
We can just basically say okay we've got a width of monitor
And we're producing this result this way for our Majors to pixels and
really m.
2 pixels now is not m 2 pixels, it's just our straightforward scaling
factor.
In fact, you know, I don't really sure what we would want to call
this, but maybe it would just be world scale or something like that,
because we could set it really arbitrarily however, we wanted to set
it, right?
And we should get the same results.
Now, it's important to just double-check to make sure that our
projection still does the thing that it's supposed to do, which is no
matter how esoteric, the window shape, that it always kind of does a
reasonable fit of what reviewing and keeps the size correct.
And it does, so that's important and we're still maintaining that.
So that's good.
But that's really all we need to do there.
Now, we're coming into the end of today.
We've only got about 15 minutes left, I think.
And so I don't want to start doing too much probably with your
perspective, divide but I do want to take a quick look.
First of all, we should rename this.
So instead of m 2 pixels, I think we'll just call this world scale.
and then wherever we were using that before,
We no longer have to have that in anything and let's also make sure
that because I don't actually know for sure, let's make sure that our
cutscenes are rendering properly since that's the other people.
That's that's a sort of a separate piece of code that uses the same
Graphics Pipeline and we don't want to be in a situation where for
some reason our cutscenes are no longer working properly.
So that all looks good.
okay, so once we've got that straightened away, the next thing to ask
is well okay if we're sort of for starting to simplify
This part of that transform process.
We're quickly going to get into a position here.
Like we're really all we've got is the world scale in here.
We could roll that world scale out into the opengl transform and
probably we should will have to take a look about at doing that at a
slightly later step.
There's no particular reason for us to do that now but it's free for
us to put it in there so we should obviously put it in there and we
will but you can see the next like systemic thing.
We actually would want to do probably is to start to tackle.
This line here and that line is obviously
A all about that perspective, divide.
And so now we have to start
Thinking about how we're going to get this data down to our output
code.
And I don't even know if right now, if we're even sending down 3D
coordinates as part of our of our render group information.
And so I'm going to have to take a look here when we do in Trenton
bitmap.
Yeah it doesn't look like we even are.
And so right now you know we said send down an X and Y axis but we
don't send down a z coordinate at all.
We send down a color but but only two
Just an X and Y for, for position.
And so what we want to do on the bitmaps now is we're going to want to
sort of like expand those out to having a 3D coordinate.
And basically everywhere in here that we were doing this, we probably
want to do that.
Since this has become will flee out of date at this point, we're
probably going to have to get rid of this guy because would have to
re-implement that entirely if we ever wanted to play with it again.
Anyway.
So we just really only have two things which are rectangles and
bitmaps at the moment.
And so I'm just going to expand both of them to have three-dimensional
coordinate instead of a two dimensional coordinate.
And then I have to deal with the Fallout from that.
I know what just happened there.
So
So I think it's trying to load some things.
I don't know what is trying to learn.
So let me go ahead and first delete those, those coordinates system
cases that are there.
In fact, Let me let me just delete that entry entirely, so it's just
not there anymore.
And then we'll sort of go through and try to make sure that we've got
here quarter system that out of there.
All right, so I think we're all good.
Now we just have to go through and make sure that now everywhere that
we were producing 2D coordinate, we're going to produce a 3D
coordinate and that shouldn't be too hard because they're typically
all going through that one routine which is entity basis, P results.
I'm just going to update that to return a 3D coordinate and I'm going
to come in here and I'm going to say, all right, I need to return 3D
coordinates so instead of just having the projected XYZ, I'm going
I need to also have the projected Z coming through here except we're
about to undo the fact that it gets projected at all.
But that makes it pretty easy.
Because now we're just all were really doing is saying, hey, let's get
all the projected values in there.
So I can just basically say that and I will get that P out.
This on the other hand is going to have to have a little more
information in it.
Of course, this stuff will also will probably go ahead and fix the
orthographic stuff.
To work through the open gym.
I choose quickly as well.
So that's going to that's going to want to look more like this.
Anyway, we'll remove the screen centering operation from it, but we
will need to multiply the entire P like that as well.
Okay, so that's what we want to do for returning these.
We now have to take a look at any of these things that are working
here.
Let's take a look at these.
So these sort of things like the screen area and the Sprite bounds,
those can now also be removed.
So we don't really need to update that code because since the Z buffer
will be in effect, these are not required anymore.
So this screen area can literally just be like a no rectangle that we
don't actually care about.
And that will be fine and we can like I said, if we have any problems
with sorting, we can just turn it off entirely because we're not going
to use it anymore and so we don't have to worry too much about that as
any real.
Real issue that's going to create a problem for us in any way.
alright, so now we're passing when we're coming down through here and
we've got our sort of
Our 3D coordinates that we want to start talking about here, which I'm
going to go ahead and, and put in.
We've got a bunch of problems because we were expecting everything to
be 2D.
So our x-axis y-axis stuff, again, is since all of that is in 2D, we
need to augment that to 3D now, that's not a big deal because we still
not using Z in any particular way here.
So our x axis that we get passed down, can be trivially expanded, you
know, to, a tattoo of a V3 by just pretending that there is no Z,
coordinate to it.
And then,
all of our math that was previously, you know, creating these Sprites
shapes, is it just
Just that I know we have this in here, but yeah, we'll just work.
So there isn't a lot.
There isn't much, we have to do there.
The same is true for some like this were drawing a rectangle and we
have a pee here again.
It's really just a question of anything that was previously just doing
an XY operation, can still do that exact same operation and just not
just don't change the Z.
Just keep the Z where it was, if you expand out into a rectangle, just
expand, the X&Y, don't change the Z and that's really all that
matters.
Okay, and so opengl rectangle now which is actually doing some of the
work there is going to have to have that that change as well.
Let me go ahead and finish this off and then we'll go ahead line.
Vertices draw a rectangle quickly and binary plus.
Where is that?
There it is.
What more here if you three.
Okay, there we go.
So, the opengl rectangle call.
Where is that?
There it is, is again going to have to take?
A Min P Animax be that rv3 is now because that's just kind of how it's
looking at the world.
And so what we can do is just ignore the Z entirely if we just want to
reproduce the exact results but since we want to start having that Z
carry through what I'm going to do here is just go ahead and pick one
of the two Z's.
So, we'll just say that will pick the mint.
Easy as the test as the coordinate for it, for the time being.
Although we might want to do something more fancy coming down in the
future.
All right, and let's see.
Opengl line vertices is the same routine.
We go.
And again, I'll just pick any, you know, what?
I really should probably do it this way.
It's a little nicer.
So, it's obvious.
What's going on?
But these are all drawn at a flat sea.
And again, it's just a really simple transform to just basically make
all of our stuff that was sort of flowing as a 2d Point flow of the 3D
point, but we're not even going to really use it yet.
We're just doing, just the basic the most basic stuff, they're right.
And there we go.
So finishing the cleanup here.
Again, we've got a couple of things which are still, you know, just
kind of we're passing things directly for for, you know,
Constructing explicit rectangles.
We're just getting rid of those and here we are in the software
renderer and the software under we can.
Of course if you want to just Nerf these at the moment, it's
Right.
And we'll have to do a bunch of updating the software and if you want
to suffer render the 3D stuff which you know, it's no big deal.
We can totally do that.
But again we don't really want to get bogged down in that at the
moment while we're working on this part of it.
So what did I do?
Wrong?
Draw a rectangle cannot convert argument three from V3.
Okay, that's probably because I did this backwards.
All right.
And so in theory now we're passing everything down as 3D but we're not
using the 3D in any way, right?
But at least we're getting those Z coordinates down right now.
What the Z coordinates actually are, of course, is a different matter
because we're not actually setting them to anything reasonable at the
moment, if I remember correctly.
I don't really even remember what those were getting set to.
It's just m.
2 pixels times.
The projected X Y.
So, it's already done.
The projection here, which is 1 over a distance to PC X.
The camera focal length x, the raw, x y, and so,
Assuming you know the next logical step and I just don't think I want
to do it with only three minutes left because we're going to want to
talk about more sickly, right?
Is just we're going to now going to want to put the Z value.
Is just going to be like distance 2pz.
And we're going to let this divide happen in opengl.
But in order to do that, we're also going to have to move the camera
focal length, and that sort of stuff.
We're probably gonna want to move those out as well.
But yeah, you can kind of see what's happening here.
It's not particularly confusing at all.
And in theory, you know, I don't know, I guess we could if we wanted
to just I don't think it is probably a bad idea but I'm just, you
know, we got a couple minutes.
We could try to sticking it in there and see now, I because I want to
give a complete description of why I would change the Matrix.
I don't want to just go change the Matrix on you, and then yeah.
So let's go ahead and go to the Q&A just a tad early.
And then next weekend, we can talk all about everything out.
How we multiply, how we address everything else?
Okay, so we have 10 cent in the explanation for homogeneous.
If you remember back in school now is kind of like homogeneous.
I'm not really sure where the term actually comes from.
If that makes sense and and I was like, if pseudonym 73 was here, he
could answer that for us.
He's off in our resident math expert, but I think the stream is not at
a time.
He can attend anymore, unfortunately but Rift and rode in with the
answer for us he says concerning the homogeneous use the Madras word
indeed comes from mathematics.
Homogeneous is used for mathematical object, that have some
scalability property here, x y z, 1 and 2.
What 2 X2?
Y2, Z2 represent the same point in space.
Therefore the usage of - coordinates into - matrices here so that
makes perfect sense.
Then if that's the case.
So in math parlance they're just talking about that property like are
saying where you do the / W to normalize everything down to 1 W,
coordinate of 1 and everything else gets divided by W.
You can see why that obviously means that if you had a thing that was
like 3 x 3 y 3z + 3 in the W, coordinate is the same as 2 x 2, Y, 2 Z,
and
To in the W coordinate because they're all gonna get / W anyway.
So those all represent the same point and so Rift and was saying that
that term homogeneous in math implies that.
Now why homogeneous is the word that would be used for that?
I have no idea but at least, there we go.
So thank you very much for writing that in because I was not sure
about that.
Valve has turn off the Sorting so we won't have flashing.
Yeah, we can.
Well, we might still have flashing but it probably won't be as bad.
The Sorting inside the render back-end sort.
Let's see.
Okay.
Where is Weir?
Burgers are sort.
Where did I start go?
That it wasn't render.
There it is.
Sorta entries.
All right, so in prep for render, I guess we could just do this.
But in order to do that yes, the problem is we're going to do a couple
things here because we don't we rely on that to produce the list.
Yeah.
So we're going to have to I don't want to do that just yet because
when we turn off sword entries, we're going to have to change the
iteration back to one that just steps over the entries directly.
So I'm I'm not going to do that.
That's going to stay on I suppose maybe what we could do.
Is just make sort entries, not actually sort.
So it still produces the results.
I guess what I can do here is just say, should sort.
As always false
Right.
Yeah, so I feel like just the problem with that right at the moment in
my assumption anyway is that the order that we output the entities,
varies as well.
So I just the fact that we're not sorting is not going to be
sufficient to stop the flashing.
I really just don't think I feel like that's just something that's
going to have to wait until we're actually closer to being done and we
can turn on the z-buffer.
I mean, we could turn off the trees.
He's, if you wanted to to reduce it but I think that's about it.
Kim Davis says the debug you is broken.
Yes, the debug UI.
We won't be able to access the debug UI until we support orthographic
transform in the because remember, the debug you, I goes to the
orthographic transform and the orthographic.
Transform is NOW essential effectively incorrect.
I mean, we might be able to just fix it quickly.
I was going to look at that once we decided if that but you can see in
here when we do the orthographic pass, it's going through a different
thing than
Then the past here and I didn't look at exactly what that would need.
In order to work properly when it gets, put on the when it gets put
out now, I don't know.
I can't think offhand of why the Earth our graphic would have broken
yet, but it
Yeah, I'm not, I'm not sure offhand.
I know exactly why it would break here, but I just I, I'm not even
going to look at that yet because we're about to make up, you know, do
a perspective divide in in the actual
In the projection Matrix in opengl.
And once we do that that would irrevocable that would irreparably
break of the the debug UI for sure.
And so we I knew it would go away that point anyway so I'm not going
to worry about that just yet because we're going to have to have a
thing in opengl that we're in opengl we actually set an orthographic
Matrix for the debug UI.
So we need to kind of do that as well.
That's just some of its going to have to happen because
Even though I'm not sure exactly why we broke it here.
I wasn't paying close attention because I already knew it was going to
break and I wasn't really going to worry about it, but I can tell you
for sure that it's soon as we put the provider, then it would be
completely broken.
So we have to deal with that separate.
Elvin, I was reading the article from Fabien about his optimizations
on the Intel software renderer and I saw him doing the clipping in a
very simple manner in screen space where he takes the min/max between
the pixel and screen dimensions because he was using Orient.
2D and barycentric coordinates to rasterize.
The clipping was only four lines of code in easy to understand why
does open jail have to do complicated homogeneous clipping?
Well,
so, I think the problem
Just figuring out which pixels to consider in the first place though
is the problem.
Once you're actually doing pixels, once you're actually stepping
through pixels, then it's pretty easy.
But you can't do the Divide to figure out where the thing is on the
screen ahead of time.
And so I don't know, since I haven't read that particular article that
you're talking about,
I'm not sure exactly what that was referring to.
But in terms of doing the clipping regardless of what you do, you
still need some way of figuring out what pixels to consider, right?
You need a bounding box at least and in order to produce the bounding
box, you need to know how small this triangle ended up being on the
screen.
And in order to know how small the triangle end up being on screen you
need to be able to do a divide, right?
And so
Homogeneous clipping is not necessarily what gpus do.
And at the very least, it's not the only kind of clipping they do
because they do do clipping in pixel space as well.
When they're evaluating pixels, they do it as well, right?
And these guard been clipping and all those other.
Sorts of things is, I don't really know what current gpus do, exactly
as their Suite of things, but it definitely does.
And so how they actually decide to do their clipping at the front end,
I don't know, but they do have to do it in a way that's consistent
with that homogeneous idea, right?
That's because that's how the pipeline is defined, but that doesn't
mean that they do it at any particular point, they just need to get
results that are consistent with having done it in the way that the
opengl spec says so that it always get predictable results right.
In practice is the camera, near plane.
And the camera focal length really differ.
I would expect them to be the same.
Yeah, they can differ.
they can differ, because
The near and far clipping planes are really just there to divide to me
unless you're trying to do some kind of special effect.
Where you're trying to clip things, in some way the near and far
clipping are really just there to set your Z precision.
Right, what the near and far clip playing are going to do is they're
going to set your range of possible Z values.
And if you push the near clip playing out further you get more
Precision in your
In your in your Z buffer, right?
So you may want to move it out further than or less that, you know,
not sure I'm saying this correctly, the near and far clip planes are
really just there because the z-buffer can only store, you know, it
stores values in it, right?
And it the Precision with which, you can resolve the difference
between two, Z coordinates is entirely dependent on those two planes,
right?
That's just the nature of the fact that the
Computer doesn't have infinite Precision, it only has however many
bits of precision, the Z buffer is.
And if the Z buffer is the 32 bit floating Point Z buffer.
Then you have 32-bit floating-point precision and if it's a 16-bit
fixed Point Z buffer, then you have 16-bit fixed precision and so the
Z buffers are never going to be infinitely.
Precise,
the focal length of the camera.
On the other hand is about how much perspective foreshortening.
You get
And that's what it controls.
So, since there's two control fundamentally different things, there's
no particular reason why they have to be the same.
If you want to change the fov of your game, you're going to change the
focal length variable, but you don't have to touch the near clipping
plane for any particular reason.
So hopefully that makes some sense.
Elven, are we going to continue supporting the software renderer in 3D
as well?
Yes, probably we will, I don't know to what extent we will, but we or
when, but we probably will at least at some point.
Elvin, if I set the near clipping plane to say 10, does that mean the
entities with a world's best Z less than 10?
They would be clipped just trying to make sure that near-far clip-ins
are defined in terms of world space.
So it's a little premature for us to talk about that only because we
haven't actually gotten around to creating that perspective Matrix
that starts dealing with Z.
So although I mentioned what the near and clip planes are
conceptually, we haven't actually talked about what we even mean when
we say near and far clipping plane in terms of
She'll specificity and that question is a very specific question.
What I would say is that in general yes you can think of it simply in
an abstract sense of whatever the after I've transformed things into
camera space.
I typically talk about my near clip plane as being the distance away
from the camera at which things start to be visible anything
Other than that is clipped away.
And similarly the far clipping plane is the distance at which once
things get further than that, they are no longer visible, right?
And like I said, the near clipping plane.
I don't know if there's a way to get rid of the near clipping plane.
That's again, maybe a question for a person who's more knowledgeable
about rendering than me.
But you certainly can't get rid of the far clip plane and just have it
so that you just get diminishing Precision, the further you get out
that's eminently doable.
And I'll try to show you how that works with when we when we write our
projection equation, I'll mention sort of how that comes into play.
Elven.
Can you use the GPU to bypass opengl and DirectX API Pipeline and just
use computers to implement your own pipeline?
That's also running on the GPU?
Well, you can, but it's not going to be as fast as if you didn't.
So yeah, you can just, you know, you could just write something in
Cuda for example, that would just
Do your own completely own software rendering pipeline, that just gets
uploaded, the GPU as a giant program and then runs right?
You can totally do that, you can output a an image and you can show
that image on the screen.
So that's that's doable.
And in fact that's how rate racing engines work now.
So for example, if you look at like the Brigade renderer,
my understanding is that's just a Cuda program that they upload, and
it's a ray Tracer, not a rasterizer, and it you know, it just tries to
render the world using Ray tracing
However, it's not going to be as fast as if you use the traditional
API.
And by traditional, I mean, like modern like opengl for point x or
something.
I don't mean the fixed function pipeline, it's not going to be as fast
as if you use the traditional Pipeline.
And the reason for that,
That's because there's a bunch of Hardware in GPU that set up to
accelerate specifically the shading pipeline in terms of frame,
buffer, access and texture fetching, and these sorts of things.
There's a bunch of things that surround that process that are
optimized specifically, when the GPU is executing code that it knows
our is specific to the rendering concept so much so that there's
certain, you know, there's, there's certain stuff in the hardware that
still actually very hard coded.
You know, I'm not equipped to say what it actually is, but there's
plenty of, there's still plenty of special purpose, Hardware in a GPU
Specifically set up for the rasterization pipeline that is not
General.
And so when you go to implement your own software, rasterizer in Cuda,
you will not have the ability to access those pieces of the hardware,
whatever they are.
Whether that's scheduling or graph traversal or, you know, clipping
things or whatever it is that they've still got special-purpose parts
for you.
Don't get the
Thought to access those parts.
So you'll get all the flops that you would have for shaders and you'll
be able to use all of that but you won't be able to use any of the
special purpose Hardware which still does exist.
And so, that's what I would say about that.
It certainly be a fun exercise to do, but it probably wouldn't be a
very good idea in terms of quality because you will end up losing
performance because of that.
We have 10.
So to avoid z-fighting.
Should we have dynamical near far complains?
I mean, that their value should change according to the nearest and
the farthest objects.
We want to render in order for the near far, clip playing space to be
as small as possible.
Yeah, I guess I would say yes.
If you wanted to try and get the most Precision you could you would
probably do that.
Yeah I don't know that that's a particularly good idea and the reason
for that is that it kind of fights with a fundamental notion of
consistency in that, you could imagine a scene where somebody throws
something at the player and that thing comes close to the player.
All of a sudden does a bunch of Z fighting starts happening because
previously, the
Bounds were out further and now they have to be moved closer and
you're looking at the scene and it degrades right?
And so I think typically the approach that you take it doesn't
necessarily look like that.
In terms of dynamically setting the bounds that way, but I don't know.
Certainly things of the nature that you just described are very
common.
When people are trying to get Shadow map Precision to be better
because honestly Z fighting is not as much of an issue.
These days unless you just made your geometry really poorly Z.
Finally fighting is really not as big of an issue as it used to
because Z buffer is tend to be pretty accurate.
Usually the problem is more with lightmaps and and comparing the Z
buffer to the light maps and and not having enough Precision there
because that's a really delicate operation where you've got, two
different ways of computing, a distance from a different places that
have to agree and
That's really ugly.
And so that's where you get those like Shadow, those really bad Shadow
artifacts.
And so people who do Shadow art to try to like do algorithms that make
shadows look better.
And have less artifacts.
They actually do a lot of stuff with the ranges which they do, in
fact, you know, like just to pick one of them.
Here's an example of of, in fact, this is a reasonable diagram.
People will do stuff like breaking up Shadow Maps into regions of the
frustum specifically because they need more Precision clothes and less
Precision further away and stuff like this.
So you can think of that almost as making multiple near and far
clipping planes for this very reason, right.
So the kind of thing you're talking about is absolutely true.
I just don't know how many people actually do anything with the main
render in that, what right?
Like the, the main production of the image separate from the
shadowing, I don't know how much of that is ever done with adjusted
adjusted, clipping planes.
Because again this isn't my area of expertise, I'm not a rendering
guy, you know.
You'd want to talk to somebody who is really up, always kept really
close up to date on the state-of-the-art in rendering because they
know all the sorts of stuff that people that tend to be doing at that
point in time.
And so, you know, I don't know to what extent people mess with the
near and far clipping planes on a frame to frame basis.
These days, the answer may be quite a bit, the answer, maybe not at
all.
All I do know that a lot of people now use.
rendering that actually breaks the scene into
Chunks anyway.
And so at that point, you're near and far clipping planes are actually
moving around, many times a frame because you're rendering lots of
little chunks, right?
And so, in that sense you might sort of say, that's kind of what
you're talking about.
Almost it's not really, I know it's not exactly what you were asking,
but it's the same kind of idea.
It may not have had anything to do because the reason they do that is
to isolate parts of the scene so that they can do less computations.
Because like that one part of the scene is only affected by a certain
lights and so on but it's definitely the case that that same thing.
Applies the near and far clip cleaner.
Now just going to apply to a very small region of space.
So you would naturally get a lot more Precision there, if you needed
it, in terms of your clipping region and what you were talking about.
So maybe, you know, that's an example of that as well.
I don't know.
And again, I would just underscore, I am not a rendering person.
It's a very specialized disc discipline, obviously, I know how
Do it because I've written render stuff before.
But I've never it's not really super where my interests lie.
So I've never been one of those people who's constantly invested in
the state of the art and Game 3D rendering.
And so in order to really definitively say what's a good idea?
What do people do currently you kind of you're going to have to ask
someone who's more up-to-date on all the stuff that people do.
I can only really give you the basic understanding of how everything
works.
Works so that you're set to go learn about those yourself.
But in order to kind of be more familiar with that, you have to do a
lot of reading and be very specialized in that discipline in order to
really know definitively the answers to questions like those
Does any of the clip and projection math change?
If we change the rendering technique that we're using, say,
rasterization versus Ray tracing or voxels?
Well, obviously, yes.
I mean, with Ray tracing, you, don't clip, right?
Ray tracing.
You just have the Ray and whatever it hits it hits.
So you don't need a near or far clip playing in Ray tracing for any
reason at all.
It's not, it's not relevant, right?
The the only point that causes you a problem in Ray.
Tracing, I guess would be would be 000, I think, although I, you know,
now I think that's probably not true.
I guess I would say no probably in ray-tracing, you still do, want an
ear clip plane because something that, you know, that that Ray
intersection math could still you'd still get a little unstable down
there.
So you
I mean okay you might still, you might still want to be some nominal
near clipping plane and and I guess, you know, the other way to look
at it would be
You still sort of have Precision issues in Ray tracing so that the
problem is still there, it just manifest itself in a different way.
When you're ray-tracing, you end up with the problem of like Z
fighting in a ring, in a rasterizer is having trouble determining,
which hit is closest in a ray Tracer.
Because that's the ray goes out, you're like, oh, is this surface
closer?
Sir, is this surface closest, and if they're very, very close together
and the floating Point, Precision can't determine between
Do in the range of section equation.
Then you've got the same kind of thing, right?
So you know, I guess what I would say, you know, to answer your
question, perhaps to answer it poorly, the math is very different,
depending on the type of renderer, but the effects are not really all
that dissimilar.
You can't fight the fact that you have limited Precision rears its
ugly head in many ways.
But yeah.
So
For the, for the ray Tracer, I guess.
All I was trying to convey was you don't need a view frustum in a ray
Tracer, right?
Because you're just shooting raised up from the camera and you will
never shoot a ray further than the side of the view.
So you don't need to clip anything to it because you're never going to
send array towards anything that wasn't in it anyway, right?
So you never have to do any of that stuff if you don't want to, you
don't have to produce.
Lives device coordinates for any particular reason.
You don't have to even Define a view, frustum explicitly at any time,
if you don't want to.
Now, often times, you will still have clipping.
In effect, it'll just be calling not clipping.
So your ray Tracer will not want to consider anything that isn't that
isn't going to potentially hit.
And so you typically have some kind of a spatial hierarchy that allows
you to narrow down the things that that Ray might encounter at any
point in space.
It just doesn't really have anything to do with the view frustum and
the reason for that is you typically use the same spatial query, you
know?
You need to shoot these rays and space.
You need to do spatial queries on them.
What you're going to
Immediately after you hit something is you're going to cast a ray off
in a bounce direction to compute, what it's hitting.
And that Ray will trivially go outside the view.
Frustum most of the time.
So you can't clip the world to a view, frustum first and then Ray
trace it, it would be completely wrong.
So that's again, like, kind of another way of looking at that problem,
if that makes sense.
All right, I think we have finished for today.
I'm going to go ahead and close out here.
Thank you everyone for joining me, for those set of handmade hero.
It's been a pleasure coding with you.
As always, if you would like to follow along, with series at home, you
can always pre-order the game on handmade hero dot org and it comes
Source code.
So you can follow along with all the stuff that we do.
You can also go to the forums if you have questions and ask questions
there.
You can go to the our patreon page.
Want to support the video series.
You can check out our schedule bot And subscribe to it on Twitter.
If you want to know, when the series is going to be live and you're
going to go to our episode guide if you want to catch up on previous
week's episodes, that's it for today.
I'll be back next week where we'll take a look at moving the
perspective divided into opengl as the next step in our process of
change.
And over to a 3D pipeline all the way through instead of just at the
head end like we have been doing until then have fun program this week
and I will see y'all on the internet.
Take it easy everyone.