And start crying.
Hello everyone and welcome to handmade hero.
The show Rico to complete game live on stream.
We just recently did a switch over to using the 3D transforms of
opengl to do our transference before we were using opengl, just as a
dumb bit mat drawing back end basically, and we did all of our
transforms
Ourselves.
But we wanted to start taking advantage of things like z-buffering,
and we want to remove stuff like Sprite sorting from the engine
because it just didn't seem to be the right way to do things to me
when we implemented it.
I just didn't have a good feeling about it in terms of scalability, so
I decided to switch it over.
And so we've done that.
Now, actually, and we had our game running with running through open
shell for the 3D transform.
The perspective scaling and such, but we still had all this right?
Sorting code in there.
And so what I did at the end of yesterday's stream is, I started to
gut that code and I got it to a reasonable stopping point, but we
didn't quite have a chance to finish all of the gutting.
So we need to go do that now.
And yeah, it's relatively straightforward work.
We're basically just returning the pipeline essentially to the state
that it was before we added this right sword.
So we're really just sort of removing what we added.
We're not really doing anything particularly new.
We're just kind of pulling out some of the parts that we added in that
really, we don't want anymore.
So let's go ahead and get back to that.
Like I just flashed up their day.
361 is the day-to-day.
So if you are trying to follow along at home, you want day 360 source
code.
Let's go ahead and open up the project in for coder.
And get started.
So if you remember where we left off yesterday, we essentially had
gutted, most of the code, but the, the render Loop we kind of nerfed
out because it didn't have anything to iterate over.
So, we're just at a grey screen right now because the part that
actually takes the push buffer and execute, it has just been if zeroed
out.
Now, the reason that if zeroed out is because we have to go in now
that we've got it all the Sorting code and what we have to do is we
have to make sure that when we push a render entry
Let me go in there.
Push render elements re not render entry, you can see how it was
working.
It calls the, the push buffer code and the push buffer code is going
to give it back the place to write the information that it's trying to
write.
And you can see this push puffer coat here, takes a data size and
unfortunately, it, you can see what's happening here.
The push buffer data at - data size, check and the - equals data size,
it's walking backwards from the end.
Of the stream, the end of the buffer and sticking things in.
and the reason that we were doing that,
if you called,
Is just because we had wanted.
To put the sort entries at the beginning of the buffer.
So, we were growing from the bottom of the render buffer up to put the
sword entries in there, and the top of the render buffer down to put
the data in.
And so, that way, we had a flat array starting from the first from
zero of the sort entries, we would sort those and then we would use
those to jump into the right place in the render buffer to find the
data for each sort entries.
Actual information.
Now, since we are now switching to not sort, and
Again the reason I didn't like what sort of because they're because
there were all this extra stuff, I was like the Z buffer is just the
right way to handle this.
It's more flexible and it doesn't have all these problems that I'm
talking about where you like, have to do all this extra work with more
elements and indirection, and all that stuff.
All of those things will eventually, even if not him nearby think even
on him hero, they would have caused us problems because I want to do
some particle system stuff.
And I think particle systems would when we start to put a lot of
particles in there, would really start to stress that system.
Out and it would roll over and die.
You know, all of that indirection and extra data and extra walking and
sorting work is just putting too much extra work per element that we
want to draw.
And when we are trying to get good drawing performance, one of the
biggest things you want to do is try to just stream out information
that we can hand to the GPU or hand to the software renderer that it
can just process directly.
The more middle information there is there the more middle in
Direction that's going on there?
It's just
Adding and adding, and adding cost per element and every time you add
cost for element the number of elements you can do goes down, right.
And so I want to move the renderer towards a more direct streaming
approach with less interference and part of a big part doing, I think
it's just getting rid of the Sorting.
So that's why I wanted to do that.
And that's like an example, right here of that, sort of thing, still
even after pulling out the sort code, you can still see the vestigial
remains of that happening.
And so, let's go ahead and continue to get rid of that.
So, here we are at the push, buffer result structure, right?
It Returns the header of the thing.
So, when you do,
Push buffer, it's got that header in there.
It's going to do.
And when we go ahead and push that on, what we can do here is take a
look and go, how is this thing?
I believe it was in the platform.
How is this thing?
Doing that?
Sort of walk down and I believe there's the render gamer enter
commands bit.
Here you can see the max push push.
Buffer size, there's this sort entry count thing here.
Push, buffer base and push buffer data at Push by base and push buffer
data.
At are the two things we're going to use to kind of walk up.
We are not going to use the the
manual sort key bit here.
And we're not going to use a sword entry count, but we do need
something that lets the renderer know.
It's at the end, right?
So, we need something.
And what we can use there is to push buffer data at if we just let
that be sort of the end cap.
So we've got kind of this is where the bottom that is.
And this is where the high Watermark is so far.
Then what we can do is just keep incrementing that as we go and we
should be fine at that point, right?
We should be able to use that to tell us where to start and where to
stop.
So when we do push buffer troops to me to put a question mark in
there.
When we do push buffer,
What we want to do is say all right.
When we do commands push buffer at to check to see whether we can fit
in here, what we want to do is say, all right, if the commands pushed
buffer at - well actually, I guess we could just say we want Push
buffer base plus Max.
Backsplash, Barber size.
This is essentially like an end pointer.
As long as we're less than the end, right?
We could do it.
But we have to account for how much wants to be pushed on, right?
So, if we were to take where we're at, and we were to add how much we
want to push as long as we're less than our end cap, right?
Then, then we're good.
And we can do the push slight aside.
Again, this kind of a check is only valid for code.
We control.
Obviously those of you who are more security minded thinking about
things where the user input comes into play.
And so on obviously these sorts of computations can fail because if
this number is big enough to cause this to wrap, it will still be less
than the push buffer end so you have to do more careful checking here
if you if you
Assumed that data size could be coming from some nefarious.
So, and so, you know, these sorts of checks don't work because this
could be big enough to wrap this value, and then the check would
succeed.
And then you would write over a bunch of memory as someone did stuff,
right?
So yeah, you know how it is with security code.
There's a lot more to consider there, but we are not looking at that
kind of code.
We know that data size is always coming from one of our routines and
games are not security critical in that way.
At least not finger player.
Ones.
That's more, Microsoft's job than ours, to make sure that a user level
app.
Isn't, you know, getting some of the root privileges on your machine,
Not that Microsoft doesn't particularly good job at it mind you.
But, you know,
What you gonna do anyway?
So here we go.
What we need to do here is switch the order of these
Going to take where we're at in the push buffer and say that's we're
going to push the next thing then we're going to increment by that
size so we're saying okay here's what the push bumpers at we're going
past that size.
And so then we return that chunk to right into and now the push buffer
is at the correct position.
Right.
So now when we're doing our push buffer code, and that's really all we
need to do there.
Get rid of this Reserve, sort key stuff.
What are you talking about?
Uh, real through to us, right?
We gotta when we do our initialization here, we've got to change that
out.
So render command struct if the mass with Versailles to push buffer,
the width and the height, so the push buffer base.
And push buffer data at is, just going to be the same.
Off we go.
So, yeah.
All we need to do there is just go.
Okay.
Now we're pushing from the bottom up, which is what we want.
And so, if we go to handmade opengl and take a look at that render
Loop that we nerfed out, what we have to do now is like unnerve it
out, right.
So, what we need to do is we need to start at like
Essentially, the base location.
Right?
So we need like a header at variable or header offset.
It's not really an offset.
It's actually a pointer.
So to say header app and we know that that header has to start at the
push buffer base.
We do have one problem.
That we're going to have to fix which has the cliprect situation.
And I suspect that that's going to have to use a some kind of a that's
going to have to use some kind of a more intelligent thing I guess.
Well, alright yeah, actually, I guess that's not true.
I guess.
There are ways that we can get around that.
So we'll take a look at that in a second.
I'll explain why I say we have to do that but we're just going to take
it one step at a time.
So we're going to go ahead and grab the header out of the
By four base which is in that command structure.
We know that's where the first header is going to be written.
Then we just have to make sure that we're always less than the push
buffer data at which is the highest place we ever got to.
So we know that at the very last time someone pushed a header they set
push buffer data at to be like the part after the chunk that they
pushed on.
So we know once we get there, we're done right?
And we don't have anything we can do inside this Loop because how much
we advance by is based entirely on the struct that we received, right?
So when we get render grouped entry, you know, render entry bitmap,
when we take a look at how these Saucy fellows worked over here.
We we know that they're going to eat
Be whatever the size is of the case that we encountered.
So here's render entry bitmap.
We know that we would have to advance by this much, but we also know
that we have to advance by however big the header is itself, right?
So the render group entry header bit.
That's this right here and this is no longer applicable either.
So the render group entry header here that has the type in the clip
directing Vex packed in here.
And sometimes also a debug tag in case we want that for any kind of
debugging information.
Information.
That's something we always have to advance by.
So we know like, you know, we can in here.
For example, if we wanted to just say, well, we know, we're always
going to have to advance by the size of the render group entry header.
So that always has to happen, right?
But then we also know that we have to add in each one of these.
We have to take however big this thing is right and advanced by that
as well.
So header at
Has to sort of Advance by that size, specific to the thing that we
encountered.
So, you know,
It's easy peasy lemon squeezy as Jeff Roberts would say but you know,
we got to actually do it.
But that's really all the code.
There is there.
Now, if we actually do this we're going to fail right off the bat.
And yeah, you can you can see exactly how that that's failing.
The first time we grab one of these header.
Well, okay, that's actually not true.
I forgot one more thing I had to do first, so that's actually
different failure.
Let's fix that failure, first, but we have a different failure in
there.
So when we grab the header, obviously this piece of code is wrong.
We need to actually use the header
That we produce there.
But yes, I believe we're still going to be wrong, even after that.
So what you can see here is, we're getting a header and it's nonsense,
right?
I mean, this is, this is not, there is no type 96, that's that sort of
Chris obviously.
So what's going on there?
Well, at least one other thing we have to fix.
I mean, that maybe we may have multiple bugs in here because we ripped
out a lot of code but at least one problem that we have is we are
pushing the the clip rect, you know, the clip rect
Typing rectangles that we use, which are used now for both the camera
transform and for clipping that is gets pushed onto push buffer just
like everything else.
Right?
And what you can see here is render entry cliprect is all, that gets
sort of pulled out of that and that actually isn't going to work if
we're walking through these because the renderer doesn't know when it
sees one of these clip Rex
The renderer doesn't know what it is.
So it's stepping through this buffer looking for the things that
Anne's it see stuff like drawbitmap.
It knows what it is.
It processes it skips over it but then it gets to a clip.
Rect and the clip art doesn't even have a header in it, right?
It's doesn't even conform to the header structure for the elements.
So what we need to do is even though we don't draw anything on a clip.
Rect we have to insert a header for them here.
And actually, put that piece of information in there, right?
So if we go to push render element here,
Oops.
And just grab that out.
In fact, we could just use somebody who's already doing a push render
element called.
You can see how it works, right?
We just have this sort of thing, we just need to do that for our clip
Rex.
So that when we do this, instead of calling push buffer directly which
we don't want to do, we're just going to call Push render entry clip,
rect and push it as a regular entry, okay?
So when we come through here then we will have that
So now we actually will have that rectangle and everything else will
work from there.
Okay, let's go ahead and build that.
There we go.
So now what will happen or what should happen if I was right about
that is we should get a break in the default case because now the
render when it goes through, this Loop will correctly, be able to
interpret the clip rect and you can see that it is a render type two.
Which is exactly what we expected, 01 to, right?
And so now we are in a good position because since we don't want the
renderer at the moment to do anything with those cliprect because it
uses them in a different way, right?
It does that serialization first, all we have to do to make the rest
of the render render Loop stream properly.
It just makes sure that when we see one of these, we skip it because
it's already being handled elsewhere, right?
So, now, it'll skip over those Loops.
So, now, it'll skip over those rather than having them trip up the
renderer.
So now, we just have to make sure that everything else goes goes
correctly in the any bugs, we inadvertently reduced, we inadvertently
introduced.
We get rid of.
And obviously, I have to do the advancement here as well.
Okay so now we're back in good shape.
Right again, we still have not turned the z-buffer on because we're
sort of inching slowly towards that so we still have complete nut.
So sorting it's just whatever order things went down in randomly so we
get all that crazy flashing nonsense but everything's working fine,
right?
The clip rectangle.
And such are not causing any problems.
Now, the render is able to access all the things that want access and
that's all good.
Okay.
So now we've pulled the sorting out.
And maybe there's a little bit of a still remain to that but not much
anymore and now we can start to focus on the actual 3D Miss of
everything that we're doing, right?
And we can try to like start to work through that a little bit more.
Well, I crunch on this biscuit.
It's a pretty good biscuit.
It's from a place called Dahlia Bakery.
Here in Seattle.
And they make pretty good biscuits.
I realize this is not relevant to programming.
But it is relevant to biscuits.
All right.
Moving on.
Okay, so
In terms of our to do list.
Now it's I think what we might want to make a little, a little, you
know, a little, you know, such and such, we made the concept of 3D
rooms that can be queried already.
And we did update the camera to move between proven cases for 3D rooms
that actually kind of already happened.
So we have some of that stuff cleaned up but we do have some stuff
here, we have to fix the unprojected.
Let's just make a quick little understanding of
Has to happen here.
So where we've got this film Project stuff going on here.
So let's take a look at what our high level objectives are now.
So we want to basically be able to turn on the z-buffer, right?
We need to be able to draw sprites or let's say draw the world in a
logical way.
And that means like stand-up cards for some things.
That means cubes for other things.
And that may be actually be it, it depends what we want to support in
terms of the stuff that we're going to draw, but we kind of need, you
know, turning on the Z, buffer is not the end of the job.
We have to sort of come up with some ways, in which, we're going to
structure things.
So that they work reasonably well in terms.
How you see them, how they work.
And talk a little bit about that.
So really we just need to sort of again in baby steps move towards a
3D more 3D version of the world.
So what I want to do in order to lead up to that because I think it
will be important for debugging.
Is basically like a freely rotatable world.
And I don't ever want the world to rotate in the actual game because
the art isn't set up for that, right?
Like it.
We don't want the game to spin and not because it's not fun for the
game to spend or something.
But we don't want the game to be spinning this way at all.
It might tilt that way a little bit.
You know, change the Tilt that way a little bit but we don't want to
do this.
And the reason is because as soon as you
Start doing this with a 2-D game.
You see how like everything is a, is a card that faces the user and,
and we don't really want that.
So you want to think more along the lines of something like, don't
starve or something?
Where, you know, the game is 3D with cards for it.
But it, you know, it never is allowed to go like this because I feel
like well as soon as things start to go like that, it starts to look
kind of crappy whereas if it's always line.
Up, you know, it maintains the believability quite a bit more in my
opinion.
So that's what we want to start looking at figuring out a good way to
get to that point and so we will.
Yeah, we will do that.
But in the meantime, what I do want to do is I want to have a way to
freely rotate, the camera in the world.
And the reason that I want to be able to freely rotate the camera in
the world is because for debugging purposes.
once we start trying to construct,
Fake 3D things, like how we want to align cards to the camera and
stuff like that.
We're going to want to be able to spin the world around.
And not have the cards turn to faces or anything but rather just see
what their actual 3D geometry looked like because that's going to make
debugging a lot easier for us, right?
If we can't ever see the world from any angle, other than just, the
one we're actually viewing the game at.
It's going to be hard for us to debug because a number of different
2D, a number of different 3D constructions.
Might produce very similar, or identical 2D projections.
And will be like, oh, you know, we tried to make this car that was
like, standing up like this, and it's not quite working, right?
But we can't tell what are the actual 3D co-ordinates of that thing
and we can't
Spin the world to see what they are.
And so that's a position.
I didn't want to find myself in.
So what I want to do is I want to be able to extend the notion
of what the game specifies for that transform, so that it can spin
everything around if it wants to and we're never going to use the full
spinning in the actual game.
Although we might use the tilting
Right, so it's not.
It's not like it's completely useless for the game.
We may want to Tilt The World Slightly just to give it a little 3D
more 3D feel to it, for example.
So you know it might be something that gets used in game as well.
It's just you know, for the most part it's a the main feature that
we're looking for here is to be able to debug our render output.
All right.
So, let's talk a little bit more about how that would work.
So right now, we're specifying a bunch of stuff in 2D and we've got
this projection Matrix here.
Now, I'd like to talk a little bit about matrices.
Again, we kind of touch on them frequently in handmade hero.
And I think I've hopefully giving you enough insight into how matrices
work.
We talked about them, like I said, many times, so hopefully you're
getting pretty comfortable with matrices.
But just going to say one more time, some things about how these work.
So that again we can continue to take those baby steps towards having
the pipeline be operating completely in 3D.
So here is day 361.
And we are talking about rotation matrices.
Right.
So, fundamentally speaking.
Hopefully, you understand how rotation works at this point, if you
don't, you want to go back to the handmade hero, where we talked about
this in depth, where we implemented rotation of our bitmaps, because I
explained it all there, but just quickly.
Again, always remember when you're working with rotation.
Remember your unit circle, right?
Here's our unit circle.
Poorly drawn by me and remember our right triangle.
Let me draw here and remember the fact that the x coordinate of the
right triangle for a given angle.
Okay, the x-coordinate is the cosine of that angle.
And remember that the y-coordinate
Of that point on the unit circle is the sine of that angle.
This fundamental diagram to remember is the key to always sort of
understanding, how to re-derive, rotation matrices, or really any
rotational element that you're working with except maybe quaternions,
because they involve a bunch of more extensive crazy math nonsense.
But even they're still based on this concept, you just need to know
more stuff.
But rotation in general, if you remember the unit circle,
you will be happy camper.
Will you be a happy camper?
Well.
What we know we need to do, right?
Whenever we are talking about rotation is we know we need to take a
point and we need to reinterpret it along new axes right?
So fundamentally what we're doing when we asked to rotate.
Something is we're saying we have a point that is currently expressed
right in some coordinate system, right?
It's expressed in a coordinate system that is not rotated.
For our purposes, right?
So the X and Y, axes are set up, so that they are aligned with the
screen or the world or whatever.
We have a point expressed in that system and to rotate that point.
What were primarily talking about is figuring out how to reinterpret
this point in the exact same way that it was interpreted before.
Just along different axes.
Those axes have been rotated, right?
They've been lifted.
Up, right?
And so the first step in deriving, any sort of rotation and again, I
would encourage you go back.
We spent more time in this before, I'd encourage you go back.
If you're hazy on this about how it works, I'm not going to re-explain
it 100% here just to avoid constantly reaching the same things.
Deriving.
These two axes is very simple, right?
First of all deriving the new x axis when we rotate something is as
simple as interpreting, this diagram directly because as you can see
the rotation about an angle for the x-axis is just directly
interpreting this diagram.
It's just literally cosine, Theta, sine Theta because hey, that starts
pointing this
Right along the x-axis when Theta is 0 and it just winds its way
around the circle.
Exactly like we want, right?
So the only tricky bit is, what do we do about the y-axis?
Because that starts this way and the answer there is, well, it's
really not all that much more difficult.
All we have to do is pretend that our diagram started pointing upwards
and if you think about what happens when it would start pointing
upwards.
Well cosine Theta is the thing that equals 1 at the start.
So we want R cosine Theta to beat the y-coordinate, right?
Here's our x-axis.
Here's our y-axis.
So our y coordinate is actually the thing that starts at one.
Right here was our X that starts at 1, it goes down to 0.
And then 2 negative 1 here.
The exact same thing is happening in y, right?
It's starting at 1, it's going to 0, then it's going to -1.
So we know that cosine, Theta actually goes in the bottom, right?
It goes in the y-coordinate and it's the x-coordinate that's going to
be something else.
What does the x coordinate?
Well, the x-coordinate starts at 0, goes to negative 1.
Comes back to zero, goes to positive one, right?
That's the same thing that sign.
Does here starts at 0, goes to 1 goes to 0.
Except the sign is flipped instead of going to negative 1 first,
right?
It doesn't go this way, it goes this way.
So all we need to do is to flip the sign on that and we get the right
motion.
Now, you'll notice this.
Right?
Is just the perpendicular operator, right?
Flip the two and negate one of them, right?
The - flip, it's just the perpendicular operator, which we've learned
in 2D before, as well.
So you could have also looked at it as how do I get a perpendicular to
this sauce?
I'll see gentlemen here, right?
And you can see that we can really quickly derive the X and Y axes
that we wanted.
Okay?
so now the question is, if I can derive axes,
How do I derive a rotation Matrix?
Unfortunately.
A lot of programmers people who aren't very familiar with 3D and
haven't done a lot of work in it so they haven't had to work it out.
Treat rotation matrices as something.
They have to look up in a book that is unfortunate because it's it's
much better to be able to derive them yourself.
And so in our circumstance here at the question is well?
Okay, you know for those of you understood everything that I just said
there,
But don't necessarily know what a rotation Matrix is or how to make
one.
The question is, how do I make a rotation Matrix?
If I know how to do this fundamental operation?
Because I understand the math here but maybe I don't know enough about
matrices to translate that into something that I could use in a matrix
sense.
Well, the good news is as we said multiple times on the stream, when
we talk about matrices, matrices are just one way of using axes to
reinterpret something.
So actually, this right here,
Is the derivation of a rotation Matrix and let me show you why.
So suppose I was to take a 2d Matrix and some incoming points, right?
And I should put axis down here obviously, so we know.
We're talking about, not the X and Y, coordinates, right?
An incoming X and Y point that I put in here.
Right, again, we've done this before on handmade Harris.
I'm just reiterating it here if I imagine that, my
Access.
My Matrix here is a 2d Matrix that has four values.
We know we've done this a million times.
Well 100 times on handmade here.
We know that we will just get ax plus b y, + CX plus d, y, right.
This is what we will get.
Well, what does this look like to?
You write?
If you look at what you see here, this is a vector, right?
It is
Essentially, the two vectors some together.
If you want to break it up that way, write any Vector.
That's something plus something on both sides, you can split down the
middle and just write it as Vector math.
I could say x CX, plus b, y, d y, and these two things are equal,
right?
Because when we add two vectors together, we just add their
corresponding elements, right?
If we further take this and separate out the pieces, we say well the x
is common here.
And the why is common here?
So it's just the AC and BD.
It's really just x times.
AC plus y times, BD and hey.
Look at what that does, that is specifically, the axial,
interpretation of this x and y, coordinate along the axis, AC, and the
axis b d, right?
Because remember what multiplication of a scalar does to a vector, if
I have a vector, right?
And it's pointing in this direction, let's say this is the vector AC,
right?
And I multiply it by some value X.
That means I'm walking out along it by X distance right now, granted,
I
Buying it by the length of this Vector.
But if this is a unit Vector, it has a length of one.
So I'm literally just going the distance X along it, right?
Because it doesn't change that amount if it was scaled right would
change the amount but it's not going to if it's a unit vector.
So the exact operation that I wanted to do here.
I have two vectors, right?
I have my x axis and my Y axis, the exact operation of walking out
along X.
And then walking out along y to a particular location is exactly what
this Matrix actually does, if I use AC and BD as my axes.
So, hey, that's exactly what I can do to build my rotation.
This is the axis for X.
This is the axis for why, I know that is what the math will do.
When I multiplied by the x, y, coordinate Vector.
So all I have to do is shove the actual values.
I want for those axes into their corresponding locations, and I am
done, right?
This is the x-axis here.
This is the y-axis here and that is what the columns of a matrix r
that is literally what they are.
The Columns of a matrix are axes along which the input Vector that
you're multiplying by is walking each coordinate.
The x-coordinate walks along the First Column the the second most, so
I should say the first coordinate walks along the First Column.
The second coordinate walks along the second column, third,
coordinate, third column, and so on.
On, right?
So if we look at how this would actually look, if we actually just
shove these values in there, we have derived our rotation Matrix.
We put the cosine Theta here.
We put the sine Theta here, right?
Because the x axis there, they are cosine sine Y axis.
Next column negative sine
Cosine Theta.
Right.
So that is a 2d rotation Matrix.
Okay.
Yeah, so there you go.
Happy day.
So now the question is, well, okay?
I get it right, I get it for 2D rotation, matrices, that's fine, but
we need 3D rotation matrices, right?
We need to have a 3D rotation Matrix Somehow Here.
And this is all well and good.
But you know, how does that extend something in 3D?
Well, fortunately for us all the things that I just said, matrices
don't really change depending on their Dimension, if they're Square.
Anyway, there's a non Square matrices, have other properties.
That, you know, we don't want to really bring in this point, but
Square matrices.
Always work the same way, no matter what dimension you're in.
So exactly what I just said, right?
Exactly.
What I just said is true of 2D.
Matrices is also true of 3D matrices, right?
The math is substantively doesn't change at all.
It still produces the exact same kind of equations, right?
And you can see me working it out here for your amusement
Right?
Here are the elements of the Matrix here.
Is what it's produced.
You can see how very clearly.
I don't need an arrow.
I suppose there how very clearly that equals ax DX, g x, plus b.
Y ey h y, plus c, z FZ.
I z
Right.
Which again if you pull out the common terms is just X adg.
Look at that column right there, right?
That's the x-axis.
Take a look at this guy.
Plus, why beh oops went behind my head there and thought I wasn't
drawn.
Why beh that's the y-axis right there multiplies, the y coordinate
that comes in.
And finally, we've got the Z axis, which is our new axis CFI, right?
And there it is.
So again, First Step, very straightforward, we now know a 3D Matrix.
is just the,
Access in the First Column, the y-axis in the second, column the Z
axis in the third column, that's it, right?
Very, very simple.
Now, let's take a look though at how we extend our rotation into three
dimensions because there's an open question.
Now, how do I produce a 3D set of axes that are rotated about some
that are rotated in some way?
Because I don't really know how to do that, right?
We looked at the 2D version and you know, maybe you kind of can't, you
know, see
Actually how that extends, because that was only for a rotation in 2D.
Well, the answer is for starters.
There is a way we can derive sort of a separate thing.
Maybe we should do at some point.
We don't want to it's not relevant ordering.
Now I'm going to focus on doing the primary rotations first because
you should do those and then we can talk about deriving, generic
rotation later.
But so there's two kinds of rotation we want to derive one because it
I guess I should
To avoid getting hit myself.
I should also mention in two Dimensions.
There's only one way to rotate really, right?
The only access we can rotate around is is sort of the axis that isn't
there, right?
We've got X and Y and we're sort of act rotating around the z-axis,
right?
We're looking down on this thing.
You know, the Z axis is pointing up.
We've got a Sprite on the screen here is the x-axis, here's the y-axis
and we're really rotating around this axis.
Right, we're rotating around the z-axis.
SS into Dr.
Rotation is around an axis.
We can't even see.
It's an access that isn't even there.
Right in 3D.
We now have at any arbitrary choice of access we could rotate about
any number of infinite number of axes, right?
Because in 3D, we can move and we can specify any sort of access we
want to write.
It's one of the reasons 3D is so much harder than 2D is specifically
because of rotations positions in 2D and 3D working identically.
There's no difference between a petition in position in 3D and 2D they
perform exactly the same.
They are simple, Vector spaces, euclidean Vector spaces with no
unusual properties rotation.
In 2D is very simple.
You saw it very, very straightforward in 3D, it becomes very
complicated specifically because now there is not
Just one axis of rotation.
There is this complicated way in which you can rotate stuff about any
number of axes in 3D.
I know it's a little bit weird but you know it intuitively, right?
You can't think of any other access to rotate something around other
than the one that comes out of the screen.
When we're talking about 2D,
But in three dimensions, when you're just looking about the real
world, you're like, well, I could pick any any line, right?
I can rotate around, right any there any line in 3D?
It could be my Axis of rotation.
There's no difference between any of those in terms of the validity of
what I get.
If I rotate into D, I can't do that because in 2D any line that is in
the plane of the actual two dimensional space would rotate things out
of
That two dimensional space and we wouldn't be in 2D anymore.
You need the third dimension in order to use them.
So the only access which keeps everything still in 2D is the one that
doesn't go in that plane at all which is the one that comes out of the
space.
Right.
So rotation in 2D is very special.
It's very different and much more simplified.
In 3D, you're in a place where now it's possible to construct lines in
the space that can also rotate things in the space and it's the first
time you can't do that in 1D or 2D 3D is the first time that happens
which is why it's special.
It's why it's hard and it's why people are constantly dealing with
So much more complex structures, like what turn Ian's, like,
exponential Maps, you know, these sorts of things just you never
really have to do them in 2D.
You'd never even have to know about them into D if you didn't want to.
Because 2D rotations you can get by with just a simple scalar and
thinking about rotating around the z-axis and that will work, you will
never be forced to confront any more significant problems.
All right, sorry for that long aside but I kind of wanted to make sure
everyone sort of understood what was going on there.
All right, so now talking a little bit more about the 3D rotation
matrices.
So how do we extend the logic that we did here, right?
This derivation, if you think about it.
The key insight to creating rotation, matrices, in 3D around.
Cardinal axes.
Is to realize that this math just works.
Unchanged.
Right.
Because if you just want to rotate around a cardinal axis, the other
axis is left undisturbed.
Now what do I mean by that?
Well, let's suppose that we were in 3D.
Here's my 3D coordinate system.
Here is the X.
Here is the Y.
Here's the Z.
Okay.
Actually.
That's horrible.
That's left-handed.
I take it all back.
Here's the X.
Here's the why.
Here is this a much better?
You can follow the right-hand rule.
That you're always in the right coordinate system in terms of left and
a right handed.
I'll just mention this really quickly a left handed coordinate system
versus a right-handed coordinate system.
Is what the winding order is of your axes.
So if I take my x-axis in my y-axis and I draw them like this, then
the question is, which direction does ego?
Does is z+ in this direction, or is it positive in this direction?
If it's positive in this direction, it's left-handed.
And if it's positive in this direction is right handed, right?
Oops,
And the reason that we call it that is if you imagine putting your
hand with like a thumbs-up sign, right?
That's the worst.
I realize that's horrible.
If you imagine curling your hand.
So here are your fingers, right?
And there's your thumb.
Well that's not just awful, that's just the worst thumb.
All right, I need Anna here to draw something for us.
This is why I'm not the artist at Molly rocket.
If you curl your hand over, right?
Here's your hand.
Here's your watch.
Underhand your thumb.
If your you take your right hand and do this, if you curl from the
x-axis toward the y-axis, right?
Your thumb will point along the z-axis, right?
So curl, your fingers from X towards Y and your thumb points out, the
Z axis.
If you do that with your right hand and it works, then you're
right-handed.
If on the other hand, I took my left hand and you know it would be
curling this
Way.
Right.
So here's my fingers coming.
This way the thumb would come out this way.
Here's the watch on the hand again, right?
The thumb would point that direction, right?
If I curled from the X to the Y and hence, dad is a left handed
coordinate system, right?
That's why that nominee that's what that nominal Ledger comes from.
Its if you curl your hand from X to Y, which way does ego?
That's the way to think about it, right?
Another way to say it is that if you were to counter clockwise draw an
arc, right?
So
Like, counterclockwise, draw an arc like that, then the Z axis comes
out from the perspective into the place where it looks
counterclockwise, right?
Because remember, if I was looking at it from behind it, would look
clockwise right?
From here, from this side, it looks clockwise.
So, if the Z comes out of the counterclockwise rotation, right?
And again, that's like the curling of the thumbs, right?
That's the thumb curl.
Then it's right-handed If instead, it comes out of the clockwise
turning, if it comes out that way, which would be here, imagine
flipping it, right?
So if I flipped it, so we had here is my x-axis.
Here is my y-axis.
Here's my Z axis.
Right?
So I'm just taking this diagram here and I'm rotating it this way.
I'm looking at it from the other direction, right?
Here's left.
Here's right.
So now if I looked at that curl, right, you can see it's clockwise now
because we're looking at it from the other side.
So if it comes out the clockwise side then it's left-handed, right?
So you can think of this as this is the clockwise curl.
This is the counter clockwise curl.
I always use right-handed.
The reason for that is not because I am right handed because like you
don't have to be more coordinated, this is an easy motion to do with
either hand, right?
So you don't, it doesn't matter whether you are right-handed or
left-handed.
So I always use right-handed coordinate systems.
The reason for that is because math tends to use right-handed
coordinate systems by default in most textbooks.
So
Because when you're dealing with 3D Graphics, you tend to bring a lot
more math in when you want to read papers and textbooks that are
written for you know, doing advanced math that you are now doing
because you have to do physics and more complex geometry and all these
other sorts of things that you're bringing into it, you really don't
want to have to constantly be switching, which handedness your mind is
working in so it helps to just pick and go with the math version,
which is right-handed.
So I always go with right-handed, so all the things that I will ever
talk about in 3D.
I will always talk about them right-handed unless I simply make a
mistake.
But I never intentionally.
Would do something left handed and again that has literally nothing to
do with left-handed or right-handed people.
I am right-handed but that is not why I do it right handed.
If math had been left-handed, I would have done it left-handed because
it's simply about trying to maintain consistency to avoid having to
flip back and forth.
If you go read something,
In the math text.
So this is math convention.
Not people convention, do not worry if you are left-handed, that does
not matter and is not relevant here at all.
It's just about the convention.
Okay, so we know our 3D matrices look like this.
Right.
We know that's what they look like.
Furthermore, we know our unit
Uncle has given us this, right?
We know that we have an X axis.
This cosine.
Sine Theta Y axis, negative sine cosine, right?
so, the question is,
What if I want to start by just picking some access to rotate around
that, I'm just going to do.
Essentially the same operation I was doing before, let's suppose I
want to rotate around the XY axis still but just in 3D, right?
So I don't want to produce a rotation that actually moves things
between axes at all.
I just want to go ahead and produce a rotation around, one of the
primary axis.
So, in this case, I want to rotate around the z-axis, which means that
the XY plane is where the rotation is occurring.
Right?
So everything in the end in XY plane or the you know, the entire
cylinder of X Y is getting spun if you will.
How do I do that?
Well, if you take a look at what that implies here, right, when I
multiply my coordinates, I've got my X, my y, my Z.
We just said that the way that this works right?
Was, was that these axes are slotted here, and we know that the
x-coordinate is going to be, you know, X, the x axis the y coordinate
is going to multiply the y axis and the Z coordinates going to
multiply the Z axis, right?
And what we just said
Was that we want to just rotate the XY around and relieving the Z
untouched.
Right.
So no matter where you are, you don't have to be in just one plane
anywhere in 3D space that z-axis is just a giant axle.
Essentially, everything is going to rotate around it through all of 3D
space, but no matter where you are in a 3D space, your Z coordinates
not going to change, right?
Because the rotation is only affecting the X and Y coordinates.
What that means?
Is we know right off the bat that this isn't should produce no effect
Effect.
Right, nothing should change.
So how do we do that?
well, if we take a look at what the values are here,
XYZ.
I know.
I want x times something.
Right?
I want y times something now.
I know what it is and then I just want Z.
Right, I just want, you know, my Z value.
Well, if I just want my Z value to be the exact same thing that it was
when it came in, right?
We know that when we do X, Y and Z, we're going to do that.
That product for that bottom, sorry, I should say, one more thing that
we know, we also know that the X and Y coordinates should not depend
on Z at all.
Either.
Right because no matter where,
You are along this Z axis.
you should not rotate more or less based on where you are in Z,
everyone rotates the same no matter whether their way far away, Along
Z axis
Right next to us, far behind us doesn't matter.
They should all rotate the same amount the rotation is constant
throughout space.
So what that means is not only should Z essentially be must be the
only thing that we end up with here.
Right?
The Z axis that we end up with here.
Should literally just be the the z-axis we started with, right?
Just 001 the, the, the Z axis, but also Z should come into
Play in no way in these two.
So the Z coordinate should not appear in the equations for x or y,
right.
So what that tells us is we can fill in all of our Matrix that
involves easy with just the identity Matrix, right?
With no change because we know first of all, that Z should be produced
with this axis.
So, we know these values and then furthermore, we know that are our
coordinates
Are right.
We don't know what's in the top two because those are the parts that
are actually do the rotation, but we know the bottom two should have
no like, there should be no change at all in the, in the, in the Z
direction, right X and Y, should not move in Z at all, right.
So, there's our sort of our, you know, our easy way to eliminate a
bunch of stuff out of the Matrix and, hey, guess what we're left with.
Only the upper 2 by 2.
And if we want to produce that same rotation, that we were producing
before with a two, by two Matrix, we can just do exactly that, right?
Because the parts of the rotation that we care about are happening,
only in the X, Y axes.
Anyway.
So exactly the same Matrix that worked up here.
Works in 3D when we only care about two of those axes, right?
Negative, sine cosine, cosine, sine that for axes will work.
Exactly correctly.
So, if we just put those in here in exactly the same place,
That they were, we can construct a z axis rotation.
In 3D using nothing more than exactly what we did in 2D.
Right?
Because as you can see exactly what we want to have happen happens,
the x-coordinate will now get interpreted, not in any way differently
in Z, right?
It's not going to move us in Z at all, but it will move us cosine
Theta, sine Theta, will move along that axis right in the world which
is what we want.
That's the new x-axis, it's been bent, right?
It's been rotated the y-axis, same thing we want to move along
negative sine cosine and that's exactly what it will do.
Right?
And again no change in Z because ours new Z coordinate.
For our point is not dependent on where we were in.
Why it stays the same
Soca producing a z.
This rotation in 3D is literally just the same as producing the 2D
rotation.
It's just now there's padding and it essentially to make sure that the
Z coordinate flows through, not only untouched itself, but also
without affecting anybody else, right?
And without them affecting it, I should say.
So it affects does not affect them, they do not affect it.
The X Y and the Z are separate completely because that is what this
rotation means.
And in fact,
at is a specifically, what an axis of rotation is.
If you think about it, the axis of rotation is the axis along, which
everything is constant, all the other axes are spinning and they're
spinning around that axis, but that axis nothing changes the measure
of things.
Along that axis are not changed in any way.
During a rotation, that's what an axis of rotation is, right?
The One Direction, a wheel does not change in a car is the axle,
right?
It's spinning all around.
If you look at it from the side, the wheel, every point on the wheel
is changing.
If you look at it from the perspective of the axle, the wheel is
staying in one place, right?
It doesn't move this way on the car, right?
If these are the wheels, they're not doing that at all.
They're not doing this right there.
Exactly, in place.
But if you look at it from the axles perspective where the axe is
coming, right at us now, everything is all the points are changing,
right?
So, there you go.
So now the question is, well, can we produce an X?
What about an excitation or what, about a y rotation, right?
Rotation around the x-axis or the y-axis?
Well, the answer is we can construct those exactly the same way we
constructed this one, right?
So, the way that we constructed this one,
To put it into the 3D context is we said let's pick right the axis of
rotation as Z.
That's what we said, right.
And so what we effectively, we're doing when we did that with said,
let's produce that unit circle.
On the X and Y axis, and the Z axis will be our rotation axis, right?
That's what we were saying.
So when we constructed our sine cosine, we're constructing them in the
plane of the XY.
And here's that cosine, here's that sign, right?
This is for Z.
What if we simply picked one of the other axes X or Y, as the rotation
and constructed this circle in the other axes, right?
So let's go ahead and pick those exact same
Let's go ahead and construct the exact same diagram, but just now with
a different axis selected, right?
So, let's say, we want to rotate about the x axis.
Well, first question is, how do we construct?
The unit circle with the other axes?
And the answer is, you still want to always obey the
Right hand rule to remain consistent with mathematics and what the
right-hand rule says, again, is whatever the axis wherever the axis
pointing out of, we want to look counterclockwise, right with respect
to it, right?
So that means constructing.
Our unit circle.
Looks like this.
Here is our unit circle, right?
It's starting from y.
Going to Z.
Here is our little right, triangle, right here.
Is our cosine Theta.
Here is our sign.
Theta.
Right, that makes sense.
And what you can see here is, when you look at how this is
constructed, you can immediately read off exactly what these axes are
going to be again, right?
We now know it's our y axis and our Z axis that are being
reinterpreted.
But you can see exactly what they are.
The y axis in this case, is constructed such that the y-coordinate
write the x coordinate is not relevant here, right?
So we don't care what the x coordinate is, at all the new Y axis is
going to be constructed, such that its y-coordinate is the cosine,
right?
You can see that.
That's, you know, what's going on the y-coordinate.
It's going to be the cosine here as it goes down, right?
So that's what are Y coordinates.
What are Y?
Axis, y coordinate is and it's X.
I'm sorry.
What it's Z coordinate is which is the other coordinate we care about
is varying as the sign varies and it's again exactly how the sign of
Aries gets positive.
First then goes to 0 again.
Then goes to negative then goes to 0 again right?
So it looks like that
And our Z axis, we can do exactly the same thing.
Our Z axis starts here, right and rotates down again doing the
counterclockwise rotation.
If we look at how that rotation works as the Theta here increases,
right?
We're going to be on the unit circle there again.
As normal there is our pick, as you can see, cosine is specifying the
Z axis, the Z coordinate of the Z axis, right?
So that goes in there and the sign on the other hand, as that rotates
around the sign is specifying the y coordinate of the Z axis.
But as you can see it's gets - at the start.
So once again it's you know, it's got that - on it and you can start
to see the pattern here.
Right?
Cosine is always cosine and you know, that's not an accident.
I
in terms of how the rotation is working because it always starts at 1
on the axis and then drops to 0 if you want to rotate the other
direction obviously you know you would you would
Probably have to think about a little differently, but assuming that
you're obeying the the right-hand rule we get the exact same thing.
So cosine works the same way in both negative sign and sign works the
same way.
In both, one of them gets the negative version.
One against the other, the reason for that again is because it's 90
degrees offset, right?
In fact, if you remember your trig identities, you know, the whole
I'll just mention this real quickly here, because it's mildly
mathematically, interesting, if you remember your trigonometry
trigonometric identities, right?
You remember some weird stuff where they lie cosine of 90 plus an
angle or whatever, right?
And what you can see if you actually draw these out is you can sort of
start to see where those actually came from.
In case they were a little bit hazy, back in math class where they
tend to not explain things very well.
So if we have an angle Theta here, right, you can imagine constructing
that same exact
Out here, right?
With the same Theta.
Okay, so this is the original Theta here is Theta, you know, same
Theta.
Essentially, this is theta plus 90, right?
It's theta plus 90 degrees, right?
Rotating up this way.
Well, whatever you were going to get for your cosine here, right?
Is not going to change, like the cosine behavior.
Is going to be exactly the same as it moves, right?
Sort of around, but the sign behavior is going to change.
The sign behavior is going to change when it gets here and it's going
to flip to - and then flip back to positive, right?
And so you can sort of start to see that difference between the two if
that makes any sense where they don't.
They don't behave the same because one of them starts going where they
start going on.
The circle is different.
I'm explaining this extremely poorly.
You know what just forget about I ever said that, that's just a kid.
That's just confusing.
But point being, you can kind of see how that is relevant here.
Because since you're always starting on the axis, when you're actually
starting on the access, the cosine is the thing that gives you that
behavior of walking around the circle when you have to be talking
about the person who's 90 offset from you,
Then you end up getting that - in there because the sign has to be
doing the work at 90 degrees.
Plus itself.
That's all I was trying to say which and I said it extremely poorly.
I'm still saying it's really poorly.
Doesn't matter, not relevant point being.
Here's our Y and z-axis.
So if we take a look at what we want to do to produce the the rotation
again, here is our Z axis rotation.
We can take a look at our x axis rotation,
And we know the Y and Z axes.
We can just slot them in exact, like we're doing before.
So there's R cosine Theta, there's R, sine Theta, here's our negative
sine Theta.
Here's R cosine Theta, right?
And then
Again the what the the x-axis is unchanged right?
There is no it's just the regular old x-axis that we would have if we
hadn't done anything, right.
So, you can see, we've got these two rotation matrices here.
Here's a z axis rotation, right?
Leave Z unchanged entirely, just affects X&Y.
Here's our x x rotation.
X is unchanged exactly the same way.
But y&z are modified.
And I suspect you could probably yourself derive, the y axis rotation.
At this point.
I will do it because obviously we should, you know, we're going to
have to do it on stream because we want to be able to generate all of
these.
Matrices, right.
If x Y & Z, we want to rotate around the y axis again that means right
hand, rule means we're going to be counterclockwise risk with respect
to the y-axis.
So again if we were standing up where the Y is positive, Y and looking
down, we should see a counter clockwise.
This is counter clockwise from the perspective of somebody looking
back down the y-axis, right?
So that counterclockwise rotation that we're doing their implies, that
we need to construct the rotation for x and z.
So we can see exactly what that's going to be.
The x axis is going to be going this way, right?
And so, what's going to happen there again, cosine is going to do
exactly the same thing that it always does is going to start at 1 get
20 then go to - right.
So we know as far as our x axis is concerned the x-coordinate of the
x-axis.
Going to be
Cosine Theta just like it.
Always is in every particular case and then we've got the the
z-coordinate part of it and the Z coordinate, part of it is going to
be getting - right away, write it in as it rotates.
It's not going to start off going positive, right?
So it's doing the sign behavior of starting at 0 and going towards
one, but - one not positive one, right.
So it's a negative sign it.
Oops.
It's a negative sign.
As it moves again, the y coordinate, in this case, since it's the axis
of rotation, not involved, write x and z are operating alone.
They do not involve y, so we know that that is a 0 in both cases, the
Z axis.
Again, same thing.
We have a cosine, the cosine term is going to do exactly what it
always does.
It's going to start at one, go to -1, come back, right?
So we know that the Z coordinate is cosine Theta.
And then we just have to figure out what is the y-coordinate.
I'm sorry.
What is the x coordinate?
The x coordinate is going to start at 0.
Go to one and come back, right?
So again following that exact same pattern, a negative sign in the
sign right to cosines Neuroscience sign, right?
So that implies a structure of our Matrix.
Pretty directly just like in the rest of the cases, we know that Y is
You just completely so we would expect it to just have, you know, no
information in it that changes at all its axis and it's projection,
both the same.
And so we're just filling in these parts here.
Right?
The x-axis cosine Theta 0, negative sine Theta, right.
Similarly Z sine Theta, 0, cosine, Theta.
And that is our Y, axis rotation.
and so assuming that I haven't made any math errors there,
I'm not particularly good at math.
as you've heard me say many times on the Stream, So I guarantee I in
no way guarantee freedom from math, errors on the Stream,
I guarantee you, we have them.
Maybe just not right now, but we have them.
Those are rotation matrices.
Okay.
so now you know how to build
The Cardinal rotation matrices.
Great job.
Good job.
Alright, so now, you know how to build the car notation matrices and
that's good.
And the question is, how does this help us Casey great?
You went down this whole diversion of how to build rotation matrices.
What?
You know, how does this help us?
What's going on?
I'm confused.
I don't care.
Give me something.
Why are we even doing this?
Well, once we can build Cardinal rotation matrices, we can actually
allow ourselves to build a little camera that will rotate around the
world and give us the ability to orbit our world and see what the
structure is, like, in three dimensions, which is exactly what we
wanted.
Right?
And the way that we can do that is we can compose these Cardinal
rotation, matrices into a little Euler angle system, like almost a
little toy.
If you will, for producing like two dials that will allow us to rotate
around our world.
And let's just talk really quickly about how that works and then we
can go try to build it.
I don't know if I'm gonna have time, we've only got about 40, 45
minutes and this these explanations cannot take a while because I have
to sort of get like,
I have to kind of get a lot of the math out there, but matrix
multiplication we've covered before.
We've talked about it before and the way that it works, right?
Is you just have like, ABC.
Well, you know, I'm going to do a slightly different way so that you
can see
She gets a little bit more of it.
So I'm going to produce a matrix C and I'm going to produce it by
multiplying a
I am be right.
That's just what I'm gonna do because I got start with that in order
to give you something to hang onto.
So this is matrix multiplication, I'm taking two matrices, A and B,
and multiply together to produce.
See right now, matrix multiplication, and Vector, multiplication are
the same thing when we've talked about this in hand M before, but I'm
going to stress it again because now it's actually starting to become
a lot more important.
A vector is just a matrix that has less columns, okay, and what
happens with matrix?
Multiplication is the rules of multiplication are defined such that.
The only thing that has to be true is the number of rows in the left
hand side Matrix,
I'm sorry, the number of columns.
In the left hand side Matrix has to be the same as the number of rows
in the right hand side Matrix, right?
And as long as that condition holds you can perform the matrix
multiplication.
Now you know this intuitively because of the way we've in structuring
our matrix multiplication, but you may have never thought about
explicitly.
So let's take a look at what I mean and how the math actually works
out.
Okay, so I'm going to draw this the way we have been drawing these
Here is our Matrix a and I'm going to enumerate the elements of it
programmer style.
Okay?
So I'm going to say that we have a right and I'm going to say that
this is a zero zero.
I'm going to call this a 10.
I'm going to call this a 2-0, right?
I'm going to go across and I'm going to put the the column number in
the first one, right?
I don't know that.
That's such a good idea.
In fact, you know what?
I'm going to do it.
Like I said, programmer style, which I suppose means we should use the
the lit.
The least significant part first.
So I suppose, I should say a 0 0, a 0.
1 is 0 2.
Okay, because I'm going for a, I want to translate this into code in a
second.
And so I believe math, notation traditionally math notation would
actually number them.
The way that I did it the first time, usually, they will put the
column as the, the first one.
And the row is the second one.
So this is just for temporary, just for briefly for now I'm doing this
the way we're going to write a for I Loop.
So the lineup but keep in mind that this notation is fungible and if
you were going to be in a math textbook, you could easily see them in
the opposite order, okay?
So again, going down here.
Oops.
Okay, so you can see how I've numbered them.
Here, they go 0.
120 120.
In the first because the row is coming.
First, then we have 0, 0 0, the column number coming S, 0 0, 0, 1 1, 1
2, 2 2, right?
And again, I'm doing this program or numbering so that we can
translate it quickly.
Don't take that as some kind of hard and fast rule because I believe
math.
Textbook will also do it the other way round, right?
And when we do derivations on handmade hero because we want a lineup
with math, we may do them the other way, round in every other case
that we're doing.
I just want to show you for the implementation side of things.
This is that's all this diagram is for
or okay.
And so here is my b.
And I'm going to number them exactly the same way.
Oops.
All right, this is my Matrix C.
This is my Matrix B.
This is my Matrix.
A
all right, so this equation a times b equals c can be drawn out this
way where we have a and and these to appear in the same order they
appear here right?
A and B and the result just goes here you know I could put it over
here I could I could do it this way to make it a little bit more
lining up with the diagram right where C is kind of off to the right a
little bit more so hopefully maybe that helps a little bit but anyway
we have a times B in that order and the order is important because
matrix multiplication will see why in a second but that's what we're
I'm here now.
Like I said, major small location, vector equation exactly the same,
the way that this multiplication works, is it steps through each row
of B and each column of a to produce a single term in the output.
Right.
So exactly.
Like, we've been doing our Vector math.
It's the first element first element, right?
So it's a 0 0.
B 0 0, right?
Then it's be 10, a 10.
And then finally oops should keep them in the right order there a 01
be 10.
And then finally we have the last one a zero to be 20.
Right?
Can already tell that?
I'm going to run out of space here.
So I'm going to frill actively delete that.
All right.
Right.
And that's our first term.
Our next term is going to use a different row of a, but the same
column of B, write a 10, B, 0 0, a 1, 1 B, 10.
A 12 b 2 0, right?
The bees are the same.
The, a is different, right?
Same exact thing one more time.
A 2000.
A 2-1.
B10 a to to be 20.
That is our first column of C.
Now that is exactly the same as the vector multiplication.
If this if we pretend that this wasn't here, right?
It's exactly the same.
That's the way I say, Vector, multiplication and matrix.
Multiplication are exactly the same operation of vector is just a
matrix with less columns, right?
A vector is just a matrix that only has one column.
Whereas The Matrix and have as many columns as it
W.
And again, multiplication between two matrices.
If you look at how this works, it doesn't matter how many columns B
has be, could have 100 columns, and this would still work totally
well, because all that matters is that I have the same number of
columns in a, as rows in B.
So once I say what a is and I say how many columns a has be, can only
have that many rows?
That's the constraint.
But I can have as many columns as it wants this
Same thing is true of the rows of a right, the rows of a, a could have
as many roses it wants.
It doesn't matter how many rows it has.
It only matters how many columns it has because the columns have to
line up with the rows of B.
Right.
That's a mighty just multiplication works.
So what might respond to location?
Says in terms of being defined for the wrote kind of multiplication
we're doing here.
There, there's other sorts of Matrix math and things that you might
care about when you're talking about.
King with two matrices that don't obey those criteria.
But the vanilla Matrix map that we're doing here and the one that we
do for, basically, all 3D stuff that we're going to care about in
handmade hero.
That simple matrix product.
The basic fundamental matrix product, it just means that a columns.
Equals bees Rose.
That's all we need to have, right?
And they can see exactly how we produced it, we just step Through The
Columns of a and the and the rows of B and multiply them and that
produces a term and we do that for every row of a and doesn't matter
how many rows of a has, we just keep going then to produce how many
columns we want here?
We would just keep going through The Columns of B.
So now
We go back to the start of a and we just say, all right, it's a 0-0
again.
Right, we're using a 0 0 again but now we are going to produce use our
product using Loops, not the plus using the column of B.
So we go to be 01.
Now instead of 0 0 again, a is this act the same a 01 but now instead
of B10 it's be 11, then we go to a 0 2 and again because of B20 it's
be 21.
Right.
And now we again reproduce exactly the same operation.
We're
You're now the bees will be the same in this column but the A's will
change, right?
It's a 10 B, 0 1, a 1 1 b, 1 0, sorry, 11 a 12 B 21?
Right again, same thing a 2-0, b, 0 1,
A21 b11.
A.22, B21 right.
Make good sense.
Now, you can guess what?
The final column is, right?
It's exactly the same pattern that we've been following.
The a stay the same on a row, the be stay the same on a column, right?
So stepping here, we now have the final column here is 0 to 1 to 2 2,
right?
So here we were 0, 1 1, 1 2 1.
Now we're going to be 0 to 1 to 2 2, right?
But the A's will stay the same so we have a 0 0 B 0 to a 0 1 V 1 2.
Write a zero to be 22.
And then again the product here, the A's are going to stay the same
from this Row.
The bees are going to stay the same from the column.
So we end up with a 10 B.
0 to a 1 1 b, 1 2, a 1 2, b 2 2.
And finally again a is from here, a 2 0, B 0 2, a 2 1, b, 1 2 and a 2
2, b, 2 2.
And that is our new Matrix right now, what you can see is it's very
very concise how this is enumerated.
It is a giant set of math and matrix.
Multiplication mind you is slow, right?
It is a slow operation because there's just a lot of Mads going on.
There's a lot of multiply add.
Write a lot of two things multiplied by each other.
Plus two things multiplied, each other plus two things all over each
other, right?
That's how these are getting produced
There's a lot of that going on, but how it is going on is very
straightforward, right?
For if we wanted to write this in a more concise summation, notation
or something, right?
And we look at what we've got here, if I can sort of try to line it
up, you can see that what we have here, right?
Is the summation.
in this case of I from 0 to 2,
Right of a very simple product.
It's a 0, I bi0 right now, if you've never seen this term before,
maybe you got to go back to remember, your high school math, right?
This is saying, I'm going to some
It's a for I Loop, right?
This is just for I equals 0 to 2, right?
The thing inside.
Right Summit.
So some equals zero sum
Plus equals write this thing a 0 I bi 0, right?
So this is Maths for I Loop, right?
And it's for I loop with a plus equals implicitly built into it,
right?
So it's saying take the first one.
Add it to the second one, add it to the third one, and the fourth one,
fifth, and sixth one, however, many Loops you want to take it just a
summation, right?
So this is all that is right.
Let's take a look at the second term again.
These are all
I equals 0 to 2, in fact, if I may, perhaps, you would permit me to
write this even more concise, right?
Because these summations, you can see what's going to happen.
They're all going to be i0 to to hear.
It's going to be the same thing a 0 I because we're still on the row
of a, right?
But now the B is instead of i 0 its I won.
Right.
So hopefully you can see what's going to happen.
I'm just going to do that for each of these positions, right?
And if you would permit me to write that in a slightly more concise
way I could put the summation outside because the summation is true
for every single element, right?
So, it's really, is summation of.
I equals 0 to 2 of The Matrix, right?
Hey 0, I bi 0, right?
And then if I go back, well, I've done it again.
I've managed to not get myself quite enough room.
Let's just pick a little bit bigger there, right?
The summation from I equals 0 to 2.
I've got a and again in this case right?
You can see across every one of these.
It the a constant changes per row not per column.
Right?
So the summation in this case here it's always 0, I right?
Because it goes across the some, the eye is in the second part is the
part that increments right bi 0.
And then, if I move down again the bees don't change, the bees are the
same in any column but the a changes so I'd have a one I right?
Oops that's one I bi 0, a 2, I be
Zero, right?
Because you can see the bees are unchanged.
They're always the same no matter which row there in here and then
moving across the A's are the same across a row but the bees change,
right?
So this is a 0 I still but now it's bi 1, this is a 0 I still but now
it's bi2.
Right?
And now again it's just copy, just copy and paste.
I'm one eye to eye.
I won.
Eye-to-eye, and in this case, we've got the be right.
It's coming from here.
Now, b, 1, B, I2 B I2.
So this is matrix multiplication.
Right.
That's all we're trying to do.
It's just the for I Loop and really if we wanted to, we could do
another for we could do multiple for a loop, because you can see these
actually have regular structure to them as well.
Write the column and the row of the result.
Tell you the constants for these, whichever column I'm on is the
constant for be, whichever row.
I'm on is the constant for a.
So three, nested for I Loops essentially give me
My whole Matrix multiply with one term, right?
So that's matrix multiplication.
Let me just go ahead and write it out for you now in code.
So you can see, hope you can see how that all got derived.
I'm going to go to handmade math and I'm just going to sort of Speck
in here.
Just really quickly and inline Matrix multiply
I don't think we have a matrix class anywhere, right?
There's no struct Matrix.
I don't think so.
I'm going to go over to the platform code where that is it's kind of
out in here somewhere.
Yeah there it is.
You can see V3 and V4 and all that.
So I'm going to go ahead and just throw in a matrix here.
So you can see it really quickly.
I'm going to make a full four by four Matrix so that we have one
Just for our own purposes and I'm going to go ahead and and just make
that 4 by 4, right?
Okay.
So I'm going to make something that is basically a multiple
multiplication operator between two matrices, so I'm going to take a
matrix, a and Matrix B, and I'm going to produce a matrix result out
of it.
And I'm going to do the for I Loop version so that you can see it and
we'll probably just leave it that way because the compiler is usually
smart enough to unroll constant Loops, right?
So I'm going to keep our notation.
Here are
For interior, some of the terms.
So I'm going to go ahead and say all right I've got an interior.
That's I
And we'll go ahead and step out words from the eye.
I'm going to use here a and say we're going to do columns here.
Right?
That's the column and here's the row.
And what we want to do is into our result, right?
We want to be able to place a some into our results.
So we've got the result here.
We know we have the elements.
So the question is, you know, we need to
Initialize this 20 obviously.
And again this is, you know,
This is supposed to be the instructive version of this, you can just
see how it works.
Not supposed to be the most efficient way necessarily or anything like
that.
So when we want to do the multiplication here we've got a some these
terms together, right?
And you can see, we've got a 0.
I bi 0, a 1.
I bi 0, right?
So it's always the, I is the column on a and the row on be right?
So I'm just going to copy.
Exactly that notation over and say that it.
So he's you can see that the second coordinate and I is I the first
coordinate is be.
So then we've got row and column, right of our result.
And like I said, the way that I did it is we've got in terms of what
is rho and what's column.
If you recall, I mean, sorry.
Pan back over to that information, right?
You can see the way I
Row is the first value and column is the second value, right?
So if you want to take a look at how this is going, when we're
producing a row and column of the output row is the first, right?
And column is the second, so we're producing one of our outputs.
And so then we just have to look up into our table here that we've
meticulously created.
If we want to produce the, you know, the 00, the row column version,
who gets the row, who gets the column, you can see that be right.
It's constant is
Always getting the column, right?
So it's always the column for be right 0, 0 0, 1 1, 1 2 2 2.
Right so be is always getting the column.
You can see that the constant for a is always the row, right?
So there's the row.
And so now you can see matrix multiplication.
That is how you multiply two matrices together that produces the
result.
In this case, you know we were doing a 3D Matrix here.
I wanted to do a matrix that's the full homogeneous Matrix like we
have to pass to opengl.
I want to do the whole Matrix.
So it's going to be a 3 in this case because it's 0 1 2 3, not 0 1 2.
So we've got an extra row and column but again the Matrix math doesn't
care about that it only cares.
There's dimensionality why's that the rows of of right hand side and
The Columns of the left hand side have the same number in them.
Now, what you can see from the construction of this Loop is you can
see exactly why that has to be
To write when you Loop through these, you can see that a is getting
picked out by R 0, and B is getting picked up by column the row and
column values in.
No way affect the up the two in any other way, right?
So that basically means that your choice of row, what are has to be is
only relevant for a because it only appears in the expression for a
similarly
Lee, the column only appears in the expression for B?
So the row and column counts are not relevant in that way.
A is free to have as many roses at wants.
It determines the R&B is free to have as many columns as it wants
because it determines the sea.
However, you see the Restriction.
It's baked into the code and into the rules of Matrix math.
I appears in both it appears as the column of a and the row of B.
And that is where that fundamental, that that
Basic restriction of Matrix math comes from because that is how the
terms are contracted.
It means that you always must have the same number.
It could be any number you want here, but that means that you have to
have the same number of columns of a, as you have rows of B, because
that is where the term is the same, right?
That I attorney that I picks out both.
Okay.
Alright, so now we have the way a way to define one of these Saucy
matrices, right?
And I could avoid initializing it here because I'm just doing that.
Some, I could just say, you know what, clear it to 0, right?
And again this is not necessarily optimal because you can see here.
Well I don't really need to clear it to zero because I could start by
initializing it to the first term of the series if I wanted to write
blah blah blah, right?
I can you could imagine pulling this out and making it be equal to the
first one of these up here and then doing this equals I equals 1 2 3.
And only something in things that actually to be some great.
So so this is the instructor version, not the optimal version.
You can make a better version of this if you want to.
But I wanted to make it look as close to the math as possible.
Hopefully, that's very clear.
What's going on here, right?
This is the row.
This is the column.
And this is, this is rows of a Columns of B.
Now, what you can also see, just by looking at the routine is no
matter what you decide to do Matrix wise.
You can see what the definition is of the result.
What's the shape of that result, right?
And the answer is it will have as many rows and I guess I should put
up here rows of a Columns of B, right?
Who put that backwards.
homes of a,
Roosevelt, there we go.
You can see exactly what the shape of that output is, right?
It's going to have as many rows that as a has, and it's going to have
as many columns as be has, right?
So what that means is your, you know, your your inputs, the two
matrices that you combine, their Dimensions, the row dimension of a,
and the convention of be will determine the shape of the resulting
Matrix.
Right.
And you can see that right in this one fundamental line of code,
right?
You can see rows and columns,
And that again that row column come that row comes from how many are
in a.
Why?
Because a is the only person who cares about our our is never even
used in be right?
Similarly columns never used in a only used in be
So again, it's very, very clear, just from typing out the code, you
can see exactly how the math actually ends up being defined, right?
And you can see that from the picture over here, as well.
Just to hammer this home.
Let's say I made an a that looked, you know, quite a bit different.
Okay, so here's one two, three, four, five, right?
So it's five columns across a and it's two down, right?
So tell me, what does the shape of be have to be?
All right, I'm giving you a little while.
What is the shape of B have to be?
You should now know this.
And the answer is the shape of B has to be at least five rows tall,
right?
Why?
Because as we step Through The Columns of a, we must step down the
rows of B.
And so that is how we know B has to be 5 tall.
How many columns does B have to have?
The answer is as many as it wants.
Right.
And however many it has let's say, it had three
Write that again, will determine the shape of the result.
The shape of the result is, however, many rows.
You had of a
And however, many columns you had of be.
And again, all of this stuff is Trivial to remember just by
remembering this fundamental contraction.
This picture tells you everything you need to know, you don't need to
remember any of that stuff separately.
You just have to remember this contraction where you have to step
down, you know you make these little lines.
I always make you can see this one, this one, this one, this one, this
one.
This one is missing.
You can see what has to line up and you don't care how many columns
you have, right?
You don't care.
How many rows you have of a or a Columns of B that just makes a bigger
or smaller result here in terms of columns or rows.
All right.
So, how does that help us?
Again, we're trying to get to the point where we can do that rotation.
Well, the way that that helps us is this matrix multiplication here.
That we just worked out how to do, right?
Where I want to produce C equals a times B.
The answer is, why do I want to know that?
Well, the answer is jumping ahead.
A little bit, is that if I were to transform a point by a times B,
it's the same as transforming it by the, by the result of the
medication, that's obvious in some sense, because if we're saying that
C equals a times B, well, that means anywhere, we see a times B, we
could substitute.
Two in C, right?
So matrix multiplication we know how to do it and we know how to make
it equal, right?
And that is exactly what we need to do in our open GL code.
Right?
Because what we want to be able to do now is do the projection Matrix
that we're doing here, plus maybe some rotation around X and Y and Z,
we want to be able to do all that stuff.
If we have the ability to take matrices, we know how to build
composite them together in this way to produce a set of transforms
that we want to do, then we will be able
To do all of the work we want to do.
With just one Matrix.
Multiply
Which is really handy, right?
All right, so let's continue from there.
So, we know how to build all these matrices.
If we want to build these matrices with four dimensions, we can always
just augment them right to have an additional identity that just
leaves the W coordinate untouched, right?
Because we don't care again about that W coordinate, right?
We're not rotating it at all.
It's another dimension.
That's not being affected by the rotation in that plane because
rotation is only half,
In the plane of rotation that we care about, it's a fundamentally 2D
rotation happening in three dimensions, right?
It is not a rotation of three dimensions happening in four dimensions
or anything like that.
So,
What that means is we can take the stuff that we derived before.
M.
4 by 4 here, right?
And I can say, you know, X rotation.
Wow, rotation
And I can make routines that will do.
You know, I'm going to stop saying that you just assume that's true
until we optimize something.
I'm going to make something that will construct exactly the rotation
matrices that we're talking about here, right?
Okay, and I'm going to construct them.
Such that we can actually see their structure here.
Now, what I do have to do in this case is I probably have to bracket
this one more time because that's actually an initializer there.
Don't know why for coder was doing that.
There we go.
No, I guess it wanted to move it over for the extra brace.
That actually makes sense.
So this would be an identity Matrix, right?
That would be a matrix that does nothing to its input.
And again, we've talked about that multiple times on handmade hero.
So hopefully, that's not something that's particularly strange to you,
right?
And furthermore, we could actually just save one of these, in case we
want it later.
We could just make one called identity.
Literally just returns that Matrix.
So now we've already worked out.
What all of these are.
Let's go ahead and do it.
Our Z axis rotation, we know is going to be cosine, sine negative,
sine cosine, right?
So it's just going to be cosine sine.
- sine cosine, right?
And what we can do here is just compute those up front.
So the cosine is going to be the cosine of the angle.
The sign is going to be the sine of the angle.
All of the routines want that.
And all we're doing to produce these different rotation.
Matrices is just picking where we're putting them, right?
And like I said, we already worked all this out, so let's just go read
them off, you know, if I could find them.
So, there's our X rotation.
There's cosine, sine.
Sine cosine, right?
So there's our X rotation, and here's our y rotation down here.
Cosine negative, sine.
And then sine cosine.
I think I got all those in the right place.
Yeah.
So now we can build any rotation Matrix.
We want in terms of cardinal rotations, we can multiply any two
rotations together to produce a rotation that does both.
And we can
Yeah, we can, we can do anything we want here, right?
We can we can produce and multiply any rotations that we want.
Now, the important thing to remember here and this is where things
start to get a little Squinkie, because we're not using shaders.
Yet, we're using the fixed function pipeline.
If I go to the platform code, I need to make a note here.
These are stored.
Such that they are column sorry row, major right?
So
Second third, fourth, fifth, sixth seventh eighth, right?
Not this one.
Then this one, then this one.
Then this one, what that means is, it's not this way.
Right?
This is opengl style and this is not, this is column major.
So I want to do it this way because I want are matrices to look math
style, right?
I want you to be able to see them math style, so when they we write
them out.
That's what we expect them to look.
Like is the way we would write them in math.
And so what we're going to do when we get over to the opengl side of
things is we're just going to flip them around, right?
We're going to before we load them in opengl, we're just going to flip
them.
And I'm pretty sure there's actually a transpose load in opengl
nowadays to even if you're using the fixed function pipeline, I could
be wrong about that.
Let me just see.
You'll load Matrix.
Is there a transpose?
So here you go, Geo load transpose, Matrix, we can look, we can call
that and it would do the transpose load, right?
So you actually can you actually can load in a matrix in row major
order nowadays?
It just this would be load transpose Matrix.
F and the problem is that is a function.
We would have to load.
So rather than do that.
And like I said, we won't
Here we get to the fixed function when we get out of the fixed
function.
Anyway, rather than do that, instead what I would rather do is just
swap the values around so that we actually end up with a matrix at the
end, that is in open.
Whales preferred format, right?
Okay, so that's all well and good.
But again, we need, you know, we need some way of doing that.
So let's just go ahead and make a transpose operation here that will
produce what we actually want in this case.
So,
remember if we wanted to,
Produce the kind of a matrix that open Jaws expecting, right,
essentially?
What we're saying is, Well, we start our things, a b c d, e, f, g, h.
I j k.
L m n o p, right?
That's the 4 by 4 Matrix that we're storing that goes in this order,
right?
Opengl is going to read it in that order.
So the Matrix that opengl is actually going to see is going to be a
e-i-e-i-o.
I am right?
F JN, right?
See you can see what's going on here, right?
CGH right.
It's reading them this way.
So all we have to do is first flip our Matrix.
So our Rose, become our columns, in our comms Camaros, that's just
that transpose.
Operator, write the transpose.
Operator is the thing that takes AI J and flips it to AJ.
I write it just flips, the indices and that's exactly what open Jill's
doing.
When it's reading out our Matrix.
So we just have to do the opposite.
We may want a transpose operator anyway, but you know, we might not
want to transfer the operator for four by fours but you know, a 6-1
have done there.
You'll see what I mean.
Later down the line but point being our result here, what we can do is
just do and I oops, it's going to take a
A source Matrix.
A all I need to do here is just do again the a IJ
I did that.
Technically, I goes on the inside.
Usually for me.
in this case and we could just say alright, the resulting
J.
I is going to equal the input.
I j.
And that's it, right?
And really it doesn't matter which order you do those in.
I just did it.
I had eye on the interior up here before so I kept on the interior at
this time but that's about it.
So you can see all its doing, they're just flipping the coordinates,
right?
So if we wanted to now we could take a baby step here because again
we're running out of time and I've had this sort of dumped a lot of
major stuff out on to you today just to get us to a point where you
start to write these things.
What I want to do here is just let's let's start by saying, oh well
okay what if we just made a thing here?
That was like
Action Matrix, right?
And we're going to start working on this projection Matrix.
We need a
Things to build that, right?
We need our ratio like our aspect ratio.
So our aspect with over height, right?
We need to come in here and then we need our focal length.
Those are the two things that we're taking right now for our
projection Matrix, right?
And I want to build this projection Matrix but I want to build it in
our format, right?
So I want to build the M4 by for projection Matrix here that we have,
but now, I want to build it in our
format.
So you should know, right?
You should know how to do this.
Because if that is what we were feeding to opengl, what does the
Matrix look like if it was in our format, right?
What's the difference?
How does it change?
Okay, tell me what I should be writing here.
That that's the difference between them.
Well, remember the difference is a transpose, right?
So it's flipping column-major to row major.
It's Jay, I equals i j.
Well, most of this Matrix is
The a, the be, the one, the 0 down, the diagonal, all of that stays in
the same place because if Jay and I are equal, right?
This is 0 0, this is 1, 1, this is 2 2.
They're not going to flip, they stay exactly where they are.
There's no change, right?
So the only thing that flips is this term right here and it comes
down.
I'm going to go ahead and make that a see.
It comes down here, right?
It goes from right here, to right here.
Furthermore, I guess I'm going to say let's do one over focal length
here.
Just that way.
Because since it, we were already using that in verse number there, I
feel like we can just have that be passed in, right?
So if that is the projection Matrix that were passing down, it's very
straightforward, right?
I can compile everything and off the go.
Oops, it's in there.
And that A and B, let's go grab those.
Got to put them in here.
Okay, so if I now wanted to try and reproduce, what I had just to get
us started and again will concentrate more on this next week when
we've got more time.
But here is what we are producing before.
We want to produce the same thing.
So if I wanted to hear what I could do is say, all right.
you know, I've got my see here, my C is going to be
Right.
I want to produce this projection Matrix so I say projection and I've
got my B and my see here.
Here's my projection Matrix and then I need to transpose it because
like I said, open Jill's taking it the wrong way.
But then I can just go ahead and load it and off I go, right?
It's got a point it at the beginning there and off we go.
So hopefully if we did that right?
We should end up with the same thing.
Of course, we don't because we're almost out of time
I think we've got everything here, right?
The beasts one.
See, that's all correct.
And then we need to do the transposon that projection to put it back
into the other form aspect with over height is in the right place.
Yes a is one that doesn't need to be there anymore.
A is one b and then the one is in the right place and the sea is the
one over for focal length.
Is also in the right place.
That feels correct to me.
Let me just double-check that.
I don't have any busted stuff there.
There we go.
Oh, weird that I did that change because I got rid of the a yeah.
So let me just jump in there.
Just to see what I messed up there.
I typed in a lot of code there pretty quickly.
So here's my projection Matrix and I just want to make sure that it's
sane that looks like what I
Actually, why is that?
Oh huh, I don't know why the focal length.
Presumably, we should have a focal length up.
There we go.
This is the one I actually want to look at as guess that that must
have been that the null one that starts.
Okay, there we go.
So now we've got the protective case that looks like what I was
expecting.
I expecting the one over .3 there to work.
So now we have to see.
Does r transpose work properly and I don't know if it does, it does
not appear to
Did I mess up our transpose?
A, i j equals.
oh,
Wow.
Talk about not paying attention for some reason.
You know, I mean, I guess if I because I was writing it math way, I
guess.
I'll stick to that.
Wow.
I was only doing 012 instead of, I basically just wasn't looping over
all the values.
That's, that's pretty great.
Wow, it's slow morning.
Hi guys.
All right, well,
that's just how it goes.
All right, let's try that one more time.
There's our projection Matrix there is the transpose.
Okay.
So yeah, that's probably our only problem and there we go.
So, yeah.
So that's the beginnings of a little bit of Matrix stuff.
Hopefully, it wasn't too daunting.
We'll get to the multiplication again.
Next week, we didn't have to do it yet and I'll there's one thing that
I haven't explained yet, I showed you how to perform a small station.
I didn't really explain why it does anything useful.
So next week, we'll, you know, hopefully you understood the rotation.
Just stuff pretty clearly.
We went through that the transpose really.
In this case is just to fix the fact that open Jill's reading things
in opposite order.
So we're not really using the transpose mathematically in any
particular way, here that's really just a bookkeeping issue but the
transpose is a mathematical operation and we may use it later as well
for other reasons you'll see.
So, really, all we have to do here is understand those things.
Next week, we'll jump into multiplication now that we've got it.
Why does it do something useful?
What can we do with it?
To make our X rotation, y rotation, Z rotation, stuff work, cleanly,
how do we combine that with projection displacement and so on?
So let's go ahead and jump to the Q&A.
and if you got questions,
Upholstery Mage.
You once said that people don't really use matrices as the storage in
real world.
Things can you talk about the Alternatives?
Yes, so typically for matrices there, what you'll see is they tend to
get used, mostly how we use them in the, in the opengl side of things
right here.
So typically, what happens is when you're done with all your work,
Produce matrices that gets multiplied together for compositing
purposes.
To produce a final transform that you that the GPU like operates on
stuff like that, right?
Sometimes you don't even do that.
Sometimes you actually pass things down, decomposed to the GPU, it
really depends on how the pipeline operates, but again, typically
matrices are used in the computation phase.
The reason they're not used in the storage phase is because you can
kind of see what's going to happen here, right?
If I'm producing these rotation, matrices, and multiplying them
together, and stuff like that, I'm going to end up with a giant bag of
numbers.
That's very hard to pull, meaning back out of.
And so there's nothing wrong with using matrices when you don't have
to pull stuff out of them.
But when you start piling a bunch of stuff into matrices for
computation purposes, if you ever want to back out of the Matrix.
You put you've mixed up too many things, right?
Like you may have gotten rotation and scaling and shearing and all
this other stuff.
All encapsulated up into these upper nut 9 numbers, the 3 by 3 here
at, they will all be up in there.
And it's very costly to pull it out again.
And so, the reason that you typically don't want to do that until
you're done needing to understand the state of something.
Is because pulling like the rotation out of an upper 3x3 of the of the
four by four Matrix here, if they're scaling already in it or other
things already in it is difficult.
Right.
It costs too much to do especially if there's shearing.
And so typically you store things as decompose because it's more
efficient.
So if you have objects that can scale and rotate, you typically store
the scaling and the rotation separate, right?
And that is why
That is why a lot of times you will see newer pipelines.
Don't do things as matrices natively until sort of the back end of the
process, when everything is already been like interpolated to its
final placement.
And then when things want to get combined, like I want to combine the
placement of this object in the world with the camera, transform with
the projection onto the screen.
I want like all those things smush together then the matrices
I'm out because they can, they're very efficient, potentially for
doing that, right?
Disused, will we use quaternions reducing rotation Matrix from
Katrina?
Seems like a good idea, I know we will probably not use quaternions
because this code is only really for camera, debug movement, and we
won't probably be rotating things in game at all.
So we won't really need to get into quaternions and interpolated.
Or any of that sort of stuff because we probably won't have that as a
thing we do.
From now on you will only be streaming on Saturday and Sunday?
Yeah, well I don't know from now on but for the time being anyway, the
stream is generally Saturday Sunday.
Pepe vote.
Would it be worth investing time doing a Sim D optimisation for matrix
multiplication or is it like killing ants with a rifle?
No it's not a bad idea to Cindy optimize any math code that you might
have.
It can it's always useful to have that optimization but in our case
this again is just for the camera, right?
We're not we're not probably ever going to have any matrices for
anything in the game.
This is just for the camera.
So it's only going to be done like once.
And so for our purposes, we don't need any semi opposition this
because we're never going to be calling it, right?
It's so infrequent that it won't do anything.
But if you were doing a tons of objects going through tons of
matrices, then you can see why, you know, maybe that point you want
Sam to optimize some of that stuff.
Padam my panda.
Panda.
Might are you going to use simpler rotation functions that are mainly
focused on smaller?
Matrices, such as your 4x4, then emphasizing another method on much
larger matrices.
I don't think I understand the question.
Could you be more specific of the question fell craft says, is it
worth having code for producing a full rotation Matrix?
X y&z at once instead of multiplying three different matrices.
The answer there is, it might be because again, you could symbolically
multiply these three matrices together and just get the results of
that, rather than producing them separately in the multiplying them.
Again, the only
To do that.
Is if you care about the speed and in this case, we're only doing this
once.
So, the speed is irrelevant, right?
We're never going to care how fast that's being done.
But if you were doing it, you know, tens of thousands of times a frame
for some reason.
So not just for our camera but like all the objects were all doing it
and everything else.
Then you know that becomes a perhaps a more useful thing to do.
Of course at that point you also might really not be doing.
Like this is Euler angle rotation effectively.
It's important.
We want Euler angle rotation for the kind of thing that we're going to
be doing which is an orbit camera.
We actually want that.
But you know, for other things we may not be loyal, or angles have
problems that manifest.
Cells in it, depending on what you're doing using them for.
So you may not want to do rotation this way at all.
Anyway, right.
That's when you start getting to quaternions or other options for how
you might be handling your rotation anyway.
So there is co I'm inferring that those braces encompassing the four
rows in this Matrix operations isn't doing anything.
It isn't creating an extra dimension in The Matrix.
So what that's doing is just because I wasn't sure if we get an error
on partially bracketed initializer list from the C compiler.
If we didn't do it right because this is the E Matrix and so I feel
like it needs, it may need that.
If we did this I'm not sure if
Yet.
Yeah, right.
You're not allowed to do that in C.
You have to fully bracket your initializers.
That's why it's saying that that's one element, it's the E element and
these are sub elements of the element.
So that's just a it's just c, b and c.
Right.
More.
I mean, if that's a little confusing more specifically, it's because
we have a struct and the array is inside the struct, right?
So if we were to do this,
Now, you don't need them.
Right now, that's correct.
But since this is embedded in a struct, the outside.
Brackets are the struct brackets.
The inside brackets.
Are the E, array, brackets.
And these are the separate elements of e brackets, right?
And you need them all for see to be happy about the initializer.
Hopefully, that makes sense.
Tomorrow.
37.
Hi, Casey haven't caught a stream in a while.
How are things going?
Pretty good?
No complaints.
Pepe.
Well, don't you have to return to?
Oh yeah, probably did I just forget that?
Yeah, so one of the weird things, this is supposed to have returned
are here.
One of the weird things about visual Studios compiler and I guess this
is just a detail of the implementation of how it works.
Is that until you call a function?
It doesn't check to see whether that function has a return value.
So what you can see here is, I compile this and it works fine.
I remove the return value and it works.
Fine.
The reason for that is it's never getting multiplied.
It's never no one's ever using this function.
What we would have seen like you know, next week or whatever.
When I come through here, is that oops, Jim is that if I was to call
it.
So let's say I, you know, did projection times projection, right?
So I just I call it, I just call it.
Now we get the error.
Right.
And you can see it is going to find that for you.
So it's not like it would be a mystery, but it just doesn't happen
until you call it.
So I guess, like, what, whatever the stage is in the compiler, in
Microsoft's compiler, where it checks?
That return value, that, that return value exists, that stage only
happens once calling to the function occurs, and if the function is
never called it's eliminated before ever.
Checking
Turn value.
What's interesting is the rest of the areas you might have not true.
So for example, if I set a equals B
Here.
Oh well, maybe not.
Okay, so there we go.
I guess equals B would be automatically generated now, think about.
So obviously, that that's not an error.
So that's why.
So if I don't have some other things like I tried to do a plus
operator and it doesn't have the plus operator, like all the rest of
the errors you might have to that.
I can think of any way will be announced whether you call it or not.
But return value just for whatever reason just isn't one of them.
So the stage at which it checks for that error just
Ever occurs at the functions.
Never called.
so, that might
That might help and IMA sorry says it might be worth pointing out that
behavior that that behavior and MSU is specific to inline functions.
Are you sure?
But that's true.
I didn't know that actually that's news to me.
Let me change it.
Yeah, I don't I don't think that's true.
Yeah, so it's actually, it's only for external functions that that
happens.
And that's because at that point, the function is technically called,
right?
So, it doesn't have to be in line.
It just has to not be called.
And when a function is external has external linkage, the compiler has
to assume that somebody is calling it.
So that's essentially effectively a call, right?
If that makes sense.
So basically since all of our stuff we don't export any functions in
handmade hero, every function is internal to a single compilation unit
effectively.
All of our functions of obey.
This rule, we will never get a warning or an error from the compiler
about not returning a value ever.
If we don't call the function because all of our functions are in line
or internal basically.
And and so, you know,
If they're not called, they're not called.
Panda, might, I kind of just joined onto this channel, sorry about the
lack of the knowledge of the code so far.
But I was referring to the case of having such large matrices that you
would consider partitioning the matrices into separate parts for
quicker rotations, okay.
So, I think I understand the question and
I guess here's how I would phrase it so matrices are a very versatile
mathematical tool that can be used in a lot of ways 4 by 4 matrices
tend to be mostly full.
The only thing that's not full about them is sometimes the bottom row
remains at 0 0 1 for a long time, right?
Up until the projection matrices come in.
Right?
And so it's not uncommon for people to use 3 by 4 matrices or you know
three rows, four columns.
Everybody say that.
Because typically that bottom row is 0, 0 0, 1 right up, till the very
end
When projection actually does do some stuff down in there but the top
part is typically all filled with numbers.
So yeah it starts out looking like it's mostly not used but pretty
soon once you multiply this matrix by this Matrix now the upper 3x3
All filled with numbers, right?
And then when we add translation in these, three numbers will be
filled.
So, very quickly, you end up with the top three by four is filled with
actual data, so you're really not.
Wasting anything most of the time in the upper 3 by 4.
But like I said, people do treat the bottom part.
As 0001 fairly frequently are specifically because it does remain
empty.
Since we are not doing much work with these matrices, I will not make
that optimization because we don't care, but if you were using them
heavily, you probably would.
Now that's the answer for 4x4 matrices in.
Space.
What I would like to emphasize is that if you extend your thinking
about matrices out to generic linear algebra, the kinds of stuff
people do for large systems Solutions and things where you have
matrices that are tens of thousands of rows by tens of thousands of
columns.
Then you absolutely do exactly what you're talking about which is
partitioned them into parts that you can operate on more quickly, that
field of
Of research is called sparse Matrix operations and there's entire
fields of research dedicated to exploiting the structure of matrices
that have known locations.
And this is for, when you have matrices that, you know, are 30,000 by
30,000, but that have large parts of them are 0.
Right?
Because at that point, it just becomes prohibitively expensive not to
think about the empty space as empty space.
That doesn't need to be operated on
Bulbous, would it not be better to make the Matrix structure?
Use our 32 array of 16 elements instead of two of a two dimensional.
One in that we simply The Matrix operation.
So well again I don't really care about this speed.
These are going to be called only a few times a frame, so it's
irrelevant.
If you were worried about speed, yes, you would want to sort of
structure your matrices to be speed specific, but I would also caution
to say, you don't really know what that would look like.
-
Sara Lee until, you know, your data.
It may be that you would want to store your matrices in some kind of
structure of a raise style rather than array of structure style so
that you actually are considering the 0 0 element.
Like if you have 10,000 matrices, may be the zero, zero element of all
10,000.
Matrices is stored first, then the 0 1, element of all the matrices is
stored, second, you know, and so on, you don't know, it's going to
depend entirely on what your operations are, what the efficient.
To store your matrices as so optimization.
You can't just look at operations and say I'm going to optimize them,
you have to know what you're actually doing a lot of because the
format that you put your data in is going to be entirely dependent on
what you're doing.
Not on looking at operations and saying, how could I make this
operation more efficient?
Because you need to know is that the operation you're normally doing?
How is the data flowing into that?
Are you doing multiple Matrix multiplies that can be paralyzed at the
the same time or do you tend to do individual Matrix?
Multiply is right.
And you have to know that before you can efficiently optimize your
code.
You can't just look at a matrix by segment optimize this operation.
You don't know the context of that operation yet and knowing the
context is crucial to optimizing things and to knowing what you should
optimize
Team R&B forgive the dumb question, but why are your include guards to
find at the bottom of the header?
Instead of the top?
Is this purely?
What you chose to do?
Or is there another purpose pound if checked at the top?
But the pound of finds at the bottom, most kind of thing, does it at
the top?
So first of all, I thought we deleted.
All that.
Are those still in here?
Are you?
Where is the include guard?
That you're looking at.
So answer number one just is that there shouldn't be any include
guards anymore.
So if you're singing include guard, tell me where it is because there
shouldn't be any include guards.
And the reason for that is because we compiled as a single compilation
unit.
So include guards are meaningless.
We're never going to include a file twice so you don't need a pound
pragma for it or a Pam pragma once core and include guard or anything
else, right?
However, to answer the question that you're asking as opposed to
saying, why the question at this point is moot
It the question, you're asking why would somebody when they do put an
include Garden there?
Like I used to in the old days, why would you put the pound to find at
the bottom instead of the top or vice versa?
And the answer there is because I want to know if I've created an
include cycle.
And if I've created an include cycle that includes
L will get automatically broken and ignored if I put the defined at
the top, right?
But if I created include cycle and I put the pound of, at the bottom,
I'll get an infinite Loop error in the compiler.
And I'll know so that's just there, so that I could see that
happening, right?
Because I want to eliminate that I didn't want to have that, but
nowadays, I compile everything in single compilation units, always.
Anyway, so now include guards are relevant.
You
Need them, same with pregnant.
Once not, it's not necessary because it it doesn't do anything.
And yet, team R&B, even in the older streams, those things weren't
used ever.
It was just because I had my old emac config that I was using just
automatically inserted them.
Whenever I open an h-file, I never actually needed them.
So even back then they were irrelevant.
They just were like out anachronism that I never bother to change in
my emacs config.
So now I just one point during the stream, I was just like, I gotta
get rid of these.
I they're not in there for any particular reason.
So
rid of them so they were always irrelevant even the beginning because
we've always compiled its in a single compilation unit fashion, but
you know,
That was just because my emac config was from back in the days when I
didn't used to do that.
And I never have to because, you know, you can still have include
guards, right?
They don't just because they're not doing you any good you can still
put them in right so I didn't need to get rid of them.
It just event.
I was like sick of seeing them in there because I'm like these aren't
doing their wire there so I got rid of them.
All right.
Are you going here?
It's getting late.
I think I got all questions there.
Hopefully.
All right.
Thank you, everyone for joining me for another person, handmade here.
It's been a pleasure coding with you.
As always, hopefully, that gave you a pretty solid understanding of
the rotation Math and how it went into matrices and how many teachers
are multiplied together.
Next week, we will go ahead and look at why we want to multiply those
matrices together, why that works and will construct the rotation
stuff using the routines that we wrote this week in order to spin our
camera around, which is the reason that I kind of wanted to be able to
do that sort of stuff.
So, we'll go ahead and do that.
And that'll be able to grow our goal for next week, which I think we
should be able to do pretty cleanly.
That's about it for.
Now, again, if you want to follow along series at home, of course, you
can always pre-order the game on handmade hero to
Comes with all the source code.
I updated every night so that you can play around with the latest
build.
If you like we have a forum site, you can go to.
If you want to ask questions, we have a patreon page and go to if you
want to support the series.
And also that patreon, I used to a lot of the stuff that patreons is
dispersed out to people who support handmade hero like for example, a
lot of that money goes to paying for annotations or the the site that
hosts the forums, for example, that sort of stuff.
So we try to put that money back into the community as much as
possible.
There's also a schedule bot, which you can go to.
If you want to know when this is going to be live.
Typically on Friday night, it'll tweet out what the schedule is for
that weekend.
If you want to know, when the series going to be live and then we got
a past episodes guide, you can go to if you'd like to catch up on
episodes that you missed and that is about it.
I will be back here next week.
Again, to just sort of show how to do that rotation stuff that we were
how to put that into use and hopefully I will see everyone back here
for that until then.
Have fun programming this week and I'll see y'all on the internet.
Take it easy everybody and have a good week.