Started again.
So we have a nice clean one to post to the YouTube archive.
Hello everyone and welcome to the 11th day of handmade hero the series
where we code a complete professional quality game from scratch right
before your very eyes.
And we explained every last little bit of it.
For those of you want to follow along at home.
You will know everything that goes into it and why.
Now, we have some exciting news.
There's a little bit of a caveat to the news.
We have some exciting news people have been asking.
For a forums and official forums where they can post things and
discuss stuff with other members Community.
It is finally ready.
I won't say that.
It's good yet.
My web skills are blow.
I am not a web programmer.
And I also tend to get very frustrated anytime.
I do anything with the web and there's a lot of cursing and this sort
of thing and so I can't promise you that this site is going to be
great overnight.
It'll probably take a while to air at The Kinks, but if you go to
handmade hero dot Oregon, hit the old.
Key to refresh it.
You will notice that the link that used to say email a question where
you just had to send it directly to me.
Now actually, has a news and forums button that you can click on and
when you go there, you will go to this little handmade hero Central
thing.
And it's got a little news that shows you like the schedule.
Now, that's up there.
So if you want to know what the schedule going to be for the week, you
can get to that.
There's an episode guide that was put together by some awesome folks.
Jason Bennett Abner, climb, Brea, Matthew, vandevander, Gustavo,
Chavez.
I don't know how to pronounce their names correctly.
So I apologize for that.
These are people that I only know over the Internet.
I've never heard them even say their name.
That is how nice they are.
They put this together for you.
And this is pretty awesome.
You should.
Check out the work they've done.
It's amazing.
You can jump to one of these.
One of these things that one of the videos from a day and they've made
the stuff where they put notes in here when there's notes for the
stream, but they put basically like time coded information where you
can just click on the thing.
You want to know and it jumps to where it is in the Stream.
So it's pretty amazing.
The episode guide.
Amazing.
They've done some amazing work there, and I cannot thank them enough
for that.
And then, of course, there's a coding resources section that you've
got that we're going to be putting stuff in, like, recommendations
from people.
And like, if you want to know how to get things running on Linux, for
example, David GAO has put together an awesome guide for that complete
with source code.
And then finally, there's code discussion that you can click on and it
is a full-on old school web forum, and I'll be trying to clean up some
of this.
It's a little messy right now, but hopefully that'll give something.
Get people being able to use something.
And in the short term while we try to clean things up a bit.
So that is all the news.
I hope that you find that to be usable.
And if you if you don't, please post in the forums and we can discuss
maybe changes.
We can make a, I'll do the best I can.
Like I said, I'm not a web guy, but I'll do the best I can.
Last but not least, we have changed so that the pre-order button now,
goes to stripe as well.
A lot of people were having trouble with PayPal.
I guess.
I didn't realize how much better stripe was than PayPal.
It's much better experience to.
I tried it out.
It's, it's way better.
You can still use PayPal if you
But that changes.
Well, so we did a bunch of work on the website.
Thank you to everyone who contributed that it's been awesome.
And and that is, you know, hopefully it hopefully it'll all go.
Well, please let us know if you have any trouble with it and we'll,
we'll do the best we can.
So that's it for the preamble to the stream.
Welcome back everyone.
I hope you had a good Thanksgiving.
If you're the if you're in a part of the world that celebrates that if
not, I just hope you're having a good, I guess a good beginning of
December.
Let's say,
Tonight we have a very interesting topic to talk about a very
important topic to talk about and that is that up until now we have
basically been doing everything in Windows.
We have been essentially getting ourselves into position.
If we go into our handmade directory here, we can see that in our code
directory.
All we have is a win32 handmade.
And if you remember, I prefix it with win32 because this is win32
code.
One of the things that I like to do and this is very germane to the
topic today, which is starting to get things into
Cross-platform setup is basically I like to make it extraordinarily
clear where the platform-specific code lives and where the platform
independent code lives.
And so I right from the beginning, when we did this made sure that I
specified, that, that was a win32 underscore handmade because I like
to underscore each particular thing with the platform that it is made
to go on.
So if there's no underscore platform identify at the beginning of it,
that means that it's generic code that should compile on everything
and if there is
A platform-specific prefix to it.
Then that means it is only for that platform.
And one of the things that this allows you to do very quickly is for
anyone who's trying to Port it.
They immediately know exactly what they have to do.
They can just do it, you know, der win32 star kind of a thing and they
can see immediately exactly all the files that they're going to have
to port for their operating system.
And that's a big help to anyone if you've ever actually ported
something to a new platform before.
You know, that just figuring out what you have to Port is a huge step.
And if you, if the
Some can set you up for Success there.
That's a, that's a big deal.
But point being, we do not have any platform nonspecific codes.
The moment.
We were only working on getting a bootstrap up and running.
So the first thing I want to do is just talk a little bit about what
is in this win32 file.
What we are going to do with it where it is going to go.
Just to kind of give people a little bit of a little bit of kind of a
heads up as to what to expect.
Because I've seen a lot of people who've done things with the win32
platform layer.
And I've been talking about things of the win32 platform where I want
to make sure that people don't have the wrong expectations for the
code that is in
In there right now, so I'm actually going to slap a to do at the top
of this.
Just so people know exactly what's going on here.
It's my keyboard is a little off center.
That is not going to happen.
That is not going to stand right.
There we go.
Let's see.
This is not a final platform layer.
And basically, what people need to realize is what we have done with
our win32 platform layer, and this.
By Design is a basically.
I just wrote the bare minimum stuff in here that we were going to need
in order to get ourselves off of win32 in order to make sure that we
basically don't have to think about Windows Much Anymore going
forwards.
So I focused on the simplest possible thing we could do for
educational purposes, which was getting a sound buffer up that we
could write directly into a graphics buffer up that we could write
directly into and rudimentary input coming in from a Gamepad and
keyboard.
Because that is mostly what we need.
There's one other thing that will need which is file I/O, but I saved
That for this week for reasons that you'll see a little later.
But what that means is I do not know and one of the thing which was
timing knowing how long things take and we did that as well.
So the thing that I want to impress upon you though just before we go.
Any further is, this is not a platform layer that you would ship and
anyone who was, you know, going crazy in the YouTube comments.
Oh my God, he's doing this or he doesn't understand that everyone can
just relax a little bit.
I would not ship this as a win32 platform layer either at all, in any
by any stretch of the imagination, but that is not what it is for
later on in the series.
Is when we start doing work on getting the game shippable, when we
start doing that polishing, work that we need to do to get the game
shippable that is when we will be concentrating on the correct way to
do everything in a win32 platform, layer for maximum compatibility
maximum performance, things like that.
But right now our goals are different.
Our goals are understanding and education right now.
And so the last thing we want to do is spend a ton of time.
Going here are the eight thousand things you have to do in order to do
thing, X on Windows properly because really that just
Obscures the real point of this series which is the educational
process.
So win32 platform stuff, we will get to later but that is not the goal
right now.
And so I want to make sure everyone understands that and doesn't read
too much in to the platform layer code as it is right now.
So I'm going to write in a big to-do list and just kind of say the
stuff that later on we'll probably be doing.
Just so you have an idea of exactly how much stuff we will actually
have to go and tighten down when we finally my ship this so that you
have no Illusions about that.
So, saved game locations is one.
sample, so that's basically like if we have state that we want to save
and we will
Where does that go?
We have to interface with Windows to find out where that goes getting
a handle to our own executable file, our own executable file.
That is something we'll have to do through this layer.
We need the asset loading path.
So we got to know where our assets are going to come from.
We basically have to have threading multi-threading.
So how to launch a thread.
We don't have anything like that, right now.
We've only got one thread.
So if our game wanted to have more than one thread, it couldn't do
that right now, so we're going to need that as well.
We are going to need raw input.
Probably, we would like to do some things with raw input support,
multiple keyboards that sort of thing.
Support groups support for multiple keyboards.
There we go.
And it, my keyword is not aligned properly.
You got to get that alignment or you can't get the speed.
You got to get your hands and just the right place.
You know what I'm saying?
All right.
Anyway, we have to do.
Sleep and time begin period in order to make sure that on laptops and
other sorts of circumstances.
We do not melt the processor down by using all available cycles and
basically burn through the person's battery, clip cursor, for
multi-monitor multi-monitor support because basically right now if we
were to go fullscreen, oh and I should put full screen support as
well.
If we were to go full screen, people could move the cursor outside the
window and it would be weird even though we're not getting the mouse
and that sort of stuff.
Let's see here.
We want to be able to do WM set cursor as well, so that we basically
control the cursor visibility.
There we go.
We are going to want to do, query, cancel, auto play, assuming that
that even still works anymore.
But something that we probably should do at least for the old days.
WM activate app for when we are not the active application.
That's a good thing to do.
We are going to need to do Blitz.
Improvements possibly using bit blit.
We are going to want Hardware acceleration.
So opengl or direct3d or both potentially who knows we could get
totally crazy depending on how things are going.
And finally, we may want to do some stuff with get keyboard layout for
French keyboards.
Was the basically International wasde and that sort of stuff
international wasde support.
And that is just a partial list of stuff.
So basically that is something to keep in mind.
So hopefully that just gives you an idea of how much stuff we actually
have to do when we really want to get things into complete shipping
State and we don't need to worry about most of these things for a long
time, but it's just worth noting that you should understand.
What we are doing.
Here is just a very simple layer designed to get us up and running so
we can develop the game and then later as we go we may Implement some
of these when we need them.
If
Actually need them to do stuff, very specifically beforehand.
We need to do that.
But we also will do them at the end when we're actually just doing
ship testing and retesting on machines and seeing, okay.
This didn't work here.
Make sure we support this there that sort of thing.
Okay.
So now that I've got that out of the way and you understand what's
going on in this win32, handmade file, the main topic for today.
The main topic for Monday is basically how to architect code properly.
So that it is cropped as easy to make cross-platform as possible.
So basically what we're looking to do here is we're looking to make it
so that the majority of the code that we write for this project, as
much of the code is possible, will be simple for anyone including
myself, but anyone who wants to to get running on another platform
optimally.
So basically there's two goals there.
There's just, there's just the getting it running at all on another
platform.
So we wrote it on Windows.
We want to get it running on Linux.
We wrote it on Windows.
We want to pour it to Raspberry Pi.
Or something like that, right?
Whatever.
We want to Port it to.
There's just the act of getting it working and we want to make that be
as easy as possible.
But then we also have to think about the act of making it optimal on
those platforms.
Meaning, the amount of work that that person is going to have to do,
and optimal is probably the wrong term.
No piece of code is ever optimal for real, but basically getting it to
the point where its performance, where it runs at a reasonable frame
rate for what one, might expect the game to run on on that platform.
So if the platform should be able to run the game at 60 frames a
And but there's a bunch of stuff with a platform that will have to
happen in order to enable that order to make that work.
What we need to do is say how easy are we making it for that person
who has to do that Port?
How easy are we making them making their lives at that time?
And now in this case, it's going to be us we're going to be doing a
lot of those ports.
So it's really saying how easy we're going to make our lives.
But in general when you're working on stuff like this, it is typical
that you will not be the person.
Perhaps it's doing all the porting work for something that you work
on.
So really you're kind of trying to keep
Other person in mind that some sense you're saying what will the
people who come along here and Port?
This other platforms?
What will they have to do?
How easy?
Will it be for them to do their job?
Will it be for them to maintain that Port, where you update your
version of the source.
Does that going to require a whole rewrite for them?
What's going to mean, right?
So those are all the things that I want to put in your head things
that you want to think about.
And we're going to talk about ways of making that easier and harder
today.
So that you can see why certain decisions cause problems and why you
shouldn't make those decisions.
And instead prefer things.
That are going to be a little easier.
Okay.
So, the first thing that I'd like to say or write really like to
introduce you to, if you haven't seen it before, is how people in
general, used to make code be cross-platform, and I shouldn't say,
people in general, I should say maybe the most prevalent way in the
old days.
So the most prevalent way in the old days is you would have a file and
that file would be doing something like our win32 handmade would be
doing.
And there would be something like the code for opening a window.
So, if you
Look at the code for opening a window here.
You can basically see that we have some stuff that we had to do in
order to get that to happen.
It was right here.
Now, the way that people used to do porting to various platforms
before is that you say, well, okay, when I need to do stuff, I'll
start at the beginning here and I'll say, well, you know, I'll use the
preprocessor.
And now, of course it, for those of you that don't know, because we
haven't talked about it, much in C.
And C++.
There is a preprocessor and what that preprocessor does allow you to
do along with the one thing that we have been sort of using it for in
the past.
Last pound, including pound to find which we've seen, it allows us to
do pound, if statements and the pound.
If statements can take two forms that are kind of equivalent to some
degree, but they can take different forms.
Basically, what we're allowed to do is say pound if and then some
pre-processor expression, like for example, pound if is running on
win32, and basically, what it'll do is it'll execute the stuff in
here, stuff in here.
Happens when that thing is 1 or sorry, not 0 and stuff in here happens
when it is 0 or undefined basically, so what this allows you to do is
define basically sort of macro variables which control certain ports
of the compilation so that you can knock Parts out when you're on
certain platforms and bring other parts in when you're on certain
platforms.
And so, what a lot of people would do is they would Define some kind
of variable, typically
It would be something like that because I believe that was the visual
C.
Standard was basically underscore win32 or something like this.
But, you know, it could be whatever.
Maybe we'd have our own for example, like handmade win32 and we
probably will do something like that for other reasons in a second.
But basically what they do is they'd have a defined like that and then
inside the code you would basically bracket the things that did not
work and provide Alternatives.
So when main obviously would not work on Linux, but you know, what
would work on Linux?
It would work if you were to do something.
Like this, right?
This is the way that you would introduce that function in Linux.
So something that you would see a lot of times is basically this kind
of pouring, you say that a little bit odd.
They're basically what you see is something like this.
And when you would compile this, if you are running on win32, it would
put in the wind man.
That looks like this.
And if you were compiling on Linux, let's say it would put it in here,
and these could even stack on top of each other.
There's an L.
If basically, which could do something like this, and then we could
do, you know another one down here for a different platform.
Handmade Mac, right?
These sorts of things.
I don't know.
It's probably the same on Mac.
Honestly, I don't quite remember, but well actually on Mac you got
you, you want to be in Cocoa.
So it's actually an Objective C and this sort of stuff.
But point being, you would see, you know, maybe Raspberry Pi or
whatever and stuff.
Like that point being is you would see a bunch of stuff like this.
And basically, what you would do is in each one of these slots
everywhere in the code.
You would go in and slut in the thing that you want to have happen.
Okay.
So basically, let's say that we had done something like that.
We've done something like this and now
Now we've got something that's going to have the correct introduction
for whichever platform.
You would have, then what you would do is you would go into your build
up batch file and in here, you would basically use what's called a
compiler time, you know, like a compile time pound to fine.
And the compiler basically allows you to do that.
You can specify minus D and then you can put the thing you wanted to
find what you wanted to find it to in a syntax.
It looks like this - the handmade win32 equals 1 means that.
Now, I'm injecting that pound to find so that anything in the code
that does this kind of an F.
It will get back a true essentially, so it will actually do this line.
So if I do this compile, yes, I would like to say that build up at if
I do this compile, you will see that it works on the other hand, if I
was saying for
Some reason that we were compiling in some other thing.
Let's say, I said, we were compiling and Linux or something you would
notice that we would get an error essentially because it's going to
actually use this other definition.
So it's now it's just a regular function and there's no each instance
and all the rest.
Code doesn't work right?
But you can see the basic trick here is, this is what you do and you
would continue this process to Port the whole function you'd pound if
all the windows code and put else's around it, so that you could
inject, whatever the correct calls were on Linux.
Hopefully that makes pretty intuitive sense to you.
It's not very complicated, right?
It's a pretty basic thing to want to do there.
Really isn't a lot going on there.
That's that's, that's confusing.
So I'm going to go ahead and change it back to our other pound to find
so we can see.
See that this thing works properly, you know, exactly why because we
may want to use that ahead in the future and so on.
So that is how you'd you'd have done it way back in the past.
I remember reading through like the canoe make source code back in
1996 or something and it's just all all over the place this sort of
thing, right?
It all the code has multiple paths.
Now.
The reason that I do not recommend writing code this way and we will
use a limited.
I'll show you a very specific place where I do think that this comes
in handy, so I'm not saying
Never do it, but I am saying, think long and hard about doing this
sort of thing.
The reason for it is because first of all it it does.
Cause a problem for exactly what I was.
I said at the very beginning of the podcast.
I'm sorry.
Thank you.
Can do this video cast.
I guess.
This is not a podcast.
I don't think with an iPod could be listening to it.
The very beginning of this video.
Guess what?
I basically said was, we're trying to make the job very easy for the
people who have to pour it in the future.
And if what they have to do is go through all.
All the code looking for all of the places where we used win32 code
and pound iffing around them like that.
And we just scatter the code everywhere and just do the pound.
If that creates a pretty big problem, right there.
It's just annoying.
You can't see where they are up front.
You don't even know where all the code is.
It's a learning process just for the person, even figure out what was
going on.
And it forces them kind of into this mindset of.
All right.
I got to go.
Look at these other sort of if statements and see what each path was
doing and whatever.
So that's thing one.
Thing too.
Is that the code quickly becomes very difficult for anyone to read
without, basically, the benefit of a cup of a editor that collapses
them.
Because if you imagine in here, we have this sort of nonsense going on
all the time, right?
And remember, it's not just that, it's everything.
It's every platform that this thing will ever be pointed to, right.
We've got all this sort of garbage going on, right?
Then pretty soon.
You're basically starting to require write a development environment.
Ain't that can understand these ifs and know which ones you have set
and show you only the selective code because otherwise you're never
going to be able to read this code.
You're only going to see one line of each function of the time because
the whole page is going to be taken up with this kind of stuff and
that's just inconvenient right there.
And it's a hard probability like, emacs.
If you do a bunch of stuff does actually do that.
It's kind of a pain.
So I don't do it but a lot of editors don't do it at all.
There's there's a number of reasons why you don't want to voice out on
someone.
You're basically putting a hard requirement on their editor.
And I'd rather not do that for such a small thing.
But those two things, the first, the second one are small compared to
the third one.
the third one, I saved the best for last, you know, I would do it and
I did the real reason that you never write code like this unless you
absolutely have to
Is because it dictates the control flow must be equivalent across all
platforms.
Okay.
I'm going to say that again.
Just so, you know what I mean?
And I'm going to be example, if you do cross-platform code, this way,
it means that the control flow of your program is shared across all
the platforms that you will ever ship on.
Now.
What do I mean by that?
Well, what I mean is, if I'm going to go through here and henpeck out
lines of
Would like I was doing then essentially what we have is the same set
of functions and the same set of if statements the same set of while
loops and we have just started inserting very insidiously, different
Escape mechanisms, Escape hatches, if you will for each platform to go
in actually do the thing that they wanted to do at the time that they
needed to do it, right?
That is very, very problematic.
When you start talking about platforms that are very different in the
way that they expect initialization and and platform services to work.
So for example, let's say on one platform in order to load resources
asynchronously.
So I want to basically have background streaming in my game.
I want to load bitmaps out of my resource file and I want to do that.
While the game is running.
I don't want to stop the game.
I want to happen continuously.
So there's no
In screen on one platform, maybe that's best accomplished with a
separate thread on another platform.
Maybe that's best accomplished with overlapped IO, who knows?
Maybe it's best accomplished with memory mapped files on one platform.
Each one of these things may dictate a very different structure for
how the game starts up, how it continues running, how it handles,
things, like messages that come in from the, from the operating
system.
All those sorts of things.
And so what I would like to impress upon you and this comes from many
many years of shipping cross-platform code.
I guess this point is 20 years of shipping code that always had to run
everywhere is that that just it's just a very inefficient way to try
and do the coding the much.
Much better way is the way that I'm going to show you now, so I would
highly recommend not doing this this method of coding.
I'm going to show you two more methods for the rest of the
Here.
And I would highly recommend.
Unless for some reason you really love what I just showed you, you
really loved this right here.
I would highly recommend not using that method as a method of
programming and stepped in one specific instance that I will show you
in a minute.
Okay.
So what are the better ways to do this?
Well, I've already set us up for success with one of the ways.
This is common.
I shouldn't say one of the ways, basically, the way that is common
between the two methods that I'm going to talk about next.
What I did was I call this win32 handmade dot CPP and my expectation
is that somebody else will come along at some point and create Linux
handmade dot CPP, right?
That's someone's going to be me.
But, you know, like I said, in a more larger project, it would
probably be the platform expert for Linux.
Whoever is job.
It is to make that be running.
Now, the way that this will work then right, is that the win32
specific code will go into these files that are marked with 32 and
there might be more than one doesn't just have to be one multiple.
Within three to underscore our and all of the Linux code will go into
Linux underscore files.
Now, the way will work the way it will work from there on is, we will
create a single shared header file that will be called handmade .h,
right?
And this single shared header file will basically include the
operations that the platform layer is supposed to be able to perform
on behalf of our cross-platform code.
Right, it will create basically an API in this, it'll sort of, create
our own platform, abstraction API in this header file and all of our
platform non specific code will call into this way.
So basically we, let's say, have something where we want to load a
file.
We will type something like load file, right?
And there's a name for the file.
I'd at this is not the actual API, we will use.
But let's say we have that, we will call this load file.
And often times, I like to do is call it platform load file, so that
we
That we're asking the platform for something.
They people who get prefixed right?
There will be one definition of that here.
Right?
And it'll do the load.
I guess.
It's got to actually return something, probably, blah, blah, blah.
But anyway, you get my idea.
There is a platform API here.
Then what happens is that API exists both here right inside the Linux
version.
And so in the Linux file, right, I would do, you know, this implements
the Linux file loading, right?
And then in the win32 version, I would do the same thing.
Right, I would basically have this for the win32 version here.
Okay.
So all that happens, now is when we're actually writing platform
nonspecific codes.
So, let's say we are in handmade dot CPP, right?
I open up my handmade that sleepy.
No, I do not want that.
I want that.
There we go.
In handmade dot CPP.
I've got some stuff.
I don't know what function this is, but I want to load a file and I
don't want this code to be relying on windows.
So they don't want any more of the code that we ever right to be
relying on Windows.
I want it to be
Lately.
Cross-platform.
I am just going to call platform load file with the filename, right?
I'm going to ask it to load that and it's going to give me back the
file.
Contents like that.
Okay, and this is the structure that we are going to use from now on.
So if you imagine, this is our main Loop or something.
I don't know exactly what it is.
This is how how that goes.
Then.
What I'm going to do is I'm just going to call into that from the
platform layer.
So once we have started things going right, once Things Are
Thing I am going to call in here when we're actually up.
I don't know where we're going to clean up this thing in a second
here.
But so after we do, you know, whatever therefore sound before?
Who knows.
We're going to call this main Loop thing, right?
We're gonna call it from in here.
Okay, and I have to obviously include this file.
So, let's do that here as well.
You too, dude, this is something I'll talk about in one second as
well.
Handmade dot CPP and I will go ahead and go.
Include handmade .h, hear that.
And I will compile.
Okay, so in here, we have to actually pretend that we implemented that
at least a little.
So now what I want to show you is basically I'm going to talk a little
bit.
Actually we talked at length about what I just did there, but in the
interim just before I go into that, I'm going to show you exactly what
I mean now so you can be 100% clear on that.
So basically, what's going to happen is we start off in the platform
specific layer, right?
The platform's of thick layer is still controlling.
Like it was when we were Windows, only, it does all of the Windows
startup stuff that it was going to do, right?
It does the same things, but then when it's ready to actually do game
work, right?
When it's ready to do game work.
It calls into the platform nonspecific layer of our code where all the
rest of our code will live.
Basically, from now on then, whenever it gets to the point where it
needs a platform service.
Again, when it needs to do something that only the platform knows how
to do file IO.
So, Network IO, Graphics, display, whatever it happens to be.
Then it is going to go ahead and call out right, that call out, then
goes right back in to the platform layer, that platform layer Fields.
The call, does the windows Pacific Linux specific Mac specific thing
here, whatever that happens to be returns back and things continue as
normal, okay?
Now, I said I was gonna talk about two ways right now.
I'm talking about just the basics that is going to be shared between
both ways.
This is, I would argue the more common more modern way of doing
cross-platform code.
I don't think a lot of people advocate for doing the first method that
I talked about anymore.
I don't think you would see a lot of people strenuously arguing that.
No, it's better to have all these if desk throughout the code.
I think this what I said right there would be relatively
uncontroversial.
You never know programming things somehow.
To be controversial even when you think they wouldn't be.
But I suspect you would not get a lot of people going.
No, you need pound.
If dust everywhere.
That's fantastic.
So now we get to the two possible ways of using the technique of I
just described, which creates sort of two different philosophical
camps for how the platform code should be written.
I fall into the latter Camp.
I think most people fall into the former Camp.
So I am not going to tell you that one of these is wrong and one of
these is right.
I am going to tell you which one I prefer and why, but I would
recommend that you
You think about them yourself?
Try them yourself?
If you don't have experience with them and decide for yourself, which
one you would like better and do that one because I do not have any
idea.
It is not an ideological war with me.
I am not going to go 50 rounds.
With someone telling them one is better when it's worth.
I'd you can just tell you which one that I prefer and then you should
make up your own mind about which one you prefer.
So first before I go into those two, I'm going to tell you a little
bit what I did with the build here because it's a little crazy and I
realized that this is
Thing that will be highly controversial, I guarantee you, but again,
not even arguing for it.
Just telling you how it's how I code.
Normally the way people like to do build environments is when you have
more than one file, which you almost always, do you start adding those
files to this CL line here.
And now, most people actually have a, much more complicated build
system than this.
So actually what they do is they have like a whole make system that
lists a bunch of files and then figures out what their dependencies
are and which ones have to be rebuilt and then call CL multiple times
once for each file, that's we built our all.
These are the sorts of things.
Many, many, many, many, many different things you could go.
You can spend forever looking at build environments.
If you are interested in build environments, I recommend that you do.
So it will not be something I ever cover on the stream.
So there you go.
You can go do that on your own.
So that is what would normally happen.
Even if you were using a minimal build process, you would often come
in here and add handmade dot CPP onto the build line and you can pile
up that way.
I don't like to do that.
I find that that just basically takes longer to compile.
So what I do instead is I do something that a lot of people.
All the unity build and it's a little confusing because it has nothing
to do with unity.
The game engine, which is what people probably think of when they hear
Unity build.
But actually what I am talking about is the concept that you just only
have one conceptual translation unit in your entire project.
And what that means is basically, win32 handmade is the only file you
will ever compiled on win32 and Linux underscore, handmade dot CPP is
the only file you'll ever compiled on Linux reasons that I like this.
I like
I like it because it means getting the build working on a new platform
is absolutely as dumb.
Simple as possible.
You literally type the compiler and the platform file name.
And it builds.
That's it.
There's like nothing else that can go wrong.
I mean, sometimes if you require these sort of things like I did here
and you don't try to do automatic determination of the platform.
Then you have to be able to do that.
That is really about it.
I like how dumb simple that is.
I like how it means that you won't spend any time fussing with your
build environment.
The other reason that I like it is, it means you never have to
forward, declare anything.
If you don't want to H, files are largely optional at this point
because since everything is in the same translation unit, basically,
if you
Just stack things up in the order that you expect to call them.
It kind of just works and you can get rid of all the duplicate typing
that you have to type for, for declarations.
It's a minor benefit, but it helps the other thing that I seem to
notice about it, is, it is crazy fast compared to how long it takes.
Compile things not doing it this way.
I feel like there's just a lot of startup time for the compiler, a lot
of overhead and including things.
I don't know.
I don't pretend to know the reasons for that because I've never worked
on a commercial compiler.
So I couldn't tell you but all I know is it is a lot faster to compile
a single-file than it is compiled.
Lots of files that just seems to be the case and I have not found a
situation so far where that hasn't been the case.
So you get a speed win too and I'm all for that.
So, that is what I did right here.
Instead of doing basically putting handmade in here.
I stuck it in here.
If we're going to be getting a little more formal with how we do that,
but for now, that's really all we need to do.
And so that is pretty much how you would set up the build for now and
forever.
That's really the end of it.
That is how I will be doing it pretty much till the end of the
project, I suspect.
Okay, so let's talk about the two philosophical branches.
We can go down and I'll tell you the one, I'm going to be going down
so that you understand the differences in can see them.
All right.
So one way and I'll start with with the way that I think is more
prevalent today so that you can understand the way that most people I
think do this.
So, one way to do the cross-platform code is basically to virtualize
the operating system out.
To the game.
Now, what do I mean by that?
What I mean by that is that instead of thinking as the game as sort of
an isolated entity and that the platform code is working with the game
or any of these sorts of things.
Instead.
What you're thinking of is just literally abstracting the literal
operation, the specific operation of the platform, abstracting that
into a virtual set of calls that your game can call as if it was
running.
Being on a that virtual operating system.
So what that normally looks like is after you enter win main, for
example, you will call gain main, right?
Well, you won't call that way, but you'll call Game Main.
And then, inside handmade dot CPP, you will have game main.
Okay, and then, what will happen in game main is, you will start
calling the platform layer to do various things platform layer open
window, and you will tell it to open a window for you and you will get
back a platform window.
Like this kind of a thing.
Okay, you will then say platform layer open sound device or something
like this, open the sound device.
Right?
And you will get back a sound device and I'm making these names up,
but this is basically it.
You will then go through and essentially do all of the startup code
that you would normally do for an operating system.
If you are writing in that operating system directly, but instead of
ever actually calling an actual operating system and asking it for
something.
Instead.
You are always calling a virtual operating system that you have made
up in your head, right?
And defined in some H file and then it is
Is doing the work behind the scenes necessary to?
Do all the stuff on actual Windows, actual Linux, actual Mac, OS, X,
right?
You're actually calling all of those things and it's doing the work
behind the scenes to make it appear as if you were running on this
magical operating system at the end.
You would have game, shut down and game.
Shutdown will do the same things.
It will do.
Platform close window, right, that sort of stuff.
I don't know why I was calling this platform layer.
That's not what I said.
It would do.
You will be doing things like this, right?
You will call platform close.
Device, right?
And hopefully this is all pretty understandable.
What this would be doing.
Basically, if you look back at our win32 handmade, you can always sort
of see what would happen.
This platform open window call.
We would go in here and we would take this code.
Write this code here that opens a window, we would extract that code,
we would put it inside the platform.
Open window call.
We would take the H wind, we would wrap that in this platform windows
struct, make it opaque.
And then, basically, we would have a
This version of all the things that we did in win32, handmade dot CPP,
make sense.
It's very straightforward to do.
I don't think you would run into a lot of problems.
If you want to try this yourself.
I feel like, you know, there isn't a lot of nuance to it.
It's fairly straightforward.
So if you want to try that and that way sounds attractive to you, then
you can go and give that a shot.
Like I said, I do not want to be ideological about it.
So I would not say, don't do that.
If that seems like the way that you would like to do it.
You should give it a try and it should be fairly straightforward.
It's
Actly.
What I just said, you take all of the things that you're going to do
and you abstract them.
Now.
I'll give you a little hint in case you want to do this.
Since I won't be spending a lot of time talking about that method
because we're not going to use it.
You may ask, how do you return the opaque stuff?
Right?
How do you do this platform window thing?
Well, the way that you do that is actually pretty straightforward.
You can do something like this inside, inside handmade outage, right?
You can call.
In fact, I'll just I'll just go ahead and do one of these for you just
so you can see.
Because it's like I said, if you want if you end up feeling more
comfortable with this method,
I highly encourage you to do that.
You should always program in the idiom that feels most comfortable to
you.
You should not programming away.
Just because I said, so or somebody else on the web said so that's a
poor reason to choose a particular way.
So just in case you want to pick this method, I'm going to show you
how to do a couple things in it.
I think that's a good idea.
That way people will be set up for Success if they choose to go that
route and don't have any experience with this.
Okay.
So if we were to do this and we want to do the open window thing,
right?
We would do something like this, we would declare a struct.
But we wouldn't say how it is.
So we basically just do a declaration.
We would never Define The Struck.
We would just declare it outside.
Here.
I'm gonna get rid of the platform load file because that doesn't
actually exist anymore.
We're that that was just my example there.
So we're going to say platform open window and you know, maybe it
passes.
Let's say the title 22 the window that it wants to open.
I don't know what it's gonna pass here.
But other stuff right whatever you wanted.
Maybe you want the dimensions to pass whatever you think you want to
pass their you pass.
Okay, and then I have another thing which is closed platform.
Window.
And that's going to take that same window handle, right, that same
window, handle, and it's going to close the window.
So what we do then is inside wind inside our Windows platform layer
here, right?
We would Implement those by first defining, the platform window in
Because one of the interesting things that you have to remember is the
win32 code is only going to be compiled on win32.
And the Linux code is only going to be compiled on Linux.
That means we can actually have two different definitions for platform
window.
We can have two totally different definitions for platform window that
don't actually have to be the same, so we can in our platform window
here, right?
We can store the H win handle, right?
This is the, the handle and inside our Linux one, right in.
Our Linux one.
We do exactly the same stuff.
Right?
But instead we would do whatever the X thing is here.
I don't remember, but I think its capital window or something like
this, right?
That's like, you know what?
I think it's that
I could be wrong.
In fact, on X.
You may not even be able to do some of these things.
You may not even be able use Windows.
I think they do some crazy stuff like that.
I'm not sure.
I don't remember.
I wrote my ex platform code a while back and having looked at it
since.
But point being there's something that goes here, right?
And it's whatever the x windows platform handle is.
So this is the X Windows window, type would go right there, right?
So then you just put the code in there, right?
You create a new one of these, right?
So you're going to have to allocate it, right?
Whether with malloc or whatever you want to use for allocation, will
be talking about allocations a lot and I'll show you how I want to do
them.
But however you want to do your allocations is fine.
So you allocate it here, right?
And you make one of these things, this is the result, you then do all
this code that you were going to do.
And the create window, you know, this equals the handle equals the
result of create window here, right?
And then you just return
That okay?
And then in here when you get a new one in, you've just look, is it
valid?
If it is valid you would do your clothes window right on it or
whatever you'd ask window to do it and that'd be it.
So it's really really straightforward.
If you do want to do this.
Basically, you just wrap up the types in your own opaque handle in
your platform nonspecific part.
You just don't tell them what it is.
You don't let them know at all.
You haven't?
They have no idea.
So they can't accidentally use it and start creating platform
dependent code.
And then on each platform, you define.
Version of that struck that encapsulates, the things that you need and
you're done and that's all there is to it.
It's really nothing more complicated than that.
So hopefully that makes some sense.
We're not going to do that.
But if you did want to do that, then you would be Off to the Races.
So, you know, you're you're good to go with that point.
So, let me make sure we're back to normal here, trying to get rid of
some of this stuff so that I don't leave old demo code around, get rid
of that, get rid of that.
And now we are back to square one.
I believe.
Let's just verify that we are back to square one.
We're still running, right?
Everyone is
Fee.
They assume.
Yes.
It does appear to be.
Why is that?
What?
Why are we going nuts?
There?
That is not a good dead zone at all.
Why are we scrolling like that?
Oh, does it, does it look like that's what's going on.
Did you see how crazy that was scrolling?
What was going on there?
Yeah.
It looks like it looks like the controller just wasn't initialized
yet.
So it was giving back some, craving it with sudo initialize.
I don't know.
It's kind of weird how these xinput joysticks behave when we get to
Windows shipping code.
I wonder if we'll have to do some stuff there.
Or if my if my maybe just cause we haven't implemented, any dead zone
handling or something.
I don't know.
Maybe it's nothing to concern about but it was a little wonky point
being we don't need to care about that.
The moment though.
All right, so hopefully that all made some good sense.
And if you would like to go out and Implement your platform layer that
way, hopefully you can kind of see how that would happen.
It's really not that complicated to do.
You just start going?
Okay?
I don't actually like doing things that way, the reason that I don't
like doing the things that way is that it is a more expressive
interface to me than necessary.
And what do I mean by that?
Well, an operating system is designed to do all sorts of things.
It's designed for applications that want more than one window.
It's designed for applications that don't want a window.
It's designed for applications that will open windows closed, windows
open, Windows, and close windows again, open windows.
Again, it's designed for applications that show up in the start menu
that appear in this task bar, that do all sorts of things.
Like use the component object model and why the old embed themselves
in other applications.
And use habla, clue object, linking and embedding register themselves
in the registry integrated into the shell and operating.
Supports a huge amount of flexibility.
And one could argue that that's fine.
We don't need to criticize the operating system for doing that.
Maybe that's the operating systems job, but when it comes to a game,
we do have to ask ourselves.
Do we need that?
Flexibility?
Is our game going to be opening multiple windows is our game going to
need to open and close windows open and close them open and close them
open and close them of its own volition, right?
Not even response to an operating system message where we could just
handle it in the operating system layer, but does the game need to
know that those things ever happened?
Does our game need to even know what a window is.
Does it care?
What a window is at all.
Does it need to know about sound devices?
Or does it only want to give us back a stream of sound, right?
And what?
Usually argue, is that you don't want to add all that complexity to
the platform layer.
If you don't have to what I'd much rather do is Define things.
The other way around, instead of the platform layer, being a series of
services, provided to the game that the the game, then constructs a
running application out of in much.
The same way that a normal winter you to application would use the
operating system directly.
I prefer to think of the game as
services to the operating system level to produce the graphics and
sound.
Necessary to play the game.
Now.
Let me show you what I mean by that.
What I mean, is that really when we look at this platform layer that
we've already written, there isn't much of a compelling reason to
abstract any of it out of this code and allow it to be callable from
the game layer.
And in fact, you might actually argue that there are reasons not to do
that.
And those reasons are that when we actually start to tighten the
ratchet on this platform code.
There may be.
Lots of very complicated logic that we need to do in order to most
carefully adhere to the standards.
That platform, there may be tons of Windows messages, like device
change.
That tells us we need to move to a different monitor at that time.
Right?
There may be things like device removed that, the GamePad got
unplugged and then replugged again, right?
There may be all sorts of special things about like this device is a
pain and so the pain should be treated this way, but only in certain
circumstances and depending on whether you're active at the time or
not.
If you think about all those things, they're different for every
platform.
Every platform is completely different when it comes to these sorts of
things.
There's a lot of very important.
Differences, compare and contrast, something, like cocoa, and the code
that you write on Mac, OS, X with the code for say, Linux.
It's very, very different.
And so, what I would much rather do is just write all the operating
system code and let it be.
All tangly and weird and do all the things that it needs to do
specific to the operating system.
And then, the only thing the game ever does is respond to a few.
Very simple request, which are giving the stuff you want to draw.
Give me the sound you want to play.
And here is the users input, right?
If you think about it, there's really only three things that it needs
to provide.
And then on the back Channel, there's really only two things you ever
need to provide.
Please send this out the network for me, and I need to read or write
from a file now.
Not a whole lot there, right?
So what I would argue is you can drastically simplify the degree to
which your platform layer, inherits the complexity of its operating
system by not, forcing it to pass that complexity on to the game and
round-trip all of the logical operations through it.
Hopefully that makes some sense.
Now.
I'm going to show you how we do that.
Basically, all we have to do is isolate a few specific locations in
the code where the platform layer wants services from the game.
And then isolate a few specific Parts in the game where the game wants
services from the platform layer.
Okay.
So for example, when we are in here, right, you will notice that we
have a while loop and this is our Global running Loop that we wrote,
We process our messages here.
We get the input from the game.
Out here, right?
And this was test code but it's not that far.
From being regular code that we could ship.
There's things we would definitely do to it, but it's sort of getting
there right now.
You'll see, I've already kind of suggested to you what then should go
on.
Well, this right here, render weird.
Radiant, that's our render, right?
That's the thing that we rendered.
Now.
We just have a faux thing sitting in there.
But that's basically the thing that renders for the game.
So I can just say game update and render right here and say this is
where it's going to do.
It's updating and rendering, right?
And what I expect this to do right here, I expect this guy.
Oops.
I'm going to put a little note in here, right?
Note, Casey.
Services.
That the game provides to the platform layer, right?
Game update and render is one of them and
I don't even know if we're going to need any more of them at the
moment.
That may be it.
Maybe they'll be some more, right?
And then here, we're going to have services.
About the platform layer.
Provides to the game, right?
And we're not even going to fill those in yet because that stuff,
like, load file.
And, like, I think I've said before, if you happen to read my blog,
I'm a big fan of semantic compression or basically compression
oriented programming, which means you should never write something in
before you actually have it working.
And you should, you should never like presuppose that an API Works,
Victor, a should always pull out and develop the API from the ground
up.
So we happen to know.
This is exactly where we would want to do our stuff.
So I'm okay with saying that game updating rendered but then after
that, I think we're pretty much done with that.
I don't want to presuppose anymore.
So I should actually almost say to do here.
We'll add those in as we go.
Okay.
So basically what we want to do here is we want to say the game update
and render, right?
We want that to basically do the rendering into that bitmap, that we
set up.
So we should probably pass the bitmap here to the game so it can draw
into it.
Right?
And then we also want to pass it.
The sound.
We want to basically pass in a buffer so we can get sound back.
Back the sound that we're going to play for this buffer, right?
So we're going to do those two things, and then at the end of it, it
should pretty much do the output.
We've got our output working.
We've got some timing code in here.
We should probably take this stuff out for now because we don't
actually care about this printf at all.
So, I'll get rid of that for now.
There we go.
I don't know.
What display the value here.
Is that some old comment comments are always out of date as Jonathan.
Blow says, comments are always out of date.
Hm.
Well, we got a lot of comments around daycare.
Sorry to jump in here.
I think I could murder a road in.
And was mentioning these.
We did change to using a lower latency already.
We already did that.
Yeah, oops.
Oops.
Yeah.
Let's see.
Do we have sine wave?
Do we do it?
Yes.
Switch to a sine wave.
Yeah, we've got a lot of things in here.
Did switch the sign.
We're not taking our to do is out after we actually do them.
We should start to look for that.
But anyway, so, okay, sorry, back to the story as it goes.
Sometimes you gotta stop and just go what's going on in there?
What is going on in there?
All right.
So basically, all we need to do is we need to have our game update and
render basically needs to provide us, a new bitmap, and a new piece of
sound and it needs to take in the input.
Right?
So we need to pass it essentially, three things, right?
Game update and render needs to take
Take three things.
It needs to take the input.
Right?
The controller keyboard input, right?
It needs to take the bitmap to Output.
Right?
And it needs to take the sound output.
It needs to take the sound buffer bitmap buffer.
I guess I should say to use instead of Doubt.
Put right?
So, let's go take the controller keyboard input in, you know what,
let's call it for things.
Let's Spanish Inquisition that because we're also going to need timing
because if you were doing a locked timer, if you were, if you were
Have a game that had a fixed frame rate.
So it always ran at 60 frames a second.
Then that's all you would need, right?
You wouldn't pass any timing information into it.
But in this particular case, since we are not doing that, we are going
to do a flexible frame rate for the game.
We need to pass in some timing information.
So the game has any idea what's going on.
So at the outset, we pretty much only need these things.
Now this may I'm going to put a note in here.
This may expand in the future to like sound on separate thread, Etc in
the future.
We may want this to be more complicated.
The calls may go from 1 to say 3 or something, right?
Because what we may want to do in the future is we may want to have it
such that we can have sound run on a different thread.
And get updated asynchronously or something like this.
And so we may want to have the game support calling it back in less of
a monolithic fashion, but we're not going to do that till we actually
know that we need it.
All right.
So basically all we're going to do is is if we run the game.
Now we can actually we've had a regression essentially, right?
We've had a, we've had a, we've gone backwards and functionality, if
we run the game now and the reason is because I took out our call to
render gradient, correct, like, if I
Look at this.
There's no more gradient because we're not calling it anymore.
So basically what I want to do, just to end the stream today now that
we've kind of seen the way we're doing platform Services is I would
like to basically pull out our first piece of platform-independent
code, which is render weird gradient.
Because if you look at it, you will notice that there is almost
nothing about it.
That is platform-specific this win32 off-screen.
Buffer is really the only part of it that for that which, that is
true.
So I'm going to go ahead and just pull that straight out, right?
I'm going to go ahead in here and drop into my handmade dot CPP, and
I'm going to stick that in here and you can see the only thing that we
really need to do.
Is we need to change this win32 specific thing to a non?
You two specific thing.
Right?
So all we really need to do is go here and take this struct, right?
This truck that we had and we need to make that something that is not
platform specific and really, it almost already is, right.
It almost already is something that is completely platform
nonspecific.
So,
if we take a very trivial step here, right?
We do game off-screen buffer.
We've got our blue offset in our green offset.
Their right got game, off-screen buffer, and we pass the buffer in to
this, then we will be able.
And I'm not saying this is how it should necessarily go in the final
thing, but we are sort of starting to get usually code goes through a
couple of Transformations.
First, so just be aware of that, but you can kind of see what I'm
doing here.
We'll start actually I guess I want to do in to do offset.
Offset.
Basically, what I want to do is just make it so up, five minute,
warning, almost out of time.
Good thing.
We're almost done.
I want to make it so that we can at least get something rendering
before the end of the stream so that you can see the first step in
platform-independent.
So basically, all I need to do now is make it so I have one of these
to pass.
Oops, those ants.
So really all I need to do is make sure that I can pass one of those
to this, and we can even do that in place here.
We can just say.
OK game off-screen.
Buffer is
is some kind of buffer.
The buffer has some memory write that memory comes from our win, 30
SQL string buffer.
We've got the with, you've got the height.
We've got the pitch, right?
And where were those guys?
Those guys were in our where did it go?
It's in our Global's here.
Darn you five minute warning.
You're using up my screen real estate Global back buffer.
That was what I was looking for.
All right, so Global black buffer memory Global bat buffered with and
lat.
Tight.
Like so just pulling those out, there should be good.
And then we just pass the address of that and there we go.
Now, if I run this, you will note that we are almost back to feature
parity.
You know, we've almost got it back to the place where we had it
before.
Now, we can achieve feature, parity pretty easily by passing blue
offset and green offset here, right?
If we wanted to do that, we could easily do that.
So, basically, if we said, for some reason that our thing,
This then we could easily have feature parity, which we should
probably do just for the end of the stream, just for fun.
I like that.
And let's see here.
What is, what is it actually called?
What is it called?
I thought it was blue offset, and green offset, but apparently does
not that.
It's X offset in y offset, right?
Because we were doing the two different ones X offset and Y offset.
So X offset y offset.
Okay, render that.
And now we should have back our controller and we do.
Okay, so I hope you can see how easy that is.
Right.
It's very, very straightforward.
That was not like a sleight of hand or anything.
For those of you who are unfamiliar with platform-independent
programming really is that simple will have to do a little bit more
here.
We're going to get a little fancier tomorrow obviously, but it is
really that simple.
All you have to do is Define a rigid boundary and then move things
across the boundary from the specific side to the nonspecific side as
necessary.
And pretty soon.
You'll be at the point where almost all the code you write will be on
the nonspecific.
Site, anyway, you won't need to write them in Windows.
But that's really all there is to it.
It is not very difficult to make very clean, very nice cross-platform
code.
A lot of people don't but that I think is literally just because they
haven't had the experience and don't know just how easy it is because
it actually is pretty darn easy.
If you just have a little bit of discipline to keep it that way,
pretty much through the entire project.
So yeah, so there's that.
So basically, what we've done is we've essentially nuked, our render
weird gradient call.
All right, it's gone now.
So that is one.
Nice, big chunk of code that got moved out and we are left with mostly
code.
The specific, the sine wave will be the one that will do tomorrow.
Probably, and then we'll look at the moving, the input as well.
But we are well on our way here at the end of the stream on day 11 to
essentially having cross-platform game set up ready to go.
And again, this will allow basically anyone who's trying to follow us
on Linux or Mac OS 10 to go use out.
You know what, this might be a good time.
Just before we get to the Q&A to
Shout out to David gal who has been doing some porting work.
If you go to the forum's, there is undercoating resources already,
even though this section is kind of construction.
There is a platform page in David.
Gal has contributed a little handmade penguin thing.
Basically what he does is he follows the stream and he shows you how
to do the same stuff, using the simple directmedia layer, which is
basically a cross-platform abstraction of windowing systems so that
you can run on Mac, OS, 10 and Linux.
And so on it is a
He well-respected Library.
The sdl is a lot of people ship games on it.
So if you were looking for a library to use to help you run on a
platform that you didn't understand or if you just want to use a
abstraction layer in general, that is probably a decent one to use.
But anyway point being he has ported that stuff and again, you can get
to that link pretty easily just going to coding resources.
It's right there.
So if you are following along at home, we are basically at the end of
this week.
We will probably have pulled most things out and we will be in
platform nonspecific land.
So you can follow along at home, exactly like you could if you were on
windows.
So hopefully that is giving you a little bit of a background in the
philosophy of cross-platform development and how it should work.
I've given you three different ways you could do it.
I've recommended
One of them but you are welcome to look at the other two and see what
you think of them yourself.
Practice them, a little maybe see what you think and come to your own
conclusion.
We will be continuing with this tomorrow at 8:00 p.m.
And I think now might be a good time to go into the Q&A, obviously, as
always, if you would like to have a copy of the source, you can
pre-order it.
You can pre-order it from handmade hero dot-org, right here, if you'd
like to and that will get you access to the source code.
I push it basically right after the stream every night.
So
Right away, you can get X to it and we will be putting the art assets
up as part of this pre-order as well.
So that if you want to follow along with the artists as we use, once
we start doing a graphics and sound and stuff.
They'll be in there too.
And think that's about it.
I've got some notes that I want to talk about in the Q&A, just some
cleanup from before, but I will look at questions first and we will
talk about those as time permits.
Okay, let's go to the Q&A.
And a please prefix.
Your questions with a at.
See me oratory if you can because that is the only way that I will see
them because I got a little scanner that scans them.
So if you want me to answer the question, then you will have to put
that in there.
So please put that in there.
Let's take a look here.
Someone says seems unsafe to include the platform independent code
after including the platform specific headers.
Yes, that is true to an extent when we clean this up and we could do
this right now.
Actually, you can already do it.
If you'd like to, you can definitely do stuff where you where you're
sort of change the way these definition orders come.
So, for example, you can do something more like this and of course,
you will still need the standard definitions of the type because we
were using those, when we can move them down, if you wanted to move
them like this.
It would still work just fine.
And the reason for that is basically because if you do not trust
yourself or even if you trust yourself, just fine, but you don't trust
windows.
And that is a pretty reasonable thing.
Windows defines a lot of stupid macros, the stuff that overrides stuff
in your code, for example, so if you want to be a little more isolated
and this is probably something I would recommend as well.
We just hadn't gotten there yet, since it came up in the question.
We might as well talk about it.
Now, putting as much of your code above, the windows include as
possible is usually a good thing.
There is no reason to put that stuff in here because we really should
just leave all of our platform nonspecific code outside of it so that
it can't see any of Windows and isn't bothered by it.
Because remember, we're basically creating one giant file.
We're basically creating one giant file filled with pound includes.
That's just all the code.
And so rather than lb including windows at the top so that everyone
can see the stuff from Windows, you might as well put it at the
bottom, so that nobody gets there.
I wouldn't necessarily call it unsafe.
I think the person who asked the question said, unsafe, but of course,
you
It in quotes, I wouldn't say unsafe, but it is just probably better
practice, not to because, again, windows can Define.
Defines and stuff in there that you don't want interfering with your
code.
And so it's probably just better, it's less aggravating because
otherwise you're going to go to their summer and you're going to call
something.
Like, I don't know, like create directory.
You're going to make a function called that.
And then find that, your code goes all wonky.
Because Windows has pound to find it to be create direct create
directory, a, or something like this.
And it's messing with you.
Let's see.
Would you always orchestrate how you do threading in the platform
layer or does it make sense for the platform where to also provide a
more generic threading job service.
So I always would orchestrate it in the platform layer.
And the reason for that is because you don't really know how the
platform wants to handle threading in that way.
It may threading, often times in games.
Oh great.
My cord has caught here.
There we go.
Threading.
Often times in games, is directly tied to Resource Management in a lot
of places.
So there's
Just do computation stuff and that's fine.
But there are also threads that are tied to servicing resource
Readiness file IO Network IO, things like this.
And a lot of times you really need that to be an integral part of your
threading scheme.
And so I find that keeping that stuff in the platform.
Layer is better.
If there's something that every single platform is doing the same.
Then that's a perfect candidate for hoisting.
It out into the platform nonspecific layer.
But really The Meta thing to say is basically, don't move anything
into the platform nonspecific layer.
That is actually different on each platform.
So if you go ahead and make open window into a virtual thing, like I
was saying before not virtual, but a thing that you're actually game
is calling that suggests that there's some bonus in Saving, the fact
that a window is going to be open, so that you want to do it multiple
times, but you're going to do that in every platform and in every
platform.
It's different code and a different procedure.
So you don't actually gain anything.
You just add complexity by having it have two ping-pong back and
forth.
So really, what I try to do in the reason that I like this, the
Dirty method better the method where it's just a service, has a strict
strict service layer back and forth is based on because it gets rid of
all that cruft, all that extraneous, unimportant interface.
Let's see.
You said last stream that you didn't really like showing the FPS
because you didn't find it useful.
Can you explain that?
Yeah, it's because it's a what, it's an inverse number.
I don't really like thinking about it because you're like how many
cycles did that code, take how many milliseconds to that code?
Take, that's like a direct measured thing.
And so you're just talking about the thing that you actually care
about.
But with frames per second.
It's like 1 over that thing, right?
If your game took 14 milliseconds to render, right?
Right.
I mean, well, I hear it's really easy to sort of show you what I mean,
right?
So basically, maybe, oh, you know what?
I think I might even have.
Do I have LibreOffice calc on here, okay.
LibreOffice calc.
Me up.
There.
It is.
The document Foundation, ladies and gentleman.
I don't know what that is, but they make a free spreadsheet and I
thank them for that.
So let's say we have milliseconds and frames per second, right?
So let's look at what the MS are for our game here.
Let's just say we basically have everything from like essentially
extraordinarily fast way higher than any game will ever run all the
way out to see there.
Something like 30 frames a
S, right.
30 frames/second is pretty common.
So I'm going to say that we basically have one over right or sorry.
I should say 1000 milliseconds over that right over the whatever the
millisecond is.
And so this is how many frames per second, we should be getting right?
And then I'm going to turn off all the crazy decimal points there.
So, you can kind of see what ends up happening with our number format
cells.
Like that, there we go.
All right.
So what you can look at here and hopefully this will make a little bit
of sense is let's say that I sped up my code.
So I actually took a piece of code that was taking four milliseconds
and I spread sped it up by two milliseconds.
So I cut out a fair bit of time.
So I went from four to two.
Well, that's 250 frames a second to 500 frames a second.
So if you looked at that, you'd say, oh, 500 minus 250, right?
500 - 250.
That's a difference of 250 frames per second.
That's massive.
Right?
Well, let's say I did the exact same thing down here, right?
And I sped up a code that I sped up code.
That took 33 milliseconds, 231 milliseconds, right?
Well, that was like, saying, oh, I went from from 30 to 40 to 30
frames a second to 32 frames a second, right?
32 to 34.
So it's a 32 32.
That's a difference of two frames per second.
The same speed up in code.
The same reduction in number of Cycles executed results in
In 50 frames a second difference versus two frames a second
difference.
So the fact that it's an inverse number creates this nasty thing where
you don't even know what you're talking about.
All I got three more frames per second.
Well, out of where were you when you started?
I need to know that to know whether that was good or lousy, right?
It might be awesome or it might be irrelevant.
Right?
So talking about milliseconds is just way easier because it talks
about the actual thing you actually cared about and it lets you know,
how impactful that change was.
Whereas looking at frames a second is just confusing.
It.
So I wouldn't necessarily say, don't use them.
If you like using them, you can use them and if you understand them,
well, then that's fine.
But that's why I don't like frames per second.
I really only ever print out frames per second at the end of things,
so that I could translate that into whether we're hitting 30, or 60
hertz, because those are industry standard benchmarks.
Basically, you've got, you got three levels, you're looking at, you
know, if you're a game, you're looking at, you're looking at these
three breaking points here, right?
I don't know how to highlight those.
These are your three breaking points for a game.
You've got 11 milliseconds per frame.
If you can hit that, you can run in VR.
You got 60 milliseconds per frame.
You can hit that.
You can lock 60, hertz on a.
So a 1080p, nice, smooth display, and if you can hit 33, then you're
at least nice and smooth.
You look animated your 30 frames a second, anything below that and
you're totally, you know, you're done.
But those are your three breaking points, right?
And so, you know,
I just find it easier to think about the most, like, ants there and
then just use these as kind of guidelines.
For, when you're talking about industry numbers.
You can kind of remember.
Oh, yeah, like, you know, what frames per second on my app because
that's what people quote.
Hopefully, that answer the question.
Okay.
um,
On the scale from genius to totally awesome.
How can you remember all this?
So it is really not a scale of Genius to awesome as well.
It is basically just the fact that actually I'm making tons of
mistakes and that is exactly what will happen to you too.
When you learn all this, I missed eight things all the time or my
knowledge is out of date things in Computing, world move so fast, so I
am telling you the knowledge that I built up over 30 years, so it
seems like a lot, but, you know,
Basically, my knowledge is, is always a little out of date, and every
last little thing we do on the stream with, with perhaps, the perhaps
the caveat of the architecture, which may be more of a Timeless thing
at least in C and C++.
With the exception of that, like, it appears that I know what I'm
talking about because I'm showing you lots of things and they work
well, but there's always better things than what I'm showing you
because someone just invented a new algorithm that's better in the
cache and because processors change the way they did it.
And so the way that I used to do it is now the not the fastest way
anymore or I didn't even know the fastest way at the time because
someone else had it.
So basically what I would say is try to consider the things that I'm
telling you.
They may sound impressive when they're coming out because you don't
already know them but really there's way more genius down the line and
so if you can if you have time as you learn these things to read more
about them, you will find that there is Real Genius Behind these
things that you can do that.
More than what I'm doing and I would highly recommend that you do
that.
I'm basically giving you the first Passover view.
That's not so genius.
It's just the whole picture.
It's like here's how you do everything reasonably.
And then for each individual part, you can go spend a lifetime
learning about that one part and being the Real Genius at it and you
will write code much better than me.
If you do that, I guarantee you that pretty much anything you pick in
here.
If you go dedicate five years to mastering it, you will be
Writing code, far superior than the thing that I show in this dream
without question, because there's always that much to learn and
there's always Hardware improvements and changes that radically shift.
The right way or the shouldn't say the right way, but the best way to
do something.
And so, there's always an expert.
And if you want to become an expert in that thing, the things that I'm
saying that you are flatteringly calling genius.
Now, you will think we're just stupid and misguided when you become an
expert in that thing.
Do we currently have a hidden platform dependency inside the bitmap
memory or is be gra.
Something that happens on the other platforms to.
So we do have a little bit.
So basically what I would like to say about that right now is you
could totally do the game this way and it would not be a problem.
Every platform will be able to specify will be able to display a BGR
or an RGB XX bitmap for us.
However, it will in the future and in fact, I can put a note here for
anyone who wants to know.
In the future rendering specifically will become a three-tiered
abstraction.
Let us leave that as a little mystery.
No, but basically all I'm talking about is the fact that rendering
because it is so time-critical.
And so crucial to the performance of your game.
Often times goes through one more sort of specialization than
everything else does.
Nothing else in your game will probably need to be specialized in any
more ways than that, but for our game, we will actually be doing
something eventually that will introduce one more sort of
In our abstraction layer, just for graphics.
And what that will be, is basically sort of a display list abstraction
kind of a thing that allows us to either do the rendering ourselves or
do the rendering using Hardware.
So, I wouldn't worry really at all about how portable this thing is.
In terms of speed.
It will be portable everywhere in terms of just running.
Okay, but in terms of the speed, which is the only time you would care
about this, because the platform layer can
He's just flip the Swizzle the bits on a flip and social.
The blitz Swizzle the bits when it Blitz, it's got a good rhyme
special, the bits when it blitz, so you could basically always do
that.
And it would just be a slight performance penalty or something, right?
But probably not even there, but we will actually be taking pains to
go far beyond that in terms of platform, accommodation.
So that's the reason that I'm not talking about that right now, but in
some sense you are kind of, right?
It's not really a platform dependency.
It's a platform in efficiency its base.
Saying, we're specifying something to the platform layer that we kind
of know might be more costly on some platforms than others.
And that is not quite the same.
As the platform dependency gets a dependency.
Suggest.
It would be very hard to overcome it on other platforms, but that's
not really true.
So depends how you want to see it.
But either way, that will we will not be actually leaving it this way
in the future.
We will be introducing one more thing because we'll need to in order
to take advantage of GPU the
On the other hand will actually probably remain locked but that will
be fine because almost all platforms.
Can now put sound in the way.
We're going to help put it.
So it's really not that big a deal and sound is so small that you
don't care about the extra buffer copy.
Let's take a look.
It seems like your approach to handling platform, dependent Services
is to prefer a many to one relationship instead of a one-to-many.
What I mean by this is to prefer having the game, be the one actual
service being provided to different platforms instead of the game
being reliant on many different platforms for services.
It seems like your approach is advantageous because the game is, in
fact, the one common service being provided and is therefore easier to
properly Implement, for all platforms.
Instead of coming up with some high-level abstraction, which might
hide some platform specific issues.
Do you agree with this description?
So do you find this approach to work for API design and pieces play in
pieces of code other than OS level services.
That is a fantastic summary.
It is correct.
First of all.
That is a very good way of saying it and I would agree with what you
said and I guess the thing I might add to it is at the end there where
you're saying.
Do you think it's a good approach for other things?
It is an approach that works very well.
When you are trying to do something specific and that is the reason
why it works, basically, the reason why you have this API design
benefit, at least what I'm calling a benefit in my, in my opinion.
The reason that you get this API benefit by doing it the way that I'm
suggesting rather than the standard way of doing it is because there
is a massive disparity in the necessary flexibility on either side of
the API boundary.
So the OS is fantastically flexible.
And the game is not games, use a very small subset of the features of
a normal operation of the flexibility of a normal operating system.
So when you have that, very dramatic disparity of a huge amount of
flexibility on side a and almost, no recoil necessary flexibility on
side B, then that is really the time when you want to think about
doing that kind of inversion and instead of propagating forwards the
the sort of abstraction.
You want to propagate it backwards and say this.
Is the service.
Let's turn it around.
Let's make the simplest thing the service.
So I don't know how useful that will be in other circumstances.
But if you do find yourself in a place where those sorts of things
appear to be true, then it probably is a thing to consider and to at
least try see how it would look.
Because you may find that it works as well as it does in games where I
think it does work rather well.
Let's see.
How did you set up visual studio to have that black theme?
When I installed it?
It popped up a window that?
Ed, what kind of theme do you want?
And I picked dark.
That was all I did.
I have no idea.
That was that was it.
I then went and tuned my fonts to be the same colors as emacs by using
the the font selection in the options menu, but that was the only
other thing I did.
During coding.
Is it easy to discipline yourself to make the code as clean and tidy
as possible?
What it actually does.
Is it encourages OCD - encoding, do you think this is good in general
or could it backfire?
I'm not sure.
I totally understand the question.
But what I would say is I find that the right balance is definitely
compression oriented programming.
Like, I say, I know that's a term that I sort of invented, so it may
not be the right one.
Like there's a lot of coding methodology speak out there and maybe
there's a better term for it.
I call it compression oriented programming.
The other people would call it something else, but basically some
people sometimes use the word refactoring, but I don't like that
because refactoring is talking about other things.
And so I don't really like using the word refactoring because I think
it implies too much, but you could maybe say refactoring oriented
prefer.
I don't know.
I prefer compression oriented programming.
Basically, what I like to do is I like to see how things go.
When you just write them sloppily as sloppily as you want and then you
look and go.
What are the commonalities here?
How can I touch?
Reduce the size of this code by pulling out common things into
reusable portions and calling them.
That is how I like to do things.
So, I don't really like to be 200.
CDI am OCD about some things to be sure, but I try not to be super OCD
about stuff.
I try to let things have some breathing room and then I pull stuff up
as they need to be.
Now.
One thing I will mention
Is you don't want to, you don't want to compress things too much.
You don't want to lock things down too early.
So it's important to always have some Breathing Room, some flexibility
in your code.
You want to be able to allow it to move a little bit.
So you don't want to like everyday, look through your code.
And go.
Let me lock this down to the minimal thing and pull out every last bit
and optimize it.
Not that's bad because your code is a living thing.
It sort of grows over time and changes and as you see more about the
problem space and you need.
Your code to do different things and do more things.
You need that flexibility.
So you don't always want to optimize even just at the API level for
this specific thing that you're doing.
You want to always keep in mind that code needs room to grow and
mature and so too much.
Oh seediness is bad certainly and I would say that it can backfire if
you do become too fixated on on that sort of thing.
Yeah.
What did you declare a function before pound Define in your header
file?
I'm sorry.
Hide in for, I don't understand.
What did you declare a function before a pound to find your header
file?
If you could clarify that question, I will answer it.
Let's see.
I'm very curious.
And do you think this would have much cookies into the file?
I'm sorry.
I do not even know what that means.
I can understand the question Marvel sidekick.
Let's see.
Onion knocks.
That question is not really appropriate for what we're talking about
right now.
We will be dealing with stuff in terms of asset importing probably
next week, but it won't be 3D.
So we're not doing 3D assets this time around.
Sorry about that.
Will we be writing our own image format and loader?
Astray?
Garner 13?
Yes, we will.
But it will be a pretty simple image for him.
At first, it will not be compressed or anything.
It'll just be the basics, just you can see how that works.
So won't be anything fancy, but it'll be there.
Let's see.
Trying to separate things into questions that are actually about what
we were doing rather than talking about things that will probably get
to later.
I don't really want to answer questions that we're going to actually
have a whole episodes about in the future.
So if you could try to make sure the questions are about what we're
doing now, not what we're going to do later because when we go do it
later I will have a whole hour and I'll tell you all the things that
you're asking the question actually.
And in fact show you
Let's see.
Would there be a way to build your platform dependent code and
separate entity in order to allow you to use it in the future?
Yes, that is actually basically what you would do.
And in fact what we sort of are doing, if you want to abstract this
code.
All you have to do is just pull out the pound include here and just do
pound include game dot CPP.
Something that's not a specific name.
And then from then on, you just go ahead and use the same layer
everywhere, every, on every game.
That's it.
There's nothing to it.
There's nothing platform-specific.
In the, there's nothing game-specific in the platform code ever,
really.
So yeah.
I mean and I should do and I should also State.
That's how I do it too.
I never write new platform layers.
I wrote one and I use that one and then periodically I improve it.
Let's see.
Will you be developing your own implementation of strings?
Probably not because we probably won't use any strings there.
Might that we will have to deal with strings a little bit for
language.
Like, we'll have to abstract some string stuff for language support.
When we have strings that appear in the game, basically, for free,
basically shipping with locales, but that's about all will be doing
there.
We won't be.
There won't be any.
Means that this will not be like the Unreal Engine where there's like
eight million strings, nude, and deleted every frame or whatever
happens.
Their craziness.
This is, this is like there won't be any string passing in the game or
anything like that.
Let's see.
Does the unity build approach work with parallel compilation?
I don't know.
Basically the compiles are so
Ask, usually, when I do this, that I haven't had to worry about that,
but I don't know how many compilers are actually multi-threaded inside
a single file.
They may require you to have multiple files to make that work.
And so you would have to break up into a couple different compilation
units.
If you wanted to get parallelism one basically for every processor,
but I don't know.
Like I said, the builds are so fast with the amount of code you need
for a game.
Like this game will probably always compiled in less than 10 seconds
without
That forms without multi-core support.
I would think so.
We'll see as we go though.
Let's see, given your unique approach.
Correct me if I'm wrong, but I believe you lose multi-threaded
compilation.
Okay, so that's another one.
Yes.
I think you do.
I mean I don't think you can get multi-threaded compilation because
most powers aren't multi-threaded in side.
A compilation unit.
I don't actually know but again, yeah, I don't care because it's fast.
It's so fast already that it hasn't actually ever been a problem for
me.
Why you static functions when there is only one translation unit.
So I don't know if you need to do that anymore.
But I have found had found at times in the past that the reason to do
it is because it lets the compiler know that.
It doesn't have to actually build an export table for those functions
and it just speeds things up because now it knows that they're all,
they're never going to get called externally.
It also can sometimes, help the optimizer.
Can now the optimizer knows every possible place where the thing is
called.
And
Was that it can't ever be called from outside.
So it's basically better for the optimizer and the compiler, usually.
But whether that translates into real savings, these days, I don't
know.
I haven't really tested at these days.
Back in the old days.
I did some testing on things like this, but I haven't done it
recently, so I'm not sure.
Let's see.
Just in the Q&A part.
Could you please read the questions more slowly, or we explain the
question after you understood it.
This is very important for archived videos.
Yes.
I will try to do that.
That is a good idea.
Hello, sir.
I'm a computer science student and I was wondering if you feel that it
is necessary to make a flow chart before coding or if you go with the
flow.
Well, I certainly don't want to start a holy were so all I will say is
that I have never found it useful to do any kind of diagramming prior
to programming because at best the diagram is
Leave the code that you would be typing and anything less than that
obscures the actual reality of the problem and means when you go to
actually use that chart it will be wrong.
And so I've always found that the right thing to do is to learn to
have a good enough cognition of how code works.
When you look at it that it is essentially as easy as working with
something like a flowchart.
But now, you know that s absolutely everything is captured there in.
Do not get into the circumstance that I often see people get into
where they have drawn some diagram or have some crazy, uml thing.
And then they go to implement it as just a mess because the uml
diagram fails to capture, all the important subtlety, in how the code
really works at a low level.
I think the question was, why the pound of fine part of the include?
Okay, thank you for thank you for questions clarifying, that pseudonym
73.
That is that okay?
Okay.
I did not talk about these.
They get automatically inserted, by my editor macros.
So if you look at the H file that I made here to talk to store our
platform layer definitions, right?
It has this thing in here.
This pound.
If what that's called.
It's called a include guard.
What it means, is that if you try to pound include this file.
It will it'll do this if and see has anyone to in pound of fine,
handmade .h, assuming that they haven't it'll actually, you know have
this code then it will Define handmade dot h and and the end if if
someone then comes to pound included again, then you won't actually
have to worry about that because it's prevented from being included
twice.
It'll say if to find handmade and hand made has been defined, so it
Doesn't include it.
That's it.
It's just called an include guard or an idempotent.
There's I don't know, there's weird names for it.
But that all it is, is to make sure that if someone in the code, let's
say, for example, handmade dot CPP.
It's including handmade .h, right.
Let's say we included hand, it made dot h as well beforehand, right?
So now it's included twice.
You can see that it still works.
If I were to go in here and remove these guys so that it actually does
get included twice.
Now you notice, you get all these errors because it gets included
twice, and it tries to redefine things and it's like you can't
redefine things twice.
That's all.
Hopefully that's pretty clear.
Yeah, why do you specify void in function?
Definitions when they don't take arguments that is just a force of
habit.
You used to have to do that.
You do not have to anymore.
So if you would like to any time, you see me do that, and I guess I
don't have one at the moment, but there we go, if you see this, right,
this is the way I've written.
Code.
You can it turn?
Equivalently do that.
If you want to similarly, I do this by force of habit where I put a
parentheses around there.
You actually that is the more common way and perhaps even the more
correct way.
You might say to write a return statement.
Those are just ways that I code that I, they're based on the way I
learned to program.
So there's no real reason for them.
They're just a force of habit and it doesn't, it's not necessary.
You don't have to do those things.
Okay, last couple questions here.
Let's see.
Do you have a specific method of solving primary problems or just
write things and solve them in place, solve them in place?
Unless they're really hard, not to think about them for a while and go
make sort of like mathematical diagrams or something, where I'm trying
to work out, how something's going to work or something like that.
In terms of like some other thing like math and not code.
If it's a code problem.
I do it in place.
Let's see.
Why are we for declaring game layer functions in the header?
What when you include the whole implementation?
Because I like, I just like to see it.
I like to be able to have H file up.
And the other thing up.
I like to be able to see these.
So, often times, I will do stuff where I actually have, you know, sort
of files for my convenience to see.
It's the only reason I break up the files to because you can just
write all the things.
You could have basically one file for the whole game, one file for
each platform layer, and that would be it, but I do break it up.
The files and just use put pound include to pull them together because
I find it's just easier for me to work with when I'm actually editing.
Let's see.
Do you think it's realistic for someone with awful math skills to be
efficient game developer.
All right, so I'll end on that question.
We will end the stream on that question.
The question is, do you think it is realistic for someone with awful
math skills to be an efficient game developer.
So that is a very complex question and I'll talk about it for the next
five minutes and I do not claim my answer to be definitive.
I'm simply going to say my thoughts on it and I think other people
would have different thoughts on it, that may be as good or better
than the thoughts that I'm about to give.
so,
You can make entire game with no math skills at all.
Okay, that's just true.
It is definitely possible to be a very effective programmer in a lot
of areas and not know any math to give you a very simple example.
if you are programming, a text Adventure,
It could be possible to make that entire thing very well and do a good
job on it.
Knowing only enough math to do pointer arithmetic.
Which is like simple addition.
And understanding addition to multiplication, basically.
so,
At a base level.
I would say that we can start out saying that math is not as required
for programming as a lot of people make it out to be.
That is true.
Second thing, a lot of times.
In fact, I was listening to something.
Other day, I was listening to an NPR story where they were talking
about like the history of sort of people in computer science and so on
and they were talking about a bunch of things and they they sort of
made this implication there were talking about people who used to be
programmers in stopped or various types of disciplines in these sorts
of things and they made this very common assumption, the MPR.
If you're someone who doesn't know anything about programming made
this very common something they said that a
Ticular person referring to when they were a child was very good at
math.
So they should have been someone who would be very good at computer
science.
Right?
And that's a very common feeling among people.
I think, they think of those two things is related where I probably
depart with.
Most people is that, I think that computer that being a good
programmer.
If you're talking literally about programming, it has almost no
relationship to how good you are at math.
I think they are completely unrelated.
And I say that from my own experience because I was absolutely awful
at math throughout my whole time, going to school.
You would never have called me a star math student by any stretch of
the imagination.
And the reason for that is because a lot of what determines, whether
you're good at math, all throughout a large chunk of the math career,
is how meticulously you can do things without making mistakes.
That's what math almost entirely is from, you know, for your first.
I don't know and years through it, probably even when you get into
college, still that way for a long time programming.
There's no such thing as that in programming.
The computer is doing the work.
It's entirely about The Logical way.
Which you break things down, which has a lot more to do about seeing
creative analogies and things.
It's a lot more like someone who is really good at explaining history.
For example, I would Peg them as the person who might be better at
some of the things in programming.
Now, it's not sufficient, certainly, but I'm just saying, I wouldn't
use math as the primary thing because math tends to be about very
meticulously, executing a small number of logical things with a small
number.
Of of things in play at any given time.
That is what you do in math for your first.
16 years of math.
But programming is about not having to be meticulous about a huge
number of things that are in play.
And the more number of things.
You can remember and keep in play and analogize and compress and
Compact and reduce into more convenient ways of thinking about them.
The better you will be.
Now other types of math are about these things, right?
And so, as you get up into higher math, you might say that they're
much more related, but the kind of math that you experience in high
school and Junior High.
A high and lower.
And even probably in college, I find to be completely unrelated to
programming.
I don't feel, they do not feel similar to me in any way.
So that's the second thing.
Those are the the am time math parts of the thoughts.
The things that saying, like I don't know that being good at math,
really has all that much to do at being good at program.
Now, here's the pro math parts.
Especially in the realm of graphics and sound, which is a really,
really important part and Graphics.
I should say physics as well, because graphics and physics are kind of
tightly coupled in that way.
Graphics physics and sound the degree to, which those disciplines.
When you code them, lean heavily on mathematics cannot be overstated.
There is so much math involved.
In doing say 3D graphics and 3D physics, so much math.
That if you are uncomfortable with conceptual mathematics, not
necessary computation, but conceptual mathematics.
I think it is safe to say you will have an extremely hard time doing
those parts of the code.
It doesn't mean you couldn't, maybe do other parts but when you get up
into there and you start talking about programming a 3D game, even the
game code, so not the engine code, but even the game code like how
characters work and stuff like that, even that it is.
Definitely something we're not being comfortable with conceptual
mathematics linear algebra.
Partial differential, equations basic, basic trigonometry, trying to
think of the other sorts of things.
Basic calculus, obviously just understanding those things is crucial
to being effective in those disciplines.
So while, if all you want to do is be a good programmer, I don't know
that math comes into it very much if you want to be a good programmer
in games.
Then, unless you pick a very specific sub genres of games, that
doesn't lean very heavily on any of these sorts of things, like
narrative 2D games, maybe.
I would say that you will have to get familiar with the math and
comforter with the math.
The good news for people who are afraid of that is, like I said, I was
awful at math in high school.
I had a very hard time with it and I taught myself linear algebra out
of a book and I taught myself differential equations to the extent
that I even know them at all out of books.
I taught myself all the trigonometry that I know now out of books
because I forgot most of what I learned in high school or just was bad
at it in high school.
And what I will point out about that.
Is that when you have two things?
A the motivation to do it because now you have a game that you want to
make and you want to make the game good and you are motivated to learn
the math Behind these things, and not just sitting in a classroom
somewhere.
While somebody talks at you and says things that don't mean anything
to you, when you're actually motivated.
And two, when you have the computer to lean on, to do a lot of the
work for you, that's the Drudge work.
Meticulous work.
It really turns things around, in terms of your ability to get better
at math.
You can also use what's called a computer-aided algebra or
computer-aided mathematics.
I don't know what they're called.
Usually now, like things like Mathematica or Matlab, these sorts of
things.
There's even like a free one.
I think, the good news ships.
I don't remember what it's called.
But basically, you can even have it help you solve equations.
If you're the type of person who wants, you know, how to solve an
equation.
You still have trouble.
Because you forget the minus sign or whatever.
There's even things that can help you with that.
And so, what I would say is, don't give up.
Hope if you want to be a game programmer and found math, very
difficult in high school.
You may find that you are able to go much further in a different
setting.
I can't promise that you will you may have just been born bad at math.
And if you are, I apologize.
There are certain things.
You just won't be able to do.
It's sad, but it might be true, but it may not be true.
And so I would definitely give it a good long try and I think anyone
who really puts their mind to it, unless they just somehow were born
without any ability to do that, that concrete thought necessary to do
it.
But I think if you can learn programming, you've got that enough of a
concrete part of the brand-new should be able to learn the math.
So what I would say is it's probably going to be more about your
determination to do it and less about the impossibility of it.
So I would highly recommend saying if that's something you really want
to do use.
Games as a motivation, to learn that math and you will be able I think
to learn it in that setting if you really put your mind to it and
dedicate several months to practice.
Even if you couldn't do it in school because I had a horrible time in
school and I hated math, hated math, in high school.
So, all right, everyone.
Oh, someone is all saying gee, good, new octave and canoes Sage.
They were saying so, there you go.
So that was the thing that I was thinking of the canoe kuenn.
So, alright, I think that is the end of the stream for tonight.
Thank you so much.
Everyone for joining us.
I had a wonderful time talking about cross-platform programming with
you and I cannot wait to talk about it some more.
Or tomorrow 8:00 p.m.
Pacific Standard time.
I hope to see you on the stream, and on our new forums to, If you
happen to go check it out.
Handmade Hero dot-org has the link if you would like to jump over
there.
Hope to see you there as well.
So, thank you everyone so much for joining me.
And also, obviously tonight a very special.
Thanks, go out again.
After the game, The Stream a lot of thinking, with the end again, to
the people who made the forums possible.
In fact, their names are baked into the forums now and will be so
forever.
We could not have done things like that episode guide.
Without the hard work of people who were really eager to help out with
handmade here, and I really appreciate that.
Same thing to the people of doing the platform ports, and stuff like
that.
It's been awesome and it really helps out other members of the
community.
So, thank you so much.
Everyone for doing that again, and, and thank you all for making
handmade hero.
Such a great thing.
I've been really enjoying it and I can't wait for the rest of this
week and the rest of all the week.
So, thanks everyone and I will see you tomorrow night.