There we go.
Hello, everyone and welcome to handmade hero.
The show where we code a complete game live on Twitch, on the air with
no engine and no libraries.
So really, you know, you could say that this is, is the whole package.
This is the complete game.
This is every last little drop of gaming goodness.
Nothing hidden, you know?
Nothing.
Squirreled away.
You know, behind the curtain.
It's all here in the raw and what we did yesterday due to the fact
that there was a regrettable incident on the train is we decided to do
something lighter, and fluffier than we had planned on doing.
So we decided to do some work on ground rendering and play around with
that a little bit.
And so, what I would like to do today is just maybe finish up a little
bit that ground rendering because we were kind of having fun with it
yesterday and so we'll just finish that up, maybe today and
Do a little bit, maybe a clean up tomorrow, and then next week, we'll
start back on closer, inspection stuff that we wanted to clean up,
really?
It's clear detection logic that we were sort of working on where the
ground was that sort of stuff.
So, let's go ahead and and do that before I open up the code, I just
remind everyone that if you are trying to follow along at home and you
pre-ordered the game on handmade hero dot-org, you should have gotten
a link in your email, that link has a zip file in, which you will find
all the days Source codes.
And if you look
Today is day 82, so you can unzip date, 81 source code.
If you want to play around with the same stuff that I am playing
around with today, you'll be at the exact same point that I am.
So let's take a look at where things were so if we go ahead and run
this year, I think we're we stop.
Yeah, we just kind of made a little thing that would Splat out the
ground.
There you can kind of see where it is.
We're still drawing some things in there.
Like our room boundaries I suppose we should probably turn that off.
But the other
Thing that I pointed out was because we didn't have any optimizations
on our bitmap letting you know, it gets very slow to put that
background in there, right?
So that's something else that we can kind of think about a little bit.
So you know what?
I'm going to go ahead and just turn off that those debug boundaries
since we don't care about those at the moment, I'll go ahead and I'll
go ahead and toggle those off.
Let's see here.
So, we've got draw a rectangle calls where we're drawing.
Those see here, actually, I think,
It's pushed rectangle calls where we were sort of putting those
boundaries in there so we had our push outline.
So this this right here we really don't want to do that at the moment
because I don't really want to see those blue lines.
Those are just there for our debug purposes.
So I'm gonna get rid of them and so we can just look at the stuff that
wasn't the blue lines.
So I guess what I wanted to kind of do here is I wanted to kind of
take a look at first of all I sort of suggested when someone in the
You had said, you know, well what would we do when we want to start
speeding this up?
I was saying, well, I'd probably do something where we would have some
kind of backing tiles, where we would draw the background once, and
then just pull it out of that.
So that the constant sort of splatting of things that we use to make
these patterns wouldn't be causing a huge problem in terms of
performance every frame, we just do that compositing on the Fly and
little like, sort of sections.
And so, that's something that we could consider playing route.
That sounded kind of sounds like a fun thing to do.
The other thing that it would be that we
Of need to figure out how to do is, well, if we want to have multiple
layers of things like, which is kind of where we started down this.
Why we started down this path?
If we want to have multiple layers.
So that there's, you know, an upper floor in a lower floor, like, we
were kind of doing here because remember, we still have this sort of
notion of two floors worth of content.
There's you can go up our sort of virtual stairwell here that we have
no graphics for yet.
If we wanted to make those two different floors and start to think
about like, where these things go, we need some concept of
That right?
We need some way to make that work.
So that's sort of one thing that we should probably think about.
And like I said, I'm not 100% sure what it is that we really want to
do.
So that's on the table what I'm going to start with because it's the
easiest thing is when we start with is just cleaning up the random
number situation, a little bit, right?
So I'm going to clean up that random number generator situation.
Just that just a tad because I kind of said we should probably do that
at the end of the stream before.
And, you know, we left it sort of in a bit of
Of of a nasty State.
You can see.
I got this to do right here.
Make random number generation more.
Systematic.
So I think I'm going to take a second just to do that.
And again, this will also set us up for later on when we want to
actually talk about random number generation where we replace this
random number table with an actual random number generator, which
would be good.
So you can see, there's really no code right now, in the random number
generator, it was just a table and we were just sampling directly out
of the table.
So what I'd like to do is I like to pull out this code, that we've
been using many times and I'd like to turn it into something that I
can just
use any time I want.
Again, straight up compression oriented programming here.
Just trying to condense down some of these things that you've seen
happening.
A bunch of different times.
So I'd like to do is introduce the concept that people can have a
stream of random numbers that they can access and make some of these
ways in which we're using them like the, you know, down here we were
trying to get a number between zero and one for example, and then we
were turning it into a number between negative two and one and all
that sort of stuff.
I'd like to sort of make that
Stuff more systemic so that when people want to use and by people I
mean me.
But you know, when we want to go use the random number generator to
generate Randomness for us, we will be able to easily get the types of
Randomness.
We want out of it without having to Think Through the math every time,
right?
so, what I'd like to point out
First of all, is that we don't typically know upfront, very much about
how the people want to use these random numbers, right?
Sometimes when you want to use random numbers, you would like to them
to be sort of effectively random, right?
So when you're asking for a random number in the code sometimes you
want it to be really completely random or at least as close to as
possible or in distinguish from random etcetera, Etc.
But other times what you want is,
Is a series that has the properties of Randomness but that actually is
completely predictable, right?
And the reason I say this is because if you think about how we might
want to do things, let's suppose that we generate a whole world right
out of Randomness.
So we're going to try to rent a random world for the player to play
through, but we would like to the player to be able to send some small
piece of information.
To his friend that that friend could enter into the game on their
computer to play through that same random world.
Right.
And now the random will be generated might have been hundreds of
megabytes worth of stuff.
But we know that it all came from this one, you know, stream of random
numbers.
So, we would want to be able to send just one little piece of
information that's like, how do you reconstruct that stream of random
numbers so that you don't have to send that whole thing across, right?
And that is typically What's called the seed, right?
It's called the the seed because you start the random number
generation with it and basically what it is when we get up to real
random number generation, that's the number that you start out with to
start running through the permutations of the random number generator,
does to produce a series of random numbers.
And of course it's always pseudo-random, really because they're not
random if they're reproducible like that.
And so you could think about that in terms of our random number.
Abel pretty easily.
Actually, because really, for in our case, what the seed is, is just
what number in the table you started on.
So, for example, if we wanted to pick a random series here, we would
just say, oh, start on number, 35, or whatever.
And just keep reading, you know, sequentially right through there.
That would be our seed because that's the only real control we have
over where we get in a sequence.
Now, we could have a little more information.
We could say, for example, what index, we're going to start on and how
many numbers to skip each time or something like that, right.
So go by twos, or go by fours, right?
Something like that.
So you can imagine different ways that we could construct our own
notion of a seed for our random number table.
But for the time being, we don't really have to care too much about
that because we're not doing those sorts of things.
I wanted to bring it up so you'd understand the concept of it because
it is something that will come into play later.
What we want to do, fancier things to the random number generator,
And what that motivates for our design.
Is that I want to have a way because looking at, you know, this is
just my experience as a programmer speaking.
We haven't seen this become necessary in the code right now.
It's just my experience saying, hey look we want to do this trust,
he'll save us time.
Later my experience says that generally what you want to do with
random numbers?
Is you never want people to just grab random numbers.
You want them to basically have some handle that they use to get
random numbers so that that handle can track.
Back up a particular stream so that you can have multiple streams of
coherent random numbers in your program.
Some of which might be actually see things that are supposed to appear
random on that playthrough like particle effects and whatever and
others might need to be controlled Randomness.
That that's, you know, producing a repeatable series on multiple
people's machines at the same time so that you can do things like,
send those seeds across and that sort of thing.
And that's something that you probably would have seen in.
Like I think even the new Binding of Isaac rebirth.
Earth.
I don't actually know for sure, but I think in the new Binding of
Isaac rebirth, they do things where you can basically like, enter a
seed or something to start playing, right?
I think that so I think this kind of thing has been sort of exposed to
users in the past.
It's not, you know, it's not an unusual thing right to think about,
So what that means is, I want to transform this code, to start
thinking in terms of some kind of a handle, right?
That's like a random series, you know, it's some series of Randomness
and for our purposes all it's really going to be you can see it here.
We've got this random number index.
All it's going to be is that Index, right?
It's just going to be that indexed that we need to pull stuff out.
But later, it might, you know, you're not mean that so much, right?
So when we draw test ground, what we'll
Do is, we'll just initialize our random Series.
So, we'll do series equals and we'll just say like, oh, will seed it
with zero because that's what we seeded it with before, or we could
see it with whatever with one, two, three, four.
It doesn't really matter and we'll just assume that this seed, call
produces a random series starting with, whatever the seed that was
input, somehow.
It generates a random series out of that.
And any any time that anyone anywhere in the world for any reason
running handmade hero creates a random series with that seed.
We
Too serious, to be the same and this case if it's just going to become
that random number index, that's what it will do and so that's fine,
right?
So then once we have that, we don't have to do this anymore because it
will start soon that they'll get taken care of inside thing.
And then I just want to pull out the things that we were doing.
So here's one of them, right?
We've got random number table and then we did a mod by 2, right?
So we're getting one and we're doing some kind of a mod and what I'd
like to what I'd like to call.
That basically is random choice, you know, we're making a random
Choice here right between things, so I want to pass that random
series.
And then I want to say, I want to make a random choice where you pick
one out of two.
Options.
So, I'm just going to pass the two options, you know, 01, whatever,
right.
And then, when I come down here, I see this other way that we were
using it, right?
We had this this one in here, where we were basically doing a random.
I'm going to call this random unilateral, right?
And so, I'll explain what I mean by that in a second.
So by the way, this is going to be, I guess this is going to be a
random choice.
So we'll call this random choice and that's going to take the random
series.
And then it's going to take the choice count like so.
And I guess this could really be unsigned because we're not going to
support negative numbers in there, and that's what we were doing here.
So that way when I implement this will know.
And then similarly, we had one here that was going to basically return
one floating-point number, right?
And it's returning a floating floating Point number between zero and
one, right?
That's what this was doing.
So it doesn't really take any inputs, it just returns between 0 and 1
and that's a useful thing.
To have it do as well.
Now, the interesting thing about this, the reason I said random
unilateral is because I like to separate my random numbers.
And again, this is just experience talking here in the way I like to
do things is, I like to have random unilateral and random, bilateral.
And what those are, is 021 unilateral negative 1 to 1 bilateral,
right?
And
I don't really know.
I don't really know where I picked up that terminology, in fact.
I guess you could also call it random normal and random by normal
might be another way to do it.
So, you know, a normalized number is 0 to 1 and a by normal.
Number negative 1 to 1.
That's pretty good too.
I'm not sure I'm going to I'm going to go ahead and stick with that
because I think that's the way I've typically prepared to do it.
I don't, let's roll.
Let's look it up.
Let's see what's a good term?
I mean it's never, it's never too late but you can see having or
relating to two sides or affecting both sides, right?
It's kind of that.
Nice sort of feel for negative 1 to 1, right, and unilateral, right?
Only one side.
Right?
So, I don't know.
I'm going to leave it that way because that's the way I typically name
them.
So let's just do that.
But you could imagine other names and you can pick what's, when you're
doing your version of this code, you should pick whatever.
Makes the most sense to you, right?
Certainly.
So that's random unilateral.
But, you know, the other thing that we might want to look at, right?
Is this format, seems kind of useful to write.
We sort of have this thing where we're doing, you know, we wanted to
produce something.
In fact, we did this whole math.
This hope we have this home a situation about it.
We that we did, right?
We came in and we said this this whole thing here,
Where we were talking about.
You know, we need to solve to produce a number between negative 1 and
1 or whatever else.
What would be nice is if we could just do that from now, on without
having to worry about doing the math, we could just ask for the random
number that we wanted, right?
So we could just say random, you know, between so something like
random real between or something like that or just random between and
say, like minimum and maximum, right?
Because then we could just do something where we say, you know, what
do you actually
I want this thing to be right now.
Of course, in this case, it happens.
It just so happens that the equation that we wanted was between
negative one and one.
So we could just call random bilateral here, right?
Because that happens to be exactly the range that we wanted.
But you can imagine us wanting something, a little more flexible than
that.
And so, you know, let's just throw it in there as well.
Just so we can kind of have that that nicely rounded out, right?
So basically that's just
It to random bilaterals like so.
So that's all good, but you could imagine taking this even a little
bit further.
What if I wanted to have a way to make those two?
You know, we could, we could do random, bilateral, bilateral, oops,
bilateral to write or something like that and and that actually
produces this kind of vector for me.
Now, we haven't seen much of that yet and I expect we'll see more of
it in the world thing.
So it's a little premature to go down that route.
So I'm not going to
but you can kind of see where that's headed, right?
So let's take a look at this right here.
This this is another case of that random Choice thing.
We're choosing bitmaps out of this.
So this would just be saying, okay, whatever that array count is, we
want to, we want to pick one of those, right?
That's how we're doing that.
Random Choice, actually, I don't need the parentheses anymore, random
choice.
And similarly, this one as well, random groups, random choice at
series array cow.
So now we've got, you know, that kind of nicely cleaned up and yeah
that looks pretty good to me.
That looks pretty good.
So let's go ahead and Implement that.
Let's make sure this compiles.
Okay.
Oh right, we didn't actually make our seed function yet.
So here is our seed function.
There we go.
Random series.
And this is our seed and our seed takes some kind of an unsigned
integer there and Returns the result.
Oops.
So in order to do our seed function, right?
This is going to be really simple.
The seed function is probably the easiest thing all we really need to
do for that for that is a sign.
The random number index to be whatever the the seed value that comes
in.
Like so, but we also need to make sure that it's sort of, you know,
that it's going to be kind of clamp.
Here, right?
So, it's going to be, it's we don't want to be out indexing outside
the range of the table, right?
So we want to do something where we're going to make sure that we mod
by whatever the array count is of that, of that random number table,
right?
So that way, it's always inside the table.
So, yeah, I mean implementing the rest of this is just pretty wrote.
It's basically what we've already done.
So, I'm going to write all these
Terms of essentially you can you can see this operation happened in
each one of them, this random, number table, unit increment, the thing
and go.
So what I'm going to do is just say, alright, let's assume that
there's a thing which is like next random you in 32 kind of a thing
where you pass the random series and that's responsible for getting
that next random number.
So, it just returns you that random number table with the random
number index.
And I can just make that index now, right?
We don't really need to Beaver,
Because inside the series.
So that series index, we're just going to go ahead and grab whatever
one is out of there and that's going to be the result.
And then we're just going to quickly test to see if we have outstayed
our welcome, right?
So the series index, if the series index is now greater than or equal
to that size of the table, random number table,
We'll go ahead and wrap it back around 0, right?
And then we'll return, whatever, it was the result that pop back out.
So once we have that really, all we need to do is produce, you know,
use that to, to produce all the other.
All the other things that we actually needed, right?
So in this case, we've got, you know, we're going to ask for the next
round of the comes back and they were going to mod it, by whatever
that choice count, is right like so.
And that's really the entirety of the function.
Similarly, same thing here like all.
I'm really doing is just, you know, literally doing the wrote
transformation of saying, you know.
Next random you went 32 replaces wherever we were going to look up in
the table.
And that's how we produce the result now, right?
So, there's that result.
We could also make this be something that's that's precomputed, right?
We could say something like, you know, divisor or something like this.
And we could say, let's
It just Lau the compiler.
A really clear way to pre invert that number, and then we'll multiply
by it instead and that's just allowing it to allowing the the compiler
to know that we're just doing a coefficient multiplication here.
Now, is that really all that important, not really in this context,
but you know, usually CPUs are much better at multiplying than they
are at dividing and phrasing things in terms of multiplication when
you can is typically a good idea.
So think since it's literally like trivial for me to modify the code
to do that, you know, conveniently might as well, right?
So yeah, let's go ahead and here and just again, not particularly
doing anything special here.
I'm not even trying to make these at all optimal or even interesting.
I'm going to say that if we want to do random bilateral, we've got
that code here.
The way we did it before, right?
It's this sort of two times.
Whatever the unilateral result was, right?
So, here's random unilateral and then you subtract one, that was, how
we're doing it really straightforward.
And finally, if we did want to implement this random between, we did,
we know we worked out the math for that.
You remember how we did it?
We basically said, okay, there was sort of a range and that's the max
minus the Min, right?
That's the total range of values.
And then what we want to do is say, all right, to produce the results.
We take a random
Some unilateral from the series.
Oops, gotta add that Series in there.
We take a random unilateral from the series and we need to multiply
that you know the range times that so that gives us somewhere in the
range and then we just add that that bin offset to it, right?
That's a that's a pretty straightforward way to produce something in
between those two.
We know that if the random unilateral produce is 0, then we'll end up
and, you know, I could phrase it this way to make it a little clearer.
So you start at the minimum and then you're just taking some amount of
the range and adding it in there.
And again, this is that this is that function.
Format that I talk about all the time, the blending function starts
somewhere and you go a certain amount towards towards the other end
and we could phrase it in that way as well.
In fact, you know what, why don't I do that just to reinforce it here
just just to make it clear.
What's going on?
I think.
Do we did we make one of these?
Do we make a linear blend function?
We didn't
Oh man.
How disappointing is that?
I thought we probably would have already but it looks like we never
did.
That's too bad.
That's too bad and I feel like we've been using it, right?
I mean, we used in the same region.
I feel like we definitely will actually, you know what, I think we
made moved it out to to the entities.
Right?
The get stared round.
Yeah, so I mean, you can see that this, this forum pops up everywhere,
right?
It's the same thing, right?
If you can see it happening, see how it happens here, and here, right?
When you have the range and the minimum and then you multiply by
whatever the amount from 0 to 1 is that you want to go.
Well, sigh.
That's just the way that goes.
But what I was basically saying is we could have done it this way
which is like a linear interpolate or something like that which is
often called lerp, right?
You can say, I want to go from the Min to the max by some value, which
is going to be random unilateral Series, right?
So that's, you know, sort of the thing that I assume that we had
already
Didn't doesn't look like we did.
But again, that's just that that blend format.
I've talked about on the stream multiple times.
It's like, you know, it's like an A and A B that you're going between
and it has that form of
Of 1 minus t times a plus T times B, right?
And at the risk of beating a dead horse because maybe people didn't
watch the old streams or something like that.
You know.
This again is that sort of it's so important that it's worth saying
over and over and over and over again, until we're blue in the face,
just so everyone.
So there's no chance that you could ever possibly watch handmade hero
and not know it, it's 82, right?
Yeah.
Just in case.
Again the way that that the reason that I say, those two are the same
equation is because if you're going to blend from a between two things
from A to B by some value, that goes from 0 to 1, which is T, right?
That is that, that sort of universal blending equation, which is 1
minus t, A+ T, be right?
And if you multiply that out you get 1, minus t a
Right I'm just distributive property right?
Straight up high school math at best TB, you know.
And so if you think about what happens here in terms of grouping these
terms, you can see that there's a TV in both of these.
So if we there, if we go ahead and group that out like this is the
equation grouped by a write.
This this term here being grouped by a so it's 1, minus ta.
If we instead grouped it bite,
It right?
You end up with plus T, you know, B minus a right that's just pulling
out the tea and you end up with a negative a and a positive B.
So B minus a right, that is the range, that's the difference between a
and b and this is the Min, right?
It's the place you're starting at now.
They don't have to be mins and Max's.
Doesn't matter what direction this goes.
You don't really care.
So, Min and Max is irrelevant really?
Just a and b but in terms of the phrasing that we were using before
it's Min and Max, right?
So you can see
That these are the same equation there.
Just grouped a little bit differently.
And yeah, like I said, you can never really repeat this too many
times, because if you don't know this equation by heart cold, you are
going to be a Sad Panda because it is basically the most useful thing,
you can possibly know it.
If you could only know one thing mathematically in game programming,
it be this hopefully, you know, a lot more than one, but
But this would be it.
So anyway,
There it is and I'm since I bothered to write it, I'm going to stick
it in here and use it because you know, gosh darn it.
You know the
This is running out of code and we need to conserve the code.
It's a scalar operation after all.
It should go in the scalar operations.
There it is.
No, it's there.
See, I knew we had it.
How come I couldn't find it.
It's my search busted.
What did I do?
I my fat fingered it.
Didn't I lame?
Alright, so there it is and you can see that I've already written it
there so that's good.
So you can do it.
Alright.
Okay.
I feel better.
I was like so ready for it to be there.
I was like hoping that was there and then I would like it wasn't.
There I was in this big letdown so.
Okay.
So it's just a search fat fingered.
So you know disaster narrowly averted disaster narrowly averted good
good.
But yes again if anyone who hasn't gotten that totally down will still
say it a few more times, I'll be on the stream but that's that's the
function that you got to know.
So there we go.
That's that's alert going on there and that's all good.
So let's finish the the fixer that the replacement here.
So
need to change this to a random Choice as well and just grab out that
There, these are land random bilaterals so we can do.
Oops, that's an address of series.
There we go.
Another random bilateral.
And let's see if that worked out for us.
It did.
That's what we expect to see.
So that's all good.
And you know what we could do to?
You know, I don't know if we actually
I really want to but, you know, we could make it so just to
demonstrate what happens there, we could make it so that this seed
kind of permutes itself, periodically.
I don't know that we really care about that but that's something we
could do.
So we could see how it changes, what the background is, but we'll
leave that for some of the time.
So anyway, what we can do is we can continue this down.
Now, to anywhere, we were using the random number table, right?
And so we can make another random series here, that's something else,
you know, four, five, six, seven,
Or whatever.
I don't know, doesn't have to be something else, could be the same
series, who cares?
We'll deal with that little bit later.
But point being, what we can do now is make sure everything works off
of this because, why not?
We spent the time to do it, we might as well clean up all the code.
And so we can do is just say, all right, get rid of that, it looks
like we actually have a random Choice variable here.
So perhaps I shouldn't have called the function, random choice.
But you know what?
It's it's an oversight.
Let's go ahead and say
That random choice is going to be, what is this, actually, a choice of
this is actually like a door direction, right?
I think is what we actually did.
So let's call that door Direction because that's actually what it is.
It's not just a random Choice, it's the random choice of door
Direction.
So it looks like we want to
You random Choice series of to here and we want to do random Choice
series of three here like so otherwise known as if that's true then we
do a to otherwise we do a three right what's that?
Basically all that was doing seems like that was true.
So let's go ahead and make that be true.
ZZ
And then we come down here and it looks like there's really not much
else in terms of Randomness looks like just the familiar set where the
familiars were going in our random familiar generator here, but we can
do that one as well, right?
We can just say that we want, I guess it looks like it's just an X Y
there, and it's an XY between
Between negative 7.
And three.
Right.
I mean, that's what we wrote here, because we're producing a number
between 0 and 9.
And there were subtracting 7 from it.
So, no.
So it's between negative seven and two.
So that's kind of hard to read and we don't even know what's going on
there.
So I think this might be another good reason to augment this with, you
know, one of these random betweens that works for integers to, you
know, if we did something like this where we can say, give me a minute
Max can integer space and get one out there.
That that seems like a pretty good idea to me.
I don't know about you guys.
So yeah, I would say
In this case, we could use that form, we can't use the lip because
it's that's floating point and you wouldn't want to produce those
Infinity values.
You need actual integer values, but, you know, we can still do the
exact same thing, right?
It's just, a Min, plus the max minus the Min, as the range.
So all we really need to do is just say next.
Random Unit 32 mod that range, right?
Like so,
And so that way that'll give us, you know, it'll start at the minimum
and then we'll make it.
We'll get a random number and will produce some offset basically,
doing the exact same thing we're doing here.
Only at least now it'll be a little more readable so we can say, you
know, random between past that series.
And then say, all right, we want a random number between negative 7
and 2.
And now at least we can see that that's what's what it's doing, right?
And similarly here, I want, you know, that random number between
It is.
Three, right, and plus 9.
So it's going to be 6 I guess again, don't really know what we were
doing there, but I guess we were just trying to figure out reasonable
places where the familiar
Could be.
But yeah, but I don't know.
So we'll just do that and make sure it works.
Okay.
That doesn't look quite right.
Are familiar, is gone.
Where did our familiar go?
Brandon between series past them in?
Get the max Min, we mod by that, we add, of course, this is coming out
as a unit 32, which is, you know, it's not the best possible thing.
So, I wonder if we want to make sure,
Sure, we can sort of do that to make sure that we've got the positive
negative range there.
But yeah, what did I must have?
Must something up.
Let's go in and set a breakpoint there.
There we go.
Wait, so no, it's offset from the camera now, so that's fine.
All right, so let's double check here.
Random between, let's see, Min and Max.
We actually want to see those in regular numbers.
So max minus Min is 9 which is what we expect.
So what's our results there?
It's negative 7 that seems like you're totally plausible value to me.
What happens here?
Result is 5, which is also a totally plausible value.
Yeah.
So, where did our familiar go?
Are familiar is up there.
So I must have really misread what we were doing.
Which again is why I said I wanted to replace those routines I guess I
was not concentrating well enough on that.
So I yeah I thought it was saying - seven such as start at negative 7
and then it should go between 0 and 10.
Right now let's see what the
No.
I feel like that.
Yeah.
But I must have, I must have misread that there.
I guess, what I can do is just take a look at what it actually was.
Let's take a look.
So what did I misinterpret here for modding by 10?
So whatever comes out of the random number table is going to be
between zero and nine, right?
Well, you know what?
We don't even have to guess, I guess we'll just go ahead and and see
what that is next.
Random you went 32
You know what?
It could be.
It could be that it was just happening to produce a number that happen
to be pretty far forward and we just haven't ever rerun it again
because you know it wasn't, it was always going to produce the same
random series since we're going through the table in the same order
that could actually be the be the whole thing could be that I
translated entirely properly, which does seem potentially to be the
case.
But let's take a look.
Let me just verify
That's the case.
We're all set 16.
So let's see what we get there.
Okay.
So yeah, we're totally fine.
So I think what actually was happening there was we just happen to
have a fortuitous random number and one time in 18, you know, when we
were kind of going through things, it turned out that it was you know,
some sort of a situation that that fortuity to fortuitously still
placed it in the right place spot on the screen.
I feel like that's probably true but you know, I could be wrong about
that.
So yeah, let's think about this for one second though.
If the monstars
Negative 3 plus 2.
Yes.
If I go back, if I go back in here and just sort of put this back in,
if I actually wanted to do, what's probably the right thing for the
familiar Randomness wise?
We probably want his y offset.
If the monster, is that camera tile plus 2.
We probably want the familiar to be it, like something that's going to
be negative off the camera tile and then it's probably fine.
However, you know far he is in either direction.
Correction - 727 or something like that.
I don't know.
Let's take a look.
See what that gives us.
So that's fine.
And let's maybe let's generate just a few more of those just to see
Yeah, so that looks a little bit better in terms of what's going on
with the with the familiars there.
Similarly, maybe give them a little more range in terms of the
locations there.
So that looks pretty good.
Yeah, and I do I feel like maybe
maybe we've got to do, you know, I realize the phrasing of this
routine is a little bit off so like
Just hear me out for a second on this.
So basically, you know, we've got this situation where we're saying
Min and Max.
And in this case we're including the max in the range.
And in this case, we're not including the max in the range.
I mean it's pretty self-explanatory, right?
If this came out to be 0, we would, it would be kind of invalid,
right?
But if it comes out to be 1, then we're only ever going to produce a 0
here, which means we always produce them in.
Whereas what we want to do, if there's a range of one is produced
either, the Min or the max, right, and so on and so forth.
So I feel like really what we would want to do to match this routine
is is include that extra
Ra, you know, the max in fact you could say it's the max plus 1, minus
the Min, right?
Because we're want to be one over from that.
Hopefully, that makes some sense and that's why we were seeing that
familiar would only on one line before it really should be on.
Three lines, right?
And so now it is on three lines and that's better so that's good.
I think that's a good thing.
So yeah, now we got that Randomness in there.
That's pretty good.
I think that's a nice thing so I'm not sure what to tackle exactly.
Next, we've got about 15 minutes to go so we probably should do
something else.
Relatively substantial, not too big but
We've taken care of everything, regarding the random number table.
Here.
We could.
I suppose also do something where we like, you know, move this move
this down.
Let's let's make sure that nobody's asking for that outside here yet
or not.
So I think we're pretty much good.
We've removed any dependency directly on that table from the code.
And so that way, when we vaporize it, we just redo these routines and
effect.
Basically, we set ourselves up so we only have to redo one routine.
Which is next random un 32.
That's the only thing that we're really after you do well, and see
that, I suppose, when we switch to an actual random number generator,
instead of a table.
So I think that's in good shape.
Yeah.
So what next is the question and I don't really know which one we
should do next.
I suppose what we could do is we could try doing.
Let's try doing a pre composite.
You know why not?
I mean it's a smaller.
It's a smallish thing to do.
We could probably do that right here.
So what I'm thinking right is, you know, I want to start, I want to
take this this draw test ground thing and I just kind of want to make
this into something that can do a composite of the ground without
having to redo it every frame.
Right.
So I want to do is say oh I want to you know build test ground or
something like that, right?
And make that make that happen.
I guess, you know, technically, I could still call
That drug test ground.
It's not really a big deal.
But basically what I'm going to do is take this game off screen buffer
thing.
I want to make that so that I can just sort of pass something, that's
not actually the real game off-screen buffer.
Right?
So here's what that was, you know.
And what I could do is just say, alright, well,
Loaded bitmap, right?
I don't know if you remember, whereas loaded bitmap load.
A bitmap looks exactly like that.
So if I, if you take a look at handmade platform and I've Got Game
asking buffer, right?
And then I've got loaded bitmap, they're really really similar, you
know?
I'm saying so I'm wondering is what if we just condense, those two
things down
To one thing.
You see what I'm saying there?
Hopefully, that makes some sense so that really we don't have two
different things.
We just have one and we go from there.
So let's say we have a loaded bitmap and we were to introduce the
pitch to that
Right and and you know, maybe loaded bitmap isn't the greatest term,
maybe just bitmap would be a better term for it, right?
Or something like that, but either way.
So let's say introduced pitch to that.
How hard would that be for us to support?
Because we only have one function really that uses it.
And so if we take a look through here, we can kind of see that that
really we don't have to care to, we don't, we don't really do much
that has to deal with with that pitch.
Well, we were really doing before, was sort of banking on the fact
that we could just use the whip.
But if we were to update things to work with the pitch, you can you
can see us doing it right here with the, with the gain buffer.
So we should be able to do the exact same thing with our source
buffer, right?
So let's just go ahead and make that modification, right?
Let's say that we go ahead and pull stuff out of the source.
The same way we do for the pitch, right?
And it looks like what we're
We're doing here.
Is we're actually pre inverting that and because remember, our bitmaps
were like bottom up instead of the top down.
You know, we were kind of doing a flip in there, but that's kind of
interesting because that means we could just bake that right into the
pitch, right?
So from now on, we could just say, it's whatever the bitmap pitches.
That's what we're going to use as the offset and then that way we set
it to flipped, or we don't set to flip, it doesn't matter which one it
is.
So, whichever way we loaded it in.
We could still the blind would now work.
I would do the right thing by reading that that pitch out, right?
And so, you know, if I basically turn this equation, you know, this
Destro thing, if I basically do, the Destro thing exactly the same way
for the source row, and it's weird that we have two of these here.
Weird that we do a plus equals a - I mean this is what we're doing,
right?
So let's do that, that that whole thing together and in fact I guess
we are Source row
Is actually supposed to be un dates here, right?
Because we're just like Destro.
So if we do our sorcerer that way we say alright we've got the bitmap
pixels, we want to add the pitch.
You know, with the the height minus one and I guess we don't really
need to do that part either because we could bake that into the pixels
pointer as well.
So that may be what we want to do there too.
So maybe we maybe we get rid of that as well, right?
Let me just put that up there for now, temporarily.
So really all we need to do is this, right?
We just need to say, all right, we need to move.
Move by our Tsar Source offset, why we need to move by that in the
pitch pitch base, right and we need to move by that Source offset X.
So this is just pre stepping us to where we need to grab out of this
bitmap, right?
And I guess by
Per pixel interestingly is is not specified in our bitmap.
We kind of know that it's always for.
So I don't know that I really want to introduce that into this
specifically.
So I might just say that there's a bytes per pixel equals four on here
for now, because we're not really going to allow multiple bytes for
Pixel in our bitmaps.
They always have to be 4.
So I'm just going to say it's got to be for.
So basically it's that.
So you can see this is the exact same pretty stepping.
Basically that we're doing nothing particularly fancy there.
All right, so if I were to do that, right?
And now I can Pilot We compile but of course we totally wouldn't work
because our loading are loaded bitmap called doesn't actually set any
of that up at.
All right.
So what we want to do here is at the end we want to set this stuff up
so we've got a pitch we need to set it and then we need to set the
pixels pointer properly right and the pixels pointer.
I'm going to set to avoid now is to make sure that we don't do any
funny business.
The stair with it, right?
So all right, so the pitch is always just going to be the width
X the bytes per pixel.
And, you know, we could actually put the b or pixel in here, but I
really just don't want to do that.
So I guess what we have to what we might want to do is just have a
global defined for that.
Like something like loaded bitmap, bytes per pixel.
Something like that, you know I'm saying.
And so that we just kind of go ahead and grab that any time we need it
because I just don't think that that's a useful thing to parameterize
in the bitmap.
I'd rather have the compiler.
Be able to see that.
It's just a constant value that doesn't have to worry about
I feel like we did Source row needs to be changed based on clipping,
like that's a stale to do anyway.
So yeah, so we go ahead and do that.
Let's go down here.
So the pitch is right there, there it is.
And what is a result is not a pointer.
So there's there's that.
So yeah, so it's just the width times.
However, many bytes per pixel, they are that's the pitch.
But like I said, we want to go backwards.
So we're going to make
- and then we want our pixels pointer to actually be synthetically set
to that top row just like we're doing before.
So that's again just this where we have that pitch, we want to take
what our old pixel pointer was that we were using before and we want
to back that up so that it's basically at the that that first row.
So I think that's the stuff that we would need to do for that.
Let's take a look.
Of course, we will crash immediately because I typed
something wrong.
Hold on a second.
Let's take a look.
So let's see, we got the pitch, correct?
Its - 10.
Are there we are properly.
This is not.
Okay.
So we've got first of all.
Hold on a second.
We've got one more thing.
We need to adjust their is now that we've changed our pointer sighs.
Right?
We would like to be able to, we need to be able to step our stuff.
Oh wait, no, that's not.
That's not true.
These are casted to you and 32s.
So these are still stepping a full pixel at a time so that's totally
fine.
That's not a problem at all.
So,
That's all good.
Nothing.
Weird going on there.
And yeah.
Okay.
All right.
So that's fine.
So let's go ahead and step through and see what the whatever it was
that I introduced.
That was incorrect.
So
Oh yeah, it's this right here.
So, the pitch being - moves us back a row.
But we needed to move forward rows because this is actually going the
other direction, right?
So that's actually stepping us back based on the direction that the
pitch is going now.
So that was dumb.
Alright, so that was our only problem.
So, we're in good, we're in good shape now.
And so now really like, you can see what I've done here is just made
it so that it doesn't actually matter for drawbitmap.
What's actually getting passed to it?
Could be an off-screen buffer or it could be another bitmap so I could
do loaded bitmap buffer now, right?
And then oops.
And then in here when we do memory, what I can do is just change This
to Memory and now everything lines up properly.
They're exactly the same.
So let's let's do pixels to memory anybody else.
What is that complaining about bytes per pixel?
Yeah, so this is just going to be this again and I don't remember why
we even have that in here.
So I'm going to go ahead and say you know, can we just remove this
entirely?
Because it says right here, pixels are always 32 bits wide.
So I'm just going to maybe just say that that has to go away, right?
And and we could we could put this in here as well, right?
Something like this because we really don't ever allow that to very
and so we should just we should just say that goes away.
So that's that's that.
Here we go.
Let's put that in here.
Get that by two pixel.
Get that bite the pixels.
I'm like that pixels memory now.
Right bitmap B pixel and I'll throw that in there.
Get Matt bytes per pixel.
Keep on going pixels.
- result pitch pixels is
Remember, that's true memory.
Now
And should be almost done draw a bitmap, right?
So now, when we call drawbitmap, right, what we can do is we can just
say, okay, everything now takes sort of one of these loaded bitmap
things and when we pass it buffer, instead of that buffer that we were
getting before, right?
We're we're calling it here.
What I'm going to do is say that, that buffer is a
She going to be all name it, something else, let's say, draw buffer or
something like that.
Draw, buffer, like so drop by for a job offer draw, buffer drop off a
draw buffer like that.
And
Then I'm going to say loaded bitmap draw buffer and I want to make it
a pointer so I don't have to make all these be Anne's.
So I'm just going to make a little synthetic one here, 2.2, like so
like that again, this is just I don't feel like making these be Anne's
vert, you know, have to have Ann's in front of all time.
So I want it to be a pointer but what I can do here is now just
initialize this to be whatever the stuff was that we were getting sent
from the 0s.
It pitch memory.
They're all just exactly the same and we could even collapse these
even further.
Now if we really wanted to oops, so draw rectangle, same thing that
can just be a loaded bitmap now and you know the name loaded bitmap
doesn't really make a lot of sense.
That might be something we want to change the future, bytes per pixel
is now not a thing.
And so off we go, here's our games to the rendering properly, and so
now if we do want to catch something, we've set ourselves up to do
that.
So, for example, I mean, you can see how slow this is running right
now, right?
Look at that frame rates just chugging along and all of that sin, that
stamping really.
So now if we wanted to cash that when we drew draw test ground, right?
When we actually do that, that draw test G function.
If instead we just did that an IT time, right?
We could do that at an it.
Now, if we wanted to, so when we do this, we could say draw test
ground and we can draw that into some kind of a buffer just to give
you an example there.
Let's say we do game State ground buffer like this.
We're kind of running out of time here.
Maybe we'll go just a few minutes over.
Think we have two or three minutes on the clock.
Spare, I didn't start right on time, but if I come in here to game
State, and I say, all right, we've got a loaded.
Bitmap.
That's just the ground buffer.
You know I'm saying?
And so let's go ahead and do that.
Then all I would need to do is my this
For thing would just have to be like make you know empty buffer or
something like this or make empty bitmap and I just want to make it
empty bitmap.
That's some size of something who cares.
It's 1024 by 1024, I don't even care at all and we just need a place
to get that from.
And so that can come out of.
We haven't really talked still about.
We still have kind of a big old standing to do for World Arenas here.
So you know,
It's it be nice if we at some point actually started to get these
Arenas into into more shape.
Something we have to do pretty soon.
But anyway, if I wanted to I can go ahead and and still use that that
game arena for this and say
Let's see here.
Say, go ahead and use this Arena, get me one of those and and and give
it back and then we can draw it into that ground buffer.
And then when we come down here I'll just re-enable this call so that
we're basically on top of it, we're going to draw that that ground
buffer and we'll draw it at, I guess, 004, now now, I mean, we don't
really know.
I guess we would draw it.
It something, you know, an offset that was proportional to the
difference between height.
So I could even do this to do case we draw,
This that Center but that's basically all we would need to do, right?
So here we go, let's do that.
Let's make this make empty bitmap, that's going to return a loaded
bitmap struct.
That has the information about the bitmap that was created.
We've got our Arena here that we want it to allocate from.
We've got the width and the height.
So there's the width and the height of that buffer.
1024 by 1024, it may have been a little bit large that may have been a
mistake.
So maybe we want that to be like 512 by 512 for now.
So we'll just take a look at that and we'll go back to make empty
bitmap, their make empty bitmap and implement it.
Now, the question is, can I implement it in 2 minutes?
Which I think is are three minutes which we had left, it seems
plausible, you never know.
So here's that result.
The result has a width of width.
It has a height of height.
It has a pitch of whatever.
The pitch is times, the bitmap bytes per pixel, right?
And then it has memory
That is going to be 0.
And you know what?
Us realized we can even use this call.
Now, think about it, to clear it.
So we don't have to clear it ourselves, which is pretty funny.
I don't know if we really needed that we could just do we have a zero
size call we do.
So we really only need that zero size call.
Never mind.
So we do have a 0 / call.
So we just want to zero that memory out.
So we'll just say total bitmap size.
And this will be an arena push where we're basically saying, we want
to push.
Well, you know what?
This is just a direct push size.
Like, so that's all that is.
So we're going to say take the arena that we were past due, the total
bitmap size and of course, we know what the total bitmap.
Is is the total bitmap size is just the width times.
The height times, the bitmap bytes per pixel, right?
And we could use the pitch for that if you wanted to.
But you know, if we set the pitch to - or something that wouldn't
work, so that makes an empty bitmap that we can draw into.
It's basically doing the same thing that we did way back at the
beginning of the series.
Oops.
What did I do wrong?
That should return.
That was right, wasn't it?
Yeah, I know what's going on there.
All right, so let's see.
Okay, so we ran out of space.
In our memory Rina.
Oh why is that so huge though?
Did I compute that wrong?
Width times height.
Whoa what?
What did I type in?
Ah Ah that's that's too large.
That's too large.
All right, so not quite there yet.
I don't see our bitmap which is not a good sign.
It was supposed to work.
It didn't work.
Let's take a quick look and see if we can find it.
So, we're drawing our bitmap now into that into that buffer.
And and we are hoping that it works properly ground buffer.
Yeah.
Like so and then we act we are actually drawing it.
Yes, in here at 0 0 and I don't know, I don't know if I will have to
delay debugging this because who knows?
I don't know how complicated the bug might be.
I don't want to go too far over time.
I'd like to make sure we have time for questions.
But yeah, I think feel like that should have been sufficient unless
I'm missing something, we are definitely drawing into.
We are not like woefully drawing at drawing outside the boundaries of
this guy and we know that because oh well you know what it could be it
could be that that we don't have a big enough bitmap to cover where
the
Actually was or something like that, but I don't think that's true
because it uses the center.
Does it not of the actual yet he uses the center of the actual
of the actual screen there, I thought M to pick
Some rest, Max bitmap Center and whereas bitmap Center bitmap Center
is defined here.
In fact we could pull that out to their fitness center so on, oh wait.
No that's the never mind, that's not the buffer Center.
That's this is the screen center.
So there's that screen center that it's using, so that seems like that
should put everything at the center of the bitmap nicely.
So I'm not sure why we weren't getting anything there.
It would be nice to see why that.
Oh,
I know why.
It's right here.
People, we're never setting the alpha channel, right?
We're noticing the alpha Channel.
We've got to set the alpha channel of our of our composited bitmap.
Otherwise, it'll just think that, you know, it's basically marked as
not not being there, right?
So there it is.
And now you can kind of see like,
You can kind of see that that we got the acceleration, kind of that,
we were expecting their, it looks like that.
We've still got some kind of bug there, you can see down in the
corner, like that should not be a notch.
I would think so.
We kind of have we've got we got something, although you know what,
that probably is that's just because nothing ever touched there.
So that's till Alpha 0.
So we probably want to do here though.
Still is just go ahead and fix the fact that we, you know, instead of
always having that Alpha
What we might want to do is is right, the alpha actually into the
buffer.
Of course, the problem with that is we actually need to think about
what the a value actually should be, right?
Like, what is the alpha that you actually would write in there and and
that's probably a topic better left for a different day.
So let's, let's, let's do that tomorrow to do Casey compute the right
Alpha here, just left a bar.
Pretty multiplied Alpha.
But when we do compute the right Alpha here, that'll go there and then
we can go ahead and actually do this for reals, where we do something
like that, and write an alpha Channel out.
So, for now, what I'll do is, I'll just say, okay, we'll just take the
alpha of whatever the thing is that we're writing, you know, just the
actual Alpha Channel itself but that's not correct.
And so maybe tomorrow, we will do that.
So this should be s.
Is a right?
Not a sa so that should be sa everywhere.
That.
All right.
So I think that's about it.
That didn't work.
What'd I do wrong there.
What did I do wrong there?
You did sa we grab sa take C Alpha.
We did all that.
We grab the a equals sa.
We do the blending based on.
- sa + sa, then we write in whatever the source Alpha was.
You went through to a plus 0.5.
We cast it back down, we shift it up, 24.
That should have been fine.
Right.
Let's let's just double-check 1.00.
It's 250.
5.0 ah-huh.
This is actually yeah.
So we at would actually would have to multiply it by 255 because we
converted the alpha to be 0 to 1 because we want to do the blending,
right?
We wanted to duel Earp's.
All through here.
So yeah.
Yeah, we deserved that so you can kind of see if I put the alpha in
there then you can see if I just use whatever the source Alpha is I
get whatever bitmap got stamped down.
Last is the one that is the one that shows through.
I mean, I could do something a little cheesy but I could do something
where we just take, whatever the maximum one is, right?
We could say, oh, you know, the destination Alpha whatever was in
that, you know, the
Target buffer.
Originally, we could do something where we basically say, like, you
know, whatever the maximum value is out of these two.
That's the one that will take.
But again, we should we should really go through it and do it more
correctly.
So you can kind of, see it starting to get a little more correct now,
but still not quite, right?
Yeah.
And there you go.
So that's, you know, that's just the, the beginnings of how we might
cash that.
And now, our frame rate is back up to normal, which is nice, even
though we're doing all those things because we only did the
Them once and now we're just reproducing them and you can kind of see.
I did that I didn't really do anything, you know, ignoring this, which
of course, like I said, we ran out of time.
We could cover how we actually want you.
That destination Alpha.
So ignoring that temporarily and well, maybe that's what we'll do
tomorrow is.
We'll talk about that a little bit more completely ignoring that for
now you can see how simple it was from you do this.
Basically, all I need to do is collapse those two things down.
So that the thing that we read from and the thing that we write to are
handled symmetrically and that's a pretty important thing to get,
right?
If you know if you can you want to be able to draw into stuff that you
draw from because that's what allows you to cash, right?
If I have all these things that are taking lots of bitmaps collage
Them together to produce the ground or whatever.
And I want to e be able to Simply take that code.
That was working when it was drawing to the screen and make it so that
it works when I'm drawing to something that I will save and use later
as a composite.
You want all of those routines to be as symmetric as you can make them
so that you can always sort of switch between which of those you're
doing without having to make it this huge deal, right?
And so that's something that you know is a good thing to know.
So as we build our render in the future, that's something you really
want to do.
And obviously graphics card support this.
Now all the with render to texture is what this is, right?
It's like allowing you to render into something that you then used to
texture from.
That's exactly what we just did, right?
And you can see that was very simple to do.
All we have to do
Was make it so that we could use a loaded bitmap struct to point to be
a desk, or a source.
And because they really all need exact same information.
How big is it?
What's the pitch?
And where's the memory at?
That's all they need.
And so, and so off, you go, alright, so let's go ahead and go.
Let's go ahead and go to the Q&A, right?
I'm going to type in the old Q&A there.
And and let's let's let's take questions.
So please keep your questions to stuff that we have been working on
and also put Q: in front of the questions so that I can see.
What's going on over there on the Stream?
Did you do?
Okay.
Casey, I missed the earlier part of the feed, but what was the
intention of moving the ground plane with the player?
Can you be a little more specific about I'm sorry?
I'm not sure, I am not sure.
That I actually understand the question.
Can you be more specific about moving the ground plane with the
player?
Every time you disagree ethics question or a collision question,
elaborate a little bit more on that stegosaurus so I and then I'll and
I'll tackle it
Why aren't random unilateral and random bilateral, not just using the
implementation of random between seems like a pretty clear violation
of dry.
Although I realize you aren't currently intending to this code to be
extremely clean right now.
So I don't really like obviously I'm not someone who thinks that
there's such a thing as dry or that it should be violated or not.
But I can answer that specific question in the context.
Of good or bad code.
So, when you're talking about functions that are this straightforward,
I don't think there's a very good reason to to reorganize them that
way, right?
Because there's a very fine line between making code that uses itself,
which is what you're suggesting right, trying to make the maximally
overlapping set of functions and basically setting things up to allow
blaz Style
Asian right?
And by blast style upper is just, I mean, basic linear algebra system.
Which was the kind of this old concept, where you basically have core
operations are broken out, so that they can be optimized individually
when you go to do your performance optimization.
And so usually what happens when I'm coding is when I'm down at the
level where I know that like each of these things is going to be a
specific operation.
And that's used when they're this simple, I don't tend to collapse
them and the reason I do tend to collapse them is because a there's no
reason to collapse them.
Usually like if I, you know, if I want to collapse them if I thought
that they were going to be doing exactly the same thing, I would
collapse them perhaps.
But if they're not doing exactly the same thing.
Like if they're special-purpose versions of each other, that you can
do, I'll often leave them broken out because I'll probably want to
write specific code to do those later in a more
isn't way, right?
So in this example, you know, really even here, I probably would get
rid of this lerp eventually, I wanted to use it because like I was
saying, as I mentioned, when I typed it in, I wanted to remind people
that it was that function.
So that's really the only reason that normally, I wouldn't even have
used it.
There usually what'll end up happening.
Is I'll try to think through what the right way to write the code, is
knowing the things that I know because random between
Is much more General than random unilateral or random bilateral.
So by forcing those to go through random between there's less
possibilities for optimization there and it makes it more confusing
for the compiler as well, right?
And so, I tend not to once I get down to a certain level, I don't tend
to just have things call it, call utilities for their own sake.
If that makes sense.
Now, would I criticize someone for doing that?
No, absolutely not.
Because the structure as it is exported to the rest of the program.
Still works fine if you do that.
So if you were to have random unilateral and bilateral, call random
between, right?
You could still have the opt, the opportunity to optimize them later
because, you know, the rest of the code is still calling random
unilateral or random bilateral as necessary, and just because your
refactoring through them, it doesn't matter, right?
Um, but the reason I didn't bother to collapse them was because in my
head I'm just thinking oh these want to be broken out anyway,
probably, right?
That's like what I'm thinking.
So I'm not going to bother trying to make sure that I have all of
these things reusing each other because I don't think that's how
they're going to work eventually, right?
So that makes sense.
So hopefully that is a little bit of, gives a little bit of that
perspective.
I'm the way I would doing those things.
So, clock, count, someone wants a clock count, but I've forgotten how
to get the clock counted.
Think we put it out here, right?
Clock .exe.
I like how something that counts the number of lines in a program is
11 megabytes large.
Fantastic.
All right, so we got clock.
And we're going to go ahead and say, all right, 4:00 let's go.
Handmade duck.
Is that how that works?
So is this not?
We're not very large, we're five thousand lines of code.
That's not large, right?
That's, that's pretty
I feel like that's pretty small.
Yeah.
Why does the seed function not have a prefix or suffix, random?
No, I think really just because there's nothing else that could be,
but I don't have a problem with that, you know, if you, if you see
this as a, you know, if you wanted to, I'd be fine with that, you
know, I'd be fine with saying that the way this works is, is this way
if you wanted to and everything was is prefix or any of, you know, if
that was something that made you more comfortable, regularize, it's
close enough to that that that seems fine.
You know, so I'm I don't know that I would necessarily have ever
bothered to regularize it in that way, because I'm not sure that
there's really any practical benefit to it.
But if it helps you keep it more compartmentalize there than you know.
And since this just takes a bear you went 3-2, you know, maybe it's
nice to have randoms to, you know, these guys are never going to get
mistaken for anything else because even if someone else had something
called random or had something,
Next to you in 32 they wouldn't take a random series pointer so
function overloading would prevent them from getting from colliding,
but random seed is definitely true that.
You know, you went 3-2 is not special so so you know, I could see that
and so that's fine.
You know?
That's that's a totally fine thing to want in the code.
Is it okay?
That random Choice, doesn't select, the random value uniformly,
depending on Choice, count argument value, it will prefer smaller
values.
For example, if random, if Max random value is 10, then R and D mod 8,
or returns you to up?
Well, I would say, no, it's not.
Okay for now, it's fine but in the long run, no, it's not.
Okay, like that's one of the reasons why having a tinier and
Table.
Like this is not a good idea, but the random number generator that we
actually use in practice.
We will attempt to make produce completely random bits in terms of
distribution.
So that's really a thing to deal with more once we actually put the
random number generator.
And at which point at which point like, random Choice should be
actually uniform in this distribution, unless there's something else
about it that I'm missing, but I feel like this should be as long as
the
As the actual series itself is random, right?
So yeah.
So I would say no, it's not really okay, but it's okay for now because
we're not gonna actually use that random table as the real thing that
we use.
Wouldn't random Choice have a slightly uneven distribution?
If the number of choices, didn't evenly divide, the maximum random
number.
Mmm.
I think you're probably right about that.
In other words, once we go to something that generates 32, random
bits, right, as opposed to this random number table table which does
not do that.
But once we move to something that actually generates 32 random bits,
the question is
You know what?
What consequence does random Choice have because it's using a mod.
And I feel like you're probably right that, there's a tiny tiny bit of
bias towards the lower numbers like really, really tiny.
Because you've basically got four billion unbiased regions and then
this one little biased region at the very end but I think you're
correct.
However, I am not good with number Theory and so I want to say that if
you really want to know the answer to that question.
You're going to have to ask someone with a better discrete math
background than me because I'm only guessing at the answer, I don't
know, certainly it won't produce any real problem.
In practice, I can pretty much guarantee you that, but if you really
needed to care, for some reason that there was literally no possible
bias ever,
You may you may have to do something else.
You may have to do it a little differently.
I don't know, right.
Okay, keep going.
When is it okay?
To pass larger objects, like r3s by value.
Instead of by reference.
So, really the answer to that question.
I'll say, two different things.
The first one is inline functions.
You can pass.
Pretty much whatever you want.
Most of the time, the optimizer in the compiler.
Should be good enough to just expand those inline functions.
Look at them figure out what they need to do.
And do the right thing, right?
Probably now,
As with everything else that has to do with compilers, you need to
verify if you care, right?
So in any circumstance, where you really care, you gotta go verify.
for other things, what I would say basically is, keep in mind that a
pointer in 64-bit code, is 8, bytes long,
So any structure that's like in the neighborhood of 8?
Bytes long, let's say that's 8 B.
16 B, maybe even 32 bytes
You know, if you pass a pointer to it versus passing it, you're not
saving much and so, especially depending on, it's really mostly.
All right, let's back up.
So when you call a function,
In 64-bit x86 and x64 code.
Our current compile Target.
We call a function x, 64 code.
Basically, what you're going to do is you're going to the compiler, is
going to push the, the it's going to push the arguments on the stack,
if it can't fit them in the registers.
According to the ABI, the application binary interface.
The thing that says how function calls work by convention, right?
Because, you know, there's no such thing as a function call at the
hardware level.
There's
Like calling a function is just calling an address.
There's no parameters, right?
So it's just expected that the code on one side of the call, puts the
parameters, in some place, where the code on the other side of the
call knows where to get them.
And so one place is on the stack, another places in the registers of
the CPU and the registers on x64 CPU, there's 64 bits obviously.
So they're eight, bytes long, they may be significantly more than
eight bytes long because there's registers
There's xmm registers there's a VX and all that stuff and those get
longer than eight bytes right?
Those can be 128-bit to and 56-bit, they could be very long.
And so basically it's going to stuff a bunch of stuff in registers for
the call and when it can't fit in registers, it will go ahead and put
on the stack.
And I don't remember what the API says.
I should remember.
I think the FBI says, like, you get half the registers for the push or
something.
I don't really remember, but, you know, it's going to be something
that's like, in the neighborhood of, you know, 64 byte something like
that, right?
So when you're passing stuff to a function, you can kind of think of
it as like, you know, if you're passing
Stuff.
That's not going to be that much larger than 64.
Bytes 80, B, 90 B.
I don't know, most, that's probably going to registers.
Anyway, you know, how much does it really matter at the end of the
day?
So I don't know.
It's tough to say.
The other thing is, you know, it's gonna be perfectly cast.
You're going to put it into the memory and put it right back out.
So you're only really worried about if you're kind of overflowing
catch this, there's a lot of stuff involved there.
So I would say, you know, it's just not something that I think about
too hard.
You know don't pass for K objects on the stack.
Certainly you don't don't don't pass things that are certainly large
but anything that's
In the neighborhood really shouldn't be that big of a deal.
And you know what, you should probably be able to do is anywhere that
you really cared about it.
Just take a look at what the computer is doing and make sure that it's
okay and time it, you know, if it's if it's in there just time the
calls in either way and see what happens.
That's really the only way to know for sure but, you know, hopefully
that gave you a little perspective on kind of roughly what's going on
in the process and to be honest with you on exit before, I've never
Ever done really any optimization where I've timed register versus out
of line.
How big things have to be?
I've never really done that Performance Tuning, so I don't even really
know what the best rule of thumb would be on any particular Intel
processor.
For example, let alone like an arm or something like that.
Kissy just curious because the background tiles are static at the
moment.
Ah well yeah so that's because we really just haven't gotten to how
we're going to put the how we're really going to want the ground to go
around the player that's just that's just we were just getting the
compositing working and so that's the only reason they're static.
We haven't really decided how that's going to work.
Well maybe we'll do that tomorrow.
Do you see yourself extending random number to have anything other
than a uniform distribution?
Yeah, I mean I would suspect I mean I don't know that we'll put it
necessarily, I'm not sure that it will go in this random set.
They get might I mean I don't know, I think about that but when we do
the procedural world generation will probably want to have non uniform
distributions so you know, I couldn't say for sure right now but I
strongly suspect that yes, we will have some way of
Getting non-uniform students.
However, will probably always start with a uniform distribution.
So our random number generator, will probably always generate uniform,
distributions.
And then we'll like warp the distributions to be calm down.
Uniform is what I suspect will happen.
I don't suspect.
We will have like a non uniform, random number generator at the core,
right?
That's my assumption.
Is this strictly handled in Ram?
Do you have plans to use GPU resources for rendering?
Yes.
Oh, we will be doing the entire game with software rendering first
because that's part of the educational process and I shouldn't say the
entire game.
But we'll have a renderer that runs entirely in software and then
later, after that, we will show how to do Hardware acceleration as a
separate path.
So you'll always be able to run the whole game through the software
path.
And possibly some of the features in the will be turned off in the
software path that aren't fast enough or something.
But yeah.
I noticed in functions, you will always use a result variable, even if
the calculation is a one liner rather than using the expression
directly in return statement, does this incur an extra copy and are
their performance implications.
So know, any optimizing compiler, that works at all.
Doesn't care about that performance wise.
There's no extra copy in debug mode.
There might be because in debug mode the compiler might not do
anything at all, but in debug mode, the compiler does so many extra
copies of that form.
Any way that you'd never notice these
But, yeah, in optimization mode those all go away.
That's, you know, the the SSA analysis of it would trivially trim that
out, you know, it's not a problem.
The reason I do it is because that way it's easier to inspect the
variables when you debug you can always set a breakpoint before the
return and see what the returns going to be without having to trust
that your debugger will give you a way to view it easily.
Do you plan to move all the other loaded bitmap memory to be in a
memory as well?
No, well yes, yes, I should say that not now but yes once we do the
asset loading path that will all be Memory Arena based right now.
It's using the debug file load stuff.
So you know
I believe, that's how that's going.
I think you've used an aggregate initializer in one place with random
series being seated IE you only have one call to random seed but you
have at least two?
Yeah, you're right.
You know what?
That's a force of habit.
I probably shouldn't do it so I was trying to be a little nicer on the
stream that I normally am.
I real code?
This is how my real code looks usually, but it's better to write it
this way.
So yes, thanks for catching that.
That's really what I meant to type rather than assuming the structure
of it.
So that's, that's actually yeah, that's actually what I would have
typed.
in my regular way that I do random series I actually don't do that but
I should
It's a little bit little bit better.
Let's see.
Initially, you put B for Pixel into the bitmap.
Sure.
Because it can be useful.
Then I asked you to remove it because
Ever changes and you did that.
But 10 or so episodes, later, you added it back because it would be
useful and now you're moving again, this is funny.
Yeah, and that's, that's not untypical in programming.
At least for me, it's like, I'm allow things to be flexible if I
especially there's some things where you just can't tell, which way
it's going to go and they vacillate.
So, I guess the funny thing will be, which way, will it end up?
I think having it constants, probably, right.
I mean, it is.
Instant we're not going to allow it to be anything else so I think
probably it should have been this way when you asked me to remove it
before you were probably right.
And maybe we'll stick with it this time because we had a real reason
to
You fix random to the uniform by generating a full.
32-bit random number do, mod next power of 2 Choice count then check
if result is less than Choice count.
If not repeat the whole process oh man
Who that sounds brutal though?
That's a loop, man.
Yeah, we're not going to do that.
Sorry.
We're going to accept the the slight bias I'm afraid.
So, all right, we are done.
We have come to the end of another full Power episode of handmade
hero, which was dedicated today, actually, to Abner Cumbre, one of our
whose name.
I never know how to pronounce.
This is the weird part with handmade sure.
Oh, I've made so many friends now through the series.
I, they can hear me say stuff, but I can never hear them.
Say stuff.
I don't know how to pronounce.
Anyone's name, even the moderators, I just guess when I see it but
this stream of course was dedicated to Abner because he had an awful
day the other day and we were talking about it on Twitter and we
decided that there should be an episode dedicated to him and
commiserating with him for having an awful day.
Because let's be honest, we have all had awful days at some point and
sometimes it's nice to know that other people.
Care about the fact that you had an awful day even though that doesn't
help your awful day at all, like let's face it the awful day, was
still awful.
Knowing the other people are bummed that you had an awful day.
Can kind of help make you feel a little better sometimes.
So this one's for you Abner and yeah, I hope that that maybe Future
Days will be better days.
So let's take a look here.
Where are we at?
We have we have come to the end of another episode.
So Dove handmade hero.
If you are someone new to the series and don't know, the don't know
the drill, you can get access to the source code by pre-ordering the
game on handmade hero.
Dot-org comes with a link that you can use Save the link that you
Because you can use it to redownload the source code and I'm putting
up a thing.
I found out that send owl has a way to re get links if you forgotten
what yours is.
So I'm going to put that up on handmade here at Oregon as well, kind
of like under here soon.
I figured it out because I asked them.
I was like, sometimes people lose their link and they need to get it
again.
How can they get it?
And they said, oh, there's this hidden thing.
It was like a good.
We could do that.
So I'm going to do that as well.
And also, we've got a patreon.
If you want to support the video series, you can subscribe to
That we have a news in forms that you can check out.
It's got a lot of good info on.
It's got an episode guide for catching up, with all the old episodes.
If you have someone who's new to the series, check that out.
Every last thing we've done every last bit of programming done on this
game, is there is a video that shows exactly how it was done, and
that's a good place to get that.
There's also Community ports to Linux, and Mac up there that you can
check out.
If you're interested in running on a different platform, before we get
to it, officially on the series, they've already done it and there's
also a place to post questions up there.
So yeah, if you're interested in the schedule, we're going to be here
tomorrow morning, I guess because it's Friday tomorrow, is it?
Not.
Yeah, so it'll be tomorrow at 9:00 a.m.
we will be kind of following up with the doing a little more of that
that ground composite work there.
So tomorrow morning at 9:00 a.m.
if you want to come back for the next episode.
If not, we'll be starting again next week and I think next week we'll
try a new time slot.
I was saying possibly 55 p.m.
might be the new time slot.
So if you're trying to keep track of all that I know,
It's a little crazy.
What you want to do is take a look at the Tweet bot.
The Tweet Bots, pretty good the tweetbot.
Basically will tell you everything you need to know about the
schedule.
So check that out.
It tweets the whole schedule on weekends and it also tweets every day.
What the schedule B, so it should be pretty easy to keep a track.
It's low noise.
Otherwise it only treats the schedule and any schedule related stuff
that comes from me like the time when my train was stuck and we
weren't sure if I was gonna get here in time,
So thanks again for joining me.
I hope to see you tomorrow and have a good Friday whether I do or not.
Take it easy, everyone.