Hello, everyone, and welcome to handmade hero.
The show that we could complete game live on stream.
No engines, no libraries.
It's just us here.
Writing code the old-fashioned way.
Where we take a look at?
Absolutely every piece that's necessary to make the game Run right
down to the little tiny pixels that we use to display it and all the
way up to like the AI that controls the characters, right?
And so we pretty much finished up all the asset file work that we were
doing, we were working on putting all of our ass.
It's into these asset files that could kind of be shipped as units.
Kind of like, you know, if you want to ship an update to the game
where you added a bunch of stuff, you could ship, you know, new
executable and new asset pack file that had all the Assets in it.
Or, you know, if someone made a mod to the game, they could bundle up
all the Assets in an asset file, and ship it or something like this.
So, that's what we were working on and we did that.
And what we have to do now, because we had not really gone and ever
looked at this part of it.
What we want to do now is make there be some way for the game.
I'm to just find out what asset files there are on the drive.
So we you know, for testing purposes, when we wrote all the code that
supports all that stuff, we basically just hard coded it to load the
three files that we knew we had created as tests.
Right?
But we would rather do now is go and make it so that our platform
layer has a way of enumerating all of the asset files that the game
should consider and handing those back to the game.
So that the game can then, you know, iterate over them load them and
now will be
A more generic setup where we can kind of, you know, have their be, if
you drop 10 asset files in the assets directory, it just returns those
10 or whatever and it's just nice and flexible, right?
So that's what we're going to do today.
It's a little bit of win32 programming again.
And so we want to kind of go back into that platform layer now that we
know what the API should look like.
And we want to make something that can gather up those asset files and
provide them to the application.
In some convenient way, we've already suspect an API for this, but it
was just kind of our first pass API.
So when we go do the implementation.
Now, in Windows, we will see whether we can actually fulfill that API
or whether we will have to do something a little bit different to make
sure that it conforms properly, right?
And so that's what we're going to do now if
You would like to follow along with me at home today, is day 154 on
handmade hero.
So if you want to unzip day, 153 source code.
That is what I'm going to be starting with here.
So if you pre-ordered the game on handmade here at org, please
download that source, code, ZIP and unzip day 153 cuz that's what
we'll be starting with your a day 154.
All right.
So,
Let me show you what I am talking about, in case you don't remember or
weren't here yesterday.
So, what I did was I just kind of stubbed out this stuff here where
when, you know, I'll also just quickly bring up the actual asset code
where we call it, good get all files of type again.
So you can see
That the the platform nonspecific code when it goes to initialize the
game and wants to see what assets are available.
It goes ahead and opens up the the thing called a file Group, which
has all the files in it of a particular type.
So we say get all files of type, begin HHA, then it goes through here.
It iterates over those files and it opens them and does some stuff
with them.
And then at the end, it says, okay, I'm going to stop, you know, I'm
done iterating.
So if you had allocated any memory or
If you had any open like system file handles that need to get close.
Now as a result of that iteration you can do so, right?
And I bracket it that way, because I was pretty sure, you know, just
having done a lot of platform layers before you know, in my
programming lifetime.
Basically I knew that iteration tends to take resources, right?
The operating system tends to give you handles and stuff that need to
be closed and all sort of stuff.
So I felt like it was probably the case that we would need an end but
we'll
and out, you know, as we go
So then what we did to test our code is I just hard.
I made a little hard coded thing here.
Where instead of actually looking at the drive to see what asset files
were there, instead, I just always returned three and I then looked at
which index, it was trying to load when it asked to load a file and I
just stuffed in what would be the correct name.
So what we're trying to do is take these little to do is here today
and we're trying to turn it into something where it actually, no
matter what HHA files are in that directory, they will get a numerated
and passed to the game.
That's what we would like to see happen.
so, if we were to do that,
You can kind of see what we're doing with, you know, we can what we're
doing on the drive here.
So, if I do a directory here, you can see in fact, I guess I'll do it
this way if I do a durostar .hh a which says show me all of the files
that end in dot h.
A you can see that we've got test1,test2 and test3 .hh a, which again,
we've hard-coded in here is going to load.
So what we want to do in the platform-specific code now is is
essentially emulate this Behavior, right?
What we want to do is we want to be able to do the equivalent of a
durostar .hh A in the directory where
Game is running and say, hey can you just show me all of those ha
files that are there, so that we can load them right that we can load
them out?
and so the way that we do that on Windows, I can show you
There's a really I don't really know that there's many ways to do it.
There's like one or two I think but really probably what we're looking
at here is fine file or fine file ux I guess this is the wrong way to
search for it.
Maybe win32 find file find first file that's what is sorry, got the
names that you're wrong.
So this is one of the apis.
You can use to iterate over files and it's probably the one that we
would have to use their again.
Like I said, there's there's not
A whole lot of ways to do this.
And especially if you want to be backwards compatible.
Like they do have fine first file transacted, right?
And you can kind of see that in the in the sort of requirements.
It doesn't go all the way to Windows XP.
So I believe if we were going to Target Windows XP, I believe that
that fine first file is mostly what we're looking at.
But again, like, you know, that's just kind of within a first
approximation.
Find first file X is probably really not that necessary for us as
Well because it just adds additional things that we really don't care
about and so we're probably fine with just fine first file and that's
pretty backwards compatible.
Like that's going to be that's going to run on basically everything
that anyone would have these days, right?
It goes all the way back to Windows XP and and pretty much no one runs
Windows 2000 anymore.
All right, so the way this API works is if we call it right.
I'm going to put it in here if we call it.
It gives us back a handle.
It gives us back like a find handle.
And I'm Jimmy when we pass LP file name to it, this is going to be a
string and remember we're doing the ASCII wide, the ASCII versus wide
pile.
Kind of thing that happens here, right?
Excuse me.
So if we were going to call it, we're going to call fine first file, a
ski right.
Just like, we find call create file ASCII.
And again, if you missed when we covered the stuff on the stream,
that's just which one you're in Windows.
You can call either, you know, anything that takes a file name or a
string can either be called with an A on the end of it.
Which means I'm passing you and ask easy string or a Nancy's E string,
I should say a Nancy string I guess.
He the probably the more correct thing to say, or you can put W on it,
which is I'm going to pass a wide character string, which is Unicode
utf-16, right?
And we don't really care about Unicode for this because we are, you
know, we're just letting asset files that there's no problem with
restricting asset files to be, you know, antsy named, right?
We don't care if people can embed, you know, crazy script or something
into their into, their file names, you know, they should be able to
call them something that fits a Nancy.
Okay.
And so what we want to do here is we want to be able to do call this
fine first file thing, and we're going to get out one of these win32
find data structures is this is an out parameter.
So we have find data and we pass the address of a flying data and so
it's going to use that file name that we pass whatever this is right.
This is some kind of a filename that we haven't really talked about
what it's gonna be yet, but we pass in a filename, we get back a
handle for iteration and we
get back this find data structure, right?
And the way that it works is the lp filename structure.
Actually be a wild card so it can actually be as you can see, from
here, the directory path and the filename, which can include while
cars, for example, and asterisks are a question mark right question,
mark is one character that can vary asterisk is any number of
characters that can vary, right?
What we can do there is we can pass in a filename, exactly.
Like what I just did up here, right?
If I was to pass in Star .hh a then I could you know I could go ahead
and have it lists for me.
Me all of those files that conform to that standard, right?
So that's pretty straightforward.
So what I want to do is do something like this, right?
I'd want to pass in something like that and then when I call fine
first file, what this is going to do is it's going to give me back the
first file in the current directory.
Essentially, because I haven't if I included a path here, it could
actually go look at a different directory, but it's going to just use
whatever the current directory is where ever.
You ran the executable from basically, we're going to look in there
for anything that could forms as well card will return us the first
file, right?
And you can see that
In the win32, find data that out parameter there.
You can actually see the if I go look at that, it gives us back pretty
much everything that we want to know, right?
It gives us back a file name, it at even gives back to 8.3 file name,
right?
But it gives us back a file name and it gives back like the times for
these things.
It gives back how big they are.
Right?
It gives back the attributes like read-only stuff like this and so you
know that's that's really all we would need to do.
Due to know what the files are, right?
So we really don't need to do much else because really this is all we
were looking for.
That's all we would have to pass to this sort of thing, right?
So if we wanted to, we could do something like this.
And then the question is, how do we get the rest of the files, right?
How do we keep getting files?
And the answer is once you call fine.
First of all, you get the first file, what you get would do next is
you call find next file, right?
And so, find next file, as you can see, right?
That's going to iterate through each of the files, and it's going to
Turn a Boolean, which is whether or not there was another file, right.
So at least, I believe that's what it does.
If I can't quite remember to be completely honest with you, by leave
us.
The balloon.
Does the function fails.
Yeah.
Get lesser or turns are no more files.
So basically like you can assume that unless you're looking for some
other error, any time, it returns false, either there are no more
files or there was some error with the drive, in which case you also,
you can iterate over it.
If there's more if the if there's a drive are so your iteration is
basically done
Whenever that happens right now, I will make as an aside a little.
I will tell you that this is kind of textbook.
Horrible API design, and I can show you exactly why that is after
we're done with it.
Just
You know, we talked about this a little bit where I yesterday stream,
I believe I talked about or maybe to Shannon.
Oh, stuff.
All up.
I guess oriented programming.
I talked about, this is the textbook example of someone not doing
Snuffleupagus oriented programming and so, after we're done, writing
the code here to use the win32 functions.
I'll show you exactly why it's really really bad.
So anyway we're going to go ahead and call fine first file.
What we then need to do is say well okay.
Is this, you know, is this file handle actually
Valid.
Because find first file may not find any asset files, right?
It's not a given that the asset files around the drive, like maybe the
installation was bad or maybe they're running it from the wrong
directory.
Like they made their own shortcut and change the working directory for
the executable to some random place.
So now we don't know where that it is, right?
Or maybe they just flat out, move the day that somewhere else, who
knows?
And so if that happens file handle, I'm sorry, find handle could just
be totally bogus, right?
It could be invalid.
And so we want to do is we want to to check against this invalid
handle value, right?
We want to say if find handle right is not equal to invalid handle
value.
Then this is a file that we want to process right process the file,
right?
And then assuming that it actually was valid, right?
Again, we're going to come in here.
And we're going to say, okay, assuming that it was valid, we also want
to Loop, right?
We would want to Loop over all of the adjustments, you know,
additional files that there were right.
Like so, and we'd pass the fine handle and we get new find data for
them, right?
And so we just keep doing that while that, you know, equal true, right
basically?
Which is just mean, you know, that's the shorthand for being able to
true.
So that's you know, how we would have to do it and then of course,
there's an additional caveat for fine first fine.
Next know if they've got it.
Here, there it is.
Which is that you have to call fine clothes on the fine file assuming
that it actually succeeded.
Now, I believe you only call it.
If I don't know if you can call it.
If the handle is invalid or not, I think you're only supposed to call
it if it's valid, but I don't know if you're allowed to call it, if
it's invalid.
That's a pretty good question.
We could actually test it and I really know.
But anyway, assuming that the handle was not invalid to begin with,
then we need to close it when the iteration is over, right?
You see at the Docks ever say, do they say?
Find first file remarks.
Let's see.
When the search handle is no longer needed, close it by using the fine
clothes function, not close handle, right?
So I assume that's only if it's not invalid handle value, because if
you just called Fine clothes,
About handle value.
What would it do?
Right?
It doesn't have any information to actually close the search, so I
think it pretty much looks like that, right?
All right, so if we were going to do this right here, you notice, we
kind of have a nasty thing where we have like, we have to process the
file into different places, right?
So it seems like probably what we what you would want to do, right?
If you want to structure this a little bit more uniformly and still
only have one Loop.
If you might do something like this, where you say okay I'm going to
do fine handle and then, you know, or you know, you could imagine
something like this.
Right.
Oops where I did a while file handle or fine.
Handle rather is not equal to invalid handle value and then we went
through like this and when we got to the end of it, right?
We would do something like this at the end of it.
We'd say find next file and we do it with the fine handle.
And what we do is we check to see if the find next file returned,
true.
If it didn't return, true, then we would just break out, right?
And then the fine clothes would be down here, you know, doing
something like this, right?
We're assuming that the fine handle was actually valid, we would go
ahead and close it, right?
And so then, at least we've got only one place where we have to
process the file.
That makes sense, right?
And so this is what that Loop actually looks like.
And what I was trying to say before in terms of you know why this is
such a bad API is you can see how unnatural it was to try to write
this thing.
Right?
The thing the person wanted to write was just this they wanted to
write you know for all files in the directory or that that match this
pattern you know process the file right.
That's what they wanted to write.
So ideally when you expand that into ceased
Tough what you wanted to see was something like, you know, this right?
Fine handle equals begin iteration you know or something, Whatever It
Is.
Well named iteration is valid find handle, you know, iteration advance
or something like that.
Right now, we've got a nice clean Loop that everyone can understand.
It's exactly what you would expect to see.
Everyone is smiling and happy.
Right?
But you know instead.
They did it in this really tortured way, where the way that you get.
The first file is literally completely different from the way that you
get the subsequent files.
So the loop can simply not be written uniformly in any real way,
right?
It's just really kind of kind of ugly right in that sense because the
thing that you're actually iterating on, right?
I mean, you could, you could
You would need.
Guess what I'm saying is, you would need to sort of have this concept
of the for Loop where you had a breakable thing in the this would have
to be able to break out, right?
And so they kind of just made it perfectly architected.
So there was no way that you could ever actually create a nice relief
out of it and then they went ahead and also made it.
So you had to close the iteration even if the iteration was finished.
And so it's kind of inviting this extra error at the end to which is
it if you forget to do this, you leak a handle for no reason.
And because it knew the iteration was over when you called find next
file and return false.
Right?
So unless that's just something where the documentation is kind of
like wrong and maybe you don't really need to or something like this.
It's kind of ugly, right?
So really bad API because, you know, it would have been so simple to
get it right.
But again, you know, if you don't Snuffleupagus that, you don't know
that you've made something so weird for no reason.
so anyway,
That lamentation aside we can, of course, still construct something
that works which and only process the file in one particular place,
which is to do it like this.
We start by finding the first file if that is valid.
We then go ahead and do fine next file, right?
And if the finest style fails, we break out of the loop.
If the find handle is valid at the end, we close it to make sure that
it doesn't get leaked.
And so really all we have to do is do some kind of file processing,
right in here right now there's a problem that we have
And again this is yet another reason why it's a little bit tricky and
this is not necessarily bad API design on their part.
Although I might argue that it actually sort of is for other reasons
that get into a whole bunch of Kernel programming stuff, so that's
separate issue.
But point being one problem, we have here is if we wanted to allocate
some space to store these files or something, we have no way of even
knowing how many of them there are right.
We have literally no idea how many of these files are actually
How many were actually going to find?
So what we can do, right?
Is we could try to do something a little bit like we could pre iterate
over them and know how many there probably will be.
But of course someone could copy a file in between the iteration the
first iteration in the next iteration or something like that.
So it's a little bit janky but, you know, we could do something like
that.
And we can also say that well, we only, you know, that's only
approximate anyway.
So we just wouldn't, if someone copied an agent, a filing in the
middle of iteration.
We wouldn't find it.
So we can say stuff like that and
it's not a huge deal, right?
But my more concerned about is the fact that we kind of said that this
was random access, right?
We kind of said here that we did win 30 win32 open file.
When we call that it would do this file index thing right?
And I'm not psyched about that, right?
I don't like that because this code doesn't really need the ability to
specify Random Access.
It's only ever going to load these files out in order, right.
Um it's not going to have to jump around or anything like that.
So what I could do for example
is turning into this, you know, open next file.
Where it just, it's whatever one is next on the thing, you know, it
opens it right?
And that's how it works.
so, if we were to do that,
Okay.
Then, I think we could code this relatively cleanly right without
having to do random access.
What we would do is, we would just go ahead and sort of pre iterate
the file, right?
So we would do something like this where we go, okay, fine handle find
first file with the filename and the find data, we would iterate over
it and all we would be doing here is we would start at zero, right?
And assume you know that the file count was going to be 0.
Then every time we saw a file, right?
We would just increment that file count, right?
So that when we were done, we would know.
We would at least know how many files are actually were then what we
would do.
At the end of it is we would reopen the find, right?
So we would do the exact same find that we did before, right?
Only this time, we would go ahead and capture that.
Data and of course we now have to, you know, go in and take another
look.
Cam a platform that a chair.
So inside handmade platform.sh, right?
We've got that void star data.
We've got the platform file group, we've got this void star data which
is like the data that, you know, it's kind of getting saved for lack
of a better term by the platform.
And so what we want to do there is we want to allocate against a
little bit of space for this thing to do that.
To have it exists, right?
And so again, just do the same thing we were doing before all we would
do is for our file group.
We would say that the file group, you know, data is going to be equal
to something.
Where we allocate win32 platform file Group, which would just again be
our platform specific extension which is whatever data we need to
process.
This.
As far as win32 is concerned, right?
And that would be the find handle.
And the the data, right?
And by the way, I've never really called this out explicitly, but you
can kind of see here what I did in these in both.
These cases is I made sort of a platform nonspecific type which is
what the application deals with and then I made it so that in both
cases there was an easy way for it to be extended now I feel like this
was probably done because we don't really need it to work this way.
We could have done the pointer version here so I think what I might
also
Say is, let's just do that as well and say that these both work
symmetrically, right?
So now there's a, you know, platform file group here, which is just
whatever the, you know, the header is or something, right?
And instead will do that thing where we can, we actually return a
pointer instead of the actual thing, right?
So return a pointer there.
We pass a pointer here, right?
We pass the pointer there and and yeah, that's a little easier.
And then of course, we get rid of the file index.
So yeah, I think that's just we might as well make those symmetric.
But again, so what I was doing there was just saying there's a part of
it that's readable and there's a part of this extended and again,
that's like, you know, we haven't when we get to the entity stuff when
we get to doing the game code, and we're talking about entities, I'll
talk about this again, but basically like C++ has class inheritance
stuff.
Is basically the weakest possible version of the concept of sort of
space-saving for dynamic Union's, right?
And I don't want to go into what that means.
Right now, it's a very important concept and one that the C++
standards committee doesn't understand, unfortunately, but we will
talk about that extensively on the Energy System, but right now,
you're actually seeing a little bit of that.
And this version is the version that C++.
Hand do, which is I have a, I have a structure, whose top is the same
across a couple of different places.
So for example, the win32 platform file handles top where it has.
No errors is going to be the same as the one in say, the Mac platform
layer, but the rest of it will be different.
And that's something that C++ has inheritance model actually can
represent, right?
And so if you want to do inheritance Air Force,
Some reason you could there's really no reason to do it, but you can
if you want to because this is the one kind of of unions unions type
space-saving like you know, basically not being wasteful on the space.
That's a union type takes up its the one kind that CPS can handle out
of the many that you might want to do.
One out of n isn't bad.
It's actually pretty bad.
All right, anyway, so that's what we're doing here.
And so what I want to do is I want to just allocate one of these guys
where we go ahead and say, okay, the platform file group, we allocate
one of those and this time I would like to free it right?
I would, because when it closes down, we don't need to leave it
around.
We don't free this one because we leave the files open forever, right?
We have to read out of those asset files for the entire game.
And so, you know, it's not really an option for us too.
ever free them because the
Game is constantly streaming data from them, but in terms of this
win32 get all files of type end.
That is something that we do actually need to do a little bit more
specifically, so we're going to go ahead and do that.
So, here we go.
Here's went through to platform file group.
So when 22 platform file group go, we allocate one of those.
And then when we return it, we return that file group.
And I guess we just want to cast that off to a
re-platform file group.
Like so when we do the virtual free, we just need to do an if file
group, right?
And this will go ahead and close this.
So if the file group is valid and of course, there are some other
things we want to do there.
I think we probably also want to do something like, went through to
file group.
Probably should do it this way.
All right, to file group.
Pointers.
Yeah.
And that's really so hold on one second here.
I don't want to continue with that just yet, but it's something like
that.
And so, here we go with win32 platform, file group.
And this is going to be the winter do file group again.
We're just going to cast it back to the type that we know it is.
So, on the way out, we cast it into the platform, friendly type, and
on the way and be cast it back because the, you know, we don't want
the platform code to really know about this kind of secret extension.
That way you've buried in at the bottom.
So, there we go.
Assuming that it's actually not null.
Then what we would want to do here is we want to close everything out.
So we want to free the win32 file group, right?
We want to free the memory that we allocated.
I don't actually remember how you got a pass Flags to Virtual free to
what you actually want to do with the memory.
So alright, you got the address the size.
Of course, the we are doing member lease.
So yeah, we're just doing member lease so I think all we want to do is
just pass to Virtual free the base pointer, which is what we're doing
the size, which it says, we don't actually need to do if we are never
actually freeing.
I mean, if we are not D committing, there's two are basically.
You know, if you can look here there's two different things you can do
when you free memory in.
Like this one is you can D commit them so that they're not actually
valid pages to use anymore but they are not actually going to become
available for other virtual Alex to use whereas release on the other
hand will actually completely put the pages back into the freestore,
right?
So that other people can allocate them.
So it's it's basically like if you were going to Alec, you know,
release some and then re Alec it, you wouldn't, you know, you just D
commit it because you know you're going to still use that much memory.
Again, your use that pace, you don't want them to actually go back
into the pool of things reveal to allocate.
Whereas in our case we're fully we're just saying we don't need it
anymore at all right.
So, that's that, and that's really all we would need to do.
But like I said, we want to keep going with the actual invitation here
and assuming that we have a find handle, we're going to want to close
that find handle, right?
So in here, I want to go ahead and check if the win32 file group find
handle is not equal to the invalid handle value.
Then I want to close it, right?
So that's all the spin down that.
I think we would probably need Loops.
That's gonna be an arrow there.
And so all we need to do is just look and see if it is.
We close it, right?
So let's go back up here and see.
So what I did here is I iterated over and I found how many files there
were and I incremented this.
So we knowed, you know, we would know how many there were, right?
so then what I need to do
Is when we actually open the files.
I now need to iterate over the files.
Kind of a second time.
If you will, I need to iterate over the files when we actually go to
open them.
So, I do one iteration first, see how many there are, so I can tell
the app so that the app can allocate it space properly, and then I can
go in here and say, all right, let's iterate over them.
A second time, again, since we're only ever doing this at startup.
We don't really care.
If it's inefficient able to iterate over them twice, it's going to be
incident either way.
So here we go.
And also, you know, there's going to be like on the order of 10 files
or something.
So in here we go.
Ahead and say we want to do the same thing after we're done.
We want to do that fine first file again, right?
And when we do that fine first file this time, we want it to go into
our win32 file group, so that everything is saved as part of the
iteration.
So we open a file Handle by doing fine first file with that file name
and I guess I'll call.
All this wild card.
That's actually more descriptive of what it is.
It's not a filename.
So do fine first file with the wild-card string and then we will put
the results in the find data, okay?
So then what can happen once we do that.
Find first file is down here
When you call win32 open file, we can start by assuming that, you know
we were in some kind of a are estate.
We ran out of files whatever.
Who knows what happened, right.
And then we can see if we actually have a valid iteration if there's
actually more stuff to iterate over and if there is try to open it
from the handle that we actually have, right.
So let's go ahead and do that.
We want to do here is say basically the same thing that we said before
we want to do this.
This right, we want to check to see if the find handle is valid.
And if it is, then we will go ahead and use the data.
So we'll say, if again, we've got our win32 file group, we're going to
have to cast that, you know, as the input parameter.
If the find handle is not invalid, then we know we can try to load the
file, right?
We'll try to load the file and off we go.
If it is equal to invalid handle value will just let the result be 0,
right?
Now, at the end of this, what we need to do is say well, okay, the
next time they call this, we've got a problem because the next time
they call this, they're going to actually they're going to want to get
the next file.
So in order to prevent them from just opening the same file every
time.
What we need to do here is do that find next, right?
We need to do this thing but what happens if we can't do it, right?
We can't break out of a loop because we're not in a loop.
Really?
We're in somebody else's Loop outside, right?
Somebody else's looping over to calling us.
So, when
Do this, this find next.
What's going to happen is we're going to get either.
We're going to get back a find data or we're not right.
And whether this returns true is going to determine that.
If it returns true, they can just call Winter to open file again and
it'll be fine.
If it returns false though, right?
What we would like to do at that point, if it returns false is we'd
like to do the fine clothes right here, right?
We want to make sure that we shut down everything right away.
And then to make sure that
Everyone knows that we shouldn't iterate anymore and to make sure that
this if statement will fail, next time through, we can just set it to
invalid handle value.
Pretty straightforward.
So okay, so I think that's roughly what we would like to have happen.
So now the only question is, when we do this, where do we get this
file name from right?
Where does file name come from?
Because we don't know anymore, right?
So I think we've pretty much done everything that we needed to do, but
that is not going to work.
Oops.
Gotta this file now that we've changed that to a pointer and we should
also do the renaming that I said we would do.
So we had a platform filing handle.
What is it called platform open file.
So we're going to call this open -
File right.
Yeah, so let's take a look at that.
However, I'm open next file.
Next file platform, open.
Next file.
There we go.
Find data.
Why is do I not have that?
Oh, named it wrong.
There we go.
And open next file.
Win32 open.
Next file.
Let's jump back here so now everything's name is changed and that's
all fine and now I just need to make this file name.
Come from somewhere, right?
So luckily like I said, find file kind of does what we want it to do
in terms of finding the actual
Data that we need.
So win32 find data that thing that we've been storing every time we
iterate actually has a see file name in it and see file name actually
is you know it's exactly the right thing.
Now if we actually go and look at this, right?
And you know what don't actually know if I can do this with you guys.
I think I think I can, I don't know if I can't, we'll find out.
I'm gonna load visual studio and you can see that they've highly
optimized that load time there.
Remember, they're not actually
having to load anything this is, you know there's no art assets
basically, you know, but they were like, you know what, it should
probably take several you know,
I know what's been going to be 30 seconds by the time we open this.
We have a you know 16 MB asset footprint to load in our game already
and it launches instantly and they thought that 30 seconds was a good
amount of time to launch something that displays text, which by the
way, they didn't really have to load because that was already the
operating system took care of that.
Probably four of them.
But you know, it's hard out there sometimes when you just have to
display.
Some text.
So anyway, what we want to do now is I just want to see if I can show
you how to I thought about this the other day.
We never really showed how to do it.
I want to see if
To show you how to quickly jump to the definitions of things in the
IDE for Windows for looking stuff up and windows.
And I don't know if this will work, it only does sometimes.
Yeah, it so it wouldn't.
So it doesn't have a way to do.
Go to definition, unfortunately, because I think if you don't build
something in Visual Studio, you can't do that.
But that's a pretty easy way to like jump to the definitions only if
you want to see it rather than having to search.
And so one thing I will occasionally do is if I want to quickly jump
to we're in a header file.
Some windows thing is defined I'll actually make a dummy project so
that I can use the browse info.
It may be the case that you can actually create browse info by passing
a parameter on the command line.
But I don't usually like to pollute my build with that because it's
just extra time that I don't want spent and I rarely actually need
this feature but I just thought I'd mention it.
So yeah, so anyway, when 30 to find data the thing that
I wanted to say about that.
Is I'm assuming that there are two versions of went through to find
data, right?
I'm assuming that there's one for wide and 14 non-wide, right?
So one for an c14 Unicode, right?
Went through to find it a groups, win32, find it out.
So I'm assuming that that's the case.
I don't actually know if that's true or not, but I'm going to go ahead
and do it, the old fashioned way, to way here to see, which one it
actually is right.
So program files x86 Microsoft Visual Studio.
Although I guess this was actually Microsoft platform SDK
Probably do we have the MP the SDK in here?
Hmm.
Microsoft SDK.
Is there it is.
Let's see, windows.
The eight point, who knows?
I don't even know which one of those we want to look at what which one
of those is the right?
18.1 a maybe
Where are the include files here?
They are.
So if I want to in here, I can grab and do win through to find data
and I can just see what the what the actual structure of it is.
They only want the Mappy one, I would want the one in Wind basemap e,
is like some kind of old the old API.
It's like a telephony thing or something.
I don't even remember what it was.
So in win base, here we go.
You can see, we've got winter, you find it at a and went through find.
Aw, so we want the ASCII one, and again, normally you could just use
win32 find data, but since we want to have the code compile, the same
for people who are using Unicode and people who aren't I?
Want to make sure that we're actually using the right one there.
So that should do it and
Really.
We've got each one.
Find next file.
I'm guessing would also require an A and it does.
So there we go.
That needs an a find clothes.
On the other hand, probably not because it doesn't actually return you
any text in that structure.
So I think that's probably all we would really need to do about that.
So there's my create file, a, my finest file a, there we go.
So hopefully I got all those
Those will see if I didn't someone, I'm sure will tell me on the
forums.
So all we really need to do now is just say, oh, the file name.
Yeah, that file name that we needed is actually pretty easy to get,
it's just the file group, it's fine data.
See file name, should give us back the ASCII that we actually need.
And so, let's go ahead and step into this.
I know I've typed a bunch of crazy win32 things here.
So, let's go ahead and jump in and see if all that works.
So, first thing we're going to do is going to allocate one of these
went through, to file groups, right?
And you can see,
That happening there in the virtual Alec and so there you go.
It's the, you know, it's got basically blank, everything, nothing
particularly in there.
And so then the first thing we're going to do is we're going to
initialize the file.
Count 02 already was Zero but just in case it didn't return us zeros.
You know, virtual out doesn't have to return us zeroed memory.
It could return us reuse memory for our own page probably.
So we go ahead and do fine, first file a and that will do it into a
local, the local find data.
Right now we're not going to we're not working into the ones that are
there for iteration.
We're just doing the one for counting and so here you go.
Here's our first find it it's test one dot h, h.h.
Exactly what we would expect.
So we think that file count and we're up to one file.
We do find next file and it goes to the test too, so we can get again.
We do find x file and it goes to test three, so we can get again.
We do find x file and now there's no more files.
So we break out, right?
The find handle is valid because we Loop through
It was able to find that first file.
So then we find clothes and now we see that we have the correct file
count, which is good.
If there's three files we need.
So now we can tell the platform layer outside that that's the truth,
right?
So then what we do is we now we start the iteration that will actually
use to hand things back to the thick to the platform independent
layer.
So we go.
Okay, the find handle.
We find the first file using the wild-card same exact iteration that
we did before and put it.
We want to put it in that, find it.
And then we return our file group back to
The platform independent layer.
So it's going to go through here.
It's going to see what that file county is going to see if 3.
So that's going to come through here and it's going to call open next
file.
When it wants to get whatever the file is.
That comes next in the file Group, which this is the course the first
time since the first file.
So we come in here.
We get our way through to file group, outright all of our handle stuff
is valid and there's that test when ha the first file that we're going
to load, we come through here and we load up you know we allocate
space for that handle it's going to be permanent.
You can never freeze going to be open for the entire run of the
application.
We then,
Ahead and grab out the C file name which is that test one?
Aha.
And then we try to load that right?
The load succeeded.
So we're all good.
We have no errors and then we're going to try and advance to the next
file.
We succeed in advancing the next file, so everything's good.
We keep going.
Right?
So now we're just behaving exactly in the same way as we would have
behaved in the case, where I'd hard-coded it, right?
We're getting exactly the same results.
So that's good.
Come back through here.
Now, we open the next file.
Same path again.
Executing only this time.
It's executing on.
H.
@J to again same as as before.
All we really need to do now is see what happens just to make sure
what happens when we do open next file and there's no more files left.
So it goes ahead and open site ha3 and then it does a find x file to
see.
Okay, there are no more files.
So let's close the handle.
Let's set the handle equal to about handle value and now we will go
ahead and exit out the loop, right?
We'll call the end function.
It's going to look, it's going to cast it.
It's going to see that it's the close.
It already closed out the iteration, so it doesn't need to clean up
that handle.
In fact.
We'd only ever really need to clamp that handle if the app stopped
iterating early and then we're going to go ahead and free that went
through to file group.
So that goes back to the operating system and doesn't take up any more
space, right?
So there we go.
So now we're doing as you know, many or as few HHA files as are in the
directory and which is that's what we wanted.
The only thing that
R not doing now is we do not actually support specifying?
What the extension is, the wild card is hard-coded, right?
So, what we might want to do here, we've got five minutes left in the
Stream.
We might want to go ahead and just finish up this API so that it works
as we originally expected to work where we said, okay, you know what,
we want to pass in that Cara star type.
So we basically
Thing here is that Stipe and we want to make sure that that, you know,
that that can actually be respected.
So, what I want to do is say we've got the wild card here,
The wild-card is just going to be some little buffer fun, right?
And it's going to look like that, it's going to be star dot something.
And so then what I'm going to do is say, okay, we're going to copy
whatever the extension isn't that.
They told us into the end of the wild-card buffer, right?
And so that's pretty straightforward, right?
All I'm going to do is say for wild card, you know, index equals to,
you know, it's going to be at the second location.
Wild card index is less than size of.
Card write Plus Wild Card index.
And then I'm just going to do you know, Wild Card, Wild Card index
equals type at something like that.
Right.
I'm just going to merge those things together.
And again, you know,
I usually write this sort of string stuff by hand, as you can see.
if I know that I just don't have much string stuff happening,
But if you were Mister, has tons of stuff to do a strings, you would
want to stop and write some string, utilities for yourself, right?
You don't really need to write these every time and it doesn't take
very long to write yourself a good string system.
So if you're, you know, don't go writing everything by hand like this.
It's not a good idea to write it.
If you're, you know, this is we're only have like four or five things,
whatever we ever do with strings, and so, it's just not that
necessary.
But
It's something to think about, right?
Like if you, if you found yourself doing this a lot, you would want to
stop and go, oh, wait a minute, you know, I can just make a string
library for myself and see and then I just can call convenient things
whatever I want, right?
And that's, you know, going to be better.
So, okay, so if I do type that equals type, and then I go through
here, I can do something like
You know, keep copying until the type is 0.
So I guess I would say something more like this if star type at equals
0 break out the loop.
Otherwise, go ahead and Advance, write something like this and you
know, just to make sure you're always null terminated.
You could just do something like that.
So, anyway, oops, probably want to actually make that an index.
So yeah.
So just, you know, want to put together something really fast and
dirty to make sure that we can fulfill the entire set of things that
we said the API could do.
Oops, for some reason that had trouble loading, the PD, I guess.
That's why.
That is because that is supposed to be brackets.
There we go.
So in we come, we make our type app, right?
And our wild card.
There it is.
We come through here and we copy, you know, that on h.h.
a we get to the null Terminator, we copy the notes area around, we
break and now we're done, right?
So that's it.
Nothing nothing fancy and and that's the whole API.
That's All She Wrote.
So I feel like that brings that sort of the whole thing about loading
asset pack files, right?
Sort of to a nice clothes.
We've got most of stuff we wanted.
There's some extension things we could consider doing, I don't know if
we want to do them all.
Like, I've got a couple in here that that I was sort of, you know,
pointing out in in handmade file format, study H.
Right?
I talked about the ability.
To remove assets.
And there's also the concept of like a Primacy number for asset files
where you would say kind of like which files had precedence over which
other files.
So, there's a couple things that we could add in here and maybe should
add in here and so I don't know, maybe we'll take a look at tomorrow
and just say, you know, maybe tomorrow on Friday, we'll just do some
due diligence and say.
Okay let's let's maybe take one more spin through the asset stuff, you
know, to like go ahead and add
Some like support for some slightly Advanced features or looking in
that direction of advanced features just so we can see if anything
jumps out at us as like oh we've kind of paint ourselves into a corner
here or whatever.
I don't know that it's a really big deal because we can always just
reprocess all our assets anytime we want.
So it's not like these asset files are things that have to be locked
down until we actually ship the game but you know it's something you
know we did the work we might as well take a day or two to sit back
and go okay, what you know what might we want as additional features.
Is here.
So with that in mind, let's go ahead and go to the Q&A.
If you have questions about what we did on tonight's stream, you
should ask them now by putting Q: in front of your question and typing
it into the twitch chat so I can see it and answer it.
Yeah.
So the only question I see right now is the fact that sit that D
Seven, Samurai actually was telling someone else to prefix their
question with q: but I don't know what the question is.
there was
Does the save file need to use this system?
Now, I don't think the save file would need the save file.
Honestly, what we'll probably do is sort of slightly change the debug
load entire file stuff to be the save file because honestly to save
files, probably not going to be partially loaded like this.
So no II don't.
We haven't done a save file yet.
Right?
Like we haven't done saved state so but I don't know.
I don't assume that it would really
Because save files don't really load piecemeal.
Usually you usually load in the whole save file so you don't really
need this additional API layer that we put in here.
This is specifically for asset loading because asset, loading is
really pretty important, right?
But you know, I guess now that I say it, there's no reason we couldn't
yeah, I mean maybe we just could
Because that we would just call get all files of type and it would
give us back all the save files or whatever and then we just, you
know, open them up I guess I don't know.
I don't know if it's a good question.
How do you feel now that you've finished this?
Well,
it always feels good to finish some stuff.
I like the way the assets time is come out, I think our tag query
system is awesome, actually.
And you know I mean it's been I don't know, it's been a couple weeks,
it hasn't been more than a handful of hours like you know, 15 hours.
I don't know how many hours have been very few hours and we coded in a
system.
That's awesome.
It's streams.
It does tag queries it like merges asset files together.
Like if you look at this it's pretty darn great.
There's a lot of games that ship with you know asset systems that are
so much worse than this and we did it in 15 hours.
So I think we did a good job, like I'm pretty pleased with it and you
know are there?
Some things will probably have to add to
The future and things will have to change maybe but you know, it's
pretty darn cool so far.
D Seven Samurai, so capex insist that the STL is the language and that
you therefore should use strings from it.
Oh, so yeah.
Like you never want to use the sdl.
Sdl is a very, very bad idea.
And, you know, you don't have to take my word for it, basically, like
all programmers.
I know her, any good say don't use the STL right?
It's not like I'm the one guy who says, you know, I don't have like a
weird opinion not to use the sdl.
The SDS gel is really, really bad and strings.
Sdl strings are actually one of the
The one of the worst parts of it.
Julie.
So I would highly recommend never using the sdl or the strings.
They're from
It's just a really bad idea and that dates, you know, that's true
today and it's been true for the entire history of the STL.
I remember actually one of the first times I was working with other
programmers and we were using the SEL strings way back when it was,
you know, it was like,
Gosh, I don't even know maybe 1998 1998.
And, you know, the game was taken a really long time to compile was
taking minutes to compile, you know, and I went and looked, and I was
like, why is this taking so long to compile?
And I know most of the stuff that I know now about how to design an
architect code, right?
So, if I, if I would be looking at code Base today, I would have been
like, delete the whole thing.
It's did.
None of this is useful or salvageable.
I can rewrite all of this in a week, right?
But at that time, you know.
Have very much experience so I don't know.
So I'm looking at it and I'm like, what is taking so long to compile
and it turned out that STDs colon colon string?
If you just replaced there instead of everywhere we use this their
standard string class with our own.
I just made my own little small string class to replace it with and
the compile times went you know, it was like something laughable.
It's been so long.
I don't remember.
It was one of these things was like it was 10 minutes and it went down
to like one minute or something and it was like what but it's you know
the SEL is
Just really bad, right?
It's architected extremely poorly.
And so what ends up happening, is you use any one thing from the sdl.
It starts pulling in all of these templates and the templates just
crushed the compiler with compile time thinking that it has to do for
no real reason, right?
All you wanted to do was have a care Star, right?
And suddenly, it's pulling in all sorts of stuff that has to be.
Specialized thinking about what, you know what, the default template
parameters are and then regenerate.
And then that gets stuffed into the C file and there's tons of C files
and balls.
I'll go
Plug up the Linker and it's just a disaster, right?
So yeah, never never, never, ever use the sdl for anything.
If you're actually talking about production code and a code base, you
care about if you're just screwing around, you know, totally fine, but
never ever, ever, use something from the sdl, it's just, it's an awful
idea and certainly not strings.
Mara Moto could you elaborate on the union style inheritance?
You mentioned in the same vein will entities end up being unions.
So entities I don't know what entities will end up being in this game
because like I said before, this game is a little bit unique and I
picked, I picked some of the game design things about this game
specifically, so I could show you.
How to tackle very difficult programming.
Blooms in the game, play code, right?
Because we could just do a game where it's like, oh, you know, there's
10 types of entities, there is a monster and there's a block, right?
And that's kind of what we've got in there now, is the Prototype code,
right?
But that's just not that interesting to me and I don't think that's
going to show you the kinds of that.
That's, that's like, you know, that's kind of bush-league at some
level, right?
So I decided to make the design, extremely difficult in, make it so
that we there was no way you were ever going to make that work.
So, I have an idea of how I wanted to try to do.
It was something I've been thinking about where I was like, I kind of
want to try the style and I don't know if it'll work or not.
So we will try a very interesting thing.
That's not really unions and it's also not not unions.
It's kind of like a half Union half not Union and we'll see if it
works.
If it doesn't work well to try some other things, but that's like,
kind of the whole point.
Like I said, many times the point of this series is not for me to show
you a bunch of things.
I already know how to do the point of this series is for me to show
you some things.
I know how to do so that now you know how to do them.
But more importantly to show you how I
Go about figuring out how to do something.
I don't know how to do because me, figure out something.
I don't know how to do is how I'm trying to show you, how you can
figure out things, you don't want to do, I'm so sorry, figure out
things.
You don't want to do because that's where a lot of the interesting
challenges in programming arise, right?
It's like, I want you to be able to do things that I don't know how to
do, right?
I want you to be able to figure out things that I don't know how to do
if I only ever taught people on the stream, how to be exactly the
programmer?
I am, that's not really that useful because you need to go solve your
own problems that are unique to your game.
And if I've never shown you how to solve those problems, you won't be
able to make your game.
Right?
And so, yeah, so what we'll be doing for the any system is it about
will be one of those big challenges where you get to watch me, you
know, flail around, and probably fail a bunch of times to get the
right architecture.
And then we'll get it, it'll be like, okay.
And then we've had a good example of like, okay, here's how you solve
a hard coding problem when you don't know the answer going into it,
right?
And so like any situation like that, all I have right now is a vague
idea of how I think, maybe
be interesting way to solve it and I have no idea if it'll pan out,
right?
And if it doesn't pan out, then I've got to come up with another idea
and try that and you know, off you go.
What's a quarrel.
So, what about updating, the asset file with more files?
How do you manage a ton assets as in knowing what is where
I'm not sure what that means.
Exactly, the way that we've done things, you don't need to know
anything about what is where right?
It's all tag query-based.
So you just say I need a hero who's 25 years old and has brown hair or
something, right?
And if there is one of those the asset value, get it back.
If there isn't it gives you back one with like blond hair whatever the
closest match was because hey no one drew it, right?
So you never need the game never needs.
Doesn't care where the assets come from at all.
It doesn't yet at that any idea,
Well, the ASCII version of fine freestyle work even if the full file
path has Unicode in it.
So,
The way we're doing it.
Yes, I believe so.
But I don't know if it would work if you did it, a slightly different
way.
So if you went in here and tried to put a path in here, and the path
was unicode.
I don't know if there's any way to onion a coat it to pass it to the
Fine first file a right?
We don't have to pass a path to find x file and finally style, doesn't
have to return us a path because it's just using the current working
directory.
So I don't think it cares whether the path has Unicode in it or not,
right?
But if you were to do something slightly different right where you
weren't doing it that way and you tried to pass the path through, you
might have a problem.
So if you were trying to do,
Like that, I would say you might want to switch to using the find next
file W for that.
Will pre-rendered fonts be included into the h a file?
Yes.
Is this the new Call of Duty?
Yes, this is Call of Duty.
12 is basically so I don't know if you saw before.
So you know what, I'll just I'll just bring it up for you.
So this is a cyber scanned mesh.
You can see here of Kevin Spacey, right?
And you know, like I said on hammy hero we're still kind of working on
the enginetech right now, it's not final and so, when we scan in his
head you can see.
It doesn't really look like Kevin Spacey exactly.
The eyes are correct, obviously, but the face is a little odd.
And so when we actually finish, the enginetech will re cyberspace
Kevin Spacey, he'll come in for a callback, that's like part of the
contract.
So it's not.
We have to pay another 15 million for that.
It's just, it's just part of the contract.
So you know, he'll come in will cyber scan them and then it will have
the proper Kevin Spacey head that's on there.
And, you know, then it'll be obvious that it's called Duty, right?
Whereas before it was a little nebulous.
So,
Pseudonym 73.
Okay, real question about the directory.
Walking API, does the requirement to call find clothes?
Make more sense.
When you consider that fine, first change in education, find next
change notification.
Refresh directory are part of the same API
It would make some sense if those had actually been part of the API,
but they weren't is my recollection.
Those are added after the fact.
So they main like, excuse it, a little more now but I'm pretty sure
those were actually added in XP across.
We're not gonna be able to figure that out, I guess from this.
Yeah.
I don't know how you figure out.
Okay, so find first, files been there for like since Windows 95,
right?
And I'm pretty sure that directory change notification was only in
like either 2000 or XP, right?
I could be wrong about that but anyway, so, you know, does it make
sense?
Maybe more?
I don't know.
I mean, what I would say is,
what I would say is the fine clothes isn't the worst part of it
necessarily it does seem kind of unnecessary, but you know
I I'd be okay with it.
What I would like to see is I don't know if this is okay.
We'll see if it is in a second here.
So if I were to do oops, you know what that wasn't the way to test it
but I meant to do is this
So since you can pass invalid handle value to it, and it doesn't seem
like it's upset.
I would say that that's probably okay, you know, I'm not too mad about
that because you could just say just write the code like that and it's
not error-prone right, you know.
That's, is that the end of the world though?
So, you know, I'm not, I'm not too, I'm not gonna fire anyone for
that.
Mostly I'm going to fire them for the fact you have to do this
two-step version and you can't do the clean for a loop that's that's
most of the firing.
How are you doing the audio?
The the audio we covered in.
There's a bunch of streams on it.
If you look at the
I'm not sure what you mean, by how we doing it?
We wrote code for audio like two weeks ago.
You can see it in the video archive on, you know, I'm handmade hero
dot-org.
If you go to the or, you know, it's a better place value would be to
go to forums and go to the episode guide and scroll down and just
find, you know, audios and here somewhere.
Let's see, there we go.
Right here.
So introduction to sound mixing implement the sound mixer streaming
large audio chunks.
The stuff.
So,
You wrote code for lineage forever, any comment on writing it on the
game.
Any other lineage games?
Any age one, pretty much spark my entire career as a computer
scientist programmer.
So, okay, just to be clear.
I didn't write code for lineage forever.
There's like thousands of games out there that have my code running in
it, because I worked for rad game tools, where we make licensable game
libraries.
So like the people who made lineage if I'm in the credits or
something.
I don't know how you're determining that that was the case, but
however you determined that was the case.
If it says that I wrote code for it, what that's referring to the fact
that I wrote like the character animation system or something.
Right?
That they licensed in used but I
Have like any, I didn't have any employees influence on the game, just
on their character Tech, right?
So I don't really have any comment on it because, you know, it really
doesn't have much to do with me.
It's like I wrote the code that did some portion of the game engine.
But I wasn't, you know, I wasn't there in Korea, you know, sitting in
an office, talking to them about it, or something like that, right?
I did meet those guys, once when we were over there, a bunch of us
were giving some talks at the convention over there.
I did meet the language guys, and we like, sat down with them at their
office.
And, you know, just hung out and talked for a little while as best we
could.
You know, we didn't speak perfect Korean and they didn't speak perfect
English.
I'll be Austrian speak any Korean really.
We knew how to say, like, please, and thank you, but they spoke
English, you know, okay.
And we had a translator with us.
So we were able to kind of talk a little bit and
So that was a lot of fun and it was cool and if they did use my code
in their game and that's awesome.
I'm glad to hear that.
I know a lot of people like lineage but you know when the reality is
when you make game technology, sometimes if you happen to be making
the Technologies for one specific game, then you might have an effect
on the game, but if really you're just making technology and people
are licensing.
It, you know, for the people who work on the Unreal Engine, for
example, there's a bunch of games out there that are powered entirely
by the Unreal Engine.
The people who make them realize I may have never even
Then talk to that team, right?
They may have just taken in religion built our game and so it's like
how much effective John the?
Yeah.
Well, you know, yeah, we made the game possible by making this piece
of technology and in that sense, we contributed certainly but did we
really have anything to do with the way, the, like ideas for the game
or how the game was tuned or the artwork?
And it's like not really other than being someone who enabled it to
happen, we, you know, and that is the entirety of my contribution to
lineage forever to the extent that I have code.
Game.
Which I don't even know, to be honest, it would have been because they
license something from rad that I worked on.
What's after the asset file loading asset memory management.
We haven't done our virtual memory management yet that's going to be
tricky.
So that's that's that's what it is.
Captain does.
I know you've heard this before, but I don't really understand your
explanation.
Why do you use pound Defiance for things like platform, get all files
of type begin instead of just normal function call.
Well, we can't do a normal function called per se, we have to, at
least do a typedef, right?
And the reason is because we store pointers to them, right?
So if you remember, like the way that this stuff works, this is only
for stuff in the platform layer, right?
So, if we look at open like next file, like the one we did today,
right?
It needs to have a pointer here because the platform API has a bunch
of pointers.
It's a little dispatch table, right?
And so, if you look at, we just made it, we made a typedef of it.
And the reason that I like to do the pound defying is because then my
typedef can use the pound to find.
And so, can the actual definition of the function.
So if I ever want to change it, I can just change it in one place.
That's all it is.
Haven't filed lace episodes due to do to.
I'm actually watching it from the beginning.
But is there any like crypting in save files regarding cheating Etc?
so, you know,
I get a chuckle out of that only because remember everyone gets a copy
of the source code when they buy the game.
So what cryptography could I possibly do?
Any encryption of the save file?
I showed you how to write on the stream.
So everyone's going to know how to decrypt it, right?
So yeah, I mean if if you can figure out some way for us to do that,
well, that would probably be pretty awesome breakthrough in
cryptography, actually, if you think about it right away that someone
could know the cryptography algorithm and yet still be and the key
everything, right?
They have all the information but still not somehow be able to access
the save file, you know?
so,
So yeah, I don't know.
That's seems like a provably impossible problem but
I'm all ears.
Infinite, Loop a tasks.
Are there any books on game programming, or general programming that
you could recommend?
You know, the problem is that I just am not aware of what's available
right now for books.
So I can't really recommend something.
Most of the books that I read when I was learning programming
I read the C programming language by kernighan and Ritchie, and I
think that's still probably pretty good book to read to learn.
See the books.
I read about C++, or all bad.
I didn't know they're about the time, but I like red.
You know?
I read design patterns.
I read Effective.
C++, I read the the LSD book.
I remember what that one's called is the purple book with the purple
cover.
You know, I read all those, I read the C++ report like Ida
subscription everything.
So I knew C++, look backwards and forwards in 1999.
You're in 2000, you know?
But in retrospect, all of those books are just bad information,
they're all not good.
So, pretty much all the books I read during when I was programming, I
wish I just hadn't read besides maybe the kernighan and Ritchie see
book.
Now, there may be some good books out there on program.
But I just don't know what they are.
And by the time that I realize that all those books were garbage, I
was already a good enough programmer to not really be reading books
about programming per se.
I would more be reading things about like specific types of algorithms
stuff, right?
Like, you know, maybe you know there's a good book on like Matrix
solving algorithm something like that's more what I would read.
So hopefully there are some good parenting books out right now.
I don't know but unfortunately I can't say because I'm
Very old, right?
I mean, it's like I'll be 39 this year.
So when you think about the books that I would have been reading, when
I was learning to program, you know, they're they're decades old at
this point and so, you know, the ones I read as a little kid, but be
like the kernighan and Ritchie see book and then when I was like 18 or
19, I read, I was reading about to those C++ books.
Because that was what was in Vogue at the time, partying, wise.
And, you know, they're just, they're just trashed.
They're not even worth the paper.
They're printed on,
What do you think about game engine architecture by Jay Gregory the
book looks solid?
I don't know.
I've never read it.
So, I couldn't really tell you, I'm sorry.
Quetzalcoatl says I meant the artist is making files.
How do you track what you added and what you didn't?
What assets have changed and need updating that kind of thing.
So, that's not really in the scope of what we're doing.
We're only dealing with the runtime package on handmade hero.
Art pipeline is, like I've said, from the beginning is not something
we're going over, right?
So that's Upstream, what I would say is usually that's a separate
system that as a separate infrastructure because it has to track a ton
of data that has nothing to do with game with it running.
Name.
And so I tend to, I don't, some people merge those and they ship their
game with a giant sweet of garbage.
That was just all stuff.
That was only necessary for when they were developing the game and
after shipping it, and I don't like that.
So I try not to do that.
So I have separate systems for runtime and ship.
I've heard of it Dev Time and ship.
So you know, for handmade hero, the way I would do it is I would have
a separate system for that but for this game I won't even really do
that because yangshin kind of feels like only do an hour a day and
Yanks and kind of just does our assets on spec because of the nature
of the project.
We don't have a lot of iterative art kinds of stuff going on so that's
more of the stuff I do for the other Molly Rocket game.
The the one that's, you know, we're doing development on not on
stream.
Mmmmm.
Is the graphics double buffered.
So it depends what you mean by double buffered, right?
There's a lot of things people may be trying to say when they ask it
something to buffered.
And so in one sense, the graphics is not double buffered and in that
in the sense in which it is not double buffer.
It is right now in our software because we're entering and software
right now.
We just composite to a bitmap and then later.
Give we copy that bitmap to Windows, right?
So
You know, we don't see a flicker or a tear because Windows compositor
is like the second buffer in a to buffer scheme, right?
Possibly a three buffer stream depending on how Windows is
implementing it probably three buffer scheme.
Really
So you might not call it double buffered or you might decide to call
it double buffer because we have the buffer that we can pause it into
and then Windows also has its buffer, right?
There are other types of things people mean, when they might say
double buffered, they might be talking about page slipping, right?
And we're not doing that and there's other sort of things like that.
So you know, I guess I would say it depends on really what you were
trying to ask in terms of what you want to know about the buffering of
the graphics.
When are you going to stream your hands coding would be neat?
You talked about doing it sometime sometime.
When I'm not actually doing the real Hamid hero stream because I'm
trying to, I want those to come to uniform and the way that I talk and
stuff should be right.
So maybe sometime will, you know, point a camera at it and just do a
thing where I'm just, I don't know, coding something that's not him a
hero.
Qw any pro.
Well, just because people would know how to beat the encryption
doesn't mean it would be a bad thing to teach us in the series.
Well, you know, I mean, I don't know how I feel about that.
Like I don't like the idea of preventing people from editing their
savegame files.
It seems very antagonistic to the user.
so,
I don't know.
And the other thing I would say is it's a losing battle because they
have the encryption algorithm, it's on their machine.
It's just a machine code, not source code.
So anyone who wants to reverse engineer, it eventually will be able to
write.
So I would say the thing I would probably teach on the stream would be
if that really what you actually really really want to do is make it
so that people can hack their savegame files, you need to come up with
a better way of doing the savegame files like you need to make it so
that it's a server side that the the server you have game servers in
the servers.
The same in the service, save the state, so that they never have
access to the safe on the first place, right?
Or something like this.
Again, I don't really like that idea.
It sounds very antagonistic to the player, the player, but the game to
have fun, and if the way that they want to have fun as to act are
saved in files, they should be able to do so.
Have you read The Tao of programming?
No, I have not.
Insofar as does it tear with arrow disabled?
Um, so I don't really know because, remember, we have not done the
final, you know, sort of display code because the final display code
would go through, you know, opengl for example, right?
Because that's the more tested path.
So, right now, we're just using the blind path because I wanted people
to not have to learn the opengl boilerplate necessary, to flip with
opengl,
Before we were done with the graphics like I wanted people to get into
the grabs quickly.
So I just showed them how to just blit their bitmap directly to the
screen, right?
That's what we do.
So what I'm assuming is that in order to know whether you would tear
sometimes with arrow disabled is you'd have to know more about how
they how Windows chose to implement stretch split.
And I don't know because you never use it anymore.
Like we won't be shipping handmade hero calling stretch split, right?
Even if when the software renderer is running will still go through
opengl because that's like the path that the you know, the hard work
that the the OS expects.
And so we want to make sure that we're doing things like other people
do because otherwise windows will probably break you accidentally.
Like they'll you know, they'll update the thing, when they tried to
fix the van engine, they screwed up stretch split or something, right?
And now nothing works.
So you tried it, you want to keep
Yourself on this path that the drivers and everyone are used to seeing
so that you will be as maximally compatible as possible, you know?
Alright, think that's it for today.
Let's go ahead and close this down.
Here we go.
Okay, everyone.
Thank you very much for joining me for this episode of handmade hero.
It's a pleasure coding with you.
As always, we have finished up our asset file stuff in.
So, you know, tomorrow, I guess what we'll do is, we'll take a little
look if there's anything that we would like to add.
That's in addition to sort of what our stated goals were.
Just take a little look over it and see, you know, is there anything
that we want to add?
How would we add it?
Does it impact the design at all?
Just do a little
Like check to make sure now that we've seen everything and everything
is working.
Is there anything that we really need to think about in terms of that
design?
So we'll do that tomorrow.
If you'd like to join me for that, that would be 5 p.m.
Pacific Standard time tomorrow right here on Twitch.
Also tomorrow, I will be speaking at the Intel Buzz Workshop, downtown
at the impact Hub and I have asked Intel to stream it live to you on
handmade hero channel on Twitch and they were super
Super excited to do that.
So in less we screw it up.
We're gonna try, it's not my specialty live streaming.
And you know, I don't they I don't think they're streaming anything
else or they're doing it.
Just for just for you guys.
Basically, they're doing it and so hopefully it will go off without a
hitch.
If it doesn't, we will, at the very least, be trying to salvage a
video file from it, that I can post later.
So, hopefully, the the lecture that I give there will be viewable by
you either live or slightly afterlife, one of the other
So if you want to tune in for that, I think it's going to be around
115.
Pacific Standard time tomorrow.
I start pacific daylight time tomorrow about 115 and so hopefully
that'll go well, but of course, you know, if you're subscribed to the
handmade, he wrote which page it should send you one of those little
notifications.
It says, we've gone live so hopefully that will all work.
We'll see.
We'll do our best but if not, we'll try to recover if we can't.
So anyway, hope to see you there for either both of those
And hey, if you can make it to impact Hub in person, be great to see
you at the event, to be sure to say hi.
Until then, if you want to follow along with handmade hero and you
like playing with the source code at home, you can always pre-order
the game on handmade hero dot-org and it comes with the source code.
Every night I upload the latest updates, we've done.
You could download them and you can play around with them.
And of course we have the complete video archive of everything in the
series.
You can jump all the way back to episode one and see exactly how to
set up the build environment and follow it all the way through.
So you, every last little detail, right?
It's pretty cool.
If you would like to ask questions, we also have a forum site.
You can go to post questions about the source code itself like that,
and it has Community made ports to Mac and Linux which is pretty cool.
And it also has a annotate episode guide that members the community
have been working on which allows you to more quickly, catch up with
old episodes and see where stuff was said or worked on.
We also have a patreon page if you want to support the video series,
that's the place to do it.
You can always subscribe to that.
And then finally, we also have a tweetbot which will tweet the
schedule at you.
And that's a pretty
Good place to go.
If you just want to know, when the series is going to be live and you
want to catch a live stream.
So that's about it again.
Lot of stuff going on tomorrow.
Hopefully it'll all go reasonably.
Well, if not, it'll be a colossal Trainwreck.
But you know what?
That's just the nature of live coding sometimes.
What can you do?
Either way, at the very least, I should see you back here.
Tomorrow night, or Friday at 5 p.m.
Pacific Standard Time, pacific daylight time on the standard Stream.
So if everything goes completely Haywire tomorrow, I guess I'll see
you Friday, but hopefully, I'll see you twice tomorrow and everything
will go swimmingly.
So, until then, take it easy.
Everyone have fun programming and I will see you on
the internet.