Alright, hello everyone, and welcome to handmade hero.
The show where we code an entire game from scratch live on Twitch
know, libraries, no engines.
So we can see, absolutely everything that has to go on to make a game
actually work.
And there's a fantastic amount of stuff in there that has to go on to
make a game work and it can be really fascinating to kind of get in
there and see all the all the stuff that happens.
I think.
Anyway, it's it's really interesting to me and I hope it's interesting
to you as well.
We are on day 50 right now and we are just about to finish up the sort
of collision detection.
If that we were doing basically what we're in the middle of right now
is a pass over the code at the beginning where we're basically
spec'ing out everything that we want in our engine.
So we're doing basically crappy versions of all of the things that we
think we will need to make the game Run properly so that we have some
functional skeleton in place that we can look at and go.
Okay.
We see how everything works together.
We see what the requirements basically are for each thing.
Now, when we go do industrial-strength versions of each of these
pieces of code, first of all, we have the other pieces of code in
place working, if albeit, Janka lie, which is kind of important, so we
can see how things work together as we make new components.
But also its so that when we go off and make a new component and we're
trying to do a like a good high quality version of it.
We're not doing that in a vacuum because when you do when you do stuff
like that in a vacuum, you tend to make a lot of mistakes in terms of
how it will interface with other things.
And you forget certain requirements that
Maybe you wouldn't have thought of if you hadn't have looked at the
usage code first.
So always write the usage code.
First big, big Mantra of mine.
And and that is exactly what we're doing.
We've gotten to the point where we have a question sector that
basically, actually already works.
It works better than I thought it was going to work.
I thought this version was going to be jankier.
That was but it's not at the moment, but that's okay.
Because we still have a feature to add to it anyway, so I'm going to
do a little bit more on the closure before we put it to bed and say,
okay everything else is going to happen with questions, directions,
going to
And when we do the, the final version of it, but there is one more
thing that I want to do because I think it's relatively important to
have something like it in place, and that is basically area-based
questions doctor.
So, we'll talk about that in a second for now.
If you are one of the fine fellows who has pre-ordered handmade hero
from him a hero dot-org, you will note that today.
We are on day 50, which means that if you download the source code
that comes with the game from last night's post day, 49 source code is
in there unzipped.
Day 49 zip into a directory and you'll be right where I am today.
So if you want to follow along that is the day to use.
Okay, let's get started here.
Let's take a look at where we were so we did some debugging.
Yesterday.
Our Collision sector is now unfortunately, more solid than I would
have wanted it to be.
So we basically have two things to do today.
One is that we have to actually do gliding now.
Like we want to be able to Glide along edges, instead of stop.
And the other is I would
To have area-based question section, you'll notice that it's just
point basically induction right now.
It's that point at the base of his feet so he can kind of go into
objects lately, which we don't want either.
So our base is just going to fix those two things today.
That's our primary goal.
The first one is probably a little harder than the second one in terms
conceptually because we already did what I already talked about the
math behind the skating.
So you kind of already know what we're going to do there.
And so right now all we really need to talk about is is how we're
going to do that sort of that area based stuff.
And so, I guess, what I'll do is I'll start off with that because in
case that takes the whole time, we can always do skating on Monday.
And the skating is like I said, we were talking about the mass, so
it's not going to be as big of as big of an investment.
So let's talk about what's going on here, over on the Whiteboard, or
as we would might call the tan board.
So as it kinda looks like a chalkboard now, so what we were doing,
right?
The way we Implement our Collision Vector is we wanted to start doing
Collision detection, where we knew when we would hit a wall in
Of just taking a point that we were, at a point that we were trying to
go to over one time step, right?
This is one time, step one frame and saying is this inside something
or not?
Right?
And when we did that, that was problematic because it meant that we
couldn't do skating.
Like we would want to do and there's a bunch of other problems that we
were going to have that like tunneling.
There are, there are problems with doing it this way.
So what we decided to do was switch to a method, where we actually
solve for the time at which we would hit something.
So we solve for that intersection point.
So now we know,
Between the two points.
We actually check all if the any Collision could have happened along
there, right?
But in order to do that, we made a simplifying assumption, which is we
simplify it down to checking a line versus whatever the shape is that
we were Collision testing against?
In this case.
We were too close and talking against four walls of a tile.
And in that simplification down to a line, obviously that means that
the person that that little fellow in there, he doesn't have any area
at all.
He's just a point, right?
He's a point moving along a line.
That's all we're testing.
So we need to do is now talk about how to make him a little bigger.
And I'm going to use the simplification in that.
We're just going to make him rectangular because that's going to make
it easier for us to implement because we're not doing the file
conjecture now, but
I'm going to talk about is actually going to be the same, the actual
theory behind it is the same no matter what shape he is.
And so I'm going to talk about him as if he was a circle as well and
stuff like that.
Just so that you understand, that conceptually the way that we're
thinking about, this actually doesn't matter, but implementation wise,
you have to step up to slightly stronger algorithms, if you want to
use dissimilar shapes and I'll explain why in a second.
So what we're doing here is we're going to talk about something called
the minkowski sum.
Also, the minkowski difference.
And what's interesting about this?
Is that like minkowski algebra?
There's there's like Mankowski was probably a pretty cool dude.
I don't really know anything about him, but I suspect that.
Actually has a lot to say about a lot of things and unfortunately, I
am one of those people who only learned enough about what he did to do
Collision detection.
So really, it's one of those things that's like on the bucket list.
I would love to go read all and actually really understand all of his
algebra stuff and how he worked with shapes and everything because I
suspect that there's probably some really cool stuff that I could do
if I understood it.
And I don't, I don't I never learn enough of it to really know.
So I
Going to tell you what is basically, the game version of Mankowski,
some indifference, which is the stuff.
We need to know about the work he did.
Oh my, I'm losing.
My voice is going to be a Gravely one.
Which is the stuff we need to know about what he did to basically do
what we need to do for Collision detection.
Okay, so essentially what you could think about it is imagine I had
two walls with a gap between them.
Okay.
And these walls each have.
Let's say if we took their Center, I guess it's hard to call it
necessarily a radius because it's not a circle but imagine there's
like a radius which basically says, you know, how the dimension here,
right?
They have a dimension of something and we'll call that will call that
I don't know s for now.
Okay.
So basically these walls have a dimension of s so they are to S this
way and to S this way they're squares.
Let's say okay and then I've got my guy.
Right, and I've got my guy here and he lets say has a radius of our,
so he's to our this way to our that way.
And when I do my Collision detection, what I want to do is I want to
drive him through here.
Right?
And we can see just intuitively that he's too large to fit.
So there's no way that you're going to fit this, this opening is less
than two are, right.
So there's no way he should be able to fit through here.
But obviously, if we were doing Collision detection, the way I talked
about doing it in a simpler form, when I was teaching how to do that,
basic line intersection.
Well, if he shrinks down to a point, he'd fit through there.
No problem.
We can easily pass raised through there.
There's tons of raise that would pass straight on through there and
not have a problem.
So the question is, what could we do?
That would make it so that we could still do Collision detection,
continuously along a ray like that along a line, so that we actually
get analytic and we know we don't tunnel through anything.
What would we do to do that?
So that we could still solve it with a guy who had an actual size to
it and not just a point.
And so the interesting answer from Mankowski is that you can actually
do a form of algebra on shapes.
So in much, the same way that you might imagine having something like
a plus b equals c, write an equation like you would learn in high.
Algebra, or even earlier, you could imagine saying?
Oh, well, if I want to talk just about a I can move the B to the other
side and say it's a equals c minus B, right?
And, and these are two ways of writing the same thing.
That's really handy.
Right?
Because this allows us even just those basic operations allow us.
To do a lot of things.
We've already used that a ton of times in all the code that we've
written just so far in the game and will use it, a ton more algebra,
just really handy.
Those.
Operations of being able to move things to either side and and talk
about what a particular variable equals.
If you have some kind of hairy equation over here.
It's pretty cool.
Right?
And it's very powerful.
Well, we can actually do stuff like that with shapes as well.
What we can do, if we essentially think of this as being a point,
Right?
That has this radius here and that radius is what gives its volume.
Instead of thinking this as a half and to cast, right?
Like what we would do, if we wanted to do this intersection instead of
thinking as having to sweep, essentially this whole Square through
here and actually do testing to see whether we overlap with these
pieces.
What we can do instead is say let's pretend that we did shrink this
guy down to a point.
What would we have to do to these shapes to make it.
So that a point moving through them behaves, the same way as a
rectangle would move through the the unmodified shapes and the answer
is actually very simple.
It's just we would have to grow these shapes by this shape.
So essentially what you can imagine is taking the perimeter of this
shape and sweeping this rectangle around it, right?
So you imagine sweeping this rectangle all around it and we would end
up
But the shape that was like this, right?
And you imagine me doing that here as well.
Sweeping that taking this rectangle and sweeping it all around the
outside and taking that outer boundary, right?
And now we produce two new shapes, right?
That actually, if you can see, you can actually see intuitively what
it is.
It's s+ R.
They're rectangles that are S Plus R from the center out, instead of
just s.
We now have two shapes that if we're a cast, it against them would
give us.
The right result.
You can no longer pass through there, and you can see that actually,
as our get smaller.
If our was like that small, they would have still left a gap that we
could still pass through, which is correct.
So as our crosses, the threshold of how big our would have to be to
fit through here, it creates a gap or doesn't create a gap based on
that.
So what the Mankowski that's called the minkowski sum there.
Excuse me.
I believe technically this term.
Is sort of.
Not even a real.
ERM.
I think it's usually just considered a some and you're either doing
the some of the negative or not.
I don't know that it's a little odd but minkowski sum is the name for
that.
So where does that leave us?
Right?
What is that actually do for us?
Functionally.
Well, if you think about Oak Rita, here it comes.
Look at that.
Oh, but it didn't.
Well, I didn't use my background.
What, what, guys what's going on with that?
It's supposed to clear.
It's supposed to clear to my background color, right?
You saw it happen, didn't you?
You saw that happen?
Why did I get?
Why did I get jumped?
All right.
Hold on a second.
Can I fill this with something kind?
Do anything?
Phil.
It's going on here, Phil.
What?
Okay, seriously, this is just absurd you guys saw that happen, right?
And now I can't seem to undo.
Why can't I undo?
This program is fired.
I don't even know what it's doing at this point.
I feel like it shouldn't be that hard to just have a thing that draws.
Okay.
There we go.
Well, that was disappointing That was supposed to be the big moment
and the big moment was totally flaccid, is basically what happened.
So, how do we, how do we clear?
This thing?
There's got to be some way to select stuff, right?
How do I select just a region in this program?
Because that select a region.
That looks like a drew a rectangle there.
That's Alexa region.
So, if I select this region, right, I feel like I should be able to
clear it.
Can I not clear it?
Clear.
I don't know.
How about fill with foreground color?
I can't fill with her.
All right, guys, seriously, this is just ridiculous, unacceptable
behavior.
On the point of the drawing program Uhn acceptable.
It's my opinion.
How come I can't, how come I can't really do anything anymore?
As far as I can tell like, I can't even do the old way that I used to
clear stuff.
All right.
That's the way you want it.
I guess we got to make a new drawing.
New drawing.
And we're back.
Of course.
I can't apparently get the colors that I wanted, either.
This is just a disaster.
This is, this is the worst thing ever.
I just want I, at this point, I think, I have to write my own drawing
program for this stream, which is absurd like, okay, where'd that
layer go?
Does anyone see it?
I don't see it.
Where is my Lair?
I think we've got some kind of weirdness going on with the other ones.
We have like a vector layer.
That is.
Created.
I don't want a vector layer to say the very least.
I want that gone.
Alright, so oh, so that's probably what happened here.
We got some weird vector layer in the mix and then we couldn't clear.
It was clearing that other layer.
Lame, all right.
Well, at least we got something working man.
What an interruption?
So annoying.
Okay, anyway, back to the topic at hand.
Now that we've got that straightened out with clear this guy.
Okay.
So what I wanted to talk about before I was so rudely interrupted by
carita, is that if you think about what happens here, right?
If I have any shape at all and I want to do this Mankowski operation,
so I want to shrink this shape down to a point and I want to expand
this shape by it so that I can do ray casting on it as if it were just
a single point coming against it again.
I sweep the shape around the perimeter of the of this shape and I get
the results.
So, if you imagine putting a circle right and sweeping it around the
perimeter, right?
You can see that basically this plus this, right?
Equals this shape.
It's a rounded rectangle, right?
There's my new shape, right?
So that's how you do the minkowski sum or how you can conceptualize
the minkowski sum.
Now, that's a very complicated thing to think about because you're
like, well, okay great.
Conceptually.
That makes sense because I'm a human and I can just imagine sweeping a
shape around another shape.
No big deal.
What does the computer actually do the like, how do I code something?
That works that way, right?
And the answer is well, in one case, it's pretty
All right, in the case where you have two shapes that are essentially
the same shape, right?
Like, two rectangles and you want to, to do the minkowski.
Sum.
All you're talking about is taking the dimensions of the of them and
adding them, right?
If this one was are in, this one, was s like, in the previous example,
then if I want to shrink our down to a point, I just have S Plus r as
my new rectangle, right?
And that's done.
So if there are two shapes that are exactly the same, it's actually
pretty easy.
You just expand the radius and you're done.
Right, but there's kind of a hidden assumption there as well, which is
that, those shapes also have to have, you know, some way to easily
parameterize them like that, but like four rectangles and circles that
would work.
Right?
If we did circles the same would be true.
If you got a circle of radius, s in a circle of radius, R and you
added them together, you get a circle of radius, S Plus R.
Right?
So that's really easy if you have that, but if you don't have that it
gets a little more complicated.
Like what about this rectangle case here?
I've got a rectangle plus a circle you can see that it makes a much
more complicated shape.
And so if we were going to do say, raycasting against that, we would
have to do very, very specialized raycasting to raycast against
circles and
Rectangles together to make this sort of composite shape, that
produces the right answer, no matter what you were recasting at.
Right?
And that's actually it's not terribly hard to do even that, but you
could imagine much more difficult ones that were like super crazy.
Like, you know, this is my shape and I'm adding it to like this shape
or something, right.
And that's going to be this crazy thing with this swept around there,
that's got like another convexity here and whatever, right?
So you can see that it would get pretty complicated.
So there actually is a way that we can do operations like Ray casting
and those sorts of things against very complicated minkowski sums if
we want to which is called gjk actually.
Which is named after the people who this is One initial from each of
the people who originally invented the algorithm.
There is this there is a general-purpose algorithm called gjk that
actually allows you to do essentially any minkowski sum operation that
you want to do in that way for things like Ray, casting or Collision
detection with any shape at all as long as it's convex.
So you can't quite do something like this without first breaking it
in.
Two convex pieces, right?
Which would be something like this.
And that's actually pretty common in Collision detection, to take
concat, concavities and break them into convex pieces because
operations on complex pieces are so much faster that you typically is
better to just do for operations or five operations instead of one
operation and do them on convex.
So typically what ends up happening is this will become becomes like
sort of a Workhorse that you use for the Collision detection and you
just end up doing it.
So that you break all your stuff into convicts pieces first.
Now for our game, I don't know that we'll ever actually have all that
many concave things.
I suspect we'll have mostly convex thing anyway, so this part might
not be a problem, but we may need to implement this as our final
Collision detection system because we may want to do, some craziness
has like poly polygonal, convex objects, for example.
And circles and all that stuff.
And at that point it becomes pretty difficult.
Usually to conceptualize.
How you're going to do stuff with a rake a.
So you typically want to do something.
That's gjk or gjk like to do it, but for purposes of just what we need
to do right now, we probably don't have to implicate.
Okay.
Thank you.
Oak Rita.
At least it's free.
At least I didn't pay for it.
I guess that's one thing.
I could think of you get what you pay for and it turns out that's not
very much.
Okay, so basically like
What we're doing right now.
If we just want to do rectangles, like I said before, we already know
how to recast against a rectangle, right?
So if we have Point versus rectangle, we actually already know how to
do that.
Right?
And so if we want to, we can easily make the guy be rectangle as well.
And we can say, you know, okay if we want to make this guy into a
rectangle, no problem.
We'll just take however big the guys radius is and add it to the
radius of the thing.
We're testing against
And we're done, right?
That's it.
So we almost don't have to change our code at all.
Thanks to Mankowski.
Just to do a simple area version.
It's pretty trivial.
Thanks to him.
Right?
Thanks.
To Makowski and so you can imagine how we would implement this in
code.
It would actually be really easy.
If we want to give that guy some radius right now, right?
He comes up here and and he can, you know, go through things really
easily and he's unique interpenetrates through.
And if we wanted to say, let's stop doing that.
Let's give him some more girth there.
What we can do is just in the code.
Why is what is?
I do?
Have another one of these as well?
I have no idea what's going on with creature right now.
I'm totally lost.
Okay.
If I want to go into the code, which it looks like I didn't ever even
open up my editor yet.
So, let's open up the editor.
Let's see here.
There we go.
So if we imagine what we would do to our code here where we're testing
all the walls, really we already passed, we already sort of determined
what the shape of the wall was by using Min corner and Max corner.
And what we did is we took the tile side and M and we divided it by 2
to figure out what the span was.
So, all you would have to do is just 2 Min corner and Max Corner
instead of using this as the radius like this is effectively our
radius for Collision, right?
It's the tile map tiles item M.
Instead of just using that everywhere, which is what we were doing
before.
All we have to do is grow that radius.
Now, by however, big, we wanted the player to be and the player
suddenly would have that much area as a rectangle, right?
So, I don't remember what we set the player with and hype to, right.
We have some kind of a thing like that.
I believe that we set earlier, not that it actually meant anything,
but we actually did have
One.
Right.
So somewhere in here.
We've got, there we go.
So we've got
An entity has a width and a height, right?
So when we are doing that Collision detection, when we're doing that,
we have a entity, we have a width and a height for the entity.
So what we could do, when we do that, radius value, because we could
say, okay, we've got a radius.
We've got a with radius and we've got a height radius essentially,
right?
And for the tile map, it's the same in both cases but in the case and
this is actually, I guess this is more of a diameter.
We're dividing it in half and S.
So this is really the diameter.
Right?
So I've got diameter with amateur, with amateur height, amateur height
x 0.
So I can think about just going okay for the with I'm just going to
add that entity within their and for the height.
I'm going to add that empty height in there and that's the width and
height that we said that the person was right and so I don't actually
remember.
Exactly what we were doing with that.
But it's kind of, I think we were using that more for drawing, but I'm
just gonna use that for Collision detection at the moment.
And so now I believe that rectangle is the size of the Collision area
or should be.
Oh, oh, dear.
What did I do there?
That didn't work at all.
Okay, I've made a slight error.
I apologize.
My bad don't actually know what I did there.
So I said that it should work.
Apparently I was, I was quite mistaken.
Hold on a second.
Let me see what I did wrong.
So we have the Tom app.
Cytometer is, we're adding that entity width and height.
Let me step in there and make sure that and and let me see what's
going on here.
So we've got the Min Corner acts in the mid Corner.
Y, which is correct, right?
Yeah.
Let me go ahead and recompile that and make sure and let's step in
there and see what I did wrong there.
I believe that should have just worked but it is fairly early in the
morning.
So I may just be delusional and there's a step that I'm forgetting
here.
So let's find out.
Okay, so let's there we go.
So when we get into a tile that is supposed to be that we're supposed
to be colliding against
Oh, right.
Never mind.
I know exactly what the problem is here.
So we do have another problem, which is that when we actually look at
all of the tiles and we figure out what the minimum and maximum tile
are that we're going to Loop through.
We do have the issue of looping, through those tiles.
We have to take into account the size of the entity because we may
need to grab more tiles than we would have grabbed that we could be
colliding against.
Yeah, this is kind of obvious.
I'm not sure why I didn't mention it before.
Just wasn't thinking this morning.
So if you imagine what we were doing is we were doing a little
iteration over the over, basically, the entirety of the tiles that
were touched.
We were looking at something where we were saying, okay, you know,
let's say the guy moves from here to here and we said, okay, what are
all the tiles?
We need to check?
Well, we just need to check the tiles into into which that falls,
right, but that's not actually true because if you think about it,
once the guy has some area here.
She actually could could hit walls that are in tiles, that are further
away than that.
So, we really need to do is look at
This corner and this corner right of that and say what are all the
tiles that those would overlap and that is actually all the tiles that
we need to check.
So reason we can Tunnel right through stuff.
Now, is we're actually looking at things that we've already passed by
them.
By the time we check them.
We've already gone under the inside of them.
So, yeah, so that's a, that's a fairly obvious thing.
I don't know why I didn't think of that before we
We hit it.
And so yes, there is another step and that is the step.
So I'm going to go back to doing this the old way, because we didn't
really need.
What I was doing before and I want to also do some kind of a circuit
here.
Let's see.
So I can I can actually move this loop back to the way that it was as
well.
We can actually do something like this where we do been Thailand Mac
style, right?
Because we said that, we're not going to allow wrapping anymore,
because that was just going to be too much of a pain to maintain
least.
I believe it will be.
So we're going to do something like this.
Where we just are back to the good old.
Familiar easy way of doing things.
So we basically have our mint.
I'll why are maxed out.
Why?
And we Loop over them AB style.
X is less than equal to 0 because this is always just easier to think
about.
And so I'm kind of glad that we don't have to deal with the wrapping
anymore because that was just going to be a huge pain.
Okay.
So there we go, and we need to make sure that we never actually wrap
as well.
So we probably want to do some kind of a, you know,
A assertion.
You know.
Something like so that we know that when we've wrapped, mint ilex, you
know, something like the fact that these should always be less than,
you know, some reasonable value, right?
We shouldn't we shouldn't ever be getting the gigantic 4 billion ones
here.
So I'm just going to slap one in there.
So, we know because we haven't actually moved our world to the center
yet.
That's something that we would like to do.
And so just in case we forget and do some stuff off the edge of the
screen there.
I wanted to warn
So we know what happened and we're not like what's going on.
All right, so assuming that I do that I just want to make sure we're
still still good here.
Okay.
There we go.
Assuming I do that.
I would now like to go ahead and account for
basically that that that player sighs this thing right here.
So what I want to do is I want to make a Min player P.
That's that's basically
What I really want to do is I want to, I want to extend these by
however big The Entity is in tiles, right?
So after I do, mint ilex Mac style X.
So, on I want to take like the mint ilex, and I want to subtract it by
The Entity tile.
With right?
Basically, I want to do that and I want to do the same for the mint.
I'll why, right?
I want to expand that rectangle out.
Like I drew in the diagram.
So I want to just go ahead and do that.
So what I need to know is I need to know how big the entity is in
tiles, right?
Rounded up basically.
So what I want to do is say essentially take the ceiling of that.
Let me take a look and see.
I don't actually remember if we ever
Did ceiling.
Did we do ceiling or did?
We only do floor?
Let's see floor.
So, we did floor, but we never did ceiling.
So, I would like ceiling for this operation, right.
Clf
There we go.
Again, that should be something that we can get to be relatively in
line eventually.
So, what I want to do here is say okay.
Well the entity tile with I know his width in actual in like M, right.
I know is within M.
But I want to know what his with would be in Tiles at this point.
Right?
So I want to know and there's two ways I could do this, right?
I could also I could do a slightly more conservative Bound by putting
it actually into the computation here and then rounding out the tiles.
But I'm not going to bother with that.
I'd rather just do a slightly more conservative thing for now and
we'll let that be something to worry about in the final Collision
detector.
So what I want to do is say well, whatever is with this /, the tile
side and M.
And I guess to be honest, I don't really need now.
I think about it.
I don't really need the ceiling.
So maybe I shouldn't bother putting that in there.
I don't know.
We'll leave it in there just in case.
But what I all I really need to do is say okay if I have the entity
with and I have the tile sided meters, then I can divide.
The width.
Sloppy drinker.
I can divide the width by the topside of M, and that will give me how
many tiles he would expand by, right?
And so I can take the ceiling of that and I'm expecting that to
generally be one.
But, you know, if you had like a real big entity, you can imagine it
be spanning multiple tiles and then it might be a wider expansion.
So I figured I'd just do it the way that we would you know that we
would want to do it.
So we're just going to take a look at that and say, okay, let's let's
go ahead and get that out there.
And since this is a this is a
an actual integer function.
So what we should do now is if we step in here, we should see that box
expand by that mint.
Ilex and mint.
I'll why?
When we go to do Collision detection.
So let's take a look at what we computed yet.
One and one which is exactly what I thought it would be.
And then we've got our Min tiles and Max tiles.
They look like they're coming out correctly.
So now we're going to expand those mint ilex mint.
I'll WiMAX tile xmax tile why?
So we're going to expand those.
Out.
So the mins get smaller the Max's, get bigger, which is
You want.
And now we're doing it over a wider radius, right?
And so, I believe that should solve our problem and it does, of
course, we do have one more thing to to solve, which I'll talk about
in a second.
So, I think we're basically this, this looks like it's actually
working exactly.
Right?
We should also probably stop drawing the walls this way because the
walls are actually bigger.
Because remember I took point nine of them away so we could see around
them.
So it looks it looks roughly, correct.
All right, so
Very sticky there, which of course is again because we haven't
actually dealt with what happens when you actually hit the wall yet.
So one thing that's happening now though, that you can notice is when
we Collide against this side and when we Collide against the other
side, that's very sticky underwear.
That's so sticky.
That's weird.
Right?
Don't you think?
Not that, that is sort of what's interesting about that.
I wonder if we have another bug, but that is this is what I was
expecting to have happen to our Collision Vector before and I wonder
if it's just because all of our stuff was tile, the line that we
weren't having that happen.
It's just kind of like this is the stickiness was what I was expecting
to happen with the old Collision detection and that I was going to
talk about how we would have to get rid of it and so on.
But anyway, so I feel like something bizarre is happening there too,
though, because I believe we're still using an Epsilon when we set
things away.
So I think we've just got a straight-up Thug in there as well.
Because if you remember we're actually placing the guy a little bit
away from the wall.
So when he tries to go the other direction, he should not actually
still be hitting it.
So I do think that he shouldn't actually be getting stuck in that
fashion.
Even at this early stage with the clinic.
So I think we have another bug in there that I'm not thinking of, but
I'm not sure exactly what it is.
So we'll have to think about that in a second.
So anyway, point being
What I was going to talk about first is the fact that you'll notice
we're drawing his height off of this.
This, this pixel here.
We're drawing his height offset from where he actually is, right.
So his center point, where we're drawing.
This rectangle, were drawing him as if the whole height comes off of
that bottom point, right?
And so what happens is when I hit the bottom Edge, I stopped where I
would have stopped if the rectangle was was done this way.
And of course, that's exactly what we would expect to happen because
the Collision detector is treating it as if it's a radius value out
from that center point.
So what we actually want to do is talk about just this area or
whatever the area is that his coach is going to be in.
We want that to sort of be the center of where he collides against,
right?
And we want, we don't want to start to think about it in the other
way.
So the entity width and height,
White is actually going to be about that around with wherever the
center is of.
Vision.
And what we want, the bounce would be around there.
So I want to start drawing him that way because that's that's the way
it's actually going to work.
If I go take a look at where we're doing that drawing for the
entities, you can kind of see what I mean by that.
We basically have a thing where we do the player left top and you can
see that we subtract the whole height.
So what we actually want to do is subtract half the height.
So now it's centered just like the old one and you can kind of see
that that that is more the rectangle that we're talking about and that
one stops the way that you would expect it to stop and so on and and
so now we're actually correct but that is not the the size.
Probably want to use for that entity with.
So what we probably want to do is make his entity.
I'm sorry entity height.
So we probably want to do is make as entity height a little bit a
little bit better.
So I believe that's an initialize player.
And so this is not really the height.
It's really his Collision height and I don't know if we want to talk
about his actual height as well.
So we may want to actually talk about dimensions in a slightly
different way.
So I'm not sure how we want to talk about this eventually.
So for right now, we'll say that that it's just going to be something
like, you know, .5 + + 1 .5.
I don't know.
How big is that?
Let's find out.
It's a little bit.
That's not what I meant to do.
That's what I meant.
There.
Are you?
Yeah, so that's a little too small.
Let's make it still a little bit wider.
So maybe his width is about one and its height is about 0.5 because of
just the way, the games perspective is, that's probably a little bit
more, like, what you would expect, the shadow of the player to be.
And so off, he goes through here and so on and he can hit things like
we'd expect.
Okay.
So what I'd like to do now is before we go ahead and do the gliding
our area code.
Is working properly, but before I go ahead and do the gliding, I want
to figure out why we're getting that sticking problem, which is bogus.
Okay.
There we go.
Yep.
So we've got our area collection back, and as you can see, with
Makowski makowsky makes a lot of things much easier than they would.
Otherwise be because you can basically use the same code that you
would have used for something else and you just fiddle with the inputs
a little and all of a sudden you get something great, right?
That's what you wanted.
So you can also see the and this is why I say that.
Eventually want to do circles.
You can see how with the rectangle, I kind of would stop here and
there would be really no gliding.
I could do whereas with a circle it would kind of roll me off into
inside.
Once we actually implement the gliding code which we haven't done yet.
Right, but you can see that that won't actually improve.
So yeah.
So what I want to do is I want to take a look at the sticking now.
So what I want to do is know what's happening here, why I can't get
Out of here.
I want to see, I want to actually just look.
At the code directly and find out why we're getting sticking.
Because I feel like with the Epsilon, we shouldn't have mailed do
that.
That's obviously not true.
And so yeah, so I'm going to go ahead and set our our Loop Point here.
So we do a loop Point set.
I'm going to move out for a while so that I know that I'm trying to
push outwards and then little bit
All right, so I'm going to go in here and say, let's go ahead and step
in and and see what's going on.
So we're here.
Let's go ahead and step in here.
So we're basically only checking two tiles.
We're checking the tile that were on and we're checking the tile below
us.
Basically is what's happening there.
Right?
If you look at them in tile X and them into Mac style, the maxxtow
WiMAX Alex.
Let's take a look at the DDP.
Make sure it's something that we want.
So that's not actually a DDP that I want.
I wanted to DDP that was going to be actually trying to move us down,
right?
Why is my DDP?
Oh, he's so tiny.
Obviously, the Collision detector, can't move us anywhere.
At the DDP is always super tiny.
Hmm.
What what is the meaning of that people?
What is the meaning of it?
Why is that happening?
I don't understand.
I was, I recorded a thing where he was definitely moving down.
We should be able to get a DDP where he's actually moving himself
down, but it doesn't seem like that's ever happening.
Let's go out and see why not.
Okay.
Game update.
Let's see.
So, no one.
What?
What is the problem here?
I do not understand what's going on.
There we go.
Okay, so I guess it just stopped in the middle of in the middle of one
randomly.
Alright, so the controller is not analog ended down.
So GD.
P-- dot Y is negative 1 GD p-- dot X is 1 move in here.
See what we've got GDP is 1 negative 1 so we have to renormalize we
get the right thing.
Multiplied about the player speed which is good.
What?
His velocity.
Was - that.
Did you see what I saw there?
How did his velocity be equal?
- what it was?
What is going on here?
We're not even updating the velocity, right?
Oh, is it just are we just seeing literally, that fact that the
velocity is never getting updated because we haven't actually gone in
and done.
And actually done any work to correct it.
That seems odd though.
Why would that be the case?
I guess.
I could imagine that being the case.
Let's just see if that's true.
I'm going to go ahead and test that just to make sense because that's
pretty interesting, I guess.
So, I guess if we just go on and implemented gliding we would have
gotten rid of the problem.
But yeah, so in this case when we did the team in there when we when
we sort of loop through here and found it.
Basically we're saying is if team in is less than 1.
No.
Then we would want to go ahead and zero that velocity out and that
would just stop him entirely in his tracks.
Right?
Is that really the problem?
That seems odd, but I guess it could be.
Let's find out.
It does look like that was indeed the problem.
Well, totally fine.
That's fair.
All right.
So I guess that means, we really didn't need to debug that because if
we just gone ahead and finish the gliding implementation where we were
going to update the velocity for our new Collision detector, it would
have just worked.
But hey, it was good to inspect any way so that we know what it was
and aren't, you know, worried about it, I guess.
So, that's fine.
So, we're now in good shape.
We've got the area working fine.
So, all we want to do now is implement the gliding and to implement
the gliding.
We just have to do the same thing that we did before, right?
Where we update.
Basically, using that same idea here where we did, we did our sort of
our balanced equation, right?
Where we actually take away all of the bounce velocity and just leave
the remaining velocity.
Right?
So if we want to do that, we still have the exact the exact same code
essentially, but I'm going to make it a little bit cleaner.
So basically, if we go down here, I'm going to say that, you know,
after we do this F, redo this test.
Well bit, I'm going to go ahead and say
We got to update our velocity instead of doing it this way.
And what we're going to do is we're going to do this inner product
thing.
You notice that the way that this is set up.
It's saying that the existing velocity, we subtracted away.
The part that we didn't want any more of that velocity, right?
And by doing the way that we did that is we used an inner product with
essentially the normal.
If you remember the normal to the wall that we hit and what's nice
about this equation, is this actually works whether or not you hit a
wall because if we just set the normal of the
Wall to be 0 0.
This would, this term would evaluate to 0.
Right.
So what we could do is just say we always update the velocity with
whatever wall he hit and when we just have a wall.
Oops.
Wall normal right here that we're going to track.
So we have wool normal and it's going to be equal to 0 0.
Always
Right, and then we're just going to update that along with our team
in.
Actually, trying to think of how I want to do this.
I don't think this thing really knows what the wall normal is.
So let's do it this way for now.
Right.
Well normal.
Equals whatever the normal would be.
And so we're basically just doing the exact same code that we did
before.
Only this time I'm setting an arbitrary will normal so we could expand
this code I guess to use walls that were not like nothing in the code.
Now really counts on the fact that the walls are horizontal vertical.
Accept our are sort of not particularly good solution up here to
testing the wall.
It's this this code right here would have to get a little bit better
to handle a slanted wall, but that's about it.
So,
I want to do is say alright, we can return whether we hit or not.
So hit equals false.
And in this case, hit equals true, right?
So will return true print hit and now I'll just go ahead and set the
normal to what.
I know.
Each of these will normals to be and off we go.
So in this case,
I'm testing us them in corner X so that normal would be in that
direction for the max Corner.
Exit would be in the opposite direction X.
Same thing here and here, right?
And so, I believe that should update our velocity correctly.
Now, excuse me, so we should be able to Glide.
If I didn't mess it up, which I may have and it looks like I did.
Did I forget to what did I forget to do here?
So well normal.
I feel like,
Why is he stopping there?
What did I want to die?
Mistakenly?
Do.
There's one thing we need to do in addition to this, but I feel like I
should have glided properly just from that.
Yeah, let me let me verify that it's not the other thing that we need
to do first, and I'm pretty sure it's not.
Okay, so it actually is alright.
Never mind.
Hmm.
I take it back.
Okay, so now we're at the situation.
He actually is blinding properly.
I take it back.
You can actually see him gliding properly there, the problem.
We have to do the final thing that I said, if you remember when we
talked about.
I thought he was coming to a complete stop.
He actually isn't, he's only stopping if we continue to try and go to
the wall.
So we're at the point where we can finally fix the final problem that
we had, which is what we were talking about before where it's, it
doesn't continue the move after it does this.
And so remember I said, we have to do a loop where we try to correct
the velocity during collision and keep trying to move him for the
remainder of the time, step.
Right?
So that's what we want to do now.
So, basically, what we need to do is say okay, we've got.
We now have to go ahead and
And do this sort of test where we're going over things.
This part here, right?
We have to do this for some number of iterations so that we can say,
we've got our mics, don't need to call it Innovation.
Index is just iteration.
I think I said for would be how many we do?
Because we don't want, we want a bounded number.
We don't want to just keep going until it's zero.
So basically, what we would start out with is we'd have a tea
remaining essentially, right?
That starts off at one point O, which is to try and do the whole move,
right?
And what we want to do now is say, okay.
We have this, we have the that player Delta.
Which is the value that we computed, that's how far we want to go.
Right?
So we have that player, Delta and the player Delta.
We're going to start off by saying we have all of the player Delta to
try and account for.
We want to try and move him the entire player Delta distance, right?
And then when we do the code for hitting the wall, we say, OK, we
start the team in meaning the minimum distance that we could go along
it is and I guess in this case, we could say, it's
.0.
Right.
Excuse me is how far we want to go and then when we finish we know how
much of the T how much of the step we've actually used right?
We know we know trying to get how to say this.
We know once we take one of these steps.
We know how far in t we've gone because at the end we have a new team
in, right?
We've updated team in to be the percentage of clay or Delta that we've
used.
Does that make sense?
So essentially RT remaining, right?
We subtract away whatever the inverse of that team in is because
essentially we've sort of said and you know, I guess we could do it.
We could do the math.
I'm trying to think of this is a good idea or not.
We could actually do the math such that we actually are always just
using team in if we want to maybe.
I'll try to do it that way.
So we start with our team and at one point O, which is we can move the
full distance along the player, Delta, right?
And then we go in here.
We update team in to be how far we actually have moved until we hit
the wall and then we try again.
To move, you know with with the new team in and we keep producing it
and if team in ever Falls to zero, so basically like and teaming is
greater than 0.
If T Min ever Falls 20.
We've done the entire movement.
We're done, right?
So that's totally fine.
So basically what we want to do is say if we didn't hit anything,
right?
Because this that each time we update this, our team in will go down
to the to the distance that it went.
Now I you know what, just thinking about this the sense of it's just
wrong.
I just don't think I can do that.
Yeah, I can't sorry in my head.
I just can't figure out a way to make that work.
Will see after I write it the with the two variables will see if
there's a way to do it entirely and team in.
I don't know if there's are not.
So I'm just going to say that we have some time.
Step remaining we have the team in and we basically say how much of
the team in do we use.
And then at the end we take T remaining and we subtract from it.
Whatever was left of the team in, right?
So basically if we didn't, if we got to go the entirety, if team in
was the entire way, so it was 1.0.
Right?
We would subtract from it.
Hmm.
Sorry, know if team in was the 1.0., We'd subtract the entire thing.
Yeah, so we always subtract how far in team and we actually went.
Yeah, that's right.
So, okay.
So what we have to do here is say alright.
Here's our player, Delta.
Right.
And Artie is how far along this we've gone, right?
So when we do our team in what our team in tells us is where we
stopped along this line.
It tells us the percentage right from 0 to 100%, right?
So it ranges from 0 to 1 where we stopped.
If we went all the way to 1, right?
If you're always 100% we're done.
So we always take whatever our team in comes out and we subtract from
how much we had of tea to begin with, right?
So,
This case.
Right.
Our team in is when we first start out our team and could be 1.0 and
we could go the entire way and we're going to stop on the team
remaining, gets to zero.
But on subsequent times through the loop, we could just say we have
how only however much T.
We actually had left to use, right?
And then we go from there.
I believe that would work just fine.
And then what we want to do is say, well, when we do our updating,
right, we need to do the updating every time, right?
Because every time we hit a wall, we need to update the player
location to that point, right?
And then we need to update doing.
And then we need to update the the velocity to get rid of whatever
Parts part of the wall normal, but we have to do the same thing, right
for our player do.
So our player Delta has to be chopped so that it's not trying to go
into the wall anymore either.
So, basically the exact same equation, where we do that bounce, we
have to do that for the player, Delta as well.
Right?
So we get rid of whatever portion it was trying to go into the wall.
Now remember this offset is somewhat expensive.
So really, we could decide just not to do that offset the player
positions thing, right?
We could decide to do the player position thing.
Outside here and have a thing called total player Delta, which
basically says, what part of the player Delta actually got used and
will Summit.
So we'll save total player, Delta right?
Is going to add whatever.
The step was that actually was used.
Right?
And then what we need to do is we need to update that player position.
So this this thing where we do the real old player, oh, well, I guess,
never mind.
So I guess since that is something that we're actually still using.
The loop we might as well keep it this way first since we're still
using the entity The Entity p.
And so old player P.
I believe old player P is never.
I don't even actually know why we still have old player P.
We're just we're just talking about entity P, really this entire time
and that's easier to update.
So I'm going to go ahead and say that we do it this way and I might
get rid of old player piece, as full player P is not actually used
anywhere as far as I know.
Okay, so to use there, so we just want to snap it once the beginning.
So that's fine.
I'll leave it around.
All right, so I got to update the end of this position with his new
position.
I gotta update the velocity with the new velocity and then I got
update how what we're trying to where we're trying to go to with the
new amount that we're trying to go to as well.
So let me take a look at that.
We don't want Total player Delta.
That's just regular player Delta.
Now we go and so, let's see how that does.
There we go.
So there's our skating Loop still getting a problem.
There.
That doesn't look quite right.
So we still got a bug but we're almost there.
Just not quite just knock, just not quite there.
All right.
So what's our problem?
Here?
We did our offset properly.
Oops.
My laptop screen has gone to sleep.
That's not going to be very good for reading a Q&A.
Certainly.
Let's try that again.
There we go.
and,
Okay.
So what we need to do now is figure out what I did wrong.
There.
We are updating.
What are we updating here?
So let's make sure I've got everything correct.
So we've got our absolute tile Z.
We've got that we've got the center tile.
Point is being computed properly.
Yes, we get the tile value.
This is the entity with that height.
That's based on that.
That's all correct.
We're subtracting into PP, which is the thing that we are updating.
So, that's good.
And then we do all of our testing, we get our well, numbers back.
We update the end of Deep.
You buy, whatever the player Delta was that we computed.
We remove the part of the player, Delta that would have gone against
the wall, normal, which I believe is what we wanted to do, and we
update the velocity of the guy as well based on that.
Well normal.
And then we take away whatever the amount is that we stepped forward,
which seems
I think okay.
So I may be I may be double counting that.
Let me think about that.
So I think I'm double-counting that because if I were although that
shouldn't have really been in effect.
The second velocity should have worked either way.
But yeah, so you would still go the whole player Delta because we are
accounting for the fact the player Delta is getting smaller.
So I think actually
Technically, this should always be 1.0 and then when we subtract it
out, it's just, we subtract whatever portion of the player remaining,
we used.
If that makes sense.
I believe that's correct.
Yeah.
So I think that was our only bug.
Not sure if you saw what happened there.
So, I'm not sure where it's still entirely, correct.
I'm a little bit nervous.
There's a weird thing that's happening there.
Which is I believe because our epsilon's too high, like, you can sort
of see, I don't know if you can see it.
Kind of when you go, he moves a little closer.
You know, what I could do.
I could we had a key.
That's what it was.
It make it bigger.
So you can kind of see he squishes into the wall a little bit and I
believe what's happening.
There is our Epsilon actually stops him before he would actually get
to where the wall is and so as he moves in a slighter fashion, he can
actually get a little closer to the wall.
So I think, what we want to do is we want to make our Epsilon tighter
than it was so.
I'm going to say.
So the Epsilon the problem is the Epsilon is only in player Delta
space which is not great.
I don't think that's particularly good and I feel like we should
probably get rid of this Epsilon eventually.
Anyway, in the real question is Hector.
I think what we'll do is just not have it but that's a separate issue.
So let's take a look and see if that's a little bit better.
Of course, that's too close.
You can see, you can see why you don't want to have these epsilon's,
right?
So we want to do something that doesn't actually have to have the
Epsilon.
This may be good enough just for now because like I said, we want to
do the regular Collision detection.
We want to do it a little differently.
Anyway when we're actually doing so it's probably better to deal with
those things there but there is that little
Weirdness that I don't love.
It's kind of hard.
You can see it, right?
You can kind of see it.
Yeah, we also have that problem of like the players velocity, as it
gets clipped.
It's causing his facing direction to be like changing very rapidly in
the when he actually hits things.
So we probably have to pick his facing Direction on something, a
little more stable as well.
But yeah, you can see kind of see how it how he scoots into the wall a
little bit.
So that's that's just lame right there.
And so I think now that I think about it, the fact that this Epsilon
is in that the wrong Space is really most of the problem there.
So thinking about what would have to happen for that essentially.
So when we actually do that team in you'd have to actually say you
know, how big is the player Delta and you'd have to adjust based on
that?
So I'm not sure I'm not sure exactly what the what the best way to do
that.
Would be because if the player Delta is really small, then you would
want to do is a really small Delta.
So you want to actually make that that minimum a little bit different.
So what I could do is say that the epsilon's not going to happen here,
you know, the Epsilon is going to be happening outside and that would
be better but still not fantastic, right?
So essentially, you know, in the case where where we actually did hit
something.
So I say equals false in the case, where you actually did hit
I could apply that Epsilon outside, which is again, not not
particularly great, having an Epsilon at all.
It's not good in general, but I could say if hit and if in the case
that we hit, we also know that we only need to do these when we hit.
So, you know, we could do something like like that so that we break
out immediately and don't have to do the test.
I don't know if that's, that's probably not really worth.
But we do know, for example, that we don't need to update any of these
unless we actually hit.
So so, okay.
So in that case if we actually did the hit then we would do it, but I
can't quite do it that way, I guess.
So.
Alright, never mind.
Never mind.
Thought we were going to be clever, but we weren't so in the case
where we hit, I'll just say this equals that Epsilon there at the end.
And the only reason I'm thinking that that's the case is because now I
can actually see whatever RT remaining was Artie remaining.
We could actually use to boost that Epsilon up to larger values based
on how far we were thought we were moving because I believe that most
of it is
Well, I'm not actually sure if now you know, what why did I do that?
That doesn't really make any sense because there really isn't that
much information that I could use outside.
It's still the same as the information that we have in here, right?
I could just do whatever I was going to do.
I could do in here.
So I'm going to leave that that way for now.
Because I don't see a super easy way to fix that without doing
something better because again that Epsilon is just going to be.
The problem is when you when you actually do hit the wall.
You've got that Epsilon.
That wants to be a little bit different.
Yeah.
See, that's just bad behavior right there.
You can kind of see I don't know if you can see that.
That will on the stream.
I believe alt one or there.
I believe there was some way we had that.
We're supposed to zoom in.
Well, zoom in is running control one.
Maybe there we go.
Ooh, I guess that doesn't work, unfortunately.
Can I zoom in there?
So unfortunately while I'm zoomed in I can't animate.
So I guess I so that Zoom effect doesn't really work for this but you
can kind of see what's happening as I as I go in there and I don't
know.
That might just be another bug.
We could look at in a little more detail.
But basically I want him to stop directly on the wall and not have
that little stuttering behavior.
And I guess I'm not entirely certain that that's the Epsilon.
So I guess what I could do to you know what, I'm going to go into the
In a little bit just because I feel like I can I want to I want to
just look and see if there's another bug in there.
It's want to watch what the behavior is that happens when he hits that
wall.
So I can do that actually pretty easily because I know that he's going
to hit this wall, right?
That's the well, he's kidding.
So if I want to, I can stop just when he's about to hit that wall,
right?
Which is right here.
So, let's take a look at what actually happens when you hit that wall.
None of these other wall should hit presumably because he's just
hitting that one wall.
Yep.
And so let's see what's our team in our team in is 0.75 and
What's a player, Delta?
Our player, Delta is negative 0.2.
So he's trying to move that much and he's basically not moving in Y at
all.
Right, Sandy - 06.
That's a very tiny value in y.
All right.
So when I update my entity P, I'm going to move him by the amount that
he was able to move.
Right?
Which is 75 percent roughly of the way to the wall.
And so,
We go ahead and do that.
Now.
Where does that leave him?
The player position?
Let's see.
Entity pee.
Where does that leave him?
Oops, versus where the wall is?
I'm going to delete some of this stuff so I can start fresh.
Where does that leave him?
So we have tile map tile side in meters, right?
That is oops.
What about two?
That is about point seven.
And so we're going to do our offset of the player now, so we do that
offset and we get an ex of - 0.19, which is actually nowhere close to
this, which is fine because we also have the player with to account
for.
So what's the entity with
The Entity with is one that's point five, so that's that's stopping
him right on the.
That's, that's doing exactly, right.
It's basically what's happening.
So I think we just have another bug here.
Okay.
So entity DP.
We're updating the velocity of the fellow himself, we have clipped his
x velocity away, which is exactly what we want.
We are taking the player Delta which is this right here, which is how
he's trying to move that is clipped as well.
And we are taking the T remaining which was all of it and we're
reducing it to just what was left after the move.
Right?
And so I think that's that's what we were expecting.
So, that's fine.
Let's see what happens now.
So now we got a team in of 1.0 again, and we're going to see whether
or not we collide with anything.
Now.
My understanding is we should not collide with anything right?
Because we are free and clear at the moment.
So I feel like if I were to set these, we should not hit one of them
and we don't, so that's good.
That's behaving as we would expect it to.
So now we have to do our offset again.
We have the player Delta, the player Delta has no X component
whatsoever.
And the DP, let's see here.
Entity DP also has none so they should really not change much at all
except in y, right?
And that's fine.
So, there we go.
And
Player Delta.
Does not get updated team in was 1.0.
So now two remaining is 0 and we should fall out of the loop.
Yeah, so we did exactly what we thought we should do.
So now the question I guess is just the second time through I guess it
was wrong.
Must be because that is apparently correct, that all looked exactly
right to me.
Nothing.
Nothing bad happened there.
Right.
So, what is happening with that nonsense?
So, in order to fix that again, I'm going to lean on our Loop Live
code editing.
As I so often.
I'm going to set that up and then do this, right?
So now he's just constantly creating into the wall and that will make
sure that he that I can basically to bug the exact case that's
happening.
Right?
So, what I'm gonna do is I'm gonna set that break point again.
I'm going to set that break point here when he hits the wall.
I pretty much believe that that Loop operated as it was intended,
right?
So it comes out, here comes out here and does its update.
If we go right, does its little dance for the facing Direction, which
is fine.
And
Yeah, and I think that should be it until the next call to move
player.
So let's see what happens in that call.
So, in the next call to move player, you come in here and we are GDP.
Should again be trying to accelerate him into the wall because I was
pressing straight into the wall - one exactly what we expect we go
through and we compute our stuff as it were mint.
I'll X is 1 into y.
X is one next hour, I believe that's correct.
Is that correct?
Yeah, okay.
Because we're about to expand it by the width of the guy.
Yeah, so we're checking everything.
Yep.
So that's fine.
So now the question is we should immediately again hit this wall,
right?
That's what should happen if I'm not mistaken.
Oh, and we do not hit the wall.
We don't hit the wall at all.
Why do we not hit the wall?
Is it because our velocity was not big enough yet to hit the wall.
That could be.
Certainly, that might be it.
We may have stopped just short of where the wall is, but I feel like
we were right on it.
So if that's the player Delta, why didn't that?
Why didn't that hit the wall?
Where is the wall X?
Would be the real question?
Unfortunately, it's kind of hard to figure out what that value
actually is.
So, all right.
So let's go ahead and say, what is the ab style x + AB style?
Why of that guy?
So let's, let's let's do this again.
Run.
Go ahead and run.
There you are my friend.
So I'm going to go ahead and stop it in there.
And I want to see which what the actual position of this wall is.
Oops.
I should make sure that we're actually looking.
Okay.
So what is the the wall coordinate here?
What actually is the the max Corner X that we're stopping at its 1.25?
Right one point 2005.
So let's find out where we actually move ourselves to when we decide
that we hit that wall.
Where are we?
So we're at one point two, five relative to the tile.
We are - to away.
And what's that tile side?
And M, right?
Tha side, m is 1.4, so that basically, oh, and I guess I
Yeah, so it's a little bit confusing just because since we do
everything relative in tile space, the 1.2 is how far away from the
tile.
You would have to be.
And I'm not sure exactly where this guy is relative to that right now
because that's kind of a hard competition to do in one's head.
But so if the max when X is 1 Point 2, then that means if between two
tiles, right?
If between two tiles is 1.4, then basically he should be point to away
from his current tile, which is exactly what he is.
So he should have hit the wall the next time around and the fact that
he didn't hit, the wall is somewhat troubling I believe.
So, so yeah, I think we're back to my original thesis, which is we've
got a bug or something that we don't a subtlety that we
Understand.
This is not a problem with the Epsilon, really.
This is a problem with the code.
So if I come in here and I'm going to test this wall again, what I
want to do is I want to take a look at what happens when we're
supposed to hit that wall.
So what I'd like to do is say, okay, let's figure out which ABS
dialects and abs tile why we're on.
When we do hit this one, right?
Let's figure out.
Out which one?
That is.
So AB style.
Y is 5 ABS?
Tell x is 0.
So ABS tile.
Why is five ABS tile x is 0, right?
That's what we're looking at for the one, where he actually does hit
that wall.
And so what I will do now is I will let him hit the wall.
In that way that he likes to do and then I will go to the next time
around.
And I'm going to step into the case where he is supposed to be
interacting with that wall.
So X AB style.
Why?
So I want abs too wide to be 5.
So we're not quite there yet.
We got to go through these two x's first, right?
X is 2.
Let's finish that up.
Let's see.
Oh, no, I missed it.
This the so slow.
Iterating watch window is so frustrating.
Gah.
All right, do it again.
Thank you Visual Studio, like apparently, it's an unsolved problem in
computer Graphics to update the watch window when I hit step.
It's just so ridiculous, how bad it is.
All right.
So we've hit it once and now we're going to go again, right?
And now I'm going to go ahead and run in here.
So that's 0 for 1, 4 2, 4, 0, 5.
So this is the one we want to know about.
We come in here and let's see.
So, we've got our relative player location.
Let's see what that is.
Our relative their location and arm in corner or Max corner.
Let's take a look at what all our values are here.
So, here's relative position is apparently higher than what?
I thought.
It was.
He's got a little ways to go, but it looked to me when we actually did
the computation before it looked to me like he didn't.
So what what is going on here?
What's the, what's the what's the issue if you will, what's our test
tile P.
What's our test?
I'll pee.
It's 050.
And 0 0 which is what we expect and what's our player or entity P DP.
What's that are offset?
so that
that's a different offset than I thought we ended with before, right.
Am I imagining things?
I thought we ended with a totally different.
I thought we ended with a totally different entity P than that last
time.
Alright, let's step through it one more time.
So, there is going into the wall.
Which one am I going to stop at?
Mustapha?
I'm here.
So there I've hit the wall, right?
And now I'm going to do my update step to hear update.
What's my entity P?
That was the entity P.
We were supposed to get.
So what happened to our entity pee?
Why is it our entity P.
Did it get changed in the second time through the loop?
Because it shouldn't touch the X, right.
So what happened here?
It did touch the X.
It did.
What?
Ah, oh the bugginess.
Oh, did you see it?
Oh, it's so awful.
I forgot.
I said I was gonna get rid of old player piano.
I didn't oh, the pain and suffering.
You saw it, didn't you?
Oh man.
Boy.
I'm glad I stepped through that.
That was a good one.
Not to leave in there.
Hey, look, it's perfect now.
Oh, that was terrible.
That was terrible.
It's coming out.
The owl is coming out, people that was a bad typos.
And I almost left it into.
I was like, that's not the final conductor.
Well, it's not the final Collision detector.
It's true, but you shouldn't leave that garbage in there.
That's just awful.
Oh, that was bad.
All right.
Looks like we're fine now.
Nope, no more cause for alarm.
I wasn't happy with what was going on in there at all.
That was just bad news.
So, the other thing that I was thinking about is, I don't know if we
want the maybe the acceleration to determine which way the guy is
facing because it's a little weird right now the way that it's working
with the velocity, but I don't know.
All right, so I'm glad we push through that.
We can go ahead and and actually go to the Q&A now.
Wow, okay.
So yeah, that took an extra 20 minutes of De bugging.
Time to find one typo.
Yeah, but that's what you get for putting in typos in your code.
So, okay.
We're pretty clean.
Now.
I don't think we've got any more problems with that and hey, it's a
lot easier to skate through.
Now, even with a rectangular Collision.
It's way easier to skate through those doorways.
Which again is why sliding is so important.
You don't think about it that much when you're playing games, but
being able to
Slide smoothly along walls is like really important, right?
It's what makes it fun and easy to play a game and not feel super
janky.
So it's super important to get that slide in there.
So it's worth the effort, trust me.
So anyway, and it'll be even better when we have a circular dude
because then the normal that you're pushing off on will sort of help
you slide into doorways easier better as well.
All right, so I think we're all good.
Let's go ahead and go to the Q&A, please prefix, York.
Questions with Q:.
So I will be able to see them.
And please keep your questions stuff.
We've done today streamer on previous streams.
Yay.
That'll be pushed through that.
Why is the heroes head 1.5 meters in DM in diameter?
I feel like it shouldn't actually be quite that big.
So like I said, the hero is too big right now.
He was is going to Get shrunk down a bit.
But he's a bit Anime styled as you can see.
So his head is going to be ridiculously large compared to everything
in the world.
I'm a web developer developer and was taught not to have more than a
couple hundred lines profile.
Why isn't the game split up into smaller?
Excuse me.
Oh, wait, I'm sorry.
I skipped over question there.
If I recall right then in a prior episode you were talking about how
the makowsky difference is good solution for finding collections.
Only between convex.
Polygons can also be a good solution for concave polygons.
If you have something else planned for that case.
Also, if you are planning on using Mankowski, differences for concave
Coalition geometry, is it also good solution in 3-D, or are there
better alternatives to handle the additional Dimension?
So the minkowski stuff works the same in 3D as 2D.
It's Dimension agnostic, which is really nice.
And the way that pretty much everyone universally like in every game
I've ever heard of in the history of time handles convex Collision is
to break them up into concave pieces.
That is almost always the solute solution.
So basically what you do is you always just use context collision and
you break up concave things into convex pieces because you can always
take any concave shape and with enough splits split it into something
convex.
So that's how that works.
I'm a web developer who was always taught not to have more than a
couple hundred lines for file.
Why isn't the game split up into smaller and more modular files?
So, two things, one.
Is that files have nothing to do with modularity, right?
So modularity is about whether or not the functions in something are
able to be called separate from other functions.
That's what modularity, like modularity is about reuse.
It's about whether or not I can reuse a
Thing.
Obviously, I'm only doing one game here.
So I don't care about linking to other games, but I do care about
using stuff in multiple places.
And so really modularity is about what I break out into functions.
It has nothing to do with files.
Files are a particular are purely arbitrary construct, right?
The actual code itself, doesn't care about files.
Files are meaningless.
And so really you should never think about how big a file is.
Unless it's something that you care about in terms of legibility.
So,
The extent that I care about files, I only care about them in the
sense that I like to look at two things side by side.
So the only real thing I do with files is I say, I like to split stuff
apart when I want to be able to look at one thing on one side.
And one thing on the other side.
That is the only thing that matters for files for me.
If it wasn't for that.
I just put everything in one file because it just me.
Your to keep track of Rights only one file.
You don't when you want to copy the source code around you, copy 1C
PP, right?
That'd be way better.
So the Dogma that you have to break things into lots of small files.
I would just say, what's the benefit?
What are you?
What are you possibly getting out of that?
You know that because the compiler doesn't care at all.
Right.
And so what is it that you think you were getting out of that?
You know, what is it that you wanted to get out of that?
And and if there was something valid, if you were getting
Out of that.
Could you get it another way?
Would be my thing because I just don't I don't think the the huge file
proliferation is good thing.
Plus we also use a Unity built here because the more files you try to
push through the compiler.
The slower it gets that's just the way compilers work.
Unfortunately.
So having monolithic files actually helps there as well, but that's
separate issue.
Is the alpha channel in the art assets, created by the artist, or do
you create them with a tool?
Alpha channels are generally automatically handled in the art package.
So basically what happens is when the artist draws it fills in Alpha
as well as color.
So when they draw you get the alpha Channel, plus the color
automatically, that's how that works.
So it's already kind of in the source assets.
How many years since you started doing games?
I mean, I think this is really, really hard.
Yeah, I mean, this is a more advanced.
Obviously.
This handmade hero is is showing real game programming.
It's not showing beginner game programming.
I am walking through every single thing that we do.
So, in that sense, it's beginner, but we're not pulling any punches.
Like, we're actually looking at the actual stuff that the CPU has to
do to run a game.
We're not just like saying, oh, instantiate object and let Unity like,
figure out the rest, right?
And so, yes, that can be kind of difficult because there's a lot that
you have to learn, but you should learn a lot.
If you want to be an engine programmer, right?
If you don't, then you can kind of just gloss over this stuff which is
fine, right?
Hand made here is still probably useful because you can see all the
stuff that's involved and maybe you don't totally understand it.
But at least now, you know, and so you'll be better when your partner
with other things, but yes, it is difficult.
I don't, I don't pretend that it's not.
There's just a lot to know.
It's one of the reasons that there are so few game engine programmers
out there.
And so and fewer still good ones is because it's, it definitely is
something that takes a lot of study and it takes a lot of practice to
be good at.
Orlando Bloom, I've never actually done this kind of collision
detection.
I always just hope the frame rate would stay high enough that the
velocity would be smaller than the Collision size and that's totally a
valid approach, right?
You just have to actually go ahead and make sure that's true.
Right?
And it does put bounds on the sizes.
That things can be.
You can't make sizes too small.
Are you have to start subdividing?
Your time steps, but you can do that if you want to write, but it's
not that hard to do it this way.
So, you know, basically you can think about it.
Here's one way to think about it.
Iteration.
Will happen.
Right.
Iteration will happen.
So, you have a choice of where, that iteration happens?
One place I could happen is in frames.
So, the way that your Collision sector works is, it's essentially,
each frame is an iteration of the glitter cousin detection, right?
And that's what you were just talking about.
Another way.
It could happen.
Is by subdividing, your time steps, right?
So you can say, well, these are my frames, but I know Mike.
Listen, sector needs to be able to detect objects that are smaller
than the velocities on these frames.
So I'm going to subdivide it and do a couple iterations of the physics
per frame, right?
And that's one way this is more efficient than this, in some sense
because it means that for the same Collision,
You're doing less work.
In this case than you would be doing in this case.
Because in this case, your frame rate itself has to be this High to be
as robust as this is out of as a frame rate.
That is much less.
Right?
Hmm.
And then the final way is the iteration only happens inside the
Collision system.
So the physics and the the game still only happen at these frame
boundaries.
But inside they're just the Collision is iterating.
And so one reason that it's better, I think.
Think to have your Collision system, be do sort of it.
The checking perfectly inside it is because that means that the
iteration happens at the smallest possible Loop scale.
So you're doing the least possible work per iteration and then lofting
everything else up to to that sort of a larger time scale, which is
good for performance.
I feel like
Can't you have multiple views of the same file with e Max you can, but
it's janky.
You've probably already answers a dream, but I haven't been able to
watch a lot of them.
And as far as I know, the Q&A Parts aren't put on YouTube.
The Q&A parts are all on YouTube.
They just happen right after the video.
So if you jump one hour into any of the videos, the Q&A is there.
What are you wearing on your hands O?
The Bots will answer it.
The Bots will answer it for you.
The hands question for the Makowski calculation will be still be able
to use the same procedure for rotating hitbox or for diagonal space
for the rotating case, would we have to apply a transform to all the
Collision of geometry to reflect a larger profile?
So that's an excellent question.
The answer is, it depends whether you're talking about animated
rotation, or static rotation?
Okay, so essentially minkowski doesn't care if you're rotated
minkowski's fine, with
Right.
So let's say I had a rotated rectangle, and another rectangle that was
rotated or something.
Right?
The same sweep, still works, right?
The same sweep.
Totally works in minkowski terms, right?
You still just get the exact right shape.
The only difference is it's no longer a rectangle, right?
So there you go.
So it's like an octagon or whatever.
So Mankowski still works Mankowski, works just fine.
With static rotation.
Our cheesy implementation that we just did were all we did was handled
right rectangles.
Anyway, obviously won't work, but gjk would work in this case, just
fine, what?
Mankowski cannot handle is animated rotation.
So let's say that.
I've got a guy who's rotating over the time step.
So he rotates from here to here, right?
Minkowski can't handle that properly.
Because that is, I mean, well, and to be fair, to be totally fair to
Mankowski.
Minkowski would still work like real Mankowski.
Would still work because you just Envision this as a three-dimensional
Extrusion where time was along the other axis, right?
So if you imagine what you were doing, here's time, here's to D.
I've got this thing and I know I'm going from here to here where it's
rotated and I've generated this swept volume that kind of looks like
that, right?
And then Mankowski would say.
Oh, yeah, just do the intersection test of
That with whatever the other thing is that you're trying to intersect
it with and hey, it just works and that's true.
The problem.
And the reason that we can't do this.
Is because it creates a concave shape.
And it creates a concave shape that there's really no way to subdivide
other than subdividing it like in two time steps again.
So minkowski, the only place that Mankowski really can't help you in
terms of the in efficient implementations of it that we use that are
based on concavity and that are based on convexity.
The reason that that Things Fall Apart is just because that convexity
during that animated rotation, but that's only for animated rotation.
So, if you were willing to say that, a 60th of a second, I don't care
about the small amount of rotation that's going to happen and I'll
just use either the beginning or ending rotation as my sweep.
Then it would work fine.
But if you actually need for some reason need to encapsulate That
animated sweep in your closing section.
It doesn't work anymore and you have to have alternate strategies.
I don't know of any one, step solution that works for for rotating
shapes.
I feel like at that point.
You're in a very difficult place.
I would recommend never getting into a position where you had to
handle that 100% animated like that because that sounds really tough.
I feel like you're I feel like you always want to try if you can to
make it so that it's okay to just subdivide to a few discrete
orientations that you care about and do the test against those.
I feel like that's
really the only probably saying way unless someone knows an algorithm.
It's really awesome that I don't know about.
How long have you been working on this current game?
50 hours is how long we have worked on the game so far.
So a little over one week of programming time, but that's with
explanations.
So if you were actually the map it into my actual programming time and
probably be something like, I don't know, 20 hours, 10 hours or
something like that.
Is it possible to make a cert so that it is possible to continue on
assertion failure?
Yes.
We haven't done that yet.
But obviously you can do that.
That is not something we have done, we could do that in a future
stream, but it hasn't been particularly important.
Are you doing any cyclomatic complexity analysis?
I have no idea what cyclomatic means, cyclomatic.
I don't think I've ever heard that.
If you want to tell me what cyclomatic means, I could answer the
question.
How would you represent a large?
Side-scrolling open world 2D where the character is basically just
walking along the ground.
So not really a platformer, but almost feels like a tile map would be
a waste of vertical space between parallel paths, one high above
another double linked list triple for branching path nodes.
I guess comes to mind but are apparently not good performance wise,
any ideas.
So I would just use I would say hang on till we get to how we're
actually going to represent the world fully at the end of this because
I suspect they'll it'll basically be the same as you would use for a
platformer, which is basically sparse possess placed things in the
world.
Is probably the best way to do it.
Tile map is more what we're using for thinking about how we're
generating the world.
And I'm not, I'm just not sure yet exactly what we're going to do, but
I suspect we'll do something that's closer to what you would actually
want the Platformers.
Well.
Is it possible to will you be considering trying to determine the
point of collision?
We are we do.
That's what we do.
That's what we just did.
So that's this.
This is the code that determines the point of collision.
And so we are.
We are accurately doing that now.
That's that's exactly what's going on.
Seems like the inability to robustly represent rotations and physics
is why complex physics and modern games.
So busted all the time.
It might be but there's other problems when you're doing a General
Physics engine.
It's usually honestly rotation is usually not the worst of your
problems.
It's usually contact.
Contact is usually where stuff gets really, really bad, but you're
right.
That rotation is a big problem.
It's just not the Collision detection of it.
It's the fact it's rotations non-linearity as it applies to contact.
That's the real bad news.
Real bad news.
So we at the end of questions, I don't see any more questions.
Oh, I meant determining the okay.
I see, greenish.
I meant determining the point of collision with the general gjk,
algorithm.
Yes, we probably will do that again.
I don't actually know if we'll do gjk.
I just assumed that gjk will be the most efficient thing for us to do,
but we could also do hand coded.
So, for example, the Collision detector in braids, I I wrote the
question chapter in braids as well.
And the way that it worked is, it's a hand coated rounded, rectangle
one.
So the way that it works is it stores.
Everything as the, as the sum of a square and a circle and it does all
of the collisions by hand in hand coded things that can do like Ray
casting versus this and overlap testing versus this and so on.
So it's possible and braid is the only 2D game that I ever had any
code in.
I think that I know of anyway,
a collision detection wise and so maybe we do something like that
because it worked pretty well in that game, but I don't know, you
know, like we'll see.
Are we doing a Raspberry Pi Port?
Just for the heck of it?
Or is there a deeper reason behind it?
Yes.
The reason that we're doing a Raspberry Pi port, or I don't know if
we're going to do a Raspberry Pi Port, but we're going to do a port to
some platform where everything is spect and we can boot straight to
the game with no operating system and Raspberry Pi at the moment is
just the best platform for that that I could find if there's a faster
if there's like a more powerful piece of Hardware, two years from now
when we're done with the game and it comes time to do a Raspberry Pi
version, then we'll do that version instead.
but right now, as far as I know the
Very pies.
The only thing that does that and so I will be looking for other
options in Raspberry Pi.
The Raspberry Pi is not necessarily something that I have any specific
affinity for other than just, it's completely documented and you can
boot straight into the OS straight into your game with no OS and
that's what I wanted.
Cyclomatic complexity a direct measure of the number of linearly
independent paths through the code know.
And we never will do that analysis either.
So it looks like we are at the end of the questions and of questions.
So I think that's about it.
Beaglebone black better than Raspberry Pi.
I think someone was saying yes, but beaglebones aren't documented.
Am I wrong about that?
Let's find out.
Right.
What?
Which 3D graphics accelerator?
Is it in the beaglebone?
Black?
Like basically, if, if they do not have full the full documentation
from the hardware manufacturer of the 3D Graphics later than it's not
useful to us.
Right?
And so, I don't know if they do or not.
So you have to look up is the 3D graphs alerted fully documented on
the beaglebone black and I mean fully as in no driver required.
We can write directly to the hardware and have full access to all its
capabilities.
Because you can do that on the pie.
So if you can do that on the beaglebone black we might consider it,
but otherwise not.
Ryan riess.
Can't you do that on a PC?
Write yourself a boot sector.
Put it on a USB stick and boot straight into your game with no s.
No, you can't.
And the reason that you can't is because the graphics cards aren't
documented.
So you can't actually use them.
You can sort of use them, you can have to use them and try to go from
the reverse engineered stuff and kind of maybe use them.
But I want a machine that's entirely documented so that we will be
able to use the entire machine.
And not have to tiptoe around and videos NDA or something.
Well, not NDA trade secrets that they won't even tell us how to
program, you know, the card or whatever.
Right?
Because that's just lame.
All right, so I think that's it for today.
I am going to say that we have finished our stream.
Thank you very much for joining me here for breakfast time, handmade
hero.
I'm glad our Collision sector.
Now, working smoothly.
I like the feel of this as well.
I like how I like, how it works.
I feel like
I feel like how we want the player to move, might change a little bit
because next week I'd like to do what I'd like to do.
Next week is get animation going for the guy so that he hops, you
know, long as he moves and as we play with that, we're going to have
to see how we want it to feel in terms of how it goes.
And when I say we, I really mean me because all of the movements going
to be tuned, so that I like it.
And I know there's a bunch of different people have different
preferences of how movement systems work.
So I can't really promise that it'll be the way other people might
want it to feel, but
Be the way, I want it to feel.
And of course, one of the nice things about handmade hero is all the
source code is available if the game ships and you don't like the
movement.
Well, that is a perfect reason to study up on the series.
Learn how to fix it and go in and change it to how you want it to
work, right?
So that's pretty cool.
Anyway, thank you very much for joining me for this episode of
handmade Hira.
It was a pleasure coding with you as always.
And if you would like to follow along at home with the source code,
you can pre-order the game on handmade here a.org, and it comes with
all this.
This code, you can download it every night from a link that you'll get
in your email.
And it also comes with the debug assets that we've been using, you
know, the little guy and the backdrop and that sort of thing.
So, you can go ahead and and pre-order that if you want access to all
that stuff, if you want to just support the video series, there's a
patreon that you could subscribe to.
And if you're trying to follow along at home and learn from the
series, there's a news and Forum site that I highly recommend checking
it out.
It's got the schedule for the week every week.
So you can go look.
For example, I'll post the schedule for next week, next Monday.
So you can see where it went.
All the times will be.
There's an episode guide allows you to catch up with past episodes and
it's got good Mark time markers and stuff that people contribute,
those coding resources page that Sports to Linux and Mac, if you're
trying to follow along a different platform.
And finally, there's a discussion board that you can go to the allows
you to ask questions and talk about the series with other people.
And it's also a place where people help me out.
If they spot typos in the code, they'll post them here.
And that's helped tremendously to have other people watching.
Because when I'm talking on the stream, I can't always concentrate on
the code that well on really, it helps.
So, thank you everyone who writes in and says, hey, you forgot.
Got to do blah.
That's that's really helpful to me and helps make sure that we don't
spend a ton of time on the stream tracking down typos.
So, that's it for today.
I will be back Monday, probably 8 p.m.
PST on Monday.
So, I hope to see you all there.
Have an excellent weekend, if I don't see you guys somewhere online.
Thanks, everyone.