Hello, everyone, and welcome to handmade hero.
The show where we code.
It complete game live on stream and
And have an increasingly baller profiler, which I typically honest
with you, don't really remember.
We're going to be, I think it was buttons.
So I think we're going to do that today today is a 264.
If you want to follow along at home day, 263 source code is what you
want to start with.
I'm going to go ahead and jump into it because I think what we're
supposed to do today is buttons and there's not a lot of mystery and
how to make a button.
So let's have at it.
Here's where we left off.
Oh, ffs.
Off we left off.
with our profiler, we were putting the pro back into profiler if I do
say so myself, we left off in a situation where
Our profiler was looking pretty darn snazzy and we could do some
things that were kind of awesome such as saying that we wanted to, you
know, take a look at this particular thing that was happening in the
game and say like okay here's some crazy number of events or something
that's all happening in here and we could just go ahead and say, you
know what, why don't you just stop for a second and let me like, you
know, pause the debug info and kind of go around and see for any given
frame.
What the breakdown?
Of the profile actually was right.
So that's pretty awesome that we could freeze the profiler and do all
this investigation we can do drilling down.
Like so right but we have some stuff that's kind of a little bit
janky.
This point, which is that once I drill down, I can't get back.
I can't say go back to the previous thing that you reviewing, right?
Or like up one level in the profile, right?
I can't do that.
I can't.
Restart.
Right.
So now that we're going in here, I have no actual way of ever
adjusting anything at all.
So like I basically can't, I can't do anything right?
And the reason that I can't do anything is because we have no way of
putting like buttons into the profiler or controls that like control,
what's going on.
So that's what I need to get started with today.
I need to also we had sort of did
Testing with low memory in the debugger and we probably don't want to
keep that going.
So if you remember we had a thing here where we did like we used eight
megabytes for the debug back buffer as a test to make sure the
recycling worked and we don't really want to do that.
We want to be able to have enough memory to store a significant
portion of the of the frames.
So I'm going to go ahead and switch it back so here you can see we've
got plenty of memory.
Now in fact we have 83 Meg's leftover I
I could, I could reduce it even more than that, but we might as well.
Plenty of room.
And so we can keep 2056 frames back and still have a healthy sort of
amount of room remaining in our debug system, which is what we want.
So, that's really what's happening there.
It's kind of weird to see those things fade in and out like that.
Anyway.
So what I need to do now is I need to sort of add more debug controls
here, besides just this like a play, and a pause button, and things
like that, would be nice as well as some things.
Excuse me.
As well as some things for controlling the profile view a little bit
more.
For example, one thing that might be nice is to be able to zoom in and
out or pan on it or something like this.
And another thing that might be nice would be 2 again to have that
back button and and some other buttons that could switch, you know, we
made that that debug sort of percentage like per frame, percentage
View, and and we don't have any way right now of bringing that back
up.
So all of that stuff would just be it's
That we could be doing right now and we can't because we don't have
any way to interact.
So as I'm going to focus on today is just adding the ability to have
those buttons.
So as you know when we have
You know, when we're sort of working the device system, we kind of had
this idea of getting a fair bit of Leverage this, it's just a debug
system.
A fair bit of Leverage out of a fairly small number of things.
So for example in our interface code, right?
Jump to here.
And our interface code, you know, we'll just throw something in here,
like a, you know, frame slider or whatever.
And then that just goes into the debug string, like everything else,
we'd have to write any new code to like handle it or anything and then
on the other side just gets picked up and goes, oh okay, you want the
frame?
Slider, put a frame slider in there.
So, what I should be able to do here is add some of these features,
right?
So that they're all kind of
So that I can add the kinds of controls that I want and have them be
usable right now.
There's a couple different things here.
One is that I may want to add.
I mean, in some sense I guess I don't know that.
I really need to add them in here in the sense that if we know we
always want the frame slider to have like the play and pause stuff on
it, I can just include it in the drawing of that and same thing with
the thread interval graph.
So I suppose maybe the easiest thing to do here at least at first is
to focus on how do I take an existing element that
Wants to have some buttons associated with it, and, you know, add
those in there.
So you can see here like, when we get to the thread interval graph.
Here is the thing that draws it.
It, you know, says here's how big it's going to be and then it sort of
puts that it draws it in here.
And what I want to do, right, is in here, I want to be able to do
something, which can draw either of these two, right?
I'd like to do something where I can say, yeah.
I Want My Graph to have like a
Type, and maybe it.
Maybe I even do this where I say switch graph type and then in here,
I've got, oh, there's the, you know, there's a thread profile or debug
graph thread profile, or something.
and then here, there's also a debug graph
rain bars.
Right, I could pretty easily do.
Something like this unfortunately I don't know what Stitch is what
time unfortunately I think that might be making things a little too
redundant.
So what I'm thinking might be a more interesting option, right?
Would be to just do something like this.
If we actually make it be, you know, up at this level of types, the
specificity.
There's nothing that says I can't have this thing change, its type
dynamically, right?
I can just set this type field and then it sets a new type field and
that way I can share this code and and still I can have this type of
be mutable by the user.
If the user would like to view this particular profile in a different
way, but I can also have the
Soon who's making the debug call on the other end when it's initially
created, create it this way, right?
I don't know if that makes sense, but hopefully it does.
And so the way that I could do that, I suppose there's a couple
different ways I could do that but basically what I'm thinking is when
we create the debug element we could just create what it's type is
there and in fact you can kind of see what we've been doing here.
This is kind of interesting which is that when we create a debug
element, we just use whatever its actual like whatever the event says
that this thing is, that's what
Do and you can kind of see, here we go, like, oh, okay, get out a
stored event, you know, of this thing.
And if we found a stored event, then you can render it.
But one of the sort of nastiness is of that and I think we can sort of
see that if we come in here, right?
Is that if the stored event doesn't exist you end up in this nasty
scenario where you don't draw anything.
And so what we would probably like to do is reverse a little bit, the
way this is working and see if we can, maybe make it a little bit more
based on the element.
So for example in here, I could say something like let's grab the
stored.
Out of this entirely.
In fact, the
Then the stored event is really just not that relevant to pretty much
any of this stuff, right?
so, if I were to do this and then take a look at the only people who
actually used the stored event,
Which is actually nobody I think.
Yeah, looks like nobody.
In fact, I'm quite certain it's nobody at this point.
So nobody actually uses that start events.
So from the element right, we should be able to determine what it's
type is if we just copy that filled up when we first see it,
And then we could switch the type of an element anytime we wanted to,
which would be nice for things where we want it to very right.
So, what I'm going to do here is say that in the debug element, which
is, where did that go?
That's not in here, that's in here in the debug element itself which
is who knows where?
I don't know where did it go?
Come on, there it is.
In the debug element.
I think what I'll do is put the type in here as well.
I don't remember what this is even called.
It's just called debug type.
so, when we actually create an element,
I never find that function.
Have you noticed, how many times I searched that function?
And I never find it.
It's get element from event.
That's what it's actually called yet, element from event.
When we create one of these,
Which is here.
Whenever we do this push direct all.
We would really have to do is say, well, whatever created it
initially, we'll just make that be whatever type it is.
And then I think we should be in pretty good shape, right?
So, this guy here, who's was drunk bitmaps.
We haven't actually made this work again.
What we will want to do is get the bitmap from the right frame.
And so I think what
Probably want to do there is this?
Use the viewing frame, ordinal would be my guess.
Do you bug event to text?
So here's the event.
This is this uses the event.
And then the bitmap uses the event.
So those are the only people that do ya and I suppose what I could do
to now that I think about it is I can just get
Up here and leave it null.
So I could say you know, in here that we only draw this stuff if
If there's a valid bitmap.
Right.
Similarly, I could say maybe something like
none of these things really have to do with the bitmap, so I could
actually do it this way as well, if I wanted to
Alright, so here I am getting my stored event.
And what I want to do here is I want to use that most recent I mean it
started viewing frame board until to get it.
So the way I would do this as I just go okay the element frames
I got the viewing frame worn at all and really this is like first
order event.
So this is like most recent or I guess this is last most recent sort
of it because there's multiple right?
There's multiple storage events for any given frame.
So maybe I'll say like boldest stored events, something like that.
And so now when I get that, I couldn't, I can choose to if I want to
grab some other event or whatever, or I can choose to use that
particular one and in the case of the bitmap, I think it's fine to use
that one.
Because if you output multiple bitmaps at the same place, I don't know
that we want to show them all we could Loop over them if we wanted to.
I'm not sure how much sense that really makes, but or we could, I
guess stack the next to each other, but I don't know that we want to
go through that.
Trouble, maybe we do.
Because they could even be different sizes.
It's quite a bit of work to go through and figure out how we would
want to lay that out.
Exactly.
And I don't even know exactly what it would mean, right?
And if there are more, we do we need to scroll them.
I don't know.
It seems like, that's a lot of you.
I work a lot of UI system.
Build out.
We'd have to do, which would all be useful if we did it in a sort of
generic way that we could use for other things, but it's just probably
not something we want to spend a lot of time building.
We don't want some awesome UI system for the debug layer of this at
the moment.
So I think probably what I'll do is just say we've got this one.
Here.
And so we'll take the oldest stored event.
and,
We'll just set that here.
So if we have an old historic event, I assume that
I assume that this is what we want, meaning the event portion of it.
Otherwise we don't want anything and this actually needs to be
Like that.
That's code.
That's valid all the time and our bitmap scale is also.
Valid all the time.
What is this?
This is just goes out here.
There we go.
So now this doesn't really have to switch on this type anymore.
This can switch on the element type.
So we still want to probably do the same stuff because we're only,
we're just going to, you know, we're going to go out to a different
one.
Just only at this point, all the rest of the code can be the same.
So let's go ahead and say that's the thread interval graph.
Let's go ahead and say that this is debug type frame bar graph.
And now we have sort of the code flow to switch between them.
So, all we need to do now is focus on making
That actual button.
This is the element.
Ah I've got too many things called element.
It's a bad name.
But you know what else are you going to do?
So you know, what would we call this?
If we weren't going to call this, maybe maybe what I could do is call
the layout elements, something else.
Let's let's see what if I did this.
not the greatest name in the world, but
And look at already, we already have this problem here.
Right.
That's why we had to change that one's name.
Let's see if that does any better.
Oops.
All right.
This is not layout, that's element.
So that looks all fine.
And this here can do the same thing as we were doing before.
Whereas if we got one of these guys, we can lay it out.
Oops, that's not good.
There we go.
Okay.
and,
I guess this is a u8 and debug type.
So we work saving space by putting that in the you ate.
So we got a cast it back out, we knew it.
So now my hope is that nothing changes here.
Things should be exactly the same and it is, which is good.
All that's good.
I don't actually remember.
Where was our, there's our entity.
This is kind of funny, like, right?
We only display those on frames where there actually is one of these.
And I guess again, that's something we could.
We could again as we're making this sort of improvement here, we could
fix that as well, right?
Because we're only displaying them when there's actually data there,
which leads to a like, sort of a flashing that happens, but we could
actually always sort of display it by just creating making sure that
we have an event that always works, right?
So we could say, like, debug event null event or something, right?
and,
Well, in to some degree, you know, even this probably we could upgrade
to considerably because the are events now have multiple frames are
German, then we could draw a little graphs on them and all kinds of
other weird stuff too, right?
So that's kind of a separate issue.
But anyway if we have one of these here, where we just have some kind
of a
You know, just a null event thing that we're printing or whatever.
What we could do is we could stuff the name of the event, right?
We could stuff the grid of the event, which is mostly what we're
printing out with whatever the elements grid was.
We could stuff the type with whatever the elements type is.
And we could leave it at that.
So,
That would mean that we can always pass an event.
Even if we didn't have one on that frame, it just wouldn't be a very
good one, right?
It just would be nothing there, but that's probably better.
And this can also be basically made to do this now, since there is no
case,
See where that's a problem.
So, let's run this.
And see.
And so now that's much nicer right now, it just prints out zeros, if
it doesn't know what's going on.
Instead of flashing instead of like changing the layout here, which I
think is, you know, strictly better to a certain extent.
Because here's a frame for example, where there's really no data at
all.
I'm not sure why that's still able to print something out in this case
because this is the collation frame.
I guess we just happened to always have it.
That's interesting.
But anyway,
I think that's better.
So now I want to see if I can add some of these some buttons in here.
I want to add some buttons that will do useful operations for us with
our profiler.
And so what I want to do is I want to do something, I guess that sets
the element type to a new type.
So I'm going to go ahead and create one of those.
I don't really know probably like debug interaction set profile, graph
or set element type, I guess is what it would be.
And so, what I'm going to do is I'm going to make an interaction for
these buttons.
And what I'd like to do is just be able to kind of Stack these buttons
up in an easy fashion.
So here is the stuff that does begin layout rectangle for this other
stuff.
I want to kind of do something else where I maybe do.
Like begin button row or something like this and button row.
I don't know if this should be, I'm not sure what you know what
exactly I want this to be per se.
But I'm just kind of sketching out what I probably want to type here.
I want to be able to say, I want to row of buttons that are going to
do some stuff and then I want to just be able to say like you know
layout button and I want to be able to like just put in here whatever
I want.
So you know, I want to be able to say like this particular thing is
thread interval graph or like or you know what this is.
Bubbly like an enum button or something I guess.
Yeah, like a state like a like a Boolean button.
I don't know what you want to call it but this is a button that can
basically be turned on, right?
It's like is this a threaded travel craft or not?
And so I could I'll call it threads for now because I don't know what
else to call it.
And then whether or not it's on is just if this element type equals
the thread interval graph type.
So basically, I'm going to pass it, like I want a button, it's called
threads.
I want you to say if you know, the element type is equal to
Traditional graph that says, whether or not this is like highlight,
like it's on right now it was so it's like true or false for the
buttons on.
And then I want to be able to do an interaction here where I create,
you know, a debug in a
Set element type interaction and that's going to be for our debug ID.
And we're going to set the element type to debug type thread interval
graph.
So that's just saying, I want a button.
I want to be labeled threads, I wanted to, you know, this to be the
criteria as to whether that's highlighted and then this is the action.
I want you to take in the case where it gets clicked and then I want
to be able to do this really easily.
So I want to be able to make another one to, which just says like,
okay, this is the frames version of this.
This will show the frame bar graph and the same thing.
So that seems like a pretty easy way to do buttons to me, and I like
that, right?
Pretty simple.
We don't have any other settings at the moment but I do have some
other things that I said I wanted, right?
I'd like to be able to go up.
In the hierarchy.
And so I want something like
Action button which is up and that action button would presumably do
something like it would set the profile graph root.
And it would set the profile graph route to like a being above where
we were now.
This one's a little tricky and the reason it's a little tricky is we
don't record that piece of information.
I don't think, I don't really remember to be honest with you, but
I don't think we do.
So for example in our debug elements here, right, there's no such
thing as like a parent.
We can't like walk to to our parent in any real case and the other
kind of nasty thing about that.
Is in the profile.
We don't really even necessarily know what that parent would be per se
because we don't know how we got here there.
There could be many ways to get to the same place that we are viewing
in our profile, right?
And so that's kind of a little confusing as well.
Now.
I mean, I suppose one thing we could do,
And I don't know how I feel about this.
I'm thinking to myself,
How I feel about it?
One thing we could do is just do our rendering and allow ourselves to
zoom and then instead of like clicking on individual things, we
You know.
We would just zoom in on them and then there's no concept of it's just
it's just a location in the profile space which might be smarter.
I don't know.
But
You know, here's so let me just do something that I know we can do
right now because I just want some way to get back.
So let's just put a root button in and so that's obvious what that's
going to do, right?
That would create an interaction that allows us to get directly back
to the root layer.
Oops.
I think I just opened up the to-do list, accidentally.
I'm not really sure how I did it, but it did.
So I'm going to go take a look at that.
In the, in the draw profile.
Stuff.
When we do the draw a profile, right?
We were creating one of these interactions and we sort of created it
set profile graph root like like so.
And so I'm going to go back down here and make that happen.
So I suppose what I could do is just do it like this.
Say we've got, you know, Zoom root.
And, and now we're going to say is, well, the element we want to set
it to is none, right?
We want to set it to zero.
And so what I'm going to do there is just say, well, okay, that's the
interaction for this guy.
And then for these guys where we are sort of creating them in line and
I guess we pretty much want to.
Well, I guess this is what we want to be able to do is make this
essentially a function, right?
So we want there to be a debug interaction function that we can just
call that right in line takes one of these.
Makes one of these and returns it, right.
So it makes
It makes one of these with whatever the debug idea is that we passed
and then it takes whatever the debug type is.
And oops.
Here we go.
And just sort of sets that as a value that can be retrieved later.
So I'm just going to go ahead and pull that out and make that be a
little function that people can use here.
Like so.
And then, oops.
Well, I got to rename this first.
and then,
It's got to finish up.
Yeah, the actual UI code so that would specify all the information we
need.
So, all we need to do now is actually make a way that these button
interactions will actually, you know, flow through the system.
We've got to make, you know, a thing that will lay them out and and so
on.
So here is like our begin element rectangle and the sort of
interaction stuff that we do for it and the end element and all that
stuff.
So, what I want to do here is I want to
Sort of influence.
I want to make a new way in which these things might happen and it
occurs to me that probably I need to pass Row in as I'm going here.
Although it technically, I guess I wouldn't necessarily have to do
that because the if I just pass, lay out all the time, that's probably
all.
I actually really need now that I think about it.
Well, but, you know, so if I come through here and I imagine that I'm
going to be passing this, and I imagine that I've got, you know, some
kind of a layout row thing happening here.
These aren't really going to pass anything.
Excuse me.
And since they're not customrendered, I can do all the rendering
inside these routines myself as well.
So that basically anyone who wants to use the button system doesn't
have to use any kind of rendering themselves, they can just make, you
know, their own buttons work.
They can just say I want a button and know that they get it.
So let me just finish checking this out here.
So we have a billion button and this is the state or like, you know,
highlighted this is the
Name of the button.
The name that's on the button.
Same here.
This is the interaction.
The Boolean buttons also have an interaction when you click them.
And I think that's really it.
So now what I need to do
and you can kind of see the methodology that I'm going through here,
right?
I did what I always say that you should do if you know what the usage
code is going to look like.
You just write it first and that's exactly what I did.
I was like what do I actually want this to look like and I wrote it
out Snuffleupagus oriented programming, as I think I called it before,
you just have an imaginary.
You imagine, you have some system that's going to do what you want,
you code to that system.
And then you see what the API looks like.
If you just imagined, you had it.
That's what I did.
And now,
Now I'm going to go actually type in the code for that system and
reverse engineer.
What actual other information and structs I need to make that happen.
and again, this sort of gets at this thing, I was talking about
yesterday when I was talking about how, I don't think I've tried,
Programming is ever useful.
It's because I never do it right?
I never actually do that.
Objects will automatically appear when you follow good procedural
programming and you know, other search techniques, the objects just
make themselves.
You don't have to think about them, they just occur.
There are a byproduct of a correctly functioning system that should
never be the starting point and never be a focus.
It should just be incidental right?
And that's exactly what I'm going to have happen here.
I'm going to take a look at what I need to actually.
Fulfill the requirements that the UI code wanted to have happen here
and that will tell me what I need to actually store and that's all
there is to it.
So anyway,
Here we go.
I know that I can't draw a row of buttons, perhaps, until after I know
how many buttons there are, maybe in this case, I guess that's not
really true.
You know, normally if I wanted to fill a specific with that would be
true because then I have to divide by the number of buttons that there
are.
But in this case I don't know that I really need to do that because
I'm just kind of going to stack buttons up along the way.
I may not really need to do that.
Now it's
Possible that I still should but I'm just thinking about it, I guess I
don't really have to.
So when I come in here and do an action button, really, I guess all I
need to do is lean on the existing element system to make that element
occur, right?
So what I can do is is do exactly this stuff.
I can say I want an action button, I'm going to begin an element
rectangle for it.
I need this obviously to have the layout system in some way now
whether it's a parameter or whether it gets passed down.
And some other thing is part of the row situation, I don't know at the
moment, but, you know, we'll see.
So I'm going to go ahead and say that I get the layout there.
I need the dimensions.
The dimension can come from me, figuring out how big this text
rectangle is.
So I have a basic
Text element thing here and you can kind of see that.
That really all I need to do is is the code for this thing.
Now, I don't know that I really want to use this explicitly though
because I believe that I want to do my own kind of custom drawing and
stuff here, but for the most part, this code will be fairly similar.
So I'm going to start with that.
But then I'm going to make it a bit different and it's possible that
maybe you won't, you know what I could do to, I could just expand
this.
This function, right?
What I could do is say well there's basic text element and that's
going to actually maybe come up here, become more of a First-Class
citizen as in the way that it works, right?
So let's put that up here, here is basic text
That does all the stuff that we need except putting maybe a box around
the thing, but even that we don't necessarily need at the moment so
we'll just hold off on this for one second and say, well okay, we
could just call basic text element.
We know what the interaction is, right?
And we know that we've got to me.
The layout and the text that it needs.
So that's a pretty good start for making an action button, right?
But the problem that we have is In N element, so we want a row of
buttons, but in N element every time an element is finished, we're
going to advance to the next line.
You can see that happening here, right?
So what happens is as this thing sort of draws itself, we have this
facing why it situation happening.
And so what I think we want to do
Instead here is is introduced into RL our layout system.
The concept that we don't always want an automatic sort of carriage
return as we're stacking up Rose.
And so what we could do is say all right, let's get rid of
Let's get rid of that.
So when we do begin, we could even say begin row and end row since it
doesn't have anything to add buttons.
Now, we could do begin row and and row.
And what that could say is all right, the layout system is now going
to go into, you know, a rapping mode or something like this.
Like, you know, Auto Line Feed or no Line Feed equals true, right?
And then
You know, in here no Line Feed or maybe if we're being sort of amusing
ourselves and we want to support nesting these together, we could do
that.
So we do begin row and we do and row.
We're just going to say that there's going to be no line feeds
happening now.
And then we would do is say, all right, we make an action button.
We just make a basic text element and maybe we make a Boolean button
for now.
We do exactly the same thing and then we don't even really need the
concept that Rose even return anything, right?
We don't even need, that's not even necessary.
So we just do this and and we're basically done, right?
There's nothing.
Nothing weird going on there.
So we could also now have a highlight for the time being that says,
well, let's draw these things into different ways depending on the
circumstances, so we could do that as well.
And the other thing that I can do now is, I can go Implement that no
Line Feed concept which I believe we have to start in here by adding
to our layout system.
Wherever that even is I
Manure, that is struct layout.
Severe is never really made it over here.
Did that?
Let's get those out there.
Let's get those into the H file.
Yeah, so what I want to do now is in these layouts, I want to have a,
you know, an incrementer, which is essentially, just the no Line Feed
counter.
And so then I guess got to come back here and Port this code, to the
new thing that I've decided it needs to be, which is, it doesn't need
to do that, that sort of return value stuff there.
But it needs to pass the layout everywhere.
We also decided that it's really just begin ruin and row.
And there we go.
So now let's just finish up by implementing that no Line Feed thing.
I'm going to first see what happens when I run it to so you can kind
of see what I'm talking about here.
So here's our profile and you can kind of see that we've got these.
These values getting printed out here.
Ah well, so going back to the root is a little trickier than we
thought.
This might want to try to say no in which oh well wait can we set it
to the route?
We can send it to the roof though but I suppose I'll just allow it
anyway.
So setting the grid 20 allows us to go back to the root.
Gotta go fix that opengl texture submission stuff.
All right.
So now we can go back to the route to our hearts content.
But we can't click on these two, for some reason, and I'm not sure.
Whoa, I am sure why we've never implemented that case, we might as
well Implement that case, while we're down here, right?
So, an interactive for in, in debug interaction,
Set.
element type then I'll we should have to do is just say that whatever
element we are ostensibly interacting with in this case,
although,
It's actually this.
Am I right?
Here's our debug interaction.
Yeah.
So it's a little janky because we can't store.
We wouldn't be able to store the way that we've done this.
You can't store like multiple parameters to an interaction right now
which is kind of lame because we want to be able to store both the
element and the the type that we want to set that element to if that
makes sense.
And so really, we want this to be a little bit more expansive, right?
We don't really want this to be.
As constrained that makes sense.
Like I want to be able to do that which I suppose I can just do that.
Make sense.
Not really much of a reason why I couldn't do that.
And so if I was to do that, I can just set whatever I want.
I can just say I want to set this element to this type and be done
with it.
Give me
let me take a look here.
and,
See.
So yeah, this checks for IDs, it checks for the types, and then a
check to see if the so this would also now just check to see if the
elements are equal as well.
And
Any time someone was going to make one of these.
It's already basically clearing that out.
So when I do a set element type interaction, really, all I need to do
now is just say that.
Well you have to tell me what element you actually meant as well.
Because that way you can basically create a generic command that can
set any elements type regardless of who's doing it or when which seems
better to me.
And there's no reason not to do it.
I mean, we're essentially sort of making a little Lambda right elect
Poor Man's closure to do what it is that we want to do when we set
that of course doesn't work which is also good but
That's because again, I didn't implement it.
So yeah, so in this case we should just be able to say well
I want.
whatever, my element is, I want its type to become whatever the
parameter was
And that's, I think it.
And of course, I have to cast that, but I guess I could even do this.
Because, why not?
Oops.
and so,
That.
Should be that.
All right.
So now, we can switch between these two pretty, pretty
straightforwardly, right?
But like I was saying it's not, they're not really like, you know, we
don't want to take up lines for a button and so that I want to
implement the row, sort of wrap wrapping situation a little bit
differently.
So it's easy for us to kind of switch in that way.
So doing that is really straightforward like I said we kind of already
set it up so that the layout system knows which which way it's in by
looking at that.
No Line Feed variable.
So all we have to do is take a look at our code here.
That does are advancing after each layout element and just say well.
Okay,
If we're in a no line feed mode, then we're going to advance the X.
Otherwise we clear in advance.
The why.
So in this case,
Where we have?
The return happening.
I suppose the other thing we need to do is
Pull this out into sort of a separate thing and I'll show you why in a
second.
Hmm.
Well, I take that back.
Yeah.
So, what I want to do is I want to be able to pass the dimension here.
To advance by like so and that way I can call it after the row is over
because if I otherwise we'll get it so that it won't advance after the
it won't go back, it won't do the carriage return, it'll print the
graph and then do the carriage return which is not what we want.
So I need a way of calling Advance element when you end a row as well.
So I'm going to call Advanced element here with total
Which will do sort of what it has been doing and then when we need to
do an end row, I'll just call Advanced element and I'll just pass it.
No bounds at all.
And so and and well not quite no bounds at all.
So,
That's actually a rectangle.
Right.
And so what I need to do here is just create a rectangle that
essentially doesn't have any bounds.
so, it would be
The rectangle at the current location which is rectangle min-max.
Sorry rectangle, too.
Don't know why I put layout element there.
All right, now, this isn't quite right yet.
And I guess we'll see that in a second and then we'll fix it and kind
of move forwards.
But anyway, so if we have new line feed, then what we want to do is
just move the layout at X rather than the layout at y.
So the layout at why would stay the same.
And what we'd want to do is get the max corner of the X and add the
spacing X2 it right, and we don't have a current concept of spacing X.
I don't think.
Or do we?
I don't actually know where these things come from.
They just come to the layout.
So I don't know if we have a spacing X.
I don't even know what that is supposed to be.
So, I'm going to go ahead and change this around a little bit.
There we go.
So we haven't defined a spacing x yet, which is a problem.
So we're going to have to make one of those and that's what again,
whatever we want that spacing to be, but that's pretty easy.
So, we can just do spacing X here.
And then, whenever we Define spacing, why we can Define spacing acts,
and I don't know what it should be, I don't really care, we can always
adjust it.
So that's about that.
Now, when we actually create this, and in fact, I guess that's sort
of, when you can see down here when we create this initially, we also
have a slight problem, which is that this layout doesn't actually know
what its original X Baseline is.
So, if you take a look in here, where we've got sort of this layout,
and we've got this app parameter,
Really, we've kind of want that to be an offset in some way, or we
want to track the two values separately, right?
And there's two and I, you know, there's there's equivalent ways that
we could do that.
So what I think we should probably do is say there's like a base
corner or something like this and an at, I don't know, something like
that or we can set a left margin.
Anything like this.
303.
I'm not really sure how we were processing depth properly.
I guess we just increment by depth automatically as we kind of go.
But anyway, point being I'm just going to set this.
So we know what our left margin was, and that's important because in
order to Line Feed, that's the only way we're gonna be able to get
back to it, if that makes sense.
So, let's see here.
In this case, I'm just going to set this to base Corner X.
We know whether they don't really know what that function is called.
All right, so first things first, make sure everything's still working
properly and it appears to be so that's all good.
And then you can see, we're already a little closer to correct.
Because now these are at least on the same line, but we still have
some more stuff that's not correct about.
So the first thing is the one that I was talking about before, which
is you, notice how it doesn't that carriage return is not quite the
correct thing and the reason for that is because we haven't tracked
what the lowest point in y is
On that line.
So this code here.
Remember I mentioned this write this code here is not going to be
correct anymore because get min quarter dim why we were previously
using that value because we knew we were just rendering one thing and
then going to the next line we knew that the only thing we need to
know was how low that thing went.
But now if we're going to stock up many things on a row, we
essentially need to keep track of what the lowest thing actually was.
So in advance element, we always have to do something here.
Here, which is going to say that like the layout next y base, or
something like this, right next?
Why line is going to have to equal, whatever the minimum value was of
our current best one.
And the one that we you know, are sort of using are seeing now.
And then when we come through here and we're going to set our our why
layout we want to set that to be whatever.
That next why line was regardless of what the current element that
we're advancing for is.
and then, when we're done with that, we want to clear that next, why I
line out
So, we don't have to worry about it, right now.
We'd also probably like this to be 0.
So, rather than looking at it this way, what I'd probably say is,
well, let's take a look at what our at.
Why is
Right.
And say, what is the difference between these two?
So if you were to try to go to them in corner from where we were, how
far would that be right?
Like what's the Delta?
If that makes sense.
And then we just keep
We keep that and this is really like next y, Delta or something.
That makes sense.
That way in it 2-0 still works for this guy and so when we get this
next why line, then what we'd say is like oh okay it's actually just
going to add to wherever we currently were will add whatever that
Delta is and then we'll be in good shape and when we clear it would
just clear, it 2-0.
Easy peasy lemon squeezy as Jeff likes to say.
And so now we've just got another thing in here which is R32 next.
Why line
And that should now check that, whoops.
Next slide Delta
Okay.
so now when you take a look you can see that now, we actually have
these properly leaving the space that you would have expected them to
leave you know before this this guy comes in and we can toggle these
guys nicely and all that stuff works but unfortunately we don't really
have
Spacing here, that makes a whole lot of sense.
And so, what we want to do is take a look with our
Sort of with our text element stuff here.
Where we're doing Advanced element on the total bounds and figure out
why our total bands is advancing so much more than it should.
Now
I'm not certain.
This is not really dim.
This is like the element wrecked.
first of all,
I'm pretty sure.
It's a name that a little clearer so that it's not confusing.
So, the thing that I'm not sure about is, this seems like it should be
correct, like, whatever the maximum coroner was of the thing that we
were using is where we would be now.
And so I think the problem I suspect is that we have our depth value
like our indentation value is kind of janky, right?
We're taking this indent and I think we're implying that indent each
time here, right?
Because that indents like baked in
And so what we really want to do is we really want to make it so that
the indent only happens on advance.
So that depth, wherever that is actually happening, which I assume is
in here somewhere.
So there it is.
When you look at total Min corner, you can see this nonsense
happening, right?
And what we really want to do is say that's not something we actually
want in here.
That's something we want to do when we actually do our line advance.
So, when we do Advanced elements in here, is really the part.
And so when we do, when we go back to the base Corner, then we would
do this.
This sort of addition based on the depth.
So now that seems a little more reasonable.
Of course, we wouldn't handle the very first one properly, which you
can see here, although I don't, I don't know why the depth is
considered to be non zero through here.
That's a little bit weird but now these things are tightly packed
which is what we would expect.
Now, maybe we want to make a little bit of space between them so we
can see the difference in them, but that's our prerogative.
Now rather than something that's required which we don't actually
want.
So yeah, get a little better.
This ghost and to be cleaned up a little bit, but definitely getting a
little bit better.
Now, the other thing that we probably want to do is take a look at
basic text element situation here and say that we want this to be a
little bit probably cleaner or a little bit more responsive.
I guess is what I should say.
So we know whether this interaction is hot
Where is the, is it this way?
I don't really remember how we do this.
That seem right.
Is hot, interaction is hot, that's what I wanted.
so, what I really want to say I guess is
Is hot.
Equals interaction is hot.
Okay, so if I know this is hot then what I could do is say there's an
item color and a hot color, right?
And I suppose, the person who's calling me could also do that but I
think it's a little bit more.
Interesting if that's just passed in here and maybe by default, this
actually does do that.
So maybe by default, you know, it's this sort of thing.
And, and then I can just say well if it's hot then we use the item.
I'm going to use the hot color, otherwise we use yet bar.
And and that seems good.
So then, you know, we get a little bit of highlighting here, which is
good and
These don't really have interactions so I should probably make it so
that hot interactions are a little less.
A little less highlight e there because I assume that that interaction
is a null interaction.
So I think probably and I don't even know like I feel like that should
probably be something that we check for.
So I feel like saying interactions are equal.
We should possibly also say you know if the interaction that we're
talking about
Is not real.
So interaction type, if there isn't an interaction, then it can't be
hot.
Right.
Because you can only really be a hot interaction if there is an
interaction at all.
So at that point, it's like, you know, makes a little more sense of
course, for some reason, again, that didn't seem to actually change
it, which it should.
Right.
I mean, that should be failing.
The is hot test because anything that's another Direction shouldn't
actually work.
What am I missing there?
Oh, I know what I'm missing.
Those are probably set to auto.
That's a little tricky since those are set to Auto, we don't know
whether they're going to have an interaction or not.
It's an interesting dilemma.
Anyway I'll end it there because we did what we wanted to do.
And we've got a little more work to do but but you know it's a good
place to stop.
So we'll take about 10 minutes of Q&A.
And by the way, lemon and T is like the total right thing to put in t
I'm not sure why there's even a discussion about that.
It's way better tea.
Tea with lemon is awesome.
It's way better than tea with milk.
Kubrick Caleb.
Not a serious question.
Why not just import npm and use left pad to indent the strings?
That is a very good point certainly that would have led to increased
robustness for handmade hero.
It's Isaac.
I think you were selecting the ground as an entity.
Is that bad for some reason?
Pseudonym 73 posted a PDF.
What is the PDF say?
Oh cool.
A length Arc.
Length, parameterization of spline curves.
That's kind of fun.
So it tries to re parametrized the Sprites flying so that it's
distance is equal is constant.
That's pretty cool.
I really have time to read this.
All right now, but I'm just kind of skimming it.
so it's basically an iterative sub divider, that attempts to produce a
constant parameter ization set of splines from a non from one that's
non
Which seems like a totally reasonable approach, right?
Sean McGrath, you know, how if you add one letter to how you get IBM,
did you know if you add one letter to VMS?
You get Windows NT.
Yes, I did know that.
I don't know if that's why they did it but I did know.
I have heard that sort of urban legend at least.
Jesse Mayer.
So this interface system is a very simple immediate mode design.
Not really you could do a much simpler one if you wanted to.
We use interaction storing, which means that we don't have a frame of
latency when you interact with the system,
We do have a frame of latency when you for highlighting, but not for
interaction, if that makes sense.
So you could actually do a much simpler kind of immediate mode
structure, which doesn't?
Which just does the if any action right in line if that makes sense.
If you had to, why are there some blue lines outside the profile
window signs?
So those are remember, normally we've got this guy which shows all the
threads separately if that makes sense.
And so if you have a really long thread that's like doing asset
loading, that takes multiple that you know, exists across a frame
boundary, you wouldn't really notice that because it only flashes for
a second in here, if you have a long asset load, that takes a long
time.
Time.
You could start an asset load in this Frame and have it last into the
other room because it's on a separate thread.
So it if that thread has no notion of frames and doesn't care about
frames at all, it just started was doing its thing.
So, you can easily go outside the profile window.
We don't make any attempt to stop that and I'm not sure I want to stop
it because it's correct in that sense.
Since this is debug view, I don't care.
Really how pretty it is.
And that is what actually happened.
It started in this Frame and went you know, to the next frame and I
don't really have much of a plan for if I don't have a thing in mind
where I'm like, how would I like to see that, you know,
Dude, in basement 1.
Visual Studio 2015.
You can use clang as a compiler.
Can you though?
I mean, I don't think you can because it obviously doesn't handle.
Deco Speck in Trends.
So decals stuck in type, so it can't compile actual windows.
Declaration.
So I'm not sure how it would work, unless I'm missing something.
Can you have are using clang CL?
Yes, I was.
All right, so any other questions?
Does not look like it.
Jesse Meyer you were mentioning before about objects are rising as a
natural consequence of properly engineered code as a system requires.
But do you do not mean a C++ object so what do you mean as an object?
Well, so an object is obviously a nebulous term.
But to give you an example.
Let's say we have this thing here.
Right.
So handmade render group is basically like a system that we use that
does our rendering, right?
It's how our rendering its buffered and processed and at no time
during the development of this did we sit down and go let's think
about what the struts are going to be.
Because that's really important, or what functions go with, which
structs because it's irrelevant to programming, it literally is
completely irrelevant.
It it does not it's not a thing that you ever have to think about for
any reason.
So what I mean by the objects fall out of it is when you actually just
focus on what the code actually has to do you just find out by what
you wrote and what it had to do.
What needs to get stored where
We know that object transform and render group are two different
things because we found that out when we wrote the code, it was just
much better when we separated this piece of information out as
something that could be talked about separate from this one.
Right?
And that's so crucial.
That's the core thing.
I mean when I say that object-oriented programming is a bad idea, you
never think about objects.
They are not a thing that you conceptualize in your head.
If you're programming properly, I literally have never seen anyone do
programming that I thought was good with that mentality.
What you do is you focus on what the code actually has to accomplish
and then you find out how the data is bundled automatically from what
you had to do.
What pieces, the algorithms actually had to draw from
And that is crucial.
So it doesn't even really matter to me.
What you want to call an object, those are the critical things.
What data gets bundled together semantically, which are structs and
what do our functions actually do, right?
Which are, you know, the action, which is the actual content of the
code.
That is the entirety of the determination of the architecture of the
system.
And you come at that by figuring out what the code needs to do and
figuring out what data needs to be bundled in.
You know what, the most efficient bundling of the data is to make
those functions work, the way they need to work, and the people who
call them be able to use them the way that they want and that's the
end of it.
So, if at any time you switch your focus over to something of the
form.
Well, a render entry bitmap.
Really like people who use a render entry bitmap.
Should not know that like there's some members of this thing and I've
got to like, you know, make sort of a private way of making rendering
to get massive.
Only some people can do and you start creating this concept that the
object is somehow an important thing.
And I need to start focusing on properties of the object.
Is just a very inefficient and error-prone method of architecting your
system.
And it does not result in good systems.
So typically if you want to go from a state like we haven't handmade
hero where you know, we're making the code and we're going fairly
efficiently along, but we're not stopping to make any of these things.
Like, bulletproof or reusable.
We're not like trying to ship a sort of a standalone system using any
of these particular components.
Um, the end people ask me this question of time, like, does this
change with larger teams?
Are all this other nonsense?
And the answer is always, no it doesn't, it's the same thing.
What you do, if you want to start making this code, into something
that's more reusable more.
Like that can be shared out to multiple people without causing
problems so on you don't do anything differently than what I just did.
All you do is you start moving code out of the each file into the CPP
file and you only put in the H file to things that they need to see.
That's all you do.
That's it, that's the end of it because then they're not bothered with
like, you know, maybe they don't need to know what a render entry
direct entry rectangle is so we just move it out of the h-file end of
the story, right?
And they take, you know, they just
See, they just see this.
You know, instead of this and now they don't have that things to pick
to them.
They don't go looking in it, they know they're not really supposed to
unless it's something important where they would go digging into your
code, right?
And we take only the functions from here that we have thought about
and made sure we Define the functions to work.
Exactly.
They should.
And we take that and we put those functions in the H file.
That is how you ship good architectures that are easy to use the last
a long time.
I'm etcetera, etcetera.
There is no other part of it.
There's nothing else about it.
If that makes sense, you have a typo in the comment for object
transform that's probably true.
You probably have a lot of typos in a lot of things.
There is no typos.
Actually, that particular case.
Yeah, just to be clear Thang is intentional like its own thing.
Sometimes there's just an accent, you know, sometimes you're going to
move this out to its own thing, but other times they're going to move
this out to its own thing.
that's,
So that is.
All right, I'm going to close it down.
Up there unsaved changes.
Well, I guess I change this.
What did I change?
Oh right, I see, I didn't really change anything.
I was just sort of typing while I was complaining about how people
shouldn't use of trade program.
All right.
Thank you, everyone for tuning in for another episode of handmade
hero.
If you would like to follow along at home with the source code, you
can always fear to the game about Hammer here at or it comes to the
source code that I update every night so you can be up to date.
We also have a forum you can go to to answer questions.
Hopefully a forum that will soon get a facelift do.
Impending release of handmade Network, which I believe is happening.
Later this month, there's also a patreon page and go to the most part,
the video series and a tweet Baht, which I will have to go start.
Now, as we talked about in the pre stream, anytime they reboot my
server, I have not actually gone and figured out how I put things in
the startup sequence, in this particular flavor of Unix.
So every time they wrote my server, have to go manually restart the
Tweet bot, which is probably not what I should be doing.
I should find out where they actually start up sequences and
It in there.
But Unix probably fifty thousand places.
It could be depending on the particular release of the particular
distribution.
So, you know it is.
Anyway, that's about it.
I'll be back here tomorrow.
5:00 p.m.
Pacific Daylight time.
Hope to see you back here.
We're seems like we're getting pretty far along on the debug code.
So I feel like we should be kind of being able to bolt everything up
relatively soon here.
I mean, feels like things are kind of converging.
We're adding some nice features and and stuff.
Feels pretty good.
So it's kind of seems like we'll be able to
Wrap that up this week maybe and move on some of the other items on
our to-do list until tomorrow.
I hope you have some other programming that you might be doing and I
hope it goes well if not well there's always tomorrow.
So take it easy everyone and I will see you back here until then have
fun.
Programming else you on the internet, take it easy.