Okay, hello everyone, and welcome to handmade hero.
The show where we code a complete game live on stream.
No engines, no libraries.
It's just us here, and this is a very special episode of handmade
hero.
Actually, I would like to dedicate this episode to, you know, I guess
I'm not sure how to do this.
Like, normally, you know, if you have someone that you want to
dedicate an episode to
In a positive way.
So you like I would like to dedicate this episode to you know such and
such who helped out with something or whatever.
But on this episode of handmade hero, I would like to do the inverse
of that.
I would like to dedicate this episode of handmade hero to how much
Microsoft is an awful company and I hate them because, basically, my
last two days have been been taken up with Microsoft, awesomeness,
because I upgraded, my
Zeenat work for the first time since 2008, and I went from Windows 7
to using Windows 8 and it was absolutely ridiculous.
How awful absolutely awful.
It was, first of all, they broke their font rendering somehow
normally.
I use Liberation mono, you've seen me use Liberation mono on the
stream.
I use it every day, well, using
In mono on the machine at work, the underscores are all missing.
Now there are no underscores in Liberation mono at the point size that
I am using.
They vanished, you go, one point size up, and they're back, so it's
like whatever in turn they assign to the anti-aliased font.
Rendering code, could not figure out the fact that a one pixel wide
underscore, should still show up when you shrink the font.
So, that was fantastic.
So now I've got to go decide on a new font to use for programming
because Microsoft can't figure out how to render an underscore thumbs
up.
All right, thing to I tried to move my visual studio.
2012, professional Edition from the machine to the new machine.
So, I install it using the same installation media I used before, I
enter the same product key that I was using on the machine that I
replaced.
And it says invalid product key.
That's it, it's just invalid product key.
Call Microsoft, give them the product key.
They're like, that's a valid product key and I'm like, yeah, I know,
it's a valid product key.
It was the product here is using on Windows 7.
The machine that I just replaced, and they're like, well, we can't
really help you with that.
But if you want to pay $499, we can create a support ticket for you to
find out.
Why
Are DRM isn't working on your machine.
I am not making a single
Of this up.
This is after like a 30 minute phone call to them.
So it's like, okay, I bought your product.
Your DRM is so broken, that it can't even figure out how to run on my
machine.
And now I have to pay you $500 for the privilege of you figuring out
how the other intern.
I maybe it's the same intern, maybe you just have one intern who
programmed both your underscore rendering code on the font system and
like the DRM for visual studio 2012.
I'm not sure, maybe it's just one guy or maybe it's a team of guys.
Guys.
Maybe you've got a whole cradle filled with little babies in diapers
with little rattles that they shake and they're just sitting around
their kind of stinking up the place and every once in a while you
decide you're going to poop out a new version into one of your
diapers.
You pick one of them up, you sit him down at the keyboard and you're
just like, hey man, see what you can do with this font code.
I'm sure it's going to be great.
So that was fantastic.
No, it's really.
It's just, it's fine.
It's totally fantastic.
That's been my past two days has been stuff like that.
I was like in and
Absolute rage.
It's one of those things where every time I have to touch a system
that involves Microsoft software, it's like the worst possible thing.
And like I end up just switching back to Linux even though I don't
like using Linux these days very much.
It's like man, I was like this close to just bagging Windows entirely
at the office.
I think sometimes we didn't have to run Photoshop.
I just go ahead and do it because using a slightly worse to bugger, is
just totally fine at the end of the day compared to the stuff that
These people put me through and that's for a paying customer like, oh
my God, these are like legitimate versions of Windows and and visual
studio professional 2012.
This isn't even like the free version of Visual Studio, which you can
download on the internet.
I just don't know what to say.
I sincerely hope that you guys continue to sort of your slide into
irrelevance in this industry, good riddance to bad rubbish.
And with that said,
I think maybe like, you know, maybe what we need to do on handmade
here a very soon, is stop streaming this from Windows, and start
streaming it from Linux because I have had just about enough.
So with that in mind we're going to be doing some more debug code
today.
And again it's going to be dedicated to how much Microsoft is awful at
everything that they do today is day 179 and day.
178 obviously is going to be the source code that I'm going to start
with.
So if you want to start with,
With the same code that I have starting with today.
If you want to follow along at home and you preorder the game on
handmade hero dot-org, you're going to want to unpack day 178 source
code because that's the source code that I'm starting with.
So, let's go ahead and boot that up here on Windows 7.
I guess, the last version of Windows that maybe works at all.
In terms of actually rendering fonts who knows maybe they'll never
ship another version that renders fonts properly again maybe they'll
just start eliminating letters one at a time from the English language
until they get
Down to letters.
They can actually handle
So where were we?
We left off at a point where we sort of had some cool debug timers
working and they're kind of groovy, right?
I mean, we're looking at them.
They're using what I like to call Windows Safe letters, which are
witcher's, no underscores.
So Windows is actually capable of rendering them even on Windows 8,
which is shocking.
You know, it's a little bit challenged in that department.
Oh no, it's not so push render element with that underscore might
cause a big problem.
Those of you following along with Windows 8 at home, I apologize.
Surrender element.
Just has a big old space there.
What can you do unsolved?
Problem in computer science, rendering an underscore.
So we've got these counters up there and the counters themselves are
pretty cool right now.
They're actually thread safe so far, so you can actually have multiple
threads that are all kind of pounding on the same function and it will
actually count the hits properly and the cycle counts properly for
that, which is kind of cool.
And, you know, we've got this nice display that updates in real time
so we can see
See it.
But we've already got a couple things that you know, maybe aren't the
best possible situation here, right?
There's a couple things that already even just at this early stage are
kind of jumping out where we, you know, we may not really be super
happy with it when it actually comes time to use it, right?
So one of those things is that there's really no.
What I usually hear the term hysteresis used to this, but ignoring the
fancy terminology there really isn't,
Think here, that helps us visualize this information in a way that's
easy to use given how fast it's changing.
So especially if we were running, it's a 60 frames, a second or
something like that.
Like in the full release mode, you know these things are going to be
flickering like crazy and it's going to be pretty hard for us to
understand what we're seeing, right?
So one thing that we might want to do is start adding some features
that allow us to more concisely view, what's happening over time with
these values in terms of just just knowing the general number like
mint.
Max average, just basic stuff like that, right?
You could imagine being kind of useful, so we can kind of see like
okay, you know, in the last sixty frames, what was the minimum value?
What was the maximum value?
What was the average something like you know, whatever I mean, who
knows something like this.
Okay.
So that would be one thing.
That would be pretty handy for us to know, just in terms of being able
to visualize these things, a little bit more clearly just, you know,
not trying to find any Trends or anything, but just just reading the
numbers.
Another thing that's closely related to that is, if there was a sudden
Spike here, right?
We wouldn't have any ability to really see that, right?
Like you can almost see occasionally we can see Little Numbers kind of
jump out on there and we can see it twitch a little bit and you know
maybe those are important spikes.
Something weird was happening.
Probably not with the level of complexity that our game has right now,
you know, because it's mostly test code and stuff like that on top of
the engine.
So it's not stressing
And just not stressing anything.
So the chances of having a really bad frame are probably pretty low,
but as we get further on in the game, the chances of having something
really weird and like performance-critical happen on a particular
frame, that causes us to miss our frame rate will go up and what we'd
like to be able to do is see when we get those Miss frames.
We'd like to be able to see who was responsible, right?
To give us a little bit of an idea, but we're not gonna be able to do
that all.
We're going to be able to know, is maybe we saw a little framerate
stutter, you know, maybe we're walking around on here and we see,
See a little stutter or something, but we'll have no idea.
We won't have any idea who caused it because the numbers have already
passed their long gone, right?
So, I think, what we'd rather do is we'd rather have some way of being
able to see some kind of a like, you know, graphical depiction of, you
know, the frames over time.
So we can see when we hit or miss our frame rate and stuff like that,
right?
So let's go ahead and start down that path.
A little bit, just seems like a pretty interesting thing to do and
this will be
something that, you know, we can do hopefully rendering
Mostly in the kinds of characters that Windows is capable of
rendering.
So we'll try to stay away from underscores being output to the screen
and other stuff like that.
Or if we find that we really need an underscore.
Maybe we can call the there, tech-support Hotline in the Philippines.
That wanted me to pay the $500.
We could just pay $500 to Microsoft to see if they could figure out
where the underscores went.
So, let's see.
Inside
I can be dot CPP.
We've got, we've got our sort of Little Beginnings of our debug print
out thing that's printing out what we saw there.
It's down here at the end where we do overlay cycle counters and what
happens with the overlay cycle count.
As you can see we print out the cycle counters at the same time,
right?
We print out the psycho counters at the same time as we look at them.
So this is actually our pass through the cycle, counters, to gather
the information to pull that information off of.
Of the debug system, right?
And then we are putting it out to the debug text buff.
You know, we're sort of grabbing the information resetting it and
putting it out to the render at the same time.
Okay.
And so what we'd like to do at this point if we want to look at things
kind of historically speaking, is we like to change that so that when
we go through and we pull the data out and we do the reset instead of
that happening, as part of the render, the render can just
Something separate that renders information that we've stored for the
debugging purposes this sort of like stored information and then we
can move where we're actually doing the pull into something whose sole
purpose is to do that debug check and maybe start keeping a longer
history of what happened.
So that then the renderer can become more complicated and draw, more
information, show more information.
Time, do sort of interesting things like that and again we alluded to
this on the previous dreams when people were asking about that.
I was like, yep.
Don't we're getting there were getting there and now we are, we are
there.
It's time now for us to think about that temporal aspect, okay?
So let's go ahead and and sort of start moving into that.
Now, I'm just going to go ahead and I sort of this is a little bit
predictive, right?
This is a little bit of me, kind of knowing some stuff that I like,
because I've worked on lots of projects before and so I just kind of
like jumping the gun.
I'm not waiting to discover it later on, so I'll just say that this
would be something we'd sort of would have had to sort of stumble into
potentially, and that is that I fully suspect that we will want this
debug info system.
To be able to visualize some things that are largely happening outside
of the platform independent code.
So for example, we may want the windows side of things or the Linux
side of the Mac OS X side or the Raspberry Pi side or whatever, we
choose to Port it to, we may not that side to be able to sort of put
information into the system.
That's about the current frame that we're on, right?
And so what I'd like to be able to do is is sort of elevate the notion
of
The debug frame latch that latch where we go through and grab all the
information.
I want to elevate that to something that the platform layer itself
actually calls so that we can guarantee that that call will be done at
a time when the platform layer knows, it's all.
It's actually done all of the frame and the frame itself has been like
fully retired that way.
When the platform layer wants to sort of announce debug things,
they'll all go into the frame correctly and it won't be like this
weird sing.
We're like, oh, it shows up as being on the next frame, even though it
was on this Frame, because the debug reset happens inside, game update
and render and then the the weight, you know, the blind to the screen
happens after that.
And so it shows up inside It Bubba.
But right, you know, there's this whole like sort of ordering that
happens there.
So what I'd rather do is kind of kind of come in here, get that, get
that sort of a little more straightened out.
Okay.
So what I want to do in here inside sort of our loop, our Global
running group but we know we even sort of did this.
We have these debug time.
Marker things, right?
That we were using when we're sort of playing around with sound a
little bit.
So what I like to do is in here when we, when we actually sort of go
to do this stuff at the very end, when we latch everything, where we
would be checking the frame count, right?
What I'd like to do there is maybe right there, that's where we do our
debug reset, okay?
And so this is going to be in here, right?
This is going to call the game.
I forget really exactly what the names of stuff was in here.
Here it is, right, we're going to call.
For that game structure.
Some new function pointer that we're going to introduce which calls
into the debug system and does that that reset right.
So, down here at the end.
After we do that, maybe we do the our dtsc to take the N Cycle count
the last cycle count stuff.
So it's done its little strobe.
And now we know some of the stuff that we were printing out here.
This FPS buffer, all that stuff.
Maybe we're even maybe we can even just do this, get rid of that sort
of dumped to the console.
Because remember, we have, this was just dumping our frames to Second.
Jimmy, it was dumping our frames a second out to the debug console,
which is because we didn't have any debug support.
Well, now, we're going to start to have some so maybe
Will do is say, you know, this is going to be our debug frame end or
something like that.
Maybe I'll make that caps because that's sort of been the way I've
been doing it.
So we called debug frame end and that will get past all the same stuff
that it would normally get past that game memory.
So it can sort of pull stuff out of that or whatever it wants to do.
We can have that work.
And then what we'll do is we'll pass that the stuff that we were
passing here, right?
So, you know, the frames per second and the milliseconds per
a frame and and all that sort of stuff, right?
So you know, it can compute those on its own.
So really all we would need to know I think Mmm.
What was this doing?
This was assuming on a gigahertz machine.
Something I guess I don't know what this was so I don't think we.
Yeah I don't know what I don't.
What is that trying to say?
I have no idea what that's trying say.
That's a good question and we don't know so milliseconds per frame.
Where is that actually getting computed?
Went through to get seconds elapsed.
Last counter
So, that's just some kind of that's actually Counting.
Up a little bit.
Right?
Before we do the flip went through to buffer and window.
That's not really where we would want it to be right.
I guess we're timing that because we don't want to time this Windows
thing.
No, that's really weird.
That's really weird.
So why did we do that?
Why did we do it there?
Because we I guess because we didn't want to wait.
We didn't.
That's how many
S, it took before, Windows did its thing.
So I really want both of these.
I guess is what I'm saying.
So I think here's what I'm going to do.
I want, I want I want more.
So, what I want to do here is instead of doing it this way, instead of
just having milliseconds per frame, I want multiple strobe points,
right?
I want to be able to sort of, in cure be able to write down like,
where some different stuff happened, right?
So where we have this large unit integer with the last counter, right?
I want to update that at the very end of the frame, probably I'm
thinking.
And then I want to take a few markers where we comp, where we compute
those milliseconds, so that I can pass them all in, right?
So what I'm going to do, here's how I'm going to do that.
I'm going to go to handmade platform, and of course, we're going to
make that debug call, but I'm also going to in addition to that debug
call, I'm going to go ahead and make a thing where we'll have sort of
a
A packet, if you will of information.
So, like debug frame and
Info, right?
And that will get passed a bunch of stuff.
So this will be like a different counters or something like this.
So they'll be you know one of these lines basically.
Right where we do milliseconds per frame, we could just make it s /
because there's no, this is just multiplying by by 1,000 there.
We can just fill out a struct, that has a bunch of these in it and I
think that's what I'd like to do.
So up at the top.
Will do debug frame and info and we'll do like, debug what would be
like frame and info and then frame and info will take a strobe at
various points.
So, what we'll do here is we'll say like, you know, this right here
will be executable ready.
Something like that and that'll be win32.
Get seconds elapsed.
To get seconds elapsed.
Yeah, like so.
So we will.
There we go.
So on frame and info, we'll go ahead and say when the executables
ready to go.
We'll put that in there.
So now we kind of know what's going to happen there.
Now, I want last counter and I guess just the current counter, so it's
like the get it's like, get wall clock itself, right?
Is the thing that I'm going to want to do.
So I want to know between the last time I took the counter and the get
wall clock, right?
I'm going to have
How many seconds it was till we got to that, right?
Something like this, and then we'll just kind of place these in here.
So we go through here, we get messages pending.
So we do a bunch of like input processing, right?
This is all input processing in here.
If not Global pause, then we actually go through and do this stuff.
So I'm not sure where I guess I would want to do it.
So that after we do all of this controller stuff, right?
Then we would do it like this, probably if not Google pause, so we
always take right here.
Like input process for something input process.
Like that and then we keep going.
So then we have inside here.
Oops, when we go through, and do all of the game updating stuff, I
guess, well we've got some audio stuff that happens here as well,
right?
We got the sound, the audio, the audio still a little janky in this
platform layer.
It's pretty janky, which is unfortunate, but we come through here, we
do the audio, and then we do the, and then we do the sleep and all
that stuff.
So where does the game actually get updated whereas game update and
render?
Okay.
Oh wait, game dot update and render.
So it's right there, right?
So probably I do one more.
I do it here.
Don't really know if we even using Global pause but not really
important.
So, this is act after Hoops after game update game updated and then in
here we have, like the audio getting updated.
All right, let's see.
Doot-doot-doot game.
Updated seconds.
Elapsed while Target yeah.
So, there we go.
Last counter work counter.
That's all good.
If not little paws.
It'll go ahead and do that.
So this is audio updated.
And then inside here, when it does the flip wall clock.
Yeah.
Now, it occurs to me that we could probably do this just with our
With our deep, we could just do this with the.
Well, I don't want to do that because we kind of had that in the other
compilations.
I don't really want to push that, so we could do that with other
things, but I'm not gonna do that.
So then we go through here, we do sort of our frame display, whatever
we need to do to actually do the frame display and do the sink and all
that stuff.
And then, so that at the very end, right is is just here.
yeah, so I don't know, I feel kind of like
I feel kind of like the global pause should not have paused this, but
I guess that's will.
I guess we'll cross that bridge when we come to it because I feel like
this stuff, you kind of want to have happen.
I guess, the reason we were doing that is because we didn't want the
debug time markers to advance or something like that, but that's
something we can probably just get rid of now.
And maybe start to look at making this a little bit, a little, bit
more intelligently done, right?
What's the yeah?
Okay, so then at the very end when we actually do this
I guess we've got this is the sleep, the weight, right?
And so that's going to be right here.
And then this stuff we can just do
Again, there we go.
I don't really this is debug code.
I don't, I don't want.
We're just going to get rid of this stuff because I want to start
cleaning this up anyway.
So we're going to get rid of that and we're going to get rid of
probably this stuff as well, because will take, I think we're may want
to take a little bit of a closer look, although well, I guess we can
leave just that last that cycle counting there and we'll pass that
down as well.
This stuff with the FPS and all that nonsense, all this stuff is going
to go away.
Right?
So that'll go away and then we'll just do if handmade internal here
and there we go.
Okay, so that's getting a little bit better.
Still not quite there yet, so there's audio updated down.
This is going to be sleep or frame timing app, you know, frame timing,
complete or frame weight complete
Something like that framerate.
Great complete.
And then at the very end we do like the total thing, right?
So at the very very end we just do like right before we call it or
whatever we do you know end of frame, something like that.
Yeah.
Okay, so getting closer, and then we call this thing, we'd pass it
this info.
So we pass it.
One of these guys so frame and info is going to be right there, and
let's take a look.
So flip wall clock.
What is flip wall?
Clock doing nowadays?
Look wall clock out, it's syncing up at that.
Okay, that's fine.
And then encounter encounter is just doing.
Yeah, this is just for the loop so we can actually use on frame.
Wait complete, this end counter thing right here can actually move
down to the end of frame so that can actually just be our actual end
of frame counter.
We don't need this anymore and the last counter update.
Their this can just be instead of getting the wall clock, will just
use the M counter and that's the end of the frame, right?
So I think now we've sort of got the beginnings of what I wanted there
and that's all good.
So let's go through and now actually make the structure that
corresponds to storing all that information that I just said that I
wanted again.
Just taking those strobe points along the way.
So we've got end of frame.
Is there we've got framerate.
Wait, complete.
Is there we've got audio updated is there?
We've got game, oops.
Game updated is there?
We've got input processed.
We've got executable ready.
And that's it, I think.
Yeah, that's all good.
All right, so assuming we pass all that in we now just need a function
that will do that.
Debug, you know, that will actually finish off that debug stuff.
So we need to actually Define this guy here because obviously, you
know, we wouldn't actually be able to have that happen.
We can't call a function function that we have never defined.
So inside here, we do something like saying.
Okay, let's go ahead and Define this thing.
I guess we'll find it right here.
So we've got debug
Frame and is our new function.
We don't need it to really return anything.
It's going to take some game memory, right?
It's going to take the game memory and then just a debug frame and
info.
That it can use to know some extra information from the platform layer
about what was going on and we'll probably put more stuff in there as
we go, right.
Okay.
So debug platform right.
Entire file is not the name of this thing, that's actually called
debug frame.
And and actually debug platform, frame end is probably the right name
for it and something
That there we go.
Oops.
Okay.
And so if I go ahead and compile that then I am just left with
whatever my random errors are, let's see what they are.
Okay, so our game now has to have that actually passed in.
So we just have to go take inside the platform API, where we have all
this other stuff.
We now just have one more debug function that the game can can provide
to us.
And again this is just a
The game provides us things that the platform layer calls into.
So we have debug platform frame end,
Bug brain and so that will just get passed in now.
And so, we just have to be able to kind of fill that out somewhere.
Where 0.32 game code.
What did I do?
Auto.
That's the, that's the wrong way round.
I don't know what I'm thinking.
I don't know where my head is today.
That's not what we wanted.
We want that to actually be in the game itself because
Something that the game actually defines, right?
That's actually one of these.
You know, I'm saying, so we want this to be.
We want this to be not something, not an actual pointer.
We want this to be something.
That's actually defined out in the game side of things.
Right.
So we want that like here, that makes sense.
So, this should actually be called.
Well, now, I'll still call it that, but it ain't a platform thing is,
my point, it's actually game side, it does the platform doesn't
provide to the game.
The game provides for the platform.
So yeah, I think that's all we really need their.
Yeah.
So then in win32, you know, where we're actually calling game update
and render, for example,
We can just grab.
That guy.
So, in here, we just go, okay, you know, the, the Deep, oops, that's
good.
The debug frame end, we would call game frame, and oops, debug.
And we would just get that from the game.
And in this case, we wouldn't probably effect is valid for that
because if the game didn't provide us a debug thing to call back,
that's okay, right.
You know, we'd crashed if we tried to call it but we just don't have
to call it.
You know, instead what we could do is just say in here.
If there isn't one of these then don't then don't call it right, only
call it, if it exists and then we don't care.
If the game never provided one, it doesn't matter to anybody, right?
That seems like a better idea.
So let's go ahead and add that into win32 game code there.
So now we've got debug frame end, debug frame end and that should be
sufficient.
Let's see, oops, got an extra got a spurious, little Spirits little
close there.
Okay, so this should do like absolutely nothing, right?
And it does because the game doesn't actually Define that yet so it's
just plain not there.
So if we want to add that in all we would have to do is I think.
Do we do?
We do our
On the command line.
I remember, it's been such a long time, we do.
So, what we can do here is we can just say, okay, we've got one more
export that, we'd like to export, it's called debug frame end
Like so, and so now, you'll notice you now I'm just expecting that to
be exported from, you know, from the platform back and maybe I'll just
add a game in there just to be a little bit more consistent with the
way.
This thing works, right?
Okay, so now, if I do this, I should get an error.
Yeah.
Which is that I didn't make one of those, right?
So, now, if I go into handmade dot CPP, I should be able to make one
of those like, the debug reset function, for example, which is
currently getting called, you can see it getting cold down here.
What I could do is I could actually make that debug reset call, be
something that ends up getting called separately.
Well, I guess technically debug reset, resets the debugging print out
stuff.
So, maybe we'll start by just keeping it separate because maybe it's
sort of is.
So anyway, when we need to do this sort of exporting stuff, you can
kind of see the way that we were doing it before here is our template
for that, right?
So if I want to, I can just come down here and say, all right, here is
my extra and see, debug should probably actually again, keep it a
little
It consistent.
Debug game frame end like so.
Do it that way.
Game frame and game frame.
And and then now I know that that will get called and I got to go just
change these guys here.
This is
yeah.
And there we go.
That's about it.
So now we're getting called with that information, right?
And now we need to actually start doing something with that
information.
That would be useful.
Now, fortunately, I can just straight-up do this right?
I can just grab the stuff and do all of this in here except the print
out, right?
Because nothing in here is actually going to be a problem.
It's all stuff that that would just work, I believe.
Except for, of course, the fact that I need to actually call this way,
right?
So I need like something like, you know, update debug records or
something like that.
And then make this guy,
Like so.
Update debug records and that should just work because there's nothing
that I've but actually relies on the rest of the game stuff here.
So as far as I know, I should be able to do something like that,
without a whole lot of problem.
So this will allow me to capture that information at the end of the
frame, which is what I wanted.
So really all I need to do now is Port, the printout code to print out
of something that is not, right is not
That instant, you know, the actual debug counters themselves.
So, how do I want to do that?
I don't really know how I want to do that but I suspect we could
figure it out pretty easily.
And so what I'm going to do again when you're not sure what to do, you
start from the side of the code that you know, right.
I know that I want to print this stuff out in a more robust way than I
was with more information stuff like that, that could sort of track
stuff over time and all those other sorts of things.
So what I'd like to do is have something where instead of this output,
debug records which does, with the counter count, the counters and
that sort of
Of stuff.
What I'd like to do is change this overlay cycle counter stuff, you
know?
And maybe even move this stuff down.
Here to just to the update call.
Like so, right.
Like that.
I like this call now to be something that just does the rendering in a
sane way, right?
And I can move this stuff up here.
So now I don't even have to pre declare that stuff, which is what I
was having to do before because now it can actually be just in line
with the rest of the rendering stuff and and all that, all that juicy
goodness.
So I can get rid of this as well.
So now, what I want to do is I want this stuff and again we still
haven't replace that standard IO sprintf from the old platform layer
stuff, which, at some point, we would like to do
It just seems like not the most instructive time for me to stop and
explain how to print out a number.
But we'll do that.
After we sort of finish this this other stuff,
So yeah.
So in here, I'm going to go ahead and get rid of this stuff.
There we go.
And now we're in a situation where we can start to tune these routines
to be doing, whatever it is that we think we might want them to do.
So, what is the first thing that I need to be able to do is be able to
get some debug memory out of the system, right?
I need to be able to get, you know, whatever.
We're going to store our debug memory in.
And obviously, we don't want that to be.
We really don't.
That memory to be stuff.
That's that's used by anything else we want, we want to sort of
unknown chunk for that and so I feel like, I don't know, I mean maybe
this isn't true, but I feel like we almost want there to be a third
tier in our platform system, right?
Which is debug memory memory.
That we put debug stuff into because in here we've kind of got this,
this situation.
Where we passed permanent storage and transient storage?
I feel like we want one more which is like debug storage.
You know, and I think we wanted then test the game when we actually
go, you know, when we're sort of clean things up for shipping and so
on, we want to be able to set that size 20.
So the debug stuff, you know, if the debug stuff isn't running, it
doesn't use it and so that you know, the release version, the game
just doesn't pass anything into the debug storage, right?
That seems to me to be probably, that's what I would like to see
happen, right?
And that way I can do something like all right, so now we've just got
another thing which is
The debug state.
And I can keep it totally separate.
In fact, I don't even have to put it in there, I'll put it over here.
So now we can sort of have it isolated off in a separate file.
It's going to be like debug State and the debug State.
I don't even know what that's going to have in it right now.
Debug you know counter State who even knows who knows it's anyone's
guess really?
But in the debug counter state will have like debug counter.
Snapshot, I'm making this stuff up, completely making this stuff up
but I'm just
I give you the the idea of what we might want.
So, in here, you know, we'd have something like, okay, we've got state
for a bunch of
Counters or whatever, you know, something like this.
And who knows how many there are.
You know, we say that we've got, you know, up to that many counters
doesn't even matter will kind of.
Look at that.
We can always just change it, it's only for debug code.
So, no one cares at all, how much that is?
And then inside the debug counter State, we just have some snapshots,
right?
And so here's the snapshots and, and who knows how many snapshots
there are?
Maybe we store, you know, the past, you know, 120 frames or something
like that, I don't know.
Why not?
And inside the snapshot, we just have, like, okay, this stuff that
would have been here.
You know, we store this information.
So you know, inside the debug counter snapshot
We would store the part that's actually relevant for the particular
frame.
You know, and then the stuff that's not actually relevant to a frame,
we would put in the debug counter State itself, right?
So this, this information would be stored, there something like
something like that.
And this would probably have pre separated these guys out because why
not, right?
So, you know, this is what I'm envisioning.
So to something that's going to store that stuff for us and
A printout of that.
Again, I really just don't have any particular idea of what I want
here.
I was just kind of slamming something in there so you can kind of tell
what I'm talking about.
What I'm going to do is I'm going to go write the actual print out
code here, and then whatever the printout code, kind of thinks maybe
that it would want their will go in and make that be what happens,
right?
Okay.
Okay, so in output, debug records.
Really, we don't need the separate function anymore because all of our
records will presumably just be aggregated together.
I would assume that's my assumption anyway.
I don't know if it's an accurate assumption but it's an assumption
nonetheless.
So, here we go.
And now, what I need to do is this is going to sort of somehow get
debug State out of it, right?
So it's going to have debug State, debug State like that.
And it's just going to take the memory
Going to cold-cast that just like we always do.
When we first enter the platform layer, we're going to go ahead and
get that out of the debug storage, right?
And maybe what I'll do here is assumed that if this thing was called,
we're only going to activate if, if this debug storage is nonzero,
right?
So that way, if anyone sets that 20 we just won't we just won't try to
do anything at all so that you can just turn it off as like a kill
switch.
All right.
So in here we would then just Loop we Loop over counter.
I guess this would be exactly the same.
It just now we would look at the debug State and we'd say how many are
of these are there and I guess
Here we might do like counter account.
Just so we know how many there are, like, whatever the maximum one is
that we've seen we put in there or something like that.
So we just go.
Okay, we'll go over counter count.
We take a look at all of the counters that we have so counter States.
And we're going to have this debug counter State and for now we can
actually just print it out like we were putting it out.
And all we would really need is for the cycle, count, hit count.
We just need to be able to get that out of out of this, one of the
snapshots, right?
And for now, we'll just try.
We'll just use Snapshot zero because we haven't quite gotten far
enough to start thinking about that yet.
So, for now we'll just say, OK, we'll do snapshot
0.
Hit count like so.
Snapshot zero cycle count.
There we go.
So that
should be sufficient.
And then the rest of this stuff should in theory, just work, right?
Because we have the file name, we have the function name, all of that
stuff should just work.
So if I go ahead and compile it, we should be good to go right, there
we go.
So snapshots is not your right, so lowercase s
There we go.
See.
Okay, so that's all good but of course we don't actually initialize
this yet.
So I'm imagining, I don't even remember if we if we set, if we
initially the game, start, we probably do.
Yes.
So basically, what's going to happen is that codes.
Just going to see that there's a zero there, it's not going to run so
it's not going to matter when it calls overlay cycle counters, right?
Okay, so the next thing we got to do is actually make this guy.
When we do our, when we do our updates here, we got to make this guy,
actually do something intelligent as well, right?
We have to make him actually capture the counters and put them into
the debug State.
That's, you know, that's that's just what we got to do.
So we come in here and do the exact same thing.
We did in the other function.
So there we go.
We take a look at that.
Debug storage and off we go.
Ernie.
So I think we started 10 minutes late today, so my guess so we
actually have 15 minutes left which is probably enough to actually get
this all working anyway.
So we do our debugging frame and becoming a receipt.
If we've got the book storage, assuming that we have a debug storage,
we then want to go ahead and update all the debug records, which means
we want to copy them out from where they are, you know, grab out the
current values and stuff them in to these actual records, right?
So, I think the right way to do that.
Would be to say, okay?
Go through all the counters that are here and yeah, like at the start
at this point in debug State, let's go ahead and set the counter count
to zero.
And then as we update, the records will increment it.
So that we know how many total counters we saw, right?
So yeah, you know what I'm saying?
You know, I'm saying to.
So basically, we've got inside the debug thing.
here inside handmade debug
We would have debug counter State.
This is like the destination, this is like the source, right?
We're reading from this, debug counter, we are putting it into this,
debug counter counter States like so
And so that will basically copy these in.
So we go ahead and do the atomic exchange to reset the value.
Now we've got these two out so now we can say just snapshots again at
the moment will just write in 20 and then in the future we're going to
want to write into you know, not zero.
Grab that out.
And while we're at it, we can also grab all the other relevant
information that we actually want.
Like, the file name, the function name in the line, number function,
name function name, line number line number, right?
So that should grab all of the information that we need, I would
think.
And, of course, right.
We've got a pass that debug state in here so that these guys know
where they're supposed to be writing, debug state32.
State and I think, let's see that Source.
I think that should do it.
So again, if I run this, we won't see anything yet because we don't
actually give it any memory to work with, but, you know, that's fine.
It won't be very difficult to give it some memory to work with.
And so now inside handmade
Win32 here when we're doing our allocations.
Let's see.
When we set the game, memory game memory.
So, what we should be able to do, here is set the sizes, so that we
actually get some other stuff.
Let's see, where we actually allocate that from.
I don't see it.
There it is.
Total size and here you can see it doing it's, it's thing, right?
So very simple, nothing to it.
Just make one more of these that actually sits at the end of
everything.
And then all we should have to do is add one more size in here like
this.
Right.
And all that we would do then is say that the debug storage size is
some amount of memory.
And I don't know how much debug memory we want and we don't really
care, maybe it's infinite.
So that's all we should really need.
And I'm not sure what you are complaining about.
Debug state.
That is not what I wanted.
I wanted to debug storage.
Let's try that again.
So, let's see if that does anything for us.
It does.
So there's those values, right?
So now we're going through that whole system.
Let's go ahead and start to sort of push through that a little bit.
This is not going to be a particularly efficient way to do this, so I
don't know.
You know, depending on the number of snapshots this this might be a
little bit ugly, but let's just say, you know, let's just say that we
wanted to start recording those snapshots now.
What I could do is inside that debug State structure, right?
I've got a bunch of snapshots of these timers.
What I could do is say, all right, let's just figure that there's
going to be a snapshot index.
For something like this, right?
And the snapshot index will just Inc.
Every time we update the debug records, it will go ahead and ink it
right.
So at the end of this, it'll do a debug State snapshot index.
It will increment that and then it'll see if the debug state
snapshotting to X is greater than or equal to the number of snapshots,
right?
And we could even do Define Max, debug, snapshot count 12.
To your something like that or just be debug Snapchat account.
If we go over that value then we will just set it back to zero.
So that allows us to now have a rolling buffer.
So, in here, it can just say, oh, debug State, snapshot index.
Now we're going to capture a whole bunch of these and so if I just run
this as is now we'll just get a strobe because we're only printing out
the zeroeth one.
So now it'll just show us the value and every 120 frames it will show
us a new value.
So roughly every 4 seconds, it will update to analyze.
What you just saw that it did, right?
So now what we'd like to do is figure out some ways of looking at
those values.
I don't know.
Let's, let's, you know, we don't have very much time left.
So let's just think a little bit about what we might want to see.
They're just randomly thinking it through.
So again, not gonna think about the performance of drawing this at
all.
I'm just going to go ahead and do some weird stuff.
First thing is first for this counter index.
Let's just go ahead and compute min-max, average kind of a situation.
So, here we go, min max.
and do we have a, do we have a float Min in a float Max yet, people
Do we have one float?
Min we do.
So, there we go.
Real pretty to maximum.
So I will set those values to inverse and then I will set the average
20.
I will then go through all of the snapshot snapshot index.
Equals zero, snapshot index is less than debug snapshot count and I
will run through all of the values in the counter.
And I will see what we get.
And I suppose the min max average here, you know what, I'm just going
to go, you know,
Let's go.
Football will call this a statistic.
Something.
So, Min backs, average, we will say debug statistic hit count the big
statistic cycle count right equals in it statistic for empty
statistic.
Deep bugs.
Yeah.
So we'll just take one of those guys will create an empty one of them.
Like, so empty, debug statistic like that.
And inside there.
We'll just go ahead and do this initialization code that I have right
here.
So there's debug statistic result, we will say result, Min results,
Max
Result average.
And will return that.
So now we can make one for the hit count and one for the cycle count
and as we go through each of these, we can just do something like
accumulate statistic and we will pass the hip count statistic like
that and the hit count to my statistic cycle count and that like that.
You know, and so we'll take the snapshot index that we want to grab.
And now we should be able to compute those out.
And we'll do like finalized statistic here.
Oh, I guess we could, you know, what begin debug statistic and debug
statistic.
Might be the better way to go, right.
That seems.
Yeah, you know what?
That's that's it.
That's the sauce right there, right?
You
It, you know, it don't try to tell me you don't because you do.
All right, so hit count.
And then we've got cycle count.
And so, what we'll do here is, we'll call this getting debug statistic
that will take the debug statistic in that will just take the stat.
So that will initialize it to, you know, an empty sort of the empty
State and then we will have an Envy bug statistic, which will double
check.
It'll say like if State Min equals real titty to maximum it knows, it
never accumulated anything.
What it will do is it will then set the Min and Max 20 just to avoid
putting out some giant bogus number, right?
And then I guess, you know what, the other thing we need is here is we
need to count in here so because we're going to need the average.
So we want to divide by how many we had something like that.
In fact, I guess we know that, we know that if we saw any values, the
Min and the max will get set.
So I guess all we have to do is just say if the count equals 0, right?
Then we know we're in a sort of or I guess we'll say not equal to 0.
Then we know that we're in a situation where the Min and Max are valid
and the average can be divided by the count to get the actual number,
if we didn't see anything.
If there's no for some reason, we didn't see any statistics, when
we're doing this, then we'll set the Min and Max 20, and the average,
and the count can stay at zero because they won't have changed, right?
So then, let's go ahead and do update debug statistic.
And that's going to take just some value.
Right.
And, you know, we could also say, let's do this in float in double.
Because, again, this is debug code.
We really don't care too much about it speed because we're going to
not include that really in our side, unless it becomes owners.
So we'll do that in double so that they can handle really large values
to.
If we're trying to count some crazy high cycle counts or who knows
what?
We'll just give ourselves a little head room there to make sure that
there's no problem.
So State count plus equals 1, I guess the count itself.
Probably doesn't have to be that.
So we could, we could say that the count itself was was going to be
something a
It more sane.
So will, you know, will back off at tiny a little smidge?
Just a Touch, just a little poke.
So, yeah.
So assuming that the state count is valid then we will divide by that
value.
If the count is not valued, we will just clear everything and call it
a day, right?
When we go to update it, we increment the count.
We will set the Min and the max.
So base will say, like if the Min is greater than the value, we want
to update it to be the value, you know, similarly if the max is less
than the value, we want it to be the value.
And finally we just want to Summit into the average, right?
So that we get, we get that value.
So that allows us to kind of do, sadistic sorbets rarely we could have
baked some things in there because we know like the number of
snapshots, there are and other stuff like that.
So we don't really have to quite do it that much, but this would just,
it's just a little general-purpose thing.
We can use anytime we want to do something like this.
So now, we've got our statistics
Oops, it means that I didn't mean stat people.
I mean I didn't mean State.
I meant that.
Don't ask me, don't ask me how the E got on there.
It just did.
All right, so this goes away and now accumulate debug debug
Identifier not found.
Oh.
There we go.
Conditional expression.
All right, so now we can go ahead and print this out.
And so what I can say is okay, if the hit count value is greater than
zero,
Then we'll print it out.
When we go to print it out, we'll just, we'll just do the average for
now or something like that.
Right?
I don't know.
That's not really well.
That's, and that's a pretty good.
Well, that's a pretty good thing to.
We'll talk about that in just one second.
I just want to get this working first hit count.
Oh, hit count.
What do I want to do there?
I want to say, if the hit count Max.
So if any, if anyone ever hit it in, any run, in the past, we want to
see it.
Okay, well, that doesn't look good people.
I don't think that's working properly.
Just gonna go ahead and say it, don't think that's working properly.
Oh, well, of course, these are floating Point values that would be the
that would be the first one.
So yeah.
If we want these we'd have to then cast them down to you 32s in order
to print them out.
Which is fine.
There we go.
Okay, so in theory, these are our average values.
In theory and so they're still going to fluctuate and stuff like that.
But now we have a values, not particularly useful what we're doing
here, but we're getting closer.
So the first thing I want to say was, well, we don't really want to
divide the average by the average.
That's not what we want here, right?
We wanted how many cycles for hit.
So if we're going to print out averages, we want the average number of
cycles per hit.
Not the average number of Cycles divided by the average,
Numbers of hits as a surly, right?
Because I don't necessarily think those are the same thing.
Does that make sense?
I'd have to think it through.
So if I was to sum up all of the Cycles we're almost out of time but I
want to know the answer to this question.
So I'm just going to say that I get to know it and that's just the way
it's going to go.
So day 179, okay?
So what I want to know here is I want to know
Cycle count and hit count average.
So if I have something where I'm like, you know, cycle count over kit
count, and I want to know these things summed up, right?
I want to know what the average would be of say, three of these guys,
right?
Then the question is, does that equate, right?
Like, meaning, is that equal to the average,
Of those guys / each other, right?
So if I divide by 3,
On each side.
Right?
Do I get do I get the correct answer, right?
So looking, you know, looking through this if I was to divide these
guys by 3 then really all that's going to happen is each of these
quantities is going to be divided by three, right?
So this this side of the equation is just going to divide.
I can divide each of these by 3 and not change the equation at.
All right, so that would just be C 0 / 3 H 0 plus c 1 / 3, H 1 plus c
2.
/ 3 h 2
Right.
There's nothing.
There's nothing mysterious about that on this side over here.
What I've actually got is.
Yeah, I mean,
If you're dividing by 3 on, both of these.
Right?
Then essentially you're not really changing the equation at, all
right?
Meaning.
Meaning if I divide both of these by three, then that's just going to
be equivalent to.
I can I can just that comes directly out, right?
That's just going to be equivalent to this.
Right?
So I don't know this.
Does not look like that to me.
I could be wrong certainly, but I guess there's only one way to really
defined out and that would be two.
Actually combine this.
So in order to combine this, yeah, I'd have to go ahead and actually
do sort of the composite where I actually add them up with each other.
So, the lowest common denominator would be H 0, H, 1 h 2.
Right.
And I don't, I don't see any way that's going to be the same.
That seems totally ludicrous.
Maybe we'll ask pseudonyms 73, but that doesn't look at all proper to
me.
So anyway,
Way.
I should spend a little more time on that.
My math skills are so Rusty.
I just don't do that much math anymore.
But anyway, so what I wanted to point out was the nice part about
this.
Debug statistic thing is, if we want another thing that's an average
we just add it right?
We do like, hit over cycle.
Something like that and we just say begin debug statistic hit over
cycle and we just literally, you know, do whatever the thing is that
we were doing down here we just accumulate that in right so we say
like you know, accumulate or or H OC or whatever.
Right.
Equal 0 0 will say h OC here.
And then we'll just do like an if like so.
Yeah, actually, I guess I want cycle count.
Over hit count.
And I want both of those to be our 64's.
So assuming that the cycle count, I'm sorry.
The hit count is not 0, then I can compute the average.
Like so right?
Then I can accumulate that into hit over cycle now.
I'm actually taking the average guaranteed we properly I don't have to
try and figure out if there's a way to make the math work out, I can
just actually do that directly right.
And it's pretty free for us to do that so we can just add arbitrarily
more statistics in there and it really doesn't become any more owners
to do so.
Okay so we're still a little bit ways away from having a full-fledged
like historical piece of debug information to look at
We now store it all but we don't really get much out of it.
So next dream, we can concentrate.
Now that we've got it all set up, we can just concentrate on actually
using it to print out useful stuff.
Right?
And that's what we'll do next time.
So with that, I will go to the Q&A.
And take some questions.
Yeah.
If you have questions about what we did in today's stream plz, press
them with q: and I
Answer them.
Right now.
Questions.
Questions for me.
Elvin asks, is a c compiler faster in compiling C code than a C++
compiler compiling?
See like C++ code.
Too many variables in that depends on the C++ compiler.
And, you know,
Whether it's optimized for C code and whatever.
Usually C compilers are much faster because they're much simpler.
They don't have to worry about as much stuff, but that doesn't mean
you couldn't make a C++ compiler, probably go at a reasonable speed
when compiling see you like code.
I will say that if someone went and dug up turbo C and like, ran it on
a modern machine, it probably would compile faster than you could even
see.
Like, you're probably like, and it would be done because it used to
compile Superfast back on like 25, MHz machines and so on a machine
like today, I don't even know what it would do.
It would probably just like tear through it.
Like it was nothing.
Shouldn't it be cycle over hit?
Yeah, that's probably true.
It should be
Uber cycle cycle over it.
Elvin, is there a standard portable way in C to get a file star to a
block region in memory in Linux?
There's FM open, but I can't seem to find equipment and windows
internet seems to suggest map view of file.
But I dont think that is it.
I don't want a memory mapped file, just file star to a map region to
such a thing exists.
Or am I looking at this the wrong way?
So I guess I don't know if.
I mean, there's no reason you couldn't have that because the C runtime
Library could easily support it but file star is not an operating
system thing.
It's a c runtime Library thing.
So it really doesn't have anything to do with Windows Linux or
Windows.
Except for the fact that the runtime libraries on those two or tend to
be different, it has nothing to do with the operating system, right?
So, I don't think I've ever tried to open a file stored memory, but I
would be kind of surprised.
Actually, if you couldn't do that,
Um, because it should be relatively simple, right?
I mean all it is is instead of backing it by a file.
So that when it flows, you know, it just a file Stars already buffered
I/O.
So all it is is just allocating a buffer for the file IO.
That just happens to
We be the whole fight, the whole thing and then it never actually
fails over to a file ever.
So it shit, you know, I don't know if it does or not, I don't know if
they have support that or not, but it's should be easy for them to if
they wanted to.
Captain.
Craft asks, are there inherent problems with using composition for
writing game engines?
Like there are problems with poop.
I guess.
Could you be more specific about using composition?
Like, what specifically do you mean by that?
Elvin.
Why is the professor able to convert a parameter to a string via the
pound symbol?
But not the other way around.
IE strings stripping, taking the inner value of the string and passing
it.
My guess is that it's because this would not make it possible for the
macro to be determined at compile time since we can pass.
It arbitrary strings.
So the answer is for the fur Dynamic strings, like strings, that
aren't known at compile time yet, that's the reason because that
wouldn't be a preprocessor operation.
But the answer as to why
Can't do that for Strings that were known at compile time.
Is it just because the C++ standards committee, probably, because
strew strip was so anti preprocessor.
He was really against the preprocessor.
He always was today, just never implemented a good preprocessor.
It could easily do that, right?
We could have so many things in the preprocessor that would be great
like parsing a string into a number, right?
Or turning a number into a string by printing it out.
With
Formatting options.
And like there's be so many things.
You could input there like, John, Blow already made his language, be
able to run any code that's known at compile time at compile time as
part of the preprocessor, right?
And he's working on his spare time.
So you know there's no reason we couldn't have a way better posture.
It's just strip didn't like it probably because he doesn't know how to
program.
Culver fly, unless I missed.
It shouldn't it be cycle ever?
Hit, rather are saying yes, sorry, I flipped it.
Students send me three averages of averages.
Need to be weighted by the population size.
This is a common mistake that you even see in scientific papers, that
try to combine the results of other scientific papers.
Yeah.
That's what it looked like to me, right?
Because it looks like there's this, like, there it is, right?
There's an extra divide there and so I felt like that you couldn't
just do it and I guess I'm right.
So that's good.
We could have, we could have, computed it more, simply, right?
We could have computed it here by just adding that term in.
Like, we could just multiply, by the 1 over the total count again, but
I thought it would be fun to show that we can just use another
statistic because then we could compute anything we want here.
So that's why did that way.
Drive dude.
Turbo.
C successor is C++ Builder from Embarcadero.
Yeah, but C++ Builder is not nearly as good as TP.
Turbo C was even in the old days when they first went from Turbo CC,
muscle builder, see what's the Builder was not as good.
It just wasn't.
So, I don't know that I trust its current internation at all, because
it's probably only gotten worse since then as well.
Elvin met a person.
Question, let's say, I want to have a generic Dynamic list.
We sighs already.
My game Library void, pointers and macros are two ways of approaching
this.
Another is Journey that code for The Unique list types.
I want, is this what you mean when you say I write C programs and spit
out C programs.
Yes.
That is what I mean if so can we do this generation at compile time
like we can do it in j.i.
or we forced to write and run next to do the desires for us.
The ladder J.
AI has some good metaprogramming support already even though it's
early and
It can do a lot more to see can or C++ can so you can't do those
things and c and C++ you have to do to compilation phases.
So, what I do is I like I do a build run, build is the way I do it
with my works or space so that it like, it doesn't build up some code
that spits out some code, then it builds the result of that code plus
any code that doesn't that isn't generated and then that's the actual
executable.
Captain craft with respect to composition.
I have a player struck that has various other structure represent what
the player is.
Composed of one could be the objects direct which is added to any
entity in the game that I want to be like an object.
Then I create functions that run on objects, such as object move.
So that anything that I want to move into the game would have, would
simply have a knob District within it yet compositions not
particularly useful.
Unless the things don't have to interact with each other and usually
the interesting Parts come from when they interact with each other.
So what I would say is wait till we get to that part and how many
here?
Because I'm going to show you some pretty crazy far out, like past the
ball and kind of stuff that I want to try for that.
Because this is my first time actually working on a game.
That was about crazy combinations of things.
So I have some stuff that I want to try and so you'll get to watch me
try it.
And I think the stuff will be a lot better than composition.
But who knows Captain Craftsmen running game engines.
How much should a programmer know about the about how the compiler
works and what is a good way to learn?
What is going on under the hood?
It depends a lot on the game.
If the game has performance at the Mackay implications than knowing
how the compiler work can be pretty important.
Also for portability, it's important to know a few things about how
the compiler works, but much less.
So obviously that's a little bit easier.
The easiest way to know how it works.
Under the hood is really, very simple.
You've got a debugger, right?
You step into it and you right click,
Can you say go to disassembly?
If that tells you what the compiler did and so what you need to do is
just get familiar, get comfortable with looking at your code in the
disassembly so that when you're doing stuff you can kind of get a feel
for in the province critical portions taking a look what's it doing
when I want to know what it's going to do?
I just look right?
Look at the debug build the release build, see what the difference is
between them.
That's the way to get to build up that knowledge, right?
And to understand what the what the compiler is doing well and what is
doing poorly and so on, right?
Right.
Similarly running stuff like ayaka which we've done in the Stream
where you can look, you know, run a perf dump.
Essentially on a piece of code play around with how its structured and
see what the compiler does differently and how the perf might change
stuff like that.
It's useful as well.
Big cat CK.
Hey I'm looking to pick a programming.
I have some basic knowledge but really would like to know where to get
started and he suggested languages, you might think are a good place
to start.
I'm sorry, it's a little, it's a little early for that.
I don't have good, I haven't put up really any materials for for
really like simple starting projects like getting into program for the
first time.
So I kind of assume that people know programming already and just want
to learn game programming and so I can't really help too much with
that eventually.
That's something I plan to maybe make some more resources about like
further down the road and so I don't know, maybe some people on the
stream know of some places to go for that, but I
I don't really know.
How much more engine work are we going to do before diving into
gameplay stuff?
It looks like we get back to gameplay stuff.
Let's see.
Oh, so we did that.
So, it looks like we've got this.
I mean, this is the stuff we've got right?
So the architecture expiration stuff, this gets back in and we're
pretty much on game.
Play for the rest of the time.
I think, right?
Well, this is metagame saved.
Game is probably, not really gameplay but you know everything else is
probably pretty gameplay.
Like you know, doing the Z Collision detection pass and like the AI
and stuff is you know there's engine work.
There, but it's so tightly coupled with the game that it's not really
something we can break out.
So that's going to kind of be all woven together as we go.
So I don't know.
I was saying, somewhere around a 200, I think that maybe we might, we
probably won't quite hit that because that's 21 more days and I feel
like we're going to want, you know, debug code.
We're going to want a good more, you know, ten days on at least.
And then, you know, I like I said, if we probably want to do so a
little more work on the renderer a little just tightening some things.
Up before we get back into the game stuff for good.
So I would say you know, day 200, wasn't I guess such a bad ballpark I
think.
Might be relatively close, but, you know, figured 8 to 10 to 20,
something like that figure.
We're be a little over that when we get back to it.
Can you run around to the game?
A little bit?
The last time I watch was a month ago, two ago, and I'd love to see
how its progressed.
We haven't done any work on the game, we've only been doing engine
work so it should be roughly the same, you know, the the, the engine
stuff is pretty.
We've got a lot of pretty good stuff now and we're running off of our
own asset files, and everything is streaming in properly.
We've got all the audio streaming as well.
We have it turned off right now because it's getting annoying.
We have like
Real-time 1080p running in software so the engine is pretty sweet but
we have still a little bit more work to do like we got some sorting
and stuff to do, but we're pretty close.
Like I said, there's not that much more left to do.
The debug code stuff is is only just starting.
Like I said, we've a little bit more to do there and we've got to kind
of go back and do some final stuff with the renderer particle systems
in the lighting and stuff like that, that we wanted to kind of put
back in there, but otherwise I think we're pretty good to go.
Go and running quite well even with no GPU right so this is all
running through our code.
No we're not touching the graphics card in any way.
We're doing all the rendering by hand and its really darn fast
multi-threaded.
In fact
I'll ask him questions, your thoughts on using a scripting language
with the game engine.
I don't really like scripting language is very much so I don't have
any thoughts on that.
I tend to just like it to make it to that the see reloads
instantaneously and in the end in game so that you don't have to use a
scripting language and you have access to everything.
so,
Blot 238 for the performance counters.
Could you perhaps color code them?
According to how far outside of the ideal effective range?
They are.
Similarly, is there a way to roughly estimate the ideal cycle count
for a function?
No unfortunately it's pretty darn hard to estimate the ideal cycle
count of a function because so much of it depends on memory accesses
and those are very variable in terms of how long they take.
So you could do, you could do an ideal, like, if all of the memory
axes were all in the cash, that's not too hard to do, potentially, and
ayako would do that for us.
But
You know, that's not that meaningful of a number, unfortunately.
You have to first form some opinion of whether you think it should all
be in the cache.
Child's E.
I have an interview tomorrow that I'm going and I'm going to have to
whiteboard how not to be nervous.
To be honest.
to be honest, I guess I don't really
have much advice for that.
If it's the kind of interview where someone asks you a stupid problem,
like they say something like reverse a linked list and want you to do
it on a whiteboard.
The easiest way not to be nervous is to know that anyone who asks that
question is a bad interviewer.
It's a terrible way to interview people and it doesn't do a good job
separating.
Good programmers from Bad programmers.
The reason for that is because nobody programs on a whiteboard and
nobody programs with someone watching them except me on the Stream.
and so especially in a situation where you're trying to get a job,
it puts someone in a very bad position and likely makes them do very
different things than they would do.
If they actually needed to solve that problem in real life in the job,
you're actually trying to figure out whether they're, you know, going
to be good at it or what, right?
So yeah, I've done a lot of tech interviewing in the past.
And I've been on to, you know, when I was first starting around to do
Tech interviews and I can tell you definitively, if anyone asks you to
solve a programming problem on a whiteboard while they watch, they are
just a bad interviewer.
So the first thing you can do to not be nervous is go.
Oh well now I know the person interviewing me is bad part of their job
so they just failed the interview that I would be having for them Step
1 so there's that
And step two I suppose would just be like hey you know a lot of people
are going to be nervous when they're in that situation.
You're not the only one a lot of people are going to make mistakes
that situation.
You're not the only one.
What the interview is trying to do is just see how you work through a
problem.
They just want to see your thought process.
So just you know try to just understand that getting the right answer
and doing everything.
Perfect is not necessarily what they're looking for, if they're any
good at all.
So you have some leeway there.
So, you know, maybe
Relax, you a little bit too.
I said it before on the stream and I'll say it again.
The correct way to do Tech interviews is to its the onus is on the
interviewer, not the interviewee and what the interviewer should be
doing.
Is, they should be drilling down into your programming history, to
find things that you have done before that, you've already done that.
You already worked on that you've already programmed.
And have you explained those on the Whiteboard because nobody is about
solving problems, they haven't seen before.
All of a sudden on a whiteboard in front of someone, they know, no, it
doesn't even make any sense.
It's so far from anything that you would ever do in an actual work
environment.
It's ridiculous.
Right?
But what you actually want to know when you interview someone in Tech
is do they actually know their stuff.
So what have they done before and you drill,
Down into that.
And one of the best tech interviewers there is is Chris Hacker.
He's the one who taught me this.
And he did it flawlessly.
Every time.
He'd be like the the you know, the candidate would be there and he'd
be like, what, you know, what have you worked on?
They've been like, oh, you know, I did this, you know, I used to work
on this banking system and it was like, you know, it was a thing for
animators actually be like, oh okay tell me a little bit more about
that transaction system and the guy would go like oh okay well you
know the transaction would come in and we have to patch them up and
there's a like, oh well, you know then crispy like oh is it hard to
like handle the consistency model for that or whatever and they'd be
like, well,
Well, you know, maybe it was this or that and then be like, okay, tell
me a little bit about that algorithm, you just mentioned for him
consistency and he would get them to do a whiteboard problem
effectively.
But one that they were comfortable with, right?
And one that they had already done, so they should know they should be
aware of all that stuff, right?
And that's the way you figure out if someone knows their stuff, you
figure out if they know their stuff, when they're comfortable with it.
Finding out how they perform on something they're uncomfortable with
is
Useless because some of the greatest programmers don't come up with
anything right away.
They're they're too slow on the spot but give them a day and the thing
they come back with you the next day, maybe better than anybody else
said in the room at the time, who is fast on their feet?
And so if you're screening for that whiteboard like, you know, Macho,
whatever it is, you're just wasting everyone's time.
That doesn't filter.
Good programmers, from Bad programmers at all.
And
It's just a stupid thing that I guess, Microsoft started that people
still do now, but it's, it's ridiculous.
And if it helps at all, when someone does that to you, in a job
interview, just understand that there allows the interviewer and maybe
that will help you not be nervous.
Alright, that's about it for today because we are out of time clothes.
Oops.
Yeah, we did that close.
Save.
Save and close.
Okay, thank you, everyone for joining me for another episode of
handmade hero.
It's been a pleasure coding with you.
As always, it has been almost as much of a pleasure coding with you,
as Windows is awful.
And that it is a non pleasure having to work with Microsoft.
As I said, this episode was dedicated to just how antagonistic they
are and how miserable they've made my life over the past two days.
So you can go ahead and all give them an official.
Thank you for nothing from me.
That said if
You would like, to follow along with handmade Hero at home, and maybe
ported to Linux or Mac, which believe me is starting to look at that.
Like a very, very high on the list priority for handmade hero.
Even though I wasn't expecting to do that anytime soon, you can go
ahead and pre-order the game at handmade hero dot-org.
Using the handy dandy pre-order button and it comes with a source
code.
So you can, you know, play with it experiment, learn from it, do do
all kinds of stuff like that, and
And and yeah, and actually, if you go to our Forum site, there's
actually people have already done ports to Mac and Linux and stuff
like that.
And yeah.
And like I said, maybe that's something that we have to start thinking
about doing a little bit earlier.
Maybe we need to move our primary Dev platform over to Links or
something.
Because at this point, Microsoft is so high on my list of most awful
people that I am.
Not sure that I really want to keep streaming from their platform.
That's it.
If you would like to know when, I will be streaming from Linux or
Windows or anything else, you can go to our tweet bot and our tweet
tweets the schedule.
It you it treats the schedule every day.
So you know, when it's going to be live and also tweets the schedule
on the weekend.
So you can go ahead and take a look at when it's going to be live.
If you want to catch it.
We also have a patreon page.
If you want to support the video series, you can always subscribe to
that.
And, you know, I don't know, I don't know what we'll do.
Exactly maybe we'll make a new patreon, tier.
That's like if we hit, you know, a certain amount of money on the
patreon.
I'll just do weekend streams to like Port it to Linux in the meantime
so that we can get off of Windows and, and not have to deal with this
nonsense anymore.
Anyway, so that's about it.
I will be back here tomorrow at 5 p.m.
Pacific Daylight time.
I think tomorrow is Friday, if I'm not mistaken, so that would be the
lasting for this week.
Eek hope to see you there and until then have fun coding on your own
projects or on handmade hero experiments or whatever else is that
you're doing, and I will see you guys on the internet.
So tickety's everyone and and have a good evening.