One of the things that we don't do on handmade hero and the reason we
don't do it is because I don't know anything about it is compression,
and compression is one of those things that is behind the scenes in
basically every game that exists.
In fact, it's behind the scenes and pretty much anything that exists.
Because fundamentally speaking, you're always trying to get a little
bit more out of a little bit less.
And so any game that ships today has a ton of compression in the
backend for you know, where you know, whatever the assets are stored
in is typically has nothing to do.
How they might appear raw when the artists created them.
And so what I wanted to do with this first session is kind of invite
people who are the absolute like experts and compression.
The people that I asked when I'm like, I don't know what to do with
this or how this sort of thing works.
Please explain it to me.
So I asked the folks at Red game tools to come and and give us like
sort of how they think about compression.
If you're someone who's interested in sort of learning more about
compression, how do you frame it?
How do you think about it?
And so,
Today it's it's a real pleasure for me to have Jeff Roberts and Fabian
giessen with me from Brad game tools.
I'm gonna sort of prompt them but I'm going to let them talk as much
as possible because because I'm a compression noob if ever there was
one.
So first of all before we get started, could you guys maybe give me a
little bit background Jeff you you know you started red games was a
long time ago.
How did you get into compression?
What what brought you to this as a you know, a technology Focus, I
guess.
Yeah, Red's been doing this for nearly 30 years and we started the
first thing I ever wrote
It was a an exe compressor which I believe is one of the first
compression things you will.
You didn't you work on crunchy too but you worked on it out.
See compressive.
That was after I do a lot of compression to.
Yeah.
The first thing rat ever sold was a something called pack.
Exe is just compressed and EXC, as you ran it at decoded into memory
and ran.
So this is for executables, like on floppy disks for.
Yeah, it's not really exactly.
So they and like, upx is what people use nowadays, but it
Just a, you know, when you run a run an executable, there's a tiny
little you can set it up.
So a tiny little program runs that expands the big program in memory,
and then you jump into it and it's as if you ran the original program,
but it's just decoding on the Fly.
You sort of have this tube.
It's almost like a bootloader, yes, where you have a tiny program
that's designed to do nothing but decompress the real program, right?
Right.
And so the constraints, there are kind of interesting in the sense
that you can't be a big program because
it's not a program that is installed on the computer all the time.
It's part of the executable itself.
So it's a reasonably pure form of compression in the sense that it's
all packed into one thing.
You know, there's the joke of like, you know, anybody can make a
compressor if you know the data that you're compressing
Because you just put the data that you're pressing in the thing and
you're like, hey, it's magic.
It was one bite.
Do you even need the one bite?
Well, to say, whether it was that one, or if you only need to compress
that one file, you don't need even that one, but if you ever want to
be able to, at least like four appearances, take a second file, and
not compress it, you need to have at least a bit saying, whether this
is the compressed power, not an excellent executable compressor.
Yes, this is, yeah, I mean, that is kind of the joke.
Of of there are certainly part of compression attracts kind of the
Zero Point, Energy loonies.
And there's really, oh, yeah, there's a big crossover in like I'm
sorry, Zero Point Energy.
I think, the only thing that I know this from is from watching movie.
The Incredibles is that he has like a little thing that he moved to
the right.
It's the right term, right?
It's for the people who imagine there's Just Energy floating around.
I think about I think a better analogy is
Because it's pretty much the same people.
It's just perpetual motion machines.
Yeah, people are really into, that was all that stuff.
So they just want to or they feel like they could get like infinite
compression or something like this, right.
Okay.
And then cursive compression, isn't it?
Something that they use as a way to make it sound like like oh you run
it and then you run it again and it's okay.
And by the way this doesn't work is also for the exact same reason.
This is about fundamentally about thermodynamics, okay.
Like it really pretty much is I mean like the way you normally do it
as meth.
Matically.
You just you can just do it by counting.
Okay.
Like say oh if you say I can compress any file.
Yes.
Like, there's just like the size of the number of files of say,
length, up to 100.
Bytes is limited, but he can count them all.
Yeah, you can enumerate them.
And if you can't say, I can compress all of them.
What you're really saying is like, I can take that set that has a
certain size map that to a smaller set because they're all smaller.
Right?
Like somehow not lose anything and it just
Be invertible.
Like that's the entirety of the argument, okay?
Which like there's some thought there.
But this is not fancy mathematics and the kind of people you are
giving within that Community will not accept that argument, right?
Okay.
Better have this program that does.
This, is that?
Yes.
And I can prove without even looking at the program that it can
possibly work.
So this is, this is kind of interesting because it's like I did not
realize that this sort of a thing was a discussion that happened.
I imagine that because compressor happened.
It still happens even today, okay?
There's no way.
The only point of all that was that
At eat the way that you kind of prevent that data leakage because like
you can imagine here a program that compressed a file by taking the
first bite of the file and sticking it on the end of the file name.
Right.
The final.
Yeah.
He has a lot of 0 B.
The files tiny but so part of like measuring a compressor to make sure
you're not cheating, is you add in the size of the file that I mean
the the executable itself, not the file name.
Look like the whole thing matters.
Not
Exe compression was nice in that sense of like, it's all part of one.
I series chance for basically, when you said it's a pure form cousin,
kind of what you mean.
Is, there's no hand-waving here because anything that you added, that
was a cheat in the executable is counted in the size automatically
since that executable is the thing, your shipping, right?
Whereas, I suppose if it was an image or something, you could just
make the compressor, bigger and bigger and bigger.
And there's, you know, there's all kinds of tricks you can pull.
So, like, if you do this, theoretically, it looks in theory like
there's this whole notion of a channel, okay?
Just
Medium, you're communicating over like, might be a Folly of writing
stuff into, okay.
And if you're doing compression, obviously, you have to worry about
what exactly constitutes your channel.
It's otherwise, it can treat.
Like, if you say so, for example, like if you're a Windows on, NTFS
files can have multiple streams and like, if you do a directory
listing it'll show you the size of the first stream I.
So one way to do a compressor is to just take the data from the first
stream, move it over to the second stream and like now like if you do
a directory listing it doesn't show up
The data is for your life but like, this kind of stuff happens.
Inadvertently all the time.
Like you can do a compression.
If you have a medium that gives you extra capacity that counts as part
of the channel elsewhere.
So for example, if you're saying, UDP packets over the network, these
have the actual data, bytes you sending, but the length of the packet
is part of the thing, right?
And you get that length back.
That's useful data.
Yeah.
So like one thing you can do, if you're sending, that's an actual
thing that people do in that.
It totally makes sense.
If you're doing say compression compression for your game and you're
sending regular packets, you can try to arrange things, so that last
number of bytes of the packet are usually zeros.
And then you just say implicitly, like if the decompressor keeps
reading after the pack is over, you just feed it zeros.
I see.
So then you can because the size is part of the thing that gets sent
over the network, you can get some data for free, right?
Which you would not really be able to use that size for anything else.
So you're sort of just pushing a little bit of extra information in
there, which is
Is exact, and it's not like, it's huge.
You get a couple bits from there, but like you have to be careful to
honestly Define what your channel is and like these things like file
size or file name.
And so on this extra metadata access permissions, extra streams.
You can put, you can hide data there if you want to, okay, he just got
to be careful.
If somebody tells you, you have the magic machine that makes these
files smaller.
You have to be really careful with it doing.
Yeah?
Okay.
I'm very interested that that came up so quickly.
But if it was like it was kind of like the first thing I want to
discuss with anybody about data compression, this thing comes up
immediately.
You will find somebody who has the same with physics.
Like there's people with their perpetual motion plans and like they
want to talk to you about it someday.
It's going to work, man.
It's just going to keep going and going like the Energizer Bunny.
Yeah, so okay.
Just to get just a little bit more background so that was all great
but I just want soap so you don't know.
So you wrote an exit compressor as the food.
The first thing that we ever in and we were kind of a hardware and
software company then and so that was the first piece of software we
ever sold and resold it to another company.
Who okay?
Can't remember who what they were.
But anyway yeah that's so I started on an early.
I find compression is a specially data compression as opposed to image
and the other stuff is a fairly it's less this way now and we can talk
about that pure.
Her in the sense that you run it and you get a smaller file or you
don't.
And so that was always appealing to me.
It's a fun thing to like it is a thing.
You can get sucked into in this is even when I was talking to check or
wedded compression to his Gamers assembly of a Checkers.
Chris Tucker.
Yeah who like can get sucked into these things of it's just a fun
iterative process and so certainly and I guess you have kind of a
clean number that's like is my program getting better or worse as
opposed to like architecture stuff for you.
Did it get better or worse?
I don't know.
And then, and now recently, that's not recently, but this is always
been true, but it's never been true more than now, is there, is this
extra axi or axis that that exists?
Which is what is, what is the speed trade-off?
You're willing to do for the amount of Corrections, which I guess rad
is, which is where we can live with because of kind of lives a matrix.
Yeah, so anyway, that's okay.
That's so we've done a lot.
Lat Redstone a lot of stuff over the years, but it's, we've always
kind of and a lot of our guys even that our game kind of programmers
have a background in starting compression because I feel like that's a
good place to be and fobbing.
You presumably.
Well, I kind of know you did because I know you but like you did not
start doing compression when you came to rad.
So how did you first?
You know, how did that come about, is something you were interested
in?
I can't hustle issei.
I don't know.
Is this like, weird soon as I knew on video compression, right?
Like, wasn't your dissertation but my diploma thesis was on video
compression stuff.
That was way after when I first started like basically, as soon as I
learned that there was such a thing as data compression, okay?
Like that.
It was a theory to it, and not just like there was you had stuff like,
pkzip that you just knew how to use, right?
And that always seemed a bit magic and then you get at some point.
I got some algorithms book on something that
Planes.
I think Huffman coding.
Okay which is one of the classic algorithms from the 50s to do this
kind of thing.
That's still practically irrelevant and once you learn about that
stuff is like oh that's interesting I'd like to know more.
Then you start getting into it.
Let's start with some compression stuff here, for people, such as
myself who don't really know what's going on.
Jeff sent me some things that he was thinking about in terms of
topics, it looks like.
Bobby has got some too.
I just want to start with one question of mine.
And then we can go with mostly stuff of yours because you guys know
more about how it should probably be laid out.
My fundamental question is just like okay as someone who sort of knows
the buzzword version of compression, like, you know, okay, that's, you
know, LZ compressor something this but really has a very shallow
understanding of it, which is where I'm coming from.
Could you, perhaps give a sort of quick, I don't know, like, guide to
just, what is the way to think about, like the
In family, if you will, because there's lossy and lossless, there's
backend entropy.
There's dictionary.
There's all these things.
And I feel like to start with, sort of a little bit of a taxonomy that
as we go through this discussion, people can sort of understand and,
and like file into a good taxonomy of where these things are fitting
into that process and where those lines are and how they blur.
And so I just feel like that would be great because I maybe have this
one in my head that's probably not real great.
And if you know you could kind of give us one that was better.
That would be awesome.
Yeah, I can talk about maybe start and then so the way I think is a
David Stafford who was a long time compression guy.
And in fact, I think you'll be talking about him tomorrow at the
little bit at the software, rendering stuff, since he was a surly game
guy, just a smart guy been around for a long time.
Used to have this thing.
He'd ask people who worked in compression of what they felt
compression was and you know you might guess.
Whatever, you know, make this little guess and he kind of used it as a
game, to start a conversation and his answer, you say, What
compression was?
Yeah, it should more of a general thing of just like, what do you
think it had?
It means like what's it about?
Yeah.
What's it about?
And and his answer was always prediction like the better of a
predictor.
You are the better compression.
You'll get like just in a very hand wavy way.
And when you say predictor he's basically meaning how well your
compressor guesses.
What will come to?
Yeah.
So so so there's this
So that's kind of what I was going to get to in the in how I think
about compression is there's kind of two halves of it.
There's like the first part is called modeling and that is usually the
prediction part of like your best, guess of what's going to happen in
a data stream or in a video stream or an audio stream or anything, you
make a guess and then you're wrong because you're always a little
wrong, your prediction is a perfect, otherwise we would need it, you
know, it would be much easier problem or in the case of Fabian
Sir that has the one bit that says this is the other stream, right?
Orange.
So so I sort of think about is the modeling part and then there's the
part, the statistical end the part where you have to clean up the
errors, the residuals.
Okay.
So and I think that's where the more interesting problem is because
you're never going to have perfect prediction and the difference
between /, really good prediction.
And okay, prediction is, you get a lot of the way with a not great
thing.
So,
I sort of think of it as those two levels and certainly like anything
else, when you do it for a long time, the big winds come from
blurring.
Those edges of like you start out when you write these things as
you're going to write.
Oh, here's our this.
And here's our back end and then over time they blur together and you
try to make a model, or that gives you things that the residual
compressor can do better on and that kind of thing.
So, here's a like, I guess, if I'm, if I'm going to try to try to
break that down.
So here's what I sort of
Got out of that.
In terms of the thought process, you tend to think of it as when I'm
looking at a compressor, I'm thinking about how I'm modeling what, I
expect this compressor to see in a very efficient likely to be
correct, most of the time way and how I handled the difference between
its guests and the actual data that I was fed and your kind of mapping
the parts of the compressor into a spectrum somewhere on this end.
Presumably, different compressors have different pieces that fall into
those parts.
Some maybe have multiple pieces that chain together, some absolute
things that are multiple levels, where you're predicting at one level
like in a PNG you're predicting pixels and then you follow that up by
a pass that doesn't LZ which was predicting B and then you follow that
up with a statistical end but that's how I break it down in my head
the two stages.
But again like once you're past kind of
Oi stuff.
You start blurring those lines, all over the place and with lossy
versus lossless compression.
Like something like a jpeg versus a pink you.
It sounds like and maybe this is not true.
So correct me if this is Miss statement but sounds like you don't
think of that as a big difference between these things you think of as
more just like, well, I'm going to store all the data or I'm not or
the residual part I'm going to store all of that or I'm not but I
don't think of that as a real defining characteristic of the
compressor or away.
To think about these algorithms, that's more just like it, it's a
critical part and it's how all these algorithms work, but it's not how
I classified in my brain and it might be different for other people.
Okay, awesome.
Gaming.
The whole also stuff is just
They're different applications.
Like if you if you're going to do backups you probably want a lots of
compressor.
I'm gonna have some thick-ass Transit you're backing up true.
Like I mean, also, I can practice like something like 80% of your
backups.
You never gonna look again.
Yeah.
So if your compressor is really good at predicting the parts that they
actually need backed up a good point that will work.
I mean that's basically a name
The game, yes.
That big Watershed between lossless and lossy is not that they use
completely different techniques, it's just that with loss.
Compression.
They, if you look at a basically, if you were to plot a curve, like
how many bits have I sent versus how good is the reconstructed data?
How close is it to the original?
Okay, no losses.
Compressor, you just keep sending bits October.
That error is 0?
Yes, because everything else is not acceptable, okay?
A lossless compressed.
So is one where you willing to stop early, okay?
That's pretty much.
And like, he tried to design the bit stream.
So that at any step of the algorithm, your options are such that you
have a good way to just send a few bits and get a lot of information.
Like reduce the error by a lot, Okay?
And like, if you look at applications, they in a game setting.
Like, for example, for networking, you will usually do lossy
compression like for example, like dead reckoning.
And so, on like the stuff, you send a network packet will not give you
the exact values back.
It has limited resolution and so on because it doesn't
That much.
So you're talking about in a game, a multiplayer game running over the
network and you're sending State packets across.
Yep.
Oftentimes you're saying you will even allow Los Lunas there because
even though it's not an image or something like this, you just don't
care enough about the Precision like this stuff, like whatever the
position of the player will usually have like, whatever 32 it floats.
Yeah.
It's like for three axes.
So every 96 bits of position and usually you will not send that whole
thing.
I see you'll send something that has lost as a form of like all right.
That's yeah that's enforced compliance.
Precious yeah no I mean they got you try to design the format so that
if you lose a packet like that degrades gracefully which is another
form of the modeling, like you have to sort of design that into the
system very interesting and you basically try to distribute the that's
actually for Network game.
That's very much designed in the anything that's important.
Think that's really important that's like State changes.
If you're going over something like UDP which can drop packets.
You just keep presenting that data at little the other.
Sag knowledge that.
Yeah, I've seen that.
You might not resend it every packet, but you have to resent it,
periodically to make sure that eventually they see it.
Yes, that's like again, it's like you just have first up.
There's this notion of error.
Okay.
Lossy compression of like how closest thing I've sent up until now to
what I actually want to have in the end, you can also like
From an application perspective like what does error mean and it's
usually about like either something about the Fidelity of the thing
you're standing or it's just about how important it is.
And so I guess that you're just saying there's a definition of error
which is not necessarily about reproducing the data stream in some
absolute sense.
It's more about like what what kind of differences we care about
versus what kind of difference is, we don't.
Exactly.
I mean, like, in a network game, like if whatever the match is over,
that's important information because that means you got to go back to
the lobby and
You got to keep presenting that because, like, having the other game,
keep continue running.
Game with when all of the players have left is a fairly significant
error.
Yes, they want to make sure not to make that mistake.
Yes.
Well, as other things you might not care like whatever.
It's some might decide.
Like if you have really high traffic, you're okay with dropping trap
messages, for example.
Okay.
Or you might decide that you always want to use because they're
important.
Yes there's stuff like voice packets their stuff like okay whatever
random packets that just tell you to play a sound effect if those get
dropped, whatever.
Not a big deal like would be nice but
and so there's this hierarchy, so,
The lossless world is all about general purpose compression, which
somebody just provides a library.
Like this is the thing that you just given an arbitrary file to, and
then you expect to get that file back to, these are generally not
tuned.
I mean, certainly some lossless compressors are tuned to a particular
datatype assume like text compressors.
Yeah.
Or something.
Like yeah, but it's fairly General and like, because the error always
has to go to zero in the end, right?
They have to be differently.
He gave the people give you back the same thing.
You just might not get as much compression if you have a encoder.
That takes some special liberties with.
How binary data might be structured, other than text data banks of the
Lost Sea World.
It's a lot more application-specific.
Yeah.
So, before we get too far into that.
Did you want to talk about how your mental model of compression as
well?
Because I didn't know if it differs.
I mean, different, you know, perspectives or was Jeff's actually
somewhat similar.
To the way you think about it, it at a high level similar.
I mean they to me it's a lot about just modeling.
Okay.
It's just basically
It's sort of a scientific process more or less.
Like you just tried to build this model of how data behaves okay and
how close or how not close you are is very easy to measure and that
that's the amount of bits you have to spend in one way or another to
just get that prediction with that model which might be good or might
be bad to actually match the real data.
I think that's part of why it is so addictive to some people, okay?
It's just that you have this very objective feedback.
Yes.
Like there's no.
And you also have no absolute answer, like most of the time.
You don't know what the smallest thing is.
I assume.
So there's always this sort of like, reaching for the The Chalice.
Yeah, thing.
Where you think you could maybe get a little bit better?
Yeah, there's a funny thing of with compression, there's no, we don't
even have like, oh, this is, this is entropically.
The smallest this amount of
Right ever.
We don't have a way to even get into that.
We can't even measure.
Even smaller stages of like, in an LZ compressor, you have something
called the parse, which is how you break it apart.
Maybe we'll talk about that a second, okay?
But it's how you jump through a file, we don't even know a way to find
a perfect.
Parse
Given compressor like a good lock, some things down and hand wave we
do.
Well, it depends on, it depends on if your stuff is chain.
If you're, if you're a dynamic system, like you have to like, at some
point estimate that like, all right, I'm going to just call, this is
closed.
It's a practical problem.
Yeah.
Like, at some point you just don't want to spend like, five weeks,
compressing, a 4 kilobyte file.
Right.
But it's not like, it's not
like you can get close it.
I'm not going to say no.
But some of the stuff you say, like, what's the minimum size for this
file?
Like that's actually mathematically undecidable like that's like
holding problem level bad and you also sort of a suggesting that it
depends.
I mean you're talking about a thing that compresses a certain Corpus
of data as well because like you said, if you're just compressing
purely General data, the answer is you can't compress it.
Like you said you had overall little overall out to the exact same.
But so it's saying how small can this get is like, well what you mean
is how small can this
Of things get on average, we're within this system within this system.
I mean the thing is the stuff that Jeff was talking about were like we
don't know what the optimal LZ.
Parcel.
Something that's not actually true that we can't determine that.
That's just that's literally just a shortest path surgeon.
A graph happens to be a really large graph and very diminishing
returns, okay?
But it's not like that's an that's a completely solvable problem.
That is economically useless to solve because I said, nobody wants to
wait three weeks to compress a 4K.
Okay, but like that is not the same level of we can't do this as they
like deciding.
What's the minimum size for this file?
Outside of this framework of like within this encoding All rights,
like within a given encoding, I see you can usually like there's a
deterministic process, which is little, literally enumerate all
possible.
Encodings up to a given length, right?
I think figure out if that gives you back the file, you want right?
Right.
Like that one always works and it's really shitty way better ways to
do that.
Okay.
Big for the LZ parse.
It's usually not even like that bad if something.
It's like, and to the third power and to the fourth power, we still
want to spend that amount of time, but that's not even an exponential
search.
So it's not that bad.
It's just so you still useful.
So essentially, I guess the thing there is for a given codec yeah we
probably can run some exhaustive procedure, possibly optimized to
eventually determine what the smallest size of something, is if that
thing was within a fairly attractive
Bill bound.
Yep.
Once it gets about that we can and you stand in it.
If the question is, how small can I get in general?
We don't have any idea because that once, once you take a particular
compressor out of the definition, it becomes the fanciful problem.
Once again the general space, you also have to somehow and coat the
decompressor itself because once you have the space of all possible,
encodings yes, you're talking about, oh, I have to have this program,
that's the decompressor and then the data it takes that.
Yes, they these two together produce the output.
Yes, this is kind of the XE compression again, right?
Except when you doing this in the map,
Go framework.
You don't use something crazy like x86 writer.
Like lots of corner cases, use mathematical model, that's nice and
tractable like a turing machine, Okay?
And like, even if I'm in that like, oh, like, there's this notion
called kolmogorov complexity, okay?
Which is just Russian mathematician as always and comig or of justice.
Is that?
Like I said, the good math becomes a lot of some Rush, a lot of
combinatoric, sand graph, Theory stuff and optimization stuff comes
from Russia.
Actually a lot of Moscow.
State University, 50s and 60s 60s, good stuff.
Like a lot of that.
Then, got rediscovered later in the US and like a lot of theorems.
They had this all figured out way before and it just because of the
cold war, we wanted now took a while for that session College to
propagate.
But okay, the stuff that call my Garf that it's just like hey it just
basically has just this definition that you determine a program and
the input data that together produces that output okay?
Which is nice concise.
Definition.
You can write it down easily and it turns out I said is completely
undecidable.
Well, I guess as soon as you include the program that you are into all
of the standards of the, our computer science problems, that you would
have whichever program because presumed that person can do anything
that a person can do.
I mean that's exactly the kind of thing you run into.
Whenever you have and that's a very practical problem to take, get
back into it.
Ground floor here.
Yeah.
It's like not go to abstract the basic problem.
We have with compression is always that you have to sort of trade off
what kind of thing in the going to put in the compressor.
There's lots of things you can do.
This might be really useful to have in there, but it turns out, like,
if you don't have this feature in the bitstream, this enumeration
process, this decision process is really easy.
Okay, once you throw this thing in that,
Like a form of dependency that certainly means that whatever you're
only N squared algorithm or linear time, algorithm doesn't work and
you suddenly falling back to an exponential search.
So you have to trade out like okay, this makes the big stream more
expressive but in a way that means that now all known ways to just
find a good solution don't work.
But if you have, if that's only the stuff that's guaranteed to give
you the optimal solution about them, whatever I still have heuristics
and my heuristic solve
With this more expressive format gives better results than optimal
solve for these less expressive form, and then, he might decide you
want to do that.
So, let me just unpack because we haven't quite gotten down to that
level yet.
So, I want to discover that I think, I know what you're saying, but I
just want to make sure.
So essentially what you're saying is okay, I'm writing a compressor.
And you know, I am creating, you know, the definition of this
compressor means I'm going to have the decompressor is kind of sort, I
guess the definition of the compression.
How it works.
Just like if I
Can write the decompressor.
Now, I have completely specified.
You let this format is in some sense, but although I could make that
thing have arbitrarily complex pieces in it, some of those May
Fly that the compressor in order to pick optimal or good compressions.
Now is somewhat intractable or practically TracFone some way is that
is everything that's on the theoretical thing.
If you look at things like video compression, yes.
Like all the MPEG standards used to be just a specified, the decoder,
right?
They did not have any provisions for.
How do you even think about this?
I see, and for a long time after the specified MPEG, they hit an idea
for how you can write a program.
I'm that generates a valid encoding like there weren't good.
They guess why?
There's no.
Yes, thank the theory of like how to write something that generates a
good output like for a human looking at this like this.
Like this looks kind of close even if you look at like now considered
old codecs like a gwaan by the time they expect a 2 and then the first
parts of impact for or like we hadn't figured out how to do good and
coder frantic to yet, I was what we know now about current video.
That's you can do way better and her friend back to as well, right?
So if you win back now and wrote the encoders, you wouldn't even have
to change like the format for a DVD.
You could just get better looking video because the encoders would
just produce better bit streams and that's also like part of what
happens.
Like, that's why like the even at the same bit rate the video you see
on a DVD will usually be better than what you have in the TV broadcast
scenario.
With the same generate that simply because like if you have, if you
have somebody doing a DVD, a they have more time to spend on the
encoding in general, and be they live
Really just have somebody going over the scenes, like looking at them
individually, like, oh, this needs more bed right here, whatever.
And so, if you're mastering a DVD for a feature film, like having
somebody spent two weeks, looking at every frame of the picture and
this, I know this needs a bit more bits here and like it's lost in the
noise.
There's so many other costs with mastering that it's worthwhile doing
that actually wears on TV broadcasters like no.
Like the street this stream is going out right now and it needs to be
like on screen 15 seconds like you do whatever.
Okay.
So it's kind of just grind the sausage and whatever comes
The other end is dinner.
Yeah, okay.
To put to put it another way, as well.
Is this is something that a lot of times people don't realize is when
you say zip a file, there isn't a exact like you can, you can produce
a zip file, that will decompress to the same file, and they'll be lots
of different fuzzy sizes, right?
Right, because the, the specification is over, is over, generalized
it.
That way, like you can have ones that do different things like that.
So certainly, the compressor, how you make those decisions on what the
what bitstream you feed to.
The decoder makes a big difference and certainly some of the fast
stuff that Charles and Fabien have been working on with doodle is be
kind of taking that to a an extreme of like writing parsers that
generate files that can be decoded quickly, right?
Like is a big part of what that win is.
It isn't just like and certainly you know rad we've
I had this ability you know in the early days it was me when you were
working on granny, I'd help optimize stuff and then we have a Brash
and certain who would work on stuff.
And now we have Fabienne who's better than all of us put together?
Who can always kind of fill up the, you know, can kind of clean things
up and make them fast at the end, but a lot of how you design these
systems is writing things that are by their nature optimizable or like
our Fab
That was a big part of the design of ink to as well, was that, you
know, that was the thing that what you can decode quick.
Yeah.
And then because that's very important and that's like, get the best
compression you can within a game time especially for being too.
I remember like this was basically like the format was to a large
extent dictated by having to decode it on Xbox 360.
Yes.
Yeah.
That was like the worst case of 360 and PS3 really cool.
Yeah, they're not good chips.
I'm glad we don't have sponsors for this cop.
I think, I don't think anybody don't think you'd be sponsored by IBM
and Microsoft and Sony decided to switch to MD for the next sure.
It's a good fit.
There you go.
That's a very good point.
All right.
So let me I don't know what's on your list of audience, so I guess
it's you're going to have okay?
So should I ask some of these then or did you have any topics you and
just go ahead?
Okay, so I guess these were from Jeff's, original email,
And I understood some of them but I didn't understand some of that.
I'll start with one that I did understand, but she was you said
modeling versus statistical it was a topic so you kind of touched on
that a little bit, but it wasn't, you know, sort of directly address.
So what did you want to start saying about that?
Well and it was Audrey but was just separating the idea of prediction
and dealing with the residuals of how you think about compression.
Like when you learn how to do compression, you kind of start down this
path of like, all right, maybe
First thing you do is like, oh, I'm sending all these integers and
they don't all, they're not all 0 to f, f, f, f, f f f.
So like, all right, I'm going to do some little bit packing.
Thing of like this value is only seven bit.
So I'm going to shove 7, B at the top of word and so that you start on
your like learn okay, okay, I made a bit Packer and now I got that
smaller and then maybe you get a little fancier and do like,
multiplicative stuff where you're like, all right, now my value is not
evenly that bit.
I'm like, oh, this is a value from, you know, one
23.
So I want to multiply those out together and so you kind of build on
this and then you start modeling where you're like.
Now I'm just not encoding the data I'm like predicting the data and
then dealing with the the Deltas.
So it's it's so often we don't know because this was actually
something that again and like I said kind of I'm trying to get the
compression from a beginner standpoint because it's not something
recovering here and it's not something that I know.
So this was something that was that I've heard you guys talked about
before.
It was a point that I think was worth internalizing at least for me
because again, a lot of these things, I'm sure are very simple for
people who work on compression.
But before you get into it, it's you don't have any traction on,
really what's going on?
You know, you might read an algorithm and say, oh okay, there's a
Huffman codec.
It does this on the bit stream or here's an LZ thing and it does
whatever.
But the prediction thing, I just like to give an example of that.
Because one of the things that you were saying was like, okay.
So for example,
I have an image that I'm trying to compress like, and maybe we're just
talking about like one small subsection of the image that I'm trying
to put out there.
So a very simple thing that you mentioned was like, okay, oftentimes
you can get much better compression.
If first before you do anything, you just subtract everything from its
neighbor first as a very simple thing because it's very very cheap to
do, right?
So if you're not that, okay?
So could you just give a simple example like that for people who are
more on my side because people out there right now are like AI.
All the stuff and we'll get to the more you know, sort of maybe stuff
that they burn so late.
But I just want for people like me you're kind of like coming out of
first time can you give like a very simple example of that so that
when we say prediction it's not kind of fuzzy and it's more like this
is what we mean.
Okay.
Yeah yes, please just for modeling.
So what that means is you have some concrete expectation of our data
looks like like if you think about the kinds of things, the kinds of
knowledge and so on you can bring into this basically like two
separate universes.
One is kinds of things, you know?
In general about the kind of data you handling.
Yes, if you're dealing with sage Apec, you know like that was
developed for things like photographs.
So like yes, natural imagery, like just digitized whatever.
And that has certain properties such as for example, that adjacent
pixels tend to look similar okay which just means very on a very basic
level.
That if you take the pixel and its immediate neighbor, like the
difference between this and it's likely to be small and you can go a
bit further and look at site.
These pixels are in a statistical sense, are correlated.
I see and if you go a bit further out there still correlate is just a
correlation is weaker.
Okay, once you make that definition mathematically precise and how
that looks you can get to a certain model and just working that chain
of reasoning through the end just that one statement of like there's a
correlation between adjacent pixels.
Yes, that correlation D case and us at a certain rate, once you go
further out, okay just
Once you have that model assumption which sounds fairly reasonable,
you get down to a chain of like, okay, if that is true about the data
then certain properties, hold and then the solutions to these things
on a mattock, mathematical level have a certain shape and there's a
good approximation to doing that kind of transform and that's the
discrete cosine transform which is what jpeg does that, okay?
So there's some mathematical transform that sort of has the right
properties for data that has this shape.
Okay, so that's a very concrete.
The thing you have in text compression is similar.
So there's these things called dictionary methods.
Yes.
And they're the assumption is that if you have text, there's lots of
repetition in there.
And I don't mean repetition at the structural level like, oh, the
sentence or looks like the one before it.
I mean, very literally, like this thing here is a word, the string of
five characters, right?
And we see that word a lot.
Yes.
Might be worth.
Just having a short encoding for this.
Yes, that's where the whole LZ thing comes into this to guys.
Lempel ziv, who did too?
A on this in 1977 1978 called imaginatively lz77 and LT 78.
The definition people generally put their name on stuff.
It's just, that's how everybody decided it.
I don't, I don't think they actually named them that way.
It's like a string substitution method whatever and like, nobody sets
all paper.
So, stuck Bells, isn't this?
The citations lz77 of the name?
Stuck very good.
There's an interesting point there where that was a watershed moment,
when
His papers came out, because there was a funny thing about people,
thinking about compression in terms of Huffman and arithmetic and
getting to the point where we're like, we're doing the best we can.
Okay.
And then these guys came in with these fairly simple algorithms that
were just this huge jump in complexity versus, I mean, that's just, I
mean compression.
So though it was a huge deal and most encoders to this day are lz77
based like well for but you also see ya and like the whole assumption.
There's like you can go down the road.
If you're in the whole statistical compression world, like calm Agora
of Mark reference on that all things, you hear a lot in this context
was all like stochastic switch.
That's what the that's like probability Theory and its modern form
came out of Russia.
So that's also why these Russians are very predominant there.
Okay, that's where that sort of comes from.
If you go down that road you get modern statistical compressors which
are basically just.
You look at data and to try to build a stochastic models.
Like what's the most likely thing to happen next and you get
probabilities and you try to encode that thing back?
Okay, what's called statistical compressors, they look at some form of
this and so the nlds Disciples of statistical compressors like name
wise.
So, the tough even for example, is like a form of statistical
compression.
We look at the statistics of like, How likely are each individual
letter in the alphabet.
The key is a lot more likely than say, why is yes.
So in that case, you want to assign short codes to the letter e and a
very long codesys, a letter Q which is very rare.
Yes,
that kind of thing is under statistical compression and then you can
look at it, I do.
What if I don't look at just a single character, but multiple
characters or I look at a single character, but also consider what?
When just before that character, or you say, like, my model is not
just what happened immediately.
Go.
But also like other data I have seen in that try to infer, complex
properties of the data I've seen so far in this stream, like, the
stuff I mentioned with jpeg is just general, like, things.
I know about the world, right?
Like I know how certain images look and I
Use that to drive.
Compression the stuff with statistical.
Coders was more like, oh, I know about data that it is self-similar
and a certain way.
And I just try to learn properties of the data stream as I go along
and they built a model.
So, how would you define the split between something like an LZ
compressor and something like a Huffman or an arithmetic compressor in
this?
I mean, obviously, it can be used together.
But, I mean those, those separate algorithms because in some sense,
the description that you just gave could sort of apply
I to an LZ compressor, it's can view, right?
It's sort of a system, is just like, as I see things, I know I can
reference things that I've already seen and that there's a certain
cost to that.
So I might adjust my etcetera, etcetera.
Right it.
So how would you?
It's mainly a matter of how you think about it?
Like hell, these can be fully understood as just, this is a form of
so-called Markov model Markov model.
Just means that you predict the data you have right now from data, you
see in the past that's really all that means, okay?
You can go a bit more precise about what that is but that's really all
falls down to, okay.
The Fairly basic thing, but the string matching stuff you have in
compression.
Like, LZ means that you don't have any kind of repetition has to have
a certain structure, you include that in a certain way where you write
down an offset.
Like this is where that string was or you built an explicit dictionary
of words.
I say this word number 351.
Yes.
So that's a bit more explicit than just saying like oh I haven't
General a probability model.
Like I said, Markov models.
As in general, are a very general theory, very general abstraction,
but you can't, you can apply that sort of thing to everything.
The string matching sting and the dictionary thing is a lot more
specialized, but has structure like, oh, that it doesn't break stuff
apart between bites or something like that.
You can do a lot.
Nicer modeling.
You can do a lot like string searching and so on, we have good data
structures for that.
There's lots of Leverage their working at that string level.
So the LZ stuff tends to be a lot faster but like chromatic
mathematical point of view and from a theoretical point of view it's
just a Markov model you it just happens to be the type of Markov model
that's most efficient by an order of magnitude.
Yeah.
Okay I can give it its just talking about prediction versus the
encoding and give you one just a very simple way to think about it.
That's less mathematical of like a specific case of you can imagine an
image that was just a wash from 0 to 255, okay?
And you have a very simple back end of your image encoder.
That is an RL that just encodes runs.
It says like, okay, there was a zero and there was 25 of them.
Right?
Very serviceable thing.
That's just like, I've been just give account in a value.
Yeah.
And we're just going to send it that way.
If the whole thing was the same color, I just send two things down to
B down and we're done, right?
So if you have that back end and you feed it, the wash.
It's not going to do very well because every pixel is different from
the previous one.
So, but if you add some prediction to it and subtract from the
previous thing,
Stead of a wash from 0 to 255.
You end up with all big run you know a 0 and a bunch of ones.
Okay, so then all of a sudden like okay, now your prediction has
helped to the backend statistical part have an easier job.
So that's kind of the split that a very specific simple way of
thinking about.
And so in some sense, the predictions and the transforms because the
transforms are the predict, like you get, I guess it's, Jimmy could
sick of these similar like, your predictor your transform, whatever it
is, is the thing that you are using to try and make the data become as
regular as
Well, for whatever you're feeding it into.
Yeah, just something that your back end is you expects to see that
thing in some sense, moves your highly compressible, stuff around in
some sense.
Like meaning I've got, you know, all the things I might never
compress, there's some things I can press very well and some some
things that compress very poorly.
I'm trying with these transforms to move.
The things I care about in to that good part and the things I don't
care about out in the thing.
So, Ergo in that example, if you if that was the only thing, your
compressor, good.
You now have a much harder time with something say that.
Well, I don't know.
Is there anything that is like this anything that awesome concerning
you're going to not do well.
Okay, yeah, I mean compression sort of bean bagging in that way, as
you try to push in the places that you care about it, bulges out and
other places and I hope it's in the corner.
Okay?
Yeah yeah, I mean that's General process.
Wouldn't do like any sort of compression task is you initially start
out with a stream that has lots of discernible structure and it's like
that
You just kind of hammer away at.
And as you do more and more like you have the scream of like this is
like the structure he extracted and that gives you that structured
data.
And then there's the rest and like these residuals like, basically.
Like at some point you have this dense, neutron star completely random
looking data.
I suggest, like, that's all the stuff that just doesn't match any
prediction and like that's random, like in a fairly strong
mathematical sense.
And so like, if you run Randomness tests on this like statistically
random,
Various as we use for random number generator, that's what that is.
It is literally random, like it's unpredictable because whatever this
latter was you, it's just like, that's all the stuff that didn't match
any predictions you could make.
I see, that's the stuff that is really random in the end.
So in some sense, you could say, after you are done with your
compressor and you want to know if you found the smallest possible,
you know thing here you would send it to a cryptographer and if they
can figure out anything about it,
It, you didn't do as good as you thought.
That's correct.
Yeah.
All right.
So do try to move on from there are certain?
Yeah, I was just, I mean, it's since this is about learning a little
bit of compression that having that separation between prediction.
And then the cleanup is, is part of how you get a foothold in this
stuff.
Especially when you start looking at this in general, you're kind of
stepping into, you know, a hundred years of thought about this stuff
so it's a way to like because there is a way there.
Can move into this slowly it's not magic.
Like you know, the joke of all kinds of stuff is when you need
something to be esoteric and magic in a TV show or any fictional
setting.
It's either compression or cryptography and those are and these are
things.
You can you you can do the work yourself to.
I thought, usually physics like is like Quantum, whatever.
Okay, everybody's friends turned off, if you could just write whatever
we want to it from there.
Yeah, just need some fancy equations on
Aboard and exactly like you say this is quantum something.
So like why it's like this is an accounting equation of what are you
doing?
His will see, that's why it's very good but I don't know any content
math because this way I can still enjoy the blackboards and TV shows.
All right, so the next thing that you had on your list there was
science versus art.
Oh and I guess I have a fairly good idea.
Probably what you're talking about whether but yeah I don't use laser
and this is a
more hand wavy but it's kind of interesting and I find it fun to think
about which is just
like I say most general purpose data compresses are based on an LZ
style algorithm.
Well the ones he used they've definitely want.
Yeah just lots of really really weird stuff.
Yeah we're talking about stuff that works at amazing rates of tens of
kilobytes per second write that compresses way better than anything
you've ever used and he won't do the shit.
You will love.
Yeah.
But but it exists in the the ones that you use in practice are all
based on this, these
Accessing things and then, but we have made big strides in compression
over that period of time too.
And a lot of that is kind of the, you know, I joke that you know the
how good a compressor is really is, how long people get to fiddle with
it.
Like how many things they can try?
How many think?
How many experiments can you run in a given time?
Because you always have as some point you have to ship but a lot of
this is the time you take the amount of data sets you have and the
things you're thinking
Talking about and in, even now, like, will find surprising things.
I like a lot of, you know, even as recently as beginning to your
Charles would discover things in his own algorithms like, oh, hey,
there's a parse here that I had not anticipated.
Should we mention the fact that the reason why we don't have all three
people who work on depression at Brad is because Charles isn't Hawaii
to us, is in Hawaii.
Yeah we are we are in the rain here.
He's in Hawaii.
That's
Right.
Laughing at us.
He's watching the stream on a beach.
Yeah, I think I might be going know.
Okay, so it's wrong.
Your he forfeits his right to tell you that.
You said something right on, guys, not here.
I'm sure he will blog about it.
Yeah, okay.
That's a yes,
Those of you don't know who Jeff is for, don't go to Charles.
This blog was Charles blue, who is, who is another compression guy,
who become complicit as his therapist log.
So if that's not, it's a public service show, okay?
Yes.
So anyway, continue with what you were saying.
So you said Charles found things in his own algorithm.
Yeah.
Like we had a fairly Lumpy
Mystical compressor, I'm sorry.
Lumpy oh, I call it.
That, that's not a thing.
Well, you don't think so, there's a Continuum from things the that I
call them, lumpy compressors, but they're things like, lz4 where you
are doing fairly big symbols, you're sending nibbles or you're sending
B.
In this case, Charles was sending full B.
Okay, not doing individual bit packing stuff.
Doing encoding big things because then your ride a bike faster than
you can pack words together and slide it over and shipped them in
Doraemon all that.
So the really fast and coders or decoders like lz4 and stuff are like
make some concessions to compression by not going quite as high a bit
packing.
So that's and the most that's like all those lumpy then.
There's no I just I just get, could I just want to get a little curve
cushion there?
Because when you say bit packing, I want to make sure I know what
you're talking about.
Are you talking about packing?
Because I've seen your not talk about packing bits on the output side.
Remember,
The splitting up of bits on the input side, on the output side.
So you can give me a little more because I'm not sure I understood
that, exactly.
Okay, so packing, what's an easy way?
I'm going to be 77 the way these compressors work at the very concept,
very high conceptual level is you are about to decode a bite or that
symbol.
And you look at a bit and it says I am going to send you a literal,
which is the bite that was in the input stream and just going to send
it to you, okay?
I might encode it, but I'm going to send you that or it's a thing that
says I want you to look backwards in the Stream at this offset and
this length and copy that data in your straight, right.
Okay.
So if you are going back and forth on a single bit, on every symbol
you have a, that has a lot of ramifications in terms of Branch
prediction, and then speed, and all this.
So what Elysee for in and other people do and even even earlier,
oppressiveness certainly, but whales
For really, really leaned on.
It was saying that.
All right, well, I'm going to encode like in.
This isn't exactly what the, but like, I'm going to encode for of
those literal Flags in a in a nibble.
And then do, okay.
So we're like you can see things of like or I'm going to try to get
more out of each little symbol that I'm pulling out of the stream so I
can do some more stuff for Speed purpose.
So as a general rule, if you're just outputting a variable number of
bits at each step, then you just need to, like, read everything with
get bits, and you need to keep track of
You are the middle of a bite and so on, that's very complicated, very
complicated.
It's like five construct.
Yes but it's complicated compared to just getting a bite, right?
So the really fast compressors tried to not have any complicated
unpacking work as much as they can.
They just tried to like oh look at this B, do this next, jump into at
a maybe doing a end like do an addition but that's about the size of
it.
Like don't try to keep track of the state in the bit but for whatever
just don't do any of that I see and so
Basically what you're saying is okay, I have this decompressor, it's
reading sort of a hybrid command data stream, right?
Because it's sort of, you know, it although it's all data some of it
is telling it sort of what to do and some of it is telling it what to
do it with you upright.
And so that is a, you know, you sort of created a new compression
problem for yourself, inside your old compression problem, which is, I
now need to figure out how to most efficiently.
Encode the way that the compressor is supposed to be working, and now
you are running the same problems by the way.
You're starting to like every compression scheme as you add more of
these methods like ways of prediction.
Like, that's one way that, for example, rich goldrich just like author
of crunch and like, as written LT happened.
A couple other things.
So, another comparison guide, be now like he thinks to tend to think
of this as basically like specifying a VM.
Okay.
Decompressor has like this set of commands that can do.
Yes.
And like, it tries to like, this is a compact encoding for telling the
decompressor what to do, right?
I like he is thinking of it in terms of Lego, I've read this virtual
machine and I have to
basically write this compiler that generates code that the decoder VM
then runs to reconstruct the data I want, right?
That's another way of thinking about it.
Although unlike a traditional compiler, you now care very much about
the executable size.
Whereas, maybe before your trade-offs were here, you compilers that go
in that direction, certain the stuff will go even standard compilers,
you know, have this option but I mean, this is critical for this kind
of compiler at that.
I mean, that there's the specialized language was there's compilers
that really go towards.
Like, if we say,
Optimization on a c compiler.
That's a very hand wavy thing.
Yes.
Because like Optimal is really not very well defined.
There's more application specific languages and stuff for, like,
compiler for say, finite State machines and Hardware.
That when they say optimal, they mean optimal as and like there
literally is no better solution for the problem as specified in this
form actually.
And there's all this is continuing between, okay?
So thank compiler in that sense, got it.
Okay, sorry, so control shoe anyway.
So bit packing.
You back.
Okay.
Charles was looking at things from how he was.
Yeah, absolutely so much for the.
So you have these, you know that lumpiness, then you have Huffman,
which is now pushing bits together, which is still lumpy but less
lumpy and then you have arithmetic, which is partially bit eating, but
there's a spectrum of like, how this stuff stored.
Anyway, in the wrong woman Roberts lumpiness in the mountainous scale.
Yes.
So so one of our encoders operates on B and and
It's very lumpy and it was in January where Charles was like just came
back and said, hey I'm getting a lot more compression, I'm a lot
faster and it was just changing the way he thought about the par.
So there's okay and we think there is in trouble specific things.
There's are there but this by the way, good moment to introduce what a
parcel is.
Yeah, like this LV thing like LZ is just literally about looking for
string matches.
Like you look like, oh, I have this string of whatever 5 b, and I
already saw that early and you just coded
Reference to where that might be just the position or it's usually an
offset from the current position.
So like whatever 4 KB back I saw this, yes, or you have more
sophisticated thing where like maybe the decoder keeps track of next,
plus a dictionary like this other ways to coat that?
Yeah, that's the basic idea.
So this little parsley.
Yes.
Was like, if you have say the work, the in English text, you've seen
that work more than once in a document of any size like this, lots of
possible ways to encode the word, the, with a back reference, right?
And these have different
Right?
If you use the one that was in the sentence sentence, right?
Before versus the one that you saw, like five Wikipedia Pages back.
Yes, like, they're a different distance from you.
And the short distances usually make shorter code.
So you have multiple ways of expressing the exact same data that have
different costs this LZ Parts thing is about looking at all the
variance, you have of saying the same thing and trying to choose the
option
That is best.
I, so there's different ways of thinking coding this thing and like,
oh, like, if I do this, like, if I include this reference to the here,
like it's just, the three letters, th e, but the word that I'm
actually trying to encode here.
So we're thespian.
I said, like thespian we had like a bit while ago but like it's a much
longer match.
Like even though the three letters I see here I could do immediately
if I just write a song.
Longer law, offset and like, look a bit further ago, I can quit a lot
more letters and it's worthwhile.
I see.
So it's all about looking at these different ways of encoding, the
same thing, and trying to decide which option you want to take.
So the free is not just for then, not just for size, which is usually
what you do.
But you might, you might have two things that even you have two
choices that are the same size and encode it, but one might decode
with faster because like, oh, it's aligned or it's right, or it's
close or it's, you did that.
So there's a lot.
Lot of hard problems there.
So sign that is right there.
I think there's a lot of air in Parsons.
Like, I think people will - like, if you're looking at it from a
statistical modeling point of view, the fact that you have multiple
ways to say the same thing, it's just bad.
It's a bug.
Okay?
From that point of view is like, you shouldn't be like, right?
That just means that the probability for these letters being phe
should be higher or lower than it.
Currently is like the fact that you have multiple ways of saying, that
means that you're under estimating the probability.
If you did that, right?
That wouldn't be the case if would be baked into the model, right?
I'm sorry.
So I feel like that's one of those things that when you set it, I'm
like, yes but then if I think about it I'm like I am not actually
prepared to re-explain that to anyone because it's a little slippery,
right?
Because it's like okay what do you mean by getting the probabilities?
Right?
Because in LCD, it's a dictionary thing.
So you're saying that that just inherently cant encode, this concept
correctly.
The dictionary thing is like it's a constraint thing and like the fact
that there's multiple possible and Coatings for the same thing,
If you look at it as a Markov model, if you do a full-on statistical
modeling at each step, I'm going to Crunch the numbers that get the
Eggheads to figure out what the exact probability of the next letter
is okay.
I like encode that properly.
If you were to do that, this ambiguity would not exist.
You have the model.
The model says, this is a prediction and, like, you would work with
that, okay?
But thank you.
Why would they be multiple ways of saying the same thing?
That's inherently wasteful.
If you think about it, in terms of like, going back to the way
beginning,
Why?
Yes, you have like, these things of list of things you can say and
you're mapping these to a different set like having two things in this
set in the smaller set that say the same thing means says really
wasted B, because these two things expand to the same thing.
So that's a redundancy here that we could exploit right because there
were these are things that I could have encoded.
That both would have yielded.
The same result that just fundamentally means I wasted a bit exactly.
Okay.
So and with LZ like that's a lot of bits like this, a lot of
variability.
Same with MPEG,
MPEG has all these motion vectors and so on, these are not very well
specified at all.
There's even as inside a frame, there's ice.
I will say, billions, just be aware that this is wrong at the exponent
by, like, okay, factor of, like, it's like Brilliance is way too
little, okay?
There's some like, 10 to the 40 or so different options of coding, a
single and pack frame.
Okay?
Are meaningfully clothes and cost and so on, okay to what you were
that there's it's ridiculous, right?
This is there like
There's thousands of bites and I'd are tons of decisions.
You make that you really can't justify other than this is what the
heuristics told me, okay?
If you were to leave and get into the next frame, which might be
referencing that ones you might make a worse decision, a better
decision on this Frame, that hurts you in the law.
So, we get a time.
I just want to make sure I know where we are.
1050, 1050 Decay profile.
So, sorry, you just have a lot of.
Should we start talking faster and compress the spring.
I just wanted to give you guys because this
Need to make this even density, it ends at 11:15.
So I want to make sure you guys know you're kind of coming up here
last 25 minutes and I don't I don't want you to miss anything you
really want so no keep going.
Yeah so the whole thing there's all these codecs that in practice like
they have this massive amount of redundancy we can express the same
thing and lots of different ways and from a purely compression if you
care about the minimum size thing, that's a waste, actually turns out.
We actually like having that kind of redundancy for different reasons.
Okay, one reason is
That we might want to write a fast encoder that will never produce be
able to produce most encodings because like all that subtle subtle
stuff with a, the versus thespian.
It's of it just never even consider those just go back.
We just we just do the first thing we come up with just roll with it.
This is your example of the TV to live TV.
Compressor, it's like, look, we just need something that's gonna spit
out.
Exactly stream.
It's just gotta be close enough.
Exactly if your Facebook whatever, serving like, you press documents,
you don't care about the squeezing out the last five fights, right?
If that's gonna make
Mean you spent like another CPU second of time?
That's pretty ridiculous.
You don't care, okay?
But you would rather this endless fights than more, but you're not
willing to spend infinite amounts of CPU time on.
Okay fact, you're not even willing to spend a lot of CPU time.
Just like you have very limited budget.
You might have things like, oh, because the way I encode, these things
as kind of heuristic, I might want to have including is in there that
I'm never going to use ever, but are useful as stepping stones from
From a to c because that having that baby step in between, if I if I
can go from here to here to here and my optimization thing is kind of
local where it changes from A to B and then B to C.
And I would never try a to see directly.
It can be useful to have intermediate steps in that encoding.
The even though you're not going to use, make it easier to find the
things that you do want to use and you're talking about this from the
standpoint of the encoder.
Yeah, meaning the decoder can't even read this intermediate
conceptualization.
I might be using might be a thing that the decoder can
Repost like if you look at it like on the whole we never ending.
He was never a good idea, neither care about this thing or this thing.
And in one case a is the best.
In one Cassius, the best and be never really make sense, but having
that thing in there as a potential thing, that the decoder engine just
getting from A to B that if you have this optimization that tries to
do incremental changes.
Yeah, be helpful.
Have having that in there very soon.
So what you're saying is essentially getting back to sort of the
optimal parse concept which if I could restate that because I think I
you guys
Sort of summed, it up there.
Yeah, we just I have a decoder.
It's got a specific spec.
I've got an encoder, and I want to basically produce the best possible
thing for the decoder, given some Metric, which could be, you know,
speed.
It could be size, it could be a combination of two.
Could be anything, who knows what the optimal parse is the thing that
processes, the input data that, you know, picks those those choices
for the decoder among equivalent options that, that yields that
Best possible result.
And that often is a said, some incremental procedure.
So you start with some fast and coding, you just use it fast.
Encoder to get an initial estimate of salt bake.
This should be yes.
And then you try to make local changes of TECO.
If I do this and this and this I get from here to here with less cost
and that's worthwhile.
So it's like a permutation based search where we're sort of saying,
okay, we know this includes the frame.
Let's see what happens when I try this.
Now, I see that it got smaller or right.
Yeah.
And so that, you know, could you could do that.
I think the text, for example, I could start changing things in the
Stream and as it goes.
Yep.
Is it fair to characterize the thing?
You said earlier as being, that there is no such thing as a search for
an optimal parse.
If your compressor was perfect in the way you described before
meeting.
Yes.
Just there would only be one way to encode the data because we've
squeezed every last pot probability piece out of it.
So now the encoder is just direct.
It just takes a thing and it goes up.
There's only one way to encode.
This only one code, this, the really high end, but that never happens.
The really high-end statistical compressor.
Exactly like that.
Okay, they have a very complicated model that running.
The decoder has to do almost exactly the same work as the encoder
because they stay in shaping the same time there where something like
LZ like, you have to look like the LZ encoder has to look for all the
possible string matches has to decide which the best one is the
decoder says, like Okapi string from there this, many bytes, okay,
Jesse.
Yes, like LZ is an example for a very so called a symmetric scheme ice
which means that the decoder has very different workload from the
encoder.
So the encoder
All the string matching, it has to look at the pars has to do all this
trade-offs that makes us figure out what the red Huffman table to use
this way to put the split Point, blah, blah, blah, all these kinds of
things.
The secret of the says that, oh, here's the supplement table go.
Oh, copy that many bytes in size.
So, like, I see something like Zip takes, whatever couple is usually
something like five times or so faster to decode than it is to encode.
Yes.
And that can become arbitrarily large Reef.
You just let it keep your problem then.
If you don't use the lip that Google has this compressor.
For example, for the zip format called softly, okay, that's a heavily
optimizing zip, compressor.
Yes, that can take hours to compress it just tries.
It just tries lots of things that you can dial, how long you want to
wait and so on, but that's so stuff.
Like okay.
They have say the style sheet that they're serving for the Google main
homepage.
Yes.
If they gonna serve it to a billion people a day, right?
Like saving that one bite.
Might be worth it, right?
It's a thing.
Anything, they don't change that all that off, right?
Like letting that run for half an hour.
If they do change the mass, the style sheet or the JavaScript is not a
big deal for them actually but the 10 B they save doing so I mean it
just all adds up.
So would it be fair to say that something like an arithmetic encoder
right?
Which is sort of one of the statistical coder back-end ideas is would
it be fair to say that?
That is a like compression scheme that has in some sense been
Finished meaning.
We have now gotten to the point where for the definition of the
problem as we suspect it for this codec, we do not need to parse the
data because it is exactly perfect for the entropy that it's encoding.
Like it.
There is nothing left to bring out of its model or is that an unfair
characterization?
The arithmetic coding and like all the school things are just like you
have, these are very mathematical things.
Yes, is transformed in this, does that thing there's no degree of
Freedom there, right, there actually is tiny bit of freedom and
arithmetic coding.
Okay.
The way we usually a medical
Because, okay, there's you have to want to know if you do this.
Mathematical point of view, you just do this with exact big integer
arithmetic like, at some point.
You just deal with 2048 bit integers, Behavior, life, and practice.
We don't do that because that's horrid and slow.
Yes.
So, practice, we just say that gay limit the amount of numbers, we
deal with, to, like, 32 bits, or 64, bits or less, I see.
And that means that.
In some cases you'd like, we run out of precision.
And in that case, we just agree on a protocol for what the decoder
encoder do.
In that case, we just truncate the Precision I see that point you lose
a few bits and you have again like possible and Coatings that this
thing will never produce ice because you limited the Precision but
that's like very very small awesome.
Yeah.
Okay.
So so anyway, that the whole ART versus science a whole point of that
was that even among our own codex that we wrote, there are new ways to
him too.
Dump out stuff within that.
And that's kind of the that.
How long can you spend on this?
Do you discover these things?
And that's the thing that as a beginner isn't something you think
about you're just trying to get it working right?
Get to and you might iterate on trying to make something smaller.
But not even thinking about these big higher-order more complex things
that like hey the parse is like a huge part of your huge magic part
that happens that you kind of take and leave over yujin.
Since it is in general, it sounds like going to be sort of
Of a large search, kind of a problem.
Those are always kind of heuristically.
Yep.
Records of things intro.
And Charles says, like, I feel like there's, it's just an intuition.
I feel like there's this huge space and I feel like there's other
unexplored spaces, so they will find that someday.
All right?
Well, this will be better compression and a much higher cost for this
will be much faster with you.
All anyway, we do have some evidence for this.
Yeah, and that.
This is just an experiment like I accidentally nor less ran beginning
of the year, which was just like, oh, I looked at the file.
I was like, changed something in the encoding and suddenly the fog of
mass for the bigger as like what happened?
It's like, oh and then it prepend a single 0, B, in front of the file.
Now, it's 4K smaller.
What the hell?
Okay.
There's all kinds of like this, okay, this must be horrible book,
whatever that tried this with a couple other comparisons to have the
same effect.
Okay?
Always in the same direction mind but you add like a single button
front of the data stream is suddenly everything changes and it's like
Mass swings like 10, 20 KB, whatever, okay.
It's like huge stuff like for a one megabyte file is fairly
significant.
Yeah.
Right in compression terms like yes that's huge.
We would kill for like 20 kids.
Yes.
Yes certainly.
Oh, we made the input file bigger and it got semi and compression.
Impersonate, somebody
He space there that.
Yeah, a compression person is somebody who thinks that 20 bits has a
lot of data.
Yeah, it's a definition of.
Yeah, pretty much so after it's somebody
Thinks that perpetual motion is going to happen so that's those are
the compressions cranks, okay.
All right.
But you have that kind of thing and they that's just an artifact of
there, being all kinds of weird, State, and feedback loops, and these
encoders.
So yeah, just turns out I having that slightly different seed of
having that 10.
But they're just means that the starting conditions are slightly
different and it's weird cortical system.
There's feedback in there.
It just means that the search ends up in a very different
Place.
Yes.
And just changing that initial condition.
A tiny bit means you find very different solutions that are better or
worse.
Yes.
So it's very much unstable that since it sometimes, these searches do,
have a tendency to get stuck in local Maxima and yep, you can just
happen to do something that kicks it out of that and now all of a
sudden, you found a much better thing.
But there's a lot of really do not clear how to actually design it
warm that up, find that other than
You said designing very long running ones that do the standard kind of
like, you know, searching lots of different spaces and all.
But I mean, just not seeing that kind of stuff happen, but both you
and everybody else is compressors.
Just means like, there's no question that there is like a lot of air
left for compression values of a lot of are like we can get a whole
person.
Yeah.
Not a joke.
So I think we're getting closer to.
There's another interesting part.
Just oh yeah.
But they're getting pussy.
And just want to say let's let's uh, do anything that you
Guys, really want with this.
It just a yes really quickly.
I mean the funny thing about this is since the encoders for these
systems are very complicated and now they're getting more so all the
time and since the rule is you generate a file that can decode to the
same file that was given you an input, you can have bugs in there and
Charles's had bugs in there that were there for a long time because
they generated correct files.
Right?
Right and and it generated an okay Parts not the best parts and then
later on.
You find oh shit.
That level that waiting was wrong or this decision was wrong or
whatever, but it still works.
So even aside from the air in the car.
So you also have like these are incredibly complex systems and like
it's there's bugs and everything.
So do you generally I mean I guess it is it just the case that most of
the data you work with is simply too large to ever try to run.
Exhaustive searches on anyway, so you literally have nothing to
compare to you just run the thing.
It gets the size, it gets and you just really try to look at the total
size.
Talk about it.
Okay.
That's a magic way to like yeah.
But how it sounds like you never do.
You do we ever or do you?
We have like a noodle there.
Certain compression levels that exists that we don't even document
that because they're just too slow to use.
All right nobody wants to wait that long for like fractal later the
day exists and some of the encoding and some of the quarters and they
are literally just there basically as
Was for us.
So there is a sort of like, okay let's double-check Ken the like if
you know really long running one, does it get any better if it does?
It means maybe we could do a little better with your stick figure.
That kind thing to give you a little token.
That's like last year, Charles did a lot of work on one of the
compressors that was motivated by that are the things we actually ship
and tell people to use.
Had certain kinds of files where it was much worse than the way better
solution that we have lying around.
I see also ships but that we don't tell people to use and that because
it's just too slow to be practical.
I see because it runs at whatever 50 kilobits a second, right?
Nobody wants to wait that long.
Yes.
So we had that kind of thing.
We're just knew that there is a right way to do this, that will give
much better results typically yeah.
The only other thing, I don't know.
That might be fun to talk about.
Flee, depending on how much time is just talked about, kind of the
optimization of these modern decoders.
Because there's some interesting stuff there that I find fascinating.
Well, how much time do we have left?
And yeah, that's good question.
Just want to make sure minutes 10 minutes.
Alright, so yeah, ten minutes.
Okay, well so so one of the things it in and LZ compressor, you have
these very tight small Loops, they're very tiny or even a Huffman
decode, their very
'Well, stages, like there's four or five instructions and you can't
squeeze a lot of air out of four or five instructions.
You can go that you're already pretty tight, but in the modern stuff
that that Fabien and and Charles did they've done a bunch of things
that rely on really Advanced optimization techniques that are talked
about a lot of, like, exploiting how CPUs work nowadays, which is,
they aren't just running one instruction at a time.
They're doing a lot of wants and I could, you may want you want to
talk about like,
Streams of a half instruction level parallelism.
Yeah.
Yeah, the concept you think about a lot of parallelism but it's, you
know, there's that's four or five or six on a modern CPU and some CPUs
don't even have six cores.
So like there's a lot to explain in just instruction perilous so just
to make sure everyone knows what that is.
Because again like we don't do a lot of optimization on handmade hero.
Certainly not like any really aggressive stuff at this point.
So instruction level, parallelism, in fact why don't you guys if you
want to do it but basically just talking about hey a single
Of a CPU.
Just single-threaded has a number of sort of ports, it can use to
execute things and if you fill all of these ports you know very
efficiently you know with a little leak and it's not possible.
Yeah.
If you fill a good percentage of these ports on every cycle, then you
are going to get a lot more out of even the single threaded code.
If you are constantly waiting on one particular portfolio, is that
that's what we're talking about here.
Okay?
And what usually blocks these ports from being filled is
like, you have us instruction steam, that's dependent on stuff that
happens before, so it can't
Do the next instruction.
Tell that retires the old one and then you're like, all right.
Well, these are, but so because these are out-of-order processors were
talking out here.
So they are looking ahead to find something to execute, but when it
tries to look ahead, it sees all of the instructions in the window,
all depend on something that is currently blocked and then all of your
ports stops as you can imagine with compressed with a with stream, you
can't decode the next thing till you got this one.
Awesome.
So the basic thing is like, if you have running a regular Loop,
whatever for I equals 1 and I 2 n.
They just kind of thing.
We're so gonna run out of room.
I like that.
You put the bracket on the in the thing with XVI.
Right?
Yeah.
And this does a thing the whole point of this in out of order
processor like these different implications of do things like you can
start do thing of x0 but the process just looks ahead like, oh I'm
going.
This, probably with X1 X2, X3 X4, just keep going ahead.
Like do thing like
as maybe this thing where they have to do a, then I have to do be
And then I have to do see it, right?
And these all take some amount of time.
Okay.
I like this might be in completely serial execution, like oh, like
multiply this by three at to whatever don't care, something like this,
like some computation, the trick is like, in out of order processor.
Like if you have like this as 4, x 0,
I like this use some on resources that there's a lot of weight here.
Right?
Sure.
And then you can also do like, okay, for X of 1,
I can just start executing that, pretty much as soon as I see this
Loop the processor can go like, oh, I'm going to run this facts of one
as well.
At least the things that well that might be wrong, but it just forces
on ahead, right?
And it's like, okay, like this because the loop is large, that's
probably at least if you cared about the speed of it probably large.
So you're, you know, as I'd like and then like the next execution is
going to be like this, and like you have this chain again, ABC, like
that keeps going before.
This is even finished and then exercise to can also start
Whoops, this is terrible.
Before any of that is finished and so forth.
So like the you have this weird Cascade where they can all start going
in parallel because fundamentally this do thing here happens to be
some operation where there's no dependence between what happens for x0
X1 and X2, right?
These can all run in parallel and I do okay.
If the loop has that shape, the problem in most compressor compresses,
is that everything has this shape.
A then B then C.
Okay.
It's the entire way through had this.
Like if you don't really what you're saying is that see kind of Loops
back up to the next a if we exactly Arrow there.
Like, we have.
So it's all just one big days.
Exactly.
And like then he has this big daisy chain wear this
An instruction going at a time.
It is terrible, right?
The problem with something like Huffman coding is that okay?
You have you're looking at a certain number of bits whatever and you
looking at the bit stream, trying to figure out how, how long that
code even is because they're variable length, and you can tell that by
looking at the data.
So you first figure out how long they could is then, you know, how
many bits to remove from the bitstream, and after that, you can start
decoding
The next thing, right?
Like after use this code at this thing, there may be other things, you
do that.
Go off on the side that are not in the dependency chain, right?
And like, those can just fill in the blanks, right?
But most of the stuff you do is just like, okay, this is my current
value.
How long is this code?
Yes.
Remove these bits from the bit stream and then I can start the next
value.
So basically everyone will always block on that step.
So you can't ever start the next thing you might want to do exactly
because like, there's don't even have the bits for this.
Just this long chain of like, look at the code figure out the
Remove those bits.
Look at the code, figure out the length.
Like, that's so there's only so much optimization can do their, you
squeeze those few instructions, and right, right?
And we do, those are all handsome, a b, and c can get as fast as a b
and c, possibly can, but they're never gonna laugh at the next day,
but, yeah, in the comedy career example.
Like, on one of the CPUs, this is literally three instructions, right?
Okay.
Like literally, okay, so there's that, see, entirety quarter.
There's just nothing else to do there, okay?
Like three instructions provide but these are all dependent on each
other.
Yeah.
So your life sucks.
This is nothing you can do there unless you like, in a regular Loop.
The CPU looks at this kind of shape, of thing, you're doing.
I know it's like, oh, I do X of 1, x, 0, x, 1 x sub 2.
And these are all independent.
I can just do them in parallel.
The CPU just does all that for you.
If you have this kind of problem and it happens to be cereal, like the
CP there is an actual serial dependency, from here, to here.
Yeah, right.
Like that is not imaginary like that has to be respected if the
program is written with way.
Yes.
So if this can be done in parallel then he have to help the CPU by
writing a different program that has some parallelism.
Okay?
So in this case it's like okay well there's an actual dependency chain
here that I'm going to do three streams
Right?
We're just have like stream 0 has ABC ABC, and then stream one has one
ABC ABC.
So you're still coding symbols, you're just there just and there's
multiple ones completely different streams in it within each stream
their cereal but you're pulling symbols out of each one I say.
Yeah and you can go to pretty crazy lengths to where what we have six
streams in some of our stuff.
So basically what you do is you say all right we want to try and get
the instruction level parallelism up.
Yep.
We know we can't make this thing any less.
Cereal as an encoding because the whole point of the Huffman is to
make it so that is cereal because anything we do that, makes it less
cereal would waste B.
Yes.
So, let's just do more Huffman's, break the stream into multiple
Huffman's and do them all at once that way, you just get, however,
much structural column as one stream grabbing a simple off another
grabbing a number there.
So it looks like I see.
It looks like you're unrolling a loop, but you're actually unrolling
it in its
Really stinks.
It's six Loops running in parallel, right?
Yes.
And that gives you.
Those are links to write R and S Y6.
It happens that this Loop like this critical path here.
This part A beans and see like, it just happens in this case.
Like why is its extremes?
Because this year happens to take six cycles.
That has a shape that can start every cycle.
I see.
So you need six streams.
So this whole thing works out, it's just and the thing is like,
there's other things you can do that go.
Of along a similar vein where to go.
I can do this using Cindy operations and do four streams at a time
they have the same problem like, oh the simply stop also has a Slayton
season.
These latencies are actually larger.
They're worse, right?
Right.
Yes.
So, with send me stuff, it's actually like you can do the same thing
but the parallelism stuff doesn't go away, right?
You can also do that on top of the vicinity so you know that okay you
do 8 W mg of these and it turns out the last sees, get worse.
So you need eight streams of 8 W?
MD like you can totally
We do that.
We have actually for Huffman's.
Yes.
You would have 64 Huffman.
So that's a lot of overhead.
Yes, walk down on a single stream.
Yes.
But you could totally do that.
I said.
So there's a lot of air left that kind of thing.
But it's just having to have these streams to begin with just means
you have to invest upfront.
And like having these extremes means you need to Signal more stuff in
the encoder.
At the very least, you need to make sure like each of these streams
needs to be
So, if you take arbitrary data from the network or from disc, you need
to check that.
There's no buffer overflows, whatever that all needs to be safe, that
validation is per stream.
So having more streams means you do more of that work.
It means that you have more overhead since you need to denote in the
Stream that keeps the native 470.
Here's the data for someone, right?
Like all that stuff gets worse.
So you do have to make sure that this is actually what you want and
the decode speed isn't that also means that like you would rather like
this kind of scale,
Taylor thing, if you do it, where you have actual separate streams,
you can do something with that on every CPU, even if they don't have
good Cindy, if they can run multiple instructions.
At the same time, having more work is that you can do in the same unit
interval will help you on any CPU, that can, can execute instruction
that can start executing instructions faster than it, can complete
them.
Yeah, because there's most because you would Target stuff like memory
operations.
For example, like this load here, like pretty much.
Every major CPU can start a new low.
Operation every single clock cycle, but they take multiple clock
Cycles to complete.
Yes, which means these dependency chains are multiple cycles Long and
there's just gaps in there.
Even if it's not a CPU, that does multiple instructions at once.
If you can't, if it's, if you could do multiple instruction at once,
of course, it's even worse, right?
Because not only do you have this Gap during this Gap.
Like you could do three instruct, right?
Yes.
Instead of, so, you have a lot more waste.
So they do these kind of things is less about compression itself, but
just how bout week, modern ones are
So unfortunately, we are out of time.
That is all fantastic.
Thank you guys so much for being here.
That was at least Friday.
Rachel for me, hopefully for everyone else as well.
Thank you so much.