There we go.
Hello, everyone and welcome to handmade hero.
The show where we code to complete game live on Twitch.
No Engines new libraries.
This is designed to show the complete process of making a game from
start to finish with every single component and peace.
You know, talked about and shown how we develop it in detail.
And the reason for that is we don't presuppose what kind of a
programmer you are or what kind of thing you're building or what
you're interested in, we show everything.
So if you want to be an engine developer, we do that.
You want to be a gain of
/, we do that.
If you want to, you know, concern yourself, primarily with animation,
we do that.
We try to cover, absolutely everything.
It's sort of like the general generalists course, to game development
and right now we're on a particularly important part of the
programming, which is optimization.
It's the first time we sort of delved into how we make code run
faster, when it doesn't run fast enough and we did a bunch of work
last week and actually made quite a bit of an improvement to the speed
of things.
It's roughly about three times faster, I think
think now than it was when we started even though we haven't really
finished doing the optimizations that we had set out to do, we only
sort of introduced some of the concepts and showed how to do the first
basic part of it and so the more advanced part of it, it's coming a
little later.
But right now we have some some parts that we were trying to do Cindy
optimization to our teen and we have some parts of the routine that we
had not symbolized yet.
Because as I said last week, they are much more complicated to do in
Cindy compared to the
Is that we were doing.
And so what I wanted to start on today is showing you how to do those
more complicated things so that you can start to write the entire
routines and Cindy, not just the interior Math logic.
So that's what we're going to do today.
If you'd like to follow along at home, you can, of course, always
pre-order the game on handmade hero dot-org.
So if you've done that, please make sure you download the source code
and unpack day, 117 Source, zip.
Because that is what I am starting with today.
So, you'll be right in the right place.
If you start with that looks like,
I've already got one of these up.
I guess I did.
CLS that.
All right, so let's load up the code and let's take a look at exactly
what I am talking about.
Here, we have our new routine draw rectangle, hopefully quickly.
And you can see in here that we have done a bunch of Cindy
optimizations on this essentially.
And I'm saying that their optimizations is kind of a hard thing to
say, because it's a little ambiguous.
Yes, it did.
Make our code run a lot faster.
But actually, we didn't really think much about
About optimizing the code really.
All we're doing is we're taking our code for operating on one pixel at
a time and making it optimizes on four pixels at a time.
So it's almost just a translation if you will which is kind of it's
hard to think of it as an optimization.
Now, it happens to make things run a lot faster because operating on
four things at once it fast enough, any one thing it wants but it's
not quite the same as some other concepts of optimization, may think
of where you save some operations operations by, like, not doing
something that you didn't have to do, which
You know, an efficiency gain or reflect changing the way that you're
doing the math, to try to, you know, optimize how the processor is
doing its stuff like that.
We haven't really done anything like that but we're already getting
significantly faster just by doing this translation.
So in some sense, it is optimization just translating it from scalar,
C code to the simply intrinsics that were using
So what I'd like to do today is focus on one part that we have not 70
is now you remember this routine here.
Basically, all of the work is done in this interior Loop here and what
we've done is we symptom Sim deed almost everything except for the
part where we load in textiles and then the part where we write out
pixels, right?
And so what I'd like to do today is take a look at just this part here
where we write out the pixels because as you can see, we then
downshift very dramatic.
From doing everything for wide into doing things in an ugly Loop and
that's not the way we want to do it because we actually have the
option in 70 of doing this in a much smarter way.
So let's go ahead and do that.
Alright, so the first thing that I'm going to do to make it a little
easier on us to start with is I'm going to eliminate part of the
problem so that I can just talk about one of aspect of it and show you
how we're going to solve that and then later we'll
I'll show you.
I'll explain how to solve the rest of it, right?
So here we are.
I'm going to go ahead and comment out this should fill.
And what this is going to do is it's going to always draw to the
buffer even if it is outside the bounds of the, you know, of the
region that should actually have been filled and what you can see
Happening Here, is that depending on that alignment, depending on how
many of the four pixels spill over the edge of the operation, that
supposed to happen.
We get a nice old black bar there.
As we write out stuff that we actually should.
Not have been touching.
Okay.
Now that's totally fine.
Like I said, we will put that back in and fix that little bit later
but what I want to do is take out that aspect of it just for a second
so that you can concentrate on the different sort of the other part of
it, which is just this, right, right.
So what we want to do is we want to concentrate on just this one part
here where we write things out and we want to figure out how to do
that in non-scalar.
Because what we're doing right now is We're looping over this four
times and for each time
we're building out our pixel manually and we don't want to do that
anymore.
All right, so let's flip over to the Blackboard for a second and I'm
going to talk about what the strategy is for.
When you hit something like this, in some decode because this is
typically the part of the Sim decode, that is nastiest.
Okay, the part that we did before was always, I said and I said it
when we did this is much easier because as you can see it looks almost
exactly the same as the code did beforehand.
The only difference is we have changed the mathematical operators in C
into these intrinsic.
So if there is a
We changed it to a function called mul PS.
That just passes the two parameters and that is sufficient to tell the
compiler what to do and we just get our four wide operations happening
for free.
We literally didn't have to think about any of this and you saw when I
did it, it was pretty much a wrote translation.
Well, this part, especially if you've never done it before, but even
if you have, if you're not particularly facile with it, this part is
not a wrote translation.
It's much more difficult than that, because you have to start thinking
about the Cindy lanes and where they go.
So, if you think about what happens,
we have something coming down, are the pipeline, right?
Which looks like this, okay?
It is a sort of a set, you know, Cindy register or a Cindy value, we
should say.
We have a SIM devalue, its 128 bits long.
All right, so this is 128 bits.
Each of these is 32 bits, right?
So, it's, it's 32 times for 128 bits long, right?
And each of these is a 32-bit floating point value.
So we
For 32-bit floating Point values and it's like red.
Zero red one, red to Red 3 in our Cindy, right?
And then we're going to have one of these for each of the channels
that we might need to write out, right?
So we also have, you know, a 4 wide one of G's, right?
We've got a 4 wide one of bees and a for y1 of A's, okay?
And you can see those in the code.
They're right here.
We actually have them.
Exactly Blended are Blended, G Blended, be Blended a right.
So you already see
Us having these.
But remember each one of these is for pixels worth.
Now, our problem is that the destination does not look like this at,
all right?
What the destination in memory order looks like, right?
Is R 0, g 0, B 0, a 0 or 1 g.
1 b, 1 a 1, right?
And so on, these are 8 Bits, right?
So each of these is 8 Bits, long 888, right?
88 and so on now what
Notice is we have the same number of actual bits total in flight, so
that's fine.
We have 128 bits of r128 of G, 128 of be and 128 of a, right?
So overall we have four times 128 bits.
Yeah, so that's all fine, right?
When we convert these, we know that.
Each one of them is going to be Smackdown from 32 bits right down to
eight.
It's so this is going to become an 8-bit value, right?
So our for by 128, effectively becomes a, and I guess this is, this is
a little bit misleading.
I should, I should probably write it differently.
It's not really, for by 128.
It's sort of 4 by 4 by 32, right?
So our 32 is going to go 32-bit float, is going to become eight.
And what we have down here is exactly the same thing, right?
We have four of these wide, right?
Four pixels.
This is pixel.
0, pixel, one pixel to pixel three, right?
So if four of these wide, each one of them has four components.
Each one of them has 8 Bits.
So once we do our conversion from 32 bit floating point two, eight
bit, we will have the exact same number of bits total.
So, we're not talking about doing anything where you have to increase
amplifier, or sort of change the total amount of data.
We have, we have the right amount of data.
The problem is that it's simply in the wrong format and the wrong
interleaving.
Okay?
So what we want to do, if we were to look at how this would actually
be loaded, right?
So remember this is memory order.
This is in memory.
So this is the zero with B.
This would be like B 0.
This would be b 1 b, 2, B, 3, B, 4 B, 5, b, 6, B 7, right?
And so here is our, our GBA rgba of all the different components,
right?
And so how many bits wide is this actual guy, right?
Well, this guy is going to be, like I said, four times, four times
eight, right?
And for it.
4 times.
8 is 16 times 8, right?
Which unfortunately as we can see up here, when we had our four times
128, write the actual amount that we're writing out is going to be
smaller than the amount that's coming in.
But again, it doesn't really necessarily matter.
As long as we can do that conversion from 32-bit float down to eight
but it's all fine.
So, that's not really that big of a deal, all right.
So how big is four times four times eight?
Right, how big is is 16 times 8, right?
Well, 16 times 8 is 128, right?
It's one of these registers.
It's the size of one register, and you can imagine why that is.
Because in each one of these 32, 32 bit floating Point values here, we
could have imagined fitting for 8-bit values, right?
Because 32 is 4 times 8, so we can imagine segmenting this
Mr.
Up into four pieces and storing them that way, right?
So if we look in memory and this is our frame, buffer rgba rgba, rgba
rgba for four pixels.
If we imagine what happens when we load that into an Intel register,
right?
If we were to load this sort of this aspect of the frame buffer, if we
were to load this piece of the frame buffer into one of the registers?
Well, we would, you know, it's a until little-endian.
An ordering, right?
So it would take the first date and it would put it here.
It would take the next date and it would put it here, right?
And so on and we would get a register that looks like this.
Right.
This is what we would see.
Does that make sense?
Hopefully, that makes sense to everyone.
So this is what it looks like in memory is zeroth.
B, blah, blah, blah.
But again, Intel loads.
This is what little-endian means.
We talked about this long ago, right?
Little endian means.
When you start reading from memory, it goes into the least significant
portion of the register, right?
So it loads it in here and then continues for words.
What this means is that if we wanted to prepare a register for writing
out right to the
To the frame buffer.
If we wanted to write out one sim deregister, we would want it to look
like this or a 0.
G 0, B 0, a 0, r, 1 g, 1 b, 1 a 1, R 2, g 2, right?
That's what we'd want to look like.
Because if we had it like that, we just store that register directly
to the memory and that would do it, right?
We wouldn't need this Loop anymore.
We would just have one one giant store, right?
We could just say, you know, whatever the pixel is, we could sort of
say, you know,
And that's am one 28, right?
We could just say that equals, you know, whatever the thing is that
we've got whatever that value is that we produced whatever this thing
is.
We could just write it out and we wouldn't have to do this Loop
anymore.
We just write out the whole register.
All right, so if that's the case, really, what we're talking about
here, right?
Our problem is we have to figure out a way to essentially turn a four
registers each with like ours, gsb's and A's in them, we need to
figure out how to turn those into this style of register interleaved.
So we need to take something that's effectively rrrr, right?
Gggg bbbb, loops and a, a
We need to figure out how to turn that into something.
That's interleaved, right?
So we need to grab like one thing from each of the registers, okay?
And so, in order to do that, what I want to focus on first.
Let's just focus on this first.
Actually, this is, this is this is going to be probably the easiest
way to do it.
Then we'll take a look at doing a little bit differently later.
So let's talk about that isolated problem.
Let's just first talk about how would we do it?
So we could take for Cindy values that we're looking like this and
turn them into 470 values that look the other way, right?
That look interleaved, right?
So you want to do it this way, okay?
Now, remember this again, is the memory order, so really?
This is the kind of the annoying part of being on little endian
architectures.
Really, it doesn't look that way in the registers were really looking
at making it look like this, right?
And so on.
Right?
And I guess now that I think about it I should probably caveat this.
I'm actually I'm slightly wrong in what I'm saying?
These are windows frame buffers not like opengl texture so actually
they're not even this way.
I should caveat what I'm saying here in memory or
On Windows, we actually are be gra, right?
Because remember Windows has the weird thing where they swapped the
are in the G values, right for how the frame buffer was stored.
So really this is if it was a standard like opengl texture or
something like this, that's the order for that which is kind of where
my head was but that's not what we actually want.
So really we need to produce.
We need to take these and we need to produce until ordered stuff that
looks like B gr, right?
So this is inside the register.
It should look like this B gra, right?
Be gra, be gra, right?
So we want four registers that look like that.
So that's what we want.
Okay, so let's focus on that first.
So we have our Blended RGB and a here.
And what I want to do is make essentially rgba 0, 0 and rgba one and
rgba to and an rgba three.
Right?
That's what I want to do.
So that's the hard part, but once we get to that, you will notice that
there is actually not a lot there.
There actually isn't much more that we would have to do to finish
things off.
So maybe what we'll do.
Well let's let's do that first, let's just do it and we have to do
there's a couple things that we have to do essentially in order to
actually finish things off.
So we'll just we'll just do it.
All right, so let's open up the Intel intrinsic side again.
As we have relied on many times, which is Handy and what I want to
call your attention to.
Again, we're only using sse2 and SSE right now.
What I want to call your attention to is, is this odd?
Oddly named,
Set of functions called unpack now, they're called unpack because they
interleaf things.
And so if you were to unpack something with say a 0, Vector 0
register, it would expand it in the number of bytes that it takes up.
I'll show you what that means in a second here.
But if we take a look at say unpack, hi epi32.
Then what this does is it unpacks and there's, and there's two flavors
each of these.
You'll notice there's an unpacked high and for every unpack, hi, I'm
kind of getting in the way.
They're my heads, getting in the way for every unpack High.
There's also a nun a'course, wanting unpacked low.
Okay.
Now, what unpack high and unpacked low do is they take registers such
as these guys, right?
And if you call unpack higher, unpack low, and then what it does, is
it Target.
So, let's say I have my arse and my G's here, right?
And I've got 0, 0, 1, 2, 3 0, 1 2 3.
So let's say I have my arse in my, my cheese here.
If I was to do an unpack, there's two kinds unpack, low and unpack
high.
If I was to do it unpack low, what that would do is, it would pick
first one from the are
It would put that into the first slot, right?
Because remember, we've got four slots for 32-bit values, right?
It would take the 32 bit and put that in the first slot.
It would then take the G and put that in the second slot.
Then it would take the our and put that in the next slot and then it
would take the G and put that in the next slot, right?
So you can see that this does that interleaving operation that we want
it to do, right?
It kind of does that expansion.
It's getting closer to this format that we want over here.
And so, the reason there's a low and a high is because it to, it
depends, you know, there's only enough room for four values when we do
the unpack here.
So, it's going to use either this for, or this for it, the highwomen
done.
The corresponding thing, starting with this guy, it would have
produced our 2, g, 2 are 3 G3.
Right?
So the unpacks basically Target, a certain width.
In this case, 30
B and a certain higher low portion to do that kind of interleave,
right?
So what we want to do is we want to use these unpack operations to
take all this data and interleave it.
So we want to see it, look like this, right?
And there's a problem, which is that since the interleave can only be
between two things, right?
I'm only going to be able to interleave two things with an unpack
operation.
What that means is we're going to need more than one unpack.
Ation.
And the question is, how do we structure those unpack operations so
that we can actually do?
The unpack, the took to get this, this actual result.
Now, what you can see is if I actually Target Two values that need to
be next to each other, right?
So let's say, I wanted to concentrate on producing this GB, right?
Well, the GB.
If I want to just use the unpack 32-bit, right?
And I want to Target that GB.
Well, that's pretty easy right to produce that GB, okay?
Because if I've got a vector of G's, and I've got a vector of bees,
Like so right?
So there's my two Cindy registers.
If I do the interlude between these two, then what I can do is I can
just pick the first parameter to be the bee and the second parameter
to be the G.
And what that would produce is that would produce a b 0, g 0, right?
B.
1 g 1.
And then I could do the same thing with the high to get the other
one's right b2g to
B3, G 3.
And now I've successfully produced that bottom value, right?
Similarly, I could Target the A and are right if I have the A's.
Oops.
and the RS like so,
If I have a an RS, I can do the unpack, their the exact same way.
So that I can end up with a vector.
That's like our 0.
A 0 or 1, a 1.
R 2 a 2, R 3, a 3.
But what you'll notice is, when I go to now combine those results, I
want to produce something that's be gra.
What I find is this the second, the cascading unpack, the next unpack,
there is no way.
I can still use a 32-bit unpack to actually produce the vector that I
want right?
Which is a RGB, right?
Because
As whatever I do.
If I was to whoever I pick, I'm going to have a be right followed by
an R, which is not what I want, right?
Because going to pick one from this one, from this one, from this one
from this.
What I want to do is pick two from this and then to from this, and
that would give it to me, right?
If I if I had one that picked you from this into from this.
Now, there are unpack instructions that unpack wider, right?
I don't know if they actually included that in sse2.
They did, right?
So one way we could do it is we could use an unpack 64-bit, right?
And do the unpack that way, and then that would that would do it.
But what I wanted to show you is actually and this comes into play,
sometimes on when you have architecture that don't have multiple
widths of the unpacking or you want to do other stuff, we'll kind of
see things a little bit later.
Is that if we don't do it that way, if we instead mix the other two
values in the first step, we can actually just use this.
Same with to do all of our interleaving, right?
So let's say that.
Instead of doing it this way, right?
We actually do it slightly differently.
Let's say that instead, we mix the ours and the bees together, and the
A's, and the geez together, right?
So we pick B and our right?
So we end up with B 0, R 0, b 1 r 1, right?
We pick that first.
And then we pick the the the A's and the g.
So we have G 0, a 0 g, 1 a 1.
Okay.
Now if I wanted to do the mixing on these two, if I pick this as the
first parameter and this is the second parameter.
I get B 0.
G-- 0, right.
R 0 a 0.
Right?
That makes sense here.
Here here here.
And so what you can see is as long as you pick your mixing order
correctly, using a
Single with you can actually go ahead and do the complete Shuffle that
you actually wanted to do all with one type of instruction.
Now, is there any real reason for us to do that here necessarily not
necessarily, but it's an important thing to understand how these
shuttles kind of work like that.
It's just an important thing to sort of think about because you know,
When you start working with these things and you never worked with
them before stuff, like that may not be clear to you, right?
It may not be clear that you can always get the shuffle you want by
picking the order properly.
So I'm going to show how to do it that way.
Just first, and I guess I already sort of did, so you can see what we
essentially said.
We needed to do one unpack with bees and ours, one unpack with G's in
days and then we need to unpack the result.
So let's just go ahead and do that.
Not very difficult.
But essentially what we have here right is, we've got that BR sorry.
I guess I should say, I'll name them in registered or register order.
So really what these are going to be just just so we can keep our
naming scheme.
Oops, are GB, so we can keep our name.
Scheme kind of clear here so that Anyone who reads the code knows
what's going on.
We'll keep them all in.
Register order, consistently throughout.
So we need to do here is produced the B 0, R 0, b 1 r, one vector,
right?
And so we're just going to say that exact thing.
This is r 1 b 1 or a 0 B 0, right?
And then the next one is the the a g, a g.
Like so right, hopefully, that makes some sense.
And then all I need to do here is do that that unpack
And again, these are both going to be low on packs because they're in
packing the 0 and 1's not the twos and threes.
So these are both going to be mmm, unpacked clothes and they're going
to unpack exactly what they said they were.
Now we have to double check because again, like I say, parameter order
is always a little weird in these things.
So I always have to check to make sure.
I know which one it's considering the low.
So the a in this case, right?
Sorry.
This is unpack.
Hi, they're the same parameter.
But with look lift least read the correct one.
So
Chloe pi32, right?
Just gonna
that in, at least type it incorrectly.
So unpack, low epi32 here.
what we need to do now, is just take a look at who actually is, is the
the person who goes in the low slot,
And let's see.
So that is
Do you words?
02:31 comes from Source.
One of course.
It's awesome that they they use a and then say Source One.
Alright well we'll assume that a is Source One for now.
So Source, One is low and since we want in low to be be will do it
this way, but we can step through the code and verify that, that's
true I suppose.
That seems like a reasonable thing to do.
And so we want be and are so there's be there's our and then here we
want G and a.
So there they go.
And for now I'm just going to get zero these out this and leave the
code running.
Otherwise as is opened, this is a force and mmm 128.
Sorry.
All right, so one of the things we have to address here which I did
not address, is the fact that again and this actually brings up a
point.
Fabien mentioned the other day to me.
So mm, 128.
I
Is of course, like I was saying when I first introduced this, it's
whether or not, it's treating it as integer or floating-point and
Fabien actually pointed out something that I did not know because I am
not, I don't really like, I've never had to really do any hardcore,
sse2 optimization to be honest with you.
Like I said, the only time I've ever really done super hardcore stuff,
was on the Xbox 360.
Which was not in any way essay.
What he said because I thought the mmm 128 I versus em, 128 was purely
a typing thing for see that the intrinsics introduced but it's not
quite, it's actually a hint to the compiler or a guide to the compiler
in terms of picking the instructions that you're trying to do.
Because it turns out that there actually is a different unit in the in
the CPU for doing the integer operations versus the ones.
That
The floating Point operations, and sometimes you will lose a cycle
here and there, if you move between the two types, so it is worth at
the limit and probably not in anything that we're doing, but if you
really care, it is worth paying attention at the limit to how often
you have to move between an M1 28.
And an M1 28i because it actually may not be free and Fabien said it
changes depending on the architecture as well.
It's just something to keep
Keep in mind, that's what Fabien said.
And he is usually right about these sorts of things.
So, what we need to do here is we just need to change the type of
this, and you can see that there is actually cast for this, right?
There's basically like a cast that converts one of the other, it's
called cast pssi 128.
And there's the same one, which is cast, cast, is I 128 PS?
So, basically, it's, it's free for us.
Sort of, at least namik, lecture wise to switch between these at any
time.
So, if we want to use integer instructions,
And we can do so right.
All right, so let's do the cast here.
We want.
We want this one, right?
Oops, sorry we want.
Where is it?
This one, right.
So we want to turn a floating point value into the integer value.
Like I said,
So let's go ahead and do that.
Let's do what it's Cass.
Pssi 128.
There we go.
And we'll do it here.
And again.
There we go.
All right.
So there we go.
And what you can see here, when I compile this, what I'm going to do,
I want to show you how this works.
What I'm going to do is again we've talked about structured art many
times before, what I'm going to do you do is use essentially
structured art here to make it easy for us to see.
This is almost like when you
Like a medical procedure and you inject, like radioactive dye in the
person to see where things are going.
We're going to do exactly that.
So what I'm going to do is I'm going to overwrite basically the the
stuff that's in these registers.
So I'm going to use a set PS, right?
Like so.
And what I want to do is I want to basically set it up so that it's
really trivial for us to see what's going on in the registers as we do
our shuttles.
So I'm going to do a set PS.
In fact, I think I might actually do it as a cast here as well, so
I'll do it this way where we actually.
I think I want to actually do it as a set epi.
sorry, my bravest banking asset Epi want to actually set basically a
What, what amounts to hexadecimal values because they'll be easy to
see in the debugger.
In fact, I guess I could even do this in a way.
That's, that's even a little chunkier than that.
What I could do is something like this, you know, the ours.
And they're going to basically be something that looks like a five
kind of.
Looks like an are maybe.
So I'm going to set this up to be like r0 R1 R2, R3, right?
You can kind of see.
The R value is like that, does that kind of?
Does that make any sense to anyone?
I feel like that's that's sort of makes makes at least some sense.
So I'm just going to do it that way to basically just make it really
clear where the values are.
And so I'm going to do that and then say eight RS 60.
So basically just going to load in those those
Small values into the RS and I want to do that with absolutely
everybody.
So I want to make, you know, basically, you know, a GS BS and an as
and the nice thing about that is the a is actually can be A's and the
B's can be B's, right?
It going through here, right?
And I guess since this is actually memory order here, now that I think
about it, I've actually got these guys not quite right.
Yeah.
Switching between memory order and register order is always kind of a
little bit of mental gymnastics.
Anyway.
Rectangle.
That's how I go.
There we go.
So yeah.
And also,
The geez again can't quite do it's unfortunate hexadecimal drops a
deaf.
I'm not sure what is a good thing that kind of looks like a gee.
Maybe see let's say it's almost a GU just you know it needs just a
little these that little extra curl at the end and then it would be
one maybe.
I don't know.
I think it's the best we're going to get so we're just have to accept
it for now.
Now, anyway and let's move that last rectangle.
Okay, so
Again, just finishing up here, making all these days, making all these
bees, making all these seas.
And those guys up top already 5S.
Last time, c, b, a b, c d.
Be a ABC.
It's almost The Alphabet Song and then each of these guys again, I'm
just going to override what's actually supposed to be in there.
So that I can use that as sort of our little radioactive tracer so we
can see what's going on and and just, you know, be sure of how the
sort of shuffling Works.
Alright, so
I guess it doesn't need.
This is in a race.
Yeah, so let's go ahead and set a breakpoint there.
I want to switch us back to debug mode for the moment, so that we
don't have the compiler doing anything at all.
I we want it to be completely, we want to completely stock, right?
So I'm going to get rid of that 02, should probably put the O2 at the
beginning.
So it's easy for us to change.
So that's the only parameter we ever modify.
Anyway.
so, coming in here,
I'm going to stop here and when we load those guys, in essentially,
what I want you to be able to see is when I go into the watch here and
I've got Blended are
oops, when dude are Blended e and dude be Blended a, is that if I want
to I don't actually
I love the way these guys get displayed to be honest with you because
it's hard to actually see exactly what the register value actually
does.
I don't know if there's a way to nowadays in Visual Studio give it
kind of an extended register thing but we can look at it in kind of a
couple different ways.
One way would be to just look at the M 128, u-32 value of it which you
can see has the values in there so that they're pretty easy for us to
see exactly where they are.
And again, this is just a little bit easier than trying to use at
least in my book is that then trying to actually use like one, two,
three or four, but that would be the other way.
It is if we try to use like, you know, some kind of number coded
thing.
So anyway, what I'm going to do is I'm going to tell the compiler to
just I'm excited.
Tell the debugger to just look at that value so we can see 128, you
32.
And so just on one line, we can see what's in that register right.
There, it is.
And and I guess I shouldn't say register.
Just that value, we don't know if it's in a register at the moment or
not.
Yeah.
Oops.
Right?
So there's our values and you can see, we've got our quote unquote,
our are quote, unquote G&R be an RA, and we've got the different ones
for different pixels.
So this is the zeroth pixel.
This is the first, the second, the third, right now, what we're going
to do is we're going to come in here and build our hybrid values.
So here is our 1 b 1 are 0 B 0, right?
And what we want to see
Because we want to see that value actually produced, right?
So let's let's do that here.
What is this?
What is this saying?
Sorry about that.
It's a 128, I right?
Of course.
Because since they had to yeah they had to rename the member.
Alright?
So now that we've produced this, we can actually see whether this is
what we've got.
And unfortunately, it's listing these now in memory order, of course,
again things it's always a struggle with the, with the little endian,
because you always have to remember, which order they're actually
doing things in.
But when they list things and see arrays, they always list them in
memory order.
So, we can't actually see the register by itself.
If we were to look at the register, of course, here is the register,
and you can see it in register order, which of course, is going the
other direction.
It's all fantastic, right?
That's just the way it goes.
But anyway, you can see
R that we got what we wanted.
Be zeros in the bottom are zeros in the next be ones, following that
in our ones following Matt.
And so again, I just all I did here was, I used the structured art
technique to make sure that we knew what we were actually doing,
right?
And especially when you're first working with these to get comforter
with them.
It helps to have very clear value because if these were just random
floating-point things, we'd be like, I don't know.
Okay.
Wait.
What was the Aragon?
It was point zero three nine five, or everything was zero so we can
Until what move where you never know, right.
And so, in this case, it's much easier.
Here we can see we did get our G zeros.
A zero, g one's a one's right, so we've got it.
And so, basically, all I've done there is just verified that we got
the exact unpack that we actually wanted, right?
And similarly I can go ahead and do this for any arbitrary number of
these.
But what I'm going to do is I'm just going to produce one final value
here.
I'm going to do the unpack low on these guys.
Choose me to unpack that zeroth pixel, right.
Like so so here's our 1 b 1 are 0 B 0 and here's
1 g 1, a 0, g 0, like so and similarly we could actually produce
number one here as well just by doing an unpack.
Hi, right?
So here we go and off we go.
So let's take a look at what we actually produced a RGB 0, right?
And you can see, if I take a look at the value that we produce their
after this next Shuffle, we got exactly what we want.
We got d, g are a, which is the memory order that we wanted, our gp1
and 128.
I use 32 same thing but now it's the first pixel.
So what we've essentially done here is produced to correct packed
pixel values unfortunately.
We still, quite haven't quite gotten to where we need to go, not just
because we haven't produced the rest of the values yet but also
because they're still in 32-bit floating-point, right?
But let's finish just so we can see exactly what's going on here.
What we would need to do essentially is unpack the High bits of these
guys, right?
And by unpacking the high B, what we do is we change from extracting
those low pixels to attracting the to high pixels and then we would do
exactly the same unpack here for two and
Really right.
That's it.
It's literally the exact same thing.
There you go.
And although it's kind of meticulous and fussy, really, there's not
much to it, you know, that's that's really all there is and if you
come through here, you can see.
Now we have actually produced all the pixel values that we actually
wanted.
The problem is that they are just in the wrong format.
They're still 32 bit float, but there they all are right.
There's the interleaved pixels, and off you go.
Now, you can see that already.
It's kind of annoying, like, look at how many instructions and took us
to do that.
It's kind of grumpy, right?
But that's just the way it goes.
Cindy, sometimes, when you have to take things that were in the nice,
70 format, you're working on, and shuffle them around, to put them off
into an interleaved source that is always kind of annoying and so you
can kind of see it happening here but we can you know, we might be
able to do some mitigation of that as you'll see as we go a little bit
forward.
So I'm going to leave the structured art stuff in here so you can see.
But now let's talk about the second part of this problem.
So you saw how we did interleaving, hopefully that's pretty clear.
Again, it's very fussy but it's pretty straightforward.
All we were doing is using one sort of set.
Get one pair of instructions, low and high unpack of 32-bit values to
do, basically that's wrestling in what we had to do is essentially to
produce four pixels.
We had to use eight unpacks, right?
That was that.
Alright, so now we have to talk about another thing which is how do we
generate values that are actually going to be what we needed them to
be, which is eight bits instead of 32 bit floating point.
And so, in order to do that, well, we've got some things that we can
just do, right?
We can certainly do a plus point five.
That's something that we know how to do, right?
We can certainly do a times 255.
So we know all these sorts of things.
So, you can see, we already are doing the time to T5 up here.
So, we've already converted it to that range.
So, all we really need to do to finish off, what was happening down
here, is to take that plus 0.5 and translate that up here, so that's
something we can just do, right?
That's something that we could have just added.
Add to this, right?
We could do an M&M, add PS.
So if we need to do that, we can.
But let's quickly take a look first to see at what's going to happen
when we need to actually produce integers instead of floats.
So what we have for that is there's conversion instructions.
You can see them here, they're called convert.
And so like, you can take a look here, convert PS epi32 convert
packed, single 32-bit, floating-point elements to pack, 32-bit
integers and store the result in dest, right?
And so that's exactly what we want to have happen.
This is the thing that we wanted we want to have a way to convert are
integers, but I miss our floating Point values are integers and you
can see that.
It's just it was a single instruction that does that, it's not
particularly difficult.
It's convert PS epi32.
So what we can do here is we can actually just do that, right?
We can make a one M&M 128, I, that's basically our into our, or
whatever we could call it, right?
And that's just going to be calling that intrinsic, mmm convert.
Yes, epi32 again that naming convention is basically.
PS is packed single.
Epi32 is extended packed.
Integer 32-bit right?
I believe is what that is?
I believe the he's for extended to be honest with you.
I don't think I've ever actually been told what it is.
I just I just assumed and so yeah, pack integers that are 32 bits wide
so that's what we're going to do here.
And again all we have to do is just do that to convert four of them at
once.
So we have this converting each of our
Going to take four of those instructions to convert each of our things
into integer, and there they are.
Right now, the question is, when it does that conversion, what
rounding mode is it using, is it using truncation?
Is it using round to nearest?
What's it doing?
Because if it's using round to nearest, then we don't need to add the
point five.
If it's using truncation, then we do, right?
And so we kind of need to know what the rounding is actually going to
be.
Now.
Unfortunately, there actually is no way to know
Know what the rounding mode is going to be, unless we set it because
the way that the SSE registers actually work for these operations is
they actually use a mode that says which way things should be rounded
and that mode can be set to any number of different rounding
methodologies.
So what I'm going to do here is I'm going to do set the rounding mode
to something known and we'll come back to that later for now, we'll
Justice.
I'm that it rounded in the way that we wanted to round, and we'll,
we'll deal with it a little bit later, right?
Because that's a separate a separate concern.
All right, so once we have these into integer format, we now have
another problem which is that there are 32 bits wide but we actually
want them to only we actually only want to use 8 Bits out of that,
right?
So what we want to do is we would like to be able to you know, get
these things together in some kind of a more useful fashion, right?
Okay, so we covered how to do it this way.
We covered how to do the interleaving if you were trying to delete the
things that float, but let's take a look at what happens if there if
we now have integers, right?
So we have integers and we know that those integers are going to be
eight bits because we clamped them already.
Right?
I believe, we already have a clamp in here.
You can see our min-max.
PS.
So we know they're between 0 and 1, and then we know it's Lima 255.
So we pretty much know what the integers are that are coming out of
here, right?
And the integers.
Oops.
Are going to be 32 bits wide, okay, but only the bottom eight bits are
going to be used so we're going to have 88 you know eight-eight like
so right.
So we're going to have you know, the ours looking like this R1 R2 R3
and then we're going to have the same thing happening.
Right.
With the geez g0 G1 G2 G3, right?
So if you look at these, we may write.
If you look at how these are lined up, we could because we know all of
these is zero, right?
All of this is 0 in here.
What we could do instead of doing the kind of interleave that we had
to do, if we were trying to produce them, actually, as floating point,
right?
What we could do instead is we could just shift up if we could move,
you know this this these 8 Bits to the next 8 Bits over.
Do you know to here?
We could then just or these registers together to produce the correct
values, right?
In other words, we could do this
Same ending and shifting operation, that we were doing here where we
shift them up, we could do the exact same thing for the wide
registers, right?
So let's see if we can't do it that way, I showed you how to do it one
way here.
And what we could have done here is I guess convert these these two
integers then pack them down or something.
But let's try doing it the other way.
All right, so I'm going to go ahead and if zero out this so, okay?
I'm going to get rid of
This.
There we go.
So if we've got these, let's see how we would do that.
Well, we know that we want the lowest
You to BB, right?
So if we were to do, we already know that we can basically do all of
our math Ops and you can see, actually I guess we haven't ever shown
this one.
So let me just show it here.
Okay, ma'am.
Or yes you can see that we have bitwise operations on these guys.
So if we want to we can go ahead and or in to, you know, values
together, right?
So all we would really need is the ability to shift them around.
Right?
We would, you know, we can order them together but we don't have any
way to shift them around.
So I can if I want to produce my outgoing pixel value, like my result
value or something like that, I don't know.
We'll call that.
Our out value.
I'm not sure we could go ahead and do that by putting together.
All of these things, right?
Like into our inch g into the and a like so on and just ordering them
all together.
But what we don't know, right is how to do the shifting, right?
So, we've got all these values, but we have absolutely no idea how we
would shift any of them.
Excuse me.
All right, did I do that right?
So this or this that or this that or this.
I don't need four ORS.
I only need three.
There we go.
So the problem is how do we actually shift these guys, right?
So what we want to do is we want to find some operations that actually
do shifting.
So I'm going to check the bit molybdenum it manipulation when here so
we can take a look at them.
Although I don't know why, it's not actually showing me anything.
I guess yoq shift I guess bit manipulation of something else.
So here's my shifts and what you can see about the shifts is,
unfortunately.
The shifts are all.
Oh wait, never mind.
I was about to say, unfortunately.
But that's not true.
We are not actually in
44 in anymore.
Sorry, I don't know where my head is tonight.
My bad.
So, that's fine.
So our shifts are or Lon s eyes, which is what we want.
And you can see here that we have a number of different options for
how we shift.
And what they are is they're what the width is of the shift, right?
So, what you can see, there is essentially like some of these things
like shift left and so on, what they will do, is they will clip when
they do the shift, based on the width that you say.
So, if you do a 32-bit one of these, if you do the EPA,
32 where it's talking about 32-bit wide, then B will shift up until
they hit here and then they will just shift out, right?
They won't cross this barrier where as if you were to use the 16-bit
wide version you would actually start clipping out on the
Bit.
So you shift up but when you hit the 16, you would stop, right?
So basically, what this does is it picks the compartment, the car, the
compartments for the shift and you'll notice there's other, there's
two kinds of shifters, for shift left, it's always logical.
But for shift, right?
There's two kinds logical in their arithmetic.
And what that is is just a quickly say, since we haven't ever covered
that in handmade hero when you're shifting values left, then the bits
that shift in, from this side are always zero, right?
So if I had some value, like 1, 1 1, right or whatever and I shift
that left, that I know that I'm always going to fill in the spots that
I shifted with zeros, but when you shift, right?
There's two things you could fill with.
So let's say, I have 1, 1, 1 0, 0, 0, 0, 0, or something like this.
And I want to shift it.
If I want to shift it that way, I could fill it in with zeros, right?
Or I could fill it in with whatever the high bit is.
So if the high bit is 1, I could fill it in with that.
So I'd get this.
Oops.
Instead.
Right?
And the reason they do that is because two's complement the way of
storing negative numbers, right?
Always has the high bit set if the number is negative.
And so, if you want to use a shift to a proximate dividing, if you
want to use like a divided by two to do the shift, you want to keep
the number - if it was - originally.
And so, the shift does that, that arithmetic shift.
That's why it's called an arithmetic instead of a logical shift
because it's for when you're doing arithmetic, that's what
Is we don't care about that at all right.
Now I just wanted to mention as an aside, okay?
So to get these things lined up, all I need to do is I need to do a
32-bit wide shifts that, I need to shift things up by 8, 16 or 24, the
same exact way that I was doing it down here.
So we're literally going to do an exact translation of this code,
right?
So the egg gets shifted up by 24, right?
So I'm just going to throw that in there.
Mmm, I want a shift left, logical.
And also, I should mention one more thing.
So there's two things here, shift left, logical immediate,
And shift left, logical, shift, left, logical, immediate shifts by a
fixed value shift left logical without the immediate shifts by another
register.
That tells it how to shift.
We don't need that right now, but you can see why that might be
something interesting, right?
Okay, so we're going to do the shift left immediate.
We need to shift the a up by 24, so, there it is.
We need to do the shift left, logical.
Oops, I forgot the Epi 3232, we need the sheet.
The shift left logical, immediate 32 cure for the be well, I guess we
don't the be stays in the bottom, right?
The be doesn't actually go anywhere.
So for the G we need to shift that up by 8 and for the are
Need to shift that up by 16, right?
And so now we're back to doing the exact same operations we were
before, right?
And and off we go.
Now, I should actually point out that or is Ann Ann's.
Don't actually care what the width is because the B get treated,
there's no movement.
So really, I believe it's just I believe the mnemonic for or is always
the same.
You don't actually need the epi32 or to say what the width is.
I think it's just si128 all the time.
That's my recollection.
Election anyway, let me see if I'm right about that.
Mmm or Hoops for.
Yeah, it's always si128 because you don't care.
If there's no, it doesn't move bits around or carry or add or any of
that stuff.
So it's always the same.
Right SLI.
Epi32 did I use the name wrong?
What I do there?
Give us give me my shift back.
SLI epi32.
Oh, I had an extra underscoring.
That's all right, so let's take a look at that out value.
Now, if I may here after we produce it here, Oops, stop it there.
So let's take a look at what that out value ended up being we have our
Oh, my bad.
I take it back.
We don't actually have our are structured art in there.
So what I want to do is I want to move the structure Dart up here so I
can actually overwrite these after their conversion.
So, what I want to do is I want to say that, you know, each of our
print, our energy, our in, to be inch, a are all going to be loaded
with those sort of faux values, if you will.
I guess, use integers.
We go.
Okay, so off we go.
and,
Let's see what we've got here.
So our out value
well, first, let's see what our interests are and so on values are
Got em, 128, you 32.
Okay, so each of these should be the correct values here.
No G.
P.
A Okay.
So we've got all the values that are what we think they should be
right?
And then we have our out.
Value .m 128, I utility to and let's see what it equals.
So that's is not what I wanted at all.
What is that?
What are those F's doing there?
It's not at all.
Correct, our bees are correct, right?
But our other
Values are not correct, and I'm not sure why, right?
So, let's, let's take a look at what?
I'm wonder if I wonder if I use the wrong thing here.
Let's see.
Shift factories just you know left by immediate 8 while shifting in
zeros and store results in dest, right?
And so oh oh!
Oh oh
Is that?
No, no, I can, that's fine.
I can shift as many as I wanted to.
So what was the problem here?
People, let's take a look at what happened here.
I want to see what the actual values are, so I'm going to break out
this routine a little bit further and then we're pretty much done.
So hopefully this will be like the last thing we do.
So, let's let's do our shifted values here, right?
She be an A and then I'm going to go ahead and just grab these guys
out of here, right?
Sargi, there's our pee.
And there's our, a SRS G be.
SI and so I should be able to expect these right and see what the what
the Oddity is there.
Let's go ahead and run that and so RS are.
Is as follows that is 0.
Well, I was hoarse by my own petard there, as they say, I forgot.
We're expecting these values to be in the range of 0 to 255.
So we were expecting these to already have been zeroed out.
So yes, my my test case was not, particularly well constructed admit
that.
So let's go ahead and try that one more time.
Let's see if we can't.
See if we can't get more reasonable results.
Yes.
So obviously the stuff coming out of this pipeline will all Willy's B8
B because we clamped it.
So we know that we've only got eight bits in each case.
All right.
There we go, much better.
So now if we do this, hoping
yeah, we will see our stuff, much more intelligently lined up and
there we go.
So there's be gra, be gra, be gra, be gra.
And so, as you can see, it's essentially, you know, I taught you how
to do the unpacked version, which is if you needed to interleave the
things as float.
But as you saw here in the case, where you don't have to interleave
them as float,
You can actually do it.
Much almost exactly the same way that we were doing in here because
you happen to have the small values all sitting in the registers in
the right places, you can just shift them over and sort of do that or
so if I get rid of this part here,
Right?
If I click this stuff out, what you can see is that now we've set
ourselves up to essentially do this hole right here, right?
So I can take that out and I can essentially just write it to pixel,
right?
I can stay if I pretend that pixel is an M 128, I write, I can
essentially just assign out to it and that should write out the values
that I produced packed, right?
And so if we take a look at that,
We can see that we've essentially gotten exactly what we had started
with which is the black bar version of the blit, right?
But that it removes that entire thing there.
And if we go over 20 to right, we should also see that it you know, it
didn't slow us down at.
All right.
Uh-oh.
I know what that, okay, thank you visual studio for crashing in the
middle of our debug session.
That's not good.
I know what?
That'll at least I believe.
I know what that is, but that would be a topic for next time.
I don't want to dive into that yet.
I assume that's Microsoft wanting us to be aligned, but, of course, we
are not aligned.
Let me see if I can make that crash happen.
I was kind of hoping I could make it happen in a way that wouldn't
crash little studio.
So I could show you what we were talking about there.
But, you know, wish
Thinking perhaps.
So let's take a look and see if I'm correct about that.
See here.
Well, I guess this is the value.
So, there we go, that value.
So,
What I assume is happening here and we can take a look at the
disassembly is sort of next topic that we have haven't quite addressed
yet but I just want to mention what it is briefly.
Where is the instruction pointer people?
Show me the instruction pointer.
There it is I assume what is happening here is that it's trying to
write to something that is unaligned.
Well actually I can see that it's trying to like write something
unaligned.
Or well.
I should verify that fact first before I say that, let me see.
Can you show me this value?
RDX - 10h.
There we go.
So 21 EB4 B8, what is that value?
15?
So there
Yeah.
So I assume What's Happening Here is that move dqa is unaligned and
unfortunately on the Intel processors when you write to an unlined
address you get a crash right and so presumably in debug it was not
using it was not using the aligned, right?
But I'm going to just see if that I just want to verify that just we
make sure you say it if pixel and 15.
Zero and I'll give a little bit more of an explanation of that in a
second.
So, if what is the problem here pixel is, you don't want me to.
All right.
Well, if pixel as a unit 64, then how does that strike you?
All right, so here we go and what you can kind of see here is that
basically if we only write when we are aligned, we don't get the
crash.
But if we allow it to write always like so
On then we get the crash.
So I don't really want to belabor that topic because that was
something I wanted to talk about later.
I assumed it would do sort of a would do the safe unaligned right
there didn't.
So I'm not sure exactly how to tell it.
Please don't do it online, right?
Right now we're just doing some test code but basically what happens
here,
To give you a little perspective on that.
Is these things are 128 bits wide.
Right.
So 128 bits.
That's 16.
Bytes and the way that the Intel processors work is they have
instructions for writing aligned and writing unaligned, right?
So what we have is 16-byte boundaries
It's considered aligned if essentially, you write only to every 16.
Bytes exactly starting from like the zeroeth base of memory, we talked
about this.
I think a long time ago, starting from the zero point in memory
alignment basically means that every 16 bytes.
Right 1632.
So on right there is an alignment boundary and it never wants you to
write to say the third bite.
You know.
It doesn't ever want you to write like that.
It wants it always to
Aligned.
So, what that means is that the pointer, right?
The bottom part of the pointer should always be 0, right?
Because 16 right is 2 to the 4th.
So the bottom four bits of the pointer should always be 0 if you're
writing.
If you're not, then it will issue an exception.
Now it has ways to write, unaligned some processors, don't some
processors when they're doing wide rights like that, you have to write
a line but the Intel processor actually has the ability to write
unaligned.
And I believe by
Using an intrinsic.
We can force it to do that.
So let me just do that quickly so you can see.
So here's the store instructions.
And I believe M&M store you.
Si128 is the one we're looking for here.
So does not need to be to be a line on any particular boundary.
So if I want to, I can go ahead and do that.
What I can do is actually issue this intrinsic M&M store you dep iope.
Sorry si128, right?
And then I can go ahead and use that pixel pointer and that out
pointer like.
So, I'm that out value.
Like so, and this will cause it to issue a separate instruction.
So let's go ahead and take a look at that.
Now, if we go remember, it was using move, dqa there.
If we go to the disassembly, you can see
Now that it's actually not doing that move.
Dqa it's using the regular mob instruction, right?
And that's that does not have to be aligned, right?
Assuming that that's actually how did it?
Let's just double-check the X pixel.
Yeah.
So that's that's it.
And so here, we're fine now and we're back to the way we were doing it
before.
But again that that alignment thing is kind of a little bit of an SES
and you can see we're continuing to get actually
They're just by doing this translation, we were at 120 Cycles.
We're now down closer to 110, right?
So we keep going.
We're keep going a little bit further.
So that is the end of the stream.
We're already a little over time because I wanted to just mention
briefly.
What that was.
Will talk about that alignment later because the alignment is actually
important and it's something that when we're done doing this routine,
we want to step out back a little bit and look at alignment as
something that we actually care about.
We don't want to get into that just yet.
That's why I don't really want to talk too much more about it.
It.
But basically what we've done now, as you can see, is we've sort of
removed
All of that looping that was happening at the bottom now.
So there's no longer a need for any of that.
Looping we build directly, the 128 bits that we want right in the
Cindy registers and then we blast them straight out and it didn't cost
us that much to do it.
It was eight instructions to prep everything and I guess not a
instructions because this is a no op instruction here.
Right?
So it was seven instructions to prep everything and then three more.
So, ten instructions total to get it down.
Into The Pact format.
So that's not bad, right?
That's not bad.
And again, that does 4 pixels at a time.
So it's actually a pretty cheap.
All right, so let's go over to the Q&A now because I would like to
take some questions in case there are questions on that.
There we go.
Again I showed two ways to that interleaving.
One way to do the interleavings with the unpacks and that's if things
are staying in floating point and have to be interleaved.
In our case, we don't have to write out the floating point, we can
just write out the bits.
And so, we did it this other way, which is to First convert them.
First, two 32-bit integers,
And then to shift the others into place and or them just like we were
doing kind of the analog of what we were doing, only four at a time.
So that's much that's very, very straightforward compared to the, it's
very similar to the scalar path, right?
The four wide path looks almost exactly the same.
It's just using intrinsics instead of the infix notation
Also, I will put in the 2D for what we're doing tomorrow.
Right?
Only the pixels there, that should fill equals true.
Right.
Will the operations be recorded to reduce the number of Ops and load
stores?
Soap.
Here's what I'd say about that.
The compiler often does a pretty good job with that ordering.
So we may be able to like when we're done when we're totally done with
this routine and we're satisfied with everything which we're you know
we gotta we gotta first handle the fact that we're not obeying should
feel here.
That's pretty easy to do but you know we didn't get a chance to cover
today and then we need to do this part up top, which is fairly
complicated.
So we need to do those things when we do those things and we're done
with the routines, we have the complete routine.
What you're talking about is essentially you're saying, can we reorder
the order that we put these things to reduce the number of loads and
stores that have to happen or things like this?
And the answer is if it's algorithmic, perhaps we can, but if it's
simply a question of trying to schedule the assembly that way, usually
the answer is no because the compiler has all the information here and
it typically chooses how it schedules the instructions.
So depending on unless the optimizers really bad, there's not that
much we can do with reorder with reordering.
These things, right?
Because not only is the processor.
I started not only is the compiler going to reorder them to try and
schedule them.
But the processor, reorders them.
Remember, the processor has a window of several instructions that it's
going to reorder in.
So the order that we put them in is not the order, they're actually
going to get executed in right?
So there's a limited amount we can do with that scheduling, so keep
that in mind.
Momo is the code, you are calculating out or or RG be a, would it be
better to do it like this or or RG or be a?
So the first two oars are not dependent on each other.
Yes, I suspect that would probably be better but again, let's take a
look here.
I want to just just to underscore this point, let's let's let's see.
Oops.
Why?
why you no want to break my, you know, wanna
set a breakpoint visual studio.
There we go.
So let's take a look at the disassembly here, right?
And see what it was actually doing.
So,
Where are the actual ORS?
Mul PS.
My we're doing alarm multiplies.
and so on doing multiplies here and add PS, 6 and 0
Add p snps.
so, I feel like
If I'm not mistaken.
I feel like it is optimized out that expression entirely.
It's not doing it that way at all.
Am I right about that?
Oh no.
Okay.
I'm like I'm like having to do that.
It's just massively reordered.
This routine quite a bit.
Here's the part where you're actually talking about.
Alright, so here's the P or right?
This is where it's doing the first or here's the next door between the
same two registers.
So it's actually done.
It's done a bunch of sort of reordering here, right?
I'm not sure it's decided to load in the textile.
A I mean,
It's kind of hard to figure out exactly what it was doing.
The shifts are linear dependent, they happened one right after the
other.
I don't know how much again like that matters depending on how the
processor is working.
But you see that the P or here then it's doing the the reconversion
then it's doing the or here.
So you can kind of see that it already, it already spaced them out
quite a bit.
so, while it's
We better.
I would say it is probably better to write it the way that you were
suggesting meaning writing it this way.
At least makes it clear to the compiler that that we didn't really
care about them being done serially.
But I suspect that the compiler or already knew that if that makes
sense and won't really generate anything substantially different if
that makes sense.
But I don't know.
So you can see here.
It's issuing, the
Chorus together.
So it didn't feel the need to spread them out.
So, you know, maybe that gives it a little bit more flexibility like
it decided to do that and it couldn't have done that before.
I don't know.
I really don't, but you can see it's
it's
in fact, I guess now, I think about, that's actually bad, but that's
the serial or hears, it actually didn't issue the Taurus together,
issued the first, or up here the second or here, and then the
combining or it did down here, right?
Does that make sense?
So it's now issuing them back to back when before it wasn't issuing
them back-to-back.
So yeah.
So I don't know like
When you're dealing with intrinsics like this, I realize it's tempting
to try and think like an Assembly Language programmer and really try
to do Assembly Language kinds of optimizations.
But what you have to remember is that unless you're actually just
looking at what the compilers doing and trying to shuffle things in
intrinsics, to make the compiler do something different.
What you're writing here in assembly is not what's coming out in
assembly directly.
So you have to take these sorts of things with a grain of salt.
This may or may not produce better code when you actually run it,
right?
Just because it breaks up at what appears to be a Serial dependency.
It doesn't necessarily mean that it's faster, one way or the other.
So we can time them and see at the end of the day.
But you know,
it's a crapshoot.
That same thing would not necessarily be true.
If you were writing this humble yourself because then you may decide
to schedule them one way or another.
But the other thing there to remember is the processor again, also
reschedules things, so it's still pretty hard.
Even at that point, you probably still have to time it to see whether
it mattered at all.
Do you need to start with 32-bit floats?
Is there further optimization that doesn't need the casting.
So remember that we're not doing any casting, so there's no more
casting, right?
We got rid of the cast entirely.
What we are doing is conversions, that's converting between float and
integer separately.
And so the answer is, well, you could try to do this pipeline, an
integer, right?
You could choose to try to do it in integer.
And if you look at the
Things that we're doing it is not out of the question that we could
try to do this in integer and furthermore, although it probably
wouldn't be any faster to do it in integer because we constantly would
have to introduce shifts, right?
I mean.
Let me just make this explicit.
So, basically, if you think about trying to do something, where you've
got integer times, integer equals integer right versus float.
Times float equals float.
This path always just works.
Float times float equals float.
That's one instruction integer times integer equals integer in our
case is not one instruction, because what happens is, this is actually
a number between 0 and 255, right?
And 02:55, this is between 0 and 1 and 0, and 1, and we want the
output 0 to 1.
A number between 0 and 1 times.
Another number of t, 0 and 1 equals 0, a number between 0 and 1 in
floating point and the floating Point Unit, does the adjustment to
make sure that that remains true in integer?
There is no such thing.
So when we do a number 0, 25 times, another number 0 to 255, what we
get is the number 0 to 65535, right?
That's what we actually get.
Make sense.
So, if we do that, what that means is, in order to use this in the
pipeline later, we then have to shift it down to avoid blowing out the
Precision of the register.
So we need to actually follow each mole with a shift right.
Does that make sense?
So it actually becomes very expensive to do the pipeline integer so
typically converting to floating Point once at the head end and
converting to floating back to integer at the back end is actually
faster than
Trying to do everything in fixed point, if that makes sense.
Same for texture by linear ads together.
Yes.
Oh Jimmy.
For the texture by linear ads, stacking the ads.
This way was, is similar to the exact same thing in terms of doing
the, the oars.
So if we want to you can, you know, you can.
You can phrase them the opposite way.
It's a little bit hard to read because there's so much stuff going on
here but there's the ad PS of these two moles, right?
And then you introduce the ad PS of the other two moles
Like so.
Right.
There we go.
And that's the exact same operation.
Oops, I missed a parentheses there so there's one ad PS.
There's the other AD PS.
What is my syntax error?
What'd I do wrong there but I miss a parentheses.
I guess I must have accidentally cut something from this.
This match parentheses.
Did I accidentally delete something from the ad P.
Oh, I see what I did.
I preemptively deleted.
The ad.
PS is from there.
All right.
Sorry.
so, our
Ta.
Let's see.
Jeez.
Here's the B's A's.
There we go.
And so, that's the same operation, but not dependent Hoops.
I must have missed something there though.
So we're add PS.
The two ads.
There's the mall Texel ABCD are gggg.
BB hoops.
Yeah.
But again, like, you know, I don't know that that actually helps us
much.
I really don't know in practice if that you know how important that
actually is, right?
Because I don't know the compiler.
You know, we're already telling it that doesn't have to obey our order
of operations, particularly hard.
So I really don't know how much that really changes life for the
compiler in practice.
You really just have to time it to see if it actually made any
difference.
It certainly didn't make any difference in our particular case, right?
If you take a look at what's happening
So with that many cycles.
But you know, we haven't gotten down to, you know, maybe it would, it
would matter more if we if we had finished out everything, I'm not
sure.
Can you compile 022 compared to last week's and parts?
We are compiling 02.
So we are you know right now we're about three times faster.
Why did you make macros for your symbiote operations versus making
functions?
Because again, I just want to take any variability out of it.
Macros are a straight text substitution, I know the compiler cannot
mess it up whereas functions.
The compiler might get confused or you know, you never really know.
Are these intrinsic the same on other operating systems are compilers
as long as it's using the Intel architecture.
Yes, these are the same as they would be in llvm.
The only thing that's not the same is the part that we're actually
only using for testing which is this m macro so accessing.
Oh wait, no never mind.
I wrote it in the way that works.
Both architectures accessing these on Windows on Visual Studio.
Mmm, 128.
Have you are Union that allow you to access their components using the
union and on llvm.
They are not, but it looks like I wrote it in the way that works on
both platforms, to access a member, which is to cast it to a pointer
that works on both.
So yes.
So so this code should work the same on any intel compiler, at the
moment, GCC llvm or
Or Visual Studio.
Why do you say unaligned store is nasty?
As far as I know, for latest Intel CPUs, at least starting from Ivy,
Bridge unaligned store, and load is not very expensive anymore, less
than 5% difference.
Well, first of all, five percent difference is a lot of percent,
right?
When you're talking about optimization, you don't want to just go
like, Oh, Let's ignore that.
But the other thing is, it depends on the processor, right?
Online stores, could be very expensive in the old days and it also is
very important to think about because some processors such as like,
Xbox 360 and so on.
Have the ability to do online stores at all or they're extremely
expensive.
You do them stuff like this.
So typically it's if you're talking about writing an optimized
routine,
Most of the time you want to come at a perspective of, I'm going to
keep everything, aligned right?
Because usually you can it's not that hard to do.
So.
And so typically you want to keep everything aligned that you can keep
aligned, that's just tends to be good policy.
It also is better for cash alignment because if we run aligned, if
we're not aligned to a 16 byte binder boundary it means we're also not
cash aligned.
And so that's another problem.
Which means you probably won't get as good a casualisation.
So in general,
We probably want to take a look at that alignment stuff.
Now, if it turns out that under filling in overfilling, are more
expensive than the cash alignment, or more expensive than the store
alignment penalty that stuff, then by all means use online.
So you know if you end up in a situation where unaligned is faster you
use unaligned, right?
But in cases where you can get aligned and you probably want to check
to make sure that a line isn't going to give you a speed win because
so, you know,
Is scalar access to m120 element still slow on Intel.
Well, it's not slow, you know, it was never that slow, but it's, you
know, it's always a downshift, right?
Accessing the elements out of am.
128 means a, you take a 4X speed hit right off the bat because you're
operating on individual elements instead of all 4 elements at once.
So your four times slower, before you even talk about anything else.
well, I shouldn't say your four times slower, you lose the 4X speed
increase and
Then you're talking about how ever long, a particular processor,
flavor from Intel takes to move, stuff out of the, the wide registers
into, you know, a regular register, you know?
So you've got, you've got issues.
Bankers are says, the presser we do is 192 instructions, so, yeah, I
mean
I don't know how long the processor window is on this particular
posture, right?
It depressor, windows are not always the same size.
I believe, so saying it's 192 instructions, I think is not necessarily
accurate and plus are you sure it's under 922 instructions, not 102
Micro Ops because those are different as well.
But regardless the processor window is, is probably large enough that
a lot of our routine is in it.
And so that's why I say ordering the instructions is kind of hard to
think about because the processor will do you know,
We'll do whatever it wants to do.
Gaston 5 says, I don't understand how one optimizes by using the
intrinsic or function,
I'm not sure what that means but the idea behind the intrinsics is
just that it gives you access to operating on things for wide.
So right now what we've done, the reason why we got three times faster
already is just because we have switched to operating on four pixels
at once.
Instead of one pixel, that's all we did and that's what the intrinsics
allow us to do.
Mmm, convert, PS, epi32.
Always truncates, would that be better than mess around with the
rounding mode?
Is that true?
I actually didn't remember that if that's actually true.
Then yes, that's much better.
I didn't know that.
It always truncates.
let me see if, if we can, I can look it up, the Intel architecture
manual but
I was hoping.
To see.
Conversion intrinsics.
Convert PS.
How is it possible that they wrote all this documentation?
Okay, here we go.
Oh, convert TPS.
I see, okay, I see what you're saying.
Now.
I'm on the same page as you.
Yes.
Convert TPS.
I don't think that's sse2, is it?
Is that actually sse2.
Let's find out.
Wow that's actually sse2.
I had no idea convert packed single Precision floating pieces with
truncation and store.
The result in death.
I did not know that I had no idea.
That was true.
That's awesome.
And the answer I think is yes that is exactly what we should do and
thank you very much for that suggestion because that was way better
than what I was going to do.
Honestly, so that's pretty great.
Yes, I think that's an excellent idea.
That just means we do have to do extra instructions here.
So one might argue, maybe we should try to set the rounding mode
instead but let's let's should be set the rounding mode to nearest and
save the ads.
We can say that.
But what I'll do here is, I'll just say okay, you know, these are
going to be mmm, add PS.
And this will be like 4:30 X, like so.
I'm going to leave it like that for now because I think that is a good
idea that you had.
I don't know.
I mean, we, as it's going to cost us those four extra instructions is
the only thing,
To do that extra ad and there's not really another place we can hide
it.
I don't think so.
You know, it's something to think about but for now I think that's a
good, you know, that's a good compromise.
So let's do half set 1, PS 0.5,
So there we go, it's pretty good.
There's dipping around, right?
You remember how slow this was when we started?
It was like awful, right?
And now we're totally, we're totally rocking.
All right, so that's all good.
Good, good.
Let's see here.
So I think we're all set with that.
See, if there's any other questions
All right, click, we're all done.
Let us wrap up.
I believe you are done.
We got a little bit more to do tomorrow.
We have to obey should fill that'll be pretty easy.
If you want to take a crack at it yourself, you are.
Welcome to do so tonight to see how you do.
It's not it's not too hard but it isn't something that we covered
really how to think about necessarily so so yeah but we'll talk about
it tomorrow.
If you want to give it a shot, a crack yourself, you go for it.
And then tomorrow, most of I imagine what we'll spend our time doing
is.
This stuff, right?
So, getting in in here.
And starting to try and turn this into stuff that can operate for wide
or as close to four wide as possible.
That is really what what the remainder of our job is.
So, we'll dig into that, and then we're getting pretty close, right?
There's not a whole lot else in this routine that needs to be
converted.
And so we're getting close to the point where we can kind of take a
look at it and make an honest assessment and say how many cycles do we
think this could run in, you know, best case?
How close are we to that?
And more importantly how
This are we to our goal of of, you know, making something that could
run reasonably well at our resolution because we can go also kind of
back out and say how many cycles per pixel.
You know, if this routinely ran at this may cycles per pixel.
What would our frame rate be assuming certain Concepts about our
Sprites and that sort of stuff.
So anyway,
That's about it.
We will do that tomorrow at 5 p.m.
Pacific Standard time, or back to our normal time tomorrow.
Let me go ahead and close this stuff off and I will save our
Blackboard.
There we go.
So thank you, everyone for joining me for another episode of handmade
hero.
It's been a pleasure coding with you, as always, and a pleasure
optimizing with you as always, and we will continue our optimizations
stuff tomorrow.
When we'll tackle.
Two things.
I was just talking about.
If you would like to follow along at home and try your own hand at
some optimization, you can always pre-order the game on handmade here
at org and it comes with a source code, which you can download every
night after I finish and and sort of play around with, it's great for
learning.
You can do that on here made here at or you can also check out our
patreon page.
If you want to support the video series, you can subscribe to that.
You can check out our forums site where you can ask questions, or
check out ports to Mac and Linux, things like that.
And there's also of course the tweetbot with tweets the schedule it
you.
So if you
To catch the series live, that's the place to go.
It always has an update schedule on there so you can find out if a
stream gets rescheduled or if there's a weird schedule for the week,
that's the place to find out.
Thanks for joining me.
I will see you guys tomorrow until then have fun programming.