Start recording.
Hello everyone and welcome to handmade Heroes show where we code a
complete game live on Twitch know, libraries.
No engines.
It's old-school here.
And again, this is for two reasons.
One is educational.
It's an order to document basically the entire set of things that go
into running a game.
So that there's a good reference, it just shows are absolutely.
Everything is done, there's no stuff hidden behind an engine layer.
No stuff hidden behind a library.
Just every last little thing, we've coded and the other reason is
because it's a lot of fun, and it allows us to
To play around with stuff in ways that you really can't do.
If you don't understand the entire code base and don't have access to
all of the code.
So it's kind of interesting thing something that I think everyone
should do at least once.
And it really doesn't take that long at the end of the day compared to
normal programming.
Like I said, a couple times on the stream I suspect that we'll end up
doing about 600 hours of programming here and 600 hours of programming
is, you know, it's something like three months or something like that
total of regular full-time work and that's just not very long in the
life of a
Programmer, you know, if you write code all day, that's really just
not a big time investment, so it really doesn't take that long to do.
Everything yourself, if you, you know, keep your keep your goals kind
of focused and you don't kind of Go off into sprawling territory.
But anyway, all that being said, last time I believe where we left
off, as we just finished, kind of getting the concept of pixels out of
our main game code and putting it all into the renderer.
So the game codec deals almost exclusively with World units and
Is one or two last little places that we wanted to kind of get rid of
it where we were still using it.
And so that's what I'd like to take a look at today, is just finishing
that up.
Make sure that's all buttoned up nicely so that we can go ahead and
assume that from now on the render is the only thing that will ever
care about pixels.
And again, the reason that we're doing that is just because that makes
it so much more easier.
In fact, it basically makes it free for us to Target multiple
resolutions because as long as the renderer is, the only thing that
cares about
pixels and the game code is all using some kind of independent unit
then, it doesn't matter what resolution we're under the game.
At the game code doesn't have to change.
Only the renderer has to be aware of that and it can be parameterize
directly off of the resolution.
So that it doesn't really have to change structurally itself, either.
So, that's what we're doing.
If you'd like to follow along at home and you have pre-ordered, the
game on handmade here at, uh, org it's day 110 today.
So go ahead and unzip the source code for day 10 9.
So that's what I'm starting with.
And so if you
Want to follow along that is what you should be starting with as well.
Now let's take a look at where we left off.
I think basically we were pretty much done with making sure that
resolution independent sort of worked.
We had kind of gone ahead and prove that if we change the resolution
between 1920 by 1080 and our half resolution which is something like a
940 by 540 or something like this.
Sorry, 910 by 540, I guess it would be right, half resolution.
We were just kind of trying to demonstrate the fact that everything
would work properly in those resolutions and it did.
But like I said, we still got some additional stuff that we want to do
specifically with ground buffers.
I believe where they weren't really working properly.
As far as pixels were concerned, right, they were still using the
concept of pixels in the actual main engine.
So, what I want to do here is just take a look at quickly at the
places that were still using
Seeing pixels to meters, right?
And you know you can kind of see in fact, we can just do a little
search and see where that is.
You can see that we have this this notion of the world chunk right.
And that's you know that's still doing a pixels to M thing here and
then we also have the concept of work what the cameras looking at,
right?
The screen with the meters and the screen height in meters.
And so what I'd like to do is basically get rid of those things
because that's really all that's left in terms of the code on the
outside.
Using pixels in anyway.
And so if we just can excise that entirely, then we'd be back in a
state where we literally didn't ever have pixels being talked about on
the outside in any way.
Okay.
So mmm.
Let's start with the simplest of the two, I think which is the screen
with an m and the screen height in meters, right?
What I'd like to do with.
That is basically say let's make the renderer be responsible for
telling us what that is, right?
Because if we do that, then we can still have it be based on pixels if
we want it to be or we can have it be fixed if you want it to be and
the renderer can basically decide when it does, the camera transform
for the game.
It can decide whether it wants to use a fixed screen width and height
in
L, or whether it wants to back compute it based on the resolution and
stuff like that.
So that way the game code just knows that it can ask how big it should
you, what the size basically should be for its culling region and the
renderer will return that and it doesn't really have to care whether
pixels are used or not.
It can just use the independent thing that comes back and that's what
I would prefer.
Because again I really want the only person to ever think about pixels
to be the renderer.
So we know that it's all in one place and so even if things that side
Add the renderer are actually using things that come from Pixel
values.
For some reason, we still just want to make sure that that's never
actually going to be something that the game code knows, it's doing
the game code should be totally unaware.
It should always think about things in sort of direct units, right?
So what I'd like to do here is just go ahead and introduce a call, we
can get rid of that for now, I'd like to go ahead and introduce a call
here that will return the information that's being asked for basically
which is whatever that Dimension is, right.
And so what I think I might do there is use one of those rectangle,
two things, right?
And what I'd like to do is say, if you ask the render group, right?
If you ask that render group what it's visible region is it will
return you a rectangle to that is that region, right?
And it could basically be this right now we could basically use
exactly the same computation we were using but just put it inside the
renderer.
So it's in the right place, you know, the right, the right code is
basically thinking about it and you can kind of see that it's related
in there.
So I'm going to put a call in here, to the render Group, which is
going to be like, something like get camera rectangle or something
like this.
And that'll be what we kind of need to do here, is say, at a
particular Z distance.
Because remember, the camera rectangle, gets bigger or smaller, right?
Depending on how far away from the camera.
It is.
So we probably want something like, get camera rectangle at Z, which
will tell us how big the field of view is essentially how big of a
rectangle in 2D.
We're looking at footprint wise at a particular Z depth.
Right?
So if we pass a distance from camera here,
And maybe I'll call that get camera rectangle at distance, right?
And maybe we'll have another one there, which is like a rectangle to
get camera rectangle at at zero or something like this at default.
0.
I'm not sure exactly what I want to call that, but basically, the
place where the camera out Target, that's right.
That's basically where the camera is looking, right?
The, the point where the
Cameras trying to look at specifically and that's just so that we can
basically assume that.
That's that's the place where we're going to be doing most of our
work.
That's like where the player is at any given time, it's that Z depth
and that's all that's going to do is just be a call that returns
exactly what get camera to distance does, but it passes unknown, a
specific distance in.
Right.
So let's go ahead and put this in here.
There's our group and we'll
I'll have this thing.
Do result.
Equals get Kim rectangle at distance and it'll be group.
And then what we'll do is group, you know, Target distance, or
something like that will do return results here.
And then, this guy will be, you know, this sort of thing where we
basically have shoot me.
Something like this.
We've got, you know, we don't really have the draw buffer here.
And so we'll have to decide whether we want to pass that in this will
have to.
This will basically be where we sort of start to decide whether it's
something that's back, solved or not, right?
So, if we decided that the camera is always the same and really has
nothing to do with pixels at all, right.
Then what we could do is we could say that this this function is
actually very specific and how it computes m, which I think is what
I'm honestly, that's kind of what I'm leaning towards doing and I'll
flip over to the Blackboard for a minute just so I can kind of show
you what I'm thinking here.
And again, this is kind of a 3D programmers way of thinking about it.
I don't know that it's necessarily the way that someone who spent most
of their days programming 2D stuff with think about it, but this is
the way I
I think about it because I'm more of a 3D programmer at the end of the
day.
So the way that I'm thinking about this is again, you know, we've kind
of got a world in here, right.
And we've got our camera, which is looking down on that world, right?
Z is pointing up this way.
And essentially, we sort of have this, this, you know, projection
where as you get further from the camera, right?
The the amount we can see is getting bigger, right?
So, if you're this close to the camera, the
We can see is only that big, but if we get further away from camera,
it's this big, right?
And so, I think what I'd like to do is just specify exactly what this
is going to be at a certain distance at whatever, our normal depth
distance is specify what that's going to be and use that to drive our
other parameters which will kind of finish out our projection
equation, how we want it to do.
And that way we can basically just say that, you know, the the view
this, you know,
What the player sees is a is a known rectangle, and if we want to, we
can make it so that it's unknown width or a known height and the other
side, just expands as necessary or something like that.
We could do that or we can make it so that we put in like black bars
or something, we'd letterbox it if they're not on a 16:9 display or
something like that, that's an artistic decision.
It really doesn't have anything to do with the math.
So what I'd like to do is make sure that the math works by basically
saying okay at
Specific distance D, which is our you know, this is our default
distance.
You know, this is our our Target distance.
Then at that distance, we want to basically say that we want a certain
number of meters let's say you know up and down maybe right.
So essentially this is like a field of view.
We talked about this a little bit.
Someone asked a question on a the end of the stream this kind of like
a field of view in why kind of a thing where we say we want to be able
to see a certain number of meters in Y at a certain distance.
That's right.
So at our Target distance, we want to be able to see a certain amount
of Y, okay?
I think that's the way I'd like to do it and then we can basically we
can make sure that all of our stuff works off of that.
And so we kind of know that no matter what happens, we've always got
that and that way pixels just aren't even ever involved.
So it doesn't matter what the resolution of the screen is it?
That matter.
Even with the aspect ratio of the screen is, we know that we always
see a certain vertical aspect basically.
All right.
So, I'm gonna go ahead and do that.
So let's take a look here, we have one projection function here and we
still haven't pulled it out at all.
It's, it's get render entity basis P.
It's still the thing that does all of our projection for us and what
you can see here is we have a focal length specified.
And we have a camera distance above Target specified.
And from that changes me.
Everything else is effectively derived, right?
So we specify those two things and then we produce everything else, we
need from that.
So what I want to do is I want to go ahead and pull those out, right?
I want to pull those out into the render group itself as basically
camera parameters, right?
So, this right here is like, the camera parameters for our, for our
render group, and these are things that you set to control, basically
what?
Now you know what kind of a lens are looking through, you know, the
fish eyes, whatever.
As you saw when we were playing these before, you can get very
different results depending on how you set the focal length and how
you move the camera in the world, right?
It basically, it controls that field of view, these two things
together, control that field of view.
Again, they're just the parameters, which is saying, essentially, how
far away is the Monitor and how far away is the Target, right?
And by setting those 22
Whatever values we want.
We can basically control what that field of view is right?
So, okay.
So what we'd like to do is say, let's go ahead and make Jimmy
Let's go ahead and make these.
Things that are initialized.
Oops.
When we actually initialize the stuff.
So, we'll put in the values that we were using, right result focal
length.
Result camera distance about Target, right?
And then, if I compile this, I just have to go in here and make sure
that these now come off of the render group instead.
So there's that and there's that focal length.
So and then we have to go ahead and finish up these so get camera
rectangle at Target.
That's just going to pass in Loops those in there.
That's camera distance above Target.
So there we go.
And let's just go ahead and finish this guy off.
What is this complaining about?
For identifier.
Get rectangle.
Oh, so is rectangle to handmade, math rectangle?
Yeah.
Sorry.
I don't know why.
I put the two like that.
I think that might be the way I did it in my previous math.
So sometimes I get them confused.
Alright, so once we're in here,
We can now actually do these computations presumably fairly well,
right all we would really need to know is what the aspect ratio of the
display is, right?
Because if we want, we can actually figure out using that projection
equation.
We can figure out exactly what the actual bounds of this thing will be
right.
If we take a look at what that projected X Y is right, you can
imagine, you know?
So here's the equation right projected XY.
It's 1 over distance, 2 pz and
Actually is this this thing right here.
That's the distance from the camera, right?
Excuse me.
So, you can actually see here.
We got camera distance above Target - entity base Z.
That's that's what that guy is, right.
So this is just the total distance from the camera.
We've already got the focal length, right?
And so, the projected ex-wife or anything is just going to be whatever
this raw X Y is,
Right?
So what we want to know, if we want to know, what the outside of the
screen is right, if we've got a projection equation, if we want to
know what the outside of the screen is,
and this kind of gets back to, I guess how we want to structure this.
Because, like, I was saying before, normally in here, you know, we've
got this m 2 pixels thing, right?
And so normally we kind of have this this sort of open question of how
we're going to specify that still.
We just kind of used it the way we were using it.
But if we want to be able to compute stuff like this,
All we have to do.
Shoot me Mom.
Yeah, all we would have to know is, you know, how big that the monitor
is right?
How big we want the, the concept of this monitor to be.
And then we know that, however, far out we go, it just it basically,
just gets bigger based on this projection equation, right?
And so really, all we need to do for the raw XY is we just have to in.
We would just have to initialize raw, X Y to be the dimensions, you
know, half the dimension of the monitor, right?
Basically, like,
Whatever this, you know, half the dimension sizes there, right?
And that would give us what that expansion is actually going to be,
right?
Because if we're talking about projecting, if we're talking about
figuring out, how the reverse projection is, I'm not explaining this
very well, let me, let me, let me try again, let me try again here.
I'm going to draw the same side view that we were using before for
doing our projection.
You can tell I've been offered a as things start to get a little
wonky.
Okay, so here's the camera.
Right here and here is are similar triangles again, right.
And so what we want to know is the outside of the screen which is the
projected x y
Right.
This point right here, what we want to know is at some other distance.
So you know, here's here's the monitor distance, right?
This is the monitor distance away, or this is what we were calling it.
We're calling the focal length, right?
This focal length.
And here's the projected, whatever the coordinate is the projected
coordinate.
We want to figure out what the raw is.
Basically, it's like the inverse of the thing for some other distance,
right?
So this is like the hypothetical distance that we put in.
We want to know
if we were to put the monitors, you know, the farthest edge of the
monitor,
Into what the projected was, what would the raw come out to be right?
And this is that equation that we have here, right?
And so we want to know the raw XY.
Assuming that we were to put in a particular projected, X Y, which
would be the corner of the monitor, right?
And so as you can see, it's in the wrong form after that, we just have
to solve this equation, but we can do that really trivially, right?
If we just, we don't have to do it on the Blackboard, right?
Here's the equation.
What we can do is First Steps A alright /, this right?
And of course, you can see.
This is already a division, so it would literally just turn into a
multiply right multiply both sides by that to get rid of this.
And then you divide by that focal length because the focal length of
course is with multiplying the Rocks.
Why?
And so then we would end up with this equation which is just the
reverse of our projection, right?
So in other words, if we just reverse that exact equation, we can now
plug in something on the Monitor and get out something out in the
world which is what we want.
So what we can do is we can get, we can really think of this, in fact,
we could even make a function for this right.
Which is just like, you know, on Project or something like that, which
undoes whatever that projection is.
And it's just this equation, right?
It just you takes in a projected, x, y and returns.
You like a world, XY, write something like that.
And this is a pretty common thing you would see in a game, right?
It would be a little more complicated than this normally because we're
a little simplified since we're in 2D, but it's basically something
that you would typically want to do.
Pick a point on
The screen and tell me where that point actually ends up being in the
world at a particular distance.
Right?
And so, we'll just go ahead and say this right here.
In fact, I guess we could take in a 3D, which is basically a projected
x y and a Nazi.
Although, that's a little confusing.
So maybe we'll just say at world z, right?
So, add a particular Z depth, and that's where this comes in here,
right?
Or I should say,
At distance from camera, I guess is a probably a better thing because
it's not an absolute World coordinate.
So if I want to know at a particular distance away from the camera,
what would the world xyb of something that was, you know, that far
away and that would give it to me, right?
So, now I can just do one project.
And I guess I have to pass the group here too so that it knows the
focal length.
Because without the focal length, right?
It can't figure that out.
So that looks like about it.
So when we get camera town at distance, we pass in that distance from
camera.
We now need to do the unprojected and the unprojected is like, so
down.
And now we're back to basically just try to figure out what we would
actually fill in in terms of the projected X Y.
Now in this particular case, right?
The thing that we don't really know is we don't really know how big
We expect that monitor to actually be.
We've got our m 2 pixels here, right.
We've got
Excuse me.
We know that we're essentially doing everything in meters.
So after we do the projection, we expand it out by that pixel amount.
So we know that we don't have to think about pixels in particular
here, but we do have to decide at this point, is how big that monitor
is in terms of width and height either way?
Right, we have to figure out essentially, the reverse of this, of this
equation, right?
Because what determines what the corner of the monitor
Here is is however, far you would have to go from the center of the
screen to get to one of the edges of the monitor, right.
Which is going to be, however, many meters.
It would take to cover as many pixels as there are on that display,
right?
And so that's why again, we still have to use that value and we'll
have to, we can, we can maybe get a little, we can go a little further
than this, but at first, I want to to show this part of it.
So if you imagine going, okay, if we've got the draw, buffer buffer,
Whit, we need to go essentially 1/2 right of the with
We need to go one half of the width and we need to go in, basically.
We want
We want pixels to M here, right?
We want to turn that into a m value and the same is true of the
height, right?
So, this is how far we would go in m, to get to the corner of the
screen, right?
And if we plug that projected XY into our equation, then we should get
out.
Whatever.
Our raw XY is is again, also, half of the dimension there and in fact,
I guess since we want the full Dimension, we can actually just not
Fly by half and just say, okay, please project out what that actual
value is going to be, although actually that's not quite right?
We still probably want to do it this way because that's the actual,
correct distance.
And then after we do the project out, then I would say, we want to
put, put that in because because we want to do the result wants to be
a rectangle centre-half.
Tim, write that kind of a thing where we construct a rectangle based
on the center which is just going to be at 0 0 and whatever that that
have
If Dimension was.
So I think that's mostly everything that we needed.
And the problem here is we just are going to need that pixels to M
value right in order to actually figure out what our screen dimension
is.
And in order to do that, that's something we have to set based on the
resolution.
Again, we don't really, why did I delete that?
It doesn't make sense.
Again, we don't really care about this.
We could just fix that meter size.
And maybe that's what we should do.
But if we do that,
we kind of also have to back solve for this.
So let's take it one step at a time.
I'm going to do this.
And then I'm going to go ahead and try to take it one notch further,
just to make it into a more fixed meter size for the screen, right?
I don't know what that still doing in there.
So let's get rid of that.
So yeah, so when we call get camera rectangle at distance for right
now and right now only, I'm going to go ahead and call pass in that
draw buffer like
And then also the pixels to meters just for a second.
So that will be something that we do temporarily and then we'll remove
them.
Let's see rectangle.
Two results.
Yes, that is multiple definition.
Get rid of that, centre-half.
Tim, do we not have that one rectangle Center just called wrecked.
Yeah.
And yeah, so these guys both have to do that although I guess we could
well no, okay we'll do it that way.
Okay.
Let's draw, buffer and pixels to M ever again.
Now, what I want to do first is I'm going to go ahead and step in here
and I want to see what we're actually getting in terms of the that
size here, which I guess actually, now that I think about it at the
moment is actually totally erroneous, right?
Like we never updated.
This stuff at all.
So it's basically just wrong when we put it in here.
This this stuff right here just doesn't mean anything anymore, right.
Because since we added in that projection it's no longer the case that
m 2 pixels
Constant in terms of where we're drawing, right?
So this these are actually totally meaningless values at the moment,
but let's just take a look at what they were.
So we've got screen wit and meters and Screen height in meters.
Oops, looks like we
looks like we've got
optimization still turned on.
Let's go ahead and turn that off useful.
As those are
Again, okay.
So if we go ahead and look at what those are, it's 22 and 12.
So 22, metres across 12 meters down, which seems reasonable, right?
Seems like a reasonable size for a room roughly.
That's what we were getting.
And so now let's go ahead and try putting in
This new call just so we can step through that and debug that.
Okay?
So what I'm going to do here is say rectangle to camera or just test,
I guess.
And we'll go ahead and call this render group function.
So we'll say, get camera rectangle, at Target, and the target will be
the draw buffer.
Let's see, we've got pixels to meters past in there.
We've got the render group like so.
And then we've got
Because the distance to camera is given.
It's just the default Target distance.
All right.
So I just want to see what that actually does when we step in here,
right?
And let's see what we actually pass.
So distance to camera is 5 meters, which is what we're expecting.
There's everything here.
Looks pretty good.
My mouse is kind of sticky there.
There we go.
So the projected X Y that we initialize it with is 11:6 which again
makes some sense.
Does that make sense?
um,
I need to think about that a little more but we'll leave that for now,
we take a look at what the Rocks.
Why is comes out rocks?
Why is 9.5 5.3?
So it's a little bit smaller than where the, the default monitor size
and then we have our results here, which should be, you know, double
that essentially in size and it is so that all looks relatively good
and off, we go.
And if we take a look at what it actually runs here,
of course, it's very slow at the moment because it's being built
without optimizations on which is sort of a nightmare, but
I guess now that I think about it, one of the nice things about being
To reload code live is if I turn on compiler optimizations, we just
kind of get that for free, I guess, in the middle of running.
And so I think that's about right in terms of meters.
Because again, if a room is 22, M and now we're looking at about 18 of
them, you can see that we kind of have a little bit left of the room
to go from side to side, so that all seems relatively reasonable.
So, let's keep on the march of tightening this down because we're
still not quite there yet, and there's a little bit of wishy-washy.
Watching us, they're in my head.
A lot of times, I'm just like, yeah, it's not quite right.
I don't like the way we're conceptualizing this or that.
You know what I mean?
So the first thing that I'd also, I guess the first thing I'd like to
do is say alright let's let's try and get back to pushing the monitor
size back to something more sane because again, that monitor size is
ridiculously large.
If you take a look at what we're saying, the monitor is at the focal
length that we're using which just seems kind of weird.
I don't really understand why that would be the case either because it
seems to me, we should be able to reduce the focal length and then
reduce the size of the monitor.
so I think, basically, what we have is we sort of have essentially a
We now have the pixels to M thing is kind of constraining us.
I keep keeping it in there but the problem with that is that it
prevents us from getting out of the business of thinking of pixels
when we're doing the transform which is kind of bothering me, right?
Because if you think about it, if we go to the render group
And we go to get render entity basis, right?
This m, 2 pixels thing.
What that's essentially doing is that's m, 2 pixels on the monitor,
right?
And we kind of mentioned this the other day.
And so what I'd rather do here is say when we are actually figuring
out what that is.
It's not m 2 pixels in the world anymore.
It's m 2 pixels on the monitor.
So on the monitor, how big should it?
M.
B is basically what we're asking now, right?
And so if you figure you're talking about a normal size Monitor and we
go back to some more same values here.
And in fact, I'm just going to call.
I'm going to I'm going to actually go ahead and actually solidify this
now, because now that I'm actually thinking about a little more
clearly m, 2 pixels on monitor, right?
It's kind of like or I should say monitor, m 2 pixels or I don't know
what you want to call this m.
I guess we can still call it, m 2 pixels.
But say something like, this is the size.
This translates meters on the monitor into pixels on the monitor,
right?
If that makes sense.
So now we could probably start to assume some Center default this m 2
pixels.
What we want to know is essentially for a certain number of meters on
the monitor.
So let's say, you know, it would be something.
Like trying to think of how big a monitor would normally be I guess
let's let's talk about something like gay.
Let's see how many meters.
So you have a 30-inch monitor 30 inches in meters, right?
So that's how many meters that is diagonally, right?
And so, if I wanted to know what that was going to be square, I don't
actually know what they typically are in terms of
What at what a normal monitor is in terms of Dimensions.
Let's just take a look, let's say, like, dimensions of a 30-inch
monitor, can you tell us what that, what it is?
Dell 30-inch monitor.
Okay, did they have specs?
Tech specs?
Let's see.
Let's see here.
Wait with where's the width and height H inches?
22 inches extended.
That's not really the screen.
The size though, I want to know what the screen size tends to be
course, this isn't 16 by 9.
Unfortunately twenty seven point two, six inches roughly of the
monitor.
It's not quite, right?
So we'll say something.
Let's pretend it's something like 25 inches.
Seems good enough.
So, let's say that we're going to be that many meters across, right?
So, if that's how many meters we are across the monitor, right?
The actual size of the monitor, then we could actually just sort of
say if we wanted to make a good approximation here, we could say that
result, m, 2 pixels here is that many times what we expect the
resolution to be, right?
We want we want 920.
Over a width of Point 635 M, right?
That makes sense pretty simple.
This is how many pixels are you know we're sort of thinking about on a
display let's say and here we go.
And now we'll put the to do in here which is need to adjust this based
on
Buffer size.
In fact, I guess what I should say is when we allocate the render
group, we probably want to specify that.
So we want to actually have that pixel size coming in here, probably
loaded, bitmap screen, buffer, or something.
Or we could actually say something like this, which is resolution
pixels x and resolution pixels wide, something like that.
And so then we can just say, okay, we know that we want to expand
roughly
Size of a thing out into this many pixels in X, right?
So, if now we have that, then we can go here and make a saner thing,
you know, that our values will now mean something a little bit saner.
I think get
And basis.
So if we actually take out the m 2 pixels.
Now from being passed in here, and we say that, it's now going to be
rendered.
Root m, 2 pixels here?
Let's see where else we've got M to pixels there.
That seems standard to me.
That's just a seems like a better way to go.
Now, I suspect, we can set our focal length of something.
That makes sense.
Instead of being as such a large value, which didn't seem right
because I feel like it should be something like point three or
something like that because it should be however, far a person,
normally sits away from their 30-inch monitor, right?
That should give us a reasonable thing, if we were to plug that in
there, right?
So let's see here.
Pixels 2 m.
Where does that actually get past?
That gets passed to draw a rectangle slowly and that looks like about
it.
So really all we need to do there is say that this is 1 / render group
2 pixels.
Okay.
This no longer gets passed.
So and now when we actually allocate a render group, we kind of have
to tell it what that size actually is going to be which is fine.
Now, foreground chunks, it's a little bit weirder because we, of
course, don't really know exactly what we want to do for that.
So that's a little that's a little wonky, right?
Look, we don't actually know what we want and that's sort of a, this
is the big to do here that we have to do.
How do we want to control our ground chunk resolution?
Because that's kind of a whole another.
That's a whole another
Ballgame there.
So, for now, I'm going to totally make this up, but but that's going
to be sort of the next thing is to get those ground chunks working and
we'll take that out.
So when we allocate this render group, we can just pass it.
The draw buffer width and height like so.
And I guess actually that's not quite true yet.
There we go.
And so now I suspect our projection should be all messed up like it is
because we actually still haven't gone in and refreshed.
Those values that I just said, we should like the focal length which
is going to be totally messed up at the moment here.
Where is that focal length?
Let's see.
Allocate groups under group
Render group and the now we can say yeah, the focal length I think
should be much smaller than that, right?
It should be roughly how far someone sits from a monitor which I guess
I don't actually know.
How big that is.
Let's say that that focal length is what is that focal length?
So I say I would say, I sit about maybe two feet from the monitor two
feet in meters roughly.
So that's point 6 that seems.
Yeah, I'd ballpark about two feet from a monitor that's about that
size.
So something like that.
And that looks pretty good, that looks like roughly.
What we had tuned it to before, in fact, and so I hope you can see
again, this was just kind of me pushing through things until we got to
it.
This was really the big thing that we had messed up before, right?
When I said things were wonky, that was the one keenness.
The wonkiness was that m 2 pixels was a totally wrong value.
Because we were on the, at the point that we were using it, we were on
the surface of the Moon.
We had projected things to where we think the monitor surface is.
And at that point, we needed to think about how many pixels should one
meter be on the monitor, right?
Not in the world, and so, this was actually like a value.
That's, that's almost, I guess in the real world, not in the game
world.
So it needs to be based on that and now you can see that we've
actually gotten to the point where we're using essentially.
All real world values like the focal length, right?
This is
M, the person is sitting from their monitor, right?
This right here is like a I could specify what this value is, it is
like, with of monitor, right?
so,
horizontal measurement of monitor in meters.
Right.
And now we sort of got a real world scenario with all real world
values.
And now, the only thing that we would play with is just how far above
the target we are.
And we know that for a typical user scenario of a typical person
sitting, in front of a typical gaming PC, they will get something that
looks exactly.
Right.
It actually has the right perspective as if things were that far away
from them behind their monitor screen.
So, it's no longer a
Medical word values, that's what it is.
And again, we can control that Distance by just sort of pushing things
further, or closer from the camera by basically just saying how high
above them.
The camera is.
And so now we just have that one value which is really nice.
I can just kind of set that to that one value to basically Zoom.
As much as I want to zoom, and then we're done right now.
That means I can go ahead as well and get rid of this stuff, which is
good.
Good.
I can say, get camera rectangle at distance, no longer has to take
either of those two things.
Because now, I could actually, these are actually being specified
directly in that in that code in the, in the draw before group, so we
can get them out of there.
So I'm going to go ahead and make sure that we store those for our
hypothetical use.
Right?
So what I want to do is say we've essentially got, in fact, what I
could do here is almost just store this
In the thing as well.
I could just store what that what that corner value is.
So, maybe in the render group, I could store a something like, a
rectangle to, which is whatever that projected X Y is.
So, this is like half Tim in meters or something like the monitor.
10:30 in meters.
Right.
And then monitor half-demon m is that projected x y
So, we'll just store this guy up above somewhere and projected X Y,
will just now pass group, monitor half-demon m.
Okay.
So that is about that and there's a little further.
We might want to go with this, I'm not sure I'd have to think about
it, but if you can just go ahead and do this for now.
So this is resolution pixels x and resolution pixels why?
And then we have
Pixels to meters, which is just 1 over m 2 pixels.
So oops, what did I do?
Group monitor have to in meters distance from camera group?
Cannot convert.
That is not the right kind of value.
We go and this no longer has to take anything.
So there we go.
And now we've got all of our stuff in theory anyway, working through
that new function.
So all we have to do now is actually use that value and what we can
do, what I'd like
To do is in fact this is probably a good time to introduce this as
well.
We have a little bit of time left on the stream so I think I'm going
to go ahead and do it.
What I'd like to do is say okay, let's switch over to using this
rectangle, this new camera bounds rectangle, right?
So this is the screen bounds, we're getting back.
I want to go ahead and use that so we can get rid of pixels to meters
here.
But if I want to do that, I I want to know if I'm doing it.
Right?
Right.
I want to know if this ends up being
Being correct.
And unfortunately I don't actually know any way to do that with what
we've got.
Like I don't have a, I shouldn't say don't know.
Anyway, I don't have a way because let's say, we do this, right?
And one way that we might figure out that that we've done all the math
wrong and it's coming out incorrectly, we're using these camera bounds
to pick
Sim region if the camera bound is much too small then maybe we
wouldn't pull any any entities into the region like we could see that
happen, right?
But it I do here.
Oh right.
Sorry about that, to do this sort of thing.
Rekt min-max.
Like, so, so, let's do that.
I guess we could just do the three screen bounds Min and V3 screen lb
Max because they automatically zero extend now, right?
So, there we go.
At least, I thought they did.
Did we not do that?
Do we leave it as 2 V 3.
I thought we did one with the Zeke's and I guess maybe we have to pass
in what we want it to be.
So the zoo or extend is an automatic.
Yeah.
So what I was trying to say here is, all right, so we're getting this
new screen bound back and we weren't using that previously.
So I'm plugging this into camera bouncing M and one thing that might
happen is like, I don't see any entities on the screen.
Like it's just the wrong rectangular something and then I would know
it was broken, right?
And then we can go and fix it and, you know, maybe that happens.
But as you can see, that's not what happened, right?
It's like everything's still working properly, but
Question now is well, I want to start actually, you know, we're
starting to get a little bit further into the type of code where I
want to actually validate that I'm doing things correctly for all.
I know it could be returning, some giant rectangle, that includes
everything.
And what I want to do is make sure that it's actually returning the
rectangle that's just the screen size, right?
And so what I'm going to do is I want to draw something in here.
And there's two things I can do here, I'll do the simplest one first
and then I'm going to do a slightly more complicated one.
But what I'm going to do here,
Is I'm going to draw this rectangle that we got back.
I want to draw that rectangle so we can actually see what it what it
actually looks like, right?
Like where it actually is and we should see it pegged to our screen,
no matter where we go.
It should be exactly.
They're right because we're solving for the exact outline of the
screen.
And so if it doesn't look like that, we know, something's weird,
right?
So let's go ahead and draw it first.
Push back that line.
So we know that it's basically at 000, right?
It's just, it's just at the, there's really nothing to that and then
we know that it's the screen bounds is the dimension, right, screen
bounds, and we'll draw that as a nice.
Lovely bright yellow because, you know, I love my bright yellows.
We go, what is the problem, screen bounds to V2?
Can we do, do we have get
Dim of?
Do we have that?
Let's see what we've got.
I want to wait to just get the dimensions of a rectangle, but I don't
know.
You've got Min Corner Max Corner.
We don't actually have get Dimension, right?
We just don't, we don't have a thing that actually gets the dimension.
So I want like a wrecked Max - rectum in that kind of thing, right?
All right.
So you can kind of see now that we're getting the exact right
rectangle for the, for the screen, right?
Which is, which is cool.
So now we can like verify, okay, we're actually solving for that
region properly and that's all good.
So we're even though we're going through all the back transform and
all that stuff.
It's now we know exactly how big it was right and so that's pretty
awesome.
But there's one more thing that we probably want to do which is like
let's say that we wanted to see when entities were coming in and out
of that active set, right?
And in order to do that I'm going to have to add some entities that
are I guess.
Oh well no I don't I could just make it so that I kind of I can just
walk away from the end of days out here, can't I?
Now I can't because we've got those spaces that will stop me.
So what I'm going to need to do temporarily just to kind of show you
this I want
Make it so that we've got some rooms that we can walk through, right?
I want to be able to walk through some rooms.
So instead of setting door Direction, 23 all the time, just going to
let it do its thing.
So that when we start the game, we get an actual sort of a real
situation.
What is this doing here?
This is, this is forcing me to go to go up a, yeah,
There we go.
So, as we walk around here, what I want to do is I want to be able to,
I want to be able to see edit, he's coming in and out of the same
region, right?
But right now, I can't do that, right?
There's no way for me to actually see that information because it's
off the screen, right?
So one way that I could do that is, I could go in, and
Move the camera out, right?
Like if I wanted to see where everything was, I just go in and move
the camera out, right?
But that's not going to work.
Because if I go in here and change the camera distance above Target to
something else, right?
If I change cameras is about Target to something quite High.
What will happen is now that we're solving for the screen dimensions,
it will make sure that it pulls all of those things in right.
Which is exactly not what we wanted to do.
We want to be able to move out and have it act like the screen is
actually smaller.
Okay, so what I want to do here is I want to introduce the concept of
a debug value there which will allow us to set both a camera distance
above the target.
That.
What we want the game to think we're using and it camera distance
above Target.
That's what we will actually use, right?
And so, what we want to do here is basically isolate.
What I'm going to do is I'm going to pull out render group camera.
I'm going to make the thing here for camera.
And what I'm going to do is I'm going to pull out all of these values
that were using to control our transform, write this stuff and I'm
going to have a, you know, essentially game camera and debug camera or
or something like this or camera and debug camera, right?
And the debug camera,
The one that will actually use when we're sort of flip to a debug
State and the camera is the one that everyone will always use except
for the actual render calls, right?
And so that way, like we can kind of have sort of The Best of Both
Worlds there, right?
I might be a little confusing at first but hopefully you'll see what I
mean in a second.
Okay, so when we come in here, I can also eliminate some of these
things like just distance above Target.
Like so now, I don't know if we actually need M to pixels and monitor
have Tim.
Now, I think about it.
So I'm going to leave those.
Just temporarily going to leave those out, right?
I'm going to leave those out.
And so if we go in here and do a camera dot distance from Target
camera, that focal length right again.
Camera that focal length camera distance above
Target.
And then I'm going to also do result, debug camera, angles result
camera.
So it's just going to be the same camera only.
Then I'm going to go ahead and set its distance to be much higher,
like I was saying, and then here again, camera focal length.
And see here camera distance about Target, right?
So now I've changed absolutely nothing but we're working off of those
trucks now.
And now what I want to do is be able to say hey when you go to do the
rendering I want you to essentially use, you know, whatever.
The in fact I guess debug camera is probably the wrong one.
This will just be game camera and render camera.
Let's do it that way.
It seems a little bit better, so render camera.
So let's keep going under camera that.
So this is render camera.
Render camera, it's good that wrong.
This is actually.
All right.
Go and this is always game camera.
And kincannon, okay.
All right.
So what I would like to do now.
Well, actually, yes, you can.
See it, since they're set to different sizes, you can now see exactly
what's going on in the world at a much more zoomed out level, right,
and you can see things coming in and out of the same region.
Now, what's kind of interesting, when you look at this, we can kind of
already see that.
We have a potential bug here.
Things seem to be moving in and out of the same region based on our X
location.
Just fine.
But they don't seem to be moving in and out of the same region based
on our Y at all, right?
And you can see, again, it's pretty cool.
The way this works.
We can see that yellow region shows us exactly where it thinks the
camera is but already just doing that simple.
Having that simple difference between a debug camera and the regular
camera allows us to spot errors.
Very, very simply in our routines, right?
It allows us this really, really convenient way to very simply, you
know, sort of call out that error, right?
And so that, basically, now it's
Free for us to set those two things separately between render camera
and debug camera.
And I don't know, we probably don't have very much time here because
you got three minutes we could go try to look to see what's going on
with that particular bug.
In terms of Y, the x is working but the why is not working.
So I could sort of try to take a look at that.
Let's, let's take a quick look here.
Screen bounds.
I got back.
That, that thing will be.
We produce the camera, balance and M.
We expand the Z.
And then what do we do with that camera bounds in M?
Expand that Z.
We then map that into the trunk space.
Let's see.
That's four grand buffers so we don't really care about that soon
bounds expansion.
It should expand 15 meters in both X and Y ad radius to some bounds
expansion camera bands and M and then we pass.
What do we actually do?
We pass in bounds into the Sim region.
And off we go, let's take a look.
Let me just take a look quickly and make sure add Radius 2 is not
busted Adam radius to doesn't look busted.
Wait, that's the wrong one though.
There is that Radius 2 minus the radius.
A Max Plus looks pretty reasonable and made some region.
See here begins Sam.
Update.
Safety margin.
Add videos to soon as the max entity radius looks like it's still
handling all of those bounds properly.
So I feel like what we should probably do is just draw this as well,
right, just to see why we're getting that kind of different Behavior
happening there.
So, what I'm going to do here is I'm going to, I'm going to have the
same region bound since it's stored, right?
The bounds are stored in here.
I'm going to go ahead
And when we push, when we do that, push rectangle outline.
I'm going to just push all of these, right?
So we'll do the screen bounds will do the camera bound and M camera
bounds and M 60 and we'll draw that one.
I guess it's white.
Let's say let me go ahead down here to where we do the rest of these
guys.
There we go.
And then we'll also do see the Sim bounds and the update.
It'll bounce or sorry, the bounds.
So let's see.
This guy, I'll be magenta.
The scabby cyan.
All right.
Too many rectangles.
Too many wrecks, too many wrecks, too many wrecks.
Too many wrecks.
So these are actually 3D.
So we want to do xy's on those and then we need that get dim call to
work on both.
We're out of time.
So this will be the last thing I do on the
Looks like tangle free so get Max corner.
Here we go.
and,
Okay.
so it looks like we don't have a bug, it looks like it's just that we
can see a little bit further I guess maybe, although
I don't know.
I don't know about that.
I'm not entirely certain.
It looks like we don't necessarily have a bug but what, what is the
cyan bound?
What is r?
Sy and EM.
Hold on a second.
I just want to say sorry.
We'll go to Q&A in just a second camera bounds and M camera bounds in
meters.
Oops.
Yeah, yeah, so that one we really don't need to draw because it's
always just ins.
He's the only thing that it changes really so we can turn that one
off.
The cyan one is the Sim bonds.
And then the simmer region bounds.
Yeah, that's kind of weird.
It seems like it's pulling things in
It's pulling things in I guess.
Maybe that's what it's supposed to do.
We have to take a look at that tomorrow, maybe that's be something we
look at as you can kind of see it's pulling things in only up to the
Not to the that outer, the actual bounds, that it expanded to.
But I'm not actually sure why.
That would be a thought, it was supposed to do all of them essentially
so because it's actually iterating over the Sim region bounds but the
same region bands that were drawing.
It doesn't seem to actually pull the stuff in there, and I guess, is
that because we only, we only actually use the updatable bounds to
pull stuff in.
I'm not sure,
I think we basically got, we've got some bugginess in here.
Is I guess what?
I would say, let's see what Adam 2D does.
It does add into the overlap restaurant.
Updatable bounds.
It pulls it in if it's updatable but it pulls it in either way.
So I feel like I just feel like something is afoot.
They're Sim Collision total volume.
That's
That's what is this?
What?
Total volume Sim region bounds if entity overlaps rectangle.
Overlaps rectangle.
Let's see.
Add radius to volume D dim.
and then,
He's in rectangle P grown.
Volume to offset p.
Huh, it just feels, it feels like that's a bug.
So I want to take a look at that battle.
I guess we will start with tomorrow although maybe we shouldn't bother
playing with this stuff right now because we don't really need to but
it might be nice.
I mean when you find a bug you should fix it.
That's my general opinion.
so,
Any overlaps rectangle.
I just feel like there's a little bit of a bug situation going on
there, because it feels to me, like, it should be extending all the
way out to the purple region and it's not.
Now it could be, you know what, it could be.
It could be that we're too high up.
It's that because those are on the lower level, I guess maybe that's
what it is.
That's a little closer.
Although I'm its now, I'm on that level and we're still not really
extending.
So,
Yeah.
I mean it could be right but it just feels it.
Just feels a little off to me.
So we'll have to we'll have to see what's going on there.
It's close to right, but it's not quite right.
All right, so let me go ahead and close this down.
We'll go ahead over to the Q&A.
Let me check out our M to pixel situation here or rather I should
start.
Whole situation.
So now we're literally only doing this for, you know, for some of, for
just this world chunk situation.
That's about it.
There's really nothing else going on with it and.
Yeah.
So we're getting real close to having this be pretty clean.
We're not quite there yet, but we're getting close.
So, let's go ahead to the Q&A, like so, there we go.
so, if you have a question,
You should type it in now with q:.
Let's see.
Will the too many wrecked song be on the soundtrack album?
I do not suspect so because I suspect that would be some copyright
infringement since.
I don't know if you know this, but I did not come up with that
particular Melody.
Robot chocolate Dino.
Should the m 2 pixels value?
Take the pixel density of the monitor into account.
So it is taking the pixel density of the monitor into account, right?
I think maybe what you meant to ask was, should it take the actual
physical size of the monitor into account?
And the answer there is not really because unless we actually know how
far the person with sitting, well, I'll explain this.
I'll explain this in detail because it's a reasonable question.
I want to make sure that it's clear to everyone.
Why it's happening the way that it's happening.
So let's take a look at what these how these values are set here,
right?
No.
Yeah.
So here's how we're parameterizing things at the moment, right?
Here is some slice of the world, right?
This is world.
Here's the camera, like we drew before.
so,
And here's the screen, right?
This is the monitor.
Now, what we need to be able to do is set up a typical size for this
thing.
Meaning how far away is the camera from the monitor, meaning the, I
essentially the viewer and how big is the monitor.
Now, it doesn't matter if that is any particular.
Set up that a user might actually do it only matters that it is
reasonable, right?
It matters that it is something like what?
The user might do.
Because there's multiple ways that the user might actually view this,
right?
They might be sitting in their living room, looking at a giant, you
know, maybe they're looking at some 90 inch plasma TV.
Right.
And so they're over here, you know, this is where they're sitting so
they're basically, you know, the right size for this thing would be I
don't know how big these things are across.
I don't know, something like 70 inches or something like this.
The right sizes for these things, maybe 70 inches across and they're
sitting like you know six feet away or something right.
That might be one valid set of parameters but another one might be
there like at a desk, right?
Which is what I was thinking more like and so it's like 25 inches
across and there.
Like right up next to it, right?
So this distance is only like you know, half a foot or two feet.
I think is what I said, right stuff like this.
Now, the idea is as long as you pick one that's an actual fairly
typical setup, the setups for how people might view, things don't
really change that much, they just scale up or down, right?
But this is basically the same as this just with a bunch of scale put
in it, right?
It's scaled up this distance and it scaled up the size, right?
The same is true as if they were looking at a tablet that they were
holding in their hands, right?
The tablet is smaller but the distance is smaller.
And so, basically, as long as we just set up something reasonable, our
perspective will be close enough to what the user is probably doing
with the size of their device and where they are, that it'll be okay,
right?
Because again, all it does is control the amount of perspective
foreshortening that we have.
So we're just trying to make sure that we come from real-world value
so that they're not completely ridiculous, right?
So, what we are, parameterizing it on again is just saying, how many
pixels across would?
We be, you know, how much, how many pixels across are?
We in our current resolution and we're assuming essentially,
That whatever that's going to be.
We want that to come out to be
It was like a trance.
What was I saying there?
I totally forgot.
We want that to come out to be something reasonable, right?
So that's how that works, but what we don't actually have yet, right?
Is we don't actually have this, this width of monitor notion I suppose
coming from any place real, right.
We don't actually have any way that that's actually being specified.
And so, what we will want to do, you know, I guess what we'll want to
do is to try to
You I don't know bake that out into a value so that we don't have to
worry about it anymore or something like that.
I mean, I guess I'm not sure.
I mean, I guess what I'm saying is I just kind of picked values that I
thought would be reasonable because they control the perspective
foreshortening and I don't, I guess I'm trying things, I don't really,
I'm not really trying to capture what the actual width and resolution
of the, or with the actual width of the monitor is in the actual real
world.
I'm
Using a typical one.
And so what will happen is, you know, ideally if the resolution of the
pixels goes up right, then what happens is, we end up, we end up doing
a wider projection, right?
But that's what we want.
And so the question you are asking is what happens when the monitor
resolution is denser.
That is exactly what this value is.
Supposed to handle, right?
So if you look at what it comes out to be,
at the moment and I guess let me go ahead and make it so that our
render camera and our debug camera, the same at the moment,
So if you look at what this looks like, we can fit one screen on.
Right.
And ideally, if I haven't totally messed something up, which I may,
well, have, if we want to, we can go in and change.
Whatever the resolution is Hoops, that the calling code is asking us
to provide, right?
And that should not change things at all.
44, is that, okay?
So if I change up to 1920 by 1080, at least, hopefully we still get
rough.
Same thing, right?
And you can see that it it's the same exact screen, right?
And the reason again for that it's not quite exactly right?
Because it's a little too wide at the moment that 1920 by 1080, a
little bit too big.
But it's almost exactly correct, right?
If that makes sense.
So anyway, what I'm just what I'm trying to get across there is the
change in resolution is automatically sort of handled by the way, that
we've structured, those equations.
Because words are M pixels here.
Because as the resolution increases, we will increase, it will control
how proportionally we increase the size of the things we project, so
we don't want to, if what you were asking is, why don't we correct for
that here?
We don't want to correct for increases in resolution of the monitor.
We want to allow increases resolution.
The monitor to expand the size of the things that we draw on the
screen because that's what keeps us resolution independent.
So that's why with of Monitor and and
Go length, right?
I mean, you can basically think of focal length and width of monitor.
In fact, I'll put them right next to each other.
You can think of the width of the Monitor and the focal length as
being the two things that we're sort of picking from a typical
real-world scenario.
And they create a universal ratio that divides out into just what we
use for our projection in such a way that we know now, no longer care,
how big the actual monitor is, or how far away the actual user is
sitting from,
MIT.
It will always give us the same perspective foreshortening, right?
It's fixing the perspective, foreshortening of the game to a typical
scenario.
and so,
We don't want to do is then re correct it based on the pixel density
because if we were to correct it based on a pixel density, then we
would no longer be resolution independent.
So we want to let the pixel density, increase the size of the
projected things on the screen because that's exactly what we want to
happen.
When we have more density, is to just get more pixels for the same
size thing in the world, right?
That was a really bad explanation, but hopefully, eventually it kind
of made some sense.
Are you sure the camera should be
Looking down perpendicular to the levels wouldn't the perspective art
work out better.
If you said the camera was at an angle?
No, because II don't want the user to.
I want this to be a game where the user can count on Motion in the 2D
plane to look 2D and not have their be like distant movement in the
distance moves, less horizontally than in the foreground, right.
I don't want them to to do that back projection.
Can you please toss u and v into V 2?
Sure.
You're just, you just wants.
This sort of thing.
We can definitely do that and we could also if you wanted and here too
we could just go ahead and do you DW like that?
And and similarly we could make those buv.
Do it like this.
Ew, there you go.
That helps
Garland of Zoom, we will know exactly how far away they are sitting.
If they have properly purchased their handmade hero branded Microsoft
registered trademark hololens.
That's a very good point.
As, you know, handmade hero is all about co-marketing opportunities,
right?
We're not at all about education or trying to do a good thing.
We are about trying to make as much money as possible.
So, selling out to Microsoft like certain people do, who will remain
nameless is exactly what we're going to.
Do as soon as we get the opportunity and the hololens is a perfect
opportunity for us to do that.
Now, of course that's all joking.
The actual truth though, there's actually a non joke, important thing
kind of encoded in that and I don't know if this is why Matthew ask
this question or not, but it's a good point.
So I'm going to go ahead and address it.
Which is to say that.
It's a very good it's now that you've seen me work through it, right?
And you've seen me go okay, in order to figure out what these
parameters should be, if we were really basing them on physical
things.
Right?
We should know stuff like how far you are from the camera, right?
In all that stuff.
When you want to create a name, truly immersive 3D experience, like a
VR Helmet or an AR helmet tries to do, right?
And everything has to be right.
It has to look binocular.
It has to when you turn around, it has to move properly.
It's all got to look correct or you will vomit.
Suddenly you need all of these values to be accurate, right?
You need all of these things to be correct.
And so one of the big kind of failures of the way.
Modern devices work is they don't report any of these values to you.
There is no calibration when a user sets up their workstation that
says, how far away from the monitor they are.
So we can't do accurate transforms that look comfortable to them, from
where they're sitting.
It's a bummer.
But with 3D headsets and stuff they have had
Start to do this.
And so one of the things you'll see if you crack open.
An SDK that's designed for use with 3D head-mounted displays, you will
get all of this information.
You will know, exactly how far away the lenses are from the eye.
You will know how far the screen is away from the lens.
You will know how much Distortion there is.
You will know the binocular, offset, all of that stuff is actually
told to you and then, you can feed them into equations.
Just like the one we were doing to actually create an exactly correct
projection that works.
With the head-mounted display.
So that's pretty cool.
And it's worth thinking about the fact that what we just did and the
fact that we were using real world units there that actually becomes
something you do directly with something, like a 3D head-mounted
display SDK because you need to get all these things.
Correct.
You can't fudge them anymore.
They've got to be exact and that is what you will see when you crack
open one of those sdks
Water lime on is real 32 ambiguous because it could either be floating
point or fixed point.
It is ambiguous a very much so it's a 32-bit real.
But actually, we don't care so much whether it's floating point or
fixed.
Point is the way I might say real 32 is what I use in my code to talk
about the case where I just want to represent a 32-bit value as a real
right?
And actually I don't care how it's being represented.
So if for some reason and as you know, some underlying
Being wanted to swap out something other than IEEE floating-point
that's actually.
Okay.
That makes sense.
So ambiguities actually fine.
Is the non smooth movement at higher Zoom levels due to not being
optimized or some sort of issue with sub-pixel smooth as it's not
being optimized?
That's, that's pretty much.
It's just because it has film or pixels and we don't we're not fast
enough per pixel right now.
Because we're really
They really, really really optimized in that renderer.
Would it look different if you scale with of Monitor and focal lengths
together?
Constrain to the same ratio?
Well,
I'm tempted to leave that as an exercise for the reader because
here is your similar triangle right here is the focal length.
Here is the width.
So you tell me if I was to scale them up by the same ratio.
Would that change the projection?
Right.
We'll leave that as an exercise.
You can you can kind of see how this would go, right?
I'll walk you through it a little bit.
So the width of the monitor, right?
If we assume that the resolution pixels x is constant.
So we're saying for a, for a given size Monitor and we say that we've
got the, the with of monitor that were actually scaling it up, right?
So if we were to say that we are essentially increasing the focal
length but also increasing the size proportional to it.
Then how would that affect the ratio of how far we project things on
here, right?
And hopefully you can see that it's not going to change that line,
right?
But again I'll leave that, I leave that sort of as an exercise for you
to go work out.
Could you put a slider for the user to change their distance to the
camera at the start of the game?
Like some games?
Do with gamma?
Yes you could.
And in fact, I've made programs that work this way before I won't talk
too much about those because I may actually ship them someday, but
basically they're like I have done stuff before which actually has a
calibration.
That's like how far away are you sitting?
And I do a bunch of stuff.
I actually look at the real size of the Monitor and figure out some
stuff like how big Tech should be on the screen based on how much our
kit should subtend, in your view for Optimal Reading and stuff like
that.
All right, so it looks like we're about done.
I don't see any more cues.
I don't see any more cues so I think we are done.
All right, let's go ahead and see.
Eve.
Go ahead and save, leave that in there so that we can play with that
tomorrow and see if I want to see if maybe there's some explanation
for that sort of weird.
Situation there.
It's kind of fun further.
I mean it's going to get to one of these.
It's going to get to a bad point.
I think not for a little while.
Like you know, I think we probably got another month or two where it's
fine but eventually we're gonna get to the point where I'm enjoying
like moving the guy around and fighting and stuff and then it's going
to be really annoying because everyone's going to be watching the
stream and being like,
Stop just running.
You're the dude around and playing the game like go back to
programming or whenever you get this done and I'm going to have to
worry about that.
But anyway anyway, I'm gonna leave it like that.
That's a good place to leave it.
Pick it back up tomorrow.
Okay everyone.
Thank you so much for joining me for another episode of handmade hero
is a pleasure coding with you.
As always, it feels good to have our projection nail down a little bit
more into be based off real world values and we kind of got everything
into a much more comfortable place.
I think tomorrow, it's probably time to tackle ground chunks because
that's our last place where we're kind of not really thinking through
how big things should be pixel wise and M wise and stuff like this.
So, and that'll also, I think that'll probably give us a chance to
expand ours.
Handling out, one more level so that we can actually start to now have
ground that is properly cashed at different heights, and all these
sorts of stuff.
So I think that's the next obvious thing to do.
It's a good thing to do, and we should do it.
So that's what we'll do tomorrow.
I hope you'll come back and join me.
Same time, same place, 5 p.m.
Pacific Standard time tomorrow on Twitch.
I hope to see you all here.
In the meantime, if you would like to follow along at home, we do have
a pre-order on the handmade here at org website, if you preorder
Order the game.
You get the source every day after I finish coding.
So you can play around with it at home, which is great way to learn
from it.
If you want to check that out.
We also have a patreon page, want to support the video series.
You can always subscribe to that.
It's very much appreciated.
We also have a forum site where you can go to ask questions and
there's some stuff on there like pork to Linux and mac and anti-that
pisode guy just good stuff.
If you're interested and finally we have a tweak, but tweets, whatever
the days scheduled start time is if you want to catch the stream live,
that's the way to do it.
Just check out, check out the tweetbot either.
Subscribe to it or just check it periodically to see.
What the schedule is.
Alright, thanks everyone for joining me.
I will see you back here tomorrow until then have a wonderful coding
day.