Start recording.
Hello everyone and welcome to handmade here on the show.
We could have complete game live on stream.
We are back after quite some Hiatus.
I was away in San Francisco, working on doing some optimization on the
witness and then of course, we had handmade Khan and yesterday.
I wanted to give my chance my voice a chance to recover before doing
the stream because we were out to like, 2 a.m.
or something after handmade con.
I went to the bar with that people were having sort of the after the
info.
After party at out of there was probably like 30 or 40 people there
from handmade kanso.
We were chatting pretty late and my voice was dead by the end of it.
I was pretty horse on Sunday, but yeah.
So we are back now and I don't know for those of you who are, maybe
not who don't follow us on.
Molly rocket.com.
You may have seen this post.
If you, if you were, if you do follow us, if you don't follow us, you
may have missed it.
Basically, there is a art pack for handmade hero that went up and you
should have received an email notification about it.
Didn't it doesn't really matter because as long as you have your
download page where you download the code every night and in even if
you don't, you can go to this lost down, look thing here and do the
have it recent thing.
If you go to that, send out a page, there's now an art pack and you're
going to need the art pack for a lot of the stuff that we're going to
be doing on the stream going forwards.
And there, this is the first art pack.
They'll be more and those art what these art packs actually are is,
they're essentially like art that yangsun's been working on that.
I've packaged up into the format that we
All designed on the stream so that we can essentially plug them into
the game and start using actual artwork that we want to use.
So, if you haven't already downloaded that art pack, it's pretty big.
I think it's like a hundred Meg's or something like that.
You're going to want to download that, get that downloading.
And I've actually got it here.
I absolutely downloaded it.
I've got it here on on my machine, so I'm going to go ahead and grab
it.
It'll be a little zip file here.
There is a hundred eight megabytes compressed.
And so if I go in here and I open up my handmade hero directory,
right?
You can see that I've got in the in the data directory.
We've got these hhas.
Remember, they're the things that we made to test out our system and
what's in this intro are, as you can see, is it's another, it's one of
those packaged hhas, right?
So all I'm going to do is, I'm just going to unzip this into this
directory.
So that now I've got the
Aha that we distributed that's the art pack and you can see, once I
decompress, it's pretty big, it's about half a gig, right?
So that's just a bunch of art from Yankton that I packed up in there.
And what we're going to do today is I'm going to talk a little bit
about that and just kind of show you what's in there and discuss what
we're going to do with it.
So that you kind of
so, you can kind of have
All about perspective on what's going on there.
Okay, so it's a first day back.
We were right in the middle of doing some, debug code.
I'm going to put that to aside aside for just one second so we can
talk about this stuff.
And the reason for that is it's like, we've been away for so long now.
I don't feel like there's any particular need for continuity because
there's, I mean, yeah, we've been away so long that anything that you
were thinking about, you've definitely paged out at this point.
I know I certainly have.
And so what I want to do is just kind of talk about this art Paxton
Out here now and I want to get it in and just kind of show you how to
work with it.
Especially if people want to play around with it on their own just so
they know what's going on.
All right.
So now if you remember correctly, I'm going to go ahead and build our
game and just run it here.
If you remember correctly, hhas are automatically loaded by our game
engine, right?
So when we run the game, it's going to automatically go.
It's going to automatically load that ha because it's in the data
directory, right?
And it's going to automatically load them all.
So basically what happens is that ha gets picked up just
automatically.
We don't add any code for it to already load it and consider it.
Do and all the things in it active, right?
But what I had to do, obviously, when I made the data pack is, it's
got stuff in it that we hadn't named yet.
And if you remember the way that we kind of named things in our in our
asset system, right, I actually think it's in file formats, that H is
we've got sort of these asset tags and we've got these asset types,
right?
And the asset tags in the asset types are things that we use to
identify assets in the game, so that we can load.
Them.
And so, what I had to do is I had to add new assets types in order to
say like what the right things were there as packing and basically
what I did is I added asset like opening cutscene right, which is a
place that we store a sort of information that that it goes with our
opening cutscene.
And also, you know, similar to that.
I added a tag shot index and a tag layer Index, right?
And so what, these were, the way I decided to do it.
Let me just give you a little bit of an idea on how the breakdown
worked here is.
What I did is I said well, okay, here's a day.
221 is I said, okay, you know, it's this supposed to be a real game,
right?
Like I said, professional quality game, professional quality games,
have cut scenes in them.
Write a little intro cutscene to kind of like, set the mood or
whatever or that plays during the attract mode before you start
playing the game.
So we kind of have one of those and that seems like the most logical
thing to put into the game first.
Because in terms of programming, it kind of gives us a way to kind of
get our feet wet, right?
Because it kind of gives a way to do some very simple animation work.
But before we try to start doing the harder core animation stuff,
which is like when you know entities in the game or actually like
interacting with other entities, there's a lot more logic there.
It's not it's not a pre-scripted thing, right?
So a cutscene
Usually easier, at least in a 2d game.
Certainly it's usually easier to code the the stuff that's necessary
to support a cutscene than it is to code.
The stuff that's necessary to support the in-game interactions which
are all going to be certainly more Dynamic and less predictable and
all that sort of thing, right?
So I started with the cutscenes because that I thought would be the
easiest thing for us to program and then we'll kind of move on from
there.
So the art packs will kind of be like cutscenes first and then you
know entities and scenery coming in.
A future packs.
So this is like the cutscene art
And the cutscene art is structured in the following fashion, like any
cutscene, there's a series of shots.
So essentially we have the notion that there's like, you know, shot
one shot, two shot 3, and so on up to shot in, right?
Which is the last shot and these are essentially like things that will
be showing on the screen.
You can imagine them as a little, you know, pictures that were going
to show on the screen for part of our cut seam in normally maybe you
know,
All we wanted to do was just show a still image.
Like, you know, here's the little handmade hero guy and he's got his
little glove there and he's like, let's do this, right?
If we want to do something like that, then we would just have a single
bitmap and we just put it on the screen and we'd be done right but
that's kind of lame.
So what I want to do is do a little bit more of an interesting style
for the cutscene, which is to say, I wanted to have multiple layers
that kind of did look a little bit of a parallax, same thing, right?
And so what I did is I had Yang should draw out so that basically each
shot consists of a series of layers, right?
So for shot one, we've actually got like layer 1 layer 2, you know.
Oops.
Layer 3 and these are designed to be composite on top of each other.
So you know, if you've got this sort of a thing maybe the handmade
Hero guys in the front maybe then there's like the orphanage of the
back and then maybe there's some like Hills or something.
And that way we can kind of have a slow sort of Zoom pan effect
happening where you get a little bit of nice Parallax in there.
You get a little bit of nice depth to the image, right?
And it really just makes the cut scene.
Look a lot more professional and interesting as compared to just
sticking a single, you know, image up on the screen, which isn't
really going to
You two look like at the Quality level, that we might like to have for
a professional game, right?
Just it's kind of a mature in my opinion.
So you should be able to know how to program something like this.
So that's the way I made it.
And so what I did was I said, okay, all of our assets that are
involved in the opening cutscene will just get asset opening cutscene
as their asset category and then they'll be tagged with two things,
one will be the shot index and one will be the layer index.
And so basically, what you could do is you can pull out
Out any given shot and layer by just saying, I would like the best
match for opening cutscene for this shot, this layer and it will give
you back that one and off you go.
So, the reason we asserted in here, right?
Like, when I ran at the first time,
Is because our asset count is actually going to be higher than the,
than the allowed number right.
The allowed number is just going to be whatever we said before, and I
insert a new one.
So that's going to hit the assertion.
Say, hey, wait a minute, there's more than they're supposed to be than
what I understand like, what's going on, right?
So if I recompile it now, we should be fine.
And now, you can see that our game is running as we would expect it to
run, like it was before, and now we're loading that ha up now,
remember we do all of our loading on demand and so that ha
Aha, it's not actually loading.
Half a gigabyte of data especially on a system like this, which is
running on a conventional, hard drive, 7200 RPM hard drive, not a
modern solid state drive with fast transfer speeds.
There's no way it would have loaded 5, 500 megabytes in an instant,
right?
You can see, when I run this at pretty much.
It's instant, right.
And it starts up immediately, it couldn't do that.
And it's so, again, it's not.
I just want to reinforce that, I guess not actually loading the HSA.
It's just loading the header of the age of 2, h, a and so that it
knows what assets are in it.
And it's doing the merge with the other.
Aha.
So it has a single asset table that it can use, but it's not actually
loading it.
It won't load the actual bitmap data till we go to try and use it.
Now, that's exactly what I'd like to do.
Now, for the rest of the stream, I'd like to try just loading in some
of that data show you what's in there and what I mean by that
multi-layered stuff.
So we'll try to get a little bit of that working on the stream today.
So if I go to handmade dot CPP, the first thing I want to check is, I
don't remember what kind of asset workspace.
We're starting in right now.
So when we do you know create game assets or whatever it is, this this
if you remember like we kind of have a little asset manager system
thing here, that takes care of our asset loading for us.
This this function right here that we call.
We pass it.
How much we expect it to be able to use for storing those assets.
And if you take a look, what we did is we set that number 216 and
that's pretty good for testing.
And we probably want to do that because you probably asked bugs in our
asset system.
So in the future, we're going to want to test that a low.
Number certainly just a bulletproof or two.
But at the moment that is much too low, because if we're at 1080p, I
just want to again, get you in the habit of doing some of this math
and thinking, about this way, if we're at 1080p right, which is where
I wanted yangshin to Target.
So we kind of, when we did the art, we made sure.
They would be good at 1080p.
So if you have 1080 P, that's a 1920 by 1080 screen, right?
And of course it's it's going to be RGB and Alpha channel.
So it's four bytes per pixel.
That means every one of these layers,
Layers could potentially be at least that big.
And if there's, if it's got some bleed, if it's got some ability to
like pan, it could be even bigger than that, right?
But just to give you a little perspective on that 1920 by 1080 times
for a take a look at that number, right?
That's that's actually eight megabytes right there.
And so with 16 MB, we wouldn't even be able to load in probably one
cutscene.
It would, it wouldn't even be able to load a single frame because
there isn't even enough memory there to load in just
Set of layers.
So we really do need this to be something more like a working set of
like you know something more reasonable.
It could be more like that, right?
That's certainly plenty because if you do 25th divided by 8, that's 32
cutscene layers, you can probably get by with that.
We might want more but you get the idea, right?
So if that's what we're doing with our game assets, that gives us a
little bit more leeway, that wouldn't change anything in the running
here, it just means that.
Now, the asset system won't have to thrash, right?
And like
I said, we will want to set that down to lower numbers.
It will expose bugs in our asset system because we haven't really
tested the asset system yet.
So we will want to do stuff like that but this just now is not the
appropriate time for it while we're working on another system.
We can assume that the asset system works properly for now even though
we know we probably want to do some heavier testing on it to actually
get the bugs out of it but we don't care about that.
We just care that the interface is what it is and and so that we can
read the stuff to it.
So we've upgraded that a little bit
And that's all good.
But now we want to do some of this cutscene coating.
So what I'm going to do here is I'm going to go ahead and just make a
little handmade cutscene file just because this is stuff that really
isn't going to affect anything else in the game.
And so I'm just going to kind of stick it over here so it doesn't get
in my way.
What I'm doing stuff again.
A lot of people ask me stuff about how you divide stuff into files and
the answer is, it's just your own personal convenience.
I always compile everything into one single translation unit anyway or
if I have to, I break it up into, you know, two or three.
If I
Absolutely have to.
But in general, I think is one translation unit, and so files are all
mushed together at the end.
Anyway, so really this is just because I just don't want this stuff
clogging up my the rest of my code.
I'm just going to squirrel it away here.
So what we're going to do is again I'm not going to try to
overcomplicate this at the start.
I'm going to start as if I've never written a cutscene before.
I'm just going to go with the basics and then I'll show you as we go
some things that we're going to kind of want to start pulling out of
it again, compression oriented programming approach there.
Just some things, we want to start pulling out to make it easier on
ourselves to write these sorts of things.
All right, so the first thing I do is is the absolute.
Most basic thing we could possibly want to do, which is just take the
first shot and render all the layers, right?
That's it.
That's all I want to do.
And so what I'd like to start with, is say okay let's go ahead in here
and do like just render cutscene or something.
I don't even know what it's going to be called and then we're just
going to go ahead and do the same kind of rendering that we've been
doing everywhere else where you can kind of see this sort of stuff
Happening Here, Right?
All the sort of things we were doing, so what?
Going to want to do is is, is basically set up everything for the
cutscene render.
So when we do this, we're going to need the render group obviously
because the render groups the thing that allows us to actually push
stuff on there.
We're going to need stuff like the transient state that like the asset
like the game assets, right?
So we're going to need stuff like that.
and then we're going to have to do is when we get in there, we're
going to have to do things like setting up what we expect our lens to
be right, like how we expect
To view stuff and we're going to have to set up.
We're going to have to make draw calls to basically like get assets.
We want like this sort of thing here, right?
We're going to have to do something like that, and we're going to have
to actually push it to the renderer, right?
So I'm just grabbing the code that we have, like, so this is really
all the sorts of stuff that we're going to be needing to do.
So, let's take a look at what we've got here.
When we pass through the render group here, we
Add the draw by first to know what the width and height is, right of
the drop off your stuff.
So I need one more thing which is just the draw before I believe
that's a bitmap right yet.
So I thought
Like so and so what we're going to do here is say, alright, let's
settle this stuff up.
We've got M to pixels and I don't know what we want to do with me.
Those two pixels here.
This is a little bit weird.
We I feel like we've always kind of danced around that a little bit
and it's just kind of a little bit a little bit janky, right.
You can kind of see like like this is the stuff is kind of a little
bit weird the way that it works and I don't super love it.
So I think we may put it to do in here.
Say like, you know, unify this stuff because I feel like we kind of
need to unify it with this and you know just kind of like figure out
exactly how we wanted that to be treated, right?
But anyway,
In here, once we've got this stuff set up and we can play with this a
little bit later.
Like I said, remember this is the code we just said like okay, how big
is the Monitor and M?
How big is our our draw buffer width.
Okay that's how big that's going to be in terms of how big a meter
should be on the screen or whatever it is.
Right, that sort of stuff and that's really kind of just going to be
fixed based on our preferences and and our testing.
Right?
But anyway so taking a look at this stuff.
What we have to do now is go, all right, we want to load these things.
Out and you can see we've got you know are matched Vector weight
Vector, if your member how these things work we just say all right I
want to pull something out of the asset system.
I give it a vector that kind of describes what's going on and it just
does a best-case match.
Again we probably have some work to do on that sort of thing in the
future but for now it's going to be totally fine.
The work we have to do in the future, is basically to accelerate these
things will probably have to compress the asset Vector because as we
get more tags, but that's a separate issue.
So anyway, if we have an asset Vector system here I'm going to want to
be drawing a bunch of these, right?
So I'm just going to make a for I Loop here where we just go through
and we grab out layers sequentially and we put them on the screen,
right?
And so we can see exactly how we would do this, right?
We got to create our match Vector in our thing, we've got for a match
victory.
In a weight Vector, we have our shot index and our layer index are the
two things that we're going to want to do.
And that's just literally going to be something like this, right?
Where we set them.
and then our weight Vector is again going to be
Back.
Same thing.
We just want to look at those two things evenly.
We'd like to get them back.
Exactly.
And I assume we always want something from the right shot, right?
So we're going to want that to obviously be heavily weighted and then
we want the layers but really we could leave us like this because
we're only ever going to be asking thing for things that match
exactly.
We never need it to really like, you know, find something else.
But if we were really being honest about it, we could imagine doing
something like this so that it wouldn't pick it up.
It it's that's this is really it's really too stupid because we're
never actually,
By using the fuzzy matching capabilities of the system, we're always
going to be asking for a very specific thing.
All right, so if we imagine something in here, we're just going to say
that we have a particular shot index and that shot in so say is one of
the very first shot.
I decided to not call the first shot 04.
The figured shot.0 might indicate like the null shot.
Like if you're trying to say there, we're not talking about a shot.
So then from there we've got layers.
And what I'm going to do here is I'm just going to do a layer index.
I'm gonna only just pull out just a very first layer like,
First layer of the that shot and we're going to render just that one,
right?
So we're going to do something that looks like this, we're going to
say, okay, here's my pic map, ID, or whatever it is.
I'm going to say, give me the best match bitmap from the asset set.
I want you to load the opening cutscene, that matches this weight
Vector, right?
And I'm going to move this guy in here as well.
So we update it every time, right?
We could probably do something like that.
And then I'm going to draw it, right?
And I'm just going to draw it right in the center of the screen.
Nothing particularly fancy there.
I'm just going to literally draw it.
You know, layer image like so.
That's all I'm going to do.
So that's my render cutscene call.
When I compile remember, this file is not actually being compiled yet
so I have to add it to the build.
Remember, this is a single translation unit build, so I can literally
do that by just coming in here and saying, all right, and made
cutscene dot CPP is now smushed directly into my main file and now
it's being compiled and hey, we didn't have any compile errors.
Look at us syntax Masters, but we're not actually calling this yet.
So if I ran the code, as you expect doesn't actually,
Do anything?
So if I wanted to do something, I would have to go in here and
actually render the cutscene.
Now, what I can do is say, alright, you can go ahead and render all
the stuff under the cutscene, all you want.
And then I'll just run to the thing on top of it.
But since the cutscene is going to be pretty heavy hitting for our
render system because lots of stuff layered on top of each other.
I don't really want the render it up, spent time running other stuff.
So I think I'm going to do at this point is start to sort of bifurcate
this code a little bit and put the other stuff into a separate piece
of code, right?
So I'm just going to say, all right, as we do this stuff where we have
like a socket render group and we do the begin renderer at that sort
of stuff.
I'm just going to come in here and say, all right, here's render.
Cutscene will go ahead and put render cutscene in.
Here like this.
And then this stuff is going to be something else, right?
I'm going to take all this stuff.
I'm going to
Just be something else entirely.
So, all of this stuff that happens here, everything right up until the
point where we actually flush the render system, right?
Which would basically be like right here.
Why do we render before we flush the Sim region?
Is that does anyone know why we're doing that?
I don't know why we're doing that.
But okay, that's a bit weird.
And I'm going to change that right now because that doesn't make any
sense.
All right, so point, being that's just weird.
And I'm going to figure out why we did that maybe there was a very
good reason for it.
I don't know if there was or not, but we're going to find out in a
second because I don't think that should be happening, but maybe
there's a reason
That that has to do with like, how things were ordered or I don't even
know.
So, I guess, we'll find out.
We'll find out in a minute.
Probably should have put a comment in there.
It was like, Hey, warning, don't move this.
If in fact, it actually needs to be moved or rather couldn't be moved
since I didn't.
I'm just gonna go ahead and do it.
And we'll find out later.
Alright, so I'm going to just go ahead and get that working and we're
going to call this, you know, rendered game or something like that,
right?
And we're going to see what it needs.
So it needs the game state.
And it probably needs the trance State as well.
And we'll see if that's enough.
It needs the world.
The world I think is just game State worlds.
Yeah, it is.
So it doesn't really need to get that passed to it for the most part,
right?
I can just make that be something that it grabs out of what it gets.
Let's see what else it needs.
Input.
So it needs some input.
That would be lets see render game.
This would be actually update and render game for being honest with
ourselves.
So, this is game input.
is not cold game, but I think it is
Right.
Yeah, and mouse p is something that can just be gotten from the game
input, if I remember correctly, right?
Yeah, so that actually can just be moved in.
Yeah, yeah.
I'm just gonna go ahead and move that up because nobody else needs it.
So again, really, all I'm doing is pulling this code out because
that's it really was our game, our render game and we never, we just
kind of left it in there because we could.
And so we,
It.
Alright.
So, render memory is an Undeclared identifier that makes sense because
that was something that we actually did out here.
and so, hopefully that all
Up now properly.
Yeah.
Alright so I'm going to see if that works.
Let's take out let's we're not actually doing the cutscene now.
I'm just going to do render game.
Or rather update and render game.
So just go to call that now and see if we still have our game, right?
I'm just going to make sure that I extracted that code properly and
didn't mess something up.
When I pulled it out because you know, you never do know.
Things are getting fairly complicated in here as we get more and more
of our engine stuff together.
You end up with a situation where, you know, you could easily break
something that you hadn't really thought too hard about before, right?
Alright, so there we go.
So this is the just as we're cleaning up, our temporary memory stuff.
it looks like what happened here is again, there's cuz as we sort of
end our memory stuff
I feel like, where does the memory?
Where does the memory stuff actually happen?
If that should happen before checking the arena.
So that actually should happen here right?
Because what happens is where do we get our temporary render memory?
We get it right here.
So we get the temporary memory for the renderer here which kind of
pushes that onto that sort of stack of temporary memory.
We do a bunch of stuff and then we end our temperature.
A remember here for it inside, update game and render.
It's going to it's going to get SIM memory and then release system
memory.
So I feel like that should have been work because they are nested
properly but don't actually know yes.
That was just because I that was just because these check Arena calls
need to come after the temporary memory stuff had happened and we
hadn't done that.
So that was a, that was incorrect.
So there we go.
So now if I want to switch from a game to our cutscene, I should be
able to just do that, right?
And now if I run this code in theory I should be in that that cutscene
rendering code.
And so now we can start working on the cutscene rendering code in the
goal is to get like you know a little bit of a cut scene on a scene
here on the screen here and we've got
Got 30 minutes to do it.
So hopefully that won't be too terribly difficult.
But who knows, right.
All right, so let's see.
The first thing we want to do is we want to make sure that we're
actually getting back a bit map here that were actually able to load,
you know, something that we can draw, right?
So, what I want to do is I want to step into the code and I want to
see.
I want to make sure that in render cutscene, that were actually
getting back a bitmap that we could actually draw, right?
So, let's see what that comes back.
As
So that is an actual bitmap and then here, we're going to go ahead and
push that bitmap on, so hopefully, it'll be able to actually do that.
You know what I'm going to do, I'm going to step to it here.
So in theory, if we come through here, we should be able to go.
If it stops showing me bunch of Constructors for things, we should be
able to draw that bitmap and let's see what we get.
Okay, so there's that height.
Oh,
Well, probably won't see anything.
If I pass a height of 0, I probably need to pass the height that I
actually want this thing to be for the moment.
We'll just pass 10, which is just an arbitrary hide.
I made up
Hey look, it's our bitmap.
I gotta cross make the screen larger enough to see it.
So there is just a layer again, doesn't really make any sense because
we're only seeing one of them and I don't really know how big I want
it.
But of course thanks to the live Loop live coding.
We actually don't even really need to make much in the way of tools
for this creating this cutscene because I can just sort of you know go
ahead and do something like this where I just create oh
There or not.
What did I do wrong there?
I just change the height.
Strings are equal.
Broke their interesting.
So it looks like we have a wee look.
Looks like we have a bug in our debug stuff for which is not
surprising because we weren't done with it with looped, let with our
left coded thing stuff, so that's that's actually fine because I don't
care about it at the moment.
So since we were in the middle of that, I'm just going to
Leave that for now and go ahead and turn off handmade internal so that
we can continue what we're doing.
So, there we go.
All right, so back to what I was saying here is our thing I want to
just make it get sort of a little bit bigger.
I want it to kind of take up a little bit more of the screen if that
makes sense.
So that it kind of that back layer kind of occupies the entire space
if that makes sense, right?
And so what I'm going to do is I'm going to say alright let's say
that's just 14 units.
High here, I'm just adjusting the layer to it fits, right?
So that looks pretty good.
So maybe now I'll just say like, okay, let's
See what happens if we load two layers in a composite them on top of
each other.
There we go.
There's a little light there.
I'm going to add three layers and composite them on top and that's
like too big.
So that layer clearly needs to be like sized and placed a little bit
differently, but I can keep going like this until I get all the layers
of the shot on there.
And you'll notice that this first shot is the familiar one that you've
seen many times before, I think there's only eight layers in it.
Like there's no, I don't think there's any layers passed that one.
Yes.
Oh, that's that's all the layers in it.
You can see it's kind of morphine.
Just now like action did some polishing on on.
It's a little more detail than the one that we use for the backdrop of
that sort of stuff.
But we kind of we have all those layers on there and that's all well
and good, right?
So hopefully you understood all that we didn't do anything,
particularly resting.
All we're doing is taking these and rendering them through our
renderer and and yeah, and that's about it.
What I would like to do now is start to work on the on that sort of
again, placement and movement that sort of
That's sort of basic stuff that we want to do with a cutscene, okay?
So let me see that went a lot faster.
I was kind of expecting that to be what we did today, but that's
already on the screen.
So I can't really make the be that what we did today because we got 30
minutes of me sitting
I'm going.
That's what we did today.
That's not very interesting.
So I'm going to jump right into the discussion of exactly what's going
on with that particular sort of cutscene situation.
So like I said, this is what we've got here, right?
We've got a cutscene and as you can see, it's got layers one through
layer 8, right?
So essentially we've got something that looks like this, right?
2, 3 4.
And so on all the way up to number eight and they're all getting
composited together.
Whether I don't know what our frame rate is right now, actually, but
we could kind of test that by having a thing that allows us to kind of
move it around a little bit.
Or I guess if I went and fixed the bug in the debug system, I could
see what the frame rate was but I don't really care at the moment.
So I think our render might actually handle this.
Many layers was kind of crazy but that's just the way it goes
sometimes computers because they're so darn fast.
But point being this is what we're trying to put together.
Now each of these layers is something that we want to
Out of position in space, right?
Because what we're trying to do with this is simulate, the fact that
we have some sort of perspective in our scene.
Now, we talked about this, a bunch.
We talked about this before when we did our sort of stuff where the
hero kind of goes up a level, and we wanted to kind of zoom in and
out, but just to recap, what's going on here, right?
We have looking for the top down now, right?
This is the monitor right here and here is our eyeball, right?
There's our little eyeball looking at it.
What we want to see is we want to see that things in the background so
layers that are back here and layers that are in the front here.
We want to simulate that perspective foreshortening effect where
layers that are in the background as we might move.
So if we move forwards, we want layers here to become bigger at a
rate, that's faster than layers that come here, we already built that
into our system by having Z depths, right?
So what I want to do is I want to make the z-depth.
I want to be able to change these Z depths that we have
So that each individual layer has a different Z depth and so that when
we pan or Zoom, the camera in and out, we get different perspective
effects, right?
So, the first thing I need to do there is, I need to create some
notion of a camera movement that will happen over time, okay?
And so, what I'm going to do to do that, right?
You know, I just need some space to store it again.
I don't care where that is right now but as
As we sort of think about these cutscenes a little more.
We're going to kind of pull that out into a little bit more of a
concrete notion of what's happening.
But what I can do for the moment, you just say, okay, we've got a game
State here.
So all I'm going to do is introduce something temporarily down at the
bottom, which is like cutscene time and that's going to be a timer
that we can drive our cutscene time from right.
And so in here, what I will do is say like maybe when we do this
render cutscene maybe I'll just pass that in, right?
So we'll say what the cutscene time is.
And what I'd like to do is say wherever
Camera is like when we're doing this sort of thing that distance above
Grant, I'm just going to slowly Zoom the camera so that it gets less
than nine away, right?
So that the 0 plane is nine away.
I don't know why we picked nine that was just what we had before.
I'm going to say that you know, maybe we'll even just call it 10 for
now because who cares?
We're just going to set all this up based on that.
Initial number anyway, doesn't matter what you said it too because I
do anything.
I'm just going to make it so we Zoom between two numbers, right?
So as this cutscene time goes and it's cutting time is obviously in s.
We're always using S for our time.
So as our cutscene time goes up what I'd like to do is I'd like to
smoothly very the the distance above the ground based on that cutscene
time.
So what I'm going to do is I'm introduced to boundary variables for
this particular thing which is like cutscene start, right?
And that's going to be 0 0 and cutscene end.
And I'm going to say that that's like over
No five seconds or something.
I'm just picking a number randomly here and then I'm going to map this
cutscene time into that range and so I believe we already have some
routine.
We wrote that map's things into a link or a range.
You can see here, clamp, 01 map to range and what I'm going to do is
I'm just going to take that and I'm going to produce that clamp T
value.
Now remember, what this does, you can pass it in a minimum bound and a
maximum bounds like so.
And then you pass in what the actual value is that you're looking at,
which is our cutscene time like, so, oops, that should be capitalized.
Perhaps,
We'll just put in here.
Thank you to Ron Gilbert and friends for introducing the word cutscene
into the game development vocabulary.
Since he was at Camp, handmade con.
I think it's only right to give him and his team credit for
introducing that term.
They as he said at the conference, he was not the first person to do
an interstitial in a game, but they were the people who coined the
term cutscene, so, there you go.
Alright, so here we go, is cut scene.
Goes basically what we're going to do here.
Is going to take that time, going to map it into our range.
So now we'll get it.
We're going to have here, this is like our normalized T.
We now have a Time Value, right?
And now you know what, I should probably be consistent here.
Let's just call that t cutscene T.
Start
The end.
And I kind of like that for some reason.
So let's just do it like that.
And now we have a value that ranges from 0 to 1 that tells us where we
are in our cutscene.
And so our distance above ground could just be like whatever it's 10
meters away - you know it goes, you know 5 m forwards over the course
of the zoom right?
so, as this
Up that will happen for now.
I would like to kind of mod the, the value so that it wraps around and
we don't really have a good way to do that, but I could do something
like, you know, you know right here.
Do we have modulus
Don't know that we do.
I don't think we do intrinsic modulus.
You do not have an F mod, it would appear at least as far as I could
tell.
Yeah, I'm not seeing it, not seeing it.
So, you know, that's just the way it goes sometimes babe.
So, yeah.
So, I don't know what to do.
Exactly there.
Maybe we'll do something like this, so we can wrap the cutscene
number.
I don't actually think we need to do that.
Lets just ignore this for now.
Let's pretend.
It never happened, doesn't really matter point, being, that will give
us that zoom over time.
So all we have to do now is go ahead and actually use these values.
So, what we do render cutscene, we can pass it.
Game State cutscene time.
Like so and then we can just update the cutscene time.
With however much elapsed, right?
So I'm just running a simple timer and and I'm just advancing the
cutscene as we go.
I don't know where we compute, there it is.
So you don't know where we have that value but there we go.
And what I want to do is say if game State T cutscene is greater than
5.0 for now I'm just going to wrap it round back to zero.
So that we can just basically Loop the zoom.
And so if we tap back to the game you can see what I'm talking about
here.
So here is US just kind of in our render is holding up remarkably well
I can't believe that software rendering, rendering a bunch of Stack
stuff on top of each other with.
Absolutely no.
Yeah, just and and it's doing the by linear scaling and everything.
It's not 60 frames a second here, but then again, we're not compiling
and release.
I kind of interesting to know.
I'm sorry.
This just it always blows my mind how fast computers are these days.
Let me just, I just want to know what are we in release.
so, if I owe to this,
Well, I guess we already build that part in release so we won't really
get any faster so never mind.
So that's like as fast as we're going to go with those things.
Stacked on top of each other without additional optimizations of which
there are many we could do.
But anyway, there you go.
So we're going to go ahead and sort of fuss with that.
So what I wanted to point out is that as you can see when we zoom in
now since all of our layers are at the same Z depth, we get absolutely
no depth.
This image has no depth at all right, there's no like
There's no feel to it, right?
And so as a result, you know, the the layering effect is totally
useless.
There is no point in having these layers.
Because as we move, they don't slide relative to each other.
So, what we want to do is we want to start positioning these layers.
Different Z depth.
So that that way, they'll be able to get some of that Parallax effect,
right?
And so, if I remember correctly, the way that we have to do that
because our render system is kind of a little weird.
I still don't love the where we ended on how we do those transforms
and this was because of the two and a half D thing, but two and a half
D things.
Always.
That's never fabulous, right?
But we have that, that transform thing and the way that I believe
happens, is, yeah, transform offset P, right?
So what we need to do is every time we set that transform offset P, we
can sort of set where we want things to be placed, right?
And so if we do something like this, you could imagine placing each
thing further back in Z like, you know, - layer index.
So each layer gets a little bit further back from where it was
That makes sense.
In fact, I should probably do something like this times are too like
that.
And so that's just going to do that, that sort of offsetting.
And now what you can see, right as I do that is, you can kind of see
that all of the layers your scale.
Now I did it the wrong way, you can see that the background layers are
doing faster and the reason for that is layer index one is the further
back farthest back layer so I actually want to move them further back
in z.
I want layer 1 to be the farthest back and layer 8 to be, you know,
the one that's
Closest.
So, actually what I should be doing and say like let's start at
negative 10 or something and add with each layer index, one thing
forward, and so if I tap back now, now you can see that we're starting
to get that Parallax effect, right?
You can hopefully you can kind of sort of see what's happening there,
right?
So again let's let's switch to sort of our loop loop Live code editing
mode here.
So we can kind of just edit this on the fly into two little bit to get
it to where we want it to be.
So let's start thinking about
This problem a little bit more specifically here right now and I don't
know what's the best way.
You know, I might, what I might do here is say let's go ahead and do
delete Window like so and let's just give myself just a little sort of
bar to work with maybe up at the top here.
Well, or maybe down at the bottom because we don't really need to see
that many lines of code.
Let's see, there we go.
So that's probably okay for now.
Oops, thank you windows, for adjusting my window, in a way that I
totally did not want, okay.
So you can see that I can kind of exaggerated this effect, quite a
bit.
If I want to buy really like exaggerating that depth right and don't
want that go away.
Oops, forgot.
That's got to be.
This would have to be more like that in order to do that.
So there is more
Duration of the death.
I really wish it would not do that.
Emacs, why do you think I want to see that?
Why?
I don't care.
You know what?
We're going to put that.
Right over there.
Okay.
Okay, so let's try that one more time.
Here we go.
So you can kind of see how we can kind of stratify these out even more
so than we are right.
I can keep going with that.
And you can kind of see, we can get some pretty ridiculous effects in
terms of how we sort of stagger this.
And the further we go back the more sort of Parallax, a you get there.
Now the problem is as you go further back the things get smaller and
so on.
None of these things are mild to scale.
So what I hope you can tell if we want to sort of put this cutscene
together a little more appropriately is we're going to have to start
specifying.
Each individual layer where we want it, placed how big we want it and
what Z we wanted at, right?
So that's the first thing that we're going to do is we're going to
break this out into something, that's a little more prescriptive about
how things are supposed to be placed.
So, what I'm going to do is, I'm going to say, let's say that we've
got a vector3, which is layer placement, right?
And I might even make it a vector for, for now, which is basically
like, you know, the XYZ and then the height right, the scaling factor
for it.
So I'm going to do that and I would do that for each of our layers,
right?
So here they are.
Like so and we're just going to say like okay they're placed at 0 0
you know 0 and scaled it what were we doing the scale right now?
14 right this would be what we would do.
You know each one of these?
I don't remember.
We should have probably noted what each of these was like.
So oops.
So we probably should know what each of these was and I guess I could
do that right now if I wanted to, but we can do that in a second.
So anyway, here's the XYZ and we've got like, you know, layer 1,
layer, 2 layer 3, layer 4 layer, five or six layer, 7, L, 8, me that
one right there.
And so, what I'm going to do is I'm going to grab that layer
placement.
Every time we go through here, I'm going to say like, okay, the
placement for this layer is going to be whatever it says in that table
like so.
And for each one of these, I can say, okay,
We're ever going to place the sky.
We're just going to place it at, you know, wherever this says to place
it those XYZ and the height of it's going to be whatever.
It says, it's height is, right?
That's it.
That's what we're going to do.
So, now everything's got the same placement or Parallax is going.
I'm going to revert to just looking at a single layer.
So there's that single layer, right?
And it's not doing anything in particular, right?
All makes sense.
So, this one is kind of I don't know, for lack of a better term.
This is our Sky back, you know?
Or something like that, right?
And what I'm going to do with the sky background is something
specific.
I want the sky background, not to move at all because as you know, if
you move forward, the sky is so far away that it's not going to zoom,
no matter how far you walk towards the sky, any realistic amount.
Human motion, unless you're in a rocket ship is not going to make the
sky, get any bigger, it's infinitely far away for all intents and
purposes.
So what I want to do is for the sky background, I want to cheat.
I want to say that, no matter what we set, the distance of the camera
to, it's going to be that far away as well, right?
So, whatever the distance above ground is, is going to be that.
So now, it won't move in theory at all.
I hope, right?
Least that's my goal.
Although that doesn't seem to have worked in any way.
So I take it.
Back that compiled, right?
Over right.
Yeah, that compiled just fine.
Oh whoops.
Did I forget to take out by the way?
No, I didn't.
Did I?
Yeah, it's all fine, that's all good.
All right, so I want this proportional distance above ground, so we're
going to the - oh well obviously duh.
So what I actually need to do is I need to take this part the teen
normal part, right?
And I need to make sure that I just subtract that t normal part away,
but that I still feel like that should have worked.
I feel like if we move, I feel like that should have been 0.
I put it in the wrong, put in the wrong slot.
That's the size, that's the Z.
Why am I so dumb?
I don't know why I'm so dumb, I guess I just am.
Alright, but it still doesn't work.
So, I'm not that dumb.
I mean, I am Dumber.
Maybe that even means I'm even dumber than I thought.
I was at the beginning, but point being I feel like if I move this
away at the same rate that it's that the cameras moving, it should
stay fixed.
So I don't really know why it's not and that's kind of bothering me a
little bit like I don't get it.
Does that make sense?
Like, why are why are we not?
Being I know why?
That's the zeroth entry.
Not the first.
Yeah.
So I should do that.
Right?
That's better.
Hey look.
It did.
What I expected when I actually looked up the actual value shocking,
isn't it?
So I should be able to do distance above ground here.
Am I do distance above ground here?
That means it's going to be placed.
I don't know why this is complaining.
There we go.
So if I do distance above ground here, now, I should get it.
So I should be able to basically adjust this guy's settings and change
where he's at, of course distance above ground means that it's where
the camera.
So I need to actually place it, right?
This means I'm literally sitting right on the camera which is not a
particular good thing.
So I need to place it back from the camera at least a bit, right?
So I'm going to place it 100 meters back.
Let's say I don't know why I'm placing it there but I just am and
we'll sort of play with these as we go.
And then I'm going to scale it up till 2:00.
I'll that it encompasses the whole screen, right?
However, big that would be.
So there we go.
Maybe make it a little bit bigger so it comes to full screen almost
there, sit like hundred and twenty maybe so it's going to be maybe 140
to Encompass the whole screen little bit more so not quite there.
Okay, so now that's not moving anywhere.
That one's fixed.
So now we can move on
The second layer and what's the second layer?
That's like this weird little Skylight thing, right?
This is kind of just a little light that Yankton wine in the sky that
was just kind of supposed to be there.
And so this shouldn't really move very much at all.
So this should also be pretty far back.
I would think but it should move maybe a little bit, right?
Just a little bit and so if I go ahead and make this roughly the same
scale as the thing like that you can see it kind of just move just a
little bit.
That's probably fine.
So this is weird Skylight, right?
So now I'm going to turn on layer 3 like so
And layer 3 is way too big right now and probably needs to be moved
back quite a bit as well.
So I'm going to move that back quite a ways somewhere like there.
You can see that looks like it's the sky is maybe moving a little bit
too much.
So I might actually also kind of kind of maybe dump those guys even
more into the background because that does look maybe sort of right
with how much the the ground when should be doing.
So, I'm going to go ahead and just move these back a little bit here,
as well.
And then,
Them, right?
So I'm going to go ahead and make that bigger like so it's not the
right size, I don't actually know.
Oops.
Yeah.
So that is about the right size.
300, 300.
There we go.
And so now that's moving because I want there to be a pretty big
difference between those two in terms of movement and that's good.
The the that row of trees is obviously you know, a little bit small.
So I'm going to go ahead and just make that a little larger there.
It is, that looks pretty good, but it's probably placed a little bit.
Oddly it should probably be sort of.
Out of should probably be maybe a little lower higher.
I'm not entirely certain so, you know, I guess what I'm saying is it
probably should be moved like up or something like that.
I'm not super certain so we'll see as I go forwards, where how we want
to place that in terms of X and Y?
All right, so here is adding another layer on top there.
This one again, obviously needs to be moved back quite a bit, so I'm
going to move it back into sort of, that, that background.
And this is, this is, I guess I
Name these as well.
This is the first row of trees or that the back mostro.
This is like hills and trees, right?
So, and okay, so I moved it back.
They're going to have to scale it up a bit again.
So here we go.
That's still probably not the size.
It should be and it looks like that wouldn't have very much Parallax.
I might drop that guy back a bit, just a little bit there so that
there's a little bit more between them.
You can kind of see that start that Parallax starting to kick in there
so it's pretty nice.
Just go ahead and start to pull these together a little bit more.
It's get that, get that up a bit.
So you can kind of see how the Parallax is starting to come together
there again.
This guy looks a little bit too low so maybe we're going to have to
move him up a little bit.
As well, sort of fill in those cracks.
Why did that not move up a bit?
Should have just me or did that?
Not move up at all?
What's going on?
What's going on here?
It's compiling but it's not moving up.
Oh, because I'm editing the wrong one.
Nice.
Fantastic.
Not the brightest bulb on the tree sometimes guys, not the brightest
bulb on the tree.
All right, so moving that up.
Let's see here.
Going up to 10.
And maybe move this guy back down, I don't know.
It's that look more right to you will see again getting that vertical
position, right?
It's probably going to take a while.
We're probably gonna have to get a little bit higher up in the layers.
Thank you for the five minute warning.
They're all right.
So this guy again, probably going to have to be, you know, more like
this or so, right.
Like something more like that.
I don't actually know how Parallax, see.
We want it to be so it's a little bit hard to guess sometimes, but
there we go.
So you can really start to see that that parallax,
Fact coming into play, right?
You can sort of I hope you hopefully you guys can kind of see how that
that's feeling now, you know, as a kind of does that sort of slow that
sort of slow pan and
all right.
So yeah, that's looking pretty good so far.
I kind of want to see just what that looks like in general.
You can kind of see The Parallax working relatively well.
So let's go ahead and add those last ones in here.
This is Hills and trees too.
Front Hills and trees.
So let's get layer 6 in there.
That's like on the side.
I also don't know.
Is this guy a little too scaled right now?
Not actually sure.
Yeah, it looks like he is a little bit to scaled, it's probably should
be more like that.
I don't know if this guy should be more like this as well.
Possibly hard to say.
Nope, you can still see the edges of that guy.
So that probably should be more like that.
Yeah, so.
Alright, let's move this down a bit.
So that's probably about right scale-wise.
Yep.
And then this guy, I don't know where this guy is.
Let's say he's at - 30 maybe.
Oops, not negative 3.
You're 30.
I said,
And then he should also be quite large, and he's also kind of off to
the side to the right side.
You can see he's kind of a right side only sort of piece.
I don't know how big he supposed to be completely honest with you, I'm
not really sure how it's intended.
But this is like right side tree.
And fence.
So I'm going to move him over like a hundred units or not.
Let's try 10 units.
Let's try 30.
That looks more right to me.
I feel like you should be moving quite a bit faster based on where he
is, wonder if maybe that would be a little bit better.
Possibly.
Again, it's really hard to say, sometimes with some of these things.
It's really very like, you know, kind of tuned to your preference, all
right?
And so, let's just kind of finish up.
We got number seven, which is our orphanage, right?
And we'll put that back - 20 and then we'll just scale it up to
roughly how we think it should be, Maybe dirty.
So 35.
It's a little too small at the start, so I guess it's got to be more
like 40.
Right.
Looking pretty good.
And now we're just need one more layer and then we're done.
So there is our form, you know, our front most layer and we got a
scale that one up to its normal size, whatever.
That's going to be probably about 30.
although that one looks like it's really close, so that might be more
like negative five, like so,
So it looks like we need to move our orphanage down a little bit.
I would say just a bit from where it is.
So I'm going to go ahead and just drop that guy by 10 units or so
oops, that's too much.
That looks that looks about good to me.
Right, looking pretty good there.
And so now we just got to finish up this guy which needs to move over
a little bit.
I think maybe one unit
Maybe two.
And probably down a little bit.
so, maybe
Maybe something like - 2 units, down.
Here, maybe needs to be just a little bit bigger.
All right.
Okay.
And so now the only problem that we have left and I'll go to the Q&A
in just a second here.
The only problem that we have left now is as you can kind of.
See, weird zooming towards nothing now, you know, as game developers
as programmers.
Maybe you're not supposed to be experts in cinematography and that's
fine.
But hopefully you would at least noticed something a little bit
peculiar here.
Which is to say that we probably should be zooming towards the action
which is going to be the orphanage, not the distance and you can work
on Azumi into nothing here.
So what I'd like to do in addition just really quickly is go up here
and add some code.
So that instead of just distance above ground here when we actually do
the camera stuff we can sort of offset these guys as well and so there
can be sort of a little like vector3 sort of like a V3 like you know
camera offset things something like this and
Yeah, and so when we do that camera off set, we can sort of do an X Y
as well.
So RT normal can go like v-- camera, start the camera and you know,
sort of thing.
And then our camera offset can be, you know, camera start.
I don't know if we do linear blend, I think we do where we do camera,
start, whatever that t normal is and camera and like this, hopefully
that'll work.
We don't have linear blend yet.
Yes, we do linear
Blend blend linear.
How do we tie know?
We have come on, folks?
I know we've written this before.
There's no way.
There's just no way, seriously.
Lerp, that's what we called it.
I don't love that term.
I don't know why I use that, but I guess I must have had a reason.
All right, so if we have camera off site here, what I can do is just
say, okay, whatever the placement x x y z is, we could just subtract
the camera placement from that and that effectively offsets everything
by wherever the camera actually is right.
It's basically just moving the camera, is moving everything by the
same as what the camera is going to move by, right?
So if I want to do that, I can set the camera start to be 0, 0, 0,
which is the sort of the star technique starting alignment of
everything.
But then when we move the camera for words, I can move.
Kind of down and and and to the left or something like that.
So I can, I can do something like moving it one unit in each
direction, right, like that.
And so now in theory when we do that, I should be able to do something
where the camera kind of, we could essentially pick the focus Point by
moving the camera as we go.
So I move this up to the top here so you can kind of see now we're
starting to focus a little bit more on the action, which is what we
want to do, right?
We want to kind of focus on the important parts of the image.
So I'm just going to tune that.
To the part where it's relatively.
It's relatively plausible that that might be what we're trying to look
at.
I happen to know because I've seen the rest of the cutscene art,
obviously that we're trying to zoom in sort of towards those windows
over there on the side.
And so we're looking at something a little bit more like this.
And so if you take a look at this scene, now, I'm pretty, I'm pretty
delighted with that.
That looks, that looks pretty darn cool, right?
And, and so, you know, we probably want to in this little bit more,
but for 41 days worth of putting cutscene stuff together, that's,
that's pretty nice.
It's looking pretty good.
And, and I think
We're pretty happy with that, right?
So yeah, so that's where we're at and and we'll tweak it a little bit
tomorrow.
So let's go ahead and go to the Q&A.
And I don't have text read anymore, I had to format the laptop for
handmade Condit was using that.
So let's go ahead and go to the Q&A.
I don't know if I can do this here from this one.
Yeah, there we go.
Let's see.
All right, folks, if you have any questions about the programming
here, please feel free to give it to me with a Q: so to speak.
Let's see.
Elephant, would you normally want to get the position scale for each
layer from the artist?
If so, how would you go about doing that?
That depends on whether or not?
The artist is familiar with any particular tool that allows them to
set up a scene like this.
A lot of artists if they're just straight, illustrators aren't they
don't know how to use like say after effects or stuff like that.
And so they just knew how to make stuff in Photoshop, right?
And so if you're working with artists like that, then the answer is
no.
There isn't any
A way to do it because they don't know how to set up a preview this.
And so you just kind of have to work with them and you where you set
it up and you could give them a, you could, maybe make a little thing
that they could use to tweak those values, right?
Like put up a little UI so they could build it in the tool and not if
you are familiar with working.
If your artist is familiar with with that like they normally work in
you know flash or something like that that allows them to set up
something like that.
Would be a move like this.
Then.
Yeah, the way you would do that is whatever that tool is.
You would have to write an importer for some
Data for that, right?
And that's going to be entirely dependent on what tool they use.
Because there's really not much of a way in Photoshop to do it.
If you really want to do it in Photoshop, you could have them set up
to layer comps 1, at the start of the zoom, in one of the end.
But that's really going to be hard for the artist because the artist
in Photoshop won't have the zine positioning.
Well, Photoshop does have some 3D utilities so maybe you could do
something there.
I've never played.
Those so I don't know and it's not really meant to be an animation
package even though it does have some of that in it.
So you probably could if they happen to know in Photoshop I do it.
But a lot of ours aren't I going to be familiar with those tools
either?
Stricken down.
I'm new to programming and no intermediate Java.
Only.
Can you explain what you use emacs for if you're using visual studio?
Yes, Visual Studio.
We are only really using its debugger feature.
That's all we're using.
So we actually build and edit code outside of visual studio.
So we use emacs to edit the code and we use a command line build.
So we don't ever use Visual Studio really for anything, other than
just the debugging process, if that makes sense.
I think you should move the sky light up a tad.
Bit.
Well, you know, if you think the Skylight should be moved up a bit,
that's something you should do on your build of handmade hero which
you can tweak to your heart's content.
I'm not really done tweaking this because I want to move the fence up
and do a couple other things as well but it's basically, you know,
it's mostly there.
Orlando Bloom.
I feel like we should have some deep voice narration.
Yes, that is coming, but that's kind of, you know, that's that's after
we get our cutscene shops in place and then we can worry about syncing
it to voice acting.
Did you ever have trouble while learning to program?
I'm currently getting my rump handed to me in Java class.
Well, yeah, I mean, I never took a perm in class actually in my life
because I learned to program when I was seven.
So I never got my rump handed to me per se, but as a child learning to
program.
Yes, if there is plenty of times, I just didn't know how to do stuff
and my dad was a programmer, and I'd have to call him in, and be like
that, can you help me debug this thing?
Because I'm too stupid.
And so, yeah, absolutely.
I can't relate to having trouble in a programming class because I
never had one, but I can certainly relate to struggling with things
because it does take a long time to become a good programmer and it,
there's a lot of things along the way that are stumbling blocks and
takes time, takes a lot of practice, a lot of practice.
Will we ever load PNG files.
If so, will we be writing our own loader or using SVG image?
I read that.
It's tricky to load png's or no.
No, we will never be loading png's.
We load our HHA files.
And so we we strictly load.
Ha files.
That is all we load.
Will your cutscenes be coded like this or be separate as data in a
separate file?
They will be coded like this because
Since we don't have any, there's no external tool for editing them
that we have.
There's no benefit to having them be an external files since our game
is currently our only preview tool
Let's see.
Do you need to know in depth linear algebra to do this?
No, well, I mean, yeah, you're not in depth, right?
You don't even know how to solve a matrix to do this, but you do need
to know at least Vector, you know, basic Vector stuff.
K.
You mentioned your code base is mostly independent for the most part.
Does that include random number generation or do you use the C library
for that yet?
My code base does not link to the C library, full stop.
My code base at work actually, doesn't link to any Library besides
kernel32.
So you only one
How do you handle 3D audio and your other engines and game's opening
allergy?
Implement something yourself.
I've never done 3D audio.
It's not my kind of thing.
I like,
I don't tend to really be interested that much in making 3D games
myself.
So I just never have to do that sort of thing.
I tend to like games where the audio is more authored and not it's not
about like placing you being in an environment or anything.
So I don't know if I ever make a VR game.
I'd probably worried about 3D audio but that's just not the kind of
game that I tend to be interested in.
Oh, the Scala has a gap at the top.
Is what you're saying?
We can kind of size that up a bit.
If you're worried about the gap for, I guess, like, yeah, we can, we
can move it up or we could size it up.
I'm not sure which would be better.
Maybe move it a touch closer.
Might also be kind of nice, maybe like,
That so it has a little more motion to it.
Have you talked further with Pat Wyatt about coming on the stream?
Or is that postponed for when Network becomes relevant?
I thought his talk was very touching in particular.
Yeah.
I mean, we're definitely going to do something with that, so we will
definitely be finding a way for Pat to do some streaming.
I don't know how we're going to do it just yet and it might not
necessarily be in the context of handmade hero because I don't know
that am a hero is really a networking, kind of a
Thing but you know will we will figure something out.
I just don't know what that will be, if that makes sense.
Captain craft.
Is this code going to be for a cinematic in the game or you just
testing functionality?
Now I know it's a cinematic in the game.
This is like the first shot of the Cinematic in the game of the of the
of the opening cutscene.
Should I use you and 32 T?
Over you 32?
You can use whatever you want.
I prefer you 32 these days, but if you want to use your in 32, T,
that's totally cool.
What do you think about adding lighting effects to the cutscene, like
a flickering?
Repulsing of the candlelight in the welcome sign.
Well, that's totally fine.
If you want to do it, that's not possible with the way that yangshin
authored, these art pieces, if that makes sense.
So there's no, the lights aren't painted separately, so they can't be
modulated separately.
That makes sense.
I mean, you could do a Cheesy thing where you just kind of like, you
know, masked out some things and kind of just flickered than that way.
But it wouldn't probably be particularly compelling if that makes
sense.
K.
I meant the image format before we pack them in the asset.
I understand.
We're currently using BMP.
So like I said, many times asset pre-processing is not cut part of the
stream so that's just it wasn't as the only point of that asset
processor that we've got in there.
Now was just to define the file format so that I could you do stuff,
like what I did where I uploaded assets that are packed in the file
format, so we will never touch that again.
That's like, as far as we're concerned, we have H A files.
They follow our file format, we load from them and that's it.
Insofar, as for adding more cutscenes or modding?
Wouldn't it make more sense to keep the Parallax constants?
Some where in the HHA file?
I mean it depends, it depends on what you want, right?
I would say no.
And the reason I'd say no is because if you want to support full
modding, we should we would probably add support for dll loading,
right?
In which case you can just add a new cutscenes by providing the code
that renders the cutscene
Right.
So I'd probably rather go that route so that the cutscenes could have
like Dynamic dynamism in them as well or be launched at any time and
stuff like that rather than trying to make up our own out format for
it.
Because in general, my opinion, art formats art form at stuff or like
data stuff, should only be for stuff.
We actually have an editor, like, an external editor for, you know
what I mean?
Because we don't have an external editor, then there's no point in it.
We could have just done a big code, right?
Super Caleb don't need to.
To use the 32 GB or 32 an opengl 32 for a few things.
You don't have to link to them know.
You can just dynamically load from them.
The only thing you have to link to is kernel32 and technically you
don't have to link to it so much as it's going to, you need to get its
its Base address to start with because without get proc address which
is in kernel32, you can't dynamically load anything, right?
So you need kernel32 but they're obviously their tricks.
You could do to not actually linked with it but there's not a whole
lot of point to that.
K, if you're running up in jail stuff, do you use glue or write your
own extension loader?
And load the function by yourself.
I have my own extension loader and I load the function pointers myself
long Boolean.
You could make a to DVR game, just room with a giant video wall.
I guess was like good and maybe someday I would
I have had thoughts like that before I believe me off topic.
Thank you for handmade kind of wash it twice already.
You're very welcome.
I'm very glad you liked it.
Purposely drifting not a question.
Just want to thank you for doing Hamid Khan and glad to see you back
during handmade hero.
Thank you as well.
And in fact, several people think of your hammock on thank you all for
coming and or watching it was really kind of amazing how much of turn
out there was it was pretty great had, I had a great time at the event
to and I like meeting everyone and seeing people at the like makeshift
Gatherings the like a dock Gatherings that that we had afterwards, for
pretty great.
So yeah.
Let's see.
Any plans for crude lighting and Shadow support for things like light
posts, light light posts.
Yeah, I don't know what light posts mean, we are planning on doing
lighting for in-game lighting.
That's, that's like the one major to do left on our renderer actually.
Gragas, will you show all content creation on stream to watching you
spend hours?
Doing cutscenes?
Might not be fun.
Yes.
Oh
Not to sound overly harsh but this is not supposed to be fun.
Making games is about doing work and I have absolutely no interest in
making the stream.
Quote-unquote fun.
It's strictly supposed to be educational and so part of it is we will
absolutely do 100% of the code that ships in the game on the Stream.
And since the cut Cinco chips in the game, we will be doing it on
stream and you are welcome to skip those episodes if you don't want.
But yeah.
I would say if watching me do it is not fun.
Then since I do it pretty quick compared to people who probably a g
before you're probably not going to be very good in terms of a
perspective career if that makes sense.
Set it for Q colons.
Out of interest.
If you wanted to implement a zoom that curved to the Contours of the
Hill forward drop forward, would you still look to implement that in
code or look at a visual tool for something like that?
Well, you know visual tools are usually for when you know that the
amount of time it takes you to do the work to support the visual tool
or create.
The visual tool is going to be less than the amount of work.
It'll take you make the cut scenes.
We only have like 12, cutscenes in handmade hero and they're all
basically like bisque like less.
In fact, this is probably one of the more complicated shots so it
probably only take us a couple days to make all the cutscenes.
So there's
Point in doing anything more complicated.
If you found that you started doing one, like what you were talking
about and it was too complicated for you to do without a visual tool
and you're spending like days on it, it's not coming together.
Then maybe you would want to think about hey is the right trade-off to
do something to support like flash or something.
So we can make it in there or whatever you want you know, Maya who
knows whatever you want to use or to make a little visual tool myself
to do it.
You know that's that's just a
Judgment call.
You have to make based on how long you think you see, things taking
and how much work you think it would be to make either an importer or
a tool that would allow you to do that because if it takes you a week
to write the Importer, then if you'd only would have taken you a week
to do the cutscenes, you haven't gained anything, right?
So, that's just you just, you got to figure that out, right?
Pinkie Pie, thanks for the stream.
K CI, you are welcome, the geek pirate.
Did you have to study algorithms in depth?
Or did you learn from on hand experience?
I'm not sure what that means.
I did study algorithms but it was usually, while I'm programming.
I mean, I did have an algorithm.
I've read algorithms books before and I read through algorithms, I
don't and I'm not necessarily using right at the moment, but I also do
a lot of practice with things and, you know, like, I'm
So weaker in areas of things, I don't use, for example sorting I
hardly ever use.
So I'm not that good at writing sorts for example.
I just because I almost never write them.
so, it's like, just
Even though I kind of know what they are.
They're less second nature to me than something like linked lists or
arrays.
Hash tables that I use all the time you know we're or any of the 3D
Mass stuff even like texture sampling and stuff like that is just if I
write so often that those are much more second nature to me than some
of the some of the classic data structures and algorithms like
You know, sorted trees or sorting I just I just don't write them that
often.
Crockett is vsync part of the render at least on my end of the stream
there is quite a bit of tearing not sure if the stream or not.
So no, we don't vsync right now.
And the reason for that is because on the on Windows platform, what
we're doing right now is we literally just blit our bitmap to the
screen.
We don't go through the 3D Hardware path, yet the 3D Hardware path
will do the vsync automatically for us.
And so when we switch, if that makes sense.
If we switch to
Going to the 3D pipeline, which we will somewhere down the road, then
we'll just have the vsync but our current renderer doesn't do any
attempts to be sink at all.
It literally just copies the buffer to the screen at that time.
That said on the vsync you are seeing is on your end.
And the reason that I know that is because since we're going through
stretch bullet that's actually going through Windows Aero which is
actually compositing.
On the vsync.
And so for example on my screen there is no tearing.
So I believe the tearing that you're seeing is actually on your end
but we are also not actually doing anything to try and guarantee vsync
on our end I believe but I could be wrong about that.
I don't know.
I'm trying to think if Arrow always does that or not.
But like just looking at it on mine, there is no vsync tearing.
There's no there's no tearing on my screen.
for example, so if you're seeing it, you're probably seeing tearing on
your video playback,
Captain craft.
Have any of the sponsors to your question that hammock on affected
your approach to certain problems?
I don't know because I haven't really been working on anything that
was related to
stuff.
I asked, I was pretty interested in Tommy's approach to like doing
everything by index in the art system.
I don't know that that will change my approach to anything, but it
definitely surprised me.
It was not something I would have expected and it was interesting and
it was like he had a very sort of rationale for it to it was like
fairly well thought through and so I just
I found that interesting and that would probably be something that I
would remember.
So I don't know that it will necessary change any of my approaches,
but
Was the Snowman intention of looking down to indicate a feeling of
sadness, or am I reading too much into it?
You would have to ask Yang shinai because I do a lot of work art
directing at Molly on our main game.
I try not to really art direct handmade hero, very much, so yangshin,
really just kind of decides on her own.
What things are going to look like?
And I only basically, like for this, I kind of just sketched out like,
here's what the shots are and and so on, and then she like does all of
the detail and unless there's something very specific
You know, I say like I need these sort of layers in it and I need it.
It's going to kind of pan this way and it's going to have these
elements, you know, but then I don't do stuff like actually do the art
direction of like it should be, you know, this way or that way or like
the Snowman needs to be sad.
Or I don't, I don't do that on this project because I feel like it's
would be just too much work.
And so, I try to let Yang should just do what she wants to do.
If there's something that I feel like really needs to be changed for
some reason I'll bring it up but otherwise
So I don't micromanage that at all.
Chism has a programming problem ever stumped, you even after Googling
and or collaboration.
So I'm not sure.
I understand the question because programming isn't
like, I don't know that I've ever been stumped by a problem because
that suggests that there's a like a like a solution to a program
problem, but there's no such thing as a solution to programming
problems, right?
There's only metrics how fast it was, how memory efficient it was, how
robust it was, how little code you could do it in, how well it
integrated with something else.
And pretty much almost all the time.
I always either know or feel like I could do better than what I did if
I wanted to
War time, studying the problem.
So I don't think I've ever been stumped by a parking problem, but I
every code I write is something that I could see doing.
Better job on by devoting myself more fully to solving it as a
problem, right?
So,
So yeah, I guess you guys are saying to add that as a quote, but I
guess.
Yeah.
I mean that just kind of seems obvious to me.
I mean, I guess it.
I don't feel like it really needs to be said like
In computer science, there are solutions to specific problems of the
form.
Like, you know what is the the worst-case running time of a particular
algorithm, right?
Like you can answer questions like that and there is like a specific
solution in the sense that there is only one.
Right?
Mathematical answer to that question.
But in terms of actual black writing, actual code that does stuff,
there is no solution to its there isn't even a problem.
There's just
Here is what the code needs to do.
It's assumed that if you know how to program, you will get it to do
that.
So then the only question is, what are all of the metrics that you
might measure how good that that particular solution is in the sense,
right?
So calling it a solution is almost wrong and I feel like, you know,
it's just our nominee nature that we say oh that solved.
The problem.
Are we worse?
Losing?
What we really mean to say is we implemented it, it's an
implementation.
It's not a
Ellucian, it's an implementation, any implementation solves the
problem or it's not actually an implementation, but each
implementation has different characteristics.
We might measure.
And by measuring those characteristics, we can compare the
implementations and decide, which one of them is the most appropriate
or best given our criteria.
Some implementations may be strictly better than others.
Other implementations might be better than others in some ways and
worse than others and some other ways, right?
And then particular pending on what you wanted to do, you may pick one
or the other as being a better.
Implementation.
When you are an intermediate programmer, how often is it?
That you use Google to help you look up solutions to hard problems?
It's a funny question, it's amusing.
When I was an intermediate programmer, Google had not been founded
yet.
Colonel Dragon, it may be
Obvious.
But there is an entire class of programmers that seem to think
otherwise, well that's unfortunate, but
What do you do?
Did you notice the Triforce in the windows?
Oh no, I didn't.
Like I said, yangsan kind of decides how that stuff goes.
I did not notice.
There's a Triforce in the windows I guess it's not quite a tri Force
because the top one is not divided.
In fact, neither is the middle one but the two side ones I guess our
Triforce.
It's not a it's not like a fully recursive Triforce but yeah, I didn't
notice that.
Students are three one of my mentors used to say that there should be
a book called algorithms data structures and trade-offs.
That is a very good thing to say.
Yes, I would totally agree with that.
All right, I think we're done with the Q colons.
So I'm going to wrap things up, close down the game like so.
Okay, save the drawing, save the drawing, save the world.
And there we go.
Thank you everyone for joining me for another episode handmade here.
It's been a pleasure coding with you.
As always, if you would like to follow along at home, and well, you'd
have some downloading to do.
But if you have to would like to follow along at home, you can always
pre-order the game on handmade hero dot-org.
And then you can go download the source code and the art pack, which
you will need if you want to follow along with all of our cutscene
work, they're going to do this week.
If you would like to do that, go to handmade out or here at, or
pre-order the game and it comes with all the source code and the
artists we use it.
So that's a good place to do that.
If you would like to follow along with a series, we also have a forum
site which you can go to ask questions, we have a patreon page.
You want to pledge?
Support the video series.
So he's much appreciated.
It's always free and release to everyone for free.
We also have a tweetbot that tweet the schedule at you and there's a
little I button here, which if you go to the website,
Light any time it'll tell you like you know in fact right now it'll
tell you the next time we're going to be live so if that helps as well
you can do that.
But the Tweet Bots a good thing to subscribe to because it kind of
helps, you know what the schedule going to be for the week if you want
to catch it live, speaking of the schedule for the week, I will be
back here at 5:00 tomorrow for probably throw a bunch of the more
cutscenes in there.
We should be able to get through like probably half the cutscenes
tomorrow now that we've got kind of everything set up, we can just
kind of do those
All once we have them all done, we will look at how to assemble them
into a full sequence and integrate that with the rest of our game.
So that would be pretty fun.
Hope to see you here for that.
That's 5 p.m.
tomorrow Pacific Standard time.
Until then folks have fun programming and I will see you guys on the
internet.
Take it easy, everyone.