Recording.
Hello everyone and welcome to handmade hero.
The show recoded complete game live on stream.
We are going to do some profiling today of our application and really
I guess what I mean by that is we are going to be expanding the
capabilities of our profile view so that we can look at the
performance more directly.
So I hope you will go ahead and unpack day 259 source code into a
directory.
If you're one of those,
Those people who has purchased the game on handmade here at Oregon.
Wants to follow along day 259.
That's what we're working with.
I am going to open up our project here and just oops, that's not where
we're going.
Let's see.
And me props.
There we go.
And let's run it.
Wait for it.
There we go.
So when last we met I love that.
Sometimes we don't get our texture downloads.
We should probably stop doing the multi-thread thing since we
determined that it wasn't necessary.
It's probably confuses the driver sometimes.
Anyway,
Here we are with our current profiler and like I said, we've done a
bunch of the work to support how the profiling works and you can view
a top-level profile now but it's not for usable because all we can do
is see, you know.
Well, there's a bunch of things that we have that are problems here.
Essentially one is that we can only see the current frame, right?
And it's going by too fast.
To really even see what's on it.
In fact, we get some texture loads and they Flash in here.
You can see them like those little red.
That's like a texture, a new
Are getting loaded for the layers.
You can see you can see that happening periodically in here.
But we have no way of ever even going back and looking at those,
right?
Because they just kind of blow right bias.
So we don't have any way to do that.
So we'd like to have a way to like be able to pause the profile, pause
the game and the profile together and be able to kind of like scrub
around and say, oh, you know, what was going on there?
Like, what are we looking at here?
That'd probably be a nice thing and the other more pressing feature
that we have to implement is this is just the top level profile bars.
This is how the frame is like being occupied at the very top level
here but you know when we go into something complicated like the game
we've just got these three big bars here that's like here's where the
time is being spent but game update is just an overarching block and
it's not going to help us understand where our time is going.
By just having a big old block that says game update.
So, what we want to be able to do, is when we're looking for
information about game update or things inside game update, we want to
be able to drill down to that and say, okay, let's look inside game
update and see what's going on inside that, you know, that particular
function, right?
And right now we don't have we can
Click or do anything.
You know, we have no interactivity.
So, there's no way for us to once we spot.
Something that looks suspicious we can't actually drill down into it,
which is a problem.
So I think that's probably the first thing we should try to tackle is
just allowing the profile view to be more interactive so that we can
sort of drill down into it.
And so I'm just going to go ahead and try working on that.
We did a little bit of that way back when and so we really just need
to sort of figure out how exactly
that's going to work.
Okay.
All right, so let's see here.
Let's see.
So inside our debug code.
I think they have what draw profile in.
We have our function, that draws the profile and inside this function.
We Loop over the events inside any particular given event like so.
And we start usually at the top level, the root, and we Loop over what
the events are inside that.
That's why we're getting the top-level profiles now Insight each of
these profile nodes there are children.
So every given profile node has the nodes below it.
So the
Nation that we want for our profile is actually they're right.
We do know for any given note.
If we wanted to drill down, we could drill down.
So the question is, you know, how are we going to actually allow that
to happen?
Now, one thing we could do is we could show a couple levels of drill
down, just right away, right?
And this is what people were asking for.
As far as, like, flame graphs are concerned or stuff like that.
But that's I don't necessarily know if that's specifically what we
would want but let's just start by implementing something that allows
us to see, maybe a little more of a of a drill down like so that we
can we can see more than one level at the same time.
Let's just start by doing that just to get our feet wet.
It's been a couple days since we've worked with this code.
So here we are inside the original Loop and We're looping over the,
the nodes.
And here we have a specific node.
and what I'm going to do is I'm going to say, all right if we're in
this specific node I'm now going to say that instead of doing a push
wrecked, call for this node, I want to try like maybe what we'll do is
we'll
we'll do a push wrecked outline, right?
And I don't really know.
Let me see here.
Cannot convert argument three from rectangle.
So I don't really remember what we supported.
We may want to add four push effect outline the ability to to pass an
actual rectangle, because it looks like we don't yes, we have to do
this nonsense.
So I'm going to add a little utility function here so that we can do
push record.
Outline.
The same way.
So we can do render group object, transform rectangle and then I guess
we don't pass a z.
For this apparently.
Huh.
Well okay, we do it because the offset has a bundled in that's why.
And so then here I'll just it's exactly the same call, right?
So that allows us to do that to draw things as an outline.
And so now, if I take a look at my profile right in theory, these
things should be wrecked outlined rectangles, see if that's true.
Although it doesn't seem to be that doesn't seem right?
Let's take a look at that call Push direct outline.
Get dim rectangle.
so, it looks like
This should be the same that looks the same to me.
So I'm not sure why that's not, why that's not.
Oh, I see why?
It's because we don't actually do.
We need to pass a thicker thickness if you will, because 0.1 we're in
pixels, that's not going to be.
That's not going to be much of a thickness there at all.
So I suspect probably what we need to do in order to have anything
show up at all since
Don't do sub-pixel anti-aliasing, on our rectangle, outlines at the
moment and probably never would since they're not something.
We actually, even draw for the game.
Let's go ahead and say in here that we have a thickness of like two
pixels or something.
I'm making that up but we'll see how that goes if that actually
changes anything and I don't think I feel like that should have Auto
reloaded so I'm guessing that didn't work but I'll double, I'll make
doubly sure.
That that's not the case.
I don't remember if we if that code is included in the platform crowd.
Yeah.
So I'm not seeing that outline and I'm not sure why I'm not seeing
that outline.
It kind of see how it doesn't show up in either renderer.
So what's the problem?
What's wrong with that?
Why is it that if we do a push wrecked
Right, we can see immediately that it's actually there.
but if we do a push fact outline, we can't
seems unusual.
So we've got the object transforms, we've got the thicknesses.
And we're trying these.
By the dimension.
I mean that all looks pretty straightforward to me.
I don't see any weirdness there.
We're just like drawing the, we're just drawing, four, rectangles, and
the rectangles are, you know, that top bottom left and right
rectangles and yeah, that should, you know, that seems pretty
reasonable.
I might step in there and see if there's anything particularly weird
about that.
Why wouldn't draw?
Here we go.
question mark, outline
And here we are.
Drawing our profile.
And let's take a look at.
Well, you know what?
I don't want to break yet because we don't actually have this open to
a reasonable size, so there we go.
And let's take a look here.
What is this?
What is this telling us?
And also let's take a look at this.
We know that actually one of our push wrecked outlines obviously
already works because this is the internals, like this is the
internals of the profile view but we know that push wrecked outline.
Oops, not that one.
don't we have I thought we had
You know what?
I guess we don't.
I guess that's our only pushed wrecked outline call for here.
Alright.
So maybe we don't have a test of it.
I was thinking what I was going to say is we have one because we draw
the those borders but I guess we don't really draw the borders because
they we draw them each as separate push Rex here.
So I guess I lied.
So we don't actually have an example of the push wrecked outline stuff
working inside.
Our our debug system at the moment.
So, yeah.
This is actually the first time
I guess that we're trying to make that happen.
Interesting.
Hmm.
You know what else is?
Kind of interesting.
This whole time when I've been like oh we need a backing transform and
all this other stuff.
There's a z value right here for our rectangles and I don't know why.
I wasn't just passing different Z values for things that were supposed
to stack on top of each other.
I think, probably just because I'm dumb, that's probably why I
actually
Well, probably just because I forget parts of the code that we've
done.
But anyway, point being so, this is our first possible, push wrecked
outline.
I didn't realize that.
So, that makes it a
A little bit different because we don't even have an example of it
working in here, but that's okay.
We know that it works in general because we obviously use it in the
game.
So I'm going to go ahead and stop inside.
Push deck, wrecked outline now, and I'm going to take a look and see
what we're actually passing in here.
So, here's the offset.
Here's the dimensions.
So inside this, it would seem, I mean that seems pretty
straightforward that we're trying to draw a fairly large thing, right?
603 102.
That should be a big, big rectangle.
So I'm not sure exactly why it isn't.
Let's take a look at the thickness.
ah,
so the thickness we're not passing the thickness through nice job
case.
Nice job dude.
Not at all good.
Right.
I added the thickness here but we're not actually passing it, so that
doesn't really help.
So that's probably it not really quite as interesting as I thought it
was going to be.
Well, there you go, they're still not working.
So, that's okay.
It's not, it's not, yeah, it's all, it's all good.
And I do believe this does reload right?
Because that's, yeah, that's in the reloadable code, right?
Yeah, it is.
All right.
So let's take a look at what I think this is now.
Hopefully, I think this is correct.
Thickness is still not correct.
What are you talking about?
How's that possible?
Ah, well, it's just a comedy of errors today.
When I went to test the regular rectangle code, I deleted it again.
Talk about making a bug out of nothing.
It's like really, there is no bug, everything's just working fine, but
I'm just you know just like slow on the draw today.
That's all I wanted.
That was all we were actually looking for.
So yeah again I'm just doing this so I can see things a little bit
more easily at the moment and so I can kind of maybe get a better
sense for it.
So here are those those rectangle outlines that I'm just going to
start by now drawing.
Inside those rectangle outlines I'm going to draw a secondary set that
allows me to sort of see what's underneath those.
And the way that I'm going to do that is I'm just going to make a
simple little
I'm going to make this into a more straightforward, little recursive
situation draw a profile like bars or something like this.
Something that I can call, you know, sort of repeatedly if that makes
sense.
And that will sort of that I'll just do each time as it goes down.
It'll it'll
Or should I say this each time as we go down it?
Will draw a new set of bars.
Now there's one kind of complexity involved here which is that the
lane count stuff is a little special because the link account only
exist at the topmost level.
So the link count kind of has to be handled differently because that's
how many threads there are.
Once we move into a particular thread, it can never have more than one
lane, right?
Because any given block is a chunk of time executing on a single
thread.
So anything that we draw inside there,
Air is not going to be as not going to have any lanes, at least not
thread Lanes, we might draw Lanes or something, from some of their
purpose, but not for Threads.
So I need to be a little bit careful about how we handle this Lane
count.
For example, like I said, is only going to be in the external code,
whereas the rest of this stuff, like the frame span, and the pixel
span and those sorts of things actually probably pertain to
everything.
And so if I was to come down here and
And grab this stuff.
I probably need to, well, I guess I'll make it so that we kind of when
we call it maybe we sort of pass some information about whether we
care about the lanes in here, because you can sort of see in here
where we've got the lane height and the lane index stuff.
Right?
And so, maybe, what I can do there is I can say, well, the lane index
thing with the thread, the node, and the thread ordinal sorts of
stuff,
Maybe what I can do is I can make that be something that's sort of
optional.
In fact, I guess when I could do is I could make that just be a
parameter that gets passed in in some way.
So maybe what I could do is I could say well draw a profile bars, for
example is going to take in some kind of an R32.
That's like the lame sort of stride like you know,
And then the lean height is a separate thing.
And so, what I could do is say well the laying index is actually what
I'm going to do to determine where I'm placing the thing.
That's true, but then the actual value, right?
So, I'm just going to say, like, here's my Lane why, and my Lane, why
is going to be this value, right?
Like this.
But then when I go to draw the thing, I'm just going to take whatever
the lane, why is.
And I'm going to add the lane height to it.
So it's always going to draw a box of the size that the caller
requested instead of doing that sort of convenient span thing, right?
So, it's always going to look like this code, like so,
Always going to do that.
but then,
We can pass in zero for the lane stride.
It will basically just be ignoring This Thread ordinal, if that makes
sense.
So, you know, it'll do profile wrecked Max, why - Lane stride times
Lane index, and that way, you know, if that's
Yeah, you get the idea.
So it'll be something like this and I guess technically, since we want
to align these, we're aligning these with the top.
What we would want to do is actually probably phrase it like this.
So we jump to the Lane that we want using the lane stride and then
we'd subtract away the height for the minimum bound and then draw up
to their right?
And that looks like something that we could work with.
So now what I need to do is I need to pass in some of this other
information, this stuff for example, probably needs to come out here.
Like so and let's see what x else gets passed in here.
We probably need all of this stuff.
Probably need everything actually.
So we probably still want to pass all this stuff in but now we're
going to pass the lane stride in the lane height.
And so now I'm just going to call this the draw a profile bars.
I'm going to pass all the stuff that we had.
I really need to remember to bind a key Allen actually added a center
view thing for us, but I haven't had a chance to add it in yet, my me
being stupid.
So there's my drum profile bars and all I should have to do now is
just past the lane height for both things and I believe that should
work right and what root node root node, I assume root node.
I think I've want to actually pass root node, not root event.
So I think I actually want that.
All right, so as you can see, which is nice actually, what we wanted,
no change to the profile view.
And now what I want to do is I'm just going to call this recursively,
perhaps once I might call it recursively.
So here I'll say okay when we get down to the bottom inside one of
these events, now I'll actually pass whatever the note is that I had.
And what I'll do is I'll reduce the lane height.
The Stride will go to 0, the lane height will go to a half and then
the rectangle that I'm going to draw in is just this region rectangle
that we got before.
So when we figured out where this bar is in our profile view, I'm now
just going to draw a profile bars inside it for the sub nodes of this.
Right.
And I can do this for all of the profile events like this has no limit
on the recursion.
This will just go forever, right?
And so if we wanted to just draw our entire profile stack, right in
its entirety we just did it right?
So here's like the entire profile and you can see the entire call
stack happening.
And every last little dude in here, right?
So, here's debug collation and so on.
Now the problem is when we move over something, it's now drawing both
things.
So what we would want to do is we want to tie into the hot, the hot
rectangle system here, so that we know will only get one thing being
hot at a given time.
So this will actually be able to be a little more scrub abby'll if
that makes sense.
But even that we wouldn't necessarily have to do, we could do
something a little bit fancier.
If we wanted to the way we would do that, right?
Is we
Say oops, what I do.
Drew too much stuff.
Apparently.
So what I could do is I could also say, all right, when we're doing
this isn't rectangle stuff here.
And I see that there's debug text to be displayed, what I could do is
actually make that happen in sort of a stackable way, right?
You could imagine some sort of nonsense, like, I don't know, like, you
know, inside debug state.
So here's here's just an example like
Where is it?
Debug extinct.
So here in debug State, I can say, okay, you know, Mouse text stack,
why totally making this up.
But then I could just say like all right when we draw this when we
when we hop in here we're going to make the mass stack.
Why reset to 0 for this particular, sweep through the drawing.
And then when I'll do is I'll say every time we put a line of text up
here where we do debug text out instead of doing like 010 or whatever
will actually just do this.
And I guess I can put 10 in here or something and then we can add to
it as well.
So I'll just be like, oh okay, debug State, you know, Mouse Tech
stack, y plus equal or minus equals I guess in this case 10.
And so now like everything that we tack on there will actually just
sort of tell us a little more information about what's going on.
So now we can kind of see like, oh, those are the two things that are
actually happening in there.
Now, obviously,
Leslie that actually is kind of neat now.
I think about it.
So maybe I actually want to do this for real and that case we just
want to know how big
What the line height is, right?
So that we can space the thought out properly.
And so in
Space that out all.
I think we really need to do is look at like the font information,
which I don't really remember much about, but obviously it should be
pretty easy to figure out because.
Yeah, here we go.
It's right here.
That's, that's it.
So rather than have that happen all the time, probably what I would
like to do is have an inline that's like, get line height.
Or get line advance.
Something like this.
And so that, that way we can just make this happen in here.
And I guess technically I don't really need to call it debug it's
obviously taking the debug State.
I probably should be more diligent about not putting debug in front of
things that are obviously because they take a debug State parameter.
So yeah, that's just going to be a way that anyone who wants to can
get a hold of that value.
And then we can just call that here get line advance.
And off we go.
Interesting.
So sis
Why is this?
Doing this this way.
Doesn't it look like the font info is sitting right here?
Riddle me, this Batman.
Can we just say debug State debug font info?
So do we need any of this is any of this stuff relevant at all.
I guess pushing the font probably is
so that it knows that it has to be loaded.
But I should check that at the very least.
This definitely doesn't right?
That's totally not necessary.
Oops, I want to take a look and see.
So push font.
Happens right there at debug start up so that's not necessarily
either.
Basically, none of this is
All right.
Well, that was a bunch of useless stuff that had been built up in
there.
So yeah, so now if we like hover over this, we can kind of see what
was happening there.
And if I go into our actual
Yeah, too much stuff to draw.
We may have to expand the size of our render group to handle all this
stuff if that makes sense.
Just because we're you worth sort of slamming on it a lot harder than
we were before.
Thanks to all the debug rectangles and all the other stuff that's
actually getting created.
So when we actually create the render group itself, which is going to
I assume be in here actually.
So you can see push buffer size and push, buffer are here and I don't
really know how big the push buffer would need to be to handle like
the ridiculous numbers stuff.
I suppose we could just make it huge for now.
So you can see like a bunch of get World Chuck calls.
It's happening in there.
So, this is pretty interesting.
You can see like, here is game update.
Here's game update, and render, and here is begin Sam.
So, you can see like, how much simulation times being taken, and
there's a piece in here, as well against Eminence m.
It's kind of cool, right?
You can see why this is pretty instructive.
Like
before we just didn't really have any idea of what was going on and
when or why or anything really?
And now we pretty much can put in our markers and get an immediate
idea of what's going on and then we can just hover over any given
rectangle to see what it amounts to, right?
And I suppose what I could probably do too is to simplify things, the
these things a little bit further, what I could do is I could like
I could try to like take things that are nodes that are too small and
maybe just aggregate them together or in some way.
I don't really know exactly how I might do that but yeah, like I could
imagine doing something like this.
So my next question is, what if I wanted to zoom in on this thing?
Right?
We want to be able to pause it so I know that that I want to have
happen.
And right now I don't really have a way to do that because as you can,
kind of see if I pause, I bad, I actually end up with the profile from
the paws, which is not what I want.
I want to stop recording debug information.
So we got to put that in there, but assuming that I do that, then you
can sort of see like what if I wanted like to see what was going on in
to sort of like dive in on that area there and see it in a little more
detail.
I feel like we want to be able to say like click on this and zoom, you
know?
I'm into that rectangle.
Does that make sense?
So that's what I want to do and I feel like you know, since this is so
jittery though well it doesn't really matter.
I want Implement both.
So we'll do pause tomorrow.
And today we'll try zoom in.
So what I want to be able to do is I want to click on this thing and
zoom into that rectangle and make that rectangle, take up the entire
profile region, right?
That's what I would like to be able to do so, like I'm here or
something, I click on this and it goes View, and then I can like see
that whole rectangle.
So, how would we do that?
Right?
and I guess,
I guess when we do debug draw a profile in
or whoops, raw profile in
looking at this thing, where we've got the thread interval graph, this
thing, when I call it in, I want sort of this thread interval graph to
be able to say, like, oh, the user did some interaction on it, and now
I'm zoomed or whatever.
Which means two things.
One is, I'm going to have to have some notion of that, in my debug
view because I've got debug views up here, right?
I don't know where they went here.
They are.
And so I don't really remember what we had here.
I guess we just had the inline block one with the dim thing, right?
So we had one of those
But I'm going to need something a little more fancy.
So I feel like I'm gonna need something here.
Like, you know, debug view profile.
Graph.
I don't know what to call this thing and that would have one of these
inside it.
So here's this block but then it would also have something like a grid
pointer or something.
Right?
That said here's the actual debug element.
I'm trying to view so I want to have something that's like because
You can see right here we're grabbing the root profile node.
Always what I want to do is grab some specific profile node.
So I want to have something I guess which would just be yeah, just
based on grid.
So it would be something like, you know, the debug wait here.
And that's the thing that would actually go grab and so, in order to
make this work, I need to have a thing that's like, oh, debug view
profile, graph.
Right?
Well, I guess I still want this.
Yeah.
Temporarily.
But debug view profile.
Graph profile graph.
And then, when this thing is getting its view, I don't really know how
this stuff even works.
Exactly to be completely honest with you.
So interval, the thread and we'll graph will just say, okay?
We've got one of these views back that belongs to this element, and
it's going to be the profile graph.
The profile graph obviously has the Block in it, so that's where the
rectangle information comes from now.
That's all fine.
Everyone's happy and it's great, and whatever, who cares.
And then what I can
You is, I can use that that ID now to fetch a new item from my, from
my profile node.
Now, this is easier said than done.
I feel like
because,
The problem is finding that node is tough.
It pretty much necessitates.
We searched through it.
In One Direction or the other.
Now, I believe what I can do is I can look up by the grid.
So we'll start with, we'll start with this.
So we have, you know, a debug node.
What's the word I'm looking for here?
We've got
Devo profile nude.
She's got the root node and by default, right?
That root note.
That that's going to be this.
In fact, I guess I'll set it to 0 but then I'll say assuming that
there is a frame then the frame
Root note.
It is like so.
And then I'll say if we got a root node, okay?
So what I want to do now is say like okay
Probably if there is no root node, set it to the default one, which is
this, which is just the whole frame.
But what I want to do here is actually search for a particular node
and so the way that I'm going to do that is I think what we can do is
we can look for a particular debug element by grid because that's a
pretty easy.
Look up for us to do.
We have a hash table, then we could look at the most recent event of
that one and get the profile, no doubt from that.
Which I think is what we want to do, right?
Does this make sense?
Anyone, hopefully, it does.
And so what I'm going to do there is going to say, okay, I need to get
that out.
So, we'll say, debug element, you know, viewing element or something
like that, and we'll pretend that we got that from somewhere will say,
if we had one of those because we won't always have one right, there
might be no element selected.
If we had one of those viewing elements, then what we're going to do
is take the viewing element.
Most
Isn't event.
And assuming that that's actually a thing, you bug scored events.
Then we would know that the profile node would be in there.
So there's the node.
Right.
So all we need to do now with the viewing element is we need to be
able to get you know do the do the hash look up which I believe we
have already so we have a way to do that.
That's like get debug element somewhere in here.
Cash.
No, no.
That's not the hash we're looking for people.
This is what we're actually looking for.
So, get element from event.
Is actually what we want.
Unfortunately, we don't actually want it to ever create it.
So I have to assume that what we want to do is something more just
like this.
This part right here, which probably we should wrap up in a like, a
slightly more convenient call because it doesn't, this thought we had
this already.
I'm going to go look and make sure we don't.
But really what we want to do is we want to say like get element, you
know, from quid is what we want and then we would pass the grid here.
So the view profile group.
Where did that?
That expression would get us potentially back a viewing element.
When we got it back, we would look at whatever that node was.
And that's the node that we would view.
Now the problem is, I don't think we have anything like that but I
don't understand.
I thought we did do this.
I thought we did look up The Thing by quid.
And I thought, the way when we were doing that is we had done the
interaction stuff, right?
We had done the drag value.
I thought that we had to do this to find where to stick the value
after we did it.
But maybe not.
Huh.
Shows you what I know about my own code.
What are you going to do?
But anyway.
So it looks like we definitely were doing it here even in debug.
Yeah, so in debug Market event we were it's just we happen to always
get it from the event instead of the grid.
We could I suppose store an event pointer.
I mean that's we have that information at the time.
So that it's probably fine, too.
I don't think I want to do that.
I think I would rather have it this way.
That's just my opinion.
So here is our get element from grid and move it up, so it's not
behind my head and let's make this work.
so, what we need to do here,
Is really just a sort of a paraphrasing of this thing.
Actually, there's really not much to it.
It would literally just be this.
I don't know why this is still called get element from event because
it doesn't take an event.
This is still get element from grid.
It's just once you actually have the hash Index, right?
So that's actually what the call should actually be.
Yeah.
And that's all fine.
I don't know why.
Draw a profile in is way up here.
When it's really something that uses a lot of stuff.
I actually don't know why we've organized this file at all.
Like we have it's kind of just hasn't like we want all those lookups
and stuff to be towards the top but that's not at all how it happened.
It may actually be the case that this is probably a good time to break
this into multiple files because it's pretty large, right?
It's like two hundred and two thousand five lines long
And it kind of contains both a core infrastructure thing which is like
how all the elements and all that stuff works.
And then also like a bunch of rendering code, that's like how you draw
it.
And really, I don't know that those things should be together like
that because it ends up in this situation.
Like we're going to have the problem of things coming before, other
things in here.
So yeah, kind of annoying.
Anyway, profile.
Roop, what will that be?
Profile graph.
Proof.
I'll graph go and if are not found because it happens below, which is
exactly what I was talking about, having to fix.
Let's see, we got our viewing element and this is going to be an
address.
There we go.
What is the problem here?
Frame route profile node.
What's the problem?
Oh, we actually pass.
We actually pass a store at event.
So actually this is this is actually fine.
We don't have to do any of that we can literally just go.
Here's the root node because we're passing it as a storage event so
that's all fine.
So frame is Undeclared.
Identifier.
That's true.
And that's because you're not supposed to pass anymore.
I've pulled that out into a variable.
Mr.
Didn't you see me?
Do that?
How dare you?
And so, yeah, now we're pretty good to go.
We just have to reorganize this code so that it can find itself.
There we go, get element from quid.
Get element from event.
cannot convert argument to
What are you complaining about?
That's because this is not called that anymore.
All right, so I think the only problem we have now is our stuff is
arranged in the wrong order.
So we just have to make that happen properly.
And if I were to reorganize this, I'm trying to think of how I want to
do it.
I could just make another file that's like debug you i.h, right?
And then put that stuff in there for now what I might do is just say
like okay let's just make this an internal call for now and then we'll
put these at the top right so although I guess actually these could
just be copied
All the way to the top.
So let's just do that.
and,
Yeah.
So what's the question now?
That's true.
We need to pass a debug State because otherwise it can't find the hash
table.
And off we go.
So now if we run it and I didn't mess anything up.
We shouldn't see anything happen.
Oh, of course I did mess something up.
Oh right at the moment we don't we are not safe at for passing 0, but
I think we do want to be meaning.
I think we want this code itself when we say to get the element from a
quid, I think we want when we pass a 0, we want to just be able to say
that results in nothing.
So like we assume zero.
We look to see if there is a grid.
If there is a good we parse it and we produce the result, otherwise we
pass through the zero, that way that code you know, user code can just
sort of do it and not worry about it.
Okay.
So now we're back in the same situation and all we have to do now is
make it so that when I click on one of these, it will, you know, it
will go ahead and make
That it'll set that good value to whatever it is that I click on and
so doing that with an interaction, I just need to make an interaction
type for that.
So up here, where we've got our interaction types
I just need something like, I don't know.
Debug interaction set profile.
Graph route.
Something like that.
and so then, when we execute these,
And I take a look at what actually happens.
I'm going to go ahead and
Put some some of this in here when we do set profile, graph root,
then, whatever.
The debug
Whatever.
The
Element.
Is that I'm looking at.
I want to actually make the well, I guess is that probably should be
an interaction.
I think about it.
But yeah in here I'm just going to do essentially the same exact thing
that happens with toggle expansion.
I'm just going to say okay
Get me the debug view for whatever the element is that I'm editing.
And then inside here I'm going to say get me the profile graph and I'm
going to set the grid of the profile graph to whatever it actually
needs to be.
And of course this point I don't actually know
Because we'll have to pass that through as like a variable.
So yeah, don't remember much about what we're interacting with here.
So there's the debug ID, there's the type, and then cures, like some
stuff that we pass I guess.
And so what I would want to do is I suppose pass a debug element to
this guy so that we can say, oh okay, whatever the debug State
interaction element, is that
That would be where the grid comes from like so and it gets set.
So, in order to do that, I need a way of setting that back where we're
actually doing the interactions and that's pretty simple to do.
So, instead of passing the mouse P, which probably like that was just
a hack I suppose to a certain degree for printing this out, but
What I can do here, a little more correctly, is I can make me move
this down here.
Oops.
I want this stuff.
I want all of this stuff to be accessible to me, actually.
So most of this stuff.
Yeah.
There we go.
So, what I want to do here is I want to make an interaction for that
rectangle and obviously we have lots of stuff for that, right?
You can kind of see what that stuff happening here.
And so what I want to do is I want to have a way of
I want to have a way specifying for that rectangle that the
interaction is to set the zoom right now, the thing that I'm not 100%
sure about is I don't actually remember much about how our power
interaction system actually keeps track of these things.
I guess all it really has to do.
You can see it happening in here.
Right?
Is the whoever the last person is through a rectangle, it just sets
the hot interaction to whatever the interaction was that was created,
right?
So really you know we could we could literally just do this.
We already know that we're inside the rectangle, so we set up this
way.
right, we know
Can make the interaction trivially.
This is our Zoom interaction.
The zoom interaction just has to have this ID.
This this elements ID the profile node.
So I guess we need to say container ID.
What I don't know what you want to call it.
The
The graph ID, we need to know.
We know the type is the one that we wanted to there where it's even
Direction set profile graph root.
And we also know that we want the element to be whichever one that
we're actually on.
So, it's this one right here and then the rest of the stuff we don't
care about
So that's that's what we're talking about, right?
So the only piece of information that we don't have is currently we're
not passing down.
Currently, we're not passing down the actual profile view itself,
right?
That profile mode.
So we need like the graph
The graph ID needs to come through here.
So that week so that it knows, you know.
Who it is?
And so that is something that we don't even pass to the profile
itself, unfortunately.
So it's going to have to be passed all the way from.
It's going to have to be passed down all the way from the people who
originally draw it.
So here when they do this, this graph right here, you can see us
getting the debug ID right here.
So we know that that's the correct debug Ade.
We just have to pass it when we draw the profile.
Like so
So yeah.
Get in there.
Let's take a look at what happens now.
Got about five minutes left.
So yeah, unfortunately, I don't have a back button the moment so that
doesn't help.
But let's say, I click on this green thing.
I don't know if it definitely set something, it's just we're now not
seeing anything, so it obviously didn't work particularly well.
So let's take a look at what actually occurred because something
definitely occurred.
So I'm going to take a break point at
Probably I want to take a break point at where we actually do that.
Clicking
I would guess so.
I think I want to do it at set profile, graph route,
I think, what I want to do is take a look in here.
So, I'm going to go ahead and zoom in on this.
And I'm going to take a look at what we actually get here.
Oops,
so here is ostensibly our debug View.
For the profile graph, it looks correct.
Here is the grid, we're going to set and so we have our debug State,
interaction elements.
Here is the grid that we're going to pass to that thing.
It's it's this and make owed him a debug collation like so and so
we're going to set that so that actually looks right to me
and so, here we are back at debug profile or sorry, draw a profile in
and inside, draw a profile in
I want to see oh well actually, you know what, I want to be one up
from this.
I want to be here and I want to see what happens here.
So let's go ahead and jump in.
Not.
There we go.
Here.
So here's where we're drawing the graph and I don't really care about
this stuff very much.
But here is the part that actually care about.
I want to know what we're looking for.
Are hopefully it's the same good that we set.
Let's see, frame display, that's I guess.
Now I think about it.
Look at what I happen to click on, so hopefully, that's correct.
So, let's see if we get anything back, we did get something back.
and,
Event clock.
So
It looks like.
It certainly looks like we've got an actual node now.
So the question is, why aren't we drawing anything?
It's a little weird, right?
Because it feels like we should be.
but I know why we don't actually have
our lane setup anymore.
So, we got a we got to do one more thing.
When we call a draw a profile in, we have to take a look and say,
well, if we're at the frame, then we would need to draw a profile in
and let the lane stuff happen.
But if we weren't, we would need to call drop profile bars because the
thread index is are going to be.
We don't want to draw offsets for the thread index has anymore, right?
That's not something we actually want to do.
Although, that's still should have drawn.
Okay?
So actually I'm not sure about that.
I'm still not sure why it didn't work.
So, let's continue.
Let's continue looking.
Now that I think about it, it still should have, it should have drawn,
should it just should have drawn in a narrower band but we should have
seen still seeing something.
I feel like
so, when I click on this,
I'm going to break.
Oops.
And then I'm going to take a look at what happens if I can.
Actually, there we go.
If I can like actually look in here.
So we're what's our profile wrecked?
Profile wrecked.
So is the center of the screen.
Gonna go ahead and hope that the center of the screen.
Is 0 0 because otherwise this is a nonsense.
Let's double-check
Yeah, that must be true.
So go in here.
Get out our root node.
There it is, although it has no children.
Why does it have no children?
Didn't we see it?
Have a child there?
All right.
Well, let's keep going.
That would be the reason why we're not seeing anything.
We draw the rectangle.
We look.
Here we go into the profile bars and I'm guessing we just, there's no
children.
So the problem is it's not it's not showing us any children for that
profile node
Hmm.
Hmm, so why aren't we getting any children for that profile node?
It obviously has one, right?
I mean, that is a child that is one of its children.
so, when I go to debug collation,
it should have a child node and yet, it doesn't
Why doesn't it?
Let's take a look.
I'm obviously misunderstanding something about that because you can
see us drawing first child here.
So when we were drawing first child, we drew a child for it and we saw
it in there but then when we click on it and it itself is the route,
There Are No Children.
Which doesn't stand to reason.
Mmm-hmm, why is that?
Why would it be that?
It doesn't have any children.
Well.
Let's take a look.
I'm going to set a breakpoint on the zoom interaction itself.
And then I'm going to move into there.
And so now let's take a look.
What are we actually setting?
So
here is our profile node.
It does not have a child.
How is that possible?
I mean we saw a draw a child, right?
What am I missing?
If we saw it, draw a child.
It has to have one.
Super puzzled right now.
It seems like everything is working correctly in the code, but of
course it obviously isn't.
So, I mean that has a child there, right?
And it's debug collation.
There's this child is debug end.
So I'm just going to hover the mouse there.
I'm going to set the break point here.
And then, I'm going to look to see.
Are we on the one that I think we're on.
Are we on debug collation?
Let's get rid of all this stuff.
We're on debug collation.
We know that debug end should have been a child of debug collation.
Apparently.
So here's our first child.
So the first child, there is a first child on it.
I think I was just
Maybe I hovered over the wrong one.
So there's a first child.
It doesn't have any other children but that's fine, right?
So that all seems good.
So there's
There's what we're expecting to put in there, right?
So we put that in there and if we go to the element and we go to the
most recent event of the element,
Does it have a first child?
It does not.
So I wonder is our element somehow busted is our back pointer busted.
There's the element saying, debug collation, which is what we would
expect.
So our node
We would expect this node right here.
Right.
Ah, but the current frame, these are actually from a frame that hasn't
finished yet.
Right.
Right?
So, if we take a look at frame a debug state, right?
We've got a frame that we're in the middle of collating.
The frame that we're in the middle of collating right now is frame 596
hacks.
That's actually going to be the most recent one because it's already
open.
So technically, what we actually need to do here,
Is rather than getting the most recent event.
We actually need to get back from the most recent event.
We need to get the one from our current frame which is kind of a nasty
search, right?
This is we don't have backwards and forwards threading in the debug
system and that's a problem, right?
Because what's going to happen is after we look this up we're going to
have the most recent event.
Where is it?
Most recent event?
We're going to have the most recent event, but we will have no way of
actually getting back because they're only threaded forwards, right?
So what we having a way of getting back.
So we would actually in here to find the one that we're actually
talking about we would have to search, right?
We'd have to do this nonsense.
And then in here, I have to do, if the search frame index equals the
frame index were looking for, right?
in fact, I probably could just say this
so if you know, we found the frame that we're currently on
Then we can use the note and it's the correct node, otherwise it's not
the right one.
And that search is super nasty.
That's slow, right?
But hey, now it actually works.
We need to get that pause in there.
Huh, I can't even click on that thing.
There we go.
All right.
So we're getting there.
So I think what we need to do is we need to actually make this a
little bit easier to look up as well, right?
But
not sure exactly how I would do that.
I have to think about that.
So I don't really know exactly how we're going to do that right now.
We kind of have this nice thing where we're going through.
We have like linked list so we can pull things out and reuse the
memory nicely.
But, you know, it may be that we have to change that to be something
that's easier to jump through and maybe we can do that.
Now now that we know exactly all the stuff we're storing, I don't know
what to take a look at that, but that's actually the problem.
So now we can actually do now we can actually
You the drill down correctly, I think in any case.
So if we go in here and we run the actual game game,
I can drill down into here and said, then we're now looking at just
updating render.
I can drill date down into update and render.
And now we're looking at that with the begins, Sam and some stuff.
What is this stuff in here?
I don't even know.
This looks like move entity.
So we've got a bunch of calls to move entity.
There's our calls to end Sims, so I can jump.
They're changing location raw.
So this will be pretty good like pretty soon.
We'll have very easily drill down.
We'll have to make like a back button, like I probably pushed makes
it.
So if you push that back button on the mouse, it goes up one, you
know, or something like that.
And then that'll make it pretty easy to drill in.
So that's that's pretty easy if that makes sense.
Yeah.
All right, so let's switch to Q and A for a sec.
That's good enough for today.
Deep Mist are you as productive in a single eight-hour?
Period, as you are on the show, over eight sessions.
Usually I'm a lot more productive because I don't have to be talking
the whole time and I don't have to I don't forget stuff about like
what I was working on, it's kind of hard to like do an hour.
Our chunk is not a good chunk usually
Popcorn 0, x 90.
Do you have that in your current game at work?
What you mean?
Drill-down?
Profiler, not sure what you're referring to buy that.
It's our debug tooling sis kaede enough to detect OS slowness IE
problems with Heap or memory performance Etc.
Well so, I mean the broad answer is it would probably let us know that
indirectly but no it doesn't show us that directly.
And the primary reason for that is just if you've ever seen this entry
on my blog,
This is the reason why we probably don't want to even try, there
actually is a thing called event tracing for Windows, which would
allow us to see when the colonel when the colonel took over and
switched out one of our threads for one of its own and vice versa.
And I document sort of the API here and I never even quite get to the
end.
I don't even think the what I show in here actually works yet, I think
there's one thing that it does.
Actually quite even do and you you will be amazed if you try to read
through and I'm I try to go through like here's how you might.
Here's how you can like tie into this event in tracing stuff in
Windows.
It's the worst API that anyone's ever designed in history.
There's never been a worse API, it's the ultimate worst API like that
you could do.
And so we're definitely not doing that.
It's that bad so we can't get that information directly.
But what we can do is see if there are things where stuff spikes in
weird ways where it looks like a kernel event, may have happened in
there for example and that we could see because those change over
time.
Now in terms of your specific question of keep or memory performance,
obviously we don't have any, he poor memory performance problems with
the OS because we don't use the OSS Heap.
So it can't slow us down because we don't ever call it.
When doing playback is the debug info, showing the pass Epi info?
No, it will show the current CPU info.
So it would show what was happening.
When that frame was replayed because like our debug playback stuff
actually it doesn't play back the behavior of the game, it plays back,
the player of the game code, it plays back the inputs, and they
recreate the game code dynamically, if that makes sense.
Oscar new are only in c.
/C p.
I don't know what that means.
Sign a cool.
What type of game is this EG FPS RPM, Etc.
It is like a adventure Reaction game popcorn to X 90.
Yes, profiler.
Guitar me 7 I discovered why I didn't see the font rendering I'm on a
25th 560 by 1440 screen with two hundred percent DPI scaling.
Do I have to use a specific resolution to make it work?
I'm pretty sure that has absolutely nothing to do with why you don't
see the fonts.
Because we don't go through Windows DPI scaling for anything.
It might be the font generator so if you try to generate your own font
files, maybe there's a problem there.
I don't know.
But in terms of the game rendering, it's not affected by that.
The game doesn't use Windows fonts services.
Hurry.
I mean, it was there a factor in, not implementing moving backwards in
the threading system not really.
There's no reason why we can't put it backwards.
Lincoln there.
The question is just is that even enough?
Meaning do we need a way of Random Access jumping two frames, in which
case they need to be more like circular arrays?
You know.
So yeah.
Yeah.
So I mean stated ultimately like so one of the things that we decided
to do while exploring the profiler stuff was we just made a system
whereby as memory got used up.
You just said, here's how much memory I want to use and as that memory
gets used up
It frees old stuff.
Now, that is potentially just bad.
Now that we kind of know, all the stuff that we have in there.
Maybe what we should have done is, say, know what happens is for every
debug element.
You create.
It gets this much memory and that's just a circular buffer.
So you can always Jump N frames backwards by just looking that many
entries back into the array.
From its current point.
Wrapped, you know, wrapped around and it wouldn't be super difficult
for us to change to that system.
So maybe what we'll do you know tomorrow or the day after or something
is just switch over the way.
We store them, because maybe that's a better way of doing it now,
right?
So,
Where we just fixed and we say, you always get 512 frames back or
something or to one of 36 frames back, that's how much we store and
that's it, or whatever.
All right, it is 6:30.
So I'm going to call it.
Poop.
Bloop.
Bloop okay.
Thank you everyone for joining me, for another episode of handmade
hero.
It has been a pleasure coding with you.
As always, if you would like to follow along at home, you can always
pre-order the game on handmade here a.org and it comes to the source
code so that you can play around with it at home.
If you want to see how it works, we also have for them, you can go to
if you want to ask questions.
Patreon page.
If you want to support this video series which of course is provided
free of charge to you and a tweetbot which tells you when we're going
to be live.
If you want to catch us live in the future, we will be back after 5
p.m.
Pacific Daylight time tomorrow.
In fact, and the tweetbot will tell you stuff like that.
I would also point out that the editor that we use on the stream, this
called for coder, you can type it into Google and you can find its
patreon page.
If you
Would like your own copy of the editor we use, you can grab it.
And if you are on the $5 tier for that, you get the customizable
version and I put in the source code, I always put the customization
file that we use the latest one that we use.
So if you want to use my same keyboard bindings, it's in there.
So check that out.
If you're interested in the editor, use on the stream, that's the one.
And yeah, that's about it.
I'll be back here.
5 p.m.
Pacific Daylight time tomorrow to implement a little more profiler.
Goodness it's getting to the point where it's probably going to be
good enough soon.
Again, we're not trying to make like any kind of professional like
debug system that we would sell or anything.
It's just supposed to be an embedded system for a game that serves our
own purposes and we can certainly upgrade it over time as necessary.
So, there's no need for us to go overboard.
Now that we've done all the exploratory work of getting the debug
system, capturing all the data and do.
These sorts of things we just need to make it usable for the few
things we want to do.
Make sure that's okay and then we can move on.
So we'll be doing that over this week and next week probably.
And then hopefully will be basically done with all that stuff and we
can move on to game coding using our debug system, which is nice too.
So that's about it.
Hope to see you guys back here tomorrow.
Until then have fun programming and I'll see you guys on the internet.
Take it easy everyone.