Hello everyone, and welcome to handmade hero.
The show we code a complete game live on stream.
Today we are going to go continue what we started yesterday.
We are now moving back.
We kind of have a sort in place that we liked and that we think is
reasonable.
We'll probably have to maybe play with it a little bit as we go
forwards, but we need to kind of come back now to the sort of the
final pass on.
Z handling in the renderer and in order to do that we kind of sketched
out some stuff that we need to do.
And it's probably going to be our job for next week, but I mean,
there's no sense wasting a day so we should get started on it as much
as possible.
Yesterday, we kind of started playing around with it and today I think
we can start making some Headway in and put us ourselves in a good
position to get it done next week.
Like I said, there isn't anything magical?
That's about to happen really?
All we're doing is now going through.
Now that we definitively know how we want to handle Z because we kind
of had to experiment to figure out what we really wanted.
Because there's an art style issues, there's code issues.
There's a lot of factors that went into deciding how Z really should
work and what we wanted Z to do.
And so now that we do actually have a coherent idea of what Z should
do, we have to go through and make sure that we just do a certain
amount of cleaning for how that pipeline looks because otherwise we're
going to start building everything on top of, kind of a frail and
janky system.
Of how Z was being handled before.
So that's really what I want to get to is the place where we're
starting to feel confident about our use of Z through the renderer
where there aren't a lot of gotchas, or why did that, do what it did?
We want to be in a place where we're like, okay, we have a coherent
idea of how we specify Z and off, we go.
Because for those of you who have watched the stream since the
beginning, you know that there's been a lot of times when we like what
should you do, okay, halfsies stop doing that.
Okay.
Easy.
Now, looks at this and not that and it's just, you don't want that to
be left in the game, right?
It's fine to go through those learning stages where you kind of go
like.
Okay, this is a little weird right now, but we're trying to figure out
how it works.
That's all fine.
But you want to make sure that once you have a coherent plan for house
So work you can get it down to a place where you're not constantly
having to second-guess it or anything like that.
So I'm going to go ahead and get started.
Today is day 3, 14 as it says at the bottom.
So you're going to want to start with de 313 source code.
If you are in the mood to follow along at home,
all right.
So, let's see here.
Here's where we were at yesterday.
And if you remember, we were sort of working on.
We want the the next sort of thing that we wanted to make sure that we
got right was when we look at what happens here with these stairs, we
can sort of see that the stairwell up that kind of goes up here.
Not all the stairs are properly included with the bottom level, right?
And part of that is because we're not coherently.
We're not actually coherently tracking.
Z throughout the, I guess, for lack of a better term, the way in which
we treat Z.
We're not actually Computing it in a way that looks at what chunkier
in because what we sort of decided was all right, we want our Z chunks
to line up with each individual floor.
So, everything on one floor is in one chunk because obviously they're
going to get pulled in together in that case.
And so then what we want to do is
Well, the the Z of the chunk should also be the Z that the renderer
uses.
So, basically like the chunks, each chunk Z each single Z chunk, is
passed as a slice to the renderer but in the actual render output as
we are using it, currently we never actually had those values happen.
And so that's the first thing that we want to do.
And then the next thing that we want to do is as you can see, like we
said yesterday, we need to start passing these slices to the render
us.
Separate slices because right now, they're all mixed together and they
just rely on the sort rule currently to sort it out which, as we know,
we didn't write to handle multiple layers like that because we, it's
not supposed to be going through there.
So that's, we need to do.
So first, we're going to try and get the chunks, the things the line
for the chunks properly and then we're going to move from there to
trying to get the renderer to think about these layers in a coherent
way so that it's known in the sorting system exactly how they work.
all right, so
here we are an entity that CPP and convert to later relative is what
we were actually using before in order to figure out where things were
in Z and what I wanted to do and I think we put a little to do in here
to this effect.
So it says here, it's the chunk see difference that tells us what the
relative layer is and we no longer care about the camera.
Z Delta because things inside of layer aren't transform prospectively
anymore.
So you can see that like this convert to layer relative bit.
We don't actually want to deal with this anymore, right?
That's not what we want.
What we want to do is start looking
At the the chunk see and you can see we wrote it here, we wrote it
out.
What the relative layer values actually should be now
We have a problem obviously that we don't actually know what the new
chunk Z is for a individual entity yet, right.
Because this world position value isn't actually going to exist
because in the same region we've moved the person and we need to know
what their chunk Z will be once we go to repack them right.
Once we once we go to condense everything down then we could look to
see what the, you know, the
See difference was here.
Let's go ahead and get that out of there.
So at that point.
Yes, we could, but we're not there yet, right?
We don't actually know what.
We don't have a coherent plan for what that actually entails.
So so what we have to do is take a look over at some region.
And in fact, we can probably also say, and I don't actually remember
this part of the code to well, because it's been a long time.
So we touched it, but
We actually go to pack things when we do pack entity into world.
I I believe that it's sort of expected that, you know.
It's yeah.
You can see it passing this the world position here.
So I believe that what actually occurs is when we do n Sim and and
there we go, when we do an end Sim and everyone's getting pushed back,
you can see that we have this concept of pack and it into World taking
the chunk pay now.
Now, the chunky is something that only gets computed in here.
So you can see it happening here where it does map any trunk space.
So, even though it pains me a little to do this twice at the moment, I
don't know that we have a lot of other options, we could just store it
in the entity and use it again.
So you know, I'll put it to do for that if we want to take a look at
that in the future but that's essentially all we're really talking
about here.
So if we want to know what the entity P would be for the chunks of the
or whatever and
To be fair, we don't even really need to keep the result of this.
We could just do, you know,
Entity chunk Z.
And when we do map interest, it's although you know, the way I think
about we probably want we're probably going to want to know that
offset.
So I'm going to I'm going to keep it the full thing around.
So if I do World position and I'll maybe I'll just call it where I'll
post for.
Now I do that map into chunks face and now I actually have what I
would need for the relative layer, right?
I've got in here and updated value.
Meaning after the
Six step for this.
After this entity is moved.
I now know what they're relatively.
Areas based on that operation.
Now once I do that I will have the relative layer probably correct.
But now I also need to think a little bit about the.
Yeah.
The rest of the stuff that we need to do with this entity.
Because you can kind of see in here, where we're doing our, where
we're doing sort of our output.
We still need to have the enemy transform, set up to transform things
such that they get displaced in Z in the right way, you know,
So we still do actually need a little more information where this
chunk is, you know, where the enemy is going to get drawn is gonna is
going to matter, and so we still have a little bit of work to do
there.
Now, I'm going to leave that for now because we don't have any of the
rest of stuff in place for it anyway, but I just wanted to point out
that that's kind of where we have to start going next.
Apparently, we don't have the world struct in here at the moment.
I meant.
Is that true?
That seems weird.
It's probably just World mode World though.
Like we probably have it.
We just didn't dereference it.
It's probably just that right?
But I guess nobody else was using it or people who were using it, you
know, didn't bother you, reference it into a local.
So now we can kind of see.
All right.
We're in much better shape.
Now, we got our stairwell sorted so that all of its sorts exactly
where we expect.
And so now, we're finally getting the part where these floors are a
little more coherent, right?
We still have the problem of, we're not slicing them up, so we still
have that error.
But at least now we've got that first pass of things that are supposed
to be on a particular floor are actually on that floor and that's
good.
That's what we want.
Okay, so the next thing that we need to do is now we need to start
getting a little more serious about the other part of our Z transform
and this is where things are going to start to get hairy for us.
So we need to, this is why we need to start tightening down and have a
really clear conceptualization of what supposed to happen because in
order to get to the next step.
We need to have a concept in the renderer.
Of the layers e and the actual Z value, right?
Because the layer Z, basically, that chunk dim Z that value is.
Now something that needs to be known to the renderer for like an
absolute sorting criteria right now, we can hack that in temporarily
and I don't know if maybe this is the way we'll actually want to do it
in the end, I don't know, but we can hack that in temporarily by
having the concept of the Z layer baked directly into the sort key,
right?
That's something we could do.
and so, you know, we don't we probably want to simplify
That sort key eventually because it's just a very bulky, there's a lot
of sort of work going on in that sort key now, which maybe isn't the
best thing in the world.
So I don't want to suggest that we can just keep throwing things in
here ad infinitum and never end up having to pay the piper.
But at the moment, as we are working at how these things are going to
come together.
Certainly that is one thing we could do, right?
We could have it so that the sort breaks these things back apart,
Now in the in the eventual version of the final render pass, it may be
that we have to be smarter about how things work than that.
It may be that we want to break things up into separate buffers, you
know, instead of sorting after the fact, I don't know.
But for right now, since we already have the sword in place, I'm going
to propose that we just do something here.
That's like an Uber app.
That's like, chunk Z and, you know, chunk Z would be
A thing that always demands priority in the sort even above manual
sorting.
So it's like this is a thing that's just it's totally takes people out
of the sort and moves them into it like basically it's like a group if
you will of sorting and so when we do that, you know, and we go to do
the test for is in front of, right.
All we have to do, there is first say that the result, whatever the
result is that we're going.
Owing to do.
You know we basically had one more case here.
You could just see, you can see why I say.
We may have to get a little bit more smart about this because you can
just see this as a very complicated thing to starting.
Go on here and that's every time we compared to people we're doing
there's just a lot of fussing right.
And so you know it's just it makes me a little nervous.
Does it mean we're actually have to deal with it?
I don't know.
We're going to see as we go forwards.
Obviously we'll find out.
This isn't a game about having hundreds of thousands of Sprites on the
screen.
So at that point, you know, we kind of get a little bit of a free
pass.
You know that is true but you know just the point of it is that as
things get more complex and like this, they start to like kind of
trigger on my radar of like, well this could be a problem, doesn't
matter right now so it's fine.
But you know, it's just worth noting when things happen to just want
to be aware of where your possible trouble points are.
You don't usually want to have them take you completely by surprise.
So we could say here that
If a chunk Z is not equal to B chunk Z, then we could basically just
say that.
Well, if a is going to be in front of B, then a should have a higher Z
value, right?
So, a chunk Z greater than b, chunk Z would be the result.
And that way the chunk Z is sort of always specified to me.
as a layering operation on top of everything else, which means that we
can start,
Feel free to group stuff in into those sort of broad categories, if
that makes sense.
And again, for the render group, this is not a particularly hard.
Like these are, these are.
When I say that these are things, that trouble me a little, I'm not
talking about code architecture wise.
They're very, very simple and not difficult at all.
I'm talking more about sort of the overall notion that I worry about,
you know,
What the cost will be in the end for certain things, not worry like we
shouldn't do it but more worried about like well in the back of my
mind I think we might have to revisit this and do something better for
the final version if we find, it's too slow.
So all I'm doing here is for manual sort.
I'm just going to go ahead and
Make sure I see what's going on.
Yeah.
So basically the only thing I have to do here is just say well Sprite
bound chunks equals object transform Chauncey.
And I think that's really it.
So in theory now that shouldn't affect anything because we're not
setting it to anything.
So when we come up here, we should see Executives kind of went the
wrong way around there.
So we should see exactly the same weird sorting and we do.
And so, now, the question is, well what would happen?
And I guess we can sort of maybe see this live, if we want to what'll
happen, if I go ahead and and change that.
That render code.
So that we actually do set the sort key in entity, right?
Because we sort of have a manual.
Sort part manual sort.
If we say any transform chunks equals World, post chunk Z.
Now, we sort of have this automatic sort that's going to that's going
to kick in for that.
So, once I've done that, you can now kind of see how it works.
And we do get we do
At Z sorting their kind of for free.
Can see how were, you know, everything's kind of nice A-line but we do
have potentially one problem of that.
I guess I don't know off hand off to think about to what extent it
actually is a problem.
Maybe, it's not really a problem.
I don't know.
We'll see what happens in the final version but the thing that I was
noticing that was a problem was when I actually go up these stairs
here.
Like so,
so, I also wonder, why is there no Alpha on the
Oh, right because I'm not, I didn't set the end of the alphabet.
Right, right.
That's it.
Yeah, that's for sure.
What I'm standing on the stairs here.
You know, I would like to see my guy be in front of the the top piece
here and so what we met, you know, I might say though that
That's not really a problem where we're going to have to solve that
way.
What we could definitely decide to do here is just once the hero is up
on that stair, they move to the next chunk up right there at a point
where that's that's a reasonable thing to do or something.
So that looks pretty reasonable.
So what I would like to do here is I want to see to what happens if I
expand out those those bounds a little bit.
To be honest, I don't really remember all that much how we were
drawing those.
I don't even know who is is drawing.
Those traversable looks like this code right here.
Yeah, so if I wanted to draw those a little bit more like actual
tiles, right?
I guess, now we can kind of see what's happening in terms of like,
what this might actually look like in an actual game, right?
As I sort of go through, it looks like we're getting some again,
sorting flicker their up.
Which I'm not really sure what that come from.
I almost guarantee you.
That's psycho problems again, but see me.
Make sure that's actually true.
We should probably all go put the debug stuff in the it in a separate
chunk now, too, so that it would be on top for since we wanted to fix
that bug as well.
Let's see here.
Yeah, you can kind of see you get some nasty cycling going on there.
I think that's just one of those things where, you know, if you're if
you sort of overlap, the fact that we're doing overlap testing in such
a broad sense, I think we get kind of a lot of unnecessary tiling,
like these things don't really overlap significantly yet.
We, you know, we get sort of that thing and I almost wonder if we
shouldn't shrink things, a little before we do our overlap testing, I
feel like that
Would be a positive Improvement for because we don't really need to
sort things that only barely overlap.
You know what I mean?
At least I feel like that would be true.
How did I get?
How did I get those things to flicker?
I know I was getting a subtree flicker there, but I can't seem to get
it to happen again.
Maybe I was down a little lower.
There it is.
And you can see there's just tons of Cycles.
Like everything is a cycle at that point.
You know what I mean?
Surprising the sort holds up as well as it does when there's so many
cycles.
So I'm curious in the sort.
When we do the sort of overlap test, right?
And we do rectangles intersect, I'm kind of interested to know whether
that rectangle intersection code.
whether that would,
You know what?
That would end up doing if I did it I can add radius to with some
shrink.
right, so if we had something like this,
And we were to say that we wanted to shrink something, you know, for
pixels or something like this.
I'm just curious.
Oh, and I forgot that's actually not in that's in the platform
specific part of the code.
So
all right, so let's say that we shrink you know we shrink things a
little a little bit here and I guess you know what?
I should probably also good to I think.
So we can use our debug system again.
Now, that we have the ability to second in there, I'm just gonna say
like hey all of these transforms.
Let's also make all of these transforms.
Oops.
Let's instead of doing in fact, I don't even know if sort bias needs
to be there anymore.
I think sort bias may not have to be there anymore.
Right.
Because I think, now we can just make chunk Z chunk, Z is now or sort
by us, and I think sort bias is completely useless.
It's because why would you ever use it when you have actual sorting
happening?
It was, it was kind of a waste e sort of thing.
In fact, let's just let's just see what happens if we get rid of sort
bias.
Entirely sort bias, oops, not soft bias group.
Here we go.
All right, so get rid of the sort bias.
Entirely and off we go.
All right, so let's see if that helps to, with our debug overlay much
nicer.
So now on here, I'm going to go ahead and turn on those groups and you
can see how much nicer that is when we don't count things that are
just barely a budding because we don't really want this order to have
to deal with that.
There's not a lot of reason for it to deal with that, right?
So you know, I'm pretty happy about that.
And that also fixes our Flickr.
So you know we do kind of now know that we probably want to break
Cycles a little bit more intelligently and we kind of had a feeling
that was going to be the case but you know, I'm pretty happy about
that.
Where that's at at the moment.
Anyway, so yeah, so if we kind of excuse me sir, excuse me.
If we see how that looks, I'm pretty okay with with that Alpha thing
in and out, as well.
But yeah, yeah.
So the next thing we have to do to is this stuff is illegal as well.
So, before we get any too much further down there, we're also going to
have to deal with the fact that these are not supposed to be skew in X
because that breaks our sort criteria as well.
Alright, so it seems like we're okay, so far
Looks reasonable here.
I think are we allowed to jump down now?
We're not.
It always picks a square.
That's like not too far down.
It looks like.
All right, so that all seems reasonable.
And we mostly just have problems with those guys that all seems
reasonable.
Wow.
So now let's see.
With the chunk Z in there and having that slicing everyone into
groups.
At this point, we're sort of doing
I guess we don't really, we don't really have a way to
Leverage any of this stuff in the actual renderer and that's kind of
the problematic part, right?
So we had those clip.
Rex we had clip Rex in there and we had the notion that we could
associate things with different clip Rex.
So we do kind of know some of the information about what we need to
do.
But unfortunately it's kind of a little all tangled up because what
we're going to want to do, right?
Is we want to
Able to draw the stuff that's in, that's in the alpha group all into
like a separate buffer and then blend it on top.
That's kind of it requires the render and knowing more than it knows
right now about what's going on, you know what I mean?
But we could say at the moment is that our fog, we could re enable our
fog properly and not really have to push that through to the renderer.
so I feel like we're kind of at a position here, where we, you know,
we
We should sort of extricate a little bit of what's going on from the
renderer.
Let me see if I can give a little bit more concrete explanation, but
basically at the top, we're going to do entity rendering and we come
through here.
We do this sort of we build this let these sets of levels.
That's what are the effects for each level that we want to have,
right?
And so each level has something like okay you know we're going to do a
particular background.
Their Blend or something or whatever.
And so what we're really talking about here is the fact that we don't
really need to treat this as we don't really need what we're getting
here, right?
Because we're actually treating this, like, we need the renderer to
understand that we have seven levels or whatever.
I don't know, five levels, six levels.
However, many we have there - 403 and over, 2 and over 1 0 and 1.
So it's actually
Really going to be six levels.
We have six levels and really, it only knows needs to know about two
things.
It needs to know about the alpha 1 and everything else.
And so, most of this is for our benefit.
Most of this is just for the fog, right?
And so if we took that out and just handled the fogging ourselves,
That would be nicer because then what we have to change in the render
is more minimal.
It's just, are you in the alpha phase layer and how much Alpha fade is
happening in that layer?
Or are you not?
So,
Let's start by doing that and the way that I'd like to do that is say
like okay you know, maybe we just do fog amount or something like
this.
And you can see in here where we sort of are doing the fog amount
computation, you can see that happening here, here's the fade, you
know, Topsy stuff.
This is the stuff for actually Alpha laying out if that makes sense.
So what we could really do here instead is
Say like, oh yeah, we don't need a clip, rect for any of this stuff.
In fact, we don't really need to be creating these clip Breck's at
all.
Probably we probably just need if anything One Clip, rect if we want
to associate or, or maybe to clip RX1 for the stuff that's in that
Alpha layer and one for the stuff that's not in that Alpha layer, so
we could do that.
Now, the only thing about that is we don't really process.
S things by their cliprect layer at all.
So I'm actually thinking probably I just want to mix that whole
concept.
I don't think we need it and we'll see why.
So I think that was just a bad idea on my part.
It was like a thing that we tried.
I don't like it and I don't think we're going to use it.
So I'm just going to pull that out now.
So we don't have it sitting around anymore.
All right.
So let's take a look inside the clip.
Rect structure.
You can see the clip, rect effects thing.
I don't want that anymore.
I don't really want any of this at all, so I'm just going to recompile
without that.
And I'm going to see who ends up having a problem with it.
So, there's us pushing the FX when the FX actually happens.
I don't know that.
Was even using it.
Let's see and everything else isn't rendered.
So for render fog amount, we know that we've got this many
I'm going to get rid of that and for now I'm going to leave the test
Alpha in even though we're probably going to yank that in a minute
here.
So when we come through here, I'm going to say, get rid of the clip
effects, get rid of all the cliprect nonsense that was happening.
We don't need any of it, it's not relevant and then I'm going to say
like okay, we'll just assume that the test Alpha.
Is one for whatever this layer is and we'll assume that the fog amount
is also set to a prescribed value.
In this case, Zero will say that fog.
Zero means you're not fog at all and fog, one means you're completely
fogged.
So then when we come in here and we do our clamp map to range, really,
all we're doing is saying well.
Okay, our Alpha is always going to be one in less it it turns out to
be 0.
Well, actually it may be that you can just always do this.
Can I just always do Clint map to range?
I think I probably could because if you have gone off one end you'll
just always be back at 1, right?
And so I feel like that's probably just fine and the same is probably
true here.
I would I would wager so we can probably just do that.
Everything can be computed just fine at that point and then we don't
have to deal with any of this.
This nonsense here now.
Now for a test Alpha, I feel like it was going the wrong way because
we're doing a one- there.
So if we want to know what the alpha value is rather than the the fade
amount we can just invert this this and we'll get it.
We'll get a reversed range.
So, I think that's roughly what we need.
Let's take fog them out there.
Yeah.
And fog mounts.
Okay, so Dad at the end here, right?
A group, current cliprect index is not gonna get modified anymore.
So we're just going to use the default clipping rectangle at this
point.
And now we are at, I think we're at a place where everything should be
working as before, but now, we just don't have any of those clip
bricks, right?
All of that stuff is, is not happening anymore.
So now I should be able to actually set the entity color blend value.
And that color blend value Jimmy.
That color button value is going to affect everything that we draw.
So what we were doing right now is we're kind of doing that manually.
I don't know if we want to do it manually or not, you know, maybe we
do, maybe we don't, I'm not sure but you can see what's happening
here, but that's also, you know, the fact that we're doing it manually
has some downsides and means that it's a little confusing, sometimes,
what's going to happen.
So maybe we want to make that be a property of the transform.
So when the
Is rectified like this is sort of how we had it a little bit before,
maybe that kicks in at that point.
So let's go ahead and try that out.
Just see what we've got here at.
There we go.
Where's that Alpha value?
There it is.
So this is p scars.
That doesn't have to happen anymore so I think we're all good.
Okay so now that I've turned that off now we're going to see those
those bits above us, right?
They haven't outfit out 20 yet.
And so now what we need to do is we need to kind of go back into the
render group and sort of I think I kind of have it this way before a
little bit, when we Rectify a color, which is something that we had
before, where do we do that?
It's in here somewhere.
somewhere when we do a store color,
You can actually see.
We've got sort of the global color thing happening here, right?
And so I think we can do we left in actually the exact stuff we need.
So I think we can do everything that we want here.
Now my only question is, when we do the store color, could we have not
gotten that from the object transform?
Like, I kind of feel like we kind of want that to be object transform
specific.
So I feel like, you know, that's better than having a global value
that sets on and off.
We already have this notion that the object transform is kind of the
thing that stores that transient state.
So I'd rather you know if we could I'd rather have it look more like
this, where we do the store color rather than ever having those global
values.
Let's see, that store color.
There we go.
If you look at what actually needs to happen here, right?
I can just do a thing where I say, like, okay object, transform
transform, and I don't know if that's a pointer or something like this
and then transform transform.
In there.
I now have the ability to sort of specify that on a per transform
basis, rather than a global basis, which I think I like better.
So, here we are in the object transform.
There we go, and I don't really know.
So these get passed around, and if they actually get in line to, I
suppose that's fine.
I think the compiler will be smart enough to do that, right?
But otherwise, we might want to start passing those because they're
pretty big by pointer.
Um so I'm not, I'm not really sure about that.
I kind of feel like we might want to start passing pointers to the
object transform, rather than saying the object transform itself.
So I might, I might suggest moving in that direction a little bit
based on the
Of those.
So okay, let's go back over here and a rent.
Clean that out a bit and we go make these into pointers everywhere.
Go.
And get Bender into two bases pee.
And let's see it because I don't really know if the compilers.
What the compiler isn't isn't smart enough to do there.
It's been a long time since I really sat down and looked at what the
compiler does for code.
And so, I feel like my knowledge about what the best thing is to do,
especially for debug code.
Like, sometimes I'll do things even if the global, I mean, even if the
optimizer would have done it fine, sometimes I still like to do it
manually if I can just because I don't want to
Have my debug builds be slow, you know, because I like to be able to
step through code cleanly, without having to deal with all the sort of
crap, where the bugger can't inspect values and doesn't know what's
going on all the time.
So, you know, to a certain extent, there is a lot of that.
But anyway, so let's take a look, here, I'm just sort of
Pushing this through.
Yeah.
And this is not a particularly interesting thing at this is just busy
work, right?
Busy work, that our tools should do it for us these days, of course
they don't.
Why would they?
We've only had 50 years of programming tools.
You know, let's not get too excited.
Okay?
So yeah, anywhere here where we were doing transforms.
Let's just go ahead and keep passing that through.
So, in here, we would do an address of an entity transform same with
here.
And here.
We go.
Keep it coming.
Keep coming.
And I don't think this needs to do anything now because now we're not.
We don't have that nasty Global making things.
Scrappy, let's see.
So.
Default flat transform.
I don't know if we're allowed to pass that.
That was one of the nice things about it is, you could just call it in
line, but that's okay, I don't know.
How often we were really taking advantage of that.
Anyway, though.
Let's see here.
So
Where are we?
We are in rendered layered scene and so okay.
So we're going to just have to take the address of that transform.
address of a set of
Transform that.
I suspect some of these probably don't really want to be just the flat
transform but who knows?
So no transform just passed address of.
Go.
Oddly enough.
Most of the stuff is in the debug system.
And you are transform transform.
There we go.
And hopefully we're getting towards the end.
Not that this isn't so exciting.
In theory, this is a computer.
Yes.
if only there was a machine that was good at doing repetitive tasks,
all right.
Hopefully everything's still fine.
There we go.
And so now in theory, all of our stuff is actually working properly
through the pipeline with that color as well, which is what we
initially did.
And so now I should be able to set those values and per entity when I
do the transform and have them do what they need to do.
So, in theory again, only in theory, I should be able to set entity
transform.
Color and any transfer multicolor.
In this case.
Now, what we know is that
The fog value.
It's dependent on what relative layer in certainly.
So, what we need to do here is say, well, if the relative layer equals
the maximum level index, then we've got the alpha.
Wise, we don't right?
So we essentially have two separate things.
We're going to do here.
So in the case, where at the maximum level and level index, what we
want to do here is create a tea color value, that's only affecting the
alpha and it is going to blend.
In fact I don't think we even need to set the color to anything but in
the other case we do need to set the blend to color to be the
background color and we need to set the tea color to be whatever the
fog amount is.
For this for this layer, right?
so as we can make life a little easier on ourselves like this,
And so I'll pull out that fog amount and that's just going to be you
know in the first portion and we're not going to affect the alpha at
all.
Right.
So at that point I think we're good and so when those colors get
stored by the renderer now in theory they should be working.
Of course, I'm not seeing that happen and I would like to set a
breakpoint please there we go.
There you go.
So, when I set that to color that should actually oh
No, default upright.
Transform it would set everything to 0.
Correct.
I think I might have to go in there and initialize those because
actually I think about it that might not clear them.
I don't really remember what it does by default.
So let's see T color color and T color.
Well actually it looks like our problem is more that our T value our
test Alpha value doesn't actually
Oh right.
Now we're back to being inverted.
So this test Alpha value here is actually now back to the old way it
was so that's actually what's going on there.
Okay, so there's our color happening inside the render.
Now we come up here and that all looks fine, so that's good.
And now we should see whether or not we can get five, we might have to
create another layer for fog.
Now, you can actually already see the fog happening, so let's create
some more layers just so we can get up a little higher and see more
fog, just to make sure what's happening is get down there, but I think
that's now a reasonable situation.
Okay?
So that is just
Is going to be inside World mode.
And when I do my ad standard room,
And I just put, you know, bunch of rooms on top of each other.
Hopefully, that all works.
So yeah.
And also, you'll note that as we put more rooms on top of each other,
I believe.
We'll see.
That's interesting.
Huh, as I say, I thought bills virus the only thing but get close to
reversible is also one that doesn't use the space partition.
Currently, build Sprite graph has a lot of stress on it right now.
And so we kind of know that that guy has just has a lot of issues in
debug mode.
I would be curious to know how he's doing in an optimized.
I'm just going to take a quick trip, quick check.
As quite quite fast.
So
Yeah, so but it's still a little bit high, so yeah, still a little bit
High.
Are tooltips look like they're not on a on the right layer, just
interesting.
Anyway, so that was Again, part of the thing where I was talking about
before I think we want to do some work to make a better situation for
ourselves in terms of how we pass things down and not have the sort
have to deal with the layers.
Oh my God.
Why are there so many heads following me?
Geez, that's creepy.
All right, so the fog looks looks correct down there though, right?
Which is all I really wanted to know.
There's too many things happening on the screen right now, and this
game.
Which is not my intention, but yeah.
Okay.
So that all looks pretty good down there.
All right.
So I think we're good.
So okay.
So now before we can really take a good look at our sort for reals
again, we still have one more thing at least that we have to do which
is start to get the Z handled correctly in terms of displacement from
a layer, right?
Because now we've got sort of two different concepts of the Z position
of an entity and that's a thing that's going to have to be dealt with.
And we've got what
You got.
We've got 12 minutes if that makes sense.
Is that right?
12 minutes.
Yeah, we've got 12 minutes to go and so yeah.
I don't know how far we're going to be able to get in that, but that's
roughly what we need to do.
I also don't really know why we're getting some bleed-through on the
layers there.
That's very odd.
Because in theory, the layer is totally Primal.
You shouldn't be able to ever see anything through it, but there are
some like peeking through of
Of of the health rectangles there, which is odd, right?
So we may have some bugs in there because that's
Oh, but you know what?
No, that's not true because we put all of those things into the graph,
which I really didn't want to do.
So actually, if there are Cycles, you could even get a bug there,
right?
So yeah, so I think that really does argue for what I said before.
Is where I like we have to do we're going to have two segments, these
things up into those different passes.
I think that's definitely going to have to occur.
But, you know, we've got some tricks for that.
I don't think that's the end of the world, if that makes sense.
And there's also some things we can do.
One of the things that's a little bit janky is that it would be pretty
great.
It would be really, really nice.
If we could always ensure that, you know, the, if we always rendered
everyone with the chunk Z, they started with at the beginning of the
simulation, instead of the chunk Z they end with, if that makes sense.
And the reason for that is, since we happen to stream the entities in
and we gather them based on chunks to begin with every all of the
enemies are already in sorted order.
If we want them to be in the, in the same region.
So we would literally not have to do any work there if we could just
count on that, right?
But of course, you know,
When somebody is moving between two regions, it would be raw wrong for
one frame.
I don't know how big of a deal that is.
I think I might like that fact so much that it feels like we probably
would want to still do it anyway.
Yeah, I mean that that kind of feels good to me I'll be honest.
That feels like something that
Feels like if you used it, you would it's just kind of too cool to not
have that happen.
And I wish we could do the same thing for the screen space sorting but
again that one's going to be too visible of a bug.
I think if you actually did that that's just my assumption.
So I think I'm going to take a look at that before we go and do the Z
thing, man.
So here is a, here's a proposal for you.
And maybe, I guess, one thing that I could do is just explain it and
not start it till tomorrow, but not start till next week.
So let me just kind of give you what I was sort of thinking here.
What I was thinking of doing for this.
Is saying, well, we've got these slices, it would be great.
If what we could do is make it.
So those slices are essentially like
Coming out in the buffer.
in the render buffer in order roughly,
And in between each layer, there would just be a barrier.
Token, like a thing that basically says like, hey, sort everything
here.
But don't include the stuff that comes after it, right?
So that we're only sorting in like in bucking like buckets, right?
And then if you put all of your entities out in order like that, then
you wouldn't have this problem.
So for example, if we go over to the sort
Where we do sort entries.
Right.
I think, although I don't actually know, I think if we just make this
be a for, I Loop that basically, like goes through and says, oh, you
know, when I do the build Sprite graph, I walk through the nodes,
Right?
And when I hit one of these nodes, you know, when I hit a note that's
got a special key in it.
I know that that's a barrier and I just stopped do the sort and then
continue, right?
So it'd be something like inside the sorts, right bound?
You know, maybe we just take that that manual key and maybe the manual
key just has a special code in it, right?
So there's maybe like a thing that's like, you know, Sprite.
Barrier value or something like that and maybe this right barrier
value, you know, is some some puffy value.
So you know it'd be something like okay you're kind of coming through
here until you get to the input node count.
And let me see what we've actually got here.
Input node count.
And index.
Yeah, yeah, yes.
So I think
yeah, so I think all we have to
Here is, instead of making this b02 input node count, we would really
just take in a value.
That was what the
note index was that we were going to start with, right?
So, we don't must just say like, oh okay, you know, whatever.
Whatever one we're going to start with you.
Tell us.
And when we're doing the build Sprite graph, we would just say, like,
okay, you know, do you know for eyelid outside where we say, hey
there's a node index or like you know, first index or something.
That's going to equal 0 assume that we run until first index is less
than whatever the count is.
And we don't increment it at all.
Actually we passed that to build.
Right graph.
And we like get it back as well.
So inside builds Frank graph.
We can return a value here.
That is whatever, note index a actually turns out to be when it's
done.
And, you know, we can even do the test here.
We could say like oh, okay, so you know, in the test will do something
where we say if we hit the sort barrier, stop right?
So do something like,
If?
A manual dots.
What is the remember what this is here?
if a manual Foo equals, the Sprite barrier value, then we just bail
And that's it.
All right.
Not a member of sorts, right bound.
Is that so?
It's in here actually.
So I guess, in that case, if it's actually in here, if this is what
We're looping over, we could actually, it actually wouldn't have to be
stored in the manual part.
I suppose we could store that in the offset instead, so maybe we'll do
that.
So in here, we'll do like
Spray Perry offset value.
and we'll say,
okay.
A manual that offset is not right.
We just want offset and and that's it.
So if we run it now because we're basically out of time, we should,
yeah, we shouldn't have any chain, so everything should be fine, but
now we should be able to go back and and and make that make that
change, which I think is what I'd like to do on Monday.
I'm going to go to build that bat and say that we're going back to
debug mode.
And then I think we're going to call it for tonight because I don't
want to start that and until then, and I think we'll also get our
frame rate back at that point.
Because right now, it's a complete crazy town, right?
Like if you look at what happens with the,
you know, right now there's everything is just nuts in terms of like
how much stuff there is getting sorted and what not,
And there's really no need to create these ridiculous graphs there.
They're just and they're going to create all kinds of cycle problems
for us as well.
Yeah, all right.
All right.
Let's go to the Q&A.
Diplo.
Where are all those familiars coming from?
I have no idea.
I mean, there's a one familiar created for every level and I guess I
don't know that I've looked at the familiar code in a while.
I don't know that we, they might just be able to.
Yeah, I think they're allowed to just go straight line a little bit.
I guess.
I don't really know.
So I think they just kind of--can float on down their code is such
that they don't I don't think they check.
For anything other than whether the thing they're going to is blocked.
This things are creepy.
So, I don't think there's any questions.
Which I guess means we can end early.
Snake looks broken.
Yeah, I guess why is there only one piece of the snake?
The snake was like, went up the stairs or something, how is it allowed
to do that?
That's a pretty interesting bug.
Snake.
How did you do that?
It went up at not even the stairs, he just went up to a higher level.
But only that snake all the rest of the snakes.
Are apparently fine.
That's real weird.
Hmm.
I also don't think we've ever seen that before.
Have we?
Oops.
It's going to be nice to finally be on game code after a.
So I can go make all this stuff a lot, tighter and cleaner.
That it's also it's also kind of stupid.
Now, the
since we haven't really written any actual game code here like guys,
seriously
Come on.
Get get out of there.
Get, I'm trying to go up the stairs.
Just come on over here for a second.
And just stay out of my way, please.
Oh, now the snake is going, okay?
That time, the snake actually decided to go up the stairs, which I
suppose is fine as long as it gets out of the way.
so yes, somehow
And we will have to develop how oh wait no.
But that's the snake that just went upstairs.
So now we still don't know where that other snake went, we have no
idea.
Okay guys, stop going up the stairs.
Where do you think you're going?
Is there even another floor?
I guess there is
this still does not answer our question as to where that for a snake
even when we have no idea,
So there it is.
So somehow that guy jumped all the way to the top level.
I'm assuming that we must have a bug or because we haven't.
Well, I guess we didn't really do much on the code for
In fact we haven't done anything, I guess on the code for Z like, how
far you can jump up, it must have done something interesting where it
was able to pick a high floor right away.
These are the creepiest.
I tell you dismembered heads floating around is just it's just creepy.
Don't know where the snake had actually is here.
Unfortunately, I can't really look.
Like I said, I'm not really too concerned about that code, because
that's not really stuff that we've kind of dealt with.
Finally, it's just weird.
Some of the behaviors you get.
Alright.
Imma wrap it up.
Okay, thank you for joining me for an episode handmade here.
It's a pleasure coding with you.
As always, if you would like to follow along at home, you can always
pre-order the game on handmade here a.org, and it comes to the source
code.
We also have a forum site, you can use ask questions a patreon page.
If you want to support our video series, a schedule about the tweets
to schedule it.
You, if you want to know where we're going to be live and an episode
guide, which will help you catch up on our past.
Fine.
Fine episodes, that's about it for tonight.
I'll be back next.
Tweak be sure to check the schedule about if you want to know when
until then have fun coating everyone and I will see you on the
internet.
Take it easy everyone.