Start recording.
Hello everyone and welcome to handmade.
Here are the show.
We could complete game live on stream and today we are going to fix
our first GPU driver bug which I can pretty much guarantee.
You will not be our last
Before I do that, I'll just simply mention.
Today is day 2, 46.
So, if you would like to follow along at home, and you are someone who
pre-ordered the game on handmade hero dot-org, you should unpack day
245 source code because that is the source code that I can be starting
with today.
And if, for some reason, you unpack some different source code than
that, you are not going to know what's going to go on at all.
You're going to like, I have no idea what I'm looking at.
This is not what Casey has and that is because you did it wrong.
So, don't do that.
What am I talking about driver bug?
What do I even mean?
Well obviously,
It's not happening on this machine, because if it was happy with this
machine, we'd see it yesterday when we actually did this, but you can
see here, here is our cutscenes running, and they appear to be running
correctly.
This is, of course, running through the hardware renderer.
Now, you will note, we didn't really have much in the way of problems
when we had a software vendor that is because we were not involving
the GPU of the system at all, which of course is where a lot of the
sort of system peculiarities come in because the protocols for talking
to gpus are incredibly
Weird and contorted.
And the GPS themselves are very varied and change a lot from your
year.
So it's very likely that you have a problem with compatibility as soon
as you start using a GPU, if you don't use the GPU, you have very
little problems with compatibility typically.
But most games nowadays have to use the GPU if they want to be
competitive graphically because most of the graphs or part machine is
on the GPU.
So, what I found out from people who post on the forums, if you test
this on Nvidia, our using multiple threads for downloading textures,
was not working properly.
Early on there.
And what they said was that for some reason and I've sent oh I keep
forgetting, I don't have to use emacs anymore.
What they said was that for whatever reason, if you create, all of the
context are going to use all the opengl context on the main thread and
then pass them down to the other threads.
Well, then it's fine and it works, but if you create those threads
act, if you trace those contacts, actually, on separate threads that
doesn't work.
And so I don't really know why.
Why I sent email to Nvidia and I gave them the source code to a, I'm a
hero.
And I just like can you tell us why?
And I'll explain it on the stream if you can set aside explanation.
So we don't know why I would assume that it's something relatively
straightforward.
Like oh we, you know, we set the data on the thread-local storage of
the, you know, of the particular thread that initially calls to
opengl.
And so there is no information on the other threads with which to
create new contexts or something like this.
I don't really know what that answer is going to be.
I could, you know, try to imagine one but I don't actually know.
So certainly there's some explanation for
We don't know exactly what it is.
All we know is that it does not work there and so actually don't need
it.
Load that, let me load this up.
So all we do know is that it doesn't work to do it that way.
And in general, with PC compatibility, you don't have the luxury of
ever really knowing why things don't work.
A lot of the time you simply have to accept the fact that if someone
runs into a bug on PC and they always almost always do that has to do
with Hardware that's out of your control.
Well you just have to figure out a way to work around it.
And in this case it sounds like
Like we don't have a particularly hard job ahead of us.
If the only requirement for getting it working is that we create the
context on the main thread and then pass them to the separate threads.
Well that is something that's really easy for us to do.
So I'm just going to go ahead and do that now so that our code base we
know is compliant with and videos drivers, as well as AMD drivers and
then we can go from there.
So let's take a look at what we were doing before.
So you've got win32 and opengl here and you can see that this sort of
does are opengl start up and then from then on after 13.
And opengl.
We had this win32 create opengl context for worker thread and that was
basically what we were using from then on
So, our download threads, we're calling this.
And the problem we believe is right here, apparently this cannot be
called on anything other than the main thread.
So, what we need to do is we essentially need to hoist that out.
And we need to call that once for every worker thread, before we ever
call the worker threads, and then when we call the worker threads, we
need them to pick that context up and use it, that makes sense.
So that's what we're going to do here and it's pretty straightforward.
There's really not a lot to it essentially.
The only real thing that we have to do here.
Oops.
The only thing that we have to do here is take our, take our code for
launching threads and
To give them something more robust than just a platform Q because
right now we're sort of leaning on the platform Q code and you can
kind of see us doing that.
It's called platform.
Oops platform work you you can see it right here.
What we're doing is we're taking this platform work you thing and that
platform work you is the thing that we're passing down I'm going to
move that out first of all because there's really I don't think any
reason for that to be there.
I'm going to move that out here because it's part of the win32
Class.
Sorry, struct definitions.
And when we're actually using these here, you can see when we go into
creating our threads and thread proc, you can see that what it gets
past when you start up a thread, is this platform work you which it
does need.
But the platform work queue is shared among any of the threads that,
that sort of consume work out of that Cube.
And since it's shared among all those threads, it means that we can't
pass unique things that need to be per thread on that cue, right?
So what we need to do is we need to
To essentially have 0 and it turns out we left it in there from
before.
So we actually already
When 32 threads, start up that went through two threads, sort of thing
that we were that we had made before when we were, almost gonna do it
the other way, that's all we really need.
So we just need to have this winter to thread startup code.
The win32 thread startup code could point to the work queue that the
thread is supposed to use.
But it can also contain the opengl are see that it actually needs.
And that's that's pretty much all we're doing right.
All right, so let's go ahead and
And get that set up.
Let's make that happen.
So what we want to do here is for our thread proc whether thread proc
gets called what we want to do.
I guess I should leave this here actually what we want to do is say
win32 thread.
Startup is actually the thing that you're going to get now when 32
threads start up,
I guess I could card call this maybe thread.
That's going to be the thing that we cast for our parameter at
startup.
Like so and then instead of getting the work queue from the parameter
now it just gets it from the queue so we're still passing the Q
through but we're passing it sort of as a subset of the other parts of
stuff because we need the opengl stuff.
So now in here, what we're going to do is say, okay, well now instead
of this needs opengl thing that was on the cue and we're just gonna
get rid of that because we don't care about them or what we're going
to say instead is if someone gave us as part of the thread parameters
and opengl RC then what we'd like
To do is call wiggle, make current to make that, you know, our our see
that we're going to use.
Now remember, in order to do that, we also still need to make sure
that we can use that.
We have a DC, a Windows d.c.
Now technically we're never going to render anything to the d.c.
all we're doing a submitting buffers.
So really the preference here would just to be to say that the DC-10
but I don't think you actually ever can do that and we check the in
video documentation for multi-threaded texture downloads.
They were passing the same DC handle that they were using before.
So I believe here, what we would want to do is probably just pass that
DC just call it like opengl DC or something and just say, okay,
whatever,
They tell us to do, that's what we're going to do.
All right, so I think this is roughly, what we want to have, is
something more like this.
Does that make sense?
Hopefully it's so something like that.
So that's the actual code that we need on the thread side and now we
just need to actually, when we start up these threads, we need to
actually build that bundle, right?
So we need to actually make make that happen.
So, let's take a look at where we call this red lips.
Red Croc,
Right here.
And so when we call win32 make you, we say, how many of these threads
we want?
And so what we actually need to do now is instead of sort of doing it
this way, I think we're going to have to switch to a thing where we
passed the win32 thread startups, that we actually wanted, right?
Because we need these things to stick around.
So we're going to go ahead and say, OK, win32 thread startup startups.
Like so and then whenever we call one of these instead of passing that
work queue to it, what we're going to do is say, we're going to pass
it, whatever the nth startup actually is.
So it's assumed that whoever calls us here is going to have fill those
out with the information that they actually wanted, right?
We can keep this here as a convenience feature.
So what we could do, if we wanted this as a convenience feature, we
don't need to just be could force the color to do this potentially,
but if we wanted to
So we could say, Okay, oops.
We could say, let's go ahead and get that guy out of here and then
we'll go ahead and fill out the Q automatically for the caller.
And that's just a convenience that says, that's absolutely nothing to
do with anything.
It's just, we could just do that to make it a little easier on the
collar, so that callers who don't care about this, don't have to worry
about setting the queue.
It'll Get Set automatically because we know that it always, it's
known, right?
So if we compile, this will just get the errors at the point where we
do our make you, oops, at the point where we do our make you, here we
go.
And you can sort of see, you know, what I should do.
By the way, I realized that are handmade project file is wrong.
I think I don't actually know if it is or not, but when I load it in
for a coder, it doesn't seem to set the compiled correctly.
Hi, wrong / and I'm trying to remember why?
Because it looks like that's where build up that actually is.
I don't know why I'm not 100% certain on why that doesn't work anyway.
I have to figure that out anyway.
Not that important now I suppose.
So let's go, let's go back to what I was saying when we call 13 to
make you.
Obviously, we don't have those startups in there.
And so what I could do is say, okay, I'm going to make these with
through to thread startups and these are the high price startups and
there's six of them.
And then I can just say, all right, well, whatever, the array county
is of those is how many are going to do, and there's a pointer to the
startups, right?
Then the low priority queues are the ones that have the opengl context
and they're going to have a different opengl context.
Perk you, right?
So I have now a thing that's like, all right, I've got to have a win
to to thread startup low price startups.
I need two of those one for each of the threads that's going to be
started.
And so in the low price startups, these ones I actually want to to
sort
Seed with some useful information.
And so what I could do is say you know low press, start up, zero
equals like create thread or win32 threads startup GL or something.
Something like that.
And so I can just say, hey, why don't you do whatever you need to do
to make this thing happen?
Here's the we no longer even need any of these things to be Global
which is kind of nice.
So I could sort of change these to be like opengl d.c.
Opengl RC that are local, right?
There we go.
And so I can call the start a function say, oh, this is the DC, and
this is the RC I want you to clone those and give me a low price
startup, and maybe like this, you know, do that twice.
So that I've got two of them.
And then when we do this, we just say, all right, go ahead and go
ahead and launch those threads.
Oops, startups.
So that's, that's roughly what we're talking about here.
So all I need to do now is write a function that instead, essentially
instead of that opengl initialization that we're doing before.
It's now going to sort of wrap it up in a win32 startups truck, but
basically do exactly the same thing.
So, I'm going to take a look at and opengl.
Here we go, in 3, 2 opengl.
If I take a look here at the stuff I've got,
See, win32 create college for worker thread, this guy really.
All I want to do is I just want to replace this function with the new
one that we've got.
So I want it to do exactly what it was doing before.
But now I want it to sort of bundle it in this way for me so that it's
ready to do thread startup.
So there we go.
So that's really all we're talking about here.
So assuming that we actually can do what we wanted to do like a.
So when we actually have a wiggle context startup situation Happening
Here,
then what we want to do is say, alright, the window d.c.
Sorry.
We don't need here anymore because we've got one.
So, you can get rid of that and we can actually call this the opengl,
d.c.
the share context is going to be this one that got passed in.
So that actually also doesn't have to be there.
In fact, we could call it here, share context the attributed already.
Have assuming that we got back the, the modern d.c.
That's really all that needs to happen.
And so in some sense, all of this stuff can actually go away, right?
So really all we want to do is say, all right, there's the win32
thread startup, this is the result.
There was the result.
Yeah, opengl DC is going to be the opengl.
D.c.
the result.
Oops, there's all opengl context.
Is going to be the one that we make.
And that's really it.
So that's all the.
That's all the
That's all the business that has to happen.
So if we do that, then I think we're in the right position.
Now for everything to kind of flow smoothly, we can get rid of the
concept that there's things that need opengl because now we either
pass it or don't and it can detect it just from that.
And so the only thing that I need to do now is I need to see if this
All right, because we also don't know if this will work on AMD, right?
We know that people thought it worked on video, but we don't know
whether it works on AMD because we're now changing the way that we
from what we know worked on AMD before these are some of the wonders
of win32 compatibility.
So if we step in here to where we create our threads opengl has
already been initialized obviously so that's all good.
You can see us kind of go through this here we create the high
priority queues those won't have opengl.
Now we create the low priority queues you can.
See me sort of going through here and creating that those startup
structures should.
Now mean that we have, oops.
We should have opengl context for all of our threads and you can see
that.
It looks like we did not get them.
I want to say that doesn't look like that worked.
It's so we got it.
We got to see why let's go in here.
Due to.
Here we go.
So we get that opengl DC, we call will create contacts are herbs and
we've got the share context.
Oh, which is no.
Oops.
Why is it now?
Win32 in it.
Opengl should be working ohm, right?
Gotta go delete those global variables.
We tried intentionally, get rid of them and then we never got rid of
them.
And surprisingly, you can't use a global variable if you actually
stopped initializing it at all.
So good.
We got rid of these two which is kind of something that I just wanted
to be able to do, because I just didn't feel like they needed to be
global.
Let's try that one more time.
All right.
There's the high art party starts.
Now, we'll go through the low part is startups.
Here we go.
And even just by the pause there, we can tell that we got it again.
So now, we've got two of those.
And now we're going to go into this function.
We're going to set one here.
So, when we actually get a thread in there, we'll see what it does
here.
Is that thread startup code got the DC, got the our see it's got the
Q.
So now it can go ahead and make that current, which is what it'll do.
Other thread will come in here.
It'll also make current so
Both of our threads have have gotten their gl's set up and are ready
to go in theory.
Now, if this actually is something that does, in fact work, we should
be able to let's see.
Run this here.
There we go.
We should be able to see textures and we do.
So now we're creating our opengl context on the main thread, and then
we're passing those opengl context through to the to the, to the
individual threads to the worker.
Threads to set as current.
And it looks like it works just fine on AMD, so that's good.
We don't know if this will work on Nvidia, but it might.
And so, at least, now we can send this back over.
We can, you know, when we update the code tonight, people who were
testing on a video can tell us.
Does that resolve the problem?
So, there we go.
So, that's really all that has to happen for that.
Now, there's one more thing that we haven't really done on the opengl
side of things.
And that's that, if you look at what we were doing here, I think I
even mentioned this before when I said do we actually need to worry
about this or not we have not gone back and actually seen whether we
in fact do need to worry about it.
And that is that in here in our win32.
Sorry, not in there in here.
In our entire trip list where we're creating our frame buffer, where
were choosing the pixel format for a frame buffer?
We requested wiggle frame, buffer, srgb capable ARB and we're passing
true, Which is far, as I know, is how we're supposed to signal that.
We want srgb on the frame buffer.
Now, what I don't know is whether it's legal to pass that if the
driver hasn't told you that it supports frame buffer srgb, like will
it just sort of crash on that or will something very bad happened?
So I wanted to do is try to at least search or find out.
If there was something in the documentation for real choose pixel
format ARB, they would tell us whether the driver was required to pass
over values.
It didn't know or not because I really just couldn't tell you.
I have absolutely no idea.
So we could see here
let's see, the fighting fires are accepted and here is the
Here's the following values that lists questions over has devised a
crew, we placed folks to see Darren Turner but this is get pixel
formats.
Again, we don't really care.
We care about choose pixel formats.
This time, it's just a list.
I shoot, I Ferris.
All the attributes are natural.
These are followed by the corresponding desired value list of turn.
It was Zero.
If if it's null same value, it was empty.
We don't care about that.
Okay.
So we could have passed 04 the float at Rib list, which I didn't do,
but I probably should have
Okay, there's those same as empty blah blah.
Blah let's see here.
The function of C is true.
If the function fails 450 to get some information get the error codes
in the country version to find select pixel formats to return based on
the entry by specified.
We know all that we have not learned anything.
Let's see.
If both.
And error is generated if P attribute I list or P.
Attribute F lists contain invalid attribute or if HDC is invalid.
So to me, that would suggest that we are not allowed to call it or we
are not allowed to put that in the
Just unless it's actually legal, right?
That seems to me.
Yeah, so I think what we're going to have to do is check for its
existence first and that's a huge pain in the butt as well.
Again this is just the whole like yeah, I don't know why they don't
know why they wouldn't have said that at ribs were ignored if they
weren't known but oh well that's what you would do.
Right.
But I don't know.
Anyway so in opengl we have a thing that can search for extensions.
In fact, you can see here
We've got a thing that searches for extensions and that's all well and
good.
Unfortunately, that's the thing that searches for opengl extensions.
It is not a thing that searches for wiggle extensions so we don't
actually know what the wiggle extensions are without using wiggle.
Get extension string, which is a different thing than GL, get string
GL extensions.
So we would have to call wiggle get get accepted string and search
that which
Think is what we'll have to do.
Now we could if we wanted to instead actually just use this guy and
say, okay, GLX frame buffer srgb, if that's present, then press
obviously it, you know, is going to support that for the destination
at but we probably could say that and we'd probably be right.
But technically since you can use a texture as a frame, buffer in
theory there is a you know, an opengl
Implementation would not be erroneous.
If it said that, it's supported X frame, buffer srgb, but did not
support using it on the actual frame buffer.
That's possible.
It could be the only supports using it on a texture on render to
texture, right?
So, I feel like to actually do the full due diligence here, we would
probably have to actually do the same search again and, and, you know,
check the wiggle extension string to see whether it's there.
I can't say it's cancer.
That's very nice thing to have to do, but I guess we'll do it anyway.
So let's take a look here at at our wiggle extensions and figure out
how to do that.
Now, like I said, it's kind of a pain in the butt, it's kind of the
ultimate irony because in order to check if there's a whale extension
I'm just going to let this sink in for a second.
In order to check for a week to see if you can load a particular bill
extension.
You have two little bit extension, not kidding.
Actually true.
Wiggle get extensions string or extensions string.
It's an extended thing that you have to do and you got to call it.
And when you call, we will get extension string.
It will first get the pointer to it and then you call it.
And it tells you what extensions there are hilariously.
Of course you can never check to see if it exists anyway, in the
proper way because you never would've been able to get a string that
would have had it in it.
And so, you just have to call wiggle, get proc address.
And then see whether or not you get it, get something back.
If that makes sense.
Then you can start calling it but only then so yeah, pretty hilarious.
It would be, you know, either you can laugh about it or you can cry
about it.
I'll leave that decision up to you as the home programmer.
Now, if we go ahead here and look at our other wiggle, get proc
addresses, we can sort of see UPS we can sort of see that they are
sitting in here.
They all get sort of grabbed at the same time and this is a fine time
for us to grab that one as well.
Gets pension string.
Would like what was called and paste it.
I did we will get extension string.
Get extensions string.
EXT, and I guess we didn't put X on the end of swap interval, but I
don't know why I'm going to put it on there.
Now, we will get
Poppy dress and there we go.
So if we get that back we can call it and then that way we can figure
out whether or not we support srgb.
So I think I'll do that right here.
Like we'll just go ahead and call that immediately.
So what we'll say is, if we got that back, we'll get extension string
X.
Then, what we'd want to do is say, okay once we've got, we will
extension string X back.
Then we will call it and find out what those extension strings are.
These are extensions.
And then we'll just use literally the exact same Loop here, but just
will check for, you know, we'll check for whatever the rest of the
stuff is, right?
So there we go.
All right, so if we get the extensions string, we then are going to
Loop over.
I don't know why what the count and at thing, I don't know why that is
actually the way it is.
We're not going to touch it for just going to assume it's fine.
So what I'm going to do here is just say we're going to search for the
one that were actually looking for and then if we get it we'll set
that srgb thing to to be thumbs to be thumbs up.
So what we need to do here is
And you know at this point it seems like we may actually want to wrap
these up in some kind of a life nice little container because they've
all got to be essentially Global variable just sitting here.
It might be nicer if we could just have it as like a little
self-contained thing.
So it's easier to see, it doesn't really change the code hardly at
all, but you know, rather than having to look at all these and guess
that they're all going.
Together.
Maybe we could put them in a struct.
It's just a thought.
So, here's extension string.
Yeah.
And that's all well and good.
We'll get extensions touring EXT.
We then need some kind of a way to say Global variable you know, you
32 open, Jill supports srgb frame buffer and what we'll do is if we
find that extension that tells us that the frame buffer is legal to
support, then we will go ahead and put that in there.
Oops, that's not what I wanted at all.
That was not what I wanted.
We'll go ahead and put that in there as true.
So then, when we know that that's true and we come down here, what I
want to do is say, Okay, I want to pass this list of things, right?
But if it turns out that we can't actually pass this one then I don't
want to pass that one, right.
And it's like 12 it's you know, or should say it's 1, 2 3, 4 5,
Five down, right.
so what I can do is I can just say like well you know, if the opengl
doesn't support this thing,
Then what I can do is say whatever that that guy was the the you know,
the fifth one down, right?
So this is 0 1 right?
2 3 4 5, 6 7, 8, 9 and this is 10.
I can just zero it out.
So I stopped the list of there right now, particularly pretty.
Oh, and I forgot we can also do this apparently.
Not particularly pretty, but it's the easiest way to do it for now and
I'll have a little comment on that in a second here.
So that all seems relatively fine to me.
The only thing we need to know now is what is the opengl?
What is the actual opengl support?
Such a frame of our string.
We should be looking for, like, what is the string that goes in here?
And I don't actually know.
So we need to go look at the srgb.
Frame buffer opengl
Shannon and see what it actually is, right?
Now there should be an extension string, I guess it's just going to be
our Big Frame buffer SRV I guess.
I'm just going to be that
Right, so if we see that, we know we're good to go.
So, there we go.
So if we see that, we think we could probably go, you know, go from
there.
And that's that's all well and good.
So we now just need, we need the function prototype for that guy.
I guess was the only thing that I forgot to grab.
So let's go ahead and grab that.
Here it is.
And that can just be thrown on in there.
So there's there's that typedef and we know this is obviously a win
API call, and we already know what we wanted to call.
It was wiggle, get extension string, EXT.
And that's it for there.
So yeah, I think that's just about it.
I guess I did.
Never rename the variable for this guy.
You asked, which I said, I wanted to do we go swap.
Here, where is that called Wiggle swap?
There it is.
So now
We should be good.
Get extension string, X initializing.
Oh cannot convert.
Oh I beg to differ.
and this guy, actually, I guess this is
just that.
So let's see.
Local variable.
Oh, whoops.
So much slower than I used to be with modal editing.
I haven't really gotten it bound up very well and I'm not as used to
it, as I should be.
So it's kind of frustrating.
But what do you do?
All right.
So let's take a look at where we're at here.
Actually, I guess I want to kind of jump.
Jump back a bit and just take a look at that in.
It's tough now.
And so, what we want to do is come through here and take a look at
that extension string code.
So, here is the extension string code.
Let's see if we got it back, we did.
So, let's see what those extensions actually are.
I have no idea what this card would have for our extensions.
What's find out route?
So hilariously, it tells us that it has wiggle our extension string.
Not that we wouldn't have automatically known that because in order to
do that we would have in order to even see the string we would have to
have already used it but for completeness
So, we've got the pixel format stuff.
We've got multi sample, we've got swap control P buffers, render to
texture read buffers, buffer regions.
There's that wiggle.
X frame, buffer srgb, right there.
So that's good.
Oops.
So yeah.
Seems reasonable.
See if it we actually detected.
So let's see.
We right now.
Are opengl sports.
I should be frame.
Buffer is 0.
We finish the parsing Loop and it is still zero that did not go as I
would have hoped say the very least, not great, not great, not great.
Bob.
All right, so let's try that one more time.
Here we go.
And now and now just make sure that I'm actually looking for the right
thing.
I'm looking for wiggle our bed frame buffer.
Oh no, that's the wrong one.
It doesn't actually have that one.
It has the extra version of it but not the r version, they're the
same.
But it just it's the different string.
So we should actually look for this one because we don't actually care
about the ARB one per se.
We just care that it supports even the extra one.
So that that's good to know.
I suppose it does make sense usually to look instead for of the ARB to
look for the X 1 because if you can use the X1, it's going to be
available in more places than the ARB one, right?
Because the older, the driver, the less likely it is to have the ARB
ones or who knows what, right?
So I wonder to what extent we should actually be trying to look for
like x 2 versions of these instead.
I don't know.
No biggie anyway, so let's try that one more time.
And here we go.
So there's that set to zero, we run to hear it set to 1 so great.
And so off we go.
So I think that's good.
I think that's all good and obviously we're still rendering.
So in doing all this stuff for compatibility sake, we have not broken
anything and so that's a plus
That brings us to the question of.
Is there anything else opengl related that we actually needed to do
that we wanted to do?
And I don't know that there is at the moment we have I guess about
gosh we've got about 25 minutes left which is quite a bit of time so
I'm not 100% sure what we should be doing now because I can't think of
anything super open Jelly that we probably would want to do.
Hmm.
Because that's really the only
I think that we actually needed there.
Where's the list?
Where is the list?
Oh, wait, it's The to do, here we go.
So, let's see.
We've got flush.
All thread cues before reloading, dll?
Okay, that's something we could go.
Try to do, we've got debug code.
We've got some audio debugging.
Rendering some stuff here with Harbor rendering.
So we actually did this.
We did srgb frame buffer in textures.
We did vsync, we did background texture downloads.
We just didn't do run into
Texture.
So I don't know if you want to try to do render to texture, we don't
really have anything right now that uses render to texture, but we
could come up with something that used render to texture.
I just don't know if that's maybe is that too big?
I mean to start 25 minutes render to texture America going to say
yeah.
Hard to say render to texture I mean is very basic operation basically
what you know it's just a way of saying instead of always rendering to
the to the thing, you're going to display on the screen I want to
render to something that I will then use in a subsequent render step
as a source texture as something to pull from right very basic concept
really not much to it but it involves a bunch of fussing in opengl as
you might expect.
T', everything always is when involves a bunch of fussing.
So that's really the only thing on the hardware renderer that we had
there and had a question mark over it.
So I don't know that.
That's what we wanted to really do now or not, but we're definitely
getting down to the end of it here, there's not a whole lot here that
that's left.
So, that makes it a little tougher, makes it a little tougher.
I don't know.
I really don't.
I don't have a, I don't have a concrete idea of what should actually
be going on there.
I feel like in general Travis, let's do flush.
All thread cues before reloading, dll?
I feel like flush all thread cues before reloading, dll is something
that maybe would only take 25 minutes possibly.
And it's, in the win32 platform layer, which is where we are, at
least.
So it's not like totally Switching gears, and it's not like render to
texture, which I think is going to be a more involved topic.
We definitely wouldn't finish it and in 25 minutes.
So, let's take a look at flush all thread cues before reloading, dll.
So, the way that this works right now and I don't really know to what
extent, you know,
And probably test to see where we're at in terms of Live code loading,
because we haven't done much with it.
And so, I don't really know at the moment, to what extent we would
have problems.
If we tried just use our Live code loading.
So, let's just take a look at that because I'm just kind of curious.
So, if I come over here to for coder and I just make it a little
smaller.
So first, we'll just try it.
If I just rebuild, what happens game is still working.
So, apparently, the reload is fine.
And let's see if I make a change to the code somewhere.
So I'm going to go into handmade dot CPP and I guess we'll just look
for maybe some hero rendering code, I don't know.
Oh wait, that's not here anymore.
That's actually over in the world mode.
We started moving things out around a little bit.
So if we're doing some of this,
Of here.
Let's look for some rendering code of some kind that we can tweak just
to we just need something, where we'll be able to visually see on our
screen like here, we go.
So here's another type hero and here are some movement code for it.
And I don't know if this is, let's see.
Push bitmap, any transform.
So here is like some stuff so I should be able to just like comment
out some of this stuff, right?
And then if
I rebuild, I won't see it.
Yeah so there we go we're in relatively good shape but and I'm
imagining this might actually be exactly the bug.
I'm talking about.
Not sure though.
I know it's not.
This is actually just for the, this is the debug thing.
So we have two bugs as far as I know, with with, with Live code
editing that we probably should try to fix one of them is the one on
the to-do list, their the other ones, this one this I believe the
problem here is that when the when this menu stuff happens with our
with our doing is, I think we're not necessarily copying everything
that we should be copying out of the string store of the game.
So
You know, we've got all our stuff in the dll.
The strings are in the dll.
When we reload the dll, those strings move around.
So we can't point to any strings and and count on that actually
working and the debug system, I think at the moment doesn't do that
properly.
So you can see here like it's doing some stuff and it's probably
keeping a stale pointer around that then sort of gets gets broken, so
that's one of them.
The other one that we've got is the technical
In we're using function, call backs right in one particular place and
that is the work queue.
So right now we have a thing that's like, where is that work?
You where is mr.
Work queue.
You two made P process or is it probably do work?
So here's do worker work and
Actually got that's not the actual that's just the stub one that we
use for testing.
So it's actually up in here right.
When three to do next, work queue entry is the actual thing we care
about went through to do next work, queue entry.
And that guy is, is the thing that's in theory would cause us a
problem because you can see right here.
It calls the Centre call back and that callback is not necessarily in
the same place from one building to the next.
So when the dll that has that function in it gets reloaded.
If there's
Work sitting on the work queue.
That persists right from one's from, you know the frame 0 somebody
cues up a job and it's pointing to the deal of the floated at that
time.
And says, this is the place to jump for the work and then you go to
the next frame and it has Reloaded The dll.
And now is a different dll that callback eventually gets called and
it's pointing into garbage in a crashes or something, right?
So, that could easily
Happened to us.
There's nothing protecting that at the moment.
So there's two ways we could solve this problem one, is that we could
have the work cues persist across the frames and not have to worry
about the callbacks by getting rid of the concept of using the
function, callback in the first place, right?
So instead what we could do is just use a single entry point for
workers in the main game code that just has a switch statement and the
switch statement will jump to the right function that we actually want
to.
All right, that gets us out of that business entirely.
That's moment.
However, now that I think about it, that doesn't really help us
because in theory, we might still be in executing some code.
In that previous dll.
So if we were to unload it I don't even know what happens at that
point.
I don't know what happens in Windows when you try to unload a dll that
you're currently actually, executing, I assume you crash.
I don't know to be completely honest with you, I'm not sure.
So I feel like that doesn't help us.
So I feel like we really do need a thing, which says that if we're
going to load, we have to wait for the cues to completely drain out.
And then once the cues are completely drained out,
We can continue.
So this right here is probably, all we really need is went through to
complete all work.
We just need to call that on every cue, right, that we've got.
And once we call that on every Q, we know that we're done.
So what I can probably do is, just say, alright, whenever we go to
reload, right?
Right here, right.
Wow.
Okay.
That's fantastic.
Who didn't update?
People?
Who didn't update the to do file.
Will somebody please tell me who did nothing, we didn't update the to
do file.
We already did that look.
It's right there.
We're even better than we thought we were people give yourselves a big
old pat on the back anyway.
All right.
Well I got nothing.
I don't know what to say.
We already fixed that so
That was sort of anticlimactic.
So yeah.
So we're down to this stuff.
Now I would basically say that over here we've got render to texture
and shaders.
Right?
I feel like we probably want to do those a little later because that's
going to just be for special effects and things like that.
Oh and hey look this guy still in there.
You don't need that anymore.
So yeah, I don't know.
Maybe we'll just call it for today.
I really don't want to do the only things we need to like move on.
Like we need to go start working on the debug code, is what we need to
do.
So maybe we just call it and start on Monday.
It's a shortcoming day because I took, you know, to be fair I took an
extra 20 30 minutes the other day so maybe I should I should just go
to the Q&A now and call it because yeah, I think now it's time to just
go finishes up.
I think we just want to finish these two next week can
How to have a good finishing week because I'd like to go start get
certain the gameplay code.
Like I said, and we're not very far from that because I feel like,
yeah, we could just get get through these guys here and then we'll be
ready to do.
Whatever, final rendering work, we want to do and then go from there.
And, you know, I could I could say that maybe if we do that render
pass, we could just go ahead and say, all right, you know, let's do
that in here as well.
We'll do a little bit of that once we actually get that, these
architectural things all straightened out then we just finish up the
harbor render as well because we'd need shaders to do like the
lighting or something.
I don't know seems reasonable.
I'm just going to say that because yeah, I don't know, I don't know.
It was a bad bad day for ideas.
I was out of ideas of what we should do.
That wasn't going to be starting, one of these things and there isn't
that much left on the to-do list that we can actually do that isn't,
you know, starting something major.
All right, so I'm gonna go to the Q&A, then it'll be an easy Friday.
Everyone's off the hook,
And you assume 73.
That's basically what an end up being.
What do we do for next 20 minutes?
Well, we should go find out that our to-do items already.
Got to dude, I probably should have looked through more of these,
maybe there's stuff on here.
That's the, I don't even know that we did that.
I didn't think so.
I didn't think we did.
I thought this was all stuff.
We hadn't done yet, but I don't know.
Maybe not.
Yeah, I don't know.
Typically, there's a bug in the, if you look at the, if you add this,
not checking the answer to be very about a different one.
Okay, let me go check that.
One also, I should mention this.
I'm kind of annoying problem too.
Is a whoops.
Yeah, that was a completion bug.
That's what we actually wanted, right.
One thing I should mention.
Is you can kind of see.
I talked about I've talked about this a lot of times and I actually
think open gel was a pretty well-designed API for its day like back in
the day and so I don't really want to harsh on opengl to be honest
with you and so I'd like to just caveat that and say that this is not
really has nothing really to do with opengl but I just wanted to point
this out so you saw all the stuff that we had to do.
With opengl to do the multi threat that overlap texture.
Download?
Right?
And the srgb frame buffer,
The reason it's so important for apis to be cleanly designed is
because every all of that stuff we just did, probably how well you saw
its Qbert.
Caleb caught a bug right there that bug that that typo that I did,
should never have even been possible.
Because all we should have had to have done was put it if the API was
properly designed, then this would just be able to be placed there and
it would ignore it if it wasn't capable
Will doing it, right?
Because there's nothing our apps not going to do anything else, right?
And if we wanted to, then you would want the API.
Just have a query that says, can you do this?
You wouldn't want me to have to change what I'm passing to you even.
So right.
And so it's kind of a good example, all that stuff.
We had to do with the multi threads in the con is above all of that is
just meaningless code.
All you can possibly do in that code is screw up, right?
And so what you're basically doing is you're creating
Eating all these opportunities for bugs on the developer side and
their way they're very likely to make them because a they don't know
like, we don't know.
I mean you saw we had a bug on the Nvidia driver there, we have no
idea, but that bug might be there.
It's not in the documentation that we're, we have no idea.
That, that could even be a possibility.
We're just trying to get the contact.
So we gave it a shot and it turned out the way we did it happen to be
wrong for some unknown reason on this particular driver.
So really, the reason that
By Design is so important, is just because every time you make a
mistake like that, you create more opportunities for bugs.
And if you take a look at how many opportunities, there were four bugs
in just, that one thing, there are dozens of places in our code.
Now, none of which need to be there.
None of which actually do anything, all of, which may contain a bug.
And that's because the API is not designed properly, right?
And if
Want, you know, a preview of a small part of my Vulcan rant.
It's that right?
It's that it is absolutely not designed to try to keep the bugs down,
it is like a festival of things that you could do wrong.
And every, you know, one open jail call.
You might see, there's going to be like 30 Vulcan calls, right?
Not my biggest complaint with it.
It's a minor thing, but they were very they were extremely
Opposed to the notion of trying to work on the API, more to reduce the
number of bug points.
And to increase the chances that the error handling on the app side
would be reasonable.
And I don't care how low level or how special purpose your API is.
It doesn't matter.
It's still extremely important that you consider bug-free use to be a
high priority because again, like
Bugs happen, a lot.
And if you don't design your API with that in mind, you're just
proliferating the number of bugs in the world.
You know.
Wait.
Wait, wait wait, hold on a second.
I'm just going to chat now is the hmh bot down.
Is the handmade he robot down?
oh,
Hmm.
So the estimate is about, as down.
We moved it over to another server ants having rough times.
Well, that is very sad.
I don't even know if I want to do him a hero.
If the Bots not here,
Now, if in sohbat is still functioning, then I'm okay because like,
oh, and there it is.
Thank you for your thank you too.
What does it say?
It's about what it is about.
Say it's about said something, thank you to Imperium tactics for
following the channel.
Oh well, that's not one of that's really not the very insightful.
Human sohbat and sohbat says so much more, insightful thing certainly.
But as long as I can see that in sohbat is there, then I'm okay, I'm
okay with that.
Um, but it would be nice to have hmh body as well.
Carrie Johansen totally serious.
When I say you should write an API book.
I would never think of lots of stuff.
Well, I guess I have that lecture and I and nobody still pretty much
does the things that I talked about in there?
So, I mean, I could write a book, but,
You know, what anyone read it?
I don't know.
I mean, there's the thing.
If you type in,
Yeah.
So there's this guy right here.
And I mean, it's got most of the basic principles in there, you know.
And it's pretty much like I think if you do the stuff that's talked
about in the lecture, then you end up with a pretty usable API and
almost nobody actually does them.
So it's not the kid for the keyboard Gamepad and B can have to this
account ever go beyond one.
Or is it there if you put the input getting on a separate thread?
Yeah.
It can't ever.
Go beyond one at the moment for Gamepad inputs.
I don't know about keyboard inputs because I don't know if we do WM
key down, in which case it could that have transitioned out could go
above it, so could Mouse.
So it's basically there, it can go beyond one for circumstances where
the
We're we're passing the message Loop.
So if we look at
Let's see when key yeah.
This right here.
So, here is win32 process pending messages.
So do you see this stuff here?
Where we do win32 process, keyboard message.
I think, don't actually know, but let's see.
I think that means that, at least for the keyboard, you could get it
to be higher.
Let's find out.
To assess keyboard message.
Yeah, so, so for keyboards, it definitely could be higher than one.
And the reason for that is, this is running through the message queue.
So, basically, if windows queues up a key up keydown, keyup key down
on our on, our thread Q, which you know, it could, I don't know that
it ever will because it might not pull the keyboard frequently enough,
I have no idea, but if it did, then that count would go would go up.
Right.
The GamePad, since we only pull it once a frame right now, that
shouldn't be able to.
But like you said, if we decided later that we wanted it to be pulled
more frequently, we could pull it more frequently.
And so I think it's important for the API to have that in there.
If that makes sense.
I feel like we want to set ourselves up for success by making it so
that would be fine that it's too slow to have it.
It's just not
Good enough to pull it.
At that frequency, we can pull it a higher frequency and the game
would still work just fine and it wouldn't break the game in some way.
Keeper.
Caleb kind of grabs Windows related.
Why do so many games especially Source games handle?
Alt-tab poorly?
Well, you know, that's there's a lot to that question.
So the, the main reason is just because they change the display
resolution.
Usually.
So one of the things we didn't do on handmade here as we didn't change
the display resolution,
Now, I'm a big proponent of not changing the display resolution, the
reason, I don't like change the display resolution is because, you
know, that the user is looking at a screen where the display is
working, right?
Because if they weren't, they couldn't click on your game.
Anytime you change, the display resolution, you run the risk of
changing the display to something that their monitor doesn't handle,
properly, or that it won't sink to write or that's buggy or weird or
not what they wanted, right?
So, I usually like to just have it be that they can run the game and
whatever their monitors in, that's the resolution.
We use.
It doesn't necessarily mean the game renders in that resolution, the
game might want to render in a smaller Resolution For Speed purposes
and stretch up to the higher resolution after the fact.
But that's that's the way I prefer to do it now.
Is it a little bit slower?
Yes.
Because you have to pay for that stretching up process and so
sometimes it maybe not the best decision and it may have been better
to do change resolution, it's just a judgment call and I would rather
go the other route.
And say, I'd rather be well, better behaved on people's machines that
are fast enough, which is most people's machines fast enough to do
that scale up.
Then use the change resolution stuff and and go that route.
So usually that's why when you call change resolution then what
happens is any time Windows detects an ALT tab it changes the
resolution back to the default desktop resolution, right?
Which is a whole nother mode change which sometimes does stuff like
moves, the icons around on the screen, or does all these other weird
things?
You who knows what goes on and they could make it so that like, oh,
you know, my my game doesn't know what's going on now.
Blah, blah, blah.
There's this whole night mirror of stuff, right?
So you know
It 100% their fault or sorry.
Is it partially their fault?
Yes.
Is it all their fault?
Know, a lot of it is just Windows is bad, at handling resolution
changes and always has been probably always will be if Microsoft had
done it properly in the first place.
All those games would just work fine and it they would never even have
to know that that was going on, right?
So, no, crying, is there any benefit to moving the main Windows
message queue to another thread?
I'm sorry if you've implemented answer this already, I'm still
catching up.
Not that I can think of
So a couple of things thing, number one is window messages in general,
I believe always come to the same threads Q as created the window.
So you couldn't really move move the main Windows message queue to
another thread per se
You couldn't literally do that, right?
What you could do that would have the same effect is launched the game
on another thread, right?
Which would leave your main thread that created the window that
created the window, free to sit there and spin on the message queue,
right?
You could do that.
So either way, I was just kind of pointing out there's a little
technicality there.
It doesn't change your question your question.
Still totally valid.
It's just I was saying you can't you can't quite right the line of
code that's like
You know, create thread jump to that thread.
And then that thread calls Peak message and handles.
I think it's like, no because since the main thread is the one that
created the window, the peak message thread, just won't ever get any
of its messages.
I believe.
That's what happens.
I could be wrong.
That just seems to be my recollection.
So, but putting that aside because like I said you could totally
implemented by just.
Okay.
So start the game on the other thread and let the main thread to the
messages, you still end up the same circumstance.
Does that have any benefits?
And my answer at the moment is not that I can think of but that
doesn't mean.
The answer is no windows is, obviously a very complicated world.
I only know a certain amount about it and no matter how much I think I
know there's always a new thing.
I learn a new thing every day, right, on Windows, even though I've
been programmed it for,
15 years.
I don't know how long because it's just vast and it changes all the
time and it's you know, one of those things that that, you know, I
just because I don't know the reason why you might want to do that
doesn't mean that someone else out there would like oh yeah it's good
to do that because you do this or something and it's better or
something like that.
So yeah.
My answer is, I don't know if one but that doesn't mean.
In that there isn't one part of the reason why message queues are good
in general, is because you don't have to babysit them.
And so some of the things, some of the reasons why you might want to
do things on a separate thread, are kind of obviated by the fact that
it is a queue.
So for example, if you were pulling the keyboard you might have to do
that on a separate thread to make sure that you pulled it frequently
enough to not miss keystrokes.
Right.
But if you're just getting your keystroke information from Windows,
and windows is is doing that pulling itself and putting it onto a cue
for you.
Well, now it's really just windows that has to make sure that it pulls
the free keyboard for going off.
You're just going to sit there and consume messages on the Queue and
those messages can pile up.
If there's been several key presses during between the two times, when
you're asked about the queue, you're not going to miss them.
You're going to get them.
All right.
And so part of the, the reason why I say, I don't know of any
particular reason why you would want to run that Q on a separate
thread is because most of the messages that we care about, getting
through that thread, our messages that can just pile up.
If we don't get to them in time, they're not, they're not going to get
dropped.
There are certain messages in Windows that do get dropped.
And so, for example, a WM paint message, windows will drop
S WM paint message.
If it's there's already WM paint message pending I believe.
I don't really know if it merges them or exactly what it does but you
won't get them all, they won't just keep piling up.
So there's things like that, that can happen, but those that's good.
Like it from our perspective.
We wouldn't have wanted tons of paint messages, doesn't give us any
information.
So to the best of my knowledge, I can't think of a reason, but maybe
someone on the thread can
so,
Gaston 5 do you use Windows GDI outside of the educational usage?
You have been showing?
No, I don't really I mean there have been times in the past where I
have but as far as in a game I don't and you can kind of see that now
like we've got the two past, we've got the software renderer in the
hardware.
Renderer you can sort of see now that we don't really ever used UTI
anymore, the hardware render path always uses it.
And even if we use software,
Rendering, we can blind through the the opengl path.
So pretty much the only thing we ever use GDI for is to create the
opengl context and then everything goes through opengl.
And that same thing is true for pretty much anything you do on Windows
nowadays.
If you're talking about performance-oriented Graphics, you really just
don't use GDI, you use GDI, just long enough to get DirectX on.
Been running or opengl up and running, but you never actually care
about GDI per se or GI Plus or any of the other nonsense Graphics
apis.
That Microsoft has been proliferating lately, direct2d direct font
text or Draw, I don't even know what they called.
The other ones they have direct font something there's direct, I don't
even know.
They've got weird, grabs libraries, the only thing you ever want to do
is get a handle, the graphics card and go that's what you actually
want.
And that's what opengl does and DirectX does and now Vulcan and mantle
and those
Things do.
So you pretty much are going to talk to those apis if you care about
performance Graphics because there's really no other sort of logical
path.
So, any more Q colons.
If you can promote for a coder, we always do at the end of the stream.
I always do.
Sounds like, you know, how to play drums.
No, I do not know how to play drums.
Sonic Ron what do you think of Vulcan what price are?
Usually, I don't like it but I don't really like you 312 either.
So
I don't know which I didn't mean API.
Quality has almost nothing to do with whether the API takes over in in
these spheres, really, if that makes sense.
So like
I mean, just just look at the state of apis in general, you know, has
it ever really been the case that if this API was really good?
That's the one that prevailed versus these other a pads.
It's not really.
It tends to be more about Market forces and who's pushing one over the
other and which one to like a does a platform better decide to push
for some reason?
You know, even if you just look at opengl and direct3d, like why are
those that I was like I'm not using opengl or you know, direct3d.
Because I think there
Awesome.
I'm using them because of the only two ways to talk to the graphics
Hardware on Windows, right?
It's not like there was there's these these plethora of API, right?
And so so who knows so we'll Vulcan replace the 3D.
Will it replace opengl?
Who knows?
It might it might not it large.
I think it largely depends on things that have absolutely nothing to
do with.
Whether it's good it has to do with what vendors push and what vendors
support and what windows.
Microsoft decides to do.
I think that's most of it Microsoft to a certain degree recently in my
in my situation seems to be losing its appetite for trying to lock
people into the windows platform per se and they seem to be caring
more about locking people into things.
They can maybe make more money from like Windows store or things like
that.
So I don't know how much they care about stuff like d3d before locking
people into their apis, Microsoft considered.
To be a huge strategic advantage.
And they really, really, really wanted that to be the case.
And I don't know if that's really so much of their game plan anymore.
You know, you see them doing things like allowing stuff to run on
Linux and porting to other things and caring more about their software
making money in the general case and less about Windows as this court
thing.
And so I think that makes it hard to predict what they're going to do
the Microsoft of five years ago would.
Of let D3, dude, I never never in a million years, they would have
specifically killed Vulcan, if they had to directly rather than Let
d3d Die, the Microsoft that today, they might have a different agenda.
Selection buffer versus Ray picking versus color picking for Mouse
picking.
I usually prefer re picking personally and that's just because I feel
like doing an entire another render pass is kind of expensive.
So it's just a kid for detecting long presses on keyboards, but I put
a timestamp in the input struct.
Sure.
I mean, that's a perfectly reasonable way to do it.
Basically what happens is, you know, when the key first goes down, you
start a timer and you increment it as you go and then you know how
long the keys been down, right?
What's next feature?
We're going to work on.
I think we're going to try and finish the debug code next week.
Debug diagramming and stuff like that.
Do you think all the modern see those denominators like C++ 11 C plus
14 6417 cos x yr, an internal joke to obscure the mess.
The language is in
well, I guess what I would say is,
I feel like it kind of underscores the fact that they don't even
understand the original joke in the first place, which is odd, because
even the original didn't also understand the joke, because, like C++,
right is a no op, if you say C++ it, increments the value of C
somewhere else but it returns, you get back.
See.
It would be plus plus, see if you made something better if we were
getting better.
But C++ means somebody else made something better over.
In main memory somewhere that you're not going to actually get the
results of in this expression.
And in this expression, you're left with just see, which is kind of
hilariously true because basically, that's what C++ is, it's like,
well, C is in there and you still have that and everything else was
useless, right?
So C plus plus
Well stated I guess they picked the name, right?
But then CBS 11, that's not a legal see statement anymore, so they
didn't even get the original joke.
Like it would have been C plus equals 11 or something, right?
Or C plus 11 in parentheses it would like they didn't even they
weren't even able to be consistent with their own joke which I guess
kind of just sums up the whole thing.
Kira.
Caleb.
Is it worth selling my soul and learning JS python for money?
I mean, I don't know, right pause.
Let's let's quantify selling your soul.
Let's say that whatever you're going to do with JS python is not
particularly bad for the world.
Let's say it's not an advertising company, it's actually a company
that does something a real service that maybe help Society in some
way.
Even if it's only commercial, Hey, You Gotta Eat, Right?
I mean, learn JS Python and make some money.
That's totally reasonable thing to do.
If you actually are talking about selling yourself, I mean like I'm
going to go work for a company whose primary job is to like mess with
people's lives and show crappy ads or something on a service.
Maybe don't do that, right.
Because we all have a choice about how we affect the world and it's
what we're willing to do.
And what we're not willing to do.
And I feel like programmers to a large extent, don't think of
themselves as having to make ethical decisions, but they absolutely
So what we do and I feel like before you ever take a job, I don't care
what kind it is, whether your program or anything else, you should
always think about do.
I think this is actually making Society better place or is this
largely something that's taking advantage of people and siphoning
money away for more important things that could be happening, right?
So I'd say, I don't know, the answer your question, the answer maybe.
Yeah you should do it.
You should take a job for the money and just because it's you know,
maybe
Anything that you don't particularly be think, particularly
interesting.
You gotta you gotta eat if it's actually selling your soul, like in
the real definition, like I'm like, you know, I'm going to go work on
for like palantir or somebody like no, don't do that.
Like no programmer should ever go to work for that company.
It's just wrong.
Let's see.
Any thoughts on sdl to not?
I have not used it.
Sorry, I don't have a lot of thoughts on it.
What technique you're going to use for pathfinding?
I don't know.
Maybe rer
Use a not sure we'll see when we get there.
LT Demi and been doing a lot of Jays.
What do you think I should do next?
Kind of bored with Jas
You know, I feel like see is a good thing to do to feel like doing
some other programming in c is good thing if you're bored with Jas
because it helps you get away from the whole like everything is
virtual and sort of amorphous and weird in the way the JS is.
It's more like concrete.
Like, here's memory and I'm actually like messing with it.
It's kind of nice.
So,
The bus Vulcan is extremely low level.
That was requested by various game engine and harbor developers.
There's probably a huge market for Deaf friendly API to sit on top of
Vulcan to Shield us from those gory details.
Don't think so question mark.
So here's what I'd say about that.
First of all, whether something is low level or not has nothing to do
with whether it's error-prone, right?
Every system has complexity and it
And some Epi is which are very high.
Level are still very complicated, right?
You know,
You could take even something like you know Mi sound system or f ma
just, you know, just a sound playing API, right?
And that API could be incredibly complicated complexity has nothing to
do with whether you wrote the API properly to eliminate bugs that
didn't need to happen, right?
So that's the first thing.
The second thing is, I actually don't think Vulcan is low level.
I don't think Vulcan is low level at all.
And that's one of my biggest
Problems with it.
Like I said, I don't really want to do this rant until I've had a
chance to actually go through it and so I can give them more specific
thing but I don't think Vulcans the level at all.
I don't think I don't between Vulcan and opengl.
I don't think either is more low-level what Vulcan actually is, is
it's just a high level API that happens to map closely to the very
instantaneous right now, state of a certain intersection of GPU parts
But in five years, it will be no more low level than opengl.
And the driver will be doing all kinds of crazy stuff behind your
back.
Just like I'm Joe has when opengl was created.
It was incredibly low level AGL vertex, call compiled to an out to a
port on the CPU.
It was far more low level than Vulcan ever will be.
Or is
so the degree to which you can say something as low level has to do
with what the guarantees are of, what that API will actually do and
Vulcan has none.
There are zero guarantees of what the API will do.
It is not low level.
It does not write directly to the card does, not compile directly to
any known code.
It is literally as high level as opengl or direct3d is Right Now.
Full stop.
And so what people actually mean when they say it's low level is they
mean it happens to be closer, cloak more closely, approximate the
series of steps a bunch of driver writers who were willing to sort of
tell each other a little bit about what their drivers did.
Sort of came up with as a common set of steps that might be happening
right now for our current batch of cards.
That does not mean low level
An actual low level API for graphics cards would be one where there
were almost no API calls.
It would just be like, here is a way to map memory and you just right
into the memory, right?
And you're in charge of building the command buffer is, you're in
charge of everything, right?
And that API would be awesome because that would have been an actual
spec that then Hardware vendors would have had to make their Hardware
comply with
And that is not what Vulcan is nor is it what Vulcan will ever be
right?
So yeah, it's a disappointment because I thought that's what Vulcan
was going to be.
I thought Vulcans.
Going to be an agreed-upon spec for basically getting rid of the API.
And instead, what it is is they just multiplied the size of the API by
like 1,000.
So now there's like, you know, hundreds and hundreds of API calls and
Most of them probably won't map to anything that Hardware does in 5
years or 10 years.
Right?
And it's just open gel all over again.
Cast of five.
How much do you follow the latest Technologies?
Do you think it is a waste of time to learn the latest Graphics API
for any development?
Yeah, probably.
I mean, it depends on the circumstance, right?
Like what I would say is that depending on what you're trying to do
with your indie game, I don't actually know what might be the the best
approach if you're trying to distinguish Yourself by being
graphically.
You know, by doing something special graphically, then it might make a
lot of sense to
Spend time following the latest Technologies and Graphics because,
well, how are you going to distinguish yourself graphically?
If you're not doing something that's, that's pretty fancy, right?
But if on the other hand, your bid calling card is your art style and
that art styles more about what the artists are doing and not about
what your technology allows or if you're any games.
More about some specific gameplay thing that you're looking at, then
how much does being a place technology really affect that, you know,
maybe it doesn't right.
And that's similar across like that's across all things, right?
Like the choice.
People often ask like, why don't I just use like Unity to make a game
or while I just do this or bars do that?
And the answer is that like, all decisions that you might make in game
development, have, you know, pros and cons.
And so, if you are happening to make a game that, that maybe Maps very
well to an existing engine, then you should use that engine, right?
The point of being a game developer and remaining educated on these
things and being good at your job, has a lot more to do with knowing
what you should do, as
As opposed to.
How to do it obviously knowing how to do it is important.
Once you know that it's something you want to do but being a capable
developer has to do with making those good decisions if you're only
ability as a developer is to have to use Unity or you're only ability
to develop our is to have to use opengl and you can't do anything
else.
You don't even know whether you should know to do anything else.
That's very limiting.
It means that you will not make good development assistance by
definition because even if you were going to definitely use an engine,
maybe the Unreal Engine was better.
Right?
Maybe that would've been a much better choice for this circumstance or
something, right?
Maybe Amazon's new engine, lumber yard or Timber Mill or sawdust, or
whatever they call it.
I have no idea.
Maybe that would have been a better choice, right?
And so keeping up with new technologies, I would say learning a latest
Graphics API is probably not so important, knowing that there are
other graphics apis, and why you might need to look into them, that is
kind of important, right?
Because
Cause if you don't know about Vulcan or what it is, but it turns out
that using it for this game was going to be important.
You've made a mistake and you've let your team down as a programmer by
not being aware that there was some path.
You should have been pursuing.
And so, I think I said this before on the stream and I'll just, you
know, re-emphasize it here that is a very important in part of knowing
how to program.
It's one of the reasons I do handmade hero as well.
It's one of the big reasons for is that a lot of programmers.
Now, don't know how to do low-level code.
And if you don't know how to do low-level code, there's a bunch of
decisions.
You won't make well, even if you're using an engine, even if you're
not programming at the low level.
And so,
Having that knowledge base is really important and you're not really
doing a service to your team as if you're a core programmer and you
don't know how to make those kind of good decisions.
That's what I would say.
And so I feel like everyone who's going to be a serious programmer
needs to know all of this stuff and be able to make good decisions.
even if that decision is not doing the thing that you knew about,
let's see.
Her Domina, why should know programmer work for palantir?
Well pounder is basically a company which creates data mining tools
for like all the people you hate, right?
Like the the whole thing about like you know, how do we, how do we
write code that finds all the Muslims or whatever?
Right, that's palantir.
So like all the like evil stuff like the US government does, like it's
pretty much a company set up to do that and you know, they're not
proud, they'll sell their technology to
Other people as well, but that's pretty much what they do.
And you know, like I just I feel like you're making a very ethically
bad decision.
If you ever agree to work for a company like that, it's just it's not
right, you know.
It's like programmers, it's the Manhattan Project thing.
It's like you got to think through, you got to, you got to actually
consider like you know, just because you're a scientist, doing science
things.
You have to try to figure out how you're going to make sure that
the world's doesn't become a worse place because of the things that
you did, you know,
Guitar.
Maybe seven does.
John used more stable specific stuff than yours do?
Does John you mean in you mean when John is programming to use my
cheapest stuff, the answer is yes.
If that's what you're asking, John in general uses a bunch of C++
features that I don't use.
He uses virtual functions hughes's.
I don't think he uses private data very much.
Although other people on the team, do he uses like,
Lambda.
Sometimes, I think.
And once in a while, he'll use a template he's though, be he's very
light on the C++ even so, so he does use more than me but not that
much more.
He'll use a few more features but he even doesn't really use them very
often.
Probably one of the reasons he's making his own language is because he
doesn't like the features in C++ and like me, he would like more
features, but he would like them to work his way.
And so, that's what j i is, right.
He's like, I want the things that virtual function should have given
me and didn't.
So I'm going to go Implement what I think that should have been and,
you know, then he's going to have a language that actually is able to
do the things he was trying to do and see those pleasant couldn't, you
know.
What do you think about the new Snowdrop game engine?
I don't know anything about it.
I believe that's the one used on like the division, but I've never
seen the engine.
I mean, I seen the division, the division looks nice, but I mean, I
don't know.
You know, you can't really judge an engine by that computers are real
fast nowadays.
So, pretty much all the engines, look decent, you know, if the artists
were good
Kb3, do you plan on using Vulcan considering the permit services that
people have been claiming exist?
I don't know.
Obviously on Nvidia, you don't really need Vulcan for anything because
you can get very good performance on opengl.
But on AMD, there's no question because they're opengl drivers are
quite a bit worse and so on, if you want to be fast on AMD cards, then
I wouldn't be surprised.
If the only way to do that was what's by using Vulcan that said, you
know,
We're in in we're a small developer, right?
And if it comes down to, like, well, I could do this whole
Path just to make the game run faster on AMD cards.
Probably wouldn't do that right?
Like that's a bad decision compared to me going in improving the
interactive fiction Tech, right?
And since I think Vulcan is a giant pile, like I'm I have no vested
interest in supporting it so it's not getting me any, you know, it's
not going to be any real benefit.
They're so hard to say.
Bella rain, since you write everything from scratch.
Why not use a language like go because go is like super high level?
Right?
I don't really like Kai level languages that much.
It's not my jam.
I guess it's different from high level features.
I like high level features, I just don't like have other languages.
Sanchez 1337.
If any what games have you been playing recently and how did you like
them?
I haven't really played much.
I was on our SI break, and I didn't really think playing a lot of
games would be a good idea, right?
So,
I have noticed that there is no more send email in the hammer here.
Website used to reply to emails.
I usually do yes.
But I was just getting too many of them to answer, so I just made the
forums so that people could post on there and then other people can
usually answer the questions for them if they're just questions about
something that that other people know.
So I would say if you really have to email me, something go right
ahead.
But if it's actually just a question about the series, then the forums
much better place for it so that I can answer it in a public place
where other people can see it, or somebody who usually what ends up
having is Martin's Mosaic who answers the question because he
apparently knows the answer to literally every question and he's
always on the Forum.
So pretty much every time I see a question.
The forms Martin's has already answered it.
It's kind of crazy.
He should really be the one doing this.
Just turn over the stream to him.
Where do you see the game developer Community going in the next 5-10
years?
I've no idea.
The main difference is in the example.
See in the language or friend is developing in three sentences or
less.
I mean, you'd have to ask him anonymous 835.
Do you have experience with posix Linux system calls fork for example?
Yes, I have called Fork.
I need to create a small process scheduler, but when I create a fork
inside a forest cycle, it messes up, I need to create an amount of
processes then save them to a fight Philistines for executing one at a
time.
so, I mean,
I guess what I would say is,
I don't see why Fork would actually break if you called it inside a
for Loop.
It shouldn't.
Are you sure you're not doing something else wrong?
I mean that said, I don't know that I ever have myself called Fork
inside a for loop.
I don't do that much Linux programming, but basically what happens
when you call Fork, is you get a clone of your process with the memory
set to copy on write.
And one of the people who calls for gets back, one parameter and one
of the people calls for cats back, another one, right?
So you then you just check which one you are and break out of the for
Loop.
Right.
You break on the for Loop.
If you're the child process, you just say if if I'm the child process
break out the for Loop, like that should work, right?
If you con, would you want to be one of the first people to play
around with j?
Or would you wait till it gets more mature?
I I think it probably depends on when it gets released.
I probably won't have time when it's when it actually is released to
look at it as one of the first people, because I'll probably be right
in the middle of trying to finish 1935.
I mean, I guess, but if it happened to conclude, if he happens to
release it at a time, when I am more free and have some time to devote
to it, then then I might be.
So I don't think it will have much to do with my desire to check it
out or not, it'll have more to do with my schedule is the time because
in order to really check out a program language, you got to spend some
serious time with it.
Like you can't just go read through it and be like it looks good or
not.
It's like I'd have to actually spend some time because you know John
is making a bunch of decisions.
And in order to say whether those decisions were good or bad, you
can't just like look at them and go.
Cole.
I don't think I would have done it that way.
It's like well okay yeah but so what maybe they were still a bunch of
good decisions and maybe they add up to something really good and
maybe my way that I would have decided would have actually been
stupid, right?
That's the whole part point of that whole process of going through
designing something.
When you actually have to do it sometimes you come to very different
conclusions than what an armchair analysis would would entail.
And so I feel like in order to really get into a separate language
like jiu gotta sweat, sit down, spend some serious time for that.
And so whether or not I do that close close to when it
release is going to be almost entirely depend on my schedule, not on
whether I want to
Are you going to check out OBS Studio this weekend?
I've no idea.
Burger Kodak.
Do you work on another game project other than handmade?
Yes, obviously, I'm working on 1935 right now.
Fact, I guess we have a website.
Even you know what, Mom
1935.com with there's nothing on here at the moment but this is
actually the game that I'm working on at the moment at my actual job.
So yeah, that's what I work on during the day.
Hello.
Alan is Fork a good API or a bad API.
I don't know, really how to answer that question.
I guess what I would say about four is that if the goal of the API,
was to Fork the process, it's a good API.
If the goal is to have ways of creating more processes, probably not,
because it's really not
It's really not what you want to do.
Usually like, I don't usually need to clone the memory of the process
and it sort of creates a need for copy-on-write page handling.
That wouldn't have otherwise been there and it's very heavy weight for
certain circumstances.
So I think what I would say is it depends on what they were actually
trying to do with it.
I don't know what their goals were at the time that fork was designed
and so either it was a good or a bad API or I should say whether it
was whether it's bad or not kind of
And what the goal was I think and I don't know.
GDC is next week.
What?
Handmade here representation of GC, I will not be at GDC.
All right, I think that's enough cues.
I think that's enough cues for now.
By the way, Alan.
I will try to remember to send you that crash, dump.
I uploaded to Google last night and then I forgot to check this
morning to make sure it was done in and send it to you, but I got that
one gigabyte crash dump for you.
Which, by the way, I think it's pretty awesome that we've been using
for coders.
We've had literally one crash and no other problems before coder
pretty much this entire time.
So it's been doing pretty awesome for a program that's barely.
It hasn't even had a non out.
It's not even in beta yet and it's already doing pretty darn good.
So
Nice work, man, it's very nice work.
All right, let's go ahead and wind things down here.
Let's see.
Close.
You know, I probably shouldn't close that because I don't actually
know if I ever bothered to say the two texts but that's okay.
Because it was already an accurate to do list.
Anyway, thank you, everyone for joining me for another sort of
handmade here.
It's been a pleasure coding with you.
As always, if you would like to follow along with handmade here at
home, you can always go to handmade here at Oregon.
Pre-order the game.
It comes with a source code, so you can follow along and do your own
experiments and learning.
We also have a forum site where you can go to ask questions.
If you have questions about stuff, we've done, we have a patreon page,
you can go to if you want to support the video series and we have a
Repot that you can go to to check the schedule?
Everything you need.
Is there the editor that we use on stream is for coder.
You can search for it.
It's a project by someone who's actually on the chat, Alan Webster and
that's what we're using right now.
You can go to his for a coder page on patreon.
Like I just did type for coder into Google, it'll take you there and
if you pledge there's three different tiers you can pledge $1 a month
to it and you just get a copy of for a coder.
If you do five dollars a month and you get four quarters,
What's the customization API?
Dll stuff you can use to program it and see which is what I used to
create the one views on handmade hero.
And if you ten dollars a month you actually get my handmade hero, one
comes with it, so you can actually get our the customizations that we
use on the stream if those interest you.
So check that out.
And yeah, check out the Tweet but if you want to schedule for next
week, I think it'll probably be a pretty standard schedule.
Next week, don't anticipate anything to weird but you never know.
So check the Tweet but until then, I will see you guys Monday for
another round.
Programming.
I think we'll go ahead and finish the debug stuff next week, probably
because we kind of left that and we just got to go back there and dig
through it a little bit and get it into a nice usable shape.
So until then have fun programming this weekend and I will see you
guys on the internet.
Take it easy.