Okay, hello everyone, and welcome to handmade hero.
The show where we code complete game live on Twitch.
No engine, no, libraries.
It's just our code here and this is an educational stream.
Obviously, it's a way for us to take a look at absolutely everything
that goes on when a game is actually running.
So including the engine including what the graphics card does
basically everything.
So we look at everything in full detail and, you know, basic try to
get get sort of a holistic.
You of how game programming actually works.
Not just a pigeon, whole thing of like, how to do this one little
thing and it's been going pretty well.
So far, we're right in the middle of a topic.
That's very important for any kind of game development, which is
optimization what to do when your code is too slow and you're not
getting the performance that you need.
And so we're taking a look at that stuff.
Right now, what we did yesterday was we kind of verified some
performance analysis stuff by putting some performance counters in our
code.
That tell us how long things take
And today what we'd like to do is start looking at what we can
actually do about that in order to start acting on the information
that we have based on the performance information that we've gathered.
So I'd like to go ahead and jump into that.
If you want to follow along at home today is day 114.
So if you have pre-ordered, the game on handmade hero dot-org, you
want to download day 113 source code because that is the source code
that I am starting with today.
So if you want to follow along at home, please make sure you start
with
That.
So let's go ahead and open things up.
Open them up.
And if you remember where we left off before, we were taking a look at
draw rectangle slowly, right?
And what we had is, we were dumping to the, the debug Port.
You can see that we would, we would every frame dump out some psycho.
Counters that tell us some interesting information about our code such
as the fact that we are currently spending about three hundred eighty
four cycles per pixel doing things, right?
And we were at the point yesterday where we want to start thinking
about what is a reasonable number of cycles per pixel that we actually
think we could get this routine down to.
And so, one of the things that we kind of need to do at this point in
order to start forming, that kind of an estimate, is we need to start
thinking about draw rectangle, slowly, a little more carefully because
we really were, just trying to get it working.
When we wrote it the first time we were just basically trying to learn
How to draw texture map triangles, we didn't actually try to organize
this code to be particularly optimal or to do anything.
Particularly interesting.
In terms of performance, all we did was do what worked right.
And so what we need to start looking at now is, can we do some
Transformations on this code to put it into what we think is a
relatively clean minimal set of calculations
Instead, it's actually doing.
And then we can look at that and go with this algorithm that we have
here, what how, how much, how many operations do we actually have to
do?
And that will kind of give us a little bit of guidance as to what we
actually, you know, what, we can actually expect to see in terms of
Peak Performance, which kind of gives us a goal to work towards,
right?
So what I actually want to do here with draw a rectangle slowly is I
would like to Jimmy
I would like to sort of Spawn this routine out.
Basically, I'd like to take draw a rectangle slowly and I'd like to
sort of pull it out into its own into into basically a new version,
right?
And we'll call that draw rectangle quickly, maybe we'll call it draw a
rectangle, hopefully quickly, right?
And we can, we can go ahead and have that and we're going to take
that.
Normal mapping out for the moment because we're not, you know, we're
not going to focus on that just yet but we're going to leave
everything else in place.
So we're going to do everything else in here and we're going to have
draw rectangle hopefully quickly.
Single hopefully quickly in here.
I go to add a performance camper for that, and we're going to make a
version of this.
That's just a little more cleaned up in terms of what operations it
actually has to do.
Let's see here, hopefully quickly.
So we now, we know that really, this, this Preamble here is not
something that we super need to focus on at the moment.
And the reason for that, of course, is that if we were to
Actually, if we were to actually optimize this part that's not getting
called per pixel, it would have very little effect on the performance
as it is at the moment, right?
Most of our time, we know is spent actually inside because the
performance counters are spent inside this, these pixel loops and that
makes perfect sense because there's just a lot more pixels than there
are rectangles, right?
And so you're spending a lot of time in here because hey there's just
a lot more pixels the rectangle.
So it doesn't matter what you do / rectangle, / pixels where the time
is spent.
No.
Right.
Okay, so what we'd like to do now is we'd like to and I'm going to
leave these time blocks for the moment to just be test pixel.
Actually, I'm not, I'm because we're not going to call these and if we
start calling them together, we can play with that but I'm gonna
switch between these two routine so I don't really care.
So, let's take a look at this first.
I'm going to go ahead and remove everything that we don't actually
need in here, right?
So I'm going to take out this this normal mapping code, right?
That we had in here.
Like so.
Believe that's everything.
And I am going to.
Make sure I don't delete anything that we need.
So let's go ahead and that in there.
Okay, did I get everything correctly there?
Okay, there we go.
Draw.
A rectangle slowly will be replaced with draw a rectangle, hopefully
quickly.
And of course, this never passed any normal mapping to it anyway when
we actually just drew bitmap that was not, so I did that.
So now I want to make sure that that's the running properly, it is.
So that's all good and we can see that the timing is the same, which
is what we would have expected, right?
Okay.
So up and draw a rectangle hopefully quickly, I'm going to go through
this Loop now and start to take a look at what it is that we're
actually doing here, right?
And maybe get rid of some of the vector operations as well, just so we
can really be much clearer as to what's actually happening inside the
routine, right?
And you can kind of see well you know we've got some stuff here,
that's that's relatively straightforward, you know, we're advancing by
pixels that seems all totally fine.
But inside here.
We do this stuff and we're doing our DOT products in that, that sort
of thing.
I just want to make sure that this stuff looks relatively kosher you
can kind of see in here already that there's some stuff that probably
doesn't make a whole lot of sense.
Because, you know, x axis, minus y axis and this like - perp y-axis,
all this sort of stuff, actually boils down to some pretty basic
things that are going to be happening in.
Taylor Forum that we could optimize out in also even in Vector form.
You can see we, you know, x-axis and y-axis are constant.
So, you know, even if we had to do it this way, you wouldn't probably
inside in the middle of your Loop, constantly be doing repeated
subtractions, and stuff like that.
So I want to take a look at this Edge testing code, and maybe make it
a little bit more explicit, right?
So if we take a look here, we've got the inner product of D with -
perp x-axis, right?
And we kind of know exactly what perk does right?
If we go in here to math.h, here is perp, right?
It just swaps the two things and it swaps.
The two things in the gates, the the Y, right?
So we actually know that the inner
a product of D with perp is just the same as if we had written out
that inner product like this, right?
So we could say at zero equals the inner product and we know that a is
d, right?
And we know that b is just the perp of x-axis.
So, we know that this term will become negative.
Here is x axis X, right?
And here is x axis y.
Sorry X swap them like so right, so we know that that's actually all
that that was Computing.
And so we can kind of cut down the complexity there by just looking at
that and going, okay, that's just, you know, a very straightforward
computation.
Get rid of that.
We go for Edge one, we have basically the same thing, right?
We've got, you know what?
And what's kind of interesting about these two here is you can also
see there be there is additional kind of there's additional kind of
stuff we could take advantage of in certain circumstances, but I'll
kind of leave that for later because you can kind of see if you know
that the y axis is the x axis.
But perpendicular, then when you perpendicular again, you just get the
x axis back pointing in the negative.
Action, right?
So you kind of have this interesting thing where you're like okay you
know, looking at this actual value you can kind of
You can kind of see where you would get some additional stuff.
In fact, I'm going to, I'm going to take a quick detour over here to
the Blackboard.
I just want to kind of look and see if we really actually need to do
what we're doing here with all of these inner products actually now
that I think about it because if you take a look at what's actually
happening here, right, we've got a vector to the pixel, right?
DD is a vector to the pixel, that's what it actually is, right?
So that's, that's
What, like d is, you know, and then we have, this is our x-axis, and
this is our y-axis, right?
and so, if we were to take D and do the inner product of D onto that,
x-axis, I feel like we really shouldn't have to
Like, I feel like we really shouldn't have to check all of those
parameters, right?
Because if we take that, that inner product,
We could actually pre, we could do something like pre normalize that
x-axis at the top of the routine and just look to see whether you know
how far it had gone along it, right?
So we could do one dot product and then just test the bounds you know
on either side right?
So I feel like we're all.
So this is probably actually not the most efficient way we could
actually iterate over this, you know, in terms of
Our equations here.
And similarly you can see right here, where Computing the U and the V
to do our texture mapping and the you
The V would also tell us whether we were inside the bitmap, right?
I mean, if we just ignore this Edge stuff entirely, right?
And didn't ever test the edges, what if we just tested, you know,
tested these two, right?
So yeah, I mean, suppose we were to compute the u and v coordinates
and just look to see whether the u and v coordinates were actually
inside the square.
That seems like a pretty easy way to go and that gets rid of all this
work, right?
Right.
That seemed reasonable.
So I'm just saying maybe we just do this as a test.
Right.
Something like that.
And I guess I don't know how we want to do inside outside.
We'll have to think about that a little bit like which, which of these
it actually goes to.
I'm suspecting we probably need to do it like that.
But yeah.
So if we were to actually do that, do we actually even need any of
this, right?
Can we just get rid of that entirely for starters?
So, let's take a look and hey unsurprisingly we did not actually need
that and our game actually got a little
Master just doing that, which is kind of funny.
Right.
You can see that it actually got.
We were up at like 380.
Something an hour it's we have three you got a little faster just
getting rid of that.
Okay.
So anyway
That seems much smarter anyway, because now we just have that inner
product here.
Time's the end of axis length.
Right?
Which seems pretty good.
But if you look at that, now that I think about it, that's actually
already doing too much work too because we could have just pre
multiply the x axis by the invitation box of length squared to begin
with, right?
And if we were to, if we were to do that then we wouldn't have to
multiply it every time.
So that seems like a pretty reasonable thing to do as well, right?
I mean, you can imagine if we did like some kind of like
you know, and x-axis or something like this, which is just
This.
X, the x axis.
We should be able to replace this with n x axis and then be done,
right?
P 2 and y axis equals that X, Y axis, so and y axis and off we go.
I don't know.
Just seems pretty basic right, pretty straightforward.
And again, everything still Blitz.
Fine.
No issues there and just to make sure that I didn't mess anything up.
We can also verify that we are actually calling that through a
rectangle.
But we quickly.
Right.
So, there we go.
And of course, it's hopping all around because it's in debug mode, but
that's fine.
All right, so again, I'm just going through here.
It's very simple.
Just pruning out stuff and getting us down to what would be a
reasonable thing to even analyze.
Because we just have a ton of stuff in here that just doesn't need to
happen as we are finding out.
So the screen space UV is not actually used unless we're normal
mapping, so that goes away, Z diff same thing, right?
I believe.
Yep.
So that all goes away.
We now no longer have to worry about the clamping because we're
actually checking to get into the into the loop.
So that'll go away and then we have our texture, boundary
multiplication.
So we've got our texture width and height, minus 2.
We need to think about this a little bit, I'm going to leave that for
one second, we've got our clamping care.
We assert just to make sure that we're within range.
Which is fine that I'll compile out earlier in release mode.
We have our textile sampling code, which I imagine.
We're going to have to get a little harder Quran, we coming here and
we've got our clamping, then we do our pixel packing and we we go into
into linear space.
Do the blend come out of linear space and repack.
So, all in all, there's not a whole lot of code here.
You can see it's already starting to clamp to clamp down a little bit.
so in order to produce this X and Y, yeah, looks like
It looks like.
Textiles.
Okay, so it looks like basically, What's Happening Here is we're
clamping the r g and B between 0 & 1.
But unless we were going to pass in color values that were greater
than 1.
We wouldn't really need to clamp them here.
Anyway, that's that was really for the other routine which was which
was potentially producing color values that are greater, we could
still put a clamp in here.
It's not particularly expensive, do the clamp but what we
To do instead, you know that.
I'm not sure if we actually care about that clamp very much I guess we
can leave it in there and because in Cindy it's going to be extremely
cheap to clamp that.
So maybe we'll leave that in just, just in case we want to set these
color values to be able to blow things out, like set color, set the
color to be you know, x 2 or something like this instead of things
that always
Keep it normalized, right?
All right.
So I'm going to go up and grab the rest of this stuff and injected
into this routine just so we can look at it right?
I want to see what it's actually doing.
So here is our srgb to linear code, right?
And what that's doing is it's taking dest and it's doing that to desk
directly, right?
So it's basically converting desk into, you know, that space by
squaring it.
So we would need that imp 255 to be up here.
There we go, and squaring it.
After we do this in verse squaring is obviously just multiplying this
thing by itself again, so that's pretty straightforward up, just one
more multiply.
And then, of course, this one doesn't get squared because that's stays
in that space.
So there we go, going to linear brightness, space.
And then linear 12, rg2 srgb, same thing again, just going to cut that
out.
Put that in here and again,
I'm really doing here is I'm just flattening this routine out so I can
see everything it does.
And think about it in one place, which is just a lot easier for me
than trying, to go chase down a bunch of separate routines, right?
So really, we've got Blended here although technically I don't know
why we even need to do that.
We could just compute that right in place.
I'm not sure why we bother doing it that way.
But let's go ahead and finish doing it this way.
Anyway, when did when did Blended we go and get rid of that.
Let's take a look, just make sure that runs everything looks good
there all good.
And so if we take a look in here,
this is a wide operation as well as is this one, and this one, we've
got several wide operations here.
Meaning they're operating on a vector once, right?
I shouldn't say wide because we're not talking about Cindy wide.
Basically, what I mean is not scalar.
So I want to do is take a look at these here.
One - Texel a times dest plus Texel, right?
So that's what's happening to dest immediately after I work with it,
right?
Immediately.
After I put it into this space, I'm essentially doing not blow this
out here into
scalar form RGB a
Here we go.
Okay.
All of these have the same operation there.
Oops, and I do.
Okay.
So let's take a look here.
I don't see a whole lot of of cruft in What's Happening Here.
It looks fairly straightforward, right?
We're squaring.
These values to bring them into the into the linear brightness space.
Which makes perfect sense.
We have to compute the textile a, which we use.
So, you know, we've got, we've basically got an mtech Salette here,
right?
Which is this value?
1 - the textile, a
Basic got an income tax Olay here.
That we're doing to each of these.
And if we were to put, if we were to smush these guys together I don't
see there's really no way to get any benefit out of these.
Like I'm not seeing any way to collapse any terms here.
It's all just pretty much multiplies that have to happen, right?
I mean I don't, I don't know.
I really don't.
I do not see anything there.
What is that?
1255 bit, that's just 255, okay, so how do we know why this one was
not using that value is there?
Is there some explanation for that?
Like why did these guys all do 125?
And this one doesn't know why that was seems a bit odd.
Alright, so those guys almost fly.
alright, so again
No change, everything is good.
And so, let's take a look up at.
Yeah, we probably need to start taking a look at the, the bilinear
blend and stuff here, because it doesn't look like there's a whole lot
else that we can actually do.
We can actually focus on.
So, we're starting to see this code blown out to everything that it
actually needs to do.
I'm going to I'm going to go ahead and make this guy be more explicit
as well.
I'm just going to have desk be actually written out in scalar.
As well.
And again this is just so I can kind of see what it actually looks
like when you're not hiding operations behind a bunch of utility
functions, right?
So let's go ahead and and make that happen.
So this is
Us producing the, you know, this is basically us doing the unpack,
right?
Dest be
dest a like, so there's the unpack and then we do the operations on
the unpack.
Now, this guy also works the same way, it's assuming that we leave the
clamp in there.
So I could turn that guy into scalar as well.
And we basically just have these operations here where we've got
Texel.
So something like this,
Bert's Texel equals Texel are
sorry.
But textile R equals textile.
.R.
X colored out our
A.
All right, so that's entirely blown out into scalar now.
And really the only part that we're not dealing with explicitly, is
this part right here, right.
So you can kind of see, absolutely everything that we actually need to
do here in explicit form, so that's pretty good.
Again, everything looks fine.
No worries.
So if I'm actually doing all of this stuff in scalar, what do I get?
When I, when I take a look at my srgb by linear blend.
All right, my srgb.
Bio layer blend, it has to do a bunch of unpacks so you can see that
this is really nasty, like, look at this guy.
This is just, this is just a beast, all of this stuff.
Is really pretty mundane.
Like, you can see there's just not that many operations here.
We've got them all written out, it's not that bad to deal with.
But this the bilinear blend with.
The sampling is just just nasty, right?
The actual loads are not that many operations, of course, you know,
they're probably slow because their loads, but
Can see how many operations happened here, you got to do that
unpacking.
You've got to do that.
That srgb to linear on all of them and then you got to do the double
Earp's.
It's just nasty, nasty, nasty, nasty, but that's what we're doing.
So nasty, it may be, but we're going to have to actually make it
happen.
Alright?
So let's go ahead and, and actually paste these guys in there, so we
can start to look at them.
let's see here by winning your sample by other your sample like
That is not that bad, right?
Taking the textile sample, it's actually not that bad.
So we'll do those a sample.
A b c and d like so which is not too bad.
And that's going to take.
Those are actually packed pixels that come in here, right?
And then when we actually grab these out, let's see.
Textile pointer.
We have texture X and Y.
So the actually hurt were already using the variables that we wanted
to use, so that's totally fine.
So and then srgb by linear blend.
But that guy in there, and that will just take Texel sample.
So, this is just going to do sample.
A sample, B, sample, C and Sample, D.
And I think that's about it, and then that just produces that final
Texel value.
There we go.
So now we have the routine semi flattened but we still have to look at
these guys, right?
And so this this is pretty straightforward.
There's not a whole lot that's going on here.
The only thing we could do is we could you know pre we could know
these offsets ahead of time potentially, right?
So that we don't have to do additional ads here but the compiler is
going to probably fold most of that stuff out.
And so just looking at this way is totally fine for now.
We have those unpacks and the srgb to linear is in here that we need
to do and then we have to unpack these lips so I'm going to start with
the lips.
Since those are pretty basic.
So the lerp
Let's see.
We've got to do tulips and then we have to let the result of the
loops, right?
Again pretty.
This is pretty beastly.
But I want to go through this, at least once this way, so you can see
it.
All right, so to do this, we've got to actually produce an
intermediate value here, right?
This is sort of, like a, I don't know what we'll call this, you know,
I guess, you know, we could even think about what that actually means
multiply it out though.
So, if you think about this in floating point, I mean it started in on
vector format scalar, right?
If you think about that actually, looks like we're doing this
operation on each one.
Right, that makes sense.
So it's basically, you know it's this
Operation on each one.
And, you know, we know that the the lerp operation is going to be 1
minus FY times the first part, right?
And then f y times, the second part,
Like so.
Make this a little easier to read here.
Right?
So we know we're doing that that operation and then each of these
larps, we are.
We know that that's the exact same lerp.
Right?
So I can replace this lerp with the same thing.
1.0
- FX X Texel.
A plus FX.
X text will be
Like so.
Right.
So yeah, I'm going to introduce just to make this a little easier to
I'm going to make an eye FX, which is basically the just 1.0 - that
effects.
And an ify is 1 point.
0 minus FY, which are the pre subtracted versions of these just so we
can look at them a little easier, right?
So it's just I FY times this expression, right?
In fact, I guess I don't actually need another
Thing, their FY times this expression.
FX just xld.
Right?
And at the end, it turns out to not be quite so nasty when we actually
multiply it out.
And furthermore if we wanted to, we could actually pre compute these
blend terms more explicitly.
Right?
Because using distributive property, right?
I can just go ahead and multiply I FY times both of these guys
Right.
Make sense and get rid of the parentheses and then I can do the same
thing here.
If I want to write again distribute FY out there.
And now if you actually look at these, we actually just have sort of
three blend coefficients that.
Do that whole ER process already pre multiply that out, right?
We've basically got like, you know, l0
L1, L2, L3, which are just these coefficients, right there is all
zero.
There's a one.
There's all too.
And there's all three.
Right.
Oops, Got actually right in there.
And so what you can see is this this whole by linear blend just kind
of folds down after you actually look at what it's doing that whole
blend.
Just fold folds down into four multiplies and for ads, right?
Because if I pre compute the terms, I can then use those for
everything that I actually need to do each one of the scalars can just
actually have that happen to it directly, right?
I can compute RGB and a all exactly the same way without
out actually having to do that sort of lerp, nesting ridiculousness.
And off you go.
So yeah.
Pretty straightforward.
Right?
Seems seems pretty simple.
You could even save a little bit more here by actually pre multiplying
the color.
And I suppose to these actual blend coefficients and if we actually
want to go that far but you can see that we're about to take this
entire expression and multiply it by these.
So we could instead multiply the 4 coefficients by these, right?
And eliminate this.
Which would actually but well it doesn't really help because it still
for multiplies, I guess so yeah, I guess Loop that just moves it
around.
Doesn't actually do anything for us.
If we were going to use these more often I suppose it would but it
looks like that's redundant.
So we'll leave it the way it is.
Okay, there we go, let's make sure that our lerp is still working at
all.
There we go.
All looks pretty good.
It's kind of hard to see.
I wonder if we maybe should.
Yeah, get some stuff that's a little closer but that's looking pretty
good.
Everything looks good.
So there we go.
Alright.
So we've got our bread linear blend.
I might start putting some notes in here, which is like, this is the
bilayer texture blend, just so we can see what's actually happening
there.
Like, so,
Huh, and so then we still have that srgb to linear and the unpacks and
then, let's see.
This is modulated by color module 8.
Incoming color.
This is plant colors, valid range.
This is load destination.
And yeah.
Everything else looks that good, this is destination, Blends and
repack.
All right, so you can kind of start to see the stages in here.
Now, we have to do this srgb to linear in this unpack still, but then,
we are after that, we have completely flattened this routine out to
look at exactly what it actually does.
So that there's no kind of mystery in there anymore, we flatten it
down and we can kind of look for any additional things in there that
are maybe not necessarily needing to happen.
But let's go ahead and just finish that off so srgb to linear, right?
This has
To unpack each of these textiles, I don't think there's very much we
can actually do to make this work any better than it actually does,
unfortunately.
But basically, if we are to take each of these guys here, just Texel
a, a pixel, a a, like so.
And then we
Just modify it in place that I think that's basically what we're
looking at.
Yeah.
So, we got to do that four times.
and,
Oops, it's no good.
All right, so now last thing is the unpack.
Everything still looks good.
Last thing is our unpack, our unpack.
It looks like this.
So there it is.
All right.
Again, this guy's going to be float, will convert that over to float
and that'll just look like this, right?
So that's actually doing Texel a just unpack sample, a right to
sample, a group's sample, a sample.
A
Sir.
And Texel PR.
Texel CR and Texel.
Oh wait, that's not what I wanted.
Big g b a a
Okay, so that unpack sample a and we need to do that for each of our
things.
Like I said, unfortunately got to do a bunch of unpacks here.
See.
Candid.
And I think,
That concludes our flattening.
And you can see there's quite a lot of coding here that has to
actually run, which is a bummer, but it's why things are slow, right?
You got a lot of code.
That's, that's a lot of code operating on.
A lot of things equals a slow program.
To say the very least.
Oops, typo.
There we go.
And okay.
So these are actually the guys doing the blank.
There we go.
Okay.
Now, all right.
So that's
Aang, I'm not sure if there's anything that we want to try to squeeze
out of here.
That's actually happening before we go.
But you can see, you know.
Yeah, it's big but it's not that big.
So at the end of the day, this isn't too awful, right?
This isn't the this isn't the worst that you learn that you're likely
to see in your programming and what's kind of funny, you know.
I don't know what to say about this sort of stuff other than just.
Yeah, this is how it goes.
You'll notice we're compiling with optimizations on, right?
So if I go in, if I go into the build,
Right.
We've got - 02, which says Microsoft C compiler.
Please can optimize this as much as you want.
So basically none of that stuff that I did should have actually sped
up the program at all.
The only thing that would have set it up was eliminating that code,
that was the normal map code.
But as we saw, like each time, as I've been going here, we've been
getting faster and faster.
All of those changes that I did actually sped the code up not nearly
as much as we wanted to speed the code up, but it's just kind of
silly, you know, these sort of, you know, just rigid Transformations,
compilers just have a hard go of it, you know, it's a hard problem
compiling.
Optimized code it is.
And so it turns out that if you structure things a little clearer and
you remove terms that maybe you think the compiler should have it ends
up being beneficial even before you actually optimize anything because
we really haven't done much that the compiler couldn't have done
itself.
We did the UV trance transformation and the remove the neural net code
about the only two things that the compiler couldn't have done itself
probably.
But you know what do you do?
All right, so we don't have a lot of time left.
We got, you know, 15 minutes left or something like that.
But what I'd like you to take a look at now is again, like I said, we
want to sort of form, you know, have some kind of an opinion try to
get to a place where we have an idea of how much time this code is
going to take to run, right?
And a little bit, a little bit of its kind of hard for us to estimate
because packing and unpacking doesn't look like it looks in when we
when we actually go to do the Cindy version of it.
Some things look exactly the same like multiplies look like multiplies
and 70.
So you know we can just look at the code and say do we need to do a
multiply if the answer is yes then that would have turned into a
simply multiply when we go to optimize it but some of the other things
like pack and unpack actually look quite different depending on
whether you're doing them in Cindy or not and so stuff like this is a
little bit harder but
That kind of gets to one of the things that I want to talk about which
is a little more complicated.
and that is,
Really at the end of the day, if you take a look at how this code
works and think about how we're going to symbolize it, right?
If you think about how we're going to start operating on this thing
wide, we actually have kind of a really nasty problem with these
unpacking 's that we do, right?
And the reason that we have a kind of nasty problem with the unpacking
is because if you look at everything else we do everything we do in
scalar form could easily be blown out to do.
Four pixels at a time, right?
You know anything that we do that's just a regular operation like this
could just be done on four pixels.
At the same time it doesn't have any particular, you no need to do
anything else, right?
But our unpack operations are actually not that way.
Because if you look at what our unpacked operations are are unpacked
operations, load a single value, right?
They load like this, one 32-bit integer and then it has to convert
that
32-bit integer out into separate channels, right?
So you can see here.
It's we're reading from the same value in a bunch of places and doing
this sort of conversion out which sort of it's a little bit nasty,
right?
And you can see us again doing it here like this, combines a bunch of
these things together to write a single thing out, right?
And so we kind of have a choice that we have to make at some point and
I think maybe now would probably be a good time to start talking about
it.
I don't know if we want to I want to kind of set the stage maybe for
tomorrow where we maybe talk about it, a little more detail.
But basically, the problem looks like this, right?
What?
Is our wide strategy.
Right.
So what I talked about on the episode, when I sort of introducing
optimization contents as I talked a lot about this thing called Cindy,
which is single instruction,
Multiple data.
Right.
And what that meant is, I said, we're essentially going to have to
start thinking about operating on four things once.
Okay?
Now for things at once, could mean multiple things, right?
If I know that I'm going to operate on for floating Point values,
right?
0 1, 2, 3.
Well, what do those values mean?
I could be talking about pixel 1 pixel to pixel 3, pixel for whatever,
right?
I could be talking about multiple pixels.
So each one of my Lanes each one of my symptoms
Lanes could be a separate pixel.
So I try to operate on four pixels at a time.
Let's say that's one way.
Another way to do it would be to map those to RGB in a, right?
So I basically have each of those, you know, map that way.
And so, when you think about how you want to operate on these, you
have to kind of consider when you're operating on four things at once.
What are the four things, right?
What, what are they?
And if you take a look at how things are working in here, you can see
why one thing that we probably don't want to do is to use this to use
the
The format where it's rgba, right?
So if we were to talk about a Sim D architecture that was RGB and a
packed into our Cindy registers, right?
You can see already that that would be kind of bad because just
looking at the operations we do, they don't chain that way, very well.
Most operations treat the alpha differently than they treat, the r, g
and B, right?
And so, we constantly be fighting this situation where, you know, we
got to we got to deal with the alpha and in a different way and we
constantly be losing like a quarter of our performance by downshifting
all the time to deal with it that way.
So what we'd rather do is always be able to do it in something where
the, the stuff happens exactly the same every time and that's why
pixels is a much more compelling thing is because all of these things,
if we were to do for a pixel at a time, obviously all of these
operations just work with
Everyday.
Are you know, if you're doing this operation?
Well you're doing it on the a Channel of four pixels at once and
you're just doing the same operation on all four, right?
Which is fine, but
The same thing I just said about RGB turns out to be true.
When you look at unpacking right, unpacking is a problem because
unpacking means that I can't just take some input values and then
start working with them, right?
I mean the the classic example for would be the r g and B here, right?
I load in, you know, let's say I load in for Pixel values, right?
And they're 32-bit packed
So you know, this is rgba here, rgba here, rgba here RG, oops GBA here
because remember each one of these things is 32 bits, right?
And this is just me, 128 bits long, right?
It's one of these wide things and normally we've got floats in there,
but if we were to talk about looking at like the frame buffer or
something like that or the texture there, these packed rgba things,
right?
So
When we load those in, we then have this nasty problem of we have to
get from this right into something where we actually group all of the
ours together, right?
So we have to grab all the ours out and
And then we have to grab all the geez out, right to produce rrr grr,
be an RA so that we can start working on things in that, pixel, in
that pixel way, right?
So, you know, one thing that often happens.
When you're talking about really optimizing for stuff like this is you
might convert your frame buffer format.
So that your frame buffer format is actually instead of storing things
this way.
It actually just stores, ours together, you know, geez together B's
together.
And so on to save this annoying process that I'm that I'm showing you
here.
Have to grab out certain things from every value.
So, I guess what I would say is about that.
We're going to talk a bunch tomorrow about Cindy because tomorrow is
sort of the day that, you know, we got our stuff flattened out here in
before we talk about how much each of these operations costs.
I want to talk about Cindy little so that everyone kind of understands
what it is and we've mentioned it much much time.
But I wanted to spend a good Blackboard session just talking about
Cindy, how it works, what it means and that sort of stuff and so that
we can go through an estimate, the costs here.
What I wanted to say about that is because the goal for this is not to
ship us off our rasterizer, but rather to write a software, rasterizer
that works the same way gpus generally work because I think that's
where educational and more interesting since there's no point in
shipping a software, rasterizer in today's day and age, you're going
to use the GPU if you want performance, right?
I think we're not going to take that step of reorganizing our textures
and our frame buffers to be packed our pack g-pack.
B and so on.
Because I'd rather do closer to what the GPU does and the GPU does do
that does does pack them.
They the GPU doesn't reorganize them.
And the reason for that,
Is that the GPU has much more powerful unpacking stuff that it can do
and it would rather have the cash locality of making sure it because
it knows it's always going to use RGB and a is together so it would
rather have that cache locality.
So instead it just has Hardware.
That does that unpacking very efficiently, right?
And doesn't have to worry about it.
We don't have that special purpose Hardware on a CPU because they
didn't, you know, they didn't put in instructions for doing that sort
of thing, but the impact is not that bad.
And so, we'll see when we talk about somebody tomorrow, they'll be
ways that we can do the unpacking, probably relatively quickly.
And so, but it might be a little less efficient than it would have
been if we had reorganized our frame buffer.
All right, so anyway, we've got ourselves reorganized here, and we're
about done with today's episode.
So that's good.
What I would.
Like to do.
potentially, here is
No, we haven't.
One thing that we might want to empty shell.
Look and see if there's anything we need to kind of solidify.
I don't think so.
Basically, like pixel centers up here.
The thing that determines whether or not, you're touching a pixel
explicitly, or not.
And how you convert from that to a texture.
Coordinate, might be something we want to make a little more solid and
a little more specified but everything else pretty much is the same
after that.
And all of this code we've already vetted like this already is pretty
much what we want to do.
It does the operation
Is that the right space?
It produces the the proper results that we want to produce already and
so given that that's the case.
I think we can go ahead and optimize just you know, this whole part
and if later on when we go in, maybe we'll do a little passive.
Do some correctness stuff.
If we have to change, just the Preamble part to pick the pixels in a
slightly different way.
That doesn't really bother me at all.
So I think we're good.
So I think that's a good place to leave it for today.
Tomorrow, we'll talk about what, what is exactly all the sympathy
stuff is that we've been referring to and what instructions we have to
work with there so that we can go through and make an estimate of how
we're going to do all these things and how fast it should run.
And then we just go ahead and convert it really it's not that much
more complicated than that, to be honest with you.
That's honestly, that's it.
It's pretty simple.
So yeah.
So if we take a look at all this stuff again, I hope that hasn't
frightened you away too much, because really just the flattening down
was just so we could make sure we see everything that has to happen.
And we know that we can do the steps in Cindy and the reason I didn't
blow out this clamp function also was because clamp is really a very
specific thing.
That's very easy to do in Cindy.
It doesn't require branching.
So it would be very misleading if I blew out the scale.
Version of these with the ifs and stuff like that.
Basically that's that's that's why that is the way that is.
So clamp will really just translate to to instructions and Sunday, so
I didn't feel like it was necessary to extract that out because we'll
be very, very straightforward.
But yeah.
So let's go ahead and go to the Q&A.
And if anyone has any questions, I will take them now.
Braden Cruiser, the way the code is written.
Now, you have a very long dependency chain.
Between instructions, will you break down the code to remove it?
So, not there really isn't a dependency chain here for, for an Intel
processor.
So, if you take a look at this, right,
We've got unpacking issues aside, right?
If you take a look at these, any given window, here of instructions,
there's tons of things that are not dependent, right?
so, you know, for example,
It can issue all four of these totally separately right?
This does not depend on this does not depend on this does not depend
on this, right?
And so as long as you have enough instructions to mask, whatever the
latency is of a particular unit or the throughput is a particular
whatever, the latency is of the particular unit, you're targeting,
right?
So let's say you're doing multiplies or whatever.
As long as you have enough, so that you can that it will retire in
time.
You're told, you're totally fine, right?
So it can issue for example, these two multiplies together and then
this one, and this one, it can issue all of those together.
And, you know, by the time it's issued four of those and comes back to
issue the next ones you're probably okay, right?
And similarly, even if it can't like, let's say it is,
Use these all and then it can't do the square yet because it's waiting
for this, it can issue all of these because these are all independent.
It can issue all of these because these are all independent, right?
And the windows pretty large.
So, you know, again, rearranging these is not necessarily all that
valuable for you to do, that makes sense.
But if it's something that you're worried about, you can certainly do
this.
Right.
You can certainly start pushing things up more together or you can you
can pull the, you know, you can pull the multiplies out so that you
square, you do the square, you know, down here as a separate thing.
I'm just I'm not sure that there's really any point in doing any of
that because there's there's really just not that much cereal
dependency here in terms of the actual window that the process going
to look at that make sense.
But yeah, the other problem that we do have though a little bit is
that there's nothing you can do about the fact that things are a
little.
See really dependent, you know, it's pixel processing.
So you got to you know, you have some sort of dependencies there but I
don't think basically the processors are very fast with how fast
multiplies move through the pipeline your the latency isn't 300
Cycles.
You know it's like eight Cycles or six Cycles or whatever right?
And so you really don't have to have that many
Instructions in the window for that to work.
Stellar 7.
Why did I write float?
Instead of real attorney to thank you for catching that.
There's a very specific reason why I wrote that something that annoys
me to no end, but I'm almost coming to the end of it now.
So it's fine.
Do a bunch of optimization work on the witness, for the past three
days, and in there, it's called float, right?
So I had to get you some typing float for three days.
Why do you do to instead of O 3 or 0 fast?
I think just because I don't really know the compiler switches these
days that well is 0-3 faster than 0 to buy any.
Let's find out.
So let's see here.
Here is our game running.
You know, we've got two hundred and forty some odd Cycles happening
per pixel there.
Here's our three.
Says, ignoring unknown option so fast.
Are you sure these are actual switches?
Stellar 7.
Do you ever use exclusive or operations to avoid pipeline stalls?
If not what do you use?
No, I generally don't because I don't tend to do that level of
optimization like generally.
Well I shouldn't say that sometimes I do use exclusive or but I don't
use them because I'm trying to avoid pipeline stalls.
I use them because I'm programming and Cindy, and you have to do a
bunch of manipulation with tests and stuff like that.
But basically, like
My optimization tends to just be, I write stuff in Cindy.
I lay it out and I write it in Cindy and then I'm done, right?
I don't, I usually do not go beyond that.
Like I said on the Xbox 360, I did a bunch of work where I did go
beyond that because it was a very special circumstance but that's not
my normal modus operandi.
Like I am not the guy who who uses exclusive or to avoid a pipeline
stall.
Like that's that's not the kind of optimization.
I tend to do.
Aren't those square roots?
Pretty expensive.
So actually they're not and that's pretty interesting, you know, you
can
I don't know if there's a good.
Thing on here for that.
But if you take a look in sse2, right?
You've got the, I just don't know if this guide has the
Some of the stuff in here, if you take a look in it and actually want,
I just want to see the square root eans.
There it is.
So, if you take a look at the in square root PS routine here, right?
This routine actually completes in a reasonable amount of time.
I'm sorry.
Sweetie.
This instruction actually competes in a reasonable amount of time.
It is not slow instruction and what's what is it on?
I don't actually know what is that blue?
I don't know what the blue is supposed to be representing.
Their this is the one I actually wanted.
Here it is.
Reciprocal square root.
That's the one.
I actually wanted.
So, getting one over the square root, right?
Which is pretty crazy, right?
One over the square root,
Is actually crazy fast.
You can actually do one over the square root in in hardly any time at
all like take a look at this.
Latency 53.
Put one and it goes down all the way down to two latency 23 if you're
on the other one, right?
But on any of the modern cores, it's a bit of latency.
But you can, you can issue a ton of them, right?
So you can actually, if you're issuing, several of them, you can
actually get them going through at one cycle per inverse square root.
And so, since we don't
Actually care that much about how accurate the square roots are I
would suppose that we're going to be able to do those pretty quickly.
You know it's a it's an inverse square root.
So we'll have to do I don't think we have access to the regular square
root.
I don't actually remember if that was what the regular, whether the
regular square root is actually in there or not, let's let's see here.
I think they added that later.
I'm sorry, I've never used this fact.
This was something that someone on the stream point out to me.
It's pretty cool.
I but I've never used it before.
Some kind of, I'm kind of lame and actually finding it.
So I feel like there should be a square root that was actually on
here.
I feel like they added square root.
Some point, right?
I mean,
Pretty sure.
Mmm.
Squirt PD.
But where is Squirt?
PS?
Well, tell you what?
And I'm squirt PS.
There it is.
Yeah.
So here, if we actually just want to do the regular square root
instead of doing like a thing in an inversion, even then it's not that
bad, right?
It gets worse if we go down but that's not that bad and that's
actually available on regular SSE, I guess.
So that's been in there forever.
So doing the square root.
Yeah.
I mean, do we want to have to spend 14 Cycles or seven Cycles
depending on the processor?
You know, know, but at the same time it's like well,
You know, it's not too bad and we can do the accurate rendering.
Now, if we want to, we can always just get rid of these because all
they were as to do light linear computations, right?
So if we find, they're too slow.
We really want to get rid of me can but that's just that's not too
bad.
So I think we could probably do it.
For example, you know, one way we could
Do it is, you know, we have some we have some overhead for doing this.
Throughput we could probably do that and try to like mask out some,
you know, try to basically like have some other stuff going on while
that's happening.
So maybe we maybe it overlapped physically.
I say I'm not sure, but I think it should be pretty good.
I think it's not too bad.
It will definitely be one of the more expensive instructions that we
ever call, though.
That's definitely true.
Will you make multiple CMD back ends know, we're only going to do one
Cindy back end because really the other 70 back ends would just be
kind of their nest.
Not that interesting.
They just be whiter, right?
Because we're not using that many fancy instructions so it's not, I
guess maybe with the unpacking there's some things we might could do
differently but I don't think it's worth it since.
We're not trying to ship the renderer as a thing that people actually
use, I don't know that there's much.
Point in doing multiple sanity back ends.
You could lost some of those variables at one more Loop.
Yes, that's probably true.
We could I haven't looked too much at which ones we would Loft out
though.
I don't think there's that many, you know, like some of these can be
moved.
But the compiler will almost definitely do those but we yeah, you
know, we can take a look, I didn't want to do.
The reason I didn't do these two was because we want to talk about
this a little bit because we still haven't sort of decided exactly how
that multiplication happens.
But yeah,
I think this is actually wrong.
If this should be minus one.
Yeah.
How expensive is the float to in conversion?
Compared to the rest of the workload?
I think it typically takes about one cycle.
I mean, one cycle, two cycles.
It's an SSE instruction, it's called convert.
You can take a look at it here.
So basically, like, you know, here's here's what you're looking at.
So I guess I guess you can actually it only takes one cycle to do that
conversion.
So it's pretty, it's pretty painless.
It used to be the case that it was nasty, but it's pretty painless
now.
Since x-axis and y-axis are usually perpendicular should be special
case for that, in the same vein should be special case for axis
aligned.
So I don't know that there's really all that much we have to do to
special case because if you look at this,
I mean, just just look at this.
All of this work is what we have to do per pixel.
So, saving the special case for the axis of line, this is just not
that interesting.
The way that it might be the place that it would be beneficial would
be the texture, lookups, because you could reuse some of them.
But again, I want to keep this relatively close to how the GPU work.
So I don't really know if I want to go down that road too much and
plus since it's going to be in the cache, when you do those multiple
fetches, I don't know that you would save that much anyway.
But yeah, if you wanted to go as fast as possible, you would probably
special case basically axis aligned so that you could optimize your
texture fetches to reuse textiles, you've already had and you probably
do both, you do a shrinking one, and a growing one separately.
Does the compiler do any automatic SSE optimization?
I think so.
I don't think it probably did it for us, but I think it does on Gees
on llvm.
Definitely has a vectorizer you can invoke but I don't really know
about visual Studios.
I pretty much always write it myself, so I don't really know.
Let me let me, let me see if I can
Get this to happen here.
so, if we take a look at what it's doing,
Go to.
Disassembly.
We can kind of look to see if it looks like it's doing anything
particularly intelligent with that.
I don't actually know if it is or not, but let's see.
Next sort we go.
Where is my right there is the registers.
Let's take a look at the SSE registers.
There we go.
So you can kind of see, unfortunately.
The answer is, no, it really hasn't done anything.
It's pretty much working exclusively in in just the lower part of the
register, right, because this is the register.
And, you know, if it was, if it was operating on a bunch of things at
once, you would see it spread out in here.
And so you can kind of see that.
It's just doing everything in scalar and keeping it in the lower part
of the SSC registers.
So, it's
Never actually doing anything out out here.
So so it didn't it didn't happen to, in this case, there might be some
feature you can turn on but I'm not sure.
Squirt SS versus squirt.
PS versus squirt PD.
Okay.
So, this is just the ridiculous.
We'll talk a little bit about this tomorrow and it always confuses me
to no end anyway.
But for whatever reason, when they introduced these engines X, you
know, they're underscore.
Mmm.
I think that b stood for a multimedia or something.
I don't even know, don't ask me, but anyway, the way that they chose
to name them is like, you know, it's mmm.
Underscore mmm.
And then it's underscore whatever the thing is that you're trying to
do, right?
So like you know, if you're trying to do square roots going to be
squirt in the middle, so the operation goes in the middle and then the
suffix is, like, what kind of thing?
It's actually like, what, what, how it's treating, the stuff in the
register.
So PD means pack doubles.
So basically that's going to operate on two.
Doubles, you can kind of see it here, right?
It's going to do to 64-bit square roots, whereas PS is
act singles, right?
So that's going to be for 32-bit floating Point values and you can see
that happening in here.
And then SS means.
I only actually needed to do one of them, right?
And so it's actually doing it on the lower.
Just the 32-bit.
The low 32-bit won't, I don't know?
Yes, it looks like this.
Also does a broadcast, right?
Pivot elements from a, oh no, doesn't it also?
So this does, it does the square root in the bottom and then it leaves
the, the upper three it like, passes the upper three through for you,
for whatever reason.
So this only does one of them, right?
And so that's why there's a PSP D in an SS.
It gets even worse.
You didn't see these, but if you have other operations like add that
apply to everything.
You also have all of these epi.
16, 32, 64, and ate.
Those are basically talking about doing an add-on on eight 16-bit
values in integer.
So Epi is like the integer.
It's an integer 16 wide and of course you can fit eight of those in
128 bits.
There you go.
This is for packed 32-bit integers.
This is too packed 64-bit integers.
This is 16 packed 8-bit integer.
Ders and so on, right?
So yeah I think the E versus the p is just to distinguish it between
when they when they had just MX that was only 64 bits wide instead of
128 bits wide.
But yeah, it's an I mean it's a mess, you know, it's he's actually a
fairly consistent naming scene but it's a mess.
Would SSE allow doing srgb using exponent?
Point to instead of approximating using one, I said of approximately
using to without huge performance.
It no.
Actually.
I mean it's not a huge performance hit but it is definitely
performance.
It requires a table.
It's nasty do it.
Raising something to the 2.2 power is really hard and so the
difference between squaring Square rooting versus doing the Race.
The 2.2 and raising to the 1.0 to point to is a pretty massive
difference actually.
It doesn't matter whether you're in SSI or not, it doesn't get easier.
The main reason why you don't get automatic Cindy is precise
exceptions.
You probably need to tell the compiler that you don't need them yet.
So what's your name 73 is talking about is the fact that and there's
actually a couple things like this which is that this see
specification and the IEEE specification, there's a bunch of things
that generally have to happen that the compiler has to obey when it's
doing floating Point operations.
And if you don't allow it some latitude,
Dude, it might not be able to do basically all of the optimizations it
could do, right?
And so there's flags that maybe turn those off and power like I said,
I'm not super familiar with them so I'm not sure exactly what they
would be sued him.
73 was talking about precise exceptions.
There's another one called floating-point consistency which has to do
with the order of operations that restrictions compiler can do.
So there are ways you can try to tell the compiler be lenient and then
it will you know maybe do those for you.
Now, we
Are saying - FP fast already but I'm not sure if there's additional
ones that try to tell it, you know, that you don't need like things,
like precise exceptions.
Let me see.
If there's any documentation for that.
So except - might be useful.
Let's see.
So let's let's try it.
We can try adding there but I don't actually know if that's going to
help us too much, but we can certainly try it.
All right, so if I go ahead and set a breakpoint in here and take a
look still, no right, still definitely not using any more of the
width, but honestly blame it.
I mean, you know, I don't expect it to Auto vectorize my code.
I can vectorize my code.
What happens if Arch, avx2 switches enabled?
I don't know.
First of all, this machine would crash because it doesn't have any x
2.
In fact, this machine doesn't even have a vx1.
This machine only has SSE
Three or something.
Maybe I see for, I'm not sure, but I'm pretty sure it doesn't have
avx2.
In fact.
No, she's I guess avx-512 that machines don't have right now.
And by the way, I looked at this the other day, this is crazy.
Has anyone done this?
Like look at it.
Look at this, I don't even know.
I got to learn this stuff.
Eventually I don't even know.
Look what is avx-512?
I FM a
I don't even I literally don't even know what that means.
Like I have no idea what these subcategories are because normally when
you go in here, right?
And you look at these, there's just you know there's there's just the
instructions for that grouping.
So you could say I'm SSE 4.2 it's like these are the things that are
necessary for by 2 but avx-512, what is this?
I've never seen this before.
So they have like broken down the instructions, into some other bunch
of these actually different caps bits that the processor would have.
And if so, who is in charge, that's ridiculous.
I sure.
Hope that's not true because who is going to actually check to see
which of this combinations you would have and whether to run them.
So I don't even know.
I hope that's not what that is because that would be crazy if that
were the case.
But yeah.
So yeah.
F ma is fused multiply add well sure.
I mean, yes, FMA is to use multi, but FMA is not the weird one, right?
FMA is is a separate thing that you can select on and off here, right?
It's avx-512 that drops down all of this stuff and I have no idea what
all that is.
So sure there's like an ifm a 52 and probably that has something to do
with fuse multiply add, but what does the rest of it mean and is it a
caps bit?
I don't know, right?
So that is the thing.
That's weird.
Not like what?
F ma or whatever, you know.
All of that said, a lot of these I don't even know what they might
mean.
Like, I don't know what a DQ would stand for either and so on, but
point being so I don't know.
Like, I don't know what any of this stuff actually means.
I don't know if like, you know, I don't know.
For example, if this is a caps but you would have to check on the
processor and then you know, if it had it then you could issue mad 52
high, right?
And if it didn't you couldn't or something because that's just crazy.
If that's true.
So I don't know what that means.
I hope that's not what that means.
That's what the
Studies mean, right?
Like, normally, if I click on sse3, this shows me the stuff that the
ss3 sse3 Caps bit would tell me if it had right and caps, that's not
really the right turn, but if I check the cpuid and I know it as a C3,
I can call these.
That's how that works, right?
But I just don't understand what this means because I don't know what
it means.
I so I gotta go read like the architecture reference man on find out
what all of this was meant since avx-512 isn't out yet.
I haven't bothered to research how that works.
But yeah it's just kind of
crazy is all.
Oh man and ESV says yeah, it looks like different caps B.
Oh,
I mean, just think it just just that's horrible.
Like why would you do that?
I mean basically at that point you're basically just saying I'm
targeting scientific Computing, right?
Because no one's going to ship a commercial product that actually uses
random combinations of these things and falls back to different paths
or something.
That'd be insane, right?
It's just too much.
So, that's just crazy.
I wish they wouldn't do that.
That's just not cool.
Oh, well,
Anyway.
All right.
Let's go ahead and wrap things up.
Casey is hungry and wants to eat dinner.
So let's go ahead and close this stuff down.
There we go.
Minimize you?
All right, thanks for joining me for another episode of handmade hero.
I hope you'll come back again tomorrow and I think I'm just going to
give you fair warning.
I think tomorrow may end up getting moved to 9:00 a.m.
I'm going to go look at it now and I may have to do that because
basically a, for those of you who know Jeff he is.
He is having two.
Well, I won't go into too much detail, but anyway,
For those of you know Jeff he is going to have to go have some some
surgery tomorrow and I wanted to go visit him tomorrow evening and the
stream would have overlapped when when that would have happened.
So I think I'm going to try and move the stream so that I can go.
Go to that.
And for those of you who know, Jeff please, please wish him well and
wish him a speedy recovery.
Not that you can't anymore because he's basically removed himself from
the internet.
But yeah.
Suffice to say, I'm going to move.
Probably move the stream for that.
So I apologize for the last-minute notice but it was kind of a
last-minute thing.
And so I will probably update the handmade hero schedule to, to move
it to 9 a.m.
tomorrow.
So we'll do 9 a.m.
both days, both Thursday and Friday.
So thanks everyone for joining me for handmade hero.
Hopefully, come back tomorrow.
Like I said, probably will be 9:00 a.m.
tomorrow even though originally, I said it was five.
I'm probably gonna have to move it.
So we'll do that.
And tomorrow.
What we'll do is we'll talk about Cindy, basically, how Cindy
instructions, work, how we write them, how we like that, the compiler
to like,
Pile them and do them, right?
We'll talk about how to how to make that happen and hopefully we'll
have some time tomorrow to actually start writing some of that we
probably won't finish Because by the time I explain how everything
works, we probably won't have enough time but between tomorrow and
Friday we probably should, I think be able to get a fairly reasonable
Cindy version of our thing in place so that we can take a look at
that?
And figure out how much how fast we think we should be able to get it
to run when we you know, at the limit, right?
And again I like I said that's a pretty important thing to want to do
because one of the problems with optimizing stuff is you kind of have
to go.
If you don't go through and count how many cycles you think something
going to run at Peak.
There's not a lot of ways to know how much performance you're losing
from other things.
That are that are that are interfering like cash dolls, you know, this
sort of thing.
And so that's
So what we're going to be doing.
So hopefully come back tomorrow.
9 a.m.
to join me for that until then if you do want to follow along at home
and you want to preorder the game on handmade hirota or you can do.
So, just go ahead and do that, you'll get a link that allows you to
download the source code so you can follow along.
We also have a forum site.
You can go to post questions and that sort of stuff.
It's also got ports to Mac and Linux if you're interested in that and
there's also anti depe sewed guide and other kinds of good resources.
There we have a patreon page rossport the video series if you'd like
to subscribe.
To that.
That's always very much appreciated and we also have a tweetbot the
Tweet the schedule you for exactly the kind of situation.
I was just talking about where if there's something like a medical
emergency or things like this and I have to move the stream and you
don't want to be sitting around going, where is handmade hero that is
the best place to get those updates because I try to keep the Twitter
stream Pretty up-to-date it as much as I can.
So that you always know what's going on with the stream and don't have
to wait for twitch to tell you that it's on or not.
So, check that out until tomorrow.
Everyone.
Please have a fabulous coding day and hopefully I'll see you back here
again.
Like I said probably 9 a.m., but check the Twitter I will post if
initally tonight.
Take it easy everyone.