Hello everyone and welcome to handmade hero.
The show we could complete game live on stream.
We have finished doing an update of our game to 3D there is one issue
that we have to address that people brought up who are ported to other
platforms.
One of the things that, of course, is true.
Now that we actually do use the 3D card if you have been following
along, we did an upgrade that allows us to use like a full 3d Pipeline
with Z buffer and everything instead of doing software rendering or
very light opengl
Like we were before I kind of decided to go a little bit more real 3D
with it, just felt like the right thing to do based on what I wanted
to have happening.
So we did that upgrade and it went actually very smoothly.
However one of the things that we did try to do last week was to
transition from any sort of Legacy opengl, which is what we had
written it in originally, just to show kind of the simple version.
We Now are up to sort of modern fairly modern usage of opengl where
we're using shaders, and all that sort of stuff.
So,
At this point, we turned off core compat like non-core compatibility
and we have the driver issue errors.
If it can any time that we do something that's outside of the core
profile.
Opengl opengl, of course, is a very old API and it's been updated many
many times.
And one of the things that they do during those updates is they allow
driver manufacturers to support any old versions of the API that they
want.
Now, they don't have to, but they can.
And so what happens with opengl when you open it is you're able to
specify to the driver whether you want the driver to give you access
to.
Legacy features or whether you would like it to give you errors when
you use them.
Now, the driver is under no obligation to actually support those
Legacy features, but a lot of drivers do support the Legacy features
which what that means is typically on opengl you can get away with
using some pretty old stuff, and the driver will just work.
Now, what we want to do is move away from all that, because it just
helps to turn on core compatibility to ensure that you're using only
the modern calls to the API.
Basically, just to reduce the amount of variability that you've got.
In terms of being able to port to different platforms, run on
different graphics cards.
If you've got a really wide support surface there, where you're
calling stuff from that was designed in 1995 and stuff that was
designed in 2014.
That's a pretty big spread for drivers to test and to get working at.
So you kind of want to stay pretty narrow and try to reduce your API
usage down to the things which are only absolutely necessary for you
to use.
And so, that's what we did.
Now, one of the downsides of that is, it does mean that any problems
on this graphic,
Scarred that don't get reported as errors because the AMD driver just
doesn't have a problem with them.
If they are not in the core profile, we may just not know, right?
Because we don't really have any good foolproof way.
There's no opengl lint program really that will go through and check
for those old calls or maybe there is an I don't know about it but
point being we don't have one at the moment.
So all we know is what the driver reports as errors but that doesn't
mean that some other driver that's more Vigilant or Vigilant about a
different set of things.
Couldn't report errors about things.
We're doing that aren't in the core profile but the AMD driver.
Just doesn't notice our in the core profile because no one had an
error checking for them in the AMD driver.
And so we do have one place that other folks when they're reporting to
other system.
Because we've got a bunch of people use the handmade here of code base
and they pour it to other things.
They ported to Linux support to Mac.
They do their own products on it, whatever.
So typically, I do get feedback from people when there is something
that another platform can catch either llvm compiler, catch.
Something.
And maybe it's not even an error could just be compatibility
difference, for example.
But, you know things that get caught from different compilers
different apis, different platforms, whatever one place.
We are still using something that I guess, got deprecated in the core
profile, and that is extension enumeration.
You're no longer supposed to do extension enumeration via the GL gets
drink, all your supposed to get an index extension string, and we can
take a look at that today.
So, I'd like to just do that really quickly before we
Started.
Mostly I'll just be blowing my nose all day, but in Between blowing my
nose, what I'd like to do.
Is fix that because that just helps people who are running handmade
hiroko.
Bases elsewhere to stay up to date and not have to worry too much.
So I'm going to go ahead and jump over there to the handmade hero
GitHub where we can take a look at that.
So here's our current handmade here at GitHub.
You can kind of see, we've got some stuff mentioned in here.
We've got this GL, get strange looks tensions fails with Jill and
valid in them.
That's the one that I'm talking about right here.
So I'm going to jump over here.
And you can see here, basically.
It's just the case that this, this is how we were checking for
extensions before and that check that you'll get string is just not
supported anymore.
And this is the explanation right here, actually.
These other folks who commented they are actually listing the correct
way to do it as well.
They basically just upgraded the API from returning, the extensions in
one big, huge Clump to being able to get individual Extensions by
asking how many extensions there.
And then asking for each extension in turn, right?
So it's pretty similar, there's not a lot of difference here.
Will be very easy for us to Port.
So I just like to support that because again, then these folks here,
who may be compiling on different platforms, won't have to worry about
this compatibility problem because I think right now, we're pretty
compact clean.
People can compile all over the place and we just work
It's worth keeping that going, you know, because it's not a whole lot
of work for us.
After we do that, the rest of the day we're going to spend looking at
additional features in the renderer that we're going to need just to
replace some features that we have and that we don't have any more
such as the alpha fading of things above the player or stuff like
that.
I want to go ahead and show you how to do some of those things.
Now that we're in a modern opengl context, and we already have
shaders, I'm just going to kind of give you some examples of how you
can leverage that.
Sort of Shader architecture to do some of the effects that we were
urging for, in perhaps different ways and, and things like this.
So, we'll just start playing with that.
And that this weekend will mostly be about how to do kind of special
effects if you will inside the shaders that are things that we might
want to do.
Before they seen, we've already done one of them, which is the
fudging, the Z value, so that we get different occlusion than you
would expect.
And so really what we're going to be doing is looking at some more
techniques that are similar to that.
Alright, so let's go ahead and today is day 374.
Let's go ahead and just quickly address that GL strings issue.
So that's again, just going to be something that happens in the
extension enumeration.
So if we take a look inside our open gel layer, we've got that GL, get
string call, that's the only place that we're going to be calling to
yell getstring.
You can kind of see it's this part where we just try to get some
information for the driver.
Now, as far as I know, there's nothing wrong with calling GL, get
string.
GL vendor Jill render and Jill version.
I don't think anyway and I didn't see anyone report that so I'm
assuming that that it's still the correct way to get those particular
things.
Oops, why did I delete that?
I'm meant to yeah.
There we go.
So I'm assuming, since you'll notice here, they're only talking about.
This particular, this particular way of calling Geo getstring, not GL,
get string as a whole.
So I'm assuming that all of these can actually stay, and it's really
just this.
That's the problem.
And what's going to happen here is basically, we were previously
parsing it into individual strings ourselves.
And so, what's now happening is, we should be able to just use GL, get
integer V.
And she'll get string I to basically get those out one by one.
So that we can actually not do the parsing anymore either, which is
presumably good.
So, you know, that's pretty much a win for us as far as I can tell.
Anyway, so it should be fine.
The only question is, which of those functions are supported and which
have to be queried.
So the problem I suppose, since we're always, since we're always
asking for a GL 3.0 context.
Now, I don't think we could really run without one we can
Probably remove anything that was previously sort of doing stuff that,
you know, was checking that we can.
Pretty much remove any paths that were necessary only on things that
were before opengl 3.0 X
Because we're just not going to probably be able to run on those
anymore, right?
Because any platform it's before up until three point x probably won't
have the Shader support that we need in order to run the game.
And so, we're just going to have to require an opengl three-point X
context or opengl ES.
I think that's 2.0, Maybe
I don't really know whether it's 2.0, 3.0 opengl es levels but, you
know, basically, you need to be sort of a, you know, at least a
10-year old Hardware.
You can't be 20 year old hardware and
This game anymore, which doesn't seem like a bad idea since nobody's
doing that.
So all right, if we come through here, you can see this result dot
extensions equals GL getstring extensions.
What we need to do is sort of stopped having this like that kind of
needs to go away, and I don't know if anyone was really looking at
that besides us, so I think it's fine.
So we can pretty much just not worry about that part anymore.
So what we really need to do here is get an extension count, right?
We need to find out how many extensions we actually have, and
Again, that was a GL, get integer V call, just a generic call to the
GL.
Like give me a number command and we're going to pass GL extension
count, I believe is what their, sorry not extensions, right.
And so we're going to need to find that because that's a new.
That's a new enum.
So we're gonna have to grab of your arm but we're using existing
function.
I don't believe you'll get integer, V has is anything we need to query
because that's a function that existed in corporate real.
It's just the enum, we're passing to it that has
Changed.
So in theory.
Oops, I accidentally hit the page up key in theory.
Now, we can just ask the extension count and then we can just go
through the extension index here.
Now, she'll get into Jervey, I think requires us to pass the pointer
where it's returned.
So although this would be handy, I think that's not actually the
phrasing of it.
It actually looks like this.
I believe,
And this is probably a CG CG lent or whatever, sorry IG L NT, and I
don't know, but we'll double-check in the docks.
So once we get that, we're going to have to iterate over it with the
extension index, we're going to have to go through all of the ones
that it says, that it has exactly as you would expect in our own code.
Nothing particularly weird going on here.
So there's, you know, the loop that we do and then in here, when we're
doing our strings are equal bit, and we're passing this, like count at
blah blah, blah, we don't really need to do.
That particular anymore because I think we just get the string now.
So let's take a look at get string I and just verify what?
Because that's a new call for us.
And we're plugging up to query it.
So we're going to have to look at the spec for that, but it
presumably, it's very straightforward.
Let's take a look.
So here it is, you can see, we passed the enum, which is the name and
the index which is which one of them we want.
And we could just switch to using this entirely as you can see.
So you know vendor renderer version shading language version.
We could we could ask for all of those injeel, getstring.
I and then 0 would presumably be what we would pass for all of those
and the the only one that would would do more of them would be, you
know, one, two, three, four in terms.
Of the extensions.
The rest of these are only one thing, right?
So here, we've got were expecting to get a string pointer back.
Right.
What's interesting about this is its passing back an unsigned byte,
which doesn't make a whole lot of sense to me to be honest.
Because I guess I don't know why you would necessarily can that.
That's not a care star, really?
Even though the secondly, is a care star, so I guess that's just maybe
to indicate that, it maybe could be utf-8 or something.
I don't really know.
They don't really say here as far as I can tell.
So yeah, I'm not sure.
But either way, it doesn't really matter.
As long as we can do something relatively reasonable here, we should
be okay.
All right, so we're doing our get strings here.
Don't look like they need to change our here.
We need our guests during I and that's going to
I have to take the string index and then it's going to have to take
this extensions, the specific extensions.
Why can I not know?
Doesn't matter.
I can just type it in.
So this will give me an extension and it'll numerator over each
extension, and we can just say extension name here is going to come
back to us.
We don't need any of this parsing now at so really all we have to do.
I don't know why we would need if 0 here because in theory, I guess
that was just the end of the parsing or something like this.
So all of this stuff can go away and pretty much all we need to do is.
Well, you know what, this, if zero was probably just so we could make
everything else if little bit
Clever than we probably need to be.
But anyway, Theory now we can just do this right in theory.
Now we can just do a regular string compare.
We don't need to count a string compare and we can look for our
extensions this way.
Now, I don't think either of these two.
Yeah, like I said, is defined.
So we need both of those, right?
And, you know, we could still preserve this path but don't really know
if we want to, but we could just say that you don't get any
extensions.
If those aren't if you're on an old platform.
So we could still do this, but it
Doesn't it's really kind of not necessary to do this to a certain
extent because the game wouldn't really be able to run on Hardware.
That was so old that it didn't support opengl 3 because that's just
really, really old at this point, right?
It's like a decade old or something like that.
So, you know, we'll put this in here nominally, but it doesn't really
need to be there.
And so then all we need to do is actually have that function.
So we're going to have to grab that again.
Out of the core are
So, we'll just go ahead and grab that.
Here's the, the H file GL, extensions is one of them and none.
Extensions is the other eye.
Although it didn't seem to complain about Jill and I'm extensions.
Did we put that one in here?
No, we didn't.
I don't know why it didn't complain about that.
Oops, I need the whole thing.
That's weird.
So it is numb extensions.
Never mind.
That makes perfect sense.
Because Jill extensions was still there, right?
I was like, what I was like, why is it on component wise?
Because extensions used to just get the whole thing.
So, it's all good.
All right.
So, Gom extensions is the only one we need there and then get string.
I
is the other piece of the puzzle.
So if I go ahead and grab that out, I can go ahead and put that in the
win32 side of things.
Here is all of the stuff that we've been adding and I'll go ahead and
add that here.
So, let's get rid of that.
We've got a concert glue B, an API, she'll get string, there it is.
I'm going to go ahead and add type to that and make it a typedef.
There we go.
And then again, same thing that we were doing before where we just do
opengl Global function.
She'll get string I and I probably should change all of these as well.
Like we probably should just go do that.
Just now that we have a way, a specific way that we're doing that.
Narf.
And so in theory now we're actually properly compiling with the the
right way of getting the extensions.
I don't know if that works or not cuz obviously all we did was kind of
throw it in there.
So I'm going to go ahead and step through it.
I want to watch and make sure that we're still checking for these
extensions correctly and there isn't something wonky going on.
All right, so that's not particularly helpful right there, right?
That didn't appear to work.
So why not?
So I guess the problem here is that we get the info before we may have
gotten GL get string.
So I think we probably need to reorganize the order in which we do
those probably need to make sure that these guys or at least the get
string.
One happens first.
All right.
There we go.
And so these will come back one at a time.
And you can kind of see them coming back here, right?
Each extension comes back one at a time.
Now, in theory, we should be able to get all of these I think.
And so I'm just going to double check that we actually do.
What's going on here?
Help.
Wow, slow morning, huh?
Gotta love that.
All right.
Anyway back to our show.
So after we get all this stuff out and we take a look at the result
here, we should see that we did get those extensions and we did, so
that's good.
I just want to make sure that we did because I know they should be
there and so I want to make sure that we were still getting the
strings back in a way that properly matched.
So that looks pretty good to me.
So we'll consider that resolved at the moment we can sort of Punt it
back to the folks who are testing on the other platforms and
If it works, and just let him know.
So this should be fixed as of day 374.
Please let me know if it isn't
So hopefully that that should basically just comply with the way that
they need it to happen on their platforms, and that's more compliant
for us as well.
Not that it matters on this particular machine but it would matter on
other machines, potentially that we're using different drivers.
So hopefully that's all good to go.
All right, so that brings us back to where we were before.
So here is our current state of the rendering and you can see that
everything is
Working pretty nicely.
This is what we expect the game screen to look like roughly and again,
we don't have the art in there yet, so we're going to put in the art,
probably in a week or two, we'll put that in.
Once we've sort of got the rest of running stuff, done all of this
looks right, the Sprites are standing up properly, or Alpha levels are
not as good as they could, because we're just, we're only using outfit
of coverage right now.
And we're not using second a secondary pass for things.
Like Shadows, we could if we could do that and we may want to
And so we need to think about that.
As a possible thing to do, will talk about that in a second.
Also, I think we have some work to do on this stuff.
Just cleaning up the way that the clipping, like, I think the clipping
regions aren't working at the moment, right?
Yeah, you can see here like this is still broken.
So we need to make sure our clipping regions are transforming properly
at the moment.
They definitely aren't doing that.
So that's some stuff that we have to do there.
And and finally, we've got to read redo sort of those Graphics
effects.
So we've got a
No, bunch of things to just to finish up, the rendering, pour it.
Now that all the renderings working properly, we still have more
things.
We might want to do,
To get ourselves back to the feature, parity that we should be at
compared to the old way of doing things and just with a bunch more
goodness, like, now we've got a z-buffer to play with and a lot of
other things that might be nice.
Okay, I really want Medical Science to come up with a way of stopping,
like allergies will be so nice.
I know they're working on it.
But I also know they haven't quite gotten there yet.
All right.
So the first thing that we need to do before we talk about any of this
is we just need to put ourselves in a position where we see the
problems that I'm talking about.
Now obviously we could go work on the debug system but I'm kind of
more interested right today in terms of looking at some of those
Shader things.
So it's want to do that first and then we'll look at the debug clean
up the debug tomorrow.
Perhaps
Now, assuming you finish this stuff.
So what I want to do here is when we're building our sort of little
bogus test World here, just that we've been using to play around with,
you know, we've got this sort of thing where we're doing rooms and we
right now we're just, we're not doing any rooms that are stacked on
top of each other.
And what I want to do is today is look at rooms that are stacked on
So I want to switch this.
Room generation over to actually do exactly that.
So, in cure, right, where we've kind of got this thing, where we've
got our door Direction, I want to just make it.
So the door direction is like always going to be up, right?
So basically, there's always going to be rooms essentially above, and
below us.
I think is what I try to do anyway, although that doesn't really look
quite right because although those two rooms are on top,
Of each other.
It looks like it's still doing rooms to the side so maybe that's not
quite enough.
Whoops, what did I do?
Oh, it was only doing two.
That's that's random Choice.
That's not what we want at all.
I want door Direction.
It goes.
This is the one I actually wanted.
That was my bad there.
Sorry about that.
All right.
So now in theory, I don't actually know if this is true or not.
Like I was saying, let me see.
I always forget how to use this.
How do I zoom?
I'm going to remember how to zoom.
What's going on here?
What is going on here?
I forget what I buy on to the stuff that we were using to.
I know it rotate is but I never remember what Zoom is what is zoom
know.
Okay so it's Alton middle Mouse button is supposed to do.
All right?
There we go.
All right.
So that's not actually zooming.
So we've got some n plus, there's something weird going on here.
Yeah.
So our Zoom does not seem to be working, but I don't actually know
why, and we're kind of in the middle.
Exactly what's going on here.
This is a bit wonky.
So I think we've got some problems with our debug camera placement.
This does not look in case case anyone was unclear on that that does
not look at all like a proper place to put this so I want to make sure
that I want to see what's going on there.
I don't really know what's going on there.
So we'll take a look.
Alright so here we go with our door Direction being three I guess
during up or down know exactly what this.
We probably at some point need to actually make this this test World
code start to build out real world code because it just takes a while
to deal with the sort of how ridiculously hacky this test World
creation stuff.
Was it was always just there so we'd have something to work with but
we kind of always need to actually have some there.
It's difficult to plunge it into the way that I needed to work for any
given time.
What I'm going to do here just to get started is I'm going to make it
so that it only generates one
and I want to see what's going on.
So, there's generating just a single room, right?
And so we're getting some weirdness here, right?
Like, I don't know what's going on there.
Like, we're getting some weird.
It feels like the world's toughest game generated, like when I right
click to switch to debug mode, I'm getting an error on that.
So I think we just still have some problems with what is considered
our, our
Like where where our world region is actually doing its thing.
I think we still got some some problems in their like it.
That's as soon as I switch the debug camera and you know the debug
camera really shouldn't have much to do with it but if you remember
it's still kind of does because we use a camera projected place for
where we're doing our world simulation which is probably not
particularly right anymore especially when you consider that, we have
debug camera and stuff like that in
Are we probably need something a little more.
Robust for a couple reasons.
One is that right now.
When we do, I think we do up when we do an update and render world, I
think we do a nun project actually.
So you can see, we do get camera Target with the render group.
I think that just goes through, whatever.
The last project value was, which means that we that the debug camera
would affect where you were simulating, which we don't actually want.
We want that to always be from the real camera, right?
So, there's some
Wonkiness there that we need to address.
And so probably that has to get fixed as well at the moment.
That definitely seems a bit weird.
I want to see what we're getting for, the re canonicalize coordinates
situation here, I want to see what's getting past what's the uh, okay.
So this is just a completely invalid offset thing that's coming
through here, so that's obviously wrong.
And again, I think that's because our unprojected call is not quite
correct yet or we are passing the, unprojected call something that
can't really work properly.
So if we take a look at the world.
Yes.
So there's the world camera wrecked coming back during debug and you
can see that that's just not.
Yeah, even remotely reasonable.
Let's just double check.
What's going on there?
It may be that that's what should happen because maybe the debug
camera is messed up or something like this, but it might also just be
that this code is,
Is bombed.
All right.
So yeah, this is nuts.
I don't know why.
This is e is passing an 8 here.
That's some hard coded nonsense from the old days, so we probably want
to just clean that out.
Let's go ahead and take a look at what's going on in here but World
distance from camera being eight, who knows why that was the case.
And you can see here that's going to pass that in.
So let's just see what happens.
We're passing in this
this to the unprotect.
To.
So there we go clip.
See the probe ZW came out as actually exactly zero.
So that's a problem, right?
The probe's, ew, in this case literally coming out to exactly zero.
I guess that's because 8 is right on, like, where the camera is or
something that, but that doesn't make any sense.
That shouldn't be true.
I don't know exactly how that would be possible.
because if this is something that's supposed to go,
oh, you know what, though?
Yeah, see this is just kind of broken, so we forgot to do when we did
our own project, this world distance from cameras, e actually needs to
be if we're going through the full projection here, this forward
projection, this actually needs to correlate to that in a real way.
Meaning the it can't be affected by the position of the camera and
it's got to be a long, the cameras z-axis, right?
Otherwise, this isn't going to work.
So actually, this this code is
Not correct.
First of all it isn't a positional coordinate.
So this this has to be 0, right?
In order to not take up the position part.
And second, this has to actually Point down the Z axis.
If it doesn't Point down the Z axis, if the Z axis is pointing in a
different direction that it's not going to work so that was just kind
of sloppy on my part and and that's something we're going to have to
fix.
This is not super related to the problem you're seeing before.
This is just again, we just finished all
This code and we have not had a chance to really do bug and test a lot
of it yet.
So you know there's going to be some growing pains in here.
All right, so first of all, what I'm trying to do here is I'm trying
to get a z-value to figure out where in clip space.
This far away from the camera in World distance we would be and so I'm
passing that in and doing a forward transform on it.
The thing is right here.
What I need to know is I need to know what this would be, if it were
that far along the negative Z axis, I guess, in this case, right?
So I need to get that negative Z axis out of the camera transform and
furthermore, I don't want to be positional.
So one of the things you remember about homogeneous coordinates x y z
w.
The one here is what allows it to pick up the position.
If I set this to 0, it will not pick up the position, right?
Because all that W being one is what multiplied
Each element in the Matrix.
That was a positional element in the matrix by setting it to 0.
I will force it to be always relative to the cameras location which is
what I want in this case, right?
Because it's never going to move.
Just to underscore what that is for.
At work may be coming to these things, who aren't super familiar with
them if I just draw it out really quickly.
What happens in Matrix land
We have the upper 3x3.
That's the rotational components, right?
The X y&z axes and then we have the position here and then a0001 the
bottom, right?
This is what the camera transform currently looks like.
And again, these are inverted since the camera transform.
So, the x is here, the Y is here, and the Z is here.
There there Rose, not columns, because the camera transform.
And this position is the inverse position X.
The are remember, this is the camera version.
So instead of just being the location of the camera, it's actually the
- rotated position of the camera and that was because that's what
needs to happen in this Matrix in order to Center things around the
camera after they've been rotated by R, which is how they will come
through right?
And we're multiplying by an XYZ, usually a one here, right?
That's going to multiply this P because remember, the X y&z
Are multiplying these in here, right?
Because the X multiplies these positions, the why multiplies these
Physicians and the Z multiplies, these positions.
But that one multiplies these, right?
And so if we change that to a zero, this is now a relevant.
It does not matter what's in there and that's what I want in this
case, right?
So I want there to be a zero there because the don't want it to have
any effect.
So the other thing I need to do is I need to get the Z axis and so in
order to get the z-axis out of here, I need to extract that camera Z.
Now remember the cameras he's in the wrong place, compared to an auto
transform, normally it would be the columns, right?
Column X column, y column, Z for the axes of the camera.
This is a camera transform.
So it's meant to invert the placement of the camera.
So the cameras Z axis is actually going to be the row here.
It's going to be easy.
And again I want to get that out.
So, if I take a look at my master teens, I don't know that we have a
get column getro call, we might looks like we do.
And so, all I want to do here is I want to get that row out so I can
use that row as the displacement that I'm using for my world distance
from camera.
See now that get roll call is going to want to get nothing zero.
It's not the first but the second row, right?
The two row to, it's a third row and I want to get that out of the
camera, transform Matrix.
So if I go through last frauds,
Word.
That's where that's going to come from, right?
So, once I get that out now, I'm good to go but the problem is we have
to think about the directionality here.
Now, remember our camera is z pointing backwards so if I was to do it.
Exactly like this, we would be the world distance from camera Z behind
the camera.
So I want to be in front of the camera because remember, the Z axis is
pointed back towards the viewer and I want to go away from the viewer,
so that's going to have to look like this.
Now, let's take
Look at loops.
There we go.
In this case, right?
I'm going to have to change the doing this because since we're now
moving in a real direction, we're not just x 0.
Y, 0 Z, is some value.
We're now an actual Vector.
We're along whatever this direction is, right.
So I have to initialize myself with a vector3 and then the 0 for the
last Gordon.
Okay?
So now I'm expecting, although I don't actually know, hold on a
second.
Now I'm expecting when we come through here to get a more reasonable
result here.
This I still think we need to get rid of because we need to actually
know how far away our Target is.
That's a separate situation.
So we'll take a look at that in a minute but just for the time being
let's assume 8 is always a reasonable value to pass because it should
be eight away from the camera.
We should not get an invalid result from this at all.
So let's just make sure that we're on the right track there.
So here's our probe Z.
Now let's take a look at what the probes he ends up being.
It should be a
Killer Vector.
Now again, the camera is actually pointed directly down, so it
actually is the correct Z here now, so that's actually fine.
But with this zero in here, now we're going to get a real value.
So we won't have as equal zero and our probes eval.
You should now have a w coordinate.
That is reasonable and it does.
Like you can see that right there.
And so let's take a look at our clip.
See our clip C is one that's
Still weird to me.
That feels like I still have some bug in here.
The reason that I think I still have some bug in here is just because
a clip sea of one would be right at the near clipping plane, right?
I'm sorry right at the far clipping plane, which doesn't make any
sense here to me, really.
So I think we're still a little bit wrong headed in our thinking,
that's just my assumption here.
I don't actually know that.
That's true but that's seem
Is like it to me, right?
And I'm not sure exactly why that would have been the case either,
because that seems like a weird clip.
See to have in this case,
I'm going to step through this a little bit more but I felt still
feels a little wonky to me.
I'm not super comfortable with that at all.
You can see that we are getting a result out of here.
So it's not it's not it's not mathematically degenerate like it was
before but I still don't think that's correct because the clip.
See value should have been something more reasonable.
It should have been something more like in the range between negative
1 and 1.
It should not have been at the extreme mm because this is a very
reasonable value of Z to be placing.
That should just be like in the milk toast region,
Of the clip space.
And so I feel like there's still a little bit, something wrong there.
We're
Broken like we were before.
So that's a plus, but we're not right.
And so you can see.
Now, at least we're not getting any of that crashing Behavior, but
it's definitely not.
That's definitely not what what we want to see.
So let's just let's just take a little bit more time to kind of get in
there because again this is exactly what we want to be doing right
now.
We don't want to let go further down the the path of working with
these things before.
We've got them a little bit more under control.
So, I want to take a look at what's going on here with that and why
that's happening.
So, let's think this through a little bit.
I want to take a look at what our probe Z value is.
And what our camera is supposedly.
So if you take a look at what we've got for our camera location,
Okay.
I think II.
Maybe Miss Miss thought that.
So, since I am in verse transforming this, the Z values that come
through here
As I do the forward, transform on them, I do want to place them.
Back into the camera space on the way back out.
No, but I think that should still be zero going through it.
Well, anyway, I'm going to step through this a little more carefully.
Hold on a second because I'm just not sure.
And I want to look at the values and actually work them through
properly to make sure I'm not missing.
Because again once you get to this point, there's just a lot of math
involved in the transforms for its it backwards and you want to make
sure that you're not
Doing anything stupid, right?
Alright, so here is the probe Z value actually, I guess I don't need
to expand its right here and so that probe Z value is an 8, which
means that the world distance from cameras e, I'm guessing that the
where's our transform here?
So the camera Z being - on why slightly?
It's this is this right?
I feel like there should be, no, I feel like it should be pointed
directly down but maybe that's not the case.
Like shouldn't this Z be directly down.
I don't know why it's rotated at all.
That's a little bit weird to me.
But you know, that's fine that it's slightly down.
So the Z coordinate coming up.
Meaning in the One Direction.
Is pointing back towards the viewer in theory, right?
So, our probe Z value of 8 is actually seems to me to be
Going in the wrong direction.
Right.
It should have been world is to commemorate this - here, why, why was
it should have been picking up this camera Z value.
So I don't quite understand what happened there.
I want to verify in fact, I guess, I don't because we have the camera
access already.
I guess.
I don't need to do it this way.
I guess the problem is this already has the projection baked into it
so I guess I don't want to get it out of this Matrix so I suppose I
want to just use the group z-axis is part of the problem, right?
I'm going to go ahead and get that row so I can look at it but that
row has built into it.
Yeah.
Okay, so that was dumb, that's the problem right there.
Well that's one of the problems right there.
So getting the row I was thinking this is the camera Matrix but it's
not last project actually or
He combined, it's the camera Matrix plus the projection Matrix, and I
only wanted the camera Z.
So what I really want is that because the other one is not the Z axis
of the camera anymore, right?
The last present, that's why we saved this value was for this exact
kind of thing, all right, so that is more correct, probe Z.
And that's what I expect to see.
I wanted that value to appear - because that's what it should have
been.
And I was upset that it was positive.
So that's why I was looking a little more deeply.
If that, you can saw that, I was uneasy about it.
That was making me concerned because I'm like, my intuition tells me
that this should be positive because I mean, because you me - because
again, pause is coming at the viewer.
Why is it - something's wrong or I'm misunderstanding the math and
something was wrong.
We were looking at the wrong, we were getting the wrong value for the
cameras, e.
Now that that's correct.
Let's take a look at the other parts here and see how they go.
So let's see what our Clips is.
So our clip C is still busted.
So I'm still not quite there yet, right?
I don't quite understand how we could get the same clip see in either
case I guess that's because the W coordinate coming out of there.
So I guess one of the problems that we do have here and this is me, I
guess just continuing to have to make life a little more difficult
myself.
Now that I think about to the problem is we won't get any Z
displacement either.
If I set this to 0.
So that means right because if you take a look at how we're doing the
projection, right?
what's actually happening in the combined Matrix is, you know,
Got some XY modification up here.
It doesn't matter what these are, actually, we don't care about these
right now, but in our zero, right?
We've got some stuff.
We're right here and right here are two values which are both
controlling the Z range.
And of course this one is dependent on W being one coming in from the
top, right?
Because it's going to multiply that Z offset.
So our equation for Z was a find, right?
It requires you know, something time
I'm Z plus d, right?
Because there's a c into D here and so I can't set this to zero and
still get a transform that produces the correct Z range, which is the
whole point of this exercise.
So it does look like I need to actually go the whole nine here which
actually isn't that bad?
I just set this to 1 to do a full transform and then all I have to do
is actually just start at the cameras position and move by the Z axis,
right?
That does put me in the right place relative to the camera.
So, I suppose, that is the more full way to do it and I think now,
hopefully I get it yet.
There we go.
I got a better clip.
See that's actually than range now that clip.
See still seems weird to me that clip.
See seems way too high.
And so, I'm still not sure that I'm doing this correctly and I want to
keep doing, you can see how many small bugs I had in here, just from
looking at this.
So, if I start at the cameras location and I move by the by this many
units, along the cameras.
Yeah.
So again, I'm going opposite because I want to get away from the
camera.
I would expect this now to transform to a relatively small clip C
value.
I would not expect it to be high like that.
I've expected to be close to the middle of the range or actually
probably even close to the negative side of the range because we're
just not very far from the camera.
It is not very far compared to the far clipping plane.
So I wouldn't expect it to be bunched up like that the fact that it is
bunched up like that suggests to me that I still got a problem, right?
Or that I'm thinking
Who this situation in an incorrectly, right?
So I'm not sure.
I'm not sure why that would be the case, because this should be
something close to the camera.
It should be eight away from the camera, like, literally just move it
away from the camera, but that doesn't appear to be.
What's happening with the clip.
See now I'm going to kind of go through here and just see what we end
up getting for results.
Because I'm not sure what we would end up getting here.
Let's see.
One, those are pretty reasonable things to come out with in this
particular case.
So it gets, it isn't quite that weird but it's just
It's just not exactly what I would expect.
Hmm.
I feel like this is one where I want to actually work.
The math out directly and see what happens.
Because I want to understand why I'm not getting that Z value that's
more in that range.
And that just makes me think that something's bested here, right?
Because that just doesn't seem like a reasonable Z range value.
So I would have expected this value, this probes, easy.
I would have expected that to come out differently.
I'm also kind of interested can I come through here?
I want to see what's going on here.
Hmm, so we're calling this function right?
And so you can CR Z + RW, sort of operations coming through here, they
look pretty straightforward, so I can't say that anything looks
particularly odd here, we've got PX X AE 0, 0, py x, AE 0, 1.
So we're kind of going along the rows which is exactly what we would
expect to see.
Do the next one.
Where one row down, down down.
That all looks totally right to me.
So I don't know.
I do not understand why that's why that's doing what it's doing.
What was what was going on there?
Hold on one test.
A hot second.
Okay, for some reason, it looked like the p-value was all zeros there.
I guess I was just cuz I'd stepped out or something.
We come through there again.
so, here's that probe Z
Interesting.
So it's x y z 1.
So, this is literally at the origin here, right?
Is what we're actually projecting from, and that's in World space.
So the camera P must be exactly eight away.
Yeah, it is, which is funny.
I guess that's why we were passing that hard-coded eight there.
So we're exactly at the Target location, right?
So passing
One down.
Okay, that's fair.
But again like if we just look at where the camera located, where the
camera position is here.
It just does not seem saying to me, that we're getting that result at
now.
Let's take a look at what we're what we have here.
All those values look really, this just looks really suspicious.
Because I thought our far clip plane was like 1,000.
Right.
All right, we're good.
Let's investigate.
I am, I am just a confused individual at this point.
I want to go take a look at at what's going on here when we actually
build our perspective, projection Matrix?
All right, so let's take a look.
Here we are in the set, Cameron, transform call.
And we're going to come through here and build our perspective,
projection Matrix.
Here we go.
And so you can see here.
Here's our supposed near and far clipping planes, right?
It's a hundred and 0.1 and so those are the the to, you know, nominal
clip planes.
We just kind of hard coding here because we don't actually have any
code right now that tries to set those.
We don't deal with nearing forklift, planes, hardly at all.
So what are our DNA values?
Write negative 1 and negative.
Point two are the two values that we're getting here and we're sort of
placing them in here.
In here.
Okay.
So let me think that through does that make good sense to me.
And we actually do our tests here.
So we took a look to see whether or not the near and far clipping
planes when pushed through here, produced values that we thought were
correct.
And let's see.
So in our test 0 case, we get a negative point one which is I guess
what we would expect to see their right and
I should think about what we expect to see there first and we get a z
equals 100 there
Well actually, these are not very good test.
These have to do their divided so let's go ahead and actually make
them do that.
Mr.
Matthew poo.
There we go.
So we really want in this case when we do this transform right.
What I really want to do is I want to do a full transform here.
Yeah and then so that when we get the result out we can do the divide
and see what we actually get.
But this is what we actually want to do, right?
so in this case, or I guess I could this way another, we have a
divided equals
There we go.
Do we do?
Can we do this?
Yes, we can.
okay, so in this case, we could now actually get
the test code to do what I wanted it to do, which is let's go through
here and see, which is, it should give us the actual
Like the actual values divided by W, right?
And these should transfer these should both go.
And after the divided they should both be equal to the near and far
clipping planes.
Right?
When we pass it in here at, they should be equal to negative 1 and 1
respectively.
Right?
Is what these are supposed to map to.
So, let's see.
So this Z Maps, the negative 1, which is exactly what I wanted it to
do.
And this one should map to one which is exactly what I wanted to do.
So it looks like we're okay here, let me just run the program a little
bit more switch to the debug camera.
And now go ahead and double-check that.
so here we are again, just again, looking at these tests XYZ, that map
Z 2 - 1
That map c21.
All right so these are correct at least in terms of verifying that
when you push the things through, that should be at the near and far
clipping planes.
At least I believe.
Things that are at the near and far clipping planes.
You get the right results out.
Although there's no positional elements here us.
So, I think, I feel like we can sort of Fairly safely say that this is
properly doing the the Z distance, right?
So nothing unusual is happening here, it's all correct.
Okay.
So now, the question is, why are we getting weird results or at least
it is
It's just me thinking they're weird results but they're not actually
results.
Why are we getting weird results in the case where
We're trying to do the reverse projection actually verify that the two
versions are corrected.
This although I think that's not what we're looking at right now.
So it doesn't matter.
But yeah, these are all the identities.
So that's good too.
So that's yeah, this is all pretty good.
So this is the other thing here.
So these also only happen.
Yeah.
So
So this is the part I was talking about before I so we probably want
to clean this up before we follow the debugging anymore as well.
So again when we're using the debug camera, we don't update these and
the reason we don't update these is because anyone who uses those
right?
Forerun projection.
Want, you know, that's how we were doing like our Sprites and stuff.
We want those Sprites to keep doing their projections as if they're
from the camera, wherever the camera was right.
What that means is our unprojected call which is also should be going
from you know, should also be the going from the actual camera
location.
Because again, all the simulation stuff should all be going from that
camera location is
We're going to use that.
What that means is that when it does the unprojected those on
projection come from, not from the debug, right?
Not from the debug camera.
So when I come down cure for last project, what I really need to do is
that, you know, we probably want to make these really explicit.
This is game camera.
P game camera ex-gay.
A wild game crazy game.
Last project.
What I think we want to do is store both of those, right?
We want to have like
Something like the render transform, I don't know.
We've got too many of these at this point, but we could clean those up
as I kind of want to store these and say, look here is the stuff.
This is the P, the X, the Y, the Z, and the projection for these guys.
And we want two of them.
We want the game version and the debug version.
And we want everyone who uses
Them to be knowing which one they're picking.
So that you don't get in this situation where you're using half of one
half the other, which is sort of what would have happened in that
previous case.
It's not good, right?
So, in all these cases, where we're pushing bitmaps and stuff like
this, all of this stuff wants to go through the game's version, right?
So in all these cases we want like what did I call it?
Guess we want.
Maybe game transform and debug transform something like that.
Right.
So we want something more like this.
And then in the unprojected, what we probably want to do here is we
probably want to specify which one of those were using.
So if you take a look at the group, you can see that what we're doing
from this.
Up here is we're getting sort of like in these cases we're getting the
camera, fresh out of it.
What we could do is when we do our unprojected, we could say, well,
you know, pass us.
You can pass the object transform.
Also pass surpassed us the render transform
Right.
So whatever the render transform is that you want to use and that way
we can sort of say, well, okay, now you can own project from either.
So if you're trying to do something like debug picking of an element,
you can bet you can ask the unprojected to unprotect from the debug
camera which is when you're looking through.
But if you're doing something where it's supposed to be like, World,
simulation, you're trying to figure out what region the camera can see
that should still be going from the game camera.
And that way you can do either or
Right, so let's just go ahead and do it that way.
I think that's a senior way to do this.
At least.
It seems like it to me.
Right.
So now we get down here to the unprojected call, and in this case, we
know, for, from this one, anyway, that we're pretty much always going
to use the Game X form.
I don't know why that.
Yeah, that wouldn't really need this part of it at all.
And so I feel like maybe this the object transform part.
Should be pulled out of here to the person who's actually using that.
So, this should probably be this, right?
And this should always just return the world's p.
And then this object transform is just an additional piece that if you
want to do that, you could.
So I don't know where, who was on projecting with that transform?
Let's just find them looks like nobody in the interior was doing that,
right?
And so maybe then what we could do is just say like we'll deal with
this in a second when we find out who is actually using that, okay?
So let's see.
This goes away and we don't need that.
And then in here, when we're actually storing all this stuff and we
storing like the projects last project, that sort of thing in push set
up, I guess what?
I'm not sure is
When we do push setup.
Why are these getting done in two different places?
Cuz last project and the camera XYZ kind of want to get updated
together, right?
So feel like this wants to be structured a little bit better.
Let's ignore that for just one second and I'm going to come back to
that in a second here.
So right?
So this is all we don't really want to do with that the moment.
Okay?
So here we go, let's take a look at this.
Unprojected also cures.
This one is really not right anyway so I'm not sure how much we care
about this stuff at all because this we have to do as a raycast.
Now if we wanted to actually do that mass picking, so I would just say
this at the moment is
Not going to happen.
So we don't care about that because we need we need to get it, use a
different path entirely for that.
And so the only person we really care about is the debug people.
They were passing default flat transform.
Anyway, so that's fine.
So what we could do here is say that these guys are just going to use
the, the Game X form because they don't have a debug transform, really
the debug you.
I always has just the main transform, it doesn't really have the
concept of a separate debug View at all.
All right.
So finally, let's see that's news take one of these.
So really, I just now need to clamp, this push setup stuff a little
bit so you can see what happens here.
When we do a push cliprect any of these guys, they all do set up
pushes and so I feel like what we really want to do there, I don't
really know.
I mean, just looking at this, right?
And I look at the prod situation, you can see that the rectangle
itself needs to get that information.
I feel like, what really what I want to do is back this out a little
bit and say, okay, we're not going to store that in last project,
because that's not really, the person who knows what should be
happening here.
Because whether or not it goes into the debug or the regular version
Is going to be the determiner of and that's only known a little bit
further outside and nobody is going to.
Yeah.
So
I guess we need to know that because we need to push on.
Whichever one is actually appropriate here, but I guess the thing is
this inverse.
Projection situation is not really what we want to store.
I guess because no one should really be looking at that one in terms
of when they're actually using stuff.
So people need to store that ahead of time.
So what we really want to do here is just pass the M4 by for that
wants to get stored, and we can still make that be last fraud, which
will just be used sort of this way.
Right.
And in here, I can put an M40 for last project soon as I'm done with
that and we can talk about how that works in a second.
So, what I do is push cliff.
Correct.
Again, all that wants to do is modify the clip rect.
So again that can just pass, whatever the last projection was that's
sufficient, because it's not trying to change anything.
And so then really the set camera Transformers where things need to
get a bit Saucy.
So what we want to do here is I want to actually build now a render
transform
And I want to build this to have all the information in it.
So X formed up.
Raj is actually the thing that we would be sending down as the
projection Matrix here although actually not quite right.
It's actually when we do the composite version, it's this guy right
here.
So we're really going to do like X formed up Raj.
like so, and now we get all the information there we can also verify
The way we were doing when we do our push setup.
Again, we're just doing our xform about proj.
And render the forward version.
And if we look at what happens here, really I probably want to just
write this directly into the place that's going to go.
So probably what I want to do is say well is it a debugger?
Isn't it a debug right?
If it's a debug than what I want to do is I want to overwrite the
debug X form.
And if it's not, then I want to overwrite the games transform.
Oops.
Right?
And then when I write into this, I'm just saying like, oh okay, I'm
always going to write into something.
So all of this stuff is always going to get written into
It's just a question of which one I'm writing into and now I save them
all.
I always save both of them so you can choose which one you're going to
use depending on on the circumstances.
Right?
So that feels a lot better to me because now we're storing both paths
which ever one you updated you store which feels a lot better, right?
There we go.
And so then we still want that last project because again, that's just
what the renderer is going to use.
So when we're pushing clip, Rex and stuff like that on, we always want
those to be whatever the renderer is going to use.
So we still want to save that last project as a separate thing but
it's not actually used for anything other than than the cliprect stuff
anymore.
All right, so I think that's all good.
What's going on here?
I'm not sure.
So okay this is just that
So we got last project last fraud, push set up, less proj press setup.
Okay, so now I'm comfortable with that.
I can just now say that we do have oops.
That we do actually have a last brought here.
And so now in theory, okay, and you can see we've already fixed one of
the bugs we had, which is that this rectangle projection was changing
with the debug camera, which we didn't want.
And so now that's stable again, right?
Because it's always going through the game transform.
So that's good as well.
And so that's just a little bit cleaner and that's all good.
Now again we've kind of got a stack of bugs or working through here
now.
So let's get back to what we're doing originally now that I know we're
going through the correct stuff, I want to go back to taking a look at
the sun projectile, which I still think is is busted.
So I want to take a closer look at it.
Here we go.
And so now, I just want to see what the transform looks like that
we're starting with.
So, let's clear out a watch window and take a look.
So, here's a transform that we're starting with.
I want to take a look at the render group as well, and looking at the
render group here.
I just want to see what the differences between these two.
So here's that debug transform, right?
And so you can see this is not being transformed.
The sun project is not transforming through the debug transform at
all.
And that's great.
Because
This is the thing that gets the simulation rectangle, so it should not
be right.
And this is why you notice that, the reason that I went down that
little bug fixing tangent was just because I noticed that it was a
tilted camera and I was like the debug transform when I first switch
into the debug view is directly down.
So I was like expecting to see an identity in the upper 3x3 kind of a
situation which is exactly what I see.
Now the X y&z axes.
These are 111 exactly what I would expect.
These are not what I would have expected.
And so I just wanted to make sure that I was, you know, apples to
oranges apples and apples and oranges and delicious tasting oranges
and all those sorts of things.
Anyway, so when I come through the sun project now, we are doing the
regular game camera, transform though, and we're not mixing and
matching which is also good.
So let's take a look though at the rest of this and see what's going
on.
Because I like I said, I think it's still probably Incorrect and the
reason that I think it's incorrect as I just don't love that value, it
doesn't make it
Lot of sense to me why we were getting getting a value.
That's such a high value in clip coordinates, what I'm worried about
and maybe
Basically, the thing that concerns me here is that it feels like
that's that would be a correct value if it was negative, right?
Z the I believe the Z buffer is supposed to get larger as it gets
further away.
I mean supposed to is not really mean anything because there is no
definition of what Z buffer values have to be.
It's just they have to get map between negative 1 and 1.
Somehow, if you want to use a fixed Point Z buffer, which is what
we're using at the moment.
So they have to get map between negative and 1 and 1, but the how they
arrange themselves in that space is entirely
early up to you.
It's whatever we put in the projection Matrix for computing.
The Z value is how they'll come out, but
We have a certain comparison function that we're using for the depth
buffer and I thought that the comparison were using is that the Z
buffer is should be less.
They should be getting less and less as they get close to you, more
and more as they get further away.
So negative one, I thought was was right at the, the near clipping.
Now, what I want to do now is verify that the actually true.
Maybe that's not how it ended up, what, how we ended up mapping it and
I'm totally wrong, but I just want to verify, you know, these
Assumptions.
Because again,
there's so much involved in a 3D pipeline, it's easy to lose track of
values here and there and if you don't at any point, take a look and
actually test some things and verify that you got stuff, right?
It's easy to have crazy bugs in there.
Dickon stay a long time and you're just happened to be passing the
right values around that, make it so it doesn't actually become a
problem, but we'll see.
So yet, I mean, here you go.
You can see the depth of
And for passing is less than or equal to, and I believe that's the
pass function and we can again will double check that with
documentation.
But what that would mean assuming that I'm not mistaken is less than
or equal.
To, in this case means you will draw if the Z value is less than or
equal to the value that's currently in the depth buffer.
What that means is that the near clip lame should be negative 1,
right?
It should be the lowest possible value coming in there again unless I
misunderstood misunderstanding those
Values and they get flipped around by opengl or something like this
but you know, assuming that's not true.
So I want to figure out what's going on there because it's should not
that.
That is not what I want to see happening.
Right.
Okay so we got to figure out why we're getting those results.
I feel like right what we should be seeing is that if we start at the
camera P, which is what we've got here.
And we walk backwards along the z-axis by World distance from camera,
if World distance from camera.
In fact, we can do this test.
Exactly if World distance from camera was exactly zero or
Exactly the near clipping plane value.
What we should see is after the transform, we should get
We should get.
Literally, the near clipping plane out.
We should get negative 1 out and if we walk the far clip playing
distance away, we should get the other value.
So, let's just put those values in as test to see what it is that we
do, get because that's just a good example of, like, us figure out a
way to probe this, right?
So, what I can do here is just say like, oh, all right, you know, when
we do this on Project, let me just force it to call this in some
circumstance here, that's going to be handy for me.
So, if I come through in World mode, where we're doing these
unprojected calls, where we do get camera acting a Target right before
that, let me just call it with exactly.
The values that I want here.
Now I guess pixels x.
Why we don't care what it is.
Really it shouldn't be relevant because we're looking at only that
first part where pixels x why isn't there?
So I'll just, you know, pass zero down and that should be fine in the
render group.
We know what that is, right?
It's just we've got that pass in to us.
And so I'm going to take a look at doing the render group.
Let's first, let's, let's look at the debug transform first, I guess,
because that's the easiest one to deal with without being saucy.
I'm just going to pass as the world distance from camera.
I'm going to pass that - flip plan.
Right?
That's the that's the - clip playing value their right.
And so we're talking about this is away from the camera so I should be
able to put in 0.1.
I believe that's the near clipping plane again, we'll check that out,
but I think that's what I'm looking for.
So now I want to be able to go through and I should be able to find
Just by using this call right here, right?
I should be able to get hoops.
I should be able to get that exact test case, so I can look at what
happened.
So, here we come through now.
We should see the debug transform coming through which I can start
with, it's a simpler transform, right?
But it looks like it's never been set, so that's not going to help us.
Hold on a second.
There we go.
So, here are setting the debug transform.
Now we can come in through the on Project.
Alright, so you can see here.
We've got our transform.
Here's the debug transform here.
It's got exactly the regular orthogonal unadulterated axis there.
Exactly what they normally are.
We have the P value which is at eight above back Z, right?
So it's eight above the ground plane which again is what we expect.
Here's our world distance from camera.
It's 0.1.
We would expect now for the p-value to basically walk it back.
So it's going to start
At 8:00, and it's going to walk back along.
The Z axis should be 7.9, right?
Or something like this.
Here's our probes e, there's that 7.9.
There's the W value, right?
So now when we transform this probes the out, I'm going to see what we
get.
So, here's our probe Z and you
Kind of see the values that we end up with here.
Let's look at our clip C.
So, our clip, see is exactly correct.
In this case, right?
We're getting literally, the perfect value app exactly what I would
expect to see and off we go.
So you know, they're, we're going
And so now let's try it with the far clipping plane.
Thank you, said that.
Was that a hundred?
Again, I guess I need to set the breakpoint.
So I set the debug camera first
And here we come through here.
Let's see what our clip Z is that now it's at 1 so that so that's
exactly what I would expect, right?
So this is working exactly how I was expecting it to work.
All right, so now let's pass a value in between those of eight and
see.
Am I just is it just that the Z is that ridiculously nonlinear?
That this is actually the expected value in between those two I mean
it could be right.
So let's see here, what we get, what's our Clips?
The so
What is that's the right value?
Wow, that is just nuts.
How much Z resolution you start to lose after getting only that far
away from the camera.
Am I right?
It's crazy how much you lose their I guess that's how divide it's the
inverse Square law kicking our butts.
At that point that's just nasty.
So no cause for alarm I guess but I guess there is a little bit of
cause for alarm which is just to say that that is not particularly
good resolution for us on our Z and it suggests that 0.1 maybe is too
close for comfort on that near clip playing.
Let's take a look, I'm just curious if we continue down the path of
fixed z-buffer.
I kind of wonder
If are near clip playing, maybe should be set something a little bit
further out than that.
I don't know if this is too far out, but I'm just curious now to know
what, our unprojected value would be at 8:00, if we set our near claim
clip playing up just a little bit, so, not particularly great even
even.
So right, just not a, not a particular Great Value.
I feel like this is just one good
Reason not to do the vanilla style Z buffer and instead use something
else, either floating Point Z buffer or W buffer or something like
this because that's just not a very good value.
Do you know this?
The range just in there is just not great, right?
If you think about how that's going to map that just makes me a very
nervous.
A very nervous Nancy at that point so that's probably something to
look at.
I'm going to go ahead and make a note of that in the to-do list here.
I'm going to say
So we should just think that through and try to come up with yes
something there.
I don't suppose.
Oh wow, that is lucky.
I just happened to look over at the chat.
I was like, I wonder if Alan is watching right now and I just happen
to look over and see mr.
Fourth dimension is talking in the chat right now.
So basically here is a question for Alan which is that?
I don't know if you've thought about this at all.
I know it's a weird problem.
But when I Keep to-do lists, in this case, I wanted to make it so that
the wrapping happened, like, if it's Dash space thing, there's the
wrapping would like rap properly.
And I know, that's kind of, like, outside the scope of where for
coders at right now because in general, the parsing is not in the
custom layer.
But I was wondering if you would consider adding a parser mode for to
do outlines that, just whatever it is will comply with it.
So like you could just say, oh, it's just Double Dash or something, is
what it is.
And then it'll line things up.
So that wherever you have the Double Dash, it'll do the wrapping
properly on those because you've done all the work to make that happen
in code and I'm just wondering if there's a way that you could make it
for to-do list, so that it would Auto indent them properly.
You know what I mean?
And
I don't yeah again, I don't know.
I'm not even sure what I'm asking for.
Just, I'm asking for someone to think this through in a way that I
could get something out of it.
Maybe it needs an open.
You know, thing here.
I would be okay with putting those in just, I don't know.
Something that's like a good format for indent, you know, for outline
ning, that that could be used to keep lists because I find myself
doing this in for a coder now and it would be cool to have.
Good layout for them.
So I wouldn't really care if it conforms to any standard of mine.
I'd rather just like someone.
And in this case I guess would be Allen because he's the one
implements the parsing but to it, to figure out what's a way.
I could structure.
Simple outlined lists.
In a way that would allow them to be formatted properly and for a
coder and I'll just use that format like I'll just convert all of my
files.
List to that format and use, right?
Because that would be pretty great.
And for coder already has all the features.
It only just only has them for code, right?
That's it.
So, anyway, that's that's all I was going to throw that out there.
And I noticed you guys are talking about the virtual white space.
I tried turning on Virtual b a few builds ago, and the problem was, it
couldn't save in a way that you could debug yet, and I think that
might be fixed now.
So actually, I just updated for a coder today on both my work machines
and here, and so I probably am going to try returning on Virtual white
space because I really want to use it.
And I, it was just
The debugging that was preventing me from using it.
So if that's actually fixed, now I probably will go to Virtual white
space.
Like now, basically, but anyway, that's separate issue.
All right.
Anyway, near and far clipping plane distance being what they are.
Maybe we'll fuss with these a little bit later and figure out what the
problem is.
In terms of getting more resolution there, that's a issue, we haven't
really talked about much and I don't need to go into it now because
we're not having any actual bugs with it, but I wanted to put that on
the to-do list because we probably will have some bugs with it.
And so we should actually get our Z's story straightened out, right?
That being said, looking in here.
Now what's going on?
Here's you know, everything seems to be sort of a little bit more
solid, they working now and that's all fine.
But now let's go back to what we were trying to do before and debug
the the other problem we were having that is that when we are creating
these screen indexes, right?
I had a problem where as I start to add screens step I'm going to try
and stack them on top of each other.
We were getting some problems.
Like for example, I don't know what is happening here.
I have no idea what we're seeing here, but we're getting some kind of
weird situation where we've got
Like the camera encased somehow in some degenerate, de Jammer to
degenerate geometry of a layer or something.
I really just don't know what exactly the bug is that we're getting
here, but we're definitely getting some kind of a problem.
So, when we stack multiple worlds on top of each other, we get a bug,
right?
And we need to start debugging that because that should not be
happening.
The other thing that we probably want to do here, I wondered or
Direction equals 3.
What is door Direction?
Equals zero, which are, which here so door down is three-door, up, is
to what happens if I do the other direction.
Just curious.
So it's only if they come up closer that it's the that it's a problem,
right?
And you can see our Z offsets maybe a bit aggressive there, you can
see that this is it's too much Z stand up.
It's actually
Large enough that the height.
Although the height between I don't know if that's a reasonable height
between floors here.
That might be a little bit low ceilings if you will.
But yeah, you can see that.
That's too much offset because they start to poke through the Z here.
So I feel like also what we want to do is calm that Z offset down
that's in the push bitmap.
Oops.
Stuff here.
So here is where we're actually doing that Z bias.
You can see the Z bias here, being set to the height.
That's obviously like way too much.
So I'm not sure what we want to do, but we want to calm that down.
Considerably that maybe too much calming down.
Again, this is just a way of biasing those values.
So we were going to need something that sort of zoom out a little bit
here.
So that also looks a little bit wrong to me so our bias I think in our
in the Shader, our biases being applied incorrectly because the bias
should not change how we see things.
Based on Zoom because that should be consistent.
So I feel like we should double-check how that that bias is being
applied in the Shader as well.
Let's go take a look at that.
So, here's our code for that.
Here's the vertex code.
So, interesting for coder will now treat this as actual code.
Is that true?
Maybe not.
He gets confused by the gets confused by the are strings.
Looks like maybe I'm not sure anyway.
I think it used to just treat them as regular strings, I'm not sure
about that.
Anyway, so take a look in here.
You can see where we're using the Z bias value here.
When we output the position, after the transform, we take the Z vertex
and we add the bias to it, it should be being added in World space,
right?
And then it gets transformed through and
That is what we give our our transform Z.
Right?
So we do the transform on both of these and we just take the Z from
the one that's been biased.
and so,
to be honest, that looks correct.
Right?
So if you look at how GL position is half, is working here, right?
You can see that this is being pushed in and what I think would be
correct.
I guess that could be Z5 but it's this is not.
This is a, this is a z that's getting transformed properly.
So in theory, the Min and Max transformed here should be working
exactly as we would expect, right?
The Min, transform for the Z.
It just does this transform on the original coordinates whatever they
were right?
Not adult training them in any way.
And then yeah, the Z bias here is only used as far as I remember.
Anyway.
Yeah, it's only used when we're actually
Putting those top coordinates, right?
And it's as the Z4 value of the V4 final value of those that should be
ripe.
When we look at what happens in here, all we're doing is extracting
that W coordinate and we're passing that down as part of just the Z
value which should only be used for the deaf buffering, right?
That's the only time that that should be used and it's going
transformed through the transforming the standard path.
So again, that should just work
I don't know why that would be.
All related to zoom.
The only thing that happens with zoom is the Z, buffer, precision.
Will drop their but that's it.
So I want to know if that's related.
I don't know if it is or if it isn't a z-buffer, Precision thing.
I don't think it is but I want to verify, that's not what I'm going to
do for that to take that out of the possible set of problems is when
we do the z-buffer, I'm going to make it use a floating-point frame
buffer so that it's less likely to be sensitive to where it is in that
range.
Although I even that's not really probably what I want.
But let's take a look and see what we can do here.
So, when we actually create these frame buffers, you can see depth
component 32 here and I don't know.
I'll try setting it as an F32 to see if there's any difference.
Is that?
Let me find out what we've got here.
GL depth.
Oops.
No, no.
Thank you f.
They put them on the opposite side as do I here we go.
I just want to see what the difference is between floating point and
non floating point at the moment.
So it's the same in both cases.
So that's puzzling to me.
So that feels like I'm doing again.
I'm just really concerned about this.
It seems like we're handling those z-values incorrectly and maybe
that's a problem with the projection Matrix.
I don't know but that's just not what I would expect to see, right?
Because that Z bias is getting applied in World space or at least I
thought it was.
But in actuality from what you can see is that bias is dependent on
the cameras.
Distance.
Because this is not rotating at all.
So there shouldn't be really any difference in the values that are
going in here.
They're just getting projected differently, right?
That's the only thing that's happening is they're getting projected.
The projection Matrix is having different different Z, offsets, right?
Or the camera, transform composite projection composite Matrix.
I'm getting different visor and you can see very clearly that the
offset almost looks like it's being applied sort of in screen space if
you will.
So that as things got closer together in the in clip space, it's like
it was applying
Their June.
I'm saying in that doesn't make any sense to me.
I don't know why that would be the case.
So that's a bit of a Puzzler and it's impervious to weather we're
floating point or not.
So I don't think it should have shown at least some difference in the
artifact.
I feel like if it was a z-buffer, Precision issue then changing
between floats and fixed.
Should presumably.
Give you different results.
I would think, but I'm not sure.
I guess I can't really verify that.
That's 100% true.
I would just expect to see something slightly change between them.
Maybe that, maybe that's naive.
All right.
Anyway, so moving on here.
So the question is, why are we getting that?
Why are we seeing that difference, right?
What's going on there?
And so, what I want to do, let's start with some simple tests.
If I just said, don't bother with the Z vertex situation at all so
don't don't actually buy us them.
I'm curious, do I see any difference there, right?
And the answer is no.
So if we look at what happens in this case, all of the stuff,
Seems pretty consistent and I don't get any, I get a regular 3D scene
getting rendered exactly as one would expect here.
Right, I don't know if any of you guys see anything wonky but I don't
everything seems pretty good, right?
No, we are done this yet.
So, I'm happy with all that, that all looks relatively good to me.
And so then the next question is.
Okay, when we are doing this e bias, why wouldn't it be transforming?
Itself normally.
Why would that Z bias not be in World space?
Or what is the thing that makes it appear?
Like it's not in World space, right?
It's being added to Z vertex.
The Z coordinate of the vertex.
It's being added before transforming.
So it should in theory go through the full projection and everything
else and it should get minimize down to a value that's relative to its
distance away.
Right.
And so I just don't see, I don't see why that value.
Would change based on the distance from the camera.
So I guess one thing is how far away those things actually are from
the camera and how close they are to the far clipping plane it could
be that it doesn't really matter what the Yeah.
So I guess let's just try some stuff in terms of the Z Precision there
and we could also try doing an infinite for our clip plane to try and
increase the Z Precision.
I believe it was Sean McGrath who was saying, just always use one and
I do happen to always use one and actual
but I just do it because I don't want to bother thinking about far
clip planes, not because I was trying to get more Z Precision, but you
know,
whichever one works.
So let's do ahead and take a look at what I could do there.
So, if I was going to just play around with that a little bit, if I go
into the math, where we create the projection Matrix, what would
happen if I just push the near clipping plane out quite a ways, right?
So you know, get the near clipping plane out to a very large value,
right?
And oh I've got a re-enable that
Z bias there.
I did that.
Okay, so that's even weirder.
Look, I don't know why that why?
You were getting a line there?
Look at this.
Look at how odd that is.
Oh, that's just the front.
That's just the near clipping plane.
Clipping through.
Never mind.
So we can just really weird Behavior hero, the Z po.
I know what there's to the Z biases.
We reduce that quite a bit.
Let me take a look at that Z bias there.
Let's restore that back to the height.
I don't know if that Clips through at the outset or how much that
Clips through.
Just razor just really weird results.
I'm just, I'm very confused right now, is basically what it boils down
to, oops.
And I think something's wrong, but I'm not sure how to go about
looking for it.
So I think we're going to have to play around with this a little bit.
I don't know.
What does correct see bias value should be here probably want to.
Take a look at that a little more, a little more closely but there's
that front that near clip playing, it's quite far out.
You can see it clipping the geometry there, right?
So it's very far out right now further out that we would want and it
looks like again, when you zoom out to about here, you can see those
pretty clearly.
Right.
So what happens?
Let's just see.
So here's the first place, I start to see some of that popping.
I'm very curious to know if I just went into math right now and set
these back to what they were.
Does that change?
So it really does seem to be about our Z, right?
So it looks like this is just a z Precision issue to a large extent,
which is nuts to me.
I feel like we must have something kind of busted.
Let's take a look at how our projection Matrix compares to a standard
projection Matrix.
Maybe we did something really wrong with how we mapped it.
Or maybe that's just normal.
I don't know.
It just seems that's just nuts to me.
That that would be that sensitive.
So I still think something is kind of weird here.
Something's going something's going on.
That doesn't make a lot of sense, right?
It just feels like things are mapped
In a very weirdly nonlinear way.
So let's take a look.
Standard projection perspective, projection Matrix.
I don't really know of particularly what any of these are going to be
but you know, it should be anyone should be fine.
I don't know if there's anything.
I just I'm looking for a stand.
It's we're talking about various to standard perspective, projection
Matrix.
Let's see.
so,
This is what we want, right?
Near post Far Over farming, a senior.
And I want to just correlate with ours, so near us forever.
Farm - New Year.
Not quite the same, right?
We have near - far.
And this is two times near Times far, which is what we have over near
- far.
So, this is backwards.
The fact that that's backwards.
Probably the it's just that we have a negative one here.
Do they just have a one there?
No.
They have a 1 there.
So I'll be honest, I'm not sure how we could both be right about this.
Did they flip the Z range?
From what we normally do?
Because that's they have exactly what we have.
It's just there's a neck, an additional negative
Right?
Because they've got a farm - near there and we have new.
Let's check another source.
Again, I'm just randomly picking sources here because I don't know if
any of these are particularly reliable.
So I'm just seeing what people in general are doing
Let's see, no.
Somebody, please just show a standard projection Matrix from opengl.
I think I tried this before but we couldn't get one that was properly
written out.
Yeah, it was like it's all the
everything.
Munch together here.
Stack Overflow doesn't have the diagram and doesn't.
Does anybody have the original formatting?
All we just need is the original Fort.
There we go.
Oh, but yeah, but this one's missing.
What's on top?
So there is at least the same as ours and it's near - far in both
cases which is the same thing we came up with so I think maybe that
slide just had a bug or they were trying to map the range the other
way around which you know, maybe that's is what they were trying to
do, I don't know.
I wish someone else would have the actual top values in there though.
But it doesn't look likely.
Oh well.
So, I don't know.
I'm very weirded out by all of that.
Well, as far as I can verify, from not particularly good sources
though, other people do exactly the same math that we worked out.
So, presumably, there isn't a lot of variability there, so I don't
really know.
I'm just not sure what to make of that.
so, I guess one thing I would like to see
Is if we didn't, well probably shouldn't leave the near clipping plane
quite so far out there.
so, with the near clip playing operating in this fashion,
That just looks backwards at the moment.
It feels like we've got something messed up, right?
Like maybe we really do have, maybe we are a mapping the range the
wrong way around and open.
Jill actually wants it the other way or right.
Like maybe we do want one of our values to be negative, right?
Like maybe we do want that instead or something ridiculous like this,
I don't know.
In what universe?
That makes sense.
But you can see it's a little bit wonky.
Huh.
Well, this is a Puzzler.
I would say there's a number of reasons why it's a Puzzler for me.
I want to double check one more thing I want to turn off the Z bias
one more time just to make sure.
Actually, I guess, you know what I'll do?
We turn off the Z bias in the following way.
So if I come through and I'm in render group, and I look at Z bias
here,
I'm going to turn it off at this at the source here.
And so here you can see that everything that's is is sorting exactly
as you would expect and it's not sensitive to how far I move away,
right?
Everything appears to be correct in that sense.
And it doesn't matter how far away I get.
I can get out.
That's the far.
Clipping plane right there.
We're hitting it.
And it's totally fine.
Totally stable, right?
No issues.
now, the instant, I turn on the Z bias suddenly even the base like
something's really borked here because even the bottom of these
Sprites, now the bottom of the Sprites again, shouldn't be
Affected by Z bias at all because the bottom of the Sprites have a z
bias, value of zero and fiery.
So something's really messed up there because that's clearly not.
What's happening because the bottoms of the Sprites are wrong, not
just the tops of the Sprites.
So the Z bias is just there's something fundamental, I can pretty much
guarantee it that I'm not understanding about.
What's going on with the Z bias?
Like my mental model of How It's Working, is not the way it's actually
working because that shouldn't it should have no effect on the bottom
parts.
Of the Sprites who's Z bias value is always 0, right?
So something's really screwy there because that should not be
Panini.
Yeah, I cannot think of what the problem would be there.
And again, that bias is entirely pre transform.
So this is in World coordinates that are coming in.
So when it's biasing in Z, it's not even biasing it towards or away
from the camera.
It's biasing it upwards in World space.
That's the only thing it's doing
Right.
And it's biasing it so right because that's its pre transform.
So it shouldn't have any effect at all.
Even which camera were using whether we're using the debug or the
release or the game camera.
Shouldn't actually have any effect because it's the worldspace
movement.
That's is where it's happening.
And then it gets transferred by the transform.
So, the transform part is separate.
It's not Z bias isn't dependent on that.
Unlike the vertex coordinates which are right.
The vertex coordinates are depended on that.
I'm trying to think if that
Is.
At all relevant there.
So in push bitmap, right?
We are using the X and Y axes here are based on the camera, so there
will be Z displacement happening.
As you rotate the camera around and and those Sprites turned to face
you.
But in the case of what we were looking at, you know, the cameras
looking kind of down on the world, there isn't going to be any Z
displacement, other than for the y axis, the y axis will have some but
it will be very
Little.
Again, these axes are coming from the game camera, not the debug
camera, so as the debug camera becomes more oblique those things
aren't pitching to follow it at all.
So that shouldn't be affecting it either.
So I really just cannot see why we're getting that.
Why we're getting that?
Extremely odd result?
It really looks like the Z.
It really looks like the Z bias is getting applied in clip space.
That's what it looks like.
But I just don't see from looking at the math, I'm not figuring out
how there's like something about that that I just don't get.
So in order for that Z bias to be dependent on the camera distance, it
has to somehow be getting past the transform, but as far as I can
tell, it's always behind the transform.
So I'm just not sure.
Oh no, I am sure.
Wow, that's subtle.
I am sure now.
Well that's that's premature.
I have a good idea of why.
Let's say that.
So not quite this Z value is counting on the W value to counter divide
it in order to get the right position in clip space.
however,
We are passing the W from the other.
We're passing the the W from the upper coordinate because we want the
Zeeman transform X and the Zeeman, transform y to get / this w.
Right.
So what we actually want to do is we actually want to pass the Z value
here which when divided by the other W gives us the same result as if
it were divided by its W.
Right?
So oh man, you can tell I've never done a z bias in the Shader before
because otherwise I would have known this already.
I always liked learning new things.
Oh wait, I already did the day 374.
Don't need to write that again.
What am I talking about?
Well, I'm talking about this.
What we did when we solved our equations, right?
As we said like okay, we want that clip Z
Right?
The way we're going to get the our clip see is we're going to take our
Z value and we're going to divide by RW value.
Okay?
So what that means is we have to solve so that Z over W properly Maps
between negative one and one, that's what we said.
We were going to do, right?
What that means is that w and z are inexorably linked in this
transform, you can't modify the Z without modifying the W or where you
end up in Clips face will be totally different than where you should
have ended up for a different world space z.
Z, you can't just modify the the Z you're transforming in without
modifying the
W because they have to divide has pieces that have to cancel out,
right?
So what we've got here is we've got a z a bias Z if you will.
We've got like a z Prime over a w Prime that we want to equal a
particular value, right?
Like this is our see, this is our value, we're trying to get out,
right?
But we're actually going to do is we're actually going to be my
dividing that Z Prime by our original w.
Right?
The unmodified W.
So we need to do is we need to make some coefficient here that we can
multiply this this this Z by such that a times Z Prime over W is going
to equal Z Prime over W Prime, right?
We need to modify the values so that it will actually come out to the
thing.
We wanted to come out to even though we can only divide it by this
value.
so what if we multiply these out, if we said AZ Prime W Prime Rams,
cross multiplying equals w z Prime right in this case,
The Z Prime is would cancel here because you know they're the same in
either case.
So we'd get like a prime W, Prime equals w.
Right?
And that a prime value is W over W Prime.
So what we actually want here for our Z Prime value, is once we have
our Z Prime, we need to multiply it by W.
/ W Prime to put it into the correct space for the divided, right?
So in this case, we know what those two w values are going to be post
transform, right?
We had seemed in transferring zMAX transfer, we know those two W's.
So we need in this case, our zMAX 2
From Z, right?
We've got our special like we've got our modified Z here, and that's
going to come in here.
So our modified Z in this case has to be the original w.
Right /.
The the new W for this one.
And that coefficient, then multiplies the Z value.
We actually have to get our modified Z.
Right.
Okay, let's see if that helped.
Hey, guess what?
That was exactly what we needed.
Rotation in this case won't really work properly because again, that
bias is expecting the camera to be placed straight up and down, I
believe.
So we do have to account for some of that.
And we also now you can see some things that we will definitely have
to deal with which I'm not sure.
We will deal with exactly.
This is a pretty good point.
Actually, I'm not sure what to do here when we have things.
Like, in this situation where you've got a block, that would be a
obscuring.
One of your other blocks.
Something that's raising up here.
That actually is I guess what would happen, right?
The Z value.
As this thing goes up further, if it extends past into the other block
you would get that bug, right?
These right?
It's are bigger than the block their on.
Which is not really correct.
Like that should not actually be happening but the result there that
you get and you can see it there, right?
Is as that comes up through the other block, it will it will pierce
through it.
Right.
I'm trying to think if there if there's ways we can make that.
Less likely to occur.
I think we could and I think the way we could do that is by saying
that, you know what, the we could have that Z bias, being more
directional, if that makes sense, meaning that Z bias could could we
could correct that to be more like we were actually tilting the
Sprites in the way they actually are supposed to go rather than just
biasing the flat on the flat Z projected coordinate.
I don't think about that.
We may still want to play with that a little bit more but at least I'm
glad I figured out what that problem was because that was really
bugging me but now at least we know that that's not bogus anymore and
that's really good.
But like I said, we still kind of have a problem here and then I'm not
sure exactly how to fix that.
I you know, while we're on the subject of these, we might as well
check look into it a little bit more because I would like that to be
correct.
We are mostly correct here, but when you have a block that's much
lower,
Then another block and you're looking at them side wise.
And again, it's not happening in very many places but there's just a
couple where you can see it.
And so I'm trying to think of where there's really only one that's
really pronounced but here maybe this is a good one to look at.
So you can see this tree is on a block that's much lower, right?
It's on a block here and so when it comes up, it comes through this
because you can see its placement in the world you know.
It's going to be you kind of want it to appear behind this block even
though that's kind of wrong.
Reason that you, you get that is because the tree should be sort of
sticking up prospectively this way, right?
It should be tilted.
And at the moment it's not so I guess I also wonder, you know could we
tell them?
We could we leave them tilted.
Is that a better plan?
I don't know.
It might be or a slightly tilted.
I'm just going to quickly play with that, just cuz I'm interested to
know.
So if we were going to leave them slightly tilted, then basically what
would be happening?
There is the.
So we're using the X and Y axis of the camera here.
And so, what we could do instead is use a little bit of
What the actual Z axis is and make that be what we use for the y-axis.
And so, in order to do that, we need to kind of give the y-axis a
little bit of the actual Z.
Or I guess the other ways that would be give the y-axis a little bit
of what it actually should be rather, than strictly changing it to be
entirely in the cameras plane, right?
Because what we're doing at the moment.
If you think about sort of how these Sprites getting generated right,
if I'm looking at one of these blocks and I put a Sprite on it, then
really if the Sprite is standing upright, it should be kintyre Lee
perpendicular to it, right?
So you know, this is the coordinate system that we should be seeing
for this Sprite.
We're here is the y-axis, here is the eclipse x axis.
Here is the Z axis.
What were actually doing, is the Sprite is aligned with the camera, so
it gets a y-axis.
Very much not that, right?
So it's X and Y, axes are completely different.
Now if we actually were going to do it, like, you know, cure, let's
just show what it would look like in the, in the case of the x axis
and y axis, in this case, we're actually what we would expect.
Well, I guess it's just what.
Well, here we go.
So basically if it's an upright Sprite, then really, the only
difference here is, we're doing exactly this.
The x-axis still is what the x-axis is.
But in this case, the y axis, instead of being just, you know, the X
and in the X and Y plane, the x axis, the y axis.
In this case are going to be in the, the plane of Z and X instead of Y
and X.
So we're basically looking at something like this,
And so, if we take a look at what that looks like here is at least I
think I did that, right?
Did I do that, right?
No, I did that in no way.
Correct.
And that is because
those.
Is need to be undefined.
There we go.
Okay, that's what I wanted to show so you can see like this is what
would happen if the cards were actually just standing upright and we
wouldn't need the Z bias in this case because they're just in the
world the way they're supposed to be.
But the problem is when you look top down, it's ridiculous, right?
I mean that is not at all.
Going to be a playable scenario to have 2D Sprites mapped in that way,
right?
It's just it's just silly, right?
It doesn't make any sense.
But that's where they should be.
And so, you can see why we if you take a look at where we were getting
problems before, let me go ahead and zoom down in here so you can see.
So you can kind of see the way these Sprites should be standing up in
front, you know, in the positions that they're at.
You can see how you get away from the, the clipping problem.
It's because the Sprite goes out into the side.
And so, in our case, when it's down here, it's coming straight up this
way.
It Pierce's straight through this Cube instead of going out into the
side, but there might be like, I sort of saying maybe there's like a
middle ground there you maybe.
You can take the X and Y, axes and like blend them together or
something like this to produce a composite version that has still a
lot of the properties.
The camera transform, but doesn't have as many errors.
I don't know.
But, you know, let's say you were to do this.
Right.
What I could do then is I could do a linear blend here.
I never know.
What we call this every time I have to look it up.
I don't know why we called it.
Something that I don't recognize.
Lerp.
Yeah.
So if I wanted to alert these two, you know, I could do x axis 0, x
axis 1 and go halfway in between them.
That's probably way too much to go.
But I'm just want to see if this works at all.
Like, what it does, it all that will, like, kind of combine, the two
ways of doing those axes and not a particularly good way but it's
fine.
So there you can see sort of a combination of the two.
Right?
And it's you know just still gets a little bit upward disc.
So I guess you know what you could say is what if we went you know,
most of the way towards the camera facing one you know.
And you can see there now it's sort of a little better like it's still
not great because it still does.
The has the clipping problem a little bit there.
But you can see it kind of goes up to the side more.
Which maybe is a good thing, you know, I don't know.
So we've got some stuff to play with they're like I don't know to what
extent we want that.
The other thing we could do is say, oh, you know, maybe we'll only use
the that that Z value from it.
Maybe we'll do that and and, you know, play with that a little bit.
So, you know, maybe the x axis actually equals, you know?
And in fact, I guess the x axis itself doesn't have to do this.
Maybe the x axis is always x axis, one, and we only play with the
y-axis is first.
So that would look like this, right?
He can kind of see what that would look like, right?
So, the trees are still kind of slanting a little bit and that's kind
of cool, right?
That starts to look more, right?
Potentially to me, I don't know, a little bit hard to say, but it's
starting to look a little bit more, right?
And maybe furthermore, maybe we just add in the Z part.
So maybe the x-axis, the y-axis is also just the original but then the
y axis is z is this alert between the two of these or
Something.
You know and again since we're trying to like simulate a 3D look with
2D art assets, it's hard.
There's no right answer here.
We're just trying to play with sort of ways we can hack those values
but that kind of looks better than what we had to me.
Getting a little bit of that.
Slanting to the side in there.
Just feels a little bit better.
So, I don't know.
I feel like that's sort of a thing that, you know, kind of looks cool
or to me, and it gets a little of that bend in as well, so I kind of
feel like that's may be good.
Also the Z bias doesn't have to come in there.
I don't know what the right value is lerp wise for that you know maybe
we want even more of that in there there's more of a slant to it,
right?
And that's looks a little bit too much certainly but yeah, I don't
know.
Having a little bit of that lerp does seem kind of good.
So, I don't know.
I may want to leave that in there.
We'll find out.
Just the slightest band.
And so again, just so you can see what that's actually doing.
Here's the debug camera so you can see that.
Now, what we're doing is we're still aligning with the camera but
we're just giving it a little more of the upward tilt than it.
So it's, they're standing upright a little more than they used to
stand up.
Right.
So we're kind of artificially inflating that stacking from what it was
that's all that's happening there, right?
So I don't know.
All right, let's go to questions.
Today we ended up investigating something I wasn't even planning to
investigate, but that was pretty educational for me.
I like, as I've never tried playing with a 2dz bias kind of a thing
like this before.
So I had no real expectations of what we would see there in terms of
problems and that was really interesting.
I was like, oh, right because this is going into Clips face the W and
the Z have to work together.
You can't just shove one of them in there.
That's not really going to do what you think it's going to do.
And so that was pretty.
Good.
I'm glad I learned that that was
That was, that was cool.
All right, so, let's see.
Question I am a fairly immature programmer.
I have dab dabbled in Java flavors of C, Python and Ruby while I was
in university.
My question is, how would you suggest with progressing your
Proficiency in a particular language is the best to follow tutorials.
I guess what I would say is it's it depends kind of where you're at
certainly tutorials and like reading other people's writings on how
they did things in this language when you're earlier on in your
programming, education is important because, you know, you won't think
of all of the stuff on your own and you want to kind of learn from
People who have already done a lot of thinking about it.
As you get further along in your programming, one of the problems is
there's just a lot of bad ideas out there too.
And in addition to ideas that are just objectively bad which there
are, there's also ideas which are subjective Lee bad so there's ideas
that are just no one should be following.
And again if you're a beginner program or you don't really know and so
when you're looking tutorials you may just be seeing just really bad
ideas.
But then there's also just a question of how you like to program and
what you find effective for you getting stuff done and that's
subjective.
And so, that's the other problem with following tutorials is you,
maybe learning
That subjectively don't work very well for you.
So, you kind of are in the situation where, as you move forward
programming, you have to kind of get both things working together.
You need to First find reasonable sources of new ideas.
That will give you ideas that you don't have yet about how to program
and techniques you can use to tackle various problems.
Right.
Handmade hero is one.
Way of watching somebody program.
See, you can see the kind of techniques I do.
If you haven't thought of these techniques before haven't been exposed
to them.
Now, you know, them and you can go.
Do I think that's a good technique?
Do I not think it's good technique later and kind of integrated into
it?
Right?
There's lots of other sources, you can go to it.
There's other people, you can watch program on Twitch.
There's tutorials you can go read, etcetera, etcetera, in all kinds
different languages.
Like you said, depending on which language, you want to learn at any
given time, I would say, probably pick one.
Stick with it for a little while.
It's probably not a great idea to if you're trying to learn to be a
better programmer to be bouncing around to lots of languages because
that's adding more complexity.
So I'd say maybe pick one language.
You want to focus on for for a little while first and then you know
maybe explain that a little bit later but then what I would say is
also as you're gaining more of that sort of exposure to techniques,
try to start to then start being critical of them, right?
And not necessarily critical of them.
From a, this is good or bad, an objective sense but critical of them
from your perspective as you practice programming and try things, go
did these techniques learn well for me which of these techniques are
working in which of them aren't and start to develop a good mental
process there where you go evaluate, don't just do something because
you saw it on this show or another show or in a tutorial, it may not
work for you, right?
And so start to develop a good habit of assessing
Programming techniques for your own use.
Are they working for me or aren't they?
And that is very important to learn because if all you ever do is just
use techniques you saw because someone said they were good or
something that's going to hold you back because the chances that all
the things that say I find effective when I'm programming because
that's the way my brain works.
And it's the way I program most effectively, the chances that that's
going to be exactly right for you are low, right?
There's probably different
Ways that you will conceptualize problems and different ways you will
solve them.
That might be subtly different from mine or very different from mine.
And if you don't have a good way of moving yourself towards those,
you're always going to be held back by programming in my style or
somebody else's style or some mix of styles that isn't the right mix
for you and so I don't pretend that that's easy to do.
It's not it takes a long time to come up with that taste of like what
are effective.
But I would just encourage you to do some objective analysis there.
Take
I'm in your programming to actually try to measure.
Write some code specifically, using a couple different techniques and
compare the results.
Which ones went better for you?
Which ones do you do?
Like the looks of more, do you find you can manage more easily?
You know, which ones are easier for your brain to wrap around and and
that I think would would probably
Be good advice for basically, anybody who is kind of coming to that
point in programming, where they've gotten enough exposure, that they
kind of know what's going on, but they haven't really turned that
corner too.
I know what's, what's an effective way to program for me, you know?
Hedge 1993's.
What is z transform?
Are you talking about in the open gel layer?
Are you talking about this here or you talk about like the min/max
transform?
That's something I know of that would fall into the name z-transform.
In this case, what's happening?
This is the vertex transform code.
So all the vertices that come down for all of the Sprites in the game,
pass through this piece of code.
And what's Happening Here
Is, you know, normally what you would see in a just a vanilla Shader
is you just literally see, like this line of code, you just see
transform times the vertex and this transform is the full transform.
It's the camera plus projection transforming one Matrix.
So it's the thing that takes World space on one side which is here and
transforms it into clip, space for opengl and the other side.
This however, this transform times in vertex here that doesn't help us
do our fake Sprite Z biasing.
Because remember we're 2D art but we're drawing in 3D which is a weird
hybrid way to place the be.
So you end up having to do some weird hacks, to figure out how to make
things harmonize properly in that world.
And so, what we do is we transform twice once with the real-world
position, and once with a offset of world position as specified by the
input vertex,
Import vertex is W.
Coordinate is actually secretly, A-Z biasing value.
We do that.
And then we compute what the Z value would be.
If it were actually offset by this, this Z bias value that's coming in
and that's what we use for depth sorting.
So it's just a way for us to make Sprite cards which are not standing
upright appear, like they're standing upright in terms of sorting,
even though they're not drawn that way, in terms of spatial, right?
How many draw calls with the profiler open up?
We're not really counting draw calls yet, unfortunately.
So we don't have a way of doing that.
We could add account
That but we don't have one at the moment.
Every shoe a few streams.
Go you showed a function that tells opengl to call us back with
messages.
Do you think it can help debug opengl issues instead of sticking Jill,
get error after every call?
Yes.
In fact that's exactly what it's for.
The whole point of that, debug callback is if you are asking for an
opengl context, that supports that
And in our case, we just ask the extensions there and it's essentially
a return it on.
If you have that extension on, then you should most of the time
because we also enable the synchronous debug reporting.
So if you if that happens then what you
What you should see occur is, as much as the driver can.
It will immediately interrupt the flow of the code and call that back
as soon as you've done something wrong so you should be able to avoid
having to spam GL, get error everywhere.
If you have a driver that supports error reporting via the debug
error, callback.
So I highly recommend turning that on if you have it available, yes.
Arif, when the new assets Gonna Be Ready.
Other new assets are ready.
I just haven't had a chance to actually use them yet, So eventually we
can switch to them.
I just haven't had a chance.
Holst 80 scenario is that handmade here is expanding 23 programmers.
And to need to understand the architecture you've designed how would
you recommend that they get into the code and understand the
architecture?
What would you need to do to prepare the system for such a scenario?
Hmm.
So I guess my answer that would depend a lot on the programmers.
Right.
So you know, if you're like well the programmers are like, you know,
Fabien and John.
I'd be like nothing.
They'll just day would be fine in here, right?
It would just there, be nothing that would need to happen.
They would just know what was going on and they would be fine, right?
And they would have a bunch of things that are in the code base are
not the way they would want them to be done.
I'm sure.
We're but they wouldn't be surprised by anything and you know, it
would be whatever.
If instead you told me like okay these are two like interns from like
college or something.
So they may have no idea what's going on in aren't super familiar
with, you know, production, programming, and whatever.
Then I would probably want to do things a bit differently.
So first of all, I would want to know what are these people going to
be working on, right?
And once I know what they're going to be working on, I might go to
those sections of the code.
A hardened them a bit.
So I pull out the parts that I expect people to must with and make
those sort of clearer internet and probably provide additional API
design work there, that was intended to clearly articulate to the
novice programmer.
What these sections of code were supposed to do and how?
And I would probably add a few top-level comments to some H files that
would say.
Say here's how this API is meant to be used.
Just so you understand, right?
So, you know, I guess that's, that's what I would say.
If we went further and said I'm going to ship this engine to people,
and they're going to build their own games on top of it, right?
I would want to do a lot more work.
So in that case, I'm now thinking about like a maintenance style
project and I would want to really sit down and work the apis and
decide exactly what the boundary was.
And I, because, right now, right, when it's my code and I'm the only
one working on it, then keeping everything flew.
We did until I want to lock down a section.
For some reason, like testing or something.
Is always the best way to go because otherwise you're just burning
friction on doing a bunch of work.
That doesn't need to be done, right?
and one of the
Common mistakes, you see, programmers, make not just beginners.
But even people who've been pregnant for a long time, you end up in
circumstances, where you'll see them spend a lot of time on code, that
doesn't do anything because they're in.
They've been trained that there's a certain idea of what good code
looks like without appreciating the fact that there is no such thing
as what, good code looks like code always has objectives and what
makes good code is how well it matches those.
Is.
And so, if you're doing stuff, like declaring private, operator equals
four classes that you are only using internally and are never going to
make an operator equals error for you have.
Just wasted your time, right?
Not to mention added code, that adds complexity to the code base, that
doesn't do anything.
And so it's very important to always keep in mind.
What are you trying to accomplish?
And what code will accomplish that most effort with the most efficacy,
right?
And so that's why I say like a question like oh you need to have other
programmers work on this or things like that.
I always want to know.
Well, what am I actually trying to deliver to these to these new
programmers?
What kind of programmers are they?
Because what I'm going to deliver in the changes, I've got to make to
work with more programmers are going to be
Very dependent on who those fragments are.
How much do I expect them to understand what I'm doing?
How isolated do I need to keep the code from them?
How much maintenance work?
Do I need to do across the boundary, blah, blah, blah, blah.
All of that comes into play and it can range everywhere from I'm
shipping an engine to external people who have no idea what's going
on, who may be very beginner programmers.
I need to maintain the code for them blah blah.
You know, which is the hardest core level of.
Meaning, I'm going to do there all the way to, my friends are coming
to work on this thing.
They're experts.
They know how to code this as well, or better than I do in all cases
and I don't have to do anything right.
They're just going to go and it's going to be fine.
And we'll have some friction along the way when they expect something
to work one way.
And it doesn't, or I expect something, they wrote work woman doesn't,
and we'll have a little bit of a snafu there, but it's minor.
And any time spent trying to avoid them would be a waste of time,
right?
All right, I'll take one more question here.
Ron Paul Vivo.
I know you don't really like object-oriented programming design but
can you provide some ways you might take advantage of hoop design in
handmade hero?
So I guess what I would say is I typically try to say the same thing
to hammer home the same point about object-oriented programming,
Whenever it's discussed.
The problem with object-oriented programming is just the
object-oriented part.
I've tried to say that a lot of times I'm just I'll say it one more
time to try and Hammer it home.
And and that is to say that there isn't any specific element of the
object-oriented design results that is particularly problematic.
Like, you know, there are times when you want to hide implementation
of things, there are times.
And you want to have things broken into pieces that, you know, are
decoupled, and you want to do, you know, there's there's times when
all of the things you might see in a object-oriented programming could
be relevant to a good design.
The problem with object-oriented programming is are not those things
because you can see some of those things crop up in handmade hero.
Sometimes we end up isolating a piece of the code.
Are we end up keeping a little thing?
That's kind of like it might look more like Anup style result like,
you know, here's this thing and it's interface is kind of well defined
and it's you know, kind of often its own piece of the code so it's not
intermixed with anything else and bubble and starts to look more like
what you would see in the result of an odd.
You know, after an object-oriented design programmer
or did some stuff or whatever, right?
So all those things are fine.
The problem is the mindset of object-oriented design, the idea that
the way you should be approaching the code is by thinking about what
the objects are and how those
Are working, that is the problem.
So I would say it's it would never be good on him a hero there's like
never a time when I think you should think about the code base in that
way.
Literally, like I never think that approaching is perching it from the
perspective of the objects is ever good, but in terms of things like
oh I want to like sort of break off a piece in a reusable way that's
you know, very specific about what is part of it and it doesn't let
anyone outside of it touch.
Touch the way it works because it's trying to you know, be sort of
hidden in that way those things all might be reasonable, right?
Those those things might all have times when you want to do them and
whether or not you want to do them, depends a lot on for each
individual element of that is the thing that you're getting from that
delivering any value, right?
And to give some a little bit more perspective on that I guess just to
just to clarify if you took something that's typical in
object-oriented C++ for example, right?
Like you took something like oh you know, I want here to use a private
section, right?
So I'm going to take all of the variables in this thing.
Let me, let me think of an example.
Here.
So, so here we are in in, you know, in game mode world, right.
And I've got all this stuff in here and, and I want to like start
making it so that no, I know that.
No one else can touch anything in here, right?
So you know, you'll see stuff like oh opportunity programmers are like
all the data has to be private.
Like that's just it's I'm trying to--.
This is an object.
So you know it's all got to be private and then there's like a public
section in the public section is going to have some stuff in it where
the functions, you know you can call.
So you know if you want this no Collision you got a call get milk
Collision or something like that, right?
You know, that's like a thing that just an object.
If someone's a serious job during a programmer day by day, you'll
notice, they hardly ever write anything that doesn't look like that.
They start that from their point and to me, it's just like, well what
do I need those features for right dick all the only thing that
clearing this private does, is it makes it so that I know a priori
that no code, that isn't declared inside the game-mode world struct
itself as a member function is
Touching them, that's what it does, right?
But I don't really have any problems with that day to day, right, when
I'm programming.
I don't care if people are touching this, any code that wants to touch
standard room definition just can.
And then you see me do this many times.
If I'm like, well, you know what, I want to start to regularize how
standard room.
Definition standard Rim Dimension is working.
You'll see me do this all the time.
Right.
That just generates an error everywhere.
Anyone's accessing it, and I look to see what they're doing now.
I know, right.
That's it.
It's that simple.
And if I want to now, pull that out into something that has to get
access in a structured way, I just do.
So I just, I really never see the point in doing the sort of wrote
mental application that object-oriented programmers, say is good to
always do these things.
They just don't help at all.
I've never found the circumstances where it was good to do that up
front.
It's always good to do it after the fact if it's good at all right?
So when I'm going to start doing those things, I would always do them
and last not first.
Object-oriented programming to me is just a bad idea, you know, if
anything the time to do it is at the end, so it would be
object-oriented cleanup, right?
Don't don't.
Whoop, whoop, might be the thing if you want to do something
object-oriented, right?
So I think that is kind of the philosophy that I have when programming
certainly.
It's what I found to be most effective is that any work you do?
Thinking in terms of objects at the head end is almost always too much
code to get the desired results in flexible code that introduces
boundaries where none should exist yet tortured thinking.
Like a lot of times you see it, right?
You see someone whose approach a problem?
I was right and you're like, wow, this is a really overcomplicated
unnecessary set of
Ode to do this simple operation, right?
And again, I think it's just because objects are not the right way to
think about problems.
And that's not the same as saying that you should never end up with
any.
You might write the right way to structure the code might look like
the result of some I trained except it also might not and the key to
it is developing programming practices.
That get you to a well working.
Nice design as quickly as possible.
Whoop never seems to do that.
As far as
Until that doesn't mean that the principles that happen in
object-oriented programming are never.
Applied should never be applied or anything like that, they very well
very well maybe.
And that's an important distinction to understand.
All right.
Yeah, it looks like everyone kind of
We're relatively I'm bored with that too.
So hopefully that answer was relatively complete.
And yeah, I would say that unfortunately, that's not the way who
principles are taught either.
Which I guess also gives them a bad rep in some sense to write.
Because, you know, if
If you think of all of the possible techniques that open Plies as
bundled with the design philosophy of approaching problems, this way,
it might appear that they're all really bad, right?
If you're an objective viewer, thinking about that together, you might
be like, oh, this is all really problematic.
It doesn't feel right to code this way, the results seem to be bad.
But again, that's, that's, I think the mentality, the design approach
is the problem.
Not that individual techniques, because each individual technique
could be valuable
In a well working design and you, as long as you come at it, from the
pragmatic, what makes the code work best perspective, you will
discover those techniques when they are appropriate and you won't use
them when they're not and that is exactly what you want, right?
And and I think that that
I don't know, I think that although I'm sure it's a controversial
answer for Loop devotees.
I've hope that's a relatively non-controversial answer from sensible
programmers because again, it's not saying don't ever use thing X,
it's just saying the mentality of always use thing X or always think
in terms of X is not good.
Think, in terms of the end result.
And then, when thing X comes out,
As oh, that look at this is solving this problem that I have
specifically.
I can see it good, right?
And so I hope that that, you know is at least, you know, it gives
enough flexibility for the individual programmer to approach elements
of poop, in a way that they can use the ones that are sensible in the
circumstances where they are applicable.
And not get saddled with the bad part, right?
Which is sort of this the dogmatic I always program everything to look
like this which you know I think any any you know, you know our
objects any kind of dogmatic programming approach that's like the code
should always look this way is just probably going to be wrong.
Right?
What are the chances?
That there's one way to always write code, right?
It's just, you know.
It's unlike I certainly couldn't tell you one way to always think
about the design of code, you know, I feel like you got to just always
the one way is to focus on what turned out to be effective and that's
not really a way, it's more of a metric, right?
Oh, and I'll just someone was asking what I think about constructing
this.
I don't use const anywhere and the
And for that is, I don't really have constant bugs.
I think I'd handmade hero.
We've had maybe like, one or two in.
I don't even want to know how many days 374 episodes.
We've had one or two, in my regular programming.
I've had zero.
So, I think mostly the console bugs were ones that I had here because
programming on stream.
I can't use all my brain.
I'm talking all the time, so my programming is worse, you know, pretty
much across the board.
I notice that a
We in multi-threaded programming to wear things that are hard to think
through, I make a lot more mistakes.
So given that I don't have any bugs hardly ever.
And when I do have them, they're fixed almost immediately.
Like, I don't have the lingering bug problem.
I don't seem to have for const, that's why I don't use it.
Because I pretty much know that I never have issues.
Where I where I modify something I shouldn't be for very long.
I just don't tell Dad.
That bug.
So that means that all the work of putting constant is just a waste
for me.
I'm gaining, literally nothing from it.
However, that doesn't mean that.
I think other people shouldn't use it.
I think basically, you should figure this out.
Exactly this.
Exactly just said, how often do you have bugs related to const?
Try not using kant's for a year.
How many bugs do you encounter?
That would have been stopped by having const.
Look at those bugs.
How hard were they to debug if they took you 15 minutes to debug and
you only had 10 of them in the year, I would say that's a pretty
strong argument for not using const.
It was hardly would save you almost nothing and it's something that
you then are saddling.
All your other programming thought with right.
On the other hand, if you have a constant tug every day and some of
them take you three hours to find.
Well, that is a pretty good argument for using constant your code,
right?
So I think
I think it's pretty easy to determine in your particular scenario
where you are programming.
Whatever you're doing, you should be able to figure out pretty easily.
Whether cost is something that is making a difference for you or Not
by straightforward testing.
So I would say just do that test and then you'll know and then you
don't have to ask me or anybody else their opinions because you will
know definitively if you should be using it.
And people are saying that's more on the chatter, singers more for
teams, and of the programmers.
I think it's the same all around.
It's basically the case that you should be able to test this.
Your team either does or does not have a problem making these bugs and
how what bugs they will make if they're consistent.
They're take variable amounts of time to solve.
So basically, to do that test,
Figure it out and then you will know for your team.
Are you wasting your time or not, right?
Because if it turns out your team just doesn't make a lot of bugs like
that, then you're kind of just wasting everyone's Time by saying that
cost is better for teams.
You don't know that it is, right?
You have to actually determine that the bugs that you will introduce
by not having const actually take a long time to find.
If you're finding that, you're just not making that many and they
don't take that long to find.
It was about it was the wrong trade off?
Right.
So that's really it.
And, and that's true for all programming paradigms.
In my opinion, every programming Paradigm that you're like, should I
do this or should I do that?
The answer is always the same.
Does it make your programming job more?
Does it make your program more effective to do it?
Then it's a good idea, right?
The problem with a lot of them is, it's hard to measure.
Const is very easy to measure because it has no effect on the code at.
All, right.
Cost is just about debugging.
So it's very easy to measure.
Do it.
Don't do it.
See what the differences in terms of your debug cost and then, you
know, right, you can weigh that against the amount of time you're
spending making sure that everything is cost.
Correct, and you now know the trade-off.
You now know what the right answer is right.
And so, if every programming practice were that easy to test, you just
do it.
Unfortunately, it's not right?
Unfortunately, a lot of programming things, it's really hard to
Do a test about which one's more effective.
So I can't give that advice for those but const.
It's really, that simple.
Are you more effective with it?
Or without it?
You should be able to test.
Right.
Alright, that's about it.
I'm going to wrap it up.
All right, thank you, everyone for joining me for this episode of
handmade hero.
It's been a pleasure coding with you.
As always, if you want to follow along the series at home, you can
always pre-order the game on hand be here at org and it comes to the
source code.
So you can follow along with all of the days.
We also have a forum so I can go to if you want to ask questions a
patreon page, if you're looking to support our video series, a
schedule bot, that tells you when we're going to be live and an
episode guide that lets, you know, when or sorry that helps you follow
along with episodes that have already happened.
So that you can
Look at them and find what I'm talking about more easily.
If you want to know when we'll be back next that is actually tomorrow
at 10 a.m.
Pacific Standard time or Pacific Daylight time.
Sorry, it's daylight savings here now
Leave soap.
See you back here for that.
It seems like we got the Kinks worked out of the unprojected z-buffer
stuff for the moment.
I still am a little worried about the Precision.
I think we may want to switch to an infinite far clip plane or
something, so we maybe we'll do that tomorrow.
But otherwise what will do is play with some of the effects that I
wanted to start with today but didn't have a time too because I wanted
to figure out what was going on with some of that projection stuff.
So that was good.
We got that straightened out tomorrow, we'll play maybe around stuff.
I want to play around today.
That's about it.
Hope to see you back here for that until then have from programming
and I'll see everyone on the internet.
Take it easy, everybody.