Start recording.
Hello, everyone and welcome to handmade hero.
The show Rico to complete game live on Twitch.
No Library, no engine, just us and our code.
And we're at the point right now where we're trying to do a little bit
of cleanup for going on break, we are going to be on break next week
because people wanted some time to catch up so we're going to take a
week off and people can catch up with the series as necessary.
So what we're doing right now is we're actually kind of going through
and just improving our handling of
Of the we're making a 2-D game to some degree, but we also sort of
have three-dimensional elements in it.
And so, we're kind of doing is saying, well, let's go in there and
we're trying to figure out exactly how we want to handle that third
dimension, how we want it represented, how we were going to handle
moving up and down between things that sort of stuff.
So we sort of Hit Upon something interesting yesterday and we didn't
quite get have a chance to really go explore.
Its 02 today, we're going to do is were actually going to explore that
for.
I get started though just a reminder anyone.
A, who pre-ordered the game on handmade hero dot-org?
If you want to follow along with today's episode coding at home,
today's episode is day 74.
So you want to unzip day 73 source code into a directory and then you
will be able to follow along with us as as we go because that's the
code that I'm starting with today.
So let's go ahead and get things started here.
I'm going to load up everything that we have going, okay?
Okay, so let's take a quick second to recap, what I thought was a
pretty interesting thing.
We kind of discovered yesterday.
Regarding how entities, how any collisions are handled basically.
So previously, let me go ahead and start a little place here for us to
draw day 74.
So
What we were doing before we kind of just implemented, some very
simple Collision things and I had sort of thought a little bit about
some ways we want to handle things.
And so we had ended up implementing just for the time, being was a
system whereby assuming that you have enmity and maybe you had like
here's the hero and here is the monstar and you know you're trying to
track them on Star.
You you know, you do something like you throw a sword.
So here's our sword or s word as the case may be
You throw a sword and that sort is going to go and maybe the sword
might want to pass through the monster and do damage like it's a it
has piercing or something so it's not going to stop.
It's going to go straight through and we had a number of ways that we
could think about handling this and there's just a lot of different
sort of concerns involved in what seems like a very simple thing if
you actually want to think it through and do it, right?
There's actually quite a bit here to think about
and what I had implemented before is, I said, well, you know what I'll
do, I'll implement
Thing which basically says, for any entity pair, like the sword in the
monstar when the sword hits the monster, I'm going to have a system
which is basically like a little like, record-keeping thing, right?
I'm gonna have a little table and what I'm going to do is when the
sword hits the monstar because I don't want to process the fact that
the sword hit the monstar any more than once.
I just want to do whatever happens when a sword hits a monster and
then be done with it.
I'm gonna at that point when it hits, when the sword hit, so the sword
Comes This Way.
It hits the monstar.
I'm going to go ahead and add in
to hear the the sort of the sword monstar entry, right?
And then from then on every other frame I'm going to look in there and
see oh sword monstar was already processed so I'm not going to process
it again right.
Then when we get to the end and the sword like you know travels the
distance, it's allowed to travel and then has to be removed.
What we're going to do is we're just going to clear all of the things
that were in this table, right?
So anything, that was in the table, I shouldn't say all the things,
all the things
That have the sword in it in this table right there.
Going to go away.
So that was an easy way that robustly how handles the case where you
have some kind of projectile and you want to process hits in any way
that you want.
You can know how many times you've looked at something.
You can do all kinds of stuff because this table can store whatever we
want and it persists through the life of that of that hit.
Now what we wanted to do yesterday was we want to say, let's have a
stairwell, right?
Something like this, where you're kind of like going down into the
abyss.
Right here is the abyss.
Or just the next floor.
And so you're going to walk down the stairwell and what we wanted to
have happen with say, okay, if here's the hero, right?
And they're walking in this direction, this is top down.
Now, this is from the top.
If we're going to walk in this direction, what I want to do is say,
Well, when the hero overlaps, the stairwell, then I want him to be
able to move downward his, I want his Z to go downward as he as he
sort of overlaps that stairwell, if that makes sense.
So, when he gets here,
Higher.
When he gets to here, I want the Z value to be the next level down.
And when he's here, I want the Z value to be essentially where he
currently is
Pretty basic, right?
But we want a system that allows us to write code like that very
easily.
So we don't have to do a lot of thinking about it, right?
We don't want to have to do a lot of work to implement things like
that.
We want our Collision sector to make that easy for us.
And so what I was going to do is I was going to say, oh right, and we
started coding this yesterday, all right.
We'll have a notion of where the things are inside or outside of
things.
So, at the start of a frame will basically do a test to see what
overlapping.
So, you know, maybe the heroes here at the start of the frame will
say, okay, he's overlapping, the stairwell.
And then at the end of the
Name Will basically say okay if he's not overlapping the sterile
anymore, that's fine or whatever, you know, we can process what's
happening during that sort of that movement, right?
Assuming so that's kind of like what we were sort of talking about
doing in the you know.
In the, in the processing of the movement of the entities.
And what I realized when I was doing that was like, well, wait a
minute, can't we just use this table directly like can't we just use
the table when we start up and say, okay, when we're overlapping
something, let's add an entry to this table.
And that way there's somewhere to store information about it, as well.
And then when we're done, we can remove stuff in that table.
That way, we're always using the same thing.
Instead of having some kind of special handling for things that over
A lap, we just have a table, which is basically telling us about the
situations that these things are in and we just use that.
And that seems like a pretty good way to go to me.
I mean, that just seems like a good way to go so I don't really know.
I mean that's just that's just seems like a good idea and it seems
like that was going to make things a lot more unified and clear if we
did that in the code.
So that's kind of what I want to explore today.
But other things that I was thinking about as well.
Were things like okay, so when the hero is traveling inside this
region and we want his Z to be mapped to, you know, where he is on
this thing.
You know, we have sort of this other kind of I don't know how you want
to phrase it.
We have this other sort of
Special.
We almost want to do a little bit of special processing because of the
fact that these stairwells, you know, if we look up from the side
view, right?
Because we kind of want to treat them as ramps.
Basically, when we do our movement processing, you know, our movement
processing is going to work like that and really what we want our
movement processing to be doing is something like that, right?
We well it would we want to move the same kind of rate so we want to
look like that, right?
That's what we'd like to do.
And so one thing that I was thinking that we could do as well
His we could sort of say, okay if we have our, our movement code, when
it does the move, you know, we've got this this sort of region.
Check that says, are you intersecting the stairwell?
If you are intersecting, the stereo, we could do that.
Check again for the destination point and assuming that the
destination point is still within the stairwell, right?
We move it down to that to that position or something similar to that,
right?
And that way we can get some I guess we should say we move it down to
that position, right?
I don't know it's kind of complicated.
It's starting to really do like full 3d processing sort of on the
movement of the chi which maybe we don't want to do you know, maybe we
just don't want to deal with that or get into stuff like that.
But I was just thinking about it.
And I was like, well, if you really wanted to handle this correctly in
terms of how you know you would conceptualize the problem in terms of
a more realistic, simulation of what happens when someone's going.
I mean you could imagine us
And going a little further and saying that there actually was an
actual stairwell, and we actually looked at where you were, and the Z
was like, quantized, right to like certain stairsteps.
So the hero goes, like, don't think that, you know, we can do that as
well.
There's all sorts of stuff we could do there, right?
And I don't know how far we want to go down that path, but it's just,
it's just something that's worth noting.
Finally.
There's the easiest thing, which I thought of which is actually a way
of cheesing out on all of this stuff and I don't know.
You know, maybe this is a better way to do it, and we could do it this
way right now and just put a note in, I don't know.
But another thing we could do is instead of processing at the
beginning of the frame process instead of, instead of, allowing the
person to leave or enter the stairwell inside the clitoris, the
Collision, iteration Loop, right?
What we could do instead is just treat that as something that only
gets checked once.
So basically, at the beginning of the
If the guy is on the stairwell, then just whatever the move is, is
just considered a stairwell move.
So the stairwell basically gets to do its operation to the guy,
whatever it's going to be at that outset and that's all there is to
it, right?
And you know, that's one way we could process it, the end then we just
say, okay, he doesn't until he actually is outside of the stairwell on
the next frame.
That's, you know, if he moves outside the stairwell, then on the next
frame, he won't be under the, under the
The action of the stairwell anymore, right?
I don't know.
Again, just something to think about and that may be the easiest way
for us to implement the stuff for now.
I really don't know which of these is going to be more interesting.
And you can certainly imagine this kind of applies pretty easily to
other stuff, too.
So let's take another case.
Let's say we take the case of like poison ground or lava or something
like this, right?
So let's say we have, we have lava here, right?
So this is our lava, right, it.
So it's so hot and burning.
It burns me right?
Ouch.
And so, you know, we have our hero and our hero moves into the lava
and our hero travels in the lava and the hero moves out of the lava,
right?
So if we want to process this, exactly right.
What we need to do is handle that case where the person enters the
lava and handle that case, where they exit the lava and actually
count, you know, if it's distance or time based actually count exactly
the
Period where they're in it in order to apply like the lava damage
right?
The cheesier way to do it is the point sampling way and the point
sampling way basically says okay I'm going to count however many of
these land in there.
So at the beginning of every frame this is not in a lava so it doesn't
take lava damage.
This is in the lava so it does.
This is in the lava.
So does this isn't in the lava so it doesn't right?
And so you know, again,
and this is just a question of how, you know,
Do we want to make this?
And so if we only want to do the point sampling method, then basically
what we would do is we would say, all right there's a separate check,
right?
Separate check where we check for inclusions in spaces, like,
stairwells lava, anything like that, that aren't Collision events, so
people don't collide with the lava and like enter and leave it or
anything like that, right?
That doesn't actually happen.
All there is is an inclusion.
Check that happens separately and then, you know, off you go.
And so that might be a better thing for us to do for now.
I don't really know where we basically say.
OK.
We'll do the
For now, we'll just say, we'll do the Separate Checks, it's easier
because we've already done the code for that.
And each time we check will just pass the full DT for the frame as the
effect time.
So if we have like a thing that was like, apply lava damage.
We tell it, the whole DT for the frame.
Apply the lava damage.
We won't try to subdivide frames and figure out exactly how much of
the time was spent inside the lava and out, but maybe we'll put in a
to do that.
Basically says, ok, you know, maybe we start leaning on the sort of
the table driven system,
And try to do some more intelligent stuff.
There that would allow us to, you know, be smarter basically about
that.
Just something about so I don't know.
I really don't.
I have no, I have no real opinion about how that that should work.
It's just going to have to be a wait-and-see thing.
So yeah, so maybe we do the simple separate check first and we make a
note, and then we see if we want to go the table route.
I don't know.
That seems like the best call to me right now because until maybe we
get a little further, maybe eventually, it'll become clearer exactly
what we need.
Because of other things and then will, you know, go on from there.
And so sort of what I saying is like okay, you know, when we do this
check for initial inclusion instead of doing all this other stuff that
we were doing in here where we were doing our overlapping entities in
this sort of stuff where we were sort of adding and removing things.
What we could do instead is sort of reverse back to the case where we
weren't ever doing that, and we just add the Collision rules, or
something like this.
And we don't actually update that overlapping list.
So we just say okay we don't update the overlapping list.
We don't pass was overlapping.
So let's see, where that was.
We don't, you know, we don't need to do any of that.
So when we do our handle Collision call, we don't actually need.
This was overlapping stuff like so on and and you know, we just let it
do its thing and we we leave it at that.
At.
So now a stairwell is no longer a thing that does collision at all,
right?
It's
Collision based object in any way.
I don't know how we were planning on doing this.
Exactly will have to want to click.
Let the take a second at the end of this to sort of clean that stuff
up a bit.
But basically.
So right now what we do is instead change this to basically like
handle, you know,
I know what you want to call it, but handle overlapping events right?
Or handle events based on area overlapping or something like that.
And so what we can do here is say, alright, we're going to go through
and we don't really need to record anything per se, but we would go
through and just say anybody who does movement past the obviously have
a thing here, where they're going to check for all the things that
they could be sort of overlapping.
And for anything that they are overlapping, we process a rule.
So it's basically like a, you know, a handle overlap kind of a thing,
right?
And so what I'd like to do is say this is going to happen before we
actually try to take any step, right?
So this is going to happen like right at the beginning, right?
Just just flat-out.
So right here before we do anything else, we're going to go ahead and
we're going to see if we're over.
Overlapping anything.
So we'll call that handle overlap.
We will pass it exactly the the two that are overlapping and we'll say
that we kind of have a notion of who is moving so the Mover and the
and the, you know, region or whatever.
Right?
And and we'll do like a should overlap as well for like can overlap,
right?
And so the entity the thing that's moving is always going to be Primal
in this case
We're going to handle it that way.
So we do, you know, we always say that the can overlap in the handle
overlap are both going to kind of do their thing.
So we'll do it that way.
And then we'll have our should Collide, right?
I guess we should keep our name.
It's really should overlap test.
Its the bad, it's bad name.
I wonder if it shouldn't just be can write Can-can.
When can we go?
That seems better should Collide.
And in fact, I guess we don't really need this at the moment, either.
This is just can Collide.
Okay, so if I do that, then we've got our can overlap in our handle
overlap.
This is not important anymore and there we go.
Except I need changed.
Its name.
Here.
And presumably.
I need to pass that.
There we go.
Alright, so now we need to, you know, I should also probably just
double check that we didn't break anything doing that change.
So let me just go ahead and make sure that our code is still happily
running.
There it goes and that's all good.
So now we need to do is just say, all right we're going to test the
entities, we now know you know they're going to overlap and I'll just
write a function which handles the entity overlapped such that.
If a hero or any other thing, overlaps a stairwell.
It's Z gets
Move downward or upward depending on where it is, right?
And that seems pretty straightforward.
Unfortunately, we're going to have to do some work to actually make
rendering show us that any real degree.
We don't have much in the way of that yet, but that can always be our
next, our next task, move and region, call that mover and region.
So the thing that's moving in a thing that needs it overlapping.
So basically, if the region right now,
Don't have anything really here but you know, essentially we're just
doing if the region type is one of those stairwell regions than pretty
much.
That's the only case that we actually need to handle at the moment.
But you know the lava case would be another example here of something
that we want to do.
So we've got our handle overlap as well and we will build that out.
That's again, just taking whoever is moving and whichever entity it is
sort of moving
Or it is contained in.
And I also said, like I was saying before I want the the time step in
there, in case there's a time-based effect that's happening that way
it applies it for a period of time so that if we do decide later to
handle little more accurately, and in fact, I'll put that to do in
here to do handle overlapping precisely by moving it into the
Collision Loop.
And you know we'll just keep we'll just keep improving things as we go
if we decide that's a good idea.
All right.
So anyway if it's stairwell the result is true otherwise Loops the
result is true.
Otherwise the result is false so that's pretty straightforward for
now.
It'll consume to get more interesting later and then when we go to
handle the overlap, what I want to do is say that assuming that the
region is a stairwell
I'm going to do that processing where I'm going to effectively change,
and I'm assuming I'm going to basically change the position and
perhaps also change that velocity to be pointing downwards as well.
You know, I'll just take a look here at how that works.
So the DDP, let me see, let me see what we're doing here.
So the DDP is passed.
It in right?
Is that what happens?
So, we're passing in that acceleration and
The acceleration.
The acceleration gets gravity added to it as well, right there,
mmm-hmm.
I mean, I suppose.
I suppose really all we would have to do if we wanted to is modify the
ground location when you were on the stairwell, right?
Because this code right here, actually, we'll just do what we needed
to do.
Scary is that is so I wonder
I mean it sounds a little odd but like I wonder if we don't just want
to do it that way for now.
So in other words you'd handle it at the end of the frame.
It be backwards looking don't love it.
But and you basically say, like, where's the ground, the ground zero
zero or something like this, right?
You see what I'm saying?
And then you would basically update the ground inside that hand, that
handle overlap call.
It's kind of weird, but it sort of starts to get it.
What I would like, which is, you know, a notion of where the ground
is.
So maybe it's not that crazy and it's probably not exactly how I don't
love the way, it's kind of weird, but, you know, in this 2D thing
where we don't really have a strong notion of where the ground is,
we're gonna have to kind of build a semantic, understanding of ground
that
Make sense everywhere.
And so I'm just going to kind of let this go.
I'm going to see where it leads because I'm hoping that eventually it
will sort of coalesce into a nice way to handle ground.
Again, like I said, I normally program 3D stuff so I'm used to having
to think about a ground is like some full 3d thing.
And in this case, that would be a real waste of time and energy for
the game to even have in it.
So it seems like you'd rather just have the ground is always the
ground.
And the only time that you really do, anything else is when you're on
something special like a stairwell or some other special sort of Z
affecting thing.
So yeah, I guess we'll just say you know we'll we'll go ahead and say
that we've got ground here.
We could even make the ground be a general query I guess we could just
make actual ground shapes and
I think we die that seems like a waste of time so I'm thinking you
only really want to handle colliders.
Yeah.
So I'm going to keep I'm just going to keep exploring this but I just
don't feel comfortable yet.
I don't have a solid idea of exactly what I want.
So I'm going to, I'm going to keep on pushing pushing here and and
we'll see what happens.
So for now I'm going to pass the address of ground so it can modify
it.
But later, what we might do is pass kind of a
Bundle of stuff to that handle overlap, and let that do it instead.
So yeah.
So, what we'll do here is, we'll just say, alright?
You can modify the ground level.
So what we'll do is we'll come up here and in our handle overlap call.
We will pass in that ground ground level.
So benefits stairwell, then, what's going to happen is we're going to
find out where you are in the stairwell and set the ground level
accordingly, right?
And that,
Also brings up another thing which is I realized how we really should
be drawing stairwells which is not with a stupid rock, which is what
we were doing before.
But it's really actually with a rectangle, what I should have been
doing was was using a rectangle.
So I'm going to take a look here and see about drawing a rectangle.
I know we've got one in our draw hip points function, so I'd like to
do is I'd like to do one of these push wrecked calls.
Oh,
Wow, just the other night.
Someone asked about Vector forest and I was like, eventually we'll put
some in for handling colors.
It looks like we already did and I totally forgot.
I knew we eventually would but I guess eventually was actually in the
past.
So, whoever asked that question, not only eventually will be put in
colors.
We actually already put in colors as before us.
There you go.
You'll learn something about your codebase every day that you should.
No because you wrote it anyway so I'm gonna go ahead and here and I'm
going to say that we're going to draw that stairwell as an actual
rectangle now so that we don't have any of this weird wondering,
exactly what it's dimensions are.
They'll just help me to debug it basically.
So I'm going to do a push wrecked on that piece group.
We've got basically a location that we want to draw and then we've got
Dimension.
I don't remember at all.
What we actually did for our
You know, conventions here.
So I'm just going to look it up.
It says, basically that we pass the group, we pass where it is, I
assume relative to the camera, so it's relative to the piece.
So it's actually just the center right there, it's no offset.
We've got the offset Z which again we don't really need any of.
It can just be drawn flat on and then we have its Dimension.
And so it's Dimension is just going to be, it's entity actual emptied
to mention, right?
So that's just going to be entity dim XY, right?
So then the color will just draw an, you know, yellow there.
So we can see.
And, and that should be
Just about all we need, I think to get our stairwell.
So let's take a look at our stairwell.
There's our stairwell, that's good.
And so, what we want to do is be able to move on to that stairwell and
just kind of, like, move on to it and have it allow us to move not
only
On through it.
But basically like to move down a level as we go or in this case, I
guess up a level so that should be relatively straightforward.
However, what we do need to do is we need to be, I guess this gets
actually a little bit complicated, a little more complicated than I
was thinking because we do have one other case that we can decide how
we want to handle I guess.
But basically
The last thing that we do have to worry about is when somebody moves
on to a stairwell, right?
There's two ends to a stairwell.
So I guess we could look at it from the side view again, right?
So there's two ends to the stairwell.
And let's say that somebody is walking up here, right?
Because here's the here's the floor or whatever, right?
If somebody walks, whoa, that was ugly.
I know what just happened there.
So somebody walks here.
We don't want them to snap down.
To hear because they shouldn't be able to do that on the stairwell.
I don't think what we'd rather do is prevent them from walking there,
right?
We want to stop them that should hit and stop, whereas if they walk
onto this end, then that's fine.
Because then they just go down the stairs like they should.
So the question is, how do we want to handle that case, right?
So at first, I'm not going to handle that case, but then we've got
that issue which is basically, you can just walk straight onto it and
we'll see what we want to do.
What we could do is put in blockers.
That block you from doing that, and the stairwell is a hybrid of that,
right?
And then the other thing we can do is handle it in the actual
stairwell processing.
So at the stairwells understand that, and I don't know which one of
those two will be more logical but, you know,
We'll find out.
All right, so if we do this now, I think we're good to go with drawing
it.
So oops, what I do.
I accidentally type you, so really all we need to do here is just say,
okay, where is the the guy inside this region?
And, in order to do that, what I want to do is introduce the concept
of a mapping for any rectangle, and because this is just kind of a
thing that might be handy and we need
For this case, we might as well do it.
What I want to do is say all right for any of our three-dimensional
rectangles, which we now have, right?
I want to be able to say there's a minimum corner to this rectangle,
right?
Let's say that this is our minimum corner, right?
And here is our X.
Here is our y.
Here is our Z, right?
And so this minimum corner and then it has the dimension is is the
distance over to the maximum Corner which will say is here.
Let's right.
What I'd like to be able to do is given a point P.
Right, let's say that this point here.
I'd like to be able to produce what amounts to barycentric coordinates
for this rectangle, meaning coordinates
Range from 0 to 1, right?
Our famous 0 to 1 because everything is nice in the 0, to 1 range,
right?
Range from 0 to 1 and which represent how far along each axis of the
rectangular, the the right rectangular prism this shape, how far you
are the box, right?
So, basically, if in X, you were here, then you would be something
like point for, right?
If you were here, you'd be like .8, if you're here,
It'd be one if you'd hear your be 0 and the same on all the other
axes.
So we'd take what's a normal 3D Vector, right?
And we want to produce those now.
How do we produce those?
Well, the first thing we want to do is recognize that the minimum is
0, 0, 0 in our coordinate system, right?
In when we're saying, we want to produce these new coordinates, we're
saying that if you're at the minimum right, you would be at the
barycentric coordinate 0, 0 0, right?
And I'm saying barycentric, but that's probably
Not really necessarily a useful term to use here.
So I guess what I just want to say is in some sense relative.
Normal coordinates relative meaning their relative to the where the
box is.
So the Box may actually be out in Space, the origin.
Maybe like over here somewhere, right?
So this may actually be 000 in our coordinate system and this is the
minimum of the box, right?
So, the box is actually out here somewhere, but we want to create a
little mini coordinate system, essentially, where the minimum corner
of the box is 0, 0 0, right?
So it's relative, we're producing relative coordinates and we're
producing.
Normal coordinates, normal, meaning they are normalized, right?
Meaning they are between 0 and 1.
So even if this box is 10 meters long, I don't want it to be 10 when
it gets to here.
I wanted to be one
So, how do we make it relative?
Well trivial?
We just subtract the place that we actually want to be 0.
0 0, right makes perfect sense.
Because if we know that we want the point Min right in our coordinate
system to map 2000, then Min minus Min obviously equals 0 0 0, right?
So, what we want to do is just subtract Min from our coordinate
system,
You could think of this, you could do this in Algebra 2.
If you wanted to sort of, if you, let's say you just have no idea.
You're like I don't know how to do that.
You can say, well, I've got a point for any point, right?
I want to I want to basically add something to it.
I want to do some kind of translation.
Right for our question, mark value, you know, whatever it is, we don't
know, vexed.
Some V for every point.
We want to add some V, okay, this is our expression and we want that
point to equal our relative coordinates
It's right.
So this is our relative coordinates or we could say p Prime.
So these are our relative coordinates.
So what did I just say?
I said when we, when we do,
In.
We want that to be 0.
0 0 well just plug those in when I pass the point Min, right?
I get 0 0 0, right?
Or the 0 Vector, that means Min plus v equals the 0 Vector, right
solve the equation for the thing.
We want to know, V equals 0, minus Min, or - min
So that lets us know exactly what we need to do.
We just subtract Min from anything, we want in order to get it,
centered around this thing, all right.
Simple enough.
But now we have coordinates that can be anywhere in this box.
They happen to be 0, 0, 0 here but they could be as long as they want.
And again, how do we normalize something?
Well we know how to normalize things, right?
If you have something at a given length and you want to turn it from 0
from 0 to the length in 2021, you just divide by the length, right?
We've done this a bunch of times like vector lengths and all that sort
of stuff.
So we have right our point - our minimum / however, long that point.
Right for any given.
So, you know, it's kind of hard to sorry.
Not how long the point was.
How long the Min is, right?
We want it to be relative to this.
We want it to be relative to the maximum extent of the axes.
Right?
So, you know, over however, long, the Min is that gives the new
coordinate, right?
So p x Min X, right?
This is basically the, the equation for one of the exes to the same is
true for the
wise and the Z's, right?
So subtract, the Min /.
You know what?
I don't even know what am I?
I'm going way too fast here.
This is not even this.
This means nothing.
What have I written here?
There's no such thing as the length of men.
We already said that.
That's, that's that's stupid.
Pretend I never said that.
That's not what I meant.
I meant the length of one of these things, right?
That's Max.
Minus min.
Yeah.
Going too fast.
I got carried away.
It's true.
Right?
Because if this is the max x-coordinate and that's the minimum x
coordinate of the thing than the length between them is the max minus
the Min, right?
So little mistake there, pretend I didn't say that.
So that's what we want.
We want that Max, minus the Min X, and so on.
So that's, that's pretty easy, right?
It's not, it's not complicated.
It's very straightforward when you think about it, but I want to make
a function that basically does that, so I can grab that value.
Anytime that I want.
So what I'm saying is I want to basically do V3, get saved very
eccentric.
And we'll pass some rectangle and some point, right?
And then what we're going to do is for each of the coordinates.
We're just going to go ahead and make those coordinates fee equal to
the equation that I just said which is you know the you subtract the
Min so a DOT min.
X so on and you divide by whatever the length is, right?
So a DOT Max, dot x minus a DOT Min got X, like so and that's just
going to be pushing the dot that way.
And that's pretty straightforward there.
Now we do have one problem which is that in the case where these were
zero like what one of the dimensions was collapsed, the The Entity
didn't have any size there that would be illegal right?
This would produce a nonsense value.
So since I don't know that we really have a performance concern here.
I'm going to introduce another thing that we can do to make this a
little bit more robust to those kinds of failures.
Which is a safe ratio function.
And the way that I like to do these is to say you pass a numerator,
you know?
And you pass a divisor, right?
And it does a divided for you.
So basically, it just does the result equals the numerator over the
divisor, right?
Like, so,
And the returns that to you.
But what we can do now is we can say.
Alright, this safe ratio will be designed to return a particular value
in the case where the thing doesn't actually work.
Right?
So if that divisor is, is not equal to 0 will do the Divide, but if
the divisor is equal to 0 will return some prefab result.
And so safe ratio 0, I usually do that as well as a safe race.
A 1, right?
That would return one in the case to depending on what the default
value should be.
And so one thing that's pretty handy to do event.
It usually is to do safe ratio and and then that just returns whatever
the N is.
And then I make essentially in line versions of the other two, that
just return, those prefab values, right?
That makes sense.
Hopefully that makes some sense.
So basically it just goes, safe ratio, n.
And passes the numerator, the divisor and whatever the value actually
is.
There we go.
Results.
And so again, this is for cases where you're less concerned about
performance and more concerned about robustness you don't care if
you're doing a bunch of if checks to see what the situation is.
And in this case I think that's probably where we would be most of the
time and certainly in we had a case where it was a performance
problem.
We just optimize that one case, right?
No, big deal.
So let's just go ahead and say that these are all going to be safe
ratios and so that way in the case where they actually have a problem,
they'll be okay.
So if one of these
Mentions is, you know, erroneous and collapses, 20 will still be able
to produce a value there, so that seems fine to me, right?
Safe ratio 0 Station, 1
Articles and trash can icon zero.
Yeah.
So that's all good.
And so that allows us to do our barycentric.
Here, you can say get barycentric and this will give us our
barycentric version back.
So now we can say that we have the Region's dimension.
Do you mean?
This is kind of a little bit of a roundabout way to do this, I
suppose, if you think about it, well I think we have Center dimension,
right?
So our region we pass in pays for the rectangle bounding box that
represents the region like so then we just say wherever the the actual
mover was we get those barycentric coordinates back and one thing we
can sort of do here, we could also assert that they live.
Between 0 and 1.
Because one of the things that's true about this is this will not
clamp those values.
I don't know if we want to clamp those values.
We could write, we could additionally.
Say that they have two teens are in one because let's say that you
pass in a pea that's actually outside the box, it would not clamp it
to the box.
So maybe we want to do that eventually, I don't know.
In this case we're only handling when we overlap so we know that
pretty much does have to be.
So what I'm going to do is say alright we get that Bary Centric back
now we know where you are and we're saying that.
Why?
Why I guess is our range.
You know, why is the thing that we want a very Z by?
So what we're going to do is we're going to say that whatever that y
value that comes back, that's how far right that's that barycentric.
Y value is for our stairwell that bear, something y value is how far
you've gone, right?
So here's one end of this Arrow host the other.
So let's just say that we take that
Value and that determines that that Z value of the ground, right?
So we want to do is say that the ground equals the barycentric V
value, y value, and we want to do essentially a linear interpreter or
a linear interpolation like alert here, right.
And what alert base is I've talked about this many times before, it's
that magic function and I said we would use everywhere and have used
multiple times already and will continue to use a bunch of times,
right?
It's this thing 1, minus t times, the starting Value Plus T times.
The ending value moves, you between two values proportional to this
tea and the tea is ranges from 0 to 1, right?
You've seen it multiple times, if you don't remember it now, be a good
time.
To go back for a refresher to where I've talked about it before or
watch the interpolation video that's on my
My thing, I have a whole video that's just about interpolation, but
anyway, so what we want to do here is say this T value, right?
The T value is our y.
That's our y value.
How far you are in thing, are barycentric, why?
And the s in the, ER, the Z.
As we want.
So, this s value would be like the Z Min and the E value would be the
Z Max for the ground, right?
And so, as you go, you go up, we could also make it the other way.
As you go, you go down.
Who cares?
Doesn't matter for our stairwell.
It would be nice to draw in a particular direction.
So, we probably could do something like that where we try to draw it a
little more clearly, which direction it was going.
I can think of a pretty easy way to do that.
Maybe we'll go through that in.
But anyway, so what we want to do is we want to do that, linear
interpolation.
We haven't made a function for it yet.
But we should throw it in here, right?
That's just as easy way to sort of do lips, especially to D3
dealerships, that sort of stuff.
We probably want all of those.
Right.
So, where is our squaring function?
There it is.
Let's make another one here, alert function.
So there's our alert function.
It will go from A to B like so.
So here's our results and our result is just a is just going to be
that.
That 1 minus t plus T times B is exactly the thing that I just said in
that we have used before that's going to be the value that we get
back.
So we're just going to go ahead and lerp using that barycentric
y-coordinate as the lerp, we're going to lurk between RZ Min and our
zMAX orz Min is whatever the Region's p.
Z value is
Write Plus, or I should say actually we can we can actually do this
right?
With our rectangle.
So if we, if we remember what our rectangle is right here, is our
region wrecked.
Region right now we can just say OK the region wrecked, it's Min Z and
the region r x, max Z, that will just learned between those right?
And that changes the location of the ground.
And now, since the guy is always pinned to the ground, basically,
he'll just snap to the ground.
Now, unfortunately, I said we don't really have any good rendering for
this stuff or anything like that course.
We need one more thing to which is that the guy can
Kitt, the stairwell.
So we need we need to actually make this so that this isn't actually
in the Collision.
This is actually in can Collide.
So we want to do here is say something like this result is false that.
All right.
So, I think now we should be able to walk through the stairwell.
I hope.
Oops, guess we set a breakpoint there.
I don't know why we must have done it before.
So why am I still colliding?
Can Collide should be returning, false now.
Oh, is it?
Because I didn't sort those two guys, right?
Yeah, that's because this isn't sorted, so we need to do this either
way.
So basically what we need to say is if if it's a stairwell at all, you
don't want to do it.
There we go.
All right, so now in theory, we should be able to do something where
we look and see how our stairwells are working.
We should be able to get these working.
We're going to need some way to actually render where we are and Z,
which I guess is our next step.
But at first, we can at least go into the debugger and see whether
we're actually handling the stairwells by inspection at all, right?
Because we just wrote a bunch of code there and we have no idea what
it does or if it works.
So, let's go ahead and actually do that.
So, we got our can Collide your hand, a collision with a bubble, but
this is what we want to see, right?
Oh my, what is overlapping the stairwell right now?
Dare, I ask.
Why are we getting called?
Right at startup handle overlap.
Oh, because we don't check for.
Yeah.
All right.
That's a problem.
We don't check for things overlapping themselves overlap, right.
We remember to do this here, where we did the sort of
A not equal to B so we did this right?
But we did not actually do that for the the overlapping so we want to
do is say that things that are you know obviously things that are the
same thing can't overlap each other.
Of course.
No, I think about it.
Why are stairwells moving?
Oh because everyone gets moved now.
We should probably have a thing that says that stuff like stairwells
don't move, right.
Like we probably need a flag for that because we really don't need to
call move entity on these sorts of things, right?
So we want to say that if that's not set and probably we want to do
something here where we do like entity
And they flag movable or something.
Right?
We probably want the concept that something can and can't move to sort
of be baked in there and some sense, right?
And the flag movable equals like that and then only look, our monstar
are familiar, those sorts of things would have that.
So let's let's double-check that.
Sorry.
I just, we just never did that and I was like why was that thing even
getting a move call?
So now nothing should be
To move, presumably now but it still is.
So what did I
So it's bright.
It's supposed to be is set movable?
Not is not set that.
That's kind of obvious.
Sorry, there we go.
It would be non movable.
All right, so nothing can move now, which is what I wanted and now we
can just go in and say when we add things like the monstar monstar, we
can say that, you know, it collides and it is movable right?
And I don't know, does add flag allow multiple ads.
I assume it probably does but it's not called add.
Flags is the thing that's a little bit weird.
Don't you think
It seems a bit strange ad.
Flat roofs.
Add flag.
Where is that flag?
Rep.
Add flag.
So yeah, this is really add Flags.
So we should probably say that for now.
Let's take a look at that at flags flags.
Flags flags, flags, flags, flags flags, flags flag.
There we go.
So that way we can just kind of go like, okay, we'll just put both in
there.
Same thing with the familiar.
Oops.
And layer and the sward should also be in there.
I think, right there we go.
We gotta clean those flags up because the collides thing is now all
kinds of weird because we're going to we're sort of working on what
those systems even mean.
Alright, so now in theory, we should be able to actually do something
with the overlapping so let's see.
What we've got, all right.
So here we are in our in our sort of barycentric mapping code.
Let's see what we were, you know, got back.
So that's, that's just totally wrong if I'm not very much an error.
So we have a bug here because our y value should not be - oh,
You know what?
It totally can be negative because these are regions that are
overlapping.
So we do we.
Yeah, right.
Like that's totally true.
We already need the clamp thing.
I said we didn't need the clamp thing.
You shouldn't listen to me.
This is why you don't listen to KC believe the, the debugger, because
the debugger is, right.
So, we've got a situation where a guy can be overlapping, the
stairwell, right?
But his point is not in the stairwell.
So it seems like we really do want to clamp the value to the minimum
and maximum of the
Of the rectangle.
So that so we do want we do want clamped barycentric.
So yeah, let's go ahead and do that.
We would a native that anyway, so no big deal handle overlap.
Let's do get clamped barycentric.
and we will go ahead and I guess we could also do
How do I want to do that?
I could just do it this way.
Right.
Something like that.
I think I like that better.
Let's do it that way.
So inside the math functions, I'm going to go ahead and do a little
clamp function here, which we may want to do something better for in
the future right?
In terms of how we implement it.
But so we want to do here is say alright we're going to have a result.
The result is going to be equal to the value but if the oops the
result is less than the minimum.
The
Equal to minimum.
And similarly, if the result is greater than the maximum, the results
going to equal the maximum and then we will return the result, right?
So I think, you know we could do that faster with Cindy.
I don't know if the compiler smart enough, it probably is.
Who knows these days and then what I'm going to do is I'm just going
to introduce a clamp that specialized again 401 because that's a very
common thing that you want to do.
So basically you just pass a value and that value
If I you just passed the value in that value will automatically have
the zero and the one passed with it.
Like so.
And that will be the result of that function, return result.
And then what we'll do is we'll just actually have the oops.
What'd I do wrong, that's fine.
And then what we'll do is we'll just have this for our various V2 V3
before, is that sort of things, right?
So for now, we'll just go ahead and say, all right, we've got that
clamp, 01, that will take.
Of the three and it will return a V3.
And the result X is just the clamp 01 of the of the input X just clamp
each of its elements.
Like so, right Z
And done.
So,
Now, we should not have that problem, right?
Where's are?
There it is.
So now our why should be 0 it is off we go, right?
And now our Y is actually coming up a little bit.
So let's take a look at what ground actually equals.
So when we ask where the ground was, oops, where the ground was
originally?
It should be 0, right?
Because that's what's normally set to, and when we're done with it,
the ground is negative point.
Five two.
Is that sensible for our ground?
I'm not sure.
Let's take
Look.
Oops.
Where is our region region P.
Its Z is at zero and it's Dimensions.
Yes.
Oh, that is actually reasonable.
But that also means our stairwells, probably not positioned quite
right.
Because it looks like where we've actually put our stairwell is in the
wrong place.
If this is one level,
This is one C Level and this is the next sea level.
It looks like the way I did it.
Oops, was I put the stairwell like that, but we really want the
stairwell to do, it's something more like that, right?
So that was a mistake.
That's a little bit of a mistake.
So let's go ahead and try to fix that mistake.
And actually, even to think about it a little further.
We really want that stairwell to include a pretty wide.
We want to test for a fairly wide area, but then only actually applies
easy from here to here.
So, what we may want to do is have a separate dimensions for the
stairwell and the actual locations where the guy is going to move
along, right?
But that's, you know, six of one half, dozen of the other.
All right?
So anyway,
We now have our stairwell.
We need to go in here and see about where we're actually putting it at
stairwell.
Let's find out add stare and yeah.
So that's just yeah, right?
We want to we want to do a thing basically, we're when we add the sky,
when we get this chunk position from tile position, we want to do an
offset of that.
So we want to, we don't want it centered around the Z level, we want
it to be.
Staggered.
So I'm going to do just because I can because I'm the programmer and I
guess do whatever I want is I'm going to go ahead and say that our
tile depth in meters.
Here I'm going to go ahead and say that we're going to offset it,
right?
So we pass an offset and the offset is going to be this.
So if it's at that Z,
We're going to offset It Up by half so that it's in the middle there
between the two Z layers, that seems like a better plan to me.
So if we do that, then what we need to do is update that chunk
position call.
So in our handmade world .h, right?
Our chunk position from top position, position isn't a position has to
take additional offset, right?
And the additional offset is just going to be
Added straight up, right?
And this will be defaulting to the null Vector, so people who calling
it and don't want to do with that at all.
They don't have to
so that I think would make it a little bit more.
Like, what I was expecting to have happen because now, if I restart so
that it's in the new Pluto, it's not showing up there.
Did I offset it somehow too far?
So it's not included.
What did I do that?
Should still put it right.
That should put it.
That should still make it so that it's actually inclusive.
Right.
You know what?
We may have one more thing we have to do for our Z, when we actually
gather all of our entities are,
Actually gathering in the Z bucket, properly.
And I don't know, right?
It's it's this thing Min chunk P.
Yeah, we're not, we're not at all right.
We, we are purely fabricating that Z value, which is which is garbage,
right?
This should actually be looping over all of the Z's that were in our
Min and Max chunk value.
So that's a holdover from when we
When we weren't actually doing an easy stuff.
So, yeah, that's one more thing that we didn't really think of, but it
is definitely something that needs to happen.
Now, what I don't know is how we're actually Computing these bounds in
the first place.
Those the camera origin, the camera region, not really sure what we
did with Z there.
Right.
What if what do we actually do for camera bounds?
So, we did a tile, you neither.
Direction, I guess or Center Dim?
Yeah, so we did half a tile in either direction that I don't know if
that's really what we want, but at least we've done something.
So there we go.
Oh, that's hilarious.
So our Z sort of already worked a little bit.
Because it's offsetting those guys by the Dare distance down.
So we're actually seeing two levels at the same time now, which is
kind of cool.
That's funny.
I didn't realize that would happen, but it did.
So now we're Gathering, both the entities on the top and the bottom
that's kind of funny.
All right.
Well, so in theory, we should be able to move up and down here.
But we don't actually, I don't actually know if we are
So, we can't go through there because it's blocked.
If we go through the other direction, can we now go through it now.
So, let's find out why we're not going up and down here.
Let's let's see.
So are we in handle overlap?
So we're not actually actually overlapping this thing.
So are our test for overlapping must not be actually hitting, right?
Are overlap test.
What do I want?
What do I want to do to check that?
So,
Rectangles intersect, how are we doing our test?
So that, you know, it's a pretty tight thing that I asked to do and
it's probably not how it like I said, we'd want to wider range for
doing that inclusion testing, because if the guy is right on the Z
value then, you know, that's a little bit iffy but at the same time,
he should be right at Z equals 0, right?
And so if he's right at Z equals 0, it's still that test should still
be passing.
So I kind of want to see why it isn't.
Let's just go a quick second into the Q&A because I just I just want
to see before.
We end for the day and pick up that to bugging tomorrow.
I just want to see what exactly was happening there.
So I set a breakpoint in the hero code and go ahead and run that.
I'm going to go ahead and now see when we step into that move entity
call.
I'm going to go ahead and see what's happening with the overlap test.
Such that it fails, right?
So we come in here and we're, we're going to do this.
This right down here.
So right here.
So let's go ahead and do that, and the can overlap thing should should
happen.
There we go.
And now we should be testing against against the stairwell, right?
So, let's just double check, but that's what we're doing.
So, the entity type is the hero.
The test entity type should be the stairwell.
So, there we go.
So let's see what our two rectangles are.
So there is our enemy wrecked.
There's our
Sanity wrecked.
And let's see.
So the problem is, our entity is slightly below the Z line because he
hasn't been, okay?
So that's the problem, The Entity has gone below the Z line, right?
Because he hasn't been clipped yet and so he doesn't hit the
stairwell, which I guess is going upwards, right?
And is placed at Z equals zero.
So it's worth noting that this is kind of a tricky situation, right?
Um if we're you know this this is again sort of underscores the
trickiness of semantic Z handling where we're basically saying all
right we don't really have a concept of ground.
You're just kind of walking along it and so I wonder if we need to do
something where like that ground support.
Yeah, I don't mmm.
I mean that sort of argues for doing the test at the beginning and
picking the ground support based on that somehow, right?
And I don't know if that's, I mean, that's the cheesy situation.
That was where I had it originally.
I don't know if that's such a good idea because it seems like you want
to end him on the ground where he is.
So I'm not sure.
I'm not sure.
I'm not sure what the right fixes for that yet.
Because again, I want I want something that feels solid to me.
I don't want a super janky concept of where the ground is.
So, you know, that that starts to sort of feel like to me that I need
a little bit more of an intelligent sort of handling for that
groundless and maybe the Z needs to be dealt with a little
differently.
Like maybe it was a mistake to
Great.
The
In here, maybe we don't want Z Motion in there.
Maybe we always want two dimensional updates and we don't do
three-dimensional updates.
And then we handle Z after the fact, I don't know the trivial solution
here obviously is to make the stairwells a little bit bigger, right?
The, the super cheesy thing is we just make the stairwells handle
that, but that's really lame.
You know I'm saying but that would do it for now.
So if I did add stare or we do this, if we made this a little bit
bigger.
So instead of it only being that long, you know it's a little larger,
right?
I'm going to put it to do Casey this is extremely not cool, figure out
a better, ground update solution, I believe that would would fix our
From there, right?
Let's see here.
Yeah, so there we go.
And now we're actually working properly, of course.
Yeah.
Whoa, what's going on there?
There we go.
So let's see.
So we can't go through here now and then, let's see if we can walk up
the stairs.
Is that up the stairs?
Is that down the stairs?
I don't know.
Which way the stairs go.
I think about that.
I assume that's we're still not quite going doing what we want.
Let me see.
What happens when we do our alert?
What's the ground value?
0 should be right and we do it at seven so we should be going up.
Let's see what happens.
Oh well, that's one more thing we have to finish before.
All right, promise this is the last thing.
I just want to see if this works.
So yeah, we actually need to use our ground value to say the least.
All right, so let's see here.
Does that work groups?
And the stairwell does go up in the up Direction at the moment.
So there we go.
Let's see here.
So that goes up and that goes down in theory, right?
I wish I had you going to need some way of telling you because I can't
really tell at all what's going on since we have no rendering but
yeah.
So that definitely, I mean he's moving up, you can even see him move
up, right?
But for some reason I can't go through here.
Oh, you know why?
I guess, because these entities are not being three-dimensionally.
Hit tested.
So that's the next thing we have to do.
Because if we have entities on here we need them to actually be 3D hit
tested.
All right, so we're getting closer.
This is kind of interesting.
This is going to be really kind of fun for me because I like I said
I've never done a game that was purely to do before.
It's kind of fun, working out how I want to handle.
Things when you don't have actual 3D, you have kind of like pseudo 3D
and you need to, you want some amount of 3D but you don't want it all,
you know, you don't want to have to go and actually have meshes in
there for everything.
It's pretty interesting.
So yeah.
So what's happening there is these entities are still blocking.
So you need to kind of like you can imagine all that test in here
where we do the Collision testing.
We're testing its entities that are below you and we are only doing
Two dimensional Collision testing.
So if you no matter how far below it was, it's not going to actually
work, right?
And so you could almost think of it as like, you know, the, the sort
of weird version is like this, right?
And easy peasy, right?
Assuming that they're on the same Z plane, then they can actually be
considered colliding with each.
They're otherwise, they're not allowed to write or something like
this.
Oops, that's mistake.
So if we did that, then in theory, you know, you can do this and then
walk through like so and then if we wanted to go back down, we do that
and
That didn't work either.
That is how I would go back down.
Right, there we go.
Guess I just didn't quite do it.
Right?
Yeah.
So pretty janky, you know, we've got a ways to go.
Let's put it that way, but at least we're sort of getting there,
right.
We've got a little bit more happening now and it's a little bit weird
how this works.
So we're going to have to kind of
Yeah, so basically the other thing that we have here is since gravity
is letting the guy go down, we're not actually moving the guy down.
We're just setting that ground.
And letting him sink through it.
It's really more like letting him sink into the stairwell, which is
why if you run over it quickly, you don't actually go down a little
and so we also probably want to treat it like a real stairwell and not
have that Ridiculousness happen, right?
Because that's just kind of dumb but that's kind of fun.
So that's interesting.
All right, I need to go to the Q&A.
I'm kind of interested in here.
Like I said, it's some of some parts I'm going to get a little carried
away with because like I said, if
Something that I don't normally work with on a day-to-day basis, then
it actually becomes kind of intriguing to me to and and I'm liable to
kind of get carried away.
So we'll put it, we'll put it off, we'll put it off, we'll start the
Q&A and and we'll pick it up tomorrow, but I'm interested.
It's going to be fun tomorrow.
And in fact, I have to wait that long now that I think about it
because it's Friday, right?
And that's a morning stream normally.
So tomorrow, it'll be nine.
I want to wait that long only 12 hours between now and then so that's
good.
It's the familiar going to be programmed to be able to go through the
stairwell or instantly teleported to the floor.
I feel like the familiar should have to go through the stairwell.
I think.
I mean, I don't know.
I feel like everyone should have to use the stairs unless they can
fly.
Like, if the familiar since it's sort of flying, maybe it can fly up
and down, like, if there's holes between regions or something, I don't
know.
I really, I don't know the answer that question.
That's a very good question and I don't know the answer to it.
So who knows.
We'll see when we get there.
What are we going to do priority for which Sprite is in front and in
the background?
That'll be.
That's so you said, I don't know what that's called.
That's called sorting.
Really is all or occlusion.
I know there's a number things you could call it, but basically, we're
going to do that when we get to the renderer probably if you wanted to
do it it's not particularly hard, right?
All you'd have to do is sort your entities by, you know.
And in fact you don't even have to write it because I
You know, we don't we're not really supposed to use Library, so we'll
write the sword ourselves but if you didn't want to, you could
actually use qsort to do it.
There's actually one built into the sea in the sea Library.
So if you look here, this thing will run a quick sort for you.
And so if you want to do it ahead of when I do it, all you have to do
is instead of actually rendering the stuff.
So I've already even
Set it up basically for you do it.
What happens?
Is this push bitmap stuff.
You know, we've got this piece group thing, that's just like a stopgap
thing.
Eventually what will do is will push all of the things you want to
render.
So they'll just be like an array and all the things that need to get
rendered, go into it and then they get sorted, right?
And so basically, that, push that piece where you're pushing things
on.
You just push those into a giant list, sort it, and then draw them.
That's all you have to do and then you're done.
So it's really, really easy.
The only reason we haven't done it yet is because I have to teach you
how to write a sorting routine, which is, you know, a sort of a couple
day thing to talk about and go through and whatever.
And so, you know, since it really isn't germane to the design, if it's
such a simple, basic idea.
It's not something that we've had to address in order to do the rest
of our work.
You mentioned that you'll be able to attack from below below above.
We were able to do that in the stairwell.
I think I said, I didn't want you to do that.
I mean, I want you to be able to, if there's something that's two
floors.
High like a giant boss monster, maybe you could do that, right?
But I don't want to, I don't want there to be like attacking things
below from up above because it always felt weird.
So, unless there's a special thing that you like drop or if you push
something off a ledge,
That would be fine.
But I just, I don't like hitting downward.
It always feels bad to me.
And so hitting only happens like in the plane, in my opinion.
So there's a question about if I already talked about programming
entity systems, no, we haven't yet.
We talked about how we're doing our spatial handling of entities.
How we're doing our update, handling of entities and also now how
we're doing our sort of a collision prostaglandins which is sort of
what we're doing.
We're doing a little of that right now as well but we have not
actually talked about entity systems or how entities like really
interact with each other.
That will be a ways.
On the line, actually, because what I want to do is when we start that
that will be sort of the point of no return on game stuff.
Meaning, when we start the entity system, we will go straight through
to the end of the game.
So, we'll have all of our engine pieces in place except the entity
system and the energy system will be developed concurrently with the
game and be expanded, kind of overtime.
Does the scope of this application include moving environments?
Yes.
So we will we will probably do a very significant upgrade of the
Collision system.
When we decide that we're done with all of the sort of featuring sorts
of stuff, so moving environments, could be something that we put in.
In fact, we could, we could sort of play with that.
I could put that on the to-do list here of things that we should play
with.
Which we could do kind of, you know, moving things, pushing other
things.
It's called that.
Yeah.
Will the game have color grading?
Yes, we could totally have color grading.
The blue and black cloak, the
Where's may appear as two other colors and some lighting conditions?
I'm telling you that has nothing to do with lighting conditions,
though.
That's, that's just the internet is messing with you.
That's about surface reflectance, which is a totally different thing.
It's not color grading.
That was not a white balance problem that was a reflectance plus
white, white balance problem because something blue cannot turn
something blue cannot appear gold
Through white balance alone, right?
That's like not that's not going to happen.
I mean maybe if the white balance was full banana cakes, it would have
to be the like worst white balance in the history of time, I would
think but maybe not, I don't know.
Maybe there's some really bad cameras out there.
What are the peace groups and how are they used useful for our current
use in Sprite rendering.
So the idea is there sort of a halfway house at the moment for our
rendering?
Because when we go to do the renderer basically what'll be happening,
is essentially what you see Happening Here with these peace groups.
There won't be a group anymore per say it'll just the piece group will
actually, just be a little thing that allows you to quickly assemble
an entity together by sticking Parts onto.
Right, like right now, we had three parts to the hero, right?
There's a torso, the cape, and the head.
And so, it's just a little thing that says, I'm putting together an
entity, here's where the entity is.
I don't want to keep having to add that offset in the peace groups
doing that, and it's also recording the things that need to get
rendered.
But in the future it won't do that.
Second thing we probably won't call it a piece group anymore.
Either necessarily will call it like a coordinate system or something,
I don't know.
But in the renderer the renderer will actually be the thing that's
recording everything that needs to get drawn.
On and then it will handle the sorting and coloring and all that stuff
that needs to happen.
Can you please somehow Uhn blank?
Swear has been removed, the net coding for DayZ, standalone and finish
what Dean Rocket Hall gave up on.
So, I will say, first of all, that I have never played or even seen
DayZ standalone.
I do not know who Dean Rocket Hall is, and I am the last person you
want to go in and fix someone else's code.
Because usually, I just get really grumpy and complain a lot.
If you want someone to parachute in and fix someone else's code,
there's really one man for that job, ladies and gentlemen, and that is
Mike's Arden.
So that is the person you should be asking because he is the guy who
does exactly that he like just parachutes into absolutely abysmal
non-working code and turns it into something that functions.
Well, enemies, follow you upstairs are down.
Yeah, I don't see why not, if they do, how will the space outside?
The camerawork should work exactly like the space inside the camera.
Not sure what you mean by that.
How will you handle sprite animation?
Are you using a library?
And have you ever heard of the spine, 2D skeletal animation framework?
I have in passing heard of the spine?
2D skeletal animation framework, but I've never actually looked at it
for sprite animation, will probably be doing it mostly procedurally.
But if for some reason we decide that we can't do it, some of it
procedurally.
I was considering doing like a little converter for spriter so you
could make them
Writer and output them.
But I think I strongly suspect will be able to do everything
procedurally.
So I think every all of the animation will probably be able to be
procedural.
And that's what I would like to do because that allows me to teach a
lot more programming.
This is not, you know, an animation.
This is not an animation class so I would rather teach you guys how to
program animations.
Then teach you how to make them in a tool and read them.
Because that's pretty boring and pretty obvious how to do too.
Who is that guy?
Who is Mike, sartin, Mike sartin know if you can find him.
Is this guy?
No, that's not him.
That's some other Mike certain.
I don't know where he is.
He's might, it's just Mike's art on Twitter.
I don't know why I can't find him.
There, there he is.
That's him.
And this is him to finding bugs in the Linux kernel.
He was one of the main guys who did there it is.
That's him.
So he's he's like a guy, he works at valve, he still work at Red, he
did it, a bunch of steam, the steam Linux stuff, he fixed, like the
the bunch of stuff in the Team Fortress 2 server.
That was busted, he fixed a bunch of stuff in the DOTA server is like
he parachutes into a lot of stuff when people are like we don't know
what's going on.
It's like I got this so you know, he's the guy who came to mind where
I just like
if you, if you're going to try and convince someone to save you on a
Jacked it ain't me because I just get grumpy and complain a lot and
that doesn't fix the problem, right?
I'm mostly the guy who writes stuff from scratch for totally new code,
right?
I'm that guy, I'm not the guy who comes in and holds his nose and then
like actually figures out what's wrong?
And fixes at all.
So Jack krauser, I'm still not sure what you mean.
When you say I mean with there being different floors, will it be
different I'm assuming not
Yeah, I mean my conceptualization of the world so far is that we want
to make it as rich as possible just because it's harder to program.
So if enemies can follow you up and down stairs or decide to go up and
down stairs themselves, that's just harder programming for us.
So I think we should do it because it forces me to have to do more
stuff.
Which lets you guys see how to do more stuff and how I approach it,
right?
So that's
He wiii make decisions that way.
I don't think there's necessarily gameplay reasons why enemies have to
go up and down stairs.
And if we found that we were taking too much time and we're have to
cut features, we could cut something like that, right?
So that's fine too but it's just that's usually the way I look at it.
It's like well is it easier or harder to program if they can go up and
down stairs, it's harder to program at the enemies.
Can go downstairs.
So let's make them go up and down stairs.
Can you run this game?
So some of us can see its current state.
Well, we haven't really done any game stuff yet so it's not
particularly interesting and I probably would have to switch to single
level to do that.
Really all we did is is we're just working on our spatial partition
stuff and our enemy collisions and that's our stuff we're basically
working on the engine.
So so there's not really a game to show per se, but if we were to take
out
Sort of the the the up and down stuff, I guess for lack of return, for
lack of a better term.
We should probably make an if for that, but basically if we were going
to do that, we would have to do.
Let's see where we do.
The three thing, we'd have to basically if zero this out, right.
We'd have to do something like this.
We did this before because right now we're making multi-floor things.
So we do that.
I think so.
It could only ever pick the other one.
I'm not sure if that's right.
We'll see.
So basically yeah, all we were doing was we were just trying to make
some basic stuff.
So we started out, we've made some tile map stuff and then we extended
our town map.
So now we don't have a tile map anymore.
We actually have entities, but we left them in sort of a tile map.
He sort of configuration.
They don't actually have to be there.
You can put stuff anywhere you want.
We haven't really put much art assets in.
So we're drawing trees, even though?
Yeah, we're just drawing trees and anyway, you know, we can make
rooms and walk between them and all that sort of stuff.
We haven't done the renderer yet.
This is basically, we wrote a temporary renderer.
So that's why things don't sort.
For example, you notice, if I go behind this tree, like, that doesn't
make any sense.
I should be in front of it.
That was the thing we were talking about earlier on the Q&A about
sorting, right?
We added projectiles in and we tested that you can only have one of
them and that's where stuff we added hit points in.
So, you know, you can attack things.
I think there's a monster back here.
Oh this this little guy we met do follows you around, right?
That was just testing having like a familiar, you know, kind of thing.
So you can, you know, attack things and they lose, hit points,
whatever.
But again like this isn't game stuff.
Yet what we're doing, since the point of the stream is, do everything
from scratch.
It's the opposite of go grab unity and drop some stuff in, right?
We're not doing that.
What we're trying to do is do the whole game from scratch.
So so people can see how to write a renderer, how could write a sound
system, a music system, like all of these things.
And so, what we've been doing here is working
on our architecture.
And I've been trying to show everyone how you build all of the parts
of the game, and how they interact, and we've making pretty good
progress on that.
We've still got a ways to go, though.
You can kind of see, we've got our little to-do list here, right?
Which is the stuff we want to work on.
We want to make a little debugging system, that's our next big thing
will probably do.
Then we want to do some audio mixing in that sort of stuff.
We want to asset streaming put in some metagame stuff, figure out how
the world gets generated and
Some AI pathfinding in fighting, then we will do our main game passage
basically, like doing animation.
Figure out how we want that to work, then doing the real renderer and
then starting on the full final game.
Like that's the code that ships from then on.
Right.
And so you know that's why it says we only do an hour a day so it's
very slow, you know?
Right now you know we're on Day 70 for that's only 74 hours of coding.
It's not even to work weeks yet.
Right?
If you work a 40-hour week, we haven't even done 2, weeks worth of
programming.
So it's not a whole lot of programming, but I've been pretty happy
with where we've been at so, you know, I'm pretty happy with it, but
like I said, there's no game to show yet so you know, come back in 50
days, they'll be more.
okay, so you know how we have the camera space and then there's a
space outside that we
See, but entities are still moving when we need to edit that code to
make it work on vertical floors.
It's okay.
If you don't get it I may be thinking too far in know, so the answer
is that there's no difference now between the code that runs in the
place you can see and the and in the space that you can't see.
The only difference is, we will probably update the space.
You can't see less frequently, right?
But the codes the same.
So when we write the code for Monsters, moving up and down the
stairwells, when you can see them, that's the same.
I'm code they'll use when you can't see them.
So we won't really have to do anything there.
Probably.
Now if we have to optimize, what happens when you can't see them,
because we need to because it's too slow and we need to get that
through put up for the non-visible stuff, then we might have to bake
special concessions, right?
But until we hit that performance, that hard performance limit, it'll
just be running the same code so we don't have to worry about it.
If it works on camera, it will work off camera.
Would be used to fix discrete animation for moving up and down stairs.
I'll link to the past, or with the goal, be to make the movement
seamless, seamless.
Absolutely.
I hate it.
When we, when the movement of my guy is not under my direct control.
The Kira Sprite will be under your Direct Control at all times, unless
like a monster has grabbed you and and you are not able to move
because you're being like restrained or something.
But like none of these candidates.
Shouldn't on senses like you'll always be in control of the guy
because it feels awful.
I hate it when you walk up to a door and like plays this, like go
through the door animation, especially if I didn't want to go through
the door and now I have to wait for that.
Then I have to go into the door.
And wait, again, when I should just be able to like push back and not
go through the door.
So yeah, definitely not always seamless.
That's like a hard requirement always seamless.
How much lines of code you have at the moment.
So, Sean blow gave us a thing that we could use to count it, but it's
not very large.
Oops.
So how you do it?
It's pretty small 4,500.
So we're we're averaging something like, you know, I guess.
What's that like 50 lines of an hour, something like that.
Not particularly much.
I'm like I said, I gotta explain everything.
So we don't, we don't code very fast on the street.
Alright, that is the end.
It looks like the end of the Q and A as well.
Good deal people.
So, yeah.
So tomorrow, I think we clearly have our work specified for us.
It's time to like play around with that code and get it working.
Well, and nicely.
We're going to have to do something.
I should, I should put this back to the state that it was in before we
did our little quote unquote demo there.
And also, I suppose, I should do inside that same region.
We had the, did we actually
Didn't we didn't we have our our should Collide thing is kind of
busted out yet.
So we have this right here that we need to think about is, well,
right?
And we need to figure out how we want to do that.
So I guess what we need to say tomorrow is basically like let's let's
go ahead and
let's go ahead and say move this back up here.
We got to sort through our list, may be tomorrow's, a Friday to side
B, good day to do it.
What I would like to do is say 3D Collision detection, working
properly should be something, we should go ahead and actually give our
guy's Z ranges basically.
So let's do that.
Let's do that tomorrow.
So
That brings us to the end of our handmade hero.
I'm going to close things down here, and we'll save our Blackboard.
There we go.
Down down.
So, thank you everyone for joining me for another episode of handmade
hero.
It's been a pleasure coding with you.
As always, if you would like to follow along at home, you can always
pre-order the game and it comes with a source code, which you can
download every night after I'm done coding.
And of course, we have videos covering every last line of it so you
can learn about absolutely anything that we've done so far and play
around with it yourself.
It also comes to the test assets I use on the Stream So if you want to
do that, head over to handmade here at org and the handy dandy
pre-order button, will hook you up.
We also have a patreon if you just want to
With the video series, because you are a nice sort of nice, sort of
folks.
We have a patreon, you can subscribe to that's also linked off there.
We have a tweet bot.
Now that tweets the schedule.
It you.
And that's a pretty handy way to keep informed of when the stream is
if you want to know ahead of time instead of having to wait for the
twitch emails, which, you know kind of are at the last minute, the
tweetbot will tell you what the schedule for the week is and what the
schedule for the day is, so that's pretty handy.
And then there's the news and forums site, which has a bunch of great
stuff on it Community maintained its got some good things on there
like ports to Mac and Linux, if you want to follow along on a
different platform, you can do that there.
There's an episode guide.
That's annotated really nice.
And there's a place to ask questions like a forums thing you can use
and I answer questions on there as do other people in the community
who are experienced programmers.
So it's pretty good.
So I highly recommend checking it out.
If you try to learn from the stream,
tomorrow will be early morning, I
It's Friday, right?
It's a Friday.
And that means a stream is that 9 a.m.
Pacific Standard time.
So I don't know if those of you who have, you know, a little breakfast
coding you might want to do, can join me for that.
Should be pretty fun.
So, I hope to see you tomorrow, if not have a wonderful weekend and
I'll see you back here.
Oh no, I won't.
And that'll be it for for a week.
Because I said we'd take next week off, if I remember correctly.
Is that right?
First week in March?
Arch.
Yeah, first remarks.
So, this will be the first week that I don't see you.
Well, I'll miss you, but we'll be back here.
The second week of March, and I hope to see you all back then.
All right?
Take it.
Easy, everyone.