Everybody and welcome to handmade hero.
Sure, we could complete game live on stream.
I don't know that there's anything particularly magical to say before
today's episode.
We just have to now go through and clean up the lighting code and
debug it, which is what I was going to do yesterday and we actually
ended up doing a lot more clean up, then I was originally planning to
do, but it was just like getting to the point where the code was just
too many things.
Things in one place, there was just so much stuff that we had tried
and it was still running in line.
I just like we're going to have to clean this up a little bit.
So that's exactly what we did.
And you can now kind of see the structure of the code is changing a
little bit and I'm going to go ahead and copy these functions
signatures out to the outside just so they can be viewed a little bit
clearer so we can see what's happening in terms of the actual sort of
flow of using the lighting system and I think if I'm not mistaken,
we've now got it down to the point.
Where you're to me?
Where you're a lot more explicit about what you're actually going to
be doing.
And so it's much clearer how the Lighting systems actually going.
So you can see here the way that we currently have, it structured
where you set up the lighting region by telling it what's going on
here.
You then push the lighting render values on if you're trying to do.
Rendering you update the lighting.
This is after you've already done everything.
And then you go to push lighting, debug values if you actually want to
put like, the debug lines on the screen and stuff like that.
Now, the problem that just mean that we have here is just that set up.
Lighting region is something that I'd rather not have to call my goal,
would have been to just have one call that's like update lighting, but
the problem with that, and the reason that we can't really do that is
because even though the lighting system would work just fine, it's
this pushed lighting.
Our values, that's the problem.
So, the way this works is, you can see it sets these light bounds here
and does the enable lighting call.
Now, anyone could do these calls, but they, so there's not any
particular reason that the lighting system has to be involved.
But the key thing here is there's this voxel wrecked, and that Foxhole
wrecked.
We only know after we've updated, the lighting system.
So that's really the reason why we have to have this two-stage process
is because we need to set up these light bounds prior to doing any of
the actual pushes that push the entities.
In the system on, right?
So that's the problem we've got.
And it's not a problem in the sense of like there's nothing wrong with
the code as it is right now.
So it's not something we have to fix but it's just something that
would make the code simpler.
If we could get rid of it, right, if I could somehow make it so that
we weren't having to do these two steps, we could just call One Step.
Well, that's just better, right?
And so I'd like to figure out some way to do that, and unfortunately,
at the moment I don't really know how I would necessarily do that.
So the problem.
Yeah, that I think we're going to have is just like do I want to try
to do anything particularly specific like specific with that or do I
want to try to like you know leave it as it is and just like live with
that that aspect of it and I don't really know which one of those two
I want to do.
I'm not entirely sure so we'll take a brief look at it now to me.
And we'll go from there.
So when I do set light bounds, what this is actually doing,
oops.
Got my keyboard is all.
Aligned weird.
Here we go.
So when I get set light bounds, what you can see, is that this is
setting.
This thing called the render setup and the render setup basically
says, all the stuff that has to happen.
For a particular.
It basically tells you what has to happen for all of the things that
get pushed on after it.
So if we set the lighting region,
And then we go ahead and for each entity we push on it's sort of
underneath that lighting region.
It's had that lighting region set.
Then it will be lit properly.
If we don't do this, then none of those entities know how to look up
there.
Lighting in the light voxel.
Now, there's other ways we could potentially do this because there's
only one light Bound in use ever.
We don't really compute multiple lighting and we don't ever expect to
do that.
So we could do something slightly different which is to say, we could
just make the lighting bounds be something Global.
And if we did that, that would probably solve this problem and it
might be something that we actually do want to do, you know?
I'm not sure which way we want to do it, but it's entirely possible.
That's like the sensible thing, right?
And so if, for example, we take a look Jimmy
if we take a look at handmade,
And handmade platform.
There's well, I guess I could just jump right to payment or commands.
If we take a look at game render commands, what you can see here is,
you know, things like the light Atlas, and the lighting box, like,
occluders in that stuff are just out here in the game render commands.
We could choose to just put the light voxel in there, right?
And if we did that, then you could just set it at the end.
And you'd be done.
The problem with this is it does make the renderer a little less
generic meaning.
You now couldn't have multiple lighting regions.
but it seems to me like that's a pretty
Okay.
Change like we don't expect to ever have to do that.
So it seems like we could just make it so that this is something that
gets set once and never changes.
So for example, if we took a look at the opengl right side of things
where this actually happens,
it's actually in here and I don't actually remember what that's called
but I guess I'll just look at the code because I know where the code
is, but the voxel dim part of things, right?
Then when you look in here at how this actually gets set up, we should
be able to see, just pretty clearly how that gets dealt with.
We would pass the setup to wherever the actual dispatch is.
So right?
It's here.
So what you can see here, you know, ignoring the clipping rectifier to
these this here, what you can see is that when we actually go to use
the program, and we're going to go use specifically the the Z bias
program, which is this one.
You can see in here that it gets the Vox Min corner and the M5 total
dim, it gets those out of the setup and it could just as easily get
those out of something else.
There's nothing stopping.
yes, from just pulling those out of the game render commands, instead,
so,
You know?
I mean, it just, it seems
It seems compelling, right?
It seems like a good idea.
So I may go ahead and try that.
What I'm going to do here is I'm going to go over to the game, rental
commands.
I'm going to move those over and just see if I like that, right?
So, let's go to the render setup and let's just pull these two things
out.
So, you know, rather than having them be part of this particular piece
of information for the lighting bands, instead, I'm just going to put
them, you know, here in the game render commands.
and,
I mean, I guess one other thing that I'm not sure about is
You know, does this have a problem, will this cause a problem in terms
of like transforms?
I don't think so because we only ever set it once.
So we're never updating it based on any other transform information.
So I think it's just fine, right?
Like the lighting bounds should just be okay.
Again, I'm a little nervous about this but I just don't see any other
way to flatten the lighting into just like,
Straight update call.
So if I move this out here so we have like a lighting voxel Min corner
and a lighting voxel inverse total Dimension.
Those two parameters that are used now and you have to get them from
the game render commands.
I should be able to change the way that this setup stuff.
Works to make that be the case, right?
And so now when you call set light bounds, it wouldn't actually push a
new set up onto the stack.
Instead, what it would do is just
Get in the game render commands.
And I believe the, you know, the render group itself, it just has that
pointer.
I mean, here it is.
So I can even leave this call.
You know, I think I'm not going to just because I don't really want it
to look like it's working in a push fashion.
So, I think what I might do is just say, look, you call it to set it
on the actual game render commands.
So you kind of have to be doing that, right?
I'm just not sure I'm going to leave it this way for now, and then if
I don't like it, I'll change it back.
So we'll go ahead and get that out of the render group and then we'll
set these two things in there.
And then all we have to do is change it.
So that that information is now coming from their game render commands
instead of the setup.
So, in here, we just need to know what those would be, what those
would do.
And so we need in here, the game render.
Tends to actually be passed.
And then in here, we would get those like this.
And that's the entirety of the change.
So it's a pretty easy thing.
Like, there's nothing magical to it, right?
And I'm assuming that we just have this on hand, because that's the
whole thing we're drawing, right?
So it's just that it's already there.
It's just something that we weren't using before, for that particular
pass.
So, what I might do now is try to flip back to the extent that I can
and
The old system real quick.
So in here, where we've got the lighting, use old KD.
I'm going to leave that on lighting, use for raised, I don't actually
know.
We actually using that.
Is that what's actually happening?
Yes, so I should be able to still compile this and make this work the
old way and I figured this would be the best way to get to make sure
that this works properly before we go any further.
Right.
Because we're making some changes here and we have to figure out like
you know, we have to debug the changes that I've made so far.
It looks like compute walk table is still running, which I suppose is
fine.
Although, it looks like I've got a bug in it.
Let me take a look at there.
Yeah, so we're not actually updating cost, so we want to do a plus
plus cost here.
Here we go.
looks like,
That's weird.
So, looks like we do.
Didn't actually.
It looks like we didn't actually if that that one out either.
So we probably want to if deaf this out real quick because, you know,
if we're not using the for Ray's version, we don't need this stuff.
Right.
So I'm just going to go ahead and knock that out as well.
So, this is
Lighting use for raised.
So if we aren't doing that, then this path is.
And again and again, this is just so I can do some like debugging with
the old version first to make sure I didn't break anything there and
then I can look at the new version separately, right?
Okay.
Yeah because you can see there's some busted stuff, right?
Yeah, I'm saying.
So we want to go in and and fix that first before we go any further,
but that's but so I just wanted that to make sure that was correct
also.
We're building with O2.
I mean, I would be right now, so we should probably build with O2 for
the moment as I'm doing this changes.
All right, so yeah.
So what we want to do here is is just we just need to fix the old
lighting and make sure that that's working, okay, with the new changes
that are streamlined and then try to pull everything out, just so it's
roughly correct, right?
So let's go ahead and go through that process.
So now that we don't have to do that set Lighting in any particular
way, I catch should be able to now make it so that this is a one call
system which is what I wanted.
In the first place so update lighting can now just be the only call
that we actually have.
And so up here where we do set up lighting region I can actually sort
of just weld these two together into single, you know, a single
operation basically.
And so, when I'm doing that, I just need to make sure that we have
sort of all of the information that we might actually need.
And you can see here like of the stuff that gets passed.
Basically, we just need this additional set of data to me.
Pass to the system and then we just have sort of one giant monolithic
call that updates everything at once.
And the reason that I want that is because
I would like ideally to have one entry point to the lighting system
you call it.
It does all of the lighting work and then it returns to you.
So that it's very clear, the lifetime of everything and what needs to
happen.
I didn't really like the multi call nature of it and I just didn't
think that was particularly useful, right?
So, I think what I want to do here is just say, get rid of that, we're
just going to have one update lighting call.
The update lighting call is the only thing you actually call.
And then there's a push lighting, render values call.
And you can tell it whether or not you want include debug, right?
And you know maybe I don't know, maybe we don't even have that, maybe
the put maybe that particular call actually just it.
It's going to do debugger not based on how I have configured it.
You'd the caller doesn't really get a say in that, right?
So that's what this would look like.
And presumably if the lighting is not enabled.
Then we just don't do this.
Now at that point it also kind of seems like, I don't know what
lighting enabled really means at this point, like I'm not sure what
we're actually trying to say with lighting enabled because it's kind
of just seems
Sort of like an unnecessary flag like if you didn't want lighting just
don't call this at that point, right?
So I suspect we probably can just get rid of that.
So I think we can remove one of the inputs, right?
Because you just, you just wouldn't call it at that point.
And that's all there is to it.
So I think that's all we really need there.
And so we'll just assume that if you know, if your
Calling that you want lighting.
If you didn't want lighting you just wouldn't call it.
It doesn't really need to do any kind of tracking of that on its own.
Now, my understanding on the fundamental unit side of things is, I
kind of thought that the world's knew what the fundamental unit was,
but I guess maybe it doesn't, which is a little bit weird because you
would think that the world's would have the information about what the
fundamental unit was.
And so I'm a little weirded out by the fact that it doesn't seem to
know the answer to that question.
And I would like to know why we didn't do it that way.
So I'm just going to quickly take a look at the fundamental unit here
and I'm going to see what's going on.
You can see here that in World mode, we set the fundamental unit, and
then we create the world's, you know, we just pass it, the chunk
demand M.
I guess the idea is that the world doesn't care what the fundamental
unit is and that's why we don't know, but
I don't know, it seems like the kind of thing the world should
probably know, eventually, I won't change that now because it's not
really the area.
The code were working on.
I don't want to make decisions in that part of the code right now, so
I guess we'll just like leave it.
But you know, you see why I'm a little bit?
Like I do that really necessary.
Okay, so now we have an update, letting call the update, letting call
should do literally everything.
And what I'm going to do is I'm just going to kind of jump back over
to the code.
That's calling that this stuff.
Obviously doesn't need to be here either and I'm going to pull that
part out.
Since it's always actually going to do this here.
Yeah.
All of this stuff can just be
Left up like so.
And then really, what we want to do here is just have these calls,
make a little more sense.
So you can see this stuff here.
Now, in theory, shouldn't actually have to occur.
Here, we should be able to go down to just where we actually finish
the lighting up, which is here.
And in this particular case, now, what we should be able to do is
replace the debug part with this and
and update lighting.
Now, we'll just take additional precautions.
Going to put it, then we won't have to call this set lighting region
anymore.
So when we call update lighting, we pass the solution, the fundamental
unit, which is here.
The spec Atlas and the diffuse.
Atlas, it looks like these are in the opposite order here for some
reason which would be very bad.
I wonder if that's part of the reason why stuff was looking weird, we
have of the world needs to get past which is this
We have the same origin, pee.
Which is this and the lighting Center, which is this.
And then we've got the occluders.
I think that's everything.
And the compiler will certainly tell us if it's not.
All right.
So now we just need to make sure that the push lighting render values
call.
I guess actually does.
What we needed to.
This is the one thing that it actually needs to do enable lighting.
What does that do?
So render group light bounds.
What are what is the light bounds for do we know?
I don't know.
Route lightbox.
I have no idea what this does.
Why do we have this?
Does anyone know?
Does anyone know what this does?
That is literally, the only thing it does is set that value for no
reason.
So,
Dad, I do not know what the point is of that.
So what we really want here is just like
Lighting enabled, I guess.
I think that's what this should have looked like,
Yeah.
So that's probably all we actually want and then enable Lighting in
the world mode stuff just goes up here at where we turn it on.
So some are up here before we actually do anything.
We probably
To turn on the lighting.
So like, you know, maybe here,
I don't actually know to what extent this stuff wants to be here.
Particularly again, this Loop probably should get sort of streamlined
at some point, but sort of a separate issue, but we would just do an
enable lighting here and then probably disable lighting here, right?
So after all this stuff happens, we do false.
Now eventually, we should actually use that.
We don't even use this right now but, you know, it's kind of a
separate issue.
When we sort of do but we don't do the right thing with it.
I guess is what I would say.
So now we're using we're doing the streamlined version and now we just
have to actually go through and make this not be buggy, right?
So I'll so it's weirdly fast.
For some reason and I don't know why.
I'm guessing that maybe the bugginess of it, made it run much quicker
or something it's like way faster than it was for
So that's a bit weird.
But anyway, so this is much better.
This is kind of more what I would like.
And so I'm going to go ahead and copy these directly in here because
these don't need to get pulled out anymore.
so, I'm going to go ahead and just grab those this way, and
Now, that we have a single way just to call the lighting system and
say, do the entire update.
Now, I can focus on that side of the code more directly and make sure
it works, right?
So now when we do update lighting, what you can see here is, we've got
initialization stuff that we want to do and that stuff can all live in
here.
We then have sort of like update stuff that involves figuring out, how
the, how the voxels shift over time and that's this code here, right?
And then we've got sort of our, in fact, this build a few slight Maps.
Now, we actually know where we would cash that we would cash it right
here, right?
So that actually gets better, too.
We then have like, the internal lighting core stuff, which runs here
and, you know, other stuff for we do the the boxes and the occluders
and stuff.
So, I think probably what we would want is to maybe like I think we
maybe want to start to streamline this out a little bit too.
This is probably not working.
In the most efficient way possible.
So if I take a look at internal lighting core, now I don't know that
we actually want this to be separate, this could just be its own
thing.
That happens out of line.
Kind of I want to say
I want to say that this can just be welded in now, right?
So, you know what you would do here?
Is you just say
Well yeah, don't know.
So the question is internal lighting.
Core is just something that we may or may not want to update in some
way based on how we are.
How we're doing the external testing so I may leave that for now.
And I think what I'll do is I'll just document this routine as we go
through it, and we'll kind of go from there.
So, what I would say is, you know, this first part here,
Is see if any settings have changed or if we've never been run before
and initialize all our tables.
So this is basically, you know, just something that initializes the
lookup tables, we actually need and instead of doing these at compile
time by making like a meta program, that generates them which we do
for the sampling spheres in most
says we just generate them on the Fly and the reason we do that is
because that way we can change these values at runtime if we want to
and it will re compute them
so I think that's fine and
sorry, I'm still feeling pretty sick.
It's been like four or five weeks of being somewhat ill.
I'm not really sure what exactly it is.
Anyway, we compute walk table here and we do, you know, the basic
stuff we need for doing our grid, March lookups at the moment, that's
not in play, the diffuse light map build we use in all the cases so
that one is the same.
But otherwise, I think.
Pretty straightforward.
Yeah, I would say that probably build a few slight Maps.
I would put it to do on this and say this should probably dynamically
allocate the map just like compute walk table and so we can fix that
one.
But at the moment, I don't want to touch anything until we return
delighting in the old system to working properly because I don't
actually want to introduce any
Or possible failure points as we go.
So coming here through here, you can see us setting up the sampling
spheres like so and setting up the fundamental unit.
You know, it occurs to me that I'm not.
100% sure if the sampling spheres are still the same.
I wonder if there's problems with that, but that's sort of a separate
thing.
We can look at all of this stuff.
I think is probably not particularly relevant, like Vox seldom
obviously is computed the same way.
It used to be, it's just one Fender fundamental unit per side, the
spatial cell count here is not used in the old system so it shouldn't
matter.
Should only be this Atlas grid here that matters.
So it's the these two values only
I'll use that should matter, and we're getting that one right off the
spec Atlas.
So it should be okay.
When we come through here, we look up those values and we use them for
doing the same computations we were doing before.
So, here, we basically just say, look, where would we actually be?
In the voxel, you know, how far do we need to move the voxel to
account for where we are, is what this is doing?
And I assume this should just work fine.
I don't actually know why it's doing some of the things that's doing
for example.
If we already have the inverse voxel cell Dimension, I don't know why
we're actually dividing by the Vox seldom there.
It's a little weird, right?
Like, like this is
Is this?
Right.
So not sure why that was not just using the value to already had
probably because again, we hadn't really streamlined this code ever.
So we didn't actually know
That we were being redundant there but anyway once we figure out
what's going on here, then we update whatever the last origin P was
and we look to see if we need to move the thing.
We call the block copy to move the voxels around which all seems
pretty good, right?
So that's the initialization, this part of the routine here.
Is update the alignment of the voxels.
In voxels to the view and I don't think we changed anything here
though.
So, I'm not totally sure.
I'm not totally sure why we would have been seeing weird flickering
artifacts there because we did have some.
I don't know.
It may not come across very well on the recording so let me kind of
show you what I mean.
So when we were running so you can see that there's two things that
are happening.
One, is that the lighting computations wrong now?
And it used to be correct.
And the other one is that as you move, do you see that flash?
So it's like the camera is one off there and so there's a couple of
places that could be coming from, it could actually be coming from the
world mode.
So in the world mode, this Cameo Simulation Center, we may need to
save that across the boundary.
Because this update here will change it.
So what we may need to do is say like
Back where we snap the lighting Center.
We probably want to fix this.
So we probably want to say lighting Sim Center.
And pass.
That just to fix that, that error.
Oops.
Not sure.
Yeah, there we go.
Okay.
So I'm guessing that will fix that problem.
Oh whoops, no, what happened there?
There we go.
And so now I would expect to be smooth everywhere and it is so.
So now we're totally good on that.
That's where that bug came from.
So, now, what we need to look at though is just like, why is the ray
casting and or voxel stuff so strange, right?
Like something bizarre is happening there.
And there could be any number of reasons for that.
And so I think at this point, now we want to sort of focus on their
product code, but let me just finish doing this.
So here's the update alignment code, right?
And I don't know why the temporary NE thing starts here probably
because that's where that code was.
I think I'll just start it here so that anyone can use it anywhere
they want to.
Because it is the temporary Reign after all.
And then in here, where we do
The next stuff.
Let's do update.
Lighting voxels.
I guess our update.
Maybe what's called update voxel values?
And I could also break this into two stages because one of them is
sort of a little bit different here.
So we could say
Update box of values and record statistics.
So, up here, we're basically saying like, you know, determine the
blend setup.
So we're left with something here, that then I'd like to take a look
at, which is the boxes.
Like, I'm not thrilled with how the boxes flow through the system.
So so now you know what I'd like to do is maybe take a little bit of a
look at.
I mean I guess you know, let's not do that yet.
Let me actually go to bug why we're getting wrong lighting results
first and then I want to come back and take a look at the boxes.
Essentially, what I want to do here is say I kind of like this.
This to not be stored anymore.
So I'd like that to kind of go away.
And we can start to move towards a.
It'll be real easy to do when we move to the new Ray Caster.
So I might put it off till then but eventually that, that should also
happen anyway.
So, yeah, so when we do build spatial partition for lighting, I don't
think we really messed with that.
The split KD stuff, we didn't end up wanting to do and I'm pretty sure
we're not going to do it.
We can always go back.
You know, we've got all the old source code, we can go back and re put
it in if we want to.
But I think what I'd rather do here is just say like look, let's now
just use the two versions The
Ask this old version we have and the new one, right?
So, we'll do if lighting use for a raise and then we'll do the else
clause and we'll do this build here, right?
And we'll just yank split Katie entirely.
So, split Katie goes away.
It's not actually working anymore.
And then we just have to focus on the
The actual rate, Caster think and pull anything that we needed there,
right?
Yeah.
Okay, so then we've got kind of multiple paths in here.
And what I'll do is I'm just going to
Remove some of them.
Debug wise, we may still want to do this especially now when we're
trying to do some debugging so I'm not going to pull that yet.
The if lighting use old KD I'm going to actually let it just run that
and then I'm just going to remove the else Clause.
So this whole thing is going to go away.
Like so.
I think, what did I do there?
How come that didn't?
What did I do wrong there?
Hold on a second.
I don't want to accidentally push.
Okay, so it looks like I just wasn't
Cutting it quite right.
So right there.
Down to their.
And so this is again just me like pruning down the code so I can, you
know, there was just so many things kind of that we kept putting in
for testing and eventually it gets to the point where it's very hard
to work with.
Right?
So we have an if use for a raise and then here I guess we would have
this still occurs regardless and then we would drop down to the else
case.
So I guess this is actually how we would do it, right?
Yeah, and so this code has not been changed.
It's still updating the spec textiles the same way, but I don't know
to what extent.
We may have changed a few things in here while we were doing some of
the optimization work.
So you may want to verify that any of that is still like working
properly.
I guess.
I don't know if we touch anything in there.
That might cause a problem, but so now we've at least simplified it
down, it should look basically the same, it does.
and,
There's a grid raycast.
Update voxel.
I don't actually know what we're doing with update voxel.
Like nothing.
So that's just old news as well as we welded that in so that shouldn't
actually be happening.
I like looks fishy.
Looks fishy is very good.
You got to understand sometimes, some numbers look fishy when you say,
I don't know that we really care about that.
But you know what I might do, I might stick it in here.
Just in case just in case.
We need to check if something looks fishy.
So we've got our voxel, irradiance computation, and we did sort of
change some of these.
Like, we do dues, the get relative P.
So we use the the voxel
Utility functions.
Now maybe I screwed them up, right?
I mean that's totally on the table and that would leak into here.
Get light leaf.
For p is like, we're not really going to be doing these anymore, so
this can go as well.
It's just not a thing.
Debug box push, we probably want to keep because we're going to have
to debug a bunch of stuff soon and we would like to fix that.
I don't know that get box is a thing.
I guess we're using it, just to verify that we don't go out of bounds
now, right?
So I guess we'll leave it in.
And add Box Storage were using as well.
I think, right?
Yeah.
On the only on the old path though.
So we'll leave that stuff for now.
Be sure the Katie stack pack is gone now too, right?
So again not really doing anything right now other than just deleting
code so that I can have a little bit more of a focused approach as to
what's going on in here.
It just gotten a little bit too crafty to really be able to like suss
out what was going on there and it'll get simplified quite a bit more
once we pull out the old Caster as well, but I just don't want to do
that till I can verify that the new Caster is unambiguously better,
which we don't know that it is, right.
So I just can't make that leap yet.
Okay, so same situation here.
I don't know that there's lighting points anymore so I feel like those
should be able to be removed.
We don't use them.
Light node is also not used, I don't think.
Katie tree node is not used.
And I think that is the end of it, right?
All right, so this is much more streamlined.
Now although there still is a ton of stuff in here that doesn't need
to be in here.
Once we can actually pick the the raycast or we're going to use.
So now we just need to address like why are we getting this weird
light Behavior?
Like it's it's
looks kind of, looks kind of like,
Well.
I mean, it looks kind of like an issue with the Ray kassar.
I don't know, I think, I mean, I don't really know, but I may have to
just kind of re-enable, some debug
Because this kind of algorithms really hard to debug without looking
at what it is.
You know what, it actually shows you.
So I'll take a quick spin through the raycast or first and see if
there's anything obvious that we can just Bingo out on and save time.
But assuming that, you know, we don't see anything.
I think I'm gonna have to take a much more methodical approach to it.
Okay, so here's the actual light Loop.
You can see how it works.
It's basically just looping through the children of the of the entry
on the box stack.
And so the way this works is it just says look we're going to start
with with one box on the stack and, you know, we're going to go ahead
and look consider that box.
And the way we do that is we Loop through the Leafs that it has
and,
you can see here, says, like, if we need to actually push something
onto the stack,
You can see.
So basically, this is the Collision detector that says, did we hit
this?
You know, essentially we know for pulling something off.
I can see how this works.
Now, I just had to repaint it back into my head.
We pull something off the stack, if it's on the stack, then we know
it's a like interior node.
It's not a leaf.
It's not an actual like occluder.
It's some kind of a spatial partition node.
We test it.
And we see whether or not it's going to have the correct set of
Things for us to process it later.
So we use should push which is to say whether or not it was close
enough for inside.
And we say if we should push and this thing is a leaf container.
Then we roll over the leaves in a tighter Loop which just streams over
them one after the other and we pull the the box out test against it
preserve the best hits using select and continue the loop, right?
So it's just a little branchless Loop that just kind of
There and runs units, Branch this assuming this is turned into a seam
of which you hope it would be.
But who knows?
We did find that msv.
See doesn't really turn things into see, mobs unless you're very
careful.
So it's entirely possible that actually doesn't.
But and then we have another CMOS version down here.
This is the thing that does, the should push for the Box pack.
And I think it actually turned out to not be faster with the seam of
those.
We didn't bother there are some weird about that.
Right?
But anyway you can see here, we just do like look we update the depth.
And the Box stock, if this is something we should have pushed on,
right?
You know, it seems pretty reasonable.
And also anything particularly weird going on.
They're not sure why that would have sort of flamed out the way that
we're seeing now.
But anyway, we go down here, we finally, when we retire, we know we
now have four hits.
I mean hopefully like maybe something's didn't hit, but we have for
Real Results.
We try to compute with the normals are that's what this whole thing
is.
And then we Loop over each Ray and in scalar, we ask it to compute the
voxel irradiance and you can see getting the components out here and
then asking the the voxel computation to like sample that if you sat
lists and blend it together.
So that's, you know, that's all that happens there.
Assuming that that information is fetched it then uses the transfer
pps2.
Basically update the spec map in just this little piece of code here,
which is pretty trivial, and it hasn't been touched.
So I don't suspect there would be much to worry about there, but, you
know, I guess you never know.
So, I think that's basically it, my concern would be that compute
voxel irradiance at
Let me.
Let me take a look at relative P.
I'm just not entirely sure, you know, I don't know to what extent.
That's correct.
I just want to take a look at it.
So it's basically saying, look, make the world PB relative.
Figure out which one it's in, which it does.
And then it just produces the uvw is.
Yeah it's a pretty straightforward routine.
Doesn't seem like it could be wrong.
The actual initialization code could of course, always be wrong
though.
So that part's a little bit harder.
Let's take a look at that real quick so you can see here.
We get the Silicon, the seldom we pass, we produce those, you know,
the inverse from those and we set the cell count.
We will set them in corner later by using rectum in dim.
Working off of the cell count in the cell Doom, just to produce,
whatever that offset should actually be.
So, unless rectum in dim was somehow wrong, which doesn't seem
plausible at this point because we use it everywhere.
But yeah, it doesn't seem like that.
Could be incorrect so that I don't know why that would be wrong.
I don't know.
So again, I'm just struggling to find anything obviously wrong.
So, I think I may have to just kind of dip down into it and sort of
Step through carefully to see what's going on.
I don't see any, I don't see any obvious explanation for why we would
be getting that.
I suppose the exterior code which we did change, pretty heavily could
have screwed something up, I mean, you know, in here if you forgot to
set some fundamental value, that would be a pretty obvious way you.
Of screwed things up because, you know, the code is dependent on all
of these values being said, because there's just as with anything with
lighting.
There's just so many moving pieces and so, it's pretty easy.
You end up with kind of this orgy.
If you actually, you know, if you imagine trying to do the lighting,
as a functional, kind of a design where you always pass everything
that everyone needs,
It just gets really unwieldy very quickly and that's usually you know
when you're know you're dealing with a system like that, you also know
that there's kind of a lot of cruft in it then because that just means
there's so many moving parts that it is going to be tricky, right?
That's that's just kind of how that goes.
So anyway, yeah, so I'm not sure I would say that.
I guess I also don't know.
As far as the lighting spheres are concerned.
I don't really remember to what extent we're out.
Putting those values.
I don't know if you even ever verified if we were out putting those
values in a sensible way, I assume that they're still correct but I
actually don't know like
We generated like a non interleaved version of this thing or
something.
And so I you know, I'm just going to go take a quick look at HHS fear
just to remember what the last thing we dumped to this file was
because I'm just not sure.
So like in here where we do output sphere inl, right?
When we did the generate octahedral lighting pattern, I want to say
that we preserved it like meaning it should be the same thing like
way.
It was.
Select.
Here's the light.
Sampling sphere.
and that looks like, it's just
That looks like it's just you know, correctly grouped.
For X is 4.
Y is for Z's.
Right.
So, I don't know.
So assuming that this is still, you know, producing reasonable
results, I guess, let me just test it because rather, than me
inspecting the code.
The easiest way is for me to just look at the actual stuff that comes
out and see whether or not it's valid, right?
So, if I go, and I can actually do that in the code as well.
When we pull those samples out, I can sort of check to see what there.
It says, right?
So when we are actually doing the ray casting and, you know, we're in
the compute, light propagation callback here for example.
I should be able to then take a look at the value.
We're using to do the cast.
Well, I guess that's probably down in here, right?
And verify that it's actually a
like I should be able to verify that it's actually correct.
This looks weird though.
So this is odd in fact.
So why is this look like this?
Here's sample directions.
Okay, so this is wrong.
This is totally wrong.
Okay, so what it looks like is happening here is that raycast is we
don't have one that's still doing it the way that it used to work
where we would pass
For re directions down.
I mean just looking at it, right?
Like that would still need to be true.
So so I think this is garbage now and you can see that it's not even
loading up the sample spheres anymore.
So if we do want this to run properly, we need to use both of those
things.
So we need to do like, light sample sphere.
And we would need to actually like load that out.
So
in order to get the sampling sphere, in this case, I think it would be
like
Basically, this same thing.
It just looks like we were just while we were doing the other code, we
just vaporized the original version here.
So this would pull out the sampling sphere in question and then this
would be the thing that would pull out the
The correct, sampling sphere value.
So if we just did, you know, array D here where we said, samples fear.
I don't remember what that is, just called sample Direction.
So if we said, like, okay, that's the sample Direction in here, we
just say like, oh okay, like
Do the Rady that you need to pass and presumably, we can just do one
and two and then update this one as well.
Now I have to go verify that that actually works.
So just fat that.
That's actually what we used to be passing because I'm not sure, but I
feel like that's mostly, right?
Like, that's, that's mostly what we should have been pulling.
So, let's see.
Okay, so it looks like that was probably the only problem, so we just
weren't passing the right sampling values.
So now, if I go ahead and run Us in 02 mode,
Looks reasonable.
Like, I'm not sure.
It's right.
Because again, we haven't even really done our lighting quality pass.
So we don't really know to what extent the lighting is is actually
proper.
But at least it's not obviously bugging now, right?
It's at least more towards the same side of things and, you know,
Looks like more, what you would expect.
Okay.
So what I would like to do here is maybe just because I don't know
that I really want to get into the other side of the lighting today
yet.
Maybe I'll say that for next weekend.
What I'd like to do now is just streamline this again a little
further.
So while I have the the lighting in a writing running form simplify
the code down into maybe two discrete branching paths that I can
switch between very clearly.
The old one in the new one just so it's more straightforward for me to
be able to like continue to do the debugging properly between the two
of them.
so if I were to try to write it so you can see that the way the grid
raycast here works is, you know, you say,
here's the one Ray I want and it returns you, the transfer PPS value
and you can see the way the other raycast works is it just does the
update sort of at the end, right?
And so the problem with
Doing it this way is again, just like you kind of have to figure out
like what are you actually going to do in terms of the difference in
updates?
The reason we did it this way here was because this code already
happened to be, you know, it was already doing four at a time.
So when it pulls out of this routine, it's got four color values that
made sense to just update those directly into the
resulting spec Texel buffer, but I'm not sure that that makes a whole
lot of sense for the other way, the raycast works because the other
raycast routine is set up to just do like
One single Ray.
So you need to do it four times in order to be able to pull out this
exit criteria, right?
now maybe that's just better maybe we do just want to wrap it in a
loop of four and
so, when you call that raycast routine, you'd still do four at a time,
you just do them see really
And I don't know.
I'm going to go ahead and say, sure, because again, that allows me to
split these two into clean like, completely separated versions and
that to me, just seems like way better.
So I'm going to call this routine here, a BB raycast.
And I'm going to call the other one, the grid raycast, which it
already was.
And then I guess I'll just try to wrap.
The grid raycast routine in this in this code, right?
So in other words, this will actually happen at the top of this code.
I don't actually know if casts initiated properly gets updated by for
in here or not.
It does.
So this code here, will basically, instead of grid raycast, actually
getting called it, just is the routine now.
So, it'll Loop over the re-index multiple times and produce in here.
The transfer PPS value, it will not like return it
Right?
So it's actually going to just produce it directly.
After producing the transfer PPS value, it will do the same rights as
this routine does.
So, you know, we'll we'll actually streamline it in here.
Like so.
And then, this routine will.
Have any preprocessor directives in it anymore.
It'll just always be what it is.
And then we'll just have
Lighting use grid will be a 0 or a 1 and I'll take a look at the
places where lighting use gets gets used here and I'll just say, okay,
if lighting use grid then we do it one way.
If not, then we do it the other way and then the Ray Caster can just
be something that gets picked
Yeah.
So like in here we'll just do a pound if
Around these guys.
And we'll say, lighting, use grid will do it one way, and then this
will do it the other way.
Right?
So in one case, we update the sample Direction and the other, we
update the Rady pull and that's all we needed to do.
So now let's actually call the correct one in these two.
So in the AABB case, it's going to look like this.
We don't need the final two parameters.
Those were added specifically to support the grid, Ray Tracer, which
we know we don't need.
And then in this one, the same thing would be true in Reverse.
Like we probably don't need.
Oh well it's already says that so we know that it's like a different
set of parameters, right?
So in this case, we know that we would probably pass those two.
So instead of the Rady single like that stuff, right?
We know that these two have to be set to the things we would have
passed.
Right?
And so things like the walk table or whatever are not actually going
to be
We're not actually going to get those.
So,
Diffuse knotless just comes in automatically re origin.
Single.
Is just whatever, this Ray origin was so that's getting passed in
directly.
Right.
Yeah.
So this
Is just going to get passed in as what we use.
In the case of this Ray origin here.
It seems like the spec Atlas needs to be in here as well, right?
Because if we don't pass the spec, Atlas we won't have anywhere to
write.
So that
Is an addition that needs to happen and the same with the spec Texel.
The sample Direction gets past year and there's a grid index and
that's everything at that point.
So then we do our Loop and our Loop needs to pull off of the sample
direction for the particular re-index for on to get this Rady, which
is what it will do and that will be called Rady single Andrei origin.
Single is just what we got past, so that's just here because it
doesn't change.
The initial grid index, we got passed in the wok table.
We pulled out ourselves and so then I think we're good total cast
initiated can just be Inked by 4 because we know that's what that's
actually going to do.
And so, in order to simplify this, we might just go ahead and say,
like each time through this Loop, we initiate a tray casts, right?
So that doesn't need to be done twice.
Okay.
So the moon direction again, we don't really know how this is going to
shake out.
That's like, placeholder code because we just have no idea like what
we're expecting to happen there, right?
Oops.
So we don't really know what's going on there and we don't really care
at the moment.
So this is lighting used grid.
Rid.
Hey Bebe.
Okay.
So, we should be able to now swap between these two lighting versions,
pretty straightforward, right?
And now we have completely separated calls for each one.
So there, you know, completely unrelated and don't like overlap each
other at all in theory.
We do have two separate calls here so we have a build spatial
partition for lighting for a bees and a build spatial partition
lighting for grids and when I might want to do is actually just split
those two out as well.
So again, we have just one like point where we call them
And and see if we can make that work correctly.
Yeah.
So I'm going to try that.
I'm going to say like, build spatial partition.
And I'm going to have like a BB and grid.
And I'm just going to try slitting this routine into two, halves to
see if I can make that work or not.
So if I grab the part of this routine that does the, a be build, it
looks like this.
And then, if I take a look at the part that builds the grid routine
And it seems like there's probably like very very little overlap here.
You know, just just looking at it.
So I think that should be pretty straightforward and now I can just do
here.
If lighting use grid, we call the grid one.
Otherwise we call the other one.
And now we've kind of like pull this code apart.
To the point where we don't like we could even make this be like hot
swappable right now.
We just have effectively a switch we turn and we run completely
separate code paths for each case and they're really not at all.
So we could we could run them together, right?
Could run them at the same time.
Without the pound, if right by just using an actual, if in the code
and that seems good just as something we can use going forwards.
So let's go ahead and run the old a B-1.
And so the other thing I would like to do here is maybe clean up the
way the Box Storage stuff works.
In this particular case, that's another thing I would like to do but
let's just see.
So when we do the grid lighting there was like a ton of bugs
This is supposed to be good raycast and so we could also maybe try to
look for some of the bugs.
Like we've got
a certain stuff.
We had accidentally disabled asserts by accident.
So we've got bugs in here.
That's an assert should probably go to debug mode.
So yeah, if I run and debug mode, I should hit asserts on things, not
being in bouncy here.
Like we've got an index and the index is apparently garbage.
So if I take a look at the cell count, you can see that it's fetching
to it's like one ahead of X where it should be.
so basically like this particular piece of code here,
Somehow this clipping to the spatial grid bound like wasn't sufficient
to prevent the index from being out of bounds, which is a little bit
weird.
it's a little bit hard to see here in 29 for
What's the actual total Downs?
Interesting.
I would like to see this.
This one was right on the edge.
So, I guess the problem that we would have there.
Is that on the absolute edge of the box?
So,
since we don't want to step over the edge of the Box, we would want to
We would want to bring the actual like total bounds.
That were clipping.
We'd want to bring them in by .5 since it wouldn't change the results,
but it would make sure we never step out of bounds.
So, what we probably actually want to do is we want to use like our
region clipping
You know where clipping region like that.
And what we would want to do is say, you know, take this thing.
and so, when we produce the Box bounds in both cases,
What we want to do is once we do that clipping.
We would want to do a Mankowski.
Some on that, I do have that, don't I?
Yeah.
Do we not have it?
I guess we just called it add radius to.
Yeah.
So what we'd want to do here is we'd want to just do an ad Radius 2.
Otherwise known as Mankowski.
Some butt.
In this case, it's just a radius so you can't add two shapes I guess
whatever doesn't matter plate.
Being, I want to add to the clipping region.
Effectively like a - shrink of half the cell dim so whatever the
Whatever the cell Dimension is, I'm shrinking it in by half so that I
clip everything just to the to that region.
I think that would work.
The only thing I don't like about that is maybe we don't quite want to
do it.
all the way into there, because the only the, the downside of doing
that is just that
Well this has an apron anyway so actually technically we want to
shrink it by one whole unit, don't we?
I mean really
Because we're not suppose we putting things in the apron anyway.
So actually that's probably fine.
Because we don't really care.
If things are in the apron, we're going to, we're not going to look at
them either way.
So that way we won't have anything that goes outside the region due to
the rounding, right?
So let's take a look at it.
If there's any other ones here.
So that looks like it's still overlapping on why they're right.
Why is that
Pun intended.
Show me.
Okay, there we go.
Because the clipping region should now be shrunk.
Such that you shouldn't ever be able to step outside like that.
although I have to go actually verify that, that's really true, but
So it does still look like it's for some reason in whiny way thinking
that it can continue to do that.
But I'm not sure why.
Oh wow.
We're not even using it.
Check that out.
So this actually needs to be box bounds, right?
So that's pretty obvious there.
So that was just the case of like, because the routine had been
written prior to the clipping.
It was
Actually using the direct box bounds there, which is not at all what
we actually wanted.
So oops, it's comma.
All right, so now we fix to potential bugs and that sorting routine.
Let's see where else we get assertions here.
In the grid lighting.
Okay, so you can see that basically, like, if you call the grid
lighting routine, you end up with basically just straight Moonlight
weird way.
Right.
So every direction hits nothing.
I'm right, you know, you see I'm saying.
So basically, like every you run it every direction returns Moonlight
and it immediately goes to like fully saturated Moonlight because and
there's literally no, there's really no direction.
That doesn't produce Moonlight apparently right let me pull out.
To a further out can see the lighting man's there.
So that's good.
I mean, we're at a reasonable point.
Now, I don't know how much time I got left over like a half an hour,
so I think that we will want to maybe push a little further down into
their today.
I'm what should I do?
What should I do with my half hour?
So I'm not 100% sure what I should do with my half hour.
Try a ferret, whether I should try to get this working or whether I
should go to the let's let's finish the cleanup and then we'll start
next weekend on that on that part.
All right, so let me switch back to the grid version here.
I mean, the non grid version rather.
And what I wanted to do here was I'd like to start to remove some of
the stuff that's getting stored in the lighting structure that really
probably should not be in the lighting structure.
So if we take a look at the at the wig, get box is working.
I think that's the primary thing that don't really like.
So if you look at where add back storage is actually being called, can
kind of see what's going on here, like basically everywhere that we're
doing our splits, like we add these boxes in, right?
And these boxes are now we
Boxes for every particular case.
Meaning we never actually use the original boxes that were passed to
us.
And so what I'd like to do is I'd like to just stop storing that array
and so what I'd like to do is basically
take a look at this and say,
a okay, like
this is going to be some other thing, right?
And we will still use it for our own internal storage.
So that can continue happening.
Oops.
But everywhere else that we use it, actually.
Why isn't this calling get box?
I have no idea.
Oh wait.
But that's shouldn't be calling.
Get box.
Should it?
Because these are Source boxes.
So that should actually be looking in the in the actual box array.
Yeah, I am.
So actually what we want to do here is we want this to be completely.
Okay?
So what I'm trying to say here is I want this to pull these Source
boxes here, out of like some kind of source box thing, right?
Like in here we would say lighting box.
You know input boxes or something like this.
So then like when you pull something out of the source here you're
pulling it out of like input boxes.
Like that.
And everybody else is using the get box part of things, right?
Which I, we should probably remove at this point.
So,
This.
code would look more like that and then when we call the split box
thing,
We would pass in the original boxes.
So in here, where we do
ABB build spatial partition.
We would just pass like actual box count and or like input box count.
and,
Input boxes.
And in that way, we wouldn't really need.
Actual box count either, you know this would just be input box.
Count?
And I don't think we want the route lighting nonsense either.
Look we're not using that anymore so let's just get rid of that.
So,
Basically what I'm saying here is we pass in the input boxes and we
wouldn't store them anymore and then this a bee boxes thing would be
something we would actually allocate so much like this routine here.
Allocates we using a push or a call the spatial grid node set.
We would do the same thing here.
So we just say like yeah whatever man, the temporary NE now gets a
lighting like solution AABB boxes.
Equals push array, you know Max lightbox count.
Who cares?
Lighting box.
Right?
So we just put that on the temporary.
No, we don't really care.
Like, it doesn't matter, and it's not an issue.
We then go through.
And, you know, we use input boxes everywhere for when we're actually
reading it of the input stream.
And I think that's really it.
I mean, that's
so that's all I really wanted to do.
There was get rid of that kind of weirdness where it's getting stored,
like the input boxes are getting stored and we put them onto the same
array for some reason like that.
I just was like nah.
So anyway, if we do it that way then both of these routines can get
past the input box like set.
Which to me feels a lot more sane.
So then the set of actual box count, it's just input box, count.
And input boxes.
Yeah.
Okay.
And in this case for the child box stuff, this is actually going to
pull out of the ABB boxes.
The split box calls are just going to take the input boxes exactly as
they were before.
So nothing particularly special happening there.
And same thing with this.
I guess, in this case, this is a 16 bit.
Value.
Yeah.
So I think that's fine and the.
So now we kind of need to fix the debug dump data stuff but which is
totally fine.
And I guess I'll just Nerf that for now and then cuz I'm going to have
to decide what I actually want where I actually want that to be and
I'm not 100% sure result.
Light boxes is kind of irrelevant at this point so that's probably
just not going to happen anyway.
But you know, we'll see you when we actually get there.
So now we can just pass right when we get in here to the internal
lighting core, the internal lighting core would take the input box
count in the input boxes as actual parameters, which is a lot better
because that way, you know, you kind of know what you're actually
dealing with here.
So be input box, count lighting box and put boxes like so and I don't
know like we may just want to like say that that has to be a 16-bit
value because we
Don't use more than that.
I don't know whether we want to do that or not.
It's hard to say.
So when we actually call internal lighting Cornell, we would pass the
occluder count.
and the occluders like that and this would go away and
I guess I didn't remember what that actually takes.
What's the complaint?
Temper Inna came first.
That's why
It's temporary NE.
And then those two, there we go.
all right, so with that point,
yeah, I don't know.
This is all the H Prof stuff.
Which I don't really care about very much in here.
So I'm going to go ahead and Nerf that real quick.
There we go.
And now I guess.
I'm going to just verify that this stuff.
All runs properly.
And we can move on.
All right.
so in here, wait, are we
In debug mode.
No.
All right, so one problem we're going to have here is that when we do
we have to initialize these somewhere now.
So like I guess when I do a BB build spatial partition, I will also
need to kind of like set this value up.
So ABB box count has to be 0.
When we start there, I suppose it actually actually technically has to
be 1.
Because I think we leave a slot.
Like 0 is not an actual valid lighting box.
so, that's kind of a separate issue, but
So that seems fine.
And so now I think we're getting a little closer to what we actually
need here.
So then if we actually take a look at handmade lighting, so we could
now also ensure that people don't fuss with these if they're not using
the correctly corresponding version of the two.
So like, you know, if you go to
The central switch noun.
Well, we could move the central switch up to the top of the H file and
then we could use that to determine which set of space partitions.
You actually had.
So we would compile out the ones that you don't have if that makes
sense.
Which might also just make sure things are a little bit better in
terms of like consistency.
So now we should
we should be okay.
The only thing here is that the like split box stuff like all of that
and kalcker FC.
Yeah, like that stuff should also be in that if because these things
should not happen either if you're not compiling that in.
So if you're using lighting use grid, then great, but it and if
there's another one, then you also get these other routines if that
makes sense.
Where was the end of that?
Function.
Right there.
So now I think we're compiling all of the code one way or the other as
well.
And again, there's no reason for that.
I could just remove those, but I just wanted to verify that nobody was
using, like both like that.
Everything was clean one, you know if you do it one way or do it the
other way.
Nobody's, like looking at somebody else's data structure there, so
that I know that they're completely isolated.
So I think now we have a clean switch between the two of those systems
and, you know, whichever
You choose is is the one you cat and they build their own intermediate
data structures and they never share right either.
So I think that's good.
So we're getting closer.
So now that that's done.
I'm just trying to think if there's anything else that I want fixed up
and then like I said next weekend can just be just for debugging the
grid walk code.
And that should be it for that so that all looks fine.
I think like the debug line stuff should probably be in the temporary
Arena now.
So like these don't need to stick around.
So I think you know, if we take a look at where that's being used and
we just go debug lines, right?
Let's just see everyone who's using it.
I mean that's pretty straightforward.
So I think we should just be able to do this.
And then we can allocate the amount of debug lines that we actually
want.
So, maybe at the top of things we do that.
So there is an interesting thing we could do there, which is to say,
like we could do that.
Just only if we don't have any of them.
So, like we could do something where we said, like when we do push
lighting,
Render values.
We push all the line segments out here and then we say, like, debug
line count 0 and after we've done that, we know sort of the temporary
memory would get freed.
So in a sense, we probably have to if we were going to do that,
yes, I guess I guess the reason not to do that is just that we don't
actually have
The ability to persist those across, you know, it's like ambiguous.
How long they should last at that point?
We could just put them in the table.
Memory.
And maybe we'll do that.
So maybe what I'll do is I'll say, all right.
Solution.
Debug lines, equals push array debug line.
And I don't know how it knows what the max debug line count is.
It was a rake out here, which is not what I want.
So I probably want Max debug lines, right?
And it would it would do that.
I think that's probably fine.
So we just say Max.
Debug line count.
Equals however many we want the maximum to be.
And then we just need that value to exist.
I think that should do it.
Oops, forgot to tell you that solution, table memory.
All right.
So, I think now we're pretty good.
That feels nice and it just feels a lot more manageable now because
we've got those pretty buttoned-up.
Nothing really squirrelly happening.
Now, everything is pretty, you know, pretty easy to take a look at
now.
so I guess the only other thing I would say is internal lighting core
is now sort of a little bit on the table, so
I would be interested to know whether I still want that to be its own
function or weather update.
Lighting should just have the whole thing in it.
And mostly what that's about is just determining whether or not.
I think it would be easier to have it be callable from the
from the external code.
And I really am not sure.
Yeah, I'm not sure.
I don't know about that.
That's a that's a tough one and I guess I would say I'm not sure.
Yeah I'm not sure what we want to do there, you know, I can
I can roll that in but the same time.
Like, I'm not sure how we would necessarily compute the stats.
We could use the debug macros to do that if we wanted to.
But look if we take a look at H light Prof here, and in terms of how
we do our pound defines,
I'm just, I'm just not sure, you know, we turn off handmade internal
and handmade slow there, right?
And that's to get rid of those.
Those pound defines and we could just pound to find them back in and
use the debug data itself in that case the debug output itself, and
maybe that's the best option.
I'm really not sure if we don't, we're going to have to
call this function right with with the data that we get here.
That's not so tough though.
if you look at what's in there,
Really, you just have the similar origin, P.
The origin P, the input boxes and the atlases and we could just dump
those.
I don't actually know what the heck it needs world for it's probably
just for alignment.
Yes, you can, you can see here, like, it needs like the, the
operations on the world struct and that's kind of a little
unfortunate.
Because it would be nice if we didn't depend on the world struct and
you can see that.
The.
Like the subtract call.
actually, let's
take the nonstop on this one.
Yeah.
So if you look at like the subtract call, like the only reason these
things need the world is because of the chunk dimension in meters and
I'm assuming like are in the same chunk is the same thing, too.
Actually, you don't even it's literally just for an assertion in that
one, right?
so I kind of feel like
Weep.
Probably just want versions of these that don't need that.
And then instead of passing the world in we would just pass the chunk
dimension in meters at that point.
It becomes possible to create a flat struct and you can call the whole
thing.
Exactly as is on in and out that seems way better.
So like I think the thing that I would then want to do is the
following I would want to make a struct here.
R.
That's like, lighting update.
Params or something, you know what I mean?
And this would take the chunk dim in meters.
It would take these two, sausage gentleman here and
I guess that fundamental unit.
And that way you would say like here's the parameters and then here's
the pointers.
And when you want to snap a debug output version, right?
You just you just use the parameters now,
I think that means I also probably want to go ahead and pull the
random series I'm guessing as well.
So like I guess, I don't know, but I'd like to take a look at how the
entropy flows through it and it would be nice.
If you basically said here, like, look the random series comes in here
as well.
So that that's also like, repeatable to the extent that you want it to
be.
So if you pass the same parameters, you get the same result and there.
Like a stored state.
So look, if you look at the lighting solution,
and you look at what's in here, you know, at this point I guess what
we could do is just say
Maybe this is what that is.
So yeah.
Like I wonder if maybe the best thing to do here would be to say look
all of this stuff is regenerated.
The random series isn't so it probably should come out and be in a
separate thing.
The same with this stuff to write like I feel like we could make one
more transformation to this code and I guess I don't want to do it in
five minutes.
Like I feel like we can make one more transformation to this code.
We're basically like at least from this point from the update lighting
call.
It's functional to the outside like so you pass in all the state and
it does the work and updates the things without having any stored
state that you didn't give it then, right?
So in other words, the lighting solution thing would kind of disappear
and there would just be two things.
What is the stored State?
You want it to operate on?
And what is the new state you're passing in?
And those two things are both like savable.
So this and the only reason I'm saying this is so that we can
Due to a nicely repeatable test setup, which we know we need.
So, I might go to Q&A now and just put it to do in here that says
like, you know, split the lighting State into pieces so we can have a
more functional esque way of calling it where the two halves
specified, the persistent and new state, so we can save them both
easily if we want.
And basically, what I mean by that is like, right now, this lighting
solution structure is doing double duty.
It is both the thing that we use to avoid, having to pass eight
thousand things to everybody in the actual lighting code because that
gets extremely slow, you want to be able to pass one pointer and know,
you can access all this stuff for efficiency, not to mention typing.
But it's also the thing that carries the persistent storage.
So like this diffuse weight map, and the sampling spheres and all this
crap.
That's in there too.
It would be nice to split those things out so it was clear like here's
the stuff that's like cashed and stored over time.
Here's the stuff that's like regenerated automatically and it's really
just for efficiency.
So like
You know, just to be specific.
It looks like this.
so, you can see right from and
You know, you can see there's four separate types of information that
are in here, right?
And each one of those types has a different behavior.
And so what I'm saying is look, we should probably, you know, figure
out the most effective way to split those into pieces so that it's
clear what each one does and they're not all mixed together, right?
Because I don't think they need to be for any particular reason and it
would just be easier to work with easier to understand and easier to
save the state if we had those clear pieces, right?
Now that we're starting to get a very clear picture of how this whole
thing works, we can start to make those changes accurately.
Right.
Is Max nude index supposed to be in bounds or one pass the bound?
It supposed to be in bounds
I'm not sure I know exactly what you're talking about, but I'm
assuming you mean inside the grid bills page partition routine.
So I'm assuming you mean this
It's supposed to be in bounds.
Just letting switches were direct lighting like the sun and moon.
So at the moment, there is a Moonlight and it's just assumed to kind
of be, it's more like a skylight.
So it's just generally a dome where it's brighter.
If you are aligned with the direction that the Moon is in and dimmer
as you get further out.
I don't know that that's going to stay in there.
That way, we may change that we probably will.
So, you know, that that was kind of just a thing that was in there
temporarily.
So that'll that'll probably get modified a little bit.
But obviously, we do have, we do want Moonlight in the game, so there
will be some way that Moonlight applies.
I just don't know exactly.
We'll end up wanting to that to be encoded because things that are
underground.
Shouldn't have Moonlight applied.
So doing it the way we're doing it now is probably not how I would do
it.
Are we doing this on the CPU purely for educational reasons?
Or is there something else?
I guess the reason is because at least at the moment,
we really don't want to require really high-end graphics cards.
So, you know, a core i7 from a few years ago and a graphics card from
a few years ago, will run the game just fine.
If we try to do like an RT X version, like that really limits.
The number of platforms, you can actually run this thing on, right?
So Ray tracing on the graphics card is not super fantastic.
If you are also requiring, the graphics card to do all this other
stuff, which we do right.
Like, we actually used depth feeling to make nice compositing.
And we use,
Msaa to have kind of nice, smooth edges and stuff.
So you know, we were using the graphics card to do stuff and we can't
just pile things on the graphics card forever.
So doing it on the CPU, seems like a good thing because it's nice to
have that option and then eventually if we want to move that to a GPU
computation, well, we would want it to be on the CPU anyway because
you really don't want to debug your lighting code on the GPU.
Like
Oh my God, right?
so, I guess what I would say is that's you know,
I think no matter what you plan on in shipping, you should probably
have it working on the CPU side first, because it's the only way
you're going to probably debug it very well because gpus just are very
hard to debug.
They don't even really let you step through code, most of the time
certain cards did and then now they don't, I don't know, it's pretty
weird but
Can I come with you?
If I demo, I already did.
We can put mirrors in every level.
Like, Labyrinth mirrors.
Wouldn't work?
Particularly well in this system because we don't have any way to
render mirrors.
We can bounce the light off of them, but the actual renderer that
renders like Sprites and stuff wouldn't actually work, right?
Like we don't have the renderer doesn't try to do that at all.
So we would need something in the act.
All we would need to put like a ray Tracer in the actual pixel Shader
to do like the rendering of the mirrors as opposed to just allowing
the mirrors to bounce light around for the lighting solution, which
that would be trivial.
It would just be that you wouldn't, you would add spikes to the to the
spec maps for those things because they would bounce directly, rather
than diffusing, right?
Can you go over the AVX scatter gather intrinsics?
I've never used them.
The last time I saw the AVX scatter gather intrinsics, they were still
larabee intrinsics or I should say actual code like actual as mmm.
So I don't actually know what they put in there.
Presumably, they look similar.
But I have no idea.
I actually didn't, if you'd asked me, like I said, I haven't looked if
you'd asked me, I didn't actually know that AV X itself had scatter
gather.
As opposed to avx-512.
But maybe it does.
No.
So I'm right about that.
So so there really isn't an AV X gather gather.
I don't think unless I'm missing it's only in the avx-512.
Like it's the Larrabee instructions that the scatter gather
But, you know, I'm guessing that, you know, if you just read the
thing, it should be pretty clear like what it does right?
I would imagine
Yeah, I mean, they're just so these, I don't know if you remember, but
like I've lamented many times that like the SEC and AVX instructions
sets, not a big fight all but the first two instruction sets, they
didn't have a way to do memory fetching for wide 8.
Wide, 16 wide, you couldn't do that, right?
So what you typically end up with is you'll do something like you'll
do a computation and you'll say, where do I need to fact
My textiles from or whatever and you're doing this for eight at a time
and all of a sudden you have to downshift into scalar like you've seen
this literally in the lighting code just now in compute voxel,
irradiance at.
So this function is almost always in a situation with the
when we were trying to do the a beer a Caster.
So in the ABB re Caster, what you see is like it comes down here and
it has to downshift to scalar to do the voxel irradiance computations
right.
And this is just a huge pain in the butt because what you'd rather do
is just keep it for wind and do them for y.
Now, in the grid, Ray Tracer, we don't care.
We can choose to bundle up to 4, but we can keep it scalar.
It's one of the nice things about it, for ssc's, it just kind of works
if you do the grid raycast way, but separate issue.
So, anyway, inside the compute voxel Radiance call.
We would like to be using the get tile clamped thing wide, but we
can't, because you can only Access Memory off of general purpose
registers.
So what the scatter gather intrinsics do finally, is they just let you
say, look, give me an address, but then you can pass me a vector
register, right?
That will actually have in it.
The index is that I should then go fetch for each individual Lane,
right?
And so scatter, and gather are just ways of writing or reading two
different memory locations using indexes per Lane rather than having
to downshift a scalar.
But that's it.
That's all they do.
Now, they're awesome.
In that, you really want instructions that do this.
So when I say that's it, I don't mean like, it's the unimportant, I
just mean it's very simple but it's really really great.
Because once you have these, if they are actually implemented fast in
the chip which at the moment, I don't actually know if they are but
like when they get them high performance, eventually hopefully, maybe
right.
And maybe they already are and I'm like, I said, I've not tried them
because I don't even have a chip that can do this.
I don't think maybe,
Maybe I do.
I don't know if my I have a core I9 that may have scatter gather.
It may not.
I don't know.
It has it has avx-512 F.
I think, but probably not any of the other avx-512 things it doesn't
matter.
The point is, if they get this working, well, it's great because now
you can keep everything wide.
So you don't have to worry anymore about the problems that you have
when you've done all your computations and nice scalar.
Form a nice Lane form and having to downshift autoscaler.
Does that make sense?
But there's really not much more to it than that.
It's just, that's all it is.
Do you have any idea how the gameplay will look like?
Are we way to finish the engine for getting to it?
Yes.
So the gameplay stuff is really not my thing.
So I would say that like, we just do engine programming here, like,
gameplay stuff is not really going to be interesting.
So, I mean, when we get to gameplay that means we're basically done
and that's
Really, like I said, it's really just not my thing.
I don't I'd not a game designer.
On the RSI front, I would say two things.
One, try to optimize your editing configuration to not use modifier
keys at all.
So get rid of control, get rid of alt as much as you can and start
doing a variable like a diverse hand exercise sport.
So rock climbing, was hugely helpful to me.
The only thing I would say is don't use gamepads gamepads.
Also seem to be bad on your hands in terms of cramping and tendonitis
and stuff, so maybe just like stop playing console games.
Those are the only three things that I know, I suspect it's different
for, every one's Anatomy.
So those are things that have had helpful to me.
If your Anatomy is similar to mind that probably helped you if it's
very different.
Probably won't.
Right?
Probably covered in some other day, but what's the best update rate to
choose for a game?
John says it's good to have it high so it looks good in high update
screens but 120fps isn't a multiple of 144 FPS.
So what do you recommend?
So, that's a good question.
So I guess what I would say is like for my purposes most if I want to
make is usually like more of a 24 frames a second kind of thing.
Like I care more about cinematic stuff than I care about action e
stuff.
Most of the time handmade here is kind of a different sort of game
than I would normally make.
So, to my mind, I be like I'll 24 frames a second, sounds good.
And we just, we just to 120 or 140 for based on that, but I guess I'm
not sure what you would do.
If you want 120 frames, I can and 144 frames a second and you want to
have a fixed frame rate.
I would say, maybe what I would do
Ugh.
So I would say 144 frames a second sounds like it kind of sucks.
I would maybe tell people who make 144 hurts monitors to stop because
that sucks.
It doesn't even evenly divided and a sample rate.
So like this is good, this is very good.
She I'm saying, it's like twenty four fifty sixty one twenty Thirty
right?
Like 4800 samples per second is like perfect for all monitors except
for 144.
So I would basically say like
set your sample rate to 240 as your core sample rate and tell people
with 144 Hertz, monitors to stop
144 is a bad effing idea, is what I would say.
As far as game design service current, it's not really like whether I
want to do it or not, it's more.
Just like I'm not going to teach game design like this.
Stream is supposed to be like me explaining, what's going on?
But that's just like not like I don't have anything to explain about
game design because I'm not a game designer, you know,
It's like I'm not going to like teach a subject that I myself.
Don't do.
I would just be making stuff up.
All right.
Make sure this is in a reasonable States.
Yes, good
All right.
Thank you everybody for joining me for the Sarasota handmade here.
It felt good to clean up the letting code today at it's kind of
bugging me a little bit, so I'm glad that's been taken care of.
I will be back here next weekend to start to look at debugging the
grid, Ray Tracer.
And then we can take some good performance samples and see where we're
at in terms of throughput.
And we can maybe make some educated guesses about about that looking
at the vtune profiles and so on.
That's it.
For today.
If you want to follow along the series at home, you can always go to
handmade here a.org and
The game it comes with the source code so you can follow along with it
and if you want to, you can try to debugging the grid raytracer of
this week.
You could certainly beat me to it.
I don't think there's a whole lot of bugs in there probably, it's
probably just a case of stepping through it carefully and fixing all
of the little issues that come up.
So I'd highly recommend giving that a shot until then have fun program
everyone, and I'll see you on the internet.
Take it easy, everybody.