Hello everyone and welcome to handmade hero.
The show we go to complete Street a complete stream live on game.
That's good.
I don't know what that would mean.
I guess we would like code some kind of a streaming service while
playing a game or something like that.
What I meant to say was Cody complete game live on stream but
apparently it's a it's a very spoon rise today to day.
Anyway, point being today, we are going to make some improvements to
our debug top list, which we are profiling list, which shows the top
time, takers in the game and we implemented it yesterday and we don't
have like all the features that we might want in there.
So this is the time for that.
So that's what we're doing.
If you would like to follow along day 266 is the day to unpack day,
267.
Is the day today, so do that and follow along at home.
All right, so one thing I maybe do want to do though is because we
indulged sssss McGrath the other day about executables that patch
themselves.
But I don't actually ever want that happening in in handmade hero.
So I'm going to go ahead and get rid of this because I don't
Actually ever want that to occur.
But you know, that's that's for the McGrath's of the world to, to
worry about it, not me.
So what I want to do is I want to go to our debug code and make some
improvements.
Here is the piece of code that I am talking about.
If you see what happens here, when we run, I don't actually want any
of these breakpoints anymore when we run, we end up in a situation
where we can get this topless, but there's a bunch of things.
The top list doesn't do right now.
First of all, it looks like sprintf is wonky and isn't obeying or with
specifications.
So I don't know, doesn't really matter because I, we can print these
out in columns are self ourselves, so we could do that.
The other thing is we're not constraining it to fall inside a window.
So like if we you know, this is ostensibly the window for the top list
and it's not, we're just drawing, we're not even like paying attention
to that.
So we might want to make some stuff for that and then the other thing
and
By far, the more important thing, the one that I think we're going to
start with first is that as we are looking at this top list, we're
actually seeing things that include their children.
So when this says that, it took 23 million Cycles to execute what that
means, is this entire block, including all the children took that but
of course game update and render is included in the game update block.
So it's not a really very helpful thing to view because we want to
know, you know the primary use for something like this.
is obviously twofold one is to say, show me the breakdown of things in
the program, but honestly, you know,
We already have a lot of ways, you know, we can look at this and kind
of see what's going on with that.
Certainly so you know, we have a way of getting a rough break down
over time and things like that but you know if we look at this, what
we want to see is where do we go.
If we want to optimize that we're kind of just, you know, we just want
to see a thing.
It's like who's taking the most time.
And so showing me game update taking the most time isn't really very
helpful, because I can't go optimize game update.
Game update is like four or five lines of code or something probably,
and then some calls out to other code.
Oh, and so what I wanted to know is what slow in the other code.
Like, tell me where in the code.
I actually, you know, tell me where I actually need to go optimize.
That's what I want to know, right?
So for the topless, what I'd like to be able to do is produce a list
that has not just a percentage of the time total, but a percentage of
the time not counting the children.
So if something happens to take 22% of the time but you know, 21% of
it
I was actually in the children, then it's only gonna show up as one
percent of the time, you know.
Well, that's not right, but you get what I mean, if something shows up
as 23 million Cycles, but 22 millions of those Cycles are acting the
children, it should show up as 1 million Cycles, right?
That's what I actually want to have happen here.
So how can we do that?
And I thought of some interesting things, by the way, after last
night's stream, kind of, when I, you know, shut it off and went away
some stuff occurred to me and we'll maybe play
If that a little bit as well because there are some interesting stuff
I thought we could do.
But so what I want to do is extend the collation phase that.
We when we're doing our collation, we actually are in a good position
to compute stuff like child times but we just don't actually do it,
right?
So we don't actually look at any of that information.
So all I want to do is extend our thing by adding 1 64 bit counter.
Which is the exclusive time actually we don't even 64-bit, probably
32-bit would be fine.
Because nothing takes 4 billion cycles by itself at the moment.
But whatever, I don't really care about the memory.
We can be picky.
In fact.
Just to prove how piggy we can be, you know, I'm saying?
So I don't care.
So I'm just going to say that in here, when we create one of these
profile notes will create a duration, and we'll just make two
different kinds will do duration, including children, and we'll do
well, actually will do duration and duration of children.
Okay, and so all we would need to do now is if we want to know the
total duration, we just use it as we have been, but if we want to know
the duration without the children, we can remove this value so we can
just subtract that away, okay?
And so, all we have to do to make that is when we're actually creating
one of these, do you like profile nodes?
This is not the function, I actually want to be in here.
All right.
Yeah, when we're actually dealing with these profile nodes when I
first create one.
So when we're doing the collation here, when I first create one of
these nodes you can see me doing that here, right, there's here and
here are the two places where I do that.
When we initialize the duration, 20, we can just also initialize the
duration of children to zero.
And so in here where we do duration of children,
We now know that we start out with with nothing in there, and if we
come to something like an end block, where we're going to compute,
what the duration actually was, then, at this time, what I'd like to
do is say, whoever the block was that was above us, right?
That profile mode.
I would like it to
I would like to include this nodes duration into that block
automatically right now.
Obviously we could do this by just going to first child.
Summing up all the durations and subtracting them but I'd rather just
have it in one place.
So I'm just going to do that while we go right again there.
Yeah there's two ways we could do it.
We could go to first child sum them all up and maybe that's a smart
thing to do but I just want to I don't want that to have to keep
happening, right?
So I'm just going to have it happen right here.
So the way I'm going to do that is inside deallocate open, debug
block.
I believe what happens here.
Is it pops the block, right?
So, if I go to, if I call deallocate open, debug block, then this
first open code block, is now going to point to some other block,
right?
So if I check and say, okay, what's the new first open code block,
assuming that there is one
I can then get out its profile mode.
Okay, so here is the parent node for the node that I was in.
It's going to be thread.
First open code block.
Node profile node.
That parent node.
As soon as Alan gets a better indentation support into for coder, I'm
going to be so happy.
I keep having to like undo indent things.
It's one of the only things I notice now.
It's that and the tab completion, other than that, it's been like
yeah.
I'm so looking forward to Summer of for coder, by the way.
Since obviously Alan esta actually go to school.
Like doesn't have very much time to program client but I'm hoping this
summer will be will be very fur coat or tastic.
Anyway,
At node.
I if I've got one which I do in the case, you know, if this if this if
it was true that parent node, I know that the duration of children is
just the thing that I can Som to, and I can add whatever the duration
was a my node.
And now I've got the
Duration in there, right?
So now I know exactly what that duration is of all the children.
So if I want to change our top list to be exclusive of the children, I
can do that.
Trivially just by taking the duration.
And let's go up here, taking that duration, and subtracting a way that
child portion.
So, for example, if I wanted to do that in here, right?
I could do, let's see.
Clocks, without children.
It's like Doctors Without Borders.
Only less altruistic.
So if I want to do that, I can just say like okay.
And maybe I do like clocks with children.
So that's clocks with children clocks without children is just you
take the total number of clocks and we take the ratio of children out
of it and so I could just quickly change this over to.
So you know, now we're doing it without that.
So now we're only going to look at the actual blocks themselves
without their children and you can already see.
We get just from that a much clearer picture of where our time is
actually being spent, right?
Because now
We're not double triple quadruple counting Cycles in our percentages.
Now, our percentages are actually showing us the percentage of time
spent in a block uniquely.
And so we can see that essentially, this is exactly what we would
expect for the cutscene essentially are, our code takes no time at all
because nothing's happening, we're just putting a cutscene out to the
GPU.
So, pretty much 100% of our time is spent in the debug system, which
has a ton of work to do because it goes and does all this stuff and
renders everything and
Whatever and in the graphics card, basically, like which is either
doing the rendering or waiting for the V blank.
Right?
If we now switch to actually playing the game then we'll see a more
balanced output.
Right?
So now we can see that.
Okay, now in game update and render, we are taking 20% of the time,
right?
Still not much because still like most of the time is being spent in
other things but because you know we got like the debug system eating
up a ton of that time but you can still see in general.
You know, we're getting more reasonable understanding of what's
Happening Here.
So for example, now that game update block, which is a nothing Block,
it's just in.
The outside is down here somewhere.
In fact, where is it?
It's right there, right?
It takes nothing right.
Remember, that was the top function before it's nothing now and
properly game, update and render, which we haven't really spent any
time putting blocks inside of to break down is taking all the time,
right?
And we can see that begins him.
Tim is a similar thing where it takes a fair bit of time.
So you know, we might ask, why is game update and render taking so
much time.
You know, that's a pretty fair thing to want to know and we could
figure it.
Start to figure that out now, right?
We can go into handmade dot CPP.
Go into game update and renovate.
And here is the code that we're timing.
There's the time function there and you can kind of see all the stuff
that I might be doing.
There's initialization code there and this sort of stuff I would
assume actually though that most of the time is going to be spent in
these guys title screens cutscene or the world render.
And we can again start to sort of figure that out.
So if I went into World mode dot CPP, Now update and render world, I
can make this a Time function.
Ocean just to confirm my suspicions, right?
And I don't really remember how this stuff works.
I do.
I have to give it a name.
I don't, right?
Yeah.
So if we unpause now and start to take a look at what the new looks
like, you can see.
Okay, as we expected update and render world is taking 13% of the
time, right?
And so that's, you know, that's more what we would expect to see and
it's not game update and render but game update and render.
Oddly enough that doesn't really add up quite the same.
Let's scroll back a bit.
So, game update and render is taking 11.
I should put some commas in here.
11 million cycles for game update and render.
but,
That's real weird.
But when we move,
To update and render world.
It's still taking the exact same number of Cycles, but the percentage
changes
because the time changed quite a bit as well.
That's real weird.
Is that just because of all this extra stuff we have to draw.
Oh, it's because it has to draw two of these because since we changed,
oh, that's hilarious.
Since our system doesn't uses the grids as line numbers.
After we change that file, we get secondary stuff.
That doesn't seem like a good thing.
That seems like a bad thing.
I wonder if we want to change that aspect of the grid system in some
way.
I'm not sure like you know you saw what happened there, right?
Where is that grid system?
Where is mr.
Grid system.
That's in interface.
So right now we unique, if I things quite a bit we use like the file
and the line and the counter.
And I wonder if we maybe don't want to use LINE anymore.
I wonder if we even just don't want to use.
In or counter.
If we just want to use name, it's hard to say, like, I don't know, I
don't know how, you know, it's hard to say how unique you want, these
things to be right.
And and maybe the right answer here is you do want those things to be
unique across reloads.
And what we really want is when we specify a debug UI element, instead
of using debug name, we just use regular name, you know, maybe that's
the right thing.
Since a UI element shouldn't get duplicated.
I'm not sure, I really don't know.
Like I said, that's our decision to make, but I don't know which we
want to do.
But certainly like, if I rebuild the game, I don't want to duplicate
these.
And so now they won't be, because they'll be using their name more
specifically, right?
Okay.
So, anyway, like I was saying, if we want to investigate this now that
I figured out what was going on there.
We can see that, you know, update and render world is taking all the
time, which is what we would expect.
So what we could do is we could go
We into that function now and see what it calls mode.
We could sort of see what it might be calling and maybe test a little
bit of these regions of code because you can see all the code in here
for the world stuff and just so we can maybe figure out what it is.
That actually takes the time so that we don't have to guess, right?
So you know, we could go in and say maybe there's a timer in here.
So that's the ground chunks happening.
This is the controller stuff, which I don't think is going to be
particularly unusual.
Here's the Sim stuff, but that's all pretty reasonable.
This is the rendering Loop.
So this I could probably push and think it already says move this out
into handmade entity, that CPP.
So we're already sort of thinking about that, but I'll put a Time
Block in here, which is like entity render.
And then we've got some residuals from a we're doing testing the
graphics but I don't really suspect that that's going to be a big
deal.
So let's go ahead and see what where that leaves us.
So right now, we're spending 20% of our time in ground chunks on
right?
Like what the fudge is happening in there.
That's probably just old residual stuff that we shouldn't even be
caring about.
I don't even want the ground checks anymore.
The design of the game turned out not to use them.
My bad but I'm just curious to know.
So what is it?
Is it how it's because there's so many ground buffers probably its
base is what it boils down to.
So if we just nuke this because I want to Nuke it anyway we'll get a
ton of speed back because this is all garbage.
Basically what it boils down to, right?
Yeah.
Now, we're down to just ten percent of the time being spent in begin
Sim and pretty much everything else is in the debug system.
So that's better to say the least, right?
And if we take a look at our and this is in debug mode, so we get a
lot faster in release mode as well but now that looks much better.
So got the D about collation the frame display, the game update taking
their time there and if I look inside a game update, I can see that.
It's pretty much all in game update and render which is all in update
and render world.
So, off we go,
Right in here.
We've got begins in this.
Debug system is amazingly cool.
Come on people.
That's just so cool.
God.
Alright.
Yeah.
If this would be one of the things that I'd spend another month on
probably of real-time, like this is just like you can probably this is
be a cool product like I could see selling this thing, right?
You just make a really great viewer for it as an external application.
I mean it's cool.
This thing is going to be so so cool anyway.
All right.
So because I mean like basically like with just a, with just a week of
full-time programming time.
Think of how awesome you could make these windows right there.
So, zygo dish now because I only have like, oh, I
Ten minutes here and there to like throw it like changing some of the
rendering code.
But you know, if you actually spent some time on it,
anyway, so
this stuff here is starting to look pretty good and you can see, we
can already use it to find problems.
We just found a huge problem and we can get rid of that problem really
easily, right?
And this will continue to be true as we go forward.
So that's all well and good.
That's all fine, and nice and dandy.
So I think that's pretty much all I really wanted to do with that went
with this window and so mostly what I think I would do now I want to
just clean up the rendering aspect of it so that it's not, you know,
extending outside of what the
Nouns are of it and and that sort of thing, right?
I think that's really all we need to do and I'm not going to go crazy
with it like we could do a lot more fancy stuff here and I won't
bother with that.
I'll just, you know, do sort of a reasonable pass.
And then gosh.
I don't know what else we have left to do really
anyway.
So let's take a look at at at making this we could do a sort of a poor
man's clip to this thing.
If we wanted to, that'd be real easy like without having to actually
add the ability to expose the clipping rectangle.
Do we expose the clipping rectangle from the render group, you know,
we should have, but I don't know that we ever did because we support,
But we don't actually know if we actually ever do that.
So where's the clip?
Rect.
Yeah so we never actually allow you to set that cliprect which is
something we probably should have done.
So I'm just going to do Portman slipping for now.
I don't think this is enough of a reason to expose the cliprect API
wise
So we'll skip that for now.
All right.
Your name.
So, let's take a look at what's going on here.
What I want to do in handmade debug dot CPP in the top clocks list.
I'm just going to say that.
Well, we're starting in the window and we're drawing, right?
So here is the thing that goes through and drawers everything, right?
This is the text buffer, just does like out out out, right.
All I want to do here is I'm just going to say well, alright, I'm
starting you know, we've got this thing that starts at a particular at
Value.
Right here is the thing that starts at a particular at Value.
And if I just said, well okay, I don't, why do I always close the
game?
By the way I always forget that.
This thing hot reloads and it's like a force of habit.
Anyway, you can see it draws off the end here.
And the reason it draws off the end here is because it just blissfully
it doesn't ever check to see whether it's off the end, right?
So what we could do,
Instead is say that we only want to keep going in the case, where the
at y plus, whatever the line advances, we only want.
Oh, sorry - what have line of ants is, so, whatever.
The next line would be.
We want that to be greater than the profile wrecked Min y, right?
We don't want to keep drawing.
If we get in a situation where we think we're going to be outside the
bounds, oops, missing a adopter.
And so now what you can see is it stops, you know, it stops actually
drawing when we're outside the window in this direction, but it
doesn't stop drawing.
If we're outside the window in the other direction.
And, similarly, you notice it sort of clears itself a little early.
So we'll always get rid of the thing before it would have clipped at
all.
And we could make it a little bit better because actually, we don't
really care about this part so much.
It's
more like, whether the Baseline
Whether or not we would be drawing yet.
If we would be drawing such that, the font that we're about to draw
will go below, it doesn't matter where we actually advance to because
that's actually too far, right?
So in order to fix any more of that, part of it, we would need to
Use the clipping rectangle.
Now, maybe we should use the clipping rectangle, I don't know.
We could, I mean maybe let's take a quick look because it's probably
something worth discussing, right?
Do you think it would be nice as making this Grabber handle bigger?
Because honestly, I can never grab it.
I always miss these days is too tiny.
That's pretty easy too.
To do.
I suspect
that is in here somewhere.
Yeah, so this thing when it draws, these guys that size box is this
thing over here, what I want to do is make the size of box, be
expanded more.
So I think this would be like an ad radius to situation kind of a
thing.
So after I make this rectangle, oops,
I you know, give me an extra four pixels like make the thing big
please.
What are you complaining about?
Ah, so you're telling me I can actually control it in both.
Well, I don't care.
That's all I really wanted.
Anyway, and why did I close the game?
Again, I always close the game for no reason.
Anyway, now I've got a bigger thing to grab onto which is what I
wanted.
So that's nice.
So yeah, so that's all good.
And we can we can keep that from drawing outside.
If we want to take a look at drawing, one more than we should have,
and I'll show you what that looks like.
And then we can take a look to see what the clip Breck situation is.
So we'll all that would basically be is in here.
What we would say is is at y itself.
It's at why itself below the Min why level?
Actually no, that's not quite right because we still might see a
little bit of the font protruding.
So we still want to do is at y - you know, with the next one that
we're going to do.
Right.
I shouldn't say the next one.
I guess what I'm trying to say is
As follows.
All I'm trying to say is here is our rectangle and we're trying to
draw inside this.
We might have the pointer to at why.
But what?
Her were at, you know, we're going to draw something because, you
know, maybe the text is at the Baseline.
We don't know whether this is going to protrude up into here, right?
So rather, what I would like to see is I want to know if the previous
one would have been there, right?
If the previous one is here.
That means the next one was here.
And there's no way that we could possibly draw because we know we
won't draw above the previous.
So I just want to make sure there's no chance that the line that we're
currently drawing, could have purchased
at rooted.
Right.
And so you know, after we advance, I guess what I want to do is say
well in fact I guess I could say something like this.
B32.
Clipped what I could say is clipped is going to be is the current at
why the one before we do the advance is it already outside, right?
So is at y already less than the profile wrecked.
Minn dot y if it is then after the advanced we would break
And in fact, I guess I could just do it here.
I could say if the at Y is less than the Min y, then after the
advanced we definitely don't care.
So we just do envelope here.
So now I believe what we should have gotten out of that, is that this
should draw a little bit outside, right?
So you can kind of see like it always draws one past the one that's
completely contained.
Is what we want because once we put clipping in, we're going to clip
out the part that you shouldn't see.
And so we want to leave, we still want that to draw.
Otherwise, we would leave like kind of an empty Gap there, instead of
seeing a little bit of what comes after it, which is what I would have
preferred, right?
Okay, so clipping rectangles, adding those to our system, I don't
really think would be particularly difficult.
I'll show you roughly, what that boils down to.
So, inside the render group, right?
We kind of have this concept of a camera transform at the moment.
And so what we can do with the camera transform is, we could say, in
addition to, you know, in fact we could also do it with an object
transform, but we can do it in either place.
We're just
In addition to telling you how we want to transform the coordinates,
we could also tell you how we want to clip them, right?
So in the camera transform, we could say that there's a rectangle 2
and this is the clip rect and by default that will be set to the whole
screen, but if you ever want to narrow that region down you can
Right?
And so any place that we were previously dealing with the camera
transform, we would now want to set that.
Correct.
So, you know, camera transform.
You can see them in here.
Yeah, like perspective orthographic and so on, right?
The other thing
You know, to be honest, let me just think this through, let me write
the usage code first because I'm thinking that I'm there.
I may want to track the cliprect separately for ease of use on the
person side.
Like I may want you be able to like push and Pop That.
In fact I probably do so I think what I probably want is something
like inside the render group, there's the clip rect and the clip.
Rect is going to have to get
Recorded.
So essentially whenever you push something on to the, to the stack,
it's going to have to have that in there.
So when we do render entry bitmap or render entry rectangle,
that's going to have to be included.
So for rectangle it's not such a big deal because rectangle we can
just clip already so we can just click the rectangle and store the
rectangle by itself.
But for bitmap we would actually need the clip.
Rect to be set properly if that makes sense.
And the other thing, I guess we could do if we wanted to and I have to
think about whether we want to, but one thing we could do is inside
here, we could also make the cliprect be something that just goes into
the stream.
And I know know how
Feel about that, but that could be one way to one way to do it.
That might be interesting.
We're like, essentially, you you, you know, you that's actually one of
the stream records is here's the new clipping, rectangle.
I don't know that I love that, though.
I think I would probably prefer.
I think I would probably prefer it if that were not the case.
Yeah, so I'm not going to do that.
I'm not going to do that.
Okay, so what I want to do here, I'm going to do sort of the simpler
method first and then I'm going to do more complicated methods.
Subsequent to that.
I think because I think we should probably clean this up a little bit
as well.
Anyway, and what I would like to do here, is just say, okay, we know
that render a direct route could just be clip directly.
So the question is render entry bitmap, it can't be Cliff directly.
And the reason for that is that although it's got a p and a size, we
don't have any way.
Way, if we were to we could we change that pee in the size to still
basically create the right rectangle app, you know, pre clipped and
store the clipped version of it.
What we couldn't do is say how the texture coordinates had to be
offset to a
For the fact that it got clipped.
Right?
So well.
And I guess now, I think about it.
Maybe that's just all I should really store, right?
Maybe that's the most useful thing to store, like, maybe the most
useful thing to store is to store UV offset.
And then what I can do is when we draw this bitmap, it'll just offset
the UVS by that amount, and that'll be the end of it, right?
So let's try that.
When we do a push bitmap call,
All, and we write one of those things on there.
Here's our push bitmap.
I'm just going to do entry UV offset, and that UV offset.
I'll make be 00.
Now, what I need to do is first, we have to do the opengl version cry
because we have to render past now, both of which would have to be
correct.
So when we render a bitmap and we call open Jill rectangle, you can
see, we've got the menu V and the max UV like.
So and so, what I would want to do here is I want to offset those by
whatever the offset actually is.
I think that should be really straightforward.
Now, the only question is, should we record the offset in the textile
space?
You know what space basically, should we encode the offset in?
And I feel like, probably what we want to do is encode the offset and
pixel space to be honest.
That seems a little more sensible to me.
And in fact, if we wanted to, we could maybe make this a little bit
more sensible by doing like,
You know, something like this.
Where we just because we know that we can't have any bitmaps that are
greater than 64 K wide or tall.
What we could do here is say well, alright, you know, we create our
one Texel thing and we create our menu V and R Max UV that were
drawing for the rectangle.
Well, now once we have this rectangle,
We just need some information about how that's going to get clipped.
You know what?
Not to think about it.
That's not enough information because I'm thinking about clipping off
of one side and we don't really know that.
So we're probably will probably have to actually score this as a real
more as a real rectangle.
Because because essentially what will happen is what if we have a
clipping rectangle.
You know, that's like this big and the thing we draw as like here but
offsets not going to do it.
So I think we're going to have to store this as a real thing, so
that's fine.
Because this is not a particularly good.
way to store this anyway, to be completely honest with you, you know,
because we're basically doing UV rendering, it seems like it would
Would be way easier.
If, when we do a bitmap that we render, we store enough information to
actually do all the stuff we can do.
Like, for example, this doesn't even have a rotation in it, right?
We like so are our thing that we're pushing on here doesn't even
support some of the things that we can actually do.
So I think it would might be more interesting to say.
All right, if we're going to like make this more real, that's actually
make it more real.
So what would we
Need in order to do the full version.
Well, we could do something like
A base P, right?
Where we store, you know, a corner and I guess maybe I'll draw this
out.
So, everyone's on the same page the way we were doing it before is we
kind of had like a base fee and then we had you know a vector here you
know in a vector here and this sort of filled itself in, right?
And that could be a reason way to go.
It's just a little over a specified, it would have allows you to turn
this sort of stuff around when
You normally wouldn't be able to like, you know, allows you to squish
things in a way that we don't really want to support probably because
it will create weird artifacts in how the text is interpolated.
So we could do something where we have like a, you know, a vector here
and a vector here, and I don't.
And, you know, we might want to support non-uniform scaling, so we may
need like just a one to one of these and then a multiplier for this,
that says, how big this one?
Is right?
So, it would be something like a p-value, you know, and x-axis and a
y-axis coefficient and so you just, it's just the perpendicular to the
x-axis, but then it's multiplied by this to allow you to do
non-uniform scale, right?
So that would allow us to do any rectangle, we wanted, but it wouldn't
allow us to say, what part of the bitmap.
We actually want to show in their right.
And furthermore, if we actually allow this rotation to happen like
this, this makes it so that we can't actually clip it, right?
You know what I mean?
So this kind of makes the problem of well, if we wanted to clip it
like this, this is no longer a rectangle.
So we would accept to have to do the clipping ourselves which we
probably don't want to do so that.
Now that I've worked through pretty much answers the question for me,
I think what we would want to do is have the clipping rectangle stored
as part of the stream.
So that you can just set a clipping rectangle, dump a bunch of things.
And then unclip because otherwise, I feel like it's just going to be
too much data stored per bitmap entry.
And if we want to increase the throughput of that, we want to make it
so that we can push a lot of bitmaps, it's just going to become
problem.
So I think that's probably what we would want to do.
So that means I can hold off on editing this at all, at the moment.
and,
We will want to do that eventually.
I think, and what I'll do here is say that there's a render group
entry type render entry clip,
Right?
And so inside here, we just have a render entry clip rect
Like so and the render entry clip.
Rect is just going to be what region we are allowing at the moment and
that should probably be not sure exactly how I suppose.
These should probably be in pixels because I believe everything we
store is currently in pixels.
So I think we want to just do a Min and a Max and probably we could
just do it as a rectangle to, right?
Alexa could just call this clip.
And so that would set the clip rect specifically and that would be all
we would have to do.
So if we're going to do that all of this stuff stays the same, the
only difference now is when we end up with one of these render group
entry types render entry clip, then all we have to do is say well,
Whoops, whenever we get one of these.
We read it out.
Now, see, this isn't going to work either.
This is really tricky adding clip Rex in here.
The reason this isn't actually, this wouldn't actually work is because
the render and the render groups get sorted.
So, we really do need to know per entry what the clipping is, because
they get moved around in order to depth sort, so we can't do that
either.
It seems like we really do need one per bitmap.
If we wanted to support arbitrary clip regions which is pretty nasty,
although I guess it doesn't really matter that much a modern-day GPU.
Probably doesn't care and our software renderer certainly doesn't
care.
It's just, it's just more traffic.
It's just a lot more traffic.
I don't know folks maybe someone out there has a bright idea.
I mean it could be that you know you'd want to re Arctic architect the
rendering a little bit if you really cared about clip Breck's a lot
and I don't know.
and it seems, it certainly seems like a
Right to have a ton of cliprect information packed in here for no real
reason but on the other hand like I said I'm not sure.
How you get around that if you want to do a render, that does sorting
which we do.
Well, I guess we'll just do it this way for now.
and, you know,
That's how that'll work.
So, inside here in render entry bitmap, I guess what we would have to
do for every bitmap that we output.
We'd have to check the cliprect to see whether or not a news to
change.
I guess.
One thing we could do to make this a little bit better is have the
clip Rex actually just be indexed and then check the clip back index
to see if it's changed and only if it's changed, set the clip rect
differently.
And in fact, you could do it like this.
You could do something like this where every header has a clip, rect
index.
So when you come off the header, you would say something.
Like, you 32 cliprect index equals zero and then we'd say, if header
cliprect index is not equal to cliprect index, then we actually do it,
right?
We actually set the clip region.
We actually praise it this way.
So if the cliprect index is equal to the, the one that this header
wants that, we don't have to do anything, but if it's not, then we do
have to do something.
So let's do it.
The other thing we could do is we could make this so we don't actually
expand the size of these either.
We could do this.
Right?
Because that would be totally fine and so that leaves it as still just
a just one d word entry.
So we don't expand the, the traffic on the, on the group at all.
So assuming that it's not what we need to do here is we need to call
GL scissor in order to sort of restrict the bounds of of what's going
to happen.
Now, you haven't seen Jill scissor before, I don't think because I
don't think we've ever called it by default, it will just be set to
the right thing.
So let me show you GL scissor.
I never
Amber opengl.
There's like a dock stocks dot Geo.
I was like, there's a place that people said to go that has prettier
docks for us to use.
I think this is it.
And so GL scissor is the way for us to and I guess we can just look at
the old cell.
Yeah, GL scissor is a way of saying exactly what it is.
We want to say it's saying let's set the region.
We're going to draw inside of and by default it's set to the whole
window but when we want to restrict the window, this is the way we
would do it, right?
And so, all we need to do is pass it.
Those bounds and off we go.
So, I'm going to say that.
In addition, when we have our thing here, where we've got game render
commands that game render commands, which I believe is in the platform
thing.
That game render commands in addition to the push.
Buffer base thing, it's going to have some number of Clips like
clipping.
What's running for?
It's going to have some number of clip, rectangles, and that needs to
be specified in here.
So in addition to all this stuff, there's basically a thing that's
like, you know, cliprect count and a, some kind of a
Guess, I don't know if you want to specify this.
I don't think rectangle twos or actually specified here, right?
But what we want to do is have a thing that's like clip.
Rex, write something like this and so that gets passed through and
that's how that gets rendered now.
Yeah, so I guess we could do something like this struct game render
cliprect.
You could do something like that.
Right, or something of that nature.
So that would pass these through.
And then what we could do is say, all right, let's grab whatever the
clip wreck.
Is that the new cliprect we need out of this thing.
So this is the new clip.
So we're going to take our commands clip Rex groups.
And we're going to add to it, whatever the cliprect index is then
we're going to do GL scissor.
And what we can do is make this clip.
Rect basically be exactly what we would pass to one of these things.
So you know, something like that, I don't know, we can change that
doesn't matter.
As long as we can translate it, into one of these calls we're fine.
So that will go through and that'll set the cliprect accordingly.
And another thing we could do I suppose is say that Cliff tricks 0.
Yeah well I mean we just say that clip rx0 has to be the whole screen.
that way on Entry, we can just do the
Well, you know, we could do to we don't even have to do that.
I think about it.
All we have to do is set clip rectangle next to something that isn't
possible, Right?
So if we want to we can separate a message saying that can't possibly
be true.
So every time through we'll set it, we probably also want to assert
that the cliprect index is less than the number that we that they say
we have so that we can check for out of bounds accesses their where
somebody's passing at bogus cliprect Index, right?
But that's about it.
So if we if we go with that so now we have a little thing of clip.
Rex anyone can reference a clip rect and off we go then I've got a
bunch of changes now that I need to make to support that.
So we know that this is going to be a u16 in here.
That's all fine.
And I guess what I should also do is when we do that push render
element, I'll do cliprect index and that cliprect index will be like
the group current cliprect index
Something like that.
And that should be sufficient.
I think I think so.
Yeah we'll say that.
We don't have that yet and that's fine.
UV offset is nonsense.
We got rid of that.
And so now in here this thing to actually exist that can be in render
group.
So our render group can have
This thing here that we call a game render clip.
Rect
It could just be called a Red Roof, but since it's exposed externally,
I called it that don't ask me why?
I don't know why that's just this stuff.
Right.
And that's it.
So we're basically, you know, done with the actual support part of it,
but what we want to and we now have to go through and actually do some
of the clean up some of those details.
Right.
So now we need a way of people for people to actually specify these
things.
So inside the render group, we have to have a thing in here, which is
like current cliprect index.
And that current cliprect index is going to have to get initialized to
0, right?
So when we have like,
The generation ID or whatever getting set here and we initialize this
stuff like here is the begin render group stuff in there.
We have to do current cliprect index equals zero and we're also going
to have to do a push.
We got to push data onto the push buffer or we have to reserve some
room for actually having, you know, some of these
Some of these clip Rex, like we need an actual array for them.
So, we've got a game render commands thing, but I'm not sure who
Actually where we actually get the clip direct stuff from.
So we're when we actually push, who pushes where do we push?
We push a render element.
So when we push on, when we push these on, we just use the push,
buffer base, plus the push, buffer size, so we're just kind of putting
it onto the end of the push buffer, right?
So nobody allocates any memory.
There's no it doesn't call isn't using Arena or any of that stuff.
It just does the pushing manually.
It's how that works, right?
Which doesn't make a whole lot of sense.
I don't know why we didn't bother just using the arena.
Maybe we wrote this before the arena and not sure doesn't really
matter but point being that's how that goes.
So what we could do there is we
I would say that when we initially get the push, before we push one on
there, or what we could do, we could even just hard code, the limit if
we wanted to.
I don't know if that's a good idea because we probably want to support
an arbitrary number of clip rectangles.
So, I'm not sure what the best trade-off is here.
Ideally,
I'm having a thought.
I'm having a thought and it's kind of crazy.
But I had it.
So here it comes.
You ready for this because it's banana cakes.
So, what I want to do is I want to support an arbitrary number of
clip, Rex up to the amount that would fit in our push buffer space.
So if we have, you know, a big old hunk of memory for the push buffer,
if you want to use up some of that for generating clip, Rex, I want
that to just work.
So what I'm going to do is I'm going to say well okay let's suppose
let's just I'll give you a for instance here.
Let's suppose we have an actual pushable push wrecked so I mean a
clip.
Rect so like I said before we actually have one on here
and this is a record of a clip.
Rect
And the clip bricks stores and actual game render cliprect that's the
data and then it also stores render entry clip.
Rect that's whatever the next clip.
Rect is.
Okay.
so that means in here when we do current cliprect index,
All I would say is, all right.
I'm going to do a push render element.
I'm going to do a push render elements or rather.
I'm just going to do a push cliprect, right?
And in fact, I guess I'll do it this way.
I'll
Chris cliprect who are, I'll do, push clip rect and the push cliprect
will be the whole screen.
I guess, one problem here is, I don't really know what the whole
screen is quite yet.
That's a little dicey.
I admit that.
Let's go in here.
And deal with that for one second.
Okay, so this is the first place I can actually do this, right?
So once we're in here, I would have to do something like, okay, the
render group,
the render group at this point can do
the actual operation that I want once it gets to this point, so I can
push a clip rect on
And the clip, rect can be the entire window.
okay, so that
I think is what I want and in here in addition to current cliprect
index, I need another thing which is that total or Clipper count, all
right, and now I think I'm done.
So here's the way I think this should work in when we actually do our
pushes of things like up in here where we have like push this push
that.
So here is like a push wrecked.
Call.
Before we do our push wrecked, we're going to have Push clip rect
and that's not going to have any transforms or anything.
It's just going to have what is the region that you are expecting to
clip?
Right?
Although, I guess if I wanted to, I could make it so that they go
through the transform.
I guess why not now that, I think about it.
so I could actually have one of these but then I will also have Push
clip rect
What does the direct one?
So this one's just going to be like, you know,
so, when I push the render element,
I'm going to get back a render attribute clip.
Rect
And I don't care what the sort key is the sort can be, whatever.
It doesn't matter, right?
The sort key is irrelevant and I'll show you why in a second.
So I'm going to do is going to push this on there.
I now have a place to record the clip rect properly.
Any here, I will track.
Where?
The last, whatever?
The last one.
Wait, I don't even need that.
I'm an idiot.
I don't even need that at all.
In fact, all we need is this.
We don't even need the entry.
This is getting ridiculous.
How crazy this is going to be.
We don't even need this at all.
That's not there.
So I could actually I guess I could say, let's call this.
Let's not call it that anymore.
Will literally just make it be.
One of these things.
Okay.
So we're going to want to push on one of these render into clip Rex.
So here is US pushing it on.
And then once we have it, we just set the x to the X and we just
truncate the values, right?
Because we know that, the screen can't be any bigger than that.
And so, we're just going to assume that that's fine.
Like if you were actually sitting in cliprect out in the middle of
nowhere, you wouldn't see it on the screen anyway.
And so we don't care if the value is got truncated.
In fact, that's just an error, I don't even care.
So we call Push cliprect we put that on there and we don't care
anymore.
Now the one thing we do care about is that this clip rect has to have
a number.
So every time, we push one of those on, we have to go to our group
cliprect count.
We need to know what the cliprect was.
So we have a result value that result value is going to be whatever
the cliprect count was.
So the only thing I really need to do here is store these two things.
So we store, you know, we say whatever the one you pushed as you get
back that one.
So the first time you push it is put is the perfect 0.
Next time is one blah blah.
So that happens and anytime you want to put your clip, rect on that
obeys, the object transform, you could do that as well.
Like so and that'll just follow the same path.
So you push it, you know, you push a p on there and
yeah, you get back all the rest of this nonsense and then you just
say, all right, we've got the, the wrecked, the the entry basis, the p
and the dim, so all we would need to do now is translate those into
Integer coordinates.
So we can hear what we would do.
We wouldn't ever do this part, we just once we determined that the
basis was valid, we would do the push cliprect with the actual values
that we computed.
So it's like he's 0.
Round real 32 and 32.
And so, all we're going to do here is just hoops.
All we're going to do here is just round these guys out.
So we got p 0 or I guess we could say PX and DMX.
Stop typing troubles and py and dim why?
And that pushes the cliprect on through a transform.
So if you want to use the standard notation that we've been using, you
can get that transform as well.
Alright, so,
Whenever you're actually doing stuff, you can do your cliprect in the
in clip.
Rect index nonsense and obviously these things are going to have to be
truncated.
We can't assert here.
In fact we could do a safe truncate to you 16 and that way it would it
would assert for us.
Nowhere.
Okay, so this would take a un 32 and it will assert that it's less
than the maximum value for the u16, and then it would actually convert
it.
Right.
Okay, so
Why that's result in there.
So now we have the ability to push the clip rex on
I'm over time or and I, I should take the pig head off because I'm not
really being piggy right now.
To be honest.
all right, so we've got the to push clip Rex and
what is the these guys are basically correct except for the fact that
they don't have the render group,
Under the head edit right there.
Didn't even need to see it.
Game render cliprect unknown size.
That's true because this now no longer a thing.
This is actually render entry cliprect.
Go and the platform code.
Wherever that is happening, is actually going to be render entry
clipart.
All right, so now I think we're all most there.
The only thing that we have to do is the weird stuff that I was
alluding to where I was like, this is going to be crazy.
So what I've done is I wanted to make it so that any time during the
rendering you can just record a clip.
Rect.
So that's what we do, right.
Anytime there's a clip rect comes in a new one, we stick it in the
render entry like we stick it in the push buffer as everything else is
going right?
And we remember what number it is like which ordinal it is so that we
can refer to
Anyone who wants to clip to it right?
But the problem is now what do we do?
We need a an array of those that we can access do random access to
really quickly and we want them all compacted together.
So they're nice and fit in the cache and we can just grab them out
really quickly as necessary.
Like we want it all nice and whatever.
Right?
Well, hey guess what?
Actually, when we are doing our rendering, you can actually see this
stuff occur.
Right.
We Loop through and we do our entry sorting that stuff actually has to
go through all of the entries to prepare them for that.
Right?
I mean we actually we had to actually do that work.
At some point I believe.
I could be wrong about that.
In fact, maybe this is not as smart as I thought it was because we do
we actually build those simultaneously.
There's going to be a big letdown.
Mmm.
Yeah, we do.
Oh, that's so sad.
Hmm.
So we put the sort at the end.
Well it's not really that big of a letdown.
I guess it just means.
I have to use the next pointer that I didn't really want to use,
right?
I was hoping that I wouldn't have to do that but I did.
That's not a starter huge deal, but I thought it was going to be
cooler.
Wasn't as cool as I thought it was going to be.
Whine, whine, whine.
All right.
So when we do an end render group, I guess it just assumes that the
commands are correct.
When we go to render them, it's going to have to do the sort, right?
And
And so, who actually does?
That op.
Tell me who does it?
Inside render dot CPP, when we call render commands to bitmap who
actually does that.
So, when third your handmade us, you pee
So it's right here.
So you can see we generate the render commands and then we come out of
here and we do the audio,
and then finally, at the end,
Here it is.
So here's the bit that does that rendering.
So you can kind of see here we come through and we make the sort stuff
we call win32 display, buffer in window.
And so this stuff right here is either going to call opengl renderer
commands.
So it's sort entries right here.
Does the sort
And what that what sort of entries?
Just like what, with what sort of entries does, we can do the same
thing.
With the clip Rex.
So basically what we do is say okay, there's sort memory, right?
And there's cliprect memory.
And we need to just linear rely, linearize, our clip, Rex.
So we need to like copy clip Rex
Right.
For when you're a step for X.
So that would pull them out and put them into a buffer that can hold
them in a linear fashion and be done.
So, yeah.
Lets you display buffer and window.
This is basically the same.
The exact same stuff.
It's probably something we should make a little bit more carefully.
Meaning this should just be probably utility because this is just
going to get copied.
Exactly.
And that's probably not so useful.
Fact, I'll do it.
So really we just need needed clip memory.
I spelled it wrong.
There we go.
so, this is
Going to give us the memory that we need.
And all I really need here is, I need to have a variable to store
that.
So in addition to the current sort memory, right?
I've got the current clip memory.
And yet those are adaptable.
I don't really know why at some point, we can probably say that
they're just not but, you know, for the moment they are
And if we didn't need to store that, I guess they wouldn't have to be,
but then when we come in here, we just passed the clip memory in and
back in.
Linearize it.
So I suppose the other thing, you know, one way of avoiding having to
do all this was I could have made it so that each one of the headers
has a pointer to its cliprect.
The problem is I just felt like that was really adding way too much
data to the system.
At that point, I don't know like it may be that that was a smarter way
to do it but you just point back into there but I don't know.
That's just what I
Just sort of my gut feeling on that.
So yeah, so hard to say.
But anyway,
sort entries.
Here is our linearize clip Rex.
And all this would do is exactly what I just said.
So it's just going to take essentially like a pointer to the game
entry cliprect version and it's going to walk those pointers, right?
So it's going to go like okay, game entry.
like Sam, and it's going to take
And it will overwrite.
Well, not really over, right, but set in the first place.
This pointer.
Where is it at?
It'll set this pointer.
To point to it.
So the commands clip Rex I guess.
At the outset, in fact, you could do it.
This way.
So it starts off for the pointer to one of these things, it Loops
through them and essentially what it does is it takes them and just
linearizes them into a flat list, that's it.
Like, so and that's it.
That's the entirety of that.
So it's just taking them.
So they're spread out in the bush buffer, it compacts them down into
some temporary memory that it can use as a lookup table and it's a
little piggy because now we need that next pointer.
I didn't actually want to put in there.
We can strip that out when we do the copy, but I won't have time to do
that right now.
So we could do that later.
But at the moment we can so render it could fucking needs the next
pointer in there.
Like I was saying and that also means that the render group needs to
track those.
So the render group needs to have a render entry cliprect first
wrecked kind of a thing.
And and really what we'll do instead of actually
We keeping that is, it'll be in the render commands effectively.
So,
Since multiple people can write to this.
since multiple people can write to this, I think these actually also
want to be in
In the commands only.
Is the other thing.
So I think inside the platform,
Struct since multiple people can open and close this.
The cliprect count needs to be kept entirely in here and this
probably, you know, since we don't super care, how big this struct is.
It seems Maybe?
I'll just expand it to make it a little clearer.
And that way there's no like confusion.
So in here, we'll just say, okay, we do first wrecked.
And off we go, this stuff all works exactly the same way and this
sets, the that memory up properly.
And so, then all I really need to do now is I just need to track this
inside render group,
so inside render group when we actually set these up,
when I do a push clip, rect
In here.
This is actually going to be looking at the commands and it's gonna
get the flipper account under there and similarly it's going to do the
daisy-chaining in here as well.
So the wrecked next pointer is going to get initialized and we're
going to do a standard doubly linked list on the sky.
So the commands first clip rect
let's do last wrecked.
We're just going to check to see if there have been any yet.
Then we just change it on to the end.
If there haven't been, then this is becomes, you know, both our first
in our last, you seen this pattern many times.
This is just a singly linked list that keeps a tail pointer.
And that should do it.
Now, this should not actually use these at all.
At the moment.
And I suppose we're probably not actually using
My bad.
Wrote that code incorrectly.
So this should actually be that.
Um, so yeah.
This should not do anything at the moment and yeah.
So inside our processing routines in opengl renderer commands, we want
to skip these guys so I'm not sure what the best way to do that is we
just don't ever even want these entered into the sort stream.
So really all we would do.
We're all we want to do is just push some space on for them.
And so I might actually not call the push entry stuff because now that
I'm not doing the little trick that I was saying that I was going to
do what I want to do here, instead is just say like okay.
Instead of calling push render element, I probably just want to push.
I really just want to do this, just this operation here, right?
So I want to do
No.
Header
There's some interesting stuff to that.
We should think about now that I'm thinking about too.
I wonder if we might want to play with the renderer,
Little bit.
Next week.
Now that we go through those sort entries for everything, it would
probably make more sense for the sort entry stuff, since we're doing
the sort to put the type field out in the sort entry.
You know what I mean?
Because you could put the type in like the top four bits of the index
and then you wouldn't have to jump in and then look
At you would have to do the read in the look.
That's just a, you know, it's things.
I think about sorry.
So, like the sword entry we could do get rid of this, this, the header
could, could not bother storing that, right?
So we could do like to do Casey don't store type here store in sort
index.
Something about anyway.
So in here, what I was thinking is if we were to do a render entry,
Clip.
Rect and grab one of these guys.
And don't bother initializing any of this stuff at all and we don't
put in one of these.
So all we would do is is grab some of the space.
So literally all we're doing would be guarding against overflow,
right?
So I just want that.
So assuming we can fit this thing in here.
The size is obviously going to be the size of the render entry.
Oops.
Assuming that this can fit.
That's all we need to know and then we've got it.
And everything else would work as normal?
So yeah, and I guess we do group commands.
And we're into commands.
And this needs to be cast.
Now.
I think that should remove them entirely from that list and so now we
should be indexing into our clip, Brooks properly which means we could
add more of them if
I wanted to write, I literally have two minutes left so I don't know
that we'll have time to do any of that, but if we wanted to try it we
could try pushing cliprect on here just to see if it did anything.
So if I was to say go in here and do
Let's say, where's the push wrecked?
There it is.
So if I was to do a push for to call that just took a rectangle.
So like this case.
So would you push cliprect clip rect
Obviously these things don't have a z to them.
Not the one that anyone that we care about anyway.
Oh I guess they know they do because they can be they could be sized
if we wanted them to be.
They just don't have a color.
So that would allow us to push a clip rect of a rectangle so I could
try.
Making that happen.
Okay.
yeah, so now inside debug dot CPP, if I wanted to actually do one of
these push Rex, I could try
I'm sure it won't work.
So you know, we'll have to debug it tomorrow and actually make it
work.
But what we would do is when we come in here to say, draw top clocks
list, what we would do in here when we actually create this element
rectangle and we do the push wrecked for it.
for the back and transform we would then immediately set the clip rect
so we do push clip rect
and,
I think that's yeah we do a push clip clip rect and for now we'll just
do it manually in place but we'll make a little utility for this in a
second, but we'll do like old clip rect.
And this will be our render group current clip.
Rect
And then we'll say okay the render group current cliprect index is
going to be this new clip, rect which we will push.
Here is the render group we use exactly.
The values were using to draw the rectangle.
So you want to basically clip to the same thing that we've got, right?
Doesn't need a color
Like so and then we would just restore it afterwards.
It's like a push and pop kind of thing.
Uninitialized variable.
That is true.
How did that end up happening?
Did I accidentally delete something in there?
Where are you at?
oh, it's because
it's because this is actually a different dim.
So it's that dim and then this is like,
This is the bassist Tim going to be.
Thank you, compiler, that was handy.
So, yeah, so that's where we're at at the moment.
And like I said, we're not working, right?
Because this, if we were working, that would clip, right?
So, we would see like that, right?
There would be clipping properly and at the moment, it's not.
So that's what we can debug tomorrow and we can also do questions, are
valid.
Maybe I'll do a couple questions about weep.
I don't have very much time for them so we can do questions on all of
that stuff as well.
So we can see in here.
When we do have our clipping right, see what the clip actually set to.
That's the full screen, which is what we might expect to see we, then
come in with a different clip.
Rect index of one.
It's also the same though.
So here is one that's trying to clip to something else.
Oh you know what?
We never enable GL Caesar.
So GL scissor is one of those things that doesn't actually take effect
unless you enable it.
So when we do our enables and we set up our like initial state
we never actually handle that, so maybe
Might be scissor test.
Yeah, maybe that will clue us in a little.
Hey look.
So actually that whole thing did work the first time, which is
ridiculous.
But hey, there you go.
So now we have clipping and the only thing we aren't that we would
need to do tomorrow.
Then is make the software renderer obey it as well, right?
So in here if
Do the platform control.
So if we switch to the software renderer,
What the heck?
Oh, right.
Because the GL says, ER, is still enabled, right?
You can see that.
It's not actually doing it.
Let me fix that one.
Choose me.
when we do opengl blit to screen or whatever it is open, till this
needs to GL disabled fuel sensor test,
If we don't want that test enabled, when we're doing that.
My point was, if I go in here and I set it to the other, renderer, you
can kind of see how we don't clip anymore.
Right.
So our software renderer isn't properly clipping to that region and
that's because we haven't told it about it, but and maybe I should
just go ahead and do it because we're, you know, I'm kind of in the
mood.
So when we do render commands to bitmap, right,
And we do draw a rectangle.
You can see that we pass the cliprect in here, right?
So we have we are we are often times passing the cliprect.
You can see the clip Brooke getting past but the clip rect is not
actually being used or rather the clip.
Rect is only being used for are tiled renderer, but we're not actually
ever updating it to anything different.
So we could call this our base cliprect if we wanted to, for example.
And then what we can do is every time we get the header, we can do the
exact same thing we did before.
And instead just take our
Take our actual clip, rect from the base cliprect.
Keep the same exact thing we were doing in the opengl renderer where
we said, like hey, you know, as we go through anytime you see in the
header a different clip, rect than the one we had what we'll do in
that case is will just update the one we have.
So instead of making some call the GL to update cliprect will actually
update our cliprect instead.
Now what we have to do to do that, right?
Because we've got an existing clip, practice the tiled.
Region.
Remember we drew we render the screen in our software, renderer in
tiles, so that each thread can render different tile, right?
So, you know, someone's rendering this, someone's rendering this,
whatever.
So we need to clip it to this but now, we also have some cliprect that
specified for the, for the actual rendering that's, that's been
specified.
So what we need to do is we need to intersect these two regions,
right?
So what we need to do is say alright, what we want to do is whatever
the cliprect that's coming out of this thing is, right.
Right, this thing here.
We want to do intersection of those.
Now is rectangle to eye.
we, you know, we could just use these rectangle to eyes and look, we
already have an
So I'm going to do that.
So I'm going to say, okay, our clip, rect
Is just the intersection.
I didn't even know.
We had rectangle, two eyes in this clip.
Code base.
We're going to take our base clip, rect and we're going to intersect
it with the one that's coming from from this thing.
Okay, and that's what we're going to do.
So I'm going to say that and what's going to happen here is we're
going to have to change because I would rather do it this way.
We're going to change our render group stuff to actually use rectangle
to I in here.
Like so.
Okay.
And so in here, what I'll do is we have our wrecked and our wrecked
has a min
Like so.
And all this is going to be is us just taking exactly the same values
that you had before and encoding them slightly differently, right?
What, what is rectangled to buy than math that h?
Oh, so we actually store them directly.
Okay.
And so then, all we have to do is translate the GL scissor to that.
So Minix and Max are end and mean why are the same, but the width is
now in coded differently.
So we'll have to compute that by taking the max X and subtracting them
in Acts.
Same thing with the why.
So let's check to see to make sure I didn't mess up the opengl
renderer by switching that to that.
There we go.
And now let's go back to our software renderer.
And see if that works now.
Hey, look.
It does.
So, there we go.
Now we've got clipping in both renderers and everyone's happy.
I will take the briefest of brief q and A's.
I wonder why debug and takes so much time.
Shouldn't the time be taken in debug collation.
Because I don't know exactly what's happening at debug and that would
make it take more time.
But oh wait, no, debug and test a draw.
It's doing all this construction stuff.
Popcorn 0, x 90, what are top three reasons for fps to go down?
What?
I don't know.
What do you mean you mean across all games ever?
Or
Or what?
Some of the right will cliprect be used outside of debug and where
might be like, I mean, I don't know but it could be used.
In the game somewhere.
It depends if we upgrade our render, at some point to do fancier
things like Matt cats and stuff.
Where, you know, we might want to limit the region that's rendered
because we're rendering some stuff that's going to get composited or
whatever, even if we didn't update the renderer, you could imagine.
Like, let's say that your your rendering, there's like a hole in the
floor and you can see down to something else, well, rather than render
the whole thing under.
Hind there and then render the thing with just the hole in the floor
and it like overdraw the whole screen you could clip out those regions
for efficiency obviously.
But
Can you elaborate on the OD plan to replace your drag function with
and move entity?
Not at the moment?
Obviously, that's that's a topic for when we go to replace it and I'll
show how to derive it and so on.
If you con, how about making the topless scrollable?
Since now we clip it it can be painful when you start profiling a lot
more so we can do that just as an exercise in how to make something
scrollable.
But in truth, we only ever care about the top couple of entries.
Anyway, you never care about anything that's down here, right?
I mean, maybe in some academic sense, you might, but for the most part
it's just not relevant, right?
So, what actually happens is, you only ever look at these things
because these are where all your time is being spent.
So you don't care anything.
That's anything that's below.
1% is so irrelevant that you just don't care.
Blah 238.
When does clipping overdrawn areas cost more than just drawing them?
Never
it never crossed more.
It can only not save you time but it never costs you more.
Because everything always has to be clipped anyway.
It has to be clipped to the screen area.
So, narrowing, the clipping can only save you time.
You don't ever, you always had to steal clip.
in certain older in scenarios that
That don't bear much.
Resemblance to how we render things today.
When clipping was more about doing geometric, clipping on stuff, then
it's possible that it could be more expensive because you subdivide
more triangles more times.
But that's that's very unlikely in the way today's render as work.
But in the old days when you did a lot of geometric triangle clipping,
having to do all the clipping for the triangles could have been more
expensive.
Obviously, that's not so relevant in the thing where you got a bunch
of rectangles, but it imagine like a 3D in a more of a 3D rendering
kind of scenario.
SS SS McGrath that's not entirely true.
The state change on the clip isn't free.
If the size changes minor it's probably not worth it.
Yeah, I guess that's probably true.
Like if you were literally clip changing clipping, rectangles all the
time for no real reason then maybe just the traffic of like hey
I had to like update these four registers you know, on the GPU or not
registers but these four entries and memory on the GPU or whatever,
that could be something you might care about.
When you switch between the renderers, the viewing frame time is
obviously affected are the clocks in our newly clipped box.
Also affected by the renderers.
I ordered distributed differently.
Yeah, so I mean, first of all one thing I probably should do we have
it tested in a while and I should probably do this is you know if
we're looking at profiling data you know generally you wouldn't be
looking at profiling data much in the unoptimized build.
So I'd probably first start by saying like let's at least turn that on
and I could
So turn on turn off handmade slow.
So we weren't asserting and stuff.
So, we had a, you know, a lot less code happening there as well.
And then we can look at the profile.
And now we can sort of see a more realistic view of like, okay.
In the actual thing that ships to somebody, what would it look like?
And okay, that's what it looks like.
So now if I come here and I turn on the software, renderer, you can
now see a more realistic sort of version of how expensive it is to do
some of these things, right?
And so you can see that now, 50% of our time is spent just rendering
stuff in software, right?
And and that's what you would expect.
Because that's what almost all the time is.
So in the actual game right in here, amusingly enough, debug collation
still dominates the time, which is pretty hilarious.
Actually, I guess that's because we call pixel fills so many times,
not sure whether we would really want to do that, that's probably
Let me, let me take that out.
Because that's generating a ton of things which we probably don't want
to generate.
So inside handmade render.
I'm going to take these ignored time function stuff, and I'm going to
go ahead and actually make them ignored
oh,
Okay.
Alright, so now I think we won't be spending so much time on that
collation.
So here's our, you know, Hardware rendered profile
Here's our software rendered profile.
So you can see, you know, basically all the time being spent in do
Todd render work, which that is what we would expect.
You can see our frame rate is not particularly great, but again, some
of that's actually it's counting having to render all this stuff as
well.
Which so isn't quite Fair because there's a bunch there, this is just
a lot of rendering that it wouldn't otherwise Pat be having to do, so
that's a little bit.
You know, what we could do is do something more like this.
This, right?
And then go in here and say pause and scroll back, you can see the
difference in the frame times.
Like, you know, there's a, this is a 24 Ms frame, 27, Ms, frame.
And then you get out to the ones where it's on, and it's 45
milliseconds.
So, it's quite a bit different when you are an art rendering stuff in
the profile view.
This is just a lot of work for under because all of these are little
these are all little texture map.
Fills you know, if we wanted to optimize that in software, we do a
bunch of rectilinear Blitz type stuff.
That was highly optimized for fonts or something so that we could draw
this a lot faster, but we don't really care about that, you know,
because you know, this isn't really part of part of it for us.
But anyway, so then if we go into the game code here, like so,
You can see that we're still even with that.
We're doing pretty good on render.
Time should probably clear the screen but it's pretty good.
Right?
And if you look at what's actually taking the time, it's kind of a
little bit odd to be honest.
I'm not sure I really understand why frame display is taking so much
time.
Oh well actually we did determine this.
It's actually it is it's just Windows eats up a ton of our time.
Yeah, that actually is Windows being crappy.
Why is draw a rectangle still?
Being clocked separately.
And that's a lot of rectangles.
18,000 rectangles.
Why are there 18000, rectangles?
Is that really a reasonable number of rectangles?
I mean, there's a lot of rectangles here.
And then there's all these rectangles in here, but 18,000 of them.
I don't know if I believe 18,000 rectangle, drawers.
Got called.
So, these should actually always be time.
All right, 18,000 does not sound right to me.
that's,
that's weird.
I feel like,
I feel like something's up there.
We should probably actually keep timing stuff like that and do a
little bit of a thing to try and ascertain why.
So many rectangles are being called
Yeah, that's really weird.
Anyway, you can see how long the this is just a tremendous amount of
time that it takes before Windows actually gets like we're done in
half the time and windows takes a long time to get us to the screen.
I don't know if that's because of the vsync or some other weird
because there's a one frame lag or I don't know what's going on, but
it's kind of interesting.
Like we'd actually be hitting 60 hertz right now.
If it wasn't for this.
That's so darn cool.
By the way.
Yeah.
Long billion.
What does opengl do when you enable GL scissor test?
It's basically saying that.
Instead of clipping to the window boundary clip to the boundary, that
you've specified because opengl always is actually clipping.
Obviously I mean, it doesn't corrupt memory and right into a no man's
land.
So you know,
Here is the screen.
Here is the scissor, right?
This is whatever you passed a GL scissor if you GL enable.
GL scissor test.
Then it's actually going to use what you pass, you'll says are.
Otherwise it'll just always use the whole screen.
So it's basically just saying do you want this rectangle on or not?
I don't even know why they have that but
it's just kind of I guess the weight opengl does things like enable
and disable.
I would have just said you always have to set the scissor so if you
don't want to clear that set it to the whole screen, right?
but, you know,
alright, I am going to wrap it up because I want to eat dinner.
I don't really know when dinner is
I didn't make it today.
So, let's see.
Close this out here.
And made.
Switch back to debug.
And I'm going to go to the to-do list and I'm going to say and I think
we certainly got logging in there and thread visualization.
I want to know.
What's the deal with 18,000 rectangles?
So, I don't know what's going on with that.
All right.
Okay.
Thank you everyone for joining me for this episode of handmade here.
It's been a pleasure coding with you.
As always, if you would like to follow along, with series at home, you
can always pre-order the game.
It is available on how many here at org and it comes with the source
code, so you can play around, even as we develop it, we also have
Forum site.
You can go to where you can ask questions and that Forum site will be
going down this weekend because we are transferring it over to the
hand, were handmade.
Network people, they have graciously offered to maintain it.
I don't like maintaining web stuff as you know.
So the folks on handmade Network are going to be taking it over this
weekend, that means it will be unavailable for a couple days while
like it gets moved over and tested basically so that everyone so that
it's not obviously busted or anything like that.
So that will be happening this weekend so you won't be able to access
the forms for two days or so.
So, but then next week the forums will be back as normal.
They'll just be hosted on handmade Network and I believe they're
planning on cleaning them up a bit too.
So hopefully, the forms won't be so janky.
They might be a little bit nicer because they'll be running on a
cleaner for him system, then the stupid Joomla one.
That was the one that was running before.
We also have a patreon page if you want to support the video series,
which we, of course always provide free of charge
You can do that at patreon.
We also have a tweetbot, the tweets cut.
You, if you wanted when we live in the next summer, going to be live.
Will be next week because tomorrow is the day off.
It's my rocket movie day.
So we probably won't be around for the stream.
That is about it.
I hope everyone has a good full weekend of programming.
I'll see you back here probably on Monday but check the Tweet before
the schedule until then have fun coding and I'll see you guys on the
internet.
Take it easy everyone.