Time start recording.
There we go.
Okay.
Hello everyone and welcome to handmade hero.
The show.
We could a complete game live on stream.
We are in the process now of working out how we're going to do sort of
our final entity world-building kind of stuff.
And yesterday, we ended with, I guess, what we did is we sort of ended
with the concept of the hero, be able to stand on something and that
something could move, right?
And
What we want to do now is sort of start finishing up that process
because I had talked about how I wanted the game to always have the
understanding that a, any individual entity is who is supposed to be
walking or moving or hopping on the ground has to occupy points on the
ground very specifically.
So it's, you know, it's it's an action game and you move the head of
the character around fairly freely, but where the character standing
and where everyone else is standing.
It's almost like chess in a way where you are occupying, a particular
square.
And only one thing can occupy that square.
And so, what has to happen is?
We have to have a solid understanding of where every entity is in
terms of what Square they're on.
And so we sort of did the first part about that yesterday but we
haven't done the second part.
And so that's what I'm going to look at.
If I can stop my yogurt from falling over.
All right, so let me just show you what that is.
Also I guess I should always remind you.
Today, stay 284.
So if you want to follow along at home, day 283 is the source code.
So, here we go.
Yeah.
So here is where we left off.
And as you can see, we still kind of have, you know, our basic hopping
is still working exactly the way that it used to and with the
exception of our rendering, that's all kind of, okay, so far.
But what we did yesterday, is we just wanted to prove, okay, I can
kind of go down and and ride this thing.
Unfortunately, we have this problem and this was the thing that I was
talking about, we need to finish up.
Is that currently, we still don't really in our entity code process.
The concept that the hero is
On a particular thing, we always use the point that is closest to his
head.
The entity is head as the thing we should jump to.
And so as you might expect what ends up happening as as the hero gets
into a situation where their head is between two points, it can sort
of wig out.
The body will keep jumping between two different things, right?
And so we want to obviously we don't ever want that to happen and now
that we have this more sort of specific concept of where the hero
actually is
Way.
And the concept of this traversable is and all that sort of stuff, I
want to basically fix all of that.
How is that even possible?
That looks like a bug.
A pretty good bug though.
You see that?
I like that.
That's probably a bug in our packing but I want it to happen again.
How do I make it happen again?
You can see that it kind of wigs out there, it jumps, right.
And I feel like there's a bug in the in the packing of that guy or
something like that, that we should look at but that's I guess a
separate issue.
But anyway, so first things first.
Let's actually go in and finish the code that we were working on
before.
And then we can look in at the sort of the way that these things are
packed and make sure we don't have any bugs there.
We can put in some assertions for packing where we can pack and unpack
something and make sure that it's not messed up, right?
Anyway, so how do we do that?
How do we get out of that?
Sort of hacky place of not really having the person understand where
the standing?
Well, we already named this thing standing on.
And so really, all we need to do, is start to take our entity
controlling code more seriously, and actually treat it as such, right?
So, the standing on
Where are you?
There we go.
So the standing on when we come through here, you can kind of see that
it's super janky in that what ends up happening is the only thing that
we use to determine whether or not we're going to hop.
Is the distance that the body is from the head that's it and so we
don't really wait.
Is that actually true?
That's like not even with that thing means actually the body Delta is
the closest unit.
So it's not even that, that's not what that means.
It's the distance to that point to whatever the point is, what we want
to go to.
So we need to this needs to not be what's happening anymore, right?
But we need to not make this be the code.
So let's think through
A little bit more how we want this to happen, right?
And if we go ahead you know I can I can sort of show you as well.
What happens if I was just to sort of if their this out, right?
If I was to say, this is not a thing and instead all I'm going to do
is just do found.
Well, in fact, you know what I can do, the easiest way to do it is
just to say, found equals false, so assume that it never finds a new
point to stand on, right?
So essentially what happens is, if I never textures if I never do
anything else, right, you can see what happens here.
And basically we just stretch out the hero infinitely far, and the
heroes head will come to rest above whatever point there, you know,
most closely aligned with right.
And that's not like I said not particularly useful for us and it's not
what we actually want.
So the first thing we should probably do.
Is make the head be a little bit more specific in how it operates,
right?
And there's two things that I want to do.
Here one is that I'd like
Keep the Z height of the head strictly controlled, so that if it's on
the body, it's always in a very specific Place, write it.
In other words, it doesn't float all around in some kind of random
way, right?
So there's that.
And then the other thing that I want to do is if you can't jump.
So let's say that.
This was actually the correct thing that should happen.
The heroes body is meant to stay on that square and like maybe there's
something.
Thing in the way here or, you know, there's something occupying the
square, so it couldn't go there.
If there's something in the way, then what I want to have happen, is
when the heroes head hits the halfway point, I don't want it to go any
further, right?
So I basically want the heroes had to stop like right there and and
not be able to go.
So even if I'm holding down that button instead of it just continuing
on like this and to Ridiculousness, I don't ever want to allow that
situation to occur if that makes sense.
So I want to stop
So that's the stuff that we need to work on for the head and then what
we need to work on is when the head does get to that halfway point, we
want to trigger the hopping event so we can say okay if we can get
access to that point then allow the Hop to occur and the head can
continue going right.
So that's what we want again.
It's pretty tricky, control scheme.
It's, you know, a lot of times is way simpler.
The way a player controller Works where you just kind of move it in
whatever Direction the person pushes and you're done with it.
In this case, we have a much more complicated scenario.
So this code is going to be a lot more complicated again.
That's just par for the course.
Not a problem.
You just gotta, you know, got to be willing to write the hard code
when the hard code comes up.
So let's start by thinking about how we're doing this.
First of all, what we might want to do is just have the body, maybe be
something, where it's hopping, is a little more predictable, so maybe
we'll do something like say, okay, let's let's pretend we're not going
to do any of this stuff.
Right, and let's I don't know what's going on with facing Direction
here.
We just copy that in.
I'm going to, I'm going to go ahead and pull that out here as well.
Okay, so I've got the facing Direction and I've got the DP here
initialized.
I've got the entity, pset2, wherever whatever.
The thing is that, we were standing on when we're in the planted mode,
so that's fine.
And then we've kind of got our other stuff here.
The dtdt Bob, we always I guess.
During this Loop.
So I'm going to put that a little closer to here.
There we go.
And the floor displace is always set based on the head Delta, which is
also fine.
So I'm going to recompile this here.
So really what I want to do now is just kind of replace this logic
that we were using, which is about what we're supposed to do, right?
Whether we're supposed to do,
The Hop or not and what's supposed to happen, right?
So what I want to do there is I'd like to do something where we sort
of say, okay?
If we're planted I don't want to start hopping unless somebody has
told us to start hopping right?
And maybe that hopping is some kind of, I don't know, it's some kind
of a request.
Maybe that hopping is actually triggered by the head for example.
So maybe this in and of itself.
Elf is actually going to be moved out, right?
Let's say we do something like this.
So we come up here to the head and we say that this is going to be
something that happens on the head side of things, right?
And I don't know exactly what will happen with it yet but we're going
to put it out there and similarly, I guess we could also copy all this
code in as well.
I don't know that we're going to use it.
But we could try.
So now, here we go with the
With the code that we have before.
And if you look, it's really just the floor displace.
I think that uses the head anymore.
Nothing else uses the head really.
So it's so I think what we could do is also move this head stuff.
Move that down.
Because now, all of these things.
The rest of the how the body Hops and stuff, all of that stuff, is now
something that we could allow to have happened separately, right?
Meaning, the hopping is sort of isolated from whether there was a head
that was gone controlling it.
And the reason that I care about this is that we're eventually going
to want hopping creatures, potentially, and we would want to reuse
this code, right?
Because there's no reason why we would have to change the code in that
case.
all right, so
in movement mode planted.
So again, this can come down here and this can be something that just
says, hey,
Is all of this code Duty, Bob.
So, all of this code is not based on the head either.
And this is just if we're in the planted mode.
So, there we go.
so now we've sort of taken the head out of that, and
I guess.
Also you know since the head distance is probably something will be
Computing more elsewhere.
I guess we could also move even this part we could move this up to the
head controller so that we never I get you right.
I mean because I guess there's really no reason not to do that as
well.
So the head controller can trivially just reach in there and do that,
right?
Okay, so now what should happen in theory is no matter what I do at
the head.
The body should just stay there and not do anything, right?
And that is exactly what happens.
Okay, so now let's go ahead and expand up this code and start to work
on the head controller.
So on the head controller,
empty space there.
Hmm.
Are we going to get new indentation stuff anytime soon?
Allen is indentation on the menu.
I don't really know what's going on with for coder at the moment.
Maybe that's not current thing.
I thought I saw Alan.
I'm here earlier, let's see.
So in through this code, what we want to do here is say, alright,
let's re-enable the parts that are have nothing to do with the
movement first, because those are the ones that we already know, we
kind of want, right?
So what we actually want to do through here is rather than talking
about head and entity and that source of I think what I'd rather do is
have head and body be specific, even and rather that way when we move
code between the two, it won't change.
Right?
So I don't know if we ever look at the body in here.
I thought we did, but I'm not sure.
It looks like we actually don't, I thought we did, but maybe we don't
anymore, I don't know.
But either way, when we come in here to do the controlling for the
hero head, what I want to do is I want to go ahead and make it so that
we track The Head and the body.
Like so,
Right.
And then we can just say well if there's a body will do body things.
If there isn't, there isn't right?
And so this code was not using the body before this code is using the
body before.
So now, I'll just go ahead and say if the body exists, then through
here.
What I actually want to do is replace the word entity everywhere with
the word body.
Oops.
because that's what was previously, The Entity that was being talked
about their but now isn't and so what we can do here is say, well,
alright, all of this stuff that was previously before
Requiring the body.
Now, existence here, and again, anywhere that it was talking about
entity.
I will just go ahead and force it to talk about the oops.
I don't know why.
I can't spell entity for some reason.
So, there we go.
Body is not am a member of entity.
Wait, what?
It's not.
Is it head?
What is it?
That is never mind and so yeah.
So the only thing that we have left that is now something that's a bit
of a little bit.
Tricky is the bounciness.
When we're in the movement mode planted, we were trying to make our
bounciness be proportional for to how far away the head was right.
And so I don't know to what degree to what degree we want to split the
code between these two, right?
But you see I'm kind of figure out like exactly how much should live
in one and versus how much should live in the other and a lot of that
has to do with how they would separate out to whether or not.
You're both operating separately versus operating together.
And the question here is just that well, this is really something that
DDT Bob, seems like it should be kind of something that's more related
to the body, but
I guess it really only requires T head distance and T had distance was
not a particularly complicated thing to compute, right?
It's just the difference between these two.
It's just this value here and so I think we could probably safely have
left it down below.
So maybe we will.
Oops.
Because if I look at this, it's only head Delta that gets used
separately.
So what I could do is say, all right here is, you know, the
hero body stuff in here.
We could just say
oops.
That we want to set the DDT Bob.
If there is a head
Then compute the head Delta.
Right now in here we want to keep the same naming scheme so I think I
want to get like I said I want to go with something like this where no
matter which controller I mean I can always talk about the head in the
body and just say, if I have a head, if I have a body whatever.
So I'm just going to go ahead and reverse what's happening here like
so
I'm going to go ahead and run.
All right.
So now, we can see essentially, What's Happening Here is we're just
getting that sort of stretching out action is happening, but we
haven't reenable the rest of the code, right?
So let's go ahead and go back in and try to make that happen.
Yeah, so let's see how this stuff works.
When we have a body were trying to find the closest reversible.
We're seeing if we found it if we were, we would switch the mode.
Oh, so interestingly enough that should have started.
We should have been able to initiate a hop, but it didn't initiate a
hop.
So I think that I messed something up because we owe I see what it is.
There we go.
Still not, right.
Not correct.
So, let's see what we've got here.
This is just sitting DDT Bob, which is when there's the head, it
wanted to do that sort of head distance Bob down, so that's fine.
And with hopping here, this should all be independent of the head so
that all looks correct as well.
And the DDT Bob update still happens in here, all of that seems
reasonable.
So I think we just have to make sure that I didn't mess up, something
in this code.
When we snap the head in the body, we come down through here.
We are updating the
Adds sort of idea of where it is and then we come in and say if we got
a body which we know is should be true, right?
Maybe it's not.
I should double check, but I'm pretty sure it should be.
I guess I should.
double check to see that we are not hopping or I should say planted
Because otherwise, I'd keep sort of setting it back, right?
So if we look here, we can say that.
The head Delta is based on these things and I guess I suppose,
I suppose those things actually now can stay down in here.
As you can see, it's kind of a little tricky like to figure out
exactly where I want everything because each thing is going to kind of
is going to want to be potentially split apart but yeah, I only want
to do the move.
I only want to update to a hop if I'm standing obviously so that has
to.
Yeah, that has to be changed this copy in works fine.
As does all the rest of this I think so.
Should be good to go.
So we're almost there but we are slammed code.
Now that actually a shears us is not always operating properly which
that code right.
Is I put it in the planting code here, but I guess that's not what we
should do.
I guess that we wanted to have
Happen, always, which makes sense because you want to be continuous,
right?
I want to be able to set up by the floor, displace in the y-axis and
stuff continuously as we go.
So that should probably be stuck outward, right?
So I'm going to go ahead and put this up here.
I'm going to say that head Delta equals nothing.
I'm going to say if we have a head we will compute the head Delta
and then, this code can
Update based on that.
Always, because why not?
And so, that's back to the way we were doing it.
Now, except now, the choice to hop is being made by the head, right?
The head is basically telling the body, you should hop, okay?
So now what I'm going to do is I'm going to go back to the code for
the head and I want to now kind of collapse these together, right?
Because we were doing, we're doing double get closest reversible on
the head right now and so I just kind of want to make that into one
code path.
So, try to think of how this should work.
Exactly.
I guess I still want to start off doing the same thing that I was
doing which is to say that I guess I don't really need the concept of
the closest P because it wouldn't happen outside this anymore.
It only happened inside.
So when I come through here and say, get closest reversible, what I
want to do is I want to, you know, entity is head.
Obviously, I still want to get that and say, is there a new closest
reversible to the one that I to a different one that I was on before?
And what I want to do,
Now is I want to actually compare those so instead of before where I
was just like oh is where's the point relative to my body or stuff
like that?
I want to say is the closest reversible, the one, the body is standing
out or not, right?
And furthermore, I suppose this code should probably be
Well I'm going to I'm going to do too, but I'm going to do it in two
sections.
I'm not going to try to merge them just yet.
So what I want to do is say, all right, if there is a body, then I
might need to do something.
If it's not that I'm headless, I'm just a floating head, right?
So if there's a body attached to me, what I want to do is say, well,
is the traversable that I found is that reversible and I'll do a test
like are equal.
if this reversible is equal to the one that the body is standing on,
Then I don't really have anything to do because the traversable that
the head would want to be on top of and the one of the bodies on top
of are the same.
If they're not the same, that's when I actually start to care, right?
So if they're not the same, then I want to started to do this stuff,
right?
I want to do this.
I want to basically say all right I don't really know that I care
about this.
I just want to say straight up whether whatever the body Delta is none
of that stuff.
None of this matters anymore.
What I want to say is if they're different right?
If the two of them are different, don't even care about any of this
either.
I'm just saying straight up if I'm not standing on the one that my
head's on top of then I want to do the movement, right?
I want to move to the traversal, I found in the hopping mode, right?
And furthermore, I can probably set this out which is to say
That if the body is not in the movement mode, if the body is not
planted, if it's already in the process of hopping, then there's not
much I can do, right.
So leave it that way, okay?
You no longer need to do this.
We can let that code flow through and it should work actually quite
the same as it was working before.
And we don't need to do any of this anymore or at least I don't
suppose.
We should, we can still sort of do any updating we wanted here.
Oops.
So we'll leave that as is
So now we just need a couple of helper functions.
What's going on here?
Closest P.
So that just, I guess we do want to copy that one piece of code.
That was getting the locate, the actual location of the traversable.
I'm going to move this over here so I'm not behind my head so much.
I can't see the code.
Do we never get that?
I guess, we don't know.
Oops.
so if we go here, too,
The code will be a reversible I guess the closest p is now just
whatever that traversable P is.
Right.
So in here where we were using closest Pi can just do closest P equals
traversable P, right?
Is equal.
Now is just a thing that we need to do in the end of the code.
When we have these traversable references, all we need to do there is
just say like okay,
These will be equal.
If they are the same entity in the same index, very very
straightforward, right?
So the result equals, you know, entity pointer
Oops.
A three-pointer equals B entity pointer.
And a entity.
Index equals B entity index and a entity.
Sorry, index equals B index.
Now technically, I only have to compare
The end of the index or the entity pointer because they're actually a
union.
So I suppose what I'll do is I'll just compare the one that would ever
be larger of the two I suppose.
But what I really want to do there, just say compare, the holes sighs,
the whole thing and I'm not really sure of the most way to do that of
the best way to do that.
So I'm hoping in the compiler.
Would just figure it out.
You know.
But you know, if it doesn't, it doesn't, it's not going to be a big
cost or anything like that.
So, let's see the ID does not operate, sorry.
We've got to do value there.
Okay.
P is not it's not.
I thought it was.
I guess I have to call get some space because to wrestle I guess I
have to call get some space.
So now we should be doing this the same stuff we're doing before but
semantically, right?
And in theory, nothing should change.
And it doesn't look like it did.
Right?
So because we haven't put in any logic other than closest point.
So closest point will still be exactly what happens always.
So yeah.
So now what we need to do is actually put in some Logic for whether or
not you should be hopping based on how far you're pushing the head
away from the body, right?
Okay.
So in here, right, what I want to do is I think what I want to do now
is actually start going back towards the sort of
the the head Delta concept which is to say that
when we get the closest reversible to the head, I guess I actually
want it to be the closest reversible cast downward would be the first
thing.
Like I want it to actually be relative to where the head is.
The thing that I'm having trouble understanding, right, is the head is
should be at the same point as the body.
So I guess, I'll be honest, I don't really understand why it's ever
this code.
I feel like shouldn't be picking
I feel like this code should not be choosing to move.
to be honest with you because I feel like the head
Is not a B is in the same place as the body.
So when I cut, right?
Because remember the head is, is a weird bitmap right now.
And so the ground point for the head is still in the same place I
think.
I mean, I can double-check that, but I'm pretty sure.
So technically these two should be calling the same function, right?
I'm not calling the same function but they should always be picking
the same point and I don't know why wherever getting that that choice
to jump to something else,
That's real confusing to me.
Furthermore, it's like kind of confusing what's happening to with the.
Yeah, I just, I think.
So I'm going to say that that's not an artifact of how we're choosing
it.
I'm going to say that's just a bug.
And so I'm going to investigate that like a bug because I don't think
that should be happening.
So, the first thing I want to do is I want to know where these
entities actually are.
I want to know where their their actual ground p is right?
And so the I might draw it, but I might also the first thing I might
do is actually just debug value it, right?
So, in hero head, I want to do debug value.
And I want to do that in.
In.
Where is it here?
A body as well.
So yeah, let's see.
So it's behaving roughly like I would expect so far, which is to say,
the bottom one is, obviously the body and you can see that it moves
when it hops and it comes to rest on the correct position.
The top one is a spring.
So it like, relaxes back to that exact position eventually.
So now let's hop on here and see what's going on.
I mean, those points are just real real close, right?
I mean, they're really just not that different.
So why is get closest reversible picking?
Something different there.
I don't know.
So let's take a look because that's that's important.
I think that's a bug.
May being it closes reversible.
Or at least in the way I'm conceptualizing.
How this thing is working.
So I don't want to go any further till
Have that sorted because that's just obviously bad.
So yeah,
All right.
so, let's go over to
Handmade some region.
And let's look at closest reversible.
So here is get closest reversible.
Here's how it works.
We Loop through the entities and we Loop through their volumes.
We call get some space traversable.
We look to see, I don't know, we still call it head to point which is
good.
Let's maybe call that two point.
And then, let's take a look at what's going on here.
So there's two point.
First we're going to do is we sort of did this thing for fussing with
the Z.
Let's take that out of the equation, temporarily because if we still
get the bug with that, that at least then we don't have to think about
whether that was involved, right?
Good.
So it has nothing to do with our crazy like preferential treatment.
We're just getting something unusual happening.
So looking at this and we get the since faced reversible.
So we look at those that to point p.
P - from P.
We take a look at the length squared.
We look to see if that looks for is better.
We then snap the entity pointer and the index.
And we update the closest distance squared to be whatever it is that
we expect it to be and that makes good sense, right?
So, that looks pretty reasonable.
So we're probably going to step through that and see what's going on.
Let me do one of the thing.
What I would like to do as well, is in World mode here, where we've
got this entity siming happening.
When we call get closest reversible to the Head.
Let's just actually call it on the body instead and see what happens
there.
So now, we're not even using the head point.
So the Divergence between the head point and the body point is not
even relevant anymore, right?
Oh right, I can't do that until I actually get over there.
Can I do matter?
Not a problem.
I'll just use livecode reloading, which is so awesome.
All right, so let's go ahead and
change this to body.
Hop on there.
We can pile.
Oh man, he hopped off before.
I could do it.
There we go.
All right, so maybe I use Loop Live code anything to do this.
Poop.
There we go.
So now I'm going to change this to body, so now the dude can't move.
And now I'm going to restore the loop point so that we're on there.
Whoa.
Yeah, we have a crazy bug.
It looks like it's, it looks like the Z values for our entities are
not getting packed properly.
I'm kind of glad we've got this caught in a loop.
Now we can actually debug it to right.
It looks like what's happening is that point is getting levered up
somehow into a different region like the Z packing is not working.
You know I'm saying.
Let me take a look at what's going on there.
Because maybe that's actually both bugs.
So, here is n Sim and some has this chunk Delta thing.
And what happens with the chunk Delta is we basically add it in before
we pack our entity down.
I'm not sure this.
That's a good place for that for obvious reasons, because we actually
should be doing that in the pack code, right?
I mean that's exactly that's that's the third thing that we do in the
pack code but let me find the bug first before I go making changes.
So in here you can see we take the region World chunky and the region
origin.
This is the chunk that entity is being stored into.
This is the origin of the same region and that Delta, right is the one
that we want to remove.
If we're subtracting.
That junk Delta off and let's also go kind of back here and just
double check.
So in here we update the camera that shouldn't really matter because
the camera doesn't change that chunk Delta anywhere, right?
So the fact that the camera gets updated here isn't really an issue
and doesn't really matter to us.
So then we come back in here and we do our, we do our MVP Plus chunk
Delta and then we pack The Entity into the world.
And that seems fine.
So if I come over,
Because I wanted to point out one of the thing so it's also not just
the hero who is moving.
It's actually the point they're standing on.
So it's actually that entity that's getting packed wrong to begin
with, OR getting moved incorrectly.
So we don't even have to look at the standing on part of the hero, so
we can take the hero out of the situation entirely, which is nice,
that makes sense.
Okay, so when this is being packed, I want to go into the world code.
And take a look at pack pack pack in a trunk.
So here's back entity into chunk.
And essentially what we do here is we just pack the references but we
leave the rest of the data untouched.
I guess I don't really know.
We pass the world position at.
And we're passing entity pee.
an entity pee and chunk PR the same thing in this case,
Right.
This is the map chunk map into chunk space.
It's basically just asking which chunk The Entity should be stored in,
right?
So we're saying hey if this is the or the chunk around which your
stored currently and here is the entity
Give me that Delta.
I'm sorry - tell me, where
That would actually be now.
How is that code even working?
Because we haven't looked at that in a while you're there.
So that's taking an offset that's dividing by the chunk Tim.
as taking a look at the tile and the tile relative portions,
Yes.
Oh really
I mean really this all seems at this point.
Quite a bit overblown as well.
Because really all we need, here is an F mod, right?
We're just asking how many tiles over in X.
This thing went, how many tiles and why, and, how many tiles and Z,
right?
So this is this is just three F mods.
so, it may be time to
Start cleaning this up a little bit as well.
Let's think about this.
So, when we re canonicalize coordinates here, right, we kind of did
this and it's a bit sloppy, right?
The way that this works is we're taking whatever the world position.
This this base posed was right?
And when we do map into chunks Space, by the way, I don't even know.
Like, how many people even care about that.
Let's go.
Let's go figure out who's using this, right?
So the simulation uses it and I'm assuming that this is just too yeah
that's just to figure out where the bounds are.
We use it in the packing case we were talking about and we use it
similarly to move the camera.
Right.
And then the only other time we use it is when we're building the
world.
So very few people ever care about this and really yeah, the chunk
position from top position really just uses it because it needs this
additional offset thing, right?
Yeah.
So, I feel like we should clean this code up.
That's what I think we should do right now.
So, what we really need when we're doing, that's not where I wanted to
be.
What we really need when we're doing this re canonicalize and I assume
that we canonicalize is only used here as well, right?
Yeah.
All we're really doing here is saying, well, whatever this offset was
Jimmy.
whatever this offset was we want to
Figure out how far that offset would move us from the base pose,
right?
And we want to compute a combined offset, right?
So we have like a total offset and that's whatever the base pose
offset is.
A plus h offset, however, much that actually is now in the future, I
think world position, I think we're going to get rid of offset from
that, and it's just going to be the three indices and they're only
going to be stored in the chunk.
So I think that's going away eventually anyway.
So like I said, it kind of want to we probably won't need this plus
offset so it'll just be the total offset.
Will just be equal to this, right?
So now if I want to know how many of these, how many steps I'm going
to
Take right.
If I want to know like what my D chunk X is because this is what I
want to know.
Right then all, I really need to do here is some kind of a modulus.
I just need to say whatever, however, far I was moving.
I guess I shouldn't say modulus, modulus is the wrong term, I just
want the integer divide, right?
I want the divide and floor, right?
And you can see that we're doing that here, essentially, but
we're sort of doing it in a,
I think what sort of a somewhat busted way anyway.
Saying modulus was not quite correct.
So, what I want to do here is I want to say, I just need to know how
far this would have moved me from my current base pose, right?
Because I'm at wherever that is, how many tile lengths would I go,
right?
And I can figure this out here.
what I can do here is, I can figure out this tile Delta
I should be able to say, well, whatever the Delta is, right?
If I've gone half the distance, right?
I get one of them and then for every one after that, I got another
one, right?
So like the first point five gets me to the next tile, and then after
that, I get, I have to go one each time, right?
So what I kind of want to do is just add Point 5 and then divide right
if I just add .52, it first.
So that if it was point five, it would have rounded up to one.
That's all I should really need to do and then I can just use a
standard truncation from there, right?
I just can use truncate towards zero and that should be fine.
So I guess that's why we were using round before.
So now that I think about it, this code I was thinking that was going
to be easier.
This code is actually not too bad, right?
This is It's using round because whatever the Divide was it's going to
round to one way or the other so that that seems okay.
And then it's adding the however many that was to wherever the tile is
that it's taking whatever the relative amount was and subtracting off.
However much it actually did go, right there should be a little
clearer here that this is a floating Point.
That's a floating Point multiplication, right?
Using Word of the
chunk Dimension is and then well I don't know.
With restarting just to double-check that make sense.
So that actually does seem now that I go back over at that actually
does seem reasonable, it's not as weird as I thought it was at first.
but,
I still.
Make sure that I don't have anything weird going on here.
And that seems all right.
So the reason thing that was throwing me off is this is the plus
equals here, right?
It's like oh okay.
I see.
So the reason we're treating we're doing the delta in here which is
why we weren't talking about Delta's out here.
That's okay.
And so similarly, I guess we should double check our subtract here.
So our subtract is looking to see what the difference in tiles is
between the two things and then it's multiplying that by however, big
the tiles are which seems reasonable.
And then it's looking at the, a offset - the be offset, which is the
Delta between
Offset.
So that also seems, right?
So that seems pretty good.
Do we use this function anywhere?
Looks like, no.
All right, hmm.
So yeah, I guess we're gonna have to step through this somehow, figure
out, what else?
I don't see just just, you know, sort of looking vaguely at it.
I don't see what the problem is offhand, unless I'm missing something.
I feel like this is probably working.
Okay.
Famous last words.
Char relative of a chunk, Tim is going to round.
Does that work in the negative Direction correctly?
I think it should right, because chunk Tim's, positive, towel rail,
the tower relative motion.
Be - you would get a negative number, which would be a negative offset
after the round, which is what you want.
You add that in, you move that direction, the towel relative amount
again, you you just subtract off, and that'll work, - lie correctly.
So,
seems right, we're passing the right dimensions for everything and
Yeah, I don't see anything particularly wonky.
So that's it.
Yeah, I think that seems that seems reasonable.
If that makes sense.
All right, so let's think about what I can use for debugging strategy
here because if it's not a mapping problem, I'm not sure what exactly
it is.
And so, yeah, I feel like I can probably, you know, it's moving by
that Delta.
So it has to be
Thing with getting the wrong chunk Z.
Right?
It's like Levering onto the wrong chunk Z or something.
It would seem at least, that would be my assumption, so
yes, so assuming that
Assuming, that's not that I suppose, when we actually look at the map
into chunks pace and wondering if there's maybe something, if the, if
it picks the well, let's take a look.
So I'm going to go into some region and I'm trying to think if there's
a likes it that's a hard case to find.
I'm trying to think if there's any way I can figure out some sort of a
more specific way of checking whether something discontinuously moves
from one frame to the next in a way that we don't,
Expect, but it's kind of a hard thing to figure out how we would
detect that case, you know what I mean?
So in here, when we unpack The Entity, we take the chunk Delta by
saying wherever the origin of some reason is we want to move it out to
whatever the chunk position is the chunk position is just at the XYZ
of that chunk, right?
And that's seems totally what we would expect.
We take whatever the p-value is the comes in and we offset it by that
chunk Delta, right?
So that's fine.
What?
I don't know.
Why is Adam T taking the chunk, Delta?
So it adds there.
So the Sim space p is this is just used as a check, but then add into
the does the chunk Delta Edition?
Yes.
All right, that seems reasonable as well.
And then the M Sims same thing, the chunk Delta is inverted and it's
added so it should cancel out.
Assuming the chunk is the same, if the chunk isn't the same.
Well, that's okay, that's still that mapping is still supposed to
work.
So let's try this.
Let's try this.
So when we call pack entity in Two Worlds, I'm going to say that pack
energy into world.
Much try to verify what ends up happening.
So packet of the into World here, we call get World chunk, right?
And then we do the packing.
What I want.
Is after I do this packing.
Would I get the same thing out again after like doing the test?
So basically like I want to test the and I want to say, well if I were
to call map into chunks pace,
Or, I guess not mapping trunk space.
I should say, if I do the reverse mapping after The Pact.
So if I say, well, exactly what I was doing here.
And I say, okay, here's the chunk, Delta, I want to subtract whatever
the chunk position is and I know what that is, right?
It's the entity pee.
And that doesn't include any offset, right?
It's just the XYZ.
No, it doesn't.
No, it definitely does not.
You see the bug?
Or at least, do you see a bug?
I see a bug.
Someone was being sloppy.
And that's something was me.
This is not the chunk P, right?
Oh, okay.
No, I guess I wasn't sloppy.
I'm going to say this is not the time to the trunk.
PS.
Have the offset removed from it, but it does have the Oxford movement.
All right, never mind.
Never mind, I was about to have to hold up the owl.
Shame.
I probably still will have to hold up the Elder shame, but in this
case, no, no shame yet, I did zero it out.
Okay.
So the chunk Delta is the difference between the chunk p and the Sim
origin.
And then the test fee is just whatever.
The entities p-value is now.
Plus that new chunk, Delta or reverse time Delta I should say
Right.
And I'm just interested now to know, right?
Because when we do the pack entity in the world is going to have that
same P from the P value that came in here.
Oh,
but this should be chunk P, shouldn't it?
So that kind of still was a bug because we're packing it into at that
chunk pee.
Let me double-check that.
Still busted.
So
no harm done.
How is the chunk?
How was that code working?
Anyway, let me take a look here.
It doesn't use.
Okay.
Yeah.
So it doesn't use the offset, so that's fine.
Okay, so I want to enable this test.
I basically want to say, hey, when I do the subtract groups
when I do the subtraction,
I was some region on.
And identifier.
Yes, I've called it region in one place.
The same region, another.
Not sure why.
So, what I want to do here is after this, I want to do an assertion on
the entity p.
X equal, the equaling the test p.x
and I want to see if this fires
and I guess, honestly, I don't really need to check the X and the Y,
because Z is all.
I'm really caring about right now and so I want to see what happens
here.
So, let's take a look at the
And that's right.
That's not a quite what I wanted.
Hold on a second.
But I actually wanted was.
To save what it was before we did the mapping.
And then to check that mapping.
Like this.
That's what I actually wanted.
Hmm, you know what?
Unfortunately, I got to stop and restart but we don't have the bug
reap rowing.
So you know what I can do, what I might do is inside win32 handmade
since we have that recording saved, I'm going to go ahead and just
play it back, right?
So at startup
Where does that stuff work?
It's been so long since we implemented that we never did a thing that
actually allows the replays to go, right?
Went through to get input file location.
Found a stray file.
Create always.
So it clears it out here.
Potentially well, no because it wouldn't create it, if it already
existed.
So that's okay.
Well, wouldn't collaborate presumably.
So then we get the max size.
Create a mapping.
And we show the memory block.
So what I'm going to do is I'm just going to start here.
I'm going to take that Loop edit.
Which is this one and I'm just going to duplicate them.
Just so I have a copy in case we mess it up, right?
So I've got this copy here.
That makes sense.
And then what?
To know, I guess is, when I push the L key.
Which is here.
Can I just make it so that we start playing one instead of begin
recording?
We just do begin input playback State one, right?
And maybe I just make this be if it's shift.
so, maybe I'll say something like,
you know, if input playing index is 0,
and,
We kind of need a little bit more logic in here.
We could actually hook this up to our debug and make some buttons for
it which would probably be what we would want, right?
But what I would like to do here is just say, like okay, if you know,
maybe the shift key is down which I think we could do pretty easily,
right?
Because I feel like we probably would have shift.
Do we ever do that?
We have ALT key was down.
We never did shift, I guess.
Put alt he was down up here for now.
And so now we'll just do if all tell is pushed off we go, right?
So if ALT key was down, this is just my little backdoor for now.
We will do
Begin input.
Playback of State 1.
That was underwhelming.
Why did that not work?
It definitely is playing it back.
So the question is, do we erase
Let's take a look no we don't erase right, that's the same file.
And that's the same file.
Oh no, I selected the wrong one.
I selected the wrong one.
I'm an idiot.
All right.
Well,
That is a feature.
We should actually.
Implement, because it's very useful, right?
It looks like I copied the wrong one.
Now that doesn't explain why this doesn't work but I suspect it's
because we clear on Startup and I don't currently preserve old replay
buffers which we would want to do, right?
It looks like in here get input file location.
Should be fine, right?
And
It's going to be the same every time the file handle.
Generic read, right?
I don't feel like it would clobber the file.
When we create the mapping.
In map view of file, I feel like it should just be the file, right?
It feels like that should have worked because I don't think we delete
them.
If that makes sense.
So I'm kind of curious as to why that doesn't work.
Let's blow these away for now.
So if I am to do something here,
I'll do Elle.
And elegant.
So now we clearly are in a loop.
Right.
And I can unloop us and now we're out of the loop.
And so now should all tell should play that back, right?
Yes.
So the problem is on Startup, we must be clearing those somehow,
right?
Because if I instead startup fresh,
And put all Dell.
Now, it works.
So I guess I must just not have hit all tell.
Oh,
it's in the win32 platform layer.
That doesn't live reload.
So we now have the ability, we did it, right?
It's just, you can't patch the wind through two layer at runtime, we
probably should have done that, but what can you do?
All right.
So that's fine.
I'm okay with that.
It's not a hard bug to Repro.
Let's go ahead and
And re-enable the hopping so I can hop mr.
Hoppy over there, right?
So I'm going to go to handmade World mode and I'm going to go down to
where we have the head Hopper, mr.
Head Hopper.
Oops, we go and do.
Do do do.
I totally forget where we were even doing here.
So yeah I was doing in here by move mode.
We do is equal for traversable 's and that should allow the hero to
hop around right and but the heroes not hopping at the moment.
At all.
So, I must have disabled something.
I don't remember what I disabled.
It's been a long day.
So in here, when I'm all this stuff looks right and the hero body
stuff is still correct, right?
And it moves
All of that.
Looks okay.
It's all right.
So tell me why I can't hop.
Yeah, that's true.
We did exceed the maximum velocity, but I want to know why I can't
hop.
So thank you for actually generating, that break point because now I
can go in here and actually find out
Where are we?
Let's see hero head.
So I am going to say, let's go to here hero.
And let's continue running.
No.
Just do set next statement and go.
So let's see, I'm going to go ahead and look in here and see what
happens when we pick the closest reversible.
Presumably it is not equal to 0.
It is, it does think it's equal.
Oh, right, that's what I disabled.
Body Tea.
Okay, let's try that again.
Getting old.
So yeah, that's right.
I was just looking at body P here.
All right, so let's go ahead and hop onto this little dude.
Unfortunately, that was not as nice and pronounced as the other bug
was.
So try that.
You know, and the more I'm thinking about this, it's got to be the
camera motion to because if without the camera motion, it doesn't
happen.
Like that point.
Doesn't work out at all.
In fact, that is why he's jumping off even is because it's wigging out
when the camera moves with him.
So, it is only when the camera moves that this is relevant.
Which again really suggests the packing.
Hmm.
So I guess it's we're way over time so I'm gonna have to call it here
but we pretty much know exactly what our culprit is.
We just have to do bug to find the specific cause but the packing is
definitely the problem because if you're not on there to move the
camera which is the only thing that can actually affect the simulation
region origin,
You can't get that to happen, right?
So, something about the way this is working, is not correct.
Something about it.
And we know that the entity is mapped into that space.
It has a residual offset on it.
So we actually already know as well.
In fact, this chunk Delta thing.
Is not even really how we would normally compute that, right?
What we actually want is to say, well, this already has the residual
in it now, right?
So entity pee.
that offset is actually the value that we
want to know versus the old entity P, right?
So in other words, wherever the dude was before
Verses where you're telling me, he is now.
Right?
Is the amount we have to move all of his positional information.
If that makes sense, because basically, I want to take him from this
value to this value, so this is really not necessary.
In any particular situation.
Sorry, I'm obsessing about this a little bit.
So let's see test fee older to P.
So now we can kind of look at this or except I'm totally off here.
Reverse chunk, Delta packing it into world.
Shrimpy.
Well, actually, you know what, I want to?
I want to debug this first.
So I'm going to, I'm going to take this part here and Nerf it for a
second while I work on this because this should wig out until I get it
proper.
Yeah.
So when I do, let's see, let me just look at what Chuck did chunked
out is actually used for.
So it's only used for nadp+, so if I want to, I don't know why there's
a negative there, that's probably the problem.
Yeah, so that's the known stable value.
So the question is, does that also caused that procedure cause the
problem?
Yeah, so we still have the same problem of it doing that crazy Delta.
So we have two independent methods of both produce the same thing
which is a good thing, right?
Because I can verify this, this is actually that I'm doing what I
think I'm doing, but I'm still getting the problem.
So there's something going on here with when the camera moves.
The pack unpack is not proper.
I hate to leave it for the weekend, but
I mean, I think this is going to require us to dig in and actually go
verify a bunch of stuff, so, I don't know.
I mean, I guess it's something that all of you can go solve over the
weekend if you want to.
So, that's kind of interesting, but it's one of those things that's
going to drive me nuts.
What to do what to do.
I look at it a little more.
I don't have to go right away so I got like it cook it, a little
longer
So re-enabling this this is just a test to verify, oops, that when I
pack and unpack immediately, I get the same thing.
Right?
And those deserts aren't firing.
So always in the moment the pack works.
Okay, which kind of suggests to me that it's the fact that when the
camera changes, we don't unpack to the same place like the camera
itself.
Says region information is somehow busted which I don't know, maybe
implies this code is not correct.
Here we are, grabbing out the world chunks, right?
And when we grab out the world chunks, I suppose, you know, one thing
we could do is assert that the world chunks are what we think they
are, right?
So we could like, assert, if we get a chunk, we could obviously add
some assertions in here.
Just say, hey, we got the right chunk, right?
So you know, chunk
If you look at what this code does, it's got X Y and Z in there,
right?
So I can insert the chunk x equals the chunk X.
That's junk.
Why junkie all equally
They're just to make sure that we don't have some weird thing with our
hash table or something which seems really unlikely.
But you know if you don't know what the bug is that obviously none of
it seems likely so you might as well check everything.
So that does not appear likely and so then when we come through here,
we create a chunk position.
That's at the center of that.
We look to see what the chunk Delta is going to be from wherever the
simulation origin is to the position of the chunk.
And that's how we're going to displace everyone which seems right
right.
I'm at the you know there's the origin is the origin of the Space
Shuttle coordinate system obviously.
So I need to figure out how to move somebody away from that, right?
So that seems right.
I Loop through all the entities.
I test them with the Sims face P, but then I come in here to do that
ad Envy call where I passed the chunk Delta.
And when I passed that chunk, Delta, that's just something that gets
added directly.
So, here it is.
The p-value, I add in that, chunk, Delta and off, I go, right?
Really not complicated.
So
I'm not sure why that would be a problem.
I don't have a lot of ideas on that.
So when I'm moving the entities out,
And then I'm moving them back in.
I guess the first and well, I guess the other thing that's kind of
weird is, we know this doesn't happen.
I guess if in other directions either, right?
Or does it?
I guess we don't really know.
Because we aren't walking across other screens at the moment.
Right.
So it doesn't look like we're getting that kind of crazy displacement
here at all.
I can reach out over there and you know, I don't get when the camera
does do that.
Do its transition?
I don't get any issues there that I can perceive anyway.
So, it's only easy that appears to be problematic.
It's so it has to be moving camera, has to be Z and you can see that
when the flicker happens, it is when it changes to the other SIM
region, because you can see that band, right?
The yellow band signifies the same region in her apron.
You can see it flashing to the lower one.
So we've got this dead to rights in terms of what's going on.
It's really just a question of what did we screw up in the math?
And why is it only on Z which is also kind of weird, right?
Because we've got the same code substantively.
We haven't really compress it down quite yet, but we've got the
substance of the same code happening in both cases.
And it's not clear why we would get a situation where one of them is
It significantly different.
I suppose, another thing we could do,
Just for some additional information.
Is while we're in Crazy Land.
I could go into the camera and make it be not room base anymore.
And now, let's see what happens.
Well, that's just a minuscule amount.
So that's not very helpful.
That's just an Epsilon problem.
Probably,
Although I suppose maybe an Epsilon up now that looks like a really
big jump.
As I say maybe an Epsilon problem isn't enough, but I don't know.
Okay, so we have a pretty clear answer there, right?
Like, look at that.
Although, you know, it's kind of weird about that too.
Is.
That is a tremendous amount of Z of visual Z offset for hardly any
actual Z offset.
Right.
I guess we're only seeing the, the camera we need to.
We need to add the camera in here as well, right?
When we do the same region, I want to see what the camera actually is.
So during begin Sim because the camera must be constantly moving down,
is basically what must be happening in that case.
So the Sim region origin in this case, I guess I'll just say origin
dot X or something.
Dutch uncle, Rex.
And I guess I'll just output these as debug values.
And then I'll also output the offset, which would be always 0.
So here is some information for us.
Here's the same region, origin, the chunk portions right.
And I'm going to go ahead and switch to the the non room base camera,
right?
Oh man.
All right.
Well, let's go here.
So you can see what's happening there, right?
We're super Levering downward.
That
That chunk.
Oh,
Wait a minute.
Is this even a bug?
This isn't even a bug.
I can't believe.
I just spent that long.
Something that isn't even a bug.
That's actually just what I threw in.
At the end of the day, the other day for testing, which is totally
bogus.
If I'm right about this, that is so sad.
So sad.
So remember, we threw in the stupid floaty thing that you stand on.
Well, that thing is just hard coded.
Where'd he go?
That's not him.
Here, he is that things just hard.
To set the Z.
So it's just going to set the Z, always down to whatever, it's going
to set it to it.
If the camera, if the camera moves down, it's going to just move down
because this is not actually moving by any legal method, right?
It's not actually doing any actual motion.
Oh, that's horrible.
That's horrible.
Horrible.
That's absolutely awful.
ah,
I'm gonna put an owl shame on top of a now.
Shame for that one.
All right.
So you guys see what's happening there?
That's awful.
Well, I'm glad we stuck around to find it because that would not be
one.
That was worth saving for the weekend.
And it does bring up a problem with our system that we would probably
want to think about.
So it's not like it's the worst thing in the world but that's pretty
dumb.
Alright?
So the problem here is just that hey, we've got a relative coordinate
system so you've got the camera and people are in it, right?
And they move around in it and they're like, okay, I moved to here.
And so, then later on, we just packed them back and say, oh well,
however, far you were away from that.
Origin is fine.
And so, then later,
It's not a big deal because when we have like the camera for example,
and I should draw this a little bit better.
So let's let's do it, across two frames.
So here's frame one, right?
And here is where this world chunk is on frame 1 and I record where
this guy is in that chunk, right?
And then later on frame to, if the camera moves this way, right?
That slides this trunk over, and that's fine.
Because it's still reconstructs his position and everything's good,
right?
The problem is, if somebody this
Coordinate.
Right?
Is always measured from the center of the simulation region.
So when I, when I unpack him out of the chunk I put in there,
Right.
But that floaty thing, which is straight setting of where it where it
wanted to be and so it was a sign in screen space, so if the camera
moved, it just kept being lower because it's like, hey, I'm always at
negative 1.
So, when the camera move down - one, it was like, where are you now?
It should have been 0.
It's like, no, I'm still negative 1, right?
So no matter how far down the camera moved, that stupid thing was
always like I'm further down the new.
I'm still further down further fought for that, right?
It's like something.
That always says, it's on the left of the screen and no matter how far
you move the camera, that way it still says on the left of the screen.
And so you just Chase it all the way and you never get anywhere.
Right?
And so the reason I say that brings up interesting problem with the
way that we're doing the system is I guess if we want
Something to kind of float up and down.
It brings up kind of an interesting question which is it seems like we
want to be able to specify offsets separate from
That are going to be packed properly.
Like, we might want to be able to specify an absolute sine wave,
right?
That's something we might want to do.
Now, in the meantime, we can always just say, like, oh, you know, well
we can just do this as some kind of a Delta, right?
And so we can just say like oh it's you know, it's going to be not an
absolute position or something like this.
So we can you know, we can sort of get around it by using controllers
that don't work that way and
Say what the trick is that I just did in a minute there because it
might be not obvious why that works.
But now, if I kind of come up onto this dude here, we shouldn't ever
have this problem anymore, even if I make this guy pretty wonky, it
should still still work.
Yeah, so that's that's more what we're looking at here, right?
And let me go ahead and try to think of how I might want to do this.
So I probably wants to be cosine actually.
So it doesn't start out with a bias.
Let's go ahead here.
And I guess we probably wanted a little bit more, huh?
Let's let's let's give it a big old swing.
I can't believe that was the bug.
That's absurd.
All right.
And yeah, so what I did there, right is the reason one of the
interesting things about sine and cosine we haven't really talked
about it too much on the serious, but one of the interesting things
about them as functions, right?
Is that sine and cosine are their own derivatives, right?
So this is just sort of the, the nature of that unit circle.
If I start off here, right?
My sign value.
Of this is 0, right?
And my cosine value of.
This is 1, right?
If I go, you know, along here and I go up to here, let's say right
then.
I've got a signed value of one and a cosine value of 0 and so on and
so forth, right?
Well let's suppose and, you know, we can just keep filling it out.
So here's cosine of negative one, hears sign, oops, sorry.
Sine value of zero cosine, value of negative one.
And then down here, we have cosine.
Sorry signed value of negative 1.
Cosine value of 0.
Well what happens if we actually plot these as vectors right?
Because I've got, you know, if I could think of
These vectors, I've got a vector pointing this direction.
The vector pointing that direction.
A vector pointing this direction in a vector pointing that direction,
right?
Well those vectors smoothly go around the circle, right?
The whole time.
And so at any time that Vector is a sexually tangent to the circle
Well, if I wanted the perpendicular right, which would be the
acceleration along the circle at that point, right?
I'm accelerating in this direction.
If I wanted to accelerate around the circle to find what was
essentially something that goes in plane of the circle rather than
sort of extending out from it.
If I wanted that right, we know what that would be.
It's just a perp, right?
We know that the perpetrator perpendicular, operator of this Vector,
right?
That's that's going around the circle.
And we know what the perpendicular Vector of something is right.
If we have a perpendicular of X Y, then it's just going to be equal to
y - x, right?
Or depending on which one we want to do - YX right?
We can have it pointing we can do the perpendicular clockwise or
counterclockwise depending on which one we want to do.
Well if that's the case right?
Then if
A vector is sign or this case is cosine sine or something like this,
right?
The derivative of that or sorry, that not the derivative should say.
But the the we haven't quite gotten there yet.
The direction sort of that on the outside is just going to be, you
know, negative sine cosine or something, right?
It's just going to be depending on which direction I want to go.
And in this case it would be.
Let's see which one it is.
So I want it to be going up, right?
So that's 0 cosine should be going positive, which it is and sign
should be.
Going backwards and negatives, right?
So this is the 14 going counter clockwise around the circle, right?
So, hey,
If I want to know how I would accelerate a point such that it goes
around a circle.
If I know the function for putting me on the circle happens to be sine
cosine.
I know the acceleration that moved me around the circle was - I'm
sorry it wrong.
Again was cosine sine?
Which is the point that travels around the circle.
I know that negative sine cosine right?
Is that acceleration around a circle.
Now this is just a long sort of geometric way of looking at the fact
that if you ever just look up in a book you will see something that
says, you know, the if you have a function of theta and that equals
cosine of theta, then the first derivative of that equals negative
sine of theta, right?
And the same is true if you have a function of sine Theta, right?
The derivative of it is cosine,
Well, that's why geometrically, right?
That's the geometric reason for why is because, hey, it's still just a
circle, right?
Because you can think of it.
You can think of cosine sine as just assert a vector pointing out.
You know, that comes out to the
Well, that just goes around.
Well, if you wanted to figure out what the acceleration was, or I'm
sorry the velocity was all around, right, you just do the same thing,
right?
You just you just, you still want a vector that moves around.
You just want to start it pointing upward instead of pointing
outwards.
So you're just taking it and rotating that Vector 90 degrees and off
you go, right?
Which is the perpendicular and hey, that's exactly what we end up
seeing when you do it.
Knowing if you knew what the derivative was ahead of time.
So all I did was I was like, oh, I
Want this thing to be based on something that isn't absolute.
So I can shove it into our system.
And so, all I did was I just said, oh, okay, just take the value and
make it be less and then just use that as an acceleration, right?
I'm velocity, right?
I did not use it as a celebration.
I'm not I'm not incrementing to the DeeZee here.
I'm just using it as a velocity directly write
But again, it would be the same for acceleration because, no matter
how many times you take the derivative, it still gives you the same
results, right?
They are their own derivatives.
So it's like, if I start out with cosine Theta and I'm like, that's my
position.
Then when I take the derivative of that,
Right?
I get Negative sine Theta if I take the derivative of it again it's
exactly the same thing right - cosine Theta because we already know
the derivative of sine is cosine so I can keep going and going and
going, right?
But the position, the velocity, the acceleration, the acceleration of
the acceleration and blah, blah blah, right?
It's always going to be cosine negative sign.
Negative cosine, sine cosine, negative sign, right?
It's just going to be that repeating all the way down to wonder how
many time you take the derivative over and over and over and over and
over and over and over and over.
Right?
And as pseudonym 73 is on the channel.
He'd probably talk to you about something like e to the I Theta or
something like this or how these things mapped complex numbers.
But I'll be honest with you that stuff is so not in my wheelhouse.
I'm not going to try but
Point being Math is Fun.
Let's go shopping.
All right, so that's it.
That's it.
That's all I have to say.
Really.
So let's go to Q&A.
Mmm.
Clemens, boom.
Wow, that is not a non topic.
Question, is there a geometric explanation for the quaternion sandwich
Product?
Where does the formula?
Q times P times, conjugate, Q come from
So I guess I could tell you where it comes from algebraically, but I
guess to be honest, I've never thought of where it comes from
geometrically.
You should have asked me 15 years ago and I probably could have told
you well not told you but I probably could have figured it out.
I'll tell you what, hold that thought for a second and let me answer
mr.
Fourth Dimensions question, because that's actually on topic.
I'm a bit unclear on why the relative positioning of Z worked is z
rebased summer in the code, actually, everything is rebased, right?
So everything works properly position.
Wise, the only thing is that you have to actually treat positions that
come through.
Well, okay, let me I can explain it much more simply, really
the only reason this code didn't work because because that
Right.
No amount of rebasing is going to help you, if you clobber, the
rebased value with a new value.
And that's what we did here, right?
So whenever we're out putting values, we can't just treat them like
they're the same as they were last frame because they might be
different.
Now, they're not different in terms of what they mean but they're
different in terms of their numeric value because they might be based
on a different starting point, all the rest of our code works because
it's all based on
I use that get rebased.
Everything is in terms of values that get re based in this code.
This is and this both get rebased.
So we don't have to worry about cold, setting entity P2 something.
Because when we cold set and ep2 something, we're setting it to a
function that's in terms of other rebates values here.
There is no re based value on the right hand side of this equation.
So, we just clobber a rebase value with an on rebase value and Havoc
ensues.
Zach see I'm still quite new be.
I'm pregnant but wouldn't comment in your code a bit more help in
situations like today.
I mean, I'd say the obvious, I say the opposite, I would say if you
watch what just happened on the stream, no amount of comments could
have possibly helped me.
And the reason for that is because the line of code was something we
added on a previous day.
That is not even in the region where we were reading.
So we would never even if we had a comment in here,
Like this is fucked.
Like let's say we knew I'm not us around spring, this is bad.
Let's say so even had a comment that was like, this is bad.
We would if those of you have heard me, talk normally, I swear
continuously.
So how we have gotten away with.
I think only three swears on handmade hero so far is beyond me but I
wanted to try and keep it relatively clean for children anyway.
So basically what happens is, even if we had a comment in here that
even if we knew, which I didn't know when I, when I was writing it, I
didn't even think about that.
Otherwise I wouldn't have written in the first place.
So even if
How I known even then if I'd added a comment that was like, hey, by
the way don't do this.
We never looked at this code.
So there's basically like and this is the, this is true of basically.
All of the things that I found in my life regarding comments, which is
that comments are really only useful when you're completely done like
basil, when you're completely done with the code and you're wrapping
it up, right?
You need to go and write a comment was like, here's how this worked
because later, when you go back, you're going to have to read that,
comment and go, okay, and I get it.
Anything else that you comment on is just you're wasting your time
because you're not going to be the comment.
Comment, get out date.
And then, if you start trusting the comments, they're probably wrong
because you probably change something.
I forgot to change the comment.
So I say never comment till you're done with a section and then put a
comment at the top of that section.
That's like, hey here is a good description.
of how this algorithm and code and stuff is supposed to work because
later when you come back,
you need to do that.
And Cuba Caleb.
Yeah, I think it was only three squares are not in the pre stream
because the priests room is fine.
But in the regular stream I thought we only have three.
If you can find more than three, let me know.
I thought I thought this would have been number of swear.
Number four, I think.
I think there were three previous ones.
I don't know.
I can't quite remember.
Long billion.
So not only did that bug affect the floating thing going to high low,
but it also is the cause of the head, picking the wrong point and the
body jumping to it.
Yes.
So what was happening there?
Right.
Is that, when that when that point got, well, let me just draw it for
you.
So here's what was happening.
Let's let's view this from the side.
Okay, here's the hero.
They're standing on a point.
Here's the head.
Here's another Point next to him.
Here's another Point next to him, right?
And this is the point right now that we're on here, is the zero line.
Let's say this is not actually quite right.
It's not the exact wasn't quite at the zero line where these points
were.
It's a different location, but doesn't that doesn't matter for now.
And this point is getting displaced downwards by that Z equals sine
Theta function, right?
Here's what happens now on the next frame, okay, everything is rebase
properly.
So we're looking through that same situation, but this fellow right
now we sort of have a change in where the camera is.
So the camera now comes down to here, all right, these guys are still
at the zero line, and that's fine because they all get displaced
properly.
So their relative positions are like this, so does the hero so he's in
the right place, but this guy right, even though he gets replaced, he
gets rebase to his peas in the right place.
He then Club.
Purrs his pee, with this displacement again, which drops this point
down to here, right?
So, is that it was here, now, all of a sudden isn't telling, it's
there.
Now, we ask, what's the closest point to here?
Well, it's not this one anymore, it's this one and snap that causes
the guy to jump, right?
So it's very, very straightforward.
But, you know,
Until you actually find a bug, it's always like what?
so,
the mind of raw.
What if you really wanted to set an absolute vision for energy?
How would you handle that?
Well, it's actually not hard because we have the chunk mapping system.
So, if you want to store an absolute position, you can just store an
absolute position with one of these world offsets, right?
You can just put one of these
Store.
Actually one of these and then every time you just call Matt and then
you get it out.
You called map into some space or whatever.
So it's not actually hard to do it's just that's not what we were
doing.
so,
All right, so it looks like we don't have questions so I'll try to
think about Clemens bombs question.
This is not a question which anyone on the stream?
Probably would have any idea what I'm talking about because we've
never covered quaternions on handmade hero to the best of my
knowledge.
But and it's been so long that it's really I have not really done
anything with quaternions and probably like seriously 10 years
probably more like 12 at this point.
so I don't think I'm probably gonna be very helpful, but
so, the question was,
And comments about correct me if I'm wrong.
But the question was, where does this sandwich you called it a
sandwich product?
And the sandwich product you're talking about like qpq inverse, right?
And what this is here is like these are quaternions
And this is technically also, a quaternion in some sense.
But oftentimes, when people are talking about this, this is actually a
vector that's been extended into a quaternion.
And is this is this basically, the core of your question?
Like, tell me I'm going to wait for the chat a little bit here.
Tell me if this is what you were talking about.
Okay, so comes on confirmed that that is the question.
All right?
So
I'm trying to think about how to to illustrate this.
So I'm going to start with the algebraic way to think about it and
then I'll try to come up with a geometric one.
Now, you may already know the algebraic reason for this and and if it
is the, and if, you know the algebraic reason for a ready, then I
apologize, but I'm going to have to work through.
It is, like I said, it's been so long since I've worked with these
that I can't just pull it out of my head at this point, so the out
Rick reason for this, is if I mean, I'm assuming again, like I Tsum,
you already know this, but I'm just going to say it anyway.
So this is actually the similarity transform.
I've never heard it called the sandwich product.
But but essentially, this is not specific to quaternions, right?
It's not really a quaternion thing.
It's just a spatial.
It's a, it's just a
It's a frame of reference thing and you'll see it in everywhere, it
exists.
Even if you could probably, if you went into looked into like the
tensor math or gravitation and stuff, you would see the same stuff
happening.
It's not specific to quaternions in any particular way, right?
I guess what?
I want to say.
So you could think of this as also being how you do with matrices.
So, if I had a matrix B and I did this equation to it, okay?
Totally separate from quaternions just straight-up matrices.
The same intuitive process is happening in both cases in both cases,
it's called assembly similarity, transform again as far as I know, in
either case called similar transform and in both cases it means the
same thing.
And what it means is Tell me the meaning of thing be in the space of
thing.
A and so in quaternions, if I was to do these the same rate, I would
say there's the
Be quaternion.
And the a quaternion, right?
And here is what it is, right?
It's the Abba transform, it's the dancing queen.
So
So first off I'd look this up, right?
I'd say if my explanation doesn't help you at all which like I said
because I'm so Rusty, it probably won't.
You can do a lot of reading on the similarity transform and somebody
out there is going to have an explanation that resonates with you.
I would suspect.
So if you were looking for sandwich product, maybe that didn't help.
But similarly transform, I think, should I would be shocked if you
couldn't find a good explanation on simulator transforms because
they're ubiquitous, they're everywhere and they're very important.
so,
Where does the similarity transform actually come from?
Now here's the thing.
Is I could have told you this this would have been second nature to
me.
While I'm going to have to stumble through it a little bit here.
So
in order to do a similarity transform on something, it helps to think
about it in terms of what this thing might be transforming.
So I'll try again because it's supposed to be an intuitive explanation
here.
Let's talk about these things, as not as matrices or quaternions,
which says things that represent a frame of reference.
All right.
And so if I have a frame of reference
That's out in the world.
So let's suppose this is x coordinate.
And this is a y-coordinate and we doesn't matter whether we're in 2D
or 3D, so I'll just draw these as 2D.
That this works in any Dimension.
This is not again, this this is Matrix math, it's not dimensional.
It doesn't care how many dimensions these things have so 2 D, 3 d, 1
D, whatever doesn't matter.
So if I have something and I have an interpretation in that space,
right?
So here's my point.
Point.
And here's my X and my y frame.
And I'm talking about maybe, an origin even and I'm talking about this
representation here.
And what I'm going to do is I'm going to say that I want the
orientation to be the only part that I care about because again since
this is a general Matrix thing, we don't have to care about positions.
In any particular way you can just say rotations and if it works
rotations it works right.
So if there was some canonical coordinate system great.
But I'm talking about this specific coordinate system here and I'm
going to call this coordinate system.
Be
And here is p and this p is, you know, being expressed?
Let's say well, I want to talk about where it's being expressed yet.
I'll just simply say that I have this coordinate system, be right?
So, I could create an equation.
We're I said, assuming that b is expressed in the outer core canonical
coordinate system.
So this this framers, the screen, if you will, what the screen is
right now, I've got the slightly tilted thing and then I've got the
actual screen coordinate system which is here, right?
Well if I wanted to talk about where P was on the screen in the
canonical coordinate,
Right.
Then I would have the equation p on the screen right?
Equals P times this thing because p is in B's space here, right?
This is, you know, you could almost think of it as p in be space,
right?
P is in the space of B.
So in order to put it into the outer frame of reference, I have to
multiply it by that Matrix or rather.
If we get out of the major sandwiches talk about frame reference, I
have to do, whatever the interpretation.
Action is whatever that interpretation operator interpret this thing
in my space so that it becomes in the outer space, right?
And in major, see this very simple, it just matrix multiplication.
We know that we know that if we multiply a point by a matrix, we
transform it by that Matrix, so it's very intuitive.
You've done this a million times, everyone knows what it is.
If there are 3D Graphics programmer and I'm assuming you would because
you would be asking about quaternions otherwise, right?
So, we know this equation, it's very, very comfortable and this is the
equation that does that expression.
It puts be out into the outer frame and you could think of it as if by
noting this a little further, you could say, well, I have in second, I
could eliminate the primes and I could say, well, let's say this outer
coordinate system will even introduce a letter for it.
The outer coordinate system is just see, well, I could say that see,
you know p in see space equals.
Whatever.
B is encoded in c space, right?
Times p in be space.
Right.
And what you can think of this doing, if you see the way I've noted.
This is you can almost think of these as canceling each other out.
So if I want to go from b space to see space, I need the be in C, in C
Matrix, right?
Because when I talk about a frame of reference, I can't talk about a
frame reference without talking about what frame of reference that is
in, right?
And that's the curse of programming, right?
Is that generically, we can, you know,
Can talk coordinate free and everything is fine.
But when we actually go to implement, right?
There's there's what'd what are the actual numbers, right?
We're feeding an actual numbers and implementation time.
So in the abstract terms, we can talk about the frame of reference be
and we don't really even have to talk about who it's encoded in.
But once we start talking about the minutiae of it, we have start
talking about.
Well, okay, what what are you talking about?
You say be when you actually encoded that, what did you encode it in
and while we're talking now about it being coded in c space, right?
So now let's assume that we introduce a right.
So we're going to have another thing here, that's the frame.
That's a
Okay, so that's my a frame.
Now the frame a is a different frame than the frame, be right?
And I'm going to call this a see because I'm going to encode them both
in the sea space.
So I have a and c space and I have b and c space.
This is again, adding a lot of things you're like I'm getting confused
AC.
So sorry, right?
I apologize.
This is just the nature of this kind of problem, but you can think of
that see space.
I'm just that's just the world space, right?
This is effectively World space.
It's just a third frame of reference that I'm encoding, both A and B
in.
So, this is exactly what you have in a normal program.
In a 3D program, you have a 3D Matrix, a a 3D Matrix B.
They're both encoded in World space, right?
And I'm talking about the two of these matrices in World space.
Let's say, right?
So that's why I'm talking about here.
I've got three spaces and a and b and then there's a c which is the
encompassing space that encompasses both of them, okay?
So now
Let's say, I want to ask the question.
Well, what if I wanted to know what B was right in the space of a
So I no longer want B to be encoded in the space of.
See I want B to be coded in space of a and you can imagine this is
being like a hierarchical, kind of a transform, right?
It's like when you do a bone system and you say like, oh, you know,
the child bone in the parent bone, right?
Well, the child bone is encoded in the space of the parent and the
parent is encoded in the space of the world, right?
So you have C is the world.
A is the is the parent.
B is the child.
I want to produce that.
Right.
If that makes sense well intuitively, we kind of know what that is and
so we could right off the bat perhaps jump in to writing that and
saying, well, I know that if I want a in, I'm sorry.
I know that if I want be in the space of a then all I really have to
do is make a be the new world coordinate system, essentially, right?
So we know what that is, right?
It's the inverse of a and C, we just take that inverse of it which is
basically doing the opposite.
Transform, right.
And then we can take anything that was in that space and that will map
it into a space, right?
If that makes sense.
Now, why is that doing?
What it's doing?
And we'll sort of get into that in a second here, but you can almost
think of this inversion.
As swapping these two, right essentially what this transform becomes
now is see in a space in some sense, right?
It's sort of saying how would I get to see if I was in a right?
So that swaps what these two things mean and again you could read the
canceling C and C cancel and we just get be in a space, right?
So hopefully this is helping you kind of warm up to where we're going
here, but hopefully, that all made pretty good sense.
And obviously, like, I don't know what your level of familiarity with
this.
But again, like I said, I assume if you're asked about quaternions,
then your
Recently comforter with everything I just said and it should be like,
okay, yes, like that's all stuff I've kind of done before and even if
you maybe didn't think about exactly this way, you thought about it
and that's relatively comfortable, right?
So it's pretty easy to produce like being a space, or I could have
produced a in B's face, or you know, whatever else, right?
So now, let's talk about that similarity, transform part of it, right?
So now, let's ask the question, what what, what is this?
This weird one that we're talking about here, right?
So we're talking about something where we're like, you know, we don't
know what we're getting.
We're getting something that you do.
You're saying, I don't really understand what why it is or what it is,
but I know that it's produced in this way.
I know that I take, you know, these transforms that I have encoded and
I know
That I'm that I'm doing that to them, right?
Should be very, very phlegmy.
Hmm.
Okay, so this is the the similarity transform like we said before,
right?
And it's it's going to basically be doing exactly the same sort of
things, as all of these operations were.
So let's see if we can read it off and see what, you know, it ends up
looking like well,
First of all, like I said before, when you do this inversion operator,
you're sort of doing the opposite mapping.
So this is really more properly perhaps written in the way that we're
doing it as see in, you know, in a space.
So I have a and c space times B and C spacetimes see in a space,
right?
And so if we read the cancels, right, and because remember how this
worked if I had here before,
Russ talking about where if I have p and b space and B and C space,
right?
You can cancel the the small to the large, right?
And we are lining up.
Essentially what's around for
We're lining up essentially the same thing, but now this time around
we don't have the same Smalls to the large, right.
They have to kind of carry through because we can't like like we had
before where we would do before you know a in see space b and c space,
right?
Or something like this, there is no cancel that happens here.
This is just a b and c space, right?
It continues.
It holds if two things that were in the same thing that kind of hold
their there.
See, right.
So these two terms combined together is just going to be the a be
transformed in see space.
So this first term we can see exactly sort of what it is, right.
And what it is is the composite of these two, right?
It's doing both A and B so it's doing a first and then be and it's
like combining the two transforms in see space, right?
That's what this would be.
That makes sense.
And then here, we just have the sea in a space.
So this is doing the opposite of what a
Of what a was doing, right?
So essentially, what we can think of Happening Here is we can think of
this as putting something, that's on this side, right into C's space,
then applying be to it in that space and then reapplying a in the same
space, right?
So it's like undoing a doing be, and then doing a again to put it
back, right?
and so, what you can kind of see in this case, and I guess, I
probably, if I, you know, if I was clever
About how I done this notation.
This would probably actually be
Possible to follow through, trying to think of how I would have noted
that.
I feel like they're probably would have been away since I was writing
these letters down just to keep you to have.
You be able to remember them?
I feel like they're probably would have been a clever way for me to do
this so that you could actually cancel them out the whole way through.
But I'll be honest, I don't immediately see how you would do that
because what you want to end up with here, right?
Is sort of a hmm.
Excuse me.
The effect of be in c space.
The effective be as if it was in a space in see space but I don't
really know.
Yeah, I have to think about that more.
Is there some way to, I don't know.
So I feel like if you were a tensor math person, like I feel like if
you a pseudonym 73, he'd be able to figure out how to notate this.
So it actually more cleanly, worked out, but Ibis re I can't, I can't
figure out how you would really think about Crossing these and, in
some way.
So I'll have to just ignore that for now.
But as I'm doing this, I don't think I've ever written it out quite
this way before.
So I never really thought about.
Hey maybe you could make these things actually line up in some way
that produced the result that you
On it but you think you need you need one more like level of of
writing probably to make that happen anyway.
Okay, so what we're doing here, right is, we're moving something
Jimmy.
We're moving something such that, a is the space that we're now in,
we're applying be, right?
And then we're moving back into the to that a space, right?
If that makes sense, we're basically undoing that previous transform.
So if you look at what happened, on the diagram, what would happen on
the diagram here is our A and C space encoded, right?
We have something.
If we, if we wanted to talk about some point that we were just talking
about, right?
Then the first thing we're doing
in is we're saying,
Okay, if that point, let's say that in point is encoded in see space.
So it's actually floating in the screen.
We first are going to do the inverse of it here.
So we would essentially be moving so that we're in a space.
And you know what I'll do.
I'll draw these out for you one step at a time.
Alright so here's a and coded in c space.
Here's a point.
Also in coded in c space, right?
So the first thing we do, if we wanted to do this now and I'm going to
just do, I'm going to do a CBC AC inverse right times a point equals
some new point.
Right.
And I'm going to call it P Prime because we're not talking about what
it actually is yet since that's what we're trying to discover.
Okay, so here's my point and see space.
Here's my frame, a see.
The first thing I do is I multiply by the inverse of that frame,
right.
So what does that do?
That takes us from this coordinate system into one?
Where a see is the root coordinate system.
So, this is now a see effectively where it was right now.
This is just a canonical Court, we've undone it.
So we wouldn't really necessarily call it a see anymore but you can
see what I'm doing, right?
I'm writing the AC so that it actually occurs
Coincident with the with the outer axes, right?
So now we would have PC would be like here, right?
Because it would maintain its relative position.
We would warp it back, right?
And now we know that we have BC, okay?
And BC was this other?
This sort of slight more slight thing.
It was right here.
Well, remember we are still applying and this is why I wrote These in
so I apologize if they're confusing you more.
But I you've got to track him somehow.
Well, B is still in sees face, okay?
And a is now.
We're see was right.
In other words, we've shifted a so that it at is now in C because we
apply the inverse of a and C.
So we basically moved in to see space.
Remember because this is now, you know, it's the seat of a transform.
So we've moved into see space.
So a is aligned with C B is in that space.
So we are now applying be as in its normal way.
We did not change be at all.
We're applying it normally.
Right, and it's the slight tilt.
So now we're going to reinterpret P in that space.
Now what's that going to do?
What's going to move it this way, right?
It's going to tilt it down a little bit.
Okay, so that's what happens after we apply.
So we applied a c.
Now we applied BC, right?
That was it there.
Then, finally, we're going to apply a see again.
Right?
So we're going to undo what we did originally.
Okay, so what we do now is we move this whole thing back.
We do this this transform again, right?
this Transformer again, which slides everything back down and moves
this new Point down here, right to apply that AC back to where AC was
Okay, so
Hopefully, you can see what that means.
We first move a point into one frame of reference AC, we then apply
the transform that we're talking about here as if it were still in the
world space.
We don't touch it at all.
We do it exactly as it used to work and then we apply a see again,
right?
So, we re move back to that space.
If that makes sense.
So essentially the similarity transform what it does.
This equation, right here, if I have a ba in verse,
then what that effectively gives me is it gives me b as if a world
space
Right.
That's what it does.
Now you may ask the question.
Well why do I care about this?
Because if we now come back to this, right?
And we say well okay that's all great but doesn't this point?
Just end up basically where it would have ended up anyway, right.
And the answer is in 2D, yes it would.
And the reason why in 2D it would happen is because rotations commute
into d, right Rotation by an angle.
Just adds in 2D.
So no matter which order, I apply these transforms in, I'm home.
Free.
Right?
I don't care.
So what I could do is I could say that a be a inverse if all I'm
talking about is 2D rotations, well, that doesn't matter.
It's just the same as a inverse B which is the same as B and you're
right.
The problem is that doesn't happen in 3D in 3D rotations, do not
commute right?
Because they are non-euclidean that way.
They don't, they do not obey.
Any sort of rearrangement.
You can't start swapping the terms and expect the 3D rotations to come
out being the same.
And furthermore this would not necessarily work if these matrices
represented something else.
So you know if they weren't rotations, if they were some other thing
maybe even in 2D we could construct something that wouldn't work
because the matrices you know wouldn't work properly, they don't
commute.
Let's say because matron application in general is not commutative it
just happens to be in the
Matuidi rotation.
so,
normally, there are actually two different things that would happen
here one would be if
Fly be.
And it would be a certain rotation and another one would be if you
applied a be a inverse, right?
And they're not actually the same, this one applies be as if we were
in a is frame.
The other one applies be as it exists in the world normally, right?
And so another way of saying that what would be it applies be as if
the world had already shifted so that a was where it was right?
But it doesn't apply it in a space.
We still end up with a world space result.
And that's why, right?
Because we were talking before about like a inverse b or some like
parental parent to transform.
Those are ones that Cascade and take something from the child from be
space, right?
If we had be in here or something like that, where we're trying to
take something from be space, all the way out to World, space will be
2 multiplied by b and a and whatever and they're parented.
That's one thing.
But in this case, we're talking about everything is in World space
alien world.
Bees and wasps the point in World space.
And now I just want to know what's the transform.
That applies be as if it were in a space.
Without actually ever putting it there, right?
If that makes sense.
So let me keep going.
Hopefully some of this is helping at all.
Maybe it's all complete hogwash.
I don't know, but like I said, it's been so long since I've worked on
this stuff.
It's a shock, I'm remembering any of this.
So my explanations are probably not as Lucid as they would be if that
wasn't the case.
But so continuing on
Think about this algebraically, right?
So let's say I have P Prime equals B P.
Okay, this is saying all right eye, and I'm going to use that notation
again.
I apologize again if it's confusing but let's say B is in c space &
and P is in be space, right?
So this is essentially the case where I have a point in coded and this
you know, we could think of this as like a bones its kind of the
system or something like that, right?
Where let's say, I've got a mechanical arm kind of a thing here.
Right.
And here is my transform for be, okay?
And I'm representing it in this in this outer space.
See and hear is this is a point that's encoded off of B that's p and I
want to know in see space what this is, right?
So I'm going to multiply p and b space times b and c space and I get P
the world P.
Okay, now I want to have this be a to link thing.
So I'm going to consider this right?
Which is the a transform and B is going to be an ace.
Space.
So we're not dealing with that anymore.
Instead, we're going to deal with a child parent child situation.
Now, we all know how to get that, right if I want PNC space again.
Well, now I've got to concatenate all the transforms a whole way
around.
Right, I've had a and see his face.
I have be in a space.
I have p in Indy space, right?
These cancels a cancels I end up with p and c space and that's how I
transform it out, right?
You've got you've seen that before.
Yeah, you've seen it like a bunch of times, right?
Now, what would happen?
However, if I wanted to do this transform the same, like I want to do
trying to think of how to
How to explain this in a way.
That makes more sense.
Okay.
So now let's say, I want to do the same transform exact same transform
but I want to encode pee in a different space, right?
I want to encode pee in.
I want to encode p as if it were in.
Sorry, bear with me for a moment.
I'm trying to think of what the best way to explain this is I'll start
with this.
So let's suppose that I was going to move P to a different space,
right?
I'm just going to move P to a different space entirely.
Well, it's free for me to take this equation and insert any pair of a
matrix.
And it's inverse because the Matrix times its inverse is the identity
Matrix.
So we always can do
This right if I want to.
So I can insert the identity Matrix here into this equation
algebraically.
It doesn't change the meaning of it, right?
I get insert 50 of them, it wouldn't change me because at any Matrix
doesn't do anything, that's the point of it.
That's why it's called a data matrix.
It's the multiplicative identity.
Just to be clear, not the additive identity, which would be all zeros.
So little think of identity Matrix, I diagonal 1s down the diagonal,
Right.
So
If I replace this identity Matrix with this combination AC a or
actually I'll do the opposite one because it'll be easier for me
inverse AC p--.
Be right then, now you can sort of see one place where I might
naturally get the similarity transform to occur, right?
Which is if I wanted to apply the composite transform of A and B,
right?
It.
But I have my points in the space.
That's been transformed by a already, right?
So let's say, I want to store all of my P points.
I want to store them pre transfer and buy a for some reason, right?
But I want to know when I store my other matrices, I want to know what
the transform is.
That would give me back what I was doing before, right?
That's one place where this tends to happen and so, you can imagine
something where you have, you know, like, I've got pee and I've got a
BP.
Right.
It often times, you'll get it a situation where you go like, okay, you
know, let me go ahead and add in that identity here.
Write a inverse a p, right?
And now I can press this down to like similarity transform.
Transformed point, right?
So here's my similarity transform.
Here's my new point.
Whatever you want to call it.
And I keep this and I keep this right?
And later I can reproduce P Prime but with a different a space, if
that makes sense.
Maybe it does, maybe it doesn't, I don't know.
To give a concrete example of that happening algebraically.
Let's talk about space change.
Okay.
Okay, okay.
Yes.
This might make some sense to, I don't know if any of that made sense
to you at all.
Hopefully did like I said I'm sorry it's just it's all really buried
back in the brain so I don't remember like good ways to communicate it
as well as I should.
So one more time coming after different angle, see if this helps at
all.
Let's suppose that I have that bone chain and now I want to transform
the bone chain, right?
So so
Artist creates a thing in Maya, right?
And the thing looks like this.
Okay, here's the route.
A here's B.
Here's C.
And here's the point.
Okay?
So we know that this is and this is some animated thing, right?
So, this is a dude's arm or something, right?
Here's like the center point.
Here's the shoulder.
Here's the elbow.
And here's the hand, right?
So, this is a bone system, and I've got an animation.
So I've got animations and all the stuff I've got.
Each of these is like an animation, right?
Track that I've got, and I've got points.
Which Define the skeleton, right?
So they're around here, whatever.
Okay.
So I know that in the tool in the art tool, my equation was always
this, right?
It was take a point multiplied by C then B then a and then I get my my
transform point out, right?
And I'm like, that's how I was doing everything.
It's all good and I know that I can just work with it and it's fine.
But let's say these have scale and shear and position and everything
else in them, so they're completely generic transforms, right?
Not just rotations.
So there everything goes in here, too,
All right.
Now,
We say hi.
Well, all of these models remodeled a bit wrong, right?
Actually didn't want them modeled with Zeke.
Going up, we wanted the model with Y going up but Maya had Z going up
and with their also modeled like 45 degrees twisted or something,
right?
So we've actually got this other Matrix M that we want to apply to the
mesh, right?
To all the points.
To sort of move them to the right locations, right?
That's what we wanted to do, and
you know, I should also mention
Well, I'll leave this out for now.
So what I effectively want to do here, right?
Is I want to be able to store.
I don't want to do this at runtime meaning, I don't want to have to do
extra Matrix multiplications at runtime.
So the trivial way to make this happen, right?
Would I just be like, oh, okay?
Well, you know, if I want to make all of this thing's transformed by
m, i just sticking them on the end.
I'll just transform everything by n.
Em, Right?
And I'll be done.
But if I was to do that right?
I would have to actually do that extra matrix multiplication, right?
There's no real way for me to get around that in any particular way.
Is that true?
Well, I guess I'm trying to construct the scheme where I have to
totally have to use this.
Because I suppose you could just bake it into this track.
If you wanted to write, you could, you could bake that transform in
here, which
Still kind of works.
I guess you'll have to just assume that for some reason you want to do
this, you want to store the peas, pre transformed by m and you want to
store these pre transfer by m.
So it really all isn't that space and by the way, we did this in
granny because people on the export path, want to be able to do this,
right?
They want to be able to bake their assets into whatever, coordinate
space they want.
They don't want to have to transform it at runtime, right?
So it is a real case.
I'm just trying to motivate why you would necessarily want to do this.
And
Simplicity is one.
There's probably other real reasons you want to do it too.
But so what I want to do, right?
As I want to transform the peas by m and I want to transform all the
matrices by m, but obviously I can't just stick an m on the beginning
because that would just transform all the Mas.
The peas would not actually be changed in the way that they should be
in.
None of these would be change the way that they should be either.
And so you kind of end up in the situation where you're like, huh?
Right.
So if I actually want to do this, they're right what I want now is I
want to have my mu.
No, this is what I want.
So I do want this.
So if I multiplied both sides by MP,
I get the right equation.
This does produce the results.
I just can't store it still as three.
I can't store it as three matrices and the point because it's got its
got this extra transform in there, right?
So the question is, what can I do to get around that?
Well, let's use that trick.
I said about, inserting the identity again, right everywhere.
Okay.
Well, if I insert the identity in between each of my terms, then I can
expand that identity out if I want to to M inverse M, right.
So everywhere I had an eye right here it can come back here at become
that there's my see.
And hear it can come that again.
So everywhere I have an m.
I mean I I can expand it to an M inverse M, right?
Well now look what I got.
Well similarity, transform day becomes the new a similarity transform
be becomes.
The new be simply layer.
Transform similarity.
Transform C becomes the new C and the transfer and point becomes the
new input point, right?
This I don't know what I'm going to call this new.
Really want to be in.
Give me some other name for it.
This is
a new.
I don't know why.
Be new.
Seenu.
And Pinot.
All right, oh, and I guess I could call them the Emma fide.
Call them F IDE.
All right.
Algebraically.
Hopefully, that makes reasonable sense to you because nothing weird
happened there, right?
All I did was say, I'm going to multiply this equation on both sides
by m.
So I'm just transforming the, the, the space by m, that's it.
I just moved the points by em.
That's all I did, right?
So, geometrically, right.
Whatever we had.
I don't know what it was, right.
Here's that P.
Whatever we did.
We just moved it by m.
If m is some weird rotation, we just moved the point, right?
That's all we did.
And then we said well, all right, insert the identities.
Expand.
Those M inverse M.
You can see the similarity transform happened here.
Here here.
And here, I'm sorry here here and here and you're left with the M on
the P, right?
So what's that doing intuitively?
Well, like I said the similarity transform applies a as if it's in Ms,
space.
So you can see what this equation actually does.
It says I want to store
P in m space with the m modification, right?
That's what I actually wanted to do.
And in order to do that, I need each of these people to be as if they
were in m-space, right?
And so that is essentially what is going on there.
It's similarity.
Transforms is doing that interpretation for you, so you can store
those with this point, pre transform, but still get the same result
right?
Still end up with MP Prime at the end.
So in grainy, this is what would happen.
If you ask for a coordinate system change, right?
It would take all your animation tracks and apply the similarity,
transform to them, take your mesh and apply the transform to the mesh,
and then you're done.
So, there you go.
Alright, so there you go.
Hopefully that answered the question.
So I guess I'll now ask Clemens found any of that.
Help at all?
Or is it completely useless?
Clemens, bam.
Thank you.
Very insightful.
Observation, can you recommend a book where I can learn more about
these kinds of things?
How did you learn it all in?
Such an intuitive way.
I mean, the answer is how I learned it.
All in an intuitive way.
Is I worked on character animation code for five years, right?
And character animation code is the place where this stuff gets
drilled into you quick because anything, that you do wrong will come
back to haunt you.
So, and licensable character animation at that.
So it was being used by hundreds of Studios.
So, every little problem that could crop up cropped up, and you have
to be able to work through it.
What I used for sources of the time.
I don't know.
I mean, I learned linear algebra out of Gilbert Strang.
People have said that's not a very good book.
So there's probably better books out there.
I don't know, I don't really remember him covering the similarity
transform, but he probably did.
I don't know that.
I learned it from him, though.
I don't think I did.
I don't really know where I learned that I really don't.
Yeah, sorry I really don't know where it's good places.
Just working with matrices, a lot and thinking about transforms a lot
helps with
Koreans.
I did a lot of the early work.
There was nobody had ever worked out any of that stuff.
At least not in our industry.
So, I was used to having to figure this stuff out on my own.
Like the quaternion multi-way linear blend was a bunch of stuff that I
had to do on my own, the, the quaternion double cover stuff for
character animation.
I did that on my own.
So I was very used to having to work these things out myself.
and,
And so some of these things were things that I probably saw in a book.
This one, I feel like I've seen this covered.
This exact thing, I think.
But I'll be honest, I really can't remember.
I don't know if I had to work that one out on my own or not, I
guarantee you this is covered somewhere.
I just don't know whether I read it or whether I had to work it out on
my own.
I don't know.
And sometimes it's something you work out on a Blackboard with someone
else to, you know, like maybe I was talking to somebody and we worked
it out you know.
So it could have been something that I collaborated with on someone
something like that.
It's not really a big, aha moment necessarily so it's not like it was
something.
I would have remembered exactly how I came about how it came about.
But yeah.
I would say the number one thing to Beyond books like books are okay
for math but a lot of books are bad at math like they don't explain
math.
Well
So I would say the number one thing to do if you really want to learn
this stuff and be really good at it.
Actually, the thing to do is write a program that renders it all.
So like I had this program, I wrote called math Vis and it was just a
little thing that Drew like grids and arrows and stuff.
And I used to do all my experiments in that and so I could draw
everything.
So, I'd like, draw all the frames of reference, like, I could draw all
these, I could draw the results of transforms and see, and it really
builds up your geometric intuition when you can see everything.
You know.
so,
you know, that's something to think about James Woodman.
Would any of this have been mentioned in the comments in the grainy
source code, or is it considered obvious to people work in the context
of this probably is pretty obvious, but like, in the grainy source
code, for example, there's a what there's a thing, the sparse, the
sparse B spline curve, fitting solver, which was a pretty crazy thing.
And it's day nowadays, I'd probably do it a lot differently, but at
the time it was kind of crazy.
That thing is absurd and there is like, you know, five pages of
comments at the top of it explaining how it works.
So some things in there are documented
Heavily because I'm like, this is very, very confusing what this does,
right?
So,
So this, I don't know, I mean, if you're working on character
animation, you probably.
But I mean,
You should probably know this by now so I don't know that I would have
commented this in any particular way I might have put a comment that's
like similarity, transform the thing or whatever, right?
And if you don't know what that is, probably you shouldn't be working
on granny.
I don't know.
I mean, I don't know like
If you don't know what a similar transformation, it's probably not.
You probably shouldn't be working on like some character animation.
But who knows, you know, maybe you could now because hey, it's already
built for you.
So just but now you're gonna get bugs and you gotta work through them.
So you'd have to know, I mean, you'd have to know that.
I would think.
All right, I'm going to, I'm going to wrap it up.
Oh, no, Milton.
I don't think I've ever seen Milton Clash before I must have done
something to make it Angry.
Let's see if it saved our work better.
This will be interesting test of Milton because I haven't ever hit the
save button.
Supposedly Milton just works and you don't ever have to tell it to
save.
Let's see if that's true.
Wow.
That's pretty cool man.
You got to admit.
That's pretty cool.
Can you undo after you reload?
Holy cow.
Okay, you got to admit.
That is pretty cool.
Right.
You just never have hit the save button and if the thing crashes even
you just reload it, it's there and the undo is even there.
That is so the way software should work.
That's awesome.
Sergey that is very well done.
Very, very well done.
I said his name wrong.
Again, it's Sergio with a, it's only Sergei on the stream, right?
It's like Serge x, y, z or something but it's actually Sergio in real
life and it's the one that I couldn't pronounce sexually in Spanish,
as like Sergio, but
All right, so I'm going to close it down.
That's pretty awesome Milton.
Well done.
Well done, sir.
If only Photoshop worked like that, I'm sure artists that Molly rocket
would be much happier if it did.
Thank you for joining me for another, for the handmade hero.
It's been a pleasure coding with you.
As always, if you would like
Follow along at home.
You can always pre-order the game, it comes to the source code.
We also have Forum site, you can go to if you want to ask questions,
you have a patreon page who wants fourth video series, the schedule
bot, that tells you when we're going to be live and then episode
guide, if you want to catch up on past episodes.
So check those out.
I'll be back here next week.
Schedule, a next week might be a little weird.
So definitely check the tweetbot for that head over here.
If you want to know what it's gonna be live until then everyone have
fun programming and I will see you guys on the internet.
Take it easy, everyone.