Start crying and now we can begin now that I'm sure that there is no
little snafu there.
Okay.
Hello, everyone and welcome to handmade hero.
The show where we coded complete game live on the interwebs using
absolutely nothing.
No engine.
No Library, we program everything ourselves from scratch as basically
both for education purposes and for just for fun, honestly, because I
like coding things from scratch.
And so today we have something
Fairly important that we have to tackle actually.
So I don't want to waste too much time before we get right into it.
So I will simply say if you are following along with the code and you
have pre-ordered the game on handmade here at org.
You should have gotten a link in your email in that link.
There is a ZIP file and in the zip file, there is ipps for every
single day.
You want to unzip day 42 source code because it's day 43 right now.
And we always start with the previous day's source code.
So if you unzip that into a director somewhere, then you can start
coding.
Exactly where I am coding.
Now and so you should be able to follow along precisely.
So let's go ahead and get started.
Like I said, on the, when I post it on Twitter today, what we're
supposed to do today is we are actually supposed to get ourselves a
little bit closer towards having some good player movement code.
By taking a look at the equations of motion, which are basically the
physics that underlie how real things in the world move, understanding
them, and then figuring out exactly what part of them we want to use,
or what we want to do in order to
To create something that feels good to play which is not always the
same as making something physically, realistic.
Usually what you want to do in a lot of scenarios is you want to kind
of know what the physically correct thing would be because the right
thing to do gameplay-wise is often close to that thing or has a lot of
the properties of that thing because people's brains are obviously
attuned to work.
The way physics works.
And to think about things the way physics works is what they have
experienced with.
But it is also often the case that you don't really want a perfect,
physical simulation, most of the time,
Because we want to kind of go more towards what's fun to control not,
what would be accurate, right?
We're not trying to make a simulation here.
Some games are trying to be simulation e, and those games should care
a lot about how accurate their physics are.
But in our particular case, we're more concerned just with the how the
player, how sort of the that hero character feels to move around.
And so in that case, what we really want to do is just kind of know
what the equations of motion are in the real world and then go ahead
and take the opportunity to sort of like
I'm a little and makeup except some equations of motion that are
whatever we think, feels the best just from playing with it.
And I don't even know exactly what those are going to be ahead of
time.
Right?
We're going to, we're going to, we're going to see by sort of just
trial and error.
What we end up thinking is the most interesting way to have our
character be controlled.
Now, if you remember yesterday, what we did is we started replacing
things with a vector structure that we have.
We actually turned it into, just at the end of the stream, we turned
it.
You're a union.
It's basically just this right here and all it is is it's an XY pair,
right?
Like that.
And we then then went ahead and made all of our code kind of start
working with that XY pairs kind of sucking that up a little bit in.
So make made a lot of things that were verbose a little bit more
straightforward, and we didn't actually spend the time because we kind
of got to little late in the Stream to actually condense everything
that we could have condensed.
Certainly we still left a fair number of things in scalar.
ER or even though we were doing them in Vector, maybe still left the
math as two separate things 14, X and Y, and that sort of stuff.
So we haven't done too much work in, that's our code but we did a
little and I don't really want to go crazy with that right now because
we can always do that later and there's really no particular need to
change working code at any particular time.
So rather what what I'd like to do now is just kind of concentrate on
this.
Can't this player P thing here.
Maybe, we'll think about looking at the camera for you as well.
But this player P is basically something that we had which is just
saying here is where the player.
Actually is in the world and what I'd like to do is start thinking
about that in terms of how we want to modify it and how we can make it
feel a little bit better.
So if we actually run the game and just look at what the game has
right now, you can see that the character motion.
We talked about this already.
Just does not feel particularly good its kind of As you move around
you just kind of feel like it's you know, it's just the most basic
thing.
It just kind of it stops instantly.
It doesn't have any kind of acceleration or anything to it or any
field are, it doesn't have any momentum.
So when I Let Go it just kind of stops immediately.
It just and there's really no, there's nothing good, really about the
feel of this particular about this.
And so what I want to do is start to fix that by.
Let's just, you know, just kind of adding in some basic stuff, give it
a little bit of that momentum.
Give it a little bit of that.
Like it accelerate and decelerate, just to give it a little bit of
that feel.
And we don't want too much in that, we don't want a crazy amount of
acceleration and deceleration because we still want the player
controls to be nice and tight.
This is an action game.
We don't want the player to feel like
Super soupy and kind of really hard to like stop where they want to
stop, but I just want to give it a little bit of something.
And so what I want to go over first is just to sort of say, what sort
of the background is here in terms of what what actually happens in
the real world in terms of things that are in motion.
And so what happens in the real world, right?
If I've got something this is my this is going to be my like a magical
sphere here, you know, maybe it's a magical sphere with a little
reflection on it.
It's like a bowling ball or something like that.
So I've got my little sphere or something.
And, you know, I want to start talking about how this thing moves
around.
Well, obviously, there's some basic things that happen with any
physical object in the world.
One of them is that it is constantly subject to a downward force and
we all know what that is, right?
That's gravity.
And gravity is a very interesting kind of a force actually, which we
can talk about a little bit more later.
We won't really have to think about it too much for moving the
character because he's not really falling.
He's always in contact with the
Out.
And we assume that like the gravitational forces are getting handled
by his little sort of Stumpy legs things that he has under there, that
kind of keep him on the ground or whatever.
But point being everything in the world is constantly under Gravity.
We know this.
So there's always kind of a downward force that that's at play there.
It's actually more of a gret downward acceleration technically.
But again, I said, well we can talk think about that a little bit more
later.
We have to worry about too much now and then any time that any object
is going to move.
It's basically
By the way, in which it moves can be broken down into sort of two
distinct.
I want to say categories or two two things.
You have to think about when you think about how an object moves.
And, and when I say this, we're talking about basically, I'm going to
just preface this by saying oops.
But this is this is rigid body dynamics that we're talking about here,
which is specifically talking about sort of the way in which matter in
the world moves.
When you reduce it down to the basic concept of just, let's assume
that all of the atoms and, you know, quantum physics and all that
stuff that makes up my little bowling balls fear thing.
Let's take those out of the picture and just say, if we just assume
they're all rigidly connected right now, and we're not talking about
what happens when the bulb
Six or what's happening at the molecular level and all these are the
things we're just talking about how the gross large sort of body that
these things form move around.
There's really two ways that we have to think about that.
One is called linear and the other is called angular, right?
And they are sort of exactly what you would think.
You.
You essentially have to think about how the thing moves around.
So like the path that this thing is taking through space, right?
How is this thing moving?
That's linear?
Are the sort of the the linear dynamics of it and, and sort of the
angular dynamics of it.
Are how it's rotating, right?
Because this thing could spin around, right?
It could do all sorts of things that in that in do sort of like a
rotational motion, even if the thing is sort of standing in one place
or sort of sitting in one place.
Now the physics Behind these two, things are not actually different at
the lower levels because again, everything is just a bunch of atoms.
Everything's just a bunch of quarks ever far down.
You want to go and those things all have physics.
That determine how
How they work and they aren't separated into whether the motion of the
atom was about the ball rotating or whether it was about the ball
moving.
So, down at the molecular level.
It's not going to be about what the bowling ball was doing out where
we observe it.
Right?
But in terms of our simulation of it, where we are making this
reduction and saying, we're not thinking about atoms are not thinking
about any of that stuff.
We're just thinking about it as one sort of gross object, because we
are treating it all as one group like that.
We have to think about both how it moves.
In space and how it spins.
Because those two things are necessary to figure out where all the
atoms actually were, when we go to actually say, okay, where is the
ball now, right.
So what we're going to do today?
We're going to focus on this part here.
We're not going to talk about this part, which is why I picked a
bowling ball because hey, a sphere.
You don't really care which way it's rotated to some degree.
When terms of how we're going to draw it, so, for just moving around,
I picked something to be nice and easy thing about in that case.
So we're just going to talk about the, the sort of the linear portion
of things.
We're just going to talk about the movement.
And so the movement, basically, we have forces in the world.
That's like, when I go to push on this ball with something, right?
When I, when I hand comes in and I just kind of smack the ball or
something else, hits the ball.
Like another ball comes in here and smacks the ball.
Basically, we have forces that are applied to this.
Object, and those forces.
Are all actually acting for the purposes.
Again of the rigid body Dynamics, sort of way of viewing the world.
You can think about reducing this object in all of its complexity down
to basically just its Center of mass.
So basically the center of mass which is, which is, if you think about
the, the entire sort, of all the matter, that's in this thing, if you
think about just thinking of where that centered, where all of it, if
you look at the, the point that basically, if you averaged how out,
how dense it is everywhere in it.
And figured out the center point of all of that density, you would get
the center of mass, which is basically a point, which if our sphere
was uniform, density, would be like right at the center.
Right?
And again, a lot of this stuff is stuff that you only care about.
If you start to actually do realistic stuff.
I'm just mentioning it.
So you can kind of know what we're talking about.
Right?
So we don't have to think really about densities and masses too much,
but it's just something, you know, Mass may come up a little bit, but
point being, if you're doing full 3d stuff, you would start to care
about a lot of this stuff anyway, so what we want to think about is,
we want to think about all of the
Forces that are applied to our object.
Okay.
So, all of these things that might be pushing on our object, at any
given time the gravitational part of it, the things that are pushing
out, directly impacts, that are happening, those sorts of things, all
of these things.
We have to consider in terms of figuring out where the center of mass
of our object goes.
And at the end of the day on any given instant.
What we want to do is look at all of these forces and determine due to
all of the forces that are impacting this thing right now.
Where is it going to be pushed?
What is the net sum total of all of the forces on this thing?
How is it going to be pushed?
Right?
And now there's a very fundamental equation that you probably have
seen before.
If you took High School physics again, it looks like this.
It's f equals Ma.
And what that basically says, is force equals mass times acceleration.
And the reason that I point this out is because forces, which are the
things that push on this ball, right?
Wind could be a force.
Example, you know something directly pushing on the ball gravity.
Could be a forest on etcetera Etc.
All of them are forces and the degree to which they affect the ball.
Remember the acceleration is what, what determines?
What's actually going to happen to the ball.
The acceleration that those four
Produce is mitigated by the mass, the mass of the, of the of the
object that's being moved.
Basically determines how much a for, how much each individual force
will actually affect the object.
Right?
So if we look at what all the forces are and then we want to see how
much those the some of those forces will affect our object.
We have to think about what its mass is and we have to solve this
equation.
Basically, for a, right?
So it's pretty easy, right?
Because it's just F over, right?
I'll if I want to solve for a all I do is divide by m, and
I get F 0, f over m, equals acceleration and that would be the
equation for the acceleration.
So, basically, the heavier object is the less.
It would move for any Force, right?
Because the M as the M gets bigger, the acceleration goes down for any
given force.
And that's exactly what you see in the real world.
The heavier, something appears to be to us the harder.
It is to push it.
That's just the intuitive way to think about this, right?
There's a lot more involved there.
But you know, that's basically an intuitive way of thinking about it,
right?
And so if I want to start talking about how physics actually works, in
terms of how it affects something like a rigid body, like a bowling
ball or whatever it is or our little guy there.
Essentially.
What I want to do is I want to talk about something, all the forces on
him.
I want to talk about Computing, what the acceleration actually is, for
all of those forces combined, right?
And so I do that by figure out what the mass of the guy is and I do my
divide and I get it, get out and acceleration.
And then again, I have to figure out how to
Relate this acceleration back to a position.
Right?
Because what I want to know at any given time when I need to render
this bowling ball, or whatever, it's goes, is that we're simulating.
I have to know where in the world it is.
That's like the primary thing.
I need to know in order to be able to display it on the screen.
It's also the primary thing.
I need to know to be able to do Collision detection or anything else.
I need to know what that is.
And so that's where we get to sort of the the hierarchy that you've
probably seen before.
Hopefully, but maybe not.
But
And velocity acceleration, right?
And this is what I talk about.
When I say the the fundamental equation of motion, the very the very
simplest stuff, that moves things around.
It's a hierarchy that looks like this and all of these things are
essentially dependent on time.
Okay, physics is all about what happens to things over time.
And so, when we're talking about when we talk about doing sort of
rigid by an answer for this or anything, sort of the thing, we're
talking about looking at this hierarchy of thing of information about,
you know, one of these
Objects that were moving around or doing whatever to we're talking
about looking.
How these three is quantities.
Change over time.
And these three quantities are all related.
If I want to know, if I say that, I have a function for an object's
position.
Then these three are related.
Very simply the first derivative.
If you remember your high school calculus, the first derivative of the
position is the velocity and the second derivative right of the
position is the acceleration, okay?
And so that is, you know, like again, these are just the fundamental
equations that govern.
How things actually work.
Sort of in the simplified representation that allows us to just
consider entire collections of atoms, if you will to act as one.
And so this, it may look a little daunting because I like he's drawing
these F of T is up here and he's got all this stuff and there's time
and I don't understand what's going on.
This is getting, this is getting confusing, but it's actually
relatively straightforward and I can kind of relate it back to what
we're doing in the code relatively simply.
We already have one of these things in the code, obviously, right?
We already have position because I just pointed that out to you.
That's right here.
That's our player P.
And we know this is our update Loop.
This is how player plea gets updated.
What were we doing?
Right?
We took the player position, we multiplied by however, much time.
We wanted to advance the Delta, the difference like however, you know,
No, the motion basically that we want this guy to take and we added
that into wherever he already was right?
And so, if you think about what that's doing, okay, again, going back
to our sort of vector, representation of things.
If the guy was here, right?
And this is my position.
So, this is my position right here.
If the guy was here, what were essentially doing?
Is we're saying we have a direction that he's going to go, right?
That's our deep layer right there.
And then we're multiplying that direction by the time by DT for a
frame.
Now.
Why did I call it DT?
Why did I call it?
DT?
Well, it stood and I didn't actually say this at the time because we
weren't there yet.
It stands for delta T tea.
Obviously is time.
Delta.
T means the difference in time, right?
It's the difference in time between two points, last frame and a now,
or in our case, since we're doing it slightly differently.
We're actually doing it.
The difference between the start of the frame and the end of the
frame.
We're looks sort of thinking about it in that sense.
So we're saying the frame.
The the stuff was here and now it's going there.
And while the frame is up on the screen.
We're Imagining the objects to move from one place to the other over
that time step.
So if we were going to do motion blur or something, it would be across
that time step, if that makes sense.
So, there you go.
So that's actually what we're talking about here.
Right?
And that's what we're doing.
When we actually do this update.
We're taking a direction.
We're multiplying it by delta T.
And that's how far we're moving him right now.
Remember, I believe we talked about this a little bit.
Now.
I guess we really talk about this too much.
So I'll mention it today because this is actually relatively
important.
We talked about scalar multiples of vectors, right?
We basically said that if I have a vector, you know, I could multiply
it by some scalar.
Like I've got a vector here, I can multiply it by say to and I would
get it.
Vector.
That's twice that length, pointing in the same direction, right?
And I don't think I ever actually said was, you can consider vectors
as having a magnitude, right?
We could consider vectors as having.
Like then we did a bunch of that stuff yesterday.
Remember we were looking the Pythagorean theorem and stuff and we're
looking at how long some of those vectors are.
So basically from here to the tip, you know, from the from the base to
the tip of the vector, right?
That's a particular length and that we call that the magnitude of the
vector, right?
So you can think of vectors is having a direction, which is sort of
the line along, which they're appointing and a magnitude.
And that direction is actually signed because it's either pointing
positively or negatively in that sense.
And then the magnitude you can
Think of, as how long it is in that direction, right?
So that's just something to keep in mind.
So, again, what we were doing, when we were actually Computing, the
update for our guy is we were taking sort of a direction upon a place,
you know, a sort of a line in which we want him to travel, which we
had set up here using what keys were down.
And then we said, we're going to move him as far along that direction
as there is time in the time, step, right?
However, big the time step was that's how far along the line we're
going.
Move him.
Now the time step of course is in seconds and it's going to be some
fraction.
It's going to be .0.
Something s right .03 three seconds or something like that because
we're at 30 frames a second.
So the amount of time between two frames is a 30th of a second.
So basically what we're doing is we're taking the vector and we're
making, it have magnitude point zero, three, three, if
If the vector was unit magnitude now, the vector isn't actually
necessarily unit magnitude, although I think it always is.
All right.
Yeah, so we always are actually setting that that Vector, you can see
here to be a length of 1, right.
It's going to be one - one - one, or one, that's always.
Got one is the magnitude and in the case, where we were going to move
both axes at the same time.
We solve the Pythagorean theorem to see what that distance should have
been in order to reduce it down.
To being the same as it was here, which means this is actually also
going to produce a vector of length 1 which, which is kind of amusing
when I think about it.
So yeah, okay, but we do do one thing here, right?
We've got one other thing in the mix.
In fact, I think I'll move this down below here, just make clerk.
So then what we do beyond that now that we actually know.
Okay, that's how we now have a vector, that sort of magnitude one.
We then said, we have a speed.
We want the player to go at, which is going to be 2.
Meters per second, right?
Because our world units are meters.
And we're talking about how fast this player is going to m/s.
Or if I have the special magic button down.
It's 10 meters per second.
And then we were multiplying the vector by that.
So we actually already did another magnitude scale.
Here.
We took a unit length of vector 1.
That's 1 that's only one unit long and we multiplied it by this to get
a vector which is that long.
It's going to be a vector.
That's two units longer 10 units long, depending on how far depending
on whether that button was downright.
and then when we actually go to move the player we multiply that total
vector by however, which is
Right here by however, much time we want to advance.
So this is essentially this.
That means this Vector, if you think about what its units are, this
Vector is the amount that the player would move in one second because
we're multiplying by fractions of a second, right?
So what were essentially doing here is this is meters per second,
right?
We're multiplying by S and just getting meters out, right?
Again, dimensional analysis.
So these are meters per second units.
If that makes sense.
This isn't S.
And so outcomes.
Second.
And again, we've kind of been sneaky about it here because we never
really came right out and said it.
But we were basically doing is we were doing all that essentially with
Vector math.
We were saying, we want to make a vector.
That's going to represent his movement and we want to represent the
movement cleanly.
So we can just say meters per second, which you'll note doesn't have a
direction to it.
This is just 10 meters per second in some direction and we let the
fact that we have a unit Vector pointing in the correct direction.
Tell us how
Construct, the motion in X & Y, that actually corresponds to this
speed.
Along that line, right?
I know it's a little confusing, but I just thought I'd point that out
just really briefly.
Okay, so we can go over this again in the Q&A.
If it's, if it's complicated know, there's a lot of Concepts here but
point being that's what's happening.
Right?
We're basically taking a position where we're starting where we've got
a direction and then we're trying to make the magnitude of our
resulting Vector, that we're going to move by P.
Proportional, both to how much time has elapsed and how fast the
player is going.
So we have a speed in meters per second.
We have a time in seconds, the S cross in dimensional analysis.
Remember.
So they get they go away.
And we're left with just the m.
We advance the guy by the meters.
And again, it's all in Vector.
So it's got a direction.
It knows what direction is going and it knows how far to go and boom,
we go, we get to our new position.
That's what we were already doing.
Now.
What is actually going on there?
Right?
What we know that position is measured in meters.
We already said that, right?
We already said that position is in meters.
Well, what is this meters per second, right?
So we did s we crossed out s.
Right.
We basically said, let me write this equation.
Actually explicitly over here.
We actually said, right?
We said we have Delta t, s times whatever.
Our player motion is so our player motion amount, you know, motion or
whatever you want to call.
It meters per second, write like this.
And I crossed out those seconds and I got meters, but what was this
sort of motion m/s.
Weird value that we were multiplying here.
We know this is a Time step, right?
We know delta T seconds is the time step.
But what was this nonsense over here?
Well, that's actually the velocity right meters per second.
It's how many meters somebody goes in a second and that is exactly
what we were doing right here.
We were actually doing a velocity based update of the position of our
our guy, we computed the
To be deep layer, which is either a two or ten unit long Vector
pointing in the direction, the players going, we multiplied by the DPT
per frame which basically gave us how much to move the guy in position
space for that time.
Step.
That's basically integration.
We integrated a velocity up to a position, right?
That's integration integration goes this direction, right?
This is a high school calculus again.
Integration goes up derivative goes down.
All right, and so we've already performed an integration.
You just didn't know, we were performing it, and that's not really
particularly surprising.
Because if you think about what happens here, right?
If you want to integrate a very simple constant quantity, you just
have some motion, that's not at all.
Dependent on any on time.
Right?
If you just have to integrate two meters per second, right?
Then obviously the integration for that, if you remember your high
school calculus is just multiplying by whatever the change is write,
delta, T is exactly how you would integrate that up to position.
Right?
That is a, that is basically a fixed a discrete integration up.
To a position now running out of space here on the board, which is
unfortunate because I'd like to keep going having these things around.
But yeah, no, I can't.
What can I say?
So let's think about this a little more explicitly, right?
Let's think about position.
And that's my f of T.
I've got velocity.
Which is my f Prime of T, and I've got acceleration.
Which is my f.
Double Prime of T right now what you know you I'm just going to write
down basically what you probably remember from your high school
Calculus class and then I'll sort of come back to what I was saying.
Just just a few seconds ago and kind of try to tie it up a little bit,
just to make it a little more solid, right?
So if I have some function of position, right?
I don't know what we want to say that it is.
I don't know.
Let's say that we just had some function of position.
So we have our F of T.
That means we're going to plug into T.
We want to get a position out, whatever it is, right, I could say that
that was something like 5T squared, you know, plus 2, t, plus 3,
right?
This is again, standard old calculus stuff that you might see, you
know, in a textbook, right?
And we all remember how you would do the derivatives, right?
If you want to take the derivative of that function.
You do this thing where you take the exponent of the variable, you
multiply it by the front.
And then you reduce it by one, right?
So you'd end up with 10 T, right?
Plus again.
This one doesn't have one.
So it's just this is just an exponent of 1.
So it's just going to remain to and then reduce it by one that gets to
the 0th, which is nothing.
And then this guy doesn't even have
Variable.
So he ends up getting knocked out entirely.
So he's just gone right?
And so we end up with something like that.
And that is the velocity of this thing right now.
You may ask like, how I don't understand.
What are we talking about here?
And again, you can think of these just as we were just just think of
these exactly what we're doing here, memory of the X and the Y written
out separately.
Think of these as the Xs and the Y's written out separately.
This is the x-coordinate of our guy.
Let's we just had a function that we said, you know, we just we said
he was on.
Rails.
So as time increases.
He's just at this x coordinate, we just compute it and that's where
he's at.
And we want to know what the velocity is, right?
So you want to know what the derivative on know how fast he's going?
So this is our velocity.
That's how fast he's going.
That's how fast he's going in X, right?
It's his meter per second.
That's what that is.
If we want to know is acceleration.
We can take it again, right?
We just go down one more time.
And again, we just this guy drops out.
This guy is removed completely.
So he just left with 10, right?
And that's actually what that's just directly what the acceleration
actually is right now.
What I hope you can see here, is these relationships are actually very
simple.
And if for example, right I wanted to know what I wanted to be able to
do this discreetly, right?
Because what you can, what you can think about here, is this is all
well and good, but it presupposed that I could write an equation.
That's the location of my guy but I can't write a location.
That's the equation of my guy.
The the users like entering, you know, commands and stuff.
He's telling me where the guy moves every frame.
It's changing and all this sort of stuff.
So I don't have the luxury of just writing.
Out some specific equation that says, where the guy is for all the
time in my game, for any time Step at the 1st 2nd 3rd 2nd, 5th.
Second, whatever, right?
So what I need to do is I need to move from sort of the way that you
think about it in high school Calculus class, which is perhaps not
very useful.
Even though all the tools are there, right?
I just need to start thinking about this in terms of doing it.
Discreetly.
So that instead of actually trying to make a function.
I'm just going to say we're going to discretize it down to one time
step, right?
And so if you think about it.
Here's our game time again.
Like we always say I've got x equals.
This is this is frame 0, this is frame 1.
This is frame to this is same three the same for right?
And so in time in t this is in frames right in t we basically at time
0 times point zero three three repeating .066 so on right this is what
the T variable is.
If I was lucky enough to have somebody who is always moving based on
just a fixed equation, right?
I really wouldn't have any work to do.
Do all I would do is just take that equation and wherever I was in
time, so I want to draw this Frame.
I just go 0 .066.
I plug it in here and I get the x coordinate out done.
Right, no problems, but we don't have that luxury because the user is
in putting stuff in all this sort of thing.
And so there is no constant equation that we can just use all the time
that will give us back the location of the guy.
So what we need to do instead is switches something where were
essentially discretize inning, these equations of motion and
pretending that the equations of motion are essentially constant over
the time step.
Meaning, we're pretending that the guy is just going to move in a line
over the time step.
And, you know,
Each the times that's going to be so short that he appears to like
curve and do stuff right on when he's actually, when you actually see
him, he appears to be changing direction and doing all these things.
Because over time, you're changing your inputs and all this stuff, but
really in any given time step, what we want to do is discretize it
down so that we're basically just taking the input that you gave and
applying some piecewise function.
The function that only is going to operate over that time step.
And then, on the next frame, we will essentially be using a different
function.
Which is a different which is response to the Keys differently, right?
And when I say function, I don't really mean much of a function at
all.
I'm just talking about a very simple function.
That's like like we already had where we have a vector Direction and
we're going to basically pretend that the guy is moving along that
Vector Direction by delta T, right?
Or something like that.
So very, very simple version of the function.
It's nothing nothing complicated.
Nothing too interesting, right?
So in order to discretize this, I guess what I would say is so, you
know, hopefully,
Ali.
People are comfortable with how to take a derivative and what we did
here.
And basically, what we want to do is say, okay.
Let's just assume right?
That every frame we're going to start down here with a constant
acceleration and then we'll just integrate it up right to get our
position to get our velocity in our position.
And we don't care about the fact that, you know, each time.
We integrate it up.
We're essentially creating a holy, a totally different function with
different coefficients.
Right?
Because if this Frame it's 10 and the next frame, that's negative 5,
we're going to completely different values.
When we do the integration up.
We don't care about that.
Like I said, we're just going to say for each frame.
We're going to pretend that we have a different essentially, a
different set of coefficients as if you will in our function here,
right?
So really, there isn't a whole lot to this.
We already did the work, you can read it right off of here.
Even if you don't know how to integrate, if you just know how to take
derivatives.
You've already got the answer, like, because we're looking at the
answer right here.
If we wanted to say, we want a particular acceleration on every frame.
Well,
Akira is that acceleration?
Right?
It's tap.
Right, that's the constant acceleration.
So let's just replace that constant acceleration right with whatever
we want the acceleration to be a whatever we compute it to be.
Okay.
We then say, all right.
Our velocity is the first integration up from that.
The 10 remember comes from here.
So this is actually
Going to be a and it's a times RT, right?
It's times whatever the whatever, the time value actually is and then
we do plus 2.
What is that too?
Right?
What does that to actually mean?
Well, the to is essentially the existing velocity, right?
It's saying this was the part that accounted for the acceleration, the
change in the velocity, right?
Because x t.
So over time, this is change in velocity.
This is the constant velocity.
So this is whatever velocity.
Was on the last frame.
This is what we're coming into it with, right.
So, this is just RV.
That's RV turn.
So 80 plus v is actually the term that we want to use for our
velocity.
Right?
And then finally, we get up here, you can see that we get integrated
up one more time.
This plus right here is just the existing position of the guy, right?
This, we're adding a new position for the guy.
We're taking his old position in updating it.
So this, this constant, that was in here before is just wherever he
was right there.
P.
Right, this guy right here.
Is the velocity.
Again, write that too.
That was the to, from right here, right?
So that's just the V.
And then here you can actually see any of, this is why I say, even if
you don't remember how you how to do integration.
You can Cheat It by just doing the derivitive and then doing it
backwards.
Remember how we got this?
We did 2 times 5, right?
Equals the 10.
So all we have to do is divide the a by to to do our final
integration, right?
That's why this was five instead of 10, right?
So instead we just have a
R22 + V + P, right.
So what does that actually give us that actually gives us the final if
I just read these off and get rid of the scribbles, right?
That basically gives us that our top equation for motion is, you know,
one half a times t squared, which is this term right here, right?
Plus v times t plus the old position, right?
So, whatever the old position was.
Yeah.
And again, this V is actually the old
Velocity as well.
The velocity right whatever.
And so this is our new position.
This is our and a lot of times we do p Prime for that.
So you don't to keep writing old.
You just assume that these were the old ones P Prime is the new
position.
So we just have P.
Prime equals one half.
Ay, t squared plus v t plus P, right?
And so if I want to note p double prime or basically the the, you
know, the new velocity right V Prime, then that's just this equation.
That's a t plus v and then
Finally, if I want to know the the acceleration.
It's just prescribed.
So basically, there is no new acceleration because we never saved
acceleration.
So there's just acceleration that we specify and now we can specify
whatever acceleration we want and we can compute any of the quantities
that we actually wanted to compute.
Now.
You will notice that these things basically don't even really imp.
These don't really imply all that much more stuff than what we were
already doing.
Right?
Essentially.
We just didn't have these terms.
Okay, we had this.
That's all we had, right?
If that makes sense.
I haven't really talked about the delta T part, but just bear with me
for a second.
There's a lot of stuff to cover here.
So I'm trying to make it.
Let's see how much we got.
Whoo, we're tight on time.
Alright, so
If you take a look here, we already had exactly that top equation.
Minus the acceleration, right?
We just didn't have an acceleration in there.
We had whatever the DT was times, the velocity that we wanted the guy
to go at, right?
And so, that was this, that's the velocity times the time, plus the
old position velocity times, the time plus, the old position, right?
So we were already Computing.
Part of this equation and your intuition, when you're writing a game
code Eve.
If you didn't know any of this stuff is to write that, right.
That's what you would write and that's what we did, right.
So really, the only thing we have to start doing now is thinking about
this other part.
That's maybe not so intuitive, which is that there's another quantity
here, which gets accumulated into that velocity.
So, the velocity is now something that's actually needs to be stored
from frame to frame, so that we know how fast something was going so
that we can update it with our acceleration, every frame, and then
integrate it into what we think, the position should be and so on.
And similarly,
In order to properly account for the effect that the acceleration has,
we want to put it in this equation as well.
We want to put in this part of the equation here, the one half, ay T
Square to account for the effect that the acceleration has over this
time step as well.
Right?
Because without this essentially, what would happen is we would be
assuming that that acceleration was not actually continuously
happening over the course of the frame.
Now we could argue which one of those we'd rather have whether we want
to have an instantaneous acceleration.
In which is what would happen if we didn't do it this way, right?
Let me let me, let me explain this a little more detail.
There's two ways we could have chosen to program.
This one is to do this step first, right?
And use V Prime here.
Okay.
Do you see what that would do?
That would still get us a t squared for our evaluation because
basically, this 80 is baked into here.
Write this term, right?
Which was normally V T, which is the old velocity times time, which
just says that velocity is carrying through from, whatever it
previously was carrying to this Frame, right?
If I change that to be V Prime T.
Well V Prime.
T.
Is this, right?
So if I multiply that out, I'd get a t squared plus v t which is close
to this but not quite because there's that one half in there.
So, essentially what happens is that 1/2 is counting for the fact that
the acceleration is being evenly distributed across the time.
Step not instantaneously applied at the beginning of the frame and so
it is
More accurate to do it that way, in terms of what you were trying to
actually simulate.
But we have to also acknowledge here for anyone who wants to write it.
The more simplistic way of just doing this and then using the Prime in
here is that we're gonna hack all these variables.
Anyway, we're going to tune all these variables to be stuff that feels
good to play and so at the end of the day, it's hard to get too
pedantic about it and go.
Well you got to do your one half.
Ay T square.
And if you don't do one half your you're not doing it right or
whatever.
It's hard to, you know, to really make that argument, right?
But what I will say, is, if you want to do real physics at some point,
you need to start thinking sweating, those kind of details, because
things start to get much more important when you're not hacking a
bunch of variables to just make the guy feel good or whatever and you
want to actually try and get realistic believable, behaviors out of
certain physical properties and that's our stuff.
So it's good to know what the equations are and how they work before
you start short-circuiting them.
So that you don't end up at a limit where you can't get past something
and you can't make something.
Feel our work, right?
Because you forgotten all the stuff in been sloppy, right?
So it's good to know.
It's good to know the rules and then break them.
Not just sort of go willy-nilly about it.
So I just want to kind of point that out.
Okay, so finally really quickly and maybe we'll have to go over this
again tomorrow.
Because there's been there's a lot.
I had to talk a lot to sort of talk some of these things out and I
feel like a lot of its just very detailed and tough perhaps to absorb.
But anyway, what I did want to say is where does delta T come in,
right?
Because those
Functions that I wrote over there, they were continuous functions.
So when I said one half, ay, t squared, right, plus v t plus P Prime
when I said that, that's just a function that where you plug in a tea,
right?
That's a function where I just plug in some T value and I get the
position straight out, right?
So what's going on here?
And the answer is well.
Remember what I said we were going to do is treat these functions as
if they only exist for
Time step, right?
So effectively what we're doing is every frame we're creating a new
equation of motion where we specify a new acceleration, integrate it
up twice to get our equation of motion that will store, you know, our
new, our new
velocity and our new position, right?
And so really, this is f of 0 at the beginning of a frame and F of
delta T, you know, however, much the frame time is is here.
Then on the next frame, we're going to do the exact same thing.
Again percent.
This is f of 0 and pretend this is f of delta T.
And what do we want to know?
We want to know where the guy would be at the end of the frame, right?
So if we want to know where the guy would be at the end of the frame.
Well, that's delta T.
That's what we would plug in.
So
We plug in delta T to R function, delta T, delta T and that's why
everything is in terms of delta T.
It's because really delta T is the time at which we want to know if he
wanted to know where the guy was at the beginning of the
Name.
We could still use the same equation.
It's just all of these terms drop out and we just get P Prime, right t
squared, if delta T if we're plugging in 0 for this, we're saying F of
0 that drops out because obviously 1/2 a zero is zero.
Same thing with v t if T is 0, the V drops out and we're just left
with P 1.
Which is exactly what we would expect.
If we haven't gone any further.
If we haven't got anywhere in time.
We would expect the guy to be wherever he was at the end of the last
frame, which is p Prime, right?
So,
Again, what we're trying to do here is we're just trying to put
together piecewise functions that get us from one frame to the next
and we restart the function at the beginning of every frame, right?
So it goes from zero to Delta t 0 to Delta, t 0 to delta, T right now,
that's not to say that we couldn't have some, some object that does
have a function that uses across many frames.
That's totally something we could do if you want to do.
It's just that's not something that's particularly useful for a guy
who's under player control.
Because when you're under player,
You really do restart your your acceleration, every frame in.
You're getting basically a totally different function.
It's not some smooth continuous function that can be mathematically
analyze in that way.
It's piecewise what it's called, right?
It's a piecewise function, which means, you know, a normal smooth,
continuous function.
Looks like this kind of thing.
A piecewise function is one that's got gas, you know, that kind of
thing, right?
And it doesn't actually have to be lines in between there.
It could be straight, you know, like this it could have curves but
then the curves, have sharp Bend points, right?
And those peace.
That's why they called piecewise.
Because there's basically it's pieces, right?
Little individual segments.
And basically, that's what we're doing with our stuff now.
Okay, so very quickly, we don't have very much time left, obviously,
because I had to sort of Yammer on it.
You about those things.
What what did I actually need their?
Well, remember I need a velocity.
I need to store a velocity, right?
I need to store and I usually use D like that's what I use.
Dd2.
No accelerations.
I use D to denote.
Well, I used EDD second derivative D for first derivative, right?
So, one of the things I need to do now is we were just working with
the velocity.
That was just a only existed on that frame.
We need to start storing that velocity because remember, V, the old V
came into play there.
The old velocity.
So we need to start storing that from frame to frame, and we can
assume it starts at 0, that's totally fine.
Because obviously we know that the guy will not be moving at startup.
He's just staying where he is.
And so then what I need to do in here is I need to start thinking
about this in terms of his acceleration.
Not his his
Velocity change.
So what I'm going to do instead here is say that this deep layer,
right?
That we're actually doing here is actually DD, right?
So deep layer is going to become the DVD player.
So that's actually his second derivative of his position.
Right?
And so now, what I'm going to do, I obviously still want to compute.
I want to compute those equations of motion the way that I said I
wanted to the thing.
So again, we have
Write them out for you again.
So, again, we have 1/2 80 Square D.
Right?
Plus VT plus old prop P.
That's our equation for.
I'm sorry.
There we go.
That's our new position.
Right?
And we have for our second derivative, right or our velocity.
Our new velocity is.
We said that that was just going to be 80, plus the old velocity and
similarly, the acceleration right is just specified.
We don't have to do anything about that.
We're just specifying it that the user is basically, this is this is
coming.
This is coming from the d-pad, right?
The user is saying what that acceleration is.
Okay, so we want to actually just compute that not too hard 1/2, write
a times t squared.
So I'll go ahead and say Square.
We need to write that we have written that yet.
So that's real.
Literally one half.
Ay, T Square dry time.
Really, just literally typing it in, then I want to do the same thing.
Or the the VT right?
The v t term.
So that's a curious, his velocity.
His velocity is the game State deep layer.
There we go, times that times that Delta.
There's tea.
And then I just need to use his old position which for, you know, just
to make it totally clear.
I'll put it in there and change this to it equals.
So that way it looks exactly like the equation.
We wrote one half.
Ay, t squared times, VI plus v t plus the old position, right?
So that's the update right there.
Very simple.
And the other thing I can then do is say I'm going to change his
velocity as well and so his velocity and there's a couple things we
want to actually talk about here.
So the velocity update is going to get a little fancy.
In this potentially because of when the player is Click colliding with
things.
But for right now, let's ignore that.
So that we can because we don't have a lot of time like I said, so
we'll kind of do a more straightforward version.
So to update that velocity to give him his new velocity again, it's
really simple.
It's just the 80 plus v.
And so I literally type that in, there's my a right.
There's my tea, right?
And and then I need my old, my old beat.
Which is this right there.
Okay, and so that's pretty straightforward.
Forward.
There really isn't all that much to it.
That is the entirety of the actual code that we would need to do to do
the update.
So all we really need to do now is actually create that that D&D
player correctly and so we could probably just leave it as it is right
now which is to say that he accelerates at 10 meters per second
squared now, right?
Because again, this is an acceleration.
So it is now no longer meters per second.
It's meters per second squared.
That is just sort of taking the derivative in time space, right?
Because remember T.
We are not taking, it's important to remember.
We're not taking a spatial derivative.
We're taking a derivative respect to time.
And so basically, we start off in M.
We get meters per second and then we end up with me.
S squared all the way at the bottom time is the thing that's
increasing in order of magnitude in in in power here as we take that
derivative.
We are never actually changing the meters because we're not taking a
spatial derivative.
We're not trying to ask how these equations change.
When we move around.
We're trying to ask how we move around based on changes in time.
And so, that is why you notice the M doesn't change, that's kind of a
topic for another day, but point being started to it anyway.
So we got our acceleration now.
And in theory, I think, actually, I, that was literally all the code
that we would need to write to give our guy momentum, but we need to
write that square function.
So in my handmade math, I'm going to go in here as well.
And add a little squaring function, a squaring function is just one
that takes its value and returns it squared.
But simplest possible thing you could imagine write a times a and
there we go.
So that's just a way and it there.
Why do you do that?
Why not just write eight times a well.
It's a little bit easier.
This might be a whole expression sometime, right.
Like,
Right?
Or something like that.
And you don't want to have to type that out twice because you might
make mistakes.
So it's nice to have a little squaring function that you can just use
to save on the type Hoops.
That's deep layer p.
And there we go.
So, I believe our guy, we probably have to slow of acceleration.
Now, I don't know if we do or not.
Now, there we go.
So basically our guy now has momentum and he behaves exactly.
As you expect, kind of like, for lack of a better term, like a hockey
skater, right?
Because remember, we've
Done no friction on this guy.
So now, he is essentially, you know, he's an asteroids guy.
He's floating in space.
He has no particular friction, but as you can see, you can see how
trivial that was.
And now he behaves exactly.
As you would expect a physical object with no friction to behave.
Just because we spent the, you know, what is it?
Five seconds.
I mean, I had to explain it to you for 45 minutes, but once you
actually know what it is, you saw how trivial that was to type in.
Right now.
We've got the correct equations of motions for the guy and it already
feels kind of fun to drive them around.
This is
Of ridiculous.
And so now you can actually see already.
The thing I was talking about, when I said the, we have some decisions
and some interesting stuff.
We have think about in terms of his velocity when he comes in here and
he sticks on that wall, right?
Our Collision detector isn't letting him go through the wall, which is
good, but we're not changing his velocity to be zero.
We're just storing his velocity.
As if it's still fully accelerated in that fully going that direction,
which means if I push the back Direction, I have to push for a while
to accept.
Seller ate him up, right?
And we could actually if we wanted to, we could probably do something
where we actually showed what his velocity was.
Maybe that'd be a good idea to do in the sort of quickly at the end of
the stream here.
And so what we probably want to do right because that doesn't feel
very good for the player to get stuck into the well what we probably
want to do very soon and I don't know if it's going to be tonight
because we're mostly out of time, but we want to start thinking about
things like obviously, when we do the friction and stuff.
We also want to think about things too, like updating velocity so that
the velocity is actually what his velocity.
Turns out to be after Collision detection, is done stopping him when
he runs into walls and stuff because that seems like a much senior
thing for the player to deal with instead of having this hidden
pretend velocity that, it doesn't really represent the velocity of the
spread on the screen, right?
So that's it.
That's really all there is to that.
So now if we wanted to write, we could do something where we
introduced some kind of friction as well to the dude, right?
And
if we wanted to write, we could say, as he's running around, he gets
some kind of a friction that's based on his velocity.
Right?
And I remember we mentioned drag as well, was another thing based on
based on the velocity.
And so I don't want to try to get into ordinary ordinary, differential
equations.
Obviously at this point, especially not with only like 10 minutes left
in the Stream, but if we wanted to right now, we could totally make
it.
So the this guy actually had some friction by doing a sort of like
approximated friction.
That doesn't actually quite do exactly the right thing.
So I'm going to go ahead and set our Loop Live code editing up here.
I'm going to have him kind of go this way and then come this way.
And then come this way again.
Like so and then have that go right.
So I'm going to let that guy run there.
While we make our modifications.
I'm going to go ahead and set him up over here.
And then I'm going to open the window.
I'm going to go ahead and do something.
I haven't done before, which is delete this window, and then actually
kind of come over here and do that.
All right.
So, here we go.
So now what we should be able to do right is we should we can see
that?
He's really swimming, like you can see how swimming it is for me when
I was controlling any kind of swims back and forth.
And so I want to go ahead and add some kind of a function in here.
That's going to reduce his speed based on how fast he's going.
So, the faster he goes, the more it will push back against him.
So like a friction force or a drag force that sort of thing.
And so again, I can't quite do this, exactly correctly because we're
going to need, are there for ordinary.
Differential equations, if we actually want to make something behave
properly, but for now, we can hack something in and so I will say, oh,
and you know, what?
We did fix the diagonal will be faster problem.
We just didn't quite do it.
The way that we said, we're going to do a little bit of that
eventually.
Anyway, so to do OD e here and so maybe we'll talk about that soon.
But anyway, so what I want to do here is I want to say, okay.
Let's apply that.
Friction Force.
Now.
I know how fast he was going.
On the last frame.
Obviously, and I also know how fast he's going on this Frame.
And so the question is I guess which exactly one do I want to use?
And this is where if you were using OD e it would be correct, but
we're not actually going to do that.
We're going to do the hacky version.
So I guess I'm going to use the old one the one from last frame.
So I want to say is kids, velocity.
I'm going to basically say his acceleration.
You know, I shouldn't do this.
Here.
I can just put it.
I'll just pack that acceleration.
I'm going to say that there's another force acting on him.
So basically his DVD player, right, kids acceleration.
I'm going to go ahead and say I want to add into that acceleration.
Here, I want to add in a force that's going to counteract his
velocity.
So basically, I'll take whatever his velocity is, and I'm going to,
you know, say that he's going to accelerate in the opposite direction
of whatever that velocity is.
And for right now, let's even say that it's the full magnitude of
whatever the velocity is.
So you remember, this is our acceleration.
So I'm just adding in an acceleration that's in the opposite direction
of the direction.
He's moving, right?
And so I'm going to save that will go ahead and compile that.
I don't know why it decided to open that window.
Do, that's probably the least useful thing.
It could have done.
There we go.
So that looks a little too strong right.
As you can kind of see when you're looking at how he's going.
It just looks a little bit too strong.
So maybe I'll chop that down a little bit.
Let's say point five, right?
That looks a little bit better and kind of see.
Right?
You can you can do is turn pretty good now, right?
So that seems like a pretty reasonable coefficient to use their, I
don't know.
Let me jump back in and actually drive them around.
Yeah.
Yeah, that feels pretty good.
Yeah, that's not bad.
Now.
I feel like I feel like he's still a little sluggish though.
So I kind of feel like I want him to be a little bit.
You know, I think maybe this this acceleration is a little too slow.
So I'm going to jack that acceleration up a bit and then maybe I can
make this guy a little bit higher.
Let's find out.
Oops.
So, you can kind of see that street even starts to look better, right?
As you're doing that and now I can make this dude, a little bit
stiffer as well.
Right?
He can sort of be a little bit higher because now I've got more
acceleration to counteract it, right?
Yeah, so feeling a little bit better.
It's still a little bit at again, the higher I crank, these two
values, the the stiffer that.
So the more that there's a counteracting force in the more that the
acceleration pushes against it, the stiffer that return to 0 is
essentially, if that makes sense.
So, if I crank this up pretty, pretty darn high, right?
And then did that, maybe?
I don't know.
I'm just, I'm just again just totally playing around with this.
Just to see.
You can see that he gets a nice fast.
Stop there.
Right?
I think I'm gonna give them.
Even a little bit faster than that.
So let's go ahead and Jack that 22, right?
This is why I said we're just going to, we're totally going to just
write whatever random numbers.
We want in here as we tune it.
So you can kind of, you can kind of see, he's already starting to feel
a little bit better in terms of that, that sort of stopping Behavior
or I'm gonna give him, maybe, maybe 1.5 the jackpot for tonight.
Again, we don't really want to spend too much time on this because
we're going to change much stuff.
So now he feels pretty nice like I could see, I could see playing a
game with that behavior.
Right?
I could see that being I could see that being just enough swimming has
to feel good, but not too much.
It might be still a little bit.
You know, there's a lot of things I'm going to want to do to this
eventually.
Let's put it that way.
But you know, for now that's certainly fine.
And of course, now I can sort of get him as it goes through here.
Now, what?
The other thing is, I can also still keep my
Ation key I suppose I can make it so that, you know, he gets a nice
big speed boost.
We and of course, since we did all that through the acceleration that
even keeps his momentum and everything, which is kind of nice, right?
Yeah, so it's all good.
We still have we still haven't fixed the Collision detection.
The question is action.
Still a mess.
So that's no good.
But wait, is our Y?
Is our oh, there we go.
That's like, are we not?
I thought maybe I broke something as he wasn't walking off the screen
there.
But all right.
There we go.
Yeah, so that's pretty good.
All right.
So I think that's good enough for today.
Obviously, we've got a lot of stuff that we'd want to do to make that
to make this more interesting.
And so I think maybe but, you know, that's the basics of the equations
of motion and I think they are relatively straightforward when you
start playing with them certainly and you know, will keep will
continue to talk about them more as we go.
Now one thing.
I did want to mention just really quickly that sort of kind of came up
with the end there and I just don't feel like I really set it up
enough for you to make.
Interesting.
Here is again.
Why vectors are so darn nice and why I said I wanted to get a little
simple Vector struct in there for us to work with before.
We actually did any real player movement code or anything.
You notice how easy it was for me to slam this, correction in here,
right?
To just say, I want something that's going to be a friction force that
acts against the players motion Direction.
Well, before we only had, you know, when this was all doing x's and
y's explicitly, it would have been
Harder much harder for me to start thinking about.
OK, there's two different directions that are happening.
What is the direction of motion?
The other one is the direction.
That's the of the opposite of the direction of the Velocity, like, all
of that.
Just totally.
I didn't have to think about because I can just go, this is an
acceleration that has a direction.
It's a vector, it knows directions already.
So I can go ahead and just add more vectors in here and it will
automatically figure out what the new composite direction is given the
fact that was adding two different Corrections.
In for the acceleration one, that's about what the users pushing in
one that's about the friction and it kind of just allows you to sort
of smush.
All this stuff together vectors allow you to keep like adding that
stuff in there.
And so again, it's really nice because I can basically say, okay.
I've got my acceleration for the player.
I started out having the direction that the person was was
Thing.
But then I added the sort of the, the force that was counteracting
some velocity already had.
And that gave me a new vector.
And then I did some other stuff like what the Collision which was
trimmed it down to hear whatever.
And the vectors just store all that and track all that really nicely
and the fundamental operations on them look intuitive.
Like, hey, look, I'm adding the negative of his velocity which acts
against his velocity, right?
It does exactly what you would think it would do.
And so Vector is just really help you here.
Because if we did all this in scalar,
It would just get so intractable so fast and we'd have x's and y's all
over the place and we were like, yeah, right.
And so that's what's really nice about that.
So I will stop talking about that now, and I will go to the Q&A.
So, starting now, please type in any questions that you have with q:
and then the question, so I can see it.
And please keep whatever.
You ask to stuff that we did on today's three more previous streams.
If you want to ask it off, topic question, there is plenty of time for
that, but we do it in the priest.
So we do it come about 15 minutes early from the scheduled starting
time and I answer whatever random questions you want at that time.
So if you do have random questions at off-topic stuff, I will answer
them.
I just want to answer them in the Q&A here.
Let's see.
So why use real physics instead of something more custom that can be
hand-tuned.
So well, we are using something custom that's hand-tuned.
Right?
I mean you just saw me hand-tuned it right?
We're not.
We didn't try to go measure anything in particular, right?
We didn't we didn't try to make this accurately simulate the motion of
a human or anything.
So the reason that we started with the physics equations is because
well and you know what?
This is actually pretty important point.
So let me really say this rather forcefully, actually I try and I try
to keep game design opinions, roughly out of the stream as much as
possible.
But I feel like this one kind of transcends game design, and there's
more about just good programming and good game development.
And that is so many games that I see.
That are especially indie games because they maybe are programmers,
who don't have as much experience with physics or whatever they feel
awful to control and they had, you know, it was something custom that.
They just typed in and that they just, you know, tuned for whatever
that definition is, but because they don't have perhaps the background
or know the the fundamentals of how physical objects work.
They're never really able to get things feeling that visceral physical
feel that you only get from starting with real equations of motion and
then tuning them into the position that you actually want them.
Which is to not to say that they're going to be accurate, but having
the full power of real physics behind you knowing what those equations
are and only violating them when you think.
Should yields a game that just feels so much more natural to a
person's brain?
Because all the stuff they expect to see happen to objects.
Does happen to objects.
Like if someone's trying to do a jump and it doesn't happen in a
parabola style shape.
It's a lot harder for them to intuitively understand how to make those
jumps, right?
And so a lot of times like you'll you want to start with that basic
concept so that the player has a leg up on understanding and using it
and
Then when you want to add air control and you want to add, you know,
whatever the double jump thrust or whatever, that's all great.
And you should do it but you should start with the basics.
So that people's built in understanding of how to predict the motion
of objects, which has been hardwired into their brain.
From birth.
Is it always having to do other stuff too?
To sort of compensate for the fact that you weren't giving them the
Baseline that they probably should have for playing the game.
And in our game already.
We have one of those which drives me insane, and that's the wall
stickiness thing, right?
When I see that happen.
It just feels awful.
And so, that's like the very next thing on my hit list, right?
When I think about what I would want to do here, and again, it may not
actually be the next thing on our hit list.
Because I tried to structure things in our in like educational order,
not in when I absolutely think I would go do them because they drive
me nuts order.
Or whatever that drives me nuts.
And so what I want to see happen there as I want to see a little
bounce, perhaps I want to see a nice smooth Glide along that, you
know, I want to have a real nice feel for when I hit an edge.
Right?
And so that already is not happening the way a physical physical.
Just don't stop.
When they hit a wall, they maintain momentum in the directions where
the wall wasn't, right.
They have that effect.
And so I want to see I want to see that happen to the object because
it feels so much better to have that actually happen.
And so yes, so I highly highly highly recommend that no matter what
your end goal is start with the closest real physical equations that
you can find to what you're trying to do and then back off them as
necessary to get the effect you want.
Don't go the other way around which is tried to start just typing
stuff in and hoping that you end up with something good because I see
that fail.
So often that I think there's a real risk there of, of jeopardizing,
the whole game because you don't get that feel of
The of the primary motion, correct?
And, and again, like I think I said in a previous dream.
If you don't get that feel correct.
Nobody is going to play your game long enough to find out the other
good things.
You may have put in it.
Your game design may be great.
But if it feels awful to move the character around people are just
going to like open it up and play it for a couple seconds ago.
This feels terrible and then shut it off, right?
And, like, you know, whoever's, you know, you try to submit it to a
competition or something, and the judges play it for five seconds, and
they go.
Oh, these people, clearly just don't know what they're doing.
We don't need to play anymore.
More.
Right?
And so it jeopardizes the whole game.
If you don't nail the compulsory.
It's right.
If you don't like
Actually, just absolutely get those basic things that everyone should
get, right.
If you don't get those right, you risk ruining all the other things
that you may have done really well.
Like you had to have a lot of great ideas that happen at a higher
level in the game.
And if you can't get that core, S to S feel, right?
You risk throwing all of that work away and, and having a game a game
failed at that could have been a success, right?
And that could have been a lot of fun for a lot of people to play.
So I can't stress it highly enough that like learning.
On how to do really good physics based programming which doesn't mean
simulation.
It just means understanding the basics equations basic equation of
motions and getting them, right.
Is a really, really powerful tool and I highly recommend that everyone
learn it and you can break the rules as much as you want to.
Once you learn them, but just don't not learn them because I think it
will have a lot of really negative consequences for you when you're
actually trying to make stuff.
Feel good.
Why not add an opposite direction or deceleration based on V, when
collisions occur doing?
This?
Slowly would allow the character to reach the final pixels.
Close to the wall.
Well, so we're going to be doing collision and what happens around
walls is very important.
And so we'll be spending a lot of time on that, a little further down.
So, so, hold that.
Thought for when we actually start working with, with, with the wall
stuff.
Are you concerned that actual physics will detract from the Purity and
elegance of the world's greatest jump code?
For those of you who haven't been with us, the whole time.
I made some of I was throwing something into demo, something very
early in the Stream and I made this thing where I just threw a sign
controller onto some, you don't even want to know what I did, but it
was awful and I said, I think what I said, I said don't ever write
this for jump code.
Yes, I am afraid.
I guess that might detract, gosh.
I hope it doesn't.
Let's see here.
What would you need to store if you wanted to reverse time Allah
braid?
Well.
That's kind of an open-ended question.
So, it's hard to say, but it does relate to physics very directly.
And so, I'll point this out.
So, the rigid body Dynamics simplification.
Remember I said we were doing rigid body Dynamics, which is a
simplification of physics that basically says, all right.
I've got some collection of atoms, right?
That makes up, you know, this block that I want to simulate and I'm
going to simulate it by reducing it down to its Center of mass, which
is some position.
I did it.
And it's orientation, right?
I'm just going to say that.
That's what I've got.
And I'm going to simulate just that Center of mass in that
orientation.
And I'm going to assume that the whole all the atoms in the block just
obey that and get moved along with it, right?
That, that the simplification in that simplification, a lot of things
just aren't real.
They don't work the way that they normally do.
In terms of the microscopic level because we're making a bunch of
simplifications.
And the I can't see these differences, right?
The rigid reread.
The reason rigid body Dynamics is so useful is because it captures
basically all of the interesting things that happen when
non-deformable objects do stuff.
Now, there's deformable body Dynamics, which allow things to squish
and do other sorts of things and that's a separate thing as well.
It's another simplification.
Yeah, but ignoring that for a second.
So the reason that we use it is because those equations of motion
capture, all of the things that are I is used to picking up on and we
go.
Okay, good, right, but one of the consequences of it is that it's non
reversible, right?
So you cannot, for example, take the state of the world, flip all of
the quantities and run it backwards and get back to where it was 15
minutes ago, and that's not because of our piecewise.
Jen.
Right.
We have our piecewise approximation is another thing that I'll get to
in a second, but I'm actually talking about the actual
non-participatory.
If the, you know, if the user wasn't even controlling someone the
actual non-participatory, rigid body Dynamics are simply
non-reversible.
And the reason for that is friction.
So basically what happens is when something slides along the ground or
when it hits air resistance, whatever energy is lost from the system
and things, slow down.
Now in the real world, that's not
True, there's all sorts of stuff that happens in physics and I don't
pretend to know all of this stuff.
But like, you know, you don't really have stuff.
Just slow down.
It produces byproducts like heat that are you know, transferring atoms
like all the all of the quantum physics is happening.
There's all the stuff that's happening.
So to say that it was non-reversible is a very different statement and
I think that may actually be reversible.
I don't even know, I don't know where physicists are on that kind of
stuff they come up with new theories.
Who knows?
But what we do know is our simplification is very
Reversible because basically what happens is the state of the world.
Let's say this was a Dye, this say this block was a bite, you know, a
Dye that you play, you know, craps with or whatever you roll this die.
It comes to rest on the table.
That's the end of the entire information you have.
So when that died, you know, it bounces, it comes down here at
bounces, roles and lands here.
If I wanted to get back that motion.
If I wanted to reverse time to, when the dye was in the guy's hand,
before he rolled the die.
Well,
I've got no information to do that.
His velocity right now is 0.
I can't negate it and have him move back to where he was.
And so, that non reversibility means that in order to do like braids
style, rewind, like you're asking, you actually have to store the
state of the world, at least at Key Junction points, like when things
stop and when they're not in free form, ballistic phase motion where
you know that you can just play it forwards and backwards and I'll be
the same.
So anytime there is friction.
Have that problem because energy is being lost from the system and not
accounted for anywhere else, right.
Another way to do it would be to record the friction forwards and then
play it back.
You know that, whatever, the way braid actually does it, I think is
just with compressed records per frame.
Like, I think he actually just compresses like a rewind stream and
plays that backwards.
I believe I don't remember how John ended up deciding to do that, but
we would probably have to do similarly, like we'd probably have to do
something where we stored records.
Of of guy's paths because these things are non-reversible.
You can't just play them backwards from state to state.
You have to actually know what happened to the guy in the past because
the system is lossy.
Let's see.
Is the character a bitmap.
Yes.
The character is.
We sewed asset loading.
Like last week ago, I believe and we loaded him in, he's actually
three bitmaps you'll see.
Hopefully maybe by the end of the week, but if not, by the end of next
week, he'll also be kind of bouncy because we actually he's made in
separate pieces.
And so I he can kind of Bounce and stuff.
So we'll be doing some more with that.
Let's see.
Are we going to normalize the vector from the input instead of just
having a special case for diagonals?
Yes.
Well, probably, I mean, I guess we don't have to, but that's how I
would normally do it.
We didn't do it that way because we hadn't gotten a normalization yet.
So you're kind of jumping ahead of us.
But, yeah, we will, at least start normalizing things pretty soon in
some circumstance.
But but yeah.
Will there eventually be a map function to help determine terrain for
friction and object collisions?
Probably?
I haven't super decided what I want to do in terms of whether there
should be a lot of slidy stuff or slowing down kinds of stuff, but
that's typical of these sorts of games.
So it's kind of in my head that we will have stuff like that, but I
haven't specifically thought of what would be super cool about doing
that.
So, I don't know yet, but probably.
You frequently say that you like names to be descriptive and you
shorten them.
When you use them often.
It seems like you use float, 32, or in 32 much more often than
vectors.
I'm wondering why V2, instead of vector to, or vector to.
The answer is actually habit these days.
I probably would prefer switching to I 32 or u-32 because I would like
those to actually be shorter.
And I just haven't done that yet, but that's probably would be better.
Why not break?
A lot of the super long code out into methods with reasonable names.
I know it's easy, but it's pretty spaghetti.
Like, so the reason for that is because we haven't decided what those
functions should be.
One of the problems that a lot of people often.
One of the things a lot of people often do is they break things into
functions.
Prematurely.
So the thing that I will point out here is that this only gets done
once.
So the only point in breaking into function, is to make it more
readable by introducing a name like update player position, right?
But we don't know if he actually want an update player position
function yet because probably will be wanting to use this sort of
stuff for updating more than just the player, right, but we don't know
what that's going to look like as we haven't had in a monster and so
on.
So I try to really emphasize not breaking things out into functions,
until you know, what they're actually supposed to do, and then you
break them out into functions.
There's nothing particularly spaghetti about it.
Like what's the spaghetti part?
It's just a lengthy function.
It will do nothing differently.
When I move it out into a separate function.
You'll do exactly the same thing.
So thinking somehow,
How that it created spaghetti - by having it in one function in that
it's less spaghetti, to move it out.
Is also a bit of a false idea, in some sense.
All you've done is made it harder for people to read the code, what it
actually does, and made it easier for them to read the code.
What it's semantically does, which is sometimes a good trade-off to
make, but it doesn't make the code any better.
Shouldn't you use a max speed variable?
Well, I don't know.
That depends on what we want to do.
Maybe maybe not.
Maybe we want the player to not really have a maximum speed.
We want them to be able to go as fast as they want to subject to a
bunch of forces in the environment.
So if they happen to float out into space somehow in some level of the
game, they could just go as fast as they wanted to because there'd be
no friction.
So I don't know, a max speed variable is kind of an artificial
construct and I don't know that.
I particularly think it's all that interesting.
Let's see.
So somebody says, friction negative acceleration based on current
velocity would feel much better in my opinion.
But that's what we did.
I'm not sure what you're talking about.
That is exactly what this is.
That is the friction.
That is a negative acceleration based on the current velocity.
That is literally this line of code.
So I'm not sure what you're talking about.
Exactly, but
Yeah, if you could be more specific about what that question was,
that's easy.
Zero wer, I could I could address it.
Can you derive the one half?
Ay, t squared, part of the position equation?
Again?
I didn't quite follow the integration derivation flow.
Sure.
And in fact, I can do it in either way.
I did it kind of the cheesy way because I'm not much of a I'm not very
good at integration.
So usually the way I remember stuff is to do derivatives.
I always remember how to do derivatives and I do those first, but I
can do it actually.
Either way.
I'm not so bad at integration that I couldn't do it either way.
So here's the derivative way.
And here's the integration way.
Okay.
So doing it.
The derivative way would basically would basically be saying, okay.
I know that I essentially have
the function for position.
Is going to equal something, right?
I have some acceleration times the squared.
I know that it's going to be a squared.
I know that it's going to be a squared time term.
And the reason that I know that it's going to be a squared time term
is because I know that I'm going to take two derivatives and each time
you take a derivative you lose one power of T, right.
So I know that in order for the, a to still exist down here, it would
have to start out with t squared.
Again, just talking through my thought process on how I do these.
So if I have acceleration times t squared.
I know I'd have velocity times T.
And I know I'd have the old position.
Right?
So F of 0, if you want to think of it that way, right or pee, right?
So whatever the old, whatever the position was at time, 0, that's what
I've got here.
So, I know that I'm going to take the old position.
I'm going to add the velocity times time.
I'm going to add the acceleration acceleration times t squared, right?
So if I actually just go do derivatives on this.
Now, take the derivative.
I would get to 80, right?
That's the derivative of this term plus v.
Right?
The T goes away.
Plus nothing because this is this has no tea in it.
So it disappears entirely.
Right?
Take the derivative again the V goes away and I'm left with just the
to a right, right.
So I'm just that's just straight derivatives going down, right?
And what you'll notice is, when I get to the bottom here, I've got to
a.
So if I was to use this as the equation of motion, I would always have
to think about my acceleration as actually being half of what I
actually am going to use to plug in.
And so really all I'm doing here when I say the 1/2 a tea is I'm
saying, okay, let's pre divide this by one half so that all the
equations can be just in a as the thing that I plug in is Michael.
Asia, right.
That's what actually I was doing in my head in order to do the
derivative.
Now the cleaner way to do this, if you
Actually know how to do math, which, like I said, I don't is to just
remember how to do integration.
And so to do in to, because that's the, that's the way you'd like to
be able to do it.
If you're a math person, it's good.
You just say I know that I've got an acceleration.
I now want to determine what is the velocity, right?
So you just have to integrate it up once and in order to integrate up
something once remember you, you raise the power of T1, right?
So you're going to get an 80, you raise property one and then you add
a constant, right?
It is whatever was there that got knocked out.
When we did the derivative, right?
And again, that's whatever the starting velocity was.
Right, right?
This.
I should probably write this better.
This is f Prime of 0, right?
And this is f Prime of 0, right?
So velocity is, is that?
Just, you know, I can keep writing it this way, though.
So, it's easier to write.
So, there we go.
Yeah, I guess I should just say F of 0 equals p f.
Prime of 0 equals v.
F double Prime of 0, equals a right position velocity acceleration and
I kind of use them interchangeably, which again is not, you know,
math.
People would not probably like how fast and loose I play with that.
And again, like I said, it's because I'm not very good at math.
So in my head they all kind of get jumbled, I think of them as both
ways.
I think of them as a function that's getting derived twice and I are
just having a strip of Taken twice.
And I also think of it as position velocity acceleration, right?
I just, they're all kind of mixed up in there.
So anyway, I take the integral once and then you take the integral
again, right?
And so, again, you have to do that process in Reverse.
You have to say, Okay, this this obviously is going up to t squared,
which means that I was multiplying by 2.
So that means I have to divide by 2, to find out what the coefficient
is this time, which is the one-half, this guy has to have his power of
T raised again.
So there's TV right integration and then there's the constant which
again is the old
even so this is actually the cleaner way to do it is to just start
with the A and go up, right?
But I have a hard time remembering how to integrate some time.
So I like to just do the do derivatives down and it's then it's clear
how you do them.
If I think about doing the derivative in Reverse, I can remember how
to integrate, but if I don't, I can't.
So, I don't know.
So that's it.
So hopefully that's pretty clear how that works.
It's pretty straightforward.
And if you don't know how to do this stuff, Thomas,
And Fini.
Is your go-to location by this textbook?
It is an excellent calculus textbook and you can learn how to do all
the calculus that you want to do.
Even.
I think I feel like it even has the garage multipliers one of my
favorite things ever, but Grand multipliers.
All right.
We're not gonna talk about LaGrange multipliers right now.
Okay.
Do you feel something like bullet or box2d of player?
Movement is appropriate every time.
Right.
It's been too fiddly to get stable response.
Yeah, I mean, I don't know.
I don't know much about those specifically but that I share your
concerns.
A lot of times when I've had experience with physics code that was
supposed to be like full physical simulation, kinds of code.
I find that it is pretty fiddly.
And so usually, and especially for a game like this, where it's an
action, any kind of game that's not supposed to be simulating about
like there's not going to be crate, stacking, puzzles, or whatever,
right?
What I tend to do is I tend to like I like I was sort of suggesting as
a good idea there.
I tried to start with a sound physical basis, for what I'm doing.
So that I know that my motion will be mostly correct.
And then I back it off to be whatever I wanted to happen in gameplay.
And I find that that's a really good approach using a full physics
simulator to do stuff while it has some advantages.
I find that they are.
Oftentimes like you said very unreliable, very difficult to control.
They can be crashy.
They can have a lot of bugs in them just by the nature.
Of physics.
It's not necessarily because like bullet or box2d is bad.
It's because physics simulation actually to do everything right and to
get everything.
Correct is actually very difficult.
And so, there's just a lot of drawbacks there.
And so, if you can, if you can come up with ways of getting real
physics into something that is itself, not a full physical simulation
that can often be the Best of Both Worlds, but sometimes you don't
have that option because sometimes you really need, if you're trying
to do stuff with all that real physical object interaction.
Sometimes you really need full physics.
And then, you know, you got
Gotta You Gotta Have It?
Let's see.
When would you want to use other integration methods?
I've read boiler is great for everything.
So actually isn't this already Euler.
This is forward Euler.
Are you thinking of backwards, Euler?
All right.
So those are numerical integration techniques so we can start with
that.
And also this is actually not really integrating in any particular
way.
Like the sort of stuff that you're probably thinking of where you have
to take large Solutions of things.
Let's, let's table that for some other time because that's like a very
that kind of question is is probably best left for when we have
something a little more complicated that we might actually want to
consider something like backwards or therefore, which I don't know if
we're ever going to get to.
But
Like stable numerical integration is not necessary for what we're
doing right here because we're never going to get into a situation
where this wouldn't be stable.
And so thinking about things like the choice of integrator is not
particularly important.
And so I just don't know if that's ever going to be within the scope
of this of what we're doing.
But yeah, it's a good question.
And then I hit return and find out that he wanted to correct.
That question to, I've read order isn't great for everything that
makes more sense.
I was like, why are you saying that we're not doing well.
I'm like, we're doing it for words or there.
Maybe you're thinking backwards or I don't know.
Okay, so let me let me address that slightly then because I can answer
your question a little bit better if that's if that's what you're
thinking about.
So the reason that sometimes you have problems with integration
systems is because they can get out of control very quickly.
So the problem is, if you think about what happens here, there is a
Time step, right?
And that time step.
Like I said, we're pretending starts at zero.
We're running it to F delta T, and we're basically saying, we have
some function that says, where our guy is going to be over that time
step.
Now, what can happen is, you can have certain equations of motion.
This is probably not going to be one of them because of how simple
we've set up things to be.
But if you had a complex system of stuff that was pushing on each
other or doing whatever it was going to do, you can get into
situations where the function that you're that, you're trying to
represent has some very critically bad behavior.
When you try to integrate it, and typically, when you're looking at
things like this, you're talking about doing integration.
That's not analytic integration like this.
This is, this is actually fairly analytical integration.
We've actually created the full equation for position.
We've just created a piecewise and we're just flat-out solving it.
Right?
But what happens, a lot of other times is, you're actually doing these
equations of motion as approximations to things that are actually a
lot more complicated.
So instead of
This is the actual equation of motion for the guy.
This is actually what it should be and we're just actually solving it.
But if instead, what we were going to do is basically Point sample.
Some set of information for this acceleration right where instead of
saying well, we're just assuming that the guy holds down whatever key
heels down in the end the guy moves in that direction or whatever,
right?
Let's say that we had some really complex physics function here that
was going to produce the acceleration right here.
And then we're going to assume that over this time step that that
acceleration is constant and we're going to
All up to see what the equations are.
Well, that could be very dangerous.
If these equations are very stiff and what that means, the stiffness
part of it means.
If they have some very sharp, should I explain this?
We're, this is, this is really an exploration that's way ahead of
where we are.
So I'm trying to think of how to explain this in some kind of nice
way.
All right.
Suppose s'posin.
Here we go.
Supposin.
I was to tell you that I wanted to integrate this like function here.
Right?
And I wanted to be able to basically say, alright, what we're going to
do is we've got a frame time steps, right?
And I want to basically say, I want to trace out this path, but I'm
only going to actually be able to sample at certain points in the
path, right?
And what you have to remember is the state of the world, right?
The state of if these equations of motion, get more complicated, then.
We don't actually know what they actually look like in practice.
That's when you have to go up to more fancy Mass.
Like I said, I'm kind of dancing around this year.
But what you have to imagine is that you're actually in a field of
functions, right?
That look that basically like there's a family of functions and you
don't know actually where the one is that you're trying to follow.
Okay.
And so at any point in this field space I can basically say, all
right, wherever I am tell me what the derivative of this function is.
I'm going to step.
Up the equations of motion forward to the next time.
Step, and that's where I'm going to say.
Everyone is.
And then I'm going to look again, and I'm going to look at the
derivative and I'm gonna do the same thing.
Right?
Well, what ends up happening, if you have these sorts of situations
where the equations are complicated enough, that you can't write those
simple closed-form things.
Like, what I just did is you can see that you get into problems very
quickly because what's the derivative here or the derivative points up
in that direction?
I step that far and I get to my next time step and I say, okay, I'm
here.
What's the derivative?
Well, the derivatives is really steep thing that goes up there.
I come here.
Here.
And I go out to here and I go.
Oh, all right, bad news guys.
We're nowhere near the old function, but I don't know that because I
don't know what the function actually is.
I just know it's this very complex thing that can't be analytically
integrated.
So, now, I'm here, I take the sample of, with the derivatives there
and the derivative is pointing back down here, right?
So basically, I step down here, and I get here and, you know, maybe
this thing curves up again, or whatever.
And so, I step out there and what can happen if you're in a very bad
situation where these lines kind of,
All go up like that.
Like let's say that they look kind of more like this sort of a thing.
You could get into a situation where you just fly off into space and
you're nowhere near the old thing that you were.
If you're doing forwards Oiler, which is the name for the kind of
integration that you do where you just sample, the derivative and step
forward, right?
One solution to this is backwards other.
And this is why I said, when you said I've read or Euler isn't great
for everything.
It's forwards.
Euler.
That isn't great for everything.
It's forward Euler.
That's not great for games.
Backward, Euler is actually very good and what backwards Euler is
backwards.
Euler is when you go to the time, step that you would next be on.
So, instead of doing it this way, where we took the derivative and
step forwards, instead.
What you do is you go to the next time step and you search along this
line, essentially for where points back to the place that you were at.
So it solves it in reverse.
What that means is you can never have
I'm out here because this guy pointed in a totally different
direction, right?
So what would happen when we took this time steps, we'd come here and
we'd look for some point in this in this area that pointed back to
where this was.
Right?
So it would be somewhere that was kind of like down here, right?
It would be off the curve but it would be off the curve in a less
energetic place, right?
So it would it sucks the energy out of the system and bring things
back to rest when it is wrong, rather than flying them off in the
middle of nowhere.
When it is wrong, right?
And so backwards Euler is actually very good.
But it's much more expensive which is why you often don't do it.
So I don't really want you to think about what we're doing, as forward
Euler though, because this is this, all this stuff is stuff.
That is way outside the scope of what we're doing.
This is numerical integration and we're not really doing numerical
integration.
We're basically doing analytical integration.
We're just doing piecewise analytical which I realize sounds like
hand-waving because piecewise analytical.
Why isn't that numerical?
Well, it's because we actually I'm actually saying these are actually
The equations of motion for the guy and they just happen to.
We just happen to change what the constants are when the user pushes
the button, right, but we know what they are and we can integrate them
up.
Analytically.
I just did it for you.
We showed the one half.
Ay, T Square thing.
And so so we're not really doing something that falls into this
category.
So hopefully that answers the question there and we're kind of way
over time here, but let me just take a look and see if there's
anything else.
Let's see.
Yes, I was going for a figure skating analogy when I said you have to
nail the compulsories.
Let's see.
We use rigid body even after the hero gets his three parts bouncing
all that.
Yes.
We will.
I'm only going to do the deformable stuff on him.
Non-physically mean the deformability will be purely a graphics
effect.
It will not be based on solving any kind of gelatinous equations to
make him like, you know, gelatinous around or anything.
Let's see.
EB 0wr, I'm sorry.
I meant that you could take some constant friction and increase it
exponentially, as velocity decreases so that the character would stop
much faster in the end of its movement without that sliding.
I am running forward, I suppose, but whatever.
Yes, so I do agree with you.
We probably will do something different for his motion.
Eventually that has some slightly different properties.
But yeah, you're jumping ahead a little bit too much.
Remember, we got to go one step at a time.
So we don't leave too much stuff on explained.
If we had to rain ice or mud, we could use that as the scalar for the
friction deceleration.
And with almost one additional line of code from today.
We'd have something convincing somewhat convincing interaction.
Yes, that is absolutely correct.
And that's again, one of the reasons to frame it correctly as
equations of motion and friction, is because you don't have to do any
extra work to figure out how those things would be.
You just literally are changing, whatever that coefficient of friction
is and that'll get even more true as we do sort of more physically
stuff in there.
All right.
I think we are done with questions for now because we are out of time.
I think I got all the ones that pertained to the actual stream.
Anyway, again, if you're asking a bunch of questions that have nothing
to do with the stream that we were just doing or that or a previous
day's code.
Come if you want to ask those questions, I will answer them.
Just come to a come 15 minutes before the scheduled start time, and I
will answer them on the pre stream.
Okay?
Thank you everyone for joining me.
For a very mathy, handmade hero today.
I'm very happy with where our guy is now though.
It just feels so much better already.
There's a bunch of things.
I still want to do the movement coach.
It still doesn't feel as good as I wanted to, but of course, we're
definitely at the park where it's like, okay, I could see actually
playing with this guy.
Now rather than, than before, it was just awful.
And so we're getting there.
Baby steps and we'll make some more baby steps tomorrow and we'll
start to get into some pretty respectable territory.
I think and that's always a good thing.
So thank you very much for joining me.
It has been a pleasure coding with you, as always again.
If Hoops.
What is that?
I don't want you to save anything from here.
No, discard discard clothes, clothes and discard.
Okay.
There we go.
Again, if you would like to have access to the source code, you can
pre-order the game on handmade hero dot org.
And that gives you full nightly access to the source code, which I
update every time after we're done coding.
So if you're interested in that, all you have to do is pre order and
you can download any time you want follow along at home.
Try playing with code yourself.
If you want to make changes and see how they work.
That's also pretty good and it comes with the art assets as well for
the all the stuff that we use on the stream for development are
included in there as well.
So that's kind of fun too.
So, you know when you try stuff out home, it'll actually
Like it does on the stream.
We also have patreon.
If you want to support our sorry patreon, if you want to support the
video series, you can click on that link and subscribe and there.
And we also have a cool site that a lot of people have spent some some
pretty significant time, making making pretty awesome.
There's the news in form.
So if you're trying to learn from a stream, I highly recommend it.
There's an episode guide.
Newly updated episode guide actually.
So it's got a nice index page.
Now that's got some cool stuff on it to that.
We've now synchronized it's pretty sweet.
A lot of folks up here that you see in here.
I've done a lot of really great work on it.
It.
So if you're trying to catch up with old episodes, I highly recommend
going in there.
It's got some great stuff.
If you click through on the episodes got like, time-coded Jump Markers
and all this stuff.
It's really awesome.
There's a coding resources page where you can look at ports to Mac OS,
X or Linux, if you're interested in that sort of stuff and other sorts
of things you might be interested in.
And finally, there is a game.
I'm sorry, a code discussion forum.
If you can jump to, where you can ask questions of stuff like that, if
you're having trouble, or if you just want to talk about something
that we've done in a little more detail, so I highly recommend, if
you're learning to try to learn from a series to check that out.
It's great place to go.
So thank you, everyone.
Tomorrow.
I believe is today, Thursday.
I want to say is that true?
No, today's Wednesday.
So we've got one more.
We've got tomorrow at 8:00 p.m.
Pacific Standard time.
So I will see you here tomorrow at 8 p.m.
Pacific Standard time, and then Friday, of course, is early morning
stream.
That's 9 a.m.
Or so.
I usually see these folks in Europe at that time, but but tomorrow, I
hope to see you all again.
8 p.m.
Pacific Standard time for some more player movement code, and now that
we got the equations of motion out of the way.
I think it should be simpler for us to kind of do do a few more things
in short order.
So, thank you everyone for joining me and I hope to see you tomorrow.