Go ahead and flip the recording so we will have a nice clean one for
the YouTubes.
Welcome everybody to handmade hero the live show where we code a
complete professional quality game from scratch, using absolutely
nothing.
No libraries.
No nothing.
So that we can basically see how every little part of a game works and
I've said it multiple times.
I'll say it again.
I think it's absolutely crucial for a good programmers, education to
kind of go in and just see how everything works and really understand
it.
Before you start to do things, like using higher level stuff for using
libraries and stuff like that.
And there's just not a lot of material out there.
The kind of shows how to do every last little thing so that you can
kind of fill in those gaps sort of as you go and become a better game
programmer.
And so, what we're basically trying to do on this stream is build a
game where we build absolutely everything.
And so far.
It's been going pretty well.
We've basically gotten through the win32 interface portion of things.
We're at the point where we're playing sounds and showing bitmap.
Stuff on the screen and abstracting both keyboard and Gamepad input.
So are pretty close to being at the point where we're going to start
actually just working on the game part of the game, which is not too
bad, considering the fact that it has been, I guess.
Let's see 17 hours, which is not a lot of hours.
We only do one hour a day.
So that is not very much to consider how far we have come.
And so I'm pretty happy with our progress and I hope you are too.
Today.
Our primary goal is to sort of finish cleaning up the win32 input.
Stuff just get that nailed down so we can kind of move on and forget
about it and also maybe start to take a look at timing in the game
Loop, which is one more thing that we've kind of got that we've got
sticking around that needs to be cleaned up.
So I'm going to go ahead and jump in here.
Obviously for those of you who have pre-ordered the game you have
access to the full source code if with the link that you got in your
email, if you download that every night it gets updated so you should
have a zip.
You look at what day were on, run 17.
You should have a zip that has all the days Source codes in it.
So you want to unzip day, 16?
Because that is what I'm starting with here on day 17.
We always start with the previous day's source code.
So if you want to follow along at home, unzip that day 16 and you will
be exactly the same place that I am right now.
When I open this up, so where we left off.
Let's just talk about that for a minute.
Basically, what I done is inside wind main, which is our entry point.
I had gone and said, well, I
I want to add keyboard input here and I just kind of quickly did a few
things to get us in position to finish it up today.
Basically, what I did is, I said well inside our wind main, we had a
message Loop where we basically processed our messages from Windows
and I moved that out into its own function here.
It's called win32 process spending messages.
And basically what I do is every time through here, we ask Windows.
If there are any messages to process and as long as there are in our
while loop, we will process those messages now, I didn't want to
actually
Our window Handler, our Windows callback function.
Basically, for our window.
I didn't want to use that to process the keyboard input because I was
pointing out a very important thing about flow control.
Basically, when Windows does its call back.
We have no control over what gets passed to that function are this was
our window callback function here.
Now, we need to have this window callback function because sometimes
Windows calls our window function with stuff directly like the WM
paint a message, will sometimes come in just completely out of the
blue.
Ooh, it won't go through our message processing Loop.
Windows knows because we registered, I don't know if you remember this
way back from like the first or second day, I guess, second day,
probably Windows forced us to register.
A thing called a window class, which talks about the window.
The kind of window.
We're making an in that we gave it a callback and it is actually free
to call that call back anytime it wants to.
So we pretty much have to make sure that we handle some set of Windows
messages in here, that can be dispatched at any time.
However,
Messages.
Do not seem to ever be dispatched out of line like that.
They always go through the actual proper message, loop with our Peak
message, and so on.
So if we want to, we can process the messages right here and just
never bother to have Windows dispatch them.
Because, normally, what would happen when it's not sending out a band
like that is Windows, sends us the message first in this Loop.
It allows us to pull that message off the queue and then it lets us
tell Windows.
Okay.
Now it's time to dispatch it to the windows routine.
Okay, to our window, handling routine.
So let's
Of a little bizarre.
It's like, we pull it off.
We look at it.
We then tell it to dispatch.
That would actually be a nice way to go.
If it weren't for the fact that windows can sometimes just sneak in a
call directly to our window.
So we have to have the window practice.
Nothing we can do about that.
But what we can do is for all the messages that don't get
spontaneously sent like that.
We can choose to process them in here and that's really nice because
what it means is we can actually just have this still be in our
standard control flow, we can control what gets passed to it.
So it's nice and clean.
It could be more functional and of course what I
Bi-functional, we haven't really talked about that on the stream.
Let's something that's worth noting.
So I'll mention it here and I'll mention it again a couple times
because it's something worth understanding.
When you're doing coding, there's kind of two general ways.
You can think about a given function even though there always are
functions and programs.
If I have a function and I will call this functional function.
Let's say this is a functional function and then I have something,
which is a procedural function or whatever.
You want to call it function with side effects.
Let's say function with side effects because side effects are
typically what distinguished something functional from something that
What distinguishes two sets of functions is whether or not into
functional or non-functional, when we use that term basically a
functional function is one, which does not modify anything other than
the stuff that it is past and that it returns.
So basically
It is going to get some some values which are not pointers to things.
They're not references to stuff like graphs that can be crawled or any
of this sort of stuff there.
They are actually getting in values, which themselves are not sort of
writable memory and then it returns something that is the result of
whatever it's going to do.
So, you know, maybe it's going to do this sort of thing.
Right.
And I am going to return that.
Okay, so this is an example of a functional function.
It
It takes two things in two things, which it does not use to go modify
other stuff.
It returns integer never touches any Global variables.
So basically it is entirely, it is functional almost in the
mathematical sense that you would think of a function in math, where
it takes parameters in and outputs a result, but nothing else changes.
The state of the program does not change in any way other than the
fact that this result was computed.
That's it.
Now, when you have something called side effects, in a function, it
ceases to be functional.
And
Basically what that means is, if let's say I did something like this
and then I had something like Foo star Foo.
And here's my Foo, right?
It's got some stuff in it.
Maybe it's got a pointer to a bar and it's got an aunt in it and it's
got a result and all sorts of things.
And in here, I just go.
All right, you know, and maybe I still pass the Y so, you know, I'm
going to go ahead and take the foo Arrow result equals the X Plus Y
and so on, or I might even do something where I look at the bar.
Our and I find out, you know, if the bar Z is equal to 5, I'm going to
do something, right.
This is more typical of C style stuff.
And basically what ends up happening, right, is you can see very
quickly that the understandability of this function becomes much
quicker much more complex when I have, sort of things that fall out of
what that diverge from that functional style.
When I'm not just taking some simple parameters in and having a simple
return, 50 come out I start to
A lot of more complexity into what might happen when you call this
function, right?
Like maybe this function is going to write two Foo result.
Maybe it's only going to write to through result under some
circumstances.
So on and so forth.
And basically what I've produced is something that in order to
understand what happens when you call this function, you have to
actually understand the structure of the data of the program and how
it exists in memory.
You can't just look at it truly and go.
Oh, I see I pass it to
Ames and back comes the result.
That's all that's going to be.
There's nothing's going to change in the state of my program.
The state of my program is effectively immutable to this functional
function.
The program state is identical to when I called it.
The only difference is I got back a result that I can now use to do
something.
Whereas in this one, the state of the, the actual data state of the
program has been mutated by the act of calling the function.
And that's kind of what we mean.
When we say side effects.
It's calling the function changes.
The permanent data store in the program, in a way.
Means that if you called it's a twice in a row or if you inserted a
call to it between two other calls, those calls themselves.
Could also be changed how they operate right to functions with side
effects getting called in opposite.
Orders.
For example, might have a different effect whereas to functional
functions called an opposite orders.
Can't because they don't change anything.
So if I call a function of one function function and another function,
a function, I know that I could swap the order of those calls.
For example, and nothing would change because the only
Only state that they're getting is what's passed in the parameter.
So unless I took the result of one and pass it to the other one.
I know that they have no connection to each other whatsoever.
And so there's just a lot of things that happen when you can boil
something down to a functional function.
And there are programming language that are all about being almost
entirely functional.
For example, like, you know, things like ml.
For example, our programming language is based around this concept.
It's a very limiting way to program, because there are so many
options.
There's so many things, the CPU can do that are off the table.
Now for you, but if you are in a situation where you can make things
more functional without sacrificing something, it is often beneficial
to do so because it makes the understandability of the program and the
reliability program increase in most circumstances because now there
isn't this knowledge of the
Eight of the program that has to be going through the programmers
mind.
When they do things in order to make the program work properly.
They can literally just see a function know that when they call it
does the same thing, no matter where in the program you are.
They don't have to worry about setting something up, shutting
something down, all these sorts of things.
And so what I typically try to do when I am programming is I do try to
push towards functional when it is not prohibitive to do so, so what
does that mean?
It means passing things as parameters, rather than using Global state.
It means passing things by value rather than by reference, if possible
and making them so that they're not going to be changed by the
function.
It means limiting the access of functions to only the things that they
need.
Absolutely need to use so that they're easier to understand.
And I never, really, ever get to a point where my code is super
functional.
That never really happens.
It's not the nature of the kind of code.
I tend to write, but I do try to make.
I do try to follow those steps.
To sort of increase the function honest of the program because every
little bit you do is a bug down the line, a readability plus down the
line that didn't happen, whatever, you know, that sort of thing a
complexity down the line that you'd have to deal with.
And so what I did like to do here is basically there's a more complex
program flow thing that would happen.
The way that we used to do things in our old win32 window Handler.
Sorry finding trouble finding it there in our win32 me.
Nguyen, do call back if this
Processing the keyboard messages here.
Right?
If this were passing the, If This Were pressed processing those
keyboard messages, it would have to have a place to put them, right?
It needs to store the result of those keyboard operations.
And in order to do that.
That means, it would have to have access to the input structure.
But as you can see, I can't pass that in here.
I can't give it the thing that's supposed to be operating on because
Windows has defined the function prototype for this call, and there's
nothing I can do to insert myself in here.
So, in
In order to get in order to basically do the plumbing necessary to get
the keyboard, basically, the place where the keyboard result should be
written, into this function would require a global variable using the
local storage in the window itself.
Using Windows to get inside of property.
For example, I would have to use something that is very much not
functional at all because it would basically be something where the,
where the state was completely implicit and you just had to know.
Oh, hey, by the way, the main window callback just magically knows
what
The right to and it got it from this Global variable and hey, don't
worry about it.
Right?
And I don't like having things like that so I can do much better by
pulling it out into a function that's under my control.
Because while again, it's not going to be functional at all because
it's using a message queue and pulling messages off accused.
So there's nothing functional about this function for the most part,
but I can make it into more of a stable, functional flow control where
I'm still passing the output Place directly in and it's
Anibal very clearly understandable in that functional way.
It's much more easy to understand for the program or what's happening
by saying.
When I do went through, due process messages.
I just pass it directly where I want the stuff to go, and that allows
me to use this function anywhere.
I want to, to basically say, here's where I want you to put the stuff
and anyone else could use that to put stuff in a different place if
they wanted to.
And anyone who calls?
It knows exactly where the results are going.
They're not in this state where they're like, I don't know.
I said I had to set a global variable first and then it figured it out
and so on.
So, something to think about something to think about.
People were saying on this.
I just glanced at the chat.
Just then they're saying I was a little too loud.
We could easily turn the oh, you know what?
I think this was not this was oh wait.
No, that's the microphone.
I think we could set the microphone down a bit though.
I'll do a quick.
Mike check.
Is that is that better?
Is that less clippy?
When I'm talking?
What do you guys think about that?
I'm gonna I'm gonna this is an example of me talking as loud as I
talk.
So there you can tell me in this dream and I glanced back at it to see
if maybe that's a little bit better, if that's less clippy for people
on stream.
Let me know if that's better, if it's harder to hear me.
All right.
There we go.
So now that you understand why I did that.
What I do need to do now is actually finish the actual keyboard
processing because we didn't actually do hardly any of it.
We didn't actually do the work of getting things into a good state for
using the keyboard.
So the first thing I want to do is I want to kind of look through here
and kind of clean up the way that we're thinking about input.
Because it wasn't set up particularly well in the first place.
So, the first thing I want to do is I want to say, all right, let's
just let's just for now because like we said, when we get down the
line later in the game is more complete.
We will kind of revisit how we're doing input and how we map things
and all sorts of stuff like that.
But for now, what I'd like to do is say, let's give the game.
Basically, let's have the keyboard come in as One controller.
Like it's like a Gamepad, right?
The keyboard comes in as a certain controller its controller 0, let's
say,
Say, and then the first game pad is controller, 1.
In the second game pad is controller to let's make it look like that.
I think that'll be a sane way to do it to start and then later we'll
kind of get into things maybe where we want to do something a little
more complicated than that.
As we see what our game actually wants, but I'm going to go in here
and basically say, oh and the other thing I should probably do is put
this it goes to make sure you don't put anything down in the corner.
I always forget to put my little blocker up.
So I remember not to put any code in the corner.
So let's go in here and just take a look at how we're storing things.
Finally, we've got four controllers mapped in here.
But what I'd rather do is up at 25.
So well for gamepads, and the keyboard is basically how we'll do it.
And so the keyboard controller will be controller 0.
But then we kind of go in here and use these controllers.
Instead.
We're going to actually say, all right.
Let's make this be controller.
This is X input.
I'm sorry.
Basically, our controller index is mapped differently.
So we'll say our controller Index.
Right is going to be the controller index.
Plus one because we're basically leaving space for that keyboard
controller.
So now there are actually five controllers in here.
Not not for.
So when we go in here, we will basically have to modify our check, for
how many controllers we actually think is the maximum.
So basically, what we need to do is we need to say one for the
keyboard.
Plus the excuse me Max count and then we'll just double check if
that's all fits and then off we go.
So that's actually what I wanted to to dupes developments.
Good spelling off to a good start with our spelling today.
Even spell.
So that's good.
Oh, and this is something that I think I forgot to do yesterday.
You'll notice we have a a link warning here.
So basically, I showed yesterday and I think some people missed it
because the stream dropped out and so if you didn't watch the Youtube,
you missed it.
I showed basically here how to on the 32-bit build, how to get it
working on Windows XP, but you can't actually use Windows XP builds if
you are doing.
64 bit because 64-bit builds with the 64-bit compiler.
Don't run on the Windows 51 XP thing as far as I know.
So basically what you want to do is we actually want to have sort of a
32-bit build line, and a 64-bit build line.
And in the future, what we're going to want to do is actually build
both potentially, but like I said, I couldn't do that yesterday
because I have to go do a bunch of stuff getting extracting stuff from
VCRs to call the right compiler directly.
Since you can't use the same compiler to build both in all these other
sorts of things, but
but basically, what we want to do is say
There's going to be to build types, right?
There's going to be one.
That's for when 64 and one that's her win32 so we could do them like
that.
But what I'd like to do is most of the stuff is shared between the two
of them.
So what I'd like to do is I'd like to just take a second and say let's
set a variable here.
That's basically like for now, we'll call it common flags and will
kind of do we'll do some more work with this in the future.
But let's just say, you know, okay, we basically want all of this
stuff for now to be in our common flags, all of this stuff kind of
comes in
Here, right.
That's our common, common compiler Flags.
Let's say.
And then we'll do common Linker flags that are just the things that we
actually wanted to pass to the two different parts.
So what's your grab that?
They're put that up there and say okay that's common Linker flags.
And basically all I'm going to do is say alright, so this subsystem
piece will take that out of the common and we'll stick it in only the
32-bit version.
Then, right?
And then this one here will just be basically the same as that only it
won't have that one piece.
And so then that'll let us do either of them.
I believe.
Oops, it's not right.
I'm missing that is that right?
There we go.
So basically all I did here just made two lines, one for the 32-bit
build.
So basically we've got the 32-bit build here.
And basically, we've got the 64-bit build here and they're going to be
exactly the same except for those things.
We might change.
The things and the future will make another variable here for release
flags as well.
So when we want to turn optimizations, we can do that.
But let's just do that and get that out of the way.
All right.
So now we've got our our controller as well.
I'm going to go ahead and make sure that we didn't mess anything up
there because I kind of was talking about a ton of things there and
hard for me to pay close attention to what's going on.
So I like to run the game periodically to make sure I didn't do
anything.
Horribly bad.
Alright.
So now that we have this, we need to actually process our keyboard
controller for real and so we need to do
Is when we actually take the new state of the keyboard controller.
What we probably want to do is say that it should actually, if we look
here, the way that I've got it, we basically want to preserve some of
the state.
We've got.
The the ended down thing and we have to make sure that the ended down
we have to make sure that if we don't receive any keyboard messages,
this Frame, we are still accurately.
Representing the state of the keyboard, which is not something we're
actually doing at the moment.
We always
Zero out the state of the controller.
So if a key goes down will receive a message will set ended down to be
correct that we implement it.
But we did in to do is actually make sure that it would then persist
to the next frame.
So it would still appear to be down.
And and so that's what we have to actually handle now.
So, what we want to do probably here is basically we only really want
to reset the half transition count.
We want to leave ended down basically the same.
So what we can do, we can do that two different ways, I guess.
Do is I'll clear the keyboard out for now and I will just Loop over
these buttons real quick here.
Basically say that the button index for the keyboard.
You know, I'm going to go over the array count of keyboard controller
buttons.
And from there.
I will basically take each one of those things and I will, I will
basically map.
I will map sort of the old one to the new one.
So, we've got the old input and I've got old keyboard controller, new,
keyboard controller.
And basically, what I'll do,
Do is I'll 0 the new one and you can see what I did here was just make
a blank one and assign it to do a clear.
And you see I did a zeroing macro to do which maybe we'll do today
during the cleanup if we've got time.
Basically.
I'm going to come in through here.
I'm going to take the old keyboard controller and I am going to grab
its buttons here.
So I'm going to get its buttons.
Pull out the button in question and I am going to make its ended down
equal to so I'm going to make the new one I should say.
Equal to the old one.
So this basically just copies whether or not the key was down to the
new one.
So that way we know that when we come in here, our new keyboard
controller has the same ended down state, but we now know that the
half transition count is clear, which is what we want, because we're
supposed to count half transitions per frame.
So when I come up here into the processing Loop, and I look at what
I'm calling.
I'm calling the win32 process keyboard message.
Basically, what happens is, I anytime I get the message I change, I
increment that half transition count.
And then I reset the end of down to the correct thing.
So this basic just count.
How many time we changed it?
I can also assert here that basically, the new state ended down is not
equal to the new is down type, because remember, we're only supposed
to be getting this keyboard message, if the state changed because we
very explicitly check for it.
Right here.
We basically say, we're not going to process the keyboard event.
If it was just saying that a key was down, it was already down.
So that's key, repeat message.
And we don't want to be a slave to Windows key, repeat settings, or do
any stuff like that.
We want to take that out of the equation.
By early.
So basically, we just want to assert that we didn't do something
stupid because oftentimes in programming, you will do something stupid
because you forget what's going on or you make a change and don't
realize what's happening.
So, we want to assert here, just say, hey, look, we want to make sure
that when we get an is down message.
It's actually a difference.
It's either, if it's true that it's down, then it's the key should
already be marked as down because our half transition count would be
wrong at that point.
And we also want to check the opposite.
If the key is saying that it's going up, we want to make sure that it
wasn't already up.
So now when I do that,
At, and fix the, the bugs here, typo typos, and there we go.
Basically, all I need to do is verify that that worked at all.
We'll go in here and there you go.
So that's me pressing the button just like I would have on the
controller and hey, it works perfectly.
Now.
We need to process the directional stick, and that brings up something
that I've been wanting to do for a while, which is we actually need to
kind of finish all of our directional stick stuff because our Gamepad
directional stick stuff still had it.
Any as well, which is basically that we had a we basically had a dead
zone processing to do where we didn't, press the dead zone because we
didn't really talk much about what the dead zone was.
Now the dead zone is basically it.
No, not, it is not a game about zombies.
Although, with the way the game industry is going these days.
It will probably soon be a game about zombies.
Somebody out there right now is maybe taking the handmade hero
platform layer and is turning it into a game about zombies called Dead
Zone.
And that is always
Possibility.
But basically, what what I wanted to talk about is The Dead Zone on a
controller and you can see here is my pink controller.
Basically, what happens is the sticks you have to imagine inside.
In fact, this is translucent.
You probably can't see it.
But inside there's a, you know, that stick basically connects to a
circuit board and it's got some Electronics in it.
I think they're usually potentiometers.
I don't even know.
I'm not a hardware guy.
So to be honest with you, I have no idea what actually goes on in
there.
But what I can tell you is that
The accuracy on these things is awful.
So basically, even though this is back at zero, like we would all
think of that, as not, the stick is not doing anything right now.
That is actually not what the electrical reading is on the stick.
The stick right now, actually thinks it's somewhere entirely else and
basically, we can even demonstrate that by basically going like, okay.
Let's go in here and set a break point.
For example.
Somewhere.
Oops, that's that's not good.
What's going on here?
I didn't mean to actually modify my code.
Yeah.
So basically, I've got the, the stick, the stick is back at its
neutral position.
I'm going to go in here to our code and I'll just take a look at what
happens when we pull it, right?
So I'm going to pull it.
Here we go.
Let's get down in here.
So basically, we pull this thing and what did we actually get back for
our X and Y?
You can see that they are definitely not zero, right?
There's no, he's in there.
And so the
Of the stick when it is quote, unquote centered is actually not zero
and that's not actually a bug.
That's just how that's the tolerances for which these controllers are
designed to operate.
Like they aren't designed to give back an exact zero.
When the thing is centered.
They're designed to be somewhere around zero and the thing is
centered.
So in order to correct for the fact that the player thinks the stick a
center, but the stick is not centered.
But we need to do is apply a dead zone, which is a region around zero
where we will effectively consider it zero.
We are basically widening, our opinion of zero, and you can see that X
input basically defines these values that they want you to use in
order to be compliant.
And, you know, so we will use them basically what they are.
If I can get the msdn documentation with them here.
Let's see.
Whoa, come on.
There we go.
Internet.
Go Go internet.
Basically what happens if I can scroll down to.
There we go.
The Dead Zone here.
So, basically, what we want to do is we want to use that dead zone,
this input Dead Zone thing, which they have.
They have actually defined it.
Again.
I don't know why they actually it was there to find begin with.
I don't know why they did that point being here are the dead zone
values, right?
Basically what these dead zones are saying, is that any value for the
left thumbstick?
That's left, less than seventy eight Forty.
Nine short.
That's a 16-bit value.
Right?
So you can kind of imagine what percentage that actually is.
If
We want to do the calculation.
So oops, help.
So basically if you imagine 32768 is the maximum sign short value -
that it would be.
And so, if we, if we actually look at what percentage that is 32 768,
if we say 78 49,  32768 like that.
You can see that that's well, you know, if you look at that number,
it's surprisingly large.
It's somewhere between a fifth and a quarter of the stick is just
Flatout being said is not usable, right?
It's like they're the Xbox standard, I guess is basically saying we
are going to manufacture stuff that is up to almost up to a quarter.
A quarter of the range is just gone right in any given Direction and
it's even worse for the right thumbstick.
That's even a little higher, that's closer to a quarter, right?
So that's that's, let's see here, divided by 32 768.
So that's actually over.
Twenty-five percent.
So, that's just to give you an example of how large that dead zone is.
It's big.
So what we want to do here is we want to basically just pretend that
if we get values that are that are in that range, that they are not
really going to be considered valid values.
We're just going to.
If they're, if they're inside that range we're just going to treat
them as zero.
So in order to do that, I'm not sure exactly how I want to do that.
I did the range mapping here.
I feel like they're basically saying that this
Have to be applied in either direction.
They're not really clear on the difference because if you'll notice
the negative range is different than the positive range.
Like I talked before, it's one greater.
So it's a little odd that they're the same.
We don't really know very much about it.
So we're going to have to take their word for it, but it might be nice
if they had done a little more documentation here to talk about the
difference between positive and negative.
In this case, because like I said, - 32 768 is a negative value, 32767
is actually the positive.
You right?
So there is a difference in range there and we're off by one a little
bit.
So it's odd that they didn't respect that.
But those are the dead zone values.
We're going to use them the way they suggest to use them.
Basically, what we're going to do here is we're going to change our
processing to basically start out by saying that the X and the Y are
assumed to be 0.
We will then go ahead and access the excuse me.
We'll go ahead and access these values will say if
The oops, if the pad all you know what I can actually do it just like
this here.
So I can basically say this whole thing is predicated on this being
lower than the dead zone in this direction, right?
Like that.
And this thing is predicated on it being higher than the dead zone.
Now.
I don't remember if they said higher than the dead zone or higher than
or equal to they did say higher.
Yeah.
Now this is
Well, that's an interesting thing.
Oh, the oh, it's a magnitude check.
Okay, that's fine.
We'll talk about that.
It's like, all right.
So anyway, this right here is basically, this right here is just
saying, all right, we were already checking, so that we did the /, the
right value, depending, whether it's positive or negative.
And if we look at what's Happening Here, we can basically say, all
right.
Now, what we're doing is saying don't even set the value of x, unless
the value on the GamePad is already less than the dead zone for - or
already greater than the value for positive.
And so,
Just leave it set at zero otherwise, right?
So you can kind of see the way that that works, right?
And then similarly, we can go down here and set this guy and and do
the exact same thing.
This guy will just be doing the same thing.
This is our left thumb dead zone as well, right?
Like that and Pad s thumb.
L, y greater than and now the only thing that we have to do is is we
have this we want like the - right.
We want to be less than the negative version of The Dead Zone, so
We needed to stick a negative in there, right?
If that makes sense, because otherwise we be checking it was less than
the positive value, The Dead Zone which a negative value always is
going to be.
So we want to make sure we catch the range on either side, right?
So that's that's really it.
There wasn't a whole lot else that I wanted to do there.
But I just want to make sure that we got that in there so we can get
rid of our to do.
And then we can also say, well these two things look very, very
similar, right?
They're almost the same.
So what we could do is we could change this to a went through to
process xinput.
Stick position, right.
Or
Or stick value.
I guess we could call it.
And then we can go and say, all right, we know that we would pass it
the LX.
So basically pass it.
Whatever the value is.
We'd pass it.
The the thumb Dead Zone value, that it should use, and then we pass it
basically the place to write that into which actually is going to be a
little problematic for us because we need to sort of group.
We need to group The the left, and the right stuff, which is a little
tricky based on how we've done it.
I could pass values to each individual one.
Maybe that's the easiest thing to do or I can I can sort of
short-circuits that process for now and not go the full route and just
do this.
So what I could do is say it's say that right.
Hopefully that makes some sense.
So we're basically say, we'll just use that same path and then down
here we would do, you know, this sort of thing Pat with the, with the,
with the ly doing the same thing there for the dead zone.
And you'll notice we're using the same dead zone for X and Y, which
seems weird.
But I guess that's how the controller is supposed to work.
Have the same dead zone for both.
I don't really know but that that appears to be what they are
suggesting.
So I'm going to go ahead and pull that out so that we basically have a
function that does exactly what I just said.
Here we go into our utility function here just so I don't have
multiple copies of this function and that is this.
So it's going to look like something.
Which basically just takes in first, the short I believe is what this
is defined to be.
It is a short.
Is it capital short?
I think is what they are.
Let's take a look.
What is the name here?
It is.
One of those State structures X input State.
Just want to verify that.
It isn't short Capital.
That's what they actually are using for their 16-bit.
We could use in 16 if you wanted to but I was
To use the actual thing that they have defined it to be so too short.
That's what I thought.
So basically up here.
We just want to take that short value.
Whichever one we're taking.
So this is the value and then we are going to take the dead zone value
as well.
We'll call that the dead zone threshold and then, inside the function
we just do exactly what we did before.
We basically, now just use whatever value was passed in as
The go and we use the dead zone instead of that so that we can
control.
If we want to use the other stick, at some point, we can use it.
And then we have the result equal to the value as well.
So that is basically all there is to it.
Nothing more and then we can return that.
So there is our processing for the stick.
Looks pretty good.
I don't know why that happened.
That was cut and paste bug, and so, there we go.
Now we're
Piling and I don't know if we were actually working yet.
We may not be.
Oh, right.
I can't test this yet though because that is on controller one now.
So, what we need to do is now actually in our code that someday will
actually process real controller input.
Hopefully, that'll actually probably be pretty soon.
But basically what we need to do is set that is analog.
So that's set to true and we need to actually check that controller.
So basically, what we're going to do here is maybe we will
Just flat-out, check all the controllers in a for Loop right here.
So basically we'll say controller index equals 0, we will go ahead and
Hoops.
That's no good.
Push to overwrite mode accidentally will basically just check all the
controllers like this.
So that will pick up because we were only picking up the keyboard now
because it's controller zero, so I'd rather just do this.
I'll change input 0 to be controller.
That and we will go ahead and grab every controller in a loop.
And for each controller will basically just do the operations directly
for each one.
Now, that basically won't work for tone Hertz, tone Hertz will get
overwritten.
So, the last controller, whoever the last controller is to report is
analog will overwrite tone hurts, but that's okay, for now.
We don't really care about that.
There we go.
Looks pretty good.
Nice and stable, and that dead zone processing, seems to be working as
well.
There's no Jitter there we can see as well.
When we start up.
We no longer have the occasional, you know joystick is moving problem.
That looks pretty good.
I should also check what happens if I unplug
There we go.
It is unplugged now and now I will plug it back in.
All right, so that looks pretty good.
However, I don't understand.
I'm not sure why you see that that happens again.
No, it didn't.
I'm not sure why we were having that weird tonal thing happening.
Yeah, well seems, okay, for now that was a little suspicious.
I want to check when we actually go I guess.
When and do sort of more thorough checks on some of this stuff.
We'll see pretty quickly if that's right or wrong, but everything else
seemed to work properly.
So I think we're in good shape anyway, so that is all I really wanted
to do for that.
Now, I want to also make a couple changes to the way the stick stuff
is handled.
And I thought about this, I was kind of, I was lying in bed and I was
thinking and I'm like, oh, okay.
I was falling asleep and I'm like, oh, I should really have done the
stickhandling a little differently.
I realized there was a smarter way to do it, than what I did.
At least, I think there is, I don't know.
It's always every time I write code, I try writing it a little
differently to see if I can get a little better, and sometimes I get
worse and sometimes I don't, it's hard to say.
So I always try to come up with new ideas and be like, oh, maybe let's
see what happens if I try code.
That looks like this and then I go and say, I know I didn't work, I
was bad or oh, there was a good thing there.
I'm gonna remember that and do that part thing again.
So what I was thinking is basically what I'd like to do.
Yes, I'd like to treat for this game.
I think I'd like to treat the stick as if it's always essentially a
d-pad and the things are buttons, but then just have an extra piece of
data that says, what the average motion of the stick was so that if
you are doing sort of motion, it can be smooth on the analog side, but
you can still use it.
You could still look at it as if it was buttons for the purposes of
like double tap, you know, like that Dash thing I was talking about.
Out because what I realized that the min-max thing, this thing that I
was proposing is actually kind of dumb.
It's way harder for the game to use.
As a thing.
And it's way harder for that to capture the thing that we want as
composed as opposed to just doing something like this average X,
right?
Average y for that stick position and basically that's just only if
analog is on, will it get those?
And I could say that this is something like that, right?
Basically, what I should do is have these be defined as as buttons as
well.
Like basically, the up-down left-right should actually be now defined
to be buttons.
The should be d-pad and buttons, should all essentially be treated the
same.
And that way when you look for things like Dash in a direction, you
just look at the half transition count for the direction, and if the
half transition count is four or whatever or three I should say, you
know, that that's a dash.
That's it.
And you can some those over time.
You look at that transition count.
If you get 1/2 transition, you look at like how many have transitions
you got in.
Say a quarter of a second and that
Right there that tells you what your, you know, whether the do dashed
or not.
So I think, I think it's just smarter to do it that way.
And so maybe what I'll do is I'll break these up into stick and button
or something like that.
Right?
I don't really know if it should be but it's like I kind of want
basically, like, a chi, guess action, you know, like that kind of
thing.
There's the action and Direction and move, I guess.
It's so smooth moving action.
That's good.
I like that.
At move up, move down, move left move, right and action up action down
action, left action, right?
That seems a little bit more interesting to me and because then that
way we basically one, two, three, four, five, six, seven, eight, nine,
ten of these are basically just have 10 buttons now and and the stick
average.
So hopefully that makes a little bit sense.
Why I want to do that.
I know it's a little confusing.
I apologize, but it's something I was thinking about and it's like
that's kind of cool try that.
And then we'll see when we go to actually make the movement of our
character, which will be pretty soon.
Probably a couple weeks when we're actually doing movement tuning,
you'll see how I use it.
And hopefully, that'll make a little more sense than to is why I want
to do that.
I'll be able to show like, okay, here's the code of why I think that
was good.
So I think that's a more interesting way to do it.
And it means that basically these become no-brainers, the keyboard now
gets passed through totally directly and correctly.
Since those were they are essentially buttons now, right?
And so there's basically like w is move up,
Right, a is moved left.
S is moved down, and D is move.
Right?
Right.
And then these are now the, the action buttons action up action, left
action down.
Right?
Right, and that is like that's it.
Like that just works pretty much.
I don't think that we even really need to do anything else for the
keyboard.
The keyboard is pretty much done.
And so then all we have
To do is down here, say okay, that changes a little bit, the way that
this thing is handled.
Basically, what we have to decide is what that threshold is for
whether it's moving left, right?
Or up or down.
I guess at first we might say that.
That should be just The Dead Zone if you're outside the dead zone,
that's a left, if you're outside.
It's a right.
So I think, I think that's probably what we want to do.
So basically, what I would say is now we're just going to literally,
we're going to get rid of all this, mid Max stuff entirely.
It doesn't need to be.
Be there at all anymore.
We can directly set these values.
So basically, we can do this sort of thing.
Let's see here.
We can basically directly pull those those sticks and stuff them into
stick, average, X, and stick, average Y, and that's fine.
But the other thing, what we can do then is now say that we are going
to use these average, these stick average things.
To determine whether there was a trigger on one of these buttons.
So basically what we will do there is say, I guess we would do this.
We could even make a synthetic version of, we could even just call
this function, really if we wanted to, we could say, process, digital
buttons with fake move buttons essentially and then actually, just
just full-on pass.
Yeah.
That's not a bad idea.
Let's try that.
I'll say what I'm going to do in a second here.
Let me just finish to make it to making this code change because we
need to actually change these or now action buttons like that.
There we go.
And basically I think that's basically it that looks about right?
Everything's good there.
Okay, and we should probably, I feel like these guys should come in
here to while we're cleaning things up.
I wonder if we should go ahead and say, start and back are in here as
well.
Back, let's start.
So let's do that as well.
Since we're, you know, it's free.
It's this is one of the nice things about pulling out code properly is
basically, you can just kind of get you can, you don't really have to
do much work to start processing other stuff.
So there's the start button Loops behind my head.
Don't want to let that get too far behind my head or you can't see
what I'm doing.
So, there we go.
Alright.
So let's go ahead and just throw those in there while we're at it
seems like a good enough reason.
To do that.
So this is stick average X and stick average.
Why just to get those ported.
We've got action down, and now we got to clean this up.
So that's fine.
We will clean that up in a second.
Is there anything else the start button?
That's not good game pad.
Should probably just be starting back out.
Assume that right?
Yeah.
So there we are all ported and now I can just go ahead and do the
thing that I was going to say.
Basically, I've already got this function written that does the
processing for the button exactly the way I want to.
So what I'm going to do, I think it's just go ahead and use a fake
value as if we had buttons for these guys, and I'll just set that.
I'll just set that value to basically, be whatever to be set properly
in the case where the the sticks are in the position that think they
should be, and not if they're not.
So, basically, all I do is say, you know, I've got this stick, average
X and maybe will basically say, I don't know, I mean, for the purposes
of
Dat of of doing dashes and treating it as a button, if it's more than
halfway.
I don't know.
It's basically like we're going to have a threshold value basically,
right.
And we've remapped things between 0 & 1 now, so we need a value
between 0 and 1.
So halfway would be 0.5., Right?
And what I could do is say, well, if the stick average X, right, is,
is less than the negative threshold.
So, if it's negative point five, right?
Then then fake move buttons, is
Otherwise, it's zero, right?
So, it's basically, in fact, all I'm really doing is this, I'm just
doing that right there.
That's it.
That's, that's all I'm doing.
And so, I basically made a fake button bit array that set, you know,
it's got the bottom bit set in the case where it's exceeded the
threshold.
And otherwise, it doesn't.
And I'm just going to say, basically that move left, which would be
stick.
Average X, you know, if you're moving left and if you're, if you're a
stick, a Vertex is negative, then you're moving to the left because -
is mapped this way and positive mapped to the right basically.
Lee.
I think that's mostly all I wanted to do.
That's that's it.
So yeah and then I just check for the threshold in the opposite
direction.
Do it for y as well.
And so now I can just call that same function, which does the counting
properly and that's it.
Whoops.
I deleted my threshold.
That was a mistake threshold equals 0.5 and that reeked 32.
That's an interesting type.
Oh, that is really all I wanted to do for the stickhandling there and
it still works fine on.
Average.
Now, of course, we still can't use the keyboard to control anything
other than just the action buttons because we're only checking for
analog controllers in here.
And so we need to also, make sure that we handle keyboard controllers.
So if the controller is not analog, which is the case of the keyboard,
what we probably want to do is say all right, let's let's process the
blue offset, at least.
So we'll say something like, you know, if that, that controller that
we're looking at here, which we know is an analog anymore.
If
It's let's say so it's stick average.
So it's if it's, if it's move left, then we will go ahead and
subtract, you know, something here.
We'll subtract one.
Let's say, and if it's, if it's move, right.
Ended down.
Would basically do Pat.
So, basically, if you're holding any of those down, we will we will go
ahead and update it that way.
All right.
There we go.
So there, you can see.
Now we've got our keyboard input working.
Awesome.
All right, so I think that's basically it for what I want to do input
cleanup.
Let's check the to dues a little bit here, just to make sure that
everything is happy about that.
Let's see to do d-pad.
Oh, we can knock out this to do as well with the d-pad.
We can just treat the d-pad as another one.
Yeah as basically as forcing our stick.
Average, if we wanted to write what we could do, right here is just
overwrite.
The stick average with the d-pad in the case, where, in the case,
where someone pushed the d-pad, right?
So what we can do is say right before we do this with our stick
average, right?
What we can do is say, you know, let's say if the if the d-pad up was
down, right, so they're pushing up, then we just flat-out set the, the
stick average y to be negative 1, right?
So, it's just, it's the full on it's as if you're just cranking.
All the way.
Although, you know, now that I think about it, I don't know which way,
I don't know.
I don't know which way the stick goes.
Does the stick.
Oh, is it - for up or positive for up?
I have no idea.
It should probably be positive for option.
It.
I don't know.
Let's find out.
Let's see, of course, the documentation doesn't bother to tell you.
Because, why would you do that?
Right?
Let's see your left each side of it.
See a sea.
Okay, so they just put in the wrong place.
It does tell us - value signify down or to the left.
So - is down so
So, stick average, why should be positive?
If the up button is pressed right?
Make some sense.
We'll go ahead and flat-out overwrite, the debt with down as well,
right?
Make sense.
Hopefully, this is self-explanatory.
And all I'm doing is basically over writing the stick value with the
d-pad, in the case, that the user used to the d-pad.
Because, of course, if you moved your hand off and started, using the
d-pad we'd want to use that because if you were trying to use the
stick, presumably you wouldn't be fussing with the d-pad.
So it seems like a pretty low risk way to to.
Are you to use the d-pad and not have you have to pick?
You can just use whichever one you want anytime and switch between
them which seems preferable.
So, I should be able to do that.
And now I should actually go to use the d-pad for stuff as well.
Which I can, there we go.
All right.
All right, that's good.
So, let's take a look at this here.
What else do we have?
Yeah, oops, that's not good.
Alright, so here stick average why I did the - I forgot to take the
negative out on the positive case.
So that's not.
That's not fun at all.
All right, so there's our move left.
Okay.
So basically I think and I got maybe I might have some more bugs in
here.
Did that pretty quickly.
Obviously, we're gonna have to test this and we will be able to test
it very easily.
Once we actually have the game up and running will draw out the stick
positions and kind of go through, run through a little test, to make
sure that it all moves the way that it should move.
Move.
And basically.
Yeah, I think that's about it that to do is about
Polling which we will do a little later.
Let's see here.
And I think we don't have a to do.
We should have another to do in here to do Casey need to not pull,
disconnected controllers to avoid X input frame rate, hit on older
libraries.
Just so we know that that needs to happen as well.
I will be showing
that how to do that much later in the Stream.
But yeah.
So anyway, I think that is mostly all we needed to do.
We have our keyboard input going, we have our two dues out of there
for things.
These are all to do is that we're going to be doing for other stuff.
We could make that zero memory thing.
Let's see, need to not pull.
Disconnected controllers.
To avoid X input frame rate, Hidalgo libraries that's in there.
Yes, and we'll do that.
We'll pack that will check packet number.
We do that and that, that looks pretty good.
That looks pretty good.
I suppose.
There's one thing we could do more while we're just in here just in
case it makes our life a little bit easier later, which is we could
also have is connected, basically, so that we can set whether or not
there actually is something on there.
We might as well throw that in now.
And that way when we're testing things we can actually test that as
well, just as a little like, you know, get things working in the game.
And so that it actually does the right thing there.
So basically, what we
I can do is say all right, the new keyboard controller is always
connected because we're just assuming that there's keyboard later on.
We'll do stuff with that where we actually pull for multiple keyboards
and all kinds of fun stuff like this.
But for now, we know we just always have one keyboard and that's fine.
And here, we basically know that this is connected if we get it.
So new controller is connected.
Controller is connected, is true in here whereas it is not true in
here.
Right.
So, there we go.
So I think that's it.
I think that's it.
That is looking good.
My friends.
But, oh, that's no good.
That is not looking good.
That's not good at all.
What is our?
What did we do?
We made it.
We made a grievous error people.
And that is, that is not what we should be doing.
That is unfortunate.
All right.
So basically we have, let me just before we go, look at that.
I wanted to I want to verify what we're doing here.
Make sure everything's kosher.
So we did everything that we need to do for our keyboard controller is
That's all fine.
We got the input and that's nice.
We should in theory always have the right number of controllers.
Do we have that?
I should also put in some assertions here.
One thing that I would like to do as well, is for getting the
controller's out.
I'd like to go ahead and make a thing for that.
I'll show you what I mean by that.
I want to basically make a thing.
In fact, I can spread it right here.
Something like this, get controller, and you pass it, the game input
and then I just say controller index out of that.
And basically, the only reason I wanted to do that was basically to
make a bounced check to basically just make sure that people aren't
asking for stuff that's out of bounds.
So base owing to do is just assert when we call that that the array
count of the input controllers is correct because we're
Starting to be a little fiddly there and I want to sort of make sure
that that's not going to cause a problem.
Basically we do that and then assuming that it is then we will
basically just access the array.
So this is not this is literally just putting in the kind of thing
that this is basically like higher-level languages often do this for
you automatically like bounds checking and just give you an error, we
can do this.
Pretty trivial for our own arrays people who write in C plus plus
might make a templated class for these sorts of things.
That you bounce tracking and we'll be doing some stuff for that later,
as we kind of get further on into making our own sorts of Library
stuff.
But for now we kind of have to do it the old-fashioned way, which is
basically just to do the check ourselves.
So here we go, ahead and say, we've got trailer index and that is
there, we passed the result back and that should be good that.
And basically all I want to do is just now make it so that everyone
has to go through that.
So what I'm going to do here
is a little trick that I like to use which is basically like insert a
bogus character into the definition of something to see where it is
used.
So the base of that can just go through all my code that was accessing
that directly before and basically not access it directly if I don't
think it should be accessed directly.
So I look at each individual one and this for example is getting it.
So I rather do get controller here, pass it, the input and the
controller index and have that return the value, right?
Same thing with these guys.
Those should be get controller.
Asset the thing and the index.
Like so same thing here, get controller input, pass the value back,
right?
And so that's just, you know, again, this is just basically checking
for bugs in making it easier for us to find them especially cuz we
have a bounds over, right?
We got to go find in a second here.
That's this is the sort of code.
We need to start putting in to make sure that we don't make stupid
mistakes.
Yeah, when we're doing stuff.
So, there we go, and we'll get controller here.
Put controller index.
There.
We are.
And let's take a look.
Oh, yeah.
Well, I already spotted the bounds over, right?
That's kind of obvious.
You can, you can see what's going on here.
That's that was just wrong.
Actually, what we needed fifth.
This computation was wrong.
You know, what?
I will explain it fully I shouldn't go fixing things before.
I actually say what I'm fixing.
I saw what the error was because I kind of knew where the air was
going to be and it was there so I did.
We'll push that for a second and this is actually I'd rather.
I'd rather have the nice demo of showing you that this bounds checking
was valuable.
So I shouldn't I was, I was saying I'm I'm spoiling my own punch line
who wants to spoil their own punch.
Like that's that's just silly.
Right?
We don't we don't wish to spoil our own punchlines.
We list it.
We wish to have our punchlines land at.
Exactly right time.
All right, so I think that was everybody what's going on here.
Hello emacs.
Come back there.
Go.
All right, so we'll go ahead and build that.
There we go, and we should bam right there.
That is exactly what we wanted.
You can see that our assertion has caught the error and the error is
that this controller access is out of bounds.
It is passing a controller index.
That's too high.
So why is it doing that?
Is because when I was fussing with that routine, I sort of slapped in
something that's just totally erroneous.
Basically what we want to do here is we want to make sure that we
don't
Go above the controller value that bit.
That is we don't want to sample controllers.
That would be outside our range.
So we are saying that will support One keyboard.
And for gamepads, that was sort of what we were saying the game might
allow for input.
So we have five input slots.
So we want to do is make sure that X User Max count never actually
goes above that.
And so what I wanted to do was clip that here.
So what we could say is the way I was saying as 1 plus Max user
account that will end up, making it equal 5.
5.
So this will actually be a loop of five which then adds one to the
controller index which allows it to write to the actually the sixth
entry.
That's no good.
That's just a bug.
What we actually wanted to do here is still only count up to four
because we're already doing the increment by 1.
So this needs to clip.
This needs to be X X User maxed out.
And we basically need to make sure that the max controller count is
actually equal to this value.
Minus 1, we need to be like less.
The array bounds - the keyboard sighs, right?
That's what we were actually trying to do.
So that was kind of just a silly.
I was just, I was just a mistake.
And so now we should be back to goodness and you'll notice we don't
get the assertion anymore.
So that was good.
And I think that basically finishes up.
I don't think we've got anything left to do really there.
That seems like we've got everything we have all of our input.
So, you know, one thing we could do in the last seconds here, but
grows the stream is about over.
Is we could go ahead and map escape to be back that back button and
and and and or the start button.
Let's say and back could be a space.
I don't know what we want.
We've got the shoulder buttons for Q and E.
And then I don't know, I guess back and start back back, could be
backspace.
I don't know what on the keyboard should be mapped to the back button.
Maybe the spacebar.
I don't know.
Let's I don't know.
We'll just first going to map these and we'll change.
And when, if we need to.
So, so there we go, just so we have those in there.
All right, everyone, we ended right on time.
And we did exactly what we want to do today, which is clean up our
input.
So, now we have keyboard input and stick input going through properly
handling, the dead zone.
You can use the d-pad, you can use the analog stick.
We even are tracking transitions for using things like Double Dash.
So I think I am pretty happy with that.
Now you may have some bugs in there because we haven't tested it very
thoroughly yet.
We will be doing that kind of in the game code will actually put the
test stuff in there because we're going to want our test stuff to be
shared across the different platforms, right?
So you can fire up your Mac port or whatever and take a look and make
sure the sticks working there as well.
So we'll take care of that in the platform code next week.
But for right now, I'm feeling pretty good about that.
That looks pretty good.
I don't have any reservations about what we've done there.
We eliminated a bunch of to dues.
We still got some in here that we should probably take a look at but
basically we're down to just a couple things tomorrow.
We'll focus on the frame timing.
And then we'll kind of go through here and clean up a lot.
Some of these other ones what folks on the see if we get frame timing
done tomorrow, if it might spill into Thursday and then Friday will
kind of be a general cleanup day.
And I think we might make it, we might finish up all of our win32
stuff and be in real good shape by the end of the week, which would be
pretty awesome.
Basically the 20-hour completely explained.
Win32 game, prototyping layer is is a pretty darn good thing.
Thing, I think we should all be pretty proud of ourselves.
If you're not proud of yourselves out there.
Well, you should be because I think we did a lot of stuff in a short
amount of time and we kept it very concise and the code is looking
pretty clean.
Again the important part.
Like I said is it doesn't matter how gross this winter to layer is
either.
We don't have to care about that because interfacing with Windows is
going to be a little gross.
All we want to make sure is that this is clean.
This is nice and clean so that our game can be nice and clean and it
is I think looking pretty nice so far.
It's such a clean boundary.
So I'm pretty excited about that.
Going forward.
I think it's gonna be
Be cool.
So with that said, we will now go to the questions.
Please make sure you put see me oratory in the question when you ask
it.
So I will see it on the little filter.
and,
Also, if you could keep the questions to code, we did today or in some
previous day, not about code.
We're going to do in the future because we will be doing the code in
the future.
And I will probably answer the questions in the course of actually
showing you how to do that code.
So with that, let's go to the questions.
Let's take a look at what's going on.
Let's see.
So it looks like maybe some people caught a bug or typo, they were
saying maybe there was all move left's, what's going on here.
Trying to read back through the stream, check the array in the
buttons.
Union might want 12 now that you've added start and back.
Oh, right.
Yes.
Thank you.
That is a good point because we want to be able to handle all these.
I wish there was
Away, so okay.
Let's think about this for a second.
It'd be interesting to know.
Is there a good way?
We can make sure that we could catch this bug like when we add stuff
in here and we want this array to have all the things, right?
And so what we want to do, there is basically we'd want to do
something like when we come in at.
Well, this exercise should be cross-platform.
So when we in here, we want to do something where we can sort of
assert that, for example, I guess the address of the last button we
We know about, right?
So button, start equals the ad equals the length of this kind of
thing.
I don't know if that makes sense.
But basically like we might want to say, let's assert that say input.
Let's see, imput controllers, 0 start, that is equal to well, I guess.
How can I do that?
I could
Racked.
Yeah, so so I okay.
So I guess what I would say is, let's say that start the address of
start.
This is going to be pretty janky, the address of start plus 1.
So I'm going, I'm going forwards a little bit there.
The address the address of start plus 1 or well, like I said, the
address of start this way, take the address of the start button,
subtract it from the address of the move button like this.
Well, I could even just do button zero, right?
That address of button 0 that should equal the array count of the
buttons like that.
So,
Right now, it's going to be off by one because it's actually should be
one past that.
So it should be the array count to the buttons.
I believe - one that's, that's the actual check.
I think, game controller input does not have a right Sergeant needed.
That is actual structure.
So, based on trying to do is do some point arithmetic here.
Now, let's see if that works.
Yes.
Good caught it.
Of course.
I'm not sure if it's actually still correct, but that caught it, and
then it should be 12.
Now.
See if that works properly off we go.
Yeah.
So basically what I did here was I just wrote something where I said?
All right, let's take where the start button is in the layout of the
structure.
Let's subtract the base of the button, array from it, which is the the
start of this whole thing.
Right?
And I want to make sure that the number that I get back is equal to
11, right?
The number I want it to equal the the array count of these minus 1.
Because again, we're using the pointer to start is going to point to
just
just before the start button structure, right?
It's pointing to the start of it.
So if I subtract it from the base, I'm going to get one less than the
total count that there are.
And so I'm just
Make sure that matches.
Now, this isn't perfect because we can still do this.
And this won't catch it.
Right?
That makes sense.
But it at least checks that the last button that we know about in here
is is correct.
Now we could do something else.
We could use a get button function that checked.
I don't know if I want to go that route.
I'm also not sure if there's any way.
Oh, you know, duh.
I've got one way we could do it.
There's a pretty easy way we can do it.
In fact, we could just do this.
I
Game controller input buttons, duh.
Why not do it this way?
Can I do that?
I don't know if I can do that.
Yeah.
I don't know.
I guess it has to be anonymous.
It's not going to let me name it.
Is it?
That's too bad.
I was hoping it would let me name it because if it let me name it then
we could just say the size of this thing, but I can't do that at the
moment.
Unfortunately.
And still keep it Anonymous, which is what we kind of wanted to do.
Now we could go and make it non and on.
As we could make it be a thing that actually has a name, right.
And we access off the name.
I don't know if we really want to do that seems like a little
inconvenient, but maybe it's better to keep the bugs.
You know, if I basically said this then we could just do the assertion
that this structure was the same size as this array, which is kind of
what we would like to do.
Hmm.
Well, one of the thing we could do is we could do something like this.
I'm not happy with any of these.
Really?
We could insert a fake button.
It doesn't mean anything at all.
And then we could just say well it's that button is got to be equal to
that the array size, right?
So it's like a Terminator button.
And now if we go in and add a button as long as we don't add it below
the Terminator, right?
If we always add our buttons up here, then that assert will fire
properly for us.
Right.
Bam, and it's, and it caught the error, so maybe that's good for now.
I don't have to think about that.
Maybe we do want to just name it.
And deal with the name so we can do it more cleanly, so I'll do note,
Casey all buttons, must be added above this line for now and that's
that's something so we'll leave it like that for now.
But thank you for catching that error because that was a good one.
That would have been annoying.
Let's see.
There's a lot of questions.
We're not going to get to all these.
There's too many questions.
Is that some copypasta or is it really supposed to be?
Move left.
I don't know.
So is there somewhere that it's actually actually wrong where we're
doing move left multiple times and shouldn't be?
Yes, that is copy pasta.
That is totally copypasta.
Thank you for that.
So basically I just forgot missed these here, d-pad.
Oh, we didn't test the d-pad yet, right?
Because we ran out of time.
So we would have found this and so as soon as we tested the d-pad, I
was like how can see that, but that's why we have done that yet.
So basically, I just need to go ahead and make these be the actual
values that they should be.
Let's see here.
Are we said down was - that's what the
Invitation said, so down Loops down its - get out of my way.
So I don't hit my head unintended.
So yeah, that was just copy pasta.
That was supposed to be that and I can test that now to can't.
I can test the d-pad.
There we go.
Yeah, yeah.
Should be right.
Yeah.
Okay.
Well, oh, you know what?
No, I take it back.
So the reason we didn't catch that is we did test the d-pad.
The reason we can test that is that's just for the button.
We don't have anything that test those values.
That's just for the thing for checking like Dash and that sort of
stuff.
So, yeah, unfortunately that yeah, that unfortunately is not actually
going to that's not going to help us.
So we're going to actually have to test that later.
Don't know if that's working properly left, test that later.
You know, what else we should do while we're on the subject of things
that could happen.
Another thing we should do is maybe fake the stick average.
I don't know you.
We could now, it's not, it's not do that.
It's done.
Well, okay.
So let me just, let me tell you what I'm thinking here.
So, when we use the d-pad, we should probably change to say that the
thing is not analog anymore.
Right?
I don't know.
Don't you think like that way?
It knows like if we see input from the d-pad, the game should probably
switch to using the same kind of control scheme as it's using on the
keyboard where it would do like smoothing and stuff for you.
So I feel like maybe we want to set this to false.
If we do any of this nonsense, I think I'm gonna leave that in.
All right.
Let's see.
Could it be good to apply some integration on the digital keys?
So we don't just set the value to binary negative 11.
Um, that's a good question.
I don't think so, because the way I want this to work is, I basically
want the, I'm only setting the stick average so that it sets the move
left move, right.
Move down, move up buttons, and then I'm setting the ins analog and
I'm going to let the
The game, use the is analog flag to say.
Oh, I'm going to start using buttons.
Now, instead of the analog stick for this controller until it goes
back to using the analog stick and I'm
Hoping that that will kind of be the thing that works best there.
Now that it's a little bit tricky because it's like well, you know,
We probably also don't want to set is analog to True.
Unless the stick is actually being used something like this.
So if the stick average is not equal to 0 or the, the, if the stick
average in either direction, right?
Excuse me.
Is not equal to 0 something like that.
That is more like, okay.
Now we've got, you know now we've got something where
The game really does know whether using the analog stick or the d-pad
at any given time and it should do.
So that integration that you're talking about to smooth out using the
digital.
That's that's will be done by the game.
Because could have to do that for the keyboard as well.
So we want to make that Unified.
Can you talk about the dead zone being round versus rectangular and at
Hardware usb hid and xinput?
Oh, you're saying who I'm not sure, what you mean by at Hardware usb,
hid, and xinput API layers.
So, as far as I know, the dead zone is literally something that's only
software side.
Like the hardware is reporting, just like it's potentiometer values or
whatever.
It's get what, I don't know what they do use nowadays, but whatever
they're reading their is reporting that
Ethical level like turned into something.
And so when you get back the short, it's just a light quanta.
It's some kind of quantization of the electrical level.
And so as far as I know on USB it, that's just on the US, on the bus.
It's just getting passed.
As part of the hid page.
Like, here's an x value.
No, here's a, here's a linear map value.
And here, it is.
As far as I know.
I've never actually looked at what they hid code Pages look like for
these, but I think it's basically just pass that value through xinput,
hands.
It to us and then it's up to us.
Us to basically do that dead zone processing and xinput as pound to
find what it says.
The spec is for The Dead Zone on the controller, but I think that's
it.
I don't think there's anything else to it as for round versus
rectangular.
I know nothing about that.
I know that they have defined it to be rectangular and I guess that
pretty much makes sense.
If you think about it.
I don't know the inner construction of this thing, but if you imagine
that there's essentially two potentiometers or to whatever they use,
like I said to read it.
For the horizontal, one for the vertical, then they're both gonna have
their own error.
And that error is not going to be circular, right?
It's not going to be based on how far you've gone to the left
necessarily, whether the Y is going to be more or less error.
If they're read independently, the error could very well, be
rectangular.
And so if the error is rectangular, then you don't have much of a
choice but to clip the error rectangular lie.
Now, what we can do in our own code is we can go,
Go and try to do some better Dead Zone processing.
If
Find it to be a problem.
This again is the first pass on the input stuff.
And so we'll have to go look and see basically what we think once
we're playing it, whether we think it's working well enough for our
game or not.
And if it's not we may have to do more fancier stuff, you know, like
base like like gradual like changing how this works in a sort of
gradual sense.
So that basically when you come out of the Dead Zone, that's at zero
and it eases in instead of right now, when you come to the Zen Zone,
you're going to be at 0.2.
Right?
Because we know the dead.
That's where the dead zone is.
So you're going to be the lowest value.
You can report for movement is 0.2.
So maybe we don't want that.
Maybe we want that it to be clipped down and to do the dead zone
processing in a different way, right?
Like you could imagine.
I don't know if we want to do this, but you can imagine.
Maybe we should do this.
I don't know.
I mean, I don't know.
What do you guys think?
What I'm trying to say here, is what we could do is it might be better
to have that value.
Go smoothly from 0 to 1 instead of jumping up to 0.2., Right?
So I guess what I'm proposing is, you know, one thing we could do to
make the dead zone processing work.
A little better is we could basically say well, alright, we
essentially know that - DeadZone threshold is not counted.
So we need to recenter our value.
So that basically
The Dead Zone threshold is a subtracted away from the divisor, right?
And the value itself, which is of course - has Dead Zone added to it,
to bring it up, 20 in the appropriate scenario, right?
This is, this is what I'm talking about.
Does this make sense?
I don't know if any, if this makes any sense to anyone, I'm just sort
of proposing this as a thing that we could do.
Right?
Does this make sense.
So basically what I'm saying here is normally what would happen and I
can go to the diagram for this just to make it a little clearer.
Go to the diagram because there is actually only one.
We've actually just always had the same version of paint up, and I
just clear it every time.
So literally, there is the diagram.
Basically, what I was saying is, you know, we've got this scenario
where basically there's a dead zone here and we've got stick values
and those stick values, start being, you know, whatever they are.
Right.
This sort of thing and we're basically saying that anything in here x
input has told us is noisy.
Right?
We can't, we can't count sick values in here as actually being valid
movement that the player was trying to do because the
Just random noise on the line.
So what happens is, if we look at the stick position, right inside the
dead zone as it moves outside.
Let's say he's moving the stick to the, right.
So he moves in this direction, right?
What are each of these values, right?
Here's the dead zone value.
And I guess we said that was 25%.
So here's maximum.
Right.
What we might want to do if we map it just directly so that this right
here is zero and this right here is 1.0.
Got my head in the way.
They're a little bit down.
I let's try this again.
Let's try it again without the Casey head.
Right.
So if I'm looking at the x-rays,
Access.
Right?
If I'm looking at this span here, I could map this end to 0 and this
end to one, right?
But what would happen there is as the user moves, the stick like this,
when he crosses the boundary, when that boundary when the when the
player crosses the boundary, it's going to jump right from being 0,
which is what we're reporting for the whole time.
It was in The Dead Zone to being essentially point to or somewhere
around there, right?
.25, something like that.
Right?
It's gonna jump right to point two five.
So the only
only values that the game will ever see our between 0.25 and one,
which is kind of confusing to the game.
If you think about it, and basically, then the whole game would have
to be tuned, assuming that the lowest value is 0.25 on the stick.
It doesn't make a whole lot of sense.
So what I was saying is well, let's subtract The Dead Zone variable,
the very The Dead Zone area away and just treat.
Just this range here as 0 to 1, right?
That's what I was trying to do.
I don't know if that makes sense.
Let's see here.
Let's see.
Hopefully, that makes some sense.
All right.
So so yeah, I don't know if that makes sense or not, or if it's if
it's not an appropriate way to do it.
Someone was saying they actually do have a round Dead Zone to find.
Let's see if that's actually true.
Let's see here.
If it's actually around Dead Zone, we can do this even better.
Let's see.
Wound.
Can be used as pausing as to filter something in it because they don't
actually say here.
They don't actually say well, okay, we can do some extra reading.
We don't have a whole lot of time.
Left in the Stream.
We can do some extra reading, to see whether it's around dead zone, or
a non round Dead Zone.
It's been a long time since I've read any xinput documentation.
So let's just do both and then we'll just use, whichever one we find
to be correct.
So let's say this is a round Dead Zone value.
If it's around DeadZone value, then that basically means the total
length of the motion on the stick is subject to that dead zone, right?
I don't know if that makes sense.
So,
Basically, what we would have to do is we have to do the dead zone
processing in up as a pair, right?
We basically have to say we're going to do a dead zone processing on
the actual Vector value.
So that would be something here.
That would have to look like well, yeah that's going to be Vector.
You know what that's going to if that's true and it maybe that is
true.
We could we could go look and see so this is something that we got.
I'm not gonna be able to explain that in 10 minutes because I have to
introduce the concept of euclidean length.
With, and there's no way that's happening in 10 minutes.
That's just unrealistic.
So basically, what I'll say is to do this, this is a square Dead Zone.
Check X input to verify that the dead zone is circular.
Someone was posting links.
I'm assuming that they checked.
On the stream.
And that it is circular or well, or, I guess you could say round the
dead zone is round and show how to do round DeadZone processing.
But yeah, if that's, that's to it, it's too bad.
It's round.
It's actually better for gameplay if it's round.
So, I hope you're right about that, because that would be nice.
And the only thing that's the downside there.
It's going to take me long to explain how to do, round DeadZone
processing.
So, yeah, but thank you for writing in that because I was not sure.
Sure about that since the documentation here, didn't say, as we were
reading it.
And that's really all I had to go on.
Well, we'll have to find some some, some documentation on The Dead
Zone.
Let me let me check that page.
I thought maybe that page before had it, and we'll see if they say
that it's rounded Zone.
And then we could we could know assuming that this documentation is
correct, which of course, we also don't know.
Just because it says, one way, or the other doesn't actually mean
anything.
If we don't check it.
We should probably check it as well.
So, let's take a look here.
The dead zone.
Okay.
Yeah, blah blah blah.
Yes.
Let's see, not really saying yet.
We can look at the example and assume that that's correct, but
Circular Dead Zone.
Well, it says it allows the enforcement of a circular Dead Zone, but
does it actually say that it is a circular dead zone?
Yeah, so unfortunately, I guess you know what?
We'll just we'll just table this for now and we'll get someone who
actually knows for sure.
I will try to contact someone who would know for sure.
Because this just says they're processing is a circular Dead Zone, but
that doesn't mean that the hardware has a circular Dead Zone.
The Dead Zone might still be rectangular in which case us processing.
Is it circular is only making it worse?
So we kind of need to actually know.
They're the input dead.
Zone is literally circular on the controller and if that makes sense,
so, I don't know.
I don't know yet because they're, they're processing it.
Circular, but that doesn't mean anything that just means that they're
processing.
Is it circular?
But they don't say that the hardware was made with a circular Dead
Zone because at the hardware is still has a Retailer's ads on.
Doesn't help us?
That makes sense.
I don't know if that makes sense.
I don't know if that makes sense, but there's some links in here.
So we'll check them out.
Let's see.
I'm 16 days behind.
Is there a better way to catch up than watching all the days on
YouTube?
Yes, there is but only slightly, obviously, everything is important.
So you got to watch it all.
But if you go to the news and form, if you go to handmade hero dot-org
and go to the news and forums link, there's a thing called episode
guide that has better.
In on it, so you can go to something like this and it's got jump it
allows you to jump around the stream.
So that is better than than the YouTube system, but it's still all
just watching the YouTube, but it does like to skip things, you
already know and that sort of stuff.
All right, boy, there's a lot of questions on here.
I'm going to miss some for the build-up at you can build for Windows
XP 64-bit using 5.2 instead of 5.1, but we don't actually need to do
that.
Because it's already building for 5.2.
Also the in line method.
Forget controller.
What happens if you pass in negative 1 for index?
So you can if you want to for this, they were basically saying should
we check against those?
You almost never have that bug.
You can, if you want to, you can you can do one of two things.
You can either do this, right?
Which now makes it so that, you know, that the value is always
unsigned.
So if they did pass a negative 1, it would fail this array count by
being way, high up.
Ffff ever be like, you know, four billion or whatever so you can do
that or you can assert that controller index is greater than equal to
0 which ever one floats your boat, but that's that's basically I mean
that's that's the long and short of it.
You almost never have buffer under runs though.
At least I don't I very very rarely have buffer under-run.
So checking against them is not so important.
Buffer, overruns you often.
I find that just the nature of the way that c code tends to work.
You are very likely to write a buffer overrun.
You are just not that likely right above or under run because you
rarely Sebago backwards with pointers.
And that's just it's weird.
It's a bias.
It doesn't really have to be that way.
But that is just the way that code typically gets written.
Let's see.
Can you do struct inner buttons type and still get the benefit?
Yes.
Oh, that was all.
I was trying to do before.
So for some reason buttons type like this sort of thing.
It did not work.
At least it didn't seem to yeah, basically, like giving it a name
ruins the anonymous of it and makes it so that you can't access the
interior by without going through it first.
So basically, you have to do it that way, as far as I can tell.
I just don't know.
I don't know any other way to do it.
Unfortunately, there probably is a C++ 11.
Anyway, I would think but I'm not sure.
I don't get using win32 prefix for function names, but compiling to
64-bit.
Okay.
So basically, that's just to tell us that this.
So this code isn't actually Windows 64-bit.
It's Windows 32-bit that you can compile as 64-bit.
So, actually, all of this stuff and we show this on the last stream,
all of this stuff can be compiled for win32 as well as when
So it is not win, 64 code is win32 code, but we can compile and 64-bit
when we want to which we do want to because that's going to be faster.
So basically it's called win32 because it actually is all win32 clean
code.
There's nothing in here that requires when 64 so we are compiling for
both and that's why the win32.
If we had a function that only worked on in 64, then would call in 64.
Let's see.
I was thinking about for game processing in put in a separate thread
so it is frame rate independent, but I heard you could introduce input
lag.
Is that true?
We are, we are probably going to do some pulling potentially a
separate thread as well.
It does not introduce input lag.
It would if you did it poorly, I guess, but as long as they're there
really isn't any reason.
I strongly suspect that.
We will want to potentially at least for educational purposes.
If not for any real reason, do a separate thread for input polling say
pulling the xinput sticks.
And as far as I know, there's no reason why we can't Implement that
with no lag.
I cannot think of any reason in my head.
Why that would have to be laggy.
I may be forgetting something.
But basically it would just stuff in a queue and the other thing and
the main throw pulled out of the queue and you could do a lock freak.
You
Even for something as simple as that, so there really wouldn't be
there would literally not even be a mutex around it.
So I don't feel like there should be any lag.
If you did it poorly.
There'd be a bunch of leg.
But if you did it properly, I don't think there should be
You said a circular Dead Zone would be good for gameplay.
Why don't you just make it circular?
The Dead Zone would just be a little bit bigger.
Well, the reason is because then you're just losing information,
right?
Basically.
Like this is why I say I actually want to know what the hardware does
because I want to actually provide as much data as the hardware gives
me.
So if the hardware was specified this way, then I want to pass that to
the game.
I don't want to circumscribe a circle like this and take a bunch of
Valid data that the game could have been getting and throw it out.
I'm saying it's better for gameplay because a circle means that you
have the same resolution, no matter what direction you're going in.
So you don't lose resolution on the stick as you go out here.
So I'm just saying the joystick is better.
If it's circular assuming that it's still, if it's so an inscribed
circle is better than this, which is why I want to know.
So basically you're saying my if to be 100 explicit, basically, we've
got some measurement.
Of the stick we're saying that measurement is noisy.
It's not accurate.
So what I want to know is is the noise on both axis.
So we have a certain bit of noise on this axis and a certain bit of
noise on this axis, which leads to this dead zone, literally, on the
hardware.
And
Case, that is how we should process it or are we saying that?
It's just the total distance.
That is noisy.
It's just however far you moved it.
So, no matter what direction you move it in.
It's still the same amount of noise.
I find that hard to believe.
It doesn't sound like how hard we're normally works, but my knowledge
of joysticks is from like 1990.
So that could very well be possible.
Nowadays.
Maybe they've got better techniques or building joysticks.
So what I would like to do, I'm
Not going to go by the msdn code because all that said was we're going
to process it.
A circular Dead Zone, but who cares?
That's not relevant, right?
We don't care how they process it.
We care what the hardware does.
So what I'd like to do is actually go talk to somebody, who knows the
hardware intimately and say, what actually, what is the actual noise
profile of this hardware?
And I'd like to process it that way.
That makes sense.
So we're basically out of time here.
Just trying to quickly.
See, let's see here.
Let's see here.
I don't think there's any more questions that I can get to.
Looks like mostly everything straight forward.
We could cover it looks like mostly just discussion of circular versus
rectangular Dead Zone and I want to go actually get some verification
of how the hardware Works before I do that.
But if it does, then we'll just do a circle Dead Zone.
We might postpone that till I talk about vectors, so we may have to
postpone circular DeadZone processing.
If it does turn out to be circular until I talk about vectors, but
that's about it.
Let's see, ya.
Yeah, some of these questions are good.
Maybe I'll just do let me do an extra five or ten minutes here because
some of these questions are good.
There's a question about direct input versus X input.
X input is easier direct input supports more devices.
So, if you want to support older Hardware, you need to use either
direct input or you need to go off the raw input or the hid system.
Which one we do.
I won't know.
I don't know, but we probably should support direct input as well as
xinput in the end.
Just so we can support older.
Is or we can just say, it doesn't really matter.
It's just an exercise in win32 programming, and maybe that's not a
useful thing to teach on the stream.
I don't know.
Yes, directs input is much Messier.
No, there isn't much point to it.
But the bottom line is that xinput just does not support Legacy
devices.
So people who have old gamepads, they won't work unless you use x
input or they can run a program.
Sometimes that Max maps, direct input, 2x input, but it's nicer.
If you do it, do it nicely for them, right?
So, there's that.
Let's see here.
I deleted the Min and Max Mac.
Yes.
That's true.
I did.
I had said that I kind of wanted to.
So, if you remember, basically, in the dead zone processing, I was
using the, the I sort of said, I wish I should use a Min and Max here,
but I didn't have one yet.
And so that was in that was in this code.
So right here, I was saying I could use that.
I don't think it's relevant anymore because especially, if we change
to a circular dead zone.
That is not relevant anymore.
So I think we don't actually need that to do anymore.
But thank you for catching that that could have been appropriate.
Will get to minute Max macros at some point.
Certainly.
Yes.
So when you use a zero controller, why don't you just do star new
keyboard controller equals brackets.
So the answer is because I don't think that used to work.
Let me let me show you what the person was talking about.
They were saying when you do this, can you just do that?
And C++ 11 may allow that?
Yeah, it does, but I'm pretty sure that didn't used to work.
I'm contouring is whether how much of those sorts of newer features we
should be using, but I guess if someone was implementing compiler,
this is a pretty easy thing to do.
Just the fact that that clear something so I'm okay with that.
So yeah, I'm fine with that.
That's totally cool.
I don't have a problem with that.
Yeah, we'll go with that.
We'll go with that.
I can, I can live with that.
I can be happy with that.
Let's see.
Looks like someone was asking about normalizing to The Dead Zone to
Max short thing, which is actually something I just did.
So yes, I whoever made that suggestion.
That is a very good suggestion.
That is exactly what I thought should be good.
Let's see here.
Standard def should include offset of you could use that to make your
assert a little simpler.
That's true.
But I'd rather just stick with the point arithmetic.
So we don't introduce more overhead there.
Maybe.
I don't know if we'll use offset of in the future, we might basically
there's a there's a macro you can do called offset of, I'll show you
the docs for it here, actually.
So offset of which simplifies, some of the stuff that I was doing,
whereas a good reference.
Here it is.
So basically, there's a macro called offset of and what offset of is
it.
The name of a type and then it takes the name of a member inside that
type, and it Returns the the Delta between the base of the structure,
the start of the structure and that type.
So it's the offset inside the structure.
So, this code that I had here right, and I'll just go ahead and do it.
I'm fine with using offset of, I don't have a problem that I guess,
but basically, if I wanted to, I could make this use less.
It can be less verbose by basically saying like, Okay, really?
All we need to know is just the game controller.
Put instead of having to give a reference to it.
I just want to say that Terminator, right?
- the offset of the buttons, array their robes.
That's not good - knob set of game controller input.
Buttons.
That is essentially equivalent to what I had written before, and if
that makes sense, I don't, I don't really think there's any reason to
do it.
And since I have to use the other one for array count, anyway,
although I could expose, right?
All right, kind of, but I think, I'd rather just leave it the way that
it was personally.
Personally, let's see.
Let's see anything else.
Anything else that I missed?
So we'll get will look at the circular dies on later.
So I'm not ignoring that we will, we will.
Absolutely, I'll check later tonight, actually to see if I can find
someone who can say definitively, what the hardware does Dead Zone
wise.
But let's take a look.
So, is there anything else looks pretty good?
I think we've covered just about everything that is relevant to
today's code.
Yeah.
Alright.
So thank you everyone for joining us.
Sorry, there were so many questions there that it was hard to make
sure we got all of them.
I think I got all of them related to what we do and I want to table
the circular DeadZone thing.
It's important.
Because I do want to model the hardware accurately.
So it's very important.
I don't want you to think we're skipping over it.
We will find out whether it's circular or rectangular Dead Zone and we
will adjust accordingly.
But even if it is circular, I gotta say, I'm afraid I'm going to have
to probably table that for another two weeks till we can do talk about
vectors because you really, you really need you kill euclidean length
to do a circular Dead Zone.
I can't think of any way to do it without that.
So we're going to have to get to that point before.
We can preserve it as a but we'll find out.
Out which one it is.
I will track down someone who knows for sure.
How these ghosts how these controllers are made internally, find out
whether they have circular, or rectangular dead zones and then we will
go from there.
That said, thank you very much for joining me for another edition of
handmade hero.
I am very pleased with the progress we made.
Today.
We have our input layer looking much better than it was before
probably still some bugs in their cause
I haven't tested it and you always have bugs until you test.
So we need to do more testing and we will do more testing in the
future.
But for now, I'm pretty happy with how we've got designed how we've
got it working.
I think it's really good, and it's going to continue to get better
over time.
So that's great.
We need to work on our frame timing.
So that'll be tomorrow.
And then after that, when we get the frame timing done, we're pretty
much closed in on just final cleanup stuff.
Some extra stuff.
I want to get in there for for, for going forwards, with the memory,
and a little, a couple other things.
So we'll
I'll have a Thursday and we'll have stuff to do on Thursday and Friday
as well.
Even if we do, finish up frame coming tomorrow, but we are well,
within reach of closing out.
The entire platform architecture stuff that we need to do for our
first pass.
And I am very excited about that.
I'm psyched to get to starting to work on the game next week.
The art is looking awesome.
Yeah.
Action does amazing art and I'm really excited to start getting it up
on the screen too.
So that's going to be awesome.
So, thank you everyone for joining me, and, and doing another hour.
Programming.
I encourage you to go to handmade here too, or if you hadn't already
where you can go to this news and forms button.
It's got like a pretty nice forms on their people in posting, a lot of
great information.
There's an episode guide.
You can use to follow along with the series and there's annotated
notes and Iker does a bunch of illustrations every week.
There's just tons of good stuff on there.
Just go explore and have fun with it.
It's some crazy web stuff that, you know, I'm not very good at web
stuff.
So it's a little janky, but it works.
So check that out.
And, of course, if you would like your own copy of
The source code to play around with, you can pre-order the game by
just clicking on this button.
It handles both Skype and PayPal.
So you will get a link and make sure when you do that, make sure you
use a valid email address.
Because, basically, it sends you a link in an email.
That's where you will always go to redownload the source code every
night because I updated every night.
So you want to save that link that comes an email because that's what
allows you to download the source code and that's also what allow you
to download the game and the asset.
So save that every time we do a major build release.
So as the game goes forwards and we
In Milestones, I'll send out an email that has a refresher Link in it.
But just make sure you save that for now.
So you can always get the source code because I don't know much about
send Alli don't, they probably is a way to kind of just have them re--
send you your thing, but I just want to make sure people don't miss
it.
So thank you very much for joining us.
Tomorrow will be 8 p.m.
Pacific Standard time again, I hope to see you all here.
It's been wonderful coding with you and it will be.
I'm really excited to get the frame Loop cleaned up tomorrow because I
think that's going to be a lot of fun, too.
So, hope to see you here tomorrow.
And thank you very much for joining me.