It's upgrading start recruiting.
Hello everyone, and welcome to handmade hero.
So as you know, I've been off for two weeks because of hand problems
and so I kind of wanted to get the stream started again but I don't
super feel comfortable programming just yet.
We'll talk about why in a minute but so I don't actually know what's
wrong with my hands yet and sort of kind of working on that.
It's only my left hand.
Actually, that was a problem.
And it's only like right here and in here, so it's kind of like it's
definitely a median nerve problem of some kind.
But that's that's very localized.
You know, it's very specific to their in there and I've never actually
had that problem before which made me pretty nervous because, you
know, I've been typing for a long time and I've never actually had
much problems with my hands, ever since I started working the wrist
braces, I haven't really had much.
In the way of problems, it's just not something I had to really think
about.
And so now, I don't really know specifically at the moment, what's
actually wrong with them, or what I need to do about it.
So I'm kind of, you know, I went to physical therapist, the doctors as
usual.
No nothing, pretty much.
If you ask a doctor about a biomechanical thing, usually, you get a
complete nonsense issue.
But yeah, they obviously have no idea as you might expect, but I went
to a physical therapist and she looked at it.
Pretty you know pretty in depth.
And you know at the very least, we know a couple things like my my arm
in General, on the left side is not particularly fabulous, my
shoulders, pretty weak compared to my right side and she wanted to
kind of fix about.
She wanted to give me a bunch of strength strengthening exercises for
my arm in general because she felt like before that stuff was fixed.
There wasn't probably much to do with the hand.
That was her thinking anyway.
And what she said, she's actually very smart.
She runs her own place there and she's the only person who's ever
actually solved a biomechanical problem for me.
So I tend to listen to what she has to say because she's the only
person who's ever right as far as I can tell.
She was actually saying that she felt probably that because this
shoulder is very weak and is not really doing very much.
What ends up happening is that like all of this muscular
Sure is actually Contracting a lot more now than it should be.
Because as it does, its work as things down here, try to actually do
stuff the this this part just gets pulled the musculature here gets
pulled and so these things have to contract quite a bit more than they
ever really actually should, right?
So she wanted to fix that first and I think that's a pretty good idea.
So, I've been doing exercises for that and we'll
It does seem like it's a little bit better now, but I think it's got a
ways to go usually these sorts of things take a while.
And so I wanted to kind of reduce my typing a bit and so I felt like
it probably wasn't a good idea to do handmade here for a little bit.
So I took some time off of that but I also tried and I'm not sure how
this is going to go, but I decided to try.
Perhaps changing my keyboard setup for emacs to be modal.
And I'm not sure about that yet.
I tried it.
I'm playing with it now that it's it's not too bad.
It's I don't think modal is as good as non-modal completely honest
with you.
I'm just not sold on it.
I apologize to VI users.
I know obviously, if you how users are pretty happy with mobile other
modal interfaces, otherwise they wouldn't use VI
Um, I'm not so sure, it's such a great idea, for Speed and their
reason for that is that I feel like there's just too much mental
overhead, that goes into knowing which mode that you're actually in
and that switching overhead does, cause quite a bit of a problem and
I'm sure that as I used it more, I will get faster at it.
Like I'm sure that would be true but I don't actually know.
That it will ever be as fast as non-mobile like, you know, could have
robot, do it as fast.
Sure, but maybe a robot could even be faster but the degree to, which
I switch between entering things and Performing operations is
extremely granular.
So, often times, you get very few switching.
A mode is is straight-up.
Just almost adding an additional key stroke, which is now you have to
switch into the mode.
Do the thing and switch out.
And so I'm not really sure it's a plus.
I may just not keep it.
I don't really know so we'll see.
So I feel like at the moment I'm not sold on it.
I did get emacs into a pretty reasonable state for being modal
actually.
And I found that, you know, there are some things I had to do, I had
to make it so it was very visible.
Like, when I switch into the mode like,
Change the color of the cursor, and I change it to highlight the line
and stuff.
So, it was very clear, which mode you're in.
There's a bunch of stuff like that, that I found I kind of had to do
in order to make modal really work, but, you know, I can, I can more
or less use it.
Now I'm much slower than I was and I don't really enjoy it and I don't
know that I'm ever going to, I'm not sure, so I'm not sure whether
I'll stick with it or not, but I did try that.
And so, we'll see.
I also feel like I probably need to do some work on organic metrics
here but, you know, like I said, it's a, it's a thing in in it's in
progress.
So I don't know when I'm going to be 100% comfortable to actually
start coding on stream again.
But I figured at this point I should probably do a couple.
Dreams a week regardless just because, hey, we can always chat about
stuff.
And you know, even if they're not official, handmade hero things, we
can spend a half hour just doing whatever and my right hand is still
fine so I can, you know, still do stuff like drawing out on the on a
Blackboard or things like that.
So that's the that's basically the current situation.
And so I don't really have anything to add other than obviously, it's
pretty important to me to make sure that my hands were okay.
So no promises on when I will actually do a full programming stream
again because I need to both be confident that I'm okay, programming
wise.
And I also need to be fairly confident that I'm fast enough with
whatever keyboard setup, I choose to use to ensure that I'm, you know,
not going to be too slow to actually program effectively on stream and
talk, you know, at the same time and all that.
So,
What I would say I will keep you updated as to anything that I find
out because I know that a lot of people out there have RSI problems of
one kind of the other.
So anything that I find out that I think might help people in general,
I'll be sure to pass on but I think in, you know, the sad fact of the
matter, I strongly suspect is that since everyone's musculature is
different, everyone's brain works different, everyone uses different
You know, keyboards and keyboard layouts, and, you know, to have an
ergonomic keyboard, user wrist, refuse risk, braces, do you use this
particular thing?
How fast do you type?
How often do you cut and paste?
You know, I feel like there's so many variables there.
And there are so poorly understood that I strongly.
Suspect that one of the biggest problems with anything RSI related.
Is simply that.
What's true for one person is not going to be true for another person.
What solves an RSI problem for me is not going to solve an RSI problem
for you and you know, maybe at some point we're lucky and you happen
to ask somebody what to do for RSI and they say x and it turns out
that X is also something that would work well for you for RSI.
You know, I have no idea.
So I really I really just don't know.
And like I said, I'll be sort of trying to work on that a little bit
going forward as we
Go and I'll let you know if I figured find anything out that that is
at all relevant but that's the current state.
And so that's really all I have to say about that if that makes sense.
So I strongly suspect no programming still for for several days and I
will you know post conspicuously if your folks don't want aren't
interested in hanging out for a half hour here or there.
I'll post pretty conspicuously on the Twitter when we will actually
start coding again.
The
Active, that makes sense.
So yeah.
So with that said, I will go ahead and go to the Q&A here and grab
some questions.
The people were asking.
So Elvin asked a question and I suppose I should probably bring up the
the Blackboard here as well.
Oops, I didn't mean to do that.
Password, safe, which I don't even know why there is a password safe
on this machine right now, but apparently got moved and now I can't
move it back.
Oh, well, good, that's great.
We'll just leave it there no problem.
Let's just say it was a good place for it.
Windows thinks it was a good place for it.
And who are you to disagree?
Sir?
Who indeed?
Well, this is not particularly speedy.
There we go.
all right, so
Elvin asked a question.
And this is, this is about emulation speed.
So, Alvin asked a question about emulation speed and basically, what
well, you know, what?
I don't actually know, I never know people's he's or she's, I think I
do know I love.
And I think it's a, he I should just, we need a, we need to like a
gender-neutral pronoun.
Because on a stream, if you see someone's handle, you have no idea if
they're male or female, right?
It's like it handles are almost completely genderless most of the time
and so unlike regular people's names, which typically, you can make a
very reasonable guess most of
Time never invented yet.
Anyway, point being Elvin asked why if you have something that is
obviously an underpowered computer relative to your host machine.
So if you have, for example, he was asking specifically about
simulating a GameCube.
Which is a power PC.
Right.
So think like, you know, think Apple.
You know McIntosh from maybe I don't know 2001.
Am I right?
I don't really remember what Circa powerpc would it have been a G4.
this is really taxing my memory so I don't really remember which
flavor the power, the power PC that's actually in the GameCube is a is
not is not the same chip obviously but it's similar like I feel like
it had all Tyvek
Right?
Which is an instruction set that's Vector instruction set.
Like I simply like SSE.
So it's, it's a very old processor though.
I mean, the processor is, you know, it's over a decade old.
And so, I guess what he was trying to determine when he was asking the
question is, why is something, you know, that's, that's why or
something over 10 years old.
Why is it slow to emulate?
Today.
And the answer to that question is actually that it depends very, very
specifically on what you're trying to emulate why it is slow but I can
try to give you a general appreciation for some reasons why?
Something might be slow when you emulate it.
If the hardware itself is not all that fast.
Right.
Okay, so let's talk about a few aspects of this.
So, first of all, let's talk about single thread speed.
So single thread execution, right?
On a any CPU single thread, execution used to get faster every year,
right?
And so if you actually looked at the speed that which things were
executing it, actually, you know, you could almost use the megahertz
as a pretty good indication of how fast things were going and, you
know, if you go back to back when I was a kid, you know, and not even
actually when I was probably a teenager so
This, you know, you might have a machine that was like eight
megahertz, right?
And then you, you talked about that in the, you know, in the early 90s
or something like that and then you kind of talk about something that
was maybe the year 2000, right?
And something in the year 2000 was like a gigahertz perhaps, right?
So, you look at the clock speeds here, and it was, it was like this
kind of a thing, right?
It was like, it was a straight-up exponential curve where things were
getting twice as fast all the time.
Twice, twice, twice twice and they were just escalating super rapidly,
right?
But then around 4 GHz this topped out completely, so this curve like
went up and then it just like straight-up did that right?
And so while until at all and you know, for various reasons people
were able to continue
Sort of getting some speed increases in single threaded execution,
most of the execution speed ceased to come in single threaded, speed,
that sort of stopped happening.
Core count started going up memory speed.
So in terms of the single threaded execution memory, speed more cash,
basically eliminating, the bottlenecks of memory started becoming
somebody could do, but the actual speed of the instructions was not
Any faster if that makes sense.
Like you were, you were sort of starting to hit this this limit of
what you could do.
And so it was creeping up at a much lower rate.
And so maybe they could do things like remove a clock cycle or two
from this or clock cycle, free from that.
And, you know, he's sort of cute cities to get faster, but it's not
nearly in the, in the sort of direct way that it that it used to.
So nowadays, the first thing that you have to
Shape is that when you talk about simulating something from, I don't
know when it was, right.
If you talk about something stimulating, something from in here, and
you're talking about simulating it in here, there's a very big
difference in terms of being able to emulate stuff across this Gap.
Then there would have been across this Gap, right?
Because if you look at the Gap back here, the degree to which single
threaded execution, was faster, was dramatic like really, really
dramatic.
Okay.
Why does this matter?
Well, first of all, if you are emulating something,
Emulating something, you can't Auto paralyzed.
Write the code that you're emulating for on a dolphin is like either
single threaded or to threaten.
I think it's only single threaded.
I can't remember what that ship did I have no, I can't remember
whether there was a second thread under or not.
So the GameCube was at one thread.
Was it to thread point being however, many threads it was, it was
either one or two.
I think it was one, but don't quote me on that.
You can't, if you have four cores with to hyper threads, each you
can't somehow turn that single-threaded workload or two or dual
threaded workload.
You can't magically turn that into an 8 thread workload.
That's just not possible for the emulator to do, right?
It would require analyzing the complete code and like doing all kinds
of Auto parallelizing stuff that's actually like an open research
topic to this day, how to like properly take completely single
threaded code and think about it and turn it into multi-threaded,
right?
That's a really
Hard problem.
So, your average run-of-the-mill emulator is not going to be able to
be doing anything like that.
That's, you know, maybe in a very limited certain cases, it could do
it, but very, very difficult.
So the degree to which you're getting that speed increase.
It's not as big as you think, right?
So that's the first thing to appreciate.
I don't want to suggest that somehow your single trade execution today
is the same as it was on a GameCube.
I'm not trying to say that at all, like I said, memory got a lot
faster.
There's there's a lot of reasons why it will get faster.
I'm just trying to say, I appreciate the fact that it's not as fast as
you might have thought it was, okay?
So that's that's thing one, alright?
So that's thing one and then think to, in fact, so let me just write
these down.
So number one CPUs today, aren't
Much faster.
At straight.
Wine code.
Right.
So, just by Just, Gotta execute a series of instructions.
Today's CPUs just aren't that much faster right there faster, but they
aren't as much faster as you expected in the old days.
You might have said, oh, you know, it's it's you look at between here
and here you look at the Richmond 8 MHz + 1 gigahertz alone, right?
You're talking about 100 times faster.
That's not true in a single thread of execution on today's machines,
probably isn't a hundred times faster than it was.
On a dolphin, right?
So, if you look at an emulator for something, like the Amiga,
And you look at what we could emulate on the Amiga on a 1 GHz machine.
Let's say maybe it seemed to do a really good job.
You're like, well, that's a very complicated computer.
How was that able to do it?
And now this Dalton thing.
Can't, we can't do it or whatever.
Well that's you know, not comparing Apples to Apples.
You're comparing apples to oranges because the single depart that an
emulator actually cares about which is the single threaded code
execution that part simply didn't get as much faster in the past 10
years as it did the 10 years before that and the 10 years before that,
we've been on the increasingly.
Sort of pessimistic curve for single threaded, code execution.
As things start to become more about getting more cores, more threads
wider instructions.
Right.
That's another thing I can't do it.
Can't widen the instructions.
They can't use Cindy, because it would have to analyze an auto
symbolize.
Again, a very difficult process.
So that's thing, one thing, two, of course.
So you might say well okay so they aren't getting as much faster as
they used to perhaps but they're still obviously faster.
Right.
There's no question we would never say that a core i7 from today or
something like this is not significantly faster still then a dolphin
from the GameCube obviously it is right.
That's definitely true.
So the question is, if it's obviously faster, why is it having trouble
emulating this thing?
Like if it's faster, it should just be able
Emulate it, right?
A faster CPU should be able to emulate a source of you.
Well, the reason for that, of course, is that emulation
Requires.
Emulation.
Emulation is not the same thing as running code.
Emulation means that a particular CPU that you're talking about and
it's all the stuff that it does.
Must be recreated accurately enough.
That the program that is running on it cannot tell the difference
between that and the actual hardware and when I say tell the
difference, I don't mean antagonistic way.
I'm not saying that it's looking for it, but in a de facto it is so.
And
What do I mean by that?
What I mean by that is if you imagine
that we have let's say we have a simple spec, okay?
So let's say we have a simple spec and this is maybe just the
instruction set of the of the dolphin of the GameCube.
Okay.
We have this simple spec and we're just like okay we give all the
developers.
This simple spec, the compiler generates code to this spec, right?
That's what happened.
When people made a GameCube game.
So all we need to do is take the simple spec and emulate the simple
spec and then we will have the equivalent of a dolphin CPU running and
can run all the dolphin things right?
And that is not even remotely.
True not
Even remotely.
True.
Why is that not even really true.
It's not even remotely true because nobody actually codes to the spec,
okay?
It doesn't mean they're not trying to go to the spec.
It does mean the compiler is not trying to Output suspect.
What it means is that nobody actually is running anything on the spec
they are running everything on the actual dolphin with all of its
Hardware bugs.
All of its Hardware idiosyncrasies
And all the programmer knows after he writes his code, right?
He looks at what he's supposed to write.
He writes his code and then he starts running on the dolphin all he
knows,
Is whether it worked.
Right?
And that's all you need to know.
Once the code appears to be working properly, he believes that he has
properly created or she in this case, she might believe that she is
properly, created something to run on the dolphin and you know what
she's right she did she will ship that and everyone who is able to
play it on there you know GameCube confirms that fact but what
actually happened there what actually happened there was this was a
huge
Of code and probably it relied on some weird undocumented aspects of
this thing.
Like sometimes when you do a particular thing, it takes a little
longer than it used to and that happened to be just enough time to
make sure that some dolphin GPU thing that was submitted completed
when it wouldn't have completed otherwise.
And so there's no bug and they never see a bug.
They had one but they never see it because technically they don't
really have one because some aspect of a dolphin Hardware is masking
that bug.
Thereby making it effective.
Lee not a bug, right?
But now what you have done is you've produced code that rely
specifically on exactly how the dolphin CPU functioned.
So what does this mean?
When you start to look at it across millions and millions of lines of
code, tons of programmers.
He wrote this, she wrote this, they wrote this right, all of these
programs, how many GameCube games were there?
Tons of GameCube games, right?
Well effectively what you're doing essentially, this is you could
think of is almost like a genetic engineering process, right?
It's basically hammering just like nature does when it creates random
mutations, right?
It's basically hammering on this Hardware with every last piece of
code that people tried to make and eventually you've got some code
somewhere in some game that relies on every last little thing.
That this thing did weird every last little cycle discrepancy every
last little quirky weird way.
If it had a divided bug in it, if it had, you know, a
A weird like stall.
Something particular that happened with the cash, something where a
value.
Get cleared in a register every last one of those.
There's a game up here that relied on it.
So now what that means is in order to actually write the emulation,
you must actually emulate this actual physical device, not the speck.
So it is not a simple matter of loading, a bunch of code, binary
translating it from, you know, powerpc to x64 and then executing it.
That's simply not the case.
What actually has to happen is you have to build essentially a virtual
CPU model and a virtual GPU model, right?
And it's virtual motherboard model,
You have to build these virtual models and you actually have to
simulate all of their defects all of their idiosyncrasies, all of
their specified weirdness, right?
Because there's stuff in the spec that might still be very hard for an
ecstasy for to emulate.
It might take 30 instructions, it might take interrupt you, who knows
what it would take to accurately recreate, what's happening inside
this this, this machine, right?
It has to create all of this and then essentially run these
Virtual CPUs, it's not simply running the code, so who knows how
complicated that could be something very, very simple on the Dalton
CPU and interrupt that fires when the GPU is full of something, who
knows?
I have no idea right now, suddenly has to be emulated in this world,
where those things aren't actually running in Harbor.
There is no such thing as the GPU interrupt happening in hardware for
this particular thing.
So that's all simulated hundreds, and hundreds of hundreds of
Instructions, getting executed potentially on the xt4 to simulate one
thing.
That didn't take any instructions on the dolphin, it just happened,
right?
And all of those timings have to be correct.
Because in any way, if they diverged from what actually happened on
the dolphin, you will no longer be able to run all the games that ran
on the dolphin.
And that's just the sad truth of it, right?
So, in emulator, authors job is very difficult, indeed.
And hopefully, this gives you a little bit of perspective on why it's
not just straight forward.
Because if it was literally the case,
That we had some powerpc code here, right?
And we had some x64 code here and we just took it and we just like,
you know, we just translated it.
Sure there's no chance like, I refuse to believe.
I mean, I don't remember the power PCS instruction set that, well, but
I refuse to believe there's any chance that wouldn't run significantly
faster.
Okay, you could just do it and it may be done.
But, unfortunately, that is simply not the problem that we're looking
at.
It's the fact that the x 64 now needs to,
To simulate a CPU and GPU and other peripheral components inside
itself, and it needs to do it.
Incredibly accurately that
It's a really big hurdle for emulation authors to overcome.
And so, you know, does that mean you couldn't still create a thing
that would do this, right?
No, it just means if you actually wanted the thing that like binary
translates, all whole game over and then runs it like, almost at
Native speeds, like x64 style speeds modern computer speeds.
That's just an incredibly hard review, know, sort of like artificial
intelligent reverse.
Veneering.
Sort of translation problem thing.
That just you know that's not what at your average emulator is going
to be able to do or if might not even be possible, right?
I mean, you get into probably nasty computer science thing is like
halting problem sort of stuff there where you're like, okay it's a
program.
We don't even know how to analyze it that.
Well, like, you know, it's really difficult to sort of figure out when
interrupts would have happened in here and how to insert the code that
would automatically know.
Just it's really pretty, pretty crazy, right?
So hopefully that gives you some perspective that said, I have never
looked at Dolphin emulation so, you know, maybe it's actually not too
bad.
Maybe there aren't that many idiosyncrasies of that particular
machine, maybe it was very clean.
There's very simple.
And if that was the case, then maybe the Dolphin Emulator is just
lousy, right?
I mean there's the substance such a thing is just it's not coated well
for Speed or who knows, right.
So I don't know and I'm not going to try to speculate on someone
else's emulator code but
It's certainly plausible that even if the emulator authors did a good
job, there's plenty of reasons why it might not be the case that you
get reasonable performance on a machine that you might think you
should, you might need a lot of extra performance to actually get it
to work.
Right?
Let's see.
Let us see able to use thumbs thumbsticks.
Wonder if one could map common stuff to controller for programming,
language to program via controller.
Yeah, I don't know, like I said, it's a little bit too early for me to
make any real determinations yet, so I just don't know.
Like I said as soon as I kind of have a more solid idea of exactly
what's going to happen.
I will I will.
Let you know.
Mr.
Fourth dimension.
I'm working on a sort of experimental alternative to Mo's that reduces
probably eliminates key holding to you.
I think that's part of the problem for you.
Like I said, I really just don't know and I would love to see that.
I'd love to see what you got because like I mean as you know I'm a
really big fan of your editor so far and I feel like if you've got an
idea it's probably a good one or at the very least it's probably worth
trying and I think one of the big problems is our size.
It's really hard to tell, what is it, isn't causing it right?
And so sometimes the best bet is to just try to, you know, do as much
as you can.
And so,
So I'd be willing to play around with whatever you've got just to see,
you know, if it helps right.
I mean I feel like everyone's kind of that way.
We're all trying to experiment to find things that might help.
So I'd love to see it if you're working on it.
In Janeiro.
Could these streams be a good time for some C++ tutorials or something
similar?
You mean like if I did like the beginner like how beginner's guide to
see, I suppose I could try because it maybe isn't as much typing
there.
We'll see.
I want to wait.
I want to do a week or so of just we'll chat and I want to have a
chance to go back to physical therapy again and we'll see I'm, it's a
little premature for me to know how long I'll actually to be outer.
What's going on here?
So, I have some more work I need to do just
Just as Baseline there.
Captain craft.
How much of the renderer that you wrote for handmade.
Here will be replaced when you move fully into opengl.
We pretty much are fully in opengl already.
We render everything through opengl.
The only thing we didn't do with textures.
Ratchet freak.
I mean we did the texture.
Find we didn't do the overlap download of textures ratchet freak.
Right.
Click and remove from list to remove keepass know.
I didn't want to remove it.
I wanted it there.
I just wanted down at the bottom, but I guess maybe that was the
faster the shortcut thing.
I don't even care.
In fact, are they they is gender neutral.
Yeah, you know, I do kind of like they for gender-neutral I use it
when I'm writing I guess I should just do it when I'm talking.
I never use it when I'm talking for some reason, but I do use it when
I'm when I'm writing.
And so maybe I'll just use it for talking.
Our be any LR, I'm working through some opengl tutorials, at the
moment and a matte quaternions now.
Okay, cool.
Ryan Roth, whether opinions on stand-up desk.
I recently switched to one of my hands feel noticeably better, you
know, I've never tried it for hands, I did have a problem with my hip
a while back well my knee really sort of hard to describe but
And I have a standing desk for that so I can try it.
I don't need it for the knee at the moment but I could try putting it
up.
I have got right.
What I did find is that I can't program for that long at it.
My back gets a little sore trying to stand for that long and as do my
feet.
But but I never really tried it for hands, so I may
I could certainly go to Schatzi.
I've been.
Reading on early computer Graphics, technology 60s and 70s, any
thoughts on the topic?
Not really, I don't know that much about 60s and 70s Graphics
technology.
I mean, that's the early stuff, right?
When I'm really, really early.
I don't know much about, that's like spaceward stuff, right?
She was Captain crafts.
You mentioned before that there are great programmers that have very
different skill sets.
What skill sets is your strongest did you actively try to get better
at it or just naturally fall into that skill set?
I would say I feel like API design is my my strongest skill set.
I would say, I would say that's typically, I tend to find that.
You know, if I was like, well, you're going to in what situation would
you pick yourself rather than somebody else to code?
This thing?
If you could pick anyone in the world API design is almost always.
I have yet to see someone who I think does as good as good as
thorough, as job on those as I do.
And so, I would say that's probably it and yeah, because like most
things like optimization, I'd rather pick somebody else than me.
Working with other people's code, I'd rather pick up.
I could think of other people, I would pick.
I tend to be really good at
At sort of first pass solutions to things too.
Like if you have a problem that people don't actually know how to
solve yet and it just needs to get solved.
I'm usually pretty good at that too, like new Solutions and they're
typically probably not going to be the best solution like someone will
come along after me and usually do a better one but like kind of
getting in there in a situation where there's really, no one really
knows exactly what's going on.
I can also usually make sense of those pretty well.
I,
I would say.
The size of dolphin is the emulator.
Not the chip.
No dolphin is actually the name of the platform so dolphin was the
name of the Game Cube before they called it the GameCube.
So like the internal name is is Dolphin.
You can see here
Where is the actual?
Well?
Rap.
At the time, we all called it dolphin because I don't think they had
actually named it GameCube when we actually had the, you know, the dev
kits and stuff at rad.
So it was always the dolphin, the dolphin, this, the dolphin that.
So I still use that that name.
I assume that they use that name for the emulator because that was the
code name for the box, but it would be weird if that wasn't the case.
And so yeah.
Chrome Dragon.
That's why every part is label the dolphin because it was, it was like
the dolphin CPU, dolphin GPU.
That's what we called it.
K.
Thanks for the great answer.
Regarding my question about rotation scaling, apologies, but I wasn't
able to find the time to research it and hammy hiroko due to my foot
on it.
Dude, you have like three weeks
The question was, how does scale rotation play nice together for
tations are stored at the first of our three dude?
What are you even talking about?
I have a full-time job.
Lame.
What are you even talking about?
You got to go back, you got to go back and look at it.
Go back and look at the code where we do rotation and we had scaling
in there, when we did the thing where we originally did.
Right before, you know, when we were doing the texture mapping, it's
still in there, the code still in there.
I'll draw it out anyway.
And biggest Panda.
Ever have to write accessibility features for people with disabilities
like RSI.
No.
Except I guess.
Yes.
Now me
And so, you know, I guess I'll be learning about that for no apparent
reason other than I am.
Now a disability.
Boondoggle, 42 since John Blow soliciting for program Integrity Jay, I
would you be interested in being involved in any way.
I think he's looking for actually like people to go program out
full-time which obviously I'm not going to do because I've got too
much stuff at the moment, but symbolic.
But what do you think, about model view controller pattern?
If you already read about this, feel free to ignore the question.
I didn't rant about it, I think I said that, I feel like model view
controller is not too far from a reasonable way from, okay.
Is there a couple things that are a little bit that I think are a
little bit confusing about the way they phrase it but it's not bad.
Sean McGrath specific to me.
So feel free to skip.
Remember that grid was really determination thing.
I spent two minutes, think about it?
I think just for 8 bit numbers.
Indicating how far in each cardinal direction you can see from that
cell solves, everything, four bytes for sale easy-peasy
I don't really understand why that solves the problem, but
I'm not really sure I ever really understood the problem, you're
trying to solve, so there's that
Aaliyah Christian, in the First videos, you mentioned that you won't
use anything like opengl.
Did you change your mind on the way?
I don't do.
We actually mention that.
I mean, we did, we did the whole renderer without it, open Jill.
And, but I feel like I always said, we're going to Hardware
acceleration.
Originally, I assumed we would do is, you would use Vulcan but I
strongly dislike the architecture for these new graphics apis like d3d
12 and, and mantle and so on.
So I think
Probably won't do them because I don't like them and don't really want
to encourage people to use them because I think they're bad.
/ act looks like Silicon Valley.
Bubble is bursting.
I don't know what that means, but it's about time.
I mean I don't know why people put so much money into things that
don't even make money, but you know, advertising isn't as big a
business.
As people think it is in my opinion and Rudi our has the RSI been
putting a damper on your work at my rock as well.
Yes, it has not because trying to switch to keyboard layouts.
I don't know what I'm going to do.
It's a problem.
It's a very big problem.
and,
And I'm not sure exactly what to do with it because I don't actually
know what specifically the problem is yet.
I don't know where the problems actually coming from.
I don't know if it's specific to typing the at the wrists or if it's
like, you know, because problems with the nerve, you kid can come from
anywhere, right?
You can have a problem with a nerve in your neck, you can have it
anywhere from the brain down, right?
You can have a problem in your neck, you can have a problem in your
shoulder.
You can have a problem at your elbow, you can have a problem even in
your
Arm.
You can have a problem in the hand at the wrist so I really just don't
know what to do at this point and so it's a little bit of a holding
pattern but and I have not really tried.
Funkier going to metric keyboards.
I tried typing on some sort of the, the Microsoft, or the, or the
split ones before, and I found that those didn't help that was before
I had risk braces.
I feel like their wrist brace has helped, like, made things fine for
me actually, and if the keyboard
Didn't help.
But that was a separate problem from this one.
So now I don't like I said, I don't know.
It could be that a learner who would help and we'll have to see as I
go for further.
Kemo sabe que si si knowledge nugget to, to Contour, not to const.
So I talked about that actually talked about that before my opinion on
const.
I don't use it, but it's I'm not against const.
Specifically.
My opinion on cost is that I don't tend to make very many bugs that
contest.
Catches
If that like that just you know, sort of the way I phrased it.
When I answered it.
For and it's still kind of my opinion on it is is basically you want
to do things that catch the bugs, you have, right?
You want to do things to catch the bugs, you're likely to make.
And so I make a plenty of bugs and I can sort of name various
different kinds of bugs that I might have writing into a variable that
I wasn't opposed to writing to.
I almost never do you know, MIT, you know, once a year or something
like this, that happens to me.
Maybe right.
I think it's happened once on this entire on.
All of hand.
A hero and that's when I can't even pay attention to the code.
That's what I'm talking the whole time, right?
And so cons to me is just a waste of time because it doesn't help me,
right?
It's just extra typing that just waste my time.
And so, for me not using cost is a no-brainer, right?
It does, it would make no sense, it's literally just straight-up
stupid for me to ever type constant.
In my code that said, not, everyone makes them kind of bugs, right?
Bugs that I am liability liable to make in my code, may not be bugs at
your level because your code and vice versa.
So,
You may find that you often make the mistake of writing into a
variable you weren't supposed to right to, right?
And if you find that you have made this a cost may be worth it for
you.
If you can help cut down on those bugs and those are the bugs.
You tend to make the extra typing may be worth it, right?
And so pretty much every language speakers.
Sure.
Like costs, which really doesn't do anything.
A lot of people think Concepts opposition, it doesn't really there's
like one or two very rare cases that concert ever helps you and they
mostly don't.
So with something like costs that's like a, you know,
It's like a language contract.
That strictly there for your benefit, basically.
Your choice to use.
It has to be based on whether you think it's saving you time and only
you know that because what saves me time may not be what saves you
time and so you need to know that it's actually saving you time and
don't take my word for whether I use it as indicating that you should
or shouldn't because it's the, it's going to be different for you.
K.
So one of the main problems is not that we're not fast enough, but
probably not accurate enough and emulation.
But at the Docks were pretty clear about everything really to the
hardware, the specs etcetera, where they really go down detailed
swing.
How everything works?
Wouldn't that make the life of emulator authors easier?
So Elven it would make it their lives easier because they know exactly
what to emulate, but doesn't necessarily mean that the emulation
getting faster because even once you know, exactly all the
idiosyncrasies of the machine and exactly how it works.
They still may be very expensive to simulate
Right?
So in order to actually make those things, reproducible, you may need
thousands and thousands of x64 instructions to reproduce one thing
that the GameCube did instantaneously, right?
And you just, that's just the nature of simulating Hardware with other
Hardware.
You, you if you have a mismatch in how that harder Works, what you
always do, how expensive it is to simulate the other kind can, you
know, it may have nothing to do with whether, you know.
How it works.
It's not what knowing that matters.
It's can you do it?
In a reasonably efficient way, right?
P fo G.
Now that I'm playing the witness.
Would you explain again?
What part you worked on sure.
so I did a couple things I did the movement system, I did all that I
did the bunch of work on the grass planting
I did a bunch of work on the editor and, and I think that's about it.
Most of the work I did is in editor side stuff but then I did a bunch
of work on the movement.
So moving the character around is entirely me pretty much except for
the part that sits just above it and decides like the walk speed and
stuff is John's code.
Like John wrote code, that's like how he wanted to feel when you move.
So he just says, like I want to go this far or whatever, and then I
did the code that does all the Collision detection in the all, you
know, all the stuff that actually has a deal with moving you around
properly.
And making sure you bump into things and all that sort of stuff.
Long billion.
I'm thinking, being a sewing machine, pedal for mode switching, Envy.
I am.
Yeah, it might be good, especially in v.
I Am.
When you have this really heavy toggle, right?
I could see that being valuable, they have foot switches that you can
buy Triple foot switches and single foot switches.
There's a bunch of different foot pedal, USB foot pedal vendors out
there a calc any suggestions on the ideal computer chair and settings
for programming, I tend to have problems with the backs of my legs.
I've actually been using one of those rubber exercise balls as a
chair, which works.
But isn't the most control thing?
I don't have any suggestion that I mean, like I said, I have RSI.
So my suggestions are pretty worthless because obviously, whatever I'm
doing is not particularly great.
But here's what I would say, legs wise, exercising and stretching your
legs is often times, pretty important, if you sit all day.
And so one of the problems you may have and you may want to look into
again, if you can see a good physical therapist, I'm like that, who
could help you with that.
At but building up an exercise routine, I exercise everyday for my
legs like I do stretches for them for no reason, other than it
prevents problems that I had with my legs as far as I can tell, and
it's worked pretty well so far.
And so, I would say, I don't know, and I can't couldn't really say,
but I'd say, if you can find someone look into potentially exercises
that are specifically designed to stretch out, you know, like your get
good, a good stretch.
Each for your legs so that they're less susceptible to problems when
sitting because sitting all the time is tough on legs if they're not
ready for it.
Do you know other Advanced algebra topics that became a thing in
modern programming like quaternions did?
In modern programming.
Sure, like all of cryptography is based on Advanced algebra stuff,
right?
You know, like division rings and mod.
And you know, number Theory, stuff, all that sort of thing is, is
pretty important.
I don't know exactly what you're looking for.
Is your qualifier, but you know, that would be probably a good
example.
I depending on what you're looking for Icarus, I thought about doing
electronics and creating custom keyboard for your issues.
Like I've got time though.
You know I mean I don't know how to learn.
That would be a lot of learning and
You know, I would, I would love it if I knew that, but I already have
no time.
You know, I'm already so strapped for time, I'll, it's really hard.
And so I do, there's no way I'd come up to speed in time, to, in the
time, I would need
Captain craft.
What kinds of jobs outside the game industry?
Translate well into game engine programming, I don't know.
It's kind of a unique field so I would say maybe you know if you're
like an offline rendering thing like let's say you work to the render
team for Pixar well.
Now you know a lot about rendering stuff and maybe you didn't quite
have to do it for 60 frames a second because that wasn't your goal but
you still care about a lot of the same thing.
So I suspect that would probably be like offline rendering guy.
Would probably be a good example of someone who wouldn't have trouble
translating into game industry.
There's some new things to think about and some old things you don't
have to think about and but you know it's a very similar discipline, I
don't know.
Captain craft.
You think the arm can ever catch up to desktop CPUs?
Or that it could be used as a good game platform sure.
Yeah, I wouldn't I wouldn't be surprised.
I mean.
My understanding was Apple's arm.
Implementation is now quite fast.
I don't know if it's x64 fast, but it's quite fast.
so, you know, yeah, I would suspect
that if you took apples arm core, and
And ran with it, you might be a make a good game machine out of that,
you know, doesn't seem far-fetched to me.
I don't study that.
I don't study arm and very much detail, and I'm also not an expert on
things like how instruction sets affect the maximum speed that things
can go.
But, you know, I think if you decided to make a high-power arm core,
you might be able to do something like that.
Yeah, sure.
Knock till what don't you like about the Vulcan dx12?
As I'm going to write up a series on that at some point, once Vulcans
actually out.
And so I'll talk more about that down the line.
Quarter Tron.
What about constant optimization possibilities?
Are there really aren't any optimization possibilities for concerts,
there's really only one and it's not a very interesting one, if that
makes sense.
It's it's basically because most of the time when you're in a function
and you get something past you as const, the compiler can't assume
that it's actually const because anyone could my actually modify its
in Cincy.
The spec allows you to cast the constant way.
Cost cast is the thing that's allowed
And so the only time that it actually helps you with optimization is
when the compiler can see that you yourself have made, the thing that
is constant, so it has to be made right there.
Can't be passed in or anything like that.
Can't be a pointer, right?
You've made the thing yourself.
It's an actual value and the compiler couldn't have figured out that
it doesn't get modified anywhere else.
So you have to then pass, it's a dress to somebody else and then do
something with it.
After the fact, that's the only
I'm a compiler can actually use cons for optimization purposes.
Any other time you can't do it and so it really doesn't help you very
much.
It almost never actually helps the compiler.
Chandler.
Carrots said that const as a concept doesn't even exist in the
optimizer for llvm.
So the only thing that actually happens is the front end.
We'll do some transforms if it knows about const.
In that specific case, I just said I think it will do the transform
necessary to make sure that it just treats that value as a constant,
but that's like it, the optimizer wasn't even think about it.
K.
I'm very sad to hear about your hands.
I pray and wish you get well soon.
Thank you very much.
I am very sad about them too.
I'm hoping that it doesn't lead to a long-term problem, but I never
know.
So, you know, I'm hoping that it gets better.
I'm, and I'm trying
Serious 33 around a 130 or so you said that opengl directory were out
back waiting to be put down and that everyone would be using Vulcan
based on your comments.
Just now you no longer feel that way.
Yeah.
So my assumption and you know,
Let me rephrase that.
So,
I guess I don't know that I don't feel that way still because I am
quite afraid that actually opengl and d3d will still be put down and
everyone will have to use Vulcan and or d3d 12 / metal or whatever.
The thing is on your platform.
I do kind of feel like that may still happen but what change was?
I actually went and read up on them and I am no longer enthusiastic
about that particular switch.
There are a lot of things.
Opengl is incredibly crafty at this.
Way too much stuff in it, it desperately needs to be streamlined and
revised.
I assume that that is what Vulcan would be just like, I assumed that,
you know, mantle was ostensibly designed thing.
When I actually went and looked at them, I don't, I strongly disagree
with almost every design decision that they made.
And so now at this point I'm like I really don't know what to say.
I'm pretty pessimistic about the future of 3D apis.
I
I think it's a disaster, it's a complete unmitigated disaster and and
I don't know what I mean.
I think we're just going to end up with absolutely horrible API that
we all have to use going forward because they're all roughly the same.
So, no matter which one you pick it, they made the same decisions and
I think they were really bad decisions, that's what I haven't.
Look, specifically at metal.
that's the only one that I haven't actually read up on yet and so, you
know, maybe it's fantastic I doubt it but
Mmv 94, have you heard about the good do engine?
Do you think it is a good tool for prototyping proof-of-concept?
I know, I have not heard about the good oh engine.
You Christian said, how do you and Jonathan Blow know each other?
Are we met through Chris Hecker a long, long time ago?
K any general tips suggestions on how to approach the code for a new
project with little or no art done for it.
Yet, we have almost a complete Game design document listing all the co
stuff we need but there's so much stuff.
It's tricky to figure out where and how to start.
I guess I don't really have tips in that working from a design spec to
make a game, is not something I really ever done.
You know, that's not the typical way in which I've been involved in
programming.
So, I don't know that I could really give you any advice, that
wouldn't just be guessing.
Me blow.
Are you familiar with NG?
I don't think so.
In fact, reduced me to them in recently and I'm now addicted.
No, I don't think, I know what that is.
Long billion.
You're probably the wrong person to ask, but you have any idea when,
if the limit of the witness will get a Linux version waiting is hard.
I have not heard anything about a Linux version, so I don't know.
The trouble with Linux is not getting it running.
Obviously, we could probably get the lytic the witness running in
Linux in that very much time on our machine, right?
The problem is when you then ship it to customers and have to deal
with the support it's kind of
Epic nightmare, especially on Linux were machines.
Often times the audio just doesn't work of its own accord, let alone
the audio in your game, right?
And so it's just a really bad platform for shipping games.
It's really, really, really unreliable and that's compared to Windows
which is already unreliable.
So you know, to say that Linux is an unreliable platform is
A lot considering a Windows is very unreliable to begin with.
So it's really, really unfortunate and I wish that would get better,
but it just has not traditionally gotten any better.
And so the reality is that if you want to ship again unless you have
to be really dedicated to it, the witness team does not have anybody
who's particularly you know we don't even have anyone on that team of
runs relax regularly and you know what's in it for them.
They won't make any money off of it.
You know, it's the number of game sales.
We've got Olympics is fractures that they literally just be doing out
of the goodness of their heart, which they made.
All right, you know, they may do it just to be nice but you have to
understand from because, from a business perspective, it's just
straight up throwing money into a fire, pretty much.
And so, I think, usually you have to do it for for a moral reason.
Like, you know, I might try to have the Molly game strip on the next
strictly because I want to support the platform.
It's not going to make any money.
It's gonna lose me money, probably or whatever.
Right.
But you know, that would be the reason to do it because it's
financially.
It makes sense.
As far as I can tell.
Elvin.
Have you ever tried building something for mobile and submitting it to
a store?
Like Apple Store, it's way.
The tedious process takes 30 minutes to build and only when it
finishes, it tells you there was any errors.
It's quite a nightmare for me.
I don't understand why there are so many mobile game rulers.
Yeah, I mean I think it's just the Gold Rush mentality.
Like everyone thinks they're going to make get rich off it.
Or something is why they do it.
I don't know because, yeah, I agree.
It's a nightmare.
And then plus Apple just denies your game for random reasons like, you
know, they just denied Binding of Isaac, right?
It's like, you're just like, okay, like, you know, you it's not even a
free.
And fair Marketplace it's completely.
It's this.
It's this completely sort of feudal environment.
And yeah, I don't like it.
I wish we didn't have those things, I don't think they're good.
Boondoggle, if doctors could grow, you clone arms on the back of a
host animal, say a pig, would you accept them as transplants under
body to get another 30 years of pain free programming?
Sure.
Yeah.
I mean I don't know how they're going to graph them on there because
that's really tough, but if somehow they would make it work, I don't
know that I believe they could make it work, but if somehow I actually
knew that it would work sure.
Rogers freak.
Would it be possible to make a front-end wrapping the next gen
Graphics apis that you like that is exactly what we have at Molly.
Now actually I kind of took matters into my own hands there and said
we're going to have a good graphics API and then I'm going to have a
thing that that shunts to these various things.
Sean McGrath with my platform game Loop is more ready?
Would you be interested in scrutinizing?
The API design?
I mean look before it's too late to change.
It went something I think is an awful maybe although it's just it's a
lot of work and I don't have any spring spare brain power for that
stuff these days.
I just like I work all the time and I really don't want any other
projects.
So probably the answer is no because the amount of time it would take
me to
Actually think through how you decide to do everything and whether or
not I think it was a good idea is like a whole project for me and I
just I don't I can't take any more projects.
I just can't between handmade con handmade hero and our projects that
Molly which involve also like doing the website for Molly and
everything.
You know, I did a bunch of artwork stuff for Molly like there's just I
can't so pretty much anything that's not a Molly project, just gets a
no and that's nothing personal.
I would love to help with your project, I want it to be good.
Good.
And like I was saying the other day.
I really like your game sort of the direction you kind of want to go
sounded really interesting.
But I just I can't take any projects so if it's not a my product, I
just it's an automatic no for me at this point.
Especially now that I don't know how my hands will be.
So for, are there any wrappers around opengl d3d, Vulcan that you
would prefer to become a full 3d API rather than just a rapper?
I guess.
Yeah hours but I don't know that we'll ever be able to convince any
isvs of that maybe someday.
I mean I HD is rather symbolic but BTW do know what happened with the
witness sound a bunch of people.
I know had issues including myself and had disabled surround sound or
something.
No, unfortunately, to be honest I don't know anything about how the
witness output sound at all.
I have no idea.
So I literally have zero insight into what people may have experienced
for sound bugs.
So, sorry, I can't really help you.
Yeah, I don't know.
Windows definitely is kind of a crazy platform for shipping stuff, you
know, compared to say console at the PS4 sign that where you do have
to, you know, if you don't, if you're not careful, you'll do something
wrong.
And then some certain motherboard somewhere, sound ship won't work
with your sound.
For some reason, you don't know why.
And then you find out later, oh, you called this wrong function, that
put Windows in this thing that the driver was expecting it.
You know, it's, it's very touchy and so it doesn't necessarily mean
that they did anything wrong, right?
It doesn't necessarily mean that they screwed up it gets.
Sometimes there's just like, oh yeah.
These weird problems on various windows installs and you just have to
then go find that out and fix it, right?
Let's see.
I'm going to I'm going to go ahead and say that we're about out of
time here.
So I'm just going to see if there's any last questions.
Power C 9k have you completed the witness?
No so the last time I played through the witness was actually a fair
bit ago and not all of the puzzles that are in all of the things you
could do in the witness that exists in the shipping version.
We're not even actually implemented at the time that I played through
it.
So you know, there's a bunch of puzzles that weren't even in the game
and a bunch of puzzles that weren't working yet.
In the game, The Last time I played through it.
So no, I have not finished the witness at
Point.
I might go back and actually play it, the final version so that I can
actually like a hundred percent it because I've never actually been
able to play the game with everything in it.
I've never done that.
Middle of something I find kind of interesting regarding the financial
viability of Linux is that in those Humble Bundle payment, pie charts
the Linux segment tends to be way above 1%.
So yeah.
Like a couple things to note about that, let's say, you have like a
phenomenally successful game, right?
Like it's like super super, super super successful.
So you met crazy money more money than, you know, you're like I would
ever expect to make on a game.
Right?
So let's say you make, let's say, you make 10 million on it, right?
So if you make 10 million dollars on it, and you got 1% of that back,
it's 100 grand.
so, for 100 grand,
you have to remember a person who barely knows like, and I'm not even
making this up, who's barely able to program JavaScript?
And pretty well.
Like it was a bit barely functional web programmer, right?
In John's neck of the woods.
So in San Francisco will make 140 Grand a year.
So, the entirety of all the sales, you would get on Linux.
If you had a phenomenally successful game and one percent of your
sales, came from Linux, right?
Wouldn't even be enough for one person to work on it for say six
months plus overhead.
Right.
So if you happen to live in some place where the cost of living is
extremely small which you may be looking at to do like maybe you live.
I don't know.
Like I was talking to people from Argentina.
Recently their burn rates are incredibly low compared to what we pay
in the United States for people's salaries working is right.
You know there's plenty of places in the world even if you were in the
u.s.
if you were in Detroit Michigan.
A versus Seattle Washington, your cost of living is, is dramatically
different, right?
And so one of the problems is the witness is made in a very expensive
part of the world and the salaries that you have to pay people in that
part of the world are very high, which means that even at 1%,
It's kind of a loss, right?
Because now there's also mental energy.
John has to maintain that build.
He has to put it up on the stores.
He has to, like, filled all the tech support, right?
So it's this huge.
It's a huge mental, Jane monetarily.
It's kind of a wash.
Maybe you make 20K, maybe you make 30k on it, thirty thousand dollars
is.
I mean, what are you gonna do with that?
You're talking about a game that made 10 million dollars, even to get
to this point, thirty thousand dollars out of 10 million?
Are you gonna bother with a whole new build?
All that porting work, all that effort, you could have.
Put towards something else you're not gonna write.
It just doesn't make sense.
And so I don't think people really understand the economics of it plus
I
No, Humble Bundle payment, pie charts are self-reported.
So that's how many people say they want their thing to count towards
Linux.
It has nothing to do with how many people actually ran anything on,
Linux, right.
So we don't really know, but what we do know, is for people who
actually purchase games at least for like, like the unity Unix numbers
or the steam Unix numbers, which is something we actually do have they
are, you know, one person less than one percent or whatever.
Right.
And so, you know that may be under account for a number of reasons,
but just right now it looks very unlikely that you're going to get a
lot of Revenue out of a Linux built.
So you pretty much have to do it straight up out of the goodness of
your heart.
And the Mac is almost the same Max, not much better, it's not just
Linux went people.
The people who buy games seem to be Windows users, that's just what
the truth.
And until that shifts, it's very hard to justify the portion of their
platforms monetarily.
You can justify them in other ways and maybe you should meaning,
maybe, maybe you should do them for other reasons.
But in terms of the specific reason of it makes money, it's really
not.
It's not
At the mental energy and it's just it's not worth it.
If you if you're in a high priced area.
Lower-priced areas the economic shift, you know, if your average
programmer makes 10 grand a year, all of a sudden pretty hard to pass
up, right?
The licks Revenue may very well be worth it all of a sudden.
So again, different locations, your company has different concerns
The size that could you stream the witness do?
You mean me playing it?
I'm going to stream some development.
So witness development things probably this week.
One of the things we'll chat about will be the witness, but I don't
know that.
I'll be streaming any playing either.
Because, what am I going to stream?
You've seen it.
Let's see here.
Let's see.
And finally long billion.
Let's change the name.
Call it steamos now is it viable?
Well cos didn't seem to do very well.
So, I don't know.
But who knows, right?
And like I said, all of these things can change.
You know, let's say for whatever reason steamos has a great Christmas
next year and everyone loves it for some reason, right?
Then it becomes viable and then you ship and then you ship a Linux
version.
Everyone will
Right.
I mean the bottom line is all Linux really needs to do if they really
want everyone to ship games on, Linux is either a make it way easier
to support the game on Linux.
So, fix all these platform issues.
So it's very reliable and very stable.
And you just, there's a very easy way to write the sound and to write
the graphics such that it never fails.
So there's no support cost, right?
Or get get, you know, show that people buy games on it, show that
there's a big bunch of money.
Sitting there to be made.
And if they did either of those two things or better yet both of
It's just, it's a foregone conclusion.
People go where the money is you don't need to convince them.
Once there's a bunch of money there, right?
And and similarly you it's not very hard to convince people if it's
really easy it's like a yeah you know it takes zero effort, here you
go, right?
And to some degree like Unity helps a lot with that, right?
Because Unity makes it pretty easy to ship a Linux version.
It's still a little bit annoying, but the support, but at least, you
know, that they are kind of doing work on your behalf to to make the
Importing less problematic, you know.
So so yeah.
All right.
I'm going to wrap that up so I can go eat dinner.
Thank you everyone for joining me.
And I will, like I said, I'll be streaming this week.
I just don't think will be do programming this week, so if you like
chatting, feel free to come back tomorrow.
Same time.
Same place.
And yeah, and we'll go from there.
Thanks everyone.
And I will, I will see you guys on the internet.