Hello everyone and welcome to handmade hero.
The show we could have complete game live on stream.
I have modified our friendly timer to work properly with the new to
our streams.
So in theory, if we're lucky day 351 here will be the first test of
the new timer.
I didn't, I literally just hacked two lines of code into it and
recompiled it and run it.
So who knows what it will do.
Anyway, I apologize for yesterday's episode having to day numbers in
it because I realized after that that I couldn't actually do that.
And the reason that I realized I couldn't do that is because the
format on handmade Hero has always been that.
There is a source code drop for every day, so that when you start on a
new day, you know, you can use the previous day's source code, and I
was like, wait, we didn't take a source drop in the middle, so we
can't have a 350 in a 351.
So I just merge the two.
So, it's from yesterday together and call the day 350, and there's a
source code drop for after day 350.
So today will be day 351 and it will be 2 hours continuous.
And there will be one source code drop.
So that's the way we're going to try it anyway so that we don't have
to stop in the middle of programming and snap a source code snapshot
and then continue or whatever else.
Right?
Doesn't seem worth it for any particular reason.
And since the stuff on, the two hour blocks, tend to go together, it
seems like it should be fine.
All right, so that's all the business.
Let's get back to what we were doing yesterday.
I think we mostly did what we wanted to do, but there were some loose
ends.
We wanted to start sort of see what it would take to multi-thread, our
sort of regional updating our game simulation, we did that.
And then there was some things that I thought were really sort of
embedded in the simulation
That probably shouldn't be embedded in the simulation because they're
very specific to choose me certain things.
That happen which don't always happen during simulation like updating
the camera and other things like that.
So we had some notes about what we wanted to investigate there.
And so for the next two hours, I'm just going to investigate those and
I'm going to see to what extent I can make that code look a little bit
more uniform and maybe pull out certain things that are kind of
Embedded in it right now that I feel like it would be better if they
if they were sort of more separated.
okay, so if you remember, we basically just have things running the
way they were running and right now, we have essentially everything is
working the way we expect but we have sort of like
See here.
If we've got it switched on.
Yeah, we have
Of like World simulation getting farmed out here.
So that multiple threads can now work on world simulation.
We are spending a fantastic amount of our time, on debug collation.
And this is kind of a problem for us.
It's definitely, you know, an issue.
I don't know if we want to take a look at that, at some point, it
occurs to me that, you know, one of the things that I decided to do
when we wrote the debug layer because we were just kind of playing
around with it, and it was interesting and I kind of want to show how
to work with some that stuff.
One of the
The things that I kind of did that I think was not very bright, is
that we kind of did a full logging system and while that's kind of a
good idea and it's interesting, the problem with it is that it then
becomes very expensive to actually work with.
You can see that like, you know, the actual amount of time that we're
spending on our game right now, even in debug mode, right?
So, this is the debug build the slowest possible, build.
Even in that mode, you know, we end up in a situation where the game
would be running at 16 at 60 frames a second just fine, right?
But this massive chunk of time, here are spent doing debug event
processing is is just really ways of Statin pretty heavily and you can
kind of see that like it's you know, it's really not that like drawing
part of this.
It's actually literally the
That's the that's the super slow part and you can understand why I
like there's 46,000 events that are getting recorded every frame,
right?
That's what that number up there is telling us and that's just a huge
amount of stuff to process at 60 frames a second.
You know, when you're up in the in the fifty thousand, things to
process at 60 frames a second, you can't just have necessarily super
Cavalier code, right?
Write your code.
Like, for example, in this case, if it's not compiled in release mode
might not be fast enough because, you know, there's just enough busy
work in the bad, debug, sort of code gen, that it's going to put you
over your budget, right?
So, you know, it's not really a cause for concern because you know,
again, it's only the debug code.
We don't really have to worry about it too much because it's like,
well, it doesn't ship in the game.
So it's never going to cause a shipping problem.
And if we do turn on optimization,
And when we run, then we don't really have as much of a problem
anymore.
But
It's still a problem, right?
And if we take a look at what's happening in thread so you can still
see like even in the in the deep in the release mode build, we're
still in a situation where yeah.
Like you know if we looked at how fast our game is running here, it's
going just fine, but this massive kind of blip here is a big problem.
I'm also kind of interested to know there's like this sort of periodic
Spamming that seems to happen there.
I'm not sure where that happened.
Exactly.
But
You can kind of see, like that's a very interesting.
That's a very interesting pattern, right?
And I'm not sure exactly what it is.
That's happening there.
I would like to see
We need to make this.
Thanks Rubble.
There it is.
So like if you take a look at this here I have no idea what happened
there which is not great, right?
Like you know when you have something like this that's like an anomaly
frame.
It's much nicer.
If you can figure out or if you have some idea of like what the actual
problem is,
And the problem is, if we drill down in here, you know there's not
going to be very much data as to what's going on because we just don't
have much marked up at this point.
So it's pretty hard to tell, like what the actual problem is there.
So, you know, that's not great and you can kind of see that in this
situation where you got all of these really long thread times here,
even in that case, like the actual other, the actual part between
begin World, change and World change is like really tiny
Right?
So, you know, it almost suggests to me that maybe people got hung up
on a mutex somehow or some, I mean, I don't really know but it's like,
it's pretty clear from this.
That we've got some issues that we probably are going to need to
figure out how to address because just looking at them here.
It's, you know, we don't even have enough information to know why we
were getting this weird flip and, you know, it's possible that this
was some kind of operating system interference.
You know, it's possible that someone jumped in here and interrupted
us, but at the same time, you know, the reason that I am not that I
wouldn't immediately jump to that conclusion.
Is that when all of our korres you know like this is quite a few
threads here, right?
1, 2 3 4 5 6 7 when all of our cores are in this sort of holding
pattern then it's you know it's less likely that the operating system
evicted our entire application out of all the cores to do something
else unless that's something else was something that needed all the
cores for some reason, right?
But you can kind of see why it's like unclear to me, you know, I mean
we're running open broadcasting system in the background for doing
this dream.
So anything, you know, who knows?
It's certainly possible that it steals a bunch of course, for work
every so often and it's not our fault.
But again, you know, without additional information, I wouldn't be
comfortable saying
Oh, don't worry about it.
It's not our fault because we don't have the information here.
Net, to necessary to actually conclude that, right?
So yeah, so that's just kind of bizarre and I'm not sure.
Yeah, I'm not sure what the deal is there.
But anyway.
Yeah.
So we've got some work to do here on the debug view stuff and in terms
of how we want to mark up our zones probably, as well.
Just in terms of what's going on.
But but anyway, just some stuff to be aware of.
So yeah, we're getting a lot of debug information sunk out there.
And I'm not really sure again, like exactly what's going on with that.
I would be interested to know why so many debug events are getting
generated and I suspect that, you know, it might just be because of
the entity block stuff that we're doing there.
One thing we could do for example in
In the entity sort of render part of things here, where we do our like
begin block, we could start getting rid of this stuff, right?
So just instead of like looking at those individual things because
that's going to open every single entity every time when we do
physics, that's going to happen.
We could start getting rid of some of these guys, right?
And then when we do sort of the debug pick entity stuff for that as
well.
Then we get rid of the debug pick entity.
In here we could just say like okay it's only going to do it if the
debuggers cut surface end of the idea.
So presumably that should generate any traffic either and I feel like
that and cut down on the events to some great do.
Well that didn't really
It would be nice to know like where most of our events are coming from
right?
Like because I don't have a good feel for it.
Let's see here.
Yeah, because I feel like a lot of these things are not going to be
called that often.
Yeah, most of these things, I don't even think should be all that
relevant.
But anyway, so and really I feel like this is just a problem in
general because I feel like that's just that's just seems like way too
many.
I feel like I'm missing something.
Oh, get World chunk internal.
Hi.
Guess what?
This is.
Should be a pretty obvious indicator for me of like what is the
problem?
So, get World chunk.
Internal is getting called a ton of times.
Okay, so that's mostly what that is, all right?
So basically like, you know, let's talk about things here.
Let's just let's just let's point out a few things, a few, a few
issues.
So
First of all, why is get World chunk?
Internal being called so often.
And the answer for that is I think are chunks.
Our world chunks are probably too tiny.
You know, I think we size them.
To be probably pretty, pretty tiny when we create the world.
Right.
And we
Can we make one of these things we pass in this chunk demand meters,
right?
And the chunk dim and meters which I assume
We have Jimmy.
There it is, it's not going to be particularly big, right Grand,
buffer width and ground.
Buffer height are kind of residuals from when we used to render these
things.
And yeah that's that's going to be really tiny, right?
I mean I guess it's not really tiny but it's not particularly big,
there's many of those prescribed so I guess we're probably calling a
tremendous number of those because you think of it we call several
deep and several wide and tall as well.
So yeah it's like probably not the best partition size.
I also since we don't actually need these anymore.
We probably want to set this in some kind of a more intelligent way,
right?
So we probably want to say like okay, you know, how many meters across
the we want one of these things to be you know, and who knows what
that is?
But let's say maybe 10 meters or something?
Is that is the chunk size?
I don't know.
We can certainly set that at our own Leisure, but in terms of how big
those chunks are, that's definitely something that we want to keep
under control because it's supposed to be our spatial partition and we
don't really want a situation where our spatial partition is actually
has.
It's so tiny that it's not actually serving.
Partition things up.
It's just like there's way too many of them, right?
Because at some point, it becomes a cost in and of itself maintaining
such small chunks and we don't want that, we want it to be a
reasonably picked size.
So, you know, we kind of have some control over how much of that is
happening, certainly.
And we can sort of try to keep that more under control as as a number
that we're concerned about, right.
and we can sort of see here, that that's, that's like a totally
That number right there is about half of what it used to be.
So, expanding it by that, much, definitely reduces the number.
However, if we think about what's happening, I guess, you know, in
truth, there's probably just going to be a lot of those chunks.
Well, we probably should do, is draw the chunks in here as well.
Like, take a look at what the the chunk grid actually looks like.
And
you know, if we were to say, let's go into some region here,
I'm trying to think of like what the easiest way to be would be to
draw them, but if we take a look at begin World, change
Here is sort of our code for looping over the chunks, that's in a Sim
region.
So, one thing we could do is have sort of a debug call that says like,
draw all of the chunks that are in this this same region.
So that would probably be something that would be good to be able to
do.
So we'd have some idea of like, where those trunks were.
And if I want to do that, do they, what I would like, is it some way
in those sort of the world code here to have a call?
That gives me back the dimensions of a world chunk.
So I can kind of know, like, hey, if I asked you here is a world
chunk, tell me what the bounds of this world chunk.
actually our that would be something that's nice to have and we don't
have that yet like we have ways and putting things into and taking
them out of chunks, but we don't have anything that's like, hey,
Get World chunk bounds or something like that, you know.
And then we would pass in you know some kind of information about the
world chunk like the chunk XY and z or something like this and
it would do this, you know, the calculations to determine
Much like this does it would do the calculations to determine, you
know, where that chunk was and return it.
So that anyone who wants to know what the bounds of a chunk, you know,
happen to be, they can get that.
So how would we compute this?
Right?
Because we've never actually had to talk about it explicitly
So what we tend to do like get World, chunk internal, right?
What we tend to do is we take these this like, X Y and Z and we just
the way that this code actually works is it doesn't even really have
the notion of a size of a chunk at all.
Anyway, like if you take a look at how this code works, it doesn't
know, it doesn't even really care.
What the size of a chunk is, you know, if you look at what these
things do, they just use the X Y and Z as sort of a ID, really?
For retrieving the data for a particular chunk at no time.
Does anyone ever care how big the chunk actually is.
So, all of this internal code just doesn't care how big the chunk is,
as far as its concerned, the person on the outside, has to know how
these things map and we're just getting in those coordinates, right?
So, really the code, we're looking at is like map into chunks face or
something like this or some similar code, like that, that has to do
with the chunk demand M, right?
Because only when we actually map coordinates into the canonical XYZ
of the chunk, is, that's the only time that we ever really take this
into account.
And the way that we're doing that currently is we're using rounding
after a divided, which means that our chunk coordinates are like
Center coordinates.
Right?
So the the center point of a chunk is where the X y&z refers to as far
as our canonicalization of position.
So that means what we would want to do is take the chunk X.
Y&z, we'd want to use those first as multipliers to put us into a
particular location.
But then, that is like, the center point of a chunk and we would
expand it by that much.
So we would have something like Chuck Center and we would love to
these
Up, like the trunk EX.
The chunk, why?
And the chunk Z we would want these to become.
A center point, right?
And we would want to multiply that Center Point, by the dim, in m to
get it to the actual location where it is, right?
So we're talking about like a hadamard product here, right?
Where we multiply each element of each vector by its neighbor.
Right, by its, by its corresponding element the other Vector.
So, the dim x times a chunk X dim light times chunk, why dim Z times
chunk, see that would move us out to the center point and then when we
want to make the the rectangle, what we would want to do is
Add sort of that chunk Tim.
Right to the center point.
But again, the chunk demand m is the entire set like a diameter and we
want to expand out from the center just by the radius in either
direction.
I don't think we have an ad diameter too.
Yeah, so what we want to do is first just have it, right?
So we just want to use half of it and then we should be able to get
whoops.
Guess we don't have a rectangular yet so we actually want rekt Center
Dim.
So I guess we've already got.
We do already have something that works, the diameter.
So then we've got a way of figuring out like where an individual chunk
is and so now in theory we should be able to draw it right inside
World mode for example where we were sort of doing our current debug
drawing, where we do like our push wrecked outline stuff, it should be
relatively straightforward for us to do something here where we sort
of say like hey get the world chunk bounds.
For some World chunk.
Let's just, we'll iterate over them later.
Let's just say the 000 chunk that's going to give us back a chunk
wrecked, and then we can go ahead and draw that chunk wrecked wherever
we want.
Right?
So we can say like, hey, you know,
Draw the bounds of this thing.
and,
I guess interestingly enough World transform because that's around the
camera P there.
We would want to sort of have this be relative to the camera baby.
I guess it doesn't really much matter how we do this, but we could say
that the offset here for example, was going to be
Get min corner.
Shun.
Correct, although I don't know how we do when we push wrecked outline?
I guess we passed the center point.
So I guess we just do like get Center.
Right.
So get World chunk bounds, needs to take the world obviously, as a
parameter.
So that seems fine.
I should probably pass a color here that makes sense.
I guess this is passing purple.
Maybe like if we've got looks like we've got yellow cyan
And purple for something.
Not exactly sure what color I want to be.
I'll make it white for now.
All right, so that's one chunks Worth, right?
And so if I come out here and I look at
I guess it's going to be one of those things where, like, you know,
it's the center of this thing.
If we take a look at how big that one rectangle is, I guess we can
kind of understand to a certain degree, why there are so many getting
pulled out, right?
Because this entire region is going to get pulled out.
So,
That's going to be something like 64 of these or something like that
and then it's five high.
So that's going to be, you know,
Something like this and then we're doing 16 of them.
So it just multiplies out, like, really quickly to very large numbers.
When we're grabbing that many world chunks, you know what I mean?
And I guess that does also mean, you know, I don't know how well we're
going to hold up, trying to do to simulate five levels down of stuff,
you know, maybe it makes more sense to just simulate one above and one
Below us or something like this, right?
I don't really know what shove those is, is more sensible, but also,
you can even see, like, we're grabbing stuff, pretty far afield here.
And so, maybe, you know, one thing that we need to do to is reconsider
our simulation bounds.
How these things are getting expanded, you know?
Maybe we only do one room in every direction and we don't get anything
sort of one further than that.
It's probably a good idea.
And the other thing too, is we probably want to align our chunk size
in some way to the actual game size, which is probably easier said
than done.
Because if you take a look at how these things work out, you know
123456789
1 2 3 4 5 6 7 8 9 10 11 12 13 14 15 16 17.
So you know 17 is a really nasty number of things to have across and I
guess we could have the world chunk just be the size of a room, you
know, because hey, we know we're going to pull in whole rooms at a
time.
So maybe that makes sense.
I don't really know.
But it's one of those things where, you know, it's, you know, we could
subdivide this into three up and down the nine but the 17 is, is not
subdivided.
Belen, any particularly clean way, right?
I mean, you can't is now really not much.
You can do about that, I could, however, just arbitrary, split
something down the middle.
But, you know, in terms of if I wanted it to sort of roughly lineup
with Tiles at all, which you'd think would be a reasonable thing to
do.
It's
not super plausible to do because the price, you know, 17 is like not
divisible by anything, right?
It's Prime so yeah, not great, not fantastic, but that's just, that's
just the way, the cookie crumbles I guess, so.
I guess what I'd say is, if we move on from there and just
Say, well.
Okay let's, let's try making the chunk size.
Maybe be roughly the size of a room.
Let's, let's see what happens if we do that.
So let's go ahead and do chunk demand M and let's just see how big our
tile size is at the moment, which I think we kind of know when we do
our work here like adding
I said, standard room.
So, let's see.
We've got, well, we've got our tile stuff where we convert tiles to
positions.
So tile side in meters, is currently set to 1.4 why we set it.
To one point four is probably lost to the the history of time now.
But about one and a half meters across is how big a tile is in our
current world.
Anyway, which is fine, right?
That's, that's totally fine.
But what that means is that if we did wanted to set it, we'd be
talking about roughly, you know, something that looks like this.
And then our world chunks would roughly align with the size of a room,
and you can kind of see that here.
And if I pull back a little bit as well,
You can see that that guy kind of buckets, all the entities, just
right?
So that that would mean that if we if we wanted to we could now kind
of try and make it so that the simulation boundary is sort of roughly
exact.
We could kind of make it so that when you do a Sim region, you just go
one of those over and then we would have, you know, 9 / simulation
we'd have nine times five floors or 45.
Chunks to pull in, which is probably a more sane thing to do.
I did leave this in, did I not?
Yeah, so yeah, I mean now seems like a reasonable time to do that
since we're looking at things from a from a room based perspective
which is something I want to do before.
So if we were going to do it that way and we were talking about how do
we wanted to expand the same region?
I think what I'd probably say here is this expansion stuff where we
say like safety margins and this sort of thing.
I think I'd probably say now's may be a good time to just, just
Just ice that stuff.
I say we just simulate a room, one rooms worth when we do updates
over, right?
And that's like maybe the responsibility of the calling code to say,
you give us the region that you want simulated and we don't try to
mess with it at all.
So at that point, we'd say, hey yeah, the you know,
The max entity radius thing is only used in here, right?
And so maybe we just say like,
Those things go away.
We don't try to do any of this stuff.
The safety margin stuff is just gone and when we do sort of the
different kind of bounds, there's there's none of that we just pull
the stuff in and we leave it aligned, right?
So we say, Okay, updatable pounds are going to be the same as regular
bounds as far as we're concerned.
So, let's go ahead and say
Some region bounds.
And the same region bounds is just going to be whatever we were told.
For now and we can always change it back if we want to.
But that's basically all we're going to do, right?
Okay, so now if we do that, what we should see at first because now,
no one is passing in anything different here.
What we should see is just that the the game is only actually pulling
in stuff that's in the actual sin bound, right?
So it's only actually pulling in stuff that's inside.
That region.
And you can see that happening here.
Now, what we don't really want to do however, is we don't, I think
alike.
Well, let me see if this is true.
As I say is I feel like we don't really want our Sim region to split
things into into like halves, like it was doing there.
So when we pass in the Sim bounds, we're going to want to pass in a
symbol and that's room aligned I think, but it seems to work.
Okay, even if we don't, which is, I guess a nice thing but I don't
think we want to be doing that.
And this will cut down the number of Road chunks that need to get
pulled in quite dramatically as well.
Which is nice.
So that's also good.
Let's go ahead and take a look.
So here we are taking a look at the Sim bound stuff, and you can see
that that just is, you know, something that we pass pass in, you can
see where we do some bounds expansion here and that's your stuff.
We don't want any of this stuff.
So what we want to do is say like, Hey, we're going to go ahead and do
it.
You can go ahead and do like one rooms worth and maybe that's a value
that we want to save from before where we sort of have a notion of
what the that region is.
So what I want to do is say, okay, if we
If we take the camera Bound in meters and say let's let's stop using
that.
I don't actually know if we want to keep that around for something we
might so I'm not going to delete it at the moment.
But let's say that the camera Bound in M stuff is not really what we
want instead.
What we want to do is take you know, a room based approach and say we
want to do three rooms by three rooms, centered around the player,
that's what we actually want to do.
So we can say like our sin bound is going to start at
Wherever the camera is centered and then we're going to expand outward
from there.
So I kind of want something that's going to be like a rectangle Center
Dim.
And I want to do like the cameras position, and then I want to do, you
know, three times screen or sorry room dimension.
And that's really all I wanted to pass down for the same bounds and
then for the Sim bounds here where we're trying to playing with the
other SIM bounds, this would be fine as well for it to use that size
and just offset it.
Right?
So you know, here's that offset where it just kind of moves it around
for our, you know, Amusement.
So that seems good to me and then I just need a way of figuring out
like where that camera actually is.
I think that
See camera rectangle at Target.
So really just the center point.
Of that camera p.m.
out of that screen.
Bounds is the center point that I want.
Rex engine overly function takes one arguments.
well, to be honest, I didn't think I was passing
One arguments, I thought I was passing to this one and this one.
Am I Wrong?
Oh, it's just because it doesn't pick up this one up.
That's fine.
So as soon as I fix that when it should be fine, so if I go to
standard room dimension,
We already kind of know what that is, right?
Because I sort of did it up here.
It's the world chunk demand M thing.
So what I can do for now she say, okay we've got
Notes and rim dimension.
And that's, you know what it is.
And we're going to want to play around with this a little bit more in
a minute here, but we should be okay.
So, let's see.
This is a V2 which I suppose is, okay.
We just need to sort of expand it out a little bit more and let's take
a look at how that's working.
That's looking pretty good.
Let's go ahead and zoom down there a little bit.
Yeah.
So that's looking pretty good but you can see where accidentally
pulling in an extra some extra chunks here, that I don't want to pull
it.
And that's probably because we're like sort of a little bit off by one
in terms of what our bounds are.
So we probably need to off by one's the wrong term, but I mean you
know, the floating Point accuracy of like pulling in these chunks.
It's probably not quite right.
So I kind of want to go in and monkey with that a little bit.
But for the most part now we're kind of getting down
To what I think is a little bit more reasonable for what we want to be
doing here.
All right, so yeah, now that we're looking at this, we're down to 3400
calls.
That's 10% less than 10% of how many we used to be doing and that's
good that just is, you know, a little bit more of a kind of a
reasonable thing to be doing there and that also means that our debug
collation is kept under control, I don't know what we'd look like in
debug mode at this point, but at least this is, you know,
Little more sane.
Yeah, so still not great in terms of what's going on here, but a lot
of it now is just packed into these functions which is, which is good,
which is what we want, right?
And so inside, do World Sim,
I feel like what's interesting about that is if you take a look at do
World Sim,
I don't think I know, like, right off the bat why that particular
function would be taking so much time.
And so I also do wonder if a lot of that is stall time and that's
something that probably we would want to take a closer look at Wright.
And, you know, this is not a particularly good way to do it, but just
to give you an example, suppose I go down here into the world mode.
Code.
That's, it's doing that world Sam and
That we have to do.
We have to look a little harder at how we're doing these locks because
this was just a quick thing to sort of get ourselves working.
When we do this ticket, mutex what we can do, if we want to is inside
the ticket.
Mutex, if we find that we
if we find that we can't get the mutex when we want it, we can
actually put something in here that's like you know,
Every time you can't take the mutex, let us know, right?
And that's going to have to be, I guess kind of down below the debug
you eye but otherwise it's fine.
And so if we run it now probably what, at least what I'm assuming
we'll see is that everyone is super stalled out.
Like you can kind of see people are just hitting that mutex all the
time and they're trying to take like they're trying to get the mutex
and they can't another way to look at.
It would probably be too instead of looking at the number of times you
go through that Loop will just be how much time do you spend in here?
Because it should be almost no time.
If you were getting the
Next when you needed the mutex, but if you can't, then you're sitting
in there a lot, right?
And so then if we take a look at the threads and we pause one of those
threads, then what we can see here is like, look at that yellow bar,
that yellow bar is how long threads are waiting in line to actually do
their work.
So all of that time, right there, just sitting there going like, hey
man, I need access to the world and they can't get it.
Right.
So
I feel like that's a really good illustration.
Just graphically speaking of why why mutexes are problematic, right?
Why you have to think through these.
Because you know, I said this when we typed in the code but I realized
that when I say something like that, it's kind of a little abstract
sometimes because it's like, well, you know, okay, he said that.
But what does he mean?
And what you can see here is like we've got 6 threads available to do
this work.
On this machine.
This machine has a lot of cores, right?
In fact, we could use even more if you weren't running obs,
And if you look at that, that means that like okay there's a lot of
course here.
And what we've done is we've essentially, you know, we've drastically
reduced the degree to which these chorus can be effective because they
all have to wait in line for this one data structure that we chose to
just lock out, right?
so, the question is,
What can we do to try and you know, alleviate this burden?
How could we make it so that these threads aren't all set?
Around waiting, for their turn.
Because if everyone has to wait for their turn, we might as well, not
have it multi-threaded at all, that makes sense.
So, let's take a look at what we could do here.
So if we go into some region and we take a look at the code here, is
begin World change.
We know that this memory arena is specific to the same region.
So we really don't have to worry about all of.
This stuff is totally multi-threaded.
Also none of this stuff actually needs to be behind a lock.
Then when we're walking through here and we're doing this sort of pull
out operation, this is the only operation that actually needs to be
locked in here.
All the rest of the stuff does not need to be locked, right?
You can kind of see all of this stuff through here is fine.
It's just these, you know, this ad block to free list and add chunk to
free list.
Stuff is is the only stuff that we need to be.
So what we could start by doing is saying well, let's
Let's let begin sim off the hook temporarily.
So let's go ahead and say we wanted to do begin Sim this way.
So we're going to ticket, mutex remove Road chunk, right?
And then we're going to say, alright?
We kind of come down through here.
You can see we do this thing where we do Adblock to free list and then
add chunk to free list.
Right now, what we like to do is we'd like to just have one
corresponding, one of these ticket mutex takers at the end, right like
so, but you look here and then we've got this Adblock to free list
thing.
This thing also,
To view text, but the question is.
Well, wait a minute.
Why are we adding things back to the free list one at a time?
Yes, that may have made sense back when we had single threaded code,
it didn't matter.
But now that we're multi-threaded, we've got this list.
We know the beginning, in the end of it, we only need to like change
the one pointer at the head and one point at the end, to insert the
whole set, right?
So why not figure out how to
add this back in on Moss, right?
So for example, we say while block here right.
What if we said this was first block?
And then said, okay, World entity block block equals first block
Process, all the blocks.
As we did.
and then,
Here, when we say adjunct to free list, right?
Maybe we can have an additional thing here which is like hey, oops.
Take the blocks to.
And we could just call this add to free list and you pass both now
again, why are we merging these two things?
They're two separate operations.
Add some, you know, two different things.
We're adding the free list.
Well, the reason is because we just want to
Reduce the degree to which we're interacting with the system because
we know that it's mutex, it's a shared system and we want to just have
one call.
We're we're like, okay.
Here's the thing.
We need to do, do all the stuff you want to do and do it as fast as
you can.
So we can get out of this mutex.
We're not going to like dilly dally, right?
Furthermore, we can help this guy out because we're walking this list,
right?
So we also know that we have a last block in addition, right?
So every time we come through here, we could say, alright, whenever we
process a block that block is the last block.
So, now, when we come through here, we can say, hey, add this chunk to
the, to the list, and also add, you know, this chain where
Telling you both sides of the chain.
So now you have the option of doing a much faster insert because you
don't have to walk the list again, right?
We already walked the list and we know where it is and better yet, we
walked it outside the mutex.
Right.
So, that's, you know, step a write a, pretty simple step that we can
take to make begin Sim, not be so onerous.
All right, so let's say we do this.
What do we need to do?
Well, the only thing we need to do is to go into our world code and do
add to free list, just has to be sort of expanded because now it's
taking two things, right?
It's taking a world chunk and it's doing that operation with it.
But then it's also taking
Like a first block.
Last block.
And previously, when we were doing ad block to free list, we did this
sort of old next equals world first free block.
And so what we want to do there is say, well let's put that on the
last block, right?
That we want to say the last block next equals the world forestry
block, right?
And we can also say, well let's make sure we actually have a list
here.
So whatever the last block of list is that'll point to our previous
first free and our first Free Will Pro point to the first block.
So that way, instead of doing it piecemeal, we're just inserting the
whole list in one go.
Hopefully, that makes some sense.
Okay, so
why is this?
Fact, we could pretty much just write this this way, now, right?
We could just write this as a, for I Loop.
Where we go.
Like that.
So I think that's really all we need to do.
Add 23 list has to be renamed, but that's about it and now let's see
if that gets us into any better shape.
So let's take a look at the profile now and let's take a look at our
threads and we pause and hey, look at how much better this is already,
right?
It's definitely a lot better.
We're not seeing oops.
We're not seeing nearly as much of those sort of long bars in there,
right?
But we still have
it looks like a little bit of that happening.
Let's take a look here.
So you can see us taking these ticket mutexes.
Most of them are fine, but you can see like a few of them, get a
little bit long in the tooth, right, where the ticket mutex is being
is being a little bit gravier, right?
That makes sense.
And so one of the interesting things about that is that look well, it
looks like up at the head end.
We spend almost no time on it.
And then sort of towards the end we spend more time.
Chances are, if we look at this, we will see that pause
Inside do world's, then we have a second time where we end up taking
this mutex and that time is is in the end World change, right?
When we go to do the end World chain stuff, we take the mutex around
that entire thing.
So we've done a good job.
Reducing These Bars quite a bit.
But then we've kind of got this sort of weird pattern here to be
honest with you.
That's a little bit suspicious I guess the problem is here we drained
out.
And so these are people who probably had actual stuff to process and
these are probably people who didn't and so now we're able to get
those times down to almost nothing so the people who don't really have
much in the way of entities process were reducing their times, so
that's good.
But let's keep pushing on that a little bit more, just so we can get
down to something before we start analyzing it in more detail.
Right.
So we've got these, these mutexes here around remove World chunk.
And so, I think the most logical thing to do here is to start saying,
well, okay, probably what we want to do is push that mutex inside.
So the person who is calling doesn't really necessarily have to think
about that very much.
So we just do.
We do the ticket inside?
Inside the call itself, right?
And then in here, when we're going through it, then same thing for add
back to the free list, which is the other thing that we do.
You make sure that happens here.
Right.
So that's all well and good.
But let's take a look at end World change, which is definitely a
little bit wonky here.
So inside and World change, this is something where we took the mutex
again the entire time.
So if we come back out to World mode,
And we take a look at here.
What's going on?
These mutex is again are things that, you know, we kind of want to.
Let's see and Sam right?
All it's doing is this and real change.
We know this isn't relevant at all.
So it's just this end World change.
It needs to be mute text.
So if we move those in here, and then start to look at what actually
hacks would have to get mu text, if we were a little bit more diligent
about it, let's find out, right?
So,
Looking in here, you can see we've got some stuff like map into
chunks.
Space junk P, it's so on.
Right, chunk Delta, updating the camera entity, all this stuff blah
blah, blah blah, right?
You can see that really the only part of it that actually, we care
about is use trunk space, use trunk space is the only thing that would
actually have to get new text here right now.
The problem with this, is that when we call use chunk space, we're
calling this for every entity, right?
So we could just mutex the one thing we need which is used chunks face
but we do kind of run a real risk here and the risk that we run is
that that's just too many takings of the mutex.
Like we're starting to just have way too much beating on that one,
mutex for this purpose.
And especially if multiple people are trying to execute these in
parallel, it's just going to bounce that cache line all around.
Then it's going to be a disaster, right?
So, let's take a look at what use chunk space does.
Curtis.
So you can see here that we do get World chunk and get World chunk, is
definitely a function that we know is going to be touching things
potentially.
If there isn't a chunk in that place already, right, because it's
going to have to do this sort of operation where we pull stuff off the
free list and that's obviously something that has to be synchronized
and then use trunk space.
Is similar right?
Use chunks face is going to have to pull blocks of energy storage off
as it goes.
So if we look at what's happening here, you can kind of see why this
is a much more problematic thing from a mutex standpoint.
Because it definitely means that we you know from the looks of it at
the start based on what we've done so far.
Um, it does seem like okay, you know, we're going to have to mutex
that thing and that's just going to get called so many times.
It's going to be bad news, right?
That's just going to be bad news.
So, don't panic yet, because actually, we can do quite a bit of stuff
to mitigate this, but I just want to kind of show you like, okay.
We've pushed it down to the lowest place that we probably can and, and
now we can run just fine in, that's good.
But we're still, I think going to see some problems, they're
withholding these mutexes, right?
And again, you can kind of see this this sort of that same sort of
pattern.
Now, we don't really know that these mutex is, are causing as much of
a problem at this point.
One of the problems is our thread view while really good at the over
level is not so good at showing us exactly how these things are
happening here.
So do World Sim begin World.
Change is happening here.
It happens a couple times that through here, and we can't see how much
time we're spending waiting on the mutex until we click down, right?
And when we click down a level, then we can actually at least see how
long we're spending on.
Begin ticket mutex and we can see that sometimes we're spending a fair
bit of time.
I begin to give me a text, but a lot of it is not really all that
problematic.
Right?
Let's take a look at end World, change.
Here's any real change.
I would imagine that what we're seeing here is just like tons of tons
and tons of ticket taking, right?
Like basically every single one of these is a tiny little rectangle
where we're taking a mutex.
And we probably can see that just by going over to clocks, you can
see, like begin ticket.
Mutex is just, you know, we're doing this a ton of times and, you
know, we're not spending that much time in it, so I guess it's not
that big of a deal.
But, you know, you can kind of see the results thereof.
Now, if we take a look at what's Happening Here.
Yeah, and World change, right is taking six percent of that time.
Begin World change, taking 17 percent.
So I don't actually know why.
Why begin World?
Change is quite so expensive.
That's kind of a little bit of a mystery if we take a look inside
their match with problems.
But so this ticket, this begin to compute X and M to commute X here.
It does not seem to be as a really all that expensive.
Which is lucky for us.
But what I was going to say is let's suppose that we did have to care
about this, is there?
Nothing we could do about it.
And the answer is no, there's plenty that we could do about it.
For example, what we could do is say, hey, when we do begin World
change up here,
Right in this code, we know that we're basically pulling a bunch of
stuff that's going to go on to a free list, right?
So when we call remove World chunk were pulling stuff data off of the,
of the world and then what we
Immediately thereafter is, we give it back to the World, by calling,
add to free list.
What that means is we have to take the mutex twice here if they can
meet X first to pull it off and then again to put it back.
Well we're about to come through here.
And do end World change and during n World change, we're going to have
to take the mutex all the time in order to put entities back into the
trunk space.
But what if instead of doing that?
We simply said, hey wait a second.
We know that we just pulled a bunch of data off.
What if we just keep those blocks around local to our thread?
And then when we call use trunk space will just pass it back in and
it'll pull off of that free list first and it won't have to take the
mutex unless it runs out.
And then we'll only have to take the mutex once at the very end when
we go to put it back when we say anything that you didn't use, but
back,
Right.
so if we want to do it that way,
Then we would have a situation where okay, up here, where we say, get
World chunk, right and we call get World, Chuck internal, and we do
this stuff, none of this stuff actually in the hash none of this stuff
actually has to be mutex too closely.
If we don't want to change the hash.
So we could also leave the world chunks in place and don't pull them
out until we actually finish.
So that all of these things could not, could could avoid be mute.
As well.
So we have a lot of options here in terms of like pushing the mutex
down a little it just I guess at this point oddly enough doesn't seem
like it cost us very much to do.
I would have expected to be honest to see that to see this ticket cost
us more, but it just doesn't seem to at the moment.
It just doesn't seem to be a big deal.
It seems to be much more costly to perform.
Our begin World change and to be honest, I'm not super sure why.
That is I guess it's just because it's the thing that actually touches
all of these entities and pulls does all the copying out.
So it's probably the thing that hits the cash, the most, or misses,
the cash, the most I should say.
That could easily be the case and then when we go to do and entity all
the stuff is already warm in the cash because we just did a bunch of
stuff with it and so maybe it just doesn't really cost very much to do
at that point.
I don't know, right?
But what you can see from the profile pretty clearly is that that's
that's definitely the case.
You know that we sort of have
That we sort of that, you know, at least as far as I can tell, we
typically just don't don't see that playing itself out very much and
world.
Just, just, just not very expensive compared to build begin World
change, and it doesn't seem like we're spending much time in those
mutexes, right?
For whatever reason.
So yeah, pretty reasonable.
And so what I assume is happening here is these are the only two World
Sim calls that actually end up having to do work, right?
The rest of them.
Just don't probably have to do very much work so they don't end up
being particularly problematic at that point.
And and so, I'm assuming to if we compile this in
Release mode.
We would be shrunk down to the point where they're where it's pretty
straightforward.
Oh no.
What happened?
We have some kind of a deadlock here.
Although, I'm not really sure why.
So here is my ticket.
Mutex, it looks like everyone is blocked on it, right?
Oh no, they're not.
Someone is in the world chunk.
Internal.
Looks like I must not looks like there must be one thing that I'm not.
Holding correctly.
So you can see that someone somehow this list has got corrupted.
This world chunk list has got corrupted and in the process of this
world chunk list getting corrupted.
We end up in a situation where somebody is now just looping through it
forever which means everyone else can't can't finish, right?
So, let's take a look.
I would suspect.
There we go.
So one thing that's true is probably we have a situation where get
World chunk is something that can only be called by remove World
chunk, right?
Like like basically get World chunk, is not really something that we
want anyone to be able to call.
I would assume except in these two circumstances where we have been
locked.
Aha,
the dangers of having two functions called the same thing.
Maybe there's something to the see people who say, no function
overloading, right?
So there's the problem right there.
See.
This was not inside the mutex, I
It to be but I accidentally put it in this wrong function.
So as a result when we called get World chunk, there we have this
problem of it would have updated it to people could have been updating
the list at the same time and off you go because yeah, because now we
have this problem where are now we have this requirement essentially
that these operations have to be done very specifically, they have to
be done behind the mutex otherwise things.
Get bad.
Right.
All right, so let's take a look at that profile.
Now again, I pause it.
So, here's our rough breakdown.
So our begin real change function still takes a long time.
So it might be interesting to sort of check, whether it is, we can see
that our begin ticket.
Mutex assuming this is relatively accurate, we're not really spending
although we have to take it a lot because we're doing it.
Every time we add an entity back in.
We don't really have too much trouble.
Stalling out in it, right?
So even though we call it a ton, it's really just not taking very much
time which is nice to know.
So that's all really good.
And, you know, most of the time in here, we're actually still spending
on render stuff.
So it's really, it's just this one begin World.
Change is really the only thing that's that's particularly expensive
for us here.
So and yeah, if we take a look at it, so that's that big green region
there.
If we take a look at it, we don't have much visibility.
Into what's actually going on in that function because we haven't
marked it up with any additional blocks there.
Because we haven't really been looking to see why it takes the time
that it takes.
So what we could do in here is sort of try to get a little bit more, I
suppose insight into what it's doing.
What I will say is inside here now, we probably want to take a look at
things at a slightly higher level and say, let's look at remove Road
chunk and and use trunk space because those are the two things that we
call.
and,
Maybe I'd back to free list.
That's another one of the things that we call, right?
Oops, I timed the wrong use chunk space again.
There we go.
I don't really know why we have two of these.
I guess we were thinking maybe if we tried to like short-circuit the
call,
But, all right.
So let's take a look.
First of all, just at the high level.
Let's take a quick look at what's going on here.
So inside, begin World change.
You can see it's still mostly all the times in there.
It's really not it's really not an issue in terms of like we just
don't see we don't see that being a problem.
Like remove Road shank and stuff, these are not
These are really not expensive.
So what what is taking the time, right?
Is it just these copies?
Let's let's see if it is.
To be honest, I don't really remember how we do our time Block.
It's been a long time.
So it looks like we can just sort of say hey, here's a block.
You can press.
To decompress.
Ends.
We don't we're not actually doing anything in here.
We're just doing the copy, but hey, let's find out if that copy is
expensive.
Because I'm curious.
So here's our profile and we do spend a fair amount of time copying
this out, but it's still not really comparable.
It's still not really nearly as much as we are spending in here.
So you know, is it, is it some other portion of it?
Let's take a look.
So let's let's maybe.
Look at a daddy to hash
So time that guy.
And then the other part we've got here is get our add brain and maybe
we can see what's happening there.
Let's see.
That would probably be in here, right?
So those are some things that we're doing, but I don't actually know
if any of them make much sense in terms of time spent.
So you can see.
Begin voting is still one of the most expensive ones.
Even if we take out the the time to do the decompress and and the time
to do the add or remove brain
It's down here.
So still pretty weird, right?
If we look at what's going on here.
I mean, entity overlaps rectangle, doesn't seem like it should be a
big deal and I don't know.
I mean if you just take a look at what's going on in here, it's a
little bit bizarre.
So I guess one thing to wonder is this, the setup code, particularly
mutt?
So, you know, maybe let's change tactics here and say, all right,
let's make sure that this part of the code is actually the part that's
taken the time.
Is it the Preamble that's somehow taken the time?
You know I'm saying, so I guess we'll do it this way.
And so we should see, you know, if we're not mistaken chunk processing
should be at the top of the list, right?
And it's not.
So that's really interesting.
That means that this part up here is is actually the part that's
taking the majority of the time.
And so, you know, the push array stuff here is doing no clear.
This push struct is doing a clear and that, you know, clear does clear
quite a bit, right?
It's clearing out this big hash-table stuff here so I don't know.
Let's push this up.
A little bit further and just say, hey, is it, is it just that clear
that's killing us?
So yeah.
I mean, if you look at what's happening there, half the time, if we
are to believe this half the time is spent in this push struct call.
Half the time.
I mean, right?
Did I miss anything there?
That looks that to me, sort of looks at least.
Like what that's saying?
So somehow this push struct.
Yeah.
It is a problem.
By the way.
I think our timer like totally failed.
Have you noticed like our timer like where is my little?
Where's the little head thing?
It ain't there.
Timer is buggy buggy timer.
Although it still thinks we're inside a session.
We'll have to take a look at it later.
Anyway, so
I guess what I would say about this is
I want to investigate that push struct a little bit more carefully and
if I kind of go into the memory Arena stuff, oops,
You know, I can could just say.
Alright, let's get.
Let's get some timing on that.
I don't know.
You tell me how much time you're spending in there.
What is the problem?
Is that too many of these?
Um yeah.
Okay.
So now that I think about it, probably if I put push size in there
with the clear, it's going to be a bit.
Let's let's do this.
Although that's still might be too many.
Probably is too many.
Yeah.
Not sure why.
It can't so when it tries to do the right here, it's getting a null.
So I think it's just running out of space.
I guess that's an interesting one though, just from having one in
there.
because I would like to know how much time that's taking
Like how many of those were calling?
Well, since I only care about timing this one, I guess what I'll do at
the moment is, I'll just go this way.
Rats will call this, you know, send, Marina.
Clear.
And then we will just use
And then we'll just know.
Okay, how much is just that one clear costing us.
Yeah, so basically like it's an even split half the time is spent
doing other stuff.
Half the time is spent just clearing that buffer.
Which is pretty crazy, right?
Yeah.
So let's start with the obvious.
Why are we clearing this buffer?
Well, the reason that we're clearing the buffer is because we need
some way of knowing whether our hash entries are filled or not, right?
I mean, that's that's fundamentally what we're trying to do here.
And so, if you take a look at what happens, we've got this, these IDs
and the entity pointer and stuff, and we've got a certain size and
identity, hashed, we're using, we could certainly
Only reduce the size of the entity hash and, you know, that would
certainly help because at the moment, if we look at how big that is, I
guess, you know, we've got the entity pointer editi IDs themselves.
I don't
How big they are?
Let's take a quick look and find out.
There we go.
So we've got a u-32 in there.
So basically, these are going to be, you know,
12, bytes long.
And so, if I take a look at how big this is going to be, it's going to
be 12 b x 4096 entries, and then it's going to be the exact same thing
12 times 4096.
Well, 12 times 4096 plus 12
12 times tips.
So it's basically got to do a 64k, clear?
Right at the moment.
So it's, you know, it's a pretty hefty clear.
I would say it does seem reasonable but I don't know that it should be
taking half the time.
I guess it's since we're not taking that much time to begin with and
it's overlapped on many threads.
I suppose that I could see why that would end up costing a fair bit of
time, but it is a little bit strange, right?
I think probably since we're at the hour mark, I'm going to take a
quick bathroom break.
Our timer should have had a little thing that was like timer thing but
yeah, you now know what we need to do.
We need to figure out a way to make this, not be so costly if we want
to take a look at why that's still taking so much time.
So, think about that.
And I will be back in a moment.
so,
I'm in an office building when I do handmade hero now obviously,
because I do it from the office instead of from home.
And so I have to walk to the bathroom and back in that time.
I thought of something.
And what I want to say is, I am going to take a quick few seconds to
look at the stream chat because I want to know did anyone else during
break?
Figure out what's actually wrong with the code?
Or not.
Anyone anyone?
Bueller.
All right, well, I don't think anyone did but that's okay.
I mean, I am the person in charge of this code.
So it is my responsibility to find the problems.
I already told you what the problem was, I already told me what the
problem was, but we collectively forgot.
We didn't forget for long because we only just typed in this code but
we still forgot.
if I'm not mistaken, we will get a very rude awakening because hey,
It's the clear that's taking the time, right?
Take client coloring 64k with taking the time.
Well, clearing 64k, today's computers do factoring.
64k not very much time to clear 64k.
Not a whole lot of time was a little suspicious, wasn't it?
So the first thing I was going to probably do is say, hey, how many
cycles should it take to clear 64k?
And let's see how far off we are from that and I suspect we're pretty
far from that but here's the rude awakening.
What happens if we put no clear in here?
Okay.
So now we're not going to do the clear.
We're going to time this and we're just call it simmering.
It Alec right.
And then immediately after the a lock, then I'm going to do the clear
right here.
Right can do the clear after the fact.
So now if it really was the clear, we would expect this to take no
time and all the time should now be pushed to the outer block, right?
I mean that's what should happen.
However, if we actually look at what does happen here?
Well I guess it's not as bad as I would have thought.
So 1.6% isn't that.
Isn't that bad?
But it's still relatively high, right?
So now let's time to clear itself.
50/50.
So now we can actually see like, okay, how much time does it take us
to do the Alec?
It's still a reasonable percentage of the time, which is the part that
I was concerned about.
I was thinking was going to be more than this.
So I guess it's not as bad as I would have thought.
And then we've got the same Arena clear, which is the separate part of
the time, right?
But if we take a look at how long that's taking to clear, in terms of
Cycles, we should at least verify first that it does that.
It is actually
That it does seem like the right amount of time for clearing, right
just to make sure that it isn't something stupid going on in there.
Okay, so the first thing that I want to verify, when we do begin World
change here, right?
I want to verify that.
This push truck is not taking too long because of a virtual Alex
situation, right?
Because one of the things that I realized when I was walking to and
from the bathroom is that if I go into World mode and we go to do
World Sim what we'll see when we do the world.
Same thing here is that nobody is using
this memory Arena until the begins him call.
So what that means is this first call here is going to be a virtual, a
lock every time.
Because remember I said we don't we shouldn't really be doing it the
way that we're doing it, right?
We shouldn't really be coming in cold.
We should just have some memory or
Sound.
Per thread that it can use, but it turns out not to be as bad as I was
thinking.
I was thinking that was going to be probably pretty bad.
But, you know, at the end of the day that 3% is not that bad.
So, you know, I guess it's less of a concern than I would have thought
that it would be, so I take it back, not such a necessary concern.
All right.
So now let's move on to the actual clear, which is this part right
here.
And again, we probably would want to get rid of this.
I mean, taking
Percent of the time to do nothing.
Essentially like it could just be zero, right?
Is not great you know we're just flushing Cycles down the the drain
for no real reason.
But let's take a look at that.
Clear.
So we're taking this clear, we know exactly how many cycles per it's
taking and you know what's interesting, we should probably print that
piece of information out because that's a really good piece of
information to have and we don't have it right now.
So let's go ahead and say, all right, you know, in the debug interface
code,
Let's see, cumulative.
Sedan.
I don't know how to spell cumulative.
George this point.
so, if we were to add to this something that printed out the cycles
per, so we could do like, you know, 502, F cycles per
So now we have the running something in there, and then I also now can
print out like, all right.
Here's the the some, right?
And here's the
So that's the total number of cycles and then here's the count.
So if I just divide the sum
By the count.
Said look like this, that would produce the number that we're actually
looking for and we want to do a safe ratio here because that number B,
b0.
Right?
I don't know if we have a yeah, we do.
So I kind of want to do like more like a safe ratio 0 here.
And I kind of need this to be.
That's 64.
So we might have to go ahead and let you know.
I I don't want this count numbers to be too high for this.
So, I just want to make sure I can still call this.
All right.
So, let's take a look.
Now if we can add, how much time that's actually taking so here, I'll
pause and then to take a look at this.
So you can see it tells me how many cycles.
Each course that needs to be, I can't really read that particularly
well.
So I kind of want that to be offset from the cursor a little bit.
So maybe I want to do something more like this.
And so if I come in here, now I can see how many cycles for some
Marina.
Clear.
so, if you take a look at how many cycles that's taking that's about
five hundred thousand Cycles,
So if we go in here, and in fact, I'll I'll just stop right on that
call.
So if I was to say hey how big is a Sim region?
So we're taking 70,000 B is how big this thing is and we're basically
saying like well we've got around 500 thousand Cycles, to clear it,
that's sort of seeing that it's taking a seven cycles of B to clear.
Right, that's almost that's like one cycle per bit.
To clear.
Certainly we could do better than that.
Even at this size I think, because, you know, these are, these are
clears, their non-temporal kind of, they're not, they don't even need
to read the cache line in during it's not read modify write.
It's like, right only.
So it's literally just plowing out the entire cache line.
And I'm not really sure why
It would be taking that long.
To clear.
I should not think that that would have been even remotely close to
the total amount of clear time.
So I don't know why that is.
Let's take a look really quickly at just what is the Assembly
Language?
Look like because it should just be like a rep and it does look like
it is so I'm just that's
And a bizarre to me that that that rep is taking that long to do, it's
clear, right?
Because that's this is the entire, that's it right there.
I mean that's the clear that's the entirety of the clear is just this
one Assembly Language instruction, right?
And that Assembly Language instruction is a repeating instruction.
That's micro coated to just
clear as big as you told it.
It really does seem.
Like that should be faster.
I'm not sure why it's not.
And I guess you know without really looking into it more deeply, I'm
not sure.
I could really figure out necessarily what that would be.
I mean I suppose we could just check like quickly a few small things
like for example,
I could say.
All right, you know, let's go in here to sim region.
And we've got this clear.
Let's say we did a no clear and we asked for a particular alignment,
right?
So inside memory Arena.
If we asked for, oops, not a ling.
If we ask for aniline, no clear.
And we aligned it to 16 byte boundary, right?
So now I would expect that that would not change the rep because I
think the rep is micro coded properly.
I wouldn't think that the rep would care about the alignment, but
let's just make sure.
So you can still it's still taking about five hundred thousand Cycles
to clear.
So then let's say, okay, we got the aligned no clear, let's go ahead
and take the size of this.
And we'll just say, okay, we're getting back one of these same
regions.
Oops.
We're going to get back one of these some regions we'd like to know
how big it is and we'd like to do like a divided so that we're only
going to look at in terms of 16, byte chunks.
Right.
So we'll say okay, do the Divide find out how many 16 by chunks there
are and then instead of calling zero struct and having it, do a rep
stas on there, will actually just clear it ourselves.
So we'll say, all right,
Let's do, mmm.
Store.
And will do.
Mmm store.
To just right you know Cindy registers out to clear this thing one
after the other.
So
Something like this.
Makes sense.
Again, not doing this for any reason other than I want to make sure
there's nothing bizarre here.
Oops gotta put a nice - in there.
I just want to make sure that nothing weird is going on and that like
you know the clear isn't somehow busted or whatever.
So yeah so you can see that that's that's a marina clear is is no
faster which is what I wanted to verify.
So like the Reps tasbeeh is doing what it can do.
No, no weirdness, no funny business there.
So that's at least reassuring.
That's good to know.
So now, we can sort of say, alright, the clear is as fast as the clear
is.
Let's go ahead and see if we can minimize the memory footprint for
this thing in some way that's going to that's, you know, going to make
it not so crazy.
All right.
so, first things first, if we take a look at what's going on with the
entity hash in the first place, when we actually add an entity to the
hash,
let's take a look at get hash by ADI there.
So if we look at these, are our two sort of half situations, we've got
hash for the brains and a hash, for the end of these.
What's happening there is we're looking at the probe and each time we
look through it, we're looking to see what the index value is.
But we never care what the pointer is, right.
The pointer is just something that ends up getting used.
As like a separate in a sort of separate pass, right?
So we've got these things bundled together, and we have to clear them
as a result.
But really, the only thing we would have needed to clear, was the
index entry, right?
That's the only thing we would actually need to clear their.
So, you know, that's kind of a, that's kind of an obvious place for us
to do, an improvement, is to remove the entity pointer from here.
And to have the entity pointer stored in like some kind of a sideband,
right?
So the end of the pointer stored somewhere else.
The other thing we could do, if we wanted to was we could actually
instead of using an entity ID,
as the cleared or not, sort of indicator, what we could also do is say
what if we just had some other way of indicating whether something was
in this Lane of the hash lat,
Or not.
So that instead of checking like index dot value like we're doing
here, we actually checked it in some totally different way like
looking into a bit field, right?
Because that would be another way to dramatically reduce the clear
amount.
Because then we would only have to clear, you know, we'd be going from
Quick clearing 12 bytes per entry to be clearing one bit per entry.
Right?
And so you know if you're thinking about 12,
B versus one bit.
It would be 96 times faster, perhaps, right?
Which hey, that's a good speed up.
So let's take a look at what happens when we want to do get hash form
ID.
Let's take a look at where that's actually going to be used and how
that's actually getting used.
So, in get entity by ID.
It looks like get our add brain and add any to the hash, they're all
kind of doing.
Relatively straightforward stuff.
So in pretty much the only case is a Danity the hash that actually
needs to do something to the audition process.
So we should be able to like again make this work in a sort of more,
we should be able to make this work in a more reasonable way.
So let's see here.
Get her ad brain.
Just uses this hash operation directly, so we could choose to weld
that one directly in.
Right?
So maybe that's the best way to start.
Hard to say.
Here's what I think I want to do.
So we'll take the entity hash bit here and let's just say that we're
going to go ahead and do this with with a bit field.
So, if we wanted to do this with a bit field, maybe we do like 64 bits
at a time.
And we just say, like entity hash occupancy,
Right?
And then we would just say well, however, big
This thing is, and I guess we could just make this a pound of fines.
Probably, the easiest way to do it.
However, big.
This thing is, we're going to say that if we have 4096 these, we're
going to divide it by 64 bits per per thing.
So that's how many entries we need in that.
In that array, right?
And similarly, we have like the brain hash occupancy and the Brain.
Hash occupancy is 256 of those divided out, right?
And if we did this and we made it work with those then what would
happen is when we're inside the same region and we're doing like the
zero struct calls.
Instead of having to climb the clearer, the wholesome region, which we
don't actually need to do anymore.
We can choose to clear just those occupancy entries, right?
So in that case, that means, since all the rest of this stuff is, is
already updated.
We would only have to clear like the null entity.
Because we would want that to be cleared.
Obviously we would clear the the entry at the end of the hash
occupants say and we would clear that brain hash occupancy, right?
But that's all we would actually need to clear.
The rest of the stuff could remain no cleared and you know wouldn't
affect us at all.
So then all we need to do is actually have a way of using that.
So when we call get hash from ID here, in this case for Adam to Hash
this would have to mark it, right?
So what I think we want to do is have these hash operating functions.
I think the hash operating functions should return instead of
returning a pointer, like they were doing before to the end to the
entity hash
Well, I guess they can still do that.
Actually it's just anyone who's actually going to use it to Mark, has
to like say like Mark or or, you know, Mark occupied or something,
right?
It just has to be able to say after the fact.
Like, hey, there's a mark occupied thing here that you have to do.
And so that's how we're going to know that.
A particular thing is occupied, right?
And similarly like if we go down to the the brain function here,
where's that at?
Around brain, when we go to add this thing in here, we have to do Mark
occupied on the hash, right?
So in either case, we always have to say like hey you know the thing
the thing has to be marked as occupied afterwards.
So then we just change up how these things are working so now we have
to have a thing that's like you know
Mark occupied.
It takes an entity hash
It's going to have to sim region as well.
And so then what we have to do just say well, alright, we've got an
index.
The index is going to be whatever the entry is - The Entity hash.
Right?
That's the one we're talking about and then we just have to figure out
which entry we are in The Entity hash occupancy.
So we would say, like, okay, that index / the bits per entry, right?
Is going to be, which one it's in.
So this is going to be like the OCH index.
Right?
So I'm just trying to figure out where we are in the bit pattern and
then,
Addition, I would need to know the bit index and the bit index is just
going to be that Arc index time 64 again - the original, right?
The other way to look at it is it's really just the index mod 64,
right?
It's whatever.
The end since that's a power of two, it could turn that into a clean
operation.
That's not an actual divided as well if it wants to, right.
So hey now I know the bit index of the ah, conducts all I have to do
to Mark.
Something occupied is say that the entity hash occupants say, right at
that index is going to we're going to or in whatever B corresponds to
that entry, right?
And that's it.
so really all we have to do their say, okay, let's say we've got
An array and an index.
This code is exactly the same no matter what we do, right?
So then we can say, Mark occupied is just pay Mark the spit off.
Here is the array.
Here's the index.
So now we have one that can be done in either fashion so there's the
brain hash
One as well.
Right.
Okay.
And of course, the weird thing is.
So in these circumstances, it assumes that it's 32-bit integers.
And this case, that's not what we want.
We want to make sure that this thing is like a long value, if that
makes sense.
We can also do it this way.
Just to make sure that it knows that makes sense.
So yeah, so we're almost there.
The only thing we have to do now is we just have to make sure.
Oops, we just have to make sure that when we actually go to do our
hash lookups we now have to check those bits as well.
So we now know like okay here's what the hash index is.
So really, all we have to do is say
If this thing is, occupied is no longer a check on the hash itself.
Because that value is not going to be initialized at all right?
So we have to do is say if it's not like we basically have to have an
is empty call, right?
And that is empty, call is just going to take whichever and you know,
are a we're talking about so entity hash occupancy, and then it's
going to take the index into the hash right?
Which would be this
Yeah, I'm saying and and that's really it.
So in both cases that's all we would really have to do is just you
know check to see if it's empty by using the the alternative look up.
rather than
rather than checking that pointer.
And so this is exactly the same operation we were doing before, right?
So before we had Mark bit and now we just have is empty and it's the
exact same thing only instead.
Now this instead of setting a bit in there, we're just going to say
that we want to know if the bit
Is that right?
So if the bit is set, then we're good to go.
What is the problem is not a myth?
That's true.
Wrong pointer.
so that's it for that and of course we don't know if we actually
getting this properly but so this assertion here is not going to work
obviously, because we don't clear that anymore we used to so we can if
we want to do like an assert is empty on
The index here, right?
So we could say like, oh yeah, you know.
Let's subtract those two out.
And let's, let's let's do the match there and did I do that.
Subtraction right here?
I did right.
I think.
Yeah.
Cannot convert argument one from some region to you 6450 fuckin say,
there we go.
So I can still do that assertion.
I just have to assert on the occupancy list and off we go.
All right, so this is not what we want to see, right?
This is saying that, that bit actually is set which is no good.
What?
I don't know, me, see here, she has a chance, occupancy and entry.
So the entry we're getting back, here is zero.
so, it looks like
looks like I messed something up.
Let's see.
So
the only way we'd get back 0 is if we scan through all of these and
there was literally no space available, right?
so really, you know, in theory, this should be
Cert that result is not zero.
Because if salt result is 0, that's just bad.
So there we can see that that's bad.
So is empty.
In this case is a case where obviously not doing this operation
correctly and
it's because this is backwards.
So what we want to do is know if this bit is not set, right?
Because we want the bit to be clean.
So really we're just looking at like, you know, that that we're
looking at an and not that makes sense.
All right, so we still got problems here, although I would like to for
debugging this, I'd like to plug it in if possible.
I'd like to debug it in debug mode because right now we're still in
Here.
Optimize mode, we go.
All right, so let's take a look at what's going on here because we
probably should step through that code.
And just make sure that it's doing everything reasonably before I get
too far down the debugging path.
But
Head is zero.
Whereas the body is something.
So technically this code really should be switching on the head.
So that's actually kind of a bug in this code but because we've got
it, I think that's good because we probably want to debug why it's not
finding that guy.
So let's take a quick look at why that's going on here.
So let's see, we look at what our hash value is.
And we're looking to see if those are empty.
By looking inside the package.
I think that looks pretty good to me.
We look at for our for whatever our index is come back as
We are looking to see whether or not the array.
At that location.
That still looks pretty reasonable for marking something is occupied.
We're marking the bit.
That's represented by the entry offset.
So here's one thing that's kind of nasty about this is that these
aren't well these aren't these are actually I guess based off of the
same base pointer so that's supposed to technically work and C as
well.
I believe.
So I think even that index computation should be safe.
so yeah, that all looks pretty reasonable to me, actually
So let me take a quick look here at add into two.
Hash here is something that I want to try.
I'm just going to say,
can we validate the hash a little bit here?
So interestingly enough like validating that hash appears to validate
properly?
Meaning we can actually verify that if we ask for the thing twice we
actually get back.
What we were expecting if that makes sense.
Hey this is the timer sort of did work it just for some reason the
little dude went away little corner window thing.
We'll just see what I don't really remember what keeps that thing up.
so, we'll have to check, but
if we take a look at the code for adding 82 hash are and I stop
At that location.
If I come through here,
It's the very first time it hits the hash so it should get out.
Exactly.
Let's see the hash index.
In this case happens to be 7 which is interesting.
So let's see here.
Hash value is 7 as well so it's going to put this guy in there at the
at location 7 and
And that looks like it's exactly what we think it should be.
So that seems like a pretty good start.
We can validate the hash, even a little bit more.
Let's validate the brain hash as well because I guess the brain could
also be part of it.
But here's, let's also save the test Centre pointer equals entry
pointer.
Well, if they're both equal to same thing, we know that.
So I guess really all I'm trying to do is verify that points to the
entity itself.
Right?
But I assume that's always going to succeed as well.
Yeah.
All right, so let's test the brain out.
So that when we do get a red brain, let's see how that works.
We get the hash here we are going to return that hash pointer.
If we do not have a pointer in there, will say okay, put it in.
So brains a Cool Spring count, right record that in there.
The hash pointer is going to be set to what we
It to be pointing to.
Questions.
So,
So, wait a minute, this is a bug.
Whoever nobody ever sets this brain ID.
Right.
So I think this was just a bug that we uncovered that happened to not
be a problem before, but that brain ID was is what's getting used
there and that's never getting checked.
Now why we needed?
I don't know because the pointer would tell us the ID.
We could just look through at the ID.
For verification but that's messed up.
So this really should have said right?
Hash ID equals ID so that's probably what the bug is and we just
uncovered one that was in there the whole time, right?
So that that's busted, that was, that's totally busted.
All right.
So
So yeah, that's that's real weird.
That is very strange that we never noticed that problem before, but
that's definitely the case.
Now it does seem like I don't really know why we would need these in
there because like I said, you can look through to the entity pointer
and find out what its index is.
So I kind of feel like these in fact there's a few right next to them,
which is why are we storing them in the hash?
And I don't know.
So it kind of feels like those should probably just go away.
How to avoid having that problem.
So, I feel like what we want to do here is now that we have that empty
concept, but we can't say is like, okay the entry instead of looking
at the index value, just look at the pointer and then see if the ID
matches, right?
And then the same thing would be here to here, right?
So we just say pointer and look
and that seems like probably the right thing to do.
And that'd be better.
Now, we still have obvious problems here.
Like, like our brains are still not working properly, so we definitely
didn't quite do it.
We're in a very bizarre sort of pattern there, but at least we're
getting a little closer.
So, now, at this point, I just need to figure out
Is there any?
They're problem that we introduced when doing brains.
All right, so we're clearing out our hash occupancies.
So that's good.
And we're clearing out our null in 2D.
So that's good as well.
And then I don't think any of these things need to be cleared.
So because they are all getting set.
So, I'm pretty sure everything else should be okay.
And actually if we look at this to, you can see that we've
successfully solved the problem that we had as well, which is that if
we look at how long it's taking to do are clear now it's negligible.
So just by switching to the occupancy to something that we could
clear.
Quickly, we completely eliminated that 13% hit that we had.
And now begin World changes is actually much lower down on the profile
as well.
And this is in debug compile.
So that's, that's the clear in debug, not even the optimized, clear.
So that's all good news, but we but we're still sort of having a weird
sort of problem, in terms of assigning things to brain.
So I'm not we haven't really quite finished yet but it is time for the
Q&A.
So I don't know, we may have to leave that as an exercise for the next
time, unless we can find it relatively quickly.
So, I'll take a quick look, just to see whether it's obvious what the
problem is, before we debug it much further, but
yeah, but
but that's just the way that is.
All right.
So what's interesting about this Behavior pattern here that we can
kind of see, which is interesting, is that we do get one?
Brain is worth of work sometimes, right?
So when I run this thing, oh, this is interesting, even more
interesting.
So sometimes you do, and sometimes you don't write.
So it's like something weird is happening.
Like there, that that brain update worked, but the rest of the brain
updates don't work, right?
And that's particularly, you know, like that's just really weird,
right?
So something about finding the brains is very touchy.
You know, who knows what's going on with it?
But something weird.
And so when we call get a red brain here and we passed the brain IDs
through, we must be doing something odd.
So maybe let's verify this a little bit.
So
here's the get hash from ID for our brain stuff.
And I guess it's a little premature.
Sure for me to say that it's definitely in the brain code, right?
That's just that was just that's really more of a hunch than anything
else but we compute those hash into season.
We do the is empty on each of those and then we're asking for the
storage index thing where we check against the storage index value.
We're just looking at the the ID of the pointed to brain, right?
So if it's empty, it'll never check that if it's not empty, if it's
been marked as occupied, then it's going to go ahead and do that much.
Right now, are we, I guess we should check to make sure that Mark
occupied is working properly.
So, here is our Mark.
I cried for the brain.
Hash, we're subtracting it away and we're using the brain occupancy
table for it.
And that is, I think roughly what we want to do.
If we take a look at the brain, not hash occupancy, it is lined up
properly with the brain hash itself.
So presumably, that should be pretty safe.
But you know again, who knows?
So let's double check here will do.
An assertion.
On a couple things will sort that will cert that is empty is correct.
So we want to make sure that our brain cash occupancy, for whatever
the the hash indexes here is correct.
So that would be hash - same region, rain hash, right?
So now we can at least assert that that we never try to fill something
that was already filled, that's good.
When we mark it occupied we could do the opposite.
So, is marking this as being filled as well.
So I'm just not sure what what the problem is that we're having, as
far as being able to resolve those IDs, when we create a new brain, we
are storing the ID and the type in there, which is what we want.
But you know what, probably we need to clear this.
Probably, we do need to clear this actually.
now, that I think about it because our brains
In fact that's probably the entirety of it.
So our brains look like this, they need to know whether their slots
are filled or not.
So at the point where we actually go to use this, we would have to
clear out the brain itself.
How was that working before?
It just seems like even that should not have been working before
without a clear, right?
Because if you want to look what's in a given slot, when is that even
getting clear?
Do we clear it down here?
And I mean, because I assume that when we push the brain ID, when we
grab out the brain ideas, you can kind of see here is, we're getting,
you know, we're getting the brain ideas out and then we're putting
something in there.
That's something that we're putting in there though.
If we if there wasn't something to put in there, how do we even know?
So it's a little bit crazy.
Right?
That those brains are not ever getting cleared.
It's just a little bit weird so I want to see hold on one second.
I want to see what happens if we clear these first.
So that's still not a problem.
I don't assume that that's not a problem.
Because now that I think about it, a lot of this memory is going to be
cleared anyway because we're not recycling it.
So it's coming from a zero pool, probably, because it comes from
virtual a lock.
So that's probably the only reason that's working though.
I'm kind of surprised that that was working before because you should
end up getting just garbage values in there.
Basically, and I think we were probably just getting lucky.
So when you come through here, right, it probably really.
That needed to happen.
Anytime you push one of those brains on but that's not the only
problem that we're having right, we're still not getting our brains
are not actually in stuff and we're getting sort of weird behavior and
in here as well.
Right.
Just really weird.
So, something is still up.
Something is is still
In a weird State and what I might want to do as well here.
Say hey why don't we check to make sure we're getting we're not doing
something bad, we added this code specifically for this purpose.
So I want to just check to make sure we don't have some bad memories
situation going on.
So what I'm going to do is say like okay let's check for overflows
here and are precise.
Let's just turn on overflow.
Checking everywhere, does anyone have any?
So we don't seem to be having any overflow problems at the moment, so
that's good.
What we do seem to be have not again is a block that's not closed or
something like that.
Just disappear.
Pierce.
So, I don't know how to come back from that.
I just have to kind of wait for Windows to decide that it's going to
suspend my process.
And we can just sit here and definitely, I suppose, and cross our
fingers.
Oh boy.
There we go.
All right.
So yeah, thankfully it eventually seems to have returned to normal.
Sort of.
The question is, can anyone actually hear me at this point?
I think they can I hope they can.
So yeah what we do know from that also is that our our memory block
situation is kind of bizarre.
So something is not getting closed or something like this.
I'm not really sure.
We're going to have to take a little bit, look at it and I'm
intrigued.
So I'm going to go ahead and look
Turning on overflow checking, we should probably have something in
there to catch the fact that if we have a memory leak it will go
forever.
Right?
It'll just keep allocating memory from the system and because the
arena allocator is in there, it'll just sort of multiply ad infinitum.
Good news is we didn't seem to have any overflows but we definitely do
have something bizarre happening with the the memory allocation in the
same region, probably in the debug.
Stuff, right?
But yeah, I'm not sure who it is.
That's doing that, I'm not sure who is unmatched there, but we're
definitely having a thing where there's some kind of weird mismatch of
open and closed blocks or something, because we get this sort of weird
misalignment.
that we definitely see showing it up, even
you know, if we just run the program normally
In fact here you can see it.
It just keeps getting more and more.
Sort of like it just keeps allocating more and more and presumably,
that's inside the debug stuff.
But again, yeah, I have no idea who is who is responsible for that and
we don't know which
Elements are responsible.
This like we don't really have a good way at the moment of tracking
when something is, you know, opened and not closed or something else
similar like that.
So I'm not sure how to go about tracking that down at the moment.
We don't have really any tools for it like at all and and so that's
kind of a bummer that we don't have any really good way to deal with
that.
So let's start with some Basics stuff here.
Let's suppose that I turned back on clearing for the same region, just
temporarily to see if there's any change.
So,
Something about the Sim region itself.
There's something in here that we had to clear that we were not
clearing, right?
so,
either the hashes themselves or the hash occupancy is not getting
cleared.
sufficiently, but the hash occupancy would seem to have to
But we now know that not clearing this Sim region is not sufficient.
Like if we don't clear it we get memory.
Use that is unbounded and bad behavior.
If we do clear it we don't.
So the question is, why are we having that problem, right?
What is getting cleared in the same region that we actually care
about?
If we look through here, we initialize world, we initialize origin
bounds
Updatable bounds, The Entity counts, right?
All get set the brains Get Set Max frankamp.
Brain, count brains all these get set
So it's really just the pointers in the entity hashes that presumably
aren't getting cleared.
So I guess let's start by saying well okay is that really the case?
Is it just that we need to clear the stuff that's been The Entity hash
first.
So it's clear that we need to, we need to be able to actually clear
those things.
Why do they need to be cleared?
Right?
What is the point of throwing them?
And so the first thing to look at I guess is when does anyone actually
ever do anything else?
So if we call get entity by ID here, we get back to Centre.
I suppose the thing well I suppose this is probably it right?
When we say get entity by ID this is probably return.
earning an entry even like
that entry pointer might be an old pointer from a previous frame or
something.
If it hasn't been cleared out because we're not checking the occupancy
here, right?
When we do get, when we get the brain, we're always doing add or
create brain, that's actually looking at the occupancy.
Well, actually, no, even that's not looking at the occupancy.
So when we call that get hash by that, get hash from ID.
We're not actually checking to see whether that thing is occupied or
not.
You know, that just wasn't something that we were doing.
So, I suppose, what we could say there is well, when we actually go to
see if the thing is empty, we could clear it.
So we could say, like, you know, if this thing is empty, then result
equals entry and result pointer equals 0, right?
And then
then say else if
You know.
Storage value is actually valid so we could do it that way and
maintain our previous Behavior.
Meaning we clear when we encounter an empty version right?
If that makes sense.
We could do that.
I'm not sure if that's the smartest thing to do, but we could start
there and then next episode deal with it a little bit further.
So yeah.
So that's obviously just that was just sort of a stupid thing on our
part.
We probably should have realized that that wasn't going to be
sufficient because the way we're checking it but we can clean that up
pretty easily and then be fine.
I think.
All right.
So, you know, now we're at least not doing any of those clears anymore
and if we go ahead and run this here, let's take a quick look at the
profile.
So if we take a look at the profile here in debug mode, we can kind of
see that exactly what we want to have happening is happening.
Let's go ahead and switch to the to the debug.
I mean the optimized build.
There we go.
And if I run this guy and we take a look at our profile now and we
pause.
So now we're in a situation where?
Yeah.
Okay.
So at least that we moved like some of that stuff out the SIM Arina.
Alex probably should be lower still.
And we forced some of that clearing into identity to Hash.
So we kind of We There is work, we probably want to do to maybe make
this a little bit more efficient, but we've at least gotten it down to
the fact where now it's mostly just the entity copying probably.
That's really an issue.
And that's good for us, right?
That's a, that's that's what we want.
All right, so now I can go to some Q&A.
Is the stream down though?
It doesn't look like the stream is down.
It doesn't think the stream is down, but I guess that doesn't mean the
stream is actually down.
But I guess I don't really know any way of doing that.
I suppose people can't ask questions if they didn't get a chance to
actually see it.
But who knows?
Well I guess we will just wrap it up since the stream apparently.
When the memory thing went down I guess the stream on Twitch
permanently disconnected and there's not much I can really do about
that.
Unfortunately I don't think there's any way of sort of
Let's see if that works.
Maybe it will, or maybe it won't.
So it looks like what happened and I'm not sure why is OBS just
decided to stop streaming even though it was still going and didn't
drop any frames.
So I think maybe in a because of the fact that when you, when it's
under memory pressure, it just freaks out.
It may be just stop streaming.
I'm not sure.
But anyway, you guys will have to go.
I guess, watch the, the YouTube post to find out what happened.
I don't want to spoil the surprise.
But I'll still take questions on the first part.
Of the Stream.
And yes, I did fix the bug.
Sorry, we're all good now.
There's a to do in zero size.
I'm not sure if you noticed it.
There it is.
Yeah.
So I feel like we kind of did verify that this is the case, so we can
actually eliminate doubt, it does turn into a rep so that's good.
The bug was just that there was still people inside so I can show you
what the bug was.
So the bug was just that there are still people who were just using
the entity pointer to see whether or not there was anyone in the hash,
they'd get back a hash ID and they just feel our get back hash, and be
like, oh, there's a pointer that it must be valid, which is totally
not true.
So, what we, what I did is I just made it temporarily be that when you
do get hash,
From ID, it does do the clear when it returns someone to you so that
this will still work, but what I probably will want to do long-term is
make it so that this is a faster thing in general.
So that you just, you know, when it does get entity, by D, it returns
like get Hashem ID returns, like a Bool that says, whether it was
found or not, that makes sense.
We should have something built into the build script that won't let
you compile.
The stream has gone down.
Is this possible do in a batch script?
Yeah, I mean it's not possible to do in a batch script in the sense
that obviously there's no command in dose for that, but you could
create your own function, but your own executable that did that check,
and then call the executable from the batch.
I'm personally, I wouldn't spend any time on that because the number
of times the stream has gone down in 350 streams has been like three.
So spending any time trying to prevent that from happening, seems like
sort of a waste of time if that makes sense.
All right, looks like there's no question.
So I'm just going to leave a note here.
Which is like check.
So yeah.
I'm just max.
Is it an option to never clear 20 for Arenas and maybe only clear when
resetting temporary memory?
yeah, so what we could do for example, if we, if we wanted to sort of
make zero, clearing more of a like, first class citizen, we probably
could do something like
assume that everything in the arena is zero, because we know that the
first time we get stuff from Arena, it will be 0 because virtual Alec
will return 0 and pages.
And then whenever we get rid of a page if we recycle the page, we
clear it otherwise we just never clear.
Because we'd always know that anything we got was clear.
I mean you could do that.
I don't think that's a really necessarily a good way to go.
Just because like if you think about what happens let's suppose
sometimes you end up doing some, maybe you're doing some image
processing or something and then you allocate you know 8 megabytes on
an in an arena that you didn't need to be cleared.
Well now it's going to think it needed to clear that stuff, right?
So I think it usually is better to just like, have the Arena's do,
what they do, where they may be default to clear a
All To Not Claire doesn't matter but having the code that uses them
know and specify when it needs things cleared in when it doesn't.
And it just clear it at that time, I don't know that there's a lot you
can do beyond that in terms of making things.
Efficient
It's certainly something you could explore but I don't know that
there's a lot to, I don't know if there's a lot, you can do
systemically there.
I think you kind of need to know Tate.
Pretty much all the time.
What did you whether you want things, clear or not?
so,
and you know what else I should probably do before we sign off your
actually let me go ahead and
Closest town is.
Why did the little why did the little head like the window for the
webcam thing?
Why did that go away?
I'll be honest, I don't really know.
What determines that thing.
So that thing kind of down window this code is just kind of random so
I don't I don't really know very much about, I don't remember anything
about it works.
so, it looks like
In theory, anyway, the target window should only fade out when the
target is not active.
And the target acted, the, the target active should have been true.
So, I'm not sure why we were getting that like, the Fate.
It should have been calling this target.
Active shouldn't have been false until
Until this line was true, which is the QA h plus however long the
queue a minute, it minutes are until we went into that minute is when
it should have set to false and that, you know.
That should be two hours after start and it popped it up correctly.
So I don't really know what happened there.
I don't know, we'll have to see if it.
if it happens again, or if it's an anomaly,
Cuz I have noticed that it's happened occasionally before.
So yeah, I'll have to keep an eye on it.
SF Gartner, is there still a benefit to using the same region since
since chunks are as room-sized and simulation is room based why not
use chunks directly?
The answer is because chunks don't actually have the data in them you
need for stimulation.
So the reason that we have the same region has nothing to do with the
with the spatial aspect of what's being simulated.
It's because we need to put everything into a single
A single coordinate system for simulation and because we want the
ability to compress our entity storage when entities get very large
when the set of things that can be true about any of these gets large,
right?
So the fact that we are aligned to rooms and the chunks are room size.
Doesn't really like the size of the chunks has no bearing on whether
the same regions necessary or not.
Might be the way to
It because the world structure is just there to to stream entities in
and out and it can store them.
However, it wants chunks size.
They could they could even not be chunked, it just needs a way of
saying, hey, here's a region of space.
I need to pull all the entities out and put them into a single
coordinate system for simulation.
So, that's what the Sim Regents for.
And furthermore, that decompression step right now is just a copy
because we don't want to bother with
with it until we're ready.
But further down the line that's going to be a actual significant
operation.
Meaning, we're going to have these fairly large entity structures, you
know, 4K / entity, or something like that.
And we're only going to be storing out, you know, a tenth of that or
something as the actual information for an entity and so that that
step is going to be important as well.
So there is
We're going to really be any way to simulate things inside the
compressed chunk version and so we don't want to structure the code
around doing that.
We always want to do.
Like a pullout Sim put back.
All right, I don't know why.
This is up.
There we go.
I'm going to wrap it up.
Thank you everyone for joining me.
For another episode of handmade here.
It's going to
Recruiting with you.
As always, if you would like to follow along series at home, you can
always pre-order the game on handmade hero dot-org.
It is the easiest way to get, like the source code and play around
with it.
We also have a forum site, you can go to.
If you want to ask questions a patreon page, want support our video
series, a schedule bot the tweets, the schedule that you.
So if you want to know when we're going to be live, that's the way to
do it and we have an episode guide, if you want to catch up on past
episodes, that's about
It for today.
I will be, it'll probably be two weeks till the next time a hero,
because next week is handmade calm.
So, if you haven't already gotten your tickets to handmade con, there
are a few left but really it's probably too late if you're not in
Seattle because you'd have to buy a plane ticket I guess.
But I think there still are about 15 tickets left remaining to
handmade Khan and so if you do
Want a last-minute ticket, you can get one, I don't suspect, you will
sell out because like I said, I think almost everyone who was planning
to come probably had to plan ahead of time to get one, but that's this
coming weekend.
So definitely check that out.
And and hopefully, I'll see a lot of you folks.
There will then be back the following weekend with the next actual
episodes of handmade hero until then have fun programming everyone.
And I will see
see you on the internet.
Take it easy.