Hello, everyone, and welcome to handmade hero show.
Rico to complete game live on Twitch.
No engines, no libraries.
And right now, we're doing some optimization work.
This is the first time we've done optimization work on handmade hero.
It's going really well.
The stream was yesterday, we, you know, on the schedule, it's the
first time we've ever done a Thursday stream and then a Saturday
stream here today.
But that's because I was speaking at a conference yesterday.
A lot of people.
So I
Didn't want to do to speaking to public things in a row because, you
know, your voice only got so much voice.
It was already pretty hard on my voice doing the speaking thing
because I did a rehearsal.
And then the regular and yeah, anyway, long story but point being a
lot of people have asked where they can see the lecture
If it was recorded etcetera, etcetera, it was recorded.
The AV people looked pretty professional actually for a small
conference like this.
They actually looked like they were some pretty serious AV people, so
it will be available at some point but I don't have a firm date for
when they will get all of the video processed and up but just as soon
as it is I will mention it on the start of the stream here.
And I will also post a link to the Twitter, the Twitter feed.
So this guy right here
He will have a post of it when it is ready.
So I'll let you know as soon as I know, but I don't know anything yet.
All right, let's get to it.
Today is day 1, 21.
If you would like to follow along the source code, you can unzip day
120 source code because that is the source code that I am starting
with right now.
So I one of the things that was tough on Thursday, was that we tried a
new tool that Fabien had sent over, that allows us to analyze the use
of the processor of the Nehalem processor.
That's in this machine.
It allows to analyze use the processor on the code that we wrote and
it's much.
It's like a much more complete version of what I thought we might have
to build our ourselves because I was like, well, you know, I showed
on, I think Wednesday stream how to use intrinsics to kind of go in
and how to use
Pound Defiance, the count your intrinsics.
They basically did a thing that kind of cooler where they would employ
inject into the executable markers that they could grab.
And then they would just read the source code out from the actual
executable and it would be able to do analysis on it.
There which is also pretty cool and honestly we didn't really go over
this too much.
I'll kind of pointed out again.
It's not it's not super relevant to what we happen to be doing right
now by just it.
Was kind of interesting to me just in general.
I I didn't really know about this.
So anyway, I just want to point it out the way they were doing.
That was with the thing that I didn't know you could do in the
compiler.
So if you remember you put these like I acav c64 start and ends.
You put those around the part that you wanted to have it.
Lies.
And then if you include,
Zica when 64 is a marks you just have to include these little markers
and what it would do on the 64-bit compiler was just this thing right
here.
So I didn't know you could do this, right?
GS B and what's kind of neat just I just want to point out what this
does because it's it was kind of news to me and I'm it's something
that I might play with in the future because it's kind of cool.
But basically, what this does.
Is it actually writes actual like, a Known Unknown piece of
information?
Basically, write it like it writes whatever.
This thing is in here you can see what it's but it's writing, right?
It's actually doing a write of a particular piece of information.
It's inserting that directly into directly into the program I guess
might be a way to say it.
So I want to just I want to show here
Roughly what this does and how this works.
Because it's just kind of interesting and today since it's a Saturday,
I don't have a schedule.
We could stream all night if we want to.
So if we want to spend a bunch of time going on tangents or doing
whatever we want, as long as we do an hour of actual programming, on
the actual game, we can do whatever else we want and it's not really a
big deal.
So I don't feel super time constrained.
so, if I go in here and I turn this on and right,
Let's go ahead and do that.
If I turn that on and then I go ahead and and, and launch our game.
And I'm going to draw rectangle quickly that when we get here, what we
should see and you know what also too, just to make it easier to find.
You know what I should do is turn go ahead and turn off optimizations
in the compiler so that our code will be, you know, more
straightforward and more similar to the actual code that we, that we
have.
So, here we go.
And let's see here is that code is run to it and I'm going to right
click here and click go to disassembly so that we can see what's going
on.
Right?
So now what I assumed and I could be very wrong about this, but what I
assume they have done here and you can see, you know, this code right?
This 6fh, right 6fh or o6f, right?
As we know it.
Is that one, one, one, one,
And you can kind of see that that that's what they had passed in that
that marker, right?
One one, one, one, two.
Two, two.
Two.
So what they've done here, is they've inserted a thing that I believe
their idea is that this is a thing that's very unlikely for the
compiler to ever have produced for any reason on its own.
A right to the general this the GS segment thing a right to that
location is not something the compiler will ever produce right?
And so it's not that it actually needs a right to go to that location.
It's that it just needs a instruction.
It knows that the compiler will never put in the command stream so
that when you tell it to analyze something, it can just scan the
executable for this.
It's going to look for that, right?
It's
Just going to grab the up.
Sorry, not that.
It's going to look for.
Here we go.
This is the address where this is the actual location, the executable.
Oops.
Sorry, this is the actual case Chancellor.
It's going to look for this, right?
It's going to look for the byte code that saying, you know, the well,
byte codes for other one word, it's going to look for the encoded
instruction that does this operation, because it knows the compiler
had to insert that and would never probably insert it for
Any other reason and then they do the same thing for ends.
They just use a slightly different value, so then it can scan from
there through the executable until it gets to the corresponding, where
are you?
Come to me, Erica till I get to the corresponding right to the GS
segment, right?
And it's basically got, it's basically.
Now, it's almost like you can think of it like DNA markup, right?
It's almost like inserting these markers into the code that it can use
to look and see where it is.
You want it to analyze.
Now, the reason that I point this out is because if you again, one of
the things we try to do on the stream is encouraged sort of these
Advanced programming practices of like, hey, you know, I just want to
kind of expose everyone who may not have had.
The opportunity to see some of these things before in their
programming.
I just want to point out where we see these things that are kind of
advanced programming tricks.
That's a pretty interesting one.
In fact, it's one I didn't really even know about.
It's the kind of thing you used to do with the inline assembler, but
they remove the inline assembler in the x64 compiler.
I never really thought about how you might get that trick back, but
now it's back.
This is a good pretty cool way to do it.
And so, what this means is, you can mark up the code using this,
right?
GS B.
Thing.
And then if you have an external tool, that wants to grab chunks of
the actual code that came out, for whatever reason analysis or, you
know, moving code chunks around hot, loading them going, who knows
what you might want to do with it, right?
But if you whatever you might want to do,
This allows you to insert those markers in there, in a way that an
external tool can trivially sweep through and find without having to
know anything else about that executable, right?
It doesn't need to know, like, how to read Microsoft's pdb file or how
to read a map file, or anything else of the compartments really
doesn't need to know how to read some other markup to figure out where
the code is.
It can just use this.
And so I think that's a pretty cool trick.
And I just wanted to highlight it.
That's how that's working.
Okay, so let's clean up another thing from the other day which is that
I had to try and figure out how to use that tool on the stream, which
was way too hard for me.
I'll be honest, it's very difficult.
I've said this multiple times but it's very very difficult to talk
while you are programming and the only real reason that I'm able to do
it as was I've programmed for so long and because I talk way too much
in my normal everyday life.
So, it's like, I've had so much practice about those things that I can
make it work.
But when I'm faced with something that
Never seen before ever.
It's really hard for me to integrate.
So I had a really hard time parsing that thing and I needed a little
bit of time to like, spend on it on my own.
So I could understand how to use the tool and so now I can give a much
better explanation of how it works for anyone who maybe didn't get it.
I suspect most people did because I feel like when you're able to look
at on the stream and you don't have to talk it probably sunk in a
little bit better but just in case it didn't.
I want to now say now that I know how it works, I want to explain a
little bit better about how it works because I didn't I was not able
to do that.
That because I didn't know how it worked, right?
And so now I kind of do, all right, so the first thing I want to say
is I want to explain what my confusion was about the tool first,
because I think that's also potentially kind of interesting.
So, I don't know if you guys remember this, but a long time ago, I'm
trying to remember where this actually was.
Where is this going to be?
I don't know.
But I think it's probably
In here somewhere.
Hmm.
Where do I find it where?
Indeed, let's search for it by name and hope we find it.
Hmm.
I don't know if we will.
I don't even know if it's on this machine anymore but we will.
We will know when the little searching Searcher thing.
If the little search researcher thing, actually completes will be able
to find it.
I actually showed it before.
So I know what you see least used to be on this machine.
What I don't know is if I like deleted it off, this machine at some
point and this machine is a totally old Nan used machine anymore.
Are so I don't actually know, you know, I don't actually remember
exactly what's on it yet.
It feels like it should have been on.
I feel like
it should have been on here somewhere, but
I'm not seeing it which makes me a little bit.
Now that's not going to be there it is.
Yeah I don't even remember where things are on this machine so it
doesn't look like it is, which is weird because it was I wonder if it
just got deleted at some point.
Hmm.
Look at it.
It's got look at it going towards the end there.
What's with the word?
Why is this little part taking so long?
Come on, come on, you can get there, but looks like it's not there.
So unfortunately,
Maybe it's in temp.
Oh, it's in Tempe.
There it is.
Now, people ask me if this was because I was mad at Jonathan Blow.
We show this on the stream once before it was like on the desktop or
something and no it's not I don't think I've ever been mad at Jonathan
blue.
For some reason I were just popping my head sometimes and I think I
was combining like blowhard with retard or something and I was mad at
something like a dev kit and so I type that in I think that's just how
that works sometimes.
So anyway,
I'm going to go ahead and show this here.
So this is the output of a tool that I wrote.
It was a compiler and what it was is a compiler that was designed to
make blit code for the Xbox 360 of various kinds of blitko, spry the
wrong word, but operations it was designed to generate 360 stuff.
And so the way the powerpc works, the this processor is fairly
document this point.
So I'm not really violent and enen DA's by explaining some of this
because they've actually reverse engineered at all.
I checked.
On the Xbox 360.
Got a processor that could issue if I remember correctly.
And again like I said it's might be a little hazy of exact I can't
remember a lot of the exact specifics but
Basically, what happened on that processor was that you could issue to
instructions every cycle, but you could only issues those two
instructions, every cycle.
If nothing was was none of the resources that they needed were
blocked.
It's kind of similar to any processor, like we've been talking about
with units, right?
And so, you know, the processor has units and if those units are
available, you could issue it.
So
Unlike the processor that we're working on, now, the Xbox 360 was an
inorder processor.
Which means that as you go through the instruction stream, the only
instructions that it can execute are the instructions that come
immediately after the ones that just got executed.
So, when it comes in here and you see something like a die,
Which, I think refers to add immediate.
So it means take the register 18 and the register 0, right?
I don't remember the ordering for these things.
If it's are 18 to ours.
Oh well, but r0 is just going to be 0, right?
So I suspect, it's probably.
All right.
Teen is the register for the destination and our zeros the register
for the source, that's my guess.
Different.
Different assembly notations, have different conventions for whether
the destination register comes first or second.
But looking at this, I believe are zero on these risc processors.
On the, on a powerpc.
Processors are zero, isn't really a register.
It's just a constant value 0.
You can use.
I don't remember if that's true, like I said, I don't remember a lot
of things about this, but basically, that's the thing I'm using to
determine that probably is Source register here because you can't
write to R.
0 would be my guest.
In fact, we could sort of do a quick spot check and see.
B, r0 is never written to but of course it's not running some other
registers to.
But so anyway,
It would come in here and do something.
Like let's say, we start on this line of execution, then what would
happen is it would be able to issue these two instructions,
potentially.
So it would be able to issue a die, so it would add 0 and 16 to and
put it in 18 in register 18.
And that's an actual immediate 16th.
The value 16 and then it would try to issue.
Add our 20s are three and are five those two registers together and
put it in our 27, okay, that's just what it
We try to do and those are the only two instructions that the
processor can can attempt to execute at that time.
So literally there is no, it does not matter if there's anything else
in here that it could be executing, it can only try to execute these
two.
So it will definitely execute the first one we assume because we don't
have anything, we're not considering the code above it.
So it's going to execute this one and then it will try to execute this
one on the same clock cycle.
If it can.
Now, what you can see from the output of my tool here, which which
generates both the code and markup of the code, it's how I wished
compiler.
Normally worked, right?
I wish compilers normally outputted the code and markup of the code so
that you could see what it at least.
Believed would be the problems on the chip.
Unfortunately, I don't do that, but I thought I want.
So when I wrote the thing, that's what I did.
So, what it does here is, it's telling you right down the side.
It's basically telling you what it thinks.
The execution clock is going to be
So it's saying I'm going to execute this on clock 0.
I'm going to execute this on clock one.
I'm going to execute this on clock five and what you can see here is
this thing over here, tells you the reason
Why it is not able to execute this instruction and how many cycles it
was delayed for.
So it basically says, okay, you know, I can't execute this add-on
cycle 0, which is where I would have been able to execute it normally
because I can actually I know the prospects for taking the time
because the pipeline for the ad is full, there's only one AB pipeline
I think on the 360 which means that once this ad went into it, the
second dad.
I cannot go into it, so it has to wait one cycle for the first ad to
finish.
Does that make sense?
Not to finish?
Sorry for the first ad to move out of that stage of the pipeline?
Because remember, on a processor, things can be staged in pipelines.
So, the adding unit, right?
Is probably pipeline, which means that things move through it in a
couple stages on a couple Cycles so maybe you can have many ads and
flight at a time but you may only be able to issue one at a time into
the front of the pipeline because there's only one slot for an ad in
every stage.
It.
So it goes into the pipeline, the first one goes in and on the same
cycle, you can't put another one in, but on the next cycle, you could,
for example, right?
So, that's what it's saying.
Saying, the pipeline was full, I need to wait one cycle, to get
another add in there, so it does.
And then on the on execution clock one, it'll put it in there then
there's this followed by yet.
Another ad, right?
And so that other AD now gets delayed for much longer.
As you can see, right?
It says that it can't execute that until clock five.
It says that there would have been a pipeline stall of one cycle.
Because again, when it got here and waited a cycle to issue this, if
this were not another ad, it could have issued this right away on the
same cycle, xx1?
Because if this were something other than an ad, that could go in a
separate pipeline, it wouldn't have.
Fine.
So it's like, I gotta wait one of the pipeline but it turns out that
that's not the worst thing.
The worst thing is it actually also has to wait for our 27 to become
free, which is additional three, which is an additional three Cycles,
right?
So you can and the reason you there, you can see, is that our 27 was
used here and then it immediately gets used again.
Does that make sense?
So it has to wait for our 27 to be completely to for the result of
this ad before.
It can issue this ad.
Does this make sense?
And you can see as we go down here, right?
The, the comparative, pretty good job.
In fact, this, I think was a pretty good routine as far as things go.
There's very few stalls in it if you take a look at this routine,
See that most of the time it got perfect pairing.
So most of the time it was dual issuing, right?
If you don't see anything over here besides the execution cycle, that
means it got a dual issue on it, right?
And you can see dual issue dual issue, dual issues, right?
All over the place, so it's pretty good.
But this is what I was used to thinking about because that's the last
time I did one of these things.
And like I said, this is why I say I was much better at Xbox 360
understanding how to do optimization on that because, you know, I
actually wrote a compiler, that could do all this, you know, a bunch
of stuff on it.
And I actually had it down to thinking about exactly how to schedule
each individual instruction.
And to do that, I had to know all about exactly how the processor
worked, and all that sort of stuff, right?
So that's what I was thinking about which is why.
You know, like I said on stream to, it was difficult for me to figure
out what was going on with the tool because the tool is nothing like
that.
And I thought I was sort of looking at a readout that was like, what
my thing produced that is not what this is and there's good reason for
that.
And we'll talk about that in a second.
So let me go ahead and bring up what the tool does, right?
So it's a 64 bit of a largely.
We want to look at Nehalem which is our the processor architecture
that we happen to be on at the moment.
and,
I think that's it.
That's all I need this app.
So let's go ahead and grab that file doesn't really matter which one I
guess we look at.
But
Here we go.
Oh wait.
That's not what I want to look at build a made-up doula.
Invalid Arch, I guess that's be capitalized.
Okay.
So why are you having trouble?
There we go.
Guess that's to be an optimized bill.
That's weird.
Oh well doesn't matter.
Anyway point being so, here we go.
What?
I thought I was seeing here, right?
Was something what I thought this would be showing with something
similar to what I was looking at.
So I was expecting these things to be something about the way.
The processor would execute stuff, but that's not what this shows.
So what this actually shows is really has nothing to do with order at
all.
The only thing this this is just a straight table, it's not an actual
step-by-step.
Read out like what my tool produced what this is is it's just telling
you, okay?
This instruction cost, this many micro Ops in this slot.
That's it.
It's just a table and that was the majority of my confusion.
so, literally, all this table is showing you is it's a
If you want to know for any particular, one of these instructions, if
you want to know what my crops, it generates on which ports of the
processor, right?
And ports are basically the like those units where you're putting
things into the unit's, right?
If you want to know how many microbes go into how many to which
courts, I mean instruction, this tells you and that's it.
So the reason that this is like that and does not look like something
like my tool because something like my tool is what you need that.
I think the way my tool works is exactly what you want for a processor
like 360s processor.
the reason that they do it this way,
Is because the x64 is a highly out of order processor.
It has a giant micro app window.
I think some on the stream posted 196, my crops or something like
this, I don't know if that's correct but it either way, I think I
remember it being something like 40, 40 Micro Ops on the original P6
or something like that, and that was 10 years ago or something, so I
could believe that it was up to 190 something like, Rob's now,
Right, so that's plausible.
So basically because it's so highly out of order.
What the processor is really doing is this looking at, you know
basically two pages of this roughly or some even more really like a
couple pages of this.
In fact this whole thing they fit in the micro app window, right?
I don't know how many lines is this told them our newest to waiting
for.
So basically half of this Loop over half like two-thirds of this Loop
fit in the micro up window which means that that it can execute any of
these things.
As long as they're not see really dependent on each other, it couldn't
pick pick any of them at a given time.
So showing a step-by-step thing would be kind of impossible because
it's like, we don't know which one the process is going to pick next.
It could be tons of these.
So instead what they try to give you to help you, optimize is just an
idea of what port will be the most heavily utilized, first of all,
and we can see that right now in this particular one, it's Port 1,
right?
97.
And in fact, it lists that for us here and the reason that that is an
interesting number is because we know that even if the processor did a
hunt, 100% perfect job and there were zero serial dependencies
meaning, you could execute any of the commands at any time, you would
still only be able to go 97 Cycles.
You that would be the fastest, you could go would be ninety.
Seven Cycles.
Cuz we know that the processor cannot issue two, instructions to a
single port in a single cycle.
So basically, that is it.
It's like, you have 97 of these things that have to go to this port,
that means you will require 97 Cycles right now, you may take a lot
longer.
Than that depending on other aspects of the processing, but you
absolutely will take 97 Cycles at a minimum.
And so that's the single most important number.
And then the second most important thing is this critical path thing
here, which I haven't really played around with too much but I believe
all the critical path thing is actually showing because there's two
things that I kind of thought about for critical path.
That it might be showing.
But when I looked at it, I was like, okay, I think this is actually
not what that is.
I believe what the critical path is showing is just it's marking the
cycle, the it's Mark
Instructions that have to go to the high pressure port.
So basically, CP as far as I can tell is just is basically at least on
the readouts for the hilum is basically just telling you when there
are when an instruction issues to the port that is that is the high
pressure port, the highest pressure port because there's other things,
I was thinking that CP could be.
It could be the longest serial dependency chain and it doesn't look
like that's what it is.
Right.
It just it looks like it's just literally telling you this but I could
be wrong about that.
Now, the reason that I say that it still might be that is because
since all of those things combined, since all of the things have to
combine to the right at the end, it's possible that critical path.
Really does still do the analysis of the longest serial dependency
chain.
And it's just that since all of these things are in some sense
dependent.
That's what it's showing us, but I don't know.
So anyway, so CP looks to me like I'll have to play with this tool
more to really say, but it doesn't look like CP at least for what
we're doing is all that interesting.
But this, this right here is very interesting, the port, the port
thing, so,
Okay, with that, in mind, we can go back to the routine and just take
a quick look at some things that we want to sort of verify.
And, you know, I was talking to Fabien, actually a starting to Fabian
last night.
I went over to see him and Sean on the, on the east side and because I
was already in Bellevue for the conference.
And so, you know, we try to hang out periodically and just catch up.
And so, you know, he actually mentioned something that I don't
remember us finding to
Be the case.
So it's a little weird, but, like he was saying that you can't run
programs that have the markups markers in them, but we were able to do
that, like, this is running with the markers that.
He was saying it crashes when you get there, but it doesn't crash for
us.
And so, I don't know if that's just luck that GS, right?
Doesn't actually cause a problem because of
Other aspect of our system or something.
You know, I don't know why he said that and why we're not seeing that
but I guess we're just lucky because I mean I'd he wouldn't just
imagine that right.
Like presumably he didn't imagine that.
It might crash, I mean he uses the tool himself so he must have seen
it crash but we are not actually getting that crash.
So we must just be not happening to hit the situation that he was
hitting either through good fortune or because we're doing something
slightly differently.
So we're actually able to run with that on, which is kind of cool.
But either way something to mention if you are using if you decide to
use this tool as part of your development environment at home, be on
the lookout for that because Fabien said that he crashed for him if
you ran it.
So you could only use it for analysis and then you try to turn it off.
You want to run the program?
We haven't seen that happen on the stream, but I don't want people to
get caught off guard.
If that turns out to be the case,
So what I want to point out here is that we have sort of, we're caught
between a little bit of a rock and a hard place if we want to get our
cycle countdown.
Now, at this point, it's unclear that we really need to get the cycle
count down yet because at this point, it kind of looks like and, you
know, we haven't really done a whole lot of looking at this yet, but
it looks more like we are hitting memory problems in terms of the
memory, throughput that we can get through in order to look up the
textiles and to
The pixels out.
It looks like that is more of a thing than our block throughput.
And the reason that I say that is because if you take a look at what
this block, throughput is actually telling us even right now it's
saying 97 cycles and if we take a look at that 97 Cycles,
if I take a look at the 97 cycles and I divide that by the fact that
we're doing for pixels, right?
You can see that we get 24 Cycles out of that, right or 25 Cycles.
And so if we're thinking that we should be getting 25 Cycles but we're
actually seeing 40 Cycles.
Then probably, there are some stalls in here, due to memory, but I
want to take care of one thing first, that, that also that Fabien
mentioned.
He was saying that one of the things that the analyzer doesn't do is
take Loops into account, and we do have one Loop in here, right, we've
got this for, I Loop.
And so when the analyzer is going through and looking at your code,
it's not going to expand those Loops.
So it's going to miss count the number of operations that you actually
To do so, what I'm going to do, even though it's not necessarily
having to do with optimization is I'm going to manually unroll this
Loop since it's a very small Loop, so that there are no branches at
all in the code that comes out of the compiler.
And that way, what will be able to do is get a more accurate count out
of that tool?
So, here we go.
There we got four pixels, right?
And now, all I have to do is change the i in each of these to be
whichever Pixel.
It was supposed to have been on because that is the only thing that
was actually varying in the loop was the I right?
So there's the I here we go with the other eye.
Go.
and,
Okay, so let's go ahead and run this.
There we go.
So that is now expanded.
What's interesting about that is, it's also slower, which is a little
bit odd, right?
You can see the Cycles have gone up somewhat, which is a little
A little bit unnerving.
But all right.
That's kind of weird, right?
I guess it doesn't like these to be expanded out.
I don't have to think about why that is exactly.
I suppose one thing I should do as well is this is not a particularly
good way to do this potentially for the compiler.
I feel like we should probably try to reorganize this a little bit.
In fact, I might just go ahead and do that right now, right?
What I would kind of like to do is, I need to figure out some way to
get these fetches stuff out, but I guess, I guess we can't really do
much about that at the moment.
So I'm going to go ahead and make these into individual fetches here,
like so.
There we go.
A few stitches.
I'm going to delete the asserts for now.
We do not have any problems with the asserts, the moment again, I'm
going to go ahead and add great our Texel guys here.
Oops.
See, all that.
So we basically got for textile pointers.
And that will be fetched zero.
Oops, 1 2 3, 3 2 1.
Okay, so those are all the fetches and then these guys are all off of
each individual Texel pointer.
So 0, 0, 0, 1 1, 1 2, 2, 2, 3, 3 3, right?
What?
What just happened?
Oh, I was dumb.
Got to get rid of the Open Bracket there, okay?
So let's go and run that.
Make sure that's running.
It's crazy.
How the cycle counts change, right?
Like it's kind of a bizarre, that's that whole thing with stabilizer.
I don't know if yours ever seen stabilizer.
There's a thing which basically tries to randomize your code layout,
to see what's actually affecting performance because there's so much
variability nowadays in it.
That the same exact code just offset where it is, aligned in memory,
sometimes can change the performance and lead you to think that things
are costing more when they're actually the same and so on and so
forth.
But all right.
So anyway,
What I want to do here, now is just grouped by sample Group, by what
we're setting for the moment off to think about, if maybe there's a
better way to do this, by just want to kind of get this organized a
little bit more, so I can start to, think about it a little bit more
carefully, because we've basically got a, we're trying to build some
Cindy stuff here, right?
We're trying to build, you know, Cindy registers that have the
appropriate values in them for us to do our computations
And so what I want to do is just change this so that I can actually
do, okay, sample, a is just it, just an M&M set PS4, it's of the
compiler can see very clearly what I'm actually trying to do, it's
like oh okay.
I just I just am trying to set one of these guys to be essentially
each each thing of the textile pointer, right?
now, I think this this is the
There we go.
This is the thing where it's always going to be the wrong one.
But we one of the things that Fabienne suggested on Twitter a long
time ago because I was complaining about is he was saying just always
use set our he was like I don't know why they even have the other one,
right?
But basically I was complaining that set.
PS always went the wrong way and and so yeah, I he was saying just use
this one because that way it goes the correct way.
You can see what I wanted was.
I want the low value to go here and then the next I want memory order
basically, and this one is in memory order.
Whereas set is in register order, like register read out order and I
it's just I find that super confusing.
So anyway I'm going to I'm going to use set are so I can do it in that
order.
And I probably will convert to using that permanently because it's
just the way I tend to think about it.
And so I would just do it.
Helped me make it would probably keep me from making some careless
errors, right?
Right where I forget that it's the wrong way or something, you know
Oops.
Why can't I go right kill rectangle.
Yank rectangle.
There we go.
so,
that's correct.
Oh whoops.
I guess I didn't quite mean to gank the rectangle in that way but all
right.
Will you live with that?
That's fine.
So, there we go.
and,
Let's get this one.
Wow.
I am sloppy typist tonight.
I was really exhausted from, I hadn't been sleeping all that.
Well, sometimes my sleep schedule gets really off, you know?
And I just like, I have a hard time falling asleep, that's just how it
is.
I don't know why.
I've always had a really hard time falling asleep, like I can't just
go to sleep for whatever reason, and sometimes it's just like, I don't
know.
It's really annoying because I wish I could like, always keep on a
regular.
because it makes a lot of things easier for you obviously because, you
know, the world operates at a particular time, but
What the long and short of it is, is I have not been sleeping too
well, because I've been getting up relatively early but I can't seem
to fall asleep so I don't get that much sleep.
So, I took a nap today just before the stream, actually, and still a
little groggy
But anyway, so I'm going to go ahead and get this all working
properly, so I should have dinner.
Wearing art.
Curators.
You went 3-2 to float.
Oh, right.
These are supposed to be set epi32 s, right?
Hopefully there is one of those, yes, forgot where we're not setting
packed singles.
Pat, we're doing packed integers.
Yeah.
So, let's go ahead and run that.
Okay.
And it's so weird.
You know it's just so weird.
The cycle counts now, we're magically faster than when we started at
40 Cycles.
Yeah, so much variability.
Like you think that's basically what the compiler would have already
done.
It's not so that's okay, that's maybe maybe it was hard for it to
figure out that these were fusing like that.
So, yeah.
But anyway, so there we go.
I don't know these all look relatively sane to me.
Okay, I don't think we're doing anything, particularly stupid here.
That's how we have to figure.
That's how we have to access that texture memory.
That seems pretty reasonable.
There is one thing we could do here.
I don't know if we want to do it but we'll we'll try it.
And we'll see if it makes a little more sense.
And like I said, I'm probably planning to go pretty long today, I'm in
the mood to do some programming.
I haven't programmed in like two days which
Grumpy about, I mean, I did do a little bit but it was for a separate
thing.
So anyway, take a look at these here.
In fact, one thing, I guess we want to do now.
I might want to check out here.
We've got o to on, right?
Yeah, I want to take a look at that total throughput count now, as
well, right?
I just want to get that that read out.
And so 103 Cycles.
So now, at least in theory this one, at least in theory, this 103
Cycles is actually the number of cycles that the thing takes because
the loop is, is actually enrolled.
So, it's accounting for all of the instructions that actually have to
occur right before it would have, had a jump at estimate jump in here.
And
Test in the jump, it would not have actually counted how many times
the loop it would have had to have gone and you can understand why,
because most of the time the loop is not going to be over a constant
number.
Probably, it would be over a variable and it doesn't know what the
variables value will be because, you know, it's looking at the code,
it doesn't have the state of the thing at the time, so there's that
Okay, I need some more soy milk.
Hold on a second.
I ran out and it's that's no good.
Okay.
Oh wait, you know did I say soy milk?
I meant almond milk.
Sorry, I need more.
Almond milk.
I do drink soy milk occasionally to, like, like in coffee.
Like, if you go to a coffee shop, I'll get soy milk, sometimes.
Sometimes they have almond milk, which is good too, but
A lot of coffee shops originally only had soy milk for people like me
who can't drink regular milk.
All right.
so anyway, what I wanted to see here, I was just thinking, like, oh,
you know, maybe we could go through and we could, you know, since we
know like you can see like these two guys here when they're actually
doing these, these fetches, I feel like
Well.
Now you know what, I think that pretty much has to say the way it is.
Now I think about it because it could be fetching any other textile,
because of the way that it's stepping through there.
So I don't know that there's really anything else we can do here when
we actually load these things in
When we actually load these things in, here's what I'm thinking.
So you see how these guys here?
We have tech support, no 0, 1 2 3.
And then we immediately load txt file, pointer 0, 1, 2 3, + 1 integer
over.
I was wondering if we just did a load you on that, I was wondering if
we could just load it and then load do a load once and then from just
doing the load once grab out the two values that we needed.
That's what I was thinking.
And I'm not sure that that actually saves any time.
Like I'm not sure that actually does anything for us.
But that is what I was thinking.
So like, you know, if we went over to the Blackboard, just to give you
a little bit of a feel for what's going on there, right?
If it's day 121
What I was thinking was okay, so we know that when we load the thing,
right?
We know that when we load it, what we are doing is we're loading this
textile and then this textile and then this text will end this
textile.
So this is 32 bits, this is 32 bits.
So, I was thinking we could just load this in one load.
Right.
Just load it once.
And when we load it once we then would have a register.
That would have like, you know, the 0th one here, the one here, and
then two things.
We didn't care about here, right?
We could also try to do a 64-bit load, which I think we can also do or
we just load these two.
I can't remember if that works well or not, but we could do those and
then just grab it out of the register.
I don't actually know why.
That would be any faster I suspect that it probably wouldn't be, but
it might save some kind of work where
Where, you know, things didn't have to happen quite the same way.
So we could take a look at that.
Do the thing.
You know what?
We should probably take a look at.
We should probably have up while we're doing this.
Hail mm architecture.
Wikimedia diagram.
So this was kind of a handy diagram, someone pointed to the other day
on the stream.
And the thing that I kind of liked about this was, I could it actually
let us see some stuff about what was going on.
Like, here's the floating Point, Adder, on Port 1.
Here's the floating-point multiply on Port 0, right?
It also has like,
Some other information like it has integer an integer ALU on each of
these guys, which I assume that that integer.
ALU means we could do integer ads on multiple ports or something like
this.
Not actually sure.
So it would be cool if we could find something that actually had a
really explicit listing.
Because one of the things that's kind of annoying is
Once we actually put an instruction in here, we can see which porticos
to.
But before we put an instruction in here, we have no idea which
porticos to write because the Intel intrinsics guide.
Like we were using before I write like this thing, the until
intrinsics guy doesn't actually tell us anything about that.
You know, we go in and look up one of these routines right?
Look, I want to know how something works or whatever when I come in
here.
I don't actually know what what that's going to do, right?
I don't know what port that's going to go to.
So if I want to do like one of these guys or something, you know it
doesn't tell me any information about what port that goes to, it'll
tell me the throughput information, which is like kind of has a little
bit of that knowledge of like, what it's going to do built into it.
But it doesn't tell me anything about how it would issue in tandem
with another instruction.
So, like the ad and the multiply
Both lists the throughput number but I don't it doesn't tell me
whether the ad in the multiply could go together and therefore
overlap, or whether they would have to be cereal because they use the
same port, right?
And so it would be nice to find and I suspect that this is something
that I can sort of go off to the stream, push off to the stream here
but basically like if there was, it would be pretty cool.
If there was a resource similar to this one, that would allow you to
quickly without having to page through a bunch of stuff quickly, get
to the port assignment information so that you could see when you were
using instructions.
Ports.
They were going to go to without having to actually first do them and
then look and go like oh okay.
Max is on Port 1.
It would have been cool.
If it had just been in here where I come down and go, maybe I'll send
it to Intel and be like please because you can imagine adding to this
tool a thing which basically like you know I mean in fact they already
kind of have since they already have it / architecture, they could
just have Port maybe.
And you know, I feel like that would be just your Good extra piece of
information to have
That is all.
Anyway, maybe I'll send them at, who knows?
Maybe they'll listen.
Until it's a, you know, they have developer relations, they might be
like, oh yeah, good idea.
Let's do it.
You never know anyway.
So, the thing I was thinking is like, yeah, when we're doing these
loads, I do wonder if the, you know, if the compiler is actually doing
the best job of managing those, and if there's something, if there's
something we could do to help it, understand what it is that we're
doing better so that it can produce better code.
And I don't actually know if that's true.
In fact, I don't really know what it's doing at the moment so it is
possibly the case that we should, you know, try to take a look at
It's doing those loads and figure out what's going on.
So I suspect that that is what's going on here.
And you can see this doing like a bunch of these mobs here and it
looks like just looking through it here.
Just looking through it here.
Move dqa X of m word.
So those guys
Yeah.
Are the four so I feel like that is what Square?
We're this is what it looks like to me.
It looks like This Is Us loading in, you know, us loading in all of
our of our textual data there.
And let's take a look at that.
If that holds any water.
Let's see here.
It's doing the unpack.
It's doing p.m.
pack load.
Q LD Q, PS r.
LD and then stirring the p.
And so yeah I think I think that is what this is.
So if it's doing that, what it's doing is it's doing a bunch of moved.
He's how many's is doing swing 1.
2 3 4 5 6 7 8 9 10 11 12 13.
Looks like that's all of them, right?
although,
Well, we've still got some of these guys up here.
I don't know because we're not doing any loads up here.
We're just doing the loads in here and then everything else doesn't
actually have to do any loads till we get down to actually doing the
load for the destination, right?
The destination is the only other load that we do at, all right?
These guys here,
So I don't know, I don't know.
It looks like
If it's shifting by 8 there, it looks like it's doing this operation.
And it looks like it's doing that.
Directly after mmm.
This is hard for me to read.
This is largely probably due to the fact that I don't spend a lot of
time reading this kind of code.
So it's harder for me to kind of like parse through it quickly but
I'm not sure.
So I don't know p.m.
pack ldq.
Can we take a look at P unpack?
Ldq?
Because I'm not familiar with all the instruction.
By name, but that's not something we called explicitly if I'm not
mistaken, right?
That is actually an M&M unpack intrinsic, which if I, if I remember
correctly we don't use right?
So the compiler has decided to do the unpack itself.
It felt like that was the right way to implement this.
So,
That suggests to me that it actually.
So it kind of redid how that code, how our code, how it thought, our
code should work, right?
It's unpacking the load.
So you know we're if we're loading one of these guys in its unpacking
that load.
Where do we got?
There we go, it's unpacking that load.
and then,
It just goes ahead and unpacks.
It twice.
Right, so you can see here.
It's loading off the pointer.
Into XM m 1.
It's loading another one in on top of it, but first it, unpacks that,
then it unpacks it again.
And it's got xmm 14.
Now is the result of a double unpack, right?
So the double unpack,
The next time it takes a look at 14.
Is here when it actually does the shift.
So just trying to reverse engineer, what it's doing there, right?
It looks like that.
Once it loads something.
It is actually going ahead and jumping straight to here, right?
So sample A8.
So the way that it chooses to produce sample, a which we have told it
to do this way is to do a load.
and,
To unpacks.
Am I missing something?
Here's the load into XM m.
1 it unpacks X-Men.
1 to XM m 2
Unpack some into XM M14.
X-Men 14 is never touched again.
Oh no, there it is.
It copies.
It over 20.
Right.
And you can see why that is because it has to use it twice.
I guess that makes some sense.
It copies it over 20 it shifts one of them down, it does the ad with 0
and 1?
It does the and I saw the and with 0 and 1 it does the and with 14 and
1.
So that's doing this right here.
Right?
Because I'm assuming that X mm0 in.
There is what contains the mask I'm sorry.
X-Men, 1 is what contains the mask ff0000 FF, right?
Because it's doing that and with both of those.
So I'm assuming that somewhere in here it loaded up xmm one with with
that value and
Assuming that that's probably, you know, where's where's that going to
be?
It's going to be the last time we touch texting one, it's that
And so this right here is called, Rip relative addressing.
Also, I believe again, I'm not the Assembly Language guy.
Ask Fabien or find another Assembly.
Language expert, if you want to, I feel bad where you're forcing
Fabien, to do all our homework for us.
but as long as he's willing,
He's a good person to ask, so we'll take advantage of it.
So anyway, basically what this is is it's a cheap way to do extra
addressing essentially the instruction pointer, like where you are in
the code, you can actually do loads off of that and it makes it easier
to load in constant space.
Clay is what that boils down to.
And so this I assume right here is what's loading in the FF 00 FF
Then it's going to end with that.
So it basically just did unpack LD cues and two of those, it looks
like it's doing two of those per sample.
I'm sorry, /.
/ load per fetch instruction, right?
And to be honest, I don't really understand
I don't really understand how that's working.
I guess it's doing it as a shuffle.
So, the unpack, presumably, it's loaded xmm to already.
Where is X mm2?
X-Men 2.
Right there.
Okay, so extra time to Got Loaded off of our nine, which I'm just
going to go ahead and assume is another one of our texture pointers.
One of the one of the cat an address into the texture.
So it's taking XM m 2.
Its P.
Unpacking it out of X-Men, 1.
It's should be worse.
Is it p.m.
pack me out?
We covered, we covered the impacts of for, with a kind of internally
values.
So it's interleaving that xmm one load with the X-Men, to load, and
then it's going to X.
Presumably XM, M14 was loaded somewhere up here as well.
There it is.
So I guess what that suggests to me?
Is it the compiler is kind of already doing a very smart thing for
this like it's actually doing it as an interleave which would make it
way more efficient than what we wrote here.
So I'm going to go ahead and say that actually, this is okay.
It looks like the compiler is actually doing pretty smart job.
Turning those into unpacks which is what we would have had to do to
make them more efficient anyway.
Yeah.
So so that was good.
That was worth.
That was worth looking into because now we know we really don't have
to play with that.
I don't think I could think of a better way to do it than to unpack.
That sounds pretty good.
Yeah.
So I think this is fine, then I think that's okay.
I think we can be reasonably happy with that this stuff.
On the other hand, I don't really know much about.
Unfortunately this is something that I've never really worked with
before on SSE.
And so specifically this stuff right here the the fetching in order to
do the fetch, we have this problem where
oh,
Well, so there's a couple stupid things.
The compiler may have already figured this out but I'll interrupt,
what I was about to say to point out the fact that we multiply by
texture pitched for wide manually, which is stupid and we X size of
you in 30 to manually for Y which is stupid.
So hopefully everyone on the stream at this point could figure out
without me having to say it.
But really how we should have done this was.
Before we did that we should have done the multiply wide if we're
going to multiply each of these values by
Our pitch.
We should just I'm sorry, each of these values by texture pitch.
We should just multiply fetch y 4x B, actually pitch and then extract
it afterwards right now, I don't know whether the compiler already did
that or not.
So it might be that.
It was kind of cleaning up our stupidity, but I feel like we should
probably just go ahead and put put in that just in case.
And let's take a look here.
One more time.
Oops, we compile this.
Yeah, let's take a look at that one more time.
Go up in here.
So right now we're at a hundred and three Cycles.
I'm just going to go ahead and do that multiply here.
So, this is a mmm Mo epi32, right?
And I want to multiply fetch X for X.
I want to multiply that by texture pitch.
Oops, sorry.
Sighs of you, you're in 32, right?
And you know what I guess.
Sighs of you in 32 though, I don't need to multiply because I know
that that's I know that size of you and 32 is is just a shift.
So I could do it by an immediate so we don't have to use another
register for that if that makes sense.
Meaning, I know that that to get something to go up by the size of a
32-bit integer.
I really only have to shift it up by.
Bye.
This is the power of to write this is for.
So it's 2 to the second power.
So I should be able to shift it up by 2, if that makes sense and that,
that would give me the value.
So if I want to, I could do the shift left by immediate and just shift
it up and that's, you know, that would get rid.
I guess is what I'm saying of this.
Right.
So like that.
I don't know why I deleted that.
I gotta keep it in here for now.
We sell to extract these but so, yeah.
So if I was to do that, right?
That should give me what I needed in terms of stepping, right?
So, there we go.
And then similarly, this guy right here should have just done.
This should have just done.
Fetch y, 4x equals m.
M Mo PS, and that should be the texture pitch that we've got there,
right?
So, texture pitch for X for x and fetch, y for x, and now, those are
gone.
and so yes, so the compiler May well have oh God, you know it's just
like it's like
It's like Casey's stupid weekend here, isn't it?
I mean, well, it's AA run stupid in weekend but right I mean what's
going on here?
That's a for why Dad people like why am I making the compiler have to
do that?
When it shouldn't have to.
Should at least give it the wide stuff so they can see it as wide.
I feel like that would generally be better anyway so yeah and this is
why did I do PS?
And then add epi32, alright for x or y?
Yeah.
You know, it sometimes takes a little while to see each individual
things.
You should be collapsing, you know, I don't claim to be an
optimization guy and it's true.
So let's go ahead and mmm set, one epi32 that so that we have that guy
there.
We can probably clean up some of these.
Some of these are probably just not even used anymore because we
Shuffle stuff around.
But anyway, texture if it's for X, that's just extra pitch.
Oops, texture pitch.
Like so.
And I feel like I don't want to jump the gun here but I feel like what
did I do wrong cannot convert.
Yes, that's true, sorry about that.
I feel like there's plenty of other stuff we could do here.
looks like,
We still need that.
Hmm.
I don't know if we want to really extract the only thing because
otherwise we could get rid of that as well.
But anyway, texture catch fish.
All right.
So anyway, there's another thing we could still do there, I suppose.
Oh that doesn't look pretty.
That doesn't look pretty at all.
What I what I mess up there.
so,
Shift left by 2 of fetch x 4x.
And then Molly pi32 of fetch y 4x by texture pitch.
4X
Mmm-hmm.
Excuse me.
What am I missing here?
I'm not asking anything.
I just forgot to get rid of the weight.
That's correct.
Yeah.
So what am I missing here?
This should multiply 4X by for although I mean well you know what, why
bother guessing might as well just step through
Check it out.
We'll see what goes on.
Alright.
So
if we go in here,
And we are we yeah if we go in here, let's find out what happens.
So we have our fetch x 4x.
And I want to see that as I 32s.
And 128 II.
Oops, I'm going to mate, I have 32.
11 12, 13 and 14.
Are the values that it looks like we are getting there.
I guess that's kind of commonly going to be the case for rectilinear
Blitz.
They'll often go in series if they're not rotated, right?
That makes sense.
Multiplying by 2
I'm Sorry by for that.
Look does look like it X for, right.
I feel like so fetch.
Why?
Nice.
Fetch y for X 0 for X.
I'm going to get II 32.
These are all from the zeroth, row of the texture.
Also not surprising.
So we won't find out much about this.
And so, then when we get to the fetch,
Xxxx.
And 128 II 32.
Let's see what we get here.
So that looks like what we would want, right?
Those are the the pixels.
So that looks correct to me.
Right.
I don't quite see what the problem is there.
All right.
Well, let's step through and do a why that's not zero, see if maybe
something obvious is going around because it's hard to say,
Hard to say about that I suppose.
Is that right?
Let me look, get to some kind of a why that's that's not at zero.
There we go.
So we come through here and we do our, our fetch y 4x.
And I want to take a look at what texture pitch.
We're exes.
And that's M 128 II 32.
Oops.
there's art extra pitch, 324
So now we're going to do the multiplication of fetch y 4x and texture
pitch.
4X
Know what I just realized.
That might be my problem.
Shouldn't just have a mole low and mole high in it.
We'll check, I'll check that out.
In just one second.
I'll let me go ahead and stop this here.
So fetch y 4x is this guy right here.
It's got ones in it so it should come out to all those and it doesn't.
That's the problem, duh.
All right.
So what mmm that was just me being Hasty and not thinking it through,
MMO epi32 does not do, integer times integer, does 32-bit by 32-bit
out to a 64.
So it probably only does the low integers or something like that.
That's just some, that's not the instruction.
I was even thinking,
King of right.
So you can see that here.
Mo epi32.
Oops.
It's not even in sse2.
Well epi32.
See it just grabs those two lows and then produces the full 64-bit
result, which is not in any way.
We want what I actually wanted to do is just multiply the two values
together.
I don't know what that just did.
Do not want to know what hockey that was.
I actually want to do a thing here where I'm just taking the low, I
want to take each of the 32 bit Lanes, multiply them together and just
take whatever the low is of that result, right?
Because I'm pre saying that it's not going to overflow into I'm saying
that they're going to be small enough values that they won't overflow
into a 64-bit result, right?
And so in theory, that should fix it.
Yeah, it does okay.
So, that was a, that was a good thing to remember.
Don't forget, there is a mole command, you will be able to into du Mal
epi32 by accident and then forget that that is not at all.
What you probably were trying to do.
So, there you go.
All right, so I'm imagining maybe the compiler was smart enough to do
that for us anyway, but there we go.
Now, one of the interesting things seriously, we could actually do the
texture memory, add as well.
Meaning we could just do that ad for a wide but on, you know, 64-bit
processors, that's actually a 64-bit pointer potentially.
So I don't want to push it, you know.
I don't want to push it that far, if that makes sense.
So yeah, so that's about it, I don't know that there's anything else
to be done with just that unpack situation here.
But now the, the most important part, it was good to just kind of
clean that up a little bit.
Just so we're not forcing the composite figure that out.
What I do want to do though now is get back to what we're sort of
looking at originally which is that Port pressure, right?
So here we go.
So who is our Port?
Who is our
Rhino to here yet.
who is our, who is are pressured, Port are pressured Port into it over
back to enter iteration are we
So some of us saying the inter iteration is what happens.
When it believes that if you were to run the block repeatedly, that
would be the problem.
Meaning it would be dependencies between Loops or something like this.
That's what someone was saying.
I haven't read up about that yet so I'm not sure if that's actually a
meaningful thing but
It actually looks kind of like to me.
Yeah.
It looks kind of like to me.
That we kind of have things a little more spread out here.
It's weird because one of the things that's I guess kind of difficult
to work through, as well, you know, when I'm looking at this and
again, this is the first time I've ever done SSE, anything with this
tool, is that the cycle count doesn't necessarily match up with the
cycles per pixel that we observe and presumably that has a lot to do
with how the memory actually works out.
Like, in theory, I feel like that this one should have been slower
because it says 116 Cycles but I feel like we had 101
Cycles up here and and that one was actually not faster though when we
had going this way.
So I don't know, little bit odd.
Anyway.
point being
We do have one thing that's kind of bizarre, right?
And we looked at that the other day and it was because I wasn't
actually sure how to use the tool.
It was a bit of a problem, but one thing that we did is we tried
taking the bilinear and making the bi-linear unpack be done in 16, bit
per per element, instead of doing it as 32-bit per element, right?
So, we were basically, instead of doing multiplies with the floating
Point Unit, we did
Plies with the 16 wide Lanes.
And there's a number of things that we could do there.
Like we could try to continue that on and do 16 bit further through
the pipe, right?
We could try reverting this back to doing the floating point because
since we know that we have too much pressure on Port 1, in a lot of
circumstances, moving the pressure over to Port 0, which is what we
had before we did.
This conversion might be helpful and so on but the problem as I see it
at the moment like I was saying is that I feel like we
I have a memory problem as well.
Which is to say that.
If we take, for example, what this tool thinks is the number of cycles
that we might have, we actually observing more Cycles than then it is
reporting.
Which it suggests that we're not getting stuff back as immediately as
we should write.
It suggests that there are some longer memory latency stalls in there.
And so one thing that we might want to do at this point and one thing
that I'm considering is now might be a time to try to switch to
multi-threading in the renderer
and the reason for that, I say that is because if you take a look at
how these sorts of things work,
Remember I talked about hyper-threading before?
So, the way these Intel processors work on anything that has the
hyper-threading in it.
is that the idea behind the hyper-threading is, it's actually,
Pretty simple.
If you imagine the processor has these, you know units, right?
She may have to blow my nose.
So, when we talked about the diagrams and I mentioned hyper-threading
at the time, but it's gonna mention again.
So, you know, the processor has these units, right?
And the way that it looks at any given time, you know, is the
processor may be is in there and let's say, you know, it's got an f p,
add right unit or something, that's adding floating Point numbers.
And then it's got, you know, some unit over here that's like doing
loads or whatever, right?
And so you know, the thing issues a load and at least use a floating
Point, add or something, and those are impressed in, you know, going
through the timeline.
You know, we've got our tix here.
Tick tick.
Tick tick, right?
So here is cycle 0, let's say, and if we issue one of these FP ads and
we issue a load, let's say we issue.
Both of those, we issue like the ad and the load both on this cycle,
right?
And let's say the load hits the cash perfectly and the ad works out
and whatever.
So, like the total amount of time, you know, maybe it takes to do this
thing is just like a, you know, maybe it's only two cycles or even
just one cycle.
And so, the results come back like right here, and it's totally fine.
Or if they were long latency, maybe they take this long, let's say,
you know, five Cycles or four Cycles or something like this.
But once they're in there, we can also issue some more things like
we've got more things to issue, so we issue another ad and a load and
we can issue another load or an ad or whatever.
Who knows, right?
And they go into the pipeline and they complete serially.
So like this guy completes over here, and this guy completes over here
and whatever right?
Again, this is nothing specific, I'm just saying, we've got things
going into these units and then we've got things coming out of them,
right?
And from the perspective,
Of like this tool what we're looking at is saying, let's make sure we
can always issue.
Let's try and figure out how to minimize the number of things that go
the minimum number of cycle.
The minimum number of instructions to anyone Port that we want to try
and minimize the maximum number.
They're right.
Because the maximum number is going to be how slowly we run because
you can only issue to that Port.
See, really.
So even though you can issue as many things as you want across
multiple ports, you can while you can
you up to four or whatever it is, you can issue a certain number of
instructions at any given cycle, you could only issue 12 any given
port on that cycle, so that becomes the bottleneck, right?
But if we are having a problem where we the inputs to these, right?
Because like an ad or a load has inputs, it's got like the address or
the things to add if we get into a situation where the inputs, the
sources are not here yet because they're coming from memory.
We're waiting for them to arrive.
What we can end up with is a situation where all of the instructions
like we get to some point and all
The instructions that we could issue all of them all depend on some
loads that have not arrived yet because like the load takes, you know,
a hundred milliseconds or so.
I'm sorry.
100 Cycles or something.
Wow, 100 Ms load that be awful.
And so, there's this big huge window and there's nothing we can do
about it, right?
So what that means is at that time when we get to that stall, right?
When we get to that point where we are completely waiting on inputs
from memory or a slow part of the lower part of the cash in L3 cache
or something or an L2 cache, probably not no one cash.
Because those are very fast, but when we get to the point where we're
waiting on that, we've got all these units that are sitting around
doing nothing.
Like we could stuff another load into the load pipeline, we could
stuff another FP.
Add into the FBI piping.
If only we had one to put in there, so the units are basically just
sitting there doing absolutely nothing and that's a huge amount of
wasted performance for us.
So what hyper-threading attempts to do is take advantage of the fact.
These are called latency bubbles.
Right.
And they're basically like little bubbles of time that form because
we're just waiting to have something to put into our units.
Right.
What we can do with hyper-threading is say well what if we just had
two streams of code, right?
So here is Loop, you know, 0 and this is Loop 1.
And what if we were just to run both Loops zero and loop.
One at the same time on the same processor on the same core so it's
still it's still
Entirely single-threaded in some sense.
Meaning there's only one thing executing at a given time.
But what can happen is it'll execute Loop 0 till it hits one of those
bubbles and it hits a point where it goes.
I'm completely starved for memory.
I can't get what I actually need to get in order to issue any more
instructions, and the units on a processor, will just go fallow, what
it then does, is it immediately task switches over to Loop one in a
very, very fast way.
It's got like a special Bank switching ability to make it so that it
doesn't have to do.
Like, register.
Save and load from memory.
There, like all the processors like ready to go with them.
That's what makes them a Hyper Shred because it's a thread switch.
That doesn't go through the operating system in that way.
It doesn't have to, like, ask the operating system to manually.
Do it right?
Which takes a bunch of time.
So, in that memory bubble, it can go ahead and switch over to Loop one
and see, does the other loop have any instructions that I could fill
in here, right?
So, it's basically this way of giving the processor more potential
things to do, so that when it gets,
Some point in the loop.
When it's waiting on membranes, like it can go go over to the other
loop.
We'll have some instructions to execute.
It does those and when that guy hits the part where he's waiting on
memory, it ping-pongs back over right it comes back to the previous
Loop and we hope that now all the memory we were waiting for on that
Loop has had time to arrive and so that's what hyper-threading is.
So what I was thinking we might do because we want our render to be
hyper threaded.
Last thing you might do is hyper thread the renderer so that we can
start to see real performance measurements of something with
hyper-threading on so that we don't do a bunch of work to optimize
memory latency that we don't actually need to optimize, right?
Because a hyper thread would have just done it.
Again with anything with that position it's very hard to know whether
you're making a good decision at the time unless you had a lot of
experience.
And so and I haven't like I said on x64 S, I do pretty light
optimization.
so it's a little bit hard to tell, but
that was just something I thought of as like, maybe we should switch
to that earlier rather than later.
So that's actually surprisingly easy to do.
It's not that hard.
So I don't know if you want to do it and make this like a marathon
stream or whatever, but we could, we could do it now.
Maybe what we'll do is we won't actually try to multi-thread the
renderer too much but I'll show how to actually
Get more than one thread working in Windows.
For example, we could at least do some of that before going to the
Q&A.
So, let's take a look in here.
Threading.
You don't, we could do.
I wonder if we should just break this up into two days though because
if I introduce threading,
Hmm.
You know what?
I'll do it the other way around.
That's what I'll do.
We'll introduce threading on Monday but we can do is prepare the
renderer to be threaded.
That's what we should do.
Yeah, yeah, that's a better idea.
And then we'll have one day that it chooses reading.
Okay?
So what we need to do to get the renderer ready for threading really,
it's we can do something pretty simple.
There's two ways we could do it and I'll sort of talk, say, a little
bit about how I'm thinking about it and I don't know.
Hard to say, what the right decision is, we can try a couple different
things, but here's what I think, would probably be smart.
So, we've got a screen.
And we know we have to render this whole screens worth of stuff,
right?
And what we also know is that typically what we are drawing
Is rectangular, right?
It has to look like that, you know.
It doesn't look like this.
You know, we're not drawing very many things that are long slippery.
It doesn't look like
This you know, it doesn't look like that.
It tends to look like this and when it doesn't look like this it looks
you know, like a rotated version of this or a smaller version of this
but it's very much this way.
And so remembering that we want to try and optimize to make sure that
we don't have things being in and out of the cash a lot and that sort
of thing.
We want to try and design how we're going to break up the rendering
for multi-threading in ways that don't put lots of extra pressure on
the caches.
So what does that mean?
Well, we've got two things that have to go in the caches, right?
We got two fundamental pieces of memory that we are working with right
technically three but one of them is probably not very relevant.
Okay, so I'll say what they all are.
Got zero one and two, and I'm sort of saying that zero is probably not
super important.
0 is the command buffer.
Right, that's the thing that we've got there that render group that
basically just says, all the stuff that actually has to happen when we
render, right?
And I don't think that's going to cause us a huge amount of headache
because it's just not access that frequently.
Write the number of command commands in the command buffer versus the
number of pixels and textiles that we touch is just not that relevant.
So even though this technically is a piece of memory that we have to
access, it's not really relevant.
I don't think
So okay, we've got that, we've got a much more important thing which
is the frame buffer.
Write the actual thing that we're writing to.
What did I do?
Oh no!
No!
What happened?
I don't know what happened.
Hey, control X!
Don't know what that does.
XXX.
Doesn't even look like that's a thing.
Control X.
This is the great.
Wow, there's a hotkeys window for you.
All right, so anyway maybe I just hit control s accidentally and it
just saved.
I don't know.
Anyway, well, I hope it's nothing bad.
So there's the frame buffer, which is obviously, you know, a huge
thing that we're writing to and reading from.
So this is basically a read right thing, and then we've got our
textures.
Which are read only.
Right.
We never write back to the textures.
Now, once in a while, the frame buffer might actually be something
that we texture from.
So, we do have in a sense, some readwrite textures, but they're, we're
just going to really treat those as frame buffers, right?
That's what we're producing like our ground chunks.
We write to the ground chunks first, but then we draw from the ground
chunks later, potentially, right?
So, it's a little bit weird in that sense but anyway, so that's how
that works.
and if we think about this,
What that means is that in terms of our managing, how the memory flows
through the system, what we're trying to do is minimize the degree to
which we load from these and read and write from these things in ways
that are spatially incoherent, right?
So like what we don't want to do with the frame buffer.
For example is we don't want to have a situation where we like
Read and write some part of the frame, buffer read and write some
other part of the frame, buffer at a size, sufficient to blow out the
cash.
Meaning like we completely replace, like a bunch of stuff in the cash
with new stuff and then go back and read and write the exact same
stuff again.
Because basically what that would mean, is we've filled the cash for
something.
Once we've then spent another whole amount of time to fill the cash to
completely other things.
And then we've gone right back and filled it again with stuff that was
already in there.
For that we could have had for free if we just done the work at that
time, right.
So we're trying to do is do a little bit of management of that
locality here.
So that we can avoid that process.
Okay.
So, the first thing I'm going to take just a try.
As I'm going to try and manage the frame buffer locality and the
reason that I'm going to try to manage the frame buffer locality is
because managing the texture locality, I feel like is going to be
harder.
The reason I feel like it's going to be harder is because there's
rules about what has to be drawn texture wise in what order.
So, it's not like I can necessarily sort things by the order in which
they use textures, because we have to do things, like, sort them, by
the order that they stack up on the screen and other things.
That's potentially for other reasons.
Like getting the correct result and other stuff like this, but the
frame buffer, it's pretty free for me to pick how I want to dice up
the frame buffer.
Right?
I can for example, if I have two threads choose to just break the
frame buffer in half and have one thread render one side and one
friend thread rather the other side and there's no like that.
There's no constraints on how I do that.
I can literally break up the frame buffer anyway, I want it doesn't
really affect anything else in the system.
So, I'm going to try it that way first.
And so, what I'd like to do is I'd like to design it so that we work
potentially in chunks of the frame buffer, right?
That are sized appropriately for the cash, right?
Meaning I would like to break up the frame buffer into pieces, which I
think will fit into the cache in, in a nice in a way that that if I
were to just operate on everything inside that region, I wouldn't blow
out the cash too.
Right?
It could fit into the cache nicely.
So there is, you know, it's not a region that's significantly larger
than the cash is right now in for
Don't actually know what the cache size is on this particular
processor, but I remember it was like a w 5580, right?
And so, you know, on this particular cache on this particular
processor, we could see what the cash was because, you know, usually
they'll list that sort of thing.
Let's see here.
Do they have L1 L2 listed?
I'm gonna have to look at a different place for caches L1 cache size,
for example, how big is it?
There it is.
Halon microarchitecture.
So let's assume that that's somewhat, right?
Although I feel like how can this is a little dis little weird?
I feel like because I don't feel like the cache size is constant for
across all Nehalem 's, right?
Is that actually true?
Maybe it is.
So it might be the old Nehalem, said the exact same L1 and L2 cache
and it's only the L3 cache that changes, right?
But anyway, if you take a look at this, you can see like the L1 cache
is 64k.
The L2 cache is 256 K, right?
So if we thought about how big that was, right?
If we thought about how big that was, how big of a square that was
even just to get, like, a ballpark value, right?
You can imagine, you know, I've got square root of 20.
56.
X 1024 is to, and 56k, and I know that each pixel is is 4 bytes per
pixel, right?
So if I want to know if that's how much pixel area there is or
whatever, right?
That's how big that thing should be.
And you can see it's actually a 256 by 256, 56 square, right?
So 286 by 256 by 4 bytes per pixel that ends up being 20 56k.
So roughly, if we were to take up the entire cache with the frame
buffer,
Obviously, you can't actually do because you need space for the other
stuff like reloading for the textures and these sorts of things.
But basically the size of the L2 cache is actually a 256 by 256 square
of 4 B pixels, right?
So thinking about that for a second that means that you know if we
were to take our current screen like how many tiles across we would
have, what were we?
What were we at?
We're at like a
1820 by 2, right?
We're at 960 right?
So nine sixty divided by 256, right 3.75.
So almost like for across and 1080 / 2540, that's like to in a little
bit across, right?
So like I said, we can't really do that sighs because it's just a
little it'd be a little too big for the cash anyway but I don't really
know exactly how big we would want it to be.
So we'll probably have to play with that size, a little like the only
way to really know I think would probably be to like adjust the size a
little but we can start to see sort of what the size would actually
be.
Right.
Like let's say we did maybe, you know, something like 128 by 128 by 4,
right?
So it was a 64k size and you know, that would be one way we could try
to say well that should fit in the cache.
Very well whatever, right.
So you know, that's an example of how we could do that.
That now we probably wouldn't do it.
Exactly a power of two sides, because we need to eat divided evenly,
sonar 1920, / 2960.
So let's say, we took that 960 right, you know?
And you could imagine dividing that into six chunks, let's say, so
they'd be like 160 is relatively close.
So, let's say, you know, 160, what's 160 divided by the, the sort of
the, the width of
Thing, we know we load for pixels at a time, so that be 40 pixels.
So we could do, I'm sorry about 40 pixels, 40 warps of four pixels.
So we know we could do like, you know, sort of 40 warps across by
however, many Works down.
We wanted to do could be a chunk, right?
So, what I want to do is I want to figure out a way that we can have
the renderer easily break, things up into chunks, and then what I'm
going to do is multi-threading wise, meaning when we actually are
using multiple cores of the processor, I will assign different chunks
to different processor cores.
So they can each work on a different course part separately, but then
the other thing we will do is for hyper threads.
We will treat them specially.
Because what I want to do is I want to maximize the likelihood that
textures hit the cache as well and because of particular H individual
core, right?
You can see on each core, it shares a cash.
So like the L1 cache is shared on the cores.
The L3 cache is shared across course, but the L1 and L2 are only
shared on hyper threads inside that individual core.
So what that means is that
Well, I do care about texture locality with some degree.
You know, I've got four mags 8.
Mags on this particular process.
I think it said eight Meg's.
I've got eight megabytes of backing in the cash for the textures.
That's a lot, but for the frame buffer, I don't have very much
necessarily because if I want to keep that local to the core and I
have hyper-threading, what?
I might want to do is take and try to dice this up in a way where the
pixels getting hit by the hyper.
Kids are like very close to each other in terms of what they need so
that like if a texture is filling it here, it's very likely that one
hyper thread will be like doing these pixels.
The other hyper threat is like doing these pixels.
Just try to do it, right?
See if I can get it to be in that way.
And so what I might want to do is not use rectangular break up for the
hyper threads, maybe what I do for the hyper threads is interleave
scanlines, right?
So basically, like the scan lines on the hyper threads it's actually
doing like like every other scanline is a different, hyper thread or
something like that, right?
Just something to think about.
I don't know if that's a good idea.
I'm just throwing it out there but I was thinking that that might be
better, it might end up being a better way to do it than breaking it
up so that they don't share any of the frame buffer.
And each type of thread does is different one because since I know
they're on the same core, I just think that might be better.
Just a guess.
So, what I was thinking of doing is basically setting up the renderer
so that we have essentially A dispatch which does, you know, render
this rectangle
Render this, you know, sub wrecked basically of the frame buffer and
you're either even lines or your odd lines, right?
This is how it works and then we just dispatch, we have a thing, which
will basically go through and do that.
Across as many things as we want.
So we can basically just set parameters at the top of it.
That's a how many rectangles what their layout is and then it'll issue
even and odd lines of each of those to each core based on, you know,
which ones are on which which which threads are on which core so
that's what I'm thinking, right?
So, we can simulate that pretty easily, right?
I can turn this off for now.
But, well, you know what I can do at the very first thing is, I can
say, well, doing even and odd lines is really pretty easy, right?
All that involves is a pre step two step, you know, one to start one
down, you know, like y Min would just be pre stepped down by one,
right?
So we could basically just do like, you know, if if even or whatever,
if you're the even lines, are the odds,
So I guess if you're the odd lines you know why Min plus equals one
would be about it, right?
So when we do this thing where we do Wyman wax, we just do it that
right?
That be all there is to it and I assume that we're when we do our, I
can't remember exactly where we're doing that.
But remember, yeah, we use y Min so we just work properly.
So
Jimmy.
So, you know, if we take a look at this, that's all we would have to
do to support odd lines.
Is that plus now when we actually step our pixel pitch, you can see
down here where we do buffer pitch, we just have to make buffer pitch.
Be a thing.
That we pre compute differently.
So that right here where we do our I guess our row Advanced might be a
better word to call it.
When we take that buffer pitch we would just take the buffer pitch and
we multiply it by 2, right?
So really, you know, you get a thing where Y is incrementing by 2 and
the buffer reduced twice, the buffer pitch for the row Advance, right?
And that would now draw like basically, you know, almost like
A screen pattern, right?
It's only going to draw every other line when we call this routine.
So if we look at, you know, we should be able to see it happen and
I'll just go ahead and and do Boule 32 odd here, right.
And what we can do is we can just pass through, you know, to do those
lines and what we should see.
Now in theory is when I run this, we should just have every other line
being drawn, right?
Which it just won't draw some of those lines, right?
And you can kind of see that's exactly what it's doing there, right?
It's only drawing every other line.
Although
Looks a little.
Why is it blinking out?
It should, it should always still draw.
Oh, all right.
Yeah, I just realized something that's not quite what I wanted to do
there.
If I say only draw the odd lines, it has to first see, whether it's
odd to figure out, whether it should pre step it, right?
That's that was pretty dumb of me, actually, draw a rectangle quickly
So if I say, I want to draw the odd lines, I first have to see,
whether it's odd or not to know, whether I step, right?
So, what I would actually need to do here is say, like, okay, if I
mod, you know, and Wyman is actually odd, right?
So I would have to say if y Min ma to, I should probably do if even
and why mid mod 2.
That's what that tells me.
Okay, so if I'm supposed to draw the evens, but the why that I was
supposed to say that I was going to start on is actually odd.
Then I have to move to the next line and then I can go right and then
I can do it.
So yeah, okay, so there's that so that's that's more what I was trying
to do here but I still don't understand the flashing.
I feel like I still got one thing.
That doesn't make sense because it should just be.
It should just look exactly.
Like only every other line is.
It's being drawn and I'm not sure.
Why?
That isn't what it looks like, right?
like, I don't understand, like if you look at that, I don't understand
why I'm getting
A yellowed version of the guy here.
And a non yellowed version of the guy here that does not make sense to
me.
Right?
Because what I should be seeing is just an every other line version of
the thing, right?
That's what I should be seeing, I would think.
Now what I can do is make sure that I clear I don't actually know if
we clear the frame of front.
We do, we clear the flavor a so that should be working and doesn't
make super good sense to me.
alright, let's try to figure out why that is
Also, I want to try to draw a rectangle quickly.
If I change it to false, we should see the other lines, right?
Yeah, so that's just not.
I've, I've done it incorrectly.
This is not, I did not do what I wanted.
Oh yeah.
Well, so for even and Run online, we need to add but we need to do the
opposite as well.
So, we kind of need to do.
This is more of an equals, right?
What we need to do is this
we need to say, right?
I don't know how to draw this out in the best possible way here, but
So this is what we do.
This is if we do evens.
And we do odds, right?
And I guess I set this the other way.
So this would be, we had even.
So if even is set to 0 or 1, and if the so the bottom bit is either
set to 0, oops 0 or 1, right?
So this right here is the address that we're writing to or sorry, the
line number
Right, the row number this will call it.
This is our row.
So if the row number is actually even right?
So it's 0 2, 4 6, right?
So this is an even row, right?
Then we want to we want to advance only here, right?
We don't Advance here.
If it was an odd row, then we would want to leave it or we would
Advance here.
So really what I want to show here, right?
Was that what we wanted to do was say if the value passed in for even
matches the value of
That bottom bit then we do it right.
So it's basically like Annie.
It's an equals here.
It's saying you know if even equals true, right right, if even is
true,
Then we want to.
I'll talk to the other way around.
So I guess we do want this to be odd, right?
I want to be able to make it do this, right?
I want to be able to make it be this.
I want to basically say,
I guess I could say not even which would also guarantee that it would
convert it to a 0 or 1 for me.
So that might be fine.
So if not even
equals the actual mod value of this thing, right?
The actual bottom bit, we could also say and one, right?
Whatever that bottom bit is of the road, then we need to advance it.
so,
That should be more what I wanted.
Okay.
So now what I wanted to do for our rectangle quickly is we should be
able to see
Glee This flip back and forth, right?
In theory.
And it still does not seem to be doing it.
What is going on here?
All right.
What is the problem people?
Oh, yeah.
Well why I think it's so many things that I forgot to think about in
that step.
I did.
Forget one obvious thing, which is that we're not pre stepping the
texture.
Probably.
Right.
P and X floor test P.
So first of all, you can't do it there.
Got to do it after we clip.
Right.
Like so, so that has to happen.
That's still not doing it after Eclipse.
Oh, there's all of our processing for that.
So we got to do that.
So that way, it'll happen after the clipping.
And then, where do we preset the texture?
Rho equals buffer memory row, Advanced extra memory.
Okay, so those are just we don't have right?
We don't have to re-type sex anymore because those are using bees.
Alright, so that was probably why we were get.
Yeah, okay, so now we look like what I thought we should look like.
So, it's just because I was doing that in the wrong place, stupidly.
So, there we go.
And now hopefully, when I do my switch, it'll actually work the way I
wanted it to
Which is that we should see the other rows.
There we go.
So that's what I actually wanted.
So now, that's good.
Alright, so now we're drawing every other row, right?
Which means that I feel like I should be able to do this where I can
draw twice in a row with the two separate ones and you can see that I
get out the full composite result, right?
So that's good.
Our cycle counts are wrong now.
So I should probably fix that so that we don't make a mistake.
So in draw rectangle quickly.
We, you know, in order to not actually have two time each time through
the loop so that we wouldn't affect things negatively.
This value, this is actually wrong now.
So we're actually doing half of these right?
So that's the way that goes right?
And there's also another thing here which is that, if the if the Y Min
well I'll do it since it's not super expensive.
I'll do it up here.
I'll also do if y min
Tweet, we Loop through to thing.
Equal to Y Max.
So if in here y Min was actually greater than I mean.
They like the only thing I'm worried about here is basically if that
pre step movement actually were to move y, Min to be greater than 1 x.
This would miscount want to put it to do here.
Clamp counters.
Right?
We want to clamp our counter ad.
In fact, I'm going to put that
I'm going to put that actually in the
handmade platform.
I'm going to put that in the actual block enter stuff.
because if the clamp counter is so that if a calc
Is this a clamp and time, but counted, so that, if we're if the calc
is wrong, it won't overflow.
The thing we can do here is people were asking on the forums for this
just to give them an easier time of compiling other platforms.
I think there were saying doing the our dtsc they were asking if we
could make the intrinsic stuff different.
They were saying that basically x86 intron was what was necessary.
I don't know if you maybe we can do that on all the platforms.
No, I guess not.
So you know,
you could do something like this for them.
And hope that that works, I don't know if it will.
But that'll give him something to play with.
First of all, they can do it.
Oh, and I guess we could do this we go.
Could even do something like this.
We could issue an error right.
Is that the right way to do it?
See here.
It might be a pragma error.
Preprocessor error.
Lb are directive.
So if you want to emit an error we can do it this way like you can
see.
So we could say that if none of these were here it's like
You know.
SSE.
Neon optimizations are not available for this platform yet, Pilar.
Just so it knows.
Okay.
So,
not that we have neon optimizations for anything, but still
So yeah.
Now that we've got that and we've got our counter working properly.
Now now we've got it so that we can do every other line, which is
good.
And so the other thing I'd like to do is make it so that we can
properly do the frame buffer split up in those ways as well.
So, in order to do that, what I need to do is I need to make it so
that when we draw the bitmap, the clipping is not based on the buffer
but on something else.
So inside draw a rectangle quickly you can see here how we do this,
right?
It
X-Men xmax ymin and ymax to these four values all we would have to do
if we want to clip to a smaller rectangle is set those two different
things right.
In fact I shouldn't have Shrunk the window.
I shouldn't have explained it the window up because we can see right
here the results of it, right?
So if I want to, I can switch over, I can say oh you know what?
Oh well actually this is the inverse this finds the rectangle.
So it's a sorry it's this part right here, right?
Here's what we do.
Are clamping.
So if I wanted to I can just introduce here some new values, right?
Which is like you know like say our car clip X-Men clip climb in
Like so perfect.
Max the climax and I can just put those in here in instead of the
other values, right?
So I can just do this is going to be clip X-Men.
And clip Wyman.
That clip X-Men.
Clip xmax.
WiMAX.
there we
So, if I put that in there now, we should get it basically the exact
same result if I run it.
So that's good.
And you can see that it's doing the same thing.
But now, what I can do is say, oh, you know, I really didn't want to
do the upper corner or whatever, right and you can see that.
Now we're only doing this one region of the screen and I can say oh
yeah like really I just I just only want to do this 1256.
I mean what?
One 128 by 128 chunk, right?
And now, it's only rendering that piece, right?
Which is what we wanted.
Pretty straightforward, right?
Pretty simple stuff.
So, that's good.
The only thing I'm a little weirded out by the edge motion there.
Because I'm not sure why that edge should be moving.
That should not be happening.
I don't like that.
Why are we getting that behavior?
We're doing our clipping, we're doing our even odd which is fine
because that has nothing to do with it.
But why are we not filling the entire rectangle?
Every time?
Because we should basically have everything that wants to fill in
there should be filling in there?
I don't understand why that's the case.
It's like are stepping over over.
Xmax is not quite correct.
I'm not sure what's going on there.
I am not sure.
So let me take a look here.
What something that will.
Yes, you can kind of see.
So I feel like What's Happening Here is we're being too conservative
on like the right hand side clipping.
Right?
It's like it's not actually always doing.
The right number of things.
Now,
Okay, so I think I get what's going on here.
So okay now that actually makes perfect sense.
So what's happening here is just that since we're writing by 4 pixels
every time but we're not actually writing by 4 pixels aligned to where
the clip buffer starts.
It's wherever the texture starts, we'll go over by that many.
however,
Need, the alignment is off.
That's interesting.
So, with that suggests to me, is that either because will want this to
line up properly, right?
We don't want once we break these up into chunks and assign them to
different cores.
We don't want to cores writing into the same memory because they may
overlap improperly, right?
So we don't want to do that.
We want them to be perfectly clipped.
So either if we, if we want to continue doing this unaligned right,
then what we would need to do.
You is when we get to the end, right?
And we actually would probably aligned to the end and do it at the
beginning.
We probably do the first time through the loop.
We would preload the first time through the loop weed.
Preload the mask for writing to be something you and in where it's
it's got that those first few pixels, masked out so that it doesn't
write them.
that's what we would probably do there, but
The question is, do we just want to always right aligned anyway?
Right, that's the other question.
Do we just want to try and always right aligned because maybe aligned
rights would be faster and we don't know because we haven't tried
that.
So what we can do is we could do a quick test to see right here.
We are running around.
It's all bundle.
Oh fun.
You can see it happening here.
Okay.
Why is our count wrong now?
Did I miss something?
Our count is now totally bogus.
How did our count get busted?
You see what I'm looking at, right?
Why are we getting one cycle per pixel all of a sudden?
What's going on there?
I don't understand, there's no way to get one cycle per pixel.
That's not even, theoretically possible.
So that's just a bogus value but I don't actually know why we're
getting said, bogus value,
Because this is still the right number, right?
That were passing, we're passing in half.
The why span X-Men - yeah, right.
And we're just dividing by 2 the number that we're submitting for
process pixel.
And it was working.
I mean it worked properly when we did it before.
So like something is busted now where our counts are totally are
totally irrelevant.
Yes, which I don't get.
so, I suppose
That is exact.
Well, you know what, that probably is, probably exactly the thing that
I said it was.
It's probably that when this thing gets clipped the weinman in the,
why Mac this actually becomes like a negative number.
And then this goes backwards.
Let's go ahead and find out if that's the case.
You know what, I just realized I realized something else.
I mean, there's so many things, I think, normally when I don't, when I
only see him for an hour, things are kind of compressed.
I'm thinking about all these things in the code now, because I'm like
in the code for long enough, you know, what else?
I just realized, we were running our assertions when we were looking
at the Deep at the code.
Like, until I replaced those fetches.
The assertions were actually in there, right?
Because we didn't actually take out our assertions, did we?
Like handmade internal in handmade, slow are still set.
Right, all we were doing is flipping 02.
So basically the assertions that were for on the fetches, we're still
in there and somehow because they were basically branches that never
actually occurred, I guess somehow they were never costing us
anything.
Or the compiler, somehow magically was able to figure out that, it
couldn't possibly happen because of the min max, I don't even know,
but that was kind of weird.
All right.
Well, it doesn't really matter point.
Being
What I want to do here is an end time.
Block counted for a second.
I want to go ahead and see if what I just said is actually the case
but I suspect that it is.
In fact I can just go ahead and do it in here.
Let's go ahead and do build up at and I'll do 02 d.
and,
yeah, so when I step into here,
Or not.
Why are we not break pointing?
Hello.
Hello, mr.
Code.
I would like you to break those out the wrong.
That's right.
Darkness slowly.
All right, my bad.
Draw a rectangle slowly.
Here we go.
So if you step in here, I assume that's what I will find.
Go to disassembly is that this value is actually wrong, right?
Like this value is actually getting to be negative, so, let's actually
find out if that is the case.
So there's the moles
and let's see, we have
To do.
We have to do.
What is it actually increment this value.
Let's take a look here.
So that is in our debug counters, right?
So, this is in global memory.
What's that actually called global global cane memory?
Debug level memory.
That's in debug level memory.
Here's our counters.
Here's the actual cycle count that we're looking for their I guess,
right?
Because this number three is the one we're talking about.
So as we come through here, that one actually worked with the hit
count.
So the hit counts, what we're looking for.
It's at six.
Six, nine, two four.
Yeah, so it's just incrementing the cycle count, but the hit count.
Is bogus.
My thing is that should
Ah no I bet.
So if those are you at 32 s?
Probably it just becomes very large negative and at some point and
wraps around or something like that you can see it happening.
See the hit count going down.
So the hit count, probably keeps going down because it produces a
negative number because it overflows the negative number.
Yeah.
Then probably wraps the hit count around until it's you know, goes
down below zero.
You can see it going down, right?
Goes down below zero and then it's a huge value.
Crap, didn't mean to type key there.
I wish you could tell that Visual Studio.
Like I would absolutely love a way to say do not.
Let me edit any code in here.
I never edit any code.
Just only show me the code.
So yeah.
So what we need to do in here is we need to just have a thing that
that's wise about that, right?
And not sure how we exactly
They want to do that, but I will probably want to do it in here so we
can actually do something like, you know pixel count.
And here is the pixel count.
Right?
And what I'll do is I'll just wrap it in an if
so, if x max
It's greater than equal to X Men and WiMAX is greater than equal to Y
Min.
Then do it.
Count.
Thank you compiler, for catching that.
So, now we shouldn't be having this ridiculous - naskh.
And hopefully, we
Our cycle count back, that's good.
That's what our debug said, count should look like.
And if we turn on O2, we should see it back down in the 30 to 40
range.
Like, it was supposed to be
Yeah.
All right.
Okay, so that's what we want and that's a good thing.
So now what we want to do is we pretty much want to just be able to
pass that in, and then we're pretty much done.
And the renderer we can multi-thread it.
We can start monitoring on a Monday.
The renderer will have the ability to sort of spam those things out to
different places, right?
So draw a rectangle quickly.
It takes that clipping.
It will need to get this passed into it and then we need to go figure
out what we want to do with that alignment stuff.
Right.
Maybe we'll do that tonight, too.
We're on it.
We're on, we're kind of going.
We're going for it, you know, sometimes you got to go for it.
I don't know how long we've been programming now.
Two hours.
Maybe.
So let's see.
So we've got these guys here, they do the clipping.
So we just need to make sure that this can be passed in.
We don't have right now.
A rectangle structure, that's in integer space which might be kind of
nice because that's kind of what we're doing here, right?
You know, if we had a rectangle to I that was basically like a you
know, just something that worked like this where it was like you know,
the sort of thing.
Might be easier for us to deal with because then we could kind of pass
these around and not have to have so many different things here.
And we could also just make a thing that does clipping with them.
So that like, you know, we don't have to repeat this kind of code all
the time would also be kind of nice just so there's, there's some
stuff like that.
That's kind of just, I don't know.
It's just it's it's handy.
Let's say.
So maybe we want to do that and maybe we want to do something like
this like cliprect, you know?
And so we do this.
And replace these guys.
and then what that would look like is that's just like, you know,
cliprect Minix Chipwrecked and why the brecht
Max X.
Kappa rekt, Maxwell.
Same here.
Graham x y x, x x y.
We go.
And off we go with our little rectangle and then we want to do is we
just want to make that into an actual thing, right?
I don't know where I'm
Put that actually may be down here.
Okay.
So, I want to grab this and I want to put this in here and I want to
do something where I can basically say, like girl, right, you know,
rectangle to I, you know, intersect so I get the intersection of two
of these rectangles, right?
And I can do something where I intersect one rectangle, to eye with
another rectangle to eye.
And it'll do that computation this this thing here.
You know.
Just seems like a good thing to do.
So what I want to do is I want to do this now where I just say you
know, a
xyxy and then this is like be
Right.
And then, you know, I guess this is really a result kind of thing.
So I can say result, Min x equals result in y equals result.
Max x equals result, Max y equals
And I can just look at whichever one of these is greater.
So to produce the new Min, what I want to do here is I want to
Be able to pick.
Whichever one I want, okay.
So in this case, so we basically if we're talking about rectangles,
right?
We've got two fundamental operations that we might want to do their
basic exact same with just one thing flipped, right?
We'll come back to that one second, right?
So if I have a rectangle,
And some other rectangle.
There's two things I might want to produce.
I might want to produce the enclosing rectangle.
Right?
So if this is a and this is B, I might want to produce this rectangle
here and that's the union operation, right?
That unify that like, makes something that that is the combination of
the two, maximally encloses, all of the area of both of them and some
extra area potentially or I might want their overlap, right?
This part right here and that's the intersection.
For clipping.
What we typically want is the intersection because we have like a
screen or an area of a screen and then a Sprite or something.
And we want to know what part we need to actually operate on where
they are, where they, where are they both?
But other times, we might want to do other operations where we're
trying to do stuff where we want to know, like, oh, I have to process
something and I want to press it only once, but it needs to
Over the entire area of like two different Sprites, I might want to
Union them together or something, right?
That's what you can see is really all these two operations are are
either taking the minimal or maximal versions of each of the
components.
So, like here is the Min X of ay.
And here is the Min X of B.
If I want the union of them, I want, whichever one is less, right?
So if this were the Union operation, right?
You know, if I'm doing Union,
I want whichever one of these is going to be less.
So if a if a has the Lesser Min X, right?
Then that's the one that I want for the Union.
Actually do this here.
If the Minix, what am I saying here?
Let's see, this is the Min y.
This is the max X then the max, why they're gonna transfer more time.
Let's try that one more time.
Alright, so if a has the Lesser Min X then we're going to take it
right where I'm sorry that's a if a had the Lesser my next we're gonna
take it if B has a lesser known as right the first time that's B's.
This is Ace.
So
Whichever one has the Lesser, my next, we're going to take it a has a
lesser, my next, we're going to take that.
If be had, the less Terminex, like I was out here, we would take that
to produce the union.
So to everyone's less we would take similarly them.
In, why the max we want to take, whichever one's higher right?
We want to take, whichever one would enclose the most amount of area
and so that's what we did here as well, right?
If the max X is greater, I'm sorry, the max X is greater, we take that
otherwise, not now for the intersection we wanted to ask with the
exact opposite, right?
We want to take whichever one of these values is actually going to be
greater, right?
So if the Min X, we take the two men X's, we want to produce whoever
is going to be higher so that we use the least, we want take the least
amount of air because we want to make sure we start on.
Whoever would start last night whoever would start first, right?
And so really all we're doing here is we're doing the exact same thing
only with the sense changed around, right?
We're just we're just picking the opposite person's thing.
Based on which is going on, right?
So those are those two operations, right?
So now, if we take a look at what's Happening Here,
You can basically see that what we were doing here is saying well okay
we want to do the intersection here.
So we were saying whoever is one is less, we'll take it.
We know that X-Men is already set to something in particular so we're
just going to say if clip rect mx's was going to be higher than it
right?
We want to take that because it's the intersection.
So we want to take whoever was higher and so here's our intersection
right?
This takes whoever was
Abby was higher.
In this case, I'm either section case if we were doing the union and
grabbing the whole thing, we would have done it the other way around.
So yeah.
So you can imagine that doing that this way where we have the the like
the fill wrecked, right?
And the fill wrecked is X Min y Min xmax ymax like so right you can
then imagine us doing rectangle to or just fill wrecked equals
intersect, cliprect Phil wrapped and that would just give us that
intersection of them.
And then obviously at the moment since we're not using the rectangles
through the pipe, although I guess we could now, right?
So now we could let's just go ahead and take X-Men everywhere that it
occurs right?
You can see where X Min occurs here we could just go ahead and replace
all of those with the fill wrecked version.
So let's go ahead and replace X-Men with Phil wrecked dot Min EX
Right.
Let's go ahead and replace.
Where are we here?
Where's my feel wrecked?
There it is.
Let's go ahead and replace y Min with Phil wrecked Min.
Why
Oops, didn't quite mean to do it there and gotten there yet.
So, let's go ahead and replace.
Why Min Oops, why Moon fill wrecked and why?
X, max.
Same thing.
Place xmax go wrecked, XX.
And then finally we would want to do.
Let's see, let's see why Max Phil wrecked Max.
Why?
All right.
So, oops, that's no good.
so now we've got it working off of the rectangle which is good and if
I go into there and I take a look at what's going on here,
I can say, well, we're doing all this with the Phil wreck stuff.
We could actually do a couple other things here.
Oh, we've got a to do, remove this to, let's do that tonight to before
we go anywhere else.
So what I could do to is I've got down here, right?
I want to get the area of this thing.
I could make that a thing to get the pixel count, right?
I could do something where I just divide by 2, whatever is
the like Get Wrecked area.
Get clamped wrecked area you know so it's not going to be below zero
basically and just pass the fill wrecked and that would be this value,
right?
So then inside handmade math, I can have here.
A thing that's just get clamped wrecked area and that produces a un 32
because it cannot be - let's say.
But I don't know, I think we probably won't stay in in three to four
everything you'll still be clamped but we just won't actually do that.
And so that in here what we can do is
We can actually just do in fact we can just do it this way.
You can just do result equals
Yes, eh, eh eh, eh and we don't do the divide by 2 because that's
specific to that particular routine out there.
So there we go.
So a Max.
Yep.
That's all good.
And then we go ahead and take the pixel count is actually results.
Now, all we have to do is say, if the result is less than zero, the
result equals zero and then we return the result.
So there we go.
Now there is a sort of problematic thing here that I'm going to point
out and I don't know how we want to handle it.
But our convention for rectangles before was that they did not include
their final value.
Right.
In fact, I'm pretty sure we said that so that they could overlap
properly, right?
Not sure where we actually talked about that.
But if you look at the min max here if you say if you if you look at
the operations on the rectangles we essentially had rectangle
operations that would do like overlap tests and the overlap test so
he's used less than on the final pixel, right?
You can see that happening.
So it's kind of broken for us to introduce this other, you know, just
because we're doing some slightly different thing with the integer,
rectangles.
It's kinda messed up in a way to have that one.
Not work that way.
So I do wonder if we want to make that work slightly differently.
Where, you know, we can just sort of rewrite this routine to actually
have it so that it does not work that way.
It's still considered
That final one not there and then we would get rid of like these plus
ones and all of this stuff would actually use the Max's and so on.
So I feel like that's probably the right thing to do.
So I'm going to go ahead and try it.
And if we hit some reason, why we don't want to do that, then we
cannot do that, right?
That seems like a good idea.
Now, in with Mac's here, we're not using those in this routine.
We think so those were for the lighting stuff, so I'm going to get rid
of those in here.
We go.
And, and we have these to do is to hear like, we haven't actually
finished with the row alignment and stuff like that either.
So, stuff like that.
We have to do fixed cast, why?
I don't know.
This stuff is not used anymore in this routine.
All right.
so,
So, what we want to do here is change this around so that we're
actually not doing not assuming that the max is actually in anymore.
And so in order to do that properly, that's actually not that hard,
right?
I mean basically all were doing here is is treating these values like
that instead and that's it.
So that's really not all that.
All that interesting.
How is this Min EX?
That's pretty funny.
If we change that one over anyway, doesn't matter.
We'll take care of that in a second.
So if we got these to the width and the height here, and we start
treating this way we come through here, and we're actually doing this.
The, the key here is just that.
Now when we're actually testing these guys, we need to test them,
that's good drive me nuts.
So I gonna I'm gonna have that
Change that just temporarily that would drive me insane.
If it just that one is written that way.
It's a little OCD there.
But what do you do?
So, the problem here is now we come through here.
Everything else will work fine, right?
Everything else that comes in here is actually pretty straightforward,
because everything else that we did in here, really, the only
difference right is that this would happen, that's it right?
We would just we wouldn't work on that last guy.
That's that's all there is.
So that's pretty straightforward and you know, these become this way
and then you know, that's it.
So it's really not particularly difficult to change.
The only thing that actually has to change
Um that I'm thinking of at the moment.
Anyway, is this thing right here that produces the extents because
what happens is this thing?
Doesn't actually consider that it assumes that it's going to touch
that last pixel.
The CLX pixel here.
And of course, it's not, that's not actually going to do that.
So
Let's take a look at this for a second.
It floors X and then ceilings X, so that's fine.
So, the floor X is in ceiling.
X is all, we would really have to do is make sure that the ceiling is
incremented by 1.
I think that's really all we have to do, so that's the floor.
I think that's it.
I don't think there be anything else, but don't quote me on that.
So,
Looks pretty reasonable.
That looks pretty, pretty, okay, to me.
So we'll go ahead and clip that out.
All right, so what's going on here?
Next x, max y, result result, equals 0.
Results.
Okay, so
what is actually, although, What's Happening Here
I have gone and broken it again.
Check it out.
We're back down.
20 Cycles.
Don't know how I keep breaking this.
That's kind of absurd.
When you think about it.
I shouldn't have this much trouble, keeping that working.
But apparently, I do, I do not know why.
Let's take a look and see.
Clamp platform.
So, we passed the count in here, right?
And we add the count, you know, the count to it.
You know, what I could do here also is just quickly do cert count
greater than equal to 0.
Okay, so that does not seem to be the problem.
There we go.
So yeah, so our for some reason, we're not getting the right value out
of here, because the hit count is drastically higher than the cycle
count that we're taking.
And so, I'm not sure why that is happening.
I do not understand why we were getting such a high hit rate there.
So let's go ahead and take a look at what I messed up.
Cuz let's not let's not mince words.
Here people.
I am the person who did it, right?
I broke it.
It was me, there's really no question about that.
So, coming here
And let's take a look, should be able to step into that.
What's the result here?
845?
So that reasonable Min x, max X.
Oh, no, no.
So this was total East.
Yes, that's, that's totally wrong.
I tried to take a shortcut there but that's totally wrong.
So, if both of these are negative, they'll multiply into a positive.
So you can't actually write you can't cheat.
I tried to cheat and you see what happens to cheaters, right?
They get punished, it's actually true in the real world.
Most of the time cheaters do just fine.
What we
All the financial services industry.
In America, I don't know.
And also in London.
Know, if you guys have that wherever you're listening out there, if
you guys also have people who primarily make their money by cheating.
So if we go in here, we need me at now to say, we need to make sure
that our with and our height are both greater than 0 and then and only
then can we actually multiply them together and actually produce the
result for the rectangle area?
Okay.
So that should, hopefully maybe for lucky that should potentially give
us.
Well, I don't know what it will give us, but hopefully it'll give us
something correctly.
Yeah, that looks like brick, debug cycle town again, and
Let's see if we can get a reasonable 02 cycle.
Count again again.
Yes, does look, okay.
So, all right, so we're not, we're not too messed up, okay?
So
Now that we've done that and change that into something, that's a
little more systemize there, we've got a wreck stuff going.
We can go ahead and hoist this up a little bit further potentially,
right?
And so what I could do is I could say, you know we've got this clip,
rect in this fill wrecked we could basically what this routine is
doing, right.
What I mean with this Loop is doing is all.
It's just trying to go through and it's
Trying to take each individual point of the four corners of our
potentially rotated texture map that we're you know, our Pepsi rotated
quad that we're texture mapping and it's trying to make sure that it
gets the Min and Max bounds of those.
So in order to do it that way, if we want to keep doing it that way
which is fine.
I mean this isn't a, this is probably not going to be a critical part
of the, the performance of the application or anything.
If we want to keep doing it that way, what we could do is just have a
thing that's like expand rectangle to include point or something,
right?
And we could say that we would like, you know, our fill wrecked to be
expanded to include 4, x 4 y,
Right?
And we would like it to be include.
See Lex and seal why, right?
And, you know, we could do it that way.
The downside to doing that is that we lose the fact that we know that
we only care about the sidedness of it.
So I don't know if we really want to do it that way.
It's a little weird to say the least what we could do.
At the very least is Loftus up one higher so do something.
This.
And just access the things out of this.
So now we're just doing basically with Max height, Max 00, something,
right?
And we get rid of these guys all together.
So we could do that.
That's not too big of a deal.
It's not actually doing anything useful at all.
Oops,
Right.
So yeah, now we do have one more thing we have to check,
unfortunately.
This is one of those things that, you know, I wish we didn't have to
check but we've seen it already happened once before and so I got to
do it just to make sure.
But let's go ahead and do this now.
Every now and again, the reason I'm doing this is just so we can use
reuse this code a little more easily because we're going to have to
clip everything.
Like we're going to have to clip all the different functions that we
do, they'll have to clip to this all the rendering function.
So we need to make sure that we add clipping for our like rectangle
outlines and all that sort of stuff, right?
But so what I was saying is what we need to check here is that putting
these things in a structure, doesn't confuse the optimizer, right?
So what I'm going to do is I'm going to go ahead and and just take a
look at this, right?
So you take a look at that?
It's 43 Cycles, right?
Or whatever per hit, and let's take a quick Gander at it here as well.
Do we still have that on?
No.
It's cool.
It looks like we can just leave that on and somehow it doesn't
actually bother the the runtime of the thing either at the moment
anyway.
So yeah, so we're doing that and that's all good.
But I also wanted to kind of see what what it was here if we take the
count of it right 160 95.
So 117 Cycles, right?
And so I just wanted to see if if we have any, if there, if it
confuses the compiler.
So I just wanted to see if we
Took out any accessing of Phil wrecked from the actual Loop, right?
Meaning this this code right here, I just wanted to make sure that
that went away
Right.
So that if I took this out,
It didn't actually affect the runtime performance in any in any
particular way, right?
So Min why you'll spill wrecked lime in
I know why I was in the habit of reversing those
There we go.
So I just want to see if that has any adverse effects.
Basically doesn't look like it does on the run time there.
And it does well.
It definitely had an adverse effect on the runtime.
I mean, not the actual runtime but it confuse the compiler.
The fact that we because 117 before and it's 113 now.
So unfortunately, it does look like we'll have to even if we like sort
of pull out the reusable code at the front end into some useful
structs.
I don't know that will actually be able to access them directly
because it looks like it's confused about that even though it's just a
stack variable, looks like a confused.
All right.
Okay, so a couple of things we could do here, we have a remove this.
And I'm assuming that the reason that we have a remove, this is
because this pixel PX thing.
We could just keep as a wide value in incremented every time at least
I'm assuming
That's what we, that's what I meant by remove this.
But yeah.
So it also looks like origin X for X.
So we could just roll all the thin, right?
So instead of using Min X at all, what we couldn't do here is just
say, all right, we've got a.m.
128.
The M 128 is, is called pixel p x, right?
And pixel p x doesn't get modified in the loop anywhere, right?
It just gets incremented this way.
Oh wait.
We
Oh okay, so it does never mind.
So what we need to do here is we need to introduce a new thing which
is like pixel p x on the for the row and that's just going to be set
to whatever that y Min is right.
So basically I'm sorry, whatever the that mean X is in this way.
So we're going to do this once still to get it initialized to what we
were actually starting with as a value, right?
we're going to do that, and
Because that's always going to be that first value.
But then what we're going to do is every time through here, we don't
actually need to re
Well actually guess we don't really need to do this at all right.
This is just, this is just, this is all
This is all just obvious stuff.
The compiler probably already did this.
I would hope as it should have been pretty obvious, but just in case,
so we can get rid of that because this is always initialized to the
correct value.
So really we're just taking this and subbing out the origin, right?
Like so and really we could have just subtracted the origin there.
Do we ever even use origin X for X again?
No.
So really we could just set this once, right?
Something like this.
I feel like and then just get rid of origin for
Entirely.
The moment because unless we set aside to do the whole Preamble and
somebody at some point, which we could decide to do, but it probably
isn't necessarily worth it.
There's just no point in even doing that wide because we only do that
there and that's it, right?
That's that's the end of that.
So that's fine.
Pixel P.
Why we could also do that way?
I don't know if it's useful to do it that way, but we absolutely
could.
I also don't know why on Earth we were doing this as a sub PS?
That's just ridiculous.
Because if you're already doing this as a set, why I don't know why
you wouldn't just do it this way, again, more Ridiculousness in our
Loop.
But yeah.
So we can take a look at that in a second.
So, there we go.
Let's take a quick look.
117 Cycles.
So how did that go back up?
What did we do that made that go back up
So I guess saving this register was actually worse than setting it
every time, right?
I mean that's what that appears to be.
The case.
Am I wrong about that?
Like it looks like setting that having it have to remember that
register was actually bad.
It would rather have just used this value which I guess it already
needed to have, right and go from there.
That's what it looked like, I don't know, but that would it look like.
So if that's the case, that's fine, you know, we don't have to argue
about it.
We can just do it this way.
And that's fine.
Let's see if it prefers that.
That didn't change it at all.
Which also doesn't make any sense.
So, how is this possible?
Someone explain to me what is going on there?
That is the compiler is just doing weird stuff.
At this point.
I feel like because why would that actually matter
That does not make any sense to me, why that would matter.
It just seems very strange.
Very, very strange.
Hmm.
I don't get it people.
I really don't.
I don't understand why that, why?
It's the compiler should not have been able to produce the exact same
code, right?
But it couldn't it didn't it had 113 Cycles here.
And then when you try to do it the other way, it didn't it couldn't do
that, right?
So that's pretty strange.
So it really wants.
It just it would prefer, right?
It to look.
Like this, that's what it would like to see.
According to the minimum coming through here anyway, right?
113 Cycles.
So it would really like it to look like this.
So we'll leave it like that.
That's what I want.
I'm not going to tell you.
I'm not going to tell you what else you should do.
Because remember, this isn't even.
This part of the code is not even getting counted by this.
So what that was meaning is that are critical.
Poor are the part of our Loop gets executed.
Most often rearranging, what was happening here, was causing it to
have a problem doing the optimization, whatever optimization it was
doing on Pixel py hoisting.
Because presumably pixel P Y, which is constant across the loop right
across the inner loop.
They can hoist out these two moles.
Right?
It can do that.
That's the only thing that pixel py actually multiplies by right?
So it can hoist out those two moles, but why hoisting out those two
moles was getting so much harder for it when I did the other way, I'm
not actually sure.
So, maybe we'll take a brief look at that just to see right.
We're getting that 113, 20 Cycles, let me hoist that out and see what
starts happening as I play with that.
So this is, you know, PP m, xor p y and x or something, no, we're
going to call that and this is py and why
That's just those two values, right?
So there's there's the X.
There's the why.
P YN X py NY and presumably now literally all I've done is waste out
exactly what.
Presumably the compiler was already hoisting out.
And yes, so it stays the same so that's what I would expect.
And so now the question is, okay, pixel py, right?
Which is getting set?
Once here we do them all.
I don't understand.
Okay, so let's say, I just look at it like this, right?
And here's that pixel py stuff, I check it out, I'm 113, 20 cycles and
now all I want to do is I don't want to just subtract origin .y in
here.
How bad is that, right?
How about how much do you dislike that?
You just like it quite a bit.
You just like it by 3 Cycles.
So you really don't want to have to do that.
You want to do this for some reason.
I don't know the reason but for some reason,
Okay.
So the Y value is only used in this Loop in that one place.
So how about I try a different tact and I just asked you to go between
these two values
Like so right, let's say I was to do that.
So I'm going to go ahead and say that these actual values here are
going to be this way, right?
Because that'll still Loop over the same actual pixels because I'm not
changing the actual pointer.
It'll still do the same number of iterations, but the multiply has
been folded in, right?
Does that make some sense?
And so then we just eliminate this all together, we're just doing a
set 1, PS, that's it.
Oh, I can't quite do that, can I?
Because that's a floating point value.
Wow.
That's that's that's why right?
Because we're trying to compute the texture coordinates there.
Mmm-hmm
Well.
It was complaining about, sorry.
I didn't mean to leave that in there.
Well.
I mean, I could try to Loop over a floating point value.
I don't know if I love that idea though.
Right?
I mean yeah, hard to say.
Wait.
How do we go back 216?
How do we go back?
How do we just go backwards people?
What?
What happened?
How did that happen?
I didn't do anything.
This is the way we had it before, right?
Before I did anything.
That's what it was, right.
What?
That's the same code.
That was like exactly the same code.
Okay.
I'm very interested to know.
Mr.
Fancy pants here.
What was the typo or the slight change that caused the compiler, to
not do it that way?
All right, got texture.
Memory of got the Phils, get the process pixel.
X Y.
Pixel p.
Y can set one origin, y 4x.
What's the difference?
Oh, that's the problem.
Okay.
It was just because since I had still, I had not allowed the actual
guy to complete.
It was just holding the dll open, so it didn't rewrite it.
Okay, that's fine.
I thought I was going crazy there for a second.
But basically what happens is, when I had it open, like I did, the
more, this is Hope holding the dll open for some reason, this guy
doesn't close the dll after it's done with the analysis, and it's
printing it out so that that's fine.
It would be nice if that weren't the case, but it is the case.
So that's what we're gonna do.
I could do it like this.
I suppose W, temp dot out.
And then try to do a more on tempt at out.
I don't know if that'll work.
Work groups.
There we go.
So let's try that actually, I should probably do it.
Temp, temp, dot out.
So,
Okay, so let's see if that works.
So if I hold that open now and I can pile, I should be fine.
Yeah.
So just going to an intermediate files.
Fine, that's totally fine.
Let me delete that though.
I didn't mean to put one you need to put temp that out in the root
directory there so that's fine.
And I'd like to capture that this should just be a line that we do.
Basically that should just be a bin because we're going to want to do
that periodically.
So what I'm going to do is I'm going to throw that into the Mist
directory and I'm going to go ahead and make that in here where we do
like you know, where we do a like clot NH m dot bat.
I'll do the Nehalem.
Right.
And so what that's going to do is that's going to, I don't know where
will actually run it, so I guess we'll maybe just leave it like that
for now.
Yeah, so this way if I just go in hm I get it and it's good, just do
that anytime I want.
All right, we'll see that like that for now.
Think about how that should go later.
Okay, so if I do all that
Kind of surprising doesn't look like, there's a whole lot of ways we
can do anything that doesn't make the compiler for feel worse, really?
About what it's doing than what?
It's what it's doing already, so that's just Jimmy,
That's just the way it goes.
I guess.
So I think we may be down to just thinking about that alignment
problem.
And so, the alignment is, is basically let's just go over this real
briefly.
We talked about it a little bit, but alignment just means that when
we're writing the stuff,
You know, we've got these 128-bit wide vectors right.
Hello mr.
Chief wake up.
Okay.
So we've got these 128-bit wide registers, right it inside.
Then.
We've got four pixels.
Here's pixel 0 yours.
Pixel one, pixel to pixel three.
And we're writing these out to memory.
And right now what we're doing is we're writing them on a lined, which
means that if you imagine memory was broken up, starting from B 0.
Right, if you imagine it was broken up into bites.
You would basically have every 128 bits starting from the very
beginning of memory starting, every 128 bits, you would essentially
have a chunk.
So, here is 8, Bits 8, B 8, B 8, right?
Like here we go.
8, 8 8, 8, 8, 8, 8, 8, 8, 8, 8 and here is 128-bit boundary right?
Or 16 bytes boundary.
And then we go again, eight.
And there's a boundary
So these boundaries are absolute in memory space.
It doesn't care where you think things start there, literally
absolute.
So, if you were to take a look at the pointer value, right?
The pointer value is going to be something like.
Okay, so this is never, we're never gonna get a pointer here because
you low memory is not mapped in this way ever because you know, the
null address is 0, right?
But let's say you had a pointer with a value of 7, right?
So that's the seventh bite right here is 0 1 2.
2, 3 4, 5 6 7, I should say it's the eighth B numerically.
So we're pointing into here.
So the question is, if I was going to do 128 bits of writing right?
16 b 1 2 3 4 5 6 7 8 9 10 11 12 13 14 15 16 so write that.
What you can see is this is unaligned in the sense that some portion
of the right that will occur happens in one of these buckets that is
broken up.
Absolutely.
And the rest of the right happens in the next bucket.
So we've got two essential, you know, anytime we do 128-bit, right?
There's only two ways that that can really happen.
One way is we're perfectly in only one bucket so we start on B 0 B 16
or something.
Mod 16 we start right there so that we write entirely into one bucket.
Or we straddle two, buckets is the other way, and we can't ever
straddle three buckets because 100 because the buckets are the same
size of the, right.
So we can't possibly get more than two buckets, but we can get either
one or two buckets that we have to touch.
And the processors depending on which processor you're talking about,
like these more or less meaning.
Sometimes the processor doesn't really care.
If you write things underlined right in the old days, that really
certainly wasn't anything.
Anyone thought about because processors could only write things at a
size at one size and like, you know, things could only write a bite.
There was no such thing as being like, unaligned on the bike, right,
or whatever.
But when things go out to starting to work on,
Or B, like 32 bits.
There are processors that were like, okay, if the 32 bits happens to
be aligned on a 32-bit boundary for B, right?
It could go a little faster let's say because it doesn't have to think
about it as much.
Maybe you're one of the processors like working with 32 bits at a
time.
It was easier for it.
If they all kind of slot it in together or something and that's been
true all throughout history since then, you know, you pretty much have
this case where
As the processor deals with wider and wider stuff some processors have
an easier time dealing with operations that line up with memory along
the boundaries of, however, why those values are.
And that's a situation that we want to investigate.
Now is this this picture situation now in some processors, that's
extraordinary.
Ali important on other processors.
It's not so important.
And so it's always kind of a balancing act that.
Did you do there?
So, the first thing we can do to test this, right?
It's we could just align our X-Men's so that we're and xmax is so that
we're always aligned basically, right?
So what we could do is we could say, you know, we've got this robe
pointer here, right?
We could just cheat for a second and say, let's pretend we were always
aligned.
So let's look at this guy here and we'll look at the this this is kind
of a it's a pretty janky way of doing this, but I'm just going to do
it briefly
It's running at like 38 Cycles right now, right?
Let me just run it.
You know, let's run it without the the clipping to because we want a
bigger test case here.
So our clip, rect is just going to be, you know, the whole screen.
All right, so there we go.
There's the guy.
We'll just do it straight forward here.
Seven Cycles, right?
You can see that's what we're getting.
So if we come through here and we now, say all right, this row pointer
the place that we're going to be reading and writing from now.
Remember, there's really not much we can do about alignment on
Textures, right?
Because the textures were randomly accessing stuff.
Right?
Straight out of them.
There's not a whole lot we can do about aligning the textures other
than trying to do something, fancier about maybe like the way the
pixels are stored in them or something, I don't know.
But point being there's those are random.
Access.
But the frame buffer is not random acts of.
So what we could do is say, okay let's pretend we were always doing a
line stuff here.
So what we could do is say all right our alignment offset so are
aligned value, right?
Whatever that pointer is look we'll go ahead and grab that pointer.
I think we have you went pointer.
We have a un pointer.
Let's take a look.
We do not.
So we don't know what the, what the pointer size is, unfortunately.
We haven't actually done any work to get that.
And I'm not sure how you'd I don't remember how you do that.
See now has a newfangled way of you can get some of these things.
So what I want to do is is have a UNT pointer and I don't know.
Is that can I just can I just Hail Mary it?
No.
So what is the pointer type?
Let's find out.
They've got to have done this, right?
You wouldn't
You wouldn't go ahead and do this stuff.
I really hope without putting that in there, so let's just assume that
it has that.
So there's I thought I saw it.
Yeah, it pointer.
It's there.
So how do I there it is.
There it is.
In pointer Inuit pointer T.
Well, wait a minute.
That's what I just hope.
I had it backwards.
Sorry.
Okay, so basically what that allows me to do is say I want to change
this to an integer that I can manipulate, but I want it.
It's the same size as whatever the pointer is, right?
So that way on a 64-bit build, it'll be 64 bits and a 32-bit build.
It will be 32 bits since this is a pointer.
So there we go, I get the pointer, I turn the pointer into the thing
and then I just want to look and see if it's if it's 16 B alignment
that we're looking for, right?
That's going to be 2 to the fourth
So, what I want to do is I want to take two to the fourth, right?
16.
And I want to just subtract one from it, right?
Because that would give me all 1, B below where the 16 is, so I can
just look at what the bottom bits are of.
Alignment, right?
So that'll give me essentially whatever.
However, far off this thing is from being alignment for being from
being in alignment.
And then I'm just going to go ahead and just flat-out subtract that
times bitmap bytes per pixel.
I'm just going to flat out move the thing back.
So this is a complete lie.
It's not even going to render the right stuff.
It's just it's fully garbage, right?
Oh dear.
What have I done?
I think I know why that happened but I don't understand why the
debugger crashes.
It's just it's supposed to be the debugger like did it?
Buggers should not crash people God.
Our program Should Crash.
We are the one developing the program.
You're supposed to be done.
Developing your program and it shouldn't crash.
I don't feel like I should have to explain this to you Microsoft.
This is not complicated.
Maybe if you spent less time, installing SQL server on my machine for
your Visual Studio nonsense and more time, making sure that the bugger
didn't crash when debugging a program we wouldn't be in this
situation.
Anyway, point being
I was trying to say,
Was that?
In here, when I'm doing this alignment, right?
The that could step back off the end of the bitmap.
So in order to prevent that I would have to sort of always clip to
something that gives me like, you know, we could just have a whole row
of padding even at the moment, right to do, stop patting by a row.
This is much like what we're doing here for the padding.
So that's fine.
Yeah.
You know what I did?
This is stupid way to didn't I hear because this we probably could
have well, no mine.
Anyway, so point being off, we go.
Hopefully that would stop it from crashing because I think we can
always, we would never fetch backwards too far at that point.
But as you can see, right, it doesn't render things in the right place
because I'm not doing any work.
After I'm just flat-out forcing the alignment to be correct, even
though the alignment is not correct, right?
And so that's not good.
Obviously, but if I go ahead and do that, well, I'm going to try and
do here is see whether moving to alignment helps or not, right?
And so, if we take a look at what was happening here, right?
And take a look at that line.
I'll just go ahead and take that out for a second, right?
Here we are running 37 Cycles.
Yeah.
If I turn on alignment, stepping
should stay the same roughly, I would assume.
Well.
Actually gets a, just a slight bit faster.
And then so, then when I wanted to do was I want to go in here and
change our load and stores to no longer be unaligned.
So you remember, we were calling load you.
Because pixel was not aligned, right?
I can change load you to just a load, right?
And we didn't have any other ones there.
And so then we've also got the store you, which is unaligned, but
let's change that to aligned.
So now I'm just using the aligned versions of those guys and that's
it.
What happened here?
So I guess I did not do that.
Alignment properly start with that.
oh,
Do not ask me what I was thinking there.
First of all, I don't know why why?
I thought I wanted to make that be that way.
I didn't want to do that.
I want to literally step it to the actual lineman.
I don't want to multiply by a pixel value.
This is how much it's off.
So we're just going to do it that way.
Yeah, that was pretty dumb.
Anyway, so here's the version that's using store, you and load you and
it doesn't look any different to me.
Right?
The speed did not change at all.
They're so basically what that tells me unless I've made some kind of
an error is that at least at this point
until we address potentially other memory issues that alignment is
doing.
It unaligned is not a problem.
And furthermore, for all, we know, even after we address other
members, that might still not be a problem.
Meaning, it's possible that the unaligned, this of the store in the
load based on the fact that there's so much other work that we do is
just it just isn't relevant and will always be better off doing it
that way so that we don't have to overfill by more pixels, right?
Because yeah.
So I think the alignment there does not really look to me.
Like it's an issue at the moment so we're pretty.
They're all right.
So we have one last thing that we probably want to do here in terms of
stuff as we're fiddling with this routine.
What we'd like to do is we would like to make sure that we actually
always fill the real clip region and we don't right outside the clip
region, right?
And so the way that that's going to work is we know that we have to go
over our pixels.
Like so right, we know that we have to do four pixels at a time.
And so if we're doing four pixels at a time,
We have to make sure that our Mask doesn't allow us to write pixels
that are outside of where we're trying to write them.
So, like, on the last,
Time through the loop when we're going to write the final thing.
We would need to make sure that our our mask was set to not include
those at an additional pixels.
Now, the other way we could do it is we could make sure that it's
aligned at the end and it's the beginning.
That's going to be on a line 24 and I'm not sure which one we want to
do there.
Probably, we want to align the end and the reason that I say that
probably we want to align the end.
Is because I'm imagining.
I'm imagining that really the way we'd want to do, this is to
initialize the mask at the outset.
And then overwrite the mask with zero at the end, right?
So here's the right mask, you know what I mean?
And
and so here's what I wanted to try and do
We're writing for pixels at a time.
I drew that potential little bit.
Large.
You're writing for a pixels at a time doo-doo-doo-doo-doo-doo
doo-doo-doo-doo-doo.
There we go.
So here are pixels that we are going to right and these are broken up
into chunks of four.
So we have two options that we could do here for writing.
Right.
I'm actually probably make these line up as well.
So let's just do it this way.
So here's option one here is option 2.
So what we want to do, right?
Is we want to fill some region.
We want to fill between here and here, let's say right?
So we want to fill 0 1, 2, 3, 4.
So there's 5 pixels to fill but we know that we're going to fill them
in chunks of for.
So you have two options here, we could either fill these
And these right?
So here's pass.
This is our first time through the loop.
Here's our second time through the loop, right?
And mask these out so that we don't write them or we can do the
opposite alignment and try to write these out of line to that, that,
that ending Edge and write these and over instead.
So here is 0 and here's one.
So the first time through the loop, we don't
is and in the other case in the first in this than last time to the
rip, we don't write these
So what I was saying is usually, it's easier to start things up than
to change them at the end because what we can do is just initialize
the mask to this, and then at the end of the loop, Clear the mask.
So that we could never have to actually ever check to see which
iteration of the loop or on.
It always does the same every time rather than having to go are we at
the end of the loop are within the loop are within the loop?
Are you in the loop, right?
Just it's just seems simpler.
So what I'd rather do is do it this way where we start at the end X
Max, and we back up X-Men to be to start here, right?
So let's do that, right?
Because we can see if I switch back on our cliprect, right?
If I go in here and switch back on our clip clip, right groups, that's
on our cliprect.
If I go back in here and and switch back on our clip.
Rect and we can actually stop this now, since we don't need that
anymore.
When we move around, you can see that.
We've got this bug here.
That I was talking about right where we overfill because we're not
doing anything to prevent that, right?
What I want to do first is change it so that that error occurs on this
side that's why I'm going to do first, right?
So what I want to do is I want to see that this Edge firm up and this
Edge becomes Wiggly.
That's what we're looking for.
So, in order to do that, what I want to do here is come up with a
different way of computing.
This, I want to go ahead and take sort of like, the fill Whip and that
is going to be the max minus the Min X, right?
That's the amount we're going to fill by and then we're going to
compute the max X and actually line that up with exactly where I want
it to be.
But then what we're going to do is the Min X is actually going to be
whatever that Max X is minus the fill with
Right?
It's going to be - however much we want to fill.
And what I want to do is I want to round that fill with up so that it
actually is based on chunks of for, right?
So again, we already sort of saw how to do this.
So we have sort of are filled with sort of are filled with alignment.
If you will, we can take the fill with and we can end it with three
you know, 4 minus 1, right?
To find out how much it is off.
And then what we can do is try to, we just need to compute the value
that we would add to it to round it up to that value, right?
And that's going to be whatever you know, assuming that this if the
fill with the line, I can do this in a better way but I'm just I'm
getting a little tired, this point.
It's getting late through this in this the easiest way.
So assuming there's fill with a line is greater than 0.
We would just take whatever it would be to add it up.
24, right.
Hopefully, that makes some sense.
Oops, putting the fill rate to there.
Correct, right?
So this is actually going to align that fill with for us at least
hopefully.
That doesn't look right at all.
What is the problem?
They're filled with the line is however, much.
We were off assuming that we are off in some way, if it's exactly, for
we're fine, then we're going to increase that fill with bye-bye.
Fill with a line.
Let's go step into it.
Like I said, it's getting late and I'm tired.
Let's take a look.
Fill with this here.
Oh alright.
That's true.
We do have negatives.
So that's irrelevant for these.
I guess we want to look at non negative values because only
non-negative values are going to actually get filled.
That just because we're in optimization mode.
Let's turn off my patience off.
So we know we're actually looking at real values and not maybe
potentially some mistakes, okay?
Let's see here.
There we go.
So we're going to feel something that's 48 wide and that should be
exactly.
That's exactly a for, right?
That's a 12.
And so fill with a line should be zero.
So when we back this thing up, we should
See exactly the same values that were in the fill wrecked to begin
with, right?
And we do.
So that's fine.
So let's take something that isn't aligned hopefully, we'll get
something 73.
That's good.
So it says that the fill with the line is one, which means that it's
one off.
Let's see if that's true.
18 times 4 is 72.
That's correct.
It's one off from.
Yeah it's one over.
So we want to add to it for - the fill with the line and this line
which is 3.
So we're basically going to make the fill width snap up to the next
largest to.
I've been like Star just for evenly.
Which is what we did with 76.
And so now we're going to set up the places that were iterating over,
like so,
oh,
Yeah, so, I mean, it all looks correct.
But again, just for getting here, that only, right, that only actually
does it.
Before we've actually stepped to the location that we were going to
step to, right?
We have not actually set up the other values that we need here based
on that adjustment.
So that adjustment actually has to happen up.
Are right?
We that, you know, I can't just do it at the end in this sort of nice
convenient way.
That's, that's not going to work because all the rest of our
calculations based on that aren't getting redone, right?
So, that was just a little bit of stupidity as is happened as happens.
So we could just do that in here, right?
Where we then say, okay, we'll take that.
Phil wrecked, will take the Min X and we'll make that equal to the
fill wrecked Max x minus, whatever that fill with this.
And that'll do that.
And of course we only need to do that if we actually adjusted it, and
there we go.
In fact, I guess we, yeah.
There we go, because if we didn't adjust it, then we don't have to
change it at all.
So, let's go ahead and check that out.
See how we're doing there.
And that looks a little better to me.
You can see we're now solid on the right Edge, but we've got like
Badness happening on the left Edge.
Just what we want.
And so now what I'd like to do is I'd like to go ahead and actually do
the clipping there since we already have a right mask.
What I'm going to say is we'll introduce this will add a little bit of
a cost to our thing.
But what I'd like to do is basically just take that right mask and add
in the concept that we have to, we have to end it with yet, you know,
like one more thing, right?
So when we do this, mmm and right, when we, when we do that, the m and
Bs here,
I want to do essentially like right, mask equals, m m-- and si128.
I want to do that on right mask and clip mask.
Right and clip mask.
Is just some value put masks.
That we set to something here and at the moment I'll just do a set 1.
PS --mm set1 epi32 to just make it be all eats, right?
Can you do this?
You know, is that allowed?
apparently,
of course, it looks like, you know?
Yeah, it looks like you have to set an integer 8 and of course, I
can't actually set that, I could set it like that, I guess, which
would say, well, you know, - one is all F in the B so I could do that.
But yeah, all right, let's see.
So yeah.
So now we're still getting the exact same result which is what I
wanted just to make sure that that extra and is working out.
Okay.
So it's set to all ones.
And so what I want to do is at the end of the routine, I want to set
it to all one.
So when we go to step to the next pixel, I want the clip mask to be
set to all ones certainly because every other time through the loop,
it's always going to write everything.
And so the now all I need to do is set this clip mask to be like the
startup clip mask, you know?
And
Startup type mask is something that we're going to set based on this,
right?
So we have a 128 I which is our startup clip mask.
Okay.
And by default it will be set to just, you know, not having to
actually click anything.
But if we have to do an alignment adjustment here, then we essentially
want to set that clip mask to something that will cause the clipping
to to work properly.
Right.
So here is our adjustment.
We know that we have to adjust by that much
And what that is is that's essentially how many pixels we want to
clip.
So what that means is if you think about what's in our clip Basque
Our clip mask right now is set like this.
It's got all ones in here, right?
Oh, ones or ones or ones or ones, and these are 32-bit Lanes.
One for each pixel.
So all we really want to do here.
is if
We are going to align our pixels if we're going to clip pixels for
every pixel.
We're going to clip.
We want to clear out, 32 bits of ones, we want to basically write
zeros in there, right?
So one, pretty trivial way we could do it is take the number of pixels
number of pixels and shift down by 32 times that number right.
W a trivial way to do it.
I don't know if that's expensive or even possible in sse2.
It's basically like a shuffle.
It's like a well let's take a look, we'll see what we got.
So what do we have for shifting and swiveling?
Just take a look.
Sue me.
So if we wanted to do that, kind of a shift that would be a shift,
that would be a shift left by an immediate.
Let's take a look here.
So shift a right by IMM 8 B, while shifting in zeros and store the
result in dest.
So actually that would just do it.
The throughput is quite fine for our purposes.
So let's just do that looks fine to me.
So we'll do.
Oh and we don't even care here, really because now I think about it.
This is startup code, who cares?
It's hardly gets run over at all.
So our startup clip mask is
Going to be equal to the MMS rli.
Si128 of the startup quick mask and this is in B.
So we basically want our adjustment times for right.
We want to to shift it that many over.
Oh, nasty.
But it's an immediate.
All right.
Well, is there a one that is very thing?
We could do.
That doesn't need an immediate
Probably not.
So, what we probably have to do here is just do something cheesy.
This, this is probably not the best way to do this.
Just in case anyone was wondering.
You know what?
It's time for one of those comments.
so,
If the adjustment is one, we need to show us.
Go ahead and shift it by one, two, three.
So off we go.
Not quite right.
It is shift, right?
Correct, because we want to clear out the top guys for the clip mask.
I feel like,
so, for every one we add,
We would want to clear out the top dudes of our clip mask.
Yes.
So I'm not sure why I feel like that should be correct but who knows?
Let's go ahead and take a look.
Okay, so come in here.
Startup clip mask.
There's the startup foot mask and
Here we have our see it in HEX.
We've got our dudes first pickle sex, because third pixel for Pixel,
And we come in here, and we've got an adjustment to do.
The adjustment is one fill with the, with the line.
That's a negative guy, that wasn't it.
So this won't, this guy won't actually be used, but that's okay.
We can still take a look at what it does when it has to do an
adjustment of one.
When I have to do adjustment of one, it should get rid of this top.
I'm sorry, this, this talk.
I?
Umm, right, it does.
So, that actually looks kind of correct to me.
So I do wonder if maybe I've got something else wrong here.
Let's take a look.
Where is our like 73, dude?
There we go.
Alright, so our 73, dude.
He's got some sombreros to clear out here.
He's gotta clear up 12, bro.
So he should only write the first pixel, so let's see what happens
when we come down through here.
Go.
Go, go, go, go.
Go, go.
Go.
What?
Was the fill height?
Nothing to fill height was nothing great.
All that, all, that people for nothing.
Seriously.
It's just absurd.
Really?
When you think about it,
So here we are in our clip masks.
What's our startup clip Mass look like.
So here is another one where we've got that.
You know we should really early out these guys I mean it's doing all
this work on stuff, that doesn't actually fit into the region at all.
Let's go ahead and just do that because that just seems a lot better.
All right, so let's do this.
Let's just take that.
Pixel count.
Here.
It's not like pixel count, more appropriately.
It should be called.
Well I'll just leave this the way it is, s, okay?
So what I want to do is at the earliest possible time which would
basically be here
I want to go ahead and just make sure that we're actually feeling
something, right?
So I'm going to go through here and say, you know, let's let's just
early out the whole thing.
and so for that, I'm just going to do like if
Has area fill wrecked.
I'm just going to make a function in math.h.
Basically like inline pool 32 has area rectangle to I and this is just
going to be equal to you know results a DOT Min is less than a top Max
and a top Min less than a top Max.
So so we're basically just checking to make sure that in both cases it
has extents on those axes, right?
So that way we are not constantly going through a bunch of Loops for
no reason.
And so now here are filled with should always be something.
Valid.
There we go.
So we've got an adjustment of to here.
We fill that up.
Right.
There we go.
We've got the two masked out there come down here and now, finally
will get to see this because I've actually ensured that we're going to
be in things that actually go into the loop, which is nice.
And so, let's take a look at what we end up getting with that right
mask.
And the clip mask.
So the right mask, there is our white mask and the clip mask.
Oh,
you know.
And this is not because I'm on stream, just to be clear.
Actually make these kind of mistakes all the time, like, my brain just
isn't solid enough on always, keeping everything in the right order.
I make these.
I actually just these are the kinds of mistakes that I make in like
reels life.
All the time.
Like, you saw me explicitly.
Say like, it wasn't like I was confused.
You saw me explicitly, say I wanted to clear out
The top guys thinking that I want to clear out the later pixels but
it's at the beginning of the row.
So you want to clear out the earlier pixels, right?
I mean that's just kind of obvious so I don't know like yeah, I don't
know why I have that problem, but I definitely do and that always
happens to me.
So I was thinking of mentally, what I wanted to do correctly, but
mapping that to what actually happens in the register, I was totally
wrong.
So now it looks like we have much more solid clipping, right?
So that's good and I'll go ahead and turn on the optimized version
which presumably should not have broken much.
It does cost us a little bit to do it, so that's unfortunate but you
know, we're going to need it if you want to break up stuff into
chunks.
So there we go, right?
So now what I'd like to do and this will actually probably hurt our
frame rate because obviously you wouldn't necessarily want to do this
for any particular reason.
But let's go ahead and
And actually break this up a little bit.
So, instead of doing this stuff here, what I'm actually going to do is
I'm actually going to start passing through that clip that those those
clip regions and stuff, right?
So what I want to do is when we, you know, when we passed the stuff in
here to draw a rectangle quickly rectangle quickly.
Oops.
Robert angle quickly.
What I want to do is I don't really want this guy to look at the
buffer anymore like the buffer width and height are just not going to
be relevant to it anymore.
And so it's just going to use the buffer memory and pitch.
And that's it, right?
So it's going to take in addition to what it's getting here.
It's going to take a rectangle to I, which is the clip rect and it's
going to take an even or odd value, which is that parameter to say.
What is going on there?
And then it is going to be
It's going to do.
This clip reps.
This clip right here, it's going to do this for initialization like so
and then with Max and height, Max should never be used ever again,
right?
Yeah.
so,
I got to be honest with you, I'm not sure.
Why?
We were subtracting 3 from the height before.
That doesn't make a lot of sense because we're writing by four things
at a time.
So it makes sense why we would need the width to not overwrite in that
way.
But why the height would have to be that way?
I don't understand.
So that's a bit odd to say, the very least.
But that's the way it goes.
I guess sometimes so let's get rid of that and then we can make it
work.
It's early off of the cliprect but now we have to actually pass the
cliprect in here.
So here's our clip rect and our cliprect of course, is going to be
This way right with an alpha Target height.
Now, this should crash or at least have the potential to crash.
I should say.
And I'll talk about why in a second.
It may not actually crash.
What's what is happening?
Something bad is happening.
Something very bad is happening but I don't know what it actually is.
Whoa.
We are like super slow right now.
What happened?
What did we?
What did we do?
Ah,
Something very bad happened, but I'm not exactly sure what it was.
We are calling this twice now but that can't really account for that
ridiculous of a thing, right?
Take take that out of the equation and we're that was still really
bad, right?
Like that's just crazy slow.
But I don't know why, I have no idea why you're so slow Robert, I go
quickly.
It's still only taking 36 cycles per pixel, according to that.
But I'm not sure how it was able to get so much slower like that, it
doesn't make a whole lot of sense to me.
I'm totally stumped by that just to be clear.
I have absolutely no idea why that would be the case.
Well.
I would like to go to bed soon.
So this is definitely one of those bugs that we are going to have to
think about how we can solve in short order, because what on Earth?
Is going on there.
oh,
That's funny.
That's just stupid as always.
So yeah, you know this has to be inverted, right?
Because this finds the area, so we were basically looping over the
entire screen.
It's a kind of increase.
That's how fast I was.
We were looping over the entire screen and touching every pixel.
For every single Sprite and it still ran that fast.
That's pretty good man.
We made this routine fast.
That's pretty funny.
Yeah, so this has to actually this is this is not right.
I'm going to go ahead and introduce the inverted, Infinity rectangle
because everyone loves the infinite, inverted, Infinity rectangle.
And what the inverted Infinity rectangle is, right?
Is this just an easy shorthand for saying, I want the Min to be equal
to the maximum.
It could possibly be and the max to be equal to the minimum.
It could possibly be so that when you do a loop like this when you
just go through it and you try to expand the bounds, it just works,
right?
So it's basically just saying okay?
You know, I want you to produce for me.
Something, which is going to be the Min X and the Min y equal to n Max
and the Min y.
Sorry at the max
X and the max y equals negative 60.
Whoops, in lien.
That's a good thing.
There we go.
Okay, so the inverted Infinity rectangle.
Hopefully, we'll save our frame mate.
I don't know if it actually will or not.
We'll find out and this is presumably.
The crash that I was mentioning so temporarily.
Temporarily will will sort of adjust our cliprect to make sure that
doesn't happen.
But then I want to actually go fix that so that we no longer have to
adjust the clip.
Rect.
Alright, so the clip.
Rect right, here's our right to do correct buffers with overflow,
right?
So okay, what I want to do here is just say, okay, let's make sure we
have four pixels on all of the borders so that we can't possibly over,
right?
No matter how stupid our code is temporarily, right?
Didn't mean to actually do that to the one I was saving.
So if I do that temporarily hope that can avoid the crash or we can
just still crash, which would be cool.
Do not know why be getting that because this should still give me at
least in theory the correct.
Well, but it totally didn't.
Why is my clip?
Rect I set the clip rectangle.
Oh wow.
Yeah.
Someone's getting sleepy.
And that someone is me.
That's the one I wanted to set.
So there we go and now we're not in the dreaded super slow.
Everything.
Right.
So now that we're passing the clip rect down,
And that's all good.
Everyone's happy.
What I want to do is make it so that render group to Output is
actually some totally other thing, right?
Actually want it to look like this, where render group to Output?
Rid of all this stuff.
Actually, you know what, though?
I do want to still time this one, I think.
So, what I'm actually going to do, I guess is make this B tiled render
group to Output or something like that.
And I'm not going to time it.
Okay.
And
Yeah, and we'll see, I don't know how we're going to actually line
this up eventually.
That's what we'll start looking at on a Monday.
But in here, where we do render grouped output,
Oops.
I actually went and made out to be, I guess it doesn't want to give
me.
Give me hand me that CPP.
There we go, surrender, group to Output.
I'm going to just call tiled render group tab.
But now,
We're going to have to do something a little fancier there but that'll
be next week's job.
Alright.
So we do our Todd render group to Output.
What?
This is going to do is I'm going to pass the clip rect in.
Like so and then I'm going to pass in.
Also, in addition to that, the even odd, right?
So in here, this will now pass the even on
All right, so we do that and everyone's happy and everything's good,
and then I just go ahead and grab this out and put it in the outside
thing.
So, tiled group will just do render group to Output like so render
group out the target with Rex false and true.
Okay, and now we can only just beaten us do one of these because we're
calling it twice, right?
And off we go.
Or not, as the case may be.
What happened?
They're calling it twice.
begin time blocked even
Toronto to quickly clip rect even.
Which is passing both.
And we call it twice once with each.
Why am I not?
Why am I not seeing the proper thing here?
I would like to know.
All right.
Let's see what happens.
So we should get no update to the frame buffer here.
Meaning I won't see anything if I try to move
This should give me.
One set of lines.
The other set of lines which it does.
Oh well,
Yeah, that's another thing we would need to do, isn't it?
So right now our clear call right?
Our clear call is actually just doing a draw rectangle and that draw
rectangle call does not in any way obey the even odd lines, right?
So we need to do is we need to update our draw rectangle call to take,
you know, the
The clipping information, right?
And that will allow us also, I suppose to start clipping the rest of
these things, which we want to do.
So that's fine.
All right so let's go ahead and do that.
Draw a rectangle.
So rectangle to I clip rect rule 32 even
And this is probably pretty straightforward.
I would think it looks like these are just doing the clip here, right?
So, so basically, this is just the fill wrecked, right?
This is rectangle to, I feel wrecked and this is just going to do
that, right?
That's the Phil wreck.
So then we can just do Phil wreck equals intersect
Direct and cliprect get rid of this stuff.
Then we just go ahead and use the fill wrecked here.
60 and off it goes.
Right.
Feel like that should do it.
Draw a rectangle outline.
Who calls?
What, what?
Does this even exist anymore?
It doesn't, it doesn't does it.
All right, let's get rid of this guy.
We don't care about him.
Not even used anymore.
Probably leave that case entirely.
And draw a rectangle, trance state, initialized test diffuse.
All right, so this guy is some kind of clear.
We're sort of cheating and using the renderer directly out from
underneath itself that will probably have to go away at some point
relatively soon because we won't be allowed to do stuff quite like
that anymore.
But all right so if we did want to do that we would have to pass it
more information.
I'm just going to go ahead and and nuke this test.
If use test normal guys I think for now.
Well.
Where is actually used?
All right, so I'll nuke this guy for now.
But just that guy.
We'll just do that with.
What was he was?
Just
Passing gray basically.
So, all we really need to do here is we need to do something where
we'd actually fill him with gray.
Give you a C3.
Build this guy with gray.
Okay.
Leave that like that for now.
Okay, so let's get back to what we were doing.
So now we have this guy, we have the draw rectangle call taking those
parents, but we're not actually using the even odd guy, the even odd
part of it, which we need to do.
So, if we take a look at draw rectangle quickly, you can see that
we've got the even there and we need to do this operation, right.
And we could actually make this operation, be something that is common
between the two routines since they're so similar, right.
They can see the way that this works up here,
When I do the the Phil, you know, draw a rectangle, where's the other
guy?
Where's where's my draw rectangle?
Oops.
Okay, so if I come over here and look at draw a rectangle, you can see
that essentially I'm doing exact same thing and I would I would be
doing the exact same thing here, right?
And so I don't know if maybe we want to make that the something you
know that's more.
More standardized, it's pretty trivial piece of code but you know you
never know.
So now I think we are probably proper properly doing every other line.
looks like we've got
because that's still in the buffer.
So it looks like we're probably doing every other line in those calls
now.
So, let's take a look and see like there, go ahead and fix that.
So we're doing both.
And there we go.
So that looks pretty good, I think.
Feels reasonably.
Feels okay, I would say not too bad.
So alright, so now we've got that working.
And so then the last thing that we kind of want to do now is I'd like
to get it so that we can do our tiles.
And so what I'd like to do is do something like this.
So let's go ahead and do a for I Loop where we do tile.
X tile, X is less than some number of tiles account X tile, X plus
plus.
And in here,
We will do a loop over both tiles.
And inside each of those, we will do this whole operation.
Like so and so now what I'm going to do is I'm just going to break the
screen up into those pieces that we talked about and render each one
separately.
So, what I'd like to do is say, okay, we've got a tile count X, and
we've got a tile count, why?
And those are, how many tiles we want across and how many tiles do you
want down?
so, what I want to do is I want to
Set that number to something relatively reasonable.
Like I think we said before you know, six or something was good,
something like that.
So maybe something like six by four or something.
I don't know.
Tell you divided by 2 is 5 40, by 40 divided by 4, seems maybe about,
right?
1925?
By 2960 divided by 6.
You know, something like that.
Just throwing it out there.
So there'd be 24 tiles that we broken up into.
Maybe that's a few too many.
It's hard to say you know, maybe we want more of like a 5 or a 4 by 4
so would be 16 of them.
So let's take a look at what that would be.
That'd be like more like 256 1080 divided by 2, so that's oops.
540 / 4135 so yeah, I don't know.
I don't know about that.
That's really hard to say again that's going to catch them up to tweak
it.
But let's go ahead and see.
So if those are our tile counts that were looping over, then we would
basically just need to know how big each tile was, you know in each
case
And I guess we don't since we're not aligned, we don't really have any
restrictions on what the tile widths actually are.
Because it won't actually affect how we blind to them.
Then we might want them to be aligned to, for anyway, just because
that way, if you happen to be building, something that covers the
whole tile, you wouldn't pay the price on both sides.
But due to do Casey round to 4,
but,
Basically, what we want to do here is just figure out how big the tile
with needs to be, so we can go ahead and do those divides output.
Height / top count, why?
And that's how many we need to do there and of course, we need our
tiles, we need the tiles to actually fill the whole Space so they
might overflow slightly right now will undercut it.
And we'll figure out what we want to do about that later.
Alright, so we do to make sure that allocator allocates enough space.
So we can round these whatever we'll figure out how we want, do that?
Exactly so we get our tiles in then all we have to do is say okay our
clip rect is actually going to be
The men ax will be the tile x times, the tile width, and the clip, and
the max X, obviously, we'll just be whatever the Minix is plus the
tile Whip, and the same will be true for the Y, right here.
Goes the, why?
And there we go.
so, if that
Is what we're going to do for the cliprect, which is now done.
Then I can adjust it by those sort of four values here and be done.
And that will now give me little guys who they should have, like on
the screen, a little blockade if you will although that does not look
what I would like, what I would have expected.
I don't really understand what's going on there with the clip.
Rect
Still got a bug.
I stand up for a second.
My legs are tired.
Tired legs, tired legs.
All right.
So if we do the tiled render group to Output here, we're passing in
the clip.
Rect and we're getting some weird Behavior there.
So I've got the clip, rect ilex time with -4.
So those are the things we're supposed to be clipping to and I don't
quite understand why we're getting that look that we just got.
So
Like basically I oh no wait that's totally correct.
Those are the the ground patches.
Which are which are getting tile rendered basically.
Which is kind of funny but that's just how that is.
So there we go.
So there's our tiled renders and we can see the tiles because I
subtracted for from them.
And so I think we're pretty close to correct their.
I don't know why we have to go look at why those ground tiles.
Do that weird disappearing thing but those are kind of a thing that
are separate our list anyway.
But if we take a look at what's going on there, I think we're pretty
much good to go.
So I think we're I think we can finally end the stream.
We've done all the stuff I wanted to do for child rendering so that's
good and we can look at the rest of it starting next week.
All right, so let's do the Q&A.
Here at midnight.
Because I want to go stretch my legs.
My poor left leg, my gimp leg.
I wish Medical Science was smart enough to fix my left leg.
But it's not.
Your top and right.
Clip is off by one top and right clip.
So you're talking about
All right, well, I got to take a look.
So, the top and right clip is off by one.
Which is you're talking about in here, right?
Is that we're talking about, you're talking about the intersection
code.
Not sure what you exactly mean by top and right clip.
But I'm going to assume that's true.
So let's see.
Well, I guess the other problem is here.
I'm not sure what you mean by off by one.
Are you trying to say that there's a calculation that should be
aligned like that.
That's being too conservative and it's filling one extra or one too,
few pixels.
So, it's either it's either not always certain but it's filling one
too many or one too, few pixels.
In the in the region to consider or are you saying that something
based on the clip that should be adjusted is being adjusted wrong?
I'm not sure which one of those you're saying unfortunately,
Let's see if I can figure it out.
So the inverted Infinity erectile, we come through here and this is
just taking the total size.
I assume you don't mean anything in here because you said clip which
is this is not the clip, this is the clip.
So when it does the intersection we've got The Fill wrecked and we've
got the clip, rect and we just want to know, whichever one of those is
going to be greater, right?
so that
I don't understand exactly why that wouldn't be this value.
Can you be more specific about that potentially?
Mmm, molo epi32 is an S SE for intrinsic.
Really.
That's too bad.
Bolo.
So don't really want to use those.
Mmm, mole low.
Epi 32.
Yep.
It sure is hmm.
Hmm.
Well.
The good news here.
Is that really?
Everything would work fine with a 60-minute?
Multiply probably if we just clip out.
the top because the fetch
the fetch y 4x.
Is going to be.
So that texture pitch, right?
I assume we can we can keep all the texture pitches.
Less than 64,000.
Because how big would that be right?
Think about this.
So 65536 or five, I should say.
65536 divided by 4, that's a 16,000 wide texture.
So that's not going to happen, right?
So the fetch y 4x.
That value.
Is just going to be whatever the the also proportional to it's going
to be whatever the height of the texture is.
So I feel like, you know, if the total texture size was always going
to be,
Well, now that could still exceed it.
Yeah, yeah, that's unfortunate.
That is unfortunate.
I'm not sure what the best way would be to make that work.
I mean, I guess you could do a mole low and a mole.
Hi.
Like, you could try to recombine the two because, you know, that each
one of them is going to be 16.
So, I see.
You can do it that way.
But at that point I do wonder if maybe this was just a stupid idea
because then you're probably introducing too many extra instructions
and maybe you would just rather have done it in scalar to begin with,
right?
And I don't know if that's true or not.
But you see what I'm saying?
Right?
You could, you could do something.
where you're just like okay yeah we've got, you know,
We've got a mole, low animal, high of the 16-bit values that are in
here, and then we try to reconstruct them.
We try to reconstruct those by ordering them together and shifting up,
you know, the the other guy.
SLI epi32.
We try to shift up the other guy by 16 and or them together like
recreate a multiply, right?
So we could do it that way but unfortunately it's a little more
expensive but I guess that's just what we'd have to do to stay in
there.
So, you saw what I did there, right?
All I was doing there was, I was
I needed to do a 32-bit multiply but there is no 33 B multiplied in
SC2.
So what I did is I just did two 16-bit multiplies and ask for the low
and the High bits of the result and just combine them together to make
a 32-bit value.
That's all I did because I knew that the two values that I was
multiplying, we're both only 16 bits but when you multiply them
together, then their greater than 16 bits.
So yeah.
We revert yesterday's code changes, where you changed by linear pixel,
unpacking code from float mode to enter, while it was faster with
float Mal.
I don't know, because I'm not sure we're ready to do that yet.
I think we should probably do that but we might want to switch some
other part of the loop to be 16 bit when we do that.
So I'm not sure what we want to do there yet.
I wanted to try and do the memory stuff first
How many more marathons fumes will be have?
They will not be often but sometimes I'm from in the mood and I
happened to be like I know that like I don't have any plans for the
day and, you know, I'm not gonna be hanging out with anyone or
whatever.
You know.
I can I can throw one in
You should give a big thanks to rigorous for sticking around and try
to give you tips knowing full well that you wouldn't see them in the
chat.
Of course I give a big, thanks for rigorous.
We always give a big thanks to him.
Would it be better to have tile sizes?
Always, divisible by 4 horizontally.
Then there would be no need to deal with alignment and masking.
Unfortunately, no, that's not true, right?
So the reason that we have to do the masking,
Is is actually because we are unaligned when we're writing to the
tiles.
So even if the tiles were aligned, we're writing for pixels based on
the texture itself, right?
So, you know, I don't, I don't know,
There is a way for us to.
I don't, maybe I'm missing something, but I don't know how we can fix
that part by aligning the tiles, because we're not aligned to the
tiles ever.
Anyway.
Does that make sense?
Don't that make some sense.
Clip 12.
Few pixels.
Look at the edge of the screen.
Look at the edge of the screen you're talking about out here.
I'm not sure.
now, keep in mind, we've got like,
Well, okay, I'm not sure exactly what you're talking about.
So we'll start with that but we also have some some annoying things
here that I just want to point out.
So I'll we're not really at the point where we've gotten down to like
looking at some of the robustness things.
So you know, there's I realize that there's some weirdness here but
push wrecked outline.
So there's a bunch of things that get outlined right now and in fact,
maybe if I turn that off for a second it'll be clearer just so we make
sure we're all talking about the same thing.
So if I turn off push wrecked outline which is
Here.
so, if we turn off push rekt outline,
Now, we can take a better.
Look at what's going on.
Do you still think there is an off by one error looking at what we're
looking at now?
And you know, maybe you do, maybe you don't, but I just want to make
sure we're all thinking about the same thing before before we go
looking for.
App that makes sense.
Just pretty sure I saw glitchy just up and pick the stuff near the
edges but it might have been doing its okay.
Well let's see, I'm because I'm just wondering like we were drawing a
rectangle outline there which is just was for a separate thing, which
is the same region and the Sim this is just like too many things that
kind of get piled on as we're sort of doing this.
Because you know, one hour a night, I got to cut some slack sometimes.
And I don't always go back and like, pull out code and put it in a way
that I can turn on and off and stuff like that.
So there's always like, debug code kind of cruft.
Things.
And so what you may have been looking at is the fact that there was a
rectangle outline outline, just the edge of the screen that if we
don't pull the camera back to show our Region's in the debug camera
mode.
It draws like right at the edge, but the draw rectangle code is not
sub-pixel accurate yet, right?
We still are using the way old.
When we wrote at the very beginning of the stream that just, you know,
fully just rounds.
And so you may have seen it kind of coming in and out over here.
I'm guessing that might have been
Ben it.
But I could be wrong.
But yeah, so I don't know if, you know, we can do it, we can can look
at this as well, right?
And like I said, you know, it may there may very well be a problem.
Still that's totally on the table, but I just wanted to make sure that
we're all looking at it fairly because other people may not have
remembered well and Fabien probably never saw that stream.
So he doesn't even know that we were drawing that, you know?
So yeah.
Tile size mod for not masking for textures, but clip best variable.
Yes, I'm sorry Martin's.
I I'm just not sure exactly what you're talking about there.
So
The thing that I don't understand about the suggestion.
But I am trying these guys back on the thing that I don't really
understand about the suggestion that you're saying, is that the clip
mask variable has nothing to do with the tile size, right?
I've started with the tile alignment.
It has to do with where the fill wrecked is relative to the tile
because we write unaligned
we are our fill routine aligns with the texture not with the tile and
so no matter what the alignment of the tile is
it's still going to have to clip either the front or the back because
the texture, The Fill region is a certain with, right?
And that fill with is not aligned to for
So, no matter what we do, we have to do that that backing up, right?
Either on the front or the back.
So I just don't, I just don't understand how a lying, the tile would
ever get you out of the business of still having to not draw those
pixels.
Because it doesn't have anything to do with what the alignment of the
tile is its, the alignment of the texture of the fill region, that's
what's causing the clip.
Does that make sense?
And Martin's, yes, I understand why you're not thinking clearly so
late because I am not thinking clearly.
So late either, it's time for bed.
Certainly
Yes.
It's pretty much one hour a day, but I think we've had a two-hour one
before to to our ones before.
And today we did the basically up a giant for our one.
It was crazy.
Like I said, I hadn't had enough program and get to.
I had to do a bunch of Toppers I conference on Friday.
So
Yeah.
And you can see it's 12:27.
Am here time for me to go to bed.
All right, folks.
Good work today though, we got a bunch of stuff resolved, so that's
pretty good.
And now that we've got tiled stuff in, we can go ahead and do
multi-threading next.
Week in that'll be pretty fun, I think.
And then we can start working on render or correct this and stuff.
Get the lighting going.
Get get our our whatever our fill rule is ironed out.
Yeah.
This is going to be good.
The render is the biggest part of the engine, really, in terms of
stuff, that's kind of fiddly and stuff.
We have to work through in the way that we're working through with,
like, observations, all that stuff that are really sensitive, because
there's just so many pixels that you deal with.
So, you know, I think we've done it pretty well, you know, I think
we've
Pretty well, you know, obviously, you know, not everything goes
perfectly but it's, it's gone pretty well.
You know, I'm pretty happy with that even chunky and have you checked
up and do an hour a night, you know, we were able to make pretty good
progress.
We've got a renderer now, that's pretty good.
I mean, you know, it's not going to win any words for world's best
render or anything, but, you know, it's totally at, you know, working
at speed and, you know, we'll be able to get it multi-threaded soon
and that's, I don't know.
I'm pretty happy with that.
That support scaling and rotation already.
So we'll have to take a little bit.
Look at what we can do with the lighting stuff which is, which is
obviously worse and much slower.
So I don't know how much of that lighting stuff will be able to do in
the software path necessarily but we'll think about it a little later
on after we have the whole thing working.
Well without the lighting will go ahead and get all that good and then
we'll switch on the lighting stuff and see what we can do there, and
that might take a little while to
It's good stuff.
All right, so thanks everyone for joining me for another episode of
handmade hero.
It has been a pleasure coding with you, as always, and it has been a
marathon session today.
Our first real Marathon session, we've never gone anything like four
hours before, so, that was kind of fun, just, you know, it's good to
work on the code sometimes for a little bit longer.
And I never got a chance to do that before.
As always, if you would like to follow along the source code at home,
the game comes the source code.
So if you preorder it at any time, you get all the source code to
every day that we've ever done and you can always download it every
night if you want.
The latest, it's always up there so you can do that on handmade here
at whore or using the pre order.
Now button if you would like, you can also support our patreon page
which is basically just supports the video.
Which of course we do is a free thing.
But if you want to support it, we love that you do and we also have a
forum site.
You can go to ask questions, get poorest a Mac and Linux or any other
stuff like that.
We've got a tweet bot.
That treats the schedule at you and we have, we have a little, we're
working on this.
It's a, it's not really there yet, but there's some JavaScript that
someone sent in that I put in that sort of work sometimes to set this
properly.
And
Hopefully when I get a chance I will go clean up the JavaScript so
that it always gets the right thing.
So hopefully eventually this live button.
Will also tell you how long it is to the next livestream to so that's
coming but it's going to be a while till I have a chance to look at it
myself.
So anyway, thanks everyone for joining me.
Next dream will be Monday back to the regular schedule.
You will not be a marathon.
Just a regular one hour stream and I hope to see you all there until
then have a fabulous rest of your weekend.
And have fun programming.