Reset, there we go.
Sorry, cycle of recording.
I got cycle the timer.
All right, welcome to handmade hero here on day 28.
We are in the middle of our sort of architecture stuff, our game
architecture stuff, where we are starting to think about how we want
this game's code to be structured and how we want to work yesterday.
We wrote a little function so we could draw a rectangle on the screen
safely.
So that would basically allow us to start doing some debug stuff.
I wanted to talk a little bit about how to
To make the rectangle colored.
Today, we're going to think about like basically colors and how those
work just really briefly at the beginning of the stream.
Again, we're saving any of the hardcore rendering stuff when we
activate the renderer, but there's a couple things I have to do just
to get stuff up on the screen.
So I'm kind of explaining them lightly and then we're going to start
generating tile maps and doing some things with like trying to move
characters around that sort of stuff.
So basically what we're trying to do is we're trying to make sort of
the initial game code, just a first pass, whatever comes to mind so we
can start to look at how it looks and think,
How we might want it to be structured because one of the big things
that I was trying to emphasize on the previous two days when we were
basically just talking about architecture and how you should think
about it is you don't want to do a lot of pre-planning because
pre-planning, you usually just don't have the information you need to
make those good decisions and you're just going to make mistakes that
will cost you a lot of time.
And so usually, what's better to do is explore first learn and then go
back and say, okay, now that I've learned what this code should look
like structurally.
Now I can say definitively.
This is the
Texture and move forward, so that exactly what we're doing and we are
going to continue with that today.
So what if you have pre-ordered the game here on handmade hero
dot-org, you should have gotten a link in your email that allows you
to download the source code.
In that source, code is a ZIP file with each day's Source.
Basically open it up and there's a zip for every day.
We're on day 28.
So you zip the unzip.
The day before day, 27 start with day, 27 source, and you'll be
exactly where I am right now.
With that said, let's get started.
We've got a lot to
You because we're right here at the beginning of the game.
There is so it's a giant open field in front of us basically.
So I am going to go ahead and get everything loaded so we can get
started.
All right, so if I remember correctly, we were at the point where
basically we can size the window.
However, we want, but we don't do anything with the exercise right
now.
We're only drawing it up into this upper corner.
That's, that's basically the entirety of our game.
There's some things that I want to do with that as well, in the future
a little bit, but we'll talk about that.
Later on.
So this is our game and we also have our handy-dandy editor here.
So, let me go ahead and open up our handmade dot CPP, which is here.
So, at first, first things first, we should probably clear the screen.
Well, you know what, let's talk about this again.
I actually do like clearing the screen to purple because you know,
what we should probably do if we clear the screen to this hideous
purple, which is not something we're probably going to use in our
debug output at all.
If I clear the screen to this hideous purple and then we go ahead.
Make a little tilemap thing that has little squares, you know, and we
color the squares in at least then we'll be able to see anywhere that
we are not actually filling because we'll see this hideous purple show
through.
So maybe it's a good idea to leave the hoodies purple in there.
I'm not so against Hades purple.
So that's good.
All right.
So what I want to do before we got started today, in terms of the
color I have this to do in here that says floating-point color
tomorrow.
What I wanted to do is just talk a little bit about that and and get
you a little bit more familiar with that so that we can make the
colors, make a little more sense than because you know, right now,
We're basically doing what amounts to sort of web colors, right?
I know you've seen it like pound AA BB CC, that sort of thing or, you
know, a, a 00 FF or something.
You've seen this in the if you've ever done any web programming,
that's how web colors work, but basically, right that is the
hexadecimal encoding of the color and there's a lot of reasons not to
like this.
It's I mean, it's basically packing the red, the green and the blue
into the bottom, 24 bits and I guess Alpha if you've got it.
But into the bottom 24, a
Of a 32-bit integer and there's not a lot.
You can really do with that.
It's not an efficient way to work with it because the most efficient
way to do math in the CPU is using the floating Point Unit and this is
not floating point at all.
Right.
So if you think about a lot of things that you might want to do with
color, like, one thing that we might want to do with color, is blend
two colors together, for example, other than we might wanna do with
colors, make it darker or lighter, like blend it towards black, right?
These sorts of things, the math for doing that is really easy to do in
floating point.
But if it's in this crazy packed format, it would be a lot more
difficult to do.
And we have to work out a cons of fiddly, bit things to do it.
And so usually what you would do is you wouldn't ever do that.
You would up, you would load it into, you know, an S SE register or
something like this and up convert it to floating Point.
Anyway.
So basically, what I want to do is get used to get.
You used to working with some floating-point colors to begin with
because that is going to be the most efficient way always to think
about them.
And if we do pack them back into this crazy format, for space reasons
at certain points in time.
Like, when we want to store them, we may decide that it's more
efficient to store them, this way, for example, then that's fine.
But that should be something that we do explicitly to save space and
explicitly for that reason, not as a general way.
We think about colors.
So what I want to do is pass three floating Point values here, red
green and blue for our color.
Now, I guess again, I'll save a lot of this, talk about it, more on
the rendering side of things, but
I guess I'll point out the reason that we do red green and blue.
Obviously, you may wonder why we have that as our as our basis for
colors, essentially.
The reason that red green blue or what's used is because that's the
cleanest sort of orthogonal basis.
You can use for the human visual system.
The human visual system is sensitive to red green and blue light.
It doesn't really have a way of sensing other color wavelengths
because white, like, light is basically a continuous wave length
thing.
You know, oscillates like light waves, right?
We, well, you know what?
We know about life, wait, light waves and physics?
Anyway, light is kind of this mysterious thing that we're always kind
of learning more about, but light essentially has a property.
When it, you know, any given sort of photon, any given piece of light
has a property that is its color and that is its oscillation sort of
its frequency of oscillation that it has is actually a specific color.
So, you know, you can have light that is actually a you
Certain Shade of yellow, right?
It's not a combination of red and green which is how we think about
yellow and programming or, you know, or artists even think about
yellow when they open up gimp, you know, I mean, we think about it, we
go in here when we actually think about color.
I don't even know how to use this little tool, but I assume there's
some way for me to get a if there's like those little, you know, I'm
talking about those little sliders that are that are around.
Let me, let me let me use color cop because that's got them.
So we tend to think
About it as like this sort of thing where we've got like a red, a
green in the blue, and the red, and the green, and the blue could
contribute, a certain amount, right?
That sort of thing.
Or, you know, there's other color spaces, Hue, saturation, value, all
this sort of stuff.
We think about it that way, but really light isn't that way.
Light is not a mixture of red green and blue necessarily light can
actually be a specific color.
If it wants to be, it can be exactly yellow or some specific yellow.
Some Pacific Wave specific, wavelength of yellow.
And so it's just that our eyes because they only sense have like red
green and blue receptors that have these kind of filter patterns that
we use.
Because we only see, in terms of those RI is can't actually tell the
difference between a single piece.
A single set of light, you know, single set of photons coming in that
all, are you actually yellow and oscillating photons that are coming
in that are like ones.
Red ones, green ones.
Red ones green, right?
So we just kind of see this like integration of the light that hits
our eyes.
We don't we can't tell that what we're seeing is a specific wavelength
or not.
We wouldn't know is my point.
So we've basically built and again, I'm not a physicist.
So take all this explanation with a grain of salt.
This is like the explanation for computer programmers, right?
It's not the explanation.
For people who study a light people who study light probably would be
like, oh don't explain it.
That way, you're totally wrong but for programming purposes, what's
important?
Stand is, we don't need at the moment or have not found any need to in
practice.
Actually represent light in any better way than that.
Because since the human visual system seems to only be able to really
distinguish red, green blue, and it sees other colors by looking at
the combinations of the red and green receptor responses or green and
blue, or red green and blue responses.
We don't really have to worry too much about the fact that we don't
actually
Capture, you know our monitors don't actually ever produce yellow
light.
They just produce red and green light very close together and when
they hit RI RI goes, oh, it was yellow right now.
It's worth noting that if we're simulating light inside the computer,
all of this becomes not true.
If you are doing a photo realistic renderer, for example, and I'm not
talking about photorealistic rendering like the kind that you do in
real-time Graphics.
I'm talking about like offline like the kind you might do for an
architectural viz.
Is like Maxwell render or something like that?
One of those renderers that does takes a long time to generate an
image, but does it supposed to be very accurate as to what light would
do at that point.
It's not true anymore.
At that point.
You do have to worry about the wavelength of light.
The actual wavelength that the light should have been because there
are Optical phenomena that depend on those wavelengths like prisms and
stuff that split light into pieces.
I mean, I don't really know what they all are to be honest with you,
but when things when you have materials that you want to simulate,
Certain materials actually respond differently in terms of the light
that they reflect based on the wavelength of the light that's coming
in.
And so if all you know is that you have a certain amount of red at a
certain amount of green coming in and you don't know whether that
actually came from a yellow or came from, you know, a separate red and
agreeing that we're coming in together.
You won't be able to compute the actual color that got reflected off
of this surface properly because you won't know which they are.
So it's not true that in.
Graphics.
We can always not care about this because it depends on the level of
realism you're trying to achieve and the circumstances.
But it is true that when we finally get to the output layer of things
when we're just trying to draw an image on the screen after, it's
already been computed at that point.
It is true that we have never really found a reason why we would have
to produce other colors.
Red green and blue is sufficient.
As long as we can control the amounts of them, the I can't really tell
the difference between this as being yellow, actual yellow and this is
being a combination of red and green.
Green pixels that get lit up, right?
All right.
So since we know that that's true, and since we know that our monitor
has a particular brightness at maximum, that it can output what we can
sort of think about is, you know, we can think about saying, we just
want a range of values between the darkest red, which is like no red
being output and the brightest red, which is the maximum read that the
monitor can output.
We've got a range between those and we typically pick 0 as the no red
value and one as the red value and zero.
No green.
One is the Grateful green 0 is the blue one is the zero is no blue.
One is known as like full blue, right?
And the reason that we do that is because it makes our math with them
be a lot easier, right?
If we set 0 equal to none right?
Of something and 1 equal to full
Then the nice part about that is that if we want to get something.
If we then want to know, sort of any kind of trafficking, what?
The easiest way to sort of show, how this happens is basically all of
your blending operations.
Everything that you might want to do with numbers is easier when you
normalize them to the range 0 to 1.
Specifically because you can always count on them being sort of in
that same scale range, right?
What's a good way to?
What's a good way to show this?
This is ample colors is not the best way to do.
Do it because really, I think a lot of times with colors because
they're separating, two channels.
It's it's not really going to be quite the same, but I'll kind of show
you an example in an other space.
So let's say I want to know how much of something I have a like sort
of a percentage, right?
So I want to, I want to know, like I've got sort of, I want to
represent in floating Point some amount of some arbitrary thing.
That thing has a range like we said before where, you know, there's a,
there's a none of it and there's an all of it and then we want to
represent everything in between, right?
And let's say it could be anything.
It's like it's like we've got, you know, we want to say that we've got
a pound of almonds, right, one pound of almonds for something like
this and we want to represent how much of that we have.
So one interesting thing about normalizing things from 0 to 1 is that
it can always be multiplied.
Convenient.
Ali into whatever the thing actually is, so if I then have basically a
percentage, right?
If I have a zero to one, you know, 1.0.0 to, to 1.0 of something.
If I ever have a ratio like this, I can trivially multiply whatever
the value is into any concept of what the maximum amount is 1 pound of
almonds 100, you know, and one Dalmatians.
However, many anything
Have I can always take one of these normalized values and multiply it
by whatever.
The thing is and get out how many I would have.
So for example, if I have a hundred and one Dalmatians, right?
If I have 101, Dalmatians, and you told me that I had 0.75 was, my was
my ratio number, right, which equivalent equivalent of 75%, right?
If I had, if I want to know how many Dalmatians 75% of the Dalmatians
is, right?
I can just multiply directly by that value.
I can say times 0.75 and there.
I know I have 75 and three-quarter Dalmatians, right?
Similarly, for my pound of almonds.
If I know I have one pound of almonds.
I can do it times 0.75.
And now I have three quarters of you know of a pound of almonds if I
have something like 735 viewers on Twitch, right?
I don't know how many beers are on to it right now.
But let's say we've got some viewers on Twitch.
That's probably a lot for a morning stream.
So, so maybe not that many.
But let's say it was an evening.
You get that many and so then we go ahead and we say, how many viewers
are 75% of them.
Well, it's 55 one and a quarter of fortunately, one of our viewers
gets gets drawn and quartered apparently and we only have a quarter of
them.
But who does our maybe that's the split attention.
So, basically, what what I wanted to kind of impress here, is that
doing things as a number between zero and one, kind of has this Fringe
benefit of, you can always do math.
You could always up convert from zero from a 0 to 1 range into any
other Ranger.
That you want, but the same is not true for if you store the values in
their actual space.
So let's say we have 101 Dalmatians, and then I said, well, now we
have seventy five point seven five Dalmatians, right?
That was the number we had before.
And now we want to know how much is that same percentage in twitch
viewers?
Right?
Well, I can't just multiply seventy five point seven, five times seven
thirty-five and get the same percentage of twitch viewers.
First.
I would have to do the Divide.
I'd have to do the
Slide back out.
I'd have to say seventy five point seven, five divided by 101 to get
me my 75% again and then I could multiply it by the 735 viewers on
Twitch and then I would get back the actual number.
Does that make sense?
So percentage or which is 0 to 1 in representing floating point is
kind of the universal storage for the amount of something that you
have.
It's a dimension free way of storing an amount.
And so we typically use it for things like this.
We're just saying how much of something do we have?
Where we don't really want to talk about any actual output units.
It's usually just the most convenient space.
So you'll see it happening a lot.
And so it's a good thing to be comfortable with.
So what I want to do is I want to do exactly that.
I want to say that we pass in an r g and B.
And then what I want to do is reproduce this color value that we used
to be making here.
Right?
I want to reproduce this color value by integrate, like sort of
pulling out what the values of the color value should be.
If we have this 0 this 0 to
10 to 1.
Now, this is again, a color value that's made to right into one of
these abgar buffers.
Remember we talked about ABG our way back to being the screen, right?
So we know that our bit pattern right is going to be, you know,
something like a a RR GG BB, right?
So what I need to do and again, this is each one of these 8 Bits.
That's 8, Bits to nibbles, 8 Bits, right?
8, B, 8 B, 8, B, 8 B makes a 32-bit number.
So, to produce one of those eight values, right?
I know I have a number between 0 and 1 and I know the maximum that an
8-bit value can be is 255, right?
So if I wanted to produce an 8-bit integer value from a floating Point
number that's between zero and one, I need to first take that and
multiply it out so that I get 255 at maximum and 08.
Them, right?
So that's one way to do it.
Right?
I could say that I'm going to have our and I'm going to make it be
equal to 2, you know, I'm going to multiply by 255 which means that I
will get and, you know, and then I can can truncate that to, you know,
change that to an integer value.
So one way I could do it is that but if you think about it, there's
it's a little there's a little bit of trickiness involved here.
There's a little bit of sort of subtlety involved.
And the reason for that is because
Does well when we multiply by, by when we do this and multiply it, by
that value.
Do you remember what I said about the rounding yesterday, you know,
when we round we talked about how the rounding Works.
Oops.
Got oh, Don black color.
There you remember.
I was talking about the number line and I was saying, all right, we've
got this number line and it kind of goes on, right?
And it's like 0 1, 2 3 4, and so on.
And I was saying in, see this, this in 32, when I, when I do the cast,
from a floating point value down to ensure value, it's going to
truncate, right?
So what that
Is if the color value was like here, right?
So let's say, I multiply this out and let's say that the value comes
out to be, you know, 0.9 0.9, which is almost one.
So, you know, so this value is something really low and multiplies by
255, and, and the value.
So, you know, our x 2 +.
55 becomes 0.9, right?
That's just what the result is.
It's right.
Like up here, but the truncation is going to move that back down to
Zero, right.
So what we might want to do is do the same rounding thing that we did
before right now you could argue about what is the more accurate thing
to do here, because it would depend on how you were producing.
These are values to begin with what you actually wanted to have
happen.
But it seems like, you know, a totally reasonable thing to want to
Round, right?
Because we know that will never produce anything higher than 255.
So because the are, if it was 1.0, which is the maximum value, we know
that we would that we're going to allow.
We know that we would never
Anything higher than 55.
So we don't have to worry about it wrapping up to 256 because you can
never produce 55.5 or higher.
So what I might do is say let's go ahead and do that same rounding
operation because that might give us a little bit of a more accurate
conversion, but rather than doing the truncation, right?
Does that make sense?
So I'm just going to do that for now.
We again, when we get to the render, we can talk a little more about
those values and really think about what the most accurate ways to
deal with everything.
I'm kind of getting close to close to my head there.
So, what I want to do, right?
Is I want to be able to produce one of these for each of my color
values.
Right?
I want the are the G and the B.
I want those all in here, right?
And oops.
And I want, when I have the are the G in the be in there, I'm going to
multiply them each app to basically get a number between 55 and 00:25.
And that's going to now be an integer value.
And so now, all I have to do is, do the bit packing again, to make
sure that they each end up in the right place in.
Now, we know that our was 24 bits up right on the bit pattern.
So, we know that that is, oops.
Sorry.
We know that it's from bit 2024, down to 16.
So we've got to shift it up 16 so that it starts a bit, 16, 17, 18,
19, 20, 21, 22, 23 24, write the 8 Bits starts there.
The green value was right below that, so that's eight bits up.
And the blue value was at the bottom, right?
So that's 0 B up.
Now, we don't actually have to shift by zero, but sometimes it's kind
of nice to show that.
So you can kind of just see it cleanly where each thing is going to
go.
Right.
It's kind of a nice thing to line up.
And then if we or those together using our bitwise or write, that will
basically combine each set of bits.
Right?
So, we've got a set of bits here.
The set of bits here.
That said, if it's here at, they'll each going to get up.
Now, of course, I lost my little cast in there.
My cast actually needs to be.
Oops.
Oh, I don't need the cast anymore.
Duh, the cast actually taken care of for of it right here, right?
So, that's actually totally fine.
Now.
I didn't want a signed value here, but I think that's actually fine
for it to be signed.
So, but you know what?
I
Actually do this.
I could I could actually make one for signed in one for unsigned for
the moment just to be explicit because sometimes, you know, later on,
maybe we care.
Who knows.
So, there we go.
See here.
And so now we should be able to specify our color values in a way.
That's a little more sort of.
It doesn't have that weird 0 to 255 thing in it.
So now, instead of that lets actually pass it, red green blue.
That's just a little more convenient and easier to understand and
let's see to reproduce this.
We have, let's see.
Green blue.
There we go.
Okay, rectangle and let me see.
There's our rectangle up in the corner as we expected in the colors
are correct.
And so now, it's kind of nice too because I can sort of
I can sort of see as we go, you know, it's much.
We go.
Does that work now?
Yeah, that way I can flip back and forth.
So basically, if we go in here, now, you can see as I go if I want it
half-bright there, I can do that and
What happened?
Oh, I didn't recompile ice creaking pal.
If I want half right there.
I can do that.
Right?
I can change it back up to full bright.
Oops, change back up to full bright.
Let's say, I want to make this more of a yellow color, right?
I can do that if I want to make it pure red, right?
And so it's pretty easy to see like how these color values mix
together and they're just between 0 and 1.
So you don't have the 255, the word 255 nonsense anymore going on.
So that's it.
That's just all I wanted to do there, right?
So already you can kind of see and I don't know if now is necessarily
the right time to do it.
But already, you can start to see to there's some there's some
structures that are starting to emerge.
Here like chances are, we're probably not often going to pass a red
value by itself.
It's probably going to come with a green in the blue, right?
And so, you can start to see already game art.
Again.
Game architecture wise, just low level stuff.
You can sort of start to see what we're
Probably want to do here, right?
We're probably going to want to make a struct that will capture the
the concept of a color so that we don't have to keep passing.
Our are jeez and bees around.
I'm not going to quite do it yet.
But you can because you know, we only have even one function that uses
it.
But think about that, just keep that in the back of your mind.
These are the sorts of things that you should start to be paying
attention to, right?
You should start kind of having this inkling in the back of your head,
when you see that you're like, okay, there's these operations that are
happening on a color.
There's a way that represents the minuend 32
To and then there's this real to this realtor to version.
I'm passing a bunch of things together.
There's just a lot of things you can start to see if you're paying
attention that.
Maybe that way a rectangle might be another one.
You can see that we're doing operations on rectangles here.
So there's just there's things that you can start to think about in
terms of what might be useful for.
The low level architecture stuff that we might want to start doing
their starting to emerge already and we haven't even really done
anything yet, right.
All right.
So again, let's make the most stupid basic tilemap, that we might want
to make.
Let's just make something extremely simple for a tile map that we can
draw on the screen.
So what I'm going to do here is really the most basic simple thing
that you could possibly imagine.
I'm just going to say alright, I'm just going to have some 32-bit
value and I'm going to make you know, a tile map of them and I'm going
to say how big do we want our town map to be across and down?
You know, and I don't know, I think I thought about this a bunch, if I
remember correctly earlier on and I'm not sure, I'm not sure what the
value was.
I'll look it up because I thought about this, I think 16 across was
was what I thought that the the right value was for the number of
tiles going this way.
And I think it might have been nine down.
It was, I think it was 16 by 9, but look roughly the same as an HD
aspect.
Splay ratio 16 tiles across by nine up and down.
And I don't know that may be a little too big.
I I work this out.
I was kind of looking at past games and what their town map sizes was
but we can adjust this in the future, but I'm just going to say all
right.
I'm going to make a tile map.
So basically all I'm doing is making an array.
That's 16 by 9.
I'm going to I'm going to reverse them here because this is the if you
look at the way, see does it syntax.
This is actually the one that gets packed together.
So these go sequentially, the 16 go sequentially and the 9.
So it's like rose and so I wanted the the
Just kind of go sequentially there.
So, what I'm going to do is, I'm actually going to Define my tile map,
right here as like, a little, you know, as like a little, I guess hand
inputted thing.
Right?
One, two, three, four.
Why would I do that?
Three, four, five, six, seven, eight, nine, ten, eleven, twelve see do
it this way.
Make it look clear.
Twelve, thirteen.
Fourteen, fifteen sixteen, right?
So, here is a tile map.
A one, two, three, four, five, six, seven, eight, nine, we go.
So
there we go.
So this is our little tile map here, which I'm just going to hand
input.
Right?
And I'm going to go ahead and make something incredibly simple in the
tile map.
I don't know.
I'm just going to do something that we would be able to see if it was
working properly.
Kind of a thing.
There we go.
Something like this where I'm just going to hand in put some numbers
that we should be able to then verify are sort of coming out.
Correct when we look at the tile map at the end of the day, okay.
Right, very, very simple.
So you can kind of see what I did there.
I basically just spammed in someone's into our town map.
And now what I'd like to do is I'd like to draw the tile map to the
screen as the background.
I'm going to clear it first.
I'm going to clear the screen just to that purple as a purely, debug
operation so that I can verify right.
I can verify what's being written and I can see if there's purple
showing through.
I'm then going to iterate over my entire town map.
So I'm going to do the row of the tile map, right?
I'm going to do the row and I've got nine of those and then I'm going
to do the columns and I've got 16 of those, right?
And again, this is not, this is just purely.
Like I said before, just exploratory code.
I'm typing whatever I want in here and when you are in this mode, and
this is just really important.
And remember when you're in this mode, anything goes, do not think
about code quality.
Do not, think about errors, do not, think about performance, don't
think about anything because the point of this code is to see what you
would type in.
If you literally just had to do the thing fast.
You just want to draw tile map on the screen, so don't think about
anything other than what is the easiest way you can think of to put
that tile map up on the screen in a way that you can.
An view, right?
That is the only thing that you should be thinking about.
You should never, ever, ever give even a moment's thought to any of
the things that you see, in those books that are like writing clean
code and like how effective C++.
Also, all that stuff should be completely shut off in your brain
because what this code is for is for us to see what the CPU has to do,
in order to do the thing that we want.
It's just to get it some notion of
What the code has to do?
And then we're just going to look at that after and figure out what
the clean way to make it is, right?
So you should be thinking about absolutely nothing at this point.
Other than exactly that.
Exactly, the how to get the thing up on the screen.
That's it.
So brain should be exclusively one track in that mode.
That's all.
Okay.
So we have our draw rectangle function.
So what we need to know now and this is like our this is our tile
value our tile idea.
If you want to call it, I don't know.
We're going to call it.
But there we go.
So we have a tile ID.
And what I'd like to do is say, well, alright, we essentially want the
color to be based on this tile idea because we only have the, we don't
have an ability to draw any Sprites or anything yet.
We haven't written the renderer.
So basically we only have the ability to draw color.
So what I'll do is I'll draw a great gray scale colors and I'll have
two of them, right?
So what we'll assume is will assume that if the value is 0 in the tile
map, right?
We'll have a gray value of.
Let's say .5 and if the tile ID actually is equal to 1, let's say then
I'm going to make it be white.
So we'll have
Gray, and white things in our town map makes sense seems reasonable.
All right.
So then, when I draw the rectangle, I'm going to need some things.
I'm going to need them in X, right.
I'm going to need them in, why?
I'm going to need the, the max X and the max y.
So, basically, I know whatever.
My Min is the tile width and the tile height, whatever.
We decide that those are right.
However, big those are
I know that basically whatever the max extra my rectangle is is just
the Min plus the tile.
However, big the tile should be across and the same is true of the of
the, of the vertical extent of the of the height, right?
So main X and Y, Max x max, why red green blue?
And of course, we're only doing gray so I can just pass the same value
for each of them.
There we go.
So, the only question is, what's our main X.
Well, we know, we've got a row value and a column value, right?
And so for every,
Row.
We want to go like each time that row increments.
We're going to go down by 1 tile height.
Right.
Which we already know is going to be a value.
So we've got the row times the tile height, right?
And row is going to an integer.
Whereas all the rest of the stuff is float.
So we need to convert that up to a floating point value again.
See what I think.
We'll just do that for you, but I like to make it explicit.
So you everyone can see that it's happening in the code.
So I do that.
Usually,
And so also, so the I know.
So there's not weird mistakes.
I find that if I ever do everything explicitly, I don't get caught by
some weird see thing where it's like decided because of some rule in
the spec not to do something that I would have thought that it should
do.
So basically, this is every column we're going to go up by a certain
amount and every row we know where I'm sorry, every row and we're
going to go down by certain Mountain.
Every column.
We're going to go over by a certain amount and that's fine.
And so what we might want to do, though is to start an offset.
So we might want to make these start a little bit further in.
So let's say we can say upper
Left X and upper left.
Why?
Alright, so there we go.
So now what we need to do is actually find those values.
Those are just constant values upper left X.
Let's say it starts at 10, right?
So they'll be a little border around the thing and 10 and then the
tile with, I don't know what the tile with should be.
We can certainly adjust it.
Let's say it's 100 by 100 tile height that and we can recompile.
And hey, there's our tile map on the screen.
So that's pretty good though, and I still got that other rectangle,
which I don't need any more that can go away.
So now we've
got our town map on the screen and of
We don't even have to do any math because that's the Miracle again of
hot loading.
The dll.
Everything gets trivial.
We can just do this and there's our tile map is smaller.
All right, let's let's make it a little larger.
Okay, that's good.
Maybe they're, that's good.
Let's say it should be 55 wide, something like that.
Just a little bigger 60.
60.
That's a little too big.
So anyway, although you know, what, if I actually just started it in
the corner and didn't have that offset, right?
You know, that's what you were thinking, right?
I think that's.
I think that's our winner.
Yeah.
Alright.
So there you go.
There's our tile map.
It's on the screen.
And of course, now we can create.
I mean, you can create a level if you wanted to, right?
I could say that this is a standard dungeon map, which would look
something like this.
Let's go.
Insert mode there.
If I want to make a dungeon map.
Now I'm making a dungeon map.
That's always fun.
We all know, right?
Because Legend of Zelda, set the set the bar and now you see it all
the time.
Like Binding of Isaac, right, looks exactly like this as well.
Basically, you've got a thing around, you got walls around the edge,
but then you have like a door right in the middle.
And that might be a reason not to use 16, because we can't we don't
have a middle value.
So we may want to use 17, you know what I'm saying?
So there's our doors.
We should probably make sure the doors aren't blocked.
Right.
Let's make sure those doors aren't blocked.
Don't block the doors people to player.
Can't get in or out that point.
There you go.
So now our player, you know, could walk in here, you could walk
around, you could walk out that way, whatever you want to do, but
that's not centered.
So that seems like a pretty obvious reason not to use that.
So I'm going to go ahead and say that 17 is the magic value, right?
I don't see why not.
So basically there's there's this extra row over here, right?
If that makes sense.
That we're going to push out there.
Let's go ahead and do that.
Oops, too much space.
White space.
So let's go ahead and push that out.
Doodoo pushing it out.
And then we can just say all right, that's that's going to be that so
if that's the case then we also have to do we have to figure out our
offsets are going to be a little different here.
So that means that you know, the the upper left is going to have to be
offset by a little bit right like that so that essentially you don't
quite see the whole tile because wouldn't fit.
Only.
And the same is probably, you know, you probably want to do something
similar.
I don't know if we could, so let's say we did that.
So you kind of only see half of that border tile.
Then what we would want to do is we want to make it 10 wide, but that
would make it so that we couldn't Center our other guy.
Mmm-hmm.
You see my dilemma.
I don't know.
Do you see my dilemma?
I'm not sure if you see my dilemma or not.
I feel like we want the thing.
the things to be square, but I'm not sure how I'm not sure how I
About, I mean, do I just do this?
So that that basically this style is always shown as a half tile.
I don't know something to think about, right?
I'm already thinking about that.
And again, like I said, this is why we do all this exploration because
I want to think about all these things up front, before I make
decisions about, like what our town map sizes and all that sort of
thing, right?
Okay.
So that's our tile map.
I'm not going to think too hard about it at the moment.
But like I said, it's already putting thoughts in my head.
Like, I got to start thinking about how I want to deal with that
stuff.
So I might go study old games, that sort of thing to think about what
the the dimensions of this tile map should be.
Now, one of the things that's interesting is it didn't used to be 16
by 9, like Zelda, for example, was four by three aspect ratio, right?
Who's on the old TVs before HD went wide screen.
And so I don't know.
That may be a
So the fact that we're 16 by 9 now that things get a little bit
different and we have to think about how we want to handle that.
Exactly.
It's something to think about.
And so I would encourage everyone to put their thinking caps on there.
Now.
The other thing that we could do, right is we could say that we have
some kind of a gutter on the screen.
I don't know.
There's a lot of things we could think about there.
And so, I would encourage you all to think about them, maybe post your
opinions because this is essentially designed question some level and
maybe think about those.
And what you what you think about them, essentially, because I'll be
thinking about them as well, and maybe that's a good exercise to do.
All right.
So given that I've got this situation where I actually have a Time app
on the screen.
It seems like the next logical thing to do is to make a little player
that can move around on them at a very minimum, right?
Because we know we're going to need that.
And so if I go ahead and here and I, you know, I want to essentially
add some storage for for my player, just a really basic stuff inside
the game State structure.
Now.
Normally, we shouldn't be able to really do much to
Sure is without while we're hot loading.
But in this particular case, I think it'll actually work.
And the reason for that is because
There is no actual stuff in the game State structure.
It's just the beginning of our memory block and nothing else is stored
in the memory block either.
So if we just go ahead and start writing to those values, it just
works, right?
So I can do that, and nothing will break because there's nothing
actually getting rearranged.
It's just adding some stuff to the end.
And so the hot loading I think will actually still work.
So, what I'm gonna do now is I'm going to draw a player in here,
right?
And the player is probably going to be out of no, let's let's say that
that the player X and Y.
Y values should probably be, I would suspect the player X and Y should
probably represent some value.
That's at the base of the character, trying to think of how to explain
this.
I might need a diagram for it, just
Just trying to tell you what I'm thinking here.
So if I have a tile map on the screen, right, and I'm looking at this
tile map, sort of.
As as a as grids and you know, I've got some notion of things like
like this is a wall, right?
And these are filled in and I can't walk there.
Well, normally what happens is the player actually the players Sprite,
right?
Doesn't stop when the top of the Sprite hits that wall.
Usually what happens is they kind of eclipse the wall a bit.
So they're actual location is typically more about where their center
of gravity.
Projected on the floor if you will write like like usually the the
player Sprite kind of eclipses the wall like this.
It comes in front of the wall, you know, and so the position if I was
checking the position against the tile map in some way, I'm not
checking the center of it.
Right.
And I'm not checking the upper left corner or the lower right corner.
I'm checking this sort of center of the bottom of the Sprite in some
sense.
Now.
I will probably do something a little more.
You can, we probably make maybe like a little bit of a circle there
for Clues injection, eventually, who knows what we'll do.
We might we're not going to probably literally just check a point when
removing the guy around, but for starters, we'll probably just do
that.
And I want to do something relatively close to I might actually want
so we can see how it feels.
We move them around.
So basically right here is mostly what I want.
So when I draw this guy, I'm thinking that.
What I want to do is say all right, where I draw the rectangle.
The X and Y, for the player comes in, you know, I don't actually know
exactly what I want here.
But I want something like the upper corner of the rectangle.
We want to subtract the height of the player, right?
So we want to subtract the height and then we want to subtract half
the width right?
Because this is half.
This is the half line and then we draw the player between there and
the width height, right?
So we kind of want to this is our this is our kind of diagram for how
we want to.
To draw that if this is the player ex-player ex-player, why right?
So really straightforward stuff here, but again, since this is the
very beginning of our work with this sort of thing.
I just kind of want to explain these things in a little more detail
for people who've never done stuff like this before.
When I do is this stuff.
It's like second nature.
It's like, oh, yeah.
I just got that would just type and like come out of my fingers if I
start typing, right, but that's only because I mean, like, when I was
little, I mean, I was, when I was like eight years old, right?
I used to draw things on graph paper and input them into the computer
for graphics because we didn't even have like paint programs or
anything like this, right?
And so a lifetime of doing stuff like this means, you can just do it
in your head, but if you've never done,
With Graphics before you have to, actually think it through, right?
And it's only, after you've thought it through a bunch of times that
you're just its second nature to you.
It's like anything else, right?
And so, yeah, if you've done this before, then, you know what I'm
talking about because you've got so many, but if you've never done
this before and you're like, whoa, you know, what's going on?
As you do this more you it will become second nature to you.
You won't have to sit and think about these things.
You'll just be like, boom.
And you've got it, but it does take a while to get to that point.
Right?
Like it's like having done it all the
Time.
It's like riding a bike.
Right?
You're just kind of like, all right.
Yeah, I know how to do rectangle Scouts and similarly, you know how to
debug them.
So you'll do the rectangle calc in your head.
You'll type it out and sometimes you're wrong and you see the wrong
thing.
I'm your like up.
Yep.
I forgot the blah and you do it, right?
So you're not, you remember some combination of how to always do it
right in your head and how to correct the things you often do wrong in
your head.
It's real funny.
You'll see it happen on the stream.
I'm sure.
I don't know if it'll happen right now, but it'll happen.
So anyway, we want to draw the player and I'm just going to do a
player, our player G, right?
Player be kind of a thing that and so I want to draw a rectangle of
the player.
I want a player width, right player with and player height.
And I'm not sure what those should be.
Right?
I don't really know.
I have no idea.
I'm going to make him the tile within the tile height at the
Moment.
But that's probably a little too wide because if he has to move
through you probably want them to have a little bit of slop when he
moves through things.
So, you know, we could even say that it's going to be 75 percent of
the width or something like that.
I don't know.
I'm not sure.
Like I said, really don't know.
So then what we're going to do is say, alright when we actually go to
draw this guy, right?
I want to do player, our player Jeep.
Player B.
And I want to do them in X Min Y is going to be our game state, which
remember I did get up here.
It's right here.
So we pulled that that's the base of our memory block.
So it's going to be the game State player X.
In fact, I probably should do this top player top and player left
that.
So I'm going to take that player X.
And like I said, I want to make
A left of the player b, - whatever half is with is, right.
So I'm going to do half, right, multiplying by Point, 5 is half.
You do half the width, move it back.
And again, that corresponds to this error, right here, right?
So, I'm taking the x of the player and I'm moving it back by half the
width.
And then I want to take the whole player height here, and I want to go
back by the entire player, height like that.
Right, and so I'm going to go ahead and say player left plus player
width.
Are top Loops that Claire left plus player wit?
Don't know how that got in there.
We're top post player height this.
And so now, I've sort of got basically.
I'm passing the left in the top as the place to start.
And then I'm passing for the mat Thumb in X-Men, why the max x max Y
is going to be plus the width and the height, right?
And that's the entirety of my player drawing code at the moment.
Now, we don't actually know where the player is.
Of course.
It's also a problem.
So, the values that are in there or whatever the values were.
So that's
Certainly a bit of a problem like the play, the actual game State
player ex-player.
Why?
And well, I guess I could do this game State player x equals 1000
something like this.
Let's say,
There we go.
And then you can see him up there, right there he is, and now we're
probably going to need some way to move him around, so we can go up to
our controller code again.
Make this a little bit bigger.
So we don't have to program in a little tiny window.
We can go up to our controller code, which we had here and I'm going
to use the digital movement.
I'm going to use the keyboard for now because I don't want to deal
with the analog movement at the moment.
So basically what we want to do is say, all right, we have these these
buttons, right?
And I'm going to say
That I have a Slayer X Delta and a player, y, Delta.
And at the end.
I'm going to take the player X and the player Y, and I'm going to add
those right this.
Okay, so if my controller input move up and down, right?
And I'm just going to kind of do this sort of thing, right?
So move, move down.
Move left move, right?
I'm going to say that.
If move up and down, then the the player X is going to be, I'm sorry,
the player why is is going to be one and if it moved up, right if he's
moving up.
Its - if there
Down it's positive.
Deep layer x equals negative 1.
If he's moving to the left because he's moving getting lower in Acts
and and hire an X.
Right.
So I'm just going to do that for now.
Should be pretty basic.
That's game State.
Yeah, and so, now I should be able to move my guy around.
Yeah.
There we go.
So, there's the dude, right?
And he's moving around now.
He moves around pretty slowly and that's fine.
Not a particularly Speedy fellow at the moment.
Point.
Of course.
I also don't actually know what our frame rate is right now because
we're not even printing it out.
And so we are going to have to do some stuff here in a second.
To think about how that should go.
So in fact, let's just do that, right?
Because hey, we've got a, we've got a player Sprite moving around the
screen.
Let's think about that.
So, what would happen here?
If I did this?
What does that actually mean?
What did I actually just right?
Well, what I wrote is, I said that the players Exposition is going to
be updated by one every time, a frame goes by.
And the, like the D key is down.
Basically what that boils down to, right there, moving to the right.
So, because this is in pixels, essentially.
Write all of this is in pixels.
That just means he's going to move one pixel to the, right?
Every frame.
Now.
There's a couple reasons why we have.
That's not such a great way to do things.
One is because our frame rate now, determines the speed that the
person moves at.
If our frame rate is 30 frames a second, right?
If our frame rate of 30 frames a second, then he is going to be moving
at 30 pixels a second.
But if our frame rate were to jump up to 60 frames a second because
the platform layer decided to run at a faster frame rate, then he
would move twice as fast and the game would play twice as fast, which
is not what we want.
So, what we want to do is we want to take the actual value that we're
getting in here for the amount that we're supposed to move by right
seconds to advance over update, right?
Of that name s.
I I couldn't decide what I wanted that be.
Let's see.
I'm going to call it DT, right?
4D time DT for frame.
So the amount of time that elapses over the frame is what we're going
to do.
Excuse me.
And so, what I'm going to do there is I'm going to go ahead and
multiply however, much the value should be however, much the motion
should be.
I'm going to multiply whatever the the movement direction is.
Essentially.
I'm going to multiply that by whatever, that whatever that DT value
is, right?
So, that way, I'm going to get a constant amount.
So, if this, if the amount of time that has passed goes down,
Then the amount of movement will go down.
If the amount of time goes up, then the amount of movement will go up,
which is what I want.
The pillow to do in here.
There's stuff that I haven't talked about yet.
And so I can't do some things that I would normally do here.
But I'm going to tell don't mention what they are briefly and they
will move on.
Okay.
So what I want to do is I want to take this DT and I want to, I want
to that's in the input structure, right?
I want to go ahead and multiply that out.
So now we have a fixed amount per per frame basically.
And of course, the problem with it is, this is now going to be
incredibly slow because that means he now moves one pixel a second.
These values are now in seconds because we're multiplying.
Lying by that DT.
And again, this is the dimensional analysis again, that I've talked
about many times, essentially, what we have is we have a dt4 frame.
Right.
So for the frame we have, this is this is essentially the number of
seconds that we're going to have.
So this is in seconds.
This is some number of seconds.
It's DT, s that we're getting passed in.
So we're going to multiply we're multiplying that by something.
We're multiplying that by a value.
And we're getting pixels out, right?
We're going to we're taking the result and we're using it as pixels.
So, dimensional analysis Works in Reverse as well.
We know that, if we ended up with pixels and we started with
Kids, we know that the thing that we're multiplying by we can fill in
the unit's, right?
Pixels is on the top because that's what we ended up with and second
says, on the bottom, right?
So, we now know that the value is in pixels per second.
This is pixels per second, right?
That's what we did.
So if we're doing one pixels per second, that's just not very many.
So let's get.
Let the guy move 32 pixels for a second.
Let's say, or you know what?
We can do that in an easier way.
Can basically say at the bottom right?
Let's just give them.
Give them some speed there.
Right?
And off we go.
Oops, where's my game?
There's one game, right?
So now he's moving a little faster.
It's not great, but it's faster, right?
Why is my move up button?
Not working.
Do we have a bug somewhere?
Nice.
Oops?
Sorry about that.
Too many windows open.
Where's my damn game?
There it is.
All right.
So then the guys moving around still pretty still pretty slow.
30 pixels of second is not very many as you can see.
Let's get them up a little bit higher speed of the game.
Maybe, maybe let's say that he should be at 128 pixels per second,
something like that.
See how that is.
There.
He goes.
Moving along.
Well, although you know what, I think our frame rate is pretty darn
low here, right?
Because look at how slow look at how jerk talk chunky.
That is.
So maybe.
We might not actually be if we're not hitting our frame rate.
Then this isn't in s anymore.
We could change to passing the actual time that has elapsed, but
that's, that's unfortunate.
So, I wonder, I wonder how slow we're actually going.
So let's take a look.
Let me go ahead and close this out.
Let's take a look because we have to hit our frame rate.
Otherwise, our timing values will be wrong.
Now.
The other thing we can do here is past the actual time value that's
going through.
Maybe this is something we'll have to do in the win32 platform layer
relatively soon.
Actually, if you think about it, I got to fix the bug now in the
platform there as well.
We change this name to dt4 frame, right?
So, there we go, but I guess our frame frame rate is pretty darn low,
which is unfortunate.
Let's take a look at what it actually is.
So we can see.
Hmm.
Are we are we not actually measuring the value though.
Am I doing something wrong here?
What are we printing out?
Milliseconds per frame.
Now we're looking at, get seconds elapsed.
So what?
So I think I've done something.
So we got a bug here.
I feel like is that actually
Milliseconds per frame.
Right.
And that is actually being measured by the win32 get seconds elapsed.
So for taking 33 milliseconds per frame, we should be animating very
smoothly.
Right?
We should see something very smooth happening on here.
And yet, do you see how jerky that is?
Why is that so jerky.
What's the bug, does anyone know what the bug is?
I'm not sure if they do.
I certainly don't.
So why is that so jerky if we're getting a totally smooth frame rate
that seems wrong.
So what's like I said, I don't know what the actual problem is there.
I would like to know I suppose it could be, this could be the the
streaming thing again, but I don't know.
I don't want to assume that, it's just OBS doing that.
And I guess I don't have a real way to test that unfortunately, but I
don't want to assume that that's true.
If it's not actually true, but it seems like we should be getting 30
frames a second.
And yet we're not what would happen.
Let's say if I changed it to 60 frames a second as our Target.
I'm just curious.
Let's see.
So game update Hertz is Monitor, refresh rate divided by 2.
Well, let's just say that.
It's not that anymore.
It's just buy one.
Well, so that does seem awfully smooth smoother.
So I wonder if this is OBS is just messing with us.
That's kind of unfortunate.
I'll have to test that separately on the stream because we are hitting
our frame rate.
As far as I can tell.
It's actually working properly and it does get smoother when we output
faster, which means that that could be because we're getting like a
beat frequency.
Mmm-hmm.
That's unfortunate.
Yeah, you know, I guess maybe I've been
So I will have to go to using a capture card.
I was hoping not to have to go to using a capture card for this sort
of stuff because I was because they seem kind of unreliable
potentially, but it looks like I may have to, I kind of need to get
Things out of the out of the equation here, if that's the case.
Yeah, you can see how jerky that is.
And that's really annoying to me.
Now.
Maybe it looks smooth to you for all.
I know it looks smooth on the stream, but it looks very jerky to me.
It's I guess all I can say, so yeah.
So, let's see if this holds water as well.
We know how many pixels up and down, we are.
So I'm going to time how long it takes to get there.
One, two, three, four, five, six, seven, eight.
So, take some eight seconds to get like, by my crappy just me counting
right, which is not a particularly good way to do it.
But if it takes him eight seconds to get to the bottom and our
He was going to move 128 pixels per second.
Then we should expect right?
That it should be somewhere around there, you know is the height of
the window and I was just counting randomly.
So it could be more like 800 or something like that.
But let's take a look at what it actually is because I'm just trying
to determine what.
Yeah, I feel like that's I feel like that's way too long to get from
the top to the bottom, if that makes sense.
So, I feel like I've still got, I feel like there's there's a bug in
here as I guess all I can say.
So, I believe we said
It was 540.
Right?
So if feels it, feels like, maybe that's twice as fast as it should be
or somewhere on there.
Now, maybe again, like I said, maybe I was counting a little bit too
fast, but it just feels it just feels off.
It.
Just feels off to me and I feel like we've got a bug somewhere, but,
of course, it is.
The end of the Stream.
So, I guess basically note Casey, we are sorry, I should say to do
Casey.
Let's
Take a close look at timing tomorrow and try to verify that it is
working properly, because it appears that things are moving half as
fast as I would have expected, right?
So, I think that's our to do for tomorrow.
All right.
Excuse me.
So now it is time to go to the Q&A.
And yes, please make sure that you prefix or questions with Q: so I
can see them.
And also, please keep the questions to what we've done today stream or
stuff.
We did on previous streams so that we essentially don't don't get too
far off base with what we're talking about.
So, let's take a look here.
Let us take a look at the questions.
Asleep.
Still oversleeping and throwing off the FPS asked enemy Mouse.
Well, we can certainly find out.
And one thing that we can do is we can adjust our sleep or we can get
rid of our sleep entirely for now, right?
We could in our sleep code.
I think we have a sleep as granular thing that we set.
We could decide to just
We could decide to just be a CPU melter and say sleep is granular
equals false, right?
And at least for me, it doesn't get any better.
Unfortunately, that's without sleep.
Right?
Because I believe.
Now we can, we can verify that that sleep is is not actually
happening.
If I go down here and set a breakpoint in the Sleep code.
It should never happen, right?
Yeah.
Basically, it's not, it's not sleep.
And I think we kind of knew that it wasn't sleep because because if it
was sleep, we would have seen that our millisecond timer is actually
timing.
What happens in that case, right?
You can see down here, where we print out this this FPS buffer thing
milliseconds, per frame was actually computed up here from the actual
count that happens after the sleep.
So we would have seen our frame rate be wrong.
If that were the case, our frame rate number, so we are we are at
least getting through the loop in 33 milliseconds.
Right?
But we're hitting some kind of a beat frequency with either with OBS
or just the window compositor where we're not actually able to update
at that rate or something or something else is wrong.
So we definitely have some kind of a problem there, but I'm just not
sure what it is.
So we're going to have to take a look and see.
You know, what?
What is what are, what are bug is or what Windows is doing?
That's supporting us, one of the other.
It's bugged because you only set DT frame on one of the two input.
So did I put that in the wrong place?
Haha.
Awesome.
Thank you for that.
Catch.
Oh, you're right.
Oh, that's awful.
That's not what I want.
That's that's not where I wanted to put that at all.
Yeah, this is again, the problem of thank you.
That is definitely our bug.
I wanted to put that where we first do our input.
It might be time to start cleaning this code up a little bit.
I didn't really want to spend any time on it.
But yeah, what we wanted to do is do it in the actual Loop itself.
That was a mistake.
So I didn't mean to do it here.
That was dumb.
What I wanted to do.
Is do it here, right?
I wanted to do it at the beginning of every frame and so that's the
reason.
Yeah, thanks for that catch.
The problem is that I thought I was setting it every frame, but I
actually set it just at the before we even entered the loop, right?
And so one of our inputs was 0.
So every other frame, it wasn't updating, which is exactly what I
thought, that's weird.
You can sense when these things are wrong.
So it was moving.
Exactly half as fast with is exactly what I felt like was happening
and my timing.
Yeah, so there we go.
That's what I would have expected.
It's still not the smoothest thing in the world, which I think is just
a no BS problem, but, you know, that's, that's much better.
Thank you play triangles for Christ.
I love that name to play triangles where Christ is.
I mean who wouldn't do that for Christ?
All right.
So, let's see here.
Let's go ahead and put that on there.
So now that's more what we would expect.
Okay, so that's good.
Now, we're good.
Everything's better.
I knew there was a bug.
I'm like something.
Something's, busted.
Thank you very much.
This is the magic of the street.
Basically, the fact that there are so many people watching the stream.
Totally compensates for my lack of ability to concentrate.
It's like, perfect.
So that's good.
So now we don't have that anymore.
We can get rid of that to do.
Thank you.
Garland abloom, possibly, we need to sink our refresh rate with the
windows vsync.
Otherwise windows will just be tossing out some of our frames and
causing jerky movement.
Yes, that is absolutely happening.
Unfortunately.
I don't know of a good way to do that until we move to opengl and
direct3d.
I wish I did but I'm not sure really how to do that.
There is a direct direct draw call that you can use but I don't really
know.
I don't know how supported that is anymore.
Well seem to opengl and direct3d.
This will be solved for us because they allow us to do that
automatically, but I don't know how to do it until then.
On the topic of the town map size.
Maybe you could go for smaller sized tiles.
Keep an even number of them on both sides and use the two middle for
the doors.
Yes, we could.
That's a good point.
We could do that, but then are the doors, but that is really helpful,
because there aren't the top doors wider than the side doors.
The problem.
Is it 16?
By 9 is the display?
So, the problem is not how many tiles there are.
The problem is that we have an odd number of tiles in One Direction,
in an, even number of tiles in the other direction.
If we want the towels to be,
We're right.
So I don't think that actually helps.
Why you don't use any created before engines like opengl es F ml,
Allegro XD, SD L.
I feel like that's been answered.
So many times.
It's because the whole point of this series is to build a game from
scratch.
I think you can get two turtles anywhere about how to load up the, you
know, unity and drop some stuff into it.
And that's not very interesting because if you ever wanted to build
anything that wasn't Unity, you can't and you also have no idea what
Unity is doing.
So when you have problems, you don't necessarily know how to fix them,
right?
And all sorts of stuff like this and you also don't have
Much of a handle on what things you do in.
Unity might do in terms of infecting, affecting your performance, all
that sort of stuff.
And so really the whole point of this dream is to show you all the
things you don't see everywhere else.
It's to do the opposite of what everyone else does, which is just grab
as much off-the-shelf stuff as they can and just kind of Cobble it
together to make a game.
This is the opposite of that.
This is to make every last thing ourselves.
So we learn how everything works and then you can decide what to use
and what not to use out of other people's stuff.
And when you do use them a, you'll be able to fix bugs in them if you
want, which is pretty awesome or
Improve their performance, which is also awesome, or you can just not
use some of them at all.
If you decide that something is crappy and you could do a better job,
you can do it.
And that's pretty important because I don't think we're at the point
yet these days where game development tools are perfect.
Are you speaking of with Floats?
Or we be changing over to fix Point floats.
Fixed point is a bad idea.
These days, Hardware likes floating point and we'll also do things
with floating Point.
Fixed Point ends up costing, you a lot of operations.
You can do things twice as wide, if you do them in in fixed.
Potentially, if you really worked it out, but I don't even think you
can.
I think you still need 32-bit because the shift it.
Yeah, so I think you can't even do twice as wide.
So I think you're basically always at a loser.
You're going to lose performance by going to fixed point.
So we're definitely not going to be fixed blank.
It's a real bad idea on Modern Hardware, I think.
Wouldn't one expect for pixels per frame at 30fps to look a little
jerky.
Not really not really and it looks it does look pretty smooth.
Now that we fixed the bug, right?
Yeah, it looks pretty smooth.
You can see a little beat frequency, which I think is because we're
not on the again.
You can, well, and you can also see the rounding, so you can see that
when it rounds over.
So when we get sub pixel Precision in for our drawing, that'll fix
that as well.
So that'll be a good thing.
But yeah.
Have you heard anything about hacks?
What's your opinion on it?
I don't have an opinion on it.
I know Daniel Ben, macdui uses it to make Ernesto, which is a game
that I like a lot.
So obviously, you can make a game in it that I like to tell you that,
that's all I know about it.
Shouldn't hero move, one pixel per frame to stop jerkiness.
No, okay, so I think we covered that.
Let's see.
Yesterday, you discussed explorative programming.
How do you compare that with the Agile development process?
That's prevalent in software development.
Are there major differences between the two?
So agile software development is.
Yes, I guess what I would say about that is I don't know what people
always mean when they say that because I feel like there's different
schools of thought on agile like
I mean, I don't know.
I guess I would have to go read.
What the latest definition of agile.
Programming is or what you think it means.
When you say that before, I can really give a complete answer.
But I guess what I would say is the problem or the reason why I think
it's important to say things, the way I said them versus Agile
development is a Giles development.
Is more about not trying to weigh yourself down with other things
you're doing.
As a productivity measure, right?
I think that's typically how they frame it.
But I've never seen them.
Talk about what I talked about, which is why you care about not doing
software planning.
Because a lot of people think, you know, talking about agile software
development.
They just talk about the not doing something, but they don't talk
about the why you don't do it in a way that I find compelling.
And so, the reason that I talked about it, the way I did is because
hopefully like drawing that map that I drew of like the projects.
Space and the state that it's in.
I feel like that crystallizes a lot clearer for people.
Why you care about not doing a lot of upfront design.
It's it's not because you know, it's more fun or these other sorts of
things which you might say about Agile development or because you
know, it allows you to respond to things more quickly or that sort of
stuff.
It's more because there is no way to set the way points correctly for
your map.
If you could then software planning would actually be very useful,
right?
And it's the fact that you can't set the waypoints, is why it's not.
So I don't know.
So so I don't necessarily know if I disagree with thing.
Things in Agile development or not.
Because I haven't read much about the latest discussion.
I had last time I read about agile software development was probably
like 2001 or something like this.
It was probably quite some time.
Might even actually might have been longer than that, but
I read about adalind about it when it first came out.
We put you that way which is a long, long time ago.
And so, so I'm not really prepared to talk about the composite
comparison to much.
They're all I would say is I agree with it to the extent, with which
lines up with what I said yesterday.
And if it doesn't line up with that than I don't,
What's procrastination a problem for you?
Yes, it is.
Absolutely a problem for me.
I think it's a problem for everyone.
When you hit a hard problem.
The tendency is to try to go do something else.
It's easier.
Right?
And so procrastination is a problem.
And I talked about this a little bit.
I think the key to solving procrastination is to force yourself to do,
a little bit of programming on the problem every day because you may
get to a point where you literally can't do eight hours of programming
on the problem and you can try to force yourself to do it, but you
won't, right.
And so the key is to never let it drop to zero.
The key is you got to get through those points by forcing yourself to
do an hour or two hours a day.
Do whatever you have to do to force yourself to do, two hours of
programming on a hard problem every day.
Even if the programming is useless and sucks just type in 2 hours of
code a day and that will get you through a lot of those
procrastination points because they do happen.
And the key is to not stop.
If you stop programming, you will you could procrastinate forever, but
if you
Two hours a day.
Eventually, you will randomly hit on the thing that gets you to move
forwards.
Do you think C++ is easier than C sharp because I took C sharp?
This semester.
It was a pain in the butt.
That's more of a pre stream.
Question.
So come at the beginning of the stream, and I answer questions like
that.
Try to keep the questions too about what we're doing for now.
Could all the print outputs have impact on the frame rate, and be the
cause of the ruffed input.
No, not really, although, I should get rid of those.
This machine has plenty of CPUs in it.
It's definitely not a plenty.
Of course.
It's definitely not going to be a problem to have Windows print out.
There's a little bit of a sync Point thing that happens there, but no,
it's not, it's not and we've solved the jerkiness so we know what it
was.
It was the fact that we didn't set the
In the right place.
Use some space on the top or bottom of the screen for statistics.
And you, I, well, we'll talk about a little bit.
That's a design concern, but we can talk about that a little later,
the desktop Visa issue will only be a problem on Windows Vista plus,
which means we can use the command to get it from the dwm there, and
use the direct draw one on Windows XP.
The vsync timing.
Does there a dwm?
Vsync timing though, or just refresh rate?
Can we pack the colors in a struct?
Yes, I think I talked about that in, on the Stream.
Is there a reason for choosing the tiles to be square except for ease
of use?
There's no in particular, the particular reason in terms of code, we
could make the tiles any size we want but I feel like making them
Square.
Makes it easy for the player to reason about them because they know
roughly that, like if they are moving up, they will cross the same
amount of tiles as if they're moving left in a certain amount of time.
So I feel like that's a little easier for them.
I don't know.
That could be just me but I feel like design-wise.
It's probably a good idea to
Sigma square tiles, but I don't know.
Just just something to think about.
Do you have anything to your almond milk?
Other than soaked, almonds and water know?
From yesterday's dream.
How can you tell the difference between needing to correct?
The direction?
You're taking your design, an actual fundamentally hard problem is it
usually just obvious at the time?
No, you should.
It has nothing to do with obviousness.
It's actually they're two different things.
So what you have to understand
Is you should always problems in programming are.
Never really about design or architecture of the code.
Basically solving a problem in programming is about whether the code
works, right?
So, you know, whether you've solved the hard problem as to whether the
code works and executes in the amount of time that it needs to execute
in that is solving the problem.
So you need to do that first and then has nothing to do with your
design walk.
That is just, did you write a piece of code that works at all.
Once you have the piece of code that works and meets the
specifications that you have for it.
Right?
So it's like I want to do this renderer.
It needs to run in this amount of time.
So I'm like, getting some code that can actually do the blind, or do
the whatever, draw the rectangle, whatever, in the amount of
milliseconds that I said it had to do.
So you do that first and that is the part that is up these the hard or
easy problem.
It may be really hard to do that and you got to spend
Three months doing, all kinds of crazy, assembly optimizations to
figure out how to get that to work.
But you do that and that has nothing to do with the design that is
strictly about getting a isolated piece of code, where you can do
anything you want, anything at all, and getting it to work.
Then, there's the problem of.
How do you integrate that into the design of the code?
And that is just a fundamentally?
Yes.
I think it's like, here are the constraints on this piece.
It has to do these things.
So how do we make it do those things within the context of our
program?
We make the changes necessary to do that and we move forwards, right?
So what you're doing that at that point is you're always sort of just
doing a check on how clean is this at this point when I integrate it
in?
If my answer is things are getting very hairy now and I can't manage
them.
Then you know, that you shouldn't move forward yet.
You know, that you kind of have to go through rework, some things,
pull some things out.
Out but that's not about solving a problem.
That's just about structuring the code, you know, look at it.
What are the reasons why it's getting hard for you to manage.
What are the reasons why it's Harry decide how to fix those and move
forwards.
So, separate the two, you got to separate the two there really aren't
hard code structure problems.
They usually just emerge about themselves.
But sometimes guess the one caveat I would say that sometimes you hit
the limitations of the language and that's usually when I go to
metaprogramming,
But, you know, if you hit the limitation of the language, you may be
stuck in a place where you're just like, okay, we got except some
Badness.
So things are not going to be ideal and that's just the way it goes or
you like like I say you go you go metaprogramming and you solve it
that way.
Would it be so bad at the tiles were rectangular if you Ortho
projector Square from three-quarter, overhead view, get a rectangle.
Anyway, it's not that it's bad.
It's that it's harder for the player to reason about this is like a
big thing that people don't I think appreciate.
But, you know, in the old days, anyone could pick up a Nez controller
and play in as game Nintendo Entertainment System, right?
And part of the reason is because it was 2D things move the consistent
rate on the screen and most people can into it.
Three, two, dimensional motion, like that very easily.
Started moving to like 3D games and a lot of this other stuff you
fundamentally lose a bunch of players in my opinion, who just they
don't have that 3D intuition.
They don't know how to project distances in a rectangular fashion like
the way you're talking about and so modern Gamers who play a lot of
games nowadays can do it.
Trivially, they totally get perspective, projection or orthographic
projection of vectors and they know how to Ballpark those figures, but
it just makes it a lot harder and like even a modern game that I like
a lot.
Not because I mentioned Binding of Isaac earlier, even a modern game
that like a lot can really make it hard for the player like Binding of
Isaac.
It's impossible to tell whether your shots are going to hit something
or not.
Like it takes a long time to learn that because it's this weird
pseudo-3d height based thing.
And like, in the old days, if a bullet hit your Sprite and they
collided, then your they collided, right?
And that's really easy for people to understand.
And so a lot of the things that I'm doing with the design of this game
is trying to make it easy for people to understand the rules, and
And how the game works in that way, right?
So they can just see if a thing hits.
My guy, then it hit the guy.
And it's not about whether that was accurate in 3D, or whatever.
It's just easy for people to see and understand.
So, I want to avoid rectangles, because that forces the player.
To do this kind of projection understanding in their head of how that
works.
What do bugger do?
Use on Linux?
I hate Linux developers.
They are awful.
I've never found one.
That's any good.
I would say best of luck to you.
I'm really hoping someone someday makes a good Linux to bugger.
We don't have one yet and that's too bad.
But I've never found it about her on the next that was that was even
remotely usable and I wish I had a Linux VM on this machine right now.
I would boot it up for you and show you just why.
Think they're so bad because people sometimes were like, oh, it's
fine, use blah blah, use code blocks or use QT, Creator, whatever it.
No, they're all awful.
They just don't work at all and a lot of times, you got to go back to
command line GDB to even get stuff.
It's awful.
It's real, real awful.
Yeah, that makes two buggers are absolutely terrible.
And so that's actually what makes developing on, Linux bad right now.
I actually like, developing on Linux right up to that point
everything.
This is okay for me.
Now.
I can use emacs and it works the same.
Obviously, as I'm windows and all that stuff and just, yeah, it's real
bad, real bad.
I really want to get salt because I prefer, I would prefer to use
Linux most of the time.
And and really, that's the thing that really makes it hard for me.
Let's see.
Why do we see nine threads exiting at the end of the program in debug
output.
Where are they coming from?
So unfortunately, you will see this sort of thing a lot.
So he's the, the question.
The person was asked, the question is asking about this stuff.
So, actually, what you'll notice, you can actually see these little
more explicitly.
If you'd like, if we set a breakpoint in our program, you can actually
click on this threads window thing here and see them.
All right, and if you look, if you don't have that window, it's in
debug.
Windows, where is it?
Threads?
It's down here.
This is the thing that you want it want to pick and what you can see
is you can actually see by looking at where those threads are and who
created them.
You can see what's going on a little bit more clearer.
So you've got basically Windows creating all of these threads.
Some of them are system threads in ntdll.
So we can't really tell who is behind them.
Other ones.
We can sell very clearly.
These are direct sound threads.
There's three of them.
Because how could you possibly make sound output with less than three
at three threads?
So they're there and then, mmm.
Dev AP.
I'm not sure what that is.
I don't know if that's the multimedia service or they're not sure what
that is Colonel bi.
Yeah.
I don't know.
I'm not sure if you go here, you can see the stack a little more
explicitly, but usually, it doesn't tell you anything again, they're
all like kind of nameless places.
It may be that if you install there, you can install Mt.
Symbols.
There's a, there's a thing you can install that's like
If I can find it.
Windows, debug symbols.
so,
Okay, so this thing, right?
If you, if you follow the instructions on here, or if you install
Windows symbol server, these sorts of things, you can actually get
symbols for some of this, some stuff, sometimes where it will tell you
what functions these threads are in.
I don't know if that makes sense, but it would basically tell you what
the function names were here.
And so, if you're really curious about what each side is doing, if saw
that symbol server and take a look at this window and you may get a
little more insight into it.
So hope that helps
Those are the threads that are exiting.
How many more hours required to get the win32 layer to shippable
Quality?
Oh.
Well, so I guess what I would say is, if I was programming on my own,
I would say it would probably take.
Two weeks of time, maybe.
If I was really programming seriously for two weeks straight, so I
suspect it's going to take up a huge chunk.
It'll probably take up 50 days on the stream to do a ship of a win32
layer.
Now.
That's that's my idea of a ship of a winter to Quality a shippable
win32 layer.
Other people certainly ship things that are not perhaps as complete as
what I would imagine.
Should it should be
So you could argue that it, we could do it shorter, but when we
actually go to do that ship of a layer, it's a pretty big undertaking.
That's why I didn't do it.
That's why I didn't do it now is because I felt like we would be
sitting here for 100 days, you know, doing nothing but win32 and I
didn't think that was productive.
So I just did the minimum necessary to kind of get something up and
running.
So not the absolute minimum, but you know,
Not much more than that.
Are we locked into a tile size?
Once we get going, or can we make that Dynamic per level or per room
later in the project?
We, we certainly could make it Dynamic.
I don't think I will make it dynamic because I want it to be
consistent for the player.
Like I want the player to always see the same tile size everywhere.
So I probably won't make a dynamic but it's not a big deal to write
the code to be dynamic.
And we probably will sort of write the code to be a little bit dynamic
in the sense that we will.
Be able to change the pixel size of the tiles at any time when we
actually get there to that point without.
So without having really had to change any code and so we will be
doing a little bit of that but I don't think I'm going to actually
ever make the tiles change depending on where you are.
I don't think I'll probably do that.
Do you have timing info?
.Q p CV.
Blank is the qpc value before.
The
blank, okay, so that's
That would be what we need, if that makes sense.
But again, I'm not sure that we really need to do that.
I don't know.
It seems like kind of a waste of time to go chasing vertical, retrace
sink on our prototype player.
But you know, if you guys want to do it you could always do it to in
your copy of the platform layer.
If you'd like.
Let's see.
Why do you not clean up your code?
It will be harder to find bugs.
If you do not, which code are you talking about that?
You would like to see cleaned up?
Let's see.
What do you think if you sell a t-shirt from handmade hero and write
on them?
I learned how to make a game from scratch.
I will buy it, good to know.
I don't know, go post on the forums.
If you want a nice to do t-shirts, we could think about it.
I don't know.
I haven't given any thought to it yet.
Sorry.
With your compression based approach.
Do you find yourself writing facades for everything?
So that both you and others are working with?
Can access your individual modules, regardless of how you've
implemented it.
So I don't know what you mean by facades.
Typically, what I will do is I do expose interfaces that are
relatively clean.
If I'm exporting it to someone else.
I will, I will typically expose interfaces that I think are clean and
insulate me from having to worry about them doing anything too
specific with with my code, that I know that I might want to change.
If that's the question you're asking but facade is kind of a loaded
word because that's not very specific.
So, yeah.
What's wrong with GDB basic?
What's wrong?
Sweetie be, is it does not display data in a convenient way.
It does not provide you a quick visual good.
Visualization of your source, code your source, code your assembly,
your registers, your watch, your debug output.
Visual Studio does a very good job of that relative to other de
buggers and GDB does not.
It's really bad at that.
Why not use clang?
I do use.
Clang on Linux.
I always use clang.
Let's see.
I'm a young adult who would like to get into coding but everywhere I
go lands up with the same stuff which leads to be boring and not
interactive.
How does one learn code?
That is a good question for the priest.
Ream come come to a stream early sometime.
Usually like 15 minutes before the handmade here.
Broadcast starts.
Come there.
And ask we talk about that sort of stuff in the free stream of time.
Since how you arrange the elements in your struck can influence a
size.
Is there a rule to follow on?
How to organize your structure?
Yes.
I think we talked about this.
Basically, it's about padding.
You might want to post on the forums about that, actually, because
the, I've talked about this extensively on previous episodes and maybe
they could link you to where it was.
Let's see.
A Melcher says you just have to right-click the stack frame in the
call stack View and download from Ms.
Symbol servers.
Really.
Is it just do that automatically?
Where are you guys talking about this?
Or
Let's try it.
Load symbols.
Did that work?
Whoa, holy cow.
That's a lot easier than it used to be.
Wow.
Can I do that here, too?
Oh man, that is a lot easier than it used to be guys.
That is pretty cool.
Alright, so if that's true that we could do that for everything.
That's pretty handy.
So let's say we take one of these threads that we don't know what it
is.
We could go to, I think we can just double click on it or something to
switch to it.
Right?
How do I switch to it?
Switch to thread?
So, if I right, click on it hits, which to thread, right now, I should
be looking at this threads.
Yeah.
There we go.
Look at that.
Empty weight for work via worker Factory.
Oh, God, maybe I didn't want to see this.
Look at all this.
All right.
Well,
Now you can see what they actually are.
You can see D sound waiting in here.
Let's see wait for multiple objects.
These guys are just all waiting on, handles base.
They're waiting for a trigger.
Something to trigger them.
ZW Trace control.
Oh, it's event.
Tracing for Windows.
Oh God eventually.
See for Windows is
I hate event Tracy for Windows.
That's who that is TPP.
Waiter pthread.
I don't know what TPP is.
That's probably thread pool.
Maybe so we can't really tell if these guys are doing because they're
really just sitting around waiting to do work.
And so we don't actually know what it is that they're doing it.
What they would be doing when the work comes.
So they could be doing any sort of any number of things, essentially.
Yeah, so not very lightning there, but that's a pretty cool trick,
right?
Clicking on this call stack and doing
That that load symbols thing was pretty cool.
It's gone now because it's already been loaded but right-clicking on
the call stack on somewhere that you don't know like ntdll, hang load
symbols.
It totally worked.
That's great.
Thanks for the tip.
Is there any thought to using gi+ to help from a bridge between GDI
and DX?
Not really because we're just prototyping so we don't care about this
at all.
We're gonna switch to opengl and direct3d for the typical version.
I think the were where the end of the stream here.
So I'm just going to double click through the questions real quickly.
See if there's anything else that I need to do.
That should be addressed.
Let's see.
What if we don't use rooms at all?
Just have levels that scroll.
So I don't want to do scrolling because I want the rooms to be able to
do the self-contained sort of puzzle /, encounter thing where, like,
you walk in and the, like, again, like the original ends Legend of
Zelda did, where you lock the doors and the player has to deal with
what's in there first before they can move on.
So, I don't really want scrolling.
I want the player to think about the screens as
All screens that are self-contained for the most part.
I want that feel of the game.
So I don't really want to have to do scrolling.
I want to be able to have it look nice when it's just one screen and
not rely on scrolling for that.
Let's see, okay.
Someone says in assert assumptions and draw a rectangle.
Well, we could I don't know if I really want to do that though.
So basically what the person is suggesting is this.
They're want to do something along the lines of make sure that each of
the color values is where we think it should be right, because we said
that these have to be in that range, right?
The reason I'm not super concerned about that.
I mean.
Oops, that's supposed to be the reason.
I don't love that idea.
Is because in practice, I don't think we're actually going to care.
I think we'll be able to the way that we do.
It will probably do something that does saturation, so that you can
actually pass 1.5 and it'll be fine.
And we also may decide to do something with high dynamic range where
we actually need to.
Allow twos and threes and fours or something.
Who knows.
So I don't want to do that, but I wouldn't say if you were certain
that you always wanted exactly this in the future and you never want
to deal with clarabelle's any other way than those assertions are
probably.
Ok, but for right now, I don't know that, I want to go that route.
If anything, what I would probably do is clamp them.
Like I actually go ahead and clamp the RGB values, but I don't think
that's necessary there at the moment.
So, all right, I think.
Oh, why do you hate event Trace?
I will answer that one question, just because I really hate event
trace, and I'll show you why go to my rocket.com Casey.
That is me.
post 29, the worst API ever made this blog post should answer your
question as to why I hate event tracing for windows with a
Passion.
So yeah, please check that out.
If you want to know why I hate event tracing.
All right.
Everyone.
Thank you very much for joining me.
I hate to say it.
But we've got a tile map and a player on the screen who can stop us
now.
Write this is going to get fun real real soon here.
I'm kind of happy with the way.
This is going.
We're going to we're going to start to have an actual game happening
here.
We have so much stuff to talk about.
We've got the renderer to do.
We've got a we got soon.
Talk about
Coordinate systems because we don't want to be in pixels going
forwards and stuff.
You gotta you gotta you got tons of stuff to do.
We got tons of stuff to explain and investigate in detail.
So I don't want to say that we're going to be in like, oh the game is
totally up and running any time soon or anything like that, but I'm
just saying it's kind of fun to have like a little thing moving around
on tile map and pretty soon.
We're going to have something that's actually kind of playable.
Right?
Like we're going to have a little rectangle running around going
between tile maps and fighting a little rectangle Lobster.
And I don't know if you're like me, you kind of get excited about
these sorts of things.
And I think one of the things that says that you're going to be a
programmer in your life is when you get excited about the simple
things, right?
Because anyone gets excited about a bunch of really cool Sprites
flying around on the screen and doing stuff, that's not hard to get
excited about.
But when you're excited about the little things, it says something
about.
Probably where your inclinations lie.
So thank you so much for joining me.
If you would like to have a copy of the source code to work on
yourself at home.
You can pre-order the game here on handmade hero, dot-org.
Just took on the pre-order button.
You will get an email with a link that allows you to download the
source.
Code every day after I finish it.
I uploaded and you will be right in the same place that I am and if
you just want to kind of play around with things, that's a good way to
do it.
If you just want to kind of drop it and play with things a little bit
yourself.
If you would like to support the series, we do have a patreon.
You can subscribe to just go ahead and click on that patreon.
And also we have a great forums community that people have been really
doing, just some amazing work on and it's just a great site.
So if you click on here and go news and forums, the main page has the
schedule that I post every
Day, so you can see when all the times are going to be.
There's an episode guide that some volunteers do that's just awesome.
You can go on here and look at past episodes and they're all kind of
linked with with like kind of time values and everything.
It's just fantastic, the work they've been doing on, that's just
great.
And then there's a coding resources page, which has ports.
It's got ports to Mac OS, X, that ports, to Linux other things about
little Windows as well.
Someone even is working on a port to Swift if you're interested in
that.
It's crazy.
How much porting is going on?
It's great.
And then there's also other
Ariel's on there for like editors and stuff.
And then the code discussion forums are on here.
There's a bunch of stuff where people talk about things where they're
having trouble working on stuff, all sorts of things.
So again, check all that out.
It's a great site and the people on it have been really great.
So I highly encourage it.
Alright, we will be back here again, 10 a.m.
Every day.
So 10 a.m.
Tomorrow as well.
I will be back here and we will get our guy may be colliding with the
tile map and maybe walking to Newtown maps.
I don't know what we'll do.
We'll do whatever comes to mind again to try and get ourselves in a
position where we have
Little zygote game running.
So we can start to sort of think about what we want the architecture
to be and we can start building it up into some proper pieces.
What we're trying to get to really is having the renderer set up the
way we want so that we can sort of say what the renderer needs to do.
So we're kind of keep pushing towards that and I hope you will join me
for that because it's gonna be a lot of fun.
So, thank you for joining me and and Merry Christmas Eve.
For those of you who celebrate Christmas.
All right.
Thanks everyone, and I will see you tomorrow.