Hello everyone and welcome to handmade hero.
The show we could complete game live on stream.
It is profiler time.
We actually have our profiler working in kind of meat right now but
it's still not super usable day-to-day at the moment because there's
like to at least two things that I think we still want to be able to
do to make it easy for us to work on it and that is first of all we
want to have a
Like pausing things so that we can like stop what's going on and be
able to use the profiler without it like jittering because like it's
updating every frame.
And the other thing that we want to be able to do too, I think is get
a couple other views in there.
Like right now we don't have a way of just saying what's the total
time for any given frame spent in a particular routine, right?
We don't do any summation stuff.
So we do sort of the, the thread utilization view very well, but we
don't do like, just What's the total time?
Been in various routines that we don't actually draw out the moment.
So be kind of need to just do a little bit more of that stuff and then
I think we're pretty good shape on the profiling front.
So let's take a look at what that is today is day 261.
So day 260 source is what you want to start with if you're trying to
follow along at home here is my project file.
There it is.
So here's the project file and here is
is the currently running state of the profiler.
The other thing is let's make it to I'm sick of it coming up tiny
because right now we initialize like the width is just going to be
last 20 all the time which is stupid because we would never want that
to actually be the case.
So I feel like we should do a thing where
inside the, the initial sort of look at a particular, debug view, I
think we should have a
Way of, where is it a way of initializing it to something else?
So, here's the thread interval graph.
When we get one of these Dimension, things back, I'm just going to do
a thing.
That's like,
You know if you profile graph you know what I kind of want to pull
that out into its own thing actually I think I want to do something
where I can like grab one of these guys out of there so I don't have
to keep typing the whole thing.
So I can say here's the graph.
It's that and then I can just do that.
So then I can
If we haven't have has area kind of a thing.
Well I could also say if graft block dot dim x equals 0,
Oops and graph block dot.
Dim y equals zero.
Then I'm just going to assume that this is the first time that we've
got it and and I'll make it, you know bigger.
So I don't know what I'll make it be.
Lets say that should probably be all the way across the screen for the
most part, I would think
I don't know.
And as far as how big it should be, maybe something like that because
it probably want it to be relatively large.
That'd be my guess.
Anyway.
What are you complaining about?
That's supposed to be an address then you can have an address you
know, calm yourself.
All right.
So now I'm hoping that when we run this, if I expand the profile I'll
get like a yeah, a default size of the profile that that's actually
more usable.
Right?
And so one of these profiles I feel like I maybe want in the profile
window like we I don't really think we've done much in the way of
having some any real buttons or anything.
I feel like we kind of want some buttons in here as well, like some
things to change the view style or something like that.
That sort of thing.
We want to get some of that in there too.
But at least now when we open it it's like a reasonable size which is
obviously better.
So in our drill down is working as well as we can drill down into
something like I said, but we can't go back.
So a back button would be nice there.
So just a couple things like that, that I think we want to be able to,
to do would be would be good.
Yeah, great.
Okay.
So that's all fine.
Let's take a look at
I would need to do.
You know what I, you know what?
I feel like would be kind of nice.
Just, you know, I'm just, I'm just throwing this out there.
You know, it would be kind of nice is if there was a way to view like
per frame stuff in slyke's like Stacks per frame as well, like a
You know, something that was just designed to show us a more.
I want some way of seeing bars over time.
Just just just hear me out on this.
Just just let me let me, let me sort of throw this out there.
This may be really stupid and I apologize if it is but I'm just going
to try.
I just want to try something here as as a different view type as well.
So in draw profile in
So here's drop profile bars right in this thing is the thing that goes
through and does the you know the bar horizontal bar kind of
interested to see like what if we did a slightly different thing that
was like like draw frame bars or something.
And this one was designed to kind of go through like a bunch of like
all the Frame data that we have maybe and it draws like the bars over
time.
I don't know, something like this.
So we could do something where we go.
yeah, like
Basically the same thing here.
Going to start with this, then I'm going to change it up a little bit.
So we come through here and we Loop through the historic events
instead of
of just doing one frame and I guess the problem is when this passes
the node, that's not really what I want either because I want to do
one for each of these
Try to think of how I want to do this.
So what I'm trying to say is here when we call draw a profile in,
we're passing like a particular event.
And that event is we have many frames worth of data for that event,
right?
Meaning we could have instead of picking frame the most recent frame,
we could have picked any like many many frames backwards in time and
so I'm interested to see a version that doesn't work that way.
Like what if I'm just trying to think of like what if we did something
that was more like draw
You know, we'll do draw frame bars here and what this does is when we
called refrain bars we pass it like a debug start event or something
that's like first event maybe and and maybe like, how many events we
want to draw, I don't know.
And then when we go through it, we Loop through each the stored events
profile node.
We Loop through like multiple frames of that and draw them all.
Right.
So something like
Let's see.
Something like we wouldn't have a lame count at the moment.
so, we would just do like
Drop profile bars.
We just do this.
and,
So, for each of these, we would go through all of the children, just
once we would not do it.
Cursive Lee.
So like I wouldn't do
This call.
But I would also right here to the route event,
I would, I would keep chasing the next pointer of the route event to
go from frame to frame.
You know, and I'd probably do something cure like ask how many frames
to draw, you know?
So,
Let's see, and maybe we default to saying, you know, oh, we're going
to draw like a hundred, twenty eight frames or something like that, I
don't know.
So if we were gonna do something like that, then we'd say, okay, like
the total space that each one of these bars takes up, right?
Like the bar with should be the frame count, like whatever the the
dimension is of our profile wreck, it should be the width of that.
/ the frame count.
And obviously, if the frame count is not greater than 0, then we
wouldn't be able to draw anything because they're you know, there's
nothing to draw.
So once we knew that and then we come through here, then I would
probably do roughly the same thing in here, only instead of drawing
like instead of doing the bars, the way we did them up here.
I'd kind of do them the other way around and I probably want this
color table to be outside I suppose, so this is probably something
like Global variable color table.
Keypad color table.
So we do something that's essentially the same as this, right?
And instead of drawing things horizontally we just draw them
vertically.
So I'd still take my cue here where we'd say, okay we've got the root
node and I'm gonna get all the information about that in order to get
that I have to do this basically.
Let's see here.
Yeah, so I get the root node out of the event that we're on.
I compute this span stuff exactly.
The way that I used to only instead of using the width.
Now, I use the height and now when I draw these things, instead of
doing the max x, max, max, Min x, max X4, where the profile stuff
goes.
This would actually be why
But everything else would be essentially the same, right?
Yeah.
And then that's it.
So, all right, so that's it.
That's
I'm really saying and then when we go to create the actual region
rekt, what we would do is say, well, I know what the bar width is and
so for each of these events we would move it forwards.
So I kind of have like a start X or an at X and I would say that
whatever the profile rectangle that we were that we were in.
I would want to start at its minimum and then each time through this
Loop, I'm going to advance by one
one bar with,
Enos, I'm moving over by one, one of those bar with and then inside
here, when I drop to me,
When I draw these, what I'm going to do, is say well, okay.
I need to draw.
I need to draw the bar, starting at this Min Y, and I need to draw it
from addicts to add X plus the bar with
And then I need to stop it at this Max, why?
So now we've just sort of converted to drawing multiple frames in
stock vertical bars, right?
And I'm no longer going to allow Lanes at all.
So what I'd probably do is say that everything has to be in the same
Lane as the first event which would automatically be true if that
event actually existed, right?
So,
Is that true?
Yeah.
So essentially you have to have the first event, you have to kind of
like have that selected because otherwise you'd have multiple threads
all in there.
And I don't, I want to only do one particular thread, right?
So I'm going to do something here, like, say well for any given
profile node that I come through here, I only am interested in ones
whose Lane index is going
Be the same as the one that is sort of the parent, right?
So if the node thread ordinal equals the root nodes thread ordinal,
then I'll proceed but otherwise, I don't want that in here at all.
Now normally that would just automatically be the case but I just
putting because I'm just making sure that if you happen to pass down
that Route, 14 the frame.
It will only draw like the first thread ordinal or something like this
or none as the case may be or maybe, I don't know, maybe that's dumb.
Maybe I'll just leave it.
I'm not sure.
I'm really not sure what to do there.
Basically, the lane stuff is just not relevant because we don't have
room to draw it now and so I'm not sure I was trying to figure out
like what I should do about that.
I'm not 100% sure.
That's the problem with the Reds.
I think you probably want just stacks for each thread.
It's probably what you want would want to do in that case, which is a
little tricky.
So maybe we'll take a look at how we might do that as well.
Okay.
That is true.
Alright, so yeah.
So now, if I run this, we shouldn't see any difference.
Because we're still calling the old one and the old one should still
work fine.
Right?
And so now what I'm going to do is I'm going to try calling the draw
frame bars instead.
So yeah, so instead of this I'm going to try here.
Oops.
Okay.
All right, and the problem that will have is that first we're not set
to anything in particular, so this will actually give us a root node,
that's actually the frames root node and that's a little bit of a
problem, right?
Because that does have multiple threads inside it, but like I said,
we're still drawing those so I guess it's.
The problem is just that they'll draw on top of each other, you know
what I mean?
And that's not great.
Apparently, we drew so many things.
Somehow.
I must be drawing too much stuff.
What did I do here?
Sort of event is first child next to same parent.
So we're going through each of these
We're drawn.
Each of its children.
Is that really too much?
Of course I should.
Also do I need to make the frame index.
The actually Captor.
Index count.
And root 2, then X Y.
So that I can put that in the same place.
So we want to make sure the route event actually exists.
We would like to be able to
Keep the frame index as well.
And make sure that it's whatever it is.
Now I'm going to for easy to bugging, I'll just make it so that right
now, let's say it.
Draws one.
So now we should have absolutely no problem with that.
And hey look, it is an actual stack.
So that's good.
I'm now going to go ahead and change that up to 10 to see what
happens.
And so
Yeah, that's that's not.
Correct.
So I messed up something because what we should be seeing we shouldn't
be seeing depth.
We should be seeing multiple copies of what look essentially like
this.
And you know what?
I guess the other problem is we're not passing at the right kind of
event.
Either we need to be passing it like the first one of something.
Right.
So really in here, draw frame bars, we want to be passing it, instead
of the root node, we actually want to be passing it, you know, this
where we do this search here, we actually don't want to pass that.
We just want to pass it.
The oldest event like we want to pass it way back when you know, the
something it can Loop through and draw more frames of
Hmm.
So I guess I'd have to do this essentially something like that kind of
hack this together.
I need to pass it something.
Like here's the oldest frame.
And I'm just going to grab out of that the root profile note.
And that's but that's not chained together.
So frustrating.
It's like almost right but we don't we just don't quite have it
correct?
Like the frames themselves should have been if we had made the frames
themselves events.
Then you could just use them directly and it would have worked which
seems like better than what I ended up with like these nodes are
synthetic and not chained together.
So now they can't be used in that way.
And that's super lame.
Right.
Let's see here.
So I think we want to kind of push on that a little bit just to clean
that up.
So yeah.
So here we are in
In this part of the code where we get the viewing element stuff.
So if instead of doing this search, I just left it be.
So you know I could do this essentially say we get the viewing element
and once we get the viewing element then we set the root node equal to
the viewing element.
Oldest event.
Now, what should happen is in, you know, normally, when we look at it,
we just look like this.
If we then go to take a particular one of these, right?
I don't know which one may be like, debug collation, then yeah.
And, and then you can see it looks correct.
Well, correct is a strong word here, but it'll draw, you know, us a
series of these over time where we can see on each subsequent frame,
how much time each of them took, right?
And so we can kind of see like frame-to-frame.
And once this space remaining gets down to zero they would scroll
across to.
I can also go in here and say, oh hey, you know, let's let's look at a
few more of these.
So let's say I want like 128 of These Bars.
And then you can kind of see like, again, a more sort of granular view
of like, what's happening over time.
So I'd like, again, I'd like to kind of support that.
I feel like we just need.
I feel like we're just a little bit off from how this should work and
I feel like maybe part of that is just the whole.
Like I do think we may want to do instead of chaining those those
things together and freeing them dynamically like we were I think
We want to do something more.
Like we just allocate a block of, you know, however, many frames of
Back Store, we're going to keep which is like, you know, 128 frames or
something like this.
Or 256 frames and we just keep that many stored events and that way we
can always just like know that we didn't, we don't have to deal with
the chaining right in that way.
And that would just be for a debug element, you know, / debug element.
Yeah.
In fact, really now that I think about it, it's just kind of an index
anyway, because you still can have multiple events on a single frame
for a given.
One of these right, there could be like lots of instances where it
occurred on that frame.
So really you just need a central table at the top.
That's like, for this debug element here is like the 128 times that,
you know, 128 frames or something like that.
And the pointer into the first event that happened on that frame for
this element.
Right that way, you could always Creek quickly scrub around on them
and always know.
I'm trying to draw a particular frame.
Give me the set for that frame, you know what I mean?
And that seems that seems maybe like what the right thing should be.
You still want the chaining like the chaining still makes sense.
It's just, you want the frame index to be there as well.
Yeah.
I think that's true.
And the other thing that I'm wondering to is when we pass down a
stored event here, I'm wondering.
About that a little bit too.
So let's let's take a look at this.
So we're drawing the frame bars.
Here's a iterating over the frame indices, right?
And the what we would probably want to do here is is make it so that
as we
I guess as we go, maybe they would would just kind of sweep around.
So you know however, many frames that we stored, we would go on that,
whatever that element was and we just go through all of the frames
that it held.
I kind of want to play with this.
So I think that's what I'm going to try doing here.
So, inside the debug element,
you can see that right now, it's got this sort of head and tail
pointer for like the each of the events and that's all the events that
happened ever forever in time.
You know what I'm saying?
And if we go up to like debug frames, and we look at frames
themselves, which are here frames, essentially, well, that's not
right.
I don't even know what this is.
Why is he even here?
This is going away.
Simon used anymore.
And Max reasons for frame isn't a thing.
None of that's a thing.
Yeah.
So what I was going to say was for a given frame, right?
We've got these route profile node things and I don't even know like
if we just if we just kind of look at
The way this works, the frame itself doesn't really let us get to the
information that we want.
It's really like we want to just have a frame index and then from any
we don't want have to search this tree basically to find individual
actors.
So what we want to be able to do is say, okay, we've got a frame index
and a debug element, the debug elements, the thing, we're trying to
inspect.
Let's jump right to the elements of the stored events that were for
this element on this Frame.
If that's kind.
of how we actually want it to work, you know I'm saying and so that's
that's really
The the part that I'm concerned about now, what?
I don't super remember is exactly how when we free these.
How do we Loop through?
Like, do we have a way to Loop through a hundred percent of those?
I'm not sure how.
Yeah, we just go through the entire hash and we free individual
element.
Events so that can still work.
So there's really not much that has to happen here to be honest.
Really all we need to introduce.
Is something here that would be called, you know?
Debug element frame.
And the debug element frame would just Ascent, you know, it would just
keep this stuff.
Like so and similarly this would be kind of nice for us as well,
because inside this we could keep how much time it took on this
particular frame.
Right?
So, we could kind of say for this Frame, You Know, What's the total
clocks, right?
In all these events.
So when we run over the events and do the bookkeeping, we can say, oh,
this element on this Frame took this much time.
That would give us a good way to show.
What our top taking elements were as well, which is another thing that
I think would be nice.
so then in here we would just say however, many frames have back
store, we have
we're just going to take, you know,
I think we just want this to be a straight-up array.
And then we can do the exact same thing instead of instead of having
this stuff happen next.
And, and all that, we would also, we would do the exact same thing
with the other with the, with the frame table here.
So, where we've got before where we have a thing where we're like,
okay, here's the
you know, here's the
first frame, oldest friend most recent frame.
We would just have debug frame.
You know, frames.
Like so.
And so I think it would just be.
Yeah, okay so we you know, we have these frames this is this is how
many there are we do the collation?
I don't think we would ever actually need to maintain a free list of
them because that would never actually occur.
Right?
So if you take a look at how this was being managed before, we had a
free list for our frames here, where we were doing, you know, next and
fries and stuff.
We could
Really.
Delete all that and say, you know, we always just have this many.
And however, Mitch the debug frame count is that's how many frames of
back data, we store and that's it.
I don't know, 256.
Let's say
So that's how much back data gets stored, no matter what and then off,
you know, off we go.
so, I think
I think that's really all we would need in terms of structural
changes, is just having the frames now, work in that fashion and the
only slightly tricky thing about it is now getting the frame out that
we're on.
There's the concept of like the total frame index and then there's
also like the frame ordinal which is just something that's going to
wrap around, right?
And so then instead of this Frame count, we would just have a like you
know,
Frame ordinal, which is like, you know, you know next three frame or
something like that.
And it would start out at 0.
So we'd say okay, you know, we're the next time we go to retire a
frame, we would put it in frame 0 and then we increment it and if and
when it gets to the end, it would sort of wrap around.
And so if you wanted to know, you know what the previous frame was,
you would need to look one behind next reframe.
If that makes sense.
So let's see, let me see how bad it would be for us to try to clean up
the system to work that way.
So let's see, so if we're drawing things like in here where we're
doing debug draw elements, what we would want to know, pretty much
always is we'd want to have a notion of what frame we were actually
drawing, right?
So when we come down through something like debug draw element, we
would need to know in addition, you know, when maybe we're coming
through maybe the layout itself.
Could track that piece of information for us.
Or maybe that's stored in the debug state.
So maybe the debug State kind of has that piece of information.
I'm not sure how we want to do that since debugged raw elements.
Something that's probably called as, you know, sort of utility.
I think we would want to do something here.
Like, what is the frame index that we're looking for?
Or the frame word null.
And that's the in, you know, index into that array.
So then what we would say is well, okay, whatever.
The the event is that we, whatever the thing is that we're going to
draw.
We would look
Inside the frame, array.
And we would get out the most recent event from the frame array, and
that's it.
So yeah.
What this part is doing now is well, this part is what we were working
on before, so I'm going to skip over that for just a second.
And let's go down here.
Okay, so now in this code where we're sort of going through and
drawing this, this debug tree, I'm going to say that for draw, debug
draw main menu.
I'm going to say for now, we'll just say that the frame ordinal that
we're using, is going to be the debug State, like, you know, Kurt,
whatever that current ordinal is, so whatever, the one that's next
free.
We don't want to draw that because that's the one replacing the most
recent frame, is going to be the one behind that one, right?
So what we're going to want to do is say, you know, go One backwards.
And then clip to the debug frame count, that's going to be that that
next frame and we'll clean this up a little bit in a second after I
sort of make sure everything is working okay with sort of where we're
going to get that information from because I think this will once we
do this change will also be able to introduce like maybe a little
scrub bar that can scrub back, you know, sort of a little time
scrubber that would allow us to kind of go back to two previous frames
back and and see what's going on, right?
So yeah.
So this is going to draw via the frame ordinal.
When we're interacting with things here is our interaction.
I assume we're always when we're you know what I mean?
Let's let's just do this even right now to make sure that we don't
have to keep typing it all in place.
In addition to the next free frame we'll just do most recent frame
ordinal here.
Which is basically the same thing but we'll just make sure we keep it
updated so that people can reference it when they care.
So really this is just going to be frames.
You back States?
Most recent frame word?
No.
And I guess we could also do this.
Oops.
And that.
Is that?
And it's the same thing in here, right?
So, this is also,
either State most recent frame ordinal and
And this is when we're interacting.
So again exactly the same
Don't remember what I called.
I think I called it for ordinal traction, element frames.
All right, and it's true the most recent frame, all of these will be
fixed in a second.
So let's see.
Oldest event.
So this is the free encode.
So, in the free encode we can basically keep the same other.
The free and code could be made a little bit simpler now.
But yeah, so what we would do here when we Loop over these elements,
And we're going to free an event.
We wouldn't really do it quite the way that we're doing it here
instead.
What we do is say, well, while the
We would want to go to whatever the next free frame was.
Whatever the frame is that we're freeing.
We would want to sort of
free the entire set of stuff in that element under that frames
ordinal.
So instead of doing it this way, we would pass the frame ordinal.
Here we would then say like okay if we're going to free that we don't
need to free this stuff at.
All right.
We do in fact don't even need a free list for frames anymore.
Which is nice.
I just eliminate some code for us, like, that's just gone.
And instead, all we need to do is say, alright when we free the frame,
we go through cure.
And for each element, we just eliminate all of the things that were in
there.
So, essentially, while element frames frame ordinal, oldest event is
equal to something.
Like while, there's anything in there, we're basically going to remove
that element, right?
So we're going to say this guy is the guy to
It will then move across.
I should probably figure out.
Guess debug.
Element frame.
Probably do this, right?
so, when I say element frame oldest,
And we're going to go ahead and free it and move the that pointer for
words.
And I don't think we really care about this part at all because this
whole thing is getting eliminated if that makes sense.
So none of this matters anymore.
So the only thing that we really need to do is make sure that that one
gets put on the DL allocation list.
So, that flushes out that whole thing, and that's it.
So now, when we call free oldest frame,
Which we're going to have to change the criteria for, but when we call
free oldest frame, what we would do is instead of doing this at all.
What we want to do.
Is simply take that next free frame?
Because next three frame.
In fact, really, we don't really need this function.
Free oldest frame is probably not necessary because free oldest frame
like all this stuff where it's got next part and stuff, where do we
don't have to deal with any of that anymore?
That's just done.
So really all that has to happen.
Is we just have to call free frame on the slot that we're going to put
stuff into.
And when we call new frame, whatever we call that.
That's actually
Making a new frame is really just taking the collation frame, putting
it into wherever the slot is.
That is the next frame.
We should place in our array in this array here, right?
We're just writing through that.
It's like a circular buffer frames.
So we never like allocate a new frame.
All we're doing instead is just freeing the old frame that was in that
slot and replacing it with a new one.
And so new frame is really the wrong phrase here, it just be called,
emit frame would really be it and whenever we were calling that we
would need a way of saying, I want to replace what's in a slot.
So we just kind of have to, we just have to do that.
That's, that's really it.
So I'm going to change this to be in it frame.
And that's going to not do any of this stuff anymore.
This is all gone, right?
This is all not a thing anymore.
All we really need is this
and it's going to take whatever the debug frame is that it should
initialize and this is it's going to initialize it like this.
So then I'm going to take a look at what we actually call that.
Does that
Doesn't actually need to return anything there.
And this code, I suppose I should just
Nuke for a minute.
So,
when we go to store an event, we're just going to have to assert on
this for the moment.
So, we're just going to have to say, like invalid code path here.
So, like, if we run out of memory, now, there's not a whole lot, we
could do.
I, well, you know what?
I suppose that's not true.
We could start freeing old frames.
If we run out of memory, we could free old frames faster than we,
otherwise would have had to.
So, I suppose that's fine.
So maybe I should think about that a little.
It more.
So if I did do that, right?
Then we would just say, well, okay, you know, there's there's the next
free frame and the most recent frame ordinal, I can actually Advance
these two things separately.
If that was what I wanted to do.
So when I saw your event, if there isn't room, I suppose I can just do
You know, reintroduce, this function and instead of it moving a free
list around all, it will do is just advance that that thing forward,
right?
So I'll give it a shot.
Yeah.
And in fact I guess I it's really just we don't even really need to
write that.
It's just whatever.
The next free frame was.
It's just going to free that and Advance it.
In fact, I could even just do it like this.
Because that's all it's doing.
It's just going to say alright move the free frame pointer forwards
and off you go.
And I suppose also
This needs to be wrapped, right?
Meaning, debug state.
Next three frame.
Needs to be wrapped to the debug frame count.
Yeah.
Okay.
So now what's going on?
I'm not entirely sure.
Frame index.
Equals debug State.
Collation.
Frame frame index.
That actually doesn't seem bad.
What's the problem with that?
Ah, just that
so, all of these really are going to be dots
Which is fine.
And then the element, whatever the element was is going to have to use
the
Ordinal that we're trying to store.
Right.
And so, I suppose the collation frame has to actually be a slot.
So really this ends up being you 32 collating frame ordinal.
So here is the framework, collating here is the most recent frame,
which is the one that we finish collating.
And then here is the one that's that's actually free.
Which I suppose.
I guess this is actually the oldest frame ordinal.
So, all of these would start out at zero.
And most recent frame ordinal and oldest frame.
Ordinal would actually be probably zero and then cooling framework.
Noble start out as one if that makes sense and then we would need to
move these things forward.
so anytime we went to store an event, we might have to make room
so yeah.
So I'll make this a thing Creole just frame.
Go.
There's the debug State.
And in here, it's a weed-free.
This Frame, it would go away and
That would be fine.
We want to make sure that we're never feeling freeing the collating
frame.
If that was the case, then we've catastrophically run out of memory.
We can't even, we wouldn't even have enough memory to store one frame
and that seems like just a bug, like, you don't really ever want that.
I don't think.
Doesn't, there we go.
So make sure the oldest frame is not equal to the collating frame.
Right.
Oops.
Collation Frank ordinal.
So if the collation frame ordinal, if those aren't equal, then we can
move it forwards, just fine.
And what I'd also like to do is say, well, okay, after we free that,
I'd like to check out.
If the, if the collation frame I'm sorry if the oldest frame.
Ordinal happens to be equal to the most recent frame ordinal.
I need to increment the most recent frame ordinal as well because it
just got deleted.
In either case, I have to do the oldest frame ordinal.
And then we just need them to be modded.
And what I could do is like increment frame, ordinal.
So that that's always going to happen.
so essentially there's just like,
No matter what we're doing.
It's going to be like, ordinal.
Is going to be incremented or I guess I could do equals for Dan'l plus
one.
Mod Max debug frame count.
That seems fair.
I think so.
Yeah.
So this is going to be most recent frame.
And these have to be addresses.
Collation frame.
So whatever this framing this is going to be, it's just a collation
frame ordinal.
Right?
Unless we're trying to store the absolute frame index there.
I guess technically we are
Probably.
so, this would actually be
That.
Not that anyone cares anyway.
And I suppose we could do this as well.
Just so it's easy to get.
What that is?
Let's see here.
so, this
Right here.
And there's two different ways.
I could do this, I could just leave it the same as it is now.
And I'm not sure how I want to do that, right?
Because the other thing I could do is just make it so that every time
we increment that we also
Pointer in there.
Which points to the correct one?
I'm not sure how I feel about that.
I'm going to do it this way for now, but maybe that's a bad idea.
All right.
So let's see.
So in now that we actually know which frame ordinal were on for the
coding frame, we can just do a thing where we treat this and I guess
we can just say, debug element frame.
I am equals element frames, plus whatever the current debug collation
ordinal is.
And then we would just say frame, most recent event.
Rame.
Frame frame.
Like so, yeah, what else though?
Let's see here.
So get element from event.
That's initializing this.
For a particular element.
And I feel like that's just going to have to clear out all of those
frames unfortunately, on the first time through.
So what I might do is do we have when we do a push struct, we can
clear, right?
So I think I might just appeal to that.
Here on push direct.
We can do.
I guess we cleared a 0 by default.
Right, the default Arena params article are so actually this is just
redundant that doesn't actually need to happen at all.
So inside our collation stuff, this is not super necessary at the
moment actually because that's always going to be set to something.
I didn't it time.
We'll have to set it and then it'll always have to be valid.
So this doesn't actually need to occur at all.
And that's fine.
Neither does this.
So what we would want to do here is at the frame marker.
Where do we actually move this guy forward?
Not till the very end.
Basically we move it forwards right here.
So that's fine.
All right, so
we don't need this.
And I assume we can just sort of sadiebug frame relation frame equals
get collation, frame cubic State and then all of this code can be a
little bit nicer, right?
It could just say like okay let's make sure all of these.
Are accessing off of that so they don't have to keep going through
debug state for no reason at all.
Frame bar scale.
I don't care about any of this.
This is not relevant.
We do that in the profile stuff.
Now
I don't think this is necessarily the appropriate Place For Paws,
actually, so I'm pretty sure that that is going to go away.
Let's go through here.
This stuff doesn't need to happen anymore.
This does because that's sort of how many frames total.
There's been, right?
Although there was something about like, total frame count and frame
counts and we really are only we just want Total frame count, I think.
So that's really it, that's actually much nicer.
Now that's actually much simpler and then when we do this stuff we
have to do a frame Advance, right?
So we have to now do a knit frame on the new Coalition frame.
So basically what we have to do is say collation, frame equals get
pollution frame.
And then we would need to do an in it frame on that collation frame.
And right here.
Before we did that, we'd have to move the frame.
You know, move the marker for words for the collation frame and if
that Coalition frame were to hit the oldest frame ordinal, we would
need to delete the oldest frame ordinal.
So what we need to do is say like you know increment, the frame
ordinal.
For whatever our the frame is that we're collating at the moment,
right?
We would also want to say that the debug State most recent frame is
now this one because we just finished collating it, right?
So it's done collating and it's now the most recent one and then
finally we would need to say if we now ran up against.
So if our if our
relation frame ordinal, is now equal to
Whatever the oldest frame ordinal was, we need to delete the oldest
frame.
And move that forward.
To make room because we're about to start writing into it.
That makes sense.
Now, the only problem is I kind of did that in the wrong order, in the
sense, I don't really want to increment yet.
I want to increment after so that I kind of wanted to say is I want to
do the wrapped version of this thing.
I mean you can kind of see what the problem is.
It's that are assertions going to fire, I'll show you what I mean.
This is going to fire because it's exactly what happened, right?
And
I'm tempted to just get rid of it and say the heck with it.
So that it's called I like the calling it that way a little bit better
but we'll see that might come back to bite me.
All right so here's our Co ladybug records again.
Now we have to deal with just this part here where we're not doing a
frame marker.
This is again.
Also pretty trivial.
I think we just grab it out and then wherever we were going to use
collation frame.
We can now just get rid of the debug, the part with the debug state.
In fact, I could probably just do debug State relation frame becomes
Collation frame.
Like so.
No, that just undo them all.
I hope not.
Maybe didn't I don't know what it did.
I don't care.
Anyway.
So, let's see, debug State frame count.
Oh, I did it backwards.
I did it backwards.
I did the replace backwards because I'm stupid.
That's what actually happened.
Yeah, let's try that again.
What I wanted was debug State collation.
Frame just becomes collation frame.
That's what I wanted.
I just did it backwards.
Okay.
Much better.
So, now we still have this Frame count situation.
I don't really know what this Frame index is supposed to do.
Really honest with you.
But I think it should just be total frame count.
And let's see what else we got.
This is all nonsense and we don't care about any of it.
So what we actually want to do now is we want to initialize this
stuff, the way that I said that we wanted to.
So we've got these ordinals and they should be set up properly.
So what we want to do is say that the most recent frame is zero--.
The collation frame is actually going to be frame 1 and the oldest
frame ordinal is going to be frame 0.
I think that's what I want.
This is now irrelevant.
The if statement doesn't have to happen anymore because we always have
a frame, we can look at.
So what I could do is say, well, there is a debug frame.
That's the most recent frame, if that's what you want.
That frame is just going to be the debug State frames array, plus the
debug State, most recent frame ordinal,
And you can go ahead and print that to your heart's content.
I don't know why the indentation in for a coder gets so confused.
Sometimes.
It doesn't seem to know about like how to close the parentheses or
something.
It's I need to get back to Allen on a couple things.
It's my fault actually that I have not been backed up on communicates.
I owe him some email so but that's it.
I mean that's all this has to do so we can just get rid of this,
right?
Yeah, now I feel like there's some things, we are probably still
forgetting, so I doubt this is going to work, but at least we got most
of it done and that's fine.
Of course, famous last words, it actually did sort of work this we
obviously, if Stir It Out,
Is this all working?
Got to be kidding me.
Okay.
well, I guess that worked somehow, let's see what happens when we Peg
the
frame.
Size stuff.
Let's see if we crash and burn.
Yeah, that's going to say.
I would be surprised.
We didn't Crash and Burn.
So, where did we crash and burn at?
Exactly.
Of course, that might just be.
That might just be some stupidity with this, which is probably true.
So we've gone through a bunch of frames.
The most recent frame is 252.
The collation frame is 137.
The oldest frame is also 252.
That doesn't make any sense at all.
Nope.
Does not make any sense.
And then they just both keep incrementing up, huh?
Yeah, so that's complete nonsense.
Just in case anyone was wondering.
I'm gonna go ahead and set a breakpoint there.
And I want to see what this is set to now.
So we let it run, we've gotten a frame 255, which is what we would
expect.
We're collating on frame 0 and that was the oldest frame.
So now we have to advance it.
So I just want to see what happens.
We go into free frame, free frames going to come through here and find
any elements that are on frame 0, which is what I would want it to do
here.
It's got some.
Let's see there, any events.
There, there are no events on frames are apparently.
So, it doesn't actually have anything to free ever get in here.
It doesn't so it's can actually free anything here because there's
nothing actually on frame 0, which is actually correct frame 0 would
be empty.
Because frame one was the first frame we ever use for collating.
So, we look at these two, and we see if they are the same.
Which they should not be right.
So we don't have to increment the most recent frame.
We drift increment, the oldest frame.
So we do and that's good and off we go.
And that seems right.
So every frame now we should have to do this.
This should actually now free some things.
So, when I come into free frame, this should actually just should
trigger.
And it does.
So let's pull that off.
Got free event, we're going to be allocate it to Loop through here and
deallocate a bunch of stuff.
That's good.
Good.
So that's all pretty nice.
I think that all seems reasonable to me.
And then we're left with the Collision frame is on one the oldest
frame.
Also on one sweet moves up to two and we're good.
Right.
So that seems pretty good.
So I'm not sure.
where our bug is, I guess our bug is what happens when you can't, when
you were not freeing through that path, I guess our bug happens when
we start hitting the system more heavily, when we launched the game,
part of the game,
And and we free out of store event.
So freeing out of here is obviously like this is obviously a problem.
When we do free all this Frame.
So I'm going to see what happens when we get there.
Obviously, it won't happen here.
Well, it would happen here.
Eventually, maybe it might not because eventually this will probably
countdown
Hmm, you know, that's a little suspicious.
So, actually, no, I take it back.
There's some bug here.
We're not actually freeing all of the memory that we allocate on a
given frame because this would stop counting down basically.
When we got to,
Once we got to the 236 frame because weed-free one frames worth of
data and add one faint of the data.
And there's not appreciably more data happening each frame.
So, we actually still have a bug.
so something that we allocate,
Is not getting freed.
But the question is, what is it?
So, here we are in free frame.
We're looking through this particular ordinal which is the one we want
to free.
We're taking a look at oldest event which would have all of the stuff
that we allocated, right?
Because that's where store frame pulls this data from.
That sure, looks like it should work.
although,
I do have one question.
What exactly is going on here?
You know, I'm saying to you.
Why is that?
Do we even know why that's a pointer?
Because I don't.
I feel like that should be baked into the frame.
But either way, it sure isn't getting freed.
And we would need to definitely free it.
I'm going to see what happens if we just do that.
You think well, all right.
When we do free frame, we look at frame ordinal.
Will go in here and say element frame.
Not only frame.
Debug frame frame equals debug State frames plus frame ordinal if
frame profile node.
Realist, the allocate.
Rain route.
Profound it.
mmm, I'm saying
Still chewing through the memory there.
So I kind of want to know where that's coming from.
That's not going to be there.
Of course, I'm way over time here.
I'm like 10 minutes overtime.
You know how I get sometimes?
you just, you know how I get
What's the problem?
There we go.
So I am curious, if this is not freeing everything, what isn't it?
Freeing is my question and I suppose we should probably look to see.
Let's take a look.
So we've got debug trees but those are fine.
Right, we've got debug views.
Those are actually also not part of the collation process.
We have.
Debug threads.
Now that in theory should be being handled separately properly.
And that's also part of the debugger Arena, not the per frame arena.
In fact I can just look
at the collation Arena, right?
Store events.
Prefer a marina.
So we only really need to look at what's coming out of the per frame
Arena.
And so, we're literally, this is the only place that we take out of
that Arena.
That's it, okay?
And so, if that's the only place is story event, then that means that
we are somehow storing events that we are never recovering when we try
to do our free event walk.
So, I definitely messed this part up right here.
When we go through the
Ash and we try to pull out whatever the frame is that were
That we're going free for whatever reason.
This is no longer an accurate way I guess of
Recovering all those events but I'm just not sure why.
Free event is the oldest event in the frame.
We then set the oldest event to be whatever came after that and we
deallocate that one that we were on.
That should move all of them from that frame out.
and we do that for everything in the hash,
What else does that have in it?
Dare I ask.
I should probably clear these.
As well.
Like after this Frame is is done.
I should probably do a zero struct, right?
But that shouldn't have anything to do with it.
So I don't know.
This may have to wait till tomorrow.
I'm not immediately seeing the answer.
And we may just have to take a closer look, basically, what happens.
It looks like is we just aren't?
We're actually leaking that memory.
So before we were properly freeing it and then I busted it.
And so now, instead of being able to always free it, when we're done,
we're leaking it instead.
If that makes sense.
So down down, down it goes which it should not be at this point, it
should not actually be going down.
And then eventually, when it gets to the end, it will hang presumably.
Like so.
Because now it can't free.
Its trying desperately to try to free memory so that it can allocate
the next event to store, but it already believes it's freed everything
that it could free.
So it's just hunting through the circular buffer forever and it will
never find anything more to free because it already thinks it freed
everything.
So, that's just really perplexing.
All right.
I think we'll have to do a little bit more.
Debugging tomorrow, I'm going to call it for here.
Any Mouse.
Do you need to wrap that plus frame ordinal in the free frame
function?
Rap.
Well, there's only two of them.
There's this one.
And there's this one.
But what do you mean by wrapping them?
We don't need to mod them if that's, you know, because this is always
inside that range because they're pre-wrapped.
Like when you're saying free at your passing, an ordinal in which is
already wrapped.
I could assert that, right?
Like we probably should like, right?
We should probably just say here like hey by the way, if you thought
you were going to free something,
That was like, outside of the frame range.
Presumably, you know, we would get bogus values and know pretty
quickly.
But, you know,
But no one's ever going to pass that in.
So also, I suppose the other thing that yeah, that's weird.
I there must be something very simple but subtle that I'm forgetting
because
it would seem
Missy, what store event does?
I'm supposed collation.
Frame word null.
We know how many events restore it were on that frame.
So the other thing that's kind of interesting is I can assert catch
this, presumably meaning.
I should be able to say you know, freed three-day event count and
every time we move something to the free list, we could count it like
so.
And then when we come down here, and we look at what the frame is, we
can assert that the stored event count for that frame.
Equals the free to vent count.
Because then we would know, right?
If that makes sense.
Now, this I suppose we also would have to count
That is madness.
Okay, there we go.
I was like, I guess I just hadn't gotten a 256 frames yet.
I'm like they shouldn't add up and they don't we stored 56.
We freed fatigue.
Okay.
That makes even less sense.
This is the only place we can get one of those.
How is that possible?
Where is the root profile node allocated, by the way?
Store event.
No event.
So it's definitely storing it on the frame.
What's the element?
So it is wrapped in an element so that one I didn't actually.
So that doesn't actually have to be stored.
So that's, that's not actually I didn't actually distort is stored
under an element.
So, this doesn't actually have to happen.
all right, so if I rebuild that and I run it,
Now, we should get an assertion that when they differ which if they
don't ever differ.
That's what I would expect to see before.
Let's see if that happens again.
So it was literally just that.
I was double free map but we had the bug before I did that.
That does not make any sense.
I mean, it makes sense why that was broken because we're moving some
of the free list of second time which you can't do obviously because
it breaks the free list.
But how on Earth was it not working originally?
That's just bizarre.
Well, never mind.
We didn't have a bug.
I lied.
I made a bug when trying to fix the bug.
Let me take a couple Q's here.
I'm a bit behind on, hit me here.
But do you typically bypass for something like off, stream coding?
All the simplified things like, rendering a bitmap.
Like how you were doing drawbitmap like an episode 39 and go straight
to the renderer.
But as well as other things like structured Assets in the like,
So, I guess what I would say is, yeah, I don't typically go through
stuff that I already know, isn't the way to do something like, if I
know that my final code is not going to be drawing a bitmap, you know?
If I knew that my final things are GPU thing, I'm not going to like
spend a bunch of time, making a software renderer obviously, right?
And so a bunch of those things I show in handmade here.
I'll because I, that is what I did over time.
Meaning, the first render, I wrote, there was no such thing as a GPU
in a PC at that time.
So the first render, I wrote was a software renderer, right?
In fact, the first several, I wrote were suffer renderers and only
later.
Once you've UK onto, I start doing that and I feel like that's an
important part of your education in game programming.
Understand how to write things like a software renderer because it
means that you will actually understand how a GPU renderer Works.
Whereas you won't understand that, if you've never done it yourself,
But you wouldn't do that in the course of running.
If you already know, if you already know how to write a software
renderer, you wouldn't write one again because you don't need it for
anything.
Like unless you add some real bit of reason to do so that not to say
that you couldn't have such a reason but most of the time, probably
not.
As for other stuff like on the debug system.
I've been legitimately playing around with it.
Meaning, I did not know exactly how I wanted this to work going into
it and I've kind of like felt my way around to figure out how I wanted
to be structured, and that's because I wanted to show how to make a
complex system experimentally
And that I still do all the time.
When I'm trying to design something new.
I obviously don't have the luxury of having done it before because
that's what makes it new.
And so I have to experiment with how to do it.
And so, you know, I've never done a debug system that works exactly.
Like this one does that has exactly the same features.
And so I kind of had been exploring to see how that works, and I'm
kind of interested in some of the stuff that I've done so far on it.
That's somewhat educational.
We can re-enable our profile view, I'll do it tomorrow, but that's
going to be good.
Dude, in basement.
One thoughts on using a static array instead of the lists?
Yeah, I just felt like I felt like most of the stuff that we're going
to want to do is very much like wants to jump to a particular frames
and running through the list, every time to get there.
Did not seem like a great idea to me, but, you know, maybe maybe it
would have been fine.
I just, it looked was starting to get annoying.
So I want to be able to do stuff like, say, hey draw like this frame
in the previous frame and I want that to be.
The or this in the previous five frames or Draw frame for of
everybody, I just felt like that would be kind of nicer, so that's the
way I.
Why did that?
They blow in Savannah, has this to say inheritance and encapsulation
to best inventions of mankind.
Oh my God in sohbat is going rogue.
That is a horrible thing to say and sohbat.
Any Mass do you prefer to use modulo or masking for circular indexing,
do compilers replace module has its bitwise and if the operator
operand is a power of 2.
So what I would say about that is
Not blowing the nose.
But what I say about that is,
Modulo should be fine.
Most of the time if you're doing stuff like debug code or things that
happened.
Early and they allow you to make your accounts, be whatever you want,
which is, oftentimes nice.
In a speed scenario where I look, I really am worried about how fast
is going to be.
You may want to do masking because masking can be faster.
Since modulo is an integer divide kind of a situation and it can be a
problem.
As far as I know, most of the time compilers are smart enough to, to
replace modulo with bitwise and when it is a power of 2, when the size
is a power of 2,
The thing modulo N is a power of 2, but have I tested that extensively
know most of the time.
If I care about the speed, I write the mask myself.
But, you know, I think compilers, yeah, are generally smart enough to
do that.
I don't think you have to babysit that particular thing.
Her Tamina.
Are we still doing the marathon training camp for the Q and A Menace
II?
Don't know that I will, I mean, I reserve the right to do it that way.
So it's get the profile koti.
Everything Sarita, what happened to it?
Some of the things you had implanted like the multiple Lanes here,
just paired know the multiple Lanes is still there.
In fact, I can show it to you.
I guess I would have to.
I just said, I wasn't going to re-enable this till tomorrow, but I
could re enable it.
Let's see rah-rah frame bars.
So this was the portfolio, we were working on and loop.
I just need to Port this code, so you need to Forever guess for their
frames.
Hey, guess what that to do is now done?
Because we have an array.
So what we can do now is say, well, most recent frame ordinal, equals
whatever the debug State most recent rain ordinal is then when we come
through here, and we get our viewing element, assuming that it
actually existed, we can access the root node directly.
In a variety of ways.
So the first thing we would do here is say, well, the viewing element.
Frames oldest event.
like so, so if we do viewing element,
Most recent frame ordinal.
And on the other hand we could say, well, debug State frames, most
recent frame word and all re-profile note.
Like so.
That's not spelled, right?
Debug frame does not have an overloaded operator, right?
You are sir.
All right.
So here is the current profile code.
You can see the multiple Lanes here, here's the three lanes, there's
just nothing happening.
These other threads.
If I wanted something to happen threads, we could turn on the software
renderer and presumably.
Whoa,
that's not good.
This looks like a bug, I must have just recently because we were
running the multiple frame view just the other day.
and that's
Intro rectangle.
Oh, you know what?
That's probably just because again, we're draw so much in the draw
profile in thing.
That, yeah, we need a way to not draw all the events, because there's
way too many events.
When we go to the software renderer, let me just turn off the
recursion for that for the moment.
Yeah, we need some way of figuring out how we would ya make?
That not happen.
But anyway, so here's the multi-frame.
The multi-lane view in action because now we actually have multiple
Lanes going, you know, normally when we are running the GPU renderer
there's really nothing for the other course, the CPU to do right now
because we just don't have enough work for frame.
The GPU is doing a lot of that work, but in
Offer render.
You can see now do tiled render work getting called multiple times per
thread on lots of threads, right?
So there's all that there's, there's the work that you're that you're
looking for, right?
Does that answer the question?
This is the risk.
You what if you aren't really learning from here where I've gone
through episodes one through 28 about four times that I thought, I
knew how to do so I tried to make the simplified win32 layer to get to
the independent layer, and I found that I couldn't do it.
Documentation was rough and I forgot what the things did.
What would you say to people who find that they aren't learning?
Well, there's two things that could be the case one is you just need
to try harder at it, right?
The other might be that it might be a little too soon for an made
here, right?
Handmade hero is not meant for people who have never programmed
before.
As I said, you know, sort of the outs of the series.
It's made for people who know how to program, but just don't know how
to program games or game engines, I should say.
So it's designed to take somebody who understands how to program and
show them how
A game programming and game, engine programming works.
So, if you are not at the point where you're comfortable doing a lot
of programming, you know, handmade hero doesn't have enough
introductory material in it, probably to get you up to speed
necessarily.
So I would say you need to do a quick self assessment to figure out
whether that's the case and if that's the case then you would want to
start with more introductory programming materials introductory, see
materials or introductory Windows programming materials.
Just to get you up to the point where you're like, okay I'm more
comfortable this stuff now and then you can do.
He made here which tends to only spend a lot of time teaching the game
engine parts.
Not just what's
Pointer or stuff like that which you know would be the kinds of things
that more interaction with Joe would have.
So you kind of need to figure out which whether that's a problem as
well.
And I don't know like since I don't know you and where you're at I
couldn't necessarily say which one of those would be the case, right?
But yeah.
I'm getting pretty excited about getting this profiler.
Good.
Because this is going to be, it's getting there, and it's going to be
pretty sweet.
All right, I'll see any more cues.
So I'm going to call it.
Call it a day.
Also, I wonder now if we do this.
Yeah.
so now, yeah, we're totally set up for tomorrow to go into frame bars
and that'll just draw like all the frames of a
Or element that we go to.
So I'm pretty pretty happy about that.
All right, folks.
McCall it
You know what I should also do should start this loading.
Is that?
There's another question for you.
Where is that was in Jake.
Owen, where was that at?
Blackboard, @j work archive.
Work archive.
Days, 100 to 199.
Why is it specifically in there?
Does that even make any sense to anyone?
Why is it in there?
Shouldn't it be out here?
Well, I don't know if you know what?
I don't even care.
Don't know.
Don't care.
Just going to keep it doing whatever it's doing and let it do that
thing.
I am going to wrap things up.
Thank you everyone for joining me for another soda and read hero.
It's been a pleasure coding with you.
As always, if you would like to follow along at home, you can always
pre-order the game on a meteorite or going to come to the source code
which you can use to follow along.
You can also support us on patreon.
If you would like using this button, you can go to our forearms using
this button and ask questions you can find out our schedule by going
to the Tweet bot which tweets the schedule at you.
And if you want to use the editor that we use on the series, you just
called for coder and you can find it by putting for coder into your
favorite browser.
And it's this dude right here, it has a patreon page, you can go to
and if you use the five dollar-a-month pledged here, you can get your
very own Alpha version of it.
That's the same as the one that I'm using.
That's about it.
I will be back tomorrow.
5:00 p.m.
Pacific Daylight time.
For more profiler fun.
I'm kind of excited about fancy profiling and I tend to be the only
person who's ever excited about code, I guess.
So I don't necessarily know if you are, but that's the problem with
you not being the people in charge of stream, I get to make all the
rules.
So, you know, what can I say?
We're profiling.
It's gonna be awesome.
I will see you guys.
Here tomorrow for that.
Until then have fun programming and I'll see you on the internet.
Take it easy, everyone.