Hello everyone and welcome to handmade hero.
The show we could have complete game live on stream.
We are covering some animation topics today and we have been for the
past few days, just talking about the various ways that you can
Implement animation in your code and yesterday we showed how to do
some.
Well, let me go ahead and give you the sort of the idea of where we
left off yesterday, in terms of how to do animations stuff.
Let's go ahead and Jump Right In by
Wait, today is day 274, so, if you are following along at home at the
code, you will want to start with day, 273 source code.
That is what I am starting with right now.
So here is the state of our handmade Hero at the moment.
Where we are working on getting him moving.
So you can see we are working on just his body jump.
And you can see there's a couple different things that we've done
there, right?
And we've sort of added some anticipation to it.
We have a nice little parabolic Arc in there and there's some landing.
And it's starting to look somewhat respectable.
Obviously, like I said, we still have a bunch of stuff to do with
respect to leaning, so that we're going to attach the head to the body
and a couple of the things like that.
So, you know, we're not we're not done by any stretch of the
imagination.
He is.
Supposed to be a severed head but we're getting we're getting further
along towards where we need to be but we haven't really covered all
the things in a mission that I wanted to cover.
So like I've kind of been piecing them out.
As we eat, do each one and write the code for each one of these.
And what I wanted to point out to you here, as you look at at at this
is, if I go ahead and slow down our time, step a bit
So what I'm going to do is I'm going to slow down the entire time step
and you know what we probably could do as well.
If we wanted to is, we could make the time step an actual controlling
like a variable that we can control you know like we could do
something like I don't know.
In the simulation we could say that there's a debug our 32 which is
like Global like timestep percentage or something like this and what
And say, oops.
what we could say there is if in,
If we essentially tweak some variable cure that will call Global time
step percentage.
If we tweak some variable will start off the variable at 100% let's
say and will you know will allow ourselves to tweak it to whatever we
want and when we get our dt4 frame so when we come in here you know we
have the input, you can see in game update and render, right?
We have this concept of
UT for frame Loops, which is how we determine how much time has gone
by.
Looks like we're not actually even using it in here, but I'm going to
do it in here so that it affects everybody.
So what I want to do here is say OK for our stimulation.
When we come in here and we get this, the input dt4 frame.
I'm going to go ahead and multiply it by whatever the global time
step.
Oops.
Global time step percentages.
Hello, why am I stuck in the menus?
Thank you, windows little time, step percentage.
I'm going to multiply it by global time step percentage and and I am
going to divide that by 100 so that it's 12:45.
And now we can adjust that percentage.
However, we want, and it will sort of control what sort of a Time step
we're taking if that makes sense.
Oh wait, you don't have to do, be 32.
You just do value for these guys.
It's only pools that needed it.
So you know now I've got sort of thing where I'm, you know, moving my
guy around and if I want to sort of slow that down so I can see it a
little bit better.
I should be able to take this and just kind of like drop it down.
Like 50 would be like half speed right?
And like 25% speed so now I'm like real slow.
So here you can kind of see what it looks like when the dudes hopping
around and there's a little hot back and forth, right?
And so it's starting to look okay, you know, it's got some animation
quality in there and it's doing okay.
But what I wanted to point out and because what I we're going to focus
on today is this part right here where you notice, it looks kind of
look, sort of reasonable when I'm just hopping when it's, you know,
going from one to the other.
But if I was to continue on, so I'm going to now go across two
squares.
Do you see how there's kind of an extra bounciness in there?
Where, you know, if a person was really sort of hopping along like
this, they wouldn't go down up down, and up again for the jump if they
knew they were landing.
And then going into another jump, they just go down once and up one's,
right?
So we kind of are in this situation where we're getting something that
we don't want happening there.
And if you think about why it's happening, it's because we just have a
single can die.
Idea of what it means to jump, right?
We have an animation.
That's what it means to jump, and it involves going down coming back
up again.
Jumping Landing going down, and coming back up again.
That's what we coded for our jump Loop and this would be basically the
same.
You can kind of think of this.
As being very analogous to, if we had had an artist, create some kind
of an animation in a tool, like Sprite or something like that, and
they just made, you know, a jump animation.
Well, this is what we would get and we immediately run into this
problem.
There's this contextualization of what's Happening.
The Landing that we want to use to create a more believable animation.
And so, what we're going to do instead of keeping that sort of canned
aspect to it, is what I want to show you show.
You today is how we can take something that was previously kind of
under a can animation control, and move just that one part out to
physical control or pseudo physical control.
In this case, where we're going to simulate that a little bit more, in
order to get a more continuous, more natural feel
He'll than if we're just trying to play Candy animations.
And obviously there are some solutions with candida Nations to a
limited extent.
We could make a candy intimation that we detect when we're doing the
double jump.
You know when we're jumping off of a land and play that, you know,
half of it and you just keep multiplying out all your cases and maybe
that's fine.
But in general if you can use some judicious simulation-based stuff,
it'll save you a lot of time and a lot of Animation budget, you know,
in the long run.
So I just want to show you that option here.
Okay, so if we go back and we look at where we were at, in our, our
hero head away, time in the rolling, I'm not in the right file there
for our hero body.
What we're doing is we're sort of taking this little movement mode
hopping thing and we're saying that when we're in movement mode
hopping, you know, here's the, here's the sort of deal with that,
right?
And it's broken to these sort of three phases.
There's the take-off phase where we kind of go down and up.
There's the landing phase where I'm sorry, there's the ballistic phase
where we're flying through the air and we this overlaps that phase.
So we kind of have a little bit going on there and then there's the
landing phase where we come back down.
That's where we do that secondary compression.
So, what I want to do here is I want to kind of shift away from this
and move that that springiness, that sort of, you know, that that
torso springiness that we manually coded in T-Bob to be a sine wave.
What I'm going to do is I'm going to say, let's pull that out to
something that's just always simulated.
So, the, the connection between the dudes,
The body, you know.
And you know the cape and the and the Torso is going to be just kind
of a spring.
And so when he wants to launch up into the air, you know, it'll push
upwards.
And when he comes down and lands, it'll, you know, push downwards and
that sort of stuff.
And we'll just let it kind of dampen itself out in that sense, right?
So let's go ahead and and make that happen.
So how are we going to do that?
Well, the first thing I'm going to do is decouple the usage of TB.
From any particular mode.
So I'm just going to move T Bob's, computations in their entirety.
I'm going to move those out into a separate thing that is not
dependent on the Move mode because we're just always going to
Emulate that as this separate variable.
Now, if we want to override it in a mode, we certainly always could,
but at the Baseline, I want to just say it's simulated.
So now all of the places that were previously Computing T-Bob are now
gone, as you can kind of see.
And so now, we just have this thing here, which is like sine T Tower.
Whatever, right?
And here's the T-Bob.
So what I need to do now is I need to assign a Target value to the
T-Bob.
Okay.
In
Other words I I need some knowledge of what the T-Bob should be at any
given point in time, right?
And so I'm going to I need a bunch of information about that and so
what I'm going to do is I'm going to create sort of a way of
prescribing, what I want the T-Bob to be, and just so you can kind of
understand where I'm going with this.
Where, as my Mischief, there it is.
Huron day.
274.
So, what's happening here is I have you know the the bottom of the
hero and I've got the cape and I've got some notion that they are
connected by a sort of a piece that can move up and down for now
that's what we're saying, all right.
And there's two things that I want to do with this one is I want to
track its momentum so I want to be able to say Well if you know I am
coming down
Just part of the you know, ballistic phase or whatever when I get to
here you know, or at any point, during this thing there's a certain
amount of velocity to that middle piece, right?
And the reason that I need to be able to track that momentum or that
velocity really we you know it's technically momentum but since we're
not really working with masses here and we don't super care about
relative masses.
It's really not much of a momentum.
It's really just a velocity.
It's you know, a momentum
has to do with mass and we're not really talking about that.
So we're just going to track, you know, we want to be able to say well
it's got a certain velocity and the reason we want to do that is
because for example, on the landing, when this thing lands, we want
the top piece to continue having that velocity even after the bottom
piece stops.
So we want some notion of that retained velocity.
But the other thing that we want is we want like a Target, you know?
D.
Or, you know, a Target position.
And the reason that we want that is because we need to move this,
dude, we still need to do the things we were doing before we move him
down, you know, to a Crouch and then we move him up to Spring, right?
That's none of that.
Has anything to do with momentum, that's internally generated.
By the jumping action of the character.
And so there is no momentum to preserve or anything.
There we just, we straight up have to like prescribed that as part of
our animation.
And so, what we want to do is we want to take the places where we were
previously setting T-Bob do something specifically with that sine
function.
And now instead, we want to replace it with a suggestion of what the
velocity should be or what the position should be one of the other so
that we can, you know, wherever it was or whatever effects were on it
before, we can go ahead and preserve those and use, you know, the
motion in one continuous way.
And so this is a pretty
You standard technique, right?
It's basically just taking what was a prescribed position and turning
it into something.
That's a prescribed velocity or prescribed acceleration depending on
the circumstance is so that it can be mixed over time with other
things, in a natural physical way.
So that's all we're going to do that.
That's that's our goal.
Of course, it's easier said than done.
But I mean, at the high level, it's not particularly complicated thing
for us to do.
All right, so let's start with something very, very straightforward.
Let's start by using some kind of a, let's, let's start by using some
kind of, a, sort of a spree system here to simulate this T-Bob, felt
this T-Bob value.
And what I'm probably going to do just to make it a little easier on
ourselves to hoops and region.
I'm going to go to here and I'm going to have a DT
So I'm going to have its first derivative as well in here.
So, this is velocity and that's the position of that T-Bob.
Okay?
So what I want to do here is I want to say, well, alright, we want to
be able to correct the T-Bob, right?
We want to be able to do stuff for the people, and of course, I guess.
I also have to stop setting it to 0.
That's obviously not going to be good.
So when I come down through the movement mode, what I'm going to do at
the end of my movement mode code and I'm ready to sort of finalize,
the character here is I'm going to go ahead and simulate T-Bob the way
that we've been simulating everything else, right?
I'm going to go ahead and do a sort of standard equation of motion.
Just like we've done many times before something that looks like this.
Right.
I'm going to take the acceleration and I'm gonna that I want to to
this thing to have and I'm going to multiply it by the time step
squared, and I'm going to take the velocity multiplied by the time so
standard equation of motion.
If you don't remember what these are, go back and look at the time, we
covered equations of motion.
And you'll notice I'm using these equations of motion because they're
the same equate, they're going to be the same equations of motions
fundamentally if we want physical, sort of behavior, we are going to
start.
Equations, even though we're talking about a value, which is not
really a position in space.
It's sort of this made-up value that we created, but because I want
the underlying parts of it to feel kind of physical, I'm using the
equations of motion as the basis for creating the thing that I'm going
to tune, if that makes sense.
And so I'm just going to start out by doing a very, very simple thing
here, which is like I said, just doing an accumulation for the
velocity and accumulation for the
Position and so we can set an acceleration for the bobbing now.
I don't actually know if I'm going to want to use acceleration per se.
I may end up wanting to just prescribe velocity directly, I don't
know.
But I'm going to start with the base physicality of it and see how
that goes.
So in this case, obviously we know the velocity the velocity is just
this.
I don't know why I said V3 there.
Our time step I think is actually technically is DP, right?
Not t.
So, you know, DT is the time step that's our velocity in our
acceleration.
Is the thing that we don't actually know at this point right now, if I
was to set our acceleration to 0, then what I would expect to see
happen here, right?
Is I would expect to see there, be no movement of that joint at all.
And that is exactly what I do.
See.
So, you know, if I come in
And I drop this down again so we can kind of see what's happening.
We're seeing that that joint is not is not doing anything, right.
Nothing's happening to the Joint whatsoever.
And, you know, we could probably do here as well, is if we wanted to,
we could go ahead.
And I don't even remember how we do this, exactly.
But I'm going to try here.
If I want to do sort of
This this sort of thing.
I'm going to set up a Live code loop.
So here, what I've done is I just recorded the motion of the hero,
right?
And here he is, kind of moving back and forth.
Now, I'm going to make four coder be a little bit smaller window just
slightly so that we can edit the code here while we watch the
animation in progress.
And this is what Loop live coding is really good for obviously,
because now we don't have to like, wonder what each individual code
changes doing.
We
It go and we just edit the animation in place, right?
Okay.
So obviously, you know, one thing I could do is I could make this
explode real quick if I wanted to, by just saying, like, let's give it
some acceleration and what should happen there is the thing should
just kind of like explode off into into space.
Oh, you know what?
I just realized, too.
These are static so they're going to get reset every time.
Hmm, I don't know that that's necessarily a problem.
Because I can edit them but I wonder if we want to put those somewhere
else, you know what I mean?
Well, I'm not going to worry about it now but good to know that that's
a bug or at least thing.
I probably don't want if that makes sense.
All right, go back to world.
No, dear.
There we go.
Yeah, much nicer.
All right.
So assuming that that's maybe made a little bit more explicit because
that's a little bit subtle.
Still, let me Crank That acceleration up quite a bit so if I crank
that acceleration up you can kind of see what's happening there right?
It just keeps going up and up and up and up and up right and
presumably it should go up faster as time goes by.
So if I was to make it the say 1.0 I would think it should be moving
fairly fast by the
Right.
Let me make it even faster.
okay, so now, we essentially have a separate, we have a separate
amount of acceleration on there that, where, you know, that were
applying and
Yeah.
And and so now you know, just thinking about that acceleration.
I can now sort of start to talk about what I might want to do with the
acceleration inside my, my other things here.
So I'm going to give this a better name.
I'm going to call this DDT Bob so that it's not a, it's a second
derivative of Bob.
And I'm also going to go ahead and place this in here.
For now.
Okay, so if I'm going to set this DDT Bob, I'm going to go over here
and place.
You know, this value of the top, I'm going to assume that there's no
acceleration and all I'm going to start doing now is just playing with
that that DDT in some of these routines to sort of set.
What I expect it to actually be in any given situation, right?
I'm gonna get rid of the T value in here because I don't really need
it.
So what I'm going to do instead is I'm going to say well okay if the
entity key movement
Less than T jump.
And I don't care about this mid value anymore, so I really need
another one, which is like, I need sort of the, I guess if it's if
it's less than T, jump than what I want.
Is I want the DDT Bob.
I want it to be pointing upwards, so I'm to push up during that jump,
right?
I want to, I want to kind of push upward and what I want to do, for
the pushing upward is I want to say like, okay, you know, maybe that's
what we had before, which is like 100 or maybe it's even more than
that, maybe it's like 25 or something like that.
and and then when I you know in the middle of the the sort of Jump
Then I dont need any acceleration at all and when I am done and I'm
No, sort of Landing the thing.
Then again, don't really need any acceleration at all on that either.
However, what I want to do here is potentially alter the velocity on
the landing because when I land, I'm going to stop the the movement of
the guy.
So what I want to do is set his the velocity of his bobbing motion
directly.
Oops, to something that's going to be fairly - and I don't know again,
what that value should be, but we'll find out let's say something like
this.
All right.
So I'm going to go ahead and
And restart that guy here.
Also you know what I think I should probably do is well what I
probably should have done is done us.
A loop that doesn't go for so long at first because we have to clean
up the rest of our stuff before this is going to make any sense.
Well alright I'll just code the rest of it.
Okay so we're going to want to play with those values to get those
into some right.
Ranges and all that.
But what I need to do first obviously if we want to look at this in
More detail as as multiple hops happen is I now need some notion that
there's going to be like a restoration to the normal location to the
back towards zero, right?
So I need something that constantly pulls this back towards zero,
especially in the case, where the DDT, you know, if you're if he's not
being activated at all.
But so what I want to do is I want to go ahead and say hey let's put a
thing on that looks at how far away I am from 0 and up.
Why is an acceleration in the opposite direction of that, right?
So what I want to do is I want to say instead of initializing my DDT,
Bob well, I guess I still want to lose 50 when I accumulated here
before I actually go and use it for anything.
I want to take my DDT Bob and I want to add to it essentially an
acceleration back towards zero.
So I know where I am.
Right.
I know, I'm here.
So what I want to do is just add some negative amount.
I don't know how much, but I want to add
Um, - amount that will push back towards that 0, right?
That will restore me back there if that makes sense.
Okay, so
let's see here.
That doesn't seem strong enough.
Unfortunately, we need something that's going to be strong.
There we go.
So you can kind of see it starting to work, right?
You can kind of see it.
It's trying its fighting to restore it.
But this, this negative velocity that gets put on there as a little
bit too much for it.
Maybe tune that down a little bit, right?
So hopefully you can sort of already see the starting to work a little
bit, right?
It's starting to be almost
Most a workable sort of jump, feel right?
You see how that's starting to look pretty good?
And so now what we really have to start taking into account, mmm.
Is what happens during The Landing part of things where I'm actually
on the ground.
Because as the head moves towards the side, I want to be starting that
jump.
So I want to be pushing down based on the distance that the head is
from the body.
And I already know that, right?
I've got this body distance here and I know the take-off distance,
right?
Excuse me.
Well, I guess I don't actually go to take off distance now that I
think about it.
So, yeah, we're gonna have to tune that as well.
This is actually based on something slightly different, but what I
want to do is as that head moves to the side.
I want the, the natural Crouch to happen so that he's ready to spring
out as necessary, right?
So, what I'm going to do here is say, okay, you know, I need to know
how far the head is from the body, and I feel like that where we ever
Computing that
it's like, I guess we weren't
No, we were Computing, some other things based on the head but not
that one.
So what I want to do here when we're planted, I want to do and I'll
probably just put this up here for always.
So I'm going to say that, there's a the head distance, right?
And the head distance is just the length of the vector from me, right?
From the from the body.
I want to go from the body to wherever the head is.
Right.
So however far that is that's that head distance.
And then we're going to say like Max Head distance for this purpose is
going to be some value that we will tune, which is how far we want the
head to be, you know, it's probably less than that.
But it's how far away we want the head to be.
What or how far the head will be when working, you know, maximally
when we're pushing down as hard as we're going to push down, okay?
So max the head distance on the Mac said distance tells us that and
what we can do here again is we can do a like a head, a t head
distance.
Now which again uses that map that sort of map command that we've got.
Where is it map?
I've got it here somewhere.
Clamp, 01 mapped arranged.
That's the one I wanted lamps are one mapped arranged.
And what I want to do here is say, I want to map from 0 to the max
head distance, whatever the actual head distance is right now and that
produces a number between zero and one that I can now use to multiply
however, much crouching, I want to have happen.
So instead of this being, the only thing that happens just
An upward Force.
Now, whenever the head is moving away from the body and we're in a
planted mode, what we're going to want to do there is we're going to
want to apply that crouching effect as well.
So that's anytime, right?
That's any time, we're in this mode, we essentially want to, you know,
maybe do - 50 or something.
We're going to take whatever.
RT.
Head distance is so, however, far the head is moved and that's how how
hard we're going to be pushing down if that makes sense.
So that's what will give us that sort of that sort of ducking effect.
Alright, so now we have to actually get this part working and it
doesn't quite look to me.
Like it is because as that head was moving, you can see the head
moving away.
I didn't actually see the DDT.
Bob actually have any effect there so when we were in movement planted
it seemed it did not seem to be actually applying any anything useful
to DDT, Bob.
And I'm not sure why.
So, let's take a look at what's going on there.
We compute the head distance.
And that looks like a fairly reasonable thing.
We have the max head distance, we don't really know if that value is,
is useful.
You know what I can do is I can quickly check just like commenting
this out, I can check to see whether it's largely just because of
that.
So it looks like that's not getting applied at all.
So it has nothing to do with the head distance computation, it's just
that DDT.
Bob just isn't actually getting applied in a particular way, it would
seem because if we were in movement planted, we should have been
getting this, this thing happening here, right?
And we should
Should have seen been seeing that come down.
Oh, I see why I've got a compile error.
What's the compile error?
No operator found.
Which takes a left hand of V 3.
What?
Oh whoops I just was missing a little arrow.
Okay, let's try that again.
All right, so that's obviously a little too strong to say, the very
least, so I'm going to back off on that a little bit, right?
And let's see.
All right, so that's looking pretty good to me.
That's starting to look quite nice and so,
I guess the only thing I would probably say here is I probably want to
tune this part to be a little bit, a little bit more.
A little bit closer.
To the edge.
I probably don't want as much time.
Like, the Hop should have happened, probably pretty quickly.
So there should be less of the other parts of this.
I should think and actually teal and probably would happen and we
don't need any this stuff.
Doesn't really need to be there at all anymore.
Teal and can just be we can just set this when we actually finish the
movement, right?
And so now like this part, for the most for the most part is just
something that we can sort of say is is
I'm things and we don't really have to worry about this at all.
I don't know if the entity DP ever really wants to be something, but
we can put that up here as a thing to look at later.
But again, I'm just going to kind of hack this apart and say, well,
alright, so here we go with that.
We that all looks pretty good now.
Oops,
Okay, so now let's try and let's try and make this be a little bit
more.
Let's see.
Yeah, we got it.
We got to just work on the tuning here.
So I want this key jump like there to be like, basically a tea thrust,
right?
And I want that to go for longer.
So I wanted to take off sort of before he finishes his upward push.
So he kind of pushes through it a little
And we'll see how that goes.
And that definitely goes up a little too high there, but I'm not sure
exactly how I want to tune around it.
So I'm going to take a look at the TT.
Bob here is negative 20 and I guess the DDT Bob here,
Should really be well, it should be nothing.
But that's what it would have been anyway.
I feel like that's a little bit of a non sequitur happening in the
animation there.
But I'm not really sure exactly where it's coming from.
If that makes sense.
I'm going to go switch off the loop live coding for a second and just
move the the fellow around myself.
All right.
Okay, so there we can kind of see what's happening a little bit
better.
Okay.
Oh right.
This is something I wanted to cover perfect.
So if we take a look at what's happening right now, you can see that.
It's just oscillating back and forth.
So this would be a perfect time to talk about this at.
Don't
I've talked about it before and I wanted to talk about it.
So I'm going to talk about it now.
So we are trying to do is essentially a spring here, right?
I'm trying to make it feel like a kind of bouncy sort of Wiggly thing.
And so when I did write is I said, okay I've got this.
This concept of you know here's the zero point right here is mighty
Bob, this is at zero and you know it's going to go positive this way
your - that way.
And so if I'm
You know, up here or down here, and I want to apply an acceleration,
that will try to get me back to where I'm going.
Well, obviously, if T-Bob is positive, I want to apply something - and
if T-Bob is - I want to play Something Positive.
So I just basically said okay you know the acceleration that I want to
apply here is going to be equal to something, right?
Some mystery coefficient whatever I want to tune because it's whatever
I want right times.
Whatever the the T-Bob value was,
And I want to always make that - so that I'm going against wherever
T-Bob is.
So that's pushing it back towards zero, right?
And this is what's essentially an called an undamped spring.
And I can show you the more formal version of it.
What the more formal version of it actually is is it says that the
acceleration right?
Whatever that acceleration?
In this case, acceleration is probably the wrong term because usually
Springs are in for space again.
Like I said we're not caring about Mass here.
Remember Force equals mass times acceleration.
So when you don't care about mass then Force equals acceleration
effectively and you're talking about the same thing.
But in a more physically stimulated system where we had differences of
masses that we cared about
Kind of important to talk about ones which ones which we are actually
sort of talking about force and we talk about Springs.
But in our case we're putting Springs directly on acceleration because
we just don't care about the mass part.
But it's worth noting in case you're in a physics space that there is
that translation that would happen there.
So anyway, we're trying to compute the force and the force of the
spring.
That we're going to apply what we typically talk about saying is Well
there's a coefficient of for the positional part of it, right?
So the coefficient for the positional part and the coefficient for the
positional part is X where we want to go, right?
So it's our, it's our Target position - our current position, right?
And so it's exactly what I drew up here.
Just I had baked out kind of a lot of different things in my head just
because I knew what they were, but you can think of this
Is actually saying, well, I wanted T-Bob, right?
So, my position Target I wanted T-Bob to be 0, right?
I wanted to be right here at zero.
So, my target value is 0, where was I?
Well, I'm at T-Bob, right?
I'm at whatever that value is.
So obviously, this term of my equation PT minus PC, I just computed in
my head, right?
The simple trivial thing, this is 0, this is
T-Bob so it's negative T-Bob, right?
That's why I type that in.
But this is the more formal way of saying it.
The target - the current location.
And then this right here, this CP, that's the tuning value, that's the
value you plug in to say, how stiff, how powerful do you want this
thing to push back towards its Target is right?
But this is an undamped spring and the reason it's an undamped spring
is because look at what it does, it will never actually Hit the Target
and the reason for that is because it behaves exactly like a pendulum
does when it's far away, it pushes very hard to get back towards where
it's trying to get to, but by the time it gets back there, it has
built up so much velocity that it shoots straight through, right?
It has no damping.
And so, what we want to do is we want to also apply a force, a damping
Force out here in another term that will make our velocity be what we
wanted it to be as well.
And in this case, I want the velocity is 0.
I wanted to become to.
I want to come to rest at that.
Right?
So what I'm going to do is add another term here, right?
Which is the coefficient for the velocity and that's going to be
whatever the velocity Target is - whatever the velocity current is
right.
And I know it, my current velocity is and I know what my target is.
My target is 0 and this right here is DT.
Bob.
Okay, so again just like before since it's zero, really what I can say
is it's just - DT Bob is the value I'm looking for and then I can tune
a parameter that helps me.
Get my damping in there.
Okay, so you see it oscillating.
We need to stop that oscillation.
So let's add in that term and you can kind of see right here.
This is my spring equation.
This right here, is that coefficient I was talking about.
And so, if I wanted to make this look more like the actual math that
we talked about, right?
It looks like this.
So there's my Bob Target - Mighty Bob and there's the, the spring
Force.
If I can put it right here, this is our coefficient for the position
of the spring.
There you go.
And now you know I can pilot it's going to exactly
Same like a change until I add in that condition for the velocity.
I don't know what that's going to be, but we'll find out in the
second.
So I'm going to add my CV again.
I want nothing.
I want to come to rest, so I'm going to, I want to come to rest and I
want to take that entity.
DT Bob, which is the velocity because that's what the current value
is.
So they're now I'm going to compile that out and you can see now that
damping for it.
That's exactly what we wanted and you can understand intuitively, why
this works is very kind of interesting.
Very simple equation was very interesting how it works.
So this term, right is the thing that's building up all that velocity
to correct our displacement.
So we have a displacement that's out.
Here, we have a Target, we're trying to get to, let me draw that the
way I drew it before us.
It's not reversed.
So here's where we are right.
Here is
rpe current here is our P Target and we've got this big displacement.
So this term becomes very large when we're out very far away and we
push we get a lot of acceleration to move inward, right?
But as we move closer to our Target, this term becomes much
Smaller.
In fact, eventually, when we hit the target, it will be 0.
So, as we move closer, right?
If you imagine over time here, here's our time and here is that
acceleration from the positional term.
Right.
It's very high you know right here when we're here it's very high and
then as we get closer and closer, right?
It's coming down that term just keeps going down and down, and down,
and down.
And this is, this is really it's linear, so it looks like that.
So that's what's happening here.
Our velocity on the other hand is doing exactly the opposite thing.
If we're just sitting out here doing nothing, sorry out here, doing
nothing, our velocity is 0.
This term is nothing, but as we pick up that speed as we correct,
we're getting it fast.
And faster and faster until somewhere in the middle this term, right?
Is going like this this term becomes the dominant term and start to
correct that philosophy.
So there's less of the acceleration is now pushing us towards our
Target and more is pushing against that sort of income and velocity.
So we speed up and then slow down to hit our Target, right?
And so there's two types of Springs under damped
and overdamped.
And really technically, there's a Third Kind, which is called
critically damped
So when under damp spring is the one we had before, it doesn't have
either.
It had have any damping in that case or it doesn't have sufficient
damping.
Now I actually want an under damped spring, that's what I'm looking
for.
I want a little bit of that wobble, right?
Because that's animation, that's that and right.
But that's not necessarily what you want for every circumstance.
So it's good to know that there's different kinds.
So under damped is what we're going for.
That's what we want.
So I'm happy with her at but there are other kinds like I said over
damp spring is a one that slows.
I'm too much.
So it will always hit its Target.
Exactly 0.
But it will take a long time to get there because there's so it's like
a really strong headwind as the position try is.
You know, it's pushing down as hard as it can.
The that counter velocity Force gets strong really quickly because
it's got a really stiff term.
And so it just kind of slowly gets there.
And then comes to stop and critically damped is right at the, at the
midpoint critically, damped is the one where it will go as fast as it
possibly could have gone to its Target while still stopping exactly on
the Target, right?
So it's perfectly damp.
It like, literally damp snow more than it absolutely had to to
correct, right.
So, those are the different types of spring equations.
You could end up with and they are just statements about these two
variables, right?
And, a critically damped spring is when these two are perfectly
matched.
An under damped spring is, when this value is low compared to this
one, not the magnitude of them, totally, but rather just their effect,
right?
Because again, these are in different spaces.
This is velocity, space, efficient space.
So these aren't going to be equal if they're equal right there.
Going to be.
But point being, it's what their relationship is in the broader scheme
of things.
So if you want a more under damped spring, you're going to reduce this
value.
If you want a more overdamped spring, you're going to drive this value
higher, right?
And if you want to critically damped bring you a trip to solve for it.
It's actually a thing.
You have to do to figure out what those two values should be.
Because it's an exact perfect alignment.
You can't just tweak the values and expect to get there.
I mean, eventually, if you did it long enough, you get to roughly the
correct answer.
But there actually is a correct solve for it that you
I'd do if you really want to but point being now we're getting now,
we're getting somewhere, right?
And I'm going to go ahead and crank up my my time step value back to
the actual time step because I want to see.
Now, roughly where we're at.
I want to see what our what our status is.
That makes sense, right.
And I think I do feel like this is the heads moving a little faster
than I think.
It normally would be, at least at the outset of the game.
You know, this it heads moving at this.
At a speed that I feel like is more indicative of maybe if you were in
a PowerUp scenario.
So I think I do want to just briefly go in for while we're kind of
working on this and tune that down.
Oops.
I want to go ahead and take that head motion and just make that head
motion a little bit sluggish by comparison.
So I'm not sure what it should be, but I'm going to play with it here.
So that's that's more.
I think that's more what I'm looking for.
Okay.
And so then similarly I think I'm also going to slow down the jump a
little bit now that I've, you know, have a slightly sore head motion,
I'm going to go ahead and here and just slow down that that hop right
now we were using a multiplier on the time step of.
So it was a fifth of a second.
It took to do the Hop.
Now it's going to be more like a quarter of a second.
So, I'm not getting that downward motion that I wanted, right?
I want, I want that downward motion as I move the head.
And I think that's, because we were right in the middle that when I
said, what's wrong with my spring.
So we know that we've got to come back to Here.
And Now find out why this isn't happening, right?
Why am I not?
Why am I not getting any any of this application here?
And I don't know, maybe it's not strong enough.
Okay, so that's the problem.
So just wasn't strong enough I guess.
Okay.
Of course, when it's x t, head distance, Tia distance.
I'm not really sure why.
The T had distance isn't something that I can tune back to zero so I
should be able to tune that back towards lower than it is right.
Let me go ahead and see if I can make this a little bit more forgiving
here.
There we go.
Okay.
I'm just leaving this exaggerated.
I can, well, I figure out how far away to make this go.
So, I feel like that's actually pretty close to correct.
So, I think that's okay.
So I'm going to go ahead here and tune this value back to something, a
little less ridiculous.
And so one thing that's a little bit odd.
Well, actually no, I don't know, I guess, it's probably.
Okay.
We're just kind of taking a minute to look at this and see but point
being at starting to feel much nicer to me, right?
This work is starting to pay off, I think, right?
Because now that hop is feeling really good, right?
It's starting to have a little bit of that kinetic Miss to it.
And honestly, the biggest problem now is, are, you know, is starting
to be more like me to start addressing stuff likewise in the head
connected, right.
But we're starting to get a much better.
Feel like a much better kinetic, feel kind of in there for that for
that T-Bob, right?
So that might still be a little much, so I'm going to back off just a
just a hair.
All right, so you can kind of feel how that's going.
Now, you can kind of, you can see roughly what I'm talking about,
right?
So yeah, yeah.
So now what I'd like to do as well, is I would like to be able to, I
want the head to snap to the body when you are not pushing it.
So, when I moving the head around, I want it to be doing what it's
doing here.
But when I Let Go, I want it to snap back to the correct location.
So I want to
Back to to neutral if that makes sense.
And so I want to apply exactly the same sort of what sort of looking
for.
I want to, I want to apply the same Technique.
We just used for the spring there to sort of suck that head back
towards where it should be and I guess I don't need to close.
I always forget that.
I don't have to close the game because we have the Live code editing.
But so what I want to do is kind of apply exactly that same theory
that I just showed you with the spring.
I want that too.
To apply to the head as well.
And so what I'm going to do here is say that the head we're going to
like sort of fuss with the heads movement there in some way.
Now I don't really know we sort of have the body point to the Head.
We don't have the head point back to the body at the moment, which
seems like probably an issue, although this makes sort of get to that
sort of.
This may get to the question that I was asking earlier about whether I
really even want these two to be do separate things or whether I just
want them to be one thing.
And I don't really know yet, which one of those is true, but I'm going
to keep them as separate things for a little bit because I feel like
sometimes, maybe you get spells that disembody your head and your
body, I mean, who knows, right?
Game design stuff.
You sometimes want to throw in ridiculous stuff at various times and
you don't want your whole game to be based on the fact that that's not
happening and then have to hack all around it.
So since they're sort of separately movable things
might as well leave them as two separate entities so that we can
dissociate them ad at a various times if we want to but what that
means if I want to kind of apply a backwards for us to the head here,
I'm going to want to be able to reach into that head and sort of do
operations now.
I think that sort of has some implications for the way we're doing our
energy stuff right now.
Like that maybe means we want to do a physics pass-first where we can
accumulate forced into people and then have them do stuff so that the
body can just reach into the head and do it.
I'm not sure.
But, you know, that's, that's sort of what I'm thinking here.
So, I'm going to look at just doing it just that way.
And the way that I'm going to do that is I'm just going to say, well,
we already have this concept of the body distance, right?
So all I really need.
If I want to do a spring, remember, we sort of had things easy.
When I did the previous spring because we didn't actually have to
compute anything we had T-Bob.
And we had DT Bob, which are the two things we needed, okay?
And these were both scalar values and we already knew what they were.
So if we want to apply the same technique that sort of simple, very,
very simple, basic spring equation.
If we want to apply that basic technique,
All we need to do is figure out a way to produce the position and
velocity terms.
Those differences that we need.
And so you know again if you look at here we don't have to do any work
to get them.
But you know, if you look at what they actually are, it's very simple
PT, minus PC.
It's basically the length.
If we, if these weren't scalars, we just need the length.
You know how far apart they are.
So we can trivially turn a vector equation into a spring equation.
Even though the spring equation is just a scalar equation.
We can trivially turn it into a vector equation by simply making these
lengths.
So previously, you know, if we're doing the force of the spring,
equals the coefficient on the positions times, some scalar Target,
right?
So, this is a position Target - the position current, and then we've
got the coefficient on the velocities.
And we've got the velocity Target - the velocity current.
If this is what we have, four scalar values.
While turning this into a vector equation is really simple.
All we really need to do is say the
the force that we're going to apply, we want to compute is just the
length of whatever these values are.
They can be any arbitrary Vector that we can take the length of their
difference, right?
And then we can do the same thing for the velocity vectors, right?
So now it's a vector equation.
And we have the force of the spring.
So the only question is well, okay, we have a scalar but we need a
vector acceleration, right?
We've got some Forest on a spring.
How do we produce a vector solution that?
Well, we know the spring is always going to act in the opposite
direction of whatever.
This is, you know, whatever this guys doing, right?
So if we want the spring to be still a scalar spring, we can just use
the distance between the two of them to a
Apply it.
And we can break this into two equations if we want to apply it in two
different directions, right.
That's thing.
One we can do thing to we can do is if we want this to be a
non-euclidean spring, right?
Are sorry.
If we wants to be a straight euclidean spring, that doesn't a
component wise spring.
We can do this on each of the of the elements individually as well,
right?
We could do this for X4, y4 Z, but assuming that we want it to be
based on the distance apart and not
The individual, you know, Manhattan distance, effectively, we want to
do it this way.
So if we're going to do that, well the corrective Force that's trying
to correct for position and the corrective Force.
That's trying to correct for velocity.
Those may not be wanting to act in the same direction, right?
And the reason I say that is because if you imagine what's going on
here, let's say that I have an object that's moving in this direction,
okay?
But I want it to be
Going 0 speed, right?
So I'm trying to make it speed 0 and it's supposed to be over here is
the location, it's supposed to get to.
So here's the P Target, right?
It's over here.
The velocity Target is going to be, you know, 000.
well, it's actually write that that
Try to, I try to use a better notation since this is in theory an
educational stream.
So, I've lost the target is 000.
But my velocity right now, right.
My current velocity is definitely not that it's got a pretty heavy x
velocity.
So, it's got, you know, 10 in there or something, right.
But then when I look at what I have to do to correct the position.
Well, the position is way down in y.
So the force that I need to compute, when I compute these values for
the forces, they want to apply in different directions.
This is the
So long, which I would want to apply the forest correct position.
And this is the axis along which I would want to apply the forest to
correct the velocity.
So what I probably want to do, right, is break these into two, there's
a force to correct the position and that equals the coefficient on the
position X, again, the position Target - position current, and if I
turn this into a vector equation, oops, I take that length.
and this gives me a scalar, this
Allure is just going to act along the direction, implied by this
measure, right?
So, I turn this into, okay?
There is a Delta value, right?
There's a Delta position and that Delta position is the position
Target - position thing, right?
This is the difference between them, right?
It's this Vector right here.
That Vector is the vector that I am both going to measure right.
So I'm going to figure out what that Delta p is.
And I'm going to use it to figure out how powerful the spring should
be.
But then it's also going to be how I apply the f p.
So the spring force will actually be Delta peas direction, right times
this this the CP value, right?
If that makes sense.
So how would we compute the direction of Delta P?
Well, if we wanted to compute the direction of Delta P, then we would
take the vector, Delta p and we would divide it by its length, right?
That's what we would be doing.
Straightforward.
Right?
So what my equation would end up being is I want to take this Force.
Here is my Force, right?
And I want to apply this force in this direction.
Make sense.
But this term was already in the equation, right?
So, if I expand this out, what I actually get is, Delta p over the
length of P times c.
P times Delta P.
Well, Delta P.
This is a linear equation.
Delta p is the same value.
So, if I'm dividing my it, then multiplying might as well get rid of
it.
Makes sense, right?
So what you then end up with is like oh in order to apply this actual
spring force, all I'm actually doing here is multiplying my CP by the
difference.
That's it.
so this equation then becomes
actions are right in the same way.
See p times Delta P, right?
And I don't even have to go through that whole length taking process.
So all of this stuff, this whole scalar thing here that we're doing in
scalar, we can actually do it directly in Vector without ever doing
any lengths or even it's separating it into its component form or
anything like that.
It will just work.
So that's pretty cool.
The rest of its again, same thing.
If I wanted to do the the forest for the vector part, I get the same
thing here, right?
Delta V and c v and so I can go ahead and rewrite my vector equation,
the force that I'm going to apply for my spring is a CP times a Delta
p and since these are two vectors I can add them together, right?
And there is my Vector spring equation.
All right.
So, and I suppose I should underscore that punch line there.
So, when we got back here, if you think about well doing it this way,
and doing it this way component wise, they actually work out to be the
same way, if that makes sense, meaning applying it per element because
you are multiplying by the length eventually, anyway, ends up being
the same operation, I don't, that makes any sense, but that's
basically the idea
so if I wanted to do this, to make a force that kind of restores the
head, or pushes the head back towards, where it needs to go, what I
could do is say, well, I know that the head
At the moment, has a DP all this tab directly into it for now.
And I'm going to add into it again, that sort of, DT times the
acceleration to give I'm going to basically set the acceleration of
that dude.
And this is again kind of a hack because I really should be
restructuring Energy System at some point here soon to make these
sorts of things a little bit cleaner.
So this is not really right, but I'm just going to do it for now to
get this part working so that we can end the day in a reasonable
amount of time.
But head DP
DT times whatever our Spring Forest is going to be here.
So this is our like spring velocity or head Spring, right?
And so our head spring is going to be exactly what I typed in before.
So, it's the head position.
We know where the body is.
We want the head to go towards the body.
Like so and we want that to be multiplied by some kind of a
coefficient here.
I don't know what it is.
And then I also want to dampen the velocity and I again I don't know
what that is but I want to take whatever the whatever that velocity is
of the the head at the moment.
And I want to dampen it so whatever that is is going to get subtracted
that make sense, and then we're going to add that head spring directly
in.
So now you can kind of see there is a head spring, its operating, it's
just not particularly forceful.
So, you know, I'm going to crank it up a little bit.
And then I'm gonna play with it.
So now you can see like because there's such a strong spring on me.
I can't really go anywhere, right?
So I kind of have this this sort of very strong pull back spring.
So I would need to sort of tighten up, if you will the see what's
going on here.
I need to to make more forceful.
The other end, the, the actual movement code for the head, right?
If that makes sense.
Cuz that's just too forceful.
Let me see.
I am.
Little.
I wonder how much of that though is also just the fact that I'm, I've
got other kinds of drag and stuff like that in there, but in fact, let
me just see what happens if there's already dragged on the dude.
Let's see what happens.
That just doesn't look right at all.
Something is something is off and I suppose, that's probably just cuz
you know, I'm doing something really ridiculous here, right?
I mean, I don't I have to go look to see even what this is going to do
because I don't know when the head DP gets can, I don't know how the
head deep.
He gets worked with in other parts of the code, but you can see like
how heavy I have to make the spring in order for it to move.
The reason that I'm a little weirded out by that, it's because you can
see how heavy I have to make the spring in order to make it move back
at a reasonable rate.
But then I can't move the head at all at that point, it doesn't make
much sense you know.
It really doesn't.
So I'm going to go ahead and comment this out just for a second.
I want to make sure I didn't mess up something else.
Right.
Because there's the, the normal speed of the head.
So you know I feel like we probably want to go in there and fix that a
little bit because it's kind of, obviously wrong at this point but
what I'm going to do is I'm for you know for the moment I'm just going
to go ahead and play with this a little bit just to get it to a point
that's reasonable, but I think we want to go ahead and fix this.
So, the other thing that I could do here is I can make it so that I
know whether the head is moving, if that makes sense.
So what I could do is I could say, well okay, I'm going to know
whether or not the con hero stuff.
I have this piece of information on the con hero I could say.
Well you know depending on on what the the con hero DDP is for my
particular hero.
I will either apply or not.
I that drag Force based on that, right?
And that, you know, that would probably be another way around, so it
was maybe the best way around it so that the spring Force, so the head
Springs back, doesn't the head spring doesn't affect the rest of the
rest of the situation.
And again, I what I really want to do, I think is make it so that this
guy actually knows.
In fact, I could just do that and he actually seeks back towards the
body when he when he's not in that mode.
So maybe let me
Let me maybe just do it that way.
So in here, what I'm going to do is say well, okay, you know, we've
got this sort of thing and I'm going to set the D DP equal to this
this head spring value, right?
When the GDP is is not a thing.
So like if GDP,
When no one's applying any force on the controller or maybe, when
there's a very little force on the controller.
So, when this is less, you know, then some nominal value
Then we will apply the spring.
I don't know what the value should be though.
So that makes some sense.
And so then really all we need to do here is we just need a way of
making that that body value be exposed to us and the way that we would
do that is the same way that we did it here, right?
So you can see that we sort of do this system entity part here where
we grab out the head course I'm going to be called Head.
We should probably rename those anyway.
So you know, here we are in this piece of code and we
say, okay, if
If we actually got a valid body out of this, you know, go ahead and
compute it.
And that'll add that restorative force.
And so now, what we would need to do is when we add a hero or guess,
it's a bad player,
We need to have them both Point towards each other.
So it would look, you know, we need to have the heads low Sim had a
hit on next point back to the body and vice versa.
So they're kind of like pointing at each other and they know who's
who.
So you can see that it's not doing any restoration right now, that's
because this world was already created and doesn't have that part of
it.
And now, so if we rerun it in theory, now we should get that
restorative Force.
oh my
Huh.
That's of course we don't have that velocity damping.
So that's an under damp spring, but it's way cooler when it has a
facing direction to it.
Right.
All right, so last things last.
Let me go ahead and finish that up.
Head P.
So, yeah.
Let's go in here and
And see.
So here's our GDP it doesn't have any notion of I guess it gets his
part, it's got dragged on it and I guess the question is the drag is
not enough.
Maybe and I suppose, what we could do is add more drag here because
maybe we want a certain amount of drag built a different drag for our
general motion or not.
But so, what I'm going to do here is say, like, okay, I want sort of a
negative force to be applied.
I don't know how much, but for whatever the end of these DP is at the
moment, we're going to counteract that in this mode, only, right?
when we get down there, you know, we kind of got this nasty problem of
that oscillation
like that's probably good enough and we just I would say we probably
want to go fix the way the facing Direction stuff works at the moment
because
I think motion wise, that's probably correct.
Yeah.
Motion wiser think that's probably correct.
And there's another thing that I want to do two, which is, I want to,
I want the motion to be biased along the Cardinals.
So the other thing that I would want to do here is really, I want this
thing to be per element.
So you know what, I really want to do here is say something more like,
you know element or equal 0, you know, e is less than 3 + + e.
And I really want to do this.
Check
To see whether you're applying force in a particular direction.
If you're applying force in that direction, I don't recenter the head
only along that axis.
So, essentially what I'm saying is, you know, if you've got the head
and you've got the body, if the head gets a little off to the side,
but then you're pushing upwards and you're moving the head.
This way, I want to suck the head back over here.
If you're not still trying to move laterally and the same goes for
this way.
So I always want the head to be centered roughly on the body.
I want the spring to restore the
Head back to the center of the body.
I always want that to happen.
If you're not moving in that direction.
So rather than do the spring Vector wise, you know, I didn't think of
this before, but rather than doing it as a single Vector.
What I actually think I want is something more, you know, like like
this and actually remember how we access elements is it just .e.
I'm not sure.
Is that how we do it?
Yeah.
So I'm going to take a look at that just real quick because that's
just another thing that I kind of wanted their that makes sense.
I did something bad.
Not sure what.
That's very different than what we had before.
I don't feel like it should have been if D DP e is less than 0.1 then
apply.
The body - the entity in that, just whatever that direction is.
and then,
Again, whatever that.
Velocity is.
Why does that not work?
I color me confused about that because that should be fine, right?
Here's my Baseline.
Oh, was that a length squared that I did there?
That might have something to do with it?
So let's see if it's less than some very small value.
Let's say,
No.
How about just if
oh,
Awesome.
Yeah.
How about you?
Take the absolute value of that?
That was stupid.
Okay.
So if we take the absolute value this, we want to know whether the any
given individual component has gone more than a certain amount.
Not sure what that amount should be.
Still feels wrong.
What did I mess up?
This is going to drive me nuts.
Because that's like the same equation we had, right?
I just have no idea.
I'm like, literally clueless, I think this is what happens.
Maybe you get too old.
You get confused because I'm taking a look at that.
I mean, let's just make it a ridiculous value.
I mean, that should not be applying at all.
I mean, how can this value?
Even how could it possibly be less than that?
I'm going to step into the burger is driving me insane.
It's driving me, insane people.
It's driving me insane.
This is one of those ones where you know you're staring directly at
it, right?
It's like, duh.
But your brain is just sort of mushy at this point and you're not sure
what it.
What is actually going on.
Your like, I don't know what's happening, what is even math?
I don't know.
Just math exist, probably not.
So,
I just feel like I don't want to step into it in the butter until I
actually have a feeling about what is actually wrong with it, because
it doesn't make sense to me.
I'm going to go ahead and just verify to myself.
Good.
I can do either of these.
So, there's my F1.
Here's my DDP, right?
That's the GDP value.
I'm going to use and I'm going to say if I think what I did is like
length squared, right?
If the length rate of GDP is less than 0.1 F or something.
I don't even know if I is what will return, it just think just to make
sure it works.
Then we just did this, right?
I mean this is all, it was just the same exact thing.
It just I didn't do right, I didn't do the components so there it is.
Working just fine.
Right.
So now the question is, if I switch to doing the exact same thing /
component, so I'm going to do it for 0 1 and 2.
I want to do exactly the same equation.
So for any given scalar value, I want to take the square of whatever
it is.
So whatever that element is DD PE and I'm going to say if it's less
than same value, right?
Then I want to take DDP of just that one component.
I want to set it equal to the scalar version, right?
Which is just the component.
Minus the component, it's going to be pushing in the direction towards
the body, which is what we want.
And then we're going to negate that velocity Vector as well.
And again, putting that it's just component wise so it's just whatever
the component is.
That's all we're doing.
How is that not working?
So does do, does everyone else know why it's not working?
And it's only me
Hmm.
Well, I guess I'll have to leave it till tomorrow.
That's very unsatisfying but I'm out of time.
You know what?
I wonder if it's just because of the drag that gets applied
afterwards.
I think that is what it is.
Because that drag force that gets applied in the movement routines,
right?
I could see that being the case cuz that
I know exactly what it is.
It's because I'm passing this to the movement routine, which
normalizes the vector, that's what's going on.
Yes, and that's just because I was hacking that together, right, once
this goes into the movement routine, it's going to normalize the
vector.
So the normalized vector is going to have a totally different effect.
So what I really want to do is not use this GDP at all, right?
I actually just want to say
You know.
There's some other one here.
That I'm going to create and then when I'm done, I'm going to add that
in just straight away, right?
So I've got that DDP and I'm going to go ahead and say like entity,
you know, DP plus equals DT times GDP to or something like this,
right?
Yeah.
So that was the entirety of the problem.
Make sense.
All right.
We got to do a bunch of work here, but we're starting to get pretty
respectable, right?
This is, this is going to be pretty cool.
I can already feel like this is actually going to be good.
So I'm glad about that because it was going to feel bad.
That would be bad.
Let's see the other day in Janeiro, like, in the New Movement, to
Crypt of the necrodancer.
I like that game and see where they're coming from, but handmade hero
already looks like, it feels so much sweeter to play.
Yeah, I think it'll probably feel pretty sweet to play this game.
It's like, I feel like the design is pretty unusual and I feel like as
I'm playing with getting this working here I can already feel like
it's going to be pretty awesome to move, the guy around and do stuff.
So
I've probably missed it.
But what exactly, prompted, switching the hero movement from analog
ruling to digital tile-based wiggle hopping?
It's the design of the game.
So I have the design now and I'm like, doing it specific to the
design.
So the design requires, it's got to be towel-lined.
And to be more clear, it's not tile aligned.
I happen to set up a grid here because I think most screens or a fair,
number of the screens are going to be grid-like, but actually, it's
just, it's fixed point.
So we could arrange those points in screen.
Anyway, we want, but you, you have to hop between points is the
important part.
See pots, doesn't math exist.
Who knows in DD is the body.
Always going to move on a fixed grid, not necessarily a grid.
But always from point to point the head can move the head gets to move
sort of freely but the body has to be on the closest whatever point
and the level generation will put down the points in specific patterns
and you have to hop through the points.
Can we get a keyboard cam?
No.
Lou Melon 55 with a player.
Be able to see the points in the design.
Yes.
I mean
Well, I mean, let me put it this way.
The art will make it very clear where the standing places are.
Unless there's a particular reason in that area for you to not know.
SEL de is the body.
Going to lean towards a header is going to stay detached.
It will lean.
So as you move will like sort of stretch it, you know, will like
stretch it kind of this way.
It's going to be a little hard, like it's a little bit tough and this
is this is true.
Anytime you do animation and games, you kind of always have to fight
the fact that the animation doesn't look as good because you don't
necessarily know exactly what the player is doing, right.
You don't know if they're gonna like go this way and stop or what's
going to happen.
So the degree to which it can kind of go down, it's going to fight.
I need to stretch to detach the head so it's definitely going to be
the case that it's a little bit.
That it's a little bit less good-looking than it would be if we didn't
care about the feel but the most important thing is that the head
feels good to control.
And so that's kind of going to happen.
In DD.
Shouldn't the head?
Always draw on top of the cape?
That's RZ problem.
So right now, we have to go do this.
We can probably do this very soon right now.
All three of these guys are actually at the same Z which is messed up
to a large extent.
And and so we've got a bunch of work to do with this or are sorting
because we now we didn't have sorting in the renderer back when we
made this stuff and we do now.
So we need to go actually have that stuff work properly.
But but like right now
I can see that it's not at all.
What you would want in the art assets, the way that we've got it,
in here is is totally bogus, unfortunately,
So here is like the Sprite so you can see like the positioning of them
is totally like wrong.
You want them to be just where they are and then in the game, we move
them up so you can tell that it's like a higher thing right now.
It doesn't know that because if they're actually at the same point and
then they're displaced with inside the bitmap, which is not what we
actually wanted.
So,
In DD.
No sorry, Trevor new.
Twill other entities.
Only travel on these points to or can they move freely?
So, it's sort of both.
Like, I think for the most part things move on the points, but there's
definitely a couple things that are like these.
Maybe don't have to, some of that will depend on, what I, what happens
when I put it in and we'll see.
But definitely a fair number of the entities, have to still move on
the point.
So we will have to write some code that moves.
Is that has a eyes that move along the ground?
Ed or loose Network because doesn't have to actually be a grid.
So they'll have to kind of path find around on it.
Is there a name for this technique of blending canned, and simulated
animations.
Is it a common thing allowed in animation 3D packages?
I guess I don't know if there's a name for it but it is the answer as
to whether or not it's allowed in animation 3D packages.
The answer is sort of yes and no.
Animators will often write expressions that control elements of like a
bone system.
To basically turn it, like not even a bone system, but like, a
hierarchical system to turn it into something that sort of works that
way, but it has to be a parameter of T directly, so it can't really
use physical simulation like we've got here.
and so, in order to actually do what we did where it's based on the
physics of the situation,
the support for it in animation, packages is pretty janky because they
physics is always really at odds.
With the way these animation packages are, were written, originally
and so it's always kind of shoehorned in and you kind of have to do
these like baked procedures and stuff to like say Okay, run through
the animation from the beginning.
Do the simulation part bake that into a channel and now use the
channel.
So it's like
The answer is yes, it's common.
Yes you can do it in packages.
Is it anywhere near as easy as what we just did know which is kind of
terrifying but you know that that depends on the package to a certain
extent.
So
You know, some packages, there's easier than others to do if you're
trying to do a mixed thing.
Where you've got certain parameters of the model are being controlled
by a physical element, as opposed to, you know, an animation timeline.
Messy old.
The why would I use an animation package?
Instead of doing what you just did and whatever you will do?
Well, the reason for that is, I mean, first of all, part of the answer
is.
Well if you're an indie developer or you're a one-man shop, like we
sort of are on handmade hero, right?
Like handmade hero basically, we've got art coming from youngji and so
we don't have to do a lot of painting and stuff so that's pretty.
Great.
But pretty much everything else we have to do ourselves for the most
part.
So if you're in that position, you know, you you would do a lot of it
like this, and you would try to
Demise the amount that you would need things to be sort of more
hand-animated eat, right?
But if you are working with some talented animators, well, you know,
they are trained to be able to sort of place timelines and make sort
of more elaborate sorts of animations that happen, and it can be very
difficult to hand code in animation.
I mean, trying to give a good example but, you know, let's say you are
Thinking of, you know, Call of Duty or something, right.
And you've got this, you know, we've got this Kevin Spacey character,
and you're doing, you know, whatever.
You're not going to code that physically, it's not even plausible, how
you would do that, right?
You're going to use motion capture, you're going to have animators who
sit there and tweak the values and get it right or whatever.
There's just a ton of data that has come in and all of its subjective.
It's not physically simulated really, it's about muscle movements and
all these sorts of human things.
So, once you cross a threshold from a visceral physical sort of
Animation style into something that's more about acting, that's more
about those are things.
It's not feasible to hand code,
All the reactive versions of these necessarily, right?
It's just too much and we don't even necessarily know how sometimes to
do those things.
So usually the answer is, you know, why wouldn't you do this?
Well, for a game, like a maid here?
Oh, you probably would, I mean, I think physically animations kind of
a good way to go for this because it's going to be very kind of
dynamic and interesting, but that's because there's not a lot of
animated pieces.
There's not a lot of like facial animations or not.
There's not a lot of these things that involved in putting tons of
data.
And so I think when you cross that threshold,
Then you, that's why you need to start looking at how you get tools,
where animators can basically input subjective, non-physical sequences
that you can then make use of in other ways.
At revenue.
Is there any plan for eventual addition of music?
Music is basically done.
I mean, we only have a little bit more work to do we you can probably
even turn it back on the current build.
You know, we've got a music file and I plays so all will be doing for
music is basically like adding the ability to kind of fade in and out
between different types of music, depending on the area.
So that, you know, when you move from one place to another,
You'll change what music you get.
So,
Ham-handed question, could you use neural networks and make something
like Boston Dynamics is Big Dog?
You know, I'll be honest with you, I don't know anything about what
the controllers were on Big Dog.
They didn't used to use neural networks like, because Boston Dynamics
is was originally.
Most of their robotic algorithms are based on raber, Hopper code,
which is not a neural.
Work.
So I didn't I don't know what big dog is or whether there's any neural
networks in it or not, but regardless, I just have no perspective on
that.
I don't, I haven't read up on any of that stuff so I have no idea what
they do for that and I don't know if they use them.
I don't know if they didn't use them.
If you could use them, I have no idea because I really just don't know
what Boston Dynamics is.
Doing these days when they were doing Hoppers, there's no neural
network required.
So most of their robots
Generally did not need any neural networks.
They just balance using standard balance algorithms from Raber's
thesis and further.
Right?
But you know, who knows what they do?
Now, I've no idea.
so,
All right, so I think we're good.
I'm going to close it up.
Okay, I should probably save this as well.
Thank you everyone for joining me, for another episode of handmade
here.
It's been a pleasure coding with you as always and it's kind of fun to
see our little hero.
Fellow starting to hop around in a couple more days.
We'll probably have some good controls sort of finished for our guy
here, which is kind of good.
It's something we can start to base the feel on and make sure that
everything is kind of doing good.
As we kind of go in there and plus as we sort of, get a little further
down that path.
Maybe we'll, you know, Implement an enemy and will Implement a couple
things for real and get them kind of working that will allow us to.
Look at the end of the
And go through and do a pass on that, to get that into a relatively
good shape, because we don't really have one right now.
And what's in there, it's kind of just from our original Explorations,
so we're in pretty good shape.
I'm pretty happy about it and it's looking kind of nice, so that's
good.
And I was pretty psyched at how the movement was.
Starting to feel.
It needs a lot of work, certainly like I'm going to but I want to kind
of get it so that it's animating properly first and then tweak that
feel a little bit more after that.
So I believe tomorrow is Thursday and we are not
Streaming tomorrow.
So it is going to be Friday's the next stream, until then, of course,
if you want to follow along with series at home, you can always
pre-order it the game on handmade here a.org and it comes to the
source code.
So you can play around with it at home.
You can go to the forums if you want to ask questions, you can click
on the patreon page.
We want to support our video series, which is always available free of
charge to everyone.
You can go to our schedule about to find out when we're streaming's.
If you have a question about
I just said if we're on tomorrow not which we're not, you can go there
and that will tell you.
And finally, we have a wonderful episode guide maintained by our very
own me blow from the chat.
If you want to catch up with past videos in the series, it's all
annotated and you can find stuff pretty easily and it's pretty cool.
So check that out.
When you get a chance that is about it for now until tomorrow.
Well, I guess I'm still Friday.
Have fun programming and I'll see you on the
Annette take it easy, everyone.