Hello everyone, and welcome to another episode of handmade hero.
This is the show where we code a complete game live on stream on
Twitch.
No engines, no libraries, we do everything from the very basic
rendering code in a game all the way up to the sort of high-level AI
code and everything in between and right now we are doing something
kind of whimsical if I may say so myself, which is we are making our
own General
Allocator, and I guess more to the point we made one yesterday, but we
did not have time to really run it or debug it.
So we kind of just put it in place and haven't really gotten it, you
know, we haven't even verify that it's even working and it is also
certainly not efficient at what it does in any way.
And so today, what we're going to be doing is taking a look at that
general-purpose allocator and egg.
You know, debugging it.
So getting it to a working State and then be may be thinking about it
looking at a little bit.
And seeing, if there's maybe some things we might,
Might want to do to make it more efficient at what it does.
Because well, I guess we haven't talked about it yet, but I'll talk a
little bit on the Blackboard later today after we do the debugging
part about, you know, what are the things about this general purpose
allocator, as we have written it that aren't so great.
Right.
So since we're coding, I would like to remind everyone who has
pre-ordered the game on him here to org.
If they would like to follow along today is day 161.
So you want to unzip day, 160s source code into a directory and that
will allow you to start exactly where I am starting right now.
So if I go ahead and go into the code base, you will remember that?
It's sort of, we did run it briefly yesterday and
Sort of worked, but it sort of didn't, like, I felt like there, you
know, it was not immediately crashing or anything like this, but it
definitely got into an interesting State there.
You can see that kind of flickering which suggests to me that, I mean,
that could be theoretically correct depending on the exact parameters
system, but it seems unlikely.
So I suspect that that indicates that it is unable to like actually
release memory when it needs to or something like this.
And so my my assumption is
But there's at least one bucket that's my assumption.
I don't know for sure but that's my assumption but it's not a
catastrophic bug in terms of like crashing but there is something bad
going on is my is my feeling that's just just my gut instinct based on
what that pattern was because yes we are running in a restricted
memory scenario.
So obviously we could crank the memory that was allowed to use up and
that blinking would go away, but that may just be masking an actual
problem.
So I would rather take this opportunity to actually go verify.
What's going on?
I assume.
We'll
Find something happening in correctly.
And when we fix it the blinking will become significantly less severe.
That is my assumption but I of course
Be wrong.
All right, so I decided that I liked this strategy where we were going
to write our own general-purpose, Alcatraz, feeling good about it
yesterday.
So what I'm going to do before anything else?
Excuse me.
Is I'm also going to start pulling this stuff out here like evict
assets as necessary.
Is not really going to be a thing anymore, right?
And total memory used versus Target memory, used is not really
necessary anymore, either, because now we just know how much memory we
have, because we just have memory blocks.
And when we're out of those blocks, we know we need to free something,
right?
That's the stuff that's going on here.
So I'm going to start by just simplifying things down a little bit.
I want to get rid of some of this code because it doesn't need to be
there.
It's just going to confuse us if it's sitting around, right?
So I'm going to go ahead and say, Target memory used and total memory
used.
I think those can just go ahead and go away, right?
Total, memory used and
Yeah, I'll just go ahead and here and say, get rid of that, get rid of
that fact.
I'll just let the compiler tell me where that's happening.
The big deficits as necessary is no longer a thing at all.
Don't have these anymore.
So I think that's good.
Okay, so now that we've gotten rid of those, let's go back and start
focusing on the actual stuff that we need to do here.
So we've got release asset memory.
We're going to say that now release asset memory does this.
Oh, well, there's our problem right there.
We just weren't actually done there.
We don't actually remerge our memory blocks together, so that's, that
would do it right there.
So maybe we don't have a bug.
Maybe we just weren't done yet.
Totally, theoretically possible.
So, let's take a look down here, right?
We're going to get rid of this.
There we go.
Okay.
So that's all good and evict asset.
Now, is something that we could actually just put directly in line, we
don't actually need a call for a victim assets because there's only
one place that evicting assets could actually happen.
So I'm going to go ahead and just drop that directly into here, right?
So to Victor assets, going to be this
Right?
And I think that might even just compile as it is, let's take a look
here.
Yep.
So, evict asset now is just a thing and release asset memory.
I guess that's only one place where that happens as well.
Now, I don't know if a choir, if releasing the asset memory is
actually, I think, I think we'll be okay with this.
So, I think I'm going to also go ahead and and drop that in here.
So we're really just talking about
Kicking this thing almost be like, just this one little nice, tiny
little function.
That's going to do the entire
Stuff.
And we can just look at it in one piece, and it should be relatively
easy to understand and I think that'll be good.
So, let's take a look.
Here, we've got the asset block, we want to change the flags on the
asset block.
And so, where is that memory coming from?
That memory is coming from this asset Arrow header, right?
So we're basically talking about about this like us, wait.
We're calling that.
How is that?
Asset header.
Let me think about this for a second, so I guess that's true because
the first thing in the asset is the header, so that would actually be,
that would actually be correct.
I guess you move it back from the header.
I'm off.
You got.
So that's all good.
So let's take a look and see if that'll still works.
And by works.
I mean, it still has the flashing obviously, right?
But that's fine.
Okay.
So I would suggest that possibly are flashing is, is actually just due
to the fact that we no longer recombine our memory blocks.
Which means eventually, they'll all the memory blocks will end up
being very small and they'll never be able to recombine and so large
assets won't be able to be loaded or things like this.
although it doesn't seem like that would produce the effect we're
seeing so maybe that really it doesn't have much to do with it, but
I feel like before we start debugging anything to say the least, we
should actually finish implementing it because it's going to be pretty
hard to debug the thing.
If it's actually not working the way it's supposed to work because we
haven't actually implemented a thing that it's actually supposed to
do.
Okay, so when we free the asset block right now, we can actually do
this thing that I was saying before where we don't have to hunt
anymore for the blocks or the block can actually come up here.
You can do if block and then we come down here and we actually create
this, this we actually free up the block.
Now that block is the one that we would be using or checking to see if
that block actually was used.
Because remember I said yesterday, I was like, well, we don't really
need to find the block more than once.
We can just say can you find any block for this and if you
Find a block for this right?
Then we're going to go free something so that we can try to make room
when we free that, something the only block that could now possibly
hold our thing.
Because we've looked at all the blocks before and found nothing.
So, the only block, the could now be big enough to hold the thing that
we want to put in there is the one that we operated on, because that's
the only one that could have expanded, right?
So when we free it, we do this, we say, okay, we Mark that is used.
And now what we need to do is we need to look at the blocks on either
side of it to see whether those blocks.
It'd be merged into this block, right?
So what we need to do is say, alright, let's look at the Block before
us and if the block before us works, then we'll merge.
And then look at the black behind us and the block behind, I'm sorry
the block after us and if that works will merge.
So what we want to do is like merge if possible, Right?
We want to do something like this where we say.
All right, Murr.
If possible the assets passing that just so it knows what the Sentinel
is, right?
I want to merge if possible the blocks previous and this block, right?
And then I'm going to expect that to return to me, you know, which
whatever it ended up doing.
So, either return, this block the block, that's the sort of the, the
pivot block and, and
You know what?
No, I mean, I'm not gonna do that.
I'm going to have it returned.
I'm going to have it return whether it merged or not, right?
So if it didn't merge block is still correct if it did merge.
Then the block previous is actually going to be the one because that's
the start, that's at the head, right?
So we'd do this, right?
And then after that's done,
We would do the exact same thing with block next, right?
So we'd say merge block and block next.
And in this case, we don't actually care.
If the merge succeeded, because if the merge succeeded, if the merge
didn't succeed, then block is still the block we're looking at.
If the birds did succeed, then block has just grown to Encompass the
next one.
And so either way, it's fine, right?
So now we need to do is Implement merge if possible and you know,
basically merge if possible will return whether or not it was able to
merge and if it can merge, it'll do that merge.
So we have these blocks right, these asset memory blocks.
And so will basically say we have asset memory block first and asset
member block s think of how I'll name them.
And the reason I'm aiming that way is because there is an implication
here that says like we're basically saying they have to be contiguous.
So first comes first and second come second in memory space so we're
going to have to look to make sure that those those in fact do line up
right now.
We know that they always will actually so I suppose that's something
we could even assert on but basically what we need to check is if
First is not equal to memory Sentinel, right?
We need to make sure that none of these are the Sentinel because you
can't merge with the Sentinel.
It's a fake thing in the list, right?
And S is not equal to assets memory Sentinel, right?
So assuming that we actually that these are actual legitimate blocks
that could in theory merge, right?
So neither of them is the Sentinel their actual blocks.
Then what we need to do is we need to see if they're both free, right?
So we need to take a look at the flags.
We need to say, if first flags, and asset memory used, right,
I guess we'd say that if not, that and not second asset memory used.
So if neither one is used, then we could merge them, right?
I guess.
We'll put a result up here.
False return false.
So and then we'll talk to true if we can merge them, right?
So if the first and second blocks are both not used
Then we need to check if they are contiguous.
Now, if we only had one big block of memory, they would always be
contiguous and we just could merge them.
But remember we want to support in case of 32 bit Windows, the
possibility that the asset system has been given multiple disparate
chunks of memory to manage.
That may not be contiguous in address space and virtual address space.
So we don't want to assume that these two blocks of memory actually
Adjacency.
So we want to check to make sure that they are actually that the size
is actually line up, right?
So what we want to do is say okay if we were to take the, we want to
basically compute where the second block would be expected, second
kind of thing, right?
We want to compute where that would be and see whether ends up
equaling the actual second block, right?
We want to do something like this, right?
So, see if
The two pointers actually line up.
So, where would we expect the second block to be if it actually
followed the first block, right?
Well, if we take the first block and we add the size of the asset
memory block header, right?
And then we add the size that the of the actual, you know, that that
memory like actually contains right then that should get us to the
very next position that could actually be, you know, where the header
for the second block, should actually be right.
And so, if that occurs, we should we would then check, you know,
whether that coincides if it does coincide, then we know that we can
merge these blocks together.
And so what we want to do there is we want to remove that.
Oops, it's not good.
We want to remove.
Do we even ever have that?
I've tried.
I think we want to remove the memory.
Header.
Let's see.
Remove asset header from list.
We want to, we want to do this, right?
Where does that get
Old anywhere.
That's the wrong one.
That's not what I want.
We've got two linked lists.
I want the asset memory block.
Does that just insert block have a?
It doesn't.
So we don't have the concept of removing the block at the moment.
We only have the concept of inserting it, right?
Yeah, that looks like the case, so if that's the case, we have to
actually do it ourselves, right?
So we have to actually go in here and emerged as possible, we have to
remove the second one.
So the next previous is going to
Pointing to the previous, right?
And the previous next is going to be pointing to the next.
So we just have to remove it from the list.
So it's out of there and now we just take it sighs, we just obliterate
like basically just say, you know what, you're done, sorry friend, and
our size is now going to be, you know, encompassing you as well,
right?
So it's basically the size of a header, which is, we're eating up the
asset member of Lok header and then we're eating up, the total size.
As of the second block, right?
And at that point, the result is true.
Meaning we did merge the two and that's it.
Right.
That's all we really need to do and then we're all good and now we
just have to actually well we have to actually debug things.
That's a little bit odd.
Ah, right.
So there is one other thing we need to do there.
So, in this case, we are assuming that after the merge, we have a
particular block that we need to check.
We need to actually check to see if the block.
Yeah, we have to actually check to see if this is true now because it
might not be true, right?
It might not be true at all.
So really what we want to do is say if there's a block and the size
would fit this thing.
So if there's a block and the size would fit this thing, it's no
longer an assertion, it's a check because after the merge, it still
might not be big enough.
Like the thing, we free may not actually fit the thing that we're
trying to fit, right?
So we still have to do that.
Yeah, let's try that again.
So yeah, I mean it's a little early to declare Victory but I feel like
our general purpose allocator is now General purposely allocating and
it's using a very constrained amount of memory and it's just paging in
the assets as necessary.
And that's why we're getting some blinking here.
We're not even giving it enough memory to really keep any of these
things, but yeah.
That's it.
I mean it's Saturday streaming properly all the bitmaps are on there
on, you know, no problems.
It's only using that fixed memory block, right?
We never give it any more memory.
Not bad, right guys?
I mean that's pretty good.
So let's take a look here.
If we go into their.
Oh, you know what?
Somebody mentioned this on the forums.
Other day, when I was doing a search and replace, we never deleted.
We push the asset counter.
When we deleted the slaughter, a we did a search and replace the ended
up.
This used to be assets.
Lots right?
And we need it.
So I've been meaning to remove that that's on my little list of things
here, there's also another one that that Martin's pointed out that I
should take care of it's on my list but if I don't need to do it right
now.
So yeah so if you know just to recap now what we do is this one push
sighs here that's it.
The asset system will never use anymore memory other than for loading
assets other than this
whatever the size is, right?
That's it.
So the whole game would run just fine.
Now actually it might just be very Blinky because they're just not
giving it a hardly any memory.
But even as it is right now, it would run just fine because it'll
never use anymore than exactly what we just gave it.
It'll never use more than 4 MB to keep its asset pages in.
So that's pretty sweet.
I feel like that's kind of awesome.
Right?
That seems pretty darn great to me.
Now the thing that I don't know, right?
And it's like I said I was going to say about things that we might
want to, you know, how are we going to?
What are the problems with this?
I guess basically is one question, right?
And the thing that I wanted to mention
On the Blackboard is if I'm just going to summarize sort of the way
that our scheme is working at the moment, I'm going to kind of give
you what the basic idea is.
And then I'm going to explain why, you know, maybe that's not quite
the best possible situation, right?
So what's going on currently is we have a you know, series of blocks
of memory.
And these things get filled up right in various ways, who knows how
not super important.
But as these things, get filled up, we end up in a situation where
each individual, you know, each individual portion here is part of a
linked list, right?
So these link, there's like a linked list running through this entire
thing, right.
So the problem that I foresee and the reason why I say that this is
not a particularly good general purpose allocator at this point,
right?
Is not because there's really all that much of a problem with how it
is allocating because I think we probably will be able to give the
asset system enough memory, that it might not be a huge deal.
The fact that it's not thinking about fragmentation and particularly
smart ways or anything.
I don't know that that's actually going to be a problem, you know?
Maybe it would be, maybe it wouldn't be hard to say.
The thing that I'm more foresee, being a problem is the length of this
linked list, right?
So what I imagined Happening Here is that this linked list is
potentially going to get very large, right?
So let's say we have, you know, 4,000
Loaded.
Well, that could be as many as 8,000 links in the linked list, right?
So that means that every time we go to allocate some additional memory
like when we go to
Load an asset, which we're going to do a few times a frame, right?
We're going to load.
You know, we're going to issue loads 456 assets of frame, maybe maybe
more, right.
It's potentially having to Loop over something on the order of
thousands of links, right?
In order to find where it's going to put this thing.
And that just doesn't seem like maybe it's gonna hold up, right?
And so, what we probably would need to do is introduce a faster
search.
Model on top of this thing.
The doubly linked list is great for merging, right?
Because the merging it can do.
You saw how quick the merge happened, right?
The merge can just do it in one Fell Swoop.
If I free that, you know, if I free this block, it just looks at this
block and this block and merges if necessary and it's done.
So it's the merge is just instant, right?
It's not a problem at all.
Never going to be a problem but what is not instant is that op is, you
know, it's this code right here.
It's
Beth.
This is the problem.
Right.
And so what we would want to do, if we were going to improve this
memory allocator which maybe we don't want to do now because maybe
that's premature me.
What we want to do is get to the point where we've got 8,000
allocations, see that it is slow gather some metrics on it and then
prove it then which is I think probably what I will argue for because
optimizing it now is kind of data free.
But what I foresee happening is we get to that point and this function
starts to show up on the profile, right?
When we're like, why is the game slow suddenly find block for size
becomes a thing that we're seeing?
Right?
One show the time, 5% of time, 10% of time, 20% time it starts to
creep up.
As we start saying, hey, let's run the game with a 4, MB 4 GB
footprint and let it load a ton of assets in there and blob up, right?
That's what I've received the problem being
And so I think, you know, if I may, I think we're going to have a
thing that's here which is like this knee probably will need to be
accelerated.
In the future.
As the asset count.
Resident asset.
Count grows.
And so yeah.
Are we going to see that now?
Absolutely not because you have to remember the number of assets we
have in the game right now is like 30 or something, right?
So the chances that we're
We're going to see a meaningful performance hit from somebody having
to iterate over a 60 links or something like this is right, totally
not going to happen.
So yeah, we don't really have any way of really knowing what kind of
impact this is going to have on our performance at this point but down
the line.
That is just something to be aware of.
So, I would say, yeah, you know, do we want to do that now?
Probably not.
It seems a little bit premature, so I would say, maybe let's look at
some other things, a couple other things, first, and we could even
just move on from out assets at this point, in to debug code, probably
or something like that.
Because honestly, like that went a lot faster than I thought.
It was going to go to do the sort of minimal stupid up.
Joe purpose allocator.
It was like two days or something, I don't even know.
It was very, very short and so I guess general-purpose alkanes just
aren't that hard if you don't optimize them is the lesson we've
learned.
So yeah, so I would say maybe we'll push that to the time when it
actually shows up on the profile so that we can do intelligent
optimization, instead of, you know, speculative optimization which is
usually not a very good idea because then you tend to optimize for
stuff, that is not the truth if you're not optimizing for
Case that you actually care about.
And so maybe, we'll just save the couple days of work that we may have
done on an optimization Bank.
Those and re hit those again in six, seven months, when we're running
around the game and noticing on a profile, but that's causing us a
problem, right?
In the meantime, I did want to point out something that Martin's
mentioned on the forums thats true.
Something that's not great.
Which is actually, I'd written this code thinking that things are
going to work one way but in truth, they don't actually work that way.
And so we do have a thing.
We want to check here.
And that is that while our era system is pretty good in that, you can
just use this platform.
No file errors, thing to handle this situation with the file handle,
we do have a slight problem, which is that it's possible for open next
file to fail completely because it's a allocation based thing.
So, the platform layer can't actually guarantee that you actually get
Handle back, right?
Because if you remember how this worked, if you take a look at at open
next file,
it needs to do a virtual a lock here, right?
It needs to, to do a virtual out to even get that file handle back.
And unfortunately, that means that the no errors thing doesn't isn't
going to fly, right?
Because this may be null and then none of this stuff would work,
right?
So, what I'd like to do is change the behavior of this slightly.
To make it conform to what I wanted it to do, which I did not do a
very good job of doing.
This time and that is that I would prefer to actually go to a
structure that looks more like this, right where we're actually going
to get a something a little bit different.
Okay.
And this is how I think I typed it in originally.
But yeah.
So what I'd like to do here is say that we're going to store a void
pointer out to the platform specific portion.
And the reason I'm going to do that is because now I can force the
important part which is the error check and the file count, which are
actually always used in the outer / part of the code.
I force those two always actually exist and be correct.
And this can be null, but I know that the other part can never be
wrong.
Right.
And so, what I do then is, instead of everywhere, using a file handle
pointer, I actually just use a file handle stored directly.
Does that make sense?
And so now, when we do these, we know that we'll always have that one
part of it and we never have to worry about things.
Going sour separately.
So if I go in here and change array, how that's going just change
these
Two handles.
So that you're actually passing them kind of bye-bye value rather than
by a pointer to what they are, that takes care of things for me,
because now you can always have this sort of short circuit data at the
top that, you know, will always be there and you don't have to worry
about what happened allocation wise.
So I'm going to go ahead and go through.
Let's again let the compiler kind of guide me.
You know, kind of guide me to, through the process of making this
work, right?
So yeah, actually.
Now that I think about it, these guys should not actually these guys
still actually want to be pointers if that makes sense.
It's just The Return part that doesn't do it, right?
Because I still want to use the same error code, right?
If that makes sense.
So I still want, I still want get all files of type and take a
pointer.
I still want open next file.
Take a pointer.
I still want these guys.
All to take pointers.
Yeah, so that's all, that's all good.
So the only difference is here, right?
This guy probably takes a non pointer.
I don't know.
We could still make him take a pointer if you want to.
I suppose, let's take a look.
All right, so get file handle for this again is just going to return
the address of the file handle in question, let's see here.
File count when we get the file group back.
We're actually just looking at the actual thing.
They're so that's fine.
Let's see here, file handle platform open next file, file group.
We now have to pass the address of file handle.
Again is address of and same here, address of address is over.
We go and try to see if there's anything else.
Interesting, their platform file error, don't actually know why that's
Do we know why that's an actual call?
Don't know that.
I know why that's a call.
Like, have we thought about why platform file error is a call because
it seems like platform file error.
Could just be like, a macro, like platform.
No, file.
Errors is right.
I guess it's not worth really belaboring at this point, but it's just
something that's a little odd to say the least.
Anyway.
All right.
So open next file open.
Next.
File is supposed to return a actual file handle, so that's supposed to
be that way.
Let's take a look here, file.
And that's going to take you a dress to the file group.
And then platform no file handles those are no file errors.
It's also going to take an address of address of
and yourself.
Okay.
Good, good.
So I think that's all we need to do there.
But now in here, we actually have to start to think about what's going
to happen when this thing gets passed in.
So all of these functions have to be changed, right?
So now these things go away, right?
And we're just left with the actual platform portion, if that makes
sense.
And so now we can go through and actually do this stuff correctly.
So we allocate one of these guys and
When we are actually going to return this, we're going to return a
platform file Group, which is like the result of this thing, right?
And so, our win32 file group is just the platform portion of that,
like so, right?
And then when we return that, we just go ahead and say return results.
So that's really it.
We're just trying to kind of changing things around a little bit here.
And again like now we don't store those as part of the same thing.
We're kind of storing separately so we can just kind of go ahead and
do that, right?
So let's take a look there.
What's that skipped over?
That looks like that's all cleaned up now, which is good.
So then what we want to do is do the same thing here.
So when we, when we grab this guy,
325 group.
Now we're just we're going to be again, taking that platform handle
part of the file group structure and casting bat, so that keeps going
again.
Nothing particularly odd happening there.
Same thing would happen here.
And now we've got a thing where a platform file handle is actually the
result.
So here, we've got the, the platform version 2 platform file handle.
And this is with three to handle and that's going to be sort of
specific.
I guess these don't really need to be called win32 handle anymore.
Because now we've got went through to handle win32 handle, always fun.
But yet,
See here in three file group.
Find handle.
That's all fine.
If I could find a handle or results, New errors, keep looking.
So, there we go.
All right, and so, when we do this, here are results.
The platform part again, is just this with three to handle that, we've
created.
And now in here, if you me
All we have to do is just take a look at what comes in and again,
switch to using that platform part rather than using sort of the the
sort of the other piece there.
So yep, those are Arrow's, not dots.
Let's see here.
Win32 handle left a platform so platform file handle results should
have been an actual struct.
and,
Take your handle win32 handle.
You go read data from file.
Also supposed to be a narrow really wanted that to be a DOT apparently
and win32 file error.
Just, this would just be on the source directly, right?
And it's already a pointer so that does not need to be repoint ered.
All right, so, let's see if I've introduced any heinous bugs here.
Looks like everything's fine and so, again, the only real thing I want
to do, there was just make it so that it was easier on the outside
code to handle the heiress situations.
It would just be like, okay guys, you know, when we do read data from
file and all that and open next file and that stuff, it can all
Cascade as errors on the file handle.
And we don't have to keep checking the file handle for null.
And whether they were errors on it, I just wanted one error code and
so that's all good.
So, another thing that I wanted to point out because people were very
hot and bothered about this on the forums,
And, you know, I don't want to say, I don't care about it.
The truth is, I really don't care about it.
But, you know, one of the things I like to do is even if I don't care
about something, if you care about something, I'm happy to show how to
do it.
So what people were worried about is they were were worried that I
guess they weren't worried that this code had a problem because there
really isn't any reason, this go, whatever problem.
But they were worried that like, if people wanted to use code like
this, in a Unicode setting, that it would be a problem or something
like this, I don't know.
People get very uptight about Unicode and that's fine.
But
It's not really something I care about ever.
So,
what I would say about this is
We are using the, a versions of the calls in Windows, right?
Which means we're passing antsy strings.
Now, we are only using it to enumerate over the files in the directory
that we are in.
And those files are files.
We created their our asset files.
So we know that they're never going to have Unicode in them because
I'm never going to type a Unicode file name into the asset files,
pretty much period.
But
If you had wanted to load asset files, that had Unicode in them, this
would not work.
And the reason that it would not work is because when you call find
first file with a as the, you know, as a suffix,
It's not going to be able to return you Unicode file names because the
win32 find data a structure doesn't take Unicode file names, right?
That's just not, it doesn't do that.
so,
If you wanted to be able to load data out of Unicode file names, you
would need to switch to using wa which I will go ahead and do in a
second here.
But I want to point out that that Cascades down one level as well, and
create file also has to be a you know and find next file also has to
be a, right?
So this this part of the code also needs to switch to using double w
is not a s.
Okay.
Now the interesting thing about this,
And I kind of want to point this out because this is intentional and
was intentional, but I don't think I ever mentioned it.
You will note that I never exposed the file names to the game code.
Okay.
I never exposed the file names to the game code.
That was a very deliberate decision.
And the reason that I made that decision was because of exactly this
thing.
I don't know what operating systems is going to run on.
I don't know what crazy conventions are going to have.
I don't know if they're going to use utf-8 or utf-16 or utf-32 or God
knows what other.
Crazy Character, encoding that a bunch of people in some committee
summer makeup.
I don't know what their past separator is.
I don't know anything about it.
I don't even know if I can iterate over directories and put path names
into file names or not, right?
Anything could go.
Anything goes down there at the bottom.
And so, what a lot of people do in the Arctic, this is they pass those
filings back through, they, let that stuff leak out into the game
layer, and that's a really bad idea.
The reason it's really bad ideas because it pushes the this complexity
of knowledge up into the game that the game didn't care about the
game.
Just needs to know asset file, savegame files.
He doesn't care what they're called, right?
It never ever, ever needs to know that information, right?
So that is why architected it so that the API was blind
The filenames, it just knows that a certain number of files are going
to come back.
And when it iterates over those files, it just asks, for them by
index.
It says, I want, you know, I'm getting the first file and I didn't
even index.
Just says, give me the next one, right?
And it doesn't care what it's called.
So that is what we want to do.
I think that's a good decision and it allows us to make this change
painlessly.
No code Upstream will have to change because of our decision to switch
to Unicode down.
Here is so that people can be less upset about themselves in their
life, okay?
So, let's start.
First of all, let's just change all the wasd W's.
So we'll just start by forcing the compiler to start complaining at us
about all the things that aren't going to work, right, when we change
these things to W's, right?
So everything's a w.
Now, everything is a w.
You just been through the whole thing, right?
So we got create file W5, next file W, all those guys up there were W
so I think we're good.
What about in here?
There's nobody should be doing anything else.
I think aw, wise, kind of like the root beer up in here
All right, so now if I compile I should get some complaints about the
fact that the strings that we are passing into these functions are not
the correct kind of string and you can see that here.
So find first file W, it's taking that wild card parameter that wild
card parameter is not utf-16.
It's a care and that's a complaint, right?
Find first file W again.
Down here, same wild, cartoon, it reinitiate the search not the
correct string.
Type create file W, the file name, not the correct file now.
The correct type right again and find x file W.
Not taking the correct handle.
Oh, you know what?
That's because we didn't we didn't do.
There's one more we did not.
Do where is it?
Where is it right there?
Right.
Now, we should get it.
So there are two fine first so wrong.
This one's wrong because it's trying to pull it out of something that
doesn't actually that that's going to be a wide care now and and the
same as here for the create file, right?
Okay, so we gotta start using Unicode strings.
How do we start using unit Unicode strings?
Well, visual visual C++, whatever makes it easy to do utf-16 because,
hey, guess what Windows is utf-16 all over the place.
So the Microsoft support that cleanly and all this other nonsense.
So, for example, what I can,
Do is, I can change from using a care to using what's called The W
care.
T, right?
And and what that is, is that's just a way of saying, utf-16
character, right?
And inside windows.
So let's see here, if I've got got a reference for it, right?
Yes is not particularly good reference.
I kind of want the msdn version of this.
Mariah.
So right, this is a way of basically, just saying, I want a 16-bit
character type and there really isn't anything to it.
Other than that's the name that they tend to give to these things.
So that, you know, when you're trying to interoperate with their code,
that uses these white characters, this is it's what it considers, a
16-bit character type, right?
So I would have to change these to all pointing to these 16-bit
character types and then this unfortunately won't work anymore, right?
So if I go
In here.
So I guess this one can actually leave that way if I go in here and I
try to initialize my wild card right to be to look like this.
Where it's star dot, right?
I want initialize it to that this.
See when it sees this, it will always turn this into a care string
because that's what C is defined to do.
So we want to do, is tell it to turn into a wide character string.
So each of these instead of this becoming a string, that's three bytes
long, the asterisk character, the dot character, and the null
character.
What we actually want to do, is turn into a string that six bytes long
to B for the asterisk, to B for the dot and to B for the null.
Actually don't know how they do that.
I simply used to buy to the no actually, no, I don't hardly ever use
utf-16.
So anyway, whatever they did to do for the know probably too.
Right.
It would have to be because it's WKYT.
So yeah, two bytes for the know, so 6 B, right?
So if we do this, we need some way of telling it.
Hey, make each character to B, we could convert it ourselves, but
probably easier is to just let see do it because like msnbc's
compiler.
Allows you to prepend an L2, the string and that says, please make it
a wide care.
And so now you can see we don't have that problem anymore.
This just kind of works, right?
Now, what's interesting is, you'll notice we didn't get any compile
errors here.
Why is that?
Well, it's because actually, we can just take our characters and stuff
them into the wild care.
And that actually works, the reason that works is because the
The F16 spec actually happens to line up with basic and see down in
the bottom, right?
So when you're just talking about antsy characters like ASCII
characters that are just like a through z and some punctuation, right?
Which is all our extensions are the wide character version is just 16.
16 bytes where the bottom eight bits are the ASCII version and the top
eight bits are 0.
So this actually works believe it or not.
So, we don't actually have to change the loop.
Probably is just fine.
So yeah, that'll work fine.
All this code would now work fine because we're passing a wild-card,
that's properly formatted but will not work.
Fine, is us doing this where we're pulling a file name, out of the
find data struct which is not actually a care star.
But again this is not particularly tricky because if you take a look
A Twin City to find data.
You can see actually that in here.
This thing is specified as a teak are right?
And what a teak are actually is is that that's its way of saying, hey
whichever way you use it.
If you use the a version it's going to be a care.
If you use the W version it's going to be a double you care, right?
So we can actually just say, oh yeah, that's now going to be a double
your car T, which means that we can then pass that to create.
5w, and it's going to be fine, right?
So that should actually probably do it in terms of Unicode as far as I
know.
But oh well or not let's maybe not.
Oh yeah, maybe not this of course no longer works because we have to
actually use half of the size of the thing.
So size of is not actually correct anymore.
We could make this a little bit cleaner if we wanted to
To buy actually saying array count, right?
Because that'll work no matter what size that thing is, if that makes
sense.
But that's basically it.
It's not, you know, it's not rocket science, but now you can load
Unicode named files for your asset files.
If that's the kind of thing that makes you happy and
Like I said, if you kept your API kind of relatively clean in this
respect, the nice part is you can make a change like this and it
doesn't really change anyone Upstream right?
Nobody cares because it's only ever passing into, you just an
extension and that extension can be simple, right?
If we wanted to make it, we could go even one more step, right?
So the extension thing assumes that, whatever the notion of an
extension makes sense on all platforms and maybe that's not true,
right?
So if we
To go one step further.
We could actually do it even crazier.
We could actually do it.
We're in the handmade platform thing.
We actually Define the set of file types.
We actually know and care about right?
And, you know, I don't know that we need to do that but we could and
the way that that would, you know, do it is instead of passing a Cara
star type, here we would pass it in numerous and we would have won a
new marinche per type of file.
I'll write.
So we would have something.
that looked, you know, like
Platform file type and we have like platform file type asset file,
right, platform file, type saved game file or something, right?
And then we would always use those to refer to what we wanted to refer
to right?
And that's not a bad idea, right?
That's a totally reasonable idea if we want to do that.
I don't remember what our convention is for enums here.
I don't think we actually
Really defined them as type deaths although we might want to I
suppose.
Because that actually assume this works just fine.
I haven't done this in a long time.
Flashbacks to the granny days when I used to have to ship C headers
for everything so you know we could do something like that, right?
And
Maybe we should write, maybe we should do that because then we're even
further removed from caring about how the operating system thinks
about files and we can support even wackier more ridiculous
situations, right?
So if we did it that way, now, when we come in here, in this
particular piece of code, what we would do is we wouldn't do any of
this.
We would just do something like, w, carty wild card.
Equals, you know, star dot star, something like this, and then we
would do a switch on the type and we would have, you know, invalid
default Pace.
Oops, invalid.
Default case, we would just have the cases here, that enumerate,
whatever those those guys are.
So we'd say, okay, in the case of an asset file, in the case of the
save game file,
And then we say the wild-card for the asset file start at.
Aha and again that's got to be a wrt for the Unicode side of things
and the save files like handmade hero save or something, right?
You know, whatever, then this code goes away and everybody is
presumably happy and excited about their life except for the fact that
I didn't capitalize that.
Okay.
And so that's really the only change we would have to make to support
that and you can see if I run it.
We're back any reading all the files correctly and all that other good
stuff, right?
So pretty good.
Nothing particularly unusual there.
Hopefully that makes reasonable sense and then nobody is passing any
file related strings, back and forth.
To cross the boundary, Everyone is always using some kind of a token
that you know, does
Require understanding about what a file name is or how it works
between the two layers of the code.
I think that's it.
I think that's really it.
So, I guess what I would say is,
Yeah, I don't really know what else to do.
I feel like at the moment I would like to crank up our asset memory so
we don't have so much flicker, so it doesn't have to constantly cycle
the assets.
I'd like it to be able to keep in memory, all of the heroes rights,
right?
So maybe we'll give it just a little bit more memory for the time
being, right?
So instead of for, you know, maybe we'll give it 16 megabytes of
memory so that it can have a little party.
And so now,
We don't have any flicker anymore and that's good, right?
And again, we'll do some stuff with pre-caching, a little later on
designed to sort of eliminate some of that flicker.
Hopefully, even in cases where you know, the asset can't be where the
asset was an in-memory already.
We want to make it so we never see that flicker.
There's a bunch of stuff we could do about that as well, but I think
we're good.
I think I'm pretty much ready to call it an episode.
I think if there's any
Other things in here.
That.
let's see, think
I think that's good.
All right, so let's go to the Q&A.
If you have any questions about what we did, please prefix them with
Q: so I can see them.
Canoe colls first rays of Moscow, son bid, you good evening.
And good evening to you as well, sir.
I humbly request to be granted to off-topic questions.
May be near the end.
I am delighted to Grant you.
Those two questions, k'nuckles fire away and I will answer them when
the on-topic questions dwindle.
Blah 238.
I asked a similar question yesterday but I guess it wasn't.
Have you thought about how the a system could work with third-party
mod?
Say someone wants to make a mod that adds new graphics sounds and our
game logic.
How hard would it be to implement a mod loader Steam?
Workshop support Etc, Steam Workshop, support.
It's not something I'm super interested in.
So I don't know that I would really spend any time looking at that,
but what I would like to point out is modloader is actually trivial.
In fact, you don't have to do anything because if you remember
correctly, our asset files merge, right?
So that you adding new stuff is Trivial.
Like, let's say you wanted to draw more defined angles for all the
heroes that works just fine.
The thing we have not done for mod support.
Is this right?
Which is the ability to remove
Of old assets, right?
To basically say, don't use, you know, don't use these fights for the
hero use mice, this new set of spray.
It's right, that we haven't done and that is something that I would
consider doing.
I don't know that I'm necessarily going to do it anytime soon but it
is something we could consider doing, you know, maybe we could you
know if you really feel very strongly about it we could do it next
week instead and just make sure that we've got all the bases covered.
But yeah.
Should there be a way to say if one of the hero assets are loaded than
they all should be loaded and are not evicted.
So like I said we want to do some stuff with pre-caching but I don't
think we want to do like a non eviction thing because our recently
used should take care of that to some degree.
And I think what we'd rather have is something that tells that that
does a precache broadcast fairly frequently that says, if I use One
Direction of a guy, I'd probably going to use all the directions of a
guy, right?
And that would be more generic.
Rick and not specific to the hero, so it would let you know, like, oh,
if you're using this direction of the monster, you're probably going
to use all the directions of the monster so you probably want to get
to Work loading those in, right?
So, I think when we get to pre-caching which will be kind of further
down the road, I think will will sort of get the Hero part for free if
that makes sense because the heroes like the least interesting case
because yeah we could just lock his assets down and be done but I
think the more interesting thing to do would be to work on like
Monsters and things because those are the harder case.
And
I think the hero will just fall out of that.
Might be off topic of wives.
After you have typed at functions in the code, Cuba, Caleb, you should
go back and watch some of the episodes where we introduced that way
back to the beginning.
I explained it pretty thoroughly there.
That's because those are those are function pointers that actually get
intended to a table.
Right?
A table that gets passed from the win32 library, or the wintry to
platform layer to the dll.
That's the game and the game calls through them, right?
So if you look at, if you look in here,
It's this, Global variable platform API thing.
That's what everybody calls through to get those functions.
So we have to type the function so that we can actually put them in
that structure.
And you can see that happening right here that platform API is a
collection of function pointers.
It's like a dispatch table and so you can't really do that without
type deafening them because well it would be just a lot of extraneous
typing if you didn't
So can you close ask, did you see the Nostalgia Critic wicker, man,
cage in a bear suit review.
I saw the link.
I think you posted on Twitter or somebody did, but I have not actually
had chance to watch it yet maybe this weekend.
Can we get a visual display of the loaded unloaded chunks of asset
memory?
When we do the debug stuff?
Absolutely, in fact, that is one big thing that I absolutely want to
do.
So that would that would search should certainly happen.
Each choice 0, I would like to hear what your definition of
enumeration is.
What do you mean by definition of enumeration?
You mean just like counting things, 0, 1, 2, 3 4 5.
I'm sorry, I don't understand the question.
Neat, you are good evening.
Casey does Windows 10 10, change the coding, if, you know, so the best
of my knowledge, nothing from Windows XP forwards changes, the coding
in the sense that you can still run the same code if you want to.
But Windows 10, certainly introduces new apis that you could use if
you wanted to.
And so, you know,
there's, there's always new apis, but the old apis usually work still
unmerge if possible.
Emerge as possible when you pass the checks and do the merge, you add
the size of the header, plus the size, but on the line before, that
you check that the size plus header matches.
But the size should already include the header.
Can you explain why?
That is?
So the convention that was used here.
And I'm not saying that there's anything particularly good or bad
about it, so it's not like it's like a good convention.
It's just what I happen to pick.
When I typed in the code is that the size does not include the header.
And the reason that I say that is because if you take a look at what
insert block does insert block sets the size of the block to be the
size, the total size - however, much the header took
So basically a block, the total amount of memory in a block is the
header size.
Plus the size, that the block says it has
Right.
So when we come in here, we want to do.
Where is the second block at?
Well, it's going to be where the first block was, plus the size of the
first blocks header, plus the size.
The first block thinks it is
Right.
And then we go ahead and say, okay if the if that is you know if the
second block actually was there then we go ahead and unlink the second
block and we say the first block, now grows to include the entire
second block and the reason for that is because it's subsuming.
All of the second Block in its entirety it this size.
Let me draw you a picture.
You've got something looks like this.
Here's the header.
Here's the size.
Here's the size, right?
So our specification for a block is that the size should Encompass
everything after the header.
Right.
So how do we know where the second guy should be?
Well, we have a pointer to the first guy we add the size of the
header, which gets us.
Here.
We add size which gets us here, right?
We look to see if the second block is there.
That is where we always like to be.
If it is there, we know we can merge.
How do we merge?
Well, first, we have to remove this from the linked list which we do
then we have to adjust this size to Encompass what the actual block
will be.
Look.
Later.
And remember what the block look like, now, is this header plus this
entire chunk of memory?
So we have to include this header because we only account for one
header.
When we when we say that the header is separate from the size.
If I absorb this block this header, no longer exists.
It's gone.
So it's part of this entire thing.
So we need to add this size, plus this size, plus the size of the
header, which was this little chunk in here.
And then yes, we don't count this header, but we do count this one
because it's gone now.
It became part of our actual usable block space.
It's like literally disappearing.
Does that make sense?
What's the cause of the depth error?
You get on rendering.
So we don't sort yet that's still a to do in our in our renderer and
so the assets, the texture is just get rendered in whatever order they
happen to go in.
So there it's like random, right?
So once we sort then we won't have the that depth thing happening.
Okay, let's take a look at canoe cools off topic questions canoe coils
says this is a long one.
You know, I'm the biggest fan of the series but I suspect for complete
newbies.
The current way you construct, the game makes little sense.
Consider this, you know, how to make a game.
So you methodically crossover, a checklist that components, you know,
by heart, mostly, of course, design, with all the tools and Tech in
place will be
I guess I can't read that because there's no Q col in front of it.
Let me see if I can get that.
I heard of course, Cyril to take place will be what would probably be
easier and more graphic for larvas to grasp is to make a little
functional game title screen game Loop game over start over and then
iterate upon it.
It's more Visual and having a little game that involves every day.
Little by little keeps the maker motivated as opposed to a pro.
That knows what the game should look like in the end.
Okay.
With this more.
So it's a tool box versus a bad game.
Good game approach.
As I see it.
Did you weigh in different models?
What ultimately set you on your current one Sandy check on my yapping.
Yes.
Oh, I actually did think about that.
And my feeling about that was actually that I wanted the series to
To basically have a break point in it, which again, I say is somewhere
maybe around day 200.
250 when the engine work is done in terms of being done in a vacuum
and we're just doing the game from then on and my thought was anyone
who didn't want to know about how the engine was made or didn't want
to know how the image engine was made.
Yet would just come into the series there because that would basically
be like what would happen if you started with unity, right?
It'd be like, okay now we've got our own engine.
So if all you're thinking about doing is powering up some existing
engine and making game in it, well, now we're at that place except our
engines better.
I mean, what can I say?
It just is.
But anyway, point being
I did think about that, and
Feeling is that that's something that I feel like people can join
later and I'm going to do an announcement at that time and be like,
okay, we finished our render engine work and we're going to start
making the game now.
So anyone who's only it was only interested in that part.
Can come watch from here on out.
And of course the one of the reasons I include the source code for the
series is that means you also don't ever really have to do that part
because you could always just start with the source code from that day
and have
You know, the ability to render Sprites and the ability to play sounds
and all these other things that maybe you're not prepared to go learn
at that time.
So, that was my feeling.
But the reason I didn't do that from the start is because that would
have required me to like ship existing code.
Basically because if you don't know how to render a bitmap, you're
never gonna be able to put a Sprites on the screen, right?
And I did not want to ship code at the start.
I wanted to start with nothing that was very important to me.
So that's why I decided to do it that way.
Where's the second question?
I don't see a second question.
Chemicals, you said two questions you had but I don't see the second
one.
Unless you're counting the previous question.
You asked about the Nostalgia Critic wicker, man.
Oh you did you nail label that zero.
Alright so I guess those were both
Well, I have answered both questions.
Let's see what else we got here.
Did I ever play freelancer?
No, I did not play freelancer.
I think I met.
No I guess I don't have freelancer.
I have Privateer to which I tried to play.
It was not good.
I like to Privateer one but I was pretty young back then.
I think I pretty much played anything in those days.
I don't see any other questions to have.
You seen Kung Pao?
No, I did not.
I don't think.
Yeah, so are we all done?
I don't see any more questions.
Feel like I feel like that's it.
Cuba.
Caleb which version of Visual Studio?
Are you using at work?
I use 2012.
I use the commercial version like I actually bought like Visual Studio
2012 and so that's the one I use.
Conan, will that point in time?
See a new intro trailer with an old motherboard.
Being pulled from the attic engine booting up, and he made her
announcement completion of the engine, perhaps the nice sign scroller
and particle effects.
I wouldn't say that, but there will be a new trailer to go along with
that.
It would not probably be as you describe it, but there would be
another trailer.
Yes,
it'd be that we finished the engine trailer.
Breath of hair is font rendering around the corner.
Yes, I think we probably would have to start on front rendering
probably next week.
I'm guessing because we're not going to get anywhere debug code wise
without a font,
I mean, we could do some very limited debug visualizations with no
font but you kind of need a font
plain flavored.
How do you render without instantiating a brush object?
Are you mean like a GDI GDI brush object?
I mean the reason that we don't do that it's because we're not
rendering through GDI.
We basically the only thing we ask Windows to do for us is to put the
bitmap that we make on to the screen.
So we do all the rest of the rendering ourselves so we don't need a
brush object because GDI doesn't do any drawing for us.
It only the only thing it does is curry our bitmap out
To put it into the compositor, so it'll show up as part of Windows is
display composition.
But so we don't need to instantiate any GDI objects, other than the
basic, like the ones necessary to send a bitmap to Windows that's
covered in.
Like, you know, the first, you know, day 3 or something of handmade
hero, I think I don't even remember but very early on right at the
beginning of the series I show how to do that, part of it and that's
the all we need GTI to do for us.
Manic the nobody will you be going the easy way and using bitmap fonts
or you'll be implementing truetype fonts.
We definitely won't influent truetype fonts.
The primary reason we won't Implement to advice because there's
actually no reason to implement truetype fonts, because if you think
about it, our game art is bitmaps.
So, it would be a very odd decision to say.
We need to allow our fonts to be arbitrarily rescaled as Vector art,
but our regular art, that's what you're actually looking at.
In the game, 99% of the time can be bitmaps, right?
It doesn't make any sense.
If you were going to make something, if you made some kind of decision
about needing high-res line art, you would first be worried about the
Assets in the game, not the fonts.
Because the fonts are not super relevant that like the fonts, don't
even really have much need for that.
so we definitely be rasterizing, Foster bitmaps and the just using the
bitmaps directly because there's really no there's literally no payoff
for
F in a game.
Unless your game is really about text.
Do you know anyone by the name of Andre lamothe?
I do not know personally, someone by the name, Audrey moth, but I do
know that there was a guy named Andre lamothe, like, a long time ago.
He used to write like these weird, like big thick books that were like
secrets of the DirectX programming, gurus or something, right?
I've never read one of those books.
I don't know what they're like, I just know that that was his thing.
Are you going to implement distance field font?
Well, distance field font so okay, I don't know if you want.
How in depth, you want me to go on that.
But distance, feels don't really work.
For fonts distance fields are very bad for fonts.
The only thing that you can do for fonts if you want to go that route
is.
You actually need to use a multi like a multi distance field,
encoding, right?
If you
We do a distance fieldfox, you will get a very very ugly ugly font.
Really ugly, not a font.
You ever want to see on a screen?
Now, the reason and I can actually just tell you the reasons while
we're on the topic.
So the reason is because your font will always be rounded.
So, for example, if this is the glyph,
Like the capital T glyph.
What you will get in with distance Fields, is all of the corner, edges
are rounded.
So what you will actually get with a distance field font is this
Right?
And so distance fields are actually awful for fonts if you want to do,
if you are trying to do the thing where you have a infinite resolution
font encoded in a bitmap, what you actually need to do is you need to
use an encoding that encodes, a variable, number of distance fields,
or functions side functions, depending on how you want to do it in.
To a bitmap and you have to actually, you know, do those in a pixel
Shader after the fact, right?
And so like what you do is for this pixel, right?
The problem is that this pixel in this font, right?
Recorded can only record the distance and its trying to record the
distance between two edges.
So it loses the information that there are two edges that needed to
meet here, right?
And so what you actually need to do is you need to encode in this
pixel.
The fact that there were two edges and have the pixel Shader and those
two together.
Other to produce the correct, crisp Edge and you could do that.
but you have to ask yourself whether that's as whether you should just
actually use bitmap fonts at a higher resolution and
Ed because there's, you know, that's pretty costly compared to, you
know, just a bit map.
Is it worthwhile to try and make a game using?
Only purpura functions?
IE.
No side effects.
Well at the risk of stating the obvious, that's not possible, really
because
How would you actually keep track of the fact that time was going
forward?
Right.
I mean at the risk of
Being overly, silly.
Even if I could make it so that I had a thing called f of t.
Where F of T produced the the frame for the game at time T.
Right.
How do I what sits here and knows to keep calling F of t with an
increment with a Time increment?
Right.
like, it cannot be purely functional because somebody has to remember
the fact that t was increasing
not to mention the fact that
how is it going to account for input?
Because if it's purely functional you need F of t plus the input
series at all T right from 0 to T because it has to re-simulate the
game from the very beginning in order to figure out what this Frame
actually should look like because in a purely functional language, you
have no storage, right?
So you can't store the state of the world because if you could you
have a side effect which is whoever updated that.
So you have to pass the
Time and you have to pass all of the input in like a giant buffer.
And so who's making that buffer would be the other question and who's
updating T like who is it?
So, I would argue that a game made only pure with, with only pure
functions.
Actually, can't exist.
In any meaningful way.
Like it's a Fool's errand, I would say.
Will you cover non monospaced fonts and font kerning sure.
It's actually no more difficult really to have non Mi spaced fonts and
is to have Mi face fonts.
It's really, it's it's not a priest able amount of it doesn't really
complicate the code.
It's a very very minor change between those two.
I mean, basically, like do the dip the entire difference between
amount of space and a proportional font is like I draw a character
right?
I draw the letter A at this location.
Well, I now have to figure out where to draw the next character.
The entire difference between kerning fonts and Ma spaced fonts is
monospace fonts, right?
Are like I draw it at X Plus
Constant and current fonts or proportional fonts, right?
Are just X plus some function where I take the previous care, you
know, previous care, and this care.
Right?
And it tells me how far to move, so it's just a single lookup table
that takes the to glyphs.
And tells it how far to move is the entirety of the implementation for
proportional font.
It is literally the dumbest thing ever like
you will be completely unimpressed when you see,
Us implement this.
Because the difference between these two is like one table, 1 table
lookup.
It is literally replacing see with a table lookup.
Functional game.
The state is an argument and a new state is returned so basically what
you're saying is it constructs an entire new one.
So you're saying you would do F of T and input and you're saying that
it basically produces this, this produces I guess you do this, right?
So you do world time and input.
and that produces like,
World one.
Because that is that we're basically saying.
So my question then is alright if that happens.
So this is our new model for the game.
Who is it?
That's actually.
What.
What are you actually doing this in?
Right.
So now I have a loop.
Let's say four
and I'm producing these worlds.
How do I actually show the world to the user without a side effect?
But where does it go?
so I'm in here, I say all right I've got W new, I call it I give it w
old
I give it the time step.
I give it the input.
I get the new one.
Right?
I then do W old equals W new
Somewhere right here.
I had to display this thing.
How do I display it?
Purely functionally.
Do I imagine?
Are we imagining that we have a functional GPU, which is some kind of
a graphics card that
that we
You know, I don't even know how do you, how do you display this to the
screen?
I guess.
That's my question.
Like how does it get how do we get something on the screen?
Because the screen is like a buffer, right?
That the GPU is trying to read out a but
Hit right to the buffer.
because,
So I guess I guess.
Okay so maybe what we try to do,
Is is it's just in a for Loop.
I'm trying to make this work.
So it's in a for Loop.
At the top of the for Loop.
Now be now I don't, I don't I don't see anyway.
I don't see any way to do it.
How much of the code, how much of the code you've written so far can
be ported to 3D easily?
Well, actually all the code is 3D.
For the most part.
The only thing that we didn't do 3D is we don't prospectively.
Correct, our textures.
So like if you wanted to use our bitmap fill to draw 3D shapes, you
would get warping.
So we would have to introduce a perspective divide to our bitmap fill
which is not hard to do but everything else in the game is already 3D,
right?
We don't really
We don't really use any 2D anything that I can think of anyway.
At least it Haskell the pure functional.
Part is hidden away from the io stuff via mathematical concept called
mode, okay?
So what you're saying is you don't really want to make a purely
functional game, you want to make
everything below the display part be functional.
Maybe
and in which case, I mean I guess I would say well if you're already
not going to be completely functional, is there some reason why you
think that the game should be completely functional
Like, is there a benefit to that?
I mean.
What, what do you gain?
Other than wasting a heck of a lot of memory bandwidth on this.
Right.
I mean it's kind of brutal and you can't cash anything really because
you have to rewrite everything every time.
So like the whole 4 GB asset footprint would have to like living here
or something.
Be pretty brutal.
No more questions.
I see no more questions.
I think it's time to wrap it up.
Manic the nobody, if you have.
I'm to answer and off-topic question.
It's been all off topic questions tonight.
What do you think of a graphic system that intentionally simulates
mode 7?
I mean mode 7 is just the ability to like flatten a to tilt.
To tilt a planer image, right?
Like I mean
is there like what would be the goal of such a system?
It seems, it seems like kind of a relic of a bygone era like when we
have full 3d, why would we want to have?
Just one thing that can be 3D like, laid down, you know.
Anonymous.
Will we be planning on implementing any networking?
No, we will not be doing any networking.
And canoe, Giggles.
Thank you for tuning in.
I know it's difficult from from Moscow, or from, from the far from
from places, far away from Seattle.
So thank you for tuning in.
I hope you have a good weekend.
All right, I will wrap it up here.
Thank you everyone for joining me, for another episode of handmade
here.
It's been a pleasure coding with you.
As always, if you want to follow along at home with the source code,
it comes with the pre-order.
So, if you want to preorder the game on handmade, here it up, or you
can download the source and play around with it, learn from it, it's
fun to Tinker.
We also have a patreon page.
If you just want to support the video series, you can subscribe to
that.
We also have a forum site, you can go to ask questions and get ports
to Mac and Linux that community members.
Have done.
Check out anti-deficit guide the community here that committee members
have done and if
I'll try and catch the stream live.
We have a tweetbot that will treat the schedule at you.
I highly recommend subscribing to that, or at least checking it
periodically, if you are someone who wants to catch the stream live,
because the schedule does change up on occasion, you know, oftentimes,
it's five days a week, 5 p.m.
Pacific Daylight time or same time depending on the daylight savings.
That's in effect.
But sometimes like, I think next week, I have, I know, I have to be
away for the weekend, so they'll probably be like Thursday and Friday.
There might not be a stream or something like this, right?
So,
It's a good thing to keep track of just so you know, when the streams
going to be live, if you're someone who likes to catch it live and you
don't get caught by surprise, all right, that's about it for today.
I hope everyone has a fun weekend and has fun coding this weekend and
until then I'll see you on the internet.
Take these everyone