Here.
Hello everyone and welcome.
I believe it is day.
It is day, 25 of handmade hero.
We have come to the end of a long journey are building our win32
platform layer.
And I know it seems like a long time has been 25 days.
But each day is only an hour of code that we get to do really, so if
you think about it, if we started on Monday and it was, you know, we
were working standard, you know, eight hour day with an hour for lunch
or something like
This.
So we are working seven hours a day, you know, we're talking about
less than four days.
So we started on a Monday at work.
We would have been done with this by Thursday.
That's how little actual coding work.
We've done it's because at only an hour a night, it just doesn't add
up to very much.
So I know it seems like we've spent a long time here, but really, this
is not very much and that's with all the explanations everything.
So building a win32 prototyping, layer is really not that hard
building a shippable win32 layer, which will have to address later on.
Definitely takes more work like they're
Stuff that we have not done because we're just trying to build
something that we can prototype on.
So there will be more when 32 work involved down the road when we get
to that point, but even then it's not going to be a huge amount of
work.
It's not going to take us years, right?
It's going to be something fairly straightforward.
So I think it's important to just kind of take a moment and go gosh,
there really isn't that much work to do here.
We haven't even done a week's worth of programming work yet and we
already have a prototyping layer.
That's got a bunch of features in it and works pretty well for
Our purposes.
And, you know, there's there's some stuff that we didn't do because
we're not using Hardware acceleration yet, but you know, adding
Hardware Solutions, actually, pretty simple, you'll see.
And so at that point, you kind of have something that's pretty close
to a shipping layer.
So, I don't know, I think we're in pretty good shape and it really
didn't take us that long.
So that said today is going to be the last day of win32 specific
coding base.
So we're going to do today is just finish the cleanup that we started
yesterday and maybe do a little bit of recap, but for the most part
after,
Today, we will no longer be thinking of win32 programming.
The only time will go back to when 32, handmade dot CPP is when we
sort of want to hoist things out of it now, because as we start
building the platform independent part of things, some of the stuff
that we did in the win32 layer will no longer be necessary to do in
the winter to layer and we'll kind of pull those things out.
And also there's a bunch of like to dues in the win32 handmade dot CPP
that are things that we can't do now because we don't have services
like logging.
But when we build those services in
The platform independent layer, we can go back into win32.
Handmade in.
All those to do is we can just put log calls in there and they'll call
up to the platform independent layer.
So, for the most part, we will be leaving win32, handmade us if you
behind, but we will still bounce back and forth to it as necessary to
kind of pull Services up from there into the platform independent
portion.
So, so let's go ahead.
And if you are, if you have pre-ordered, the source code using
handmade here, adorbs handy-dandy pre-order.
Martin.
You should have gotten a link in your email.
That link contains a zip file which has tons of Zips in it.
Each one corresponds to a day.
We are on day 25.
So you want to unzip day 24 source code.
That is what I am working with right now, and that is what you will be
working with as well, if you are following along at home.
So let's go ahead and bring up the handmade hero source code here.
I never remember what the source tree looks like, somehow, but I have
some notes which I'm going to
Take a look at here just to see what else it was that I wanted to do.
Okay.
Sorry about that.
This this headset is is causing me problems today.
Never have wet years when you're going to do a headphones oriented
broadcast.
Okay, so it looks to me like there's not very much left to do.
They're just a couple little things.
So I think we'll probably do is try to do those couple little things
and then I might go ahead and do
Work of speeding up.
Our replay stuff because I talked about some ways we could make that
faster, especially on a machine, doesn't have an SD drive.
Which this one doesn't.
And so, maybe we'll play around with some things to see if we can't
make that faster because it's a little slow right now on that on the
record.
So, all right.
So the first thing that we want to do is let's just go ahead for the
sake of completeness.
We do think we talked about this a little bit on the forums and it
does seem like for most platforms from what people could could
determine.
We could actually do a fairly cheap call here and most of the time,
get the monitor refresh rate.
That's what people.
Anyway, we're not sure.
So when it comes time to ship this stuff, we're going to have to do
certainly, a more thorough job of like testing it on a number of
platforms to see if we're getting a reasonable one, but when it comes
to shipping to will probably use a different service for syncing with
the vertical, retrace.
Anyway, like, you know, opengl and direct3d will actually be doing
that sink for us.
So we may not even have to care at that point, but I believe monitor
refresh rate queries, we can actually use the one that we avoided
using.
Excuse me.
I believe it's, these are not, this is not, it's the, it's the get
system.
It's like, get system metrics something like this, call that we can
just call and it assuming that it doesn't encounter one of the
conditions where it doesn't know the monitor refresh rate.
Apparently, it will actually return.
And okay, monitor refresh rate.
I believe, I'm not sure if it's actually, I think you know what?
It's like get device caps.
I think was the one we were looking at we
Got it already.
I was just like, it doesn't look like it's going to always return it.
So I was shying away from it.
But apparently it'll be fine.
Yeah, so this is it.
So it's basically get device caps with this V.
Refresh thing.
And this was the part.
I was scared about, but apparently, most of the time this actually
does work.
So since right now, we're hard coding.
It.
It's probably better than nothing to go.
And actually do something real here.
So we can basically say that there's a monitor refresh hurts.
We'll assume it's 60, which is what we were already doing.
But then what we can do is go ahead and call this get device caps on
are on the actual into me on the actual HDC of our window.
And in theory that will at least sometimes assuming we can you know
actually rely on it at all.
At least give us a better monitor refresh in case the amount of
repression something else in Windows actually did know.
So basically
We'll do here is we'll say, all right, we're going to get an impact
which is the V.
Refresh win32.
Refresh rate will see what that is.
If win32 refresh rate is greater than one, basically.
Because we know we might get a 0 or 1.
It's documented as possibly saying that if it's greater than zero or
one, will assume that it actually is giving us a valid value.
Now, whether this is how reliable this is, we don't know.
This is definitely something we would have to, you know, have to spend
more time investigating if we wanted to ship this.
Directly, before again, for prototyping purposes.
We should be okay.
And so from there, we should be able to define the game update hurts.
Let's go ahead and let's see.
Do we have a where do we actually use game update hurts?
Where is that used?
Looks like that is used.
So the game updates hurt.
We're kind of relying on that to be around number.
I don't know how, I don't know how good of an idea that actually is
because if if it can't be divisible by 2.
Almost all the monitor refresh rates are going to be divisible by 2.
So I don't know how much we really care about that.
But you notice like, if we're storing this an integer here, then if
this was going to be fractional, then we'd be in a problem.
Let's say this was 59 hurts, right?
That would be kind of nasty because we're not getting the right result
here for Target seconds per frame.
So that doesn't that doesn't fill me with joy.
I don't love that.
So I'm wondering if maybe we can just go ahead and do something a
little saner here.
Let's see what we've got.
So latency sample count that isn't used anymore.
We can just, we can just ice that I believe latency sample count
entirely right at least.
I think so.
And yeah, so game update hurts.
We can fix with that guy right there as well.
So gaming update Hertz is really only used here in safety B.
So, in safety B, it looks like, I mean, we could just use an actual
and actual real 32 there and just do the math and then
Then cast down, right?
I mean we can certainly do something like this right where we're
actually just doing the math.
It's loading point and then at the very end, we cast it back to some
kind of an integer.
So I feel like that's probably fine.
And then we know that at least will handle fractional values.
Okay, so I'm basically going to say, alright, let's just let's just do
it that way.
Right?
What's interesting is you'll notice game update Hertz is always used
inverted, right?
It's always / game, update hurts.
So it's almost like we probably shouldn't have bothered.
We probably should do it inverted already right?
And just multiply by it since it's always used that way and you know,
whatever.
But yeah, that's like that's not the kind of thing.
You actually need to worry about but it's just kind of caught my eye.
All right.
So anyway, we need our HD see here.
So we need we need to do our get DC of the window and then we can.
So we're going to, we're going to query this for the refresh and
hopefully this will work.
We don't know what we're going to lie step in.
And make sure at least works on our machine, right?
Because we don't even know that yet.
So I'm going to go ahead and just go ahead and do that here.
In fact, I guess we can just pull up pull on bracket that call
directly.
And then all we need to do is clean up anything where this was not
going to?
Yeah.
Okay, so we can wear.
This was not going to work with our with our change of that to a real.
What did I do?
Okay.
I've got a convert this guy to an integer.
So once we do all this math and
A point.
Then we can convert it to an integer and that'll be fine format, this
a little bit better.
Let's see.
And then so the only thing we have to deal with is this guy.
We don't really care about this.
I don't know why I even made it based on game update hurts.
We just need some number of debug time markers.
So basically, we could just say that there are 30 debug time markers
or something.
Right?
I mean, we don't we don't really even care how many there are the last
the last twenty are kept or something like that is fine.
So that should probably be fine and I'm going to just take a
Look and see, and make sure that all that was kosher.
So at least we're still working.
Okay, I want to go ahead and take a look at what that call looks like,
where we get the vertical.
Refresh.
Let's go in here.
There we go.
So, let's see, we get the refresh, d.c.
Back.
We take a look at the refresh rate.
It does return 60.
We release it.
We go ahead and set that model for refresh rate.
Okay?
Game update Hertz is 30, which is what we wanted and everything looks
kosher.
Okay, so that's that.
Fine, no, big deal there, but that seems fine.
So that's good.
I would say taking a look here.
So I'm going to cross that off of our list do do so we got that looks
good.
All this looks good.
So I'm going to introduce a little concept here that I want to do,
which is I realize it may be a little confusing and it probably won't
make very much sense until we get a little further into things by just
want to introduce a
Concept here that will save us some time and it's kind of the way I
like to do things.
It'll save us some time.
It's basically it's sort of one of those.
In my experience.
It is a good idea to have one of these things and have it early so
that you don't have to sort of add it into your code later.
It's just, it's sort of a, a Having learned by doing, kind of a
situation when you are porting, you find that, you tend to need these
things on win32.
You actually don't really need the thing.
I'm about to do typically that much because there's
You can get around it.
But on other platforms that aren't always.
So what I'm going to do is in the platform nonspecific layer.
I'm going to introduce something and you'll just have to take my word
for it, because you won't actually see why this is necessary for a
little while.
I'll just have to kind of tell you why I'm going to kind of tell you
now why it's a good thing to do, and you're just going to take my word
for it.
But basically, what I want to do is introduce something called a
thread context, right?
And what a thread context is is, it's just a handle.
Or an informational structure that's passed along through every
execution chain in the game.
So basically, Whenever I Call something in the game, like we've got
two functions in the game and that may be all that will ever have, but
whenever I call something in the game, the platform layer will pass
this thread context.
It'll just pass that into into whatever calls and right.
Now the thread context will have absolutely nothing in it, right.
Because we have
No idea what that's eaten going to be used for.
Like I said, it's something that you just have to take my word for it.
But basically what will happen is any time that you actually use some
kind of operating system service.
You're going to need to use one of these thread context.
So basically what I want to do is say alright, if you ever call back
into the platform layer at all, you're going to have to use one of
these thread contexts.
And the thread context is essentially like something.
You know, that's going to get passed into these for example, so
whenever you ask
To free file memory or any of this stuff, you always have to pass your
thread context.
And essentially, all this is, is it makes up for the fact that not
every platform.
Does a good job of giving you information that you can use about what
thread you're in when you're running multi-threaded since we haven't
covered multi-threaded.
Like I said, it's a little bit difficult for me to explain why this
actually matters.
But I'll try to do a little bit of that in a second here.
So, all right, let's go ahead and get that compiling.
And then in here, let's see here.
Go ahead and get that in there.
What did I do debug platform B entire file.
Did I not call it thread?
I called it context.
Fantastic.
Nothing like a starting the day off with inconsistent naming always.
A good thing.
Could tell, how absentminded I am when I'm trying to talk a stream at
the same time and just often hard for
for me to focus on the code that I'm writing, makes it kind of
difficult to be honest with you.
All right.
So what we need to do is pass that thread context here again, nothing
is actually happening with it, but we need to pass it.
And so what I'm going to do is just create a dummy thread handle.
Basically, it's just going to be thread context like this and it's
going to have absolutely nothing in it.
Nothing important whatsoever.
Again, did it again really want to call that context for some reason
and then these guys just get that empty handle.
All right, and so what I
What to do here?
Is, I want to introduce this concept, just because the thread context
is, it's basically.
There's a lot of things that happen when you go to start doing
multi-threaded code, where you want to know which thread is, which so
you'll be inside some code, and you'll be doing something and you're
like, this could be made a lot more efficient.
If I had say one buffer per thread that each of these threads could
write into, but unfortunately, I'm in the middle of this code and I
don't know what what
Buffer goes with the thread that I'm in, right?
So there's just these kinds of situations that you get into when
you're in the middle of coding stuff.
That's multi-threaded where you really want.
One thing per thread or you want to know which thread you're in for
some reason and have one thing inside your own code per thread, that
sort of stuff.
And so typically you want to be able to Define like thread indexes and
have pointers to thread specific things in Windows.
If you're not in a dll or well I should say from,
Deal in Windows, most of the time you can get what's called
thread-local storage which will sort of do this process for you.
So that you don't need that thread context handle, but there are other
platforms where that's not true, and depending on the circumstances,
you may have may not really want to do it in Windows, either, and
blah, blah, blah.
So, really, I'm just setting this up sort of as a predictive thing
where I just want to get in the habit of having the game code, always
know.
No, sort of a thread handle for itself that it can use and it does
take a little bit of overhead to do this because it does have to get
passed around.
But on the whole I find that it's just easier to do that than to deal
with the Alternatives.
So that's the way I'm going to choose to do it.
In this particular case.
I'm just introducing this now.
So that's it.
We don't have to do anything with it.
Now.
I just want to get used to that and get used to kind of having that
get passed through because I would like to be able to use that for a
bunch of different things.
That's all there is for that and the other thing that I wanted to do
again just miscellaneous.
Clean up is one thing that I did notice is we don't pass any Mouse
input to the game and we don't need that for any particular reason
because we won't really be supporting them the Mouse as a controller
like you'll be playing with the keyboard because it's kind of more of
a digitally kind of game.
So the mouse isn't really probably going to be appropriate, but what I
would like to do in case we want to develop some debug over.
Les systems that might be more appropriate for using with the mouse or
if we want to use the mouse to like move elements in some kind of an
editing mode, or anything like that.
What I would like to do is essentially introduced here, just some
mouse debug stuff, right?
So, you know something like, you know, a mouse buttons flag and a
mouse X Mouse, why sort of a situation, just something like that where
we can sort of pass the mouse information.
Game.
And it can be super janky and awful.
It doesn't even matter because it's only going to be used for our
debugging purposes.
But you know, I just kind of would like to have something like that in
there and maybe we'll use the half transition count thing.
I don't know if that's a good idea.
Maybe we'll use the half transition count thing for that since
everything else uses it.
So maybe we'll do something like this where we do mouse buttons and we
say, okay, you know how many Mouse buttons are there on this thing?
I think there's five on this thing.
I don't know if Matt mouse mouse button.
Many Mouse mice have so many buttons these days.
And then, of course, we've got a mousy I suppose as well, which is
that little mouse wheel thing.
And so I just want to create that state there have it so that the game
can get it.
And also, let's go ahead and just go drop in, you know, something
where where we can see if we're actually passing that correctly, and
then I'll pass it correctly in win32.
So we have that little, we have the render Player thing, right?
We have a render player call.
Let's get that up.
Above my head.
And so maybe we'll just go ahead and say let's render where we're
getting told, the mouse is right.
So we have a mouse X in the input layer, and we have a mouse why in
the input layer.
So let's just go ahead and do that.
So that we can see that we have that mouse cursor position and then I
will go in should compile now, I think, yeah, I will go in and just
add the minimum necessary nonsense to get.
The mouse out.
So basically in year, if we only care about where the mouse is right
before we call it really?
Okay.
So when we process our like xinput stuff, we do our controller and put
stuff we can do it right here.
We have that new input pointer.
Right?
We have we have new input and we just want to go ahead and set these
values, all these values here.
So that'd be mousex new input Mouse.
Why new input Mouse Z.
I don't know if we can get
get in the way that I'm about to do the other ones, but if we don't
support Mouse wheel right now, I don't really care.
That doesn't actually matter to me very much and then we'll at least
track those.
Those those three buttons as well, there or buttons, as I
occasionally, say them.
Nice spelling there.
Casey.
So what we can do, if we just want to, if all we need is just a mouse
information.
There's actually a get cursor pause function in Windows that will
basically tell you.
Where the mouse is at any given time, it's pretty trivial to use,
right?
Basically.
What you do is you call This And the main cursor, whatever the main
Mouse is on the system, wherever, you know, this little thing is that
I'm wiggling around right now.
When you call that, you can just get wherever it thinks that thing is,
so basically, we can say, this is the mouse location.
We can we can get that and then we don't even care if this thing fails
or not.
Literally does not matter to us because this is strictly debug
information.
So we can then take a look at this point structure that comes back and
it gives us this long X and Y.
Now, the problem is if we use this directly, well, you know what?
Let me, let me show you what happens if we use it directly so that
you'll understand exactly what I mean.
So I won't have to give this explanation blind.
You can actually see what actually happens.
So, if
If I go ahead and run this, you'll note that we are getting that
Mouse.
You can see that we're getting that Mouse position, but you'll notice
that it's wrong, right?
You see how that's kind of wrong.
So what's going on there, right?
Well, what's going on, is that is when we call that get cursor, that
get cursor position function.
It gives us back the cursor position on the screen, but our window our
coordinate system actually that we're drawing on.
Although we haven't covered coordinate systems much yet.
We're
Talk about that a lot when you get to the renderer, but if you think
about it, if we say the point 0 0, we're talking about this point
right here, but on the screen 00's up there.
So you can see it lines up exactly where if I move the mouse all the
way to the top like that.
Now we're in the upper corner.
So what we need to do is we need to find a way to sort of map that
cursor position into our Windows coordinate system because this is in
the wrong coordinate system and coordinate systems.
Like I said, we'll talk about a lot.
So if you don't know what those are and your little lost right now,
it's
Ali.
Okay, just ignore it.
We are going to talk about this a lot later on when we start
implementing our coordinate system stuff.
So you will have plenty of chance to kind of understand that.
And this is not you an important part of the code that were writing it
now.
So you can literally ignore this entirely.
If you want to, I believe there is something called screen to client.
Remember the name correctly screen to client will basically do that
mapping the exact mapping that we want.
You pass it a window and you give it the point and it just Maps it
from the screen into your client Rec Space.
Now, you remember, we did that, get client.
Thing that basically says, what our window rectangle is.
Well, it's literally that mapping, it Maps it into that rectangle,
which is exactly what we want.
Right?
So we can just say, hey, get the screen to client for this window that
we've got and map it for us, please.
Right?
Oops.
Missing.
Yeah, /.
They're all the sudden so that will correct it.
And now you notice that it is right on target.
Now.
Remember, we're drawing our rectangle as if the upper left corner is
the position.
So that's why it's there.
You know, we if we were actually doing a
Oscar sir, we might want to do an arrow or we might want to like
center of the rectangle over it or something like that.
But for now, we can tell that we're getting the input properly.
So really, all we need to know now, is we need to know whether or not
we had a mouse button up or down.
So the way we could do that if we wanted to is we can sort of do that
in in line with that with when we sort of do all that keyboard
processing, you know, this sort of stuff.
So what we could do there is, we could say, alright, let's go ahead
and process.
Up Mouse down messages here, right?
We could I think we also could get them.
We might be able to just kind of
I'm so I'm so torn.
I'm so torn.
It depends on how we want.
How robust we actually want our Mouse processing to be.
Since it's just debug.
I'm tempted to not even bother and maybe just see if, if we're fine.
Basically, I'm tempted here.
Ladies and gentlemen, what I am tempted to do, I will tell you, I am
tempted to just go ahead and just query it straight away.
Right?
Right in here.
And just, and just see how it's
All right.
I think I'm going to do that.
So I believe this is this is crazy.
You know, don't ask me why I know this stuff.
Hey, it's a, you know, you wish that your brain didn't even have this
information in it because it's just so ridiculous that I even know
this stuff.
So, basically, there's a function that gets the state of the keyboard
for you and it's the state of the keyboard as of your last message
that you pulled off of the message queue.
Because Windows tracks that for you,
And so, you may be asking, why would that matter at all?
Why would we want to do a get key State call?
And you can see that it Returns.
The high-order bit is set at the key is down that the higher order,
bit is not set.
Then it's not down and it's a short.
So it's 16 bits.
So, basically, we could use this to see whether keys are up or down,
and you may be saying, why would you care about that Casey?
Because we are not looking to keep re looking at the mouse.
Well, if I remember,
Directly and I sadly, I think I do, remember, collect correctly.
You can actually ask for the mouse cursor, VK code.
So, basically, if we do something like, look at the VK Code table,
which I assume I can just look at here, virtual key codes and just
typing any VK in there.
There it is, right.
This is exactly what I'm talking about.
You see, those vkl button, vkm button, you can ask for those as if
If you were asking for a key so I can literally go through here and
ask for the R button.
The M button and these X buttons which are those extended buttons.
X button 1, x button to I can ask for those as if I'm asking for keys.
I can ask them at any time and it will tell me whether or not they're
down.
So, you know, let's just do that.
Let's just go ahead and do that.
I don't actually remember, we think we have a utility call here.
That'll do this sort of weird.
Stuff for us that we needed to do for our for our cycle counts.
So where was that guy?
It was to Due Process keyboard message.
This, this is actually I think all we really need right?
Because we're sort of treating this, right?
Just like a keyboard message so I can just call this.
And it'll do exactly what we want.
Right?
We can just Loops.
That's, that's great.
We can just just do this.
I think.
And then and then use that this get key state, for whatever, the
button is.
And, and it with that, with that Top Value.
And I believe they said that it was, it was a short, right?
So the high bit is going to be one shifted up by 15 if I understand
the documentation correctly.
So that's that's like, all we really need to do.
I think
Let's find out.
Let's find out L button, M button, R button, x button, 1 and x button
to will be in there.
That'll be lovely.
I suppose.
And I think in theory, that is it, let me see if that's true.
New input mouse mouse, buttons is not.
A member of new input.
Is that true?
Are you lying to me?
I doubt you are, you're a compiler.
You don't often lie, although, sometimes you do.
You never know.
So game and put Mouse.
Oh, well, if it is if you spell it wrong.
There you go.
All right.
So I think that's literally all we need to do to process that.
Yeah.
I don't think there's really much else we have to do, and we've got to
do here if you ever want support Mouse wheel, which I don't know.
We don't really have zooming in this game because the 2D games so we
probably don't really need the mouse wheel for anything.
But we found out we did, we would be sad because we're not supporting
it.
All right.
So what we need now is just some way to
See if those are working.
Let's go ahead and again, leverage our render player function here.
When you can rent, you'll see this.
This is this is just how programming Works to, it's kind of cool.
Soon, we'll start to be having a lot of functions that we can reuse.
We haven't really gotten to that point yet, but we're gonna be there
very shortly.
Once we start building renderer tools and all these other tools and
it's kind of nice.
Once you have one thing working it builds on itself so quickly like
before we had really, no way to indicate anything and now we can just
call this one function that draws a rectangle from zooming and we can
essentially use that function to do all sorts of other stuff.
So right, for example, I can do something where I just say.
All right Mouse,
Tunes 0 and downright.
I think that's what we have as our thing.
I can just do that.
And see I should see a rectangle happen.
Boo.
What did I do?
New state ended down is not equal to is down.
Okay.
So that's our assertion there.
I guess, I guess.
I don't actually know if this will work then, do we do we, because we
don't.
Okay.
We don't send this guy toggles.
So, this would still yeah this, this, this.
So, I wonder if I just want to make this function, you see what
happened there.
What happened was?
We were previously guarantee.
Essentially, that we always handed.
This guy is down.
Not as down, is down, not as down.
We would never hand it like to is Downs or two is UPS in a row because
we are processing incoming messages.
I think what I'd rather do here because I want to make this more
robust so I can just throw it, whatever.
This current state isn't have it work.
I think what I want to do is kind of just say, you know, if it's not
equal, then do the processing and that just will just work at that
point, right?
Because that
We can use it for more things.
And I don't know.
I feel like that's just going to be more what we're going to want, so
I can throw stuff at it and it just works.
So you see that up in the corner.
You see that guy there, that's showing us that the button is down, and
pushing the button up, down, up, down, up, down.
So, that's totally good.
Let's go ahead and real quickly.
Drop a for, I'm gonna drop a 4 on this.
Yo, let's go ahead and whip out that for Loop.
Everyone knows how much we love a for Loop button Index, right?
Because I wrote this once, no, need to write it again.
Just write it once.
Raptor Loop in there, right?
Let's go ahead and loop over all of the ones, right?
That are that are in this array.
This mouse buttons are a, I can just say for everything in that array.
However, many there are going to do one for each of it.
And then why not go ahead and add something.
Let's say 20 times the button index to just move it over.
So I'm just going to move the move where I render over by 20 pixels
every time we increment that button count, right?
If we
Go.
There's there's our first three buttons left middle, right?
There's our 2 X buttons on the side.
There we go.
Mouse input done completely finished.
So that's always good.
Can I hold them all down at once?
Yeah.
There we go.
It's hard to do on my mouse.
I don't have like, you know why?
I don't have some kind of crazy gaming mouse.
I need one of those mice where you put like weights in them.
So your mouse is like totally perfectly counterbalanced.
That's the way you get the high score as yo,
Like who uses a mouse without weights in it?
It's ridiculous.
Come on, I'm totally behind the times.
Alright, so that's all we really needed for mice.
Mice has nice Mouse.
However, you want to say that, debug mouse cursor, done, and I'll see
anything else on this list to be honest with you.
So I think that's basically it.
So,
There we go.
I'm going to go ahead and slam in the slightly potentially more
optimal version of the Replay code because I don't really know why
because just because some people were nervous about how long it took.
And so we might as well spend a little bit of time since it's not
particularly difficult, basically, using all of the crazy, huge amount
of system resources that we have now, to speed it up because I mean,
hey, if you're going
Have machines, you know, this machine, I don't even know how much
physical memory this thing has.
Let's see.
So this thing has
Why so total so I guess that's telling me we have.
12 gigabytes of memory.
Is that is that what we want to say there?
Let's say that that's true.
So if we have 12 gigabytes of memory, and we're only taking one get so
yeah.
So we can we can just abuse the physical memory in this machine.
We can just, we can, you know, what?
I think it's time.
I was going to save this for the right time, but the right time, maybe
now.
I think it's time to get piggy.
That's what I think.
I think it's time to just like be a total pig and just use all the
memory in this machine because it's their right.
So I don't see any reason why we shouldn't just go to town.
It seems like if you've got the pig hat on, you know, nothing's gonna
stop us.
So let's just say, let's just go ahead and say because we can that
what we're going to do here is we are going to create
Backing stores for all of this stuff, right?
We're just going to go ahead and create backing stores for for this
game memory block.
So we'll do that one way first and then we'll do it.
We'll do it in a slightly different way immediately thereafter.
So what I'm going to do is I'm going to say that we have a particular
count and of of these win32 replay buffers, right?
And and basically the winter if you replay buffer will have a void
star.
Pointer to the memory block like that.
And then I'm going to have this here and maybe what we'll do to is,
maybe we'll say what the back and file name is.
So we've got the replay file name like that.
I don't know.
I don't know how necessary that's going to be but we'll we'll go ahead
and do that.
I think that that should work.
Okay, so we'll say that there's the wheat replay buffer and these are
our replay buffers and we're just going to say that we have four of
them.
Why do we have four of them?
Because I said, so that's something we're going to have.
And so
So, we will go ahead and move that up here.
So, we have the game memory block, which is our actual memory block,
and then we have the replay buffers and they have their game memory
blocks, inside them as well.
And so what we'll do now just to start with is we'll just virtual Alec
buffers and instead of writing the that state to disk will write it
just to the buffer real quickly and see how much performance benefit
we get there.
So basically if we refer to compile this if you remember where we were
Were at, before is grab my little Gamepad here.
We are moving the guy around and you can see when we hit that Loop.
There was this big old Paws, right?
Real long.
Pause while it wrote that stuff to disk.
And so, what we want to do is see if we could speed that up.
You want to make that faster.
So, right here, what I'll do is I'll just Loop over those buffers
again.
It's a looping day today is the kind of day where we Loop.
So we're going to say that our replay index.
Is less than the array count of those replays.
There we go, replay index.
There.
It is.
Replay buffers.
So that is our win32 state.
What did I call?
It went 3-2 State.
There we go.
Replay buffers.
And for each one of those, we are going to just go ahead and allocate
a block.
So this is the replay buffer.
It is going to be equal to whichever one.
We are on replay index like that.
And we are going to go ahead and
and allocate huge amount of memory.
All right, so we've got the memory block here.
Excuse me.
The memory block is just going to be this exact thing, right?
We're just going to do the exact same allocation.
So they're all the same size.
We don't care what the Base address of it is because we're just using
it for temporary storage.
Right?
So we don't care about the base dress is whatsoever.
We have the total size that we were using before same amount.
We want to do the read, write as well.
So we're just going to do those virtual Alex and then we'll go ahead
and insert that we got them because in debug mode, we want to make
sure that we actually can allocate all this stuff.
We want to know.
Ahead of time.
If I replay buffers aren't working.
Looks like we can get them pretty trivially.
If you are on a low memory kind of machine that would not work.
You'll get an assertion there.
Again, this is something that we will to do.
Maybe we will change this change this to a log message so that people
can run on machines with less memory when we actually have some kind
of a logging system.
Okay.
In fact.
Act.
You know what?
I'm just going to go ahead and do it.
I'm going to say this is going to be diagnostic, but we're not going
to report it.
Currently.
We're just going to do that.
All right.
So we've got the replay, buffer memory block thing.
We want to verify that we actually got it.
So actually the diagnostic goes here and then we'll all we're going to
do is on that elk.
All right, you know, we call begin recording input when we call that.
According input begin function.
What we want to do is we're going to move this to do because we're
actually doing now.
We're going to go ahead and say that instead of doing this gigantic,
right?
We're just not, we're going to ignore the right for now.
We're going to pretend that never happened and instead.
We're just going to seek to the place in the file that we would have
been after we do the right?
Because basically file handles the way that they work.
I don't know that we covered this yet.
So I should probably talk about a little bit a file.
Handle in win32 stores where it last wrote to.
And whenever you do a right sort of a pens, the rights just keep
going, sequentially in the file.
So if you open a file you start out assuming that you're going to
write or read from the very first bite in the file and then however
much you write or read.
It.
Moves the sort of the location that the next operation will occur.
It moves it by
Never you did.
So, if you try to write 300 bytes, then the next right will happen.
300 bytes into the file, you then write 500.
The next one will be 800 in, you know, right?
So as you kind of do the rights, they just stack on top of each other,
but you can also do seeking, right?
So you can do.
Think it's called set file, pause.
I don't know what it's called.
Set file pointer.
Is that what it's called?
I'm not sure what it's called.
We're going to find out in a second.
What it's called if msdn MSDS slow, man.
So slow.
Let's take a look.
I don't know if this is the the right thing.
I think it's set.
File pointer is all we really need.
Let's take a look at set valper.
No, ux as well.
See what that is.
Yeah.
So this is I think what we want this is, yeah.
This is what we want.
So step file pointer, X just moves, whatever that look that file
location is talking.
Is it just sets it to somewhere?
And so that's what we want.
What is the minimum?
What's the minimum system XP.
So that's fine.
So basically what we can do.
With this thing.
As we can say, we can give it a constant.
The constant says we're in, the files are reference point.
The current point, the end of the file, the beginning of the file.
And in the our case, we just want to say from the beginning of the
file.
We want to go a certain number of bytes and it's the number of bytes
that would have we would have left if we were going to write to the
file with the B to right thing.
Right?
So however many we would have written.
So all I want to do here is just leave space in the file, you know, I
want to leave the space at the beginning of the file for that block.
So that later.
We can write it.
So we're just going to call this.
We're going to pass that handle.
We're going to pass it the large integer.
So we've got see here.
This is a file position.
Right?
And this is again, those large integers with the quad part, how we
this is, how we set the 64-bit thing.
So we're basically going to do that that b written.
And in fact, you know what, this will this will also solve our to do
about the total size we can now actually do that total size.
I think we can do that properly.
Now if we do it the way we're about to do it.
So that's going to be nice to kind of get
Of a limitation there so we can have greater than 4 gigs of store if
we want there.
So we're going to get rid of this, right?
We're going to stop having this right work.
And we're just going to assume that we're going to set that that total
size as the new position.
So that all of our input gets written after that big block would have
occurred.
So.
Alright, we got the file position past that in there.
We don't actually need to know what the new position is.
We'll just assume it's right and we're going to do file begin as the
location.
So go ahead and compile that
what are you complaining about compiler?
No, Constructor could take the source, type too low.
Does it not take an address of?
It just takes an actual large integer.
You all right, even easier.
So we're going to do that.
And then in in lieu of the right instead of the right we're actually
going to do is we're going to just do a copy.
We're going to we're going to do a mem copy.
Essentially.
I don't know if we can just have Windows.
Do that copy for us.
I don't actually remember.
I think we can.
I believe that's totally valid.
Yeah so we can
Ask Windows to move to copy a block of memory.
Us from a source to destination with some length, right?
And I think that's just fine, but I don't know.
Let's see.
Well, yeah, I don't know if I want it to.
Yeah, this is this is looking less like what I want.
All right.
Well, you know what?
We're going to call it.
We're just going to call it for now, later on.
I think we'll we should have all our own memory moving stuff and maybe
I'll rather call ours in the win32 layers.
I usually try to call.
Win32 functions.
I don't know why that is, but I just kind of like to use win32 inside
win32.
That's not particularly logical.
I appreciate that, but that's just the way I do it.
All right, so we're going to say the state game memory block thing.
That that is where our game memory is.
So we're going to use that.
As a source.
We know the total size is is how much we want to copy.
And we know the destination is going to be that that memory block for
the recording that we allocated in back at that startup.
Right?
So we're going to do this.
Now, what we have to do, of course before we do any of this stuff is
we have to check whether this block is actually valid.
So we have to check whether we ever got.
The recording block.
So, if you take a look like, I'm going to go ahead and assert, this
input recording index is is less than that array count as well because
we might as well check our bounds here.
Essentially.
I just want to say all right, let's make sure the recording in.
This is inside the replay buffers and assuming it is.
We're going to get the replay buffer out, right?
So here's our replay buffer, our replay buffer.
Is is going to be whichever one.
It was asking for and we are going to try to get this record block out
of there.
So I guess I could just use replay, buffer, Arrow, memory block.
If the memory block couldn't be allocated.
I don't want to try to write to it or we'll just crash and that
doesn't seem like a good idea even though it is debug code.
So I'm going to go ahead and say, all right, let's let's check to see
if we actually have some memory there.
And if we do then we'll go ahead and do the copy and that's fine.
And the same thing will happen.
In fact, I could go ahead and make
So utility function since we're going to call it twice right here, I
could say this is get replay buffer.
Right?
And that replay, buffer thing takes the win32 state.
There's the state, and we go ahead and say that, that is this right
return results.
There's the results I can assert.
Some people were nervous about the potentially that it could be under
flowing.
I don't know how realistic that is, but we could also do this in
unsigned index.
Now, we
Oh that it can't be less than zero.
Okay, so I'm going to go ahead and make that happen.
Tidy it up there.
We can we can pretty much just assume now that this replay buffer.
Can be had by doing the wind to to get replay buffer.
This pig hat is hot.
Ladies and gentlemen, I hope I stop being a pig soon because I am
melting in here.
All right, cannot convert for win through to repeat buffer tube of.
Yes.
That's true.
We need to take the address of it.
And so, there we go.
Because we're asking for a pointer Index right past that there and we
should be good to go.
We don't need this anymore.
So there's our copy memory.
All right, so hopefully that'll work and we're just going to do the
exact same.
Same thing on the, the other side, right?
So we're going to do the exact same thing when we want to begin input
playback.
We're going to use the input playing index, get the replay buffer out,
assuming that there is a valid memory block for it.
We are going to go ahead and instead of this read file, that we used
to be doing this stuff right here.
We don't actually do that anymore.
We're just going to do the copy file.
I'm sorry the copy memory right out of the memory block.
So we're just reversing what we did.
So,
Copy it like that right now.
I don't know.
I slammed a bunch of code in there and you know that it's hard for me
to talk in code at the same time.
So, I don't know if it's going to work but we'll try it and see if it
does.
Oh, you know, what?
Forgot one thing before I even try it.
So we have to do the same thing with the set file pointer as well,
obviously because we up here left space in the file by it by
pretending, we did the right.
We basically move the file pointer pass where we would have done the
right.
The same is going to be true for the read file.
It would have move the pointer and we
To duplicate that behavior because we're about to start reading there.
And so, we need to make sure that our reads line up with where our
rights were and I can cover that in the Q&A.
If that's a little confusing, what happened there.
We can talk about that in a little more detail.
So we'll do the set file pointer here and that's going to be on the
playback handle.
We've got the file positions going to be that total size again.
Looks like that's looks right to me.
Everything's good there.
So let's take a look.
Let's see if that's, that's, that's something we could actually try.
So do the L.
That takes a phenomenally long time.
Did we crash or something?
I assume.
He crashed know.
Why did that take so long?
Shouldn't that?
That should not be even doing any disk operations.
So what is going on there?
That feels odd.
Doesn't it?
Feel odd to copy one gig of memory at the memory bandwidth.
This machine, something something's up.
Something is fishy II.
Want to tell you?
Ladies and gentleman.
I feel like something is very
Very fishy.
I think we've got a bug, a bug that is that is perhaps has been in
there since the very beginning.
I need to think it through.
But let's, let's see here.
Let's see here.
What happened?
I'm going to, I'm going to, I'm going to add a couple output debug
strings here, but we'll step through that and just make sure we know
what's going on.
Let's see here.
When 3 to begin recording input.
So, I guess the other thing we could do is not do this file thing at
all as well just in case that is creating a problem for somebody.
Well, let me just double check one thing.
Yeah, so like what is it doing there?
Right?
Is that really the cost of the copy because it seems odd that the copy
would take that long.
So this is Bears investigation is what I would say, so what I'm going
to do is I'm going to go ahead and comment out the copy just to see if
the copy has anything to do with it to see if the copy is really
taking that long.
Haha.
So it has nothing to do with the copy.
The copy is commented out in our code.
And we still have that huge cause, right?
So let's take a look even further and go.
All right.
What about the file pointer thing?
Three to get input file location ago.
According handle.
In fact what we could do, you know what I'm going to use a little
because we don't have a profile or yet.
I'm going to go ahead and use output debug string to sort of spam
things here.
And use a little technique that I often like to use, which is a
basically just going to go ahead and spam.
I'm going to spam indexes out to the debug Port, right?
And I'm going to spam them at each particular location.
So that we can see who stalls because I don't know, really know who
stalls.
This is not a glamorous way to do it.
But, you know, in short order, it's something we can do.
So let's go ahead and size that down there.
Get the output up.
There is our output.
So here, we're going and then we go l.
So, did you see what happened there?
That was pretty interesting.
I would say.
It actually got to hear relatively quickly.
So something after begin recording input is actually causing the
problem when 3 to begin recording input.
So we just have a flat out regular old bug.
That was presumably causing problems for us.
Even before this is very good.
I feel like, I feel like this is, this is a good thing that we looked
into this because we just had some we just have some other totally
erroneous Behavior happening.
Probably down in here somewhere.
We just have
Think stupid going on, if that makes sense.
So I want to see, I'm interested to know.
Yeah, what what exactly is going on there?
Because that was an interesting stall.
It stalled right after spam for.
So let's I guess I could step through it maybe and see because
remember,
It printed spam for right, you saw what happened.
You were here it printed this and then it didn't print this for a long
time.
Now, if you, if you could, think about what that means in terms of
flow control in terms of what happened in the code.
It means that we got.
I can never find my way around an MSP.
See we got here, right?
And then when we exited from that,
You remember when three to begin recording input is called here.
So we did whatever we were going to do here.
We exited out of this function of win32 process, pending messages,
right?
And then we we actually, you know, I don't know what happened.
We executing this.
This part of the code.
Just executing through all this for some reason, this time around
before we ever got to the frame output stuff because we still output
the
We still output this stuff, right?
Where did we output?
BT?
L 33?
Okay.
So basically spam for before this, this line right here.
The BTL line is all the way up here.
And so some something in between.
Yeah, in between when we, when we called the right up here, which is
happening here in between there and that BTL line took.
An enormous amount of time.
So I wonder if we could figure out who that is.
Let's just see if we can.
What's the name of this function Again?
Win32 Begin recording input.
Yeah.
This guy.
Let's see if we can figure out, who is responsible.
Just really simply.
Again, a profiler would make this very simple, but we don't have one
yet.
So we're going to do this the old-fashioned way.
So here we go.
We're going, we end up in here.
This happens that copy takes a little bit of time but not that much,
right?
And so we come out, here we go through.
Let's see what happens.
So we come out, you come in here, we get these things.
We process the keyboard messages, we go ahead and get our X input
State.
We do this a couple times you do.
We finish all the controllers.
None of them are.
Other are connected to come through here.
We try to record the input called the right file.
What?
Hmm.
Very interesting.
So it's as if the right file.
So I guess it's because the right file is having to actually reserved
all when it when you do that set file pointer call.
Is actually reserving all of that space.
Something of that nature.
Let's see if that is true set.
File pointer X.
Let's see what happens.
If we get rid of this, this file pointer situation here, go f-zero.
Let's see what happens if we if we go ahead and do that.
Yeah, so that's way faster right way, way.
Way way way faster.
Hmm.
Very interesting people very, very interesting.
So basically the act of setting the file pointer appears to be forcing
the operating system to actually like go through and do all of the
work on that span, which we really did not actually need it to do.
So.
I'm not sure how to solve that problem.
Exactly.
I'm not sure how to tell it that.
We don't care very much about that.
We could make it so that we have two separate files one for the input
stream in 14, the backing store.
I don't know.
I do not know what we want to do about that.
So what I was going to do, I'll tell you the rest of what I was going
to do is I was going to go ahead and do a memory map file, which is
basically where you tell windows that a portion of memory is just
supposed to be mapping a portion of a file.
I was going to do that for the memory block.
And so that way Windows would just commit it to disk when we closed,
or crashed or whatever and wouldn't think that it needed to write
stuff all the time now, I don't actually know if
Windows, I don't actually know if windows will be smart enough.
If I do that memory map and then we do the set file pointer thing.
I don't know if it'll be smart enough to know what to do and not to do
what it's doing right now, which I assume is that it's taking the time
to go ahead and Pat out that file.
Yeah.
Yeah, so very interesting and and you can see in fact, to Loop edit
HMI is very tiny when we don't do that.
And so it's very big when we don't set the file pointer because it's
only recording, just the input into their.
Yeah, so I don't know what we should do.
I don't know.
Maybe we should try the memory mapped file thing and see what happens
just for education.
Isis.
I don't know or maybe we shouldn't.
Maybe this is a bad idea.
I'm not sure I really
No, I'm torn.
Here's what I will say.
Let's try the simplest.
Let's try the stupidest thing that we can think of so far.
And Let's do let's do the stupidest thing and we'll see if the
stupidest thing works.
So so difficult.
Alright, so basically what we're going to do here is
Let's just try.
Let's try it.
Let's do map view of file and we'll see what happens.
So I'm going to see if Matt, I'm just gonna see if map view.
A file will be relatively easy for us to do.
We'll just try it.
We'll just put it in there and we'll see what happens.
So it should be pretty easy.
So, basically, what this does is this tells Windows to correspond a
piece of memory with it with a file.
And every time you touch the memory, it will write it to the file,
right?
So it kind of just it sets up a mapping between the two.
And so if I wanted to do
Going to go ahead down here.
And I'm going to go ahead and do that in that inside that Loop where
we do the memory mapping thing.
So instead of virtual allocating this we're actually just going to
going to have that memory is actually just going to be a map view of
file.
Right?
And so what I'm going to do is I'm going to go ahead and change it.
So that what we do in here essentially is we do file star.
Hmm.
Yeah, the handle.
So this is this is the file handle.
This is to the replay file.
Yeah.
So basically what we're going to do is we're going to say all right,
we got the replay buffer.
We're going to have it's not really file handle and it's not file
star.
Don't know why I did that as a handle again getting kind of confused
in my head.
All right.
So we want to do is we got this.
We want to basic setup, this memory mapping.
So we need to call this, I guess.
Memory map might be the better word for it.
So we're going to have to get that memory.
Somehow.
So we've got the file mapping object.
We are desired access is is going to be everything.
I think we want to do read, write and copyright.
Well, we don't want be so we just want all access I believe.
Yeah.
Yeah, so we want found that all access that again just doing the
stupidest possible thing here.
The offset in the file is just 0 0.
The number of bytes to map is whatever that total size is, right.
And that's all.
So we're just going to say, hey, look, I want you to map this file for
us, please.
And I want it to be this big.
So that's all that's going to do.
And what that's going to do is that's going to return us an LP void,
which is the memory block.
So, basically, instead of virtual allocating the memory, we're asking
Windows to basically set up the memory as a map to the files.
So we don't need to Virtual allocate anymore because basically the
memory map will do the allocation and it's not really an allocation.
It's a mapping.
So it's allocating the memory, but it's also saying that it
corresponds directly the disc and windows.
Bands that Hugh a does not begin.
Now just in case I was wondering because I want to actually see if
this works.
Ignore the timer, ignore the timer.
So yeah, what we want to do here, is this memory map.
We just got to figure how to get that and I assume we just need open
file mapping.
Let's see here.
Let's see opens a name file mapping object.
Let's in fact, you know what?
Let's see about create file mapping.
Let's see handle the file from, which create the file mapping.
The file must be open with access rights.
Compatible.
Yes, that's fine.
Will it create the file if it doesn't exist as my question, let's see.
Because that's that is a problem for us.
If that doesn't work.
Let's see if the others is for the function called which enhance the
existing object.
That's fine.
So yeah, you know, maybe this will just work.
Let's go ahead and try it again.
We don't have a lot of time, just gonna go ahead and try it.
Basically, what we're telling Windows here is what the file is that
we're trying to map to so we have to pass it a file handle of course,
so we're basically
We have to do replay buffer.
I guess I will still need the file handle as well.
So we'll do a file handle the security attributes.
I think we don't care, so we don't care about that.
At all the F, protect.
We want readwrite.
Access to the pages.
Certainly good.
We've got the maximum size high and low, so the maximum size high and
low, we actually need to get out of the total size, so I don't
actually know.
Are and then we got our, we got our file name as well, our replay file
name, which we haven't filled out yet.
There's the replay buffer.
There's the file name.
So I guess we can just call this.
Alright, so we got that.
And basically the total size here it wants us to pass the high and the
low separately.
So I guess what it's asking us to do is something like this, right?
It's basically saying alright, it wants the high first, right?
So I'm going to shift down.
This is a 64-bit value.
I'm going to shift that down by 30.
To and pass it.
So that will get that and then it will, and then we'll pass the bottom
just, you know, as is, which I assume we want to do, just and it out.
So basically just pull out those bottom bit.
So I'm going to pull out the bottom 32 here.
And the topic here.
I thought there was I feel like there is ways to pull those out that
that Windows just had.
Like I said, I usually like to call Windows is functions.
I feel like there was a macro for like, you know, there was no, it's
like high word lowered, but I don't know if they exist for
Or, I don't know if they exist for bigger types.
There's High B and low byte, but I don't know if there's a high long,
there's a make long now because I don't know.
You think they would have it, right?
They have stuff for extracting, the other pieces, but not that one.
Alright, well, we'll deal with that later.
I guess the fact that maybe we'll make our own macros for it.
I don't know.
Just seems like they should have had that.
Since if they want you to pull apart 64-bit values.
They should have had a thing that does that.
So that everyone does it uniformly incorrectly, right?
Who knows if we wrote this bug Ali, you know, you want a macro so that
the user doesn't have to screw up or Can't Screw Up.
I should say if there's no real reason to not have that habit.
So, all right.
So we need to make one of these file names.
I'm going to go ahead and and and make that happen with the HMI file.
Let's see here.
So we've got this guy and we will have to start making this, do
something a little smarter.
So what I need to do is insert the name in
They're so I'll use that Windows sprintf function again that we had
before to basically make one of these for each of the slots.
So I'm just going to go ahead and create a string here using that slot
index.
Using the windows has formatting function that we used before and
we'll just make that.
So we can quickly get one for each of our files.
So, we'll call this win32 get input file location.
Excuse me, and we will, we will actually open.
The file handle directly in that, that that code down.
So instead of opening it on when we actually start recording or stop
recording.
We'll just open it right off the bat.
Yeah.
So what we want to do here is take that that file name, where is okay,
so we have to open the files.
Well, we want to do.
We want to do everything that's in here.
We want to move all of this stuff.
Every last thing that was in here.
We want to move all of this stuff into here, essentially.
And we want these
Has to be generic, read engineer, right?
We want both kinds of access to it essentially, and we will go ahead
and say that the right file is gone as well.
We want to keep this guy in there.
We gotta get rid of that.
You have our copy memory.
That's all good.
I have to get rid of this guy.
So there we go.
Copy memory.
We don't want to open the playback handle.
We don't want to get the file name.
We don't do any of that stuff.
That's just going to happen automatically now.
All right.
So first we have to generate
File name, one file name for every one of our replay buffers that we
have.
So let's go ahead and do that right off the bat here will generate
that with the replay index.
So we'll have one for every file.
One for every replay.
A different file name for every replay.
So will generate that.
We will then go ahead and open the file handle.
Oh, so I should, that is true.
I do need to keep doing this part.
The recording handle does have to be the replay buffers file handle,
right?
Right.
There we go.
Like that way back, handle and recording handle creating handle.
Here we go.
So I do need to do that.
So in here, I don't know if we need to open a second handle.
I don't know if this thing eats the handle and we can't ever use the
handle again.
So I don't know if we can't use the same handle that we were using or
not.
So, we'll have to take a look at that in a second.
But for now, we'll just open one handle.
So we have a replay buffer.
And it has a file handle, right?
We're going to open that with both read and write privileges so that
we can both read and write from it will create that file handle.
I don't know if we need to pass a thing there that says it's okay for
mapping will see you in a second.
I'll read the documentation and find out then we should be able to map
it.
We do the map.
We we've been got our memory block in theory that will then be a
backing store and that's in theory.
All we would have to actually do now.
I don't know if there is anything else that I'm forgetting here.
Chances are hard.
A good that we are but let's see.
Replay buffer, file name.
So, wait a minute.
Why am I passing the file?
Name twice?
Did I not actually have to do this?
Create file.
I feel like that doesn't make sense.
I feel like I was going too fast there, and I write, because you see
what I'm saying.
I passed the file name in two places.
Doesn't seem right.
Right.
So either, I don't have to create this Handler.
I don't have to pass that file name.
It seemed it seemed odd if I had to do both.
So let's just go back here and pay a little more attention staff.
So quickly and just see what happens.
So the name of the file mapping object.
This is Paramount.
Oh, yeah.
Oh, okay.
So this is not this is not the file name.
This is not what we want.
Yeah.
So we, this is just if we wanted to refer to this mapping by name, so
we do need to make the file handle.
That's, that was not supposed to beat a fella named.
That's just, that's just a wrongheaded thing.
Okay, so we have the replay, buffer, get the file name.
Go ahead on that go in.
So let's step in here and see what, what crazy stuff we have wrought
now.
Because I just, I just did a ton of crap there.
And so I think it would be good to go through and see what I did.
Because even I don't remember everything at this point that we just
did.
Okay.
So, first things first, we're going to get a file name.
And oh, right?
We can get rid of that assertion.
Now we were previously asserting that it was only slut index 1 because
we weren't handling slot into C's, but we are actually handling slot,
indices now, so we can get rid of that.
So that's fine.
Off we go.
So let's step back into there and see.
There we go.
And let's see what that produced Loop.
Edit 0.
That looks good.
So we get that file name.
Let's see what the the file name produced.
Let's go ahead and delete these guys.
Go, go, go away.
There we go.
Let's take a look at what that replay buffer looks like right now.
Okay, so it should have the file name in there.
It does.
We try to open the file handle that succeeded.
We try to open the memory map and that did not succeed.
So we have an error there.
That's bad.
Right?
That did not work at all.
Nobody's.
Why is that execute read, right?
I did not actually want it to be executed, right?
That's wrong regardless.
But yeah, so we have some, we have some some bad news, you know,
there's, there's, there's some bad things happening here.
So this call is wrong.
And then this call fail as well, obviously, because if you can't, if
we can't get the fat mapping.
All right, so let's let's go ahead.
And first of all, I don't, I don't understand why I've got
Age execute read, right?
Because we're not supposed to be executing anything from this.
So that's just that's just wrong.
I think we, this, this is what I actually wanted.
We wanted page read, right?
Yes.
So this is this is inside create file mapping.
We've got the the FL protect what this should have been is that should
have been paid rewrite.
So that's what that should have been.
Okay, and then I want to know what these guys are.
So this is, this is let's make these these
He's maximum size, High maximum size, low thing, and what, let's read,
what those actually are.
Let's see remarks.
The hierarchy were to the maximum size lower.
Do you were to this filament?
Yeah, the maximum size value is equal to the current size of the file.
So, no, I don't want that.
So I want this to actually be.
Yeah.
I want I want this to actually be what we think the size is so these
are going to be Max sighs.
Hi.
And I'm saying that, that is
This right and Max sighs low, and I'm saying that that is this, there
we go, and so max sighs.
Hi, Max sighs low.
And we can, at least inspect those and see what they are.
And let's also see what are the requirements?
Are there requirements on.
On these guys as well.
It's not like I just baked is backed by the operations and paging
file.
The H file parameter specifies that when have you felt that across the
entire range of pages committed.
We don't care.
I don't think they care about that stuff.
All right.
So what I want to know is does this have to have any kind of just have
anything special about the file handle that we should know?
Let's see if I'm mapping creates a film.
I've got a specified.
Size is backed by the system paging file.
Now, we don't want to do that.
I wonder if it
Set the the size of the underlying file to be big enough.
I don't know if that's a requirement either.
We'll see.
So the other thing we can do here is I assume that when this fails, it
will set the last error in Windows to say, what the error actually is.
So we could call get last error and see what that error is.
So I'm going to go ahead and put a call in there so we can take a look
at it.
So yeah, so I'm going to go ahead and here and say this is failing.
So let's take a look at what that is.
Are.
Our equals get last there.
And so let's say we go in here and we run it.
And our file handle.
Oh, whoops.
It's the memory map that fails not the file handle.
My bad.
I want to see that actually.
Okay, so we come in here, we call this and it's wrong.
What's our high and low, by the way that looks about right to me, Max
sighs.
Whoa, let's see that in hexadecimal for
That wait a minute.
Wait a second.
What is the total size?
Hear that, right?
Okay.
Yeah, that's right.
All right.
Okay.
Yeah.
All right.
I can be satisfied with that.
Anyway, so we got the, we got the, the Mac side of the max Laszlo.
They look about, right.
Let me let me verify that they do go in that order as well.
Just want to make sure that that's the case high and low.
Yes, so we've got that done but we didn't succeed it getting our
memory map.
Oh.
This time we did succeed at getting our memory map.
What, what what do we talk?
So is it just the execute bit?
That was the problem?
Weird, so it's a fact that was page, execute read, right?
I guess that's about the only thing we changed.
All right, so there's no error now.
Let's see if map view of file succeeds.
It does so off we go.
Yes, that's very odd.
So now we have those files mapped, which means in theory, those files
should exist in the build directory, correct?
And there they are.
They're all the right size as well, which is good.
So, I don't know.
That looks like, it worked very strange.
So, that's
I guess that was just because I had the execute bit acts out
accidentally pasted the execute one in there, which I should not have
done.
But I guess that was just, that was the only problem.
All right, so when we're actually doing the recording here, let's go
back and check to make sure we're doing this correct properly.
So when we say, we're going to be recording, we go ahead and we get
that replay buffer.
We take a look at the input recording index and we set that to be, you
know, what's, what's being recorded.
Currently, we go ahead and set the recording handle.
Don't even know if this is actually necessary anymore, but probably
is.
Anyway, we go ahead and seek past the part that we mapped.
And then that way all the rights will happen past there.
And then we copy the memory into that memory map block that we use
before.
And the same happens in Reverse down here.
So I don't know that this may actually just work.
I don't know if it will or not because I don't know if you can memory
map a file and write to file handles like that, but we will certainly
try.
So,
You what happens now?
So we go down here.
We hit L, we get that really long.
Pause on that first, right, still happening, which is annoying.
So we didn't, we didn't read, we reset the state properly, but we're
not reading back from the file properly.
So I do wonder if perhaps this thing does not actually work.
The way that we would want it to, I'm not actually sure, but it's
still getting a bit.
That's that still looking a bit wonky.
So let's say just for the sake of argument that we split this into two
streams, temporarily to see what happens as a baseline in that
circumstance.
So let's say we pass a slot index.
And a pool.
Whether it's the input stream, right?
So we
Something like this.
And so then there's just a loop edit and then it's underscore string.
We take a look at what whether the input stream is set or not.
If it is, then it's the input.
Otherwise, it's the state, write something like that.
And then we'll just actually do a separate open and a separate closed
for these guys entirely.
So what is this?
Does not take four arguments.
That's true.
It does not take four arguments.
So let's go ahead and do that and put file location.
So what I want to do here right is I want to sort of go back to the
old way of doing it, but just for the input stream and we're going to
store the state in a separate file.
So the input goes into one file, the state goes into another file just
so I can see what the Baseline performance is of that and so we could
figure out why writing to one file is causing us so much headaches.
We've got the input stream thing coming in here.
So this is not the input stream, right?
It is not.
And so if I compile that I should get the thing, that's not the input
stream and then I do the begin recording input stuff, so we can hear.
The recording handle is now not going to be that file handle.
It's going to be an actual file handle.
We're not going to do the seek to seek is out.
We're just going to write to a separate file.
And so we're going to do it like this, right?
There we go.
File name and file name, we go.
Lovely, lovely, lovely.
So we're just going to do this, right?
We're going to go ahead and get the new file name.
That's what we're going to end.
We're going to create that file entirely from Whole cloth just like we
were doing before.
So I'm going to do the create file a, I'm going to use the exact stuff
that we were using here.
So file name,
That generic right?
And there we go.
So we've got the clothes handle thing.
Oh, you know what?
This was dumb as well, because we didn't want to keep closing it.
It doesn't actually matter because that was long after our bug
occurred, but that was something to that.
Was we shouldn't have of ever been bothering to close the handle that
was just dumb.
That would have caused problems later.
We just, we haven't gotten far enough to have them cause US problems.
All right.
So anyway, we've got our
File here, generic, right?
Create always, that looks fine to me.
We don't need to do the seek.
So we do that recording handle will close it.
When we end the recording, We Begin playback will do the opposite.
The playback handle will now be this thing and we'll go ahead and do
that.
So we take that out and put my index.
So now we're going to we're going to open the the file for read and
will do open existing to try and get the input back.
And that is again not going to do the seek and then with the clothes
comes back.
So I think that's roughly all I really wanted to have.
Ben what is what is the complaint?
Yeah.
File name is not need to not need an address there.
What, why was there an address there?
Oh, because that was just full on the lon Salon bogus.
That's what to take the state.
Not, the founding.
Don't know what I was thinking there.
Okay.
So let's take a look at what we've got now.
So off we go, we hit l.
So that looks fine to me.
Right?
Nothing particularly odd there and it does seem like this is now much
faster than it was right that pauses pretty brief compared to the old
paws.
I think there's no doubt that that's considerably faster, right?
Yeah.
So, yeah, I'm a little confused as to why the behavior is such that
setting that file pointer causes that problem.
But it's not like we really care because having them into files is not
really a problem for us.
It's totally fine for us to do that.
Let's, let's delete these guys here.
So, if they're gone.
So if we go ahead and run, this startup is instantaneous, even though
we have mapped those files because all it's doing is reserving the
space on the disk for them.
Right?
And that's fine.
But now if I go back into here when I initially do that, I do get a
you know, it's a much shorter pause that before but I'm still not sure
if that's how long the pause should be.
That still seems like perhaps a little long for the copy seemed to
take that long, which was kind of odd.
I feel like the memory
Within this machine should be higher than that, but maybe that's just
my intuition being incorrect.
I'm not sure but point being were way faster than we were before.
So that's at least good progress.
And I maybe we don't necessarily need to belabor the point much longer
we can think about this a little bit more and you know, someday we
want a bonus thing to do.
We can look at it again.
What I think would be interesting to do here, maybe is too.
I wonder if we want to actually support all four of the streams.
Now, by actually putting in
One two, three four kind of a system.
Maybe you hit alt 12 record that or something like this.
So you do alt one and then, you know, ended or something like that.
I'm not sure.
Hard to say, we'll leave it like this for now and if we ever need
anything it, when we need more, we'll use more.
All right.
Well, I think that's probably.
We enough for now because we did blow through a bunch of Q&A time,
which I will just go long on the Q&A.
I like on Fridays to kind of go along.
I don't try to think if there's anything else I want to do.
I don't think there is.
I just wanted to look and see how long that would take.
And this is something.
If people want something to play around with it, home trying to figure
out exactly what is taking the time.
There might be interesting seeing, if that copy memory thing happens
at a reasonable speed as well.
Like should it be taking as long as it is?
How long should it take to copy one gigabyte?
Height of memory because I'm not sure what the memory bandwidth is of
this machine.
Right?
Like I'm not sure how long one megabyte should take to copy.
And so what we need to do is actually figure that out.
I don't know.
I mean, I guess we could potentially if I go in here I suppose we
could take a look.
This is a w 5580, right?
That's the processor type.
And so if I were to go here and say, w55 a team,
Memory bandwidth with somebody.
Tell me what it was right?
So, let's see.
I don't know what the memory bandwidth is.
There's a lot of things that have the word memory bandwidth.
I don't know if they will actually tell me what the memory bandwidth
is.
Let's see, is this mb/s unbuffered memory test?
Is this unbuffered memory bandwidth?
Mb/s.
Higher is better.
So
I mean, okay, so I don't actually know right.
I mean, I'm not I'm II know nothing about this CPU.
I don't even remember.
Like, I had to look up.
Even what would she be was in this machine?
But if this is actually an unbuffered memory test, right, it's saying
that this is the number of megabytes per second, right?
So, ten thousand megabytes per second is in like the 10 gigabytes a
second range, right?
So 10 gigabytes a second means that it should take a tenth of a second
to copy a gigabyte of memory, right?
I mean
In theory, it should really not be taking the amount of time that
we're seeing.
So it feels like something is still kind of wrong there.
And so maybe I'm just misreading this but you understand why I'm a
little apprehensive about what we're seeing.
So I don't actually know again what these I'm not sure.
I'm not even reading these Pages because I don't have time to kind of
sit here and and read through them on stream.
But like it's a bit odd.
Let's see what this says.
Here we go.
Here's the spec sheet, right?
Here's the spec sheet for the w55, 80.
And so, here's the, the stuff here.
UPI, speed, right transfers, computer components are between
computers.
We don't actually care about that.
Where's the memory bandwidth?
Max, memory science?
Wow, that's a lot of memory 144 GB.
Max very bandwidth.
32, GB s.
So
You see why I'm perplexed.
Right?
You see why?
I don't feel like we're doing things correctly because if the
processor is supposed to be able to get a max memory bandwidth of 32
gigabytes, a second then, even if we were only getting like, 10% of
that memory bandwidth, we should be getting 3 gigabytes a second which
means it should take 300 milliseconds to copy a gigabyte of memory
that is taking more like a second, right?
And we can go time it and see exactly how long it's
But it ain't as fast as it should be.
So there's something else, like
The operating system is interceding in a way there.
I think that is making it perhaps so that like, you know, maybe those
pages that were mapped to the file as we're doing the copy into them
or something like that.
I don't know.
Maybe it's maybe it's getting its having to sort of write them for the
first time.
I did it.
Let's see what happens when we do to records in a row.
Let's ask that question, right?
So there's the first record not taking too long but still takes longer
than I think it should.
Okay.
Now we Loop and We're looping, right, but I can stop looping if I want
to and do another record, right?
So
So that makes it may actually just be the initial work of the paging
the initial time that it has to do this stuff.
Maybe that's the case because now it's like alright, let's do our
recording and it's like
Yeah, I don't know.
I don't know.
It's a little bit.
It's a little bit confusing to me.
So, all right.
Well, let's just go ahead and and and I'm sorry, I'm sorry.
I'm obsessing on this.
I know that it's just on the Friday stream.
I can obsess because I don't have any hard deadline to stop me.
So anyway, let's see if this is down, if the input recording index is
0, that's it.
So we need a way, we don't have a way to stop recording, right?
We have no way to actually end the recording.
So we need to do is if the, if the info recording is 0, then it
starts.
We need to basically say we need to we need to do if state plate
playing.
Playback index or whatever.
It is.
What's the what's input playing index if that equals 0, then we do
this.
But otherwise if if not, we end playback and Playback.
Oops getting too close to my head.
So right like basically I do is say okay if there was nothing playing
then if there was nothing recording then we begin recording.
Otherwise we end recording and begin playback.
If there was something playing we just stop whatever was playing right
and I feel like that should do.
Do it.
And I want to make sure that actually works because there's like some
ping-pong logic in there.
Right?
And I want to make sure that that it actually works somewhat reliably,
right?
So I'm here, I hit L.
I do my little dance.
I hit elegant and we're playing back.
We're looping right?
Looping.
I hit Elvis top and now we're back in control.
Let's see if we can do it again.
L, do up and down.
It's a little Sawtooth.
Bloop.
Yeah, so it looks like we're good.
Yeah, looks like we're good.
I would call that certainly not shippable quality, but I would call
that good enough for debugging purposes for now.
So, yeah, let's let's say that that's good.
And the other thing, you know, what I want to do here as well is I
want to do the win32.
We do that sort of drawing of the audio buffer, the sort of succinct
display thing.
So I want to basically get rid of that for now and say that this is is
not going to
Pain anymore.
See here, when 32 or you know, what am I allowed?
Let's, let's talk about this for a second.
Am I allowed to do this to prevent that warning?
Can I just do still leave it the call in, but have it be on a call
that can never actually happen.
Additional stress.
No, I guess.
I can't.
All right.
Well, in that case, I guess we will just go ahead and comment out that
call for now.
And talk will just get rid of the call entirely.
And then the win32 sync, display went through to sink display.
We are going to, cause the next time, we revisit that, we're going to
put it the drawing up in the actual platform code using a real
renderer, so we can draw stuff for real.
So I'm just going to go ahead and and comment out this stuff entirely.
Because we don't actually need it and we will be moving it out into
the platform layer later.
So there we go.
We are now at least only doing
So we're been the Tigers on we're at now least only doing the
rendering that we actually need to do in the game and everything is
rendering inside the game, which is what we wanted.
We still have our frame rate print out and that is something.
I guess we can turn off as well at the moment.
We got rfps kind of print out here, we can turn that off because I
don't think we actually care about that at all.
So, we'll turn that off.
And these will be things that like I said, will hoist up into the
actual platform code when we have.
So we can have a kind of real debug displays and not these sort of
hacky ones.
So we're not printing out anything every frame anymore.
So that's good.
Kind of have that going.
Do our input Loop, double check that that actually works.
There we go.
It's in good shape.
Alright, I think that's it.
Everything else seems relatively good.
Alright, so let's call that for the day.
We did an extra 30 minutes today of coding because I was kind of
curious about what was going on there with those memory mapped files.
I feel like there's still more, we need to learn.
I feel like we need to learn really like what the most efficient way
is to get Windows to kind of
To do the most efficient thing there and I don't know if maybe we need
to not do.
I'm not trying to think it's like the copy memory is doing something
else that we that we, that it shouldn't be doing or what exactly is
happening and will have to time it.
Maybe we'll do some profiling.
So so I would like to know more about that.
I'm not satisfied with my understanding of what Windows is doing in
that case, and I feel like there's stuff that were missing.
So I'm going to go ahead and say to do Casey recording.
I'm still seems to take too long on record.
Start find out what Windows is doing and if we can speed up defer,
some of that processing.
So yeah.
Yeah.
All right.
Well, that is it for now.
Let us let us do some Q&A.
I think it's time for some Q&A.
So, please put see me oratory.
I'm going to go ahead and whoo, I'm hot.
Get my hair is all I got Pig hair.
You know what?
I can't see it.
Let me see what I look like.
Yeah.
It kind of matted me down.
I'm all matted down for the pig.
You know, it looks like some kind of it.
Looks like some kind of a skull cap here, right?
Yeah awful.
All right, anyway, but you know, when you wear the big hat, you got to
take the consequences, right?
You can expect to have fabulous hair after you wear the big hat.
All right, so I think that's it.
Let us do questions and that'll be good.
And that will be good.
And please put Senior ettore in your question.
Let's see.
Maybe first copy is causing Alec and 0 on fault.
Maybe a second copy could be would be fast.
So yeah, I mean that's what I was assuming is basically.
Like there's some kind of like Windows is clearing in the pages or who
knows what's happening, but it doesn't really explain.
Why the second copy wasn't more instantaneous?
I mean 300 milliseconds shouldn't be even that perceptible to us.
Like, it shouldn't look like a second pause.
So I don't.
And that was, you know, it's supposed to get 32 men, 32 megabytes Peak
and it was getting 10, MB s in the Sandra Benchmark or whatever.
That means.
It should only be taking, I'm sorry, 10 gigabytes.
A second.
That means should be taking 100 milliseconds.
That should be.
We should only see like a 3 frame pause right to do that copy.
So it's just a little
Little dicey, so I don't know.
Yeah, and and what we really need to do, if we want to, if we want to
investigate this further, it start timing these copy memories.
See, how long they're taking, and make sure it's reasonable.
Let me see.
What is that?
Total size set to again, make sure I'm not misremembering.
So it's 1.
GB + 64 megabytes, right?
1 GB, + 64 member MB transistors.
Sorry, I'm just
trying to think here.
So I think that's all correct.
I mean it certainly seems it.
So if we come in here, let's double-check, if we come in here, we do
total size.
Oops, total size is undefined win32 State, total size.
Right?
Let's do X decimal display.
And that does look like 1 GB + 64 MB that that does seem reasonable.
So, yeah, I mean, I don't know.
I don't know why it's having such trouble.
But yeah, we'd have to start doing some more serious profiling.
Which someday we will do when we have more profiling tools.
Can you turn off the sound?
Can you log onto the chat?
So the app will autocorrect turn off the sound.
Do you mean just not produce the debug sine wave?
But as for logging into the chat, I login by RC is the problem.
So, that's the problem with the auto correct.
Let's see.
An interesting part of this project is that you're implementing.
All the components yourself that you take as given in an existing game
engine.
That said, do you intend for these components to be reusable in future
projects?
IE there by almost, creating a new game engine in its own, right?
Or is it all or is all the code tightly coupled to handmade hero?
I guess what I would say is I'm not sure because it will depend how
things come out.
I am not trying to make a game engine that can.
Used.
So I will not be doing anything extra to make things reusable.
So it is likely that a lot of things will be relatively tightly
coupled to handmade hero.
That said, it may be that in the course of making handmade hero.
There's a number of things that just happen to be easily reusable
because that's just the most sensible way to write them anyway, but
yeah, I don't care about making a reusable engine.
That's not part of the goal of the project.
The goal is to make an engine that runs handmade hero so that you can
see how it works.
That makes sense.
Us.
Why the pig hat?
Because we're being piggy.
I mean, we allocated like five gigabytes of memory on Startup, right?
That's very piggy.
You have to admit, it's kind of piggy.
Why don't you use the visual studio?
Profiler and analyze performance?
Well, honestly, because I'd rather write it ourselves.
So you can see how to have a built-in profiler.
So we will be like making our own like profiling tools.
So we can kind of see how they work.
That makes sense.
C.
300 milliseconds.
Yeah, but 300.
So I was saying, 30 seconds, cause I just randomly said, 10% of the
bamboo bandwidth.
So that was like a maximum, the standard Benchmark.
Looks like it said, 10 gigabytes a second sustained.
So, you know, if it's 10 gigabytes a second sustain that should be 100
milliseconds or, you know, three frames, right?
Which is just not that many but maybe, you know, it's hard to say
well, if we actually timed it which is what the next.
Be, we would know for sure.
How much longer is taking?
Does it lack if you save a smaller file size?
That's a good idea, because that's pretty easy to test.
So, suppose we take a look at these and we just say we're going to
delete them.
Right?
So we delete all our HMI files, they're gone, right?
And let's say we go in here and now say that instead of allocating a
gigabyte.
There's just no transient storage.
It's it's, you know, another 64 GB megabytes of transient storage.
So now, we're just writing 128 megabytes, much, much less than we were
before.
It's certainly much faster.
Right, there's no question.
That's much faster.
So it's all becoming.
So is definitely proportional to size.
There isn't a some totally stupid bug where we're just doing something
really, really dumb.
But but yeah, but it's it what exactly whether it whether it should
should be that slow though is
Is another question.
So yeah.
Yeah, I'm sorry.
I'm not I'm not going to turn off the debug sound because we're going
to be replacing the debug sound with actual sound playback.
So we just kind of have there's going to be sound sounds going to
happen.
Yes.
The CPU memory bandwidth only valid for on die.
Memory know I that that number.
So where was that page?
Okay.
So basically this I believe well, actually I'm not sure where is the
cash bandwidth?
I don't know what all of these are actually referring to but basically
the the memory bandwidth that they quote is for actually out to main
memory.
At least that's always been my experience in the past.
So 32 gigabytes a second is the speed.
It can talk to the memory bus that actually goes to memory, right?
So at that's not talking about the cache which is the thing that's on
chip.
There is no on-die memory.
We in terms of memory.
It's just the cash.
Right?
I mean it is on die memory, but we don't have stacked RAM on the on
Intel chip.
So it's not like there's two gigabytes of memory like sitting on the
chip or something.
There's only just that cash.
So basically like the cache, the cache bandwidth should be much higher
than 32 GB s 32 gigabytes, a second would be pretty slow for for the
cash.
I think.
Is the intent of saving the complete Game state to support something
like a rewind function, that braid allows.
No, you would have to do a much more efficient implementation.
If you want this to be a runtime feature, this is a debug feature and
it's so that we can tune things.
So like if we wanted to work on, you know, the feel of oh, you know,
you push the button and it shoots and like, oh, we've got the muzzle
flare and all these sorts of things.
And we want to start tuning all those effects and whatever we can just
do it.
Whatever the action is in game.
With the looping on and then edit the code live as we go and see the
results.
So it's not meant to be a gameplay feature.
It strictly for our debugging purposes.
It won't leave.
It won't even be enabled in the shipping version.
It's only for our debug build.
Will you do a string pool?
Probably not a string pool know we will probably do a string stack,
but I doubt we'll ever do a string pool and it won't really be a
string stack.
It'll be a we will use stacks for our strings, but they will not be
exclusively for string stacks.
When you say the platform a circular, does that mean game code and
renderer and logging sorts of things or is there a sharper distinction
between some of those?
If not, could you clarify, your naming and layer structure, just a
little.
So, basically, the only structure that we have is, there's the
platform code, which is like, 32 underscore, or later.
They'll be like mac underscore or Linux underscore, and then there's
all the rest of the code.
So, basically, the only distinction that I'm making is essentially
between stuff that only runs on one platform and stuff that runs on.
Every platform.
So the idea is I want to push.
Much code is possible up into the stuff that runs on every platform so
that you don't have to do a ton of work to implement each new
platform.
You want to only do the work that's necessary to do the stuff that is
different on that platform, right?
A quick test on might be see.
Gave me around 3 gigabytes a second.
So that's pretty bad memory bandwidth, but that might be logical for
older PCS or laptops.
Maybe, I don't know, but that seems kind of low.
What kind of processor do you have?
See ya Uplink coder.
Do you know what?
What CPU you have?
Can you can you look at which CPU have if you go into like the this
guy and look at this?
Is that would be interesting information to have?
But yeah, I'm just that, that's not cash bandwidth.
I refuse to believe that's cash bandwidth.
It's so low.
It just seems like that would be crazy for cash bandwidth, but
Maybe I'm wrong about that.
Is it time to split the source into more files?
Well, when we start programming in handmade dot CPP, we will be
splitting him a DOT CP into lots of files.
Yet.
They'll be, they'll be lots of files there whether we'll ever split
the win32 file in the model files.
I don't know if there's a real good reason to maybe but there hasn't
really been any real reason to yet.
Woody non caching right be faster for the memory copy, you know the
SSC, right.
Instructions that bypass the cache.
I don't see why it would be because the cash is not really the
problem.
Here.
We are out of cat like we're writing enough memory that the cash can't
help us at all.
So I'm like usually the reason that you do a right to bypass the cache
and again, I'm not really a CPU guy.
So maybe there's another reason why you would do this, but my my
understanding of that was the reason that you do a right that
bypasses, the cash is because you don't want to pollute.
The cash with the contents of the right, but in our case we're reading
and writing so much memory there that were entirely out of cash in
both cases.
So avoiding polluting, the cash would really have nothing to do with
what's going on.
The cash.
I mean maybe you should do it just because that way the whatever was
in the cast beforehand still in there so that you don't take a hit on
the next piece of code, that's going to execute but I don't think it
would change the right speed because since the cash is very small
like, you know, I don't know.
Let's say 8, MB here.
It says, right?
And we're writing a gigabyte, the cash just isn't involved.
We're out of cast the entire time.
So the only number that matters is here.
Like we're not going to get any cash.
Affects.
I don't think but I could be wrong about that said I'm not really
asleep.
You guy.
When are the four HMI files created?
The HMI files are created right here in this for I loop at startup.
So, you know, we come in here, we sort of do our initialization.
We have our window, we get the refresh rate.
We set up the sound, we allocate the memory for the game.
And then we do a loop over each one of the replay buffers that we want
and we create the file right here.
So here's the thing, that creates the file.
Here's the thing that map's it into memory or rather.
Here's the thing that creates the
It allows us to map it into memory.
And here's the call.
That actually Maps it into memory.
An AMD A8 6600 K.
So that is an AMD, A8 6600 K memory bandwidth.
Let's take a look.
If we could find that out.
What is this?
Here we go, frequency bandwidth.
Okay, so that's actually not.
That's not actually.
Well.
Not, I guess this is, this is a little confusing.
There's a lot of different coats here to memory up to 21 gigabytes.
A second dual Channel memory.
Are you using it in dual Channel mode?
Would be the first question.
If you weren't it would be, you know half that right?
There's a Mobley.
I don't actually know.
So I feel like you are a third, the speed of this chip.
I don't know what you would be in practice like on The Benchmark here.
Uplink coder.
Is there a benchmark?
Somewhere, Benchmark, discrete, pray for four months ratio of our
performance thermal design, pros and cons model.
Number not even know if this is a legitimate site that I'm looking at
here.
I'm just wildly searching to see if I can get some memory bandwidth
numbers.
Max memory bandwidth, integrated memory controller is between 99 cent,
right?
Yeah.
29 9 is the
Memory bandwidth.
So yeah, I don't know if you're getting three.
It's a tenth of it.
Yeah, I'm not sure.
This is kind of a to be continued thing.
We're going to need we're going to need real profile Fair.
What's going on here?
I think this is not going to be a trivial thing.
Are you going to do a mobile Port Android?
For example, with the game Loop of a mobile game, be any different?
So I might do a mobile port to Android.
I haven't decided yet.
I don't like having to deal with Android because it's all Java nasty
Ridiculousness, but you know we could
The ndk and compiled mostly and see, and maybe go that way.
So maybe we'll do that.
I'm not sure it's possible, but not necessarily going to happen.
We will definitely do the Raspberry Pi port at some point.
And that basically is a mobile.
That's a, that's essentially a phone.
You know, it's an old phone is what the Raspberry Pi basically is.
So we will be doing that as for whether the game, Loop is any
different on a mobile game game.
Oops, our it depends.
What you mean.
Obviously the win32 code is all different.
Like the phone, whatever, the phone operating system is, will have
completely different platform layer, but the game itself will be
written the same on all the platforms.
So there won't be differences there if that makes sense.
How about disc great speed and access time?
Well, in theory, we shouldn't have to pay for that because since it's
all in memory Windows can be as lazy as it wants, writing that stuff
out.
So in theory, we don't care about what the disk speed is because we're
all in memory now and basically we did a memory mapped file.
So that windows with lazily put it out to disk whenever it wants to.
But it no longer has to do that before it can complete the operation.
So in theory, it should just be memory bandwidth of copying, the GB.
That's all that should have to happen, right?
Um, so, you know disk write speed shouldn't have been involved.
Why is the CPU even involved in a memory copy like this?
Hmm.
so,
I guess the first thing I'd say is I'm not sure what you mean by, why
is this CPU involved in a memory copy?
What else would you imagine doing?
The memory?
Copy?
I guess are you thinking of something that's like a dma engine or
something?
Because really like the memory somebody has to move the memory from
one place to another.
And the CPU is the thing that does the memory Ops.
There's a memory controller on the CPU and, you know,
I guess I don't know if x64.
I don't know if any x64 chips have a way to kick off a memory.
Copy, that doesn't involve the CPU hand holding it.
You know, a bulldozer core might have something like that because that
it has the, I mean, I guess what I'm saying is, I don't actually know
if the compiler can generate x64 instructions.
That would do a background memory copy kickoff that the memory
controller does.
I'm not sure that's all.
Like really would be really modern stuff and I'm not aware of it one
way or the other but traditionally speaking at least, you know, in the
old days the memory is operated on by the CPU.
So the CPU has to manually say take this and move it here.
Take this and move it here.
Take this moving here.
So the CPU is the thing doing the copy, most of the time.
What was the reason for choosing get cursor Paws, instead of just
responding to the WM?
Ousted message is the message, pump, not fast enough.
No, it was just convenience since we were only going to pass it once
for frame.
Anyway, I figured why bother handling a message.
Why not just ask where it is when we're about to pass.
It.
Just easier than doing the other thing.
Have I ever programmed in Java for how long?
No, I have not.
I mean I have programmed in Java but never for long enough to like
I've never done like a major Java project.
I've only done like the barest amount of Java programming where I was
like, okay.
What is this?
How do you do this?
Etcetera, Etc.
And so if we wanted the reason I was mentioning that as if we wanted
to do an Android port.
I believe unless they've changed it recently.
You still have to write a bunch of java code at like the interface
boundary to call your C code because all of their operating system
stuff all has to go through Java.
And so you have, you know, you're talking about installing the
basically a whole Java SDK environment with the Android SDK, and all
that stuff and dealing with it.
And, you know, it's all really annoying because I don't care about
Java, and I don't want to program Java, but
It's kind of forces you to do.
So, right.
Why is the CPU even involved in a memory copy?
Like this, wouldn't the copy speed, mostly depend on how quickly
memory from one part of the memory gets to the CPU and back.
In fact in my mind.
It seems like large copies should be something that could skip the CPU
entirely unless it has something to do is paging.
Okay.
I see the rest of the question now.
Yeah, so hope that kind of answered that basically what happens is the
CPU is still the thing that's in charge of the memory controller.
So it's still involved in doing those copies and I don't know if they
have memory controllers.
Now that'll do those copies.
Asynchronously.
We're just kicks them off.
It certainly could be done.
I just don't know if it is done.
So, I don't know, but basically, when you see that memory speed.
That is sort of what that is.
When you see the memories fade in the CPU, that's telling you how fast
the CPU could issue instructions to the memory controller, right?
Like, how long, how, how fast can the memory controller respond to
when the CPU says, give me a piece of memory.
And what's important to recognize is it's only over.
It's the only reason you would want that asynchronous copy is just to
the CPU, can go do something else, but you're not making it any faster
by taking the CPU out of the equation, because the CPUs clock speed is
way faster than
in the memory can be handed to it.
Right?
The memory bandwidth that the the memory controller can hand back to
the processor is way less than the processor could handle.
So we're not getting slowed down by the fact that the CPU is involved
at all.
Only thing that you would say about it is the CPU can't go do
something else while it's happening.
But definitely the CPU, the CPU could chew through the memory way
faster than the memory controller is handing it back.
So the fact of the CPU involve is not making a slower.
So that is probably why they don't care so much about asynchronous
copies because the CPU is so much faster that like, you know, just
launched it on the core and let it go or whatever, and it'll just
basically be sitting in some hyper threat or something, but I don't
know.
So
Is it worth reading games in Java?
Well, I don't want to write games in Java.
But that's my personal preference.
If you want to write games in Java, then you should write games in
Java.
I mean, I don't know whether I'd say it's worth it or not.
I mean, I do know that there are very few games that shipped that are
successful that are written in Java, but that is you know, I mean
Minecraft would be example of a game that was successful that was
written in Java so it can be done.
And then the other thing is, you know, a lot of the reason that high
High-performance high-profile games are written in C and C++ is
because that's what high-performance programmers program in.
You know, could they go do a high performance gaming Java?
I don't know, probably not, but maybe they could, you know, if all the
high-performance programmers, decided to go spend their time, trying
to figure out how to make Java run fast.
Maybe they could, I don't know.
So I don't really have much of an opinion about Java other than I
don't like it.
And I don't see the point of it.
So I haven't bothered to learn it and program in it, but if someone
else wants to do that, then that's totally there.
Prerogative, my main problems with it or basically that like I don't
see the purpose.
Like, it doesn't seem to give me anything that see, doesn't that
doesn't give me.
I'd like, yeah, I think it has slightly better introspection support,
but I can get around that pretty easily in my own code.
So mostly Java just doesn't have what I want, which is like pointers
and things like this, that are better at expressing memory.
Direct memory access.
It forces me to use garbage collection, which I don't want to do
because garbage collection, just waste CPU time, for no real benefit,
so,
Don't like that.
Aspect of it runs on a VM, which means I don't actually get to see
what the code is and can't necessarily manhandle the assembly a lot of
that stuff.
So I don't like any of that.
So I just don't see what the point would be of me go.
It just seems like a bunch of stuff.
I just have to fight.
And basically, if you use some kind of a Java, if you use some kind of
stuff in Java that allows you to kind of get past those things, then
you're basically back to see anyway, so I feel like I should have just
been programming in c, right?
I mean, another way to say that more concisely would be all the stuff
that Java ads to see it's stuff.
I don't want and it gets in my way.
So that's why I've never bothered going the job around.
But if you're somebody who wants garbage collection, you know, who
wants a VM, who wants those things.
For some reason, you have like legitimate reasons for wanting those
things then maybe it's a good language, read a part of my game and I
don't know.
Are you in dual-channel right mode on your system, I believe.
So, I mean, I'm not actually sure, but I believe this system was set
up with dual Channel, but I'm not sure.
Does the MB have any effect on the performance of the memory?
Oh, you mean like, how much MB there are?
I'm not sure.
Again.
These are things that are like modern memory systems.
I'm not an expert on.
So I'm not really prepared to say at all.
I do not know.
Yes.
Oh, Tom.
Tom Forsythe is saying that CPUs do have dma units but they're not
easily available for user programs.
It's all IO stuff.
Yeah, that's so that's what I would assume.
Like, for example, I would totally assume that like especially like
AMD chips that have the well and an Intel chips.
Now, have the graphics stuff integrated into the CPU.
Right?
And so you're going to probably have a sync, copy stuff happening.
I mean, so you have to have support for a sync, copy stuff in there.
I just don't think this.
CPU ever accesses it really in that way.
I don't know.
So I, you know, it's probably stuff that only the kernel is doing or
only the chip is doing based on Graphics things, or, I don't know.
But yeah, so I don't have much experience with that.
But Tom is saying that is basically, it's more or less confirming.
What I was saying, which is that you don't really get to use async
copies in your code.
What do I think of tdd test-driven development?
I assume I think it's not particularly useful for games, because games
tend to be very hard to write in ways that can be test driven.
But sometimes it's useful for subsystems.
Like, if we have, if you have a system whose configuration space is
very small, then you can use test-driven development.
Okay, but games, the things that are hard to debug in games, tend to
be things that cannot be written with Tess.
Like, there's no way to write them to be tested.
So so TD just doesn't really work.
The reason tdd is popular.
In other Industries is because they are spare programs are much
simpler than games are.
They have very well-defined inputs and outputs.
So tdd works in those circumstances much better, right?
Can you explain the bit shifting?
Yes, I can.
So the pitch shifting we did was really simple.
It's just in terms of the it's the high-low thing.
So basically what happened is I had a 64-bit value but I because of
the way Windows setup their API, they don't accept a 64-bit value,
they accept to 32-bit values which then they will reassemble into one
64-bit value.
So in order to take this 64-bit value, which is the total
All size and produce two 32-bit values.
The high part in the low part.
I first needed to get the high part out.
So I shifted down by 32, right, which basically moves the high 32 bits
into the low, 32 bits and clears, the high 32 bits.
I then just go ahead and assign that to a 32-bit value, which is, you
know, basically, this is a cast here, right?
This is doing this, right, so I'm now truncating that I'm lopping off
the top.
I then do the opposite to get the low 32 bits out eye mask, right, the
load.
D2, B, which will clear the high 32 bits.
And then again, do the cast.
So this is basically, I'm just extracting these two things.
The, the drawing of this, by the way, I tried to get Credo working.
I don't know if it will, but I tried
To get it working.
Let's take a look here.
Let's take a look.
So if I, if I oops here hit create here.
I don't know if it's going to work at all.
It was a little creepy as a little crashy.
I will say, at least on Windows, it is.
So it was a bit problematic, but let's take a look.
So here we go.
Okay.
So what we're looking at here is we've got a 64-bit thing, right?
So this this
Entire thing, here is 64 bits, right?
And so, that means we've got a high 32 bits, right?
And a low 32 bits, right?
Hopefully, this makes sense.
So this is our value here.
This is total size.
Right?
It's 64 bits long and we got some some bits up here, and we got some
bits down here.
And what we want to do is we want to extract this into two separate
pieces, right?
We want to basically be able to, to do this operation into two pieces,
the high piece and the low piece, right?
So what I did is I said, all right.
The first thing, you know, we can we get them into ways in order to
get the low 32 bits in order to get this part out.
Really.
All we have to do is cast it to a 32-bit value which I did with that,
parentheses d word.
Right, which will convert the value to only being 32 bits long.
But in order to make sure that it didn't do something like take a
look.
I want to make sure the compiler knew that I wasn't trying to convert
the value to the closest 32-bit number in which
It would, if there was any bit set up here.
It would be.
Just like, all the bits set down here.
I want to just extract just that part.
So, what I did with that, and remember, ffff ffff, there is just all
1s in the low bits, right?
It's 32 ones up here.
So, what I do with that and is, I basically had all zeros up here,
right?
And all ones down here.
I do the and which, again, nothing up here, too.
Are what set up here since all of these are 0.
If the, since all these inputs of the answer is 0, it'll knock out
everything that's in here.
So it'll be all zeros up here after we're done.
And then, since these are all ones, anything left in here, will still
be there.
So the and basically just, you know, takes just this part and puts it
into a separate value for us, right?
So that's what this line does, right?
It doesn't end to knock out it.
Basically, it keeps this part of it, the low 32 bits, and knocks out
the top part convert to a 32-bit value.
And that's our low for the high.
What I did is I said, well, I want all of these, right?
I want this, this side of things.
But if I just go ahead and cast it to a 32-bit value, it's going to
keep this bottom part and throw out the top part.
So I want the opposite of that.
So what I did is I shifted this down by 32 to move, these 32 bits.
These 32 bits shifting down, shift zeros into here.
So, I've already got all zeros at the top and the 32 bits that were on
the top, go into the bottom.
Once that happens, that those 32 bits from the bottom.
I just do the cast, and now I write them in here, right?
And that's what this line.
Does.
It just shifts down by 32 and conversed with 32-bit value.
So that extracts, the high extracts, the low and then I've got the
high and low and I'm done.
So, hopefully that makes some sense.
So somebody says you can create a performance heavy application in
Java without the garbage collection.
If you configure it to run as real time instead of virtually, I'm not
sure exactly what you mean in real time instead of virtually.
But again,
Like, I'm just trying to underscore the fact that I don't want to have
to fight a garbage collector.
And a VM to make my application fast in.
See if I write it.
It just already is fast.
So all I'm doing with Java is adding headaches for myself, where I
have to fight the language to make the code, do what I already could
have just written to do and see.
And so that is the real problem with high-level languages these days
and it's frustrating because I feel like people don't seem to
acknowledge this fact, which is that I don't ever want to fight the
language.
Performance performance should be a given.
I should be able to write code that tells the CPU exactly what to do
and if the high-level language can't do that, then it's it's just not
interesting.
I don't think that's a useful thing.
We should have high-level languages.
But what they should be is they should be built on that concept and
then layered on top of that, core ability to write exactly what the
CPU should do, should be facilities for more easily, expressing.
Those things that
You would construct so that they can lever on top of these of one
another and I've yet to see the high-level language.
That does that.
They are all.
They all don't do that.
They all are misguided in some way or another, that makes it so that
they fall short of that goal in my opinion, which is unfortunate.
But someday I think we'll have one and then that will be a really
awesome high-level language because then you will have the benefits of
high level programming without the drawbacks that all of today's
modern high-level languages have, which is that you have to fight them
to get your performance back.
Do I consider visible?
Basica programming language?
Yeah, I mean, I I think I've only used Visual Basic once and it was
many many.
Many, many years ago.
I was think I was writing some like word automation stuff in it or
something.
But anything that allows you to program a computer is a programming
language and Visual Basic certainly allows you to program a computer.
So yes, I would definitely consider it a programming language.
I don't know what else I would consider it if I didn't.
That a programming language.
Connor rents C++ or C sharp.
Is that a question?
I'm not sure if that's a question.
On the memory CPU speed.
I see the answer is that the hardware doesn't do this?
I guess I'm just envisioning a system where the GB of memory never
visits the CPU.
I am envisioning that the memory could receive an instruction that
says locally move.
The gigabyte over to this location.
So, yes, mr.
Fourth dimension.
That is a deep.
What's called the dma engine usually and they are they exist on many
things.
Including modern CPUs.
Just I think just not in ways that you can really use.
The way that you're thinking of on things like a PlayStation, right?
Like on the PlayStation 2 or something, you do a lot of exactly what
you just said.
There's like dma engines that you program to move memory around and
stuff, and they are kind of like their own little processors, that all
they do is move memory around.
And so that is a thing.
It's just not a thing that's common on x64 chips because the
instruction set just didn't grow up around that.
So you just yeah, you don't really have.
That thing available to program in the iso.
Like it's just not there, but I feel like I could be wrong about this,
but I feel like I'm like, a bulldozer core or one of these cores.
That's like an AMD core.
I feel like there's probably ways to kick off dma and stuff on those
nowadays, maybe in mantle.
I don't know.
I like I said, I don't, I haven't done any of that stuff.
I don't know if you can or not, but I would be surprised if there
wasn't some of that going on unlike the modern integrated Graphics
CPUs at least.
That's a good point.
Tom Forsythe was pointing out that one thing we could do if you wanted
to not do this bit shifting.
Here is we could use large.
Jur, right.
That thing that that Windows uses, we could do something like.
Okay, large, integer Max size for the file mapping.
We just say, OK, the max size.
We have that quad part that we've been using, right?
We could do that.
But then, instead of doing, we can just use that to extract the two
values that we wanted.
Right?
So basically, it's a union, right?
If you remember unions, when we talked about those and see,
Basically, we can say that, here we go.
This is the Union, right?
And you can see the union has a struct that has a low and a high,
right?
And it also has a this quad part.
So if we assign to the quad part, which is 64 bits, we can then read
out of the low and the high part and those will actually give us back.
The 32 bits that are the top and the 32 bits that are at the bottom,
right?
So we can actually just have the compiler do it for us if we want to
and it'll jump through the rid, the code.
If we just do it, this
Right, right, and then you don't need to worry about doing that
operation yourself.
Does that make sense?
So, you know, now we've done basically exactly the same thing, right?
And so that's yeah.
So Tom Tom for us was just pointing out the fact that I was saying
there was no macro and there isn't a macro, but he was saying, oh, you
could use large integer, which you can.
So you can just use that as a way to kind of convert values assignment
of the quad part pull.
I'm out of the high low, or you could do the opposite, you could
assign to the high and the low, and then pull out the quad part, if
you were trying to assemble a 64-bit value, so kind of useful.
In your mind, what would be a good way to demonstrate to a potential
employer Proficiency in the type of engine programming?
You are teaching.
I know this is a long way off and I'm still just learning.
But to prepare for the future.
What would you recommend to be honest?
I have no idea.
I am not involved in the kind of hiring that happens at like lower
levels of game development, where you're talking about, like an
entry-level position or something like an entry-level engine program
position.
So I don't know how those decisions get made and I don't know how
people come to the attention of the hiring people.
So I'm afraid I can't really answer that question.
All I can really tell you is that at the end of handmade hero, if you
actually understand everything.
We did in handmade hero.
If you really do understand it and could do it yourself afterwards.
Then you would be immediately able to contribute to.
an engine team, I think, but
How that translates into getting hired.
I don't know.
Right.
All I can guarantee you is that I'm teaching you the stuff that you
do, the mental processes, the code structure, the architecture,
understanding the way debug things, the way to profile things, that's
good enough to be on an engine team that we can guarantee now how to
get hired on engine team.
I don't know.
So that's like a, something for an HR person, perhaps to answer.
But I'm not, I'm not too familiar with that.
Chasing tiger, thank you for the thank you.
He was just saying, thank you for the stream.
I am delighted that you like it.
It's really awesome to come and see people on the stream.
To be honest.
I've been, it's just been awesome.
How many people have come to watch handmade hero?
Because I didn't think that many people would, at least, not till the
game was up and running, and I could say, hey look, there's like a
cool game.
You should come watch, How It's being built, and people are like
interested.
From the beginning, which is kind of awesome.
It's made it.
So it's not lonely.
You know, I'm not sitting here on the stream going.
Hello, zero viewers.
Let's talk about whatever today.
It's like.
It's this pretty exciting to know that I'm talking to a large number
of people who are actually interested in what we're doing, so, it's
been pretty awesome.
Let's see here.
What defines the boundary between a high-level language in a low-level
language?
That's kind of a good question.
And I think it's a little nebulous, right?
Like it's kind of something.
That probably doesn't have a very specific definition.
It's kind of more about your sense of it.
The way I think about it is I would I would draw the boundary.
I would probably draw the boundary.
at whether or not it has features designed to
whether or not it has a significant number of features that are simply
designed to create code as opposed to that are designed to create code
structures as opposed to things that are designed to tell the
processor what to do.
So like a low-level language is one that has features for generating
assembly code like directly General Assembly Language.
So C is pretty good at that.
It basically just has a bunch of features that pretty much all they do
is generate.
Instructions on the CPU, right?
And I would say a high-level language is one that has a set of
features that are designed to create whole structures of code.
That each themselves have how they would generate Assembly Language.
So it's like coming up one level from that specificity.
So and a high-level language I think of is having
layer where it's like, you know, an example would be
Let's say that I write a bunch of low-level code, that is all the code
necessary to make a stack of objects, you know, like a memory stack
and I think of a high-level language is something that allows me to
generalize the concept of a stack.
So that anytime I want to Stack, I can make one using this code that
I've written and have a bunch of control over, which features, the
stock has how big the things on the stack are, how often it allocates,
it all that sort of stuff.
So I'm kind of like, meh
Programming at that.
So I'm pulling back a level and allowing myself to generate code using
parameters as to how the coach should be generated and different
languages succeed or fail at this, you know, in various ways.
So whether something is a good high level language is different.
From whether it is a high-level language, certainly C++ has a high
level language.
It's just a really bad one.
Right?
But it is trying to be one is just awful at what it does and some
other languages, you know, probably something like python.
Is a very good high level language at certain things, but in terms of
actually creating what the determining, what the CPU does it's awful.
So at some level it's a bad high level language at one goal.
A goal that I find important which is giving the high-level programmer
control over exactly whether that's happening on the CPU when they
care.
So, you know, like I said, I've never seen a good high level language
so far.
I'm still waiting.
When will I start actual game logic?
Probably Monday?
Well, maybe Tuesday, Thursday, Wednesday.
I know sometime next week.
Will start game logic, have I heard of the rust language?
Yes, but I have not actually played with it much.
I only curse or really looked at it.
It did based on sort of the attitude of it.
It didn't look like something.
I would be interested in.
But, you know, it's hard to say without having actually written.
Programs in it.
Obviously the language I'm most excited about is John's.
So the language, I hold out the most hope for is is the one that John
blows working on because he seems to be one of the first people
designing a high-level language you has like a proper approach to it,
I think.
Have you ever dealt with programmer, burnout?
Or how do you deal with the fact that often there are days almost no
code gets written and on some days, massive amounts of code gets
written.
So, I guess what I would say is.
I rarely have any problem with programmer burnout, if I'm just writing
code that supposed to do something.
So I've never had that happen, per se.
What I do have a problem with is when I'm trying to develop a new
technique.
And I just don't know how to do it.
Right?
Like when I'm working on something that either, I don't know if it's
even possible, which can happen.
Sometimes.
Like you're like, I don't know if what I'm trying to do is possible or
if I'm working on something where I'm like, I'm not sure how this
architecture should work.
And there's a lot of different ways, it could work and I have to kind
of think them through those sorts of things.
You can definitely get into that situation where like, nothing is
getting done.
Typically.
What I try to do in those circumstances is be self-aware enough.
Recognize the fact that nothing's getting done.
So recognize the fact that you didn't do any work today, be like,
okay, we're in a bad situation.
And then what I would do is I take that opportunity to go.
All right, I'm going to write at least an hour's worth of code
tomorrow on whatever first comes to mind.
Right?
So let's say, I'm having a lot of trouble with this architecture and I
just can't figure out the right way to do it.
Then what I tried in like naoko got done today, like nothing got done.
It was like eight hours of sitting in front of computer and doing
nothing.
Then the next day.
What I'll try to do is just like, all right.
I'm going to take the first thing, I think of for this architecture,
even if it's
The stupidest idea.
Like what even no matter whatever my last thought was that was what I
got to when I was trying to figure this out, no matter how dumb it
was.
I'm going to just implement it.
Because a lot of times you find is just getting the code out there and
then having something to work with is enough to kind of break through
that barrier.
And so, typically what I find is the way that you get into those stuck
situations, the kind of talking about those stuck situations, often
are because you're not coding, you're trying to think something
through, and you're trying to think it through too far, and you've
reached the limits of what your mind can comprehend without seeing it
and without playing with it.
So what you need to do is get it out there and so I usually find that
that's the way.
Do it.
And if you can, just make sure just force yourself to write an hour of
code a day, in those situations eventually you'll break through and
you can get back up to writing, a reason amount of code.
The only thing you must not let happen is, is stopping writing code
entirely.
When you do that, you risk run the risk of getting into that
circumstance where you have several days and you don't get anything
done.
So that's what I would say about that.
Any Source or book recommendation for understanding the concepts you
use better?
Not really because I don't think there's any been a lot of books that
are like.
I find that most programming educational materials.
When I look at them.
I'm kind of horrified at the things they're teaching.
I'm like that is not the way to Be an Effective programmer, right?
And so I have a hard time recommending, anything because I'm like, I
don't know.
I'm not sure there might be some books out there that are good, but I
don't know what they are.
Certainly the
X.
I read when I was right.
Program are not good.
But yeah, so I don't know.
I'm sorry.
I don't have a really good recommendation.
Have you seen game programming patterns by Robert?
Nistrim?
I don't think so.
Although I think someone has sent me that recently.
I haven't read it yet, but I think someone was talking about it.
Are you going to use any design patterns?
So the phrase design patterns is a little confusing to me because
people use it differently to mean different things.
I guess.
What I would say is, I have my own set of ways that I do architecture,
and you could call those design patterns.
They're, like, whatever you want to call Casey's design patterns.
And they're like, these are the ways.
I tend to structure things.
And in that sense, then yes, I would like, you would see these sorts
of things used in various places of my code and they're similar,
right?
In terms of design patterns like the design patterns that are maybe in
the book design patterns.
I don't
I find that those.
Are very odd things to call Design patterns because they're more like
utility classes or something out there really straight.
Like I don't really understand what people mean when they say design
patterns.
So, I feel like different people use it to mean different things.
So it's hard for me to answer that question, if that makes sense.
Do you find it?
Useful to learn many different languages to gain perspective?
No, I don't.
I think programming works from first principles very well.
So I think what's valuable to learn is how CPUs and Hardware work.
That's what I think because anything you will ever do with a language
is just generating stuff for the CPU to do.
And so the most important thing is that you understand how the CPU and
the CPU.
Them works.
If you understand that, then everything that is efficient about
programming can be built on top of that.
And in fact, when you think it through from first principles in that
sense, that is the easiest way to recognize and realize what's so bad
about Minor modern high level languages because you can see as you go
up each level you go.
Okay, here's how I, here's how the CPU Works.
Here's how I'd program in Assembly Language.
Here's how I program it and see.
Okay.
That's okay, but I lost some stuff and you can
Sort of see what the problems are in.
See?
Just by looking at what you can do at assembly versus what you can do
and see, see loses, a bunch of things and you're like, that's a
bummer.
So a better C language would fix that.
And then going from C to something else like a python or Ruby or C++
or whatever your higher-level language of choices.
You can see how they basically just don't get it.
Like, the people who designed those languages, don't understand what
you actually needed to make your job of programming in c easier
because or rather program.
Simple language, you might even say easier because they don't allow
you to Loft the commonalities up, which is what you're trying to do.
You're trying to make something that will allow you to say.
Here's the Assembly Language that I wanted to generate.
I want to specify that once and I want to love that up into something
that I can easily specify in a variety of ways such that it meshes
properly and does, you know, things properly?
Whatever, it's so obvious when you look at it.
what you really should be doing for it to get to that high level level
language and
I don't know why universally almost all have a level languages.
Don't even seem to try to do the right thing.
I don't know.
I think it may be because the types of people who do language design,
maybe aren't the types of people who write efficient programs.
It might be because languages are hard to write.
And so you spend a lot of time focusing on other things and don't
realize that you should be focusing on this.
I don't know, but I find that hole high level language Mass to be
rather.
Or frustrating because I find like they're mostly not very
intelligently done.
So, I would say,
What do you think about using VCS for one man projects?
I always do use version control system for projects.
Even my own projects.
I have one that I wrote myself and that's what I use.
I wrote it to do the things that I want to do conveniently.
And so I would recommend using a source code control system.
I don't super like the ones which that exists currently, which is why
I wrote my own, but I feel like most
People can usually find one existing one that that's suitable enough
for them and use it.
So if you, if you can find one, that's okay for you and that you're
comfortable with and you should you should use it, I think.
What's your mindset when looking at a problem?
That's new.
How do you approach a new coding problem that you have?
No predefined idea on how to solve.
So we will be seeing that in the Stream.
So like there's I've intentionally set up a bunch of stuff like in the
game design that I've never done before in a game logic or anything
and so will be I will be sort of showing you how I work through it.
I'll make all the mistakes.
I'll Rectify them.
I'll revise the architecture.
I'll do all those things so you can watch.
You do them.
So that will be very well elucidated as we go as we go through the
Stream.
Well, I read a book after handmade here is done.
No, I don't think so.
I think handmade hero will be probably what what I can contribute in
terms of education.
So
how long have I been in the industry?
Two decades in the industry.
Tiny concert has a question for me and Tom Forsythe.
I've always been a hobbyist, The more I've learned over the last year,
the more I love programming.
Your opinion is going back for a 4-year CS degree a waste.
If I want to learn to make things that don't suck.
That's a tough question.
I'ma let Tom answer that one because he actually went to University
and I did not.
So I'm not really a position to say.
Perhaps, the problem with high-level languages that they are less
General but more domain-specific in the first place.
It could be.
I think it's just that they don't care about the right things.
I think they get caught up in trying to be clever within their own
framework and they don't understand that.
The point of programming is to make a CPU, do things.
And so, what you're trying to do is have the most concise way of
expressing, exactly what the CPU should be doing.
It is not to have the most concise way of expressing.
What the language is doing?
And those are two very different things and I feel like high-level
languages designers just don't have never understood this somehow
which is weird, but that just seems you the case.
How does your source code control differ from something like get or
SVN?
Well, basically, it's designed just to be used by me.
So it's basically just it's one command you type c mirror.
That's it.
So whenever you're done working for the day, you just type c Marin and
that's it.
There's no push-pull update get grabbed from diff whatever.
It's nothing.
It's just like seamer.
That's it.
And then you just have a directory on the server that's got all the
versions.
So if you ever want anything, you can just go browse them and grab the
one you want.
So it's just designed.
To be as simple as possible and stop getting in your way.
I find that like get an SVN, make me do a bunch of stuff that I don't
want to do.
Like, I don't ever want to think about the source code control as far
as I'm concerned.
The source code, which allows us to safety net.
It should only be there to catch when I've accidentally, like, deleted
a file or accidentally modified a file that I wouldn't want to.
It's only supposed to be able to get that back for me and anything
else.
It does slows me down.
I don't want it.
So, so, yeah, it's one command.
That's all seem error.
And, and I vastly prefer.
For that.
Okay, looks like we've come to the end of the questions.
It is 130 that's been a very long stream today.
Thank you very much for joining me for handmade hero.
If you enjoyed the program, we do have a patreon that you can support
by clicking.
You can go to him a hero dot organ, click on the patreon.
If you would like to, to essentially subscribe to the series.
Also, if you want the source code, you can always pre-order the game
on the animator at org, and you will get a zip file link to download a
zip file that has
Everyday Source in it so you can grab any day that you want and follow
along at home.
If you would like to discuss the show news and forums is the button
for you.
You can go on there and there's a great site that has all kinds of
stuff and episode guide with links and stuff time coded and everything
coding resources, which has ports to Mac OS, X, and Linux on it.
If you want to use a different platform than Windows.
And then also Co discussion, we can ask questions and all sorts of
stuff.
So that is it for today.
We will be back on Monday at 8 p.m.
Pacific Standard time.
I certainly hope to see everyone there.
And thank you very much dries.
I hope to see you on Monday.
Take it easy, everyone.