I have cycled the recording you couldn't see it because it's on the
other machine now.
But hello everyone and welcome to handmade here of the show where we
code a complete game live on stream.
This is our first Dream.
Officially back, trying to see if we can use the new machine setup to
successfully stream some programming.
Now, for those of you who have been following us, you may wonder why
there is such a long break.
The reason they were such a long break is because
We stopped programming on handmade Hero on the last episode because I
crashed the computer that was streaming because the AMD drivers did
not like some of the Shader code, we sent them.
Now at that point I decided that what we would probably have to do is
build a to machine streaming setup, because if we wanted to do some
Advanced Shader work, we were likely to keep crashing things because
video drivers crash, I should shouldn't say crash computer.
We didn't crash bureaucrats the video driver, but crashing, the videos
driver takes down, OBS, which takes down the stream.
So, what I did is I ordered some computer parts and I built two new
computers, which would have been ready about two weeks after that last
stream.
However, one of them just did not work properly.
It was super flaky, it would blue screen all the time.
I tried testing it with mem test and had all kinds of weird Ram errors
on it.
I tried replacing just about everything and swapping all sorts of
things much just in the system.
After several weeks of debugging, I finally figured out that oddly
enough.
It was a bad CPU.
It was a
Core i7 7 700k probably, that's my fault for not having read up about
this.
I 7700 case, apparently, they're not very good.
So that was kind of dumb.
I don't know why I ordered one.
I think I was just in a rush and I didn't do my homework.
So I ended up having to are met through Intel, which took a while
eventually.
I got the chip back and was able to finish the machine builds, like,
two months later or something like this, so it took a long time, then
we got the machine set up.
And we tested streaming last weekend, and now, it seems like things
are working well enough.
I think we can start programming again here on the new machines.
Part of the new machine built also meant replacing the Aging
ten-year-old machine.
Well, I guess, is only 7 or 8 years old.
This point with a modern machine, which is pretty great because it's
like way faster than our old machine like way.
Way faster and made, here are probably runs at a Breakneck Pace
nowadays compared to what it used to run at.
But anyway, the core i7
Good K is now working fine and we can program on it.
We also have a modern GPU.
It's a 1080 in here, so we can play around with stuff.
All we want and have full horsepower opengl 4.5.
If we wanted anything else we want to play with is on the table.
However, I don't want to start with that today because I don't know if
this setup is really going to work for recording and uploading videos
to like actually do 1 1.
So this
First episode here, I just want to do some basic programming.
On something, not handmade he related.
So, if we lose the stream, it's no big deal.
And nobody has to cry themselves to sleep about it.
Now, all I have to do to get our set up working, here is substitute
that W.
Dr.
I believe.
And then, we already set up everything on the previous stream, to be
exactly like it was on the old machine.
So you shouldn't have to learn anything new about what I'm doing.
It's the W.
Dr.
Very similar to the old W Drive.
It has all of our same commands built into it that we used to have and
all the same programs installed like for coder and Milton and so on.
So it's really basically identical.
You shouldn't notice anything that I had to do, all this reset up, but
you who are following along at home with a series, should not have to
worry at all about what happened?
You should be able to plow straight through exactly where we left off
from now on.
So we don't really have much in the way of goals for today.
Again, I'm just going to do some light programming and I'm going to
just verify
That everything went okay, that everyone could read everything, that
there was nothing particularly busted going on.
So all I'm going to do for starters is I'm going to go into the
handmade directory and inside there, I'm just going to make people
were asking me to play around with a ray Tracer, a little bit.
So I'm going to go ahead and make a ray directory here and I'm just
going to go ahead and copy out of the code directory.
We have a build up at.
I'm going to copy that.
Tin to the ray tracing directory.
I guess, I don't need to specify the name there, I can just do that,
and if I open up that code directory there, oops, Ray directory,
there, and look at the build-up at, I should be able to get rid of a
lot of this code, but I can keep it in place for just doing the bill
the same way it normally gets built, right?
So what I'm going to do is I'm going to get rid of
Some of this stuff, you know, what's interesting.
We could take out this handmade streaming stuff, even the regular
build now because since we're streaming by capturing the HDMI output,
we don't need to worry about that anymore.
I don't think but that's a separate issue.
So anyway, we're going to do a build into the same build directory.
We're not going to do any of the fancier stuff that we do here.
We're just going to do one really simple, build right here where we
let's see here, do the main build.
Like that is all we're going to do and if we look here, we've got
Sort of the build of the handmade win32.
You know this sort of nonsense here.
What I want to do is switch this to building Ray and we'll just call
this Ray dot CPP.
And we don't need to Output a map file specially or anything like
that.
We should just be able to do a simple line like this and that should
build.
I think a ray tracing program for us without a lot of fuss.
So I'm going to make one cure and I'm just going to include standard
IO, dot h.
And I'm just going to type in a boilerplate c program, nothing fancy
just a, you know, exactly what you would see in any kind of a
I see, put see, basic C, programming book that's like my first C
program, right?
And so we'll just go ahead and do a printf Hello World kind of a
thing, and that should make us a program.
Now, when I build this, hopefully if the build works properly, things
should be OK.
Wait, am I not in the right directory?
Hero and I have to make a project file in for a coder probably as
well, so that it knows.
What we're doing here.
If you remember correctly, I sort of have this concept of a project
file that sets the build directory.
I kind of made that as part of my config so I want one of these as
well for my re-program just so I can have that work properly.
So if I go into that re-project, I just need to make sure that it's
instead of looking in that directory, it's looking in this directory.
Both the top line is for the build, the bottom line is to like load
the source code, right?
So now in theory, maybe if I did that right and I load that
re-project, if I do a build it should build, there we go.
And presumably if I look back in that build directory.
Now I've got the radon exe, there it is.
So if I run it I should get my hello world and I do, right?
So that's all well and good.
And so now the question is people wanted to we wanted to make a ray
tracer.
which is something again that
Is a simple program.
Well, some of them are very complicated.
Actually, in commercial programs, like something like Maxwell, for
example.
But a ray Tracer is a program which fundamentally renders images of
something, whatever you have as a data description language.
You know, maybe they load scenes from Maya or maybe they,
Are a bunch of spheres sitting on the checkerboard which is much more
common.
But a ray Tracer is essentially a program that renders scenes by
taking a camera location in the world that they've created and sending
individual lines out into the world to see what they hit and based on
what they hit, they produce an image.
So we will do a really, really basic
One of these to start with, you will have very little in the way.
Of solid math in it because I'm just going to do the most basic thing
and then periodically from time to time.
If we want to we can go back into it and make like parts of it like
the lens simulation or something be realistic.
Instead of just a dumb you know pass through kind of thing.
Like what we're going to do now, we're we're essentially doing almost
nothing physical at, all right?
We're just doing the most basic most trivial things that you can do.
So, here's
I would like to start with.
I would like to start with the way of saving an image and we can
leverage the fact that we've already done this on handmade hero.
We already have ways of loading a bitmap, if you remember correctly.
We wrote this into.
I think it's in our simple preprocessor now where we've got a like a
BMP loader in here somewhere.
Oh not simple preprocessor.
Sorry.
It's our simple asset.
There is test asset Builder if you remember correctly.
So we've got this this thing in our asset pricing code that we wrote
and you can go back and reference it which is basically just like
loads in a bitmap.
And what we want our raytracer to do is the opposite of that, right?
We want our raytracer to Output a bitmap and fundamentally speaking.
If we already know how to read a bitmap in, we should know how to
write a bitmap out, right?
It should just be the inverse process.
So if I want to write a bitmap
Should be able to take essentially the same process that I was doing
here, right?
Where we sort of, I could modernize these two that we sort of Switched
how we decided to write our Types on handmade hero.
I can modernize these real quick here.
I like the short names a lot.
I switch to them recently and just really enjoy their conciseness.
So we can go ahead and do this exact same thing where we sort of have
this notion of hey here is what a bitmap looks like on disk and rather
than using sort of the load bitmap procedure, which loads went in, we
can do the opposite which is just something that writes one out,
right?
And so that's the first thing that we want to do is be able to write
some code that just creates a bitmap and saves it to the drive because
that will allow us to Output our image to something.
We can see, we don't need this to use any Windows specific functions.
Because if we just write a file to a drive, then any any operating
system at all Linux, Mac, Windows, whatever.
If there's a program at the can read a BMP file, which they all can,
then this rate
Her will just work and that is far preferable to opening a window or
something like that.
Where we would then
Hand on the operating system where some libraries that are dependent
on operating systems or whatever to run.
So lucky for us, we can leverage that sort of niceness there.
So let's go ahead and try to get that working.
The first thing we're going to need is to figure out how big of a
image we want to render.
So let's just say that we have a sort of output width and we're going
to set that to 1920 and an output height, and we're going to set that
to 1080.
So we're just going to make a, you know what, since I'm streaming at
1920 1080 and
Probably don't want this to go full screen at the moment.
Let's actually do something a little smaller.
Let's do 1280 by 720 so it's so it will fit in a nice window we can
see on the screen without without much fuss.
Okay?
So let's say we have an output with and output height and we're going
to Output, let's say just rgba pixels and so we're just going to do
standard 4 bits per pixel, how you know, where we going to put this
data, right?
Like, how are we going to get?
Put this data in something.
Well, I would say, let's go ahead and moloch chunk of memory that we
can use for storing this and will make each pixel just be again and
sort of an RGB value, right?
So I'm just going to have a pointer here to the output pixels.
And I'm just going to mallik again, very simply here a chunk of
memory.
Now, you know that we don't, you may be unfamiliar with me a lot
because we wrote Our Own memory allocation on handmade here.
Be kind of because again we were writing a full game with like a
complete platform and all this stuff.
I'm just writing a simple Ray Tracer here, we're just using the C
runtime Library so the C runtime Library which I really don't use on
handmade here.
Hardly at all is provides a memory allocator as well.
It's called malloc it's just think if it is the same as like virtual
Alec it's very different because it's actually much higher level and
sits on top of virtual I like basically but for our intents and
purposes it's the way we can get memory in a platform.
Like way from the C runtime Library that's built into every C
compiler.
That comes every second power so that we know that it will somehow
call something in the Opera system on Windows, it will be virtually
lock eventually to get memory for our backing store.
Now, it's worth remembering that just because we never really talked
to us in here.
When you use something like a sea, runtime libraries Malik.
It's actually weirdly optimized thing that keeps free lists and does a
bunch of work behind your back.
So when you call Mal que have no idea what's going on it,
Could be reused cycling, a piece of memory that Gottfried before.
It could be talking down to Virtual lock to get new memory to give
you, you have no idea what it's doing.
You just know that it's going to give you some memory, you can use the
size that you wanted.
Okay, so I'm going to go ahead and take the size of you 32, which, of
course is for.
I'm going to take the output with and the output height here and I'm
just going
Allocate that chunk of memory.
So now I know I have output pixels that I can use.
I'm then going to go ahead and just write something to the output
pixels so that I can verify that I'm writing things correctly.
When I say about this bitmap.
So what I'm going to do here is say I've got an out pointer that out
pointer is going to equal the output pixels.
I'm done going to step through each pixel and I'm going to use an X Y
so that I can change it to a checkerboard or something in the future
if I want to.
So, I'm going to say that I have a y coordinate, the y coordinate as
less than the output height and then I'm going to increment it.
I'm going to say that I have an x coordinate and the x coordinate is
going to be less than the output with.
I mean increment that and then I'm just going to go through and,
because I've decided to order this.
Now, remembered, we Malkin piece of memory.
We have a lot of options about how we wish to treat that memory.
I got us enough memory to store 1280, x, 10, 720 X for, which is a
whole screens worth of rgba pixels at eight bytes per Channel.
But we haven't specified what we mean by this chunk of memory.
I'm choosing to represent it as
Eating where each successive 32-bit value in that chunk of memory is a
separate pixel along X.
And when we get through 1280 of those pixels, we're going to go to the
next line.
We haven't decided yet whether we're bottom up or top down.
We can decide that a little bit later, but right now it doesn't matter
because all the only difference will be whether our image is flipped
vertically or not, right?
So we'll have to decide again.
When you out can chunk of memory and say I'm storing some pixels in
it, you have to decide.
I'd what you mean in terms of its layout because it's just a block of
memory in a computer.
It has no inherent ordering.
So you have to decide how you're choosing to assign each pixel value.
We're on the screen.
You mean that to be because later on when you go to output something
like a file, like the bitmap file or to a window, you have to know how
those pixels are posted map in order to copy them into that location
correctly, right?
But that's something we'll address a little bit later.
So as we write each out pixel, I'm just going to write
It's very simply here.
We're going to ignore the alpha Channel entirely because we don't care
about it.
I could set it to FF just to indicate that it should be full but it
doesn't matter because we're going to most ignore it.
And what I'd like to do is I'd like to write
Just a straightforward red value here.
So I'm going to say that red goes in the bottom.
Green goes in the middle blue goes in the top.
The reason I'm going to do that is just because I think that's how
bitmaps nor bitmaps normally use Windows or byte ordering where the
blue comes.
I'm sorry if I use Windows ordering the blue would come first, it's
the kind of opposite of the normal, so it would be blue in the bottom.
Green in the middle red on the
Top, which is kind of the opposite of how like big-endian machines
used to do it.
They used to do read first, then green, then blue.
Neither here nor there, just point being, we're going to use be gra
coming from the bottom, which is in memory order rather than rgba.
That's all.
So once we get rid of this, once we sort of execute this line of code,
we should have a giant thing full of red pixels.
I'm sorry.
Full of blue pixels and we can now output that to a bitmap.
So how do we uh put that to a bitmap?
Well we know that we have this stuff here that reads a file right and
you can see that it reads in the entire file.
It starts at the very beginning of the file and it looks at this
bitmap header and then it also says that here's how it got the pixels.
Right.
It takes a look at wherever the start of the file was and then uses
the bitmap offset parameter, which is again, a field in the file right
here, to tell it where the bitmap is.
So that's pretty straightforward.
And we can just do that exact process in Reverse, right?
I'm going to create a bitmap header here.
I'm going to write it as the first thing in the file.
I'm going to clear it, I'm going to set the parameters that are
relevant, right?
Like red mask, green, mask, blue mask, those sorts of things.
I'm going to set all this stuff.
Exactly the way that we read it in and cross my fingers, that there's
nothing else that most programs that read in bitmaps are really going
to need.
So let's go ahead and do that now.
And we'll see what we can manage here.
So we've got
File type.
In fact, let me just copy all this stuff down here and initialize it.
There we go.
So, header file type.
I believe this in here is just a secret code.
Which we can go look up, what it's supposed to be and that's no big
deal.
I assume file size will check
Is probably just the size of the entire file.
I don't actually know that that's true.
Some some file formats treat the file size as the size separate from
the header.
So you skip the header.
When you talk about the size, I don't think that's the case here.
But we should verify reserved, one, and two.
We can just leave 0 because hey, if they're reserved, we probably not
responsible for setting them to anything, other than zero, the bitmap
offset is going to be we're going to put the pixels after the header.
So probably this will just be whatever, however, big the header is.
That's how far forward we need to go to get to the pixels size.
I am not sure what that means.
That's probably just the pixel size.
Oops.
So I don't really know again.
What that is?
We do know what the width and height are.
Why?
That's going to be our output with and our output height planes in
this case.
I assume get set to 1 and I assume bits per pixel, get set to 32.
I don't know that this is true.
We'll see you in a second but we do know what compression is set to
because we're asserting it, right?
Okay, so size and size of bitmap are different, apparently.
So again, we don't really know what those are supposed to be set to.
Horace resolution invert, resolution.
I think just get set to 0 when you're not talking about a
We're not sure about something for print.
I think those were meant for print so I think these can be left at 0
or rather just not set it all because we know they'll be set to Zero
by this line right here, right?
And colors used in colors important.
I think can also be set that way because I don't think those are used
for anything other than palletized things.
However, our red mask on our green mask and our blue mask, these do
need to
Up to something.
Because this is what tells the loading program, where the red green
and blue are.
So again, I said I was going to use Windows format here so that's
where the red channel is going to be mask too.
That's where the green channel will be.
And that's where the blue channel would be.
And if I line these up a little bit, you can courtesy red with the
exception of the alpha channel here that doesn't get used Reds in the
high Greens in the middle Blues in the low, right?
So again, we don't really know what these other ones are here.
I'm going to not set them to anything yet until we go look at some
information that tells us what it is.
So we will definitely do that.
But I want to finish the rest of this code here.
So now what we need to
Is we need to write to a file.
We need to write to some file.
That we can use to see what the results are.
So again, we haven't really done much with this in handmade here
because we write all of our code going through our own custom OS
layer.
So you may be a little bit unfamiliar.
I think we did it once.
Maybe for the preprocessor, I don't really remember.
But we're going to use against because we're on the C standard
Library.
Well, I guess I don't need standard live but I will need that from
Alex.
I'm gonna put that in there as well.
Standard Libby.
I think is what you require for Malik.
You may need memory .h from Alec, I'm not sure.
We'll see.
I don't use the C runtime Library much.
So it's I don't typically remember what this stuff is but
Way the C runtime library.
Has a built-in concept of file IO so we can go ahead and do that.
If we do want to do file IO, you know, I should I should also switch
switch over here because I don't want my head to be in the way we go.
If we're doing file I/O, it has this concept of a file handle.
And if similar to sort of the way we they work in hammy Hero on the
win32 side, on the low level side.
So we have a file that we're going to write and basically what you do
is you call this function called f open which takes the file name that
you want to open.
Which in our case I'll just say like for the moment test Dot bitmap
and then it takes a string of all things that tells you what
permissions you wanted to use and how you want to open.
The file W, is the code for writable file which erases the existing
file that's at that location and replaces it with a new file that's
length zero.
And you can start writing from the beginning of the file, which is
what we want.
There's a bunch of other things you can do.
You like W plus an A&R for readable you know, blah blah blah so you
can it but again I don't care about the runtime Library so I'm not
going to spend time teaching how to use this stuff point, being this
basically emulates, the create file stuff.
We did on win32 in a sort of Less Direct more funky and unpredictable
way that goes to someone else's C runtime code it also introduces
buffering so when you use these calls, you go through an output buffer
that is
Sort of meant to increase performance and usually doesn't.
But, anyway, we open a file.
We also have to close the file when we're done with it.
F close is the corresponding call to F open.
So this opens the file, this closes the file again, this is nothing.
You wouldn't find out in the first five minutes of reading a see book
and I got it don't care about.
It's not interesting, it's just an equivalent to the same things we
were doing on win32 in the regular handmade hero to do these sorts of
things.
It just introduces a layer of unnecessary abstraction and Croft in
between us and the operating system.
So anyway open and close of the bitmap and then all we have to do to
write to the bitmap is basically say, okay we're going to use an F
right?
Oh.
And because we're going to use an F, right?
One thing I have to point out here.
One of the aspects of that unnecessary craft.
I almost attempted to leave it in just so you can see it because it
happens all the time when you use the unnecessary crafts.
Is by default the C runtime library for some unknown reason.
Introduces crlf translation which is basically End of Line.
You know how we put like this in backslash n to talk about End of Line
and it generates a 13 or whatever you know ASCII codes are meant to
have returns but they're different on Linux and Windows and Mac.
Each one has its own End of Line.
Some use backslash R box session which is like ten thirteen or
whatever.
I don't
Number of the exact ASCII codes.
Others is just faxed.
Us are others is backslash and so it's like 10:30 nor just 13 or just
10 by default the C runtime Library converts between those for
everything you output.
Now, this is really annoying because if you're trying to Output binary
data, it will corrupt the binary data by replacing tens and 13s with
like different, you know.
So you need to tell it not to do that.
And the way that you do that is by putting a binary of be in
Here flag.
So F open knows oh by the way, I shouldn't touch this data when I'm
writing it out.
It's nuts that that's not the default, but the C runtime library was
designed around text input and output so they prioritize ASCII sorts
of operations.
Anyway.
So F R8 is a weird child, it takes multiple things here it takes.
First of all, the buffer that we want to write which in this case is
just a header.
It takes to well I'll show you the documentation for it because it's
really wonky.
It takes two things, a chunk size and a number of chunks basically so
you can see here it's like a size and account and then what it does is
it returns.
How many of those it wrote?
So basically what you do here is if you want to write like 20, records
that are all the same size and you want to know how many successfully
wrote to the file, you can see why you might use that.
We don't care about that.
We just want to do one right of the entire header.
So we're just saying one and the size of the header.
If we cared, we'd check the return code here.
I don't care at all about that, so we're not going to, but after we
write the header, we then need to write the pixel data.
We know that that's got a total size here, which I could compute if I
wanted to.
To Once because we have to use it for allocation here, right?
And then I can use it again to write.
So I know that I write the correct size.
So what I'll do is I'll write the output pixels here.
Using output pixel size to the out file and then I have written a
complete bitmap file, the header, and the pixels, and we're done,
right?
So what I can do, if I want to be a little bit more explicit here
about it, is I can make an error if we don't open the file, so I could
use an fprintf to the Airstream.
For example, and say, error unable to write output file.
And then put output file name here which I can store.
Like so.
Okay, so pretty straightforward, not particularly complicated, let's
go ahead and get this compiling.
So the first thing we need is, we need the types that we use, because
we have a few different types, or that we're using, and we need to
define those types, right?
So, in here, we can just say, all right, we have
But you know, a Karen signed short unsigned.
Hinton signed.
Like soap.
And then we have the same thing for our sign types.
Right.
Pretty straightforward, while I am at it, I will make a float 32 as
well and let's take a look here.
This function is may be unsafe Securities, are you okay?
Yeah, thank you.
Visual Studio.
The last thing I think we want is Microsoft warning us about what may
or may not be secure.
I think they're probably the last people who should be making any
sorts of declarations about that, but
Save those sort of comments for another day anyway by defining CRT
secure.
No, warnings on the build line, we get rid of that warning and now we
have a program that we can run.
Now, I am going to go ahead and run this under the debugger so we can
step through it.
It should not work yet because we have not filled in all of those
bitmap header Fields.
So, we've got some work to do but that's okay.
So here we go.
Loading up our
Our program in the debugger.
I'm going to go ahead and set the properties.
It doesn't need any arguments yet but the working directory, I'm going
to go ahead and
Set maybe to handmade Ray data and I'll just make a data directory
here.
For it to run in where we can place data files when we need them.
So let's go ahead and step through it just so you can see what we
basically wrote.
So we still have our printf.
Hello world in there eventually.
We'll change that to something fancier right?
That'll say you know we're running some programs and it's good and
whatever.
So here we go stepping through to oh my God there's so much stuff
happening here.
Okay.
There we go.
So we're going to create our bitmap header file.
Here it is.
I think we have 0 turret or not.
I got to turn to bugging, turn off 02.
We don't need optimization at the moment.
We're able to Output our file properly and write it and exit, which is
what we wanted.
And so now if we look, we should see that in that data directory we
should have a test bitmap file.
Which we do now probably we can't read it because again, it doesn't
have.
You can see.
It doesn't really know how to read this file.
Probably, I'm guessing yet because we haven't filled out like the
magic value.
And we haven't filled out some of the fields, but we've basically got
the program at putting an image.
We just need to finish filling out those fields and we should be good
to go.
So let's go ahead and figure out how to make that.
Happen.
Here is our header struct.
Let's go ahead and uncomment these lines and write out all the fields
that we didn't write.
We will provide
the information necessary to write them properly.
Okay.
All right.
Here we go.
So, first things first, let me look up the documentation for the
bitmap header.
And see if I can't find something that tells us what each of the
fields means so that we can write them properly.
So let's see here.
Okay, so here's the header field.
You said, if I a bitmap file, it's supposed to be 0420, it supposed to
be 42, 44, D and hex.
So we can just go ahead and set that, right?
That's no, that's no big deal.
So,
We go.
I assume it wants 42, 4D, and memory order.
So that's actually going to be 44 to write because remember, run a
little endian machine.
So the first thing about my order goes here, second thing in memory
order goes there, we then have a file size which is the size of the,
the whole file in bytes.
We actually do know what that will be, because we know that it's the
size of this header, plus the output pixel size, right?
So, we can fill that in.
We then have a sighs.
Okay, we
So are we to reserved, which we don't set for its the offset starting
out as we got that as well.
So this size field, we need in here somewhere else.
Let's see, where does that go?
What does bitmap info header?
I believe.
Oops, I believe this is what we're looking at here.
Yeah.
So we need the size of the header.
That's what this size field is.
So that explains that, the problem though is, is it the size of this
header?
Meaning - this part?
And if that's true, we actually need to subtract away this part of it.
So, I assume that that is the case, which means that this 16.
So we have 2 B, 4, b 2, b 2 b.
Four bytes that part needs to not be included, right?
So two plus two, plus two is six plus Eight Is Right.
Is what 14?
I think that's what we're looking at here because we got eight bytes
here and six bytes here.
So I assume that that's what that means.
Just guessing here doesn't quite say it says but it says this header
and says 40 bytes.
So for
1 2 3 4 5 6 7 8 9 10 to 2 B is for by.
So yeah.
So it just
This, I guess.
So I think that should be right height in pixels width in pixels.
We've got the number of planes is one bits per pixel, should be 32
compression method.
Should be 3 again which is not compressed size of bitmap.
Sighs rotate.
A dummy 0 can be given for bi RGB bitmaps.
This is a bi RGB bitmap.
So we should be able to put past zero their horizontal resolution of
the image pixels per meter assigned image signed integer, we don't
know what the pixels per meter should be.
I don't know pixels per meter.
Let's just, let's just say that it fits in a meter.
Well, let's just say the pixels per meter is 1000.
I don't know.
I don't know how many pixels for me to there should be
Probably more than that.
I have no idea is this into print image so we don't have that concept
of pixels per meter.
Write the number of colors using the palette or zero.
I think that's zero here, important colors, zero when every color is
important, generally ignored and I think that concludes our bitmap
writing hopefully.
So let me go ahead and run.
Yes, to all.
I'm gonna go ahead and run this here so that it'll write out our
stuff.
Oh, and you know what else I wanted?
I did want to go ahead and turn off 02, so I want to switch from an
optimized build to a debug build.
Here we go.
So okay, if I run this, it should rewrite a new bitmap file and I
don't know if it will or not.
Looks like it's still not quite happy with our format.
Although it did actually load it up this time, so we're a little bit
better off.
I just don't know.
Now actually we're not I guess just double-clicking.
It work this time for some reason, instead of not double-clicking, it
So, we're still not quite right in our, in our filling out of the
header structure, but I'm not quite sure why.
So let's take a look.
We might have gotten something wrong here.
Let's take a look at the header.
Okay.
So, let's take a look at our header.
Now again I don't really know in this file type field.
I don't know if it should be 40 42 or 42 4D.
What I'm going to do here is I'm going to cheat a little bit because I
can is, I'm just going to say, well, alright, I know that there are
other programs that can write a bitmap out to the drive.
Right.
So why don't I just have one of those, right?
Something out to the drive and then I'll look and see which values it
set the thing to, to begin with, right?
So you
Know, if I created something.
Are in paint or whatever, right.
And then I went and save it out to some file that I can read.
Let's go W handmade Ray data.
I'm going to just pick bitmap.
Like so and I'm just going to say, oh yeah, this is like reference
that bitmap.
Now, I wish I could do 32 bits per pixel, but it didn't have an option
for that.
Maybe I should download like gimp or something, so I can do that and
double check.
But now, we basically have the ability to look at a reference file and
see what that looks like.
So I'm going to go ahead and do that.
I'm just going to say, oh, are you know what?
Let's do an in file.
Let's do an F open here of
Effed up bitmap.
That's what I called it right.
Sorry, reference top bitmap
And all I'm going to do here is I'm just going to do ref header, and
then I'm going to do an an F read from that in file.
I'm just going to f----- read in into the reference header.
I'm going to read in what its contents are, right?
So now, when I run to here in theory, I should have a ref header here
that I can look at that.
Shows me what someone else, who writes a proper bitmap Road out,
right?
So here's the header that we wrote.
Here's the header that they wrote 40, 42 looks correct because
It's the same in both of them.
The file size is going to be different in both.
The reserved here is obviously cleared.
Because it doesn't mean anything to either of us, the bitmap offset.
Our header is bigger than theirs, which is a little confusing.
Now, I guess the question I have here is, is the bitmap offset
supposed to be from the beginning.
I assume it's something.
I'll double-check that.
But anyway, size of the header.
Ours is much larger.
So, I wonder if we should get rid of some of this extra fields, we
have width height, planes bits per pixel.
Again, we set our bits per pixel up higher than theirs, which I assume
is.
Okay, compression is 0 on theirs, it's 3 on ours.
I assume it's should be three.
Let me double-check that I read that wrong.
When I was when I was, when we were looking at our loader now we
expect 34 uncompressed.
Right?
So as a bitmap, all these are set to 0 so maybe I should just clear
those out and then they didn't set a red mask.
Mass because they didn't have that part of the header.
So I don't know.
Maybe we should just stop doing that.
Maybe we're confusing the issue by having those there.
I'm not sure.
But we could get rid of those to be more compliant with what they're
saying, right?
Did they set size of bitmap?
I don't remember if they did.
So let me get rid of those which will make us closer to them.
Because we don't need those Maths for any particular reason.
So let me do that one more time.
I'm just trying to get the number of differences down to the smallest
possible.
Number right?
So now we're the same there where the same here, bitmap offset is the
same size as the same width and height are obviously going to be a
little different planes.
Is the same bits per pixel is a difference.
Now, and compression is a difference, but I think that's because they
use our alien coding.
Let's take a look at that.
Bitmap file format, see what that compression actually means.
Whereas the compression pixel storage compression.
Sure, they are.
Oh wait, bi bit fields, we actually want bir GB.
So, why were we setting compression?
Did I did I read that wrong?
Assert, header compression equals 3.
Why did we want to assert that?
It was bi bit fields.
I guess because we were using the extended header when we were loading
which we don't really need to do so.
Yes.
I guess I would say.
Let's set compression equal to 0 VI RGB is what we actually want their
I guess bi bit Fields is maybe if you want to use
rgba, I'm not sure.
So let's see if this gets us any closer.
Got stop the debugger so I can build.
Yeah.
And now we should be really close to the reference header, right?
Bitmap offset of the same size is now the same.
Planes bits per pixel is the only difference here.
We have all zeros here are size of bitmap.
They set the size of bitmaps.
So I'm going to go ahead and set the size a bitmap because we do know
what it is.
And let's just see if that gets Us close enough to be read.
Oops.
So we're better, right?
We are now a it's now, okay?
It's it's loading it, right?
But we are not getting what we expect.
We're
Thing all grey which we should not get right.
We want to get red pixels because that's what we try to Output.
Oh typo, we never Advanced our pixel pointer.
Right, it was just writing the first pixel the whole time.
There we go.
So now we've got our blue image and that's what we expected.
What I want to do here, now is just emphasize the directionality of
the image.
So what I'm going to do here is say, if why
Is less than 32.
We're going to write one color and if Y is greater than that, we're
going to write another color to put a band at the first pixels of the
image.
So what I'm going to do is say when Y is less than 32.
I'm going to write read and then I'm going to write blue everywhere
else.
So now that I've run it, you can see if I look at our image, we've got
the Red Band at the bottom and what I wanted to emphasize here was
just the fact that
again, we have a
I don't know what how you want to call it.
We have a sort of directionality to our image, the we've written B to
the file, but the person who's reading those B has to then assign
those values to somewhere on the screen.
When it goes to play the bitmap, and it has a decision to make, is it
going to start with the bottom row, or is gonna start at the top row?
And you can see bitmap files by default, they start at the bottom row.
Now, we can switch that.
If I remember correctly, we can start at the top row if we want to.
By setting the width.
I'm sorry.
The height to - I think is the convention in a bitmap file.
I just happen to know.
That's the convention.
So if I convert this to a signed value and flip it, sign like this, I
should be able to get it to, to flip that around.
And what you can see is we've written the exact same thing, the disc,
but just by changing one aspect of the header,
We flip it around.
So we have the option of having a bottom up or top down.
I don't care which one we have.
So I'm just going to go with the more conventional bottom up, but keep
in mind that our bitmap is bottom up.
So we're writing the bottom part first, this is important, because
when we go to generate image, we have to be aware of that fact.
Okay, so that's all well and good.
Let's go ahead and just take a moment to get this out of here so that
we don't have to think about it anymore, right?
So, let's go ahead and make a little bundle of Love here for our
image.
Let's just say that we have a, an output image or maybe.
We'll just say, we just have a generic thing called image.
That will have in it a width.
Height and a pointer to the pixels.
So maybe I'll call this an and you know, image 32 or
Like this because it's an rgba image or something like that in case we
want later to have ones, you know, maybe an image, you 32, something
like that.
And that's just to do that.
We may want like a floating-point buffer later and if I wrap that up I
don't want it to look the same as this, right?
So I want image you throw to be like a big town, like output format,
kind of a situation.
Okay.
So what I'm going to do here is I'm going to introduce again a pound
to find.
You see many times on handmade here are just a thing too.
Basically allow me to mark functions and just say, hey, their internal
because I don't, I'm compiling.
Everything is one C file.
I don't want it to Output stuff to a Linker table or anything like
that.
So, I want to just tell the compiler, hey, every function, I right,
just buying it directly in.
Don't make an export record for it.
Don't do any of that stuff because it can just slow the compile down.
So, everything since I was compiled, a single translation unit anyway,
I don't want anything externalized, everything should be
There's any internal I just don't like using static as a keyword
directly because it means too many different things.
So, I like to use internal this Bentley mark, my function.
So I know that I can search for regular static later if I need it.
All right, so I'm just going to have a thing here called, right image.
It's going to take a file name and a pointer to one of these images
here.
In fact, I might just pass it as a whole struct because it's a small
struct so that's fine.
And what I'm going to do is I'm going to grab all of this information
here that we had previously done.
And I'm going to put it up into this this right image function, right?
So I'm literally just pulling this out of here so that it's not
clogging up the code.
I was trying to write down here because it's a pretty well isolated
unit that I can then use to write images any time I want to write out
image, I can just have one, we don't need the code here that loads in
the reference bitmap anymore because we've got it working well enough
that it's not
An issue.
So I'm just going to go ahead and get rid of that particular piece of
code.
But everything else I'm going to keep because we want the rest of it
right?
So there we go.
Okay, so get rid of that.
So this is something that will take an image and it will write out
exactly the information that we needed here.
So I just have to pull the where I was pulling stuff.
So, you know, previously I was pulling information just from stuff
that I had just right in line.
Now, I'm passing in that information, the form of the structure.
So I've got a generate that information for the width and the height.
I can describe it here for the outfit pixel size.
I need something to compute that for me.
So I've got output pixel size, right?
I need to figure out what that is.
So
if I do something like this where I have a function,
Can basically make that arithmetic that generates the pixel size be
something that anyone can ask for.
So I can take an image to 32 and say What's the total pixel size of
this image that I'm looking at and then it can say, okay?
You know, it's this, you know, so I can say image with
types of image height times size of
You 32, is the size of one of these pixels, one of these images.
So if we do something like that, then I think this routine is
basically done.
That's all it really needs.
Similarly, in here, when I go to create this image, I can wrap that up
into something I can use as well to anytime I want to create an image.
I can just do something like this image.
Or maybe I'll call it allocate image, right?
And all that's going to do is say, what do you want, the width and the
height of the image to be?
And it will do this operation right here.
We go.
And so what that's going to do is say all right I need the total pixel
size of the image and that's easy to do, right?
I just asked for it now.
I need to actually make one of these.
Image wet wet image height equals height and then the image pixels.
Is just an allocated version of that, right?
So now I have a way to ask for the size of images.
I can allocate 1.
I can write it to disk, we're in really good shape here.
Everyone's happy and dancing around.
So here's my image.
I'm going to say allocate image, I'm going to say 1280 by 720.
I'm then going to say okay let's Loop over the width and the height of
the image like so and set all the values, then I'm going to ask it to
write an image and I'm going to write the image to test out bitmap
right and off we go.
Now the output pixels, I just messed up that should have been image
dot pixels, but other than that, I think we're okay.
So let's delete this stuff here and see if it gets properly recreated
there it goes and there's our test bitmap just great.
So now we have the basic functionality.
We need for our raytracer to Output to allocate a basically a place to
write its data from
and we also have the ability to, you know, sort of make as many of
those as we want and write them out anytime we want.
So we can do anything.
We need to do there, right?
So that's done.
What's the next logical step?
Well, the next logical step is, we need to have something to raytrace
and we need to then start writing the ray Tracer, right?
So the first question is, well, what do we want to Ray Trace right?
Like, what can we write in a simple piece of code here?
That would be useful to Ray trace and the reason you often see, Ray
tracers, demoed with spheres and planes is because those are very easy
to write procedurally, right?
I don't need to
Food, Amaya, file or some kind of data file, to be able to make
spheres and planes.
I can just do a simple little function.
That's like place the sphere here and we know that a sphere only
needs, you know, position and a radius, and it's done, right?
So this should be pretty straightforward for us to do if we want to,
we can just make a thing that retraces a bunch of planes and spheres.
So what I'm going to do is I'm just going to set us up to have a
little set of raisins of planes and spheres that we can re
Race and we'll go from there.
All right, so I'm just going to create a little stupid scene
description here.
What I would like to have the ability have two files open at once if
possible so what I'd like to do over here is inside handmade Ray.
I'd like to do a re .h that can just put some of the stuff that we've
got in here.
I'm going to go ahead and put that stuff into the header file.
Like so she probably want to leave these in the C file.
Right.
And so that way I can just I like to, I like to separate things
between each file on the CPP file.
Even though they're all compiled together, I like that things need
Falcons easier for me to have two windows side by side where I'm ice,
trucks on one side and my code on the other so that it's just easy to
remember where things go right?
And I can read my structs.
So, what I need to do here is I need to have some kind of a world that
I'm going to retrace, right?
And I just want to have in it like, you know, okay, I've I want to
have a plane and I want to have a sphere, right?
That's what I said.
And so I need to Define these a plane and a sphere are both defined.
Ironically, basically the same way, but I'm creating two separate
structure them anyway, because who knows?
Maybe I want to do.
I mean, I really don't need structure for these.
I'm kind of in my head debating, whether I really need to bother with
that.
Yeah.
so,
I'm going to.
I'm just going to make these a little differently than I would
otherwise just to make it a little
Or so.
All right, so let's say we've got the plane normal and the plane
devalue
Right.
And here, I've got the sphere position and the radius, right?
So what you can see from here is they're the same definition.
They're both, just a V3 and an F32, right?
A plane is fundamentally a normal and a distance along the normal.
A sphere is fundamentally a point with a radius, they both happen to
be 13d value and one scalar value or a single for four long Vector.
If you want to think of it that way, like both,
Just a V4.
So you can see why I'm kind of
ambivalent about that particular.
Yeah, that particular thing.
But anyway, in addition to that, I also probably want a material in
here.
Something that would allow me to do, like a color value and will
probably store some other things in there.
In addition to the color value as we go for right now, we'll stick
with just the color value.
But in the future, we'll probably do some things that are a little bit
more fancy.
I'm going to actually call it a V3 for a minute.
So it's just going to be an RGB color value in.
That'll be it, and we'll expand that later as we
To do more things fanciness, with respect to the ray tracing.
So I guess I will just say in here.
We'll have an addition to this information will have a you 32, which
is Matt index that's the material that will be used.
I'll put that at the end for now.
And so all I'm doing is just creating a data set that I can read
through here.
And I'm not going to think again too hard about these because I'm just
going to assuming that will.
I'm assuming we'll just change these later on as we go because we
probably won't want them stored in this format in the
Sure, and you'll see why a little later on.
But I'm just I'm just creating a basic version here.
I can't even put a note in here.
We will probably do some more stuff with these later on.
So I'm just pretending, I don't know anything ahead of time here.
I'm just creating some basic stuff I can use to read out in my
raytracer for the base for the start of things, right?
So what I want to do here is to be able to create a little world
struct that will create some things like a plane, and a sphere and
stuff like that, that I can race against.
And I want to be able to have as many planes as many spheres is I
want.
And I want each of those to be able to index into some array of
materials, where the material specified, just a color at some point.
But since this is a ray Tracer, you could imagine the future, maybe
they specify other things, right?
So they might specify more complicated pieces of information.
Something such as.
How translucent material is how what?
It's reflectance function is like maybe it's diffused versus specular,
you know, these sorts of things, okay?
So what I want to do here is I want to have a way of creating one of
these worlds.
So I'm just going to create one of those.
I'm going to basically say that we have, you know, one material,
I'm going to say we have, you know, plain count.
Equals.
I don't know, equals one.
Let's say
Sphere count equals zero for now.
Something like this and here, I will just create a material.
And a plane.
Now, I will want my materials color to be an RGB value.
Let's make it red for now.
I will want the plane.
To have him at index of zero which it will by default I guess and you
know what, I know what you know what?
No no I'm going to take that back.
I think I'm going to do a material count of two and I think I'm going
to I'm going to create two of these.
All right, and I'm going to I'm going to treat them separately.
So I'm going to make a material that's black and a material that's
red.
And I'm going to go ahead and say that the plane has a matte index of
1.
Now, why do I do that?
Because if I've got a plane I also want to have what happens if you
don't hit anything, right?
Because you can trace array and maybe you missed the plane entirely.
Well, there's only a plane in the scene.
That means you didn't get anything.
So I need to have the ray Tracer, do something when it hits nothing.
And what I'm going to have it do is just use materials.
Row and return that color.
All right, that's it.
Okay.
So now I've got a world here, you know, I've got to make sure the
material kind of to my materials, the plane count of one and I got my
plane.
I'm a sphere account, and my sphere is right.
And I could retrace them here.
However, I still have one thing that I don't know which is I don't
know where the camera is going to be pointed, right?
So I need some information about that but we'll take care of that in a
minute, right?
So let's go ahead and compile this.
And what we're going to find is that because we're not including the
handmade hero math Library.
We don't have a vector type yet, right?
You can kind of see here.
We have this problem where we're like, okay, we don't know any of this
stuff.
We don't have any of these.
You three things.
We're just we're just confused here, right?
We don't know what's going on.
So what I need to do is I need to pull in some of that stuff and we
can go ahead and do that by, looking at what we've already written in
handmade hero, right?
You can see we've got all of our sort of V2 stuff in here.
Now, if I look through this in the handmade math directory here, I
guess one question is where yeah, like should be just product proud
include the handmade hero one, or should I copy it out into a
standalone?
I guess.
I'll copy it out for now.
So here's our our V2 V3 V4.
Like so and I'll just sort of put that up here.
Maybe I'll make a special re math.h so that they don't get clogged up
in here and I'm going to replace the refill.
Real three twos with F32 is here like.
So, but this is just a handmade hero math.
That's all it is.
Nothing more fancy than that.
I will also copy my Max values here.
So, we have those days, you might want them.
And the other thing I want to do is I want to grab like all of our
math functions like dot products cross products, that sort of thing
into the math Library, as well.
So let's take a look at which ones of these we need here.
We certainly don't need the I ones the moment.
Well actually, you know what, we can keep, I think about it.
We could keep those hips.
Well, we have a lot of stuff on here.
We don't need anything that works with matrices yet, so let's leave
those out for now.
Like get Rogue column, translate rose, 3x3 like that sort of stuff in
this Game Gear with this.
You can always put them back in if you want.
Orthographic projections and perspective projections, I'm going to get
rid of these.
Well, I basically anything with a matrix, I'm just getting rid of
We're not going to use this yet.
There we go.
So we don't need to transform functions or the multiply functions.
So then I think we're left mostly
Okay, we got some rectangle functions.
We don't need in here.
Go.
I don't really need any of these rectangle functions.
But I hope that's the end of it.
All right.
so when we do our pound include after we do this, we want to include
our math Library here, like so
Did I not make one of these?
I saved this.
Didn't I didn't put it in the wrong place.
Probably put it in the wrong place, huh?
Where did it go?
We don't know where it went.
You went to handmade code, all right.
Yeah, so now we have to do is just again, replace the old type since
we're only using new types in this project.
Oops, I messed that up.
Let's replace, you went 32 with you 32 and I guess these are the only
places these are used.
Yeah, and let's replace real 32 with f 32.
All right.
So we don't have our pie here, so let's see if we can grab pie 32.
I don't know where that's at.
it is so we'll have our pie in our Tau
And then we have lips.
We have to do our sine and cosine at the moment.
We don't really need sine and cosine for anything.
So I'm going to probably get rid of those as well.
F 64 is, we don't need at the moment.
So I'm gonna get rid of those as well.
And then we're good.
So square root.
I'm just going to make a little dummy function here for we may want
that.
And we may need to sin square.
Root can be kind of slow if you don't use the mm intrinsics I'm
probably gonna want to replace this with an intrinsic.
Will include the sea runtimes math library but we probably can't
afford to actually use it so we'll have to deal with that when we get
to the performance side of things.
So round real third 322 in 32, same deal here.
Make a little stub for it.
So since we want to round this thing, real 322 un 32, you know, it's
going to truncate by default.
So we kind of need to do like a biasing operation here.
But both of these are going to want to be done through SSI eventually
so we'll deal with that when we come to it.
So finally we just need our be thirty twos which are just
And I think we are good.
All right, so there we go.
So again, we haven't done anything here except for set up a world that
we can actually Ray Trace.
In order to do that, we're going to have to place our plane somewhere,
right?
That's kind of a prerequisite.
So in order to place our plane somewhere on, let's go ahead and go to
the world's here, right?
At H.
In order to place our plane somewhere, we'd actually have a way of
specifying the plane.
And so, we need to set the n and the D value of our plane, which we'll
get to in a second.
But now it's come, it comes the time.
This point when we are going to have to use some Milton to explain
things, I believe.
So let's get that going right now.
Okay, so let's talk about this real quick.
Mmm.
so, a plane
We want to raytrace something and right now we're going to retrace the
plane in order to retrace the plane.
We need to know a couple piece of information about this plane, for
example, where it is, we know we're going to have a camera set up
somehow and the cameras gonna be looking at the plane.
And so what we need to do is we need to shoot raised out from that
camera and figure out where they hid now.
The easiest way to specify a plane is just using what's called a plane
equation, it's called a plane equation because it defines a plane
space that extends infinitely in all of its directions that are in the
plane.
So, it's got in 3D a plane.
Would be two-dimensional, right?
It doesn't include one of the dimensions.
It extends infinitely in those two dimensions, and not at all in that
third dimension.
It's perfectly flat.
So the way we typically Define that is by using again, the inner
Product, which we've talked about many times that handmade here.
I'm not gonna explain it again here.
You want to go read, watch the handmade here on inter product, use our
handy search feature on The annotation page to find it if you don't
know what it is.
But we're going to use a simple plane equation that says that this
Vector here which is the normal to the plane, the normal to the plane
dot product with a point, right?
Any point on the plane, plus the D value for the plane equals 0.
This is the equation we're going to use to define the plant, right?
This is the normal to the plane.
The D value for the plane is the offset from the origin going
backwards along the normal.
So let's say that we have the origin was here.
So here's the origin you know which is 000 in World space, right?
And here is the normal to our plane, that's the normal to the plane.
Well, if we didn't have this D value, all of our planes would pass
through the origin, right?
They would just pass through the origin.
Why would they pass through the origin?
Because the definition of the plane would just be that the dot product
with a point has to equal 0?
Well, a DOT product with a point in three dimensions is just going to
tell us how far along this normal.
You are.
And if it has to equal 0, it means you always must be.
Excuse me, mapping to the origin, right?
Because the dot product along this thing has to be zero, you must
always be mapping to the origin.
Along that line.
Now, you could be anywhere along the plane, right?
That is tangent to this line, but you can't ever go anywhere on this
line, which means that this plane here that I've defined can never
slide relative to the origin.
I couldn't have the same plane but just backed up a bit, right?
Couldn't have it out here.
That's what this D value does.
The devalue corrects for the fact that we may want the dot product to
be actually some value along this line.
And in this case like I said it goes backwards along the normal.
Why does it go backwards because it's plus d equals 0.
If we instead phrased, it m transpose P equals D.
Now it would be how far along the normal we go, but because we've
transferred it to the other side in in
The effort to write it as a single.
One-sided equation equation with equaling zero on the other side.
It's backwards along the normal.
Right now.
What happens if you write this out, you get n x PX +.
N YP y + n.
Zp z + D equals 0.
This is the dot product part.
This is the depart what you can see here is you get the traditional ax
plus b.
Y plus CZ plus d equals 0 the a fine.
Asian in three dimensions that you probably have should have seen
before.
This is just a very straightforward way.
Finding things so that's our plane.
I'm just going to define a very simple plain.
I'm going to define a plane that just points up in the Z.
Let's will make ZB up and I'm going to have the D value be just 0.
So this is the plane that passes through the origin.
It points directly up.
So it's the XY plane passing through the origin.
The simplest possible plane.
We could hope that a fine and there it is.
Okay, so now we need to go ahead and do some actual
Will Ray tracing here.
So what we need to do is we need to start figuring out how we're going
to build this image.
Well, here's the thing that builds a generic image, right?
But I've already written
And what it does, is it steps through each pixel and it just sets it
to an arbitrary value, right?
Well, what I want to do here is I want to start retracing to find out
what I actually should see from here.
In order to do that, I'm going to need a camera position obviously,
right?
I got to need a place that we're looking from, and I'm also going to
need a camera Direction.
I'm going to need kind of a camera position, and I'm going to need a
camera like direction that note we should call that camera are, maybe
for camera ray.
I don't know what we want to call it, but point B, we need some way of
figure out like what we're pointing down.
Okay, actually, do you know what I want to call it, but we haven't
gotten there quite yet.
So for camera position.
Well, I know, I want to look down at this plane, right?
So I probably want to be, you know, I can put the camera anywhere
since the plane extends infinitely.
You next and why doesn't really matter where I put the camera relative
to X and Y axis.
But for Z, since the plane is in the z-axis, I need to be a bit above
it.
So I'm going to set my camera P to be like, 10 units above.
And we haven't specified what these units are yet.
So we don't really care.
But 10 units above the thing, let's say they might be M because that's
probably what we'll end up.
Sending them to when we start to get more physical, will probably pick
meters, but
You know you're laughing now and then we want to be pointing slightly
downwards so we can look to slightly down at the plane, right?
So if we're looking just slightly down at the plane and you know what
I could do maybe I'll move the camera backwards along.
Like the y axis for example to so maybe I'll be ten back and you know
and one up or something instead.
So if I was going to do that and I want to look at
and I want to look at say the origin because maybe I'll put a sphere
there in a second.
How are we going to do that, right?
Well what I want to be able to do is I want to be able to create
essentially a little screen where the camera is like.
This is the camera, and here's the plane that I'm looking down on,
right?
I'm going to want to create like a sphere here or something.
And I want to play nanosphere Sitting on the plane like a traditional
Ray traced image, right?
So, in order to do that, I want to create some kind of an axis system,
because I'm kind of a coordinate system here where it lines up with
that sort of idea, of looking down.
So I want to create basically a synthetic coordinate system for my
camera.
So I can construct raise that will shoot out from it, right?
In a way that makes sense.
Yes.
So in order to do that, I'm just gonna do something very
straightforward.
I'm going to say, well I know what the Z axis of my camera should be
which is the thing that I'm going to look down.
It should point back you know it's a it should I want to look down the
negative Z axis just like our convention in opengl, right?
Just to keep it simple, I want to look down the negative Z axis, so my
Z axis should basically just be pointing up from the origin to the
camera.
So it's just the cameras position is just that Z axis, right?
From the origin of the
Because that's the camera position - the origin, right?
Well - the origins, nothing and I want it to be unit Vector.
So I just need to normalize it, right?
And I assume we have some stuff here like normalizer 0, I can just
call that to normalize that.
Sure, it is.
But then I need the other actions as well, right?
And that's going to be my z-axis.
I need to know what my X and my y axes are
So what are those axes?
Well, we already covered this at when we did our cross products and
stuff like that right?
Oops.
I considered a question mark there.
Just not up and you know what?
This is handmade math.
I don't want to edit handmade math.
That's my bad.
I want to hand edit Ray math if I'm going to do anything here.
So anyway, I want to be able to do stuff like the cross product and I
want to be able to create, you know, an orthogonal coordinate system
for example from that.
From that starting coordinate system.
So, what I can do here again, is used the cross product to help me
out.
So I know that I've got a z-axis, right, and I know that, I know what
direction I want sort of up to be pointing the right.
I know that this is my camera z-axis.
And I know that this is the universal z-axis here, right?
And if I cross those two, so if I crossed my Universal Z, axis with my
camera Z axis, remember, right?
Hand rule cross Z axis with my camera Z axis, I'll get an X
Is pointing out, right?
So if I do a cross product,
Of the universal Z axis, with my camera Z axis, I'll get that camera
X.
And I'm going to need to normalize that, right?
Because it's going to be pointing, it's going to be an X axis that's
that's not unit length.
And then if I want my y-axis, I'm going to need to cross those two
together again.
Right.
So I'm going to have to take my Z axis in my x-axis.
I mean need to cross Z with X to get y, right?
And I believe that should give me what I want.
I'm going to double-check this though because this is a very you know
easy thing to get wrong when you're just sort of thinking it through
Oops, I meant Type X there.
Thank you, compiler.
That was a good catch.
I'm going to go ahead and step here and I'm going to look at these
briefly, but I'm not going to learn much from looking at them.
So I'm going to make a controlled test case in a second where you can
see what's going on.
But I just want you to sort of get the feel for what I'm doing here.
So you can see what I've created is an axis system.
You can see that my camera x-axis is negative 1, and you can see that
my Y and my Z axis are set to, some sort of values that are difficult
to inspector.
But they're basically like one
You know, 111, you can see that.
That is orthogonal, which is great.
So we know that we're basically doing the right thing, but I'm not
sure if my x axis, the point in the right direction.
I need to think about that for a second, if I camera P, if my camera
placement is back at 10, then my Z is pointing positive.
Kind of a y+ 10 which means that my x axis if my Y is pointing
positive 10 and I'm sorry, my Z is playing positive 10 and I want my
y-axis to be pointing sort of upwards, right.
It should have a positive Z value, which it does, which means that my
x-axis cross my
My wife is it?
That just seems wrong.
Just and I'm wondering if I got the sign wrong there, ought to think
about that.
And I want to test something.
So here's an easy test.
I can perform
If I set the camera Z axis to the actual Z axis, right?
I should get back the unit coordinate system if I did it, right.
And let's see if I did here.
Oh.
Well actually you know what?
I can't quite do that because I'm using the Z axis as the generation
that as the cross product for Generation there.
So that's a little bit iffy.
I would need to use a different axis for it.
So let's say instead that the camera z-axis is going to point directly
down, why?
Right?
So, I'm just looking straight in the plane.
And let's take a look at this.
So if the Z axis is pointing directly down, why
Jimmy windows.
So, here's my plane, here's the origin.
So the Z axis is pointing this way for the camera, which means we're
looking this way.
I know that I want my y-axis to be positive Z, right?
It should be pointing up.
So the question is, what direction is my x axis pointing?
If this is y, and this is z right X, cross y should be Z.
So my x axis should be pointing this direction, right?
It should be 100 because X cross y should be easy.
And you can see that.
It's negative one here.
So I think that's right.
That's telling me that I believe my assumption before that, I was
that.
I had an error in the ordering here is correct?
Because I don't believe that should be the case.
So let's take a look one more.
Look at how I constructed this and see what I did wrong.
Okay, so, I know I had a z-axis and I was crossing it with the regular
Z axis to get my x axis.
So, if I'm crossing with this, I would expect to cross from y to Z to
get an X pointing in this direction.
So, did I do that?
From y to Z to get my ex
Right?
So I feel like that should be giving me the correct answer there.
From why towards easy to get my ex that seems like it should have been
correct, right.
At least to me.
Right-hand rule would suggest.
So here's where I'm why I'm confused.
So here is
One axis that I have.
Right, it's 001.
Here's another axis that I have.
Ah, you know what know, I drew the diagram wrong.
This is positive y.
So that is not the direction.
This would go.
It would actually be going this way in this plane, the way I've drawn
it.
So I drew a left-handed.
I am.
So you actually don't want what I said, right?
I drew the diagram left-handed by accident, which was dumb of me.
I drew the plane saying that this was Y and this was X.
But then when I said along positive, why I drew it this way, which
flipped the handedness of my coordinate system and led me to make the
wrong decision, based on the right hand rule, right?
This is actually other coordinate system looks and you can now see
that if I wanted to produce my x-axis
Yes, I would cross from y to Z to get it which is the correct
Crossing.
Right?
So, it should, in fact, cross the opposite direction it should cross
from this end, this is actually the camera Z axis, right?
It should cross from the camera Z axis towards that.
Universal up Axis, that would produce my ex.
Once I have the X, then I know that if I want to produce the Y from
it, then in order to produce the y-axis, from just having the x and z,
I would cross from thes e to the x.
So, there we go.
So in theory now, I think that should be correct.
There we go.
And again, you can see that would have cause it's a lot of headache in
if we let it stand so you can see why I wanted to create that, just
inspect and double check because it's easy to make a typo.
When you do something like that or like I like in my case it was a
diagram typos and don't you call is diagram.
Oh,
And I don't want that creeping into the code.
Okay, so now we have a coordinate system to work with.
So now we're going to do the simplest possible thing to get our rate
face or started normally.
At this part in the, the ray Tracer.
If you're doing a full raytracer, what you need to do is create a lens
aperture, some idea of how you're stimulating like a camera, right?
Because fundamentally, what erasers doing is stimulating how light
propagates through lenses in a camera onto a backplane, which like, so
we're not going to talk about yet because that's a tremendous amount
of complexity to bring into the program at this stage.
We just want to get something basic working.
So what we're going to do, instead, it just figure out some way to
shoot raised at the screen at.
All, right.
That's all we're going to do.
So what I'm going to do is I'm going to pretend we have a very simple
construct which is that we know we now have a y-axis for the camera,
and an X axis for the camera and the Z axis for the camera.
I'm saying we're looking down this direction.
So I'm going to do is I'm going to say at -1 units out right along the
Z.
Axis of the camera from the cameras position.
This is all camera stuff.
I'm going to say, we've got a little
Imagine.
D square.
Well it's actually going to be rectangle.
You don't will even start with a square so you can see.
And then we'll move to rectangle that just goes like from negative 1
to 1 and a negative 1 to 1 like so that we're going to treat as our
image that we're going to shoot raised through.
Right.
And I'm just going to step through the various positions on this plane
for as many pixels as we have.
I'm going to go across the plane and I'm going to shoot the Rays out
so that I can see what they hit.
Right.
Because fundamentally that's what I need to get the ray Tracer
started.
So what I want to do is I want to say, all right as I go through here,
I want to convert these values.
These why from image from, you know, x from 0 to image with wife from
certain image height, I want to convert these into
A ratio along that plane that I can use.
So, I'm going to call this, like, plane y, or I should say, like, you
know, that that image plate.
So I'm going to call this like,
Maybe like, let's just call it y ratio.
Now.
That's bad, too.
I don't know film film.
Why?
Film X.
And what I want to do here is say, well, okay, I know that I have a
y-coordinate and an image height and I know that that if I divide the
Y by the image height, I'll get a number from 0 to 1, right?
And that number from 0 to 1, tell me how far across this film plate.
I am.
But I said I want to go from negative 1 to 1.
So what I need to do is subtract 1 from it.
Let's start at negative 1 and I need it to go twice as far because
going from 0 to 1, I get to go basically.
You're too, right?
So it starts out negative 1 goes to 1.
Right.
So, there we go.
And now I have a film X film Y, which are the ratios of where I would
be on this little thing here, right?
So then, all I need to do to create a point through which I will shoot
this Ray, like a point on the image plane that I'll shoot the ray
through all, I really have to do is go, okay, start wherever the
center of this thing is, right.
So I've got, you know,
Film Center.
And I know what that is, is just the camera position.
Plus, however, far along.
I want it to be along the camera Z, but I'm going backwards.
Remember, so I'm going backwards.
However, far, I want to go there will say one unit for now, and I'll
just call this my film dissed.
And remember these are this is just a Cheesy way to get the raise to
start with.
Eventually, we would want to put in a whole camera aperture here where
the film is actually on the other side, right?
So the film would actually be back here.
The Rays would actually pass through a lens on this side, through the
focal point of the lens back onto the image plate but we're not doing
any of that yet because we just want basic raised and to debug basic
Ray casting.
So we're taking all of that out because you don't want to run before
you can crawl.
You know, you gotta crawl.
First, debug your crawling before you try to implement your running.
All right, so with a film exfil, my ratio now, I know that if I take
this Film Center, right?
And I can basically a film P here by taking the film Center Point and
adding the film X and film.
Why ratios along the camera X and Camera?
Y axes, right?
So again, I'm just starting here and I'm walking out along those to
produce a point on the plane.
Now, I
Need in addition, a size idea.
I need to know like a film width and a film height here.
and I need to know, like, basically a half of those
because again, like however wide it is, I'm multiplying a value from
negative 1 to 1.
However wide it is, I if this was W, I want to multiply it by half of
w because I want the maximum I go in a direction to be half that cuz
I'm starting from the center, right?
So here I've got a film W film H and I'm going to say those are just
again one.
And then I'm going to say half film W, equals film w.
Like so.
And that just gives me again, a simple way of constructing a location.
So now, I want to shoot my Ray.
So my film Ray is just going to be or I'll just call it Ray.
Direction.
So I knew the race starts at the camera location, I know the ray
direction is going to be the normalized version of whatever.
My film point is - my camera location, right?
Because I'm just shooting at in that direction.
So, then I have a real origin Ray Direction and I'm ready to ask, you
know, basically the color here is going to be whatever our raycast
function does with
Origin.
Ray Direction.
And taking this world into account.
So there we have it.
That's how we're going to get our color.
We're going to start at this very origin.
We're going to cast out in this Ray direction.
We're going to assume you have a function.
That could tell us what the color is there.
The color is going to come back and
We need to convert that color.
And I think we already have again, a way of packing that color down.
We have RGB Pack 4 by 8, it's going to expect the values to be 255
based there.
So we got to do, we got to do a little, something something there,
right?
But we can do that pretty easily by just converting it first.
So if I do RGB Pack 4 by 8, that's going to expect a
V4.
So what I'll do here is just say, I'm going to take a final color
value here or or like like BMP color and I'm going to say that that's
a V4.
I'm going to say that the alpha value is going to be 255 and the color
value is going to be 255 times.
Whatever the color is, we get back right?
That way I can call RGB pack for
I can call RGB packed 4 by 8 on the be a fun color, get back a pact
color.
And then when I write this in to our bitmap, instead of writing, the
bogus value here, I can actually read a real value into the location
and get something real.
Now, if we compile this, hopefully, oops.
Hopefully we don't miss a star there.
Hopefully, at this point.
Now we have this raycast and we need to implement it, right?
We need to say what that raycast does.
But before I do that, that's going to involve a lot of math and work
on our part.
And so before I do that, I want to make sure that it can just even
return color values and and have them written out properly, right?
So when I do my raycast and I I'm expecting it to take a
Here.
And I'm expecting it to take a ray origin redirection.
Like so, what I want to do is I want to make sure that if I, if I, you
know, make a result value here, they'll get packed properly.
So first of all, let's do the most simple thing.
Let's return 0 and see if when I run the program I get back a black
image, right?
Because I want you know, I don't want any color values here at all.
So I'm expecting to see a thing of the day director, that just all
black and I do and that's good.
And now that
It's verify that I can return back a color value, that makes sense to
me.
So let's say I want to Output read as my color value.
Here we go.
And now let's look at here and see and you can see it's wrong already,
right?
It's blue.
So that means that these this are GBA Pac.
4x4 is is packing based on RGB ordering.
So what I probably want to do is use a, the B gr a pact
Which I think does in the opposite order.
Yeah, so I really want Biggio.
Pack and there, I've already gotten rid of a bug that would have cost
us a bunch of headaches later again, just by taking it cautious, and
making sure that you do simple test to ensure that you don't have some
kind of a stupid, you know, stupid thing going on there.
All right.
So now we need to take the ray casting and actually try to do
something realistic with the raycasting.
That's actually going to produce some results that we can verify mean
something to somebody at some point.
So, let's go ahead and
And try to do that.
So what I'm going to do first that's going to say, well I know that
what I said, what I wanted to do was take the materials.
And take a look at that first material and I want to take its color
and assume that, that's the result.
So if I never hit anything, if my rage is mrs.
Everything in the world I'm going to use material zero as a color and
I think we set that to Black so we'll just see black.
If we don't hear anything then what I want to do is I want to look
through all of the things in the world and see which one I hit first.
Now, remember the link one thing in the world, you have to worry too
much about that right now.
But in the future we're going to have like multiple spheres and planes
and stuff.
We
Don't know which one we hit first.
How do we know which one we hit first?
Well, if you look at what's out there in the world,
I've got these spheres, I Got This Plane, I'm looking at it, right?
Well what I want to do is I say when I cast a ray, I'm going to start
producing these values that are where I shit.
So here's a bunch of places that this Ray would intersect the geometry
of the world.
I always want the one that's closest to where I started from, right,
because the first thing I hit is the first thing I have to process.
Even if this thing is translucent, I want to process the hit here
first and then keep casting through.
I don't want
Do something weird where I use, like afar like a back hit of this Ray
because then I'll get an incorrect, sorting order of things.
So I want to make sure I was take the first hit, what that means is
I'm going to go through here and do all of my hit detection.
I want to do it based on who is closest to the real origin, right?
So I'm going to start out by saying hit distance and I'm going to use
that Maxim F value.
So I'm going to do hit distance, equals F, 32 Max.
I'm going to go through there and when I take a hit I'm only going to
process that hit.
If I actually found that I did.
I that it's closer than any of the other hits I've processed, right?
So, here we go.
I'm going to start out clean and x equals 0.
I'm going to let plane index run up to the number of planes in the
world.
Step through each of them.
I now want to get out a particular plane.
So I'm just going to take that plane and say, all right, whatever, you
know, we've got here.
Let's go ahead and Factor.
You know what, I might just grab it out in wholesale planes, plain
index.
I'm going to grab that plane and then I'm going to do the intersection
test with the plane and I'm going to basically to say like if you know
I want some kind of a hit distance here so I want like a like a this
distance kind of a thing, all right?
So how far it was so I want to do like Ray intersects plane
and when I do that intersection of Ranger sex plane, I want to do re
origin Ray Direction and then the plane normal.
So I want to do plane normal plane D like so I want to do that.
Ray intersection test here.
And to be honest, when I think about it, I probably could do this in
line.
I'm probably going to leave.
Let's just leave like that for second, but I'm going to say if this
distance is less than the current his distance that I wanted.
And furthermore, it also has to be greater than zero.
Because remember, when we do these tests, we're going to be using the
math.
That it's very difficult to write math that test for intersection with
array because array is like an infant is a is a half space.
You know, it's
Has an origin point and it doesn't extend back in the other direction.
The math that we're going to write is always going to intersect with
like a line or something.
And so we need to make sure we clip it manually after we do the
intersection and get rid of the ones that are that are zeroed, right?
So we're going to say if this if the distance is greater than 0 but
less than the hit distance, right?
Then we can process the hit.
So at that point we will say all right we're going to process the hit.
We're going to say that the hip distance is going to now this is now
the closest hit and we're also going to say that result is going to be
the materials color of this plane.
Like so, all right.
Really?
Really basic.
That's all we want to do.
And if we compile this, we should find Hoops, we don't have float Max
and that's because we don't have
slow down.
Eh, I believe ya.
And so now, all we really need to do is write Ray intersects plane.
We need to write some of that takes a plane and a ray intersects them.
Now again, this is not particularly hard math to do.
Fortunately, if we have a position and array.
Like so, so here's our Ray origin.
This is our Ray Direction.
And we've got a plane out in the world and that has a normal devalue
like so what we need to do is figure out a way to intersect these two
things, right?
We have to figure out a way to to find this point.
All right?
Well, what do we know about array?
Well,
Let's say that we've got that re origin in this case, we know that
we're starting at the ray origin and we know that we're marching out,
I'm gonna introduce a synthetic T value here, which is the saying some
amount of marching along the ray direction, right?
This is the equation for the ray where T is greater than or equal to
0, right?
So we're going to start because this would be t - this is t+, right?
So we're going in this direction.
I don't know what is happening there.
That's probably something.
You awesome pain windows.
I have to figure out turn off but we're marching in this direction as
long as we want.
So T can just get in front of them out to the maximum floating point
value and we know that our plane, right?
So this is the equation for re-write.
This is our F of R 0 Rd T, but really it's just F of T because these
two are fixed for our purposes, so our F of T equals r0.
+ t,
R&D, right?
And this is the function for the re our plane equation.
On the other hand, we already said what it was its n, p+ d, equals 0.
So if we want to know, when a ray would land directly on the plane,
this is the equation that tells us we land on the plane.
We know p p is this, right?
So, if we substitute in this equation, for the point, we can find out
and solve for T, we can find out when
When we would hit it, right?
So we do n, r0 + TR d.
Plus the equal zero we then just have to solve, right?
This is a transpose here.
So n transpose.
AR 0 plus T and transpose.
R d plus d, equals 0.
That's our equation.
Lucky for us.
T only exists on one term here, so we can isolate things really
quickly.
We have n TR D, equals negative, D / -, and transpose AR 0, the
negatives cancel.
And I believe we're just left with n transpose AR D, equals
The over.
Boo.
I left my T value.
This is sloppy math day just pretend none of that ever happened.
Pretend you didn't see that, but I meant to write was we only have a
t-value to solve for that.
Leaves us with t and t are D, equals - d - n TR 0.
And then, what I meant to do is take that guy and put him on the
bottom, divide through and TRD to solve for T.
So we end up with negative d - n TR 0 and TRD, right?
This is a DOT product, this is a DOT product, this is a known value.
So all of these are known and our d and r 0, all known very simple.
Result, right?
So to get this distance value.
I just have to read it off - plain D, which is that value there -
inner product of the normal to the plane and whatever the ray origin
is right.
I want to divide that by n TR D, which is the inner product of again
that plane normal.
And whatever the ray that are D is the right direction.
And I have my answer, right?
So we can get rid of that.
Now we do have one problem.
Goodbye denominator here.
And the problem we have with, this is an inner product, can produce a
zero.
If the plane normal and the ray direction or perpendicular, we would
get a zero in our denominator and we cannot divide by zero.
Right, that would be bad.
What does that mean, physically?
Well, what it means is I've got a re Direction now.
I've got a plane normally it will hit the plane, right?
Even if the planes going this way, we'll get an answer.
It'll just be a negative answer, right?
But if the ray Direction and the plane were the same, sorry if the ray
Direction and the normal were perpendicular.
So the the plane is running exactly parallel to the ray.
They never hit right?
They'll never hit each other.
And so what the math is telling us is that there is an undefined place
where we cannot find the answer at all because there is no answer and
that's actually the math being really good there.
It's telling us that these two things can't intersect
so, what we want to do there is say, if the denominator
Is between some very small bounds, right?
So, we've got some tolerance value here, right?
Let's say it's very small.
And basically, if the denominator itself is less than the negative
tolerance or I should say, if the absolute value, let's say,
Don't we have an ABS?
I don't know if we do, doesn't matter what I could say is if the
denominator is less than the negative tolerance.
Or greater than the positive tolerance.
Then we can continue.
But if it's not, we can't it just didn't hit right?
Does that make sense?
And so now we have a thing that will raycast against this plane up,
borrowing math typos and stuff like that.
That's bad.
You know, we wouldn't have won but that's the basic idea.
So now what I want to do is I want to introduce something because now
we're actually going to start testing this.
I want to do something that will make.
Lives a little bit simpler.
Whenever we build, I want to go ahead and run it and I want to, you
know, so I want to do a push d.
Basically, to the data directory.
And I want to run the program.
Like so and that way when I run like so and you know what?
And let me also put a little thing in so I can verify that it's
running.
so this way we can see that it does, it's Ray Kasten and then it
finishes
There we go.
Recast and done.
And so now we can actually go see the result.
Every time you run, I'd like it to pop up our result to so we can see
what the result is.
So I'll also just do a start on the output value which is test up at
map.
And there it is.
Okay.
So here is our resulting value.
It looks a little busted to me but I don't know whether it's because I
set up our stuff busted or whether the ray Tracer is busted, we got
partly the result we wanted which is half red, half black, which is
what we should get.
But I don't know whether we're if the red should be on the top or the
bottom based on what I set the plane values to so we might have to.
So now we just want to debug our stuff to make sure.
We've got the correct things in mind.
Also,
We're doing a bottom-up bitmap and that is what we set up our film to
do as well.
Why is pointing upwards?
So in theory that should all be correct as well.
But again, we need to verify all of these assumptions so that we can
start our Ray tracer on solid footing and not have any weird like
weird nonsense going on, right?
Okay, so let me go ahead and check what we set up for our world here.
Here's our planes.
We said that our planes.
Normal was pointing straight up.
Our D value is right down the middle so it's it's just a p.
Origin pointing upward, so that's fine.
And then our camera P.
It's supposed to be kind of up above the surface, so the red should be
on the bottom, and it's not right now.
So, I think we've got a bug there and I want to take a look at it.
So let me just double check again that we've got our right equations
here.
I just want to test it one more time.
So let me just just double-check these equations.
I want to make sure they're right, and I'm gonna step through them and
see what's going on and make sure that we don't have bugs in there.
Okay.
So,
We have, I'm gonna do this like more slowly methodically here.
So we have n transpose.
P plus d.
Equals 0.
That's our plane equation.
We then have Jenny
Our equation for the ray which is I'm going to write this a little
more compactly here.
But actually I'll write it the same way I did before which is re
origin plus T redirection right?
And that equals our Point substituting these in I get in transpose,
right.
Origin plus T, right direction plus d equals 0.
Multiplying out.
I get n transpose.
AR 0 plus T and transpose.
R d, plus d, equals 0 subtracting over to the other side.
We get T and transpose r d equals negative d.
- n transpose AR 0 dividing out.
I get - d - n transpose AR 0 / n transpose r d--
Right, and N transpose Rd is here.
And that is our denominator.
It's correct - plane D- plane n times, right?
Origin is correct there.
We're dividing by the Dominator.
That's our T value.
That all looks good to me.
So that all seems pretty straightforward.
I don't see any real obvious errors in there.
Yeah.
I don't see anything particularly strange going on there.
The real origin is the camera position.
The radial direction is the film P camera P.
So I think this should be giving me what I expect there again.
I don't think there's anything wonky going on there.
So let's go ahead and try to figure out why we're getting.
And you know what?
I also want to, I'm going to set that background color something
slightly different cuz the background of that viewer happens to be
black.
So I want to see exactly how
How?
At the images as well.
So must set this to like a just a gray, just so I can see ya.
So this looks like exactly backwards from what I would expect, right?
It looks exactly like the wrong.
Scan out and I assume we're not flipping or bitmap anymore, right?
We're doing bottom up so that seems right and
And so we must just have one simple error in here and I just don't
know what it is.
So I'm going to go ahead and step in so I can just see if I see
anything that I don't like that would save us some trouble and give us
a clue as to what's going on.
So there's our Ray origin.
We're up one, and we are back 10, right?
Or forward 10, I guess that makes sense.
our redirection is,
Negative X.
That makes sense because we're looking at the image plane - why, which
also makes sense somewhat
I'm not so sure about that.
So let's hold on one second here.
Since I was drawing it this way before with the negative 10, I kind of
want to be a little bit more matching my mental model.
So here's the plane.
Here's why here's X that's Z.
I wanted the camera back here.
So that's actually - why and I just want to set it that way so that
we're matching my mental model.
So that we're looking down like this, it just helps me to debug
things.
If if I'm not like thinking of the wrong thing in my head,
Okay, so yeah, the film centers should be the film distance, which is
one down the negative Z axis, which should be this axis roughly.
So, it should be like four words this way.
And I think that's a little bit closer to what I wanted.
Okay, so let's try it one more time.
All right.
So let's take a look at the rate.
Origin -
And one that's what I wanted.
Ray Direction the Y being positive.
Is correct because we're going that direction.
And the Z being positive also makes.
That, that doesn't make sense.
Does it?
Because it is Z should actually be negative when we're starting out.
And the reason that I say that is because the cameras y-axis is
effectively more or less pointing Z along Z, right?
And if the cameras Y axis is pointing along Z, I would expect it to
initially be shooting downward because the film.
Why should be negative 1 at the start, right?
So something's a little off there.
And I don't know what it is, but it needs to get fixed.
So I'm going to step into that.
See what I messed up.
So let's first check film X and film.
Why you should be negative 1 and negative 1 which they are
Let's take a look at film pee.
Why I hate that.
I hate that.
It the new wind Visual Studio.
Doesn't move you down to the next line.
When you hit return, that's super sucky.
This is visible to your 2017, and I don't like it.
All right.
So camera p 0 - 10 1 film p is negative 5.
That makes sense because of the film, that's the film X offset there.
I'm gonna look at Film Center as well.
That should be 0.
It is, it should be slightly further and y and z.
I think that looks pretty much all correct to me.
That looks pretty much all correct to me.
So now, if we look at film P, what's the camera X camera?
Oops.
And that's going to take forever.
To get used to have to hit the down down.
That's that's terrible.
Why do they change that?
I have no idea.
So, camera X is negative 1.
As we expect camera, why is a highly negative
Value, but it should be a positive Z value.
That looks like we still have a bug.
Right here.
So when we are producing these values, looks like we still got a bug
here.
So, R Cross of cameras, easy with the up Axis.
Let's take a look here.
So, we're looking to produce this.
Here's our camera X camera Z, camera y.
And what I would like to do here is, I would like to ensure that, you
know, these are all accurate.
So if we take a look at what supposed to happen here, if I know that I
have my up Vector,
And I prescribe mice easy, if I have a seat C, Vector crossed with an
up Vector, what I want to be able to do is cross up and Z together,
right?
That's why I do here across up and Z together.
Did I did I liked think I had?
Did I like undo a correct thing here or something like that?
Because this is 2.
This is back to where I thought I was starting from, right, but if I
have an up Vector, and I crossed CZ that actually does still argue for
the direct the way that I had it before.
Right?
So c z here is going this way.
I have an up, I would cross up and Z to get X, right?
I would then cross Z and X to get y.
So did I like, talked myself out of the right solution before?
I think I did, I think I had it right?
And I changed it because of that diagram mess up.
What?
I really my mental model, I thought my camera piece of it - 10, I had
it at 10.
I wonder if that was the entirety of it but that is now correct.
And that is the bitmap that I expected.
Yeah, I I talked myself out of the correct code.
That's pretty good.
All right.
So anyway we have our Ray and our plane as you can see, when I run
this.
Now, we get our red plane and we get our gray sky, if you will, I
don't know what you want to call it, but we get that.
Whatever that is.
So now, what we need to do is we need to say, all right, we need to
add our spheres to this, right?
Because that was the other thing that I said that I wanted.
So I'm going to go ahead and add a sphere.
I'm going to put about the origin.
And give it a new material.
This will be a blue Sphere for, who knows why it just will be.
And then what I want to do is I want to add that sphere in here, just
like we did before with the plane.
So now I have a sphere and if I run it, what just happened?
Hmm.
So why would adding a sphere there?
Cause our mat index to be wrong plane dot.
Matt index should still be one.
It should still be picking.
Of course, this should be 3, but that should have nothing to do with
it, right?
How did we get blue?
0 1 & 2, we set the colors.
Here, we're taking our world materials were using the mat index of the
plane.
That should index into the materials properly.
That's bizarre.
Let's check out what happened there.
I'm going to take a quick look here.
At our world.
There's our spheres.
I hope that was a good typo.
There we go.
Alright, so we yeah.
I just accidentally set the plane index.
Again, Matt index.
That's good.
So now we need to actually have a loop that that takes into account.
The fact that we have series as well and so this is going to be
similar but all of the intersection code will be different right?
So here is a floating are spheres out.
Basically, everything is exactly the same.
The only thing is we need to now put in the intersection test for a
sphere now.
Unfortunately, for us the intersection test for a sphere is a little
more complicated but that's okay.
We can still work it out.
We're all Brave programmers here.
It's fine.
So here is what happens if we want to do a sphere.
Do the same exact procedures you did for a plane right?
Remember how I did it?
I said, well, I've got the equation that says, what?
The
His point is and so all I need is a thing that takes a sphere as
equation and tells me if a point is on or not and we know how to do
that, actually, right?
We know that the equation for a sphere is just the same as the
equation for a circle.
It's just going to be all of the value squared equal.
It - the radius equaling zero or whatever.
Right?
So we know that, for example, a sphere is just the point x squared.
Plus the point Y squared plus the point Z
Z squared equals the radius squared or another way to write that is
minus the radius squared equals 0, right?
It's moving over to their side.
So if that's the case, we can trivially.
Do this exact operation exactly the same way by leveraging.
The fact that we actually know what those points are right because we
can basically solve the equation for T.
Again, just like we were doing in the previous case.
If we take a look at what happens here, x squared plus, y squared plus
Z squared, that should look pretty familiar to folks that is just the
dot product, right?
Of a vector with itself.
So this is just P transpose P.
Minus r squared equals zero for the love of God Windows.
What is that weird back button thing?
Does anyone know what that is?
Some kind of just real thing, I don't know.
So, anyway, we essentially just have P transpose P.
Minus r squared equals zero, right?
That's all we're trying to compute here.
So P transpose p.
Is this right?
What would that look like?
So P transpose P would be R 0 plus t or d transpose.
Right.
R0 + T Rd, right?
It would just be
This here.
And since the dot product does distribute, we can probably just do
this in sort of a
What's the what's the word?
I'm looking for a way we can, we can do this as if we were doing a
regular multiplication.
Right.
So we can do R 0 transpose, AR 0 + T Rd transpose AR 0 or a origin or
whatever you want to do plus the same thing again, right?
So This this term is actually going to be squared here, right?
Plus this term squared as well, right?
So Plus
T squared.
Actually, that's not true.
That's a to yeah, right.
Because that
R0 T, Rd T Rd?
R 0 is 2 times TR D 0 right?
Plus t squared.
R 0 transpose, AR 0, right?
So I believe we can get away with that because
As the dot product happens to distribute, we end up with a quadratic
equation in t, right?
That is this value.
So literally, the whole equation is actually just substituting that in
right for p transpose p.
I get the entire equation.
So, unfortunately it's a quadratic equation which means I have to use
the quadratic equation to solve it.
But fortunately, it's not like that's a huge deal, right?
Because the quadratic equation is the quadratic equation.
So if I organized
These terms I get t squared r 0 TR 0, right?
Plus the T term, which is T to r d transpose AR 0, right?
And then the constant term, which is R 0 transpose, AR 0, minus r
squared, right?
So actually, this is our D.
So that's actually an R&D and my handwriting is an impediment to the
math.
Right.
So it's going to look something like this where we have a quadratic
equation in like a BC Hoops, see to calculate the intersection for the
sphere.
So, in order to do the quadratic equation, right?
It's the standard thing of
Gosh, can I remember this?
It's like negative B plus or minus square root of
B squared, minus 4AC over 2A.
Is that the quadratic equation?
You can tell I do a lot of work on interactive fiction these days and
not a whole lot of work on 3D rendering because I can't even remember
the quadratic equation negative B plus or minus B squared minus 4AC
over 2A.
Okay?
So I can remember the called activation, I just can't be sure that I
remember the quadratic equation which is just as bad anyway.
So let's think about this for a second, this is going to be our
equation for T which is the file how far along the rail we went,
right?
And so what does that mean?
Like what what are we getting here?
What do we what are we?
What are we trying to say?
Well, if you look at this equation it has a plus, or minus in it and A
Plus or a minus means fundamentally speaking, we have two solutions,
we have negative B, minus this value.
Over 2A, we have negative B, plus this value over 2A.
So when we plug in these a,b,c into this equation, get the solutions.
We get two solutions out, why are we going to get two solutions out?
Well, the reason we get
Stitches out is if you look at what happens when we send a ray through
a circle or a sphere or any other kind of quadratic embedded in a
space, we get two intersections right, there's an intersection here
and intersection there.
So it stands to reason that we would get two equations out there.
Correspond to the near and far hits of that plane.
We want both and we need to look to see which one of them we get.
That makes more sense to us if our Ray origin is here and we hit this
one.
First we want to keep that solution.
Not this one because we don't want to process The Far Side hit of the
sphere, right?
so this is fundamentally what we're doing, and we're fundamentally
saying that Rd squared to our dr0 and
R0 squared, minus r squared.
We're fundamentally saying that this is what we want to compute.
I may have been slapped with the math there.
This may be wrong.
So we may have to more carefully go through the terms there in a
second to make sure I didn't mess them up, but that's the basic idea
of solving these equations.
That's how we would, that's what the steps I use.
The solvent are correct.
I just bad meticulous Mathai.
I would like a good computer algebra package someday but there aren't
any so.
Oh well.
So anyway what I want to do now is I want to actually compute that
value for T.
So what I need to do is I need to specify basically two different
values.
You know, I needed t0 and T1 or I could do a t+ team - for example and
then I need to compute like - p d plus the root term.
Over 2A.
And again, I also need similarly to to do the the corresponding -
version, right?
I know my root term is the square.
Root of B squared, minus 4AC.
So I've got B times B this for a times C.
And I knew my denominator is just equal to 2 .0, x.
Eh
Okay.
so, if we look at these,
If we look at these terms, what we can see is, there's two places we
can go wrong.
The first is, if the denominator is 0 again, right?
So, that's one way we would not intersect with the sphere.
The other way is if R square root becomes imaginary.
So if the square root becomes, you know, less than 0 less than 0,
right?
At looking at these values, what you can see is minus 4AC, right?
We know that the real origin squared cannot be negative, right.
There is no way.
For the origin squared to be negative and there's also no way.
For our to be negative since the radius.
So we know we're subtracting a value, a negative value away from a
positive value there, and we don't really know how they will compare.
So we don't know what the real Origins like compared to the radius.
We have no idea how far the, you know, those two things are so don't
really know what to say about.
See a is Ray Direction squared, that's always positive right for is
always positive.
So it's really see that would determine whether this is a positive or
negative value.
And
Don't know, which it will be B squared on the other hand is always
positive.
So all we really would need to know to know whether we're always going
to be a valid term.
Here is whether our D transpose AR 0 times 2 is always going to be
A more positive value when squared, then, whatever C could potentially
be in terms of a negative value, right?
And unfortunately, that's kind of a difficult thing to analyze to know
whether or not that can ever actually go.
You can see that it's a little bit tricky, right?
Like B squared, which is this value here,
Already transpose AR 0 could I mean that could even be 0, right?
So this term could be zero and so the question of whether or not ace
the squared a is the and the squared I'm sorry not squared a the
length of the direction Vector which we kind of actually know already
is one because we normalized it.
So to be honest we know that in all these cases a is 1.
I guess what I would say is we know that the so here's what, you know,
what we can we can prove this without actually have to do the map.
We know that the ray direction is never going to be anything other
than one when we're feeding it in, but we also know that we can miss
the sphere.
The reason we know we can miss the sphere is because, hey, if here's
the sphere and the thing is going this way, we won't hit it, right?
So, we know that this term must be able to become like an unsolvable
math value.
Right has to become imaginary at some point.
So what that tells us is you know this since this denominator can't be
the problem.
It's got to be here.
So what we know there is yeah instead of checking the denominator like
we're checking before, it's the root term that we need to check now
and we need to make sure that the root term is going to be over our
tolerance value, right?
For now.
Right.
Okay, so assuming our route,
Oops.
Assuming our route term is over our tolerance value, that's the thing
that would determine whether we can start testing.
This stuff is now no longer relevant to us.
And so we want to do here is now C.
We want the whichever one of these two is closer so what we want to do
is say basically our T value and what I probably should have done up
here.
Instead of this distance is to call this the T value because that's
what we're really talking about all the time.
Right.
So what I want to do here is say that let's assume that the T value is
equal to the teepee value.
Right now, what I'm going to do is then say if the T N value
Is.
Is greater than zero.
Right.
So it's in front of us.
And it is less than the teepee value, then it's a better hit.
Does that make sense?
So I only want hits in front of us.
And I want to see whether or not it's better than the teepee hit so
it's closer.
So I'm looking right?
And then what I'm going to do is just test T here.
The same way I was testing it before.
And so then the last step here is I have to fill in these terms.
So this is going to be the inner product of R&D with itself.
B is going to be too.
Times.
The inner product of the two of the right origin in the right
direction and C is going to be the inner product of the rate origin
with a self-, the radius.
Like so, so hey we got our sphere so we couldn't have been too wrong
but it's not the right place.
So we still have some problems, right?
We've got a we've got a bug here of some kind right now.
The first thing you'll notice is I have a problem with Origins that we
haven't discussed.
It should probably not have had any effect here, but the fact is we
have to correct for it anyway, if we want to get further down the
line.
So you'll notice what I did is when I said, what the Spheres equation
was where was that was right here, right?
You'll notice that.
Use P.
But really, this doesn't have the center of the sphere represented
anywhere.
So technically what these are is, they're always like px- sphere X,
right?
It's, it's got to be the position relative to the center of the
sphere, which we did not take into account, so we were just using it
as if the Seer was always at the origin.
The store is not at the origin.
So what that means is that that point equation that we have in there,
all of the things that we had before
Or where we were sort of saying P transpose P.
We actually need those to take into account that that subtraction,
right?
That's going to happen there.
So this Ray origin really whenever it's used needs to be more like
local origin, right?
Or sphere relative origin.
Right?
So the sphere relative rate origin is going to be the worry origin -
the sphere origin.
And then, just by substituting that in there.
We can use the same equations, right?
Because that's basically, like, before we were, we did all the
equations with a sphere centered at 0 0.
I need to move everything so that it's now relative to that sphere.
So again, like I said, that doesn't affect the image at all.
I just want to get that out of there first off, but the reason that
that shouldn't affect anything is because when we set up the world's,
where is that?
We left the sphere at 000.
Right.
So now we know there is some bug with the way that we're casting are
raised or the way that we're doing, our sphere intersection that is
called the our stuff to show up a little bit off center from where we
expect it to be and we need to figure out why that is.
Now, unfortunately we have a problem here which is that we don't
really know whether that's because of something in our camera code
that's wrong, which could be the case.
Or if there's something in our sphere intersection code, that's
Which could also be the case now, positively unwisely.
I am going to assume that it's in the camera setup code.
The reason I'm going to assume that first and look for that first is
because nothing in the sphere intersection code right now.
Screams x-axis to me, right?
So when I look at this, that looks more or less correct in Y and Z and
just not X and that to me suggests that there's something wrong with
my equations for X only and in order.
For something to be wrong with my equation.
For x.
Only X has to show up special somewhere.
It does not show up special here, it does.
Show up special down here.
Right.
So that's all I really have to go on and again I don't really know.
That's a shot in the dark.
It's just again something that I'm sort of like--.
Using to focus my attention first.
So, right off the bat, I see a typo, Right?
Image, .height, image.
Height is wrong.
It should be imaged with and that, that's the entirety of the problem,
okay?
So good getting closer.
So now this points out of thing that member, if you go all the way
back to beginning, when I said, like, we're just use a square for now.
But we need a rectangle eventually when I talked about that image
plane, now we need to address that that problem.
So now we have a problem which is that hey, we are casting a square.
We are shooting at are raised in a square pattern.
The imagery producing is not a square.
We could choose to make it a square, right?
Does, don't need to be there anymore.
We could choose to make it a square right by replacing this with 720.
Now, we've got a proper image, but we would like to be able to cast
any image size we want and account for that, right?
So in order to do that, what we need is an aspect ratio handling in
there.
So that when we cast a wider Dimension, we expand how far we're going
in that direction.
Now, I'm going to say that we always want to just do one point.
Oh,
As our basis and we could do it either way.
We could say that 1.0 is a maximum, or we could say that 1.0 is the
minimum and it doesn't really matter which one we do.
I'm going to say one point is the maximum just for the heck of it.
And so, what that means is, we need to look to see if one of our
Dimensions is higher than the other dimension, right?
We need to basically look and go.
All right, is the image with greater than the image height and also is
the image height greater than the image with
Right.
And what we need to do here is adjust the one, if the other is wrong.
So if our film with is greater than our height, they what we need to
do is we need to shrink our height down, okay?
So we need to take whatever our image height is.
We need to shrink that down.
Around here has got to be sure.
Oh wait.
No, no, no, sorry.
I don't need to do that.
Just, I don't need to set the.
That height can remain the same.
It's, it's just the film height that needs to change.
I need to shrink the film height down, so that's proportionally,
correct.
I need the height to be correct based on the image height.
So, what I need to do here is say, well, whatever the film width is
right.
I want the film with times a conversion that will convert it over to
the same.
Proportion.
So if I take the ratio of the image height, to the image with that
will tell me how to take a whip and produce a height from it.
So I'm going to keep
Film with constant and recreate the film height out of it, right?
And I can do the exact same process in reverse.
Here.
And again this is just dimensional analysis at its most basic I'm
basically saying.
Well alright, if I have a width
I'm going to multiply it by.
A height over with.
To get a height out the other side, the widths cancel, right?
So, again, I have a high time Computing, so I want to end up with
height.
So, I want width times height over with, to cancel the widths and get
a hideout.
Same at the opposite is true, in the other case, right?
So that's just shrinking that Dimension down.
So now you can see we're producing a proper image.
That's just got the aspect ratio of correct in there and presumably if
you wanted to.
We could now just set whatever we want here.
You know, if we want to do
1096 by 2048 for some reason.
I don't know why you want to do that but now we can run our Ray Tracer
and it'll take a lot longer because there's way more race but now we
have like just an image.
That's like much more.
Can I zoom in on this thing somehow?
Why isn't the mouse wheel work?
I'm just because this program is extremely slow.
I guess how do I zoom in?
Can you seriously not zoom in.
There we go.
So now you can see we just have a lot more resolution but we basically
did the exact same thing, so that's good.
So we're really resolution dependent there and that's good.
I want to see my Ray Kasten.
You know, that took a long time because this is a really an optimized
program and we're not in compiling an optimized mode, and that's a lot
of raycast to do in with some slow code.
What I'd like to do here is I'd like to go ahead and have a progress
update somehow.
So, what I'm going to do here is I'm going to go ahead and say while
we're out putting this here, I'm going to just output some status as
we go.
So I'm going to come through here and just do something like
So here's me just doing something that will just print out Ray casting
row, you can see that it kind of goes, it's not very good for use in a
non console window.
So maybe I shouldn't quite do that or have a mode that doesn't quite
do it that way, but if we were to run it from here, it would make a
lot more sense.
So here's the
Data directory.
If I go back to build a legacy you can see it sort of printing out
their nice.
Sort of status, what I'm also going to do.
Here is I'm just going to go ahead and make it so we don't do that
every time.
So I'll just do if y.
You know, mod.
Let's say every 64 lines.
Right, and now it'll just do like, you know, 01234, whatever kind of
thing.
Right here.
It would be really cool if someday for coder supported that optionally
because it could, it would be interesting if it did.
And the other thing we could do here is make this a percent if we
wanted to write.
So the thing I could do is say, well, let's divide by the image
height.
And now we should get like some nice percentage values in there as
they go, right?
And that's good.
So, that's nice.
And the other thing we can do is we can f flush here.
To make sure that we actually get those printouts happening as they
happen instead of, if they're in a buffered scenario, which they might
be on like a Linux, for example, would probably buffer those up,
right.
So, there's a nice little guy, a nice little Ray Tracer that rates
everything.
It produces images that look awful right now because we haven't really
done much to make them.
Look not awful but and it's very slow but you know it's it's a start
right?
So there's started to retrace.
So, now the question is well, all right, let's just
Let's do like something slightly more complicated here, just to get
things rolling.
A little bit better.
So let's try doing something that's a little bit more realistic.
Only the barest, barest amount, more realistic like we're talking like
tiny tiny, tiny bit of realistic.
So so so very very
Minor Improvement.
Just so we can see what a ray Tracer.
Should look like a little bit better on.
I'm going to basically create an arbitrary Skype value here.
Let's say .3, I'm going to take again that material for the plane.
I'm going to say is like you know 0.5 0.5 0.5 let's say and I'm going
to take the material to color here and say that that should be
I don't know.
Point 7f,
.5 f.
Point 3F, maybe something like that.
Now if we run this again what you'll see is we just get kind of
nothing particular, interesting.
We get like a gray plane and you know, maybe I'll give the be a little
bit of color to the incoming lighting.
There's a great plane like a it's like a sky you know, whatever.
Right?
So there we go.
We've got some material values there.
And what I'm going to do is just a very, very straightforward thing
where when I raycast here, what I'm going to do is say well whenever I
hit something, i-i'm going to maybe keep going, right?
Like maybe I'll just like continue casting through the world, right?
And furthermore, what I might do is say, well, I also am going to say
that we've got as R 0 value.
So are like our Min hip distance, I'm going to say that that's like
some small value as well, right?
So I'm going to go in here and say that like Min hit distance
And this is really janky right now, like I said we're not really you
know a lot of these things you don't want to do eventually once we
start talking about more sophisticated stuff will just make Min hit
distance here, just temporarily as something to work from.
Okay so what I'm going to do here is I'm going to say well what if I
just want to maybe like raycast
Repeatedly, right?
So here's our
are we down?
What I want to do here is I want to say like, all right, let's suppose
we're going to shoot multiple Rays when we actually shoot out a ray,
right?
So I'm going to do like a ray count equals 0.
Re count is less than I don't know.
Let's say, four.
Plus plus re account and 8 is probably a more sophisticated number,
but it doesn't really matter.
So let's say I'm going to cast a trays and what I'm going to do is
every time I get a hit, I'm actually going to change that the idea
about where the origin is and about where the ray direction, is that
I'm coming from, right?
So I'm going to have a thing called Next origin.
Next Direction.
Like so.
And I'm going to have a thing which specifies, whether or not I
actually ever did hit anything, right?
So this is just a, like, hit something.
So, I'm just going to say hit something people's true.
Like, so, and I'm going to have some idea of a color value in here as
well.
Right?
So I want to know, like what color I hit.
there's they don't really need to clear these, but
And honestly, you know what, I could probably do is just like hit
material.
So this way, I'll know what material I hit.
Maybe I'll call that hit Matt index.
And what I could really do is just use that.
Instead, so all instead of having a Boolean which I don't really need,
I'll just set hit Matt index equal to 0.
I know that 0 is a non thing, right?
And I'll do my hit Mac index and then what I can do at the end of
this, as I can say, if hit Matt index, I know I hit something
otherwise, I am done, right?
So great, you know, break out of the loop, we don't have anything.
More to do here, right?
And so, what I'm going to end up here is I'm going to end up with
essentially a
Sort of a stack if you will of materiel operations as I March through
the world, and we're going to have to probably keep track of some of
these things here in, in a, in some kind of reasonable way, but we'll
get to that in a second.
So as I come through here, if I hit him, if I hit a material index and
I have the next origin X Direction thing.
What I need to know here is, I need to know where I would cast from
next.
Fi when I hit something.
So I need to know the point that I hid in the world and I also need to
know the Direction I Would cast off in.
So I need to know like the surface normal at that point for example.
And so maybe what I'll call that instead of next direction is next to
normal because really it's not the next Direction necessarily, right.
Okay.
So what I want to do now is say alright I've got a next origin and
next door Mille.
So in this case, if I'm Ray casting a plane.
I know that the next origin is just the point on the plane that I
ended up at.
So it's just and this is the same in both cases, whatever the
redirection is, I know that I just go whatever the t-value I find.
I just go that far in there I am but the next normal is, you know, not
Related to that, it's just whatever the plane normal is, right.
Because that's, that's the, the normal to the surface is whatever that
plane normal is.
So if I come down here for hit distance, it Matt index.
Again, same thing here, I've got to compute these two.
My next origin is the same, right, but my next newer mole is not the
same.
My next normal is going to be based on the sphere and in order to
figure out what this the sphere normal is.
I really just have to look
look to see what the direction is to, from the center of the sphere to
that origin, right?
Because the normal at the point on a sphere, you know, whatever the
serious.
If I know that this is where I hid.
The normal is always just from the center out to that point, right?
That's always going to be tangent at that point.
So, the next animal is just going to be whatever the sphere origin is.
- what of that next version is.
So if I hit something, I can choose to continue casting, and what I
can do to continue casting is I can just say, well next origin.
That'll be my real origin for the next cast.
Ray direction will be the real origin and off we go.
So that will just let me keep casting.
I can like bounce all through the scene.
Right.
And so now, all I need to do is have some way of recording all that
information that I got there.
And and once I have that information doing the light propagation that
I need to do in order to produce.
Yeah.
Like the the
What should I say?
I need to have a way to take that light path and produce what I think,
the lighting should be along that path based on how the light has been
provided, right?
So we have a problem here, which we which we really need to resolve
and we can, I think resolve this fairly straightforward actually at
the moment, what I'm going to do is when we set this color here where
we have the mat Index, right?
so, what we want to do here is when we find the Hitman index,
And we do our bounces.
If I reset this temporarily to just do a single Ray, count cast.
Then that means whatever we hit for the material index.
That could be our result color, if that makes sense.
So I'm just going to do that really quickly.
Just for a second here, I'm going to do World, materials, hit that
index, and I'm going to make the result color, be equal to that color,
right?
So it doesn't really it guess it's not smart enough to realize.
We'll do this for now, but it's not smart.
Realize that doesn't need to do that.
So there's our program, the thing I was going to say is what I want to
do here is I need to expand our material now because I want to do
something a little bit more realistic.
I want to expand our material to have some concept of whether it emits
light, or reflects light, right?
So, I want like an admit color, and I want a reflection color, right?
So this is like, how much?
Light it reflects.
This is how much light it emits, right?
And again, I'm not actually doing anything physically.
Corrector I'm not trying to do anything along those lines yet.
I'm just doing the basics for what to make this work at all right?
Okay.
So, in order to set an admit color, for each of these things and all
that stuff, I need to kind of make this a little bit more, I need to
admit color, reflect color, I don't want the well actually don't need
to set the reflect color for that one.
And I don't need something to mix colors for these.
So it's going to be more like this.
I want the sky to admit that color.
I want the other two to reflect these colors but not omit anything.
And so now I have like an admit color and a reflect color, right?
So, what I need to do is I then need to use those colors in some way
that actually makes some sense, right?
So when I cast my re out, I then have a path that I can use to
propagate light if actively through along the path, right?
I have some number of bounces.
So if, for example, I put this back up to eight.
I'm going to bounce this rate eight times when I don't hit a material
index at all.
So if I don't hit a material index here, then
I actually need to do is produce the final color at that point, right?
Because I know that I would have the that zero color incoming at that
point and I need to do something there, right?
Okay, so let's figure out how we would actually go about doing this.
We basically need our result to be an accumulator at this point.
So we don't want to initialize it to this color anymore.
What we want to do is set our result color up to be nothing, right to
be black.
Okay,
Now, what we want to do from there is say, well as we go through our
raise, we have some degree to which these colors, get Dominion sized,
right?
How they how the reflectance kind of goes.
Now, what we would want to do ideally and what we probably switch to
doing later.
When we want to be more fancy about this is we've got our Ray path
here, right?
And our Ray path is like the cameras, here, it hits a surface.
It bounces off cast somewhere.
Some of the surface that bounces off and off we go, right?
Now, the problem with this is, if you look at what happens here, we're
casting the raised in this order.
This is re 0.
This is very one.
This is Ray to or
If this is our thing that we hit our emitter like we hit the sky here
and this is like emitting light, right?
Then what we really want to do is take this emission value multiply it
by the coefficient of reflectance here.
Multiply it by the coefficient of reflectance here and so on, right?
But we're going in the reverse order.
So we need to do is save up, what we would have X as we go so that
when we get to an emitter we can actually track that, right?
So we effectively have an attenuation value here and that attenuation
value starts off at one because we have not attenuated the light at
all.
So when we initially cast The Ray, there's no light absorption at all.
We're going to see whatever we hit right there.
and if we hit a material,
Right?
When we hit a material, we need to do two things.
First of all, we need to see what that materials admittance is, right?
So I want to do is find my Mac here.
Find what my Matt actually is.
Let's do it like this and I'll just say World materials hit Matt
index.
So, what is the material?
I hit.
This is the material I hit.
And then what I want to do is say alright that material it has an
emission color and a reflectance color.
I want to take the reflectance color of this material and multiply my
attenuation by it, right?
So I basically want to like keep a running attenuation of how much the
light is an attenuated as I step out across the re.
Right?
So starts out at one no attenuation make a hit.
How much will that?
Attenuate it this much right?
And off I go.
We're going to have a cosine term in here but we'll talk about that in
a second.
So I'm going to not I'm not but the coast interning at open this would
be a to do not but we'll get that second.
Then the other thing I want to do is whatever the this if this service
is itself, an amateur, if this service provides light, then what I
want to do is I want to propagate that light back to the camera by
taking however much all the attenuation has been so far not including
this one so I'm gonna do it before I do the update of the
Attenuation.
And I want to take the emissions color of this surface and do the
hadamard between those to find out how much of this light will
propagate back to the camera.
And I'm going to add that into the result.
So that gives me for any emission that I find at the place.
I just hit whatever attenuation all along the race so far.
I got to put that in there, right?
Then I can go on to do my, you know, more and more and more, right?
And the same thing that happens here for hit.
Matt, next, this is going to have to happen.
For the final one as well.
Like so meaning, if we don't hit anything, we'd want to propagate back
the emission color of
The null material right?
When we're done okay and that's what we want to do.
That's the color value that we would produce on this re right coming
backwards.
I don't know why that got typed in there.
But so for the, when we go to cast the secondary Ray, we have the
normal right now, but that's not very useful to us.
If you think about it, the normal is not a particularly useful value
because that is not a direction to cast a ray in.
So we need to talk about that.
So we need to do a reflection here.
And there we go.
Okay, so let's go ahead and run this and we're going to get some
results.
We don't really want, but what do you do?
So here is our the result of our scene and so far.
Actually this isn't too bad right.
It kind of looks like it should look, we have a sky which is as bright
as it is right, we have a ground plane which is reflecting the sky and
to a certain extent, a level and we have a plane sphere which is
Acting the sky again.
Attenuated a certain level, right?
And that's not bad.
Actually that's that's starting to be pretty reasonable at some level,
right?
That's like okay, we're starting to bounce some light around.
Okay, what that's good.
But again now we have this problem of well.
Alright, so we're doing multiple bouts of our light so we hit
something we go.
When we found this guy, if you think that's what actually happened.
We, when we hit this plane, we bounced up and we found the sky, right?
Which is what we wanted to do.
So we're getting there.
Were getting sort of closer to a ray Tracer is actually producing
something useful, but we're not quite there yet.
We don't affection of a cosine and
Don't have one more thing we need, which is more than one re per
pixel, right?
And we'll talk about that now as we wrap this up.
So we're almost done actually with a reasonable rate racer, that just
doesn't have any physical light transport our materials, but that
actually sort of works, right?
This is why Racers are always such a good thing to write because they
produce interesting looking images that you can be kind of happy that
you got, but they don't take very long to write, right?
You can
Like I just, I didn't have that much stuff to write to actually make
them work, so that's why they're kind of a nice rewarding thing to do.
All right, so what we need to do now is we need to sort of extend this
little bit by, by making this reflectance, take some things into
account that we actually would care about, right?
Okay, so let's take, let's let's think about this for a second and and
give ourselves a little bit of a reflective function here.
And it's not going to be good for Flex Flex, not going to be
physically accurate.
We're not trying to do anything fancy here at all.
I just want to get a little bit more of a ray Tracer done.
So we can call it a day and say we were done, right?
okay, so let's suppose that with I
Surface, so here's the camera.
I'm looking at a surface.
I cast some Ray and I hit the surface, right.
I know the normal to the surface.
So what I could do is say, well, if this is a perfectly stuck as a
mirror, I know which way I would bounce out.
Right.
So perfectly specular surface bounces out in exactly the direction.
It came in right at comes in this direction at bounces out perfectly.
So if I'm at a glancing angle, it's a glancing angle and basically,
you know, the angle to the plane of the thing coming in is the same as
the angle going out, right?
That's a reflection and we know what it is.
However, when I'm looking for light sources, what I'm effectively
doing is I'm saying, well, I need to know what the in what the
lighting is for this surface, from all the light coming in that
bounces out in the direction of the camera and we've had multiple
streams on lighting a hammer here, go watch one of them if you don't
know how lighting Works, watch one of them.
So we could have two different kinds of services.
One is a very reflective surface that reflects light directly like a
mirror,
But then, we could go all the way to a service that was very diffused,
like chalky, that just takes all the incoming light and reflects it
evenly.
And so, what I need is, I need a value that tells me how I want to do
that, and if it's one of those chalky substance has, I want to look
randomly out in all directions of the hemisphere?
If it's one of those highly reflective surfaces I want to look very
carefully in One Direction, right?
And there's different ways we can do that but what I'm gonna do right
now is a very biased technique because, again, we haven't gotten the
point.
We're going to talk about like sampling and physical reflective
functions.
That's our thing.
So do a very biased technique and the bias technique is just I'm going
to take random points in the hemisphere shooting in the hemisphere,
and I'm going to collapse them down to the reflectance, the pure
reflection Vector based solely on a single parameter, right?
So this is not physically accurate.
Wait.
It's just going to give us an approximation.
We can use and then the next time we revisit our Ray Tracer, maybe the
thing that we'll do is we'll try to increase the quality of this
Legend transport, and that's when we would start to get into those
sorts of things.
So we're just going to call the specular right now.
Zero is pure.
Defuse one is pure speculation.
Right.
I'm talking mirror.
The team's they often use but chops and mirrors are not purely,
secular diffuse, they're just closer.
So it gives you some intuition
All right, so what I want to do here is say, alright, if I'm going to
reflect this Vector, I need two Reflections function.
I need to reflect it around the normal and we know how to do this,
right?
Folks.
We know how to do this.
We discussed this on handmade hero.
If we have a normal,
And we have a vector that's in coming.
So remember we had a re Direction, it was looking like this so the re
directions pointing that way, right?
So if we have a retrograde Direction pointing that way and we want the
raid to come out along that reflection, what do we need to do?
We did dot product it with the normal, right?
That's going to give us a negative in this direction and we need to,
then subtract that twice to bump this back up to this, right?
Very simple equation.
So what we have is we have our Ray Direction,
And we're just going to add that inner product of the ray Direction.
With the normal, we're going to add two of those in, right?
So we start with that redirection, we're pointing down this way.
Right now, we're going to add two of those, right?
And we're going to add them in the direction of the normal itself.
Again, taking an incoming Vector, we want to reflect it back up around
the plane, right?
So, whatever this direction is, that's pointing here, that's our
normal.
We want to go ahead and make sure that we take however, distance this
was here alone, that normal, and move it up twice to produce that
reflection.
So now we have comes in, comes out, so there's our a Direction, that's
reflected.
And well, I like I said, I wanted to have a coefficient here.
So what I want to do is I want to produce a V3, that's like a bounce,
like a pure bounce.
And then, what I want to do is I want to produce a random bounce which
would be, you know, not taking into account the incoming Direction,
just randomly bounces.
And I want to blend these two things together.
So then I want my Ray direction to be equal to my pure bounce, and my
random bounce.
I want to lurk between those two.
So I want to go from random bounce.
If the value is 0 for the materials specular,
I should say let's call this scatter because it's not a real value.
Let's go this cat.
So I want to take that scatter value and I want to alert between the
random and a pure bounce based on how much scattering there is right.
And what I'm going to do is to produce the random bouts here, I need
to just figure out something that's in that hemisphere right?
So what I'm going to do is I'm going to take that next normal.
Right.
And that is
That is the thing that's pointing upwards like this.
I know that if I take the next normal and I just add like a random set
of values to it, right?
I should be able to get something randomly permuted, and again,
Random bounce vectors are actually really hard to do, right?
Because
Evenly distributed points over a hemisphere that correspond to a
sampling pattern and are not biased.
And that and are produced quickly can actually be fairly challenging.
You'd be surprised.
There's a lot of people who've done various attempts to do that,
right?
And there's, you know, better and better ones, but it was not an
obvious thing, right?
It wasn't like one of those things computer graphs are just like, oh,
and then we just do this and it works and it's perfect.
It's so
This is something we would have to come back to later because we're
not gonna do some particular good right now.
So, to take that next normal, I'm just going to add a random bilateral
Vector to it and then normalize it.
So I'm just going to say normalize
Random bilateral Vector.
So that's just, you know again a vector we're going to need a random
series here.
And what we can do for right now is we have a we can just use R and
the C runtime Library function, it's awful.
So we'll want to put in a better random number generator at some point
as well, but right now, I just have a thing where I can say random
bilateral.
This is just a number between 0 and 1.
So do random bilateral three times and normalize that.
So here's our internal.
If we were to and of the lateral your to unilateral
And what these are going to do is just produce, random numbers will
use the C runtime libraries function.
Again it's awful.
So we will have to replace it.
This is nothing to do with the fact that we because remember this
program, we're using the steamer trunks, not like a maid here.
We try to avoid the C runtime Library.
I'm not trying to buy this here on time.
It just ran just he's awful.
So we will need to replace it in the future.
I so want me to do here is I'm going to say, all right, let's go ahead
and produce a result here.
That result is going to be the Rand function, mod or sorry, / Random
Acts.
Which is the maximum value can produce.
So this should give us a number between zero and one anytime we want
it, that's random.
And then for the bilateral version of that I can just produce a result
that is two times random unilateral
Minus one.
Right, and so now we have a way of randomly bouncing our stuff off.
It shouldn't again produce any different results because it should
still, hopefully most of the time, find the sky or whatever else it
needs to do, right?
And so we should be pretty good to go at this point.
So yeah, I mean, like I said, hopefully that's not working properly.
That's the new Ray.
And and yeah, like presumably I could I don't know if it ever really
shit down too much.
But yeah, anyway, so we should be using in a bunch of cases.
Pretty random reflection vectors here.
Random bounce.
Matt scatter, pure bounce.
Actually that's so.
You know what the normalized needs?
We need to normalize here as well.
We don't really need to normalize our Ray directions, but I'm doing it
anyway.
Okay, so I believe this is working.
Why do I believe it's working?
Well, I believe it's working because if you actually are working as a
the wrong term, I believe this might be working.
The reason I say that is because if we zoom in here what you can see
is that various places have black dots where they did not find it, Ray
intersection with anything, right?
And that would correspond to if it hit the sphere.
Now,
Reason, I don't quite think it's working is because we should have
seen some potential places where we hit the sphere and all things
should be black dots on the sphere as well.
And the fact that there's not is troubling to me.
So, I think we're not quite right yet.
We probably have to take a look at this and debug it a little bit.
So we just make sure I know what's going on here.
The pure about should be the ray direction that we cast.
It should be the inner product with the normal, obviously.
And that's that's yeah.
That's what we want, x ray Direction and
X.
Whatever that next thermal is that should correct us to putting out.
If I take this out and just do ray Direction, equals pure bounce.
I should get no black dots.
For the most part, right?
Although I should in theory, pure bounces right here, should hit the
sphere.
Right.
So, that does seem a little wrong because these should not be hitting
these should hit the sky.
So we still have a little bit more to do here.
So let's stick with pure bounce, temporarily
And and figure out what's going on wrong with that.
So let me just walk through what I did here.
When we hit the plane, we're going to set the normal to the plane and
that seems about, right?
And we're going to set the origin equal to ah there's our problem.
So we didn't start at the re origin when we walk to our new origin.
That's that's yeah, that's just wrong.
There we go.
So we're getting a little better here.
How do I zoom?
Why doesn't the mouse wheel work?
It's really weird.
The mouse wheel doesn't like work in this app but I don't know why.
So again not quite right because this is not exactly what I would have
expected to have happen, right?
This still doesn't look quite right to me.
I should be seeing some discoloration here, where the pure bounce
would have hit the sphere and I don't know why I'm getting these
little artifacts in here.
So again, still buggy, right still, not quite right.
Next normal, in either case, looks pretty good.
And when I do my hit Max index, I'm accumulating the attenuation thus
far along the ray times, the emission color coming from here seems
about right?
The attenuation is going to increase by however much the reflection is
happening here.
It's going to attenuate further.
I'm going to step to wherever the next origin.
Is we really could just keep the hit the best distance.
Like I could just say, let's let's forget the next origin thing for
now, just to simplify things and just say,
It's just the hit distance.
Right?
So we're just going to move along that right direction, right?
And then the redirection again is just going to be whatever the rate
of reaction was and it's oh there's the bug.
I said I subtract those values and I didn't subtract them.
Okay.
So they're so now I think we've got that to bugged or hopefully and
we'll see though that doesn't so we still we must still have a general
bug in here because that should have changed like the fact that pure
bounce being incorrect.
Here didn't make any difference in the image is not correct, right?
Ooh.
Didn't mean to leave that open so we have next origin.
Undeclared identifier, there we go.
It didn't actually compile.
So, this guy actually does have to compute that.
Hmm.
So is there an easier way to compute this?
Yeah, there probably is.
Actually that information that we need probably came in here so we
have sphere relative re origin.
So we know that we're really just saying
Well now, all right.
I'm not going to try and overcomplicate this but we've already done
the work here.
I believe to actually get what we want out of this so we could prep.
We I think we can reuse this information to get the normal out really
quickly.
So that's a separate issue.
But anyway, so we'll do this here.
So T times J Direction plus 3 Origin - sphere P, right?
What you can see here is this is just going to be the relative origin.
So this is going to be zero relative, radio origin.
I believe, because if you look at what this is, this is the new hip
point, right?
Is there a origin plus the redirection times T?
We're going to - the sphere P but Ray origin - fear p is already
computed as fear relative re origin.
Like so, so I believe that's the correct way to do that.
Okay.
All right, so let's take a look.
Here me.
Zoom in.
So, what we're seeing here is kind of a little bit odd.
We can see the bottom of the sphere, now, as the plane cuts it as if
the plane itself is transparent.
Now what that implies to me is that our Ray direction for some reason,
is not getting flipped properly because we're looking, we're
continuing down through the plane, which we shouldn't do.
We should be bouncing back up, but I don't actually know why we're
getting that artifact.
How we're actually
Lee doing that, right?
So the re Direction times the next normal should be a negative value.
And so, when we subtract it out, we should like that subtraction
should, you know, should work?
And I could normalize that just for good measure but that's not the
problem.
Something else weird is going on there, right?
But you can see what I mean.
We're getting, we're basically doing a hit and then punching through
to get to the next one as if we didn't change what the ray Direction.
Actually was right.
And I'm not sure why we're having that Oddity occur.
Something weird is happening there and I don't know what Inlet well
actually.
You know what?
Maybe that's just correct.
Maybe that's just the reflection of the sphere.
In the plane.
Right.
It could be.
So maybe I shouldn't call that a bug, just yet.
Because I don't actually know if it is, that could actually be
correct, shockingly enough.
All right, so we have a little more work to do.
Your let's let's push forward a little bit and I'm going to call it a
day pretty soon because this has been plenty of programming for a test
stream.
Here we go.
I'm going to put that random bounce back in here, right?
Okay, and this is actually looking good.
I know this is that's going to come as a shock because this doesn't
look good.
But is actually looking good, right?
But you can see is we've got some random noise in there now and it
looks like it's getting darker as it kind of gets to places that
should actually be darker because they'll hit each other and so on.
So I'm actually thinking that's pretty encouraging probably.
There's still some bugs in here but what I want to do now is the last
step of the process.
I just want to go in here and say, all right, let's take our
our casting and let's just do more than one sample per pixel.
So right now what we're doing is we're taking a color and we're just
doing one cast.
What I want to do here is I want to do a bunch of raycast, right?
I want to do a re-index equals 0 R and X is less than raise per pixel
re-index plus, right?
And I don't really want to do this exactly what I'm showing you here.
I want to do it a slightly different way later but you know at the
moment we're going to do it this way.
So what I want to do here is to find a raise for Pixel and let's just
say we cast, you know, 16 raise for Pixel, and I'm just going to go
through and I'm going to say, however many raise for Pixel, we have
How to make a contribution value, which is 1 over the Rays for Pixel,
right?
And there's some stuff we want to do here.
This is not the right way to sample this, but we're going to do what's
he say stuff later.
But we're going to take a 1 over the race for Pixel value now.
We're just going to say that that's the contribution.
So we're going to take the color as a sum of a series of Ray, casts
through the world, right?
And what this is going to do is going to make it take a lot longer for
us to do our image.
You can kind of see it's taking a long time now to do and we can speed
this up dramatically by compiling and release mode which I'll do in a
second here.
Now that we're not really stepping through it at the moment.
But this will basically just do a lot of recasting.
And then what you can do is you can see that when we take our average
there we start to get a better image, right?
This is starting to look more like a real Ray casted image, and, and
the like, there's a bunch of stuff we haven't done yet that we should
do, we don't have the cosine term in here, which we need to have in
order to get the attenuation properly accounted for
Or and I'm not going to be too specific about it here.
other than to say that because of the sort of angular
Happens due to raise, we've talked about this before, handmade here is
lighting stuff.
The aperture size here, right is different than the aperture size
here.
So, as the red gets more angled, it attenuates more based on the
cosine of the angle.
What we want to do here is say we've got an attenuation amount that
attenuation amount is going to be the reflectance color attenuated by,
right that redirection next normal cosine function.
So basically,
Lee, when the ray Direction, the next normal are directly in line with
each other.
And again, the redirection has to be kind of flipped so that they're
looking upwards.
I want this.
Cosine attenuation to come in here like so.
And if the cosine attenuation is less than 0.
I want the cosine tation to be 0, right?
And then I'm going to attenuate that reflectance in there.
Oh, you know what?
Please stop.
I want to I want to have a more sped-up version than that, please.
So I'm going to go to the build up at
There we go.
And so, here's our raycast.
And now we've got well actually that
Seems a bit harsh.
Let's take a look at that term when we're time.
so, the cosine attenuation is the inner product of the ray Direction
and the next normal
I feel like that's correct, though.
Maybe I shouldn't get into this yet because we have so many other
terms that could be wrong here.
Yeah, I do.
I probably shouldn't be throwing in one physically accurate thing
without the rest of them, because then you're going to end up in a
situation where, you know,
Get results.
You definitely don't want.
But I suppose that's a different story.
Let me kind of get that again.
Oops.
I mean it does look sort of correct.
To be honest.
I just don't, I feels a little too steep for me, and so I feel like
it's probably because of the materials, not being that way.
So I might kill this for now.
And we'll deal with that on another stream when we actually have some
time to look at the rest of them.
Alright, so now we have a, you know, sort of semi, you know, a pseudo
Ray Tracer.
Let's just try putting in a couple other things here.
Just really quickly, right?
So what I want to do now is I want to say, all right, I'm going to add
another sphere.
So I'm going to say that I've got two spheres.
And I'm going to put the other sphere like I don't know, off to the
side.
Right?
And maybe I'm going to I'll move it like
Closer, a little closer to us as well.
Like so and then maybe I'll put another sphere up in the air
somewhere.
And, you know, we should use a rake out for this.
Like so, where we just compute the size of the array, based on what we
defined it as.
So, that way I can just say, like, hey playing count is the array kind
of planes.
It's your account is already kind of spheres material, count array
count of materials.
And then, that way, when we're in here, right?
I can just go like, okay, you know, we've got this many planes.
This miniseries whatever and it's like no big deal.
Okay, so what I want to do is I'm going to set these to some different
materials here.
I'm just going to make some more materials for us.
And so, what I'm going to do is going to make one of these like, you
know, a sort of a cherry red sphere.
And I make one of these like,
A sort of mirrored, green ball or something.
And so what I'm going to do is these materials now have you know this
extra parameter here, that's called scatter.
And what I'm going to do is I'm going to take that scatter scatter was
a it's like non scatter, right?
Like it's really non-standard.
But anyway, I want to make
It's one that's in, that's oops.
So, here we go.
What you can see now is our green ball, right?
That's up there is, I mean, this is like I said, this is the really
cool part about Racers is that, you know, you've seen, I've done
almost nothing, right?
It was like a few hours of programming.
I wrote everything more or less from scratch, right?
I've bit my up writer, the braised stuff, whatever.
We copied some stuff from the from the math library is about all.
We did.
But you know, how long it would have those few things have taken a
written, so it's very little code in there.
You already get something that does some kind of interesting stuff.
Like here is a reflection thing and whatever you know and and you can
even see it's not reflecting this because it doesn't reflect red light
very much, right?
And so since this knocks out all green light, it shows up black in
here just, you know, it's just interesting, right?
And furthermore, we can do kind of testing stuff like we can even even
with just such a dumb program that doesn't have any like we're not
really doing anything physically correct.
Yet.
We can even go in there and just say, oh, you know what?
Let's make it only partially reflective, right?
Which is kind of wild but we can do that, right?
We can have a sort of more complicated material and you see
This gets kind of fuzzy.
Right.
So that's pretty cool.
And so, the only other thing that I'd like to do here is right now,
we're running out these colors.
We're not handling the srgb translation, and it would be nice to be
able to do that.
So, what I would like is I'd like to be able to do a linear one to
srgb 555, just by taking like a square root in here or whatever, just
a quick,
One of these guys that can do the, the srgb translation.
so that when we go to pack this color,
instead of maybe doing it this way, I'm going to actually use the
linear 1s or to be 255, so that it'll actually encode it a little more
correctly here.
So let me actually do it this way.
So in here, I'm just going to do a V4 of the color.
And 55.
So this we will gamma correct just to make sure image is right and you
can see that's a lot different looking when you gamma correct it.
So when you go from linear light it's just going to be very dim and
wrong.
If you don't gamma correct now, that's not the correct gamma.
Nice to have the real gamma function in here and so I don't know, like
srgb function.
What is the actual srgb equation?
Actually want it in this quite a detailed terms.
I just want to know what the actual
Value is here.
I don't want this transformation.
I just want the
This is all I really wanted.
So, here's srgb to linear.
We want the opposite.
So we want this, right?
This is the equation.
I actually was looking for and so, I just want this because I want
something a little bit better.
That's some crazy aunts.
They're all right.
So 0.003, 1308.
And 12.9 too.
So we have a conditional here so we you know let me let me make
something that transfers a single component.
So let me let me make something here which can do
linear to srgb.
This will be exact.
This is the SS RGB value.
Here's the linear.
Oops.
No.
So this is the linear value.
I'm gonna produce the S value.
and so, what I have to do here is I have to say, okay, if the incoming
linear value
is less than or equal to
this magic constant.
Right.
Then I need to set it.
Two s equals L times 12 .92.
And otherwise.
I just do this power operation here.
So I do 1.0 I5 f
times the power L 2, 1 point 0, f /, 2.4 f.
Right.
-
5f.
Like so, so that's the equation.
We're going to use there.
And I'd also like to clamp this, so I'd like to do something where
it's like, okay, if L is less than 0 L equals 0.
If L is greater than 1.0 l equals 1, point 0 and then we produce RS
value.
Right.
And maybe I'll write this like this.
There we go.
So, there's our exact linear.
To srgb.
And so, then when I can do, is say, alright, our bitmap color value.
Is going to be exact linear to srgb.
I of each of the input color values, are G.
Be
Oops, we got a bugbear.
Missing semicolon.
Confusion 2oo, sorry, power.
Let's just put that in here with a square root.
So off we go with our recasting this in theory.
Should be the correct srgb image.
We have done zero testing at this point.
So we really just don't know if it is or isn't and you know.
So I don't pretend that that's correct.
We could have lots of bugs in here but it's a good first start.
And the next step would be to go through and start verifying color
transport and putting in real color transport equations, verify that
are
Srgb is right and that bitmap is correctly.
Encoding it.
I don't know if we have to set flags that bitmap to tell it.
That's srgb properly blah blah blah blah blah blah but we're
relatively good there.
As far as you know, as things go.
Let me also add some other spheres here.
Let's go and add a sphere with material index for here.
I wonder if I should just bake the materials directly into the things.
I probably should have, I don't know.
I do that indirect reference, it's just going to make things slower.
It's just kind of dumb.
They probably should just include the material in them.
I'm saying to you.
so this will be a more reflective when it's well, we'll put this one
at like,
So there we go, right?
Like
That's that's the basics.
Now like I said we're missing our cosine attenuation term in here, so
things don't look right at even not even really close to correct and
and because we don't have like a real reflectance function, either on
their there's problems with that.
So we have a lot of issues with respect to that reflection.
and,
Yeah, and so this is really the next thing that would have to get done
properly.
Where the cosine attenuation is actually in there, it might be better
now that we're in linear light space properly, but it's still just
looks overbearing to me.
Like, I've messed something else up but I'm just not sure.
What exactly that was that?
I messed up, right?
But it does look messed up for lack of a better term.
It, the fall-off is too harsh and I'm not sure exactly what it is.
So when we go through here and actually, like are careful about what
we're doing in terms of how the razor attenuated and how we actually
perform the reflection and scattering and all those other.
It's a good things that we'll probably isolate why we're getting that,
you know what looks like a to Harsha and attenuation coming off there.
I also don't really know.
What did I set the light too?
yeah, so that light
what?
Let's try one of the thing.
I'm going to pick one of our spheres here.
The red sphere.
I'm going to actually make that in a minute color.
Plus we can have a light caster.
and just so we can see if that's working properly and, you know, it
doesn't
Look like it to me.
Probably because I think in Mission at that scale, probably because
we're again, we're not really.
Physically accurate in here.
Emitters need to be much brighter than diffusers.
And so now you can see that that light is actually starting to get to
provide some, some actual value here, right?
There you go.
So at least the emission is working properly.
It just
You know, because nothing is a physically accurate value at this
point, it's a little iffy.
So let's wrap up again.
We have a ton of work to do here.
What's up?
Put a note of the top so people know.
So anyway in the ray Tracer here you know, off we go.
The only thing that I figure we should throw in just at the last
minute.
Is this Ray origin?
Ray Direction stuff.
I'm going to compute it every time.
Like this and you might be like, well, why are you do that, right?
Because, you know, if I run it now, it's just I'm just recalculating
the same value multiple times for no reason.
And the reason is because, well, it took, if we were to actually do
some sub-pixel sampling in there, we could get anti-aliasing for free,
right?
I mean, if you look at it right now, we're casting these Ray's out.
Oops.
Didn't mean to do that.
Here we go.
So if you look at it right now, we're casting all these Ray's out.
And so that gives us a better like these colors get smoother.
As we increase the sampling rate there but all of these don't improve,
right?
So the colors we get less noise in here, they're still noise, but it's
less than it was, right?
As we increase the ray count but we don't get any better
anti-aliasing, but what we can do is just Jitter are starting.
Samples.
And then we would get that Ray tracing that that extra amount, right?
So if I were to take, for example, this right here,
And just Jitter it by half a pixel in either direction for X and Y.
We
Some rate, we get some anti aliasing for free.
I mean, it's not free but it's like, you know, it puts it all in the
same pipeline, right?
So if your I'd just go like, okay, let's let's take our
Let's take our values here and say, well, okay.
I want my film X to be a, I'm sorry.
I want my office to be a land random bilateral?
Right offset.
From where it would be.
But then I don't want it to quite be a full 0 to 1 negative 1 to 1,
because that would be way too much red.
I want to be a pixel in size so I want to multiply it by 1 pixel like
picks something like this.
So we can just say, okay one pixel is going to be 1.0 over the image
height, right?
And with like so and I want these to be again half.
So what I'm going to do is actually do it like that, right?
So if I move a half pixel in either Direction, as a scattering
function around, I can then like, basically get some anti-aliasing
there, for free, and free is probably the wrong word to use here, but
looped in with everything.
And so now, if I zoom in there, what you can see is, it's getting a
little smoother, right?
It's still not great, but it's getting smoother.
It's no more noisy than anything else.
Is probably at this point.
Let's go.
Zoom.
But you can kind of see, right?
You can see getting some of that taking a little bit of the edge off
and so if I increase the raise for Pixel to, it will take longer,
right?
But if I want to produce a better image like a, no, he's just cast
more raised and trade essentially time.
For for image quality, which is a nice, right?
A nice aspect of rate racers,
So here's a higher quality image and what you can see now is if I zoom
in there, right?
It's starting to get relatively smooth and a lot of places but you
still get a lot of noise because hey, we're not doing anything smart
on sampling right now.
And just in general rate, Racers tend to need a lot of samples to
converge on anything, right?
So maybe we want to do even more than that.
And if we wanted to do more than that, then the problem we have that
we run into almost immediately is that we first of all, we can Cindy
this so we can be wide, which is great and we can cast like 8 or 16
raised at a time.
Probably only eight on this because it's, I,
As avx-512.
But the real problem we run into is if we're a c runtime Library
function.
If we just use the basic C, runtime Library, don't have threads and we
really want threads because we want to run this 8 wide 8 threads of
time.
So we want to locate wide and 8 threads, but we don't have the ability
to do that.
So, you know, we probably have to introduce a little bit of Windows in
here just so we can get more threads.
What I'm going to go take some questions before we end, but before we
do that,
I'm just gonna start this running so that as I take questions, if we
have any questions where's my little
Switcher thing.
There it is.
The ray Tracer can be tracing as we go.
Alright, Madam 87 is this series for total beginners in game
programming?
Yeah, it's for total beginners in game programming.
But not total beginners in programming.
It assumes, you kind of know how see Works sort of.
So if you start a beginning of series, it will assume some knowledge
of see, it won't assume any knowledge of game programming.
Can you girls?
Ask is it possible or how hard is it to have a debug system built into
your project?
That completely eliminates the need for a dedicated side debugger?
Not really, I mean, you still need, you can have a debug system that
you that is kind of custom-built, but you still need a way to step
through things and typically that requires an external program at
least to get the harder bugs, so you can build your own sort of side
thing and that would work.
Oh, my mic is bouncing again.
You know what, I forgot.
I can't wear the hoodie or I can wear it, but it has to be like open.
Sorry about that.
We, this is a known problem and I just forgot I can't wear the hoodie.
Hey, Something to Remind Me.
By applying, I just saw an old video where it says the project will go
on at least until 2016.
How far along towards the end of the?
Are your hand mirror?
I don't know.
I estimated like, six hundred episodes and we're only at like 400
episodes right now.
So,
Yeah, at least 200 more episodes.
So probably at least another year of episodes.
One of the things I forgot when I said at least till 2016 through 2016
is I was thinking for some reason that six hundred episodes was two
years but we don't stream everyday.
So it's actually a lot more than that because we don't actually do a
swim every day.
So six hundred episodes actually mapped to like 4 years or something,
right?
This is going to be uploaded with the normally hmh code as well.
Yeah, I'll stick it in.
It'll be where that?
Where that directory is there?
Best alloy said there's a bug in the denominator check.
Thank you!
I will take a look at that now
Okay.
Oops.
Go
There we go.
oh,
thank you.
I don't know why I type that in.
That's about typo.
So denominator is less than the - Clarence sorry or denominator is
greater than the regular tolerance off we go.
I don't know if that change anything and probably didn't really change
anything in practice, but we'll run it again, just to be safe.
All right.
Best chili.
Shouldn't you initialize your material?
So emit color and ref color are initialized.
They automatically get initialized to 0.
Because I use that Open Bracket, close bracket equals Open Bracket,
close bracket on the array, so the whole array gets cleared to zero.
Just used maybe instead of Reinventing brdf what you call reflectance,
use some well-known, brdf like Disney's.
You can look at the implication of one in EG blender.
Yeah we could use a simplified like a
Standard reflectance model.
I believe dice also published their own, which is similar to the
Disney one.
Could be used raycasting determine a scene in real time.
That would allow infinite visibility like with sparse voxel octree as
opposed to rasterizer rasterize errs versus Ray tracers.
Doesn't really have anything to do with infinite visibility.
You can have a rasterizer that does infinite visibility just fine.
In fact, there are many, so that's really not part of it.
The reason is Ray casting is usually for better reflectance.
Right, because rasterizer is have a lot of a lot of trouble with light
propagation.
After use all these hacks to get light propagation to work, whereas
Races, they just work because hey, they compute the ray tracing very
Very much like it gets compute in the real world.
So really the
Them is they're just too slow.
So the reason we don't see real-time Ray tracers is because they're
just too slow for complex scenes.
But yeah, if you can find a way to make it run fast enough, then off
you go, there is one sort of pseudo real-time engine.
It's called Brigade that does Real Time Ray tracing i-it's code is
pretty similar to the code.
We just typed into, they actually, that does it on the GPU so it can
be very paralyzed and fast.
And most of the stuff they have to do there is like with seen
optimization by using like KD trees and stuff like that.
To optimize the rate reversals.
Whatever happened to Al bot, I don't have a labott set up yet.
Why not?
You standard thread.
I don't really want to use a standard Library.
It's so terrible.
It's just coincidence that they're three of the sphere is all.
Have their top bottom line up.
Exactly on the horizon or is that an artifact of something we're
doing.
I mean, it's probably an artifact of the way, the camera setup.
I guess, but I would have to think it through more.
Could you just insert pragma OMP on the Ray Caster Loop 02 to try and
make it run on multiple processors possibly?
But I'd rather do it right.
Which I mean at some point we just should do it right.
Could you disable Windows Bells?
I hate these sounds.
You know what?
I haven't heard any of the sounds.
You guys heard the sounds?
Oh, cuz the black magic device is still set.
Okay, that should have been muted.
Sorry about that.
Messi Elda.
The anti Alias has roping artifacts, why?
Well.
I mean, I couldn't say for sure but roping roping are defects are
going to occur.
Any time you have a box filter e like process happening, which is
basically what's happening here because we're not really using any
kind of good randomization for that.
So I don't know that you're ever going to really get rid of those.
You would have to intentionally do like blue toys filtering on the
actual points you were sending out.
So really it's mostly just a case of 256 samples in a square is going
to basically amount to a box filter which is going to have a rope
artifact.
But that's what's going to look like, right?
The other problem is that the zoom on this thing is going to do it by
linear filter, right?
So what we really need to do is open this in a program that will view
it fairly, which I can try to do.
I love this, right?
It's like Microsoft has made their stuff.
So complicated, even they mess up.
How to add something to a context window?
In their own default program inside their own explorer that can't even
get it right?
so here, if we zoom in on it,
You can see it's not so bad, it's not that ropey actually but you know
it's never going to be perfect.
With the growing popularity of multi-threading make procedural
programming harder.
But yes, it already has, I mean, people already have to do a lot of
work to make sure their stuff is set up from the ground up for
multi-threading when you wouldn't prefer to write and there's
techniques.
You know, you can employ that help make it better and there's, you
know, ways you can structure code to make it more likely to work well
multi-threaded but none of that changes.
The fact that that's that's
Had the programmer had to think about normally in single-threaded
program you never had to think about any of that stuff.
So even even techniques that make it easier for you to do is I still
mental overhead.
That you don't wish you wish you didn't have to do, right?
Can you make one of the Spheres a mirror?
Yes, I can.
Hmm.
Which one of the Spheres do you want to be a mirror?
The green ball, maybe, or the blue ball, or maybe the tan ball?
I don't know.
Let me just add another one.
Now, I'm going to not make it completely reflected because you can't
make anything perfectly reflective or light could Bounce Around the
scene forever, which you don't really want in a ray Tracer.
When you start to, especially when you start to do more physically
accurate stuff,
So, no such thing as a pure me really, but it's okay that won't
actually break anything.
If you have a pure mirror, so that'll be fine.
And I'll just stick in a forest fear here.
And that's fear.
I will put maybe off in the distance sort of on the ground so I'll
make it maybe you like
this.
And we'll let that go for a little bit.
All right, so, it looks like that's all of the questions.
I will say that I was very happy with how the question prompter worked
out there.
That was pretty great, so I'm very happy about that.
Is this source code included with $15 for handmade hero Source?
Yeah, I mean, you have to wait till I update this
So tonight, when I update the repositories, it will be in there.
But yeah, I'll it'll just be in there.
Oh wait, you're right.
You are right.
You know what I probably should have done this with an initializer
list, so I wouldn't have to worry about that.
But it didn't.
So, hold on a second.
Also, the sphere is in the wrong place, right?
So
this last fear, I actually want to be forward and why?
So I want it, I want that, I think is what I wanted.
Can you share the question prompt your code to I miss?
Some of the stream and would like to see it.
Eventually, I'll get around to that, but it's on the other machine.
So it's not in the handmade hero Source, directory the moment.
It's also like so boring.
I don't know why anyone would need the source code to it, but
Genesis 3.
I mean before if we could use traditional re-crafting like Wolfenstein
used to determine mesh visibility in the distance just using diffuse
lighting.
Not really sure what that means.
All right, so there's our Pure mirror ball back in the distance there.
You can kind of see what's going down with that and yeah.
I mean, there you go.
That's that's the long and short of it.
All right, folks, that's it for our test stream.
I think we did learn one valuable thing, which is I have to remember,
not to wear a hoodie closed, which I am likely to do.
So, I'm not sure what to do about that because the mic does bump into
it.
I guess I'll have to figure out something else there to use, but
But yeah, so thanks everyone for joining me.
I think that went fine.
So tomorrow will either start back on him here tomorrow or improve our
Ray Tracer.
And then either way, we'll be back to him a zero coding.
Either either tomorrow or next weekend, but it looks like we're good
to go.
And yeah, and everything worked out pretty well.
The stream didn't crash the new machines are both running.
Okay.
So that's
That's yeah, that's good.
All right.
So let's go back here.
And wind things down.
There's our final image for the day.
Let's let's say, you know what?
Let's save that off.
Today is the 21st, so that's 2017.
1021 first.
Image First,
A image.
So that's not bad for a first, you know, for a couple hours of on
stream programming where everything was explained.
I'm happy with that.
And again, really what needs to happen now is we just need to like,
You know, get a better, get a more physical model of how the light is
going to propagate.
And I think you know those are two things that Cindy is it make
everything run, insanity and threaded so that the speeds, okay?
And then go ahead and
And get the get the light transport working properly, because the
light transport in there is kind of a joke and it'll look a lot better
if we actually like get some real physical values in there.
And so we can see some some good light transport results because the
ray tracing stays the same regardless, right?
Look, Ray tracing is Ray tracing?
That part can be upgraded separately from the light transport which,
you know, once you know, a path through the scene that you want to
transfer it right along, that is a separate problem, right?
so,
Anyway, I'll go ahead and close this down.
Get all this stuff out of here.
Get rid of that.
Sure we'll save that.
Why not?
Close that.
Close Milton.
Articles on, just let that up.
All right, thank you, everyone for joining me.
For our first day back.
We didn't do any handmade hero.
This was I don't know what we categorize this as this is like a
handmade practice session, I guess just to make sure that everything
was working.
Okay and it seems like a strange working, okay.
So we will try returning to regular hand material programming, very
shortly.
If you want to follow along with a series at home and I will upload
that ray-tracing source code.
You wanted to get that and play around with it all the source code
comes with the pre-order.
So if you preorder handmade hero on handmade here at org, you can
start playing around that source, code yourself and do experiments
with the ray Tracer.
If you'd like to play around them or if you want.
If you're looking for some extracurricular activities to do, in fact
you could go ahead and approve.
The light transport you can look up online some information about
physical light transport, or you can also
So get if you are the sort of person who has a bunch of money and
doesn't mind spending it on things, you can actually go to the
physically based rendering book.
Where is it?
This guy you could go order a book such as this one which is about
physically based rendering and you could read it and you could use
some of that knowledge.
Edge to improve the light transport or add a real Lens model to the
camera.
Like I said, there's no lens on the camera right now and there's just
a plethora of things that you can do in terms of improving the quality
with that bear bone structure, that's in there right now.
You can sort of upgrade the pieces and make them more and more robust
as you go.
So that's about it.
If you want support the video series, we have a patreon page.
We also have a schedule bot.
If you want to follow us, you can see that it says a little too.
Turbot and it post a schedule for every weekend and that reminds you
when it's ready.
So that's kind of handy thing of trying to catch us live.
We also have a fantastic episode guide maintained by the wonderful May
Blow from the chat.
And he also has a patreon.
You can support where he annotates, lots of people's stuff.
So this is a pretty cool Patron to support this byblos project here.
I don't know why why does that go?
Why doesn't that go to his patreon page?
Does anyone know, is that a bug here that should go to his patreon
page?
Shouldn't it?
Because this goes to 0, there goes so, it's I don't know.
This is kind of confusing.
Because that goes to my patreon.
That should go to midlas Patron.
I don't know what's going on here.
You got me but point being out of the handmade Network folks probably
have done some things to the layout.
I have no idea but the point is there's a patron for supporting the
episode guide but anyway the episode guide is pretty great.
Like for example, I mentioned the inner product
You can actually do stuff where you like search through all of the
episodes 4 times when I talked about the inner product and it'll kind
of give you some information.
So, like, you know, a nice talk about that reflection function and,
you know, here's some of that stuff and, you know, probably have
talking about the dot product to right?
Here's dot product stuff.
So I would highly recommend utilizing that if you have any sort of
questions, it's a great resource.
And again, you can support the patreon for the people who do that.
Because
It's really nice to them.
They just did it themselves.
Like I had nothing to do with it.
It was entirely volunteer maintained so that's it.
I will be back tomorrow as the lit live countdown.
Timer says 19 hours from now.
I'll be back here to do some regularly scheduled stream programming.
I hope see you back here for that until then have fun programming and
I'll see everyone out there on the internet.
Take it easy everybody.
And I will now switch back to the streaming computer.
Pewter and stop the recording.