And start recording.
Hello everyone and welcome to handmade here on the show.
Rico to complete game live on Twitch.
No engines, no libraries.
It's just us and absolutely all the code with the exception of
Windows, which, you know, it gets in our way it does but it's the
platform you got to shift on what can I say.
So here we are writing on top of Windows someday and I hope that day
is it's feasible down.
The line will work on a platform where we can get rid of the operating
system because that
To be really homemade and, you know, I'm looking forward to it.
But if you're a game developer,
There's no getting around the truth, your daughter's ship on Windows.
It's where all the games are purchased.
So if you want to feed your family, you got to shift their.
So
Here we are shipping here and we are in the middle of well honestly.
We're not really in the middle of anything.
We did a bunch of optimization stuff and it was actually very light
optimization stuff.
I just showed how to do 70, and then multi-threading, we didn't really
try to push it too far, but it turned out to actually be extremely
fast because processors are extremely fast these days, it was kind of
surprising, but we wanted to start to do some other things and kind of
push forward into some of the areas that we hadn't quite finished yet
and sort of let that come back around to optimization so that we could
really crank things down a little bit more in a separate path.
So right now we're doing is a little more architecture work.
We're just trying to push the render a little bit further forward into
a state where I feel like I'm comfortable saying.
This is what it does and we can probably live with this for the entire
project, you know?
I mean, we don't have to lock it down, we can always go back and add
things.
But just something that I would reasonably believed, you could write
all of handmade hero in and not be hamstrung or anything.
So we're just doing a little bit of that pushing.
So it's a little bit, helter-skelter a little bit, anything goes for a
while.
Well, we kind of go through and, and push on all the pieces and get
them to line up.
And one of the things that we wanted to do was get ground chunks,
rendering separate thread.
And there's some things that we have to be able to do to do that
because there's some parts of the engine that we haven't built out yet
that are required to do that.
And so that's what we're probably going to take a look at today.
So
Let's get started.
If you would like to follow along with me at home, please remember
today is day 131, which means you want to unzip day, 130 source code,
if you would like to follow along with me.
So, if you ordered the game on handmade here at org and downloaded the
source code unzip, one 30-day 130 is zip.
That's what I'm starting with right now.
Okay, so here we go, here we go.
We had sort of an amusing thing that happened.
If you remember at the end of last dream, we were zoomed out.
Here in kind of a looking at things.
So if you take a look at what's going on here, there's two things that
we wanted to start taking a look at one is that, you know, you can see
that we're doing these ground chunks on-demand, right?
And the little yellow ring.
Is that we're kind of zoomed out for debugging purposes.
The yellow rectangle here is where the the screen would actually be
when we're at normal size when we're not zoomed out.
So that's what the user, the gate, that's what the player will
actually be seeing is what's in there.
And so our goal is obviously to make sure that we always have ground
chunks available for the player when they go through there.
Now, we have a problem, it's not that much of a problem because our
render is a lot faster now, but you can see, we get a slight frame
rate hiccup.
Just a slight one.
When we create those new
Ground Chuck's, right?
And we could fix that into one of two ways, right?
One way, we could fix that is just by making it a little less brain
dead when we create those ground chunks because right now we're
actually doing that in a really stupid way that revolves a lot more
Graphics work than it ought to.
But what I'd rather do is I would rather go ahead and multi-thread
that just because I know we're going to want to do some
multi-threading of this forum where we have things that are working in
the background.
And so I think it's probably a good time to
Get something like that working again because we are trying to nail
down all of our engine stuff and that is an engine thing.
So in order to make sure that our engine is is looking like I want it
to look before we start doing game stuff, I want to make sure that
we've got a few things happening in that overlapped fashion.
So what we want to do is we want to start being able to run that on a
separate thread and let's take a look at the reasons why we couldn't
do that.
Now, the first thing that,
We need to do is a little bit of cleanup because we actually didn't do
this and it was total luck that it was working at all.
It just so happened that we were aligned.
Now, for those of you who don't remember this pad thing, right here is
the only thing saving us from faulting.
So let's say, I compiled our code and it doesn't have the pad in it,
right?
So the path is not there.
I go ahead and run this.
You'll notice we we go ahead and we get a certian trigger here because
our
Is not aligned.
And of course, if I remember is not aligned in our optimized, renderer
rendering code won't work.
So, the only reason that that was turning out to be true that are,
that are renders, could could could work on the tiles on those ground
chunks was because they happened.
They just happened to be aligned.
Now, we knew the frame buffer was aligned because we made sure the
frame buffer was aligned, so that was an issue.
But when we go to render to those tile, chunks, those ground chunks.
Those were not aligned.
And so, what we want to do is make it so that if I don't have this
padding here because remember, the transient state is that the state
start of the transient buffer and then we kind of just push things
onto that buffer.
Those ground chunks, where they are, alignment, wise is affected by
how big transient state is, okay?
So what we want to do is make it so that we can run it this way and
not have this assertion fire and not have it, of course crash because
again if I commented out that assertion it's not like it would just
work.
It would actually just crash a little later on, right?
So if I, if I take this out, right, and I run this code will crash
when we actually go to do it, because this load isn't aligned load,
and aligned loads will fault if their destination is not actually a
line, and the same would have been true down here for our store.
You can see that our store is also an aligned store.
Remember store without a u is aligned store loads out of you.
If this restore you it's unaligned and then it's fine.
But we wanted to use those aligned stores and loads.
That's the instructions we want to use.
So we're using those and that was fine because everything was aligned
and we had other reasons for doing that that had to do with cash,
contention and and race conditions.
Hopefully you watched all that, you know why that is we went through
it in a lot of detail.
So the first question is, how do we fix this problem?
How do we make sure that those tiles are going to be aligned properly?
Now, we know right, when we create these ground chunks.
So we have our
Transient you know stuff here right?
We have our transient stuff.
We know when we're calling this make empty bitmap stuff that we
probably want to make sure that these things are aligned.
But what we don't have is a way to actually make sure they're aligned.
So when we go in to say make empty bitmap here, if we wanted to make
sure that this was a lined, we know right here when we do our push
sighs, we could tell that allocator that we needed to be aligned if
only there was a way to do that.
At and unfortunately, there is no way to do that but what we can do
obviously is we can write 1.
If we go in here and we take a look at push sighs.
Let's go ahead up here.
Precise.
What we could do is say oh okay, let's go ahead and say that.
There's another parameter that comes in here which is just the
alignment, which is what kind, you know, what alignment you want.
And how many bytes did you want this to be a line too?
And we'll say this has to be a power of 2.
Right?
And we'll just default it to for, will say that.
D, word alignment is the default alignment and that if anything else
if you want any other element, then you have to ask for it explicitly.
So what I can do then is I can say, all right,
We've got our result here.
This is what our pointer would be.
We've got our base in this, this stuff here.
Right.
What I want to do now is see if there has to be some kind of
adjustment, right.
And we've done this code before we've done alignment code before,
right?
Because if you remember, when we were actually doing our draw
rectangle quickly,
We did code.
That looked a lot like this, right?
When we came in here to do our clipping, we did stuff like oh is this
a line?
24 pixels.
Remember, that's the way we were doing this here.
Is this a line?
24 pixels?
If it's not aligned 24 pixels and we were doing and three, they're
like art remember and 33
To bottom bit set, right?
The one bit and the to bit add them together.
You get three.
That's what three is.
It's the two bottom bits are set.
So we're saying are either of the two bottom bit set, if they are,
then this thing ain't line 24, right?
Because anything aligned to for will have both bottom, B a0.
So, we'll go ahead and check those and we'll do something about it if
they're not there, right?
So that's what we want to do.
And specifically, we want to, we want to move up because remember, we
can't move backwards to a line because that would move into memory.
That's already being used.
So we need to move upwards to put us at the next boundary.
So what I want to do is say, okay, we've got this Arena base, right?
So we can say this alignment that we have here, we can say we can do
exactly the thing we were doing before, right?
We can say that if that I guess I should explain this part a little
bit, will make an alignment Mass care and I don't know if I don't know
if we've gone over this before.
I think I've done it before about know, if I, if I really actually
talked about explicitly.
So I'll just go ahead and draw a real quick.
Since this is the first time, maybe that we're really talking about it
in the memory context explicitly.
But if you have some binary number, right?
In this case, let's say, I've got, I want to align to that for right?
Well, hopefully, you guys will remember your binary here.
So, here is a bite.
Let's just do a bite.
Remember what the bits in?
This is the one, B, two B.
For a bit 8-bit 16-bit 32-bit 64-bit and 128-bit, right?
So, if all of them are set, you'd add them all together, you get 255,
which is the maximum height can store, right?
And if you add any other combination together, you can produce any
other number between 0 and 255.
So, if you come in and you see something set as for, then you would
expect to see.
This right, the for bit is set and the other bits are not set.
So now if we want to know if a given value is aligned to 4 B
boundaries and we're saying that that means that these have to be 0.
Right?
What we're looking for, is a mask that allows us to test to see if
these bites are set and a trivial way, we can do that for a power of
two is by subtracting 1 from the value.
Because if we subtract one, right, what will happen?
Is this will turn into a 1
This will turn into one and this will turn into a 0, right?
It will borrow over, you know, 100 minus 1, where each of these is
binary will keep borrowing from itself it.
Oh, it had to borrow, you know, a to write had to borrow again, a two
and then it borrowed.
And so you end up with a
You end up with the 100 minus 0 0, 1 equals right 011.
It's analogous to how you do it in decimal, but unfortunately, it's
hard to imagine.
Because normally, if I do this,
Right?
You would think of me doing 100 minus 1.
You're thinking of going like, oh okay, I've got to borrow, you know,
this way.
I'm borrowing this and turning this into a 10 or something like that,
right?
But of course, in this case, the highest number you can actually have
is, is a one in a column.
So, borrowing, something from the next one just gives you a to.
I don't know if that makes any sense, probably doesn't.
I know?
It's a little bit confusing but hopefully you understand what I'm
talking about in binary, you can
Also see that this makes sense logically.
If I have four and I subtract 1 from it, I would expect to get three,
right?
And of course, three is the bottom two bits set 1 and 1, right?
So hopefully, you can also see that that just makes sense.
Logically, just in terms of the encoding, even if you're uncomfortable
of doing the math in binary, you can see that it works just in decimal
and then if you re encode it back.
So all we have to do to take a power of 2 and turn it into a mask is
just subtract 1 from it and that will produce the mask of the
It's that should not be set if we're a line to it.
So, what we can do here is say, okay, if we have a situation where the
base pointer is not aligned to the alignment mask, the first thing
that we do is we can push up, we can push up that alignment, right?
And the way that will do that is, I'll say, okay, I've got a memory
index which is my alignment offset.
And at the end of this whole situation, what I will actually do is I
will take the arena bass and I will do the arena base plus the
alignment offset.
So, do you read a base?
Plus the arena used?
Oh, you know what?
I actually have to look at Arena used as well.
Hmm.
Alright so I've got to actually do this a little more slightly here
because I have to the way that we've encoded this has to go this way.
All right.
so, let's talk about the basically, the pointer the results, pointer
All right, so if we take a look at what happens here, this is the base
pointer for the arena.
This is how many bytes have been used and so if I add those two
together, right?
I get what the actual result pointer will be.
And so, what I want to do now is make sure that I can actually align
that so that, you know, the the result will be aligned to the value
that we passed in.
So, I produced that alignment mask and these are the B that these are
the bits that
I know can't be set.
I take a look to see if any of them are set, if they are set.
What I want to do is I want to go ahead and move up, however, many it
would take me to produce the alignment, right?
So, the way I'll do that is I'll just say, oh,
Let us say the alignment offset is going to be whatever the alignment
was, right?
Because if I was at zero, I'd add the whole thing - whatever sort of
that oops,
- whatever portion of it we've already gone, right?
So I want to go the whole way to the alignment and I'm just going to
take whatever portion of it, we found there.
I'm going to go ahead and subtract that away.
All right, so that's the offset that we would need to add.
So what I want to do here is then say okay the size that they
requested I now have to assume that I want that size to be inflated by
however much I need to align because remember we are trying to see.
We're trying to make sure that we have enough room in the buffer.
We need to include however much motion we're doing for that alignment
so that we can properly track the size.
So we go ahead and move the size up there.
We did assert to make sure that we have still room in our Arena
because remember we don't allocate any more space currently we just
use the space that we have.
So if anyone
Overflows that that means we've hit an error condition and things are
very bad.
And so then off we go, right?
So when we do this, our result pointer, then the actual, the actual
result value is just going to be the result pointer plus the alignment
offset, right?
And that's going to be turned into a void pointer.
Here we go.
What what are you complaining about Arena base?
Yes, right.
Sorry, forgot to change that into result pointer.
There we go.
And result pointer.
Okay, so just going over this one more time.
And we can make this a little bit more efficient.
But this is we don't necessarily care a huge amount how efficient this
particular routine is at least not at the moment.
So again, we just want to take a look at where we would put this
thing.
This is the current location that it would go.
We want to make sure that we can actually align it.
So, we say, okay, if there is some residual there, if it's not
aligned, see how much we'd have to add to bring it up to alignment,
right?
We then increase the size by that much.
And then we just do our assertion to make sure that we can fit that,
you know, in here.
We then add in the that new amount as the amount that's actually used
in the arena and we return that pointer so we can go ahead and run
that election step through that routine just to maybe show you what's
happening in the actual binary code.
I feel like we're probably still building in 02.
Let's switch this downshift to debug here.
Okay, so here we are in push size, right?
And if we take a look at what that result pointer would be right.
Here's the soups.
Here's the result pointer.
I'm going to go ahead and also show.
Here we go.
There's that result pointer.
And I'm going to also show the memory Arena, right.
So you can see, this is how big it is.
We haven't used any of it yet, and this is the base pointer, which is
where we're at the moment.
So we come through here, we build that alignment, Mass, where I like I
said, it's three exactly what we're expecting for an alignment of for.
We take a look to see if there's any residual, there isn't because
this is already aligned 24.
So we don't add
Into the size.
And we basically end up doing exactly what we're going to do and we
produce a buffer pointer.
That's that's right, where where the base is, right?
And so I feel like that's probably working just fine, but then, of
course, we still haven't solved our problem because we're not actually
passing an alignment in there.
We're just letting everything be aligned to 4 and we need those ground
tiles to be aligned to 16.
So let's go ahead and do that in make empty bitmap.
When we do this precise here, what I'd like to do.
Let's go.
Back in to hammer that H, we take a look at the push size here.
Now, I want to make sure we can use this VAR.
Make make sure we can use these push sizes.
We can always specify an alignment.
So what I'm going to do is say that after the things that you have to
specify in these macros, what I'd like to do is specify the VAR args
stuff.
I'd like to specify you know put whatever you want the end of this
macro and it'll just get sort of stuck on to the end.
Now if I'm not
Mistaken.
There's some nonsense that only happens with msv.
See it's like you need to use the paste operator or something like
this, or maybe it's GCC and it's, yeah, it's this syntax right here.
So, I do not remember which one doesn't work, and which one does work?
Whether it's VCC where the weather's ccrm SVC, but point being,
there's a special case that happens when you don't when someone might
not include any additional arguments and there's different ways that
you do it.
And so I believe this is the one that works on everything.
It's what I remember and it looks like bunch of random people on stock
exchange, or talking about.
I don't know, or sorry, stock overflow, so I'm not entirely certain,
but that was my recollection anyway.
So that's the way we're going to do it for now but we'll have to rely
on some people who compiled on other platforms to tell us if that's
okay.
So there you go, we've got our VAR spacing and and that's just I don't
even know exactly why this syntax came about.
But basically just saying take these guys and stick them on the end
here.
All right, so now I
Able to say 16 there and I should be able to run more properly.
Hopefully, at least that's the goal and it looks like we're fine now.
So we stop crashing course.
We're in debug mode.
So those ground buffers take extra long to render but that's actually
good.
Because now we can start to look at taking getting things
multi-threaded which we want to do to sort of overlap that work
anyway.
So hopefully we can use the fact that they take a long time actually
to sort of be a little bit of a help to us.
In that endeavor.
All right so hopefully everyone understands how that works.
It's really simple.
You can do this a little bit more efficiently bitwise so that you
don't have to maybe do as much work there.
But hopefully it's fine that way.
It's not that frequently called thing.
So I think leaving an explicit so you can see exactly what's
happening.
It's probably a good idea.
So, there we go.
There's the push size.
All right, so the next thing that we need to address is we don't have
really when we make our transient state right now, we don't really
have any notion of temporary buffers that people can use.
And so the problem that we would run into very quickly if you take a
look at what happens with, with Phil ground chunk here.
Right, what we want to do is we want to be able to call this thing,
right?
We want to be able to call a function that would do work on a cue and
we want the work that's done on the Queue to essentially be this this
whole routine, right?
We want this whole routine to happen on a cue so in some sense what
we're looking for?
Here is something that probably I mean I you know, I don't even know I
guess we could really just do the entire thing.
On it, I'm not sure, but I'm going to I'm going to partition it a
little bit at the moment just because I'm not sure how much we wanted
to do, but basically what I'd like to do is say, okay, I'm assuming
that it would not be that just queuing this stuff up is not really a
problem, right?
Meaning if what we did, I guess I'll I'll take this guy back out again
here for a second, right?
If what we did was just queue up all the push bitmap things and then
just didn't ever render them, right?
We just didn't ever do anything there.
I'm guessing that if we did that, we would not actually have any
pauses, right?
That's just my assumption.
And I guess, you know what?
I could.
Also, let me, let me go ahead and put ourselves back in here just so I
could be double sure that we wouldn't have any pauses or anything like
this, so, get render entity basis.
Let's go ahead and
Back in there.
And so, here we go.
We're walking around.
And I don't feel like we've got any problems.
I'll go ahead and compile in 02 as well.
And I feel like we're pretty good there, right?
We're definitely not hitting any of those really big long hiccups so I
think we're probably fine there so that's all good.
So what that means is we could we can leave part of what we're doing
synchronous, which might be beneficial to us, depending on how we want
to do things because we might not want to have to lock areas of the
simulation or other things like this, that might be involved.
When we're actually pulling out this stuff like right now, we could
totally do all of this asynchronous, but in the future,
If we were looking at things like where entities were in drawing stuff
like that that might cause us have to lock some things that we don't
want to lock or who knows what else.
And so I would like to make it so that this could run synchronous
produce the sort of the the the thing that needs to actually get
spawned and then spawn it.
So essentially what will happen is just this part right here will get
pushed onto the separate thread and then we'll be fine.
And what you can see though,
Oh, is if you take a look at how this is working, you can see why this
would be a problem because right now, we've sort of created temporary
memory for this render group to store those commands, Okay?
And then we end the temporary memory block right after we do this.
This tiled render group to Output.
So if this were to become an overlapped operation, that's going to
execute for a period of time, we can't very well release the memory
for it.
Right after we spawn that sort of
Running.
Right?
Because we basically be getting rid of the memory out from under it
and it'll still be using that memory and it'll just go crash or who
know because it will read garbage from there or something as we
overwrite it.
So, what we need to do there is we need to have some way.
To have like a temporary storage area, where we can put these things
so that the background task is capable of doing it without having, you
know, without essentially getting overwritten, if that makes sense.
So if we want to do that, it's not probably going to be too difficult
to do.
Let's just take a look at how we might go about doing that.
If we go take a look at the transient State here, right?
What I'd like to do is just say well, okay, we've got the transient
State and we have a memory arena in there.
What I'd like to do is introduce the concept of sub Arenas that work
inside a single Arena, right?
So basically, I can take it Arena and I can break it up into smaller
Arenas.
So that if I have people who are doing work and needs,
Space for it but they all need to be operating at the same time, I can
just pre segment up my memory into a couple different chunks and they
can each have a chunk and do whatever they want in there and I know
that they won't conflict, right?
So there doesn't have to be any locking or any thinking about it.
There doesn't have to be any overhead introduced.
I know that I can just if I have some bounds on how much space those
people might need.
I know I can just pre segments and let them go and they'll be no
performance penalties for me, right?
And also no possibilities for bugs with like synchronization or
something like this.
So what I want to do is start introducing this, so I want to have a
memory Arena here, that's going to basically you know, maybe and maybe
even a couple of them which will be foreground chunk filling, right?
And so we'll call this something like you know this memory Arena will
be the ground chunk render groups or something.
Arena's ground chunk.
Arena's, I'm not sure but we can basically say we want a couple of
these.
We want a few Arenas in here that we'll use for ground chunks, right?
and then what I'd like to do is
Have some notion of a rolling count, hear something that will allow me
to cycle through using these Arena.
So that I can fill a couple of them, like, I can kick off a couple of
them and know that they'll get worked on.
And then, as they are retired, I want to be able to know when I can
use another one, right?
If that makes sense.
So I don't have any specific idea about how I want to do that.
Maybe something like this?
I don't know.
I mean, I don't actually I could just even make it so that it's always
just at the beginning of the Arena.
I'm not sure you think about this for a second.
Hmm.
Yeah, well I'm going to push ahead on this a little bit.
But I'm starting to get a slight sense that I want to do something a
little more interesting here, but will.
In fact, I'm just going to go ahead and say this.
I'm going to say that we want something that's like, you know, a task
with memory or something like that.
And I want to just go ahead and put that in here, right?
So it basically has an arena that it can use to do stuff.
And then it can have like, you know, a being used, right?
So something that says whether it is actually currently in use or not,
right?
And so we'll go ahead and say that we have a, you know, task with
memory and then we'll just have some some tasks here.
And I just, you know, I want some of those I want four of those or
something like this.
So if I have something like that, then I can go ahead and make sure
That I can, you know, create some tasks and I can kind of Spawn them
off there.
And then I know that that, you know, I can, when there are some of
these that are free, I can use them, right?
And we can make more of them as we need.
So let me go ahead and
Just crew make a thing that creates one of those.
Let's see here.
So when I do this initialize Arena stuff, what I want to do now is I
want to say, I want to be able to make a bunch of these tasks.
In fact, I might go ahead and put that up here at sort of a more, you
know, right after we do this initialization, what I want to do now is
actually create those, right?
So I'll go through and I'll say
Okay, for each task, that I have I'm going to go through and that's
how our maybe these are re count everybody I have.
And for each one, I want to initialize this thing.
So task with memory, so we have a task, trance State, tasks, plus task
index.
So for each task we're going to say that it's not being used obviously
and it's a Rena is going to be whatever.
This this guy has here, this trance this Tran Arena.
What I want to do is have something where I can I can specify that.
I want to have a Submariner, right?
So I want to take that transient Arena and I want to base to be able
to carve out some subsection of it, right?
So, you know, maybe I want my task to have a 1
Like stack effectively that they can work with, right?
That they can some allocate out of and so that will create that,
right?
That will create that that's ever Rena and I guess to keep it in line
with the way that I was doing it before.
It looks like we basically point to an arena and say fill this out.
And so that's what this would do here.
All right.
So hopefully that's pretty clear how that would work.
And so when I do feel ground chunk, right?
And we take a look at how that actually works at the moment.
We don't this this routine again is kind of placeholder.
It's just kind of a silly routine so we won't really play with how
these are getting kicked off yet.
We'll think about how we want to do those maybe a little bit later on,
but we'll assume that once someone has called Phil ground chunk.
What we essentially want to do now, is when we call Phil ground Chunk,
we want to get
Unavailable task, right?
And then what we want to do is is our begin temporary memory and
temporary memory stuff.
We actually want that to be part of the task sort of completion
notion, right?
so we want to do is say alright let's go ahead and have maybe two
things here which is you know,
Trying to think of how to say this.
So essentially what I want to do is make it implicit in how this thing
works, right?
That I'll just when I begin a task, all the memory is going to be
temporary because when the task is over or that memory will get
flushed, right?
That's what I want to have happen.
So what I'm going to do here is it might ask with
Thing, I take the temporary memory and this will just be like, the,
the memory flush or something.
What I want to do is, you know, when you say begin task, they'll be a
way to begin a task here.
And then they'll be a way to end the task.
Memory.
Like so.
And so, what I want to do is this begin temporary memory stuff here.
That will not actually be happening outside in the ground chunk.
That will be happening when we do the begin test with memory.
So in the transient State, I'll take the trance State.
Here will do this.
Begin task will actually do the Contemporary somewhere else and then
we'll do this and temporary memory somewhere else as well like.
So
Yeah, and so, then our call back here that actually does this work,
the to tiled render, work stuff, that will actually happen.
When that actually does the work, it will call end task with memory
when it's done.
Okay, so we'll get rid of this, okay?
Okay, so what I want to do is I want to go ahead and say that
This thing when I do feel ground chunk, I'm going to use this begin
task with memory thing.
I'm going to use an if around it.
So I'm going to say if begin tasked with memory then we will actually
do this ground buffer filling stuff here, right?
And off we go.
Wish I had some tissues here but I don't know.
Well, I guess I'll just remain stuffy.
You know how it is.
Anyway, so we've got a couple things that we want to look at here, but
I'll take them one at a time.
But basically, what I want to do is say begin to ask memory and only
if that returns true.
Do I actually do the work of filling the ground chunk?
Okay, the reason that I want to do it that way is because when I do
begin task with memory,
It's possible that there are already too many tasks running and I
don't want to just launch like a ton of tasks, I only want to launch a
certain amount of tasks enough task that I have time to do or whatever
so I want to keep it limited.
So what I'd like to do is make it so that when you go to spawn a task
you may or may not be able to spawn that task and you just have to
deal with it, right?
So if you're trying to put on work into a background Q, you can't just
Spam it out there.
You've got to actually think about it a little bit.
Now we could do stuff that
And involve that like we could make it so that they're just build up a
work queue.
But if that's the case, you know, you run the risk of like how do you
know that thing isn't growing out of control and so on and so forth.
So I'm going to keep it a little bit more under control in that for
now and just say if you, you know this will basically tell you if you
are able to get a task or if you are not okay.
And so what we'll do is we'll just Loop in here, we'll Loop over the
tests that are available, so we'll say, task, invests from from there
to the task count, right?
Right count, there we go.
Plus plus task index.
And what we'll do is, we'll go ahead and grab one of those tasks
memories out of there and we'll see.
For each one of those.
We will see if it's being used.
Right?
And if it's being I should say, if it's not being used, if it's not
being used, then we will say that.
We have found a task that we can use and that is the one that we will
use.
Right?
In fact, I guess the found task thing, what I really probably want to
do here is say task with memory, right?
Probably want to do it this way.
Instead of a pool probably want to just return the task, right?
So there's the
Ask right?
And this go ahead and does found task equals task and off we go,
right?
So assuming that it finds the task, it'll also do it can also do it
here.
It'll begin the temporary memory for the task, so we have test memory
flush right, memory flush.
Oops, Arena.
So there's that task Arena.
I'll basically say I'm starting a new temporary memory set for this
guy.
I could also here if I wanted to probably I suppose this could
actually be where I also do the end temporary memory but yeah I don't
know if that's AI, don't know if I want to do it that way.
I think I'm gonna not do it that way.
Anyway, so when we find a task, we then go ahead and say we're going
to start using
Sorry memory flash.
We're going to start temporary memory block.
So this whole Arena can get flushed at the end of things and then you
know, when we're done here and we do the end task of memory will do
the memory flush here, like so
Right.
And that will just go ahead and flush that out.
And so that's really mostly what I need to do here, right?
And it will return that task with memory back to the guy so that it
can do whatever it wants to do with it.
And if it doesn't find one that it's just going to return 0, right?
So then when I do that, that Grand Funk, I've got the task with
memory, here's my task.
And so if I get the task then I'm going to go ahead and do this stuff
that I'm going to do, right.
Okay.
So we've got some things that we'll have to deal with a little bit of,
you know, as well in there.
We'll talk about this a little bit later, but then when we go to do,
tile render group to out,
What we want to do is this is the thing that we wanted to put kind of
on the other the background threads here.
Right, what we want to do is make this the on the background threads,
what I'd like to do is well, when we do the tiled render group to
Output, I don't know if we have not think we have any way to do it non
tiled right now.
So what I'd like to do is also have it so you can see that we kind of
kept it in here, we kept it so that it was possible for it to do it.
Non tiled still, right?
So if we do tiled render group to Output, we can actually do, we could
actually do something here.
Where we do, you know, render group to output.
And we can actually have a pool here which is like tiled, you know, or
multi-threaded or something like this, right?
And what we can do is assuming that we do want to do it
multi-threaded, or if we don't want to do it multi-threaded, we can
actually do it.
Essentially both ways, right?
We can have a thing that does does both.
Times trying to think of what the easiest way to do that is I wonder
if it's easier to just actually have a separate routine.
I think it might be though.
So, looking at it, it looks like it's actually easier to have a
separate routine, so I would leave that as tiled.
I'm thinking and go in here and say, all right, there's also just
render group to Output that's non tiled, right?
The way we sort of had it before, and what that does is it still does
the same stuff but now it's not gonna
Actually.
Do any tiles here at all?
Right.
So it doesn't do any of this stuff.
It'll still at least verify the output memory, is the same there.
Let's see here.
We could also assert that the width is proper, I guess the way I could
do this is is actually do it like this right where we just say that.
So, keep these guys in there, get rid of these.
Still do that alignment there.
Get rid of these entirely like so and there we go.
Right.
So this would be the path that does things.
I guess I need one of these work guys so work and this is just me
calling it the same exact thing single-threaded, right?
So we're basically just saying we want the whole region to be in the
cliprect we don't actually care.
I guess this actually
It goes like this.
So I want to pass all that which actually no.
I look at it looks like we don't even need this tile with it.
Looks like that was more something that was done here to make sure
that as we strided, we were always aligned
As we went from tile to tile so actually we don't actually need this.
It looks like we're just good.
We just have to set up a cliff Trek.
That's the whole screen screen in this case, it's the ground buffer
but you know what I mean?
And so then we just fake it and we do tiled render work as if we were
doing a tile.
But really, we don't ever do it actual pile that make sense.
So, we do call this here right, and we can even pass because we're
not,
Using the render queue, right?
The render queue could be passed as 0 here.
If we wanted to, in fact, I guess what we could do is do it like this,
right?
Just so we know that you don't need a render queue to do this, so,
there we go.
And that yeah, that looks more.
Correct.
So you said the runner group there, I mean, a Target.
So, this now needs a way of being called, again, sort of like this,
this needs a way of being called as a separate task so that it can do
everything that needs to do and this guy, of course, also, we never
quite finished.
This impasse with memory, this guy needs to be passed the task, so
they could do this, it needs to flush the memory and then it also
needs to set being used equal to 4.
Right, for good measure, we should probably do one of those complete
things here.
We would probably want to put one one of those complete, you know,
previous rights before future rights, kind of thing that we were doing
right.
One of those read barriers and I feel like
I'm trying to think if we if how necessary that actually is, but it
seems like provided that we actually switch this to be an inline,
which it probably could, because it's very small, right?
It does seem like we probably want that to be in here right now.
That doesn't actually do anything on again on MSNBC, but it's
something that we might want to put in there, you know, a barrier.
Well, you know what it does.
Like I shouldn't say that MSP.
See, it does mean something.
It's just a XXX.
For it doesn't, but it's the read barrier on msv.
See, so if we take a look in here in our handmade platform stuff, and
we want to start sort of putting some things in there to Define these
intrinsics, right.
Actually, I guess we also have an intrinsic, handmade intrinsics file.
We could put them in here as well, right?
So in our handmade intrinsics, we can do a compiler, M SV C and then
we'll do an else where we don't actually know what this thing is yet.
We don't know what it is here.
We should probably could put an error but I'll let it compiled for now
and just put it to do.
Here need to Define these on GCC llvm which is probably the only
platforms that we
Clea also be compiling on besides.
I'm SEC.
So incomplete previous rights before before future rights.
We know that that's
You know right there and we know that that's this guy right?
Right barrier.
I know I put a tea under there, I think I've been working in another
code base a little bit too much, so let's keep going here.
I think we've got about 15 minutes left, according to the clock
because we went pretty late when we were starting.
So do tiled, render work, do tiled render work.
We need to cannot convert.
Argument to write that just needs to be an address.
Already has a body.
That's correct.
It does.
This is actually filled ground chunk work.
And we have to Define these, so that's all good and in tests of memory
needs to take the task.
So, alright, so we're basically putting ourselves in Striking Distance
now to start doing these tasks, which is what we wanted.
All right?
So if you imagine what happens here, we're going to be doing this,
begin task memory stuff, right?
And what we need to do here is when we do this allocate render group
instead of using the Train Arena, right?
There's only this is where the memory was coming from.
We wanted to allocate this, this transitory nothing.
What we want to do.
Now, is we want to go ahead and allocate the render group instead from
the tasks Arena.
So the tasks arena is what we're going to use.
And we probably want to allocate for the render group since we're not
doing anything else.
We probably want to allocate like everything that's in the task Arena,
right?
Because there's nothing else.
We probably want the whole however much the task Arena has.
So when we do the allocate render group, you probably want to do is
like get Arena sighs remaining or something and we'll just allocate
the entire thing to the render group because this doesn't actually
ever allocate anything else.
So it's not like it would ever actually
Need anything else to do, it's rendering so that so that's fine.
So then what we would need to do here inside that task as well.
And I guess that's where our other allocation would come from.
We would need something that allows this to do its work, right?
So we would need a fill ground chunk work structure and that would
have to have the things in it here that we would actually need and you
can see exactly what those are because I've already written out what I
want them to do, right?
So all we need to do is actually have a way of getting those in there,
right?
So you know, render group, we've got the output buffer.
I don't even remember what this thing is.
What's an output buffer render group bitmap buffer?
Is it just buffer?
Is that all we were renting to?
Yeah, I guess it is just buffer.
Yeah, so I guess it's loaded bitmap buffer.
Yeah, I guess looks that way.
So these are the actual things that I need, right?
So if I go ahead and say that, you know, the thing that you pass to
this fill ground chuck,
Work is one of, you know, one of these sort of structs that's got the
stuff in it that it needs then I can just go ahead and pull those out
as it goes and it can do it sort of like clean up at the end.
And of course this thing has to be the last thing because it's going
to sort of it's going to self-destruct basically you know this this
sort of self destructs everything.
So there's no way to recover after that.
Like that's got to be the last thing you do.
When you do stuff.
All right, so if we come down here now, well, actually, yes.
We don't need to do anything in particular quite yet, but we just need
to fill out one of these.
That's thing that tells, you know, that's basically got our work
requests in it.
And so, what I want to do is take the task Arena and I want to just
allocate from that first, so that task Arena.
I'm going to go ahead and do a push struct on the task arena for one
of these feel ground, chunkworks, and then I have that and then I can
fill it out with the things that
Need later on.
So when we get down to the bottom right before everything's over, I
can basically put everything in it so I can put it in the buffer I can
put in the render group.
And I can put in the task, right?
So if I do that,
I should be able to now do exactly what we did in the render group
when we responding a task where we do this sort of thing where I do a
platform at entry.
Right.
I do a platform add entry to the trance State.
We've got that low priority queue, that's for stuff.
That's, that's, you know, happening sort of in the background, I've
got, do Phil Gramm chunk work or whatever it is.
So Phil Gramm chunk.
Work.
And I've got the work order that it needs to do.
So, there we go.
What is he has an address that we go?
So now I just need to implement the other functions that I said that.
I wanted that I haven't actually implemented for the arena.
They're actually pretty straightforward right there.
See if we take a look here.
So here is our Arena structure.
We have a size and a used.
So in order to do a get Arena size, remaining, sort of a thing,
there's not really anything in particular, we would have to do there.
We can just go ahead.
And compute that directly say get Arena size remaining, there's the
arena, right?
And you know, the result,
Is just going to be the used amount, right less.
The used amount is going to be subtracted away from the total size
that it had.
And that's how much space that there is left.
Now, it's a little confusing because actually when I do get a Rena
size remaining, technically, you also need to know what the alignment
is of the thing that you are going to use was.
So I'm going to make this mirror it like this.
So that you can sort of say okay if we were going to do the alignment
also and you know adjust the size that way, what would happen there,
right?
If it was going to be a line because remember alignment can eat up a
little bit of that.
And so you know, if I was to do that, what I want to do here is
essentially I'd want this code to give me some indication.
And I want to be able to reuse this code, basically, right.
You can see when I do this.
It produces an alignment offset, right?
And the alignment offsets, what I do is what I use for everything.
So what I'd like to do is have a thing that's like, you know, inline
memory index, get alignment, offset, something like that which goes
ahead and does this computation for me.
And it can also do this in here, right?
Like so and yeah.
So then result pointer I'd have to in here, I'd have to also do
This operation again.
so,
Base for interviews.
Do you know what I could do to?
Well, not only need to do that so we can basically do it this way,
right?
And that should I think work?
Yes, that'll work, fine.
So actually, this will just work.
Now we go.
So if I do that,
And I have get alignment offset, I can now make sure that I always
account for that when I'm doing operations that involve thinking about
the size, because this will come back properly.
And so, then I guess I need to do this equals get alignment offset
Arena.
Then we grab the alignment offset here to add to the sighs.
I didn't mean to copy that out.
And so this just needs to learn return, that alignment offset.
And now what I can do is say that the result is going to be, you know,
Rina size equals this - you're the, the part that's used plus any
amount that it would take to move me up to the alignment that the
person is trying to ask about, right?
Oops, that's not what I meant to do.
Too many errant Keys.
Okay?
So there we go and we just need the alignment offset now to be
initialized to 0 and we should be good.
Go and this takes the alignment.
So does this?
Oops, not the alignment offset.
And off we go.
So this needs an address on it.
And conversion from size T to you and 32 possible data loss.
Is that so,
Oh, is that so tell me who is saying this is true.
Get Arena size remaining.
Where is that?
There it is.
It's producing a memory index.
Let me indexes, it's all of doing memories.
But who's complaining about this?
Argument conversion of science to you, Aunt.
32, of course it doesn't actually tell me who it is.
So maybe it's allocate render group that's complaining about that
probably is.
Let's go take a look and see what allocate render group is expecting
to see.
That is exactly what the problem is.
They're so let's go ahead and make that a memory index.
Okay, and these guys should be as well.
I suspect.
Oh, well, you know what?
I think about it.
I don't know if that's actually true because do we really want our Max
push buffer size to BU n?
32 have to expand to be.
You went 64's, probably not.
So I think actually what I wanted I think that's not actually what I
want to do.
So I think I do actually want to cast this.
So I think what I'm going to do is something like, you know, you went
32, you know, cast this to enter to.
I'm only, I'm a little bit nervous about that, so I wanted to be a
saturation here.
You know, what I want to do is I want to do like,
You know, something where I'm going to do, either the UN 32 version or
ffmf.
If it's over, I'm going to, I'm going to say also to do here.
Do here.
Safecast from memory.
You went to Unit 32.
It won't be a problem at the moment but I'm worried that eventually it
might go over or something like that.
And then we would be sad.
All right, so submarine has are very straightforward.
These are really really easy for us to do.
So if I come in here and I want to make one of these sub Arenas, all I
have to do is say, okay, I've got a memory Arena.
I want to make a sub Arena out of it.
So I pass in the main Arena and I have the result.
The result is going to be
Same here.
So the result size is going to be whatever the size is that's passed
in because Serena's have to have sizes.
So there's the memory, you ain't right sighs?
That's their size.
The result base is going to be me pushing that size, right?
And I guess I probably should have an alignment here as well, right.
A base alignment, although I could just force all of these.
Since for submarine has submarine has maybe want to always have an
alignment that's like going to be the full alignment, you know.
So I don't know how how true that really is that we need that to be in
there.
I don't know, we'd have to think about that but I'll leave it just as
a big alignment for now.
So yeah, so we've got the size in there.
We've got the base, which is going to be us, grabbing the the that
amount we're going to have the used, which is none, and the temp
count, which is also none.
So actually those can just remain uninitialized and that's a sub
Arena, that's all we need.
That will basically create a sub-region that gets sub allocated out of
separately.
So memory index, that's what I actually wanted.
Don't know why I said, never you in probably should never you.
It's a little more descriptive.
Anyway.
Oh, but it's not a un I guess, actually memory in t.
Well, either way.
Okay.
So, let's see.
Push size.
Comes back.
I gotta make this be you in a pointer.
That's fine.
We've got our severinus happening here.
Oh, right.
I said that I wanted this to be this way, right?
Because I want it to be nearer the way the other one worked.
So that's fine.
No, big deal there.
But if we do that, that means we have to initialize all the variables.
So we'll have to do it.
Like that.
Okay, so I think that's just about all of it.
Unfortunately, there's still so
Yeah, there's still a bunch of stuff.
We're just about out of time, but there's still a bunch of stuff that
we haven't quite covered yet.
In terms of how we would probably want to button these tab things task
things up, but we're sort of getting, you know, we're getting a little
bit, we're getting a little bit closer to having something where we
can just use it to do generic work instead of, you know, only that,
that sort of
It's very specific render workload that we designed it to do, but
hopefully, you can kind of see how this is starting to work out.
Right?
So, you know, when we come in here to fill Crown, chunk what we're
doing now is we're using the separate Arena that we have just for the,
for this particular task that we're going to launch off, we put
everything into that.
And then we go ahead and say, hey, put that in the low priority,
queue, get to it when you get to it, and we're all fine, and then we
leave.
And so we can queue up for of those at a time and they can just be
doing, whatever it is that they're doing.
And then when they're done, they'll get released back to the system by
saying that they no longer do anything by using this being used.
Taking that out.
It's not anything fancy at the moment but it should put us into a
situation where we could actually debug it and get it working.
At least that's the theory.
Okay.
So what am I looking at here?
I don't know what I'm looking at here.
Hold on a second.
Not sure that we should start to bugging this or whether we should try
to do it tomorrow, but let's take a look.
All right, so I'm having an issue here, where my chunk is a nonsense
situation look here.
She probably compile and debug mode.
Yeah.
All right, so let me take a look at where we're at here.
I am in the middle of the ad wall stuff so this is just coming
through.
So I obviously broke something because this has nothing to do with our
threading when I was doing the arena stuff.
I obviously broke something with our Arenas because you can kind of
see in here.
We haven't actually done any of the ground chunk stuff yet by the time
we come in here.
So this is actually just some kind of separate some kind of very
separate error so I probably broke something when I did the alignment.
So I'm going to go in to push size and
What I broke because I did that pretty quickly and I probably just
ruined it.
So, let's see here.
Alignment offset is zero.
That's good.
The size is something.
So that's going to happen.
We go ahead and do that.
We generate a result pointer and we come out.
What's that allocating the world?
Let's take a look at the world so that just totally failed.
Right?
Oh wait, no.
Sorry.
So that's all good chunk.
Doing M looks good.
The chunk hash is there.
There's chunk hash everyone loves the trunk cash.
So we come through here, we're calling push size.
Again, what's the alignment offset?
Now, it's nothing again.
That's good.
Size is all good, Irina used.
See what we're looking at here.
So we've used some of it.
We're still using some more off we go.
This all looks pretty reasonable.
Okay.
So, let's come out here.
And see load in some bitmaps.
It's all good.
so now, let's take a look at
I came State see what we're looking at here.
Here's that World Arena.
It's hasn't really gotten filled up at all, yet.
Still got plenty of room.
and so in, we come here,
add standard room.
And when do we start crashing?
We don't crash for a while actually.
So we're adding walls just fine, you know, off we go, no real, big
deal and we're adding walls, we're adding walls.
So what does it look like when we actually get to the point when we
crash at Ground identity at wall game, update and render?
So it's not like we're out of space or anything.
We have plenty of space and where
Looking at some stuff that looks pretty valid.
We come down into ad wall, we're adding a ground identity here which
is just our way of adding something that has collision with it, right?
So we've got it, our entity low happening change into location.
So, that's taking a look to see if it's going into a place.
It is so it goes ahead and does that it does get World chunk.
The chunk comes back that shot comes back.
Okay, so
That's fine.
Actually and well, no, I shouldn't say that we're inside.
Get real chunk at the moment.
The chunk location.
Is all good.
But the chunk hash plus the hash lat.
Is not.
Mmm.
Well, it could have been because of the next in hash as well.
I suppose, we don't actually know which of those it did.
Let's take a look hash lat.
Is 3.
So World chunk Cash.
Plus hash lat.
So that's valid.
It's next in hash that is not valid, right?
That's totally totally bogus totally bogus.
So I wonder if this is messing up.
I'm just going to go ahead and see if it does.
So that was not the problem as far as I can tell.
So, all right.
Next thing to try, when we do our push sighs I'm going to assert some
things here.
So when we're done doing our push sighs, I'm going to assert that the
size.
So this thing I'm going to do is size in it.
All right so the initial size would take the memory index here sizing
it.
All right so I'm going to assert that the size is greater than equal
to size in it.
So we're reserving at least
And as much memory.
As you know, was requested of us.
Oh
Nice, that's lovely.
Well, that would, that would do it.
That's, that's, that's great.
I don't know what to say about that but you saw the problem there,
right?
I put the thing that advances in the wrong spot, I don't know.
Yeah, that was, that was pretty dumb.
All right, so let's see here, where are we at?
Got an assertion and I'll keep render group Next push, buffer size.
Ah, so this is the maximum size, but it also needs to take the struct
into account.
So, I'm going to go ahead and say that.
When you do allocate render group there allocate render group, let's
see, and made under group.
How can I do this?
I want this to basically allocate to take into account that Max push.
My oversized.
I want to take into account that this
But that it needs to not have this in here.
I could have it subtract within the meaning of this means something
else.
I don't really know.
Hmm.
I'm not sure what I want to do there.
I'm not sure.
So maybe if you do allocate render group and the max push buffer, size
is zero then it does the one for you.
That's kind of janky.
I don't love that but you know, you could do this right.
If Max pushed on for size equals zero, Max push the oversized equals
get a ring size.
Remaining that I don't love it, but I didn't see a lot of other
options at the immediate moment, right?
So that's that's what we're going with.
That's what we're going with.
Okay, so let's see here.
Push Truck.
Fill ground shook task Arena so that actually looks like we're almost
running here.
So, I don't know.
I'm sorry about taking up too much of the Q&A, really, but I kind of
wanted to see what was I kind of wanted to see how far away we were,
and we don't seem to be that far.
So, if I take a look at the task Arena here, it's all filled up and
looks like a temp count is 2.
So it's like, it never did the end here.
um,
I never said it to being used today.
That's kind of stupid.
So that's obviously not going to work either.
When I do begin test with memory, obviously I need to Mark the task
before I return it.
I need to say that it is being used, right?
Otherwise, it'll just be tried to use again.
All right.
So anyway,
yeah.
Anyway let's go ahead and see.
Now, how we're doing here, let's take that build-up back and change it
to a know to go ahead and run.
So now we've got some stuff happening, the background and rendering,
and like, we're not really giving it enough of a lead time to always
hit.
So, we've kind of got a problem there, but we've seem to have taken
care of our really long stalls.
So that's good and those ground chunks are rendering in
The background now, which is what we wanted.
So, yeah.
So that's good.
And we can also go ahead and maybe now and paying back over here.
Now, that we have those operating in the background, we can also sort
of come in and, and, and change that get render into the basis to be
debug Style.
So here we go.
Do do do, do do do so yeah.
Basically, all we really need to do now is query a little wider and we
should be pretty much good to go on the background background tasking
right.
Background tasking to do.
Do, do do.
Yeah.
Oh good.
So like I said, we got a couple things we can cover.
Like, right now, we're drawing from those bitmaps at the same time
that we're riding into them, which is not super cool because like,
right, we don't guarantee that they're actually done before we start
bleeding them so we probably want to put a little trap in there.
Something that says, hey I'm actually I've been finished and if that's
not set, like don't draw me because that would be bad, right?
So you know stuff like that.
But but yeah, so hopefully you can see that working pretty well now
and we've gotten rid of our hiccups, so we're maintaining a nice
smooth frame rate, which is what we want, no matter what the situation
is.
So that's all good.
So let's go ahead and do a quick Q&A.
Don't have a lot of time, but we'll do a little bit at least.
Let's go ahead and switch to Q&A.
I'm glad the handmade he robot actually listens to my queue a request
now because before it definitely did not.
Let's see, does anyone have any questions about what we did today?
Does anyone have any questions about what we did today?
If one of the tasks with memory which has several tasks with memory in
front of it calls and test and every first will this stuff in front of
it be screwed up or this case is no not possible because I have
feelings, I don't understand something.
So, I think you're thinking about what would happen if all of the
tasks were using the same Arena, but they're each using their own
Arena.
So, here's what actually happened.
Just so you can see here is the transient Arena.
Mischief.
Please keep up with me.
Waiting for you.
There we go.
So this is the transient Arena.
Right?
And this is allocated on Startup to be some giant.
It's like how much memory is the machine will take it.
All right, so I don't know.
Give me four gigabytes.
However, much you got.
What's the, what's the player got in there?
We're going to use it for something.
We'll find something to use it for.
So we allocate the memory that's in the machine.
And now we're going to divide it up, right?
So first, we put some stuff in there, right?
Like, you know, some stuff gets loaded in here, so this is other
things, right?
Who knows what they are the Tran the the actual trans States and here
at the top, right?
But other things,
Whatever then oh and the ground like there's there's the round chunks
themselves are stored in here, right?
The ground chunk.
Bitmaps are stored in here.
So you do this stuff and then what I did is, I said, oh, okay, I'm
going to slice this part up and make some separate Arenas, right?
So this is Task zeros Arena.
This is Task ones.
This is Task, 2 is this is test 3s.
So these are rinas are actually totally separate.
So all four tasks can be totally asynchronous and happen in any order.
They get their own memory playground to play in so they don't need to
talk to anybody.
They don't need to synchronize.
Anybody they can do whatever they want, as long as they do it entirely
inside this Arena.
So when we go to kick off a ground Chunk, we stick all the render
group stuff into the arena for the task.
That's about to get spawned, right.
We then spawn the task.
We let it run to completion and then when it's done, it just sets a
little marker, right?
So remember up here, in the trance State, we have a, those being used
right?
Say, whether the task is being used or not, we have those.
It just sets one of those little being used things to 1 or 0.
It sets it to 0.
So we know that that one is no longer being used and every time we go
to kick off a task, we just look for one of these that has its being
used set to 0, right?
And if we find one, that's the one we kick off.
So everyone's totally segregated memory-wise.
And that's why we don't have to care who ends firsts or whatever, it
doesn't matter.
We already had memory reserved for the ground buffers.
Why couldn't we just use that memory for the threaded stuff?
Well, that's where the bitmap goes.
So we can't use the same memory for the
As we use for the render group, right?
And also we have a lot more of them, right?
So there's something like 256 ground chunks on 128 ground chunks,
right?
Right, there's 180 ground chunks and that's the memory for the bitmap.
It's a 256 by 256 bit map.
Okay so where were you going to put that render group stack?
Which I don't know how big it is.
Lets you know, 10K or something.
Where were you going to put that?
You can't put it in here because this is what you're rendering to.
You would overwrite the render group in the act of filling in the
bitmap, right?
If you stuck it on the beginning, then all 128, ground chunks.
Bigger by whatever that is 16k.
Who knows how much it is get bigger by that even though will only ever
use four of them at a time.
So that's a huge waste of a ton of memory, right?
So we don't want to do that.
So what we did is we made memory for the chunks, that's only made
memory for the tasks themselves per task, so that things that only
live the life time of a task can go in there and not take up permanent
storage and things where there's a lot more of them.
What are the lines on the screen?
Let's see.
Why are there lines on the screen?
Are you talking about these lines?
These are in our debug mode so that we can see.
This is where the camera would see.
This is where the simulation region is and this is where the outer
bounds of collision consideration are, right?
So the user never sees any of that stuff.
The user sees this
Right.
This is how the user excuse it and of course this yellow line would
not be there.
That's the yellow line that's showing the camera bounds, right?
Yeah, if that makes sense.
That actually reminds me of something, pretty handmade.
But I wanted to see stretch TI B.
Let's see.
I'm not sure.
I feel like,
Is that the edge what?
I don't know.
I think we have some kind of weird thing.
I guess I do have some kind of weird alignment bug or something.
I feel like we shouldn't be seeing that unless we're calling this.
Are we calling this path?
Why would he be calling this path?
Though if window width is greater than equal to buffer with times to,
I feel like we shouldn't be calling that path, right?
But let's, let's find out.
Let's find out if we are not.
So I'm going to change it.
To only have an offset there.
Nope, that's it.
So we are we're calling the wrong path.
I don't know why.
Is the buffer width set to so is the buffer with is probably rounded
up now.
Or something like that.
Oh, no, it shouldn't be though.
Yeah, I don't understand.
The window width.
Is greater than, or equal to the buffer with times two.
Oh, I see it's because, actually, that's this is just the case for
stretching, which we didn't want to do and okay.
Okay.
Never mind.
I just confused there for a second.
So really?
Yeah, like really what we want to do is we need another path here
where they're equivalent.
So I'm going to go ahead and just for now, comment these out until we
do something smarter here.
So we'll just
We'll just go ahead and actually, I guess I'll do it this way.
Yeah, I was wondering what was going on there.
It's kind of annoying.
I think Chris Hecker was mentioning it to, he was, like, why are there
black bars?
And like, I, we've got the windows side code is doing some stuff.
So let's go ahead and get rid of those.
There we go.
So now as you can, you can see it correctly, that that's the yellow
boundary that we were looking at when we zoom out that just shows
where the camera is going to show.
So, you basically start to the task will foreground chunks to run
another thread, can you use this mechanism for other types of tasks as
well?
Yes, that's why I did it that way.
So we can, we can put back any kind of background tasks we want on
there.
And, of course, the renderer also runs through that same task system,
but it just doesn't need the temporary storage.
It's an immediate thing.
So that's why we never had to make any temporary storage for that.
Why not put the stuff at the top of the transient Arena into the
permanent storage ground?
Chuck bitmaps?
Because they're not really permanent, right?
They can be recreated in any time so we could actually throw them
away.
If like the operating system says, you need to go into a low memory
state or something, we can throw them away and then recreate them.
That's why the transient
Why does it flash magenta once in a while?
Is it because we're drawing without the working finished?
Yes, that was the thing.
I was saying before where we probably want to do that locking their
although technically we could just never bother doing the Locking
because our goal should be to, oh, he's cue up those regions before
they'd ever be seen.
So you would never actually get into that situation in the first
place.
But yeah, that is what's happening right now since we don't ask for
them early enough.
All right.
Looks like we're done with questions.
All right, so I will wrap things up.
I will wrap it up.
Okay, let's close down.
Close it down.
Save everybody's favorite.
If all right, thank you, everyone for joining me for another episode
of handmade here.
It's been a pleasure coding with you.
As always, we now have a bunch of things that run a multi-threaded,
and that's kind of cool.
We've shown both how to do optimization with all this reading and also
how to get rid of lag with multi-threading.
And so we kind of got both of those working now and that's pretty
cool.
And they're both working through the same.
Very very simple test system.
We built in the operating system that's just a few lines of code in
the operating system layer.
So that's very satisfying as well.
It just shows you don't need a whole lot to build.
Multi-threading, it's actually very, very simple if you just don't
over complicate things for yourself.
So
That's the good news.
The bad news is we still have more to go because we gotta go look now
at some other renderer Z staff.
So we still have more work to do before we can call our rendering
stuff done.
So we want to go work on that and that's what we will be doing
tomorrow and I hope to see you here for that.
Same time, same place, 5 p.m.
Pacific Daylight time on Twitch and I hope to see you all there.
In the meantime, if you would like to play around at home of the
source code, if you preorder the game it comes to the source code.
So if you go to handmade here at Oregon pre-order the game you can
download the source.
Go and play around with it at home, which is great for learning or
doing whatever else.
Just if you want to sort of experiment with it, go to go nuts.
Anyway, we also have a forum site.
We can go to ask questions and we can also get ports to Mac and Linux
there that community members have done.
If you're trying to do that yourself.
That's a good place to check that out.
We have a patreon page, you can go, if you want to support the video
series, you can subscribe there.
And also if you want to know what the schedule is going to be because
we're trying to catch it live, we have a tweet Bob little tweet the
schedule at you so you can go ahead and follow him and he will take
care of
Things.
Or maybe it's a her.
I don't actually know the gender of the Tweet.
But to be completely honest with you, all we really know is that it's
going to eventually become sentient.
You know, when people like Ray Kurzweil talk about the singularity
that's they're talking about the talking, about the tweetbot, the
handmade hero tweetbot, which will eventually become sentient, be able
to self modify, replicate and destroy all of mankind.
But until that happens, like I said, we'll be back here tomorrow,
coding handmade here, an event, to try to finish a nice game engine,
and a nice game on top of
Before the tweetbot becomes sentient destroys the world so I hope to
have your help for that.
I'd love to see here, have a great time until then take it easy
everyone and I will see you tomorrow.