Hello, everyone, and welcome to handmade hero.
Sure, we code a complete game live on stream.
Yesterday we did some debugging of our Z bias function among other
things, transform related and I actually learned something new.
I suppose it wasn't really something new in the sense of it was just
math that I already understood certainly, but I didn't understand it.
Deeply enough was clearly the case because
It kind of surprised me when I woke up.
I was like, oh, I never thought of that before, and it was kind of an
interesting moment.
So I highly recommend taking a look at that to bugging, if you're
interested in those sorts of things, it was pretty interesting to me.
I was like, okay, yeah, that's right.
If you want to do this either by his properly, you got to do it this
other way, not the way that I was thinking about it, which was, which
was wrong.
That's because Z is kind of a special value since it's actually
produced to work specifically with the Z buffer in a way that is.
Unlike the X and Y coordinates, since it is the one that contributes
to the W term, so you can't really think of Z the same as you think of
it as X and W even though obviously they'll go through the Matrix.
The same way when you're just like conceptualizing it because it's the
one that determines the prospective divide amount.
There's a there's consequences there when you follow the math through
that.
If you haven't done it yet, haven't tried to do Z biasing yet.
You may not have thought of.
So that's been interesting.
Today, we're just going to take a look at
Couple things one, we're going to probably play with the shaders, a
little, just to sort of show, how to get some effects back that we
wanted to get back.
And then another thing that we'd like to do is we'd like to get back
the ability to work with the camera properly.
And this is something that I guess we've never really had in handmade
hero.
We've always kind of just hacked the camera, and now that we're in
full 3d, I think we want to pretty soon enough time to get to it
today, probably not, if you're playing with shaders too much but
We want to get to the point where the camera movement is very logical
and clean and now that we're in 3D, we have a pretty easy way to do
that.
We can just have our room definitions in the game.
As we do now, specify sort of where the camera should be.
And then we can just interpolate the camera to be at those locations
as necessary.
And so, I think we can make a nice clean camera setup.
Now that we have sort of, a more coherent idea of where things are and
what they are in space anyway, I don't know if we'll get that today,
that might be a next weekend thing, but today is day, 375.
So, if you want to follow along with what we're doing today, you want
to start with a 37.
84 in terms of source code, let me go ahead and load up for coder
here.
And I'm going to go ahead and open the project.
Let's go ahead and compile, and you can see that where we left off,
we've got sort of this, this two layer situation going on here.
And if I switch the debug camera and pull out
You can see we've sort of got two stacks of rooms on each other and
the top room, we allow rooms of what other sizes here.
So, you know, these rooms are just kind of generically created and the
room right now on top, is a little bit bigger than the room on the
bottom.
Now what I'm going to do just just for our sort of use with the Shader
situation that I was just discussing is when we actually do the screen
count here,
I'm going to just stack up a bunch of rooms on top of each other.
That just keep going down.
Ad infinitum.
So if you take a look at what we've got here, you can see, we've just
got a stack of rooms that goes down.
It goes down 10, actual rooms deep, but at the moment, we're only
drawing four of them because the simulation region only picks up that
deeps worth of rooms, right?
But if I were to actually go down, we would pick up another room so if
I was to, you know, kind of go down here now we don't have a way of
going down at the moment.
I think we took those stairwell situation.
Out.
I think we could probably now put stairwells back in, but we haven't
really taken too much of a look at that.
So we'll have to play a little around a little bit more with that for
now.
Anyway, all I really want to do here is observe the fact that when I'm
looking at this, you can kind of see that I've got this hole here, and
there's some, you know, some stuff going on below here.
And you know, that's, that's this part of the room down there, right?
And what we can sort of also see is this
Room doesn't itself have a hole there and I would like it to have a
hole there.
So again, I'm just going to hack are really crappy temp room,
Generation stuff here.
To always have one.
Where is that 0 standard rooms?
What I'm looking for.
Sorry, not simple room.
So here's the ad standard room, call and inside.
Here, you could see us kind of going through it and we have this like
left hole right whole thing.
I'm just going to stuff left hole to be one always
I mean, I suppose why not might as well just put both on there?
And so, now you can see down more levels, right?
You can see, we've got one, two, three, four levels of you here.
And this is the sort of standard camera angle.
I can pull back more.
You can kind of see what's going on here but now there's like you know
there's a hole that goes kind of straight through it there for
whatever that's worth right.
And you can kind of see some stuff that we're going to now have to
start to clean up and this is good because we want to start a fuck.
Start to finalize all these parts of the code.
You can notice, if you look down at the bottom here, you can.
Can see that this room here.
Only some of the of the actual tiles are present in the room, right?
You can see that and you might like, like fours,
There's a tree here, but there's nothing under the tree, right?
The tree does not actually possess a block underneath it and like, how
is that possible?
And the answer is because our room, you know, our simulation region
only extends down to about like here.
So anything that's below that won't get picked up so any entities that
comprise the floor, I'm sorry.
But that is that correct?
That's not the correct usage.
Comprise is it?
I never know.
Let's just, let's just pause for one second.
Yeah, if that's the wrong, use of comprised.
So pretend I didn't say that.
What I what I should have said, is the floor is comprised of these
blocks that would have been a proper usage.
When I said the the blocks that comprise the floor that's the
incorrect usage of comprised so don't do that.
That was just a bad idea.
Anyway.
So basically what happens here is that we get up, we pull in the stuff
to the simulation region, we don't pull in Far Enough down and get all
these.
Now that's not necessarily a problem, but it's something that just to
be aware of.
We may want to move to a more room Centric model in terms of what we
pull in.
You know, we've got a flexibility there and we need to start
finalizing how that stuff works.
As we move into gameplay code, we don't want a lot of that stuff up in
the air, probably
so what I'm going to look at today is before, if you remember, we have
the ability to have this stuff down here, have sort of a distance
based fog to it, whereas, you got further down, you ended up with, you
know, these these rooms below us were darkening out, and they would go
out to like the gray, this gray background color, for example,
these things would kind of fade out to that color and the way that we
had to do that was very tortured and strange, if you remember, it was
this sort of really error-prone procedure of actually bucketing
entities in the entity render Loop into which room
We thought they were in and setting their color to that to the like to
be modulated so that it was going to fade to Grey and each slice of
the room faded to gray at a different level, right?
So each one of each
Room slice, as you went down, would set it to a different color,
right?
So we'd end up with this one up here being full color.
This one would be a little grayer.
This would be a little gray.
This one would be completely great out, right?
And then as you move down, they would, you know, reduce those grade
levels.
Now, thankfully for us, we now have a full 3d pipeline in place, which
means we can do a lot more stuff there.
We don't have to be.
So constrained, as we were to just listen colors at the head end
because we actually know the depth of everything now.
So we know actually how deep each of these things is on the screen,
right?
We know basically the the distance from the camera, if you will.
Because in order to implement the z-buffer, we needed to know that.
So the Z buffer is, if you think about it, a literal encoding of how
far everything is from the camera, that's exactly what it means,
right?
And I don't really know, you know, I don't suppose there's any good
way to do this, just because we don't have the ability.
At the moment to do any kind of frame capture here.
That would be really great if we could but at the moment I don't we
can't.
And so we don't have, you know, any sort of way to to look at what the
depth buffer is.
Now we could try in the opengl renderer, I don't know.
It'd probably be too much of a waste of time to do this but we've got
this depth attachment here.
And it's this text handle one that were looking at here, right?
And this Frame buffer gets gets this this texture handle what we could
do is is actually resolve that texture handle instead, and
unfortunately I would be negative 1 to 1, which would mean it wouldn't
quite look right.
But we could try it.
Let me just see, right?
If I can
If I can do that, just just to give you an idea, I don't think it's
going to work but you know I might as well.
Try it quickly just in case.
so we've got these Global frame buffer handles here and I think
when we do the blit frame buffer.
Yeah.
So we're not really, hmm.
So I'm just trying to think if there's any real wages.
I think maybe if I did an open Jill rectangle I could this does their
resolve but the resolve doesn't really yeah.
It doesn't really help us with the depth part of things.
So if we did here, if we had the frame buffer, I don't know if depth
buffer bit, I don't think, I think the problem if I do depth buffer
bit here, it would just lit the depth buffer to the other depth
buffer.
I don't think it's going to it would not blit the depth buffer to the
color buffer, right?
Just take a quick look here.
But it would be nice to be able to show.
Oops.
It would be able to nice to be able to show.
If you've, if you're on a machine that's at all modern, you can run
something like render dock or nvidia's, and site and this would work,
but you could just, you could just view the depth buffer in there.
But I was taken from the read buffer of the read frame, buffer and
written to the draw buffers of the draw frame buffer.
So I wonder if I could just swap them swap out the
I think I could probably just swap these around, maybe that could
work.
So if I look in here,
so we've got Global frame, buffer textures.
Right.
And you can see us storing that one.
If I just do Global frame, buffer textures here.
Can store this in theory, I could do something.
Like this.
Maybe.
I am totally making this up just in case anyone was wondering.
I have no idea if this will work at all.
So if I went ahead and said, okay, the depth attachment for this thing
is nothing.
Right.
So, in here, I basically said, okay, the depth attachment is nothing
the color attachment.
Is going to be the depth buffer that we were previous rain to as if it
was depth, right?
Then what we're going to do is do the do the blit to the screen so
that it will read out of this Global depth over here.
And then what I'll do is I'll swap them back.
Right, so I'll just say, like, okay, yeah, now that you did that.
Thank you.
That's good.
Let's go ahead and
And reroute that.
Now, I don't expect this to work at all but I figured it was worth a
5.
Second try, right.
It's not sure.
I totally understood that error message.
Oops and I accidentally have pinned it GL frame.
Buffer texture to do failed because the image cannot be attached to
the referenced attachment point.
That's unfortunate.
How do I undo?
How do I get this out of here?
There it is.
Nope, there we go.
All right.
So that's giving me an error on this one here.
So the depth buffer can't be attached to the color attachment.
It looks like
I guess so I guess there's really no way to do this without actually
invoke invoking.
A Shader call here.
I guess, you know, we definitely could read from this in a Shader.
I guess we just can't read from it here.
Although it since it's a multi sample, I would have thought we would
have had to resolve it.
Although maybe what we'd have to do is, do the do the frame buffer, do
the blitz flame effort to resolve it?
And then read from the depth of her, I guess, I'm not sure.
It's a good question.
All right.
Well,
so much for that.
All I will say is at some point, if I can upgrade this machine or
something to a machine that can have a capture program on it, it's
pretty easy to you don't have to do what I'm doing here.
A lot of times it's, you know, building in debug stuff into your code
where you can visualize stuff like the depth, buffer is always good.
But there's actually tools that can do this for you now so that you
don't have to do you know, instrument your code all the time with
stuff like that.
Try to get it working because what you can do if you have rendered
duck or nsight is you can just run the program under those and they
will capture a frame for you and then they will allow you to inspect
your textures.
And so since
Since we just have those textures right there that represent the depth
buffer, you can just click on them in the program and it will show
you.
I'm not going to waste any time trying to get that working.
I know we could we just have to figure out the right path of like
resolved and then then we probably have to draw a rectangle to the
screen that had the texture on it.
That converted the depth values over to color values and so on we
could definitely do it.
So it's possible in here it's just probably a little time consuming
Anyway.
We can do the same thing and what we want here, you know, is very
similar to a death buffer, right?
If we want to
Out of have that Fade Out effect happen.
What we really need is, just some way of figuring out how, you know,
far away.
Something is from the camera when we're drawing, and changing its
color based on that.
And now that we have access to shaders, that's not particularly
difficult for us to do.
Right here is our vertex code for example.
And what you can see in the vertex code, is that the vertex code right
now, sends down the color, that's just whatever we specified.
So, whenever we push the bitmap on.
Remember, we're specifying some colors,
It just sends down one color per vertex and that color per vertex is
passed directly through that color.
Then gets modulated here with the texture to produce the final color.
It's very straightforward.
And so if we want to modify how this color is being computed, we could
and we could certainly use the Z value at this point to do.
So because if you look at what happens here, we have access, not only
to the world z but also to the transform Z.
So if you take a look at what's passing here, we have the modified Z
value, that modified Z value is in Clips base.
So this modified Z value is a value from negative 1 to 1 that tells us
how deep we are and furthermore that modified Z
Right.
Actually.
That's sorry.
That's not quite true.
This is not from negative one to one yet because it hasn't been
divided, right?
If we were to divide it by Zeman transform, then it would be from
negative 1 to 1, right?
So all we really have to do is decide where we want this fog in our
current setup, right?
We just need to produce some function that says for the distance away
from the camera and perhaps do it in Clips face, right?
How, you know, for this distance of the camera, what do we actually,
what do we want this fog to look like, like, what's the curve that we
want the fog to look like?
And we can have a linear fall-off for the curve.
We could have a, you know, exponential fall off.
The curb could do whatever we want.
But basically we just need some way of computing, a fog, darkening
value, so
Really, what we're talking about here, you're the days.
375, is we want something where you've got the distance from the
camera, right?
And then you've got some color value here, which is, you know, I guess
we would say fog amount.
Going up, maybe I should put that over here.
And so, you know, we could say that zero is no fog and one is full
fog.
So one is like just the color of fog you would see nothing you just
see gray and 0.
Is a mix between the two and calling it fog in quotes here because
really, we're just talking about a distance fade.
Just an effect.
We're trying to have we're not really trying to say that it is fog
because fog is a separate physical phenomena that we might want to
simulate in specific ways.
We're looking down on things and you don't typically have fog looking
down on things so it's more like dust or like just you know we're
talking just more about a generic effect that's used to distinguish
layers of the level from other layers which does not necessarily imply
that we're trying to simulate actual fog because
Actual fog would be a separate thing that has a bunch of physical
properties that we would want to study before we went trying to do it.
So this is not, this is fog and quotes not fog in the real world.
So, you know, at first, let's just do this kind of basic thing, right?
Let's just do something that looks like this where we say, like, as
the distance gets greater, the fog gets greater and that's really all
we need to know, right?
And we could do this in a number of spaces, we can do this in World
space.
We could do this in camera space.
We could do whatever I want.
I'm going to say, let's do it in World space.
Why?
Because it's the cleanest thing for us to represent really.
It doesn't require any sort of thinking on the part of the user, the
user can just specify fog values in a very straightforward way and off
you go and this procedure will be almost exactly the same thinking as
we were doing with the transform when we did on Project, right?
So what we want to do is we want to try and map this onto the camera
somewhere
so, if this is our camera,
And this is the getting, you know, further away farther.
This is getting
further away here.
What we want to do is say well you know in between here and here let's
say is maybe, you know, not fog.
Right?
Because we don't really want this is again, this is not supposed to be
an effect of physical fog effect.
It was a physical fog effect would probably want, you know, particles
or something to tell us where it was.
But this is more of a depth cueing.
It's a depth cueing effect for the players so they can tell the
difference between different levels of the game, different levels of
the room, right?
So in the levels that's right in front of them, we don't really want
to fog it because we want them to see that level as it is.
And so what we really want is sort of a start and end, right?
What we want is sort of a distance where the fog starts, right?
And maybe I'll call this fog start and fog and right.
And so what I want to do is I want to Define distances preferably in
World space, right?
where,
It's like the fog start distance is from here to here and the fog and
distance is from here to here.
So we kind of know how far away from the camera.
The fog starts and how far away the ends.
We would then do a standard, you know, just T mapping like we do in
the game all the time.
Where we'd say, all right.
Let's measure the distance from the camera, right?
So we have some point.
Let's figure out where it is on the distance from the camera.
And let's compare that to this range.
Let's say, let's put it into this range.
If it's on this side of this range, we won't fog it.
If it's on this side of this range, we will fa get completely.
And if it's anywhere inside the range then we will map it to an amount
of fog proportional to how far it has gone.
Right?
And at the moment we won't actually do any kind of curve here.
But once we have this as a t-value, right?
That's telling us how far in between there.
We are we could pull plug it through any kind of function that we
want.
If we later wish to have something, you know, wacky going on in terms
of how the fog gets interpolated, because we think it's better, or who
knows, what?
But for right now, we'll just have it be linear fog.
So the further away you are the more
Fog, you are directly.
There's no sort of
There's there's no modification to how that falls off, if that makes
sense.
So if you think about what would happen here to do that, what we
really want to do is inside this camera, transform?
Right.
We kind of have the information that we need already and so in a sense
really we probably don't need to pass very much down but we will need
to do a couple additional things.
Just to give us the information.
We need to produce the results from the fog, right?
So the basic things we're going to need here is a fog color, right?
And then when we when we're down here, producing our fraud color, what
we're going to want to do is we're going to want to do our sort of our
lerp Command, right?
So you remember, we've got this lip command here and we've got 80 be
where we're going from one thing to another thing.
So we want to go from the vertex color based on the T fog which is
we're going to compute the higher that gets.
We're going to go more towards a fog.
Color right.
So we're going to Loop between these two.
Now we have a problem which is that we defined this lerp function,
right?
And so one thing we could do here, if we wanted to is we could just
implement this.
This in the Shader we could literally copy and paste this and change
this, you know, remove the inline, but otherwise it Shader code is
very close to C code.
We could actually just put this indirectly, right?
But it just so happens that that lerp because it's such a common
function in
Graphics.
Remember I said it was like the one function.
I'd take to a desert island with me because you need it for basically
everything in games.
Lerp actually is built-in.
It's just not called lerp and so I guess I don't have that quick runs
up.
It's actually called mix.
So hold on a second.
Let me let me show you that we are sorry, glsl quick reference card.
So this is a remember I showed you you guys this before, but you
should probably always have it up.
I just tend to close it for whatever reason, you can see all the
built-in functions that you have to work with here.
And this one right here is the one I'm talking about.
It's called mix and you can see that it kind of has a couple of
different versions here, you can look at, you can also see that
they've got some other versions.
So, mix is a linear blend.
They also have
Step, which is like, a, you know, sort of a curve that looks like this
and then there's step which is just the hard Edge.
So, they actually have some, some built-in sort of curves that you can
play with that.
You don't have to implement yourself whether there any faster than
employing themselves, depends greatly probably on the hardware,
because a lot of times our Hardware probably just expands us out to
the actual linear blend code.
I don't know that there's a lot of direct Shader support for it
necessarily.
but if there was
You would get it.
So, you know, if it does what you want better to use the built-in
probably because the built-ins always going to have the greatest
chance of being actually implemented in the hardware and some fast
way.
You know, the only time that isn't true is if you're going to do
something approximated.
So for example you know if you're going to call sign or something and
maybe this Hardware or a lot of Harvard doesn't have really much in
the way of sign.
Maybe you need to do some kind of approximate sign or something like
this, you know?
Those are usually the only times is if you if you suspect that you
need a very approximated value, that is going to be significantly
worse than what the Shader is required to produce.
Then maybe in that case you know don't call the built-in but for
something as simple as lerp you pretty much always want to call the
built-in.
Because it's I mean at least as far as I've ever experienced gonna be
the most reasonable way to ensure that the compiler knows exactly what
to do to get you the right thing on that platform.
So in our header code here, all I'm going to do is I'm just going to
Define so that we can still use our own terms everywhere in the code,
including in shaders.
I'm just going to pound to find some stuff up here.
And so, some of the things we can do.
For example, is we can Define our RF 32 to be float.
So now we can actually make these BF 32s, right?
Furthermore, we can Define all of our Vector ideas to be there, Vector
ideas,
Right.
So that's pretty handy as well.
So now, these will actually look like our code rather than their code
and that's kind of nice because then you can cut and paste in between
your shaders and your C code and it mostly just works, right?
You'll notice that pretty much everything here would just work, and in
fact, it will work even more if we do something like this.
So now we can even use our initialization style, right?
And that's pretty nice as well.
So, yeah, if you start to look at this, you can see it.
Kind of just looks like our code now, which is nice.
And then there's a lip here.
And we just need to define the lerp, in our lerp.
We structure it, ATB they have mix and you can see, mix is actually
different.
It's a becomes first.
And then, the T value comes last.
Actually, you probably can't see that because it's too darn small.
Let me go ahead and make it a little bit larger there so you can see
it.
So, this is what we're talking about here.
You can see there's an X and Y, and a, and the a value is the one that
we're talking about here.
So you can do whatever you want.
Here, vectors or floating Point values mix.
Accepts them all.
So you just need some tea, you just need two things of the same type,
and then a t-value to blend between them.
So we want to change it from a TB to ABT and then the lerp is lined up
properly.
And what we
Right now is to calculate that t fog value.
Now, to start off with, I'm not going to do any fucking at all.
I'm just going to leave it, you know, on modified their.
Oops, did I do wrong?
I was gonna say,
So that we can verify that everything.
Is working properly, but I have, I have committed some egregious
error.
I suppose it may be because this value is not being bound, although we
should have got a compilation error there.
Yeah.
So what did I don't think I did anything there.
Did I
I should also probably do this.
All I did was change these pound.
Defiance, I didn't think I did anything, particularly weird here.
We've got this slurp to the fog color but the tea fog value is 0.
I think I put these in the right order for mix ABT.
I assume it goes from A to B.
I guess.
I don't actually know that that's true.
If that wasn't true, I suppose that would do it.
So I guess I should probably test that.
Let me just take a look at what the mix.
Is.
so, if I take a look in here with the mix value actually does,
It doesn't actually tell me which direction mix goes.
So let me just double check that before I go any further.
Mix performs a linear interpolation between X and Y.
Using a two-way between them, their terms of icelanders x times 1
minus a plus y times.
A that's so that is what I thought.
So I would have assumed that that would have worked nicely.
I'll go ahead and pull this out for a moment.
Just to see if I did something else horribly wrong.
There we go.
So I've done something weird.
I'm just not sure what.
So if I go ahead and Skip fog color here and say instead that I've got
a tea fog value like so and then I've got a fog color value and let's
just say that that fog color value is 1 1 1, if I was then to lerp
between them using the T fog value, I would expect that vert color to
just stay what it was because this is zero and so whatever.
I put here for fog color should just not have any effect, right?
So let's see.
We got an error here.
So let's take a look error message.
Undeclared in Far fog color.
Is that true?
Oh yeah.
That is kind of true.
There we go.
So that's fine.
So the problem was just that when I put it up here it was not so fine.
You know what to, this is going to be uniform.
So that's the incorrect vertex stream value so that probably could
have caused some bad things.
Yeah, there we go.
Sorry, uniforms are things you set once as we discussed before and in
values are ones that are actually coming from the vertex stream.
And we're obviously not supplying a fog color per vertex.
We're just applying a fog color generically
All right, so if we continue now now on here.
Now we can also say like all right.
If we wanted to again, we could just replace fog color with something
like white here and then what we could do or actually, you know what,
I'll just I'll just use a gray for the time being and then if we
wanted to again, we could just test this by blending halfway and now
we should see our game kind of
Can by that amount.
What's the can't modify you from?
All right, fine.
Why you can't modify any?
I have no idea.
So, here you can see us blending between these two colors, right?
So, we've basically combined the two and that's a little bit odd only
because
Looking at that, it for whatever reason, the cubes seem to be fogged,
much more aggressively than the bitmaps are, which I'm not sure why,
that would be right?
So, when reading from,
When reading from a texture, that's not 1111.
We're kind of getting a very different result there than when we are
not doing that.
I'm not sure why that would be right.
That's let me just crank that up to a full one value so that it's
literally completely fog.
Yeah.
So that's kind of weird, right?
Like we should be seeing everybody getting completely fogged but we're
actually not
Seeing everybody get completely fogged.
Oh,
Don't know why.
The fog color is Alpha value would be different.
So the fact that there's the, the bitmaps come through with no
apparent modification, doesn't make a lot of sense to me because
here's the texture sample, right?
Where we're taking that samp, the color value from the texture that
comes out into text sample.
And you can see that what we're doing with that is, you know, we
Square it.
If we have
If we don't have the srgb, we should have the srgb.
So the squaring shouldn't be happening.
So we're just taking the texture sample which will have been mapped to
linear Colour space where then taking the result color as being,
whatever the fragments color was times the texture sample.
And then that's what we output directly now.
The weird part about that is, you know, the frag color here, right
should be the same for everybody, right?
I mean, we're taking whatever the vertex color is.
And we're producing.
a blend between them now, I assume
and I guess I don't know, but if I was just to assign, oops, if I was
just to assign the frag color,
As the fog color itself then you know I would have expected.
What is it talking about?
Geo and able vertex, array a tributary parameter index has an invalid
value of 0xffff.
Oh really?
ah,
so if I never use the, the vert color then it doesn't need to be
specified.
That's kind of unfortunate because it's like, okay, I'm still
specifying here.
I'm just trying to do some debugging to keep that out of here.
I suppose we probably can run with that error.
I can just set the next statement to here.
But it's going to happen every time, right?
Yeah.
So I pretty much have to have a way around that.
I guess what I could do is try to pretend that it was being used, but
I don't know how I could really do that.
Like, you know, if I sign to it here like so it's probably going to
get optimized out by the compiler, because the compiler is going to
know that it gets overwritten by fog color.
So you're still going to probably get the same thing.
Oh no.
OK, there we are.
So here we are doing our bitmap drawing, right, and you can kind of
see that we're getting even though I'm setting the fragment color
specifically to what the fog is.
In this case we're getting it, modulated there?
Okay.
Start, I think about that's actually not wrong though.
So I think that's actually not incorrect.
Now, I think about it so because there's no textures on the cube
though the cube will always just be what the frag color is.
And so since it's modulated, since we're multiplying the two together,
I guess that's actually exactly what you would expect to have happen.
Maybe it's just a slow morning.
I'm not sure why I thought that was wrong.
Because yeah, if we replace the fog, if we are entirely at fog color,
right?
Then it just means we're going to get half values for everything.
So what I really want is not exactly that, right.
What I really want to do here is I want to have something that will
completely replace these values and that's not what this modulation is
going to do for me, right?
So I really need more information in here in order to do
This work properly, I suppose, I could do the lerp directly in the
pixel Shader, which seems a little bit more expensive.
But, you know, it's and I probably could do it be a little more clever
and not have that happen.
but basically what that would involve is me saying, well, okay, so
there's a fragment color here and there's also, you know,
Oops, there's also a fog color.
The fog color would actually be in here.
Right?
And so, then addition to the fog color, we just say like, okay, we've
got a smooth in F32, that's going to be the fog amount and then we
would actually do the lerp in here.
So we do our frag color times, our texture sample and Wheeler pin here
and say, okay, that is going to go from T fog to fog color.
Like so right, we then have the fog color defined in here because
again we're not going to specify quite yet.
Although eventually what we'll do is we'll pass it in from the
outside.
Outside.
And then in here, we're just determining what the actual tea fog value
is.
And so we're going to pass that value from the vertex Shader to the
pixel Shader through one of these interpolators.
Right?
So we have a smooth out, fog amount in that corresponds to the flute
fog amount smooth in here.
So it comes, you know, it gets assigned here and then that means the
fragment color is still just a Vertex color and we don't touch it.
And this, this is, you know, we could also call it frag fog, but we
don't have to keep calling it frag and
nothing.
If we don't want to, that's just sort of the convention, I had
adopted.
And so then our lerp will be done in the pixel Shader and we could do
whatever we want.
Their we could you know, after we get the the Texel
Know what was going on there.
Under credit party fog, that's true.
Here we go.
And so this is now what I would expect to see.
And so now if I change the fog amount to something else,
I should get less of it.
Perfect.
Okay, so now we've got more what I actually wanted for fog and that's
all good.
However, I still need.
Now, a way to make that fog, be based on how far away you are from the
camera.
So, what I need to do is I need to compute compute, fog amount in some
reasonable way.
Right now, I know that the Z axis
I know where the z-axis is in this transform, right?
Because I know that it's the third row of the of the transform
normally.
However, it's already been modified with the it's already been
smooshed down in the projection Matrix and all these others.
Two things.
And it's relatively cheap for me to specify uniforms here because we
only have true to draw calls total
I think something like that.
I'm not to dropped calls two batches program changes.
so I think I'm just going to keep things simple for now rather than
prematurely optimize anything and just say, look
What I need is a fog start.
I guess I could just do a camera p and then I need a fog start.
Distance.
In a fog end distance.
I then need a vector to measure along.
And that should be my complete.
That's all I really need for fog, right?
I need to know where I am.
I need to know the direction along which I'm measuring.
And I need to know how far the start and the end are right.
So now it's very simple to measure this.
Again, this is just a set it a billion times on handmade hero, so I'm
not going to say it on the on the Blackboard again, you should just
know how to do this operation.
This is when we've done many many many times, right?
We know the location of the vertex, right?
It's going to be and we probably want to use RZ biased one.
So that, you know, the fake Z coordinate, is the one we actually use.
So we have our Z vertex here.
What we want to do is take our xever, Texas XYZ coordinate, right?
We want to figure out how far along that axis it is.
So, first of all, we're going to say, let's subtract the camera
location, right?
So, that gives us a vector from the camera to the vertex
Then we want to dot product it, right?
And you know I don't know what they called.
A proctor shaders welcomes.
I think it's just dot but I'm going to Define it to be ours.
We want a DOT product that with the direction, you know, so that now
we've measured along this direction that will give us.
Because again, remember a b cosine Theta, that will give us how far
along this fog direction.
We are assuming the fogger X is unit length, which of course, we will
always make it because we're specifying it ourselves.
So that's our distance and then we now know that we have some value.
That's how far along that you are.
We just need to map it in between these two, right?
And again they actually have I think the function we want, here's the
clamp.
Let's see.
Do they have one that does a clamp plus normalize?
I don't know if they do.
It does not look.
Like they do.
At least I don't see it.
So I'm going to guess that they don't just because I don't see it.
So we're going to have to implement clamp the clamp range stuff
ourselves as far as I can tell, because they do have the basic clamp,
so we can, we can do the initial clamp correctly, but we can't turn it
into a value between 0 and 1 correctly as far as you can.
So, although well,
This sort of does it, although we don't really want.
The smooth part is the only problem.
Yeah, so I don't know I don't see it there.
So I'm going to assume that they don't have it because I don't see.
I don't see it.
So we're going to need our this is the clamp normalized map to range,
right?
This one.
So we need to implement this function because we don't really have it
yet.
So it's not really a pound of fine like these other ones were.
So we want to basically put this again in our header code so our
shaders can use it.
So here's our F 32 F 3 to F 32.
And we got to implement this.
This sausage gentlemen.
We're going to use the same code here, but we can do it a little bit
fancier, right?
Because clamp 021 does actually exist.
In a sense.
So if we want to, we can do clamp 0 to 1 that can be defined, you
know, that takes a t-value and that just issues there clamp command.
However, what is it?
Clamp min max.
So, it's been Max, right?
And then clamp, which is our clamp
Is min T Max.
Or I guess I should say.
Yes, I'm leaving these location now.
That's a clamp T min max, right?
So I think in this case we probably don't want to bother checking the
range here because we'll just assume that in shaders.
We since we're trying to do performant code here, we're not going to
be passing down ranges that don't have anything in them.
So we're just going to assume
that this works.
And so now we've got a clamp map to range which is going to work just
fine for our purposes.
It just basically does the divide and re-centering, so there's our
clamps are to unmapped arranged.
So now what we should be able to do is say, well, this whatever this
value here is what?
Well you know let's let's do it here.
Let's just call this fog distance.
and then we can say that the fog amount
Is this going to be a clamp map to range?
And that range that were using here is the fog start distance, and the
fog and distance, right?
And so that should just do it.
The problem now is that we're not actually specifying any of these
uniforms, right?
So we don't actually have the ability to do anything.
Now, if I run this, I should get nonsense results because we don't
actually have any of those uniform specified, right?
Let's fix our compiler errors.
Oh yeah, inner.
We've got a
Fine.
So let's take a look at what the dot product is inner.
Maybe think it's just not a b but I'm not sure.
Yeah.a be.
Okay, so I'm going to go ahead and assume that nothing is incorrect
there.
Although we don't know, there might be other incorrect things in there
but we don't haven't specified any of this stuff and we need to start
specifying this stuff.
So let's start by look wiring that stuff up because that's something
that we're going to have to do regardless and then we'll debug
anything.
That might also be buggy in addition.
So you can see, we've got all these get a trip location on census
here.
That's fine because we can just go ahead and
Exact same thing.
So, in terms of all of these values, wait, this is not its uniform.
These are uniforms not verdict.
AB, there we go.
So now we just need for our basic Z bias program.
We now need to just pass these down again.
These are actually in the fragment Shader but we're asking for them in
the program in general, because you asked for uniform locations for
the final compiled result.
Not for individual shaders, but rather for the linked version.
So we want
We're all of this stuff.
Is we want to know where the camera p is.
We want to know where the fog direction is.
Oops, we want to know where the fog start distances.
And we want to know where the fog and the distance is.
And that's really all we're doing here.
And then once we've got these obviously, I need to have these
In here, so we can store them.
There we go.
Once we've got these, we just need to actually set them to something.
So when we actually turn on that program and you can see us doing
that, right here, we've set up.
One uniform are sorry to uniforms one for the Matrix, one for the, the
texture, sampler.
All we really need to do now is just set them all to stuff that we
want, right?
And the hardest part here is just us, it's going to be the routing is
figuring out how to get that information in here.
alright, so here's our
our problem, right?
We don't know where that's going.
Fog direction is what a1f I think.
No, it was a 3F.
This is the one f.
Start distance.
And as you can see, our problem here is like we need some way to
figure out where this stuff is going to come from now.
if you've ever,
If you've ever tried doing like, say like you have like a television
or something, I guess maybe you have telephone cable or something like
this.
in the real world, I've seen, like, for example, the apartment that I
live in now,
And they I see this very commonly now in New they build new buildings
in Seattle.
I think this
How they build them because they figure everyone has like a fancy
entertainment center or something.
So what they do is you've got some kind of a conduit through the wall
that wires run and you know maybe the telephone cable runs through
there in some cases or stuff like that or in a television station of
the HDMI cable runs through or whatever.
And it's very hard to like get stuff through there, right?
It's hard to like put things through these conduits.
So, one of the things that you'll often do is, if you already have one
cable through there, what you'll do is you unplug that cable and you
tie two or three cables to it, then you pull it through and it pulls
all the cables through.
And then now you've got more cables going through the conduit, right?
It's kind of this, like, cheap way to thread things through
And so if you want to do something like that, or use string or
whatever, you know, what you're doing is based saying, well I've
already got one.
I already know how to get one thing through here.
It's already through there.
Let me just like sort of piggyback these other things on the route it
took.
So I don't have to try and figure it out again.
Like open up this wall and lay a new thing or whatever.
I'm just going to use its path, right?
That's not too similar to the situation.
We have right now.
So what we're looking at here in our render group, right?
Is we have this idea of a clip rect which now is not really a
cliprect, right?
And you can see we've got a note here to rename it specifically
because it's become more than a clip.
Rect you can see that we've got essentially the conduit that we want
is this thing because it's like for example where we get our camera
transform and obviously the fog setup and the camera transform, our
kind of intimately linked together.
They're going to be basically the same
Thing.
right, so when you look at that,
It starts to make some good sense that render entry clip.
Rect is kind of more like a setup for this textured quads, right?
It's more like what this is going to do.
And what's interesting about that is, at this point, it's starting to
look more like we really don't need these two things, right?
It looks more like we don't really need the clip rect and the these to
be different because the only reason that we had to specify clip Rex
in the first place as separate entities, a separate entries into the
render stream was because we had to specify one primitive of time like
one bitmap at a time, right?
But if we wanted to now, we could simplify all of this stuff down.
By just saying the render entry textured quads is the only thing that
we really specify to the renderer.
For the most part, we've got this rendering to blend Target situation
that we are not really using any more.
We might bring it back at some point, but for the moment and even if
we did, it's so infrequent it could specify everything it needed in
there as well.
It starts to become a question about like, wait a minute, why are we
even having this as a separate thing, right?
Look, why do we even have all this nonsense?
That's happening to check whether clip brakes are the same and all
this stuff.
This is all just cruft at this point, right?
It's all just crufty and instead what we could do is just have this
batch which is this thing right here just specify everything it needs
and then the batch is just very large, right?
Because the batches are very large now they're like there's only two
of them.
So I mean large is relative term, but I mean, in terms of how many of
our Primitives we fit per batch.
It's a large number
So what I think I'm going to do first is I'm going to piggyback this
information on the clip.
Rect and then what I'm going to do is ask the cliprect by merging it
up into the render at your text, would quads.
And then we'll be able to simplify that system even further, which is
always good news, in my opinion, right?
I also don't know, is any of this stuff, is any of this stuff anything
anymore at all?
I don't think it actually is, for example, does anyone even use these?
I'm curious.
The answer is no.
The answer is still, no, this is all just a craft that we had in there
at one point and got rid of right.
And so you can kind of see where we're going with this, right?
And eventually, what that means is our renderer can be simplified
dramatically at that point because we'll end up having probably just
only like, two things like particle systems and bitmaps, right?
Or we could even just have one thing.
And in that thing, it just has a Boolean that says, are you changing
textures per entity or not, right?
Because that's the only difference now between our between
What are particles might want to do and what our batches of regular
quads would want to do is, it's just that, right?
That's the only real difference there.
So, yeah.
All right.
So let's take a look at the stuff here and by the way there's another
kind of nice aspect of specifying these separate from the viewing
Matrix in addition to just it being a little bit easier to understand
for us so that we don't have to try and reverse engineer stuff from a
matrix that may have had multiple things amongst into it.
We can be more direct and it's easier to determine whether we've done
it correctly or not.
In.
That's at a Simplicity there's actually another benefit which is that.
Now we can view the world from different directions and see the fog as
it was coming from another Direction.
And again, that helps with the debug view, it means that we can leave
the fog.
So that the fog always comes from the game camera even as we view from
a debug camera.
So that allows us again to have that dual specification, which eases
development, so that we can inspect things more closely without
changing them as respecting.
We're not going to Heisenberg them as we go.
So,
Let's go ahead and put in what we need here, right?
We need a camera P fog Direction.
Bugs, start distance and a fog and distance.
That's what we actually need in the clip.
Rect
and then in here, what I'm going to do is say okay, those are all
going to come from the the current cliprect what we want here, where
we've got this clip, rect index.
And we pull that out.
What I'd like to do is just always have that around, right?
So you know I want to be able to access that cliprect it in its
entirety here and I think I can do that.
Pretty clearly there.
So then what I'm going to do is I'm going to in here I'm going to just
Ask for this pieces and will soon.
We'll fill them in.
In the render group.
So there's that fog Direction.
Fuck spits.
I'm just pulling them out of this structure here.
Like, so,
There we go.
And I think that's all good.
Now, we don't have any of these uniform functions and that's fine.
We'll just grab them from core ARB and I think we're mostly we should
hopefully be roughly at the end of the stuff that we need from crore.
Because now we're pretty much able to specify most of the things that
we want to specify.
Famous last words, I guess.
Let's jump down here, do do there we go.
So you can see all these things here.
I don't really care too much about
Some of these.
But let's just grab these guys here.
and this guy,
I sense that usually maps to the way you would way we would most
easily call them.
Those are the ones that I'll pick.
and then in here, we'll just do type
and I think we're good.
Alright, so here we've got these other ones.
We've got the 1f.
We've got the oops.
That's not where I want to do that.
Want to do it here.
So, GL uniform, what f?
And then I had to fv3 FV and 4fv, right?
What is the complaint here?
Redefinition.
Oh, we've already got four.
Fe
We do already have for Fe never mind.
So I don't need that.
When I just need those other in between ones.
All right.
And it wants to know how many vectors we have in that array.
And in this case, we have one
Cannot convert, argument to type float.
Yeah.
And so now we just need to actually get those.
So what we want to do here is again just where we're doing.
Our, we will get proc address stuff.
Oops, that's in winter, too.
Not there, there it is.
So, what we want to do here is just use our little helper macro there,
which is very handy.
I should transform all of these to that.
Now, that we've got, it's much better than the alternative one we were
doing there.
I think that's everything.
So now we'll have those functions and we should be able to call them.
Of course, we're still not setting those value to everything, but at
least we are passing everything through the pipeline properly.
So now the question is just well, when we're actually pushing one of
these things on, we need to actually have some way of storing it.
And so, the push setup situation here.
Needs to actually store these so you can see where we're doing our
kind of group situation here.
And updating our Rex this stuff has to now keep all of that
information.
Now what I want to do here is I want to prepare myself for the
changes.
I'm going to make two just to keep things simple.
So the render entry cliprect, you can see that it's got a bunch of
information in here.
What I'd like to do is rather than storing all of this stuff, the way
that we're storing it now.
I'd rather go ahead and just have the render entry clip.
Brackets stealth just store the last one you pushed on there.
So in other words, rather than all of this stuff, I'd rather just have
render entry cliprect have like, last set up on it, like so.
Something like this and then I'd like everyone to just use that,
right?
So when you specify one of these and it actually works, right, you
will go okay, whatever the last one was, I'm sorry, whatever.
This one was, we're going to remember that next time.
Okay, so that's what I want to have actually happened here and then
this stuff doesn't actually occur at all right.
That stuff just doesn't happen and off you go, right?
So then it's going to cause a bunch of work for us obviously, but
that's okay.
And so, you can kind of end.
We may need the, the current cliprect index made still need to stay
there.
Actually, let me just see for temporarily.
Take a quick look.
Yeah, so we're going to need.
We also need the current effective index.
That's got to stay there.
Okay, so here we got like last render Target right now.
What I'm basically saying is that, you know, since that's on here, I'm
just going to say the group last wrecked or whatever it is.
Render Target index.
And similarly group last wrecked.
Dot prod, right?
Oops, it's not a strict.
What is it last set up?
so you can always just pass whatever the last thing was, if you didn't
want to change it which is really all these are for
And then I just got to finish doing that exact same thing, right?
So okay, so when you call puts it up here, you can see that we're sort
of passing to push set up since we store them in the max, I'm going to
change this to actually just passing them since that's what's actually
stored.
so instead of the width and the height, we're just going to do you
know, Min Min
Max Max.
And then when we do push set up everywhere, instead of passing those
bounds, I'm going to actually pass the the Min and Max properly.
So here's the Minix.
Here's the max axe.
Oops.
Then why?
Max Max.
Why?
There we go.
And that's like,
Makes this pretty easy as well.
So inside push set up here, this is always going to be last setup Min
X Plus setup.
And why set up Max X?
That's set up Max?
Why setup?
I'm going to Target index and same here.
Okay.
So, that should be good.
It's not
Oh, it's the wrecked.
I see.
And really we could just pass the rec directly here.
In fact we probably should be doing that and not sure why we're not.
Maybe I'll change that as well.
So now all that stuff like flows through properly, which is good, but
again it's still a little cumbersome.
So I think what we want to do is just clean this up a little bit
further.
And probably say something, like, when you push a set up on you, just
give it the new setup, right?
And so you can see where I'm going with this.
This render every clip, rect is just going to end up being a setup
struct basically pretty soon here.
So it'll be something like this where you just say push set up and you
get the new set up, right?
And then we do this push we just to say you know we're going to push
this render element on.
We get back a render entry cliprect.
We've got a I guess it maintains you know like these next pointers and
stuff, right?
But everything else we just set ourselves so you can kind of see like
there's you know everything else in here.
Besides the next pointer is just set by us and it's set by us right in
here.
So really all we have to do in this case is is update.
A couple things and you can see what those things are.
So here's the the last wrecked stuff, right?
Here's the last wreck stuff.
Here's the max.
Target Index.
This can now be done here.
So, we need to update these two, but all the rest of this stuff is
actually not that way, right?
All of this stuff can go.
And so, really, all we need to do here is just say that.
Right.
And then everything is fine.
So I think that is a more saying we do this because you can see API
wise.
Now, it's going to be really easy for people to update.
Only what they want.
I'll show you that in a second.
In fact, I guess they could do it in an even easier way than that.
Now that I think about it.
Yeah.
Okay, so I'm I don't even need this.
So what I can really do here is just say
Well, no, you're going to have to do that copy, either way.
I'll think about this a little more carefully, but
Let's just leave it like this for now.
So, here's the first set of call, we're going to pass the new setup
in.
There's a way to avoid a double copy here, but we don't really have to
worry about the moment.
And you talk about that a little bit later.
So, all we really need to do is grab out this render Target from the
new set up, so we can take a look, well, or the wrecked and Target
index.
There we go.
So, we make sure we track that Max and now push setup, just always
works that way.
So, the reason I thought this was interesting is because now, what we
can do is, we can say, oh, okay, so you've got a render entry clip.
Rect is the new setup is just going to be whatever the old setup was
That's what you're going to start with.
And then you just modify the parts you actually care about, right?
Right.
So now you just say, okay, it's whatever the last setup was, here's
the new setup and then when I push the setup, I just say there it is.
So then I don't have to like, specify any of that stuff.
And it's just nice and clean.
I just do whatever the new setup is that I actually wanted, right.
And I think that's really much easier.
So then here, same thing applies, right?
I go and I need to set this situation where I was setting the new
clip, rect up or whatever.
It was.
Speaking of that, is there a reason?
Is that push up again?
Anyway.
So when I'm actually doing the setup here, same thing would apply
here, right?
When I push the setup, instead of specifying, all these last set of
things, this is the only thing I'm actually trying to modify, right?
So, what I can do here is again,
Back, same thing.
When I go to actually create this, I can just say, oh okay, I just
need that forward.
Transform is the only thing that I'm actually trying to set here.
So when I do that set up, I'll just do a render entry cliprect new
setup and that new setup will just equal the old setup.
Then the new setups projection is going to Loops want to do.
It's going to equal this one that I computed, and then I just push it
on
And off I go.
Right.
The same exact thing is true here.
For pushing the render Target.
And then, I just push on.
The new value.
And I think that's really all there is to it.
Now that means we can even use the utility functions here now which we
couldn't do before.
So that's actually kind of nice to this is a rectangle to of some
kind.
Right rectangle, to eye.
Do we have any rectangle with tight calls for these guys?
Wrecked min max.
So we don't have one of those for rectangle to eye.
It looks like because we had like all of these right Min dim min max
we had all of these but we didn't do them for the to II version.
Unfortunately, which we should write.
We should have those
and so, all of these I guess are just
Going to be.
That.
And I don't know that we ever did a vector type for for integers,
right?
We don't have like a V2.
I do we or do we not?
We don't.
So those are going to have to
I feel a little bit more clever.
So these are going to have to take like Min Ax Men.
Why?
Max x max y, although typically
Yeah.
There we go.
And again, all of
You were just going to be.
Completely Road.
I don't know that we want Center Half Dome here because since its
integer half versions or a little bit squirrely, ER because it's like
how did you want around the half and stuff like that.
So you probably don't want to fuss with that quite yet.
So we have someone actually using it.
So now we can actually have sort of a more standardized way of talking
about these, which is nice.
And in here, we could just say new set of wrecked equals recommend
dim, and then pass all this junk to it.
That we had
And off again.
So what is this is render group?
And what is this?
This is for the first one.
So, in this case, what we should be able to do again, is just push on
render entry cliprect initial setup and that initial setup proj can be
the identity, the initial setup wrecked and be erect Min.
Jim of 00.
Excellent pixel height.
Not that anyone uses this but there it is initialized.
Anyway, so we still in theory won't see anything because everything is
all black, since all of that fog stuff is not set and properly it yet,
but we just basically reorganize the code to make it so that multiple
things can trivially flow through everyone now.
So now we can preserve those fog values.
Okay, so I would assume that we would want to do here.
Is set the fog of something that doesn't do anything if you don't want
it too, right?
So in theory, if the fog start distance was you know one and the fog
and distance
Was to or something like this or even if it's just 0 and 1, then if
the you know, the other things in here will be cleared.
So the dot product with the fog direction will always produce nothing
that should prevent the fog from kicking in and we should be able to
debug that down if it doesn't work yet.
So all I did, there was just make sure that the fog distance had some
actual range because I think the reason we're seeing Zero there
because remember,
In initial setup.
Now we've analyzed, everything is 0 that will flow through the entire
time.
Every time we put a clip, rect on all of that stuff will be fine,
right?
We'll just always copy those same values which are just 0 for the
composition and 0 for the fog Direction.
What that means
is that every time we do that dot product will get nothing back.
So we get 0 which means that as long as the fog start distance is at
zero or greater, we should never see any fog except when fog and
distance is also 0 because then that range has shrunk to 0 and we're
going to be dividing by 0, which is undefined, which is why I think we
were getting black there.
So any value here at all, doesn't really matter what it is, as long as
it's not the same as the fog, start distance, would be fine, right?
And so that's all we needed to make sure we were doing.
Okay, so our next question is just all right we've got the fog.
Start distance, plug-in in distance set up, probably.
So now you can have no fog.
What if we now want to actually turn the fog on?
Right?
So we actually want to have some way of putting some actual fog in
there.
Jimmy.
So when we do set orthographic, for example, we know that we don't
want to have any of this fog in here, I'm going to put this up here so
we can fuss with it.
I'm going to say like okay so when we're doing Ortho we want the fog
direction to be 0 just so we never get any fog.
And regardless of what we do, obviously we want the new setups camera
pee.
To be reflected properly.
So
We want that to come through.
So now, the only question is fog Direction, and so what we want to do
here is again, save that fog direction, we want that camera Z, it's
like this.
We want to measure along the negative Z axis, right?
So the Z axis comes back at the viewer, we want to fog to get larger
as it goes into the screen.
So we want the fog direction to be along the negative Z axis, right?
So now we'd actually be measuring the fog correctly when we're not in
an orthographic scenario, and we can also set the fog.
Start, and end here to something and play around with it, right?
If we want to, we could say, well the fog starts 10 away and ends, you
know.
50, you a, I don't know making this up.
I guess we'll let's do it shorter so we can see it better.
and now we're actually passing down some real values and so if you
look at what's going on there, you can actually see now that we're
getting
The fog applied exactly, as we would expect it to be applied in terms
of distance.
Anyway, you can see that the first layer down gets a little bit.
The next are done gets more and then, finally get a lot more and, you
know, maybe that's not, you know, maybe we want that a little closer.
No, like maybe the fog start distance should be more like eight, so
that the fog is a little bit more pronounced there.
Who knows?
Maybe this should be back a bit more, I'm not sure, but you can get
the idea.
Now we've got the ability to set that distance big fog and you could
tune it however you want.
I'm sure we'll tune it when we're further along and fussing with sort
of like policy Graphics sort of stuff but you can see that's working
exactly as we want.
Now the only thing we don't have at the moment is really any idea what
the fog color is.
So, if you take a look at in our render group here, you notice, we're
not specifying any color information for the fog and that's a bit of a
problem.
I think we just forgot to do that in here.
We're not specifying any fog color.
We need some way of controlling the color of the fuck.
We could hard-code the color of the fog certainly, right?
We could you know in here we can certainly set the color of the fog.
To be something specific if that's what people prefer.
But in general I don't think we want that because
Hmm.
We may want the fog to change with depending on like whether you're
inside or outside or stuff like that.
So even though I can sort of tune it in here to a specific file color,
I think we want this to be an actual value passed down to the Shader
from the external code.
So I think we want something like this, where the pixel Shader
actually gets a fog color Vector for from the exterior code.
And then, that way, we can set it to whatever it is that we actually
want.
Now, remember, this is not an
RGB value.
This is an actual linear color, linear light value and that's
important to remember.
So we kind of have to keep that in mind but yeah that's that's really
all we need to worry about there.
And similarly in here we can sort of set that fog color to something.
I don't know what we want it to be set to
But let's just say, it's something like that.
It's also not clear to me that we really want the fog to have Alpha.
So it might be better to just call this a V3 and then when we're doing
this lerp, we could say that, you know the result color Alpha value
is, oh he's going to be, you know, maybe something like this where we
just say, you know,
We're going to take the modulated color here.
And we're going to.
Only blend part of it.
So the alpha value flows through unchanged and it's only the RGB I
think you can do this too, right?
Yeah, I'm doing it right here.
It's the RGB will come through looped but the result the a will come
through.
The alpha value will come through unmodified, right?
So something like that.
Okay.
So then the fog color is is just a multiplier on the on the r g and B.
I'm sorry, just a looped value for the r g and B.
And that I think makes a lot more sense to me.
So, okay, so that means in here, we need a fog color.
And we also now need some way.
Of setting that into the opengl pipeline.
So again, that's going to have to be in here, right?
We've got the fog Direction and now we also want a fog color
Like so.
And the way that we set it up is going to be exactly the same.
So it's just going to be one of these.
And off we go.
So that's really all that it takes.
And in theory now we can set the font color soon.
As I do bug, our Shader connector with 3 component, Vector float,
What are you talking about?
Show me that Shader again, sir.
Ah,
there we go.
So now we can set that fog color programmatically as well.
And so you know, if I want to I can do that at run time now because
that's getting set here in the the render group.
So you know, if we wanted to to, you know, you can imagine it having
colored so there's a like, a purpley fog, right?
And I don't know what our clear color is right now, to be completely
honest with you, I don't really remember what
We're doing, we're wise.
So our background color is this.
So I'm just curious if I set it to the same thing as the background
color, what would happen?
Should sort of appear to fade out a little Boop's.
So that should be kind of more of a fading out to the background sort
of a thing.
Let me go ahead and see where is the fog and distance.
There it is.
I'ma set that fade really close.
That doesn't seem to quite work.
So I'm a little so I wonder if that's
I would like to know why that's doing that.
This is another one of those color.
Started to be spatial sort of issues here.
So you can kind of see that that should be fading out to the same
color as the clear color but it isn't.
So I want to double-check, I want to see what's happening with the
clear color.
So when I say clear, what actually happens there,
It just sets the clear color to that color, okay?
So what happens with that clear color
So it sets the clear Colour keyer and writes it into the frame.
Buffer at the question is, does it do?
Does it do an srgb transform on that clear, right.
This is always the annoying part about srgb.
Is the stupid like fact that it's never you always have to like dig
through the doctor figure out who's supposed to be doing srgb
transforms and who's not and what state is, blah, blah blah.
You want just two things which is like, here's a clear.
It's going to write these values in and here's a clear that's, you
know, going to go through srgb.
I guess.
I ask you really probably only want one.
Maybe not.
Hard to say, anyway.
So, I don't know which one of those is doing.
I would like to know, I don't know, we have our srgb, linearize stuff
in here.
And so one of the things I could do is
Take it from srgb to linear to see if that needed to happen.
I could also do the opposite which is to take it back which would be
the square rooting version.
so, let me just see what happens if I do either of those
So that's with srgb linearize.
On, which doesn't seem to have really changed it.
Oops, that's not a thing.
Yeah, so I'm not really sure what's going on there, if I square rooted
the values because that's what's actually going to happen to the
values.
Inside that Shader, is there going to be applied in linear light
space, and they're going to come out?
So if the other one wasn't linear, then what I would need to do here
is I need to like fun, linearize, which I don't actually have.
So, I would need
I would need like linear to srgb.
Right.
I don't know if I have doing that, but something like this.
Oh wait but I'm changing the wrong one here.
I didn't actually want to change that one.
That's the one that's actually affecting the clear color, my bad.
It's actually this one I want to do.
so, if I want to square these
Let's just see what each of these would do.
There we go.
So that is exactly what it was.
Its srgb.
Oh srgb.
So basically what that tells us.
Is that guess that, that clear does not go through srgb?
I should really start labeling these.
So that we know, since we have to figure it out.
Every time probably better to have these, this color is not
In linear space is in srgb space directly.
That seems to be the case, right?
Because if that's the clear color,
These right here are getting square rooted on the way out to go, back
to srgb, right there getting squared on the way in and square rooted
on the way out there getting square rooted.
Right here, right?
Because here is where the value is getting used the fog color and so
everything gets squared in an instant.
Again in the case where we actually have real srgb, it's not which is
actually on this card.
It's not really squaring exactly it's a, not quite a squared curve.
It's a 2.2 gamma curve or the some junk on the end.
So you know but approximately speaking it's squaring it and then
Square rooting it on the way out.
So what we know is that square root, right?
Puts it back into srgb color space.
So it's linear here and then the square root puts it into srgb color
space since I had to square.
The value for my fog color.
That suggests to me that in order to match the clear color, that's
just the me that the clear colors being applied directly.
So the clear does not go through even if the frame buffer was set to
srgb, is the clear?
Does not actually obey that setting.
The clear just writes the value directly.
Without going through the srgb transform first.
Right?
So happy birthday.
That's how that goes.
So what we could do is lock these two colors together to which
probably is a good idea for now borrowing you know, later on decisions
that we might want to do.
If I just said okay.
Let's go up here to the clear call.
When we set that clear color, I'm going to set the group, oops.
Let's set up at that point so that everyone after this they will get a
fog color.
That is just the squared version of whatever these are.
I like that.
Like so.
Okay, so now maybe possibly in theory but I'm not 100% sure.
It doesn't seem to be quite still exactly correct.
Right.
And it right now you can also see we're not since that there's only
one last setup and we don't change it for the to the fog is always
sort of doing its thing here.
I don't know why is that doing black?
Did I mess something up?
When I
what did I do wrong there?
I think maybe this clear, is this clear happening?
When is this clear happening?
Aha.
It's happening before the set camera transform.
So that's not great, right?
We would want that to happen for it at the moment.
Just kind of a drink it way of setting that right.
There we go.
All right, so that seems quite good now.
Right.
That fogging feels feels quite good.
It goes out to the background properly.
You can kind of see it.
It sort of Fades, everybody out exactly the way that we would want.
And, you know, it's distance wise, it's set pretty wonky right now.
It's just exaggerated but that's, you know, not a huge deal.
So, we've kind of got this start distance and distance here, and then
we're setting those inside the camera to be, you know, these values
here.
So
Probably, you know, wants to be a little bit more generous with the
fog.
I'm just guessing because you probably don't want to well I don't
know.
Maybe you do want them out that much.
I feel like these levels should probably be further down one way or
the other, but that's neither here nor there I guess.
So, all right, so now we've got our fog in there.
And that's exactly what I wanted to do today.
So that's all good.
So the other question is we still got a little time, live my life,
like probably like, 15 minutes left.
Right.
So, we have another question to address here.
Which has to do with Alpha.
This was kind of interesting.
We probably won't have time to do it in 15 minutes.
We can least start talking about
So the other thing that we want to be able to do is if the hero was
on, you know, one level of the game and you know, there was something,
there was another level above him as he was maybe moving up and down.
That was kind of interesting and you didn't want that level you want a
little too kind of fade in as it came down.
Sort of like an alpha out as it comes up, right?
So like
we probably want to create a stairwell again, but the hero can kind of
hop down to demonstrate this a little bit more.
Let me go ahead and stop that case.
So we can see it.
So what I want to do here is like, you know, we still don't really
have our room band stuff set up at all properly.
So we kind of need to do that pretty soon here.
But we want this guy to be able to hop down these cubes, right?
And right now, there's no way for him to get down there at all
because, and besides the fact that the camera we don't have proper
camera bound stuff set up.
So we don't track where he is properly, which will do probably next
weekend.
We don't have any cubes from to hop down here, right?
We'd like to have cubes from to hop down here so that he can get to
the next level.
I had pulled those out sort of because of I thought sorting why, as we
weren't gonna be able to handle it, maybe we can't handle it now
because we've actually done the full 3d stuff visually.
I don't know that that's necessarily true, but it might be true.
So we might as well try it.
And see.
Let's take a look here.
Ad standard room.
because before you know we had sort of an effect, you know what, let
me let me take
It's out temporarily as well as so that sort of note you know room
noise.
You can kind of see here now is this is what it would look like if all
of the cubes were leveled.
So I want to see if I can put some cubes in there.
It's like a stairwell, he can kind of go down, right?
and,
We sort of had code in here.
Here's the right hole.
If
You know, we wanted to make this stuff still happen, we just need
these Z values to drop down a bit, right?
Or to go up a bit, one of the other
and so I feel like in here, you know, we should be able to kind of do
something like
Looking at this, you got this kind of P offset thing.
So if I was to go ahead and say that inside the right hole, the P
offset for these things is going to be some random thing.
Let me just see what that does.
It should give us.
Yeah, so you can see like now we've got some cubes in here and they've
got random Heights.
So maybe I go now and say like, okay let's make the height be
proportional to
The offset Y, and it starts at, you know, it starts at negative 2
there.
So I'll just say, like, okay,
The offset y, plus 2, is the start of this thing and I'm just going to
take that value as a floating point value, which so that will go from
zero to four or whatever.
We'll just multiply it by something.
I don't know what it should be yet.
And I guess maybe I want it to go downward to, I guess.
Now, I think about it, I'm not sure.
But you can see.
Now I'm starting to get a little bit of a stairwell situation going in
there.
Great that I can hop on.
Right?
So let me just take a look at that.
So yeah, I don't want a random bilateral anymore.
I just want the offset to be the offset that it is.
So there's a stairwell going up and I guess I sort of want this
stairwell to go down.
Probably, I guess for our present purposes, I mean, doesn't really
matter.
But, you know,
So there's a stairwell going down, I don't think it goes down enough.
Not sure, maybe it does.
I guess it does.
I take it back.
All right, so now in theory this dude can hop down here.
You can see we still have problems because he's too tall.
For his location but you know that might be something we can fix.
You can kind of see that he hopped down there, right?
And he ended up here.
We need those to be like a little lower.
We also need the room.
I feel like the room.
Height needs to be, you know, we could do
What we could do in this case is we could say is this one?
Is this value here?
A probably the height of these cubes.
I'm interested to know if I can just shorten these cubes up a bit.
So that's maybe a little bit easier for us to deal with, right?
You can kind of see what's going on there, just as a sort of
placeholder situation.
So let me go ahead and kind of move these guys down a little bit more.
All right.
So now that's a little bit more sensible, do poops.
Amanda Castle my way.
Dude, get out of there.
Okay.
Come on guys, come over here.
All right, good stupid familiars.
Here we go.
All right.
So basically what we're talking about here, and I guess this is
goodbye.
This is where I can end it for today.
So, that's probably still a little bit too much.
Basically, we're talking about here is just getting the alpha in place
so that we can so that we can make this process work.
So, when you hop down here, you want that top floor to Alpha out,
right?
And
Because once you're down here, you can't see yourself at all.
And as you as that level kind of comes up towards you, we want it to
Alpha out.
So that's the next effect that we want to put in there.
And that's not really as much a Shader effect as it is a render pass
effect.
But, you know, we can, we can sort of cover how that works tomorrow.
This is kind of funny.
It's funny looking at something from this angle when the Sprites stay
at their other angle, kind of cracks me up a little bit.
Alright, anyway,
So yeah, so that's all we're talking about here.
I'm going to go ahead and put in this.
Minimization back because it makes it easier to see the grid.
Yeah, so yeah, I think that's where I'll stop for today.
And then next weekend, we'll start tackling the room based stuff and
and clean up sort of some of this Dimension stuff.
So that we'll have all that working properly because I think that's
pretty reasonable now, right?
All right.
Okay.
Oh you know what I could do?
Since I've got the 10 minutes, let me go ahead and make that change to
the cliprect stuff so that that's not something that gets pushed on
periodically.
I want to change that.
So let's just do that while since I have a little bit extra time
today.
I don't want to start something new, let me do that.
So let's call this this clip.
Rect thing, let's get rid of this and call this like render setup or
something, right?
This is the setup for the rendering which says, here's the clip.
Rect
Right.
Here's the render Target.
Here's projection Matrix.
Here's the values for the Shader, have a party and then we can say, is
well, a render entry, textured quads just has the setup, but it's
going to use in it, right?
So that's just all it needs to know, is it just gets that in there?
And then we don't need any more of this stuff where we've got, like a
cliprect index situation coming on here.
And yeah, I don't really even know that we're going to need this type
field anymore.
We'll have to see what ends up happening when yeah, when we get there.
But, you know, it may be the case that that doesn't really have to
happen.
We'll find out.
So anyway, we could get rid of clip Rex and then those just don't have
to get pushed on anymore.
Those just aren't a thing.
They're like off and they're unrelated, right?
And, which is nice because it means now that people don't have to skip
those, and everything is just kind of hunky dory there, right?
I also don't know.
Are we even using this anymore?
The render transform thing.
Oh yeah, we are down here.
So we could start using this setup stuff and have a game set up in a
debug setup.
Separate as well.
I don't know if you really want to do that or not, but we have options
there obviously.
All right.
So let's see, we don't care about this much.
We can just change it to render setup, that's pretty easy cliprect.
Indexes no longer have to be a thing at all and in fact that can just
go away, that's just not there.
Current cliprect index and transient cliprect this.
This stuff is just not relevant anymore.
I don't think the only person who
Actually cares about that to debug system, but we can support it
pretty easily.
All, we would need to do
In here is just say like, okay well, whatever the last setups one was
we just need to store.
It's actual rectangle, right?
So we would just say, okay the old cliprect equals whatever the render
group,
Last set up cliprect was is what we need, right?
And so then later after you do, whatever it is that you're going to
do, we just need to restore it.
We also need to push on a new
Set of quads because the quad things just kind of Aggregates those
quads together, right?
Okay.
Where is the render group thing here?
I just want the push clip.
Rect
So what I want here, I just I guess that really all I want to do is do
a push set up, right?
So I'm going to call Push setup.
I'm going to say for this render group.
Here's the new setup.
Render setup.
It was Brenda group last setup.
Old clip.
Rect equals new setup clip.
Rect right.
So I'm just preserving the old one here.
I'm setting it to a new one here and then off we go and then I'm just
going to do the exact same thing on the way out.
So here I'm going to say, let me get whatever the last one was and
then let me set.
The new one to whatever it was before off we go.
Same thing is true here.
Really know this.
This is not a thing now.
So when you get rid of that although I guess no wait.
You know, I could I just wouldn't do the push setup.
So if you wanted to do it you could I just instead I just do
So I just save the clip.
Rect that is currently the case.
I just don't push a new one on, so you could use the that call
structure if you wanted to as well, I suppose.
All right, so push setup needs to be in here.
Now,
another interesting thing about push setup, though, is that it doesn't
actually have to
Push anything?
That's separate issue.
This is going to be a bigger change that I thought was going to be I
probably shouldn't have done this right?
The industry and this might go a little late.
All right, so push that up.
Just got to change the name of this guy.
Here we are.
Again, all of these are just render setup.
unfortunately, we don't yes so these
Really all push setup does is if you look at what's going on in push
bitmap, when you do get current quads right, you can kind of see well,
okay, whatever the current quads, are that gets cleared, every time we
push a render element on, right?
Right here.
But all we really have to do is every time we do a push set up, call
that set up.
Now, invalidates, the quads that we had set because we're basically
taking these quads and we're buffering up more quads.
As we go, anytime, we change the setup, you can't continue to buffer
quads because you have to use a new set up.
Now, for those quads.
So every time we do a new setup, we would just clear.
The current quads at that point, we now don't need to push anything
anymore, right?
All were doing is this, that's it.
We don't chain these guys together.
There's no next pointer.
Anyway, so, the only thing we actually want to do is is this right?
We checked to make sure we didn't need to have a one more render
targets but otherwise the only thing we do is we say okay thank you
for the new setup.
That's great.
And then we say that we need new more quads, right?
But that's it.
And I think you could probably also see that this is
we could optimize out this copy entirely because people now if they
want to can just access the exact setup,
Directly.
So this is going to, this is going to optimize away to nothing.
Basically, after we've done this, which is pretty cool.
So anyway, so looking at here, yeah, we got this.
New setup, render Target index.
That's all fine.
So we have to make sure that we actually pay attention to that.
And that should be fine.
This is not a render into clip rack.
This is a render setup.
Okay.
Let's see.
Push setup doesn't take a value anymore and similarly all these guys
are just like render setup.
Clip.
Rect
and,
Just keeping it going again.
Do an absolutely nothing interesting here.
Just pulling out old code.
Okay.
So hopefully you can see what I'm doing here again.
Really straightforward Transformations.
This is just me, looking at that code and noticing that really it was
just doing a bunch of busy work.
And so I'm just getting rid of all that and saying, look, we don't
have to aggregate these anymore.
We're just pushing down quads so we can make this a much more
streamlined operation.
So that's all I'm doing, right?
Really, really basic.
Okay.
So here are some stuff.
This is using a trim.
This is a transient cliprect situation right here, right?
So I'm just going to do transient clip.
Rect
And it looks like, I don't know who's actually changing the cliprect,
though to a default, clipped Rex.
So I guess I just want to do that.
Like so and we're going to actually have to make those not be indices
anymore if that makes sense, but that's that's fine.
Again, this is another transition clip.
Rect
And that's just going to be the render group.
And really what I want here.
So what you can see developing Curacao
Is this render group call now when I push a Transit Krypton there and
go to pass a rectangle 2.
I.
So what I actually want here is I want this object transform thing,
instead of doing this, I don't actually want it to do this at all.
Like that's not useful to me.
Really what I want is, you know, get clip.
Rect.
Like so and I want that to produce the rectangle to I that I should
actually use.
Right?
So what I want here is I want a rectangle to I result.
It's going to produce this rectangle after doing the transform and
just return it to the caller.
So now they can use it anywhere they want to because now you don't
have to generate a clip rect from it, right?
So,
So, now when they do Transit clip practices, like, okay, like I don't
need to do any of this stuff anymore, it's all gone.
All I have to do is just say, hey, get me the clip, rect
Right.
This is the clip brick that I'm going to use so get me that clip rect
and then it'll automatically get, you know, handled.
So this result is gone now because we're not doing that kind and yeah
and this one's the same way.
So we've got this default cliprect in here in the debug .h.
The practice and that's a rectangle to I.
Now
This is going to be the same thing, transient clip rect.
Things are going to block the project.
Okay.
Clip.
Rect
And there it is.
Right?
So, that'll get that clip.
Rect and then we don't need this anymore.
The default cliprect here.
I guess again, could just be last set up with bricks.
Oh I guess I actually meant render group.
Is that what?
Yeah.
Sorry, render group.
Last set.
Okay.
So that's actually all of the changes that we need except for one in
the actual game code.
We've actually excised all that stuff now, but the render entry
texture quads needs to have the render setup remembered for it.
So whenever we do get current quads now,
To push one of these on here, right?
You do get current quads, you can see, we've got the current quads
being pushed on, we need it to to suck in that transfer, right?
So when it does this, the situation here, I guess, yeah, this is just
double checking to see whether we have enough room.
So assuming that all of this works, okay?
If we don't have current quads, what we need to do is just say
whatever that setup was
But the group is currently using.
That's what we're going to use for the group when we push it on.
So it just kind of copies that into that struct, so that's it.
All right.
So then what we need to do is get rid of all of this stuff because you
know, basically the stuff doesn't need to happen anymore.
So cliprect index and as a concept just goes away and all of this code
here actually comes down into
In fact, I don't really know why this switch statement here is inside
that check.
It seems a bit weird.
Like if you use render targets or clip Rex render targeting, this is
listening because I guess that's just a kills it.
And anyway, taking a look at these right this clip.
Directing that stuff all of these things don't have to happen anymore.
Like nothing that has to do with cliprect counts or indices or any of
that has to occur at all.
Right.
So basically all we have to do is just this this work right here that
we were actually doing to set up like the scissor and those sorts of
things is all we really need.
So what we want to do is just move this down, I think here too.
When we are actually going to use the textured quads and so once we
get those texture quads out, then we can do all of this work, right?
And we'll take a look at that in a second.
In the meantime, we no longer
Anything we have to do with clip Rex here, so those will go away
entirely.
And so all of this stuff.
Can kind of get sucked out one level.
There we go.
And so now we really just have two cases.
One is when we are trying to do a render Target blend and we're going
to deal with that at some point in the future potentially.
When we actually re-enable those if we if we re enable them
Okay, but then I render enter entry textured quads here.
That is the place where we're going to actually do this setup.
So if use render targets, that's actually going to be the thing that
does the buying frame buffer here.
I think at this point, there's no way to not use render targets
because we pretty much always use them but we'll leave that in place
for the moment.
So we'll just go ahead and say that we've got the render setup here.
And that's going to be what we're going to look at.
So what we're going to say is if the setup render Target index is less
than or equal to the max render Target index.
Then we're assuming that we can proceed with this call.
Right.
This and so and we kind of need to think about this because if we're
what we really want to say is this render Target index.
Yeah.
Let the think about this a little bit more because this this switch
doesn't actually work.
So anyway, we come in here, R transpose is still going to be correct
right to get that projection Matrix out.
Although now we don't really need to transpose it because if you look
at what happens to proj, it actually only gets used in one place,
right?
It actually only gets used down here where we're loading it in.
So if we want to we can just have that do the transpose for us.
So instead of transposing it GL, uniform Matrix 4fv.
We were previously having that do the transpose.
I'm sorry to not do the transpose.
Where is it?
So here that is and you can see we had a transpose flag there, and we
were passing in false for it, so we could just pass through and not do
the transpose, right?
So that's all good inside here, we've got our clip Breck situation so
that just pulls the cliprect out directly from the set up.
We can look at this here, where we're finding the targets.
I'm going to go ahead and say what if we just did this?
Maybe that's a little bit better.
And then everything else should kind of just flow through, right?
We were going to say all right, here's the clip.
Rect
They're here is our render Target stuff.
So all of this stuff should just work, right?
We're just checking to see if we need to bind a new Target.
We're only going to do this.
Presumably, if we were going to bind a new Target, if we weren't, then
we won't.
So we go ahead and do that.
We do our cliprect.
We get that out of the set up like so we do our use render targets
Like I said, I'm not really sure we want it.
We kind of need to revamp how this works, but that's okay for now,
it'll, it'll be okay.
It'll be fine.
We set the GL scissor, then we come through here and we don't need
that anymore.
We have just set up for everything so we don't need clip anymore.
And again all that just comes out of Arkham and it's really nice,
right?
Okay, so now in here, we still have this clip rep problem.
For our, I'm just going to Nuke this because again we have to redo our
software renderer at some point and we'll sort of cross that bridge
when we come to it.
There's no sense maintaining it.
Now when we're still kind of working on what they should look like, so
now we don't need linearized clip Rex anymore.
That's just gone.
Which means we don't need prep for render anymore, because we're not
sorting and we're not linearizing, the clip Rex, which is great
because that means all this stuff goes away.
It means you have prep for render is just gone.
Which is fantastic.
It means when we call prep anything that was taking a prep, no longer
takes a prep.
So again, just really simplifying the stuff down.
It's really nice.
Let me go ahead and jump to those so software render commands.
Where is that?
That is
Here.
Let's just get rid of that everywhere.
And now we just need the opengl version.
Okay.
Now, the end of a stream is not a good time to do that.
I guess I just forgot how much it would be.
I was assuming that wouldn't work at all, and it actually just work,
just great.
So that's nice again, just a very simple mechanical transformation of
how the things were structured.
Their.
But turns out to be really kind of nice because what you can see now
is, we're getting a much cleaner.
Of going through to do our render commands.
Now basically, we just set up our rent, those render targets.
And now we're just looping through really just sets of quad batches
and the quad batches have in them, everything that we need to set up
the program, specify the vertex data and off we go, right?
And it just gets us out of a lot of bookkeeping that we really didn't
need anymore.
We don't need any of these anymore, right?
We don't need the cliprect situation.
We don't need these firsts and
Blasts anymore.
Those can all go away.
Let me go ahead and take this game.
Render prep structure goes away.
Sort entries, obviously should have gone away a long time ago, but
we're just getting that, you know, nice sort of spring cleaning out of
the way where things now can be just a lot more straightforward.
And again, no loss of functionality here, so that's good.
I'll go to a brief Q&A since I took up the time there.
So we're all good.
Yeah.
And again.
Mmm, that's a bit odd.
I'm not sure.
Oh right.
As you say I was like, why is the framerate 60 frames a second at the
moment?
Because it's supposed to be starting that because of the game Sims
Point query thing is slow, but I was like, oh, it's because we only
created two levels.
So it's not doing as many of those super slow Point queries.
We never optimized.
Has the framerate tanked after employing fog or was that a wrong
impression mind that is definite.
Very definitely, a very wrong impression of yours.
The frame rate is currently unrelated to rendering completely.
So essentially what happens.
First of all, even in that case, if you just compiled without with
optimizations on your at 60 locked, right?
So we currently don't have any frame rate
Albums at the moment.
However, really, it's all of our time is actually spent in some
unoptimized World Point creates off.
That's N squared.
So as you add more entities, the world it just gets infinitely slow
right and we just haven't done any work to look at those things yet,
because we haven't been working on that code.
But I think even if you create a bunch of levels, if you're in, if
you're in an optimized build, you're still fine because hey, computers
are just fast these days.
Yeah, so you're still 60 frames a second.
According to this 16 milliseconds there.
Again, with OBS on, you get some variability in the frame rate and
stuff.
I find
But, you know, for the most part, 60 frames per second, just fine.
However, if you have this many levels where we've got 10 levels coming
down, so you've got a full for with all of those entities hopping
around on them.
What ends up happening, is, if you don't compile with optimizations
on, there's a really slow function.
We've got that does checking of what's around an entity that really
tanks.
So you can see that frame rate, they're just really tanking again.
Nothing to do with the rendering, we have to
enable our profile view soon.
We'll do that.
When we get to it, you can see that that on top.
We also have the debug stuff takes a lot of time, but I think it's
really that point query.
Mostly you can turn off the debug stuff if you want to like so.
And see how much of a difference that makes?
Yeah, but you can see it's still slow, right?
So it's really mostly just the fact that that point query that
unoptimized point query just takes all the time and it just so happens
that if you compile with optimizations on that function gets
considerably faster and then you're at 60 frames a second again.
So, at the moment rendering just isn't an issue.
Even on this is tenure, I'm not sorry, this is seven-year-old Hardware
but even if that, it's just, we're just not putting enough on the
screen for rendering to be the problem.
Right.
so,
alright, let's take a look at some questions here cuz we have quite a
few.
I'll try to get through them.
May blow ask now that we're full 3d may be may be worth extending the
debug visualization rectangles into the third dimension.
Yes, I think you are probably quite correct.
We have not had a chance to do that yet but that would be a very good
idea because it would allow us to draw bounding boxes.
Basically which is probably more what we're going to want to see.
So yes, I do agree that that would be a good idea.
Nicola asked the framerate question and the fault of that was, why
would you in this case compiled without optimizations?
I don't get how it changes that much your frame rate.
Sorry if this is a dumb question.
The answer is basically because well this is really a question that
probably deserves.
It's not a dumb question at all, you
You're asking a good question, the, there's just a lot to it and I'm,
you know, since we're kind of over time there at the end that this
would be AB is a bad day for me too.
Try.
This question, but I'll do the best I can.
And recently, we've pretty time.
So what ends up happening, right?
If we take a look in some region, I can't remember the name of this
function, exactly.
The one that is really slow here.
Let's take a look.
Doo-doo-doo-doo-doo-doo doo-doo-doo-doo-doo doo-doo-doo-doo.
Here it is.
All right, so let's just take a look here at what's going on.
I'm just going to try to give you a little bit of a feel for this
because it is important to understand and a like I said it's
definitely not a dumb question.
It is a very good question and I would like to try to explain it.
So here you can see the game running.
I've stacked up a bunch of rooms.
You can see, the game is running.
It's actually less than even 30 so it's not even quite hitting 30
frames a second in this current state.
This is a the unoptimized build.
Now we know that we turn optimization on were at 60 frames a
And everything's hunky-dory.
And in, you know, off we go.
So the question is, you know, a first u.s.
question, why wouldn't I just always compiled optimizations on, right?
So, that's one path.
Question.
The other half of the question is, well, why does comparing with that
citations on make such a big difference, the frame rate?
And so the answer here is like so let's start by taking just a few
observables that we could see about the game.
So we know it's taking 40 milliseconds to frame right now in this
debug build I'm going to go ahead and take get closest reversible.
And I'm just going to tell it.
It can't run.
So what we're going to do here is we're going to say look, you know,
we're always going to return just a result that that is is saying we
looked for an closest traversal and we couldn't find it right
unfortunately.
Guess now that I think about it, I don't know that everyone can handle
this never happening.
That's a good question.
I don't know if I can actually because people need to be placed
somewhere in the world initially.
You know what, here's what I'll do.
Let's try this.
I'm going to make a global variable.
Well, kill switch, and I'm going to set it to 1.
And then I'm just going to say if kill switch.
Do this, right?
And I guess I could have done this with hot code reloading as well.
I didn't quite think about that but, you know, well, so here we are
running the game again, like it's taking 40 milliseconds of frame and
and right, so you know, if you think about there's 1,000 milliseconds
in a second, right?
So if you wanted to hit 60 frames a second, you want to be at sixteen
point.
Six, six milliseconds should be how long the frame takes because that
means you're just waiting for the
At that refresh at that point, which is what you want, right?
So now, if I come in here, and I say, well, okay, let's set a
breakpoint there.
We're in some region.
Yeah, let's go down to get closer to reversible.
So here's your host reversible, I'm going to set a breakpoint in here
and I'm just going to set kill switch.
Now it was was one, I'm going to set to zero so that code path won't
run anymore.
So this code path just is not running anymore.
That means nobody can move now, right?
So they're just not able to actually go anywhere at all, right?
And you can see what's happened to our profile.
We've actually gone down 15 mil whole Ms.
Right.
We used to have 40.
now, at 25 and that was just from this one function,
that's all we did was take out this one function.
So that one function alone, just one was taking as much time as his
entire frame takes to do the 16 millisecond, frame in a 60 frame per
second game.
Okay, just this one function.
Now why?
Okay?
Why is that happening?
How is that possible?
Doesn't make any sense, right?
You looking at the code, look at how tiny it is, right?
How many lines is that?
It's only, you know what, 943, 2975 with 30 lines of code, something
like that.
So, let's turn that kill switch back on again, right?
So now we are running this again.
And we're back up so you can see.
So very clearly just this, this part of the code is taking all the
time.
And so let's take a look at why.
Well, if we step in here, we can see that what this is doing is it's
doing a loop first for get close to Roseville.
It's doing a loop over all of the entities in the entire Sim region
and that's 1339 right.
So, that's actually that's actually
Did entities, that's looping over, write everything in the same
region.
It's going to Loop over 1,300 and Annie's.
And for each one of those, it's going to Loop over there traversals
now.
That's okay, because this is not much of a loop.
Most things either have one or zero traversable, but then what it's
going to do is it's going to go through here and it's going to do some
fairly straightforward.
Just pulling pointers out, so that's not too expensive, right?
And then it's going to do a little bit of a length test here and it's
going to get the one that found.
So when we look at what this is doing, it's doing 100, 1339
operations, and those operations aren't too bad, right?
So you might think, well, 100 1100, operator, sorry.
That was not the right number 13:39.
You might think well 13 39, that's not that many operations.
How could that possibly be taking all that time?
Well, if
Just go up, one more level, right?
So let's go out here and see where this is getting called, right?
And this is getting called inside the, the execute brain call, right?
Can see this call, where excuse the brain type.
If we step out and see how many of those were doing, you can see that
we're doing 13 of those, right?
So we're actually doing 13 times 13.
Nine, right, or seventeen thousand of those operations, right?
Every time we want to simulate, we're doing 17,000 of those
operations.
So now we have to ask ourselves.
Well, how many cycles does this processor actually have to work with
in a 60th of a second, right?
How much would it actually have?
Well, we can actually do that math.
I need to get to the little thing that, no, we don't need to go to
send owl.
Where's the, where's the computer?
Can I get properties on that?
Yeah, so if you look at the process properties of the processor, well,
this is a 3.19 gigahertz processor, right?
That's, that's how fast it's running.
So, in a single thread of code, that means I have 3.19 GHz are 1000
times 1000 times, 1000 Cycles, right?
That's how many
Cycles.
There are
Okay, so did I do that right 1000 times?
1000 times 1000, right?
That's a gigahertz x 3, .19.
There we go.
Now, that's how many cycles in one second.
This processor will execute.
Now we know that we have to hit 60 frames a second so that means we
have 530.
Well okay.
So 53 million write Cycles, 53 million
So you can start taking a look at these two numbers.
Next to each other, to give you a little sense of scale.
So 17,000 versus 53 million.
Right?
All right.
So now let's ask the question if we have to do 17,000 operations and
we have 53 million total operations, 53 million, total Cycles.
How many cycles per operation.
Do we get
For 17,000 operations, right?
So I'm going to divide by 17 407 3054.
Now, 3054 Cycles isn't that many cycles anymore, right?
So that means the interior of this Loop that we were talking about
here.
This one right here, let me jump back to it so you can see it.
The interior of this Loop has to execute in only 3054 A Cycles.
Now, remember,
Something as simple as missing the cash.
Right?
Could take hundreds of Cycles.
Hundreds of Cycles.
So now we have to go through here and look well, okay, so what is this
doing?
Let's go to the disassembly, right?
So here you can see the disassembly of a routine, right?
And it's actually fairly substantial.
Right, what's going on here?
Got all sorts of things in here.
We're making calls out to operator, - right.
We've got, you know, a bunch of stuff in here.
That's, that's, you know, making calls out to get some space
reversible, all this stuff.
So, we take a look at how many cycles we expect this to be.
There's just a lot of stuff going on here.
Let's see how many times we call something.
We call the block timer to enter it.
Well, that's, that's not inside the loop.
So what
We won't look at that one at the moment.
So let's look at all these here.
So let's look at all the times we call out to a separate routine the
assembly.
Here's one call, right?
Here's another call to operate a - here's another call to length
squared.
Here's another well, that's the called the end the block, right?
So we're going through all this assembly code here.
Here's what we actually have to do.
Here's the work that actually has to get done, right?
So we're doing work here.
Each one of these is going to take potentially multiple Cycles
depending on the circumstances, some of them overlap.
So it's kind of hard to know necessarily but you can see what's going
on.
We're going to make an actual call out here to get some traits of rest
will.
Look at all this code that has to happen.
Here's a bunch of set up that has to occur in order to make this work.
We're setting up the stack frame for this function that we just called
in to get some face.
Reversible.
Look at all this stuff were clearing out this whole value, right?
We're doing all this work blah blah blah blah.
We're making another call out to get reversible.
That's going to set the stock.
Again, we're calling out to operator plus equals on this thing.
Look at all this code.
I mean, are you looking at all of this code that calls out to operator
plus which sets up the stack frame for that, right?
Tons, and tons and tons of work being done here, right?
Just tons plus, not to mention.
Look at this stuff.
The insert a security cookie.
Check call in here to do some kind of nonsense that the compiler
wanted to do to check the stack for security purposes or something,
right?
Look at all that stuff.
Okay, so compare and contrast that let's now do the exact same thing
and remember all of that everything that we're looking through there
plus all the other calls everything on this epic to only three
thousand Cycles, it had to happen.
It
Right?
And that's if it had all the time in the frame total so nothing else
could have happened.
And so you can start to see how that's just too slow, right?
That has to be a small for that function has to be a small fraction of
our frame time.
It would easily take the whole frame time, right?
Because all that stuff.
But now, let's look at what happens if we actually compiled our code
in release mode instead.
Okay.
Now let's go down to that kill switch.
Here we go.
And let's take a look at this function again.
So now we're coming in through here.
I'm going to go disassembly.
And let's take a look at what happens.
So first, let's go through and Mark all the places that we call
something right, just like we did before.
I'm marking all the places that we call out to something.
Every single one of them, right?
I've not skipped a single one.
You noticed something, I didn't mark anything.
Why didn't I Mark anything?
Well, I didn't mark anything because we didn't call anything, why?
Because when you turn optimizations on the compiler will in line all
small functions and remove all of that extra Croft.
So now we have something that went from having tons of extra code that
got pulled in to having all of those functions fuse together into a
nice clean series of mathematical operations that can all happen in a
nice little tight Loop, right?
So now, if we step through here, you look
It's happening.
It's very straightforward.
It's just moving in those pointers instead of calling a bunch of
functions to get them.
It's doing the math right here.
Right loading in the map and doing the math to do the comparisons on
the, on the difference, right?
There's the multiply it flies in the ads and so on and then it's
storing the results as it should, right?
It's just doing it all in one.
Nice, little tiny space.
So now, even though this function, is still super unoptimized because
it's checking all entities for no reason, even though it should be
doing a nice tight, spatial query, the optimized
Has gotten rid of all of that cruft, and so it's able to run well
within the budget.
So let's not even close to the, you know, 3,000.
Again would have been what it would have to do, in order to hit 60
seconds, if it was all that was running.
It's probably now able to run in just a couple hundred Cycles, right?
So it's completely out of our way unlike before when it was just this
huge falling mess, right?
So hopefully what you can see there.
Let me get rid of that kill switch, because now we don't need it
anymore.
So hopefully, what you can see there is optimized, code makes a
massive difference unoptimized code when you add, when you, when the
compiler is not told to optimize the code at all.
What ends up happening is, it's just going to literally do every last
thing you told it to do.
So, if you have an inline function,
It's not going to do that because that's an optimization.
It's just going to actually call out to that function actually set up
the stack frame, blah, blah blah.
Why is that?
The case, even?
Because in line would be very simple for it to do, right?
Even quickly.
Well, that now gets to the answer to your first part of question,
which is why don't you always compile an optimization without two
losses on the reason is because if you compile with optimizations on,
you are no longer able to inspect your code through the debugger very
effectively.
What do I mean by that?
That.
Well, let's take a look at that exact function that we know how to a
lot of stuff happen in it.
Let's go ahead and see what happens when we try to step into it,
right?
I wanted to bug that function.
It's not working.
Let's say, I mean it is working right now but it's let's say it
wasn't.
Well, first of all, when I step I'm stepping, look at what's going on.
It's not even going in order, right?
Why wasn't it going in order?
Well, it's because it's optimized code.
So now the optimizer has rearranged a bunch of the operations and you
can no longer expect them to happen in the order in which they're
listed that makes it pretty.
Placated to debug right there because you're Jumping All Around, which
is pretty uncomfortable.
If you're trying to just look at where errors occur in the program,
write the next problem we get is well, okay, how about I look at tests
entity, right?
And I want to look at something in test entity, right?
Okay, so I'm taking a look at that in there.
When I'm looking at that, I have no guarantee that the place that I'm
at actually is referencing that properly at all, right?
Because we don't know what the state is of these up to this point.
It may not have written to it yet.
Even though it looks like it should have, or something like that,
because doesn't have to, to point would be.
Another example, let's say, I want to look at what the value of 2
point.
Is this PP - frumpy?
Well, I put into the background, says it's undefined.
Well, no, it's not.
It's right there, right?
Well, not really and, the reason for that is because when the compiler
compiles, the optimizations on its free to remove temporary variables
or not.
Remember what they were.
If it's fused all the operations together in a way, that's hard to
extract, right?
So now I can't even look at
The values of my program.
I can't even tell what they are.
Same will probably be true of death square of testdisk U squared,
right?
If I ask for that value, I get it just doesn't know, right?
It's like, I have no idea optimized all that away.
It's all kind of messed in there in one big thing right now.
Even, I might be able to get closest distance squared.
Yeah, so I can observe the results.
So I know.
Now, looking at the result of this, I do know that it did compute test
these squared and that it was 30 2.1, 2:00 to 6:00, but the debugger
totally lost track of where that was because again, the compiler
optimize that whole sequence out and it can't remember how to
correlate those, right?
Now better debuggers are able to more to extract data more cleanly
here, right?
But in the case of optimized code, there's a limit to what they can
do, even very good debuggers, and a lot of
The buggers like visual Studios isn't that good?
The debug information doesn't necessarily track stuff like, oh, I
computed this and I put it in a register and I never store it back out
of the stack.
So if you want to know where it is, you got to go look at this
register because that's where it's hanging out right now or whatever,
right?
So that's why I typically compiled without optimization.
So I'm Because, unless I'm actually trying to look at performance,
it's a lot easier to step through the code.
Furthermore that goes doubly true on handmade hero.
Because on handmade here, I'm trying to teach people stuff on stream.
It's very hard to teach people stuff.
When I would constantly have to be saying, oh yeah, you can't see this
value because the optimizer opt-outs it out.
Or oh these are jumping around lines about trying to show you how this
is working but it's like jumping all over the place.
I'm like yeah that's because it rearranges or whatever.
That's just not very helpful.
Right.
So hopefully that answers the question for you.
All right, let's see.
Master Yoda says, how do you feel about uniform buffer objects?
Am I right to assume the render setup struck could be past the Shader
as a uniform buffer object instead of separate uniforms?
Yes that is exactly true I like that stuff it's just not always
supported everywhere the best you know the best stuff is usually when
you can just write to some memory and then hand it to the driver and
say Hey give this to the Shader so the closer you get to that the
better it is.
Always, in my opinion.
And mess.
I said, how does the hero know if it should hop to the lower level?
Instead of the upper level at the end of the stairs?
Where is the code for that?
That is just in the thing that says get closest reversible.
In fact, I think it was the thing.
We were just literally just looking at I believe it just looks for
whatever the closest one is.
So the reason that it hops to the one that's the lower one.
Read the higher one is because it's been going down in Z and the
closest one was always down a little more and so by the time it gets
to the lowest are it's down so far that the
Ones.
Nearby it on the lower level are closer than the ones on the upper
level.
What does the software vendor look like at this?
At the moment you can't really run the software under at the moment
because we've changed the formats all around.
So at some point we'll have to go through there and kind of just re
clean that up.
Probably don't want to do that anytime soon.
But you know, someday when we want to do like another pass in the
suffer under, we could go do it and it would be fun.
I think.
Christ says, 42, I assume the problems you solve in handmade here are
fairly representative of problems we face as a Game Dev.
Can you comment about any social aspects of being gamed a VG, how
collaborative or supportive the community is, or what it's like
sharing code base with a number of others.
I guess, what I would say is that's it's like anything else, it just
depends on the team, you know.
Some teams work really well together and others don't.
And so, you know,
It's really just a question of the mix of personalities.
I would say there's nothing specific in game.
There's nothing really different in game development, compared to
anything else.
So, you know, much like you might work at a company, you know, I don't
know.
Let you go work at a company that does something you work at Starbucks
corporate or something on a managerial team or something.
I would imagine.
It's exactly the same, some of those teams, just they all the
personalities, like, get along pretty well with each other and it just
works nicely other times.
It's a disaster and some people are like, you know, don't get along
with other people and
You know, in fighting and and its belligerent and whatever.
And I don't really think the game industry is any different, you know,
some teams you get are just really great teams.
They're fun to work on and you get along well and you are a good
version of yourself on that team.
Other teams, you just can't stand it and you're a bad influence on the
team or other people are bad influence on you or you fight with people
or who knows and you know the older devs get and the better they get
at working with other people, you know?
It's similar.
Like I said also to other companies, right?
It's like people get better at working with people.
So over time sometimes
Times that improves.
But just in general, I think it is just about a mix of personalities
and there really isn't a lot.
You can say, beyond that game development isn't special, so everything
that would normally apply to whether or workplace works well, or not,
it applies here.
And somebody who's a horrible employee in on one team might be great
on another.
Team just because the mix is different and they get along with the
people better, you know, and that kind of stuff that's just true.
You know, and I really don't think game development special.
I really don't.
If you want to know the line count on handmade here, we actually have
that somewhere here, right?
I don't know how to run this thing.
There you go.
So it's about 20 thousand lines of code, I guess.
And keep in mind, right?
That is all-inclusive.
So there's no libraries in here, right?
That has everything.
In its entirety.
Loading bitmaps initialize, the renderer, the software, renderer, the
simulation everything.
Sound playback, there's no libraries at all.
So we are that is every line of code.
The only thing right now that we don't have in our own code is like a
couple math.
Functions are calling the C runtime Library like sine and cosine.
But that's it.
And we don't use any data structures from anyone else.
Either we don't use
Like all the data structures we write ourselves so we write our own
linked list or on hash table, whatever.
We don't use anything so 20,000 all inclusive.
And we could get that number down it's bigger than it needs to be at
the moment.
We could we could certainly slim things down to fourteen thousand
lines.
Probably I would I would imagine pretty easily also that includes the
software renderer
Right, so the software renderer is in there as well.
We haven't updated it to the new format yet, but it has a complete
software renderer
Capable of rendering the game when it was in 2D at 60 frames a second,
actually, in software.
So that was in there too.
So yeah, we could get that down a bit and maybe we will try at some
point but it's also going to get larger separately because we're going
to have to put a bunch of game code in there, right?
Because we're going to have to put a bunch of monster code in a bunch
of world, gencode in there.
And that code tends to be a little big because it's just a bunch of
random, you know, human decided things.
This monster does this thing.
And he, you know, hits you for this, many points of damage and all
that sort of stuff.
So, you know, that's going to increase the line count.
When we start putting that stuff in there,
As well.
All right.
Okay.
I'm a wind on down.
Thank you everyone for joining me for this episode of handmade hero.
It's been a pleasure coding with you.
As always, if you
Want following the series at home, you can always pre-order the game
on handmade hero dot org and it comes with the source code so you can
play around with it at home.
We also have a forum so I can go to if you want to ask questions a
patreon page, if you want support the video series, schedule bot you
can use.
If you want to know when we're going to be live and an episode guide,
you can go to if you want to catch up on past episodes, that's about
it for today.
We will be back next week at which point we will probably do.
I think probably want to do the alpha fading level stuff.
So I think probably what we'll do is a break that into two parts.
One is, will clean up the camera code and try to make that kind of
final and then we'll sort of do the instrumentation of the render code
to make that work properly.
And at that point, I think we're in pretty good shape because then
we're kind of night in pretty smooth territory.
In terms of 3D this, we still have a few problems to iron out at the
moment, they're really not so much.
Problems with the structure of the code or anything, they're really
just more aesthetic problems.
I don't really know what we're going to do about sort of the problems
with how Sprites are, you know, sorted in the world with with blocks
and that sort of stuff.
Now that we have the Z buffer in the Z bias in there, it's pretty good
but we still have some problems.
When things pass through other things and I don't know, we might have
to think about it a little bit harder or we may need to shrink things
down a little bit so that they fit in the world a little bit cleaner.
I don't know.
We've got some work to do there and that's just some stuff that's it's
really just about decision.
Making about how we want to sort of fit the two dienes into the 3D
world that's about it.
I hope to see you back here next week for that until then have fun
program everyone and I'll see you all on the internet.
Take it easy, everybody.