Hello, everyone, and welcome to handmade hero.
The show we could have complete game live on stream.
No engines, no libraries.
It's just our code here.
Running the entire thing right down to rendering the pixels.
We don't even call the GPU, if you can believe that.
Right now, we're in the middle of doing some, debug code for
ourselves, we decided it was time to have some nice debugging tools
that we could, you know, use to better visualize what our code is
doing.
And make it easier to find bugs that are in the code.
When we have
Or even, just to even know that the bugs are there.
Sometimes you can have very subtle bugs and if you don't have good
visualization, you'll kind of there will be something wrong but you
can't.
It's hard to put your finger on it or some things are acting strange.
You don't really know why and stuff like that.
So good to bugging code can be very good for a number of reasons.
It shortens the debugging time but also lets you find more total bugs
than you would have found.
Otherwise specially kind of subtle performance bugs or things like
that that are kind of tricky to find sometimes with traditional
debugging.
So that's what we're doing right now.
This is going to be pretty much all coding here because we have a
bunch of stuff that we want to do.
So there's not going to be much Exposition, we already talked about it
on the previous two days, so it's going to be all coding it today is
what day 178 if you would like, to follow along with the coding at
home.
And you were one of the folks who pre-ordered the game on handmade
hero dot-org, you will want to unpack day, 177, the source code from
day.
One.
77 is what I'll be starting on day here on day one 78.
So go ahead and do that.
You will be where I am right now, and where am I right now?
Well, let's take a look.
Let's take a look.
So, you know, if you remember correctly, last time we had just kind of
put in the ability to do some automatic debug automatic performance
counter stuff that improved upon the stuff that we had before but
there's a bunch of stuff that we would like to do this for starters.
We were just using the font code that we had in there before that we
wrote but that was, you know, using a very large font, right?
That we were using for testing.
So we could see the
What's up, you know, nice and close and all that sort of thing.
And so obviously, you know, if you know, if you look at that, that's
not going to be a very effective way to do a debug display to say, the
very least because I mean, you know, nothing for nothing but you ain't
gonna fit a lot of debug information on the screen if that's the size
of your font.
So what we probably want to do at this point is go over to our asset
Packer and ask it to pack up for us up.
A tiny font you know a font that's going to be
You know legible you know, barely legible for us but that fits a lot
of information on the screen at once.
I think that's basically what we're going to look for and maybe we
want also a monospaced font because we don't have really much in the
way of any kind of advanced typography.
So you know, our debug print outs are not going to be laid out pretty
or anything.
That.
So we may want like Mah no space for something.
So that we can line things up, manually with spaces, you know, old
school, editor style, which, you know, we've talked about this before.
It's probably why, you know, editors these days still use monospace
fonts is because they don't have good typography.
So we don't have good typography there.
And so, our debug layout should probably be something in a monospace
font.
I would think so.
Let's just get that going.
Let's just, you know, do a little bit of that first just so we can
kind of be in a better position to start.
About what we want to do with that debug display, how we want to get
that kind of working a little bit more, more fully.
So in the acid Packer here, I think we have a thing that writes out
fonts by themselves.
Am I wrong about that?
I think this is it.
Yeah, so you can see this writing out the fonts here.
So what I'd like to do is, you know,
Like to have some way, probably a picking fonts I guess we haven't
really done much with that yet in terms of picking fonts, so maybe we
want to do that as well.
What we could do here is in our handmade asset .h, we don't really
have much in the way of support for like selecting things
specifically, but our tag system can totally be used for that, right?
We can make basically and a set of enumerated tags for lack of a
better term, right?
And we can go ahead and sort of say that we want a specific type of
font.
So if I look at the
All formats.
For example, we've got, you know, sort of these things facing
Direction, Unicode code point, that stuff we could have something in
here that's like font type, right?
And we could say, you know, something in here where it's like, you
know, zero is a debug or, like the default game font one is like the
debug font or something, you know, or maybe we want to do something a
little bit further up.
So then case we want to use something else, you know, we could do
something like this.
In fact, we could
even do something like this, right?
Asset font type and we could do like font type default.
And font type.
Debug, you know, and we could just use those.
So if we wanted to do that again we really shouldn't have to you know
we haven't really done a whole lot of testing of our asset system but
I suspect it all this stuff is probably totally fine.
We'll find out but we'll go in here and just say, Okay, I want to set
this to be the default font or something, right?
And then, I can go in here and sort of do the exact same thing, you
know, with the with, with a different font.
So I can just say, all right, let's let's make another.
Here.
Maybe I can even just kind of bracket that off.
I could even make this just be a thing that we do for all our fonts.
So I could I could just do like something like internal void, add font
like this and just kind of grab this whole thing, you know, and do
that.
And that way I can just have different.
Fonts where I can say which fonts I want them to be.
So I can just say, all right, you know,
What's the font file?
What's the font name?
You know so then in here we just go
like so add font.
And again I'm not really doing anything interesting here.
All I'm doing is just you know trying to make it.
So it's easy for us to have two fonts in here which we've never really
tried before.
So as we should have probably tested that before we moved on.
But you know what you going to do?
God do stuff as it comes up.
So yeah, you know, start with that and we can say now that we've got
that font name font file and font name.
Let's go ahead and compile this and make sure this all work site,
okay, it's got a, got to have the assets obviously.
So pass that in there and then, yeah.
Looks good.
So if we want to add a new font, so this tag here, we'd want to pass
that font type in, right?
Because we don't know what the type should actually be.
So we can say, you know, which type of font we want and there's the
type there so we can just go ahead and say, all right.
That's that's going to be this and then we can do another one where we
pass font type debug and the font type that we would want for debug.
You know, I guess I probably just use this one here that we've got
Liberation mono, like C program, Windows fonts, Liberation, mono
regular, you know, something like this.
And and so in there, I would just say, okay, you know, see Windows
fonts Liberation law, no like that.
And then, you know, I don't actually know what the name of that one
is.
I think it's
Liberation space mono, di Tri it Liberation mono but I guess I could
also see Windows fonts.
Oops.
I could just see what it says.
The name of that is so, where is Liberation mono Liberation?
But there's a lot of fonts on here.
I think this machine is said lots of things installed on it.
Like you know, it had Adobe Premiere on it at one point or and like
other package like that because we used to use it for other things.
And so now that it's been like kind of replaced as a, as a streaming
machine, doesn't actually joining us.
That all these fonts you nowhere,
Fill in there.
Yeah.
So just Liberation mono.
So that's, I think that's fine.
That's what I use in my editor, so maybe we'll use that.
So if I do Liberation mono, let's go ahead and compile this.
And I'd tag tag font type.
Let's see free from asset font type to real 52, possible loss of data.
Well, you know what?
Let's just go ahead and cast it then.
No harm, no foul.
So now that we've done that, I don't know, that's going to pack some
fun stuff in there, and that's fine.
So we'll go ahead and see what happens if I run.
It will go to the data directory.
And we'll run build test asset Builder.
So yeah.
Let's see what happened there.
Well, the test fonts got about twice as big which is I think exactly
what we would hope for and of course we still haven't quite done.
What?
We still haven't picked.
A smaller size is still going to be huge but at least we can test the
Dual font thing which will give us some perspective on whether we're
working, right?
And then we can go ahead and try to add that that size in there
separately.
Oh dear.
So we do have some kind of a bug here.
It looks like right.
Oh you know what?
Well, no.
I rebuilt the fonts.
And then we reran.
So I'm not sure why we're getting a bug there.
Oh dear.
So, our asset count is massively wrong.
So, something very bad has happened during loading these files.
As you can see,
Well I guess we don't necessarily have a problem with the tagging but
we do have a problem with something else.
So why are we getting that problem?
Why are we expecting to load a lot more of these than we actually
loaded.
That's a little bit weird, right?
Hmm.
Well we know we merge multiple files properly so I guess I don't know
why this would have had any particularly unusual sort of operation to
it.
I don't know why we would be getting some kind of a weird situation
just from that.
However, you know, let's just go ahead and step through it and see see
what our what our actual problem is.
What I'd like to do first is I'm going to go ahead and delete
everything but the font one just so we can
Narrow it down to one thing and just see if there's you know, just
make it a little easier on ourselves.
We don't have to debug all these other guys, the same time.
So we've got like test1 test2, all that stuff.
Let's just get rid of those.
So now all we have is test fonts dot hhha.
So all we're doing is loading the fonts
It says that where it should be expecting 201, fonts asked us to come
in instead, we only get 101.
So we're basically, you know, we're missing essentially well you know
you can kind of see what's happening there.
Almost already.
We're missing one entire character set for some reason, right?
I mean, there's just it's just gone.
So something.
Is a little bit fishy.
So I'm going to go ahead and step in here and see if I can see what's
going on.
Hopefully, it's something not particularly to nefarious.
So as I come in here, let's see which desk type ID.
I'm actually looking at this is the this is the asset type count,
right?
So we only have one file.
Here is the file.
It should be the test fonts AJ file, right?
And let's see what it's got.
The asset type array.
How many of these actually are there so far in the file.
Let's get the header.
So the asset type count is 19, which seems a little odd because I
don't know why it would have all those additional types in there.
I guess.
Maybe we just kind of spammed those dinner, something like this, I'm
not entirely sure the asset count is 201 which I think is what we
would expect 104.
Fine.
And then the 0 the reserve 0, there's the tags having 44 tags does
seem a little bit odd, right?
Because it's a, it's a bit strange to only have 44 tags when you have
this many assets because each of them should have like like where are
all those tax coming from, right.
It's a little bit.
That's a little bit odd.
I think in and of itself asset types.
I know what's going on, right?
Right, tag count.
I'm looking at the wrong one.
Tags is just the offset in the file.
I just got confused there, so don't worry about that.
I take back what I said, but I count of three that seems fine asset
type count.
We probably just write them all out, even if there's zero, so that's
fine.
So all of this actually looks totally reasonable at first blush.
I'm actually fine with it.
I just got a little confused, reading it there anyway.
So let's continue on.
When we look here, they said, we're not reading font glyphs yet.
We're just reading type ID 0 and turns out.
There's none of those anyway.
So since there's none of them were not actually going to do anything
there and that's fine.
This is I think that's going to be true.
Pretty much the whole way through.
Right?
It is a little weird.
So death type ID, let's see here.
Let's go through, let's go through.
To see where we're at.
So under the file, indices under the source index,
The Source type ID should be something else.
Right?
Why are there so many Source types with zero?
Like why is that type ID?
Always 0?
I feel like our thing that writes out our assets is doing something a
little bit wonky, wouldn't you agree?
Let's let me I want to
I don't like the look of that that looks just kind of wrong.
So I would like to take a brief look to see how it's actually writing
that out, its writing out this asset types array, right?
And so what does it actually do there?
Where is that asset types getting set right?
And and I'd like to kind of, in fact, you know what I can do to before
we go any further in this, let me just jump over to that asset
processor and let's just actually see what
Doing because it seems like it's just not it seems like it's actually
a little janky and even though this may have nothing to do with the
bug that we're seeing eye.
When I see something janky, I prefer to go find out what's going on.
Because, you know, I'd like to always understand what the code is
doing and if I don't, if something doesn't make good sense, I should
at least figure out what it's doing first before declaring that it's
fine, you know.
All right.
So yeah, it looks like the way this works.
Is it never actually initializes the type ID for these guys.
Or something.
Like the type ID maybe only gets initialized if the thing is ever used
and that seems a little bit odd but there it is.
And yeah I guess that's I guess.
That's exactly what would happen.
It grabs that particular one there.
Okay.
You know what?
This is probably the bug because this probably happens.
Yeah, that happens twice, right?
So we don't really want to do that.
That way.
I don't know if you can see that, so that actually that, actually, if
that's not the bug, it is at least something that would in totally
cause the bug.
So it's at least part of its, it is at least totally wrong and would
do exactly what I just said.
Because if you, if you look at what happens here, every time we go to
start adding a particular asset type.
When we do begin asset type, you can only call that once.
And so I think
Calling it twice.
And so we should probably make it so that, you know,
we should probably make it.
So that that's an error, at the very least, I would think let's take a
look here at how that's at how that works out.
So in the test asset Builder,
Dude, you do again asset type in the test asset Builder.
This thing is going to get called when we do the ad font, right?
Pretty sure the add font actually, just does that?
Oops,
Yeah, you can see it, does the begin asset type.
And then, you know, you can't reopen these asset types, right?
So that's that's just not cool.
And you know, I don't know if I really want to upgrade this thing
because like I said, this is just kind of a
It's not really meant to be a, it's not really.
To be a full-fledged system, you know, it's just supposed to be an
example of one so I don't know that.
I really want to spend a lot of time making it better than it is than
it is, but that's not going to work like, right?
That's not going to work at all.
And so, what we would want to do, for example is we'd want to go
through like the fonts and so maybe, you know what, here's a pretty
easy way that I could do it.
I could just make it.
So that in here we do those fonts like as a group, right?
So in here I just go through for each font and do this.
All right, so I go like, you know, font index.
Zero less than like array count fonts or something font index, or
whatever.
You know what I mean?
Add all the characters do the little dance.
Have a little party and then here, when we begin asset type just do
the same thing, right?
That seems like a reasonable compromise, you know, something that's
not too much of an annoyance.
And so then what I can do is in here, I can say, Okay, loaded font,
you know, fonts
Bracket.
And then I can just go ahead and load the actual fonts.
Like so,
Poop.
There we go.
And then what I would need to do is I need to store I guess it's a
slightly another piece of information.
Like you know I don't know, desired font something like this.
I would need to store which of the tags.
I want with it.
There, I guess.
In fact, maybe, I don't even want to do that.
Maybe I want to be able to do the tagging more explicitly.
So probably what I'd do is I'd still just do it this way and then I'd
add the tag down here, right?
I do the tag adding down here.
So, something like this.
Add font asset.
And then I pass the font, right?
Like so.
Oops.
And and then I'd add the tags that I want for that, fine.
Yeah, that seems fine to me and I suppose I could also even do
something.
If I was so inclined, I could actually make it even a little bit
different than this.
I could make it so that I just pass which font I want to this thing,
and have this actually be a little routine, so I don't even have to
put them in an array, but I don't know.
I don't know if that's worth it.
So I'll just go like this for now and leave it that seems fine.
so then that elude those fonts
and then we'll have loaded font font equals fonts plus font index and
that'll just enumerate over the fonts
so,
Yeah, so that we have other characters for them.
And that seems fine.
Again, this is not really supposed to be particularly good code and
isn't so that's fine.
That's going to be a comma.
and, and
Cannot to a pointer to a pointer.
All right well
I'm not sure what this is, shouldn't that be an array of pointers to
loaded fonts so load font, or oh, does load font actually just
returned a loaded font?
Now that's right.
So, that should be fine.
What is the complaint loaded font star star to loaded font?
Oh yeah, sorry, just a little mental.
It's a little mental break there.
All right, so now we've got to do is we have to fix sort of the
Fix the rest of this stuff.
We've got to add it.
The ability to change the size of the font as well, right?
So this, hopefully will fix the bug that we had were the fonts were
being written out in properly, but let's verify that first.
So there's run the test a set builder and let's take a look at what
we've got.
We'll go ahead and see what happens now.
If I run the actual game, there we go.
So now let's see.
If we can pick a different font, let's let's go in here and see maybe
in handmade that CPP.
What I'd like to do is say when we go to pick our font here for the
overlay cycle counters and that sort of stuff, we need to find the
font that we're actually going to do debug text line.
Here's that push font with the font ID.
So I'm going to take whatever font it was getting from the font ID
when we do the weight vector,
I feel like that wants to be set now so I can pick which font I want.
So yeah if I do that I want to set the font type and where exactly is
that asset Vector its dot e.
So there there it is.
Tidy.
We go.
So that weight Vector, I want to go ahead and set the font type thing
to, like I want to make sure I get it and then I want my match, Vector
to be, you know, whatever.
That
Debug value was there so font type debug, so we'll grab that out.
And then we'll see if we get a different font.
And we do lovely.
So that's great.
That lets us pick our fonts.
Now, by just using the tag system, we can set our tags and get
different fonts out of it.
And that's exactly what I wanted.
Because, I believe, at least, I believe that that is a different font.
Of course, it's hard to always know.
Let's double-check
Yeah, so we can get different fonts and that's the party great.
Everyone's happy.
Everyone wins.
It's fantastic.
It's fine.
Totally fine.
So now I want to make it so that I can specify the size that I
actually want for these fonts.
Because right now, when we load a font, I think the size is just hard
coded into it, right?
We just in the load font, we never bothered to make it so that you can
pass something and we just set it to something.
So let's just say that this is the pixel height here.
And then will, you know go in somewhere and wherever that height value
was, will put it here.
We're going to go ahead and make all our clothes to load font actually
specify that value, right?
So we had 128 before so we'll keep that.
But then for our Liberation mono I don't actually know what, what am I
actually using here 11-point?
Well that's eleven point.
I don't know what the pixels are.
I don't know, we'll just try saying 12 pixels high, but I have
absolutely no idea.
So hopefully, that'll do something resembling anything.
And I don't know where, well, we'll find out.
All right, so let's see what happens if I run it.
All right, we're still, we're still using the aerial there.
So, now, let me switch it back to the debug font and see if we get a
smaller font.
That's one that we could, you know, debug with little bit better.
All right.
So, that may be a little too tiny.
That's a little too tiny even for me and you know, obviously you guys
are in a situation where you would see even less than I can see at
this point.
So, so that's, that's not great.
Not not great.
Not great.
So, let's, let's, you know, just give it a little bit more room to get
a little bit more room, the sake of the stream.
Let's let's go ahead up to 20 and see if that helps at all.
All right.
So that's a little bit more reasonable.
I don't know if that'll be super readable on stream, but you know it
since this is our debug display, I think we're just gonna have to live
with the fact that, you know, you got to be at 1080P or something.
If you want to be able to read the debug display with me.
It's a debug display people, okay?
It's got to fit a lot of information on the screen if it's going to be
useful.
So that's just, that's just how it's going to go.
You're going to have to live with it but there we go.
Now we've got our stuff.
Looking looking pretty correct.
You can see that.
Game update and render.
Like I've talked about before is wrong because of course, it stays
open because the renderer is, you know, it's is the thing that's
actually drawing a.
Do you like to play?
So, like I mentioned at the end of last frame, we got to do some stuff
to actually get these to be correct for profiling, the render as well,
which is obviously something we want to profile, but our one called,
we know that is make being made and completes is in here.
You can see that it's got its cycle counts and that cycle costs were
hit and it's got the number of hits as well, so that's pretty handy.
And if I go in, now we can start to kind of see what would happen if
we wanted to start using this a little bit more.
Seriously are a little time flock function, right?
So here we are in handmade dot CPP, you know, I could start to, to add
profiling to this very, very quickly.
Now, I don't really have anywhere in particular that I want to
profile, I suppose but you know, let's say we wanted to start
profiling things.
Probably not going to be in this file right there.
Going to be in somewhere else.
So let's say we want our Sim region stuff to be profiled and so we're
just going to start profiling this stuff, right?
So here's our move entity call.
It's time that
Right here is our entities overlap call.
I don't know time it.
Why not speculative kalai?
I don't know.
I mean, I'm not even really pretending to be reasonable at this point.
I'm just kind of spamming these guys in here, because why not?
Guess what we can do this now because we have the power.
So I've just spamming these things in anywhere.
I want to, I don't care.
It's fine.
It's all fine.
So we'll put those in there and now we'll recompile.
And again this is exactly what I wanted out of the debug system
because now we just run it and hey, look.
Now we can see like where everything is happening and what's going on,
right?
So we can immediately see what our cycle counts are through all of our
code you know we can we can kind of see what's going on in there
without having to like stop and do a custom kind of a profile run or
something like that.
And I can keep going like that in anything that we've got in here,
right?
I can, I can keep going for, for whatever, whatever stuff we've got.
So I don't know if handmade entities, got anything in it and I don't
think it really does know.
Let's see.
Handmade
What else we got in here?
Canned made.
Asset audio math.random Sim region handmade World dot CPP.
So let's see what's in there.
Change entity location will time that changing any location raw will
time.
That anything in here.
That's got other stuff, get World chunk, totally.
That let's see what else we got.
Render groups, we probably want a Time, those right?
An optimized and all that stuff but we've got some stuff to talk about
there but I'm going to I'm going to drop those in there anyway because
we might as well drop them in there like audio in the render groups,
you might as well put in there.
So let's see here.
We've got play sound time that we've got up a playing sounds will time
that
Let's go ahead and do the render group as well.
Right.
Render group.
What do we got to see?
Draw a rectangle or time?
That sample environment map.
These aren't even really getting cold at this point but that's okay.
Draw a bitmap sure just in case, change saturation.
I don't know what that does.
Probably some stuff I did.
Because someone asked me on the stream to do it and that's fine.
Put this in here.
And let's see what else.
Render group to Output tiled, render group to Output timed block.
I'm just putting these everywhere.
Just try and stop me, you know, just try.
I dare you getting render and render.
These are just the pushes, get ready to render entity basis P.
Probably not necessary to time.
But why not?
All of the pushes here we can do that.
Sure will time it?
Why not anything else here?
Okay, so now we've just basically, we did exactly what I said I
wanted, which is it's free.
Now, for us to just time those things, we can spam them everywhere.
And now we just have a ton of heads-up information, right, that we can
use.
But we've got, there's a bunch of problems.
So first off, like I said, we've got one here that you can see that I
talked about before which is that the timings for anything that
encloses the rendering are just totally wrong, right?
Because they the block that's timing them is open when it actually
gets printed.
So we have to do something to delay, our timings by like one frame and
like put them somewhere and print out the timings from the previous
frame.
For example, so that we can have those
To be closed before we go to try to access them.
So that's, we need to do that to finish.
Go up updated render so that's one problem.
Second problem we have
Right.
Is that when we go to do some of these other performance counters, we
don't actually we're not thread safe.
So anything that might be called from multiple threads, is, could have
totally,
Results.
Right.
Because as if two threads open and close the blocks together, or
whatever, we have, no idea what's going to go on there, right?
And furthermore, those threads could be running doing something while
we're printing it out which means the block could again be open.
So we have more work to do if we want this system to be able to handle
everything and maybe we don't, maybe we'll get to something and say
okay this is a little too hard, maybe we won't try to, you know, make
it work at that but we should at least start trying to push a little
bit.
Either in now to sort of shore up the system a little bit more
completely, right?
All right.
But even without even if we didn't do any of that, this still gives us
a tremendous tremendously, more useful picture, right of what we're
doing.
Because if you can see here, we definitely have.
You know, if you look at what's going on,
You can see that already, we can see a bunch of cycle counts.
A bunch of hit counts.
We know like how many times we you know how many before we had no
idea.
How many render elements we pushed for frame.
Now we know we push about 760, right?
We know it takes about thirty eight Cycles to push one of those blah,
blah blah, right?
So there's actually stuff.
And I mean, keep in mind that the cycle cast, this is not an optimized
build.
So the cycle counts are not that meaningful because they're going to
those Cycle house would go down if we compiled an optimized mode.
So there's that
Right.
But, you know, at the very least, we're already starting to get some
more sort of a feel for what our program is doing, which is exactly
what we want from this debug code.
Even just that very little that we added, yesterday already gives us a
tremendous tremendously more insight into what's happening, right?
So the first things first, let's take a look and see if we can find or
think through some ways.
In which we could address some of these problems at the very least, I
think we should be able to solve the one of something's open during
the render because all we have to do is delay our results by one
frame, right?
So let's see if there's anything that we can we can do there to make
that happen a little bit better.
So right now what happens is when we do our overlay cycle counters
that is the thing that does the reset.
So what happens here is when we actually call in to this
One who's going to be over, you know, going to have the cycle.
Counters overlaid had better be closed by now.
So, what we need is, we need a way of having that sort of closure
happen.
We need a way of having that sort of heartbeat, do some kind of like a
copy.
So that every time at the end of the frames it does like a copy of
that memory.
So that we know that it's, you know, not being used.
It's not in the middle of being used.
so thinking of through,
I think.
Let's, let's talk about this on the white bar because I think,
actually there's some kind of creative things we could do here.
I think,
You know, I think I take it back.
Let's start with the threaded one.
Let's start with a threaded one instead, because I'm kind of
interested in to see.
I'm kind of interested in thinking about the threaded one first.
So let's do that.
Okay, so here we are.
It's day.
So let's do thread safe.
Performance.
Counters.
All right.
So thing number one, right, take a look at the way that I implemented.
The performance counters here, because it's not the smartest way to
that we could have done it.
So, do you see what I did?
What I did is I add the hit count, that's fine.
But when I do it, the our dtsc is, I just take the cycle count, I
subtract first.
The rdcs see value.
Then, I add back in and what that's essentially doing.
Is it subtracting the start time from the end time, right?
Well, that means that if another thread were to come in here at this
time and
Read what the cycle count was they'd get a completely ridiculous value
because it's using that as like a temporary buffer, okay?
So, what's happening essentially, you know, is you can you can imagine
let me try to give a little bit more maybe of a specific thing there.
What we have is we have our total, right?
And we do our total, minus the clock value, right?
And we write that out to the new Total and then we do our total right.
Plus this is like clock start.
Let me, let me write this, in a slightly born Matthew way we subtract
out the start value.
Right.
And that gives us a, I suppose our T1, and then we take our T1 and we
add in the clock and time and that gives us our T2, right?
And so, if we expand out what that actually ends up being the goal
here is to end up with C minus CS, right?
The starting clock time, the the ending clock time, minus the starting
clock time is the Delta clock time, right.
That's the Delta clock time.
That we actually want to add in there.
How many clocks elapsed?
Well,
we're counting on, you know, we're doing that through here, but that
means in between here.
Any thread that views this value?
Even if we did everything properly, any thread, that looked at the
value would get T1, right?
But T1 is not valid T1 is, never an actual total thread.
Performance time, t0 was, and T2 is, but T1 is a valid clock time -
some absolute clock value.
It's totally bogus, right?
So we just want to make sure that we never have a T1 in there.
We want to make sure we go right from t0 to T2 so that anytime you
observe the thread value.
It's correct.
And that's really easy for us to do, right?
All we have to do is do the start Cycles here.
Like so.
And then instead of modifying the cycle count, we just never, we just
don't have to ever write to that, right?
We would we would never actually have to do that.
We could just go ahead and say, all right, take the cycle count here.
And add to it, whatever the start Cycles was, which will record.
Whatever the start Cycles.
Was subtract that out.
There's the Delta cycles and then we'll just record, you know, we'll
get that will take the cycle count and we'll increment it by this.
So now we would know that no matter when another thread goes in there,
it's going to be correct.
So that's all good.
All right, but we've got another problem.
We've got another kind of little ugliness, right?
And the ugliness, is that if you take a look at what happens here, and
we've got to do thread safety thing here.
If you take a look what happens, two of us, could be trying to modify
the hit count or the cycle count at the same time.
Now we don't care if two people are modifying these values because
these values are just always going to get overwritten with the same
with the correct information.
So it doesn't matter at.
All right, does not matter in any way.
It's a totally Superfluous, right?
But the hit count and the cycle count, we want to modify atomically.
So, what we want to do here is we want to do a locked increment of the
hit count so that it can kind of accumulate.
So, we'd rather do here is, we'd rather have our, handmade intrinsics,
and I'm going to feel stupid for removing it because we have Atomic
increment here and I think I removed it.
Oops.
Do what we want to do is go, okay, atomic.
Increment.
And we probably want to do, I don't know, you know how many cycles is
going to take it.
I'm going to take more than four billion cycles.
Probably not.
So we could do 32-bit Atomic increment, right?
You could do atomic increment.
You 32.
We could say what we want.
Here is the record cycle.
Count, tried the record hit count.
We want to atomically increment that by this, right?
Or this is really Tha mehcad, right?
So, you want to do an atomic add?
We want to do the same thing for the cycle count, right?
So Atomic, add the cyclic.
count cast this to you 32, like so,
and so, as long as the process,
It's Atomic ad, which they all do.
We don't even have to do any kind of compare exchange locking.
None of that, we just say, okay, we needed to, we need to be an atomic
ad and off we go, okay.
It's very, very straightforward.
And let's go ahead and do this here dealt the time.
Let's go ahead and pull that out like so just so you can see very
carefully where the atomics are.
So I'm just now I just need that function, right?
I need Atomic add you 32.
The volatile and the at end.
When we do the interlocked, I think this is just interlocked add.
I think that's all we really need a tent and there's the result of the
comes.
I think, that's probably all we need to do, but I'm not sure.
Let's take a look in Turlock, ad.
Wow.
Locked pair Exchange.
Intrinsic functions.
Excuse me.
Please load up my intrinsic functions.
Add, that's not the end.
I don't like didn't actually want those.
Those were not the ones I wanted.
I wanted the other list.
That for mips who still programs mips seriously.
All right.
So let's see here, let's let's get some interlocked compiler
intrinsics
Oh wait, is it up here?
There it is.
That's the one.
Interlock exchange dad.
It's not a good one.
Do you like that, compiler?
Yes, you do.
Okay.
So I'm going to take a look at interlocks change dad.
With the underscore.
Like so I just want to see what returns.
This doesn't tell me what it returns.
Why does it not tell me the initial value of the variable pointing to
the by the atom?
So it's the one that comes back.
originally, so
This note, Casey.
Returns the original value prior to adding
And I'm just going to take a blind guess at this one.
Well, let's get this one right first, but I'm going to take a blind,
guess at the llvm one and then the people on the forums can tell me
what it is.
Because I've implemented before I know VM.
So I should be able to maybe get close in 64.
Yes, that's fine.
There we go.
Cannot convert.
Oh, the cycle.
Count was a you.
Third eye doesn't need to be any more.
It does not need to be at all, which means we've actually got a pad in
here.
We could, you know, we could do something creative with it.
and yeah, you know, we could even
Now we can prep because the hit counts probably going to could, could
in theory rap, if we were counting something large.
So I'm gonna, I'm gonna, I'm not gonna try to pack that down further,
right?
You could imagine doing oops, you could imagine doing that and getting
it down a little bit further, but I'm just I'm just not I'm just not
gonna do it.
All right, so let's take a look at this.
Now that certainly doesn't look good.
All right, so we're not quite there yet.
We've got a little bit of work to do.
It's true.
That's totally fine.
So what exactly have I?
What if I, what if I ruined?
What kind of a life have I ruined for us?
What have I done?
Let me just go back in here as well.
I want to do one more thing which is let's see.
In my print out routine.
In here.
I also want to change these guys to be
I actually want to change these guys around slightly.
So what I would like that way, what I would like to do here is I'd
like to do a exchange of these.
I'd like to do an atomic exchange of these guys so that we can
actually do the reset atomically as well.
That makes sense.
Now we could actually do something kind of crazy.
Oh man.
I'm kind of thinking that we could do something kind of awesome here.
So what we could also do, I won't quite do it yet.
So you know what I'm not going to quite do this yet.
I'm not going to do it yet but we're gonna do it.
It's just I'm not going to get because if there was a bug in my thing
before so we're just we're not going to be yet, then I'm going to do
it.
We're going to, we're going to, we're totally going to do it.
We got 10 minutes left for it's so good to do it.
We're so totally going to do it.
So I movie funny, let's find the bug first.
Let's just find the bug first, right?
So, okay, what do we have going on here?
That's probably just because we're printing out.
I-64 is when these are not I-64.
So let's get rid of that first and that'll fix that.
Okay.
And then let's go take a look and we'll see that.
Looks a little more.
Reasonable.
Certainly.
Now things are looking pretty, calm and fun.
Okay.
So, yeah, alright.
We've totally fine.
So now what I'd like to do is I'd like to make sure this is atomic as
well, because why not?
And what I was thinking is we could actually make sure that the cycle
count in the hit.
Count are, actually always updated atomically together, by just
merging them into one, you 64.
So we could basically, you know, do something where we have the hit
count on the top and the cycle count on the bottom.
Or something like this, and furthermore, that means we could have, we
could steal some bits.
So the hit count in the cycle.
Count could actually not both be 32.
If we wanted the cycle count to be able to go over 4 billion, we
could, I don't know if we do, but we could
It leaves our that ability open to us, right?
So how that would work is we'd have our hit count here right?
And the hit count Jimmy
Would just get stored.
So hit count.
Bulls head count in it like that and instead of doing the atomic adieu
32 cure you would not do that at.
All right?
We would just snap the start Cycles.
That's the only thing that would happen.
We would stop the start cycle.
Now what there's another thing that's kind of annoying here.
Again, this is just the part about.
I wish we could sort of pass something to the destructor of this
thing.
You know, like kind of say that at the bottom, I want to do something
else.
I'd have to think about.
There's some way we can do that.
I don't think there really is, but
Not an issue at the immediate moment.
But when we do this Delta time here, right?
What I can do now is, I can say, okay, take the Delta time as a user,
you 64 then, or in the hit count as a you 64.
Shift it up by 32 bits.
Right?
Then we just do one Atomic.
Add you 64 to the hit count cycle count with just the Delta of both.
That makes sense.
And so then instead of our intrinsic being about a u-32, it's actually
about a you 64,
That makes sense.
So then we do an interlocked exchange, add 64.
And I guess I don't really know what it wants us to pass for that on
msv.
See just an underscore underscore in 64, okay?
That would allow us to be completely Atomic.
The whole way through which is pretty sweet.
So then we have our hit count here.
We have our cycle count here and that's just going to be, you know,
the the end, I'll grab this out here.
So we've got the what's that thing called?
D-damn ladybug, can't, what's hit can't cycle count, right?
So the hit count cycle count, we grab it out like that.
Then we say, okay, whatever the hit count is, is just going to be this
thing shifted down by 32.
Right.
And the cycle count is just going to be that same thing with the top.
Mast out of it.
So and 0xffff ffff, right?
Just get those just those bottom fits.
So then we've got the hit, count the cycle count, we've extracted
them.
And now we just use them as if we had stored them, that way to begin
with, right?
Pretty easy.
And now for clearing, we also just do counter hit count cycle.
Count equals zero.
So we just clear one value and it clears the whole thing, right?
And so, in theory, that is now allows us to be completely Atomic with
the ad.
Which means that now there's no possibility of, you know, getting the,
the getting the cycle count with the wrong hit count and Reporting the
time wrong because when we divide by the cycle count to get the number
of cycles per invocation, if this, if they hit count was off by one
because someone's block hadn't finished updating the hit count, but
had finished up.
Kidding.
The cycle count, we would have
Sort of like missed report for just that one, right?
So we don't have that problem anymore or I should say we almost don't
have that problem anymore.
Our read from this thing and are reset, are not Atomic and we would
like those to be because we don't want to read from it and then reset
it after and miss an invocation, because then, we might, we might
miss, we'd miss one invocation of the thing, right?
That we were trying to count so that we can also fix by just having an
atomic exchange, right?
So we have a stomach exchange, you 64.
That's going to take a you 64 volatile and it's going to take a you 64
new.
It's essentially exactly the same as comparing exchange but instead of
ever doing it compared it's just always going to do the exchange.
It doesn't care.
What the original value was, it's just going to swap them, no matter
what it is, because that's all we actually needed to do in this
circumstance, right?
So now we can call Atomic exchange on this guy, so that'll do the
clear and give us back the original value.
And that makes sure that now we're always reporting, we're always
clearing as we do the report so that nobody is ever going to be able
to get in there in between that and and have us overwrite it when we
clear, right?
Okay, so let's take a look and see if that works now.
alright, so now I think I think
we are actually printing things out in a relatively sane fashion, I
think.
I think.
We're thread safe.
Right?
I think no matter how many threads are pounding on that, at the same
time,
It's going to get some proper late.
And that's fine right now.
There's some things we might want to do to get better information
about that thread stuff.
But as you can see, we now have pretty stable reporting.
All of our accounts are lining up nicely are cycle counts, look
plausible.
So we're getting there, right?
We're getting there.
So that's pretty good.
And we get these very low overhead at this point.
There's very little going on that time.
Block thing and really there's only one Atomic operation which is
right here and you know,
Those atomic operations are not particularly expensive.
So we're in good shape.
This is pretty cool.
I think this is pretty darn, pretty darn cool.
But we're not quite done yet.
So, when we print these things out, we are only putting out the debug
records main.
We also remember have the optimized one.
So in here, we've got a Time block and we're not reporting that one
yet.
So what I'd like to do is go ahead and explain expand this out a
little bit right to do sort of a debug output debug records.
I don't know something where I can pass which array I'm
Trying to do.
And that way, it will be able to be called twice, right?
So if I do that, and I have a hero, you know, I should say to do stop
using standard IO, that's another thing we've got to do.
Because technically that's a library, even though it's built in to
see, it's still a library and I don't like using libraries.
That's not really the point on handmade hero, so we want to get rid of
that anyway.
So I want to pass here, whatever the the array count is so I need like
account, right?
Counter count, ironically enough and a debug record pointer
Counters.
And then here I can just do two of these output.
Debug records output debug records so I can output the array count for
debug records Main and the array count for debug records optimized.
Like so and past the pointers as well.
There we go.
So in here, then I can just do counter count and I can do counters.
Counters.
And now we can print out both.
I believe, let's see, who poops you go.
Debug records optimized is an Undeclared identifier.
Well guess what?
My friend a you're right.
That's true because it's right down here I believe but I'm gonna just
going to go ahead and pretty clear that for you so that you can print
it out.
Yeah, the problem is though, we won't know what the count is.
Hmm.
Hmm, we won't know what the county is.
So we're going to have to do one more thing, actually, right?
We're going to have to do this, debug records optimized count equals
counter.
Right.
And then that and I guess this is going to have to be a concert
because there's no other way to do it in C without saying const.
I believe, right?
Am I right about that?
So, there we go.
Unresolved external symbol on technique consti bug records?
Optimize count.
It's right there though.
Why?
Why are you not accepting it now?
Because I said an extern it.
All right, so now that we're looking up there looks like we're doing,
okay now that's a little odd.
Why is draw a rectangle quickly showing up twice?
It's a bit odd.
Don't you think?
Oh, I know why?
Because it's got two pieces to it.
Yeah so what we probably should do is do something like draw.
We should probably when we when we print this stuff out we probably
should do something like printing out the fuck.
The line number as well.
So then we can see that there's two different ones, right?
Lovely, isn't it?
Running with all these threads as well?
That means we could do other stuff too, right?
We could even go a little bit more hog-wild.
I gotta go to the Q&A here, we're almost out of time.
We're pretty much out of time, but I should say, well, if we're thread
safe, right?
We can just go ahead and put Phil Graham Chunk in there, right?
Although I guess that doesn't really make any sense because I was
doing you work.
So let me rephrase that
Put it in there.
How about handmade asset?
What about in here, load a set directly, we'll put that in there.
You know, find block for size acquire, asset memory.
Why isn't that time should be timed, right?
Course, it should be, everyone knows.
It should be timed loud, sound but bitmap
When it's free to do stuff, you do it, right?
And so you want to keep that you want to have that sort of path.
Of least resistance, be the right path because if the path of least
resistance is the right path, then you're always on it, right?
It's never a drudge work to do the right thing.
Boom.
And so, as we walk around, you can actually see those guys.
Come on their briefly like the as the ground chunks get filled, right?
That's what that's showing.
And so, that's a good another hint to of other stuff.
We're probably going to want to do because those things are only on
their very briefly will want ways to build a see what they were on
previous frames, right?
All right, so that's good for today.
Let's go ahead and go to the Q&A.
If you have a question that you would like to ask about what we did on
today's stream, please put it into the chat with a q: in front of it,
so that I can see it.
And SZ, this was again pretty awesome.
Thank you.
You are most welcome.
Thanks for tuning in.
The buzz.
Wouldn't a union be helpful for that?
Hit count cycle.
Count.
It just seems unnecessary having to remember their offsets and or
lengths when you're talking about an atomic exchange, I don't really
want to deal with that stuff like when I'm when I'm doing stuff like
using atomics I want to micromanage that because I just don't want to
have to think about what the C compiler is might have done or what the
C++ Committee in their infinite Testament.
Wisdom might decide to do with the Union that messes me up, right?
Let's see, Elven yesterday I asked about preprocessor, constant other
than found lying.
Sarah, I did some searching I found about time and date.
Maybe it's useful for us to include a time-date stamp in some of our
logs.
I mean maybe.
But remember the time and the date or the time of day of the
compilation so it's not particularly useful for us to have that other
than probably, you know, you know, maybe we bake that in just as a
thing when you're like, if you're trying to report a bug because so
you know which like build it was or something, but it doesn't really.
Help us probably beyond that.
Can you align the text into columns with with percent 32s in the
sprintf or something?
Yeah, I mean you could do
You know, I'm assuming you could do something like that if you were in
the so inclined.
Is that the actual Syntax for the string with though?
I don't actually remember.
So, if you wanted in columns, the cycle counts going to be tough,
right?
The cycle counts going to be like a bunch of things.
Let's see here.
Still not quite still, not quite right.
Is that?
Is that my we're looking for?
I should I need to remember to go make Loop live coding work with a
debug system because it's not much work to do that, but
So yeah, there you go.
Elvin you mentioned yesterday that destructors are called when the
scope of the object ends?
I just wanted to note.
It seems that if you use it to exit a function instead of return, then
the destructors won't get called if you use what to exit a function.
Like what do you mean by?
If you use it to exit a function,
To any McGee?
Will you marry me unfortunately?
I cannot
I'm already married and Seattle, well, Washington State, and I guess
the federal government in general does not allow polygamy.
In fact, Utah wanted to have it when they entered the Union, right?
I believe, but the federal government said no as one of the conditions
of joining so you only have one spouse.
Panic 00 won't already TSE.
Give wrong results.
If your thread is preempted and scheduled on to a different CPU
between the Constructor and Destructor calls.
Yes, well,
Okay, so
yes, it does.
But there is a, but
if you are concerned about that, which I am not particularly concerned
about because, you know, that'll just show up as a blip, right?
If you are
Concerned about that.
You can you can actually let me rephrase that.
So that is what I want to know, right?
I want to know that a blip occurred and I want to know where it
occurred and then I can later be like, okay, it was an operating
system task which or something like that.
That's all fine, right?
But if you're trying to time things and you want to take the the
context switch out of the equation, you can't do it entirely because
it's going to mess with their cash and all that kind of stuff.
So it's not like you can completely remove it but you do have the
option Windows.
Actually.
Really does a save and restore our dtsc thing.
It's like get thread cycle times or something like this.
Windows.
Get read cycle count.
I don't remember
Here it is.
So what this guy does is,
It's not that one.
It's this one.
No, it's not that one either.
Which one is it?
There is an actual call.
You can make to get the thing that you sound like you want.
And I just can't remember what it is, but it trust me, it's in here
somewhere.
They added it at a particular time, in Windows.
There's it that, where they'll actually save and restore the thing.
And it's not, it's said that one says, it's not what it is.
It says when says
I don't remember.
I'm sorry, I just don't remember what it is.
You can get the information you want?
They added a thing to Windows that would that will save the our dtsc
when the task of switched out.
And so it knows the amount that was used and will account for that.
So if that's really important to you just go, you can probably just
search online or something and find it, but there is a way to do that
in Windows.
I don't know if there's a way to do it, another os's,
Man, he's saying, are you working any other games other than handmade
hero?
Yes, I have some work, I'm doing on the witness, just at the end here
for some stuff.
And then I also am working full-time on a game.
It's a different game during the day, at Molly rocket, which hasn't
been announced yet?
Twist makes me.
It's General partner question.
Do you have any general advice for optimizing code performance,
multi-threading algorithm Flex, analysis cetera, go watch the streams
on optimizing optimizing that we've already done.
That's my first set of advice, we didn't do like, all the optimization
stuff, there's more to come, but go back and watch the ones on
optimization for intro.
K.
Sorry, I made a typo.
The first question you mentioned yesterday that is structures are
called when the scope of the obligations.
I just want to note.
It seems that if you use exit to exit a function instead of return
than the destructors won't get called.
So just to be clear, exit, doesn't exit a function, exit exits, your
application.
So the reason that the destructors don't get called in that case is
because you've terminated your process.
So, obviously, there are structures, can't get called because it's
been terminated
Does that make sense?
Exit doesn't exit a function, exit, exit, exit.
Closes the entire app.
Whist.
Uh so the values are pretty hard to read when they're changing,
literally every frame.
Wouldn't it be better to average them?
Well I wouldn't say it's better to average them necessarily but we as
you as we sort of go forwards with this, you'll see the stuff that I'm
going to do I have a bunch of things we're going to do in terms of
visualizing those values.
So yes, but we haven't gotten there yet.
Panic 00.
Have you considered keeping the timers in thread-local storage instead
of using atomics every time you write them?
Well, first of all, I don't think that would that was not good.
I may have just spilled a bunch of water on my keyboard may have
spilled it.
Let's just say, well, may is probably the wrong term, definitely did
might be a better way to say it, you know, see how it.
Let's see how the we'll see.
How it how it responds.
So yeah.
And that was unfortunate.
Apparently, the keyboard is still working.
Which is odd, but lucky.
So, first of all, I would ask why you want to do that because
thread-local storage is only available on certain platforms and
involves a bunch of things that you may or may not want to do, right?
If we did them in thread-local storage, you have to answer the
question of, how do you get them out of thread-local storage, right?
When do you do that?
Who is the thread that would do that?
Do all of your threads then lock up on a single, debug pull pull
And if so does that ruin, what you were trying to observe, right?
So think about what that means, if you're going to put them into the
local storage.
And then think about the fact that atomics
Are free.
I mean, they're almost entirely literally free, they don't cost you
anything, right?
Most of the time they're like a few Cycles.
So
You know putting them in thread-local storage.
Doesn't sound like a very good idea.
It actually sounds like actually impacting the performance quite a bit
more perhaps significantly more than you.
Atomic.
Qbert.
Caleb are lock free data structures.
Worth the time they take to write that depends on the circumstance,
right?
Obviously if you have something that's performance-critical then you
may want to look for you to structure if you don't, you don't
Terry roar words.
Do you think it would be worthwhile to make the time records?
Hierarchical like a call tree and how would you go about it?
So I don't really think that it's particularly useful.
I mean, typically, that's for people who don't know how their own code
works for the most part once in a while.
There's a reason why you might want to do that, where you don't really
know on whose behalf something is being called.
But typically, I don't find the hierarchical thing particularly
necessary.
Now, one thing that is useful,
Is when you know that something inside something else is taking so
much time to subtract that time out, sometimes that can be kind of
Handy, but the problem with that is, if you're trying to track
hierarchical calls, you end up in things that, you know, that is
something that may require thread-local storage to do correctly.
So you have to be really sure that you want it, because if you, if you
aren't careful, you'll end up sort of impacting you're
The thing a lot more intrusive to get that.
Now, we could try.
I haven't thought too much about it in a while.
so, I'd have to think about
You know.
if there's some ways to do,
I mean, you know, on a platform like Windows where they're
thread-local storage, it's probably not very expensive to do.
So we could do the tracking without it being like a huge deal, right?
So yeah.
I mean
We could consider it.
We could consider it on platforms without thread-local storage without
without reliable thread-local storage.
It would be, it would be a bit of a, an ugliness, I think.
Can you explain the difference between mutexes and interlocks?
So when you say interlocks, you mean like the atomic ad and stuff?
So yes, I can.
but I guess those
Terms are often kind of used.
A lot of these terms are used somewhat imprecisely in certain
scenarios.
I guess I would also say so it's worth noting that
You kind of have to really be precise about what you're talking about
but alright, so inside the processor.
We've got Coors, right?
So here's core 0 and here's Core 1 and these cores have caches.
So inside the core, here's the L1 cache for Core 1.
Sorry, core 0, and here's the L1 cache for core one right now.
What's going to happen on an atomic?
The only thing that's going to happen on the Tomic, is that a
particular chord?
The one who's accessing the atomic.
So when I say, when I did that Atomic add right, the only thing that
happens on that Atomic is it's going to check to see.
Whether this is in my cache right, whether the address that's being
added, right?
So, you know, here's memory.
And here's like the L3 cache or something.
If there is one, Whatever whatever the shared cache is our.
So I won't even say L3.
I'll just say here's the shared caches, here's the exclusive.
Caches meaning catches only perk or right.
So these are per core caches.
These are the the show caches what I do.
The atomic add.
The only thing that's going to happen is the external part of the
memory system.
The part that's outside the cores.
This core is going to say, I now need to own whatever that address is.
So if we're going to do an atomic add to like this address of memory,
right?
It's going to make sure that I have exclusive access to that.
Which means that, if this guy previously had it, it had a value in it.
He's going to mark his is stale.
Right?
It says, is not exclusive.
Like I like someone else is using it, right?
This is the messy protocol stuff that we talked about before that you
can go look up.
That's all that's going to happen.
So it may involve a transfer where it has to like evict it from this
guy and bring it into this guy's cash, right?
But that was going to happen anyway because if it wasn't in this guy's
cash, he had to load it anyway to get it because he has to add to it.
So that's literally it.
That's all that happens on that Atomic ad.
Is it is it's going to do that exclusive, it's going to mark it as
exclusive.
It's just like if it was going to write to any other memory address
it's the same
Thing, right?
So, all it does is, it makes sure that the only thing that makes it
Atomic is the fact that the read and the write happened together,
without allowing an eviction in between, that's it.
Otherwise, it's just, it's free.
It's really not an expensive thing, right?
A mutex is not anything like that.
A mutex has an arbitrary performance penalty to it, that depends on
the Locking situation.
So what am I
You Tex is is a mutex.
Like built on top of this.
Right?
So understand that you know you got this a mutex is a programming
construct built on top of this system.
What a mutex does is it says okay, I have two pieces of code right
here is code.
A here's code be.
They both want to do something but that's something is complicated.
So they've got this piece of code, each of them have some code in
here, right?
And we know that this code and this code cannot be run at the same
time because they do some stuff that would conflict.
So you want to make sure that only one or the other runs at that time.
What a mutex is it uses the atomic operation of the processor to do
something like us?
Have a memory location, that's like a lock and that lock is just set
to 0, when, no one owns it.
And it's set to like some
Our value like 1, when someone does.
So it'll do an atomic on that thing.
Like an atomic compare exchange for example, to set it to 1 and if it
gets back a zero on the atomic, compare compare exchange, it knows
that it now owns the lock.
So if a does that and sees that it gets back, a 1, it will run the
code, right?
And B does that same thing gets back a one knows, oh, somebody else
holds the lock.
I'll just sit here in a loop and wait until this until whoever's done
with it, releases it.
It.
And at the end it does a set of the thing back to zero.
So it has done.
Be, will then see it in the loop go.
Oh, it's zero now.
Do the atomic compare exchange 21 and run my code.
So a mutex is like an unbounded amount of time that has to go by and
you have to have loops to like sit there and check right?
And mutexes can be more complicated to, they can involve the operating
system if you want to put, like, a thread to sleep, if the mutex is
taken, so that you can give the processor time, somebody else while
you're waiting on the mutex.
So you can have operating system mitigated mutexes, which allow
threads to give time back to the OS.
So, a mutex is like a way, like way more.
It's, it's not even remotely comparable to this.
The only time that's remotely comparable to, this is the case where
the mutexes on contended
And you still have a little bit more which is you got that Branch
that's happening in there.
But at that point, if you're just going to go through and you never
contend, you never contend that lock.
Then it's just going to be like an atomic.
It does the atomic it exchange compare exchange succeeds.
I run my code.
I set it to 0 at the end.
That's pretty darn close, right?
So, a nun.
Contended, mutex is basically, you know, it's not going to be a
preacher be more expensive, a contented.
Mutex could be, it can be as much as this cost.
The entire time of this be whilst, all right?
I just want food.
Wait about the values.
Can you draw a graph out of them?
Yes.
But, wait, wait, you got to, wait, be patient.
Be patient and see.
Elvin.
No, save the tree IMAX Blues.
They're actually Cherry MX Browns.
Tt, b JM will you be able to fix the click bug?
At the end of sounds with the debug system?
You know, honestly we could fix the click at the end of sounds
probably without the debug system.
But yeah, I mean, you know, we just haven't bothered spending any time
on sound, but yeah, we could make that a good excuse like, you know.
We could make that a good test of our debug system, like, could we
make it easy to find that bug, right?
Not a bad idea.
Guitar Free, can you still time a smaller section inside the code?
Or does it just work for Whole functions?
Now you can time a smaller section as you want.
Just wrap it in braces, we already do that, in fact, so for example,
handmade optimized, you can see here time block, this block starts
here and ends at the closing brace down here.
Right here.
So that is a sub time block, so you can time any block you want, just
enclose it in braces.
K.
I noticed you prefer to keep things on the stack and return by value.
This helps with locality of reference as more cash friendly.
And my right one is the stack size something to be concerned about
too.
When returning by value is the time taken to copy the object and
return.
It something to be worried about maybe when the struct is large.
In this case, you prefer to return a pointer to the object yesso
typically, return and pass and return by value.
You have to struct is large, and the function is not in line.
Then yes you typically want to use a pointer or something to for stack
size.
It's not really something to be too concerned about because I tend to
not use that for particularly large things.
Sparkly guy.
How do threads?
Wait, unlock free structures, do they?
Well it depends on lock-free structures.
A lock-free structure, is really.
It's a misnomer.
I got confused about this.
In fact earlier on stream and in fact, Fabi and corrected me.
He's, you know, like because he's more of a perfect guy than I am.
He knows this stuff a lot better than I do.
I'm like more of a generalist kind of programmer, so you know anything
that's perfect.
Elated like multi-threading and optimization.
He's, you know, he's the go-to guy and what he point out because I was
complaining about the phrase Lock Free when he pointed out is like
lock-free was a stupid name.
It's weight.
Free is actually the correct term introduced by herlihy in this paper
that like I swear to God if
Isn't the best paper that anyone's ever written.
It should be.
I don't remember what his name is.
Exactly.
I'm sorry how you spell it?
There it is.
Mitchell herlihy.
See if I can get it here.
Wait, the
Herlihy, there it is.
Think this is right.
Let's see.
Yes, so Maurice, sorry, man, I'm sorry.
I don't know why I thought it was Mitchell.
So this paper is insane.
I have not had time because I Fabi and brought it to my attention.
Only like a few weeks ago or a month or two ago when we were doing the
optimization stuff originally this weight free synchronization stuff.
This paper basically like just totally it just totally powned
multi-threading.
Nobody knew like anything about multi-threading at all and then this
paper came along and he basically just solved it all.
He was just like hey guess what guys?
You know all the open outstanding questions we had about
multi-threading I just did, I did them all and I just stuck them all
in one paper.
Like I know that sounds ridiculous but actually if you go read the
paper it's like totally true.
It's like, oh, it looks like
Just pound it.
And now we're done and it turns out that he was just right, and so in
this paper, he actually introduces all the correct stuff and he called
it, wait, free.
And he's actually more correct lot.
Free programming has nothing to do.
Like lock is a dumb term.
It doesn't mean what it sounds.
Like it means weight.
Free is the more appropriate term and what it's referring to is the
fact that multiple concurrent processing multiple
concurrent workers.
We'll never get into a situation where they do not guaranteed lie,
make forward progress eventually, right?
They never get in the situation where they might stop making forward
progress and he explains like a bunch of these things and he also goes
through like what are the properties of a processor necessary to
ensure that these are possible?
And so this stuff is pretty great.
He introduces the concept of a consensus number which is brilliant.
It's basically the idea that's how many different things could come to
an agreement.
About the state of the world, right?
And he basically proves that without compare exchange.
If you only have like Atomic increment or Atomic decrement, you can't
achieve a consensus number greater than 1, which means that like there
are algorithms that simply can't be implemented on that processor,
right?
But Atomic compare Exchange
Actually allows you to have a consensus number of infinity, which
means that you can have as many people as you want agreeing about the
state of something using just that operation.
So yeah.
So anyway point being
Read that paper.
If you want to have your mind blown because it's insane to think about
how much crazy stuff he did at just at once, just like poof.
So more easterly.
I'm sorry, I got his name wrong.
My memory is not what it used to be, but there you go.
And so if you want to know how threads wait on lock-free structures
actually think in terms of weight free structures, read that paper, it
explains it.
But the basic idea is that you make sure that when people do things
They're always only doing them for a prescribed amount of time and
never wait on each other.
They just do an operation and release.
Right.
And it's you can kind of see, he talks about how to do it with like a,
you know, you can imagine doing with atomic compare exchange as well.
It's relatively clear.
So the stream is technically over.
So let me just take a
May just take a quick Gander here.
Cast of five.
What's wrong with pointers to inline functions?
Is that, is that a joke?
I'm not sure what you mean.
How can you take a pointer to a function?
That doesn't exist, right?
An inline function is basically a macro.
It just gets expanded inside, whoever calls it.
So you can't take a pointer to it because there is no, it hasn't, it
doesn't exist in memory, right?
It's just get spammed out to everyone who used it.
I'm not sorry, I'm not sure if you're joking, if you're a serious,
that's the answer.
If you're joking.
I don't know what the wasn't.
I mean, I'm not following the chat so I can't tell.
K.
Y U.
Skips my questions.
What question did I skip?
I answer all your questions.
Blur Barry.
Did you get a degree in CS know what's your background on programming?
That should be hmh bot should answer that for you but also you can go
to the links underneath the twitch stream would tell you that
And it looks like that's about it, I think.
I think.
Yeah.
All right, let's wind it down.
People wind it down.
Save
minimize or try to minimize attempt to minimize and fail.
Close.
Okay.
Thank you everyone for joining me, for another episode of handmade
hero.
It's been a pleasure coding with you.
As always, if you would like to follow along at home with the source
code, if you preorder the game, it comes with a source code.
Even right now, even before the game is a game, you can follow along
with the, just the engine building in the source code, if you would
like to, and you can do that on handmade hero dot-org.
Just by clicking on this handy little button.
We also have a patreon if you just want to support the video series
and pledged to it, you can do it there.
It's always very much appreciated.
We also have a forum site where you can go to ask questions get ports
to Mac and Linux that community members have done.
You can look at it and say depe sewed guy.
The community members have been working on.
We also have a tweetbot.
So if you want to join the stream live like perhaps you did today, you
can go to the tweetbot and either subscribe to it or just check it
periodically to see when the stream is going to be, it always has
adopted a schedule on it.
So that's a good place to go.
Watch got stream live.
That's about it tomorrow.
We will sort of continue our exploration of debug code.
We sort of have the beginnings of it.
Now, right.
We've seen how to do one set of markup and we have a nice little
display that showing, you know, how many times we call various
functions and how long they take?
That's a good start.
But there still is a lot more we could do.
It's not a particularly good view at this point.
It doesn't really show us some of the information we might want.
It doesn't show us information over time at all, there's much things
we could do so we can start to press on that.
A little bit.
It also we don't have any sort of other markup, right?
All we can do right now is take timings we can't see data very easily
or memory so we got a bunch of more stuff we can do.
So over the next couple weeks that's what we're going to be doing.
So if you want to see us continue with that right back here tomorrow
5:00 p.m.
Pacific, Daylight time will be added again tomorrow.
Adding some more features to that.
So hope to see you there until then have fun programming and I'll see
you guys on the internet.
Take these everyone