Here we go.
Hello, everyone and welcome to handmade hero.
The show Rico to complete game live on stream, on Twitch know,
libraries, no engine, it's a complete educational stream here on
handmade her.
Where really we try to make sure that every last little bit of what
goes into game development is covered.
So no matter what type of programming, you're thinking of, we will
eventually do that here on the stream.
And right.
Right now we're in the middle of some, pretty interesting stuff.
We're doing optimizations for the first time here on handmade hero and
we're right in the middle of transitioning.
During a routine from regular scalar C code into intrinsics which
allows us to take advantage of the assembly instructions on the x64
processor, which is what we're running on right now.
And we've already seen a 3X speed up just from doing the basic stuff
that we've done so far just to kind of underscore exactly how
important these are.
Even before you start really looking seriously at the optimization of
things literally just translating routines, in this fashion can have
pretty massive speed increases and so we're going to finish up some of
that today.
Hopefully
Lee because we're kind of coming to the end of that translation
process.
But before I go ahead and get started with that, I just want to remind
everyone.
If you preorder the game on handmade hero dot org and you would like
to follow along with today's episode, it's 118 is today.
So download The Source zip and unpack day, 117 out of it and that
will, you know, give you the exact starting point that I'm, you know,
using today.
So, let's recap where we left off yesterday, because we had a very
specific
Saying that we were about to do on when we kind of stopped yesterday.
And so we want to pick up, right?
Where we left off.
So, if you take a look at where we're at, if if you run the thing
we're running through all of our SEC past but you see, we have these
black bars on things.
And the reason that we have, those black bars is because in order to
do some work with, you know, with changing over how we write pixels to
be Cindy, we commented out the line that actually checks for this
should fill thing.
So, if you remember how this worked, since we're filling for pixels at
a time, we had created a little array here called should fill
And each time we went through a pixel, we set should fill equal to the
bind the Boolean operation, which says, whether or not it fell within
the rectangle that we were supposed to be writing out, right?
And so if you come down here and look, we commented out.
The should fill because we didn't know how to implement that in Cindy.
Right.
I have not covered that yet.
So I didn't want to put that in.
and so, you can see,
That we have a little to do here, which is to say, right?
Only the pixels where it should fill equals true.
And when we run it, you can see what happens when that's not
occurring.
You can see that we're writing these black pixels here which were not
supposed to be writing because up at the top Loop.
Right.
You can see us right here.
Setting should fill.
I wheat.
We do an.
If and we don't actually
Any of this work when should fill is not set to True, right?
So there's just nothing in the buffers.
So when we go to write it out, we just write out garbage data here.
Okay, so what we need to do is we need to start writing in some way
that's going to actually preserve that information that should fill
information.
So what I'd like to do is talk really briefly about how this process
is going to work.
It's not very complicated.
But again, since this is all completely new, we have not talked about
any stuff like it on.
Handmade here.
I just
To make sure everyone's on the same page.
So right now where we got ourselves to yesterday if you remember is we
have a 128-bit Cindy register right?
That we have prepared.
And we essentially have rgba rgba triples, and I'm sorry.
Rgba quads in it, right?
We have stuff that looks like this.
Like so, and what we want to do is we want to be able to write this
out in one big chunk.
So we can just use one instruction to write the whole thing out into
the destination buffer, but the problem is that the destination
buffer, right?
The destination buffer may only have some values which were actually
supposed to overwrite, right?
This is for Pixel values, right?
This is pixel 1 0 1, 2 and 3, right?
And it may be that we're only supposed to write in to say these two
pixels, okay?
So, you know, given that that's true.
Well, there is one thing that we can do right off the bat, right?
Which is that we could just make sure that if we're only supposed to
write into these two pixels, we could just make sure that these other
two pixels that were going to write.
You know, are actually filled with valid data, okay?
And if these were filled with valid data which is whatever was in the
destination beforehand, then it doesn't matter that we're going to
overwrite them.
We're just going to overwrite them with whatever they were before.
So what we want to do at least want to look at doing first and we'll
see if there's any reason not to do it this way, but we want to look
at first, is what we can do.
To make sure that when we do this, if we've computed new values here
and here, but we're not going to process these values that we still
stick.
The old values from the frame buffer into these two positions so that,
you know, it will still produce correct results.
Now,
Now, one way to think about this is that well we want to save all of
this work that we're doing here.
We'd want to not do all this work for pixels that we didn't have to
do.
But at the moment since we're doing things for wide really doing the
work for a single Pixel as expensive as doing it for all four.
So unless we tried to figure out, some way to pack different pixels
from different locations and then scatter them back out later which is
probably not worth it for four pixels, but hard to say, you know,
We're not going to try that right now.
What that means is it's totally okay to just do all these operations.
For all of the pixels.
The only problem is that if we do all these operations for the pixels
when we get to the end, right?
We would have to have figured out a way to essentially stuff all of
these Texel ARB RCR.
Do you know all of this stuff that's going to get operated on?
We would have to have figured out a way to shove values into all of
these that would reproduce whatever is already in the destination.
After going through all of this entire pipeline which seems like a
little bit, it just seems like a little bit of trouble, right?
I mean, that seems like a bit of a bit of a stretch
Another option that we would have, right, is right before we're about
to write it out.
If we were to take our Vector of new values, right?
So, we've computed new values in all four slots and our Vector of old
values,
Right.
If you were to take these and we know that these are actually invalid
and these are the only two that are correct.
What we could do is use bitwise operations to combine these two.
So that we end up with a final Vector to write out, which has old in
the places where old should be and new in the places where a new
should be right and it's pretty easy to see what we would need to make
that happen, right?
We already know that we can combine two vectors
Right by using or right?
We know that we can take, you know, and, and sort of, if we had all
zeros here, right?
And all zeros in here in these two vectors, we could order them
together and it would leave the news in the middle and the olds on the
ends because the zeros would not interfere, right?
So, the only question is, how do we knock out these values and in the
places where we don't want them and turn them into zeros?
And the answer is we can use and for that
Right?
If we were to build a mask which was essentially that looked like this
right, you know, it's ones and zeros here, right?
So all zeros here all ones and here we could end this with new to
produce, you know, a new template we could and the opposite, you know,
the not of it with the with the old and then or the two together,
right?
And that would produce a final Vector that looked like this.
So we know the exact operations we would need to do, we all we would
have to do is make sure we can produce a mask value that basically has
all zeros, where there should be old values and all ones where there
should be new values, right?
And then we could do it.
Pretty trivially, in fact, you know, it would just look like this.
We would take out right that maybe I'll make a new one just so we can
see it make something called masked out.
If we go ahead and do an or here and I do an or with that you know the
and
Like I just said, oops, I didn't mean add mint.
And there we go.
If we were to and the out,
Like so if it were to and the out with our right mask, right?
Which is what it basically is, it's the place that we're going to
write with and then I were to and the original dest with the right
mask, right?
And something like this, but I want the inverse of it, right?
And I believe, I think there might be a mnemonic this by don't
actually know.
Let me see here until intrinsics guide.
Our trusty friend, should probably just leave this tab open while
we're doing this.
Mmm, and not.
So you can see here that basically, this is Computing, the not of B
and then it is re the not of a and then it ends it with be.
So probably want to do it this way.
So you can see the mask more properly like so,
So you can see here is we are effectively producing amassed version of
the out by taking the original dest masking out, the places where
we're trying to write taking the new result, you know the actual
pixels we computed masking out the parts we don't want to write fusing
them together and then over writing the entire destination, right?
And so if we just go ahead and write Mast out here, all we would need
to do is compute this right mask somehow.
And make sure that we're storing our original destination.
So, let's go back up here and make sure that that's actually
happening.
So, in the load destination, for example, we would have to make sure
that that always happens, meaning it cannot be inside of this, for I
Loop conditional, right?
It can't be only if we're going to fill it, we have to load it always
but once we do that, we could make sure that our desk tars gsb's an
days when they come out.
We could preserve those now into original dest, right?
Actually.
Now that I think about this, we haven't actually Cindy eyes this.
So these are still actually being directly up converted to float.
So, I think what I'm also going to do here in the meantime, actually,
we'll just leave that.
Like this.
I'm going to actually put in one part of this.
This that we haven't done yet.
I'm going to have original desk here.
And I'm going to make that be a load you.
I'm going to show you this right here.
See.
So, do you see this?
You see how before down?
Yesterday, we did that store you which says store on aligned and it
allows us to take one of these 70 registers and write it out to a
pointer.
I want to do the same thing here.
I want to do an explicit load and I want to do an explicit load of
exactly the place that we're writing.
Right.
So I essentially want to do exactly this and say what was there in a
position that we're writing what was there before hand, right?
So I want to do one of these loads to get that original desktop and
then later,
As we haven't Cindy eyes this, we just won't touch this for now.
We'll leave that loading the way it was.
But later, once we have this, this load working, we can actually
change this all this code to be working off of sympathy as well.
So that's what we, you know, obviously, we were planning on doing
that, but I just want to jump the gun a little bit here to make sure
we have that original desk just as it was
Okay, so we come down here and then we're going to have is we're going
to have well, besides that syntax error for my typo.
We're going to have a problem with right mask basically, okay.
And the problem with right mask is we have never computed, this
explicitly,
So for the time being what we're going to do is again just like we did
with our other things, we're just going to approximate this.
We can set it to a dummy value at the moment and I'm set one SOS a
epi32 and we'll just set it to 0 should do it.
So we're going to have a right mask of zero.
If we in fact, look at what's happened.
Now, we don't write anything and that is exactly what we would have
expected.
Because if the right mask was set to 0, that means you'd never write
anything right?
Whereas if I set the right mask let's say to all ones.
So each 32-bit Lane of the right.
Mask is all set to ones.
We should see that it returns to our previous thing which is just it
always writes everywhere.
Right, so that's good.
So now all we have to do is figure out a way to set, right?
Mask equal to the proper thing and of course we can sort of just do
that down here by using sort of our cheesy set macros until we know a
better way to do it.
So let's go ahead and do that.
We will essentially set it to
You know, all FS.
Got one too many.
There we go.
And so now we're setting, the right mask, only in the cases, where we
thought we should have filled.
We're setting that right mask.
Okay.
Oh, oh, dear.
That's, that's a bit garish.
What do I have to say?
That's pretty cool.
What, what just happened?
I, I was not expecting that effect, but it's it's pretty great.
It's like some kind of a like fancy artistic filter that has been
applied to our game.
That's
That's just bizarre.
You got to admit.
That's pretty bizarre.
Wow.
All right.
Well, you know, I kind of tempted to try and figure out a way to
preserve that particular thing.
Oh, but you can see why it's because it was a floating Point.
Seth, that was happening there.
So we kind of need one again just temporarily that works.
An integer that that was cool though.
You gotta admit, that was pretty cool.
But this is what we actually wanted, right?
We actually wanted something that masks out the
Use and now you can kind of see that happening properly.
That, that was pretty darn cool.
That, that was great.
So I guess setting it to extremely high, floating-point number does
some pretty awesome stuff.
leave that as an exercise to the reader to play around with if you'd
like
Okay, so now we're properly masking out things based on the right
Mass.
So we've gotten rid of our black borders and so that's yet another to
do down.
Now, I want to mention another thing here, which is that again are
helping friendly Fabien wrote in to me to say that we actually can
count on pretty much always, unless we change it.
The SS.
He's rounding mode for convert PS.
Just the regular convert PS, which we were using yesterday.
Before we change it to the ad will actually do round to nearest.
By default and that is what we should leave the rounding mode set to
he said anyway.
So what that implies is that really we don't have to worry about those
ads.
We can just count on round to nearest being the normal thing that it
does and if round to nearest is the normal thing that it does, then we
don't have to worry about doing this half.
So we're pretty much good to go just with that so we can get rid of
that to do as well because apparently that's just easier for us
anyway.
So we're all good.
So there we go.
And there's our little happy hero.
He's running pretty zip Ali.
Now, to again, we've already got them down to like the 110 cycle
range, but we now have, you know, we certainly have a bit of work left
to do before we even finished translating this entire thing.
So what I'd like to do now is move up to our last remaining for I
Loop, which is this Loop right here, okay.
so,
The first thing I like to focus on is again.
We know how to do some packing and unpacking and things like that.
So I feel like at this point we should be able to move these things
which we're doing for.
I Loops for doing the unpacks of ours.
The geez, the bees that sort of stuff, we should be able to move those
essentially outside into Cindy, right?
That shouldn't be too hard because this is all stuff that we have done
before.
We, you know, we we did essentially the reverse of this, we did the
packing density.
Down and so we should be able to go think about it for a little while
and then just be able to produce something that does these unpacked.
So what I want to do here is I want to go ahead and move one of these
outside and I'll
Head and move.
Let's say Texel a are outside.
Like so and what we want to do is we want to convert this to Cindy.
So instead of doing it this way, in here, where we have the those
Texel samples which get loaded, what I'd rather do is have it so that
the Texel samples are actually just being loaded.
Straight away out of a you and 32, let's say right.
And I guess we don't even need to to do it as a unit 32, I guess I can
just put it in the low part of an actual m120.
A tie that seems like that would be fine as well.
So I'm going to go ahead and say that we've got this this sample, a
here, right?
I'm going to go ahead and say that we've got that sample.
A
I think we want it to be stored in the bottom of a 128.
I have to think about that.
Maybe we don't, maybe we actually want them stored, sort of stride it
or something like that.
I don't know.
I mean, the other thing we could do is for now just say that it's
actually the UN 32 and then we'll load it in later.
I'm not sure what the best thing to do would be.
But again, we have four of them.
So let's go ahead and just start with that, right?
And what I want to do is say here the sample, a right?
We're going to grab it out of the I like that, right?
Then when we come down here, we know we have four sample A's.
And we could, if we wanted to write, we can also just go ahead and do
it this way.
For starters, right?
This would just be the explicit version where we actually do them all
sort of piecemeal, right?
Oops, that's no good.
Yeah.
And so, if we take a look at that, right, will get essentially the
same thing that we had before, right?
Nothing bad happening.
And we could do this for all of them.
Pretty trivially.
Again, it just kind of generates a lot of code that spammed out there.
But we could do that pretty simply for everything, right?
We can have all of our samples be done that way.
If we wanted to, we can do VC + D.
Exactly the same way, right?
And then, all of these guys would move out there as well.
Okay.
So here's what that looks like.
And again, then we just have to do these guys.
This way.
And again, I apologize to anyone who doesn't like waiting for me to
kind of structure things like this, but I find that it's good on the
stream to just take it one step at a time, so that everyone can kind
of see exactly how things go and in the future again.
Oops, I do that in the future.
When we do more Cindy stuff, if we decide, we want to do more assembly
stuff, we can, you know, take some shortcuts and not do that.
But, you know, just for a little while everyone learns at different
speeds, I don't want to kind of jump into things and just write stuff
and Cindy right off the bat, I want to be able to kind of show how
this stuff happens and especially with a routine like this, this this
specific part of this routine, kind of the Preamble where things are
loading.
As I think, you'll see it's going to get a little hairy in
R because just of the way the fact that we can't load things directly
in the format that we've liked because they're coming from these pack
textures definitely does mean that things are a little bit more wonky
like the stuff that we're going to have to do is going to be a little
bit more, a little more sketchy if you will.
All right, so now everything is running, sort of that sort of more
direct way, right?
And what's kind of interesting is you can see again like I said I just
kind of point this out every time it happens but you can see that our
cycle counts actually got less.
We're now down below 100 Cycles, often times.
And what's kind of interesting is that, you know, hopefully that's
might strike you as kind of counterintuitive because we move stuff out
of a conditional, right?
Move stuff out of a conditional into a place where it's now always
happening all the time instead of only happening during the
conditional.
And so I know that some of this stuff can be counterintuitive.
It's worth pointing out that like, processor the way, the compiler
optimizes things down and the way the processor executes them and so
on can lead to some very non-intuitive results.
And so especially with routines of any significant complexity, like
this, you you might be surprised when ends up happening when you move
things out like that.
So anyway, just pointing that out.
But let's continue on.
So now we have the destination,
No.
And I think the destination actually might be the easiest one for us
to start with.
We have our original Des, which we've already done a load you for here
and we know we're always going to load it.
So maybe what we'll do is we'll start by doing the load destination,
you know, I don't know.
I'm gonna finish this.
ER, maybe what we'll actually do is the right mask, I don't know.
We'll see, we'll see you in a second.
So let's go ahead out here and and finish this guy off.
Like so, and again, we have to do this.
Oops.
Okay.
So here we are again, move.
Some more stuff outside, and check out what happens when we move
things outside the conditional, we just saved another 10 Cycles by
cutting, and pasting the code out of a loop.
All right, and by the way, anyone in thought we weren't going to get
down to 50 Cycles, the pixel, which?
Yeah, we're almost at and we haven't actually finished translating the
routine.
I think we've got a really good shot at it.
Yeah.
Anyway so we've got those and now we're still just kind of stuck with
this stuff here and so what I'd like to do first of all I kind of
changed my mind a little bit as we went there.
What I kind of want to do is say let's fix this right mask nonsense.
Okay, so we're Computing these u and v values here, right?
And then what we're doing is we're comparing the u and v values to
make sure that they're obeying these certain constraints.
They have to be greater than equal to 0.
And less than or equal to 1 both of them do, right?
So what I'd like to be able to do is I'd like to be able to go ahead
and compute that right mask directly without ever having to actually
do this sort of scalar extraction because if you look at what this
code is doing here, it's grabbing out pieces of these vectors and
doing them in a loop.
What I'd rather do is figure out.
Can I compute this should value?
This should fill value as its own wide value can
I basically compute right Mass directly without packing it into each
of the four lanes separately.
And of course, the answer is yes, I can.
The SSE instruction set gives me a lot of opportunities to do that.
So let's introduce SSE comparison operations.
So if we take a look in here, there's actually a special category for
this right compare.
And you can see that we've got a ton of comparison operations to
choose from
All of these intrinsics, you know, kind of our will map to a different
sort of comparison.
We want to do but for example we've got a greater than or equal to and
you can see here and mmm comp greater than equal to PS.
And what that does is exactly what you might think.
It takes an A, and A B, and it looks to see if a is greater than b, if
it is, it puts all 1s in the lane and if it's not, it puts all zeros
in the lane, okay?
Now, this is exactly the kind of operation, you know, this instruction
set was
Designed for the most part to do the sorts of things that we're doing.
So, it's basically designed exactly to produce this thing.
What it will do is it will take a look Bai Ling, right?
So we have a zero should say the site.
We have a 0, a 1, a 2, a 3, right?
And then here, we've got b0, B1 B2 B3.
What it's going to do, if we say could do a greater than or equal to
is, it's actually going to compare each lane individually, right?
And it's going to produce in the result.
It's going to either produce all zeros in the case that it's false.
Or all ones in the case that it's true.
So it's literally set up specifically to produce these kinds of masks,
why?
Because if the concept of doing an, if no longer makes any sense in
wide operations, the only time you ever want conditional control flow
in wide operations, is, if all the values are 0, or all the values are
1, right, meaning it would
Have to be something that would apply to everything because if you
think about what an if does, and if predicates some set of operations,
right on you know, some some condition of the inputs, well, if some of
them could be true and some of them could be false which is what
happens if you do for ifs at once.
There can't be any control flow because you can't only partially
execute some operations for some parts of the lane and partially
executed for others, right?
So, if that are not on the entire Vector at once, if that are only
between lanes stuff, cease to become ifs, and they become masks,
right?
What ends up happening is it always takes for anything that you'd
have, right?
We do an, if op 0 else.
Up 1, right?
So we're doing an F on some condition and we have some operational
going to do.
If it's true in some operation, if it's not what ifs become is.
Instead you just always do both of these, this becomes up, zero up
one, right?
We do like a equals zero be quills up one and then we do a we do
essentially a select.
You might say we do a select of a and be subject to this if whatever
this
Liz and we pick the parts, the lanes of a where the conditional was
true.
We pick up 0, right?
And the lanes where this condition was false, we pick the second top,
right?
And that is precisely what this, right?
Mask was set up to do before, okay?
We're always Computing, both the value, that's in dest, right?
We loaded it and saved it.
And we're always Computing the result of all four pixels because we do
that computation, right?
So what we're doing essentially with that, right?
Mask is where essentially Computing both sides of an if statement and
selecting / Lane which one we wanted to do?
Does that make sense?
So
What we can do is we can use these comparisons to generate that,
right?
Mask directly because SSE was set up to do this because they knew you
needed conditionals but you couldn't use conditionals anymore you have
to use masking so they set it up to enable exactly that masking.
So what we're going to do instead of our right Mass being set to 0 is
our right mask is going to be set up to
Will the results of these comparisons, right?
so if I just take exactly this comparisons here, if I go ahead and
say, we've got em em and
PS, like so.
And I've got an M&M and PS that happens on two ands, right?
Because if you look here, we've got, we got to do this and this and
this and this, and we've got to add those together, basically, right?
So we're doing for us, or for things and it together
so when we do that, we've got to on the you and to on the V what we
want to do is say we want to say is it greater than or equal to
We want to know whether you is greater than or equal to the zero
Vector which we already set up up here, right?
We already have this zero Vector, we already have the one vector.
So those values are already loaded or we've already set them up, I
should say.
We also want to do a comparison for less than or equal to with one,
right?
And then we're going to do the exact same thing on v0m.
M less than equal to 1.
So now we've produced the right mask strictly by using SSE operations,
right?
And if I go ahead and compile that
What is the same cannot convert?
Oh yes sorry this right.
Mask is actually needs to be cast because it is not it's coming from
floating Point values.
So after we do all of the Anne's we're going to have to actually cast
it.
You know, we're going to have to do one of these si128.
There we go.
So now we're producing that, right?
Mask entirely, just by using operations, and you can see that it's
actually working quite nicely here, right?
So there we go.
Now, unfortunately, we're still actually doing all the computations
here and we're doing the computations.
Because we still need to load our Textures in scalar.
As you can see right now.
We have a problem here which is that we can't just get rid of this if
entirely and just always load the textures all the time.
The reason that we can't do that is because we might be loading out of
invalid memory, right.
We, you know we have to make sure that we're always actually loading a
valid value out when we, when we do this because otherwise we could
access memory that was in.
Salad.
So what we probably want to do here, right?
Is, we probably want to clamp.
Are you in RV to make sure that they're never out of range.
And then we could always load the textures, even in the cases where
the textures were not actually going to be used.
Now that might not be the most efficient thing, but that's something
that we can do just off the bat to make sure that everything works
properly.
So once we have the u and v here and
Convert it and we've actually computed the right mask.
What we can then do is take the U and the V.
And go ahead and clamp them because now we know that any pixels that
are going to be written with the u and v have actually been computer
with the proper you envy and anything where the u and v was out of
range.
Has already been masked out and won't be valid.
So what we can do here is we can just say, OK, U equals mmm and we
already did this code before you remember this thing right here,
right?
We do this to do a clamp between zero and one so we can just go ahead
and clamp the values like so right?
So there's our clamp and now we can actually get rid of this entirely
if we want to, and we should be in a situation where we're never
actually going to pick outside of the texture because it has been
clamped ahead of time, right?
So let's take a look, if that works.
Oh dear.
Well, to suffice to say, no, that did not work.
I'm not exactly sure what I did wrong there.
Of course, let's see.
What did I do?
It looks like this is actually Max PS.
It's doing the maximum of 30 and the minimum of the u-value and one
that's should be.
Correct.
Should it not what happened there?
Oh, there we go.
Typo.
Didn't put the v in
I wish you would be didn't look so darn similar.
So there we go.
Now, our little guy is ripping around just fine and we're always
loading the textures so you know they're always filled in there.
We're never doing.
If so we never have to compute it explicitly we still have a for I
Loop because unfortunately you know we've got some stuff that has to
be done here for I Loop wise but we also are kind of getting to the
point where probably we could do some of this wide as well, right?
We could probably go ahead and leave.
Only the Texel fetch.
So let's go ahead and do that part as well.
We might as well just you know we're on a roll here.
People we're on a roll we might as well sort of go with that roll,
right?
So we have the X and Y that gets pulled out here.
I'm thinking maybe we can just go ahead and do all of these
computations in sympathy as well.
So let's try and do the txt.
Why one's right shall we?
Because that seems like that should be fairly straightforward.
Okay, so do in order to produce txt why, what we would have to do is
we have to preload a vector with texture with minus 2 and 1 with
texture height minus 2
All right.
So, up here.
and then 128 with M2,
Let's call it.
M m--, set 1, PS.
Just grab this out here.
Here we go.
So what we want to do is grab that value and make up a four wide
version of that and then let's make a high temp to.
There we go.
And do that one set, one PS.
Yeah.
So now we've got both the height and the width minus 2, and we're just
going to go ahead and use those right here to compute this is Echo
Valley, because these are just wide multiplies, right?
They're just going to do a multiply across the board.
And so, if I go ahead and grab this out here,
We still have to do this for my texture, boundary stuff.
So we'll have to modify this a little bit later but that's okay,
right, so I'm just going to call this m 128 tx4, right?
Click so.
And I believe this only actually gets used inside here, right and I
right about that it does appear to be the case.
Yeah, so we're going to do these wide.
And then in here we're just going to extract them.
So we can still use
Some in scalar.
Right.
And again, I don't actually know ahead of time when I'm making these
steps.
I don't actually know ahead of time.
That all of these things are things.
We actually do want to do in that in this way.
So we're, you know, we'll have to maybe backpedal on some of these we
don't actually know, but we're, I'm just doing the whole
transformation first so that we'll have everything in Cindy except the
textile loads and then we'll see about what we can do to make that
extraction fast.
Alright, so up here, if we want to compute these values, what I want
to do is I want to change this over 2A.
Memo PS right where I multiply the U Vector for wide by the width M2
Vector, right.
Which is just going to do that.
Multiply for all of the pixels at once instead of downshifting and
doing them in scalar.
Like we were doing them before.
There we go.
So we can compute those values.
We also could do this the rest of this to write.
If you look at this like FX and so on there's really no reason we
couldn't have done those as well if we come down here.
Like so and we have these FX values.
You can see that the FX value is really just a subtraction and
subtraction.
You know, for this right here.
So what we could do is we could just call this txt why we could do the
cast and Cindy as well, right?
These are actually, sorry and 128.
We could do the cast and send these as well to produce that X vector
and that y Vector, right?
Like so I know,
This is interesting.
This Y is actually.
Done in kind of a weird way there.
Why is the why not called why?
I oh, I guess because, yeah.
So I feel like these are a little bit poorly named because there's the
in slept here that actually are those things and then we shadowed it
effectively with the Y parameter, which is kind of janky, right.
That's a little bit nasty.
I don't love it to be completely honest with you.
So I'm going to I'm going to maybe introduce these as fetch X.
Fetch why I think might be a better thing to do.
Just for the moment.
Let's do it like that.
There we go.
And then we've got this stuff and this stuff
Right?
So what I want to do is go ahead and get it down to this.
So that we've got these fetches here and what this is going to be is
this is going to be an m
And EM fetch out right foot, just going to sort of extract that value
from something that will compute up above.
Which will just be, you know, fetch X for x or something.
Something like that.
Okay?
So, this will be a fetch X for X.
This will be the fetch y4y.
Oops, that's why 4X
So essentially, all I wanted to do here was introduced that convert PS
right?
The thing that does the the rounding or whatever.
The problem with this, of course, is that the convert PS is going to
be working.
In round to nearest, whereas what we wanted to do was truncate, right?
So we're going to have to do if we want to truncate.
The value is, we're going to have to do a sub first to subtract .5
from it so that it will fall into the correct bucket.
I believe that's the correct thing to do.
We'll have to take a little bit more closer look at that later.
But again, since we can't actually
Do that work.
Since we can't basically ask it to truncate for us, although wait a
minute.
No, that's not true.
We can do the truncate.
We learned that yesterday, in fact, because I believe Martin's pointed
that up for us, we actually can use that thing.
That always does truncate right, there was the mm convert PS.
Which always truncates.
With truncation.
All right, so that's actually super handy.
We don't have to do subtraction either.
Can just do that and get ourselves.
Always truncated.
Okay?
All right, so we do the multiplication here to produce RT, X Cy.
Right.
That's where in the texture, we're going to fetch in floating point.
We then truncate that to produce the value that we were using to
figure out exactly which pixel to get directly out of the array.
And, you know, turn to give us our base corner for our, for wide
fetch.
Right.
We then have our FX and FY, which we were
Computing.
Excuse me by figuring out what the fractional part of X and Y is.
So all that's going to be is a subtraction between again, the the
truncated version and the non truncated version.
So we just have to do subtraction from t x and t.
Why of essentially upconverted, right?
We want to do, we don't want to cast, we want to convert epi32 PS.
We basically want to do the conversion of the other direction.
Take an integer and convert it up.
Floating Point.
Let's see where that is where that is compared close-ups are not
convert convert so that's going to be it converts epi32 PS.
So you can see this one here, goes the other direction, right?
It can it converts the integers up to floating point which is what we
were doing before, right?
So we can do exactly that operation.
To up convert the rounded versions that we just did.
Which are these
There's RX there's our Y and then that's doing this operation that we
use to be doing in the loop.
It's doing that for a wide and then we're down to literally just doing
just those Texel fetches I think everything else is now being done
properly there.
See here conversion from float to int possible.
Also dips that's supposed to be an.
Am I like so?
And I'm a we did a bunch of Ops there.
So I may have gotten something wrong but I'm not sure.
Looks like it's
It's all correct though.
So we got that converted properly and we are now down to under 70
Cycles as well, which is kind of cool.
Right, there we go.
Okay, so looking back up on here, right?
We still have a plenty of work to do because we actually have a bunch
of other things that we kind of cut and paste it out of that Loop, but
that still aren't done actually for wide and we can get these guys
now.
Since they're all none of those guys have to be initialized in that
kind of janky way anymore.
They can all actually be be done just in time down here, right?
So we can do
basically, this
All right, and in theory, the compiler should not complain about that
anymore.
We had only initialize those because the compiler was complaining and
so now they aren't complaining anymore.
So that's a good thing.
And so we should be able to basically get all of those done this way
like so
Oops.
Thirsty.
See.
And finally d.
Okay?
And now the Blended and dust also work that way, right?
We can come down and see those here.
Certainly dest obviously is exactly the same.
As the other ones were believe Blended is a little further down
there's desk
And down here, where is our Blended lended?
There it is.
So our Blended can actually be done.
Just right in line.
I think right.
This could just be M1 28.
Like so defined as it's used.
Alrighty, so off we go again.
Again, we're well south of 70 Cycles.
Now per pixel, which is pretty darn cool.
Kid things continue to get faster, literally just from translating
things and assembly.
And if I come back now and take a look at where we're at, we've got
almost everything in CMD, except for the textile loads, which were
probably have to stay out of some because there's no such thing as a
Cindy fetch.
Unfortunately, it be great if you could fetch things for a wide,
that's
Thing I think in avx-512, but, you know, it's not here yet, so we
can't do that.
But all this stuff is happening for white up here and everything below
here is happening for a wide.
So really, we're just looking at this part.
Now, we're we're extracting those textiles and up converting them.
That is the only part that is not happening for wide, that could be
and should be happening for a wide.
So let's take a look at how to do that.
We have our low destination here, we want to basically do the reverse
of what we were doing before.
When we were trying to write pixels out.
So what we have right, is when we load from the destination, we've got
something that looks like this.
Where we've got packed pixels in here that are packed in sort of this
again be gra, you know, be G, ra, be gra be gra, right?
That's what we've got and what we want to be able to do again is we
need to take one of these guys.
A single one of these guys and we need to be able to unpack it out
into something that looks like this, right?
We need to get
all of save the bees.
We need to get all of those out into vectors that look like this,
right?
Right.
And then immediately after down with that, we got to do exactly the
same thing for the other components now.
Fortunately, I mean, I think we can probably do this in exactly the
same way that we were doing it before kind of
Reverse.
If we were to knock out if we're to mask out all these values and just
leave the bees, right?
We could then convert the be in place because we know it's a value
between 0 and 25.
We know it's a bite, right?
We convert it in place and then multiply it to convert it to a
floating point value, right?
So we actually can do essentially the exact opposite of what we were
doing on the desk and it should in theory be fine.
So for example, if I'm going to Target desk be I'm just going to knock
out the desk bees of all of these here, right?
And we have original death, which is the loaded version of our
destination that's packed in that, that way.
So if I want to go ahead here and create a version of death, be that
comes directly from original desk.
Instead of being done in this sort of piecemeal scalar fashion, where
were, you know, writing all over the registers and doing ridiculous,
extraction stuff.
If I wanted to do that all I would have to do is first mask it out,
right?
And again, we know we just did this, right?
We're just going to do a mask where we
Mask out a portion of the of the thing.
And so we want this to be like basically our Arlo mask.
So we want this to be you know our mask 255 or something and call that
but like you know basically this this value mask FF maybe let's call
that.
So we want to end this with a 4 wide replica FF to do that operation,
right?
And then what we want to do is we want to up convert that using
convert, PS epi32,
we want to basically up convert that into that, that endpoint now it's
a 025 floating point value.
And so then the only thing that we would have to do following that
right?
Is we have to well, I guess, you know what, I don't think we have to
do anything after that, actually, because the desk is already getting
taken care of down here.
It's already being done with its in 55 multiply so, really, actually,
I guess that's it.
That's the entirety of what we have to do.
Am I wrong about that?
We just need
We just need that mask.
If F value to be declared which again is really, really simple.
All that is mask FF, right?
All that is is set one epi32.
It's just one of these
Right.
Oops.
What is the question?
Not convert?
Argument one from 2128.
Oh whoops.
Sorry, I always get the sense wrong, which one we're going to.
This means we're going from an Epi 32 to a PS value.
There we go.
So that converts our blue channel, right?
And there's no reason that we can't do all of the destination that
way, right?
Because it's going to be the exact same operation in all cases.
So now
Essentially just got, you know, RGB and a we can do all of them
exactly this way.
All we would have to do is shift them into the right place, right?
Because they're all exactly the same mask operation.
All we need to do is, you know, right before we do that mask, make
sure we shift them down, right?
So we just need to make sure that we do a right shift and I guess I
don't remember to be honest with you.
What exactly the pi3 to, I don't even remember what the shift value
actually is.
It's something like rli for right?
Logical immediate.
Car.
Shift right?
Logical immediate.
Is that what it is?
Nope, you guessed wrong Casey shift.
Shift, right.
Logical immediate.
There we go.
Epi32.
All right.
So shift.
Right?
Logical immediate.
There we go and we want to be able to shift that down by the our
shift.
Which again is 16, right?
It's exactly like it was up here.
There we go.
So we want to shift the G by 8, which is our eighth shift and we want
the alpha to be shifted by 24, which is the alpha shift, right?
And so we can stack those I guess by their memory order just for fun.
Right.
And that's about it.
So, that gets rid of all of this and makes that kind of a nice more
clean, more concise fashion.
Like, so,
And still didn't lie, pick up, much on that again, we're kind of down
to the plate where we're only doing saving a few things and I don't
even know how much the processor might be able to figure some of those
out for us.
But anyway, we can now do the exact same thing for these guys in
theory, but it's a little bit harder because remember, we have this
problem, where we actually don't load for textiles, we have to
replicate, if you will
We have to kind of like well here let me just show you on the board.
So when we were doing dust, it was easy because dust already have the
values in here, right?
What we want to do with our texels is.
We have four different samples, right?
We've got sample a sample, B sample.
See, and Sample D.
And we, those are actually the samples that need to get Blended for
each of the pixels.
And each of the pixels has a separate one loaded.
Right.
So we essentially have if you will a matrix which is kind of kind of
nasty, we have a 4 wide Matrix for tall.
Tracks right?
Which is broken up.
Like so, right?
We have, which pixel we're operating on, right?
So we basically have like, you know, pixel 0 pixel.
Well, I guess I'll do it in standard order here.
So we have pixel 0, pixel, one, pixel to pixel 3, but then we also
have sample, a sample, B sample.
See, sample d right now.
What we would like to do is we'd like to be able to treat those pixel
values.
Treat those sample size as if they were packed pixelize even though
Came from multiple locations.
So what we want to do is prepare an a, a sample, a value.
That actually packs a 0 here, A 1 here, a 2 here, and a 3 here, right
into one Cindy register, so that we can do the operations on all the
pixels at once.
Like we were doing before, right?
So, in order to do that, what I'd like to do is say, well, let's make
this sample stuff actually be packed in exactly that way, right?
Let's make that be packed across the pixels.
So instead of having that array, we're going to make these into packed
registers.
Packed per pixel like so.
And then these guys are going to become 128 and 128 eyes, right?
Makes sense.
So once those guys are packed now, all of these things can actually be
done.
Right?
This way, as an MI value,
In fact, let's see.
Can we do some crazy Kung Fu here?
Let's find out if we can.
So I'm going to do a keyboard macro.
I'm going to search for wax sample, right.
Go back to it.
Insert the em, I hope in the parentheses, look for the bracket, close
it space come over and do that.
There we go, and off, we go.
Macros to the rescue.
Here we go.
And done.
All right, now we're doing things out of pack registers as you can see
no change, Although our cycle count continues to drop of course.
So there we go.
So now that we've gotten those into packed, we can start to look at
these and do these exactly same way.
Now, they pretty much are exactly this operation, right?
Because now, we essentially have what is the equivalent of the same
packing format in original dest in each of our samples.
So, if we want to do these,
Axel's we should in theory, just be able to clone exactly this code,
right?
We should be able to say that Texel.
DB right Texel DG Texel, Dr.
And Texel da are just the exact same things.
All that we were doing to unpack the desk but we're doing them off of
that sample, D that we prepared, which is basically a 4 pixel pack
version of the previous thing.
And then we just get rid of all this.
And we've got that little concise piece of code to process Texel d,
right off we go.
Everything looks good, right?
So essentially, what we can do is we can just
Do that for each of these and then we get rid of all of that, sort of
scalar version of the code and everything.
Can now be done why.
So, if I just go ahead and delete all this, just get rid of all this
code, goodbye, and just do each of these.
Once for each of our texels for each of our, you know, bilinear,
textiles texture samples here, like so
Let's go ahead and get those out there.
And Sample a.
We now have a pretty much everything converted to Cindy.
There we go.
And hey, look at that.
We're pretty much right down to where we wanted to be 50 cycles for
Pixel, strictly with just converting things to Cindy.
We're basically already there and we haven't really even done anything
else yet.
So, that's pretty awesome as well.
Okay, so we've got two minutes left, right?
Trying to think if there's anything else that we didn't do in here
that we have load destination unpack?
Paxil samples.
It looks like almost everything is now going through there except the
Texel fetch.
That looks like pretty much it.
I might be forgetting something, but it looks pretty good.
So there's one thing that we could do also right now which might be
kind of fun.
Which is I was saying before, what happens if you, if we don't really
need to set anything, right?
If you take a look at what happens here, we compute these u and v,
vectors we compute our right mask, right?
And I'm going to go ahead and move this original desk computation kind
of down here just for a second thing that loads the destination we
compute this
Mask.
But what if the right mask was all zeros, right?
So what if none of the pixels actually needed to get written?
You know what I'm saying?
If none of the pixels get written, we could effectively, do you know,
a giant, if around this whole thing where we just don't do any work at
all.
When we know that we're completely all four of the pixels are
completely outside of the fill, right?
We could do that.
And what I wanted to point out was there actually is a thing that
allows us to do that, right?
There is a thing called move mask, right?
And what move mask does you can see here.
It creates a mass from the most significant bit of each 8-bit element
in a and the stores, the result in dest.
So it basically takes every 8 bit and it puts it out into a scalar,
right?
So if we wanted to, we could also just do just trivially just to see
if it helped at all.
We could do a move mask Epi on the right mask and only if something
was set right.
Only, if some pixel was going to get filled, would we actually do the
work?
And so we can run that here and you can actually see the results right
now.
Unfortunately, that doesn't seem to give us any that doesn't give us
any speed when there.
But I just wanted to point out that it's possible.
If we were looping over a bunch of pixels which to do here,
Later recheck.
If this helps there's no point doing it doesn't help just want to
point out that it is possible to get things out of the conversion out
of the four wide into scalar if you want to do tests.
All right, so let's go ahead and go to the Q&A.
I think we're in pretty good shape here.
Looking at how things are working.
Doesn't look too bad.
Does not look too bad.
At 55 Cycles.
A pixel.
This is plenty Zippy.
You could easily play the game this way.
If you were so inclined,
All right.
Could you not just align the ex Corde to a 4 pixel, boundary upfront
and thereby use aligned loads and stores?
Yes, we absolutely could but you're getting ahead of us grumpy giant,
you are getting ahead of us.
Basically, I don't want to do that just yet because you'll notice that
we're still doing some nonsense here with with pre making the width
and height not actually be full so that we don't overwrite them.
And so,
I have to go back and properly allocate our frame buffer to make sure
that it's aligned in the first place in order to make all of this
stuff work properly, right?
So we just have to do this.
A couple things I want to show how to do before we get to that, but we
will actually do that.
I don't know that.
It'll actually have an effect on this processor but we will be doing
that.
Probably I suspect will test to make sure it's faster.
We pulling this code over into the ground Splat soon.
So actually this would already be working for the ground Splats if we
turned it on there, I turned off the ground / just because you know,
they were eating up a but they are what gets called first.
And so they were eating up a bunch of time.
But I, you know, if we turned it on, it is what's getting used for the
ground spots at the moment.
But those are so heavy weight.
At this point, I'm afraid, I don't know that we've sped it up enough
to make a difference with that code right because it's just doing way
too many of the Splats for a large number of reasons, one of which
being the fact that it's doing it in perspective at the moment, right?
So you can see we're still super janky there because we've just got
So much more Phil that's happening because of those those grants
chunks.
You know, one thing that I could do, I suppose to ameliorate that a
little bit, if you want the ground chunks on temporarily even though
now's not really a good time to have those ground chunks on because we
just haven't, we haven't done what we need to do that code but what we
could do if you really want to is the ground, buffer count, if it was
extended to a higher number would make it so that it
Miss the cash every frame and that would probably be sufficient to
make the ground buffers a little more usable.
But you can see, it's still every time it has to fill that cash.
You get that hiccup, right?
So we've got we've got work to do before.
We can really put the ground chunks in as I guess what I would say and
we have, you know, we've got a bunch of stuff to do here, you know,
like you've got to get rid of that blinking and so on, we've got, we
got a ton of stuff, we got to do.
So we'll get to the ground chuck.
I stood enough but that's why I did not have them in there.
Temporarily
Is it me or after this wholesome deconversion the cycles per pixel.
Pixel are much more consistent.
To be honest, I don't know if it's possible but I don't know.
I have kind of missed the past few days.
I'm wondering if doing CPU intrinsics, like exclusively for sse2 and
your game code is bad.
Or are we targeting sse2?
For example?
Shouldn't we wrap everything into platform, static file.
So it's easy to flag other Target platforms to compile.
Well,
So yes and no.
First of all at this point.
No, you definitely don't want to do that because nobody on this stream
besides me, potentially.
Well I mean there's other people on stream who are more, who it are
watching the stream more for entertainment purposes but people who are
learning from the stream of never programmed as a sea before.
So it would be massively putting the cart before the horse to try to
design an abstraction layer for your, for wide operation stuff before
you even ever optimize the routine, right?
And even so I typically always write the routine, the first time
directly in whatever the platform is that I'm working on.
And then I worry about pouring it over right.
It's a really bad idea to Target things ahead of time.
If you don't have some specific reason to do so or if you don't know
exactly how you want to do it, right?
Because then you know you don't really gain anything by doing that.
We know that this is the code that we now want, and we could easily
abstract it by just replacing
The intrinsics by macros that will compile to other intrinsics on me
on say, right?
So there really isn't anything to be gained by pre abstracting.
It that said will be have to do some platform work on this later.
Honestly, my gut feeling is no.
I don't think we'll ever run this on anything other than SSE.
The reason that I say that is because on the only platforms that we
might Target for neon,
The renderer is not gonna be running in software, like we're not going
to run a software renderer on an iPhone or something, right?
We're not going to run a software under on an Android phone.
We're certainly not going to run a software renderer on the Raspberry
Pi, right?
So this sse2 stuff is more for our edification to see how you do code
optimization for a thing like a software renderer.
And it's so that we have a complete view of the entire pipeline of
what renders the game.
But in
He will.
This code ever be ported to platforms, other than sse2, probably not.
We might do other sse2 optimizations elsewhere in the game that will
have to run a multiple platforms because you know for the physics or
something maybe but for the renderer probably not.
What does it mean for intrinsics that don't have a specified
throughput?
I it depends.
Which intrinsic are you referring to?
Instead of loading the destination first, would it be faster to skip
that step?
And instead do a mast, right?
Egm mask, move si64.
Well.
The only way to answer a question like that is to try it, usually, so
if you want to try a mass move, we can certainly try it.
So, here's the mass move conditionally store, 8-bit integer, Ellen
elements from a into memory using masks elements or not story when the
highest bit is set to the corresponding and a non temporal memory
hint.
So I don't know, we
You know, it's kind of interesting that this is mass moved.
So, it's interesting.
I guess there's no penalty for unaligned if you do a mass move, so,
all right, if we switch to a line we wouldn't be able to use this.
But for the moment we're doing a line anyway.
So yes, we could certainly try that.
Here's what that would look like.
So that's a mask review si128 and that is the out parameter, the right
mask parameter and the address to, which we are writing, right?
And it wants that as a care star.
So there is that mask move?
So let's take a look and see if it helps us
Here is our game running right now.
It seems to Min out at 55 cycles per pixel at the moment, right?
And then if we go in here and we switch to using the mask move,
And we take a look at what happens.
Well.
That certainly doesn't look very good.
Does it?
It is three times slower to use the mask move.
To be honest with you, I don't know why it's three times slower to use
the mask move.
But it currently is three times slower to use the mass move.
So, yeah, again that maybe a exercise left for when Fabi and does some
streams for educational purposes, because I don't know why that's
lower.
But at least turning it on in this simple case that was definitely bad
because if we just don't do the mass move, its way, way way, way
faster, three times faster.
In fact,
How are you doing?
Got other questions?
Would it be a good idea to just simply for all?
Math operations, in all our programs.
Well, yes, and no.
So Cindy is only useful if you happen to be able to do four things at
once, right?
So it's worth noting that when the when you're doing regular math,
like when we do stuff like, you know, this
This operation is done in the CMD set, right?
So if you take a look at what this actually does, if I go to this
assembly, right?
You can.
And I suppose I should probably turn it so we can actually see see
here, turn it to debug mode.
So when I compile and debug mode here, let's come in here.
And we're going to do this this compilation.
So, here we are.
In the disassembly.
Yeah, so if we go ahead and we do all this, this nonsense right load
things in of a Cess.
All right, I take it back.
I was going to say we should be able to see it do, but it's calling
up.
Oh, okay.
We're it's still actually doing the call.
That's why I was confused.
I'm like, where to do but it didn't in line it.
So that's fine.
That's all fine.
Try again, Visual Studio try again.
So this is actually where we want to be sorry about that.
This is what I wanted to show you.
So, if you look at what happens here, right?
It's actually using those same D registers to do all the operations.
Right is still doing everything in the exact same way.
It was doing it before, right?
The only difference is that instead of, you know, it'll, it'll do like
this mob to XM M 0.
It's going to put it in the x10 register and then instead of doing a
multi multiplication of the pack singles, it just does a
multiplication of just the first Lane, right?
So you're still, it's still, it's using the same.
It's doing essentially the same thing.
The only difference is is not doing it for wide, right?
It's still, it's still all exactly the same stuff, it's just not for
wide, okay?
And so the important thing to understand there is the only way that
you get a win from switching to the compiler.
Intrinsics in terms of the width is if you can actually do four things
at once all the time and a lot of times it's not the case.
A lot of times you don't have it set up to do it that way.
Right?
So that's one thing.
The other thing is that it may not be worth it to figure out how to do
the same D properly everywhere, it may be too much work, right?
And it may be that the speed wind that you would get out of it is is
very limited, right?
So you also want to be able to Target pieces of your code that where
you think you're actually going to be able to get a performance
increase by forcing, all of the data to work in a 4 wide fashion
because it's not free, right?
You've got you got to do.
You got to do?
To put it in and out of that format and all sorts of things like that.
Example of an intrinsic with no throughput.
MM, cop gtps.
I have a guess as to why that probably is, but let's find out.
Interesting.
Well.
Well, you know what?
I don't know.
Let's see.
Let's take a little closer look.
So, here we are in the Intel architecture guide.
And we'll take a look at the compiler intrinsics the actual
instruction set documentation for those intrinsic.
So here we are.
Compared packed single integers for greater than
And let's take a look and see if it's got any information about it in
here.
That would help us understand what's going on.
I don't know they will but we can at least take a quick check.
Let's see.
Forms a 70, sunk a for greater value.
W is still in the source up rinkeby Ms.
Yes they see Second Source operating.
Okay 0 strategy will you d?
So I don't see anything particularly noteworthy here.
So, I don't know.
I do not know why that is the case.
So what we could do
well that's signed integers as well.
I feel like that was the wrong one there.
Cop gtps.
Let's just make sure we get the right one there.
So, it's comp PS is what's actually being called C mpps.
Okay.
Compare pack single Precision floating Point values.
This is the actual operation for the one that you just asked about.
Let's see.
So, I do Wonder.
A little bit about this.
Note.
The processor is with CPR.
Do 1 H EC X AV x equals 0 to not implement the greater than greater
than or equal to naught greater than or not going to lations these
comparison can be made either by using an inverse relationship, using
not less than or equal to to make a greater than or by using software
emulation when using cell from which the premise swap, the operands
copywriters, administrative protect the data, that will now be in the
destination, and then perform the compare using different predicate.
So, I'm not sure.
I'm not sure.
So let's take a look at what comp PS throughput says here.
Let's take a look.
so, it looks like
It at least looks like documentation wise here that the throughput is.
Is 24 comp PS?
Actually assuming that I'm reading this right here.
Let me see if anyone else has a particular.
I know if anyone else has
something we want to look at there.
So I don't know why it's listed that way in here, to be honest with
you, I'm not sure it looks like the answer might actually more
correctly, be too, but somebody more familiar at this would have to
answer that because I don't see an obvious answer.
And grumpy giant post.
That agner fog says, the throughput is one, which also seems like a
pretty reasonable thing that would be true.
So I don't know.
It might be because of the fact that it's not sure.
But it's, I mean, it's even listing comp PS as the instruction here.
So I don't know.
I don't know why.
It thinks the throughput is Dash.
It would be nice if someone from Intel would tell us.
Maybe I'll try to ask someone and be like, why is it's a dash here?
Anyone else?
No.
Alright, I guess we have come to the end.
And mr.
Stone 56.
Yes, it is.
The amount latency is the total amount of time.
It takes from start to finish for any given issues of that
instruction.
Whereas throughput is, if you issue them back to back, that's how many
you can eventually get due to the overlap.
The marsala.
What is the end goal of the optimization trying to get below a certain
threshold or just getting everything converted?
The end goal.
The optimization is actually for us to go ahead.
We haven't done this yet.
We have probably will be able to do it tomorrow I think, but we're
trying to basically have everything converted so that we can get an
estimate of how many cycles per pixel.
We think we should be able to get it too.
And then once we know that number, we will see how close we can get to
whatever that theoretical number is.
Anyone else?
We all good.
Does size of variables and stuff matter to Cindy like 30.
It versus 64-bit.
Yes, the size absolutely does matter and the reason it matters is
because it determines how many of them you can fit inside a single
operation.
So Cindy registers in SSE are 128 bits in AVX, their 256 bits.
And in avx-512 there 512 bits
What that means is the maximum number.
Of things you can fit into a single register which is how many you can
operate on at once, is that number of B divided by the size of the
data type.
So if you are doing 32-bit values, you can operate on four of them and
SSE, eight of them in a VX and 16 of them in avx-512, right?
If on the other hand, you wanted to operate on 64-bit values,
You would only be able to fit two of them at a time through the
pipeline in SSE.
Four of them at a time in AV x, + 8 of them at a time in avx-512, in
addition to that.
Some operations may be more costly in 64-bit than they are in 32-bit.
So when you look up one of the operations, you may find that doing,
for example, a divided and 64-bit is more expensive than doing a
divide in 32-bit.
So in some cases you may be you may get hit twice, it may both be
operating on less and it may be
Lower.
So it does matter quite a bit and typically what you want to do is you
want to use the smallest size variables that you can to still do the
operations that you need to do.
That makes sense.
It's the SS C code.
Doing any cash prefetch or hinting stuff yet?
No.
In fact we are not even aligned yet.
We have not gotten to the memory part of things.
Yet we just did our translation of the routine into Cindy directly and
we haven't done any other work at all.
So there's no pre-caching there's no alignment.
I think if there's anything else there's no non-temporal stores,
although in this case, I don't think we would want those.
So there's very little besides just the root transformation.
I'm not sure how much we're going to get out of that.
Prefetch might get us something.
I don't know.
We're going to have to find out, but it's hard to say, Obviously,
until you test it.
It's kind of running surprisingly fast at the moment.
It's down to like 50 cycles per pixel.
That means the total routine is running at something like 200 Cycles.
So you know a 200 cycle Loop doesn't have a huge amount there.
There can't be that many memory stalls in a 200 cycle Loop.
Right?
So unfortunately I don't know that we're going to get a huge amount of
wind from prefetching but you know if we're lucky
Some of that 200 Cycles is sitting around waiting for something that
could be prefetched.
I don't know if it will be or not.
We'll just have to see.
Couldn't we use a half float instead of floats, as we don't need that
much of precision with only two and five discrete values.
We cannot use half float because the SSC operations do not support
half float.
SSE 2 does not have multiplication etc for half with floats so we
can't use them at the moment.
We could try to implement half float, ourselves ourselves but my would
suspect that that would actually be much more costly than if we just
use 16-bit fixed point.
So if we were going to do that, we would probably try try to do 16-bit
fixed Point instead because 16-bit fixed point would be way easier to
implement than
32-bit float.
Now, whether 16-bit fixed point would be faster or not.
It's hard to say, it's might be something that we might want to try
doing.
It's something that I kind of had the back of my mind.
If you look at how this routine ended up, there aren't that many math
operations.
So it's possible that maybe we could get a win there by being creative
about how we did stuff.
I don't know.
It's it's, it's hard to say.
I suspect that it would be a bit of a battle but, you know, if we
could keep it similar to the number, the same number of operations
somehow but be able to go down to 16 bit.
That would that would double the amount of pixels we can do at a time
and that would be pretty awesome, right?
So,
There's that.
Use the normal map code going to be converted to Cindy.
Yes, eventually.
I think we will try to convert the normal map code to Cindy once we
actually figure out how it should work, exactly?
Right.
Anyone.
All right, I think we are done.
I think we have come to the end of the stream.
So let's go ahead and wrap things up.
Okay, thank you, everyone for joining me for another episode of
handmade hero.
It's been a pleasure coding with you, as always, it was kind of fun to
get to the end of the Cindy translation stuff today will sort of look
at things.
A little bit outside of that tomorrow, but it's pretty cool.
We've come a long way, right?
When we started this, our game was running so slowly that you could
barely move the character on the screen at all.
And now we are totally running like 30 frames/second, no problems, so
optimization for the win and we haven't really even hit it with all
that much of an optimization Hammer yet.
All we did was take advantage of the processors ability to do for wide
pixel operations, and that was enough.
For us to, to get a pretty massive speed win.
So I hope you've enjoyed that and we've got some more good stuff
coming.
In terms of optimization that will be doing pretty soon.
Here, we'll do some more tomorrow and certainly, you know, throughout
the week and then we also have, you know, multi-threading, which is on
the horizon because multi-threading the render is also something we
can do.
That's not particularly difficult that get will get us a significant
speed Improvement because you know pretty much all machines.
These days have between four and eight threads, you can take advantage
of that actually do accelerate.
Hardware by using them.
And so that's something that we probably want to take a look at as
well.
So we'll maybe take a look at that.
So just a bunch of good stuff coming up.
Hope you'll tune in for that again.
Tomorrow, 5:00 p.m.
Pacific.
Daylight time is when we will be live if you'd like to catch the next
stream.
In the meantime, if you like to play around with source code at home,
you can always pre-order the game on handmade hero dot org and it
comes with the full source code so that you can play around with it at
home and do your own experiments play around with optimization.
It's a good way to learn from the stream.
We also have a forum that you can go to which is a place to ask
questions.
You can also look at ports, the community's done to like mac and Linux
that sort of stuff.
There's an annotated episode guide, things like that.
We also have a tweetbot, the tweets, the schedule it you.
So if you want to
Be kept up to date when the the next live stream is that's an error
and what the whole schedule for the week going to be?
In fact, that's a great place to do that.
You can subscribe to that Twitter feed and it will tell you so that's
about it.
I hope to see you all back here, tomorrow.
5:00 p.m.
same time, same place.
Until then, please have a fun coating evening and I will catch you
guys tomorrow.
All right, take it.
Easy, everyone.