Hello, everyone, and welcome to handmade hero.
The show we code complete game live on stream.
We are doing some z-buffer work.
I've already explained it all when we started to make the changes for
it and we probably would have been done with the changes this past
weekend, except we took last weekend to do some ketchup streams that
had been scheduled for a while.
One was a mock interview with Sean McGrath that we were supposed to
do.
And we did that.
And the other was a handmade con 2016.
With Charles Bloom and we did that.
Both of those were really cool.
If you haven't checked them out, you should check them out on the
handmade Hero YouTube channel.
But now we are back to programming.
And so let's just go ahead and dive right back into it.
I should open up.
Where's my Milton at?
I should open up my Milton case, we need to draw some things.
Let's go ahead and close that off and
Let us open up our project today is day for 60, so if you're following
along at home, you want to open up day 359 source code and start with
that.
That is where I'm starting with.
So let's go ahead and get the project open and building.
Now, if you remember correctly, since we've switched over to the
z-buffer now we are
In sort of limbo, we are old.
Sorting is not going to work anymore.
And we haven't quite gotten to the point where the z-buffer stuff is
enabled.
So if you run the game, it's just a flash A Thon, right?
Everything's going nuts.
And everything is always in the right place and the game is
functioning as it should.
But the Sorting is completely haywire and that's exactly what we
expect to happen.
So that's not unusual, but it's just worth pointing out that that's
where things are at.
So, obviously, our goal is to return our game to like a stable
appearance, but using the Z buffer instead of
Right, sorting, which is what we were doing before that is now
disabled.
So if we go to render group, remember what we were sort of doing is
slowly sort of moving the projection operations that we had here and
get render entity basis fee.
And we were slowly moving them over into opengl and we already have
done a little bit of that.
Work.
So let me, let me grab that here.
Here you go.
We already have done a little bit of that work because we had this
sort of notion of these.
This opengl screen space here that we were using.
And before we had a bunch of stuff in here, that wasn't really
relevant that we could basically fold into the opengl screen, space
operation.
And what we were doing prior to our changes in open, just the screen
space to sort of undoing stuff that we had done in get render entity
basis.
And in some sense this is work that we probably should have done
anyway because it makes more sense to have this stuff in the actual
render layer than it does to have it in the code that just pushes
things on to the render stack.
Probably, you know, it's it's six of one half-dozen the other but it
just makes more sense to have it that way because it gives you more
flexibility in the render back end.
It's a little bit more bookkeeping but and what kind of see that
happen a little bit later on, but in general, like a kind of it's nice
to kind of move the stuff over because that way the renderer back-end
can use the
Full horsepower of whatever it is operating with.
So in the case where you have a software back end, what we doesn't
matter because software has to do the transforms like it would have in
either place.
But when it's using a hardware back end, you can offload that work
onto the GPU which is in a game like this exactly what you want to do.
Since, you know, you have a lot more GPU power than you need for the
typical 2-D game.
These days, right?
Gpus are set up to run something like Battlefield 1.
And so when you're throwing something like handmade,
About them.
You know, they have more than enough horsepower.
You're not in a situation where you have to be thinking about, should
I try to keep some of the work on the CPU?
So that I, you know, don't use up more GPU, resources, that I need for
some other thing, right?
So just being aware of that, it's like good to kind of have it so that
the render layer can have that ability to offload work to the GPU
because we know we've got the horsepower there.
So the more stuff we can push over there.
The more CPU, we free up for doing stuff like gameplay.
And in this case, we know pretty much that we're not going to stress
out.
Out a GPU with something like handmade hero because we're not trying
to reduce, like Photo realistic 3D Graphics or something like that.
Where, you know, you might start to get concerned and need to do
things on the CPU side, for whatever reasons.
Alright, so here we are, get render entity basis p.
And what you can see here is we've still got this m 2 pixels concept
going on here and really the m 2 pixels concept.
At this point, I think could probably be retired.
All it really is, is a scaling Factor right now.
That's it.
It doesn't really do anything else at all.
And so if we take a look inside the camera code, right?
And we look at where m 2 pixels is getting set, it's just a scaling
factor for the game.
Now that's all it is because everything has been transformed.
It's in World space now and being operated on that way and we don't
really need that m, 2 pixels transform for anything in particular,
right?
It's just sort of an arbitrary idea of how we want to scale the game,
but we can just set the cameras.
To be greater or less than based on that.
And it doesn't really matter in one way or the other, because it's
just an extra multiplicative Factor, right?
It's just something that cancels out the z a little bit, so we don't
really need that factor for anything in particular anymore.
And we could just decide to get rid of it, right?
We could just decide that it's Superfluous and we don't actually need
it.
Let me go ahead and grab where we're setting it here.
Let's see.
I guess that's in our camera.
Here we go.
So, when we set this in code, right?
We're setting these m 2 pixels.
Where is our perspective call?
No word.
Is your see where work on that.
It's right here so you can see us doing this.
I think and get standard camera parameters.
Probably, is where we're doing it.
So camera parameters?
Oops.
Why can I not find this get standard camera?
The ramp?
I typed out parameters.
All right, so if we take a look at this function here, you can see us
doing sort of a nominal computation in order to get this scaling
Factor here, right?
So we've got this world scale concept.
If we were to just say that the only camera program was going to be
the focal length, right?
And we just don't scale the world anymore by anything in particular.
We would end up with something that looks like this everywhere.
We were using the world scale, you know, would just go away and
subscribe to take a look at what happens if you remove that.
Entirely.
Right?
So everywhere that we had been passing the world scale that goes away
and we're just left with just the focal length.
And then we take a look at those calls in where we've got orthographic
and and perspective happening.
And if we take a look at the other thing too, that you'll notice is
the only place we use.
Orthographic is for our debug UI, and when we call that, you'll
notice, we don't even use the m, 2 pixels transform because we were
just using screen space there.
Right?
So, if we take a look at what's actually happening there, and we go to
those functions.
And we remove m 2, pixels entirely, so it doesn't need to get past
anymore.
Like so now we just have to remove it from this function.
And and that's about all we should have to do.
So we take a look here.
We are multiplying at this was just previously only ever a one anyway.
So there was no actual operation of the m 2 pixels there.
Here it would be would get rid of it as well and then let's see where
else we've got it.
Here it is.
So that just goes away.
Same.
If this is the unprojected here.
So obviously anything that we were doing in the projection had to be
unprotected here, we've gotten rid of it.
So now we don't need to do that anymore.
Are we using monitor half dim in meters for any?
Thing either.
See here.
M.
Just curious where that's being used at the moment.
so it's being used here where we want to do, our fit distance to have
to write and
Get camera rectangle at distance, right?
So basically, we're using that monitor half-demon M.
We're using that because we need to know how big the screen is, right?
And I feel like if we could rewrite, these two routines to be
agnostic, and just use the transform that we know we're doing with the
screen area, so I think we could get rid of this as well.
So
Because that's just going to be a function, the pixels to meters.
We should be able to figure out how to do that.
Just from using our transform alone, using the focal length and so on
Isn't this focal length supposed to be right if this focal length it
does get passed it in the perspective but not in this one.
So in the orthographic case we can do this trivially because we
basically know.
Oops, we basically know that this is the size of the screen.
Always right?
The size of the screen is always going to be the pixel size because
the orthographic operation doesn't actually change this at.
All right, the, the pixels,
M is not relevant here at all.
Right.
So you know monitor half dim in meters and the screen center are the
exact same thing in this case, right?
Because we just have half the screen length in pixels is going to be
half the dimension at.
That's, there's no difference there.
We don't have to convert anything because pixels are the actual unit
at that point.
So we're good to go.
So, the only thing that's a little confusing is what we do Under the
perspective, transform in terms of doing pixels to M.
And again,
right now, the only place we're actually using any of that is when we
look back at,
When we try to do things where we imagine, what is the like in the
world, what is the area that the monitor can basically see right?
And that's what we needed it for.
So, in order to do that we just need some way of getting rid of this
and figuring out in Reverse.
We don't necessary have to do that now, but we'll have to put that on
our to-do list.
I also am interested in if screen center gets used because I don't
think it does.
Either you can kind of see that it really
Doesn't get used much.
It's only for reverse.
It's the same.
The same thing only for reverse projection.
Right, you can kind of see how that works.
So all of this stuff is basically only used for reverse projection now
except for the focal length, which is the part that we're actually
using to generate the perspective transform.
So I think, in terms of what we actually need, we probably can just
reverse everything out with with just storing the screen.
Dimensions, is probably all we need.
So I think what we probably do in here is say, alright for the camera
Transformer, probably not going to store the screen center anymore,
we'll probably just store the screen dimensions.
Right?
And this will be like our new consort of compact definition and we'll
go from there as we go.
So let's just go screen dimensions.
There's the pixel width and pixel height.
Oops, we won't store the half dim anymore and this will be the same in
both.
And this will go away.
And so really, these will become essentially the same and the only
real difference here is whether you set the focal length and the
camera P that's about it.
So, these are basically that now the same routine, we could even
really merge them.
If we wanted to buy, just passing a Boolean in here, for whether, or
not the thing was prospective or not.
So, for example, if we wanted to we could just have something that was
more like this.
And this would just be this routine.
Exactly as it is.
And this would take a superset of the parameters.
Right?
And and that's all we would need to do, right?
So then when we're doing a perspective transform, we just say, oh
please set the camera transform to this vocollect and this camera p
and we'll just pass false because it's not orthographic.
And then in this case, will pass through and will make up the focal
length and the camera P just like we were doing before.
And then we just have one routine groups.
We'll just have one routine that sets that up and either you can use
it in either way.
So then, if we start to look at this, like I said, The only things
that we have trouble with here are unprojected
Which unfortunately is not going to work anymore because you can see
it needs to do some operations that it doesn't have the information.
It needs to now screen center, though.
If we take a look at what's going on here, it really only is looking
at unprojected it's looking at the screen center, there's not a lot
more information that it actually needs here if you look at it.
So actually if we wanted to make unprojected work properly,
We all we really need for screen center.
In this case is to generate that value.
And since we know, since we actually already have that information,
excuse me.
We already know what that what that value actually is we can just
compute it here, right?
The screen center is just half of the screen dimension, right?
Because we know that's what we you know when we're correcting for
window coordinates after the fact we know that we want zero zero in
the center of the screen.
So we just need to go halfway to the width halfway to the height,
there's nothing else to it.
So from here, if we want to, we can just say transfer and scream dim
and produce that value, that solves that problem.
And then everyone's happy.
I thought we also had a problem with the fit render distance, the
monitor half demand M, who is, I don't know who's calling this or
where they're getting that monitor half dim in meters.
So I'm just going to take a look fit camera distance to half, Jim.
It looks like nobody's using this yet, so I guess we're off the hook
for right now, but as soon as someone to use is it, we're going to
have to replace that they'll run into the problem of not.
Having that value basically.
All right, so that's where we're at.
And now when we call it, what we should get is basically exactly the
same game but we're just be at slightly the wrong place, right?
There along zoom level.
And the reason for that is we were applying a world scale before, and
we're not applying a world scale.
Now, now, that's makes it pretty simple for us to deal with,
obviously,
All we have to do is when we're setting up where our camera supposed
to be, we just move the camera closer, right?
There's nothing else in particular that we have to do because it was
just a uniform scale that was happening there.
Really isn't much else to it.
So all I need to do here is when I when I do add room code and we're
creating how far the camera should be.
All we need to do is just say like, okay, you know, we need the camera
to be at a different height, right?
And we don't really know.
Yet because we haven't done the rest of the work.
We don't really have a concrete idea of
Exactly how we want the camera to work yet because we're still doing
our transition to 3D but otherwise, we're pretty much what, you know,
we're at the place where we want to be.
Now, the white rectangle there is I don't remember what that's
supposed to be representing, but it looks like that's in the wrong
place.
So I'm interested to know, we should take a quick look, just to see
where our debug rectangles are supposed to be and just make sure that
those are still working properly.
Early.
So, the white rectangle is this one.
Here.
So, the white rectangle is
World chunk.
I don't really know.
What that's for?
Or why it was there.
I'm gonna get rid of that because I don't really know why we needed
that at the moment.
But I am curious.
So it would be nice if we had
A little more information here, like I don't see our other rectangles
which is not.
I don't know why we don't have our other rectangles here because I
feel like we should see our other rectangles like our screen bounds
rectangle and furthermore I don't know how we're doing our screen
Bounds at the moment, so we should take a look at that as well.
Like, where is our screen bounds?
Get camera rectangle at Target.
So let's take a look at that Target.
There it is.
So let's see.
So monitor half-demon m is still being used.
That's the problem.
There we go.
I knew I was going to say, I knew somebody was.
Yeah, I think we did that search.
I was like, I should have been somebody else.
Okay, so let's take a look here at what we've got.
I don't know why we still have this.
Unprojected old situation going on here.
It looks like we didn't, I guess it's because we wanted one that
didn't have an object transform with it, I suppose.
But anyway, so if we take a look here at our projected X Y in her at a
distance from camera, this thing is using an unpredictable and it's
pushing them monitor have given me.
Down there.
And what you'll notice about that is that's not actually I think this
was just kind of a sort of cheating a little bit and we probably did
it first so we just did it in the minimal way, which is fine.
But if you take a look at like unprojected, for example, in
unprojected, what we have the capability to do here is unprojected
actual screen coordinates.
Since we know the dimensions of the screen, we should be able to get a
camera rectangle.
Out of that.
By just unprojected the two corners of the screen, the minimum corner
of the screen, the maximum cournot screen should unprojected to the
rectangle that we want, right?
So, it should be relatively straightforward for us to do that.
And the other thing that I would say about this, it's a little bit odd
is if we look at what's actually happening here for rec center half
dim again, this is kind of a nonsense number because this is not
It actually placed in the world where the camera is going to be
either.
And so you know, we
part of this is kind of a misnomer routine and it was actually
It's clear that we didn't actually care about that.
Like we did the screen bounds that were passing, right?
Is just sort of a rectangle that doesn't have a placement in the
world.
You can, you can see that.
You can see that pretty clearly here, right?
When we actually call get rekt camera, rectangle, at Target with
render group, you can see that we create the boundaries from that, but
then when we actually go to use them, we pass a camera p as well.
So those Sim bonds are actually just the rectangle.
And what's interesting about that is we could actually start just
passing a rectangle that was in the correct space potentially.
But the reason that we don't do that is because
Because the rectangle would then have to be in full coordinates, not
local coordinates so it wouldn't just be floating point value.
So yeah, so when we call camera record, get camera angle at distance.
What we're really producing here is just the size of that rectangle.
So it's really not a rectangle in some sense.
It should just return a V2, which is the size.
That's probably what we should have done to be a little clearer about
what you were actually getting but you know, we didn't do that so
maybe we'll change that
Anyway, so at this point, what I would say is let's use done project
here as the thing that we want to do.
Now, the object transform is, you can see the object transform has an
effect on these.
The object transfer will modify the
Thing we're using.
What's unusual about the object transform is I don't think well now,
okay we do so you can see us using the Z value for the unprotect,
they're modifying, you know, getting combined with the cameras either.
And so I think if we if we want to do unprotect here, all we need to
do is just not actually bother using any object transform at all and
then we should be fine.
So we don't need unprotected bold anymore at that point, that can go
away.
And if we do kick camera, rectangular distance with distance from
camera, being the information we need there, then if we take a look at
object transform, which is here,
Right, we can do.
Get default.
You know, the thing that gets the default object transform.
There it is.
Will you see if I transform?
So if we have the default flat, transform their all we have to do is
then set the Z for that, right?
To be that distance that we wanted it to be the distance from camera.
Now, the distance from camera in this case is measured in the opposite
direction.
Action, right?
So the distance from camera and this case should actually be
Well no I guess it's just always going to be.
No, because it would be negative because this is, from camera, is
moving out along the negative Z axis.
So, the distance from camera, and this case would be negative, right?
Because Z comes at us and we're saying, we're pushing this away from
the camera, is the phrasing of this routine.
So I think that we just want that to be negative distance from camera,
right?
And it won't matter.
In this case because it's going to be 0.
Anyway, since the one we're calling is this but, you know, just to be
consistent.
So if we produce that transform and then we do a nun, project--
Then what we can do is we can get both the things we want, so we can
get min corner.
And that'll just be a nun.
Project-- with this object transform and the pixels x y is just going
to be 0 0.
And then the max Corner, we would just pass the screen dimensions.
So then we have fun transformed the point of the bottom of the screen
and we untransformed the point at the top of the screen and this would
give us the real rectangle, right?
So that's the actual thing that we actually wanted to know as a, as a
rectangle 3.
Right.
Because now we've got a rectangle, three result.
that hasn't been quarter and a Max corner and I don't remember how you
can we constructed these
Recommend Max.
There it is.
But now that's producing the actual rectangle in 3D space, that
represents the rectangle that the camera can see out at a certain
distance.
Which is what we want.
And I feel like this is a much nicer way to do this.
Like I said, we're just kind of this is nice going through this and
turning into 3D it.
It makes me happy anyway because it sort of, you can see things start
to get more and more uniform less hacky, right?
Because instead of sort of making all these decisions about how we
were doing 2D stuff, condensing it down to 3D just makes things much
cleaner.
Like, okay, so now we run projecting, we just have one on Project
call.
Everything else is phrased in terms of the on a project called the
unprotect call is getting more and more simplified.
You can actually see
even here that the unprojected call is now just one thing that happens
with the perspective transformation slightly differently than the
orthographic we could if we wanted to actually do this, right?
and then in,
in place of a
It's just the this again.
Right.
And so this sorts of gets a little more condensed as well.
And
Just gets nicer, you know, as we go.
So, all right, if I compile that we've still got a little bit of
problem stuff to clean up here.
Obviously, I don't pee is not a member of object transform, is that
true?
Where is my object, transform?
It is offset.
P we go, we've got a screen dimension here, which I think it's the
camera transform that has that in it, right?
and then down here,
We have that rectangle three that we're getting back, like so.
And then we just have to take care of updating render World, which is
the places actually use.
So, we want a two-dimensional screen bands out of this.
When we get this back we're going to get camera wrecked.
Our world camera wrecked.
So if we want that screen bounds, what we need to do there is we need
to say, all right, if we just want the screen, bounce back from this,
we've got the world camera rectangle that world camera rectangle does
have the information that we need.
So, we just need a wrecked, you know, min max, for this, for this
sausage gentlemen.
And we wanted it to be based at V, 0 0.
And then we just wanted their the dimensions of it too.
Sleepy like World camera.
Rex Min Corner, remember how this is phrased here?
Dot Min.
So we just wanted, it's Min corner.
And Max Corners, subtracted.
And that's all.
So we just want we just wanted the 2D span of this thing, so that's
all we're going to do.
So in theory now we oh dear.
What have I done?
So, in theory now and only in theory, as you can see from the running,
we have that straightened out but we obviously have a problem in their
summer, so we will have to go and figure out what, what?
We set ask you, oh, I know why it was rectangle Center, Dim, this was
supposed to be centered around, zero zero.
That was the foreign we wanted, okay?
We still probably have problems in there but this is it.
There we go.
I guess we don't have problems in their.
So in theory that gives us back that rectangle that we wanted, and it
looks like that's giving it back to us properly, because now we're
simulating the region that we think we're simulating, which is what we
wanted.
All right now.
I don't know why.
I'm not seeing it, though.
That's a little bit weird.
I wonder if I set the debug distance.
Like, I'm just not seeing those rectangles, which I don't.
And why I'm not seeing those rectangles, right?
The pink rectangle.
Is there, but the other ones aren't, which is even weirder because
that means it's working.
Sort of
Okay, so let's take a look.
We're drawing the screen bounds, the Sim bounds, and the world Zoom
region.
So, the pink one is the world Sim Sim region bounds.
So the Sim bounds in the screen bounds are both like used to build
that.
So, it seems sort of bizarre that that we're not seeing those like we
should I'm going to step in here because I just want to see.
Like at this point, I'd like to know what those actually are, so
If I come in here and just take a look inside World mode at that
actual code.
I just want to know what the oops the values of those are.
Looks like I did pick the right one.
So here we go and you can see us getting the dimensions of these
things here.
So here's the screen bounds.
Here's the Sim bounds, here's the world Sim Sim region bounds
All right, so the screen bounds are nuts.
I think we can all agree that they are just completely ludicrous.
So we're going to take a look at what's going on there.
The Sim bounds are very reasonable.
So I'm not sure why we're not seeing those and the world Sim Sim
region bounds, okay?
So those just happen to both be in the same place so we're just
drawing the same thing twice in this case.
And I guess that makes sense because we decided not to enlarge the
same region anymore.
I think is what ended up happening with that.
So, I guess that seems reasonable well prep.
We're probably still play with that a little bit more as we go, but
that, that makes sense.
So, here in our push rekt outline call, we know that that our screen
bounds are janky.
So let's go up here and find out what's going on with that.
Especially, because we're using those here to produce some other
stuff.
So I'm not sure.
I guess it's because we don't actually use the boundaries of that when
we get to the end here.
So let's go ahead and step into our transform call and see what I
messed up there.
Here we go.
With our their camera transform.
So the distance from Cameron, this case should be 0, which is what we
would expect.
So now we're going to do a nun project-- with that transform.
and,
Let's just take a look at what the current camera transform is screen,
dimensions wise.
So here's that screen dim, it's exactly what we would expect, right?
1920 by 1080, that is exactly the size of the screen that we were, we
would expect to see there's the focal length, which is what we set it
to, I mean, within floating Point Precision, anyway, and there's the
camera p.
Well, okay.
So
That's that's a problem.
So the problem here we don't have distance from camera anymore.
So the way that was working as distance from camera actually is going
to have to be passed, to be what you actually think the camera
distance is so because the camera transformed doesn't
Isn't giving that information at the moment.
What what's going on there?
Because that's the problem right there.
So, how is that working inside?
Here we've done.
We've set the perspective camera here so that should have already been
set and the camera offset should have been.
I would have thought the camera offset should have been we go and run
that.
The camera offset should have been set to something like 11.
Right?
So what's going on there?
Like that.
There you go.
I mean, there's a camera off set of 10.
We're setting that here.
So the camera P should be that thing, right?
There's the 10.
So now, when we come in here, why wasn't I seen that?
Did I just lose?
I just looking at the wrong thing.
No, not there it is.
Okay, so that's all fine.
Okay, so here, we've got our screen Center information, which is
exactly what we expected to be.
In this case we're setting the zero.
We're trying to get the 00 corner for our pixels.
So we do our own projection, we subtract the screen center away and
then we should have a balanced coordinate.
We do this is definitely expecting.
We're taking the camera pz and the offset pz.
So in this case we should end up getting you know that 10 value here
and we're dividing that by the focal length of
Three.
Right.
And then we're multiplying it by the unprojected, so that should give
us.
Where's our unprotected?
That should have given us.
That, that is not.
What I would have expected.
So I think, you know what, I just realized.
So this is not the correct transform anymore because this is still
doing the on project-based way.
We used to be doing the transform, but we are using the sort of shrink
to negative 1 to 1 and then blow back out to the screen transform now
from opengl.
So this transform is not going to be accurate.
We need to redo this fun project.
All right, so we actually need to redo the sun project to match the
transform that we're actually doing.
Now, one of the things, that's probably true at this point is because
we want to match the unprojected here.
What we probably want to do is we want to sort of unify these two code
paths, right?
So we've got we're setting this Matrix up here and this is the Matrix
that will, you know, things will be getting X.
In opengl will be probably want to do.
Is have some way of saying, let's set this Matrix.
Let's think about what this Matrix should be in our actual render code
directly so that when we want to do something like a nun project, we
are always doing that in a unified way.
So, I feel like we want to get there.
I don't know if we want to get there immediately.
Like, I'm going to, I think I want to fix this unprojected first and
then smush them together more.
But I feel like that's where we want to go, right?
Because otherwise, they're sort of separated pieces of code that just
happen to line up with each other because we worked out the math for
them, but it would be nice if we just had, you know, if we just had
this Matrix.
For example, let's say we just kept this Matrix inside the render code
then
We go to unprotect.
We just unprojected by The Matrix, right?
And we wouldn't have to think about it as two separate pieces of code.
That happened to line up.
It could be a little more unified.
So I feel like we want to get there at some point but right now we'll
just kind of work this through the way that we need to for this
particular function.
And we'll kind of just keep an eye on it.
So here's day 360.
And this is unprotect.
So, here is our project projection Matrix.
And we've got, you can see the diagonal happening here.
So these are the two coefficients that were using.
So anything that comes in here is going to get multiplied by
2 on and off.
Sorry, it's gonna get x 2 for the.
But the x + 2 times the width over the height for the Y, right?
And that's going to shrink it down and then it's going to get expanded
back out by opengl using this.
The screen size, right?
And you can see that what's missing here.
First of all, is we have to think through what part of this cancels
out.
It may be that this already canceled set up, but you can see right
here that you already have a problem.
Which is that the screen dimensions itself opengl has to is doing
Normalization for us.
So we do a transform in our coordinates come out negative 1 to 1
negative 1 to 1 in all dimensions opengl then multiplies by the screen
dimension.
We are not dividing by the screen dimension here, right?
Which we would need to do.
So the you know, when we do this on Project, the first thing we would
need to do after we do the shift right here, we would need to take the
X.
And the Y and we need to basically unless you know take that inverse
screen dimension and put them back to negative 1 to 1 coordinates just
like we were doing before right in order to reverse this transform and
then we also need to obey this the aspect ratio offset of them right
because we're doing that here.
So we have to also do this exact operation in Reverse which is going
to be the sort of the doubling.
Multiply, and then we can finally at the end of all of that undo the
other piece of the transform, right?
So the unprojected XY dot X here is going to be, you can see what's
what what this is here.
It's going to be a divide by 2 here, right?
Or a multiplied by 0.5 and then
For the y coordinate.
It's the same thing except it also has to invert this.
So, it's the height over the width there.
So, we've got essentially a height, I'm sorry.
It's the width over the height there.
So it's the height over the width here.
Right.
So you can see me just doing the opposite of what we were doing right
now.
Since this is a divided.
And this is a multiply I can just roll these in together.
If I want to write Hoops, same here.
and I could think of this as the aspect correction term,
Right.
And furthermore since I've already got a divided in there,
what I can also do here is say the, you know, let's just go ahead and
And leave the aspect term, the same as it is in the other one.
Because you see here, we had X over y.
So if I just put that in the didn't in the numerator here, that will
invert it.
So that way, our aspect term is the same term in both which again like
I said, I want to kind of mush get these to be a little more uniform.
So that undoes the projection that opengl is doing for screen
coordinates and then all we have to do is take it from there that
would produce what we would expect.
In terms of our own project.
So from there, what we would need to do is say okay, we then once we
have it in there, we've got to finish doing our Z.
So from there, we would take it to just the, the stuff that was in the
open.
Jill basis.
I'm going to start the opengl, the get render render entity basis P
stuff and you can see what's going on there.
There's some nonsense with the hide off floor and all that stuff, but
we were going to, we were going to get rid of that stuff anyway, so
that's the full kind of come away, but
We've got that 1 over distance to Peak focal length that's happening
there, but that's really all that's happening the projection.
And we've done that part.
That part is still happening here.
So we should be okay.
Now, I don't know if we've got everything there, but at least we're
closer now and let me see if I can step into that code again.
I want to take a look at at that code now.
So here's our world camera wrecked.
Computation and that's much better, right?
That's what we would have expected to get.
So now, I think we're in much better shape.
You can see, there are camera.
Rectangle.
Looks like it's much nicer.
Aligned, exactly the way that we would have expected it to be when we
go back to the config.
Turn that back to false and then you know now we're in good shape.
Now we've got those those rectangles exactly where I expect them to be
now.
So now we're much, I'm a much happier camper.
You can see that one bounding the room and then the other one bounding
the camera and they're perfectly tight.
They're right where they should be and that's what I wanted to see.
Okay, so like I said baby steps for our conversion to 3D baby steps
and you know, I should take maybe a second just to mention while we're
doing this.
I never said this at the beginning, but
I should just kind of mention sometimes people get really scared when
they have to change code and like this and you know,
the way that you get to a well working engine and a really good design
and all those sorts of things is to always keep your code very
fungible and maneuverable, like we have done,
And to not be afraid to make changes to it, right?
To always believe that you can work it out that if you think it
through and look at how things are flowing, you can come up with good
changes and break things into baby steps where you can just improve
the code and get it towards.
You need to go those.
It's crucial to not have that fear because it will really hold you
back.
If you're always afraid to go, make serious substantive changes, or if
you think you have to rewrite everything all at once, too.
To do something because a lot of times taking the approach of just
like let me delete everything and rewrite the whole thing while.
Sometimes that is necessary.
A lot of times, keeping the code fungible and making small changes
towards what you need ends up with a much more robust much better
design in the end because it's hard to conceptualize everything in
your head for a giant thing, like a game engine.
And so, what we're kind of doing here for the 3D transform.
It's an important to move the thing from 2D to 3D.
It's very important to understand that these are the kinds of changes.
You want to feel comfortable making.
Don't be scared about them, they are very large, but if you break them
into small pieces, then it's not so scary.
Because each individual thing, you can measure understand test.
See if it worked have an opinion about whether it got better and
unless you literally just can't see any series of steps that will get
you from.
You are to where you need to go.
It's very sound, very reassuring, programming practice, you can go
through.
So even though this is a very significant thing, take an engine that
was supposed to be 2D and making it 3D engine.
Instead.
It's really not that bad.
As long as you just do those steps and you could see like that camera
thing was exactly that.
So, I took a step.
Why isn't this thing working?
Oh, let's go.
See, why?
Okay, right, we need to unprotect mean those two match up.
How do we make those match up?
There we go.
Oh, we notice something that we probably want to improve the the
perspective transform should probably exist.
In a unified place.
So now we've got something you're kind of in our mind of like this is
a way we can improve the code.
That is how these things are supposed to work there, how they get
better and that's how they get better reliably.
Because as long as you're always pushing it forward and doing those
small changes and seeing that they made an improvement, you're in good
shape.
All right.
So now what I'd like to do is focus a little bit more on trying to get
the actual Z stuff work.
The way that we want it to work.
Because right now, we are not using the Z.
So we as a little bit summer, obviously are using it.
We are not.
The Z is not coming through to opengl, right?
This is the Z happening here, and what I'd like to do is get that Z
moved over to opengl.
So that opengl understands and sees
Our Z coordinates again which right now it isn't doing.
We are passing the Z's down.
But we're only passing them down after they've already been projected.
So what I'd like to do now.
Is try to get this down into the opengl code.
Okay.
Now this is a relatively difficult change, not because the math is
going to be complicated, because the math actually isn't going to be
all that complicated.
But rather, because right now, we don't have a concept in in our
rendering system.
Of the transform for Z being set at any real time.
Okay, so when we call opengl set screen space,
You can see it happening right here.
When we call opengl set screen space, we just kind of set it and then
forget it, right?
It's a set and forget kind of situation but we're probably going to
have to do is take our clip rect concept which is the thing where we
sort of have stuff that references a particular product or probably
going to have to do is take that clip.
Rect concept and at augment our cliprect concept to not really be
about clip Rex anymore, but to be about transforms in general.
Because we need some way of telling opengl what the camera transform
is.
And we don't want to tell it with the canned camera.
Transform is for every Sprite, right?
That's just like, we didn't want to tell it with the clip.
Rect was for every Sprite we could have, right?
Every Sprite could have its own clip.
Rect
but since most Sprites tends to go with a single clip, rect
like those big batch of sprite, they're all the same clip, rect we
want to be able to specify that once and not have to change it every
Sprite if the Sprite doesn't change clip Rex and the same is going to
be true for our camera transform.
When we want to set, what that Z perspective, transform is of the
camera.
What we'd like to do is just set that one time and not have to set it.
Every single time we do a Sprite right and you can see why we would
have to do that if we've made know.
Concession to it because what we are doing here is every Sprite.
When we get the Sprite, we're taking the current camera transforms,
focal length, and we're using it to compute with the Z value.
Is if we were to get rid of that and just passed down, Distance 2pz by
itself.
Right without the focal length, then opengl would have no idea which
brights went with which focal lengths.
In a case, where we change the focal lengths, multiple times, in a
single frame, which
we're totally free to do right now.
Right now, the fact that we don't means if we wanted to, I suppose, we
could just hard code a focal length into opengl, but I mean, even then
we sort of at least,
The concept of the orthographic projection versus the not orthographic
projection, because eventually we're going to want to re-enable, our
debug display.
And in order to re-enable, our debug display opengl at least needs to
know the difference between all the stuff that came down in the
perspective and all the stuff that comes down in the orthographic.
So at some point if for no other reason than just because we have a
debug overlay or other, you know, we'll probably have other UI
potentially in the game that might want this as well, so it's not just
for debug.
We at least at least need some way of setting two different camera
transforms and once we can set to camera transforms we might as well
have a way to set an arbitrary number in case we want to do different
things with it.
Right?
Because we have to have that Concept in there at some level.
So that is why we need to do this is we need to get that camera
information down and like I said we sort of already have this in the
clip, rect concept.
So we might as well piggyback on top of that because it's already a
thing that allows us to have our Sprites reference
Thing that gets changed in frequently.
Right, so that's pretty good and there's stuff we can do with that.
Now we'll probably be able to improve this further because once we
really get to the full to the z-buffer, we won't need to have the
concept that Sprites reference a cliprect anymore.
We'll be able to have it so that Sprites just come in batches with the
clip.
Rect at the top which will be much more efficient because then we
don't have to do this check on every Sprite.
And when I say much more efficient I basically mean, hey, you probably
Even really notice it because it's not that big of a deal to compare
two integers together, but you get the idea.
It's more efficient conceptually anyway and we might as well get rid
of code.
That doesn't do anything for us.
So, yeah.
Anyway, so that's what we want to get to.
And so, that's what I'm aiming for here and let's take a look at how
we're going to do that.
So right now you can see that we have this sort of clip wreck stuff
happening.
When we start off, we set our cliprect index to something that's
invalid.
So the first time through we will always set the clip.
Rect what that means is that if I wanted to, I could move opengl set
screen space into here.
So that when I pull out the clip rect and I do the opengl bind frame
buffer, I could put opengl screen space right here if I wanted to,
right?
And in some sense the the bind the mind frame, buffer called me.
I guess I can put it up here.
I don't know if it matters where we put it.
Exactly.
But you know let's say I put it there.
What I should get here is exactly the same thing right?
There should be no difference between those two so we're happy camper.
When we do opengl set screen, space right there.
So what that means is,
Sorry, I'm so stuffy today.
what that means is, if I have opengl set screen space here, I could
have opengl set screen, space do something more complicated now, and
I'm going to want to do that because now it's going to start to become
potentially at certain
Perspective, projection Matrix, right?
So there's other people that use opengl set screen space and you can
see them here.
So for example, this this sausage element here, open Jill, displayed
bitmap.
Right, that's using it.
But what we kind of need to do is bifurcate these two things.
Now, because they're not going to be the same.
So, what we need to do here is kind of move this guy in to this, this
code here.
And furthermore, this this isn't really correct at the moment either,
because we sort of change this from the way it was working before.
Because I think this one previously did the unprojected encode, so
this draw region is probably wrong.
Now, or, you know, this, this opengl rectangle call with the Min P.
Max B is going to be wrong now because it's passing width and height
that isn't getting corrected for right.
So I think what we'd want to do here is passed down.
coordinates that are you know, - 121
Because that's what we're actually passing through.
Right?
I believe, how is this working here?
So that's a negative 1 to 1 is x 2 and a shift up.
Yeah.
So in order to get the correct screen space stuff out of there, if we
expect it to go into,
I'm going to say,
We're entering our second, our have pleasant.
I'm going to say, like, in fact, do we have an ability to do this?
Yeah.
We don't.
but you want to know something we're about to
so yet, one thing that I tend to like to do
This is kind of an amusing code path.
I'll show you how it works.
So if we are in handmade
Internal.
If we're in hand me the internal we can just insert on this if we try
to build a release mode build with it, basically that we would ship to
customers.
It's just an error, right?
Because you can't put that in the
Anywhere.
So, this is basically a little thing that says, hey, you can't ship
any code that has something not implemented that supposed to be
implemented.
So I can put that here and I can say to do this, needs to be worked
out specifically for doing the full screen draw.
And we'll do that in a second because well, we'll do that when we get
back to the software renderer, I guess.
So I'm curious now as well, if I kind of want to think about this
transform a little bit more.
Let's go ahead and grab that out here.
Okay, so if we're in here and we have opengl set screen space.
Now, one of the things that's true is we don't use the modelview
Matrix, you know I'm saying, we only have the projection Matrix there
at the moment.
So for now I'm just going to load an identity Matrix into the model
view up front, right?
Because we're never using that Matrix and I don't need it for anything
now.
I think we're probably going to switch to shaders at some point.
And what you'll see is that when we switch to shaders at that point,
there's no such thing as projection and model view, matrices anymore.
Anyway, these are just things from the fixed function pipeline, that
opengl did for various historical reasons in our actual shaders.
We will just have one Matrix anyway.
So I'm just using the projection Matrix because we only really want
one Matrix for all intents and purposes for doing our
Wouldn't it computations?
And everything should be in this Matrix.
So I'm never going to use the modelview Matrix because when we
transition over, which I think we probably will you don't have two
matrices anyway because if you think about it there's really not a lot
of reason to have two matrices.
The only reason you ever do to transforms is if you have a secondary
space you need to do computation in and so we can look at that we'll
look at that stuff a little bit later.
It's not really
Worth putting it into your brain space right now, but basically yet
that that's why you're not seeing me do anything at the model view is
because generally won't stick with one Matrix for everything for
coordinate computation and if we're going to do a second major,
something else, it would not be so that we could have two stages of
transforming.
It would because we need a secondary space for computation for other
reasons, or something like that.
All right, so anyway, if we look at the projection Matrix here and
We take a look what we're doing.
Here's our aspect ratio.
Correction, like I was saying before, and you know, this to this is I
don't even know why we're still bothering with a safe ratio here.
I mean, really what this is, is just a x to, you know, this is, this
is just, this is just that and so,
Really the only safe ratio part of it is just the with over the height
is the only thing that that was doing and really, we don't even really
need that because I think we should probably just not run.
If the width and height aren't both greater than 0, we should just
turn off the renderer and not run.
That's probably the safer thing to do so that we don't have to worry
about degenerate things happening at that case.
But
For now those are our two actual pieces of transform information that
are happening there.
And again the reason that we're doing that is because we want to put
things into the correct space for opengl.
Now, the only thing that makes me a little bit confused.
Right now is why the two is there because what are we actually passing
down in terms of coordinates here, right?
Like, you know,
Here we go.
So if the center of our screen is at 0 0, right?
And you know, we're talking about
passing down coordinates here.
If we were going to pass down, coordinates that are negative 1 to 1,
you know, -1 to 1 or whatever.
If we're talking about this as our world transform, then, I'm not
really sure why we were multiplying by 2 there because in theory, we
want to divide by 2 right 0.5 to
Ourselves into the right coordinate space, right?
Because we want negative 1 to 1 or or really, we wouldn't have to
multiply by anything.
Right?
If we're, if we were already talking about a coordinate space, it look
like that.
And so I'm not sure why we decided to do that, and I'm going to look
really at docstoc GL, 4gl perspective or glue perfect.
Well,
just to make sure I'm not crazy about that.
That is not a very good.
Nope, that's not what I want.
That is what I want.
No.
I just want somebody to have that Matrix drawn out for me.
That's what I wanted.
Although, it's like they're missing, even, that's not quite right.
Come on, folks.
Just, I just want it laid out as a matrix.
Please, how hard is that?
I can't be that hard.
Can it
I guess it is that hard.
Well.
Let's just pretend I found it or something and ignore it anyway.
So when I'm looking at this, just only reason that I was thinking that
it's like basically these are just dependent on what the coordinates
are that are coming in right.
And because what we do, what we know is that what we want to come out
of here is the negative one to one space, right?
But in terms of what comes in here we have to have an opinion about
what's actually coming in.
Order to yeah, in order to.
Know what those values should be, right.
And so we know like one thing we do know for sure.
Is that GL viewport is going to do the viewport transform at the end
of it so we know exactly what the coordinates need to be there, right?
We know that this is what's happening to our coordinates going in.
So we definitely know that they are negative 1 to 1.
When they come out, that makes sense.
But what we don't know is what we wanted them to be when they come in.
And so the x 2 again is kind of arbitrary in this case, right?
This could just be an identity transform that just corrected for the
aspect ratio.
And it just means things get get a 2X scale on them.
The fact that we
Are the fact that we are, if we were not doing the x 2 here, it would
get it to X scale on the right.
So, in theory, right?
Like I could just get rid of this and it would just change the size if
that makes sense.
Oops.
It would not change the behavior at all.
It was in terms of anything else, it just means that were not getting
that scaling, right?
So, if I come in here and I turn it back to two,
then we get that that scaling, right?
So that's really all that's happening there.
And yeah.
I'm just not sure we care about that, right?
I'm just not sure we care about that at all.
It seems to me like that's just Superfluous and I can't remember it.
I feel like the only reason we had that
When there was because we were previously passing coordinates that
were 02 width.
And 02 height.
Right.
That's what we were passing down.
Then we change to just passing zero to one
On both.
And if we're passing 0 to 1, then you can see why the transform would
need to make it 0 to 2, because it's going to shift it back by
negative 1 in order to center it.
But now we're not doing that anymore right now.
We're just passing straight coordinates and we're not trying to
correct for that.
So the only thing that we actually need to correct for is that safe
ratio, you know what I'm saying?
And so I feel like we don't really need that anymore.
Like I don't think we need that x 2.
I just we would again just adjust the height of the camera and I don't
think there's any other reason for that too.
I could be wrong about that and we're going to have to work out the
projection math in a second here anyway.
So I suppose you know, hold that thought but that's just
What it feels like to me, it feels like that was a Superfluous.
That was left over from something we were trying to do before that we
no longer have to actually do so let's just keep that in mind.
All right.
So let's talk about this again.
I already explained the projection Matrix on a previous episode, so
you're going to want to get familiar with that if you haven't already,
but we never really talked about the Z coordinate of the projection
Matrix and we need to start talking about that now.
So let's go ahead and talk about that.
Okay, so if you take a look at what's happening here, you can see.
We're trying to divide by a z value, and we are trying to multiply by
the focal length, right?
So if I were to phrase this more concisely, that it is phrased at the
moment, it would look like this.
Correct.
So we're trying to take this value that's coming in and we're trying
to multiply it by this coefficient in order to do our projection.
But what you'll notice about this is the Divide, involves a value that
coming in from the point itself.
Because you can see this distance 2pz, actually takes into account
more than just that value, right?
So the distance 2pz here that we compute, we do this distance.
Above Target - 4 Z.
The floor.
Z comes from the object transform, which is /, Sprite right now.
Why am I harping on that as being so important?
Well, the reason I'm harping on that as being so important is, if you
think about what's happening in our Matrix here,
Right?
We are trying to produce a result, right?
A resultant vector and what's in our Matrix here, multiplies by these
things.
All we can do is multiply if we want to include this in a divisor, we
have no way of doing that in a matrix.
Right, there is no way to take something from here and put it in a
numerator.
Sorry, a denominator here, right?
All I have is coefficients.
All I have is the ability to do this in.
Every slot.
Right.
That's all I can produce so I can have an arbitrary fraction here you
know I can have one over the focal length or whatever I want here
because the focal length is a constant that's part of the transform so
it could go in a numerator because I just stick it already pre divided
into my Matrix when I create my Matrix but the Matrix is constant for
a batch of Sprites and this is the thing that varies per Sprite.
And I need to get something that varies for sprite into a denominator
which I can't do.
Right.
So that's where that synthetic divide comes in, right?
That is where we sort of augment this transform.
And remember, that's why I was saying, oh, that's where the
homogeneous coordinates come in, what's defined to happen is after the
transform is done, they'll there will be a value in the W coordinate.
Right whatever the W Prime coordinate is that comes out here, right?
I'm going to have an X Prime y Prime Z Prime, and it w Prime.
What I am going to do is after I do this, not part of the Matrix math.
I'm just going to divide everything by the W Prime
So basically what I'm saying is whatever my w comes out to be I will
always end up normalizing by it.
So the W always comes out to 1.
That's just the rule and all the rest of my coordinates get / it.
However it's going to go right?
And as we learned before a Maffei person helped us before I asked why
we even use the word homogeneous.
You'll see that talked about for this and that is actually because of
that W.
So what the homogeneous actually means is homogeneous refers to space
spaces or number systems where you can represent the same number
multiple ways in terms of scaling, right?
And what you can see is this is a four dimensional vector.
And what we're saying is we don't care what the four dimensional
Vector is that comes
We're going to divide so that the W coordinates always one which means
that there's a whole family of vectors that all mean the same thing,
they have different scalings, right?
So I could multiply everything in here by some scale factor whatever I
want and I'm always no matter what a is.
I'm always talking about the same point because the / the W Prime at
the end if there's a scale in Bear, right?
If
and I guess I wrote that poorly, you know, it's if I have sort of a
and then
That right whatever this a is I'm going to produce the same points
always right because I can just arbitrarily scale this four
dimensional vector by 5 and you know since everything gets multiplied
by five when we actually go through and do the Divide out by the W
Prime that 5 gets canceled, right?
It just goes away because everything was scaled by it.
So that's where the homogeneous comes from.
Is the fact that you can scale these vectors however you want.
Right.
So anyway, that is how I am able to get my Z into the Divide.
You can see the Z has to come into the W component somehow, because
the only thing that's going to end up doing a divided is the W.
So, it's got to go there, right?
So, let's just start thinking about what that actually means.
I'm going to go ahead and erase oops.
Here we go.
Okay, so I'm going to go ahead and start talking about that.
So let's say all I wanted to do was divided by the incoming Z.
That's all I wanted to do.
Well, what would we want our x-coordinate to be?
Well, we just want to divide the x coordinate by Z.
So obviously, we would just not change it, right?
We would just have it be X.
Right?
1 times x 0 times y 0, x 0, x 1.
So it's X.
What would I do for my y?
Same thing, 0 times x 1 x y 0, x e0 x 1.
Write X Y, what would I do for my Z?
Don't even care.
We might as well leave it the same, but we don't care.
Because we're not talking about that yet, right?
And then finally, what do I want for my w-well?
I want to divide everything by Z so actually my w coordinate, which
used to look like that to produce this, right?
Because we just want to one there.
There would be no divide now has to look like this right 0 times 0 0
times x 0 x y.
1 x e0 x w.
Now, what I get when I do my divide right nor that is I get X over Z,
right?
Because the W coordinate is z y over z z over Z and 1.
And there's my divide.
so, I can produce
Any single divide value that I want now because of this extra Row, the
homogeneous part of this Matrix.
The additional coordinates gives me the ability to prepare a divisor
using any combination of the input that I want.
So now, instead of having to be handicapped by the fact that I cannot
do it, right?
I cannot control divides by things that come in the input.
Now, I do have the ability to do so it's just how I produce my w
coordinate.
You see how that works.
So basically we can think of this Matrix, as an arbitrary transform,
that's allows us to produce an x, a y, and a z, and then a divisor, so
that we do have one opportunity to do a global divide across each of
the coordinates computed however we want it.
Which happens to be just enough to produce a perspective transform.
Right?
So now that we have that knowledge, right?
And remember things are reversed here because this our seas are stored
column-major, not row major and we talked about that before.
So remember what that is.
So this Matrix is actually flipped from from math notation
unfortunately.
So what we'd want to do here is if we were going to do it to match our
Matrix it would look like that, right?
That's where we'd put.
That coordinate and if we put that coordinate there right now our
projection Matrix whenever it does, its projection will be taking the
Z coordinate and it will be forcing everything to / it.
Now, what we know is that we don't actually want to divide by just the
Z coordinate, right?
So if we were to say inside are, you know, RP coordinates here.
If you were to take our raw XY,
And we wanted to take the distance to p z is the Z coordinate.
We could bundle that up here like so right.
We'd say we have projected XY, projected, XY raw.
I'm sorry.
Rolex, why?
Row XY.
And then here, we've just got our distance to pz.
So if we were to take that
What we would see is our camera focal length is now no longer in
there.
We're just passing the thing that varies per Sprite and we could get
rid of
This piece of information entirely now our scale unfortunately.
We still don't know, we've slept to produce that by this equation,
right?
So we still have to produce that unfortunately but our p-value we
could pass through as it was right.
So, what's interesting about that is, this is in terms of scale, we're
going to have to unwind how that works because we want all of our
stuff to be passed down correctly.
So we'll have to unwind that.
This is going to be a unamusing two-step process.
But so yeah, I guess our scale values are going to have to just come
out to be one now and basically the scale.
Yeah, well, we'll see in a second.
So I'm going to stuff that for now.
And we're going to get rid of this.
And here we're going to pass them down.
So we're just going to pass down the row XY and where the distance to
pz and the focal length, I guess what we could do is say we'll put the
folk will for now just to get do baby steps.
Again, will actually take the focal like been there since we're not
passing it down yet, right?
So now what we know is to reproduce this, we just want to be able to
do the / these by this value, right?
And so, in order to do the divided by this value,
Like you can see here it's multiplying the row XY.
We're just going to want to flip this, right?
Because we're going to be doing a / it, not a x.
It like we were doing there so it's going to have to be flipped around
and then when we do this here, when the Z coordinate comes in, we will
now actually be able to shove that into the W coordinate which will do
that divided for us.
Right.
And so we're not quitting.
Now we got to talk about the scale but just so you can see what
happens when we run it.
Here you go, right?
Okay.
So not particularly reassuring here as you can see, but, you know, all
of the rectangle, still work correctly.
And if you look at why the rectangles work correctly, it's because
they don't need that scale value, right?
I don't think the rectangles, well, actually, is that true?
The rectangle shouldn't need, the scale value as well.
And setting the scale value to one is probably
I'm gonna have to go step through that to be honest.
I don't remember exactly how we did the scaling.
But yeah, I don't know why that worked.
I would have expected it not to work yet because we haven't really
addressed some of the finer points of that there.
Casey is very confused.
So, hold on.
I'm sorry to interrupt the explanation there of what we were trying to
do but you know, when I get confused, I have to go investigate.
So I can't very well continue an explanation when I'm not, I'm
confused.
So when we do our rectangles, I would have thought that those would
have had to have the scale correct as well because they the rectangles
get Scaled just like everything else gets scaled.
So when we do a push wrecked,
It does the scaling just like everything else right here is it you
know?
Here is getting the basis.
Scale comes back and multiplies it by the dimension and off it goes,
right?
So you know that that rectangle Dimension is the scale.
Jim that comes through.
That's should be no different from the Sprite case.
Which is doing exactly that right here, spit map.
It gets back at dimension.
It's multiplying by the scale of just like before.
Okay, well no, I guess.
No, I really don't see it.
So, in one case, we have the x axis and the y axis getting multiplied
by the size.
In the other case, we just store the dim directly, but I'd really just
don't see why those two things would produce subtly different results
for us.
So you can see here, we've got
The rectangle call it scoring opengl rectangles passing the dimension
that it gets in from the code.
And that's it right?
And in this case we're doing the exact same thing as far as I know,
right.
You can see it here where these are already X that Dimension and you
know they're getting expanded out to it but I just don't understand.
I don't understand why the rectangle case is working because the
rectangle case I would have thought wouldn't have worked any
differently from this one.
From this case, right?
That that just doesn't make any sense to me because
Theory.
The they should have been equivalent.
They're both using the scale value.
That comes back either.
Both of them should have worked or neither of them.
Should have worked, not one worked on the other didn't.
So there's a subtlety here that I'm feeling to appreciate in terms of
What's going on with?
With the bitmaps.
And I really don't know what that is.
So I suppose.
One thing is, if they're getting clipped
Do rectangles not get clipped.
In some way that that bitmaps do you know like are we throwing them
out or something?
In a way because, you know, because of some piece of information.
I don't know that's really bizarre.
So I guess, there's one way we can figure that out relatively quickly,
right?
Whether there's any sort of funny business going on there.
So let me just check what I might do is go pull out all the sort stuff
first and then will, you know, that'll probably take me the rest of
the stream and then so that's all gone.
And then we can just focus on debugging that just the transform part.
Next tomorrow, extreme.
But yeah, that's really weird.
So I want to check to make sure we're actually getting into here and
and getting reasonable values.
I mean those look sane, right?
You know, those those don't look like ridiculous values.
So you know, I don't understand why we wouldn't have something
reasonable here.
Let me let me go ahead and see you next and Y Min x max y, Max
X + y, 0.
That.
That may be the difference.
Let's take a look.
Let's take a look folks.
We may have just lucked out that I happen to see that right now.
So it doesn't take very long to find if this is, in fact the case.
Yes.
Thank you so much for all of that.
Yeah.
Well, there you go.
So the difference is in opengl rectangle, we were actually passing the
Z coordinate and in in bitmap we weren't.
So the reason was not because there is anything different about, the
two cases in the head and it's because in the back end, we never
passed the actual Z.
So, if we just switch to passing the Z, we should be fine actually.
Okay, there we go.
So there we go.
And now one of the nice things about this right?
Is that now we get rid of that scale value as well because now all of
that's happening in the back end transform.
So inside render group.
If we take a look at that render entity basis P maneuvering, that's
going on,
We now can get rid of the scale value entirely and remove it
everywhere that anyone was doing anything with it, right?
Because it's not, it's going to happen as a natural result of what was
that?
What was going on before?
So in terms of like this stuff here where we get the size and that
sort of stuff that's happening here, we don't need to take into
account the the basis anymore.
We only need just the raw size for Stuff.
Wherever we were operating on it.
So again, that that basis, that scale just goes away basis that scale
goes away here.
And so, that's again, another simplification that we can do, right?
And similarly, we should be able to get rid of the valid as well.
And so, what you can see here is now when we get our entity basis, B
result stuff done, really, it's just going to be a V3, right?
We should be able to now just go.
Hey,
let's get rid of that entirely.
and,
It's just a V3.
That's all it is.
Right.
Which is pretty great.
And simplifies a lot of stuff for us.
Oops.
I got a I keep meaning to one of these days.
I got to update my for coder.
I, you know, have I always keep it updated on my dead machine and I
haven't updated it on the street machine.
And I made some changes to my config and I also, you know, updated to
the latest version and stuff.
And so now, some occasionally I have a hotkey that's different or
whatever.
So
And it is very specifically that one.
Alright, almost there.
And we should be good now.
And so now we've gotten rid of just a bunch of stuff here.
Right?
This is getting much better and we still need to pull out all that
sorting code that we don't need anymore.
But let's just keep going down this path a little bit here.
So now we can sort of see like all right in the orthographic case, we
do nothing.
You know, result is just equal to the incoming.
Point shifted by the camera.
Transform, look, that's it, right?
In the other case.
Now we've got a little bit of business that we do here, but it's
getting, it's getting increasingly more and more and more concise,
right?
So we're going to probably get rid of Ortho wife, Rumsey entirely,
Is my suspicion.
So yeah, we are going to have to take a look at some of these and just
Figure out exactly what we want to do here.
But so this stuff should be getting
Should be getting cleaner as we go.
Alright, so we no longer have to do any clipping to the near clipping
plane because the the
Opengl is doing that for us, right?
So we actually can just do this directly.
And this right here is our sort of our orthographic height transform,
which we need to sort of figure out exactly what we want to do with
what we're probably going to have to address that a little bit later
on.
And so, yeah.
We're getting pretty close here.
We don't care about this anymore.
And so really, what you can see is we're getting very close to being
able to just pass the distance pz.
All we really need now is a way of setting this focal length for our
camera transform putting that up into the actual code into the actual
camera code.
And so maybe that's the thing that will do now, right?
We also have that 2x scale that we removed and again I'm not 100%
certain about that.
I feel like we got to take one more.
Really careful.
Look at that to make sure.
What that value should actually be in there.
But assuming that we want to keep this the same, we're going to have
to sort of zoom in.
Not sure how far not that far.
All right.
About that.
Okay?
So again getting closer this needs to be calibrated and we need to
recalibrate the camera stuff anyway.
But you know, we'll leave it like that for now.
So what we need to do
and also bear in mind, our unprotect,
Well, I just write this.
Ah, run project needs to be updated to be in line with with that piece
of code as well.
But anyway, so now when we get down here, what we want to do is take a
look at
how to move that focal length out.
And what we had before right is we've got these clip this concept of
these clip for x.
And the clip Rex are sort of, actually one of the few things that
crosses that boundary like that's actually render structure, that's
understood on both sides of the of the API boundary, right?
The surrender, entry entry clip, rect
Is it something that, you know, we prepare and that that is understood
by both renderers and you can see it here.
That's got a render Target index, and it's got their rectangle and
it's really not a clip rect anymore, but that's sort of what we're
calling it.
It's fortunately,
just what we're stuck with, in terms of the name, we can rename it
later if we want to do a global renamed.
So all I really want to do now is add in here, what we need in terms
of camera control.
So if I was just to say, let's put the focal length in here, right?
Then what you can see is it's lined up correctly.
So that inside the opengl code, when we actually need to get that
focal length, what we can do
Because we can stick that focal length in here.
When you take a look at what's happening inside render group, you can
see that right now, we would be passing the Z, but we need to divide
it by the focal length first.
So, what we could do in here is say, well, this is just going to be 1
over the focal length and we'll get that focal length from the clip.
Rect right because we have that piece of information.
With us and that would reproduce the same transform that we're doing,
because it would provide that one over when we multiply the Z, right,
because distance 2pz would now be the thing that stuffed into the Z
coordinate and then when it gets multiplied by this coordinate to put
it into the W, which is what's going to divide, will end up with
distance to pz / the focal length which is the same term that we had
originally which is what we're trying to reproduce, right?
That's what
we want to divide by.
Okay, so given that, that is what we want to divide by.
what we need to do now is figure out how to set this focal length and
so what happens is when we do our clip, rect
And we call Push cliprect what we want to do when we call Push clip.
Rect is we want to every time we do a push cliprect, we want to pass
that focal length in addition.
Right.
So here's our focal length, getting set here.
Like so and then just whenever somebody pushes one of these to push
the clip, rect what we can do for now is just take a look at the
camera transform and get the focal length out of it directly, right?
Because we have it so we can just do that if that's what we want to
do, right?
We don't set the camera transform here at all.
Do we?
All right.
And so when we call Push left bacteria and we're calling this for,
okay?
So this is pushing the clip Rex for the various floors for the alpha
clip rect.
So in this case, we just need again the camera transform.
so, whatever the render group goes in this case,
Past the focal length, right?
So what we need to do now is we just need to respect the fact that
hey, if we want to do that, the problem is when we do a, the first
push cliprect on the begin render group here, we don't actually have
the focal length that we actually need for that initial cliprect,
right?
We don't know what it actually is.
And so, in some sense, now, when we're doing sort of this set camera,
transform set, camera transform and begin render, group are kind of
now, like, they need to be
Sort of smush together, right?
Because when we do
Begin render group.
In this case, we have two.
Yeah, we have to have that information already available, if that
makes sense.
What's really interesting here is.
You can also see that we keep the screen area out here.
So I guess I really didn't even need this because that was in the
render group so that was really kind of redundant.
I didn't really notice that when we first did it.
So yeah, we should probably take care of that as well.
And this sort of set camera transform is kind of a thing that yeah.
Yeah, we can, we can condense this down quite a bit.
So if you take a look at what happens here, if we do render group,
what what I'm going to do is just push a new clip rect on.
I'm past that focal length.
Like so.
Okay.
And I think there's some interesting things that we'd be able to do
here.
What does it want from our 32 to you 32 for the pixel width?
So I guess we can just use render group screen area or whoops.
These are all YouTube.
See you soon?
Yeah.
All right, so we can clean this up fairly fairly considerably here, so
you can see that.
Now, we're getting the exact same results.
We are getting 2 for, which is nice.
But now we're actually doing that divide with, you know, with the
focal length.
We're actually doing that in opengl, right?
So now the focal length is actually coming through here and getting
set with the camera transform.
Now, it looks like we've got a whole bunch of stuff that can collapse
out here, so we might, as well just do that and make this a lot
cleaner since we know the screen area.
Sure, that means the camera.
Transform itself can be limited to not actually have that information
and I think we're going to see a lot of stuff starts to come together
here.
So if we want to we can just say OK, the camera transform.
No longer needs that screen dim anymore, right?
That's just not on the table anymore because we can just get that out
of the group.
Right.
And that produces what we what we need to produce.
It looks like that's actually a rectangle.
I don't know why that's a rectangle instead of just a dimension
because we are never really doing anything else with it.
See here screen area, it's always produced as a 002.
So with height, that's the only thing we ever do with it.
So I feel like we can just treat that as a regular screen area and be
done with it, right?
I feel like we could just do this and and that's it.
So that just becomes the screen dim.
And everywhere we went.
Getting that out of the camera, transform before we just get it out of
the render group now, right?
Like so.
And same thing here.
So what's interesting about this if we take a look at it, the screen
dim pixel with pixel height stuff is only.
Yeah it's just not being used there so it's really only used for this
call.
Now to get to redo the cliprect.
But I think we're all good.
Still.
Yes we are.
So again, just simplifying that further and then the next question is,
what can we take that to, in even, you know, can we continue to push
that down?
And just say well, alright, so the
Berkeley the focal length, the orthographic.
Can those just beyond the clip?
Rect now since the clip, rect is just going to basically be our
camera, transform?
Right?
And the answer there is, well, we need some information about those so
we can't keep doing this thing where we just, when we do current
cliprect index, where we're sort of we can't keep doing the thing.
We were doing where we don't, remember the cliprect itself.
So in here we're going to have to store a cliprect where we when we
push it on.
Here's our first flipper call.
We're going to need to store that current cliprect as an actual
accessible value.
So every time we do the current cliprect index bit, right?
So current cliprect index when we do the push wrecked on these two
guys, right?
Which looks like the only time that's actually set.
Need to actually record the value.
When we do push clip rect, I'm not sure.
So what we're probably going to have to do is take a look at who's
actually using these values and have a thing where that because I
guess people switch between them, right?
We're kind of going to need an ocean of which one you're talking about
at any given time, right?
And the current cliprect index part itself.
I think we're in order for the way we want to use these.
We're just going to have to clean this up a little bit, right?
Because we need to get that information out of the clip.
Rect and right now we can't really and people can set that arbitrarily
and may want to ask questions about it, right?
So we can do it this way and this will work okay for a second.
But we're going to have to do it a little bit more intelligently here
in a second because we don't have the information.
That we need at our disposal, right?
All right, so let's take a look here.
How do I want to go about making this change?
Because this change is actually a Little Bit Sassy in my opinion.
So I guess one way to make this change is let's just double.
Let's just over do it, if that makes sense.
So, we've got the camera P here and we're setting it in the camera
transform.
And basically, what I want to do is I want to get rid of these two.
I pretty much want to get rid of the camera.
Transform, right.
And I want to just have cliprect and then we'll probably renamed
cliprect like to be camera transform, right?
So that we just have one Central structure that encompasses everything
we need for that projection.
And then when that way, when we do forward or backward, Direction were
always talking about one thing, and it's Consolidated in a nice place.
I only have 10 minutes left though, so I don't want to try and make
the whole change once.
In fact, maybe I should just go to the Q&A now and we'll do that
tomorrow.
That will be tomorrow's job.
And we'll just leave it.
Like it is at the moment that may be a good idea.
Yeah, that may be a good idea.
I could go, although I have to admit, I might as well, you know, what
I might do is let me go pull out some of the sort Keys stuff.
Let's just see what we can do in that regard, right?
So I'm just curious here.
What could I do in that in that along those lines?
Like, what could I do if I wanted to get rid of sort of the push
buffer sort stuff?
So, what I want to do here is kind of get rid of some of this
vestigial remains where we're doing the the sword entries, and those
sorts of things.
So what if I just sort of, got rid of those entirely and trying to
move us back to where we were before.
So we just have a
Our group entry header, and we actually are just pushing those in,
right?
In place and I want those to go up like they used to well, oh no,
those still do go up.
So that's fine.
Because these were the ones that are pushed on the end.
So what I'm going to do is, I'm just going to say, alright, suppose I
get rid of the sorts right bound stuff entirely.
So it just doesn't get pushed on anymore at.
All right?
So it's going to get rid of that, we don't push that on anymore.
Now what should probably happen is, I won't see anything on the screen
at that point because well, that's interesting.
So somebody's still thought they were pushing something on.
I guess.
I'm not sure why.
Oh, because
I do.
When I do that push buffer, I do push a sword entry count.
So what I got to do is I got to get rid of that sort of 3 count,
right?
Because we don't want that anymore.
We don't want the sorts right bound stuff anymore.
Right?
So this stuff is is no good.
So, we're just talking about this.
So the only thing we need to do and yeah, and that's it.
So we get rid of push, buffer data at we put the header there, sort
bounds, sort into account that stuff goes away, right?
So, that's how we're pushing stuff at the moment.
There we go, but now we should see nothing.
I would think.
And the reason that we should see nothing is because we're not
actually pushing on any of the sort entries and I push render
elements.
Kill is looks like people are looking for these Sprite bound.
So let me go ahead and really just get rid of them.
So we can clip out all the code that was referencing them at all.
So this means in our object transform, you know, or rather, let's see
in our stuff that talks about Sprite bounds.
We would just get rid of all of this stuff, right?
It's all gone.
None of this, it's all just, you know, it was fun for a while.
You know we did we did what we had to do, but it's gone now.
And, and goodbye, right?
Alright, so we're get rid of all these guys and we get rid of oops.
Get rid of sort barrier.
Although actually, I suppose, let me just leave the call to sort
barrier here for now.
Just because we may want to still use that even though we're not
sorting, we may still want to Clump things together occasionally.
So, you know, I won't remove that too early.
All right, so here's our push render element call.
We get rid of the sort key on there.
The aggregated, Sorting is gone.
And let's see here.
So get Bound for that.
Looks like it's all not necessary now.
And the screen area is not necessary either.
Five minute warning.
All right, let's
Here.
Not enough actual parameters for macro push render element push
element.
That is because it's still taking these things, which we don't want it
to.
And let's take a look good.
Some of these other ones.
Those go away.
We no longer need to call them.
Where is that?
At Sprite bounce, Wing area.
Not necessary.
Oops.
We'll get rid of the Aggregates work key.
We will have to do some work with those in the future.
So it's not like we get that entirely for free, but
And then so the draw bounds, we don't have that anymore, right?
Because we won't be having any of those sort Keys anymore.
So those are all gone and the show sort groups is gone as well.
And then we just have to get rid of the all the Sorting code because
the Sorting code can no longer operate.
So, build Sprite graph is gone.
Unsorted output is gone.
Recursive front-to-back is gone sword.
Entries also gone.
Linearized, clip Rex still definitely exists.
So you know prep for render is still going to have to do that
operation, but that's about it.
And then, I think we're back to normal except again now.
We should not see anything, right?
Oh, and I forgot to eliminate that guy.
It's an unnecessary exertion.
Oops.
Under element.
So here, when we get that push sword, entry, where was that sort entry
being scared is so push buffer.
Results is just going to be the render group entry.
Header is the only thing that will come back now and we could probably
get rid of this struct as well.
If we wanted to,
And when we do this push here let me get the invalid code path.
I guess, you know, I'm not
We could probably just not draw the Sprite.
So I'm not sure why that's a hard fail.
There seems a little odd, but whatever, we'll cross that bridge when
we come to it.
So yeah, so here we go.
Let's see our sorted index count.
I'm not sure why this I guess the sort of the next town is not getting
initialized because we don't really even want that anymore.
So let's go ahead and clip that out.
Sorted index count,
That in the platform code, probably.
So, when we do the game render prep this code goes away, right?
It's just the clip Rex.
Now,
And so this Loop is now what has to really be updated so that we
correctly pull out sort of the header values instead of what we are
pulling out now which is you know, not that.
So really this code is going to be a
I guess just a Max sighs.
Really because these things that were pushing on are variably sized
and we're advancing by a variable size each time.
And so since we're advancing by a variable size each time, really, I
think what we want to do is say like, okay, we've got the header
offset that's going to be starting with zero.
The header offset has to be less than the like render buffer size kind
of a thing, and then we don't actually do any of that.
Instead, what we do is in any one of our cases, when we see something,
we need to advance by the correct amount, right?
However, big the thing is that we're actually looking at.
So we have the header and we want Advanced by the header size, but
then we also need to advance by whatever the sizes of the data, right?
I'm not going to do that this time around, right?
I think I'm just going to do if zero here for now.
And that's what we'll do tomorrow.
And I think that's about it.
So let's see in our software renderer as well.
We've got one of these loops.
Here it is.
So we're going to have to do the same thing here as well, right?
And there's the header offset.
And so now we just have an on Loop, right?
It's not going to do anything and we can leave that like that for
tomorrow.
And so all we have to do is just restore that Loop and then the
Sorting code is gone which is nice because that way we don't have any
of that nastiness.
So let's go ahead and go to the Q&A.
Wow, no questions.
Well, we can go home early, I guess.
all right, well, if there's no questions, then I will just tenderly
and that will be that
Quarter Tron, can you please go double-check your Matrix math in your
last drawing and Milton sure.
Okay, what is the Matrix math?
You want to be able to check.
Okay.
So you just want me to redo this multiply I guess so x times I mean I
can do it all the way out.
Let's hang out with me.
Get rid of this here.
All right.
So, we're multiplying Vector times Matrix.
are so we have 1x + 0 y plus 0 Z Plus 0 times 1, we have zero X, Plus
1, y, plus 0, Z Plus 0 times 0, oops, sorry 0, x 1, here we have 0 x +
0, y plus 1, Z Plus 0 times 1 here and we've got
0x + 0, y plus 1, Z Plus 0 times 1 here.
So you know simplifying these out, you you just get X because all of
these go away, y, z and z.
So x y, z z which is what I wrote, right?
So that
More scroll.
Right?
Ish.
Okay.
This.
So this is x / w y / wz /, W and w.
Right.
Okay.
Okay, quarters, right?
Well, you know, it never hurts to double-check, right?
I mean, you know, math is
And and I'm Rusty at math, you know, I don't do as much math as I used
to and I was never particularly good at it.
So,
You know, double-checking math is so he's rarely.
Is it a bad idea to double?
Check your math?
I guess is what I would say.
Um let's see.
Okay.
Are you planning on making a video featuring everything you made?
You mean like a summary video?
I mean eventually like when we're all done, we'd probably do something
like that.
Right.
But you know that's going to be a while.
We got to finish the 3D stuff and then we have to implement a bunch of
game code so that you have something to play, you know, with with an
objective and loot and things like that, that go into these game.
Things that people game.
So, you know, will will be be do a summary video at the end?
Pepe Val.
What do you have in mind when it comes to shaders?
Do plan to use them to sort?
No, I don't really have any plan for shaders at all.
Other than just than the fact that
I think we would probably have to switch to them for.
For lighting.
Like we're going to want a little bit of lighting stuff in there and,
you know, a couple things like that and we, you know, we don't need
anything complicated but shaders are really.
The only reasonable way once you are drawing on the GPU to really get
a lot of that stuff.
So you know the Z buffer will take care of our sorting for us.
Mostly will have to do a little bit of stuff to in there.
That's, you know, in a Shader, we might have to offset the depth
value.
So because we want to do stuff like
Have artificial, like, overlap changes, based on, you know what,
supposed to be on top of what and, you know, who knows what else.
So there might be a little bit of stuff like that, but, you know, that
the shaders by and large will not do much, you know, it's just even, I
guess I'm trying to say is even just basic simple things.
Like basic lighting calculations.
You might want to do,
Once everything is rendered on the GPU, assuming you want to do those
light calculations per pixel, you have no choice but to do them in the
GPU.
Anyway, so even if you don't care about the speed, just doing, if you
just want per-pixel lighting, you have to write a Shader.
That's the only way you can put it your own even very simplistic code
in for doing some light calculations.
And the only way you can do any lighting calculations in the fixed
function pipeline is using this ridiculous.
Slight system.
That's really bad and was baked into the original opengl thing for
back.
When Hardware could hardly do anything compared to what it can do now.
So you know, do we really need shaders for anything?
Not really but you know, this small expense of
Querying it and uploading a Shader is usually worth it just to get the
Simplicity of being able to write our own little lighting equation in
there.
You know, when we when we need that that's all
Let's see.
Je KSG, how long till ship?
I don't have any particular plan first ship.
Like I said, this game is a teaching project so it doesn't have to be
released at any particular time.
So it'll shift when we have implemented.
All the things that I think are interesting and useful for us to
implement in the context of the game.
And, you know, we've done a nominal job on having enough game there as
Also that, you know, it's a play, a nice, playable experience that
people would enjoy, but that's it, you know.
So so I don't have a ship date in mind.
Rome.
I'm running out of excuses to clean the garage, so someone asked
something long.
Okay, so I'm basically here for to allow you to procrastinate from
cleaning your garage.
I see, I see how it is.
Orgasm around.
Could you expand on the topic of refactoring, sometimes all the code?
I use get to move to move on but keep my old code.
So I think I'm scared of changing things.
Yeah, like I sort of alluded to there when I had that brief kind of
interlude and said that you can't be afraid to change things.
I guess what I would say is that it's difficult.
It's difficult to get to the point in programming where you are
comfortable programming.
What I would consider a professional level which is a bit of a
misnomer because there's plenty of professional programmers, who can't
do this.
Professional just means you get paid for it, I guess but getting to
the point where I think you know you're a good programmer you go you
typically go through a couple sort of phases and what's interesting
about it is like you kind of return back to where you came from.
But just much better than before, when you start out programming,
you're not afraid.
Usually, because you just don't know anything, right?
Like you're just typing code in and you're just happy to see it work
and you haven't been inculcated with any, you know, nonsense about
what's clean code or stuff like this.
And you also don't have any experiences where you've gotten burned by
something.
So, you know, you're in this sort of Fairly innocent place as a
programmer where you just can do whatever you want.
And you're not afraid because
Cuz you don't have anything.
Afraid of the only thing you might be afraid of is that you can't
figure out how to make the thing you're trying to make, right?
Your may be afraid of your incompetence if you will right.
But you're not afraid because you think something is wrong?
Or something's going to happen?
You're just afraid.
Maybe at most you'd be afraid because you just don't know how to do
what you want to do at all, right?
But you're not afraid of making changes because you don't have any
reason to fear those changes, you haven't, right?
And then as you learn more, you actually, I think become more afraid.
Because now you've gotten burned in situations, you've made code that
then was brittle and you couldn't change it.
And it was all a disaster and it was too slow or who knows what
happened, right?
Or you've heard a bunch of lectures with people getting up saying, all
these things about what's good code and what's bad code and oh you
didn't have a overloaded equals operator in your private section of
your class and you're a bad person and all this other stuff.
Right and your heads all mixed up about stuff like that because you
don't really know what to believe and you don't have enough experience
yet to really get to the point where you're certain about what's right
and what's wrong in terms of your programming practices.
So you're kind of mixed up and it becomes fairly fearful and I think
an important part of getting to be a good programmer is getting past
that stage to the point where you're comfortable, letting design
emerge and letting good code emerge through series of refinements,
right?
And and respecting the fact that good code is code, that works.
Well is easy to change, doesn't have a lot of bugs in it.
That's what's good code, not some arbitrary set of things you're
afraid about doing or not doing right.
And getting that point is difficult, right?
Because it requires enough experience with programming to be
comfortable with programming, the act and being confident that.
You can spend time to work on code, relax.
Know that you're going to take a week or two to do something that
you're going to, you know, how to break it down, you're not scared
about what's going to happen when you start down a path because, you
know, either the path will materialize or it won't.
And you'll be able to tell that it's not and back back up, right?
And getting to that point is difficult.
I don't think there's a Magic Bullet, that's just part of being good
at your job by having done it.
And by also, in some
It's rejecting the Notions that there's, there's these golden rules to
programming that are about specific code.
Because really, as far as I'm concerned, that's not true.
The only golden rules to programming are focusing on those results,
right?
Golden rules to programs are about how you go about your mental Act of
programming.
Not about what the code actually looks like because
Not only does what the code looks like.
What's the right code?
I think vary from programmer to programmer because different
programmers work in different ways.
But also I think it's the case that any rule you might come up with.
There are probably very good cases for breaking that rule.
Right?
You know if the rule is about specific things in your code, you know?
And so I think it is difficult.
Doing large design work, and large systems, work is difficult.
And operating on the level, we operate on handmade hero is difficult,
right?
Knowing keeping this whole arches.
You think about how much fungibility there's been, how many changes
you made in Hammer, how many systems are interacting, and how we kept
that all under control.
And we've never really had a problem, keeping our game running and
going through these changes yet, that's hard, right?
And it you know, since I've done so much programming in my lifetime, I
am able to keep that.
Anything under control.
It's not a given that you can do that.
When you first starting out, you know I wouldn't have been able to do
that maybe in my first couple of years of programming, right?
Because I just wouldn't have had the experience to make sure that I
had the good sense to not go down really bad path and not put the code
in really brittle positions, right?
So that's just about gaining experience and unfortunately, I really
don't think there's anything.
Anyone can tell you up front that makes you suddenly get there.
But you can but the the good thing to tell you and to internalize is
just that you can get there and that getting there is about trusting
the outcome of the code and believing what you see, when you work,
right, seeing how code works and seeing what produces good results for
you and believing in that.
Is much more important than watching a bunch of experts.
Tell you something about what the right code looks like because that's
just not so useful at the end of the day, right?
Those things are really not what to focus on, right?
And you'll notice I try not to do that very often on handmade arrow in
general, right?
I very rarely try to say when you write this piece of code, it should
look exactly like this because that's just not really interesting.
And you will come up with those as you become a better programmer.
You will come up with your own hard and fast rules for certain things
that you find are always good for you and that may be true but it
won't necessarily be true for other programmers because those rules
are usually about compensating for some shortcoming you have.
That makes it so you don't make mistakes and I do those for me.
Like all of my hard-and-fast rules that I have are about making sure
that I
Have bugs in ways that I myself often accidentally make those bugs.
Right?
And so, another person another programmers brain isn't going to have
the same propensity for the same bugs.
They're going to have a propensity for different kinds of bugs.
So the sorts of things that they do that are hard and fast rules for
them are about compensating for their shortcomings, right?
And so if I tell them these rules about how to compensate,
Wait, for my shortcomings.
It may just be wasting their time because all they're doing now is
guarding against bugs that I wish make, but they may never make those
bugs, right?
And same thing with the design.
If there's certain aspects of design that always kind of are
problematic for you.
And so you make these rules about design that keep you out of those
traps great.
But that those may not be the traps that I would fall into.
So I don't need to obey those design rules, right?
And so I think that's sort of the problem.
You know, at the end of the day it's all just machine code.
And any machine code that executes and produces the right result in a
reasonable amount of time is good code end of story and what the
source
Looked like and pretending that somehow you can look at that and
assign some objective measure to whether that code was good or bad, I
just don't believe that because I fully believe that who the
programmers are that need to work on that code.
Largely determines what that code needs to look like to be good,
right?
Because what it means to be good code for them.
maybe very different than what it means to be good code for another
team because the things that they do and how they work,
The code is amenable to it or it isn't.
And, you know, somebody who writes a book that says, this is what good
code is.
It's just simply not true.
If you then take that same stuff, that supposedly, good code and give
it to programmers who program in a very different way.
All of a sudden, all of the things that code was assuming that it
needed to guard against for bugs and that it assumed it needed to be
flexible and modifiable by these programmers is not not not true
anymore.
Because these programs over here, they program in a different way.
They have a different methodology, they make different kinds of
mistakes more frequently and different kind of stakes less frequently
than this other team.
And so I think that's very important to understand.
And it's a very important part of becoming a good programmer is
understanding that and understanding that, that's what makes good code
is.
Contextual not absolute.
If that makes sense, the only absolute metrics of good code is, did it
perform correctly when executed, you know, didn't have a bug and was
it efficient?
Those are the only objective metrics we
For good code.
And so, all the other things that I have nothing, they don't have
effect on that, like, const or
Putting things in the private section of a class.
These things have no effect in the vast majority of cases on those
objective metrics.
So,
They are about whether the programmers on the team.
Need these things to be efficient and work.
Well, not about whether the code is in an objective sense.
Good, because they don't affect the objective measures of the code.
All right, let me take one more question here.
Let's make sure it's a hard-hitting question with a lot of content to
it.
Well actually, here's one that I'll answer look at the I keep missing
the free stream so it what time tomorrow will it start?
Basically the schedule is pretty much, always right?
So if you go to here and click on schedule bot,
This tells you pretty clearly the pre stream generally starts at the
broadcast time.
Sometimes it'll start 15 minutes early but the most it'll ever start
is 15 minutes early.
I and usually it starts right around the time.
It's supposed to start.
So you know if it says 10 a.m.
the pre stream starts at 10, a.m.
sometimes it'll start at 9:45 but that's the very earliest.
It will start.
And if your file, if you follow me on Twitch.
So I mean, if you follow handmade Hero on Twitch, it sends you an
email in theory when I go live as well.
So it's supposed to be
Okay, so
let's take a really important question.
Are how often do you clean your garage?
If you don't have a garage where do you park your car, if you don't
have a car, how do you get to Kansas?
And the answer there is, I do not have a car.
If I did have a car, I would not have to clean the garage anyway
because I live in an apartment building which has a shared garage,
which is cleaned by the maintenance people for the building.
And it's like this giant industrial garage, right?
So it's not like I can't store anything in it.
Either.
You notice anything a clean the garage?
You've got all this like you know, my rake and my trash barrel on my
lawn mower or whatever.
I you're not allowed to store, your own personal junk in the
building's garage anyway, so there's not much cleaning.
The only thing they ever do is the maintenance staff power washes, it
down at some point.
To get like the dirt and that's once every couple of months or a year
or something like that.
Anyway, so almost, nobody really cleans the garage.
In really the same sense.
Anyway without a car how I would get to Kansas as I would fly but that
is how I would get to Kansas.
Even if I didn't have a car I mean if I did have a car because it's a
really long drive to Kansas.
I feel like you know if you were going to go to Kansas from here via a
car
Guess, I don't know.
We're in Kansas, what city were talking about but there's the there's
the driving I guess.
And you would be driving for an entire day with no sleep.
So probably two days if we're realistic to get there.
So I feel like I would not, I would not do that, I do obviously know
that sometimes the fastest way to get to Kansas is to click your heels
together.
If you have red ruby slippers, I don't have red ruby slippers.
So returning to Kansas.
Via magic is not, you know, an option that I have available to me,
but, you know, I obviously would encourage people who do have magic
slippers to use that because it is cheaper than airfare.
And you know,
And popcorn of X 90.
Yes, John and Casey are in the same city for the moment.
John though, is not in Seattle full-time.
He's up here.
Only part of the time.
So whether or not we're in the same city is kind of depends, I guess
is what I'd say depends on the month.
For the week.
Alrighty, then.
It's close it down.
Thank you everyone for joining me for another sort of handmade here.
It's been a pleasure coding with you.
As always, I am pleased to see the code getting simplified now that we
are working on the 3D transition.
I feel like that really kind of keeps things a little bit more under
control now that we're sort of unifying that pipeline, so that's
making me happy.
That's why I want to do it.
And it looks like it is going exactly the way I'd hoped.
So that's good.
And getting rid of that Nexus of sprite sorting makes me happy too.
Because I just,
Didn't have a lot of confidence in it.
I didn't like it.
It was too much code executing in a two crucial part of the pipeline
in a place.
That doesn't scale well because it's where you push Sprites through.
And I really just didn't like that and then make me comfortable.
So, I'm happy.
See that we're moving away for that.
And I think it's yeah I'm much much happier about that and I think
there's going to be a lot of really good things to come out of that.
We will continue down that path tomorrow.
We'll get rid of the Sorting code and we'll sort of start to solidify
that cliprect stuff in a sort of more efficient way as well.
You'll see how will do that.
I think there's some pretty good ways we can make that happen and
start to clean things up more.
So that's that, I hope you'll join me for that.
That's tomorrow.
10 a.m.
same time, same place.
That's Pacific Standard time.
For those of you in other time zones, that's about it for today.
Yeah, if you would like to follow along at home, of course, at
handmade hero dot-org, you can pre-order the game and it comes to the
source code.
So if you want to follow along at home, you can do that.
We also have the Forum site.
You can go to ask questions a patreon page.
If you want to support the video series, we've got a schedule bot.
You can go to if you want to know when we're going to be.
And a fantastic episode guide maintained by mid low, you may have seen
him on the chat and yeah, if you're trying to catch up on old stuff,
that's a great place to go.
There's also a great search engine that SF Gartner made.
I don't actually know when that's going to be.
Do we do we know, does anyone May blow do you know when that really
nice?
Episode guide search feature is going to be sort of fully rolled out.
I'm assuming I mean, is that going to get rolled into the episode
guide at some point proper?
Because it's pretty amazing.
It's really, really good.
And it leverages all those annotations that you made.
In a, in a really great way and I just don't know when that's getting
when that what the plan is for that, I can show you where it is here.
It's
Oops.
Missed an IO.
That's what I meant to type.
So yeah, I don't know what the plan is for this or what's going on
with it.
But if you take a look here, you know, mid load, does these, fantastic
anime annotations here in the episode guide but you can't really use
them as effectively if you don't know what day you're looking at.
If you do know what they are looking at, you know, you can go here and
it's a pretty efficient, right?
You've got all the things here and you can jump to any one, but if you
don't really know what you're looking for, becomes difficult,
Halt.
But with this thing, it's pretty cool.
You can just type in what you're looking for and you can see all of my
blows and annotations that match.
What you've typed in?
And so when you come in here, you can jump to one of them and then
it'll show you right in line with the video actually.
And as the video plays, it actually shows you how far it is through
that thing as well.
And you can actually jump to specific times.
It's a pretty great feature, and the UI is designed really well too.
So yeah, us off did an amazing job on that and I don't know when
that's coming, you can access it early here by going to that URL.
Let me see what Midler has to say, on the chat.
Says yeah we will roll it into the new annotation system planning on
working on the new system.
Probably two months from now after handmade Network, version one is
settled.
Yes.
Oh, so that's pretty great.
That's so that'll be kind of moving into antigen system, I guess over
time.
It sounds pretty amazing.
So I would recommend checking that out.
If you haven't yet, eventually, it'll just be rolled into this button
where we're that goes.
It'll have it, but it's pretty great.
Oh, hey, and he is on the chat too.
So thank you very much for building that, that's pretty great.
And yeah.
All right.
Anyway, I'll be back here tomorrow for some more of the three
decoding.
Hope to see everyone here for that until then have fun programming
yourselves.
And I will see you on the internet.
Take it easy, everybody.