Hello everyone and welcome to handmade hero.
The show Rico to complete game live on stream.
We are back after taking a break, we took a break post handmade Khan
and we did a couple streams.
During that time, we did some streams on people, switching careers,
from whatever their current career was to a career in software
development and we had a bunch of really cool stories people wrote in,
so we read those so definitely check that out.
If you haven't seen that already, it's kind of an interesting side
side that side project but I guess
Side stream to handmade hear, a sort of like additional information,
and I kind of shouldn't doing some stuff like that just in general as
because one of the things that I talked about in those streams
specifically was just the fact that a lot of times on how many here I
get asked questions that I don't know the answers to not technical
questions, but like personal questions.
Like, you know what, you know, what would you recommend if I'm trying
to switch careers to?
To software development, or what should I learn?
If I'm going to start doing game development and these sorts of
things?
And a lot of times it's like, well, you know, I haven't written a
surly been through the kind of circumstances that other people have.
You know, I started programming a very early age so I don't know what
it's like to come at it later on in life and decide.
You want to make a switch to it, those sorts of things.
So I find it really helped doing this.
This pastor is a streams, I found it really helped to just like ask
people.
You know, because there's a lot of people out there who now follow the
show, which is awesome.
And they're willing to tell us their stories about what happened to
them when they did go through those those different paths in life
towards getting to being a software developer as their primary career.
And so I'm kind of interested in doing some more of those, you know,
just further down the line whenever we take a break or whatever maybe
in in the interim during those breaks or whatever just asking people
People to write in and seeing if we do get any time we get a good
collection of story, it's just kind of doing a thing where we read
them because I think it's pretty handy and it just kind of gives a
broader perspective on things than I can give by myself.
Because I don't really have any experiences to draw upon other than my
own, which are, I think actually relatively unusual, right?
Like, I'd, I don't know that there's that many people who started
programming as early as I did.
And who really haven't explored any other career options.
It's not necessarily the common
For software development.
So it doesn't necessarily provide a lot of utility to people who are
coming at it later than that you know.
Even if it's something as late as doing it in high school, it's still
pretty early by most standards but was much later than I ever consider
getting into it.
So I really just don't have much knowledge of that, you know.
I don't really have the the personal experience to draw from to sort
of say, like, all this is what it was like.
This is what was hard.
It was easy, because what's hard to a seven-year-old is very different
than what's hard to a 15 year-old potentially, which is much different
perhaps than what's different for a 30 year old, right?
Because their life circumstances have changed quite a bit and their
existing knowledge base and what they've already sort of grown to do,
habitually in life and these sorts of things change, very dramatically
over those, you know, sort of parts of your life.
So anyway,
I'd like to get back to programming.
Now, we're here at a 352 and I believe hopefully our to-do list is
still pretty good guide in terms of what we want to do.
And I believe we're just sort of tying things up.
We really don't have much to do in terms of game engine stuff anymore.
Like, I feel like we've taken a reasonable amount of time to go
through.
Just sort of demonstrate how to look at a game engine, all the
different parts of it and we've sort of done everything that you might
think you might want to have in a game engine in terms of like at
least one example of how that thing might be done.
And so we were just looking at finishing up this multiple SIM Regents
per frame stuff and the multiple SIM regions per frame.
Stuff is just a way of us trying to figure out.
Can we leverage multiple processors in the machine to simulate?
Different places in the game separately, right?
And there's a couple different things that was important for us to
sort of figure out how to do there and we're sort of working through
those.
So just continuing down that path a little bit just to do some stuff
like clean up the camera usage and that sort of thing on the other
hand
After that, I think.
And it's still a guess a little bit of a question, but I'm pretty sure
that I would like to do it.
I might want to rewrite one thing that we've done, which is that we
did our renderer in 2D and I'm kind of glad we did that, because I've
never done really a 2d renderer before for the most part.
Like, it's just not something that I have experience with.
I've always really done 3D even, you know, very early on in my sort of
programming.
I think even as early as you know when
A little before like maybe Junior High School.
I think was probably the last time I ever really did much in the way
of 2D engine work to be honest.
And so you know I had never really done a 2d engine and so I just
don't love it.
Like I feel like there's just too much in it that sort of not flowing
through a nice uniform pipeline.
There's just too many special cases for things that I don't really
like it.
so I think I would prefer to sort of upgrade our Graphics to sort of
3D now that doesn't really mean we're going to pull in any 3D assets
but I'm basically just
About hey instead of rendering tiles.
Maybe I'll render like little cubes you know more like a Minecraft
sort of style where the the textures are on the sides of the of the
cubes or on the front of the cubes or whatever.
So when you have like raised pieces it's actually like a little 3D
thing and then the actual characters are actual Z buffered stand up,
you know cards.
And the reason I want to do that is just because although the z-buffer
is something that you, you know, you don't necessarily want to use if
you can avoid it because obviously well it cost bandwidth for one
thing.
But primary reason being that that you can't necessarily do as much
with transparency and stuff like this.
If you count on the Z, buffer to resolve your debt problems for you
without sorting, those are pretty minor concerns compared to all of
the stuff that we had to do to sort of make sorting work reasonably
and I really just didn't like that.
I feel like it's it just creates an ugly engine that with a lot of
Sort of pitfalls in it.
And so I would like to make that transition before we move on to just
writing regular game code where we're not really thinking about the
engine particularly much anymore, and we're just working on things
like how to enemies behave.
And how do we want rooms to be generated and that sort of stuff.
So that is, I think what we want to get to is just this little break
point here and then we'll do this thing and do a sort of 3D graphics.
Upgrade.
And just kind of move our stuff over to that and then Collision
detection, I'm not actually sure how much we actually need.
We already implemented the main kind that we wanted, which is the fact
that people can't stand on squares that are occupied and that's done.
So the other kind really is just for probably mostly projectiles
things, hitting other things like that.
And so now that we know exactly what we need that for just going
through those routines and cleaning them up and doing like solid
implementations of them because I put in one a long time ago, there
was a really basic implementation.
That is not one that we want to ship, but that's still in there and
just moving that out and making it a little bit more.
Reasonable is all I'm really talking about.
So that's it.
A i storage is probably not something that we can really tackle at the
moment.
And the reason for that is
In order to have something like a i storage.
We have to have some notion of an AI.
Who wants to remember things from frame to frame?
Meaning, right now, we pretty much only have enemies who do their
planning in a very local sense, and who don't store particularly much
information.
We don't have, for example a enemy which needs to store complex World
Knowledge or something like
I don't know that we really need to ever have anything like that.
It's kind of on the to-do list here, just because it was sort of a
thought of like, well, we haven't developed anything for that Tech.
Should we need something like that?
But I don't really have anything in mind.
That would require anything particularly complicated here.
You know, I guess the thing that I would say is like, even something
like pathfinding, I don't know that we really need anything in
particular with storage.
We can probably just in the entities themselves store a few steps of
path if we want, that sort of thing.
So I don't know.
So,
Going to just basically say that that probably isn't going to happen
until we actually need it if we need it.
Because I don't think it's particularly relevant at all.
So I think.
Yeah, like I said really, what we want to do here is just focus on
finishing up the multiple submarines, multiple some regions per frame.
I think that's the last thing that we were looking at before we could
basically say like, all right, not really anything else to do here.
So let's go ahead and do the 3D upgraded
We'll just do the graphics and and collision for 3D and and call it a
day.
Engine wise.
And really that would mostly be, it's not a huge deal to upgrade
something to from 2D to 3D.
It's mostly just going to be sort of me having to explain a few things
that we did not cover in much detail because we didn't actually need
to.
We tend to think of things, mostly a screen space.
We have introduced anything like clip space, for example.
So there's some things about a 3D pipeline that we kind of need to
talk about but otherwise, there really isn't much.
We have to do in practice.
Then sort of make more rigorous our ideas about where things are in 3D
and how we're going to deal with them, because we already have a
back-end that supports opengl and stuff like this.
So moving that over to just using regular 3D is simply a question of
working out the math, a little more carefully and showing like how
that sort of stuff works.
There isn't like a whole re-architecting that has to happen or
anything like that.
Plus, we are already sending stuff down to our render in three
dimensions.
We already provide 3D positions for things and so really all we need
to do there is just instead of pre-processing that into 2D rectangles
that are in screen space which is kind of what we're doing now.
We're just going to leave that data untouched and pass it down more
directly and that's really all we're talking about here.
So again not really that complicated what we're talking about, it's
not really a big deal so I'm not anticipating that to be a huge thing
in
In terms of actual stuff we need to do.
But it is a rather big deal in terms of us kind of trying to teach a
bunch of stuff that is
Not necessarily important in the when you only have two t.
So it will take a while to do because we're going to have the ticket
fairly slowly.
And I'm going to have to go through a bunch of Concepts that we don't
really have to visit in the 2D sense.
But other than that it would be pretty straightforward.
I think.
Okay.
So, let's remind ourselves where we are here.
Pretty much.
Like I said, everything, I think is,
Is still kind of very straightforward right?
Where everything still running, okay.
And our kind of weird AI is jumping around and are weird like head
based particles.
I got to have to ask Anna what she wants for particles.
I'm assuming she'll want some particle Sprites but yeah, basically
there's not really that much in terms of stuff that we don't have, as
we kind of talked about before, we're pretty good to go on engine
stuff.
So I think the only thing we really want to do is finish up the
multiple SIM region stuff.
And we'll go ahead and and deal with them.
We'll go ahead and deal with our 3D changes.
Now, one of the interesting things to hear is that I'm pretty pleased
with how everything is working as well.
You know, like I said, we've got some stuff that's not as good as you
know, maybe we would want it to be, but one thing that is pretty nice
is, you know, we already handle all the stuff we kind of wanted to
handle and it pretty worked up pretty well, at least so far.
Now, we haven't, you know, shipped anything yet so it's, you know,
it's too early to declare Victory on anything certainly.
But our design seems to be holding up relatively.
Well, you know, this world can be arbitrarily big.
We tried just slapping down tons of rooms and we don't suffer really
any performance penalties, right?
We still run at 60 frames a second.
Everything's fine.
Even though we can simulate as much of the world right now is we kind
of want to and we successfully we don't suffer from any floating Point
Precision.
None of these things.
So all the stuff that we kind of wanted as far as I know, we've pretty
much
Each got right.
So we can we can literally create worlds that would be extraordinarily
large here, I could walk through all of them and none of it's a
problem.
And again we also can simulate as much of it as we want to at the
moment.
And, you know, just and the parts that we don't want to simulate don't
have to be simulated, and it doesn't create any issues.
Etc, etc.
So all that stuff, seems pretty good and I'm relatively happy with it.
But like I said, the the to dienes part of
I'm not particularly psyched about so yeah.
Anyway, so that's really all there is to that.
I'm going to go ahead here and exit out of here.
In terms of the simulation region stuff, it's going to take us a
little bit.
We haven't programmed in a while to kind of get back into it, but if
you remember what we were doing before in World mode here, you can
kind of see where we've got simulation happening.
You can see where we were playing around with this.
Here is the actual primary region of the game, where the player is
standing.
This is where we do the work.
That we actually want to do for the game, you see.
But up here, we had an example of what happens when you want to do
simulation for the part of the game that you can't see.
And hear, we basically, like,
Farm off a bunch of threads which all those threads can go and do
actual simulation of different parts of the game.
So what that looks like right is right now.
Other parts of the world are being simulated.
If we take a look at the profile, you can kind of see that happening.
Here, I'll go ahead and pause the profile on a frame here and you can
kind of see that we've got World simulation happening on a number of
threads, right?
So that
Really just to allow us the opportunity to take advantage to
multiprocessor, machines, to stimulate more of the game world than we
could.
If we were only simulating one on one core of the machine.
Now, we don't really need this yet obviously, so it's just sort of a
test to make sure that the technology would hold up, okay?
If that's something that we wanted to do, but, you know, like I said,
it's good to.
It was good to
Just figure out like would we be able to do that with our with our
architecture?
And the answer appears to be?
Yes.
Now what I wrote down in terms of to dues for that is well okay you
know we have a number of things about the Sim that we you know we
tried to clean up the fact that they're running a multiple we try to
kind of isolate.
What we were going to do with the simulation and you can see here in
do World Sim exactly what needs
It done, it creates a memory Arena.
It does a begins him step which is like preparing to do simulation.
It does a simulate step, which does the actual simulation and as an
enzyme, which would have finish this up.
And then it, like, freeze, the memory was going to be using one of the
things that we wanted to do was not do this anymore.
We wanted to sort of have a Rena's that were set up specifically for
work on multiple threads.
So that
It's something we definitely want to look at in a second and then the
other thing is here in update and render world.
You can see why we broke it down that way.
We have this concert begins him again but then there's other stuff
that we might want to do like check for joining players and then we do
simulate, right?
And then we do and some all the way at the end and while the
simulation is open, we also draw some things that we care about and do
things like taking the the camera deltas and that sort of stuff,
right?
And so, you know what we tried to do here is basically make that
Relation of stuff work so that we could do it in both cases and use
the same code in both cases.
One, one of the cases is we're just going to go ahead and simulate the
game part that you actually see.
And the other case is we're trying to simulate something where it's
off screen.
So we don't care about the camera.
We don't care about drawing any additional things like at all, we
don't care about checking for joining players because they wouldn't be
joining in those regions.
They be joining in the region, we could see etcetera etcetera,
So that's what we did and that was all relatively good but there's
still some stuff in there.
Like so for example, if we take a look at what happens here in and
World change, which is a big part of vensim, right?
If we take a look here, a 10 cm, you can see that, mostly what enzyme
in is is just finishing, the use of the temporary memory, for whatever
that temporary memory is and calling and World change.
Whoo-hoo Tire boy.
All right.
So and World change when it comes through here.
A lot of the work that it does is checking this you know, camera
following entity index situation, right?
And what that does is, that's just a thing, which updates the camera
in the case, where the entity that the camera is supposed to track is
in this simulation region.
And so the sort of the aspects of that that I'm interested in here is
saying, well, I don't really love that because I don't
really feel like that's appropriate thing to be stuck in the middle of
this multi-platform simulation stuff necessarily
It's kind of hard to say so I'm not sure that we want that happening
all the time in here.
Now maybe we do maybe we don't it's kind of hard to say but if you see
how this goes, in fact let me go ahead and just demonstrate this.
If you see how this goes, it creates an entirely weird dependency here
on the same region stuff that really wouldn't have existed for any
other reason, we have to reach into the world mode structure and deal
with this camera following entity index bit here.
But the only reason that we have to do that is because we're updating
the camera right here in line.
And so it creates this weird sort of knowledge in the same region of
the whole game World situation for no reason other than it needs to
have this camera, following entity index.
And so, you know, is there anything wrong with that?
Not necessarily, but it does mean that I've sort of created a
dependency that I wouldn't ordinarily have and you can see here when
we do begin World change, we do not need any of that.
That right?
We only care about the actual world struct.
The, you know, the
Thing that actually stores the data for the world, which makes sense
because that's what we're operating on.
But, you know, our ending World change is not symmetric, you know, it
should
Look like that because it's just ending the simulation of this world
region.
But instead, it takes this because of that sort of ancillary camera
aspect.
So what I'm kind of interested in here is like, can this be pulled out
as well into a special-purpose thing?
That's only there for people who care about the camera and isn't there
for people who don't care about the camera.
So that it's not sort of creating this artificial dependency between
these two systems that are really isn't quite there if you will and
you know again.
Then why do I care about that?
And mainly, the reason I care about that is that in general, I like to
try and separate out things which are really dependent and things
which are not really dependent.
And the reason for that, is that it just makes code simpler to, to
maintain over time, right?
In a circumstance, where everything talks to everything, right?
Where all of my routines are grabbing stuff from everywhere, it makes
it very hard to isolate it
Your piece of the code and say, Here's exactly what this does.
And here's exactly what it needs to function.
Right.
It gets it harder, it makes it harder to continue to do that because I
never really know what other things.
You know.
It's too hard to keep that out in your head potentially at once.
What parts are depend on other parts.
So reducing those dependencies
Is just a helpful tool when you see a dependency like this one that
really doesn't need to be there.
Removing, it is usually a good thing to consider for that reason.
This is very much like again sort of the functional programming style
of looking at things just to a lesser degree, right?
It's saying you know, functional programming is about saying there are
no side effects and I pass in everything that I that I need to operate
on explicitly.
It's and so on and so.
Right.
And, you know, if you want to take it to the nth degree, you would
say, well, I'm going to pass in literally, everything by value, right?
Like, I'm going to enumerate, absolutely everything this thing needs
and take as return everything that it possibly could touch.
You know, taking that to the nth degree is is, you know, maybe the
purest functional programming, you could imagine doing or something, I
don't really need to do that, but I do believe in minimizing
dependencies and side effects where possible.
No because again it just makes it easier to think about the program.
You know, it's very a purely functional program is very easy to reason
about because it just doesn't have very much.
You have to look at, you can see from the function signature in a
purely functional program.
Exactly what a function needs and what it does, right?
And that's very handy, by contrast in something that does a lot of
side effects.
It's very hard to understand necessarily all of the things that it
touches that's also what makes
it powerful and it's why side effect based programming is the kind of
programming that almost everything is
At some level.
Again, just because you need to do that to Be an Effective program, or
it doesn't mean, you don't also want to appreciate what you're sort of
giving up for that freedom and ability.
And that is sort of that understanding of exactly what a function
actually touches and what it could do.
So in this case, that's why I've sort of singled this parameter out
here is something that I'm like, well, I don't really believe that
this routine needs access to that.
And I would rather have a version of
The team that didn't do it.
So the question is how do I you know like if I was going to pull this
out let's just see what does that actually look like, right?
Scram get this here.
So here I've pulled it out.
Oops, gotta get my key bindings, I forgot I changed my key bindings,
one of my key bindings for Fork Road, it was only one of them, but I
changed on my debe.
She never got to move it over here.
So if you look at what happens here, this is where
camera code used to happen here.
So, just put that in for a second so you can see what happens here,
right?
We used to do this, mapping the map in a trunk space bit and then we
would do some stuff with the movement of the enmity.
And then, you know, we would update camera code and then we would sort
of retire that information back into the world, a structure.
And this is the place where eventually we would sort of pack the data
for the entity, but we're not doing that the
Because again, we don't have a need to do that up until like more
towards the end of development, when we're more cared about space and
speed and so on.
So that's all that is.
But now we can look up here and say, okay, so if somebody wanted to do
this part of the process, right, what do they actually need?
So, let's take a look and see what if I was to make this a function
that was just, you know,
update camera or something like that for, you know, entity movement or
something like this, right?
So if I was going to do that, the question now becomes.
All right, so if I was going to update the camera for any movement
here, what would I want to do?
You know, if I was passing the stuff in?
So, you know, I've got an entity structure, right?
Obviously that's going to work.
Let's take a look at what our other compiler errors.
Are what do we actually need here?
So we've got the world mode.
All right, fine, we'll pass the world mode in for the moment, game
mode world, I think.
Yeah,
And we also need the world.
And we need the entity P.
Alright, so let's take a look here.
We're looking at the room based camera.
That's the
Only one we actually want.
Right?
So if we're taking a look at what would happen here, maybe we just
say, well this is the part we actually care about we don't do the
other kind of camera anymore.
So if I want that, what do I get right?
And it looks like just from doing that.
It looks like this function is essentially totally isolated mobile,
right?
So that's actually perfect.
I want to look at what the world what the world's actually used for
here because it says it wants the world's what's going on there?
Oh, that was just
To test some we're is that used, okay, so we need map into chunk,
space to figure out what we're doing with the camera there.
So we need that's why we need that.
So if we were going to update the camera for any movement, you know,
it would look something like this.
Okay, but now, like I said, we've sort of pulled that out we're still
in debug build, right?
No.
Okay, so we've pulled that out, right?
But now if we ran our camera wouldn't function more because we're
never calling it right?
That thing never gets called by anybody, right?
So if I come through here and, you know, we'll do whatever we're
doing, I can walk off the screen and and, you know, not good, right?
Not great.
So,
At that point.
The question is who calls this and why, right?
And when so, we don't probably need to do this anymore where we say,
like entity ID Value, World mode, camera following entity index, the
any of that stuff, right?
All I really need to do because I can access entities is, I just need
to make sure that when I pass this, I'm only passing the entity that I
actually care about here.
And in fact, in some sense we could pull out the
No camera stuff into its own thing.
We won't do that at the moment, but anyway,
So really what I can do here is to say, hey you're only going to call
this thing with this ended with the entity that you're actually
following.
And so,
Shooting and so we can just assert that no one's trying to do that
with any other entity for the moment.
Right?
And later on, we may want to do stuff where we change how that works
or something.
But you know, for the moment we'll do it this way.
So okay, so if we're going to do update camera for any movement, we'd
pass in the entity, that is the one that matches the camera following
editing index.
But we need to do that somewhere, right?
And so, if I go into the world mode itself here and I take a look,
We're we're doing the main update.
You know, this is sort of where we would want to do that in that
stuff.
It would normally I guess happen right here because this is where this
is before the enzyme would happen.
Right answer.
If I was going to do that.
I could just call update camera for end of the movement and I could
pass the world in the world mode.
And the only thing I would need here is the camera entity, right?
And I don't know what that entity is.
So the question is, where do I get that in any from?
Well, in the same region stuff, we should be able to access, it editi
by its ID because we already have to do that for a bunch of reasons,
right?
So, we've got a function right here that will use the hash table in
the same region for this.
Very purpose.
So we should be able to just call that here and get an entity by the
ID, which we know because it's from the world mode, the camera, right?
That's exactly what it's from.
So, here is my begin Sim, right?
And I'm going to get back the world, Sim the world Sim has the same
region in it.
So I know that inside here, I can just access that.
And then the only question is, well, where is that?
You know, what's the entity ID that I need?
Well, that was exactly.
Only the thing that we were just talking about here, we actually store
whatever that entity index is.
We store that in the world mode, that's the entity that we're
following with the camera at the time.
So I just passed those two in.
It should give me back the camera entity, right?
And I assume I can also say well, okay, you know, if there is no
camera entity, don't try to update it.
But presumably there always is for the most part, right?
All right, so now in theory, I should be able to follow my My Little
Hero, friend here.
He should be able to hop out of the room.
There we go, there we go.
And you know, we've basically just restored that functionality.
But now that routine doesn't actually have any problem with being
coupled sort of, to the ending of the simulation.
So that's good.
Now, that's out of there.
And I like that better because now we can see more concisely sort of
what's happening with the begin World change and World change.
I might go ahead as well and just say, let's move those two functions
next to each other.
Our tears, begin World change, right?
And here's and World change and that way I can sort of also just see
them, right?
Oh it's like looks like that.
May be easier said than done.
This can certainly move out of there though.
We go.
And let's see, create an MD, delete, MD pack, entity reference, create
edit.
And delete entity.
Certainly don't need to be there.
Those can go outside as well.
I think.
Damn.
And so really it's just there to packing things that will intercede.
So anyway, I think that's it for that and you know I could put these
above it as well.
I could say those go right here.
And then we can just see relatively easily.
Those two routines.
Here's the begin World change one, which is getting relatively
respectable.
And then there's the end will change one, which is also getting
relative respectable.
And so it's got the pack in the unpack there and the, the pack and
unpack again, will then become more of a real thing.
You know, far further down the line, once the games already, you know,
more complete the game part of the game, not the engine.
So that's it.
Okay.
So if I take a look at pulling out the camera concept and something
clear an optional, I think that's really all I need to do right now.
We could take it one step further.
I don't know if we want to and that step further is inside the game
mode thing.
Here, you can kind of see, we've got camera offset, camera P, last
camera, speed camera, following entity index those things could be put
into a camera structure.
So for example, we could say something like this
which would essentially be
oops.
That sort of thing.
And then what would happen is any time we were working on something
like this, where we were previously talking about the world mode, we
would not necessarily use the world mode anymore, so if we take a look
at what happens with World mode here, you can see that almost in every
case we're talking about the actual camera stuff.
So the only place we're using the world mode as the world mode is by
looking at the room, Delta and the room Delta is really sort of
More of a property of where you are in the world at that point, so
that probably should be more of a query on the world, not on the world
mode anyway.
But anyway, so if you take a look at what happens in there, if I just
scan through sort of what's Happening Here, you can kind of see that
in a lot of cases, we're updating this, it would just be like a adding
an extra dot in here.
So let's go ahead and do that since I took that stuff anyway or just
him showing.
How do that step?
You know, let's just change this to
Stew last p and p an offset and following entity index.
And then we'll go ahead and switch on here.
So if I just do something like this, right?
See how that's changing.
All I'm really doing is is changing it to a dot in all of these cases.
Nothing, particularly exciting.
Hear that.
And again, same thing.
Let's take a look at this so that's would just be this one kind of
inverts itself a little bit.
That's camera.
Last P.
There's camera P, almost done again.
Just a mechanical transform here.
Just literally pushing it down one level.
First, there's our camera P.
Again,
And Camera offset.
Let's take a look at this here.
There's
and,
Almost done.
Okay.
So at that point again, now we've just all we've done is just kind of
move code into a different place.
We should get rid of.
I'm like, I'm kind of tired of those weird teleport regions, which we
were playing with before.
Let's go ahead and stop that.
Poor fellow for from bouncing around so much.
There we go.
Where were those things?
Were they on here?
I don't remember.
Yeah, there we go.
So it's this weird like Target ref.
Situation here.
That's the one.
So this thing.
Going to be Auto boost.
Now we've everyone should be a little bit more same.
So anyway now we should have again the exactly the same functionality
we had before which is all we were really looking for.
And so that's all fine.
And so now what I can do is I can also say well, okay.
Now, some of these things that we're taking the camera before, let's
just take a look at where they all were.
And again, one of the ways that I like to do that, a lot of times just
kind of go in and say, well, if everyone was accessing
This camera previously.
I'm just going to go ahead and get rid of that there and now I can see
everywhere where people were talking about the camera.
So obviously update camera for any movement because he had all the
compiler will error out.
Now all the time when anywhere and we try to access it.
And so, if we take a look here, what happened?
When we do update camera-friendly movement, really?
This is all talking about the camera.
So, if I just said game camera camera, I wouldn't need the world mode
anymore except for one very specific circumstance.
Right.
So I could go ahead and here and just say like okay everywhere in here
where we were accessing this off the world mode, I'm just going to
access the camera directly now, right?
And that's kind of handy because now and I guess I need to.
There we go.
Fatal error.
All right I wasn't expecting you to fatal error on this because the
only thing we need the world mode for I guess I should go ahead and
change these as well to camera Arrow.
Since instead of camera dot, those will all be are as once the
compiler figures out, it isn't really that fatal, okay?
So the only thing we need the world mode for is that typical floor
height, which again, I think is probably more of a property of the
world.
If anything, I think that's something we're going to want to upgrade
anyway in the world structs and so on.
But if we were to take a look at the world here, where we're looking
at this, I'm gonna just going to put that in here as like typical
Floor height into the world so that we can just kind of access it
there, right?
So, let's take a look as well at
In fact, typical floor height is really just a chunk Tim and M z, if I
remember correctly.
Like, I'm pretty sure, actually, we could just do it where we were
saying, hey, the room, Delta is, you know, a particular size,
whatever.
But what I'm kind of interested in here as well, is looking at this as
a non-relative phenomenon.
So I'm going to, I'm going to
kind of hand wave that here for a second and just say, like, okay, it
is whatever it is.
Let's go see what see here?
Let's see, what typical floor height, actually is.
It's three.
We go.
And now I think when we look at any of these are other ones that I
want to look at.
No.
No, that's fine.
So all that's pretty much fun.
All right so in here yeah when we are talking about the camera, I'm
just going to pass that in here.
So World mode camera.
I'm going to pass that in will change the world mode camera to this
and off we go.
When we do the update camera entity for Canada movement, I want to
push that camera first.
Incest thing the operating on there, and there we go.
Alright, so what
I wanted to say about this room, Delta stuff is one of the things that
I definitely don't like about how we're doing this at the moment now,
that we're sort of in the camera world and I think when we move to 3D
this would be, also a very good time to think about that.
Is if we wanted to have.
Multiple size rooms in the game, right?
So imagine wanting to sort of have maybe a double length room or
something like, you know, twice that was twice as wide or high as
another room and you wanted the game to pull out.
So, it kind of like the camera went up higher and showed you more of
the world.
When you were in that room, that's a pretty reasonable thing.
I want to do right.
You know, there's nothing and there's nothing in the engine that would
really prevent us from doing that.
But right now, we kind of have this hard-coded notion that the rooms
are the size that they are as far as the camera is concerned.
So, that becomes sort of problematic.
And so I think we need
Kind of going forward, is the ability here to say, well where am I in
the world?
What room am I looking at?
Because I feel like the a room, as a concept kind of needs to be baked
in.
Now where a room is you know, it doesn't affect any any entity stuff
or anything like that, but it would need to just sort of be a nice
little
It would have to be something that just sort of said, hey here is like
a bounding box that says this is a room as far as this area of the
world is concerned and this is the room you're in at the moment,
right?
And if we look at how room Delta works here, we wouldn't really need
to do any of this stuff.
The way that we're doing it either.
What we could do instead is
Just say when we have decided we're moving from one room to another or
whatever room.
The hero is in, we can just say, oh well, whatever room the hero is
in, let's move the camera towards that position, right?
And that's a sort of a, you know, much more sort of straightforward
thing that we that we might want to do there, right.
Hopefully.
All right.
So, you know, that's a thing.
I think we want to probably get two and maybe we'll do that with the
3D thing.
I'll put that in the to do here.
Let's let's take a look.
So we'll call that 3D, you know.
So something like that.
Basically.
Okay, so now we've got our, you know.
Now, we've got our fairly basic stuff happening.
We're we're, you know, we're doing our simulation work and we have
pulled out almost everything from it that we don't think needs to be
there.
And so, let's see here, we've got the camera stuff, pulled out this
stuff, I think again, look, I'm pushing down a little bit.
And we did exactly this, we eliminated World mode from The Sims step
entirely, they're all that.
Well, that's not actually true.
So we still have in simulate that still happens.
So we're not quite done with that yet.
That's we're not, we're not quite there yet.
So let's take a look at what's happening in simulate there, for the
world mode.
So let's see.
We're in the same region.
Where is our simulate call?
See
So right now we're doing is we're doing brains and let's see typical
floor Heights being passed through here.
The typical floor height gets passed around a lot to say the least.
All right.
So anyway, let's take a look at when World Nuggets past.
It looks like World mode isn't really used for very much at the moment
actually.
That's interesting.
So really it's just the entropy and the floor height that's all that
it's used for and then it would be gone entirely.
That's pretty great actually.
All right.
Well, let's go ahead and finish that up.
Then it's further along than I thought it was.
Say the least.
So we're getting there.
That's good.
Good news.
All right, so let's get rid of that.
And now we can basically just say like okay,
All that stuff goes away.
Okay.
so looking at World mode now, it also looks like Okay so
Let's see, simulates taking it.
Let's let's let's let's keep pushing this a little bit further right?
Because here you can see a fairly concise version of this.
Yeah, so let's take a let's take a little bit closer.
Look at this.
And let's see.
You can rip two, worlds, worlds.
So, let's take a look and see if we can't push that a little bit
further because it looks like it's almost there actually at the
moment.
So I'm going to come in here to sim region.
I want to take a look at begin Sim or sorry, begin World change and I
just want to see so that doesn't take the world mode yet at all.
So that's good and if I look at begin World change, I'm sorry if I
look at begins.
What does that actually need the world mode for?
Yeah.
So that's really it's really just for updating the camera.
Or rather looking at the Delta, you know, the camera Delta that needs
to happen there.
I'm kind of interested as to why that's still happening where it's
happening right?
Like why that's happening inside begin Sim because again that's really
not something that probably needs to be happening there.
Like I don't know that the camera P needs to be computed there
anymore, right?
Because if we take a look at World mode here and we look at where
we're actually
Using that.
Let's take a look.
And we say, OK, simulate world's mode camera.
Let's see.
And do some here camera.
P is just not used, right?
So it's only the case, where we actually care about it.
We only care about that case in here, right?
So I think that's probably something where that's actually not what we
want to be doing.
Yeah, pretty pretty much at.
All right?
So when we call do World Sim here,
And we call begins him.
It's just using the world mode to get that camera for no reason.
So yeah I can verify that that's just yet.
Again this is exactly why I want to go through and remove these
dependencies is because you know, there's a lot of stuff in here that
just doesn't really need to be happening in most of the paths, right?
So I think this circumstance is really, you know,
This stuff really only wants to happen on this path.
Pretty much it.
The only time that must happen, right?
So World mode camera p.
In this case, that stuff wants to happen in here as the way that it
would tell it how it was going to do like, essentially where the
simulation was going to take place, if you will would be passed in
like this.
And then in the case where you were actually updating that camera P,
it would come in here where you do the subtraction at the end of
things, right?
I think that's how you would want to do it and so whatever that Sim
that previous, mm Centre was that would be, I guess coming in here?
Let's take a look at that.
So here's the Sim Center.
I'm not sure, I'm not sure.
We, it's still just the same.
It's not even gonna get updated by that.
So really, it's just saying,
I'm not even sure because these two are the same value, right?
I mean, am I missing something here?
Because the Sim Center me, just let me just verify to myself that.
I'm not delusional about that because it sure does seem that way.
So we take a look here.
We say here's the Sim Center P, right?
It's the same as the camera P.
So in this case, we're going to do that subtraction there.
Well, that's subtraction.
Is we now know completely useless, right?
Anything that's going to be, an offset is going to be in here.
So essentially, it's just that
Right?
Nothing needs to happen.
And presumably, that's it, right?
So if I want to, I could just start using the camera here, exactly
this way.
And, you know, go out of here and still works right, and I don't think
there's anything particularly weird going on there.
So really, that is not necessary at all.
So, if we take a look at the world mode stuff here again, that's just
really, this could just be
Passing down the world and this is not necessary at all.
So, the Sim Center and the simulation bounds.
I'm not even sure why we have both of those because presumably the Sim
Center always has to be the same as the Sim bounds, right?
You wouldn't be like what does that even do at this point, right?
It just seems like something that's probably at this point.
A Vestige will remain.
So if we take a look at begin,
World change and I look at the world position origin, right?
Yeah.
So that's all that's doing is it's just there to say like okay this is
the center point around which the simulation will occur and this is
the yeah.
So really we don't need to pass that world mode at all.
All we need to do is have somebody pass in that Sim Center.
So we know where we are.
Simulating that combined with
Rectangle would give us that and this doesn't need to be here at.
All right.
I guess I should just verify that that's yeah just remember what that
is that this is the region.
We want to be simulating in that case so I'll go ahead and grab that.
Where's that right here?
So when we are going to call begin Sim all will do is say hey we want
to begin some, we want to begin some right there.
And then when I come back up here and take a look at
What we're doing in the other case where we do begin some with the
same bounds again that in this case we now need someplace.
How are we doing our Sim bands here?
We do Works in Balance.
So all this should probably just come from the work structure so we'd
probably be wanting to do.
Oops, we probably want to be doing something like work Sim Center P
where that's
I think that would sort of be passed down.
Okay.
And so in this case we'd say what are the Sim bands and
What's the Sim Center?
If I take a look at where we're actually doing that stuff.
In fact, previously we were sort of doing this offset directly this
way, which is not stable.
Floating-point why?
It's like we couldn't get arbitrarily large with that, right?
That's the whole reason.
We have our concept of the separate center staff.
So, at that point, we want to say, okay, let's do some Center P here.
And we would want to do something where this actually gets baked in.
So, there is no offset here.
The same bounds are just the same bands as they are, right?
And what we want to do here is use the actual World coordinate system,
to just put the chunk, use the use, the trunk offsets, right?
So all we would want to do here is say like, okay, we've got a world
position and like, again, we're doing this fairly arbitrarily, because
we don't, we're just testing.
But here's our Center Point.
And we want a chunk x a chunk.
Why in a chunk?
See.
Well, we wanted those relative I guess to the camera was previously,
how we were doing it, I believe.
And so let's go ahead and say whatever that camera was.
So we've got the world mode camera p.
is where it'll be and then, we'll just say, like okay, the chunk X,
And the chunk, why?
we'll just offset these and you know, I don't know by who
Much may be negative 10 or something.
In each Direction, maybe -15 chunks or something like this seems
relatively straightforward and yeah, there we go.
And now we just want to multiply that by yeah.
By our Loop.
And now we've done the offset in a way, that's, you know, floating
Point say, for however, big we want to do it as well.
Not that we care about that, for this particular circumstance, but
it's just good to know that, that's what we're doing.
Maybe these should be further away, I don't know, who knows how far
out they should be if we wanted to be roughly similar what we were
doing 100 100 before.
So you know, if we want to take a look at what the default chunk size
is I think alike if it's 100.
Take a look here.
I don't remember what.
Where we actually allocate the world, but let's see.
So if we're talking about are chunks, being like 1.4 by 1.4.
So if we wanted a hundred of those, right?
We're talking about see, something like
Seventy.
So, do something like that.
And that's really all there is to that and now we can sort of finished
up that clean up, right?
We also don't need to pass the camera P back in this result at all.
It's got the same region in the Sim memory thing the past back.
We don't need these anymore so that's nice.
And then we can compile this.
Let's see
Getting there.
All right, so let's finish this up.
When we do update and render entities, let's see, we're passing down
the camera P there.
So that, that camera p is really just again.
All that was was just the Sim Center, the piece of the Sim Center
information that we had there.
Which which we don't really want, right?
I mean it was, it was
See her, if I can.
Put that back.
It was really just the offset was pretty much all it was.
I think let me just double-check that that's true.
Yeah, so I think that's really just it's all it is, is the offset.
And so when you're talking about update and render entities, you're
just talking about whatever the offset is.
When you want to actually render.
And so I feel like that's something that we would just pass down here
and that's just the camera off set.
It doesn't need to get passed through in that weird.
Kind of way.
It was just like, overcomplicating how that piece of the program was
working.
So we should be able to hearsay or we do the simulation.
We're going to do the rendering assuming that we do have the
rendering.
We just have like camera set as a thing, we passed down and then
camera offset can just be passed.
And through directly, right?
And I think that's pretty much all there is to that.
I don't think there's anything else to it.
All right, so let's keep working that through and see if we're right.
Let's see here.
yeah, in simulate again, we don't care about this because we're not
rendering
Inside begin Sim same situation here.
We just want to pass the world's past the world.
Not sure why we're passing the camera P to check for joining players.
That seems real weird.
That seems really strange because this is the camera off set.
Which I don't think is what we actually wanted to pass here.
That makes no sense whatsoever.
Yeah, so that makes no sense whatsoever because that's like only
moving when we move in between scenes.
So I think that was probably a holdover from other stuff.
I don't think we care about that at all.
It's only the offset.
So this, if we literally just past the zero point, that would just get
us the closest thing to the center of the simulation region, which is
all we really care about there.
So I don't even think we need that.
In simulate, we do want to pass the camera offset, which is here.
Particle systems.
Want the exact same thing.
Oops.
And yeah.
Fink.
That's all there is, don't quote me on that but I think that's all
there is.
I would say I'm a little suspicious there.
I was
Just happened.
That was a little odd.
Everything appears to be working properly, but I am a little bit
weirded out by the fact that the game is running faster for no reason.
So that's
you never really wanted that to happen.
I mean, hey, it's better than the game running slower for no reason.
But, yeah, that was a little surprising.
I'm not sure exactly what happened there.
That's not great, should probably investigate that a little bit
further in a second when I'm done cleaning this up.
But so okay, again, moving sort of slowly forwards here.
So now when we look at what is happening with the world mode, we're
really only talking about
Happening inside simulate and inside simulate.
We're just looking at passing some really basic stuff through, you
know, basically, we're passing extraordinarily basic stuff from the
world mode and there's really no need for it to really be there
anymore.
I wouldn't think now.
I don't know, I guess these don't need the world anymore, they don't
need access to the world, which is what we want because it's just as
the pull in pull out.
So really all we need to do here is we need the
The brains need to get their entropy from somewhere, right?
So we need to have some notion of what that entropy value should be
for them to access Randomness.
Essentially and I'm not sure where the best place to get that from is,
but
I guess what I would say on that fact is
because multiple people are accessing that entropy at the same time.
Potentially I don't really know.
I don't know if we want to take steps to make that entropy be more
friendly for multi-threading like because it's just something that
does a mathematical update.
I don't know that it actually ever matters if two threads romp on it
at the same time and replace the value.
That one of the other was trying to use, I don't know that that really
ever matters.
So it's probably fine that we just don't as weird as that seems.
But I don't know, right?
So that's a little bit questionable, you know another way.
Look at it would be that every thread should use a separate entry
stream so that you don't ever update have two people updating the
entropy at the same time.
But again I'm not really sure I can think of a real reason why you
care about that.
That may just be isolating something for no real reason.
Yeah, that's a tough question.
I can't think of any real reason why.
So yeah, so this stuff doesn't actually need the world.
The typical floor height here is one thing that we do need again.
I'm not sure exactly how we want to handle that.
Let me take a look again.
What that's being used for.
We put that back in temporarily so I can take a look.
Okay, so yeah, so let's take a look.
If we go out to the update and render entities,
I want to look at what the typical fluorides being used for.
I'm pretty sure it's just used for sorting people into which floor
they're on, and that does seem to be the case.
Yeah.
So again, I'm not sure that we actually necessarily need that.
I mean we can do distance-based fog without that.
There's a lot of different things we can do if we want that to, you
know, if we want that to be a thing.
So I'm not sure, I'm not sure what we want to do.
They're passing it down.
Like we do here is obviously totally fine and we could just make it.
So we pass it through simulated as well.
Because obviously, anyone who's calling that needs to know.
The world structure as well which means you know we could just pass it
here directly.
So I'm going to Bubble it up for now like just to see what happens if
we say typical floor of light here and this is not how I want to do it
eventually but I'm just going to do it this way.
Temporarily is a typical floor height and then I have you know the
game entered get passed down so that we're literally just passing the
things we need specifically rather than grabbing them out of stuff.
If we end up like that, I want to take a look at what that
Entail, when we call simulate here, obviously we can do World typical
floor height.
And then we need a way to get that entropy and again, that would still
require I think the world mode, right?
Well.
In here, same deal, right?
And so we've doubled it up, one level and so these are getting
slightly better but they're still, you know, pretty, it's still pretty
questionable at the higher level.
That those things would actually be necessary if we take a look at
Going on here.
We started to get this into a pretty respectable state.
In terms of what's going on.
We've got our begins to ma Ren Sim and are stimulates depth and
they're getting relatively clean.
You will note though.
However, that executes brain still uses game state for stuff, it would
be nice to get rid of the game State, because passing the game safe
down here is not probably.
So we want to do, if you remember how that's working at the moment.
You can see that the reason that that's there is because it needs to
access the actual controller information that's happening.
When, you know, when the game gets input, I think there are ways we
might want to do that.
That would not involve this right but
As always, it's kind of a little bit it's kind of a little bit iffy so
trying to think of where I want to go with it from here.
I don't know how much time I've got left.
I think I've got about 12 15.
I don't know how long I've got.
So we started at 10:30, right.
So I've got 12:15 12:30.
I got to, I've got to about 12:30, I think either that or 12:15.
I can't quite remember.
But let's say 1234 now.
And I need more water.
So I think what I might want to do is start hammering on the game,
State side of things, but then there's again, I kind of think that
game entropy thing is kind of a little bit of an open question because
I'm not sure, you know, if that because that's more of a world.
Same thing.
I'm wondering if that be Long's more in the actual World itself.
You know, I'm wondering, if that's something that wants to belong in
here, potentially?
It's really difficult for me to make a guess about that at the moment.
if you look at like the world made stuff and you just look at the
constants that are in here,
Hard to say hard to say.
Mmm-hmm.
What is time?
So yeah, looking at this sort of stuff, like we've got the particle
effects in there, you got the effects, entropy the particles are
using, we've got the game entropy.
Yeah and so looking at this world mode,
Looking at this world mode.
And by the way, as far as this to do is concerned having a separate
camera struct as a good way to start that process.
If we did want to do that because if you play split screen, we
duplicate and have two cameras trucks, right, cameras truck per
player, that sort of thing.
So I guess what I would say here is yeah like you know, I've got the
world.
I've got the camera in here that makes sense.
I've got the, you know, standard room dimensions stuff that doesn't
make sense.
I feel like that wants to move into the world.
The world should.
You should really query the world and get those pieces of information
based on your location particle.
Cash, does make perfect sense in here.
I don't know that last use.
Entity storage index should be there.
That seems like that should definitely be on the world.
Um because that is what you create entities with, right?
So yeah, I feel like we've got some thinking to do about where these
things go.
The energy is a good question because I don't really know where that
would go.
And I don't have a strong opinion about it, right?
It seems like it's a property of a world itself because it's something
that, you know, if you were going to save and restore potentially, you
would restore save and restore the entropy, you know, not.
You know this game really doesn't matter.
I don't think because we're not trying to have any kind of a
repeatable thing that goes on but you know, in a game that was
repeatable if you were trying to do that, then you would clearly want
that to be with the save.
Entity data, right?
So it kind of seems like that's something that should be in the world
proper.
Whereas effects entropy would be something that's more with the
particle cash sort of stuff, right?
you know, so if I had to say, I would say it look more, you know, like
It feels like you'd want that in here, right?
It feels like, that's something that would be in here, right?
Because the world is sort of this thing that stores information and
there's maybe a little bit of global information, and there's such a
spatial information, it kind of does seem like that would be the right
thing and I like this is entry that does not affect the gameplay.
It's why is it called game entropy then?
Oh sorry there's well I can't read that does affect the airplane.
All right, good.
So yeah, let me take a look at where that getting initialized.
And so, if we wanted to inside here, I guess we could say, when we
actually create the world for the first time we could initialize that.
So, and
you know, if we would go so then
Every time we were talking about that game, entropy we would be
talking about it off of the world struct.
so,
Really, that's about it.
And so then again.
Yeah, and with typical floor height
I think maybe I just want to start addressing that because it's
bugging me.
Let's just do it.
So standard room dimension in, typical floor height.
I want to start making those little more systemic.
So inside the world like what I want to have happen here basically
because I want you to be able to ask
what room you're in.
And then I want you to be able to like
use the dimensions of that room at that time.
If that makes sense.
You can even imagine a allowing rooms of different heights to be
stacked on top of each other.
So I'm just trying to think about like if you're going to make this
into a sort of a more robust system, what I want to be able to do is
when I'm pressing the world.
I want to be able to get out, Notions of what rooms are that I can
then use for these purposes.
That previously, I was not that I was doing sort of hacked, right by
just like saying, well, I kind of know how big a room is, so let's do
this thing.
So what I'd like to do is say okay, how do we get that room Concept in
here?
And to me, you know, one thing that I'm thinking of sort of here is
well, what if we just had a room?
Be like an entity in the world, right?
So there's just an entity called a room and every time you have a
room, you have one entity that sort of encompasses that rooms space
and that's what you actually use, right?
and I feel like this has some attractiveness because to me, that
basically says, well, when we do are like begin simmer in Sim, it
means we could sort of, you know,
All of the room entities that we see basically build up that knowledge
of what the local area is.
And then, you know, we're kind of done at that point, right?
We now could freely create these rooms wherever and when we exit the
bounds of one of the rooms whichever room we happen to be in, we would
just then transition to pointing the camera so that it encompasses the
other room.
And I feel like that's just a more sane way to do it, you know, then
constantly having these sort of Notions of what's the, what's the
height of a floor or something like that?
Which I don't really care about, you know, the code shouldn't really
have.
Worry about things like that.
I don't know why it would ever be something that's really all that
necessary to know.
So I'm just kind of, I'm just kind of curious if that could be the way
that we would work it out.
And like I said, I've got I think I've got about 40 minutes if that
makes sense.
So yeah, yeah, maybe maybe I'll take a look at that.
So how would that work?
If we were going to do that, right?
If I take a look at the end of these struts in here, you know, and I
kind of got any of the types sitting around and I've got, you know,
whatever these things are here and you type stairwell.
I don't know that we even have stairwells anymore, but if I did say
that there is any type room and that was just a thing that was going
to be like a bounding box for room, you know.
I can obviously create those and maybe I start by just making some of
those, right?
So every time I add
Standard room.
Which is the call that we have here.
So we say like okay yeah, you know, ad standard room,
In addition to making all the entities that comprise the room, you
know.
Maybe it also makes an entity for the room itself, right?
So I do I don't know what I'm going to do exactly here, but I do like
kind of a begin and thing.
Although, to be honest, I don't know that end entity does anything
anymore.
Yeah, it doesn't really.
So really what I want to do here is say okay.
let's go ahead and and get our entity here into the
world mode.
And
and an a
And so, all I really want to do here is say, okay, this entity will
have a bounding box, that is whatever the rooms shape is effectively,
right?
And I can make that be sort of a special case to if I want to.
I can make it so that room and he's in particular just have room bands
on them.
And that's like, they're only property that they happen have and I
should be able to construct an entity that therefore you know,
basically has that what we need, it would be centered about the center
and it would have extents that Encompass the entire size of the room.
So if we take a look at what that would entail, I guess what we'd want
to do is say
well, alright, you
Here's the chunk position from tab position that we were using to
create that.
So if I was going to do that, I'd say it's just
No offsets, that's the actual position, right?
That's where it's going to be.
and,
All I need to do now is actually give it a room, something the size of
a room as the as its bounding box, right?
And then that would be what it would need to have.
So
If I do begin entity.
And I want to attach something here to it.
I'm not sure exactly how I want to do that.
Let's take a look at begin ground identity here.
You can see that it passed equation, volume, I guess I could just do
that and pass the Collision volume.
That's the size of a room.
The thing is, I don't know that I really wanted to be a collision
volume.
I may want it to just be something more straight for that but for now,
let's say we'll stick with what we've got.
So we'll say We'll create a ground identity, and we'll pass it room
key.
Jim and room Collision will just be something that's the size.
Because again, I'll just stick with what we're doing.
Currently one, try to change too many things at once and so
Here is our simple Collision.
So if I made one of these where I just want to see here makes it look
rounded Collision.
Is presumably what I want.
I don't know if any of these are actually what I want, to be honest.
Because the grounded Collision.
Is actually centering its Dimensions.
So that the center point, I think is not where we want it to be right,
because you can see this like dim Z Plus offset, see nonsense, right?
So if I actually did something here where I just said like, okay, make
simple Collision,
Then I could say well, alright.
Then I could say, well, alright, I just want to make this to be
centered around.
How, how rooms are actually centered.
And I guess now, I think about it, I guess I don't know how we're
really considering rooms being centered, may be grounded.
Collision is really the more appropriate way for that, because if all
the things are standing on that flat plane level, you know, maybe
that's actually fine.
So, I don't know.
We'll start with that and I guess I'll see where it goes.
So, what I want to
Here is say well how many you know I know what the standard room
Dimension is, right?
It's we're saying it's 17 here.
What's the tile dim is 1.4, right?
So the standard room Dimension we're saying is 17 by 9.
And the tile depth in meters or rather, the room vention here.
Is the typical floor height?
There it is.
So yeah, so if we take a look at that and just say that's what that
is.
And what if we just say okay now we're going to say we get rid of that
standard room Dimension.
If we do that I'm kind of interested to see like where we can go from
there.
I also want to know where people use that standard room Dimension at
the moment.
So I know kind of what I'm going to have to be up against.
Too much, in terms of changing that over.
So it looks like basically the Sim bounds are being set to being the
standard Rim.
Dimension is how that's working.
So we were just really want to
We would want to sort of make that be a more.
Fundamental concept, right?
Of just simulating a particular size.
I guess we would maybe do a query for the room that we're at and then
just look one room to each side and not actually and then use those
bounds without actually ever free.
Prescribing
Exactly how big that that would be.
All right, so for now it doesn't necessarily matter.
So I'll leave it in but we could probably pull that in a second.
Okay, so the next thing I need to be able to do here is I'm able to
see these things, so I know what's going on with those.
So I think traversals not what I want.
I got turned back on volume rendering, so let's take a look here.
What is the question?
We have a vanity transform and render group.
Let's see.
Can actually see all the stuff that's there.
So push wrecked outline is expecting a render Group which we pass it.
Suspecting an entity transform which we also pass.
Its expecting a rectangle, either a V3, which in this case is what
we're passing it.
A V3 and Jim to, and then a V4.
So it's just the real.
It's the, it's
This last floating point value here.
That's the part that we're not passing.
So let's take a look at what we want to pass for that.
So that's just the thickness.
It looks like so we must be passing because it looks like that should
have worked, right?
there's the
group object, transform.
There's the offset, there's the dimension.
There's a color and the thickness should have been Auto filled in so
I'm not sure.
Let's see what it thinks.
I see that's just needs to be an address of that's it.
All right, so
If we have our little transforms drawn around us are going to, I'm
going to pull out so we can see ya.
So what I want to be able to do here eventually right?
As I want to be able to get to the point where I can see that the room
bounds are actually you know that there's an actual bound around the
room that we're in, right?
I want to be able to see that and I'm not sure that we then would
really need the yellow or white bow.
Here that we were drawing before because those are sort of hacked
bounds that were just drawing where we thought the room boundaries
were and so on.
So let me take a quick look at that as well.
That's inside World mode here where we just kind of draw.
Here we go.
Where we've got like, okay, push worked out line, right?
Where we're drawing that stuff in here we draw.
What do we draw?
We're drawing the screen bounds, the simulation bounds, and the Sim
region back.
Bounds.
I don't know that those two are really all that different.
I guess, we previously did have them be different but nowadays,
they're kind of not.
All right.
So,
I guess I'm not sure what we even care about the screen Vans anymore
for
I guess it's just because that's what we were using for simulation
previously, but
yeah, that's
It's really not even something that we really use anymore, right?
So, it's handy thing to draw, just so we know that we're still
Computing it properly, but again, you're not really using it for much.
Okay, so if we want to draw now the if we want to put in entities that
are the shape of rooms.
What we want to be able to do is sort of see.
We want to be able to see clearly what those outlines are.
So, what I might do here is I might go ahead and say, let's take out
the trees for a moment and, you know, maybe or we could just maybe
turn off entity drawing for a second.
So,
Will actually be able to see a little bit more.
Clearly, what's going on?
If I were to put in an outline there, if I want to do that.
all I would have to do here is just
Stop any?
Stop any usage of the, the actual pieces.
And so here we can see, we're sort of more abstract, Lee, what's going
on, right?
And there we go.
So what I want to do yet again and maybe I'll have to turn off even a
little bit more of the stuff that we're drawing here just to make sure
we could still see it.
Because it's going to roughly fit exactly that bound.
So I might turn up a couple more things in order to see it, but so
let's go ahead and temporarily turn these off as well.
And well, I'm still getting the white region there, so I actually want
that.
I think
Okay, so here, we've got just rectangles drawing, and I guess the
particle systems are still there.
The little test particles.
We do wonder why our particles, we sort of turned off.
Some of the
The updating here, right?
Why did?
When did when did that happen?
Our particles.
No longer we turned off a bunch of stuff for our particles but I don't
remember what we turned off.
Exactly.
I think we turned off like the upward velocity of them, perhaps.
I can't quite remember.
Here's the actual.
May the protocol forward in time if he was famous basement.
So it looks like we were just trying to isolate
what was happening so we probably just did that, right?
There we go.
Not sure why if we wanted to do that right now, but I just like, I
forgot we never turned our particle like sort of push back on.
Who knows why?
Alright, anyway, point being
I want to now be able to see these rooms so that I can verify that
they're getting created in the same place in the right place.
So every time we do add standard room, what I want to do is figure out
a way that I can add an itty here and that entity will sort of
Encompass, the shape that the room actually is.
So all I really need to do.
I think there is set the type of the room to be inanity.
Does that make sense?
Where is that actually set?
Of course, the other thing.
Oh, so do we actually eliminate the entity types entirely?
So, I think we would actually just need to have this be sort of a
separate concept that's case.
Like I these gone now.
Yeah, so we need some way of knowing that this is a room.
Well I guess we don't really even need a way of knowing it's room.
We just need at the moment.
We just need to actually be created there that I need to actually be
able to see that.
It's that, it's, that it's sitting there.
So in theory, that should be creating it, but I'm not 100% sure that I
can actually see it.
Now, of course, again, it may be, that it's just kidding behind those
things.
So, I kind of need to be able to turn off, even more to be able to be
sure that I can.
It.
So if I kind of go into entity and also turn off rendering
traversable, 's maybe that would give me enough.
I'm not sure that it would though.
Well, let's see.
right because we can't really even still tell, you know, it'd be
really hard to see whether there's there's entity kind of going
On behind there, if it was just between, would just be getting
overdrawn potentially.
So I need some way of being able to peek back behind there.
And I'm not sure exactly how I'm going to do that.
You know it looks like it's there, right?
Because it looks like that's the boundary and I have it selected at
the moment, but I don't actually know, right?
So I think that is actually getting creating the right place but I
would like a better way of doing that.
I suppose one way to do that, would just be to turn off the trees
entirely.
Let's take a look.
so Inside Out standard room, when I'm actually adding the
Walls.
I'm just,
I'm just going to not.
Okay.
So yeah, so it is there.
Now, I can actually see it and if I go ahead and move out, let's see
here.
So yeah, it looks like that actually does work.
Just fine and those rooms are now being created, so I can actually
look and verify that that's actually true.
However, like I was saying before.
Okay, so we do still have a problem now, which is that we don't really
have, however, any
We don't really have any concept, though that rooms are special in
that way.
And so I'm not sure what we want to do about that, right?
So let's let's take a minute and think about that, I can turn off the
volume stuff here.
One way to do that.
Is to just end.
In fact, I guess now, I think about this kind of interesting.
One way to do that, would to be to, you know, sort of use brains for
this purpose.
So we can basically say, like okay, walls are all participating in a
particular brain type.
So every time you get a wallet gets added into a brain slot.
I'm not sure I remember.
In fact I don't think we do that would do some interesting things with
bringing that would create like a brain limit.
I guess what I'm saying is here.
So we have brain types, right?
And brain types are just the things that it's like, which AI
controller you want on your thing.
And so, you can imagine reusing that effectively for doing the gather
for rooms, right?
It's sort of like a brain for the camera, if that makes sense.
So if for example, I said, oh, There Was, You Know,
A room brain.
And so anything that was a room.
Got added to the room brain.
In theory that would work, the thing that it creates is it creates a
dependency here where you're basically saying like, Okay, now the
maximum number of rooms that you can have in a simulation region, is
proportional to the maximum number of slots in a brain.
She don't know, is really something you want to do, right?
And so I'm a little reticent to go that route, even though it is kind
of convenient and nice.
So it kind of again it feels a little bit like that it wants to be
more of a First-Class citizen that I don't really know, right.
It feels like it wants to be something where the where the world has
more knowledge of what a room is and doesn't have to come at it quite
so sideways.
And so I do worry a little bit about making it that in line with how
everything else.
it's got a nice attraction to it in the terms of well it just reuses
stuff that we already have, but I don't necessarily like
I don't necessarily like some of the implications there so I'm not
really sure that's I find this to be a really tricky one.
I'm not sure how I want to do that.
I think it makes a lot of sense for the rooms to be stored as
entities.
I just don't know if it makes sense to overload, the brain concept for
them.
So I'm kind of thinking that maybe more what I would prefer there is
like the simulation region.
You know, itself.
Keeps a separate list of rooms.
So anytime it on is going to unpack a room, it, you know, is going to
record that and it's a separate marker.
In the end of the thing that says, you know, this is a room.
So, let's take a look at what would happen if I did that.
I'm just curious to know because let's take a look at all the people
who have to actually deal with this as a thing.
So, you know, when we're doing update and render entities here, we
sort of do this, this stuff with the, you know, with the typical floor
height and that's used for computing, sort of a like per level.
Fogging effect that goes on there, that won't have to happen anymore.
With a z buffer, right?
Because once we have the Z buffer, will be able to just have actual
fog that that goes down with a, you know, in a regular kind of Z
fashion.
And so I'm not sure that that's really all that necessary.
So I don't know that anyone in here is actually ever going to Care
again about that particular piece of information, right?
We don't need any look, we were going through extraordinary lengths
here to try and sort entities into floors properly and then have those
floors, you know, get out.
Outfit separately and all these are sorts things but we don't really
need to do any of that anymore.
We can now just do two passes with the Z buffer and be done, right?
So it's definitely in the kind of thing where I'm like L all right
like you know we can we can face some of this over to the GPU as
something that it has to deal with and then we don't have to really
deal with it much at all.
So you know again floors in that sense aren't particularly necessary
in any way either.
So it's it feels like it's really mostly about
The camera is the reason that we actually care, you know.
And the only person who'd really be caring about it is when we go to
do that camera update,
So it's kind of like we almost don't need to know it all in a lot of
cases.
And that does seem.
That does seem pretty likely.
So taking a look at update camera for entity movement here.
Like, let's imagine what would happen.
Suppose that we just brute force it, right?
And then we weren't even doing anything particularly interesting
suppose that we just did a for I Loop here and said, okay let's look
at all the room and two teas that are in this simulation region
because you can look at what's Happening Here, Right?
You look, your we're looking to see if you're outside of the room.
You know that you were that you were
Last in.
So, you know, you can see here, we're saying, is the entity.
Why outside of whatever that room apron is?
And when it's outside of that, you know, that's when we start that
that transition, right?
I feel like we could just do looping over the entities and find the
two closest rooms to wherever the entity is, and then just do the
interpolation that way, right?
And this would be the only thing that ever actually cared about that.
And
that's pretty compelling to me because then we would literally not
care ever about this.
We wouldn't have to keep them in the brain at all.
We can still use the brain type for this purpose.
If we wanted to, but we wouldn't ever have to actually add them to the
brain set.
And we could also, if we want to have an out-of-band place that we
stored those
So, yeah.
I mean yeah I guess I just think say like let's let's imagine
What this would look like.
So imagine we said there was a type brain
For room.
And we say here like hey by the way of these are special types.
Which are used to Mark special entities.
So let's say we didn't have a particular brain type and that was brain
type room.
But when we begin the world change,
And we come through and repressing the entities, instead of actually
creating a brain for this brain, we actually do a test for us to see
whether or not the brain type.
Well actually the brain value can just be 0 and the Brain type
Will be set to room.
And that'll just work because it won't try to unpack the brain if the
value is 0.
Right?
So that's perfect, that's exactly what we want.
So, that's kind of cool, right?
So that means we can just use this to Mark people, and it's
essentially a free entity typing system.
If we need that for certain special types, I guess, I'll put this down
here and that way I can Mark those but I can still leave the brain
slot as zero.
So for example, in here, when I actually make one of these in add
standard room,
I can just go ahead and say, well, when I set this entity, I'll just
go ahead and set the brain slot.
I believe that's just the stuff down here.
You can see how it's normally done, right?
So if we take a look at this, you can see.
We do brain slot, and I don't actually want any of that stuff to be
happening, right?
So brain slot, I guess I can just leave it as zero, brain ID,
See here.
I want someone who's going to set that.
How are we setting that before?
Like the monstars use them, right?
Yeah it just uses add brain.
Yeah, so that actually works perfectly because then we're doing like,
okay the brain ID.
We could just be like
something like special brain ID and then we can just say like, okay,
let's say what we want, the specific type to be so let's make that
Brain type rim and when we do yeah you can see it.
We got no brain here, right?
And when we do that, I could say special brain.
and I feel like,
I feel like when we do add brain, that's just it right those brains.
Where is it actually getting that type from when it does those, the
brain slot, right?
So I don't really want the brain ID.
I just I want the brain slot is the one I actually want.
So this is really a special brain slot is what we're actually looking
for, right?
Yeah.
And so when we're talking about the brain,
They're what I really want to do is say like okay I want a way to get
a special brain slot back which is like special brain slot that and I
just say brain type that makes sense.
And it initializes that.
Like so, and so that means even the index would be fair game for us.
We could set the index to something here.
If we cared about it, we don't really care about it.
In this case, because we don't have any actual information to store
there, but you could actually store additional information are if you
wanted to.
We just don't happen to want to.
So if I do that,
Brain, touch you, it's okay, it's fine.
If I do that, I now I shouldn't break the brain system at all, because
it shouldn't even be getting used.
It's just kind of stored there as a piece of information that we can
use as sort of a demarcation, right?
And so when I take a look at that,
And I guess there's really not necessarily since we are talking about
doing a new stuff.
Sparse, We could decide to move that out into a separate variable if
we want to later.
But for now, we'll just use it that way.
Inside the same region.
What I can do is say like okay.
You know, when I'm unpacking these guys, I can say if the destinations
brain slot type is, you know, one of these special types that I care
about, I can do something different here, right?
I can say,
When I get one of these, do something with it here.
So if I wanted to keep a separate list of rooms, I could I think I'm
just going to brute force it at the moment.
I don't know that, that's a great idea but I think I'm going to just
so I don't have to put a constraint on the number of these that there
are at the moment but we may want to
We may not want to do that for all time, right?
So if I take a look at,
some region when I'm updating the camera here for any movement, I
guess, what I'm saying is in here, we would just say like okay
Let's Loop over the entities.
You know, maybe we keep a separate list of those during unpack, so we
can Loop through the rooms separate, you know, as a separate thing.
Probably something we'd want to do, but
What I can do here is say like, all right, when I Loop through all of
these, let's just get the room, whatever the room, the player happens
to be in at that time, let's just get that.
Let's just figure out what that is and and call it a day, right?
So if I Loop through here and say, like, okay, here's the enemies,
I'm going to need the stem region here.
and all I want to do is say, well, okay, for all the entities that we
had,
I'm just going to look and see if I've got any room entities.
And if I do, I guess I just want to look to see is the center of the
same region inside that room because that would be the determiner of
which room I was technically in at the time I believe, right?
That's that's sort of the
The determining Factor there, right?
And I guess I don't really remember exactly how we were eventually
moving the camera per se.
I think it's just once we get past the apron for setting the new
camera P, right?
So
Yeah, you can see we only really do it.
If we get past that room, Delta
All right, so the room Delta here.
I guess we have it set to just be
Literally twice, what the or rather?
What that, actually, I think multiplies out to be.
Let me just double-check.
That's true.
So, 1 point 4 times 17 2015.
Yeah, so it's a little bit bigger than the current the room.
Delta is just a little bit off from the actual room size.
So, if we want to hear, we want to just say, all right.
Let's suppose we were going to compute.
All of these things from the actual information.
We get
About the room itself.
So we, you know, we want all of this information, but we want to get
it dynamically.
So if we take a look at that all of this stuff,
Is basically dependent information, again.
I don't think we actually want to do this, after we're done.
I want to make the camera move a little bit smarter than how it's
doing right now.
But just for the moment, this room, Delta piece of information here is
really just, it's just the size of the room, right?
So if we search through here and found a room,
That was the, that was included the Simulation Center, right?
And remember, I know the Simulation Center because it's 000, right?
It's always the origin of the of the simulation.
We always all things have been mapped into that space.
So if I was to Loop over the Collision region of this thing or and
really I could just even probably use a Point query test here because
we've got say you know
The overlaps rectangular, right?
And you can kind of see where we pass Collision volume in a rectangle
and we look to see whether they those points intersect.
So this is in rectangle, function is exactly what we need for that
purpose, right?
And so, that's really all I'm talking about here.
So, what I would do is I'd Loop through all these entities.
I say, for every entity, if it happens to be a room type, you know, is
is 0 in it, right?
If point or entity contains point, right?
And then I just passed the center of the simulation region which is
always 0 0 0, I passed the entity in question.
And once I figured out whether it contains that point, then I'm done.
Now, I know the room that we're actually in and so I could say room
In room 0.
In fact I can move this down here now and I can just say, like okay in
room equals test,
Once I knew the room that I'm in, then I just need to use the balance
of that entity to figure that out.
And in fact I could if I want to make that be a property of the actual
Collision test, it could return which of the rectangles it was
actually in as well.
And I could just say that information because if you take a look and
see isn't a rectangle, see
See.
so inside here, I believe we typically have to well
Okay, so we do have the total volume.
So I guess what we can do is just always use the total volume.
All right.
That's fair.
So I guess we could just always say like.
All right, so the room, Delta itself is just a total volume for this
entity, right?
So we just say, you know, whatever the in-room total volume is that's
going to be whatever the room, Delta is now mind you at this point, we
also have the problem of, well, we may not have found one and if we
haven't found one, we probably just want to leave the camera where it
is, right.
We may also want to just do an assertion on that.
Yeah, we'll see how it goes because probably there isn't a time when
that should really be happening.
So when we do this and we Loop through entities, we go.
We see if we find one, I guess, I can say any overlaps rectangle.
I suppose, we could actually just reuse this function if you wanted
to.
I don't know that I really want to.
But if we did,
It would just look like this.
I have here, a thing which says here is a volume.
I want to know if an entity overlaps it.
So I give it the I can just give it the volume, that's a 000 volume.
It's like the null rectangular, right?
It's just whatever the nothingness is, right at the center of the
simulation region.
If the, if that if the entity region encompasses that then that's
technically they're right?
again, not really necessary but it's just to reuse this function at
the moment since, you know,
No, reason not to while we're starting to get things going.
So total volume for entities.
I guess.
I don't know.
It has an offset p and a dimension.
I'm kind of interested to double-check that here.
So here's one of the overlaps rectangle and we're checking to see if
something is inside a rectangle.
You can see that it uses the offset P there, right?
So if I want to do the find the room, Delta I just need the size of
this thing.
So all I care about really here is the dimension
for the time being.
And so this now needs the same region or to do that update step.
Looks like this comes first.
All right, so I think that's about it and like now we're going to have
to do actually debug this, but I'll probably save that for next dream,
right?
Because, you know, right here, we should be going outside.
And presumably, that's not getting picked up properly.
Let me double check to see where we're at.
In terms of that, there we go.
Yeah.
And you can see it's not actually able to find one.
So let's just do a quick to do this will be a really simple to bug but
we'll save it for next time because I'm going to want to kind of go
further into this as well at that point.
And let's go ahead and go to unite.
Okay, so this is a three-part question 1.
Do you ever work on large multi million lines of code, code bases,
like, Chrome, GCC unreal, etcetera, the full build Dev process.
You've been using works for small projects, but how do you scale?
So I guess I would say that that's sort of a
I guess that's sort of a, that is not something I want to do, kind of
a question, right?
So it's like, in my mind, if you have a code base that you cannot
compiled in, you know, 10 20 seconds, then I probably wouldn't work on
that code base, right?
So if you took something like Chrome or GCC or unreal or whatever I
would just point out, lots of stuff about that, right?
So first of all, if you have something that for some reason actually
does
Have as much complexity as it would as would require multiple millions
of lines of codes which by the way, none of those three projects do.
Like I would not consider Chrome or GCC or unreal to necessitate that
many lines of code.
But let's say, you do have something, which legitimately the problem
with it, is that it necessitates that many lines of code, not just
that, there are more lines of code than there should be in the
project, which is the actual
I mean a lot of those cases, right?
For example, GCC, you know, there are compilers that are incredibly
tiny.
So the way I would write a compiler is I'd write one that was much
much smaller than GCC.
I consider the size of the code to be a actual problem and small code
to be a feature.
So I don't consider it outside the scope of an answer to say that's,
you've you've made a mistake up if you've gotten to that situation,
right?
But let's say you did get into that situation and you're you know,
maybe you're coming on in your you've just been handed you see see and
you have to use it right?
I didn't like the very first thing I would do is break it up into
modular pieces that I can build and work on separately, right?
Because if I can't rebuild the whole thing in a reasonable amount of
time, that's a huge, huge, huge problem.
I would consider that the most important problem to solve on any
project immediately is, if you can't build the whole thing in a
reasonable amount of time.
Because it just it really severely affects the ability of programmers,
to make large-scale changes to the architecture.
They just can't do it, they won't be able to do it.
If it takes you know 30 minutes for them to see what A change is like
that, it touches a lot of things.
And so I just don't feel like that's a, that's a
A way to program that that is sustainable.
So that's what I'd say.
So I would actually turn around and say if I can't build a project
with the unity build, basically right with the ability to just like
build it all as one build and go.
If that's taking 30 seconds, a minute 10 minutes Heaven, forfend, it's
a half an hour, then that's problem.
Number one, like that is the thing.
I will be working on until that's not true anymore.
I would not even dream of touching any other feature of the code base.
So, I solved that problem, it would be problem.
Number one,
So yeah.
Let's see.
So / 2 Y is past video archiving disabled just because like I did not
like the fact that those videos were being used because the and and
capped basically like the the on stream like discussion stuff, that's
not part of the official recording is not supposed to be permanent,
you know, it's not supposed to be a thing that that
Gets archived.
And so I had the twitch replay stuff enabled because you know people
had been using it that way but then you know, it's gotten to the point
where people
Like, saving those, or clipping them out, or doing something that, and
that, that's not the intention of them.
So, the fact that I couldn't really keep that from happening means
that I just turned it off.
I mean, in the closet, the back will actually close.
I know, I'm just happened to be close to the back wall.
Sylvester's too.
I don't know if unrelated questions are allowed, but how do you stay
so focused on your programming and are so efficient.
I guess, I don't know, I don't think I'm particularly efficient.
I certainly don't feel particularly efficient on stream because
talking a lot about stuff, kind of slows things down to, I guess I
would say,
you know, don't don't allow yourself to do other things other than
work on the, on your code, on your computer, is a really good way to
do that, right?
Like staying focused on things, is kind of about not allowing yourself
to go.
Do other things while you're while you're essentially working on
programming and you know that's actually something that amusingly
enough doing something on a stream actually helps with a little bit
because if everyone's watching you program, you're not going to go
like read the internet or
Right?
Or at least, hopefully not.
So that's, that's one thing that's kind of helpful at work.
Normally I just don't my computer isn't plugged into the internet so
the only and I don't install anything on it.
So my computer is literally nothing other than a compiler, the
debugger and my code base and that's it.
It's not plugged in the Internet.
It's not plug in anything other than the the backup server, right?
And that's just because yeah, like there's always a temptation to go
do something else and so I find the easiest way to not do something
else.
It's just not have the ability to something else and you know, that's
what it was like growing up because there was no internet, you know.
And so you know, it just tends to be about trying to maintain good
habits and I think anyone can learn to focus and stay focused.
Sometimes it requires
Paying attention to things that you wouldn't normally pay attention to
like, for example, making sure that you things that you would never
necessarily think of can be important.
Like, for example, what you eat, like what you eat in the morning, you
know, maybe you work better on a cup of coffee and you know, some
bacon or something like this and how much you eat is important.
You know what your blood sugar is what your mental state is, that sort
of stuff is affected by these sorts of things.
Getting regular exercise stuff like that just you know, maintaining a
healthy sort of environment for your brain, in terms of both, what's
on your computer, what you're doing with computer.
But also like physically also helps a lot, right?
If you're feeling tired all the time,
Or you're, you know, you're, you're having a sugar crash or whatever.
Those are bad things that would that make it hard to say Focus to
I think the sweet up is due to wrong, offsets of the simulation
regions, for the multi-threaded tasks.
Use the tile size for calc.
Not the chunk room size that could be true.
Yeah.
Like if those are not.
Well I don't really know.
Yeah but yeah I agree with that because I didn't I'm not particularly
careful about what was going on there since those are made up.
Points.
That you intend to use 3D will the code support software rendering?
Yeah, I think so we may not support all the features but we I think
we'll probably still keep that path updated.
Is the career advice episode.
Upload it anywhere?
I'm having trouble finding it.
It'll be up.
It all three parts will be up shortly as a blog post and they'll also
be on the hand.
I mean, they'll still be on YouTube, but they'll be in a blog post to.
So all three are kept together and with links, I'll be copying and
pasting links from the things people wrote In.
You said, you want to remove the notion of rooms layers from the
drawing routine but don't you still need it for fading in the room
above you?
I don't believe so because like I said, since we're going to move to
3D will now be able to use the standard tricks we would have used
their which is to say, all we have to do is just go like okay you
know,
There's a certain height above the camera.
What when we set the camera in this update for camera routine, we know
how high that the ceiling of that room is and that'll just be a
property of the camera that we then use with the z-buffer to do two
passes, one pass with for everything in front of that Z level, and one
Pastor everything before it into two separate buffers.
Right?
So we now kind of have the ability to do a
Of of sassier things.
Let's see, posting me.
You said that 20 seconds to build is a reasonable amount of time.
Well I wouldn't have to say it's a reasonable amount of time.
I would say that it isn't necessarily the amount of it isn't.
The amount of time where I would, automatically think it's a problem.
Right?
So, if it takes 20 seconds to rebuild the entire project, I wouldn't
necessarily stop what I was doing and go focus on that as my primary
problem, right?
I like to keep things much faster than that, but I can live
It in that range, somewhere around a minute.
It becomes obviously, the biggest problem you have right?
And you know where exactly that breaking point is is hard to quantify
the faster, the Build, The Better pretty much down to about somewhere
under a second.
So, you know, a bill that takes one s better than a bill that takes
two seconds, right?
But
At some point, a bill that takes 50 milliseconds is not better than a
bill that takes 100 milliseconds for the most part.
At least not in any way that I've ever been able to German.
So yeah, I don't really know how to quantify those things in any way.
Other than to say that there's an obvious Breaking Point somewhere and
I mean, you know, 30 minutes is obviously a disaster which is not a
straw man.
There's lots of bills that take over 30 minutes to rebuild the whole
code base and I that's just a huge problem, right?
So,
all right, last questions off topic will handmade con 2016
video-on-demand be on YouTube soon?
It's out of my hands right now, folks volunteered to edit the videos,
and they are editing the videos to combine the camera footage because
it's just a bunch of rock camera footages when they're done.
They will be posted.
But I don't know when that is
Come and see me too.
How long did the witness take to build?
I don't remember, but quite fast by comparison to most projects that I
kind of come onto that I wasn't in charge of like I want to say that
you could build the whole project in 30 seconds, maybe on a good
machine.
So you know was it as fast as I would like projects to be built.
No was it well within tolerable range?
Yes on the witness.
I would say.
The thing that I had much more trouble with was startup time of the
game and I think that was probably because I didn't really know enough
about how to do some of the artwork flow things.
So I usually ended up getting around that by having a
like a
Test level thing that I kind of built that I could load into, and not
have to go through whatever was having.
But there's I think the, the way that the witness was was structured,
there are several parts that I wasn't really very knowledgeable about.
And so, my experiences with it are not really representative of what
it would be like if you were someone who's normally on the team, but
I'm, you know, my recollection of building the witness was that it
was, you know, well with
Thin, the speed.
Of rebuild that would not be a problem at all.
And again, that's because John cares about this sort of thing, right?
You know, he, I don't think he would be super psyched if his if his
game took someone saying 5 to 10 minutes to build.
Like, no, it's nothing like that.
The witness was very fast to build by any modern game standards.
Like I said, a lot of them are just incredibly slow, you know, if the
you can build the entire witness engine and game in probably, you
know, I'm imagining the amount of time it would take you to build, you
know, 10 files of the Unreal Engine.
It's, you know, it's it was very sensibly architected for that.
All right, I'll go ahead and wrap it up.
Okay, thanks everyone for joining me for this episode of handmade
hero.
It's been a pleasure coding with you.
As always, if you want to follow along at home, you can always fear to
the game on handmade here a.org and it comes to the source code.
So you can play around with it and learn from sort of the sort of
stuff we're doing on stream.
We also have Forum site if you want to ask questions and a patreon, if
you want to support the video series, we have a schedule bot that
tweets the schedule at you.
And I'm going to be upgrading that soon to correctly handle weekend
stream.
Little bit better right now.
I kind of threw it manually because it was really built for weekday
streams.
And then we also have an episode guide.
You can go to if you want to catch up on stuff that happened before,
that's about it.
I will be back next week for more programming where we'll try to
finish up that room based stuff and maybe create some different sized
rooms in the game.
So we can verify that, that's actually working properly, until then
have fun programming, and I'll see you everyone on the internet.
Take it easy, everybody.