Hello, everyone, and welcome to handmade hero.
The show where we code a complete game live on Twitch every night,
except not the past two nights, because I was away on business and
almost not tonight because I was on a train back from Portland.
I live in Seattle and I was in Portland, Oregon.
And what happened was, I guess the train in front of us, hit a
pedestrian, which does not sound remotely Pleasant for The Pedestrian.
And I guess, when that happens, right, I mean, not a common Occurrence
at least, hopefully not a common occurrence, but I'm assuming that
there is a lot of stuff that has to go on.
First of all obviously you're going to have the whole Medical
Response, you know, I don't know if the person was all right, or what
happened but then I'm assuming
Being that in order for the trains to run.
Again, you have to inspect the tracks and the trains and all these are
the sort of stuff.
So they basically came on, you know, our train was stopped at Tacoma
Station and they basically came on and said, all right, look at right
in front of us, hit a pedestrian.
They called it a regrettable incident.
That was the word.
They use to describe it.
They were like there has been a regrettable incident.
And so, you know, I'm actually kind of mildly amused by this because,
obviously, I don't have
Any connections especially don't know who they were.
I'm not having like an emotional response or anything to it, but the
fact that they called hitting a pedestrian, a regrettable incident
already kind of hits.
My satire boat.
I'm like, well, yeah, I mean, that it's pretty regrettable that's
that's for sure.
Like, if there are things you're going to regret it be like the time.
I ran over that guy with a train is definitely one thing you might
regret but you know I'm like all right so I'm like okay that's fine.
So
Sitting in the chair, they finished making this announcement.
They're based like, you know, could be an hour or two delay you know,
we don't know, it could be a very long time so we'll let you know as
soon as we know something, they undo their their microphone thing
right?
They stop.
And I'm like, okay, I guess we'll be sitting here for a while.
15 seconds later.
I mean, maybe 30 seconds, right?
But, but less than a minute, they come back on and I'm thinking oh,
they must have like gotten word now.
Like they must have gotten some information back about like you know,
whether it was the person, okay, well the trains be able to run, you
know, whatever and they're going to tell us about it.
No.
They come back on and they say and this is an announcement from the
dining car.
The dining car is open so if anyone wants to get any snacks or alcohol
we have alcohol candy and so they rolled straight from.
We hit a pedestrian to this would be a good time for you to take
advantage of our dining car.
It's like we ran over somebody time for dinner.
I can't argue with the logic about the efficiency of the situation,
but I do feel like, at least in most cultures, I guess I don't know
that much about cultures worldwide, but in a lot of Western cultures
there's a little bit of period of mourning typically, that's sort of
implied for respecting people after you, run over them with a train to
be to say the very least, but you know what you going to do?
So anyway, I was lucky enough to have
My wife sort of tell me because I was, I was able to use the, she was
still back in Seattle and I was able to use the Wi-Fi on the train.
She was like, well, you know, there's a bus that goes from, like, not
far from that train station up to Seattle, like, maybe you can go
catch it.
And so, like, I did and, and I'm very glad I did because the train as
far as I can tell, from looking at the Amtrak site is still at that
station.
So, unless
SI streamed handmade hero over the Wi-Fi on the train, which let me
tell you.
If you think some nights we've had bad streaming problems from this
set up.
I don't even want to know what that would be like but that's you know,
that's a, that was the other option.
So thankfully that worked out.
I got home, okay?
And and handmade hero can continue.
Hopefully we will be able to get through this stream without a
regrettable incident.
And with that said, let's go ahead and get started.
So if you are following along at home and you have pre-ordered, the
game on handmade hero dot-org, you can go ahead and unzip the source
code today.
80, we're on day 81, right here.
So unzip date, 80 source code and that is the source code that I'm
starting with right now.
And that is what you'll want to follow along with at home now.
Personally.
I am feeling a bit drained from this travel Extravaganza.
I had been supposed to get in at 5:30 which would have had time for me
to relax and get ready to do some.
Handmade here are programming but that didn't happen at all.
And so I kind of feel like I would like to do something a little light
and fluffy.
It's just you know, just to sort of ease into it.
So I'm not I'm not heading straight from running over a pedestrian
with train to and happen.
Take the bus to get here on time.
Blah blah blah, all the way too hard Collision detection problem or
something like this, where I'm going to have to focus on things too
much.
So, I'm wondering if there's something in this to-do list here, that
would be a little bit lighter for us to do.
Maybe something that, you know, we could kind of play with it.
That wouldn't really be super serious, hardcore hour and be something,
maybe a little bit fluffier, and
And I don't know.
We have
In.
Well, this was kind of just our brainstorming or like Kirsten things
that we might want to do and so I don't know what, what I think I
might do.
I'm just gonna throw this out there.
What I think I might do is maybe we should try to add some sort of
drawing to the the ground because it's kind of weird.
Like when we don't really have much in the way of rendering and that
was fine because we're not really working focusing on that right now.
But we kind of don't have any real.
Real way of seeing the floor there.
You know, we kind of Drew in those trees to show the boundary of a
room, but we never actually Drew anything for the floor.
And so as a result, you know, you go upstairs, you go downstairs.
There's no real indication of where the floor is.
We're just kind of drawing some representative stuffs, so we can kind
of see, you know, a representational version of what's going on and
know that it's sort of working.
But that's, you know, that's not maybe, perhaps,
so interesting, so if we wanted to take care of that,
I was trying to think of what we could do.
That would be relatively simple and in the direction of the sorts of
stuff that will do when we go to the renderer for real.
And so if you remember what we've got in that art directory, there,
the stuff that's already checked checked in quote unquote, I guess
we're not really checked in but that's in the project in that data
directory, right?
That test to thing, I checked in had some of these, like, ground
Splats in them.
And of course,
I can't believe you them in Windows picture viewer because for some
reason it doesn't work.
But you know if if I edit with gimp and load those into to a
reel-to-reel image viewing thing, you can actually see that they're
alpha'd.
So that they're kind of like these ground Splats that are meant to
allow you to kind of build up a little bit of ground as you go, right.
You can kind of see that it's like a little bit of like this is a
little bit of like a stone thing but it's got
Some sort of transparency in it.
And, and here's another one, right?
That would go on top of that, that kind of smushed together to make
like a stone, a stone or dirt area, right?
Same with this one, and this one, right?
So they're just like a couple things that you could smush together to
make sort of an abstract, Stoney, kind of texture on the ground.
And similarly, I don't know why it opened that many versions of gimp
for me.
I really didn't need that many.
Leave.
There's like some grass Tufts that can go on there, right?
I'll go ahead and grab those up and also some grass that works the
same way as the stone right here are some some some Alpha grass
things.
And so, you know, if you think about kind of how these are meant to
work to just build a little bit of a background, if I was to cut and
paste.
Is Anna paint package for those of you who are, you know, familiar
with how these sorts of things work, right?
If I were to cut and paste this, so I cut and paste, you know, a new
one in here and make a new layer out of it, right?
I can go ahead and and sort of, reposition that layer and you can see
that when I do that, it sort of looks like if I go back and look at
the image.
Now it's sort of looks like I've extended the grass area out, right?
It's like, it's like a brush.
It's like a stamp right that I can use to make things.
Look kind of like an organic texture that goes for a while larger than
the original one was certainly and here, I'll add the other stamp
As well, right?
So here's that other stamp, I'll put that one over there.
Let's say and and maybe we'll, we'll duplicate this layer again and
I'll put that down here, right?
And so you can kind of see how like if I just duplicate these things I
can kind of make an area.
That's, that's kind of grassy but that isn't necessarily obviously
repeating.
Now, ideally, you're not going to do this with just two brushes like
this, right?
You know, ideally you're going to use more than just that, right?
Because you can already, sort of start to see, you'll see some kind of
patterns in it, if you only have two brushes and, and that may be a
little bit too much, but you can kind of see how that's meant to work.
And similarly, like, you know, if I start adding in the other brushes
here like this,
Oops, that's not right.
My gimp skills are, you know already in question here?
All right.
So you know if you add another one here, you can sort of start to see
how maybe you make an area, that's got some some Stone to it, right?
And just from using this technique, you can't necessarily get perfect
results.
There's a bunch of things that we'd want to do like we you know, and
again, using continuing forward on the stamp front, I could start to
even show you sort of a little bit with some of those look like
Right.
I can start stamping in some of these detail things here, right to
cover, like the boundary between them that sort of stuff, right.
Making a few of these little guys here, you know, that kind of come
around and, you know, you can start to imagine building up a world
this way.
And so the, the vision that I have for the vision that I have this is
sounds like some kind of a Silicon Valley, Ted Talk.
What I am planning to do
In terms of requesting stuff art wise is eventually in the full art
pack for handmade hero.
What we'll do you know like what we ship with the actual game is?
We have lots and lots of these kinds of pieces for making ground
escapes, right?
So we could put a bunch of stamps in and make kind of semi organic
feeling things that, you know, are able to look non-repeating.
But that's still have a reasonably high quality level.
And don't look like a tile map, right?
A tile map would have very
you know, rigid boundaries and look very repetitive and
You know, rectilinear because that's how it's constructed and this is
a way of loosening up those constraints and making it so that we can
have a little more freedom to make things feel a little more or a bit
more organic where you can't see the seams as much.
And you know, if we do it well enough and if the source art plays well
enough with it, you can kind of get to a point where it sort of looks
like someone hand-painted each individual screen instead of it
actually being assembled four pieces right now, you probably can never
get all the way there because
Cuz you know, a hand-painted thing can have a lot of little touches in
it.
That maybe it's too hard to reproduce with these kinds of techniques
without going overboard.
But it certainly gets you something that looks a lot more distinctive
than a tilemap or stated alternately.
It's something that lets your artists produce higher quality results
in less time than they would have to do if they want to use a tile map
because you could imagine still doing something of this quality level
with talismans, having tons and tons of tiles and being really
About how the tiles matchup and stuff like that.
Certainly there are artists who are very good at that but that's a lot
of work.
A lot of mental overhead, a lot of dealing with constraints that's
just a lot harder for artists to do.
And in some cases, there's things that they just can't do in that way
because it doesn't work out.
Right?
And without the basically, just painting everything and giving you a
you know, tile map, that was essentially just a series of tiles that
reconstruct, pre-made backgrounds.
So yeah, so that's basically what I want to do and so we already have
the ability to do alpha Blended Sprites and so although it will
probably tank our frame rate because we haven't actually written a,
any blink code that works?
Well at all.
And that's a tall efficient.
We could still make something that kind of built up some ground this
way, so maybe we should go ahead and play.
Out that a little bit because that's like I said, something that's
kind of light and fun, it doesn't really bring in any anything
particularly new.
It's just kind of a setting up some stuff to see how that's going to
work, and I do want to do that sooner rather than later.
And the reason for that is I would like to see what we want to do in
terms of pulling these into like Sim regions and stuff because I'm
imagining that things like this, we may still want them to go through
the editing system because
That allows us to use our spatial partition and all that sort of
stuff, but we may not want to bring them to the same region because
they if they're just background, we may not need them to actually do
anything.
Now, some things they want to go into the same region, some things may
not want to go into the same region, right?
Like these little Tufts of grass here, for example, maybe we want them
to go into the same region because as you walk by them they like
flutter a little bit, you know, where there's like you know they react
the breeze or maybe that's handled in like a different way.
And so
These don't go into some reason but they do go into some other list
that, you know, just has artifacts on them that sort of stuff.
And so, you know, we kind of have to have some plan for how that
stuff's going to go.
And so having some
In there now will allow us to make better architectural decisions and
it does make some sense for us to play with it in advance of doing the
rest of the stuff.
So let's go ahead and take a look at that.
So what I'm going to do here is I'm going to start by again, just
loading those in nothing, particularly fancy.
What I might do here is say well we have those loaded bitmaps.
I'm going to go ahead and make like to sort of arrays of these stamps
for now.
something where we're going to do, like a
Grass.
We had to Grass ones.
We had, I think, four stone ones, right?
And, and we had those Tufts, I don't know how many tests we had three.
One, two, three.
Yeah, I think that's right.
Yeah grass.
Zero grasses are one Ground Zero through 4 and I guess.
So we had we had rocks to we have these little rocks there, right?
Forgot about those, although I don't know that we really need to do
anything with those.
So, Okay, so we've got the
I guess, you know, is one of these is any of these like a decorative
rock.
Those are big.
Yeah, those are all pretty big rocks.
So I don't know about those.
So let's skip the rocks for now and we'll just use some of those
Tufts, so I want to load these up, right?
And again, we're not dealing with our asset streaming or any of that
stuff yet.
So we don't care about this code at all.
We just want something that will load them in and so we've got that
code already working here, right?
We've already got ways to load those bitmaps in, so I'm going to go
ahead and just load them in.
Again, just in the stupidest way possible because you don't want to
think about this at all, this is not important.
This is not code that will be used at all.
We will have some very different way of dealing with with art Assets
in the future fact.
That's one of our to-do items so there's those two grasses, a load
those in.
We've got those Tufts
I'll go ahead and load those in so, you know it if I was smart I'd cut
and paste after I added it to be correct.
So there's this Tufts, right?
To and lastly, we have the stones and I'll load those in.
Okay.
And
Let's see.
Oops, select paste bug there.
What would update program be without a cut?
Paste bug, though, at the end of the day.
Really?
So let's go ahead and and build that make sure that's all good.
That seems all good.
And so now I guess what I'd like to do is is let's skip let's let's
not bring anything unnecessary into the problem right now.
Let's just straightforward, see what we can do with compositing.
So what I'm going to do is I'm literally going to straight up just
draw that compositing right in here underneath before we do anything
else, right?
You know, we're going to we come into the draw Loop here.
This was our
Clear call, right?
This clears, the screen to that gray.
That's behind it now.
So, what I'm going to do is literally right after that and I'll even
just cut calves it off.
I'll basically just say like you know draw test or something like
this.
We'll just put it up there because I think we're going to want to kind
of save it as like a thing.
It's like, okay, this is how we sort of, when we were playing around
with this is kind of what we did.
So we'll do like a draw test ground, right?
And, and that'll just give us a little function here.
We can play in and then when you know since tomorrow we'll probably
get back to what we were working on with the Clinton detection, then
we can just turn it, it will just comment it out and it won't, you
know, won't get run.
So I'm going to have this group, this draw test count round function
and the first thing that I want to do is I want to have some way.
Of of looking at how these things composite together.
So I guess I just want to have that sort of that drawbitmap call.
In fact, I don't remember.
Do we have we only have one drawbitmap call yet that has the alpha
with it.
Yeah.
So we just, this is our only called, right?
And that's in screen space.
So those are actually using just straight up stream, core strip,
stream, coordinates screen coordinates.
Wow, so yeah, if we're just going to draw this looks
I also need that game asking buffer, which I did not pass.
I'll have to pass that.
And then I'm just going to draw a couple of these.
I'm going to draw the some of them will start, I guess, maybe with the
grasses.
And what I'm going to do is, you know what, maybe we'll just draw them
at some random locations.
So, we'll just draw a random grasses at random locations for now.
And we have that random number table, right?
We were doing this, this thing here.
So I could go ahead and just steal that for now.
And yeah.
And we can go ahead and pull that out later.
You know what might be nice to is to sort of make that random number
Stuff a little more systemic and maybe that's something we'll do too.
So you know what I'm going to do, I'm going to say that, that's
another thing that we'll probably do today to do Casey.
Make random number generation more systemic right and we might do that
real soon.
That might be something we do just as soon as I get this sort of thing
loaded here and drawing.
All right, so if I want to draw one of these grasses, I'll just screw
up, draw This Grass, I'll draw it at, I don't know, 100 100 for now
because I don't have any better idea of where I want.
Draw it.
And I want to draw it at full Alpha obviously, in fact, I guess I
don't need to include
Because I'm going to draw it full Alpha.
So, let me take a look here.
Draw test, ground is not take tips true.
Let's go ahead and pass that screen buffer.
What is this?
Ah, and we need to that loaded bitmap has the width and the height but
we
Specifically get the pixels out of it.
I believe.
Is that true?
I don't know if that's true.
Let's draw a bitmap dude.
Just drawbitmap take it takes a loaded bitmap.
Oh I just need to pass a pointer so that's all good.
So I think that should give us something where we actually do, see
that grass show up, and there it is right now, like I said, it's
always just drawing it in screen space, it's so when I move it just
going to move with the camera.
So it's gonna be the same
Place on the screen because we're not even thinking about how they're
getting pulled into the world or where they are yet, that's not even
on the table, right?
So now, what I'm going to do is I'm going to try just splatting down a
ton of those, and I want to see what that looks like, if I splat down
ton of them.
So, let's go ahead and take the random number generator here.
And when I say, random number generator, I mean not really generator
because all we did was use a random number table at the moment.
Random number generation is sort of on our to-do list of stuff to
talk.
About how you do it and to implement one.
So right now we're just using a table of random numbers.
So yeah, so I can go ahead and do this and grab one.
Out of there.
And I'm just going to say that, you know, we'll just we're in pixel
space right now which again is not particularly useful.
In fact, I guess, one thing.
Maybe we want to actually make this not be in pixel space so we'll use
that m 2 pixels for example.
So will actually make this this number B and M so we'll do like x m
And why M?
Or I could even do, let's see p just a position for the grass here,
right.
And so when I initialize this, what I'm going to do is I'm going to
try to initialize this, to a value that is going to be within reason,
right?
I want to pick random points on the screen to draw this grass and I
need to come up with numbers.
If we're doing our mirrors to pixel thing, you know, I want to come up
with numbers between like -
M, + 16 meters or something, right?
Or negative 20 meters in plus 20 or something like that, right?
But our random number generator, right?
Whatever the random number generator is is only going to produce
values within a certain range, right?
Because it's just, you know, no matter what we end up doing there,
we're always just going to have some random entropy that it produces.
And of course we do have a little bit of a problem here which is we
don't actually know what the range of these random numbers are we just
grab them off of random.org right there.
Just some random numbers that we got.
I don't even remember what their maximum value is.
But you can see just looking at these right, that there is no, the
high bit is never set in these, right?
So basically, like it's not the full 32-bit range of unsigned
integers.
All.
And in fact, I guess I could look here 0, x 7, 6 5.
So it looks like it looks like we never have any values that are going
to be higher than, you know.
Oh, X500, yeah.
It's in fact, they don't even use the first hex digit.
Right.
So there there somewhere, I don't know.
Can eat.
Can emacs's quick calc do this.
What is like one of these numbers in
In decimal.
Oh, it can't do that.
Oh well too bad.
I was hoping that quick calc might save the day there but it didn't.
But anyway point being yeah, these are relatively small.
So what we don't actually know is we don't know what the maximum value
of our random number table is but you know what?
That's not a particularly hard thing to figure out.
So I'm going to go ahead and figure out what the maximum number is in
there.
I'm just going to go ahead and say all right we've got a max value,
the max value is assumed to be zero at the
Set, which is, of course, the smallest value that you can actually
have.
I'm going to say that I've got a number index and that, that runs the
whole length of the random number table, right?
And then I'm just going to say that if, you know, for any given entry
in the table, whatever that happens to be, I'm going to say that if
the thing that I've got is less than that, then I'm going to keep it
right like so.
And so you know, if I go in and
And and actually run that code.
Now that'll tell me what the largest value is in my random number
table.
And thus, what the largest number is that it could possibly produce.
So let's go ahead and grab that break point here.
Hello draw test bitmap, there it is.
Let's go ahead and run through that and see what the max value is.
So there's that max value.
So I'm just going to take that max value and I'm going to put that
into our random number generator, right?
As a thing.
Thing that we know.
So if I go in here to the random number thing, I'm going to say you
know maximum random number.
Is that right?
You know Max random number.
I'm not a big fan of the all caps.
Why do you have to shout all the time?
So anyway
That's the maximum value that can be produced.
So, what we know then is, if I want to produce, write a floating Point
number, if I want to produce a float, and what I'm getting back as
these random, you went 32s, right?
That I know range from zero potentially, although I don't actually see
Zero there either.
I wonder what the minimum value actually is, I probably should have
done that too, huh?
Let's take a look.
You and 32 Min value equals Max random
Brr, right?
Or I guess I could even do this.
I wanted to be clever.
I said it to the maximum of the minimum.
I set the minimum.
To be the maximum.
It could possibly be so that anything that I hid in, the loop will be
less than it.
Which and then I'll just always take, whichever the less least value
is, I'll keep them to lose.
This is, by the way, a very common programming programming pattern, if
you have, never seen it before.
If you want to, just keep track of a minimum or maximum value, while
you're processing things, you just set an initial value.
That's the smallest thing or this, or the largest thing that the that
it could possibly be.
And that way when you go through, no matter what the entries are in
your actual set of values are comparing, you'll always pick out the
smallest and the largest of them, right?
So let's go ahead and run that and we'll see what the minimum value is
as well.
Let's go ahead and run that.
Oops, that probably would have worked.
I guess because our reload would have would have caught that but just
- well recompile it.
So that's the smallest value that there is as well right there.
Okay.
So those are, those are our
Hence we could just treat that one.
Small enough that we could just treat that one as 0 but you know we
computed it, you might as well leave it in here.
So there you go.
So that's our range.
So what I'm going to do is I'm going to say all right,
Let's assume that that we get back, one of these random integers.
And we know that at maximum, it's going to be, you know, this value
right here.
So if I want to produce a floating-point number, what I can do is I
can take whatever the value is that I would get back, right?
I can take that random number table entry and I can divide it by
whatever the maximum is, right?
So if I, if I, you know, move that up to a float and then I divide it
by whatever the maximum
You could have been, I'll get a number between 0 and 1.
That is how big it was within the range of the values that we get
back.
Right?
So that's a pretty easy way to turn random 32-bit integers into random
floating Point values.
It's very common right?
Nothing particularly fancy going on there and that's one way that I
could create a random point.
So that means now after I have that random Point, I've got a number
between 0 1, unfortunately,
I actually want, you know, if we assume that the center of the screen
100, for example, which is how we've been rendering stuff so far,
If I assume that the cameras pointed at 0 0.
And so what I really want to do is if I'm trying to you know put grass
around a central point or something.
I would want a number between negative 1 and 1 for example so that I
could multiply by some radius that I want to put things around based
on the point.
And so if I want to do that, I need to figure out a way to turn a
number between 0 and 1 into a number between negative 1 and 1, right?
And so that's again, pretty easy.
That's just scaling up the
Range and moving it, right?
And so the way that you typically think about these things again, it's
second nature for
When he's been programming for a while, but if it's not the sort of
thing that you do, you might not be familiar with it.
So I'll just, I'll just draw it out quickly for people so they can
see.
So, there's day 81, right there.
And so what we're doing here is we're saying
Okay, we have a number that's mapped between 0 and 1 so it's in here,
right?
And here is my my number line.
And what I want to do is I want to take that and I want to transform
it so that instead of being between 0 and 1, it's between negative 1
and 1, right?
So it actually occupies this range
Yeah, so there's a couple ways, right?
You can think about doing this, the intuitive way that you just do
after you've been programming for a while as you go, okay.
This range is twice as large right.
How do I know it's twice as large?
Well the maximum minus the minimum right is 1 minus negative 1 that's
the range.
You know it goes from negative 1 to 1 which of course equals one plus
one or two.
So the range is too.
In this case the range was 1, 1 minus 0 is 1, right?
So I know that it's twice as wide that interval.
So the first thing I'm going to do is multiply it by 2 to get it so
that the range goes from 0 to 2.
So now it's big enough, right?
So I'm going to multiply by 2, then when you to do is just shift it
down so that it lines up with the original part, right?
And so, what I want to do is say, okay, we need to move it down one,
so I need to subtract one from it in order to line it up and then I'm
done, right?
And so you just intuitively would do that in your head.
And if you're in programming for a while, you're just like, oh, okay.
I've got some function that produces a number that's between zero and
one, right?
And so if I wanted to make it between negative one and one, I just do
two of it - one and that now equals a range of - oops of negative 1 to
1, right?
So, I mean, I can't really say, I don't know why these are the sorts
of things that programmers, just end up doing in their head.
I think it's because you do him.
So often, you just end up.
Yep.
That's that's the way my brain just automatically does it.
So I don't really sit down and work out the math for doing things like
that, because you've done it so many times that you're just used to
it, right?
And so you could if you're doing things like this and they're a little
too complicated for you.
Like maybe not this one, but something that's slightly more
complicated.
You can choose to work out the math, a little more explicitly, right?
You could say, you know, something that would give you.
I would give you some indication of what it was going to be.
Like you could say like you know, I have an f of x and I want it to
map to this negative one to one thing.
Right?
And you could say like all right, what I know is I want F of 0 to map
to -1 and I want f
Of 12 map-21, right?
So here I'm saying I'm saying I've got this interval 0 to 1 and I want
it to map that way, I know, to example values, right?
That of what it is that I'm that I'm inputting into this function,
right?
And so over here, whereas I did it sort of like where I was I just
kind of read it off and did it by rote.
I end up with an equation that essentially is just 2x minus 1,
whatever that input function was right?
So we'll call that thing X because I wrote it as f of x but really, I
don't even know why I bother doing that.
It's not really an f of x.
It's just the random number 0 to 1 range, that comes back.
So we ended up with a thing that was 2x minus 1, right?
That was the actual equation that we were going to use and that's the
Thing that we would type in right here.
But if we didn't know what that was once we have this, we do have to
essentially points defined on whatever our function is.
And so if we wanted to we could make up an equation and and see what
we solve for.
We could we could sort of see what it tells us the result is and it
sounds a little weird, but I'll show you what I mean.
mean, so, all we have to decide is what what type of curve
We want, right?
Right, like, what type of curve do we want this thing to take?
Because we've set to sample points.
So we could use those two sample points to figure out what the results
of what the resulting function that we want actually is, but we
haven't said is what happens in between, so we've said, two points is
what it is, but what happens in between.
So all right, you told me that when I input zero, I want it to come
out as negative 1.
When I am put one on to come out as one.
But what happens in between is it, you know, a
Is it just a linear progression between those two?
Is it a parabola, right?
Does it get like, is it slow and then fast and then slow, right?
And you can imagine if I drew the graph here where I said, all right,
I've got that and just to be a little more explicit.
I'm sorry, I'm not, I feel like I'm not really communicating as well
as I'd like to just to be explicit when I say f of x.
So I know math can be daunting right when I say f of x.
What I'm talking about here,
Is the function we wanted to find, right?
And I feel like the reason I confusing is because I was using f of x
up here.
So, let me just recap clarify, just to be absolutely cementing it,
right?
So if f of x is the function we want to find, right?
This is the function to find.
The X in here.
The thing that I'm plugging in is that output from the thing we
already have.
So we have a number between 0 and 1 and we want it to go between
negative 1 and 1, right.
And
X.
Is that zero to one number that we're trying to transform that that f
is transforming into the thing that we actually want.
You know, that goes from negative 1 to 1, right?
And so if you take a look at here, you know if we were to plug in X so
X goes from 0 to 1.
That's what we're saying and we were to look at what happens to f of
x, right?
Where this is let's say.
To do.
So this is one, this is like .5, and this is negative 0.5.
And this is negative 1, right?
So we're looking at what's going to happen to this this function that
we want what I'm saying here is well, okay, we've defined what happens
at x equals 0.
We want it to be here, and we've defined what happens at x equals 1.
We want it to be here.
But now, what we need to tell math in order for math to help us is
what happens in between.
Does it look
Like this, does it look like that?
Does it look like this?
Right?
You know, what is the shape of that thing because math could produce
all sorts of things that could produce a thing that looked like this,
for all we know?
Right?
So we need to give it a little more information and the way we give it
that information.
Like, what determines that is?
What does the function look like and specifically, what is the degree,
right?
The degree of the polynomial.
And if you remember from your math classes, which
Really, you've had at some point back in grade school, whatever your
algebra class was degrees of polynomial is, like, if I have a function
in X, then the degree is like, what's the highest power?
So, you know, if I've got an x to the fifth plus x, to the fourth plus
x, to the third plus x, to the squared plus X, plus a constant, and
that's my function of X, right?
Then, I would say that this was degree five, it's a fifth order.
We often say, right?
It's a fifth order, polynomial.
And so what this determines, what that order is, that determines how
complex the curve is between those two points, right?
When that I'm asking for, if I say that I only have a first-order
thing, I've got X plus C equals f of x.
Then I've got just a line that goes between them, right?
But if I was to say x squared,
Plus X plus C.
Now, I've got a parabola that goes between them, right?
So it could have like this kind of shape, right?
So hopefully that all makes reasonable sense.
That's sort of what we're talking about here.
So, in this case, I don't want any kind of complicated curve mapping
between my things.
I just want to linearly take 0 to 1 and map it to negative 1 to 1.
So it should be, you know, it should be a perfect.
Linear mapping between those two so that as I slide x from 0 to 1
smoothly, it slides from
- 121 smoothly at a constant speed.
To where we are in that space, right?
And so what that means is that I'm looking, I don't want any of these
higher orders in here, it means I'm looking at something that looks
like this.
And so what I do is, I set up an equation.
That's the most General equation, for, you know, a function of that
kind and I just go ahead and solve it, right?
I said these are my two points that I've defined.
So now, I know my f of x looks like some
Efficient times X plus some, you know, constant that's the simplest
form.
I don't know what these two are.
I have no idea, right?
I'm just gonna let math figure it out.
So I plug in my to sample points, I say that F of 0, right?
So f of x, that's going to equal
A time, 0/2 there, plus b.
And I said that, if I plug in 0, I want negative 1.
So that's going to equal negative 1.
Well, that means b equals negative 1, right?
I mean, zero times a is 0 so that means b equals a good one.
Boom, I've solved my first unknown that I had and similarly, I can now
plug in my second sample point, right.
I can say F of 1 is going to
Equal to a 1, right?
Because I plug in for x and then I already know what B is.
I know that b is negative 1 and that's going to equal 1, right?
And so if I have F of 1 equals a minus one, equals one,
that means a equals to write because I move the the one over the other
side and it lo and behold, I plug those two things in, I get f of x
equals ax plus b or 2x minus 1.
And hey, that's exactly the thing that I did in my head in a totally
different way but that's the function we're looking for.
So again, you know, like I said, kind of wanted to be like the stream
so you know, I want didn't want to do anything, we're going to be
getting too deep into the code so I figured I'd just go off on a
standing here and show you
How simple that stuff actually is.
Basically, you could do this for any kind of curve that you wanted if
you know, in a sample points and obviously you need more sample points
as you get higher up in degree.
Because for example, there's there's this notion right of degrees of
freedom
You could sort of think of them as where the more power you have in
your function, the more, you know, you got x x squared x cubed x,
right?
The further, you go up the higher that degree of polynomial, the more
degrees of freedom, it could be thought to have meaning, the more
constraints it can hit on here.
If I have an equation in X, well, it can hit two points but that's the
most, it could have hit because remember the equation got completely.
Determined just by.
Plugging in these two points completely determined, there was no more
degrees of freedom left in there.
There was no more slack, the equation was what it was.
So if I had said a third thing, if I'd said, f of 2 is 12, Well, we'd
be out of luck because either that's already redundant.
Meaning when you plug in F of 2, you do get 12 out of this.
But hey guess what?
2 times 2 is 4.
Minus 1 is 3.
You don't write or the true you know you're in a situation like that
where it doesn't
Equal it.
And then this is not possible to satisfy, so either, it's not possible
satisfy or it's redundant.
And that opens up whole cans of worms.
You can solve redundant systems and you can also solve
over constraint systems.
That's like, when you get into things like, you know, least squares
and singular value decomposition, and all these sort of cool way out
of scope for tonight, linear algebra things.
But when you're just dealing with the basics, what you want to
basically thinking about is just how many degrees of freedom you have.
And so, if you have a equation in X, you've got those two degrees of
freedom you can hit.
And if you went up further, like let's say, I went up to squared, I'd
be adding another point.
I
Hit right?
So if I went up and I said that I was going to do f of x equals, write
ax squared, plus BX, plus C.
So now it's a parabola right now, it's a thing that's going to look
like this or whatever like that or who knows what depends on the signs
of these things.
Then now, I know in addition to having these two points, I could hit
one more point, right?
I can pick one more point to hit and it would solve for the parabola
that curves just so right so that it could hit them.
And, you know, by the way, that thing I was saying about redundant or
or impossible.
If you looked at it on the graph, a redundant point for a third point,
you know, for if we were back at the f of x equals ax plus b, right,
that can solve this line that can draw a line between those two
points, redundant would be if I gave it a third point to hit that was
happen to be right on the line right now.
It can do it but if that point is off the line, yes, I could hit that
with the parabola version.
The simpler version, its it can't.
No way.
It can draw one line that goes through three points, right?
And so with the other linear, algebra techniques and stuff do to, to
work this out, is other techniques.
What they do is they allow you to specify other things you can do to
still solve it.
So like maybe you say, well, alright, I realized that there's no such
thing as a line that passes through three points.
But what I do want you to do, is, give me the line that passes the
closest total to those three points using some metrics.
So, the, I want you
To minimize the total distance between the line and the points or
something like that, right?
That would be an example of what math could do by elevating up to hire
more.
Math.
You can still you can still solve even though there's no way to do the
actual physical and you can still get Solutions out of these by saying
I'm willing to give a little bit up and the math will go.
Okay well will you tell me what you're willing to give up?
And I'll tell you what the best answer is and so that can still be
very powerful, right?
Alright, so that was a nice long digression.
I feel good about that, that kind of cleared, the pallet kind of kind
of, got me got me out of the train running over people's mood that we
were in when we started.
And so, what I want to do here is just just I'll throw that in there.
So that's what we said.
That was two times the input, right?
Which is this stuff laughs, I guess.
I don't even need to print size that, right?
It's two times that input minus 1.
That's what we solve for it.
Hopefully, we did the math, right?
Didn't make a mistake.
So that's the the input.
We want to basically do this some number of times, right?
I'm going to start with just one Rask index.
I'm going to start with one so we can make sure it worked, but then
we'll Crank that number up.
And then what we need to do is we need to transfer form that into
something that centered around the origin of the center of the screen
because it would start there.
And, and that's it gets the m 2 pixels in it.
So we want to do
This, we might call this actually, the offset not p, and we might say
that we had a center of the screen, right?
In the center of, the screen would be that buffer, width buffer
height, we've got in there.
I would have not hyped him.
So if we take half of those, that would be the center of the screen.
And then we can go ahead and just say, alright, we've got the point
for our grass is the center of the screen.
Plus the offset.
I scaled by that m 2 pixels, right?
And when we go ahead and draw that, we need to know the location of
it.
And so I'm going to go ahead and grab that location out right here.
And that should give us a grass at a random location, Right theory.
And there it is.
Hopefully, that's a reasonable random location.
We don't know.
And if we were to go ahead again and increase that number, so let's
say I increase this number to 10, we should see more grass show up
there.
Does it looks like we're not?
Oh right, we forgot to say how many meters we wanted our radius to be
right.
So this is a radius of 1 meter so they're going to be all kind of
clustered.
But what that does tell me is is that really oh, and also we're using
the center of the screen.
Which is we've got a couple more things to work out recently Center
the screen, which is we probably want the center of this like World
drawing here.
No, that's not true.
That's not true.
We are using the center of the World, Part were drawing.
So we're clustered around here and so that seems a little bit off.
But you know what?
We're also not accounting.
We're not, we don't have the center point of the bitmap.
So that's the other thing that we should probably do.
You is account for that center of the bitmap, right?
So let's do that as well.
So we have the bitmap center-right that's going to be equal to
whatever this this this grasp, it map is here, right?
So I've got grass 0, what were these called width?
So I've got the width there and the height thing, State grass height.
So we'll grab that bitmap Center and what we want to do now again is
displace out of the bitmap center.
Now, I don't know if we added that to the drawbitmap call.
I don't think that we did, did we?
No, we did not.
So we don't have an offset baked in there as far as I can tell.
So we're going to have to that ourselves.
So it's Center
That's the location that we're actually drawing it.
And then when we actually draw this here, we want to go ahead and just
place it for that bitmap Center.
So that we're drawing about the center of it now, right?
And so now I feel like that should be more centered.
I feel like it probably is although it's hard to really say this is
kind of an eyeball sort of thing.
Looks like it might be a little low.
I wonder if I had a bug in there.
Oh yes I used grass, one height.
That was a little bit of a typo there apologized so that looks more
centered.
So now I think we're closer there.
And now we just need that radius.
How big do we want to Splat?
How big of a thing about these?
And let's say 10 meters, I don't know how big that is.
We'll just say that.
That's a good amount there.
And so we just multiply that Offset, you know, that random offset by
thing.
And now again, these are going to be a circle because we're generating
random numbers inside a square.
So if we wanted to do a circular stamp down, we have to do some extra
work.
So right now we're doing a square stamp and so there we go.
There's our grasses, stamped.
And I don't know how far we can push this before our sort of bitmap
routine rolls over and dies.
I don't know if you can see that but we kind of at the framerate kind
of chunks when you get enough of those in there.
And again that's because we don't have any optimized drawing routines
of any kind there, but there you go.
You know, they're starting to look okay, they're they're getting stamp
down the way that we wanted them to be and so that's fine, right?
And we can keep on cranking that number up into just making it super
slow but you know, for our for our purposes, we don't care.
Look at how slow that is.
Check that out.
Out.
Oh the pain.
It'll be fun to write the renderer and start to tackle some of these
problems, but there you go, you know, that's what that looks like.
And so you can sort of you start to see this starts to create a grass
texture, even just from one and you can see.
So you can see kind of how that technique can be effective.
And again, when you look at this, the problem that you see is you see
those obvious patterns in it and that's why you kind of need there to
be more variability in the stamps that you're stamping down.
So you don't get that problem.
Right.
All right, so we've got some some random points.
Let's let's just make the radius of its smaller and the number smaller
so that we can still we can just see kind of what it looks like on
there and
There's our little grass patch.
And off we go.
So that's all good.
And so you know we've only got about five minutes left.
So maybe what I'd like to do now is just kind of clean a little bit
of, just make a couple little tweaks here to it.
And then maybe we'll play a little bit more with it tomorrow because
we just kind of got it working.
And what I wanted to say was, you'll notice there's a pattern that you
see kind of creeping in here, which looks like this sort of thing
where we're doing, you know, in fact, we did this twice
We had a coefficient and then we had two integers that we were kind of
lofting up there.
What I like to do oftentimes because I like to provide a Constructor
and again, I'm sorry when I use these terms, I sometimes I try to
correct myself so I don't actually use terms.
That means something very specific in other languages in like if
you're actually doing social room, I don't even Constructor a this is
just a function that returns a value but it's the thing that we use to
make Vector twos, right?
So whatever you want to call that.
I'd like to make one that makes a vector2 out of integers.
So if you pass it, you know like an in 32 X and Y or a Unit 32 X and A
Y and maybe, you know, you can even do, do something like this where
you can kind of say like, all right, give me integers.
And I'll do the cast automatically to make that V-22, locked it up for
you.
And so, you know, it's just this kind of
And the thing that cuts down on a little bit of that redundant typing,
which, you know, is something you want to do.
If you can, you don't want to be sitting around.
We don't get paid by the number of lines of code that we write
unfortunately.
So we can't just rejoice in our cutting and pasting.
So you know, that's just a, that's a pretty easy way to do that.
I don't know if we can just do this.
We may get into some hot water with sees casting rules.
We do that?
We'll try it first.
We'll see what happens.
But basically, the reason that I like to do stuff like that is because
then, you know, that,
Line becomes this line, which is a lot clearer, right?
That just looks a little bit easier to deal with right.
And so again we can do that here as well.
And that's just that's just like a little convenience that I find
that.
It's nice to have, right?
So that's good.
The other thing we might want to do just for fun.
I mean, there's no sense not doing it, just at the very end here.
We've got about two minutes left.
Let's go ahead and make that loaded bitmap sort of a parameterised
thing, so we'll call that stamp right?
And and will say that we're going to, we're going to grab the the
grass out there.
That's whatever the random number table thing gives us back, but it's
whatever the random number table gives us back mod to, right?
So we're just going to grab, you know, remember how we do this?
For putting putting out integers, we get a random number.
And then we we just say we only want, whatever it is, whatever the
remainder is after we divide it by the max number we want.
So we're going to
Zero.
We're going to add one and we're going to get back one of those loaded
bitmaps and then we can sort of say okay well you know will stamp
down?
Whichever random bitmap we picked, right?
It doesn't matter what it was.
That's what we're going to do and then we pass that to the function.
So now we've got something that's drawing both of them and you know
that kind of scales up nicely so that we can have a bunch of different
graphs stamps and they would all work.
Now we could also do
do something where we pick Stone stamps, right?
Equivalently we could say if random number table, random number and X
plus.
There we go, we could say that we want to do that.
We're depending on what's random number.
We did again doing the mod 2, so it picks one of the other will either
grab a stone, you know, or will grab a grass and I can do this.
I can make this a little more systemic to buy sort of saying.
All right, let's get that array.
Count of whatever the thing is that, we were picking in there too.
Right?
And that, that gives us, or should give us both the grass in the
center of the, what did I do?
It didn't do that.
Right.
If random number table, mod to get the grass.
Why am I not seeing any stone in there?
I'm not seeing any stone.
Did I make a foes?
Foes Pas.
We grab out the stamp.
We draw it.
What did I do?
And we mod by the number, but we never see.
So I'm just gonna go ahead and say,
say that equals Stone quickly just to make sure we've we did do our
Stone stuff properly.
Did we not?
We did not huh?
So do I have a typo down in the stone loader?
Maybe.
I don't know.
Where is that?
Where is that code?
There is our Stone loader.
We loaded up those stones.
So what did I do wrong?
You guys already know.
I assume it's been a slow day.
Oh well that would do it.
It ain't called Stone people called Ground.
So we just loaded nothing and we didn't crash because I guess when we
when we load nothing we just stuff a little bit map in there.
I guess I can't remember what we decide to do for that.
All right.
Well, that's how that goes sometimes.
But hopefully now we've got a mixture of grass and stone.
I still don't see any stone.
What is the deal people?
Round.
I'm gonna finish this up before we go to the Q&A Ground Zero Zero.
Ground.
It is called that, is it?
Not Ground Zero, Zero dot BMP.
So there it is and that assigns to Stone.
So it should get in here.
Why is it not, you know, you counted.
That's why you don't count your code chickens before they hatch,
right?
You don't count your code chickens.
Before they ask my stone is still not working.
Seriously people, seriously, that is where we are at
What's going on here?
There's the grass, the grass works fine.
But as soon as I switch the stone, I get nothing.
Nothing on that screen.
So why am I having trouble loading?
Whatever that ground is.
They're like, What's the problem?
People Ground Zero Zero.
Oops,
The test too.
So I'm going to step into that real quick because I want to know why
that ain't.
Why that ain't doing?
No Loudoun.
I don't see anything obviously stupid yet.
So I'm going to I'm going to see.
I want to know.
Oh, we can restart the game.
Duh loading.
Only happens at startup right?
All right, this time's a charm.
I'm going to count the code chickens before they hatch.
Here we go.
Bam.
That's what I'm talking about now.
We've got that stone in there, right?
Yeah.
And you know what the heck?
Just the top off.
Just a top.
It all off.
You know?
Why wouldn't you just, why wouldn't you just do this, right?
Why wouldn't you just go ahead and say, you know what?
Let's tough it up.
Let stuffed it because we've got the Tufts, you might as well use the
Tufts.
That's what I say.
So, there we go.
So, yeah, you know, it's not the world's most gorgeous looking ground
in the world yet, but you can already kind of see, you know, once we
kind of massage just a little, once we get this going and also
No, once we give you no gangster in the opportunity, to kind of like,
fill this up with cool Sprites and all that sort of stuff.
Like once we are further down that road, you can kind of see how it's
going to look cool, right?
Like, it's going to look a lot better than if I was just having a
little tilemap stamp down because it'll have this really nice organic
feel to it.
So I think we're going the right direction with that and and you know
more on that to come later.
But for now let's not belabor that point.
Let's just go ahead and and say that we will start the Q&A here on day
81.
Please.
If you could, please make sure to prefix your questions with Q: so
that I can see them.
And please try to keep your questions and stuff we did today or that
we were going to do.
I guess or that we had been working on but not on stuff that we're
going to do later or off-topic questions because we'll do those, we do
those in the pre stream.
If you want to ask an off topic question, please come back about 15
minutes before some scheduled start time on another day and ask it and
we will cover it then.
Cover it then.
Yeah.
Yeah, the fancy autoload, dll stuff.
So one of the things that that I said kind of at the beginning when we
were talking about that is I was like, here's the stuff that doesn't
do, right?
Doesn't rerun the initialization code.
You can't have pointers to functions or straight or hard-coded strings
in there and you know, that's just the way it goes.
You can fix that, right?
You can solve these problems.
And one thing that I will say is the problem that we had
Tonight wasn't really a problem.
You took a couple seconds to fit, I mean, well, a couple minutes to
fix.
It wasn't really a big deal, but the probably adds a night where it's
like stuff getting loaded that actually when we do the asset
streaming, that'll fix itself because the asset streaming would take
care of that it would look and see oh I don't have something it would
go grab it.
So really that part is not too big of a concern because really the
only reason we even see problems like that at the moment on for those
loading things is because we don't have real loading code yet.
So those two things will end up working together.
Either, if that makes sense where you'll end up having the auto dll
loading right now is actually weaker than it could be, because it's
not backed by any other systems that are helping it.
So, there's that,
Is there an art team working on this game?
There is an artist working on this game, but since I have to be so
slow, I can only program one hour a night.
If we actually had an art team working on this game, oh my God, they
would be so far ahead of me, right?
Like because because they can work 8 hours a day and I can only work
one right?
That's not good.
So there's one artist working on the game and and that's a pretty good
balance I think because I'm I can't go very fast because we cover
everything on the Stream.
So, you know, if there were any more than one artist and she's only
part-time there's any more than one artist, it would there they'd be
way too far ahead.
I'm always the Coco says Max render.
Number should be set to fix number 10, 000, 000, because episode 35,
when you went to random.org, you chose to Generate random numbers from
0 up to that number.
So, yes and no.
If you it depends what your goals are.
If your goal is to make a fair random number generator, I agree with
you.
You need to be whatever the range was for the random number
generation.
But if you want to fill space
Then know you want the random number generator to sometimes be able to
produce the maximum value, right?
Which in our case it would never would actually be able to do now if
that makes sense.
But so that's why I think it's actually better to use whatever the
actual maximum was, but yeah.
Obviously that wasn't a serious comment.
What wasn't a serious comment?
Pseudonym 73, what wasn't a serious comment?
But on top of question, comment.
Do you want to mention tangents when designing curves?
Probably not now because they don't really mean anything in the
context of the thing we were doing.
So I'd rather save that for some time and we're talking about like
maybe when we're doing animation because you know, it would be a
little more natural to bring some of that stuff in because there's a
lot of stuff we could talk about as far as solving for functions there
and it's like, we don't really have any thing to motivate tangents in
that example, because that was just a simple linear mapping, you know?
Panic 00, would you ever actually use a higher degree polynomial
interpolation aren't there better ways to make interpreting curves?
That are more stable?
So, okay, it depends what you're asking.
So I'll answer answer the question you probably aren't asking but just
to get it just so it's clear to everyone else and then I'll answer the
question that you are asking, I think.
But the question that you were asking is, would you ever use a higher
degree?
That the question that you literally asked that maybe you didn't mean
was, would you ever actually use a higher degree polynomial
interpolation?
And the answer is, there's no such thing as interpolation that isn't
hired.
Re polynomials or the one we used, right?
Like anything that you could name, pretty much.
That was an interpolation is a polynomial interpolation of some kind,
right?
Bezier curve, that's polynomial.
It's a its third order typically, sometimes it could be second order,
right?
B spline.
Same old thing.
That's a, you know, usually a third-order could sometimes be second
order.
There's there's rational and irrational ones, but
Still that order, right?
So yes.
Do you use those higher ones?
Absolutely.
The standard polynomial you use in most part in most animation,
interpolation is a x cubed plus BX squared, plus CX, plus CX, plus d,
right?
That's the standard that you're going to use the standard polynomial
form, right?
And you don't see it written this way because you see the terms
arranged for efficiency in terms of evaluating, you know, bezier curve
or something like that.
But but it's still a third order polynomial.
That's what a bezier.
Curve is a bezier curve as a third order polynomial.
Now, I'll answer the question that you were probably asking, which is
not what literally got said, right?
Because, you know, I know it's chat, right?
It's hard to actually be specific about the question.
It's not
Great way of trying to communicate, right?
So if you take a look at this, what I was talking about was solving
for those points that procedure, the the solving for endpoints
procedure, that is not typically used for interpolation.
And the reason that it's not typically used for interpolation is
because if you don't leave any extra degrees of freedom in your solve,
for something called fairing, which were getting kind of off topic
here but it's okay.
I mean, it's on topic of Dane printer, just not what we were doing
today.
Per se, if you don't leave any extra degrees of freedom, what happens
is your functions, do very undesirable things in terms of
interpolation.
So, for example, let's say you were going to use a third order thing
and solve for it the way I did.
So you have third order so you can specify for points.
Remember, linear is two points, quadratic is 3 and
And and cubic is for, it's always one more Point than the degree that
you have.
Right?
And you can see exactly why that is.
It's because there's a constant.
So you're solving an equation in however, many, you know, whatever the
order is, if it's third order, you're solving an equation in four
unknowns, coefficient, on x squared, I've coefficient on X cubed,
coefficient on x squared, coefficient on X and coefficient on X to the
zeroth power.
Right, there's x to the 0 here, which is the constant
X to the zero with is, of course one, right.
And so, if you take a look at at this and you say, well, I've got four
unknowns.
I can plug in four points, right?
So you go like I want it to go here and here and here and here now any
sane person takes a look at that and goes, oh no problem.
I'm going to produce the interpolation.
That looks like that, right?
Of course you would.
But what you don't realize is
Actually, there is no third order polynomial.
That looks like that, that passes through those three points, there's
some other polynomial that does potentially but not that not third
order.
The third order polynomial that passes through these points actually
looks like something ridiculous.
Like, you know, this sort of a thing.
I mean it will wouldn't have two bends in it but it's, you know, it's
like that, right?
That's the third order polynomial that actually passes through them
and that and that are not what you wanted.
You wanted a nice smooth interpolation.
What you got was something that hit the exact mathematical values you
input with.
Third order equation, and that's just a limitation of that sort of way
of stating the problem.
And so typically you don't do this if you are trying to fit curves the
things you use extra degrees of freedom and you do what's called
fairing, which is basically saying we're going to put into the solve
depending on how we choose to formulate, it mathematically, we're
going to put into the solve the notion that we do not want extraneous
wiggles, or things like this, right?
And there's a lot of different ways you can do that.
Like, one very simple way to
That is remember I was sort of telling you about that thing where I
said like oh okay you know maybe there's no way for a line to hit
these three points.
Remember I said that up above but I can formulate equations that give
me like a line that passes you know as close to the three as possible
so I can get that line out of it right.
Well, the same is true for more complex interpolation.
If I was to say, you know, I want you to use a parabola to hit these
points.
Well, a parabola is x squared.
Plus, you know, x squared plus BX, plus C, right?
Equals 0.
That's my, that's my Parabola, right?
So, if I'm going to solve for these three things, if I use again, more
advanced math and I you like a least Square, solver something like
this,
I'm going to get by plugging these in, I'm gonna get a parabola that
actually pretty nicely approximates those things.
Right.
And the reason that that happens is because the system now has a lot
but the math has a lot more information about what you actually
wanted.
Right up here.
All you told it was hit these four points and it's like, hey then I
hit him.
Right.
Let's go get ice cream, but it didn't know that you're in your head.
You were Imagining the smooth curve because nothing in the problem
statement, said, what smooth was?
You just had a preconceived notion, right?
And the math doesn't know what your preconceived notions are.
And so, one way to fix that, like a saying is add that information in.
And so one thing you can do is use more advanced solving.
Not like the straightforward literal equation.
Solving we were doing here ones, where you're going to solve systems
of equations that are more complicated than this.
Even though we're still only trying to find a parabola.
And what we're going to do is say let's specify those points.
We were trying to hit like these three points.
Let's say, but instead of it, then producing this kind of nasty thing
that maybe we didn't want that has extra wiggles or whatever, we're
going to add more points in so it knows that we want it to follow.
Follow this path, right?
And probably is probably a bad choice because usually The Wiggles a
parabola can only curve once, right?
So it's usually you usually need to be up in the X squared's before
you start to see those extraneous Wiggles, right?
But you can still have it says long story.
This all gets into a lot of Animation stuff that maybe we'll talk
about at least some of it only doing the animation stuff.
But so point being what you may have been asking.
And so I wanted to answer was was yet, do you want to do this solve
for advanced interpolation stuff?
And the answer is, no, you don't, you need to do more advanced styles
of solving.
But when you do those Advanced out of the sobbing, you're still
working with the same equations, you will still solve for this
equation.
You just won't be solving it as directly.
So, the answer to the literal question, you asked, would you use
higher order polynomials?
The answer is, yes, you absolutely would just not, you wouldn't find
them through the same route that I was saying, right?
Hopefully that.
That makes some sense.
Hi.
Let's see, let's see.
What sort of optimization would you do on that ground stamping?
Well, I mean the answer to that is we're going to see exactly what
kind of optimization I'm going to do on that ground stamping because
that is the way that I plan to do the actual backgrounds for this
game, as we go forwards and we need them to run efficiently.
So, the answer is, I will probably take two different approaches to
it, depending on whether we're running under Hardware acceleration or
not.
When we are not running under hard acceleration, what I'll probably do
is use a compositing buffer so that we only do the ground stamping
once for any area as it comes into view and then you know, so it was
sort of like a sort of a rectangular update scheme where as we scroll
around we only fill in the part we need and then
It comes out we as you move away we kind of jettison, whatever parts
we don't need.
So it kind of be like a tiled updating scheme so that we don't every
frame wreath stamp the whole ground area.
Right.
We're only re stamping a little new bit of it and
Probably stick that on an extra threads potentially like, you know,
that might be something that we have threads working on to speed
things up and that sort of thing.
Now, in Hardware Land, we have a lot more horsepower to play with.
And so what I'll probably do there is we might still use a caching
scheme like that, but it's on the GPU.
So that we're doing that stamping on the GPU into a texture that we
can reuse.
So we don't have to do all that building every time.
But a bunch of things we just won't blind in there.
Will blind them every frame, such as the little ground Tufts, so that
way we can have the grass, kind of respond to wind in that sort of
stuff.
So it's not pre composited in.
So basically, we'll try to look for opportunities to use that extra
GPU, horsepower to do something cool but will you know will have a
scheme that works for the software renderer so we can kind of learn
about how that works, right?
You are treating both ends of the random numbers, the same, but the
current system you can get one, but you will never get 0 because you
are not considering the Min though.
Perhaps you're not getting, you're getting close on scary.
Yeah, so again, like I wasn't really being particular about this.
Even the max one, I wasn't really mean particular.
I just wanted something that would roughly work.
So when we're going to will, maybe we could even just go ahead and
talk about the random number generator sometime soon and actually put
in a real one.
The real one is not going to have these little
Stations.
And so in theory, this is all kind of not that useful, but yeah, we
could easily say, all right?
If we know if we wanted to make this so that you could actually
produce zero out of it as well.
What you would do is you'd say, okay, this this, this equation here,
right?
Where I'm dividing it out.
So I'm producing a number between zero and one cure, but we know that
will never actually be 0 because we know that random number table
could never return a 0.
What we would do is say
Say, oh, okay.
Well, you know, whatever it does return, we subtract them in from
that.
So now that we know it does go from zero to the max minus Min and then
we divide by that new, you know, range.
So it'd be very simple to add that in.
But again, like I don't really super care about this at.
All right.
Now, and this random number table.
Table is not something we actually want to use in production.
It's just something to avoid having us have to discuss how to
Generate random numbers right now and or more, simply back when we
first put it in, but we will be talking about Generate random numbers
and then we'll have a random number generator which will have
More of an opinion about how it produces hours and we'll make sure it
can produce all the numbers between 0 and 1 that are floating point,
you know?
Let's see.
Do you plan on having things like dirt paths and if so would you draw
them using Splats and stamps?
Yeah.
I think we will draw them using Splats and stamps but again like
certain elements of the ground might have to have additional logic
like I mean, you know, like we're not going to just throw stuff on the
ground like this.
This is
To get things started.
So we're talking about things like a dirt path or maybe more more,
interestingly dirt.
Path isn't isn't perhaps all that useful because that's a very
calculus up.
But let's say Cobblestone path, something with a regular pattern on
it.
When we find ourselves wanting to implement stuff like that, we will
have to be more careful about how we are doing.
This stamping process if we want something that's going to be a
reasonable result, right?
And so, certain things are going to be harder to do than others.
Now, maybe what we'll decide as we just don't care, we don't want to
spend the time on that, we'd rather spend the time on something else,
so we won't do that for something.
But assuming we get to the point where like we really want a nice, you
know, Cobblestone path in here.
And, you know,
Randomly sort of throwing down stamps is not going to do that.
We got to start thinking about how we're really going to align things
and do things in a useful way.
They're right.
So, we'll look tack those we come to it, but we will still do some
kind of procedural generation for them.
It may just not be, it might not be such a free-form stamping as as
what we sort of started with here, right?
So your ground texture design is essentially Mega texture.
No, I wouldn't really call it Mega texture.
I mean, so there's a lot of elements to megatexture assuming that
you're talking about in Tech 5,
And we're not really using sort of what I would say is.
So we really need a way to take polls his what we need because I can
explain to you exactly why this isn't Mega texture.
But I'm not sure if that's actually something that's interesting to
people like because you know, Mega textures like this esoteric thing
John Carmack made.
And you know, explaining why we're not that.
Maybe not super useful but but yeah.
Based on the screen, it appears that you need to know math to do this
type of activity.
Is that correct?
That is correct.
Yes, you do need to know math to do this kind of activity.
Trial for any more on-topic questions again, for people asking stuff,
like did you learn higher-level Concepts from University or elsewhere?
Those are good questions for the pre stream.
If you want to come back tomorrow, you know, anytime before a
scheduled start time, we were at 8:00 p.m.
tomorrow.
So if you come at like 7:45 and ask questions like that, we do random
questions that aren't like that aren't specifically on what we're
working on.
Anything else?
I think I got everything.
I think I got everything so I guess I'll try to explain in three
minutes since there are no other further questions, the V on topic
question.
It was totally on topic of whether the ground texture sign is
essentially megatexture.
I'll give it a go for you.
All right.
So this is this was this was my plan over here and this is Mega
texture over here.
So, my plan was simply to say, all right?
We've got a screen, right?
And so I'm just going to assume that that screen is you know broken up
into chunks that I want to compute, right?
Like so on.
And I'm just going to say, alright for any given screen, let's see
what the chunks are that are available.
Let's do the chunks are that are visible, right?
So again, it's very much like, where we do for our entity spatial
partition, it's the same thing.
In fact, we could even tie it to that.
It could actually be in the tile.
Chunks we go.
And say, did we produce this one yet or not?
If we, and do we have it, like, in a cash basis or not?
If we do, we just draw it.
If we don't, we say, we need to generate it right?
We generate it and we store it for future.
Really, really simple, that's it.
So I'm just talking about looping through those things.
And then basically, you know, if you think about what we've got,
there's basically a cache of these things, right, entries?
And so we look through here and we say, okay to render this, we need,
you know, we need a b c, d, e, f, g, h i tiles.
Right.
And in the cache are a you know see G and H.
So it goes like okay got a render this tile.
Do we have that a?
Yeah we've got it, put it in there.
Great.
All right we've got be.
Do we have that?
Put it in there great.
And I may not even go that far, right?
I may just say all right, you know what, this is way simpler than
that, we don't have to worry about that.
Really, we've just got a screens worth.
So we know we have the screen filled on the previous thing.
We now know we moved some some amount so the you know, we moved the
screen.
So basically, like this is the part we have filled, but this is the
part we need to view which means that this part
Is still we still have.
Right?
So we just draw that part from before and then we just fill in this
part over here, right?
So it's like a dirty wrecked up to the scheme.
So we might even be simpler than even that right?
Mega texture has a lot more to it.
What megatexture does is megatexture says that essentially there is
just one giant image, right?
And that giant image is broken up into tiles.
So it looks sort of like this game at the head end but first what
happens is the you allow the GPU right?
Or whatever.
The rendering system is to First do a pre pass.
So you know so step one is you do a pre pass on the screen and you
draw everything, right?
So you actually draw, you know, the game with the hero and the little
Sprites and whatever.
They're right, you know.
I mean, and then you say, OK, when we do that drawing, instead of
actually drawing the color values, we actually want, instead, we just
draw, you know, IDs, we draw something that tells us what we would
have needed to sample from, in terms of textures, it sort of bitmaps
for each individual location, right?
So, this thing doesn't look at all like an image.
When we draw it in step one, it looks like a total
mess of colors, right?
Because those colors are actually IDs.
That tell us things, we then look through that and we say like okay
find all the IDS in the cash, right?
So we say anything that showed up on the screen then we look at the
cash you know this thing.
Same sort of idea ABC here, right?
So that part similar.
Find all of those, right?
And and, and, and use them.
But unlike this scheme, they're not actually laid out as a cash if you
will, they're laid out as an image.
So they're laid out in a scheme where, you know, they would they're
they're in there.
This is really hard to explain.
This is going to take this is going to take too long.
All right, so that's not actually true.
You could Implement, megatexture was, let's, let's just go with it.
I'm not going to say how they actually do it.
Normally because it says, it's actually laid out in a texture and
there's other consequence to it, but let's ignore that because that's
kind of cheap you think.
So let's say they were in a cash, right?
You find all the ideas in the cache but the key thing to understand is
unlike my scheme, where there's just some number of things, I was
saying, you know, there's 64 tiles in the cash and that's it.
So you found it you found it.
If not you throw something out of the cache and
Pullin you make a new one, right?
And you put it in there.
That's not what happens here.
All tiles are in the cache all the time in mega texture.
So you will always find that the the ID that you wanted, the thing
that you wanted will always actually be in there.
The question is just what resolution and so what Mega texture does,
you know, if you think about it it starts with like one 4096 4096
texture or something, right?
Or whatever the size is, I don't know what the minimum size is, maybe
it's more than that.
Maybe it's just 1226 by 256.
You could implement it, however, you want it.
It starts by saying when I start the game, I have one 256 by 256
texture, that's already like a tile.
In fact, the I guess you would probably implement that way whatever
your tile size is you'd say, I've got one of those, that's the whole
game.
Every image in the game is in this 2056 text.
If I 26 character, right?
So it's all packed in there, where like this one pixel represents like
a whole town or something.
The average color of like a whole town, right?
I'm not really exaggerating.
This is actually how it works and so then what you say is, all right,
the cash is not little tiles that correspond to things on the screen.
The cash is like, multi-resolution, one of the tiles, which may never
be evicted, is this?
We're tile that has the whole game in it.
So if I need to look up, IDs 63, right?
Well, if 63 doesn't exist at a high resolution and our or a low
resolution or any resolution, really, I can always fall back to
whatever Texel coordinated was in this to video scientific sector and
draw the thing at its average color for the region, right?
So there is no failure case for this, it just gets lower and lower
resolution, right?
And then when I do fail to find something in the cache at the
resolution, I wanted.
So I'll always succeed in finding it, but I might not find it at the
residence I wanted.
So this this idea of 63 also says, like, oh, it's 63 at a detailed
level 7, right?
I then say, okay, if fix something from the
That's like a least recently used thing or something like that and go
load this one so that soon I will be able to draw it at the right
resolution.
So, the cash ends up actually being this sort of multi this thing,
that stores things and all kinds of resolutions and you're constantly
sort of putting new things fresher lower lower or higher, resolution
things in there depending on how you are trying to manage that cash
out.
Right.
Does that make some sense?
So I'm sorry I didn't do a very good job explaining that I really need
a long time to swing by the mega texture but it's not really.
This this is much.
Fuller, then this is, and really, this is not a good choice.
Well, I might argue, this is not a good choice period, because there's
reasons that Mega texture is not a good design in my opinion.
Look, I don't think Mega texture was a good idea if that makes sense.
But even if you thought it was a good idea in 3D, I think you would
really say it's not a good idea in 2D because what this is designed to
handle is the fact that you don't really know ahead of time what the
bitmaps are that you're going to need because 3D so complicated in,
you're looking over vast Vistas and then down at the floor and all
these.
Right?
And so it's trying to manage that level of detail stuff.
Really cleanly, that's its goal.
We don't have that.
We're 2-D game.
We know that everything is basically going to be the same resolution.
It doesn't.
You don't get this sort of Longview distance close-up.
Zoom thing happening.
And so we can pretty much just no we don't need multiple resolution
versions of these tiles.
Really we know exactly the resolution.
We're going to need all the time and we know it in advance it's like
it's a stuffs coming over here.
So there may be some places where we have to work through it like with
animations, we're not sure exactly what we're going to need to load or
something there maybe.
Some parts that are a little bit trickier for us.
But on the whole it's just not the kind of situation where we need
that Dynamic level of detail, fungibility that Mega texture was
designed to give you.
And furthermore, we certainly don't need this step.
Although you could argue that, you know what, you could still maybe
call it Mega texture, even if you don't have this step where you draw
it.
See what IDs but we definitely need that because we know exactly all
the stuff that's going to be drawn pretty much and we just won't, we
don't have the kind of
Including things, including other things or that, or the backs of
things not being visible.
We don't have much of that in a 2-D game.
We kind of know what's getting composited and we know that if it's not
visible right now, it'll be visible soon, right?
Whereas that's not the case in 3D, so hopefully that I don't know,
maybe that answer that a little bit, but there you go.
Why do you think John Carmack is a hack?
And when are you going to say it to his face?
I don't think John Carmack is the heck?
I think John Carmack is one of the greatest game programmers that
that's ever lived.
I just think, like, any programmer, even the greatest programmer that
ever lived doesn't always hit the mark megatexture just wasn't a great
scheme.
Right?
And, you know, maybe he disagree with that.
Maybe he thinks it was successful.
I just I just don't think it was a good design and that's easy to say
in hindsight, you know, he doesn't know going into it, he invented the
thing and a lot of times when you make something when you're working
on it, the first time, you don't know if it's going to
To be good or not, you've got an idea and you've you think that
something could work but you know, whether it actually pans out on the
end exactly the way that you'd hoped and whether it solves the
problem, you hope was going to solve in an elegant way you don't.
It's very hard to know, but something especially as complicated as
Mega texture and in an environment, like a bag of extras been
developed, where gpus were a lot more primitive than they were today.
There's just, it's just very difficult, right?
And so, John Carmack has made a lot of very good engine design
decisions throughout his career.
air and so hopefully I would think he would not mind me saying that
one of them was not particularly good because I mean the guys got a
very long track record of very great designs behind him and and yeah
not only that but John Carmack
He ain't the most emotionally, volatile, dude out there.
And so, even if, for some reason, he was paying any attention to what
I had to say which is unlikely in the first place.
He doesn't care.
Right.
In fact, what he would probably care most about was that I didn't do a
good job explaining it because he's a kind of technical fellow and so
that would be the thing.
He'd be like, yeah, you didn't explain megatexture very well.
I'm like, yeah, I know.
I was under time pressure, man.
But what I can say is also if you do want to learn about Mega texture,
more specifically, I would encourage you to go look up sparse virtual
textures.
There's a video by Sean Barrett at nothing's.
Is his Twitter handle Sean Barrett.
She has a whole video where he shows how they work and he does a great
job explaining them and he also covers the actual minutiae of it, like
how you do mipmapping on it trilinear and padding and all that sort of
stuff.
And he shifts sample code to, you can go down the same code, you can
just see, you could be like, you're some, I get extra Works.
Here's a complete working example, right?
And so, so I would highly encourage you that if you were curious about
actually not, you know, a better explanation than what I gave for how
Mega texturing works.
I would highly recommend that you check out
Lecture on that because that will totally clear it up for you.
So there you go.
All right, folks, that is the end of another hopefully non regrettable
incident another episode of handmade hero.
So thank you all for joining me this evening.
I'm glad I was able to to make it home in time to do the stream.
It was fun.
I'm glad we did something kind of light and fluffy that kind of
cleared, the kind of cleared the mood for the day out for me.
So now I can go
Go to bed a little happier and that's good.
So again, if you, if you are somebody, who wants to follow along at
home, you can always pre-order the game on handmade hero dot-org and
it comes to source code.
So if you want to play around with stuff like we talked about tonight,
you can go ahead and do that.
You can pre-order it on him.
A hero dot-org comes the source code, you get a link in your email
save that link because you can download the source every night.
So every time I update it you can redownload it again.
So don't forget.
So that's a good thing.
We also have if you want to support the video series if you like it,
It and want to support it.
You can always subscribe on our patreon page as well.
We also have a news and Forum site that community members contribute
to its got a Forums on their people answer questions and I answer
questions too.
Sometimes I get annoyed and and, and post annoying things.
But most of the time I post good answers.
Okay.
Most of the time I do and then we also have a schedule bot, which
tweets the schedule at you.
So if you want to know when the streams are coming up, you can check
that out and it keeps you up to date.
So definitely check all that stuff out and hopefully I'll see you back
here again.
Tomorrow night at 8:00 p.m.
Pacific Standard Time actually pacific daylight time.
I think those are they coincide?
I don't know how time zones work.
I think they're made to be maximally confusing to everyone but it's at
8 p.m.
on the west coast of America, whatever that time zone is called right
now, PST PDT song.
And so I
Hope to see you here for that.
It would be nice to get another night of programming in with you.
And we will maybe play around with that ground code a little bit more
because it wasn't quite done with just kind of fussing with that.
So, I know it's not really what we're supposed to be doing.
Now, bolts we do a little, maybe we'll be able to make this week, be
playing a little and then start back on the Collision detection
finalization stuff next week.
We're trying to clean that up.
So anyway, thank you very much for joining me and I hope to see you
tomorrow.
Take it easy everybody.