Hello everyone and welcome to handmade hero.
The show Rico to complete game live on stream.
We are, yeah, we are probably, you know, mostly done with the
substantive part of our rendering update to 3D we were previously just
doing kind of flat 2D rendering and now we actually have full 3d
rendering and yeah, I am not sure exactly what we should be doing
today but I feel like the right steps because
Our kind of in a little bit of an amorphous Zone where we kind of want
to do some cleanup and get a bunch of things back on track that we're
sort of in limbo.
Due to that transition, I would say, probably the most important thing
is now to go make our camera work reliably and our room structure kind
of work a little bit better.
So I feel like, that's what I'm going to focus on today.
We'll see where it takes us.
Obviously, maybe we end up somewhere else but I think I'd like to do
Do today is spend an hour or two, just getting the camera room stuff,
a little bit better straightened out so that it's not a weird kind of
hacky system.
It's always been a little hacky back in the 2D day as well.
We never really sat down and made like a really good.
Here's where your viewing what's going on?
Similarly like you know, typical thing that might happen in games,
like this is when you do something like, I don't know.
You flip a switch or something in a door open, somewhere.
There's like a little bit of a cutscene kind of thing where the camera
might pan over and focus.
On it so that you can see that.
That's like it opened the store over here, and then come back, you
know, stuff like that.
We would like our camera to be able to handle properly and so, and
we've never imply anything like that either.
So, just designing a camera system and doing the, you know, the code
necessary to make all that stuff work.
Cleanly is a pretty worthwhile thing to spend some time on and it's
not super complicated like it's not particularly onerous code.
Once we've sort of done the work, we've already done.
One involving allowing you to set an arbitrary 3D location and view
the world from it and all that sort of thing, we've already done all
the hard work.
So really all we're talking about now is just having a coherent
structure.
That says, what is the camera doing right now?
Where is it trying to focus?
You know, does it need to move there?
Is it far away?
Is it trying to cut their, or interpolate there?
Just a little bit of, you know, basic AI Logic.
On top of it, not even admit, it's not real AI, just more.
Like, just a basic controller.
Kind
The thing on top of it is all we're really talking about but it just
going through the motions of putting that in place and also the notion
of rooms having that beset coherently and having the camera be able to
think about that coherently.
So it can say like, okay, I know that I'm supposed to be viewing this
room or this tile or this, whatever.
I know what that is.
In three dimensions.
I know how to figure out the place.
I'm supposed to view that from.
Let's go ahead and move there.
And I think that's what you want to focus on first when we get that
done, then, I think the other thing we want to do is thing I mentioned
before is just have the ability to knock out things that are in
between the camera and the player.
So that if the player is, you know, underneath a layer where they're,
you know, on the second floor of, you know, a three-story building or
something in that third stories in their way.
They, you know, that third story wants to Alpha blend away smoothly
when they come up to that third
Story.
It should blend back in that sort of thing.
I think we want to go ahead and enable in the renderer side of things.
So I feel like that's kind of where we're at in terms of stuff that
needs to happen.
At that point, I think render clean up and just putting in maybe some
some nice path for stuff like particle systems or things like that.
Just kind of rounding out that field and just making that feel like
it's a little bit more finished.
And solid is really, I think the complete package
For doing the full 3d upgrade.
And then I would say, we're basically done with that, and we should
move on to a different area of work, whatever that turns out to be
based on what we feel like, so.
Alright, today is day 3, 77.
If I'm not very much an area, let me double check to make sure that
that's actually true.
Yeah, there you go day.
376 is right there.
So, there we go.
So I'm going to go ahead and open it up.
Day 376 is source.
Code is what
Going to want to start with if you're following along with today's
programming at home.
And let's go ahead and just do a quick build and show where we're at.
If I remember correctly, the last thing we did was draw a room
boundaries.
Let's take a look here.
Okay, go.
And I think we also kind of said, maybe someday we'd work out the mass
for math for the cross product in a little bit more detail.
I'm not super motivated to do that today.
I'm not interested in doing a lot of math grinding this today, so we
probably will skip that till a different time since we really don't
care.
Very much about the cross product.
In any particular way, at the moment.
Anyway, it's really just for drawing.
These little debug volumes is the only reason we needed it in the
first place.
So anyway, as you can kind of see where drawing debug volumes now so
we can
it's nice because now we can actually show stuff like where we think
the rooms are and so what I'd like to do is sort of move into
Basically, like get a little bit more involved in the Collision volume
stuff and maybe set those a little bit more reasonably for example.
Right now, you'll notice what we're doing is we're setting like
Collision volumes on these trees.
I don't really know.
Now at this point what we're doing with Collision volumes but I think
you know what I would say is based on the design of the game we really
don't need Collision volumes for stopping you from moving because
When you move, you can only move two unoccupied squares, right?
And everybody has to stand on squares.
So really what the Collision volumes are for is for floating objects.
So basically projectiles and things like those creepy floating heads
that are there.
I don't know that will actually have any creepy floating heads in the
game.
But, you know, we'll probably have things that are floating that do
not necessarily occupy a squares.
And so Collision volumes are really mostly for that purpose, what that
suggests to me is that we probably don't need anything, really all
that complicated for a collision volumes, a simple, you know, Cube
Ivo.
Well, not cube right.
Rectangular prism might be the correct word for it, but basically like
a three-dimensional rectangle is probably all we really need for our
Collision volumes at this point.
I don't know that we need, you know, we did something a little bit
more complicated.
We had a way of you actually specifying a whole series
of course, in volumes where you could say, you know, I've got this
many different
Rectangles, and so on, we may just want to say that like every entity
has a bounding volume and the bounding volume is, you know, either a
sphere or rectangular whatever and that's just good enough for now
because we don't really have any need for anything complex.
And we're not I don't think going to because like I said, most of what
is actually the important Collision detection that really has to be
rigorous in the game is mostly about making sure that players and
Monsters, occupy squares fairly, and that is taken care of with a
different system.
So given that that's the case.
What I would say is I think we should be able to go in there and
change that around.
And then from there, what we could do is make sure that our room
Collision volumes are set per room correctly and that'll be easier.
Once we have in the end of destruct, its bounding volume represented
directly in in there, right?
So that's all really academic at this point.
I don't know why the find results window ended up down here.
That's just the Mysteries and the magic, the the breathtaking magic of
Windows of Visual Studio.
Let's see if that fixes it.
Yeah, that fixes it.
There we go.
I think it's probably cuz we just didn't have a Fine Results before so
it had placed it down there, so let's let's fix that and there we go.
So now I'll go and start doing the thing that I was talking about.
So for starters, let's get room boundaries in there and let's try to
make those room boundaries work relatively.
Well, if we go into handmade entity then one of the things I think
that we were doing previously that is not particularly great.
Is we have the entity Collision volume group and that's stored off the
entity as sort of this permanent storage, right?
It's like what happens is we have different Collision groups and they
are created at startup basically.
Lee, and those Collision groups.
We say this is you know what the canonical tree has a collision
volume.
And I don't know that, that's particularly interesting.
Like I said, at the very least we would need scaling on there because
if we didn't scale, those, there's no way to really represent.
The fact that each room has a different Collision Vol volume in terms
of the room dimensions, right?
Which is the problem that we're facing at the immediate moment.
And so what interests me, there is just figuring out like, okay, we've
got two ways, we could do this either.
We stick with the a version where we basically have a bunch of static,
Collision volumes, and you're just referencing the one that you
actually need.
And having some kind of a scale value.
That tells you what that needs to be, or we just store a simplified
Collision volume directly in the entity.
So for example we can either say here's the scale and we apply this
scale like Collision scale to the Collision volume so that when the
Collision volume represents just a standard size, you know, 1 by 1
tile by 1 tile by 1 tile room, and it just gets scaled out to fit the
whole room or something like that.
You know.
We can do it that way or the other way we do it, is we just have a
rectangle 3 in here.
That's like Collision volume, right?
And these things go away.
So I don't know which of those is the most useful obviously but it
seems like this is the simplest way to go for now and you know it
allows the rectangle to be centered in any way around the entity.
So even if the entities position is, you know, on the ground but it's
a floating thing.
We can represent that because the Collision volume itself has a Min
and Max in all three dimensions, right?
And so I think that's I just feel like that's probably
What I would want to go with because I feel like this is overbearing
and doesn't really make a whole lot of sense, because I just don't see
us needing it for anything.
Because collisions I feel like are just going to be more
straightforward than that.
Now that may be a naive way to look at it.
I'm not sure.
But that's just kind of the way it feels at the moment and I feel like
the Collision volume would give us enough tuning to figure out what we
want.
The hit Area to be for our guys and just leave it at that, maybe I'm
wrong about that.
But you know,
And again, this Collision volume rectangle, three, it gives us a
bounding volume.
We can then set that bounding volume and say, you know, we could have
a flag that says that, you know, it's cylindrical or spherical or
whatever.
And so, you know, we would have the opportunity to sort of fine-tune
it to different shapes.
If we wanted to, it doesn't only have to be a rectangle if we then
find that a rectangle for whatever reason, just doesn't fit certain
entities in a particularly good way, you know.
Some entities are very rounded and want more of that or more
cylindrical, you know, we
Can we can use that.
And so I think I don't know.
That just seems like an easier way to go at the moment.
So I'm thinking maybe we do something like this, and we just let that
change propagate through.
And I go ahead and I
Go ahead and sort of fix the problems where that would become an
issue.
So you can see here we've got this entity overlaps, rectangles and
you've got this total volume here and now the total volume is just a
rectangle three anyway if I remember correctly.
So really instead of total volume all we have to do here, I think is
past Collision volume.
That's all that really needs to happen there.
Let's see.
Here are going to from entity Collision volume.
Wait what?
It's a rectangle three, right?
Cohesion volume.
That's the destination.
That's an Envy.
What does it need to pass?
Their hold on a second.
Let me take a look at entity.
Overlaps rectangle, so that takes an entity Collision volume and we
don't really want that to take that all we really need to take at this
point is a rectangle three what wasn't a deacon Collision volume.
I'm interested to know.
Let's take a look here.
Oops.
So it's yeah, it's just another version of rectangle, three right?
So that was probably just dumb because the moment we don't really need
it.
I mean, dumbs, probably a wrong word.
It was just thinking in terms of like, well in the future maybe we'll
mark these up or something, but at the moment.
Yeah.
I don't think I really want to.
Like I said, so we really just get rid of this right and and rebuild.
So now what we would say is that all of these are not necessary
anymore, right?
Those will just get built right into the things that we actually want
them to be and all of this stuff will just be based on.
Yeah, the rectangle.
And so on.
So let's see.
When we do the growth here, we have any overlaps rectangle and we have
the volume and the rectangle.
So this is the end of the volume.
And so, really all we want to do is in this case, we want to know if
these two rectangles overlap, right?
And We're translating this rectangle by this p.
And so I feel like this is stuff.
We should have had in the math Library.
I don't know why we're doing it by Mankowski in this case, because
it's not really necessary.
I want to see
So you can see, we've got intersection code here, and we've got
intersection 4 rectangles already.
So if all we want to know, if two rectangles intersect really all we
have to do is call this, right?
And we call the entity volume and the rectangle, and the only
difference that we need here, right?
We can.
Go like this.
All we really need to do here is we just need to move this editi
volume, so that it's
Over by however much p is and we already have a way of doing that,
right?
We have offset so we can just say like hey offset this entity volume
by the placement of the entity and then overlap it with this rectangle
and tell us whether or not there was any overlap.
That's all you really need to do there and then we're done.
So again pretty straightforward.
When we do update camera for entity movement, this is a function.
We're going to be redoing, so we don't have to worry too much about
it.
But at the moment what we can do is say well, okay, again we have the
exact same
Thing, in terms of of, instead of calling isn't rectangle.
We can just again, dude.
Editing.
Overlaps rectangle.
We can fact call the exact same thing.
We can say, if and of the overlaps rectangle, right?
And you can see us creating this stuff here in ways that we probably
don't have to do anymore.
We were sort of working with the fact that our stuff wasn't stored
kind of nicely and rectangles.
Before, here's the test entity P.
Here's the test entity Collision volume.
And then we just want to know if it overlaps the rectangle for the
room and so the in room volume, let's see.
Here are sorted by petitioner will entity P entity p.
In this case,
I guess this is the tests entity if it is a room.
So the test entity itself, I guessed it yet, the test sanity, we're
just doing entity to entity.
So what we probably should have here is if entities entity
Overlaps entity.
Right?
Is really all we want to say, we want to say, does the entity that
we're asking about overlap?
The tests entity which is the room potentially, right?
It's with if we made it through this, if then it's a room and if if so
then we're done, right?
At that point, we can get the rectangle for the room out at that
point.
And proceed.
So in fact, a lot of this stuff, you know, is probably this room Delta
here, which is the dimension of the room is just the, you know, get
dimension of whatever the Collision volume is, but it's not offset
properly.
So really room Delta is not the right thing and all of this code is
going to go.
So I'm just going to mark this with like, you know, to do Casey stop
using room Delta.
Start using K controller and that will fix that in large part.
So all we need to do now is augment that entity overlaps rectangle
call and say, we've also got a similar one which again is just another
way of calling the rectangle intersection function, but making it easy
on ourselves so that we just can call these and not have to think
about it.
Going to say, hey, do these overlap and it knows to grab the right
things out.
So again, exactly the same thing
here, it's just a call to ask, whether the
Intersect which we've already implemented.
And so here we just the difference is that we've got to offsets to do,
right?
So we want to know whether a is Collision volume.
Offset it by Ace position.
Intersects B's Collision volume offset by bees physician, right?
That's the only thing we're asking it to do and we've already got all
the code for that basically.
So let's see here.
Oops and this is in the wrong order.
There we are.
Oops.
And off we go.
So when we've got entities overlap, that was the function, we were
looking before at and I get, oh, no, I guess we didn't know we had one
of these.
This is the one that goes through all of those and this one is just
not necessary anymore, right?
Where is?
So the Epsilon, it looks like it grows these by an Epsilon.
Does anyone use that Epsilon?
Because we can put that
So nobody uses that Epsilon.
So we don't care about that at all.
That goes away and it's been replaced by the new one that just uses
the rectangles and doesn't use this.
That doesn't use the volumes.
So now let's see what we've got here.
So here is what this is, our move entity call which again probably
eventually we would replace.
This was the one from a long time ago.
It's just there for moving people, it's looping through these volumes
which doesn't need to do anymore because it only has one volume,
right?
There's only one thing to collide against so there's just one
rectangle.
Here, which is going to be the first entity Collision volume.
We take a look at what we're actually doing here.
So we've got volume and test volume.
So really that's just, you know,
How are they doing?
They're p-values.
How are they doing the placement values?
I'm not really sure so there's the relative.
It's got nadp+ volume offset pee test entity P so it looks like they
don't care about the volumes too much I guess.
And then it were testing.
So the interesting thing about this is we have to get the centers of
these I suppose in order to continue having this routine work, the way
it does which is probably fine.
So what I can do here is I can say we've got volume dim and volume
tea.
And this is just going to be we again, we don't need to Loop over the
volumes because we know there's only one entity here, right?
And so we just have entity Collision volume and this is a get
Dimension call, which will return us how big it is, and this we can do
it.
To call to determine where it's centered around and then the rest of
this code should work, we don't have to Loop over the test volumes
because we know there's only one.
So again we'll have test volume dim, get them test entity, losing
volume, and test volume key.
Get Center test entity, push your body.
So once that's done the rest of this code in theory should just work
and really all we do is we just get rid of the arrow, right.
Because now we've basically derived those values from what we're
storing,
The relative again will do, would do exactly the same thing, I guess.
It's nadp and test and a teepee.
Oops, don't leave those.
We just need volume pee test volume pee.
Right.
And then all of this again not particularly useful code but at the
moment we might as well leave it standing groups.
Indent please know what's going on.
There we go.
So then
I think we're good and that's about it.
So now when we're drawing these, we knew there's only ever one to
draw, right?
And what we can do is say, you know, if has area, and then go ahead
and test it, right?
Or rather, go ahead and draw it at that point.
And then we do push volume outline.
All we really need to do is say well, okay, we're going to get a
rectangle 3.
That's the the draw volume, and that's again, just going to be an
offset.
The Entity Collision volume.
And the enemy's position.
That's the volume we're going to draw.
And off we go now.
I don't know if we need to do any additional work there in terms of
like the can Collide has area stuff.
There's a little bit, it's a little bit over specified potentially,
but if we take a look at what happens in here, for example, when we're
doing this can Collide, I'm going to go ahead and say that in can
Collide, we probably also want to do
These are set then we're probably one another check which is like if
has area a collision volume and has area be Collision volume because
if they don't both have closure area then that's not going to happen,
right?
So yeah.
So similarly in here I think we don't have one of those for our 3
dimensional case.
Move to the more modern type names.
So here's a wreck.
Go three.
So in order to have area again the only thing that has to happen here
is it's got to have something, it's got to have a span in every
dimension.
So it just has to have the, it's men be lower than its maximum on all
three bounds.
Instead of just one of those bands.
So, I think we need to change it to this style, because we actually
use vectors in these as opposed to hard code because I think we wrote
it a little later.
So it was.
There we go.
And off we go.
So now let's see in the semicolon stuff here, missing something.
Because your volume.
Yeah, so make simple grounded Collision again.
Now these would just be like rectangle, 3, where they are basically
returning.
Go ahead and modernize these as well.
I like these new short type names that I switch to.
I should have switched them a long time ago, but I don't know.
I always used to type it out longer
They're nice, they're nice and Tiny anyway.
Let's see, we don't care about this because we don't need to push a
struct into anyone's Arena anymore.
So all we're doing now is just basically doing a rectangle Center gym
so we just do wrecked Center Dim.
This is the center.
This is the gym.
And that's it.
So now anyone who was doing a simple grounded Collision before, who is
using one of those can just call this function directly and set their
Collision volume using that.
It also means that we don't need the world mode anymore in here which
is nice.
It's just like hey produce me a rectangle that conforms to the
standard that I was talking about.
So in here when we do begin entity under the Collision equals, null
Collision that again, does not need to happen at all.
All we can in this case just have it be zeros.
So what we can say here is it's a wrecked Center damn or recommend
Max.
Of just all zeros.
And that's a non collider, that's what it would be if it was cleared
to 0 as well.
I don't know if it gets cleared because they're at the minute at the
moment, I don't know if creativity does I should check to see what
that's supposed to do.
Let me just take a look because it may be that that's redundant.
Clear 20 is a nice feature.
So I may have obeyed it in this case so we zero struct that.
So I think for now let's just say like everything else it just gets
cleared so that's nice things.
Get initialized with a non colliding volume.
Which is good because we want to have to set a volume in order for
them to collide which is nice.
So begin ground, identity.
In this case again, can just pass rectangle 3 for the Collision
volume, in that case, and then we set that
I am up there it is, and we're done.
And then in all these cases where we would have been passing like
monstar Collision here.
Now, we can go ahead and actually just have these be called in place,
so we can adjust them to whatever we want them to be.
We can, if we want to.
And again, we could just make this a function call.
So, if I take a look in here in World mode, monstar Collision, instead
of storing those like we were doing before.
Okay.
So it looks like monstar and familiar and stuff.
Looks like those don't actually have
Visions, so maybe let's just get rid of that.
Because it looks like that's just kind of annoying.
Now, at this point,
Right?
And let's go take a look here.
Which ones we actually have.
So, you can see and hear the only ones we have.
Are these sonal Collision Body Glove monstar and familiar those that
don't exist, right?
So monstar Collision, oops.
Head is in the way mon Star Collision.
Doesn't need to have a collision.
It doesn't have one at the moment, you're a body collision.
Also, does not.
So the fact that we set that two colliding doesn't make a whole lot of
sense because it doesn't really.
So I don't know if y That's set that way.
So that's weird.
The hero head Collision is supposed to be there and here it is.
So we should be able to put that in there and just say make simple
grounded Collision, oops, and that's, you know, just what we had
passed originally.
So we're literally just doing the exact same thing so I feel like the
body should not have the collides flag set but maybe I'm being dumb
but since we're not colliding it, you can get rid of that.
I also think now I'm not sure why we would necessarily have volumes
and Clyde, I guess, maybe for things like rooms, which may have
volumes, but don't want to collide.
I don't know what to think about that.
A bit more as we get further into the end of the system.
Hero glove Collision doesn't have one at the moment, either.
So that can just go away.
And also this is not passed here anymore, it's just head Collision
volume equals makes it look round of collision.
So that's fine.
Let's take a look.
If anyone else has a monstar collision it looks like a monster does
but monstars shouldn't have any Collision now and so now if we compile
we should get back to ones that actually do have Collision so there's
the familiar.
Let's take a look at what that was familiar Collision.
Oh no, that's made does not have a collision.
I thought.
It I guess that's why I can pass through things.
So probably should have won but it doesn't at the moment.
So we'll leave it like that until we add one and I guess we would have
to have it be set to colliding there.
All right, so let's see.
We should have a wall Collision somewhere, right?
There's the wall Collision.
So this wall entity should have a collision volume that Collision
volume should be this.
Nowhere else used it.
None of these were used anymore.
Obviously, that's not used for Collision.
See what's going on there.
So that's a little more complicated that gets used in one place and
it's got a specific kind of volume that's used with it.
We hold off on that one for one second.
Let me see if stare Collision is used.
So, add stair uses it and here's their Collision.
It does use make simple grounded Collision so that can just be entity.
Because I don't think we've got any stares in at the moment.
I don't think we use those anymore but we'll keep it in just 44
Amusement purposes.
So there we go.
Collision volume is there.
That should be it for that.
And then we've just got room Collision which we definitely don't want
to work this way anymore.
So this one is the one we're going to be changing.
The room coercion volume here is going to have to have a better.
Oh, so here it is.
This is what we need it to do.
So we want to call this here.
There we go.
And that's probably I don't know if that's right or not, but there we
go.
Make simple grounded, coercion.
Yeah.
So to see if that if that looks like it's in the right place.
All right.
So room Collision is not used anymore either.
So now we're just down to floor Collision.
That's the only thing we have left.
So let's take a look at that.
So floor Collision is used here when we're doing the room, creating
the room.
We've got it here.
So it looks like it's still only used in that one place.
Move out from behind my head there.
There we go.
And so we should be able to fix that pretty well.
Now tile depth in meters here, we've got
Add wall tile depth.
Is down here.
That's typical floor height.
So, let's go ahead and put that in.
Here you go.
Same here.
Oops.
We go and floor Collision.
Again, needs to be done specially.
So, for Collision is here.
Let's grab that out.
And just add that up here, poop.
Okay.
so, this all goes away and we are left with
that.
We can then use that here.
Oops, I delete.
What that actually was though.
So, makes it before Collision is just something that makes.
I guess I don't know what that does.
In fact, I don't know what why does he even have a floor Collision?
Now that I think about it.
I don't even think that's necessary.
Because floors don't collide with anything at the moment.
I think that's actually just meaningless.
All right, let's see that use a semicolon.
Walkable Dimension, that is just the ex-wife, or the gym.
Okay, that's pretty easy.
That's just Collision volume.
Dimensions Hoops.
Which only wants the X and Y there.
I'm not sure what the walkable dim and walkable height.
Bit is exactly.
Not sure.
What we use those for taxing my memory at this point, but we'll leave
it in for now.
None of this stuff has to be here anymore.
That's gone.
And we're done.
So now in theory, you know, depending on how much we messed up.
We should have something relatively sane happening, but we probably
missed something up.
Let's take a look.
So here we go.
You can see that we've got a little bit of a busted piece here.
Some, you know, we're getting double translation on the drawing,
right?
You can see that.
I think that might just be because we're offsetting
Those volumes and unnecessarily when we draw them.
So it may not really be anything other than that, okay?
Because the entity transform already does the transform by entity P.
So we literally don't need to do anything.
It's literally just that I forgot the in a new transform would already
do that.
So I think that's probably it.
Alright, so now we are back to something relatively sane there.
As far as I can tell.
Anyway.
So now let's just figure out how to get our room stuff.
To be showing up a little bit better in terms of volume.
So, what I want to do here is I'm going to color these if entity flags
and the D flag collides, I'm going to set it to one color and if not,
I'm gonna set your different color.
I'm going to say color equals standard color.
but if it collides,
we'll set it to something else.
And this way, I can just see pretty quickly, I'm looking at.
All right?
So pink things are colliding at the moment, purple or blue, things
aren't and now we can see a little more cleanly.
I think those are our rooms.
So if you look at our rooms right here, you can see that our rooms up
here to be I think
Right.
I mean, it looks to me, it looks to me like our rooms up here to be
bounded properly.
I mean, for the most part, right.
The only problem that I see with the rooms at the moment is that
they're lined up too high.
So, you know, you imagine what we're going to do with these room
structures, right?
Is we're going to say, okay what room are you in?
You know what I mean?
So we're going to say we're going to try to figure out what room is
the
Hero in.
So we can move the camera to view that room.
And so if you take a look at what's going to happen here, you know, if
we cut where we're cutting, you can see that line right there is where
this this is that rooms lower boundary.
If I look from the side right, you can see where that boundary is
right there, right?
You see what I'm looking at?
And what you can see is some of the floor tiles for the supper-room
are actually in a place where they're technically, if you were
standing on one, at least the bottom part of the entity would be
outside of the room.
And so, I think what we want to do is bias those downward so that our
notion of where the tiles are for a room that tiles are always up in
their actual room.
And so, for example, what we're doing right now, when we're creating
these entities in,
World mood, when we do like ad standard room here, which is our little
room test code thing, you can see that we do that the Z value.
So this is the code right here for figuring out like where tile is
going to be placed inside the room.
And you can see that we have the X and Y are not jittered at the
moment which is fine because we're trying to make it
Wild reconyx saying that looks pretty tiled for the most part you can
see here that we've got the Z value of the Z value is a random
bilateral.
If you just go up or down by .25 and I think we want to do here is
only go up basically, right?
Like I think what we want to do is say that this is going to be like a
random unilateral only upward and then we'll set it.
So that the Baseline for the room is bull is like the distance down
that that piece is going to be whatever the sort of depth of a
world of a of a Overworld cube is here which is like I guess it's
Point.
5 units down word, right?
I think that's what that is.
So if it's point five units downward, then what that means is we want
the room itself, right?
To sort of bias, those pieces upwards by that point five.
So I think what we actually want to say here is like, okay, it's 0.5
f, plus whatever that random unilateral is so that everything is OE
skewed upward.
I think that's what we want.
Anyway let's take a quick look at that.
So here's what that looks like right?
And now
I can see the floor is so much more sane place, right?
So you can see that Flora Line is now all of the tiles for that room
Are Up In what would be technically considered the bounds of the room
and that feels a lot better to me, right?
That seems like a lot more saying, what I will say is we've got an
issue here in terms of our floor height, though, you can kind of tell
that we've got this rather nasty situation where the depth of,
Of a room is pretty tiny, right?
Like I feel like we probably want there to be a quite a quite a bit
more depth to create a bit more space between the rooms basically like
more modern construction.
We want the the 12-foot ceilings not the 8-foot ceilings right when we
hop down here but anyway you know it's as the hero kind of goes down
in here.
So yeah, I feel like we roughly have what we want now in terms.
The room setup.
But again, I feel like we want this Delta, whatever.
This Delta is here to be, you know, to be big to be bigger.
I feel like it's just too tiny at the moment.
Right?
I also feel like maybe there's not enough variation the tiles now
because before we were going up and down by that, and I think, now we
want to be able to go, you know, because we are going up by .25 or
down by 2.25 at a maximum.
Then we reduce that to only going upward by .25, that's half the
range, it used to be.
So, I think what we really want to do is more like this to again, get
a little bit more variation.
I just wanted a chunky feeling room just at for a test purposes,
right?
That kind of exaggerated that Delta and I think that's,
A little bit better in terms of what it might be at the at its most
exaggerated.
Ripe.
And so now we're kind of closing in a little bit on what I want to see
happen here, but I think now we just want to make those dreams a
little bit bigger.
And then we can start to focus on the camera code and doing something
useful with that camera code.
In the meantime, I'm going to since I have allergies, as you know, I
will blow my nose for Anna millionth time today.
All right.
So that's like, yeah, that's all pretty good and everything is right.
You can see, even this one right here, which is pretty low down, is
right on the Baseline, which is what I want.
So that all feels pretty good.
These bounds here, look really wrong to me.
So I think our again, we have a bunch of work to do with their
projected rectangle stuff and that stuff has to get fixed.
So that's going to have to get improved at some point, but that's sort
of a separate issue at the moment.
That's the
Emulation bound information stuff some of its right?
Like that's correct.
That looks like the right simulation Bound for the most part but
Yeah, I don't know.
all right, so
I think all I want to do now is just increase that height.
So, if we take a look at what's going on here, you can see our ABS
tile stuff, right?
Basically, what's happening is when we do chunk position from tile
position and that sort of stuff.
I think our problem here is that the tile depth in meters is messed
up.
And so I think we need that chunk Tim and m dot Z to be different than
what it is, right?
It's
Square at the moment or rather, it wouldn't be square at all at the
moment, but that's fine because I don't think it is.
Anyway, and so the chunk dim and M
You can see typical floor height here.
I feel like typical floor height wants to be very different.
So I feel like, you know, typical fluorite want something else.
I don't know that we're obeying that everywhere really at the moment,
so we might need to do a little work on that.
But if you take a look at what that expands out to now that feels a
little bit better to me game-wise.
You know, maybe that's a little bit too much.
I don't know, you know but if those were floors of a building now, I
just feel like that's a little bit better.
It's not
Realistic.
Certainly, you know I mean you know it if that's the height of a tree,
I don't know that a typical Building height is going to be that much
drastic and maybe I can knock it back a little bit.
Let's say to something else so you know something that's more like
this.
I don't know how how realistic that is is probably not at all
realistic but it feels a little bit better to me in
Terms of the height difference between rooms, maybe I'll knock it
back, one more, I don't know.
But it needed to be at least that that much.
The other thing that I think would be interesting.
So for example, you notice we've got this problem here, right?
And I don't know that there's much we can do about it, just directly
where you've got when the hero kind of comes up upstairs.
You can imagine what's going to happen here.
He's going to clip through this geometry.
If he's, if he's relatively tall, we can tune it.
So maybe he doesn't as much.
You saw his head clip through there.
I wish these familiars would leave me alone.
Hey guys, could you, could you not could you just not
Everyone's blocking me.
Okay, there we go.
So when I come down here, right, can see me hopping down.
You can see that we poked through there and, and the circumstance.
What we're looking at here, right?
Is the hero standing on on this, this plate right here but that Z bias
that we have in there makes and poke through rather than than not.
And you know, it might be that that Z bias is just too high at the
moment and that just getting rid of the Z bias would get rid of it.
But we don't
No, what would happen.
There it also is probably the case that the hero is too big for this
queries on because he's actually if you take a look at him he actually
kind of extends a little bit more.
He extends too far to the side to even be on a single Square so you
can see like he extends further outside the bounds of the square.
So really probably part of it is that the hero probably needs to be a
little bit smaller or perhaps the other way to look at it.
The tiles need to be.
A little bit bigger.
And let me take a look at that here tile side.
M, for example, you know, it may be that tile side and meter is kind
of needs to be expanded out, you know.
Maybe they that needs to be more like this or maybe it just needs to
be that the hero needs to be shrunk.
Right?
But it feels like that would be a little bit better.
And again, the tiles themselves, I guess have to kind of be why our,
why didn't we make those proportional?
I don't know why.
That's a good question.
Also, don't know why nobody's able to actually hop at this point we
must be using that as some kind of a search distance, that's hard
coded, we have to get rid of a lot of that hard coating, which will do
as we when we do the game code.
So it's not no big deal but so if they were further spaced out that I
think we'd have less of a problem here as well.
Because again, you know, the hero would not protrude into it so much
as he would at the moment.
So that might be better but I think possibly the right thing to do
there because I don't know.
the think about it, I think we want the tile side to be what it was at
the moment and we just want the hero to be a little bit less poofy,
you know, maybe shrink them down a little
So, let's see.
Let's go to entity here or right.
That would be an ad piece actually.
So it's you had hero when we construct the hero.
This hero, isn't it?
At player not out here.
Inside here, you know, if we, if we sort of tone down the size of the
here, a little bit, see what that maybe is more reasonable in terms of
width.
At least, now he fits inside a square, which is a plus, right?
And so when it comes down here, that looks about right when it comes
down here, you can see like you kind of swell of course the camera
moved as well in this case.
So it's hard to say exactly if it was back a little bit but still it's
going going to go through there and then when it's get down here, it's
out.
So it's really only that.
Stare that that second stair but I don't know.
We'll see what happens.
Point being what I was going to say there is we have an option of
fixing that by actually sort of working around that problem, even in
the case for the heroes large, we can work around that problem by
actually having the camera help us because if the camera moved over to
where the stairwell was when you went downstairs, then
Then you would end up in a circumstance where it would be straight on
to you and you would not get that overlap, right?
So, that's another option.
For example, if we imagined in at standard room,
If we imagine that we were already in line with the stairwell, which
would be what world position P left.
Hold down to floor below.
Here is okay, so we go right whole this part right here.
If we were to set off set X to Zero instead of three.
So the stairwell was right in the middle of the view, then you don't
get that problem, right?
So you can kind of see how if it lines up with the camera.
Course that is if I can get these guys out of my way, I should turn
them off.
They're really annoying.
These sausage gentleman sasi, bodiless disembodied, heads.
So, if I come down here now, who is in my way, why can't I jump down
there?
Somebody's in my way, but not sure why.
Or maybe it's just that, that stairwells too high for sorry, for some
reason now.
I'm not sure why.
The difficulties of illustrating things, when you haven't finished,
the actual game code at all, and all these heads are flying up towards
me, it's kind of creepy.
There we go.
So when I hop down these you can see now there's no problem with
interpenetrating because you know, just because of where the camera
is, right.
It doesn't, it doesn't have the same problem.
And so what we could do is just force the camera to align to move over
to where you are.
When you go down a stairwell,
L would
Another problem would be another way to avoid having that Graphics
artifact because there's nothing we can really do about it.
Like I said it's just an artifact of trying to do some 2D you know
stuff in 3D.
We're making these sort of hacks to allow you to do some stuff that
you wouldn't normally be able to do with the 2D art to make it appear.
Like it situated in a 3D World kind of nicely.
And at that point it's just like well you know you're going to run up
against certain places where it's unclear if there's really any way to
hack it to make it not have an artifact.
But sometimes what you can do is just like make it so that case
doesn't happen, right?
So all we really have to do.
There is go like okay, can we do something where
Where will force the camera to compensate for that fact and, and make
it not cause a problem.
So anyway, looking at this, this looks a little bit more right to me.
Now, I feel like that gives us enough space here between floors to
make it feel relatively, right.
Again, they're much larger than floors would be and say a building,
probably in reality.
But I just kind of feel like gamey for gaming purposes.
You want there to be a lot of room there and
The dungeon wants to kind of feel deep like when you're going down
that there that's quite a bit below, you were something like this so I
feel like that's a little bit more, right?
All right, so that's really all we need to do with the Collision of
volumes and we still got about 45 minutes left.
So all we should really have to do now is move over to working on the
camera, which I don't know if we'll finish today, but I feel like that
was all we really can.
Do need to do with the question firemen out there simplified and clear
what they actually are.
So let's take a look at the camera code at the moment and just see
what's going
And with it.
So I believe we have in here.
So yeah you can see this this here it's this is a note.
It is mandatory that the camera Center be the same region Center for
this code to work properly because it can I add the offset from the
Sim Center to the camera as a displacement or it will fail when moving
between rooms at the changeover point that changeover Point problem I
think is also something that we can avoid here because the camera now
update camera for entity movement what we can do is
Probably make the camera be an actual entity with an actual brain that
updates itself.
As part of the world update, I feel like that probably would just
work, right?
At least, it seems like it.
Now, maybe it's better to keep it separate because that means we can
run it guaranteed Lee after the person moves.
But anyway, so here is the code that we were using before it which
seems pretty reasonable where we say.
Okay, any room entity.
Let's see if the players in it so that way we know which room the
players actually in, right?
And that's pretty straightforward.
Let's get rid of room, Delta.
And let's let's just use in room, right?
Because the other thing is come from there in pretty much entirely.
Right?
If we wanted to, we could actually do these outside by just saying,
you know, whatever it's it's in room pee.
Right?
So you just get rid of these.
So now if we know that this is the room that we're trying to view and
we know where that room is, then all we need to do is say, well, I'm
trying to move toward that room.
Right?
I need to move in the direction of that room and I'm trying to member
if this to do is still apply Center to be Sim Region Center,
So yeah, I think this can go away.
If we just stop thinking of that room, Delta as a thing and just have
the camera, be the camera without any displacement because I don't
think we need that for anything in particular.
I'm trying to think if we do, but I don't think we do.
It's an interesting question.
Let's proceed, a little further and find out.
Anyway, so we've got which room we're in at the moment and so we know
where we would want to be in terms of where the camera should be.
And then we know where the camera is right, we know both of these two
things.
So, essentially, what we would say is like, okay,
What we want to do here is track the world space position of the
camera through the entire system.
So again, it seems like we want the camera to be in the Sim in the
simulation itself properly, right?
We want the camera to have a better notion to unpack itself relative
to the the Sim region.
And I think is that what we're doing here?
No.
So what I want to do, I guess what I'm saying is
We have the cameras.
Hold position and I think we want to do is unpack it into the Sim
region, then update it as if it's an entity and then pack it back and
return, that I think that's what we actually want.
So let's go ahead and try to make that work in the same fashion.
All right, so if this is the room that we're in, we should be able to
compute essentially what I wanted what I want to compute here.
Is, you know, I've got a rectangle.
That represents the room.
Right?
And if I've got a rectangle that represents the room and I want to
view it, I should be able to come up with.
I've got to put my little day heading in days 377.
At this point, what I should be able to do is say, what is the camera
location that would most.
That would be where I would want to view this room, right?
And I should be able to come up with a Target position for the camera.
Right?
So if I have a Target position for the camera, then I would know.
Okay?
This is where I need to view the room from and once I know where to
view the room from, I should be able to take my current camera
position wherever it is and drive it toward that location.
And that way it gets me out of this whole situation that I'm looking
at here with the whole like, you know, problem of room apron clamped
map to
Is Bounce height, blah blah blah blah, right.
I should be able to make a thing.
That just kind of nicely goes between one room and another room as
part of the camera interpolation or whatever has to happen.
And if we go right,
Okay, so what I want to do here is construct that here is the two
values ice cream before hand.
But I don't know, they really care what those that much at the moment.
What I really want to know is where is the room, right?
And what is that rectangle?
So what I want to do is I want to take the room volume that I'm
viewing and I can get that bite again, just doing an offset by saying
whatever the in room placement is of the in room Collision volume.
That's the room that I'm trying to look at, right?
Like that's
What?
I'm trying to view at the moment and so then what I want to do is say,
well, the camera should probably be centered around that.
So the camera or the target position should probably be whatever the
center is of that room volume.
At least the X and Y of that, right?
And then I want to be up some distance from that center.
Now it's the ground.
It's the floor that I usually look at a rooms, so really, we probably
want to say.
It's something more like the center of the room volumes X and Y, but
it's probably the room values.
Minimum Z that were looking at, right?
And then, what I want to do is I want to offset that by however, far.
I want the camera above that room.
So the target pz values would probably be increased by whatever.
I don't know, however, much I want here.
I'm gonna, you know, think about what I want that to be and probably
base it on the size of the room as well, so that I can frame the rooms
nicely.
Then I'm going to get rid of all this this
Was going to say crap, but let's say wonderful code.
Entirely in and all of this stuff will going to get rid of for now.
So, let's just get rid of all of this, right?
And yeah, let's just just say and in Room camera height can go away
now as well.
Because we'll just do that automatically for now.
And so, what we need to do now is first, let's start by just snapping
the camera directly to that location, right?
So here's the region origin.
Here's the room.
Campy that's going to be that Target pee.
We don't care about this at all, or wait.
So camera has a separate offset.
Which we shouldn't need any more really so I don't really want that
probably anymore.
Probably just want to do some other stuff with that separately.
Let me take a look at that.
So you can see here, we've got this offset here, that gets applied to
things and I don't know that.
I really want that in there anymore.
Let me go ahead and set it to zero at the moment, but
But we can come back and visit revisit that in a second.
So here we are doing whatever it is.
We're doing hopping around having fun now for whatever reason.
Oh, because the cameras.
Yeah, so this is the part where private to take a look at like I was
suggesting but that's okay.
so you can kind of see we the problem that we have at the moment is
that
If we want to move to considering the cameras location to being actual
physical location in the world, which is what I would like, what we
then need to do is have a way for the camera to articulate to the game
where it's actually trying to view.
Right.
And that is what would tell us what the Sim region should be right.
So what we want, here is something that's like when we go in and do
update camera for entity Movement.
We know this is the room that we're in.
We want to basically say here is the simulation region room center,
right?
This is where you should be centering that about.
So we want something like, you know, Simulation Center.
And that should be like that and we would say, then okay, the target p
is the Simulation Center plus that 8 or something like that, right?
And then what we can do is instead of having this offset, I can say
that the camera Simulation Center is going to be equal to that
Simulation Center.
And the camera p is going to be something entirely different, right?
Like so and so if we go ahead and do something like this, I think
that's a little bit better.
That Simulation Center bit.
Now allows me to say like okay there's a world position P.
There's a world position, Simulation Center.
And then we get rid of the offset.
I think that might do the trick.
So now camera offset is not going to be anything by default.
Buster screen, shake or something going on.
That's good.
And what we need to do now is say, well, okay, you know, we're doing
this thing where we're saying, the world camera record is get Wrangle
rectangle, at Target render group.
We don't really, I think want to do that anymore and I don't the
screen bound stuff.
We probably maybe, you know, might be something we actually want to
do, but at the moment that's not this, this stuff is not what we want.
We want to do something smarter here.
So when we have our Sim bounds and we do this, this sort of nonsense,
We need to do this a little bit smarter.
Here we need to do this this more reasonably and in fact what we could
do is actually just or what that rooms worth of size is as well, we
could have sort of something that uses that and so maybe we want to
store that as well at the moment I won't do that just yet.
But what I would like to do is say alright.
So
Let's take this world camera wrecked situation and let's get.
This is all just this is just garbage.
We don't really want to do it this way at all, but what we want to do
here say okay, let's figure out where in the where in the world this
is going to
The simulation region should start, which is coming from the camera,
which is telling us where the Simulation Center should be.
So when we do this, we're saying okay, here is the, the camera P.
This is where I want you to lay around.
We don't want to do that anymore.
Right, what we want to say instead is here is well, I guess I still
That here is the Simulation Center that the camera wants which may not
be necessarily where the camera itself is, right?
We don't want the simulation necessary, we send around the camera
because the camera might be moving around.
We want the
the ability to specify here is where we're simulating in.
The camera is some are slightly different from that potentially
perhaps quite a bit different from that depending on the
circumstances.
So that's where we're trying to simulate and
And then we just need to know how big of an area.
We're trying to simulate at the moment again.
I'm not sure we want that to really be based on any of the things that
we're talking about here.
Probably what we want instead, instead of that is something, you know.
We probably want something.
for rec center gym, that's literally just
This sort of thing.
And I don't know that we even want any of that other stuff at all at
the moment.
Alright, that's, let's take a look at what we get here.
Of course.
Now I, we also need some way of initializing that Simulation Center.
So now we've got all of them set.
So the Simulation Center will actually be initialized to something
which is good.
And so now we just need to fix the one more fact which is that the
debug offset stuff at the moment appears to be initialized to zero in
a bad way so we're going to have to fix that as well but other than
that, I think we're good to go.
All right, so one last thing, let's go ahead and get that.
So we've got the Simulation Center.
Initialized.
We've got the last p and p initialized, but those will we don't really
need to initialize those for the most part because they should get set
automatically at some point.
I don't know where the player is.
Do we know where we add a, where do we add the player?
And I don't really know.
So we add the player wherever the same region.
Currently is the closest reversible 2000 so that should be ok.
Probably anyway.
So I want to take a look at that that initialization of the camera
offset because we get some problems, the debug camera, where were
using debug camera, we need their the debug camera Dolly to be
something reasonable.
Which at the moment, it isn't.
So let's take a look at that, David Cameron.
Ali.
So the part that's weird.
So here's the thing that ends up happening.
So at the start because debug camera dolly is 0, we end up with this
problem of the camera can zoom in and out because there's no known
Focus point to it.
So what we need is we need a way of talking about how far you are away
from the Simulation Center, which is a separate thing, right?
So we really want this distance here, this camera Dolly distance and
also the
We were rotating around like the pitch in that sort of stuff.
Also needs to be respective of what that Center Point is.
So when we're constructing, the debug camera, we kind of need to look
at where that point is.
Because now we just have a camera position and we don't have an offset
from that position.
We just have a camera that's like, sort of floating around.
It doesn't have that sort of construction of.
Here's the center point, and we're back a certain distance from it,
because we got rid of the offset, which I think we want to do.
I don't think we really want an offset on there.
I don't know.
I don't think about whether we should,
Should keep it that way.
We're, we're, it's got to pull back.
That's that it knows about
I'm trying to think of whether I like that or not.
Because on the one hand it's much nicer.
If you're just thinking about the cameras, always having a particular
position in the world and you could just treat it like an entity.
It's like, here's where the camera is.
It's this entity in the world.
It floats around does what it wants to do.
But on the other hand, it's also nice to be able to say well okay, the
cameras focal point is the entity.
So wherever we're looking at is the entity, you know, and the offset
from there is just how we're sort of orbit viewing that.
Whatever that is
So it's really difficult for me to really say which of those.
I feel like
it's more appropriate so I don't know.
Maybe I do like the idea of just an offset Z there and I just don't
want that to be the thing that we animate.
So I do want the cameras position to move in the world for its focus
point.
I don't want it to laterally displace X and Y but maybe, I do want a
distance, displacement on the camera as a separate control so that the
camera itself is its focus.
Is the entity position of the camera, essentially.
So that's the question and I don't know the answer to that question.
That's that's one.
That's like I feel like it's one of those six, six of one half-dozen
of the other that whichever one you pick.
There's going to be some difficulties.
You're going to encounter with the way you chose to do it and there
isn't one particularly right way.
So I feel like either or I guess at the moment at the movement what is
happens with camera offset here?
So, I mean, I guess what I could do is say, all right, if that was the
case.
I could still choose to do that.
I'm just really not sure about it, but if I did that,
it would look like this, and
I guess technically it's redundant to say camera since it's in the
cameras direct we all kind of know that and then what we would do is
say yeah okay so when we update the camera position, we would say oh
hey by the way the camera Target Z is whatever we compute that to be.
Sorry offsets.
And then that part would work properly I think yeah it's because then
we would still be focused on the part that we're focused on which is
probably good and the other thing that we can do there is now it's
pretty trivial I guess to say whether we want a locked camera or not.
So like for example if we want to lock the camera to the players
location, we can also do that pretty easily because we can say like
okay yeah, if we want
To make the target, PB The Entity P, for whatever reason we just can.
And then we end up with getting back to a scrolling mode in theory, or
maybe not.
That's supposed to set the camera p.
Did I miss something?
Do we not use our okay?
We don't use the camera.
We don't actually take into account the difference between the two of
those.
Placements.
Do we?
So we didn't really write this code.
When we set up the camera, we just assume that the Simulation Center
is at the center of the projection as well, which is not true.
So, what we really want here, when we create the view for the world.
So we create the orientation, we create the translation, you can see
it happening here.
This camera offset actually wants to be more to also have the Delta
Delta
From SIM, right?
And so we want to have a thing there, which says, we have to put the
simulation where the simulation should be relative to the camera
Center.
So we need something like, what is that in the world?
We've got that call.
That gets the difference between two things, right?
It's like a subtract call.
Here it is.
so in this case, we want to say, like, okay, take the worlds,
And I want you to subtract the cameras.
Which one is it?
That.
Again, I want you to take the cameras position and the simulation
region.
And of course, this is the way we're going to be translating the world
and it looks like, so the way that we've written, this here is the
camera offset plus the camera Dolly.
So we're actually talking about where we're placing the camera, and
then we're creating a camera transform from it, which means, we're
inverting this value, right?
These are
The Columns, these are the axes and the
placement of the actual camera.
So what we want to do here is say well the camera is at this location
relative to the world and then we're inverting that to place the
world.
So I believe we want to say tell us the Delta between the Simulation
Center and the cameras location.
That's the Delta that has to get applied in here and off you go.
So
These have to be addresses of.
Then I think that should be correct.
Or not.
What am I missing here?
That.
Is probably bad.
Code that never gets run, does not have an effect on your game.
That's just something you should probably be aware of in your actual
life.
So anyway, so now we have the ability to scroll a room too.
And what's worth noting here is now we can scroll the room which we
may want to, do you
For large rooms or something, who knows, essentially for free there
because we can just turn that on and off.
And if we ever want to turn it off, right, we just can
And it will snap back and we can make a gradual snapping back of it
right?
If we want to.
And now that's just a lot cleaner because of the simulation region is
not thinking about where the person is there.
Just think about what room they're in which is really all we actually
want there.
So I feel like that's kind of good.
I also feel like maybe that we could again experiment with turning
that on and off.
So one example like I said,
If we wanted to pull the camera in line with the player when it get
when the player gets to something like a stairwell so that it's kind
of in line with the stairwell.
We could like tag certain traversable as or something like that.
Where it's like, hey, if the player is on here, do this thing or
another thing is like, hey, here is a region that if the player is in
I need you to, like, pay attention to something that's happening.
I don't know.
Right.
So what I'm thinking there is like, let's say, you know,
I don't know if we're over loading, this brain thing a little bit
much.
I think we probably are.
But if you imagine doing something here, where we're testing these
entity overlaps, right?
Well we could do is test the another overlap as well.
Which is to say, let's take a look and see if you're in any other
regions that have special overriding camera concerns that are
different than the room concerns.
So we could have like you know what room you're in and then like you
know, special camera.
Or something.
And so we could detect if you're in the special camera region.
And if you're in the special camera region, we could do something
special right?
And for the moment, I'll just do a thing where we'll say for in the
special camera region, then we'll do the the, you know, the switch to
the entity mode, or something like that, just to show how that would
work.
But then we'll do something, you know, a little bit better in terms of
like detecting the camera a little bit more.
I also for the moment, might go ahead and switch us to optimized build
so that we get a better frame rate.
So we
60 frames a second for testing, right just so we can see you know it's
easier to test something like a camera when you're zipping along in a
nice way.
So you know, here's the current state and what I'll try to do here is
just make something that's like, okay, let's say that when we hop to
hear something and go down the stairs or start going down the stairs,
it'll switch the view to something that like, lets us see that a
little bit more easily or I don't know, something like this.
Not sure this is something we actually want in the game but just just
showing like how to start making the camera.
Be a little bit more flexible in that sense.
So if we make something like an energy here,
And you know, maybe I'm a Canada flag or something to this to this
extent, which I think is how I probably should have done the rooms as
well.
I don't know that they wanted to be a brain per se that seems like a
bad idea, but, you know, we'll sort of start to clean this stuff up as
we get a little further down the road, anyway,
If we have something like this in here, I could do something like, you
know, like this.
So that we can detect things that are going to be, you know, relevant
there.
We don't need that code anymore.
That's not there.
So now we can create volumes that that control the camera in some way.
Right.
And so the way that we would do that is in handmade entity.
I'm sorry and handmade World mode when we're creating it, you know,
when we create the stairs for a standard room
What we could do here is say like okay, where are the stairs are in
this thing?
Let's just add another entity here.
That's going to be like specifically, just for this test, will begin a
ground identity here and we'll end it here.
And the placement of this entity is I guess just going to be whatever
this is this this P offset or whatever.
I guess now, I think about it.
This is this is really outside of this stepping to.
So after it's really after we're done, we would add it.
And so we want to add something that puts, you know, a volume in place
for the.
So the entity can
An entity that has that flag set?
Whose bounding volume is like the region of the stairwell so that when
you go in there, you would you know, it would it would detect that and
do the right thing.
So we want to set that flag, first of all, so that it will know that.
This is something that's, that's entity is going to control the camera
when you're inside it.
And similarly, you know, we need to set a bounding volume Bond
bounding volume for it, that sort of logically places it.
It needs to be.
So what I can do for that is say like okay we know the Collision
volume is going to be a rectangle.
Of some kind here.
I don't know what I have to work with.
It looks like these p-values, what is this standard room thing look
like?
where is that standard room so you can see
Of these World positions here, right?
So what I can do is just grab one of those and then create the
dimensions that should fit around it, right?
So we know where the hole is in the world.
So the p-value for it would just be that the room, right?
There's alt P.
We know that the hole is that offset x 3.
I guess these are a values here, right?
So, Plus radius
so, you know, we would want these indexes into it.
So there's the X
There's the why.
And we know that like the offset X in this case should be 3.
The Y offset should be the middle which looks like zero.
So it should look like that.
That's the center of it and we know the Collision volume I guess we
can do a Center Gym in this case.
We know it should just be centered, just around 00, I guess.
Or that's may not actually be true.
Maybe want to do a min max.
So what we want to do in this case is we know that the Min is going to
be well, we know we're going to be only a half tile.
In X on either side, right?
In fact, probably a little less than that.
Even if it's about overlapping The Entity, we probably want to it to
be very small.
So we probably want like an X, you know, X gem to be something pretty
small like tile side and M should probably, it should probably be just
a very small fraction that so it'd be like kind of thin because it's,
it'll be an overlap test, so if we get close enough to it, you know,
it should be fine at that.
So tile side and M, we know that the the mean is going to be.
Oops, the negative X DM here.
The max is going to be the positive X dim.
Z wise, our minimum is actually going to be down from our position
because we're you know we're talking about going down the stairwell, I
believe, right?
Because let me just double-check yet because these are Z this this
stairwell is created in a downward fashion not that it really matters.
I guess we could do not for one but you know, the downward stairwell
means that the Z.
I'm going to leave the y4 S.
The Z value of R.
Suppose, this is
Also, when we constructed this way because it's symmetric and Y as
well, the Z values are going to be a symmetric.
The minimum is going to be negative, however, far down.
It takes to get to the bottom of the thing.
Probably,
So it's probably like whatever that the that world's typical floor
height, right?
It's probably going to be, you know, most of that.
It's probably how far we would want that volume to be.
And then here, you know what
Stop.
Probably maybe a little bit above the surface.
So you know, maybe something like
And I think we get the world in here, right?
Yeah, we do.
So that all works relatively well.
So the only thing we really need to figure out here.
Oh, is this P relative to what is this P relative to then?
Is that that world position p is not stored anywhere?
Is that really true?
No, it's stored.
It started right there.
I'm confused.
Here's what I am.
Oh, it's because this p is actually just a sin region p.
Interesting, well, I guess that's not that problematic.
We just need to be able to do that mapping.
So really, it's just this
Does that or does the mapping for us?
I guess I can do that.
So now we need a wide dim and the ydm in this case is going to be the
tile side and M as well.
But it's going to be, I guess it's two in either direction.
And then typical floor height is actually World mode, not world.
There we go.
And I think that should create it.
Now, we should see a bounding box up here there, right?
And there it is.
So it's a little wonky.
Okay, so it actually, it's actually a less than or equal to 2.
But that last one is actually the stair that you step on, I guess.
That's okay because we probably want to do it when you get there.
So that's probably fine.
That's probably fine.
So let's just see how that goes.
So here I go over to it.
So it's sort of worked.
But it was took a little bit of time.
Took a little longer than I wanted for it to that to detect.
I got to turn off these familiars.
They're driving me nuts.
How many of these are we adding?
One per room, I guess.
We're turning those guys off their, they're driving me nuts.
All right.
So, it seems like it takes a little bit too long, like, that should be
detecting it, but it's not.
So I'm interested to know.
Let me see if we set the bounds.
Wrong.
Okay?
So there's the problem is that's the only bounds we have on the hero
right now because it's just the head.
That's actually a collider.
And so this is too low, right?
That means to be X.
That needs to go up above where, it's going at the moment.
So, if we take a look at again, it adds standard room and just change
a little bit.
How we're doing that height there?
So you can see here, this is the the Z extents, why?
I'm not sure what's going on here.
I guess.
That's because things are offset, artificially from there.
So we're going to need to be more than that.
I guess what we can do is say, well, let's go ahead and make it extend
up to the top of this room as well.
Not all the way up to the top, but pretty far up.
So, now there's a pretty generous volume there.
We hop in here.
Now, we're going to go down the stairs that way, right?
And off you go.
So hopefully that's fine.
We still get a little bit of clipping there on that.
Because again, that guy is just really tall.
I think that might just be the case that we need.
RZ bias values to not be so big as they are.
It's probably all that that's happening there, right?
So now, you know, but let's keep going on this front.
Although I would like to see.
So if I actually, if the hopping was working, yes, you can see, it's
still kind of pumps through there a little bit.
Let me take a look.
I want to take a look at what happens.
We were in debug mode.
I wonder if debug camera should always snap to the location of the
hero
It's probably the right thing to do but you can see how much lower
here.
So I think those Z bias values are too high at the moment,
potentially.
So I'm going to just go ahead and remove those a little bit.
So I think maybe the Z bias is just too much.
It's causing things to pop out way more than I think, maybe they
should
So, I just want to take a look at that helps at all.
Yeah, so that's better.
Right.
So now you can see that that camera volume is doing exactly what we
want, right?
It's like when it comes in, there were triggering the camera to go to
a different location.
The problem is, as you can see, like, this way of saying is like At
first, we'll just set the camera set to where the entity is and off we
go.
The problem with that obviously is that when you do that, it's going
to be very jarring.
So like, you know, if we were to leave it like that in the game, it
would be very disconcerting to, you know, you don't really want that
to happen.
You just want the camera to maybe start to move over there, and if the
player doesn't end up going down the stairs then don't and then, you
know, if they just are breathing right through it, don't do it at all.
If they start going down the stairs, maybe do it a little faster, who
knows?
Like there's a bunch of things we could be doing there that we're not
doing right in that sense.
And also its
The head doesn't?
We need to work on a bunch of this stuff.
The it'll be nice to finally get into their game code and just do that
for no other reason than finish up.
All the animation stuff to be nice and solid.
But anyway because you can see, the head doesn't actually go downward
hardly at all.
It floats downward at a very slow speed.
So it actually it stays up quite High, you see if I can demonstrate
that a little bit better.
See how slowly that comes down for whatever reason, not sure what the
reason is.
Whereas that's how far down it should already be on the second stair
and it didn't even get there.
By the time we got here.
So the spring on the head for vertical is just not correct at all.
But anyway, that's neither here, nor there.
Anyway.
So well, alright, so I guess that's all we're going to do today
because there were now at the five-minute warning.
But tomorrow, I think that's pretty clear.
What we should be doing tomorrow is we should just go ahead and make
a, make the camera moves smoothly so that, you know, it moves over
gradually and then moves back over every time, you know, it wants to
change position, it's being more gradual and it thinks a little bit
harder about
Where it should be looking.
Let's go ahead and go to the Q and A
And I don't have I had to reinstall this machine that I use to monitor
the chat because Manjaro was complete was dying.
A rather horrible death on me.
And so I was wondering if someone could say, could make it do Q&A in
the, in the twitch chat.
I don't have a login on this one.
Yet I can see the twitch chat.
I just can't type into it.
Chuckles.
How's it going?
Two questions, one, how come rad aren't owning every Avenue of
compression existence like video codecs, okay.
And to is handmade here at some point, beautiful will be beautiful 2D
animated like the excellent.
Excellent hallo night that everyone should play.
By the way, you can you girls?
I don't know why.
You always try to get me to play Halo night.
I played it.
I did play it.
I mean, I have it.
I can't remember how I got it.
I want to say that it was in some kind of a bundle or something,
because I don't know that I actually bought it or maybe it was on sale
in like a steam sale and I bought it.
But somehow I did end up buying it and I did play a little bit of it.
That's about all, I can say I have not played much of it.
As for whether it will be 2D animated, there's not going to be a whole
lot of Animation in handmade here.
I probably will because most of it will be somewhat procedural
animation.
But we do have a bunch of art from Anna that we can put in.
And so pretty soon, when I get a chance to build a new art pack, we
will we will do that because it's a lot better are for what we're
doing as well.
It's like at the proper perspective and stuff so it will look more
correct, which would be nice, too.
As for how come rad aren't owning every Avenue of compression in
existence like video codecs.
I well, I mean the reason is because I think they do own.
The only ownable part of video codecs.
They do right?
They sell a proprietary video.
Codec for games and it's the video.
Codec that's used in every game.
Pretty much, you know, there's very few games that don't use it.
If they show video
They can't own something like the MPEG spec because that's a giant,
patent licensing, pool situation, where nobody owns the codec.
It's just a bunch of companies who are trying to extract royalty fees,
and also companies, who want to do video stuff themselves and are
trying to lessen their patent, royalty fees, get together and put a
bunch of patents in and make a god-awful heinous giant codec, that is
a real pain in the butt to use and that's the, you know, open standard
which is not really.
Reopen.
And there's that.
That's, that's all there is really.
There isn't another market for video codecs out there.
Nobody buys video codecs for movies because, you know, Blu-ray disc
has to have the Blu-ray standard movie format on it, which is going to
be mpeg-4 or whatever, right?
And that is a giant patent licensing hands-off situation.
That, you know, you can't, you can't get into that market at, all
right.
All rad could really do was patent a bunch of video things and then
put them into the MPEG patent pool, but
The people at rad such a you know, have the same opinion as I do about
software patents which is that they're bad for the industry so they
don't do that.
So I don't know that there's anywhere else they can really
No, you know, I don't I'm sure they would Branch out into another
Avenue of video compression if there was somewhere that you could make
money doing it.
But I really just don't know that there is
Sausage.
Superb.
Why don't you search and replace with a new short and sexy data types?
I should probably, maybe someday we will spend some time to just takes
a while.
Oh, Halo night, I'm sorry.
I was thinking Shovel Knight because you were I thought you were the
one who was always telling me that Shovel Knight.
Do you just only ever recommend to me to play games that are called
something night Halo night?
I would very much like to play.
I didn't know it was out yet.
It's on my wish list, so maybe I receive.
I don't know if I got a notification or not, I will definitely play
Halo night.
I have not played it yet, but but I would, I will definitely be
checking it out, yes.
Sorry, I got confused.
Did beef is the camera for this game going to be plenty smart or just
a little smart in this staircase?
I imagine you might want to measure the velocity of the player to not
have it affect the camera if the player is rushing straight past.
Yeah, I
I would say that's a pretty easy thing to add.
I wouldn't say that's particularly smart either.
So that's a level of smarts like that's that's not too smart for this.
I think like, I don't want to have some gigantic AI camera thing or
anything, but that's a pretty reasonable thing we can add that
doesn't, it's not too smart on the smart, it's not too smart for its
own good kind of thing.
So, I would be totally down with that in that, we just have to get a
little further on the, to actually have the camera doing e
interpolation first to make that do it.
But yeah, I mean checking the checking the velocity of the players is
not too bad.
You know, in in terms of that Collision for example if we you know in
here where we say if any of the overlaps entity what we can do is just
say like oh yeah you know the the inner product of these.
like,
I guess I could do it here.
Not sure how how I would want to do is exactly what we don't even need
to do the inner product really, unless we specified a V3.
So, for right now, we could even do it even simpler.
We could just say, you know, if the entity which is the player in this
case, if the entities velocity, what do we have?
Is DP, I guess.
That is in the y direction.
Not sufficient.
Let's say, you know, if it's less than some value than, you know, our
sorry, it has to be greater than some value in order to actually care
or something like this, right?
So we can definitely do that.
And then in theory, you know, when the players hopping or wrong, it
won't do anything there, but if they start to move down, it will,
right?
So something like that is really pretty easy for us to do.
The only thing is yeah, but in order for that to still, in order for
the camera to feel it, all good, we have to add the interpolation,
which we can do tomorrow and maybe we'll say to do
Make entity parameters that control velocity direction measurement.
But yes, so I do think that's a good idea, but
as we all day is the debug text draw order.
Still inverted.
It seems so by the looks that you liked text is a professed working.
Yes, so we haven't finished updating the debug stuff at all.
There's the clip rex have to be fixed in there and the debug draw
order has to be fixed.
I don't know if that might be the only two things, I don't know, but
we will, we will fix them eventually when we're done with.
When we were finishing, all the cleaning up from the different camera
stuff, but team R&B Greenies Casey last week during the wonderful a
mermaid shot, you demonstrate how to dynamically create code in
memory, you have mentioned in the past how you do a fair bit of
metaprogramming and I always envisioned that you would generate C C++
code to files when you tackle metaprogramming do you write out to disk
first and then have the compiled or do you do it all in memory?
Some of what you did last week?
I would like to do it all direct compilation but I have never had
enough time to really write a good code generator.
So I don't do that typically when I generate code I generated and feed
it through an existing C compiler somewhere.
So you know, if it's if the rest of the project is being compiled with
Visual Studio, it gets compiled with Visual Studio or whatever if it's
llvm it Sylvia.
I don't currently do any code gen.
I would
I'd like to.
And I have sort of the start of some of that stuff that I've done kind
of, in my spare time by just have not had time to devote at work to
it, to really making a good code generator for x64 that I can switch
to.
So that, you know, I don't have to use official compiler anymore at
that point be nice because then I wouldn't have to use compare at all
really because I could just parse the sea and dump it into the code
generator and then off then you don't even have to use them as we see
anywhere at all.
Which would be nice.
But there's just a lot of stuff that's involved in that, you know.
Debugging also becomes a problem at that point, right?
Because you know, generating ecstasy for code is one thing.
But you got to generate debug symbols because if you don't generate
debug symbols, then you can't step into the code, you've generated in
the debugger, and that becomes very difficult to debug, right?
So, you know,
just it's a lot involved.
Hey Casey, I was messing around with four by four matrix,
multiplication implementations and whipped out 10 variations some of
which naive and others were opto with Cindy out of curiosity
performance test them on BC clanging.
GCC, I was very surprised results as the compiler seem to be doing
very different things for this simple task, for example, on GCC the
Nate, the naive version sometimes.
Beat what I thought would be optimal.
Cindy, seems like it was able to Output better intrinsics, but on
clang, it was the opposite msv seems to have failed at honor
A loop and all implementations were crap except for a manually
enrolled Cindy version.
I realize this is a rat hole of a problem.
But is this really where we're at?
In terms of philosophy of right?
Once the ladies provide you the best thing for any for the platform.
Any thoughts, I guess the first thing I would say is I'm the wrong
person.
There's probably a good rant about that somewhere.
I'm the wrong person to do it and the reason for that is because 99%
of my time is spent doing architecture.
And code to do stuff.
That is not 100% performance critical, right?
As soon as you drop into Cindy, you're talking about stuff that's
going to be performance-critical.
You're probably not going to be doing a lot of Cindy optimizations to
the level, where you're looking with the compilers outputting, when
you're not talking about performance critical stuff.
And I just write a ton of code and a lot of that code is not in that
category if you take someone like Jeff or Fabien, who live day-to-day
a lot more in the we are trying to do.
Translations two things, a lot of time, you know.
I don't know exactly how much of their time they spent doing it.
But I would say 20 or 30%, might not be an unreasonable estimate of
how much time Fabien or Jeff might spend thinking about something like
how the stuff that they're writing is going to get executed on a on a
Target platform, right?
Because again, they tend to do stuff like okay, they'll make bank or
something, and there's certain amount of code and bank and yes, that
had to happen.
But then at some point transitions into optimizing Bink.
For lots of platforms and getting a
to run, well, and lots of platforms and all these other things.
And now you're thinking day-to-day a lot about those inverse Civic
ways.
So I'm kind of the wrong one to rant about that and I think you put
the right people to rant about that are people who have to deal with
this day to day.
But what I can tell you is, I think for certain the state is very poor
compilers, I would say there's two separate things, one is the
compilers are not very good at it, and the other is that the languages
are not there, if you think about it, see, with intrinsic,
Which is the current state of the art.
As far as that's concerned.
For day-to-day programming state of the Arts, the wrong term.
It's the current thing.
You mostly have to work with, right?
Because you can't be introducing all these Specialized assemblers or
something else into your tool chain.
You know, you got a program day-to-day, you talking about code, that's
get checked into a code, basic is compiled with Visual Studio or clang
or something, right?
All you have to work with these intrinsic.
Those intrinsics don't really do a very good job of either a making it
easy to specify.
What's going on or be being able to manhandle exactly what's supposed
to happen as a result.
You do end up in situations where the simple code, you would write.
That should be relatively clear how to make it work.
And very straightforward optimizations like Loop unrolling.
You might want to have happen, often can go horribly wrong.
When the compiler gets its hands on it and that's unfortunate.
That's why we have things like IP C or whatever it is.
The the is that what it's called the Intel compiler that that is made
for doing why'd you know, versions of things.
That's why we have some of those markup things available where you can
more easily, Mark something up in the compiler, knows what you're
trying to do and it can generate good code for it.
Those things have not mainstreamed as well as they need to write.
And so now you're constantly in a situation of like, well, maybe, you
know, we can go, do you know, compile this part of the code on this
other compiler and get better.
Default Behavior, unfortunately, that's not the default thing.
Again, I think this is mostly because most programmers, who probably
affect the C++ specification are not game, programmers and more.
Specifically, they're not getting programmers.
Like the people at rad, who spend most of their time, have to deal
with this stuff.
They're probably people.
Well, they're not people like me because the C++ standard wouldn't
look anything like, it looks like it was me but they're people whose
job duties look, more like mine.
They're writing code where the performance critical parts are
Very uncommon in terms of the amount of code they have to write.
So they're not focusing on that.
And they're not pushing that as hard as they need to, to get it to a
better place.
So, you know, I'm sure someday maybe it would get there but it's
probably not where it needs to be.
And that probably explains most of what you're seeing.
However, again, I'm I can't really rant on it because I'm definitely
not the right profile of a programmer to really even say how bad they
are.
Sometimes I do drop into assembly and look at what's getting generated
for certain things, but that is such a rare day for me.
Given the in
Warmest amount of programming.
I have to do every day, the amount that's performance.
Critical is super tiny on the current project I'm working on, right?
So, that's just a reality of the type of project that be working
happen to be working.
On, and it does happen, but it's just really rare.
And so, I'm just not in a position.
I don't have enough day-to-day experience with it to really say,
here's what these compilers are doing.
And why I do think that the place that this hurts the most oddly
enough, I think at the moment is not so much on PCS where you have so
much, heavy iron performance.
A lot of times tons of cores, really wide.
Same D out of order execution.
Giant caches blah blah blah, the place where you really feel it is in
the poorly designed mobile chip market, right?
Some chip designs are probably quite good.
I've heard that Apple's A9 is pretty amazing.
For example.
Other chip designs out there.
Apparently not so good and it ends up being really important how you
and schedule your instructions or whatever on.
You know some of these chips because they're really bad at, you know,
doing working around poor assembly.
You know, an Intel chip is very good at working around for assembly,
right?
It doesn't mean that better assembly, you know.
Better instructions teams aren't still better.
They are, but the chip does it.
Menace amount of work to handle bad code.
Well, that doesn't become the case on some of these chips in power
constrained, their less mature architectures, that maybe have less
good Engineers working on them as the people, you know, who knows?
There's only so many great chip Architects to go around blah blah
blah.
In those scenarios you may end up in situations where the, the degree
of meticulousness
Of the code that you can turn around those platforms, can make a huge
difference.
And that's I know I've heard some things without naming names of chips
or the people complaining about them.
I know I've definitely heard some things about stuff like that where
it's like, yeah, okay.
So would we like better ability to compile things on ecstasy for yes,
but ecstasy for is super powerful X would be like better things to
deal with this random phone.
That happens to be a common Android phone or something.
It's like, yeah, that's where we really.
It because it hurts us really bad there.
When we fall off the good path and the compiler is generating like a
lot of stuff that falls off the good path, you know?
So I remember, you mentioned some point that you were really
interested in salt and Sanctuary, have you played it?
I don't think I ever mentioned that I think you're thinking of someone
else.
I did not work on that game and I have not played that game and to the
best of my knowledge.
I've never been interested in the game either, unless I have been
forgetting something.
We're just now.
Could you please explain once more why you did keep camera offset Z is
it for movement between Tom apps or something else.
Yeah so the reason for that
It is really very straightforward.
It's just it's unclear.
Whether it's a good idea or bad idea the idea behind it is just that
well okay.
So the way that we view the game is like this, here is the world we
use the trees, you know whatever.
Here's the hero on it.
The way that we view the world is you've got a camera that's looking
down on things, right?
And there's the hero.
And so the reason that I thought the camera off set Z, you know what I
wanted to do was go from a version where we were talking
talking about the center of the room as where the camera was.
And then we had an offset that would move the camera around, to
wherever we actually needed it, and I wanted to change from that to
something, where we know where the camera is for real.
And the camera has its own real position and the Simulation Center is
something else and it may or may not be looking at that.
however,
It does make a difference which one we want to encode.
The focus point of the camera, like, where it's looking or the camera
itself.
And what I decided to do was in code, the focus point of the camera,
which can still be somewhere other than the simulation reading.
So, you know, if here's the map, we may be looking over here but
simulating based on this, right?
So, the camera might be looking here.
So like, in the case of where we move down the stairwell, for example,
but the question is, do you can code the location of where you're
looking from, or where you're looking?
And what I decided to do was in code location.
I was looking at which means I need just that pull back because we
don't allow the camera to slide relative to its focus focus point.
But we do allow to pull back.
So really that Z is just how far back were pulling and the reason that
I wanted that to be encoded is because I feel like that might be a
value that wants to be encoded separately for like bounce movement or
something that I want to encode to the separate piece of the
coordinate, just to make it easier to deal with, that's it.
More 85.
If it's off topic last tomorrow, during pre stream but fall upon D,
virtualization, your main Christmas virtual functions was the
overhead.
You get from the interaction.
That's not true.
That is not my main criticism about virtual functions.
My main critic criticism criticism of virtual function is everything.
There's the overhead is bad, the way it is.
Stored is bad, it is not serializable.
It's you cannot control the virtual function table yourself.
There's there's tons of problems with virtual functions.
That's not the only one.
You can't make things fit in the
Amount of space if you want to.
So you can't use like packed arrays correctly, blah, blah, blah, blah
blah.
So there's tons of really bad problems with virtual functions.
They're only useful in very specific circumstances and the speed hit
is by far not the biggest one of those.
The speed is actually the most unlikely one for me to complain about
because in a lot of cases you
Use Virtual functions.
You might not care about the speed because maybe you just don't have
very many calls, right?
So the indirect call is not the bad part of virtual functions.
It is a potential bad part in some circumstances, but it's by far, the
least offensive part of them because calling through a function
pointer and calling through a virtual function are usually not that
different.
There's a double in Direction in a virtual function so it could be
bad.
It could be worse, potentially, but it might also not be worse.
It depends on the
Circumstances.
So it's hard to say it certain chips.
It's real bad but the exits before isn't one of those chips.
So,
I think that's basically everything.
All right.
I'm gonna go ahead and close it down.
Thank you everyone for joining me, for another episode of handmade
here.
It's been a pleasure coding with you.
As always, if you would like to follow along at home, you can always
pre-order the game on handmade here dot org and it comes to the source
code.
If you want to play around with it yourself, we also have a forum so
you can go to ask questions a patreon page.
You can go if you want to support the video series, a schedule bot,
which tells you where we're going to be live and an episode guide
maintained by The Fabulous May blow which tells you pretty much what
we did every where there's also a crazy search feature that I don't
know if it's in.
Yet, I don't think it's in there yet because I think they're still
working on it.
You can see here that this is the episode guide table of contents.
There's like a search thing coming to, which is kind of amazing.
I don't know if we've got a demonstration of that but it's nuts.
I was playing with it the other night.
This is I think going to get introduced into the episode guide at some
point but basically it's kind of crazy.
You can go here and you can type in like anything you want.
SF Gartner did this, as
An interface to me, blows episode guide.
You can do nuts nuts.
So stuff like you can say, like virtual or virtual function or
something.
And it shows you the times that I've talked about it and you like,
click on it and it jumps right to the time that I talked about it,
right?
And it even has like a timecode is thing.
We can jump to different parts of where I was talking about it, it's
just crazy.
So
Yeah, that's coming soon to as well.
I don't know when that actually is getting integrated in there or what
the plan is for.
That I should probably ask me blow what's going on with that or us
off.
I don't know what the status is of it but it's pretty amazing stuff.
So the stuff that people are doing with the episode guide is just
crazy.
It's Way Beyond anything I was ever expecting to have as a resource
for pulling stuff out of the archives but there you go.
So definitely check that stuff out.
I will be back here tomorrow.
I think we're doing the 10 p.m.
I'm sorry, 10 p.m.
10.
Am Sweden tomorrow.
Hope to see everyone here for that and we'll gain will maybe work on
some interpolation code maker camera, a little smoother there.
That's about it for now.
I will see you back here for that until then have fun programming and
see everyone on the internet.
Take these everybody.