Crisis averted.
Yes.
The crisis has been averted, hna.
You.
The crisis actually has not been averted.
Unfortunately.
The reason that the stream is starting late today is because
Well, we're having a little bit of a problem.
I wanted to get rid of my taskbar.
I was talking about this on the last.
On the last stream and I thought I had seen, some people say that you
could finally get rid of the taskbar.
Again, used to be able to enter the test bar on.
Windows XP.
And of course, when they introduced their improvements,
Two windows with Vista and 7 where they improved everything.
They improved it.
So that it no longer works.
So you can't actually hide the task bar anymore.
Basically, you only have this thing that basically it always pops up.
If you go back up to the edge of the screen and it's awful.
And so you used to be able to, there's a thing in here that said
taskbar is always on top or whatever and you could uncheck that and
that was awesome.
It was like, totally
Perfect and did exactly what you want because then all of your full
screen Windows would just be over it which is what I wanted.
But I don't know what to say.
So basically, I was trying to get rid of that.
I was looking on the web for some of these things, basically.
And yeah.
Couldn't find it.
There's, there's like some tools you could course they got rid of it.
So thoroughly that you have to see taskbar always on top Windows 7 and
like I was trying to find people who are talking about this sort of
thing and there's like utilities you can install where I tried
installing one of them but didn't actually work.
So basically like
You know, when you're not used to track bar, start menu, BlahBlah, it
seemed like to keep taskbar on top unchecking that box.
This is what I actually wanted.
Like, I've been surpassed the 7 plus Tech taskbar tweaker.
Does.
This job better than my code.
I recommend you selling said, I installed this.
I do not actually see any option for doing it.
So I don't know if I'm just using the tool wrong.
I haven't tried this one yet.
I guess I could try it just to get a few more viruses on my machine.
You know, it's always good but I don't actually know.
Yeah, if it would actually work, I could try it.
And I don't, I just don't understand why this guy thinks that this
tool does it.
They doesn't actually say how you would do it.
You can see here.
Like, I've got this thing installed.
If you open it up, right?
I don't even see an option for it.
I don't even see, I don't even see a heading where the option would
go.
but I don't know, like there just doesn't seem to be
I got nothing.
There doesn't seem to be any any actual thing here to click on.
You know, I'm saying.
You know what I'm saying?
Anyone, no, no.
Non this no one on the stream, probably knows because
I'm guessing that people on the stream, probably have already moved to
some other thing.
I should probably try to install a classic shell and see if that has
it or one of those other shell tools and see if it you know can
replace this whole task bar with something more usable.
But yeah, so he says install 7, plus taskbar speaker.
Here is 7 plus taskbar tweaker.
I do not actually see any options that actually would work dropping.
Hovering thumbnails pin left.
Click other high, the start button that actually does have the start
button.
That doesn't help.
Show desktop button can go away.
That doesn't help either.
Although I'd be fine with having that go.
I never use that button.
Just like s is good, but doesn't help here Reserve empty space doesn't
help doesn't do anything in our case.
I just I don't know.
I guess I could look at the help me.
The help has something.
Let's see, search top.
Some of these symptoms that you tune aspects of the tweeker disabled
10 topmost.
Oh,
wait, so
It does have a setting, but how do you access the setting options X?
That's what you can use to manage objects is it can be opened from the
tray icon?
Okay.
All right.
Let me see if I right click on the tray icon Advanced.
Okay?
Wait for it.
People.
This could be exciting.
This could be exciting right here.
Apply.
Okay.
I think I also accidentally shut this thing off.
So it's a run at startup.
Okay.
All right done.
There we go.
Let's take a look.
That does not appear to be disabling, topmost to me, but maybe it did.
I don't know, doesn't look like it.
Let's take a look by default.
Passwords are taught this option, allows change Behavior.
Always on top, not always on top, but not over.
Okay, so I gotta set it to two.
Rtfm, I guess is the answer there.
Let's try it.
One minute left in the Stream.
Can we do it?
Can we do it to return?
Apply?
Okay.
Oh my God, look at it.
Are you looking at it?
Look at how beautiful that is.
That is so excellent.
Although it ruins other topmost windows.
Like my top most windows are now not topmost anymore.
So close and yet so far.
Why would you taunt me like that people?
Why?
Well, I guess we could also just double-check trying could exit the
timer app and then start the timer app again.
I suppose it's see if that helps.
There we go.
So I guess it just it.
Did it to all top level Windows.
It must have messed up the Z order.
All right.
So what day are we on?
I don't even know.
What is it day?
37.
I want to say, Let's Take a Look, What day, what actual day are we at
right now?
Sorry.
We may have actually solved this problem.
So I'm pretty happy about that.
But let's see what make sure we're on the right day here.
Video archive day, 37 was yesterday.
So we're on day 38 today.
All right.
Well, that's pretty exciting.
You have to admit that is is pretty exciting.
I am relatively excited about that.
Let's get all this stuff straightened out.
Again.
That means we no longer have this ridiculous unused area at the top of
the screen.
We can actually have everything go up to the height that was supposed
to be.
Let's see, does RE/MAX go to the whole?
Look at that?
That's fantastic.
Well, that is just great news.
I'm very happy about that.
That is super cool.
You know, this is a little things.
You know, I'm saying?
Even if someone else had to write them for for Microsoft, at least
someone did there we go.
All right.
I guess we can start the stream now.
I hope everyone shared in that Triumph.
I don't know if they did or not.
Can't see what's going on on there.
Yeah.
Yeah, I think everyone's pretty except excited.
I know I am.
So let's go ahead and get the, get the gloves on here and we will, we
will go ahead and start the stream.
Now that we've had that, that small victory.
I guess, I can close the old command prompt from yesterday as well.
Get back to our standard standard screen.
And we can actually get programming, which seems like a pretty good
idea.
Since this is supposed to be handmade hero, not handmade fighting with
the windows user interface.
Taskbar out of the way, even though sometimes that is what programming
ends up being fighting with Microsoft to get it out of your way is
often thing that does happen when you're programming.
So, you know, it's not that far off I suppose.
But let us go ahead and return to the program.
Hello, everyone.
Welcome to day 38 of handmade hero the show where we coded complete
game from scratch using nothing, but our typing a little fingers.
No libraries, no engines.
So we can actually see
See the complete process of making game and you can learn how
absolutely everything works, right from where the pixels are drawn on
the screen, all the way up to how the game code operates at a high
level.
So today we happen to be at the point where we are putting Sprites on
the screen and we are not doing our full render yet because that's a
little bit more of an involved process.
But basically we just wanted to have something where we could easily
put some graphics up on the screen for our own testing purposes.
As we are sort of going through and figuring out what we want.
Engine architecture.
And one of the big parts of that obviously is going to be what we want
for our rendering architecture and it's kind of hard to make those
decisions without something to work with.
So that's what we wrote yesterday.
But we have a couple things left that we need to do to it.
So that's what we're going to be doing today.
If you'd like to follow along at home and you went to handmade here at
Oregon pre-ordered, the source code.
You should have gotten a link in your email address in your email,
inbox and that link will allow you to download both the art assets
that were using and it will also allow you to download the source
code.
So if you download that source code
today is day 38.
So go ahead and unzip day, 37 source code out of the source code ZIP
file.
So zip file is basically has a ton of little zip files in.
It's like a Russian nesting doll kind of thing.
And there you go.
That will basically give you the same source code that I am starting
with right now.
So let's go ahead, we've got a bunch of stuff to do.
So, let's get to it.
I'm going to open up the debugger here and just point out where we
were before, if you remember, we were looking at putting the Sprite up
on the screen, but the colors were wrong.
And so,
Question was, what was going on there?
And it turned out that since I think it was my fault.
Actually.
I had run a little resizing tool on some of the I'd run imagemagick to
resize, some of the bitmaps and it wrote them out in a different byte
order than the ones that came straight out again.
And so, basically, what we have to do today, we figured out this at
the end of last dream that basically the bitmap header has these
things of the bottom red green and blue mask that we figured out, and
we've got them laid out in here.
So we know where they are and the in the files.
Well, that basically tell us where the red green and blue components
go and it's I guess assumed that the alpha is just whatever these
aren't because there's obviously an alpha component as well and there
isn't an alpha mask parameter as far as I can tell.
Although maybe there actually is an extended version of the file
format.
I'm not sure, but when we were looking on, on the website of the
documentation, it looked like it was only red green and blue but
doesn't really matter because we can tell if the alpha is because it's
where the red green and blue isn't.
so,
what we need to do here is we need to, I don't know if you remember
this.
But basically, we already we're doing a thing where we were swapping
around the order of the stuff that came in because it wasn't the order
that we wanted.
So, our pixels were packed with a BGR, which is this thing right here.
And so this is actually not correct anymore.
This comment we've learned is erroneous.
And so basically what we need to do is change this to say what's
actually going on, which is the byte order in memory is determined by
the header itself.
So,
We have to read out the masks and convert our pixels ourselves.
Right?
And so that's what we're going to have to do today.
So basically now we assume that when we load one of these BMP files,
we have no idea what order things are in.
And we basically have to go ahead and figure out where they are.
Now we could for we, now know, we know that, basically, none of the
files that we're saving, you're going to have anything other than 8
bits per channel.
So, we do know that we're basically looking at a number
0xff, kind of a mass, but we just don't know where it actually is in
the 32 bits.
We don't really know where it shows up.
So what we need to do is we basically need to get a shift value for
each of our components.
So, if you think about it, we basically have a redshift not to be
confused with the kind of red shift that they use in astronomy.
Obviously, that's a different kind of red ship, but we have a
redshift, a green shift, a blue shift, and an alpha shift, right?
There we go.
And so what we're going to have to do, is we have to figure out what
those are and they're gonna have to come in here and actually get them
out.
Right?
And so when we actually build our thing, we could make this a little
simple by taking the actual color value, grab that, and then we could
do it this way.
Just make it a little more easy for us to write here.
We basically can figure that we know, we need to put pack things such
that the alphas on top.
Then the red, then the green than the blue, right?
So what we need to do essentially, is
We need to shift the red.
Well, you know what?
Unfortunately, I don't know that there's really any way we can do the
shift totally generically in with only one shift.
I'd have to think about that because really, we need to shift it.
It could have to shift in either direction, right, where, where the
red is in our source.
I don't know if you guys are already on the same page here in terms of
what I want to do.
But basically, I've got something where I've done.
You know, I've got a 32-bit value, right?
This is my 32-bit value.
And essentially, I've got the eight.
Here, the this is 8, Bits, 8, B 8, B, 8 Bits, right?
This is the low, this is the high, and basically, what I need to do is
I've got, you know, some set of things.
I've got the red is Summer of the green of Summer.
The blue is somewhere whatever.
So I've got my ABCD and I basically need to rearrange these right in
some arbitrary way.
Like I have no idea where they actually need to go.
But I know that I'm going to determine where they need to go.
So what I need to be able to do is I need to be able to mask it out
and then shift it to the right location, but I don't actually know
which direction is going to have to go.
It may be that like this was the green before and the green now has to
go here.
So the shift would actually be a left shift, right?
It be getting higher but it could be the other way around where it's
actually below.
And so it's actually Gonna Be Right shift, right?
And since I don't actually know if there's really any way to write
that concisely, what I think I'm going to have to do instead is first
shift it down and then shift it up.
So I know that my shifts are
Always basically are always going to be to the right for the
parametric amount.
So basically my to take the C and I'll shift it down by the alpha
shift value, right?
Whatever that Alpha shift value is, I will end it with with the mask.
So that I know that I've basically, now just got the alpha sitting in
the low eight bits, and then I'll shift it up by 24 to put it in the
position where I actually want my Alpha to be right.
So that is basically what I'm going to do for each of my values.
Just so I can
Usually a lot of times people call this like a swizzle.
Not really sure why they call it a swizzle.
But a lot of times I do so I basically want to get the red the green
and the Blue by shifting them down like this masking them and then
putting them back into the place where I actually want them to be like
that.
And so really, all I need to do here is figure out what the shift
would be to get whatever the value is down into the bottom down to the
bottom eight.
Bits problem is, I don't actually have that.
I have the mask.
And I don't have an alpha mask technically, right?
Hello.
That was odd.
What I actually have.
I've got the red mask, right?
That comes out of the header red mask.
I've got the the green mask.
I've got the blue mask, but the alpha mask actually, isn't there?
As far as we know, right?
I don't actually have an alpha mask.
So what I'm going to do is I'm going to assume that the alpha mask is
just wherever there wasn't a red, a green or a blue.
So if I
Or the other mask together.
Basically make a composite mass that would mass for red green and
blue.
All the same time.
I'm going to assume that the not of that.
If I flip all the bits in that, that I'm going to get basically where
the alpha is, right?
Because that will basically give us wherever the other ones aren't,
right?
And I'll just I'll dummy up these values for a moment just so I can
show you what I'm talking about.
For those of you who may not be super comfortable with bit operations
yet.
I think it's amusing, actually, but I think someone was actually
asking, just on like a stream like yesterday or the day before or
whether we, how, if B operations, normally get used in today is like
all about bid operations, right?
So the answer is definitely yes.
Anyway, so if we read out the red green, the blue mask, you can see
them here, right?
There's the red mask, the green mask, and the blue mask, that's saying
it's basically the Reds in the high Greens.
In the second down the blues and the second from the bottom and the
end the alpha.
We don't
No, we don't get that.
Right.
So what I'm going to do is going to order them all together.
Which will basically produce 0xffff, right?
And then I'm going to knot it so you can see that.
Basically what I get is I get what the the part is that isn't filled
in in any of these other ones, right?
And so that's what that that's what I wanted.
Just wanted to fill in that extra value.
Right?
And I can do that a little more explicitly, if you guys want just to
just to see what I'm talking about here.
Right?
I can do it in two steps.
I wish they allowed you to step into an expression and be so much
nicer.
God.
What do
All the things debuggers could do and don't.
So there's the alpha mask first before I have not had it right?
You can see basically, or them together.
I get the composite of all of those masks, basically.
And then the not just flips, just flips what the actual values are,
right?
So that's what that's what I was doing there.
So that gives you all the masks, but now we have a problem, which is
basically, we need to actually know, essentially, what the lowest bit
is that set in these values, right?
Because we need to know how far down to shift.
So we're simply want to count how many
There are that are zero starting from the first bit and going up to
the very first bit that set right now.
What's interesting about this is, this is actually something the
processor can, sometimes, actually, just do for you.
It's called a bit scan, right?
And basically, like, well, you know what?
I can even probably search for it here, right?
So if I look in here and say, B can forward, there we go.
If I take a look at this here, you can look at the msdn.
It's actually compiler intrinsic, the compiler.
Can
You instructions for it.
Basically, what it says is, it'll search from the least significant
bit, right?
Which if you remember, if I was least significance at the bottom,
right?
So this is this is we're talking about the bit here.
This is the most significant.
This is the least significant bit.
This is the most significant one, right?
And this in our 32-bit value.
So this is B 31, and this is B 0.
Okay.
So basically we do B, can forward.
What we can do.
There is we can say, okay.
What I'd like you to do is, give me back whatever the position.
Mission was where the first bit was set.
Right?
So tell me which bit was the first one set, which is kind of what we
want.
Because up here somewhere.
We've got eight bits set, right somewhere.
And we want to know how far to shift them down so that they line up
right here.
So they start here.
And so really what we're trying to do is we're trying to do a bit scan
to find where that value is, right?
So we can implement this ourselves obviously, right?
We could go ahead and actually search for it so I could do for example
I could come in here and say internal and I could basically have I
guess a Bool 32, for example, if I guess I don't really know because
this the way that this processor I don't actually remember what the
how the actual instruction works, but it looks like the way this thing
works.
Is it basically returns a Boolean that says whether or not it found a
bit at all and then it writes to an index to tell you where we're that
index, where it did actually find it.
So if we were going to mirror the way that that work base,
It's an unsigned care that it returns.
And so I don't actually know that I care about that so much.
I'm going to do a un 32 there and then it's going to be an unsigned
in.
That's the that's the index as well.
So basically it looks something like this.
It's can forward, right?
And if I go ahead in here and say, all right, I want to implement this
myself, right?
You can kind of see how we would do it.
It's not particularly complicated, right?
We just have a un 32.
Well, I can actually do a pool 32 here because it's still 32-bit value
and I can, you know, found equals false.
I can then do a search like literally with a for Loop, right, which
is, you know,
Equals zero, test is less than 32 plus plus test, right?
And then I can do value and one shifted up by whatever the test amount
is.
And if that turns out to be set, right?
If value, and one should set up test, turns out to be set, then I will
write the value of the bit into the result and otherwise, I will not
and so that will basically give me, you know, whichever one.
It hits.
Now if I find one.
Oh, sorry.
I've I've actually done that slightly backwards if we're trying to
look for the first but that's set not the first with that's not set.
So we actually as soon as we find one that is set.
We want to stop looking and if we didn't hit one, we will write to our
index value, right?
So if it's a zero, we count that as a, as a as an index.
Okay, nevermind.
No, I'm correct.
I was correct.
The first I'm sorry.
I got I confused my own self there.
As soon as we find out the set were actually trying to return that
index.
So we just set the index equal to the one we found and we break out.
Everything should be fine.
Right?
And and I guess we set found equal to True here so that we know that
we actually found when we can return the value properly.
Now, let me take a look here because since I confused my own self
during the explanation, let's actually go ahead and make sure that we
actually did it correctly.
So this is redshift, we pass the address of red shift and we will
basically look and see red found equals that and we can assert read
found like so, and then we'll compile that.
Oh, right.
We already have the redshift we go.
So, and what was the problem?
Cannot convert argument one from in 32?
Oh, yes, right.
Sorry you and 32, there we go.
So, if I go ahead in here and actually step into it, what I should
find is that I pass in here.
I've got a value that I'm checking for.
It's all the way at the top.
So I'm expecting the value to basically 24, right?
So I come in here.
And I keep shifting up test to see whether it actually hits against
the value.
It's not going to hit for the first twenty four times, right?
Blah blah blah blah, blah.
Well 23 times.
I should say turn off.
Hexadecimals.
You can see 13, testing testing, testing testing, testing testing up
to 20 22, 23, and now, 24 should hit it writes back to the index.
So, now, the index gets 24 written to it.
At least that's what should happen find out.
Oops, start Index, right 24.
We say that we did find it and then we return.
So, there we go.
We've done.
The B can forward.
And we say that red was found.
The red shift is 24, which is exactly what we wanted.
So that's the B can operation, but we're now doing it a very slow way.
So what we'd like to do is we'd like to actually have the processor,
do it.
And this is the perfect time to talk a little about the intrinsics
things that I keep alluding to, but haven't actually done yet.
So, maybe today we will actually do intrinsic so that we can
The B can forward.
Okay.
Yeah.
Also, I should point out for those of you who aren't familiar with
these, there's a bunch of these sorts of things.
Right?
So you can actually count the other way as well.
If you want to do from the from the high downward to count, like the
basically the zeros that come at the top, you can call the reverse
version.
So so, you know, you've got, there's yeah, there's a bunch of
intrinsics that will output those sort of things that the combat the
CPU can do, but that don't really have any way of specifying them in
C, /, say so,
Let's go ahead and get this working first with that.
But then, what I think we might do is just go ahead and do that today.
So we can go ahead and do move this into the intrinsics and call the
MS, VC version, and there we go, and we can leave this, you know, sort
of slow implementation as the reference implementation as well, which
will be nice.
Because that would basically mean that, you know, we wouldn't have
sort of a yeah, we wouldn't have a problem if people wanted to compile
on an architecture where the CPU can't do that and
A just need a slow version of it to make it work.
That's good too.
Because remember, this isn't really time critical here.
So at least for this function, it wouldn't matter.
If you could, you could use the slowest possible thing and it wouldn't
really matter.
Right?
So the other thing too is I wonder if I should fix the API little bit
because I guess we can always wrap the intrinsic in our own in line
that just kind of would get, you know, kind of felt a little bit.
I could make it so you don't have to pass an address there basically.
So I could do something more like this, which is like a bit.
Scan result or something like that, which is, you know, whether or not
it was found and the UN 32, that was the index, write something like
this.
And then that could do something that looks more like that in line, B
can result.
So B can result and that would equal, you know, nothing at first.
Having some typing problems today.
It was true.
And so then when we actually go through, we will then return the
result here and we will do results that index equals tests and results
found equals true like that and break out and then we'll return the
result that way.
And so that would be a little handier than having to do sort of
passing the address nonsense, which doesn't seem particularly useful
to me.
I don't I don't
Really think there's any reason to structure it like that.
I was just mirroring the way they were doing it in the other one.
So now you can basically do something like this where we basically
have these.
So we'll just get the bit scan results out of our mask values directly
like that, and we'll do the B can forwards here.
And, you know, the other thing I might do, since I'm kind of in charge
now and not Microsoft at B can forwards, kind of a weird term.
Maybe I would do something like
Find lowest find least significant.
One.
Bit personally, significant set bit, something like that, right?
Because that actually says, what it is like B can forward.
Well, what do you mean by forward?
At least now?
We know, we're trying to find the least significant one that set and
so that actually seems, maybe a little more saying to me.
I don't know, I guess it would depend on endianness things and blah,
blah, blah, but I think that might be a little bit better because at
least, I understand what that is.
When I read it at least on one architecture, it makes sense.
So that seems like perhaps a better idea.
So let's go
And do that will now get each of them out blue mask, and Alpha mask.
So now we have found those and now we just shift those by, their
indices like so index, index, index, index.
And we can also do an assertion on each of them because basically,
we're not supporting loading anything but doesn't have all of these
channels at the moment.
Maybe.
In the future we would.
But for now we want at least ensure that we don't actually
accidentally load something that doesn't have one of these channels.
So let's take a look at where that puts us on the scale of fixing our
color problems.
Hey, it looks exactly right.
It to me.
Now.
The only thing that we're not handling now is, of course, the alpha
blending around those the edges and on the background.
And that's the next thing we have to do.
Anyway, so that seems like a pretty good thing to do.
I'm going to go ahead and say though, that, since we're, we've got a
fair bit of time here, I'm just going to go ahead and give the
intrinsic thing a shot.
Just because it's about time that we
Started talking about those sorts of things.
We don't have to do very much.
It's not very complicated.
It's a very simple thing to do so it might be a good one to start
with.
So basically what I want to do in here is I want to move this B can
result.
I want to move this out and I want to move it to here.
Right?
And so, what I want to do is be able to have this this function, such
that if we are
Compiler.
That can do it really quickly.
It will do it and, and not have to go through this for Loop.
It'll it said, just tell the processor to basically tell the processor
to do it, you know, in a much more expedient way if that makes sense.
So really, what I need to do here is I need to be able to figure out
whether or not, you know, basically whether I'm on it, what compiler?
I'm on if that makes sense.
And as you know,
No, I said, I talked about quite a bit at the beginning, you want to
keep all of your stuff segregated as much as possible in terms of
keeping platform code out of platform-independent code.
Right?
So, you'll notice that we buried everything inside, win32 handmade and
you'll notice, none of this stuff leaks out into our main code.
All the win32 specific code is all in here.
Right?
But there are limits to what we can do there.
If we don't want to sacrifice performance, like what I could do here.
Right is like a call a function back in the platform layer that did
this operation.
Right?
And that would keep it and I could even pass in a pointer to that
function.
So it was completely isolated.
I could do all kinds of stuff.
But the problem is the only reason why you ever care about intrinsics
in the first place is for performance.
If we didn't care about performance, we just run this for Loop, right?
So the intrinsics file, the whole point of this intrinsics file is
going to be the, this is the place.
Where we make a compromise and say that, this is the place where we
are, allowed to do Platform specific stuff that can be directly
included right into the code of platform nonspecific stuff, if that
makes sense.
And again, the only reason we're doing that is performance.
If we didn't care about performance at all, if we literally just had
no performance concerns, then there would be no reason to do this.
There'd be no point.
You would just always do things the way we had been doing them.
But in the case of intrinsics, which are, which you're only using
really
You're caring about performance in the first place.
This is where that sort of stuff comes in.
And so what you want to do is you basically want to have it isolated
again, you know, even though it's you're sort of saying it's okay to
mix things up a little bit here.
You still want it as isolated as possible.
And so you want to basically boil it down to like a file or two that
have compiler switches in them and that bring in that sort of non
independent parts of the code.
Right, so that's basically what we're going to do here.
So what we're going to do is basically say, you know, if the compiler
is msv, see right, then we know that we can issue this thing, because
this compiler happens to support this B can forward thing, right?
And we want to do from low LSB to MSB.
So we're basically going to call this one.
We know that, in this case.
We're scanning a 32-bit value.
So basically what we're going to do here is we're going to call this B
can forward.
The result found is going to be equal to that return value.
We're going to
pass the address of the
That we wanted to be set and it'll set it and then we're going to pass
that value.
And so that's just going to allow it to do it right there.
And we're going to make sure this is marked in line.
So hopefully, if the compiler isn't Dumb, it will go ahead and say,
oh, yes, we can go ahead and inline this directly and turn this into a
instruction, right?
So that's about all we have to do there.
But we have to do this compiler and determination.
And so, I'm going to go back to our handmade believe, it's handmade
platform, right?
Yeah, in handmade platform.
What I'm
Going to introduce at the top kind of like, you know, we have this
sort of basic.
This is like the basic setup for the code.
This is what has to happen in the code.
I'm going to do a little thing here, which basically says, you know,
compiler M SV C is 0 and maybe compiler llvm.
Because I know those are the two things.
At least that we will compile under, right, and what we will do is
will sort of do an if here on some kind of thing.
Basically, if you know, if not,
Compiler msv.
See, I should do this way.
If and F compiler, MSNBC.
And if and if and F llvm this, you know, I could write these out a
little bit more cleanly so you can kind of see what they're doing.
So short, if end f is like a shorthand could do to find that.
So what I'm going to do is if the compiler variables and maybe I'll
even make a little section here like this and just going to be, you
know,
No note, Casey types like this.
Thank you, emacs, for, indenting me, for a pits, finding the C++
bracket.
There are doing the indentation, which I didn't actually want to do,
what you gonna do compilers.
So basically, what I want to do here is I want to basically say, okay.
If the build system, whoever is building us our batch file, whatever,
if they want to explicitly set what the compiler is, then we'll just
let them set it.
So basically we're only going to set these if they're not already set
then.
So we're going to end.
We're going to clear them to 0 or actually, I guess what we could do
is if they're not already set, right, then what we do is at the end
here.
Now I still need to do this.
So we need to do something like if the, if the compiler is not set at
all.
If we have no compiler set whatsoever.
Right?
This sort of thing.
Then inside here is where I'm going to actually try to determine what
the compiler actually is.
So if neither the compiler things have been set by anyone, then I'm
going to go ahead and try to see what the compiler actually is.
And MSD.
See, for example, will automatically Define something that tells us
what it is.
I don't remember.
It's like Ms.
Seaver.
I mean, I think it's it's something like that, but I want to actually
go see
See what it actually is before I make that block Proclamation,
underscore it, Miss Seaver.
Yeah, almost underscore Ms.
Seaver.
So basically
I want to do that and say if that's true.
Then compiler.
M SV, C equals 1, right?
And then what we'll also do is we'll do an else here.
And in this case, we'll just assume it's llvm for now, but we'll put
it to do here which is basically like more compilers or something.
Right?
Maybe even like that.
And So eventually we'll do something a little smarter than that as we
go.
But right now we're only compiling an MS VC.
So, you know, for now that should be good enough.
So when we actually do that, let's take a look at what happens here.
Oh, right.
We have to undefined compiler, it because we Define it 2-0 and you
can't just change it.
Unfortunately, you gotta undef it first like so and then when I got 11
missing end of, so then there's a end if they're.
All right.
So now it's coming that B can forward is not defined and that may be
true.
Let's see what has to be defined in order.
Therefore that to exist somewhere.
Let's see.
Well it looks like we just need to do that or do we actually have to
pound include intron .h.
I'm not actually sure if we need to do that or not we could take a
look.
I guess the first thing we could do is try this first and see what it
does.
So if we are defining msv, see, we can basically now have our little
section where we do the things that,
We want to do if M SV C is here, such as that pragma in terms of
function not declared.
So, okay, so I guess we have to do include this file as well, which is
the intrinsics and then we'll see.
Okay, B.
Can forward cannot convert argument one from you in 30, to start to
unsigned long star.
Why not types pointed to her unrelated?
Is that really true?
Why would those be unrelated, I guess unsigned in and unsigned long or
technically different types.
Oh, the mysteries of C++, Ivan program it for so long, and yet things
like that, always still confuse me.
I'm like, what actually do, you believe the technical difference to be
between those types?
And I have absolutely no idea.
Oops, put that in the wrong place.
There we go.
So I believe that should probably work.
Let's find out and see if it does and hey guess what it does.
And now let's take a look in there and see what it actually did
differently now when we step into it.
So if you step in here, you can see that this is actually using this,
this line that we
Talked about, and if you go to the disassembly, we can take a look at
what it does.
So essentially what happens here is, do you see this BSF?
That's B can forward.
It's literally one Assembly Language instruction.
That does all the work of that for Loop.
Now, don't let that fool you because Assembly Language Learners can
still take a while to execute sometimes.
But the point here is basically that
That is so much more concise certainly to the processor and it's
probably going to be much faster than if we were to actually have two
micro to code the loop ourselves.
Because if this is executing something in microcode, that's still
going to be a lot faster, right?
So basically, what happens here, in fact, you can even watch work,
what it's going to do here is going to move the value.
This thing right here.
It's going to load that value into the eax register, right?
And that's this register right here.
It's a little confusing because we're in x64 mode, which means that it
uses are a x to denote the ax artistry.
Because it's 64 bits long.
But really, what we're talking about is we're talking about the bottom
portion of it here, right?
We're talking about the bottom 32-bit value.
So, when we do that, you see how it loaded it in there.
There it is.
You just loaded it right there.
And now it's going to call that BSF function on the value in the
register to load it out.
Right.
It goes ahead and does that and the destination is also EXO.
It's going to write the result back in there.
Right?
And you can see that it wrote the result back in there.
And that's the result that we were expecting, right?
That's what we wanted to actually have again.
It's the next
Small, which is why it looks like an 18 instead of a 24.
But you know, that's that's just well, you know, I can, I can.
Here you go.
So x 18, right?
You can see that, that's just the hexadecimal encoding for 24.
So there it is.
And then that is the entirety that right there did like the entirety
of that, this Loop, right?
So, that's intrinsics in a nutshell.
They're really pretty simple.
And basically, what we want to do is we want to do those for anything,
where there is a convenient CPU instructions, so that we can access it
because we don't want to go around especially
When we start getting more time critical code, we don't want to go
around wasting a lot of that stuff that the processor could do for us
by obvious getting it.
Now.
It's possible that the compiler might have actually been smart enough,
sometimes depending on the compared, to actually realize that this is
a bit scan forward, but why make it do that when we could just go
ahead and say this is exactly what we want.
Right?
And so now we've done that and we're in good shape.
So now we're loading our stuff and we're pretty happy.
But if you actually take a look at what happens here, you'll notice
that we would like to be able to composite.
This guy on top of things and right now we're not actually doing that.
And so that brings up use of the alpha Channel, which we should talk
about.
Now.
It's actually very, very easy for us to make this work.
But, you know, well, you know what?
I'll do first, I'll basically show you the really simple version
first, and then we'll talk about it a little bit.
So, as, you know, the alpha channel, right?
If you remember, how this is, how this works, in the actual art tool.
Let me see if I can actually.
How would I do this?
I'll go too.
A handmade data test and I will load up that hero front head.
There we go, edit with gimp.
So if we look at this here.
You can see that basically you've got your red green and blue color
channels.
But you also have a fourth Channel and that channel is called the
alpha Channel.
Now, most people probably sort of, you know, even if you don't know
exactly what that is, you know intuitively now what it is because
you've probably seen it in pain.
G like, you've probably worked with it before, right?
And so, if we take a look at the channels dialogue, let's take a look
here inside gimp.
There's a channels dialogue, right?
Which is this, you can actually see.
I can turn off the channels and we can actually see the alpha Channel
by itself.
Right.
Instead of the other channels, which is basically all the alpha
channel is is it's basically just something that says where the image
exists and where it doesn't and it's got partial values around the
edges.
That basically say, well the it was transitioning at this point,
right?
It was transitioning.
It's anti-aliasing that edge basically, right?
It's giving a partial value because the shape obviously can't be rep
is not perfectly pixelated.
The shape was actually supposed to be a smooth line that went through
there.
And so, these Alpha values are basically there to kind of smooth that
out.
And to sort of give you that gradual fall off.
So, it's not a hard cookie cutter Edge, right?
It just kind of feathers.
The things that's the background for you.
That's the way the art was set up to work.
So right now we're drawing those
Green and blue channels but we're not doing anything with the alpha
Channel.
And obviously, since the alpha channel is the only thing that tells us
where the image exists, we need to start doing something with the
alpha channel to display.
The person such that display things on top of other things, so that
like bottom layers show through Upper layers, right?
And so inside our renderer, this is going to work.
Well.
Yeah, I won't say how it's going to work in the render in a surly.
That's that's a little premature.
So, let's not say that word.
Let's say a different word.
What I'm actually going to say, it's not that what I'm going to say
is, let's talk about one way.
We could easily implement this for our testing purposes, for our
testing purposes.
What we can do is basically do exactly what Photoshop or anything else
does, where we basically just think about things, in terms of layers.
We could draw something first, we could draw down, you know, our trees
or whatever in the background, right?
And then, we want to stick a guy.
On top of that.
What we would do is we'd essentially think of creating a separate
layer, right?
Which has our guy on it.
And basically, what we'll do is when we draw that layer will only draw
in the places where the alpha Channel says, there was actually a shape
and we won't touch what's underneath in the places where it's not.
So will basically do compositing very much the way you would think
about in Photoshop where you have one layer and you're basically
drawing layers on top of each other and you just don't draw where the
alpha Channel says there isn't anything.
A thing and that gives you the so through.
So it's basically like it's like taking pieces of paper cutouts and
stacking them on top of each other wherever it was cut out.
You can still see through to the thing.
That was underneath, right?
So that Alpha layer of alpha channel, is basically telling us where to
do the cutout.
It's basically what tells us how to do the cut out.
So, how do we actually Implement that, right?
Well, while we are drawing, right, we basically have something, you
know, we've got our trees, you know, they're there and then we've got
our guy and
Got the alpha channel on him that says where things exist.
And basically, it's 0 everywhere where he does not exist.
Its 255 everywhere that he does.
And at the edges, it's somewhere between those two values, right?
So it's basically a brightness value, you might think of it between 0
and 25 that says what, you know, how much he exists at that particular
point.
So what we would like to do right?
Is we like to think about that essentially for now as an opacity value
basically to say how much of the guy Blends through and by the
Way we could use this Alpha Channel as well, for partial transparency.
Like if we have something that's supposed to be, sort of ghost-like,
that we want to sort of only partially blind on just, like in
Photoshop, how you can paint the alpha channel, to be some middle
value, like 128, or something that's partially translucent.
We might want to do that too.
So what we'd like to do is use this value essentially as a way of
blending in between the two, right?
So I don't want to talk about that yet because let's just do the
simplest possible thing.
Let's do something that just for
Starters uses zero or 255 or sort of rather on or off.
So, will basically say, if it's zero, we won't draw anything and if
it's 255, or sorry, if it's anything from 1 to 255.
Anything in between, we will I guess.
Another thing we could do is say, 128 is the cutoff.
So basically anything less than 128.
We won't try anything created the 128.
We will draw right?
You can pretty much see how we could do that.
Very simply, right?
Because we're iterating over all the pixels of the guy in our
drawbitmap.
Er Team right.
We iterate.
Over all the values here to do this dest plus plus equals Source plus,
right?
So what we could do instead is we could go ahead and change the way
this works.
We could do both, we could always do both advances, right?
And we can isolate just the copy like that.
And what we could say is if that Source value, The Source part that's
coming in extract the alpha, right?
We shifted down by 24 to get, just the alpha by itself.
If that value is greater than 128, then we do the copy.
Otherwise we do.
Makes sense, right?
So if we did that,
And we ran it, we now get much more of what we would expect to get,
right.
We now get something which doesn't draw the guy everywhere where he
had an alpha value less than 128 and it does draw the guy everywhere.
There's a value over 128 and all we did was just add that one simple
test, right?
That's all we were doing.
Now.
What you'll notice is it has a very hard edge around him, right?
If I was to do the the the zooming on this, right?
Let's say we go into creating their own.
I don't actually know if how crito work sir.
Can I do a paste as New Image paste into New Image?
I don't know what you're asking me.
I don't know.
I don't really know how to use this program.
Does this what I want.
I don't even know.
All right.
Yeah, I guess it is.
It's doing what I wanted.
Okay, good enough.
So if you look in here, you can see, you know, there's a lot of
antioxidants.
This is very smooth Graphics.
There's a lot of anti aliasing everywhere in here.
There's a lot of kind of, you know, blurring of those edges to make
them a little smoother.
That's kind of the way the artworks, but when we get to this guy,
you'll notice there's no smooth.
There's no blending there at all.
So it's a very hard pixel Edge along the guy.
And the reason for that again, is because we're not using any partial
Alpha values at.
All, right, we're not doing anything to try and use those values that
are in between 0 and 255.
We're just making a hard cut off.
Now, what this is often called.
In fact, you'd see this called this in
3D Graphics lot.
It's called Alpha test is what this is called, which is basically a
hard clamp limit, which basically just looks at the alpha value and
says, I'm either going to do an operation or not based on whether the
alpha exceeds a threshold or not.
And that is exactly what we implemented.
This is basically Alpha test right here, but we'd like to do, is
something a little bit better than Alpha test.
We'd rather do something that's actually some kind of an alpha blend.
A blend that uses the alpha Bal you to compute.
The, the resulting color that will.
What's underneath to actually and show through what's underneath in
case, the alpha value is not to be 5, that make sense.
Now we are going to do this in the slowest and dumbest possible way
because I'd like to make show the math being explicit.
And so this will not be fast by any stretch of the imagination.
It will be very slow.
But again, we are not writing the render at the moment.
What we're trying to do is write stuff that we can use and so what I'd
rather do is just so well, you know what,
No, I'm not going to talk about how to do any of the fast stuff.
We're just going to do it being the slowest possible way.
So what we'd like to do now.
Is we'd like to go ahead and and see about how to actually do that.
Alpha planned.
Now, I probably shouldn't spend too much time belaboring this because
there's actually an entire video in fact of me explaining
interpolation.
And I don't know whether we want to rehash that entirely on the stream
or just to that just crash.
I think creates it just totally crashed on me.
It did, didn't it?
Yes, it did create.
It.
Just totally just crashed.
It just full-on.
It's full-on.
Went away completely.
Well, what you gonna do?
Let's launch it back up.
Come on.
You can do it.
It was working.
So, well, there for a while.
See, I tried to make a new image.
I guess.
The, the thing to remember is never tried to make a new image.
People.
That's the rules.
You don't ever want to make a new image.
All right, that's fine.
Make the image please.
There we go.
Hello.
All right, okay.
So, here we go.
So what we need to essentially do here, right?
Is, I want to make something that allows us to smoothly blend.
Between the two values.
So we have a background value, right?
Don't know why that's always the hand shake just is, I guess the hand
was what they thought was good there.
So I have a background color that's coming in.
Right?
I've got a hand.
Apparently that's drawing this.
Now.
I've got a background color.
It's funny to have it be a hand like that, that help at all.
Nope.
That doesn't help at all.
Welcome to the mysteries of the universe.
Ladies and gentlemen, I've got a background pixel.
So this is one pixel, right?
I've got a background pixel and I've got
A foreground pixel, right that this is the spry.
Guess I'll call this the Sprite pixel, the bitmap pixel that we're
drawing, right?
So this is what ever is in the buffer, and this is whatever, is in the
thing.
We're putting on top, right?
And so, in this code here, we've got a source at a desk, right?
So, basically, this is the desk.
This is the thing we're writing to and we've got the source here.
This is the source.
This is the thing that we're trying to draw down.
This is the guy's head, right?
So, this is the trees pixels.
This is the head pixels, right?
So now if we do this,
what we need to do is this is some color, you know, let's call that
color a and this is another color will call that color.
Be.
Wow.
This is awful.
Like I can't even click down anymore.
I tell you computers these days.
Nothing ever works anymore.
Okay.
So I've got these two colors, A and B.
And what I want to do is I want to produce a third color, out of
these, right?
I want to produce a see that some blend between a and b and what I
want it to.
You is I want it to blend based on that Alpha channel, right?
I want the alpha channel to blend it such that when it's zero, I get
a.
And when it's 255, right?
I get B.
Does that make sense?
So,
When I actually go to do this.
What I need to do is figure out some some mathematical way.
Of getting from A to B smoothly based on another value, right?
I need to figure out some way to pick because if you think about the
number line, right, you know, I've got to 55 at the high end for each
Channel and I've got zero at the low end, right?
Essentially what I'm doing here is I'm saying I've got two points on
this and I don't really know where they are.
In fact, they don't even have to be any particular order, a could be
higher than b or vice versa or whatever, right?
So this is let's say, and this is what I say.
Colors, obviously, I mean one channel so we could think of this as
just the red channel, right?
Or the green Channel or the blue Channel, just one of them.
So what I'm going to do this, I basically have whatever was in the
background, whatever that channels color was, right?
That's here.
And then I have whatever the the new color is that I'm blowing it up.
Whatever that the Sprite is, whatever is in the guy.
and,
Here.
And what I need to do is figure out a way to produce all of these
values in between here, right?
I need to be able to produce all of those values based on what the
alpha channel is based on what the app that Alpha Channel says.
And if you have a channel 0 that I'm going to leave it where it was,
so I'm not going to touch the background at all.
If the alpha channel is 55.
I'm going to drive it all the way to be, right.
So essentially the way you could think about this and the way that I
usually like to sort of explain it to begin with.
Is that you can think of it as being based around one of the numbers
we can think of it as being based around the number.
That's that's zero Primal.
So the number where we have zero yields that value which in this case
is the background color, right?
We could think of starting there.
And what we want to do is we want to start there and we want to sort
of go some distance towards be where that distance is going to be 255.
If we went all the way right and 0 if we didn't, so
How do we produce?
What that?
What that actual distance is?
Right?
What's that value?
Well, if you know, rudimentary math, you already know what that is.
It's just B minus a right B.
Minus a is if you will almost and we haven't talked about vectors yet,
but it is essentially a one dimensional Vector but it's basically the
Delta, right?
It's the, it's the difference between a and b such that if I were to
take a star today and add back in some, you know, this this
The full portion I would get be and it's pretty trivial to see why
algebra wise write a plus B minus a well the to the a positive and a
negative cancel, and you just are left with B, which is the value that
I said we would get right.
So this is basically the core, the core of the thing that we're going
to use to determine how to blend something, right?
Because basically all I really need to do is take this expression, the
a plus the B, minus a right and say as if I can figure out some way to
only add part of this in there, right?
All I really need to do is stick some kind of a percentage in here,
right?
Some kind of a value that's like a percentage from 0 to 100%, right?
If I could just multiply this by some percentage, then I could go any
percentage of the way from A to B.
Just by changing.
What p is write a plus, some percent of the distance from A to B is
going to give me exactly what I want, right?
So, if we go ahead and build on that assumption, right?
If I want to say, I've got a plus some percentage here, right?
And also by convention, this is often called T.
I'll just point that out to you.
We can use that because you'll see it uses this way for a often.
But some percentage of the distance from A to B.
This would basically give me that value.
That I wanted.
This would be that result in color.
This would
The color that I wanted out, right?
So really all I have to do is figure out how to do this.
Now.
What you'll also notice is I can rearrange this expression in a couple
of different ways.
If, you know, algebra, which I'm hoping everyone on the stream does
because well, honestly, I've never thought about how to teach algebra
before.
So I don't suspect that would give a very good explanation, but
assuming, you know, algebra, then you also know that I can pretty
trivially Use the distributive property here to distribute T into this
expression.
And I would end up with these terms, right?
A
+ TB minus ta, right and I can rearrange those terms.
Anyway, I want to so I could group them this way, right?
I could group them here by just removing this term, this term here
moves here.
Right?
And this term stays where it is, this term, slides there.
If I do that rearrangement, what you can see here, is these two front
terms, both have an A in it, so I can pull out the 1, minus t there,
times a plus TB.
Okay, and now you have what's usually the more canonical version of
what's called a linear blend, right?
This is usually called a linear blend and what it is in either form,
doesn't matter which one you find more attractive.
They're just different ways of computing, the exact same thing, right?
Algebra.
It's the same thing.
All they are our way of taking one thing in.
That's your, you know, your starting value one thing in that you're
ending value and basically being able to produce anything in between
them by plugging, in this percentage value here, but we haven't
actually talked about how to actually make this percentage value work
in practice.
I just kind of magically wave my hand and said we had a percentage
value here.
So we now need to talk a little bit about just how that guy works.
Right?
Well, literally in the mass sense, and if you're doing this entirely
in floating Point math, it could literally
Be a percentage, right, you know how to translate percentages.
Again, if you've had high school math or whatever, you know, how to
track to translate percentages into floating Point math.
100 percent, right is 1.0., 50% is 0.5., Right?
0% is 0, right?
So the numbers between 0 and 1 all inclusive in, there are just those
percentages.
So really in this expression, if T were to rain,
Between zero and one, including on the fractional values in between
it.
Then no matter what a and b are, I don't care what they are.
They could be colors.
They could be anything positions in space.
Whatever doesn't matter.
This will give us a blend between them.
Right?
This will allow us to move smoothly between the two of them.
Okay, and so, if you're interested about in more about this sort of
stuff as well, I would also recommend if you do want to go to YouTube
on the handmade.
In fact, Youtube Casey Amira Tori, I think is what you would type in
here.
Let's see here.
Casey, Mira Tori on YouTube.
There we go.
You can actually see in my videos page.
There is a witness Wednesday part 10 interpolation video and that is a
full-on 50-minute explanation of interpolation and how it works in a
lot of different ways.
So basically, if you want to watch that for more information, you can
do that as well.
So, where are we at here?
We've only got seven minutes left.
So let's go ahead and slam in the floating-point version of this so
that we can actually see it in action and then maybe we'll go ahead
and fix it to be fixed.
Point version later, but basically you can see exactly what I'm
talking about here.
Right?
So
If I was to go in here and write the floating-point version of this,
let's go ahead and see what we get.
Right.
What I would get.
First of all is I got to extract my read.
Write and so my red channel is going to basically be shifted down by
by 16.
Whatever is in that Source, right?
And then masked off.
So, there we go.
And convert it to a float.
So, that's a number between 0 and 255.
There we go.
Do do so, then we have green.
I guess I could just do r g and B short, right?
The green is the eighth and that's zero then the alpha channel, right?
I need, I just said, I need it to be a number between 0 and 1.
Well, this will be a number between 0 and 255, right?
So if I want to turn a number between 0, to 5 into a number between 0
and 1, I need to divide by that range.
So I need to divide by 255.
So, that way 0 will map to 0 255 will map to one and everything in
between will map somewhere in between.
Right.
So now I've got an ARG and it be that are actually in floating point.
Now I need to do the exact equation.
I just said I need to create my new red.
So I'll say that my red is now going to be equal to 0.
I forgot something.
I need the desk as well.
So I have my source, ours and my desk ours, right?
I've gotta I've gotta pull them out of here so that I can blend with
them.
Right.
So I pull out the Death Star of the desk G, the destiny, and I've got
my Sorcerer And source.
And to be fair, I guess, I don't actually even care what these are.
We don't even care if these are r, g and B, we just care that their
Channel 0 1 & 2, right?
We don't even care.
So we could be wrong about these shifts and it wouldn't matter as long
as we do them all.
So anyway, now I'm going to actually produce my result red.
And my result red is just going to be the exact equation that I just
specified.
It's going to be a plus T, A minus B, if I wanted to do it that way,
or I can do it this way over here, which is 1 minus t plus t b.
Right?
So I
I can do it this way, right times a plus T times B.
So we'll leave it that way for now.
And will basically, say, okay, if I do one, what's mighty well might,
he's the alpha value.
That's the thing.
That's, that's actually causing it to work there.
And then what's my a, and my B, my a is going to be my destination.
Red X, my source red.
Because I'm trying to get to the source red, right?
So that's all.
Red is the B color and the background color is the a color, right?
All right, I believe, that's what we said.
It was.
And so off, we go now we'll go ahead and just do that for all of them.
Got to move that up a bit.
So it's not obscured by the five-minute warning.
The dreaded five-minute warning, the oops.
Okay?
Okay, be be like that.
And then, once we're done, we have to then reassemble the
Resulting value back into something that we can actually use.
So, what I have to do now is actually do sort of that that build back
again for the thing that we're going to actually write for desk.
So we have to actually write something to dest, and what we're going
to write to test is going to be our our board with r.g.
Ordered with our be, but we have to now turn them back into actual
actual rounded values, right?
So we have to actually round the values each time now, so,
Like that, I suppose we could just go ahead since we know these are
always positive.
We could also do this as a truncation which would be a little cleaner,
right?
I could do it this way where we just actually truncate the values,
plus, the rounding amount.
Like so, which I think, you know, probably is a little scenery here
since we are actually doing this per pixel, per pixel, things are very
expensive.
So we do have to watch out even in our test code so that we won't get
too slow and not be able.
For us, not for us to use it but we may replace this.
We probably don't want to be doing this necessarily in floating Point
math, the way that we're doing it here at now.
Anyway, but anyway, point being.
So here we go.
We're going to actually take these values and pack them back into the
places that they normally go right?
Like so you basically unpack them and pack them.
Oops.
816 like that.
The our get shifted back up, think I've put everything in there, don't
know.
I wrote that in pretty quickly.
There will have to step through this and see if it works but I believe
If we typed it correctly, we should have.
I'm not going to open.
I'm not going to paste things in the Creed anymore lesson learned.
We're going to paste things in to get from now on that way, if it
crashes, we can still draw in the background.
So now let's take a look at what happened.
Can you see?
And hear?
How that, how that looks now, where you've basically got?
You know, that kind of smooth that nice smooth edge.
Now, that we're being the alpha channel, so that's a much nicer comp,
right?
That's just a much nicer thing to look at, right?
And yeah, I mean,
That's, that's Alpha blending in a nutshell.
Right?
And so what kind of alpha blending actually is?
This?
This is a straight, linear blend between the two.
There's other, like I said before, on the previous screen, there's
lots of different things.
You could mean we say Alpha bunny.
It depends on what that blend equation is, right?
So basically this guy here, this is our blend equation that we're
using there are other blend equations.
So what I'll also say here is to do Casey someday.
A we need to talk about premultiplied Alpha because we are not talking
about that at the moment, but now is not the time to start that
discussion suffice to say.
This is not be multiplied Alpha but I'll just leave that for a little
thing that we can talk about later on because at the moment, it's
really not something that you need to think about whether it's pretty
multiplied or or not, but it is something that we will have to think
about a little later on because it affects the math in very important
ways.
And we will need to switch to using pre multiply multiply Alpha for
our final assets and so on.
So, since we are basically out of time here, I believe.
Yes, we have one minute left.
I'm going to call that done for the day.
We have our alphabet.
Working.
Oh, you know what?
I'm not going to quite call it done for the day.
I might do one more thing.
Although I think this this actually will cause us to have a couple
bugs, but I'm going to go ahead and make our our hero head.
Actually draw at the location of the player now.
Yeah, so there we go.
So there's our hero head, very exciting.
He's not actually in the right position.
But at least he moves around there with the guy very much fun.
Yay.
For Alpha blending.
We're pretty close now.
So, I think basically,
Tomorrow, we'll have a little guy walking around instead of our
rectangle because we're pretty close.
All right, everyone, that is it for now the Q & A has begun.
Remember?
I only start looking for Q Colin's when we start the Q&A.
So please, if you have a question that you'd like, answered now is the
time to post it to to the twitch chat.
Put a q: front of it.
And please keep the questions here in the post dream to stuff.
It's actually about the code that we wrote today or in previous day's.
If it's something, that's off topic and about something else.
Please come before us dream sometime often times.
I try to be on the stream, about 15 minutes, early to answer just any
off-topic questions that you want answered.
And so I do answer those, which is not on the poster because this is
the one that kind of goes into the recorded, handmade hero stream for
people to learn on later and I don't want to have lots of off-topic
stuff that they have to skip through.
Okay, tiny typo in function, name finally significant set.
B is missing an eye.
Okay.
Thank you, death lizard.
Let's take a look at that intrinsic, find least significant.
There we go.
That's better.
Let's go ahead and fix that.
Find least significant bit.
Okay.
Thank you very much.
That is a, definitely a typo.
Yes, that's true.
So Mo zaiko was talking about asserting.
The compression mode is true.
We only load one type of compression now, which is compression mode 3.
So, while we were asserting The Masks, we should probably also go
ahead and assert that the header compression mode is still in that 3
mode because we don't load any of the other compression modes at
present.
So we'd want to
If we got a file that didn't conform to that compression mode so that
we could be warned about it.
It's a good point.
So also someone was saying we don't need that intrinsic definition
anymore.
Well, we do actually need so I do that's not actually true.
So
I'll tell you what the person is saying, and then I want to make sure
that that is actually the case that I'm not sure it is.
So we'll, yeah, we'll talk about that.
So basically what the person was saying, they were saying that the you
don't need this pragma intrinsic if you include intron .h, but I'm not
100% certain if that's the case.
Let's find out.
So let's say we do that right now.
Let's go take a look at the code that gets generated just so I can see
if it actually still does that as intrinsic it might.
But I just want to make sure because I don't actually know, sometimes
it doesn't for other functions.
I'm pretty sure it doesn't.
But for this function because they may not have done a separate
implementation of it.
Then it might not.
So that's, that's definitely possible.
All right.
What am I looking for here?
I'm looking for load bitmap, right?
BMP.
So, basically, in here, what we want to do is take a look at this and
see what it generated to go to disassembly.
Nope.
So it does it.
Okay.
So that's totally fine.
So then it is fine without it.
Sometimes, the reason that I don't that I sometimes if you, if you
have, if you don't put the private intrinsic, it'll only use it in
optimized builds or whatever.
And so I wanted to make sure it was we there's no reason for us, not
to always use it.
But as long as it always does, you that then that's totally fine.
Would it be worthwhile to avoid converted to float when doing the
alpha blend?
Yeah, well.
So this is one of those things that basically what we have to say is
who knows.
So technically, I think it probably would be in this particular case,
right?
But we're so far away from actually doing performance oriented stuff,
that who knows.
It may be.
That it really, just doesn't matter for our purposes at all in this
particular case, but for something, this trivial you can do it
entirely without moving to float.
But you know, first of all, you never do this, you'd load the whole
thing as a Cindy Vector.
Instead of doing the channels individually, like this is just not
We aren't thinking about performance right now.
So thinking about whether you could convert to float or not is just
not that relevant because there's so many things that are wrong with
this and from a performance standpoint that it's just not really that
useful to think about it.
I mean,
It's a I actually would suspect probably that at the end of the day.
We won't even be storing things in this format.
We won't even have a RGB as we might have like a buffer of a as a
buffer of ours and a buffer of geez and so on, right?
Like so things might
It's worth being aware of how your code is performing, but it's also
worth knowing when you don't really care about some differences.
And in that case.
I think that's a difference.
We probably wouldn't care about that much.
It might be interesting to do it, just to show how you would do it
without, converting it to float.
But yeah, do I expect this to be a major performance thing?
No, not really because we're already performing so poorly probably
that.
I'm not sure how much worse this would really make it.
You know, it's hard to say.
Why is the windows logo stuff?
Isn't that the I have no idea because I don't know if you caught at
the beginning of the stream.
I was doing that.
That tweak thing that 7 + taskbar, tweaker thing.
And it's the thing that that's causing the windows to not be on top.
It might be.
It might be possible.
That that's a thing that was intentional.
So, let me see if it's in the advanced options.
I'm not sure.
Let's see.
Let's see why that's doing that.
You know, that's in the help over here.
So C option, z x, and
Fix this.
But when the classic theme is used clicking on the screen Corner, no
customized, horizontal paging.
It's a shown two o'clock loves to customize.
Show desktop button.
It's rest reverse the direction.
Yeah.
I don't, I don't actually know if there's a thing.
I'll look for it later, but I don't see unfortunately.
I don't see a way to get it to stop doing that.
So I think that's might just happen for a while until we figure out
how to get rid of it.
Let's see.
Are there other ways to use out or are there other ways to Alpha
blend?
And should you be taking into account?
Which colors are easier to see?
Like, green appears to be brighter than red.
So assuming that, I understand your question correctly.
I think what you're asking is, are there other ways to blend between
two colors?
Such that you're not just using per Channel.
So the first thing I will say is that yes, there are many ways.
You could consider blending between two things.
This is a linear blend.
For starters.
And it's linear in whatever space, the colors are in which themselves
may not be linear.
So we haven't will talk about this a lot.
We get to the renderer.
But basically what you have to understand is that the colors that are
displayed out of the monitor or actually not linear.
So basically, you know, we think about these colors and we're doing
this math.
The math actually is assuming that the colors are are linear a lot of
times but actually the way
Work is there's actually a curve.
So basically, you know, there's a color value that you set.
So there's basically a value from 250 0 to 255 that we are setting and
we're calling that the color, right?
So, what happens though?
Is that when that value is given over to the display?
It actually goes through a number of mappings potentially once
potentially on the graphics card.
And once potentially, by the monitor, that actually changes the
perceived brightness of that to not be linear.
So, then there's brightness here, right?
And so what actually happens is there some curve that happens here,
right?
You know, there's there's some curve you can imagine where as you
change the actual numerical value of the color instead of it getting
you know, if you change it from between 0 and 10, the difference in
brightness, may be much more than the same distance, right?
240 to 250 or something might be a lot less.
Of a difference in brightness, right?
Let's say or vice versa, depending on how those curves are set.
I think they're usually set in this way, but I can't quite remember
their exponentiated, right?
Yeah, so well for exponentially, they won't be this way.
I don't know.
Let's take a look.
So just to just to give you the, it's been a.
This is the first Graphics programming.
I've done in a long time actually.
So, you know a lot of this stuff is Rusty for me to be honest with
you.
So, let's see.
The srgb Gama curve?
Can we look at that?
Can we get that up here somewhere gamma curve.
Here we go.
So linear space, and there's well, that's not what I actually wanted.
I wanted one on one side and one with the other.
This is not giving me the values.
I want.
I just want brightness on one side and value on the other.
I'm not looking for gamma correction.
I'm actually looking for just that.
Doesn't anyone bake it down.
I just want someone who's baked down for me.
That's really all I want.
Well, let's take a look at see if this has it so srgb.
That's actually got the full color Cube.
Here we go.
Srgb intensity is versus HIV numerical values, right?
So basically
Let's see, which one is red.
So srgb numerical values are red curve.
These are the numerical values.
And I assume that's the intensity.
Showing exact look impressed value of serving at linear intensity.
Or at a linear intensity of this curve is linear.
So the gamma is 1, which curve are we talking about?
All right.
This is not what I wanted.
I just want, why can't I get what I want?
Maybe I'm misinterpreting these diagrams, but I literally just want
what I just drew.
I wanted something.
That's the value that you put into the buffer.
It's coming out and how bright it appears on the monitor.
That's all I wanted.
I don't know why.
I can't get.
I just want one graph.
That's just got that curve on it so that I could show you, but I don't
know.
Okay, so we can't get that curve.
Maybe we'll look up that curve.
I'll look up that curve out.
Side the stream.
So I won't have to waste your time watching me.
You try to read through documentation, but basically point being it's
nonlinear.
So it's entirely possible, that that is a bad thing for your blend.
Right?
You may be doing Alpha blending a and you want this this Alpha was
expecting it to be.
You know, let's say a smooth linear transition.
So as you change Alpha, you get a smooth step all along the way.
But instead, you're actually, if you're doing it in this,
Exponentiate space.
Unbeknownst to you a little bit of the blend actually goes a long way
in terms of what the perceived blend towards.
The new color, is things like that.
So there's Alpha corrected versions.
You can do some of these things.
There's other blend equations that do other operations that aren't
designed to basically map.
One thing on to the other.
There's pre multiplied versus not, non P multiplied, Alpha, which is
basically getting rid of this 1.0 - a term and baking it into the to
the I'm sorry gets rid of
A term and makes it into the SSR term, which is another thing
altogether.
So, there is a lot of stuff that goes on here.
I don't know if that's exactly what you were asking, but that's how
that works.
Whether you take into account the fact that channels work differently.
I don't think so.
Because the images themselves have already had that taken into account
and you need to smoothly blend between them.
So you can blend in a different color space like you could blend
instead of letting in RGB you could blend in HSV or you can blend and
log or you could do other things like this.
I don't know whether that's really such a good idea though, because
then what you'll get is you're not going to get smooth changes in the
colors of the pixel elements on the screen since they are r.
G and B, so I think that's probably where you want to be for the
operation that we're doing.
But if you were trying to Alpha blend, if you're trying to do an
alphabet, that was trying to do something else like smoothly.
Hughes of things together.
Then you might want to blend in a different color space one that
wasn't based on our gnb one that had different properties.
I don't know.
Sorry.
I don't have a good answer to that question.
Really?
I don't know.
Yeah, I don't think I answered that very well, but there are different
ways of
Things.
But I don't know if they are exactly the way that maybe you're
thinking about it.
Are we at all concerned with the destinations alpha or blending with a
transparent destination?
So, well, we are and we aren't basically, we're not concerned.
The reason we're not concerned with the destinations.
Alpha Channel at the moment is a because we don't
So, two reasons.
First of all, we never really right?
The destinations Alpha Channel because we don't care about it at.
All.
Right, so you can see in this expression.
We don't even write it.
It's always zero, right?
The destination just always going to have a zero Alpha Channel always.
Now, that doesn't mean you have to do that.
You can do rendering that uses the destination Alpha channel to store
important information that it will use.
And this is basically something that we may explore later when we're
actually doing our actual renderer because there's reasons why you
might want to use destination Alpha to do things.
But for right now, we don't have a destination up.
However, what I do want to point out is this doesn't have anything to
do with blending with other transparent things because that actually
just always works because basically since we are
Since we're basically, since we are always drawing things in Photoshop
style, like I was saying before we're going to layer things down such
that we start with the bottom layer, right, which has just whatever
our base coat is, right.
It's some grass or something, right?
And then we're going to like, right onto that a tree or whatever, and
then we're going to write on top of that.
The guy that's in front of the tree, since we know, we're always going
to be doing that.
Photoshop on top of, on top of, on top of, on top of compositing.
We will always work because just like Photoshop layers.
Always stack on top of each other properly.
We will always stack on top of each other properly, if we were to draw
out of order, right?
So in other words, if we're trying to draw stuff stacked up,
Right.
I'm going to try and do it a really bad stacking diagram here.
So if this is our background, and this is Sprite one, and this is
Sprite to if we're always drawing in this order, right from the
bottom.
Most thing to the top, then stamping down.
We know that all we're doing is writing in the colors of this thing
where they exist and blending them with the background, whatever it
was.
So another transparent thing that comes on top doesn't have to care.
That the destination buffer is actually already the combination of two
things.
It
Here, it'll just stack on top of it properly.
So it doesn't matter to this guy.
Whether this guy had a transparent portion or not because that's
already been resolved by this guy by this operation right.
By the time this guy writes to it.
It's as if they're only ever was one buffer.
Because all the things that came before, it have already been slammed
in their right if we were going out of order, if we were going to try
and render the top thing like the this bottom thing, then this top
thing, then the middle thing.
And this has to insert between them, then that's the point where you
start worrying about what the what was actually written to the buffer
before?
Right?
And that's all huge mess.
So basically what we want to do as much as possible, since we are 2D
game, we have the luxury of probably being able to do always, to
always know the order in which were drawing things, and that will let
us do a bunch of things that are actually extremely difficult.
In fact, sometimes impossible in 3D renderers, which is basically
order independent transparency.
Is what they have to do and they have to do all kinds of work to make
that stuff happen properly.
It's really a nightmare for them.
It's WHY games really hate stuff like looking through several sets of
windows at some Smoky particles, right?
Having it.
Lots of translucence is actually really hard in renderers for a number
of reasons.
So they try to avoid those sorts of things or do them with sort of
what they'll usually do is they'll they'll actually break apart.
The pieces of the scene that are transparent partially and they'll
sort they actually will sort those they'll draw everything.
It's not transparent first and then we'll actually sort the
transparent pieces and draw those in passes.
Just like we're going to do for our rendering.
But we have the luxury of being able to sort all of our stuff.
So everything will just work for free in that way, but they don't have
the luxury of that because they have a much higher primitive count.
They have a much higher primitive per pixel count than we do.
And so they don't they can't get away with that.
Right?
So yeah.
Will the final Blend favor, the source over the destination or is
linear good enough.
I'm not sure what that means.
We're really not favoring anybody.
We're just using the alpha channel to tell us how much of the
foreground should come in at that point.
Right?
How much of the source should be used?
So I'm not sure.
Can you restate that question?
Let's see.
How would you deal with other picture formats?
Such as PNG, jpg, GIF, Etc.
Well, we just write a loader for whatever the other format was or if
you're lazy and don't want to write another loader.
You could just run a conversion tool and then load them that way,
right?
You could just run some freely available conversion tool back from
virtual like imagemagick to batch convert your stuff from whatever
your Source format is into bmps.
You could either load them yourself or do that or like I said, I'm
handmade here.
Are we right?
Think of a scratch but you don't have to write everything from
scratch, you know, there's no reason that you can't use an image
loading Library if you'd like to and there are several that are
available.
This thing called free image.
Loads images, you know, your mileage may vary, but there's libraries,
you can use.
So, it's entirely up to you.
Yeah.
Why is the mass so complicated to use?
I assume the BMP format does that because it is somehow easier than
doing something else?
Why isn't the master?
Specified something that can just be ended with the value or
something.
So I don't know why they chose that.
It seems like a really bad idea to me.
What I would have done is I would have specified the order just hard
coded the order.
And if I really wanted to different orders like 14 little Indian 14
beginning and I would have had a flag, but you're right.
The masks and BMP are complicated to use for no real reason.
Like why do we have two bits?
Can them because they're just it was not a very smart format or store.
The
Often there to right, like store the shift and I'm like, what spend an
extra 16 bits at the front of your at the front of your file format,
right?
To to tell what the shifts were.
Something else that came up earlier stream.
Did you mean to call the Arts under power llvm and clang?
I always call llvm.
Because really, it's, it's not clang, that really is the thing that
determines what the intrinsics are.
It's llvm for the most part because llvm either has those intrinsics
in the bytecode or doesn't and if llvm doesn't have the, in transition
the bytecode then it's like playing is just, I mean, client just a
thing that like spits out llvm byte code, right?
Like and so if llvm byte code, has the intrinsic that it has it and if
not, it doesn't.
So I typically always think of it as llvm, but you could call clang if
you wanted to, it's up to you.
In the pits can function.
What about returning the index and have it set to negative one.
If not found.
I see search functions doing that a lot.
Yes, you could do that.
I find that to just be a little more error-prone.
So I would rather have there.
Be a clear rule that you can switch on, because the compiler is
probably going to reorganize that stuff anyway, and so it just seems
like an easier thing to do.
Can you go over the linear Alpha blend diagram again?
Sure.
I certainly can.
So a linear blend is actually something that you can think about
working between any two things, even if you don't really even know
what they were as long as they obey a few simple properties, right?
You could almost think of it as just any two points in any space,
right?
As long as that space obeys, some linearity things, which let's not.
Let's not get too crazy for the moment.
But basically, if I have a point that I'm going to
And a point that I'm starting from right.
And I want to linear blend between these.
All I need to do to be able to do a linear blend is have a way of
producing the sort of the the difference between the right.
I need a way of being able to say
- be, I need to be able to produce that and what that is like a minus
B, right.
Sorry, B, minus a because we're going to be.
So, B, minus a is basically telling me this motion.
It's telling me how to go from A, to B, right.
So, on a simple number line, right?
If, if I'm talking about just five.
The number five is B.
And the number two is a I subtract them.
Right?
And I get three, it's the amount of steps.
It would take the distance, it would take to get from one to the
other.
Other right?
But this works in all Dimensions, not just one.
So I'm just going to say, like, okay, it's something, it doesn't
matter, two dimensions, three dimensions, for Dimensions.
I don't care.
As long as we're talking about is, you know, basically euclidean stuff
here.
As long as I can produce this, I can do a linear blend, and the way I
do that linear blend is you can think about it.
Exactly.
Like you think about starting some place and walking somewhere else,
right?
If I started a
And I add in this difference.
This movement right here, that B minus a right?
And I add in b - A.
I will get to be that's just how it works.
Like you can think of it very simply if I take the distance between
these two things and I walk it, I'm going to end up at the other one
right now.
Technically.
It's not quite a distance.
It's actually a directional distance.
Right?
I know what direction I'm walking to and that's why it's important
that we're talking about signed numbers here, right?
Be, you know, if I say, like, I said before, I let's say be, was was
actually three and a was, the five are sorry this to was what I said
before.
Let's say B was to, in a was the five.
It's important that I don't end up with three here.
When I do this operation.
I need to end up with negative 3 because it's a direction.
I need to know which way I'm going, right?
But basically, as long as you can produce that you could end up with
this, which is basically just I mean, it's a simple.
As as this it's b equals a plus B, minus a right, this this equation
right here.
If you can produce that equation for the things that you're talking
about linear blending is a simple as introducing this right.
You can produce that new Point by saying instead of walking the whole
distance between A and B.
I'm going to walk some portion of the distance between A and B.
Some fractional value that can be whatever it is.
It could be 50%.
It could be 25 percent, whatever it is.
And I will get however far along their I need to go and that is a
linear blend.
Like I said, you can use algebra to rearrange it.
If you want to you can multiply this out.
If I have a plus T B minus a
Equal, some new value.
I know that if I rearrange that I can use the distributive property,
T, B, minus t, a like that.
And I can go ahead and regroup.
The terms, these two a terms.
I have a I have a 1 here in front of my a coefficient, right?
And I have a minus t here.
So that's just 1.
Minus.
T times a plus TB.
I just regroup.
The terms like group.
German this term into one term and then the TB still there.
And that's the other form of the linear, blend that you often.
See.
So you've got those two different formats.
They're right.
And so that's linear blending in a nutshell.
It's very, very simple.
Extremely powerful.
This one equation is so powerful.
Actually that you will see it.
Under Li almost everything we do in this game.
There will be almost no part of the code that does not at some point
compute, some variation of this thing.
So, trust me on this one, you will have if you don't quite understand
it, now, you will have a lot of opportunity to practice because this
is literally, this is probably if I had to say and I don't know, I
haven't thought this through, I'm just saying this off the cuff, but
if I had to say this is probably the most important equation in all of
gaming, like games need this equation, probably more than any other
equation.
And there's tons of equations that are important to gaming, but if you
could only have one
This is probably the one you would need because the games can't do
anything without a linear blind because everything else is built on
top of it.
Nonlinear blending is built on top of it.
All of rasterization is built on top of it.
All of Animation is built on top of it.
It's just incredibly incredibly important.
I'm an experience with Windows.
I know we do a large virtual.
A look at the beginning.
Is this basically the same as M map in Linux?
Yes, for the most part.
I'm not super experience with em map, so I'm not prepared to say
exactly but what I would say is I would encourage you if you have
questions like that the best place to go at the moment since I haven't
really looked at the Linux stuff and haven't done an implementation of
it yet.
If you go to handmade here at or click on news and forums,
There's a coding resources page.
If you go to that coding resources page go to the Linux listing and
click on handmade penguin, sdl Port because I believe and I'm sorry if
I had turns out to be wrong, but I believe he actually explains how to
do all of the stuff that I did in in in Linux so you can kind of go
through here and look.
So there's that M map and it appears to be in the same place as our
virtual Alex.
Oh, so take a look.
Look at that page handmade penguin because that that would probably be
the best place to go for an exploration since I know he's actually
worked it all out already.
Let's take a look here.
What bit value?
If it is 50% brightness?
Well, it'd be you have zero, and you have 255.
So you can
Think of it as 127.
Well, okay.
So here's how to think about it in our actual thing.
Right?
Here's how to answer that question basically.
So, you know that the alpha value that we're pulling out is going to
be whatever the alpha value in the bitmap is divided by 225.
Right?
So if you think about it, what we would want to do is say all right,
if we have 128 divided by 225.
What is that?
Well, it's .50 something?
Something something, right?
Not quite exactly 5127.
/ 255 is point for a 98, something.
Something something, something.
Something.
Right?
So, the actual answer is that there is no actual value for exactly
5127 is a little bit low.
128 is a little bit High.
What do you do?
You could have just this math to make it exact, you know, if you
wanted to write.
But but the problem is you want to make sure that one is exact.
So you need to make sure that to view 5 by 2 to 5 is 0.
Like, if we were to do, 128 divided by 256, you get an exact.
So if we divide it by 256, or you can get exact, but you could never
get one because then your highest value is 256 285.
You would end up never quite being able to get one either and that has
consequences as well.
Worst consequences in fact.
Let's see here.
Let's see.
What else we got?
Does the display blind operation actually do anything with the alpha
Channel?
No, it just write zeros to the alpha channel.
It's only using the alpha Channel as a control to basically control
how the blind operate.
So it's reading it but it never writes it if that's what you're
asking.
Which I think is what you're asking about.
Now.
The solid curve on Wikipedia's gamma correction is the linear space.
Intensity should be what you were looking for.
Okay.
So you're saying, go to Wikipedia and look up gamma correction.
Did you say or something else?
What I'm sorry, I just spaced out there.
Let's see, but we're out of time.
Let's just grab it.
The inside, curve on gamma correction.
Okay, so gamma correction Wikipedia,
So you're saying there's a solid curve on here?
Okay, so you're saying this curve right here?
Hopefully it's what you're saying.
So I didn't do the reading it.
But assuming that, that's a solid curve.
Basically, is this what are the two axes though?
The dotted line is linear transfer function.
Satellite shows here, T.
There's difference.
What are the axes?
By the way, which axis is, which?
Hi there, guys.
Can you tell me what the axes are?
Because which one is, which one is the brightness?
And which one is the input value?
Correction, the dotted line indicates a linear transfer function.
The solid line shows how a typical CRT behaves.
The dashed line represents the inverse function.
So, yeah, so I guess I don't actually know.
It doesn't say I assume this is brightness and this is the input
value, but I guess I don't actually know assuming it was and you can
see that's what the curve looks like.
So it actually has a lot more kind of resolution there at the bottom.
Then at the top.
There's not a lot of resolution in the brightness, but I don't know.
I don't know if that's reading the just
Because it doesn't actually have things.
So we'll have to look at that a little more detail later.
All right.
Let's see.
I think that's about it for stuff.
We can cover today.
We have gotten, this is pretty good.
We have gotten to the point where we can now do layered graphics on
the screen.
So I'm thinking it's a, you know, it's kind of a question to some
degree about where we go next.
Like you know, what, what is the next thing that we should be doing if
we're actually talking about moving forwards on the game.
And so, what I was thinking of doing next is working on our player
motion code because I think that's important because it's going to
talk, it's going to basically speak to how we need to do our Collision
detection, which speaks to how we need to interpret the tile map.
So I was thinking of doing is basically saying, all right, maybe we do
a little cleanup tomorrow and Friday of stuff that still needs to kind
of get cleaned up a little bit, just looking looking at things like
that.
See what we want to do in terms of that sort of stuff, but maybe what
I was thinking is so we'll start.
Next week on like actually talking about linear algebra and vectors
and will actually start writing the movement code for the guy for real
so that it feels good.
And we'll talk talking about Collision detection for real so that we
can kind of see what we need from our engine for that, because that's
a really big important thing to spec.
That's one direction to go.
The other direction to go is, we need to talk about how to actually
build these background bitmaps, right?
Which is to say, take the tile map and kind of go ahead and build the
background bitmaps.
I don't know which one we should do next.
Kind of a tough thing to say.
So it's a toss-up.
Maybe we'll flip a coin.
Maybe we'll take a poll.
I'm not sure both of them have to get done before.
We know what our what our engine spec really truly is.
So it's something to think about.
But for now, we can at least be happy that we now have a nice
splitting engine, we can use so you can put stuff up on the screen
which is kind of nice and from now on we'll always have Graphics to
back us up, which is much nicer than looking at a bunch of rectangles,
my opinion.
So, thank you everyone for joining me for another.
ER, episode of handmade hero.
It has been a pleasure coding with you as always.
And it was a pleasure talking about the linear blend, which like I
said, is one of the most important things you will see it, come up
again and again, and again, on the stream, so it was nice to finally
get to that.
I think that's a pretty big milestone starting to actually use the
linear blend and I get them.
Like I said, we'll talk about it a lot more in the future, and we'll
see a lot.
More about it.
And what kind of learn more and more about how interesting it is and
how intricate you can basically how amazing it is that you can do so
much for such a simple function and basically how it underlies
everything if you will.
So anyway, thank you very much for joining me.
If you would like to follow along at home, with the source code.
You can pre-order the game and it comes with full source code already
every night.
I update the source code and you'll basically a link in your email
that you can use to download the source code.
It also has the artists that we've been using on the stream.
There's a
Separate zip file.
You can download if you want to use like, you know, the little guy and
the backgrounds and that sort of stuff for doing your development.
And so, you know anything you're basically completely follow along at
home and all the assets that you need to follow along completely at
home, come with the with the with that pre-order.
So check that out.
If you're interested.
We also have a patreon.
If you want to support the video series, you can always subscribe
there.
We also have that news and Forum site, which I showed just a few
minutes ago, which has a ton of resources for people who are trying to
learn on the stream to a lot of great stuff, the schedule for the
week.
Is posted here.
There's also the episode guy, which allows you to catch up with old
episodes.
Got nice annotated video series on their coding resources.
Has the ports.
Like I showed before and other resources, you might need like good
documentation stuff, and there's a form you can post in when you need
to ask questions.
So please check that out.
If you try to learn from the series.
It's a great resource, and there's a lot of very helpful people on
there who are very nice on the forums who will also try to answer your
questions if I'm not around to do so, so thank you very much for
joining me.
I will see you tomorrow.
Same time, same place, 8:00 p.m.
I am Pacific Standard time on Twitch.
So I hope to see you all there.
And if I don't have an excellent Thursday, see you later, buddy.