Hello everyone and welcome to another allergy driven performance of
handmade hero.
We have to fix some bugs today.
Well, I guess not really even fixed some bugs per se, but re-implement
something that we broke.
We did a bunch of stuff to improve our pipeline, to do everything
using full 3d because we decided we wanted z-buffering rather than
having to Sprite sorting.
But part of that meant kind of doing a regular 3D pipeline for reals
with projection.
Using all these other sorts of things that you would normally see.
And
I will be blowing my nose continuously today, while we fix the part of
the code that used to do the debug overlay.
Because although we did all the code to make the regular game code,
the regular game drawing, go through the full 3d pipeline correctly.
We never did the code and necessary like sort of conduit for the debug
overlay to work in the same fashion because the debug overlay now just
basically goes through the same path as everything else.
Which means
Being drawn in full 3d which is kind of nice.
We can probably make use of that in various ways but it also means we
have to do stuff like make sure we have a correct orthogonal
projection Matrix and make sure the coordinates are lined up properly
and all those sorts of things in order to see our debug overlay again.
So that's what we're going to do today.
And if that goes really smoothly and we finish it early, which who
knows if it will debugging is always especially if it's 3D and we
don't have a 3D capture system, which we currently don't because this
system unfortunately cannot run and site or render dock.
I need to upgrade to a different machine.
Sometime soon anyway because we can't do that.
This could take a while and when we actually figure out what's going
on and get that all lined up correctly, then we will move on to
implementing some features that we want to have that.
We sort of implemented before in various ways that might not have been
the best ways before depending on the circumstances.
But they were basically ways of doing stuff like distance fog.
We had kind of done that manually before we can now do it in.
Way, we can also do stuff like the we had previously had to do
manually separating out the floor, above the hero.
If we wanted to Alpha fade that in when you went up and down and all
kinds of stuff like this.
So there are a bunch of things like that that we can do.
We can actually do those things in a much more procedural way.
Now, that doesn't require the code to actually do shuffling at the
head end because since we are going through a z-buffer and those
things are Z based based effects.
We will have
the ability to do a bunch of nuts stuff there.
You'll see in a second we can we can kind of just lean on the GPU.
You to do that stuff for us.
All right, so let's go ahead and get started.
Like I said, this will be a stream filled with mucus, just absolutely
disgusting lie.
Filled with snot and you are now, like, living in my world.
This is what happens during allergy season and mind.
You, this is what happens during allergy season.
For me when I take allergy medication, like I took a allergy pill this
morning and I took one yesterday
owing to and this is,
This is how often I have to blow my nose when I'm on allergy
medication.
I don't really understand why my immune system thinks, it's necessary
to attack little particles.
Well, I guess I actually do know why because I actually it makes
perfect sense.
Why my immune system attacks those particles but
I wish it wouldn't.
Anyway, let's get started here today is day 373.
So you want the 372 source code if you want to follow along.
And again, what we're going to look at here is just it's handmade
projection or project.
Let's see.
All we're going to look at today is just this debug situation and see
what's going on.
How do we make sure that it gets lined up properly?
So we've got a set camera, transform call.
You can see it right here and what we were doing with this.
Is just trying to.
Get started, setting up, the proper situation, for the debug it, the
the debug coordinates, and the debug font stuff to to work properly.
And so there's two basic things that could be going wrong here.
I mean, there's obviously other ones that I might not be thinking of,
but there's two that come to mind immediately that we need to sort of.
Make sure are correct in the new system because they were completely
different in the previous one.
Again, one of them is trying to figure out what the coordinates are
going to be for the debug things.
We were previously using a certain set of coordinates for debug stuff.
We now have to make sure that if we want to either, we change those
coordinates which I don't think we want to bother doing because they
were fine before or the more sensible route.
Which is what I was going to do is just make sure that our camera
transformed that we set up in 3D pipeline is set up to accept those
coordinates.
Up early and place things where they should appear on the screen
relative coordinates in the same.
You know, so that those courts have the same meaning that they did
back before we switch to the pipeline that we're using now.
So that's thing one.
Thing too, is we are now going through Z buffer.
and that means there's a near and far clipping plane, and we don't
really know what the Z coordinates are for this stuff that we're
Ending down.
Now my you know for example, the near clipping plane is 0.1.
If that's the case that means that in effect that might not be what we
want as well.
We may want the near clip playing to be back a bit from there because
since this is orthographic, we can set the z-score thing to whatever
we want.
Since I believe the Z coordinates.
I don't actually know what we're doing.
For Z coordinates and here, it's been too long.
Since we've we've worked with it at all, but I think the Z coordinates
may always just be 0.
And if that was the case, then it could be that our coordinates are
already being transformed correctly.
We don't know again.
We have to verify this and we're just getting clipped off of the the
near clipping plane.
Because if we're drawing it z0, but then your clip claim is at Point
1, we're drawing point one behind the near clipping plane.
Right?
So if we go into the math code and we look at Arthur graphic.
Now, the reason we have an ear clip plane is for two reasons.
One is that we want to be able to not have stuff come right up into
the face of the player, right?
So you're supposed to kind of keep things a little bit away.
So conceptually, it makes sense that we have an ear clip playing in
perspective.
The other reason is because we need someplace between, which we can
sandwich our Z coordinates.
If we want to use the fixed Point Z buffer, rather than a floating
Point Z buffer.
However, if you think about it in orthographic, projection, there is
no real reason for that.
For that Z coordinate to be in front of the camera.
The Z could be behind the camera because the Z is arbitrary since
everything gets projected.
In a sheet directly on to the screen with no foreshortening, right?
In an orthographic view, you can just as easily dressed up this
behind.
You is stuff that's in front of you.
So the near clipping plane, you know, in a in an orthographic,
projection could be, you know - and there's no reason there's nothing
weird that would happen there in a perspective situation that doesn't
make any sense because you can get down to the point that the the used
actually standing at something that passes through that becomes a
divide by zero scenario, which doesn't make very much sense.
Right?
In a lot of ways you can see why that would
Be a weird Singularity kind of kind of place to be for the math
although you could still work it out right because it ends up being
zero over zero.
So if you know if you had if you were being super fancy I think it
would you could still make it work obviously, but anyway and then when
you got behind it, you're talking about things that you shouldn't be
able to see because you're not looking that direction.
And so it doesn't make very much sense and perspective world to do
that in orthographic world.
The really Z has no under the like it has no meaning
Other than just the buffer just the depth so you can easily just pick
- coordinates you can throw things at - coordinates are positive corns
it doesn't matter it's all going to project onto the screen just
flatly with no foreshortening.
No mirroring when it goes behind you and none of that stuff because
you're not doing a device.
By any coordinate.
So we could have the near clipping be behind us and it wouldn't
matter.
I believe we did the mass such that, that would have just worked.
I don't think we assume that n was positive anywhere.
So I'm just going to try setting that as well, just to see if because
we are drawing at Z equals zero at the moment I think for the debug.
And so I just want to say.
Yeah.
So so that was the only problem that we actually had as it turns out.
The problem that we had was just that our Z coordinates were behind
the near clipping plane so they were getting clipped out, right?
That was that was it.
Everything else was working properly, it would appear.
And so you know obviously at the end of yesterday's session we did do
the the one piece where we did set camera transform.
So we did need to do this as well.
If you remember that to set up that core enhancement but it looks like
we set up that cord transform properly first guess.
so, that was nice and
Well, first educated guess I suppose and then we had to do that that
clipping to prevent that from happening.
Anyway, now that we've got that though, you'll notice I'm not really
able to click on it which is not great.
I don't know why that is the case because I wouldn't have thought that
we did anything differently there.
So meaning the graphic stuff should not have changed that, so I'm not
super sure what's going on with us, not being able to do.
Debug click, so I got to go take a look at that.
That may be that it is still working.
But the sense the direction is going the wrong way.
I don't remember whether we had why going up or down in the debug
system and so I'm not sure if that has something to do with it.
What I'm going to do just quickly is I'm going to create an incorrect
projection here to shrink down what we're looking at.
So that it's smaller.
You can see what I did here, where I've taken what was previously
here.
And I just shrunk it down to half the size, just if I can see if when
I click on it which it should still click here.
Yeah, it doesn't.
So it may be Loop sets.
Not what I want to do.
What's going on, stop running.
Okay, there we go.
Oh, I accidentally for clothes for coder.
That was not what I wanted to do.
It would be hard to program with no editor.
All right.
So if I go ahead and assume that now the problem is just that the
clicking isn't working properly, I'm not sure again.
What that would be.
It's been a while but in terms of clicking I know I that we've never
done the unprojected stuff if I remember correctly.
So that might be what we would need to do.
Working.
Aha.
Yes.
So you can see here, we've got a nun, project-- call.
And that's basically saying, hey, here's the mouse X and Y, and the
mouse X and Y are
in screen space originally and we need to translate those from the
screen space to the actual drawing coordinates that we were using so
that we can correlate them with what we drew
No, I don't actually know when I say screen space.
I'm not sure I even remember what we were putting mousex and mousey.
Why in?
I assume they're pixel coordinates but I don't even know that I don't
remember.
So the first thing I want to do
is find out what those even are.
So, you know, the easiest way to do that is probably this actually
And I'll just go up here and say, hey could you go ahead and print
those out for me?
Actually, what are those in the input layer?
Yeah, they are our 32s.
So
I just want to see what those are so I know what we were placing those
in.
Yes.
So those are just in pixel coordinates and you can see that it's
ranging from zero to 1919 here, right?
And 02 1079 here.
So it's basically just saying what pixel you're on on the screen and
why is going up so it's harmonized with the math.
So Windows is our Windows platform.
Layer is flipping it around.
Windows would not be reporting it that way.
We are reporting it that way.
So, all I need to do there.
Is do the complete on production from Pixel space.
So let's flip over to that.
That's over in the render group stuff.
You can see The unprojected Happening Here, Right?
And you can see the what we were doing for the unprojected, in this,
in this case here, right?
We've got the object transform and then the pixels x Y, which is what
we were passing with the mouse and so on.
So, here what we need to do,
Then what we definitely aren't doing in anyway, right.
Is we need to undo, all of the steps that open jail was taking.
When It produced these coordinates, right?
So the first steps looks a lot like what opengl does, right?
You can see we take the unprojected X Y and we subtract that screen
center from the pixels x y to produce that, right?
So what that's doing is that's saying, okay, we've got something that
ranges from 0 to the pixel.
To the width and from 00 to the height and what we want is something
that's centered around the center of the screen, because that's the
first thing that opengl would have done in Reverse, right?
You can, you can sort of, imagine us taking the opengl set of things
that does to the incoming points and just doing them in Reverse,
right?
You know, we've got a projection Matrix, right?
You know, that looks something like this potentially.
Actually, I guess it looks a little bit.
It can look, it can look one of two ways, right?
Here's the perspective and here's the orthographic versions.
So, you know, we've got one looking that way.
One, looking that way.
And one of the one there.
So
We've got a matrix that looks like this where we've got some some
values filled in and sort of a big dipper configuration here, a little
dipper configuration.
So we know we've got points coming in.
Write x y z is coming in.
We know that this is always going to be wondering are transform we're
transforming by this shape and producing a result here, right?
And this result is in clip coordinates, right?
So this result is in negative 1 to 1 space in all Dimensions, right?
X y and z.
And that's clipped, then we're going to take these output values.
So in this space, right, we know that we're taking values that range
from negative 1 to 1 in all ways.
Right?
So we're imagining that.
And given that information, we are having to produce actual pixel
coordinates to render stuff it.
Like opengl obviously, has to actually do that to fill pixels, so it's
taking that and it's mapping that to the screen.
Right?
So it's taking this and it's doing a mapping of that to the screen
where, you know, the bottom is 0 0, the top and you know the top
corner is 1920 1080, right?
Well, one pass the top corner.
It's actually 1919 1079, right?
And so the first thing we want to do, if we are given a point in this
space is we're trying to get back to clip coordinates so that we can
continue back down this fight, right?
Because we're going the other way here.
So instead of multiplying by a matrix clipping and then transforming
to screen space from the clip space.
We're trying to backwards.
So this is the clip space transformed here.
This you know thing that was going this way, we're trying to go this
way.
That means the first thing we want to do is Center about the middle.
because remember these
The centered around the middle.
They weren't around the lower corner, right?
And so what we need to do is first do that.
So to do that, we would take the center of the screen and subtract,
you know, we would take whatever the point is and subtract it from the
center, right?
That gives us that wherever that point was, if this was the point here
that gives us it centered around here rather than centered around
here, right?
And that's exactly what we're doing is the first step.
So that first step makes a lot of sense.
This next step, not so good.
Good.
Right, this next step.
You can see here has the aspect ratio baked into it, but we don't want
to do that anymore.
It starts off pretty good.
Right.
You can see unprotected.
XY dot X and Y.
This right here is normalizing to the screen.
That's again.
Exactly what we do want to do because we want negative 1 to 1.
So this point five over screen dim X multiplier is exactly right?
Because what we would end up having is well actually is that exactly
right.
Let me just double check that.
Make sure that.
Before I say that something is exactly right.
That it actually is.
So here we end up having the width, right?
And the key here is that the width itself is not what we want to
normalize by.
Right.
We want to normalize by half the width because we're centering around
here.
So if something was all the way over here, we want it to map to
negative one.
And if it was all the way over here, we want to map to one that's a
span.
This span is only half of the width, right?
So we wanted to
Take the point x and divide it by the width / 2, and of course if we
divide by something over to the two can come up.
So we end up with PX.
Over W times that point five, right?
That's the that's the divided by 2 coming up to here, right?
So Point 5, PX /, / W is exactly what we want.
However, you'll notice the aspect ratio is baked in here.
We don't want the aspect ratio of baked in here.
Why don't we want the aspect ratio baked in here anymore?
Because it's in The Matrix.
And I don't mean the one where everyone is attached to, like, a like
a, like a machine that makes them think, they're in virtual reality.
otherwise known as Facebook's Oculus you know dreams we're talking
about one the one that we set up to do our camera transform
And so, what we need to do is say, well, when we do a nun, project--,
we need to know what that camera transform is.
I believe we do know what the camera, transform is because we store it
right here.
See last project, right?
And so we have a projection Matrix called last project which is the
thing that things would be projected by and we know that that last
project Matrix is the thing that we need to do use to undo whatever
our transform was right.
Like that's the key.
That's that's the the Crux of it.
My sense.
Now there's going to be some some fussing here you'll see in a second
I'll show you how the fussing occurs because we're going to need
something that we don't have right now and it's going to be a little
bit intricate how we get it but it's going to be okay, don't worry.
So if we come through here and we take a look at what's going to
happen there, rather than doing an, if transform orthographic, or any
of this stuff, like this stuff is just not relevant anymore.
Right instead, what we need to do is we need to look at last brought
here and we need to make that be something that we go back through.
Because if you look at what happens after we change, things to the
negative 1 to 1 space, we end up having to go in through here through
through the
Reverse projection, right?
So if you imagine this part of the process, is the part that we would
have to do next.
This is if this is a matrix whatever this Matrix is, right?
Here's our X.
Here's our B.
We've got something where previously
We were doing a standard Matrix transform.
We are multiplying this Matrix, a by an incoming point, which we'll
call X and it was equaling B, which was the output.
This we now have to reverse, right?
We're now taking B, which is this right.
Here are clip coordinates and we want to know what we started with
right?
We're trying to say, what will would we have put in if we wanted to
make, you know, this BB what comes out of this projection Matrix and
so that's a classic
Linear algebra.
You know, the very first thing you learn how to do in linear algebra
solve this equation.
You need to multiply both sides by a inverse, right?
Which is the The Matrix that turns a into identity, right?
At the base of the cancellation Matrix for a.
So this cancels out and you get x equals a inverse B, right?
So this right here is, you know, for those of you who aren't familiar
with linear algebra and we've done it a couple times.
We talked about the fact that like a inverse, a equals the identity
Matrix.
We did a bunch on that but I want to go back and handmade here and
watch that part if you're uncomfortable with what that means.
But basically
It's sort of like the same concept of multiplicative divided, right?
It's basically saying, okay, if I have some number a let's say that
number is 5, then I could think of, in terms of multiplication, if I
wanted to say a inverse a equals one, write something that would turn
a into the multiplicative identity.
The thing, the value, which makes it do nothing when multiplied right
it does not.
Change its value.
So we want to know what is this value a inverse such that it times a
would equal 1.
Well we know that a equals 5 in this case so we would say well a
inverse times 5 equals 1.
What does a inverse?
Well just divide both sides by 5 to find out and you get 1/5, right?
And lo and behold that's exactly the same thing that we would think.
If we took a look at this, because 1/5 times 5 does equal 1, right?
The same is true of matrices, that is all.
We're looking for in these matrices, right?
We've got a multiplication here A times x equals B.
We want to undo it, right?
We want to know what would happen if, if we wanted to solve for x.
Well, what we want to do is divide
By a right.
We want to divide both sides by a but in linear algebra, that doesn't
actually exist.
The division is not a thing that can happen with matrices.
You can't divide by a matrix in in order to cancel it like that.
Instead you have to multiply by its inverse, but that's the same
conceptual operation.
And so we do that to both sides in the trick is, we need to know how
to invert a matrix.
We need to know how to take a and get from a, to a inverse in order to
do this because we
I have no way of doing that.
Here we have no way of solving this equation without that because we
used that ability to get to this equation, which does tell us the
answer for X, right?
And so given that that's the case.
What we need to know is an inverse value right?
Whatever?
The opposite operation is for this Matrix.
We need to know what that is for our last project which is easier said
than done.
It's a fairly complicated Matrix of this point.
I warned you about the allergies.
Anyway.
So we need some way of actually producing that a inverse B and that's
the key.
That's the thing that we have to figure out how to do now.
One thing that you'll notice
Is that if we take a look at what any of these matrices look like,
they're not that difficult if we look at them alone.
So here's the perspective, projection Matrix, and it just has four
values in it, right?
It just looks like this.
It's got ABCD here.
Well, you know, it's a times c b times c, d e.
Right?
So it's a c and we can call a see something else like we can just call
that like you, let's say.
And BC can be V.
So that way we don't have to keep writing it.
We've just got you.
We've got V and then we've got DNA.
Right.
And then we've got a negative 1 and a 0 here.
And we've got zeros everywhere else.
Okay, and if you look at this Matrix, what you can see from this
Matrix very quickly is that it wouldn't probably be so difficult to
deal with this.
If we were just dealing with just this one Matrix in isolation,
And because what happens when we multiply by x y z w, we see the
results here are not particularly complicated.
This coordinate is just ux, right?
There's nothing else.
That happens to this coordinate.
There's nothing else there.
Similarly this just gives us v y right?
That's it.
So when we come through here, we can individually invert the X and Y.
Really trivially here, it would be very simple to understand how that
would happen because all you have to do is divide by you or / V,
right?
Which tells us exactly what we would need for our inverse Matrix,
Without having to do any kind of fancy math on it.
We would know that the inverse Matrix here would just be 1 over U,
right.
Because when it multiplies by this, if it has to produce X again, it
has to knock out the you which one over U is the only thing that will
do right, and you can't have any other values involved because none of
these could be in play.
You have to just take just this one and multiply it by 1 over U right
stated alternately you can imagine, in fact.
So let's say, just to give you an example, or to give you an idea of
how this works, right x.
Y z w, we multiply through, you know, how to do the matrix
multiplication, right?
X x uy.
Item 0 z x 0 w x 0.
You produce you X now just pretend we're multiplying this vector by
this Matrix again, right?
This new Matrix we want to make well, we want to get our ex back and
we've got you X.
So what's going to happen here?
Well, there's going to be four elements to this Matrix.
Let's finish them off just so we can hear 0 0, d e.
So this is d y plus easy, right?
And then, this right here is just going to be negative.
Z is the only thing that's in
All right, that's it.
So, that's all we've got.
And so, if you take a look at what's going to happen down here, when
we multiply, it's like yeah, okay, if I want to produce X again, what
do I have to have?
Well, I gotta have one over you here because that's what's going to
multiply this term and I've got to get rid of the you.
That's what will give me an X.
When I do this matrix multiplication, if this was the incoming vector,
and this was the new Matrix, right?
Here's my a inverse.
Here's my a right.
This is my baby.
This is my ex
So when I'm doing this, I can see exactly what that is.
And similarly, I can see exactly what this is right.
Those are those are almost like read them off.
Easy like you don't even have to think, right?
It's just obvious.
So it's only once we get down to hear the things start to get a little
bit more tricky.
But if we skip this third guy, for one second, you can see that this
is also extremely trivial to work with in a sense that we know exactly
what the Z value was because it's down here in the fourth component.
Right?
So we can just ignore this entirely and say, well, I don't really care
what that is, I don't need to know what
All you is.
I've got Z and Z is what I want, right?
Furthermore W is always one so we don't have to reverse engineer it.
So what that means is now we can see for what we would multiply here.
We would just multiply 0 0 0, negative 1, right?
That's all.
We actually needed there because we just need to get that negative Z.
We don't want any other contributors and the W has the negative z in
it, right?
So that leaves us with a z.
Here.
And we know that we just want to one here so that's just going to be
0.
0, 0 1.
So hey guess what we inverted this Matrix without ever having to
really think too hard about it or do an actual 4, by 4 Matrix
inversion?
Which let me tell you is something you probably want left to
Mathematica because actually gaussian eliminating it or something else
is gives a huge pain in the butt.
Okay, let's check our work, though.
Is that correct?
Well, let's go in here.
And erase these guys out.
And just see what happens if I multiply these two.
All right, so take the First Column first row, this is going to be
you.
And one over U is all that's in there and hey guess what that produces
a 1 which is actually want.
Now remember what we're aiming for here is the identity because a
inverse times, a should equal the identity.
So if I multiply this by this, I should get you know 1s down the
diagonal 0 everywhere else does it happen?
Well it's certainly going to happen here, right?
Because multiplying this row by any of these other Rose is going to be
zero so that's all good.
We go down now to the second row.
Again nothing in that first coordinate, right.
Because this this one over U and this V don't don't coincide at all.
Go to the next one.
The one over V and the V do coincide.
So we've got Loops got a one there because going to be V over V which
equals 1.
Which is great.
Now we've got this row 0, 0, 0 negative 1.
What that means is that again, as we go through, for each of these
elements 0 is going to be multiplying everything but the last value.
So we're just basically getting a 0, a 0 and hey, there's that - one
that coincides with the negative 1 here.
So that's a 1 right on that final time.
And then the last time we've got this, this guy and visceral
multiplying.
It there's just that one negative one there.
That's going to multiply this guy which is going to put a 1 over here,
so it's basically just producing the exact identity.
Make sure you wanted right.
You got you got this row times.
This is nothing this row times.
This is oh wait.
Did I mess that up though?
This row times this.
No, no.
It isn't because this is not this, this is not.
Because we're multiplying this row times.
This column that's going to give me a negative one.
So I think I'm
A slight mistake there didn't?
I should this be a night?
This should be a negative one.
Let's double-check that.
Let me actually write these.
It's hard for me to multiply these side-by-side like, like upside down
like this.
I like to be able to do them where I can see it, but let me just check
that one more time.
So I know that all those are correct, but when we get down to this
last row so you x 0 0 times 0 0 times 0 0 times 0, that's a zero zero
time.
Okay, so then we're going to go down to this column here, right?
So this column here 0 x 0 v x 0 0 times 0 0 times 0.
So that's still a zero as well.
Now we're going to go to this element here so it's this column times
this row 0 times 0 0 x 0 d x, 0 and negative 1 times negative 1.
Yeah.
So
Should have been a negative one there that was that was incorrect of
me.
Looks like, right?
At least that appears to be the case if I want that to be.
Yeah, don't try to be the correct value.
yeah, and then the end and then the final column
Zero zero.
Sorry, this is just this is just bugging me for a second here.
So if we are going to stuff, this is what we're going to end up with
in here.
If this is what, you know, we have negative Z in here.
And we want to be able to get back a one here.
this is actually a little confusing if we write, if we want to be able
to get back a one,
In this location.
Then I need something.
which would X this
gives me a 1 so that's actually more complicated.
I led you astray there by saying that that part
Was as easy as it was.
That's not true.
That's just a bald-faced lie.
I'm going to undo that lie right now.
Here's why that was a lie.
I like in my head sort of did a little brain fart there and said well
okay since the W coordinate so he's one you can just do 0 0 0 1 and
I'll do it.
That's not true.
This is our input Vector now.
So I have to actually make these end up equaling 1, right?
This is all I have four inputs.
So if I want to get a 1 in The W, I've got to make a thing here that
will actually produce that which is harder.
Right.
That's a harder thing to do.
So you can see what that's going to have to be, right?
I I need to figure out a way to make some combination of these values
equal 1.
Right now there's a couple of ways that I could do that but if you
look at what happens here, I can't do it with any combination of these
three terms.
Right?
These two.
And this one because they share nothing in common, it's an x, a y and
a z, no way of combining these.
Ever going to produce that result but because I do have a d y + easy
here.
Right.
Actually.
Why is that look like that?
That's
It's not what that is.
That's that's that right?
That's DZ plus e.
Why did I think I was?
I was one off on their.
Well it's not a good math day, huh?
Yeah.
Right that there.
There we go.
Right 0 times x.
0, x, y, --d, x z.
Right, plus e.
Don't know why the why I got stuffed in there?
That doesn't make any sense.
So that's actually what we've got there.
Right?
And so, yeah, if you take a look at what happens here, what I was
about to say still is the same, but I just want to make sure that was
the correct term.
So I can't really do anything to create a one by using these two
because I don't have the same terms.
I can't use this one in this one.
I can't use this one that one, but these two, both have a z in them,
right?
So I should be able to do something potentially to make this work out
so I can get values that actually make sense in the bottom, right?
And so, we can take a look at what this would be.
If I just said down the bottom here, if I just said I had, you know,
what would be the right letters for this?
Let's say I did like I J K L, right?
We basically know in this situation, I and J are useless.
They're not going to produce anything useful for us, right?
So we're basically looking at just k.
I'll actually use just all use iron Jacobs are easier to say Well
they're actually let's use I MK K and J.
That's pretty good.
So if we have two coefficients here that multiply these can we get a
one out of them is basically what we are wondering, right?
In other words, can we figure out some way of getting a one back up in
here?
When we actually do that inverse right when we're multiplying by
these.
So, I want to produce a 1 in the output.
I want to multiply by 0 0, KJ to do it.
And so that would just give me K DZ plus e, right?
And then J is is multiplying this.
So - Jay-Z write equals 1 is it possible to do so that's K.
DZ plus ke minus J.
Z equals one group the terms.
So we end up with
The to Z terms coming together that's K Dee right?
Actually I suppose I want to solve
the tricky thing here is, I could really it's kind of a free variable
problem, so I don't know that I really
I don't know that I really have is our it's going to be over, there's
going to be more ways to do this than just one, right?
Because we've got essentially two variables there to play with and
those there's only one actual output value.
So we don't really have a completely defined system here but either
way.
So let's go ahead and keep moving these around.
So if I, if I
If I take a look at it like this, I should be able to just pick an
arbitrary value for one of these.
So what I could do is say, let's just pick one for Z and see what
happens, for example, that presumably would be one way to do it, so
let's try that.
So if I just said that Jay was equal to one, I would have k.
Do you see pussy?
minus Z equals 1, excuse me again, these terms are
Well.
So now what I want to do here, I guess actually there's no need to do
that because I want to solve for K anyway.
So let me just move the Z over there side.
I get K DZ plus E equals z, i get k equals z over DZ plus e right?
And
It looks like in that case, that's still a little bit dicey, right?
Because it almost works, right?
I would get 1 over D, in this case, if it was just this turn, but the
plus e makes this problematic.
Hmm.
Jimmy.
So that does not quite work.
Hm.
The reason I say this doesn't quite work, you'll have to forgive me
for having an allergy allergy math morning.
If the reason this doesn't quite work is because I can't sets, I can't
use Z in the actual values.
I have to have Z cancel itself out, right?
Because if I wanted to use the in the values, yeah, I'd have to use
them.
If I want to use the in the, in the value itself, that's not possible.
Because the Matrix has to be a set of constant values, it can't be
something that's proportional to one of the input.
Use which in this case would be the Z value, right?
So that's not allowed.
Now, in this case, it would cancel partially but not fully, right?
So we could, for example, divide the top and the Bottom by Z, and you
would get 1 over D, but it would be plus Z over Z which is not
possible to create.
So it's almost there but not quite looking at this slightly
differently.
What I could say is well okay.
I know I want this Matrix to come out like this and so what I need to
do is figure out what I could do Matrix wise, that would make that
happen.
So given the set, the fact that the Matrix looks like this so far,
what is something that multiplies by these values?
That gives me that in the end, right?
And so you know what I would have there is I'd have these four
equations.
I know that I would have to have a 0 here and a 0 here because there
can't be anything here or here.
Right.
And then I would know that I would need to have a zero here as well.
I'm sorry.
I know that I have to have a 0 here, as well.
So multiplying by this, I can't have anything in this location, right?
Well, no, that's not true.
Sorry.
So I would know that I would have one equation that would tell me what
to do here and it would have to work with the D and the negative 1.
So that would be one equation.
I can use right 0 times 0 plus 0 times 0, DK minus J, right?
Um, so DK.
Minus J has to equal 0 and then finally I need a 1 here so that would
be zero.
Zero ke, right?
So just ke has to equal one.
So those to do, give me a set of equations, I could solve now and that
actually works quite a bit better for me.
If I know ke has to equal 1.
Then I know that K is just 1 over e, right?
Once I know that K is 1 over e, that means that D times 1 over e.
Minus J.
Equals 0 or J equals D over ee, right?
So that means my actual Matrix.
if this is to be believed,
Right.
Is going to be 1 over e, 4K.
Is that right?
When I review 4K.
India / e4j?
All right, so let's see if that checks out so 0 times 0 right here to
here.
0 x 0 e times 1 over e is 1 right and 0 times D over eight so that
does equal 1, which is exactly what I wanted.
Let's see about this value here.
Equaling 0 0 times 0 0 times 0, D, / e, and then - do you / e.
So that is exactly one.
Alright, so this does look like the correct inverse Matrix now despite
a
A bit of morning brain fighting there.
And again this was just by doing it by inspection without actually
trying to invert The Matrix in a kind of proper way.
It was a little, I thought it was easier than it was at first.
So I probably should have been a little more rigorous about that I've
but, you know, sometimes you get you get lulled into when you see that
nice starting diagonal structure, their into just being a little bit
lazy, which I was however, it looks like now we've got the correct
inverse Matrix here, which means if you take a look at what happens,
And we now have a way of constructing the inverse projection.
Without actually having to invert The Matrix.
But unfortunately our projection Matrix, if you look at what happens.
Our projection Matrix is actually produced slightly differently than
that.
It takes to projection Matrix, which yes, does come directly from this
stuff, right?
But it takes that Matrix and then it multiplies it by this camera
Matrix, right?
And that camera Matrix is another sort of fancy set of components
right?
XYZ axes and a in a position, right?
So all that is a little bit wonky as well.
So what do we do about that?
Well, because we remember we have to do the complete, we have to undo
the transfer and buy this.
Well again we can lean on, linear algebra a little bit here.
And just take a look at what happens.
So we've got a situation like this, right?
Our projection Matrix is a combination of two of these things, right?
It's a and b.
Well, if you take a look at what would happen, if we have a, and b
times a point, right?
This is what we're doing essentially.
And we want to undo this.
We want to solve for p.
Well, we can use the same trick that I applied before.
If I multiply both sides by a inverse,
I would get this.
Right?
And this a inverse, a is going to cancel out so I get a inverse P
Prime equals BP.
Right.
That's all good.
Keep going.
Multiply both sides by B, inverse
Now I have the solution to the equation.
I wanted, I want P the input.
I have the output which is p.
Prime, I know that I multiply by B inverse a inverse to get it right.
What that means is that if I have a matrix, a b, which is what I have
for my projection, I can compute its inverse Matrix right there by
inverting.
Both of these separately and swapping the order.
Right?
So the inverse projection Matrix
is actually just the B Matrix inverted times, the a matrix inverted
and that I could do,
One because I did invert b or sorry, a already.
I did already invert the projection part by hand and we know what that
is so we could build it directly.
And the camera transform, right?
We can do all kinds of sliced up with because we know our camera
transform has a very specific structure to it, right?
So we'll take a look at that in a second, but,
what that does mean is we want to augment and this is something that I
generally do all the time for these routines in in the real world in
life is like typically have a thing called like, you know,
M, 4 by 4 inverse or something like this.
And what it has is like forward and inverse in it.
And when you make a routine, you just generate both the forward Matrix
and the reverse Matrix at the same time, right?
We don't need these here anymore.
so this our Matrix, I'm going to call F now
and we call this one, eye is bad because it means identity.
So let's call this reverse.
Not a great word for it but I guess it just depends on your
perspective.
Pun intended.
All right so if I want to make the forward Matrix, I know it looks
like this.
If I want to make the inverse Matrix, I now know what that does look
like.
Let's go ahead and
It's that.
So, this is 1 over a times C.
And then just zeros.
This is 1 over U times C.
And the zeros.
There we go.
And then this is all zeros in a negative.
And this is all zeros and then an into inverses Francis is 0.
0 1 over e.
Do you already?
Right.
So now we've got a reverse Matrix here and what we can do in our test
code as well as we can do.
Like I and we can say, let's make sure that the reverse times the
forwards actually does equal.
The identity Matrix that makes sense.
So, let's just try that and four by four.
In results.
I guess we could do this as well.
Like, I suppose, I could do this.
That's a little better, isn't it?
So now we've created both of these and we return that result, we get
both of them back the forward and the inverse right because they're
pretty cheap for it to build both of them, if that makes sense.
And we can also test them here so we can say result, inverse times
result dot forward.
Too many initializers.
It is.
How is that too many initializers?
This is supposed to have two Matrix 4 by 4, isn't it, right?
Here's the first one.
It's going to be one of those cases of more brackets than anyone has
ever had before.
Do you just want me to bracket that more?
Yes, so here we go forward.
And there we are.
All right, and so now in perspective, projection, we can just grab the
Word out we don't have to change this routine yet but we can jump into
our math now and actually test what we did because you saw that I was
having a little bit of a slow math morning there.
I don't want to just dump that coat in and go, I'm sure it works fine,
it'll be great because that's not probably a same way to do things.
So I'm going to go ahead and go to perspective.
Affection.
Here we go.
And when we produce these two matrices, now I can take a look at the
resulting Matrix when I multiply them together.
And again, we should expect the identity Matrix if we don't get the in
and make sure we know we messed up now.
There it is.
So we're looking good here, right?
And we can test this a few times, obviously, oops, I Don't Wanna Stop
wherever there was a stopping, there we go.
So you can kind of see like I'm just verifying.
This is always going to be in a matrix and that's good.
That's what we want and and everything's happy and these are real
values coming in.
Are so that's all good.
Yeah, right.
So now we've built the forward and inverse matrices for that.
Let's just do the one for the orthographic projection because that's
like basically the exact same Matrix, right?
It's going to be pretty much identical.
Just a little bit simpler probably.
So we can do the exact same thing.
So here's the orthographic projection, right?
The Matrix is even simpler because it's only got one off agonal
element instead of to off agonal elements and it has a 1 in the final
position as well.
So we're talking about an even easier solution here.
So let's go ahead and do it.
We'll see if I can not be as much of a math, but since I was on the
previous one.
So here's, I'm just going to do this one directly since, hopefully
everyone gets the idea by now.
Oops, some drawn problems.
Here A B, it's a b d e, so a 0, 0 0.
Be let me have it.
I'm having a really bad drawing time right now, for some reason, 00.
0 0, d e.
00:01 Boot.
And now we want to multiply these together.
All right, so same thing is true here.
We know that this is just going to have to be an inverse a there's no
other way around that, right?
So, if we look at what happens here in order to get a one, we just
have to have an inverse a same exact thing as before.
Same thing here with be, that's going to have to be a 1 over B to get
that to happen, right?
Oops.
and again, that
These all have to multiply out the same as well.
Alright.
So 0 over B, that's just going to give us this row, which is what I'm
sorry, 1 over B is going to give us this row and then we move on to
getting this part to work out.
So now we have to have D, we would need a 1 over D here to get a 1,
but we also have the E.
So we need to be a little bit more careful.
This one, this row with the 0001 as well or this column here.
it's going to be a little interesting to, but
We know, a couple things.
So first of all, a times this row has to equal to 0 here, right?
Which means that we know that the first value would have to be zero
because you're not going to get an A to cancel that from anywhere
else.
So we know that that has to be zero as we come through, right?
That's that's just a given.
Furthermore when we come through here, multiply 0 B 0 0 right we would
know that we have to cancel out the be so that has to be zero as well.
And so then here we are just left with 0 0 D 0 which I guess means
that yeah, if for this row is well this would have to be a 1 over D
because there's nothing, there's no other coefficients.
This is the only one that we can actually use.
So, in order to get that one there, we know it has to be 0, 0 1 over
d, right?
And then, finally, for this one, we would have 0 0.
D, the whatever D would multiply this guy, right?
So this is going to end up
Being an e over D term.
Right here.
So if we need this to equal zero, we would need to then have this x,
we would have to subtract an e over D here, right?
So this has to be a - e over D.
In order to get this to come out to 0 which we need it to, right?
I don't want that to read improperly some do - you ever do way over
there.
So then it's right you can see what happens.
We get 0 times 0 0 x 0 e times 1 over D is e over d, right?
1 times.
Negative B over D is - yard eat those cancel out and become 0 which is
what we want.
And finally we have all these are going to be 0 against.
We don't want the a to multiply in.
We don't want the be to multiply in.
We end up here with zero.
0d x 1 over D.
That's going to be a 1, right?
This is a d over D here.
As well as we come down to multiply through.
Oh wait no.
Why am I saying that?
We're not mouth like that.
R 0, 0, 0, 0 0, d x, something but we don't want anything so we just
put a zero there, never mind and then 0 times, whatever would be here
which we don't have to think about yet.
And then furthermore last row 0 times 0 0 times 0 0 times e + 1 times
1.
Right.
Okay.
Just want to double check for brain farts again.
On that one.
They didn't put those in the wrong place.
So multiplying down the row here.
Okay.
Whatever 8 times a is 100 000 000 B times B, right?
That's one there.
00.
000 000.
1 over D times.
D is d, right?
Which is 1.
So 1 over D times, D is D over DT which is 1 and then 0 times,
negative a over D is just 0
which is what we want.
So that's good.
Yes, that's all good.
Then let's take a look at this 10 times 0.
0, times 0 e x.
That is one, over is e over D and then 1 times negative B over D, that
looks right to, all right, so think that looks right.
Let's double check because again, slow math morning means probably
making a mistake somewhere and 4x4 inverse.
Let's take a look.
V equals.
whenever a
and again, I'm just copying this from the math.
Not doing anything here.
And - you ready?
All right.
Let's see how that does.
So, coming into the orthographic projection here.
And let's take a look.
Do we get an identity or didn't we?
We did.
Good.
All right.
So, I think that is now satisfactory.
Although she is 0, is that right near plus far near - far?
Oh yeah, that is correct.
All right.
So, what does that give us?
Well, now we actually have M by M 4 by 4 in verse that we can take
here.
Right and to produce our projection Matrix.
Now we know that we can do it by going like this.
Gonna.
Do that.
So we can create a projection matrix by using the forward transform.
But now we also have the inverse transform, which means that if we
wanted to make an inverse, right?
So that when we do our setup, we store both of them.
We can actually do that by taking the reverse and just having a camera
C inverse as well.
Right.
Oops.
Because remember, if we just swap the order of these two and invert
them, we would get an inverse that does exactly what we want.
So the question is just how do we build an inverse camera?
See, because you can see here is US building the camera transform.
so, if we take a look inside math,
Here's our camera, transform right?
Does that make sense?
So the question is just, how do we make an inverse can be transformed
and in fact, you can imagine us doing the exact same thing here that
we did before.
If we could make this camera seba forward and inverse as well.
Then we would just say, well camera, C inverse, right?
So, we could have exactly the same thing that we had in all cases,
right?
So, the question now is just how do we make this produce em 4x4
inverse rather than just a single
Goal and four by four.
That's what we're trying to do.
Because once we do that, then we have a complete inverse.
When we have the complete inverse, we're pretty much done with our own
project because all we had to do for unprojected is actually take
those coordinates.
Those clip coordinates that we already had that we you know, reverse
the screen space transform on.
And push it through that Matrix and out.
We would get the the correct on projected value, right?
So the question is, what is this Matrix?
We know we're making this thing here but what is what is this, you
know.
Well, this one becomes a lot more Analytical in the sense that you
kind of got to put on your thinking cap a little bit harder than
before.
It's not just a bag of numbers we can just look at, right?
It's a lot more complicated than that, we're talking about something
we're alright, we know we've got a row here, that's the x-axis, right?
And then a 0, we've got a row here.
This is the y-axis.
And then a 0 or 0.
Here, this is the Z axis, and a zero.
Okay,
And then we've got the position and a one.
That's what we're looking at, right?
As a matrix.
This is the camera Matrix.
Well.
Let's take these two in separate parts.
So what did we learn from looking at the way?
We were inverting matrices.
Before what you can sort of see is that upper pieces cannot be
affected by lower pieces in a way, to put this, how should I put this?
So, if you think of a matrix as being like, this sort of a thing,
right?
We're like, if I have a 4 by 4 Matrix, there's a 1 by 1 Matrix and
then a two-byte.
Matrix and a 3 by 3, Matrix on a 4, by 4 Matrix, right?
It's like it's growing each time.
Well this one by one Matrix here.
It's got to invert exactly the way it inverts.
Right.
There's nothing there's nothing.
These values can do out here to really change what the inverse of that
thing is going to be.
And the reason for that is simply because like
How should I put this?
You can see the way this was happening up here, right?
When I'm multiplying, these things together, I'm going to get this row
times.
This row to produce this value, right?
And there's not a lot.
I there's, I'm never going to involve anything else outside of that,
right?
So in some senses I guess maybe it's wrong to say like the one by one.
But you're looking at it in slices that look like this, right?
And this bottom part is now no longer involved in producing.
Value.
So, you always have this sort of way of kind of looking at the Matrix,
if you want to of isolating pieces of it and you can, you know, you
can think about those pieces as being
You can think about those pieces individually, if you can identify
ways in, which they will not affect, or other things cannot affect
them.
This is a really bad explanation.
Let me try that one more time.
So, if you take a look at the structure of this Matrix, right?
You can see that it has this 00:01 on the bottom, right?
If you take a look at how that will have to interact when I multiply
this by its inverse, right?
So,
Give yourself a little more room here.
When I multiply this by its inverse what is that telling me?
Well these three zeros down here mean that when I do this
multiplication to produce this value.
I'm not considering what happens here at all right.
Furthermore, this part right here, I'm not concerning what happens
here at all right, or here.
So essentially what's happening with this Matrix is I know that when I
compute the inverse, I don't have to care what happens here.
All, when I produce this inverse so I know that I'm going to have to
produce this upper 3x3.
Without using these which means that the only things I have for
producing that three by three are here.
Right.
The can't be in here.
Because those those vote terms can't contribute.
Furthermore, I know that the only thing that is in these coordinates
is the position and the position is certainly not going to be involved
in canceling out the axes since they're unrelated which means that
this part of the Matrix which is the part of the inverse Matrix, that
would multiply p is also not involved.
So that allows me to focus on just the upper 3x3 and know that this 3
by 3 and this 3 by 3 come together to form this inverse without the
participation of the outer rows.
I think that was a better explanation.
Hopefully that made some sense to you.
All right.
so, the question is,
if I have an X Y and Z axis in here,
Oops.
So, if I have an X Y and Z axis in here, how would I go about
producing a matrix which when multiplied here would produce the
identity Matrix?
Well, those of you that remember all of our discussions about the
inverses, the transpose, right?
Do you remember this?
Basically if a is an orthogonal Matrix a inverse equals a transpose.
Remember that?
Well it just so happens that if this were an orthogonal Matrix and we
know that it mostly is, right?
Because if these were unit length and they're at right angles to each
other then it's orthogonal, right?
That's the definition of an orthogonal coordinate system.
In an orthogonal Matrix is the basis vectors are at right angles to
each other and our unit length.
If that was the case, we would know the transpose was the inverse.
Why was it?
Well, we did this before.
It's because if I put the transpose in here, so I flipped these around
so that instead they were going by rows, instead of by columns.
I remember, we did this before us.
This is just review.
Hopefully, remember the dot product of these, which is what we're
taking here.
When we do the x times, the X Y times, y, z times Z right of each of
these vectors.
The dot products here are going to equal 1 if it's the same vector and
0.
If it's not why?
Because the dot product of a vector with itself, if it's unit length
is 1, right?
Because
Over the dot product is a b cosine Theta.
Right number, this ate a dot, b equals a b cosine Theta.
This is always going to be 1.
This is always going to be one if all of our vectors are unit length.
So we're just talking about cosine Theta, cosine theta4, 2 things that
are pointing exactly the same direction which is what will happen.
If I multiply a vector by itself is always one if they're pointing at
90 degrees to each other, it will be 0.
That's just what the cosine is at 90 degrees, right?
So I will get this Matrix if I put these in like this because the only
time I will get a one is when the vectors are exactly the same Vector
x times x.
And any time I do x times y, I'll get a 0 here and here anytime they
do x times z, l get a zeros here and here many times I do y times,
they'll get a 0 here and here that is exactly what I want.
So all I need to do to build the camera.
Matrix is just flip these around unless
unless,
They were the wrong size has right?
What if these were longer or shorter and now we never do that for the
prospective transform.
But we did do that for the orthographic transform.
Remember in our orthographic transform, we did a little Shenanigans
here.
We like shenana.
We did a little like flipping around and shenanigans and stuff, right?
And all that.
Good things where we did a set, can we transform?
And here we go.
There's the shenanigans, right?
So these are still
Worth these vectors are still orthogonal to each other but they are
different lengths.
So the it is not an orthonormal or orthogonal Matrix.
For some reason, orthogonal matrices are not orthogonal vectors
they're orthonormal vectors.
Don't ask me how that terminology came about but it did.
Right?
So we need to be able to correct for the fact that although, we will
always produce a diagonal matrix by doing this.
These values may not be ones.
They may be other values, right?
Because if x had a length of 2, instead of 1, then 2 times 2, is going
to be for here rather than one times, one being one.
So we're going to get the wrong values.
We get the squared length of the vectors coming down the diagonal.
Whatever are we to do?
Oh no, it is not possible to solve The Matrix, everyone give up right
now.
That is not true and it's not true because we know that this is the
equation that will be in each of these slots, right?
So we know that all we have to do is just change the length of these
to counteract.
Whatever the length of them were over here specifically, if I know
that this length is going to come out to to I just need to make my
other length.
Come out to one over two and I'm done.
Right.
So again, very, very straightforward for us to do this when we create
that camera transform.
I basically need exactly the same thing for that upper piece, right?
So here's
I know what I call this is call this a
and be.
All right.
Oops.
There we go.
So if I stop these into the comms again, I'm almost correct.
But not quite because I've got some issues here still.
And that is that these lengths may be wrong.
So what I want to do is multiply each of these by correction factor
and that correction factor, should be whatever the inverse length is.
So, what I want to do is say 1 over the length of x times x, right?
Or I should say X over length x, that would give me essentially the
Version of it, right?
So that's going to that's if the length was to.
Now, the length will be hat, will be point five, right?
So,
Like so on, but again because this already have that length, what that
will end up doing is that will not give me the correction that I want
trying to explain how I got a coefficient in here.
And I think I'm just gonna have to show you.
All right?
So if I have a vector, right?
Let's say I take a vector, a, right?
And I know that the length of a is equal to 2, right?
Then if I do a over, sorry if I
To a over length of a and I want to know, what is the length of this
new Vector, right?
Well, that's just giving me something over to whose length was
already, too.
That's just going to give me a length of 1, right?
That's not sufficient for our purposes.
That's normalizing the vector to a length of 1, but I want it to be
the inverse of its own length.
So I need to divide by its length again.
Does that make sense?
So after normalization, you would you
I'd go by the length again.
So after you divide by the length, you have looked.
Again, that's just the square of the length right there.
It's, I'm basically like dividing by the length and then dividing by
the length.
Again,
Hopefully, that makes some sense and we don't have a divide operator
for vectors yet, do we?
Yeah, we don't.
I'm going to make one.
Math.
Operator times.
There we go.
And so what I want to do here is I want to just make something that
will do a divide of these two, right?
And so, all I'm going to do is say, Hey, whenever I get a divisor,
right?
Look, something that's going to divide out.
What I want to do is just say, all right, take that value and invert
it and then multiply it, right.
So again I'm not really I'm just sort of still doing a multiplying
operator here either, I'm just asking it to do, I'm asking it to do
the inverse of the value first and then do the multiplication because
that's the same thing as Division.
And so we don't have to write another operator.
We don't actually have to write one of these.
It does division, right, we just pipe it through multiplication.
That is not what I want to do yet because we don't have the test
function in there yet, okay?
So that is the first step.
Here's our camera, transform.
So that is the first step and that will get us the upper 3x3 correctly
but there is also this other portion which is the translation portion
of the Matrix and we have not addressed that part yet, right?
So if we take a look at what's going to happen over here, when we do
our multiplication, we know that we're going to get exactly what we'd
expect in the upper 3x3 Now by by using these X transforms.
Why transforms, right?
And then furthermore, we know we've got this position in here and the
position piece.
We know we don't want involved in any of these, right?
So presumably we know we don't want anything over here, so the zeros
over here can stay, but what we do need to do is as we're producing
these values over here.
Yes, so as we're producing values over here, we're going to have to
deal with with that somewhere.
Alright, so let's take a look at a couple more things here.
So as we do our multiplications for here, right?
We're going to get nothing in here because of this, as we do our
multiplications for these values.
However, rather these values, we're going to have to deal with, sorry
these values.
We're going to have to deal with the p because it's going to multiply
all of
These.
So basically what happens here is we get p transpose X, right?
We're going to get pee.
Time's the, the x that we put in here, we're going to have P transpose
X, right?
In here, and we don't want that.
We want a zero here, right?
So, that P transpose X.
And then, we have to put something in here right into these values.
That's going to solve that problem for us basically.
So, whatever we get in here, has to fix the P transpose X problem.
We need to get Negative P transpose X in here, right?
And actually, that's
Lee what we want since we know that the first terms have to produce
this Matrix, we know that these are non-negotiable.
So we know we're going to produce a p transpose X up here.
So what we need to do is put something in here, which when multiplied
by this 1 value, right here will produce a negative P transpose X to
cancel it out.
Same here, this has to be negative P transpose, y negative P transpose
Z.
Now remember it's not the actual x-axis from the original, it's the
modified
x axis.
So we actually need to take that one that we've produced that's in the
column already and transpose, you know, take the dot product of it
with p and put those negatives in there, right?
Because that's the only thing that's going to eliminate it.
Once we come down through here to do these, I think we're basically
all done, there's nothing else.
We really need to do.
So the bottom can stay 0, 0, 0 1.
So it's just these values that need to get modified.
All right, so let's go ahead and make these actual vectors so this is
like you know I'm going to call it.
I x i y z for now.
Okay, and we can build this exactly the same way, so we can do a
Translate.
I assume translate just stuff that in.
Yeah, it does.
So we can do a translate on this and this is not the most efficient
way to build this.
We probably could make a much more efficient way to build this, but so
we can go ahead and do it.
Translate on this.
And what we need to do to do the translate is just make that special
Vector, right?
So this is the IP vector.
Okay.
So what's that?
I P Vector will.
Again you can almost look at this exactly the same way.
If you take a look at what goes on here, what is that?
What what does that end up actually meaning right - P transpose X and
our peaches, right?
Those are just the the
The Columns here, right of these of these.
Vectors so really, I mean, I'm just going to build it manually because
I don't really see any reason not to but it's yeah, it's, it's again,
very straightforward.
I'm literally just taking the this - P transfer.
- P transpose V - P transpose e and just doing it directly here,
right?
So what I want to do here is take the inner product, right?
That's the transpose.
I want to do the negative of whatever that this value was.
So we kind of need the composite a p-value here.
I want to save that, right?
And I don't know what we would call that I'll call that alcohol at a
p.
The P that went into a
So we want to take the dot product of that with our various vectors,
that's all we need.
and since each of those is - I'll just skip that
And do it like this.
Right.
And that should give us what we need.
Now we've got our inverted X are sort of our inverse components.
We've got the three axes corrected for length, so they don't have to
be length one and it'll still work.
We then have our IP values which is just to correct for those those
off components and that should be basically everything that we need.
Now, we can test this exactly the way that we tested the other one.
We can use the same same bit here.
And what I could do here is I think we have a
We're go, so we can look at this test case and we can see whether or
not the inverse works properly in this case as well.
So looks pretty good.
You can see we've got a little tiny values on the off diagonal here.
That's understandable like this is not infinite Precision.
So those are actually pretty reasonable values.
You can see they're very very tiny there.
However that's not good.
So, we do have a bug.
You can see we've got a bug there.
See that those should both be zero values and they're not right, so
that's not.
We have we have made an error.
And let's find out what the area is.
So for whatever reason we never have a problem.
Well, looks like the bug wasn't in
Math.
It was in the typing as is.
So often the way I'm like, why is our x value always correct in our y
and z are too well, how about?
Because you didn't type in the equations for the other two correctly?
That could be.
There we go.
Nope, still got one.
So now we've got everybody correct.
Except except just the Y component.
Of.
Just the Y component, the Y of the p-value.
let me also double-check, I want to this camera, I want to put in some
crazier values to it there, so there's
Okay, so taking a look at this.
It's just want to see if it's always there or not.
So no, it's like it's does definitely have problems in the P
component.
You can see that we're pretty much getting correct in versus
everywhere else.
As far as I can tell, these are obviously very tiny value, so they're
basically zero, so that's fine.
The math is not always going to be exact.
It's going to be a little bit off in the bottom, so that's all fine.
So it's really just the, those P values that are incorrect.
So let's retake a look at our p-values there and make sure that I'm
not doing something.
Well,
I guess we know that I am definitely doing something dumb so let's
find out what that something dumb actually is and take a look at it.
Okay.
So we have our IX here, r, i y here, ri Z here, and then we've got
zero zero zero one down the bottom and what do we have ostensibly on
the top?
I'm sorry on the P values.
Essentially, we have the inner product of the P values that were
coming into whatever.
We're in the original Matrix, right?
We've essentially got those negated and and Dot product ID with each
of these.
So here in theory, we've got negative P, transpose ax.
You know, I kind of need better.
I need more mathy way of writing that if I'm going to have a bunch of
equations here.
So let's call this like we'll just call this U V W so you the W 0 0 0
1 like so and then here we are putting in - Peter.
Suppose you - P transpose.
V - P transpose W, right?
And our incoming Matrix is an is the x axis down here.
The 0 y.
0 Z, 0 and P with the one.
Yes.
Okay.
And what do we end up with well?
X dot U is 1 by definition.
In fact, we already know that we've got this working properly.
We tested it.
So, that's all correct.
Obviously, these are all going to be zeros down here.
And this is going to be 1 here and we know that that's all true from
testing.
So our problem is this up here.
So let's see what the problem actually is.
This is going to be P transpose U, right?
It's PX time.
Yeah.
So I don't know.
This looks right to me that's going to be P transpose U and then we're
going to multiply 1 times negative P to you.
So, that should be a zero.
Same thing.
Should happen here.
This should be P transpose V, right?
And then we should have a negative P transpose V there and then same
with this, this would be P transpose, W minus P transpose W, right?
So these should all work out to be 0 there.
That's what I would have expected.
so, I am a little confused as to what
Oh no, no, no, no.
I this is a camera transform.
It's already inverted.
I was building in.
I was totally, yeah.
Well, it's been, it's been a bad math morning.
It's the other way round.
Duh.
I typed it in correctly but I did.
Yeah, it's the other way around.
This is a camera transform.
So it's XYZ this way.
Yeah, yeah.
Alright.
Well hey man, this is why you test, you know what I'm saying.
It was the other way around.
This is what we're actually dealing with.
And so when we put these in here it's actually this way.
Okay, now it makes much more sense.
Why we're getting the wrong result?
It's going to be
PX.
Right.
Sorry PX.
X ux butt.
Py times, U times V y+ peasy.
X wz, right?
You can see it's doing a DOT product but I'm sorry these are not
This is those are all exes.
So, it's actually doing a cross this way.
So, the negation we want is actually not a DOT product with one of
these vectors.
It's a, it's a DOT with the X components of it, which is very
different, right?
It's actually this.
Right.
The AP is still going as if a DOT product but it's going this way.
Does that make sense?
So, that is what we actually need to do, because we need to take the
dot products across this way.
Because, again, not I was thinking of it as built for in summertime.
For some reason, my head I was thinking, oh, we're building the
opposite of a
Of an object transform.
We're not.
This is a camera transform.
So we're stuffing the rose, the input values that we get are going
into the rose of the source Matrix but yet simple enough fix and you
can see.
Now, we're Rock Solid on that only very tiny values on the off
diagonal and everything else is fine.
Let's double-check with some fancier matrices here.
There we go.
And still Rock Solid.
So that's that's very good, right?
Can see the only things we ever get there.
Very, very tiny values on the object.
R.
Who lot of math this morning.
I wasn't awake enough for it as the case may be, but it worked out
quite well in the end.
So I'm happy with that.
Math is always fun fine if it makes if it works out, cleanly in the
end.
All right, so back to where we were before, we're kind of ready to go
now because we've got all the stuff that we need, so we can make a
projection in an inverse projection together, right?
And we're all good to go.
So if we want to save now when we do this push set,
Call.
If we actually want to extend that to be something that saves the
entire setup, right?
We can do that.
So what we're going to do here is just extend last projection to be
one of these more fancy matrices, right?
So now we can say, Okay M 4 by 4 in proj.
And we can say project forward.
And proj.
Inverse.
We get both of those and now we just pass that along, right?
And so, then our push set up call.
Needs to remember that.
And then everyone else has to abide by it, right?
This part here.
Where do we set the last projects?
There it is.
So we save the last project when we do our, when we push this down, we
don't need to know that.
You don't need to know the inverse.
So we can just save that and, let's see.
It move forward for proj.
Probably should keep this.
And really, I should probably call this composite, right.
The state's more accurately, what it actually is it's the projection
plus the camera transform.
So that's about it, let's see here.
This is the identity Matrix and so really, that's just four by four
in, I
And I can, I do I probably can't do this.
Can I
Thank you.
So I think that's about all we would need for that.
Now, we should have the exact same pipeline running, but now we have
the ability to access the inverse of our projection at any time.
So now inside render group when we do a nun project, if we want to
You can see the unprotect here, right?
If we want to, once we adjust back to screen space, all we need to
know is what the Z value actually.
Is that we're working with here, which we do have, right?
And once we know the Z value that we're working with, we can go ahead
and do the reverse transform on that right now.
We have some issues here.
And that issue is just that the value that someone's going to give us
for the Z is going to be a little bit confusing because they need to
give us the Z.
When we do the sun project, the Z is going to range from negative one
to one but they don't really know what that is, right?
They don't know what the negative one to one value actually is
Because they're used to thinking of the Z as just being a distance
from the camera.
But here, it's already been transformed into clip space, right?
So it's kind of confusing and it's a little bit tough for them to
understand, what they're actually looking at, in that case, right?
So when they give a distance from the camera, in this case, what we
kind of need to do is figure out, okay, what would the forward
transform of that ZB?
And when we need to invert, transform that Z back, right?
So it's kind of a difficult operation but just bear
with me and we can, we can work through it.
So
Basically what we're saying here is, right.
Let's just look at the whole thing once again, because I know that
it's pretty confusing and I threw a lot of math at you.
So, we've got a p Prime, right?
And we've got an A BP.
This is what we're working.
But after this, it actually also goes through to screen space, but
presumably, hopefully everyone's all comfortable with us on doing this
screen space part of it with this part right here.
So we're not going to talk about that right now.
So we're just talking about this.
And so basically what we're talking about is this right here, here is
a 3D coordinate in the world right here.
This B value, probably should have drawn that slightly differently.
This B value right here, right?
That's the camera transform.
This is the projection.
Right.
And this is clip space.
And then we have a way of taking clubface to screen space but we're
assuming we sort of taking that out of the equation.
Now by just reversing it.
Okay.
So now we know we can reverse this, right?
We can reverse this just by using that inverse transform that we had.
So once we have like will recall, we're going to rename this clip
Space X Y right or just clip space.
Right.
So once I have this, the question here, this is z value.
We don't really know what it's going to be obviously, and this stuff
is kind of busted at this point but we'll just stick with me here.
Just leave that for a second.
So we have this clip space here and the clip space part of it.
If we actually have the Z value set correctly, which we don't yet, but
if we did, then we would know that the world's face version, right?
Would just be whatever that inverse Matrix was times, the clip
coordinates, right?
So, whatever our last projection Matrix, the one that we're using
those trying to protect from whatever the inverse Matrix is of that
times.
Those clip coordinates will give us back our world space and then the
result that we want to return can just be the world space - that
object transform.
Now, I don't remember how we're applying the object transform at this
point.
I just want to make sure that I remember that.
I double-check how we're doing that object transform.
So let's take a quick look at that.
Here's the push bitmap call.
So push quad.
Let's see.
Object transform.
Use bitmap Tim.
So it looks like the object transform doesn't have an offset in it
anymore.
Let me double-check that.
Because where's that?
Offset P getting applied.
So it's getting applied right there.
All right, so that's a little wonky.
It's not the greatest thing in the world, but that's okay.
We can stick with that for now.
So in one project we still do want to do this offset P because that's
actually happening inside our own code, so that's fine, right?
so, it's literally this
Right.
We can, we compute the world coordinates by inverting.
The transform that we were doing on everything?
We then compute the object, coordinates by subtracting away.
The offset P, which is the thing that they had told us to apply to it
before, right?
And that's it.
So all we really need here in order to complete this in theory.
Anyway, if we've done all of our work correctly and there are a lot of
moving Parts here so maybe we made a mistake somewhere.
But in general, all we would need in theory is to know what the Z
coordinate actually.
Is that they're trying to unprojected now, why do they need to know
that right in orthographic?
They don't because the Z value is going to be ignored.
So in terms of our debug picking for just the the system that we're
looking at right now which is the
No, clicking on the UI.
It actually won't matter.
We could set the Z to anything and it wouldn't matter.
And the reason that we could set it to anything, and it wouldn't
matter is because the Matrix doesn't use the Z, right?
It's an orthographic projection.
But if we wanted to do stuff eventually and I think we do because we'd
want to restore this functionality as well.
We're no matter how you were looking at this world.
If you wanted to be able to click on individual entities, and get, you
know, hit test them right, basically like figure out what you work.
Looking on, we would still need to be able to figure out distance
based stuff, right?
We would need to know like, oh, if I'm clicking here, I need to have
some way of inverting like a distance as well, right in the
perspective sense.
So we need a way of being able to pass some Z value down as well or at
least get something back, which allows us to work with that Z, if that
makes sense.
So, we need to do something here and presumably.
if the person doesn't want to,
You know, the person wants to be able to specify something that is in
something.
They understand, they don't want to specify clip coordinates because
they have no idea what that means.
Right.
When they say unprojected they're going to be thinking o if you want a
z-value.
I've got I'm looking at the screen.
I've got a point on the screen.
I just want to pass a world space distance.
That's how far away from the
Camera.
I'm imagining that point to be or whatever, right?
They want something in that space.
They don't want something in clip space, which is negative 1 to 1 and
they don't know what that is, right?
The person calling this function is not going to have any idea what
that value should be.
So we need a like Z distance here and it's, you know, that's world, z
world distance or something like this, right?
So what we need to do first before we do, the unprojected is turned
that world distance Z into an actual clip space z value based on the
current cameras location, right?
And fortunately for us we do have a fairly easy way of doing that.
What we could do is say well okay.
If you're talking about a world distance from the camera,
I could construct a vector that's just our like probe point, right?
Which is going to be the world distance Z.
At the center of the screen I could then transform that out, right?
I could do.
Transform that value out.
So it gets you know, moved forward.
So it gets transformed into whatever it should get transformed into
right.
And then I would know what the clip Z coordinate should actually be
And again this is going to get divided though.
By, you know, if I take a look at that, that value, I do need to know
what the W component actually is here.
And so, if you take a look in our math routines,
Can we do an M4 by 4?
We definitely did right here so you can see when we do multiplication
to your we do an M4 by for multiplication, we actually do that.
That multiplication does not involve the Z coordinate.
We just I mean doesn't it doesn't return to us what the W coordinate
would have been?
It doesn't even compute it right?
But we actually do want that to be the case.
So we actually do want a transform here.
Right?
We want to transform that does all of those.
And what we could do is we could say, well, let's we could extend this
to take a V4, right?
And if we send it to take a V4, then we would just be able to do a V4
P.
Let's go ahead and put that in there, right?
And we know exactly what this would because it's pretty Road, right?
yeah, so then when we do an operator 3, if we have
Three, that's returns of e3.
Like, in this case here, what we can do is just do a V for that
extends, the p and and then takes the XYZ of the result, right?
And that works.
That is true.
There we go, right?
So you know, continuing on when we take a look at what happens here,
right?
So when what we want to do is make this actually be a probe, see that
actually is a full view for when we get the V4 back.
We would just do F32, you know,
Clip Z we can just create that Cliff, Secord it now by doing exact
would open.
Jill would have done it would have done this transform and then it
would have divided by the W coordinate, right?
So whatever probe zzz, Z coordinate was it would get / probes, he's W
coordinate and that would be the clip.
See that clip?
See is then we could pass directly in here and say Here's what the
clip coordinate.
Here's what the Z coordinate is at this point on the screen as far as
it being that far away from the camera, it does the inversion and then
we're done.
Right now we do have a situation here.
Let's see.
So yeah.
We do have a situation here where we're going to have to actually make
the operator for that but that's pretty easy, right?
It's just extending what we already had to not do any of that dance,
right?
And then everything else is fine.
Alright, so now we're passing these coordinates, we need to think
about something a little bit different here.
You can see that we were fussing with the trim, the distance from
camera nonsense.
Here, we want to get rid of that now and actually use this directly
because now our stuff is all supporting it properly so we can just
pass that world distance.
Z, I'm going to call that world distance from cameras e, just to be
really explicit about it.
We go.
And now we're getting a lot closer to a nice fun project called,
right?
So debug pick entity is going to have to get a lot more interesting in
the future.
I'm going to
I'm going to talk about that in a second, although I don't know that
we're going to do anything in particular with it.
There we go.
So now, yeah.
Now, we're probably still pretty buggy here because I doubt that that
pic is going to work.
First time out or anything, but
We should be able to now.
Start working through this a little bit more specifically, right?
We should be able to get.
Oh, that's pretty interesting.
Are these is that going through a nun?
Project--, I'm not sure what that's why that's doing, what that's
doing, but it's pretty interesting, whatever it is.
Anyway, now we have the entire pipeline set up properly to do the
unprotect, but now we actually have to make sure that that all that
code is working as it should be.
And then I haven't made any mistakes in it which of course is pretty
easy to do with that many moving Parts.
Thankfully, we did check the inverses.
So we know that those inverses are working properly and we could do
one further, check on the inverses, which we should.
Because again, all that math, it's easy to get something wrong in
there.
Another way that we can check that inverse is we never checked the
inventory.
Of the Composites, but we could write.
So you can see here.
We've got this composite.
so, if I want to take a look in there,
what I could do is say here's the eye.
Make sure the combination of these is also correct, right?
So, let me just check that one real quickly before we get down to the
other nitty-gritty of the debugging.
There we go.
Oops, there we go.
So there's that Matrix and again, you can see nice diagonal ones.
They're still quite good, right?
Again, as you get more and more terms in there, you get further and
further away from perfect.
But these are all still very tiny values compared to 1, so which is
what we're looking for on the diagonal so that that looks quite good
to me.
That's still looks nice and inverse dish.
So that all seems pretty good.
I'm pretty happy with that.
So let's take a look at that unprojected now.
Real quickly.
We might not have time to finish that today.
Because we're almost out of time, but let's just take a look at the.
Well, I guess I can just do this.
I don't really want to be doing this for every entity here.
Why can we just can we skip a bit here, folks?
Let's go ahead and skip over simulate to here.
And now can you show me a eject?
There we go.
So here is where I want to be.
There.
Now, I
Here, anytime I want.
All right, so let's step into the sun project-- here.
Here we go.
And so this unprojected again, I don't know that.
We really we're not really accounting for the object transform scale
in here either.
So this this actually needs to get a little bit fancier potentially as
well, but we can ignore that for now.
So here in our own project here we've got our probe Z value coming
through and we're going to do that computation for what the clip C
value is the clip C value is zero which is exactly what we would
expect.
Because again Z is not used
Anyway here.
So let's take a look at what our clip Space X Y, comes out to be
groups.
Okay, and so our clip coordinates again, look totally reasonable
because they have to be negative 1 to 1.
So that's, you know, at least reasonable what I would like to do,
though, if I can miss, if I can.
Yeah.
Okay.
So if I have the
Breakpoint bear.
You know what?
I think I'm going to do.
I'm going to leave that break point there because I want to transform
some coordinates where I know what they should be because it's going
to be hard to look at these numbers going through if I don't have any
idea.
What if it's just like, okay, it's within bounds but is it really,
right?
So what I'm going to do is I'm going to stuff the mouse here to what I
think should be something that's in bounds, right?
So I'm going to say that the mousex.
Has to be 0, and the mouse y has to be 1079, right?
So, that's the upper left corner of the screen.
And so this way, I can verify that the transform is doing what I think
it should do.
Otherwise it would be pretty tough, right?
So, here we go.
Let's see what the clip space values.
End up being
So, I can already tell that that's wrong, right.
You know, I haven't even gotten to the complicated part and that's not
right because these were supposed to be values that would have undone
the screen dim stuff, right?
And they did not do that at all.
Right?
So that's just wrong.
So we're off to a good start in a debugging sense, not off to a good
start into programming sense.
And so, let's go ahead and fix that.
So when we take a look here, what happens?
oh,
Because we've already divided by point 5, for some reason, there was
already a divided by 0.5 in there, which means we're dividing by 0.5
twice, which doesn't make that's wrong to begin with.
And then also it's probably wrong a second time.
There we go.
So, I don't know.
Oh wait, no no, no.
That's, that's fine.
So, this is the screen center screen dim that's actually fine.
So, this is just taking it and subtracting the screen center,
nevermind, I panic there for no reason.
Then we're trying to do here is normalize these.
So it's negative 1 to 1, so dividing by the screen dim.
So this was yet, this was actually another
Brain fart there, right?
It's if we divided by the screen dim, it would actually be half of
what it should be, right?
That's what we would have expected.
Because I must that up, right?
If you take a look at what happens here, we're saying that we've got
this full span here, which is the width, we've turned it into half of
that.
So we want to divide by half of the width.
So somehow I, yeah, we want to do X over with the over to and somehow
I turned that into a .5.
I even said that, I remember, I said the two comes up to the top.
It should be a times B.
Right?
I mean that I don't know what I was thinking there.
What was I thinking?
Bad, bad.
Bad math morning.
I'd like Bab.
Bab math morning.
All right.
Anyway.
So that was just really impressively bad on my part, but that's just
how it goes sometimes.
So after I compute this now, we've got clip coordinates.
That actually look correct, which is nice.
Now, we can take a look at what the world transform is there.
Oh you know what though?
We also don't have our normalization here, so we're missing one more
step in here, right?
We also don't do the / Z part of this of this equation.
Which is also going to be wrong.
That's not going to be a problem in this case.
But only because this happens to be orthographic, so we can ignore it
for a second, but otherwise, it happens to be wrong.
But anyway, so let's see what the world P ends up being here.
-1.6 -1.0, that still looks a little wrong because in theory,
in theory, the coordinates coming in here yet are the coordinates
coming in here are supposed to be
02 1920, right?
We're supposed to or rather - 962 960, right?
So it looks like, we're still getting an error there if I'm not very
much mistaken.
Because yeah, those that just looks
That inverse looks totally wrong for.
Oh, that's because I'm looking at the wrong one.
All right.
Never mind.
We're actually.
Okay, I need to step to hear first.
There we go.
So that looks like the correct coordinates.
Now, I panicked again there for a second.
Let's see.
There we go.
So now we're getting a little bit better, although, I still don't
know, because we're not actually passing the mouse coordinates yet.
Let's take a look.
There we go.
All right, so now that's working properly again.
Although it looks like our clipping is not.
So we do have one more bug there.
Looks like our Clipper our clip rectangles are messed up as well,
right?
You can see, look at what's happening there with those weird.
Yeah, so our clip rectangles are messed up again.
Or messed up for the first time in this situation.
So you can see there's some weird.
There's just some weird stuff going on here.
So it's almost there, but it's not there yet and we also have to work
on the Z.
You can see that are the Z is inverted.
That's why they're it's black text with white instead of white text
with black.
But we're pretty close now.
All right.
Okay, so that's getting closer.
I'm going to go ahead and go to The To Do List here.
This is what's happening at the moment.
so, that worked
We did a lot of stuff here.
So really we're just on this.
And in order to get this stuff working, we need to do handled / Z in
done project.
Fixed clip.
Rectangles for debug you, I and fix Z settings for you.
You are.
So we're pretty good here.
We're making a lot of progress that wasn't a very long time.
If you think about how many hours we've actually spent on, it wasn't
very long to do a complete transform of all of our code from 2D
sorting based to full 3d pipeline.
So, that's pretty good.
I'm pretty happy with that.
I'm going to go ahead and do Q&A here.
Because now we're pretty much everything is re-enabled almost.
We got probably one more weekend maybe of stuff to go through.
Unless we had any real big snags, but not that much.
and I guess this is nicer because
I don't know that this
but we are to solve this, but we'll go in and take that.
Mabel.
Oh am I right?
In thinking that today's work has had the cool and not immediately
expected side.
Effect of beginning to level up the debug camera in terms of mouse
picking or of entities or did the diva camera have that before.
Anyway so the debug camera may not have had that before.
I don't remember.
That's a good question the before picking amenities was only done in
2D and now we would have to do it in 3D but that's fine.
Right.
So I guess what I would say is it would definitely be leveling up to
the fact that it could do rotated picking of entities at some point if
we choose to re-enable that but right now we're not doing it because
in order to do to 3D picking it 3D picking of entities, what you have
to do, right?
Is if you imagine you're looking out at the world and there's entities
out there, you need to create a ray and then you need to do a ray
intersection test.
To see what you hit when you go out in that direction, right?
And so it's a very it's a more complicated thing.
Very different from what we were doing with the 2D case.
Do you plan to keep the assert in opengl debug call back my driver is
sending a lot of debug information that fires the assert.
So yeah, we don't have, we can remove that for you if that helps the
Is basically that the opengl debug call back can send lots of just
informative messages to you, right?
And that's one of the reasons that they have those things like first
severity and all that stuff so we can turn that off.
We could add something that checks which messages were getting and
things like that.
But yeah, we don't need that at the moment, so that's fine.
We can leave it there.
And the other thing we could do is we could say, also
When we have that procedure we get a severity value and we could just
check to make sure that we're only going to assert on things that are
actually relatively severe, right?
So for example, I could I could go to Doc's out you yell
And just take a look at this here.
So that severity value here, know if it's documented.
Curtis.
She'll debug severity.
Low medium or high.
Right?
And so what we could do is is try to take a look at that.
I don't know you know I'll leave it if they're it out and just put a
like to do Casey should this always assert on severity medium?
Hi messages, perhaps, and maybe what you could do is, is if you could
check Kim and see what the severity is, that's coming in, when you're
getting those calls to debug call back, what do they tend to be low
medium high or notification?
And maybe we could just filter those out that way, we could still have
the assert trigger on anything.
That's an actual error because it would be nice, right?
Lucid Frost.
Why do you think it is not popular to do X forward, coordinate systems
Tron?
Blow was talking about it yesterday and it seems like a good idea at
least in terms of rotations.
So I guess the first thing I would say is I'm not sure why it would
matter what axis was forward.
Is there some reason, what's the benefit of having XB forward as
opposed to anything else?
Being.
I guess I don't understand why it would matter.
Mansfield oyu Square length.
How does it compare to length squared probably just because I'm was
being dumb.
Length squared is probably better actually
So, if you take a look at what I was doing here, squaring the length
is this is just a waste of time because it means you're squaring a
square root.
So if I just do this it's a faster way to do it anyway.
Right.
Because the reason for that is when I compute the length squared, I
don't have to do the square root right by Computing.
The length I was having to do another square root which I then
squared, which is just a waste of time.
It's just a waste of operation, right?
So doing the length squared directly is actually better in the case of
vectors, it's just better.
So no that was that was just me being dumb there, I wasn't doing that
because there was some smarter
Because there was something smart behind it.
That, that is actually what you would want to do.
Let me just double-check that in break anything.
Obviously, for I check that in, but yeah.
Where were we?
120, will you consider a faster matrix multiplication algorithm other
than inner product?
No, so we don't do very many multi Matrix multiplications, so we don't
need to do anything, particularly clever.
We hardly do the Matrix like the number of times we call that function
is very low in a non debug setting anyway.
And even if we weren't it, really just isn't going to be a dominated
part of the Computing time.
Most of the, you know, Vector math that's being done, is being done on
the GPU.
When it's doing the vertex transforms, not not on our side.
Jeff G Melton.
Is there a road map for what you'll be working on over the coming
months?
Know, we pretty much just work on, whatever seems reasonable to work
on next as we go.
Mansfield the probes you think when a bit too quick for me I didn't
fully understand the role of world distance from cameras e.
And how are you going to generate it?
Are you going to talk more about that next time?
Yeah, I can.
About that really quickly.
Now, it's not that complicated actually.
So when we're talking about this picking procedure, right?
I'm going to look at the sot this view from the side.
So here's the eyeball.
And here's the world, right?
So we've got stuff out in the world.
So when you want to do and one of these sort of like, inverse things
where you're talking about, let's take a point on the screen and turn
it into a world space coordinate.
Well, the problem is, you have to pick where in the world you imagined
it to be because in a perspective transform, if I said that this point
on the screen here, I could be talking about any number of points in
the world because a point on the screen defines a re-write.
It
To find an entire line of points going out because there's all those
points map to the same point in screen space, right?
So I need to know when you're asking for a world location.
I need to know what you actually mean and so you need to give it
something here to disambiguate.
So what's a pretty useful way to do that is just say, okay, tell me
the screen location and how far away from the camera.
You think the you want to talk about in terms of where the screen
essentially was placed what this allows you to do is say like okay,
you know, let's say that I'm looking
At a point that's 10 meters away, right?
And I want to like imagine that I was drawing on this plate, that's
ten meters away.
Where would it be in screen space?
That's all this is doing, right?
So it's allowing you to specify in a distance from the camera.
That's in World space units, but in order to do that we first have to
transform that into clip space.
So I know what the clip coordinate actually is.
Since you are only doing quads, would it be possible to upload a
constant index buffer once with the maximum number of vertices and
then never touch it again?
Yes, it would.
However, I think that also would still be less efficient than then
using the using a geometry Shader.
Now it could be possible that we want to run on platforms and somehow
don't have geometry shaders, maybe and in that if that's the case,
then maybe it would be better to do something like uploading next
buffer or just passed down an actual index.
Buffer just actually build it, but all of those things will work, I
believe.
Yeah.
Possible, that square link can result in a zero and blow up.
No, because this again, remember, is inverting the camera transform.
And we will never be setting a chance for camera transform with an x y
z Vector, length of 0.
If we did, we wouldn't see anything on the screen, right?
Because the in order to see anything on the screen, those vectors all
have to be of a length.
That's not zero.
So, we know a priori that that can't be true.
Unless we have a really bad bug somewhere else, in which case it's
that bug, we would want to fix and not the fact that we divide by the
length squared.
Kim says he gets open till messages with severity.
Debug severity, notification low, and debug severity.
I'm sorry, debug certification and ebooks.
Pretty medium.
What are the messages you get with?
Debug severity, medium.
Are they things?
We can fix.
Because I feel like we shouldn't maybe be getting debug severity,
medium ratchet freak.
Even a simple pass through geometry Shader is a decent perf hit
Really.
Why wouldn't have expected that but interesting?
Tag.
Sorry.
Didn't see the whole stream.
But why no, 60 frames per second with the move to core GL?
Because that's actually not where the time is being spent at the
moment.
It's actually in this other function, that's unrelated, but two
things.
First of all, if we build with
the full answer is basically just that it spent in a bunch of other
things that we're doing like our debug tracking and stuff like that.
If I turn on optimizations for starters then I think we are 60 frames
a second.
Yeah so with optimizations on we are already 60 frames a second but
even with optimization is off, it's not actually in the drawing at all
with optimizations off.
It's actually just too because we don't have an accelerated.
We still have an N squared, entity Point, checking thing and now
there's
Stuff in the world that that's not at all acceptable.
If we fixed that, we would not have a problem.
Also, our debug stuff takes a ton of time if we changed that stuff.
We would also be 60 feet per second.
Even debug I believe, however,
Of course, we can't actually see that it's 60 frames a second.
Here we would not be able to 0
This is interesting.
Ah, that's a good point.
So we have to make sure that enabling that debug callback only
happens.
I don't know if you saw that, we don't specify the compatibility, we
don't specify the debug bit in a non debug setting.
So we actually don't want to call this.
I believe that's in.
How many internal?
So, I believe this is also 60 frames a second even without any
optimizations on because we just turned off all like, the debug
tracking and junk like that, which takes a bunch of frame time for no
reason.
We can't see it.
Obviously, because incomplete release mode.
You don't get any of the additional counter stuff.
Probably want to make a frame rate counter.
We can view even in fully release mode for obvious reasons.
But so, yeah, so the answer is the drawing.
The drawing is probably hardly takes any time at all at the moment
when we get our profile stuff back will be would be able to see that
better.
But really, the it has nothing to do with with the drawing at all.
The drawing is fine.
It's just other crufty parts of the code that we have at the moment
that make that not happen.
Like I said, it would be nice to be able to see this, but we have to
re-enable this first in order to do so.
So, at the moment, we won't be able to view that till we finish.
Bring the clip stuff working there and then we'll be good to go and we
can actually see what's taking the time.
Kim, Jorgensen medium, recompiling fragment Shader for program 3.
That's an interesting thing to call a severity medium, but okay.
Hmm.
So I guess the only thing we could probably safely do in there is
severity.
Hi, I guess.
Does that sound right?
So like, you know, maybe we could do something, like if severity
equals GL,
And I would have to grab this.
So, I can put these guys in here.
And we'll just say, if it's high, go for it.
Oops.
Maybe let's say.
Live like that.
All right, I think we're about done for the day we're out of time.
Anyway so I'm gonna go ahead and close it down.
All right, thank you, everyone for joining me for another episode of
handmade hero.
It's been a pleasure coding with you.
As always, if you would like to follow along at home, you can always
pre-order the game at handmade hero dot org and it comes with a source
code so you can play around with it.
We also have a forum site, you can go to to ask questions a patreon
page and go to.
If you want support the video series, a schedule bot, the tweets, the
schedule at you, and episode guide, so you can catch up on old
episodes.
I am pretty happy with the way, the 3D stuff all turned out.
It seems pretty good so far and next weekend I guess we've
Got two things we need to try and do.
I don't know if we'll have time to do all of them but one of them is
to do the unprotect for perspective as well and clean up some of the
debug UI clipping stuff.
So we need to do those two things but then we need to move on to some
things are a little more wild which is like doing the Z distance based
fog and some stuff like that, that should be kind of fun to do as
well.
So we want to do that stuff next weekend and then hopefully I think
that's all the 3D stuff.
We need to do at the moment and we can move on to other parts of our
to-do list, may be doing, I guess, starting to do some World
Generation or so stuff like that.
And we'll have to throw in new artwork as well.
Which will be kind of a pretty big overhaul for us because we're going
to have to start actually thinking about how entities are built up and
you know, different pieces of them and that sort of thing for real.
So that'll be a big change here.
So we've got some pretty serious work ahead of us, but it should all
be
a fun work because it's all stuff.
That's I guess.
We'll make the game look more like the final game, right?
Because now we'll have like artwork that looks reasonable and stuff
like that.
Which should be a pretty big Improvement.
Anyway, hopefully I'll see you all back here next weekend for that
until then have a good programming week and I will see you on the
internet.
Everyone.
Take it easy, everybody.