So I'm going to go ahead and hit that recording flip button there and
we should be good to go.
Welcome to handmade hero.
It is a sleepy Friday morning here.
The fact that I am always sick apparently now, which is a late motif,
of course means that I never get any sleep, which is awesome.
So I'm kind of a little blurry at this point a little bleary-eyed.
But I think it should not stop us from doing what we need to do today,
which is just some like last odds and ends in the win32 stuff.
For we do next week will basically be clean up and transition over
into game code is what I'm expecting.
So I'm not sure exactly what we're going to do today.
Besides the file I/O, we're going to have to kind of play it by ear.
I need least need to show you a little file IO stuff.
But other than that, we're going to have to kind of decide, maybe,
probably Midway through the stream.
Exact, what we're going to do.
So, welcome to handmade hero.
We are on day 15.
It is the third.
The end of the third week of handmade hero coding, and we are closing
in on having our complete platform.
Stuff running, where we basically have our game code isolated in a
platform, independent layer, and we've got our win32 implementation of
the platform layer.
And so that we're all set up to do porting in the future.
And that sort of stuff.
If you are following along, if you're one of the folks who pre-ordered
the game and are following along with the source code at home.
You will want to unzip day, 14 source.
That is what we are starting here obviously on day 15, so let's jump
into that and this and talk about file IO a little bit.
Before I go ahead and implement it.
It's actually going to be pretty basic the thing that we're going to
do very straightforward, not a lot to talk about but I just want to
give you the sort of the the high level overview.
So basically in games file file IO typically breaks down into two
distinct categories.
One is loading.
What is this?
What are essentially read?
Only assets from something.
Basically.
This is your music, your sound.
Your art artwork, whatever happens to be if it's 3D 3D models and
textures if it's 2D than the Sprite bitmaps and so on basically what
you're talking about when you're talking about that primary I/O
functions, you're talking about getting stuff off of the drive and
into memory where the game can use it and you're never touching these
files.
Other than that read.
So it's essentially read only that, you're never writing to them.
You're never putting stuff out to the disk.
You're only pulling off of
the disc.
And by disc, this can mean a number of things.
Sometimes it can mean the network potentially.
Sometimes it can mean an optical drive, but in our case and most often
nowadays, it tends to mean a hard drive of some kind or an SSD drive.
So something that's the main Drive of the machine or a secondary, but
still primary style drive.
Basically something that stores all of the users games.
And it's got all the assets on there.
So, that's class one.
Glass to is saving basically the state of the game.
And so this is where the game actually reads and writes.
Basically, what's going to happen is there's the configuration for the
game.
So if your game allows you to run say in windowed and full-screen
mode, that would be one example of something that would need to get
saved their stuff.
Like, if you have separate settings for how loud, the sound versus the
music is things like this.
So there's stuff that's the configuration of the game and then there's
stuff.
If that's like the state of the of the game in progress at the players
playing.
So like a save game file or if there's unlocks things that they've
unlocked so far, that sort of stuff that forms sort of a secondary
class and that class is things that were basically writing to as well
as reading from.
So it's stuff that the game creates along the way and then pulls from
later sort of to figure out what the state was.
The last time the game was run because obviously the game runs
multiple.
Times.
And there's no way to persist things across those runs.
If we want to, without writing them to disk first and then pulling
them back in.
So we basically, when we're talking about a game, I oh we're basically
talking about two separate classes of IO.
Usually one that's for reading and writing files and one that's for
just reading them.
And they also tend to have different sort of criteria for Success.
The sort of saved game things.
Typically are relatively tiny.
They can typically would be loaded in a flat call.
That doesn't really have to be streamed or anything like this.
Whereas, with the with the read-only stuff where you're pulling in
assets, typically games nowadays, like to stream that stuff in the
background so that the user isn't sitting on loading screens any
longer than they have to did.
You try to overlap that work, as much as possible with other things?
Keep the game running.
So, basically, with the with the assets, you're reading a ton of
It typically gigabytes worth of data potentially and it's not
something that's instantaneous anymore.
It's not something that can be ignored as a performance criteria,
because it's happening all the time.
And it's, it's operating on a large scale.
And so typically, if you really want a well performing game that, that
other class, the read-only class of IO that we're pulling in the
assets that has to be a lot more hardcore Engineering in there.
Then just the reading, right?
So I want you to understand those two two things separately.
Now, we don't want to at this point.
Try to address the specifics of these things.
Just yet.
We kind of have to crawl before we can walk here because if I start it
on two or three weeks of, let's design a very efficient asset
streaming system with multi-threading.
We would be putting the cart massively before the horse because we
haven't even gotten a game playable yet.
So it'd be really premature to kind of go in.
And say, all right.
Let's let's focus on the asset loading system, but
Obviously, we also can't get our game running with real Sprites or
anything unless we can load stuff.
So, basically, our job today is to just put in a minimal set of file
I/O functions that we can use to get the game running so that we can
get it to a point where we know exactly what we need.
At least from the asset streaming system.
Hopefully, from both the asset streaming system and the save load
system, get it to a point where we can see exactly what we need.
And what would be optimal API wise, then we can write that API and
then spend a week or two.
Implementing the actual win32 subsystem that will properly service
that in an optimal way.
So that's our goal for today, basically.
So thankfully, that's pretty simple.
We don't have to deal with all the complexity that we would have to
deal with in a real system because we're just trying to get the basics
working.
So basically what we're going to do here is we're going to I'm going
to Quick say roughly how file layers are used kind of used to be done
and then how they're typically done today.
Because how they're done today is a lot better than how they
Are done.
So I just want to show you real quickly, how that used to work.
So in the old days, basically, what would happen is you had something
that was basically a file file handle.
So typically what you would do is let's say what I wanted to do is at
start up here.
When we're initializing our game.
I wanted to load a bitmap and I kind of know where that bitmap is.
Let's say, you know, normally we wouldn't know where the bitmap is
we'd have.
Some kind of asset thing that finds assets or whatever but let's say I
just know where it is.
So I've got a file name here, and I know that I'm going to load
something like backdrop or are you know what let's just make it test
dot BMP or something.
So I'm going to try and load this file.
Basically what happens here is when I'm going to load the file.
I would say something like file handle, file equals open file, right?
And I would pass it that file name and then it would, it would give me
Back a handle to the file and then I would then from there, do things
like read from the file.
How many bytes I wanted.
Let's say I wanted to read 128 bytes from the file.
I would say that and I would give it a buffer.
So I would do something like this.
I would say here's a buffer of 128 bytes, right?
And then I would read from that buffer basically like this.
So maybe I'll say however, big the buffer is and the buffer size and
this would typically be ifft.
So I would say if
The read succeeded then, you know, I can use that thing use buffer.
If it didn't then I have an error, right?
This is an air-conditioned but couldn't read from the file now at 0
and of course at the end of this we would also have to clean up that
file handle.
Right?
So basically that is that is basically how this works.
Now.
There's a lot of things not to like about this.
So first of all, the way that it works is,
You can imagine if I was going to do this again.
If I needed to read another thing out of this, right?
Maybe I got to read another 128 bytes, or maybe I got some other thing
in here but for to something like that and so I'm going to read 256
bytes.
Assuming I read the 128 bytes, you end up with code that looks a lot
like this, right?
And there's definitely things you can do to minimize the degree of if
Enos going on.
If you were to do it this way, but the thing that I want to point out
here is this is basically
We a streaming API.
So what it assumes is that we're opening the file in a method where
we're going to pull things from it incrementally.
And we expect the underlining underlying file system to basically
maintain sort of a location in the file.
And when we asked for bits of IO, it's pulling it from wherever that
is, right, and we're pulling and pulling and pulling.
And we're assuming that basically any of those pulls could fail, like
Anytime we do a read, it could fail.
And that's, that's not a, that's not a overly cautious, assumption.
Because if you think about it, at any time, the hard drive could fail
the file could get locked, the file could get deleted.
The user, could could flat-out pull the drive out.
If it's a USB drive, they could just yank it out of the machine.
So realistically it is true that any read can just fail.
That's just flat-out.
Out the case.
Same thing on consoles is that DVD drive gets ejected.
Well, that's the last time you're going to read from that DVD until
the user Danes, to put it back in the drive again.
So it is a realistic concern that the reads can always fail.
So basically what we've got here.
Is we've got a something that is doing a bunch of work.
We don't care about to support that streaming thing.
Basically, we're introducing a bunch of failure cases.
Every read is a new failure case that we theoretically have to handle
or have some strategy for handling in a more Global sense.
Right?
So that has to happen.
We also have the problem of the the threading safety and we haven't
talked about multi-threading it all.
So I'm just going to mention this and not going to detail.
You'll understand it more.
If you don't know about that.
Later on, these file handles are very stateful.
They store a location where you're reading in the file.
So if two different people wanted to use the same file, they need
multiple of these handles because each one is writing two different
position.
So basically every thread needs its own file handle to sort of talk
about where in the file.
They thought they were reading all sorts of things like this are bad
and then two is if that's not enough, keeping.
Everything on there.
The final thing that's awful about this.
Is it, is it totally synchronous, like this, read the code that
executes after the read can't start.
QT because it's going to start touching this buffer.
The code that's after the recant start executing until the Reed has
completed.
And definitely it's true that the hard drive is the slowest piece of
memory in your system.
Even if it's an SSD drive.
It is much slower than the CPU is executing much lower than main
memory.
And so basically what we're talking about right here is stalling the
whole program at this point where the read happens.
And so especially if we're going to do two reads in a row and stuff
like that.
It's just awful.
Because it means we're like waiting and then waiting again, when we
could have just said, hey we need to do both these reads, Q those up.
Let me know when you're done with them, and then we'll process them.
Right.
So basically, there's nothing good about streaming base file, I/O for
our purposes.
There are perhaps circumstances where you really do need to talk about
things as if they are streams worse, where streams make more sense.
But in our for our purposes, they make no sense whatsoever, especially
because we are always going to be.
Reading stuff that we know how big it is, like, basically, we're never
going to be in situations where we're reading from an 8 GB stream and
we just want to pull pieces off of it, which is a case where a
streaming might make some more sense.
If we have an 8 gigabyte file.
We know how it's subdivided up and we're going to jump into it and
grab a whole, a set of the time.
We just want to do those whole asset reads and just have the operating
system tell us when they're done with them.
So we basically don't want anything to do with this even in our test
layer.
Even for just the basic stuff that we Implement.
Now, we want to set ourselves up for success by at least starting to
go.
All right, let's make a file API, even for the debug for are, you
know, sort of training wheels, purposes here, to get things going.
Basically, even for that.
We don't want to do things this way.
What we would much rather do is basically just say for our debug
purposes.
We're just going to always read files or chunks of files at once in.
In a block we're basically going to tell it where we want to read and
how much we want to read and we're going to assume that we do all of
our reads to like all of that read is together and succeeds or fails.
So if you're loading a bitmap file, we're going to load the whole file
at once and it's just going to come back to us as one big chunk.
Right?
And basically what we're going to do is we're going to use that for
the entire time that we don't have a giant packed asset file.
And then when we move to having a pact asset file of some kind, we're
going to use.
More like a streaming system where we're going to be multi-threaded at
that point and then we'll start talking about always having basically
that one file open and doing sub reads out of it, but we're never
going to do the streaming thing.
The streaming thing is just not going to be the case.
The only time we would do anything with streaming stored of IO will be
if we write a log file to disk for debugging purposes or something.
That's that's it and we're not going to do that right now.
Anyway, so what we want to do is something that looks more like, you
know,
This bitmap memory equals read entire file and we pass the file name.
So it looks more like that and then free file memory, something like
this bitmap memory.
And so basically what we're going to treat it as is we're going to
treat it as we're going to treat it almost like a memory allocation.
We're going to say we're going to basically allocate this file in some
sense and it's just going to appear in memory and
You'll notice I even alluded to this in the previous stream.
Basically, this is the one thing that we're going to allow to be
around trip.
You remember I was talking about round tripping and trying to minimize
that.
So, the one thing that we're kind of going to allow to be a round trip
is going to be file IO, but mostly only for this for this training
wheels version because in the real version were even not, we're really
not going to even allow round-tripping in the real version in the
fullest in the full concept of the word round tripping.
What we're actually going to do in the real version is we're going to
write to a queue that will get processed asynchronously.
So this is the most round-tripping thing.
We will probably see in the entire layer and it's only going to be.
It's not ever meant to actually run on the user's machine.
Probably, that'd be my guest.
So we're never really going to ship code.
Like this in the final version.
But basically this is how we're going to do it.
We're basically just going to do a thing that says, please read this
entire file.
Now, I could do this in one of two ways.
There's two totally valid ways.
I could decide to do this.
One would be to get the size of the file first, right?
And so, you could imagine something like this file size equals.
Get file size of the file name, right?
Then I would use that game memory to basically say, the bitmap memory
is going.
Be, you know, getting it memory or Reserve memory, write for, for the
file size.
And that would that would do this.
So, this would sub allocate out of that chunk of game memory that we
have, then we would go ahead and say, ok, then read entire file into
memory.
And we would give it the file name and we would give it the memory
pointer, right the bitmap memory like this.
Does that make some sense?
So we basically say, okay, get that file size read
Get get enough memory to hold it and then put it in there.
That is how we would write it if this were going to be a permanent
API.
Probably because I would want the game.
I wouldn't want the the operating system to be doing more memory work
than it has to probably.
I wouldn't necessarily say that has to be that way.
We still even if we were shipping it we could let the operating system
allocate it.
The reasons for that is we could use file mapping or things like that.
Possibly happen.
And also it's already something that can fail.
We know that a read can fail.
All the Reed can fail.
So having the operating system, allocate memory and read.
Doesn't introduce a new failure point.
But like I said, I do like knowing exactly how much memory the game
needs.
And so, having files be allocated in the platform layer.
Dynamically doesn't wouldn't feel great to me.
So if we were actually doing this API for real, we might consider
something like this.
Since we're only doing this in a debug sense.
This is basically, this is basically what what we're going to do.
So we're just going to let it do the whole allocation.
Then we're going to release it later.
Does that make sense?
Hopefully, that makes some sense.
So basically come to me, this will return a null pointer of return 0.
If it couldn't read the file, or couldn't allocate the memory, and if
not, then we assume we got the whole read and it worked and then we
can process it and off we go.
So that's basically that's basically what we're talking about here.
Hopefully that makes a fair bit of sense and isn't too complicated.
So that's that's basically all we want.
And what I'm going to do here is this is a platform call.
Obviously, we're calling into the platform.
At form here.
So I'm going to prefix it with platform and I also want to sort of
make some kind of note that this is, is really not for runtime use.
So I'm going to call this debug.
I'm just going to put a flat out debug in front of it so that we kind
of know that if we were to search through the code for this, we would
kind of see it light up like a Christmas tree that this is not really
supposed to be hanging out in a shipping build.
There's other things we can do about that that are kind of interesting
for
A, we have we have this handmade internal thing and in the future,
what we might do is we might do something like this, where, if
handmade internal exists, then we Define these and if it doesn't, we
don't just to make sure that no one can actually call them.
So basically, you know, we might have something we're only if this is
the case, do these, get defined at all, you know, does that make
sense?
In fact, we could even do that now, maybe I just will.
So basically what we're talking about here is when you go to do
Your first shipping build, you got to you got to have this stuff, go
away.
Right?
Just something we could do.
We'll do it for now.
It seems totally reasonable.
So we're going to basically just say, you know, what for file I/O,
that's just the way it goes.
Now that goes in this.
Remember we set this up here, basically services that the platform
layer provides to the game.
We said they're going to be a couple of them.
Well here is our first one.
It's a debug ability to load a file and to release that file.
So basically that's what we're going to do.
We're going to say here is the file.
Name.
And we're going to say here is the memory to release and again,
there's a lot of other things.
We might can be concerned with here.
Excuse me.
Hmm.
Man, all right.
Basically, the things we might be concerned with is, do we need to
support UTF filenames, these sorts of things.
This is for debugging only.
So we know, we're always ever antsy, so we don't really need to think
about this much.
Now, I want a symmetric thing.
So in addition to reading, I would also like to be able to write.
So I would like to be able to say platform, right?
Entire file and write entire file would just be here's the file name
to write to here's the memory to, right?
And then here is the memory size, how big it actually is.
Now one thing we might do is we might want to say or we're never going
to allow writing a files that are more than 4 gigabytes which point we
would make this.
Us a Unit 32, I don't know which one I want to do there.
It's I think we may want to support writing giant.
Maybe maybe not now probably not.
So we could we could just say that that's going to be under under that
size.
So there you go.
That's basically all we're talking about here.
And so that's really pretty, pretty straightforward.
You can see if we compile everything compiles, fine.
There's not much to talk about there.
All we have to do, is we got our Linker warning says, we haven't
implemented these, but I can just
Implement these now.
So here's our file layer.
We go into win32.
Handmade dot CPP.
We're just going to drop those in there and you can notice we already
did the implements five.
I was talking about this and I already had dropped this in here as a
note.
So basically, we're going to go ahead and delete that old stub and
make this here.
Okay.
There we go.
These should be marked internal as well.
You go ahead and Mark that because basically, I said, all of our
functions are internal just to help the compiler out so that it knows
there's no external linkage or
compiling in just one file, so,
What I need to do here is straight-up call windows and say, hey
Windows, read this, entire file for me.
Nothing.
Nothing, interesting going on here.
It's going to be the most basic.
Most basic thing that there is, we're not going to get fancy at all.
So we're just going to call a function called create file and and also
one that gets the file size.
So basically, this is this is what we're going to call to open that
file.
Basically, what I'll talk about what that does in second.
Leave.
There's just a flat-out file size called.
We'll, just tell us how big a file is, nothing particularly
complicated about that.
So, there we go with that.
And, and I think that's mostly all we're going to need.
We're going to get that file size.
Then we're going to, of course, she's me have to close the file as
well, which is the close handle call.
It can close any type of handle including a file handle and then we're
going to need
One more, which is read file and that will be the way that will
actually get it in.
So there we go.
Alright, so so really, there's not a lot of mystery here.
I'll kind of explain what these things do but it's like pretty darn
boring.
So basically what happens is first we say, all right, we've got to get
a handle to a file because operating systems like handles basically
the way operating systems tend to work is
Resources that are on the operating system sides sockets, files
streams, whatever they are processes, you name it and basically they
need a way of talking about those to you the the the process that's
running and they use handles for that.
Those are typically just, you know, indexes into a table or pointers
into kernel memory.
That say, here is the thing that I'm talking about on your side.
So for a file, we basically want to say hey, here's something.
I want to read from the disk.
I'm going to give you the name of it and I
I want you to go open that and give me back a handle, so I can keep
talking about it to you and telling you what to do to it, like,
reading it and getting it sighs.
Right.
So, basically we need to pass the file name, then we need to pass a
bunch of stuff that's largely meaningless for us.
But that makes them more sense in Windows.
If you actually care about other things.
Basically what these are are like things like how we need the file to
be open to how we need to be accessed.
So if you look in here, the documentation msdn, you can see this
desired access.
Basically.
We just telling you a Windows.
What we actually
I need to do because Windows may allow multiple.
There's basically different ways of opening files, where the operating
system can determine whether multiple people can open the file the
same time.
So basically, we need to tell it.
Do we need to read or do we need to write or both?
And then we also need to tell it later in this.
This is what share mode is the next parameter.
What do we allow other processes to do?
So, we may open a file for reading and we know that we want it to not
be written to it.
At that time.
So we may say well, another process could open it for reading but
don't allow them to write to it.
Right?
Similarly, if we're writing to a file.
We may say don't let any other process read from it or right from it
because we're modifying it right now.
So it's basically, like a mutex.
It's a lock that basically says, all right, when one person have the
file open, the operating system allows them to basically say don't let
other people do stuff at this time because we will create errors by
doing that.
So what we know here is, we're just reading a file so we can just say,
generic read, right?
We're just
Going to read from the file and then the share mode.
We know that basically anyone else could read from it.
Right?
But we don't want them to delete or right to it because we're don't
want them to modify it while we're doing something while we're doing
this, with one read that we do.
We're only gonna have it locked for a very short time.
So that's fine.
So, there you go.
Now security attributes.
We don't care about.
This is basically, if we're trying to do things more about like, which
whether the file handle can be passed to a subprocess and all, there's
all sorts of other things that you might care.
About, but we don't care about those for our purposes.
We're just reading the file ourselves.
We don't have a subprocess.
We don't have anything else.
We need to worry about there.
So it doesn't matter so we can pass null for that.
Again.
I use zero instead of know, some people like to use null.
And so if you want to use, no, that would be a null for you.
Not a zero nose defined to be 0 and windows.
so when we when we're opening a file, obviously, we also have the
ability in Windows to basically say, create the file or don't create
the
Well if it didn't exist already, so basically what it kind of needs to
know is if there's already a file on the drive, what should I do with
it?
And if there isn't a file on the drive, should I make one, or should I
return an error?
All that sort of stuff?
So this is a read.
This is our read call.
We're saying we're going to read something from a file.
So what we want to do here is we want to say, okay.
I want you to always open a file that already exists.
If there isn't a file existing, I want that to be an error so that the
game knows.
It was trying to load an asset that just plain a there, right?
So that's that's it.
So flags and attributes is basically stuff.
Like, you know, when you go, I don't know, you probably have
experience with this.
If you're a programmer at all.
I'm sure that you have if you go on to your drive and your right click
on something to get properties, there's this stuff down here, read
only hidden that sort of stuff.
Basically, you could specify those things.
If you were creating the file, you can specify those things.
You can also specify a bunch of other flags that have to do with how
the Opera,
Some is going to use this file likes, weird stuff like delete on
clothes, right?
So you can have a temporary files that kind of get to cleaned up
immediately after you close them where you don't have to do it and the
operating system cut, I can do extra stuff there because it knows
there's all sorts of other stuff overlapped.
IO is like possibly how will do, I think we might use IO complete
reports, but that ignore that stuff for now.
There's there's things you can basically set that are how the file
will be read from and those might be relevant to us in the future, but
they're not right now, so,
I don't think we actually have any flags and attributes.
I can't remember.
It's been a while since I've written any file IO code in Windows.
Typically, I use my eye, you know, I have kind of stuff that I have
written a long time ago and used, but I don't think there's anything
we really care about in here.
So I think we can be 0 again and then the template file.
Again.
We also don't need any of that stuff.
So we're basically, we're basically fine with this and basically it's
not equal to invalid handle value.
That is what it will return.
So basically, we're just going to go ahead and try to open the file.
Using these flags.
I think I've got him set.
Right?
But will double check and make sure that I do then.
We'll go in here.
Once we have an open file handle, we can ask for the size.
Here's the file size now, get file size is a little Antiquated.
So we might want to call get file size, the X.
Let me show you what the why I say that we don't really need it for
our purposes, but we could just to be a little more complete.
Basically, what we've got here is.
Yeah, so you can kind of see what
Ins.
This get file size function returns A d word.
Basically, you it's just kind of its just kind of janky.
Let me see if there's a, if there's a less janky one.
Don't know if there is or not.
Yeah.
So let will use the non-genuine.
I'll tell you why.
It's janky and then we'll go from there.
So basically get file size, was written kind of in the days before
64-bit.
A file obviously can be more than 32 bits of space wide, right?
32 bits is 4 billion.
Bytes, roughly, and for, that's a forgery.
File.
Now, anyone who's ever BitTorrent in stuff knows that 4 GB is not
necessarily that large.
You could have files that are more than 4 gigabytes, large, a single
file.
So when you asked for the file size, it needs to return a 64-bit value
because a 32-bit value won't hold the size of some files on a drive.
There's nothing that says that files on a drive.
Have to be limited to four gigs anymore.
I think there used to be in the fat 32 days or something.
There's probably a limitation or something like that or in the regular
fat days are certainly was but there isn't any more certainly not an
NTFS and not on XT XT XT for.
So basically, what you end up doing is when you do a get file size,
it's got a return you to have
Of the third of the 64-bit value, the high 32 bits and the low 32
bits.
And then we would have to basically shift them up and order them
together to put back together.
The actual 64-bit value, right?
Which is not what we want.
We'd rather just have it return a 64-bit value to us.
So there's this get file size, e^x thing.
And if we look down here, we can see it was supported on Windows XP,
which is our minimum supported client.
So this is a function.
They introduced later which basically just flat-out gives us the
64-bit value, which is what we actually would prefer.
/.
So what I'm going to do instead is use get file size X, pass it that
handle that we opened and then pass it.
The address of our file size value, right?
So that, that way, we don't have to deal with that janking.
It's just makes life a little easier for us which, you know, we want,
if we can get it.
So we're going to define a large integer.
We've seen this large integer before.
I don't know, if you remember, when we're doing query performance
counter.
So that quad part is the 64-bit value that we were looking.
For.
So basically file size dot quad, part is what we're looking for tuning
and all.
We're going to do here is assuming that we got the file size.
We will go ahead and try to Virtual a lock that thing basically in
the, you know, something that's that big that will give us our memory.
So this is essentially the result that we're going to return void,
star result.
And then we are going to see if we got it.
If we got the memory, we're going to go ahead and try to read.
Into it by read file like so there we go, and assuming that worked.
There we go that in there.
Then we're going to have to handle some failure cases.
All right, and then of course at the end assuming that we were able to
open the file, we're going to have to close the file as well.
So we're going to go ahead and close this file handle.
There we go.
All right, so a couple things to talk about here and then, of course,
I'm going to return the result.
There we go.
Now, this will just be on here.
Freeing is is Trivial compared.
It's just virtual free.
I believe it was the we've never had to free memory before.
This is our first time.
People think it's just virtual free.
I don't remember what we need to pass the address, the son.
Is okay.
We're releasing it though.
So we don't actually need the size.
So it's just release.
Memory least.
I think that's it.
So we're just going to release this memory and that's, that's all
we're doing.
So that should be it address free.
Let's see.
A dress size free.
So basically, what's going to happen?
Here is we have a little bit of a janky scenario going on.
But there's not a lot we can do really.
We could memory map, the file, you know, there's, there's other things
we could do here.
I'm going to try and keep it a little simpler than that.
So basically doing it in the straightforward way, where we read it
like this.
Basically we're going to read from the file handle.
We're going to pass it.
The buffer that we allocated, right?
We're going to ask it to read the the file size that we allocated as
well.
And there's, there's some tankiness in there.
And then let's put that in there as well.
And then we're going to pass 04 that overlap parameter because that's
a that's, the overlapped parameter is a thing that basically lets us
say, oh, we want to do this read asynchronously and we're not at that
point yet.
So we're going to pass zero for that first passing the handle where to
put the stuff you read, how much we want you to read.
And then a pointer that says the result.
So basically what you can see here, excuse me is if we really wanted
to support reading large files.
We would have to actually do a loop here because the read file
function in win32 doesn't actually let us pass a 64-bit value.
It was a d word here.
So I'm assuming I'll just get a compile error.
Hopefully.
All right, I gotta do.
Our virtual Alec actually have to pass the rest of the things do it.
We go like that.
So we've got
Zero and that there we go.
So basically the problem here.
There we go.
The problem here.
Is that this guy?
This quad part is actually a 64-bit value, but read file,
unfortunately, doesn't actually take a 64-bit value.
So, if we go in here and we look, it just takes a d word.
Right?
And the problem with that is the d word is not Siz only 32 bits.
So, if the file actually were larger than 4 gigabytes.
This, this would fail, the allocation would probably succeed but the
read would just flat-out fail.
Now we don't actually care.
About right.
Reading in our debug.
We're never going to read a 4 gigabyte file into memory in one.
Go like that.
That's not something we're going to do.
So what we can do here is just assert.
This is again where the assert thing comes in which is nice.
We can just assert that that file size.
Quad part is basically less than the maximum value.
That we would get here.
Right?
So this sort of a thing basically that it's less than the maximum
32-bit value, then that you can have or up to it.
I suppose.
We could be up to it.
Exactly.
Now, one of the nice things we could do is, and this is something,
maybe we'll do next week, when we're sort of going through to dues, is
defines for maximum values because it would be nice here to be able to
do something like you, Aunt, 32 Max in that.
So people know why we're trying to test
It's that because we're basically saying is the max value and the
standard in .h, I believe or limits .h, there's there are C runtime
Library function.
Seen there are platform defines that tell us these values so we can
actually get them pretty easily as well.
So anyway, that's something but for now, we could just say assert that
the sizes less than 32 bits and then we're fine, right?
Then, and then we're totally fine.
So, after that, we could do something like this file size 32, we could
we could even make it explicit.
Doing here, right?
And and off we go.
So that is one way to do it.
Another thing we could do.
That's that's also safe and I kind of like I kind of like this a
little bit is we can define something like this where we do safe
truncate 32 or something like this like that and then we pass it in 64
value, you N64 value here.
So maybe something like this safe, truncate you N64.
And that basically
Says, all right.
I've got a you N64.
I want to, I want to truncate it to 32 bits and I want to make sure
that there's an assertion around it.
So I know.
So here is the value.
I'm just going to bake this.
What we did in there.
Right?
So I'm going to assert that, whatever the value is, is less than
whatever the maximum is, right?
Something like this.
And then I'm going to go ahead and say all right.
The result is going to be that thing.
Truncated and then we returned it.
So just a nice little inline function here that does that truncation.
Now, I can see what's going on a little cleaner.
I can say,
All right, safe, truncate that and that makes me aware that at least
always in debug mode.
I know that I would, I would get an immediate hard error.
If for some reason, the things weren't small, like, I thought so.
So, you know, I'll put that out in our in our platform independent
layer because it is platform independent, basically, in our little
utilities here, right?
That's just, that's just kind of a nice thing to have.
So I like that, I like doing stuff like that.
We're now I can just bake it out and just know.
No, now from, now on anytime, I'm going to do on those truncations.
I can feel a little more comfortable that at least they're getting it
asserted.
So, if someone starts using this code for purposes other than what I
thought, they'll immediately get that assertion and know what's going
on, why their code isn't working anymore.
So that's one thing right?
There we go.
So, okay, so we now we're okay, because we're basically saying we're
never going to read files that big, so it's fine.
So we're checking the file size and make sure that it's going to work
and it will hopefully work.
Once we get in here.
We're going to do our read file in our read.
How can fail, of course, right?
So basically, if since our read file can fail one thing before I
forget to, these are all a functions, right?
Because they take a file name.
Yeah.
So this is a create file, a for those of you who are doing Unicode at
home.
All right.
Anyway, so basically when we're doing these, when we're doing this
Reed, the Reed can fail.
If the read fails, we don't want to return the memory.
We want to free it.
It right here, right?
We want to basically say free this memory that we had immediately
because we don't want the memory left sitting around.
So that result that we did we want to free that and set it to 0.
So that it's as if we never allocated in the first place, it's the
same as an allocation failure.
Basically, if the read fails, because otherwise, if the read fails, we
would still have, we still had the memory, we'd return the memory to
the to the caller.
They would think they read the file, but it actually what they have is
garbage memory.
There's no sense in
Enforcing the the layer to figure that out on its own, right?
So we don't want to do that.
So assuming here.
This is the success case File read successfully and then we get there
we go.
Now, you might wonder why I left an empty when here I just like I like
to get further nested in success and put my errors in the else cases
and and you know, logging in there.
So, you know, maybe we'll do some logging here, right?
That's the way.
I like things to always look, that is the only reason that that looks
like.
Like that, so we could we could have logging in here for an inability
to open files and stuff like that.
Right.
Make sense.
So that's that's all that is.
Yeah, pretty straightforward.
So that's basically it.
There isn't really a lot else to it, besides that.
And, and if we were going to do a right, it's basically the exact same
stuff.
Let me compile this and make sure we're working here.
Oh, right.
The actual bytes red.
Let's see here.
D word, b, read that will tell us how many we actually read.
Now.
The interesting thing here is technically the read could read less
than how many we asked it to read.
I don't think that's actually possible in any scenario.
That isn't going to wear.
The read isn't going to fail meaning.
I don't think it can.
I don't think that it can read less.
If we know that the file is that big if someone went in and truncated
it maybe in between then it would fail.
So, you know what?
I might I might say I might go ahead and say let's handle that case as
well.
Let's so let's say here.
Let's just also say that we want file size 32 to be equal to B read.
So we're basically going to say,
Do this read.
Assuming the read return.
True check to see whether B read in file size or equal.
If they are, then considered success.
Otherwise consider it a failure because just in case we hit someone
truncated the file.
Between there and we only read part part of it out because technically
the way read file always works in things as you can, specify a larger
value than the size of the file than is left in the file.
And basically, it will just give you back.
However, much it could read.
That's just how they're usually defined and that's not an error that's
just allowed.
And so, if someone went in and truncated the file, while we in
between, when we got it Sighs, and when we read it, technically we
would hit that error case, where it would just it would, the read file
would succeed, but we would
Get back less bytes.
So we want to consider it a success only if we actually were able to
read the whole file.
So I'm just going to go ahead and say that.
Now notice we took advantage of the short circuiting here.
When we did the read file.
We're saying we're not going to do bother doing this check until after
this is done.
And so the fact that we know that this has to happen before, this is
the only reason that works.
If see could do these in any order, this code wouldn't work properly
because this could be evaluated before the read file and of course
read file, modifies B story.
B red.
So that wouldn't work but we know that c is required to execute these
in the order.
They appear on the line.
That's how the and the operator and is defined to always do.
It's the thing before it first and then the thing after it.
So we know that that's going to be okay.
So that's that's our read.
We can step into it now and see if it worked.
Of course, we know that that file that I asked for, it doesn't exist.
So what should happen if things are working properly here is it should
be an error?
So, let's go ahead in there.
What?
I actually want handmade that CP, which is not open yet, but that's
okay.
We'll just set a break point where we actually call it and then we'll
step in there.
So, all right, so we come in here and basically we're going to call
this again.
We're passing it test dot BMP.
So that's going to call create file and that should just flat-out fail
and it does.
So what we need to do here is we now need to give it a file.
That actually could be loaded something.
Actually exists.
So I'm just going to pick a random file temporarily for purposes of
testing.
Let's take a look.
What is on W Colin's?
Let's see.
Handmade.
In fact, you know what we could do?
We could just say this.
That is a c preprocessor, macro that inserts the name of the file that
got compiled.
So I could just try to load myself basically, so I come in here.
Let's see.
Let's take a look at that file name.
W, handmade code.
Handmade always good.
So let's go in there and see if we can read that.
We did the, the create file, and the file handle came back valid.
This time.
We take a look at it.
We get the file size and let's see what that file size.
Actually.
Is it?
Well, you know what?
Let's see it in decimal because that would be better.
There we go.
So we'll take a look at that file size.
It's 3091 B.
Does that square with our expectation?
Of what the file actually is on disk.
Yep, 3091 exactly.
Right?
So that worked fine.
We're going to Alec that memory will take a look at it.
Check the results that works fine.
The read file succeeded, which is what we would expect.
We close it and we come out here.
Now in theory.
We now have our quote, unquote bitmap memory.
Of course, it's not really bitmap, but we could take a look at that
memory if we wanted to.
To write we can see what's in there and what we would expect to see is
the contents of the file, right?
Because that's what we did.
We told it to load it off the disk.
So here's that address.
I'm going to paste that address in here.
There we go.
And hey lo and behold there it is.
There's our file looks exactly like it looks.
So there you go.
So that all worked fine.
Then, we're going to go ahead and free it.
Going here.
The virtual free gets rid of it, which is exactly what we wanted.
You can see it Vapes.
The least the member back to the OS.
So we can't read anymore.
Exactly what we wanted.
So that's all good.
And we are pretty much done.
That.
Is that is file IO, very exciting.
Now again, just to be clear on things.
This is only for debugging, you would not want a virtual Alec every
individual file like that because virtual Alec is for large
applications.
I think it's minimum allocation size is 64.
K.
Maybe something like that.
It allocates in 4k pages, but I think you can't allocate less than 64
of them.
Because basically the granularity of it is,
That.
So you're using up that much of the virtual address space.
I do.
Although you may not care.
It's a long story but point being you don't want to be doing lots of
small virtual Alex.
So the only reason we're doing this is because we know that this is
only for our debugging purposes.
You wouldn't be you wouldn't be doing that normally and if you care
too much you could do this.
You could call Heap a lock.
If you, if you actually cared about it because that will use the
actual OS Heap which is designed for more small applications like
that, but we don't care about that.
So we're just going to stick to use.
Virtual work for now.
So that's it.
The only thing we need to do now is basically clone this function for
writing.
It's pretty straightforward.
Basically, we don't need to do any of the allocations stuff anymore.
So that simplifies our life quite a bit.
Nor do we need to get the science for things.
All we really need to do is just open the file right to it and close
it.
So basically all we're going to do here is change, what we're passing.
We're going to do generic, right?
We're going to say that we don't have any file sharing, and we're
going to be do a create always basically
Well, actually, you know what?
I got to go look.
And make sure what the actual flags are for saying.
We always want to overwrite everything.
Let's double-check.
All right, so create file basically, going to take the share mode is
zero right?
Other possum opening at all.
That's what we wanted.
So we're changing our share mode, 20.
We're asking for generic, right pillars.
We don't need to read from it.
So we can just say generic, right?
And then we've got create always.
Let's see.
Yes, I think we're good.
If the specified file exists, the function overrides the file, which
is what we want.
If it doesn't exist a new files created.
So I think that's exactly what we want because we want to overwrite
old files.
So that should be it's that's all we really need.
That's all we really need.
So then when we come in here, we're just going to write the memory to
it.
So we're basically just going to do the equivalent right file.
We're basically what we do is we pass the memory size.
Sighs there.
And the memory, that should be it.
Like that.
Something like that.
I don't actually know what you pass, the right file.
Let's take a look right?
Wow.
There we go.
So right file, we pass the file handle which we did pass the buffer
which we did.
We pass the number of bytes to right which we did.
Then we need the B written which is equivalent here.
B written.
And then we've got the overlap parameters.
So there we go.
Basically the same.
We are going to basically do.
None of that.
I guess we could log it, if they wanted to, when we do our logging and
that is it really, that's not a lot to it.
Basically, the same stuff here.
We're going to assume false failure and then we're going to set our
result parameter to whether the B written equals.
The, the size that we were trying to, right, right, like that.
So that's it.
Really, and you'll notice the way I have structured these I tend to
like to make a result variable set it to failure at the outset.
Which I try to make V2 zero value as much as possible.
So the default failure is zero there.
I try to do the operations and when I get all the way onto the inside,
I will then set that result to whether or not the thing succeeded and
then up, and then let that fall out, that's tends to be the way that I
write these functions.
I find it's pretty clean and makes it easy to verify that everything
went.
Okay.
So that's our right entire file and nothing really special there.
It's just the inverse of the read basically, you know.
Opening is the same.
And then just instead of calling the read, we just call a right that's
it.
Nothing else to it.
And of course, we don't need to do any allocations there.
So it's a simpler function, so, out.
And here we could do that.
Now, we could say, basically we don't call this bitmap memory because
it ain't a bitmap.
So we're basically to read the entire file.
Then if we're here, we'll do Platform, right?
Entire file.
And basically what we'll do is we'll write out a test file here.
I'll just say w handmade.
Test dot out, like that.
And whoop.
Almond milk fail.
There we go.
Always got to put it out here a little further.
I think that's the right thing to do.
Okay.
So basically all we're doing here is I'm just going to read the file
in and then I'm going to write out an another file.
That's basically a test file will put that in the data directory.
Just just to test it.
Let's see, does not take one arguments.
You're very right.
Sir.
It does not.
Oh, good point.
See this is the this is the thing, people always got.
You always got a right to usage code or you're going to miss stuff.
You always got to have the usage code, never, develop an API without
the usage code.
So basically, what happened here is, I forgot one crucial thing, which
is when we actually have these.
Where was that there?
There it is.
When we actually
Is when we read the entire file, we need to know how big it was as
well.
So we actually need debug read file result.
You actually need to return the, the, the data like the contents of
the file.
But we also need the flat, the content size, right?
We need both of those things and we don't have them right now.
So, basically, what we need to do is we need to return this from that
read entire file function.
Does that make sense?
So, that was good.
Catch their who always write the usage code, you got to have that uses
code.
Otherwise you go ship that thing to someone and then you realize that
no one can actually use it in practice.
It's so good.
The usage code.
Saves you so much time.
Always, always, always develop the usage code.
Developed usage code if you can.
All right.
So anyway, here's our actual result.
We're going to initialize that there and then what we'll do here is
when we come through assuming that the file was read successfully,
then we're going to have own
We're going to actually have a void star.
Well, no.
Yes, we have to have results to our contents.
So, everywhere we were using result before you actually have result,
start contents, is the thing like this like that, like that.
And like this.
There we go.
Looking good.
And then, all we want to do here is basically assuming that we
actually if everything succeeded, we're going to set that content size
equal to the file size like that.
Let's take a look here.
So now we have to actually do this, debug read file result, file.
So we're going to read that in.
We've got file dot, contents.
We're assuming that's going to be true.
There we go.
Then we're going to go ahead and write that out file dot content, size
file, dot, contents like that.
And then we're going to free that memory.
There we go.
Yeah, so that's
That's it.
That's pretty good there.
Let's take a look at what happens?
Yeah, now and you'll notice.
So here's one of those things, if we had, if this would have been part
of our system.
Remember I was saying for debugging purposes.
It's nice to set that base of virtual a lock.
Well, that's exactly what would have been nicer because our memory
window would have been showing the right location already.
But since virtual apps and returned,
Things every time for when we don't specify the Base address it
wouldn't.
So that's the kind of thing that I sang for.
Our regular game code is nice to have that, you know, when you can get
it anyway, so here is our file.
Let's take a look at the contents to make sure they're correct.
There.
They are.
Now we're going to write to this file.
So let's step in there.
Let's see if we can open that file.
Now.
We should on the drive.
Actually.
Start to see it show up.
So if I go in here to the data directory, we should see it.
There it is, you know, it says zero size because it has not actually
finished the right to it.
Yet will do the right and I believe it'll still show zero size.
Yeah.
So basically the way that NTFS typically reports these things it'll
say zero size till it actually closes.
Handle, so you'll notice the B, the free B went down by the amount we
wrote.
So you can actually tell that it did the right but it stays 0.
Then we close that handle.
We now should see it.
Go to the sighs.
There.
It is and off we go.
So that's it for that off.
We go, we come in here.
We freed the memory and we end and now if it worked properly we should
see as well.
The fact that that file is the same file.
So if
If I go ahead and open it now, right, there it is.
And that's, that's what we wanted.
All right, so that's about it.
There isn't a lot else to it.
I don't think we actually need to save this test code anymore because
the problem is this, this path is hard coded here.
Right?
And we don't really want a hard-coded path in this thing.
That was just for testing purposes.
So unless we were actually going to start doing it.
I guess we could do, you know we could do.
We could just do that because the data directory,
Our startup directory anyway, so basically what we can do is say well,
alright in the solution Explorer.
We right-click on this thing.
We did properties and don't know if you remember I set this to the
data directory so that we wouldn't have to use absolute paths for
things.
So what I can do is I can just say test that out here and that'll
right to the data directory because that's that's it's just going to
look for that in the current directory.
Right?
So what I can do is something like this, then when I run it in theory
that should still write out that file and there it is.
So that's good.
Good, that that'll be.
That'll be good for now.
So I think that's it for file IO for the debug.
I don't think we'll need anything else to get ourselves up and running
because will base to be able to load.
Our bitmaps are sound files, that way and we'll go from there, and we
can write our state out using that.
It'll be pretty basic, but it should should sort of work.
Now.
I'm going to add some notes in here, basically, to the to, this this
part right here and basically say just to be clear.
Note Casey these in fact, you know what?
I might even do it this way.
I like a little
Important thing there.
Oh, I don't know, man.
That's that's going to have to get fixed.
So on my in the emacs file that I shipped out.
I guess I didn't include the the, oh, yeah, I didn't include important
and study.
So this is an old because this machine had an old index file.
I'm going to go ahead and do that right now.
In fact, just so you can see, I'm going to look up what my colors are
normally for them on my other machine because I this is relatively
important for me.
I like these a lot.
What I typically do.
Is in here in, this is just in the da TMX file.
So those of you who are not using body Max, don't have to worry about
this.
But what I typically do is I basically have a thing like this where I
Define some other keywords besides the besides the to do and the note,
which I already have to find.
I've got study and I've got an important and then basically what I do
is down here I've got
Study and important and then those are dark.
No, they're both yellow.
I guess.
Let's see.
So these are yellow and yellow.
All right.
There we go.
So, important notes are just ones that are like, you got to read them
and study is something that I want to look at later.
So I use those pretty typically.
That's that's that's relatively important.
Okay, so sorry about that little Excursion, but you got to have that.
These are not for doing
Anything in the shipping game?
The, they are blocking and the right doesn't protect against lost
data, right?
And basically, what I mean by that is when we do this, right, let's
say we were updating the person's unlocks.
The file on the drive where they save their unlocks.
And you know what, while I'm well I'm saying this discussion.
I'm going to go ahead and restart emacs there so that I can get my 0
or not.
Let's see.
There is the problem.
Died to find one of those one of those things wrong.
Oh, I did.
Yeah, man, I tell you, you cannot, you cannot trifle with Emax people.
You cannot try for with you, Max.
I'm like the worst emacs guy because I know nothing about emacs.
I only like pigeonhole.
I'll learn the basic thing.
I forgot that for some reason, emacs always wants you to do what's
going on here.
Always want you to do these defines first, man.
If you're emacs, doesn't if you're emacs file, is busted.
You're just in a world of hurt because none of your stuff works
anymore.
Okay, so make face font lock, can't even see that.
There we go.
Make face font lock study face.
And make
Bass song.
Glock important face.
There we go.
Forgot those.
Okay.
There we go.
Now we should be back in business.
Hopefully anyways, let's take a look.
Now.
Does that work properly and made, uh,
Where's my important?
There?
It is.
So I like having that just so it kind of sticks out a little bit.
Basically, what I was talking about here before we go to the Q&A.
What I was talking about is when you write to a critical file, so
let's say you've got the, the unlocks on the, on the user's machine.
Like what stuff they've unlocked in the game.
You typically don't just want to overwrite the old file.
And the reason for that is your overwrite could fail and only
partially overwrite.
The file leaving them with a corrupted save file.
So what you want to do?
Instead usually is right to a different file and either have a rolling
buffer scheme.
So basically you have like an A and A B file and you write to the be
file.
Then you write to the a file.
Then you write to the B file on alternating runs of the game so that
and you load whatever one is most recent or
You write to a secondary temp file, delete the old file, and then
rename the file into place.
So that at least, you know, that it's the renamed would have to fail,
but you're not going to run out of space on the drive and fail or
stuff like that.
So we want to, when we actually do the stuff that writes to the save
game file.
We're going to want to do something much more protected than this.
I hate when games.
Don't do safe ways of saving stuff and then lose your saved game or
something like that.
I hate that.
So we're, you know, we're gonna make sure we don't do that.
So anyway, I think that's everything for file IO that we wanted to do.
I don't think there's anything else.
So, next week, we should be in good shape to, just go through clean
things up.
Basically are clocking values, need to be cleaned up and then let's
look at some to dues keyboard input should be piped through.
So we're basically, we already get the keyboard input.
We don't pipe it through our input system.
So, basically next week, just cleaning up everything that that we
hadn't actually just finished and then we should be good to go.
We are basically at a place where we've got all the
Line stuff for the for the game, to actually start to exist which is
pretty darn cool.
So with that, let's go to the Q&A and see if anyone has questions
about what was covered.
Please make sure that your question has senior at, Orion it so that I
will see it.
And also, please keep questions to stuff.
We have implemented today or in a previous day.
No questions about what we're going to implement because we're going
to get to those when we Implement them.
Let's see.
Will the game be able to carry on in spite of some big-time failure
like a graphics?
This reset and a software rendering make that easier to deal with.
Yes, the fact that we have set up a software renderer does mean that's
easier to deal with.
But in general with files and GPU and all that stuff.
We will try for the most part to make it so that and that we ride over
transient failures as much as possible, you know, if there's stuff
that we literally can't recover from then, obviously not.
But, you know, we'll try to be relatively good about that.
And that's one of the reasons I say that these are debug
Only because these these aren't these are set up for Success a little
bit.
In the sense that if this fails, you just get one failure and you can
handle it pretty easily.
So these are better than the average in terms of apis for that.
But we're going to try to make them.
I'll show you what we're going to do.
We'll be doing some stuff that really does handle stuff pretty well.
So that basically if you yanked let's say this was what running off a
USB to USB drive and you yanked it.
The game was still run, just fine.
Only you wouldn't be any time.
There was sort of been something new.
You'll just see like a
Think error bitmap or something, but then when you jam that USB drive
back in, it would start working again.
We'll try to make things work.
Roughly that way.
No other games ever work like that, like, nobody writes stuff at that
safe.
Pretty much, but we will because again, this is for educational
purposes and we should show how to do stuff, right?
Instead of just doing the minimum necessary to ship.
Would it make sense to call normal file size and assert, that the high
32 bit value is 0.
Yes, and no, I think that actually technically misses one case.
So basically, if you look in here, if the loops is not read file, file
size, yet file size.
I think there's it's a little janky or even than you think it is.
Because if you go read this, if the function fails
The return value is invalid, file size and invalid, file size.
I think is actually 0 x FF FF FF FF, which means that if you had a
file that was exactly the largest.
You could have a 32-bit file, get file size.
Looks like it just failed.
Right?
So like it says, right here, when file size is null, the results
returned for large file sizes, and you will not be able to run the
actual file size determined by get file size.
Eax.
If the function fails, and it's non null and you got to use the get
last error, so, basically, you'd have to call get last error to
determine whether the file size was actually 0xffff, and I don't want
to do any of that.
So it's just even if you're only doing 32-bit files, reads, you want
to call this, I think.
Just let you handle one more case without doing any actual work doing.
Less work handle, one more case.
That's just all good, right?
Let's see here.
Where are we?
It'd be useful for us to write our own allocation functions
specifically allocate sections of our earlier already, reserved
temporary mayor, memory.
I'm having trouble understanding why we were doing separate
allocations.
Well, so, the reason is because this is only debug code.
So there's no point in writing an alligator to handle it because we
wouldn't shift that allocator.
This is only allowed to be in the internal build.
So you would literally just be wasting your time if you went, and
wrote an alligator that allocates out of your temporary memory because
It's not going to ship, never write code that you don't intend to
ship.
If it doesn't do anything that helps you in debug mode.
So calling virtual.
Alec is free for us in debug mode.
So it's there's really no reason why you would do what you're
suggesting.
It's strictly would just waste you time and get you no benefit.
So you don't want to do that.
We will be sub allocating out of our temporary memory for all the
stuff we do in the game.
That's actually stuff, you know, all the stuff that we do starting
right after we finish our clean up next.
all the stuff we do from then on will be some allocated out of the
game memory, but that yeah, you really you really don't want to waste
your time like
I know it seems like I'm doing things that could be considered by some
people to waste time.
Like why are you just letting the system do all your allocation for
you and stuff like that.
I actually am getting benefits out of this, right?
I'm getting fault tolerance.
I'm getting a knowledge of exactly the footprint so we can, we will be
Port.
We can Port it easily.
We're actually getting a lot of efficiency because we don't have to
worry about making our allocator be performant because we won't have
one.
So there's actually a lot of benefits to the things that I'm doing in
my mind.
Anyway,
But I don't just waste time like I won't just go right in allocator
just to write one.
That's not something I would do.
I only write an alligator if I actually am gonna get some utility out
of it.
So that's why we're not doing that is because there'd be absolutely no
use to doing it.
Let's see when we Implement some kind of cloud storage for the rights.
So.
Probably not because as far as I know, the only circumstance where we
would have access to cloud storage is steam, which I think, does the
cloud storage for us.
So if we release the game on Steam, then we could call their API for
doing that.
Certainly, but we don't have a cloud.
Like, we don't have a server.
So, there's no way we can really Implement cloud storage for our
stuff.
You know, if we do steam integration of some point, which would
require valve to give us steam approval or something.
Then we could, we could use like the cloud storage that they
implement, but then we won't really be implementing it, right?
They implemented it.
So, yeah, so there's really not much we can do with cloud storage.
Let's see here.
I know you removed it for now.
I'm not sure what you mean by it.
That sentence but I know you removed it for now, but wouldn't a
reserved memory method with an arbitrary file size.
Still introduce a failure Point.
Since it could fail like virtual Alec and we have simply moved the
memory, allocation burden onto ourselves.
I'm not sure what you mean like I was saying before, this is never
going to be called in the game when you actually ship it.
So these can fail, but we're never going to actually call them in the
game.
These are strictly for our own debugging purposes.
Has and like when we write asset processing code will use these
because we don't care the asset processing only happens on our machine
and we know when it failed.
So so basically, these are not to be shipped.
So I'm not sure.
I understand the question.
Could you go over the difference between transient and permanent
storage?
Again?
It's hard for me to see what kinds of memory will be used for each.
So, we covered that in yesterday's Q&A.
If you missed it, you can reload your emacs eggs without blowing
everything up.
Each time with eval buffer.
Can you like so you I know about eval buffer and sometimes that works.
But for font lock, you have to do a bunch of stuff to make that work.
If I remember correctly.
You have to turn off Van.
Lock, re-evaluate the buffer reload fought, like, there's like, a
bunch of steps.
So I just usually restart emacs instead of trying to remember what
they all are four simple things.
I'll use eval buffer, if it's just like adding something I'll use it,
but I don't think you can use it.
In this case, you have to do a bunch of steps in addition to eval
buffer and I don't remember what they all are.
Let's see.
What are you drinking?
I am drinking.
Almond milk spiked with coffee this morning because it's my morning
coffee.
So I just put instant coffee in the almond milk.
It's like coffee milk.
Let's see.
Are there any other benefits to doing one?
Massive allocation aside from having one failure point also does the
order of properties in your structs matter when it comes to
Performance efficiency?
Yes, and yes, the other benefits of doing one.
Massive.
Allocation is like I said during debugging, we can have a stable base
point for our allocations.
So that's pretty handy.
You the only other way you get that is by doing a bunch of work to
turn off Windows address randomization.
So that's a pretty big benefit.
There's other things.
To do later in development that allow it to be like there's a lot of
fringe benefits.
You'll see as we go that we're constantly taking advantage of the fact
that we just have one big allocation.
So yeah, there's a lot of them the order of properties in the structs
does matter when it comes to Performance and efficiency.
I'm not really the right guy to tell you what they all are, because
I'm not enough of an optimization head to know these days, exactly
what they all are.
But just to give you a trivial example, let's say you had a lot of a
struct.
Right.
Let's say you had a lot of struct and you did something like this.
Let's say you type that in and you had 10,000 of these.
Well, this actually because of the way that sees packing works.
This will actually cause this to bloat out quite a bit more than if it
was done like this, right?
Let's say I've got something like this here, right?
This is a better example.
Okay.
This is my fake struck.
There we go.
Let's compile that.
So basically here is just a trivial example.
And like I said, I'm not the guy to give you the rundown on this, you
want an optimization head, someone who studies it all the time and
especially on Modern machines, but I'm going to give you example of
the sorts of things that could happen.
So let's take a look at the size of fake struct here and well I can't
because I don't actually have one.
So let's make sure that I actually get one so that I can I can
actually make that.
Happened in 32 handmade.
So let's go into wind Main and just go ahead and say fake struct a
this fake struck BB.
And I'm going to do this.
All right.
And let's step into that and take a look.
I'm going to ask for the size of a and the size of B.
What what is the problem here?
What's going on?
Why am I not able to actually a, we compiling an optimization with
optimizations on or something.
Did I?
Did I forget to turn that off?
Know.
Why can I not?
Why can I not expect our inspect my stuff?
What's going on here?
What's going on here people?
Felt like the op is should not be.
Maybe I had to turn would have to turn all optimizations offer that.
Okay.
There we go.
Well, yeah, it was just optimizing those out.
So I guess we don't have our optimizations fully disabled which is too
bad.
But oh well, alright.
So what I wanted to show you here if I can manage to not cough.
The death first is basically inside my hand.
May .h I Define two different structs.
They have exactly the same members XYZ and UV and basically, you can
see that
They have exact same types.
The why is 32 bit and everything else is 8-bit.
Same exact straps.
Let's say, I've got 10,000 of these, right?
Well, if you take a look at the sizes, you will note that a is 12 B,
and B is only eight.
So basically you have wasted four, bytes of memory per structure by
going with this ordering as opposed to this order.
No other difference between them whatsoever.
In terms of when you are using them, yet.
You've basically caused yourself a massive amount of memory blow
potentially 4, bytes per.
So, however, many you had 100,000 of them.
It will see you at 100,000 them.
You would be wasting four hundred thousand bytes and don't really you
don't have to care too much about the memory because memory is cheap.
Oftentimes, but performance is not and reading all that extra memory
in all that cash pollution is going to cost you.
So yes, the order matters.
It's because how see, decides to pad things out matters and you got to
make sure that you pack your things in properly.
So that's just one example of how it could be a real problem for you.
In practice.
Not just theoretical one.
So the order does matter, I'm just Nest not decided the guy to tell
you exactly everything about that that you might want to know, but it
definitely matters.
You mentioned, wait, two games, really usually?
Right to a second file rather than using some sort of safe, right?
Function.
That won't overwrite it if it's somehow fails.
So, no games don't usually.
And that's why they often mess up your saved games and stuff like
that.
There is no such thing as a safe, right function.
I mean, well, there are transacted write functions that in theory
would be okay, but no, oftentimes games just full-on do lots of tiny
rights to the save file.
And if one of them start fails or something hat or Runs Out of Space,
right at the time when it was about to try and write the last bit of
that file in it just flat-out corrupts your stuff.
Or if the game crashes, this is another one if the game crashes right
in the middle of
To save file, which happens then you've lost the whole save file
because it's just corrupted and you're done.
So games, don't normally do that.
They should every game should do hundred percent.
Safe writing, if they can, the way I will probably do it in this game
as will write to a secondary file will write, basically rolling
buffer.
So we'll say, like, let's say we got 16, save files and will just
write to them sequentially and then wrap and then we'll just look at
whichever ones, latest and load that that way.
No matter what happens, even if there's random
ins will always at least make sure we can roll back to a previous save
and not lose everything that the user tried to do.
Let's see.
Do you miss multiple return values and see for the moments when you
have great C hat?
Seek allows you to have multiple turned as far as I know.
Oh, you're saying, I see you're saying, do I miss being not be able to
do like tuples just in line.
It don't like.
Okay.
So I think that I think he's asking do I do I miss not being able to
just have a quick way to just say this returns to things, you know,
like like like this, right?
Put the two things in here, instead of having to actually device
truck.
Not really.
It doesn't bother me to type this.
Yeah, it could be a little shorter, but it's fine.
I mean, would I prefer it if it looked just, you know, just like this,
you know, something like that.
What I prefer that probably, but it's not really that much typing.
It's one extra thing struck blah.
So, you know really care, does it really matter?
Why don't we just map the file into memory?
I mentioned that and the reason is because I didn't want to
overcomplicate things because this is only for debug.
So the only reason to just do them to the to do the memory map would
be if you were concerned about whether Windows could get performance
out of using the backing store and stuff like that, but I don't care
about any of that.
This is just the debug read.
So memory mapping the file just introduced as a bunch of complexity
for no reason, so that's why we didn't do that.
Let's see.
During one of the earlier cast, you mentioned that you're not a fan of
high-level languages.
Well, I'd rather not tackle that now.
That's probably a pre stream question because it's not really about
what we were working on.
Let's see.
Will allocating a single amount of memory upfront, make it more
difficult to selectively enable disable certain features of the game.
Since there could be many combinations, each requiring different
amounts of memory.
I don't think so, because basically, we will be allocating based on
what the system's capabilities are.
So which would also determine what options you are not allowed to
enable.
So I think those are both be the same.
I can't think of any options that actually affect memory though.
In our case.
Yeah, I don't think so.
But I could be wrong and if I again, we have flexibility here.
If we want to, we can always have it so that the platform layer could
redo the allocation and change how big it is, but we, it probably
won't really ever be an issue.
Because again, when we allocate that memory, if we can always choose
not to use it all as well.
We're just reserving the memory with Windows essentially.
So what we can do to is just reserved, the maximum, we can always
reserved for gigabytes.
Something assuming we're on 64-bit thing and then just not use it all.
Why does the order of fake struct A and B matter?
Well, it's like I said it because it changes the size.
And the reason for that is that see a lines things to their their
boundary.
So basically, if you have an 8-bit thing, it's going to be it's going
to be on one bite boundaries.
If you have a 32-bit thing it's going to be on 34 B boundaries.
So if you have an 8-bit thing, followed by a 32-bit thing, it's got to
insert 24 bits of Paddington.
The next 32, bit B bout to get to the next four byte boundary or
32-bit boundary, right?
So that just happens.
Why did you do the B macros?
But hesitate on the swap?
Is there, some hidden complexity on pointer swaps?
So the reason is because so I'll tell you just to get back to what
where the what the person is asking about suits, just to give you some
context if you don't know.
So here is the thing.
I did to swap the pointers.
I basically did new input assignment to tempt then assigned old and
put two new and put in this, I attempt to Old input, right?
So the problem is, if you want to do a swap, you kind of have this
nasty problem.
So, alright.
So you see how I wrote that there, it's pretty clear what happened,
right?
It's pretty obvious.
What's going on?
You could read this code if I want to do a swap, right?
If I do swap a be right, like this, then the problem is, how do I
write that?
Right?
If I wanted to put this exactly in there.
I've got this.
I've got a, I've got be a, I've got a temp, right?
This is this is what.
Oops.
Yeah, this is what this is.
What's going on?
Ten people's a a quills beep equals 10 sir.
There we go.
That's what I actually wanted.
So I basically got this.
The problem is I don't know what type temp is like.
I have no idea, right?
Because in the macro, I can't figure out what type it is.
So you could use a template and C++, but I don't want to introduce
templates in here because I don't really want to ever use them so that
when we if we ever write our own compiler, for this or whatever, we
wouldn't have to support templates.
Because they're mostly useless.
And so you're basically just wasting a bunch of language space and
adding a bunch of complexity for for largely useless feature set.
And so, basically, like you could use templates here, but if you
actually want to write the swap swap macro without knowing you'd have
to pass the type, right?
Like this, oops, which is a little janky, right?
Or if you don't want to pass the type, you can implement it using an X
or basically, there's a way you can do.
You can do a swap by xoring things together to just sort of do the
swap in place.
I don't know if you guys know what I'm talking about, but basically
like xor swap is like a thing, right?
You can see it's like a famous thing.
In fact, right.
So basically, it's this thing you can read about it if you want to.
And basically what happens is, it's a way of using the things in place
to do.
Do a bunch of exercises with each other that produced the ends up
producing the swab.
Does that make sense?
So, that's the only way you could really write it in a macro that I
know of, and I didn't really want to do that.
Just like, you know what?
I don't even know if I'm going to swap that many things.
I'm just like, forget about it.
Whereas the bite stuff for macros is Trivial.
There's no reason not to do it.
So I just did it.
Hopefully, that makes sense.
And yet the people were saying, C++ 11, decal type.
Sure you can do that.
But like I said, I just I don't want to introduce language complexity
if I don't have to right.
Let's see here.
So structs with unions in them have bad performance issues as well.
No.
Structures unions in them.
Don't have any putting a union inside.
A structure doesn't have any performance implications.
The basically you always have that alignment thing.
So, stuck inside the union would also have the same alignment
constraints wherever it appears in the struct, but there isn't any
special thing about unions that makes them a problem.
They're they're the same as just any other member of the struct.
You mentioned, iocp 40 IO completion ports.
That's what comments about saying for a sync file.
I/O.
Are you planning to use multiple worker threads?
I've been doing some multi-threaded e-poll code on Linux, and it's
very janky API, unless you're only using one worker thread.
There are even a few articles on lwn dotnet only about how to safely
remove a file descriptor with e-poll.
So
On Windows.
I suspect we will use IO completion ports and just queue up all our
reads and do them that way, but I don't know for sure.
You don't even need worker threads at all.
You can just queue them up and windows to do it for you.
So the worker threads would only be on the code side and we probably
would only need one.
Because all it's really going to do is like, copy the memory and
stuff.
Although we could try to speed that up by doing multiple CPU, if
there's like,
Lot of decompression work or something, we could do that, but I don't
know.
As for Linux.
I have never tried to do efficient overlapped IO and Linux why I'm no
idea might be a nightmare.
I have no idea.
Well, we'll find out when we get there.
Basically.
That'll be interesting experience for me as well.
Because I don't know how you do those things on Windows.
Very optimally.
On the swap.
Why does it have to be a macro, wouldn't a function?
Do the job and cover the janky complexity with types in the macro?
Well, yes we could and so that's like I said, I just didn't want to
think about it much we could do it.
But the problem is if you make it a function, you have to have one a
separate function for every type, right?
So, yeah, it's a little it's a little janky.
Even even then you have to have one function for every type.
You're trying to swap.
Let's see.
F Radix, why do I Define the swap macro to be pound?
Define swap, do type of 80?
Again?
I don't want to introduce any more language features.
I basically just want.
See, I just want if you can write a c compiler.
I want you to be able to compile handmade hero.
So the only thing we're really doing is overloading is I think the
only thing we're actually going to really be allowing because I think
it's valuable.
It's like it's sort of a necessity.
Does array count macro work with strings.
No, it's because the string isn't an array.
So so it wouldn't work with strings.
A sink I/O and Linux is nutty.
All right, if Juan says, so it is probably true.
Juan 3D is actually watch on.
He is working on the rad to bugger right now.
In fact, and he knows Linux things a lot better than I do.
If he says, the async io is nutty, then it probably is pretty nutty.
All right, are we at the end of questions?
We have two minutes left.
I think we've answered all the questions brown or blue.
I think the answer is Brown at the zoom.
You're asking about the switches on the keyboard, to be honest.
I've been a little bit.
I really like the dust keyboard three and I really like the Das
Keyboard three, but I don't like the dust keyboard.
For as much, the keys are feel too heavy to me, like the
Springs are like tighter or something.
So I don't know.
I mean to do a test side by side, with the Das Keyboard 3, and the 4
to see if I'm just imagining that.
But I liked the Das Keyboard threes key, feel a little bit better than
the Das Keyboard for it.
To be honest with you, Clemens bound.
It actually works string.
Literals.
Yeah, so when you're asking about the array count string thing, so if
you happen to Define, if you, if you happen to Define your string
slightly differently, if you did this.
Then I think a re count would not work for you.
But if you did this it would because that actually is an array now in
terms of what see does, so I'll double check that for you here.
But I believe that's true.
So I believe that basically, if we went in here and said in t-bar, AC
equals array account bar and went boo.
AC equals array account, boo.
I suspect that one will be correct in one will be wrong.
That's just my assumption.
Let's take a look Bareilles.
See there.
We see ya.
So basically, if you happen to be talking about
about a literal array.
You defined as an array c will actually properly initialize that as an
array.
That is the string and that'll work.
But that's really the only time array count would work for a string.
It'll never work for anything else.
So, yeah, again, I would not recommend using a rake out with a string
ever because you're very likely to make a mistake.
As you change the code that you as the code like kind of goes through
changes.
Oh Clemens, mom was saying you could do it.
I see what you're saying.
You were saying actually this and yes, I was that works too because
that's similar to this one as well.
It's actually a simpler case than this one.
So yeah, those those should both work.
I would think.
Let's see.
All right, last questions here.
Looks like there are no more string questions.
So I think we're done.
Is there any chance to continue John and Casey show?
I don't know what John and Casey show is but the Jeff and Casey show,
if that's what you're talking about.
It's just that Jeff and Casey show.com.
It's been going continuously.
It's still there.
It never never didn't can discontinued itself.
All right, people.
Thank you very much for joining me for another edition of handmade
hero.
We are closing in again.
Like I said yesterday, and I think we're, we
We did what we want to do today.
So I think we are closing in on win32 being essentially done in our
platform independent layer, essentially being done for the time being
which is pretty awesome.
We can move onto a fresh new set of things to work on all of, which I
think will be pretty, pretty cool.
So, hopefully, you'll join me next week.
Again.
We're starting Monday at 8 p.m.
PST again.
Hope to see you there.
We'll probably do a little bit of cleanup or we might push a little
further forward ahead first just because it's a Monday and we can and
then maybe save the
in up for for Thursday and Friday, something like that.
I don't know exactly what we'll do, but we'll do something like that,
but next week should be pretty fun.
So, I hope to see you guys here again.
If you would like to follow along with the source code at home.
You can pre-order the game on handmade hero dot-org and that'll give
you a link that you can use to download the source code every night.
And that's going to be increasingly important as we go.
Because this will also have the assets that you'll need to follow
along at home with a actual like Sprites and stuff like that, which is
going to be important going forward.
Words, also, if you want to discuss, ask questions and discuss news
and forums has like the schedule for the week.
It's got a code discussion area where you can ask questions, all sorts
of stuff.
So, check that out for sure.
It's also got extended episode guide.
And the Twitter feed, as always.
I tweet every day when the stream will be, if you're curious.
You can always take, check the Twitter feed.
So check all that stuff out.
Thank you very much for joining me for another episode of handmade
hero, and I hope to see you Monday at 8:00 p.m.
Sharp.
Thanks everybody, and I will see you next week.