Okay, hello everyone and welcome to handmade.
Here are the show recode complete game live on Twitch.
No library's new engines.
It's just us.
And we are in the middle of sort of straightening out our asset or
assets story.
If you will thus far on handmade hero because we've been working on
engine stuff.
We haven't thought very hard about how we want our assets to actually
be stored and loaded in the real shipping version.
Of the game.
And so one of the things that we have to do, before we can call the
sort of underlying layers of the game done, is we have to figure out
how the assets are going to be stored and how the game talks about
those assets so that it can retrieve them and make meaningful use of
them.
So it knows like what is what, and it knows what to put on the screen
where and all these sorts of things, it needs information about what
assets, it has available to it.
And so that's why we started doing yesterday just because kind of one
thing led to another we had done assets tree
Aiming work and I was kind of saying, well in order to go any further
on this, we kind of have to have some idea of like what the asset
table is and all these are the certain things.
So that is what we're in the middle of doing right now.
And so I'm going to go ahead and jump into that.
Just before I do today is day 1, 34, which means that if you are
trying to follow along at home and you have pre-ordered, the game on
handmade hero dot-org, you will want to unzip day 133, out of the
sources.
IP that is the source code that I am starting with right now.
And that is what you should start with if you want to be editing.
Same code that I am in order to follow along.
All right, so if I remember correctly, we only just had gotten started
because we were actually working on finishing up some asset streaming
stuff yesterday.
So we only just barely started talking about the game asset stuff and
what we might want to do in terms of how that stuff was organized.
We had this concept here of an asset tag and asset bitmap, info, and
asset group, and stuff, the group hadn't really come to fruition much.
We hadn't really talked about that very much, but we were kind of
saying, like, yeah, I don't know about this.
It's hard.
Say, but I wrote kind of a little example or Timur.
It's like oh imagine if I had these tags on assets and I wanted to
pick, you know, certain assets out of out of a hat or something like
this.
You know, this might be the kind of way that I could Envision doing it
and so you can kind of see me doing this, this sort of tag-based
matching and waiting thing here to figure out, you know, what would be
out of a set you know, of a
A set of assets, which of the assets would best match some example
where I was saying, I want these particular values or whatever, right?
And so I don't know, I don't know how much likes that has.
It was just something that I kind of pulled out of thin air.
But what I'm trying to do with this and where I'm trying to go with
this is, I need to have some way for the game to talk about
The assets that are in the asset file without actually necessarily
knowing what they are.
And the reason that I say it that way is because let's say that we
want to do something like have some trees, right?
We've got trees in the game right now, we have one Sprite it's just a
tree, right?
And you know, if I go over here and the Run the game as it exists at
the moment you can see that there are these little trees that are
lining kind of the the play area there.
We just kind of we kind of wanted to make like in the shape of a room.
So we just stuck some trees down there, right?
But as we go forward and we want to make more interesting
environments, obviously, we won't necessarily just want to have one
single tree Sprite.
We might want to have like several trees, right?
And we might want to have like Forest have different types of trees in
them.
And furthermore, we might mop those forests to have different types of
trees, depending on where they are in the world.
So that there can be different types of trees and different types of
forests and all these other sorts of things, right?
So you can imagine that there could be a fairly wide notion of what is
8.
Free Sprite even inside just this one game.
And so, for that reason, we need a way of talking about tree Sprites
in some way that's different and more expressive than just, what I
kind of did to Simply Port.
What we had right now, which was to just have a single, you know, a
single token.
Basically that says, I want a tree and the asset system gets me back a
tree, right?
So what I would rather do is I would rather have something where the
asset system can say something.
Like, get me back a tree.
Tree.
And I want a tree with these properties, and I don't really need to
know how many trees Sprites you have or what their characteristics
are.
I just know what I'm looking for in terms of a tree and you give me
back something that matches as close as possible.
What I actually wanted.
And the reason that this is kind of nice, is it because it means that
without actually changing the game code, you can upgrade the set of
visual representations that are
With the game just by updating the data pack, right?
So, if you action is only delivered, you know, one tree or five trees
to me or whatever.
And I put them in the data pack and I write the game code and later we
go and see like, oh, we really wish there was a little more variety in
this type of Forest, right?
It's kind of nice to have a system where I don't really have to do any
real work in the code, to be able to just start adding more tree
Sprites to it, right?
And furthermore, this allows kind of some easy modding to happen as
well.
It means that if people want to add their own tree Sprites to the
game, the game engine doesn't have to be recompiled just to allow
someone to add some more tree variety or to make trees that are more
specific to an area where that didn't actually exist before, right?
So,
That is.
That is the idea.
All right, that's that's what we're going for here.
So, I'm going to go ahead and talk about.
Easy part of it.
And we'll come to the harder part a little bit later.
Okay, so if I take a look here into the data directory, right?
If we if we go into the handmade gyro data directory, we have two
things, right?
We've got test where we've kind of got this this stuff where we're
starting with version of just the hero.
And some layer example, things like from the startup screen or
whatever, right?
And then we also have this test to which had some very
Variants on things as grasses that had some grounds, right?
And then we had some rocks here, right?
And what I kind of want to do is take one of these, which is like the
Rocks seem to be the most varied, although the trees I guess the
trees, we could also kind of do as well.
If we wanted to
But the trees in the rocks, have this sort of thing where I can
pretend even though they're not really set up for it quite yet, but, I
could pretend that these guys had certain properties, right?
Like, for example, this is a rougher rock.
This is a smoother Rock and maybe that one's in between right and this
one's a Flat Rock and so on, right?
So, you can imagine me, sort of classifying these guys, with some tags
that say, what their properties are in addition to the fact that like,
he's a tree, right?
And so one way we could potentially,
Our sort of setting this up because we could think about the tags as
sort of having maybe one sort of Primal identifier that says, what?
The actual like, sort of type of the thing is, you know, this is a
tree.
And then we could have an additional piece, which says, here are the
tags which just kind of talk about what the quality of this tree
actually is right and seemingly for that type where we have that.
The type part I could also sort of say, you know, we could do that for
tags as well because one thing that you could imagine is you know
let's say that I have trying to think of what would be a good example
here but let's say that I have something like the hero
Well, there's three or four parts to the hero, there's like the hero
head, there's a hero torso and there's the hero cape.
And if I think about those pieces, I could imagine maybe wanting those
to be subdivided.
So I could sort of say, Okay, I want to hear, oh, I don't know how
many parts a hero has.
So I'm just going to trust that you will tell me how many parts of
hero has and those parts themselves could potentially be classified on
something, right?
And that would be the assembly part of things that we were talking
about.
So we have a bunch of stuff there.
I
I feel like we want to kind of tackle all that stuff.
I feel like it'll be useful for us to tackle that stuff.
So I'm going to start with the simplest one.
Which is just that sort of flavor matching that sort of I know that I
want a rock and I need you to sort of find a rock that fits this
The criteria.
That's what I would like to do first.
And so that is what I'm going to try now.
Okay.
So since we kind of have this, I'm going to go ahead and say we've got
a thing here which is, you know what?
I'll just have Rock in here.
I'm going to go ahead and add that in.
And then what I want to do is say that when I actually go ahead and
get out a game asset, when I pull out a game asset like rock, what I'd
like to do is I'd like to make it so that that game asset which I
guess in this case, you know we have this called a game assets lat and
maybe what I kind of want to do instead is just actually go ahead and
Call that a game asset like so right and to some degree I don't even
know if we really need to call it a game asset, it could just be
called an asset.
I mean, there's nothing else in here besides assets, right?
I mean I'm sorry there's nothing else in here besides the game so it's
probably stupid for me to call it a game asset when we kind of all
know what it is.
Similarly I could just call this assets but you know, either way
So any or maybe the asset, you know, system and manager who knows
whatever you want.
But anyway we'll leave that aside.
We have now this concept of the asset ID that we bring back stuff as
and I'm going to go ahead and say that this is you know, an assets are
a right like like so and the assets array is going to be something
where this is the sort of the primary word that you use to talk about
stuff.
So when we say that, we want something in the game we're going to have
to say one of these sort of
Fixed asset ID types, right?
We're going to have to say, and I guess, you know, now that I think
about it to maybe these really should be asset type IDs in that sense
as well, because we kind of have to say, you know, we kind of have to
say which ones, it's not an individual asset, right.
It's a particular set class of assets, right?
And so we have the assets and then we also have in addition to the
assets
We kind of have other tables here that mirror the previous table.
So, although we were using Game asset ID to previously talked about
bitmaps, we probably actually want to have in this here.
The asset slop stuff.
We probably want to talk about this as like assets lot for bitmaps.
You probably want to have that, but we don't actually know how many
there are going to be, right?
Because we were using the system where we where we passed around
bitmask by d's.
We still want to be able to do that.
For asset loading.
So really we want to keep that that notion around.
But now I think what we want to do is it have some notion of a bitmap
count, right?
We want to have some notion of how many there are and we don't
actually know how many there are till we load our asset file, okay?
So we want to do that.
And and so this is going to be sort of a blind pointer.
And so when we go to load the initial asset table off of disk,
That is something that we will grab is all of those bitmap infos in
here and yeah, so we will get that they won't have the assets and the
assets, of course, in them will have sort of some notion of how to get
to that.
So we're going to have so asset is probably the wrong word.
If this is asset type here, right then what we're going to have is
something like an asset type, you know,
To falls off the asset type ID.
The asset type will be the thing that will actually be looking at
into, and that's where we can get out our numbers.
Right?
So basically say, like here are asset types, we can pull those out and
once we get an asset type, then inside there, it will tell us all of
the options that we have, for that particular asset type that seems
pretty reasonable to me.
So this would be something.
And again, we'll have to go write the usage code to actually know
exactly what's going to be.
But I'm just kind of brainstorming out here into the
Jealousy.
Like what the date is that?
I actually have.
So I would need something like the number of these, right?
Like how many I have of a particular asset type.
And then I would need some notion of of of where they all were, right.
I'm trying to think now for asset types,
Asset types.
I wonder if I actually want to do split these because there's going to
be audio assets and bitmap assets.
I'm trying to think of whether I want them split.
I might.
Even though they're pretty much going to be roughly the same, you
know, we're in other words, we're going to have something that feels
something like this, right?
We're going to have we're going to have this sort of thing, right?
And so when we go to look up an asset type, and we say, you know, I
want to rock.
The question is, do we have two different asset type tables as well,
or do we just have one and they're all in here.
So the sounds also come in here.
To like, hit guy or whatever, right?
That sort of thing.
So I don't know.
I'm not sure exactly what we want to do there.
You know, we're only going to be looking up one or the other.
But since they're very, very similar.
I do wonder if maybe we just want to leave it the same.
So I think I'm going to do it that way.
I think I'm going to I think I'm going to go ahead and actually do it
that way and and maybe I will call this a an asset type ID.
Maybe I'll do asset type like that or I could do a tea.
I don't know what, I don't know what I want to do for this.
It's hard to say, usually I like to prefix them with something.
But I'm not sure.
Exactly.
But in this particular instance, asset type backdrop.
That's the type Shadow.
Yeah I could I could live with that.
So anyway, in here, where we've got the asset types that's going to
give us something like count and then inside there, we would need to
have some kind of an index into one of the the info arrays, right?
And there's going to be two different types of infrared Rays.
So, yeah, I mean, again, it's unclear in terms of the matching how we
would actually want to do it, but this part is specific to a bitmap,
right?
But
This part isn't, so you could imagine something like, you know, we
actually have the asset here.
You could imagine something like the asset has the set of tags on it,
like so that sort of conform to that matching stuff that we did.
So we have this is a tag ID, right?
This is a tag ID.
So we would have up here and asset tag ID.
Oh, but that's both are 80.
So frustrating.
I guess we'll just call these tags.
And we'll call these assets that made the decision for me.
That's how we want to do it, I guess.
And I won't bother putting in asset type there.
I guess, even though that's really what it is and this is also that.
But anyway, so we'll have tags here and the tags will just be, you
know.
the stuff that we actually want to put in there, so
We can call it smoothness.
Was basically what I was saying about the Rocks, right?
There's a smoothness and then maybe a height, something like that, or
flatness.
And that would be example of some tags.
So we could have on our rocks, right?
So yeah.
So let's see if we have those tags on the Rocks, we have the asset
type ideas to get the rock out.
We could get the rock out by finding one of these assets, which has
the tags.
And then finally, if
As tags match.
Right, we need to know what we would actually do to get it.
And so, the final thing that we would need to do, there is just
whatever the actual ideas into the into one of the slots, right?
So, this would be at slot ID and you would just be required to know
which one of these two arrays.
You were looking up into bitmaps or sounds because you're only going
to be playing one of the other.
So that's really never a danger in my mind and so that would be
roughly the structure that we would have.
okay, so that seems
Pretty reasonable.
So we'd have something like, you know, first asset index and one
passed last asset in the X.
And this would basically be something that if we wanted to.
We could load directly off of disk because these are actually fairly
right.
These could all be something that we could save directly to disk and
borrowing, Indian this conversion we could actually just load it flat
and use it directly, right?
So we could do one big flat load and have
A11 sort of giant set of asset information things here and that would
pretty much do it.
So, so let's go ahead and let's go ahead and take the Bold step of
going out and making handmade asset dot h.
And I'm just going to pull this stuff out and I'm going to put it in
here.
And again, there's no real reason or Rhyme or Reason for any of this,
in terms of why I tend to pull things out in this way.
It really just has to do with my mental ability to keep things
separated.
Sometimes I just like to have stuff come out into separate files so
that I don't look at it or think about it when I'm doing other stuff.
I kind of put it away in another file, right?
And so, there really isn't any kind of code reason as far as I'm
concerned.
If you can, remember it all, or your editor is good, unlike, you know,
Emax, maybe it has really good ability to kind of Jump Around.
Didn't think about things of you things then you could just have it
all in one CPP file like, there really is no reason for H's or
anything.
Or multiple files unless you really like them for some reason, right?
Or your source code controls merge is really lousy.
So anyway, if I go ahead and do that then in the game state, I'm sorry
in the in the transient state, right?
When we have one of these game assets, things it'll sort of store.
This stuff will expect that to be kind of loaded.
And what I'll do in the meantime is that kind of pretend that we have
a function that loads these guys in.
But that doesn't actually live these guys in, right?
So, you know, like at startup where we would go ahead and ask the, you
know, ask the platform layer to load in for us a pack file.
Like you know, directory kind of structure thing that says all the
stuff that we have instead.
I'm just going to say
Call a function that will create one as if we had loaded it in.
So that in the future, when we're ready for that, I can go ahead and
And replace it with a call to something that actually loads it.
Right?
So let's go ahead and do that.
So I want to say trance State.
What is this assets?
Right?
And so do we, we must at the moment.
Actually, because the that guy has a sub Arena, right?
That it's actually allocating from.
So at the moment, we're actually are using that.
So I think what I might do instead of that being embedded, I'm going
to go ahead and make it a little clearer about when this happens here,
right?
I'm going to go ahead and say that game assets.
There's like a pointer to it here.
And what I'm going to do is right here in trance State.
When translates getting initialized, I'm going to say,
Say that trance State.
Oops, trance State assets equals allocate game assets or something
like this.
Right.
And that'll like, load this guy up and, and it'll do the sub.
It'll do like this sub stuff here, and whatever as well, right?
So, I feel like that should probably the task stuff should probably
come first because tasks are kind of a primal private primary sort of
concept.
So those should be in there.
I feel like the high priority queue and the low priority queue should
also be primary things.
So I feel like these guys should be in
As well.
The only thing that I'm a little bit nervous about is actually, I feel
like those maybe should be things that always happen just all the time
whether or not the trance state is initialized or not, seems like a
good idea.
Meaning this sort of seems like kind of thing that should always be
copied in in case during hot loading, the cues.
Oh, but the queues can't change.
Never mind.
The cues are not saying the change during hop floating, so that's not
actually necessary.
I take it back.
All right, so yeah, that's all good.
We got the task.
That's setup will allocate the game assets.
And in order to allocate the game assets, we would need to pass in a
couple things here and maybe one of the things that we passing is how
big we want that to be.
I'm not entirely certain, but let's go ahead and take a look in here.
Let's see in game hoops and made assets that age.
So, in the CPP file, we would have something like allocate game assets
and that returns one of these guys game assets.
And that is going to take one of these Arenas.
Right because it's got to do all this stuff down.
So game assets assets, that's going to be a push struct.
That's going to go on to whatever Arena that we're told to use.
And we're going to create one of these.
We're also going to take the
Submarine out of that right?
Oops assets Arena like so and then this will probably, like I said, be
something that we actually pass in here, right?
So our trance State Arena, oops megabytes
Our translate arena is what we want this game assets to allocate from.
We want the sort of MB here to be 64.
That's going to be the size that this thing is going to use.
So here's our memory Rina, here's the thing.
What do we call this?
We call this a memory index.
I don't love that name.
But what you gonna do?
So we're going to allocate however, much it tells us to allocate as
our sort of sub arena for making space for things.
And then we need to know a couple quick things about how we're going
to do work here, right?
And so we need the trance state.
So I suppose we will have to pass that in and we need the debug
platform beat entire file for now though.
Hopefully that will be replaced with something else.
Eventually, right?
So we have to translate in there.
We got that.
So this is the transient State date.
Trance State.
And then we have the debug read entire file.
Huh.
Where is my game assets?
Where are you?
There it is.
Could remember the type of this guy?
Read entire file.
And that should just about do it.
That seems good.
All right, so let's go ahead and patch up all of the nastiness that
this is going to create having move that stuff out here.
So I'll go ahead and include handmade asset dot h.
And then, in the CPP, I will add in that handmade asset CBP and then I
got to figure out how to
You sort of calm down.
All my compiler errors and let's take a look.
Okay, here a bit Maps.
I did not actually mean to move that out yet.
So why did that get moved out because that's here in game assets,
right?
All right.
Well, that's fine.
Suppose we can move that in here for now, since it's going to become
part of this anyway, in sort of the near future,
All right, so game asset ID is now an asset type ID, right?
So that's fine asset type ID.
And let's see.
So these These are technically not going to be game asset ideas
anymore.
And in fact really, this load asset is not what we want anymore.
So really, we're going to have two of these, right?
We're going to have low bitmap.
And load sound.
Those are the two, you know, sort of not sure what you want to call
them.
Those are the two audiovisuals AV AV resources were going to have
So the sound system will call this one when it needs something and the
renderer would call this one when it needs something.
And these are not going to be passed, that they're simply going to be
passed straight up IDs right.
That are, you know, for sounds or 44, pit maps, that would be looking
into the sounds of the bitmap arrays, right?
So, that's how that actually is going to go now, I don't actually
know.
Do we move that over yet?
I don't think we did soloed asset, right?
It's in here and as is the stuff that does the work.
So what I'd like to do, I guess is go ahead and sort of grab that out
and we'll have to grab a few other things out as well.
Put that in here.
So yeah, what we want to do here is take load asset.
It is not really load asset.
Its load bitmap, right?
And it takes the Unit 32 ID, it does exactly what this does.
So this is all still totally what we want.
That's all good, right?
So nothing particularly needs to change their and then we would also
have again a very similar one that would be responsible for pulling a
sound out of the sound.
So that's all good to.
All right.
So when we do push bitmap, again this is going to be a un 32 ID,
that's some bitmap ID that we have.
We could if we wanted to try to make this a little bit more robust by
just introducing a fake type for that, I don't know if we really want
to do that or not but I can show you what that would look like.
So you know it would just be this, right?
Something this this straightforward as well.
I'm talking about.
And so this would literally just be hey to make sure that people pass
these things around typed a little bit more.
It's literally just a little bit of an extra insulation there could
compile time checking to make sure that it doesn't like cast to
something automatically and someone accidentally try to specify the
height and they end up specifying a bitmap ID and all everything.
You know goes goes pear-shaped as they say.
So we could do something like that and then in here, we would do a
load bitmap call like that.
And so that's, that's all relatively well, and good.
And in here, what instead of an asset ID, which I think, are we so
sorry?
No, we don't even have to store the ssids ever.
So, so that's what it would look like.
And then, in the load bitmap called, wait, where was that was?
I'm handmade of H.
Okay.
Those should also be moved out as well.
Those should be moved out to here like so and I can go ahead and move
these out a little bit as well.
So we have the bitmap ID there.
So when we call get bitmap or expecting a Fifth map ID, there we go.
That would get are loaded bitmaps out by the ID value, okay?
So all right, so let's keep going on the compile errors, assume we do
load asset work.
Instead here what we what this is actually this is load bitmap work,
it's not load asset work.
It specifically the thing that loads a bitmap so it's going to have a
bitmap ID.
And this is going to be low bitmap work as a function.
It goes ahead and uses one of those little bit map.
Work.
Things does it's little fancy dance here.
Debug load bitmap of course should also probably be in the asset
system.
Now, write debug little bit map so that should kind of get pulled.
Let's pull that out.
There we go.
And yeah, there is
And what else?
We need bitmap.
Header cast to come in there.
There it is.
And all right, so what stuff down a line, top down a line is just
something for doing that sort of faux alignment stuff.
So okay, so in here when we have to actually use the the IDS now we
have to access them because they're actual structs.
That's all good and tasked with memory and begin test with memory are
things that now have to actually things that actually have to be
called outside.
So I don't know where we want to put these exactly in temporary memory
complete previous rights to asking use.
I don't think that needs to be inlined in any particular way.
So I'm just going to go ahead and make these be things that we just
pull out like so.
Load asset work is now load bitmap work.
Like we said,
And work ID is going to be tidy.
So,
Map ID value.
And switch id, id that value again.
So these guys are now just asset right guy underscore as asset
underscore so that's not much of a big deal.
Load asset work is now load bitmap work.
And read entire file is getting passed in here.
What is the problem?
People problem is trance State.
It's not actually supposed to be used for their and I didn't mean to
use it but there you go.
So there we have it first tag index.
Okay.
So our pick
spring is not really a function yet, so I'm just going to get rid of
that temporarily
Our allocate render group, what does this taking the game assets,
right?
It needs to take them like that.
We've got the grass here assets.
Arrow grass is what we actually want and again these will be sort of
very soon now be transitioned over.
So this is actually kind of not that interesting but we should you
know again want to kind of get everything ported over.
So it's worth spending a little extra time to take stuff that
You know is is going to get changed and still Port it over, just so we
can have things running on it.
So
Is it Tran Arena?
Yeah.
So all of these are assets that they should be assets Arrow.
Yeah, well good.
This allocate render group still needs to be changed over and then all
of these guys who are GI underscore should be asset type underscore.
No.
No actually just asset underscore my bad.
So yeah.
Yeah.
So we have a problem here, right?
Which is because we haven't quite ported things over yet.
These are not bitmap IDs actually so that did just catch the bug that
I was saying is why you might want to introduce a bitmap ID, right?
I type that in there, not really thinking about it and that's not a
bitmap ID.
That's an asset ID which is like a family of bitmap potentially.
So yeah.
That's, you know, something about.
That's all I'm saying.
So in this particular circumstance, right?
Where we're drawing these things, I guess what we need to do is have
some way that we can translate just reporting purposes.
So we want to do something like, you know,
Get first bitmap, something like this where we can talk about you know
the game assets or something like this and we'd get the first bitmap
ID that was in there.
Again just totally for porting purposes so it would be.
So it would be something like get first bit by D and then we would
pass the the game assets, right?
So, trance state
Assets like so and this would just be something that allows us to do
that translation pretty quickly, right?
So in here, we'd have something like internal bitmap ID,
Right.
And this would be our game.
Sets and this would be whatever the game asset ID is so asset type ID.
And this would just go ahead and translate that into some sort of
bitmap.
Now, what we can do again at startup is make it so that literally,
it's just is just whatever the asset type ID is right.
We can make the mirror
That's some spelling right there so at the outset we can make it.
So it's just direct translation.
But then we will make it get better as we go, right?
And so now what we need to do is just go ahead and translate the rest
of these to that, like so,
See here, asset.
That.
There we go.
All right.
so, I think
Allocate game assets.
Must return a value.
You are correct.
It must
Oops, I guess the game was still running.
I didn't even remember that.
The game is still running but apparently it was okay.
And so now what I want to do is again in here I want to create sort of
a fake circumstance, I'll come actually back over here.
First of all, to cut out some of the other stuff that was in here,
like this asset prep stuff, this is all now stuff that should be in
here, right?
Loading the bitmaps and all that stuff.
So this kind of sets up the
Is these things which will eventually go away in the asset type table.
Now, what we're going to do in the asset type table,
Well actually guess we'll just leave that for a second.
What we'll do is we'll set up the bitmap and sound count stuff.
So we'll just say okay, the assets bitmap count is going to be equal
to the asset count and the assets bitmaps is going to be a something
that's that that's that big right?
So it can so it can hold that many things, right?
And so we just have that many assets.
Lots, they're the same.
Thing will be true of the sounds, but at the moment, we don't have any
sound.
So you have one sound.
Let's say, we don't actually have one sound but if we did, you put it
in there.
And and so that would allocate this the table for sounds and you know,
the asset type array is just the asset type array.
And we'll have to deal with that a little bit later on when we when we
get a little further, right?
All right, so I think that is sufficient, right?
I think that is sufficient.
And so right now, this is still switching on basically a totally bogus
value because like I said, these we haven't really kind of gotten to
the point where we're being a little more thoughtful about it yet, but
that's just the way it goes.
Sometimes.
Let's, what did I do here?
Bitmap count Arena.
Push array.
So, what is the Syntax for push array and made out h?
Push array Arena.
It is the count first and then the type
urgh.
What else?
We got?
Thread.
The thread thing.
Just seems to have been a complete waste of everyone's time.
I had a reason why I was going to do that.
And it really just didn't materialize.
So I think I may just say that we're going to need that and if we want
it, we'll put it back in later but it's just going to go away.
It was a stupid idea to add something before I needed it.
That's kind of the opposite of what I always say to do and
unsurprisingly.
If you have a rule, that's a good Rule.
And you don't actually follow it.
You quickly find
That you wasted your time because you can always go back and add
things in, right?
And when you go back and add things in, you know, how you actually
needed them, right?
Which is way better than trying to guess how you were going to need
them.
Which is not so useful, right?
So yeah, so that was stupid.
And we are going to Nuke it right now.
So where is thread?
Red comma, it's just getting good.
Bide everywhere it existed before it's gone.
Nobody loves it.
Nobody cares about it.
Also, I don't know why I'm even bothering to pass this around, right?
So we should probably get rid of that as well.
Because we already have this notion that we can do these Global calls
here.
So, really what we should have done, especially because this is a
debug call, is this should have just been a global variable, for debug
read entire file, right?
And then we just delete it later.
To find all the places that it was called.
And then, you know, make sure that they're gone, probably what we
should have done a long time ago.
So let's take a look, let's take a look at read entire file.
Where is everywhere that that's used and let us get rid of it.
So goodbye to you.
You're gone, that's fine.
Give a glow bitmap is just going to use this directly, right?
So this is just debug read entire file.
Let's keep on going read entire file, debug bitmap, just takes the
file name.
Now, it doesn't take that, right?
That's just kind of stupid.
So we'll get rid of this and this and this
What else?
The assets read entire file, goodbye read entire file.
Also goodbye.
See this just how it should have looked in the first place.
But sometimes you know you just sometimes you don't clean things up
until you should until you kind of like get sick of it and you're
like, you know what?
This is, just a bad idea.
Let's clean that up.
So there we go.
Specially with a debug call, it's just not worth the time right.
It's not worth spending your time passing this pointer around for no
reason.
It's a debug call, you might as well just set it.
There's really no point in not doing so right.
I can't really think of a single reason why you would do that yet.
That's what I did.
I think they're just sort of like a
I tend to not introduce Global variables very often in that sense, and
so maybe that's just like, kind of residual like you tend to not
introduce them even maybe sometimes when you should have.
But that's another issue I guess.
All right.
So anyway, keep going with that.
Read entire file.
There's one during to on file.
That's good.
That is not good.
Go away.
That is good and
It's good.
Okay, so we're back to, I think pretty good shape here.
So let's go ahead and and jump back.
Actually, let me jump back here.
So let's let's now just make sure that we set that.
So, in handmade dot CPP, when we're setting our callbacks right,
Right at the top here.
When we sweat our call backs up, we just copied them out from from
here.
Yeah, I guess I could call that debug platform read, entire file, deep
platform, read, entire file.
And that's a little nicer.
All right.
So yes set top down a line.
Something that should probably have been in here.
So let's go ahead and put that in.
And there we go.
Alright so now thread goes away.
There should be no thread.
Brad should just be eliminated entirely.
So now we've got rid of it so that's all good.
Yeah, and now, man, we just did a lot of stuff.
So we got to go here ahead here, and take a look at what we're doing.
So, those are totally wrong, right?
Those are not supposed to be going, trance State assets.
Those are just supposed to be straight up assets, right?
Wheat or sorry.
Kill rectangle.
So that's good.
Let's see what else we got going on here again, tomorrow, we got a lot
of Trance state, so let's need to get rid of that.
There we go.
All right, so that's good.
We're back up and running so that's all fine.
Nothing particularly unusual happening there.
So so yeah, so that's all good.
A lot of cleanup today.
This is this is getting good.
Alright so we've only got about 30 minutes left.
So I'd like to do is kind of push.
See if I can get to sort of the final step of flipping this thing over
into the, the new structure not for these other guys here, the red
guys yet will tackle those tomorrow but just for the other guys who
are right now, just getting translated by the ID directly.
So what I want to do is I want to make it so that these guys are
Kind of loading out of out of these.
These various file names here, this is going to be totally temporary.
Because again, there are not going to be any file names.
So yeah, so what I want to do is I want to make it now so that we can
actually set up that asset array which is this got the asset types
situation thing, right?
And so what I want to do is set up one for each of these guys and
we'll set it up just fake, right?
So we can have, you know, backdrop equals assets.
And it's going to be a crap assets.
Asset types.
Like, so, when we grab that out, we can then set that to something.
So, the asset type backdrop, you can see it has here.
What we can say is, you know, we have to obviously introduce an array
to store these other things.
We have two other things, we have asset tags and assets, right?
And so, if I go ahead and say I have assets, so a set count,
There we have it and I've got tag count.
Now, I've got sort of all of the things.
Scented in here that are, you know, that we're kind of saying our part
of this asset system.
And so I can allocate those.
I can say the assets.
Arrow assets is kind of a little bit weird you have to admit, but I'm
not sure.
Yeah, I'm not sure what else to do about it.
So we'll just leave it that way.
So I'm going to go ahead and push on an array of assets.
Here, I happen to want one per bitmap at the moment.
So I'm just going to use the bitmap count, right?
So that
Change when we actually load off disk or for now, we're just going to
use however many bitmaps we have.
That's my assets, we have.
And then the tags were not going to actually allocate it all at the
moment.
So we have tag count, I'm going to say zero and the tags are also zero
and so those will come in a little bit later.
So when we grab a backdrop, the backdrop, right, this the asset type
here, it says, how many there are, and where the first one is and
where the one passed.
Last one is, right?
So if I have a backdrop
I'm going to set the count equal to 1.
I'm going to set the first asset index equal to, you know, asset index
something, some kind of rolling value backdrop, one past less last.
Asset index is also going to be this.
So again, I'm just kind of basically making the database manually here
if that makes sense.
Because, you know, until we actually write 12 disc, I need something
to kind of sit in its place.
All right, so one pass last asset index and that index those will both
be set there and then I need to do the asset for backdrop and so I
guess I'll do it.
You know, I'll do it this way, type type type and then this will be
asset asset equals assets.
Assets plus tight, first acid and EXO will take that particular asset
this asset first High index.
Zero and one pass.
Last time is 20 and its slot ID is just going to be whatever its asset
index actually was right.
Like so so that just basically makes you know, for the backdrop and I
guess I can just go ahead and do this for all of them, right?
I can say bitmap id0 bitmap ID is less than asset count bitmap ID.
And so really, it's just I guess I should say asset ID.
For each one of these, it's just going to do.
The tape.
Setting it up 1 to 1, right?
So nothing particularly interesting happening.
They're just setting up.
Basically done Mighty dummy, tables for everything and then I guess I
don't even need, right?
I don't even need this because we know what it is, so that's all all
fine as well.
Oops, asset ID.
Past last tag index So that's its up that table.
And now in theory, we would should be able to actually implement this
function, right?
Which is to say that if we have a bitmap ID, say this is the result,
it'll be set to 0, we should probably have a null bitmap now that I
think about it and a null asset, right?
You know what I'm saying?
That seems like a good idea idea.
So something like asset.
None.
You know, I'm saying and then the bitmaps there's also like a dummy
bitmaps.
I feel like always having zero being sort of a reserve slot for like
nothing is kind of a good idea, right?
And in here we could also do when you call load bitmap, if for some
reason you're trying to load bitmap id0, it just doesn't do it.
So you know,
If not I do value and right.
So it's basically like
saying I need a valid bitmap idea.
Otherwise I'm not going to try to load the bitmap.
I'm just going to ignore you.
When you say to because we never need to load the null bitmap, right?
It's just going to be no.
So that seems good.
Yeah that all seems good so that does that the way we want.
So this starts out with the null bitmap there and then what we'll do
is we'll actually try to do the look up now.
So we'll go asset types right with the type ID.
This gives us back the asset type
And then from that asset type, we can grab the first asset very
easily.
so,
Jimmy.
So from there, we can say, you know, the asset equals the type first
asset index.
Yeah, so that's assets.
Assets.
So now we've grabbed out the first asset and then assuming that there
actually is any, you know this this thing actually has any at all
because it's possible that there were no assets of this type.
But assuming that there were any
Then the resulting bitmap value is just the assets slot ID, right?
Like, wherever that guy is
and that's it.
Let's see what happens.
Here, asset types.
What did I do?
That's supposed to do that.
Plus getting tired.
Been a long day, being a long day.
I am going to go out a limb here, pun intended and say that we have a
problem somewhere because I don't know about you, but I'm not seeing a
lot of trees there, right?
Not seeing a lot of trees there.
All right, so let's okay.
Let's go ahead and step through it and figure out what's going on.
Make sure everything is kosher.
Looks like, you know, for a type particular asset ID.
It's the count, 14 sites.
Nexus.
Whatever the ID is one pass last one.
Oh wait.
What?
Why is there a count and what doesn't make any sense?
Why would there be a count and arrange?
Does anyone know what I was thinking about when we did that?
That's that doesn't make any sense.
That's what this is.
That doesn't make any sense.
I would either have first asset in this and account.
Or not right?
Yeah, I don't know.
Alright, that's kind of dumb.
Well, pretend we didn't see that and we'll decide whether you want to
count or one passed a little bit later, we can always change between
them.
It's not too big a deal but I don't know why they were multiples of
this.
So what I wanted to do was actually this, right?
I wanted to do.
If first us at index is not equal to type one passed last I said
Index, right then get the thing out now that
Shouldn't have caused our bug at all, but that was just dumb.
So we want to get rid of that.
So this asset ID, this is so it's one asset ID that all looks good to
me.
And yeah, so that all that all looks fine.
All right, so let's go ahead and step into this.
We, let's take a look at what happens.
First of all, let's take a look at the table.
To make sure that those are reasonable.
So here is our assets.
Oops.
Assets is undefined.
Something tells me we need to switch to the debug build compiler.
Can't find anything.
Well, the debugger can't find it but probably come out until it was.
All right?
So if we take a look in here, we've got seven bitmaps and seven
assets.
That's what we wanted essentially, and in the asset table.
Oops, that's not what I wanted in the asset types table, right?
First asset index, first asset index, one pass last.
So these kind of go up as they should in the assets, First tag index.
Let's see what it looks like.
If we take a look at all of these right slot.
ID, First tag, index one passed last tag index that's all fine, and
the slot IDs look like they roughly go.
What 0 1 2 3 4 5,
6.
So they do reference the bitmaps properly.
I would think so that seems.
Okay, let's see what happens when we actually try to get one of these
guys which is get first bitmap ID.
So let's see what happens.
We coming here, we're asking for a tree.
So we pull out the one that corresponds to tree for assets in index is
3, 1 passed.
Last is for, right?
They are not equal.
So that's good.
We grab out an asset.
What is the asset?
The asset has a slot idea of 3.
So we set the result value.
So what is that actually equal?
That's a value of 3 and that is I assume what we actually would expect
it to be and it is because where they're lined up at the moment so we
go ahead and get that.
That's good.
When to push bitmap, push back bats going to call get bitmap with that
function, right?
It should return null because we haven't loaded it yet and we should
ask to load it.
So we come in here if not ID value which should be true.
Oh,
Oh yeah, P naught ID value.
It should be Heidi value.
Yeah, it has been a long day, all right.
That's probably the bug.
One would assume.
Yep.
That was the problem.
It is true.
Let's make sure we didn't have, I guess we should double check.
Make sure we don't have any weird performance things going on there
because we were running it in the other mode was nice and Zippy.
Yeah, it looks nice and Zippy.
All right, so that's good.
We got all that stuff set up.
So now, we are properly going through that in Direction, which means
now we can start to actually use that indirection on tomorrow stream,
which will be good.
So, I think that's good.
We're starting to get a little
A bit of a database structure here to things where we can kind of, you
know, essentially have our own version of, you know, a query.
If you will where we can say, hey, I need you to get me back asset
that follows this criteria, it'll do a match, it will come back to us,
and so we're getting there.
We got a little bit further to go, but we're getting there.
All right.
So why don't we go ahead and go to the Q&A?
Like so.
This way.
All right, so if anyone has any questions about what we're doing,
please go ahead and put a q: in front of it and type it in, so I can
see it.
And please keep it to stuff that we are doing so that it's kind of
something that's on topic.
And, and while I wait, I might do one really quick thing that somebody
pointed out.
Well actually, I'll just do the Q&A and if we have extra time that qao
I'll go do one more thing.
Let's see.
Abner coin Bray, you won't be using any formal database for the game.
Correct.
Why?
So the reason why is they're actually quite complicated right?
Because there are many many reasons why a formal database like
something.
That would be like a SQL database, right?
Or something would not be useful for the game and it's kind of
difficult to cover what they all are.
But
It all kind of boils down to the fact that we have a very specific way
in which we want to retrieve things.
And it's very easy for us to code that by hand in a way that is very
fast.
And to know that if we need to get more sort of acceleration out of it
that we can custom build it around the one kind of query, which that
we do.
Whereas if you use a database, that's something off the shelf.
You are constantly trying to shoehorn your access pattern into its
semantics and it really just causes all of these headaches for you
that you wouldn't otherwise have and so in a lot of the things that
database does for you like Atomic operations or you know distributed
storage and all these things we can't take advantage of.
So you're basically just accepting a huge amount of risk.
And gaining basically nothing back, right?
And so, you know, that's, that's the sort of short part of it, but the
longer part is actually a lot more in-depth.
There's, there's a lot, I actually studied databases for a long time.
I've written my own databases.
I wrote a game that runs on databases entirely, and so, I have a lot
to say about that, but it is not something that can even fit in like,
The whole QA, it would kind of have to be like a very long series of
talks about like here is what databases do and don't do and do and
don't understand and here is why they're bad for things and here is
what would be better and that sort of stuff.
But
for this particular case, I think,
A lot of that stuff is not necessary to understand.
It's not even a sorry to understand databases.
It's simply a case of them having far, too much bulk and far too much
domain.
Mismatch for the case that we're trying to do,
And so, while you could try to implement something like a weighted tag
match on top of a database, you would basically be fighting it to get
the performance.
You probably could have just gotten by writing it yourself in, not
that much time.
Like the amount of time you would probably spend dealing with it over
the car.
So the product, you know, would make it so that you really weren't you
worried, you're getting a net loss as opposed to just in planning
yourself.
So, yeah.
So this is not
Case, like sometimes on handmade hero, you know, with like the bitmap
loading code or something, right?
Sometimes I am a hero, we write something ourselves, just because the
idea is to show how to write things from scratch.
That's what we're doing.
It's educational, right?
In this case, I'm not writing this myself to be educational.
I'm writing this myself because we actually need it.
A database would not serve our purposes very well, if that makes
sense.
And it's just because there's just a really big mismatch between what
it does and what we do and how much it does and how much we need it to
do.
Is there any way I can download these episodes to watch on the go?
Yes.
Absolutely.
If you would like to download them if you go to handmade here a DOT
org, you can go to the forum's button.
And if you open up that forums page, there is a code discussion forum
here in the code discussion forum.
There is a downloading videos using BitTorrent sync, option.
And as you can see Martin's,
Is actually kind of a ninja.
He like answers, everyone's questions on the forums.
I don't actually know what he does for a living, but he must be a very
knowledgeable coder.
It seems like he's always answering people's questions before I even
see them.
But he basically set up a BitTorrent sync, and what I do is I send the
Raw videos to Martin's and he puts them on his BitTorrent sync.
So those are actually even better than the ones you can get on YouTube
because they've never been recompressed their direct recordings from
obs.
So if you do want to download them, you can do this.
I believe Martin's keeps it up to date but I don't know because I
don't actually have BitTorrent sync.
So I'm not sure what the status is but I believe that's the most
efficient way to do it.
why could you see as opposed to Java are so we're doing like basically
low-level educational programming, where we show how everything works,
and Java runs through a VM and is garbage collected and blah, blah
blah,
A boss.
So that's not really a very good language to teach how like to program
a CPU.
Java is like, too, abstract for our purposes would basically the way
to say it.
Assets include compressed, Sprite, sheets, audio video, and Bone
Riggs.
Yes, if we were going to have those, we will probably not have bone
rigs or video.
We will have Sprite sheets and audio because since our animation is
going to be procedural as much as possible.
There's never going to be an animator, actually rigging and animating
things.
We kind of have to do that in code, if that makes sense.
But if you had an animator who was making bone rigs, then they would
be an asset.
Which
You could choose to put in the asset system, you wouldn't necessarily
have to.
You could choose to make all bone Rigsby, like a resident thing that
gets loaded at startup or something if you want to.
But yeah, I mean typically I would put them in there so they can get
streamed in and out in case they're large or whatever.
Any more questions?
Well, since there are no questions at the moment, I'm going to do
something that someone brought up on the stream.
It's a very minor thing but I thought it was interesting.
So I kind of wanted to address it, that made sense.
So here we go.
So if you recall all the way back to, when we very first started
programming, like the first week or something.
What we have, you know, we've got the sort of hot code loading stuff
that works.
So you can like
You know, you don't have to reload the game to change the code, you
can just change the code while it's running and that's cool.
But we had a thing that I kind of vacillated about if you remember and
it was is initialized.
And basically what I said was, well, should we pass is initialized in?
Or should the game?
Just look at the first bite of the permanent storage and if it's like
zero then it knows that it wasn't initialize.
And so then it should set it to True, right?
And I didn't really have a strong way of doing either way.
So I was like, all right, we'll just do it this way and I think I said
like, well this way it could force the game to reinitialize or
something, or I don't know, I didn't have a good reason, one way, one
way, or the other.
What somebody pointed out on the forums?
Was the technically, we currently have a bug, it's not a bug in the
actual game, but it's a bug in our sort of debug system, right?
Which is that, since we allow allow that lie, looped live recording.
If you hit the loop live recording start before, the game has actually
even ever been called once.
Then it will record the zero doubt memory call the game, the game will
initialize itself and it will go.
Right?
Then later when you when you hit the loop point it will go back and
properly, initialize everything to Zero by loading it off of disk, but
is initialized, will still be set to true because that never gets
changed.
Which means that there's technically a bug there, which is that, you
know, the game thinks it's initialize but it wasn't and it'll crash or
something, right?
So that means it is much better to make the other architectural
decision than the one I made which is that this should not be passed
in and it should Simply Be incumbent on the game to have its own is
initialized.
That's baked into its actual data.
So that if it restores a zero doubt version
It will work, right?
So that's like way better.
So now we know and that's the reason I wanted to cover that was like,
cuz that's sort of exactly the kind of programming that I like, we had
an architect session.
We didn't know what decision to make.
So we just made one later on.
We've got actual real data about a real bug, and we haven't seen
anything else to suggest that our old way was somehow better.
So now we totally know how,
Should work.
Like we kind of know the right way now because we have a proof
positive bug that happens because of the way we chose to do it, that
we would have to work around whereas if we just done it the other
architectural way, it would have just worked, right?
So basically this
Right.
This is what we wanted and and that's way better, right?
and so yeah, so that's like a better way to do it and now I believe
I'm not 100% certain, oops, when I do there,
Actually also how did that compile?
Is initialized.
Okay?
Because it just lets it be set to 0 by default.
Yeah.
Okay, that makes sense.
All right, civil a second.
Let me get this working properly.
So this looks at memory permanent storage.
It looks to see.
If game, state is initialized, it should be if not initialized, there
we go, and off we go.
So I think that correctly, fixes the bug again, not a bug in the game,
but bug in the debug layer and I think it sort of definitive
The answer is that architectural question and so I just wanted to
bring that up.
Alright so there we go.
How on Earth do you procedurally?
Generate character movement?
You would be very surprised at how much you can do with procedural.
Movement, I will point you to a fantastic example of it.
I guess I don't know if you guys know him, there's a fellow named
David Rosen, he made.
Well, he kind of started the Humble Bundle.
I think, actually I want to say I'm with some people but he runs
wolfire games and he made like loup-garou and he like overgrowth.
He's working on now.
But if you take a look here, he gave a talk, which hopefully the GDC
Vault will let out of it.
Secret vault, long enough for you to watch it.
Oh cool.
Keep it looks like maybe he posted it.
So, if you watch this, I think that will give you an idea of just how
much animation you can do without ever actually having any real art
happen.
He uses a couple key frames but like only a very few key frames and
you'd be kind of shocked at how much animation he
Gets out of them and it looks pretty decent to.
So I would I would check that out if you're interested in it, but, you
know, we'll be doing it later on the stream.
So,
Can you run clock again?
I always forget how to run it.
Is it clock handmade code?
Is that?
So, how you do it?
I don't
I think that's it.
Yeah, we're getting up to the 10K.
Mark.
It's crawling up there.
I'm not sure how game big the game would be when it shifts.
Good question.
Hopefully not too large.
You want to try and keep your code kind of tiny, you know?
So yeah.
Have you ever used unity3d?
No, I have not.
What advice do you have for relatively new programmers, who are trying
to ditch the oop mindset and move on to things like data oriented
design and compressor oriented design.
So the advice that I would have
Depends on the person.
So, if you are somebody who learned to program and then learned
object-oriented programming and it messed you up,
then what I would say is just go back to the old way you programmed
and start again from there, that's what I did.
And it works really well and just focus on sort of
Programming the old school way, where you're the sat down and tried to
get something to work and then add on to that the compression oriented
steps where you go.
Like, okay.
Now I'm going to pull some stuff out and now I'm going to try and make
some things that like, you know, are repeatable things that I've seen
myself doing often.
I'm going to make repeatable pieces out of those, right?
But if you're somebody who never learned how to program on their own
and was taught poop first,
then I'm afraid, I don't know because I've never been in that position
myself.
I don't know what the right thing to say is.
I think what I would say is try to put the notion of the programming
language out of your brain and try to think about the computer.
What does the computer need to do to solve the problem that you have?
Right?
What are the literal steps that the CPU must do to solve the problem?
Write that as simply as possible?
That is the foundation of coding.
And everything that is structural language wise that builds up should
build up from that and not lose sight of that, right?
And so, that's just something that people who learn to program by
themselves without anyone ever telling about object-oriented
programming.
That's what they naturally did.
Because when you naturally sit down and try to learn to program and
you're just kind of like hacking around on a machine and just kind of
poking at it, you always are coming from that mindset.
When you were learning, you were like, oh, I want the computer to like
put a red dot here.
How do I do that?
And that's what you were thinking, but in your brain you weren't
thinking, like, oh, do I need to like, abstract the concept of us?
Green and red should read be an object that oh what is this?
The pixel an object.
Or is it a group of objects?
Is there a container?
Do I have to ask a factory to get me a color and that color is red,
you know, like all of those things just weren't in your head.
So you learned how to program the right way?
First?
And then what happened is, when you started getting up into things,
where your programs were pretty big, and you were like, I need ways to
manage this.
Then you like, kind of found Hooper something and it kind of ruined
everything, right.
And so, what you want to do is just try to get up to that point right
before the ooh, pruning, throw away, the oop and realize that.
That first part was all correct.
You don't need to rethink it.
You actually we're doing exactly the right thing.
The only thing that you need to do is change the way you do, your
higher level organization.
Don't think about soup instead.
Just think about how can we reuse little chunks of this code, right?
And when you start thinking about that, you just naturally, pull out
the pieces that are reusable and those pieces then can have pieces
that are pulled out that are reusable, right?
And again you just compress compress.
Compress right?
And it's not like it's magic, you can't just do it.
You have to like, practice that to and learn all of the different
ways.
You can try to compress things.
But that is the right way to do it.
And then that way you don't have to think about objects.
You don't have to think about those sorts of things.
Are all sort of, these really kind of extraneous Concepts that really
don't have that much to do with programming.
And instead, you'll see that the closely related forms the parts of
poop that worked at all, which are not many.
But the parts that did will naturally arise, you don't have to plan
for them.
You don't have to plan for objects anymore.
Objects will naturally appear because they are the pieces that as they
got compressed.
They were the thing that is sort of encapsulated the data that this
thing needed to work, right?
And so you can even arrived at the same like basically the same
program even sometimes from an object-oriented mindset and a
compression oriented mindset.
The difference is the compression, origin mindset, Took a ton of the
work out of it, right?
Right?
But most of the time you end up in very different places, but that's
good.
Because usually, the odd place is a bad place and the cop places a
good place, right?
But yet, and so, and so that's the thing.
And again, I want to emphasize that like
Object-oriented programming.
The problem with it is not the concept that there could be an object,
right?
The problem is, is the fact that you're orienting your program.
It's exactly what it says object oriented programming.
It's the object oriented the whole word, that's the problem, right?
An object may not be a problem, like it's not a problem.
If an object suddenly appears in your code, like oh my God, I gotta
get rid of this object, this is a disaster, right?
Because data gets bundled all the time, right?
That's a, you know that was before object, you're probably right.
To programming as a concept ever occurred, data got bundled and there
are algorithms which operate on the data.
And you could choose to link those two things together.
You could do all sorts of things, right?
And so the problem with object-oriented programming is the fact that
you are orienting the thinking around the objects, not the functions,
that's the problem, right?
So it's the orientation that's bad about it, not whether you end up
with an object that's a really important distinction to understand.
and because it's
I don't want people to get in this habit of thinking that, so if I
ended up with a bundle of data somehow that was bad because that's not
bad data does get bundled together.
It's a way of reducing the number of things that you have to talk
about in a particular piece of code, right?
And so, where the problem starts coming, is all this, the sort of
object orientation start where you start to say, like, oh, things have
to be objects, which are always encapsulated and they have private
member functions, which are the only things that are private, remember
functions that can operate on their private data, which are the only
things that are allowed to do that and that's important.
Like, all of that stuff is actually not important.
That's like bad ideas, right?
And so you want to get
Of those but you don't want to necessarily get rid of the concept that
you might have bundles of data.
And there's functions that kind of go long with those in the in a sort
of way that you maybe say, okay.
I'm going to sort of put this aside as a library.
So make that right?
Because C library still exists and you know, the C library is not
object oriented by any stretch of the imagination.
But it has something like a Time structure that has day month and
year.
And it has some functions that operate on that, right?
And the difference is that the
the functions are Primal and they can operate across many different
types of things.
They don't have any particular adherence to any sort of like, Oh, I'm
a friend of this, or I can only accept the private of this or, oh,
we've got to pass messages around or any of this sort of things,
right?
They just have certain bundles that they do use to talk about in those
bundles, are units of information that we found to be convenient
rather than having to pass everything in and everything out all the
time.
Right?
And so hopefully, that gives a little bit of
Effective on how those sorts of things shake out and what is and is
not important in the various models, right?
All right, looks like we're all done.
No more questions.
Looks like we got no more questions.
All right, so I will go ahead and wrap things up.
Let's close down here.
Boop.
Loop.
All right.
Let's see.
And what was our clock?
70 7400, I guess.
It's
Does it actually say how many are oh that's the actual lines of code.
I see but there's comments and other things.
So the actual total number is these like added together if you just
want actual lines, wait,
oh,
I guess I don't understand.
So why is this a 76,000 lines?
Oh, that's the speed.
That always gets me.
I'm sorry.
All right.
Never mind.
All right, now we can wrap it up.
Thank you, everyone for joining me for another episode of handmade
here.
It's been a pleasure coding with you.
As always, if you would like to follow along with the code, you can
always pre-order the game and handmade here at org and it comes to the
source code.
So, if you would like to follow along with the source code and play
around with it at home, you can always do that by pre-ordering the
game.
I upload it every
night so that you can use the latest one.
The next day.
We also have you go to hear me here at our org patreon page.
You subscribe to if you want to support the video series, there is a
forum site.
You can go to ask
Enter get ports to Mac and Linux looking to anti-deficit guide other
good things like that.
There's a tweet box, you can use if you want to know, like, when the
streams to me live at tweets, the schedule and that sort of stuff, and
then finally, we also have a little Live Now button.
That was contributed basically.
It says, when, you know, this like a countdown timer till the next
dream.
So if you're just curious, how long it's going to be two were on
again, you can always check that out too.
So check all that stuff out.
It's all pretty useful and yeah until tomorrow we'll be back here, 5
p.m.
Pacific Daylight time tomorrow.
How to do a little bit more work on the asset system.
I hope to see you all there and hopefully I will maybe do a little bit
of that tag matching.
See how that system kind of works.
So yeah we like it and make some decisions about where we want to go
from there.
So thanks everyone for joining me and until next time, happy coding.