Alright.
Hello everyone.
Welcome to handmade hero.
The show where we code a complete game live on Twitch from scratch.
No library's new engine, and
Today's kind of a good day.
I think I'll have to see how it goes.
You know, you never can count your chickens before they hatch.
Sometimes they hatch into a little stillborn chicken fetuses and
that's no good for anybody.
But what I will say is, you know, like I like I said, when we started
this I was like one of the big things that we're doing here is we're
trying to put enough code down in sort of like a primitive form that
we can tell how everything should be structured.
So that when we go
And we start writing individual pieces that are meant to be shippable
quality.
We don't fall into the standard trap of over-designing under designing
designing the wrong thing, doing all the sorts of things that happen
when you don't write the usage code first, right?
I've said that many times always write the usage code first and it's
very important.
So that's what we've been doing and the entire time that we've been
doing it.
I've been looking at some more advanced features in the entity stuff,
the low and high frequency set thing and be able to scale to large
numbers of entities and that sort of stuff.
And that's something we wanted to do but it was never quite clear.
Exactly how we could architect the code to make that work.
Nice and cleanly.
But that was okay for me.
Because like I said, the important thing is to get enough code down
that you can see and slowly over time, good solutions to how you want
to do.
Things architectural e kind of work their way up from the code that
you have down there and
It's really just a matter of sticking it through and, and trying doing
enough sort of trying of things that you want to have to accomplish to
get to the point where you can actually do it.
And so, while after the stream last night, I was lying in bed and
normally I don't I'm not super good at falling asleep.
So typically, what happens as I like go to bed and then I'll just get
up like 30 minutes later because it's pretty clear that I'm not going
to fall asleep and then I'll do some stuff for a while, and then I'll
go back and try to fall asleep again later.
So, I was lying in bed.
And what I realized is, I finally realized.
I think the crucial thing that with the high and low frequency stuff
that can make it into a nice clean architecture.
And so, I want to talk a little bit about that.
because I was pretty psyched that's like yes, this is the thing that
I've been waiting to sort of
See click in a good way.
So what I realized is, and what day are we here on handmade here?
We're day 63.
So what I realized here on day 63, right, well, I guess this was a 62
when I realized it but I realized we have two constraints that are
coming together, right?
We have two constraints, the constraints are number one, we want a
Extremely large world, right?
So we want to be able to handle worlds that are
Large that floating Point accuracy would immediately degrade if you
were to try to store them all as single floats, right?
So we wanted to say that our engine could support that again.
Not because any into particular engine has to support that, but
rather, because we want to show how you handle it in code because it
is something that does come up.
If you want to do large worlds and you want to do them, right?
So I wanted to put that in there.
We had another thing which is extremely large, entity counts, right?
So we basically have two scalability things we want to talk about one
is about float Precision, right?
And one is about basically about processing power, if you will.
Right, this is about processing power.
The problem with extremely large worlds, is that we will run out of
precision in a 32-bit float, to deal with them if we just did
everything in float and pretend said, whatever anything goes, the
problem with extremely large entity counts is that we don't have
enough processing power to, basically do to just write code where we
write the code for every entity.
And then, just run all the entities in the world all the time that
will never scale to very large, enemy counts.
So we have two competing concerns here.
And what I realized is I was not thinking about them together.
I was not thinking about how they related to each other, I was
implicitly dealing with their intersection but I wasn't thinking about
it.
Overtly.
And so what I realized is that if you think about it, overtly I think
that shows the way to doing the good architecture that handles both of
these things, which is our goal in this design process, right?
So let's talk about that.
What does this float Precision thing?
Make us do if we don't want to just use doubles, if we don't want,
just go to 64-bit floating-point, which there's a number of reasons we
don't want to do.
Either half as fast, be there's platforms that don't support them at
all natively.
See we don't actually necessarily even need that much Precision blah
blah, blah, blah.
There's all sorts of reasons why it might not be a good idea to
strictly go to doubles, right?
But the real big
Just a performance, right?
We know that we're going to be half as fast if we don't, if we did
that.
So we'd like to make sure that most of all of our stuff that's
happening, you know, all of the computations that we do for everything
we'd like to be able to do those at full speed, we'd like to be able
to do them in float, so that we can be fully for wide on 8 wide, or 16
wide, and 70.
Instead of too wide for wider, 8 wide on Sunday, right?
So we get basically twice the performance of, for, in float.
So, we want to do is we want to be able to do, we want to be able to
To live in that world, right, want to be a live in that world, but
what that means is that whenever we do our calculations, if we're
doing everything in float, we have to be doing it around some origin
Point.
That's local, right?
So, what that means is if we have people everywhere in the world,
right?
And this is
You this is the giant world.
Let's say right, this is the giant world, if we're looking at the
giant world and we say that we have all these entities that are like
over here, right?
And we want to talk about how they work in order to process them.
All, what we do is we first pick a local origin
and what we were using was the camera for this in our current code,
right?
We would take the camera and we just figure out where everyone was
relative to the camera, right?
So if you imagine what happens, we've taking a little slice of the
world, right?
And we're saying, wherever the camera is, you know, we just say where
the entities are relative to that camera and then because we know
that's a very small neighborhood.
Right?
That's only, you know, a few metres across.
We're talking about like, a 50 meter by 50 meter square, right?
Whereas, this might be like hundreds of
Is there something?
You know, I don't remember what we calculated it, but, you know, this
is huge and this is Tiny, this is not a problem for float Precision,
we have plenty of precision here and we could do our calculations and
Float.
No problem.
Right?
So what this implies is that we're always doing these calculations
right in a local neighborhood.
Okay.
And so that's what led us to the whole.
We had low frequency and we had high frequency entities, right?
And what we were doing there is we were saying we were storing
basically, like an extended detail version of where the entity was
that involved tile positions, right?
Like a tile, chunk position and at offset, right?
So we were basically storing and and alternatively like again, if we
were on machines, that support doubles, we could store doubles here,
but basically, we had like the slow version of where people were were
in this low entity, right?
But the High version of where they were,
Just in a vector to write.
It was a vector to float.
So basically this gets translated to this and we would do our
calculations here but then we kept having we I mean, I don't even want
to say problems necessarily, but you could tell even just from an
early standpoint that there were just a lot of fussing involved in us
having to think about which state we were talking about the, whether
it was this position or that position and keeping these two things in
sync and all this other nonsense.
And it was really just a drag on the
The coating, right?
So so there's that but there's another problem and there's a problem
that we hadn't actually gotten to yet but that we sort of were setting
up to deal with which is the scaling to extremely large, entity counts
and basically what that was was saying.
Okay, so there's low frequency entities and high frequency entities,
right?
The all of the entities are always exist in the loaf.
Frequency set essentially their the data that actually describes the
entity and then there's this high frequency version of The Entity that
we actually use for.
It has some additional stuff in it, right?
And that's how we were handling this and when I said was well we're
going to want to be able to do processing on these low entities
because we want things in the world to keep happening, even when
you're not around it, so we want to be able to sort of have
People who are maybe like the example I gave was, you know let's say
there's like a creature or a guy who's like, go to go somewhere take
something from a location and bring it back, you know, I don't know to
his lair or something.
Who knows there's something going on out here and we want that to kind
of keep going on it, because it might be nice.
Give the world a nice emergent.
Feel when the player comes upon this and sees that, like, all of the
apples are missing from here, and they go to this little apple thief
and he's got all these apples in his back room or, I don't know
picking stupid things, but you know what I mean?
You want to be
Able to see that sort of thing happen.
And furthermore, if you came right here and watch, you would see this
guy, come back carrying an apple and all that sort of stuff, right?
We want to support those kinds of things because again, hard to
program Ergo, we want to show it on the stream because the whole point
here is to learn how to do Advanced programming techniques.
So what I said was, well, we'll have the low frequency set, and then
what we'll do is, we'll just operate on this low frequency set at a
lower rate.
And then the high frequency set will be where all the magic happens.
So things that are clothes that are in the camera view, get the
high-frequency detail and so on so forth, right?
But in the back of my head, I was really worried about this because
I'm like, well now we have to write every entities code twice, right?
We have to write like code that works for when they're high frequency
entities and code that works for the low phrase.
Like that doesn't sound very good.
I don't really know what to do about that.
You know, just it seems like there's going to be a lot of work there
and it just sounded bad, right?
So that was worrying me as well.
So all of this stuff was kind of built up.
So, what I realized when I started with sort of not even really
thinking about it or just kind of like must have been a background
process in the brain.
Was I realized that that was exactly the wrong way to think about the
low-frequency entities, right thinking of range, based processing of
them.
I was just playing dumb that was dumb.
There was really no reason to think about them in terms of index
ranges, right?
You remember?
I even set it on the stream.
I was like, let's go ahead and we'll just process like a thousand of
them at a time or something, right?
There's no that doesn't make any sense.
Why would you do that?
That is what would cause you to have to write things that operate
directly on the low entities instead of doing that.
Why not just basically have a second camera
I have a second camera that just moves around the world, simulating
the pieces of the world in chunks, right?
So that every frame you do to camera things basically, right?
You do the ones for where you can see, which should always be
simulated and then periodically at a lower frequency, you know, you
will basically sweep through all the other parts of the world,
focusing, the camera on them.
The virtual camera, in this case, map, all the things into the high
entity space, do the processing map them back to love.
Low, right?
So basically what that means is now we can get rid of the concept of
Operating on a low entity at all right.
You will never touch a low entity.
There's never any reason to write.
It's strictly a storage format, which is what I kind of wanted when I
started.
But I just couldn't figure out how to do because of this dumb thing,
right?
It's like I would have rather had it so that, you know, I would rather
have always thought of low entities as just like a compressed or like
an archival format.
Right from my high ones, they just they map in here and they stick
sleep in this state.
Right.
And then they mapped back.
That's how we would do it in a normal game, that wasn't trying to
simulate things anywhere, right?
That was there was doing something simpler than what we're trying to
do.
Here, we just compress the high entities or map, the high-end, he's
back into here you know, and some of its not compressive, sometimes
actually expansion like it's storing it in this more detailed format
for the position, for example.
Right.
But in general you know I'm saying, we archive them to low and then we
bring them back from low into High when they come back on the screen,
that's what we would normally do.
And so the thing that was was causing me all the problems though was I
was like, we can't
Do that because we want them to still be live.
Well we can all we have to do is just always use Regional processing.
I don't know why I think of it before but that's just the way
programming work.
So it's the reason that I say to always do things by writing the code
first is because you need to give yourself the time to realize things,
they're always going to be obvious in hindsight.
But if you don't get the stuff out on the page, right?
Or in the editor, I should say.
And you don't have some time to look at how it's actually working.
In reality, you're never going to be
to have those insights because you just don't have the information you
need.
And so this leads us to what I think is a very good way of structuring
this.
And we're going to start today.
I don't think we'll finish because we have some restructuring to do.
But basically what it's going to be is you never touch low entities,
solo enemies are narrow sir, there are storage format only
Right, so what happens is?
We have a New Concept basically.
I don't know exact what we'll call this right, but will basically say
there's a simulation region, okay?
And again, this is exactly what I was talking about.
When I say engine architecture, you do it by seeing how things go and
then you pull up from there.
And that's exactly what we're doing.
We're looking at what happened and we're going on.
Ah, now I can finally see how things are supposed to work.
Now, I can really see a true, a very important piece of my
architecture.
Come to fruition.
So what we'll do is we'll have a thing called a simulation region.
A simulation region is a rectangle in space just like we sort of had
already with the camera, right?
But it's completely self-contained in the code.
So it stores a high entity list for itself, right?
It stores its bounds and it's got a very well-defined beginning and
ending right in time in the code.
So we start it.
We map all of the entities in too high for that.
We run the processing and then we map them all back.
Too low, right?
So, basically, this is an entirely self-contained thing in the code.
Simulation region, you can do them anywhere you want, and you can do
as many of them as you want.
And they come and they go, right?
They never persist across a frame, boundary ever.
Right.
And if we ever wanted them to persist across the frame boundary, that
would be an optimization.
So basically that would be something we'd add after the fact.
So that means now, we don't have to write two pieces of code, all the
pieces of code.
For simulation always happen.
Exactly the same way, right?
Always.
Always exactly the same so that totally symbolizes our life quite a
bit and gives us one of our key Architectural Components assuming
again, that it works out when we go try it.
And so this is basically like this is a key component, right here.
That'll make sense.
Hopefully so again, not terribly different from what we've been doing.
It's very similar, but it organizes all of the pieces properly.
So that the problems that we were having with our current system,
don't happen anymore, right?
And basically no one ever looks like we have these problems with
moving entities, writing back to below and all this other stuff.
All of that is now totally gone because everything only happens on
high detail entities and only at the very end are things all written
back to low as a storage format only and I really like that because
that to me seems really, really pretty darn good.
Okay.
Now there's one thing I want to mention which is is like sort of the
the slight wrinkle which has nothing to do with this.
Exactly we would have had it in the other system as well.
But something that's want to kind of point out because I think we got
a design in some, what's the word for it?
Affordances for it.
One thing that we didn't never actually deal dealt with and it I think
we can do deal with it pretty easily.
Now, is that in the past when we map things into our active region,
let's say this is the active region here.
This dotted line, then we have entities right in the world.
Here are some entities in the world and here are some more enemies in
the world.
If we simulate all of the entities in this region, we have a problem
and that is that entities near the boundary may be allowed to move
outside of the boundary because on their time step they be able to
move across that boundary.
And in Crossing that boundary right?
They will not Collision detect with any things that were outside of
the boundary and entity that was right here or right here.
Would never have been brought into the high frequency set because it's
outside of that boundary.
So we need to be able to do is we need to be able to say okay
simulation actually happens inside a conservative boundary that is
less than the one frame movement distance away.
I'm sorry.
It's more than the one frame distance movement away from a secondary
boundary which is where everything gets pulled in.
So this outer boundary is basically the like the the, the high
boundary.
And this is like the Sim boundary.
So things in here, get Sims things in here, get pulled in, but not
So they're just standing there as colliders in case something tries to
go out there and hit one of them right.
But they themselves are not allowed to move.
Right?
At least not in this simulation pass.
Does that make sense?
They could still be active entities, and they still could be simulated
by something that went and did another simulation region that was
right here or something like this, right?
But what we want to do, is make sure that we essentially don't ever
have that case, where something could go outside of where it needs to
go, right?
Where it's allowed to go.
So there's, there's nothing to think about.
Alright, so, I hope that all makes sense, I'm going to go ahead and
start the process of making that happen.
Like I said, that's going to take a little bit of reorganization,
which tends to be a little slow when we do it on the stream because I,
as I explain things, right, there's a lot of text moving around and
doing stuff that, that maybe makes things a little slower than it
would be.
If we were just going to reorganize it flat out.
But even so, I mean, even when you're just programming down in a
stream, it does take a while to do all the texts shuffling and stuff.
That's necessary.
Inside a reorganization, right?
So that's that's worth, that's worth noting.
It's never really that fast to do.
So it's gonna take a little time but I think it's definitely the right
thing to do.
So I'm going to go ahead and just flat-out.
Start that process, get us into position that does exactly what I just
said because we already have all the usage code written essentially
that should guide us and allow us to know that we have all the stuff
that we need to support it.
So
First things first, let's go ahead and say that we have handmade
simulation region.
I like that name.
It seems good enough to me and so we have a handmade simulation
region.
Well, I actually need to call it handmade.
Simulation recent, simulation region will be fine.
I guess I could call it the same region, but I don't know.
It's okay.
All right, all right, all right, we'll call up some will call.
It said, we'll call some reason.
No, need to introduce extra characters for no real reason.
So let's call it.
Made some region.
That's good enough.
All right, structs Tim region and assume region is going to what I'm
going to do bases in a move.
The stuff that used to be fast and loose and kind of always existing
in two places on a move that over in the simulation region.
So basically this over here is going to look like that, right?
And I'm going to call these just flat-out entities because
everything's going to work on these entities primarily, right?
So we're going to have an entity count and then we're going to have an
end of the array, right?
And that's going to be that's going to
Look like this.
Now I'm going to get rid of this cap here, this entity cap, I'm going
to say that we just have a pointer and the pointer points to however
many is in this entity count structure, right?
And I might say that, we also have a Max entity count that can exist
here.
So, maybe there's some Headroom on this.
When we actually make it, I'm not sure that we even need that, but
we'll just leave that there for now.
Okay.
so,
That's our Sim region.
None of these other things are particularly relevant to the same
region, but now what we know is we kind of have this, we've got this
sort of set camera call and what I'm going to do is I'm going to say
that this is going to get broken up now, right?
So, instead of a thing that goes through and looks, whether things
need to get mapped out of the high frequency space into a low
frequency space, this offset and check frequency by area thing, that's
now no longer on the table.
Right.
Everyone gets mapped in and out of the high frequency space every
frame.
That's just how we're going to do it.
And like I said, if it turns out that that's too slow, then what we'll
do is, we'll go ahead and will optimize it later as a separate thing
that we do.
But there's no sense in basically, premature optimizing that, at this
point.
So,
In our Sim reason.
What I want to do is take that offset and check frequency by area of
call.
Right offset and check tickets in by Eric Hall and take a look at
that.
And you can see that basically all that does was it was moving things.
Packing things into low entities as they went.
But that's really, you know, we're it's really pretty basic.
So really all we have to do is just make, I don't even really need to
cut and paste that, right?
It's super, super simple.
There's really nothing to it.
All we're doing.
Here is saying
Like end simulation region or something, right?
And some region.
I guess you could just call it n Sim, right?
And that takes the same region.
Okay, and then when I do that NSM, I'm going to Loop through all the
entity count, you know, I'm going to take this, I'm going to say for
each entity, right?
So I've got an empty index here for each entity.
That's in the region.
I want to map that entity out and into the low space, right?
So right here, again, we'd have that high entity, right?
And I guess we don't call them high these anymore.
They're just going to be entities.
So then we have an entity, right?
Like so.
That's going to point to this guy is going to point to the entities
that are in the region and each time through I'm going to advance that
pointer, right?
And so what we do each time through here is we just map The Entity
into the low space, right?
So basically what we're going to do here is I don't know what we'll
call this is that.
Exactly, but I guess we'll say, we'll say store entity, right?
Or something like that.
So we'll have low density and store energy.
I guess what we call them will load them out of the sort of that back
in store and then we'll store them back.
To it.
So we're going to store this entity out.
And so what we would need to know there is where were storing.
The end of the two will assume right now that that's stored in the
entity structure itself because that seems logical, right?
So we'll just do a store, entity will write that in a second that
maybe something we actually right here, in fact, we could just say
store entity and the reason that we don't really need a function for
it is because I'm thinking that, like I said, we will probably want to
do it so that you
Early, never ever ever translate between high low frequencies, any of
that stuff manually ever.
There's just a controlled load and store.
It could only happen in one place and it happens exactly the same way
every time.
So it might just happen right on in here, right?
So whatever we're going to call that in a second.
So then we also have the same thing here, right?
Which is begin Sim and that's again it's going to take a SIM region or
I guess rather.
What it probably would do is return a Sim region, so you'll do a begin
Sim.
You get a sim region back then you can do your Sim on that same region
when you're done, you end.
Right makes sense makes sense.
So inside begins him.
What we would be doing here is we would be doing the stuff that was
happening in this in this call right here, I like how we said do this
in terms of Tau chunks for it to do, which is exactly what we did.
So we want to do here again, is take this code that we already wrote,
that just looks at sort of that region in
Little partition.
It says water all the entities in it.
And any of those entities that basically fall within the camera
balance are going to, you know we're going to find them are going to
pull them out.
And so we can do here is say that.
When you do your begin Sam, you just passed in that rectangle,
whatever, the rectangular trying Sim, right?
So this is the bounds of the region.
You pass that to begin, Sim and then that's what we use for
everything, right?
So camera bounds is now just region bounds, right?
Region, bounds?
Like so and the region bounds, I guess we need to also, give you what
it's centered around because that needs to be one of those, those
higher frequency positions, right?
That needs to be one of the more specific things, right?
So, this is the Region Center and that's the region bounds like
so-and-so.
Camera p is just reading center, right?
So there we go.
So we go ahead and we Loop through all of these things.
We find all of the entities that are relevant to us, and then we're
going to go ahead and map them out.
This also means that now, the low entities, right?
We no longer have the double pointer situation which is really good.
We do longer have low and he's pointing to highs and highs back to
lows.
We only have entities that point back to their storage location,
right?
Because that's something that we presumably always want.
To be able to do correctly, right?
Furthermore things are gonna get even better people.
They're going to get even better.
Just you wait, I can see it.
Coming down the pipe.
I can see it.
Can you see it?
Yeah, maybe you can't see.
It doesn't matter.
It's there.
All right.
Anyway,
so if we go ahead through here and we say all right we've got our low
entity, it no longer has to point to the high today because that's not
I haven't any more, right?
And then we no longer need this entity structure because you're only
ever going to be dealing with one or the other kind of entity.
I believe, I think we're going to want to do that, so that you just
everything kind of gets moved up into the high entity.
I'm not sure exactly how we'll handle that.
For now we're going to have to think about that a little bit more, so
this will go away eventually but I think I'm going to leave it just
for a little bit because as we sort of Port the code over, I don't
want to go too far too fast.
Alright, so basically the low entity indexes we now no longer have to
check to see or anything, whether they need to be moved in because
everyone needs to get moved in because no one's in the state yet,
right?
So what we need to do is we need to be able to sort of pull those guys
in.
And so what we're going to do here, I don't know exactly one of the
things is when we do this begin Sim it's a little unclear.
How we exactly want to divide up the memory that we're using because I
don't know how much we care about whether the entity array is
continuous or not.
It's something that and we don't know exactly how we're going to
process these.
So I'm not going to think too hard about that yet but later on because
we want this to be relatively, we want this code to be relatively fast
because once you build one of these begin Sims,
I want all the code that happens inside it to be fast.
We may have to think about how we're going to actually place these
things in memory, but for right now, I'm not think about that too
much.
All right, so we go through the end of the indexes.
We grab out where they are, we then have a pointer to the low.
And so, then right here what we need to do is we need to add it into
the to to the the same reagent, right?
So this would basically add a little entity to the same region will
call that.
I guess I'll just call that same for.
Now, I'll call some reach, call some region and that I guess we need
to do the check of the camera space p as well.
So this actually doesn't
Happen.
But this does because we don't want to move it into anything that's
not really in the camera region, so we'll do that.
And so, there we go.
So that's the check right there.
If it's in the rectangle, will add it in and we already know where the
cameras face p is.
So I feel like that should happen here as well, right?
So, that's where that is in camera space.
So that looks good.
So that is allows us to add an entity to it.
So it'll go a Danity.
like so, and I think that's about
It for that function for now.
All right.
So adding these going to take a SIM region
And it's going to add a new entity to the end here, right?
So for now we're going to do an assertion on this or I guess we'll do
an if statement like so.
Will do an if to verify that we have enough room.
So we want to make sure that the The Entity count is less than how
many we're allowed to store.
I like I said, later, we might allow this to be more flexible.
We'll see.
We'll see how I feel.
Later on.
But assuming we're good to go there, I'm going to do an invalid code
path here as well.
Just so we know that it'll assert when it hit so we can see whether
we're overflowing or cap.
So we'll go ahead and do the fact that the entities Sim region
entities.
So
So basically, we're going to do is going to use a new entity from that
any list after making sure that we've got enough, I'm sorry, entity
array, and then that will go ahead and add the end of the.
Now, we've got the low entity, the low compressed version of him here.
I guess what I probably should do to is this should be a fairly
simplistic, you know, relatively straightforward entity, I don't know
you.
We could call this a Sim entity as well.
Maybe I should just to differentiate it.
I like that.
I like that a lot.
So I think maybe we'll call that a same entity.
Yeah, okay, okay, that's good.
So let's call that a Sim entity and more turn that from here as well,
right?
Same entity.
And we will grab it like that so that will add it in a tea, but it
won't do anything particular to it.
I'm going to clear it for now, like I said, I'm not sure whether we
actually care about that too much to do Casey.
See what we want to do about clearing policy when the entity system is
more fleshed out.
But for now, I'd like to clear 20 just to avoid bugs of that nature
because that way we know.
Everything is always every time you make it entities, always cleared
to a good initial State.
What I also could do is just clear out the whole array at startup.
I don't know.
We'll think about that.
But anyway, so when we get new entities, this will get basically give
them back to us and that's fine.
So the entities get added in there and I think that's really all we
need to do for that for now.
And then in the case, where you've got an entity that just
You a new entity, in the case where you're trying to add an entity in
a slightly more verbose fashion where you've got both the the low
entity version, right?
And so I guess I don't know we're going to call this I think we're
going to call us a storage on any probably, right?
And we could call it a whirl density.
We could have similarities and World entities.
So world of these are ones that are stored out in the world thing.
I'm not sure exactly what they should be called sin.
Entity sounds good to me, because the entity that's involved in a
simulation region that makes sense, World entity, maybe is the right
thing.
Because that's what it is.
We have the world storage.
We could change the name of that, instead of making it a world, we
could call that like spatial part, I don't know.
We're going to call it World Manatee for now.
So will basically say this is the source entity and this is going to
be the death penalty.
So basically we have a death entity that's that's going to get
received from here and assuming that we get one, we're going to say,
okay map.
Or like a convert the store identity to a simulation into tea.
Right?
So I don't know.
Yeah, it's still.
It's I think storage is the right thing because that's what I used
here when I was talking about it.
So it's going to call a store identity.
I like that and then I could call that store it as well.
Maybe.
Yeah.
Source is good.
All right, so let's call it.
Let's let's do it like that.
And then we also note here that that are oops, typo.
We also know Kira that our entity is potentially going to have a
physician passed to it, right?
Like we did here when you're creating one out of
No out of whole cloth like that, we know that you're going to have a
world position for him as well, right?
And so that's going to be okay, sorry that you shouldn't say World
position, a simulation position because you've already done the check
to see whether they should move in.
So you've already got that, right?
And so, basically, his simulation position is just going to get set
directly and doesn't have to be computed, right?
So that seems like a good idea.
What I could do is make this an address, do something like that and
then make this a pointer like so.
And then I could say you know if we know what it is, then great, if we
don't know what it is, then we go ahead and build it and that would
just be doing it like this, right?
Let's get cameras they speak.
Now the problem is get camera, space p is actually not what we want
anymore either because we don't have a concept of a camera anymore.
I mean we do outside of this but the
Region itself, basically tracks where it thinks it is right.
It's got these two parameters baked into it, right?
There's the Region Center and the region Bounds at that.
All right.
Excuse me.
So we want that to actually be, we want, we want the Region Center and
bounced to actually be the things that are used.
Not any kind of a notion of a camera.
So get camera space p really should never be happening anymore.
Get camera, space p.
It's just a special case.
So we want to we want to kind of get rid of that and say all right
instead of gets cameras paste P.
What we've got here is something else, we've basically got something
that's like get region space p.
If you will, we have get region.
Space p.
And that just takes a Sim region, right?
Like so
And it takes whatever that store identity is.
and,
And that's will do the conversion.
So it does the diff it.
Does that subtraction?
We're going to need the world pointer here.
So I'm going to assume that the the Sim it set.
The same region will store a pointer to that world.
So I can grab it.
It will go ahead and use its pee now, right.
It's what do we call that it's center, right?
Or I should,
Use the word origin because that's kind of a little bit better origin
at the same region and that should basically give us what we want to
have happen.
So there we go.
We'll need to store again in the same region will need to store the
world so that we can get back to it.
So when we call begin Sim, we're going to need to use that world
parameter here, right?
So we're going to have a SIM region world and we're going to have to
set these them region.
Origin, equals origin Sim region bounds equals bounds like so on.
There we go.
Lovely.
So that looks reasonable, right?
And now we have a get region space p which is exactly what we want.
So we can pass the same region to it'll get a 3D space V and down
here, that same thing can be used instead of camera space p.
So now this can just use some region origin, so so region origin and
then Min corner for the same reason bounds.
Okay.
And similarly, in here, we should be able to do some region origin and
this should be get region, space key.
And that should be able to face take the read the same region there
and this is Sims case P, right?
What did I actually?
Region space.
It really shouldn't be called region space.
It's really be called Sim Space.
Probably write some space key sounds a little bit better.
So let's say that get-get region space is going to be gets in space
like that a little bit better.
Alright, so that seems good.
Everything seems reasonable there.
Lovely.
And so, what we're going to need now is I guess we're going to need to
sort of just do some, some sort of Smashing here to smash everything
back into a reasonable State.
Here is the stuff that we know we needed before on here.
So, this will be a storage index and this is basically something that
tells us where this entity came from, right.
This is all relative to the same region but we don't need to comment
that really as much anymore, because, it's now it's much much clearer.
We can put some comments at the top potentially the talk about that a
little bit more and so, there we go.
Now Artie Bob is an animation thing that I don't think we want to have
any more.
But what is this?
Does mean very clearly.
And this was sort of something that probably should have happened
originally
Generally.
Anyway, which is that velocity?
Is now something that has to be stored across frame boundaries?
Obviously velocity is something that has to be stored in the low
entity as well, right?
So, in the low entity,
In order for things to persist we need to keep that velocity around so
that's going to go in there.
Hi Ade basically goes away entirely.
That's just gone.
So our similarity has this information in it.
Yeah.
That that it wouldn't otherwise if needed
Same with the facing Direction.
And even I guess T-Bob for now,
Can go out into the low entity because the low energy is really, we're
going to be focusing all of our attention in terms of splitting things
up.
Anyway.
So that seems pretty fine, pretty, pretty good to me.
So we've got our z and d z.
This this chunks, the this stuff we're going to have to clean up a
little bit because we did add Vector 3 eventually.
But we've never really quite gotten around to handling Z in a logical
way.
We're going to postpone that for now again because one thing at a time
So that's all good.
Now we need to do is start actually making this work a little bit
more.
Straightforwardly by cleaning up the code that we do have and making
it work within these confines.
Now, one thing I do need to do is I need to be able to actually
allocate one of these Sim regions.
Right?
And so what I'm going to do is I'm going to for the first time in
introduced the concept of a transient of the of the transient stack,
basically?
And so that's something that I think we probably won't have time to do
today.
So I'm just going to leave it as a placeholder and then we'll do it,
we'll do it tomorrow.
So if I go ahead here and I say we've got our memory Arenas right?
I'm going to say that we will have some way of doing this a little bit
more fancy late in tomorrow.
So we're going to say here that we based have a memory Arena which is
the simmer Ena and later on we're going to have a more stronger notion
of where that's coming from.
For now we're just going to use that.
and so, from the simmer Rena, we are going to allocate
The space that we need to store the simulation system.
So what we need to do here is we just need to do a push struct right?
On the simmer Rena.
Excuse me to push our Sim region.
Like so we need to initialize vatsim.
Oops, region.
We need to initialize the, The Entity bounce for that, right?
So we need the entities, some region.
Mac said we count.
We The Entity count itself, which we want to start at zero and I'll go
ahead and move these into the order.
They're actually in.
So as world origin, bounce back some account edit account.
So the max entity count for now, we'll set up something High to do,
Casey need to be more specific about entity counts.
In fact, this could actually be very high because this is a transient
problem.
Is anything we could really set this extremely high.
We're using it very large scratch space basically.
So we could, we could think about that a little bit later.
How exactly we want to, we want to deal with that process, basically.
And then are entities.
We should there's there was, I believe, was there already a push a
reg.
Yes, there was a push array.
So what we can do is we can go ahead and get our way of entities as
well.
So there we go.
See, Marina.
The count is going to be that Mack sennett account right in a thing,
it is a semantic, right?
So that grabs all of those entities, and then when we're done here,
what will basically do is, you know, we'll assume that this Arena
releases the memory that we've used.
So, we basically grab all the memory up front, we do all the
processing and then we push it away.
That makes sense, and we'll have to deal with that later.
So
I'm, there we go.
What we do our enzyme, we just need to do the store back to low, which
at the moment, I guess we can actually Implement because we already
have the code for it.
It's a make entity low-frequency, right?
That's this code right here.
And so if I just go ahead and add that in, you can just grab the parts
of it that we wanted.
Essentially we already know what the
We already know that we don't care about the high frequency index at
all.
All we care about is the low frequency Index, right?
And so that low-frequency index is going to be, whatever, was in this
storage Index right here, right?
So we basically have that entity storage index tells us where the
Senate he's going to go.
Nothing scuse me.
I'm still sick as often.
I am on the Stream.
Can't stop programming, just cause you're sick.
You gotta keep you gotta power through.
I mean, if you're really sick then don't program if you're really
really sick but you know, I'm certainly well enough to program it that
way.
All right, so I grab my editi here.
Mmm.
Let's take a look at this here.
We've got the region and account.
We're going through envies.
That's what I want.
We have the storage index.
So the storage index is based going to put these back into that low
entity array, right?
And so, where we have that was actually in the game state, which is
not necessarily where I would necessarily like them to be.
I think those maybe she would be better served now that I think about
it in the world but
We can talk about that later, let's see to do, maybe don't take a game
State here.
Low entities should be stored in the world, something like that, but
for now we'll go ahead and do that.
So, in order to get the low energy out, right?
We've got the low energy which we're going to change the name of I
guess to store identity, right?
So, the stored
is going to be the game state store identities, for now,
Something like this, we're going to go ahead and grab those out like
so.
You know what?
I guess before I change the name, I guess I could do store it into T's
just still low entity just to make the porting a little easier at
first, and we'll just make that up to do.
Do Casey change the name?
Stored entity.
All right, so we grabbed the store identity, we don't care about this.
That was some debug code.
We don't care about any of this.
So I guess we didn't in that code.
We didn't actually do the packing there and make entity low frequency.
We didn't actually ever update that code.
So, this is just kind of garbage code, really?
It doesn't even work anymore, so that's no good.
Now, the entity pairs goes away because entities are no longer paired
in that sense.
Use only a pointer back in One Direction so they don't really get
validated.
And, and for sanity into high doesn't make any sense.
Either offset and check frequency by
We got rid of because we now have that that concept you never actually
do move things out.
So that's fine.
So that goes away.
So that's good.
Make any high frequency.
We already essentially did is the camera space p part, which is done.
So that goes away as well.
This is the part that we actually well, no, we don't need that either.
Yeah, we don't need that.
Either really because we've already replaced that entirely as well as
all of this.
So, yeah.
So that's good.
We don't really need any of this all goes away.
It's all toasted at this point, add familiar.
So, what we need to do now is, it's this part right here, change
entity location is really the part that we care about.
So that was the thing that I was looking for, for this code to give me
and it turned out that code have nothing to do with it.
So what I want to do here is as we spend through them, this is the
part that actually to update.
We have a to do here which is basically like, you know, Save State
back to the store identity, but right now, once High entities
Do state decompression.
But for right now, I suppose we don't really have that now.
Maybe what we could do is we could say that all of the things exist in
the same entity as well.
That's kind of an interesting idea.
I'm not sure you want to take that step yet.
So we'll just say that that's going to change a little bit later on.
All right, so when we change entity location, we pass all the same
stuff for the game State.
And now this right here is that stored index.
So, this is the storage and do.
Of the entity, right?
We have that low version of him, we know where he is because that's
that's just that and then we have his new position is basically going
to be whatever we derive from that, excuse me.
From that chunk space mapping.
So what we'll do is we'll take that new paint that same set of calls
here.
And now it's not going to be the cameras location anymore.
Again, it's the Region's location that were mapping around and then we
have that offset from that stored in our entity, which is just the P,
so that just works, right?
Okay.
So that all looks good.
Pretty straightforward, pretty straightforward, so that's good.
And now set camera.
Pretty much doesn't do anything.
If I'm not mistaken, let's take a look.
So, basically, we don't need to do any of this.
We need this in something.
We need to save.
Just this concept of how big the camera was.
So I'm basically going to I'm going to move that into.
I'm going to save just this piece, right?
Like so, so we don't need this.
We don't need any of that.
We don't need this anymore, we don't need this.
So really all we need to do here.
This will be some kind of function basically where we choose me.
This will just be some kind of function where we actually do our begin
and some so it'd be something like, you know, Sim camera region or
something like this, right?
And we wouldn't actually need a new camera P.
We would just go ahead and say, all right, take the game state.
Figure out how big we want that camera bound to be and then just go
ahead here and do the begin some Ensign pair, right?
So it's going to be like, oops.
It's going to be like, all right, you know, here's our Sim region.
Go ahead and make it.
We don't know exactly what that region is yet, but that's fine.
We've got the world and we've got the origins going to be the camera.
So this is the camera P, right?
And then we've got those camera bounds that we just computed.
So this is the region.
We want to sim we go ahead and do that and then we'll, you know,
Write some code in there for actually simulating the entities, which
we haven't quite done yet.
And there we go.
So that's all we really need to do now.
So Sim camera region, we just collapsed and we could probably just
move this whole thing back down into the main game loop.
It's not really even a function anymore for all intents and purposes.
So, really, what we got to do now is is just that, right?
We
Do that right here.
Nothing fancy about it, there's our Sim.
And then when we do this here, this is updating where the camera is
actually supposed to be.
So what we want to do there, I think.
Is I think will actually want to update the camera when we do the
simulation end, right?
So what we'd want to do is basically this we'd want to do that right
here.
So this will update the camera for us.
If that makes any sense, when we actually have things in the hiset
right before, we're done.
If the, if the camera was supposed to be following in any it will, and
we might make this into a more General system later, that actually can
do stuff on anything, but that's definitely the right place for it.
So we'll take a look at that when the time comes.
All right, so that's about all of the Restriction that we need to do
there.
This will actually do that Sim then we'll do the render, right?
And I guess we don't want to end the same till after we do the render
because we probably want to walk.
The SIM for our rendering, right?
So we probably want to do it.
Like this.
And in fact, the simulation in the renderer might kind of be working
together, right?
Because we that's the way we're doing it before and that may just
happen.
So will Bridge the Sim will Bridge across the two of those?
And so then when it goes through these, we no longer have a concept of
a zero index on high entity.
We don't have to anymore because now there is nothing that refers to
high entities ever for the most part.
Excuse me.
Well, I think about that.
We are going to need a way.
For people to point, we are going to need a mapping.
Basically that allows you to get from low entities that reference each
other up to hyades.
We could do that with a map or we could do that in place, so we'll
kind of have to see how we exactly want to do that.
I'm not sure.
A map is definitely one easy way to do it or a hash table would be one
easy way to do it and I'm not sure if we want to do something.
I think that probably the smarter way to do it wouldn't be very
expensive.
I think that would be a smarter way to do it than actually threading
it through like it was now because I don't think you want all those
pointers running around.
So I think we'll probably be able to Hash table so we're gonna get rid
of the concept that there's a that you ever ndex intentionally in the
high into the array.
That way you'll just use a pointer or something similar.
All right, so I think we are good to go there.
So here we'll just go through that same region, it's entity count, 60
entity index, like so this is will get much cleaner.
Now, I think and this will have an entity like this same region.
Entities.
And so that's M region will go ahead and loop over that.
We don't need low.
Use anymore.
Although we kind of still do have to do them temporarily because we
aren't really fully decompressing in and compressing in and out or
anything like that.
So we're going to temporarily leave those in until we get a further a
little bit further along.
Excuse me, on the porting.
So we'll still have our entity and Arlo entity will have to sort of
pick up the slack in a couple places.
We don't care about this anymore.
We get our GT for the frame, we have our low entities facing
Direction,
Still there blowing, 50 60 and let's see what else we have to do.
This is all drawing.
These are all just drawing calls.
So update sword.
For now, I guess we'll take both of these and same with update.
Familiar update.
Monstar those will want to actually pass both of them.
Probably.
And then from there, I guess the high
T, let's see here.
What if we got I don't know.
I don't again since we're kind of in the middle here.
I don't remember where the split was on some of these things.
So let's see.
Handmade
Sim region.
All right.
So yeah.
So most of these stuff this stuff is actually on the other type of
entity now but that's okay, we're no longer doing this this piece
group.
This all looks completely, non empty based so that's good.
So really only all over.
The only thing we're dealing with is this this is still using that
entity P.
Like so high entities Z that is still.
Yes, entity Z into Z XT Z
Still entity everything.
Here is still on empty.
That's fine.
And it looks like there isn't anything else in particular so those
still are on the low end of T which is all good.
So that's all good.
The most part.
All right, that looks nice.
So the really what we have to deal with now is just the update, the
update calls, I think as most of it and the other thing we're going to
want to do is move that code for the from the player we're going to.
On a move that down as well.
Alright.
So let's see how we're doing here.
We got to go ahead and include our Sim region as well.
So and made
Same region dot CPP and handmade same region.
H.
And I'm actually think that should go there.
That should probably go up here.
So let's go ahead and start our debugging process.
Let's get rid of this for now because I want that to be going
eventually entirely.
So let's just assume that we get rid of it entirely.
Let's see, Sim region entities
Excuse me.
Let's go ahead and do that cases style.
There we go.
Binary equals operator found, let's see.
Simpie, right, that's it, pointer to let's see.
Low against his fate, for the low entity, that's actually Source,
entity, to type out game, State low, entity is plus, sorted index.
The game state is undefined, that is actually true.
It is undefined.
So, we have to pass that here as well.
And so, this would be another comment where I'd say, we passed the
game state, but to do
Do if entities were restored in the world.
We wouldn't need the game State here, right?
So let's just something to think about, right?
All right.
So let's see.
This is actually the same region bounds.
Let's go ahead and file that we've got.
Our entity is a Sim entity, that's proper there.
We have our up and we're at the Q&A.
So I think I'm going to stop soon.
I might just take quickly go through the rest of this pass, just to
clean up some of these but that's where we'll end it store it into
sees, what are the stored entities that is?
Hello entities for now, right now, right about that, loyalty to low
entity star.
Here we go.
Entity camera, following entity for sanity into high case.
We don't actually need that anymore.
That would basically just be something that we use to sort of get with
that is and so that would maybe be our first case to do that hash
table.
This is basically be entity mapping hash table.
And that's something that we'll want to do.
I'll guess I'll put that here as well.
To do.
Need a hash table here to map low entity into C's, or I should say
stored in the end of these two SIM entities,
All right, so it's time for the Q&A.
So I'm going to stop here.
I think we have a plenty more work to do to sort of, get everything
organized.
So I don't want to go any further into the Q&A.
We'll do it tomorrow properly.
So yeah.
If you want to go ahead and preface your coal questions with q:, that
would be excellent.
So I can see them and please try to keep your question stuff.
We've done today or on previous dreams.
If you want to ask questions about other stuff, please come 15 minutes
before a scheduled start time of a stream and we do
Off topic questions, then.
Recommendations for names instead of stored entities.
You can have the stasis entity and stasis region for the
high-frequency.
You would keep the Sim.
Regents them entity.
Yeah, I don't really like stasis necessarily because they're not in
stasis.
They're just being
Stored temporarily, they're still active entities in some sense,
right?
So I don't know.
I'm not sure it's hard to say sim region and some entity seems good
stored restore or storage any?
I don't know.
World storage and store identity.
I don't know what to think about them.
They're kind of just being stored away till we need to come.
Grab them out again.
Since we know that an entity speed is bounded, couldn't we calculate a
Sim region with bounds such that no entity can move outside of it
during the frame that way.
Anything that the entity could collide with will be pulled into the
same region?
No, unfortunately, not because it's a, it's an unbounded problem,
right?
This is what I was trying to say.
So let's say that you start with this Sim region bound and you say all
right.
These are the entities that are in that bound.
Well, I know that this person can't move any further than this, right?
So my new sim region bound would be here, but the problem is that now
pulls in this entity and so then you have to do the same process
again.
Oh, well I know that this entity can only go that far.
So, here's my new sim region bound, which pulls in this entity and I
know that that entity could only move that far which falls in this
one, right?
So it
What's happening is if you if all the entities in the same region are
considered live, it will grow forever to Encompass the whole world.
So what you have to do is have a notion of a lot of Live And non-live
entities inside the same region and it'll be really easy for us to
deal with.
Don't have to do any special code.
All we have to do is not update ones that are outside that boundary
right.
In fact, I'll make a note of that here.
Just remember to do it.
Basically, what we want to do here.
Is to do check a second rectangle.
To set the entity to be movable or not, right?
And maybe that should actually be done in here.
Well, we'll see.
Because entities could get created.
Yeah, it's a long story anyway.
My paint source code.
Ah cool.
So my paint does that source code so I could possibly go fix that.
How many to dues do you have a lot?
I put lots of two dudes in the code.
Basically.
I don't hardly ever look at to dues until later in the project, but I
like to put them in because you could always go look and go, oh,
that's not relevant anymore.
And delete it.
But if you forget one that's bad.
So at the end of the project, you want to be able to have a way to
search for them and just see and make sure that there wasn't something
critical like to do.
This will explode.
You don't want that, you know, to stay in there, right?
So we have a thing.
Actually.
In here somewhere.
Let's see.
So we have a thing called Static check right and static check will
check for for Global variables so we can do in the code base we can
say static check.
Oops.
And that'll tell us everywhere that anyone used a static, right?
Which is pretty awesome because it can verify that we never have them,
which is what I wanted.
And so that's just kind of cool.
So what we can also do is we can make it a similar thing inside a
static shock, which is like to do check, right?
And that would be something that would allow us to do just a quick
sort of validation thing where we do like to do is found.
And then it would just look for that right?
Or something like this.
And so,
See and this way I can just quickly like at the end when we're
shipping will go through and remove all the to dues that are no longer
relevant and we can go through it address.
The ones that aren't are relevant, right?
So to do is very good.
I think they're a good thing.
They don't cost you anything to put in and if they're unlike comments
that are trying to like tell the person something I don't like to use
comments a lot because they tend to end up being wrong to do is really
aren't that way because you can quickly when you're doing your due
process.
You just go through and see if they're wrong.
Is throw them out.
They don't have that same - downside that comments do to me.
How will you handle the disparity and update rate between off-screen
and on-screen unities?
Does it matter?
The answer is, hopefully it won't matter too much, but it might.
And so really what we're going to want to do is, we're going to try
and want to keep that as very low.
Like hopefully we'll be able to write some pretty fast update code so
that we can handle lots of enemies and it's not too big of a deal.
So that it will be like a difference of like normally entities up to
60 frames a second and then off-screen, you know, the rest of the
world updates it like, you know, something like instead of 30 frames
per second or 60 frames a second, they operate it like five frames a
second which isn't that big of a deal like things probably won't break
but if it turns out that it's more like once every 5 seconds or once
every 10 seconds, we're going to have to do some extra work to support
that but we'll see.
What happens when we get there?
Well the same region away from the player calls.
Large time steps from the north.
Yeah, so that's the base of the same question.
So yeah, so the problem is always going to be, we still want to
simulate the world as fast as possible.
So we're still going to want to try and keep the number of sweeps
through the world to be relatively High.
But yeah, hopefully it won't be too bad.
If it is then we have to take steps to then we have to actually start
writing some extra code to do more efficient updates of people when
they're when they're in that other SIM region, right?
I missed whether this new system is based around discrete rooms or
integer map coordinates.
If it's based on rooms, would it be trivial to think in cords instead?
It's not based on rooms it's just it's free-floating it's just a
camera region and that camera region can be anywhere.
What will happen if your sim region and player location are at the
same place with a bug out?
No.
So we have two options and I don't know which one of them are going to
want to do.
But basically what we'll have is we'll probably use something like a
generation index and the generation index will tell us how many Sim
steps forward each thing has gone.
And so what we'll probably do is store some kind of a generation
index, like you know, I leave.
I'll put a note in here, too.
So, do it.
Generation index.
So we know how up to date this entity is.
Basically we'll store something in there that lets us know how
recently he was processed.
So there's two regions overlap or if the camera region comes into
somebody who hasn't been updated, it needs to know how much updating
to do for them.
We should basically be able to do something that does are some
reasonable job there.
Again it's going to still be a little complicated.
We'll have to work out a couple things because again scaling up
everything and making everything work nice and clean is hard this
though I think
Architecture gets us a huge portion of the way there which is good,
but there are still going to be a few things that we're going to have
to.
We're gonna have to see how they work out in practice.
Why is the low high frequency system?
So important isn't creating basic gameplay rules and AI interactions
in a small world more aligned with your philosophy of doing the simple
thing first?
No, so I think I don't want to give a misleading.
I don't, I want to be 100% clear.
When I say, do the simple thing first that doesn't mean do the wrong
thing.
First,
What I mean, is Implement, whatever.
Do whatever you can to get the thing working that you need working.
Right?
And I know I want to be able to scale The Entity count up high.
That's a requirement.
It's not an option.
I'm saying flat-out, we want to be able to create as many entities as
we want.
Like if we want literally to have 30 million entities in this game, I
want it to be able to work, right?
So that's a hard requirement of the it's not negotiable.
So I did do exactly what I said which was right.
What would make that work?
I just started typing it and you saw what we did we did the low
frequency High, everything I was like, all right, let's try this.
Let's try mapping between them and we kind of got that going and the
same was true of the of the large World thing.
I was like, okay, we got a map in and out.
And so I did exactly that process of going through and doing whatever
came to mind to get it working.
And then I realized right now, which was very
Be for me.
I realized last night because I felt like eventually we would see the
right solution.
I think we now have
I finally was like, ah, yes.
Now I see how to architect this.
So all of the problems go away, right?
And I think that's what this will do for us.
It'll be a success to a point where now everything is nice and clean
and it's very easy to code for.
And the reason that I wanted to do this first was because everything
we write from now on will be in terms of this thing.
So, starting with something that doesn't handle any of the things that
we need to handle is not the same as writing.
The simple thing first.
As writing, the simple thing first is only valuable simple isn't the
right word for it.
I guess is what I would say, it's whatever you can think to do that,
satisfies the requirements.
And sometimes that means the simple thing, right?
And in a sense case it's I would even still describe it that way.
Write the simplest thing, you can think of that, does what you need it
to do which is what I did, but it still needs to do what you need it
to do.
You can't write something that doesn't do what you want to do just
because it's simple.
Because then you've learned nothing, right?
And so that's really, really crucial to understand the difference
between those two things over designing means trying to actually make
a complete system before you actually understand how it has to work,
right?
Moving away from that.
Doesn't mean writing something that doesn't actually satisfy the
requirements.
You have.
So what you want to do is you want to write something as
straightforwardly as you can, that satisfies the requirements and then
you want to architect up from that.
And that's exactly what we did.
I wrote the most straightforward code as I was going and you saw how I
was kind of getting complicated and nasty.
And then I was like, ah, I see how we can do the architecture.
Now that makes these things
I'm clean.
So the other thing to think about is these systems are different.
So when you said, you know, why not get AI interactions or gameplay
rules, those are different systems.
How we handle?
Where look things are spatially.
Has nothing to do with how the eye works, right?
The AI has to use those systems but it has nothing.
It, it still has to be a completely other design problem that we're
going to work on, right?
And so as I went,
You notice that I kept adding new things to the system, like I added
that floating familiar.
That was a step towards adding Ai and game rules.
We started adding the sword.
That's exactly what I was doing.
But I'm constantly looking at all of the pieces that are in play there
and going.
Oh, okay.
I see.
We've already gotten to the point, even with just these things in
there, where it's becoming difficult, to work on the code because of
the complexity that's involved with maintaining the high and low
frequency and the positional stuff and
No, I need those things.
So it's kind of like now is a good point if you can think of a way to
do it to level those things up to a better architecture, right?
And I was reluctant to do that for a while because I haven't thought
of anything that was a clear win.
But now after we got enough out there I was like I see what the clear
winner is.
Now, let's do it.
And so I think this is the right thing and that's why I did it now.
Instead of doing it before again, I didn't think about it clearly
enough before.
So if I done something like this before, it would have been a bad
idea.
And it's hard to say.
When you get those ideas in your head, what they should be or
shouldn't be.
That's kind of the, a little bit of experience talking.
Knowing when you get an idea that you're like, ah, this one really
does solve a bunch of problems that I've been having.
I've seen all the problems I think, you know, this is a good one to go
with Now versus going.
I don't think I quite have enough information yet, right?
Making those judgments calls is obviously that takes a lot of practice
to know about.
How will we update low frequency regions?
Given the sparse nature of the world?
Probably will just spin through tile.
Chunks will be my guest.
We'll just go through the hash table.
Maybe we'll string will go through the, the hash table and pick out
tile chunks.
Look for tile chunks, that haven't been updated in a.
While update around them which will pull in any Tau chunks that are
nearby.
They'll do the update Mark, all those toxins updated and keep going.
Is there a major advantage to using for is instead of Wiles?
No for loops?
And while Loops are exactly the same, in terms of code that gets
generated, they're just notational.
So basically like if you want to anytime you see a for Loop, you could
just write it as a while loop, right?
So like that's the while loop version of this for Loop and so there's
really no difference of them.
It's just the reason that people prefer for Loops often times.
And the reason that I myself right for Loops when I write them, it's
because it shows more clearly when you're reading what the elements of
the loop, are it just, it, kind of bundles, them were nicely together
in a while loop that kind of spread out, especially when there's a
bunch of stuff here, right?
You start to lose track of what the blue parts are or if things get
inserted.
Add in here, right?
So the for Loop is just a nice way to kind of bundle those things
together.
What will the entities that are not visible on the screen be doing?
I can't really think of examples of things that need to be updated if
they're far from the player.
So, an example would be,
and again, until we actually get to the game are specific, game will
have specific needs but giving an example from like, if you imagine
just a random game, the sorts of stuff that I think would be nice to
be able to do any time we want is let's say that the player you know,
goes ahead and
Excuse me, goes ahead and, you know, Toxin and PC and the NBC says,
oh, okay, you know, I'll go fetch that thing.
I would like the MPC to then be able to like go and walk somewhere
else in the world, no matter what you're doing, fetch the thing, and
like bring it back.
And then he's there again, right?
And maybe he goes there, and he looks for it, but it's not there.
So he then goes and look somewhere else for it.
And if you were like, walking around and went up somewhere, you might
Him like walk by like, you're on a screen in the MVC, comes on the
bottom and walks by and walks off the top.
If you like, hey, I know that guy.
Where's he going?
And you could follow him.
I just want to enable stuff like that.
I know games don't do it very often but I think they'd be cooler if
they did, it's just kind of a nice emergent Behavior thing.
And so since it's a it's an interesting programming challenge.
I decided to include it in our engine because I think it's worth us
figuring these things out.
It's part of the teaching process of showing how to work.
Through programming problems, that are difficult.
If we just wanted to make
Make a game where we just had a simple to, you know, if we were just
going to clone Binding of Isaac or something, there's it's really easy
to program, right?
There's one room.
Nothing happens anywhere in the game of the worlds are tiny, there's
like five enemies on the screen, right?
We could trivially right that we've already written most of the code
that you would need, right?
So the idea is not to show how to program the simplest game possible
because I don't think that's very interesting.
The idea is to show how to program a game whose game design is vastly
more complicated than 90% or even.
That on the games that you might see.
So, you can actually see how to work through very difficult
architecture problems.
Not just, hey, I've got a simple platform or something because that's
just not that interesting.
I don't think.
How many low entities does it take to screw in a light bulb?
Well, now if you actually are talking about just stored entities, that
are not mapped into the simulation set, there is no number of them
that could screw in a light bulb because they don't get a Time step.
It's only once they are Sim.
So if you're talking about if you include the fact that there's the
low-frequency simulation thing going around simulating them then you
know I suppose it depends on
The update entity called for that particular type of entity and how
many you know hitpoints the lightbulb has that sort of stuff.
Your voice is about to throw in the towel.
Be careful.
We need your tumor.
It's true.
My voice is tomorrow.
Stream may be a silent stream where you just watch me rearrange.
The last remaining pieces of code and compile.
This
first far storage.
Why not store the XYZ cords?
Bit shifted into aniline integer to use it as a composite key into a
dictionary or hash map so we are.
We're basically already doing that.
The only thing we don't do well.
I mean I'll just go ahead and load it up.
So, here you go.
Where's Mike?
Where's my get chunk?
It's in here somewhere.
There is get World chunk.
So if you notice, that's exactly what we do.
Right?
There's the hash lat, there's the positions.
So like what you're saying is exactly what we do.
If you're asking literally, why we don't pitch shift, it's because
Well, there's to do better hash function, so we haven't analyzed it,
but oftentimes just packing the bits together isn't the best way to
throw things into a hash table.
So we're actually multiplying by primes, not that, that's particularly
better.
We actually want to analyze these in have some real Prime sir.
This was this is garbage, but bit shifting is probably not what we'll
want to do because we want to do something probably that that tries to
look at how our world Jen tends to generate worlds, and make something
that that is going to use the
Able well, for those kinds of layouts.
Do you approach design a similar way to your architecture?
I expression based design design sort of merges itself.
We're going to excetera.
So if you're talking about game design, I'm not a game designer, so I
can't really comment on that.
I, I don't do game design.
I just do game programming.
It's multi-threading in the scope of topics for the project.
It's sort of wasn't.
I mean it was for the renderer, the software renderer because that was
a good place like a do it, that would make sense, but it wasn't
originally because the Raspberry Pi only had one core and I wanted to
port to that eventually probably.
And so, since that's also our slowest platform, being multi-threaded
didn't seem like much of a good idea but all that changed in a big way
because recently, they announced that
Raspberry Pi is getting a refresh and it's going to have an arm cortex
core.
Arm cortex chip with 4 cores.
So now multi-threading is absolutely on the table and updating
multiple SIM regions in parallel is absolutely something that we will
probably want to do when the time comes.
If a Faraway room gets updated and the rooms around that are updated
to don't, we have this recursive problem where the around rooms need
their neighbor to know again, because you can do simulations half
cited, right?
We can do, like, just move the entities here in this region, do those
moves, right?
And the things nearby them aren't allowed to move.
We can do stuff like that, right?
And we do introduce problems like If This Were, if this were some kind
of
A multiplayer online game that we're working this way, it would
probably be a bad idea because you really care about things like
fairness there and all these other sorts of things.
But we have the ability to sort of tweak, you know, all the things
that are getting updated out there completely under our control and we
have the ability to tweak, their a eyes and change the way they're a
eyes work to make it.
So that that's not really going to cause a lot of huge problems.
If we see it causing problems, we can probably fix them.
So I don't think we're going to have a problem with that aspect of it.
But we'll see, you know, we never really know.
How much work would it take to turn the game?
The game you're making from a 2d world into a 3D World?
I'm not sure how to answer that question.
Because it's very ambiguous, are you talking about rewriting the
crytek engine or you talking about literally you just want the things
to be you know 3D models you loaded out of Maya but its exact same
game, otherwise?
Right?
Because there's a huge difference between those two things.
To clarify my early design question.
I just mean, as far as your design decisions for handmade hero.
Well, so far, I haven't really done exploratory design with handmade
here because I mostly did it just sort of on paper because I haven't
obviously been doing any of the zine on stream.
So I can't really do emergent design in that sense.
When we actually do Implement, all the game stuff that I sort of
already wrote down that, I thought we should do once we get all that
working.
Then yeah, we probably will do fairly
Lee organic design that way.
Because like I said, I'm not a game designer so I don't have really
strong opinions about that necessarily so we probably will do stuff.
It's like, well, I'm on stream and I like oh, we implement this
feature.
It also be cool if you did this, we'll just do that.
And so there probably will be a fair bit of design.
That's very emergent there because, you know, again, the focus of this
product is on programming, not design, and
As we think of fun things to implement, we should just Implement them
and see how to program them.
That would be my preference.
All right, I think we're almost out of time.
We are almost out of time, it ends at 10.
It looks like we don't have any more questions.
So we're right on time we are right on time people so that's pretty
good.
That's pretty good.
I would say in my in my humbleness oddly that humble opinion.
All right.
Well, I guess since we're at the end of questions now is a good time
to wrap up the stream.
That's very good.
We're right on time.
And I'm pretty excited about where we're at.
I think this is going to help us out a lot.
I like this design decision.
It's looking pretty good.
So far, you know what I should do?
I should save this out so it'll get shipped out now.
It's black.
It's the Blackboard art file in the Mist directory.
So that when I upload things, in case, anyone wants to look at the
diagrams, but I think that is
For today.
So thank you everyone for joining me.
It's been a pleasure program with you, and I was very happy to put
that stuff in today.
I think tomorrow is going to be great when we wrap it up and we can
kind of sort of started focusing on the low high anything, because now
that I actually feel really good about that same region stuff.
It gives me those really well-defined places to do the map in and out.
And I've kind of been waiting for the right time to start thinking
about that map in and out.
And so now that will sort of material as I think over the next week.
So we're probably
I want to do is over the next week or so.
So, next week,
Probably all next week.
Throw a ton of stuff in that low entity like whatever we can fit do
finish, the hit point stuff and I don't know what else in there, but
just whatever we can think of pickups.
Like maybe you can go walk around and get different swords to throw.
And I don't even know chest.
You can open that kind of stuff just pile, a bunch of stuff in there.
So that we really bloat out that low entity class huge right.
And then take a
That and go.
Okay, how can we now start to think about how we want to deal with
these?
Where we know we're going to have tons and tons of these guys tons and
tons of these things.
How do we start managing that and sort of, in the same vein, I'd like
to get the property transfer and stuff in there.
I talked about that something where, you know, things touch other
things and they pick up properties from them or, you know, you cast a
spell on one thing and that thing keeps that state.
And so that when it does something later in abused, that something
else, I
To kind of get the cram those things in there so I can start to see
how they feel because that's the next thing that I want to nail down.
Any system wise, I think that's going to be really important.
So, I want to push towards that.
I don't know if we'll make it before, break people have been asking
for a week off, for quite some time and so that first week in March,
Said, we could take off because I'm going to be away anyway, I'm going
to be visiting my parents so it's easy for me to just go.
Okay, we won't stream while I'm away.
So people have that week to catch up.
So we've got two weeks.
I don't know if we'll get all the way there, hopefully next week and
then the week after week and if you just keep piling stuff in there,
I'm hoping that we'll be able to kind of get to a point where I'm
comfortable saying, there's enough things in here that we can start to
make decisions.
Don't know if we will or not but I'd like to do that if we get there
before I break.
That would be pretty cool because then we'll have that hole.
Break to think about it, and we come back, we could do the energy
system that would be pretty cool.
So we'll see.
Mmm, that's where we're at again.
Thank you so much for joining me.
I will be back here tomorrow night 8:00 p.m.
6 Center time, I guess.
Yeah, tonight was a late start because we wanted to watch John,
obviously, any time, John is streaming updates to his programming
language.
I want to watch that.
So we always delayed the stream and that's on but tomorrow night
there's there's no other things going on.
As far as I know, so it
60 time tomorrow, right?
Back here on Twitch, if you would like, to follow along with the
source code at home, you can do.
So right here.
Basically, if you preorder the game, you can download the source.
Code we posted every night after I'm done programming.
And of course, you can go check out the video archive.
There's videos all the way back to day.
One which tell you exactly how to set up a build machine, how to work
with the source code.
It shows you every step of the way, how I built it.
So you can go through every last thing.
And see how it was made.
So that's pretty cool.
And you can do that here on handmade here.
At org we also have a patreon.
If you want to support the video series, you can always subscribe to
that.
And there's a news and Forum site, you can check out which has a bunch
of stuff like the schedule for the week.
The schedule, freaks also tweeted by the tweetbot if you want to have
them delivered right to your Twitter account, you can do that here on
the tweets button, but the news report says that it's got a discussion
board, it's got old episodes annotated.
You can go in the episode guide, It's got ports to Mac and Linux got
all kinds.
Good stuff.
So check that out if you're trying to learn for the stream of great
place to go.
So I think that's about it for today.
Thanks everyone for joining me and I will see you back here tomorrow.