Already.
Welcome, everyone, to another episode of handmade hero.
The show.
We code complete game live on stream.
Now, I don't know if I'm supposed to say who it is.
So I'm not going to until I get official permission, but I do want to
share with you something.
I received in the mail today which is that, you all, of course, know
the owl of shame.
But I received in the mail
The owl, shame baby, which is kind of amazing.
Right.
It's exactly like the Alice shame, but smaller and cuter.
Now the note that came with it suggested that it should be the outlet
of guilt, but I don't really know.
I think it may just be a lechaim baby in my mind and like when you
have something that's only a little bit shameful and it's not as
shameful, then out the baby comes out.
But when you have
Really shameful, then the big, you know, Big Mama comes out, and so
I'm going to keep both owls available so that depending on the size of
the screw up, I can be shamed to the to the you know, extent that is
commensurate with the mistake.
So anyway, thank you very much for the baby L and like I said we'll
have to we'll post an official, thank you to the Twitter if it's okay.
I like I said, I don't want to say anyone's name on stream who doesn't
want to be?
Be named on stream but but thank you very much for sending, that's
pretty awesome and I have a feeling it will show up on the stream the
next time I make a baby mistake which let's face it.
I make a lot of.
All right.
Today, we're doing just a little bit more work on our mode, switching
stuff.
Today is day 2, 28.
So if you'd like to follow along at home and you have pre-ordered, the
code on handmade here at org that's you want to start with de 227.
And so, that is what I am starting with.
Right now.
I believe we essentially had everything done, except I told you there
is a bug but was a bug.
We can't really hit right now.
It's a bug in the fact that we would have some threads accessing a
mode after it was already gone but otherwise things are pretty much
right?
We have this like sort of placeholder for our title screen.
This this red sort of clear here.
Got to get some art for a title screen and then we go into our
cutscene and we have our cutscene kind of going, right?
And that's all good and we can enter the game and now we can sort of
walk around and do our thing that we want to do.
We can exit the game now and it will go back to the cutscene and it
restarts properly now which is what it should.
I think we should probably change it to go back to the title screen
but you know either way it's trivial
Online change depending on which one we want.
And then, of course, we can go back into the game again, right?
And so, all that feels pretty good.
But like I said, there's some stuff that I think we want to address
their in terms of making this a little bit more solid.
One of them of course is the thread bug that I was talking about where
like we want to make sure that if a particular mode spawns, a bunch of
threads.
We need a way for it to clean up those threads when it when it ends.
So that it knows when it can actually shut down the mode for reals.
And the other thing that we need to do is we need to
To make sure that we can create separate standing modes for doing
stuff like maybe pre like, I don't know what you want to call it but
like pre ceding like like the way that we were prefetching.
The cutscene stuff.
It would be nice if we could do something like that as well.
Probably because we want to be able to do stuff like when we go to
start the cutscene we may want to be able to to prefetch into it or I
don't even know.
I don't
No, but point being, I could see there being away at a time when we
would want to do that.
So I'm that might be also something to look into eye.
It might be something also to put off, I don't know.
But at the very least, I feel like we got to take care of that thread
bug situation, even though, I don't know that we're going to use the
ground chunk, compositing stuff in the end.
I guess what I would say is just because the ground chunk stuff might
not be used, doesn't mean we won't want to have there be some thread
stuff that does happen, right?
So that's where we're at at the moment.
And then I feel like after that gets taken care of, I feel like I want
to maybe.
I feel like after we come back from break, I feel like I want to maybe
go back to the debug code a little bit and finish up the stuff that we
did there.
Just so we can have that in place because I think we're mostly there.
In terms of stuff for gameplay code.
And I kind of want to start that and, you know, have the New Year
bhosle be spent doing new gameplay stuff.
And so, you know, we just got a few things left to take care of, get
the debug code in good shape, get the renderer like, we got to put a
sort in the renderer and do a little bit of lighting work and then I
think we're mostly good.
So I want to just take care of that stuff so we can get get on with
things.
So, yeah, let me just quickly sketch out what I think that particular
problem is
So we have this concept now of this game mode, right?
And so, we've got this this notion here that says like, okay, you
remember this game State used to be this huge thing and now it's
broken up into two different parts.
So there's stuff for the title screen stuff for the cuts and stuff for
the world mode.
When you're actually playing and then it has some stuff that persists,
right?
So all that stuff is the way it is.
But if you take a look at how this works, you can kind of see that.
Well, there's this notion that we, you know, have this sort of game
mode or whatever.
And then we also have this this notion of tasks with memory like down
here, this tasks that are that are running.
Maybe working on something specific in the, you know, in that
particular game mode.
And when we close the game mode, we would like that to go away.
Now, we have two choices of what how we can approach this problem?
Choice, number one is to say that actually we don't ever associate
things in this way, right?
Like for example just to just to maybe give you a little bit of a
perspective on what's Happening.
For example, in the asset system right now we have a bunch of tasks
that are running to load assets off of disk dynamically.
That's our streaming system, right?
It's to make it so that we don't have loading screens and don't have
pauses and stuff in the gameplay.
But you may ask.
Why did those why are those tasks?
Not a problem whereas the ground chunk tasks are right?
Why don't why am I not worried about this asset loading things?
Well that's because the asset system is totally decoupled from the
game mode.
The asset system just knows it has to load assets and it manages the
asset store and that stuff doesn't have anything to do with what mode
you're in.
So it doesn't matter whether it's loading assets for the title screen,
or for the world mode, or for the cutscenes or whatever those tasks
are just doing their
Thing and they never depend on any of the data that's in here.
They're completely decoupled.
So the only kind of thing that we're talking about here is we're
talking about tasks that work directly on data, that's in one of the
game modes.
And furthermore, we're talking about task because we have another set
of tasks, right?
Which is the renderer tasks.
Why don't we care about those?
Well, those tasks, all get spawned and stopped.
In the middle of one frame, they never hang around outside the frame.
So when you change game modes, you don't care about those tests
because, you know, none of them are running.
They don't span a frame boundary like that.
So, the only task we actually care about our task switch access.
The game's mode state.
So something in one of these guys,
And which persist so they, you know, they'll happen over multiple
frames right now.
Ground chunks are the only things we have that do that.
So we have two choices.
Choice number one is say we're not going to have any tasks like that,
right?
We could just say we don't want to do that.
That's an option and choice.
Number two, is that we track them in a way that allows us to shut them
down when the mode is changed.
That's what we can do.
So I don't know which is the better answer there and the reason that I
don't know, which is the better answers because I don't know what we
will actually need in the finished game.
So my gut instinct normally would be to just probably get rid of them
because I feel like after having done some of the design stuff, it
seemed to me like probably
I wouldn't really be able to use the ground chunk stuff much because
the way the design was going dynamically
Eating ground things like that wouldn't probably actually work very
well or would be what I should say.
Is it said of not work very well, it's something that is probably not
necessary.
For the most part.
So yeah, it just seemed like something that probably at the end of the
day is not really all that necessary to do.
So my gut instinct would be to remove them.
The only problem is, I don't know if maybe there's something else
besides making ground chunks.
That would, you know, that would span that, that space, right?
Something that would take up, you know, sort of a bigger chunk of that
time.
And so, what I think I would
A is the only thing I can think of that really falls into that
category, might be World Generation and the reason I say that is
because let's suppose that the game starts and the players trying to
play the game since.
I don't really want there to be much in the way of loading screens.
Like, it don't want to stop the players experience ever.
If generating the world takes 1020 seconds, 30 seconds depending on
how complicated and how large
World, it is if there's a lot of stuff that's going to create that
world that's going to be a 30 second loading screen, right?
And you've seen this in games before, like for example, when you try
to start a game of Don't Starve, for example.
You sit there watching it, say that it's generating the world or
whatever and so if we don't want that we would have to do is just
start the player so they can start playing in the first little area of
the world.
While in the background, we're going through, like, generating the
rest of it, right?
And so, I feel like that is something we probably would want.
It seems very logical that we would want that and that will clearly
have to happen over multiple frames.
So I feel like that argues strongly enough to me that these tests have
to be treated that way.
So I think I will probably say let's go ahead and support it because
even if I go ahead and pull the ground chunks out, so the ground
chunks are no longer involved and we don't need this for them.
I would still I would still need it for avoiding the loading screen in
that situation.
That's what I think.
It's just what I think.
All right, so how we gonna do this?
Well, we have this concert of tasks with memory and that goes in the
transient state right now.
Right.
We've got four different tasks with memory that are that are happening
there.
And I suppose really all I need to do is tag these things with whether
or not they're going to have to be flushed out in the case where the
game mode changes, right?
So it's kind of like a, my dependent on a particular game mode would
probably be all.
I would really need to know for that to happen, right?
At least.
That's what I think.
I'm not.
100% sure.
That's just what I think.
Think.
So let's go ahead and say that.
Have that.
Let's do a very simple version of this first one that's synchronous
and that causes maybe a stall and then we can look at doing one that's
better and that may get into the memory stuff that I kind of wanted to
do anyway.
So let's take a look.
Let's say we have something that's like task with memory and maybe I
want to do something where I say like okay in addition to tracking
whether it's being used here, I'm also going to track something like,
you know,
Ends on game mode, you know what I'm saying?
And so, then when we do our little tasks with memory thing where we
have, like a task with memory begin, right?
This thing here begin to ask with memory when we call that begin task
with memory.
I'm going to say, you know, does it depend on the game mode?
And then when I create the actual task, I'm going to set depends on
game mode to the correct value.
That's all I'm doing good.
I'm doing the very simplest thing that will solve the problem and of
course I should probably also change the definition here.
32 depends on game mode and so now I can just look and see who uses
that.
Well obviously load bitmap doesn't right, sound is not good.
Font is not.
And so then we just got begin task with memory in for the ground
chunk.
And this is the one that does.
So now I know which ones do
And we're good to go, right?
So now what I can do is say when we are going to clear the game mode I
can do the simplest possible thing, like I said that maybe isn't the
most performant and I can just ensure that all of those tasks closed
down.
And so, the way I can do that is when we go to set game mode and I
clear out the motor, me know what I can do is write before that.
You remember, we have the ability to wait on tasks to finish, and I
don't remember exactly.
Actly.
How we do that?
It's something like you tiled render work.
Oh, it's in the optimized version.
Let's see here, render tiled render here, it is.
So you can see it happening here where we do this, this output stuff.
We have platform complete, all work render queue.
So, what I can do there is, I can easily sort of wait for all of that
to happen and then and then
Only at that point, right?
So I could say something like, oh okay, complete everything that was
going to happen.
As far as the, the game state is concerned, right?
So the I forget what this would be this.
We'd actually need the transient State here.
I believe because we need that Q.
Although I guess that's in the game memory.
Kind of remember exactly how we did this.
But that's the low priority queue here, right?
And so what we could do is say like okay, you know, wait for
everything in the low priority queue to finish.
And then off, we
All right, so we would need the transient State here.
And we would need to wait for that to finish.
Now, we actually only need to wait for it to finish, if there's
anything that's actually depends on the game state, but, you know,
presumably that's fine.
That makes sense.
So we can do that and we can also do something that's like need to
wait, right?
And you could then go like, okay, take a look and see if anybody in
there is actually doing anything that we care about.
So, we basically say, okay, you know, task and x equals 0 task and X
is less than
Translate it count and state tasks.
Task Index, right?
So I can do something like that and say you need to wait, equals need
to wait or tasks.
Whatever this task is.
Depends on game mode.
So if any of these depend on the game mode then I will force them to
complete all work.
Otherwise, I won't.
So, let's take a look at that.
Task memory does not have never would operator.
That is true.
Yeah, and now we would just need set game mode to actually get that
thing that it needs.
Get the, the additional state that it needs.
So it would need the transient state
In order to wait on that cue.
And that's it.
Now it does strike me as slightly odd.
Well, like, I feel like almost that should have been in the game State
struct because it's not really all that transient if it's something
that depends on the game mode, I guess.
But it's hard to say.
Anyway, point being, when we do set game mode again that needs to kind
of have the transient State come through, and it's kind of annoying to
have to pass these.
So I do wonder if
Actually, just collapse them and do some, some fancier footwork there.
But either way, I'm just going to do the mechanical process for now
and that's something we can obviously fix or futz with a little bit
later.
So let's go ahead and that in there.
And now we got to push that out one more because those are going to be
in here, those aremy lofted up here and so they need transient state.
What's that?
Okay.
Play into a cutscene.
He's trance state.
And may or may not have it play title screen.
These
That one doesn't have it.
So that would just be transient state.
And if it getting past the translate then I can just get the assets
from there because that's already in there right?
Playing intro.
Cutscene same thing.
So there we go and think that's probably most of what we would have to
do.
Transient state has not been initialized yet at that point.
And so that would need to that would need to happen a little bit
lower.
And so that would be something where that looks like something where
we would probably want to introduce the thing I was talking about
before, so I feel like we would want something we're in here.
We say game mode, none, right.
And then, what I would do is say okay, on Startup, you know, when we
actually start up after initialization, like these two guys,
Miss going to say, all right.
Play the intro cutscene, if the game State game mode equals game mode
men,
And that way, I know that each of these guys are initialized, that's
about it.
I think.
Oops.
And play worlds.
Also needs to get that.
So let's take a look at play World world Road.
Guess the transit state.
Okay, so I think that's it.
Hopefully, anyway.
Oops.
No one more.
and,
Done.
So, in theory now we are good to go.
At least, I think but we do have one of the things that I want to look
at.
But let's go ahead and see if this works, right?
Okay so there we go, here's this coming into the game here.
Is this exiting out of the game right now here's this coming back into
the game so that's all good.
I may also want to make it so that when you exit out of the game
instead of playing the intro cutscene to plays the title screen if
that makes sense.
Oops, not there.
But here.
So, in where is it?
It's actually enrolled mode I guess.
When we do this, when there's no more Heroes left, I would like at
that point to go back to the title screen.
Because you know, that just makes a little more sense.
Right.
So there's one more thing that I want to look at which we did sort of
silently before and I kind of want to make sure that we actually go
look at it now and I'm going to show you kind of a little trick.
So, here we go.
Back to the title screen, right?
And then we can jump into the game title screen.
If you let the telescreen schedule, go to the cutscene.
And there we go, right?
That's all there is to that.
So anyway, point being
If you'll notice we hit F5.
It takes a while before that Fade Out starts and that's new.
If you remember when then actually happened that happened when we
first added clear 20 on push and what I suspect is happening is since
we are clearing all of our memory, 20, probably a very large
allocation, that happens gets cleared to zero due to our automatic
clearing now that we probably don't want to do.
I suspect that I can cheat without actually using any profiling by
using debug break all.
So, if I just run the game and do break all, I should say, hey, look,
I should be able to break in the that giant clear of the chunk.
And hey, you can see exactly what's going on here, right?
You can actually see that it's asking not to clear 20 and and this is
still going to clear it to 0, right?
So in this thing that's making the empty bitmap that's going through
all the ground buffers, its clearing them all for no reason
whatsoever.
So that's just kind of.
Yeah.
I mean, you see what I'm saying?
Right?
And so, I feel like that's something we probably want to address and I
would like to address it now before it gets any more out of hand and I
think you can also see.
Like this right here, would clear a giant block.
So, I want to to address that.
And here's how I'm going to dress that since we've got time on today's
string before we head out for Christmas break.
I want to address that and the way that I want a dress that is I'm
going to change the way that push works.
So the way that I want Push to work now is I want Push to take two
things.
I wanted to take the alignment and whether we cleared a 0 because we
just straight up made clear, 20, be a
a thing.
But now I want to make some notion of how this stuff should work,
right?
So what I'd like to do is say, okay, there's going to be a new thing
which is like push params or something like that.
Look Arena push / amps and what that's going to do is the arena, push,
params will say something like oh okay, you know, what's the what's
the flags Arena push flag?
Like that.
Arena flag.
Clear 20.
You know I'm saying and then it will also have a thing like the
alignment.
So the alignment will also be you know, kind of baked in there, you
know, I'm saying, so that way when you do whatever it is, that you're
going to do, there's this concept of the the the sort of alignment is
going to be baked in there in some way, that makes sense.
And so, and the flags will be bundled with it as well, okay?
And so then what I'm going to do is say, alright, let's say,
Something like inline, Arena, push params, default Arena Rams for
something like this.
And all that does is say params.
Flags equals Arena flag, clear 20 alignment equals, whatever that
default memory alignment is right.
I'm going to get rid of that Turn 4 amps.
And now instead of memory index alignment, these are all going to take
Arena push the Rams and
As their parameter and they'll default to default Arena params.
Does that make sense?
Hopefully that makes some sense, right?
So then in here, when we use alignment this is just going to be params
alignment now.
Otherwise it's exactly the same and now everybody will do who was
doing the alignment stuff before will do exactly what what that guy
did.
They'll all take this and so that stuff can be bundled when you do the
push and I'll show you why I wanted in a bundle like that instead of
adding additional parameter.
Other than the fact that you can see it's kind of convenient here the
way that I'm doing this you know, for initializing the defaults.
But that's a look at that second and so then what we can do is we can
say if params the flags and
Oops.
And
Arena flag, clear to 0, then we clear 20 but otherwise, we will not
clear to zero so that now gives us an ability to clear things for not
depending on how we want to do it, right?
Okay.
So now actually this effective size for, I actually can just go ahead
and pass that through directly, which is kind of nice and let's see.
Sub arena is also going to take the
M&M's.
So this will be Arena push params g equals default in the params and
there are the programs we go.
And so now, I think we're in pretty good shape.
Okay.
And so we can now do something like a line.
No.
Clear.
Right.
We can now create sort of this custom set of very convenient phrases
that look very readable and tell you exactly what your push is going
to do and it all kind of flow through properly.
Right?
So now we've got our default Arena push for.
Is it now?
We can also do like that.
What I just said, where I've got.
Okay, I'm going to make one called a line.
No clear.
And align no.
Clear.
Will take the
It will produce one of these.
Which will be set up to do, whatever it is that does.
And then we just make sure we set all these the way we want them.
And everyone says, which one of them they want to use.
So there is a line, no clear, that won't align it when it does, what
it's going to do.
And it's all good right now.
The hilarious thing is, I believe we actually would probably want them
be cleared because they call clear out the mixer channel.
So I should probably do a thing that you're like, are we sure?
We don't want to
Let this do the clear.
Because that might be faster than this, but I don't know.
So anyway, point being, that's what I'm talking about.
All right.
Similarly here when we do make empty bitmap, here's a push sizes,
trying to do it again.
Since we have this clear 20 thing and we've got clear bitmap clear
bitmap just call zero size.
So really what we could do is get rid of clear bitmap.
I think we don't need that anymore.
My guess would be we don't and I think we can get rid of it.
So now all we would have to do is say well okay.
We know we may or may not want to clear this so we can just say clear
20 if we're going to if we're going to clear it will
One way and if we're not, we're not so we can do a line clear and
align no clear.
And both of them can be aligned to 16 if that's what we want.
Makes sense.
So yeah, something like that.
We could also do something with a Boolean, you do.
You could imagine something like this.
if we wanted to and that might be fun because then we can say, Oh
either we're going to do a clear or we're not
and then that would just be like, oh okay, so a line, 16, clear 20
No, I'm saying.
So that's kind of Handy, too.
All right, so let's keep going with that.
What I want to do now is I want to just go find everywhere that we did
a push, right?
which is quite a few places, but
An intractable number.
And I just want to take a look at how we were passing them, and make
sure that we're using.
Now that we've got new features that were actually using them.
So here is, for example, a thing where we do a clear 20 that's
probably fine because that's just an array of ground buffers.
Those ground buffers aren't that big?
I do not think so.
That's all fine.
That's has nothing to do with it.
And neither does any of this.
These are just the actual code blah blah blah blah blah, blah, don't
care, don't care.
So there's a push size and we're this is a push size where we do a
push and then we write we immediately
We immediately right to it.
So that is presumably something where we want to do.
No clearing right?
We don't want to do any clearing in that.
So that does the push size that it would do, don't clear and it writes
to the, the entirety of the thing that it allocated, right?
So let's see about this.
Oops, that was actually something I want to look at.
So that's fine.
Because whoever does the sub Arena can say whether they want it
cleared and what the alignment is.
So that's all good.
So let's step back through there, push truck for task work, that is
literally just getting over written completely, so that does not need
to be cleared either because it does.
It's a load asset work that gets overwritten completely.
This one looks like probably might as well clear, that one, because it
looks like it's actually setting it up here, so that's fine.
Again.
Same with this guy, probably doesn't need clear creating the game
assets, that should be cleared in.
Good luck with a push size here where it's taking over the sizes that
definitely doesn't want.
If I bet that was what was taking most of our time, because that's the
whole asset store getting zeroed out for no reason whatsoever.
Here's our push array with the asset file.
That's something I think we might as well clear.
That seems pretty straightforward to me.
Asset type array is getting read from the file immediately afterwards.
I don't know whether we want to clear that or not.
That's a really good question.
If the read file failed, then I suppose we would file error.
Out so I suppose that means we don't really have to clear it so I'll
go no clear for that guy as well and let's take a look at these guys
so we've got asset counts tag counts and yeah I don't know if we want
to clear these or not you know what I'm going to do I'm going to leave
them as getting cleared to be honest.
Sometimes I find it's just better to clear better to be safe than
sorry.
So we'll see if it creates any problems doing it that way but if it
doesn't I'm going to let those guys clear.
So those are no clear already.
Here is a bitmap push call that doesn't relate to the memory system.
That's just it happened at push in the name.
This stuff for the cutscenes against.
Those can get cleaned out.
Don't care about those at all.
These are welcome to clear themselves.
That's a push.
Up call.
Here's push font again, that's unrelated.
Push wrecked.
Unrelated all of these guys are other stuff.
There's push struct.
Get a clue.
But again, that's debug view that can get cleared.
Yeah, so here again, those are, these are all find clear, because
those are not performance sensitive anyway.
So it's always, like I said, better safe than sorry.
I'd rather clear them out.
And yeah, all the debug stuff, I'd rather just have it.
Clear.
That seems like
Like fine fine idea.
Okay.
And so, let's see in the render group, we have a push truck for the
renter group, that's fine.
That should be cleared, that's all good.
We've got to push size here for the max put buffer size that should
definitely knock it cleared because that's a push buffer and the push
buffer is getting overwritten all the time.
Anyway, that should not be cleared, I don't think that's a good idea.
So, let's see here, push render elements, that should take care of it
itself.
So let's keep going.
That is just talking about the push buffer.
And let's see push bitmap push render element push bitmap.
If it map on track blah blah.
These are not actually things that push memory which render elements
push struct Sim region when we do begin Sim.
So there's the zero struct SIM region hash which is the majority of
it.
So I think what we want to do is just let it clear.
The whole thing that seems like a better call to me.
Then we got next in hash that can clear out, that seems reasonable
again.
I like having those cleared, I like the extra safety in case.
There's some forgotten variable.
That's always good.
Can create world that can clear.
Just fine.
And dandy block also fine.
Pair wise, Collision rules also fine, push struct.
Yeah.
What is the saying, not World Arena change using the fundamental types
Arena?
I am going to let that to do stand for.
We look at it before but yeah that can easily be cleared.
No question.
So can that for that matter, simcha entity Collision, volume group,
push struct that seems fine to all of.
That seems pretty good to me.
All right, those are some other bitmaps.
Feel ground chunk back in, definitely clear mode Arena.
That's fine.
See, bitmap wrecked outline again.
Nothing really in there.
That's all just graphic stuff and down.
All right, so now we've kind of told what, to clear and whatnot to
clear.
You can kind of see that we've got this one that I didn't Define yet.
That's just don't clear.
So we now need to make sure that we actually have that one.
So we've got no clear.
That doesn't take anything.
All it is.
Is the default with nothing.
All right, so now these guys.
What do they actually do will sew a line.
No.
Clear.
Should take the alignment and do it.
This guy should take the alignment and do it.
This guy should, presumably use the default, so we could actually even
just do default Arena params and then just set the flags to basically
just not have Arena flag, clear, 20?
So really, we just say, whatever the default was, you know, we let
that do its thing and that seems pretty fair to me.
Yeah.
In fact, we could do that on all of these, we could just have it be
that we clear that flag.
You know what I'm saying?
So that flag gets cleared and then we overwrite the alignment.
I guess is what I would say.
This guy kind of needs to rewrite it but it could do something.
It could actually just do this.
Right.
So if you clear
Else.
You don't.
So that way, every time we do it, we actually start with whatever the
default is.
So if we added more Flags to the default, these guys would just
inherit those flags, which maybe is a better idea.
I don't know that it is or not, but I'm just going to say that for
now, we'll do it that way.
Okay, insert block that's wrong.
That's gotta get a parentheses around.
It obviously six that and now I think we're in better shape.
So hopefully and I don't know if this is true.
Hopefully we'll get closer to running faster.
Okay, we do which is good.
Again, that's something I've been wanting to do for a while and
hopefully that's something that.
Yeah.
Now, you can see it runs much more snappily, so that's all good.
So, we're in good shape there.
Yeah, right.
Good deal.
So where are we on time?
We gotta we had about 15 minutes of the class.
We've got about 20 minutes.
Left is what I believe that we have.
And so, one other thing that we could do, now, I'm trying to think
about whether
It's is enough time to really do it.
I wanted to go ahead and start making the the concept of the memory
Arenas flow all the way down to the operating system level.
Because I really wanted to do some stuff where for example we could
have a Rena's that can grow where the operating system just gives us
more memory as we grow them.
And the reason I want to do that is for example.
First of all, we may want to just run on the PC that way for example
because it's the PC as virtual memory and people may want to run
really huge worlds or something, we might want to just let them use
all the memory in their machine if they want.
Right?
Whereas on something like Raspberry Pi maybe where we've got a
specific amount of memory we got to fit into, we wouldn't do that.
But more importantly, even if we always make sure the game only runs
within a certain fixed, allocation that starts the beginning, because
we just want to do it that way.
Even on the PC, our debug system should never have to run through
that, right?
The debug system is a separate set of memory and that should be able
to run through some grobel thing.
But just ask the operating system for more memory and who cares,
right?
It's the debug system.
Never ships on the user's machine.
So, I did want to add that, but in 20 minutes, I think that might be a
little bit, it might be a little bit tight.
I think it's my guess.
So yeah, so I'm not sure exactly what we want to do there but that
definitely does seem like something that I want to do eventually.
So the question is, what do I want to do now?
And I don't really know.
That's a really good question.
One thing that we could do, you know what might be fun, what might be
fun as to start fixing the render or sorting, that seems like
something that might be fun.
And there's a couple of things in the render that I wanted to fix.
That was ready to that.
So what we could do is Implement a really, really
That sort like a bubble sort or something in the renderer.
So that when we come back from break, we can replace it with a good
sort or something like that.
That might be fun, right?
That's that, that I could see that being at the thing, right?
And I don't even know that we would get to that if we just started
that that's the other thing.
So maybe that's a bad idea to because if I started it, you probably
wouldn't get a chance.
Pension, because really the hard part about the Sorting is going to be
figuring out how to structure the stuff in the push buffer in such a
way that it can be sorted conveniently.
So there's there's that which is also kind of weird.
I don't know, maybe it's not that hard.
I'd have to think about it.
All right, let's just take a look II.
Don't have any better idea of what to do.
So we might as well look, right?
I mean if I don't have a better idea let's just take a look so what
happens at the moment, right?
You know, we've got this sort of this concept of
Rendering all our stuff.
And we kind of do a thing where we go.
Like, okay, you know, when we do our tiled render, we call tiled
render group to Output, so sorry.
No, that's not what we call.
We call something a little lower level than that.
I mean, are a little higher level in that first.
Right?
We call.
Yeah, child artist.
So we call tiled render grouped output times where I've seen the wrong
function.
That is what we call and whatever that does, is it sets up a bunch of
thread work, where the render can run a multiple threads and it lets
the platform layer go, you know spawn.
Make sure all those guys can do the work.
And sort of Spawn it off, right?
And so each one of those is going to call the function that that's
going to call is is this thing right here?
Do tiled render work and that do tiled render work function.
I suppose that's probably in are optimized.
Do tiled render work?
Or is it not?
Where is it?
Here it is so that do table render work.
That's going to go ahead and do, you know what's kind of funny, too?
We still do our alternating even odd lines thing.
Even though we were going to do something where that would be hyper
threaded base.
But we never actually did that.
I don't know if you guys remember that because we never really went
and did any super serious optimizations on the renderer because
somehow the simple optimizations we did and it up making it run at 60
frames a second 1080p which is crazy.
These machines are so darn, fast these days.
So anyway, yeah, that's kind of hilarious.
We should probably just stop doing that scan line alternating.
It probably just slowing us down at this point.
In fact, I wonder if we should just try it and see if it is like
whether it gets faster to not do that, right?
I feel like I feel like it just would.
Yeah.
I'm-i'm-i'm so tour and I know there's so many things we could be
doing and so little time you only got
You know 15 minutes left on the clock here.
It's ridiculous anyway but yeah that's kind of funny like we do render
group to output and we've got this concept of the even odd things and
we don't even use them and I don't know that we ever will because I
couldn't think of a good way to actually launch the hyper threads to
like interleave together like that because you can't really
synchronize.
You don't even necessarily know when to hyper threads are going to go
pick up something from the job queue.
So yeah, let's just pull
that join us.
Pull that out.
It just seems dumb.
You know what I mean?
Just seems kind of dumb.
Let's pull it out.
Let's just do it.
Let's just say.
So yeah.
Like let's let's figure out what our frame rate actually is at this
point let me go ahead and to handmade handmade the build I guess is
what it is.
Build that bat, let's go into build up at and turn on him internal
because if I remember correctly all this stuff was still working.
It's just a question of
of not supporting the hot code reloading because we had finished some
of the toughest rings.
So what's the problem here?
No.
Constructor can get Arena.
Sighs remaining Katarina size remaining is taking the alignment value
of 1, I guess.
So I guess I would just do no.
Clear one or something or align.
No clear.
Something like that.
Alright, so there we go.
There is our rendering there and you can kind of see that we're a bit
slow on the cutscenes, which is what we would expect because we're
doing all the over drawing.
Right.
And I suppose, the other thing we should do is take out our lock loop
for now.
So if I go into win32 handmade, we had a thing where we were, you
know, basically time here.
So, we have real V bank support.
I said I was turning that off, so let's take a look.
So that's what our current timing is, right?
It's like 3633, right?
So again, I'm not actually going to try to optimize this.
If once we actually want to do optimization, we need to do something.
We're actually taking really consistent, timings not just kind of
like, messing around and seeing it, but I just wanted to make sure
that the frame counter was up there to make sure that I didn't do
something really stupid like change for the even and odd thing and end
up like super tanking, our frame rate.
First want to make sure we kind of knew roughly.
What it was so that when I do this because I wanted to pull this out
because we're not really going to use it and it could only be wasting
time.
That I'm not doing something that I don't actually just not understand
and to turn out to make things much worse, right?
So I'm going to take that get even thing that that even odds in this
thing and I'm just going to get rid of that entirely.
Okay, so we got draw a rectangle and draw a rectangle quickly.
Draw a rectangle takes even.
I'm going to take a look at what even is actually doing.
So all it does is offset.
Yeah.
So all it does is say oh if we were only since we're doing even and
the Min was at one, I'm going to advance but I'm pretty sure we can
just get rid of that, right?
And now, we would just do plus plus on these guys directly and we
should be good to go, right?
And then draw a rectangle quickly is, are optimized one.
There's our even if I look at for even it looks like it's still just
basically doing that and then when we again when we advance
Row to row.
We would have to do something to make sure that we weren't going by
twice.
So there's row advance.
Two times, buffer pitch.
So I think, again, all I would really have to do.
There is say just regular buffer pitch, and then the row Advance
should be correct, right?
I think function is not take arguments.
Is that true?
Draw a rectangle quickly.
Do we predefined that we do get rid of that.
So there we go, and let's see if that works.
Any better.
Fanta.
It's beautiful.
Isn't it?
Look at how beautiful that is?
Well, we totally nailed it guys.
Good job looks really good.
I think it'd be hard to argue that.
That we totally did that seamlessly.
All right, not not a great showing, not not fabulous.
That was not really very good job.
It's true.
But don't worry about it, you know, just this, let's not worry about
that.
So okay, let's let's take it a little bit slower here and and see if
we can figure out what I messed up.
So the clip rect is is properly set here because we were doing evens
and odds separate of that.
So we know we're still doing our region stuff, and that should be
correct.
These guys don't care about even odds at all.
So we only have the two functions draw, a rectangle, and draw a
rectangle quickly, right?
So what we should be able to do is we should be able to just like,
look, I
The final inspection for doing all hopping the bugger, this guy
shouldn't have done anything differently, right?
You can see that.
It's pretty much straight forward.
It was, it's just incrementing.
Oh, we didn't change the counter.
That's the problem on this guy.
We're still in incrementing y by 2 each time.
So that would that would do it.
Yeah.
So there we go.
And if anything that definitely did get a little faster, but again,
like I said, we're not really timing it so I feel like but it's the
same basic values as it was before.
Or so, I feel like that's a safe thing to remove.
We don't have to care about that.
We're even odd thing anymore, so that's good.
All right.
See what's going on here.
Yeah, so that doesn't look any different to me.
I don't know if looks like different to you, but like I said, we'd
have to really tie it to be sure.
But I don't think we want to proceed with that interleave thing.
Because it just seemed like a dumb idea.
Maybe not who knows just want to double check.
So okay, inside the render group then all I want to point out is in
order to put ourselves in a position where we're going to be able to
sort these things, we need some way of knowing like what we're even
sorting.
So when we do that that that do tiled that sort of do tiled concept,
right?
So in here we're we're like tiled render group, what's it called?
Do do tile, better work.
That guy.
So when we do our render group to Output that's going to Loop through
all of these guys, as we go, and it's sort of going to it's going to
do it's going to do the rendering operation immediately whenever it
sees the guy.
And so right now what happens is our stuff, just gets drawn in
whatever order, it's shown there.
And so we would have to do instead is figure out a way to like draw
these in a different order, right?
In some other order.
That's that's really the long and short of it.
And so in order to do that we need some way to to sort them in order
to sort them.
We need some way of of.
Looking at them as a, you know, as a whole we need some way of being
able to compare, you know, one to the other and swap their locations.
And typically we usually want to do that in a way that's fairly random
access.
And as you can see from the way we did it, here are pushed buffers are
packed.
So we have we Advanced by a base address each time as we go.
And if you look at what we actually have four things that are in here,
one question might be whether that was actually a good.
Good idea if that's even necessary or if these things can be the same
size, right?
Because essentially, all we've got and, you know, possibly all we're
going to have is just fixed some things that could have been fixed
size, right?
Like, all of these things could probably be the same rough size, and
then we wouldn't, then we would just have our our actual push buffer
would be something.
We could just sort in place, you know, what I mean.
And that seems like,
Good idea.
however, that said
It may also be the case that we don't super care because it may be the
case that what we actually want to do is just first fix pre-call
everything to see what falls inside each tile and then only sort have
each thread sort only the contents of its bucket, right?
Because remember the way I render work is we break the scene into
tiles and each thread renders the different tile of the screen.
And so, what we could do is just say like, oh, we'll do a first pass
and that first past builds like a little array of the things that
actually need to get output.
And then from there, we sort those, right?
That seems kind of compelling to me.
I feel like that's probably the way we should do it so I feel like we
might want to start with something like that.
I feel like that might be the best idea.
Yeah.
All right, so let's let's see what we would have to do for that.
So when we do our do tiled render work, when we actually do that, we
would need some weight place to store that that information, right?
We need a way to store that and lucky for us.
We actually know the maximum number of things that we could possibly
have.
And so I feel like we could easily do something where when we do our
push buffer like in here,
When we do this stuff, where we say, like okay, you know, here's our
push buffer.
We could also do a thing where we just count as we go through, we
could do like push buffer element count or something like that, you
know what I mean?
So, however, much stuff is in there.
We can just track it and so,
We do push buffer size, like, when we do allocate render group and we
set the push for, besides the zero.
We can also set the push, buffer, element count, 20,
and then every time something gets pushed, you know, every time a
render element gets pushed, then when we do that render, when we do
that that push we increment
The element count.
So that way, we would know exactly how many elements there actually
were.
And does that ever get reset?
Just curious.
Oops.
It does.
So we could also say that, right?
So it gets cleared on on and render as well seems fair.
So that is a pretty reasonable thing to do, I suspect and that way
when we go and we're actually going to start the do child render work.
We would know when we prepare our work struct, like this thing.
We could give it a space for its temporary storage, so that sorting
that it needs to do, we could just say, all right, you'll get a place
for your sorting and I don't know what that D, but it be, you know,
whatever the tile sort entry or something like this, right?
And it'd be like an Offset, you know, push buffer offset.
And like this,
Key something like this.
And we would just say, okay, you know, when you are, when you are
called, you have your sort sort space, you know, you just get some
space that you can use for sorting and that'd be pretty
straightforward, right?
So when we call render group child render group to Output, or I guess
really, in either case, we create that
That sort space.
So that would just be like, all right, the work sort space is
temporary memory.
So we're going to need a way to get temporary memory and I forget how
we did our begin temporary memory, forgetting stuff.
We just do it off of the memory Arena and so I assume that's going to
go on the transient arena there and so we want some place to do that
work.
Yeah.
Well.
Just trying to think of exactly how we want to do this.
Cuz the sort space has to happen in both cases and I just want a nice
clean way to do that.
You know, essentially what I'm thinking is something like okay,
This guy.
Well, you know, honestly I think it's just this.
I think it's just that these guys have to be given the temporary Arena
that they're going to use and I don't actually see any or this guy
doesn't actually do anything with an arena usually.
So I think that's going to have to be something that you just pass in
the temporary memory, right?
So the arena where you want to get the temporary memory from.
And so then all it would do is it would say like okay you know, at the
start of this, I'm going to do begin temporary memory on the temporary
NE.
And then I'm going to end it.
Here.
Right.
And that's really it, I think.
So, here is the sword entry.
And I need however, many of those as we have render elements, right?
So I need to say that the render group push push element count or
whatever pushed buffer element cap.
I need to get space for as many entries as there are elements because
that that may be there may be that many of them.
So yeah so we could do that and that's good.
Push a ray needs to take the tempering as well I think.
Yeah and so that's same thing needs to happen in our tiled one and I
don't actually know
Yeah, that anything weird has to happen.
It's basically exactly the same.
So this is going to just be oops.
this is just going to take the same stuff and do exactly the same
thing only instead of allocating, one of those going to allocate one
per
right.
So that's just going to say, all right, for each of these guys, the
work sort space.
Is going to be that.
And we're good.
Okay, so these guys just have to take the translate Tran Arena.
I believe is really all that has to happen so that they can allocate
their sort of their temporary memory from it.
Oh, although this guy since he's in a task
He would have to get it from his own memory.
This right here.
Okay, so that's fine.
And tiled render group to Output.
This guy gets it presumably from the Tran, the actual Tran Arena.
Not that.
Yeah.
Wait a second.
Where was that?
Why do we have two calls to tiled render group to Output?
Do you understand that?
All right, the debugger calls it.
Okay, that's totally fine and I don't really know.
So in the debugger also again like I don't really know very much about
how we want that guy to manage its memory.
But presumably, since it's just using the temporary memory right
inside that window, it doesn't really matter.
And it can always use like, the debug arena for that or it could use
either of these.
Actually, I don't think it matters at all because it's only within
that tile.
State that it would ever care.
So I think that should be fine.
And and off it goes.
All right, so I'm going to end it there and that's actually perfect
because then we're not really getting into sorting at all.
So it's not like a cliffhanger anything, but now it's good.
Because now we have a situation where these guys in their Tubman to
work.
They have space for sorting.
And so, really, what I can do when we start off is we can take this
render group to Output stuff.
We can go ahead and make that right into those entries and off you go.
Off you go from there, and it will take a little more time to do, but
should be okay.
So I'm going to go ahead and go to the Q&A.
We could take a couple minutes of Q&A here and then that'll be it for
a while.
And we come back, we'll get our render ass properly sorting, which I
think would be a good idea.
Sergey RGV.
Could you tell us roughly how the expanding Arena would be
implemented?
Yeah, it's totally trivial.
Right?
So like I mean, it's super, super trivial.
The only thing you do is right here instead of this assertion you
replace this assertion and instead you just do it.
If if you can't satisfy it you just call the operating system from our
memory.
That's it.
So the only complexity comes in in implementing the temporary memory
thing because that has to rewind.
So there's a little bit more there.
You what you'll see.
But it's it's like stupid simple, right?
Insofar as it's, the lower level memory, nothing you mentioned.
PC basically just what Malik virtual act does not really because
virtual lock and Malik actually do memory coalescing and stuff.
They're a little more complicated than memory Arenas are like the
simplest form for the most part of allocator and Malik actually tries
to like reuse blocks and it allows you to free and allocate in any
order and all that stuff.
So that's a worse problem, right?
That's a little more of a serious thing.
Simon Denton, I got the cane our book to learn.
See any other useful resources.
I take online stuff with a grain of salt.
I don't know the wrong one to ask you.
Probably the stream.
Is the better people to ask cast?
05 is interlaced the same as interleaved.
You know, yes or no.
Interleaved is just a general term.
That means that you're doing two things.
Alternating interlaced is a very specific term that refers to a way
that displays work and it refers to the display methodology of first
displaying all of the even rows or odd rows, depending on, which
parodies start with first displaying every other row, then jumping
back to the top and doing every other
Row that you didn't do, right?
That's very specifically interlaced.
So interlace is a very specific term interleaved, could mean anything.
Interleave can basically mean anything that alternates between two
things is an interleave, so, interlaced, very specific talking about
displays interleaved could be talking about anything.
Connor rents.
What should I do with my life while handmade hero is on break?
Well, I set you up to implement a sort, implement the sort.
Beat me to it.
Everything is there you should in two weeks or however, long.
It's going to take it.
Should be a little less than two weeks, probably or something like,
two weeks before I will be back here in able to program on this
machine again.
You should be able to get all that working.
Super Cub, which algorithm do you plan on using for sorting?
I don't know.
We'll start with a bubble sort.
Which is the stupidest kind, like the most basic kind and then we'll
try implementing one of the more complex sword, sorts like a merge
sort and we'll actually see what the performance is.
Because sorting is weird.
Like, sometimes, stupid sorts are better than smart sorts, depending
on the circumstances.
So it's kind of hard.
K.
Why are we running in a Windows application using wind main instead of
a console one?
So the reason is because if you build your app, if you build your
Windows, executable as a console, then when people launched it, it
spawns a little console window.
Always, it's no way to get rid of it.
And so, it's just really unprofessional to have a game that starts up
and it has this.
It's, it's window.
And the stupid console window there, right?
So, if you really want that you can't, there are some ways of getting
around it.
And what you do there is you actually look to find your console window
and then you hide it.
So no one can see it.
But again, since we don't need that, I don't understand why you would
ever do that.
Like I'm not sure why.
You wouldn't just build it as a Windows or regular Windows application
instead of a consultation, right?
K3.
Why was the interlacing leaving at in the first place?
It was added because
I was thinking it might be a good idea to have hyper threads where
each hyper thread was rendering, an alternating lines, because then
they would hit the cash optimally on that core.
But I never could really think of a way to make, to force the threads
to actually run in that way.
So I think it was just kind of a waste of time.
Insofar as how many to do is, are there in the code now?
I have no idea.
Not that many, I guess, let's see.
227.
Is there much overhead this morning to render threads every frame
instead of keeping them around?
We do not spawn render threads every frame, we keep them around.
And yes there would be quite a bit of overhead spawning.
The memory frame, which is why we don't do it.
Culver fly.
Do you always start with software rendering when working on games?
No, I don't ever start with software rendering.
I did that strictly so that people on the stream could learn how a
graphics card works.
Because if you just call a graphics card and say, draw my Graphics,
you never have any idea how they actually work.
And so only people who used to have to write renderers from before the
GPU days, like, in, you know, 9594 they all know how they work, and it
gives them a lot of insight into Graphics, you know, stuff.
And so I wanted to make sure everyone had that experience.
At least once,
For New Years.
Can we get a marathon?
Maybe I'll think about it.
Ryan Reed is, can you do really smooth animation GTI, without vsync?
I don't know these days.
Windows is very different nowadays than it was when I started
programming on it and I haven't played much with the arrow compositor.
So I don't really know.
I really have no idea.
It's not that relevant for games because you have to go through the
GPU eventually for games, more directly.
Anyway, like even if we kept our software rendering,
Never did a hardware renderer.
I'd still want to do the small bit of code to get us running through
opengl so that we can get vsync, right?
So I really just don't know much about about what would happen if you
decided not to do that.
Simple question.
But how do you forward declare a struct in Pura?
See, I have type def struct Fufu.
How do I forward declare this?
I tried typedef struct Fufu, but didn't work, I don't know that you
can
Do that.
I'm sorry.
I don't know.
I probably didn't know one point and I probably forgot.
M, 1, E LL.
Do you have any opposition for not putting transparent pixels?
No, we just.
So right now, this is like, again, this is one of those things where
like it's just crazy, how fast computers are.
So it's sick that this thing runs at 30 frames a second basically
because this is like, I don't even remember how many 10 levels of
overdraw, it's a strong everything.
So like everything behind the house is getting drawn like ten times on
top of each other, right?
And there's no optimization
He's in there for that right now.
So if we wanted to, we could speed these things up dramatically,
right?
We could probably make these things render at four or five times the
speed they're running at now.
But it's just crazy how they're the CPUs are just so fast that if we
want our, if we wanted our cutscenes to run at 30 frames a second we
don't even have to do that work, which is crazy.
That's just it's just sick.
Yeah, it's just it's so bizarre.
Let's see here.
Hubert Keller.
Once you have sorting implanted, do you think you will change the
render to draw front to back?
We could, we might
It's not a bad idea, like I said, when we talked about it before and
we could do some optimizations there, but yeah, I don't know, it's a
good question.
Elvin.
Is there any way to use a console instead and hide that talking about
Windows applications from task manager, Etc?
I'm not sure what you're asking is there any way to use a console
Stead and hide.
That hide?
What?
Act binary.
Can you give a quick overview of the way?
Memory is managed at the moment push Arena.
Begin temp, Arena Etc.
Well yeah, I mean there's really very little to it.
The way that we manage memory is extraordinarily simple and like I
said, it's, that's kind of why I always say that it's not that big of
a deal.
Like it takes a little bit of work on handmade hero because we don't
really have that much code for it and I have to write it all on the
stream.
But once you've written some
Usually pretty easy to just ignore memory management almost entirely
and there's just a few places in your software, you care about it.
So,
But in terms of memory management, right now, all we do is we just
say, we have a block of memory and it's however much you want to use
for the game.
So, let's say you want to use a gigabyte of memory for the game or
something, and then we just partition it into slices.
So we say like, oh this part will be used for the assets or something.
This part will be used for the game or whatever and technically we do
this a little bit early.
So really instead of giving the game, the whole one gigabyte, what we
do at startup, as we actually say, this part of it is one chunk.
Right.
This is a chunk and this is a chunk at the operating system level.
So we have this thing called like the permanent Arena and the
transient Arena.
But then all that happens is once we have that we just start stacking
things up on it, that's it.
That's all we do.
So a given arena is just a big buffer of memory.
We start here with nothing in it and as we put things on it we just
push them down, right?
So we just keep pushing it down.
So, here's the thing, there's a new thing, there's a new thing, it's
just a stack and the way we handle temporary memory is we just say,
remember where the stack pointer was use, all this stuff, however, you
want, and then jump back.
So when you're done with it, we just pretend it never happened.
And then the new stuff that gets out.
Edible right over it.
That's it.
There's nothing else there.
It's the simplest darn thing.
All right.
I'll switch.
Are you still using top bat file compilations?
Yes, this is our heroes are our build.
Here's our build system.
That's the build system.
All right.
All right, I think that's just about it.
So I'm going to wrap it up.
Let's go ahead and save all this up and close it on down.
All right, thank you, everyone for joining me for another episode of
handmade here.
It's been a pleasure clothing with you.
As always, if you would like to follow along the series at home, you
can always go to handmade hero dot org and pre-order the game in which
comes with the source code even as we speak.
So, every night I upload the latest changes and you can play around
with them.
There's also a forum site, you can go to where you can ask questions
or if you are anti-deficit guy, there's a patreon page.
You can subscribe to.
If you want to support the video series.
And there is a tweet bot which treats the schedule.
If you want to catch a series Live and the next time we will be live.
Be after Christmas break, I will not be here.
So I cannot keep streaming, unfortunately, I would if I could, but I
can't.
So keep an eye on the tree pod, find out when that is, I suspect, it
will be sometime around New Year's.
So check back around then or just make sure you scrub feet Bott.
And it will tell you that's about it.
Hope you guys have a good holiday season and doing whatever you're
doing.
And I will see you guys on the internet in the meantime.
So take it easy.
Easy everyone and I'll see you in 2016.