Hello, everyone, and welcome to handmade hero.
The show where we code a complete game live on Twitch.
We don't use any libraries and we do not use any engines and the
reason for that is because we are absolute control freaks here.
People, we are absolute control things.
It is just simply not acceptable to have other people touching our
pixels.
Those are our pixels, and we want to put them there.
And we don't want somebody else going around deciding how those pixels
go that it's simply unacceptable and we are not okay with it.
So right now we're in the middle of doing some optimization work and
the kind of optimization we're doing is multi-threading and we did
most of the work we need to do to multi-thread yesterday.
So, we are in a position today.
We got one thing, we should probably fix, but we're in a position
today after we fix that to go actually have our newly-created,
multi-threading system actually, do some of the rendering work.
Will allow us to start seeing how that that performance is affected in
the face of multi-threading.
So with that in mind let me get right to it.
But before I do let me say that today is day 125.
So if you have pre-ordered the game on handmade here at Oregon, you
want to follow along with the source code you want to unpack day 124
is source code.
That's the thing you want to do because that is what I'm starting with
right here right now.
All right so when we left
Our fearless, handmade hero yesterday.
We were at a point where we had gotten our little simple job queue guy
working.
It's not a very complex q but you know it got the job done.
And we had tested some various things.
We have our little strings pushing in here and we had it so that
everything seemed to be working relatively straightforwardly.
Although, you know, we don't have any real serious testing hear of it.
So, you know, we're not we're not like totally confident.
That every last thing has been ironed out, but we've got it, working
reasonably well.
So, the only thing that we hadn't done is this main thread here,
right?
The way that this works, is this main thread here?
When it does, all this work and pushes this work on here, we had it,
go ahead and go into this, spinlock to wait to see when the other
threads were done.
And there's two reasons that we don't want to do that, right?
This was just like a placeholder, there's two reasons, why we don't
want to do that.
The first reason is, obviously that it wastes a bunch of battery
power, right?
Your to have a set thread just sitting there waiting for other threads
to do stuff.
That doesn't seem like a very good idea to me.
Hopefully doesn't seem like a very good idea to you.
And secondly
It actually waste performance to write.
Because if we're going to be using this thread, instead of having it
waste processor time sitting here, checking the same variable over and
over and over again, for no reason, wouldn't it be much smarter for us
to actually use the this work to this thread to actually do work.
So, what I would like to say
Just to The suggestible Listener.
Is that instead of ever because we can do something here, we could
have it weighed on a signal and Signal it or something.
We could we could put this thread to sleep and solve the battery
problem and the performance problem because another thread would take
care of that way, it would work, right?
But we're wasting a bunch of time doing that sort of handshaking, when
really, why bother because what we could do instead is just stay well
whenever we kick off a bunch of these threads, if the main thread that
actually queued up, all the work,
It's to sit there and wait for the other threads to finish.
Why doesn't it?
Just do some work itself.
Like, what is it some kind of lazy lay about?
Like, that's no good, right?
So what I would like to propose if nobody has any objections is here
in our thread proc, we actually change this around a little bit,
instead we make a little inline function called like, you know, worker
thread or do worker work or something like this.
And that just returns a Bool 32.
And what I want it to do is I wanted to do this this operation right
here, essentially, right?
I want it to do this, this interior bit, right?
So it's going to actually do that work, do that actual stuff that was
happening in here, right?
But it's going to do when it does this check, right?
It'll actually do it like this and it will return whether or not it
actually did any work at all.
Right.
It'll just it'll just see, okay?
so, at that point,
what we'll do is say, you know, did some work equals false
And then, you know, call in here, will return, did some work.
And that way, anytime we go through here will actually say that we did
some work and return it out, right?
So, now, what we can do is we can say, you know, if do worker work
didn't do anything then we go to sleep, right?
Like, so that's it.
All right.
So now what we can do, just got to see what I have to pass this here.
What does this actually want?
It looks like this just needs.
Well, it needs the printout.
It's logical thread index and it needs nothing else, really?
So we'll just go ahead and pass that logical, thread index, logical,
thread index.
Like so.
There we go.
And I will go ahead and we need the thread into the go away.
And that's
that.
So if we do it this way, right now, we have the ability to let our
normal thread out here, right?
Actually do work.
So, what we can do instead is for the entire time, but if we haven't
actually completed everything,
We can actually have this guy do actual useful work, right?
And what we could do here is we could say, all right, if we're going
to have eight threads working, right, then we do seven threads worth
of of work up here, we launched, seven of those threads here and the
eight thread, right?
Is actually going to be our our main thread.
Okay?
So now what this thread will actually do is it will spin lock a little
bit.
It'll spin lock just at the very, very end.
What?
Probably what we wanted to do because we don't want to ever shut down
completely.
We want one of our korres always going full speed, probably, right?
So if we do it this way, what we should be able to do is make it.
So that now anytime this main thread, what's this main thread does,
all the queuing, it can then sit there doing actual work the whole
time and then only once there's no more work to do, will it actually
pop out and finish, right?
And so if I go ahead and run this now we should get the exact same
behavior we got before, right?
We still get
Waiting so it doesn't actually go anywhere.
But now we can also see that it's actually doing work here and we can
also even see that that that main thread thread seven actually did
something.
It actually did some of the work right, which is perfect, that's what
we want.
So this gets us out of the business of ever using an actual signal
level thing or anything, to put the main thread to sleep, we can just
leave the main thread on and that should probably be okay.
We can revisit it when we go to ship.
If there's any reasons why we see that it made.
Be untenable to continue doing so.
But for now, I think that's probably the best way to do it, right?
So what do we want to do now?
Right?
We want to start moving this into some kind of format that will allow
for the the renderer itself to actually make use of this thing, right?
We need to sort of get this in some way that the platform independent
code can actually start to do this.
And I don't know exactly how we want to do that.
Like I said, you know, a lot of times on the stream I try to actually
design stuff while you are watching.
To me rather than having an ID ahead of time of how I'm going to do it
just so you can see how I work through it.
So I don't have any preconceived notion of how that might happen.
I'm simply going to go start doing it, right?
And like I said, I always try to follow the compression oriented
programming approach of just like, see what you have to do, to get
something to work and then look at what.
Look at it after you, get it working and go.
What can I simplify cure?
What?
Can I make more robust?
What can I pull out as reusable?
Blah, blah, blah, blah, right?
So we're going to do exactly that.
We're just going to jump in to render group.
And the the handmade renderer group stuff here and we're going to take
a quick look to see what we could be doing in terms of getting this
thing to be multi-threaded, right?
And like I said, there's one problem with the renderer right now
that's a thing that is a problem in terms of our multi-threading that
will address a little bit later.
I'll talk about that a little later, maybe tomorrow, whatever it won't
ever caused a crash or
Thing.
But it might cause some bad results for us.
So we'll talk about that later.
But for right now, what I want to do is focus on this guy right here,
tiled render group to Output, right?
And so, what I want to do is I want to figure out a way that when we
call this function, just very simply as want to figure out a way we
call this function, I want to be able to dispatch these on multiple
threads, okay?
So you can kind of take a look here.
You can see what we've got, we're calling this render group to Output
thing and
We're calling it for each of these tiles.
So, what I want to do is my very first step.
We haven't really talked too much about how we're going to try and get
hyper threading to work here.
That's going to be a.
It's going to be a whole nother situation, but for the time being what
we'd like to do is just be able to take each of these tiles and launch
each of these tiles on a separate thread, right?
So we've got this for I Loop and what we want to do is figure out some
way to make the four I Loop turn into something.
Are several threads can be pulling from what that for I Loop is
generating, you know, over time basically.
So
I feel like,
The first thing that I would like to do is make it so that we're just
kind of able to recreate.
If you will, what the the tilak style why stuff is without having
actually, having to have multiple things here, although maybe, you
know, I guess is we don't really even care about that.
Our work queue is pretty General, maybe we just go ahead and actually
use the work queue seems pretty reasonable actually.
All right, let's just do this.
Let's do this.
I don't know.
I'm gonna just go Whole Hog on this.
So what I want to do is I want to just pull the work queue entry
straight on out of here.
I want to basically just say, all right let's let's make that now, be
a thing that is in our platform header file that the game can utilize.
I'm just going to say let's full-on do it, right?
So, maybe up here somewhere after we talked about the debug cycle
counter stuff, and whatever.
I'm going to go, go ahead here,
Say, all right.
We've got work to use entries.
And maybe the way that we do the work queue entry thing is will
actually just say, you know what, I really want to deal with anything
too unusual here.
so, I think what I might say is
Although you know what?
I'm going to even take that back, I feel like we could even do it with
variable sized stuff.
I think we can pretty much do this almost the whole way.
Alright, alright.
Alright I take it back, we can pretty much do this, even with variable
sized work entries for almost no cost actually so that does seem like
the right thing to do.
All right so let's start extracting this out a little bit more so what
we want to actually do right here.
Is we want to be able to make sure.
You can see what actually happens here.
We want to be able to make sure that we can push things on to the
work.
You safely.
Now, right now, we don't actually have any need to push things onto a
work queue from more than one thread at once, right, we only have one
person.
This is why I say about single producer.
We have single producer, multiple consumer, we base, they have one
person producing work and then many people Gathering up the work.
So, for now, since we know that that's really all we wanted and that's
possibly all we'll ever want because we don't necessarily
Necessarily have an envisioned use case for multiple producer,
multiple consumer since that's the case.
Currently, I'm going to go ahead and say that.
What we want to do is change this guy here to be called something
like, you know, add work queue entry, right?
And what add work queue entry is going to do is add work.
Queue entry will leave this.
The the semaphore handle will now be something that's, you know, some
kind of global variable that's for managing
He's or something and we'll kind of work out.
Exactly how we want to do that.
Probably, I'm guessing what we'll do.
You know what, we won't even have to make it Global.
What we'll do is we'll we'll have a thing called a work queue here
that has it in it, right?
And that'll just be blind.
That that that work.
You thing will be blind.
The platform layer will be will be structured.
Such that the, the game never actually sees it.
Okay, so it'll pass back in the work queue, right?
And the add work, queue entry.
All that will actually do is it will just basically tell you which,
which work queue entry, it was going to be in some sense, right?
Or you're essentially going to tell it which, which work queue entry,
it was right, so we're not going to pass in the string.
We're just going to we're just going to assume that you did the right
thing to fill out your cue, whatever that Q is.
So all we're going to do is guarantee that whatever you did
beforehand.
Um it's very 'red which it would pretty much have to because it's a
function.
All we're going to do here is we're just going to release that
semaphore.
So all add work work queue entry is going to do.
Is it's going to go ahead and release that semaphore.
Oh, well, you know what, to?
I also want it to manage the the entry count thing, right?
So, basically up in here, somewhere in this work queue, we are going
to have here that entry count and that's going to be a volatile like,
so.
So the end to end, in fact, I guess we probably want all of these
things in the work queue, right?
We just want all the things that we had before.
There we go.
So, we're going to go ahead and do it that way.
Like, so, do the increment, do the semaphore stuff?
All that looks good.
No, no.
We're just there.
And what that actually means is that if we call in here, that actually
means that I won't have to
Make these platform nonspecific.
I can pretty much make these be just baked in here, right?
So, that's pretty cool.
So, we can, when we do complete past rights before future rights, we
can actually, just go ahead and put those in here.
Explicitly.
Like so to make sure those fences happened.
All right, and by the way I did double-check this the right orange
stuff in the CPU and it looks to me, like, what I said yesterday was
not actually true anymore, it looks to me like, the x64
Ordering has been weakened from what it was on the x86 a while back.
And so I'm actually not comfortable saying that it has the strong,
right, ordering?
Any more, I want to do a little more research on it and ask some
people at Intel, but it does look like now on x64.
You do want to do s fences to ensure that your that you have a store
barrier in the actual code.
So it's good that we put that in there.
It looks like it is actually necessary.
But I want to find a little bit more out about it, but for now I'm
going to go with.
We do actually need to do the store barrier there.
Once upon a time.
You didn't need a store barrier but but you do now.
Alright.
So anyway,
I can put in the Reed barrier as well.
I can copy that in here so there's our read barrier.
So
So now this entry is this work queue entries thing.
That's actually I'm going to go ahead and pull that down here for two
are into our test code.
I'm not going to actually allow this this code up here to do that so
that we can play with that a little bit more.
Although I guess I should say we probably still will need to make it
the global.
Well we do the testing but it'll be a global below the thread procs so
that it can't see it.
All right, so what we want to do is we want to say, all right, we've
got this work you, right?
And the work queue entry is again, as this is now a test thing that
goes down there.
So we've got these work cues, and the workkeys have a semaphore handle
that they need to release.
And they have their sort of Q elements like the, you know, the
pointers and so on.
Right.
And what I should also to have in here is a Max entry count, probably,
which just says, how high this thing can can ever go right?
so,
When we actually do worker, do the worker work diem.
So what do worker work actually is going to be is it's going to be
sort of a two-part thing.
Now it's going to be a one part of that is going to be begin, worker
work, right?
Or Begin work queue which I say Begin work.
Queue operation, you can work.
You begin work, queue work.
Sounds weird.
But that kind of is what it is.
I don't know.
Begin work, you work, there we go, that's what it is.
And then we have an end to work you work, right.
And essentially, what going to happen here is these are going to call
in and they're going to have to do, it's more or less.
The exact same things that were happening in here, right?
So what we'll have to do is when we we're going to probably want to
get rid of the sub, The Logical index stuff there, but we're going to
do here is we're going to say, all right.
On the Begin work, you work.
We will actually do this part here where we actually, DQ and entry,
right?
So that is going to return an entry index that makes sense.
And then in the end, in the end version, we want to do the back half,
which is the interlock increment that says, okay, we actually have
completed thing.
And so these are going to be both again off of that queue.
So, here we go.
These both will need to take the queue.
And so when you begin Q work that will basically return you whatever
the thing is that you should be working on, right?
And we'll make that an in 32, I guess you and 32 that comes back.
Like so.
And turn entry into x.
What we can do here is we can do something where we have some value,
we could make this a Bool and we return the value.
I'm not sure which exactly what to do.
I might actually say that we're going to do something like work.
Queue work result or work queue item.
Something like this, Buhl existed.
You know, like whether there was something to do, and
There's the index of the work item that comes back, right?
Like so.
So, something like this.
Gets returned.
So work queue item.
Here is the result, the result exists equals false because there
wasn't anything we return the results, otherwise we set the it as the
entry index, if there actually was something to do and we go ahead and
set that exists to true and off you go, right?
So pretty simple.
Pretty straightforward.
So at that point I think we're in good shape.
We've got NQ work here.
All that has to do is q that is is make that empty completion count
happen.
I think.
I'm thinking.
Just for a second.
So
What I really want to do.
Are right.
It is
Well, no, I guess.
Yeah.
I feel like really this is the this minimal thing is really all that
actually has to happen, right?
Begin Q.
Work and Q work.
That's really it.
I really think that's that's that's all there is to it.
So I think that's all we need for now.
So I'm just going to leave that there.
And then I'm going to go grab this call down here, right?
This entry count, not equal to completion count, and I'm going to make
that be another call.
You can call here, right?
Which is going to be
Is you know is work or is all work completed.
All right and in the work you like so that will simply check to see
whether the queue has those two guys equal to each other result equals
Q.
Yeah.
And I guess, technically, we probably want to reverse the sense of it
because that's the way we're using it before.
So I guess I want to say is
if work exists in Q4 unfinished,
Or Q work still in progress.
How about that?
So then we can basically say, okay, you know, if you know, in a spin
lock like this, we can say, if the cue work is still in progress on
our Q then we would, we would be continuing to work on it, right?
So I think that's okay.
All right, so let's keep going here.
We're getting there, we are getting there in terms of abstraction.
So we have a way to basically bracket this thing.
So we basically do something like work queue item, item equals Begin
work, queue work.
I guess we could, you know what?
Now we could make these a little more logical.
We could do get next work queue item.
Like so.
That makes it a little more logical Q.
If item exists
I guess we can maybe say is valid might be a little nicer.
All right, if item is valid, then we do what we wanted to do and then
we return, whether we did some work there.
In fact, we could just return item is valid.
It's all we really need to return.
Don't need another Boolean there.
And then, in here, we just need to do retire, work, or Mark Q, item
completed, write something like that, and then we pass that item in
there, and probably the queue, right?
So then we have it here.
Mark Q item completed.
We take the cue and we take the item now, we don't actually
The item, but I'm just going to have it.
Take it just just for in case later we want to do it just to make it a
little more and make it a little clearer what's going on here.
But off we go with that increment and that's fine.
So do worker work.
Now actually should be able to do what it needs to do so long as we
actually have again.
Now we can kind of bring this guy back up here so long as we actually
have something for him to work with.
So this is the thing that you actually write out in the platform
nonspecific code, right?
It would do all the stuff.
It does here and then it would just it would go ahead and grab that
entry.
Based on the thing that came back, so it would say work queue entry
entry equals in trees.
Yeah, plus our item index.
That's the thing that we would print.
So, let's see how that goes.
Oops, is now a bear.
Next entry to do.
Okay.
So in here these just are referenced off the queue now.
Like so,
Entry index is not actually necessary, just its index.
All right, and so do worker work actually does need the work queue.
So, there's that queue.
And logical thread index here, I mean I guess we'll go ahead and keep
passing that because that's just something we wanted to do.
So that's fine.
But here we go.
Let's go ahead and put the cue in there that will put make that part
of the thread info.
And where is that thread in 2013 to thread info?
That's comes down here.
That's really only relevant to thread prop like so,
So, let's make our work queue.
Q.
There we go.
And then input string, we just need to actually make push stirring.
We need to make an actual version of push.
During that does the calls properly.
So we need this to be avoid.
We need it to take a work queue.
So
We need it to take a string.
And we need this to do just the same stuff that was doing before,
right.
We need to come up here and we need to do one of these add work queue
entries and we call it an entry here and an item here.
I feel like we should maybe say entry versus item.
I'm going to say that it's going to be entry so we're just going to
oops.
So we're just going to replace item with entry.
There we go.
All right.
But of course in here, this is actually our string entry or something
like this, right?
This is the one that's actually defined for this guy.
Spring entry, there we go.
Okay, and this is, this is our string, so there we go.
And let's see.
So here's our push string, so inside our push string, we're going to
have to pass the Q that we want here.
So I'm going to go ahead and change semaphore handle everywhere to
just be Q.
So
and pushing on on to this Q should not be very complicated, right?
All I need to do is do an ad work entry.
Like, so to let it know that there's a new one in there and we always
know what the entry count actually is on this thing because it's kept
in here.
So I guess the other thing too would be, I would want a call here.
That tells me what the next entry count actually is on the sky.
And, you know, just it doesn't have to be sword.
Although technically that could also just be stored external, right?
So it's a little, it's a
Little confusing.
In that regard.
But we'll just do it this way for now.
We'll do this way for now, so here we go.
Get next.
Let's see.
Get next available.
Work queue index.
And that'll take the pointer here.
And this will just right now, be returning, whatever.
Whatever in Tri County is right.
So like so, because again, we're single producer.
So that's fine.
Don't have to worry about that.
That's a very simple call.
So, in here, what we can do is say, all right, we're going to do get
next available, work you index.
So
This is our index.
We ask for it from the queue, we then add the work queue entry and it
advances it.
And we need to make sure that we do all our writing before we do this,
right?
So we do entries or what are these called string entries?
What are these entries for just do entries index string to print
equals string?
That's it, right?
And so that's really all there is to it.
All we have to do now is actually make the cue, right?
These are going to have to be at Q so but all we have to do now is
actually make that Q the Q really just gets initialized to zero and
then has the semaphore handle show up in it.
That's about it, right?
And I guess now that we look at now that I'm looking at that
At as well, that actually means that the semaphore handle actually
doesn't have to be.
Here because it's get it off of the queue, right?
So we can just do Q semaphore handle, like so?
So really, that's that's easy as well, get rid of this and just say
info Q equals address of Q and that guy is now working on that cue.
Pretty simple.
All right.
So while Q work is still in progress, we have at Kew
function does not take one arguments.
What are we talking about?
Do worker work so it needs to take the kit, right?
Yeah.
Alright so we've made all of our changes now and hopefully I haven't
broken anything and then I probably have broken something that we can
see.
So let's take a look at how we did here.
Here's our thread through all working on things.
A 0 1 2 3 4 5 6 7 8 9 0 1 2 3 4 5 6 7 8 9 looking good.
All right.
So what we have done now is, we've basically made an abstract version
of the queue that we can put into the platform code now for the game
to use, right?
So what we can do now is when it gets, when it gets past this right,
we can have a way for it, to add things to the queue and to, to
dequeue them right?
Now, normally, like I said, I don't really like round trip functions
very much.
So I try to be conservative when I add things that are where the game
is going to call back the platform code.
But in the case of performance stuff, there's not a whole lot, we can
probably do about that.
That's the kind of thing that really, this probably needs to happen.
So, we pretty much only have two options.
One option is that we heart?
We like, inline this in.
So, if we care about how fast this is actually running, we would
inline the sin.
If we don't care about that, we just passed the
Should pointers here.
And I'm not sure which of those we actually want to do what I would
say is looking at it here.
There's such small, there's such a small amount of code that it does
kind of feel like maybe it wants to be inlined.
But on the other hand I don't know like we're not popping thousands of
these a second so you know we're talking about maybe doing 50 or 60 of
these so the number of function calls that it would make through the
pointer are not very large.
So I don't know it's really kind of a tough call.
It's kind of.
Of call and furthermore, I can get rid of get next available, work
queue index.
It can act.
You can actually keep your own index there.
That's actually, you know,
Yeah, we could also do something slightly different where we we could
actually just put void pointers into this Q would be another thing
that we could totally do.
So, I don't know.
So we could get rid of get next available.
Work queue index and would leave us with just add work queue entry,
get next work, queue entry and Mark you entry completed, right?
Which would just be three calls and that would be it.
So, you know what we could do even further actually?
We could, we could actually make this even less.
So observe the fact that Mark queue entry completed, right?
We could actually snuggle that call into this guy, right?
We could actually make a single thing.
That's like, I've completed one.
Give me a new one.
And that would be totally fine, right?
Hmm.
I think I like that.
So I could reduce this down to a simpler thing that wreck involves
less calls by simply saying that when you call getting that first
rookie to entry, I can call this complete and get next work, queue
entry.
And then when you pass in a work queue entry here, right?
Essentially what happens.
Is it marks the one that you pass?
Incomplete completed and then proceeds, right?
So what this would do is it would say, okay, if completed is valid
then we do an interlocked increment on the completion count, right?
Like so and then we go ahead and do that return.
That seems pretty cool to me, right?
So if I then rewrite, the code to do that,
Sort of like the Army is winning went out program.
I go ahead and
Andre sort of like rearrange this routine slightly to say that do
worker work, you know, I want to actually pull out the get mixed Q
part of it.
I want to just save this one part here, right?
So what it would look like more is it would look more like complete
and get next work.
Queue entry.
right, would look more like
This right?
So complete and get next work.
Queue entry.
I've got some some one of these guys here, one of these work, you
items.
Right.
Give me.
So I've got one of these work queue entries and this is my entry, it's
just cleared to zero.
Then when I do complete and getting its work to entry, I just passed
that in and I passed the queue and I replace the entry that I did have
with the new entry.
Pretty straightforward.
All that does is that gets me out of the business of now having to
call anything twice.
So when I do that, I then say, all right, if this entry is valid then
I process it.
Otherwise we go ahead and halt, right?
We go ahead and and and stop.
So if the entry is valid, I do work or work here.
And pass, maybe the entry in there and so the Q no longer gets passed
to this guy.
Oh, and I got a pass that logical thread index read info.
Fred index.
So yeah, so do work or work here.
What I'd rather do is say okay, don't don't bother passing in the
queue just pass in whatever the work queue entry was right?
And The Logical thread index.
So I'm going to assert that.
I got past a valid entry like that.
I'm then going to use it and I'm not going to return anything.
Alright, so there we go.
So now
Down here.
This Loop will just do this.
It will say
entry entry.
Right.
And then it'll say,
Get the next one.
And if the next one is valid, go ahead and go ahead and use it.
Here we go.
So exact same Loop, pretty much only in this case, it's got it
actually just exit out and starts running in the case where it needs
to do its thing.
Okay.
So, let's see what else we got here.
That's right in 40q.
Address of Q.
And this is just the enemy.
Okay, so now we're down to only three functions that we would need to
expose.
To get this key working.
So that seems pretty plastic to me.
I don't really have a problem with that, right?
We've just got in and I guess I was saying you could actually get rid
of this one as well, so they're just be ad there.
Just be two calls, add work queue entry and complete and get next
work.
Queue entry, right?
And if, so again, we could even be a little weirder here.
And I don't know if we want to be but we could be if we were so
inclined.
We could actually make it to this takes a pointer and then it wouldn't
ever call this
I mean, the reason I'm differing here is just because I want to get
rid of this function call, it's not necessary.
It's really only there to avoid the possibility that the exterior
entry count gets out of sync with the interior entry count.
I'm going to I'm going to go ahead and I'm gonna go for it.
I'm gonna go for it.
What I'm going to do because I feel like I'm going to want this
expanded sort of functionality a little later.
Anyway what I'm going to do is I'm going to say that the work Cube
maybe is like really two separate things.
Like maybe there's base, there's like the queue and then that points
off into other buffers that that can describe the job so that we can
use it for sort of any jobs that we want.
And that would also allow us to make it maybe be
That was, you know, because we're going to want more.
I think we're going to want more features in here, eventually
So yeah, I think maybe what we'll do is we'll just say when you add
work queue entry, you'll give it a pointer and that pointer will
basically, you know, will essentially be the thing that tells you what
the work queue entry was going to be.
So we will actually, I'll keep it.
I'll keep the concept that there's external stuff that's happening.
In addition, right?
So we go up here, I'm going to go ahead and say that I'm going to
reinstate this.
I know.
Said I was getting rid of it.
I lied.
So this is the the user pointer, right?
And then we've got our work queue entry.
And each queue of ours will have some number of these.
Right?
Which is the queue size.
I don't know if to 5256 is the right number, but now I can get rid of
Max entry can't because it's just going to be that that 256 number.
So we have that cue when we add something to the queue, we will go
ahead and and and actually write that pointer in here.
So what I want to do is I want to say that the queue entries for
whatever the entry
Count is.
That's going to that user pointer is going to equal pointer.
We're then going to have the barrier and then we're going to increment
it right?
And also put an assertion here that because I think we want to make
this a rolling buffer eventually but I'm going to make a assertion
here that says that we have room to stuff the pointer in.
All right, so they do that.
First things first.
So this is work, queue entry storage.
I guess is really what this is, right?
And that's just the sort of the storage area, they're going to compile
that.
So string entries.
Now we don't actually have what we would have to do here is pass like
void star.
This is the this is the entry data, something like this.
And so now what we're actually doing in fact I guess we don't need the
entry database be in the things we can get rid of that entirely.
Actually, this right here is now going to be a void Star, right?
And in fact, I guess now that I think about it, that void star
actually tells us to which one it is.
We could simplify this even further.
It just keeps going.
So we've got the user.
This is the data or whatever you want to call it, right?
So that's actually just
Already in there.
So now we don't even need this.
We don't need the string entry, really.
All we're going to do is say, okay, well, the thing that's getting
pushed just, we know it happens to be a string.
So we're just going to go ahead and say that the entry data was a
string and that's it, right?
Nothing more to it than that.
So when we finish this off here, we're going to get that index back,
right?
And we want our interlocked increment there.
And essentially to do, we're going to pull off, whatever the the data
was of that thing.
We're going to say that the queue entries and whatever that index is,
we want the user pointer to come back and put that into the data,
right?
And then we push string all we really need to do now is we just need
to actually pass the string directly so you don't even need to do
that.
So that'd be it, right?
So that's it.
That's really all there is to it.
So now let's go ahead and run this again.
Make sure we're still doing.
Okay, looks good to me, right?
Everyone's happy nothing.
Weird is going on here.
So I think that's all good.
Don't know why they go in the order they go, it's always very strange,
right?
But that's just the way they synced up.
So now we can actually do is I think pretty much anything we want with
that everything should be fine.
We have the problem right now that we don't ever have a way to do a
queue reset, but we're going to turn this into a rolling buffer so
we'll hit that assertion and we'll deal with it then.
as we want to turn this into a circular buffer, eventually
All right, so if we wanted to get this going now, we should probably
be able to do this relatively straightforwardly.
I should think, at least, I hope so.
Let's go ahead and see what we can do.
I'm going to go ahead out to platform.
I'm going to start hoisting these guys out.
We've got essentially three functions that need to get called here.
Add work queue.
Add work queue entry.
And get next work queue entry and Q work still in progress, right?
So I think that's that's basically everything we need.
I think least it looks like it is.
Yeah, and there's a couple ways we could do this.
I'm not sure exactly how we would want to do it.
I mean the other thing we could do to is well yeah I think there's a
need to do that.
Hmm, okay, so I want to think about this a little bit more.
So I guess the other thing too, if we keep collapsing, this down, I'm
sorry.
I'm kind of getting into this.
It's just
If we actually just wanted to make this be a dispatch Q where it just
calls people, right?
So the work queue entries just have who to call and then a like a
bundle of data for that person right.
If we were to do that, then all you would really ever need to call
would be add work queue entry, right?
And then one other function, which was the combination of basically
that was like, a combination of sort of the, the this this Loop right
here.
I'm just trying to think of like.
So when we actually go and do it,
I'm gonna flip over and write the other code just real quickly because
before I abstract it out, you know, I say right?
The usage code first, I kind of want to see what the usage code will
look like over here and see how that goes.
So let's pretend that we were going to do this, right?
Let's pretend we were going to multi-thread this so we know how many
tiles there are ahead of time, right?
So we could do something where we're going to do like, you know, tile
render job or something like this, you know, our tile render work.
And that towel render work would have like, you know, tile X tile,
white really only needs one number.
I mean, this is not really.
You could back all this out with only getting an index back.
Because we could figure out which tile we were on from that.
But so I'm going to make this struct a little more complicated to show
what we would do, if we have like, a more complicated job, we were
queuing that couldn't be not.
That the job is more complicated was coming.
I mean something where it requires, pushing a bunch of parameters on,
right?
So I'm thinking like, okay, you know, we want to basically do this
thing that looks like this where we're sort of treating it as a
full-on dispatch, right.
What we'd want to do is then have a thing that's like okay here is the
like do you know, do tiled render work something like this and this
thing would just take like percent, you know, data that'd be it,
right?
And it would know that day
It was actually a tiled render work thing.
So it would do that, right?
What would cast it?
And then it would proceed to do this.
This stuff here.
So it would go ahead and say OK, you know, we've got this stuff and in
fact I guess we could even make it just actually be the calls that it
does here for now.
So in fact, we could actually just put the clip rect in there too.
I mean, why not?
Let's go Whole Hog, right?
So there's the clip.
Rect so it doesn't.
You have tile X, Tau y, right?
So then it just says, okay, you know, I'm just going to dispatch this
stuff like so, and for now we're not doing the hyper-threading, so
we're actually going to do
Both sets of lines, evensen odds, right?
We're going to do that tiled render work.
So then, what we do in here is we just say okay you know we've got
some stack of these, right?
This is like our stack of work and later on we could we could allocate
this but we pretty much know you know what our tile counts are, right?
So it's just at I'll count x times the top count.
Why?
Right?
I'll count x times, talk out.
Why
Like so can I do darn?
You see here's the thing.
I hate const with a passion but you notice that if you put in const
suddenly the compilers okay with this, right?
Like somehow that was not.
Okay, but this is okay.
It's just so lame.
Like why did I have to type constant?
It is constant, right?
And you had to know that in order to do this
Like so annoying anyway, but I could do it that way, right?
I can't do that.
So, there you go.
Anyway, so if we do something like that, then we would know that we
could just push all the stuff on here, right?
So I could do you know work into x equals zero and then each one of
these would basically be something like, Thailand, or work, or sorry,
work array, maybe so,
Work equals work, array + work.
+ x + +, right?
And then in here,
Buffers with overflow.
All right, I think that's all right.
That's because we're doing large clip Rex anyway, so, we'll go ahead
and store in here, render group that goes render group work, output
Target, equals out the targets and work, cliprect, equals clip.
Rect
Right.
And there we go.
So if we did that,
And I wanted to make this thing.
Do its thing.
Right?
What I could do is as I go through that work array, I could just tell
it.
Oh, you know what?
When I quit that Rick array, I'm going to do now.
I'm going to do that, that add function, right?
I want to do add work queue entry.
And I want to pass Ad work queue entry the function to call, right?
So it would be do tiled render work.
Like so and I want it to be, I want to have some pointer here, right?
Which is that?
Right.
So that basically to oops I don't move.
Thanks so I want to basically add to the work queue entry.
I want to add the stuff that it needs to do and I would need to know
what the Q was here, which is basically a render, its the render queue
So, I don't know.
We've got something like this.
Q a begins now.
Oh man.
But I was really enjoying this.
This is going to be cool.
Well, ask Not For Whom the Bell Tolls, the Bell Tolls for thee.
That's fine.
So this will be a platform work queue or something like this, right?
It would be passed in here and this is the render queue and it would
use that cue to cue up, the work that was going to do, and that would
all be fun and delicious.
So, it would go ahead and do that.
And then we would come out here and we would have this guy, wait,
So this is, this is one of those things where we kind of want to.
Like, do we want to kind of like
complete work queue, right?
Platform.
Something like platform.
Add work queue and platform complete work queue, right?
Something like this.
So what I'd like to do is I probably just make those off of the queue
themselves so I'll probably just do something like
You know, render queue add entry like so and we'll just stick the
function pointers in there and this will be render queue complete all
work.
Right.
And I think that that's really all we need to do.
I really like that, right?
So you can see how this is going to happen, right?
Hopefully, you can see if we can compile this here.
Platform work.
You so, basically, what I'll do here is say, oh yeah.
Platform work queue.
That's not really in there right now.
And this is not really in there right now.
Compile.
And then, of course, now if we run thing, we won't see anything
because
All my things.
So just to leave us in a compilable state, we can just do this right
into work and x equals zero work.
Index is less than Loops should make this work index work account,
that should be work, count plus plus work index.
Yeah, and then we would just go ahead and do your work.
Right.
And so now we're still working in theory, well, or we could just cross
crash immediately.
That would be cool.
I always like when that happens, what was the problem here?
Data child render work data, is it not passing it to Todd render work?
Work + work count.
Oh nice.
That's so he's good that's gonna go right off the end.
All right, so that's always good now, we render again.
So, so, basically.
We've basically done everything we want.
We've spec the API.
We've got things sort of worked out in the other side.
So this is going to be great.
We just connect these things, two things up tomorrow.
This is going to be super sweet and then we have a general work queue
actually.
So that means we could pass a couple cues in and we could start just
farming stuff off to Q's all day long.
We could have our background, we could have it back.
Mq working on ground tiles for example, right?
So that's pretty awesome actually.
I'm excited about this but I will go to the Q&A.
I will go to the Q and A now.
This is pretty cool.
I'm excited about this.
I don't know why I'm excited about this.
It's not like I haven't been to work you before but I think that's
what makes someone a lifetime programmer.
Is the fact that they enjoy writing stuff for no apparent reason?
I'm not seeing a lot of programming questions.
In fact, there are no programming questions.
You, seriously, we have no programming questions.
If we have no programming questions, then I fully expect all of you to
be like, multi-threading programming experts.
At this point, you had better be awesome at it, if I'm not getting any
questions.
Bring Cruiser.
Will you start new threads for every work queue that you make?
No, I don't.
I don't suspect that.
We will.
What I will do is I think I'm sort of thinking in the back of my head
about how I want this to work.
now that we've flushed it out,
unfortunately.
like,
we're going to have some number of, of
Elements that have to occur, right?
And when we are rendering, we want all of our horsepower going to
rendering because we have to get that out in a certain amount of time.
But when we are not rendering, we have the luxury of like having our
threads do other things potentially, right to go work on other stuff.
So the only reason that I wanted there to be multiple queues,
potentially is so that the platform layer could be told at various
times.
Like.
Oh okay.
Right now you need to focus your all your energy on doing work from
just this one Q.
Do not ever grab anything from one of the other cues, right?
And so that's probably what we're going to what we're going to do.
I'm probably going to make it so that there's 22 qs1 for background
work, that doesn't have to be completed in a particular amount of time
and one for basically like computation stuff like this that has to be
computed right away.
That makes sense.
Okay, so I do see a actual programming related question about
multi-threading.
So I'm going to answer it.
Someone said they still don't understand the use of volatile and
memory barrier.
And hey, since we don't have any questions today, I can spend a lot of
time answering that, right?
So yeah, let's go ahead and do that.
Let's go to the Blackboard.
Ladies and gentlemen, the handmade hero.
Board on day 125.
So here is fencing.
Memory.
And code fences.
Okay, so here is the C++ code.
Here is the x64 and here is the processor or we could just have a
stall that makes it.
So I can't draw.
All right, here is the problem.
In the C++ code.
I do something like this data.
You know, pointer like maybe, you know we actually have this right?
Oops.
You know, entry data or Aero data, something like this equals the
data.
and then I had the
Entry count plus plus.
Right.
So what I need to do is I needed to set what the data was supposed to
be in the queue and then I need to increment the counter that says oh
you know, we've got there's another thing in there, right?
Now complicit in this, like I've said before, other threads are
looking at entry count to figure out whether there's more work to do,
right?
They're doing that thing where they do.
Next is less than entry count, right?
So the instant that entry count gets incremented, one of our other
threads might start executing, which means that, as soon as this is
visible to another thread, this had better have actually been written.
Because if it wasn't, then they will pick up invalid data and either
crash or do old work again or to knows what.
Right?
So hopefully that's clear.
So we need to ensure that this happens first.
And this happens.
Second right?
We need that this is a hard constraint.
Our program must have this be true.
If it is not true, our program will not work.
It will fail intermittently.
Okay.
So the first problem is this step compilation.
During compilation, there is absolutely no dependency between these
two things as expressed in the code.
These are completely independent instructions to the C compiler.
It has no way of knowing that we wanted this to happen.
So it may
Very well cross the streams, right?
It may very well go.
Oh, you know, what it's way more efficient to increment entry count up
here.
So, it produces x64 code.
That's like, you know, that's an ad up here, right?
Like a dent, recount and one, or whatever.
And then, oh, this thing, down here, there's the mob that's going to
go ahead and take data and put it in entry data.
So it's going to do that here.
Right.
And hey guess what?
Just by the act of compiling our program, it broke it is now in the
wrong order and it is incorrect.
So that's the first thing that is thing one the compiler fence.
So putting up a fence literally called a fence because things are not
supposed to move past it, right?
Putting in the compiler fence tells the compiler.
Stop that garbage.
These two things need to be in the correct order.
Right?
Never ever do that.
Always put these in the exact same order that they came in in the
code, right?
So here is where the ad goes here is where the mob goes.
Okay, so that's compiler fats and the compiler fence was underscore
right barrier.
It's not doesn't do anything.
It is literally not even compiled in anything.
All it is is a marker that says compiler.
Do not reorder rights along this fence.
If these were reads, we would have put read barrier because it's
whatever you're trying to bury her, right.
And if you don't want anything to go between the fence, it's readwrite
barrier.
That's like nothing.
Can you know, no reads, no rights can cross this line?
Alright, so that was problem number one and it is solved by the
compiler fence problem.
Number two,
Is out of order execution.
Right.
So basically, we've got the Assembly Language code.
The processor is going to execute it, but remember, the processor
actually has all sorts of things, it can do to change the order in
which things occur.
So it may very well be that they are in this correct order here
because we put in our compiler fence, but when they go into the
processor, the processor looks.
Let me go so I can actually do this move now but I can't do the ad
right now.
So I'm going to go ahead and do them off first and I'm going to do the
ad s
That might happen.
Furthermore, a processor may have a right order, buffer,
Right.
It may have a thing where even if it guarantees that it executes, he's
in the same order for it.
They may go into a holding buffer for doing rights which don't get
flushed out until later.
This is a separate thing that processor sometimes have who knows,
right?
And so, in order to fix this, we need to tell the processor not to do
this.
Monkey Business.
And that is where the actual fence instruction comes in.
Right?
So, that's thing to and that is underscore.
Mmm, underscore, fence of some kind, it's either full fence.
Which is MM fence.
Or it's a store offense for which is for rights, and, or a load fence,
which is just four loads, right?
So these things are actually equivalent across the board.
So underscore read, right?
Barrier.
Right.
This is oops, right barrier and this is freed barrier.
These things are all equal, right?
So basically to tell the compiler that you want a complete fence, you
do read write barrier to tell the processor that you want to complete
fence.
You need.
Mmm fence.
If you want both people defense, you have to put both of them.
Same is true for right barrier.
Right barrier says, do not move rights around compiler pass this line.
Store fence says CPU, don't move rights around and if you want night
of the compiler, nor the CPU you have to put both of them.
And again, same thing.
Now these are not always necessary because interlocks usually do them
automatically.
So like an interlock exchange and stuff like that.
I believe automatically doesn't, mmm, fence essentially.
But assuming that you're not calling that, in that particular place of
the code, you need to definitely do it.
Did that answer the question?
Hopefully, that answered the question.
Can entry is valid be removed and replaced with a test to see if entry
data is not equal to null probably, but we're going to read rearrange
that code a little bit tomorrow because I changed how I want to be a
pi to work there when I went to sort of merge them.
So we're going to do that, what is your take on naughty dog's
approach, using fibers plus manual, memory management, plus manual
management and thread Affinity to core instead of using classic
classic worker job approach for multi-threaded gameplay.
My answer is I have not really studied how they do it, so I don't have
an opinion.
The work.
He will take any function to do it.
Multi-threaded does.
The function need to be special so that this will work.
No, not really.
It will be able to work with just about anything.
The only requirement is that function, if it is executing at the same
time, as other functions Hast, they can't conflict, right?
They can't be like writing to the same location or something like
that.
So like in the case of the tiled renderer you have to break it up into
those tiles so that they don't conflict.
What are Limon.
Please write a lock freak.
You even though, I don't know what those are.
And if you used one,
This is a lock freak.
You that is exactly what we implemented.
So if you take a look at this guy right here, this work queue, it is a
lock freak.
You
At the moment.
It's not quite what you would normally consider a lock for you because
it's not a circular buffer.
So we will make this a circularbuffer eventually and then then it will
be more proper cute.
How many CPU cycles does spawning a thread cost or better?
What's the minimum amount of Cycles to work into threads to gain
speed?
So, you'll notice that essentially what we've done here is we have
gotten rid of the cost.
This morning, a thread spawning.
A thread is actually very expensive.
I mean, at the scales that we work at and so what we want to do is we
don't ever want to spawn a thread, what we want to do is have a bunch
of threads already.
Spawned sitting around ready to do.
If there's a lot of work to do, they should be always working and not
ever going to sleep.
So you'll notice that's why I set it up this way.
This code will actually not get pulled out.
This is going to be exactly what it does.
We will launch eight threads at startup or whatever and we will leave
them ready to do work so that they can wake up right when we have
something for them to do without having to go through any overhead of
launching.
So what we're trying to do is get it down, so that there really isn't
very much cost at all to multi-threading things.
So yeah.
I don't understand why you call it a queue.
If it is done potentially simultaneously, the reason is because while
work can be done simultaneously.
The elements of the queue are actually pulled off in guaranteed order,
right?
Meaning when people put work into the queue, it goes in in the order,
in which it is submitted.
And when people pull off work off in the queue, it comes out in the
order that it was submitted.
So it is very much a traditional fifo queue first.
In first out right.
Meaning the
You put into it as the first thing that comes out of it.
That is the traditional definition of a queue.
And so, it is a cue the fact that as people pull off of it, they are
doing the work that it says to do in.
Parallel doesn't really have anything to do with it because that work
is General work.
Who knows what that is?
The actual cueing though is always an order,
Wasn't there already a bit of thread related code in the win32 file.
There is a thing which says what thread you are on, but that's it.
And we may work that in here a little bit.
We may not
Will you add a cool graph over time?
That shows what tasks EG from, which subsystem each thread is working
on at each moment.
Yes, we can add that remind me when we get to debug visualization to
add, well, you know what?
I will.
Go ahead and put that in here.
Let's see.
It's kind of hilarious.
How we did this totally out of order.
I do not know how we got.
So, yeah.
Well we moved it to the top anyway.
So we kind of and we actually did a lot of this stuff already.
I'm pretty excited about this, anyway.
Let's see.
So we've got all that stuff and debug code.
Let's put this in here, thread, visualization that in there.
So this is kind of cool.
We're actually, this is going to be where this is going to collapse
quite a bit.
When we take a look at this, we've already done so much stuff that I
was sort of planning on doing.
After the fact, it's going to kind of change the way this this all
works.
Well have to kind of update this list at some point.
It's going to be weird.
All right but anyway
So, it looks like we're finishing that in effect asset streaming I
guess since we'll probably actually happen right after this.
Since we've already got our thread stuff going.
Yeah.
What you gonna do?
Stuff just goes in the order.
It goes like this and so I think what we probably want to do is yes is
maybe just go ahead and do something like this and then come back down
to it.
But yeah, it looks like it looks like this is
of what we have ended up doing in terms of our order.
So yeah.
And thankfully we already did a bunch of this stuff that we want for
animation to so animation is going to be like kind of a breeze.
I think because we've already let we've already done like texture
mapping so we can just freely move our stuff all around.
So that's going to be pretty cool too.
Yeah, that's pretty exciting.
All right.
Is false sharing between the entries in the work queue potentially
problematic.
False sharing.
Can you be more specific about what you mean by false sharing?
Does volatile clear the assembly registers?
I pushing them into the stack and then restore my popping.
Yes, that is exactly what it does.
Although usually it's not the stack because usually the volatile is
actually in global memory somewhere.
So it's usually actually not on the stacks, on the Heap.
But yes, same difference it pushes them to Memory and back.
Why would you want to compile our fence and not a process fence?
And
Versa.
So basically as far as I can think of any way, I can't, really say why
you ever want, just the compiler fence on x64 on other platforms.
Compiler fences, make more sense because the processor may be strongly
ordered in terms of its rights.
So it's only the processor that you're trying to fence.
I'm sorry.
It's only the compiler that you're trying to fence on x64.
I need to do a little more reading about what the current state is.
Of the ordering.
So it may be that that those are actually never really useful.
I don't know.
Shouldn't mmm fence imply.
A compiled.
Compiler fence.
Surely.
There's no point, otherwise, I'll be honest with you.
I really don't know if it does or doesn't
Let's see, huh?
Mmmm fencing again.
Let's see.
Do they have any documentation of it?
I mean, I guess all I can say is I don't know.
I would never want to trust that it did until I actually saw some
definitive thing that says it does, because it's so simple for me to
just include read, write barrier in there that I just would.
But yeah, if you can find a page where they specifically talk about it
and say, yes, we always do it but I don't know if they do or not.
Have you implemented friction?
I guess, sort of our guy does slow down as if he was under friction
drag basically
So thread management is a bit like memory management in that you want
to set it up ahead of time rather than allocating them on demand.
Yes, I that's a good way to think of it, actually.
Much like memory management.
Creating a thread, just like allocating memory is very expensive at
the operating system level.
And very expensive.
I mean it's not s, it's actually quite quick but it's very expensive
in terms of game scale stuff.
So typically what I like to do is just get what I want from the
operating system first, and then I'll deal with sub allocating it out,
right?
And so, it's the same with memory, it has is with time.
I want to be able to control how the threads are dulled at work.
I don't want to have to create and Destroy threads through the
operating system because that waste a ton of time and the same is true
with memory.
I don't want to allocate and free memory from the operating system.
I want to be the person who manages how that memory is carved up.
So, the operating system doesn't incur any overhead.
The code to ask, how many threads will be done simultaneously.
Casey by the processor is to be added.
Yes.
Although I'm not sure how to add it now because we need something that
says, hey, I'm on a machine that streaming.
So please don't use all the CPU.
Otherwise twitch throws a fit like it can't or OBS rather.
So I'll show how to add it but then I'll guess I'll comment it out in
force mind always use eight.
I don't know.
Is it possible for work?
Queue entry to spawn?
Another work queue entry.
Not yet, because, again, like I said, this is actually a single
producer multiple consumer queue system.
So if we wanted to work entry to be able to see, if we want to do
work, you enter this one.
Another work queue entry.
We would need to make it multiple producer single consumer.
I'm sorry.
Multiple producer, multiple consumer, which is a little more
complicated.
So I don't really want to do
Unless we have to do that.
So if we find that we have to do that for some reason, then we'll do
it, but I'd rather not because it implies a little extra stuff, that's
not as good.
False sharing causes the processor to skip the cash when different
threads access stuff on the same cache line.
Sorry, I still don't really follow you.
False sharing cause the processor to skip the cash when different
threads access stuff on the same cache line.
I guess you mean multiple threads executing on the same processor
core?
I mean, the processor wouldn't know when two different like if one
core doesn't know that another core is accessing stuff on the same
cache, line until the cash is talk to each other.
I believe.
So they always go through the cash was my understanding on the x64.
So I'm not sure what you're talking about on the exit site, does it
happen on the Ecstasy for what you're saying?
Are you sure that maybe this is something that only happens on
different kinds of processors?
On.
MM fence.
Somebody has found perhaps the place where they talk about this.
Let's take a look here.
Somebody sent the link in Juni.
We no longer support the documentation for processor can Transit
operators for SC, intrinsics private, Intel to answer to the question
raised to the second power just does treat the sa-2 been repairing
transects as implicit Ribery, okay?
So, yes.
According to this bug report, that someone found that it, mmm.
Fence should insert read?
Write barrier automatically to answer the question that someone had
before.
All right.
Soon.
I'm sorry actually I can think of one use case for a compiler fence
without a memory fence writing to CPU, special registers like control
registers are msrs.
So I don't actually know if those are considered stores though, are
they, because normally a store fence is talking about stores out to
the cash not stores to a CPU register.
Right.
So I don't know if an S fence prevents reordering of rights to the
mxr,
BMX CR, anything like that.
So, I don't know if that's true so you can send me three.
I don't know if that's actually I don't know if an S fence would
prevent that, I guess is what I would say.
So let's see one last question.
Getting back into C C++ coding out.
Well, stream has ended getting back into CC plus going after many
years.
Don't know why?
You're mixing c-style structs and C++ trucks.
We don't really have any C++ trucks.
We only have C style structs everywhere.
So, alright, that's about it for today.
I'm going to go ahead and close things down.
Tomorrow's going to be exciting.
I'm excited about this work.
You I think it's going to be pretty cool.
It's going to be pretty cool.
Pretty darn cool.
Wait, that did not close.
There we go.
All right, thank you, everyone for joining me, for another episode of
handmade here.
It's been a pleasure coding with you, as always, and it's been a
pleasure coding with with you in a multi-threaded sense.
You can almost feel as if we're all sort of coding together at the
same time, but thanks to our work.
You not colliding, which is always good if you want to follow along at
home.
As always you can pre-order the game on handmade here at Oregon.
It comes with a source code, you can download the source code every
day after I finish work here and check it out.
And play around with it, which is a good way to learn.
If you would like to just support the video series, we also have a
patreon, you subscribe to it's much appreciated.
We also have forums, we can ask questions get ports to Mac or Linux or
in view an antidepressant guide, the community maintains which is
pretty cool.
We have a tweet Papa tweets the
You.
So you can subscribe to that if you want to know when the live stream
is going to be tweets, the whole schedule every weekend and stuff like
that.
So you can know in advance and we also have a little Live Now button
donated by the community which basically does a countdown timer.
So if you want to know when the next live stream is going to be it
should give you a little countdown timer so you can tell.
All right.
Thanks everyone for joining me.
I will see you guys tomorrow.
Same time, same place 5:00 p.m.
5:00 p.m.
Pacific Daylight time when we will wrap up some of our
multi-threading.
Maybe we will, maybe we won't even be finished.
I mean if we got to connect it and it renders we're closing in this is
pretty exciting.
A week of multi-threading coming to an end.
All right everyone hope to see you tomorrow and until then have fun
programming I will see you on the internet's.