Okay.
Hello everyone and welcome to animate.
Here.
Are the show?
We could complete game live on stream today?
We are going to do a little more sorting.
We're pretty much done with sorting.
There's really not a whole lot to say about it.
It was really just an excuse to talk about a few CS things that we
don't really talk about much on handmade hero, and probably are more
for sort of self-study sorts of things, but I do want to finish up
what we were doing with.
With the Sorting just so you can kind of see today D 234 on handmade
hero.
So if you want to follow along at home and you're one of those peoples
who has kindly pre-ordered handmade hero on handmade here at up or you
will want to unpack day 233.
That is a source code that I'm looking at today.
Now if you remember from Friday, we tried to see if it would be
reasonable for us to implement mergesort in place and it did not seem
like it would be.
It seemed like it would just be very expensive and involve a lot of
like move, you know?
Complex, not complex, but expensive moves of the buffer to really do
it in place.
So we tried just not doing it in place and and that was obviously
very, very easy to implement.
In fact we implemented that you know, in just just a few minutes so we
have that working.
which means we can now
We can now freely choose at any time whether we want to use a bubble
sort or merge sort.
And in fact we could I suppose make these just for the sake of the
people who might want to play with them at home, make a bubble sort
and merge sort you know, that sort of thing where we just do
You know, some kind of a generic thing where it's like, okay, you can
call the merge sort or you can call the bubble sort.
It's your choice, so cures the bubble sort and then in here we just
say, Okay, bubble, sort count, entries temp space,
And then we can just pick which one of these we call.
And so, you know, we can comment bubble sort and call the merge sort
if we want to and everything is, is happy.
And so in here, yeah, like I think we can just say first for that, and
then we pretty much have that pulled out again.
Not doing anything here, other than extracting that.
So now, we've got the bubble sort and merge sort.
And so really, you know, that's really all there is to it for those
sorts.
There's not much to them, people want it.
Know about the Radix sort, this was a very thing something that really
people were excited about.
I don't know necessarily why they're that, excited about it.
But you know, if they are that's great.
It's always good to be excited about things.
By the way, the fact that I'm still so Tethered to this and I can't
even sit up straight, I look to find a cable that would, you know,
this is a, this is a like an iPhone, not an iPhone.
Or like an Android, just whatever a tip, ring ring sleeve, right?
It's one of the things it's got like, the microphone.
The headpiece, like you plug into a cell phone and I just looked for
someone who made a cable along cable that was like a plug for that, on
one end, you know, just one plug that you plug a head for a standard
cell phone headphone microphone cable into and on the other end just
to mic Jacks for the, you know, what are they quarter inch Jack's?
I can't remember what they're called, but that go into the back of the
computer.
So it goes into the headphone slot and the
and their microphone slot and I could not find anything that was
longer than like that long.
So if you happen to have a link handy where it's like, here's a cable,
that's like a nice.
Like three foot long cable or something.
Even a foot long cable, would be way better than what I have.
I would really appreciate it.
Okay, enough about that.
I'm still tethered down.
Its Libyan oppressed by the cable, by the cable, man.
So let's talk about Radix sort because like I said, people were
excited about Radix sort.
So I would like to, at least cover it.
I'm not the best person to talk about it.
Sort, I don't write Red X or it's hardly ever if ever.
Not that I Really Right sorts of any kind all that often but it's not
certainly not something that I spend a lot of time thinking about.
But point being, let's talk about what a Radix sort is and how it
works.
I mentioned it briefly the other day.
I'm going to say what it is in a little more detail today.
So today, 234 Radix sort now a Radix sort a again, like I said, I'm
the wrong person to really explain them because not my area of
Teeth.
But the way that I would think of a Radix sort is, we talked about the
concept of a stable sort.
Right?
We talk to someone asked about it on the Q&A and I sort of explain
what that was a stable.
Sort is a sort where you have some set of items, okay?
And the order in which the items occurs,
Is not changed, if they don't need to be sorted.
So any any ordering that's currently in the list, if two items are?
If it does not detect that any particular item is out of place in that
list relative, something else, it will not change their relative
location.
So for example, if here is my list of things
And I perform my sort, right.
If this list instead, we're say something like this.
Right?
And the sort was designed to just sort on the first character meaning
to sort were running is sort in alphabetical order by the first
character.
Don't look at the second character ever, just first character and I've
got a ABAC bdb, you know, whatever.
Right.
And I do this sort.
Well in order to satisfy this criteria, right, this criteria of a, a
be
CC appearing, in order.
We know that the output has to look like this.
It has to look like a, a a,b,c c, right?
Because we know that in order to satisfy the criteria that the first
letters we sorted, the best look like that, but what we did not
specify is what would happen to these actual elements because these
elements all have a as the first character.
And this element also does, there is no, we have defined no criteria.
A afore how they have to appear in here?
Right.
A, the definition of sorting does not specify what has to happen to
elements that sort to the same relative location that don't have any
determining between them when they are compared the compare equal not
less than or greater than or whatever.
Right?
And so this concept of a stable sort a stable sort is one that
preserves the order in which the things appeared in the original list,
right?
And so in this case,
There would be only one actual answer here, even though we're not
defining any additional sort criteria, we are defining this, you know,
sort of additional non sort criteria if you will, or maybe you could
even say we were defining additional search criteria.
The additional search criteria is where it was in the list, right?
Which as I'm saying it out loud.
I realize again, since I never work on sorting, I had never occurred
to me, but it seems like can't you just make
like isn't
any sort a stable sort.
if you just,
Add the original ordinal.
To the sort key.
Like, if you wanted to take a sort that wasn't stable and make it
stable, can't you just say that the sort key is just whatever the key
was Plus at the end of that key, whatever the position was in the
list, originally?
Doesn't that just give you a stable sort for free?
Like why do you even care?
If a sword is stable when you could just add that to the cake?
I don't know.
These are the kinds of questions I don't care about because I don't
really care about sort, but point being, it would seem to me that it'd
be pretty easy, but we don't care about that.
Right now, I'm talking about ready to start.
Forget I even said it.
Just a thought I happen to have.
Anyway, so what we are doing here is just saying, hey, we're adding
another criteria if we say the sort is stable, it means that anything
that occurred in a particular order here, has to occur in a particular
order here.
If it's, you know, if it's otherwise
To do so, right?
So since all of these here AAA have no restrictions on the order they
come, it has to use the order they came in here so it has to be ABCD,
right?
I'm sorry, abce.
They have to go in this order and that doesn't matter about the
alphabetical nature.
Like this could have been be here and a here, and a here, and a here,
as well.
And then this would have had to have been Bae, right?
It just has to be whatever order comes in here.
Now, this is still free to come after meaning, it's still supposed to
change the order of this and this because it is supposed to sort on
the actual part that that is that you were requesting, right?
So it does
Is the order.
It just doesn't change the order of anything.
It doesn't have to change the order of, and that's the stable sort
part.
Okay?
So hopefully you're all clear on that.
So now, a Radix sort is basically, like I've got to just Define it as
some number.
Of successive.
Stable sorts.
On some part.
Of the sort key.
This is really what we're actually talking about.
When we talk about a Radix sort, a Radix sort is basically repeatedly,
stabili sorting your list of elements on only a portion of the key at
any given time, right?
So let's take the simplest possible example for a Radix sort,
Would be where we don't have anything in particular in the sort key.
Other than, just a series of bits that we know represent a number of
our sorting by, right?
So let's say we had something like a 32-bit integer.
What's the sort key?
Okay, and what we want to be able to do for our 32-bit integer is we
would like to be able to to put our list in order based on how high
does number is.
So it's just a straight-up sort on how high the 32-bit integer is will
even say it's unsigned, right?
Okay.
So, how Radix sort decides to tackle?
This problem is, it says well, okay, I know I've got some series of
items and I know there are 32 bit integers, right?
So here's, you know, some 32-bit integer, you know, 105 or actually, I
suppose, what I should do is, is break this down to make it easier for
IMAX with explanation, let's break this down into B.
So here is like, you know, this is this is B 0 through 7, this is B.
8315.
This is B 16 through 24.
I'm sorry 23 and this is B 23 through 31.
Make sense.
So basically, I've eight bits in each of these, right?
And
I don't know why.
I just did that supposed to be 24.
So you have 8 Bits in each of these, right?
And you can imagine we just have some set of 32-bit integers.
So this is, you know, these each one of these slots holds some 32-bit
integer and for the sake of discussion let's just say that I'll
alphabetize them here in the order.
They would come.
So for example, let's you know I'll just pick Reza's G.
This is z this is a, this is f e.
X q, right?
And so this is just to let us know quickly because we're going to be
having, you know, if I have to if you have to imagine some 32-bit
number of they're pretty large like 4 billion, something or other
could be in there, or whatever.
Let's just say that these letters represent.
The order that they come in, I could even be a little bit more concise
and say that since we have one, two, three, four, five, six, seven of
them.
We can just use, like, ABCDEFG.
So it's like, you know,
You know, G first then a then C then B then e, then F ABC.
Where's my DD ABCDEFG?
Right?
So we just know that the numbers come in this order so if we were to
sort them we would expect the 81 to come first and then the D and then
and so on that's just to make it a little easier on us when we're
looking at these things, right?
Okay, so we know that these are 32-bit integers.
And so, what we want to do is we want to sort this array using the
Radix sort into something that's going to come in the proper order
instead of the in correct order, which is what it starts in or we
assume it starts in otherwise we wouldn't be calling sort.
So, what we do for a Radix sort, is we just sort it in place multiple
times and we sort it in place, multiple times by slicing the sort key
up into parts.
And The crucial observation here is that if you can write the sort key
and this is actually more or less required for a Radix sort.
Although people have come up with many clever ways to turn things that
don't quite seem.
Like, they look like this into things that are right exportable,
because you can kind of think of it as anything.
You could sort by slices kind of works this way.
So if you can turn your sort key into just something that looks like a
series of bits, then what you can do is choose.
Used to accelerate the sort by slicing that into portions that are of
a size where you can do some tricks, right?
So for example, in a traditional Radix sort, if you were to slice it
into 8 Bits, as I've done here, where we have our sort key and we have
like each portion of it of the sort key is a particular 8-bit piece.
Then, for example, if I have some number that's relatively complicated
you know the the number that we're actually talking about is like, you
know, in hexadecimal
Is, you know, for ef-1, you know, be a 95 or something.
Right?
Then in here.
You could imagine each particular part of this number,
as it as it occurs in the original sort, key each part can be broken
down into 8-bit chunks, right?
I can slice each one of these sort Keys into a pick chunks.
And what do we know about the result of sorting on any one of these
particular 8-bit chunks, right?
Well, if I was to sort on just the highest, the most important ones
right?
Like suppose I'm going to sort and I'm just going to look at those top
eight bits
Well, if I just sorted on just the top eight bits, I would know that I
would roughly right?
Roughly organize my list by order of magnitude, right?
Meaning anything that's really important to the value of this number
comes in this first bit here, right?
These first 8 Bits are the most significant ones, not shouldn't say
first, these high order eight bits are the most different ones if that
top bit is set, right?
That changes the value.
By the maximum number, a bit can possibly change the value, right?
It's to to the 31st is what that bit controls?
Whereas the bits down here, could never possibly hope to affect it,
right?
So what I'm getting at is that if you were to sort by this, this is
the most important thing to sort by, right?
No matter what happens down here.
These should never appear in anything other than ascending order after
the sword is done, right?
Because
If they were at anything other than a sorting order, it wouldn't
matter how what order these parts of the number we're in, right?
And you can see this, if you think of it, not in binary and easier way
to think of it would be if you had something like 101, 107, 100 106
207, right?
When you look at this you can immediately say well it doesn't matter
if these parts come in order, right?
If you were to take this and you were to say 0 1 0 1, you know what
I'm sorry.
100 101 106 107,
Or sorry, rather, 2007 107, right.
I put these in order but these are not in order, right?
And so since this is the most significant part, this is not the
correct, sort order.
We all know this to be true intuitively, right?
But that's actually a more General concept.
You can just apply to sorting and think about inserting the these have
to go in order first.
Then these then these, right?
And that is the
crucial idea behind the Radix sort is that you can sort by the most
Portion, right?
That part has to be true.
And then inside any section where the most significant part is
equivalent, right?
Like right here, for example, I'm sorry.
I got to put this in actual order now, inside the places where the
most significant part is all the same, then you care about what the
order is for the other things but only that right.
If these two differ, you don't care if these parts are in order.
If there was a 20-6 here, right?
Again you don't care if the to 0, if the sixes came together here, you
don't care about that because the to overrides that and now you only
care about what happens between
This part when these are already sorted, right?
So, that's the main content of a Radix.
Sort is saying we have to sort by these first, then these, then these
then these right?
But there's a reason why you don't apply it quite exactly.
Like, what I just said, Okay?
The reason why you don't apply it quite like I just said, is because
again if you consider what happens when you sort of buffer, if I was
to sort first by the most significant thing mean
Can I call sort on it first?
Then I call sort on the next one, right?
You would end up with the obvious problem of of it, would rearrange
the order, right?
So, there's a couple ways, you know, you could choose to have the
Radix, sort work.
You could choose to make it go in and basically, either order
depending on whether you sub sort ranges or whether you sort the
entire buffer.
And there's really
Ways you can implement, it will take a look at that in a second.
But anyway, conceptually that's what a Radix sort is doing its saying.
Let me slice, this, the sort key up into chunks and sort just one of
the chunks first, then another chunk than another chunk.
And if you imagine just doing it to one buffer over and over, then you
can sort of imagine why I was saying about a series of sable sorts.
If I was to just sort the buffer based on the lowest order thing
first, then I sorted
And stably by the next one up and then the next one up and the next
one up.
When I got to the end my buffer would be sorted, right?
Because like again taking this example, the first sort puts these in
order so it says oh I've got 10 10, 100, 1, 0 1, 1 0 6, 2006 right 10
7, 2007, right?
That's what it says.
Again all of these are now in order.
But these are not right, then it sorts by this stably.
Have to make any changes, then it sorts by this against stabili.
So, it goes.
Okay.
I've got 100, 100 100.
And 6.
2006, not in place.
107 would come there, right?
Then I've got 2006 2007.
Stable sort and so now, even though I only sorted on this was only
starting on this digit, that time, I end up with the right answer
overall because the stable the stability of the sort means that I can
sort just by this and since I know these are already in order, I know
that the final result will come out in entirety ordered entirely
right.
Okay.
So that's basically how Radix sort, like, what the idea behind Radix
sort is right.
But the question is, why would we care about that?
Like, why do we want to slice it up?
What's the magic that makes it like, what does slicing it up?
Give us.
Yes, that would work to stably sort this thing in place, you know, in
the case of the 32-bit number B, 4 different times.
But why do I want to sort it for different times?
Well, the answer is because once you chopped
Down the total number of possible, things possible values of the sort
key.
Once you chop it down into something, tractable like 8 Bits.
What do we know about eight bits?
Well, there's 256 possible values.
In 8 Bits, right?
8 B is only 200 spots of ice.
It's trivial these days on Modern computers to do something like in t.
Count 256, right?
Right.
Very, very simple.
No one would bat an eyelash about that.
So what that means is, if we can, if we can make something that's
that's this small.
We can start to use interesting table logic to reduce the actual work,
we have to do.
So, in the case of a Radix, sort, what we do is exactly something like
this.
We say, okay, let's start with a table.
That tells us how many of each type of sort key.
We have we know that once we slice it into B that each byte value for
the sort key, can only have 8 Bits of data or go only 256 possible
values.
So in one pass, we're only dealing with 256 possible sort Keys.
We could run through the thing again.
Om time to go through all the elements right?
It would only take Owen time to go through all the elements once.
Look at that section of their sort key and increment the count value
to tell us how many of that sort key we have, right?
So again, coming up here to this example.
If we were to do this, you can imagine making a table.
This again is base 10.
So we would have something that was like count ten right?
For each of the digits.
We would go through here and we would say, Okay 40's, we have 14 ones.
We have to, I'm sorry one, right four sixes,
We have to this one in this one for sevens.
We also have to write everything else was 0.
So once we know this now,
After we're done, it is Trivial for us to put these in exactly the
right place, right?
Because now when we come through the second past, right?
Because we do a know one thing to get these counts.
Now if we just Loop over the elements again, we can say exactly where
they go because we know if something has a sort key of one, it just
has to go after the first one of these.
Right?
If something has a sort key of seven, it just goes after the the
second one of these, right?
So we can just do two passes, right?
So, it's basically 0 to n to do one of these.
We do two passes, first account, how many of each we have and then to
put things in their place that's really all we need to do in terms of
the N.
right now, if we just do that exact operation,
Four times in a row for our binary, right for our for our 32-bit guy,
if we just did for 8-bit passes of that to anything, we would have
something that was 04 times 2N, right?
Or a 10.
We would have something that was a 10 to put all of the things, all of
these in order, no matter how big the in is the end could be a billion
and it would still only be eight billion cost now compare this to and
login.
It or O N squared, which were are other sort options.
And you can see why this might be kind of nice, because if the number
was a billion, Well, Log n or say four billion login, in that case
would have been 32.
But here are constant, is only eight, right?
Which is a very big Improvement, potentially,
Makes sense.
Now again there's a little bit of an extra cost here which is that
like I've got to initialize this table, two zeros and I've got to do
these, you know, these counter comments.
So you know, it's not free to break it up into this.
But again in terms of scaling and remember, that's what we were
talking about, with order annotation in terms of scaling.
You can see that this scales very well because unlike the other sorts,
which always scale by some super linear factor of n either squared or
a log n.
The Radix sort is one of the very few sorts that does not.
It actually just scales by n.
And again, it does that by taking advantage of the fact that what you
actually store in a computer is typically finite, it's not an infinite
Precision arithmetic, kind of a thing, it's finite and so you can use
that finiteness to slice it up into more tractable parts.
Right.
If these were infinite Precision numbers, this would not work
But because these are very specific, finite Precision finite bounded
numbers which is what we typically do with a computer.
You can take that shortcut and make it work, right?
Okay.
Let's see how we would need to do that.
It's going to be a little complicated for our particular case,
unfortunately.
Because right, we have a Radix sort situation where we don't actually
have a 32-bit integer sort key.
We have a floating points or key.
So we're going to have to do something with that to get our sort to
work properly.
But for now we can just pretend we don't and write the sort first and
then we'll deal with the fact of how do we transform our problem into
an actual Radix, sort.
Let's see how much time I have.
I think I started at 5:20.
So I actually have until about 6:20 to finish.
So we've got a bit of time here.
So here's our Radix sort.
And here's I'm going to go ahead and
Put that together there.
And so now we'll just get rid of our Birds sort and we'll call our
Radix sort.
And so, how are we going to do it?
What we're going to do?
Exactly what I said before?
We know that our count can be no more than 32 bits because that's the
value that we got passed in.
So we know.
We only have 4 billion or less items.
So we know we can just use a that for our accounts.
So, what we'll do is, you know, sort sort key accounts or something
like that.
And like I said, if we know that we have just a third
Floating-point number will assume for now that it's only going to be,
it's going to only be four passes, right?
It's going to be 32 bits will do it by B, just like I did in the
diagram there.
So, that means we've got 256 possible, sort key values for each slice
of our thing, right?
Okay.
Now again, we need to clear that 20 which is kind of unfortunate, but
like I said, it's just there's some cost to setting up the Radix sort.
I don't think there's a lot of ways around that.
So, the first thing that we would do is we'd say, okay, we've got
To go through and we've got to take our sort keys and figure out how
many of each kind we have.
And like I also said for each time through, when we do this, we have
to have some way of doing it for each slice, right?
So we also have a thing here that's like, for our sort key, if it's 32
bits, we know that we have like a bite index, do it, right?
And the B index is going to have to be
It's going to have to go up, right?
We're gonna have to slice the bottom bite off.
Then the next bite, then the next bite the next fight.
If we want to do it from stable, sort from bottom up, right?
At least significant byte to most significant byte, we could choose to
do it.
I think potentially it would be possible to maybe do it another way,
but it would be a little fuzzier.
So, anyway, so we'll do it that way again.
Like I said for for stable sort passes over the array to sort it by
each increasingly more important bite.
Right, every time.
Okay, so we go through here, we have our B index, we then want to Loop
over our items, right?
So this is just our entry index into the array.
And so, as we come through here, we just need to say, whatever our,
like, our entries are
Whatever our particular entry is here, it has a sort key.
And what we need to do is call, like, sort key to you 32.
Right?
Because like I said, we need it to be you 32 for this scheme to work.
So we need to call that and we don't know what that is yet and
honestly to be completely, honestly, I'm gonna have to think about
what that is because I'm not really sure, but we've got something
there, which is going to pass in this floating point value and we've
got to turn it into a u-32.
Okay, so so this is our Radix value.
This is the thing.
We're actually going to sort on.
Once we have that Radix value.
We know that we have a bite index here, that
Going to operate on.
So we take that Radix value and we shift down by the B Index, right?
Because the B index 0 we're going to take that first, at least
significant byte.
So we need to shift down as it goes up to the next pass through by
tanks going to be one.
We're going to shift down by eight bits, right?
8, B, 8 Bits.
So each time we go through, we want to take out a successively higher
part, and again, we only want just that just the 8-Bit value at the
bottom because we're doing eight bits at a time.
So we got a mask it out and so
Here we go.
So now we have, like our B piece or something, whatever you want to
call it Radix piece, something like that.
So this is the full Radix value that we're sorting on.
This is the piece that we're starting on in this pass.
And then we go to our sort keys.
And we say, whatever that piece is, whatever that pieces.
We got to increment that count because now we know we have one more of
those.
Right?
So there we go.
That's all of our key counts.
Now, we can also do something else here, which is keep track of the
total, and you can do this in two different ways, but we do need to
No, I'm sorry, that's not actually true.
We don't need to keep track of the total.
I know why I'm saying that we need to, we need to do the running
total, which will do here.
Okay, so we go through there, we keep track of how many keys are now.
We have our stuff set up so that we know are sort key.
Counts are however many, there are in each one of our effectively
buckets, you could almost think of them.
Right.
We know how many sort Keys fall into each possible.
8-bit value that there is okay.
So now we want to go through our different sort Keys like directly and
say for each of our sort key.
For each of these entries into our sort Keys.
We now need to know
the running total like of all the sort keys that happen before them.
Right.
Because remember the next thing we're going to do is we're going to do
a thing here, oops.
we're going to do, you know,
First pass, count.
How many of each key, right?
That's what we're doing here.
And then here, we're going to do
Second Pass Place.
Into the right location.
Okay, so by the time we get to the second pass, when we get down here
and we extract the Radix, peace, we have to be able to essentially do
this and place it exactly where it needs to go.
Right, that's what we actually need to do.
So in here, what we need to do is transform this sort key count to a
sort key offset, right?
And in fact we might want to actually call it that to begin with
because that's what it ends up being, right?
So then what we do is we say, alright, we initialize our running total
and say we're going to start off.
Obviously, the first thing we'll go in slot 0, that's pretty obvious,
right?
So we go through our sort keys and say, all right, we've got the sort
key offset, whatever.
This sort key offset actually is we want to take that value and save
it for a second, right?
This is like the count at the moment.
We then want to take that sort key offset and say, okay, for
this particular sort key, we know that it would start at wherever our
current total is so wherever we would, you know, however, many things
were occupied in the list up to this point, that's where we would
start putting things that have this sort key and then we would say,
alright advance that running total by whatever our count actually was,
Do you see how that works?
I'll just briefly sort of say it again over here.
So we've gone through our list, right?
We've done a no end pass over the array of entries, right?
This is the entries and we've counted how many of each sort key we
saw.
So in this past we end up with sort key counts.
Right now, what we need to do is do another pass where we can put
things in the right place, but in order to do that, we need to know
where the right place is for each type of sort key.
Okay, so we've got these sort key counts, right?
And we've got 256 of these, right?
And what we need to do is we've got something that looks like oh
there's you know sort Keys 0.
Well that's got three sort key.
One that's got none sort Q2 that's got five sort Q 3 right and so when
I come through on my
S.
Om pass to put the entries in the right place.
Well uh oh I can't look up in here.
If the first thing had a sort key of to all I know is there are five
of them?
Well that doesn't tell me where to put it.
What I need to know is what was the sum of all previous sort keys,
right?
Because the correct place to put to put something in the list.
If it has a sort key of to, is after the third one, right?
Because there's three elements before it, it will are occupied.
Pied by people with a sort P of 0.
So they have to come first.
Those first three are filled by the people of zero, right.
So when I do this, I'm gonna have some of the sort Kia 0 here, 0 here,
0 here.
And then I can start putting people with the sort key of
Right.
So all I'm doing here is just summing up keeping a running total so
that I can change these to the to be offsets of where those sort Keys
occur, right?
Finally.
In the second pass, right?
And this is Casey change counts to offsets.
So finally in the second pass, I go through each one, I do the exact
same thing as I did in the first pass where I get out that Radix
piece.
This is the sort key for this pass.
And what I need to do is take the sort key offset.
For this Radix piece.
And I just need to put this entry there, right?
So, I need to say, dest of that equals source of Index, right, and
that does the sort move.
Now, remember, I may have many entries that have the same sort key
piece.
In fact, that's the whole reason I counted is because I might have a,
who knows how many arbitrarily many I could have count many, all of,
Could have the same value this time round.
In fact, many of The Times They will, the top values might be all 0.
For example, if you're a sorting, some low 32-bit values.
And so each time I place one in here, I need to increment that offset
because the next one who comes through here, will have to be placed in
the, in the subsequent slot, right?
So you can almost think of these Source key offsets as basically 256
pointers in some sense, 200 basis.
That say where the next place is too, right?
The element that has that sort key.
Okay.
All right, so now what you'll notice about this is I'm just straight
up romping over my array, so source and desk can't be the same here,
because, right?
I've got to have two different things.
So, again, Radix sort In-Place, probably exists don't even want to try
it.
So, Radix, sort want some temp memory?
Okay.
So, here's my first and here's my temp, right?
So I'm going to start off and say, well, I've got tile sword entry.
And I've got my source, my source obviously Begins by pulling from
first.
I've got my my dest that begins by being temp, right?
And then each time through here, I'm going to do a swap, right?
So I've kind of got a swap value, that's, that's going to be equal to
dest.
I'm going to change desk to be source, and I'm going to change source
to be swapped in.
So I'm just going to go ahead and ping.
The buffer is so each time through eyesore into a new buffer, right?
So the first time through sort and dest source and estar first attempt
next time through it goes from temp to First next time through it goes
from first attempt next, a ghost room, temp 2 first and hey, what do
you know?
I believe that actually puts it back in exactly the place that we
wanted it, right?
Okay so that oh and this has to be source as well.
Sorry so that is basically a Radix sort.
I may have type some bugs in there but that is basically the idea and
and there you go.
This is obviously not an arrow.
That's one of these and there we go.
okay, so our sort q2u, 32 we don't actually know what that is right
now so you know, we could just just straight up cast it, that will not
actually work, but now we have our Radix sort running anyway, and so
if I now go to to run this, presumably, this will not actually sort
because we probably won't get that lucky with the floating Point
values, so we should hit an assertion, which will tell us that
actually, hey,
Great job guys but you didn't in fact, sort the buffer.
Now, the first thing I want to make sure is that I actually did that
correct in my head and that we are actually putting it into the
entries output area as I would have expected.
Let me see if that's the case.
Well, I guess I wouldn't really know even if it was the case.
So actually, I guess what I would rather do is just step through and
verify that that's true.
So, let's go ahead and come through here and I'm going to run to the
end of this routine.
And I just
See what desk is equal to, right?
So here's first, here's temp, what's test equal to so it's okay
perfect.
So the last time through the loop, it will swap the things.
So if I was correct desk, should be pointing to Temp at the end and it
and it is so that's exactly what I wanted.
So that's good.
Okay.
So maybe I did the rig sort, right?
Maybe I didn't, I don't know.
We haven't actually gotten that far yet, but because what we need to
do now is have something we need to turn our 32-bit floating-point
value into some strictly ascending 32-bit integer.
Value.
Right?
So you can see the problem here.
This only works when you can actually slice out the b and compare them
as if they were actually parts.
Of a singly ordered 32-bit surgery is a 32-bit numbers floating Point
values.
Again are not exactly going to be that, okay?
And why aren't they?
Well, if you remember this is the 32-bit
IEEE float kind of value here.
What do these look like?
Okay, what does a 32-bit?
Point value.
Look like we talked about this.
We've talked about this, right?
And it looks like this, it's got a mantissa, it's got an exponent and
it's got a sign bit, okay?
Now the sign bit, if I remember correctly, doesn't that help us here,
right?
Because the sign bit will be set to 0 if it's positive but it'll set
to 1 if it's - right.
And the way that we're
And right now we will sort negative values as being greater than
positive values, right?
We will put negative values after positive values and obviously, that
is not what we want, right?
So at the very even right off the bat, we're in trouble because the
sine value creates obviously a problem for us.
Now, the rest of this probably doesn't really create a problem for us
because the exponent is the part that is the most important in terms
of how, how much magnitude and number has, right?
We're trying to sort these by magnitude in, you know, this is our Z
value.
Essentially, we're trying
It effectively, ZZ magnitude for the most part, the exponent is the
most important part that says, you know, two to the exponent here is
exactly what we is exactly what we want to come first because the
mantissa is actually the least important part, right?
That's the like you know, one point, you know, some number thing here
that's part of our scientific notation.
It's this it's mantissa times 2 to the exponent, the to, to the
exponents.
Obviously, the most important part because the mantissa can only ever
be one point something.
Right?
So this is already in a natural order and the mantissa part would just
work sorting by the mantissa would just work because the higher the
value their, the higher, the value is, and that's fine, right?
So mantissa, we don't have to worry about those bits could actually
stay exactly the same the exponent part.
I think also just works and the reason that I think that part just
works is because the exponent
Is actually set up biased instead of being like - n2n.
I believe the way that floating-point exponents are stored, our is
they start at like 0 to 127 is considered - and like 128 to like you
know I'm sorry.
It's only seven bits of the I think this is only 7 B actually.
So it's actually a 02 like 63 or something, right?
And then 64 to 127 is positive.
I believe that's how they're stored, which means that, I think the X1
itself also goes in the proper order.
Meaning, these are negative exponents, so they'll be very small
numbers.
These are positive exponents so they'll be larger numbers.
So I believe exponent Plus mantissa.
As B is actually probably fine meaning we can just we can just use
that value.
Its I think only the sign bit that actually would cause us a problem.
I think right now.
Let's take a look.
And see what's going on here.
If I break into what's going on, it's complaining that I didn't
recompile.
Okay.
Well, here you go.
If I stop, when it, when it gets confused here, right?
And I take a look at the entry.
So how many entries are there?
There's, there's not very many right.
There's only eight entries and here is a are
Let's see what we've got.
So, here are my values.
I'm not quite certain that looks.
Busted to me.
Does it not as that?
Is that right?
What's going on there?
I wonder if we wonder if I've got a bug in there.
Let's take a look here.
Are those really the values that are got entered in?
Let's see.
So, here are my entries.
I've only got one.
There is my entry, okay, so that's just some some giant number.
Let me, let me try to get some more.
I want something that's going to have more entries here.
That's the count value, right?
Here we go.
Sorry, I got to stop down the Radix, sort.
All right.
So let me see.
I want to get something where we've got like that.
Ate, those eight values there.
There we go.
So 43.
All right, so, let me take a look at my 43 values before I go weeks,
or what do they look like?
So, here's all my values for some reason, they're all - right, and I
guess that's just some kind of artifact of how we're passing them in.
But I guess that's okay.
I'm not sure.
I understand why they are so I guess they're because they're further
down, I don't know.
It's a little bit weird, but we have to think about why our sort keys
are what they are.
It doesn't matter point being we can see them and they're all
Right.
So, you know, Radix, sort and Theory should be totally wrong for how
that works.
In theory, I would think although that weirdly did exactly the right
thing.
so, the sign bit,
The sign bit should have made that happen wrong.
Oh no, it wouldn't.
I guess, because the sign bits always on for all of them but yeah,
well, no, that's still be wrong because which they should have come
out in the opposite order.
Should they not have
I feel.
He should have come out with the 457 at the bottom, right?
I don't know about that.
How did it do it, right?
I feel like it should have done it wrong.
I'm very confused by that, but I'll go take a look and find out why
That's just really unusual.
We're Not Unusual.
It's just not what I expected.
So let's try that one more time.
Okay, so here we are stopping at a Radix sort that didn't work
properly and here are, it's a, it's an eight long one.
And so, here they are.
And, yeah, they're just like, totally not correct.
Right?
So, again, this is what I would have expected more, I guess.
but,
But I don't know.
Oh,
Maybe it's just because yet you know what I I'm not actually just
casting.
This is what I probably should be doing if I just want to cast to a
you 32 and if that was actually converting it, so that would have
actually just gotten rid of the floating-point part.
So that's that's why I was just forgot that we weren't actually
looking at the bits yet if that makes sense.
So now it's doing what I what I would have expected, right?
Which is that it's not actually sorting these things at all correctly,
right?
Which is here.
We go for 31 values.
So like - 532 is at the end, that's really the smallest number but
because it thinks the sign bit is effectively is one when the number
is higher in zero and snot.
We end up in a situation where we, we have the sort of that sign.
Bit confounding, the sort.
If the sound it wasn't set, we would be totally fine.
Right.
If for, for positive floating Point numbers, this would just
Twerk.
But unfortunately, we don't have that option.
So really what we would want to do here is we want to turn this into
a, we'd want to turn this into a 32 bit number that properly reflected
the sign bit.
So I guess what you would do here is say, well, you know, if the sign
bit you can imagine saying if result and 0 X8, right?
This is if we have the sign bit set, otherwise we don't, right?
And I believe what we could do is say well,
If the sign bit wasn't set.
then these things will just sort correctly, but we need to make room
for having
For that - piece, right?
So I might say, all right, if the sign bit wasn't set,
Like if the sign bit.
Was not set, set it.
So positive values get their sign bit set.
Right?
- values need to go like in the opposite order because the bigger the
number, the more - it is, right?
So essentially what we want to do is like invert the meaning of the
bits, right?
We want to do like a subtract effectively, that will do like a carry,
I guess.
So that the numbers flip around.
This is probably not the most efficient way to do this at all but
again I'm just trying to figure out something that would work, right?
So I need in this case when the sign bit is set I need some way of
making the numbers go in the opposite order so that like you know 01
comes before 10 right?
Like in other words,
Normally in binary, if I've got, you know, 0, 0, 0, 1, 1 0 1.
1, as the order things are sorting in, I need them to go the opposite
way.
So that instead I get 1 1 1 0 0, 1 0 0 is the actual sort order now,
right?
So, I wonder if can I just literally flip the bits?
Is it like that?
Simple?
I mean does that just work?
It seems like it might I mean I'd have to think about whether I can
really prove that that's true, but in other words, if that sign bit is
set, can I just can I just
Facts or the value, right?
Can I just X or the value and just flip all the bits in it?
Or rather just just set it to not itself.
I don't know.
Seems like that's too easy, so maybe I think I'm probably just totally
missing something.
But I'd be interested to see what that actually does.
So let's step in here.
We're is that there it is.
So I'm going to step into each of them want to see what this does in
each case.
All right.
so here's my result value and this is
A negative number, right?
So and this is like a negative number that has basically everything
set.
So, what, what is this value?
This must be a special case.
This must be like, one of those like, yeah, it's like the real
minimums, like, where the Clear goes, right?
I think that's what that value is.
It's like a clear, you know, clears want to sort all the way to the
back always.
So that's like the maximum value.
So, you know that I guess we
I won't learn anything from this but when we flip it, we get that
right.
Is that correct?
like I said, it's hard for you to think about
We're never going to know what this one because that's the oh it seems
to only appear by itself in most of these.
Let me
Let me see.
There we go.
So I'm just going to do a thing where I'm going to see if I can just
jump back in here.
Oh you know what I can do.
I think I can just do something where I
where I extract.
Yeah, this would be a good thing.
So I'm going to just extract the sort keys for some things that I know
what they are, right?
Meaning I'm going to go.
All right, tell me what the sort key.
Is for something that I'm going to just feed you to be like so I want
-1.0.
- 2 3 4 5 .5, right?
All right, so just some basic values and I want to see what this does
because like I said, I've never really done this before.
So I have no idea what the best thing to do is just want to explore it
and see what I get.
Right?
So there is a result, a result, be result, see result, D result, e.e.
results.
F
G h, i j.
Okay.
So here we go.
Result a is negative 1 and like you can see that it won't have the
high bit set so that's good.
This seems because we haven't done this yet.
There we go.
okay, so all these have the high bit set and they do go up by
Either way that I would have expected, right?
So result.
And then C then C 0 for C 0?
8, CB, so those those seem to go in order, right?
I mean that looks about right to me.
Yeah, I mean, that's, that's what I would expect.
Right, I don't see anything particularly odd about that.
We'll have to play around with it a little bit more.
But and then these guys for the negatives, negative one is properly
higher than negative 2 to the negative 3, lower than that - 4 - 5 .5,
lower still.
So that looks, you know, I'm probably missing something but that looks
like cursorily correct.
So let me see what my actual problem is here.
Where we start to get the assertion.
We've got in that case, 11 values and the entries.
For those 11 values.
Are still, so those are still going up.
Those are still going up in.
In the order, as if we hadn't fixed it.
Why is that?
Dare I ask.
We need to turn our 32 bit floating point value so I strictly sending
it through to.
Yes, that's true.
When the sign bit set, we flip the values.
So what does it think?
The sort keys are for these.
I pray tell sort key to you, 32 of - for 57.0.
And what is sort key to you.
32 of - 470, 7.0 and what is sort key to you.
32 of - 53 2.0,
So tell me it looks like our sort is just broken because tell me how
we sorted these in that order, if these are what the sort keys were.
So that looks actually like I just have a bug in the actual sort to
me, right?
Because those should not be in that order.
- 47 shouldn't come first, it's higher.
Right.
So what did I mess up there?
Why is it not?
Let's let's see.
Can we can we jump back here set next day?
Can I jump in here, possibly?
Let's find out.
So here is our source and we've got how many again 11.
So here's our source ears are dest.
Right.
There we are.
So if I come through here and I count my values, let me see, sort key
offsets,
Actually, I guess I don't super care about this quite yet, but let's
see Radix piece 255.
Yeah, that's that'll do it.
That would do it folks.
Notice that I'm shifting down by the B index, but yeah, not exactly
correct.
Is it, when the bite index is used as a bit shift
I'm not going to use a Flawless shame because we're in the middle of
debugging, but like that's a baby owl of Shame like, come on, like
Right.
I would I would say baby.
I love shame on that because I mean, seriously.
So yeah, I think we probably want to do maybe something more like
that.
So we'll actually do 8, 16 24.
Let's try this again.
Hey, look, it works now.
What a shocking surprise.
Yeah, anyway, so we are Radix.
Sorting are things now and that's all good, you know, no complaints
there and the Radix sort seems to be working nicely and so everyone is
happy and everything's fine.
Great, fantastic, good.
There we go.
All right.
So
That's our Radix sort.
Yeah, don't have a lot to say about it other than you asked for it.
You got it and that we got a little bit of time left for Q&A.
So we can go over to Q&A.
and if you have questions about the Radix sort,
I'm not going to promise that I can answer them, but
you're welcome to ask them.
Ratchet.
Freak.
Why didn't you build merge sort from the bottom up?
Well, because we didn't really get to the point where we're actually
trying to optimize one of these sorts yet that makes sense.
So it depends which one of these we actually want to do.
And to be honest, I don't really know if we decide that mergesort
should be the one we keep, then we would implement it so that it, you
know, does the minimum amount of work, but I don't know that it would
be since we bothered with a Radix sort.
I'm guessing that the Radix sort will end up being the one to use
because we'll have more than two hundred six elements.
Most of the time I mean I assume I don't know.
Fod 669 your Radix sort looks like it's 08 and because you're doing
two passes over the list.
/ B.
Couldn't you make it o5n by getting all the offsets counts in one pass
at the cost of three more 256 element arrays?
Yes I think.
I mean, here's the thing.
I'm not prepared to say whether something is a 10 or 5 n or anything
else because that's the Cs sort of stuff.
And, you know, you might say that well, but then you have to clear
this thing multiple times per something.
And so it's doing that many more rights.
So it doesn't matter, right?
I mean, I don't know, it's like,
Doing passes over the list.
Versus just this is why I think they don't put the constant in there
is because it's not really that relevant because doing passes over the
list versus doing more operations inside the loop.
You know, it's like it's sort of six of one half-dozen of the other.
In terms of what you'd actually say, the complexity of the algorithm
was.
So is it a potentially better to do this in terms, you know, of a
In terms of a performance thing for our purposes.
Probably, yes.
I would assume.
But then again, that's the sort of thing.
We would just have the time to figure out, is it something that
affects the complexity of the algorithm know?
Because it's n regardless that makes sense.
Elvin, of course jumps in with a horribly off topic question.
But he did Market with off-topic.
I'm a bit confused about axis angle rotations versus quaternion
rotations, I thought quaternions do represent an angle and axis of
rotation.
What's the difference, the answer is that all rotation representations
encode in Access in an angle because it acts as an angle is what
defines a rotation if that makes sense.
So, essentially the difference between all of the different rotation
representations is not whether they encode in acts as an angle.
It's how.
So, if you take a look at the common ones, right?
You've got Euler angles.
Or, you know, I it's very confusing because there's Euler angles,
which are like three angles, right?
Which is, which is like three things of rotation, you know.
First I rotate around one axis, then I rotate around another axis and
then I rotate around, you know, I gotta draw yet another axis.
There we go.
Yes, I'm learning.
Is this three-set sequential rotations?
Around three different, axes, right.
There's also things called Euler parameters, which are not the same
thing will ignore that for now.
But boiler or other parameters are actually more in the like
quaternion exponential map family of things.
But anyway, yes, that's like Euler angles which are encoding, the, the
rotation around like, like three different axes sequentially.
So I rotate around this axis, our return on that Axis or Taro this
axis,
But the result right is still some orientation that you could have got
to buy starting at wherever the, you know, at rest and rotating by
some angle around some axis.
So this is the encoding but the result is still a single rotation
around a single axis because all row two orientations can be
represented that way, right?
So then we've got something like, you know, axis angle
And that's where I have, you know, like oh and we could, I don't know
what these are normally, they're like fada fee and something.
I don't even know what this guy normally is, you know, Omega, I don't
know.
Whatever he is.
So the Euler angles are three scalars, right?
Axis angle is typically, you know, I've got something like this.
Right, maybe I'll write it this way.
So access angle is like, you know, I've got an A
The rotation and angle.
So here, I just directly encode it exactly what it is.
And like I said, any orientation can be encoded that way, but you
know, this close includes explicitly quaternion.
Is again, just another encoding.
So, instead of a Theta and an XYZ, in this case, I've got instead,
I've got sine of half the angle times the X sine of half the angle
times, the Y, sine of half the angle times the Z, and then cosine of
half the angle.
In the W, right?
So here you can kind of see it's actually sort of a composite form.
It's actually a thing where I've got a vector, it's got its got the
cosine of half the angle in the bottom.
It's got the sine of half the angle in the top times that axis of
rotation, right?
So these two are the same thing.
These two are the same thing but we just we actually did some trig.
We divide it by 2 and did some trig on it, right?
So the encoding for quaternion
Less Direct.
There's a lot I could talk for very long.
Time about why?
That's true.
I'm not going to do that right now but there's reasons why they do
that, obviously, they don't just do it for fun and then there's the
exponential map, right?
Exponential map is just a direct multiplication of axis angle.
If I remember correctly, I believe that's true because I believe,
exponential map yet exponential map.
It's been a long time.
So I represent things exponential, map is sort of the same as
instantaneous velocity.
Angular velocity.
So it's just literally like some angle times, the vector, so it's a
vector that looks like this.
Right, I directly scale the vector by the amount of rotation that I
wanted to do.
And so again that's like this.
So, it's a vector.
That's a multiplication of these.
Again, these are the same.
These are the same.
So again, still its axis angle all the way through.
It's just which encoding you're using.
That's, that's really all I have to say about it.
I guess.
So yeah.
All of the encoding is, are different in the sense that they encode,
different numeric values.
But they are all orientation.
And in orientation is always, can always be thought of as an axis and
an angle of rotation around, that make sense.
So far as I noticed, the frame times are growing quite large now.
Are you planning to optimize the software under further or switch to a
hardware-accelerated?
Aim, I'm not sure they're still totally do usable for development so I
don't super care.
I'm not sure what the frame rate difference is if I turn again, I
don't remember what the actual performances for if I turn it down to
low res, right?
So if I say Where's that stuff?
If I decide to run in a half or quarter res mode, right?
And I, and I also turn off our debug stuff.
I'm not sure what the feel is of the game.
So yeah, so I probably would not optimized further.
I just run in low-res it for now, right?
Because that's super Zippy and totally fine for
Making the game.
How much is that?
How much of that does the debug system suck up in terms of time here?
Probably law, huh?
And actually, no.
That's not too bad.
So basically yeah if we just if we just are willing to go and low-res
then we don't have a problem so so I think I can find with that for a
while.
Alrighty, let's see.
Any other questions?
Think we're good.
All right.
Well, no further questions.
Then I will shut down the stream.
We go.
And I'll save this.
All right, thanks everyone for joining me for another episode of
handmade hero.
It's been a pleasure coding with you.
As always, we have pretty much finished our sorting, we just gonna
have to decide which one to keep, and I don't even know if we have to
do that.
Now all of them work we could save that for some time when we're
profiling and have a lot more enemies on the screen.
So hey we wrote them all there in there.
Now some point we can optimize them if we so choose or even write an
entirely different sort.
Now that we know what we're doing, but that means tomorrow, I think we
should probably move on to something new.
I don't see any real reason to belabor the point.
I think you guys all get it by now and you kind of see how sorting
works.
It's not a huge deal at the end of the day and I don't think it's
going to be a significant part of our running performance anyway.
But if it does become so such, then we will obviously be able to take
care of that.
Now that we kind of know what what our options are.
So that's it, if you're would like to follow along with series at
home, obviously, you can go ahead and pre-order the game on Hamid org
and it comes to the source code, even right as we speak.
So you can play around with at home and follow the episodes on your
own.
We also have a forum site where you can ask questions, we have a
patreon page, you can spread the video series and we have a tweetbot
that we'd schedule at you and that tree pot right now, we'll be
tweeting it.
You that we will be back here live tomorrow at 5 p.m.
Pacific Standard time to move on.
To our next thing, which I don't know what it's going to be because we
only have a few things left to do really before we Implement our
actual game game.
Which, of course, is the part that's terrifying because I'm not a game
designer, so that's going to be rough.
But
God, you at some point.
So anyway, until tomorrow, I hope all of you have fun programming.
I'm I will see you on the internet.
Take it easy, everyone.