Okay, if John is done, that means we should go ahead and start here.
Three minutes.
That was not too long to wait.
I think I'm pretty excited about John's new language.
I hope you guys are too.
It's the first time I've seen anyone, who really cares about the same
sorts of things that I care about, try to make a new language.
And so I'm pretty optimistic.
I think maybe a year or two from now.
I can do handmade hero in j.i.
Or something fun like that.
And I think that would be a blast.
I'm sure there's a bunch of cool stuff we could do with.
It anyway, thank you for indulging.
Me and waiting the extra few minutes.
I wanted to catch the the whole thing, a job, John's presentation, but
it is time.
Now, for day, 18.
Am I correct people?
I believe it is day.
18 of handmade hero the show, where we create an entire game,
professional quality from scratch.
No libraries.
No nothing.
So we can see how every last little thing actually works.
And to me, that is very important, because I think it's crucial to
really kind of understand how everything works.
Even when you do, then go on to use libraries or use engines, just
having that full perspective.
There, that lets you at anytime drop down to a low level and fix
anything that you need to, or to understand why something might be
going wrong in code that you're using that kind of stuff is just so
valuable.
And so we are going to do it all here on this stream.
We're going to keep on making sure we go into detail every last little
place we can.
So today on our we've got a pretty big to-do item that we've got to do
today.
And I don't know if we're going to get it all in today.
So we're going to try.
And basically what we have to do is we have not actually done the work
to make a proper synchronized timing Loop to drive our games.
So we could go ahead and make our game on the platform layer that we
have now, but we would be at risk of having greater audio latency than
we should have.
We would be
At risk of sort of having just synchronization problems there.
We just haven't quite gotten to the point where we really understand
the timing of when things show up on the screen and when the audio
plays out the speakers.
And so I'd like to do a little tightening there before we even start.
I know, I've said later that we're going to go and have a pass on the
win32 platform, where we're going to ship, where we do a bunch of
things that we've been putting off that, our performance kind of
stuff, that sort of thing and compatibility stuff that we're not
addressing now, but this, I want to address sooner rather than later
because
All of the decisions that we make in the actual game itself are all
driven off of this timing.
So when we are playing the game, when we were deciding, how long
things should take in the game.
Every last thing we do is going to be based on on to me is going to be
based on whatever that clocking is.
So if we have that clocking wrong in the platform, prototyping layer,
that we've got now, then we're at risk of making a whole bunch of
tuning things.
things in,
Wrecked in our game and then when we go to finalize the platform layer
and tighten all that stuff up, then we have this problem.
Where.
Oh, now all the tuning values that all of the stuff that we tuned in
our game and all of the stuff that we thought was right for
playability of the game.
As we were developing.
It is actually all wrong.
So what we want to do is just take a little bit of time now to go
through and kind of make it a little more coherent, what it's trying
to do and make sure that we understand that so that we can know that
we don't have any critical problems.
That will lead us to make a bunch of bad decisions and that we have to
kind of redo later.
Anyway, yeah, some of them screams.
I don't forget to start recording the problem.
There is, I did forget to do the stop, start recording.
So that just means I, it's really used to convenience feature for me.
It just means that I have to go through and take the file and just
clip out the first little bit before I upload to Youtube.
So that the YouTube archive doesn't have a bunch of me watching John
on the stream, although, who knows.
Maybe it should be a bunch of me, watching John Street, but ignoring
that.
So what we need to do today,
Is we need to go take care of that?
So if you have pre-ordered the game, then you have access to the
source code.
You got an email that has a link in it.
That link allows you to download the source code every night.
So, I highly recommend you do that because if you would like, to
follow along with what we are doing today, here on day 18, you just
unzipped the day 17 piece out of your zip file, that zip file has
every days in there.
So you can jump to any day you want and work on it.
So if you're looking at this video, you want to be a day 17 Source
unzipped
That is what I am starting with and that is what you should start with
as well.
All right.
So before we go and actually do any coding, what I want to do first is
take a look at the goals that we have for what we're trying to what
we're trying to make.
I want to, I want to really kind of go over sort of the, the high
level picture.
So that everyone understands what we're trying to do.
Now.
I took some recommendations from folks and I downloaded this package
called Smooth draw, which I guess is is
Thing that they use on Khan Academy or something like this.
Just to see if it's any better than the thing that that we were using
the paint Microsoft Paint.
I tried it a little bit and honestly, it doesn't seem to actually be
any better.
It seems to be basically just the same thing as we had before here.
It doesn't actually seem to be all that much better.
But you know what, we'll give it a little shot and we'll see how it
plays out.
So what I want to talk about is I want to go back to that diagram sort
of that.
I've been using for quite
um time where I'm talking about the various frames when they're
computed when they're displayed that sort of thing.
So I'm going to make some tick marks on our timeline here like this.
And basically what we have here is is this is T going for, is this is
time.
This is our timeline, right?
And the timeline, you know, I can I get asked, can I get a?
Can I get that little low smaller time line that gets smaller, didn't
feel like it got much smaller.
I don't know.
What did you guys think that?
Got smaller hard to say, let's go even smaller.
Other than that time, why do you know what?
It's just not very good.
I don't know about this program will give it a little more.
Will give it a little more time.
But I'm not I'm not optimistic.
That this is actually, you know, yeah, what what it, what can you do,
something?
We can address a little later perhaps.
Anyway, basically if we take a look at what happens here, we start the
game at some point that will call t 0, right?
And basically, this is when the game actually begins running.
So the person runs the executable and we got to do our Windows startup
stuff and all that sort of thing.
Now, at some point we actually start the timing.
So we actually take a look at what our timer value actually is.
And that was query, performance counter was the thing that we were
using to measure time.
We're going to take a look at what that timing value actually is.
And when we take a look at that, that first time example, we take is
going to be the first Benchmark that we have, for figuring out how
much wall clock time has elapsed during our code.
So, I'm going to
Called t0 vat, actual time.
That is our first.
Look at a query performance counter, right?
That's our T equals 0.
Now, what's going to happen?
There is during this first interval during this interval here, right?
During that first interval.
We are going to be displaying essentially nothing, right.
This is just plain Blackness on the screen.
We will, if anything we just have a cleared window.
There's nothing there.
Because we have not actually prepared any actual, anything really?
We haven't actually got a frame buffer that we can show.
So, extending backwards as far as time goes, is some sort of Blackness
and then there's going to be some tick.
Mark, That's the first tick mark, where we actually display a frame.
Now, if we want to, we can also call this t 0.
It depends this.
This is again, we're gonna have a bunch of decisions.
Here.
We have a bunch of decisions.
We could also call t 0.
The first the the first frame flip.
Right, we could call it here.
Right?
So, I don't know which one we want to call T equals 0.
We could call it the start, we could call it here hard to say
something.
We're gonna have to decide in a few minutes, but basically, at some
point during here inside, here.
We are Computing frame 0, right.
We are Computing frame 0 audio and video, right?
We've got both of those coming online.
So we're doing the computation work inside this time interval to
compute those.
When they are done, we will then flip them.
So that right here.
And coming forwards to here, in this interval.
You can actually see frame 0 displayed.
So on the screen, you will see frame 0, right?
And ideally, what we'd also like to do is have audio 0 show up right
along with that.
Right?
So we want audio zero to come right here as well.
I don't know.
I don't know you guys feel about slashes 20.
Sometimes I feel like it's a little classy, you know, it feels a
little European, a little fancy.
So maybe I'll just
Go ahead and put that in there.
Put that in there.
So, what we've got now, is we've basically got a time interval.
This could have been as long as we wanted right because Blackness is
on the screen and no audio is playing.
So this is silent Blackness, right?
Sounds like some bad sci-fi movie Silent Blackness is here.
And then once we start here, we have both audio and a frame on the
screen.
So what basically happens is this can be arbitrarily long.
This this time interval is arbitrarily long and we don't actually
care.
How long it takes it could take an hour.
Well, I mean we care about that because we don't want to keep the user
waiting obviously, but doesn't matter how long it takes because there
isn't anything actually being displayed.
So as far as the user knows, they're not going to see any glitches or
hear any glitches.
If this takes too long because there's actually nothing going on.
It's just starting up.
The, the window has just come.
Come on screen, but once we get to hear this, now, we actually have
some Target for the amount of time.
If this is going to be on the screen.
This is basically a fixed duration here.
Right?
Oops.
That's not very good.
This is basically a fixed duration that we have to compute the next
frame.
Now.
I want to really underscore why I say this is fixed duration, because
there's a lot of stuff.
Like, I don't know if you guys have seen Nvidia, has made some
announcements and there's been announcements unlike other standards
and stuff about variable frame rate displays, right?
Basically, normal monitors to me, like the kind you would normally see
from just today.
Normal monitors have some framerate that, they update the image app.
And so, that framerate whatever the monitor is updating at is also
what we would like to update at.
If the monitor is refreshing, the image right at 60 frames a second.
So that's, you know, 16 milliseconds or so, 16.6.
Something like 17 milliseconds of frame.
Right, if you think about that, we want to synchronize with that
presentation because if we do something other than 60 + C, Ms of
frame, then we will essentially be offbeat with the monitor.
So if you imagine the monitor has kind of a timeline down here as
well.
If it was updating at a different rate than we were, let's say a
little bit less like this.
Right, of course, and if I can get that out of my head, there we go.
Basically, what will happen is eventually we'll miss a frame.
So right here, it won't matter here.
It will display.
It will display this Frame here.
It will display this Frame, but here it will display the same frame,
again.
The monitor will and will have to wait.
A much longer time than the user has used to been seeing.
It's used to seeing this interval.
Now.
It's going to see this interval and we're going to see.
We feel like we skipped a frame to the user.
So we want the monitors refresh rate and our refresh rate to be the
same.
Right?
We want to update roughly the same frequency.
So we're consistent so that every time the monitor goes to get a new
frame.
We give it a new frame.
That's the goal so we can do that on either the monitors actual
refresh rate.
Like let's say it's 90.
She hurts or 120 hertz monitor.
We can do that actually hundred twenty Hertz, or we can do it as some
subdivision of that.
So let's say we're up in our game at 60 frames a second.
And the monitor is 120 frames a second 120.
Hertz, 60.
Hertz Hertz is just cycles per second.
Well, as long as we're a multiple of 2 or something, an even multiple
three, whatever away from that, then we know that we're never going to
hit that beat frequency problem, where we're going to have problems of
skipping a frame.
As far as the monitors concerned and having the user.
See
Apparent change in animation speed.
I'm sorry.
I made, I made some homemade almond milk today and I didn't do a very
good job.
It's kind of rough.
And it kind of scratches your throat.
A little bit.
I don't know how to fix that.
Exactly.
I got to think about it.
I'm still new at making almond milk.
So yeah, what you gonna do?
It's not the store bought brand.
So all right.
Basically what I wanted to say about that is that there's a lot of
talk now about variable refresh rate monitors and basically what those
are monitors that can update at Whatever frequency you want for the
most part.
So basically what happens is whenever
A frame is done.
You just say display the frame, right?
And so you might say, well, why do we care about any of this isn't
isn't the future going to just be, you take, as long as you need to
display the frame and then you display it.
Isn't that fine?
And I don't understand the attraction of that to me that just sounds.
Absolutely awful.
I do not understand why anyone would ever want such a monitor at all.
And the reason that I say that is because I feel like it always forces
you to be completely wrong with how you displayed your animation and
The reason I say that is because imagine how the computation cycle
goes on one of these variable frame rate monitors.
Well, I come down here.
Right?
And I'm basically saying that I'm going to use a variable frame rate.
So it looks something like this, you know, who knows what it looks
like.
Let's say it looks like that, right?
So we've got something here.
Let's say this is going to be, you know, something like 30
milliseconds.
This is going to be something like 16.
This was like 20, right?
And this was back to 30 again.
We have a completely variable thing here.
So what happens, we know that 30 milliseconds has elapsed.
These are milliseconds here.
We know that 30 milliseconds, has elapsed between here and here,
right?
Something was on the screen here.
We don't know what it was, what we're saying.
This is some point in time.
So as with the previous frame, who knows what happened.
So let's talk about starting here.
Well, we know that the world updated 30 milliseconds between
Here, right.
We know that 30ml sense of Time Has Gone by.
So we need to tell the physics engine for whatever frame is that we're
going to display right here.
We would want to tell it 30 milliseconds because there is a state of
the world here, right?
This is World State 0.
This is World zero, and now we need to display a world State one,
right?
We want to render what the world looks like 30 milliseconds into the
future.
Okay, but there's a problem.
We don't actually know.
No this value yet because we have a variable frame rate monitor and
we're going to flip whenever we're done.
We have no idea what the 30 milliseconds is.
And most of this time is usually rendering, like this is rendering
right here, right?
So, the physics happen somewhere in here.
It's got to know right away before we even have any idea how long the
framerate is.
It's got to know how much to update the World by, how does it know to
pick 30 milliseconds?
Well, it doesn't so it probably looks at the previous frame for a
guess.
Well, if it looks at the previous frame, it's always going to be
wrong.
It's going.
Get 30 milliseconds here, but surprise, this took 16 milliseconds.
So, now you've got a world that appears to be moving twice as fast.
Then we go here, we look in it.
So it's actually turns out to be 20, but we thought it was going to be
16.
So this is actually a world that appears to be moving slightly slower,
blah, blah, blah, right, so I do not understand, I don't, I do not get
it.
People who believe in this technology.
Please feel free to write in and tell me what the attraction is
because I do not see it at all as far.
As I'm concerned you need to know what you expect your frame rate to
be in the future and you need to guarantee that you're going to hit
that framerate in order to get a smooth believable.
Looking non hiccup.
Be sort of Animation unless you just don't care, you know, and so this
I think is very important.
So what I would say is variable update monitors might be useful if
your frame rate if you can guarantee your frame rate, but you happen
to know, it's always 45 milliseconds.
Let's say of course, that would be pretty bad.
So, let's
It's something like 20, you know, it's always 20 milliseconds.
Well, that's fine.
Then as long as you're fixing that rate but really a variable refresh
rate monitor doesn't actually help you in during the course of your
game.
What you all you really can use is something that's essentially a
fixed rate monitor where you can set the rate.
And so that that I think is kind of mostly all I wanted to convey
about that.
I don't really understand the attraction of those things, much at all.
And I think if anything, they're only good.
Good because they allow games to run it.
Other frame other fixed frame rates that aren't 30-60-90.
Basically, maybe you can get, you know, you can use 70 or something,
and you maybe you couldn't do that before in any realistic way.
So I don't know.
Just something to think about, want to get that out there.
So maybe I'm maybe I'm thinking about the wrong way, but I, that
that's always been my problem with that whole concept.
So for me, whenever I do a game Loop and looking at timing stuff.
I always want to have a Target frame rate and we try very hard to hit
that frame rate.
And if for some reason we're not hitting that framerate, we pick a new
lower frame rate and we're always trying to stay fixed at whatever
that framerate is.
So if we're trying to run at 60 and we can't let 60 we drop down to 30
or something like that.
And again, maybe that's where, you know, these variable friends could
come in.
They allow us to change our fixed frame rate, but I never want the
frame rate to be variable.
I never ever ever want that because there's no way to actually make
that work properly.
Your physics is
Is always wrong if you do that.
So when I want to do is I want to make a frame Loop that basically
obeys this sort of thing where it's going to fee.
It's going to have an opinion about the frame rate.
It can hit, right?
So it knows how many milliseconds that is, will call that the target
milliseconds.
So we know what our Target.
Ms is, right?
The target Ms.
Comes in to physics, updates the world, right?
So we got our update here.
It's the target Ms.
Drives our update.
We do our render, and then we do our page flip of that render, right?
As a close to the boundary of the target milliseconds as we can write,
then we do the same thing over again for the next thing.
And now this may be pipelined.
So remember this may go off to a GPU or something, which actually
delays everything by a frame, while it chews, through it, or whatever.
That's fine.
As long as we are, always pushing it at a synchronous thing and we set
it to synchronize say, with the with the, with the
Blank or whatever, that the monitor refresh will still be just fine.
As long as we always know that we're updating with a particular Target
in mind and that Target matches our flip rate.
And that is what we're trying to do.
Now, for the audio.
We have a slight other problem here.
The problem with the audio is ideally what we'd like to do is feed
just exactly the amount of audio that we need every frame.
But if we do that, we do run the risk of if we miss like let's say
Say we missed a for our 30 millisecond time, right?
So we actually missed and we're going to have a frame lag.
Well our audio would skip here.
So we have two choices because you know, we basically need to make
sure the audio is always there.
On time.
We have two choices, always get the audio there on time.
Meaning.
Our frame rate is a hard constraint and we've basically written the
game to never miss framerate.
The other one is always feed the audio somewhat further ahead.
And there's two methods of doing this one method is just too, like to
be a frame of lag off, right?
Or something or half a frame of lag off, right, in order to handle a
whole frame, miss.
You kind of got to be a whole frame of audio ahead.
Right?
So that would incur 16 milliseconds or 30 milliseconds, depending on
the frame rate.
This is at 60 hertz.
And this is at 30 Hertz.
I should probably start saying 17, because it's really, it's
86 repeating, right?
It's 1,000 divided by 60, but
What I mean, when I say 16, its code word for Seventeen, sixteen and a
half, whatever, you know what I'm saying?
Anyway, basically what happens here is I'm introducing audio latency,
so I could try to reduce that, audio latency by doing one of two
things.
One thing I can do is always feed two frames of audio, but when I do
hit my target, when I do find that I wake up and I've got plenty of
time to update the audio, so I'm here and I go.
Okay.
I got plenty time to update the audio up.
Update it as overwrite the old stuff that I wrote.
Right?
So basically always always give it an extra frame, but don't use that
extra frame.
If we have time.
We'll just Splat a new one, right?
That's one way of doing it.
Another way of doing it is like I said to just always actually write
one whole frame ahead and a final way of doing it would be to have
like a thread or something that sitting there waiting.
And it looks to see if we've updated
Did by, like right here.
And if we haven't it emergency flushes another frame of audio, right?
So, it's kind of like a guard, right?
So we got, we got a couple options.
We've basically got one always hit.
You know, we've got always hit the frame rate.
We've got overwrite the frame, overwrite the next frame.
We've got a frame of lag.
And we've got a guard thread.
And there maybe even other methods.
Those are just the ones that I happen to know about and have ever seen
used or use myself.
So I'm not 100% certain that I can honestly argue directly for any one
of these in particular.
It's kind of hard to say.
I think the one that I would rather go with because it's simpler and
enforces, sort of a little bit of discipline would just be going with
option.
1 Option, 1 is the easiest option is to always hit your framerate,
right?
And one of the things that's interesting about that that I like is I
like the mentality of saying
This game has to hit its frame rate instead of just allowing it, like
oh it kind of got slow sometimes when we don't want to optimize the
when the explosion happens or whatever and it gets slow.
So just let it get slow there and will compensate by having the frame
rate looks crappy, but the audio doesn't skip.
So we're happy, right?
I don't love that.
I feel like if we write a game and the user is being reasonable.
So they're playing our game and not running like another game in the
background or something, where they deserve to hear some audio skips
if that's where they're going.
I would prefer kind of to say, we always said our frame rate.
So, you know, we target 30 Hertz.
Let's say, and we always get there.
And if we don't hit 30 Hertz, then that means we have to optimize
whatever it is.
It's making us not hit 30 Hertz.
So I'm tempted to go with this one first.
I think that might be which one I go with first, but I wanted to
mention these other ones because maybe we'll have to switch to them.
If we find that we run satisfied with what I'm talking about here.
Or
You may choose when you're implementing this basically, to, to go with
a different option because you care about different things, because
many things in programming.
There's not a right answer.
They're simply a question of your priorities and those priorities will
lead you to, to make a certain decision or a different decision.
And it you can't really say that the decision was wrong or right, you
could only say if it was wrong or right based with respect to some
priority system.
Oh, so, there you go.
Hopefully, that makes some sense.
So, we need to do a couple things that were not doing right now.
In order to make this happen.
The first thing that we're going to have to do is we have to figure
out some way of knowing or at least getting some idea of what the
monitor refresh rate, even is because we want to run at that refresh
rate.
And so we kind of have to go ahead and take a look at at ways to
figure out what the refresh rate is of the monitor that were actually
using now to be
Honest, I haven't done this in a long time, and I did write down some
notes about how I used to do it, but it's going to be a little dicey.
And the reason for that is I don't really know all the stuff that
happens essentially, with sort of with multiple monitor scenarios.
So, if you take a look, basically, here's the, here's the thing that I
was thinking about can actually see get monitor refresh rate.
Let's just take a look here.
Where is our msdn msdn?
Here?
It is.
Let's take a look here.
I'm pretty sure that some of these are just not actually well.
Okay, this this might work.
So this might actually work because it does take the HDC.
So we'd be able to pass our Windows device context handle.
And let's see if this is going to be something that we think is a
reliable value.
I don't actually know if it is or not, but we can sort of see.
So here we go.
The current vertical, refresh rate of the device in cycles per
And so basically this, yeah, a vertical refresh rate value of 0 or 1
represents the display Hardware as default refresh rate.
So that's not really useful.
Right?
That's not going to tell us.
We actually need it to say something like 60 or something like that.
That's if it's if it's just going to tell us if it's just going to
tell us something nonsense.
He like that that's not going to help us so we can enumerate.
We can also enumerate the monitors.
Try to find it from there.
I'm not entirely sure.
What the best way to do it is
Day, is this is this is a good question, and I'm not super prepared to
to answer it.
So.
Yeah, yeah, I don't know.
I don't usually trust the stack Overflow answers.
I found them to be wrong a lot of time.
So I don't tend to look at these very often and this doesn't look
particularly convincing here either.
So I don't know.
I'm gonna go ahead and say that I'm just going to do.
I'm just going to go with the numbing the monitor.
This is the kind of thing that I do nowadays and I haven't really
played around with refresh rates too much.
But I just want to kind of.
I feel like this might be the most useful way to go because I think
this will probably give us a way to get it.
So I'm going to take a look at this.
Basically, anytime display monitors is the thing that allows us to see
basically, all of the things in the system that are monitors, that can
be explained graphics.
And I believe we can do a pretty easy way to actually get the one that
we're on as well.
So, let me take a look at this, then.
We call get monitor, we can call, get monitor info on those, and I
believe that sort of thing will be able to allow us to ask for stuff
about the refresh rate.
I'm not actually sure that that's actually true, but I think it might
be.
So let's take a look here, monitor info.
Yeah, we can see still not still not the case.
Let's see, get refresh rate of H monitor because I really like to be
able to do it from here if possible, because I just don't, I just
don't accept.
We trust the other thing.
Yeah, so you can, I don't know.
I'm sorry.
I'm having in hauling so much here.
I just a lot of times these things are pretty crazy.
So, basically, excuse me.
It looks like the, this device mode structure here would actually tell
us what it is.
We want to know.
So, let's just see if we can get one of those relatively easily from
from the Monitor and whether that gives us back.
I'll just test it, whether it gives us back.
At the actual information that we want.
It looks like it probably would.
So let's take a look here.
This height display frequency, right?
So is that Define?
Let's see what msdn says again, msdn can definitely be wrong, but it's
usually my first go-to.
I trust it more than stackoverflow anyway, so, let's take a look here,
frequency.
What that basically says is this value is also known by blah blah.
When you call this, the summe return with
What is with this zero and one thing?
Well, alright, I guess, I'm not sure what way I can really
definitively say what the monitor refresh time.
Actually, is.
It does not seem to be something that's worth coming.
So, I don't know.
That's, that's kind of, that's kind of disappointing to me normally.
So I mean, just to be clear.
The reason that this doesn't normally come up, is normally what
happens in opengl and direct3d is you set them into a mode.
Where they flip on the monitor refresh.
Anyway, so when you do that, all you have to do to figure out what
your refresh rate is, is time.
How long it takes to flip in one of those two things and then you
roughly know what the graphics card is doing.
That's pretty straightforward, and not that difficult.
But in this case, if we actually want to know because we're doing the
flip, we're doing the blind ourselves.
So we don't really have that freedom.
The way you would use to do, it is with direct draw, but direct draw
is kind of old and deprecated.
I don't know.
We
Try to do it director, aw, get vertical refresh.
This is the way that I used to do it in the old days.
We could we could try to do it.
I don't actually know whether that will be sort of whether that will
actually be accurate though.
When we ask for a particular monitors, vertical refresh.
So, let's see what it actually says here.
I don't know what this is.
This is some crazy stuff here.
Let's see anything.
Particularly interesting here.
No, this.
This looks totally that.
Looks totally off the rails.
This is the msdn page but it's for the flip call.
So I don't actually know if that's something particularly useful and
it's Windows mobile.
So that's not going to do it.
Yeah, I don't know.
This may be after something we'll have to save for tomorrow and we'll
just have to put in the value.
I'll go look at my old code that uses direct draw and we can try it
unless there's some better way to do it that we can find because we
can't really if we can't rely on, one of these things to not give us
back.
R1, I'm not sure what we can really do because if you look at like I
don't know if we look at this code, it doesn't look, particularly.
It doesn't look particularly useful.
There's really nothing you can do there.
The default.
Refresh rate is not something that that seems to be defined anywhere.
So anyway, excuse me, we'll have to tackle that tomorrow, I guess and
I'll just I guess I'll do the direct.
I'll guess I'll do the direct 3D version.
I'm sorry, the director all version.
I don't know what.
Well, so that's not the command prompt.
We won't.
We have our own custom command prompt.
There we go.
Well, that's disappointing.
I was hoping that there would be an easy way to get it but it looks
like there isn't that's the that's the sad State sometimes of
operating systems something.
Like getting them on to refresh rate.
Should be just like one call.
You're like, here's though, the monitor I'm on, tell me what the
refresh rate is and it should guarantee to give you back the refresh
rate.
And I do not know how we get into situations, where that is.
Not the, the sort of the standard thing to happen.
But you know, what do you do?
That's
That's just life.
As a programmer in the platform layer.
It's one of the reasons will be very happy to get off the platform
layer next week.
So we don't have to deal with stuff like this.
Alright, so basically we're going to have to do is we're going to have
to assume that we make up a refresh rate.
And so for now we'll just call it will say that there's a refresh rate
up here, will say that this is a refresh or monitor refresh Kurtz and
that will be just 64 now, right?
So we'll just say it's 60 refreshes per second.
And we'll say to do, how do we reliably query this on Windows?
Because we don't know maybe directdraw is still the way to do it which
would be kind of scary because directdraw is deprecated.
So that would that would not be my preference.
But what do you do?
All right.
So then what we can do is from that we can compute some synthetic
values, right?
We know that from that, we can compute, how much time we
to go.
In seconds for every frame.
So basically, the seconds elapsed per frame, right?
Is going to be the MS, 1,000 milliseconds per frame /, that monitor
refresh hurt hurts, right?
That's going to give us how many seconds are elapsed every frame.
So, I guess the other thing we should say is we need we have a game
update hurts as well.
Right?
And I sort of was saying that we probably don't want it to be the
monitor refresh rate because
we're going to not probably hit 60 when we're doing software
rendering.
So maybe let's say this is 30 as well and basically will derive this
from this once we actually get to some place where we can get this
value.
So, you know for now we'll say it's that divided by 2 or something
like that.
So really the second laps per frame is actually going to be our games
update hurts because we'll probably be only flipping every other time.
So that's how much we want to actually have elapsed.
So the first thing we need to do is actually measure this which we
already
Put in the basis of and then we want to actually wait until we get to
the point where we're at.
This this time elapsed and then we can go ahead.
And sort of delay, if you will, our page flip to just the right time.
So that we get, you know, 60 frames a second, or when this case, 30
frames/second.
Whatever our game updates, Hertz is.
So, what we want to do is down here somewhere, right?
After we've done everything.
Remember, we have a thing.
We already kind of puts a thing in here, where we query, performance
counter.
So, we know how much time has elapsed, and we were printing that out
before we were printing that out right here.
So, we basically have a value
Which is the counter elapsed and we actually did the milliseconds per
frame thing here.
And so what we want to do here is change up what we're doing a little
bit.
What we want to do here is say how much time has actually elapsed so
far, right?
So seconds, elapsed for compute basically for work.
Let's say how much we actually had to do.
And we know what that value is.
That's this right here.
So we're going to go ahead and do that.
And that's just this particular thing.
We don't actually care about this.
The 32-bit - I'm sorry, the 64-bit nice of that because we've already
done the subtract.
So that's all good.
So once we do that, we basically have and we don't need the Thousand
anymore because that's that was to compute milliseconds.
So really all we need to do is divide the time that elapsed by the
frequency of that of our account of our clock of that Windows reported
for our clock.
And that will give us back how many seconds elapsed during the work
that we did for our frame right.
Now.
What's going to happen here is that's going to be different.
And the other value, the value that we basically computed up here,
which is how much s we want to elapse for frame.
So this is the second slept for frame Target and we could actually
call that Target s laps per frame or Target seconds per frame.
Something like that.
Right?
So we have a Target second per frame that we're going to see like
basically how much
Time we have left.
So assuming we're always trying to be under it, right.
So we're assuming that we essentially have, we almost want to have
sort of a while loop here.
Right?
We want to kind of say, while the seconds elapsed.
We could even think.
Yeah.
In fact, I might change it back to so far because we could just go
ahead and do, you know what?
Because we're going to put that up their mind.
I'm Gonna Save it that way.
That was good.
So I'm going to do seconds, elapsed for frame, right?
And we'll start that off by saying we're going to actually
Be doing this, this query performance counter.
We're going to be doing this actually inside a loop.
So we're going to take a look at the seconds left for work.
We're going to say that we're going to start with that and we're going
here and say if the seconds a lap for frame is less than what we
actually wanted.
So if it's less than the Target, right?
Then we're going to take some action to basically, make sure that we
are not going too fast.
So we're basically going to going to slow things down.
So the first thing we can do and this is just the CPU.
Melting version is, we can just do this.
This again, right?
We can just go ahead and and and full-on do this sort of thing.
Now, you can see that this is gonna start to get messy if I keep doing
something like this, where I keep, you know, I keep checking and
checking in checking.
So we're going to probably want to pull this out and utility function.
But for now, we should probably be fine.
So what we'll do is we'll just keep getting the end counter over and
over.
We'll look at the counter elapsed and then will basically do the
seconds.
Elapsed for frame computation will just do it inside this Loop, right?
We'll just keep on doing it and doing it and doing it.
And so what we should do, oops, don't want to find that again.
What we basically should do here.
You know, what I can even do.
I don't even need to do that.
I can just stick that right in there.
There we go and make that divide a little clearer.
There we go.
So basically what we can do is just keep on doing this and until we
get to the time when we actually get above the target seconds per
frame, right?
And then we can go ahead and do our flip.
So in theory, if we actually do that now, in fact we should actually
that should actually just be basically a locked Loop that forces us to
update at 60 frames a second.
Now we can we'll have to verify that that's actually true but let's
just go ahead and make that happen here.
Where are we?
There we go.
Let's see.
Why am I not?
Why am I not getting any input here?
That does not look reassuring?
I feel like we should be getting some input, but we are getting no
input whatsoever.
That doesn't sound good.
Something has gone horribly.
Horribly wrong.
I suspect that probably this while loop was busted.
Hold on one second.
Well, S 2 laps for frame is less than Target seconds per frame.
No, that's should be.
What did I do wrong?
It was off to a good start in the Stream today.
When the first thing I
Pin is already lousy, but you know, programming is like that some
days, some days.
You're on and some days you're off and on days when you're off, it
just means you got to do a lot more debugging and you know it when it
happens, but you know, what?
Can you do?
He's got a you just gotta you got a chin up, you know, and get through
it.
Anyway, let's let's go in here and step in the debugger.
Hopefully it'll be relatively obvious.
What?
I messed up there because we're not actually updating.
So I think what's happening is this while loop is is never actually
making this get big enough for what it should be.
So
Oh well.
That was easy.
It looks like we left a yeah, that's good.
That's stupid.
All right.
What I basically did there is I computed the target milliseconds per
frame instead of the target seconds per frame.
So that's that's pretty much the entirety of the bug.
Not, not particularly interesting to say the least.
So, okay, in theory, we should actually be going at somewhat more of a
consistent frame rate, but I don't actually know if that's true.
We should be going at 30 now, but I'm not sure if that's true, that,
that audience.
No, skipping like crazy, so I'll have to take a look at what's going
on there.
So let's take a look here at that while loop make sure that's actually
running properly.
Okay, so this is wrong as well.
So this end counter has to actually be done outside.
So let's let's go ahead and pull.
I don't know if you could see what was happening there.
But basically we need we need to update our last counter to be proper.
I mean, the fix is very simple.
It's this right here, but let's this code is now super messy.
So I'm going to go ahead and pull that out.
Let's see if that makes a little bit.
Okay.
Yeah, so that looks that looks more, correct.
All right, but this is still super ugly here.
So we got to pull this out.
So let's start by pulling out this the clocking stuff into something.
That's a little more understandable.
Right?
So let's basically say, first of all, I kind of want to go ahead and
say that the the query performance frequency, this thing right here.
I kind of want the query performance frequency to basically be
something that can be always access since we compute it once.
I want that to be just
Global variable.
That's just whatever the frequency is and we initialize that startup.
So what I would like to do at least is have this variable basically,
right?
I'd like this to be a global.
So I'd like that to be a global variable.
So the perfect count frequency is basically going to be this thing
here.
See that we had it at the four per count frequency.
So basically we just want a global variable that always lets us know
what that frequency is so that we clear it once and then we can use it
outside.
Side in a different in a different context.
And so then what we have is we basically have our rooms.
You mean.
We have our actual call that does our computation.
We want that to be something that's kind of nicely encapsulated.
So I'm just going to pull it out here and I'm basically going to have
a way of saying, snap a counter at various places and then take a
difference on them.
So basically, I want something here, which is basically, you know,
it's just an inline function, that's going to do, get seconds elapsed,
something like this, and it will take two different ones of these.
So, start and end, let's say like that.
So, take the start and end and then they'll do this computation
properly.
It'll know that basically, whatever the elapsed time is here, you
know, it'll do end dot quad, part -
Start dot quad part.
It'll do this, this reliably.
So, we know we don't have a typo or anything in it.
We can debug it once and make sure it's right.
Basically, we'll just do that seconds elapsed.
It'll do that computation and then return it.
So, there we go.
That
So that's fine.
And then we also will have one which our bait which is basically just
a way to get a clock value.
So went through to get get wall clock.
Basically, that will actually do this query performance counter and
just return that value directly.
So that way, at least we can see it's a little clearer.
What we're actually trying to do with it and we can go ahead and
return that.
There we go.
So, now we can replace our stuff with this and hopefully it will
Be good.
So perf can't frequencies there.
Let's go ahead and put this up with our Global's and we'll call that
Lobo.
Perfect count for currency.
So, perfect, count frequency and that should never change during the
Run of our program.
So we should be good to go.
Now, in here.
We need to replace our all of our stuff that we were doing for query
performance counter.
But we actually want to do here is say, okay, our last counter is
equal to
I went through to get wall clock, right?
Like that and we can leave our our dtsc's for now.
We're going to do something else with those later, but our dtsc is is
very prosperous Pacific.
So you can't really use that for timing.
If you're at you can't use that for timing that runs on the user's
machine.
You can only use Query performance counter for actually timing stuff
on the on the user's machine.
So our game code has to be driven off of create performance, counter
are dtsc's only for timing code for profiling.
Because how it behaves varies from CPU to CPU and all sorts of other
stuff.
So you don't want to ship a game that uses our dtsc for actual game
time.
All right.
So then we get down here.
We can say this is basically our work counter.
So our work counter win32, get wall clock, will get that there.
Then we have.
Those are so that was our cycles that can go up there till we deal
with it later.
So we have our work counter there and we want to know our seconds, the
elapsed are, let's just call this work seconds, elapsed like that.
Guess they went through to get seconds elapsed and we'll give that.
Between our work counter basically work.
Counter and our last counter.
So that's the the actual last kind of gets updated at the very end.
So
Think that's roughly right.
What I want to do.
Then I'm going to go through here.
And this is going to be our work seconds, the elapsed, right?
We're going to go through here and say we're going to update our check
counter basically.
And that's going to get the wall clock time here, wall clock that, and
then we're going to get the S laps wins here to get seconds elapsed.
And we're going to try to time in between the last counter and our
check counter, right?
And we can also just basically do this, right.
Kind of nice having functions encapsulate, our stuff is nice because
it just makes the code so much, read more readable, right?
So we can basically just sit here and keep going.
In fact, we could even be even more ridiculous if we really wanted to
and put that expression right here, but I don't think we need to go
that far.
That doesn't seem useful, so will not do that quite yet.
Anyway, I'm going to F0 out all these things for now because we're not
dealing with them at the moment.
Then at the end here at the very end.
We need to update our last counter.
So basically, what we can do is we can say
say that our encounter here, large integer and counter equals 1/2 to
get wall clock, which is what we wanted and then we can set the last
counter equal to that.
Now the this this guy here, I'm going to leave all these guys together
and stick them down at the very end.
This stuff needs to probably be cleaned up a little bit.
But yeah, let's just move all that down there.
Okay, so that should be about, right.
I think that looks about right now, of course, the problem is at the
moment.
We don't really have a good way to tell even whether what we're even
running at like, we have no actual way of knowing what our actual
frame rate even is.
And so, that's a little bit of a problem, to say the least, when you
actually look at it.
You know, it does it look consistent now, oh, you know, sure, right.
But how do you really know?
And so we kind of want to do is probably have some way of actually
trying to verify that and one thing we could do and I think
This is probably what we should do in maybe in the remaining time is
put a little counter that just goes up every frame that we can
actually time with, you know, like a stopwatch or something and verify
that in like a minutes worth of time that it is actually gone up by
the amount that we should think that it should right by, you know, 60
times our frame rate.
So 60 times, 30 or whatever it is, but maybe I don't know.
Maybe, we'll do that tomorrow.
We're getting kind of low on time here.
So let's just keep going with what I was talking about here.
So what we do want to do
We kind of want to stay here.
Even though this is while loop work will work just fine.
There's a couple other things we want to do here.
First of all, you need
What we do want to do is we want to actually verify that we didn't
miss a frame.
So in the if s allows what we'd like to do is put an else at the end
of this while, right, but you can't actually do that and see.
So, what we want to do here is say, okay, if the seconds elapsed for
frame was actually higher than the target.
Then we've got a problem, right?
Because if it's actually a little bit higher, that means we missed our
frame rate.
And so this is something we want to do here, says missed framerate,
you know, that's that and we could we could even do an assertion here.
But the problem is the assertion would lock up.
So what we'd really like to do is, is this this will be a thing that
will log and we'll be able to see that actually pretty soon.
I don't know if we'll do logging next week, but pretty soon.
We'll be able to start seeing some of these things that we wanted a
lot, but we don't have a system for yet.
So the other thing we want to do is this will basically just melt the
CPU if that makes sense.
Basically, even if the CPU did all the work that it needs to do for
the entire frame in a millisecond.
It's still going to sit here in this spinlock, doing a ton of work
constantly checking the performance counter, right?
It's just like wasting CPU time.
So what we'd rather do is we'd rather see if there's any time left
that we can actually use to just sleep.
Just tell the operating system to put the
Pewter rest or do other work that it has to do.
So, what we'd like to do is use this command from msdn sleep, which
basically choose me which basically just takes a number of
milliseconds and it waits it basically just wait for that number
milliseconds.
So what we would like to do here is basically say, let's do that sleep
for the MS, you know, sleep Ms.
Basically, right?
And so in here we're going to say that we have a sleep milliseconds
and the sleep.
Is going to be how many milliseconds we could afford to sleep, right?
We going to say.
All right, we'll take the target seconds per frame.
Okay, like that will take the seconds elapsed for frame will subtract
them.
Right?
Why did that not copy?
There we go.
S last per frame.
Will multiply that by 1,000.
Right?
Because this is in seconds and now we've got milliseconds and that's
how many milliseconds or left, right?
That's how many milliseconds are left to.
Wait.
What we want to do now is that's going to be a fractional value
obviously.
Evening.
And so, we only want to, we basically want to truncate that if that
makes sense.
We want to sort of, you know, what, I forgot to.
I forgot this right here.
There we go.
We, we need to actually wait to display the frame.
This would actually have displayed the frame and then waited which is
not particularly useful.
So, what we want to do here.
Yeah.
Is we want to go ahead and see how many milliseconds we can sleep.
So to do that, we're going to go ahead and truncate this fractional
value.
We're truncate the fractional value out to a d word after we compute
it.
And so that will give us how much we could sleep.
And then we will sleep.
Now.
There is a huge problem, though, with doing this.
Unfortunately, which we probably won't see when we run it here.
But it's there.
You'll just have to take my word for it.
Oh, well, you can kind of?
Yeah, you can, you can
See it.
And it's it's something that it's hard to see when we don't actually
have something running and when you're not in certain circumstances
and whatever.
There's because there's a whole bunch of stuff that ties into this but
we'll get to those in a second.
The problem.
Is that basically, this sleep function in Windows?
Has a certain granularity with how long it can.
It can actually put your thread to sleep.
So, if it decides when you call it, that it's going to put your thread
to sleep.
Meaning your thread will no longer be executing.
It is going to wait for the next scheduler, granularity to wake you
up.
Now, what that means, for those of you unfamiliar with operating
systems is inside at every operating system.
There's some code called a scheduler, and a scheduler is what decides
when threads run?
Like, when different processes run, when the threads run.
It's basically the thing that makes your operating system preemptively
multitasked.
It's the thing that lets you run a bunch of different programs at once
and it dulls out the work, you do without the
If you time to each of these programs to allow them to do the work,
right?
But what happens is that scheduler basically has to be sort of a thing
that interrupts what's going on.
If you imagine you have one program running and you need to let the
CPU do some work on another program.
Then the Opry system, you imagine have to like interrupt, right?
It has to jump in and say, okay, stop the process.
Hold on that, you're doing like, emacs.
Let's say stop emacs.
Hold it.
I gotta go run the code for this timer overlay that Casey wrote right
or something.
Like
This if that makes sense.
So if you think about what happens there, however, frequently that
scheduler wakes up is the maximum is the minimum amount of time you
could sleep for, because if your thread goes to sleep, it's not going
to wake back up again, until the scheduler comes back on the CPU and
looks to see.
And goes.
Oh, he wanted to wake up in X.
Ms.
X.
Have elapsed.
So, I'll wake him up.
But if the scheduler only wakes up, so, let's say every 50
milliseconds, and you ask to
For two milliseconds.
Well, you're actually going to sleep for 15 milliseconds because the
scheduler ain't going to wake up every two milliseconds.
And look, she is name, so we can fix this.
It's not a perfect fix, but we can fix this.
We can fix it with something called time to get in Period.
Now what time begin period is it's a weird?
I don't even want to know how this ended up being the way to do this.
You can sort of see how, but oh my Lord, you would think there'd be
something called set scheduler granularity.
But know what actually happens is time begin.
Period is like an old multimedia system call for about for setting
when you would get, callback timers and what resolution they had to
be.
And of course, the Callback timers couldn't happen.
Open the timer granularity, unless the scheduler was.
Making up at that granularity.
So it ends up setting the schedule granularity in Windows and it sets
it to whatever this period is here, right?
So that period is in milliseconds, which means the scheduled
granularity, we can set all the way down to 1 millisecond, which is
fine because we're only going to sleep at a millisecond granularity.
Anyway, I don't know if that makes sense, but hopefully it makes
sense.
I don't actually remember, to be honest with these been a long time.
I don't actually remember how you make this call.
It escapes me at the moment, but we'll go ahead and put it in here and
she's me.
So basically you call time again, period, and you pass it.
The MS granularity that you want to use me.
So, basically desired scheduler milliseconds, that is one.
So we can just do people reading this code knows what's going on.
Note Casey set the windows scheduler granularity.
To 1 millisecond.
So that our sleep.
Can be more granular.
So let's do that.
So there we go.
And now I just can't really think can't remember is whether you need
to actually well, you know what, you know what, I think.
Yeah, you know what I think.
I think there is one of the things that we want to do.
I'm just it's the old, the memory is kind of, you know, jogs.
I don't actually remember.
Let's see if there is.
I felt like there was a way we could figure out to verify.
That was right.
Well, we can look at the H result at the very least.
So if this mm result thing, that comes back, if that returns time, no
are successful.
I like time or no can do.
That's interesting.
Someone had a sense of humor there.
So basically, if that does this, then, it's okay to sleep, or I should
say sleep, is, is granular.
Just true.
In fact, we could just do this.
You can just record this like that will 32.
Sleep is granular equals that, so,
There you can sort of see, I'm just based on recording whether this
worked.
So if it believed it could set it, then we'll then we'll set it.
Now, the thing that the reason that I wanted to record what it is is
because I don't want to introduce this sleep, if the operating system
isn't going to be able to do it.
So basically I want to do, if sleep is granular than allow the sleep.
Otherwise don't allow the sleep.
Does that make sense?
Now that was a like I said a multimedia function.
So in order to link with that, we have to link with the multimedia
Library, which is pretty trivial to do and is this on all windows?
So
So, that's not a risk.
It's not a linking risk, I believe it's when mmm, that lib.
Yeah, it is.
Of course.
Remember you can always determine that by going down here, but
sometimes I like to see if I still remember.
So, all right.
Now we have basically gotten that working.
Our sleep should be more.
Allure.
But we still have no idea.
Whether this is working right?
Or not.
Like we've got no idea and so we can't really make a conclusions yet,
but we're out of time for the day.
So this may be incredibly buggy.
We don't know, but at least we've gone through the theory of what
we're trying to do.
We've started to make ourselves try to Target lock to a frame rate.
So that's good.
And tomorrow, we should be able to go through and actually clean up
the audio side of things and do some testing to verify that we're
actually running at the frame rate.
We think we are.
Because all of this stuff is probably buggy before we test it.
So not tested yet.
Probably buggy.
Right?
So we will do that.
You know, what we could do as well.
We could go in here as a very simple test.
Not particularly great one, but we can go in here as well and turn
this back on.
This would give us a little bit of a sort of an idea if you will of
what's actually going on.
It would do our old print out.
We had so counter elapsed.
We would just need to go this here, counter elapsed milliseconds per
frame, like that.
So the milliseconds per frame is win32, get wall clock.
Sorry get seconds elapsed like that one thousand and then we would
just do and counter last counter like that.
So that would give us
Us.
At least a little bit of an idea what's going on in.
We don't actually need or do we.
That's Global that counter elapsed.
We don't actually have that unfortunate.
Okay, so let's get rid of the frame right here for now.
Well, that's easy for us to compute again.
Let's just go ahead and zero that out.
We'll do that in a second and buffer is redefinition.
We've already got a buffer, not surprising.
Let's see.
That was buffer.
Well, actually, yes.
I don't care what it's do FPS buffer and then we're done.
So I'm just turning this on as a last little thing we do in the fridge
so we could take a look.
Oh good.
It's telling us a warning about this.
Well, what do you want me to use?
I guess it's basically giving us a security warning here.
And that security warning is because you might have a buffer overrun,
which is fine, but this is debug code.
So I wish it wouldn't do that.
We could turn off that warning, but I believe there should be some
kind of a guarded printf.
You would think.
Oh, it's still thinks that's unsafe.
What would you like me to use underscore S?
I guess.
So, yeah.
Going to use this.
What do you want me to use?
Alright, well, hopefully that works.
Basically.
They try to increase security by doing these things and they often
fail in the end up.
Just annoying you.
But, you know, they were trying, at least they were trying to do some
security.
So we look like, we're pretty close.
We've got a
Is to go before we're actually really accurate but it looks like we're
sort of getting our thirty-three point three, three, three, three,
three, three, three, three, three.
We have some reasons why we won't basically the thing that we haven't
done yet is we don't include this this time information properly and
some other various things that we're not doing properly.
So there's definitely some other stuff that we want to kind of do to
try and make that a little more accurate, but at the moment, it looks
like we're pretty good.
So we're getting there.
So that's good with that.
We are now at the way.
We should be at the Q&A because we started three minutes late and it's
903 now.
So we should be right where the qh should be.
So let's go ahead and do some Q&A here.
I'm going to open up the twitch chat.
Please make sure to put seem your ettore in your question somewhere,
so I can see it.
And please keep the questions to stuff we've done on this dream or in
some previous dream because stuff about future stuff is stuff.
We will get to in the future.
So, alright, let's go ahead and see what we have for questions.
Let's see.
If we are locking.
The framerate won't that mean that this engine will slow down the
entire game.
If a person has a bad computer and cannot hit our frame rate.
Yeah, so we're not locking the frame rate.
That's kind of a, that's not really what we're trying to do here.
What we're trying to do is run at a fixed frame rate.
So what we will do as we go forward,
Is in this code, this right here, this target hurts.
We will update what?
We are trying.
What the framerate is that we're trying to hit dynamically so that the
user has a computer that can't even hit 30 frames per second.
For some reason.
We will we could drop down to 15 for example, and then the game will
still run at the right speed, but the frame rate will be very slow, we
could do that.
Now I would argue that we should probably just put up a big old box
that says, you got to buy a new computer because you shouldn't ever
run a game at 15 frames.
S basically unplayable.
But
But we can decide what we want to do at that point much later, down
the line, but we're not we're not saying the game has a fixed frame
rate.
We're saying that we're fixing the frame rate at any given time so
that we know when we're going to flip.
So that our animation is consistent, but we can always change what
that fixed frame rate is if we want to.
And then the game will always use whatever we tell it is the framerate
to do its World updating.
So we have the flexibility to run at 60 31:20, whatever we want to run
at based on.
Speed of the end users machine and the game will respond accordingly.
Even if you could grab the refresh rate of the monitor, how do you
synchronize with it?
Well, so for our prototype prototyping engine, we won't probably
bother synchronizing with it.
Direct three directdraw actually does have a thing that allows you to
wait for the vertical blank and we
Use that if we wanted to.
Again, depends, if you want to use direct draw, which nowadays is very
deprecated.
Unfortunately, I don't know why.
It would be nice if they'd maintained it, but basically for a
particular we probably won't sink with the monitor.
So that's fine because all that means is that will be like off one
frame.
Potentially all will get a real get some tearing like a line down the
middle as the as the frame is flipped.
But when we actually go to do the final platform layer will be
outputting through
the opengl or direct3d, and those have ability to set a flag.
That just says automatically sync.
Like, when you do a flip flip it with the monitor.
So we won't have to worry about that.
That will just be taken care of by the operating system.
When we push a frame down, it'll automatically sync to it.
So we don't actually have to do that ourselves for the, for the
shipping game.
Doesn't the sleep function go in the surrounding If instead of the
while loop, well, it can go either place.
I should think, right?
Because basically this should I mean one of the things we should do
obviously we could certainly put it.
Well.
Yeah, we could we could certainly put it here and you would assume
that that was, that was accurate.
But really, the thing that I didn't do and need to do here is make
sure that we don't bother ever climb the operating system to sleep
isn't.
Out.
So that's a bit of a mistake.
And so yeah what the person was asking is why don't we just do this
outside and they're totally right?
We can do it outside because there's no need to do it inside the while
loop because the second time through the while loop sleep milliseconds
is always going to be 0.
Presumably assuming we actually slept for the time that we thought we
were going to sleep.
So, I don't know.
You could put it out there.
You can put it in here.
It doesn't actually matter where you put it as long as you checked the
milliseconds to make sure that they're greater than 0.
So I don't know.
I feel like if it's inside the while loop, it catches some problems.
Like let's say, sleep doesn't sleep us for the time for some reason
because the operating system just thought it was going to just wake us
up writing, right away.
Again.
For some reason, then we just spin lock for no reason and maybe we
want to give the operating system the chance to sleep us again.
So I feel a little more comfortable.
Having it in here.
Although that said, it does do one extra computation, which maybe we
would argue is bad for the spinlock.
So I don't know.
It's really hard to say.
I guess we'll leave it out for now, but I could go either way on that
and and whatever you want to do in your version of this code.
You can make that judgment call.
Let's see.
Does win32 fill sound buffer?
Need to come after the vsync loop?
Yeah.
Well, so we need to and I'll put in to do just so you guys know who
are following along at home, who might be confused about that.
Where is okay.
So basically
Sound is wrong now because we haven't updated it to go with the new
frame Loop.
So I haven't touched down at all.
So sound is just wrong and I don't want to patch sound right now.
Like I don't want to to fix this or anything because that's
interesting.
I don't know why.
This is note should be.
Oh, I guess it's just saying stuff because that basically I don't want
to touch down at all because we're going to redo how
During the sound timing.
So I want to do that in line with with with the rest of it.
So don't think about sound at all.
We haven't looked at sound at all.
It's totally wrong and doesn't obey the diagram that I was drawing at
the beginning that I said that we wanted to do.
So tomorrow.
Our job is to make sound line up with that diagram.
Check dwm, get composition timing info on msdn.
If arrow is on well, I'd rather do something that that worked without
Arrow.
Because I'd like to work on Windows XP and the direct draw one does
work on on Windows XP.
So I probably won't use that.
But thank you for pointing that out.
Could you explain the potential advantages or detriments to handling
update and render on separate timers threads?
Is there ever a good reason for a programmer to update the game State
more frequently than they render it to the screen.
So, no, there isn't a good reason to update the game State more often
than they render it to the street to the screen.
However, there is a good reason, tightly related to that.
There is a good reason why you may need to subdivide some aspects of
the update into more granular updates than the rendering.
And so the example of that would be
Let's say that your physics time.
Step needs to be one-to-one.
1/20 of a second.
But your game frame rate is only 30 frames a second.
Well, then you kind of are in a situation where you're going to have
to run the physics update more frequently.
So you have to kind of run it on a subdivided time step.
So there are definitely ways that you could do that with separate
threads if you wanted to.
There's, there's a lot of different ways you can attach.
That problem.
But obviously the simplest one that doesn't involve threading or any
sort of stuff like that is just to run the physics in like a for I
Loop inside the game update, its face like we're going to do the
update for the game.
We need to update the physics four times for everyone update of the
game.
So we just call it four times with a quarter of the time step and
we're done.
So that definitely does happen whether or not you should multi-thread
that and then update the game at a different time.
I mean,
I don't like that kind of thing, but I wouldn't necessarily say that
it's wrong because you can sort of see Arguments for why you might
want to do that.
I mean, I don't know, I don't love it.
But but I would be hesitant to say that it was the wrong way to think.
Just I don't particularly love that.
So I think it adds a lot of complexity and I'm not sure you get a lot
of benefit for it.
Let's see.
If we are locking.
No, okay, already answered that.
How would you adjust your memory management strategy for devices with
limited memory.
We haven't done a memory management strategy yet.
So wait until we actually do our memory management and then that
should become clear.
I think.
What we miss frame rate due to the sleep because while you're
truncating to Ms.
You aren't accounting for the up to 1 millisecond granularity would
just removing one millisecond from the weight work.
Well, I don't think so because I mean basically this is going to give
us how many milliseconds to sleep and it's going to be fractional.
So this value is going to come back.
Like ten point three.
Milliseconds.
Let's say if we then truncate it, we get 10 milliseconds.
That gives us point three milliseconds of time that has to be spent
spin locking.
So I don't think we would miss the framerate at all there.
Now.
There is a separate problem, which is that we're not accounting for
the fact that if we
Actually, we're talking about doing this in sync with something.
We would want to account for how long this took, and wait for how much
- that.
But we're in, we're encapsulating all of the time because we're using
our encounter.
We're always counting for all the loop time, because we're subtracting
from last counter, which gets sent here.
So we're actually accounting for the time that it takes to flip as
well, but I don't know.
So I don't actually think we would need to do that.
But if the MS, if the Sleep MS.
Lee causes us to sometimes sleep, an extra Ms.
Then.
Yes, we want to subtract that.
Now, something we could do here just for our own benefit is assuming
that we went through here and did the target seconds per frame thing
and whatever we could assert basically that the first time when we
actually check the time here, we could assert that it that it is like
this, right?
It could assert that test s laps for frame is
Than 0, right?
Or sorry is is is less than Target s, right?
So to sort that we didn't sleep too long.
We could do that and we can see what happens there.
Just to see if we ever Miss and we don't, which is what I would
expect, right?
So basically, we can see what I'm doing.
There is I'm just saying, Hey look.
After you do the Sleep, let's verify that we didn't, we didn't like
sleep past the frame time.
So we didn't do the thing that you were worried about it doing and so,
I don't think it's going to do that from the readout here.
You do.
Notice that this is just
Not right.
Like this should be really close to thirty three point three, three,
and it's not.
So we still have bugs.
So I don't want to say that we're not buggy, but I just, I just don't
think that thing you're talking about is actually happening, or if it
is happening.
It's happening a different way because we should be, we are starting
this year and we now can see that.
That that's that's not actually the case, right?
Hopefully that's clear.
What's happening?
There.
Carl and oh, Bloom says, shouldn't tear.
If we were in windowed mode in Windows, at least, unless people
disabled.
Wdm are.
Oh, yeah.
I think I assume that Arrow does all of its compositing on a flip.
So we shouldn't see tearing, but if you are on Windows XP, you might,
I don't know.
I am not sure depends on the operating system and what you have.
Can you fix the physics animation frame rate without fixing the
graphics frame rate?
So if you miss a frame, just run the physics more than once before
rendering the next frame know that that doesn't help you.
You still showed the wrong thing, right?
We don't have to run the physics multiple times because our physics is
going to allow large time steps, probably.
So we'll always have the physics be able to run the right amount of
time to catch up to where it thinks it should be.
But just to sort of illustrate the problem here.
Based on what you were sort of saying.
So I'm going to go ahead and clear this out.
Fantastic.
Of course, that's exactly what I want to do is make it tiny for some
reason.
I do not understand why I did that but that's fine.
Let's go ahead and zoom back in there.
Wait.
Oh now the zoom is to what what?
This is not look like a good program.
No, smooth draw.
No.
Okay, anyway, so basically what I was trying to say to that question
is, let's say we're here and we've computed, you know, so we're on our
fixed frame rate.
So we advance the world 16 milliseconds, right?
We advance the world, we plus 16 milliseconds and we That was supposed
to show up here, but we missed it because we took too long and we
ended up here.
So it was basically a plus 16 millisecond update and we end up
With a 30 millisecond interval, right?
What I'm trying to illustrate here is this is wrong.
No matter what.
Now, it's just you showed a wrong frame.
This Frame should have been at plus 33 milliseconds in physics time,
but it was actually at plus 16 milliseconds and physics time.
So it's just wrong, wrong, wrong wrong.
It's all wrong.
It is all wrong.
So what a lot of people do is exactly what you're saying and it's
totally wrong.
What they do is they then go okay I missed that.
So what I'll do is it took 33
Sounds.
So I'll make this Frame.
Add 33.
The time.
But now this Frame might flip in 16.
So now what you've done is you've like wronged yourself twice.
This is 2x wrong, right?
So this is always wrong and no, don't like know much like Smooth draw
is.
No, don't do it.
That way.
What you need to do is try to figure out how much time you think this
Frame will take to draw.
And that is how much you need to update your physics by never use the
last frames time.
I'm unless you then decide that that is exactly how long you're going
to gate this Frame Time by and you think you can hit it like the
previous frames time doesn't tell you anything about this frames time
because you don't know what happened on this Frame.
It could have been that something unusual happened on this Frame, that
isn't going to happen on this Frame.
And so they're not going to be similar times.
So you need to be aware of all this stuff and make good decisions,
instead of just mindlessly, forwarding that last frame time for this
Frame time, because that's just totally wrong, a lot of games do it,
and it's totally wrong.
It's never correct.
Why are we handling sound and video differently?
I'm afraid.
I'm not sure what that means.
If you could tell me what you mean by that.
I will try to answer that question.
I suspect it's probably a good question, but I'm just not sure exactly
what it means.
Let's see.
Bring Cruiser check if Deidre works on Windows 8.
I have problems with old games that use it.
Well, yeah, I mean, we're not actually going to use D draw just to be
clear.
We would literally just use the D draw, call that gets the monitor
refresh rate, and then we test to see if that was reliable.
We're not actually to use, direct draw to draw.
Yeah, cuz I don't think that's very supported.
It should be.
I wish they had done it.
Wouldn't you want to fill the screen buffer before you hit the frame
flip points that the monitor could grab the correct data when it
refreshes.
Well, yes, but, you have to remember, we don't know when the monitor
is refreshing.
So all we're doing here is we're just creating a loop that will keep
our game running at 30 frames a second.
So that all of our timing decisions will be correct later when we do a
win32 layer that outputs through one of the modern graphic apis, like
opengl and direct3d, then that we will
A different strategy of doing exactly what you're saying, which is
pushing the frame down and then waiting and letting the flip happen at
the right time, but we don't even know when the flip is happening
here.
So we can't actually do anything about that.
There's just, no way.
So what we'd rather do is wait the right amount of time here before we
flip.
So that we know that our flips are always happening.
Because remember, this is variable time up here.
The game may take variable time to update and this will take a
constant amount of time roughly or should so we want to do.
Is wait to make sure we're up at the 33 millisecond time?
Then do the flip right there.
Isn't d-word an integer.
Yes, but why sorry, it's an unsigned 32-bit integer, but I don't
understand the question.
It is, it is.
But if you could, if you could tell me why you were asking that, I may
be able to clarify more if that makes sense.
Sorry.
Go off topic, but will the art and Music Creation?
Be live-streamed.
No, those are done by other people.
So that's a separate thing.
What do you think about having a fixed physics time unconnected to the
drawn frame Time by interpreting positions of objects based on their
time differences?
The answer is, I don't really know what I think about it because I've
never done it that way.
There are some attractive features of it, which is that?
It kind of lets you have a more consistent gameplay experience.
Potentially, if it's done, right?
Because it would allow you to make sure that the physics plays the
same in some sense on all platforms, whether it's a 50 hertz, 60 hertz
display, something like that, but
I feel like you're doing a lot of extra weird stuff there that may
actually end up giving you a worse experience because the user is
putting in, put in at a time.
That actually is before the time.
That is the latest thing, the physics or Eddie knows to be true.
So, the user actually now has input lag, that they wouldn't have had
before an input.
Lag is not good for gameplay experience.
So I really don't know.
I'd be torn, I don't think it's a great idea.
But maybe if you did it, right?
It is.
So I don't know.
I can't speak to it really in any other than a gut reaction because
I've never implemented the game that way myself.
Anytime you compute World update, shouldn't that just set something
that says if we get there early wait until it's ready.
Doesn't that also handle the new Dynamic vsync stuff.
I always wait if you beat your time, but if you miss you get to update
right when you're done without tearing.
Yeah, I mean, that is, that is in some sense, a quote-unquote benefit
of the variable sink stuff, but the point is never miss.
Like, you should never ever ever miss your frame rate or it's
To be a bad experience.
Like, unless you only missed your frame rate by like a tiny, tiny
fraction.
In which case, that maybe the user couldn't perceive, and maybe that's
a good thing about those variable.
V6 is like, hey, I missed it by just a tiny, tiny amount and flip then
that's fine.
But you kind of need to make sure you never miss by anything other
than the tiniest fraction even in that case.
And so if you can only ever Miss by the tiniest fraction, you should
just not miss it.
All like I mean, it's not that different saying I have to hit 17
milliseconds versus
in point six, six, six, six, six milliseconds, so I don't really see
there being that much of a difference between those two things, but
you know,
It is what it is.
Certainly it's not like bad that they're doing the variables think
thing.
It's always better to have a variable Sigma honor because there's more
you could do with it.
Right?
It can only ever help.
It was not a hurt unless they broke something when they started doing
that, right?
So it is always better to have a variable sink monitor.
It's just like,
I just don't know if it's worth the cost or whatever that they mean it
eventually.
She brilliant.
Presumably, just be free to kind of have that logic in there or
something and then we just always want it.
But it's like
Do I really see much of a benefit to it?
No, it's like a super, super minor incremental thing.
Like it's not, it's not a big deal.
I feel like.
So that's that's all I was trying to say about that.
I'm not trying to like pesum eyes, those monitors and time with God
their crap.
I think they are better than what we have.
They're just not much better.
Let's see.
I think that might be all might be it.
That might be it.
Are we done with the Q&A?
Are we is that it for Q and A.
I think we maybe don't the Q&A five minutes early.
That is good stuff.
That is very good stuff.
All right.
Well, I mean, I will wait for another minute to see if there's any
last questions that come in to use up our remaining now four minutes,
but if not, I think we have we have ended the stream a little bit
early.
Even though we started late, we made good time today.
Although I really wished I could have finished up sound today as well.
But you know what, we'll do it tomorrow.
So that'll be fine.
So that will be fine.
All right.
Looks like there's no questions coming in there.
It looks looks good.
All right.
Well, oh, nope.
Oh, well, there was a, there was a bunch of things that just came in
there.
The minute earlier.
I watch one of Chandler Karis talks where he describes relationship
between data structures and algorithms in the context of C++
performance.
He mentioned that you could lose compiler observations for an object
by bringing its address into it.
Its identity.
Could you shed some light on exactly what this means I'd have.
Go re-watch it.
I'm not sure what you mean by the phrase bringing its address into its
identity, but I could go watch that we could talk about on a future
stream.
So that's good.
Is it worth talking about timing resolution in kernel or two deep?
Well, I mean, I think we can't really talk about the timing resolution
in the colonel largely because we don't know, like the windows kernel
is closed source, as far as I know.
I've never seen it.
So anything that I said that was talking about the windows kernel,
would kind of just be talking.
You know, hypothetically and going off of like what people post in
msdn blog posts or something.
So maybe there's a good lecture out there.
There might be a good lecture out there by Windows kernel.
Guy who talks about the timing and we could go by that.
But honestly, like I don't really know much about the windows kernel
timing.
I don't know what they do in there.
I know that time to get period changes.
The kernel timing, but I don't actually know much more.
Much more than that.
Pretty sure Chandler was suggesting passing by value because the
compiler had a lot of problems optimizing through corners.
Yes, that is true.
But that really only helps with inlining.
I think he was talking about, inlining the optimizer, you could
actually make your code slower by passing, things by value.
If it can't in line them because it would have to actually do the
copy.
So pay.
So you have to kind of know, you kind of got to actually look at what
the compiler is doing.
You can't just go always pass by value, always pass by pointer or
Are you kind of have to say, let me see this code?
Why is it slow?
And let me see if I can make it faster.
By changing, the way certain things are passed to it that.
So as a good rule of thumb, super small things, always should be
passed by value, obviously because it's easy to do so, and it's like,
if they're smaller than 8 bytes then they're smaller than a pointer.
Anyway, so you should always be passing, 8, B things by value, you
would think, because passing the pointer to them takes as much space
as passing them.
So, you're only incurring a speed hit, but things are
Only bigger than a pointer 64, byte things.
Let's say dirty to bite things at that point.
You may be getting into the territory where you have to actually know
that.
The compiler really can optimize it before you actually get a win.
So so be careful, I would say about that.
That is what I would say.
All right, I think we are done with questions for the day.
Thank you so much for joining me, and I hope you also enjoyed John
stream earlier today.
I know I did, if you would like for them to use me to follow along at
home with the source code, and the graphics assets.
Once we start working with Graphics, which will probably be next week.
I think you can pre-order the game on handmade here at the org and
you'll get a link that allows you to download the source code every
night.
You can go there as often as you want and download the latest source
code.
That is really easy to do and it has a source code for all the days,
so you can go jump back to any day and follow it that way.
If you'd like to talk about handmade hero, there is this news and
forums link here, which is pretty cool.
You can go to the episode guide, which has a bunch of like, annotated
references for past episodes.
You can go to the code discussion page, which has a bunch of stuff
that people are talking about and I answer questions on there as well.
So if you have questions, that's a great place to post them, all sorts
of stuff like that.
There's also if you click on the ham you hear a central thing the
Schedule, for the week is always up there.
So that you know what the hours are going to be just a bunch of good
stuff.
So that's also a good place.
If you want more, handmade hero information, so thank you.
Everyone for joining us.
I will be back here again at 8 p.m.
Pacific Standard time tomorrow, when hopefully, we will finish up our
Loop and then we can do a little fun stuff on Friday.
Have a little fun thing plan we can do on Friday, which I don't know
how many people can make it to the 11:00 a.m.
Stream.
I know it's an Austrian.
We got a little fun thing we can do on Friday, if we get through our
If we can get through the sound stuff tomorrow, so hopefully we will.
Thank you everyone for joining us.
I will go update the source code and the videos, and I will see you
here tomorrow.