Okay, hello everyone, and welcome to handmade hero.
The show Rico to complete game live on Twitch know, libraries.
No engines.
It's just us.
And our little typing fingers.
We have come to the point in the code where it's time to do a sound
mixer.
And as I explained yesterday, in excruciating detail, sound is kind of
a weird beast, but most of the things that we want to do in terms of
mixing sound for games are actually fairly simple and straightforward
and so, this should not be terribly.
Challenging endeavor.
So what I think we will do today is Right a very basic sound mixer to
start with and just get that working properly and work out what we
would like the interface to that, sound mixer to be and then what we
will do, probably next week is maybe drop it down into Cindy and make
a few concessions to how it works.
So that we can make sure that we operate properly wide.
We don't really have to go nuts, optimizing it or anything like this,
but just wanted to kind of do a little work there.
Just we can see if there's any conceits we have to make in the API to
make sure.
That, that sort of stuff works smoothly.
So we're going to be coding today, a bunch of code.
So, if you would like to follow along at home, it is day 140, make
sure you unpack day, 139 source, code out of the zip.
If you preorder the game on handmade hero and downloaded that source
file, you want, you want that code to start with?
Because that is what I am starting with today.
Okay?
So if you remember where we left off, we had loaded that yesterday was
just a day where I explained everything.
But the day before that
we had loaded sound files, we loaded wav files, and we have it so that
we can play back any one of them that we chose, I left it in here,
where it's playing back, you know, a like what was I going to say?
We left it playing back, am a piano sample and one of the things that
we have set up right now which, you know, maybe isn't a good idea.
But the way that we had our platform code set up is if we miss our
frame rate, we get tearing in the audio.
So for example,
Can you hear that little like skipping, right?
Whereas if you you know, if we're running that's in debug mode so we
don't make our frame rate.
If we're running an optimized, we don't get that right.
It's smooth.
And again, that's just because we don't actually try to do anything to
prevent that sort of stuff from happening.
We assume we always said our frame rate and we're only outputting it
as many audio samples as would be necessary to cover that Gap, right?
So going from there,
let's take, let's take a minute to think about what we're doing here.
What we wanted, what we want to do and you can already see that.
We've like I said, got one in here where we've got our game output
sound here.
What we want to do is we want to take this little Loop here, which is
all it's doing.
Is copying looped.
The sound that we loaded the sound samples.
We loaded is copping those into our sample out area here.
And what we want to do is take this and convert this to something that
can play an arbitrary number of sounds at an arbitrary arbitrary
times, and have it all getting mixed down in some kind of satisfying
way, right?
So that we can have as many Sounds playing as we want and not have to
worry about it, right?
So that's our goal.
And in order to do that, right, the way we have it set up right now.
Actually you can see is we have a separate call for get some samples.
And the reason that we have a separate call for that is because we
thought we, may want to call it sort of separately from the way the
rest of the stuff in the game state was working.
So, I don't know if we want to make this something that can be called
on separate threads or not, I'm not sure about that but in order to in
order to do that there were a couple things that we might want to
think about in terms of locking that sort of stuff so rather than go
down that route.
First I'm first going to write it just assuming.
That whenever we produce the sound samples for the game, that is
synchronous with the rest of the game.
So in other words, the game, you know, other than our background tasks
that we have running like building tiled things and whatever, other
than those, we are not calling game.
Get sound samples on a separate thread, it's just running in sync with
the game for now, and we might change that in the future, but for now
we're just going to assume that that's true.
So, what I want to do, first of all, is I want to go ahead and have
some
Um, idea of what sounds are actually playing, right?
So in handmade dot h, here in sort of the, this is probably going to
be in the game State.
I would assume we want to have some idea of all the sounds that are
actually playing at the current time.
Right.
Just something like this.
And so probably, I don't know, I mean, there's a lot of different ways
that we could represent that maybe a linked list is something that
seems pretty reasonable, right?
We just throw things on the linked list and we just assume that
everything in the link.
This is playing we could do that.
Another thing we could do is just have an array of a certain number of
slots and we just say that we always play Only, You know, the number
of sounds that are in the slots and so if you try to play something
and there's you know, or and the slots are full, we just don't play
it, you know, some kind of a thing like that.
I don't really know.
So for starters I think what I'll probably do is I will probably go
ahead and make it be linked list space just for the moment because
that seems like that seems like the most straightforward thing.
So I'm just going to have a thing like playing sound like so on and
it's just going to have a way to change itself, and then I'm just
going to have a pointer down here.
That's like, you know, playing sounds right?
That's it.
Or I guess I'll call that first playing sound right.
And in this playing sound instruction here, this this playing
SoundLink.
What I want to do is I want to use its
See the same sort of thing that we use for the renderer for now which
is it's going to keep in it one of those sound IDs right?
You remember we had this this concept here of representing things by
d's and the reason we did that was so that we could have things that
got loaded streamed in and out and we could still talk about the one
that we wanted to talk about.
Right?
So I want to have a particular sound ID and I want to say that like
this is the ID that's playing, okay?
And then furthermore, what I need to know is I want to know some
information about it.
So for example, I might want
I want to know what it's volume is, right?
I might want to know like a number between zero and one.
That's like how loud this thing is 0 being silent.
And one being the full volume sound was recorded at originally
So I'll throw that in there.
Another thing we might want to do is since we're stereo.
We could technically say that we have like two volumes like a left and
a right volume.
So this is what you know the you know what channel it goes into
something like that, that seems reasonable as well.
So I want to know that information and I also need to know.
Right?
If you go and look inside this thing, I need to know where I am in the
sound.
So as that sound plays over time, I need to know how many samples of
the sound I've consumed so that I know when I'm
No writing sound when I'm sort of gathering sound from that sample.
I need to know how many samples I've already played, so that I don't
play them again, right?
When I'm when I'm copying these out into the output buffer, I need to
know, sort of a play cursor inside that sound, if you will.
Right.
So I'm going to say, we have another one here, which is like samples
consumed or something, right, or our samples played, something like
that.
Okay?
And I think that's probably enough to get us started.
Here, I'll go write the loop and see if that makes sense.
But that seems like roughly what I want, you know, something where we
just have this, and we just go through them and we, and we, you know,
play them as we go, right?
Okay.
So in this Loop, what I would want to do is I want to say, okay,
I've got these playing sounds, right.
So here's my playing sound, I'm going to grab out from the game State,
you know, whatever.
The first one of those is, so let me grab out the first playing sound,
go ahead and check that, are we here?
And assuming that, that's valid.
I'm going to go ahead and operate on it.
And every time I operate on, I'm just going to move to the next one in
the list.
So inside here, we will operate on all of the playing sounds every
time we want to produce our
Examples.
and, you know, now I think about too
Another thing we might want to do just thinking about it a little bit
more carefully.
We might also want to queue things up in terms of samples ahead of
time.
So we may want to be able to set samples play too.
Like a negative number right?
Where we could kind of say like okay we want to delay, we don't want
to play this sound for like, you know, half a second or
I don't know if he really want to allow this and if we did allow it, I
don't know that.
We want to allow it at this level, but point being, we could allow you
to set that to be a negative number so that it's essentially weights
and then plays it a little bit later on if that makes sense.
Okay.
So assuming that we wanted to do it that way, what I then want to do,
is I want to essentially do exactly this, this same Loop that we're
doing here.
So for every sample, that's in the sample buffer that we're trying to
Output, I want to go ahead and output the sound but what I want to do,
as you can see in here, we've got our original Loop is just copying
16-bit sample data right into 16-bit output data.
And this is not a particularly attractive option for us here.
Because if you think about what's going to happen there as we're
accumulating values into their, we might get a lot more, clipping the
necessary if we were actually to just use 16-bit values as our
intermediate buffer.
So let me just quickly pop over here and explain this one part.
It won't take very long, but let me just give you a little bit idea
here, right?
So if we are in 16-bit, right?
So this is plus 32k, this is - 32k, right?
If we are going to do everything in 16-bit then if I have to sounds
like the first sound looks like this, right?
And then I have another sound that, you know, looks like that.
Let's say, right.
Well, when I add these two sounds together, it's going to clip because
putting this on top of this one, you know.
Well, this one already toured Eclipse, let me draw some a little bit
more piecemeal.
There we go, putting this on top of this one right there, right?
Is going to clip, that's going to end up out here.
But if I then add a third sound and that third sound looks like this,
right?
Adding this sound onto the two of them means that it would bring it
back down into range.
So actually, I didn't have to clip playing these three sounds.
I could have played them all together because this one cancels out
some of the effects of these two.
And brings me back into representable number.
So typically, when you're going to do sound like this, you at least
want to do.
If you have 16-bit sound, you're going to want to do in a 32-bit
space, right?
So what we will probably do here is just use floats because that will
allow us to also do our modulation and then, you know, are rounding
and all that other stuff will work out magically.
So, what I would want to do is I think convert from 16-bit to float.
Do the mixing then convert from float back to 16 just at the
That the head and tail end, right?
So what I want to do here is say that I've got a sound buffer, right?
This is the, this is like the real real buffer likes like so on.
And this is probably per channel, right?
So I've got, you know, I've got two different channels.
Here.
And yeah.
I want to be able to write to both of these channels.
Maybe I'll actually do this real Channel 0.
I'll be something and real Channel 1, right?
And we'll set those to something in a minute.
So what I want to do is when I come in here, I want to do is
essentially the equivalent of what was going on here, by stepping
through the samples.
But this time I want to actually do it in float space, right?
So what I want to do is I want to take the sort of the the
Last year, right?
Best zero and desk one.
Which are going to be these real Channel values, which are the
floating Point representations of our mixing buffer.
And what I want to do is I want to take each individual sample, out of
the, the loaded sound, whatever this sound is, which I guess.
Also I'm going to have to go ahead and actually call here.
So let me go ahead and grab out that code.
Where is it?
It's not load sound, it's get sounds.
We don't actually even have one of those yet, so we're gonna have to
make that as well.
So here's the
Sound, good sound, get sound sound, ID, sounds, I d.value, right?
So there we go.
So, what I want to do here is say OK, for this playing sound first, I
need to get the loaded sound, right?
So we'll go ahead and get that will get that from the assets, which I
guess is just in.
We've got that transient State there.
So, transient State, trance state
Equals transient State.
Oops.
Transit storage.
And the trance state has the Assets in it.
So all we should have to do is just say there's the assets.
We want, the sound ID is whatever the playing sound says that is
playing and then we can just see if we got it back, right?
If we didn't get the sound back then, we don't have to worry about
putting because we don't have the data, so that's fine.
And maybe.
I should put in here as well.
A couple things.
First of all probably want to actually call load sound on it right.
Probably want to tell it.
Hey that sound I need that sound.
You should probably go ahead and fetch it as soon as possible but the
other thing we probably want to do is we probably want to say since we
missed some samples here, maybe set a volume fade in eventually to
prevent it from popping when it actually does happen.
Right or delay it until oh you know what?
And that's probably that's actually a good idea.
Maybe we just delay the sound to it actually is loaded and in fact
that's what already happen.
If I just don't increment that okay.
Yeah yeah.
We're gonna, we're just gonna leave it because that's what will
actually happen.
If samples played isn't incrementing, if we just never move it
forwards, then we won't miss anything.
So so that's actually totally fine.
Okay, so in loaded sound, we go ahead and get the sound.
If we've got it, we go ahead here and and start looping through the,
the sample count.
And and then we need to actually do sort of a the actual some here,
right?
So what I want to do is I want to some like I was saying sounds just
all add together.
So what I want to do is I want to some whatever the sample value is at
this particular location in floating point, I want to sum that.
And first I want to multiply it though before I some it by whatever
the volume is for this particular channel, right?
So I want to go ahead and say
You know, that whatever the volume is, maybe I'll pull those out into
temporary, so that it's obvious, probably, what's going on as well.
So, volume 0 volume, one will just be playing sound volume 0 and
volume 1.
So there you go.
And in here we will just do that summation, right?
And so all we really need to do to do that is to get out, whatever the
sample value is and to get out the sample value, without worrying
about the edge conditioner.
Additions which we're going to have to worry about in a second.
But without worrying about the edge conditions, all we would have to
do to get that sample.
Value out is just figure out where in the sound, the loaded sound
samples, we actually are right.
Okay, so let's see here.
What we have in handmade assets is right here.
So there's our loading sound samples, zero sample index, that would
grab it out.
And of course, we know also that we have an offset, which is samples
played, right?
So we're going to have to add that in there.
So I guess we should also, we should probably account for that as
well.
In fact, what I probably should do is just say Okay loop from samples,
played two samples, played plus sample, count, something like that.
And that way, the sample index just is the right Index.
Right.
So, yeah.
And I'll put a little to do in here for handling stereo to do Casey
handle stereo.
And we can take care of that in a second.
So that's really most of what we're talking about here.
We do have to do one of the thing which is that at the beginning,
right?
We are going to have to clear this out because if we're summing into,
if our idea is to Loop over all the sounds and some into the
destination, then we either have two choices one, we could special
case the first sound and have it.
Just copy instead of some
Which maybe we want to do for performance reasons.
But at first just to get things working, we're going to take a
slightly simpler approach, which is just every sound gets handled
exactly the same.
And in in, you know, at the very first at the outset, before we do
anything else, we're just going to go ahead and clear those those
channels, the real zero.
Real one channels will clear those 20 first so that our son will start
out at zero without us having to special case anything.
Thing in particular, right?
Okay, so we're getting there.
Now, at the end, we still have to do this Loop that we were doing
before, right?
And what we need to do here is again, we need to sort of switch things
up.
We need to switch, what what are meaning of source and death is here.
So, we're writing into the destination, we write in.
We sum all the sounds.
So, now we have the sum of all the sounds sitting in these real
Channel buffers.
What we need to now do is Loop over those.
And read out of them to get the actual resulting, some values.
And then we need to actually write to the output buffer, whatever the
actual values are converted to 16 bit, right?
So we need to basically, you know, convert these to, in 16s by taking
whatever should be in, you know, whatever.
We find in that in that channel and and rounding it.
Right, something like this.
Hopefully, that makes some sense.
All right.
Let's do Source.
1 + 3, .5 F there we go.
So now what we're doing is like running into the Left Channel, we grab
whatever's in the source, zero buffer and we round it, right?
Because this is going to do a truncation.
Then the same thing is true for the the right channel, you know, round
it.
And that's really that's really all we're talking about.
I got Advance these guys as well.
So that's that's it.
And this just down Converse.
This goes ahead and takes the
But the some floating point that we have there and turns it into 16
bit output for the channel, which is what we were expecting.
I'm going to go ahead and get rid of that test sample index because we
don't actually need any of this fact.
We don't need any of that anymore because we're actually trying to
replace that with stuff now.
Okay.
And so now we need to do kind of the rest of the stuff here.
and we have,
again, we've got some important stuff to do here because this will
basically just run out to the end of the sample and then crash, right?
So we need to do some stuff that actually bounce the region that were
working over as well, but I'm just writing out the entire routine as
an example first.
So, in the trance state, right?
We have the ability to grab memory from the transient Arena.
So if we want to we can certainly just do this with temporary memory
you know which is what we want.
So I'm going to go ahead and do that.
If you remember, we had a way of doing this.
this, we could basically just say I
Temporary memory here.
So I'm going to do that, right?
This is our mixer memory so I'm just going to say, hey man, I'm going
to, I'm going to take some memory, just for a second from the Tran
Arena like so and then I'm going to and then I'm going to end that I'm
going to use the end temporary memory to give it back just as soon as
we're actually done mixing, right?
So again that's basically just a stack allocation kind of a thing only
instead of it coming from the stack, it's just coming from our
Block of memory in the same sort of way that it would come from a
stack, right?
So I'm going to do a push array here to get a Channel of reels, and
that is going to come again from that tran Arena.
So and when I go ahead and push that on, I'm going to need however
many there are four for the samples.
Right.
Like so so this is just going to give us those two arrays that we need
to work in.
So then we go here we will clear out the mixer channels.
Then we go ahead and some all sounds, and then we have our convert to
16 bit.
Very simple.
So that is actually the entirety of the mixer for the most part and
now we just have to go deal with a few friend of Kate's, finicky
things, right?
What we need to deal with, first of all, is the concept that the
sounds are, you know, are finite in duration.
So, when we come into this Loop, right?
If you think about what's going to happen, we've got the loaded sound.
It has a particular sample count.
When this sample index gets past that sample account when it gets
Beyond it, we
It read from any more.
We'd crash, right?
Well we wouldn't crash we'd read into some other memory because we've
kind of allocated these in a block.
But we don't want that to happen, right?
That's going to start playing garbage into our Sound Stream and so it
well, it won't crash, it'll certainly sound awful and that's if not as
bad at least pretty bad.
So what we want to do here is we want to have some notion of whether
or not this sound is at its end or not, right?
And so, what I want to do is come up with a notion cure, that's like,
you know, maybe something where we talked about the samples to mix,
okay, and we'll start out assuming
That the number of samples that we want to mix, you know is is however
many samples are actually in the the output buffer.
But we can then say, well I'm also pull this out here.
Samples remaining and sound right?
Well, how many are remaining in the sound?
Well the number of samples played in The Sound is where it's at.
And the sample count is the total that it has.
So if I subtract those two, I can say here's how many samples are
Remaining, right?
So then when I can do it,
If the samples to mix is actually greater than the total number of
samples that I have right.
Then I want to mix less right.
I want to mix just the number that we actually have.
Okay?
And so, when I do that, then this Loop here, instead of running over
sample count, can just do samples to mix and that will allow me to
avoid any possibility of over running the buffer.
Now, that does put us into an odd situation, right?
SLI.
Because then we're going to come down here and we're going to say oh
that playing sound well, we've got how many samples were played.
We're going to advance it right by however many we mixed.
And now what might happen is we might be at the end of the sound,
right?
We might have mixed right up to the end of that sound, and if that's
the case,
Then we want to get rid of this sound, right?
We want the sound to go away.
You know, it's not it's not useful anymore, right?
It's not it's not going to, there's no point in leaving it in the list
when it's not actually contribute.
Anything that would just create our list, you know, make our listeners
proliferate and just get bigger and bigger and bigger and bigger
forever.
And that's really not helping anybody, right?
So what we want to do here is we want to have a notion that at some
point, the sound can get killed.
And this is that point, right?
This is the point where the sound gets killed and so in order to
You that what I want to be able to do is remove it from the list here
and maybe put it onto a free list so that we can just use it again
when we, when the time comes right, when the time comes to play
another sound, we'll just reuse that bit of memory.
So we'd have something like first free playing sound, right?
Something like that.
So that would be ideal, right?
And so what we'd want to do here is say, okay, when we get down to
here, we have playing sound and it has you know a next pointer, right?
So the next pointer, if we're going to free the sound, what we want to
do is take that first free playing sound.
It's in the game State.
We want that, you know, we just want to basically chain this on here,
right?
That's the easy way to change that on.
WE based say, okay now this is the new first free sound and its next
point is going to be whatever was in there before.
So we're base just
Sing it onto the top of that free list, right?
So it'll get recycled the problem with this is, if you notice what's
going to happen up here, when we come to the end of our Loop and try
to go to the next one playing sound, has now been taken out of the
list.
We were trying to iterate so we can't very well use this anymore,
right?
We can't use this as a way to get to the next one anymore.
So what we actually want to do is we want to snap that next pointer
earlier, right?
We want to stay here.
Hear that we have a next playing sound.
Grab, what should be the next playing sound and then we get to the end
of the loop.
We use that instead.
So that way when it gets overwritten here, it's not a problem.
And that's just a very
Cool thing that you see in a lot of Loops where you have to remove
stuff from the list you're iterating over.
You typically want to do this so that you can protect yourself against
the act of having the thing freed screwing up, your iteration, right?
So pretty simple.
Like I said, nothing special there but just, I don't know that we've
ever done that on stream before.
So I figured I'd point it out, very common thing to see happen.
So there we go.
That's that's what we're looking at here.
And for the moment, I'm not actually going to allow those sound delays
but I, you know, like I said, we left it kind of the possibility open.
So I want to go ahead and say that we're going to assert that.
The samples plate is always greater than equal to 0.
So that if we do start doing delays later, we'll remember that we
didn't actually write any adjustment code gain.
Our mixer to actually handle that.
So, yeah, that kind of makes no sense.
We don't want to
Yeah, you get the idea.
So at this point we do have some kind of, we do have some issues that
we kind of want to address.
Probably, I think, I don't know if it's a good time to start
addressing them but if you take a look at what happens here, we do
have a little bit of an arena dichotomy in the game State.
We have a World Arena but we haven't really addressed.
What happens when we have things that want to live outside of the
World Arena.
As sounds probably do.
There aren't very many
Things in the permanent game state that probably do want to live
outside of the World Arena.
But there are some right and they're things that may persist across
the creation or deletion of a world and although it sounds weird.
Sounds are that kind of thing?
So, for example, if music is playing
When the player goes quick to main menu or something, you don't want,
those sounds to go away, just because the world that was being played
goes away.
And so the world that's being played and the sounds are not really,
you know, they're not really linked in that way.
But we don't really have to deal with that yet.
I just, you know, we can sort of avoid it for now because it's not
really talking to me.
But at some point what we do want to do is start thinking about these
things in terms of having split that up, you know,
As something like World Arena, you know, and and sort of meta Arena,
right.
Kind of the things that get allocated, which are going to just be
flushed whenever the world gets destroyed versus things that are kind
of semi-permanent, they exist across worlds.
And like I said, there's not a whole lot of them but one example is
sound and there's probably, you know, some other example somewhere
that we will hit.
There's not a lot of them.
They're, you know, it's not zero is the point.
Okay.
so, what we want to do now is we want to go ahead and actually create
this, this, this list here, I don't actually know if we want to
Do one of the things first which is that I don't know that we actually
implemented.
The load sound stuff in the asset system.
Like, you know, I don't know where we got on that.
I don't really remember.
So when you call load sound, you know what, actually happens when I
call this, right?
I called debug load way time on info.
File name is info file name even ever set anywhere.
Would be my first question and let's see.
That's the sound info, right?
So sound, infos.
So I don't think we like, we haven't actually done.
Any of this is is part of the problem, right?
Meaning, there's there's sound infos here and the sound infos are not
actually are not actually set to anything.
Right.
Am I wrong about this?
Correct me if I'm wrong but I'm pretty sure that that's
Way things go.
So we had sound infos here and we're not actually setting them to
anything.
And so what I would like to do is is, you know, try to maybe make that
be a little bit more concise.
So okay.
So let's go ahead and here and maybe we'll say, you know, we've got
some sounds coming in here now, so I'll make this bitmaps for now.
Note Casey get maps and no to Casey.
Sounds and in here, we're just going to say, okay, we've got some
sounds that I had put in there, right?
That we had whatever they were, I don't really remember.
So we're just going to look.
We had a bloop, we had a drop.
We had a Glide, we had music.
We had pop, these are probably not the ones we will want to use in the
final game.
To say the least but you know that's what's in the directory, you
know, that's just that's what's in the directory.
It's a nice, 30 megabytes sound here.
So yeah, so fine, that's what we've got.
That's that's what it'll be.
So what I want to do is I want to kind of duplicate the same exact
thing that we were doing before as far as having these assets sound
wise.
So we really just want to
To extend this to, you know, sort of talk about sounds now.
So we have that bloop that's in there.
And there was three, one, two, three, four of those, right?
That's what we want to do is add, you know, do things like add sound a
set where we have those those bloops in there.
So there's bloop 0 0 dot wave and one, two, three, four and remember,
this just in for people who weren't here.
When we did all this, this is just entirely temporary code, it's
because we have not
Defined our asset file, our asset pack file format and directory yet.
So we just construct it in code for the time being but all of this
code that you see here will actually just go away and we will just be
loading essentially this data off of the disk.
And so, what we're doing now is just putting in a little bit of code
that sort of simulates.
What we expect to have tubes that I forget, s crack.
I think I did.
It just saying that's that's what we expect to have, so that we can
proof it all out and be like, yes, this is what we want.
And then when we're ready, I'll go make us a proper pack file, that
conforms to the format that we have specified here on the stream, and
then we can just delete this code.
You can go away, right.
But until then, we're going to keep doing it by hand here.
Just so we can again not spend a bunch of time, making an asset file
format in a pipeline and all these sorts of things that actually don't
do.
What we want, right?
We want to make sure that it actually does what we want and not just
something that we guess that we might need.
Okay.
Let's see.
So pup, 00 and pop one, and this is asset music and asset pop.
Okay, so there we go.
There's our, you know, there's our
Well there's our assets and so what we need to do is create the
equivalent of a bitmap asset, we need to create the equivalent of that
for sound.
So in here we need to do something where we say add sound asset, it
won't would not have an alignment, right?
And so I think yeah, this just kind of comes in here and does a debug
add sounded so I think and there's really nothing else to it besides
that.
There we go.
And then when we have that, debug, add bitmap info, we just need an
equivalent of that, which is like, debug add sound info.
And so, the sound info in here is just going to basically be all of
this stuff, but with sound replaced in it, right?
I think that's literally all there is and no none of that, right?
So what we do need to do here is the debug used bitmap, count.
We need one of those for sound, so we know where we are.
Our debug Loops debug used sound, oops, bitmap count.
And so we want to set that debug used sound count like so, all right,
so yeah, that should be basically everything I think.
Oops.
Forgot my little a Sands there.
There we go.
So where are we at?
Where are we at here?
These sample index.
As our Unit 32.
So I guess loaded sample account and samples played this should be.
You want 32 as well?
That's a little bit annoying there.
I'm not sure we want to do that long term.
So anyway, now I believe when we do a loud sound in theory that should
actually happen without issue.
So let's go ahead and see if we can make this
New system that we've got emulate, what we started with at the
beginning of the stream.
Just so we know that we're on the right track before we go ahead, then
and make a way of adding like a bunch of things to the list.
And so, what I'm going to do is at the outset when we first start
The game going where we did that load bitmap now.
Right, where we where we sorry about little bit about where we did the
load sound before.
What I would like to do is actually allocate something, that allocate
something that's going to be playing, right?
So right now, I'm going to put this in the World Arena, right?
And I'm going to say this is going to be a playing sound, and then I'm
going to say that the first playing sound is going.
Equal that, right?
So I'm just basically stuffing first playing sound.
I'm stuffing something in there.
Again, totally temporary, not going to keep this for anything, but
just want to see if our stuff that we just did actually works.
I'm going to tell it to play sound ID.
Well I guess I can actually have it be something that actually does
the first asset.
So in handmade asset, let's see here where we do our match asset type
and all that stuff.
Best match asset, all that stuff.
So what I would like
To do here is I'd like to do maybe that get first bitmap ID and that
sort of stuff.
How did we?
So this is kind of stupid looking at.
It will take care of that in a second.
But so when we do our, like, get first bitmap ID, we don't really
care.
The asset, doesn't really care whether it's doing a bitmap or not.
And so what we kind of want these functions to
Be able to work whether or not they're using bitmaps or sounds, you
know what I mean?
And we may want to have a way of asserting that they are the correct
things that correct types that you're asking for something like that.
But I feel like in general, these want, to operate on, whatever,
right?
And so I kind of feel like what we actually want here is just things
that get back the slot IDs, and then we'll just have little wrapper
functions that actually wrap those into the ID, so that you get a
little bit more, type safety out of it, through the rest of the game.
But I feel like that's really the better thing to do there.
All right, so what I want to do here is I want to to change this stuff
right?
I want to essentially say okay we've got to get first bitmap ID but
all get first bitmap ID is is is like this get first slot ID, right?
Assets type ID.
It's literally just a little wrapper it's just all it does is wrap
that up for you like that, right?
And then this is actually get first slot ID and has absolutely nothing
to do with with bitmaps.
It does not care about the bitmaps at.
All right?
So that's that's more what I'm thinking right.
Does that make sense?
And so similarly get random asset, you know that stuff's would be
Exactly the same.
It would do.
This would be random.
You'll still be get bit random bitmap from and this was just kind of
an oversight when I was doing it.
I just wasn't thinking particularly hard about it when I did it, but
now is a good time for us to go ahead and make sure that we don't
continue down that path because it was a stupid path.
So there we go.
So we can do that.
Get random bitmap from and then this one.
Oops.
And that's sorry.
Get random slot from.
Like so and I don't know I feel like this should be get first bitmap
from these names.
Are not really that good either, so that's a little bit better.
Get first slot maybe get for random slot from that that naming looks a
little better to me there.
And so this will actually, again, we'll do that same exact
transformation that we did before returning, just just the slot ID
directly, and not think about it too hard.
Beyond that like so.
And so now this is random asset from and get for a slot from
Slot slot from and then finally, we have that best match from and so
will again copy that down for a bit Maps as well.
Like so and there we go, best match asset from
Best match tip map from.
We call this kept at this this asset mashing, we just pass it, exactly
what we have and that's all there is to it so then we go get first lot
for everything.
That's good.
Get best matched asset from that, will return the slot ID as the other
ones did.
So there we have it and done.
So now these
These guys are wait.
What are you complaining about identifiers?
Not found yet random
So now these guys are actually get random bitmap from, right like that
this is get bitmap from.
This is a syntax error but we want here is get first sound from and
then we have best match asset so this is get best match fit map from
Like so.
And these are get first, bitmap ID is get first bitmap from right?
Okay.
So get first sound from now.
We need our asset stuff again to to have all of these same things for
sounds and so the reason I didn't want to duplicate all that code.
So all I'm doing here is just changing bitmap to sound in just the
wrapper functions.
And that way all the rest of the code will work exactly the same way
that it did before, right?
So, you know, really very simple.
Nothing particularly fancy going on there.
There we go.
And so on just one and so we say, get first sound from we need to
pass.
Oh you know what I can have to wait until we do get the transient
State because that will have the actual Assets in it.
So we need to actually do that here.
So we're going to do get first sound from and when we do get for a
sound from we are going to grab
Jimmy.
We are going to grab that asset ID.
The music asset ID, right?
Transudate assets.
And so that should create our first playing sound.
I think I still had the next pointer to fill out their game State
first playing sound next equals zero and that should be basically it,
right?
That should create it for us.
Let's take a look and see since we changed a lot of code there or I
should possibly say, we added a bunch of code there.
I want to go ahead and make sure I can verify that all of this stuff.
Is actually doing what it's supposed to do.
So, let's go ahead and and make sure I also want to well, will I
guess?
We'll check a little bit later.
Anyway, let's take a look in the Train Arena stuff.
To see how things are going.
Let's go in here.
What is the problem access violation writing location?
Oh, my
What have we done?
How many assets do we actually have?
By the way, we've got plenty right 17.
So, what's the problem?
It's
there we go.
Come in here.
Oh, we're still in release mode.
Hold on one second.
I would like to step through this.
Okay, so we allocate the assets, we come in here and set our tag
ranges up.
That's all good.
Oops, I accidentally hit F5.
U sound count is less than sound counts.
I don't count as one add sound asset so we just set our count too low.
Yeah, great obviously.
That's not going to work again.
This is all stuff that we'd really don't have to care about.
We just have to make sure that it works on a farm produces because we
Of this stuff will be set in code.
This will all be set in the PAC file because we'll know exactly how
many sounds there are in the PAC file when we packed it.
All right, so let's see if we can look at what I wanted to look at
now.
So let's take a look at that game State first playing sound and see
what it got set to.
So it's actually got a valid ID which is good.
Hopefully that means we actually located an actual sound slot.
The next is no our volumes though.
I think about it.
Those should not be 0 because obviously if we want to hear the sound
we would have to give it a sound that is something other than 0.
So let's make that full volume for now.
And then down in the rest of the code we can we can take a look at the
mixer now that we know that something is actually going to be given to
it.
So let's go ahead and
Come in here.
There we go.
All right, so we need to load the sound because it hasn't been loaded
yet.
Eventually
We go.
So in here we can grab out, our volumes, grab out, the destination
channels, which presumably have been cleared.
Let's let's actually make sure that that's actually true.
Yeah, we're going to go in here and see how many samples we're going
to mix.
We're going to mix the exact number that.
It told us to mix is that we actually got past.
I wonder how many samples do we actually get past?
Let's take a look at our our sound buffer.
1920.
All right.
so,
There's us accumulating into here, grabbing those sample values out
and accumulating.
Presumably eventually the sound actually has some sound in it and it
will accumulate, but that looks pretty good.
Then we're going to advance the playing sound and to keep on going,
right?
And that should be fine.
We're going to go ahead and here and the output buffer.
Okay, so that looks reasonable.
And so let's put ourselves on something where we can hit our frame
rate and then see if that plays back as we might expect,
Okay.
So now what I might do is just add something that would allow us to
trigger those sounds easily.
And yeah.
For the most part, we've pretty much got the mixer all sorted.
Okay.
So what I want to do now is do a sort of, a simple little thing that
allows us to to spawn a sound, right?
And what I want to do when we, when we did our playing sound thing,
right?
Where we were doing these allocating these playing sounds.
What I want to do now is I want to go ahead and move that back up
here.
Again like I said, we have the, you know what, we have the sub Arena
stuff, now,
Yeah, it's not worth thinking about.
Well, we'll talk about this later at some point.
We have to actually go through and talk about memory a little bit more
than we've talked about it so far because we need to do some actual
partitions and, or do a dynamic pull from the operating system, one of
the other.
And I'll probably show how to do both of those actually at some point,
but now is not the time for that.
What is the time for?
However, is
To assume that we can go ahead and abuse the World Arena entirely here
and allocate.
Our sounds willy-nilly from it but what I'm going to do.
So what I'm going to do is I'm going to make it to do for that.
And then we'll deal with it a little bit later.
So internal void play sound.
Here we go.
Okay.
So in place and what we will do is we will have it take a sound ID
that you want to play, right?
And it will take also, I guess the, the game state that you're trying
to play it on and then it will go ahead and just do exactly what you
would think it would do, right?
It'll say that.
We want a new playing sound.
It will grab it.
It will initialize it, the same way that it was being initialized
before, right?
And it will then put it at the top of the list, right?
Oops.
And so this is just going to be the sound ID and I guess at this point
to, you know, we could well, you know what, I'm gonna bother.
I'm just going to have this returned to playing sound handled and if
people want to mess with the volume afterwards, they can write.
So there we go.
That's, you know, us playing the sound that allows us to play a bunch
of sounds and they'll get added on there.
The only thing that I would like to do, what do we got?
We got five minutes left.
The only thing that I would like to do beyond that is I only want to
actually do this, if I
After you.
So I'm going to do here is say this is the first free playing sound.
So if there's a free one, use that, if there isn't right?
I guess I'll do it this way.
Oh, you know what?
No, that's not the way you would do it.
The way you would do it.
If you were smart, is you just go?
If there isn't a first free playing sound, then you just go ahead and
say game State, first free playing sound equals the push, right?
Let's track game State, first replaying, sound next equal?
0.
That's all you would actually do if you were smart.
So, then,
We would do this.
And now everything is nicer playing sound blowing.
Sound blowing sound like sound.
Thanks.
Okay, so what we do here is we say all right if there's nothing on the
free list just stick a new one on the free list right?
And set the next 120 if there is then just assume from then on that we
do have something on the free list, right?
And, and Advance the free list to the next thing, right?
So that that doesn't do an else tries to use this one and then I think
we're done, right?
That's all we need to do.
Let me go ahead and compile, this looks good.
So what I'll do now is, I'll say, alright, when we do the trance State
thing.
Now, after we get the asset stuff initialized now, I could do a thing
where
Just say play sound, this sound and the game State, and that should
start our music, right?
For us.
And it does, so that's good.
And then, when I want to do is now to test the fact that we can mix
things, I'll just go ahead and say that.
Whenever we do that, you know, the hero thing, where it launches the
sword or whatever, I don't actually know, I don't remember, we had
some sort of janky,
And here, that was whatever whatever you do, this sword stuff.
Maybe we'll just go ahead and play some sound, right?
So we'll play random asset from right.
Get random asset from sound from so, trance State assets and our asset
is going to be whatever.
Whatever would be something that has a bunch.
I think, blook seems good, right?
That seems good to me.
Play sound does not take two arguments.
whoops, get random sound from
asset blue.
How many arguments does it take?
That's what I really wanted to know.
The random series.
Do we have a random series?
I don't actually know if we have a random series to give it is the
only thing, right?
We don't we don't even have one.
We haven't really done anything where we want a random series.
I guess I got a stick a random Series in here somewhere.
Random series.
General entropy.
So yeah, alright.
General entropy
We'll see that guy.
Let's see.
Random series is that not?
I don't remember how any of the random code Works to be completely
honest with you random series whereas it's down there.
So is it just hasn't been included in here.
Where is handmade random actually included?
Dare I ask.
Let's see.
So it's in here.
So I just needed to be up in here.
It's really all we're saying, right?
There we go.
So how do we see do?
We do we have a way to seed or do we not have a way to seed random
seed?
That's how we do it.
So we need to do random seed like, so I just need to see the sky with
something for now.
The series is now just going to be game state general entropy
And now we should be good to go.
All right, so let's see if this works at all.
Yeah, except we have uncovered a bug, I assume in our removal code
there, which is unsurprising.
I typed it in rather quickly and on stream, it's a little hard to pay
attention to things sometimes, so let's take a look, dude, I do
everything that I do, things correctly here.
In are playing sound when the sound is completed.
Playing sound next equals game State.
First three playing sound.
Game State first or second equals playing sound?
I did not I definitely did not and I can tell you what I did not do.
Although maybe I should give people a chance to pause if they want to
guess what it is.
And that's well.
I'll draw it.
So here's our linked list, right?
And again, this is the kind of thing.
It's hard to always remember these things on the stream.
So here's our linked list.
And that's why I instantly knew what the bug was as well because it's
something you would probably just know if you were paying attention,
or you're typing it in and not talking.
But point being here are is our linked list.
And all I did was take care of this part of it.
I didn't take care of the part that actually points to the new guy,
right?
So here's our sounds, if we're removing this guy, this guy's next
pointer, needs to hop over it, right?
So, you know, I need to actually keep track of something like this
when we're going through here.
That's, you know, going to be, it's playing sound sort of the like in
pointer, you know, who's ever pointing in here and that's going to be
this guy, right?
Because that's where we actually came from.
First.
First playing sound,
Then as we go through what we actually want to do and I mean I guess
you can even do it, we can just do it playing sound, could be playing
sound pointer like this and then let's do it this way.
So we actually take with us the address of the person who's pointing
to us, right?
And as long as what's in that address is a valid value, then we're all
good, right?
Okay.
So yeah, so then at that point, we can say, as we come through here
playing sound itself, is just going to be playing sound is just going
to be playing some pointer, right?
And then the next playing sound we actually don't want to know what
that's going to be necessarily anymore.
I mean, we do, but what we need to do, when we come down here and
actually Advance the new one is we have to advance playing sound
pointer, right?
And playing sound pointer.
We actually need to know what was the pointer that was pointing in to
whoever we were, right?
So we don't actually need to do this part anymore, if that makes
sense.
Because we're still holding that original
So we don't need to do it quite that way, right?
We can get rid of that guy.
So what we want to do here when we remove this dude, right?
And we say playing sound next right?
We put them on the free list like like this, right?
Before we do that, we need to make sure that playing sound next is
actually, what gets put in playing sound pointer, right?
So what we want to do here is say, okay.
Playing sound pointer, right?
Playing sound pointer equals playing sound next so that we can
actually have that guy point.
You know, the, the thing that was originally pointing to us is now
pointing to the person who is after us, right?
And the reason that this is a little bit tricky is because at that
point it, then you wouldn't actually have to do anything to add to
make the list Advance, right?
That already advances the list if that makes sense.
So at that point, right?
You would literally not have to do anything.
The only time you have to do something is an in fact, I guess I could.
If I wanted to I guess I could just put this out here and do it this
way.
So at the end, right?
All I would have to do is either
I remove the guy or I move playing sound pointer to be whatever
playing sounds.
Next field is right.
So that's we're stepping through because it's very complicated and I
understand that that's probably a little bit odd.
And also I have to step through it because again, on stream, it's a
little bit tough.
But let me just show you what the idea is here.
It actually simplifies the loop a little bit, which is ironic because
it's a complicated thing to do.
But it actually makes the loop be a little simpler anyway.
So what we do is before we were talking about the pointer to the
playing sound.
Now, we're talking about the pointer to a location that points to the
playing sound so are
Looking at the slot like we're looking at the place that holds the
pointer.
So we start out by taking the address of 1st playing sound, which is
the thing that's pointing to, you know, the first thing we're going to
we're going to look at.
Right?
So we coming here and we say all right let's go ahead and get the
playing sound out of the slop that we're currently looking at.
And then everything else precedes is normal, right?
Oops.
What happened there?
Oh, duh loaded sound is not actually a valid thing at this point.
So that's that's that is not going to work.
I take it back.
Sound finished.
Yeah.
They're being look good.
Sound finished equals false.
There we go.
Okay, so we come in here, go back to what I was trying to explain
ignoring that part.
And you know what?
I should probably also do for you is switch to debug built, so you can
see me stepping through it in a more sane way.
There we go.
So in we go, and so now at the end, if the sound was finished, we do
some fancy footwork.
If it's not all we're doing is saying well, okay, previously, we were
pointing at who we were remembering.
Whirring, who pointed to us?
Like the pointer that pointed to us?
We were remembering it, right?
So all we need to do to go forwards, is say, alright, whatever the
thing is that we're actually talking about then we just need, it's
next pointer.
Now that's the pointer.
That's actually going to be the thing we want to remember, right?
So we grab that out, right?
Then we come through and we keep going.
Now, I want to go ahead and do once we can see when the sound
finishes, what happens there?
So here's a running and there's now and we've actually finished.
So when a sound actually finishes, what we want to do is say alright,
we were tracking the person who was pointing to us.
So now we want them to point to whoever comes after us, right?
So we just replace what was ever in that pointer.
You're tracking with with the next person, right?
We then say, let's move ourselves to the free list which is the same
as before.
And then we continued on.
Knowing that now the thing that is going
He looked at in this Loop is actually already the next person, right?
It's are ready the next person in the list and so we continue, and
then that's it, right?
And that's, that's the end of it.
There really isn't much else there.
We said, don't think so anyway.
Okay, so what is going on here?
We have a loaded sound bug though.
Looks like we have a different problem.
if I'm not very much an error,
Sample index, what is loaded sound?
so we have another problem this time it looks like with the math, ah,
Nope, it's not a problem with the math.
It's just a problem with our play sound function.
Obviously, when we played the sound, I was trying to make sure we set
everything, but we didn't actually set.
Everything samples played needs to be reset to zero as well.
There we go.
All right.
All right, so I think we're all good now.
Let's take a look here.
If I set this back,
here we go.
Not exactly the sound that you probably want to happen when you shoot
in a game but
We're all good.
Now, I think.
And so, that's really all there is to it.
We've got some more stuff that we'd want to do, but that's, that's
basically it and I'm a little over time here.
So, let's go ahead and go to the Q&A.
yeah, and by the way, so one thing that I will mention here
Just in terms of full disclosure.
So also, I don't love Loops like this.
That do the singly singly linked list removal from inside the list.
I don't really like writing these by hand because they are a little
finicky and hard to understand when you write them that way.
So I do I usually generate them.
I like, you know, I think they work, okay?
It's just they're kind of hard to understand when you write them.
So I do tend to to reuse that bit of code.
I don't write that by hand normally
Doubly linked list site, often do right by hand?
Audrey II, do generate them, but I actually don't mind writing them by
hand.
I should say, because they're not finicky like that.
Is the sound buffer logarithmic or linear?
And do we have to account for that in building the sums for the
buffer?
So, sound buffers are linear in in, like sound, apis, they're not
logarithmic
That makes sense.
All games Network video.
Do you already have someone composing, the soundtrack actually, I
licensed music for the soundtrack, we met in the future.
It depends like what how much money the game makes in terms of like
sales amount?
I would like to be able to release the music into like with, with the
Game Source eventually possibly possibly into the public domain.
But at the very least,
Release it under copyright.
And that's not something I can do with the music that I licensed.
So, at some point, I may, if the game made enough money, I would try
to hire someone to do music that I could include basically as part of
the, the source code as well, right?
Because like the art, for example, we have the full rights to
So I can release the art in any way that I want to whenever I want to
which, you know, we may want to do some of that, right?
And so, you know, kind of like the code where the codes going into the
public domain.
I may want to release some of the art for people to use as well.
Like for example, you know maybe we take some of the art and say
anyone can use this in any game if they want to you know, and I don't
know what my plans are for that.
I just want to make sure you have the option.
Yeah.
And so with the music, I don't have the option of doing that because
of the license that it's under.
So we may try to rectify that in the future so that I can have full
ability to control what happens to it afterwards, but I don't have any
idea if we will have money for that or not.
A reminder about the parameter order in interlocked increment and the
bug it covers up.
Oh, so is this this is this.
The q1 I had to mean to fix this for a while and I don't know if this
is the one you're talking about.
I'm gonna go to the one that were talking about are interlocked
increment though.
Okay.
You know what?
I don't know what you're talking about.
Are we using interlocked increment?
Interlock increment Q completion count.
So I don't know what bug you referring to.
Unfortunately, you have to be more specific.
I was actually thinking of this one, which is that when we set, when
we do, the atomic compare Exchange in here,
I thought there was a thing.
Yeah.
So the problem is that if we can't begin this task what we want to do,
like if the task begin fails, we want to make sure that we set the
asset State back to being unloaded, right?
Like like that because otherwise it would go to queued but no task
would ever actually get assigned to it because we run out and then it
would just never be able to be loaded, right?
And so yeah, that was not obviously something we were talking about
today but it was a bug that we talked about on the forums and that we
needed to fix.
And so
I did want to put that in there.
When mixing in mono sound to stereo volume of each finger should be
50% for Center pant.
Why?
Why would that be true?
I guess if you want to move it, I see what you're saying because you
want to be able to make it go, a hundred percent into the other
channel.
I'm not sure.
Yeah, I guess since they add two sounds out together, I could I could
buy that.
I could I could buy that being a reasonable default, I guess.
You know what?
I don't know if I don't know, maybe maybe I'd buy that, maybe I don't.
Like it depends whether you want the sound to be full volume when it's
in the center.
Right.
So I don't really know if I buy that.
I think I might just prefer it to just get quieter as it comes over
here, right?
So I'm not sure.
I'll put it to do in there for you but I'm not necessarily sold.
Soy sauce, the kid, will this audio code?
Allow you to play the same sound simultaneously.
If you start the same sound before it finishes the first time.
So you tell me, you saw me code.
It soy sauce, tell me whether you think it will or not, and why?
TF nwe, reminder about the parameter code, the second and third
parameters in the compare and swap.
I was thinking of the wrong function, thinking,
Second and third parameters in the compare and swap.
You're talking about Atomic compare Exchange.
ah,
Yes, I see what you're saying.
Did we have them?
Did we have them in the wrong order?
Let's take a look and made intrinsics comic compare exchange.
Expected new.
Ah, yes.
They're past the wrong way.
How was that working though?
that's,
So, we just had some we should probably look into that.
Though, that seems just like we must have had another bug.
So, I wonder if we should try to maintain the same.
I'm going to go ahead and do an atomic compare exchange you in 30 to
search here, to see where we use, it only in those places.
So I'm going to try and keep it the same as Windows because because
Windows does it this way?
And that way people won't get confused including myself, because I
believe that this is normally the way it goes, right?
Let's take a look.
Locked compare Exchange.
Exchange and comprehend.
Yeah, so the expected it goes in the final one.
So yeah.
So that is how we would expect it to go.
We would expect it to go like this, right?
We're setting it to queued.
We expect it to be unloaded right comic.
Sitting Duck.
You'd like so
And that's what we expected to have happen.
But we must have had some other bug because why was that ever working
right?
In fact, I don't really know.
It seems like that shouldn't have worked, right?
Because it should never have actually done the exchange and it should.
Oh, but it would always return unloaded, right?
So yeah, so that actually would work.
It would always return on loading because that's always what it would
have been, right?
So yeah.
The audio seems to be frame rate depending at the moment, could put it
in a separate thread or using interrupts.
If you can make it not frame rate dependent using interrupts would not
be super possible on Windows, but you could put it in a separate
thread if you wanted that would help make it not frame rate dependent,
although you would have to do work to ensure that that thread was not
starved.
So because there's no guarantee, right?
That the operating system is going to actually wake that thread up in
time.
So so yes and no really what you want to do.
Usually and we probably will, look at this a little later on.
Usually, what you want to do is a, you want, always make your frame
rate, but what you can do is you can put more audio into the buffer
than is necessary to get to the next frame.
And then if you did make your frame rate, you just overwrite.
What was in the buffer with the new stuff?
If you didn't then you you just, you know, go out a little further and
the sound won't actually sound like it's skipping, right?
But that's not relevant.
He's super much of a concern at this point.
I mean a because we should always hit frame rate.
So it's going to be very rare like the shipping game should never miss
the frame rate that's that's just bad, but if we do want to have some
way to guarantee that we don't have a sandwich, we have other ways
that we can take a look at that down the road because, you know,
sometimes you might miss a single frame once in a while because like,
you know, Adobe Reader is running in the background and take some of
your time away or bad things like this.
Would you mind adding a sink valve compare and swap for GCC clang?
Know, I could totally do that, although I don't remember it off the
top of my head very well.
Do we have another compiler defined in here yet?
Don't really remember.
There it is.
So I also don't know what's the right barrier is, would be the other
thing.
It's some heinous as mm thing last time.
I remember it was like, it's like you put in a nasm instruction or
something like this.
So if you want to tell me what you want there for GCC as well, we
could do that.
But yeah, I can put that in there.
So if it's sync Val that compare-and-swap on llvm, this is the value.
So it's the other way around.
Are you saying that it's the other way around for GCC?
Anyway, take a look at that and tell me also maybe what you want there
if you're trying to compile.
Okay.
So you're saying azzam volatile
That will do the fence.
That looks like, what?
I remember roughly, I always thought this was kind of a little bit
crazy.
But yeah.
All right.
So yeah, I don't know if that helps or not.
We can when I when I push this code up and you guys can download it
and test it and see what happens.
Then you'll be able to say whether, you know, it actually worked or
not.
We can we can fine-tune it.
No more questions.
I'll answer the question about whether this could play sounds on top
of each other.
Let's just go ahead and do that by way of demonstration.
So instead of playing bloop, let's just play something very loud.
I'm sorry, very long.
Right.
Little sound.
Very good to have this many piano scores playing at once.
But as you can see, it totally works.
Kind of cacophony.
It's like Philip Glass or something.
Rabisu, the reason why it works is because, you know, if you take a
look at how this thing works down here, right?
Playing sound is a totally separate concept from the actual sounds
themselves, right?
We basically said that we have a separate list of sounds, so separate
list of playing sounds.
So we can create as many entries in that list as we want and all of
them could all point to the same, underlying sound buffer, right?
So this Loop is happening over however many playing sounds.
There are not however many loaded sounds.
There are right.
So we basically have a system where it's completely divided, right?
We've Got Loaded sounds over here and we've got playing sounds over
here.
Okay?
And so, if we load in a sound and we have the music in here, we can
just go ahead and stack up as many playing sounds.
As we want that all point to the same piece of music, right?
And each one of these because we partition the data properly.
So, that the sample count that had been played so far is in each of
these, they can each be.
Different position in time, right?
And this is a very important thing to understand, you always want to
separate your asset data from your instance data, right?
This is like an instance of a sound and this is like the definition of
a sound and code terms, right?
It's like when we Define a struct and then we have lots of objects
that are that type, right?
We say like you know, I mean even the playing sound itself, we Define
the struct once that's what's in there, but then
We make a bunch of them, right?
And the same thing is true for our asset system.
We have
You know, a loaded sound that we actually create but then we can play
it as we want to have like records that instance, it as many times as
we want.
So that we can play it, you know, on top of itself or however many
times we want and all that sort of thing, right?
Something that makes sense.
All right, let's close everything down.
I don't see any more questions.
So I think we're good.
Oh, one more Cooper.
Caleb, why use a linked list as opposed to another data structure?
Like a vector, the reason you use a linked list here is because we
tend to add and remove things randomly and vectors tend to be vectors.
You can't add and remove things from randomly without cost.
When you add something into a vector, you have to resize the whole
thing potentially or you know, whenever you get to, you know, the end
of it basically, whenever you fill it up, you have to resize it more.
And when you remove things out from it, right?
You would still have to do the free list, tracking.
Otherwise, you have to compact the whole thing down.
So for random removal in this case, it's much easier to just use the
link list in this case.
And part of that reason is because the we don't need random-access.
Like we never need to say, what's the third playing sound, right?
And so, when we have a situation with random addition and removal,
And we don't need to ever do random access.
That's a time when a linked list tends to be pretty handy, right?
Because that's exactly what it does.
Well,
But can you take the output of the sound summer mechanism and play
that sure if you wanted to?
There's no reason why you couldn't.
All right, I'm going to go ahead and call it.
It says stream has ended.
So, I believe the stream has, in fact, ended.
All right, everyone thank you very much for joining me for another
episode of handmade hero.
It's been a pleasure coding with you.
As always, it's nice to have sound mixing in there in zygote form but
you know you could you could ship a game with, that's a mixture.
If you really had to just doesn't have a few of the features that we
probably want to add like I mentioned on the previous stream that are
pretty basic and we should probably add them.
Anyway, that's what we'll do next week.
We'll continue down the sound mixing Road just a little bit.
Just put a few more features in there.
Maybe make make it Cindy as well.
So we'll go ahead and do that.
And I hope you'll join me for that again.
That'll probably start Monday.
I don't know what time, but check the, the tweetbot for the schedule
until then, if you would like to play around with the code yourself at
home and experiment and so on, you
Always get it by pre-ordering, The Game and handmade hero dot-org
using the little pre-order button.
You can go ahead and check that out.
I upload the source code every night after we're done coding here so
you can play around with it.
There's also a forum site.
You can go to ask questions, get ports to Mac and Linux and other good
stuff like that.
So check that out.
If you're trying to learn from the stream, it's a good resource.
There's also an annotated episode guide on there.
That's cool.
There's a patreon page if you want to support the video series and
there's also a tweetbot between the schedule to you, as I mentioned
before if we try to figure out what schedule going to be for the week,
check out that.
That tweetbot, it's pretty handy.
Alright, everyone that's it for handmade hero.
I hope you guys have a great weekend.
I know I will, because I just got a beta build of the game that I
haven't gotten a build of in a long, long time.
And I can't say what it is because it's not announced yet, but I'm
pretty excited.
So I will have a very fun weekend.
I don't know if you will but I hope that you find a game out there to
play so that you will too.
Alright, take it.
Every tease, everyone hope to see you back here Monday until then
have.
A great weekend and have fun coding.