And stop and go hanger that.
Hello everyone and welcome to handmade hero Morning Edition.
It is very good to see all of you bright and early here.
10 a.m.
Saturday.
Sorry Friday morning here in sunny, Seattle, Washington.
I guess what I should say today is we are kind of wrapping up a little
bit of what we were doing.
Obviously, handmade hero.
For those of you just joining us is a show where we create an entire
game from scratch using nothing, but our bear little typing fingers.
No engine, no libraries so that we can kind of see everything that's
involved in the full stack of game development, see how it works, out
of really low level, and basically gain a good understanding, and have
a lot of fun in the process.
To, it's just fun to kind of be able to do everything yourself and see
how it works.
It's just kind of got
Really nice feel to it.
Right?
It's like it's like doing that woodworking project or whatever that
you always wanted to do.
It just has this kind of great feel to make something directly where,
you know, that you were kind of making it all.
All from scratch yourself.
If you are following along with the series at home, and you have
pre-ordered the game on handmade here a torque.
You should have gotten a link in your email.
That link has a zip file with every day of source code.
Today's date 35.
So if you want to follow along unzip, day 34 into directory and you'll
be exactly where I
I am today and where I am today is we were just finishing up sort of
making our virtualized.
Tilemap system sort of work for reals.
In a sense that you can actually have sort of a large world with
little sections that are stored by the town map.
That is what we were doing.
And we were almost there yesterday.
We introduced the concept of a memory Arena where we sort of basically
put stuff into our permanent store.
And I'd like to go ahead and sort of dive back into that today and
kind of talked about it a little bit.
And sort of talk about how it's working and where it's going.
All right.
So let's go ahead and see where we were at.
I'll just load up the code here and run the old game.
So we basically didn't have a chance to actually make a world at all.
We only had a chance to kind of slap down some stuff.
So maybe what we should do before we do anything else is just kind of
make it so that we're actually making some rooms for a little guy to
be in.
That's something that seems like a pretty reasonable thing to do.
I would say.
So let's go ahead and try that.
So on Startup, basically, what happens is we have this thing that was
looping over 32.
By 32 screens.
And then it was just kind of setting towels.
It was setting them totally randomly.
So what I might like to do is just set some walls in here.
And so maybe I'm going to go ahead and say that whatever the tile
value is that tile value, will default to be nothing.
But if the tile x equals 0, let's say or the tile x equals tiles per
width minus 1, so if it's on either edge of the screen, we
We are going to say that the tile value should be one, so they'll be a
blocker there.
So.
Basically, making our horizontal walls and then we can also make our
vertical walls, the same way essentially, and this should make rooms.
I think, oops Got actually use that towel value.
This should make rooms.
I think that are sealed, right?
It should make rooms that we cannot get out of that.
We are kind of just stuck in.
And there you go.
We can't actually get out of them.
And you can see that this is kind of like a room like we used to have,
right?
This sort of thing, but we don't have any doors yet.
So, all we kind of really have to
Do here is make some doors.
So let's go ahead and make some doors real quick.
How do we want to make doors?
Well, I guess in here will say that if the tile y equals tiles for
height over 2, then we don't want to make the door, you know, I
started then we do want to make the door.
And if not, then we don't and the same will be true for our tile X,
right?
If it's going to be tell spur width over.
To then it's right in the middle.
So we'll make that door and I think that should basically make doors
for us everywhere, so that we can.
If you want to walk through things.
Now, we should basically have sort of this really really large world.
And of course I can speed sort of through it.
We now just have room upon room upon room stuff in there with nothing
in particular going on or happening in any of these rooms.
We should be able to get to the end of it.
We only made the, what 32 of these.
How many do we make?
And
Or actually, remember how many of these we made 32.
So if we walk 32, if you walk 32 of these four words, which is a lot
of them, we would eventually get to the end but I don't think I'm
going to sit here and do that.
So anyway, that makes rooms and rooms and rooms and rooms for us to go
through which is all well and good.
Excuse me.
But now, what we want to do is we want to make it so that maybe we
basically have only rooms, we don't have just a full grid.
We want to start testing our sparseness.
You know, what I'd like to do to actually, let's let's do this as
well.
Let's actually try something here.
Just to see what would happen.
Let's actually try doing something that will totally tanked our frame
rate, probably because of the slow way that we've done things here,
because we're just kind of looping over everything.
What if we
To go ahead and actually make the tile size much straw smaller and
draw a lot more of them.
So for example, up here.
Remember the thing that determines how big our world is we have our
our tile side in pixels, right?
We have our tile side in pixels here and our m 2 pixels.
If we were to make the pixels extremely small, let's say we were to be
able to fit 10 times more of them in there.
So we made our tell side and pixels.
Be only six.
Right, we could go in here and we could query a lot more pixels.
In fact, you can kind of see what happens if I just do that.
You notice we're just drawing a very small.
Version of our tile map, excuse me.
And so now, the question is, what could I do?
You know, could I go in there and basically just draw a much larger
version of the map.
So, to do that, I just have to actually pull more and we'll want to be
doing a lot more stuff than we're doing here.
Also, these are just debug drawing routines.
But anyway, if I go ahead here, now again, this is really inefficient
what we're doing.
But you can see that we basically have our entire mapping drawn now,
well, not our entire map but a much larger version of it.
So, we can kind of see what's going on.
Now.
What I would like to do, I guess at this point is say, if up section
of the tile, map was not initialized.
So there isn't anything in it.
I'd like to draw that in something other than gray, just so we can see
it or rather, you know, have some way of knowing what it is.
Because right now, when there's nothing in the tile map, we just
return 0 and so you can kind of see for example that I'm like kind of
off in space there.
So maybe I don't know.
One thing that we might want to do.
You start to talk about what a, you know, like is there a concept of
an invalid tile?
So we can kind of see where our tile map just doesn't have anything.
Because out here there was nothing we did initialize it, but we're
just returning zero whenever we look for a tile chunk and don't find
one there.
Right?
So what I wanted to do is kind of say, all right.
Well, maybe you know, if the tile map comes back 0, right, let's say
that that we basically have something where
We get the tile value and if the tile ID is going to be greater than
0.
So 0 will actually mean.
There's nothing there at all.
And we just won't draw anything right now.
Unfortunately, so far we've had zero in our tile map 0 has meant
nothing.
Excuse Me, 0 has meant that it was walkable.
So I'm just going to go ahead and arbitrarily because I can and we
haven't thought about this at all.
Obviously, I'm going to go ahead and set these to basically be one and
two.
Eventually, we're going to have to think about what we actually want
to start on our tiles.
And right now, I'm just randomly slapping number codes in there.
Completely willy-nilly.
So I'm just going to go ahead and do that.
So now we have zero means there's nothing there.
One means it was walkable to means that it was a wall and so I'll go
into the tile map now and all I really have to do is that is tile
empty thing and this is a good example of why we'd want to start
having enums for these.
But this codes I'm sorry.
These tile storage is not really going to be how we're ever going to
store tiles.
Really.
We're going to have a lot more data than and you went 3-2 probably.
So it's not that interesting to
Start defining e times the stuff but I suspect now.
Yeah, they're.
So now we can kind of see what's going on.
Right?
We can see that.
There's nothing in the world out there.
We haven't actually defined tile chunk for those locations.
Because remember, this down here is 00, actually, we started the guy
out pretty close to it.
So back here is like, some really high number.
This is like four billion that tile is 4 billion for billion.
Right?
Because the world is toroidal.
Like I said, it wraps around, and so now you can kind of, see roughly
where we have defined the world and where we haven't.
And so, that's kind of just a nice sort of thing to kind of understand
if that makes sense.
So, going through here, what I am now thinking we should do is we
should actually only make rooms in some places.
Now.
What I'd like to do is start talking about random numbers, but it
might
be a little premature again.
This is the place where we could lean on the C runtime Library so that
I don't have to teach random numbers just yet and we can still have
them but we would like to have some way of making.
Oh, you know what?
No, there's an easier way to do random numbers.
That doesn't involve me leaning on the C, runtime library that we can
do.
Okay.
So there you can see.
I walk to the end of it.
We've walked 32 up.
So there you go.
So what I'd like to do now is maybe do something where we kind of have
a random
A random number sort of thing that happens.
What I'd like to do is basically say, okay, before what we were doing
is we were doing something where we're was, I hand me that CBP we were
basically just looping over the screens, 32 by 32, and we were just
making a new screen.
What I'd like to do.
Now is just say, instead.
I'm going to do a number of screens, right?
I'm going to do screening and x equals 0.
I'm going to stream just less than 100.
So I'm going to make 100 screens, but I'm not
Going to stay where they are.
So we'll start out by saying that our screen X in our screen, why are
at 0 0?
But instead of looping over it.
I'm just not going to say where the screens are.
So we're going to make a screen at the location that we're at, but
then we're going to choose to move to a different screen based on some
kind of random number.
Okay.
Okay, so I just took a look at the at the screen and I noticed people
talking about the art and yes, I'm excited to get to the art, that'll
probably be happening very soon.
Now.
I just had a bunch of stuff.
I kind of want to go through with you before we start dealing with the
renderer.
But yeah, the artist for the game.
Yeah, action Lee is awesome.
I'm really, really glad that she was interested in working on the
project because her artistic is fantastic and
Yeah, the stuff the stuff for the game is just looked absolutely
gorgeous.
So I think the game will look absolutely beautiful.
But yeah, I'm glad you guys think so as well because I thought her
stuff was really really quite fantastic anyway.
Moving on.
So here we are.
We're going to do this number screen.
So what we'll do is we'll lay out a, you know, the same thing, we did
just a room with some doors in it.
And then what we're going to do is say okay from there.
I'll just going to randomly.
Move one of the two, I'll either increment screen X or I'll increment
screen y, but not both of them.
So I basically do.
If random number something like this equals zero.
That or I should say if random Choice equals 0 else do this.
It will do screen X Plus Z equals 1 or screen y plus Z equals 1.
So we'll just kind of go in whatever direction that is it.
So now we just need a way of making a random choice, right?
We need to be able to make a random Choice somehow so that we can get,
you know, something that allows us to pick randomly whether we want to
go.
To the right one or up one, right with our room.
So we're going to start out.
We're going to make a room.
Then we're going to choose to either make a room to the right of it or
the room above it.
That's all we're doing here.
Right?
Very, very simple.
So we'd like to do is figure out how to make a random choice.
Now normally, the way random numbers work.
And like I said, we won't really get into random numbers just yet.
We'll be making our own random number generator.
Once we actually start doing the World Generation stuff for real, but
at the moment I just need something.
So we can kind of split down rooms in a random pattern and start see
how our sparseness thing is working.
So, what I want to do here is just sort of point out the fact that,
okay, random Choice.
What I need to do is I need to take a random number, and I need to
produce one of two options.
And so, the way that that's typically done is using the mod operator.
Now the mod operator, as we talked about before on the stream is
basically something that doesn't divide and just talks about the
remainder of that divided in integer space.
So if I divide something by 2, I know I will either get a 0 or a 1
because the only remainder you can get when you divide something by 2.
Is 0 or 1, right?
That's all that's going to be left.
Assuming we're talking about positive numbers here.
So, if I take a random positive number, I divide it by 2.
The remainder will either be 1 or 0.
It can never be too because then we would have had one higher when we
did The Divided, right?
So the mod operator is something that takes some random number and
turns it into a number of choices for us.
And that's exactly what we wanted.
Right.
So, all we need to do now is do some random number.
Here, we need
To have a way of doing a random number.
And what I'm going to do is just avoid the issue altogether for the
moment.
So we don't have to start talking about random numbers today because
it's not really a good time for it.
We want to spend kind of a week, talking about them or something at
some time in the future.
Maybe not a week, but at least a couple days.
So I'm just going to have our table of random numbers for now and then
I will just put in to do.
Here are random number generator will be something that will want to
actually do a good job on since this games procedural generated.
We really want a good random number.
Obviously, so what we're going to do is just do this and I'm going to
say that we essentially have a random number table.
Hear that, we can initialize with a bunch of random numbers and then
we'll have a random number index.
And that random number index will start off at zero.
And I will also cert here that the random number index is less than
the array count of the
Number table, and we'll just make sure that we make a big enough
random table to have all the randomness that we need for now.
Again, not a particularly glorious or beautiful solution, but that is
just what we have to do to get things started.
So there's our random number index and now we will go make our random
number table out here and that can be a internal Global.
There is our random number table and our random number table.
We can now just go grab a ton of
Of random numbers, I guess there's a easy way to do this on
random.org.
Usually I feel like we can typically get them in different formats as
well.
Where is it?
Listen more?
No numbers.
Integers integers sets.
Here we go.
Switch to advanced mode.
We want hexadecimal.
We want values between
One, and four billion.
Ideally actually, guess I could even be 0.
We would like to generate.
I don't know.
Let's get at least one full 4096 load of those.
Maybe we could even get more than that.
If you wanted to I'd like for a billion in here to be the largest.
So let's go ahead and actually get the exact 4 GB number 4, x, 1024 by
1024 x 10.
For.
So I'd like that to be the largest.
There we go, and we can go ahead and format those in eight columns.
So, let's see.
Bare-bones text document.
Lets see get numbers.
Oh, seriously guys, seriously.
All right, fine.
Yeah, that's right.
One minute.
All right, why is that?
I have no idea why that would be, but let's go ahead and just accept
our limitations.
Because again, this is only a temporary solution.
So I guess that'll be fine.
We've got all our stuff in here, get numbers.
There we go.
So there's our random numbers, right?
They're lovely.
They're a little smaller than I would have liked, but I can go ahead
and cut and paste those in here.
And now, I've got
Some entropy and entropy is always kind of good.
So now I will go through and just format this in a way that actually
would allow us to compile it.
This is a good case for again the C macros.
So let's say that we have something that looks like this.
I will go ahead and start my macro recording.
I will come out here.
Delete that put a comma in.
They're gonna hear delete that put a comma in there.
Come out here.
Delete that comment in there.
Oops.
That's no good.
Let's try this one more time.
I'm not.
Well today not a good editing day people.
Not a good editing day at all for Casey.
All right.
This might still work though.
It doesn't.
Let's try that one more time.
You know, it's a good day if the macro if the keyboard macro goes
right the first time and you know, it's a bad day if it don't right.
Alright, so let's try that again.
Do this for Words, Oops.
Wow.
I just it's like I can't even type.
I don't know what's going on.
People.
I do not know.
All right.
Let's try that one more time.
How hard could it be?
You know, really?
Shouldn't be that hard.
Being completely silent here, so I don't mess it up.
All right.
Okay.
There we go.
Well, you know what?
I forgot and I forgot to put the 0 x in there.
So I'm gonna have to do this again.
So, you'll get to see me make another keyboard macro.
We're, I'll probably mess it up.
So, you know, yeah, not a good editing day.
Maybe it's cuz it's Friday.
Maybe it's because it's early in the morning.
Maybe.
It's because the coffee has not kicked in yet.
I'm drinking coffee, almond milk.
This morning, homemade.
Quite tasty.
Yeah.
What can I say?
I like me.
Some almond milk.
Alright, so, let's go ahead and you notice how slowly Max is doing?
This is kind of crazy.
You know, Call of Duty can render 3460 nowadays, photo-realistic
frames per second, emacs can apply a keyboard macro in less than a
second kind of amazing.
Ladies and gentlemen, kind of amazing.
What are you going to do?
Add new Editor, to the list of things I got to do in my life.
Alright, still going still going here.
God look at how it's so slow and it just gets slower and slower and
slower.
Absolutely awful.
I do not know how they ended up in such a place.
Look at how slow that is.
How much more of these do I have to do?
This is going to take forever.
It's never going to finish.
Ugh.
All right.
Let's see what I can do here.
And what if there's something I can do here that, would speed things
up.
Maybe it's because I hit the, will the Kama automatically tab it yet.
Will I suspect?
It's probably the tab.
It's super slow to.
Yeah, that's really unfortunate.
So what happens here, when I do that, it doesn't actually do the, you
know, K.
So, let's try this one more time without me doing tab at the
beginning.
So we'll do Define keyboard macro.
I'll just do 0x.
Let's go, Delete space.
Oops, oh, X comma, delete space, 0 x comma, delete space 0x.
I probably could have told you how to make a random number generator
in the amount of time.
This took 0x, right?
You know, it's like welcome to absolutely horrible editor for once you
wonder why I say, you know, a lot of people ask me why I use emacs
with, don't recommend it.
It's because well, I'm used to it and it's hard to find.
It's hard to take the time to switch to a new editor.
Stuff like this.
That's just absurd, right.
It's like this should be instantaneous.
There's absolutely no excuse for this.
Not being 100% instantaneous.
But of course, it's not.
You know, what?
I could probably do too, if I switch to text mode.
I bet that a bit yet.
It's the C++ indentation feature.
There you go.
C++ indentation, apparently is way too much four for emacs to handle.
So there you go.
That's the that's the money right there.
Now.
It's like totally instant, right?
That's that's so sad.
But yeah, what you going to do?
What are you going to do?
Emacs lisp, not the most performant thing in the world?
People let that be a lesson to you.
All right.
So there we go, and I'll turn back on C++ mode eventually, but now we
can actually do things at least that are somewhat fast.
So I can go ahead and finish this guy Define the keyboard Macro for
this just like this.
Man, that was ridiculously bad.
Just so awful.
All right, there we go.
And now I can go ahead and just kind of finish those up.
Like so.
Okay, there we go.
Now we have a random number tip generator and I can actually turn C++
mode back on, so we get our proper indentation and I don't obviously
want that polluting up our source file.
So I'm just going to make a handmade random dot h for now.
And we'll just stuff that in there and forget about it.
Right?
And so now we've got our random number table sitting there doing its
thing and I'll just go ahead and have Emax take the incredibly long
time.
It takes it to in depth.
Look at how long it takes to indent that.
Look at that.
It's just crazy.
Thirty-four percent complete this to be a percent done indicator to
end up five hundred lines of code, uh, the pain and suffering.
How is it possible?
People?
Look at this.
So embarrassing.
Right to so embarrassing.
I reported this, by the way, will actually a viewer, actually was
reporting this, a handmade here, a person when I was complaining about
how slow emacs's, I sent them a file where this kind of thing happens,
and the maintainer said it's unreasonable to expect it to go any
faster.
Der.
That's what the Emax people wrote back.
I'm not kidding.
I guess they just don't understand how computers work or something.
I don't know.
It's awful.
Anyway, so here we are at our
The number table situation.
We got to include it obviously, so we have to go in here and do
handmade random dot h.
Kind of put that in there.
We'll deal with that later.
Let's see.
What is our problem here.
Oh, I think what did I actually call this?
I think I just called it Global variable or something like that.
Yeah, so now we have something random we can look at.
So what we're going to do here.
Like I said is our routine now is going to do its little.
It's going to basically do the same thing.
It was doing with to make a screen but instead you can see when it
comes in here, right?
It's going to actually after it's done right here.
Is it making the screen right saying?
The towels for one screen after it's done making the tile for one
screen?
It's going to go here.
It's going to get a random Choice.
It's going to use that to decide which one of these it does and
Really, you know, it makes a different one every so often.
Let's see if that's actually true one.
See here, random choices 0.
Yes, it's doing what it's supposed to do.
And then we're just going to increment, one of the two values
differently depending on it.
And so, there you go.
We've now made exactly what I kind of wanted to make their we've made
sort of a random, a random thing where we have all of our, all of our
rooms kind of laid out in a random fashion, right?
They kind of just kind of go up now, you know, this is not a good
random algorithm for laying out rooms because it can't even double
back on itself.
I just wanted something that would create a shape that
And a block, right?
That wasn't just a solid block, and you can kind of see how that's
working here.
But now, what we need to do is I also want to draw where there are and
aren't tile maps for the world.
Right?
I want to be able to draw locations where there are an aren't store
where there is, an isn't storage.
So, in addition to uninitialized, I also want to draw, you know, sort
of see where the storage is, if that makes sense.
And so what I'm going to do for that is I'm going to say that whenever
we make a tile map for now, right here, where we actually create all
of our tile chunks.
Right here.
I'm actually going to also go ahead and just initialize them.
All right, so I'm going to say that.
We basically have our tile count in our tile.
Count is this thing, right?
This is how many tiles there are per Chunk in our town map.
What I'm going to do is I'm going to spin over that that whole
Tiles, right?
So here's the towel count.
I'm going to spin over the whole set of tiles.
I'm going to initialize them all to zero, so that we can see where our
tiles are and aren't.
If that makes sense.
So, our tile chunks, Italian, the x equals 0, right?
Like that.
Excuse me.
Oh, sorry.
1, not 0.
No operator fan.
Which takes, what?
What are you what?
What is the problem here?
What did I do?
What did I do tile chunks that?
Oh, right tile.
It's actually this, so this is tile chunk index.
There we go, index, like that.
So I'm pulling out each individual tile chunk.
When I allocate it.
I'm going to set it all to one.
And so then when you run it what you can see is, we're not storing
anything sparse at the moment, right?
We've still we actually did create storage for this whole area.
We're just not actually ever writing any walls into it, but we did
actually store the whole area.
So what we'd like to do is just nominally make this a little sparse or
now just using the
Stupid as possible thing.
So that we can, at least verify that we are sort of doing things in as
far as method.
And then, we can sort of leave it from then on as a to do, when we for
when we're doing the engine, proper to actually have a smart smart
storage for things but you can kind of see what I mean.
They're right.
So what I want to do now is I want to make it so that we only actually
start to to allocate space for the tiles when we actually need to
store tiles there.
That makes sense.
Instead of, you know, right now I've got this thing, which basically
preallocate sits basically as if we,
Just did a one giant array.
It's not sparse at all.
So now it's time we've done all the work.
Now.
It's time to actually make our tilemap sparse.
Right?
And so I'm just going to quickly because I know this is a lot of stuff
for people who've never done this before.
So, what we were doing right?
Is we store these tile chunks of tile?
Chunk, right now.
I think we set it so that it was basically 16 on a side is what I
believe we set it to.
Yeah, that's what we said it to here.
And so basically what we were doing is we're creating 16 by 16 chunks.
We created, however, 128 by 128 of them.
So, we basically made a big block of these chunks, and each one of
them basically gets filled in, so it's the same.
It's exactly the same.
As if we had, just right off the bat made a giant
Tile map.
That was oops.
128 times 16.
That was 2048 by 2048, right?
That's basically all we did is we made a 2048 by 2048 tilemap.
So what you want to do now is start to store that sparsely so that the
simplest thing we can possibly do.
Here is say that instead of having child chunks, always have their
tiles in them.
The tile chunks just won't have the tiles yet.
So instead of doing this spin over the array, where we actually sort
of this right here that does the this allocation to actually put
tiles.
To the Tau chunks.
We're just not going to allocate them.
We're just not going to do that that step right, instead.
What we're going to do is when we actually need to set a tile value
when the tile chunk comes back, if there wasn't a tile chunk, if that
Talent didn't have any tiles in it, then what we'll do, you know, this
is a if tile chunk tiles is not initialized, will initialize it right
there.
So right there at the time when we go to do it, we will that that is
when right on when we actually
When we actually find that we're trying to set the value of a tile
chunk, that doesn't have any tiles in it.
That's when we'll
It.
And similarly.
I think what we want to do is when we do a get tile value, we
similarly want to say if the tile chunk tiles are there because we
want to always do that as well.
There we go, set tell value, we'll check that as well.
Now, Sceptile value really probably doesn't need to call this this
checked one here, but, I don't know.
Well, we'll leave it there for now just in case.
And this doesn't need to be there either.
ER that's just some copypasta as people on the stream like to say
anyway, so what we're going to do is if we find that there's no tiles,
we're going to initialize them right here.
We're just going to basically do.
Okay.
We have this tile chunk, right?
We're going to do the same thing we were doing before, but now the
tile chunk will be allocated just in time.
So soon as we try to write into a towel chunk, that hasn't had any
tiles allocated for it yet.
We're going to go ahead and say make those tiles right now.
Push them onto that Arena that we've been passed, which is
Supposed to store them, right?
We need to know what the tile count is.
Again.
That tile count value is defined by our chunk, Tim.
Right that chunk.
Tim.
It's just the chunked in squared, right?
It's just a, it's because we're everything square at the moment.
So our child count is just that chunk.
Tim squared.
We're going to allocate that we're going to go over the tiles, and we
are going to go ahead and fill them all in with one, right?
Make sense.
So that's all.
I'm going to do, that's it.
Nothing particularly chunk.
There we go.
What's the problem push array, right?
So now we actually have to Loft that Arena stuff up a little bit
because I had just kind of declared it right where it needed to be.
But actual people are starting to use it now.
So this stuff I'm just going to go ahead and pop that up into here so
that everyone can use it.
Who wants to use it like that to me for now we'll have to this will
probably become its own file because we'll have our memory stuff in
there.
But for now you need to worry about that and now we can actually see
our
Of storing stuff sparsely.
So now you can see that basically we're not storing the tilemap
everywhere in a giant rectangle.
We're only storing the tile map around the places where we actually
have rooms, right?
And so that is much nicer and uses a lot less memory.
So now we can have much larger worlds in terms of span and we will, we
won't pay for a bunch of space that forces the storage for them to be
rectangular, right?
To be a giant rectangle.
Does that make sense?
Hopefully you can see what I did there.
So now we're only storing the places around, you know, we're using 16
by 16 block.
So there's still some wastage as you can see because it has to be
aligned on the 16s.
I 16 blocks, but we now have a nicely sparsely stored world.
That's only exist, sort of in the places where we actually needed to
write data, right?
So that's pretty cool.
That's that's good.
So we've gotten to the
Least that I want us to be for our tile map storage.
We are now starting at sparsely and we can store very large things if
you can imagine.
Like, yeah, basically
We can you know what?
We can even go ahead and say now if I go back in here handmade that
CPP, you can see how this kind of feels.
You would never actually know that.
This was the case.
If we did a couple of the player will never have to know that the
world doesn't exist outside the part that they can see.
So what we could do, for example is when we make our doors, let's go
ahead and make our random Choice sort of at the head end.
Let's let's just move this up here.
So,
sleep, when we come into the screen, you make the random choice about
which is going to be and then we basically say okay if we were going
to go one screen over in X because we're now we're making
We're making doors on either side.
Right?
So basically, what we need to do is we need to basically say where the
door should be.
And so we can, we can sort of do something where we basically say.
You know, is there a door?
Is there a door on the left?
Is there a door on the right?
So on, so will they say like this drawer, right?
Or top down or bottom, something like this?
And so what I'll do is I'll set those out here so that there's no
doors to start with when we make the random choice.
We will be determining whether there's a door in one of those places.
So we'll say, you know, if the random Choice equals 0 else, right?
And so, what did we say?
We said that we go
One to the right.
So there's a door on the right in the case of this, right?
There's a door to the top, in the case of this, right?
Then we've yet to the bottom will clear those out, right?
Will clear all of these back after we're out of here.
So after we finish making our doors will clear all these out right
like that, but instead of clearing them to 0 what will do is will say
welded the door to the left is where the door.
To the right was on this screen and we want it to carry over to the
next screen.
If there's door to the right here, they'll be a door to the left on
the other one.
So we're just going to say that basically door to the right.
I'm sorry door to the left is whether there was a door to the right on
this one.
Right?
And we're going to say that the door to the top is whether, or not,
I'm sorry, sort of the bottom is whether or not there was a door to
the top on the other one, right?
So, because those are the two doors that would be determined by the
previous thing.
And then we're going to say, you know, that the right in the top door.
Are cleared out because those are going to get set up here.
Okay, so just do it that way.
It's, I know it's super janky and weird again.
I'm just trying to make something real quick.
This is not again.
Please do not make worlds this way that I'm doing them.
We will be doing a lot more interesting stuff later with that.
This is just something to kind of guess going.
so,
Here we are in our tile stuff.
What we want to do here.
Say basically, we've got each of these is going to be a separate case
now, right?
And again, this is a little bit piggy code, but that's okay.
This is only happening on Startup.
There's nothing particular to worry about here.
There we go.
But basically, this is just the same code.
Here we go.
Just doing a cut-and-paste reuse as it is called quote unquote.
And so now, basically, if the tile x is 0 on the tile, why?
Is half that is going to be in effect.
We can kind of make this.
I guess we can basically just make this a much more concise case.
We can.
Basically just say if the tiled x is 0 and the tile Y is not equal to
the middle right?
Then we're going to make there be a wall there, right?
All right, that makes sense.
And this tile X.
The only thing we need to do now is say well if they're also was
supposed to be a door to the left.
Otherwise, we're going to leave it as a wall, I guess.
So.
And
Its title x equals 0.
It's going to end and there isn't supposed to be a door to the left.
Right.
And that I think, am I correct there.
Is it my correct there.
So if there's a tie left in, oh, and no, no, it's not door left or
this is very complicated.
I'm not sure.
I'm going to get this right?
Let me think about this.
So if we were going to draw a wall,
We draw a wall if tile x equals zero.
And it's not, we're in the middle because if it was in the middle, you
wouldn't draw it.
But if it's not in the middle, we'd also still draw.
If there wasn't supposed to be a drawer to the left.
Because if there's not supposed to be a draw, to the left, we need to
fill it in.
That's right.
Oh man, that's crazy.
That is just some crazy, some crazy iffing.
But I think it's actually correct.
I don't know.
Don't take my word for it.
Okay, so yeah, we'll see if that will see if it actually works.
That's that's what we'll do.
So yeah, so there's the test for the other one.
Basically, this is for the door on the right.
If there's not supposed to be a door on the right, or if it's in the
middle.
Then then we would then we would put the put the Blocker in there,
right?
Is that right?
So tile X, and
I got to think this through one more time.
In fact, I kind of almost have to make the larger tail for it.
The tile x equals 0.
We're going to make a wall.
But it also has to be the case, vet there, that we're not on that
part.
Then we'll make the wall, or if we're.
Yeah, I don't know.
I'm thinking that's based roughly.
Correct.
Let's just assume that it is.
We'll do it in testing me.
Honestly, that's that's that's hurting my brain to even think about
that.
And to the degree that I have to think about it right now.
So if there's a door to the top,
Oops.
Wait.
No.
This is how I 0.
So, this is door to the bottom.
There's not a door to the bottom, or this is not equal to Middle.
There we go.
So, that's that one.
There's are incredibly stylish door, bottom code, and then, similarly,
the tile, why?
This is our door top coming out the top and that is this and there we
go.
Oops, man.
That is some ugly-looking stuff right there.
That is some ugly-looking stuff.
Let's see if it works at all.
Probably not.
Yeah, probably not.
Of course.
It works.
A little almost worked.
It almost worked, but we've got one our door to the top.
Code is busted somehow.
What did I do here?
Let's see door top.
If tile y equals tiles, right?
- 1.
And it's not the door top.
Or tile X is not equal to.
There we go.
I forgot my not equal to there.
Hey, so there we go.
It's really surprised that worked.
But there you go.
So now we've actually got doors that only lead to where the rooms we
actually made were, which is kind of a nice thing.
So that's all good.
But basically, what we want to do now is we want to say, okay since
we've got since we've got that let's see what happens if we drop the
player actually into sort of the location more for real.
So if we actually go here now and cut this back,
Down to doing what it was doing before.
So we're only kind of drawing right around the player and I change
back to doing sort of that closing view.
So now you can imagine if the camera was locked in here, right at the
camera is like that then really the player would never actually know
that we're not storing the world outside it, right?
Because it's never there.
Never actually going to see anything other than this.
So they're just going to think that the world exists everywhere
because
Coz everywhere.
They see, it does exist but it really doesn't secretly.
Does it basically outside of that sort of area.
Now, of course, you can still see it now because we allow the camera
to kind of roam over there, but we can even fix that if we want to
know, if we were, if we were doing smooth scrolling and wanted to
allow the camera to move all the way over here.
All we would have to do is make sure that we made an apron around all
the rooms when we are basically setting the tiles so that we make sure
we actually fill out to however, far.
Or they could get to a wall.
Make sure we always have some stuff out there for.
Look at and then even that would work.
So basically there's no real downsides to storing its parsley.
You can always make sure that every where the player could have seen,
you actually set some tile data and then you're good to go.
The other thing we could do.
If you didn't even want to do that, although I think you would want to
do that.
So you could control, what was out there and make it look reasonable
is, you could also make it so that when you get, when you find that
there's nothing there, when you get to a place where there isn't
anything instead of just drawing nothing, you just draw some random
stuff that would fill it in, right, you draw in
Um, fill in stuff.
There you could do that as well.
So yeah, so now we're at the point where we've kind of got, you know,
our tile map stuff.
Seems to be working properly.
Yeah, everything seems to be going relatively smoothly.
No, real, no real issues so far.
And this is already kind of a fairly large map to walk through by my
goodness.
It takes a long time to get through 100 screens.
Oh,
My goodness.
Yeah, that is taking that is taking a while.
Oh, all right.
I'll stop walking through the world.
Now.
I will stop walking through the world.
Now this, you know, it kind of reminds me that our test code here.
Kind of reminds me of the old Adventure.
I don't know if you've ever seen that.
There's like, this old Atari 2600 game called adventure and if you've
ever seen it, but it reminds me of that because basically, like this
test,
Fix that we're doing here.
We're we're just trying to show that our tiles are working and looking
at things is what the actual shipping graphics on the old Atari 2600
games looked like?
So if you actually go look back at Adventure, it looks a lot like this
only it didn't have smooth scrolling.
It, couldn't scroll.
So it once we actually lock the camera, then it would literally look
just like this.
It was kind of crazy, but that's what games looked like back then.
And that was a very popular.
That was a famous game Adventure on the target 2600 ship with Graphics
that look
Like this, if you can imagine that for those of you who weren't there
at the time, I suppose, that's probably pretty surprising, but that
was the truth and we loved it.
I mean I played the heck out of that game.
I killed all the dragons.
I found the black dot.
Yeah.
What can you what can you do?
So anyway?
We're pretty much done with our tile map stuff now, so if we kind of
go back here and take a look at how that's working.
Hopefully everyone understands roughly.
What we did.
We just have a very simple thing here called tile map.
You can Define it to be sort of however, size.
However you want.
Now, one thing I will point out is that this is actually a little bit
inappropriate this tile size in pixels, and M, 2 pixels thing.
I'm pretty sure we don't want that anymore because the tile map knows
nothing about pixels and probably just doesn't want to.
So we probably want to do is get rid.
That and push that over here for now, basically into something that
sort of gets initialized as a separate piece, you know, like this
because that's that's just not part of the tile map.
That's not a relevant thing.
And so what I was thinking is maybe we just go ahead.
They that the the tile side and pixels is something that sort of
exists in the renderer.
It's a renderer concept.
It's not something that exists in the tilemap.
Just so everyone knows that using the tile map.
That that's not a thing in there.
That makes sense.
All of these are sort of things that are
Excuse me.
See here.
Tilemap Undeclared that we go and then this is actually the tile map,
so that's just so basically I've just pulled those out.
Right, and I'm going to make tile side and pixels, be something.
That's just an ocean in the renderer.
So once there's a renderer will think about where that needs to live.
But for now, I just kind of want to get rid of that idea entirely from
the tile map because it's really just not aspect of the tile map.
Our tile map doesn't care about pixels.
We just did all the work to make sure that it doesn't care about
pixels.
And so there's no point in its storing that as if it did care, it
should just not be an aspect of that.
So we'll pull that out and that
We're back to where we were.
Okay, so hopefully that's clear to everyone what we did.
Now.
We have a virtualized tile store.
It's the thing that we haven't done yet so I can get rid of this now
because we have done beginner sparseness.
But basically we want to sort of have another to do in here which is
real sparseness, which is basically to say that we still are storing
an array.
We're storing array of pointers to tiles.
So however, big our world is exit with them.
Height-wise, right?
You can kind of think of it.
Where's my drawing?
Where's the awesome drawings?
I do.
Okay.
There we go.
So we have our world, right?
It's 4 billion tiles by four billion tiles.
And we know that right now, essentially just randomly.
I set it to 16 by 16 chunks, right?
So they're we're doing these, so one little section of the world when
we store it Maps out to a 16 by 16, but basically what we've done is
we've said that however much part of the world, but right now we're
just talking about this part of the world is all we made.
We're doing 128 of these two of these
Chunks, right, by 128 of them, is all we could possibly store because
right off the bat, we are saying that this array.
The tile chunks array were only allocating that to be 128 by 128.
Right?
So it's an array of 128 by 128 pointers.
So we essentially have still a rectangular array, but we've just saved
a lot of space because we don't store, we just store a zero in there,
if there's nothing and then we store the pointer.
Or if there actually is something.
And, of course, that's a pretty big savings in terms of the sparseness
because, if you remember, if a tile is 4, bytes currently.
And a 16 by 16 of those is going to be 1 K.
So storing just eight bytes of a pointer.
Instead of 1 K is obviously a big savings.
Well, you know, it's a x divided by 1024.
It's it's less than 1% size.
So that's pretty great.
But we'd want to be even more sparse than that if we can because even
if we were going if you're going to try and store a whole world's
worth of that that just would be still pretty onerous.
So we're going to want to probably do.
Real sparseness.
So anywhere in the world can be represented without the giant pointer
array.
That's something that we're probably going to want to do just as an
exercise because there are sparse lookups that we can do that.
Will not be doing it that way.
So let's do one more thing to our town map.
Now, I think we could probably handle it.
Not particularly difficult.
I suspect, which is that we'd like to get Z in there.
So maybe we'll add the ability to kind of go up and down, if that
makes sense.
So, maybe we'll go ahead and say that we're going to have two levels
of up and down for the moment.
Right?
If that makes sense, will have a tile champ count.
So we'll just have like an up and a down.
I don't know why I'm doing this.
But I feel like we kind of need to have an up and down at least in
there to begin with.
Once we have a better sparseness.
This will become kind of a non-issue.
But for now, we'll have to do the array that way.
So we'll have a tile chunk count Z as well.
And then when we have our absolute tile indexes will have an absolute
tiles.
E also, right?
Now Z is a little bit different.
It's a little bit different from RX and Ry.
Because you can't see more than one of it at a time, really.
Maybe you could see two levels of it.
Sometimes, depending on how you want to do things.
But in general, you know, Z is not the same X and Y, you see big
chunks of it but Z is usually like these whole planes of play that you
go up to or down to and you're on a totally separate kind of level.
And that's the traditional way, that games work for whatever reason.
So it's kind of handled slightly, you know, just just a little bit
anyway differently.
And so, for example, in the tile chunk position, you wouldn't have a z
at all really.
Well, I guess you'd have a towel chunk.
See you would have that, but you wouldn't have a tile Z because there
is there's inside a chunk there just be one slice, right?
You'd never actually store a voxel.
You wouldn't store like a volume for it or anything, right?
So what I want to do is go ahead and add that extra layer in.
So cure when it does this, we're actually going to going to store one
more layer tile chunk count Z that will basically just have, you know,
sort of that secondary plane if you will, so then in here when we were
actually doing our lookup, so we have to kind of start to think about
that.
So when we set our tile values, we're going to do these get chunk
position for us.
And that get chunk position for us.
When we do our tile value stuff.
We're now going to always be taking one more value, which is the app
tiles e, right?
And and that's going to come in here and that's going to get passed
through to everything.
So we're going to do that.
That's really all we need to do here.
I believe we just do these sort of things where we do.
Our get tell chunk, get tile, chunk takes the extra Z.
Nothing particularly odd.
There.
We leave everything else, the same?
Again.
This tab style Z gets passed in here and can pose ABS taozi those get
passed through, then we're doing our get chunk position.
It basically just gets
Right through.
It doesn't actually it's not a virtual address, like the other things
are.
It's just the Z plane.
It's just where we are.
Accessing in the Z plane, right?
So, ABS tile.
Z, is there.
There we go.
And when we're setting the tile values, again, same thing when we set
the tile X know that, we're going to pass those through test tiles e.
And when we get the tile values again, going to pass them through.
Exactly the same way that's taozi.
Nothing again.
Just really just adding this extra coordinate on, it doesn't really
require almost any work on our part.
So tile X and tile.
Why for setting tile values on checked again, we don't actually need
them here because we're only inside the tile map.
Once we get down to this point.
Same thing here, get tile value and checked.
We're don't need Z's once we're at that point.
So really the only time we actually need the Z is, is
We are actually dealing with stuff.
That is actually getting a tile chunk itself.
So getting the tile chunks that actually requires a z now, and that's
also going to have to be bounced check, because if you try to get
something outside of the legal range map, chunk count Z, then we're
going to prevent you from doing that.
And now we just need one more access or which basically allows us to
pack those guys in there.
So again, just like we did before you can kind of see
See, the universal access pattern.
I talked about this on a previous stream.
Basically, you have the X, which is the, the one that adds just one as
you go inside our memory.
Because again, I don't know, if you remember the diagram, I drew a
sort of that universal access pattern memory is One D.
So, we just have a big old line, right?
Oh my God, that's the worst lie.
Never.
Let's try something slightly.
Oh my God.
I don't even know what that's supposed to be.
So this is memory.
It's one-dimensional, right?
It just has one index into it.
But now, we've got something that is
All right, we've got essentially a cube that restoring here, right?
We've got a cube and so we've got an X.
We've got a y, and we've got a z, and we're trying to store this cube
in here.
So, the way we're doing it is
Slicing it like this.
First, we go along X.
So, this is X, right?
We pack X, we pack that line of X into their.
Then we go up 1 in y, and we pack the next row of X in there.
So, now here's another X, but it's the X that's one up in y, right?
Xxxxx when we get to, the end of all of these, X's we go up one in Z
and then we pack another row of x's by Y and then by Z again, right?
So what that means?
Is is every time we go up 1 and X, we are only moving one forward in
memory.
But if we go up 1 and Z, we're moving one whole X count, one whole
length of X upwards.
And if we go up in Z, removing one whole giant planes were so removing
wise number of x's forwards, right?
So, that's exactly what this math is here.
It's saying that the Z is going to be the chunk count.
Y times a chunk context.
That's how far.
Even Z how far you move in, why is just a chunk context?
And how much fire moving X is just the X, right?
And that's that packing that packs.
A three-dimensional thing into a two-dimensional thing and that is
exactly what we are doing there.
Okay, so,
Let's take a look here, get tile value unchecked.
Once we already have a touch hunk.
I don't know why I did that.
That was not necessary.
Sceptile chunk, those don't eat it because they've already got the
chunk.
Once you've got the chunk.
You don't need Z.
So, there we go.
And now we have we're at our five minute warning, of course, so it's
good that we're kind of wrapping this up here, our ABS tile Z.
So we'll get our tell value got a real ex Rel.
Why, what is the problem?
Get?
Tyler value.
That's supposed to be not too.
Yeah.
Why does that take a test LZ?
I have no idea.
This was just that was just me being super sloppy, when it's anything
that already has the chunk, doesn't need the Z.
So I have no idea why I was adding those.
That was just dumb.
And so now, we're always gonna set, basically, our ABS tiles E20 at
the moment.
So that we can reproduce what we had before that makes sense and then
get tell value.
Get tell Val, you know, overloaded function.
Yeah, that's right.
So, we need to draw whatever our players Z is at the moment.
So there we go.
ABS to XY and z and now we should hopefully, unless I made a mistake,
be exactly where we were before, but now we have the ability to go up
and down if we would like to.
So we can go ahead and do that.
If we want, we can create essentially something if we want to, that
would be a stairwell, right?
And so I'm going to again go ahead and just continue the madness here.
I don't know if a lot of time to quite finish this, but what I will do
is I will say that if we decide on this stuff here when we
A random Choice.
Let's do a random Choice out of three.
If the random Choice equals 2, then if the random Choice equals 1,
we'll do it like this.
And then down here.
I'll do the same thing if they're in Choice equals to or if if the
random Choice equals 1.
Like that.
And so what I'm going to do is say that if the random Choice equals to
the ab style Z.
Basically if AB style Z equals 0, then I'm going to set ABS, tau is
equal to 1 so this will be a little go up from there.
And otherwise if AB style Z was already equal to 1, then it will equal
to 0.
So I'll just toggle whichever one.
It is on that random choice to write.
And so up here.
I will do the same.
Thing.
I'll say if random choice is to, then we'll sort of take a look.
This will be going up.
This is this is going to have a door up sort of thing.
And this is going to have a door down if that makes sense.
Yeah.
So whichever one it was that would be lets see, your up this false and
door down equals false.
And so then the same thing happens, here that happened before door.
Up equals door down, or I should actually say that.
What happens here is is, we don't actually know which order these kind
of have to go in.
It was that I'd make some kind of error with my indentation.
I feel like I did.
It's telling me that I did.
Yeah, there it is.
And I need to kind of remember what the ABS tells you is for the
player Hazard for that thing as we go through.
So, what I need to do here is say, basically if there was a door up,
Right else not.
So what I need to do here is say if there was a door up, then there's
going to be a door down next time and not a door up.
And if there was a door down right then there's going to be a door up
next time.
This that.
And finally, if there was neither been, there's neither, right?
So I believe that would work.
I'm not sure.
But now what we should see is I should be able to get somewhere and
there shouldn't be an exit to the room.
Yeah.
Well, actually, I don't know why that's there.
That's a bit odd what's going on there?
What did I, what did I make?
I made, I've made an error in the code.
We're basically at the Q and A.
So I'm going to stop playing with this for a minute, but I want to see
what my error is.
Random Choice equals one screen, X screen why random Choice equals one
screen, X screen, y AB, Stiles, equals 0 your
In that case, door up door down.
So why did we actually get a different thing there?
I don't actually know.
Oh, well, it could be, no, we should never have that case happen.
We should never have a case where there's a door, right?
And then we don't go right.
Am I?
You know what I'm saying about that.
So that's just kind of busted.
Why did that happen?
Let's, let's look at that again, which.
Which, which I want to take a sorry about that.
That I want to actually see why that's wrong.
Like why we can't get there if that makes sense.
You know, I'm saying to you.
So that was just the second room, right?
That was the second room.
So let's take a look at what happens in the debugger.
There we go.
Probably just something that I spam down because I was going too
quickly.
But so here we are.
We're going to come in on our second room.
Right?
Our screen index is 1 on the second room.
We'd pick the random Choice, the random choice is to.
So we're going to have our door down equal to true and our other
doors.
Should not have any other doors, correct?
What's our door left door?
Right?
Door, top door, bottom.
Drawer down up or down.
Okay.
So basically there shouldn't have been a door, right?
So what happened is our door, write code, broken or something.
Do you know what I'm saying?
Like, why did we ever?
Why did we have that happen on the thing?
We should always.
Be having walls basically everywhere.
So when we get there, let's I guess go ahead and and see if we can get
to basically the middle of things so tile.
Why what is tiles for height?
Divided by 2 tiles for height over 2 is 4.
So, let's go to 4 and see why we get that door there.
Okay.
Now we're at four.
So we come through.
Here, let's take a look at what happens.
We say the tile value should be too because the tile x is 0 and we
don't have a door left.
You know, I just realized.
Why didn't we have a door left set?
For this guy.
Do you know what I'm saying?
Because it should have set door left equal to door, right?
And the previous room had a door, right?
Something's busted.
Oh, that's my awesome.
Super type.
Oh, yeah.
I was trying to set door up.
Door down equal to false.
I believe here.
Oh wait.
No.
No, that's, that's the right door, right?
And or top or supposed to be false.
Yeah.
No, that's correct.
That wasn't a typo.
So I want to see what happened there.
Why didn't our door carryover?
I'm obviously just being dumb today and I apologize for that.
So we'll use up a little bit of Q&A, but I often go a little bit over
just because if there's a bug at the end, I don't like to leave a bug
in there.
So I'd like to go ahead and find it.
So, let's see here.
Random choice.
Our random choice on screen, index 0, huh are random choice on screen,
index 0 was actually to have a door up.
So that means that there should be no doors.
Oh my God, I know what happened.
It basically went up and down and over Road itself.
Oh, man.
Yeah, that's right.
I forgot to do.
If you already went up you can't go down again.
Ha ha.
So it basically just went up and down and overwrote the room that was
previously there before.
Oh, that's funny.
That's funny makes perfect sense, but that's funny.
Okay.
So basically yeah, what we want to do here is say
That our random choice is going to basically be yet slightly
different.
We're going to say is if door up or door down.
So if we were previously, if we had previously gone up or down right,
then we are not going to allow the next move.
The next move has to be lateral.
So we're going to eliminate the option for it to ever do.
What it just did, which is go up and down again.
Let me see if that makes a little more sense.
Yeah, okay, so that's much better.
So now we're locked in a room, right?
And we need to be able to go up or down.
And so, really, all I wanted to do, there was just say, like, okay,
you know, you know, I don't know.
There's some fixed location.
So if tile x equals, you know, 6 and tile, y equals 6 or something
like this, or maybe this is 10 or something like that, right?
If if we're at that tile or something.
Then, you know, tile value equals.
I guess.
Three, you know, if you're up.
This is not a particularly good way to do this.
But if door up is, you know, is set.
Then it'll be 3.
And if door down is set then it will be four.
And then all I was really going to do is say, okay, if you know, if at
the time that the player moves on to something like this sort of
thing, if, you know, when the player moves on to it, well, you know, I
don't really want to do that quite yet.
So we'll just draw them and we
Actually, we'll handle will actually handle ladders starting next
week.
That'll be, that'll be a good thing to do.
So, all I want to do now is just make sure we draw them.
Basically will do if tile ID.
Use greater than 2.
We will set that gray level to be that.
So now we should at least see our our doorway, there.
It is very exciting.
But of course, when we step on it, we can't actually go into it
because it's not a legal place to stand at the moment, but there we
go.
So, I'm going to end it there.
And then tomorrow, well, I guess it'll be Monday will actually
Implement going up and down just we can do that.
And then maybe we'll look at storing things sparsely in a slightly
different.
Way, I'm not sure so that we can have kind of arbitrary ups and downs
in our world without having to only have two planes.
Which is what we have currently.
All right, now it's time for Q&A.
So I'm going to go ahead and start the Q&A filter.
So, please go ahead and preface your questions with q: and I will take
a look at them.
Please try to keep them to things that we've programmed so far.
Let's not talk about stuff that we're going to do in the future or
other things unrelated to what we're doing with.
Try to keep it on the code because
this is the on-topic Q&A.
If you want to ask questions random, like what do you think about such
and such a language or those sorts of questions?
Do those come early to a stream, some time and we do all sorts of
questions before the stream.
So that's, you know, come a little bit before the scheduled time 15
minutes or so.
If you want to ask those kind of questions, and we will handle those
questions then.
Do you want to go over demorgan's laws or k-maps to simplify those
Boolean Expressions, you know, we can sort of point to them.
But to be honest, I never do that sort of stuff.
It's very rare that I actually do that so you can see
The thing that he's talking about here, if you want to go to
Wikipedia, basically, there's a set of things that say that a certain
binary expression is equal to another binary expression.
So for example, like this is a, you know, not A and B is the same as
not, a or not B, right.
They equal the same, they evaluate to the same thing.
And so, you know, if you have kind of hairy Expressions, such as the
ones that I was writing, which are kind of crazy.
Which are these sorts of things here and you want to start trying to
make these a little more simplistic.
You can do that.
I tend rarely to actually do that in practice.
I almost never do.
Usually, what I end up doing is pulling things out into simpler.
I usually let the compiler, do that work for the most part and I pull
things out into names, like I pull things out.
What if we were actually writing, if this code was code, we were going
to keep and not just Tesco where I was kind of just like doing things
out.
Typically, what I do is I actually just make boolean's up here.
A things.
I am on left side or am on right side and then I go from there because
typically the compiler will do these sorts of things for you.
And I don't find that there's a whole lot of reason to actually do
them myself.
I tend to try to prefer to make the Expressions as clear as possible
linguistically.
And so when I go through and look at something like this and go I want
to simplify it.
I tend to focus on the linguistic simplification and not on trying to
simplify the number of Boolean operations that actually occur.
That makes sense.
But if you were interested in that kind of thing, it is a good thing
to mention.
It's a good thing too.
Read about.
So I would say yes as they basically said, you might want to take a
look at this.
Or I don't know if truth tables, has a good documentation.
Yeah.
So a truth table is basically something you do where you basically
make you sort of make a like a almost, like you would a spreadsheet
where you have all your conditions and you start to say, whether, you
know, if this condition is true in this condition is true.
What's the end result of my expression, right?
That's another thing that you can look at as well.
But again, I don't really tend to use those things in practice all
that much.
Do you have emacs commands with Visual Studio?
I have trouble trying to get this to work with Visual Studio, newer
versions.
No, I don't have any max commands with Visual Studio.
My visual studio is just using the stock installation.
I don't, I don't actually have it bound to anything.
Have you already decided?
What prng algorithm you're going to use?
I think so, but I'm not 100% positive, but I think so.
We'll see you when we get there.
As you put the time UPS in three dimensions, could this be related to
a voxel octree algorithm?
Probably not.
And the reason for that is that voxel octrees are optimized for when
you want to look at all three dimensions in the same way.
So an octree is very unbiased.
It's basically, if you're storing things in an octree, basically, what
an octree is for those of you who don't know.
An octree is something, which basically says I have a
three-dimensional volume.
And what I'm going to do is I'm going to start dividing that volume
into eight sections, right?
So you can imagine basically planes cutting my volume.
I don't know if you can understand this this diagram kind of like into
a Rubik's Cube, you know, kind of way.
So that now I you know, every time I want to I take that volume.
I divide it and I end up with eight cubes that are all 18.
With the size of the original Cube.
And if I
To I can then make that, you know, again another division for any one
of those cubes that I want to make higher resolution.
I do it again and so on.
Now, those are interesting algorithms, when, you know, that you're
filling the space relatively uniformly in all three dimensions.
Meaning there isn't a bias in one of the dimensions that isn't getting
filled as much or something like that.
It makes sense to have something like an actuary and similarly, it
makes that sound actually when you're viewing things fully in three
dimensions.
So you're as likely to be looking at things in Z, as you are as an
extra and why, and so on, we don't really have that circumstance for
our game.
We're looking at a game World typically and we may, depending on how
we decide to do it.
I don't know how our game will shake out.
But at best, you know, will only be looking at probably one or two
slices of the world.
Like maybe if we have the, you know, the guys here and there are sort
of like a cutaway
And you can sort of see what's maybe below you a little bit or
something that you're looking down into a lower part of the dungeon or
something like that, you know, maybe we're looking at two or three
slices tops.
So that's, you know, three levels of Z or something like that.
That might be getting viewed.
Whereas we're always looking at, at least 17 wide by 9 wide in the
other two dimensions and there's a lot more fill in those Dimensions.
Like, we typically won't have a 17, High stack in.
Z, you know, we'll probably have a 10 high stack and see where
dungeons are something at most, whereas we're going to have thousands
wide Stacks potentially in X & Y, depending on how big the Overworld
map isn't that sort of stuff.
And so an octree is not a very good choice, as a way to partition our
world.
I don't think because it's sort of doing a lot more work to get you
benefits that we will never realize, you know, an octree is more like
if you're making Minecraft or something where you're looking and
you're your
Trying to build the world that you can that you're doing a lot of up
and down to reversals on.
You're looking at big mountains and stuff like this where you're
trying to have kind of that fully 3D thing.
But for a 2-D game, they just don't make a whole lot of sense.
So we will probably not be looking at a voxel octree type structure
because it wouldn't really do much for us.
It basically be giving us a lot of power that we would never use and
there's always a cost of that.
Is there a reason of Chunk size to be a power of 2 there is and that
is because the thing that we were doing the trick that we were doing
for the lookup is doesn't work if it's not a power of 2, so if you
look at the way we're doing the lookup, it's here.
Right?
What we're doing is we're using a shift in mask to separate to split
out the values and so we can't do that.
If the chunk size isn't a power of 2.
Now, that doesn't mean that the chunk size should stay a power of two
because it may be that this operation just isn't that.
Sting and we can do it with a regular divided.
Because if you think about it, if we wanted to do this, all we're
doing is essentially doing a divide and remainder.
This is a divide and remainder operation.
And so
Divide and remainder.
If you think about it, right?
Right now we have a 428 is our is our number, right?
We set it so that the 16 by 16 so that the bottom part is for the top
Parts, 28, what we're doing when we do, the shift is, we're taking the
whole number part, which is the 28th.
And that's our chunk, right?
Index.
And we're taking the remainder, which is the bottom part and that for
is becoming the tile inside that chunk.
Right?
What we could do, if we
We wanted to have an arbitrary one is we could just do a divide and
remainder, right?
So, instead of doing shift to get this guy and mask to get this guy.
What we could actually do is to get this guy, we could do divide, we
do / the dim, right?
And that would get us the top part and it could be any size we wanted.
So we could, if we wanted to have it be aligned to our screen size, we
could do, you know, / 17, let's say,
And then we could do mod by 17 and that would get us our our tile
index.
So we could if we if it turns out that storage is the most important
thing and then this operation doesn't actually have to be that fast.
We could very well go with a scheme like that.
And that's something that ends up being a determination to be made
when we're actually implementing the engine and performance tuning, it
and stuff like that.
The important thing is at this stage of the game is to try and not do
things that would preclude us from making those choices.
And I don't think we have really done anything like that yet.
When do you use Define a set of global variables entirely up to you?
Really?
There is no particular, like, right or wrong answer to that question.
But there are actual differences between them and it's important to be
aware of those differences.
So, that you make the choice that you want.
Obviously, any time that you have something that has to be to take
parameters.
It has to be a pound of fine, certainly, but if you're talking about
something like this, like, pi32, that could be either, write it.
That.
Or it could be defined like this, right?
Hmm.
You could do either those two things.
I
I personally pretty much always use pound of fines because I don't
really see any reason, not to, but you do lose one thing.
There you gain, one thing which is that it doesn't have a type.
Meaning you could for certain circumstances.
Like, let's say to give a very straightforward example.
Let's say you have something like that.
Before can be used in pretty much any circumstance.
Now, it doesn't matter.
It's not signed or unsigned.
For example, it's just for whereas if I did something like this, now,
it really does.
Of type, which means that the UN if it's used in a circumstance where
a un 32 causes something bad to happen.
I can't use this anymore.
I have to cast it or something like that.
Right?
So the downside, I'm sorry.
The upside of using a defiant kind of funny is that there is no type
to the thing that you're doing.
It's just the expression and it gets inserted in there directly.
Right?
However, that could also be a downside if you want it to have a type
meaning if you want it to only be used in a circle.
Stance where you have a un 32, sometimes you can do that.
Like in this case where we've got a floating-point suffix.
It kind of gives it a type so you can do it that way.
But sometimes you can't do that.
Like, if you wanted the thing for to have a particular type, it's hard
to make that happen.
If you want it to only be an 8-bit type for some unknown reason,
that's a place where the doing Global variable of can help you because
it means that it does have a specific type.
So if you wanted that, that's the reason why you might do it that way,
right?
There aren't a whole lot of other reasons, but you know your mileage
may vary.
Why are you using inline in variables?
I have no idea what that means.
I'm sorry sub lose.
We are not using inline and variables.
There are no variables declared within line.
So I'm not sure what you mean by that.
Why don't you spit flags for doors and such.
Well, the reason is because we haven't gotten the town map storage
yet.
We're just using that number just to be totally clear.
This number is, is just a total.
So this this will be, you know,
Real structure for a tile right now.
We're not, we're just using that number to test the tile map stuff,
but we have no idea how we want to start tiles yet.
That's going to be completely determined on dependent on what we want
in our game.
So so it's not going to be a bit flag or you went 3-2 or anything like
that.
It's gonna be something more complicated.
Why would you prefer an array of tile chunks instead of a door entity
which links to a tile map?
So the reason is because we may want to view them.
So, like I said, I wanted our world to be consistent and to feel
consistent.
So I'll show you the difference between the two cases.
So what the person was suggesting is when we have a door, right?
Why don't we just make that door point to some other location that you
go to when you enter the door, right?
Instead of making their be a
Metal tile map where you go up or down, based on that, right?
And the example is or and then another one would be, you know, why do
I have a door with tile chunks on either side, where we basically?
Can walk through it?
Why don't?
I just have it so that the tile map basic just has a thing there and
then the other one has a matching thing, right?
And they just teleport between each other, right?
Why not do that.
So why not just use teleporting when you walk onto something?
Instead of actually make it continuous?
Tell chunk world.
The answer is for two reasons.
The simplest one is that I want to be able to do things anytime.
I want that involve a more complex display.
Of the world.
So for example, if we wanted to zoom out on the world for some reason
in the game and show a higher, a larger window on the world.
This scheme doesn't work right, because as soon as you try to show
more than one room at a time, now, you actually need to know where
they are spatially related to each other.
You can't just have teleporters that teleport between them as if they
were doors and the player doesn't know the difference, right?
So there's that.
The same is true, the exact for the exact same reason.
It's true for
Down as well because like I said, we may want to have a circumstance
where like you're walking up here on something, right?
And there's a hole in the floor and you can see down below you to the
lower level.
Tilemap again, having a teleporter is not going to help here because
in fact there isn't actually a connection between those you can't
actually get there like you may not be able to walk down there.
You may just see it and then the the actual way you get down.
There is like somewhere else, right?
So we always want to be able to query the whole world consistently, so
we can show things.
Similarly.
We want to know.
Some stuff, for example, we may want to do things that involve the
geometry of the world.
Like let's say just for give you a very simple example.
Let's say that we wanted to have something that breaks through walls.
So for example, let's say we want to implement a boss monster who can
shoot through walls and they'd make it, they bore a hole in the wall.
Well, that's incredibly difficult to do here because when they bore
our world, a thing in this wall, you have no idea where that was
supposed to go.
You would have to annotate it or something and say, what was supposed
to go or you'd have to
Search for the nearest portal, figure out where that portal goes and
assume that the things next to it are that, right?
So it's really limiting to do this.
You never really want to do this.
If you can avoid it teleporting, as a means of moving somewhere in
Geometry.
That isn't really, a Teleport is usually bad.
The only time you want to do teleporting as if it's actually
teleporting.
If there's a portal here that's supposed to go to some totally random
portion of the world.
That's a perfectly good case for teleporting and we may well have
those but you never want to teleport for something that's actually
geometric movement because then it constrains your game design and all
these ways that are kind of not that good, right?
The another example would be sound, let's say I'm in this room and I
want to hear the fact that there's a boss monster in this other room.
Well, it's pretty easy to propagate sound, right?
And so like if the monster was walking here and I was standing right
here and I'm listing through this wall, right?
Let's say, in fact, there's no door in the wall.
Maybe it's maybe it's like a solid thing and there's the boss monster
here and I'm here.
Well, I want to be able to propagate that sound through the wall.
Can't do it.
If my whole system is based on Magic portals because I have no idea
how these rooms are connected.
So hopefully that gives you some set a good set of reasons of why you
typically want things to be geometric and be able to query them.
I very geometric way and so our tile chunks are a way of virtualizing
the world so that we can still always query it geometrically if we
want to, but we can also make it be very huge and sprawling and not
have to worry about making it be one giant array.
Are you following Robert C?
Martin rules?
Sorry.
I have no idea who Robert C Martin is or what his rules are.
So I suspect we probably are not, but I do not know what those are.
Are we planning to load/unload the tile chunks on demand or will the
entire world map stay in memory.
I'm thinking, it'll probably stay in memory, but we could unload and
load them.
I don't know what you'll notice is, it would be trivial for us, to do
load and unload, because really all we have to do here.
We've basically set ourselves up for Success.
They're right here.
If the tile chunk were not found, we could page it in right here, if
we wanted to.
Now, that's there are reasons why you don't quite want to do that,
exactly that way.
But because of stall,
And stuff.
So we do something a little more complicated if we were going to page
and page out, but you can basically see that paging Paige in and out
would be pretty much free and when you did the page in here, you could
just go find the least, recently used tile chunk and page that out.
So you could change.
It would literally take like 30 minutes to change what we've got here
into a demand paging scheme, but I don't know if we'll ever actually
need to do that.
How much of this code will get used in the final procedural?
Code of the game?
It looks very complicated to make any changes here at linguistically.
Are you talking about?
Are you talking about this?
This code here?
That just does are like none of this.
This is getting deleted as soon as we actually start doing World
Generation, but I just needed something to spam stuff out into the
world so we could test our tile map code.
So this is just garbage.
It's complete garbage.
If it helps, I can put it to do there for you.
Because this is, this is total garbage.
We're we won't be using any of it.
Are we planning on making the time?
I've layered Graphics.
Physics logic, Etc.
Well, I don't know if it'll be layered.
Perhaps in the way that you might be implying that in terms of like
like we won't be starting to separate tilemap chunks or anything for
the different systems, but we will be having data in the tilemap
that's designed for use by different systems.
Like the graphics part will be different from the physics part.
Probably.
I just, don't think they will necessarily be separate.
They'll probably
we be kind of merged together.
Am I listening to something or is it just to hang them?
Like it's just to hang the microphone.
Well, it also so that I can hear our game sound once we actually start
playing more sounds in the game.
Why are primitive declared like bull 42 and in unit 3 2 instead of
just Bool indent the reason is because basically I like to insulate
myself a little bit from the platform in the sense that I like to
basically Define my own types so that I can switch to switch them.
Whenever I want to.
That is sort of a holdover from the old days.
When these didn't used to be defined in, see, you didn't used to be
able to have types and see that where a particular size.
So you always had to do it.
And that's where I got in that habit, and I don't really like, putting
the underscore key on there.
So, at this point, it's just basically the save me from typing
underscore T, but
For bools, the reason I don't use the actual dual type is the actual
Bull type has semantics.
I don't like, I actually want my Bool to just be an integer so that it
doesn't have to convert to true or false all the time, which can have
performance implications.
So that's why I don't use the pool type, but the other types of just
force of habit, really?
Because nowadays you could just use these and be okay.
Let's see.
A lot of questions that are not related to the programming.
So I am skipping them.
If we're using sparseness because we're worried about the size of the
tile map.
Would it make sense to go further and think about compression?
It might, again, that's something we'll have to determine I suspect.
It probably won't because I suspect that the sizes of our world will
not be that big compared to the sizes of the art assets.
And so it compressing the tilemap probably wouldn't really get us very
far because basically our assets are probably going to be huge because
we have so many bitmaps and stuff.
So I suspect it wouldn't make sense.
But if it turned out that the tile map was creating memory pressure
that we were worried about then.
Yes.
How computational intensive is as far as storage and does it become
more intensive as you get more sparse.
So yeah, the problem.
Basically, the trade-off with the sparse storage is specifically that
there is a computational complexity there that you are paying.
Because if you think about what happens and this is a very good
question.
I'm really glad that you asked that question.
Thank you ride car to basically what happens with Spar storage is.
If you think about it, if we have a, if we want to do a 4 billion by 4
billion,
Old.
And we were able to just flat-out store it, right?
And one of the kind of one of the sad things is if you actually think
about this a little more carefully.
You realize that
I could actually just store it if we had more control over the memory
management unit.
We could actually just map a range of memory that was reserved, but
not committed and then only commit it.
Once we actually go to use it but it is a lot of reasons why that's
very hard to do and it's not very portable.
So really OS is our lousy is really the reason why we can't just
flat-out use a regular accessing team.
It's
It's really lame and I hate it.
But this is the truth.
And so maybe, like on the Raspberry Pi, we literally will just be able
to do a straight mapping.
It wouldn't be 4 billion by for building because I don't think that's
64 a bit.
But if we ever do a home brew, that's actually a 64-bit.
We could do a straight mapping of 4 billion by 4 billion and then only
fill in the parts we want.
And then we would pay almost no computational cost for it.
So OS is our lousy Windows kernel doesn't care about, you doesn't
care.
About you.
Is one reason for this for this whole thing, but basically, what we
have to do is we have to implement that virtualization.
Ourself and so, to implement that virtualization instead of just
letting the mmu, do it, what we have this 4 billion by 4 billion
thing.
We would like to be able to just do that direct access and the direct
access would just be, you know, basically a multiply and add and a
memory look up, right.
It would be y times with plus X or if it's a little more complicated
now, it's Z times.
W Times h.
Plus X, this is a constant.
So you're basically talking about to multiplies to ads and a memory.
Look up, extremely efficient.
You're never going to notice it, right?
That's how you would get the tile instead.
What we have to do now is we have to do that shift, and masking to
figure out where we're getting it.
We got to go pull that tile out, see if it's there and if it is there,
then we do the access and that's a lot more expensive.
Right?
I mean, you're probably talking about literally 10x the work because
this is just so simple to do that.
Even though there's not a whole lot to do in the
As far as storage, it's still going to be no matter what we Implement.
It's still going to be a bit of nastiness.
So yes, the reason that we do it is because we want to have large
worlds that don't have restrictions on their dimensions in sort of,
like, they can be kind of long and skinny, if they want to be in that
sort of thing.
And so we are paying a real cost there and the better we do at
sparsity the the more closely we mapped the sparseness to of the world
to the storage, the more expensive that sparseness does become.
And so, it is a real cost and it is something worth thinking about.
I'm hoping it's not going to hurt us too bad on this particular game,
but it's definitely the case.
And so yeah, it would be way better if you didn't have to do it.
Let's see.
Let me I'm just going to Quick.
There's a lot of questions.
I'm going to see.
Maybe take five more minutes just to see if there's any other
questions.
That are about what we were working on the tile map.
Let's see.
So, we say the tile sparsely, but every room is saved, should rooms be
created, only when the player comes closer to them.
So I kind of answered this on a previous stream, but I'll mention it
again because there's something that you should understand.
This is a very fundamental Concept in programming actually to
understand, and that is the concept of best case, worst case.
So, let me just take a minute because it's exactly what you're asking
about.
I want to take a minute to describe best.
First as worst case, and why you have to care about the difference
between those two?
so,
A lot of times people make the mistake of trying to optimize for their
best case, but really, what you mostly want to do for game development
is you want to optimize for your worst case.
What does that mean?
Well, I'll give you a simple example from first person shooters
because these make this is sort of a good example of when you care
about it.
Let's say, I am making a game.
That's a first person shooter.
And I'm talking about a time.
When the player is here and they're pointing this direction.
This is a top-down View, and there's a wall there, looking right at
the wall.
So the thing that they're going to view, right?
Is this the in their first person view?
This is looking straight.
Ahead, here's the little gun.
The thing that they're going to view is a wall, right?
And somebody looks at this and goes there's all this stuff back here
in this other room that's behind the wall.
Whatever.
And there's you know, there's all this stuff.
There's people walking around and I'm like, wow, we're spending a lot
of time because we rendered all the stuff that was behind the guy only
to then draw a wall that was behind, you know, other stuff is behind
the wall.
The only to draw this wall that you can't see any of it.
Right?
Wouldn't it be nice?
Nice to write some inclusion code that says, oh, I'm looking at this
wall.
So I shouldn't draw any of this stuff.
I should just skip it and draw the wall, right?
Well, that's a perfectly reasonable thing to do.
But what you have to think about is the fact that a couple seconds
later, right?
The player moves over and they're looking through a doorway into that
same room.
Like here's the doorway.
So they move over this way and they're looking into the doorway,
right?
And now they're seeing everything that's in that room.
Right?
So basically, all you've done is save a little bit of overdrawn.
This case, if you spent a lot of time doing that optimization, right?
And you have to be aware that
You're essentially doing here is, you are optimizing for your best
case.
Your best case is staring at a wall where you can call out the rest of
the room.
Your worst case is going to be something like the guy is standing on a
veranda and looking out over an entire like planet and there's like
mountains in the background and a giant Sun that speaking out and
trees.
All this stuff and tons of people walking around in here.
That's that's your worst case because there's nothing including
anything in here, right?
And so you kind of need to focus on this which is this thing here when
you're talking about, how you're going to optimize, you have to talk
about like lots of level of detail and things that you're going to
have to do that.
Can't just be about looking for the one time that you were staring at
a wall and going.
Oh, I can really optimize that case and get the frame rate up because
it never matters what your best case framerate is the player doesn't
care.
What your best.
Freight case frame rate is they care what your worst case framerate is
they care?
When you come out here and you look at this and everything falls
apart.
It all goes pear-shaped and you're super slow.
Right.
So, how does that apply here?
Well, basically, what's happening is let's say in our game.
We want to have destructible environments or whatever.
Right?
So I've got this room, the thing that I was just talking about.
Let's say, we want to have a boss monster that breaks through walls,
right?
So, I've got this room and I've created it, right?
And I've done this thing.
And now we know that sometimes there's monsters, the maybe writing
boss - there's just monsters that can shoot through a wall.
And now the wall is destroyed, right?
Well, if you base your entire scheme, the way that you're getting your
storage efficiency or
Ever is that rooms only exist?
When the player walks into them, then what do you do?
When you start modifying the rooms, you've got to store that data
somewhere.
So now you've got a case where every time there is one of those
monsters than it does the break through the wall thing.
Now, you've got a store those rooms and you're not storing the other
rooms.
What that means is in the worst case where you have a world filled
with those monsters that are destroying things.
You've now gone from having to store, no rooms have to restore almost
all the rooms because you got to store all of that damage that
occurred there and think about it.
Adding thing on top of that you will say you want to write in
footsteps.
Say you want to have people be able to burn things, say you want them
to be able to push things around.
Say, you want to be able to have them to create new trees with a
spell, whatever, you've gone from again.
You're focusing on the best case, which is the case where rooms don't
get modified.
And that's not the case I care about.
I care about our worst case.
I want to make sure this game works well for games for what, when in
the game design, we're going to allow the player to have a lot of
mutability to have rooms.
A lot of effects on them to a lot of things that happen in them.
That's really more what I'm concerned about.
So I want to start by saying, let's focus on that.
Now, if we get to the end of the game and we find that there's just
that could never happen, like you just don't ever change the geometry
room hardly ever then, then maybe it would be a good case to start
thinking about that.
But I don't want to design the engine up front around the best case
because then it will all fall apart.
If we decide that the design actually needs that worst case, so, I'm
focusing on this for now and we can always optimize later.
If we find that actually our game is mostly in the best case scenario.
Let's see.
Are you worried about memory leaks yet, or do you think we answered
this question yesterday?
See?
How could we have a memory leak?
We haven't allocated any memory.
We can't have a memory.
Like, right.
So I'm not sure what that actually means.
We're putting all of our stuff.
Our world map is in permanent storage.
We will flush that permanent storage overdone.
So we can't, we literally can't have a memory leak yet.
So it would be kind of crazy to worry about it.
Something that literally cannot happen yet.
So, no, I'm definitely not worried about memory leaks.
Arteries, bad.
I see places where you could use them, but don't know.
I use Turner's.
They're totally fine.
Sometimes I just think they're a little harder to read.
But but no, I in fact, we've already used turn reason the code in
certain places.
I believe.
So attorneys are totally fine.
If you want to use them, go for it.
I do use them fairly frequently.
Let's see.
Okay, getting to the end here.
Why is it not possible to save the full map?
But I think this will be the last question.
Why is it not possible to save the full map megatexture did this to
you didn't it?
So the answer is, we could save the full map, but we couldn't keep it
in memory.
So for example, Mega texture is a good example.
Mega texture would not fit in memory most of the time like the whole
point in mega texture is your paging it in and out from disk, right?
So basically, assuming that we want our map to fit in a reasonable
amount of memory, we
Can't we have to store its parsley and and also just we just don't
want to waste all that space for the most part, saving things where
there isn't anything just seems kind of wasteful in general.
But yeah, if you want to do megatexture, you're talking about an off
disk scheme.
So that's kind of saying like, okay.
We've got a 4 billion by four billion thing, right?
And so if you wanted to save that, let's see how big that would be.
I mean, you even that you wouldn't be able to really save the whole
thing, right?
So that's
Four times ten.
Oops, for x 1024 x 1024 times 24 equals this.
And that's a squared.
So that's that big, that's how big that is.
And now if you want to know that in say terabytes, we can divided by
1024.
Oops.
That's no good.
So well actually just going to do this in gigabytes.
So that's 4 GB by 4 GB, right?
Would that would that be an accurate statement?
So I think is that correct?
Yeah, so it's basically 16 times 4.
So this would be 64 GB.
I believe to store 1 d word per tile which are probably going to want
to store a lot more than that.
But even if you just started one, d word for tile, that would be 64
GB.
I believe I'm doing that math correctly.
So basically 64 GB.
Nobody has that much memory in their machine these days, eventually,
then maybe they will, but not right.
Now, so you'd basically be talking about storing 64 gigabytes of data
on disk, and then paging it in and out.
You'd probably try to compress it.
May be on disc as well.
I'm not sure.
You'd have to store 64 GB.
You got the page it in, since it's procedurally, generated.
That means you would be writing 64 gigabytes of data, at startup of
procedurally generated stuff.
How long does it take to to write 64 GB?
Well, I think hard drives right at something like 500 megabytes a
second.
That's two seconds per gigabyte.
So you're talking about
Two minutes of startup time.
Just to write your game world to disk, just not looking promising,
right?
So so I think it's pretty much safe to say.
You're never going to want to do this in a procedurally generated
game.
You really do not want to store the full map.
If it's going to be something large, you want the sparseness because
we're not going to actually have a 4 billion by four billion world
because the the player could never walk through it.
It's going to be something much smaller.
So basically, you want to just focus on storing what we actually use
and not storing all the rest of it.
So we don't have this huge data management problem that we don't
really need to solve that makes sense.
All right, so I think that's it for today.
I think that is about it.
Am I wearing my earphones backwards today?
Yes, I am.
I actually am doing that.
Oh, and that's right.
I forgot.
Someone was just mentioned on stream when I did that math.
I actually totally forgot that we have multiple planes to, right?
So it wouldn't be just, it's not just for building my farm.
It's 4 billion by forbidding Muhammad.
Easy slices.
We wanted as well, right?
If we weren't storing its parsley.
Right, so it's going to be, it's going to be 4 GB.
It's going to be.
Yeah, it's going to be way bigger than that.
In fact, it's going to be 4, x, 1024 x, 1024 1024 and yeah, I
couldn't, I forgot to do the gigabyte squared.
So that's even the wrong calculation.
I did that calculation wrong.
So this is how many tiles there are across we square that to get the
total number of tiles, right?
Where's this, the square button Square it?
That's it.
Total number of tiles.
Now, how many slices we want?
Let's say we want, you know, 16z slices at least right?
So 16z slices.
That's how many tiles we have total, right?
So now if we copy that number
Right.
We're going to divide that number by, let's say a gigabyte, right?
So that's a gigabyte.
So this is actually the number I was way off.
I forgot to gb2.
I did four times for, but I forgot to squirt.
You know, I did, I did for GB x 4 GB.
I did 4 times 4, right?
Which is 16, but I forgot to gb2.
So that's GB squared, right?
That makes sense.
So I forgot to record it.
So now I've squared the GB looking at its way worse, right?
In fact, let's go ahead and change that to terabytes.
Now, we're talking about.
In 68 million terabytes, so you couldn't even store that on a drive.
There's no such thing as a 268 terabyte drive.
So, yeah, so forget about it, like like whole world storage for that,
those dimensions of isn't going to happen.
All right.
I think we've come to the end of the questions.
So, thank you, everyone for joining me, handmade hero day.
35.
It has been a pleasure coding with you.
As always we are basically finished up our tile map stuff, our Tom app
storage stuff.
So we kind of know now at the end of day 35 year, we kind of know.
What we want our engine to do for tilemap storage.
It's kind of pretty, I think it's laid out reasonably.
Well, so we'll be able to write this pretty clearly.
We know the sort of stuff we need so we can start moving on.
I think next week.
We'll add our little up and downs just so we can have them in there.
But I think next week we'll be ready to move on to some something
else.
So that'll be good.
Maybe we'll start to think about how we're going to render the tilemap
graphics.
So the stuff on top of their, maybe that's what we'll do next week.
I'm not sure.
I have to think about what I want to do next week.
What's the most important thing to do?
We've also got player motion.
Think about.
We've got monsters thing about
So we've got a bunch of things that we need to do.
But yeah, so some let's think about not sure what we'll do next week,
but please, if you enjoyed the series, please think about joining us
for whatever we do decide to do next week.
I promise, it'll be interesting.
We'll be doing it Monday at 8 p.m.
Our standard slot Monday, 8:00 p.m.
Pacific Standard time.
So please come back for more game programming.
We would love to see you here.
If you would like to follow along at home with the source code.
It is available.
Anyone who?
Where's the game?
Go ahead and close this down here?
Anyone who pre-orders the game on handmade hero dot?
Org, gets instant access to the source code.
You can go on.
Download everything.
I update it every time immediately after we finished work for the day.
I upload it.
So you can play around with it yourself, learn from it and do whatever
sorts of things you want to do to sort of learn game, programming
inside the context of the handmade hero.
Sourcetree.
So if you want to preorder that you can download that.
And again it's updated every day so you can download it a fresh and
keep track of where we are.
Are on the series.
If you just want to support the video series, we do have a patreon.
You can subscribe to so you can head on over there.
And if you're trying to learn from the series, there are a lot of
additional resources, you can use at the news and Forum site.
If you click through there, there's all kind of stuff episode guide a
discussion forum.
The schedule is posted.
They're usually on Mondays.
There's ports to Mac and Linux if you're interested in those.
So there's all kinds of good stuff there.
So please check it out.
If you're trying to learn from series is a great place to go.
Thank you everyone for joining us.
We will be back here, Monday, 8:00 p.m.
PST.
It's been a pleasure.
Always and I hope to see you there.
Thanks everyone and have a good weekend.