Okay.
Hello everyone, and welcome to handmade hero.
The show where we code and entire game live on Twitch, from scratch,
new libraries.
No engine.
And basically, you know what?
Honestly, it's pretty much going to be awesome.
Like, I mean, that's all we really need to say.
I'm already starting to get that feeling.
This game is going to be awesome.
And so there's really not much more to say.
Let's just start because we were doing a bunch of cool stuff yesterday
and now
Now is the time when we can sort of finish up a bunch of the things.
I think that we had started down the road to doing.
Well, I don't know finish up, but we'll do some kind of interesting
other things that I've been wanting to do for a while.
And so I don't even want to take too much time to Preamble this.
I just want to get going.
It's programming time.
I ate like half a bag of chocolate chip cookies before the stream,
which is not a good idea.
So, I'm a little bit wired right now, and that's fine.
But anyway, if you have pre-ordered the game on handmade hero dot-org,
you should have gotten a link in your email, and that link has a zip
file.
You can download
With all the source code in it.
What you want to do is download the source code for a day 53, because
we're on day 54.
And so you unzip the previous day source code and you can code right
along with me.
So, if you're doing that, do that, now is the time to do that.
Alright, so if I remember correctly, we just gotten to the point where
we'd put little entities in the world to represent all the walls.
So basically now the entities we made these little yellow entities
there.
That are all around the side.
Those are all the walls and we now have a situation.
Where is your name?
Where we haven't actually quite finished doing or figuring out exactly
how we're doing are sort of like to level and two-tier entity system.
Right?
We have entities that are sort of in the field of view and act right
of active entities that we want to consider at a high frequency and to
do like full gameplay on and then we also have entities that are
further away from the camera that you can't see.
And that aren't in the immediate vicinity of the player, and we want
to allow those to run at a low frequency.
So that
We can still simulate them and have it rich interactions going around
elsewhere in the world.
Potentially that the player could experience the effects of later when
they go there.
But that aren't going to suck down a ton of CPU time.
If we want to scale The Entity count up to really high numbers, ten
hundred thousand.
Who knows how many so what we need to do is kind of continue down on
that path.
It's kind of fun to see him bounce up and down for some reason.
So we want to do is continue continue down that path.
And also put in we
Have.
We have currently no spatial partition or anything like that.
So also Collision detection right now is extremely inefficient because
we're colliding against all the high res entities all the time.
So, even the ones that are like off-screen were colliding against.
So we need to start pairing this down and making this letting this
coalesce into like a nice good system that we sort of started on that
on that path.
Is a little bit taxing for me to do unfortunate because it's weird to
do this in like one hour chunks like this, but I've been trying to
keep it mostly in my head.
I page it out during the day when I'm working on other code and then I
tried it page it back in now, so we'll see.
Hopefully won't make too many mistakes.
So anyway, what we sort of started doing here is we sort of started
making it so that as the camera moves, we have this set camera call
and what the set camera called would do is first would go ahead and it
would map out.
So it would change the
Entity residents of any entities, which were sort of, we're currently,
in the high-frequency set, and no longer need to be simulated, high
frequency.
And then we would go ahead and go through all the entities that were
in the like, outside of the high frequencies and might need to come
back in.
And one of the things that I was saying yesterday and I think is
probably true.
Just I'm looking at how this is going and whether I want to deal with
it or not and you'll notice that we still have never come up with a
real good idea of what would even be in a low energy because we
Had dormant low and high and really everything ends up in the dormant
or the high entity for the most part.
So really, the only thing is that would kind of be in the low entity
that I can think of are like, movement timers or something.
I mean, like the difference between a dormant entity and a low entity
is just whether or not, they would get ticked periodically on that
sort of periodic update.
So I'm kind of thinking that maybe we just have low frequency and high
frequency entities.
That's what I've been thinking because I don't want to over complicate
something for no real benefit.
So maybe we still would have the concept of a dormant and it e which
is a low entity That Doesn't Really Ever Need.
You ticked, but maybe we just don't ever have that and that's fine
too.
I don't know.
It's really hard to say.
So I think what I'm going to say is let's just go ahead and make that
change.
Let's just go ahead and say that we just have low entities and high
entities and we don't have that third tier just to simplify things
because I haven't seen the need for it so far and so I'll let that
need re-emerge.
If it turns out to be true, but if it doesn't then we'll just
Count ourselves lucky that we've got one listing do with, and that's
that.
So let's go ahead and remove those dormant entities entirely, right?
And I guess I'm going to replace dormant everywhere that.
I see it with low, right?
So I just got, that's all I've got now.
So I can go through and do all of these.
And then there's some places where we have dormant entity stuff.
That just goes away entirely.
Like here, where we've got two of those in the compiler, should tell
us about that.
Just fine.
I think.
Yeah, so I've got rid of the low entities and so now they're gone and
I think things would probably still work roughly the same as they did
and they do so that's good.
No problems there.
There we go.
And so now, let's think about this a little bit more carefully, so,
I've got ways of adding entities now.
That are in here.
And one thing that's interesting about adding entities is I think
technically entities probably should always be added in the low State
and then get moved to high because most entities are always in the low
State.
Like, when the whole world gets generated.
Everything will be in the low state, right?
Nothing be in the high state.
So really that high state is just for a limited number of things that
are just right around, you know, just that are just right around the
the cursor right around the player.
Right?
And so typically we would expect to have lots and lots of low entities
and not very many high entities.
Right?
So the next thing that I think might be a good thing to do is to start
thinking about it in those terms where instead of having like I did
this thing and I thought that was kind of clever, but the thing that I
was thinking of is I wonder if it maybe makes
More sense to or to already even now start to partition into high and
low entity sets that aren't mirrored.
So, you know something that looks more like this where we start to say
that the low entities in the high Andes, don't map to each other.
Like they're not one-to-one correspondence has there's a ton of low
entities and there's only a subset of those that are actually in the
hiset at any given time.
Right?
And furthermore, one thing we could do and I don't know, you know,
like here's I'm just throwing this out there.
R.
One thing that we could do, that's kind of amusing.
Is we could think of hi entity set as basically consisting of some
fixed number of entities.
Like we could say that there are always two hundred and fifty six
entities, simulated high resolution or something, or always 64 enemies
simulator.
I don't know, right?
We could say that.
And then the nut the entities are in that set are just however, many
entities, whatever the 256 closest edit, these are right.
So as you move around, it's just always keeping the entities.
Guarded by whoever is close to the players in that set.
I don't know if that's actually something I want to do, but I just
thought I'd throw it out there.
So that's kind of thinking of us.
Like, oh, that's kind of interesting.
That way we have like a bounded set and we know that's always what
we're simulating in terms of fixed kind of thing there anyway, so,
yeah, so, you know, if we did it this way, then what I was thinking of
doing it, so the entity residents would go away, right?
And what would happen is something like the low entity structure would
Just have a writer on it that basically said, you know, where is the
high entity?
Right?
What's the high in the index and that high in the index would tell you
if it was Zero, it means that this guy isn't in the hyades set and if
the if the high any index was set to something, then it would tell you
that the high entity was in fact present.
Right and symmetrically.
I could do it where you've got the high entity has a pointer back to
its low entity as well.
Now.
I don't actually know if both of those things are necessary.
It may be that we could make it so that that was not necessary but
it's just kind of an interesting thing to think about like so that way
we would just go we'd look up there are low enemies when we need to
move them too high.
We just do that and put record.
The fact that they're in there and then the hiney set when we're
spending over them.
We grab the low entity that we want.
If we actually need it, we grab that low entity out of the pool by
doing just a dereference, right?
So that's something to think about.
Another thing that we could think about doing is that
The high entity could just include the low entity in it, just straight
up.
So in other words, we would copy the low entity data out into the high
entity.
But there's reasons why I think that could be dangerous.
And that's because we're going to have people who simulate primarily
on low entity and I want them to kind of try and stay in sync.
So I think for now I want to go with the front.
The forward back pointer thing, that just links them up and then as we
see how the patterns emerge and when we
Getting into more like performance or any things and we start to maybe
care a little bit about whether that's a little too much to have
these, like references, going everywhere and you know, pulling
randomly out of things, the random memory accessing patterns, you
know, then we can start start a start to think about it, whether we
need to do something different.
So, yeah, so there you go.
So, what I want to do now, is say, Okay.
So let's go ahead and do that.
Let's create things only in the low entity.
A list and let's let's let's start treating the high-end TV list a
little bit more specifically, right?
And so we've got this high-end to do list here and we'll have a high
into the account and a low entity count.
Basically, so that we basically know we kind of have two different
ones that I'm putting an underscore after this temporarily because I
want to see everywhere that's used and I want to think about it a
little bit.
And so now what we can do is you can say alright when we want to
change and entities residents, right?
Then really
When we're changing its residents.
I'm trying to think if we ever actually need this function again.
Or whether we want this to be more make high and I make low because
we'll always know which one of those two things were doing, if that
makes sense.
Let's take a look change and City residents.
So get entity actually does have it parameterize.
They're here.
They're there.
So those are yeah, so I'm thinking I'm thinking that we probably want
this to kind of change up a little bit, right?
I'm thinking that we kind of want this just be a make high in a make.
Whoa, so basically like there's a way of there's something that moves
a low to a high and there's one that gets rid of the high right and
you never really have to move the high-back, right?
Because I think that that would always sort of just automatically
happen because I think we said that we always keep that that low State
updated.
Anyway, so really all we have here is we have a like move or
Move it, but make entity high frequency or something.
And get rid of this for now.
All right, and we also don't really need this anymore for the most
part because all we really we know that you always have a low.
And so if you got a bundle, you just check to see if hi is not null.
That's the only thing you have to check for, right?
So if I do make entity high-frequency, I'm going to say which entity
it is that I want, that's an index obviously into the low.
So I guess we should start to call these low index.
And that's probably something that I might.
To start actually having a tight for hard to say, but like a it's the
index type just so people don't.
Well people but people being me don't make mistakes passing the wrong
kind of Index, right?
So let's keep an eye on that and if I do make that mistake, that would
be a good indication that.
It's a good time to do that, right?
I like how we still have implement this year.
Even though we already implemented it.
Like I said, comments always stay ill.
So alright.
So if we want to do this, we want to make it any high frequency.
What we need to do first is we need to go ahead and pull it slow
entity.
Right?
So we grabbed its low index out like that and then we need to check to
see whether it's high into.
The index is actually 0 because if it's high, any index isn't zero,
that means it's already got a high entity and we don't care, right?
So if we need to move the guy too high, then what we need to do is
first assert that there's room for him in the high table, right?
If there isn't room for me the high table, he can't move.
And so one of the things that you about that, actually, I guess we
could also say we could also go ahead and just make sure that that's
always true.
So that that's not true will start it as an invalid code path, right?
And I don't know if we actually ever find one of those and made
platform.sh their assertions in here.
Yes, there are.
But we don't over, we don't have them.
So I'm going to go ahead and find that fine invalid.
Code path and invalid code path.
Is just something that I like to do, which is essentially an assertion
that I stick.
That always asserts in some place that I never expect the code to
actually get in practice, but which theoretically could happen.
And then I don't want to create a bug at runtime, right?
And so one example of this is that technically our game might not do
all the things that supposed to do.
If we try to make an entity high frequency, but it's not able to
because we run out of room in our hyphae.
Fancy table.
But technically, we shouldn't just straight-up crash.
Right?
Like why not make it so that we just keep running but everything's at
low frequency instead, right?
Seems fine.
So I would say, all right, we've got our energy High, we've got our
enemy low, whatever that hiney index is.
So at this point, if if whatever that high entity county is if
Same state High and the count is less than whatever.
The array count is of the high entities, right?
Then we're going to go ahead and say that, it's ok to add it.
Right?
And so now the high index is going to be equal to whatever the edit
account was an incremented, so that we know the next one, you know,
we're just taking a slot in our high anything and then we'll go ahead
and grab out that high and then the rest of the function can proceed
as normal, right?
So all we did is just push someone out of the top of that.
That high-end be array, right?
So that's all good.
Now we're going to map the sky into the camera space.
And again, also another thing here is it's important to point out.
So this number pretty much has to be fixed.
So this is not really a case where like a lot of times we talk about
garbage collection and automatic memory management is a bad is good.
All these other sort of things.
This is actually not what I'm worried about here.
So this is not this, the fact that I need this High entities thing to
be a fixed size has nothing to do with memory management.
Actually.
It does happen to me nice because
It means that our memory management will be fixed and that's fine.
But that's not actually why I'm doing it.
The reason I'm doing it this way is because I high entities are the
performance cost.
And so I know that I'm basically going to have a certain budget for
high entities, right?
I know that.
However, many I can afford and we'll find out what that is later.
But however, mind I could forward is is limited by the CPU time per
frame.
I have to process them.
So I can't just make this an unbounded array that grows.
It has to actually be limited in a realistic way.
So when we start talking about memory management, those sorts of
things were really going to be focusing more on this array, which is
going to hold lots of guys.
Potentially not this array, which is going to be limited to a small
number of guys which is you know, 2265 12.
Something I who knows how many guys.
But however many we can successfully process at speed for whatever it
is that we need to do.
Okay, so we grabbed out the next time entity that we need there and we
do the same stuff that we used to do on it, which I think is fine.
And now after we set all this stuff up we can record the fact on the
entity low.
The fact that it has a high high entity Index, right?
Which is that.
So that's the thing for moving us into the high frequency space.
And then if I want to do the opposite would make entity low frequency
that I've got two choices and this is this is largely.
I guess this is really just about performance.
I don't actually know that there's any other thing that that would
matter here about whether I do a free list or not, but you can see
I think I'm going to do it this way.
We'll see how it will see how it goes.
So what UPS?
That's there's not going to be an if there.
And also I guess now that I think about it, this is wrong.
It's okay if it's already got a high so it's only that.
But I wanted to insert a valid invalid, code path on, right?
That that's like I didn't want it the hot, if they already has a high,
that's totally fine.
That just means someone wanted to make something high frequency that
was already high frequency, which is really not an invalid code path.
That's probably something we'll just allow so that people don't have
to check first that can just say, I need this guy to be high entity,
high frequency, and it will be
So we really only want to do assert if we ran out of room so that we
know, because we want to try and make our game so that we always do
use the right number of high energy.
So that's really what that's about.
Alright, so that is that and let's make sure that that compiles.
Okay here, let's see.
Okay.
So then when we make someone low frequency, we're going to do the
opposite of what we just did.
Assuming that the guy
and that's backwards again.
Yeah, it's if he doesn't have high G's.
Yeah, little slow today.
Little bit slow.
All right, so assuming that the guy does have a high index in this
case, then I need to pull him off of that list.
So he shouldn't be on the high anymore.
And so what I need to do first is say and I could pull this out here
to high index.
so if the high index is at the end of the array that I don't have to
worry about it, so if the high index is
Is equal to however many entities there already were in that high
energy list, right?
Hi, entity count.
So it would be equal to that.
I should say minus 1, right.
So if the high-end x equals the count minus one, then all I have to do
is just decrement the count, right?
Because it was the last one, so I just decrement it.
But if it wasn't, the last one, then I have to move it into.
I have to basically fill the Gap.
That's going to be left, bye-bye.
By closing that whole right?
So if you imagine we just have an array here right?
Dude here.
Am I high entities?
Right?
I've got 0 1 2 3 4 5 6 right and then I've got my low and of these
here, right?
And these guys are pointing into this in various ways.
Although hopefully not to this one because that's illegal.
So I've got all of this stuff set up.
What I want to do is say, all right, if I'm going to remove this guy,
right?
So he's going away.
I don't want to leave an empty space there.
We could decide to do that, which now, that I think about it might
actually be the right solution.
Just mark it as not there so that when you're when we're processing
through it,
Yeah, that's that's probably better, huh?
You know that we want this to be a constant time processing.
So we know that we have to support being able to process everything.
Yeah, so why am I even thinking about this?
Never mind?
I take it all back.
I don't have to do that at all.
So we're just not ever going to.
We're just never going to decrement that count.
I think what I'll probably do is I'll probably just keep a free list.
That seems like the most logical thing to do.
I don't know.
I'm so torn right now.
You can see why I'm touring, right?
Because we know that we're going to have some budget for processing a
certain number of entities, right?
And so, you know, let's say we can afford 256 entities.
So when we're doing the processing of these I feel like there's no
reason why we shouldn't just skip ones that are marked as done because
we know we could have crossed them if they're all filled.
So we don't care.
If we paid the performance penalty of skipping.
One that's not there in the iteration because it doesn't matter.
We could have we saying that we have a CPU budget to process them if
they were all filled.
So it seems like that would be fine.
And then all I would do is just keep a free list which basically
points every time you eliminate one of the high nineties.
You just add it to the free list.
And so then when someone wants to take a new slot, it just pulls it
off of the free list, right?
So that seems like a pretty reasonable way to do it.
I don't know why I wouldn't, but then the other thing that I was
thinking of doing was saying, okay?
When I pull someone off, I'll just take the last guy who ever is the
last guy on the array and I'll move him to that slot, right?
And then just reduce the count by one and the reason that's a little
less janky.
Little more janky is because it does involve doing the copy here and
then setting, this guy's whoever was pointing to this, right?
Setting them to point to their, you know, it's like
I don't know.
Which do you do.
They're both fine.
And so normally I would do that if I wanted to keep the array compact
for processing purposes, but I'm already saying that I need to that
their array is only as big as my processing could handle any way at
maximum.
So that's not a concern.
So it seems like, yeah, I don't know.
I'll keep the array compact for now.
Let's just say that will keep the array compact for now.
I really don't know.
That's just what I'm gonna do.
So,
That that we happen to removing the last guy, then we're just done
right away.
Otherwise, we have to do the remapping.
So otherwise what we have to do is say well, okay.
Who is the last guy then?
Right.
We need to basically say whoever is the high entities, right?
So.
whoever is the last one and this is
I guess.
Last index last High Index, right?
So if we were going to remove the last time index, then we're done.
Otherwise, we're just going to grab whoever that was.
So that's a high entity.
Last entity, right?
Is this guy?
so,
We'll grab that last entity.
We now need to rock him over where the other high entity was.
Right?
And I guess, what's one thing that's kind of interesting about this is
we might have the high energy index as well when we, when we want to
make someone low-frequency.
So it's kind of a little tough to say which way we should be doing
this.
Whether we should pass the high end index here or not.
But either way we'll we'll think about that a second.
So this is this is kind of our whole or are
Entity, this is our delete identity.
Right?
And so our delete identity.
He is at high entities, High Index, right?
So what I'm going to do is I'm going to go ahead and say that the
delete identity now equals whatever that last entity is, right?
And then I'm going to say that whatever wherever he who ever was
whichever low entity was pointing to him as his high-end.
OT, right?
I just need to go ahead and
I just need to go ahead and tell him that it's been moved.
Right?
So he has his high entity index, like so equal to whatever our high
index was right to do.
That is not what I wanted to do.
That is not what I want to do low.
And so, this is basically saying the low entity.
That the last entity corresponds to.
His high-end to the index.
Now, points at where we just wrote, we just where we just filled in
the array.
And in either case, I guess this always happens.
So really, this is just if they're not equal to meaning, if we do have
to to fill now, in either case.
Use me in either case that entity low, The Entity lows high density
index.
That's getting romp, is always going to revert now, to not having a
high entity, right?
Because it's become low frequency.
So I think.
That's right.
Well, I'm step through that once to make sure I didn't typo anything
up there.
All right, so the get any call.
I think the get any call, I don't even really know if we're going to
have a get any call anymore to be completely honest with you.
So we'll see who's actually using it.
I'm not entirely sure.
So yeah, I think I think get entity is basically just going to be get
entities just going to be a thing about getting low entities.
I think that's really all there is to it for the most part hard to say
hard to say indeed.
So
Let's think about this for a second.
But yeah, I think that's, I think, we really just don't care about
that.
So I think this is going to be, I think this is just going to be Get
Low entity potentially.
I think that's really all we're going to have.
And I think you're not going to really do a get high entity call.
I mean, I guess I could just apply both of them and they are assumed
to return like zero if they don't exist.
So be something like, you know, low end of these
Our result equals 0 assuming that the result is between the zero, you
know, the first valid empty and the last valid entity, then we'll go
ahead and return it.
Otherwise, you return?
No, so I'm going to, I'm going to say that, that's how this works.
So, yeah, so basically yeah.
Yeah, I like that.
All right, so,
Let's go ahead and do that.
So that's just low news plus low index.
That's how we get that result.
We don't care about any of this stuff, that's not going to happen
anymore.
So that result goes there and then we will go ahead and put those
right here for now and low becomes high.
So that does that and low index.
I guess we could just do
Make that two.
So those are symmetric.
Sometimes it's nice to have to be symmetric.
All right, so I think
That should just about do it.
So, if we're going to add an entity, that now means that we're always
adding a low entity, right?
Entities are just, you know, they're just going to be low.
And let's go ahead and assert here, that the entity that the low empty
count is less than the the low entity array size.
We will go ahead and initialize that entity so we'll do it like so we
go and that will be it.
We don't have change anything else.
These guys basically add low entities, and I feel like, with the
entity index to these guys don't really need it anymore.
I think most of the time because now entity index and this is kind of
nice.
Doesn't really mean anything to people, they don't need to know any of
these index anymore.
It's not really important.
In fact to some degree.
Well, now I guess you kind of still do need to know the end of the
index when you're doing that front and back pointer thing.
So, all right.
So anyway, so these are always low entities forgetting here and this
is Get Low entity and there we go.
So that's a that's that.
I'm a little.
I think that's a there's a little inefficiency baked into that.
Unfortunately.
I just I feel like maybe we want to be returning pointers in some of
these cases, but that's okay.
No.
Big deal.
So let's see.
Identity identity.
It's add low entity now.
So, there we go.
That's going to tea and low.
So this is just like that, and I guess I could also do this.
Okay.
And you can see that I'm, you know, this is the kind of thing that I
do a lot.
I often times write code multiple times.
I'll just go through it.
Several passes.
You can see.
It doesn't take me that long, you know, I'll spend a few times doing
it.
Put things in remove things, pull them out.
It's like, this is, this is definitely the part where you're like
shaping the clay and seeing what the back it looks like.
Right before you decide to sculpt the finished piece.
You just got to be willing to kind of go over things multiple times
and like get them until you're pretty confident and you need to do
that actual work.
Mayor of trying different stuff until you get it, till it feels good.
And that's, that's really important.
So, I don't mind.
Like, the fact that we write and rewrite, a lot of these things
multiple times because like I said, as long as you keep those rewrites
fast, they don't cost you anything and they end up producing a much
more high quality result at the end.
All right.
So now if we're adding a player, again, we don't care about any of
this stuff at all.
So we need to do here is just take a look at this camera, following
entity.
X assuming that that equals 0, then we'll set it to equal to our
entity index, which is fine.
See what else we got here.
So now we're going to do these are Loops slowly over the high entity
Index.
Right?
And so, this is just going to full-on get those directly High
entities.
This is just a nice straight Loop because this is we're going to have
to start making this.
This sort of code is going to have to start being performant.
So how did we get to hear?
Exactly?
We have a move player.
So, we need to pass.
I suppose, a high entity here, right?
Because it was only High entities can move, right?
We only have this, this function, only works with high entities.
So we go ahead and do that here.
I think, well, you know,
Let's think about this.
So, I'm trying to decide whether I want that low high pointer thing
where they're bundled because I had that right.
I'm trying to think of wet weather.
I want that, like, do I want to keep using that or not?
And, you know, maybe I do.
So maybe I do want that to still work for the most part.
And, and this would just have it below Index, right?
Because, you know, you can always get the, the low index if you have a
high and, you know, you just get the high-end except you have a low,
But you might not have a high so you might not have the low index.
So that's really the only thing that we need there.
So, we'll see.
We'll see.
Anyway, so I'm not sure if I actually want to keep this or not.
We'll see or whether I still want accessors on it or not.
But what I do need to do is be able to compare these two.
So I want to do is say this right here is the high end of the index.
This is basically the test High under the index.
So we're just looping over those High entities to test to see if
they're there.
So we're going to go ahead and grab.
Basically, High entity.
Test Ima Be Like.
So we're going to go ahead and grab that out and we know we can get
the loaf.
We need it, but we're just not going to get it right now.
So then we go ahead and say all right.
And in fact, I guess we don't even need to do that quite yet, but we
could do first is say if the entity index that we're talking about
here if that test, hi, this is not equal to us, right?
So this is whatever we are.
So this is entity.
.Hi, whatever are our
Indexes, so I guess is actually energy, low high-end, the index.
So if the two indices differ, then that's how we know that we need to
check, because that means it's not us.
So, because we don't Collide against ourselves.
So then we go ahead and grab that test High entity.
And, and I guess, we also need to grab the one to see if it collides
or not.
We could, we could lock that up.
So that we wouldn't have to pull the low entity for every single
person, but we might end up just doing that in a different way.
A like will only enter people into the grid, they Collide or something
like this, right?
Yeah, so test high energy, we've got it.
Slow entity index.
Like so
And I don't remember when we did make empty, high frequency to be,
remember to put that in there.
No, we didn't.
So entity high-low, empty index should always be equal to whoever
created him.
Right?
Yeah.
So, that's that.
See, here low entities doesn't have underscore yet.
So we have tests low entity.
Don't know why I renamed it.
That way.
I should just call it test and too low to keep it symmetric test.
There we go.
And I guess I could wrap these guys get into an actual low and high if
I wanted to.
All right, let's go ahead and do that.
So, if I do the entity structure, because I'm trying to figure out
whether or not, I want this to happen, right?
Chest entity, low index equals entity, good to me, equals.
Test MD.
Hi.
Hello, so there's my hi.
There's Milo.
And the low index I have to get off of the high, right?
So it's actually this guy and I could do it that way if I want to
like, so, all right, so that produces the test entity and
Now, I can finish the rest of this routine, which probably would just
work, because it's already set up to work that way when we do the hit
entity index.
They hit entity index.
Should presumably.
Well.
What do we actually need that?
For at the end?
We just need to see whether we need to do anything to it.
Right?
Yeah, so we just need to see whether it wants to go like up or down,
or those sorts of things.
Right?
And so, we probably just want to, we could save the pointers there, if
we want, or we could just
Save the high index.
Not sure.
Which one.
Or we could say the low index for that matter.
So let's go ahead and say it high into the index for now.
So, what we'll do is we'll say hi to the index equals test tied to the
index and we'll do that in all the places where we needed to actually
remember who we hit.
There we go.
So in the space, we remembered where we hit.
We now can say, all right.
Hit high and BMX, this guy.
So if I want to grab his stuff out, we can go ahead and say there's
the high entity, right?
And this is the hit high and that is hit High entity.
I don't actually do that.
I guess I know this is always full game State hides.
The index.
Yeah, so I almost want like a direct one that doesn't assertion to
make sure I'm not referencing outside of anything.
But that doesn't do the bounds checking, so it would compile out.
So I have to think about that one later.
I'll have to think about that one later as well.
All right, so that would be that and hit low would be.
Like this.
And it looks like we only need the hit low for this guy.
I probably could have just saved that.
Maybe it was a mistake to save the high instead.
Let's see ya.
And that's literally.
All right.
So those are done.
And now, we need to Loop over our high entities and that's totally
fine.
We don't need to check our high entities because we know that
everything that's in the hire.
A now, is high properly.
We are doing all the same stuff that we were doing before.
But now what we want to do is we want to be able to yeah do.
So.
This is a little bit tricky.
This will actually change people's residences in this Loop directly.
And what I'm thinking is I wonder, do we, is this all the place where
we would always do it, right?
Is when they come out here because if it was we could actually bake
this right in here.
And I'm kind of thinking maybe that is what I do want to do.
Essentially.
The only place that you can have, it happen is here.
And the reason for that is it makes the iteration.
Not tricky, right?
It means that the iteration is pretty easy for us to handle and we
don't have to deal with it in any other way.
So basically, what we do here is we'd say We're looping over these
guys, right?
We're checking them, and if they're not inside the rectangle, then we
go ahead and we we pull them out.
We pull them out.
Bye-bye doing that swap that I was talking about and then we just
don't increment the pointer.
So the person that we swap into place.
We just don't increment the pointer.
So I'm thinking that it looks something like this, right?
So we've got the high end of the account.
We Loop over everyone there.
We check to see if they're in the rectangle if they're not in the
rectangle.
Then we grab their entity Low by just looking at the high entities,
low into the index.
So we've got it.
Now.
We already know the highwomen.
Index.
Right.
It's this.
So we just say this is our high index.
So get rid of that.
So that's just a nice Loop.
Very very straightforward.
We checked the rectangle is this is the the not very frequently.
This won't happen.
Presumably very frequently all.
Well Mike because I guess we don't set camera that off.
And so we take a look to see if the hi Auntie index.
You know, I take it back.
There is one other case we have to handle when somebody walks out of
bounds.
We will have to handle this.
So maybe I just want these two routines to be like aware of each other
so that the iteration is still easy because what?
Worried about is that iteration this, this mutates, the array, right?
So the iteration, if it was just a naive, iteration would fail to work
properly, right?
So it's just something, it's just something to think about.
That's all.
So yeah, so basically, like let's say I call this here is all I'm
saying, right?
So this mutates, the array.
And so, we wouldn't want to increment The Entity index, but that
assumes, that we know, right?
So it's basically if it's in the it's in the rectangle.
Skip it, if it's not in the rectangle get rid of it, right?
But that assumes that we kind of know exactly how that that removal
function is working.
And it's kind of, I don't like, you know, having that be so implicit
in the code, Sara Lee, it would be nice.
If there was a way to kind of avoid that a little bit, right?
And so I don't know like maybe the best thing to do there would be to
kind of like sort of couple pair these guys together, right?
Say, you know, make entities, low frequency by by area, right and that
that does this Loop, right?
But it does the loop right here.
And, and yeah, just so I guess offset and check frequency by area.
There we go.
And so, we'll call that function and they'll this will kind of be
coupled with the previous function so that they're in the same place
in the code and they make a little more sense.
Right?
And so this will just pass what that and the offset is, right.
So that's the offset there and let's see.
I'll check.
for area and of the offset frame, 60,
So this right here is what my offsets going to be, and this is the
thing that I need to pass for the bounds for checking.
So that's going to be camera bounds and so we'll just do that and that
can still be, you know, that could be an inline.
So it just still sticks it in there.
But just so it's, you know, clear what's going on in these guys.
Right?
Most of these could really be inlined for the most part.
Well, this one might stay out.
All right, so I think
I think if that is how I would like to do that.
So everyone is inside the rectangle gets skipped, everyone who's not
just gets deleted from the high in 2D array and then this has to be
over the high and 50 count.
So,
And that's much better going over the low entities.
It's the same thing only now, instead of doing changes, you residents
were pulling make entity high frequency, right?
And that
Is that?
And I think that's really all we need to do.
Oops about that.
So we do need to do this and say, we're not going to try to move
anyone if they're high into the index is already set because we know
that they already have a high entity, right?
So this is only if they're there.
Heidi is set to 0 and then
Past the game State.
Yeah, and then we need to reserve our zero entity in both places.
So we do need to do a identity and we need to do a basically a reserve
a slot in the high entities.
So Heidi count equals one as well.
So that basically, we never get below that one because the high end to
the index of 0 has
To be reserved for the no entity.
So what else we got to do here for controlling entities?
So an entity that you're controlling?
We do want that to always be high.
So I'm trying to think though, exactly whether we want how exactly
want to do that because it's basically this move player function that
ends up wanting to do that.
So I'm not sure exactly how we want to handle this.
So what we want to do I guess is we want to First say
Whatever the player index was for controller.
Let's check to see what that is.
Right.
So, we've got low index for the player, Right is coming out of this
thing.
And so we want to do is say if the low end X is not equal to 0, or,
yeah, I guess we could change the sense of this and say, if it is
equal to 0, right, so assuming that it's equal to zero, that means
that we are checking to see whether or not this controller is going to
start controlling.
A player, right?
And that would do this.
So we'll say ended down in the index equals add player.
So we're going to add the player game State players for controller and
at the index.
That all looks good.
No weirdest there.
And then in the case, where we aren't then we're going to do the move
and the move does require that the player be in high.
So this is one case where we would have to say, you know, make sure
that the entity is actually a high entity.
So, I don't know if I want to still do the thing.
I guess, if I just have a get high entity that that forces entities to
hide, that would do it.
It looks like I'm trying to think of whether this guy even cares that
much.
It looks like they this this guy.
Is also use the high.
So yeah, so I feel like what it's looking like to me is what I want to
do is have a is is maybe have entity?
Maybe.
That's maybe when you call get high entity, that gives that is the
thing that returns an entity struck, that has both pairs and the index
in it.
That seems to make some sense to me because that's looking like the
use its path.
Turn, right?
That's, that's the time when you actually do that operation.
So I think maybe that's the right way, right?
Yeah.
So in this case when we add it slowly file, we don't need to turn them
too high, but when we actually move them, we would need to turn them
too high.
And so that's the controlling entity equals get high entity.
Right?
And so when you call the get
It's a little bit weird to call it, get high, and because you're
actually passing a low index to it.
Right?
But it seems like you never really get an entity by its high index.
That's really just something that you use when you're looping over
them in processing.
So it's hard to say it's hard to say how I want to do that.
Exactly.
So we'll think about it some more, but that's basically what that
would do.
So get high in today.
Would actually look like this, you would pass a low index, right?
And the way this would work is you'd have a result.
you would first do a make entity high frequency like so
Right, you would always do that on the guy when you call high and you
would.
Then in fact, the other thing you could do is say that make high
frequency, could return the high frequency pointer.
Although in the case where one already exists.
Maybe you don't necessarily want to hard to say, but we could say that
this works like this, right?
we could say that if it,
if it already has one, we just return it.
Right.
So we've got high entity, entity, High 0.
So in this case, we do entity.
Hi.
Equals this.
So, there we go.
And we would do that here as well.
But in this case, it be empty, low.
Hi index.
All right.
So if we have a hiding this already, we just get it.
If we didn't have one, then we make sure we create it like that, like
so.
And then we return the entity high and that way in here.
All I have to do is say okay.
Salt is going to have the low index.
It's going to have the low entity, which is just whatever, the game,
State, low entities, plus below, indexes.
Five minute warning.
Man, so close and yet so far too.
And then it's also going to have behind.
So, there we go.
So we've grabbed those that's all good.
And I guess I'll allow it so that when you call get high entity, we
will allow it where you can call it with with something that would be
out of bounds.
And it will just, it will, it will silently fail on that.
So I, maybe maybe I just want this to be an assertion.
Maybe that's the right thing to do because it seems like you should
never be getting a high-end see that way, but we could change it later
to say that you can pass a zero here and get zero back right, get a
zero pointer back.
I don't know which one we want to do about that.
I really don't know.
So we'll find out to do should we allow passing a zero index and
return a null pointer?
Maybe who knows?
Okay.
So, let's see here.
Let's see.
So when we are looping over the tests entities and you got to get the
load.
Yeah, that's that's was a little bit janky.
I didn't love that.
All right, so get high entity.
So when you controlling entity, we pass that gets the higher energy.
That's fine, discuss the hiring to do as well.
And this could just basically look to see whether it has a high
pointer.
Assuming it does, it goes ahead and use this it.
Let's see.
The low end X has to be between those bounds.
This is going to Loop over the high entities only right?
Because it doesn't actually need the low for anything and I mean, it's
a sorry, it always needs the highwomen.
And so that, that is pretty much it for that.
This is the high entity index here.
Like so you go hide T's plus High into the index.
And then our Lou entity is just going to be gotten from.
The high to itself.
So high into the dot fluency index.
Okay.
And that's it.
Right?
So there we go.
Now I don't sure that's going to crash horribly because I did so many
random things there.
That's way too many to have not made some mistakes, but that's
basically what I want to do.
And there's I think I want to do one more pass over it because I feel
like I want to clean up that entity handling there.
Hmm, let's see.
All right, so this guy needs to check so that would be a case where
that would be a case where it would argue for the thing that I said,
where it should just check the bounds to see.
And so, I don't know, like, let's do it because it looked like that
was sort of something I had wanted to type in so we'll let it let it
happen.
We'll see if it's good or not.
Alright, so we're not working properly there.
We did not properly create.
Other high entities there.
Why did we not create that?
Why do we not handle them?
Oh, we still haven't done our wrapping yet.
So we still have not fixed the rapping problem.
If you remember correctly.
This, this this thing here is not correct yet.
Which is yeah, we don't have time probably to do that stuff today, but
let's just take a look.
Let's see if that no.
Did I do that?
Right?
So I'll test it.
I thought that would have.
I thought that would have been good enough to fix it, but it might
have been a different problem because we still, if you remember
correctly.
We still have the problem here.
Of making entities high frequency.
When we're doing the checks.
We have, we don't support the wrapping properly because we said we
weren't going to start wrapping and this would actually fail in
rapping, but you're not actually know why we didn't get the entities,
when I fixed that problem.
I also looks like he's not in the right position when he moves there.
So we've got some stuff.
We got a deal with here.
So let's go ahead and start our debugging.
Pass probably won't finish it, but we're compiling now, so that's
And we can finish it tomorrow.
In fact, it won't be long, right?
Because this tonight Thursday, so it's actually a morning tomorrow.
So it'll still be fresh in in our heads.
Okay.
So let's go ahead and take a look briefly at what's going on here.
Maybe I will go ahead and step through the that set camera call.
As a good example of seeing how things are working.
So let's go ahead and check this guy out.
Check.
We don't care about that function because we don't have any high
frequency entities yet.
So we want to do is take a look at our low frequency entities.
Presumably the problem here is the mint, I'll Mac style thing.
Yeah, so that's the wrapping problem.
So let me go ahead and set those 20 temporarily so I can see what was
actually going wrong.
Why?
The end of these weren't getting added to the high frequency list.
So, let's assume I guess the one with the easiest way to do that would
be to say, let's assume that we're going to add everything right.
Everything gets added.
So, here we go.
We go through here.
Same a Kennedy, high frequency.
We take a look at it.
Slow entity.
We see that it does not have a high-end V which is true.
We see that we have
Store it, which is also true.
We assign it a new index which is the first index.
Which seems also correct.
We grab its entity High pointer.
We initialize its entity High pointer.
What happens here?
So that's what reasonable.
That seems reasonable to me.
And off we go.
Okay, so that all seems pretty reasonable that looks like it's going
to make a bunch of high entities to me.
So what happened here?
Was it our rendering call that failed?
Let's find out.
We are hitting our invalid code path.
At May Kennedy high frequency.
So we added more than 256, of them.
Oh, right.
Because we were adding all of the entities that were in the world
entirely.
Well, that does seem a little bit odd.
Because there shouldn't have been more than two hundred, six entities
in the world total.
Correct.
Am I right about that?
So, I kind of feel like this is getting called more times than it
should have.
For example, if the high energy index was not being set, when an
entity actually goes into high frequency.
It looks like it is.
So I'm not sure why that would be, but let's take a look.
So if we go into the game State, and
Take a look here at the high end of these list.
All right.
So, let's see.
Looking through here.
Let's see.
What kind of numbers.
These are loaded index.
150.
Well, we have a lot of low entities.
I guess.
I take it back.
How do we have that?
Many, that doesn't sound like the right number of entities.
How many screens did we create?
We only created like two screens, right?
So, how many walls there that doesn't make any sense.
That feels like there's way too many low entities in the first place.
You know, I'm saying to you like it feels like add wall, got called
way too many times, but let's let's find out.
So let's see what happened there.
Let's see if I come in here.
All right.
I'm going to run to here.
Start the program fresh.
If I look at my game State, I've got one low entity, which is the
reserve.
No entity.
I'm going to gun run through here, and I guess I'll run through here.
One-time first, so let's run through here once.
Loaded account is 48.
Run through here again.
And what's our cap now, 94.
So there's only 94 low.
He's so this just looks like a typo bug where I'm incrementing?
Milo entities.
Ah, that's the problem.
I'm still doing a ray count on these guys, but we actually have a
regular.
Regular count now.
So this should actually be low entity count since we only have a
certain number of those and the same is going to be true for any of
these guys.
Okay, so, let's see if that's better.
I feel like that should be better.
Won't fix the problem, or it will fix the problem.
So,
Now, we are back to parody at least and that is a good place to leave.
It.
Still got a few more things.
We really need to do here though, because we got to start doing our
spatial partition, but it's getting better.
It's definitely getting better.
I think it's in better shape.
Now things are starting to shape up.
The reason that I like this is because we can start to see things
breaking off into nice little chunks, right?
I can start to see this looking like an actual engine that I could be
happy with, right?
Because we're starting to have nice.
Little Loops like I can imagine writing a nice fast loop.
That's a thing that goes through and checks things for whether or not
they need to be moved out of the high frequency set like that.
And I can see making a spatial partition, that accelerates that,
right?
The same is true for this other loop down here.
This one.
I think we could do the same thing for, right?
So yeah, I'm feeling pretty good about this.
I think we're getting to the point where this is probably what it
should be.
We just got to push a little further and just kind of massage
everything out into exactly where it's supposed to be, but I'm pretty
happy about this.
I don't expect this probably gonna be too many questions since this
was mostly just code rearranging stuff.
That's sometimes.
That's what you have to do.
Excuse me, but either way is time for the Q&A.
So let's go ahead and start the Q&A in case there are questions
because well, sometimes there are questions that even when you don't
expect it to be questions.
So let's go ahead and do the Q&A.
Please prefix your question with Q: so I can see it.
And also probably try to keep it for stuff we did today and stuff that
we did on or something.
We did the previous day's so that we're basically like, you know,
staying on topic.
You want to do off-topic chat, that's cool.
Just do it pre stream.
So come like 15 minutes before one of the scheduled start times and
that's when we do off-topic chat.
Is there an advantage of making the size of the low energy and high in
theories?
A power of 2, probably not, that was just me being a programmer and
oh, he's picking powers of 2.
We don't know what we'll do with these.
Like I don't know how big these will eventually be.
These will be based entirely on performance.
Will be seeing how many high-level entities we can support.
I'm guessing it probably actually be fairly High.
At the end of the day, but I don't know.
We might have a lot of complexity and how we do our simulations of
them.
So maybe maybe it really won't be that many.
Whereas the low entities will actually be quite huge.
Probably.
I'm imagining that low entities + like the properties.
Like how are we decide to store low enemies plus, their properties
will account for most of our game, memory is what I'm assuming.
So, yeah.
This is a third person game, right?
Yes.
It is a third-person game.
What process would you have gone through for creating a controls and
movement?
If This Were a 2d side-scrolling platformer?
No different.
Really?
We haven't done the controls yet though.
So you probably got to wait till we actually cover those.
Like right now we just have a stand and thing, right?
We've got like a stand-in thing that moves the guy around but that's
not really like what it's going to feel like because we got to do
animation first and integrate those two things together.
Other to see exactly how we want it to feel.
But yeah, we wouldn't really do all that much differently our
Collision detector, like basically right now gravity only happens when
this guy jumps whereas with a platform of gravity is more of a
concern, more of a going concern.
But otherwise, it's really mostly the same code.
Not that much of a difference.
Do you feel today will be re-written during optimization?
Yeah.
So again, all we're doing right now, is getting all of our stuff
arranged so that we know what our spec is, right?
It's basically so that we can see here is the layout of the code here,
are the apis to everything and then we can go to ok.
Now, let's go.
Write the final question.
Detector score at the final renderer.
Let's go write the final, you know, any system and they'll all be
based on exactly this work that we've done here in the first, you
know, two or three
Weeks.
Which is what we're doing here, is all about getting that out.
And so it's giving basically, you just need some substrate to start
working on those systems because without a substrate, you're working
on the systems in isolation and they will be bad and you'll have this
huge problem when you go to try and bring them together and you'll
realize they don't mesh well.
And so what you want to do is make a simple version that meshes well
and then start iterating on the system's themselves to get them up.
To where they need to be.
I don't know if it's been answered before, but did you consider large
fixed Point integers for both entity types?
Like, Tom Forsythe seems to prefer instead of having to swap between
floating point in the high-frequency entities.
So
I don't necessarily think there's, so here's the thing.
Being able to do everything in floating Point, has a lot of advantages
because really things are always set up for doing almost every
platform now has four wide floating-point, that's fast, right?
And it's usually faster than fixed point because fixed Point usually
takes two operations to do things that floating-point can do in one.
So I like to have everything work on floating point.
Locally around the camera.
That's the way I like to do things.
That's not to say that Tom is wrong about what he's doing.
He may be right?
That that's a good system for certain circumstances.
There's just this.
Not the way I like to structure the code.
So, the way I structure, the code that would be strictly slower.
If I did large fixed Point integers, but the way he structures his
code.
It might be the other way around.
Right?
So, what I like to do is, I like to have everything operating at float
in floating point at full speed.
For everything that you can see because you always can write.
And then the only time that I convert things out to integer to store
them, that's like the slow path.
And that's, you know, done separately.
And so you can already see.
We've gotten to the point where we've basically done that like, I've
already done that step.
So like the move player code that used to work in the other space is
now entirely done just all in float so we can optimize this really
well.
Now we'll be able to make our connection.
Entirely float based and then all we do is at the very end.
After all the computations are done.
We just map it back once and that's basically free, right?
So this way, I feel like it's kind of superior than trying to use
large fixed Point integers for actually doing computation because if
you do that, you can't go full speed in your main Loops, which I feel
like is not a good idea, but Tom may have different opinion about
that.
And so, you know, you should ask him about how he would structure
these sorts of things with with large fixed point.
Would it be?
Easier to keep a list of empty, empty slots to add them there.
Instead of always moving and changing and changing one of the
pointers.
I don't know.
Remember I said, I wasn't sure which one I would prefer and so, I just
did one of them.
I think it doesn't matter.
I think neither of them is better.
I think they're just the same.
The reason I chose this one in my head was just because it's less
complex because you don't have to.
Then have the concept that entities are marked as empty.
So when things are looping over them, they don't have to constantly
check.
Is there actually someone here or is there not some one here, right.
So that's why I did that.
It basically it keeps the complexity in the deletion code, which is
what's creating a complexity instead of spreading it out to all the
code.
So I felt like that was a better choice, but we'll see.
Are you familiar with slot maps for game object storage?
And do you think you'd use them for this project?
We use them for our engine, I might be, but I don't know.
The term slot Maps.
Can you describe it?
And then I can answer definitively.
So I'll have to give you a course.
I'll have to give you 20 seconds to answer because it's going to be a
delay of me.
Asking you to describe the slob maps and then you have to answer and
then I can see it on the twitch chat.
Somebody described the slot Maps.
Describe the slob Maps.
Nobody wants to scrap the slot Maps.
Well, unfortunately, I can't really say whether I think I would use
slot Maps if I'm not sure what you mean by slot Maps.
So, there's that.
Hello, Garland.
Oh, bloom.
Any thoughts on controls for h.h.
On controller list?
Touchscreen devices like tablets?
No, not really.
Because I don't like I've never had fun playing games made for
controllers on tablets.
So I'm a little bit like
I am weary of doing anything like that because I've never seen it
work.
Well, now, that doesn't mean after we're done with the game.
We couldn't go.
Hey, I guess the new product on handmade hero is to see if we can get
it on an iPad in a way that doesn't feel awful and maybe, you know,
maybe we could do that.
It certainly like a thing about my head.
I think it could be possible to do what I want to do at the game on a
tablet I guess.
But I don't really wanna think about that right now because I don't
play games on tablets.
So it's kind of an afterthought for me, but it's not to say that it
would be something fun to do later.
So maybe we'll do it.
I could get an Android tablet in here or something.
so,
Pseudonyms Timothy says, I think a slot map is just an implementation
of handles W indirect reference through a table.
So I don't know if we'll ever have to do that.
I suspect we probably won't need to do that.
Obviously, you want to avoid that if you can, because doubly indirect
references are slower than direct references.
So unless we had a really good reason why we need to W directory,
wouldn't
but, you know, if we need to, we need to
Will hear me here always be 20 scale feet.
Tall know eventually.
He will be scaled properly, but we don't really have any need to at
the moment.
What am I drinking water right now?
What I call a slap map is an array that can have arbitrary empty slots
and each slot has a virgin number for self-validation.
Yeah, I'm it doesn't seem like something we would necessarily need but
we might for transient entity stuff.
So we'll see if we could we might have something like that, but I
don't know.
Yes, it's a weird to call that thing a slot map.
It just sounds like a handle.
I mean, it's just it's just a.
Yeah, it's like, it's like the old Macintosh operating system, right?
It's like everything is a pointer to a pointer.
I'm not sure why you called a slot map.
But yeah, like I said, that's just that's just, like technique.
That's like, you know, will we be using linked lists possibly.
It depends if we need a linked list, right?
And so, yeah, we'll use a slot map.
If we end up in a situation where that's called for.
I wouldn't really consider that a major design decision though.
That's just a tool.
Like that's like, a hash table.
Sometimes you use it.
If the thing,
Also, our hash table, right?
So I don't know.
So we might have something like that in there somewhere, but I
wouldn't say it would be like a major feature anything or it's just a
little thing, you do.
All right.
Have we concluded?
I see no more questions.
I'll check for another few seconds to see if there is another.
Estrogen.
Know anyone?
All right.
So I think we are done.
The stream has concluded.
So we will call it.
We are almost at the point where I'm happy with the Highlight any
stuff.
But like I said, I want to do one more pass.
So tomorrow morning.
We will kind of go through and bolt a little bit more of this down.
And I'll probably like move like, I'll probably start moving things
off into a separate file.
Now that I kind of have like, what I expect from The Entity stuff.
You know, happening.
I'll kind of calves that off because it's starting to actually become
something in its own, right?
So that's what we'll do tomorrow morning since today is Thursday.
If I'm not very much an error.
It is in fact, the time flies.
So tomorrow 9 a.m.
Bright and early, it will be breakfast programming with Casey.
I may even have my breakfast with me.
I don't know.
I'm not maybe not, it's not I'm not going to promise something like
that.
I don't know if I'm gonna have my breakfast with, maybe I will, maybe
I won't write who's to say?
The point being.
Yes, of course, I want to stop debugging but point being, I would love
to see her tomorrow if you're so inclined.
For another day of programming here on Twitch, Don a.m.
Tomorrow morning, when we all sort of tidy up our entity situation and
then I don't know, we're moving on to next.
I guess.
The thing that we're moving on to next is I think I'm going to add
some entities and add some hit points and stuff like that.
So I can start to maybe balloon that out a little bit.
I don't know really hard to say or we could move on to animation and
save the rest of the stuff for a little bit later.
We also got to do 3D.
It's all some.
Yeah, so many things, so many good stuff, so many good things on the
horizon.
So, anyway, I hope you don't admire for the end of the Energy System
stuff.
If not, then I will see you back here on Monday 8:00 p.m.
60 times standard standard schedule on Monday.
Either way.
It has been a pleasure coding with you as always, if you would like to
follow along home to source code.
If you preorder the handmade Hero game on hand, me here at org.
You will get a copy of the source code and you'll get a link that you
can use.
Download the source code every night as well as the test assets that
we've been using here on the stream.
Those all come with it.
So check that out.
If you're interested in following along.
We also have a patreon.
You subscribe to if you want to support the video series and we have a
news inform site to check out if you're trying to follow along and
learn from the series.
It's a good thing.
It's got the schedule on there.
It's got an episode guide with past episodes.
You can go to to kind of catch up or review old material.
It's got coding resources, where people have ported the game to other
platforms and stuff like that.
It's kind of cool.
Check that out.
If you try and follow along or Mac on Mac or Linux, it's really really
handy because people have already done ports that you can look at and
we have a coating discussion board where you can post questions.
As an I asked questions on there.
So to other people, it's pretty cool place or just want to talk about
the series.
That's the place to go.
So, that'd be irate the and check out if you're trying to learn from
the series.
Hope.
See you all here again tomorrow, 9 a.m.
Again, and if not, I'll see you Monday at 8:00.
Either way.
Thanks for showing up and hope to see you back here is real real soon.
Yeah, I guess that's it at nine twenty.
Ten minutes early.
Good night, everyone.