Start recording.
Hello, everyone, and welcome to handmade hero.
The sure we could complete game live on stream.
We have taken the Bold sort of voluptuous step if you will into
Hardware rendering here on handmade hero.
So we now can actually switch our game between our own software
rendering path, where we render all the pixels, by our very own hands,
which of course is slower because we, you know, aren't taking
advantage of the giant GPU, that's in most machines.
But we now also have a path that does take advantage of that GPU.
Not really, to the fullest extent possible in the sense that we are
doing.
You know things in not necessarily most efficient way in there yet.
But even so it is a pretty dramatic increase in the frame time.
It's something like 20 times faster on the GPU than it is on the CPU
at the moment.
For example, if I remember correctly, maybe, not that much.
At least 10 times though.
And so we made that change.
But yesterday we sort of talked a little bit about the fact that there
are these extensions in opengl and some of those extensions are
extensions.
We actually need even if we don't write any shaders.
Even if we use what is essentially opengl one point x, which is what
we're calling right now to render our game, old old old.
You like, like our open GL code right now, would run this game on
Windows NT, 351 the very first version of Windows that's on the
Branch that we're even talking about would run.
That's how old opengl we are at the moment.
So we would went on literally anything like there is not a piece of
Graphics Hardware or software because it was software rendered in NT
351 in history that wouldn't render our game right now.
As far as I know,
but even with that,
there is one extension that we needed or I should say pair of
extensions and that is the fact that our Sprites all of our like our
assets are set up specifically to be in srgb color space now if you
don't know what that is go back and watch those episodes.
It's important understand why that makes a difference.
But point being we needed to use the extensions to opengl to tell it
that those were srgb Sprites other herb.
Textures, basically, when we use those textures because without that,
we get the wrong results for a rendering because the color values that
opengl is using are not, don't mean what it thinks they mean and then
we have a problem.
So we needed at least that extension.
Now what we did yesterday is we just kind of threw it in there and use
the extension but we never actually tested technically whether the
extension exists.
Now that's probably actually fine because I don't think there actually
is any hardware that any gamer is going to be using today.
That doesn't have the extensions that we chose to use.
To use.
But in order to make our code a little bit more correct and also
Same time to try to set us up for if we do need to legitimately query
some experts tensions, a little bit later on where we really don't
know whether the hardware that the person is running on will support
them.
We want to write a little bit more code to do that check again.
So that's what we're going to do today.
And then after that, I don't know, I guess it depends on whether that
how long that actually takes us after that, I'm not sure.
There's very much left to do with
are opengl stuff.
So I think we might have to wait till next week because we got to
start our next major task, which is getting our texture downloads to
happen in the background.
Because one of the things that you'll notice right now since we are
just doing a totally hacked thing to test because remember, I said, we
were just kind of put something in place when we run.
Our game.
You can kind of see that every time.
Well I don't know if you can see, it's not a stream.
Actually don't know how the video is, but point being at least when I
run it or if you run the game at home you can kind of see that when we
switch to from one game to sorry we switched from one cut scene to
another cutscene.
If that cutscene has like a lot of layers or whatever it may be, the
case that we get kind of like a pause in there, right?
Where the texture download, there's a little bit of a hiccup at least
I think.
Was it was happening.
I can't quite remember if we actually saw that for reals.
We'll see you in a second here if we, if we see it.
Let's just wait a little bit, just to ensure, let's see here.
It probably won't be 21 that like maybe that hat seen.
There'd be quite a few of them.
Well it's not just not too bad right now.
Actually those download seem to be going actually really well which is
nice.
Let's see about the Hat scene though.
Cuz that scene has several layers.
I never noticed those little Tomatoes back there.
I like that basket of tomatoes.
Yeah.
Okay, so you saw it.
Hopefully, you actually saw it.
There you have that really distinct jump.
And that's basically like, hey had to download just a few too many few
too much texture weight and their that one as well.
So somewhere around, you know, four layers or something when you get
to that, fourth layer, that's just too much and you notice that even
just in the cutscene.
So let alone in the game where we might be running around, and
something big pages in or something like this.
So, you know, we want to figure out how we're going to deal with that
part, in some way that makes it.
So that
Don't have this risk constantly that that we're going to have a frame
hiccup because the texture download had a problem.
Because in our regular source code, right, we don't have that problem
because we do everything on separate threads for asset loading.
So, there's no, the renderer never has to be in this situation where
it gets stalled, like that, we
Sorry, I'm kind of enjoying running around here in our weird little
groundless level.
Yeah.
Yeah, sorry, I should not be bothered that.
Let's clear this out.
There we go.
So anyway, that's the only gonna get worse by the way, because we're
pretty soon.
We're going to be working on game code, and I'm going to be sitting
there playing the game, and I'm going to forget that, I'm supposed to
be developing it and gonna be like, oh, it's fun.
And then it's like, all right.
Sorry about that.
So I was going to say is that's really the big thing.
We have to do it next week, so I'm guessing the today will be a pretty
light stream.
Maybe there's something else that I should do that, that we can think
of, at the, in the meantime, but I don't really know.
So I'm just going to go
Read and write that one piece.
And if it doesn't happen to take all stream, then we'll just we'll
figure it out, right?
We'll figure it out.
We'll figure out something else to do.
I'm sure there's plenty of to do is right, that we could do.
Maybe there's some simple in there.
All right, so hey Hardware acceleration is in there now and let's
leave improvements you probably don't care about.
So I think we're going to pretty good shape.
Now with that, that's kind of nice, this couple things in here.
We probably do want to think about you with like some of these things
are probably worth taking a look at anyway.
So,
What I was talking about before, right?
We have this win32, you know, in an opengl call and what I was talking
about with the extensions, right?
Is this part right here where we sort of have these extensions that we
want to use?
We want to enable these but we don't know whether we can enable them
or not.
Now, wiggle, swap interval.
We kind of don't really need to check for and the reason is because if
we get this function back then we pretty much know that the only thing
I could do.
So technically to be correct opengl.
I believe you're always supposed
Check for the extension string but really in practice we wouldn't have
to but with these we absolutely do have to because we have no idea if
the implementation will have any idea what this means and so I don't
even know what could happen, maybe it's fine to just pass a GL.
Enable that it doesn't understand, maybe it'll just ignore it.
And in that case, even in this case, we probably don't have to
actually check the extensions, but I'm not sure.
In general, probably does seem like if you wanted to rather be safe
than sorry.
Don't call a random driver with a random integer that it doesn't
expect.
Because who knows?
Maybe the thing just like up and crashes on you because it looks into
a table that's does not big enough.
You know, who knows what could happen?
So yeah, do you need to do it?
Could you probably leave it like this?
Yes.
Will we leave it like this?
I think it's probably best not to.
So I'm going to go ahead
And actually make these things work in some way, that's a little bit
cleaner than that.
So, first of all, I'm going to move these guys out of here.
I'm going to put these into opengl, the opengl code because that seems
like a better place for them, right?
And then in here, what I'd like to do is say okay, I'd like to because
these are the same on all platforms are not specific to Windows,
right?
So, I'm not gonna that's, that's why I'm not leaving them in the
winds, win32 side of things.
And so in here, what I want to do is
Have something called Open Jug section is available but the problem is
what I would like to do is I don't want to keep searching the entire
extension string thing every time necessarily.
So what I'll probably do is make a little thing here that just allows
me to check to see which extensions are available in which ones aren't
in just one sort of pass through right?
And and yeah it won't necessarily be it won't be as efficient could be
even more efficient if we use the hash table or something.
This but it's only a start up.
So it's not something that we really want to.
Engineer.
But what I would like to do is say opengl extensions like this and
then I would like to be able to check for those extensions as we go.
So I want to do something where it's like be 32 you know, for each of
these guys and I guess we don't, I don't remember which extensions
these are in.
So let's take a look.
Let's find out where that is.
Oh sorry I mean that
You know what I just realized.
All right.
Never mind.
I was going to say something and that something was stupid.
I was going to say, you know, I just realized how come it works when
we're passing rgba RGB eight?
When we're BGR and the answer is because this is opengl is internal
requested format, what it's going to store the textures as not the
submission format and we are correctly, passing be gra for the
submission format so it knows we were passing be generated data.
So that's, it's all.
It's all good.
So yeah.
So let's see.
Where is that specified?
What is the extension for that?
Is it this x texture srgb decode?
I guess.
I think that's the one.
We would presumably want.
Let's take a look here.
Srgb, does it actually Define srgb 8 somewhere so it should be eight
Senators.
Apply to the textures of us.
Want to have blah, blah, blah.
So, is this the one?
Is that the actual one that defines it, though?
So it was just this means that the normal linear educated for the
shine.
You could have just extra texture so they can be used with Samplers.
Yeah, yeah, I guess it's this one.
I guess, it's this one.
Add one new row.
All right, so I guess it's this.
I'm not 100% certain the extension stuff and opengl is not book keeped
as well as I would like to say, the very least anyway we'll do a be 32
of that that's whether or not that is their right and then we'll do
another one for a frame buffer srgb and we'll see if that's there as
well.
So that one is some other extension, our frame buffer srgb, that's
that extension.
And I guess we want
And I guess we want glr frame buffer srg because the wiggle one is a
given.
Since obviously, if this is there, then we can do the other one,
right?
So that should be fine.
So what we want to do now is we want to have a thing here which can do
check, you know, open gel check extensions.
And that seems like a pretty straightforward, right?
And what that's going to do is that's going to just assume that you're
in a context right now.
So you know, opengl Chuck extensions.
so that this can just be called and then I guess probably what we do
is, you know,
Maybe what?
Maybe we'll say opengl get extensions or something like this, it will
do it that way.
And then we'll just say like okay, you know, we'll call that and we
could find out what the extensions are, right?
And then we'll just say like okay whatever those extensions are
Will tell us what we wanted to know here.
So we'll just be able to say all right, this extra texture decode, if
that's on, then we can set our default internal format.
Similarly, we got the arm frame buffer one, so if that's on, we can
check it.
And then that is really, I think all we would need to do is take a
look here.
So then we set the Implement something that actually produces this.
So we'll start by saying all of the extensions are not available,
right?
Because that's the default state, is that we don't have any of them.
So then what we need to do is we need to ask opengl.
What are the extensions?
What extensions do you support?
And the way we do that is there's a GL.
Get string command in opengl.
Oh wait, we've got that cool doc site that someone sent in GL get
string.
So basically in opengl right, we've got this GL, get string call.
And what we can do is we can call this function, g, l, get string and
it will return like basically a string to us like so,
It will return a string to us and we can, we can sort of get all of
this information that we might want.
Now, as you can see,
There's actually, the extensions part is only just one of the piece of
information, you might want to get.
And so, while we're at it, I think it might be nice.
Since these are basically strings that stay around, there's things
that we can use.
We could do a thing where we just sort of say in here.
What all the parts?
What are all of the like
Language version.
Oops shading language version, we could just say what all those are so
that we always have them around as well in case like we're just
curious there we need to print them out or who knows what those may
come in handy later.
So, I think what I actually want to do is just save them all.
So maybe we'll say opengl opengl info may be right.
And so maybe this way we'll just say, oh it returns whether the
specific extensions that we're looking for there.
But it'll also include some other valuable information because we may
want that information for other purposes.
So we might as well just do that all in one place.
Since we don't really know what we might need and we're already in a
position where it's it makes sense to get it all at once because it's
like that's all the code kind of is in one place and makes sense in a
nice way, right?
So we'll just go ahead and grab these guys out here and get all the
strings and put them
Back where they belong.
There we go.
Okay, so we've got all of our strings in there now and all of these
are ones that we don't actually necessarily care about at the moment.
In fact what I can do to though it's like an I can sort of show you
guys that first, like we can actually go see what that actually is.
What you'll notice here is this one right now, we can't actually get
and the reason for that is that is in opengl 2.0 extension and we're
still in opengl 1.0.
So technically,
This guy we can actually get because hey opengl doesn't have a shading
language so it's not surprising that you can't ask what it actually
is, right?
So what I'm going to do here is I'm just going to put that in
something where we're just like you know what, there isn't one and
then we'll continue from there.
Alright.
So here is our our info now and our info, we can use it for these
purposes.
There we go.
And that's info.
Oops, info.
And so now when we run this, we should be able to do opengl
Info and take a look at what it actually says.
And this is the first time we've ever done this.
Like, I don't even know, I don't even remember what Hardware is on
this machine if I ever even looked in the first place, probably just
some point.
But here it is.
It's an ATI firepro V8.
700, it's running in 3.3 compatibility profile.
What that means is the
Real version right is actually open.
It's actually supports opengl 3.0 X.
Right?
So in fact, you can see, even if you come back here to talk about to
yell, you can sort of see what that entails, right?
So anything where there's a gl3 like active Shader program would not
work because it requires for but active texter would because that's in
three right or something right.
And here's the begin query indexed only in for, but begin transferring
for you back is in three.
So anything that's in three would work on this card, right?
Far as I know, there may be a couple things that have capability B to
them, but I'm pretty sure that, if, if you're in opengl 3.0 core, you
have to support them all, if you report that you're in, if you're
three, I don't know though, don't quote me on that.
So anyway, there we go.
We've got our opengl info.
We can see some information about the card and that's great.
But now we need to actually figure out what's going on with these
extensions.
So what I'd like to do here is just say like, okay, let's let's
Let's Loop through these and see what we've actually got.
So, once we have the extension string, we should be able to do
something.
Like, if you remember, when we did the stream where I showed, how to
make a parser, we should be able to do something that basically gives
us back one at a time.
These extensions and then we can compare them, right?
And look to see if they're equal.
So we want to do is do something that like goes through each extension
and they'll do like, you know, if string equals something like this
and I just can look for each of these
And I can probably do something actually like this.
if I want to be sort of Sly about it,
Right.
And, you know, we can make as many of those as we want.
So that would be pretty straightforward.
And you'll notice I just put it in 0 here.
So that all these cases, look the same.
Don't know why I did that.
I just thought it was nice to have each one.
Look exactly the same.
So, all we need to do now is have some kind of way of doing string
equals.
And like I said, we already did this on our parser, right?
So, when we did the simple preprocessor, for example, we have one
here.
That's like whether a token equals something right.
It was
In here sighs.
I thought we did.
Maybe I'm Wrong.
There it is.
So we're just talking about this code right here, right?
This is the exact piece of code that we're talking about, nothing
particularly fancy, but that's what it is.
And in fact, this token code is almost exactly what we want right now.
I don't know if we want to make this into a general-purpose thing.
I don't even know we may already have something like this in handmade
hero.
One of the things that were not particularly good with on a hero and
part of this is just the nature of the way that the stream is kind of
a have to be an hour chunks.
We don't have a lot of time for like Library,
Building where we're like, let's make good sensible place for these
things to live or whatever.
So I don't even know if we've got a string equals kind of stuff.
If I already have a function like that I might I might not and it
looks like maybe I don't at the moment.
That's what it kind of looks like to me.
So I'm going to go ahead and grab this guy out and I'm going to I'm
going to make him actually exist in somewhere.
So I don't know where to put it like I said, maybe we've got a
handmade string.h, maybe we're actually have that.
I kind of don't want to because I hope we don't have much.
Oh, there we go.
Strings are equal.
We do have.
It's right there.
Yep.
No worries.
At all.
All right, so if I just go ahead and grab this guy,
Yeah.
Look if I just grab this guy's thing and I say strings are equal and
then I have an a length and a and a b where the maybe the B is does
not has an unknown length to it, right?
Like we like that's an Ask easy string.
Then we can go through here and just do it this way.
So we say, at equals B, we have a length here.
That's a you, mmm.
Which by the way, was correctly, pointed out, that, that should be you
and pointer.
And then in here, we have pretty much the exact code we want.
It's just that, and, and that's the function.
Right.
So this allows us to do a thing where we basically inside here, go
strings are equal.
And this is the thing we're checking for, which is a Nancy Z,
terminated string.
And then the other string that we want here is just the like extension
count or like, you know what, maybe we'll just do, like count and
start something like that.
Counting at, I don't know.
Something like this.
And so here, what we can do is we
Get each individual extension and we can process it accordingly.
So, I'm going to start by saying at equals result extensions.
We're going to do a while loop here.
I guess, while at is actually pointing at something valid, then what
I'll do is, I'll say, all right, I'll stay with the end, it starts it
at and it goes until it hits.
Some kind of white space.
I guess in fact, when I probably should do, is something like while is
white space?
face start at Plus at so skip any white space that might be there then
I'll say while you know
Car car and he goes out there and I'll say while you know star end and
it's not white space.
You know, I'm saying, I'm going to advance end so there's this can to
the end of it.
So now I have like where it starts and where it ends and so then I can
just say like okay the count for this guy.
is just going to be whatever the end is minus, whatever the ad is,
Makes sense.
And so that's how long the thing is.
And the at is is exactly what the app should be.
So then we can do our comparisons and then at the end after we're all
done.
We can just say at that point, start at wherever we end it and keep
going from there.
Make sense.
So I'm literally just like, picking out strings out of this extension
thing, which by the way, I suppose, I never mentioned so you guys
don't actually know why I'm parsing it.
This way, the extensions that come back is just a giant long really
long string and each each extension name is just stuffed into the
string with, like, a space in between it.
So you'll see in a second.
So really all we need here is the white space part of it and I don't
know if we've got a white space tester, we do.
So we'll put that in there as well.
In fact, I don't know, we might want more of these eventually, but
okay.
So, anyway in handmade that H, I don't think we have an is white
space.
Yeah, we don't.
So we do now.
And so end of the line, we also need because that those depend on each
other looks like, there we go.
And we can sort of
D Bula.
Fire those
Like so.
Alright so inside handmade opengl.
That stuff is in what handmade dot h which I don't think it's actually
installed here.
So what I probably want to do is put these somewhere where they can
be.
Just as like a commonplace so maybe the platform where we have some of
these like little handy functions here.
Those can sort of get thrown in there.
Maybe down in here.
Okay.
Oh, that's gets me every time I keep forgetting that, we decided to
make this see linkable for people who are reporting to other
platforms.
Hmm.
So I kind of need like a shared Library place.
I need like a handmade shared dot h or something like this, right?
Something that we know, gets included in everything.
And I'm not sure.
What just happened?
Why are we not?
Why is handmade shared .h?
Not a C++ mode thing.
I don't even want to know.
No, I don't want to know handmade shared .h.
There we go.
So, I just kind of need some place to stick this stuff.
I feel like that's going to be included in both places, right?
So handmade .h, right?
It can include, it could include this stuff and then we can start
sticking things in there.
That makes some sense, so it's like handmade shared .h, it's in there,
but then it's also in like win32 handmade .h.
It's also in here.
That makes sense probably after intrinsics.
In fact intrinsics and math could actually be included inside this so
it could be something like this even
Right.
And that way in here, we just we just assume that those are going to
work that way, right?
Okay, let's see.
Where are we here?
Gotta put some parentheses in there.
All right, so let's go ahead and go a little further with this and and
try to get this working.
So, let me just show you before I go any further with the programming,
I just wanted to show you guys what I meant about that extension
string.
So here is the extension string.
And as you can see, it's just a giant ol mess.
But basically what it is, is the extensions are just every extension
name that this particular graphics with this particular opengl.
Implementation supports is stuffed in here somewhere, so you can even
see, like here is the one that we wanted.
GLX frame buffer srgb, right?
That happens to be
One that we're looking for glr.
Oh sorry, I know.
That's the EXT one we were looking for the ARB one.
Maybe we should look for the extra one actually, but there's GL, ARB
frame buffer srgb right there.
So both of those are listed as being exported, maybe we should use the
X to 1 because the X1 probably is even older, right?
And it would support more cards.
I don't know which one we want there, but then there's X texture srgb.
Decode.
And, and that should be in here as well.
I would think srgb.
So, it looks like that's actually called X texture srgb, not decode.
So, the decode one is probably a different one.
This is why I was saying, is having trouble figuring out which one was
supposed to be.
So I think we actually want it to be this.
I think I just was asleep at the switch there.
I think that's what we actually want and I just don't know.
I suspect we probably want
my guess is we probably want the extra RG because that's probably the
one.
That's that's further back if that makes sense.
Let's just let's just find out.
So let's see.
Oops, I meant frame buffer.
Where'd that guy go?
GLX frame, buffer srgb.
So yeah, so if we use this one, instead of the are blown, the extra
ones come first before they get promoted to our extensions.
Like I mentioned on the previous Stream So that one might actually
have have more support for it further back now, probably it won't
matter.
Like I said, because these are extensions that almost every graphics
card probably has now I suspect but point being, you know, if we're
being proper about it which we're trying to be, then that is just the
way that is.
So let's go ahead and
This in here.
And then we'll take a look.
So what I'd also like to do is verify that they are the same ID so I'd
like to verify that they're the same here.
So I'd like to figure out what g l frame Beaufort, srgb is defined to
in this extension, if we can, which I don't know if we can or not.
So let's see.
It's it.
Is it
Eight DB9.
Yes.
So there it is, right?
So that's what we want and it's frame buffer, srgb.
EXT is the name of it, which I don't know if we actually need to
change it, but that should be fine.
All right, so that all looks reasonable now to me.
But now we still have to actually implement this code for actually
checking the extensions.
So let's go ahead and recompile this guy here.
Oops.
Pretty 32 on there.
And this is
That one, this.
Is that one?
So anyway, if I run through here now and I get to my extensions.
So now I'm just going to like get this parser working so let's see.
So there's at we skip the white space which in this case there isn't
any we take a look at where the end is and let's see if that should
that should point to the space that next space there.
And it does, which is exactly what we want.
Let's look at the count, the count is 14, but that's 14 hex.
The count is actually 20 so let's see.
1 2 3 4 5 6 7 8 9 10 11 12, 13 14 15 16 17 18, 19, 20, exactly what we
want.
Let's see about strings are equal.
We'll call those we then do adequate Zend and we start here.
So, now we come through and we're at White space, so we skip the white
space and we keep going.
Okay.
So that all seems pretty good and let's see if we actually correctly,
identify these guys.
It looks like we did in both cases.
So I think we're all good.
I think we've got a parser.
Now that actually works.
Okay, so that's the extension person in a nutshell.
Yeah, we we got a ton of time left though.
I mean honestly we've got like 20 or 25 minutes left so I guess.
Yeah.
I guess.
We're going to have to do something else that will take about 20
minutes, because there ain't much more to say about extensions that I
didn't just do, so we can get rid of our to do.
That's that's all good.
And, you know, I guess, one of the things we could do here is inside
handmade opengl.
We could actually, we could actually make this be a more common thing
because, you know, we could do something like opengl
It up or something like this.
You know, we're open Jill initialisation or whatever and this part is
going to be common.
Right across all of our platforms because we're going to want to check
for these same extensions.
We're going to want to use all this stuff.
So what we could do is just say, hey everyone could call that.
And the only thing that the platform used to do is anything that's
specific to it like this wiggle, swap interval part of it, right?
so that seems probably like more saying thing to do at that point,
Yeah.
That's what I think so yeah.
That's it for that and I'm not sure what else we would do with opengl
here.
That would only take 20 minutes.
That's kind of a tricky question.
So well, we could try to put in buffers.
I don't know that buffers will make any difference here because the
texture changes are going to be the thing that's going to be
problematic there.
So yeah, maybe we could try baby while we're in the middle of
implementing, you know?
Maybe while we're implementing extensions.
You know what we should do because this is probably going to be
important for our texture downloads.
What we should probably do is do show how to do context escalation.
That's probably the, that's probably the most sensible thing to do.
All right.
So I talked about this a little bit before but I'll just say it again.
So, opengl has gone through many revisions obviously in its history
and you sort of a scene a little bit of a, how that works.
And I explained it a little bit more detail, so go back and watch
yesterday's episode.
I think is where we talked about this, but I'll just say it again.
What happens in opengl is the initial version that shipped with
Windows was opengl one point x.
I can't remember exactly which one it was like, 1.1 or something?
Like this.
Maybe it was one point two.
And
And, you know, as it went, it opens yells evolved away from there but
Microsoft never bothered to update the bindings and windows at all and
they never bothered to require a newer version of opengl.
So, you know, you can still ship an opengl one point X driver if you
want.
And the reason for that, of course, is that they have skin in.
They want DirectX to be the primary Graphics things so that any chance
they get, they try to make opengl less attractive.
That's just and again, that's not me being flippant.
I actually I know lots of inside information about those.
Things and and they really are exactly that awful there.
So basically what happens is all of the opengl progress comes from the
driver manufacturers for the most part and and Microsoft gets dragged
along kicking and screaming with that.
And so what happens is, the driver writers themselves are.
The people who are updating opengl, right?
So when you actually pounded kludgy L.H with, we did to access the
windows.
All findings you really including what amounts to a you know decade or
two old set of bindings and everything else that has come since then
you have to get by querying and using these extensions.
Now extensions are an actual first class citizen in opengl.
In the sense that it's meant to be extended and vendors are allowed to
add their own extensions.
So they
These extensions.
But over time, the extensions get cooked sort of agreed upon as
generally useful things and when they agree that a bunch of these
extensions is going to become sort of a new version of opengl.
They update the core version number so it becomes opengl 2.1.
Opengl 2.2 opengl 3.0 opengl 4.0 whatever right?
and so what they did with opengl 4.0
Actually be honest, maybe I've done this in 33 point.
Now, I can't quite remember when they introduced this opengl to didn't
have it but opengl 33, maybe had it.
What they did is they said okay opengl 3 adds a ton of stuff,
mandatorily like opengl 3 requires that you have a certain set of
shading language is available in certain Shader stages and all this
stuff.
So opengl 3.0 requires a bunch of stuff, opengl 4.0 requires much
stuff, which means that you don't have to query.
Each extension piece mail to find out what you can use.
You can just say are you opengl 3?
If you are, I just assume that you have all this stuff and you better
run.
Right.
So opengl 3
There's a way we can query for an opengl three context and that opengl
three context.
If we get it, we know that we have everything that we might need and
since almost everything that you're going to run on these days is an
opengl three context or above.
That's a pretty good idea.
Do we need to do it?
Not necessarily, but
That same process that allows you to query for a more modern coal
context, rather than querying extensions.
Piece of mail that exact process actually allows you other options
that you don't have.
When you normally create a context, one of, which being the ability to
create more than one context, so that you can use it on multiple
threads and still have them.
Share texture handles.
And so, what you can do with that is you can actually use that to say,
download textures on one thread while you run the game and render on
another thread without those Khan.
Those contexts fighting each other because I believe the actual
requirement in opengl is that you are not allowed to use the same
context on two threads at the same time, it's single-threaded that
way.
So if you want to use a context,
In two different threads, you actually to make two different contexts.
But if we make to context and we start sending textures down on one
context and rendering on the other, if we have no way of telling
opengl that they're sharing their texture handles, there's no way to
actually benefit from that.
Now, there are some ways you could do that in the old days but it was
all kind of a hack.
And so, what I'd like to do is go ahead and use the actual context,
escalation stuff to sort of show.
How
Yet one of those open till three contexts and then we can use that
when we need to next week finish off our base implementation of
Hardware acceleration by downloading Textures in the background on a
separate thread.
That isn't the main thread just like we were loading our asset.
So that's what we want to do, right?
Okay, so let's let's do that.
This is a win32 situation.
Obviously because when we create the context, Truman 32, when we do,
we will create context.
Now, this is going to look like it's pure banana cakes.
Again, like I said, this is because Hardware vendors don't have a lot
of choices.
Microsoft doesn't really help them out here.
So I don't really know that you can blame and video or ATI for this
sort of thing.
I'm sorry, AMD, but when you call Regal create context, we will create
context.
As you can see, takes no, actual parameters.
Right.
It just creates a context.
So by default, what it does.
Is it creates a context?
That's only requirement.
Is that it at least support opengl like 1.1 or like I said, whatever
that first version is that ships in here.
Okay?
So, opengl, like 1.1, or whatever is what it will give us back.
If it has the capability of doing more, it will give us back more
potentially, right?
But we're not asking to require that so everything that we might want
to.
We have to query as extensions and that's just the name of the game,
right?
Okay, however, what you can do?
Is use a extended opengl function again like I said everything's
extensions because it has to be and it's called ARB create context.
And what that extension does is it allows you to call a new thing
where instead of just asking for a contact in general, that's
arbitrary.
What you can do instead is request a specific set of features for your
context that it must have and those are set.
I don't even know where they're listed here.
Here they are.
You can require a specific major version, a specific minor version,
certain other aspects.
Like for example I there's a bunch of flags we could set and those are
like whether we want them to be debug compatible whether we want them
before we're compatible right?
Whether we want them to be core compatible things like this can be set
in here and these are basically things.
Which control what kind of context we expect to get back?
So, if we want to do this, what we need to do is get a handle to this
wiggle, create context that ribs function.
And then we need to call it, okay?
And we've already seen exactly how to do this.
So, this should not be a mystery to you.
We already know exactly how it works.
Gets the same as what happens here, right?
All we need to make.
This happen is a typedef of what we expect, the functor should be
since he knows how to call it.
And then we need just somewhere to put it.
We don't really need to keep it in a global variable because we're
never going to call this function other than a start-up time.
So we can just say this wiggle kind of at ribs are that we call once,
right?
So we can take this guy and we can we can call them just one time.
All right.
So let's go ahead and do that.
Remember like I said, this is totally something is exactly just going
to do.
The same exact thing we already did.
So there's absolutely nothing bizarre going on here.
You can see how we did, this will get Brock address but we're going to
do that exact same thing.
So here we are.
Only I'm going to put this above the in it actually.
So we can do this.
We will create context of trips are.
We could say, hey, let's see whether or not this thing exists.
So I'll say again exactly the same thing as here.
No change.
The only difference is now we're going to use will create, contexts
are as the function.
If that comes back.
then we now know that we are in, you know, this is
Or I should say a modern version of open of gel.
Whereas here it would be
This is an antiquated.
Version of opengl.
Okay, so in the modern version of opengl, what we can now do is we can
call this
Function to get what we actually want.
And again, we pass Pace with the same things.
We pass window DC, we do a share context, right?
And a share contact is actually pretty important.
We don't need to use it yet, if that makes sense.
And the reason we don't need to use it yet is because like I said,
we're not actually creating a second context for texture downloads but
that's exactly what that's going to do like what we can do now, it's
in a way that we
Couldn't before we create a context is passed.
Some other context that we want to be able to share all of our data
with which is exactly what I said we wanted.
And the whole reason why we probably really want to use the modern
contexts, right?
So we don't actually need to shortcuts.
That's fine.
But we do need to use those at ribs and those at ribs are basically
just like a list of pointers to it's right?
So it's basically this
Just a big old list of events.
And then the inst describe, what actually has to happen.
Now, we need all of these guys, right?
We need all of these guys to be defined and they're not defined right
now.
And so what we want to do is in opengl in our inner opengl thing, we
want it sort of a window specific area.
And it's, we don't have to isolate these.
These don't have to be isolated because there's no harm in defining
the windows things here, right?
They can we
To find the Windows 10, the Apple.
Once your we can Define everything because they're just pound to fines
that are just generally true and and we just would never touch that.
We never actually use those right on the on other platforms.
So that's totally fine.
So then in this at ribs these come in pairs, right?
So we can say is like oh we want to Major version we'd like our major
inversion to be at least three.
We want our my minor version to at least before I don't know what a
layer plane ARB even is so I'm going to look that up because I don't
think I've ever asked for that.
The layer plane to the render cost is bound to the attribute.
Value has the same meaning and allowed values.
Is the layer playing parameter of will create content layer, conducts?
What is this?
I don't even know what that is.
It's looks like it just if I want to if I have a display that supports
multiple planes that are maybe we combined it Hardware time.
Yes, this is just for overlays which we don't care about at all.
So we don't even need to specify that.
I don't think we can just skip that bit entirely.
So, what we need our flags though.
Let's put some Flags in there.
Oops, put some Flags in there are flags are, whether we want
debugging, and whether we want forward compatibility, I assume for
compatibility means, should you give us access to more stuff?
I think the answer there is probably always, yes.
And do we want debug?
Well, probably, if we're in debug mode, we would want debug, right?
So probably we'd want something like will always take forward
compatibility.
If you've got it and then,
Maybe we'll do this or maybe we won't, right?
So we could do something like handmade internal will ask for a debug
guy, otherwise not probably, right.
And then we've got our profile mask and the profile.
Mask is just specified as whether we want core or compatibility right
now, we're going to want compatibility and the reason for that is
because technically the functions that we used like if we
Go over here to our handmade opengl that CP the fixed function
pipeline.
Remember, I said we're gonna start with a fixed function pipeline,
which I showed you here.
The fixed function pipeline doesn't exist in modern versions of
opengl.
They got rid of it, everything goes through shaders.
So you have to just write dummy shaders.
If all you wanted was the fixed function stuff, you still have to
write little dummy.
Shaders.
That just don't do anything, but they still to be there, right?
And so we want a compatibility profile because what
It says is hey don't give me only the 3.0 stuff.
Give me the old stuff as well so I can use it.
Now, that's not guaranteed to succeed.
A implementation doesn't have to support the all things, which is why
I said, eventually we want to just move away from it and not call the
fixed function anymore.
I just wanted to show you how to do that, because that was the
original opengl in the modern opengl.
It's really not that much different.
It's, you know, you can still understand it pretty easily if you see
this stuff.
But again, some of the stuff goes away, we'll want to remove that as
we move to shaders, which we want to do anyway, because we're going to
have a couple special effects and kind of things that probably want
the ability to reach in there and muck with exactly what's happening
in the shaders.
We would probably not want the fixed function pipeline to be.
The only thing we have access to, anyway, so that's
A hassle in any way.
We're, we would have had to do that work, regardless, if that makes
sense.
It's just, you know, once, you know, one step at a time, so I think
this is everything.
I believe the way you end, this is by terminating it with a zero, but
let me see.
The list consists of a sequence of name, value pairs terminated by the
value 0.
So that's what we want.
So there's our at ribs, here's our context call.
And here's our modern context.
And then in here we can say, like, okay, if we were able to get a
modern context, then let's go ahead and switch to the modern context.
Right.
And we can even delete our old context, right?
We can get rid of our of our opengl RC
Right.
So we can just straight-up swap them.
And so this is why I called it.
You'll notice the thing that I said originally was like, hey it's it's
like escalation the reason I called it context exhalation was
specifically because in order to call wiggle get proc address, you had
to have created a context.
First, you can't actually call wiggle create context of trips are,
until you've made an existing opengl context of version 1.
So you basically have to like, say I'm
In my opinion, your stuff.
So the driver can get up and going, then you say, hey, by the way, are
you a new one?
I know like, Microsoft doesn't want opengl to succeed, so they didn't
actually bother to make a good way to do that, but hey, could you give
one to me and they're like, yes, right?
And so you do that and then you try to create one, if it succeeds.
Now you can switch up to the modern version.
Makes sense.
So that's how you do that.
Oops, that's an S60 for, that's how you do that.
And so let's see if it works, right?
Because again like I said, all this stuff is kind of a little touchy
so you know, maybe I forgot something.
You'll note, I do all this stuff kind of from memory and you know I'm
old.
So anyway where is my opengl went through to and it opengl here it is.
So here we go.
Let's step in here and we're going to ask to see if we can get our
contract.
Trip art function.
You can notice that we did get that, right?
And I point out something else interesting about this because this is
some stuff that people were sort of asking about the the drivers to.
Oops, that's not what I want.
So, you can see.
If we inspect this value note, where it's pointing its pointing into
the ATI driver, right?
So when we are making these function calls, we're not going into a
library, right?
This is what I was kind of try to explain before when you link with
the opengl library, you're not really linking with a library.
You're just connecting yourself with the actual driver.
That's doing the work, right?
That's actually what's
and so in this case, we've asked for a function and now we're, you
know, we're, we're basically calling directly into it because unlike
when we link with the library and it uses an actual import table,
we're actually getting the thing back directly ourselves.
And so now we call into it via pointer, instead of it, patching up our
code, right?
So we get that now we know we can call it.
So we create our list of attributes which you know, is everything that
we might want there.
And then we come through and we can call create context of trips Barb.
You can do it that took a while, that's because now, the HCI driver is
going off going, okay?
All right, let me get all that stuff set up for you and then we got
back a context so it worked so that's good.
Which means we can escalate we're now on opengl 3.0 which is fine.
We can delete our
Context and off we go.
So now we're actually running in opengl 3.0.
What that means is that these are actually Superfluous calls because I
believe all this stuff is required in opengl 3.0.
I don't think you can, I don't we don't really need to check this
actions but we might as well because this allows us to run on older
Hardware even than 3.0 if we wanted to so there's no real reason to
get rid of it, right?
It just gives us a little extra layer potentially a backwards
compatibility.
So yeah, unfortunately from what I can see here when we're on the
modern 3.0 it looks like it doesn't want to let us use the old
compatibility stuff, right?
It looks like we're not getting any rendering there and the only
difference was that we asked for a 3.0 context so I'm guessing that we
didn't actually get back a compatibility profile.
Maybe
We asked for one, we asked for one right here, but we didn't get one.
I'm curious to know I'm going to try.
I want to try without this guy.
But I'm curious to know why that didn't work, but we're doing
something that the 3.0 context like doesn't like, right.
So okay, so it's the for capital B.
Let me go read.
What that does I must have misunderstood what the forward compatible
bit?
Is it probably prevents you from doing anything that's going to get
removed or something like that.
Let's take a look.
So, there it is.
If the wiggle context for it can pedal a bit are beset in wiggle
context, flags are been a fork and pedal contacts will be created for
Cabella costs are defined only for opengl version 2.0 later, they must
not support functionality marked as deprecated.
okay, so basically what we want to do is we don't want to actually
specify this
Probably at all actually, but we might want to do it for testing,
right?
If that makes sense.
So I think that's everything we want to do.
So I'm going to go ahead and call that the end of the screen because
now we have that profile.
And so now once you have that, this means you can use shaders.
You don't have to query even and extensions for them.
You can just straight-up use shaders and and that will tell you what's
going on.
Now, what also will work there as well, is we could now if we wanted
to, we could query the shading language
Version as well.
The only problem is, we have to go to find that string.
We have to Define GL shading, language version and we could actually
do that now, right?
So we could say, let's see where that's actually to find somewhere.
I don't know where.
I've no idea where
tell me what the value is.
0x something fine.
I did this the other time do it again.
Where did I had it the other day?
Opengl extensions.
Header file.
Where did it go?
Because in one of the it was in one of these but I got guy jumped
right to it before and now it's like mr.
Doesn't want to do that for me.
There it is.
Core ARB shading language version.
And so the question that I have and I don't really know if it's true
or not but I guess.
I guess we don't want to do this unless we know for sure that we've
got a more
In context, right?
So what I might say is inside here, right?
Will Define the sky.
GL shading language version, so that we can call this, but maybe what
I'll do is something like this.
So that I know that I'm only asking because I don't know which
versions that would be allowed.
We could query an extension for it and then asked but I feel like this
is probably safer, right?
And maybe I'll do a thing where we just say modern context is actually
in here as well.
so that way, we'll say,
This will be something we actually pass through.
Right.
And we could add another layer of security here, potentially something
like this just in case that that fails
we could do it only if that actually worked
opengl get info.
Actually needs to pass this context.
And so now we should be able to see the shading language version as
well.
So when we jump in here, at least in theory, when we call that our
result is,
Is it tell us?
So opengl 3.3 is the latest I'm sorry.
Glsl 3.3 is the latest shading language.
We'd be allowed to use right?
There is later shading languages.
There's a, there's a shading language for and and we can't call it on
this graph screen because it grabs cards from like 2010 is pretty old
at this point.
So there you go.
That's it.
That's how you do that.
Start up.
So hopefully now everyone's got that under their belt.
This is happy and great and so we can go to the Q&A for a little
while.
We got about 11 minutes left.
So if you got questions, let me know what they are.
Icarus looking at win XP and cards.
Looks like they need GL 2.0.
As the max that can support more or less if you use Tiara cards.
Yeah, I would suspect.
I mean,
Going like I said, back all the way GL 1.0 I think or maybe 1.1
something like that was what was originally in Windows?
By the time when XP came around, I would.
Yeah.
I'd be pretty surprised if there was anyone who wasn't at least 2.0,
but I don't know.
In the function opens you'll get info.
Why do you do an if 0 else end if rather than just commenting it out?
I'm not sure what you're talking about.
Do you mean this thing?
It was because I wanted to keep both cases and for the very slick,
reason of, as you noticed, I eventually turned it into a real.
If is that what you're talking about?
Not sure.
Let's see.
It's a far as for srgb.
Do you have also have to set wiggle frame, buffer, srgb capable ARB
when you choose the pixel format?
Or is that something different?
You know, I have that exact same question and I do not remember
I really don't know and the documentation is so crappy like that
should be pretty much obvious whether you have to do that or not, but
unfortunately, it's like not that obvious so we could try to figure it
out.
obviously, it's pretty easy for us to set that, but
Capable car.
Let's see.
this, this guy is pretty uninspiring as a
Actually, it's not what I want.
Wiggle frame, buffer srgb.
Accepted by the pi r, choose parameter of Wiggle, get pixel format, a
trip, VX We Go, premium will choose wiggle, choose pixel format EXT,
accepted by the cap parameter.
So if we wanted to call wiggle, choose pixel format EXT.
Maybe that would be the place where we could do that.
So, here's wiggle, X pixel format.
This is that's functions to query pixel format attributes and to
choose from a list of pixel formats supported by a device.
So here's some extra ones that allow us to say other things.
So like yeah, you can see
There's a bunch of stuff.
Overlays underlays swap methods.
um,
so the question is, do we need it?
And I don't know.
I'm not sure.
Let's see.
Components.
This is working.
Boots are taken to be fixed Point values.
Yep, if framebuffer srgb is enabled and the value of Fame of
attachment color, encoding for the frame buffer Testament, correspond
to The Coasters.
Srgb.
so, I'm gonna have to say,
I'm gonna have to say possibly?
Yes.
Face on that sentence.
because the way I read that,
Is is saying that if frame before srgb, is on only if the actual frame
buffer that you're using is marked as srgb.
And ours won't be.
Unless we specify that
Which would mean I think in order to get it actually working, which we
think we do want to do, because our textures will be right, but our
frame, buffer would still be potentially wrong weight.
It
the thing is,
I guess well no we want it basically just gives us another level of
accuracy, right?
Instead of treating the frame buffer as linear all the time.
So around the outer edges, it's going to be really subtle but it would
matter.
It could, it could it would actually matter.
So, I think what we would want to do is, we'd have to do the wiggle,
the extended pixel format, right?
We want wiggle, choose pixel format.
Something like this, right?
I think we'd want to actually call whistle wiggle, choose pixel,
format arm, and I think we want to do it.
So we want to do that on Monday.
Because yeah, I think the only way we can actually ask for that is
through this, I don't think we could set it using the choose pixel
function that we're currently using.
Maybe I'll have to do because I do think we want that and it does
sound like from reading the extension that it won't work.
That's what it sounds like.
May I ask you a question mark because I guess we're not really so sure
about that.
Let's see, Colombian for Connor rents to just left.
What is, um, data type and what is it used for?
I will watch this recording that is just an unsigned memory sized
integer.
So, it's basically like 64-bit on a platform that 64-bit pointers
32-bit unsigned on a platform that's 32-bit pointers so it's um,
pointer tea.
Well yes that's what I'm talking about.
I didn't notice you did more of their okay sign ekron, what's the
difference between srgb and rgba that is covered in a lot of detail
back in the previous dream.
So I would go walk I'd watch the streams on srgb encoding.
Well to be honest I don't know that we really cover it all that
thoroughly we covered gamma correction and that's what it is.
But srgb is a particular color space.
Right.
So srgb.
Is a color space.
And it's a color space that has a particular gamma curve.
That's like it's like to point to its.
I think it's like to point to gamma curve.
So it's like it's, you know, it's it's whatever the color is, it's
raised to the 2 point, 2 power everywhere except down at the bottom
where it's not where it's linearized out.
And particular way, I don't remember the exact specifics, but it's,
it's the one that adobe proposed, and it's the kind of the prevalent.
That that gravis cars Implement and you can kind of see here.
Let's see where is
Where's the actual curve?
I don't actually want perceived intensity, is I just wanted just
wanted the actual curve.
I like, what is srgb?
And why is it so important for e-commerce?
I was like, okay, I don't know that I would have thought it was that
important for e-commerce but I guess it is.
I'm always bad finding graphs on the Stream.
I don't know, I don't know where it is, but point being
There it is.
This is the image.
I think I wanted.
There we go.
So point being, as you can see it's a pretty close.
It's pretty close to just 2.2 but it's not exactly the same.
And why it's not the same, I do not remember, it's some finicky
reason, like it wanted to be more well-behaved numerically at the
bottom or something like this.
So, it's basically the same gamma curve as a monitor was, with the 2.2
standard way that they used to be, but it's a little bit different and
now all monitors have a, an srgb mode that you should set your monitor
to, by the way.
That's, that's that curve.
So anyway, srgb is just that encoding and so it's a, it's a way of
encoding colors color values such that they more closely put the
detail like where they put the resolution of the color space, where
your I can see it rather than where it can't.
And so what happens with a gamma curve, right?
Is if you imagine a linear brightness response.
So here is like the input color value.
Here is like the color value from 0 to 255, that we might specify look
in the in the game.
Or 0 to 1 point 0 if you're in floating point, right?
And here is the brightness that the monitor outputs
that makes sense.
If you're linearly outputting brightness, then what happens is, you
end up with the resolution in in the wrong places because your eye up
here is really bad at perceiving.
The difference between brightnesses, so like bright.
Is hard to discern.
The difference between a point here and a point here for your eye, to
discern.
In terms of brightness, it's hard for it to tell, right?
However, down here in the dark areas, it's easy to discern.
So, if you have a point here and a point here, your I can very easily
tell them apart.
So what that means is, if you for any given encoding encoding them,
linearly means either, you'll have way more either, you'll have way
more sort of resolution in the brights than you want in order to get
the resolution of the dark that you need or
The brights are roughly how much you need.
The darks will be way underrepresented and you won't have enough
resolution.
So, the solution to that is to use a curve.
So that as you go from 0 to 255, or 0 to 1, depending on which one
you're doing, as you go through that curve, you have lots of values
down in the darks, right?
Because you notice the same number of dark values output to a very
small range of brightness has.
And then, you have very few values up in the brights,
So like, you know, five steps up in the brights, might account to like
some big area here, whereas five steps up in the darks, or counts for
only a very small area here, so that it's basically just bending that
curve to give you the output resolution where you actually want it so
that you don't have to to transfer 16 bit color.
Sample per Channel, 16 bits per channel, to get the resolution.
You can just use 8 bits per Channel, which is really actually kind of
important.
Because even today, right?
4K monitors, you have to go to HDMI 2.0, just to get 60 frames a
second on those.
Right?
I think it.
Can you even?
I don't even have, you can't, I think that can do it.
But point being all that stuff, like the cable quality and the HDMI
specs and all this stuff, those are all fighting to give you enough.
If bandwidth to the monitor right to actually be able to run games at
high res, at high frame rates.
And if you start throwing away that bandwidth there by saying, okay,
now we got to have 16 bits of color to represent.
What we need to represent or something, right?
You're totally through, you're totally ruining your ability to get
high res, High frame rate because you're wasting it all on these extra
bits that you didn't really need if you just had a smarter encoding.
So that's why you need these gamma aware and Coatings.
That's not to say that eight bits is really enough.
Even with a gamma encoding, you probably want more like 10 bits or
something.
I'm guessing, maybe even more as displays become more High dynamic
range.
You may be mean me even more like 12 bits or 14 bits.
Who knows, right?
But point being no matter how many bits you use, even if you use that
many bits you you want to maximize that value per bit by putting the
curve to align with your eyes, perceptual ability so that you're not
throwing away.
It's on the on the high end or having too few bits on the low end.
Let me just check to see if there's any other questions before.
I sign off.
Any other questions that like need to be answered?
That are pressing.
Pressing.
I just checked my Dell monitor.
It has Adobe RGB as a well as srgb modes and they look fairly
different.
So what's the better one?
Well, that just depends on what you're displaying.
Srgb is the best one for games because that's what games will use
Adobe RGB.
Might be the one that has the really weird crazy multi-part function.
I don't remember.
there's this one that's like,
Super weird, where's the equation?
Show me the equation.
Oh no, this is not.
So this is
This is not good at all.
You definitely don't want this.
Never mind.
He said, I don't think so.
You know, I'll be honest, I'm the wrong one to ask.
I'm so not a color space knowledgeable person.
So this is the 2 part 1.
This is when I think of I think this is the one you want.
That's certainly the one that I think the graphics cards Implement
that was my recollection.
So I think that's the one.
You typically want to set to
Orlando Bloom.
I've heard a lot of monitors, aren't even really 32-bit color
sometimes.
Less with differing in the monitor.
Yeah, I think that's actually possibly true because since it's never
been one of those specs, like basically, a lot of other things have
been specs that people have hiked on, like, TVs and stuff or whatever.
It's like 60 frames, a second, or 120 frames a second or whatever they
start helping them, and then TVs, like have them, whatever they are,
whereas bits of color people have not like pushed yet, as a thing.
So yeah.
You end up with people cutting Corners so they can sell it cheaper,
TV, that still looks like it has the same specs.
Anyway.
I'm a shut down now.
Yeah.
There we go.
Thank you everyone for joining me, for another episode of handmade
here.
It's been a pleasure coding with you as always.
And it's been a fun week, we added opengl rendering to our game, which
is kind of fun.
And now we have access to a heck of a lot of computing power in there
for doing our rendering, which is kind of nice.
The CPU was pretty good at rendering but of course the graphics card
which is totally made for it is better.
So that's it for today.
If you want to follow along at home, you can always pre-order.
My handmade here, a torque and it comes with the source code so you
can play around with it even as we speak.
I uploaded every night after we're done here.
So you can play around with it and experiment if you would like to do.
So we also have a forum site.
If you want to go ask questions, we have a patreon page where you can
support the video series if you are so inclined.
And we also have a tweet bot that tweets the schedule at you.
So if you want to catch the stream live, that's the place to do it.
We will be back here next week I suspect unless for some reason we're
off so definitely check the Tweet but for information about that
until then have fun programming, guys, and I will see you all on the
internet.
Take it easy, everyone.