According start recording.
Hello everyone.
Welcome to handmade hero.
The show where we could complete game from scratch.
Every absolutely everything is on the stream.
There's no hidden secret things.
I do.
Well, people aren't watching and we basically use new engine know
libraries.
No nothing here, just straight-up C plus, plus compiler and and
currently we use the C runtime library, but we're thinking that
probably eventually will get ready even that by the end.
So we're trying
And very hard to basically, show.
Absolutely everything that happens in the execution of a game.
So that literally every last little thing that goes into making a game
Run, we explore on the stream, explain how it works.
Show how its developed and kind of give insight into why it's
important why that piece does what it does.
The way that it does, so that you can really Come Away with a complete
understanding of everything that happens when a game runs on a
computer.
And I guess on a console for that matter to, they're not that
different.
There's some nice things about consoles.
You don't get on PCS where you kind of know the hardware a little bit
better because there's, you know, a very specific set of it.
But on the whole they're not that different these days.
They're very, very similar used to be the case that consoles were very
different from PCS.
Not anymore.
They're basically just little pieces in a box.
Anyway, if you have pre-ordered the game on handmade hero dot-org, you
can download the source code.
You should have gotten a link in your email that allows
You to do that.
And if you would like to follow along with today's coding, what you
can do is, you can go unpack day 60 because we are on day 61 right
now.
So just unpacked day, 60s source code from the source code ZIP file.
It's like there's a zip file that you download has just everyday zip
just sitting in there, so you can grab that one out, unpack it, and
you will be exactly where I am today.
So that is that, let's go ahead and get started with with the coating.
Right now where we're at is we are trying to go through and make
essentially, what is sort of a placeholder version of the game,
something that just has a little bit of everything, so that we can see
the sorts of structure that emerges in the code.
And that is what we will be basing.
Our actual industrial-strength engine code around.
So, we've basically done little dummy, implementations of everything
which are okay, but not great, and they're just there to get something
in.
Quickly that were able to sort of test with and see the structure of
now what I did before on the stream, just before I guess it would have
been Friday morning was, I added hit points and you can see that now
we draw some little hit points below the guy, he's got three little
hit points there.
We also have this little familiar who follow him around and then we
have this little, we just use the Torso from the guy to draw as a
little monster that sitting there.
And so we kind of wanted to do now is just get some monster activity
in.
So, we kind of wanted to
To make it so that this monster could somehow maybe follow the player.
Bit maybe attack the player a little bit and maybe we'll give the
monster some hit points as well and then allow it so that the monster
and the hero can sort of trade damage in some reasonable way.
Again, just so we can sort of build up an understanding in code of
what the sorts of operations are and how they have to occur.
So that when we start building the systems for real, we will not make
sort of the obvious mistakes that a lot of people make when they start
trying to write systems without any knowledge of the
things that need to run on those systems.
That's a very common mistake, not just for amateurs, but also, for a
professional programmers.
A lot of times they will make the mistake of writing a system before
they actually know how that system should be used.
And that's a really big mistake.
So I always say right the users code first and that's exactly what
we're doing.
We are basically making a bunch of synthetic usage code so we can see
what we need to do.
So right now we don't really have anything.
Any even way to attack.
We do, have a way to jump for no real reason.
So what I think I might do is go ahead and replace that.
I'm going to move that jump over to the spacebar and I'm going to go
ahead and bind the arrow keys over to just something simple.
Like maybe a standard for way shooting kind of a thing.
Just something where I can attack basically in a direction, right?
Maybe something where I can can just
Packing a direction by pushing, one of the keys and then we will see,
you know, when I do an attack in a particular direction, I want to
make it so that I can count the fact that if that hit a monster that's
in the area and and take away hip points from that monster if so.
So I want to do that.
And in order to do that, I would also have to give our little torso
monster.
They're a hit points himself because he would need something to
decrement from.
So that seems like the most straightforward thing to continue with as
we go.
So I'm
Going to go ahead and get that going.
So if I want to add hit points to the monster, what I would need to
do.
Well, of course, one thing I need to do is open the editor.
To say the least.
So what I would need to do here is I need to make sure that the
monster can have hit points just like the hero can.
And so right now we haven't split out our entity data.
We just have all the end of the data in one place, which basically
means that, you know, there already is, the concept of hit points in
every entity.
Right now, which again is something that we at least suspect, we will
actually not want to do in the final entity system.
But for now that's, you know, we're just putting things in here so
that we can see how they work.
Were so that means everyone already actually does.
Technically have hit points.
We just need to initialize them to something at the start and then we
need to draw them.
Right?
So what we need to do here is we need to go down to the hit points and
we need to see those are actually getting drawn when we draw our
player.
Right here is the hero drawing code.
Here is the code that draws the hit points, that won't really be any
different and we don't really want it to be different.
Presumably, we want to draw.
Hit points.
Basically with the same code, no matter.
They are and then we just tweaked some parameters like maybe what
color they are something like that.
But for the most part, we don't want to redo the logic.
So no matter how we end up drawing hit points, I think we're going to
want that shared.
So basically, what I would say here is we want something like draw hip
points right?
That we can just call on this guy.
And that's just going to be this code here.
That way when we go down to the monstar, we can draw hit points on the
monstar and the monstar will have them as well.
So I'm going to go up here and just just put that
at code in there.
And I'm going to have this be called, Rohit points, like so, and I'm
going to just pull that out.
Now.
I need to call it multiple times and we just need to see what the
stuff is.
I actually need it to do.
So, if you look here, there's not a whole lot to it.
Basically, we've got that low entity.
So we have something here where we want to do the low entity, it wants
access to that when it's doing this positioning here.
It looks like it wants a piece group, right?
It wants to be able to draw the
The things on onto one of these peace groups.
So let's go ahead and make sure that it has one of those as well.
That's where it's going to put, its drawing information.
Like so.
And then looks like we just need really, that's about it.
We just need an x coordinate for where these things are being drawn.
And I think that's, that's just about it.
And, in fact, I guess the piece group kind of takes care of that.
Let's see here.
Is that really all we need?
What else do we need?
Push?
Push wrecked entity piece trip, right, so that's
Doesn't doesn't take an address, but that's it.
That was all we needed.
So I guess we really don't have much work to do to move that out.
That was really pretty trivial.
So now our monstar can have them as well.
And if our monstar is going to have them, we need to initialize.
Those hit points to something.
Because right here, you can see that we've got those.
And so when we add our monstar, I'm again going to just pull out the
code there, which is something like in it, hit points and then we'll
just say for now that you say,
Say the hit point count, you know, however many you actually wanted in
there and and that will just do this code right here.
So we'll pull that out like so and we'll go ahead and say that we do
in it, hit points and we pass that that entity low, which is all it
should really need and then how many hit points we want?
Which in that case was 3 and I guess for the monstar the monstar can
also have three.
Why not?
So we do the this right here.
We will then have the low entity which we have a few low and that will
go ahead and set it to the hit point count.
We will want to assert obviously because we don't really have much in
the way of flexibility here yet just to make sure that the
Point array can actually store the number of hit points that it's
asking us to do, because we're storing actual data with each hit
point.
So, it can each individual like heart.
Essentially on the person can have perhaps potentially property
associated with them.
We're not sure where that's going quite yet.
Those might be entities themselves in the future.
We don't know.
So we're kind of have a simpler system at the moment, but we met kind
of Ratchet that up a little bit.
We'll see.
So anyway, we now have a situation where we've got the hit points and
we need
to initialize them all.
So I'm going to go ahead here and do a hit point initialization Loop,
where I just say, for every hit point that we have here.
That's the basically, the max hit point.
Count is getting me that information.
I'm going to go ahead and set that that filled amount equal to
something reasonable.
All right.
So we also need to see Point.
Good point equals entity low hit point, plus the point.
Sam.
And then that hit point is just going to be Flags.
There are no flags on this one and the filled amount equals fully
filled essentially.
So that's that's that.
And so that will initialize our hit points.
And so now, let's see if we actually get.
Yes.
So now we have monsters.
Sorry, mon star are monstar and our hero both have hit points.
Now are familiar doesn't because we decided or we didn't directly
beside but we
And go and add them to him, which I don't know if the familiars will
have them or not.
Possibly, some will some won't, we don't know.
But now let's go ahead and make it so that we can attack our monstar
and eventually kill our monstar as well.
I think we probably want to be able to kill our monstar.
So let's do that.
So if we're going to attack we're going to need some way of attacking
and I don't know if I actually put in anything.
I don't think I have any any real Sprites in here yet.
That would be related to this.
Let's see.
What's in here.
In the handmade data, oops, that's the code directory and may data
directory.
Of course.
We we know that Windows is bad at actually being able to display these
but we should be able to sort of see what they are.
Anyway, even though it's display is messed up.
So there's a little Bolder thing I could use that as projectile.
It's a bit large to say the least.
What have I got in here?
I don't think I have anything particularly good in here either.
Yeah.
Yeah, not a whole lot I can use, so, maybe that Boulder is going to
have to be it.
So let's go ahead and pick that one out.
Whatever is the smallest one.
I think that's probably the smallest one Rocco three.
So we'll just basically say that that is kind of going to be our
attack region.
And so I want to make this I want to basically say for now, let's
stick with the Zelda e style of
And I know that originally in, Zelda, you had two different cases if
you are full on Hearts Center projectile out and if you weren't it
didn't.
But let's go ahead and say for now, like we're just going to do
essentially something that's like a sword swing.
So we want something that is going to come, you know, be a hit region
that lasts for a brief amount of time, next to the player, anything
that gets touched by that is considered hit and take some damage, but
it doesn't really do.
Thing, you know beyond that.
So there's a lot of ways we could Implement that and it's not
necessarily immediately.
Clear how we want to do that.
It is a little bit confusing, right?
Because there's many, many ways we could do it one way we could do it
is to have that actually be a special state that occurs where someone
is striking.
And we know that that's the case and we actually have code
specifically check for it.
Another way to do.
It is to have it so that it's basically piggybacked on top of an
entity.
So there actually is sort of a sword entity.
That sword entity only comes out during the strike and during the
strike if that entity collides with other entities, then we know that
it has hit them right.
So that
I think is where I'd like to go with it.
I basically like to make it so that
Let's see here.
Hmm, actually know how to do.
Zoom in and out very well.
Alright, there we go.
There is zoom in and out.
So what I decided to do, by the way, is I decided to start just saving
these into the handmade hero directory.
So, from now on, we should actually be in a situation where all of the
drawings from now on are actually saved.
And if you have Mischief or use the trial version, there's a, I think
there's a trial version.
Free version or something.
If I know there is actually a full free version, if you have the free
version, you can actually go and do it.
So, from now on what I'm going to do is, I'm just going to take a look
at the day number down here and I'll actually just kind of do like a
day 61 Landmark up here and then so I'll try to draw kind of down
inside this and then I'll move over as we go.
So that way when you load it up you can go look at the drawings if
people want to.
I don't know if they do or not, but just in case since it's now with
Mischief, it's easy for us to do that.
I'll just do that.
So, Kira is mainly the problem.
What I was just saying is relatively straightforward, right?
I've got a hero entity, right?
Here's my hero entity.
And if I had some other entity that was just generally, not visible.
That's my sword strike entity and when it when you do the sword
strike, you know, the sword comes out here and then anything that
touches it takes damage.
That's actually relatively easy to implement with what we already have
because we already have
Nobody to tell when things touch of the things obviously.
But there is a kind of unusual circumstance that we have here, which
is something that we hadn't addressed yet.
Right, which is that the sword entity.
Let's say that there is a monstar, right?
So there's a monstar here, right?
This is monstar.
Let me actually draw that a little clearer.
So this is monstar, right?
So if monstar is touching the sword, our Collision routine that we
already have will be
To tell us that monstar is touching the sword.
That's not actually a difficult thing for us to do because we already
have Collision code that will tell us that the problem is if this
sword Strike last some number of frames, like let's say that the sword
last ten frames, right?
So you push it and it's out there for ten frames.
If that's the case, we will find that we will get 10 frames worth of
strike evaluations.
Right?
So what we need to be able to do is we need to be able to have some
conception of the fact that only the first time that this sword
touches someone on that strike.
Do you actually get it counted as a hit because otherwise it would
actually go ahead and take 10 Hearts off of.
I whenever they were hit because on each frame, it would go.
Oh, the sword is touching the monstar.
So minus 1 hearts on the monstar and then the next frame, it would do
it again and do it again and do it again, right?
And, so, for however, many frames, the sword strike was visible.
That's how many hearts would take off.
So what we need to do instead is we need to have some kind of a
concept, right?
Which we haven't really done anything to deal with yet of the
initiation of a collision as opposed to the maintenance of a
collision, right?
So we need to basically know
is this Collision right new?
And we need to know whether it's new because if it's not new, then we
don't want to actually process that stuff.
So there's a couple ways that we might want to think about doing that
for the sword.
One way we could do it which is kind of the realistic way of Sword
would work.
In some way is actually problematic for us and I'll tell you why in a
second.
But what that basically would be is you test to see whether The Sword
and the monster overlap initially.
Versus whether The Sword and the monster overlap as a result of
whatever happened on the frame.
So, on the first frame, when a sword strike occurs, you note, the fact
that the sword was not in even in on the screen at first and then it
is now.
So all collisions are new on the frame after that you go.
Okay, the sword was on the screen, ish Ali.
So check who it was touching.
And then after we do our movement update for that frame, see who it's
touching now and anyone.
Who it is, newly touching.
It wasn't touching before count the strike for them.
Right?
But we really don't and that's like just more of a like.
Oh, I'm actually like pushing a sword into somebody kind of a thing.
I don't really think we want to do that because you get into like
we're cheating scenarios where you can kind of oscillate on the
monstar.
Like if you can move it back and forth a little you could you could
hit the monster multiple times.
So I think gamey, why's the actual metric for whether you hit someone
with a sword is really pretty straightforward.
It's
Basically, like on the initial frame, right?
Wow, that's a bad handwriting.
On the initial frame is actually what we're talking about here.
On the first frame that the sword is, you know, where the sword strike
is initiated things that are touched on that frame by the sword.
Take damage things that aren't aren't right.
That would be how we would do it, right?
now, just because I want to continue down this path of why this is
kind of complicated and warrants thinking about
Let's so this is, this is for a stationary sword, right?
So, this right here.
Is all at the sort of a stationary, right?
So this is like a stationary sword.
Now, let's think about what has to happen if the sword is moving,
right?
So this is a flying sword.
Okay.
Now, we have an even harder problem because now, if here is my hero,
right?
And here comes the sword that he comes out.
The sword is actually traveling in this direction.
So it's a given that the sword is going to go through some number of
monsters on the way.
Right?
Could be zero if it was just a bad shot, but it could be maybe two or
more, right?
And you know, we could cheese out and say as soon as the sword hit
somebody the sword disappears or something like it's a One-Shot sword,
but that should be a game design decision.
We don't want to do that.
Just because our algorithm is lousy.
We would like the game to be able to have for example, different types
of swords, some that have piercing would be what this would be called.
and so, what we'd like to do is allow the sword entity to travel in a
line and whenever it hits a monstar, we would like it to do damage to
that monster only once,
right.
That's what we would like.
And unfortunately.
I can't say, I know any solution to this problem that does not involve
actually just tracking the information.
I don't like the only way I know to absolutely guarantee that there is
no way to cheat out on.
This is if you actually just remember who the sword has hit and who it
hasn't hit and you only
Us to hit once make sense, okay.
Now, you may ask, why don't you just use sort of when does it enter
the person and when does it leave, right?
So only on entrance, but the reason for that is because you end up in
situations where, what if the monster and the sword were moving in the
same direction, right?
So suppose The Sword, and the monster end up in a situation like this,
and the Monsters moving that direction, the sores, moving that
direction.
Well, you could imagine a thing.
Even if you had really good Collision detection.
And it implemented everything perfectly.
You could end up with these two things perfectly lining up.
So they just overlap, right?
And because of numerical imprecision you oscillate as to whose side.
This is on as the monster and the Sword move in that direction and it
causes multiple damage, you know, records to happen here, right?
You could imagine this.
You could imagine it with the power.
Of imagination.
No, it's an open question.
Whether this is a case that would ever happen enough for you to care.
Right?
Furthermore.
You could imagine a situation that's not so unusual.
Maybe let's let's talk about another one.
Suppose here is monstar, right, and here is sword.
This is a very fast monstar, right?
It's a speedy monstar.
The sword is a slow sword for whatever reason.
The slurry is sort of traveling this direction.
The monstar, the Speedy monstar is staying still.
Okay, on frame one, hears frame 0 on frame 1.
The sword is.
Here.
It is an valid entrance.
We know that it was not overlapping the monster before and it is
overlapping the monstar now, so we correctly record - one hearts.
Right, but now the monstar accelerates in this direction and the
monstar is faster than the sword.
So on frame to write the monstar has actually gained some ground on
the sword such that by frame 3.
The Sword is no longer catching up, but now the monstar stops so on
frame for
The sword re-enters, the monstar, this would Now record.
Another - one hearts and would be a bug, right?
If we assume that the definition for our game.
Is that something a sword can once sword strike can only do damage one
time right now, we could change the definition and say that, if it
does enter twice like that, that's more damage.
Maybe that's a good definition, but it's
Noting that at that point, we would be making that.
We would be making that decision based solely on the fact that we
didn't want to implicate.
It a more robust scheme that could handle either right of those two
things.
So, I don't know.
Like I said, it's very complicated.
It's more complicated than you would think a lot of games cheese out
on stuff like this, a couple ways.
They cheese out is by like turning things Invincible for a second
after they get hit by something, thus eliminating this problem.
Altogether.
Another way is by eliminating the swords the sword once it hits
something.
It's gone.
There's a lot of different ways.
You can choose out on something like this and we could eventually
decide that we want to do exactly that kind of cheesery.
And then we would cheese it out, but
Least At first I would say instead of picking the cheese route.
Let's try and pick a smarter route.
And so the route that I would say that we should pick there is
actually have some notion of whether or not a sword can hit something
multiple times or not.
Right?
So, I think what we probably want to do is have essentially a sword.
We want to have something called like a, you know, a hit table, right?
We want to have something where we can record every time something hit
something.
NG in a mutually exclusive State like that.
Let's just go ahead and record that somehow so that we can go ahead
and prevent double strikes of this nature.
Now, I don't think this is a particularly costly thing.
Even if we Implement stupidly and the reason that I don't think that
is because we have to ask the question how many
Hits per, you know, second are really happening here, right, you know,
assuming that this is a zelda-like game, you're talking about having
something, you know, like 10 is actually a lot of projectiles on the
screen.
It's isn't bullet-hell.
So, you know, if this was in a bullet, hell game, you can imagine that
you would have some kind of a circumstance where you're thinking.
Oh a hundred isn't a very large number of
Or maybe even a thousand, right?
But in our world 10 is a pretty good number that you would think.
Like that's a pretty hectic screen.
The player is pretty frazzled.
If there's 10 things flying out there, certainly if there are 100
stuff has gone totally Bonkers and the number of like actual entities
on the screen that can be hit and have Damage, Done to them is going
to be real small.
Again.
I think in that 10 range, right?
So I think we're talking about circumstances where this table is, you
know, like a hundred entries.
Long or something, something that we could scan exhaustively if we
wanted to every time a collision occurred and not actually care at all
because again, there's only 10 entities that could even get hit on the
screen and go in time.
Sir.
Talking about 10 times 100 is 1,000 iterations total to process.
This.
It seems like something that's really just not that big of a deal.
So I feel like they hit table is kind of the right way to go because
we can also maybe we can get some Leverage.
Regina of this, right?
There might be other things we can do with the hit table that we might
want to do later.
That would be hard to do without it.
Because the hit table is pairwise, write a hit table records.
The fact that something happened between an entity and another entity.
And we may want to store information.
They're like timers or other things like that.
That would be difficult for us to store in the entities themselves,
which are not pairwise.
Right?
And entity itself doesn't have information about all the other
entities.
So, by having a hit table, it gives us a
Convenient way to store pairwise information, potentially?
In a way that would prevent us from having to blow entity structures
with lots of little arrays or other garbage like this that we would or
pointers to optional arrays, which would be more like what we do,
right?
We wouldn't have to bloat those things and it allows us a really nice
convenient way to store that and also in a way that is much more bound
double, right?
It's much more Bountiful for us to do this.
We can set aside some space for this.
We can set aside an iteration count for this and know that at the
worst case.
We would not cause some kind of a memory overflow or use too much
space or something.
We would just there be just a thing in the game where if there were
thousands of things happening on the screen hits at one time.
One of them wouldn't get recorded or something.
Right?
One of the hits wouldn't would be able to happen twice or something.
So at the very worst case, we would only regress back to what would
happen.
If we didn't use the hit table.
There's nothing particularly negative that happens in that case and I
don't think that case, whatever happens.
So we're good and certainly will assert.
So we'll know if it does and we can adjust accordingly, but I think
we're pretty good there.
So I think this is what we want to do.
We want to have a hit table.
We want to have the sword to Unity, and we'll go ahead and just put
that in.
As I just described.
It.
Looks like we've got about 30 minutes.
That should be enough time.
To put something in along those lines.
So, let's go ahead and check out our move entity.
Right?
We've got our move entity call.
And what we want to do here is, we probably on move entity.
We probably want to do something where we're going to, we've got, you
know, we've got our Collision detection function, right?
This is our Collision detection function and in some sense for our
sword.
It's much too heavy weight because the sword is not really moving the
Just comes on the screen.
I guess if we actually have the sword kind of travel out, maybe I take
it back and we shouldn't have a sort of string.
We should have the sword actually travel out, just because it's a
little, it's a harder case.
So maybe we'll do that.
And so then when we do this, iteration, when we go through here, every
time we hit something, what we'd want to do is is we already have it
set up to process these collisions when they occur, we could go ahead
and process those collisions.
Now for real.
So we could actually do something where we actually handle the
Collision do something intelligent with it.
So for example, the thing that we would do here is when that happens
we would go ahead and yeah, and we would just go ahead and make that.
Make that decrement to head cap.
Now, there is a
there is kind of a slight slight issue that I didn't discuss, which is
we need to know when things can get eliminated from the hit table,
right?
In the case of the sword.
It's kind of a known, it's a very easy Thing.
Once the sword strike stops, all the entries in the hit table that are
about the sword can go away.
Right?
So, the sword strike only has to track that during that time.
Now, whether that's, whether there are more difficult metrics, we have
to worry about
Sort of further down the road.
I don't know, but that's just, you know, that's just an example of
something I think about.
All right, so let's go ahead and make a sword, right?
So let's just add one in here sword like, so.
And so when we do our, we have our ad monstar right call and we can
basically have an ad sword call and add sword.
Call is going to be pretty straightforward and add sword called
doesn't actually have to have a location.
Because the sword is not really at a location at the beginning.
And so that's kind of a good thing this reinforces.
I remember I said when we were working on it before, as like, I don't
know whether we need to have the concept that entities aren't at
locations.
And I think this kind of answers that question for us.
If we want to have things like swords that kind of come out to do a
strike and then go back into sort of like, hiding the sort of stuff
that we put into our world to handle the concept.
Things might not be somewhere, actually isn't wasted.
We are actually going to make legitimate use of that.
And so, that's a good thing.
Again.
It reinforces sort of a feature that we speculatively allowed for
other reasons specifically, just so that the null and
You could exist and I sort of said, I don't know.
Do we want to do that?
Justin only?
Well now we know there's a real valid reason why we might want it that
kind of supports that as a general decision to me in my mind.
All right.
So we have our sword here.
We know that the sword does in fact, Collide, although I guess in some
sense.
No, it doesn't Collide.
We do do Collision testing with the sword, but it doesn't stop things.
People can walk through the sword if they want to.
At least that's how I remember games.
Like Zelda, generally work so hard.
Does not have hit points, obviously.
I saw it does not have a location at all.
So it's at sword.
There we go.
Having a little typing problems there, so we don't need to do this and
we don't need to do this.
We are just adding a sword and the actual position is nothing, right?
So that would be, how we would add a sword.
We would then say, when we add our player, our hero, right?
Rip said player.
When we add a
Are we know that the player should also always have a sword I assume
for now.
I mean, I guess obviously later on that's not exactly what happens.
You kind of pick up Swords or other stuff like that.
So I'm not sure how we do that.
Maybe that's another thing we should put on the list of stuff to try.
So if we want to add a sword, we've got out of Sword here and that's
going to return an ad, Lou entity result for us.
So this is our sword, right?
So if we add our sword here, what we'd like to be able to do is store
with this player.
What sword?
It is theirs, right?
So again, that comes in here, let me get rid of this for now, since
we're not keeping particularly good track of this.
So, this comes in here now and this says, basically, like what is my,
my sword low index?
And, again, this is just kind of we're building out this here.
And my, my assumption is that after we add a sufficient amount of
complexity.
This will be huge and it, hopefully, we'll have a lot of different
things in it.
And then that will put us in a perfect position to do, like the past
that we need to do where we go and think about how we're going to
store this stuff.
Right?
Because not all entities have a sword.
So why do they all have a sword low index?
Right?
Or something like this?
So anyway, so if I go, I'm going to say that this entity the players
entity.
It has a sword index.
Sorry, low index.
And that is just the end of the low results.
I don't remember what the end of the low result even has in.
It.
Add low entity salt entity.
I don't even know what's in there.
I guess just slow and low index.
Okay, so I can just grab the low index app.
So now we actually know exactly what sort it is.
So now when the player actually goes to use that sword.
We can go and do that.
So I guess what we would do here is say we also probably need some
kind of a timer or a distance metric.
I guess something along those lines because when the sword is active,
we know that.
Like, you know, when you throw the sword or something, in one of these
games, typically, what will happen is the sword?
It may well.
First of all, I think if it hits something like a tree or something
like that, it's obviously going to stop traveling.
So,
Hits a wall.
Like I'll stop traveling but it may also, we may also have a situation
where, like, if the entity if the sword entity goes for too long, like
there should maybe there should be a Timeout on it.
So, I don't know or a distance, not like, you can only throw the sword
so far right before it stops.
That seems pretty typical.
So I assumed you'd probably want something like that as well.
So we'd probably want something on here like a timer, right?
Where we're going to set that to something that's going to take.
Down.
And when it takes down, the sword goes away, right?
And this might be a distant total distance.
Traveled seems a little smarter.
So maybe we'll say, distance remaining or something like that, right?
So we'll look at that and we'll see how that goes.
So we've got distance remaining.
And now we've got our sword.
We have created The Sword.
And so now, what we need to do also is I guess draw the sword.
I said that we would just kind of throw in there.
One of these like cheesy Rock bitmaps.
I think we said it was Rocco 3, something like that.
So we now will do is kind of a Cheesy way of representing sort.
Since I don't have a sword bitmap in the art pack yet.
Mmm, so, that'd be here, sword.
And then when we're actually down here, drawing stuff, we would just
say, what do we want swords to look like?
Right and swords are just going to be like walls, where there's really
nothing interesting in them at all.
They are just sword.
Now, if we're actually using that rock 03, I guess is what it was if
we're using Rocco three, I need to kind of see where we should Center
it around.
I assume, we'll just use the middle.
So, however, big it is, well, I guess I'll just, I'll just kind of
feel out what the middle is and gimp.
Mmm.
So probably like right about there.
So that's like 29:10, right?
So, 2910 is the, the centering point for that guy.
And that is the bitmap.
Now, in general.
I guess the sword should kind of be a little bit off the ground, which
means it probably has a shadow as well, right?
Got something like this.
So I guess the swords technically have Z height and will probably give
it a little Z height when it gets thrown.
That's what I would say.
All right, but we'll deal with that a little bit later on.
Okay, so now we've got swords and something that we have to check now,
which we weren't checking before is when something is a high Envy or
low entity or whatever.
We weren't previously, checking to see whether it actually existed
somewhere in the world.
I guess.
Well, it wouldn't wouldn't be in the hyemi set.
So that's what would prevent it from from happening.
It would drop out of the high Andes set or go into the high-end be set
when it exists or didn't exist in the world because the criteria for
moving, something from low to high is that it's in the camera region,
so,
Hmm.
Yeah, so I think that's good.
What I would like to do.
Now is let me clean up any errors that we might compile errors, that
we may have done here.
So, add sword obviously has to be above add player.
So the compiler can find it.
Rocket science, C compilers can't find functions if they don't happen
in order.
All right.
So let's go ahead and actually change the speed V.
The action up, I think is what it was.
Let's change that to be whatever the spacebar was.
I don't remember what we call.
That in our platform layer.
We had a we had a couple different buttons.
I think that it was I think this it was actually the start button that
was that for jumping.
So obvious, buying that start button.
I don't think we're actually going to have jumping in the game, but it
was kind of funny to watch him jump.
In there, so I'm going to leave it in for now.
So I think.
Yeah, there we go.
Okay, so start button is also the jump button at the moment.
It makes no sense.
But that's just the way it is.
So now we just need to bind these other Keys.
The arrow keys to launch a sword in a particular direction.
All right, so let's start by saying.
Okay, we know that.
If we got a situation where the controllers action up button and it
down, oh, you know what I could do to hear.
Well, I don't really want to everybody.
That's not going to be useful.
I was gonna say something but then I just changed my mind.
So we basically have a direction for our sword to go in and we're
going to assume that the sword doesn't go in any direction.
And then if they actually push it in a one of the action directions
will just launch the sword, right?
So we'll say that there's the up-down and the left-right Sorting right
like that.
And when that happens, we will set the d sword to be the direction.
We want the sword to go again.
Nothing particularly interesting here, just really really basic stuff.
Just something so that we can kind of have a sword going and see what
happens as a result.
So there's left right and there's right.
Like so, so that allows us to launch stored in any given Direction,
but now we need to actually make sure that we take our sword and
launch it.
So, after we move ourselves, what we want to do is say if that d sword
is.
So I guess the dot X is not equal to 0, right?
Or d sword.
Y is not equal to 0.
So if we gave, if we actually decided that the sword should have some
launching here by setting it to one of these things.
That was the case.
Then we need to initiate that sort sequence.
So now first we should check to see if we even have a sword, right?
Because technically I guess we don't have to have one, right?
The person might not be having one.
So we should check the sword, low index.
We would see whether or not we actually got one there, so we could
look at get high.
We had a, we had a call that was like, get high entity or something
like this.
It was like force entity to.
Hi, right?
Like so on.
So what we could basically do is just call this, right?
And so, we want to force the entity to.
Hi.
that's, that's whatever the
Which entity actually where is RO controlling entity?
That's what it was.
So controlling entity is what any structures so are controlling
entity.
We want to take that and say that it's sword, low index.
We want to force that to be a high-energy.
So this is our sword.
We've grabbed up.
We've got our sword now, right?
And if our sword, we know that it could come back - like nothing it
could come back, come back, nothing at.
All.
Right, so assuming that we got a sword back because if this if this
sword low index was 0, this will just return a null pointer.
And because there's no Soren to have.
So this will force the sword entity into the hiset.
Right?
What we want to do now is say, okay.
Now let's actually move the that sword to where we want it to be.
Now.
What's interesting about that is I'm kind of interested to know Force
entity into high, probably already does the mapping, right?
So it would really want to do is before we did that.
This is kind of inefficient.
I don't love it.
Kind of what we would want to do is we want to get the low entity
first, set.
Its position to where it should be and then force it into high, right?
So it's kind of annoying and inefficient.
Maybe I want to change the way that he power Works a little bit,
right?
I just don't love it because I would like to be able to say to do that
in all one go, but I can.
So
No, I could do.
Maybe I like it this way.
Maybe I like force enemy into hi.
To actually take an optional place.
So when you force into the hiset, maybe that takes a position, right?
So it's like, I want to force this end of the hiset and I want to
force it in the hiset here, right?
So basically what that would do is it would it would change the enemy
location like so, right.
So this would change the end of the location and then it would force
the enemy be high-frequency if it wasn't already.
So we'll change the entity location will say that.
The end of the location is is here.
And then we'll start some money.
Well, you know what?
Maybe this isn't even really that.
Maybe I'm even being more ridiculous here than I thought.
Because what I could do to is say, well, maybe we don't ever even get
it time.
Maybe we don't get it.
Get it.
We don't, we don't treat it as a highly at all.
Maybe we just treat it as a low-energy the whole time, right?
That would essentially be saying.
All right.
Let's see whether there is a sword, right?
So will basically say low entity sword.
Equals Get Low entity and we just we just get it.
There we go.
Assuming that there is one we then change its location to where we
want it to be.
And then we don't maybe we just don't process, We Don't Force It into
high.
We let the camera stuff code just forced into high as it would know.
So maybe I was maybe I was overthinking things and I should just let
the, the systems do their job.
I do think the change any location.
We probably have to think that through a little bit more because I
feel like at the
The moment, right change?
A location should map things into high.
Probably, if they're within the camera bounds, if that makes sense.
So I feel like there should be a to do here that's like to do if this
moves and entity into the camera bounds.
Should.
Automatically go into the hiset immediately and that's really at the
end of the frame on the next frame.
That would go into the hiset when the camera did it check.
But do we want it to go in immediately so that for the rest of the
frame after its created, for the rest of that frame, it actually goes
through and I don't know.
So I'm just putting it to do in there.
All right, so I get that low entity out.
I go ahead and and, and see if I if there actually was one, and if
there was, I'm gonna go ahead and set it to be where the player
themselves actually is.
So this controlling entity here, whatever that controlling entity is
that entity is position is where I want this entity to be for now.
We'll maybe, we'll, we'll set ourselves up for Success here to say,
where we want that to be so that we can modify it later.
You know, set the Z or whatever we want to do there.
So we'll have that and you know, maybe we even do set the Z here or
something, but we'll play with that a little bit later.
And so we're going to change the end of the location.
We're going to change that that sword entity is location.
So
Right, and I think that's really all we needed to do.
What is the zero?
That's where it was.
So, I think that's correct.
The only thing that I would say is if the sword is already in play,
you shouldn't probably be able to recall it.
So what we probably should do is verify that the sword is not actually
already inserted in the world.
And unfortunately, right now, I don't think we really have a way of
representing that.
We don't have that notion in our actual entity structures, right?
Correct me if I'm wrong.
But there really isn't anything that says for a world position,
whether or not that world position is valid, right?
So what we could do is introduce some notion of that, right, we could
introduce some notion that a certain set of this chunk, indices
indicates an invalid offset, right?
And that would probably be something along the lines of one of these
very large values like in 32 Max, right?
And so, what we could do is say that there is such a thing as that an
You sort of a rep there, right?
So the way that that would work is when we add a low entity, if the
low entity didn't actually have a position that was asked, that was
supposed to be the position where the enemy should be.
Right.
Oops, then what we would do is right there.
We'd set, it's, it's sort of settings for its position.
We'd set that equal to the null position.
Right?
Like basically like a position that says it's not in the world.
So the null position would just be some function that returns a world
position World position.
This there's our null position where you can anytime get one back.
It's basically just one of these that's set to something that
specifically lets us know that it is not valid, right?
So it's just this, let's say some k x is, is that right?
And we return it because we know that you can't put things there.
We already are using tile, chunk uninitialized, as a marker, in our
hash table.
So you're not allowed to use in 32 Max as a valid location for
something.
So what we could do is just say that is what the null position is.
Right?
And we could kill her.
Everything else is 0.
I don't know if we should or not, or if we should let it be garbage.
But for now, I guess we can compare it to zero because why not?
So this will set that to to be what we just said, however, we would
like to also do is say is you know, we want something where we can say
is null and we give it a whirl position and I guess we could.
Since that's an inline we could just say results equals P chunk X not
equal to tell chunk uninitialized, right?
We could also say is valid instead is valid might be a little bit
better.
And then that would be right this way.
That's the way I actually wrote it was for is valid.
Okay.
So if we do that, then what we should be able to do here is we should
be able to
We should be able to go ahead and also add an assertion that whenever
you do a change entity location.
What we could do here is these could note, we wouldn't have to make
these Corners anymore.
If we didn't want to write, we could make it so that they actually
were just using the invalid.
Or valid.
I don't know if we want to do that or not.
We'll see.
But what we should do is we should say that we can assert either that
the old p is null, or that it's valid, right, but you should never be
able to pass.
Us an invalid position as part of the thing where we're changing the
locations, right?
Because this already has passing zero, is that?
So we'll just do that and make sure that that actually works.
What was I doing here?
We're all position.
That's true.
It does not have an overloaded.
You are very right.
And these are just copy paste - obviously those should not have start
in front of them and then changing the location.
Let's see cannot in for our get one from K-State to memory Arena.
What are you talking about?
Change entity location?
Let's see what's going on there.
Change entity location world.
Change entity location.
It should take an arena.
Why did I, what did I cut?
And pasted this from such that it didn't take the arena.
That's particularly odd.
Yeah.
I don't know why.
All right, but either way, we do have our Arena here are World Arena.
So we have our oh, I guess it doesn't take the game say it just takes
the World Arena and the world.
Like so that's
So, let's take a look here.
What do we got?
Changing looking at, first one from area, to remember, Irina address,
that should be fine.
Five repetitions star that should be fine.
So what we need to do now is check to see if the sword is there and
it's doesn't have a valid position, right?
Then, we know that we can move it to someplace where it actually is
going to be valid and that should move in behind be set.
So that would make the sword up here.
Now, that is all it will do.
That's the entirety of what it will do.
So I don't actually know, I don't actually know what we need to do.
Here is set a breakpoint to actually see if any of this, if any of
what we just did was working at all.
Let's take a look.
So, let's go to the part where we launched it and I'll launch it to.
Let's see.
Let's see here.
Okay.
So, let's see what happens.
Here's my guy, I go to launch the sword.
What's going on?
So sword p is what, it's in 2000, chunk.
It's at a location.
I assume that's where the player is.
I don't actually know.
But that would presumably be where you can go ahead and do that.
Looks like that works totally as expected.
So that's good.
And then we would expect on the
Pass through we would expect to then get into a position where we were
going to draw it.
So we would expect to hit this, not this time, through the loop, but
next time through and, of course, we don't.
So for some reason that is not getting moved into the high entity set
for reasons that are not immediately clear to me, because you would
expect
Afterwards for that to be moved to the Heidi set.
And then it will get looped over here in a way.
That would eventually tell us.
Okay.
It's time to draw this.
Now.
What's interesting about that?
Let's think about this first.
I think that.
Yeah, I don't think.
Yeah, I feel like that should have worked.
So something in our change entity position there or attempt to
interview location, something in our change into location, did not
properly, put it somewhere where the set camera call would find it.
The set chemical would have happened immediately thereafter, which
should have brought it into I guess now.
I think about it right there should have brought it into the active
set.
So for some reason it did not get added.
Now.
What I'd like to do here is have a way to sort of check that.
That procedure.
And so what I'd like to do is see which entity that actually was and
what I'm going to do is I'm going to go in here and put in a call so I
can just stop on that one when we do the set camera.
So inset camera when we do this the the make and
Frequency.
What I'd like to do here is just basically stop whenever we find that
entity and make sure that, that something weird is not happening
there.
Right?
So let's go ahead and do that here.
Let's see.
We got the low end the index.
Let's do if low end of the index equals, you know, three, let's say,
or I guess, we'll just say if the in test empty index equals 0 if R
equals test any index.
And we'll break here.
So this will be like in through equals 5, okay.
Silence and mismatch.
I'm so sorry.
I did not mean to do assigned unsigned mustache.
So, let's go ahead and check now to see what happened.
There would go ahead and do this.
And again, we haven't done much with our spatial partition yet.
So we may just have some bugs in there.
This is the first time that we're actually really doing anything
substantial with any of our stuff.
So let's go ahead and set that break point as well and that one
So let's go ahead and we've got one set when we actually start.
There we go.
Oh, wait, I can't.
There's quite do that yet.
I suppose.
So, when I actually do, my my shot.
There we go.
Let's take a look at what that entity index actually is.
So, the sword is index.
90 2005.
That is a lot of entities that we've created so far.
So, we've got 90 2005's our entity.
Oh, we're out of time.
I'm going to go ahead and just finish looking at this just because I
want to see if it's if it's actually finding here and then we can
finish the debugging tomorrow.
So I'll go here, I'll step to it and I'll take a look and see.
We're going to check against test and an index.
So I'm going to go ahead and set.
Um, test entity index to be equal to 925.
There we go.
So now we'll break in here when that guy actually gets found, right?
So, let's see.
Okay.
So basically, he's just not going into the spatial partition in the
right place or something, right?
Because he never actually gets found in this in this call Series,
right?
He never that never actually happened.
So if you actually go and look,
Look here.
I'll just verify that it actually did it right test end of the index.
Let's Take a Look test any index equals 0.
That's not going to work.
I did that wrong.
That was supposed to be a static, my bad, local persist.
What do we actually call it in?
This code base?
I forget.
I think it's local.
Persist.
I could be wrong about that.
Local persist.
That's what I actually meant to do.
My bad.
Let's try that one more time.
Now.
The sword should be the same thing here, actually.
Because as far as I know the, you know what, I should probably move
this up.
Spies do this there.
Yeah.
So what I want to do here is I want to go ahead and do that one more
time, come down here.
The sorted presumably is at the same energy index because I don't know
why it wouldn't be.
So let's go ahead and verify that.
That's true 9 2005.
It is exactly as we would expect.
So let's go back up and try that one more time.
I actually meant to yes Otep test any index is now global so I can
just set it to whatever I want and run and see if that ever actually
hits and it doesn't have
So that's concerning that basically means that something I did there
was unless I made a typo.
So, assuming that I did not make a typo, what that means is our
spatial partition is not quite debugged yet.
Because once we do this change, entity location to move the sword P to
its new location.
It should be at the same location as the entity is.
And at that point, it should, it should be triggered as something
that's, that's essentially going to be moved.
In with the camera state, so if we take a look at that call again,
sorry to belabor it here.
I'm just kind of curious.
I would like to know if we take a look at what happens in that call.
I'd like to see what spatial partition.
It's actually added to, right.
So let's go ahead and get that chunk here and see.
So we got back, chunk 000.
There's already 10 entities in it, which looks reasonable.
Right?
And and so there's those those low entities.
There they are.
Right.
And so what I'd like to do, there's the player and the monstar,
presumably and the familiar.
What I'd like to do is see now, when we add this right, let's add that
in what actually happened there, block entity count.
What did I miss that?
Did not go up.
Something weird happened there.
Let's try that one more time.
I need to step through this more carefully.
Clearly.
All right, so we get a chunk, we get a block.
The block is, is the first block, which is exactly what we would
expect.
So if I look at the block or bull clock as perhaps, I type in, I have
the edit account, they store 16.
/, so 10 is fine.
And so what we should be doing here is we should be incrementing it by
one.
Now.
It could be that the just the compiler being ridiculous.
Oops.
That's not what I meant to do.
So, I want to do one more check, which is just, let's take this
actual.
Value here, this actual pointer value.
So we could take a look at it.
Even after the, the scope exits because visual Studios awful at being
able to show you variables when they exit scope.
It's really, really bad.
So I what I want to do is just make sure that we're still looking at
it properly.
So fidget World empty block that at that pointer, there it is, and
there's those low entity index.
So 10.
This one should get filled next, right?
These should just be these should be relevant entities that aren't
actually doing anything, right?
now, because there's
Only 10 in there.
So we go ahead and do that.
This should increment it by 1 and stick it in there, which it did.
And so this is, you know, this block that has 11 things in it.
Now, the question is, why does that block not get iterated over to
move things into the hiset?
So, let's take a look when we go into set camera.
Let's just find out.
You know why it does that.
So offset and check frequency by area, we don't really care about.
That's the thing, that's that's removing things from the hiset.
We want to know why.
Something is not being added to the hiset.
So, let's take a look.
That men chunk P.
It's negative 2, negative 1 0.
Let's Take a look at the max chunk P the max junk P.
So that clearly would include the chunk that we're talking about.
So let's go ahead in here and take a look at our our code.
So we're going to grab the first chunk here.
There's nothing nothing in it.
So that's fine.
Again.
We're looking to see this block come up.
So what I could do to is I could just make it right here.
Where we actually where we actually see, which blocks are.
But, let's go ahead and look at the chunks first.
So, let's look at the chunks.
There's so here we go.
There's our chunk.
The chunk was 000, if I remember correctly.
So, we should be able to find chunk 000 here at some point, right?
What is our chunk?
Why chunk EX
This one, there's chunks zero.
All right.
So our first block is the actual block that we thought it should be
right and so entity 10 should actually be the entity that we're trying
to do the sword, right?
So let's see what happens.
We go into the block, don't know why it highlighted that line that's a
little odd.
Let's make sure that nothing weird just happened.
There.
Block.
And then let's step through this.
So we go through.
We're looking at the first entity.
It's 40, that's exactly what it should be.
So that's not necessary.
We come through here.
We're going to go through.
Let's let me just go ahead and put that in there, low entity index
rights 41.
And so we can go through several of these until we get up to the one
that we actually care about and all of these are already in the hiset
which is exactly what we would expect.
And but the next
One is the one we actually care about.
And so, here we are, this is actually 90 2005, which is the one we
actually care about.
So let's go ahead and see what happens.
We get its camera space p, right?
It's camera.
Space p is apparently complete garbage.
Why is this camera Pace?
Pace P complete garbage.
That's no good.
That's no good at all.
All.
So I guess the lesson here is that change and a deal.
Nation does not actually set the location of the entity.
It just updates the thing.
And I guess we kind of knew that if I maybe had been programming this
code base a little more regularly.
We just kind of know that.
So the question is, should I do something to just ensure that?
I mean, it looks like we're always doing that set anyway, so I guess
what I'd say is, can we just get rid of this?
And make it so that that always properly updates it, right.
So that was it.
We really didn't have much of a bug there.
It's actually just in our sword code that the spatial partition was
working just fine.
So really what we want to do is here on change entity location.
What we would want to do here is on changing the location.
We just want to update it.
So it basically at the end of this function after everything is done.
We'd say if there was a new position assigned to the guy, then we go
ahead and say assign that new position to where they are, where they
actually are, right.
Oh, so that's why we didn't do it.
We don't even have the low entities address.
All right, that actually makes some sense.
So I guess, what we want to do is we want to make that a little bit
more.
Yeah, we want to make that V8 something, where you actually pass a
little bit more in there.
Right?
We want to make that.
So that so that, this is more like a change, any location raw,
something like that.
Right?
And then we've got something more like this, right?
And that's enough code.
Now that this is probably not going to be something that's called in
line at all.
Alright, so this is going to be where we pass, you know.
The low end of the index and the low end of the pointer, right?
So if they can actually be assigned properly and so in that case, it
just goes ahead and punts directly to the the other function.
So it does the set like so.
And then it will also go ahead and handle the assignment so that we
won't have that kind of bug because that's not a bug.
We want to be having a lot, right?
It's annoying and it's hard to track down takes a little while.
Ow.
So I'm going to go ahead and make that so you call through this from
now on and what that's going to do is going to say, if there was a new
P then it goes.
And it says that the low entities P equals the new P.
Like so, but if there wasn't, then it'll say the new NP equals, the
null position, right?
Like that.
And so that should basically do it.
I think that's about it.
This will.
Now this would now just work.
I think could we just call that straight away if old PR in the same
chunk old P Nu P but if there's no old P, what happens if old P it
does this?
And I guess it, what we want to do something where it does if Nu P do
this, right?
So we won't do that.
If it's behind my head, I can't see what's going on.
Yeah.
So what we want to do is allow this function to take it so that they
could both be null.
So, at that point you wouldn't even have to do this anymore.
You just do that.
And then this happens to be, no, it just works, right?
And that looks pretty good.
Pretty good.
I would say.
Okay, so this note doesn't take that obviously.
So these guys all now just take that low entity.
As well.
And then, I think it's all good.
I think for lucky that fixes our problem.
This guy doesn't over assignment here.
It looks like our no, he doesn't.
So that's fine.
To change, entity location, that will take that actual sword entity.
And then, I think that's done.
All right, so hopefully we fixed our bug.
I don't know if he did or not, but we'll have to take a look, I guess
and see.
See if we did.
There we go.
So yes, there we go.
We were able to drop our sword now, so we're all good.
Alright, so basically, tomorrow, we will continue on that.
That route will implement the table that I talked about the beginning
here.
And then I think that's should be about it for our sword.
And then, we can sort of focus on what happens with hip points and
that sort of stuff.
So, that seems pretty reasonable.
So I had to go about 5 minutes over there.
I think we started about five minutes late, so it wasn't too much
longer.
That's that's that's not too bad.
It's good.
Like I said, you never want to leave bugs in your code base.
You always want to find them as soon as you possibly can, especially
in that circumstance, right?
That was a good one.
A fine too.
Because we move the code into a better place.
Where that bug can't happen really anymore in that way.
And so that's like what you want to do.
You want to always be moving towards something, where bugs that happen
once, don't happen again.
Because it doesn't cost a lot to hunt down any individual bug.
But if you have the kind of bug that perpetuates itself, that's where
you start getting into trouble.
All right.
So let's go ahead and and start the Q&A.
If you could, please prefix your question with Q: so I can see it.
And please try to keep it to stuff that we did on today's stream or
that we have done in a previous dream.
If you want to ask off-topic questions or ask about things that we
might do in the future or how we might do something.
Those are totally fine.
To ask, but please ask them during the pre stream.
So come about 15 minutes before the stream starts.
That's when we do off-topic stuff.
All right, QA it is Q&A time.
What do you mean that Visual Studio is horrible at showing variables.
So I can, I can I can actually tell you exactly what I meant I can.
I can literally just step through that same thing again that I was
showing before and I can, it's the kind of
Classic case of how bad Visual Studio is showing you variables and it
might be my imagination sometimes.
You know, my memory.
I'm old, right.
My memory is not so good.
But I seem to recall that this didn't used to actually be a problem.
I feel like they actually broke this.
But who knows?
So here we go.
I'm stepping through here, right?
And I'm in a situation where I've got this variable, it's called
block, right.
And here it is to find right there, and I want to see what happens to
block after this line is executed, right?
So, this is literally what I just did, right?
You remember seeing me do this?
So, I have this block, it has this array.
It's got a name of the account and I want to see what it does to this
when I step over this line.
So, I hit F10 to step over the line and Watch What Happens.
Right?
You have no idea what happened now.
This is what it shows.
You.
It shows you stale information.
This is not even what is still at this pointer.
Right?
It's freaking ridiculous.
And now if you hit the refresh key in it, deletes the whole thing,
right?
And I don't know if there's a way, I don't know.
Like, you might be able to just refresh one of them like so here's
block and here's this and I step and now like I refresh just that one.
No, you can't even do that.
So it's just awful like it knows the pointer the porters.
The same.
It didn't change a show.
Me what's at that location, right?
It's horrid, and it didn't use to have this problem.
It used to be in like Visual Studio, 6 and stuff, or at least in five.
It must be five or six.
It would just still show you this after the fact, it just be like,
well, that's this is what at the memory now if you want to see it and
like, yeah, I do want to see it.
And so you have to go through all these gyrations.
It's just, it's really bad.
Visual Studio has gotten worse with every revision.
It's awful.
And unfortunately, you have no choice but to upgrade because you need
the new code gen.
Like you need to be able to upgrade to the newer compilers to Output
to like x64 first.
And then to AVX avx2.
You need to upgrade to the newer compilers and when you upgrade to a
compilers, you have to upgrade your debuggers because the older
debuggers can't support those new instruction sets and blah blah blah.
And then your debugger just gets worse with every revision.
So,
So yeah, this debugger is like 10 times worse than to the letter that
came with Ms.
Vc5, its way, way worse.
And unfortunately, that's just, that's the, yeah, that's par for the
course.
It's Visual Studio.
You just you, you like brace yourself every time they compliment
upgrade.
Your like, what are all the things that they broke in the upgrade,
right?
When doing exploratory experimental programming, I find it difficult
to decide between seeing things through or switching to a different
approach.
There have been many times.
Is where I start off on a path and things are going great.
But eventually, I stalled due to some unforeseen problem often.
I spend a crazy amount of time thinking about how to solve get around
the problem.
Even in simple ways analysis paralysis, if you will any suggestions
literally just keep on writing code, no matter how dumb it is,
question mark.
I'm out of cough drops, which is never a good thing side side note.
so,
It's a kind of a case-by-case.
Basis is what I would say.
Obviously and this was kind of a thing.
This actually came up on the forums a little bit.
Someone had pointed to a person who had a blog post, who is kind of
saying that, you know, I often say compression oriented.
Programming is a good way to go, right?
You explore.
You can press, explore compress, right?
And this person wrote a blog entry.
Excuse me, where they were talking about how, like well that doesn't
really work because you might compress the code wrong, right?
Which is a hilarious objection to have, because it's kind of like
saying, you know, you asked someone, if you go ask, you know, Usain
Bolt or whatever.
How are you running?
And he's like, oh, well, you know you like you start off and you like
move one leg in front of the other one.
And you push on that one while you lift up the other leg and put it in
front of the other one and just repeat that process.
Right?
And then someone goes out on a track and they like follow those
instructions.
And they're like, why am I not running as fast as Usain Bolt?
I didn't break this and you're like, yeah because, you know, you suck
at running like sorry, right.
And that was the case.
Freshen the blog post.
And so the answer there is like, we're all trying to be Usain Bolt,
right?
We're all trying to go in that direction.
We're trying to get our Sprint up to that speed.
We're trying to do it.
There's the argument about what is the right ways to run meaning the
mechanics of it.
But then there's also just the practice involved, right?
And no amount of knowing how Usain Bolt runs is actually going to let
you run at his speed.
So what we're all trying to do, and I try every day when I'm
programming, I'm constantly trying to improve as well, right?
I'm trying to I'm trying to get to bolt land, right?
Is there's there's the analysis of the mechanics and then there's just
the practice and unfortunately, at some point it is the case that the
practice is what really counts the most.
And so what I was going to say about your question was, there's a
split there, some of what you may be running into is stuff that you
can think about, in terms of abstract mechanics.
Like, am I putting one foot in front of the other, right?
Like, am I?
Pushing off, right?
Am I doing these other things, right?
Then we can talk about abstract lie, but the other half of it.
From the from the analogy, right?
Is just the practice, just the running everyday and tuning, all of
your instincts and your Locomotion and everything, so that you've got
it down where you can really go super fast, right?
And that's the part that is not necessarily something you can talk
about abstractly, right?
Because there's so many different techniques that you might learn and
intuitions that you might build up over time, having architected lots
and lots of pieces of code seed, how they've gone understood what
their limitations are that sort of stuff, that bank of knowledge is
not really replicable with someone just saying, here's how to do this
process.
Right?
And that is also something that I think is a problem.
A lot of computer science or computer.
Programming related stuff, is they talk about methodologies as if
those methodologies are themselves executable directly, but there is
no such thing as that in my experience.
I've never seen a thing where you can just say here is how you design
code to someone and then they go design.
Good code.
That doesn't happen.
You can say here are this different procedures and how they work
roughly.
But there's still a tremendous amount of inherent knowledge.
Age that nobody has figured out how to communicate that.
You just have to practice and get better at right.
So to answer your question, specifically after giving that friend of
very long framing about it, right?
Is there's two things you can do to get better, if you're having
trouble with code architecture.
One is to think about whether there are systemic things.
You are doing that are problematic.
Right?
And that is the first part that I talked about and that stuff, like,
are you actually writing enough usage codes?
First?
Are you actually taking the time to think about how something supposed
to work?
Are you actually spending the time to stop and write little use cases
for all the things that you were doing and verify that you really were
writing them the right way, blah blah, blah, right.
Are you actually doing the mechanical steps of
I'd like compression already program data or any program.
Whatever it is that you think is the methodology that you want to use.
Are you actually doing that or Heaven help you?
If you're an object-oriented programmer still same thing applies,
right?
Are you actually doing the steps that object-oriented program
professionals would have told you to do, right?
And that part, you can do cerebrally like that's the part.
You can sit down and say am I actually following the advice of the
people who are experts in this field.
Am I actually doing the same things?
They're doing, right?
So, I don't know.
Like I said, I can't see how your code.
But you know, the first question we ask is like, can you identify any
of those things that you're not doing, right?
And then the second part of it is to go.
Okay, if I don't think that that's my problem.
So I'm looking at the kinds of problems.
I'm having and I don't think that's it.
I did try the use of cases.
I did have a good idea of what I wanted this code to do.
I did have examples of it that I wrote and then when I went to do the
architecture, I still mess it up.
It that is a case where I think you're probably just in that
unfortunate place where you just haven't had enough practice yet,
right?
And there's really nothing you can do to short-circuit that process,
other than write lots of code, right?
The more code, you write, the more practice you will get and the less
mistakes like that.
You will make, because you will have seen the consequences of
different types of compression.
You can do of different types of structure of the code and then
So when you are making your decisions, they'll all be that much
better, everytime, right?
And so one thing you could do to accelerate that process is you could
start trying to tackle smaller problems.
Take something that caused you a problem.
Like you're talking about, you're having a problem.
So you've I deleted something that was causing your problem.
Can you pull that problem out?
Can you iterate it on a few times?
Can you take your solutions that you then come up with?
How do you feel about them?
Can you post them like on the hammer hero forums and we'll look at
them and see what other experienced programmers have to say.
About those Solutions.
Are they good?
Do you did you make obvious mistakes?
What were those mistakes?
Right?
And bye-bye may be cranking up that iteration time.
You can get more practice at the parts, you're bad at, right?
Instead of having to go through coal projects, with only them coming
up occasionally and then you're really not getting that much practice
at any.
Given one?
And the cost is high for those mistakes because you've got this whole
thing around it, right?
And so I don't know but yeah, but that that
That's really all I can say about that.
Is that gives the full framework of how I think about?
Anyway, if you want to run like Usain Bolt, you gotta be willing to do
both things.
You got to be able to know that you're doing the right stuff.
Mechanically, but also that you're just practicing every day and
getting all of those subtle things that no one really quite yet is
able to communicate how to do them in a way that doesn't require you
to learn them yourself and have them ingrained you got to do both and
I don't know that there's really any substitute.
Those things.
Will you handle the case where a sword in a monstar would hit each
other, but are moving toward each other so fast that they pass through
each other without colliding, in a single frame.
Yes, or move entity code already.
Does that right arm move entity code, which will just probably call it
the sword as well.
Our move enemy code already handles that case, right?
Because remember, we did Mankowski and we did Ray casting so we don't
tunneling.
Can't happen in our system right now.
Do you think cheesing like making enemies Invincible for ten frames
after being hit is a game design sin or just something you'd rather
avoid.
I think it's it's if we were going to use the word sin, I think it's
just a handmade hero sin.
Like, basically, the reason that I'm doing this stream, right?
Is because I want to sort of demonstrate how I do game programming.
And so, what I want to do is try to do a good job on all of the things
that we do, so I'm trying to make sure that we set everything up to do
a good job when, you know, in a couple weeks or so.
When we switch over to doing the real engine code.
I want to show how to do a very good job on each of those pieces.
And then, you know, at the end of the day, the goal for the series is
to have each thing that I showed how to do be done at a high level of
quality so that people can learn from it.
Right.
But I don't want to do is show how to avoid doing.
Good work by designing the game to not require it, right?
but,
That does not mean that's what you should do when you are making your
game.
And the reason for that is because certain game design decisions,
could save you a lot of time coding.
If a particular algorithm necessary to handle a particular aspect of
the game design is very hard and changing the game design to something
else would not actually cause a problem, but would eliminate this hard
thing that you don't have time to do that, may get the product on
sooner.
It may keep the momentum of the project up.
It may do a lot of
Positive things for you.
And so I definitely don't want to say that.
Nobody should cheese things.
All I want to say is, you should know how not to, and then you can
make an informed decision on every individual case whether or not
cheesing was good or bad there and then you either cheese it or you
don't based on your instinct for whether the total impact on the
project will be better or worse.
With are you cheese or not cheesed?
Because again, there's only so much time in the day.
Everyone, you know, times the only non renewable resource, right?
As they say, so if you go into something and you think, oh, I'm just
going to do as hardcore engineering on every last thing as I possibly
can.
Well, that's probably honestly, as much as I admire that mentality and
as much as I think that's an interesting to have on some products
sometimes, if that's what you wanted to do, right?
And it's sort of what we're trying to do here and that will keep
trying to Aspire to right.
As much as that's interesting here that may not be a very good
attitude to have when you're actually developing game.
When you're actually developing the game.
You might want to have more flexibility, know what the good
engineering would be learn enough so that, you know, so that you don't
have to cheese.
But then at each individual Point decide to cheese or not based on
what would be the best for the project in the hole, right?
That's important because if a project that would have taken two years
takes ten years because you refuse to do any Cheese's.
Something right?
That was four more games.
Maybe you didn't make.
And so yeah, this one game may have no cheese in it whatsoever.
But was that a good decision for the whole time?
Right?
And so you always have to be making those trade-offs because
everything is a trade-off and you can't have one dogmatic.
That you just always go by because I think you'll end up making bad
decisions if you do.
Symmetry.
Why not just use the auto window so well because I was trying to look
at something specific and I like to have my watch window set up so
that I see the things that I see.
Like, I tend to set up things so that they're it's listing exactly
what I want and things don't move around in, don't change.
You can use the Autos window for people who want to use it.
It's in the debug Windows Auto, right?
It's right there.
Like, you can see it here, and and this gives you the things that are
kind of like what it thinks you want to see.
Unfortunately, you will notice that the problem that I just said, was
that have the watch window is even worse with the Autos window.
When you step over that block, everything goes away.
So, even though you could use the Autos window to save you, some time
typing things into the Watchman, do if you thought that might was a
problem.
I personally don't like the element so I don't use it.
But it's worth noting the Autos window does not solve the problem that
I just showed.
Is visual C++.
Still better than open source Alternatives.
The debugger is although give them a few more revisions and maybe it
won't be like the developer gets worse with every time.
So, at some point, it may be that Visual Studio debugger is so bad.
That future Creator is as good, right?
Or something that could totally happen because every release
Microsoft's ships a worse and worse to bugger.
So basically, like, at some point, it may be that
That it actually the open source ones are actually better.
That could happen.
But at the moment.
No, the visual debugger is still better than any open source soon, as
I see the compiler, on the other hand is much worse.
So the open source alternatives for compilers like clang, clang is
much better than Visual Studio compiler on every front, pretty much.
There may be a few optimization things.
That msec does better.
I'm not sure but by and large clang does everything better.
So if you're talking about the compiler,
Clang is far superior.
If you're talking about the debugger Visual Studio, unfortunately, is
still pretty much the best you're going to get.
It's a sad State of Affairs.
When visual Studios, the best of butter you can get.
That's where we're at.
It's a sad world.
I'm just living in it.
What would you think about adapting the art style to be easier to
implement either at all or this early on the trite example, being for
the sword Collision?
You mentioned?
What if you were to say something like the sword is going to teleport
along the path instantly in one frame and some red line a bit like
anime, that would be persistent through a couple of frames.
Basically potentially fundamentally changing, the art style with a
purpose of getting things to run better.
Are there any examples of something like this occurring that you might
have heard of?
So again?
Yeah, I don't have really much to say about that question that I
didn't already say, you probably typed it in before I set all the
stuff that I had said.
So, yeah, same thing applies there.
Yes, you can always pick.
You can always get out of a programming Jam by changing our tour game
design.
I don't want to do any of that on this dream because the goal here is
to show programming.
So we're going to take everything head-on and stick with it until it
works.
We are not going to change the game design to benefit the programming.
We're going to do the opposite, pretty much exclusively, but that
doesn't mean that isn't a valid option for you.
On your projects.
You have to make that call every time based on what you think would be
best for the project.
Let's see.
Um,
so it looks like we've only got maybe two more questions.
So I'll answer these two blocks of three.
Are you working on the road to bugger?
No, I am not but yes, I would I would start using it on handmade hero
if when it's ready if the red it's red chips a debugger even primitive
Like A Primitive one.
That's decent.
I would I would totally switched it on the Stream.
But I haven't gotten one of those yet.
You always talk about the ways of programming when you started or when
programming was at its prime.
How can an 18 year old?
Know what it's like, or get the knowledge.
You have about programming, are there?
Any books are languages or something I can do to learn the old ways of
programming.
So, basically, handmade hero is mostly trying to be that bridge to
some extent.
That's why I started the project and it's what we try to focus on.
We're sort of trying to show the old school way of programming, but in
a new context.
So, you know, we know, now we can allocate 4 gigabytes of memory and
it's not a big deal, right?
So we accept those things, and we try to do powerful things with them,
but we still write everything from scratch.
We still write everything, you know, at a low level and we build up
from the low level to a high level as we go on our own and try to
practice that same sort of stuff that people did.
In the old days, is it as hardcore as the people who did in the old
days.
Is absolutely not.
They were writing things in Assembly Language from scratch and it was
a much harder World.
They barely had to Butters half the time, didn't have to bother us at
all.
We have it very easy compared to them, but I am trying to kind of
create that bridge too.
What are the good things from the old school programming?
How can we bring them forward?
And how can we kind of encourage other people to keep doing them?
Are there?
Good books on the topic?
I don't really know, you know, if you just want a taste of that sort
of thing and just want to get a feel for it as opposed to like a good
thing to use to maybe for Less.
Sorry for learning per se.
I feel like the Bruce are Twix.
Don't know how to spell his name.
I feel like there's a couple books that were kind of classic in that
way that you.
Might be able to, to take a look at, this would be one example, right?
My computer displays graphics and animation.
This is by the guy who wrote Flight Simulator, the original flight
simulator.
I can't remember if there's other books along these lines, you know,
maybe one of Mike, a Brash has books.
So, like the Zen of Graphics programming or something like that, you
know, take a look at those.
Those are available.
Those might be some that would get you to sort of have a sense of what
used to go on back.
Then they'll go through the thing of like, getting a texture map or
down from 40 cycles per pixel to three cycles for Pixel or whatever,
you know, those sorts of things.
And like how they even implemented flight simulator at all, on an
Apple 2, which was kind of crazy at those times and that sort of stuff
that might give you a sense for like the kinds of stuff.
They went through, as a as to how to learn to code like them.
I don't know because I don't even know how to code like that.
Like I wasn't really in that.
I wasn't alive in any meaningful sense in the 70s.
I was I was born in 76.
So by the time I was four years old.
The 70s were over, right?
So I never really experienced any of that.
Learn to code to like 83 I think.
And so, you know, I really just don't have that same kind of
background.
Let's see.
All right, so I'll answer two more here.
Why do you pick C++ of all things?
So interesting, like, I don't know why people think C++ is such an odd
Choice, when almost every game is programmed in C++, right?
People people kind of look at it in like, oh my God, why would you be
programming game and C++ as if somehow not all games are program to
see us, but almost all games are like the vast majority of games in.
Are programmed in either C++ or something lower than C++ like C or
assembly?
Right?
It is only very, very recently that game started beer.
It being written, really in anything other than C++.
I mean, if you went back and start talking about things like there
were games written in fourth or modulo or, you know, stuff like this.
But, you know, games were written in things that were as low level or
lower level than C++ throughout all of history.
And so really, it's only very recently.
recently that things like C sharp or
Ava have been languages that anyone would consider writing a game and
the only reason that they can do that.
Now is basically, for one of two reasons one, because they don't
really have much in the way of serious performance requirements, which
is often the case or two.
Because most of the game is actually still written in C++ and they're
just writing the part that sits on top of that.
So for example, anyone who writes a game in unity, well, a lot of the
unity engine is written in C++.
It's only the like part that your game.
That's like the script stuff.
If that's written in C, sharp, right?
And so, since on handmade hero, we're showing how to write the whole
thing engine included.
Obviously we would not be using something like C sharp or Java that
that would just not be a smart choice at all.
So really C++ is kind of the only choice.
I would say if you actually want to write a high Performance Engine,
it's pretty much the only thing that you really have at the moment.
Unless you we're going to use straight.
See, which is again, we kind of are mostly, but we use some CSS
features, so we're almost kind of going that way.
Or you go Assembly Language /.
Some other kind of like, you know, D, maybe or something like that,
but C++ is not a surprising choice.
I feel like if you asked any game program in the industry at random,
I'm you know, what would you start playing a game?
And right now they probably say C++.
It's not a strange choice.
I think it's only strange to people who aren't maybe professional game
programmers.
I'm not sure.
But I get that question a lot.
And it's always surprising because it's like
Yo, man, all games are programmed in C++.
Last question, let's see here.
I thought there was one other one on here that I was going to ask
answer.
Maybe I've got everything.
Maybe I got all the questions.
I think I did.
I guess I'll just as an addendum to that answer.
One of the questions I see here, which is would there have been any
easier language to program the game in?
And yes, there probably would have been an easier language to program
the game in if you didn't want to do the engine.
And you didn't want to do some of the more advanced game design stuff
that we're going to be doing.
I could have scaled the game down like it.
Let's say we just wanted to make Legend of Zelda.
That's it.
It's literally Legend of Zelda.
We could easily have done that in like, XNA or python pygame, right?
And largely.
The reason that would have been easier is not because the language is
any easier.
The language is really aren't any easier.
The main reason, it would have been easier as because there's giant
libraries that do everything for you.
Right?
So if we just decided not to write,
Engine and not to write.
And to just use a ton of libraries.
Then there would have been easier.
C++ is not a great language for libraries like the libraries that are
available C++ aren't.
Don't tend to be as full complete.
I find as some other things so, you know, yeah, you could go use x and
ay, and it'd be easier because if you weren't trying to write an
engine, you just use the engine exists or you could go use unity and
some like that.
So easy is all you care about and performance isn't
Super important and special considerations for bunch of game design
things.
As an important etcetera, Etc.
Then you can definitely go with something easier and basically what
that boils down to, it's less about the language.
It's more about the libraries at that point.
It's about finding something that has all the libraries that do what
you want, you know, and like, as another obvious statement.
Let's say you were going to make a first person shooter.
So you kind of just pretty much know what you're dealing with.
Exactly.
You could go use the Unreal Engine and you know,
Going to be able to handle a first person shooter, right?
It's a professional code base that ship multiple first present for
you.
Just use it and off you go.
Right?
So things like that, you know, if you're just looking for easy,
there's definitely ways that you can do things that are designed for
you to do the least amount of work.
Those would be different options.
Certainly.
All right.
Hmm.
I think that's about it.
I'm going to I'm going to call it.
It's getting a little late here and I will say answer, two more quick.
He's here which is to be able to surpass the processes that affect our
language decode games.
And what would you have to do is a language that would make you better
than C++?
Just go watch.
John blows stream.
John Blow is making a language.
That's better than C++ right now.
And it probably already is pretty much better than C++ right now
because C++ really hasn't advanced in about 30 years.
It's pretty much as bad as see, see was a good language for its time.
But C++ really hasn't had anything of value.
For the most part, John has been adding a lot of things of value to
his language.
And so I suspect that the answer to your question is go watch John
stream and he will show you exactly all of the things you can add,
that makes a language better than C4 coding games.
and,
And then I'll also say to the person who asked they can have a witness
Beta key.
I am not in charge of doing out witness beta keys.
You will have to ask John.
All right, so that's it.
And let's go ahead and wrap it up for the day.
Let us, let us close down.
Like so close close.
Close.
And minimize.
All right.
Thank you very much.
Everyone for joining me for another episode of handmade hero.
It has been a pleasure coding with you.
As always.
I will be back here tomorrow night.
Same place.
Same time 8:00 p.m.
Pacific Standard time, on Twitch.
Where I will be going ahead and doing some.
I guess basically will be having these guys fight.
So I guess the monster and the hero with his new sword sword will,
will be able to attack each other and, and then kill each other.
I guess we'll go ahead and plan Implement that tomorrow and and
continue on our path towards getting everything.
Nailed down for exactly what we need the engine to do, and I think
that's pretty good.
Seems to be coming along.
Well, in my opinion, I think everything is going roughly the way that
I want it to.
So I'm pretty happy about it and I
Hope you are too, if you would like to follow along at home and do
experimenting on your own and that sort of stuff.
You can always pre-order handmade hero and it comes with all the
source code that you can play around with and of course, all the
videos from past days are all available as well.
So you can see how to set it up and how to use it by watching those as
well.
If you want to do that.
You can go to handmade hero dot org and hit that pre-order button.
That will do that for you.
If you want to support the video series.
We also have a patreon.
You subscribe to.
We've got a schedule bot that you can follow on Twitter if you do this
tweet,
Thing, you can follow that button.
It's got like the schedule tweeted every day.
So, you know what time the stream is.
And we also have a news and Forum site that I highly recommend going
to, we're trying to overhaul a little bit, do some more stuff up
there.
I've been working on that a little bit lately, to kind of get it out
of the web nightmare.
That is Joomla.
But if you go there, it's got stuff like a discussion board.
You can post questions and ask, you know, discuss things with with
fellow developers who follow the series.
It's got resources.
So if you want to follow along on like Mac or Linux, which are
platforms.
We haven't poured it to yet.
There are people in the community who have already done those ports
that you can piggyback on.
You can go see how they did it.
You can download the source code, they've often times posted it for
free, so you can go take a look at that.
And it's also got an episode guide that you can use to catch up on
past episodes.
It's a lot better than using YouTube directly for the ones that people
have annotated.
So I'd highly recommend checking that out.
So yeah.
Hope to see you here tomorrow night.
Same time.
Same place.
Have a wonderful Tuesday.
Day, and I will see you then.
Take it easy, everyone.