Hello, everyone, and welcome to handmade hero.
The show where we code complete game live on stream.
We have a special guest in the studio with us, who will be joining us
for the rest of our streams, as a trusted companion.
If you have noticed, if you are a observant viewer, you may have
noticed that there is now a little owl icon up in the corner here.
This a like on was generously donated by quarter Tron.
If you see seen him around
On the streams on the IRC or on the twitch chat, as quarter Tron, key
sent me a pretty fabulous device.
A few months ago, about two months ago, I haven't had a chance to
really play with it.
I had a chance this morning to do so and make sure it was all working
and so I have it set up.
Now, it is a notification owl, that is actually a physical device, and
I don't know if you can see this here on the webcam, but it's a
little, I don't want to stretch the
Chord too far but it's a little owl and well let me see if you can see
that on that.
Let me bring up the little window and see if you can see that here.
It's really hard to for me to.
I can't quite well, you know what, I can unplug him.
There we go.
It's a little owl.
And on the back of the owl, is a like USB plug can see you kind of
have a USB but and if you plug this USB, but into the cable and plug
it into the computer, the owl can be told to light up.
And so, for example, when you first plug it in, it'll light up, just
to tell you, it's working.
But now if I go on too,
A stream.
And I'm going to go onto the handmade Network IRC, which is where it
listens.
If I talk to a labott and just say something, then he will, The Little
Owl will light up.
That is how this works.
I don't actually know.
I should probably restart him here.
Here we go.
All right, I don't actually know if I think only quarter Tron can
signal him, I did give info about the ability to Signal him as well.
And so, at some point, we'll have to get in sohbat to be to be able to
Signal him for various reasons.
Yeah, there he goes.
So I don't know if you can see this again because I think the cable
doesn't quite reach as long as it might have to.
Maybe I can just put it in the corner here.
There you go.
So I'm going to go ahead and try to Signal him here.
So you on the IRC.
You can see you see how he lights up like that.
That's what
So what that means is, I will be able to see if there's something a
problem with the stream.
Like there is sometimes we had this happen.
So I wanted to try and get him working.
We had this happen where the stream.
I there was a hotkey or something in in OBS that made it.
So that my like webcam took over the full size of the screen last time
or something.
So hopefully, the the
A labott signal, can be used now to to Signal me when there is a
problem and I trust that we can add people to the owl bot signal, okay
list.
So that someone will always be watching and signal if there is a
problem.
So, there you go.
That is our new feathered friend and thank you very much.
The quarter Tron for sending that in, it's pretty awesome.
I think he's kind of got this down now.
He, I think he was saying that he now makes these guys.
They're, they're basically like little, I don't know, like bath toys
or something little or like cat toys or something that he then like
kind of Hollows out apart in the back and puts an Arduino into, it's a
pretty great idea.
So
You should set up a little store notification.
I will store.
All right.
So that's that is our special guest and as long as he is up here or
she, I guess I don't know the gender of this owl.
But the friendly notification owl can let me know if anything weird is
going down.
So we are now good to go.
All right I will go ahead and get started here.
Let's go ahead and open up the project.
and if you remember from last week,
We're actually the part where almost everything is what we wanted it
to be at a basic level.
The only thing that we were unable to get working on this graphics
card is apparently, for whatever reason, multi-sample rendering, which
we now use multi sample rendering is not available with srgb, which
makes not a whole lot of sense because those things should probably
not be related, but I guess they are.
I mean I guess I could see why they might be if you're writing to
multiple samples maybe the hardware that does the translation is only
works on Sample zero or something like this if that's possible it
seems unlikely obviously but you know it's how should I know right?
I don't know how the internals of this card work.
I'm definitely not in the position to say what should or should not be
easy in the particular pipeline that this card implemented because I
have no idea what they implemented.
But suffice to say, that means our Graphics are
Not quite correct.
So what we're looking at here is almost an exact replica of what we
had had before we decided to put all the 3D stuff but there's there's
like all the colors are too dark right there.
They're being rendered as if they have srgb.
So like the textures are in an srgb format, the rendering is set to
use srgb but srgb is not available in terms of the texture that
We're to which we are rendering.
And so, as a result, we get incorrect results.
Now we can fix this by implementing srgb ourselves and maybe that's
the right solution.
I don't know if we just Implement srgb ourselves.
What that means is that we will Square n square, root our colors as
they come in and out of the pipeline and we would just do this
manually.
The reason this is not a great solution is because if you really want
to do this,
Correctly.
You would have to turn off, bilinear, filtering in the hardware and
actually take the bilinear samples yourself because bilinear filtering
itself wants the correction of the srgb done before the bilinear
combined.
Because remember if you're trying to do linear math operations, which
by linear as its name, implies certainly is you want to do that in
light linear space, not in srgb space, which is an exponential space
where bilinear filtering will not produce the correct results.
So,
That being said, I'm not sure how to progress.
On this particular card in a way that makes a lot of sense because
certainly, we don't want to, you know, we don't want to handicap all
the modern cards out there that would have no trouble turning that on.
So I think what we have to do here is probably try to figure out some
way of detecting whether a card can't do this or not and if we detect
it then we can do the squaring and square rooting in the Shader.
But if we don't detect it, then we won't.
That seems like the best plan.
The problem is that's easier said than done and the reason that that's
easier said than done is just because, well, I don't really know if
there's any way to do it.
Other than just trying to create the texture ourselves.
Now maybe that's the best plan.
I don't know and then when we try to create the texture we will then
find that it failed using check gel error.
And then when we find that it failed, will try again without that flag
and see how we do.
That's the only thing I can think of right now.
I don't think there's some other way.
I don't think there's a capability, kind of a query.
You can do that asks, whether or not you can support multi sample plus
srgb.
So I think that's pretty much where we're at right now.
I can't really give any more of an estimation than that.
So what I
We're going to have to do here is you know, if we've got this sort of
situation here where we've got supports srgb frame buffer and default
internal texture format I feel like probably what we're going to want
to do here is maybe regress this a little bit and maybe just have
something that's like supports srgb or srgb support.
Right?
And what we could sort of do here is just say like, all right, if it
has srgb support everywhere then we turn it on everywhere and we do
srgb and Hardware whereas if we detect that it doesn't have srgb
support.
Then we do srgb nowhere and we insert into our Shader code that will
correct for the srgb that's coming out of the textures.
That's the only thing I can think of there.
Be something smarter to do, but that's when they can think of right
now.
So since that's the only actual likes bug, we have at the moment.
That's a I think the first thing to rectify because we can't really
call our rendering done because there's so much stuff I want to do,
like I want to go clean up how we're mute.
Like, right now we're still using partly opengl fixed function
pipeline because I just showed how to add shaders, just lacks week.
I'd like to go in and like, get rid of the rest of the fixed function
pipeline so that we're entirely on shaders and buffers or something
like that.
Just to clean everything up.
I like to do that.
But before we do that, I would definitely like
To make sure that we are rendering properly, that's really it.
Now, I suppose the other thing I should do to, actually I guess before
I go too far down that road is, I don't remember how we were
initializing our opengl.
Exactly.
So I want to, I should probably make sure just just do a check to make
sure that we didn't do something in initialization that would make us.
That would cause us not to have these capabilities when we actually
should have them.
So, for example, in our attribute list, right?
You can see that we pass a bunch of information here in
Terms of what we want for our pixels.
And then in terms of our opengl context, we have a bunch of stuff
here.
Like major version, our band minor version, our been stuff like that.
So I don't really know which context we would necessarily need.
Like it may be that a 3.0 context isn't supposed to be able to have
the srgb frame buffers with multi sample for all.
I know you know I don't know.
So it could be that we just needed to make this go up further.
So I don't know if
This card supports opengl 4.0 but we could try we could just see what
happens if we did that.
I don't know what would happen, but we could take and set a breakpoint
in their it during initialization and see whether we get higher
context, if we ask for it and then if we do ask for the higher
context, I could try again to see if maybe in a higher context setting
we would get that better texture format handling, I don't know like I
said it's this totally just speculative on my part.
So I'm going to go in here.
You can see us getting extensions here and then our initialization.
So in this right here where we do context of trip Barb, I'll just step
in and see did we get one?
We did not so it would fall down to a backup context in the case where
we ask for 4.0.
So 3.0 is definitely the Baseline.
I don't know if I can ask for 3.1, let's find out if I can
So 3.1, I can ask for again, not sure that would do me any good at
all, especially since we have a compatibility contest specified.
So, I'm assuming it would not my assumption is that it would not
prevent us from doing something with the compatibility bit set.
But, you know, I don't really know again.
Drivers are very fussy and finicky, and they don't conform to spec
most of the time.
So I just want to be doubly.
Sure, that there isn't something going on there.
That's preventing us.
Getting back to work.
So if I now come in here and I turn this back on, I'm expecting it to
still not work.
I'm expecting it to give me an assertion there.
Just got it, clean that up.
Its
this now,
Yeah.
And so we still are unable to call that we are still unable to call,
Geo text 2D multi sample.
So I'm assuming that it just can't handle that for whatever reason.
This card can't do that.
So I'm going to go back to win 3-2 handmade and turn that off because
I don't think we really need that for any particular reason.
So 3.0 context is fine.
So in here, basically, what I need to do now is have a way of instead
of this being a default, internal texture format.
I need to have a way of specifying this as not being srgb and and
figuring that out.
So what what we need to do I think is go in here and have a test where
we basically call this function and see whether we can call it at all,
basically create like a canary in the mine field.
So to speak, where
We can try to do this call and see what happens, right?
So I'm guessing that we do something down here.
Where we would say, all right, you know, GL text image, 2D
multi-sample Geo, oops, texture at their, it was 2D multi sample.
We would specify that Max multi sample count, which I could just get
Once.
In fact, that could be done instead of being done here, we could
actually pull this out and put it in the open gel.
Structure itself, right?
So up in here, where we've got
I guess it could be Glu in.
It's called pap.
So, what I can do now is say, alright, I've got that Max multi sample
count.
I'm going to go ahead and get that robe open gel.
I'm going to clamp it as well to 16 because I don't want to ever be
higher than that.
That's, that would just be excessive at that point for our purposes.
So when we take a look at the multi sample,
We can then use it to say.
Let's go ahead and try to create one of those.
I need to bind a texture here and I need to bind the oops.
I need to bind a texture and try it.
And then
Undo it.
I don't remember if we need to bind it to that Slaughter.
Not, I think we do.
Yeah, we do.
So, I'm just going to bind a texture to that slot.
A dummy that doesn't really exist.
It doesn't do anything.
I'm going to try here to just make one, right?
And I'm going to pretend that it looks like the screen, right?
So it looks like a dummy kind of screen that we might expect to use,
and then we could say, all right, if we can get one of these with srgb
then we will use it.
Otherwise we will right.
So once we've set that default context firm and we look at this will
specify the texture.
We also want to delete that texture after we're done.
So I guess, I don't know how to tell it that, we don't need that
texture anymore, which is interesting.
I guess I could GL text image, multi, sample was 0 but I need to tell
it that it can release the the
The state backed by that, I could do that with delete texture by doing
a gen textures and then, delete textures, let me double check to make
sure that that's the right way to actually get rid of that because I
want, I don't want that texture sitting around because it's just
taking up graphics card memory at that point.
So, let me just take a look and see what that does.
Specifically, oops.
So I think we can just call that.
I think we can just call GL delete textures.
Test texture.
Equals 1.
And for good measure, I suppose we could actually just have it, do it
GL textures, one test texture.
And so here you know I'm just going to go ahead and create this test
texture.
See if GL text image 2D multi sample works and then delete it if it
doesn't.
So what I'm going to do here is just say
You'll get error to clear the air and then he'll get error to get the
are back.
So I'll say if you'll get error equals Jill no error.
In this case actually what I really want is not equal to.
And what I'll do here is just say, okay in the case where it doesn't
work, we'll just regress from what I said, right?
We'll go back to just doing
Our GPA.
So what I can do here is I can clean this up a little bit more.
To what I could do here is just say like okay, if we're going to
If we're going to do this, we might as well get this guy first, right?
And then only if we actually we're going to set this to True, let's
just only do the test in there.
That way I can do it a little bit more snazzle e, right?
If we were going to do something that would have the frame buffer
support and the texture support already and we think that's going to
work, then we go.
Okay, let's try the test texture now, do that.
And if it equals know,
our then we'll go ahead and do it and will enable it here like so,
Right.
And so then the only change we have to make there is the texture
format.
We were going to use.
We have to supply that in here.
Right.
So now we come through and we say, all right, if we have a chance at
supporting srgb, let's go ahead and try to create a texture here and
see if the texture is created properly then we'll assume that we can
do it.
If it's not then we'll assume that we can't do it and off we would go
right.
I think that's about it.
I think that's really all we need, they're right.
So I'm going to go ahead and test that out and see if that actually
works.
We don't know if it will or not.
We need to go ahead and put that in.
There we go.
Real nice sample count.
It does seem like 32f.
I'm not sure why I put 32 F in there.
That's probably not useful.
We don't really need float.
Should probably be 32.
Floating-point, obviously only has 24 bits of precision, whereas an
integer has 32 bits of precision and we don't need a wide range.
So we're, you know, a very small view distance in terms of what we
See on the screen.
So I feel like we just probably want a 32-bit integer there but that's
that's I don't know why that was like that.
That's just how that is.
Just how that was, and it should be changed.
So, okay, we just gotta change these to the max multi sample, count
variable that we now store permanently when we do get texture, what is
the problem here?
GN, okay.
Sorry it's not an unsigned, it's a signed integer apparently.
There we go.
And
I guess what I'm not sure about is supports srgb frame before.
I don't actually know who's using that right now.
Does anyone know, support groups?
So, I want to do a search.
Sports srgb, frame buffer.
So that's in win32.
So that's really just used by.
By this.
So that's not really a Boolean, right?
So really the only thing that I'm not really building that we use in
the open gel layer so that really all we're talking about here in
terms of stuff we care about.
In fact, I don't know.
That's interesting.
I don't know who even sets this or why.
I guess it just gets set in the info.
Would be my guess.
Anyway it's not a very good indicator of it.
So really what I want to do is like Shader srg Shader, Sim srgb, we'll
set that to false.
And in here what I'll do is say the Shader has to simulate srgb in the
case where we don't support it.
I guess I would do that like this.
Right.
So then we would get down here to our Shader code and in our Shader
code, we need a way of specifying whether or not it needs to do the
srgb in the Shader, right?
So what we want to do here is basically introduced, probably like it
if deaf or something like this.
So we've got our header code here, right?
And here's the, here's the header code.
What we want to do is probably do something like, well, okay.
Here's the header code which normally doesn't have very much in it.
What we want to do is add, you know, do kind of a an if that will
determine which kind, you know, which we're going to do here in terms
of header code vertex.
So, what I could do to is maybe when we do open, Jill create program,
maybe I have header code and I have
Fines or something like that, like this.
And so, what I can do is when we actually do that, opengl create
program,
That defines will go in here as well.
So everybody gets these like pound defines, that's another thing, in
addition to the header code that goes in there and that way, what we
can do is we can have like all of our code pretty much intact and then
we can have our defines and those would just be nothing.
But if the Shader has two SIM srgb then we can set the defines equal
to something else, right?
And so maybe we set the defines to stimulate srgb or something like
that or shaders him srgb right?
We can pound to find that to be one.
And that way all of our code in here is free to use a pound of find
for of that.
Shader CM srgb.
Does that make sense?
So we're basically just predicating are shaders based on whether or
not we got srgb support or not.
I don't know why I put a see in there.
There we go.
So now when I run this out in theory,
we should wait.
Who
what?
Okay, so I guess the version number has to be with the defines
apparently
And I guess I could use the same syntax error using before.
There we go.
All right, and so we can then slip our little pound finding there in
the rest of our code, can stay the way that it was, which is good.
So I think hopefully, that's good now.
And so now what we
Okay, that's pretty cool.
It's already doing that detection, I guess.
And turning off the frame buffer, right?
So that's pretty nice.
All right, so what we need to do now is actually sink think through
the way that we're doing our srgb and actually have something sensible
in here that will work.
As we go.
So, if we take a look at what's happening, we're gonna have to do a
couple different things.
But first of all, we know that when we do this test here, we're going
to come through and we're going to have a problem where we will either
enable or disable frame buffer srgb.
If we enable or disable framebuffer RGB with that mean, srgb is what
that means is that the final blit, where we take, and we go from the
multi sample, buffer down to the actual buffer, strips on the screen
that will be doing Sr.
That will
Be doing an srgb.
Version or not.
Right.
So
Just to make this a little bit clearer here.
so, we basically have
Texture.
Buffer.
And screen.
Right.
And so we have a couple different places.
So here is like, to srgb.
and this is a from,
Srgb.
This is a to srgb.
This is a from
So, every one of these arrows has an srgb conversion on both sides.
So the texture right is encoded in srgb.
If we have srgb support for our textures, then the srgb conversion
here can happen, right?
So we would not have to correct for that, but we would have to correct
for is this srgb?
Would not occur, right?
We would not be able to have srgb happen when it actually goes to,
right, to the freight to the backing texture buffer, right?
This is our multi sample buffer.
So one way we can fail is we can't do it here right.
Another way we can fail.
Similarly, is we are able to do it here and these two thankfully
happen symmetrically as far as I can tell, right?
So if this texture cannot be set to srgb format, then both of these
will fail.
And this is effectively not doing a two or a from
right.
Then this one could fail separately, right?
This is a separate type of failure and that's the failure when we're
going to go do the resolved, right?
So what I would say is we probably need all of these to be Atomic.
The reason we need them to be Atomic is because when we do the
resolved we don't have a Shader involved there right now we're not
loading anything into the graphics card and we shouldn't be expect to
be able to necessarily because it depends on the hardware that could
take their resolve and do something smart with it, right?
So what we pretty much have to do is say that there's two srgb flags,
there's basically texture read
and frame buffer, right?
Oops.
Okay.
So basically what we're looking at here is we need to support either
of these two things failing.
And when this one fails, what that means is something in these two
failed, right?
It could be either.
One of them is not supported, we don't care which one if it's not
supported then we have to simulate it in the back of the Shader right
here, right?
And so either we have to simulate it on one side or both sides or you
know, one side of the other or both, right?
So we're really going to end up with.
I think two different things, which is like
Sim texture load, srgb and shaders Sim.
Text right, srgb.
And so we assume that we'll have to do either of those two, right?
But that we don't know whether we'll have to do both or one or the
other
We know on this card will have to do it the right one, another cards
we might have to do both on some cards modern cars, presumably we'd
have to do neither right?
So what we want to do here is say okay we'll assume you have to do
both of them if the frame buffer supports RGB and and and right and we
have all these sorts of things then we're gonna try this stuff but
honestly this one is separate so really what we want to know.
Is a little bit different than that.
We want to say if the GLX texture.
Srgb is there.
Then we'll assume that the text load is false because if we know that
GLX texture srgb is there then that means we know will be able to turn
on our texture format.
Our texture format for reading textures will be correct right for and
and that means we will need a second one here, instead of just one
default internal texture.
Format, we need default, Sprite texture format and a default.
Frame buffer, texture format, great.
We need both of these.
So what we want to do here is say okay, our default Sprite texture
format is going to be set separately because we know that that's sort
of control differently.
And will again assume in both cases, that we will.
Fault.
Just right.
That we will set it to the correct value by trying to do some checks
here.
Okay, so we have a default Sprites texture format if you vote for a
vector format, this right texture format is just if we think we have
it we will we will use it.
And then we will not try to simulate the load.
On the other hand, if it looks like we might get the frame buffer will
test it and see and if we can, then we'll do default frame buffer
format and we'll set that.
Flag to let us know.
We don't have to do that.
Shaders Sim text, right?
Okay, so now we have to fix up the places that use that
in the code.
So here we are.
We're allocating texture.
This is going to be a default Sprite.
Everything's going to be defaults breaks at that one.
Place that allocates.
Yeah, this guy basically.
Go.
And so now we just have to in here actually handle these.
So what we need to do now is is have these sort of predicated, based
on what we found we may want to make it so that we can sort of create
this string.
Dynamically.
So what we might do is since we're in a place where we can concatenate
strings together, we could just make something that sort of prints
these out into each other.
Let's let's take a look at that here.
So here's our format string call.
I'm going to go ahead and use that to basically build a dynamic string
here.
So I'm just going to make this be some giant string that we can stick
stuff into that that may be excessive.
And so what I want to do here is just say like okay let's format a
string, let's pass it, this guy and then I'm just going to go ahead
and pass it.
Some strings here, right?
First of all,
I guess we have the version one.
And then and I guess I actually now I think about it that can just be
baked in there because we know that's always going to be there.
It's the other two that we're not sure if they're there.
So then we have one for our text reads.
There we go.
And we have another for our text rights.
That was what we called it, right.
Shooters Sim text read and write.
It's load.
All right, so now we've got one where we can actually build the
strings together.
So there's the two strings that might appear and then we'll pass.
Are.
So what I can do here is just say, alright if Shader semtex, right?
Srgb is true.
Then we'll add that string otherwise not same thing with text read,
So now depending on whether or not we want Shader semtex, right?
Or Center 7, text read, we'll put those defines in or not, right.
The other thing I guess I could do which maybe is a better way to do
it is just have this be maybe maybe just something which prints it out
every time but adds the right value to it.
So I could just do a % D there.
For example, maybe that's a clearer way.
Right?
So then I would just say, Okay, print out the shaders him text, right?
And the Shader semtex read.
Put those two out and, and just put a 0 or 1 there, depending on
which, which ones are on or off, right?
And so then we don't need any ifs at all.
We're just going to produce that string.
Concatenated then we've got the header code which we don't really have
to take advantage of yet vertex code and fragment code, right?
So now what we need to do is actually use these and what I can do is
In here.
I can I can do it if shaders semtex, right?
And a Shader semtex read.
Not to just correct these.
So basically, you can see what's going on here in the Shader, right?
I can, I'm basically adding two stages.
Here is the place where we sample the texture here, is the place where
the texture gets output, right?
And so, when we go to write this back to the frame buffer, or when we
go to read this texture in, in those two places, I could stimulate the
srgb, transform myself, right?
So what I need to do here is essentially effectively the same thing.
As we are doing in our software renderer, right?
It's the exact same thing.
So, if you take a look inside the code for handmade here already, and
we look at the render code.
You can see draw a rectangle quickly here.
Here's our code for this and let's see.
Here's our unpacked by linear, right?
Let's see.
So
Looks like this is the conversion here so you can see, let's see.
We should be doing in a course, is very always, very hard to read the
code.
When we've
Is it all out like this?
I was going to point out where this happens, but let's see.
So this right here.
this right here is actually doing so this is taking the
Red blue and it's actually lining those up.
You can see it masking out the various parts.
So this is actually separating out the parts of the texture and then
cured doing the bilinear blend.
Here's the bilinear blend of the texture.
So it looks like we don't really do this properly, the squaring of the
or maybe we did, and maybe we did it back a little bit further because
this is actually the destination now that I look at it.
So, this is loading, the destination and doing the squaring of the
destination.
But I don't see where we're squaring the source.
And it might just because we cleverly put in a way to do that in here.
I'm not sure.
Because I don't see it.
I don't see it obviously in here but maybe we just, I'm not looking.
I'm not looking in the right place.
But either, or this is the exact thing we're trying to simulate here
on the destination side, you can see it squaring the values on the
incoming and then on the way out again, we kind of have to do the the
reverse process and you can see right here that happen as well, right?
We've got the MMR squared PS.
So what we need to do is that same process, the are the G and the B
need.
To get flipped back up, basically.
so, when we go to right out,
Right?
And when we, when we read in, we have to do the text sample RGB, we
have to be able to do a square here.
So texts sample RGB has to equal basically times itself, right?
It just has to get squared and like I said, in shaders, unlike the
way, we wrote it in shaders, when you do a multiplication, it
defaults, if it's a vector to just doing component wise.
So it's the hadamard product.
Duct, which is what we would want to square, right?
Similarly, on the result we need to do, basically a square root.
I don't know if you can write this this way, but that's what we need
to do, right?
So I'm not sure.
Oops.
We'll have to check the Shader reference card to see whether that how
allowed that actually is.
In terms of, how do you do the square root part of things?
I know we had one up before.
Okay, so there's our square roots in the inverse square root.
I don't know whether square root is to perform is more performance.
Intensive.
That if inverse square root is an approximate square root, sometimes
that is the case.
So I don't know if we can tell it it, we may have to use inverse
square root and then invert it.
I'm not sure.
Hopefully, we don't have to.
So in theory that will just work and we'll be able to get that to just
do what it needs to do vertex.
Soak a fragment Shader undefeated in fire result.
That is not obviously what we want.
Sorry, result color.
And this is supposed to be
Sold color.
There we go.
Try that again.
So now we've sort of got a couple of different things happening here.
We'll talk about those.
Okay.
So now, I believe our colors for our Sprites should be more correct,
right?
And they do look more correct to me as well, right?
When I'm looking at them, that actually looks like the correct colors
to me, which is good.
So I think we now have everything working properly in on that path.
So when we and properly, I mean, for the case, where the shaders for
where multi sample doesn't support it and we have to
Simulate the srgb in the Shader right now.
We don't have another card here that does it properly, so we can't
test to see whether our path actually works, as part of our path is
supposed to turn this off when we get in the circumstance where the
card can do it.
So we really need to test it on another piece of Hardware eventually
which will try to do, but at least we have it working.
I think correctly on out in our particular case here now we do have
another problem.
However and that gets to the next set of things that I want to do.
And that is that the rest of the pipeline.
Line, however, doesn't go through this path, right?
The rest of our pipeline is still fixed function, and still doing
things.
Old way.
And so, for example, our cubes are still the wrong color because our
cubes are still specifying colors in srgb space, but that path is
unaware of the fact that the frame buffer does not support srgb
conversion, right?
So it's still using the wrong colors, which means our cubes are darker
than they should be.
Everything else is correct, but that is not so, okay.
So we're definitely getting closer though.
Like, you know, our little hero guy I think is now more of the correct
color that he's supposed to be.
Be, he looks right to me now.
Anyway, whereas before he definitely didn't and so I think we're in
better shape for that but we still have to deal with the fact that the
other code is you know the rectangle code in the cube code is still
kind of on the Antiquated path.
So that's I think where we need to sort of move towards.
We also have a few other items that we want to take a look at
eventually.
Which is based up.
Basically, we want to segregate our code out in terms of stuff that
has transparency in it you can see right now that for example our
shadows in like these cases which are doing Alpha.
Remember we no longer have really any Alpha per se.
We only have multi sample, which means that we end up in a
circumstance where our
Because we have the only eight steps of alpha due to the fact that
multi sample, we only have eight times multi sampling on.
You can see a lot of banding in anything that's transparent.
You can see it in the Fade Out of these guys.
You can see it in the shadows and so there's probably some things we
could do there.
That would increase our Fidelity by not always relying entirely on
Multi sample for Alpha and go and maybe
Doing something where we segregate, for example, our Sprites that have
translucency transparency, like, the Shadows do segregating them into
a separate buffer so that they can get rendered after the fact without
Z checking.
For example, would be one way that we can make that work.
So we may be able to do some things that will drastically improve the
quality of those sorts of drawing operations.
But we, you know, like I said, there's
There's costs associated with everything and so you'll have to see as
we sort of go through it.
What the trade-offs are.
But at least for things like Shadows which tend to occur in isolation
and which where mistakes are not as visible on them.
There's some pretty easy ways.
We can get free real Alpha in there and so we probably will want to
Okay, so that's it for the srgb part.
For now, like I said, we kind of need to play around that on a, some
better Hardware that can actually play around with this and see what's
going on.
So I think all this stuff should now be more.
I were correct and and something we can can use going forward.
What we need to do now is just take a look and see about modernizing
the rest of the part of the parts of the pipeline that we were sort of
leaving in the old school format.
I want to take a look at buying frame buffer here for a second, just
to see how that's working.
All right.
Okay so what we need to do now is basically just go through and start
to clean out the parts of this that are sort of working differently.
Now one of the things that you'll notice if you take a look at how
this this code is structured right now.
So you can see that we've got our render entry bitmap code here.
And you can see that basically what it's doing is it's kind of taking
these vertices and it's doing a very predictable, sort of out sort of
Blowing out, if you will, it's taking the vertices and it's doing a
specific sort of amplification of the information that's coming in
which are these like axes and stuff.
And then it's doing this sort of like creation of these with the Z
bias and whatever.
Right.
And then if you come down here, you can see the render entry Cube and
it does exactly the same stuff, right?
It's taking in some inputs and it's doing this amplification, right?
And then you get down here to render entry.
Rectangle.
And that's effectively the same thing to write.
It's calling the up in jail rectangle call but otherwise it's pretty
much doing exactly the same thing.
And so what I want to look at today is let's in preparation for sort
of cleaning all this out and making this more concise and
And useful.
Let's talk about maybe what?
If we were to just change the format that we submit these things in
and we just always submitted them as, you know, quads or something,
right?
Like, we always submitted them as or as triangles, you know what I'm
saying, something where we would just say, let's clean up.
Let's not have multiple different type things.
Come in in terms of drawing, let's just have everything just draw
textured triangle since that's what we know.
We end up doing it the low end, right?
And furthermore, since we know that we're actually always textured
quadrilaterals not textured triangles, maybe we can figure out a way
to make that work as well.
Right.
So let's try this, let's just try moving it that way.
And so, what I want to do here is I basically want to get rid of these
other paths, and I want to bake these paths into the render group side
of things.
That's on the app side and have the opengl output side.
All it deals with is just textured quads, that's it, right?
That's what I would like to do.
And so yeah, if we could go ahead and do that I think we might be in
some interesting shape here because then that sort of simplifies our
render a down quite a bit.
We can start to do some more useful stuff with it, okay?
So if I were to do that, let's go over here to render group.
and what I'm going to do is I'm going to maybe say let's say we had a
render group entry that was like render group entry type, you know,
textured,
So basically I'm going to introduce a new type here and I'm going to
use that type to sort of maybe slowly move everything over to that
type.
And then I'll just delete the rest of the types that aren't extremely
specific.
Like, for example, this one, we probably need to leave in there.
The Red Door Group entry type, render entry blend Target, right?
There's things that do like compositing operations like that.
And that would probably have to remain, you know?
Least, I would think so.
Okay, so you know, let's keep going with this.
So, if I have a render entry textured quads, what I want to do here is
say that I have such a thing as a textured quad, and this textured
quad is going to be sort of just a minimal information, you would need
to make that happen, right?
So the textured quad,
In this case is going to have maybe a textured vertex.
Concept.
And so what we would have here is I'm going to pack the color down.
So I would say at every vertex we would have a color value.
I'm also going to say that we probably I don't know if we need texture
coordinates or not because really they're just going to be zero to one
pretty much all the time.
So I don't know that those are super necessary.
Actually, they could just be inferred, would be my thought.
So it's a little bit hard to say, but for now, I guess we could say,
will pass down the texture.
Coordinates, just why not?
So it's also going to have texture coordinates.
So this will be like a UV coordinate, and then it's going to have a
position coordinate as well, right?
And if you look at the way these are structured, it's a little bit
unfortunate because we end up having with our textured vertex here.
We have four floats, right?
Which is 34 32-bit values.
So we have
Pack of four.
Then we have 2 plus a third.
That's the same space as a float.
So it's kind of like there's this one this is a little bit of an
alignment here.
It would be nice if we just had one more thing but we don't really
have one more thing for the vertex right now that may be okay because
again I think two graphics cards tend to be pretty good about being
able to deal with the unaligned packed, sort of formats of stuff.
So it's probably
Fine, but I'm just pointing out the fact that, you know, in, I'm
always like try to get things lined up into good chunks.
But yeah, neither here, nor there.
So, we're basically have four vertices for Quad, right?
And so four of these, at least, that's one thing we could say, will
come out nicely.
So in this case, where we've got seven of the, we've got, you know, 4
plus 2, plus 1.
So we've got seven of these guys, but we're going to do them four
times items up with 28.
It's not quite as bad.
I guess.
Maybe, maybe not.
But oh wait, no, that's actually good.
That's actually pretty good.
Because if, if the textured quad itself is that sighs I suppose we
could.
Well, yeah, I don't know.
I'm kind of babbling at this point.
Let's forget.
All that.
Alright, so here's the next part that we have to think about is for
every textured quad, we need to specify a bitmap, right?
So there's some bitmap that has to be specified of here and that
bitmap has to tell us effectively what texture went on this
quadrilateral, right?
That's what we need to know.
And so you know you can see that if we were doing this in software
that's a pretty reasonable format for it.
But as you know, vertices and textures are sort of handled completely
different differently unfortunately.
Jimmy on the graphics card, right?
So we do have this sort of nasty problem where vertices are things
that we want to submit to the graphics card, but textures are things
that we have to handle outside in our Loop.
Now, it's worth noting that this is only because graphic cards.
Haven't been completely modernized yet.
It's actually not true at a fundamental level.
So, for example, let's say you're on an Nvidia card, a modern, and
video card.
Right?
Well on a modern Nvidia card, it's actually the case that you can have
a texture pointer.
You can actually have that inside the Shader.
So you can actually have something where you've got, you know,
vertices and a texture pointer actually on the card and the card as
it's doing.
Rasterization can actually go look, use that texture pointer.
Seems that texture pointer for a primitive if it wants to write and
video cards are very general purpose at this point.
And they allow you access to a lot of those features which is pretty
awesome.
AMD, it's pretty much true as well.
Although the access to it varies more due to this driver things and
stuff like this.
But the real problem, the thing that pretty much always holds it back
is is not those two, it's the Intel.
Chips, the Intel chip, still have a lot of sort of antiquated Notions
about what is state that has 2 B managed on the outside and what the
state that has to get managed on the inside.
And so, you know, even though on a modern GPU, you could think of a
lot of things like the pointer to the texture.
As actually being something that's actually dynamic in the Shader that
is not true because of the limitations of some of the like on of the
integrated graphics.
Parts from Intel, make it such can't just do it that way.
But someday, you know, we will be out of that world.
I hope that that day just isn't today.
So what I would encourage us to look at here.
Anyway, is just the concept that?
Well, what we might want to do instead is say something like, you
know, bitmap array.
And vertex array.
Where we know that we would just be taking these vertices say four at
a time to create the quads, but our bitmap pointers would actually be,
you know, sort of stored in a separate referencing array.
And the reason that I say that it's just because, you know, as we move
forward with trying to make our Hardware path, may be a little bit
better.
You can imagine us wanting the vertices to be all in one.
Nice packed area that can just get sent to the graphics card as
opposed to, you know,
as opposed to having to segregate them first out of the bitmap array,
that's out of a packed array that has both bitmaps and vertices in.
It is all.
So I'm thinking that we probably want something more like this, so
rather than having individual of texture quads, which is the more
logical like way to think about it.
We may want to have them these two separate arrays.
So kind of like we do in simply land, where you have a structure of
arrays, rather than array of structures.
We're very much going that way.
I think with this, we will want to go that way where we can sort of
start.
Segregate stuff out things in bulk that can be handed to the graphics
card as a chunk.
Like in this case, where we have this vertex array, I think that's
more what we want to do, right?
Now, things get even more complicated than that.
Potentially because we may also in this case want to do,
Where we have that memory provided the or aligned, or specific to how
the graphics card is operating.
We may want that textured vertex, array, to be a chunk of memory.
That the graphics card gives us rather than a chunk of memory.
We hand to the graphics card, right?
And the reason for that is again, we kind of went over this a long
time ago and handmade hero but I'll just specify it again.
the reason for that is, if you think about how these things are
working on a PC, where the memory is disaggregated, so we have GPU
memory
And CPU memory.
Remember that these two things are not the same, they are in different
places on the motherboard, right?
And furthermore, the CPU also has cash, right?
Which is not the same.
So there's a memory hierarchy here.
And this is the slowest of them all from the CPUs perspective because
in between the two is the PCI bus and anything that we want to do, has
to go through the PCI bus.
Now, maybe on some super fancy.
Empty situation, it can go right from the cash to the PCI bus in other
situations that might have to write through the main memory to the PCI
bus who knows, right.
None of that is really important to us at this point.
It's just important to recognize the fact that there is a big old
special bus in between the CPU and the graphics card memory, no matter
what we do.
And so you have to account for this, right?
What that means is typically we may end because of the way that these
two
Are operating in parallel, right?
These are two different ships, operating, and completely different
clocks that completely different times.
What we often need to do is build up in CPU memory, a buffer of stuff.
And then later the GPU will kind of come across the PCI bus, get this
stuff and it will get transferred back, right.
So it will sort of fetch that memory over to itself, where it can
actually use it for drawing.
What that means is this may have to be placed in special memory.
Write a special region of CPU memory, and that region has to be a
region that set up to be mapped to the GPU, right?
The GPU depending on the architecture.
Cannot necessarily just grab any part of CPU memory.
It may have to grab a part that specifically set up for its transfer.
Why is this?
Well, you have to remember that virtual memory exists.
On the PC, right?
Everything that we do in our CPU on the PC at our level which is app
level.
It's above the
All right, everything that we do doesn't deal with actual physical
addresses.
The address is that we deal with our virtual addresses which are
translated by the CPUs virtual address table into actual physical
addresses of Hardware in the machine.
So, every time we give an address and say, hey here's a place in
memory, I want you to read or write from.
It's actually going through a translation table, to find out what the
actual address is of actual physical memory, that it can send out to
the memory bus to actually get that or hit the cash to get that out of
the cache.
If it's, if it's hot.
Not right.
So at some point right there is a physical address and that physical
address is what's actually used when you actually go out the bus to
memory to get it.
But in terms of what we're talking about inside the CPU at our app
level, all of the registers are actually containing virtual addresses.
Now, why this is important, and why bring it up now is because the GPU
when it fetches things across the PCI bus, it is not made aware of the
CPUs virtual address.
Table.
Why?
Because if it was, it would have to have this whole separate scheme of
syncing, all of the virtual address tables across to the GPU, right?
Which is a complete waste of time, most of the time because most of
the memory that the CPU is using in Virtual addressing isn't memory.
The GPU ever needs to access.
So you'd be spending a ton of time sinking virtual address tables
across to the GPU and you have to synchronize that access.
So you knew that no one was ever accessing the wrong thing because
someone didn't get an update or whatever, right?
Might it be this huge mess?
So what happens is the GPU needs to know physical addresses, usually
or at least not necessarily physical addresses, but at least like
consistent addresses, right?
When you give the GPU something to do that involves main memory, it
has to have a reliable way of accessing that memory and not having to
worry about the CPU changing what that memory means out from under it.
Or
Changing where that memory is located.
So, when we talk to the GPU, we can't just send down a virtual address
from our process space because we don't even know if that memory is
resident.
Write that for all we know that memory could have gotten swapped out
to disk or something, like the operation could do whatever it wants.
We have no idea.
So,
As a result in certain circumstances depending on the architecture
depending on the driver blah blah blah.
What we may want to do is use memory for reading our vertices that is
specifically set up to facilitate GPU transfers without a copy and
what that means is it would have to be put in memory that is locked.
It has to be put in memory, which is locked to a known physical
address and which the CPU and operating system will not move until the
GPU can use it, right?
And so, there's facilities for doing this.
And we'll take a look at those potentially later.
It's not always a good idea to do.
It depends on the circumstances like I said.
But in order to allow our renderer to take advantage of that in the
future, if it needs to, we may want to be aware of the fact that the
platform layer the operating system layer may be the thing that gives
us the memory specifically, for doing things that do GPU transfers,
this is less true for textures, and the reason that it's less true for
textures is because textures arse whistled.
So, depending on whether there's hardware stores along or not and all
these other things, whether or not you actually care about your
textures, being put into memory, that's locked, is a separate issue,
and it's less likely to be true.
It's sometimes true, it depends.
This is the nasty world of multi-gpu programming, but in terms of
vertices vertices are not swiveled.
When they go down the pipe, vertices go down just as they are.
And so it often times can be useful for you to put vertices into it.
For that is in a place where the graphics card can access it, and it
does not have to be first copied into a locked down, memory range
before that happens.
So, again a lot of, like, hand-waving there because we really just
don't know on the PC, usually, what have, what of a suite of things?
Might be happening under the hood, because it depends on the card,
depends on the driver, depends on a lot of things.
So we don't know.
But what we do know, is that it's possible and when something is
possible, and we know we might want to take advantage
Advantage of it.
That means that we need to architect our.
So the way that we have are things set up at the higher levels of the
code, in order to make sure we don't preclude the possibility that it
happens.
And so that's why I say this is a something we want to think about
saying, hey, the vertex array that we're dealing with here, we
probably want to have it.
So that that vertex array can be stored in GPU locked memory in.
Well, in CPU memory, that's been locked for GPU access in case that
It's out to be an important transfer criteria.
Will we be kidding?
The case where we actually care about this?
Probably not, but again, just trying to show some of the concerns here
that you might have.
We probably will not be pushing enough vertices for that to matter.
But, you know, if you were talking about a heavy vertex, throughput
situation,
It's something to be aware of.
All right, so when we do render entry texture crowds with quads, what
I'm thinking of here, it's like, okay, we've got a little bit map.
We've got a bit of a a we've got a textured vertex and that's going to
point to this vertex array.
Here we may want this to actually be more of an index.
So we may want this to be like vertex array offset.
And then that textured vertex array would be something that was more
like stored on the render group or in the render commands.
So like in the game render commands for
Apple.
Oh, they are.
So in the game Rider commands, when we've got the situation here and
we've got like the push buffer and that sort of stuff, you know, I'm
thinking of something more like this.
So we have a Vertex array here.
That's the, that's what we would be writing into and that vertex array
is filled with these textured vertices, right?
Like so.
And so I've got this textured vertex array, and I can write into it
and now it would be something that is provided to us from the system.
And we're just sort of writing into it.
And so then when we have something come down the pipe like this, where
we say, here's the textured quads that we're trying to write here is
the offset into that vertex array that I expect you to use to start
with.
Now we know we can just have one big bulk buffer of vertices and then
we're just sort of talking about
Hey, I need you to use these vertices out of that vertex array, right?
And again, that's just a step towards making things a little bit more
efficient than they, otherwise would be.
And so, you know,
So then I'll be really need here is up to to round it out would be how
many of them there are and so we just have like a ray of bitmaps
pointers which say which textures to use and then we've got how many
quads were going to draw and the offset into the global sort of.
It's not really Global but it's you know, it's Global to this render
pass array of vertices that we're just writing into with all of the
vertices that we ever need.
So then when we're done with a frame, we can just turn around and say,
hey,
Grab this card.
Take this whole vertex array, just the whole thing.
It's all in there, right?
And then, you know, we can piece it out and say, draw these with this
texture of these, with this texture of these, are this texture and so
on, right?
And that's really all we're talking about.
So that's that's sort of, I guess what I'm getting at for how we could
start to sort of transition these things over.
All right, so let's say we're on the opengl side.
How would we Implement something like this just as a first pass just
to get it working.
So let's say we're here, we see one of these textured quads doodads,
right?
Well we know how to draw one of these guys, right?
So it's going to start with that code.
And what I want to do here is just encourage you to kind of look at
how much work.
So this is to draw one Sprite and look at how much work is involved
here.
We're actually setting up like, what program to use.
We're setting up these matrices, right, we're setting up like all the
stuff that needs to happen here, right?
And a lot of this stuff is just busy work, it doesn't need to be done
every time certainly, we don't need to change the program every time
if we're using this program for all the quads, you know, that's
something we can do once and then every
Odd can can use that, you know, going forwards, right?
So we can set the program once and then we can, you know, for every
quad it's just sending down a new Quad but the same program so already
we can save that, right?
The same thing is true of our of our transfer Matrix here, right?
Probably we could just save this and the begin all of that stuff.
Doesn't have to happen.
/ /, trying to lie there, right?
So all that stuff comes out.
Let's go ahead and make our for Loop here for each triangle.
And so then inside our for I Loop, what we're doing really here is
saying, hey, we've got a quad index and we're going to go through our
quota quad count here.
This is, I gotta change the surrender.
Entry textured quads,
And off we go.
So let's take a look here.
We would just say the entry quad count.
Like so, and we now know we have basically a few pointers.
We've got our vertex pointer which will not s where we go here.
So we've got this vertex array inside our game commands,
And we know the offset of that because we know inside the entry, we
have the vertex array offset.
Where'd that guy go?
Right here.
Right?
So we know the vertex V offset there were talking about so we know
where we start in the vertex array, so this is our, our textured
Vertex.
So, that's the vertex we're looking at at the base.
We then have the count, which we know is how many of the quads were
going to do?
And we have a pointer to the bitmap that we can sort of advanced as
well.
So we can say like, here's our bitmap
And that's just going to be equal to this entries bitmap array as we
start with, right?
Like so, all right, so we know that.
That stuff right?
That's all pretty basic.
So now as we go here, what are we looking at?
Well,
Got a load of bitmap, I suppose.
I should probably do it this way, something like this before.
Every that and so I can say OK, the bitmap is the bitmap at this point
and will advance it one because we know for every quad redraw, we need
to load a new bitmap out and then the textured vertex, we know is the
vert at, right?
But we know that we're going to have four of these, right?
So we know that we're going to have like vert 01 route to invert 3.
EXO.
So we can just grab those out as well.
And now, we have everything we need to draw with.
All right.
So now we don't have any of this stuff anymore.
Right.
None of these things are going to be here.
We do have to bind our texture.
Obviously, I don't know that we need to bother with this.
If I don't think we do because our texture coordinates are packed in
there.
So we don't have to test this anymore.
And so we really just need to do the buying texture.
Now, I suppose this is a case where until we use something more
advanced than the fixed like pipeline, I'm not allowed to
To bind a texture inside of begin end.
So for now, I will have to turn that off and put it on the inside but
eventually, we will want that to be more efficient as well probably.
So I need to Again, by in the texture here, that we're that's coming
in from the bitmap.
So we'll do that with that.
And then I've got these are all for creating the UV coordinates, which
we're assuming we will do on the other side because they're already
into the packed into the vertex, right?
So what we need is
In terms of our values coming in, we do have a color and we need to
specify our color to opengl.
That color is a pact 32-bit value so we want to be able to specify
that color as a as like a GL color for you.
Be basically
And you can see here, the one that we actually want, which is whoops,
that's three.
Which is this one GL color for you.
Be now we have to unpack it.
So again, this is this is going to get more streamlined.
When we switch away from the fixed function pipeline because that
unpacking can happen automatically in the vertex Shader actually.
So, this is actually going to be
A lot less efficient right now than it will be when we're actually
reading them directly.
But, you know, I want to do it one step at a time, both for ease of
debugging and so that you can kind of see the steps as we go through
them.
All right, so what we want to do here is we want to do a GL and we
probably want to do this as a separate as as like a macro basically
which is like color you be macro or something like this where we can
just specify in here this color
And it will unpack it, right?
So what we want is something like this, where we specify, you know, a
color value,
And then that color valued translates into a Geo color for you be
where we're actually going to do.
This sort of thing.
So we're going to take that, you know, that packed about version and
this wants rgba.
So the r value in our case, as far as the packed colors are concerned,
we have to pick some kind of a format
So I'm just going to specify that this is rgba packed so it read a BGR
in a register, for example.
So that means that the bottom is the red one up is the green and then
we get to the blue and finally the alpha is packed at the top, right?
So that's what I want to specify their as my color.
So we're going to draw in specified.
That is color and so we know that we would specify a color per vertex.
Right.
We also specify UV and so we know how to specify that as well, which
is like this.
So rgl Tech Support to F can be a 2fv in this case because it's just
the vertex u v.
And then same with the vertex 4fv.
We know the position we actually have as well.
Right?
So we know that's what we're putting out.
Right.
So now we just need to do this in a way that's actually going to draw
it as two triangles.
Now, what would be nice is if we could just do GL quads, which
unfortunately,
I do I think in the fixed function pipeline we can probably still just
do eventually.
We'll have to do you like to see.
We'll do a little well to do a little trickery.
If we want to get the modern pipeline to do it because there's no such
thing as quads.
You have to kind of set up a try strip with the restart its kind of
But it's doable.
So, what I probably can do is just do it like this.
If this card allows me to specify quads, which I don't remember if it
does, or it doesn't.
So that's going to be anyone's guess really, whether that'll work.
It's a really good question.
Probably, I should try it first.
Somewhere else to see whether it works before we go diving in there.
So yeah, that's
That's something I'll go do right now.
So, these all have to specify the float part of them because it
doesn't understand how to take the structure and produce a float from
it.
There we go.
And so, that's path isn't getting called right now.
We're just calling this old path still.
So it's neither here nor there, but one thing at a time, so what I'll
do is I'll just test to see whether quads work or not.
I can go up here into where we were doing this before, and say, let's
if we change this to quads, does that work temporarily?
Because we're going to want to draw as quads later.
So we can specify less things to the graphics card.
So here's that lower triangle and then we just need the upper triangle
that
Max Max version is there.
So we need the min max version, which is where
Yeah.
Yeah, so that's fine.
So we can use quads for now and then we'll show how to kind of do
those.
Because eventually we're going to have to switch away from GL.
Begin an individual text Cord sending down to that sort of stuff.
When we get to that point, I'll explain kind of what I mean by quads,
not being supported anymore.
And you actually do something different, it's a little wonky.
But it's, it's basically, it went, from being something where you
specify, how Primitives are assembled in a way that makes it
reasonable to specify quads to have
Sort of more flexibility about how perimeters are assembled.
But as a result, you have to construct the ability to make quads
yourself, kind of, if that makes sense.
So, you'll see that eventually
Alright, so here is sort of a way of outputting these textured quads
and you can kind of see how this works, it's very straightforward, the
only kind of wonky part about it and the thing that's a little bit
problematic is just you can see that we sort of have this problem of
binding, the texture every quad, right?
This is actually one reason why depending on the hardware you're on
Why people like to use things like texture?
Atlas has for example or other things like that those are really just
work around.
Like there's no point to a texture Atlas right other than to work
around basic limitations one of which being if texture binding is
expensive so that you, you know, because you can't put it in line with
your other data.
Another reason, if graphics cards cannot efficiently, manage non power
of two textures.
There's a lot of reasons for it, but they're all just basic
workarounds right there.
Just workarounds from the concept that you can't deal properly with
having just in line with things a pointer to an arbitrary rectangle
that you're trying to blit, which is what you would have wanted for
drawing us, right?
So anyway, we've got this situation now where this should draw quads
Lee.
Of course we just now have to feed it, some actual quads that it can
draw.
And so what we'll do at first is we'll just start by setting up a
circumstance where we can feed our Sprites down as these quads and see
how that goes, right?
And that's what we'll try to do.
So we have two problems that we need to address.
One is the bitmap specification array and the other is the vertex,
specification, Ray the vertex specification array is the one that I
want to come from the platform side.
So,
When the game commands themselves, get allocated.
Render commands, here it is.
So when the render commands get specified here, you can see where the
push buffer gets put on here.
In addition to these and we do render command struct that render
commands truck.
Now needs to have some additional information with it.
So you can see here like the put buffer width height stuff going on
here and so then there's the push buffer and the push buffer base data
at sort of situation.
So,
What we want to do is also specify this vertex array.
so that when we have this render command struct, it needs to specify
that
So if we come back here to where the push buffer is created, you can
see that happening here.
You know for now what we can do is just specify the vertex array as
well.
Now what we might want to do is say Max vertex count just for our own
checking purposes.
There's no other real reason for it.
It's just for our checking to make sure we don't go over.
so I don't know what our Max vertex count is, let's say our Max vertex
count is going to be
64k of vertices, why not?
And so when we win three to allocate this memory, we will go ahead and
do Max.
Vertex, count times size of.
Textured vertex.
and then,
and that's it.
So now we have a Vertex array.
And we need to actually start using that vertex array and putting
stuff in it.
Obviously Max vertex count
and,
We need to actually write the vertices in there and we need to figure
out how we're going to write our loaded bitmap stuff out and I don't
really know.
At this point, you're completely honest with you.
I'm not sure how I want to do that.
I mean, I kind of feel like it probably should just be part of the
push buffer.
Maybe.
I mean, I think that's almost certainly the right way to do it.
So let's do it that way.
It's high allergy season here folks.
And I'm a naughty boy.
All right, so let's go ahead and take a look at how this will work
inside.
The render group, what we're going to want to do is have a way of just
kind of like aggregating these overtime.
So inside the render group probably what I would do is say all right,
we've got this render group here, the render group is going to have a
thing in it called texture Vertex or
to called render entry.
certain vertex, textured quads, that that guy
I'm a Savage in color to called car and quads, right?
And what this is going to do is current quads is going to have a
thing.
It's going to have some calls associated with it.
And so, what I'm going to have here is like begin quads.
And N quads.
And what this is essentially going to do is it's going to like push an
entry onto the render group that's for the quads.
As they're getting pushed on and what I'd like to do is I'd like to
kind of have that be part of the push.
The sort of the push entry structure if you will.
So when we do a push render element, I think I'd like that to kind of
be in line with it.
And so, what I want to have happen here is like when we push a render
element on, I would like to make that.
Well, I guess let me, let me not go too far with that yet, let me just
see because I kind of got to work with both of these at the same time
here, till we remove the other kind.
So what I
Do here is when we do a push bitmap instead of calling push render
element, but I really want to do is take all this code that I had here
and I want to just do what it was going to do inside the opengl code,
right?
So remember this is what it used to do.
Is this stuff?
Right.
So in here, what I'd like to do
Is something more like this.
Is this still happening?
That is very interesting.
Hold on a second.
So in this case, if the Sprite was flat, it doesn't.
Oh I see we use the camera.
Axes only.
If the Sprite is not flat at the Sprite is flat, then we just use the
regular axes.
All right, that's fine.
Anyway.
so, what I want to do here is, I want
Just do this, right in line, so rather than storing up the information
necessary to do this, I want to get rid of all this stuff, right?
But I want to actually sort of have this, do all the sort of out sort
of the blowing out of the data right in line.
Now at this point I assuming we have a bitmap we never call push
bitmap on something that doesn't have a dimension.
So I think that's probably fine.
Am I right about that?
Yeah, so the bitmap has to be filled in so we can actually do this.
One thing we can do is since this can't be drawn if these aren't both
here, I suppose I could just just make this whole thing predicated on
that actually, right?
And basically say all right, you know what, if the bitmap is invalid,
then we're just not even going to entertain that at all.
So when the bitmap comes in here and we do all this stuff for it,
instead of this pushing of the entry here, we're going to do something
slightly different.
But before we get to that, I'll also say that, you know like the
x-axis that sort of thing.
These are actually going to be
there's a bunch of noise outside that sounded like,
Dramatic.
And if you heard it.
There's like sirens and things.
I don't know what's going on.
We don't need another pointer for this.
All right, so if you take a look at what goes on here, we sort of have
a situation where we can collapse.
A lot of this work that we were doing here.
We can just call this mean p.
If we want to, we have the Z bias.
It's already there, right?
So we've got all this information that we can use and now we can
directly do the computations that we were deferring to later.
So we just directly do all of these.
Obviously we don't need any of this stuff.
And where's our Primo color?
There it is.
So now what we need to do is we just need to create the these
vertices.
We need to write those out as our verts rather than calling GL to
store them in some way, right?
So we fill compute all of this information and we need the color
value, but we need to be able to pack the color down here.
And so I believe we have a packing call.
Do we?
Somewhere.
I just don't know what we called it.
Yeah, there's a crazy stuff.
I want to know what's going on outside.
I'm gonna go.
Look, hold on one second.
Sorry to drop the Stream.
So I'm not sure what is going on outside but it's kind of nuts.
Like there's there's like a bunch of police outside and there's like
loud kind of explosion e noises but I don't and there's tons of people
like lined up on the streets.
I don't know exactly what it is.
It might be some it might be a protest or it might be a parade of some
kind.
I have no idea.
It's a very, I literally don't know what's going on.
This is the the hazard of being on stream.
Downtown in downtown Seattle.
I suppose.
Let me see if there's a explanation of what's going on here.
From somewhere.
News related.
Let's see.
I don't see anything.
I do not see anything.
So I guess it must not be anything, particularly weird, maybe it was
just something that was supposed to be happening.
I do not know.
Anybody know, anybody know, does anyone on the stream now?
That's quarter Tron.
Looks like you posted something from Komo News live police fire
scanner.
What is that?
Ah, that's pretty cool.
It does anyone know what it is?
I don't know.
Well, okay, it's rather disturbing.
I will say, it's doesn't make me.
Feel super comfortable sitting here streaming with this going on
outside, but I guess it's better than being outside.
If you see me duck down at some point during the stream.
Yeah, I may have to end it.
Prematurely what?
How about?
I don't know how long is Life In The Stream?
What time are we going till 1:00, 1:15?
I guess.
Is that right?
I don't remember what time I started 1130, I started at 1:15 right?
So yeah, I guess let's let's try to survive for 15 minutes more.
Yeah.
All right anyway, so moving on if I if I just want to write these out
to a Vertex dream, right?
Then I'm just assuming that I have here a pointer to somewhere in the
vertex buffer, which will worry about how to get the right one later.
But I know that I'm going to eventually have these textured vertices
and I have to write them out, right?
So at some point, I've got a textured vertex, star, vert here,
whatever that texture vertex, Tarver,
Is that is going to be where I'm writing and I'm going to like you
know, output 1 vertex, Advance it to the next one output 1 vertex
advance to the next one, right?
So what I need to do is just write to my vertex.
I need to write the P.
I need to write the UV and I need to write the color.
Like, so, now in this case, we need to pack our color down, like I
said, couldn't quite find that.
So we'll take a look at how to pack that down in a second.
We could just write it in here in line here, if we can't find the
existing one and then I need to sort of like keep these all the rest
of this stuff, exactly as it is, right.
So the position of the first
Vertex and you know, you've ease of the vertices.
These are actually going to be all exactly as they appear here, right?
So, I'm literally just streaming after this buffer.
Exactly the same stuff that I would have been streaming out to the
opengl.
Immediate mode.
Old-school fixed function pipeline.
I'm just putting these into memory.
So it there's really no I'm not doing anything differently in terms of
the computation or development of the values.
All I'm doing is I'm just writing to memory
Previously, we were handing to open gel by a series of fixed function
pipeline calls.
That's it, right?
So I'm literally just making a very simple mechanical change to what's
happening to the vertices and that's it.
Okay.
So this will write out effectively, the four vertices of the quad.
And like I said, what we want to do here is we want to write these out
sequentially.
So that we're writing to me,
So that we're writing 24, different vertices.
Oops.
That comprise the quad.
Or I should say that constitute the quad.
So there's our four vertices and then after we've written them, we
would want to advance the vertex pointer by that, you know, by for.
But again, we don't really know exactly how we're doing any of that
stuff yet.
So we need to sort of have a more coherent system for that in place
and we'll deal with that in a second, right?
First, we need to do is figure out a way to smack this value down,
right?
Because this is currently a veck for that's coming in, that's a
premultiplied veck for.
We need that premultiplied veck for to have some more, you know, be
compacted down, be a little more concise so we need some way to pack
those colors down and let's see.
Like I said, I don't know, I thought we had written one of those, an
RGB one of those.
In fact, I know that we have
I just don't know where it went.
We're at scampered off to.
So, okay, here we go.
So here's Pack 4 by 8 and what you can see here is this is packed 4 by
8 but it's in the old format, right?
And so we want in addition to pack board by 8 and unpack 4x8, I think.
We also want them to have both versions of these.
So what I probably want to do here is say, hey, let's go ahead and go
to the math Library.
Let's put these packing calls in there because they're pretty
generally.
Useful.
Right?
And then what I'd like to do is have both versions of them.
So I want unpack 4 by 8 and Pack 4 by 8 and I want RGB versus our GBA
version.
Is be gra, right?
So this would be the gra unpack be gri pack.
and then we want the
switch version as well, right?
So you want both of these.
So instead of, in this case, where we've got a RGB in descending
order, we want rgba and descending order there.
And the same thing is true here where we're going out to our g b.
A so it's just flipping those two around.
So this is going to be an rgba Pack 4 by 8.
Right.
That's going to pack it down and and that's yet all we really need out
of that.
So let's see here.
Wait a minute, what is XX?
0 x axis and y axis are in here.
So we're going to call this x axis to.
This is the two dimensional sort of.
Version of that.
And we can make this code, much more efficient as well.
And we got to change These Guys, these are be Gra.
Unpacks.
Okay.
All right.
So I think we're good now.
All we need is a way of actually streaming out the, the bitmap and
texture vertex data, which we don't have.
So now we've got the code ready to do all the rights.
We just don't have the actual right themselves.
A, similarly, you know, we need Somehow Here, we need to do like start
bitmap out equals bitmap, right?
I mean, we need something like that and we don't have that either.
So in both cases, we need that.
And we also need some way of advancing the those four words and that
kind of stuff.
So what I want to do here in the render group is I when we open the
render group, I need some way of specifying where those pointers are
basically.
And when we do the begin and the end stuff, we need some way of
saying, here's where, you know, in the buffer hasn't been taken yet.
So I think
Probably since the render commands actually care about that a little
more specifically.
I think that has to be in here, right?
Because if multiple people open a street open a render group at
different times of the pipeline, they need to be able to know where
they're writing into the sort of that that vertex array memory.
And so on.
So we need probably a Max or discount and
And a Vertex count, right?
And so we need that to be
Satisfied like this so that it can sort of output as it goes, right.
Okay, so when we're running to the vertices, that one is probably as
simple as actually using the render commands themselves.
So, that's actually kind of pretty straightforward.
I think, what we can do there is just say, alright, we know we've got
our render commands, the render commands have the vertex array in
them, and we know we're going to write into the vertex array at the
location that is currently indicated by its vertex count.
And then we need to increment the vertex count by 4 because
Going to use four vertices, right?
But I think that's all we really have to do.
Similarly, when we do that, we should make sure that the amount that
we've used is reasonable and has not exceeded the maximum, right?
I think that's mostly what we need to do there to make that work.
Now, here in the binary, operator equals situation here, you can see
that I've accidentally kept the part that opengl needs, which we don't
actually need to get rid of that.
And so that leaves us with only one thing which is the bitmap out
part.
Right?
Okay.
So now we're definitely getting much closer.
And we have not we have thankfully avoided getting shelled by whatever
bombardments were happening outside the window, which is also helpful
I suppose.
So, what we need to do now is figure out how we're going to actually
take the render entry for the quads and output it.
Now, what we can do just at first is a pretty, as a pretty basic way
of getting this working is to do the, the absolutely dumbest thing
which is to push one render entry, textured quad for, every time we do
this, which is exactly the opposite of what we want to accomplish
because the whole point
Into this is to do multiple that once but we can start by pushing one
each time.
Right?
And if we do that, then we should be able to get it working and then
add a thing to the render Group, which Aggregates them.
So then whenever you call push bitmap, it just sticks it onto an
existing one that's in there and so that's where I'm trying to get
with this, right?
But if we just do it one at a time, now then it's pretty
straightforward.
What we need to do is just have some place to put the bitmap out stuff
that we're talking about here.
When this entry comes back we know what the entry has to have in it,
right?
The entry is actually
I'm very, very straightforward.
It's just these three things, right?
So the entry
Bitmap array, we need that to exist, somewhere.
We have the quad.
Count the quad count.
We know is one in this case, because we're not aggregating yet the
vertex,
Offset.
We know what that is.
It's the commands vertex count.
And so, all we really need to do here is have that bitmap array, be
something we can use.
Now, when we call Push render element, I believe there's the size
here, right?
And so, what I want to do is, I want to use in this push render
element.
I want to actually use something a little bit Squinkie here to use the
technical term where instead of pushing render elk calling push render
elements.
I meant through the macro, which does the cast for us?
I'm going to do something a little bit swankier, and I'm going to say,
hey, let's call the the actual function itself.
Let's go ahead and put into the
What is this called?
Render group entry type.
We go.
I'm going to go in ahead and actually call the function directly so
that I can say, give me the size of one of these things, plus the
size.
Of a bitmap pointer.
So now I know I've got some extra size at the end of this thing and so
when I am done getting that back, I know if I want to I can tell it
that the loaded bitmap
Array in question is actually just going to be right after the entry.
So I'm pushing the entry memory and I'm just assuming some extra space
at the end of it for that loaded bitmap, right?
And so what I'll do here is say, okay, the entry bitmap
Array is going to be equal to the bitmap that comes in and I only have
to push one of them, right?
This needs to get specified.
There we go.
And so now, I think I'm actually pushing those on, right?
I believe anyway, so hopefully that's good.
Of course, I appear to have done something incorrectly.
Ah, yes.
and in here,
Because I'm including that when we encounter one of these ones, in
addition to advancing the size of this, we also must advance.
An additional size which is however, much after we've gone past the
render entry textured quads.
We also have to go however many loaded bitmaps there were in our
bitmap array.
So the quad count times, the size of a loaded bitmap pointer
Right, as we advance forward.
Okay.
So as you can see, not exactly a stunning success because we are not
seeing our Sprites, but that is the idea and
Now, we just have to debug that and I wanted to do it this way like I
said before, because I want to do it one step at a time.
So now I want to just be able to bug one thing at a time, not half the
debug, both the aggregation part and the bundled part here.
So you can see that this is calling the same path for all intents and
purposes.
So I just have to go to bug now and see why.
I'm getting a difference between the two of them as we go.
Now I'm not crashing.
So that
Just that the texture loading is at least loading out of a reasonable
place.
But, yeah, we have to take a look and see whether these vertices are
coming through in a reasonable fashion and everything else.
And so, yeah, we'll take a look.
We will take a look at that.
Just doing a quick scan here to make sure I didn't do anything
obviously wrong that jumps out at me.
So anyway, the a re at the entry plus 1, that is logical quad cab
being one is logical.
We are opening our quads.
We get four vertices out of it, and we are specifying the color, you
be srgb.
And a there which is exactly what I would expect it to look like.
That all looks pretty reasonable to me.
And these are set up with the same values that I was having before.
Again, looks pretty reasonable.
So I'm going to go ahead and here and I want to just take a quick
look.
I'm going to set a breakpoint inside the renderer to just see what
what those values are coming through.
As again, as just a sort of sniff test to make sure that when I see a
quad, it seems like a, you know,
Sensible quad and there isn't.
It isn't all messed up.
So here's a bitmap, it's a pretty reasonable looking bitmap so that's,
you know, I could easily see that being something reasonable in here.
We've got our vertices.
Let's take a look at the hexadecimal.
Kind of not particularly.
Okay, this color is the super wrong.
Ah,
Yeah.
Okay.
I'm I'm I'm not quite right here.
The RGB pack 4x8 call.
I just realized I was a little overzealous.
There wasn't I?
So these
Don't x 255.
Right.
They just
unpack.
Directly, right.
So, that's not particularly useful.
You have to multiply by 255 first, right?
You need you basically need to do that before you could actually use
them.
Oh my God.
okay, that's
That is.
That's pretty good.
I was not expecting that.
I just realized that we didn't properly use.
The the we didn't.
That was, that was pretty good.
Yeah.
We did not use the the proper value there.
That was all right.
That was funny.
So.
Okay good.
Just in time for the Q&A.
We finish what I wanted to finish, which is getting that set up and
ready for us to move away from the fixed function pipeline.
We've got some more work to do, we'll do that tomorrow, but I think
that's a good place as any to stop.
I'll go ahead and go to the Q&A here.
This used right?
Simulating srgb, texture loads and extra fragment rates is not enough
srgb.
Also affects blending, which you can't emulate.
Yes, that's true.
In fact, emulation of srgb.
I also want to be clear.
It's totally stop.
It's just a stopgap thing to do so that your game runs at all in a
reasonable way, but it's not even correct.
Because again srgb, especially if you're using actual srgb, is not a
square.
Square root either.
So even even just if you take blending out and you take by linear out,
right?
Because remember our bilinear will be wrong as well because the
bilinear happens before the squaring.
So this is just a you know, kind of a patch that's like okay if your
graphics card for some reason can't do this.
Then you can run through this pipe and will at least not look,
obviously completely wrong, but it's not at all.
The correct procedure and I think you can even probably see.
I mean I know I could be making this up but I suspect that there's a
dark Fringe here.
That's darker than it should be as well on the Sprites for example,
and like, just in general, you will have incorrect results if you are
expecting to have RS,
CB and your game is set up for it and you don't get it then you have a
problem, right?
It's like there's no way to really fix it entirely that I know of
anyway.
So the risk.
Oh, do you have a license for all those cubes?
What do you mean?
What do you mean a license?
Brooke tag, what texture will you use for Rex and cubes?
So four rectangles and cubes, those will all have textures.
Eventually we could use a zero texture if we want to talk about solid
color but the cubes actually are supposed to be textured.
They're just not textured right now because we haven't updated to a
new art pack, but the cubes will have textures on them, like grass and
stuff.
MTS marks is it worth testing srgb and msaa in the non opengl
compatibility mode.
I'm sorry, I'm not sure what you mean.
What do you mean by in the non opengl compatibility mode?
Do you mean not setting the compatibility bit?
If, if you mean, not setting the compatibility, but I'll just answer
that before you actually have a chance to respond, but if you mean by
not saying the compatibility bit, yes, it is.
Absolutely worth, testing it, but we can't test it yet because we
haven't gotten rid of all the fixed function pipeline stuff.
Once we're, once we've removed all the fixed function pipeline stuff,
which is what I will be.
You know what, I'm working on getting us towards, then we can turn off
compatibility mode, but at the moment, we can't because I'm pretty
sure that opens you
Alcor profile, three removes immediate mode.
I could be wrong about that.
Jim says will you be using more than one Shader program?
If so how do you minimize switching between programs when rendering?
So at this point if we I don't know that we will have very many Shader
programs we probably won't but it really depends on the circumstance.
One of the things that's true about rendering with Z buffer, like we
are now is that we don't we're not super dependent.
The order of rendering.
So if we want to, we can have some buckets.
And when things come in, whichever Shader they need, they just go into
that bucket and then we render each bucket with, you know, set the
Shader and render everything in the bucket.
So we can certainly do something like that if we care.
I again, I don't know how many shares were have.
The other thing you can do is actually have branching in the Shader,
sometimes at the branches are cheap enough and since everything's
always going through the same Branch, you can actually just use Shader
branching.
if you have, if you have more fine-grained switching than that,
MTS, mock said, you could unset it and just see if the assert will
fail.
Yeah, we can if you want to just see if it can get there.
We can certainly try it.
Yes, so I think you have to specify core.
Here.
Is the thing.
Let me look up this.
That's the one we want.
So we already have it, so I believe you would just specify that.
And I guess if I was cool, I would probably do this.
So now in theory a nothing will work, okay, wasn't expecting that.
Well, so yeah, I'm not sure why that allowed us to work at all, but I
guess it did.
So that's interesting.
Because I would have expected the fixed function stuff not to work.
Maybe they didn't remove it till 4:00, I don't know.
I thought they were moved in three so I thought that would have aired.
It might be that this driver just doesn't do the error checking
properly that's also possible.
I have no idea.
But that worked apparently.
So alright.
Alright so now in theory we're passing core profile bit so that's good
and if we pass core profile bit, now we can just see over inside
opengl.
Let's see here.
So it's still errors out, even in court profile mode.
So, I'm pretty sure this car just doesn't do it or the driver doesn't
know how to enable it or something.
Insofar as says are you passing a major minor version to?
I think the bit might be enabled sub 3.2?
Well, we are.
I mean there's a minor version here.
I can certainly pass 3.2 and see if that does anything.
Right.
Where is?
So, we did get, we did get the context.
But still no dice.
Yep.
Looks like looks like weird pretty much good to go.
Now, in terms of end of questions, so I'm going to head and wrap it
up.
Insofar, as I saw insofar as join the chat, I will just end the
stream.
I wanted to ask you a question, so I'll be right back over to the
chatting in a minute here.
But let's go ahead and wind this down.
Okay.
Thank you everybody for joining me for another episode of handmade
here.
It's been a pleasure coding with you.
As always, if you would like to follow along with hers at home, you
can always pre-order the game on handmade here a.org.
It comes with a source code so that you can play around with it.
We also have the Forum site, you can go to ask questions a patreon
page.
You go to.
If you want Sports video series, a schedule bot, which lets you know
what the schedule is going to be for the weekend and an episode guide,
that lets you catch up on old episodes.
Now we also
We'll be back here tomorrow.
And as the schedule bot says, you can see here this weekend schedule
is 11 today, 10 a.m.
tomorrow.
But you'll notice here in the US in the Pacific time zone we have
daylight savings time.
It happens tomorrow.
So actually I believe that this will be at the same time tomorrow.
Because basically what I did is I set them at the same time for the
weekend but the time zone changes over.
So tomorrow it will actually be at the same time but it it's actually
an hour earlier because of the fact that the clock go back.
I think I did that, right?
I could be wrong.
In the clocks, go, the other direction.
I have no idea but either way, we'll be here at 10 a.m.
Pacific Daylight time tomorrow.
So just be aware that the clocks do change for trying to make that
broadcast.
That's and I don't know.
Your time zone may not even have daylight savings time.
In which case, you'll be even more confused than I am, but there you
go.
So that's about it.
I hope to see everyone back here tomorrow.
Assuming that the time, change doesn't miss, everybody up until then
have fun programming it and I'll see y'all on the internet.
Take it easy, everybody.