Okay.
Hello everyone, and welcome to handmade hero.
The show where we code a complete game live on Twitch from scratch.
Using no libraries, no engines, no artificial colors or preservatives
none of that stuff in here.
This is 100% organic Computing at its finest.
It commands a premium price at your local, organic market place where
there is a premium price on everything.
And the grocery bill is very expensive.
You know, the places I'm talking about and those are the kinds of
places you can find, fine, handmade hero code products.
And speaking of which, if you are one of the people who have
pre-ordered the game on him, a hero to org, please remember that.
You can follow along, exactly, with the code from today.
It's day 49.
So, if you would like to grab that zip file, you can download all the
source code in it, find a 48 zip and unzip that you will be exactly
where I am right now.
And where am I right now?
It's
Very good question that you have posed to me.
Obviously, you know, sort of telepathically because obviously I can't
hear you right now.
But, but in my mind, right?
I'm receiving.
That question from you, loud and clear.
And basically, if you remember, we were at the point where we were
saying we have to, you know, I showed a very, very basic form of line
intersection to sort of get intersections.
Working in the game.
And then I said, we need to move up to the next level of complexity.
Now in order to get better Collision detection.
And so we were at the point where we did Implement some Collision
detection for him, but it was not particularly good.
And and so we need to start thinking about how to make it better.
And one way that we need to make it better is we need to start
handling things more robustly.
Instead of making them infinitely.
Thin I talked about this a little bit yesterday.
I'm trying to show a bug here that we should have.
I thought
Demoed it pretty.
Well, there it is.
Where you can kind of sneak through thin situations.
I'm also wondering what happens when it gets down there.
We get this weird situation where we, where we kind of where we get in
some kind of a weird hang situation.
I don't know what's going on here and I want to check it out to see
what the problem is.
So
ha ha ha.
All right.
Why?
Why have we never seen this before?
That's very, that's very bizarre.
Wait, how is that even happening?
You see what's going on here.
We've got a mint.
Ilex of one am in tile.
Why of 31 past Mac style X of nine?
Which is fine and then one path Max Max tile y of 0.
What's going on there?
What, what is going on there?
How did the
Of two values, equal equal 3, and the maximum of two values.
Equal 0, methinks me thinks that we have a bug here, people because
that should not be the kit.
But how is that possible?
Right?
So someone's got a typo unfortunate that someone's me?
Because no one else even has the ability to edit code on this machine.
So, honestly, it's really hard for me to sit around and pretend that
someone else is at fault because pretty much it's always going to be
me.
So, let's see what?
The values are that we are putting in there before I continue talking
on the stream.
All right.
So, let's see what we've got.
Here are AB style lie.
Oh snap.
Yeah, well, I'm glad that we happen to be testing right at the
wraparound point.
Do you see what happened there?
This is kind of interesting.
Just goes to show you wrap around is hard.
Sometimes wraparound is hard.
So.
What happened?
There is actually pretty interesting.
So.
We've got our ab style-wise and the player has just moved off the
bottom of the screen, which causes his y.
Coordinate to rap, to the top tile, right?
He's going on to the the top of the screen right at the very top of
the map.
So basically, he underflow 0 and goes to, you know, four billion,
which is exactly what we expect to happen.
And that's fine.
But when we do maximum of these two, right, it obviously picks this
one as the higher value, right?
And that's exactly what it should do because it is the higher value.
But then
Me add one.
It actually becomes a lower value than this in the sense.
And the reason for that is actually because the mint ilex and mint.
I'll why that we were at that we were using right?
What we wanted to know was not actually what the maximum value was
between the things that we were going to.
We actually wanted to know is just how far those whichever one was the
furthest from the mint ilex.
Mmm-hmm.
So I wonder what is the more stable way to do this computation such
that we do not have that wraparound problem.
That is very intriguing.
Right?
And I feel like probably what we would want to do is something like
say.
All right, let's actually test the thing that we want to test which is
which one is the farthest from meant ilex, right?
So we would find out here essentially, you know, which whichever one
is the farthest from it and the subtraction
Do the right thing with regards to rapping.
I would think right?
Because we know that these two are relatively close to each other.
And so in theory, it's the subtraction would always work.
I don't know if that's actually track to think about that left to test
that out.
Right?
Because let's say that this guy was, you know, some kind of was like
four billion or something and then mint ilex.
Was was going to be now that wouldn't work either because that would
still produce that would still produce that 4 billion value, and then
that would be totally wrong as well.
Mmm-hmm.
How am I going to do that?
Stably?
Hmm.
That's a very good question.
So really the problem too, is we don't even know which one should be
the minimum either because we don't really know which one is
technically, we just need know that we need to visit all of the tiles,
but we don't actually know what order to do the men.
That's tricky.
That is a tricky problem.
And one of the kind that I'm not particularly good at.
This is one of those like this is one of those bit fiddly sorts of
problems.
Mmm-hmm.
What do I want to do here?
It's kind of interesting.
Oh, no.
Where is the Whiteboard?
What have happened?
I must have closed it when we were doing all of our color fussing.
So here it is.
Let's go ahead and open that up.
Hello, krita.
There we go.
Oops, there we go.
Okay, we're good.
Of course.
I still need to pick up the background color.
There we go.
Okay.
So this is a very interesting problem that we have here and I'm not
it's entirely certain how to solve it.
It's very, very, very interesting.
I think what we have to do is sort of rebase our variables temporarily
to sort of, think about it in a different space.
So here we are at 0 0, right?
And the player has moved off the bottom here, so
Looking at a situation where the players starting position, was
something very low like zero or one, you know, something like that and
he moved to a position that's like four billion, right?
So what we want to do here is we want to start at the 4 billion and we
want to add to get to the 0, right?
And I guess we could say that.
What we want to do is always pick whatever the direction is, that
would be
The shortest to go, right?
Because we know that these are supposed to be close together.
And so we always want to do the subtraction that would yield the lower
of the two distances, right?
So yeah, that's one way to think of it.
Right?
So basically if I had, if I'm going for a billion to 0 or if I'm going
0 to 4 billion.
I know that going from 0 to 4 billion, will actually be relatively
short if I go in the negative direction, or if I go from, for if I'm
going in the Pub's Direction, going from 4 billion to 0 will be like
to be short because I just add one and I'll get there, right?
Or if I was going to one, I dad, you know, to and I'd get there.
So I need some.
A convenient way of producing that.
That iteration type right?
So I need some way of saying, what is the thing to start at?
Right?
And what is the thing to finish at?
And it needs to work on both boundaries.
So it needs to also work when I'm at for a billion and I move to 0,
right?
So I would suspect, let's think about this.
So I would suspect that if I just took
Mmm, if I was to look at these and go, okay, if the difference between
like one way I could do it and this is I may be a little bit cheesy.
If the difference between the two values is greater than, you know,
that sort of halfway marker.
So basically in t32 Max over to, right?
If it's if that distance between them is greater than that, then I
know that I've wrapped around.
So I could detect the case in which that occurs.
I don't know if that's the best way to do it because I'm trying to
think if there's some way to just do it with operations, that will
directly yield the correct thing because a lot of times with unsigned
into, if you think about it, you know, long enough you come up with a
clever thing.
We're just like, oh, okay.
This always works correctly, no matter which way I do it, right?
So one way, let's see.
So so let's say, let's see what the cases are here.
So let's say that I've got, I've got something like
Row 2 1, right, I've got something like 120.
I've got something like 0 to 4 billion, right?
And then I've got something like 4 billion 20, in terms of like
interesting cases.
So these are the normal cases, right?
And that's where the min max works just fine because it just picks,
whichever is the lower and whatever is the higher and goes between
them by adding one.
And then these are the are the are the ones that don't that wouldn't
work right now.
So, one thing that I
I'd do is say well.
Alright, what if I just always start at the location, the player was
so, I always start like 0, or 1 or 0, or 4 billion, or whatever.
And then, I just think of it as a problem of, I just need to know
which whether to add one or subtract one on each iteration of the
loop, right?
I just need to know which one of those to do and obviously, right in
this case.
I would want to add one.
In this case.
I'd want to subtract 1.
I want to subtract one.
In this case.
I want to add one, right?
So these would be ad case.
Aces.
These would be subtraction cases, right?
So the question is given these examples.
What is the thing I could do?
That?
Would produce that value.
Right?
Like what would actually produce this particular thing?
So like these guys are examples of if I do the subtraction, right?
If I
If I did the new - the old right then I would get exactly the sign of
that result would give me which one I wanted to do certainly in these
cases, right?
Because if I did 1 minus 0, that equals 1, right?
And the sign of that is the direction I want to go.
If I did zero minus one which is, which is this case, I would get the,
I would get the negative one in signed, which is also the reaction
that I want to go.
However, in this case, if I were to do
20 minus 4 billion.
I'm sorry, 4 billion, minus 0 I would get a plus 1, right?
And this case, if I did four billion, so it gets the opposite of the
sign there.
And so that doesn't really help me still determine what the sign is of
the values with that.
I'm going to same thing with like greater than or less than right.
Like I can't really use that which is sort of just the same as a
subtraction, right?
I can't ask whether the thing I'm going to is greater than the thing
that I was coming from because in this case, that would be a problem.
So what I can do again as I can I mean, this is the thing I keep
coming back to this is definitely the easiest is like just check to
see whether the distance between the two things is that and then flip
the iteration order.
But mmm-hmm.
Is there anything else I could do?
Well, wait a minute.
Is that actually the case?
Well, no, I think is it?
Because if I did the arithmetic, if I treated this?
Well, no.
No, that doesn't really help.
Mmm-hmm.
I don't know.
So I guess I'll just treat it.
I guess I'll just do the simpler case the simpler way to do it for
now, but this is something this bears.
Some thought.
Because I feel like if we spent some time on this, this would actually
come out to be something relatively clean.
That would not involve a bunch of checking about the rap point, right?
I feel like we should be able to do this.
Oh, wait a minute.
Haha.
Oh, wait a second, though.
You know what, this might work because 4 billion - 0 in signed would
actually come out to be negative 1.
Right, and 4 billion - I'm sorry 0 - 4 billion in signed.
Okay.
All right.
So we got to check this out.
Let's actually let's, let's, let's look at this.
I'm sorry.
I know this is probably not the kind of thing that interests.
People on the stream, but you know what?
Sometimes I'm here every night.
Sometimes you just gotta go with.
You.
Just gotta he's got a bear with me.
So here's what we were doing.
Right.
And that's not that's not really any good.
So I'm just going to go ahead and say let's let's nuke that for the
moment.
And so we're going to say, all right, we've got a mint.
Ilex and the mint.
Ilex is just or sorry.
I should say.
Well, we're going to still call it mint.
I like Steven.
That's not what's called, because we'll leave the loop the same but
then we'll change it after assuming this actually works.
At all, which I don't know if it will.
So what I want to do here is say okay, right.
I'm going to start wherever the player was and I'm going to go to
wherever the player is going.
So actually, you know, I guess I will change the loop because I got to
change it anyway for those things.
So we'll say start tile X and then we'll say one past and tile X and
that's going to be whatever the new player position is like.
So there we go.
There we go.
And then we just need, we need a Delta X and a Delta y, right?
And the Delta X and the Delta y are basically going to be the sign of
these values, right?
So what we need to do is say whatever the sign of if I was going from
the start tile X, you know, to the to the end tile X or vice versa
here like so.
Start tile.
Why like that?
And so, then the only kind of iffy thing about it is just if they are
both the same, right?
That's the only thing that's kind of annoying because I can't actually
it wouldn't actually get anywhere when I do the ad I suppose.
That's now that's that, that wouldn't actually quite work.
So, you know, what would be a little bit?
Better is if we did this Loop a little differently to.
So if I could just say
If I could just do it like this and say, okay, what we're going to do
is say we've got the this and then we're going to do this Loop and
this is going to be a while, right?
So, okay.
There we go.
While
Not equal to the last one, right?
So yeah, we'll do it like that and and we'll increment it there as
well.
Well, I guess that's actually got to be a plus equal since we're doing
a Delta Direction thing.
So that doesn't really give me a place to put it.
So I guess this is just going to actually be this.
There we go, and we'll have to check it manually.
So if AB style y equals,
Mac style.
Why?
Or should say and tile why, then break else increment.
There we go.
Okay, that's what I actually need to do there.
This is what we do is we just say, alright, we're going to start here
and then we're going to go until we hit that end Thailand.
We wanted to make sure that we actually process the end tile and if we
don't, we will go ahead and break out of it.
Right?
But this is going to have to be Delta Y and this is why they yeah,
what did I get?
Okay, so then I can do the other one exactly the same way.
So I'll do that.
I'll do this way.
And I'll do the exact same thing in here for this Loop.
So we'll just keep going till we hit that that end like so.
All right.
So now we've got it.
So we'll just do, okay.
We'll go through all of them and we'll stop when we hit the end
tilak's.
I like that's a little nicer regardless because then it's not, we
don't do one pass canned just to make it.
So, if it's a nice for a loop, so there we go.
And now I need to actually compute these things obviously.
So in order to compute them, I'm doing some traction here of anti Lex.
Yeah.
- start to like so and so I want to see what the subtraction actually
does for me.
So, let's take a look.
Mmm mint.
I'll Y is actually supposed to be start tile.
Why start tilak's?
There we go.
Okay.
So let's set a breakpoint here so I can take a look at what's going on
here.
So when our dude comes in, we've got an old player, piano a new player
P.
And let's see what those actually are.
I don't wait, but the dude isn't moving.
Why are we getting this kind of craziness?
That's a bit odd, but you say,
oh, because it's the first time it's been re canonicalized.
That's a bit odd.
Don't you think?
You see what I'm seeing?
Why is it?
Why is the X and Y value, 5 and 5.
Like, how did that even ever get set to 5 in 5?
This is interesting.
Today is becoming a bit of a clean up day.
What is that?
That's a break point.
Is that what that is there?
And even know that it showed me those there.
I guess it's because this is 2013.
I don't have 2013, I have 2012 at at work.
All right, so I want to see what's going on there when we initialize
that player.
So,
Why is he coming in with such a because he's been set to that.
Why is he set to 5 and 5 as his offset?
That's not a court canonical.
Coordinate at all.
That's just bizarre.
All right, so get rid of that.
I must be some hold over from something old.
So let's try that again.
Now.
We're at least in a much better position here.
Alright, so we have the start tile X and that's this is what I
expected to see.
Now.
We have the start Telex and the entitle, x x and tile, why?
And those are what we would expect.
So now we would expect compute.
No Delta's in this case, which is the case that I was prepared for in
why I wanted.
The breaks that breakouts this way.
So basically what happens is we immediately break on both of them and
we're done.
So we only do that one test, which is what we wanted.
So now if I do something a little bit more, like a little little more
relevant, so let's say I'm going down here and I do that.
Now I can set a breakpoint.
Well, he's actually moving and take a look at what he actually does.
Okay.
So we go start Telex and start tile, Y, and N Telex.
X and tile.
Why?
And now we should get.
Oh, you know what though?
I did forget to do.
I've got to just take the sign which is all I actually want to hear.
All right, so let's try that again.
Where are we?
Where was that?
Okay.
So, what I want to do here is just do sign, which I never remember.
I almost never call that on integers.
This is a, this is not a normal thing.
How do, what's the, what's the C plus plus, sign bit?
I don't want the C++ when I just want the regular one.
Let's see.
Well, we'll take a look here.
I was hoping it's the regular one.
Okay, so it is just sine B.
I can call that regular.
I didn't want to use some crazy C++ this, but that's all I actually
wanted and that's trivial operation to do, right.
It just has to look at the high bit to see whether the high bit set.
So I could actually do that myself if I wanted to, in fact, maybe I
just will I mean I could just shift it down, right?
Yeah, I could shift to download that might Sykes.
And so I'm just going to do it this way because that's a little
clearer to everyone else.
So let's say sign of or something like this.
And that will be in here and that should be totally in line and we'll
check out see if it is sign bit and that will be for an in 32 C value
and sine B value.
Okay.
So oops I said, sign bit sign up.
There we go ambiguous.
Call to overloaded function.
My there are quite a few of them there.
Oh, I can only get, I can't actually get the sign of just a regular
value.
I want to just a sign of the regular value.
I guess I'm going to have to do that myself.
It looks like unless I'm wrong about that.
I just want sign integer.
I thought there was a standard one for it.
And I just it's escaping me at the moment, but I was quite sure that
they're originally was least.
I thought there was but I guess not.
I guess not someone on the stream will tell me later.
That's usually the way that it works when I forget one of these
things.
All right.
Well, I guess I don't get to get to know that but I feel like the
compiler.
Very least should be able to do it pretty easily.
Yeah.
All right.
Well, let's take a look at what it does here.
So if I were to say, if value if value is, is greater than zero, then
it's one else.
It's negative 1.
Right, that sort of thing.
Of course.
I also would like to know.
I don't really care what happens at the zero case.
Hmm.
Maybe I would say that if it was at zero will also call it 1.
So I have to have a tiebreaker in there, right?
Because it could be exactly zero which case there is no sign.
So, I don't know.
So I want to see what the compiler produces for that.
I'm a little bit interested to see, actually.
All right.
So let's take a look here though.
And just make sure that that's working at all as a first at the first
step.
Okay, so that's just still produces zero.
Or what right now?
Sorry, it should produce one, which is perfect.
No problem there and let's keep going.
So, if I go ahead and do this guy now, I should be able to see ya.
So, start Telex start to, I start Telex.
Start to why?
I will say.
It's a little odd.
Want to see something else here.
Why?
It's still a little confusing.
Like this doesn't make sense to me.
I feel like we have another bug here as well.
It's definitely added buggy kind of day.
I think today is just going to be a debugging day.
We don't normally do that in the Stream because I kind of go through
things quickly and we don't have time to really stop and think about
things.
But so why if I was moving my guy down right because like, you know,
If I run this, the guys going downward, I guess, if I set the break
point, right?
When he jumped back up to the top maybe, but I'm going to make sure
that that doesn't happen now, so, I'm going to set that break point.
Well, I can see exactly where he is, exactly where he was moving.
Right.
But even that jump of the top, that should just be a memory of store.
So that wouldn't even show up that way.
So, I want to see what these values are, right?
Start tile X.
So, how is the end tile X4?
Like how is that happening?
Why is this x value for?
Who is doing that, right?
Because the guy is not moving anywhere in X, so, it doesn't make a
whole lot of sense to me that, that, that would happen.
I want to see what's happening at the top of this function.
Yeah.
Okay.
So let's see.
DDP.
What's DDP?
It's zero negative one.
That's exactly what I would have expected it to be.
So we come through here.
We do our length squared - there we go.
I've got that 1.0.
We multiply by the player speed, we add in.
Well, that's actually totally fine.
Right?
Because that's a very, very small X number.
That's that's like, you know, .004 or whatever.
So that's totally fine.
Maybe I was just misreading it before.
So new player pee.
New player old player P.
So they both day old player.
P already has an ex of 4.1.
Actually in it.
Which doesn't so how big was that?
How big?
Oops, how big was a tile map on a tile on a side?
Maybe I'm just like forgetting my old.
Look at I'll side and M is only one point three nine.
So you should never be able to have
And offset of for that's like totally not allowed at all.
Right, so we've got, we've got some bug's to deal with here.
So let's actually, I'm just going to step straight up step through the
code directly and figure out what's going on here.
Because we've got, we have some bugs lurking, at least one probably
more lurking in our code.
And I think the most important thing to do by far before we go, any
further would be to get rid of them.
So I'm going to go ahead and take a look at the startup code here.
I guess I'll take a look at what happens when we actually initialize a
player and see see what happens in there.
Okay.
So let's go ahead and run the game and when I initialize my guy, I
want to see what his situation is Right entity.
So and interestingly enough, when we do get entity with that energy
index.
I am assuming that we were clearing but we could double-check that as
well.
So when we start that all looks
Totally reasonable.
The offset is 0 which is exactly what I would expect.
And so, let's see what happens.
Here we go, through is controller stuff and that nothing else will
happen here, which is exactly what we would expect.
Because no other controllers have said anything.
The camera is following this entity.
So it's going to go ahead and take his Z value.
It's also going to do a subtraction here to see whether it needs to
adjust to follow him.
It does not, so that's all.
Fine.
And let's see.
We don't actually have is entity even defined in this scope.
I don't even know what that's actually showing me.
Anyway, so we're going to go ahead and draw the bitmap.
We do this stuff.
We draw everything, which is good.
Go ahead and draw the tile map.
Nothing particular interesting there.
This is the end of it was looking at.
So we go ahead and we're going to do so entity index 0, we actually
shouldn't ever draw.
That's the no entity.
So we wouldn't we don't even have to actually Loop over that in a day.
I couldn't make that just Loop.
Start at one, The Entity exists will prevent it from happening but
something to note.
So, all right, when we're in here, here's our guy again.
He still has an X.
That's what we expected.
So that X is totally correct.
And no problems there.
So that's all good.
So I suspect that basically.
Oh, you know what?
You know what?
I just realized this may be the bug that we.
Yeah.
Yep.
So this could actually be this right here.
I forgot to fix this typo.
We talked about on the forums briefly as one that we had to do.
So we're supposed to reconnect lies before this.
And also this re doubles my previous to do about wanting to take care
of the re canonical Hice problem, which maybe we'll
You as well tonight.
So yeah, okay.
So now that we've got that straightened away because one of the
problems right with that recognize thing as I sort of said we'll deal
with that in a bit because I didn't really want to go fussing with it
too much because we're really not sure what we're going to do with a
bunch of those things.
Yet.
It means you have to type that re canonicalize, which is just kind of
error prone, right?
And it's not good.
So let me go ahead and get us back now because I think what happened
is basically when I moved the guy over here.
Here it was never Rica nanak lies in his position.
So he was constantly offset way over from where he was, right?
So now when I do this again, I think we should see like a better.
We should see a much better set of tile pieces of Tau information here
5353.
Perfect.
That's what we expect to see most of the time.
It should be in the same tile and there we go.
With our Delta is Delta 1, Delta 1, okay.
So, there we go.
So now he's doing his thing.
Let's go ahead and see if I can if I can break us again.
So I gotta get through here.
Like so, come on, you can do it.
There's bugs in the Collision detector.
Come on.
I know you can do it.
We know there's a bug.
The Collision detector is a little too good right now.
We want it to be a little bit worse than it is so that we can glitch
through it.
Easier.
Come on.
I can't demo the glitching.
If you don't let me
Through there.
Come on.
All right, you know what?
We're just going to make a door.
We're just going to flat out.
Make a door there.
That's what we're going to do.
It could also be that now that we fixed that problem.
We're iterating over.
Walls better write, it could have been that that problem was also
causing us to not iterate.
Over the door is properly over the over all the tiles that we should
have been, and we were missing them.
So that's why I was able to glitch through it.
So easily.
I'm pretty sure we could still go through it.
If we tried though, because like I said, the Collision detector
currently I think still is kind of buggy.
But yeah, it may have been that that bug was was what was allowing me
to do it so easily because it wouldn't check the right tiles.
And so we were able to get through it.
Well, I want to test my
tapping solution.
So what I'm going to do is, I'm just going to force their to be.
I'm going to force their, to be a door there and I can do that in the
thing.
That creates the tile code.
I can just straight up, say, you know what, guys, there's always a
door in the downward Direction because hey, I want there to be.
So frankly.
It's just like, okay.
Oh, you know, what I could do to?
I could just say, you know what, there's always, there's always a
door.
It's like surprise.
No,
No one gets too close.
Anything.
Oops.
Yeah, that's the opposite of what I want to do.
My bad.
Right?
What I want to do is come down here and reset it to what?
Yeah.
Sorry about that.
Okay.
So now if I come down here, I should be able to trigger the case and
we can actually test it.
Now.
It looks like it was not quite working there.
So what I need to do is just go.
All right.
What can I do here?
I need to set a breakpoint that's basically conditional on that.
So I'm just going to go ahead and write that in.
So I can take a look at my Delta case where I will do the wrap around.
So basically what I'm going to do here is say, you know, something
like if and tile
Yeah, if n tile, Y is greater than n.
Ty Lex, I'm sorry.
Aunt, I'll Y is greater than start tile.
Why then I'm going to just want a break right there.
Right?
We'll just stop right there.
So I'm going to set a breakpoint on that and it's just something I
like to do a lot of time.
So I'll just write some code in that breaks on the case that I
actually care about just like right there and then I can just go ahead
and look at what happens.
So the start towel start to write n tile and tile exactly what we
thought was going to happen.
Right?
We're going from 0 to 4 billion.
So we produce the Delta X of 1 and the Delta y of negative 1 which hey
is exactly what I wanted to have happen surprisingly enough.
So it did.
So it turns out the wraparound arithmetic is totally what you want.
So
What was the problem there is really the question.
What was the problem?
So we do these tests and that's fine.
And then what do we actually record is the entity as the new player
position do?
That's correct.
That's all pretty much what you would expect.
So, yeah, that seemed like, it worked.
Exactly, right?
So, what was the problem?
Why did we have a problem with not seeing where the guy was
afterwards?
Right?
Because if I'm not mistaken, where is our dude, right?
Whereas, our dude is?
Gone, which seems undesirable to say the least.
So what I'd like to do is go ahead and say at this point.
I'm going to go ahead and break in the render and say, where did my
dude go, right?
I don't know where he is.
He should be here somewhere.
So let's find out.
First of all, let's find out where the camera is because that's
interesting, right?
And then, we can figure out what the diff is.
So what's the diff?
What is the difficulty, the diff between the camera and the guy?
Is negative 9 and a gigantic y value.
So, the camera does not appear to have properly caught up with the
dude, which, which seems a little odd.
Oh, right.
Yeah, so this is also going to have to get upgraded.
Now to handle the wrapping, right are moving the camera to handle the
wrapping by wrappings complicated.
You got to you got to have your stuff together.
I wonder if if allowing rapping was a bad idea, I guess for
educational purposes.
Maybe doesn't because you get to see me after go through all this
stuff, but it's crazy.
How much stuff you have to think about extra.
You can't just cheese out, right?
So I forgot that we basically haven't done much with the camera.
What I'd really like to do with the camera here is do something more
along the lines of search for the closest camera point that we want to
view, which would be something that would be generated along with the
world.
But in the interest, of doing something more
Straightforward, I guess, what?
We'd rather do here is say, if the camera supposed to be basically
every 17.
Maybe we just do a divide of that absolute tile for the guy.
And we just set the camera to be wherever that actually is right for
now.
Because that would always that would always work and that may just be,
you know, a better way to leave it in there.
Something that basically just says, what's the closest centered screen
for the dude and set it to that?
All right.
So, of course 17 doesn't evenly go into 4 billion.
So at the wraparound Point, that's pretty interesting at the
wraparound point.
You wouldn't really even be able to quite do that, right?
Because if you think about it,
This is turning into a much more interesting stream for me.
Probably not for everyone else.
But so if you think about it, we've got this situation where we're
saying, we're viewing the the, you know screen.
Which is a certain, you know Dimension that we wanted for playability,
which is 17 by 9 or something like this, right?
And remember what we're actually said, it was 17 by 9.
So for a 17 by nine screen, like those numbers, don't go into four
billion and some odd, right?
The, the actual 2 to the 32nd, right 2 to the 32nd.
That number of tiles isn't evenly divisible by 17 or 9.
So, when we do our rap,
Rapping right?
We would not be able to put a screen right there.
Right?
So at the wraparound Point, you'd get this other, you'd get a screen
that was like misaligned or you get, you know, yeah, you'd get
something that was sort of going to be half off like, like that.
And you'd see part of the of the top part of the world, which kind of
breaks what we would want to do, right?
And so,
So really if you want to have that properly, you do have to always do
it so that you kind of know, right?
What the actual.
You kind of know what the actual.
Places are in your game and what constitutes a screen and you always
have to actually use some additional information.
If you want to do it this way.
I wonder if this just means that rapping is a big No-No and we don't
want to do that.
Right?
It could mean that we just would encounter all kinds of problems like
this, where we thought something would work.
Okay, but then it turns out that when it's on the edge, you know, it
won't, you know what I mean?
So, I wonder if we want to say, we always start like right in the
middle and we never let the
World's wrap around to the other side.
So instead of being toroidal topology, right?
We say no, we're going to have discs topology, right?
I don't know.
It's a good question, but it seems like it seems like if nothing else
the fact that you can't do it, the screens evenly means that you could
never actually, if you wanted all 17 by nine screens, you would never
actually be able to make it go.
Go the full way.
So like at the very least, you'd think what we would want to do is
say, okay.
It's not for billion around.
Anyway, we'd want to do, like, whatever the closest multiple of 17,
was 24 billion, right without going over.
So, it just seems to me.
I'm just just thinking through that.
It just feels wrong, like, it feels like.
All right, if we can't have that workout in a clean way, then maybe we
just disallow it.
It's like forget it.
You're not allowed to do that.
We have some way that we set.
The initial place where I swear screen start is, you know, is in the
middle somewhere and rapping is just not allowed.
Mmm-hmm.
I think I might just go ahead and say,
For now because it really just feels like it's going to introduce bugs
and we don't get much out of it.
We only just did that because it was like, oh, hey, you know, we don't
have to, you know, why not right was kind of the reason to do it at
the time and it seems like it's just more trouble than it's worth at
that point.
Right?
Because you get a bunch of stuff that would have been much easier to
write that it's now not so.
Okay.
I think I'm going to say that.
I think I'm
It's going to ixnay it right now and say we're not going to allow the
wrapping to happen.
We're only going to say that we have to do.
You have to start in the middle and go from there.
So I believe screen X and Screen y-yeah our initial values.
So we would set screen X and Screen.
Y to be like in 32 Max over 2 and 32 Max over to like so, right.
And so that way we would start off.
Oh,
And we have to adjust our tile map our tile chunk indexing as well.
So that's actually a good reason probably why we didn't do that
initially.
So if you remember we have not implemented our storage yet either,
right?
So our storage for Todd chunks was still going off of the fact that we
just allocate a hard-coded array of those two chunks at the beginning
and go from there.
So, yeah, I don't know.
Maybe we'll have to will will do this as a to do for when we actually
Really Implement full sparseness that can take any values in which
again, not something to do.
Now waiting for a full sparseness.
And then I'll say, okay, we'll just set this to something.
That's at least not going to rap.
For the moment and we'll leave it at that.
Okay.
So back to where we were now that we've at least looked at all these
bugs that we have here and I might I might want to go ahead and second
what's going on here.
There we go.
That back in.
Okay.
Wait a minute.
I forgot there's another problem.
If I start you off on 1616, then players have to be initialized to be
where who wear that actually is.
You know what, I should probably 22 when we actually drop a player
down when I initialize player.
I should probably put them somewhere where the camera can see them.
Right?
That would make sense.
Because we have a camera P.
Right?
And so what I should probably do is make the camera P start out to be
looking at the first place in the world and then
Make sure I put the players down near where that camera p is or I
guess I could do it vice versa.
But either way I would probably want to say.
Okay, we're going to start.
If we're going to start the world off there.
We want to have a place for the players start off as well.
So we'll do see 16 by 16.
And you know what, I guess even this is kind of not really all that
necessary quite yet.
Because if I was just to leave it at this as long as I put those walls
back in, we're actually fine, right?
The only actual problem was because we were glitching through that
wall because we never generate anything that can go in that direction
either.
All right.
So let's get back to the Collision detection thing because we've got
so many things that we want to do to do here.
It's like going to be nice.
We kind of want to.
Start chopping through the so I just don't want to go chasing down a
bunch of these things that are bugs, that are only because we're sort
of at the point where it just kind of defining engine stuff.
It's much easier to fit through this door.
Now that we're only a point.
It's kind of a shame to ruin that in a second, but that's what we're
going to do.
Alright.
So basically what I wanted to do today was just start talking about
how to make our Collision detection.
Wider.
It does look by the way, that like that, glitching through the wall is
almost impossible to do now, even though I still think it should be
possible.
I guess you
Just much harder.
Yeah.
I don't know why that's going on.
I don't know why that's not going.
I should say suddenly we got robust Collision detection.
It's not pretty sure it's not actually robust.
But what can I say?
So fixing that typo in terms of re canonicalizing, was actually most
of the problem.
It would, it would appear for being able to phase through the wall at
all.
And without that, it doesn't look like you can really do it anymore.
So, oh, well, not as much motivation, but even so we still have a good
reason.
And why we want to talk about what I was going to talk about today.
We really have still have two.
Good reasons, right?
How much time I got left.
It's going on here.
No, I got no time left.
Well, okay, I can still do some of it.
So let's do a little bit of it.
Too many, too many weird bugs and stuff to talk to to look through
today was not a good day for streaming new stuff.
But you know, sometimes you got to go through cleanup sorts of things.
All right, so
What I wanted to talk about today was just how to start making the
connection better by looking at the guy as more of a area rather than
a point.
And of course we still, you know, you can see the effects of that
already which is because you can enter penetrate this wall like that,
right?
And we want to kind of fix that.
And then we're going to do the stuff where we actually allow them to
Glide as well, which is sort of one of the other reasons that we want
to do Collision detection stuff.
So what can we do, right?
What I want to talk about was what can we do to get it so that he's
not
Sticking in that wall and I guess if we only have 12 minutes left, you
know one thing I could do is just say that for tomorrow.
I'm trying to think if there's others bugs since today was almost an
entirely debugging day.
I'm trying to think if there's other buggy sorts of things that we
would want to do.
So I could just introduce it and coat it tomorrow since it's very
straightforward what we actually want to do as well.
And I don't know what are some of the other bugs that we had.
I could look for some of our to dues and just see if any of them were
Were there.
So maybe I'll do that.
Since this was the thing that caused us, the real problem.
Maybe I'll fix that canonicalization thing.
So maybe what I'll do is say, okay.
What I want to do in, we were you know, that was a pretty bad bug that
we had and I want to make it so that we're unlikely to have that bug.
So what I'd like to do is go ahead and say this offset parameter,
maybe we just don't want that to be something that gets modified very
often without being able to re canonicalize after.
Now, it's not necessarily the case that
we want to prevent it from always doing that but we just in general,
we'd like to go ahead and say that we're going to re canonicalize
that.
So what I'm going to do is I'm going to go ahead and introduce a
function that does the the change and the re canonicalize together.
So I'm basically going to say okay, you know offset I'm going to say
we've got Tom a position here like like so I'm going to say that we
have offset, tilemap position.
Or maybe I'll just do offset and we'll pass in the thesaurus value,
right?
So this is the pose.
And P dot offset will plus equal to whatever the offset is that you
want to pass in and you pass in that offset, right?
And that's that's really all I'm talking about here.
Something that's going to do that and then we'll Rican, Annika lies.
So, where did I actually get?
That re canonicalize from RE canonicalize position, this guy.
So we'll do that and I guess it needs the tile map as well, because of
course, it needs to know how big the tile side is in meters.
So this is what we will actually be doing.
There we go.
When we want to offset one of these Taliban position peas, and that'll
just return the new one.
So, we've got the new one here.
Well, I guess I can just return the old one return.
Like so, so that would basically just be a little inline function that
just does the two operations that we were doing manually before and
that would allow us to to not make that mistake because then we'll
just use that when we offset things.
And so what I can do is just sort of make a note to myself here.
Sometimes I'll do this and say, okay, let's take a look at the people
who actually should be doing stuff with this.
Let's go ahead and make that happen there.
And this is kind of this.
Is so I've talked before about how I don't like private.
So this is tends to be what I do instead of private.
If I have I probably it tends to be like a note to myself that this is
not something that I should be updating very often, right.
This is like the most that I'll usually do is I'll do something to
make it so that it's like, oh it's got a marker on it, right?
So that now I know.
But every anyone who wants to do Shenanigans with it still, can I just
want them to know that?
Okay, just make sure that you're aware of it.
It.
And I'll put a note in there in a second that says, what's going to
happen there?
This needs to take it.
Map, obviously.
So that should be everything Tom at position.
And then we just do this right now map and then we don't have to do
Rican a lake lies anymore.
So basically all these guys are fine.
But of course they would look like this.
But we could probably get rid of them as well since we're not really
using that anymore.
So we've got the offset in there and this guy will be the same.
So that's a new player P equals offset the old player P with that.
So that's already much nicer to look at as well.
So, there we go, and that will just look like that.
In fact, we don't even need to have new player pee in there at all.
Now, I don't think this new player P the views.
It's not, so that's fine.
Okay, so these guys who are actually accessing the values, that's
totally fine because they're the rendering code.
So that's fine.
So now we should be good to go and or not cool way.
Well today is a horrible day.
This is like the worst day I've had on the stream.
I think ever nothing has gone right for me.
It's been awful the entire time.
What did I do to deserve this?
So what what did I do?
That's what I did.
Yeah.
So again, I probably shouldn't even write that.
That's just a stupid way to write that.
And that's part of the reason why I deserved that stupidity.
So, there we go.
So, basically, now I just have it so, okay.
Everyone now just does their offsets directly and in theory, that will
make it a little bit easier to avoid having problems.
There's still another thing that I would really like to do the thing
that I want to get to eventually.
And so, I'm hoping that as we kind of round out how we're doing.
Stuff over the next couple weeks and finally go.
Okay.
This is how everything is going to work.
I'd like to get to the point.
I mean, the thing that I've been thinking about lately, basically,
it's just that I'd like to give the point where we don't have these
all these crazy position things happening anyway, because what I
wanted to have happen eventually, I'm just not exactly sure how we're
going to get there quite yet.
What I really want to have happen, right?
Yes.
I want to have it so that when you're kind of, when you're on the area
of the screen, everyone is just in regular.
Regular float space.
And then everyone who's off-screen is in their tile map positions.
And when you move onto the screen, right?
You become a floating Point coordinate relative to like the center of
the screen or something, right?
That's what I really want to get to because I my intention is I don't
really want to be using those tile map coordinates at all eventually
like
Goal, eventually was to figure out a way to make it so that we always
map everyone into the float space, do all the game there.
And then when things leave the screen and have to persist that aren't
relative to the screen, then they go into some kind of cold storage
where they're just in tile map coordinates.
That's my goal.
I'm just not quite sure exactly how we're going to get there yet, but
I want to assume.
As we do like, some more of the stuff.
I'm feeling like, I can probably just make that happen.
All right, so we're okay.
Now we're back to we're back to dude, being at parity and we
accidentally improved our Collision detector quite a bit by fixing a
bug, which was not my intention, but there we go, and we sort of
decided that we don't think wrapping is going to be such a good idea.
Now.
I don't know, it's possible that it like really those were the only
things we had to fix wrapping by just feel like will end up with tons
of problems that are happening.
If we allow that rapping to continue that we just don't want to have
happen.
So we may just try to always
Make it so that you never wrap around.
You never actually use the toroidal thing for all intents and
purposes.
It doesn't exist.
That is probably the best strategy to avoid sadness, but I don't
actually know.
So we'll just leave it at that.
So anyway, not a very eventful handmade hero, mostly just a bunch of
garbage that had to get cleaned out and that's fine that has to happen
periodically, but tomorrow we'll do the thing that I wanted to do
today, which is just make the Collision detector properly, handle
dilated things basically.
So that you can sort of do the guy can be a shape and the wall can be
a shape and intersect them together, which is what I wanted to do, but
was not going to happen, what we go along.
Also do,
Is is somebody was suggesting perhaps.
There would be a way to set the default inside the settings.
There would be a default way to set these colors.
I don't know if that's actually true but I will take a real quick look
to see if that actually is true color management.
No, probably not color management.
Ha color, selector settings, shade such a color patches.
I could make them color patches.
I suppose, I just want there to be some kind of a default.
What's your default canvas?
Order doesn't help.
Yeah.
Yeah, it doesn't look likely.
So I think we're kind of
We're not, we're not in good shape there.
We're not in good shape, but what you going to do?
What are you going to do?
Okay, so I don't imagine they'll be a whole lot of questions, but I
will go to Q&A.
Anyway, maybe we'll take some off topic questions because there's
really not much to talk about.
It was just a basic bug basic debugging day, which I'm sure they'll be
a lot of on the stream and just haven't had to do them very much
because I guess the code we've been doing has been simple enough.
That it hasn't really been the case that I've had to look at stuff
much but
if you want to go ahead and send me a question, prefixed by Q:, I
would be delighted to answer it and
And if that question is, why did we have to do that to bugging?
The answer is because I don't know, we were sloppy and now we've got
some stuff.
We all now know at least that from now on will avoid using offset
directly and only people who really need access to it will actually
access it for now and we'll start doing this way, but I want to get
out of that habit because really
I just don't like the fact that that there's constantly this sort of
interchange between the tile indices and the writer ones.
And so the way I like to do to level coordinates like that as I always
like to map everyone into the same space, do whatever the game is
going to do and then map everyone out at the end and that way you're
not worrying about whether you have to canonicalize.
So this is really even though this is like, you know, you might think.
Oh we encapsulated this a little bit so it's fine really, it's just
it's just bad and it's not
Necessary.
And so I want to get to the point where we don't have that anymore as
well.
That makes sense.
Do use diagrams a lot in your actual work, even when it is just for
yourself.
Only if I'm doing something particularly tricky, I guess.
But yeah, I draw em diagrams.
In my notebook when I'm trying to work stuff out.
That's that's tricky.
What do you recommend for learning C++?
I don't know, to be honest with you.
A lot of people ask that and first thing I'm the wrong one to ask
because I learn C++ so long ago that I don't know what the current
resources are for it.
I suspect there's better stuff than when I was learning, but I don't
know.
Try, setting handmade hero to start at the midpoint between tiles and
hit down to see if you can slip through.
So unfortunately, I don't think you can.
And the reason is because we're doing a greater than or equal to check
on the walls, right?
So it's more, it's more difficult than that.
I believe this is the thing.
That's getting us, right?
So you can't slip through the cracks because it actually is covered.
And so I may be wrong.
This may be watertight.
I I didn't think it should be.
I assume that it wouldn't be but I was wrong to bug that we had was a
totally unrelated bug.
And so the I was just thought it was that bug because I was kind of
expecting to have that and I was going to show how to fix it.
But we really didn't have to do that.
Now.
I feel like if we made the Epsilon 0 though, I feel like we still
could glitch through now, right?
That's feels like it.
Probably shouldn't happen.
But maybe not.
It might be that that it's so exact at this point because they're
vertical and horizontal lines, which are really hard to mess up.
It could be that that's yeah.
So even with a no Epsilon, it won't go through at this.
So, I don't know.
What can I say?
The Collision sector is better than it should have been.
It's a good problem to have I suppose.
But you know.
What can I say?
What are your initial thoughts on dx12?
Well, I like this new trend towards direct like push buffer access
kinds of things and stuff like that.
So I'm I am thumbs-up on opengl next and DirectX 12, theoretically and
mantle, but I have to actually see the final shipping products.
First before I can say whether they're good or not because you know,
there's plenty of room now.
Between a good idea and a bad implementation, right?
There's plenty of it could still be lousy or something, right?
Why is my code over 900 lines?
I don't know.
What do you mean?
Because it's 916 lines, I guess.
How about using signed values for the Tha coordinates starting the
world at 0, 0, and allowing movement, to - Physicians is just about
the world array indexing.
We have now know, like week.
I mean, yes, in some sense, because the world in this thing, we have
now is not quite done yet.
But know we could easily use sine values.
For what I plan was planning on us doing in terms of those map
lookups.
Stream went offline.
Is that Twitter?
Is that me?
Why did the stream go offline?
I guess it doesn't look like I ever went offline.
Huh?
I wonder if twitch is just Twitchy.
Why don't you like private?
Um, I don't like private because some code has to access stuff and
then I end up being in this situation where I gotta make things
friends to get at it and all this stuff.
So I just don't like private.
What?
I really just what I like to do is just make a note to myself that
this is the thing that is only for special occasions.
And then I'm fine with it.
Private just gets in my way usually.
So I don't I just don't use it.
Let's see.
Is there any background information?
You can give us new viewers.
So there's, there's a whole page handmade here a.org that has like a
ton of information.
If you want to check it out.
If you're just new to the series and want to know what's going on.
I highly recommend checking that out.
It's got a ton of stuff on it.
Courtesy rapping.
Go about float space.
Do you envision any complications with broadcasting, a sound from the
float position in the next room?
So I don't know.
Like I said, I I because I don't like the design things up front.
So I don't like to say.
We're going to do X or going to do, why?
Right?
The whole reason that we're playing around right now and just kind of
like feeling out what we want to do is specifically because I'm not
sure how everything should work.
So what I what I'm thinking or at least what I've been thinking and
we'll see.
What happens is I'm thinking that what will probably do.
If everything worked out perfectly and I don't know if it will maybe
it won't.
If everything worked out perfectly.
I feel like what we would do is say, okay the game takes place in
something, you know.
That looks kind of like this.
Right?
So it's basically got, you know, your room and maybe like the 3 by 3
by 3 because it'd be like a cube or whatever the three by three by
three of the rooms around it.
Right?
And all of those are in float, right?
So your position relative to the center of that is all in float.
And then what happens is when you move right from one room to the next
there's just
An event where you move over and the camera changes to here, right?
And then everybody's position is just updated to be in the new room in
anyone who falls outside of that, like, who is in here, gets baked
back out to tile positions.
And it's just, you know, is now dormant and I'm thinking will still
run, like, high-level AI sorts of stuff on the tile map stuff itself,
so that they're still all the world is still active, but only
The stuff in here is actually in float and going at any given time.
That's what I'd like to get to like.
This is like, you know, hearts and and flowers, right?
And bunny, rabbits, you know, I don't know how to draw a bunny rabbits
necessarily.
but,
Something like that.
Maybe, I don't know.
That's not a very good bunny rabbit, but you get the idea.
What is your preferred scripting language when you need it?
I don't I don't really ever use scripting language.
I'm curious, if you have to deal with memory misalignment.
Yes, so we will have to do that on the stream, actually, if I, well, I
don't know what you mean by memory misalignment necessarily, but like,
we will have to do stuff.
When we do our allocations to make sure that like, for example, all of
our stuff that's that uses SSE is aligned properly.
So we will be dealing that lecture later on the stream in when we're
doing the render and stuff.
Any reason you're making it somewhat more complicated than it should.
Yeah, I just don't want to have, I want to be able to have large
worlds.
Right?
And I went over this before and basically the problem is, I don't
really want to use doubles because doubles are half as fast and
sometimes way more than half as fast way less than half as fast.
So it doubles are bad for performance and I don't want to just use
floats because if I just use floats, the world can't be that large,
right?
And you get that bat like Minecraft.
Where people walk for a long time in this start jittering or whatever,
right?
And so I want to make sure that we handle sort of as large of a world
as you could ever possibly conceivably have.
And so, what I'd like to do is get it so that we're always floats
locally, right?
So everything just plays out in floats, in the world locally, but then
things kind of get stored out to the tilemap not as floats, right?
How are you supposed to draw the game on Windows 10, without a
hololens?
So actually
What you you guys can't see this but the when you're looking I don't
know.
If you see like out here, this is not real at all.
Most of this isn't real.
Like I'm not sitting here programming today because I was busy during
when the stream of supposed to happen.
So what I actually did is I took one of the Prototype hololens has
that I had and I just put it over the webcam and it's just a are
projecting me, sitting here, talking to you doing the programming,
right?
And that's proven to be a pretty
Way for me to make sure that I always have the stream out on time to
everyone but so that I but I can also, you know, head out and just,
you know, hang out at the restaurant for a while and just, you know,
you know, have a few drinks that kind of thing.
Just take it easy.
Is the system rendering off-screen objects in the background?
I'm sorry.
I'm not sure what you're referring to if you mean in the scheme that I
was just outlining.
That is what I would like it to do eventually.
No, you wouldn't bother rendering any of this.
You you'd leave it unrendered but you'd simulate it.
Oh, the struct name.
ABC initialization looks odd and I couldn't find it online.
So what that is is that C++ 11 s way of doing initialization.
So, basically, in C++ now in their infinite, decimal wisdom, they have
decided that this is how you have to do things if you have a struct
and you want to declare one of those, right?
And you don't want to give it a name.
You have to do this.
Right.
I don't know why they decided that was the case.
But that's all that is.
That's like a, that's just an inline declaration for in for a C++ 11.
What's the estimated date for the release of handmade hero?
Very far in the future.
I think eyeball parked like two years or something because it goes so
slowly, I can only do an hour a night.
Right?
And I'm talking the whole time.
So I'm programming at not even the speed.
I would normally program yet.
So it's, it's going to be a long time.
However, pair programmed, not really.
No, I don't know if I have a guest on the stream, but maybe
Do I go hard in the paint?
Absolutely, I mean, one of the biggest problems is like, you know,
sometimes I'll just, I'll just straight up file out of a game, you
know, but I want the Defenders to be scared of me.
You know, I don't want them to think that I'm a guy who's going to be
in there.
All like, you know, keeping, you know, having a safety margins.
Like there's none of that.
It's all contact, all the time with me.
Could you remove the old render weird gradient?
Yeah, I could, I mean, I think we loved it so much, but you know what?
I will we could get rid of it.
Sad to see it go.
Why is it such an issue with wrapping?
Is it because you aren't using World coordinates?
Well, no, it's the issue with wrapping was just because you end up
with your indices going.
You can't you can no longer rely on min-max, right?
So it's nice to be able to use min max and know that you can say like
if I have two locations and I take the minimum of them that I get the
smaller of the two, right, and that the distance between them will be
reasonable, but
What happens if you allow rapping right?
Is in this case, it may actually be that you'd wrapped around.
So you've got these two, which means this guy is actually here, which
means that the Min is this guy and this is the max and the distance
between them is massive.
It's like four billion or something, right?
And so you have to end up writing all your code, much more carefully
to be able to do stuff.
You can't just do the things that would be intuitive.
And so, I just don't think that's a very good trade off because we
don't get anything out of it.
We already said, we're going to have 4 billion by 4.
Lien world.
We can just put it in the center, and no one would ever be able to
walk to the edge.
No matter how long I sat there.
Where did you get your education at?
I am uneducated and educated.
To see handle pointers any different than C++.
No, not not in any oops.
That's not what I meant to do.
Not in any meaningful sense.
Know, there are some things like
When you're talking about like classes and stuff, like multiple
inheritance and things like this.
There's there's things that you could argue are different about
Pointer handling in C++ potentially, but like basic pointers are the
same.
Do you use Version Control?
And if not, do you promote it?
Yeah, I mean I do use I always have a system that backs up my files
like I don't use Version Control hard.
Like some people like some people are all about like branching all the
time and doing all these other fancy things.
I don't really ever do any of that.
But I do use just the basics of Version Control.
Why not change?
The tile widths and Heights to 8 and 16 as the closest powers of 2, to
still allowed to Royal world.
That won't cause camera issues.
Well, that's a note.
So the reason I don't want to do that is because basically wrapping
just isn't important, like we don't have any reason that we actually
need wrapping.
And we're not even talking about the world rapping, like we can still
Implement World rapping in the sense of the player would experience
rapping by just saying, okay, this tile Maps over here like so
Step onto it.
It just works you over to the other side or something, right?
We could totally do that.
But in terms of actually having the map itself be toroidal thing.
It doesn't get us anything to have that be true.
And so since we don't get anything, it seems like a bad decision.
To make a gameplay restriction, which is what the map size would be
make a gameplay, restriction out of it, just so we can get some
feature in the engine that we don't even care about, right.
So what I'd rather do is say the game can pick whatever it wants its
base to pick 1617 by 9 because that's better for gameplay.
And who knows what we'll pick?
We may change that, right?
That's just what we had it set to buy.
Now, think that's like a Zelda issue number.
That's that's why.
Can you explain how you use?
Makowski addition to your polygon Circle Collision system?
Yes, we'll do that tomorrow though.
Basically all we're going to do.
I mean, the first thing we'll do is the very simple one.
I don't know if I bother doing the circles yet because we may say that
for the full Collision detector past that we do when we're writing the
engine proper, but all you need to think about it.
It's very easy.
If you want to do a minkowski sum of two, rectangles, it's the same as
putting sweeping that rectangle around and just making a bigger
rectangle, right?
And you'll see, it's very easy.
If you just do the same shape unrotated,
It's very, very easy to implement and I can show you, I'll show you
tomorrow, very simple way to implement.
It's very, it's very basic, it gets harder.
The reason it gets harder as when you want to start to do fancier
things.
So when we do the full closure sector will be handling more stuff
like, oh, you know, I don't know that.
Well, Bob, I don't know that will actually ever have rotating
Collision volumes in our game, but we might and we want to and the
system that will probably end up using will support them anyway, but,
at the very least, like having Circle,
And in squares and ellipses and stuff like that is something that you
can.
Think about, it's definitely much harder than just doing say
rectangles systems of axis, aligned rectangles, but we're going to I'm
going to at least show the rectangle case tomorrow, because really
quick and then we'll save the rest of it.
Potentially, for when we do the full question doctor.
Are you eventually going to add tile entities?
So after we do the animation control stuff like after we get basically
like we're pretty close actually because the Collision detector is the
last kind of finicky thing there.
The next up we're going to do is basically like having some guys
moving around the screen that interact with each other, so that we can
start to work up towards that stuff.
I'm sorry about where everyone maps in and Float space, and then Maps
out, and that sort of stuff.
After we do that, then we'll move on to actually, spec'ing out how
we're going to do the world stuff and that's when we'll start doing.
Happening on those tiles because I want to basically start building
the maps.
And the reason we didn't do that back when we first got the Tom a
purring is be working as we hadn't have vectors yet at all.
And so I want to do vectors.
I thought the easier way to start with vectors with just have one or
two things because when we start doing World building with vectors is
going to be a little more complicated, we're going to have a lot of
stuff that's going on there.
So,
How much Focus are you going to be showing towards tile entities?
I'm not sure.
I know exactly what the phrase tile.
Entities means, though.
I'm not even sure that we'll really have much of a tile map in the end
game.
Like basically, I just felt like maybe tile map is the easiest way for
us to generate the world, but we may not it may not really look very
tilemap e at the end, so we'll see.
And and we may just ditch the tilemap thing altogether.
I don't know.
So we will see when we actually do the world map pass, where we're
really creating the world.
We will see where we end up because I don't know the answers to a lot
of those questions.
It's my first time making a 2d, like walk around a game like this,
almost everything else I've ever done is full 3d.
So it's pretty, it's pretty educational for me to go through this
because I get to see like, how do I want to handle all of these things
and I'm not sure yet.
So I'm, you know, as I go.
I kind of player I'll be playing around and going.
Oh, I like this.
I don't like this.
How tall are you?
I'm 6 foot and about like a 3/4 of an inch.
Maybe not quite 61.
What if you translate a 9x9 tile grid to the player as origin before
doing any world math?
Yeah.
I mean, like I said, that's kind of what I want to do.
Basically like we'll be getting
We will figure out something, right?
Something.
will be figured out but I'm just not sure what it is yet because
Still kind of building the basic stuff that we're playing with.
And, until we're done with that.
It really won't be possible for me to say definitively.
What I want to have happen.
What do I use to draw create data?
Oops.
Creature with a Wacom.
What is this?
What is this thing in 2003 Graphics tablet?
In 20s.
How you spell that?
20s, who knows a Wacom tablet.
Let's leave it at that.
For rapping, you could just check if the new value is between you and
Max and the nearest house multiple of 9 17 that subtract the
difference.
Well, no, you couldn't though because you have to do that for the
entities as well and the camera.
It's just it's very janky at that point.
Right?
It's not a good situation.
Can you explain what float space is exactly for us?
Newbies?
Sure.
so,
here's the deal.
Inside a computer, right?
You've got integers.
Which is a way of coding numbers.
Such that you have some number of bits in them.
Right?
Like 32 bits.
Let's say would be a typical number and they're stored are mapped to
the numbers 0, through something to, to whatever the number of bits
is.
So 2 to the 32nd, in the case of an insurer that sort of tube.
It's actually two or three s minus one.
Because it can't store that final one.
Right?
But there's also floating Point numbers and what floating point
A are floating Point numbers are way of using the bits inside your
computer right to actually talk about numbers that are not just
integers that are not just whole numbers, 0, 1, 2 3, right?
Whatever that don't necessarily have even spaces in between them and
which are allow you to sort of specify things small, or large,
depending on how the circumstance depending on what the circumstances
that are storing them.
So, what they do is instead of taking all 32 bits and just using them
to encode,
An integer.
They split it up and they encode an exponent as part of it and a
mantissa as part of it.
Right?
And those are actually very much like the scientific notation.
You may have seen in school, right?
Where people say something like oh, this is 3.12 for e to the fifth or
whatever.
You know what I'm talking about where they do that that scientific
notation nonsense, which is basically saying I'm always writing
everything.
One number, and then the, the trailing digits as decimal, and then I'm
telling you how many, you know, where to move the decimal, point to
the right.
That's how they're encoded.
And that allows it to basically float, which is the name of it float,
where that decimal point is so that you can represent things that are
very tiny or very large with the same kind of encoding and things,
don't have to be evenly spaced like they are integer land or anything
like that.
So the problem with floating point
Is precision, right?
You have a Precision problem?
Because what happens with floating Point numbers as you might expect,
just like with with that scientific notation, right?
If I have a limited number of digits, I could store, which is
basically what happens when you're talking about a 32-bit number or
something.
That computer.
I have a limited amount of information there, right?
If I had a limited amount of information and I've got, you know, that
3.125 E2 the six or whatever, right.
If I've got something like this, if I
Only have say four digits to represent, then what that means is if I
was at a to the zero or write or e to the negative 1 or something,
right?
Then I actually have quite a bit of precision in my 3.125, in terms of
how big the smallest thing movement.
I'm representing is because what is 3.125?
E to the negative 1.
Well, it's Point 3:1-5 a very small value, right?
And so, what's my Precision there?
Well, my Precision is all the way out to four decimal points, right?
Four decimal places.
That's pretty small that I can support.
They're right.
But now, let's say it was E10, right?
Is what I was doing.
Well, now, I've got to move that decimal, place, 10, places this way,
and it's like three 125000, write something like this.
And now what's the smallest thing?
I can represent?
Well, the smallest thing I can represent Now is really huge.
It's like 5 million or something.
Right?
And so the problem is just like if you only have a certain number of
significant figures in your, in your any number here, floating Point
values and computer suffer from the exact same problem as they get
larger.
They become less precise until eventually you get artifacts from that.
Right?
And the artifacts that you would get is.
- right because as I like, you know, if as my as I'm talking about,
say, I've got a dude, you know, you're playing Minecraft or something,
right?
Here's my Minecraft world, right?
And I start out at the beginning of my Minecraft world and I start
walking in this direction.
And I walk in this direction, for a very, very long time, like days or
whatever, right?
And I start getting out very far.
And now, all of a sudden, the camera starts being kind of jerky.
And my position kind of starts wobbling back and forth or something,
right?
Well, what's happening?
There is the position of the player got so large that the actual
distance that the actual Precision of where it could remember that you
were standing is now, so great that you can see the Gap.
You can see the jump between any of those two positions, right?
And stuff starts to go really wrong.
And so,
I wanted to do in this game just to show really it's for educational
purposes.
Like we could write this game without it, but for educational
I wanted you to basically watch me.
That's the worst handwriting.
Let's try that one more time.
And you.
Occasional.
Purposes.
For educational purposes.
I wanted you to be able to watch me kind of struggle through it and
have to deal with all the complexities that arise from allowing giant
things and trying to do them in a way that was still going to be
performance-critical, not by just saying doubles.
Let's switch to doubles, which are floating Point numbers, which have
twice, the Precision because doubles are very slow.
Right?
And so, we want to do is try to use floats, because they're at least 2
X2 speed, if not faster.
Oftentimes much faster.
And so, we want to do is see if we can do that.
Again, for educational purposes.
We wouldn't have to do that for this game.
We could just, we could probably still make plenty large worlds for
the average player, but it might be fun.
When since we're doing the work, it'll be fun for people to make these
worlds.
That it takes them seven months to play through.
I don't know who's going to have the stamina for that but
Will you create a map editor then know?
It's a procedurally.
Generated game.
So there won't really be a map editor.
/ say the maps will be generated every time.
Catching up with the past.
Video seems like you could use bit Fields or a union to
simultaneously, have abs tile tile chunk Rel tile in the tile structs.
Is that something that makes sense to do?
I don't think so, but I may not be understanding what you're asking.
Exactly.
Noob question, what's the best way to learn how to code?
I don't know.
That's a good question.
When I started out.
I learned basic first and basic isn't really something that even super
exists commonly today.
I mean, there are Basics out there but they're not like things that
receive a lot of development effort or anything like that.
And so I don't know.
I think the best way to learn to code is whatever you're motivated to
do.
So go, like, grab a unity game or something in or a moddable game and
hack on it a bit like in an easy language like or gamemaker, something
that's like design.
Just allow you to write a little bit of code and get some results.
I would say that's probably the easiest way to get into it.
And then when like, you're ready to kind of Step Up to more serious
programming than learn C or C++ or something.
I thought floats and doubles with the same speed in your FB, you know,
they aren't so basically in you've got a couple of different widths.
So what happens is,
Right.
Typically, the operation is that you're going to do in.
Any in any math?
Intensive, stuff is going to be something where you where you've got
for either 4X, 8X or 16x floats at a time.
So, basically, what will happen is you'll have four floats ABC, and d
and you will add them to four other floats d e f and g or something.
And you'll do that.
And that will take like, that'll be like a two-cycle, throughput thing
or something.
Right?
So you'll do for floats into Cycles.
It's roughly something like that.
If you're talking a vxr avx2.
It's a 8X or 16x.
Right?
If you do doubles, if you switch the doubles, you can only do two at a
time.
So if you do doubles, you would only have a and b.
So then you would be doing 2 x into Cycles.
Right?
So basically, it's half the speed.
Anytime you do doubles, you take an immediate half speed, hit to
switch to doubles.
so, the only time you would want to do that is
Well, I mean you might just do it because you don't care and that's
totally fine, too.
You might be like, you know what, it's just easier to write the code
this way and I don't think the speed is going to be a problem.
That's one totally valid thing.
Another way is if the work that you're doing to stay in float is more.
Complicated is more than twice as complicated, right?
As what you would be doing in doubles, then it was a lose.
So you're right about the memory footprint.
The memory footprint is obviously always a problem in that doubles.
Take twice the amount of space.
So that is always a problem.
So it's their cash on friendly as well.
But even just, before you start thinking about cash affects their half
the speed.
All right.
We're at the end of the questions and it's the end of the time.
That is some really, really good.
All right, so that's pretty good.
Alright everyone.
Thank you very much for joining me for another episode of handmade
hero.
It has been a pleasure coding with you.
Unfortunately, today was just a pretty straightforward bug day, but
that's totally fine.
We haven't had one yet really for the most part.
So that was pretty good tomorrow.
We'll do Collision detection since we don't really have any reason not
to.
Now we've sorted out the things that we want to sort out today.
So that's done.
And so basically, we should be able to implement our up, a big
Collision detection, and that will be basically the end of the
Collision detection for now.
I don't think we really have anything else that we super need to do.
And so then we'll probably move on to just getting a couple things on
the screen doing different stuff.
So we can start to look at like some animation, basically is what I'd
like to do going forwards.
So if you're interested in that, please join our in the Clinton,
please join me tomorrow at 9 a.m.
Pacific Standard time for our for Europe, Friendly Feed and
Then of course, we'll be back here at 8:00 p.m.
Pacific Standard time on Monday.
So thank you everyone if you would like to preorder the game and get
the source.
Would you can do that?
You'll get a link in your email.
You can do that a handmade hero to org.
If you preorder the game you get a copy of source code emailed to you.
There's like a link.
You can use every night to download the source code after I finish
coding.
And we also have a couple of.
We have a patreon that you can subscribe to.
We also have some good resources here on forums that hand be here at
org.
There's the schedule for the week is posted.
There's the episode guide.
You can check out which if you want to catch up on old episodes,
there's a coding resources page which has ports to like mac and Linux.
If you're trying to follow along on a different platform.
There's a good place to go and then there's also a discussion board
like a forum.
You can go to post questions.
So I highly recommend checking that out again.
If you just go to have me here a dark side everything.
It's got the pre-orders, got the page.
Krauts got the news and forums so you can get everything there.
All right.
Thanks everyone for joining me and I will see you tomorrow morning to
finish up our clothes injector.
Thanks, everyone.