Fresh one is a freshman right there.
Hello everyone and welcome to handmade hero day 37.
This of course is the show where we write a complete game from
scratch.
No libraries.
No engine, so that we can see absolutely everything that happens when
you make a game.
And it's sort of like the complete soup-to-nuts process it so that you
can kind of learn about every last little thing that goes into
executing a game.
So there's no more Mysteries.
There's no more.
I don't really know what it does down there, kind of stuff.
We're going in cleaning out all the cobwebs.
To the basement.
If you will finding out what your creepy grandfather put down there,
you know, stash in the basement or what?
What weird sort of pickling experiment.
Someone did and you really don't want to necessarily eat it, you know,
so sometimes it's gross is true.
But there's also kind of this nice sense of knowing what the hell is
in your basement.
So, without further Ado, let's pick up where we left off because we
have some, I actually thought overnight of something very important
that I should tell you guys about.
Out for people who don't already know about this and I realize it's
the perfect time to do it.
So I'm kind of excited about that.
But first, I will mention if you have pre-ordered the game and you
would like to follow along at home on hammy here dot org.
There's this fear R2 button.
If you click that you should have got a link in your email that link
should have given you a download.
Basically a page you can go to and there's to downloads there.
There's one that's a source zip that's updated every night and you
want to extract basically out of that zip file, the source code for
36 because we're on day 37.
And then you want to if you haven't already you're going to want to
extract the.
There's a there's basically an asset zip as well that we're working
with.
Now you want to extract that asset zip out into the data directory.
So I'll show you where that stuff is in a second.
So that is for folks.
Following along at home.
I am going to go ahead and Jump Right In Here.
And talk about the thing that I want to talk about.
So I'll say where we left off.
And why?
I think it's important to talk about thing that I want to talk about.
All right.
So if we go ahead in here, I made this little debug BMP loader, right?
Where basically, we were trying to load in a bitmap file that we
stored on the drive.
Now, like I said, basically, what we have here is in our directory, is
we have code and misc, which is what we've been working with before.
All the code goes in here.
Mrs.
Just kind of a
A place where miscellaneous stuff ends up stuff like the emac that
fig.
But now we've got a data directory.
And inside that data directory.
I gave you that asset zip that you can download.
And it's got this sort of test thing in here, which has a bunch of
stuff.
And we want to load this file, right?
Which is a background.
A.
It's basically like an image right?
That we need to load.
And so what I did was I loaded this file in write test background dot
BMP and
What I did is I said, well, okay, you know, we wrote the code to just
load it in.
It's pretty simple.
We you know, we read the file in, we look at the header, the header
was correct.
And then we used the offset those in the header to get at the pixels,
but we really didn't do anything more than that.
And it's a very end of the stream.
I kind of said, well we could we could just dump the pixel straight
out to memory and see what they look like.
And I did that and, of course, it looked like this, which is partially
not surprising because there's a bunch of things that I didn't
actually do in the thing that dumps.
It's literally just dumping them out.
So you
Wouldn't expect them to look right.
Even if they weren't busted, but what I realized is rather than
debugging this, what I should show you because I think I could
probably debug this straight away.
I've done enough loading of art files and stuff in the past that it's
probably would be pretty easy for me to go ahead and debug this by
intuition.
What I'd rather do is show you sort of the proper low level, basic way
to debug something like this starting from scratch.
And actually it involves another step that you are going to have to
do.
And I need everyone who or doesn't already know how to do this sort of
stuff to actually, trust me and believe that this is something you
want to be able to do.
So what I want you to do is you want you to find a paint practice that
you're comfortable with, if you don't already have one.
So for example, I usually use gimp.
We've been trying out Kita on the stream.
That one seems pretty good as well.
But usually I use gimp and you can get that for any platform.
And so, what I want you to do is I want you to
The pit program that you're comfortable with that is reasonably, you
know that works reasonably can save, you know, a variety of file
formats and whatever.
And what we are going to do is we are going to make a piece of what's
called structured art.
It's basically a art file that is designed to make it easy for us to
debug it.
Right?
So what I'm going to do is I'm going to make a file.
I'm going to make one that's pretty tiny for starters, right?
I'm going to make one.
Let's say I'm just picking these numbers totally.
Randomly, I'm going to make one that 60 pixels by 40 pixels.
Okay, that seems totally reasonable to me.
So here is my 60 pixel by 40 pixel bitmap, right?
Then.
What I want to do is I want to kind of come in here and I want to make
this guy.
I want to make something where I'm going to be able to put a pattern
into it, such that when I load it in to our program.
I know what I should be seeing everywhere.
I know what the values.
Should be right.
So, what you have to do in Gimp, you need to add an alpha Channel.
If you just have one by default, in order to get something that
actually has Alpha like this, right, which is what I actually wanted.
So this is actually, this is this has a zero in the alpha channel
everywhere, right?
And so now, what I want to do is I want to kind of go in there and I
want to put in something that I can easily understand.
So I'm going to use the pencil tool and I'm going to go ahead and set
that size down to like one pixel.
It's kind of awful gimp is at editing pixels.
So like, you know, for stuff like this.
Could arguably you'd actually be better served with a with with
something else.
But you know, it's something.
I know how to use.
I'm going to use it.
So what I'm going to do just as a very simple example of what I'm
talking about is I'm going to go ahead and make one red pixel right at
the beginning.
Okay.
I'm going to go down here to the last row and I'm going to make a blue
pixel, right?
And I again, I'm actually making something that's literally 250 500.
So I'm going to go in here and make something that's like the
Now, the other thing to 5500 255, I'm going to put that right there,
right?
And then I'm going to go ahead and say, all right, at the very end of
the row.
I'm going to, I'm going to put a green in both cases, right?
So I'm going to go ahead and say, all right.
Let's go 02:55 0, right.
So I'm going to put that green.
I'm going to put a green right there.
And I'm going to put a green right here.
There we go.
So there there, I've got my
Sort of pixels in known locations and then I'm going to also
furthermore do something where I get that second row the second row.
I'm going to set to be yellow.
Okay.
Right there.
And I think that's about it for now.
So this is my bitmap right now.
You may ask why on Earth I'm doing this but their answer is because
well the things that are going to go wrong when I actually do this.
So, you know what I should do.
One more thing, I think actually I should do one more.
Nothing.
I'm going to set the next pixel.
Basically to be lets say, maybe white.
I'll set the next pixel to be white.
So everything set.
So the next pixel will be white on that one.
And on this one.
So basically what I've done here is I've put colors in very specific
strategic locations so that I could see.
So that I would know when we look at the actual binary that we load
in.
I would be able to see where things are.
I think I'm also going to cap with black potentially just as one
further thing, just so I can kind of make sure that there's zeros next
to these guys.
If that makes sense, something like that.
Yeah, looks a little better.
And so now what I'm going to do is I'm going to export this, I'm going
to export this as a special test bitmap that we can use to essentially
calibrate, our loading code, that makes sense.
So this is structured art dot BMP.
Let's say, and when it comes up with all of these options, what I want
to do is say, all right, I want it to be in the 32-bit a RGB format,
which is what I tried to save the other guys in.
And, of course.
You know, maybe I didn't quite do it right but that's the format that
I want to save in.
So 32-bit a RGB which is what I thought we were using.
I'm going to go ahead and Export that like so and now we have a bitmap
whose structure.
I know exactly.
Right.
So I'm going to come in here now.
And I'm going to go ahead and I'm going to look at that bitmap in the
loader and see if I can verify that we are loading things properly.
Right?
So, it's that structured art.
Instead of going in there.
It's structured.
All right, bitmap, right?
That's what it's going to be.
And I am going to step in here.
Like so, and now after we read the entire file again, we're reading
structured art dot BMP.
We look at the header, and the header should tell us the things that
we thought it should be such as the width and the height, and it does
look like, that's actually the case.
So that's all good.
And then, we have sort of this bitmap offset that supposed to be where
the actual pixel start.
And so we're using that here to offset ourselves to that location.
And so, now, what I should be able to do is look at the actual pixels
themselves, and I should actually, now be able to see
Structured values that tell me what I am actually looking at, right.
So if I look at these pixels, and I'm going to go ahead and say, let's
look at the first row that comes in, right.
And I'm going to go ahead and say that I knew that thing was supposed
to be 60 wide.
In fact, you know what, I'll look a little bit further than 60.
Let's let's look at like 64 so we can see a little bit over the edge
of that first row.
And so now, if I look at this, what do I see right?
Well, I see that.
There's that
FF, there's that that FF on the low that's filled three pixels in,
right.
And then I see a bunch of stuff that looks kind of.
I don't know, that looks sort of like, it's almost as if we were to
read this in in little endian format, basically, this would actually
be, we would expect that to be the red that to be the green that to be
the blue and this to be the alpha, right.
But if this were in big-endian format again, we would expect it to be
the opposite, right?
So,
Expected to go.
Okay, the top part would be the alpha and then sorry the bottom part
would be the alpha.
So be rgba, right?
Looking like that.
So looking at all of these zeros here, it pretty much tells me that
either we're off by a little bit or these are getting red in, not the
same color order as we think of them, right?
Because when we were thinking of them, this was a this was our this
was ji.
This was be and it's pretty.
Clear that our bitmap when we made, it was not at all.
Like most of the values in it should have a zero Alpha.
And so that zero is clearly our Alpha.
And so why the alpha is ending up there is a very good question,
right?
And something that we need to think about.
So let's think about this a little bit more if I go in here, and I
look at my two rows that I've got.
I've got blue white, and a, and a, and a black, and I've got a red, a
it in a black.
Now, it occurs to me after I'm looking at it here since we don't know
which order red and blue go in.
I probably should have swapped these right.
When I probably should have done and I guess I could do that right now
is use something unambiguous like green which will show up in the
middle channel, right?
That'd be an easier way for me, to sort of Bullseye.
Exactly what order my stuff is coming in at because I don't know
whether the bottom row stored first or whether the top row stored
first.
I mean, I kind of probably do because I think I remember stuff about
the bitmap format.
But again, if you're coming at this completely fresh, you wouldn't
know it could be stored from the bottom up could be start from the top
down, heck it couldn't, you could even be stored like columnar for
all.
We know, so we want our structured art to have enough information in
it that we can literally figure out basically anything that we might
need to know.
Just by looking at what comes out in the structured art, if that makes
sense.
So I'm going to change.
I'm going to change around what we did.
There we go.
Okay, blue blue, and then I'm going to go ahead and Export that.
So now I expect to see red is at the top, green is at the bottom.
So whether I see,
Thing that looks like a blue or whether I see something that's like a
red.
I know that I'm looking at that unless they started this way and went
that way, which I've never seen before an entire thing.
But even if that happened, I would know because there wouldn't be a
white in between.
So I would see that the black came immediately afterwards.
All right, so I'm going to step back in here.
Going to go down here again.
Take a look at that pixel pointer.
So there's our green, right?
We know that's pretty much unambiguously going to be green because
there's no way pretty much that if this is, we know, this is the alpha
at this point.
So be kind of now know that that's the
The green Channel because it's, there's no nobody's in the history of
time.
As far as I know ever, stored, green, red or blue.
In the middle.
It's always green and ends up in the middle.
So that means we're looking at this row.
So, basically, we're a bottom up.
We're storing the bottom row first, and we're going upwards, right?
And we now know the format, the format is that the first thing is the
alpha channel, the first bite, because you remember, we could also
look at this invite order if you wanted to.
So we can
And ignore endianness for a moment and just look at it and B order,
right?
Here's that first pixel.
So we now know that like, the first bite is an alpha value.
The second byte is, you know, either red or blue.
We don't know.
The next one is green.
And then the next one is whatever this one wasn't, right.
So it's a something G.
Something is the byte order, right?
So, I can basically say right now that I've determined, that rather
unequivocally, right?
Note, KC B.
Order in memory, is it's a, a something, something, Gigi something
something.
So all I need to know now is which one of these is green?
And which one of these is blue?
Well, that shouldn't be too hard.
Because here's my white.
Here's my black.
Here's my, my sort of Alfred pixels, right?
But when I get to the end of the row, if I go 64 of these out, right?
So, I get 64 of these out.
I will see right here when I get there.
Sorry, this and more human readable form in terms of it.
Right?
So, I get 60 out.
Is the end.
Right?
So, this was the last pixel in the row was number 59, and I don't know
if this will, this reset it.
Of course, it does.
Thanks.
That's so helpful.
Thank you visual studio for you, unbelievable.
Anyway, so, basically, you know, here is my Alpha pixels that have
nothing in them.
And then I see the black value, which is what I expect to see.
Right.
And again, I guess, I know now that I'm on this row, so I'm not
wondering what
Jerome on this row.
And so now I expect to see a blue and that's blue.
So now what I know is the order is goes Alpha first, right?
Then blue, then green, then red is I guess what we're basically saying
is happening here, right?
So again, if we look at that, we've got to multiply this out a little
bit more.
If I want to look at it and fight order.
But invite order in memory, it looks rather unequivocally like we are
seeing again Alpha values.
First.
And then, like I said, when we kind of come down here and take a look
at it again, so I can be sure of what we are looking at.
It's always hard when you are off at off pixels.
So there's the alpha, something, something, something, Alpha,
something, something something Alpha, something, something something.
Now, we have Alpha the color, something something, right?
And so, since we expect that to be blue, that means that blue comes
first, right?
So I believe,
That this is our order in memory and again, pretty much determine that
strictly from the structured art, right?
I determine both in and let's see bottom up.
So basically, we also know that we start with that bottom row first.
So again, that is Without Really knowing anything about the.
The bitmap file format.
That was basically a way that I could reverse-engineer how the data is
stored using this, this sort of trick.
Now in the case of bitmap, we can just go have.
We could just have read on the internet, what the format was.
So it's not so important to be able to do this perhaps, but two things
are kind of nice about this one, it definitely AIDS in debugging,
because if your bitmap loader is broken, even,
Do you know the format?
You may still have written buggy code, right?
And finding that buggy code is way easier when you know what you're
looking at in in sort of the, the variables and in the memory, when
you know that the first pixel should be green or the first we should
be read.
It's much easier to verify that it actually was, whereas, if you're
just loading some bitmap that an artist made, who knows what the first
pixel should be.
It's really hard to tell and you have to keep like looking back and
using like the eyedropper and you hope that that pixel doesn't exist
somewhere else.
That could be duplicated, you know, whatever.
So there's that there's also the case that when you are a game
developer, you will also find yourself often times dealing with file
formats that are just plain not documented or not documented very well
and being able to do these kind of structured art techniques.
If you do have access to the art tool that creates
The art can be really handy because you can push structured stuff
through.
See what comes out on the other end.
And that's basically a little bit of Black Box engineering, you can do
to figure out the stuff that wasn't documented.
So there you go.
So now we kind of know what we're dealing with here.
We know, we're dealing with a byte order.
That's a b gr.
And so what we want to do is that's actually not very good for our
purposes, because remember, when that actually gets loaded in?
So in little-endian right?
When that gets loaded in, we basically have a thing that's going to
Put, you know, it's going to essentially reverse this if you actually
go about it, the a comes first, then the B, then the then the G, then
the are then what we're going to have is that AA is going to get
loaded in first.
Then the BP right, then the GG then the are are right.
Now.
What's kind of weird about that is that that's almost what we want.
That's almost what we wanted.
But we have our a stored at the top instead of the bottom, right?
You know what I'm saying?
It's just a little bit weird.
It's like it's closed.
It's just no cigar.
Like if we are expecting it to look like that, but it sure looks like
from the data that it actually.
It's shifted like that.
So what we need to do is kind of shift it down and move the alpha back
to the top, right?
That's what we would need to do to make this thing correct.
And so I can actually write a loop to do that.
And then it would be in the same format that are pixels were actually
in, right?
Like I could do something where I just do this, right?
I could do something where I do Loop through all of these sorts of
things here, so,
Go, you know, header width or whatever, plus plus Y and then I do, you
know, for you.
Aunt, 32 x equals 0 x is less than header height plus plus X.
And then inside here.
I basically take the pixel.
So I have a
Porter to the pixel and each time through, I'm going to basically say
that Source desk equals Source desk and I'm going to just kind of
Shuffle it around a little bit and then I'm going to move sourced as
forward.
So basically Source test is going to equal to equal to base of the
shuffle here.
I need to shift it down by 8, so that I line up the are G and the B
where they're normally supposed to be, but then I need to or it with
itself, shift it up 24 to, basically get that Alpha up in the top,
right?
So I just got a I just going to basically rotate that around.
I believe that will give me something that's a little bit closer to
what I would have been expecting, right?
That's that's kind of, yeah, that's a that's going to be laid out in
byte order a little bit better than what I thought.
Now, of course, I don't actually remember what these were called, the
header.
Let's see.
Assignments.
I do write.
These are, these are signed in the header, and I'm going to put a
little to do in here because I happen to know this, but I'm going to
say or I'll just put a note note Casey.
If you are using this generically for some reason.
Please remember that.
BMP, files can go in either direction and the height will be negative
for top down.
So, basically, after something, I know about the bitmap file format.
Also, there can be compression.
Etcetera, Etc.
Don't think this is complete BMP, loading code because it isn't
Something like that.
Just in case anyone thinks this is a BMP loader.
It's really not it's just going to load our assets temporarily.
So but ignoring that I basically done the the little Shuffle that I
think is necessary.
So I'm going to go ahead and take a look and see if basically that
that produces color values that are more in line with what I expected
to see instead of instead of what we were actually getting.
And so here is our source vest pointer basically, which we are kind of
modifying and place again.
Believe this, this pixel right here.
Is this one down at the bottom?
Right?
And so what I want that thing to do is I want to have r g and B.
I want to actually move the Alpha from the bottom to the top.
Right?
So what I should see afterwards is basically that yes, which is, which
is what I got so that will, that will do the shuffle for us there, but
we still have another problem.
Our other problem is basically,
That are we're basically bottom up instead of top-down.
And so I guess I don't really know what I want to do about that one by
the other.
We could just say that our art works that way because there really
isn't any reason not to have it happen like that.
So I don't know what I want to say about that.
Maybe we'll just go ahead and leave that, but we could also invert it
here if we wanted to go the other direction, right?
That's something we could decide to do.
But for now, we're just going to leave that.
All right, and so now, if I actually run this, I don't remember.
Or what's our, what's our code down here that we were just using to
test to put things on the screen.
I don't remember.
Okay.
So basically what this is now this code actually needs to kind of know
the size of the thing that it's actually going to be copying if we
actually want to start trying to copy things correctly.
So one thing that we are going to have to do is we're going to have to
store some information about this pixel pointer that we have here.
So we're going to have to make, you know, pixel width and a pixel
height.
And when we load the thing, we're essentially going to
Have to fill out all those values.
Now one thing that you'll notice is that base.
Well, I guess you know, what I could do though.
I guess I could I could hold off on that as I can just say that since
we know what those are I'll just go ahead and and hard-code them in
for now.
But you know, obviously in a couple seconds here, we're going to have
to make that real because we're going to be loading arbitrary bitmaps
and we can't hard-code things.
So 60 by 40.
So base.
So we know we have to copy 40 rows and we know we have to copy 60.
Columns.
So there we go.
And when we copy this out, what we need to do now is we need to make
sure that when we're copying the source of the desk here.
Actually copying from the right places, right?
And so, I guess I should I could also do it this way.
I could say, I could put the pixel with that were copying in here.
We're copying it that like that and the, let's see.
There we go.
I might make those sign for now.
And so this is pixel height and this is pixel width like that.
And then what I'm going to do here is the destination, right?
I need to advance that every time I'm not going by
The this is not going to fill the screen, right?
This bitmap is too small.
So what I need to do here is I need to actually go ahead and in the
dest.
I need to sort of turn this into the format, we were using before
where we basically have a Destro, right?
And if I remember correctly inside our buffer, we actually sort of
inside our buffer code.
We actually had the stride that we actually wanted to use, right?
If you remember, we had this our pixel pitch, so really, I'm going to
go ahead and say,
That we've got sort of a Destro pointer, and at the end here every
time we do Destro plus equals that buffer pitch, right?
Like this.
So we advance.
And then here is where we actually do our desk by taking where the
actual row is.
And again, that's because we're not actually filling a whole row here.
So we need to actually use that pitch to advance to the next row.
And we don't want to use, we don't want to have the offset that we
happen to get whatever.
We don't want to use this like pixel pitch.
We've moved pixel pitch forward and we don't want to start from there
on the next.
Do you want to start back at the beginning?
All right.
So basically we're going to do that.
We're going to copy out of the source, and this should be, I guess,
basically upside down now because we haven't done anything about that.
We're copying into the the other buffer, all right, side up.
And there, you can kind of see that we're sort of starting to get that
bitmap there.
That looks a little bit more correct.
It looks a little bit more like what we would expect to see.
I'm going to go ahead and choose me, do a little one more thing here,
which is that the amount that we're going to copy this row thing.
We kind of want to be able to do this on
Both sides, right?
We kind of want to be able to copy regardless of which ones bigger.
So if the source right, if the source row was if the if the thing
we're copying from happens to itself be larger than the screen, we
want to be able to handle that as well.
Whereas right now, we wouldn't because we just keep on copying right
off and wrap around to the other side of the screen, right?
So what we want to do here is basically say, okay we're going to use
that.
We have the pixel within the pixel height, but we need one more thing.
Thing basically, which we'll call like the blind with and the blitz
height, right?
We need how much we're actually in a copy and we're going to assume
that those are the pixel width and the pixel height for now, right?
But in the case, where that the blind height is actually bigger than
the bigger than the screen.
If the width or height or bigger than the screen, then we're going to
use the screen size.
So we're basically clipping the amount that we're copying to the size
of the screen so that we never overflow the screen size, right?
Circus weed.
That would be bad weed, overwrite memory, or other bad things.
Okay.
So, there we go.
So that's just a simple thing to guard against that.
I've got my pixel width and pixel height here.
We're going to have to load those from a file.
But first I wanted to do this part.
We're basically we go ahead and we get the source row.
And we have the Destro each time.
We go through Source, row is also has to be updated.
So that's going to update by that pixel width.
Again, that moves us from one row to the next row.
Right?
And the other thing we need to do is since we're copying top down at
this point.
Remember our information.
Our our bitmap is actually stored.
Excuse me is actually stored upside down.
So we want to do is we actually want to copy from the top of the
bitmap, which is actually the last row and we actually want to move up
each time.
So instead of adding pixel width, what we're really doing is time to
subtracting pixel width, right?
We want to start at the very last row and then move up.
So really what we want to do is pre Advanced pixel pointer right by
the pixel width times.
The pixel height minus 1, right?
We want to basically go all the way down to the last row and start.
There.
And that way, we'll copy the thing right side up.
If that makes sense.
Then we basically go through here.
We're going to use that blit height and that put with all right, just
to go ahead and copy things out.
We do the pixel copy like like so as they say oh and I got to actually
make a source pointer here, right Source row like that.
Okay, so let's see what we get there.
So hopefully that would be right side up.
Now.
I wish that I had zoom in but I don't think I do at the moment.
That's unfortunate.
But what I can of course, do is I can select this window hit alt
printscreen and then go over into Camp.
I can then do paste as new image.
And now I can go ahead and zoom in there and see what it is that I'm
looking at and let's take a look.
So there's our image.
This is what we expect.
This is what we got, and, hey, it's exactly right.
So, everyone's happy there is joy in Mudville and structured art has
saved the day now, if we go ahead and flip back here and say, well,
okay.
Let's try loading, something a little fancier here.
Let's go back to our other bitmap and see if we fare as well, because
maybe we won't.
So, let's take a look at, I forget what that was called in the
handmade hoopster, handmade test.
Test.
It's called test background dot BMP.
So basically, mmm-hmm.
Now, I guess that's fine.
Alright, anyway, so we're the day address tree and we have test
background dot BMP.
So now let's see if that works.
Now, we need to know again.
You're not actually saving the size.
So let's go ahead and set that pixel width to what we know that thing
actually is.
I forget, we're actually had that, I think was in the properties
dialog due to do there.
It is 1024 by 576, right?
So, it's 1024 by 576, and of course, we don't know if we did our clip
incorrectly because our previous statement when you used it.
So this may just flat on crap flat out crash because we didn't really
even look at to see if that code was correct.
But, let's take a look.
Hey, guess what it worked.
So there we go.
Oh, there's our bitmap loaded off.
Disk.
Exactly.
Like we wanted of course, now we've essentially overwritten the whole
thing with our Graphics, which is maybe with this as basically
overwritten our entire tilemap Graphics, which is probably not the
best thing to do.
So maybe let's go ahead and move this up to the top.
That might be a little bit senior of a thing to do so that our Tom app
draws on top of it or something like that.
I don't know.
Just something just randomly thinking out loud here.
Not sure if that's the best thing to do or not, but we could go ahead
and do that, right?
We could go ahead and draw that here.
And then we could do something like only actually draw the rectangle
in the case where it was actually also not empty.
Right?
We could do something like this.
I think this would work.
For example, I don't actually know if it will or not.
What did I do wrong there?
If tile ID is greater than 10 because we still got this thing in here,
right?
So we still got our clear.
Let's get rid of our clear.
There we go.
Much better.
And so now we've got our backdrop.
There.
It is.
Very nice.
So, we now have a backdrop, that's just kind of sitting there.
Doesn't really do much for us.
But we now know that we can load our deficits in and that is pretty
handy.
Right?
That is always a good thing to have.
And like I said, we're going to need it for almost everything else
that we do in the future.
We're going to need that.
We're also going to need to load some sound in here eventually, but
you know, what you gonna do?
All right.
So we've got some graphics in there.
That's a happy day.
Everyone loves it when Graphics are in there, but
We kind of only have part of the story there because our loader
doesn't actually return the information we need.
We had to hard-code the pixel width and the pixel height.
So I think what we want to do now, of course, is we want to go ahead
and actually have some way that that can be returned directly like,
you know, something like this like a loaded bitmap, write something
like this.
I don't know what we're going to call this eventually.
Like I said, don't think about it too hard.
Just start, you know, basically you're typing in what Chris comes to
mind so that we can actually return it.
So we know
We need that width and the height.
And then we also know that we need the pixels.
Those are the things that we had for our loaded bitmap.
And so now what I'm going to do is I'm going to try and just change
this code over just in place.
Like I said to use one of these so I know if I had one, it would work.
So let's go ahead and say that we have a loaded bitmap here.
And this is going to be that backdrop that we had.
So we have that somehow.
We don't know where we got it from.
That's fine.
And then, we basically replace these pixel width, and pixel Heights
with basically just the back.
Up with and the backdrop height, right?
Like this backdrop with backdrop, height like that.
And similarly when we come down here, that pixel pointer is not going
to be the game special pointer anymore.
It's just going to be backed up, Arrow pixels, and the same things
going to happen here with backdrop with, and then backed up height
like that.
Right?
So, that's all we need to do there.
I think the best of it pretty much takes care of itself.
Again, this one just replacing that pixel width there and let's go
ahead and compile that and then, yes.
This is the only thing where we get it from.
We don't know.
Well, we know we want to keep this around.
So we'll go ahead and put it in there.
There we go.
That's our backdrop.
And so here we go.
Loaded bitmap, backdrop equals game backdrop.
There we go.
And so now, we've actually got it.
Of course, if I run this, we will just go ahead and crash because we
haven't actually initialize that at all.
So basically what we want to do is we want to have our load bitmap
return, something that we can stuff in there which implies again that
are load bitmap structure returns a loaded bitmap, which makes pretty
good sense.
I would say so we have loaded bitmap.
Oh and you know what?
That's not really a pointer.
Is it?
There we go.
So that's going to return to load a bitmap that loaded bitmap is going
to be the result.
There we go, and then when we come down,
You're when we load up the pixels are result, pixels will equal.
Pixels are result with will equal the header width and our results.
Dot height will equal the header height like so.
And then we just have to kind of whoops typo there, gotta fix this guy
to take the address.
So now we are loading in the bitmap in theory.
What is the problem?
That's game State we go.
And so now we should be able to load it.
And hey, does that the same thing?
It did before but now we can load any bitmap.
If we want now that we can load any bitmap.
We want things, get pretty easy.
If we want to load lots of bitmaps, right?
We could just load anything that we wanted to write.
We could go ahead and load just about anything we could load in here.
Let's say we load player, of course our player.
I don't know if you noticed this or I should say our hero is broken up
into pieces that have to get assembled right like that the bottom the
middle and the top.
If that makes sense.
So we kind of need three pieces for our hero.
That's true.
So I guess what we probably want to do.
There is go ahead and load three pieces of our hero so that we can
reassemble him, right?
That seems like a pretty same thing to want to do.
So, let's go ahead and do that.
Will load player head will load player cape and we'll load player
torso and we'll just pick one of them.
Let's say move it will, you know, the forward one.
We can go ahead and load that in there.
So let's put that up.
At the top where we actually did our loading right here.
So we're going to go ahead and do player head.
That.
This will be I guess it's not the player really.
It's really the hero, you know, I mean, it's a hero after all look at
him.
You can tell he's got bravado.
So test hero.
There we go test hero, and I'll load the front one.
So test hero front underscore.
So, basically, we need to do three of these.
So we have test hero, head, test hero, Cape test hero torso, and the
Responding bitmap files.
So there we go.
We've loaded all those in and hopefully
That will just work.
Let's take a look and see if it does.
Doot-doot-doot and game state.
Let's see what we got here.
People do do.
Look at that.
We've got some very nice hero Graphics all loaded in everything's
kosher and so if we want to display these on the screen, obviously we
could just cut and paste this code that displays the other thing.
But really, what we'd rather do is just obviously have a utility
function that draws a rectangle on the screen, but instead of drawing
it, the old school way.
This time it will actually just go ahead and blit Graphics are the
screen.
So what I want to do is I basically want to copy this stuff out,
right?
Entirely.
Just go ahead and eliminate that and replace that with something
that's basically like, you know, blit bitmap or drawbitmap, something
like this.
And then we pass the game backdrop here and some more information.
I don't actually know what it is.
And so I basically want this to be bundled up so I can call it
multiple times and draw the hero as well.
So here we go.
Go ahead and get that in there.
We have drawbitmap and it is going to take some stuff.
You don't actually know what it's going to take yet.
We'll find out when we actually go to type it.
So here's our draw, a rectangle call in our draw rectangle.
Call in.
Our drawbitmap call are actually quite similar.
They both have sort of a similar sort of thing going on here, right to
me.
But now we have to do is we actually have to work on this bill it to
the point where we can actually wear it.
You can actually do something of similar quality to our draw.
Rectangles.
Remember when we did our draw a rectangle call our direct and call
handled passing coordinates off the screen and all sorts of other
stuff.
So we kind of need something a little more industrial strength that
when we had here.
Although at first we could just use exactly.
We have here and assume that we always pass correct coordinates that
are
Never actually going to be off the off the left or top part of the
screen.
So yeah, so let's let's start off.
I guess.
Let's start off.
Simple and just do that.
So let's start off by saying we have a drawbitmap call.
We're going to pass an ex.
And a, why to it that we want to actually use?
That's what we're passing.
We're all we were using reels.
So let's go ahead and use reels.
We're going to pass floating Point values for their X and the Y.
And then we're going to pass a loaded bitmap and we want to be able to
basically, you know, have it show this loaded bitmap at that location.
So it's going to take this little bit map.
It's going to show it at that location.
We're going to need that buffer, obviously, because we need to
actually draw that in there and then we'll just assume that that the
that X and Y now have to be
Valid at the moment and will crash if they aren't and then we can go
ahead and modify our routine to be more robust in a second after we
get everything working.
So we have our bitmap now and so we don't need backdrop anymore and
backdrop here, becomes bitmap.
Basically, right, bitmap bitmap, it map, bitmap like that.
And I guess most of this code just kind of works, except we now have a
starting X and a starting y.
Basically, we need to do this sort of code that we did before where we
do a rounding operation to figure out what the actual X and Y are for
the blind.
So we're basically going to have the same sort of thing that we had
before where we pass and real values, but now we have to sort of round
them to be, you know, more specific to be integers that we can
actually use to specify a particular pixel, not something in between
pixels.
All right.
So then we can go ahead and do this.
This check is kind of meaningless now, because since we're allowing
you to move around, that's not going to actually work.
In fact, I guess what we could, we could actually account for just
that movement here by saying that the blind with it starts up, being
the bitmap width and height, but if the blind with is greater, if
basically the amount that we're bleeding is greater than the screen
with, right?
What we actually want to do is say that the X plus the blind with is
greater than the screen with, then we need to
Go ahead and adjust that split with to be.
Excuse me, to sort of end there.
It's sort of a min/max x if you will.
In fact, I guess we could, you know, what?
We could do this very similar to how we did.
Now, I think about it, we could just use the same basic code as we
used for our rectangle, right?
There's really no reason we couldn't.
So let's actually just start with this code.
In fact, now that I think about it, right?
Because we know that we have an x y, and we have a Min, and Max X for
X and Y, because the Min and the max are determined by whatever this
bitmap is, right.
So we could really just use this code, almost exactly as it is right
in here.
I could just start with this.
So push that down a little bit and say, all right, we start with this
code, we go ahead and say we have them in Acts, the Min Y and those
are equal to the rounded versions of of that, sort of re-election,
real?
Why that we start at?
And then the max X is basically just that real X plus whatever the
bitmap with is, right?
That's going to be the other end of our rectangle, right?
Because we know that we are rare.
Feeling a rectangle on the screen.
We're just filling it with specific color values instead of one color
value, right?
And so we can basically construct the same rectangle, do the same
clipping that we were doing and then fill it.
Now we have to pay some more attention to the code that happens in
here, but for the most part that'll work.
So if I, then go ahead and say, all right.
This code is exactly the same, right?
This is exactly the same Loop so we can still use, you know, we can
still use our our drawing Loop that we had before.
We just have to make sure we do the adjustments that we were doing
before in order to get the X and Y in there, all right.
So our Destro calculation is exactly as it was basically, Destro is
this right?
Because we're still the actual part that fills the rectangle is
operating exactly as it used to no changes.
And so you get that that buffer pitch Edition get everything works.
Basically exactly the same.
So the only thing that has to be modified now is that we actually have
to change where we're pulling our source Row from.
That's the only thing that actually has
Change.
We can leave it so that we're not actually doing that yet, but it's
definitely a to-do item because, basically, once you start clipping,
it'll be wrong and you'll see that in a second.
So let's go ahead and say Source row needs to be changed based on
clipping.
All right, so I think we can sort of we just leverage that code there
because we know that that actually did the clipping properly and it
looks like this will actually be more proper.
So I think that's correct.
Oh wait, but I need to actually change it so that our X and y's Loop
the way.
That they should.
So this is actually supposed to be Loop this Loop, and this is
supposed to be that Loop.
There.
We don't have the blind with we're doing the between the Min and the
max now, so there we go.
And now, when we do our drawbitmap call, we should be able to already
call this for drawing that game us, the backdrop there.
So what I should be able to do is I should be able to essentially make
now what is what amounts to a drawbitmap.
The drop the draw a rectangle call, but
I said now I can pass a bitmap so I can cost the backdrop.
We're drawing the backdrop at 0 0, for now.
Just to see if that works at all.
Basically, if it can do the exact same thing that we were doing last
time and so got a present address in.
There we go.
So, let's go ahead and run that and that looks about right.
Nobody is crashing.
No one's unhappy at the moment.
So that's all good.
And if I go ahead in here and go up to that drawbitmap call again.
Well, actually, what I could do here.
Is just then draw, the player immediately thereafter, right?
I could say.
All right, let's draw the player as well.
We now we know we have the hero head and we can draw it.
We can even draw it.
In fact at the location of the hero, if we wanted to when we draw the
players location here, instead of drawing that rectangle, we could
draw this bitmap.
So what I could do is say the player left player top, we'll just
I'm past that player top Loops player, left player top.
We could just go ahead and pass that and there's our little dude.
He doesn't look particularly.
Correct, though.
What's wrong with them?
Do you know what happened to the to the poor little fellow?
Look at what happened?
He's all messed up.
I feel bad for him.
I feel like he's he has been, he has been by traversed.
Looks like, is there somehow is there some way that this actually
stored to opposite?
What what what happened?
What's going on here?
How did we get?
How did how did that happen?
Someone has to explain that to me.
That does not make a lot of sense.
So, how did this guy?
How did he end up drawing differently than test background fellow over
here, right?
What what, what's going on there?
I have no idea.
That's a very, very strange.
I wonder if this is I guess it could be.
No, I don't think could be an alpha thing.
I think that's just literally a bit busted.
Well anyway,
What I want to do then because I feel like that should have looked the
same.
So I feel like there's some kind of a format issue going on here.
I wonder what I'm wondering is if there's something that I'm missing
about how like, is there an actual flag or something?
That said because he looks like he looks almost like he's been by
Traverse.
So basically as if his red and blue channels have been flipped right
to just to give you some some indication of what I'm talking about if
we went into our
Arlo bitmap command here.
When we did this flip you can sort of Imagine.
Like let me let me actually in fact, let me do it explicitly.
Let me pull out the components.
So here is channel 0, right?
Here's Channel 0 which is basically just
The very first thing.
Well, I guess I could just do this by.
I don't even have to do it.
That way.
I could do it this way.
Source, dest equals U and H star pixels, and I could just do it this
way.
Just, you can see it a little more clearly, right since we don't care
about this code.
This is, this is just random code that were writing.
We don't care if it's fast or anything.
Here are the here are the the channel.
So, the first, this is the first bite.
Second bite, third bite for bite, right?
And what we were doing is we were basically constructing these by
putting
The very first bite in the top, so we were putting the first bite up
at the top assuming that it was the alpha, right.
We were then ordering in after that.
We were saying what did we say?
It was it's it's a BGR.
So we were starting with that.
We then we wanted the are so that's actually
Sorry, I was thinking about what we did there.
For a second.
I was like, wait a minute.
That's very odd.
But yeah, so the a the first thing our Channel 0, we're basically
saying our assumption is, this was the alpha.
This was the red.
This was the green.
This was the blue.
That's what we said.
Right a oh sorry.
No blue red.
We said alpha blue, green red.
So I want to pack them with the alpha on the top.
And then the next thing, has to be the red and so the red is C3.
So c 3 is actually shifted up 16 then is the green which is c 2.
To write and that shift it up eight.
And then we have finally, the blue, which is shifted up.
Not right?
And that's what we were doing.
Sorry Source, guest Source, desk Source desk.
Let's test.
There we go.
That's what we were doing.
Right?
And oh well, hmm.
Try that one more time.
Yeah, I probably should have only cast that one and then wrote this
one.
I don't know.
What can, what can you do, right?
You went 3.
D 2 Star Source test and then Source distance equals 4.
Are you okay?
So that should be correct now, so this is what we were doing and I
just made that a little bit more explicit so we could play with the
channels.
And I guess what I was saying is the guy to me now looks like he
somehow is stored in a different order than his friend like it kind of
looked to me like if we swapped the red and the blue channels that he
would look correct or something.
No, I guess not.
So I don't really know.
I don't know what his deal is.
I don't know why he looks so.
I'd like that.
I'm not sure what exactly is going on such that he looks that way.
I don't understand how his his his data is encoded, right?
Such that he has that sort of weird Look to Him.
Now.
My first thought was that this was like a premultiplied alpha
situation where the alpha needed to be multiplied to guess the guy but
that wouldn't make any sense.
I don't even want to explain what that is at the moment because his
the solid
Out of him.
Should look correct, even if that was the case.
So I'm not sure.
I don't understand why he looks the way that he does, and I don't know
if there's something that I'm not understanding about the way that the
file is saved, that is causing him to to look that way, if that makes
sense.
Now, there is one option and that is that maybe that are offset is
busted like the fact that we're painting him.
Not at zero zero.
Like our rectangle blood is is wrong.
So just before I do any deeper,
Investigation.
I'm going to go ahead and and and you know, it all back out this
change that I was doing since we now verify that it had nothing to do
with the pixel swap.
I'll leave it back at the more efficient, sort of the, the simpler
encoding of the
Guy.
Do, do, do, undo.
Undo.
Undo, undo.
There we go.
So what I do I do here is just see if I instead of instead of player
left instead of drawing there.
If I just draw him, you know, at 0 0 what happens like if there's no
offset, does that change anything, you know, and I don't know.
So it doesn't change anything.
So there's nothing weird going on in the blit per se.
Yeah, so I don't know.
That's very, very strange.
I guess what we should probably do is take a look and see if there's
any particular.
It's in the file.
And then also take a look at what's going on in the actual, you know,
in the actual binary.
So if we took a look at this, is this is the one that we're actually
loading here.
So if I go in here and I take a look at this guy, let's see.
So, how big should he be?
He's 144 by 217.
Right?
So if I were to do the calculation of how much memory, how big should
that be right 144 times to 17, I would expect
Act, if I exported this guy to see him, take up 125k, basically
something like that.
And let's take a look.
That's exactly what we're seeing roughly.
So if I, you know, if I divide that by 1024 120 2.0, see ya.
So basically he does look like he's being stored in raw format, which
is all good.
And I just so I don't really know why he has that reddish tint to him.
Does anyone?
I wonder if the people on the stream already know?
This is one that I wouldn't have guessed like, it's not immediately
saying anything to me, but I'm wondering if I'm just forgetting
something obvious because we are already loading, one image properly
that you know, that is coming in.
Correct.
So another thing that I guess I would try is.
Let's see.
Let's verify that it happens with everything.
Oh and I could also check to see if I blip the other image again as
well.
If it comes out weird too, I guess.
Well, you know, it could also be a thing with
This is the first time you put something that's smaller than the
screen.
So I guess there's there's a number of things we haven't actually
tested.
But anyway, I keep forgetting that.
I don't have to actually that I can just leave the game running so I
could just do this.
And then I can come in to the actual thing here and say, okay, hero
torso, and recompile and then we, you know, get the Torso so they're
all red.
I mean, all of them are red.
Tinged basically is what it boils down to, right?
That's red tinge.
I'm guessing that that also Cape is as well.
Yes it is.
So, and they're super red tinged.
So,
I'm not sure what to make of that.
Exactly.
I really am not sure what to think about what's going on there because
it's obviously a line still correctly.
I don't know.
I do not know why that would be happening.
It's almost like the alpha.
The fact that has an alpha channel is changing the red somehow.
Very curious.
Let's try one more file.
I'm just interested to see.
So I'm going to go back to bleeding hero, head here.
And instead of letting hero head.
I'm going to change here ahead to actually be some other file that has
Alpha.
So testing layer 04, for example, so let's try another one.
Basically, that doesn't have any Alpha in it because that one doesn't
if I remember correctly.
So there we go.
And so that one's correct.
Right?
That actually looks exactly like I expected to look, let's try one
that does have Alpha in it.
And so that actually also does look correct to me.
I think.
Let's let's double-check.
Let's load up three there that does look proper.
That's what it looks like.
Yeah, so I don't know, everything works, except our little hero.
What's wrong with our little fellow?
You know what I'm saying?
What's the problem?
Of course, that doesn't have any red in it.
There's that so I guess I should probably also go ahead and try.
Go ahead and put one in there that has red in it.
So I think 00 would be the right one for that.
Probably.
What is, what is 0?
0 0.
That one won't actually show from where we are.
Oh, well, you know what?
I could just draw it.
I'll just I'll just go back and keep drawing it at 0 0 again.
So we'll go ahead and do that and look at 0 0.
So now we should see that that sign post on there or not opes.
Yeah, there we go.
So that looks correct as well.
Everything basically looks right.
Except our little dude.
I don't know what is going on with our little dude, but he appears to
be incorrect.
So, let's see if I, if I go ahead and
We're on the sky.
Yeah, everybody looks right.
These are all expected.
I know it's kind of weird that they're there but basically they would
get Alpha doubt.
Once we actually do our Alpha blending to actually show the things
that are underneath it.
So what I'm focusing on is in here and basically our hero dude, for
whatever reason seems to have this problem where he's redshifted and I
have no idea why that actually is true.
I'm wondering if the test something
With when it wraps around, I don't know.
Don't see why that would be or the pre stepping doesn't seem to make a
lot of sense to me.
Either trying to think if there's any reason why that would be I'm not
I'm not getting any ideas here guys.
I'm really not.
So this might be something we have to sleep on it.
Be nice to get it, catch the bug in the next two minutes, but without
doing a little bit of digging and actually,
I'm not sure that we're likely to at least than I'm likely to.
Yeah, so all of those guys are redshifted basically.
Every last, every last one of those guys is red shifted, even though
pretty obviously other people can read it.
So I guess for the last two minutes, I might, as well just do a quick
little exploration and take a look at what he has.
For example, I guess I'll go ahead and restore this guy to front head,
and I'm just going to go ahead and look and see if
If that header of his has anything unusual in it that I am not
expecting to see.
So, let's go ahead and step in.
Here we go.
Ahead and load this guy.
And of course, unfortunately, I guess we are not really looking at
everything that we might want to look at at the moment because there's
actually more.
I don't know if you guys remember when we looked at the that the BMP
file format thing online.
If you remember there was extended headers, there was stuff that came
after the header that was
Just the stuff that we were looking at.
So for example, in version 3 header, right?
You had compression which is a compression.
What compression method was used?
You had size of bitmap Horrors, resolution colors, use this sort of
stuff.
So what we could do is also kind of look a little bit after this, we
could say, all right, you know, let's go ahead and take a quick look
at what we have after the header.
So read result, contents.
That will just take a look here.
And I think, what is it?
D word, compression.
So basically, we can take a look at what's in there.
I guess it's time for the Q&A, so we won't get very far.
But let's take a look at what we've got here.
So I guess which oops, that's no.
Good.
There we go.
So I guess we're.
Where are we on here?
There's the, there's the BM part.
There's the file size, which is, I guess a d word, right?
So there we go.
Oh, I've got it right here.
Duh.
So we got the file type, got the file size, which is that we've got to
reserves, which we have, we have the offset, which was that, we have
the size, which was that
That's a little weird.
Wait a minute.
Why is that?
Why is the size 124?
That doesn't make very good sense.
Does it if you think about it?
Hmm.
All right, let's keep going with that.
So if 144 says the size.
What is the size supposed to be?
Oh, it's just the size of the header.
So that's fine.
Okay.
I'm more relaxed.
Now that's totally fine.
If the size is just supposed to be the size of the header.
That's totally fine.
So, no.
Okay, no, no need to no need for alarm.
You got thing.
Got the planes.
We got the bits per pixel, which is 32, which is what we wanted.
And so if we go ahead and look at what happens after the 32, well,
Let's see, 7132.
We're going to need a little bit more.
Just give me a little bit more visibility there, please.
So if we see what happens after the 32, which is what I was interested
in after that 32, which is a un 16, so there it is.
Basically, we've got a 3.
So that's that's what the compression value is.
So what is a three in this file format?
0 indicates?
The data is a compressed, one indicates 8,
Orally to indicates for a bit early algorithm.
But what is 3?
Nobody tells us what three is apparently but that is what it is.
Is it not?
There it is.
It's three.
I'm pretty sure right people.
So we've got some kind of a weird compression thing going on is what
it looks like.
So if I have this guy here, what happens if I export him a new and I
go ahead and Export him to test here, a front head bitmaps.
I try to override him basically, right.
And I go ahead and hit replace.
What what sort of options do I have?
I can't turn off compression on here.
So somehow we got a compression format.
That isn't uncompressed, I guess.
Apparently, so, what was that compression format?
I'm very interested to know.
Let's take a look here.
3 indicates that bit Fields.
Encoding was used, what?
Pray tell is bit Fields, encoding.
Let's see if the bitmap of abla.
Do we have a documentation of bit fields and coding?
Or are you just going to state that it is bit Fields encoding and
you're not going to tell me anything else.
So as the value has to be 0 in the fit.
My data is uncompressed include biblical but right.
But what is a bit Fields contain bit Fields 16 and 32 B 6?
32-bit BMP.
Files contain bit Fields masks values in place of the color palette,
but I don't know that.
That actually the compression field must always be value of 3.
When a file stores, 16-bit data, 16-bit pixels in the Windows.
NT.
Format are two bytes in size and are stored in big endian order.
Okay.
So this is I guess, what we actually do know, sorry.
I'm blowing through the Q&A here, guys, but I thought this was kind of
an interesting because we basically see what the problem is that the
data actually has some compression in it.
So, yeah, so I
assume that what we should probably do is actually let's just take a
couple seconds here and do this.
And I guess tomorrow, I said, I probably knew tomorrow, we can go
ahead and and a bug that I thought I tried to save these guys
uncompressed, but I think I know what actually happened now that I
think about it, but that's okay.
We're supposed to be learning about file formats.
So let's just go ahead.
We'll just go ahead and read whatever that data for write is as an
exercise tomorrow.
All right.
So what I did want to do though, just before ending their is, in
addition, our header now that we kind of know what's actually in
there.
Now, let's go ahead and say that we must have these extra Fields as
well.
So let's, let's go ahead and put those in there, right?
So we have a d word for compression that we actually want to look at.
Now this compression.
We've got a size of bitmap.
Field in there.
We've got Horrors resolution, which I guess is some kind of a thing
that talks about the DPI of the image.
I guess, you know, trying to say something like that.
I suppose not that.
We care about that at all, but colors, used and colors importance.
There we go.
Colors.
Important.
And so now we can take a look.
I suppose that that compression value and actually think about what
that's going to be.
So if we go in here,
And I set a breakpoint, we should be able to see that.
The compression value is not set on these guys and see.
It is later, but maybe not, maybe that won't be it.
So, this is 3 here, right?
So it also it says, 34 compression on the first guy, we load right for
game update and render.
Which is this dude right here and that guy renders properly.
So that doesn't make a whole lot of sense.
But again, we'll have to go see what that maybe the
Fielding coding, we need to know, maybe it can sort of shift them
around or whatever.
Right?
And then if I kind of go in here and load the hero head instead, oops,
let's go ahead in there.
I load the hero head that also has compression three.
So they all have compression set to 3, which is this bit field
encoding.
So, I guess we just lucked out that we loaded it properly properly.
The first time we must have, I'm guessing because that's the only way
that that probably could have worked the first.
Time.
So, basically, what we need to do is we need to know exactly what this
is.
We need to find out what the bit field encoding was and so, oh, I
guess it tells us right here, bit fields.
And so, if the bit map contains six times three bits per pixel, then
only a compression by 3 is reported and the red green and blue mask
Fields will be president following the header in place of a color
mask, Taste of the color palette.
So that's producing.
So maybe this is actually saying oh, hey guess what guys?
We can move the red green and blue around anywhere.
We actually want to.
So it's not really compression.
I don't know why you would call that compression.
But apparently they decided to.
So, let's take a look at what those are.
They're saying that they come directly after the header.
So we're basically saying that these would come sort of right here,
right?
So they would actually come
Let's see here.
They would actually come.
Right here, right?
In the case, where you actually had that you'd have red mask, right?
Green mask.
And blue mask that and those are all d words apparently.
So let's go ahead and take a look now and see if those actually differ
and maybe that's our thing here.
So let's go and hexadecimal.
So, there we go.
There's the red, there's the green.
There's the blue and the alphas where we thought it was.
So that is what we thought.
So the next one, and hey, guess what?
It's in a totally different position.
Now, I have no idea why they would do that.
But that is what they did.
So there you have it.
So basically all we really need to do to fix.
This.
I was correct.
I guess in my initial assumption that they were moved around and so I
guess all we have to do and we'll do this tomorrow because I don't
want to go any further into the Q&A.
But all we really have to do is make this little guy here that loads.
The thing.
It's going to have to obey these masks parameters so that we can
actually get
Our values into the correct place.
Alright.
Well, that was all I really wanted to get done today.
Anyway, tomorrow, we can fix that bug and then we can go ahead.
And of course, we have something else that will be fun to do.
And talk about, which is basically that, after we fix his color
problem.
We will also want to start going in and doing obeying the alpha
channel on him when we actually do our blitt.
And so that's going to be something that we will also do.
And yeah, and so I think that'll be a lot of fun to talk about just
how that works.
It's not particularly complicated but
It'll be interesting.
All right, so I'm going to go ahead and close that down and call that
the end of things for today.
And then I'm going to say it's time for Q&A.
Please prefix, your questions with q: and try to keep them to stuff
that we've done today or stuff that we've done in the previous stream
so that we can stay on topic.
If you want to ask off-topic questions.
You can do that in the pre stream.
Come about 15 minutes before we start handmade hero and you can ask
anything you want because we always do kind of random discussion at
that.
Alright, let's see what we got here.
Let's see if we have any questions.
Does that make sense?
Somebody says that we have a typo.
What type of do we have here?
Colors user?
That's not right.
There we go.
Colors used.
Okay.
No questions.
It is a question free day.
Probably does not matter but you have why associated with with oh,
you're right.
It doesn't matter, but we should fix that because if we ever, if we
ever actually did something serious in there, it would break.
Like, if we tried to do the up down flip that, that would break.
So, yeah, that's, that's a good typos to fix even though it doesn't
actually have any effect.
This, this particular loop the loop could change later, and then we
would be like, what's going on?
When we stick to using bitmaps the duration of handmade hero or delve
into the lands of PNG.
I don't know that we'll ever use PNG.
We might compress these when we get to when we want to start shipping
things, but we won't necessarily use PNG for that.
We might you know, when we're going to compress, things will think
about how we want them.
Compressed.
We probably won't just you know use PNG because it happens to be a
slightly compressed format or whatever.
PNG probably wouldn't compress our stuff that well either.
I mean, it might compress things like the Sprites.
Okay, because of, you can do that, you know, can do rle compression on
the rows or whatever.
But you know a lot of the graphics are very painterly and so PNG.
By itself might not help, you know, you'd probably have to do like
quantization of it to palletized or something and then it would help
more.
I don't know it is but I'm not sure about that yet.
We'll have to see what we want to do when we get to when it gets to
the time to think about compression, but we don't even think about
that for a long time.
What's the advantage in defining the bitmap header yourself as opposed
to using the windows supplied bitmap.
Info header?
Because this is platform independent code.
If you were to use the bitmap info header struct, then everyone who's
compiles, handmade Hero on, other platforms would immediately break.
So can't really do that.
How about fixing PB file loading?
One dlls Reloaded?
I would like to, but we're already cut.
Let me see if there's questions.
Let me see what we have for questions.
Here's my Q cone working.
Yes, but I only start filtering when I say it's Q&A.
So if you put Q colons before the Q&A, they don't get looked at.
So it's only cues that happen after the Q&A.
Are we converting are loaded images to a runtime texture format?
Well, I mean, we will eventually be having to put them up to GPU.
So at that point we I mean, I don't know that we'll ever bother
compressing them.
We might it depends whether we're bandwidth starved or not and really
care about that because obviously compressing things has a cost, but
in terms of image quality, but that's, that's way down the road.
That's not something we need to think about the moment.
Why not use a simple custom format for assets?
We might we very male we very well may use a simple custom format p7.
Samurai.
PNG is lossless.
Yes.
It is lost this with somebody suggesting that it was not lossless.
If somebody was suggesting that, PNG was lossy.
That's that's not really true.
However, I would point out that we could use it loss of weight.
Because what you can do is you can quantize the image in a way that
makes it compress well with PNG, which does make the process law.
See, even though ping itself is not lossy.
So saying ping is lossless is a little misleading because it's really
About how you're using it that determines whether it ends up being a
lossy.
Because like, for example, if you want to actually get good
compression out of ping, you actually have to make it law, see,
instead of lossless because losses just doesn't get you very good
impression.
Are you going to do different blending modes?
Other than Alpha blending?
Well, it depends what you mean by Alpha blending.
Obviously Alpha.
Blending just means blending that involves an alpha Channel and pretty
much probably are.
We will always be using an alpha Channel, but we may use different
blend modes as in.
We may use additive right, which is still using an alpha Channel.
This is technically not Alpha blending, what we're doing right now.
In terms of like if you wanted to name it.
It would actually be called like you know mod or I guess, this is
probably still be additive with premultiplied Alpha it be inversed.
Inverted destination is what we'll probably be doing first.
So, yeah, so Alpha blending is misleading because Alpha blending just
means blending that uses the alpha Channel and there's lots of
different blends that can all use the alpha channel.
That makes sense.
You start filtering before an okay, number of questions happen before.
And well, I can't because people who post Q Colin's, during the stream
may have had their cue Cullen's answered by stuff.
I did in the Stream, So Q Colin's have to start.
Once I'm done explaining everything.
So everyone has to hold their cue Colin's.
If they actually want me to answer them till the point where I say,
I'm done, so that we know that I haven't answered any and I don't have
to kind of like wheel backwards and scroll through a tons of questions
to see which ones were not answered yet, if that makes sense.
Should asset loading, Kobe platform independent or platform-specific
in this case.
Would you put the load bitmap into the game, dll?
Well, the little bit map right now is in the game, dll, so that is
where I did put it and that is where it belongs at the moment.
Now, it's possible that on some platforms.
You do need to have some part of the loading.
Kobe platform acidic, but it's highly unlikely that the part that
actually processes.
The file format needs to be platform-specific.
It may use some platform slightly specific things.
Like intrinsics that are different that are like pound defined
differently across platforms or stuff like that, but it's often times.
It's not platform.
Civic enough to put it into like the win32 section.
For example.
I think the alpha blending question.
Meant, will you move one pixel at a time or blend movement between
pixels?
Oh, are you?
Oh, okay.
So you guys aren't talking about Alpha blending at all.
You're talking about sub-pixel rendering, right?
Is that if I'm getting you correctly?
If you're talking about, will be doing sub-pixel rendering, the answer
is yes.
Well,
Okay.
It's very complicated in this is really not.
This is really premature to explain this at this point, but I'll give
you I'll give you the capsule overview.
Okay?
So basically there's two things, there's two things to talk about.
Right?
Let's say these are two pixels.
Okay.
Well actually, I'll do for so that we can see both X and Y.
So these are four pixels, right?
So there's two different things here that are involved.
There's sub-pixel rendering, which literally means that you can have
shapes that you are.
During rendering that pass through pixels and you are actually trying
to account for this slight.
Like, how much of the actual pixel is being sort of touched, by that
shape and you're rendering it out accordingly.
So you that's like, anti-icing it's like, multi, sampling, that sort
of stuff is for this sword technique, but there's a different thing
that happens when you're doing transparent bitmaps, and it's actually
ends up being texture.
Filtering.
Technically that gets you, the subpixel movement that you would
normally associate with multi sampling.
So, what actually happens when you're doing Blitz, is you have to
imagine the fact that the bitmap itself, right?
So here's the bit map of the guy right here.
He is.
Mr.
Mister dude, right the bitmap of the guy actually always has an apron
essentially of non rendering pixels.
Right.
He is in the middle of it and all around him.
There's at least a one pixel wide border of nothing, right in his
bitmap.
So what actually happens is that each individual pixel is not actually
rendered sub-pixel e.
It's actually rendered on a full pixel boundary, but it pulls from a
portion of the guy that can straddle multiple pixels, right?
So what happens is, when you actually get to the
Part where the guy is defined like right here, when you actually go to
draw that.
Let's say that you're drawing Hoops.
Like I got rid of his leg.
Sorry, dude, when you actually go to draw that, lets say you're
drawing these two pixels here and you're drawing them out of right
here.
Like this.
Then what happens is, depending on the shift, the subpixel in this
actually happens.
Fetch of the of the guys bitmap and you're actually fetching Blended
texels out of the guys, bitmap drawing solid, but the textile that you
fetched is actually at some has its Alpha Blended here, right?
So the alpha blending, when in terms of that the Restorations
rasterization Target, we may actually always be non sub-pixel, but we
will actually get partial Alpha movement from the guy because he
We'll be moving.
The fetch will be fetching out of his pixels on a line if that makes
sense.
So this is really I you don't have to understand this.
Now.
I didn't do a very good job explaining that because we're so we don't
we haven't talked about any of the things that are involved here.
But basically we probably won't ever need to do this because we're a
bit mapped game.
This is more.
If you have this is if you have a lot of stuff that's not coming from
bitmaps.
Like if you have actual polygons that are actually have edges is
This happen.
So like when you're trying to do 3D and you know, the silhouette edge
of a guy is defined by the actual polygons, right?
The interior is texture so you'd have to worry about it.
But the exterior is like the, you know, is defined the polygons that
exterior is where you start to have to deal with the actual multi
samples and sub-pixel rendering stuff like that.
I hope that answered the question and I was probably pretty bad
answer, but I guess another way to answer that question would be like
we'll get there and we'll talk about all that stuff in detail.
When we get Alpha blending working, we need to care about monitor,
monitor gamma due to color B values, not linearly mapping to monitor
brightness.
Yes.
Well,
I shouldn't say, yes.
I'll say at least technically.
Yes, you can often get away with not actually doing that and almost
nobody can tell the difference.
But, you know, it's at least something we should mention when we get
there.
I saw a game that has quarter pixel scrolling.
What is that?
I have no idea.
I assume that it's just a really bad version of General sub-pixel
scrolling where you only can scroll by fourths of a pixel.
I don't know why in this day and age.
I have no idea.
Why you couldn't always have completely smooth, sub-pixel scrolling,
but who knows?
Let's see.
Will we be doing?
Resampling to get bitmaps on the screen at arbitrary?
Size, is yes, we will be doing that.
We will actually be doing generic.
We will be doing full transforms, just not perspective.
So basically we'll be doing rotation as well.
we'll,
Made here.
I have Morton kinds faithful Hound.
Well, it'll have more than kinds faithful Watchdog because I already
cast that.
If you remember at the beginning, when I said, I needed material
elements for all of my spells.
I cast Morton kinds faithful Watchdog.
That's how I guarantee that we can't be surrounded by ogres.
And as you'll notice we have not been surrounded by ogres this entire
time.
If you want to see something else too ready, this is me attacking the
darkness.
I cast magic Missile.
What program did you make the cool command text on your trailer?
With it's homemade?
Our bitmask going to be in an atlas file sometime in the future.
So, I don't know again, like a lot of these questions are about what
we're going to do, but I think,
I mean, I've tried to kind of hammer this home, but maybe I'm not
doing good enough job of saying it.
Don't try to have too much of an idea about what we are going to do
because we don't know what we're going to do and it's way too.
We haven't written enough code and done enough.
Exploration to know whether an atlas file would be useful at all.
Right?
And so I really want to make sure everyone understands the fact that
in terms of Technology.
You always want to let yourself do the exploration to see what you
need to do and then do it.
So sometimes the questions makes sense when
Like, are we going to be doing sub-pixel rendering?
Like that's like a sort of thing to do.
We want to have that feature?
And that makes sense.
But an atlas is not a feature.
It's an implementation that gets you, you know, basically how you're
loading your bitmaps out.
We don't want to make those kind of decisions upfront.
Like, what we need to do is see what we're doing in terms of pulling
bitmaps off of disk and how we're using them and then make a decision
at that point.
Does it make sense to have something?
Like an atlas where things are packed in or not and so on.
And so we really have to think about what's makes sense for a
particular times.
And you always want to make those decisions.
Once you have the information.
You don't want to pre say, we're just going to do an atlas file if
that makes sense.
Because it maybe that's a really bad idea for the throughput, for our
game, in this case, right?
I saw a height times width.
Minus 1 in the reversing code, should that have been height times
width minus one without the parentheses or am I missing something?
So I know the code you're talking about and I'm sorry I kind of I
probably should have stopped it.
Explain that a little more directly.
I try not to explain this stuff too much, because we're going to be
writing a whole renderer where we're going to be spending like, you
know, weeks talking about nothing but pixels and alignment and all
these sorts of things.
So I didn't want to belabor the point, you know, twice.
So I do apologize for that.
And it's good, you know, please do ask questions when you see
something.
When you see something that doesn't make sense because I am kind of
glossing over some of the stuff since I know we'll talk about it
later, but it's good for you to understand it now as well, to a
certain extent.
So basically what you're talking about, I believe is this code right
here.
So, what's happening here?
If you remember, we've, we've got ourselves into a situation where we
loaded something where we're thinking about it this way, meaning we're
thinking about it in terms of this being the top.
And this being
The first in memory, right?
But we actually had is that what we think of as the bottom is actually
the first, right?
So, what I wanted to do since our screen like this is the bitmap in
memory.
Since our screen is not, that is not the case.
Our screen has it stopped here.
Right?
What I wanted to do, was copy it out, starting with the screens top,
which means that in, we're kind of we're going downward in memory this
way.
We're getting higher higher addresses this way, right?
But this has higher addresses going that way.
So what I wanted to do was basically move the pointer to the pixels in
the bitmap.
I wanted to point to the actual top, and then just go subtract from
the pointer to move it down as we go, right.
So while this was getting well, this was getting added to, to move its
pointer down every row.
This one's getting subtracted from right.
So what that means is I first have to advance it forwards by the
entire size of the bitmap.
But not quite because if I will answer it forwards by the entire size
of the bitmap, I'd be pointing to there, which is not what I
I want because the rows are still stored as they normally would be
there.
Just stored in inverse order.
So what I need to do is I need to basically go to the end of the
bitmap - one row, right?
You could think about it as if I added the if I if I added the whole
size of the bitmap, I wouldn't actually pointing to this pixel what
I'd really do pointing at would be like the Phantom pixel that we
right here.
Right?
I'd be pointing one past the ant the last pixel.
And so what I need to do is I need to go that far, but I need to go
that far -
One row.
So I'm actually on the last row instead of one past the last row, so
that's what this function is doing.
Its saying, this is the stride, basically that's the pitch, right?
That's, that's the amount to go pro.
I'm saying, go as many rows down, as there are in the bitmap -1, so
don't go past the last row, go, right to the last row.
And then each time.
I'm going to subtract 1 from it.
So hopefully that makes sense.
in tiles code, will the
where it's possible to move, be imported in bitmaps to
I'm not sure what that means.
Exactly.
Basically, if you're asking about what's going on here, like this,
nonsense with this background check, dude.
That was just me screwing around.
We're not going to do anything like that.
In actuality all of this, all of the tile map will actually be
rendered with graphics on top of it.
So that was just me, you know, I was just playing around because I
thought it was funny.
There's really no, that's there's no Rhyme or Reason to that.
It's not a useful thing at all.
I was just I was just playing around.
Let's see.
You can simplify drawbitmap a bit by changing Max x-intercept ization
to Min X, plus b map with same for height.
Sorry, what were you talking about here?
Oh, you're just talking about not by basically not having to do the
rounding twice.
I'm guessing is what you're talking about.
At least I think that's what you're talking about.
So, yes, and no.
So basically, the reason that I haven't done that yet is because
eventually we're going to extend this to be able to blit part of a
bitmap.
So eventually these will actually get passed in as a real.
So I didn't actually want to do that at this time.
Those will actually get this will actually be replaced soon.
But, yes, if you wanted to, you could just make Max X have this.
This be added to it.
And that would be fine.
Why not embrace the inverted bitmap format as the new screen format?
Since we're also using, why up for player to a as well because that's
just kind of arbitrary if that makes sense.
Because and in some sense, we will like basically the what actually
the underlying bitmap coordinate system is is going to be determined
by the operating system for the most part.
So we don't actually want to pick one or the other.
What we want to do is make sure that our layer of that draws things
takes in a uniform coordinate system.
That is the one that we
We like and then, you know, actually does the drawing off of that and
we don't really care what happens outside of that.
Right?
So we could do that.
That would be totally fine.
I don't know whether it's worth bothering to do it.
But, yeah, we could do that.
Mostly, what will end up happening?
Is eventually, we probably will be in a why up cord system, one way or
the other?
Because I believe if we, you know, if we switch to opengl for doing
rendering later on, it's going to be y up, usually, depending on how
you set.
Things up.
But yeah.
All right, we have reached the end of the screen.
The screen that's good.
The end of the Stream So I think it is time to call it a day.
Go forth and play around or do whatever it is that you're going to do
on this on this Tuesday evening.
So, yes, thank you everyone for joining me.
It was kind of fun to get bitmaps up on the screen today.
That's a pretty big step forward for us.
I would say because it kind of means that now we can start thinking
about what our game is going to look like.
Like whereas before we really couldn't.
So basically all we have to do tomorrow to kind of round things.
Out is allow ourselves to actually use.
Basically do something intelligent with the red green blue mask so
that we can load all the images.
And then I also have to go in and do alpha blending on the Sprites.
And like I said, we're probably going to do that.
We probably will do premultiplied inverse.
This is the inverse
ocean color kind of stuff.
In inverse multiplied, color of the destination.
I don't know what you call that modulated blending, maybe but it's
premultiplied destination Alpha modulator.
I don't even know.
This is the case where I feel like Sean barie could help me out here
and tell me what the correct name is for when you have premultiplied
Alpha and a Sprite, Which we're going to have to do and then you're
going to do alpha blending where you basically do 1 minus the alpha in
the source, fright times the destination color so that you end up with
Alpha blending.
As if you had done source and death separately.
I don't even know.
I have no idea what you call that.
I don't know if it has a standard name, but basically like I trust
that if it did, he would be able to tell me, so maybe he could tell me
before next week when I'll be able to name what the actual technique
that we're doing properly.
But even if he doesn't, we will be writing it tomorrow.
So, please join me tomorrow at same time.
Same place 8:00 p.m.
Pacific Standard time, on Twitch, where I will be
Be going ahead and fixing that red green blue, Mass thing.
I'll be writing the code to make it so that we can see through.
So we may say I've layered Sprites on top of each other and that is
pretty much the end of what we will need to sort of move forwards with
our engine architecture.
So we can kind of just bake those off into a corner and, and carry on
with things.
But now we will be able to use Graphics anywhere.
We want to, which is pretty great.
So that said, if you would like to follow along at home and want to
get access to the source code or art assets to play around with
yourself, you can go
Go ahead and go to handmade here at org where you can pre-order the
game and you will get a link in your email that can download all of
those things.
It also has all the previous day's source code so you can go catch up
on old videos.
If you want to code along with me from a previous day.
You can do that as well.
There is also a patreon.
If you want to support the video series, you can subscribe there, and
there's a news and Forum site.
You can go to, which is pretty cool.
It's got all sorts of fun.
It's got the schedule.
It's got an episode guide with annotations that you can use.
It's really great.
It's better than watching them on YouTube.
For sure.
You can go to the coding resources page for those ports to Mac and
Linux and all sorts of goodies there and a code discussion forum that
you can post in if you would like to ask questions, so please go there
if you're trying to learn from the series.
It's a great place filled with good resources for you.
Thank you very much for joining me.
It has been a pleasure as always and I will see you guys tomorrow.