Alright, hello everyone, and welcome to handmade hero.
So we could have complete game live on stream on Twitch.
No engines.
Do libraries is just us here all by our Lonesome, 's programming,
some, some tasty little low level things for everyone's amusement and
today we're going to be looking a little bit more at the renderer
which is now running quite nicely.
Thanks to some optimizations but we had some stuff we want to do to it
in terms of just like cleaning up some code.
Now that
You kind of see how most of it is supposed to be working and so we
want to kind of go back and do that.
Now today is day 129, right?
And if you want to follow along at home, you want to unpack day 128
source code, if that makes sense.
So let's go ahead and get started.
If you want to follow along with me, that's the source code that you
want to be on and that is the source code that I'm loading up at the
moment.
So here we go.
Let's go ahead and lock compilation directory there.
I guess I never do.
I normally do the lock compilation, directory on stream.
I can't remember if I do or not.
So yesterday, we surprisingly got ourselves back to working exactly as
we should, which could given the number of things that I changed.
I felt like it was very unusual that that happened.
But what can I say?
We got lucky I guess and so, you know, off we go.
So what we want to do now is you can see that we've got our ground
Honks back here, right?
And we're sort of marking off where the ground chunks are.
What I'm going to do is I'm going to turn off those markers because
what we wanted to do today in terms of working on the render is get it
so that we can use the renderer for pre compositing bitmaps again,
which involves doing stuff without the perspective transform because
like to produce those ground chunks.
We don't want the perspective transformation there, right?
So let's go ahead in there and and turn off those lines.
So we can see the seam edges and I'm hoping also that the seam edges
will bring up another thing that we want to take care of in the
renderer which is pixel centers which I've sort of alluded to.
So in here I believe we have a thing that that manually says like hey
can you outline where the ground chunk is, right?
And it's like this right here.
So I'm going to go
And turn that off.
So that we don't have to see.
Any of those like yellow lines, all right.
So as you can see from this right, we no longer have seamless
rendering of our ground chunks, right?
Which is what we would expect and the reason for that is a little bit
subtle and it's you know, it's probably been a while since you thought
about this since we haven't talked about the ground chunks in a while
and so I apologize for you know, bringing it back.
But this is just something that we, you know, didn't really couldn't
address till we finished up a bunch of other things, you know?
So much stuff on our plate.
So why is this happening?
Because if you remember, we had our ground chunks, producing a nice
seamless generated texture.
Why are we getting, you know, this this pattern and the reason that
we're getting this pattern, don't forget this, by the way, it's very
important.
The reason that we're getting this pattern day 129, oops.
Is because what we used to do right is we had tiles here, right?
So here's tile a and here's tile be and they have.
But
What and what we used to do is we used to make sure that these would
have, but by always drawing all of the neighboring tiles whenever we
drew one tile.
So if we drew tale right?
We would Splat, you know, we were doing all these Splats down there to
produce the sort of the texture.
And what we would do is if there were Splats that would be in B, but
that came over to the side, right?
We would still do that Splat when we were compositing a so that it
would you know, still do the composite there, right?
And so in that way, we ensured that everything
Is continuous.
But this presupposes, something it presupposes that the coordinate
system is always the same when we're doing these things and it's just
offset by however much, you know, however, far the center's are away
from each other, right?
That was true back when we had a purely orthogonal transform, remember
there's two types of transforms.
We talked about, there's perspective and there's orthogonal and
orthogonal transforms, our ones, right where we have this sort of, you
know, concept.
That we're looking down.
You know?
We have our we have our eyeball here, right?
We're looking down on the scene in, orthogonal transform is one where
it doesn't matter how far away you are no matter how far away you are,
you always project in straight lines that are that are perpendicular
to the screen onto the screen.
So it doesn't matter how far away something is.
It's always at the same location.
It doesn't actually change its horizontal or vertical position on the
screen just by getting
They're in or closer, you know, to you when you're doing this.
So this is orthogonal transform, a perspective transform is one where
that is not true, right?
That's one that looks more more like this more like kind of a cone
shape, right?
This kind of thing.
And there when something gets further away from the eyeball, it
actually gets it actually, as it gets further away, it actually
projects to a place sort of shrunken towards the center of the screen
if you will.
So, as you as you get further away,
You move closer to the center of the screen, right?
Because things that get further away, they sort of pass out.
Remember we drew sort of this just perspective diagram a bunch of
times like this where we like, okay a point that's actually here.
Orthogonally would be projected to place here on the monitor if this
is the monitor, right?
Whereas in a perspective transform it actually gets perspective
projected here so you can see things move towards that Center Line.
And of projection, right?
And so what we're seeing now is we're seeing this problem of we didn't
take any of this into account and we were doing these prospective
transforms, all of a sudden on things and we didn't actually take into
account at all what that would do in terms of our archive you know
creation of these bitmaps here.
And you know we don't actually need to switch to an orthogonal
transform necessarily.
We could still keep a perspective transform and do it but we at least
have to be aware of what the
Is so that when we set up our rendering for these guys, we set them up
so that they would work out.
Exactly correctly to still be in the same place relative, right?
So for example, if we were going to keep it in a perspective, in a
perspective mode, when we do this displacement to say, oh where are
you know, what is the offset that we're going to use for the center
for the think place that we're looking at?
We would have to determine exactly how wide this this sort of
Captured area is and displace it by exactly that much, right?
And what we were doing is we were just placing it by the pixel size of
the bitmap, which has no relevance, right?
It doesn't mean anything.
The pixel size of the bitmap doesn't at all.
Tell us how far we would have to move from one to the other.
And so what we probably should do and I guess that this this seems
like it makes the most sense to me.
Well, we probably should do is actually just
Keep it at perspective.
But just actually talk about.
Okay, we've got a little region that we want to capture, let's make
sure that we place the camera, so that is going to capture that region
and then do the rendering right.
I think that's the more sane way to go about it.
So, yeah, that's what we're going to do.
And let's take a look here at, at the way that Phil ground chunk
situation is working, right?
So what we end up having here and, like I said, I think this will get
into some things in terms of the render that stuff that we need to
clean up if that makes sense.
So, when we go to fill the ground chunk, right?
You can see what we're doing here, we're creating a render group, we
create the buffer, you know, with the height of that, we're trying to
fill in terms of how big the ground chunk is.
And then we just kind of go through here and we don't really think
about it anymore.
We just go ahead and do you know, all the drawing that we were going
to do?
And the width and height?
Height that we actually use is the chunk demand meters.
So we actually are placing these things correctly, right?
But we are not actually doing in any particular way.
I don't think anyway is accounting for where the camera is looking at
how big, the cameras area actually is.
And in fact, if I look through here, I don't even see us actually
doing
We even where is Center.
How are we getting Center?
Center was chunk offset times with chunk offset times height.
Yeah.
So are we passing that in?
No.
Okay, so we are passing that in we're passing now.
Where is that getting?
All right, I'm confused.
Where we ever even?
Dealing with this.
I don't even know.
I am totally confused right now.
Yes.
Oh so we really just don't do anything here to try and deal with that
at.
All right.
So really we're just all we're doing is we're fully just counting
which I guess worked fine in the in the old days because that's all it
was all we're doing is counting on the width and the height there.
We're just totally counting on those which are, which are sent to the
chunk, Tim and M, we're just totally counting on those to just work,
right?
And yet we didn't actually do anything to ensure that that would
actually be the case, right?
So I don't know if you can see this but, you know, width and height
here.
Yeah, it's going to be the chunk demand M.
We're going ahead.
And we're using those but we haven't actually told the renderer that
that's how big we want.
That region to actually map to write because you remember inside the
renderer, it's making some assumptions about the size of the Monitor
and stuff and it's setting up the transform when we, you know, by
default right to work off of that.
So it's just assuming it's getting all of this stuff in here and it's
just assuming that that's going to line up properly.
But there's no actual reason to think that that will write.
There's no, these are totally separate things and they actually have
no relationship to each other.
Other, right?
So there's no reason to think that this would work in any particular
way like distance above Target here, as you change distance above
Target, whatever you happen to set it to, you're going to get totally
different results as to what the tiling offset would actually be
right.
So what we needed to do is we would need to set, we would need to set
things up, so that we're clear about how big the region is that we're
actually rendering to that's like pretty
Didn't.
And so we need to work that out, right?
That's basically what we need to do.
So we have our transform set this way at the moment.
and I guess to,
Honest, I don't really know how we want to do this, so I'll tell you
what I'm thinking about in my head, what I'm thinking about in my head
is that inside, Phil ground chunk, right in the future.
We're going to want to be able to stick things into the ground chunks
sort of at will like.
We're going to want to be able to do things like maybe put Footprints
in there when someone walks around on it or something.
You know, I mean like if you think about what's going on here, right?
Like as I move across this thing, maybe I want to write.
Nothing into that buffer, you know.
So I feel like we're going to want to be able to address ground
buffers in terms of coordinates.
That actually mean something in the real world, right?
So I think what we want to do is we want to make it so that we're
actually writing into the ground chunks, using actual real world
coordinates based off, you know, maybe the center of the chunk, right?
And so we're doing
Matt right now.
Actually to a certain extent by saying but you know we're kind of
we've kind of got that this routine written that way, right.
So I don't actually know once we switched our through traffic stop
multiplying this I don't actually think we want to say that anymore.
So if we take a look in here with and height in there, go ahead and
yeah.
So if we have the width and height in here,
And we say, you know, chunk doing m x, hm y.
Then that actually is what we want, the width of this buffer, to be.
And then when we go in and use our coordinates, we want them to be
relative to that, which it seems like, we are pretty much doing right?
The halftime of that would be would be exactly as as stated, right?
But because our coordinates are now are going to be relative to the
center anyway at this.
Point.
I feel like we no longer should really have to deal with that, right?
Oops.
Because I don't think that actually don't think that actually needs to
up.
No, that's fine.
All right, there we go.
So we do need that.
We just need that to figure out what this splatting span is
essentially.
So okay, so if we do that, right, and we are doing all of these in
regular coordinates, so,
We're splatting in World coordinates, which I think is what we want to
do then.
We want to.
We want to have some way here of.
Of telling the renderer to use that transfer, right?
And so I think I'm trying to think about if there's
I'm trying to think about what the reasoning is that I need to go
through here in order to make sure that this works properly.
So first of all Center, I don't feel like Center actually ever needs
to be taken into account now, right?
Because everything by default is going to be off of the center.
So I feel like really, when you're stamping, all you need to do is you
need to, you know, you're already going off and 0.
Oh, no.
OK.
That's fine.
That nevermind Center is just there to handle the other chunks, so
that's fine.
Yeah, that's that's as it should be because Center will be 0, 0, and
we're on the current chunk, right?
So that's all fine.
So I think, yeah.
All we really need to do is make sure that the scaling of these
matches the scale that scaling that we would be seeing if we were
looking at the ground chunk at its standard.
Like flat plane at the sort of distance above it that we that we were,
right?
And I'm trying to think about how that should work.
I'm just trying to think about whether we want to because I guess once
we have the world coordinates in here, if we change it to
orthographic, it would still be just fine.
Mmm-hmm.
Yeah, this is a bit of a Puzzler.
This is a bit of a Puzzler for me.
So I think what I'm going to do is I'm going to start by writing what
I want to be able to say here if that makes sense like I'm just going
to call the renderer effectively with sort of a you know an API call.
Basically that says here is how I want to to treat.
The transforms and then I'll go back.
Work it out in the render into some way that allows it to support both
cases, right?
So,
and I do think now that I'm thinking about it more, I do suspect that
we really do want this to be orthographic because what I want to be
able to say is just here is the, the M, the width and height in meters
of this chunk that I'm rendering.
So whenever I slap something into it, it should be exactly that,
right?
So the more I think about it, I think we really just do want to be
able to set it up for orthographic.
So, I think what I want to do, is basically say, like orthographic,
you know, something like this.
And I say that you know, the render group is orthographic and you
know, I pass, it may be something like here's the width and height.
Of the, you know, of the buffer that I'm writing to.
And then I also want to tell you the width and height, you know, of of
like in World units.
That that is.
So here's the like pixel dimensions.
And here's the world dimensions.
And then I want you to just deal with that, and make sure that I can
do everything that I want to do from there on out, right?
So, maybe something.
Nothing like this, right?
That seems like that seems like what I would, what I would prefer.
So yeah, yeah, I like that, and I'll leave that there.
So I think this is basically what we want, right?
We want to go ahead and say decide what our push buffer sizes.
Okay?
That's that's probably something that should be here, right?
Okay.
So in
Here.
Right, we're we're going ahead and we're figuring out how big we want
them to be.
We then set up the orthographic display mode, everything through here
will, now be directly in World units, which I think is what we want.
And then when we're done, we are done right?
And then what I want to do sort of symmetrically is I would like to
whenever we're doing that anywhere else, right?
Whenever we're for some other reason doing a allocate render group and
about to do a bunch of friend ring.
With it.
Then what we want to do is say the equivalent thing, right?
We want to put it into a perspective mode and, you know, past that
stuff in and that way, you know, we will allow people to freely switch
between them however, they want to, right?
And that'll be easy.
So, basically, if I come in here and I say, all right, I want to
perspective mode.
Here's the width and height in pixels of the buffer,
And then the stuff that I could pass in here, I guess would be like
this sort of information, right?
It would be
It would be this stuff, right?
So I would pass in like the focal length.
I'd pass in the distance above the Target and I'd pass in like the m 2
pixels.
M to pixels in this case,
You know, like I said that's kind of a value.
And in fact, I think maybe this is a good thing to get this out of the
renderer, right?
M, 2 pixels would just get passed in to the renderer here as part of
setting up that perspective.
So it's basically just saying, you know, here's here's the transform
that happens for m 2 pixels, which is basically what the other thing
is doing as well, right?
So they're basically always saying what they want those
World units to be.
And they just it's just part of that perspective, transform and then
this stuff would just get set directly to that, right?
So down here we'd have something that actually does these things.
So it sets that stuff like that right, monitor half dim in meters is
something that would I guess.
always have to be set essentially after, you know, whenever I'm
assuming
Whenever this stuff changed, right?
So this stuff has to be done here as well, right?
We'd have to compute pixels to M by taking the safe ratio, there of
whatever the m 2 pixels is that it's passed in.
And we'd have to do that monitor have Tim in meters as a computation.
That sort of facts, it out and I think that's roughly what we would
need to do, right?
So,
If we are to make one of these guys here, right?
Which is render group and it you basically pass in, you know, a width
and a height here in pixels.
So like pixel with pixel height and then we have a m m to pixel value,
which tells you how it should be scaled.
And then we have our focal length and our distance above Target.
There we go.
And focal length.
Yeah.
That looks reasonable.
So, I guess I'll change these to use the same name as we were doing
over here.
Although resolution pixels x is not the same thing, right?
Resolution pixels x is not really the same thing, so I don't know.
It's a little confusing.
We should have to, we should think about this a little bit, maybe
later about whether we want these values to be specified separately.
Meaning you don't always you might, you might want the 10:30 to be
different, it does matter, it's fine.
Alright, so in this case, let's see, leave the to do in here just in
case we want to think about that some more later.
So in this case once we have that perspective transform that sets up
all the things that we would need to set up there and so but you know,
we may have to change these parameters around in case we actually want
to do something else.
In case we find that orthogonal needs to be implemented slightly
differently.
So worth the graphic,
Yeah.
Render group be passing here.
Render group group pixel width.
Pixel height.
And then we just want M with and M height, right?
And so what we need to figure out here is, let's see how we want to do
this.
Oops,
pixels to meters.
We don't actually need anymore, right?
So in fact, m 2 pixels will actually be different depending on who is
using it?
Let me see.
Where m 2 pixels actually is getting used.
All right.
M 4 pixels is rejected.
There's the scale.
Yeah, so that's literally the only place that m 2 pixels is getting
used.
At all.
All right, and then pixels to meters.
So that's being used in a couple different places, right?
Yeah.
And what do we do for our reverse mapping?
For unprojected, all we do is just yeah, we just do the straight
forward.
Stuff at distance from camera.
So for unprojected we're just doing this the the straight focal length
computation.
Mmm,
So if we were going to go full 3d with this, we would change these out
to probably homogeneous and do them that way.
I'm not sure that we really want to do that.
So I'm trying to think of what the most convenient way is to allow
both of these things to flow through the pipeline as conveniently as
possible.
Obviously some of these things are trivial.
The screen center is the same in orthographic and the monitor
half-demon m is very straightforward because we're actually passing in
what we expect that to be right.
So that's also very simple but
So I guess what we could do is just say you don't actually get to to
specify that maybe they have to still, they have to be rectilinear.
Like we could just force it that way.
And then not have to introduce sort of that warping because basically
if we have both of those in there, that was the problem because it
ends up making sort of this, this warping concept if that makes sense,
which is, which is a bit of a problem.
So we could do here is say, alright, you know, we've got the pixel
within the pixel height and then the m 2 pixels and it has to actually
be exactly that because then we would not have to change anything.
Right?
Then most of the stuff just flows.
Properly and there isn't actually any any weirdness there.
So all we really have to do is think about how we want to set up
focal, length and distance above Target to make sure that things
worked properly.
In, in terms of this transform, we might have to introduce an extra
variable there, right?
So I'm going to take a look and see if that's reasonable to do over
here in phylogram chunk that when we do orthographic, you know, and we
pass, we pass that there.
I guess what I need
Would need to say here.
Is we need to say that the width equals the height, always?
Now we're not allowing it to be were pee, right?
And then the chunk dim in meters.
So if you wanted M to pixels, you would just take whatever that is,
right?
So you know the width and you divide it by however many pixels it was
and that's the m 2 pixels value, right?
So we could do that and that's always good but now we have this
problem of you know and you know I guess I can compile this and make
sure that we're
Going to work here first before I do anything, fancier, but let me go
ahead and first get everything.
Untie pode.
There we go.
Focal length, right?
So we don't know what these are are Mississippi's 21 in one allocate
Brenda group, right?
We need to get rid of the extra information getting passed here.
Like so and resolution pixels x is just this value, so that's fine.
And so I just want to make sure that we didn't break anything by
introducing that and there we go.
So, now what we have to do is we have to make sure that we have some
way of making that orthographic version work.
And so now we gotta, yeah, we got to figure out how we're going to do
that.
So here's our orthographic version.
Oops.
And what we know is we've passed in the m 2 pixels and we've passed in
sort of this this additional information here.
So, this is our m 2 pixels value.
But now, since we have,
Since we have this perspective, respect this perspective, projection
going on.
What we want to do is figure out some way that we can turn it off,
right?
So in the render group, when we do that render, we gotta change the
name of this function because it's a it has nothing to do with
entities at all anymore but you know what do you do?
So eventually we'll change the name of that function you could just
call it project and so in this function right we've got some stuff
that's happening here that we wouldn't want to do so for
Cool, what we would want to do in orthographic, right?
This is if it was orthographic, what we would want to do is say okay
the results,
Hey Liz.
You know, it's always going to be 1 point 0.
The result valid is always going to be true because it doesn't there's
there's actually no way to have things scale in any particular way,
right?
The result key is always just going to be this it's never going to
have anything else involved in it.
It's literally actually never going to do anything other than do a m,
2 pixels transform on sort of the, the actual value that gets passed
in.
So
In fact, we could just say it's this its original p x y, right?
So you can kind of see that that this is all we would do, right?
So it sort of the graphic this is all we would have to do.
It was not Arthur graphic, we need to do this other stuff, right?
And so when I'm just trying to figure out is you know, what do we at?
Yeah, what do we actually want to do?
Where is the?
Oh right, scale gets handled outside of this.
That's like, where's the scale parameter?
Right?
Doesn't matter.
So this is what we would want to do for orthographic.
And so, what that means is that the result p, as that happens we would
have to just make sure that projected X Y stays the same as original
pxy, right?
And the way that we could were calculating that at the moment is we
take whatever that raw XY was, which is this value here, right?
And we're going ahead and we're multiplying it by the focal length
over the pz distance, right?
So there's not going to be any way for us to set that so that it
doesn't.
So that it doesn't change the value.
So, in order to do this, we have to, like, at least introduce some
other nominal value that would make this work, right?
And so in order to do that, I think what I probably could do here is
say, you know,
And also I guess scale is also a problem.
Mmm-hmm I mean really, it just be the case of either introducing an if
or introducing coefficients, I think I'm just going to do the if like
I think the if is really just easier, right?
I mean it's just a question of just doing.
You know, this sort of thing.
I may just be the right thing to do for now, right, I don't know, it's
the easiest thing and when we could expand everything out to have the
extra coefficients, and we effectively we doing sort of an affine
transform.
Sorry, a homogeneous
From on it but I don't know.
It doesn't seem like we really want to do that.
Call that orthographic.
So yeah, so I don't know that that to me just I can't really think of
any reason not to do it.
So I'm just going to do it and then later, I guess we'll see if it
turns out to be a bad decision then.
Well, we'll know when we get there and it's obviously a bad decision.
So orthographic in the case of perspective is going to be false or if
the graphic in the case of orthographic unsurprisingly will be true.
And so in this case focal length and distance above targets.
We actually don't know what those would be.
I guess we could just claim that they're very large.
I suppose I don't actually know because what we want to do is make
sure that the Z clip plane stuff, doesn't clip everything.
So we may need to adjust the values to prevent clipping from being a
problem.
I don't actually know.
Oh dear, that's no good.
What did I do?
With the graphic is 40.
Whoops, That's a classic mistake there.
I had the if switched their get render entity basis, so it's actually
if orthographic, it does, this set of things here that out.
There we go.
all right, so
Now we just have to actually get everything working properly Isis.
It's clearly not.
As you can see, everything is a little tiny baby flat there, but all
we should have to do now is actually work out the specifics here and
we should be good to go.
So let's take a look.
If I go to my render group stuff here and I go to my get render entity
basis p.
So in here, and I'm doing that with graphic transform.
I want to take wherever the center the screen is, I want to multiply m
2 pixels to take whatever the X Y that comes in.
And I want to expand that out to to be a m, 2 pixels that seems right.
I don't want to scale anything, everything should be, whatever the
actual scale in meters, that it is, so that's fine.
and,
I guess this is not.
This is not correct though.
It should not.
It should not the original P, it should just be P, right?
So that's a bit of a mistake, so, yeah.
So that's fine.
I don't think that really had much to do with our problem, but that's
fine.
And so that should give us, I think what we wanted in terms of a
transform, that should be correct or studying were still wrong.
That should be the correct thing.
Okay?
So then what we need to do on the other side, and handmade SVP is we
need to go through and see what's going on here with that.
So, when we push a bitmap on here, and we're saying stamp, there's the
location for it.
I don't actually know.
Sorry.
I it's been so long.
I've forgotten what the definition of push bitmap.
Even is at this point.
So we pass it.
A height and that height is in.
M, it looks like right?
So we're passing in something.
We're splatting something down.
That's four meters.
Is that?
Is that correct?
Each ground Splat is 4 meters wide.
That seems very wide.
I don't think that makes a whole lot of sense.
Of course, are things are too small at the moment, so obviously, it
does make, it would make some sense.
But I don't think that's correct, either way.
So I feel like that actually needs to be smaller that actually needs
to be something probably proportional to the width.
I would say of these chunks, but in general, I don't know how big one
of those flat should be.
It should probably only be.
I would think it would be like a half meter or something would be
More like what the height of one of those should be?
I that would be my assumption anyway.
I feel like that, you know, on the ground, right?
It would be, you know, the Splat that seems like something a little
bit more reasonable and one of these little grass chunks, you would
think would be really pretty tiny.
So I think that's more what it should be.
Unfortunately, we still have some problems here because we're getting
some nonsensical results there but that's fine.
So if we take a look at this here,
We are still passing, m 2 pixels correctly, I believe, I just want to
make sure that we've got our scaling set up properly.
So if you look at orthographic m, 2 pixels pixels, 2 m is the inverse
of that the monitor half dim, and M is calculated correctly in that
regard.
So that's all good.
M, 2 pixels,
And that's the value that we're multiplying by, right?
So m, 2 pixels should be something relatively High.
I'm going to go ahead and step in there and make sure that there's no
funny business happening.
So I want to break in orthographic so that I can take a look at it.
So, inside orthographic, I just want to see what everything set to be.
So here we go.
Pixels to meters.
Is 42.
Which looks about, right?
That seems like a perfectly reasonable value.
Let's think about that for a second.
So what is the pixel width?
The pixel width is 256.
Presumably, the height is the same.
Oops.
Yep.
And let's see what the M wish to pixels is right.
Should be inverse of that.
Oops.
And then furthermore, I want to step out and see what the actual
ground chunk, width, and height are width and height.
So, a ground chunk is 6 meters by 6 meters, right?
So, just a ballpark that that's correct.
So, all that looks fine, that all looks fine.
Let's go ahead and step in here and see what we've got.
I'd rather do it.
I do it.
I would really rather have chunk Offset.
You know what?
I'm just going to cheat.
Don't do this at Home Folks but I wanted to see what happens in chunk
offset the one that we're actually in.
So I'm just going to full on
set the troops.
It's not what I want to do.
Just go ahead and do that in there.
There we go.
Come through here.
All right, chunk offset extra set that to zero.
And so now we should be able to compute these guys.
And Get It Center.
Offset is all zeros.
Yes.
So when we actually come through here and we compute the p-value, what
is the p-value?
The p-value is like two meters in every direction.
Which is kind of weird that happens to be exactly the same, but we'll
just pretend that we didn't that.
We're not concerned about that for now, and we'll go into push bitmap.
Off we go.
So inside pushed bitmap, what is the size?
The size is 1/8 of a meter tall and a half meter high, that seems
quite reasonable to me.
The alignment values or fine.
That's not really an issue here.
We haven't really had.
What looks like any particular problem with alignment entry P.
So that's in
Huh.
Oh right, we transform everything ahead of time now, right, right?
Right, that's totally fine, totally fine.
So, what's the scale there?
The scales 1.0, ah, that is the problem that's fine.
That was worth debugging because I hadn't been thinking it through,
quite right.
So that kind of set me, right?
So you can see, we're not actually scale II.
I didn't really pay attention to what scale was supposed to be there
when I did it.
So you can see that scale includes m, 2 pixels.
That's what makes the sizes scale out properly.
So we can't have it.
Be 1.0.
It has to be the scale value.
So that's why everything was super tiny, that makes a lot more sense.
Okay.
Of course, we're not seeing anything which is not particularly good to
say the least.
So let's go ahead and
See.
What the problem is there, but I think that that was definitely that
was that was a bit of a snafu there.
So that's glad we sort of took care of that if you will.
Okay, so, if we go back now and step again, to to that, push bitmap
call, right, let's go ahead and see well, you know what do I still
have a break?
Point set in the Phil ground buffer.
Now, I don't let me go.
Back there.
Let's go in here and I'm going to go ahead and set these guys again.
Just go ahead and overwrite values, why not?
And then when we generate these I'm going to go into push bitmap again
and I want to see what it actually does, right?
Yes, set your security cookie.
Okay, so in here when we push through, let's take a look at what we
end up getting with the entry.
Here's the size.
All zeros is not a particularly good size that seems very bad.
So what's the problem?
Height is 5.
What's the basis value?
The scale is .02 38.
09 243.
What is m 2 pixels?
Dare I ask.
Okay, that doesn't make any sense.
Because m 2 pixels was 42 before
Right.
What am I looking at?
I've obviously done something horribly wrong.
I guess.
So there's our that graphic.
Let's take a look at render group.
There's our transfer m, 2 pixels.
Oh, are we doing this backwards?
Wait a minute.
We've got these backwards.
Right.
I mean M should end up being a lot of pixels.
And we've got these like inverted.
I'm not hallucinating, right?
So pixels to meters.
Right?
If you had pixels you would it would not become 42 like a pixel is not
42 meters and if you had a meter it would not be point 0 2 pixels,
those are like backwards.
So how did we end up?
Did we just have the these two things phrased the opposite way the
entire time?
You see what I'm getting at here, right?
m, 2 pixels times, the projected x y
How is that possible?
So, did I only make that mistake in just the orthographic one?
Pixels to meters.
Right.
So I guess I must have just made it wrong here.
It's m 2 pixels.
So okay.
So that I'm just stupid stupid.
It was literally just that we were passing in pixels to M here instead
of m 2 pixels.
All right.
Fair enough.
That would explain it.
So yeah getting closer still not there yet.
I don't know if you can see there's there's still like I think kind of
obviously a couple seems in their can kind of see stuff happening.
So we're not we're not quite out of the woods yet but release getting
a little bit closer to where we should be in terms of regenerating our
ground patches.
Also, I guess maybe I was a little
Too aggressive on the size of those things, although we could just
have a Transformer on.
So I guess I'm not going to say that definitively yet so yeah.
So, I'm also not sure which ones were looking at their because we have
the I don't remember how we set up the ground chunks.
But either way, we should be able to get this back to normal.
What's interesting is that
What's interesting is that some of them seem very close whereas other
than seemed quite wrong like that seems very wrong.
This seam right here, seems like quite incorrect, whereas like this
scene here seems less incorrect, but maybe that's just happenstance.
Okay, so it seems it seems like more wrong here.
Maybe I could convince myself.
I'm just trying to it's very odd to have it be.
It should be like,
Wrong everywhere, I would think, but maybe not.
So all right, so that seems pretty reasonable.
Now that we've got the orthographic in there.
So now we just have to actually like debug it and and get it, get it
back to correct, all right.
So if we do the buffer with a knife now and now we're actually I think
passing the correct value for m 2 pixels.
I think because again, we have it, the sensor versed m, 2 pixels
should have pixels on the top M on the bottom, right, because it's
supposed to be Erasure that converts between the two in that that
direction, not the other direction.
So in here, I feel like
Shunk offset x times, the width that should actually give us what this
that actually should give us the location of the center that we are
working around.
That totally seems valid to me.
I don't see any problem with that, at all, when we're doing the Splats
in here, we're moving them around by whatever half the dimension is
and that also seems fine to me, but it seems like they're getting
Bread out a lot further than we would have expected them to be right
because we're not seeing a hundred Splats, you know what I mean?
So I'm just going to verify that.
I'm going to say here, like half dim x equals, 0.01 F, or something,
or 0.05, F, just to see what happens if we tell it to Splat in a much
more concentrated area.
Yes.
So, there's, there's like, the more concentrated Splat version, right?
Right.
I'm also going to turn on.
I think what I'd like to do here is turn back on the lines,
temporarily until we get things bleeding properly.
So that I can kind of see where the boundary actually is for stuff
because that will help me as well.
So I'm going to go turn that back on and I'm going to have this.
Clear?
Will I'm going to clear it out to two purple?
Let's say
All right, let's do this.
So that's correctly, stationed about the center.
So if I am to take the half Dimension and drop it in half again,
right, what we should see is we should see it fill about half the
space, which we do that seems about right?
I don't know.
I don't really feel like there's a hundred things there, but maybe
that's just me just pointing that out.
And so, all right, so if we go to the regular full,
Science.
You know, that that does seem to be roughly, correct?
I feel like that's, that's totally
Possible, but I just don't know that.
That's a hundred.
One, two, three, four, five, six, seven, eight, nine, ten.
I mean, I could convince myself, I could convince myself, but I don't
know.
And so yeah.
If if we're talking about a half meter, I do wonder about the sizes of
things here.
I think we may have our sizes a bit, a little bit odd, because I don't
know, maybe, maybe,
M less than I think, but I feel like making these things.
Be a whole meter long is kind of a little absurd and even then they're
still a little smaller than we probably would normally use them to be,
so I don't know.
It's like two meters is actually a very large.
So I don't know exactly what's going on there.
That's that's a little odd to me.
Yeah.
Well anyway so all right, so for take a look at that, at least I'm
fairly confident that the transform is like within the realm of
correct now.
So let's take a look at those seems though and see what's going on
with the seams.
I'm going to go ahead and
Remove our yellow outlines.
There we go.
Okay.
So yeah, I don't understand why the seams are gone.
Other they are.
I was like, they're just probably really hard to see and you can see
right there is a very clear seem right?
Probably should do something.
To sort of accentuate the seam.
I am not sure exactly what to do in that respect.
I'm guessing that probably we should just change the colors of things
vary dramatically in the ground chunks or something.
You know.
So like an example I guess I'm out of time but an example would be,
you know, maybe we have something that's like
But like takes the chunk p and does some kind of a checkerboard
pattern with it because like if you look at what the ground, buffer P
thing is right?
It's going to be one of those coordinates that we have for the world
where we got a chunk X junk.
Why chunk Z and so what I could do is I could have something that says
what that should actually be, right?
So, I could say, like, chunk X, if
X equals, you know, chunk y mod 2, or something like this, right?
Do some kind of checkerboard pattern here.
So, like, you know, color equals V 3,
sorry for will just color it like bright red for one of them and
And bright blue for another one, maybe something like this.
And then when we, when we push on the bitmap we'll just say, we would
like it to be.
Oops.
Yeah.
We'd like it to be colored in that way and I think we implemented
tinting fine to the pipeline.
We don't really test it but so I just wanted to see
What's going on there?
So yeah, you can see
well, that's a bit odd.
To be completely honest with you that's a bit odd but you can
definitely see the seam.
It's not as pronounced as I was perhaps hoping that it would be, but
you can kind of see in certain places.
Anyway, you can see the scene.
Yeah again less less pronounced than I thought, maybe that it would be
but I guess that's that's just the way it is.
So I'll have to stop now again because it's time for Q&A.
So I wanted I want to be able to go to the Q&A first but that's what
we'll have to do tomorrow is you know, fix our seams here but it's
kind of good.
We're in a position where we're, you know, everything is kind of
working relatively well other than whatever our slight error there
Is and I think that also probably were fast enough now, that if we're
in 02 mode, even though we're not multi-threading that rendering it, I
suspect that yeah.
The the pauses are really not bad, you can see that.
There's only a little bit of pause for recreating the ground chunks
there.
So, I suspect that once we actually, you know, once we actually put
that on a separate thread, our ground shrunk system should be pretty
solid because it's all
already only a very little, a very slight hiccup.
Right?
That's happening there.
So, we're getting there.
But let's go ahead and go to the the Q&A.
Let's see here.
Yeah man, it's crazy how fast this thing runs in release mode.
I just don't even know what to say.
It's going to be awesome.
I think at the end of this maybe by the end of next week, I'm hoping
will be in a place where we can have some pretty solid Graphics here
too, which will be really nice because they'll be high frame rate and
we can get rid of all that, you know, we can, we will do the sorting
and we'll do the proper layer of the ground chunks, and that'll be
pretty nice.
We'll have lighting by then, probably not.
But
Because that's a whole, that's a whole other optimization problem.
D matsuki, when do we make everything hardware-accelerated to get?
The amazing powers of rotation?
Oh, oh, I'm sorry.
I did not realize.
Somebody must not have been watching the stream, you do know that we
already have the powers of rotation, right.
Did you know that?
I don't know if you like maybe maybe you weren't with us, right?
But if we want to rotate stuff we totally can we just don't actually
have any reason to do so at the moment.
But for example, if I wanted to inside the render group here, when we
do push bitmap,
Or not push bitmap, the thing that actually renders the bitmap, I
guess I should say.
Here's our bitmap code, like draw a rectangle quickly if I wanted to I
could totally make that be something else, right?
So if I do it this way instead,
Right.
Actually, I guess I should do it this way.
Right, so if I want to, I can totally say that.
Oh yeah, our x-axis is actually.
Something totally different.
Then the normal one that would be fine.
Right?
So I can I can totally just just do that if I want to
say.
This is basically just forcing every bitmap in the game to be rotated,
right?
We
So we don't need no.
Stinking Hardware to get the power of rotation, bro.
We've got the power of rotation right here.
If for some reason we didn't feel like that was enough, you know, we
could go ahead and I don't know do something like this.
Oh man, this would do it differently on every thread.
Oh man, this will be so bizarre.
This is going to be super weird but we can do it because why not?
So yeah, Hardware, not required for rotation bro.
We implemented that.
Not turn that off now.
Go back to just using the regular x and y axis.
Will we see how to find expensive functions that are called between
frames so far?
We simply only the pixel render right now because we know.
So yeah, we will when we do the debug view stuff, we'll put in a
little bit in terms of just like a heads-up, profiler, which you can
use for that, but if you are trying to do that on a large code base,
that's not one that you know, intimately.
Then that's usually where you would use like a tool, you know, like
vtune or something.
You know, a sampling based profile.
If you like if you have no idea and you don't control the code, like
we control the code, very tightly here and handmade here at, right?
We wrote it all ourselves so you know I'll be sort of showing how we
keep an eye on things in that context.
But assuming that you know you you were in some code base that you
don't have that kind of control over.
You may need to use like some kind of sampling based profiler to help
you find stuff, right?
So
Different kinds of techniques for that and will be I'll be showing the
one you use when you're writing everything yourself.
But there's other techniques you can use if that makes sense.
Andy matsuki, there's no need to apologize.
I actually really enjoy how ridiculously fast this software renderer
ended up being, even though we didn't really even do much optimization
to it.
Like you probably could be significantly faster than it is.
And so any excuse to go oh you want rotation and scaling?
We've got.
That is good.
So by no means, do you need to apologize.
I'm very happy to show that off.
Again, because I'm still kind of totally surprised about it.
We gotta go finish off the ground chunks.
I'm glad we're working on those now, because once we kind of put those
in where, I don't even know why they're blinking right now, that
doesn't even make any sense to me.
So we have to go, you know, they've kind of been sitting in there.
Not really fully implemented for a while so I want to get rid of the
seams and get them quite everything being done correctly here on the
new render and then we can have a very nice Forest to explore which I
think will be pretty nice.
Girl and Doubloon.
Can you briefly?
Go over the rest of what we're going to do to the engine?
Before we start implementing gameplay code.
Yeah, it's mostly in our to-do list.
I think we listed most of the things that we were going to do.
So, we have to finish off the renderer, right?
Which I kind of wanted to throw a particle system in there and I kind
of want to throw in some lighting and we did a bunch of work on
lighting already.
So we kind of know roughly how that goes.
But we have some, some unknowns in there that I wanted to kind of
finish up.
Asset streaming is pretty simple.
Like, there's not a lot to it, but we have to actually go, right it
because
Right now, we just load everything at startup and I want to make sure
that we're set up to load stuff in the background.
The debug code.
Is just some very straightforward stuff that we need, but like, fonts
logging diagramming and like adjustment things, right?
Some of those things that we might want this, this stuff is just, you
know, it's probably a few weeks of work, at least, just to Dewey.
There's nothing really all that interesting about it, I guess.
Like it's kind of straightforward, but it's important to do because
you kind of want that support there, so that you can do it.
And then audio is really basic, audio will be super, simple will be
like a week or something.
Of us.
Just let me just showing like a here's how you write to an audio.
Buffer is really simple but that's basically what we have to do.
So there's there's a fair bit of work there still I would say and then
this stuff is basically game at that point like you know we kind of
got to go revisit a few things but we're basically into the game at
that point this this will all be very gained Cody and so I probably
would say that there will be this will be split up into two.
Passes.
They'll be sort of a architecture exploration pass as this is labeled
where we'll get a few things looking production-ready like it's like,
okay this is what we think.
An entity will really be doing with some animation and some
pathfinding or something you know, right?
So that we can get one guy solid and then from there we'll switch into
production where we're just kind of like now saying you know building
lots of more stuff in there, but this will be kind of fluid as we go
between
Those two, because all of these things are are kind of intimately
related.
Like, you know, we'll be working on like the entity system in here and
out there and they'll just be.
So this is this part is not really segmented.
It won't really be able to be segmented in that way.
But it'll be something like that.
Right now to get more performance out of the render, you multi-thread
it to render the screen in chunks, that is correct.
Gpus are parallel by Design.
So how did these two concepts differ?
So I'm not sure, I 100% understand the question.
but,
I mean, I can try to give you a little bit of a background on it, I
guess.
So there's two different kinds of gpus.
There's tiled and non tiled.
And non tiled ones are nothing like the kind that we have basically.
Well that's not true.
So one part of the way we do things is exactly the same as the GPU,
right?
So the part that's exactly the same is that we process a bunch of
pixels at a time, right?
Using Cindy so that's exactly the way the GPU does it, right?
So the way we're processing pixels is very similar to the way a GPU
processing was the only difference is we process for pixels like this,
right?
Whereas they usually will lose your Lee process for a pixels like this
and moreover, they're usually wider than we are.
They're usually more like a block of 16 or something, right?
Which by the way, is exactly what we would be doing if we had avx-512.
but we don't,
In fact I don't think this machine even has a VX stew Old.
So yeah, so we happen to be for wide.
So we're doing it this way, they're usually 16 wide least.
So they're they're going to be in a bigger block.
So there's that, so that part's always the same, but in terms of how
the work is distributed, actually, there's two different kinds non
tiled, do like rasterization of things in some way that has nothing to
do with regions of the screen necessarily, right?
So, those are basically talking about taking triangles and processing
the triangles, and to be honest, I don't really know much about how
they do their memory control.
I've no idea.
Like not at all tiled, architectures on.
The other hand are very similar to what we do and what they do, right?
Is they break the screen up into chunks just like we do and then they
process each chunk, you know, as kind of its own separate bin and gpus
that are tiled work, very similarly to that, they have a render, they
have a queue of things that they're trying to do pixel operations are
trying to do and, you know, multiple independent threads on that.
You may go through and operate on the different ones in parallel.
And when one's done it will retire that bin and go pick up a new bin
and that's like actually what will happen inside the GPU at eyelid
architecture review, but these are usually on mobile
And these are usually on desktop.
So, the machine, the
Vgpu in this machine, for example, is probably non tiled and probably
isn't operating exactly this way, but a mobile GPU is often tiled.
And often does look quite like this.
But I don't, I've never really worked on a GPU.
Like, I've never been involved in the hardware designer or programming
of a GPU, that was like,
A desktop GPU, a traditional just out GPU.
I worked on Larrabee, but Larrabee is very special because it was a
ray of x 64 cores.
Basically.
So you know, it's not representative of how things would work
necessarily on a regular GP or anything like that so I don't know that
initially translates but but point being you definitely have this this
sort of difference here that happens with the desktop gpus and I'm not
super familiar with how they end up breaking up the work.
If there are no better questions, wouldn't the solution to internally
link objects in an arbitrary amount of linked list be performance
problematic or is there a smart solution I'm missing here?
I'm not sure what you're referring to, but no, it's not performance.
Problematic, oh, the solution to internally link option, an arbitrary
amount of linked list.
I don't think you usually linked internally link objects in an
arbitrary number of linked list because it's not really
Possible.
You usually have to externally link objects if you want an arbitrary,
number of linked lists.
If you have a known number of linked lists, that's when you can do it
internally, that makes any sense.
I feel like the ground chunks move faster than the trees on the same
plane that may be true because I don't actually even know if the
ground chunks are being placed where the trees are like we haven't
even gotten that far yet.
So we got to go in there and clean that up.
The gaming industry is too hard to enter.
Why do potential programmers waste their time?
Hmm, I have no idea probably because they want to program games, I
don't know.
I don't really know how hard it is to enter the game industry.
I did it so many years ago that it was nothing like is today.
So
there's a lot of mug action going on.
Are you one of those coffee blooded?
Programmers, know it's actually was water in here.
I drink coffee in the morning.
I drink like one cup of coffee, basically, in the morning, pretty
regularly.
I vacuumed in studying a degree in computer science.
I love gaming and the concept of creating them is fairly interesting,
but I am not entirely mathematically inclined.
This being the case, would you suggest I stay away from game
development and steered towards my original plan of software
engineering?
I guess it depends whether you're not mathematically inclined in
general or whether you're just not good at learning math in math class
in high school because I was awful in math class at high school but I
found that that's not really a problem when you're doing programming.
If you don't like math period Then you had don't be a game programmer.
That would be a bad idea because there's a heck of a lot of math.
I have Ruby and JavaScript background, and I was wondering if you
normally do unit, testing, behavioral testing in gain woman.
Or is it just too hard because of visual elements?
Yeah, it tends to be.
I mean you can unit test some things in game development like there's
some core components like a memory allocator or things like that,
right?
You can write some unit tests for them and sometimes that's a good
idea.
If those you, if those things are complex and you can suss out some
bugs.
That way, I've definitely done some unit testing in the past of
certain core components, depending on the circumstance.
But in terms of the game itself, you can't really do unit testing very
effectively because it's so interactive.
And so visual that it's very difficult to construct unit tests that
actually like constructing unit test to actually, that would actually
find the bugs would almost be prohibitively expensive.
So what you tend to do is you tend to do more randomized testing and,
you know, that's, that's really all you can do, unfortunately,
On your site, you responded to the question.
Why are you doing this project with game for girls need to start?
Creating high-quality teaching materials for their trade?
How much progress have you made towards developing the twitch VOD s
into high-quality teaching materials, actually, I think the twitch
videos are that, that's why I'm making them.
Like I, that's what I think these are.
I think this is a good high quality, teaching material because you get
to see how someone actually does their programming.
So I wasn't saying that in the sense of like someone needs to make
something else.
I was saying, I think this is one of those things.
But I think other people will hopefully make other things as well,
right.
I'm hoping that hammy here won't be the only one of those
Do we know how many milliseconds per frame?
We have right now for game logic so far.
We push 60 frames per second, but it's hard locked and maybe we got
already some room for game logic.
Yeah, I think we probably have plenty of room for the game logic that
we're going to need for this game.
I'm not particularly concerned about that.
And the reason for that is you have to remember the the tremendous
difference in scale between the number of pixels there are on the
screen and the number of entities, there are in the game on screen at
any given time.
So if you take a look at it, right?
You can think, you know we're doing 1920 by 1080, right?
That's 2 million pixels.
And you know the number of entities on the screen is something like
100 most, right?
So you just order of magnitude wise game.
Logic is probably not going to be a huge deal and we're already set up
for background, simulation of things that are elsewhere in the world.
So hopefully that'll allow us to not worry too much about the scaling.
Well, everything need format programmatically animated or will it be
done by an artist or both?
Hopefully everything will be programmatically animated.
Do you have a YouTube channel?
Yes, you can actually find it by going to handmade hero dot-org.
And this button will will get you to the to the YouTube.
Can you show a snippet where you implemented a hash table?
I think we only used a hash, like, construct in one place so far.
Right here.
And I don't know.
This is kind of a joke which is that I said all code bases right
before they do a hash have a to do which says better hash function.
So we put one in it's almost guaranteed that we will ship with it
still saying better hash function that's like the joke.
You had to be there.
Anyway, this was the hash table.
Right?
What we do is we take the x y&z coordinates of the chunk of the world
that we're trying to Hash, we produce the hash value, we look it up
by, you know, masking out, whatever.
The, the part of the bits are that that are not actually valid for the
table.
So that we basically modded the table
and then we go through here and, and, and take a look at at the actual
values that are in there, right?
You can see that it's externally, chained.
So, in that hash, lat, we kind of keep looking through the hash, Lots
till we find the Chunk we wanted.
So it's sort of a hash table with a linked list, which is called
external chaining
If Vulcan is that by the time you Harbor start surrender, would it be
possible use Vulcan?
Yes, although I don't know if we're going to need to do Harbor,
exploration of the renderer now because we're so darn fast.
I assume we will do it, but maybe we won't even have to do it before
we ship.
Why do you think Microsoft decided to omit the 1080i resolution option
for the Xbox one?
Man?
That is way off topic not to mention the fact that I don't know
anything about what Microsoft decides their doesn't decide to do.
Do you plan on commenting?
Code before releasing the engine.
I think we will probably go through and try to document some things at
the end, just to make it easy for people to who are coming to it,
fresh to see.
But, you know, that's a real that's so far down the road that, you
know, who knows what we'll do.
I mean, that's like a year and a half from now or something.
Right?
So I the answer is, I don't know what we'll do.
Probably.
You know what truck?
Probably at least try to put headers on various things that say.
Like, this is the section that deals with blah.
It's a hash table and you store things in the world this way, you
know, and that way people will kind of know roughly what they're
looking at in any given particular place.
I don't think comments or that useful in general, unless you're trying
to describe what's happening because like, in general, like I prefer
to just have it.
Clear?
What the thing does by, you can read it, get World chunk.
It gets a real chump, right?
Like and you can see it's a hash table, there's not a whole lot.
What's the comment going to say?
You know, there's really nothing to say, but I do find it useful.
Like once you really sure that assistants done to come up here to the
top and say, let me just give you a brief overview of what's
Happening, sort of in here that tends to be the more useful kind of
comment.
So,
You know.
Robbie is just insane that we can have so many laggy games today.
When CPUs gpus are that fast, thank you for bringing some light into
the reasons for that but programming and or languages.
Yeah, I mean I say this all the time and I know that it's true but you
know, people don't, you know, I don't know.
It's just how it is like machines are incredibly incredibly fast and
especially when you know you're talking about games that are you know,
2-D game or something like that.
There's there's absolutely like no excuse for it to ever really be
Get your slow because you have so much horsepower like what's going
on, right?
And once in a while, there's nothing you can do about that because
it's Windows as being is misbehaving or the graphics card driver is
misbehaving.
That is true, and that is not the game developers fault, right?
But a lot of times it has nothing to do with that.
A lot of times the game developers just chose, they just didn't know
how either didn't know or didn't want to spend the time to write the
right thing.
And so then every gamer who plays the game has to deal with loggy
loggy choppy frame rate or, you know,
So whatever else and so I feel like it's important to try and set
those goals.
I feel like it's important to try and have some standards as game
developers where we say.
Like you know we should know that if we're on these platforms that
have enough horsepower that we should be able to deliver a good
experience like that's should be front and foremost and unfortunately
it often isn't
Because a lot of people come in with it, thinking, what's the easiest
way for me to write this thing?
Oh, I want to use like C sharp or something, right?
But just making that decision, may be means that they'll never be able
to ship the game that they had in mind without having this.
Stuff for these, you know, having to have loading screens or who knows
what else because of limitations in that thing.
And so, yeah, one of the things I try to hammer home in the Stream as
often as possible.
Just like, I think it needs to be made more of a priority when people
sit down that the number one thing that you can't let go of is good
solid performance.
And then after that, you can start to think about what is convenient
for you to do.
That's fine.
But having good solid
Remnants, as an absolute hard requirement, I think is very important
and it's not only important for your game, but it's important for the
industry as a whole.
Because if people demand that, then the tools we'll have to start
providing it.
And like if nobody used C sharp because of these problems, they would
have to go and fix it but because people use it anyway and just let
their games have these problems, you know it doesn't get fixed right?
Because they're just like it's fine.
And the answer is, we don't want that to be fine, right?
We want that to have to be fixed.
And so, it's good to have these as like things because they make a
difference.
To the Clay Center has to play the game at the end of it.
And and I feel like people Gamers deserve to be Gamers deserve to have
a fluid solid experience because the machine is capable of delivering
it and it's our job as program is to ensure that that happens first
and then make life easier for ourselves second.
Let's see there.
Any of these that are on topic
Is unsafe memory key for high performance optimizations needed for
modern day games.
I've heard, this is the key reason memory.
Safe languages like rust and Haskell won't be able to take over for
extremely low, latency applications, or drivers, but I don't know
enough about the domain.
I guess what I would say is,
I don't really know if it's true that the concept of memory.
Safety actually has to imply performance problems.
I think it's more, just the case that the language is, which currently
have memory.
Safety are inappropriate for high performance.
So, I think it's entirely possible that in the future, we will have
languages that are both
Safe and high performance.
We just haven't gotten there yet and so it's important to distinguish.
I think some of these things because
it's like for example garbage collection, I think maybe the kind of
thing which will never
can never be high performance.
But memory safety is not the same thing as a garbage collection and so
it's important to distinguish between those two like the act of a
thing, which tries to analyze pointers at runtime to free memory for
you or something is never going to be performing in my opinion.
I don't think you even ever need to explore that as an Avenue, but I
think there are ways that we maybe we might be able to construct
memory, safe languages, which do not need those things.
That are still memory safe but which do not require the kinds of
things that these other languages are requiring to operate.
And so, my suspicion is that we are simply too early on in the
development of computer, programming to see those Solutions.
And so at the moment, it appears like, memory safety and performance,
fight each other.
But I suspect that in the future, what we will actually find out is
they are actually very harmonic and that actually a language that
gives you high performance will also give you memory safety because
they actually probably go hand-in-hand.
I think it's just another level of thinking that we haven't gotten to
yet.
That's my suspicions, but we'll have to see how it shakes out in the
next two decades or so.
All right, I'm going to go ahead and down shut things down.
Let's see here.
Save
and close.
Close close.
Okay.
Why is that?
Okay, well, there we go.
Got a little selectable text there I guess.
Thank you everyone for joining me for another episode of handmade
hero.
It's been a pleasure coding with you, as always,
What can I say?
We're getting to a good place.
I think I'm pretty happy where things are going we got a little bit of
debugging to do here with our ground tiles but I'm optimistic that
pretty soon here will be at a place where we can have some nice solid
World exploration going on and that's really the whole point of making
the renderer work nicely and smoothly there.
I'm super happy with how fast the render is.
It was surprising to me how fast it is.
So I continue to be pretty thrilled about that because I think it
means we may be able to run all of handmade hero through a software.
We're renderer for the entire development cycle, which is I was
assuming was totally out of the question.
It turns out that it's not out of the question at all.
So yeah, I don't know what to say about that.
It just was a nice little surprise, thank you until for making very
fast machines.
So that said, if you would like to follow along at home and do your
own experimentation, you can always pre-order the game and it comes
with all the source code so you can download the source code every
night after I'm done and play around with it yourself.
If you would like to do that, you can go to do that and made here at
or use a little pee order button.
We also have a forum site, you can go to from there which really
you can ask questions and view an annotated episode guide which helps
to view like past episodes and there's also like ports to Mac and
Linux and stuff up there that community members have done in case
you're trying to run on other platforms before we get to them.
That's one way you can do that.
We also have a patreon page if you want to support the video series,
that's place.
You can subscribe.
And we also have a tweetbot the tweets, the schedule.
So if you're trying to follow along at home everyday, you can check
out that tweet blog because it will tell you.
When the stream is going to be
It helps to catch it.
So that's that.
Thanks everyone for joining me.
We will be back here tomorrow.
We're off Friday, but we're back tomorrow.
So tomorrow, 5:00 p.m.
Pacific Standard time.
We will be right here on Twitch.
Hope to see you all there.
Until then, please have fun programming.
Please remember, our helpful message that we included here.
Don't forget it, it's very important.
Rule number one of programming, so you got to keep that in mind.
But as long as you keep that in mind, you will have
Have I think a good programming night and I will see you back here
tomorrow.
Thanks everyone.
Take it easy.