Next speaker, of course, again like pretty much everyone at handmade
Connie's our introduction but it's kind of a unique, a bit of a unique
perspective which is that the the games that John's worked on have
obviously been ones where there's quite a bit of like design and
programming kind of coming together.
So it's there it's sort of a, I think, perhaps a little bit of a
different perspective than people who work Strickland technology, such
as myself, who don't sort of think about the design, don't sort of
think about those things.
But on handmade here, obviously we
He's tried to focus on the programming part of programming, but even
though we don't ever really get into that design stuff, if you are
going to be someone who works on programming, and who works on these
sorts things in the game industry, it's something that you really have
to be aware of because, like, a big part of whether the design works
are a big part of whether it goes, well, is whether or not that whole
sort of like overlay of programming and design works well, and does us
for thing.
So, the thing that I really wanted to talk to John about was kind of
that that sphere of what does it mean?
Mean you know to have like the the technology and the programming sort
of like conflict design and how does that process work?
All those sorts of things and I couldn't think of anyone better to
talk about it because well he's one of the best programmers.
I know and he's one of the best designers.
I know.
So let's-- Joan please give a warm welcome to mr.
Jonathan Blow.
Oh, are you on?
We got to unmute you.
Just a little switch on the top.
I think I saw the red light.
It's it's deceptive.
There's been a shortage of chocolate eating is what I'm getting at.
So, yes, I've got all of this to myself, except for whatever I leave
for Ron at the end, so which is up to you, I guess, right?
You could decide to leave it.
Nothing will find out the president.
I should have put some aside.
All right, so so first of all, let me say thank you for taking time
out of your schedule to come to this at this time because the witness
is like a month away, Randy.
Here to Saint and he's hurt.
So we have let the games ladies, both of our fault.
But thank you so much for coming.
I sort of I guess like I hope this isn't that loud actually but I
wouldn't worry about it.
I mean, it's, you know, it's part of the Fireside Chats a fireside
chat.
It's meant to be intimate.
And if you get the mic right up to like, get the little like squishy
sounds and
You say that like, it's funny but I was doing Kemp voice at various
times for over a month month and a haircut.
And when you recording stuff straight into a mic in a little room and
listening to it, it's really kind of disgusting actually like when
you're really paying attention to it professionally.
So, yeah.
All right.
Well, you can choose to be a disgusting as you want.
That's that's up to you.
That is my policy.
So let me start out by well, actually, let me start out by actually
getting the, the Mischief window back up here.
If we can
There we go, in case you want to draw, let me start out by saying, so
what I kind of wanted to talk about and it's going to be a little hard
for me because like I saying beforehand, like I have worked with you
before and I kind of know a bunch of stuff about the way you like to
approach things that's our stuff.
So I'm going to try as best I can to pretend to forget all that so
that I won't leave things out when I'm asking questions.
But I apologize if I can't do it.
I'm going to do my best.
But what I want to talk about is like if you look at sort of the
Game image working on now in the game that you did beforehand.
So if we look at braids and the witness one of the things that I think
is kind of really remarkable about those projects is that unlike most
games that I see the degree to, which the programming is customized,
to the design is like dramatic.
Like there are games where there's just a tremendous amount of actual
code that seems to go into the design if that makes sense.
I don't know if you would agree with that or not, but that's kind of
like as an external person.
It's not like oh we made a little thing that allows
To swap the gems.
And then we just made a little leveler that we place the gems and
whatever.
And like, off it goes, it's didn't look like that.
So kind of what I want to start off talking about is
How do you look at, you know, development, these days because you do a
lot of the programming you did, you do a ton of the programming on the
witness you did trying to programming on braids, almost all the
program braid?
How do you look at Development coming from it?
From that perspective of I am both the main person who is thinking
about how this game works as a game, but also I'm the person who's
doing all of the code for it.
Like this.
What does that feel?
Like, when you sit down, what do you thinking?
How does that go?
There's a, there's an analogy.
InDesign.
In the situation with design and running a team trying to get the game
done, right?
Because even braid was a small it was you know me with there's a few
people people helping out.
It wasn't all me doing everything right but there's an analogy to what
Mike was talking about at least during the object oriented or data
oriented design talk.
And possibly a little bit today, which is just right.
You have a, you have a problem, right?
And the correct mindset.
He was saying this about
The meat boy thing, the correct mindset is to do, what is required to
solve the problem, right?
And that abstractions that come in are really only useful to the
extent that they help you solve that problem in the most efficient,
expedient, whatever way, right?
So to begin with, right, the barrier between design and programming is
only an abstraction, right?
Okay, first of all it has there are certain Contours that that sort of
tends to conform to you in reality
Because if you can type code and make it work versus can't, that's a
hard that's something in reality, right?
But, but that's not really a thing that determines disciplines, unless
we decide that it does, okay?
So, what is the problem, right?
The I just said, all this is determined by what solving the problem,
the problem.
Is I want to make a certain game, right?
And when I started a game, I don't even know what the final design is,
right?
It's there's some idea and a direction to go to pursue the idea and
metric and the metric is the important part of, how good does this
have to be for me to want to ship this, right?
And not have wasted my time and fortunately with the stuff I've worked
on so far.
It becomes apparent early on that.
We're going to hit that and then it just becomes a ton of work to hit
it, right?
Okay.
Now, how do you hit it, right?
So if the problem is we want a certain game that's at a certain level
of quality and it's not just about quality as some abstract scalar but
like there's an idea behind the game that we want to do justice to,
right?
So in grade there was some stuff about time and if we didn't explore
that much about time, it wouldn't have been that interesting of a game
even if it had like
Cool platformer physics or something, right?
It wouldn't it would have failed to be about what it was trying to be
about, right?
So there's a, there's a Precision idea where there's, there's
something that you're trying to machine, right?
Like if you have a lathe, you're trying to get all the curves, exact,
right?
So the Machinery has to be sufficient to make those curves, right?
And so whatever, whatever makes that Machinery work, well and
efficiently is the right thing to do to the most part.
There's some
Of orthogonal human factors like the people who work with you hate you
and want to kill you and you know whatever.
But if you only if you're only time Horizon is the when the day of the
game ships, yeah you can simplify all that.
And so when you're sort of describing it in that in that way, you're
sort of saying that the metric is sort of this that's that's the the
game design.
I guess what you're choosing to.
Okay, the whole point I just
Guys, I failed to get to the actual point of why I was saying all that
stuff.
So your team or whoever is working on the game, is this tool, right?
And the point that I was trying to get to is when someone designs and
programs they are inherently much, much more accurate of like a
tooltip for the lathe.
Can someone designing talking to someone who programs.
Okay, you have communications barriers, right?
You have the fundamental Communications barriers between any two
people.
Then also, you have two people who think very differently about
problems, right?
That's because I'm Different disciplines and you have people with
different goals because everyone has different goals.
Now, I've been so if you're a designer right, and you tell a
programmer do this and that, and that, and that, right?
It starts to become a little bit of a resentful situation because it
is the designer, the programmers boss.
Like, why should that be, man?
I went to school and learned all this stuff and I work really hard and
this guy just says ideas of what to do in their
Stupid, like half of whom aren't going to work, right?
It's a fundamentally.
It's a little bit of a
Messed up way to set things up.
And yet that is assumed by default to be the way that you should set
them.
Upright.
And I've been the passive-aggressive programmer on the other side,
which, where it's like, oh the the instruction is too.
And you guys all know what I'm talking about by the way, right?
Where it's like, okay, program this and I'm like, I'm gonna make it a
little different than that, right?
And then and then you have an argument with the other person about why
it's not exactly what they said.
And maybe sometimes you make up a reason why it has to be the way that
you want it to be.
This is just human nature.
But but then if you're at the, if you're in charge of the whole thing
and trying to make it come out accurately, that's going to be maybe a
little messed up, because it in my position.
As the passive-aggressive programmer, who is doing the thing that I
believe was most interesting or best.
That's inherently a different idea than idea, for the whole game,
which was not my idea to, you know, and so there's
At the same time though you have to make a framework for people to
have creativity and get like if you don't let the program or make any
decisions, he's going to be very unhappy and do terrible work.
And what so you just have to make sure that everybody can make
decisions and be creative and do the best work and have this Arc where
they're getting better at everything they do.
But also, it has to all come together with great accuracy or
Precision.
People get pedantic about accuracy versus Precision.
Every time I read that
Still never remember, which is which so it seems understood in this
context.
Yes, you're like so talking about that specifically though.
You still do a tremendous amount of the game, play programming, yonsei
the witness, even though there are several programmers, who work on
that project, you you actually still do a ton of that.
And you think that is an essential part of the active design in the
game.
For the way that I design it is right, because because I don't decide
on day one or year one.
Like, here's the whole game.
Here's the design document, and now our job is to go paragraph by
paragraph.
The design document make it happen, right?
And that's a strong man because nobody really does that anymore.
But, you know, there's some interpolation knob you can dial from like
extreme waterfall.
Everything is decided in advance space shuttle or whatever and you
just have to fill it in and like
We're just winging it every day, right?
And neither one of those is very successful for game development,
right?
You have to be somewhere in the middle.
But I am a big believer.
So what interests me about design is that I'm discovering something,
right?
I have an idea about what I want to explore in designing the game and
sometimes it sounds really stupid and it's hard to communicate like
why do I want to make a game about tracing some panels, right?
Like a line, right?
That sounds completely stupid.
There's actually a very deep idea and you know because you've played
the game, right?
It's
Very interesting, what happens?
Spoiler warnings?
Well I'm not going to spoil the game two months before it comes out
but you know so there's there's something there that's being unrolled
or Unravel, you have to find it.
And at the beginning, I have the idea of what it is.
In my idea of what it is, is not even what the idea of what it is.
Will be, by the end time we get to the end, right?
It's a starting point, right?
So it's sort of so you have to be able to iterate.
It's like an iterative actual it
or solver.
It's like we have to seed it with initials, guess we know that that
initial guess is not actually the answer.
So we're going to have to go through some process try and actually now
find where the answer and like any iteration process, the speed of
iteration matters in the accuracy of iteration matter.
So if you want to get to somewhere, very refined, you had better be
able to iterate quickly, and you had better be able to understand the
results of your iteration.
To a deep degree and when that's all in one person's head, it works a
lot better.
Okay?
Right.
Because I don't have to communicate the results to myself.
I just look and I know, right?
Like when I went, you know, if I program some interaction and I go
play it and I just know.
That's like at least a week and a half of coordination and okay,
correspondence between multiple people to get that same result because
you're the results appear yet.
Give an example of why that blows out to meet people who don't know.
You're talking about sort of like the concept of I have to tell
someone I wanted to do.
Then it's not going to be quite like what I wanted or is that like,
let's send that out a little bit.
Any one of those steps is fractal, right?
Like I'm going to tell someone what I want to do.
Right?
Step one is impossible, actually, right, unless you're doing something
very wrote like unless you're close
Somebody else's game like yours Zinger.
Somebody in your just like, we're going to change the way the farmer.
Looks?
Right.
Instead of gems, we want fruit this time guys.
Yes.
You know, trying to make some R&D games which means that I'm not, you
know, pretentious art where I can write down what the theme is like.
The theme is don't throw a stone if you live in a glass house, right.
Okay.
Right.
But the theme is something that I barely have traction on, because
that's what's interesting to me, right?
If it's like, if the theme is, don't buy a bad piece of computing,
Hardware that?
Yeah, I don't know.
Some, some topics are simpler than others, right?
And if you're artistically driven, you're probably going toward
nuanced topics, okay?
And those are the things that if you could communicate it without
making a game, you wouldn't make the game because you could just write
an essay or I could record myself talking on YouTube for 10 minutes
and I would have to spend six years making a thing where you trace
panels, right?
It's much more.
Shit way of communication through.
So step, one designer explains to programmer.
What needs to happen is actually not possible, Right?
Which is then why these feedback loops get really snarled, which is
all there are some things that look extremely irrational, sometimes
that actually,
Are a result of that process being not possible like oh the designer
was saying, do this and do that and do that.
And then one day they just turned around and all that stuff that we
worked on they just threw it out.
The window.
It obviously wasn't that important, right?
Yeah.
And what it really is is sometimes things are just very intangible,
right?
And you're trying to get a certain feeling or a certain sense and the
way we do even in my own head, I might try one Tack and all
That's not really doing what I want.
So let's go over here, right?
And when you externalize that into multiple people, it starts to
become more wasteful of a process.
Which at some point then these external like lack of resources.
Lack of time limits that process and limits where you can get to in
the end and how well you can get there.
And how many people you piss off on the way and who quits your team's,
right?
Or who quits the game industry completely.
So it's, it's a very complex thing and just like with
Just like, with strictly programming the fewer people that you have
working on a program.
The better it's going to come out because there's just not as many
problems.
Yes, it's the same multi-disciplinary situation.
So, I guess taking a look at that and mapping, it kind of onto the
programming part of that to like because, you know, you have to do
this iteration, right?
And you're looking for this idea, you're like I have sort of a search
space in mind.
I have these things I want to
Lore and as I explore, I'm going to come up with new things I want to
explore and so on it just implies also just at the coding level that
there's going to be a tremendous amount of flexibility in whatever you
make.
Meaning you can't sit down and just know that I'm making, you know,
they can't be Wolfenstein 3D or something where it's like, I know that
it's this thing and we're going to make this rendering engine and it's
this.
We base, they're making sort of like a Clockwork kind of a thing,
right?
It's kind of got to be this this understanding at the very outset, I
would say
The way that the code is going to be written, has to be designed for a
lots.
And lots of fungibility, would that be a correct statement?
Yeah, so tell me a little bit about your perspective towards that and
has it changed over the years and it hasn't really changed.
I mean, so what I'm going to say here about how to program this stuff
is not even you know?
So so on the team working on the witness right now there are I'm not I
can't
Not be counted as a full-time programmer.
I maybe like a third to half a time at this point, because I'm doing
all this content stuff and whatever but then there's three full-time
programmers on the team.
So what I'm going to say is my opinion, which I communicate to people,
but the way the team works is I just let people do what they want
because it's still small enough that that can happen.
But the, the way that I work is, I type the absolute simplest thing
that will go in the right direction at a given time.
Less unless I detect while I'm typing it, as often happens like, oh,
this isn't really right.
Deleted change, right?
But like the, the way I've talked to you about this before I think,
You know, all right.
Something like okay, I
Trying to think of an example that is not a good example.
I'm going to write something that just handles the line tracing and it
needs to be efficient.
There's almost nothing you could do.
That would be inefficient, which is why it's not a good example
because computers are fast.
But, you know, I've got to do something that manages the data
structures of like what are you doing on this panel and yeah you know
because when the when the lying is going to cross over itself.
That's a very simple Collision detection problem.
But you have to do it.
Yeah.
It has to it has to be and and you may decide to weeks later because
it's early in development.
That wasn't really the kind of interaction you even wanted, right?
So you do want to spend a lot of time on this thing.
So you just write the absolute simplest thing.
And usually, what that involves is ignoring everything you learned in
school about how to program well, okay, right.
Because most of what we learn about how to program.
Well, is, is like insurance policies against bad things that will
happen.
Wait later?
Yes, some other time by another person.
And a lot of the time, of course, those things will never happen.
Yes.
So that's in those cases, it's wasted work but even when they will,
And even when I know I'm going to need to replace this thing, probably
a year from now, I don't care because a year from now I'm going to
have a better idea of what it needs to be.
Anyway, right.
So today I'm just going to make the simplest thing that I don't have
to think that much about it's kind of crappy.
It's not going to scale that well, but it is going to let me it is
going to be very modifiable.
That's the other aspect, right?
Right.
So the more you optimize something, the less you can modify it.
Yes because optimization is you know, you have a very
A general thing which is like code that you know where performance is
not a deliverable of the code, right?
Just functionality and then the more performance is a deliverable.
That's not really a thing, right?
It's performance on specific Hardware is a deliverable so then you
have all these tendrils about how it is.
The code interact with hardware and the more you optimize.
The more you just squish this Play-Doh of the program onto the Contour
of the hardware till it's like a hundred percent of it.
Yes, is all determined.
Many by your CPU architecture or whatever, right?
You don't want to go that far in that direction, if you know, you're
just going to replace something later.
Right now, the reason all this works is because it's not like we're
delivering a game on a blistering time scale.
Like if you only have time to type something once and deliver it, then
you can't do this.
But if your concern is I'm trying to make the best design, right then.
I'll program it five times.
As if I need to.
Hey, this is an attitude.
It's very different today.
But when I got into games, you know, I started my first game company
with a friend, the absolute worst time to start a game company, right?
Yeah.
It was January 1996.
Yep.
Cue test.
Came out, like, February something 1996.
If you guys remember that, we were just figuring out how to do 3D.
Yep, it was all software around.
Yep.
You know, like a handful of people in the world knew how to do this
efficiently and you decide to a network game.
Yeah.
Networks multiplayer server client.
Server drop-in Dropout.
He was amazing.
Yeah, nobody played it.
I tried to find a screenshot from that game.
Yeah, either way and failed.
I could not find it.
Okay.
There's like one that's like the sequel to it or some.
Yeah.
Well it was swindling game that we kept.
Yeah I was like but anyway anyway
Who was I talking about?
Well you got me was asking you about sort of the degree of
flexibility?
You need in the code in?
You were talking about why?
Well, you were talking about why it's possible to do it the way that
you're doing it, because it's not in the short time scale, and then
you said there's an attitude.
We didn't quite get to the attitude.
That was different.
Oh, right then than it is now so back then, you know, I started as a
programmer with some ideas about design, right?
So, I on this first game, I was right in the 3D pipeline, right?
I was writing the texture map.
Where you trying to be perspective, correct and do the fixed Point
math, and all that good stuff.
Right?
And computers, were changing fast enough, that four months later,
literally at the height of it for months later, Your Design decisions
would have been different, right?
Because they are going to be changing like a 486 66 and then like a
Pentium, something right?
It's just like what?
Yeah.
And you didn't understand 3D that.
Well, so, you know, one of the reasons this game wasn't that good is
because we
So much time, programming it, but that's because what you had to do,
you had to do that in those days to have something that runs fast.
You know?
I mean, the story about how much iteration Carmack in a Brash did on
Quake.
Yes.
Like they did at zillion things.
Yeah.
And that's what we did in those days because that's what you had to
do.
And now the attitude is different because there's this natural thing
of like oh I programmed this it just I just got it to work.
It's so precious.
I'm going to put it over here.
Okay?
And it's done and we're never going to, you know, she and it's in the
90s.
He was like, no.
The day you finish it is a day.
You start rewriting it, okay?
What?
By the time you get to version 7 of your texture map or maybe it's
okay, right?
That's kind of the same sort of a process to as with the design
process.
You're talking about where it's like, it's more of a search process
where it's like, we don't really know exactly what we're building
here.
And the only way to gather enough information to know what we are
supposed to build is to build something, sort of like it first.
Yeah.
See what happens, right?
Yeah, you got it.
You got it.
To jump in the pond before you can find things in the pond I guess,
right?
Or something, that's not exactly what I was thinking.
It's a murky pond so you can't really see.
Got a grope around.
Yeah, fish.
Get in the way.
Yeah.
Light you fish in the pond.
Yeah, okay.
Well, so moving back to, I guess, sort of the, the original part about
structure in the code for that flexibility, right?
Yeah.
So when you sit down, you're going to do the absolute simplest thing
possible.
Right?
Which I've heard you say before, as well as like kind of just a
general good mindset to be in which I totally agree with is, you know.
I don't want to overcomplicate this thing.
And so probably my first intuition, especially if you've been
programming for a while, your first intuition, on how to write it is
probably good enough for that first pass and if you try to overthink
it at that time, you don't have enough information to make a better
decision anyway.
So in general, that does seem like a good mindset but
I do feel like on a lot of projects, right, that doing that to
exclusively ends up with a thing that's just a mess and you can't
experiment and it anymore because it isn't Flex one of us.
So I feel like you actually have some, there's a skill.
There's there's a layer on top of that.
That I see you do that.
That does have to do with it.
You know, like the property ID systems and those sorts of things,
there are sorts of things that you've started to develop.
I feel like in the way that you build games that are designed to allow
you to have that mindset in the small while not
During a disaster in the large was wondering, if you could maybe share
some of that respect.
Well what you do is first, you don't have the skill and then you have
a lot of disasters, right?
You see what the pattern was of what happened, right?
And you build it.
And what it is is just
You know, I'm going to write something messy.
And first of all, when I do this, I'm visualizing.
What is the day when I'm going to swap this out for something better
if I need to and how?
Well is that going to go?
And how is that swap out going to happen, Okay?
And then, right because there's a small number of people on the code
base, at least at the team sizes I work at.
You have to know that every time you go back and interact with that
thing and you constantly reality check it, right?
So, like at some point if it starts to become a different thing than I
thought, because
You know, one day, we added this other way to query this system and
then that sort of became the main way because I grew out and became a
bulbous Apparition at some point.
You then you have to interdict and say no.
Okay, we don't any longer understand the situation and maybe it is
time to refactor this or something, right?
But so would you say that if I was to sort of restate that as a
method, it's kind of like, okay.
I'm writing this code and even the first time that I write it, I kind
of like play act in my head what if this was really important, like it
turns out that this test thing that I'm doing here.
Thing that I'm playing with on the design or whatever the code, If
This Were to become very crucial that it work quickly or do something
or, you know, that it's going to have ramifications.
Games or whatever, you're going to kind of go through that in your
head a little bit even during that first, right?
Or only right after the first, like, where does that first thing
happen when you have enough experience, you can do the first pass at
that like it's reflexive.
So just happens because know when you have the idea of what you're
about to type.
Yeah part of that idea is
Here's the life cycle of this thing about type, right?
And, and you just know,
You just you have a feel of how Harry is this thing, right?
And, and those of us who have been around a long enough to type a lot
of things, most of what we type.
Just doesn't even set off any alarm Bell, right?
I mean, almost everything that I'm going to do.
I just store some stuff in an array and iterate over the array like I
pulled some things out of here, a right.
Like, it's not that part of her grabbing is not the right.
The at some level of experience, the hard part's all come from complex
systems, right?
And interactions that were hard to predict, when you sat down right
initially.
And so, I would say the other part of what, what I'm not saying yet or
what.
Feel is lacking from what I've said yet, is that the other reason to
keep those components simple is because that later part is the
important part, and okay, you want to prep for that later part as as
well as you can.
So if you prematurely optimize, for example, the problem with
premature optimization is not only that you spent the time to
optimize, okay, right.
It is also
That after you have optimized, you've produced a piece of code that is
more brittle and has more connections to the rest of the code, right?
So if you have some graph and each piece of code is like it Circle in
the graph, right?
There's some level of connectivity of what number of things talk to
other things.
And I don't even mean via function calls.
But like, you know, this thing you know, data is set up in a certain
way.
And same day, this guy needs to know that and this guy needs to know
that there's something right.
There are constraints that
Happen and complexity the way I visualize it.
And this may not be the best way, but it's the best way that I know of
complexity is just the number of arc's in that graph, right?
So if you have n modules in N arcs, there's just all connected one by
one and it passes through that's an ideal program from Heaven, okay.
That does not exist in reality but is very simple because we can just
modify the front and back half of any piece of code and the Ark.
Now can be whatever we want because yeah, and the point is let's draw
this.
This your mind.
Yeah.
So this is you know this is like an amazing simple piece of code right
now.
The thing is, you know, if this is I don't even know what this is
like.
This is some user interface, right?
And this is like simulation.
I render this program is so simple.
With no point.
Putting these because already this is wrong because, right?
Your UI cares about rendering so, but you know what happens, a real
program, right?
Is something more like this, where you got a bunch of things and just
start drawing these all day, right?
Because these these just go forever, right?
Yeah.
So
Complexity management of software is about reducing the number of
arc's because actually the arcs are way harder to think in school you
usually, you know, you usually think about the circles because that's
what they teach you to think about.
Like, oh, this is an object and it has these policies and everything.
If everything could be inside this object and that would be totally
fine.
But that's not reality, right?
In fact, most of what you care about is actually in these arcs that
I'm just messing up by drawing arrows, to the arcs, almost always
determined things even at the optimization stage like
Foreman's.
It's almost always about the arcs and not so much about what goes on
in Academia.
The arcs are called cross-cutting concerns, which makes him sound like
just one little extra thing you should think about sometimes.
Actually, it's almost everything that you care about especially and
the more optimized your program is the more of these that you have
right.
And even so you know the number of arc's that you can draw between n
circles is O of N squared.
Yeah so we completely optimized program
Is O of N squared and gives you N squared.
More things to think about, whereas the perfect beautiful program that
doesn't exist is n, right?
N squared is a lot bigger than n as n grows.
Yes.
So part of what's happening is keep N squared.
Small?
It's just like optimizing runtime.
Yeah, right.
But you're optimizing.
How many things I have to think about?
However, right.
I mean, I've said all this, you know,
Like optimizing code makes the code more complex and create these
problems.
But we also have to optimize the code, right?
So there's a very intelligent trade-offs that have to be made about
what deserves complexity and what does not and you should be able to
justify those by mapping them all the way.
Again, if we're talking about some lathes with extreme, accuracy by
justifying it, by mapping it all the way to that final shape, that
you're trying to cut, okay?
Like,
Hey, this piece of the curves going to wobble a little bit.
If this thing isn't running at 60 frames as whatever, right?
So in some sense you might say that when you in your head like you're
thinking about this system and you're like what do we actually need to
think about in terms of its complexity or how it's going to be
designed or whatever?
You're actually in your head thinking about the end state of that the
game itself and what its design needs.
How critical is this thing?
This doesn't erase it should erase their, yeah.
Yes.
Now and of course that's always just a heuristic, right?
Because you never, you never quite a future.
And so, would you say that that's true on, you know, that could say
well I just I just wanted to if anyone like Zips to the middle of the
recording or something, I want them to at least have some idea of what
the picture is.
And that picture was completely dominated by this line, it's perfect.
Now, it's a totally
yeah.
it's
self-explanatory.
Yeah, everything else as well.
So really, I guess, let's see 35.
So really, we can just take the next 30 minutes off because if
everyone just looks at that diagram for long enough, they'll get the
rest of it.
Pretty much by by osmosis.
Yeah, by diffusion.
So, okay, taking that a little more concretely.
So your structure at the outset when you're talking about something
like this, right?
I mean, I'm going to explore, you know, I'm putting myself in your
Shoes here.
Yeah, I have some I'd design ideas that I've started out with and
we've already said that, I have to iterate on these design ideas quite
a bit potentially to get to, you know, depending on what the game is
to get to the final place where I'm actually comfortable that we got
it.
Like, it's like, okay, we got to the place.
I actually wanted to get to.
So I have to do a bunch of iterations and these iterations obviously
are going to, first of all, involve creating new nodes to this graph,
right?
I'm adding New pieces of code and also obviously new arcs to the graph
as those go, right?
Yeah.
So, I guess what I would say is,
I'm approaching each individual node that I add.
I'm approaching each one of those as here is a piece of code that I'm
going to try and write as simply as possible.
And I'm not going to try and overcomplicated just whatever gets the
job done in this engine, right.
But then there's a separate part which is that all of the inputs into
that like whatever has however it has to get the stuff that it needs,
which in a game like for example the witness is actually extremely
complicated.
There's so many things that it might be wanting to know about, you
know, as far as like what it needs to do to actually test this part of
the design.
What's your thought process?
Like for keeping that I want to say superstructure in place, right?
Because that's sort of the policy or like the services that are
servicing the arcs between these things.
Like, you know, there's a bunch of things.
Like the thing I mentioned the other day to you which is like it's
pretty impressive that over the entire development, the witness you
could almost always still load a save game, right?
Like, tell me a little bit about that sort of background of how that
works and are there things in particular, that you've learned over the
years there like having systems work, this
Way tends to make it much easier for me to do the small pieces in a
way that doesn't start screwing with the whole system, right?
Well, the you know, the reason the reason we can load a save game
specifically so I'm not sure that I understand really the question at
a general level, so we might have to iterate for a little bit, but the
save game time specifically.
All right,
That is just the same system that I had in braids, which I had
arrived, just through experience, right?
Like,
You need to serialize your stuff, you need that to be robust and good
and pretty fast.
And you need it to be flexible, right?
Although I don't get carried away with flexibility.
So for it, we actually just had this conversation in the office.
The other day we are not forward compatible, right?
Okay.
So you have an old executor if you have a new execute old executable
in a new save game, right?
We crash right now voting.
That which is fine, but we want to do.
About that for release, probably cuz you never know what's going to
happen to have in the wild, I mean, on a console, it's probably fine,
but I'm PC.
But again, that's relatively easy to add, right?
But the main concern is backward, right?
Like you want people, you know, we push, we push updates on Steam all
the time and to the greatest extent possible.
We want people to just get the update and playwright with whatever
savegame and
That's worked ever since our first build went on Steam, which is
several years.
At this point, the main thing that breaks it is content, right?
Like we push content that
Right, you change where you were in.
The prison has been standing on the thing that you move your.
Yeah, that's obviously not going to work but I mean in general, if the
game could be playable, usually was yeah, my experience.
So but that was just again, you know, having enough problems and
having to solve them, seriously enough that at some point you just
arrive at an opinion of what's the best way to program?
It's the same reason I don't use list now, right?
Okay, team, right.
It's what I want of the things.
I was taught in college, was how cool scheme is, okay?
For all.
The reasons that now I do not care about because I have evaluated them
in the context of The Wider world and discovered that I don't care
that I can use a redevelop print Loop because that's a very primitive
thing that almost never gives me useful information, okay?
Or I don't care that the syntax is all parentheses in that.
That's beautiful from subjecting, right?
So in that same way, you know, there's there's just problems.
That you have when making game and one of them is serializing and
whatever right?
And once you have her down those problems so well that like there may
still be issues but they're Epsilon compared to all these other issues
that you have you just consider that solved and you don't need to
worry about it unless you someday come up with a design that
challenges those assumptions.
But I think the more experienced we get the more that that happens.
So when I started in games,
Nobody knew what a quaternion was right.
It was a while before we saw that and then and then there were debates
about whether that was the right way to do things.
Right?
And now usually people like a quaternion is I think now this default
thing yeah there's reasons why you don't want to use one for specific
cases but in general it's solved.
Yeah.
So serialization I feel like is most
Solved, apart from issues of how the hell you interface with the
programming language and stuff.
Because write C++ is terrible for it.
Very tear.
So you have to make a decision.
Like, do I
Do I do something where I pre-process header files right and pull the
data and then do that or do I just force you to do extra work?
Every time you declare thing, I went for option, b force you to do
extra work because I had terrible experiences with option.
A when I was a contractor in The Wider world, like I did a summer at
Sun Microsystems messing around and like they're gooey thing was
I'm forgetting the name now but the sun they used it'll like a version
of it'll look like a priest.
Like answer that you would you would generate a thing and it would be
okay.
It was an annoying, build step, and then you'd get a header file full
of integer, IDs that would change every time, okay?
Right.
So that was, they didn't even solves it was a shit, right?
It just, it was annoying.
And I like,
I like knowing what's happening and I like keeping the core of stuff
simple and just my experiences with that were bad enough.
Yeah.
But you decided not to that.
You wanted to be more manual just because of that.
Yeah, I also had some bad experiences with some
There's like this language informix 4gl.
I don't know if anyone in the audience this is but he was like a
language that people would paste on top of SQL.
Okay?
To like, try to add value and in reality, it would like to pre-process
down to SQL, commands, that we're not really checked in the right way.
So okay, then you get an SQL error and you have to like map it to your
source code.
So genetically in me I hate that stuff.
Okay, I've had so many problems.
So you want some?
So yeah.
We're is too much detail and something that doesn't warrant that much
detail.
But well, I actually so I have a follow-up on that that even from
that, which is that.
So in general would you say that you start out with certain ad hoc
code for these things?
Like I'm going to write down and write the simplest possible thing
certain core systems.
Stay around long enough through multiple projects that it's just like,
they get refined to a point where now they're no longer kind of a
question in this.
Like in your node graph, for example, where it's just we big those
down to, like, we can rely on.
This is how this should probably go and everyone else can just assume
that.
That's the way that's going to go kind of a thing.
And you've got a point now on it or is it is like, know it's hard in
the systems are the system's sort of in some sense, conceptually a
little different now because they've gotten to a certain point of
maturity.
Or is it still always kind of the same attitude where it's like now
it's just another piece and well so in this particular case of the
witness
It was not even a question for example, again with entity State,
because I went from a game with a relatively challenging problem
statement around NBC, right?
It was about rewinding time and having it be perfect and being able to
go forward and backward in time.
So,
You know, there's a very robust serialization deserialization system
to go from that to what games, more typically want to do, which is
just like, I've got a level with some stuff course, it's an open world
level, so that was an ambitious part.
We have about 70,000 entities in our world, which is big for an indie
game.
Yeah, it's not really big for AAA game but those are all live at once.
So the, you know,
70,000 live entities, but that's not 70,000, is not a scary number for
a modern computer, right?
As long as you do something that is roughly constant, her thing,
you're fine.
Yeah, at that level unless you're the Windows File system and you put
70,000 files in one folder which we then had to do terrible things to
work around.
Yeah, well there's a directory perverse.
Only have 100 subfolders so he's not making this up.
This is actually a thing that actually happened.
So every every entity has a new
Clydie, right?
These days are about 6 digits and
Let me tell this whole story because mmm.
Yeah, right.
You think like, oh my God, how do you do multi-user collaboration?
It's such a hard problem because we're building this open world
environment, right?
And everybody's editing the world at once.
You can't really lock part of the world.
Just people do everybody changes things, right?
And like, how do you think that that's like, a really wicked problem
and all the way you think it is?
All your energies are very easy to read, text files and everyone's a
separate file, and you just check it into some version.
And it works fine.
And you don't, you don't do the one or two things that will break
that.
Like, the one thing that will break it is like you have a group of a
group of entities and people are adding and removing things from that
group all the time.
Yeah.
And you could make a source control system that understood the
semantics of oh, the order of things in this array, don't matter, but
in reality.
Yeah.
So instead, when we store things in groups, you have my energy stores,
the group I'm in, and then we reconstitute that reload time.
I think that's very fast.
Right?
But anyway, so every entity is a text file.
So we have 70,000 text files and Ignacio, just needed to speed it up.
So, he was like, well, what if we make 100 subfolders by the last two
digits of the entity ID and then that's where you go to find what was
the slow part.
So, you know, you you sort of approach this problem in very much
exactly the way that you're saying.
Which is that like you just said what's the simplest thing that would
possibly work.
Yeah, if we want to edit a whole world, it's built out of entities.
Let's just make a different file forever and that's exactly what's
good.
Solve the conflicts as we know that it can merge text files.
Yeah, right.
Yeah.
And so, and then we ran into and the simplest version of the system
was like the simplest version of what you just said.
And then we ran into problems with the group thing and like one or two
other things.
And then it started getting slow once there was a lot of content,
right?
And what got slow was it subversion?
Just Windows barfs.
When you get over a certain number of files, a full, what happened?
Just around 11,000, when you go, where they can't like, open in them,
or
I don't know, I don't know how the file system is set up.
So what I mean what did you see happening?
Well it's not a it's not a UI level thing.
But yes, even when we would boot, right to start to read the files,
you know, we use what's the freaking API, right?
So like if you didn't create file or something like that, you know.
Yeah, the find first file.
Find next file regular that starts taking a really long time.
Okay.
So just iterating over the files that are actually Windows like at
11,000.
That's too many just starts going on.
Nobody should have that many files in a directory so we're just not
going to.
Yeah.
Okay.
All right.
So then you Bree had to break it up into separate directories and then
iterate the directories.
So you're basically just creating your own tree, which is what NT in
theory should have probably doing, but yes, okay,
All right, so that's actually worked remarkably well to I guess I
hadn't thought about that but the fact that you can open world edit
the witness and everyone can have the same time, they carry since
mean, it's insane.
And it's just a bunch of text files.
Yeah.
Well, in case anyone is wondering, whether the attitude of do the
simplest thing works.
It's pretty good.
Yeah.
I should have thought of that.
Glad We Came Upon it.
I mean, there was that's not the only thing.
There's a bunch of things like that.
Like, the only reason that we are able to make a game.
It's so games taken us a long time to make but it is a really big,
really complicated game.
There's like a lot of stuff in it and we're a very small team.
We've got testers now.
So I think we have eight people including testers various
Swim in the dog and the dog.
Yes.
09 team of nine, one of them only eats cupcakes in ever gets in.
Yeah, bad hire but good for morale.
so,
You know, you have to like being able to build systems to let you make
a game is a luxury, right?
Yeah.
Sort of it's necessary to a point and then it's a luxury and we
straddle that line all the time and you know I'm not always going to
claim in the best way, you just have to allocate your effort, right?
Just like with anything, right?
So there's something stupid in the game right now that we just have
never fixed right?
We do we're very focused on iteration.
People have talked about
Irrigation is important and we do that.
You know, you can the game will just like Hot Load textures and all
that.
So you just change the text in Photoshop, you see it on the screen,
our editor, and the game, or the same program.
So you just hit f11, you're ruining the editor, which is a separate
copy of the world, where you move stuff around.
Hit.
Save you press f11 again and all the stuff is moved.
Right.
There's like literally zero iteration time apart from inconveniences
involved in how long it takes a start-up which is like probably 45
seconds or something.
It's that's more.
Yes this side.
I'd of tolerable.
Yeah, but you know, there's things that are kind of terrible.
So for example, if you're working on an animated entity with a lot of
Bones and you change it, a lot, the game kind of crashes sometimes,
because it hot loaded something with like a different number of bones
and
Match something it didn't something didn't get cleared and it probably
would take a day or less to fix but we just got too much to do and we
don't edit animated things that much just like me just like sorry your
game is going to crash today is in we just bear it, right?
So there's there's always trade-offs there.
So, I guess, one thing that I kind of wanted to get at with the sort
of iterative model of how you're developing things and the systems and
that sort of stuff is just I guess if you are, if you're working with
other people who aren't necessarily iterating on the design, right?
Because you've got programmers who are working on doing stuff like
making sure the rendering works and that sort of stuff.
How do you sort of manage that part of the process?
Where you're trying to iterate on design?
And other people are trying to build these other systems and you're
kind of running in parallel because you've had now multiple years
where actually, you have been adding stuff to the design.
Like the design did not stop three years ago and then people have just
been programmers, something you still had stuff, we have in some
stuff.
Two weeks ago.
Yeah.
So having that like like, can you talk a little bit about?
Is there anything in particular to say about this concept of like,
okay?
How do we make sure that these other people who are trying to do their
job of making, like the rendering fast or something?
And I'm still trying to like change maybe have some of these puzzles
work a little bit and I'm implementing some slightly new things
code-wise in there.
How does that?
How does that work out?
You have what?
Like have a lot of interaction or you try to structure in the code so
that they don't, you have to have a lot of interaction in the
beginning so that everybody
Stands with the hell we're doing, okay?
And that's much easier to do with people who are actually on the team
is full time.
People is much harder.
You know, we're talking about this in the context of programming, but
there are other things that have functional effects on the design.
For example, were working with architects who professional architects
who designed buildings and like they'll design some buildings for the
game but what they design.
Is what you play and stay, don't understand game design.
So, there had to be some very complicated conversations, they're
right.
And then, because they don't work for you, they're gone.
And all that effort was wasted.
At some point, is very high effort to result ratio, whereas someone
who's a programmer, the team, it's a much lower effort to result ratio
because they're sticking around.
Hopefully, for at least a while, and they get it, right?
And then also on my side because I understand,
Programming generally.
I don't even know what decision Ignacio made on the renderer this
week, right?
But I know how renderers work.
Okay.
So like I know preemptively, if I'm going to do something, that is
probably maybe going to be slow, and then we can have that
conversation knowing that you may need to have a conversation is much
better than just like I did something and it breaks is my audio
dropping out.
It keeps, I think it's okay, it's a little echo.
My ears are dropping out.
I'm getting old well, one thing so,
So I guess along those lines.
Would you say that it's important?
For somebody who's going to design a very ambitious game like the
witness or something that would you say that the the programmer
designer who's doing that sort of lead work that you're doing there?
Is it kind of important for them to have an understanding of all of
the systems that in some sense?
Meaning the fact that you've worked on all of those yourself in the
past, right?
Yeah.
Has that been critical meaning?
Do you think that it would have been you know you know significantly
worse if you didn't know how a render worked with that, opposed really
difficult.
It challenges for you.
Yes, at many levels.
So it would have made the game a lot harder to make.
Okay?
Right.
So again, similarly did Mike's comment like you should go read the
manual for the CPU, you're using like the engine is the manual for the
design that you're shipping, okay?
Right because how is that design ever going to happen if the engine
doesn't but you can only do what the engine and we're bordering on
spoilers, right?
But and we won't go purely into spoiler territory.
But
but,
Like a third of the design of the witness.
Just what the ideas wouldn't have happened.
If I didn't know how to program 3D Graphics, right?
Okay.
Like if I didn't know, okay, how RGB color were right?
Yeah.
Specularity and whatever, right?
Like that.
Yes.
So that's what we would have had a much worse game, right?
And actually, the same thing happened on braid on great.
It's like,
The first, like, really interesting thing in the design is how you
have some entities in the world that don't get rewound anymore, right?
They sparkle green and you rewind some things and it takes them out of
sync with others.
Yes.
And the origin of that idea was just because I was making the rewind
and that function, like I said, everything is iterate over an array
and do stuff on this function, was iterate over this array.
And look up the old state of the sanity from this other Heap and copy
this Fields.
Yeah, and you was looking at that and your
Like oh, I could skip some things.
Yeah, that's the whole game design is like I could skip some things in
this array.
Yeah.
And there you go.
And that's a, that's a programmer idea.
It's not really, I mean I designer could come to that same thing but
it would be a very different route and I don't know if I would have
come to it by that route and I suppose some of the things to where
you're like, the example of the world, where your x coordinate in the
world equals time, it's kind of a very natural thing that you might
arrive at as a programmer, which would be
much harder.
If you're just kind of sitting back there thinking about it,
abstractly, you may never get.
If you come at game design, like I want to make a metaphor for ya
time.
Being tied to my emotional state or something end up with something
that sucks, right?
I mean that's usually what happened.
I'm not, I mean, games are designed that way.
You can feel it when there's nothing that way.
Right.
You get something different.
Yeah, I'm not trying to say that you can't design games.
That way you can you just
Put a great deal of effort into solving the problems.
There's different problems, right?
It's like when you make a program, that's an equation versus a
program, that's if statements.
Okay.
It's very different in nature.
If statements kind of suck, but you can make some very good things
with them.
You just have to put in a lot of work to make sure there's continuity
between all the cases.
Yeah, whatever, right.
It's like that.
So I think we are writing very talkative.
I feel like I haven't said a thing.
I think we've got, I think we got about 20 more minutes of sleep on
the clock.
So we have, we have
We can go through a couple more things there is to it.
So that's actually kind of, I'm going to ask a question about that
even though this was totally not something that I had thought of
asking it all before, but that's kind of an interesting metaphor.
So you're talking when you said the, the S statement versus the, the
equation there, it's really talk about things like well, if I have a
single equation, I know that this thing is continuous and you're
saying if I'm making a bunch of if statements to sort of model,
something that I expected a continuous, I have to make sure that each
of these cases, when you would be transition from one to the other,
you will line up exactly with her.
Yes, why
You, why did you reach for that?
Like like why did you go with that analogy?
Just then I was a little thrown by it.
What was I talking about?
Were talking about the design of something being not programmer
oriented, right?
Oh, because so the way that I do design and I think that there's a
small school of game design is a number of people who do things this
way.
Small number, a small number that I know of okay, and it's about, you
know, we're building a system, it says the software is
I've system that has some Dynamics.
Yeah and you're exploring what the Dynamics are of those systems and I
try to turn some way that minimizes feedback and so you can you can
pilot where you're going in terms of that exploration.
But fundamentally, you're exploring things that are there, okay?
Versus
I'm telling the computer what to do, okay.
And in this moment, you know, the princess steals a car and driver
seat of drives to somewhere and something I don't know, okay.
The point of that is totally arbitrary idea that you then need to
force the computer to do.
It's a different.
It's going in different directions is Daniel been drug recalls this
top-down versus bottom-up, but I don't say
Because I think top-down versus bottom-up is very overloaded in a lot
of other ways of thinking about different things, right?
But it's similar, if you want to think about it, is top-down versus
bottom-up.
You can.
And I do, I don't do just bottom up, right?
I do, bi-directional.
Yeah, but there's a whole lot of bottom up, and if you start fighting
what starts coming, bottom up, you get something that sucks.
So, basically, when you come at something from a top-down perspective,
when you come at something, not one of the people who strictly does
that.
Yeah,
You're sort of looking at that as more I'm coming at it from a
top-down perspective and to make that a little more concrete for whom
you are.
I think about it that would be like I have this idea for this exact
thing.
The player might do in the witness.
Versus here are some rules in the witness that might create puzzles.
That would be like top-down versus bottom-up.
Might be a reasonable way to say that or do you want to do?
Want to have a more specific way?
Well, the rules had to come from somewhere.
Yeah.
And that's really the bottom up as where they come from, so even lower
than that.
Yeah, like, okay.
You know, I've got this line that I could draw.
Yeah.
And what, like, what are the properties of that?
It's, you would think there's almost none, but there actually are some
Some right?
Is there?
Do you limit the length of it?
Is that, is that a dynamic, right?
Right.
Is it, can it cross itself, right?
And those at first blush sound like arbitrary rules, but they come
from a certain investigation of what are the parameters that play in
this very constrained idea, space.
And if I'm to be highly competent about exploring the small space,
what do I do with those parameters?
Right?
Versus like a top-down thing would be like,
You know, when I draw the line the alien spacecraft compute its heat
ray in that direction.
Yeah, and then I can burn a tree because that trees burning, I'll be
able to read the book that's baked into concrete next to the tree or
something, right?
It's an infocom game.
Yeah, infocom wasn't the worst at that.
I would we all know who so sorry I meant to say it's a Sierra game.
So I guess then I can go back with that in mind and ask the question I
was going to ask before which is so you're sort of saying that the
top-down approach when you do employ, it is more about giving you some
more ideas about what to investigate to create the bottom up things in
some sense, right?
So like I come at it, I said like, oh, I wanted to do the thing where
the alien spaceship shoots, The Burning Tree and lights up the book
because I feel like that will tell me like that will generate more
sort of like systemic rules that I can.
And then use to create the problem with that example, is it's to
systemic because light actually Shines on the book, right?
Right.
You would need something where like when there was a prophecy about
the Burning Tree and then the old man comes running out of the Hut and
and then you steal his Cane because you needed the cane to prop open
the door.
Exactly.
That's the new example, okay, because there's nothing systemic there
at.
I'm not going to remember that, but well for it's a record.
But for me, I need to remember it right now.
We can't review the record when I'm going to ask
Oh shit.
For the original example, though, the light is the example of the
bottom-up thing coming from the top down it.
So if you're going to do it, right?
Yeah, you're coming in at top down and you're saying, oh like this is
a situation, I'm going to explore, what would be the but like what are
the systems?
I have to program to make this actually occur and then you get to the
party.
Like oh maybe light shining to illuminate things is part of my game
rule set is that more of a way that would make sense like right?
And then you have to decide how important of a part is it.
Yeah.
And urea
Set from time to time.
Is my game really about this or not?
Am I is my game design like an amoeba kind of absorbing this idea and
in growing to support it.
Yeah, that's a good thing to do to an extent, but then at some point
you got too many things, right?
Yeah.
The thing other thing I was going to say, is the top down also.
So it does two things.
One is, it gives you a starting point, right?
You have to start somewhere.
Yes.
And you could start purely bottom-up, but I have never done that.
Okay?
So, purely bottom-up as an example would be, you're literally just
sort of starting to make like a physics.
Sandbox, would be example of a bottom-up think.
I'm just gonna start making some simulations, and I don't really have
an idea of that, like, or is that not?
You had the idea to explore a physics sandbox.
Okay, but real bottom-up would have to be, like, I was working at some
other job someday.
And my program did something.
And I quit that job because I thought that was interesting, and okay,
right?
Like pure bottom up is very, very hard to find, okay?
I literally had no conception of what
Going to happen.
It just happened?
Yeah.
All right.
But so then the other thing is top-down guides you because you're
trying to go somewhere that has some human interest to it.
If you purely there's a paradox, right?
Because you have to be very interested in systems and what happens
with systems and
You know, you have to be able to observe and take joy in what's
happening with your system and then make your design.
Be able to show that to people and take joy in it and communicate that
at the same time, if you find every system, interesting, that's going
to be really boring to almost everybody in the world.
Right.
Okay.
Because you have to have some sort of a criteria for what?
Makes a system generally?
Interesting.
Yeah.
Someone who's not a systems programmer or something, I don't know.
Right?
But again, that's also if you put too much,
That in, that's what makes the game bad.
So, so fine.
It's a little pinch of salt.
So I guess, let's see how much time we got now.
Okay, so we're just about to wrap up, I guess.
So, would you say in general, like when you sit down to do design work
on a game quote unquote, is that really something?
Is that really the way you think about it in your head?
Or is it more?
Just like I sit down to work on the game and whether I'm programming
or designing in quotes or whatever are not really
Separated activities or do you feel like there's definite like here RN
modes that I'm in and I switch between those mode.
Like, what's the kind of like mental model that you have?
Because since you are doing lots of different activities and like like
the other day, I saw you take a walk.
I'm gonna take a walk because I have to think about some game stuff.
Yeah.
So what does that mental for me?
There are and modes, and they're not.
Again there was no very solid barrier between them, but there's a
Continuum and so
Ying is toward one end of the spectrum once you're experienced right?
Which is when your experience,
Want to make a game happen again.
You, you know, how to type a reasonable approximation to the answer to
almost any problem that you're really going to have, okay?
You don't have to sit down and figure out the architecture of how I'm
going to, I don't know.
Let's take something like, how, I'm how am I going to do Collision
detection in this game?
At least to a first approximation?
You don't need to spend a week.
It's like I don't really care.
Like, if I was writing it from scratch, you would just be like okay
top level.
There's going to be a quadtree or Grid or something.
Right?
And then you do a query for who's nearby, and then you do some kind of
triangle triangle and maybe later, you insert more, accelerants in
there, whatever.
It's not.
Who cares?
I can write something, it will work until it needs modification,
right?
And that's mostly the experience talking there where it's like, I know
what these systems are look like.
So, I know I can just sort of fudge one in temperature and and that is
99.9% of programming time and okay, some point.
Okay.
Part of that is again because our languages and tools are not that
good if with really good languages and tools, we could maybe knock a
half a 9 so we could get it down to 99.5.
Our is that your goal with Jay?
I may be okay, but 9:30, we're j.i.
has half a knife and abilities.
Yeah, but, you know, I that's just a thing.
Like experienced programmers can make stuff happen and then even, you
know, even if your
Amaizing.
You're not working most of the time so it's a two-step thing.
See, what's happening?
Yep.
And then usually, what's happening these days is like I'm missing the
cash all the time and you just know how to approach that, okay?
So maybe the details of how you approach it vary a little bit but you
don't, you don't have to, I don't know.
The more of a serious of an optimization it is.
Then the more you have to go figure it out, right?
Yeah.
So that's why there's a Continuum right now.
On the design side.
I don't want to be doing that is design, right?
I don't want to make a MOBA that suggests like Dota 2.
But you know, I don't like the way razors thing goes out and then
comes right back in.
I wanted to stay out for a while, whatever, ambitious design, ya know
which is just to say that in design.
If your
The reason we repeat ourselves conceptually in programming is because
we have to because code reuse is not really as much of a thing as we
wish it was.
If code reuse actually worked, the way it was supposed to.
We would always be solving bigger and ever bigger, more ambitious
problems, and our knowledge from the past would not apply so.
Well right instead, it applies tremendously well, right with design, I
try to make things at least that are new and that my understanding of
a designer does not kick out an answer.
Answer to everything immediately.
Yeah.
If it does, it bothers me and it makes me think like, oh, I'm not
working that hard.
So it's kind of very different from the programming side.
And so what has to happen, right?
Is the magical thing where you're in a shower or in bed, you wake up
the next day and you just have the idea.
The magical shower.
Yes, you're in the magical shower, that sprinkles know or or just, you
know, or I've been designing for a while and I'm stuck on something
and I go program for two weeks and then I come back and I know the
answer, right?
So there's there's this very subconscious processing.
If you're going to take that model,
Of things.
I don't.
If you look at ideas of what the brain is all through history, it's
always analogous to the most technologically sophisticated thing of
the time.
Oh, really.
So now, it's like, the brains a computer.
Right in the early 1900's, it was the brain is like, a very
complicated telephone switchboard.
Oh, really?
Yeah.
And then you can trace back.
So, but to take that analogy, right?
That is much more important for me in design than it is in
programming, simply because I don't need it in programming, almost out
of that if I needed it.
Then I probably go take a walk so to hear out calm and make this line
not intersect itself but that's just stupid right?
Like?
Yeah.
Okay.
So, I mean, it sort of sounds like what you're saying there is that,
like, the mindsets almost completely different.
It sort of sounds like, with approach, recording problems, and
president promised, to some degree.
But with the design thing, there's, you know, so, okay, this high
level idea has just appeared to me as out of this new handle ideas of
In the basement.
Yes, exactly.
And then, for this particular game, for example, in the witness,
there's a lot of instances of puzzles, right?
Yeah, sometimes I'm just messing around with an idea to see what
happens.
To find a bottom up things.
Yeah, and like, oh, this kind of makes an interesting puzzle.
Let me the top down thing says, oh, that looks interesting.
Okay.
And then let's drive it.
Bottom up a little more, sometimes.
It's like sometimes I really do get a little more top down because I
feel like
We're trying to build a thing that touches all these points in this
idea space.
This one is missing or it doesn't have very many think we need to fill
that and that's a very unhappy time because it means I have to be a
lot like a computer, okay.
And I have to start iterating on different like, okay, I want this
particular idea in the game.
It has to be in the game.
That puzzle doesn't do it.
That puzzle is to do it.
Oh this does.
And then I wake up in the next morning without the preconceptions of
how to solve it.
And I saw that trivially a different way that
Makes the puzzle and I'm like damn it, okay?
Right and so there is a very, very much more iterative.
I'm just trying a bunch of stuff mode.
Which is not the same as the bottom of design mode, but it's a
different bottom of.
This is why I don't like to say, top down bottom.
So it is, it is a Top Line, bottom.
You have the space and you've got a number of different sort of things
that you're talking about there.
But it's like you have a particular point in the space that you're
driving towards and
So as opposed to just a more free exploration where I'm just going
like, oh I'm seeing what sort of happens as I try these different
things out here.
It's like I'm actually evaluating each one by a different metric.
Not the general game metric of, is this good for my stated goals
mortis?
Like, am I getting closer to point x?
Like do I think this is kind of getting in that very nice eventually,
I kind of get in there and say, yes, I finally found the puzzle that
satisfies these criteria that, you know, it has to sort of fit in
this, in this area.
Totally.
So let's see.
Do we have?
What do we have?
Nope, we are
we are, we are out of time.
We are officially out of time.
I believe we hardly got to any of your questions.
No, we got two tons of my questions, right?
I mean, the thing I had to skip, was Jay questions, basically.
But I feel like that is something that we could easily handle.
The next handmade con after AI is used throughout all of Industry.
If it's happening next year, that may be a little early for, that's
what I feel like.
It'll be government certified somewhere around the summer after you
kind of get it out there and then it'll be space shuttles.
And
And so on.
All right.
But so as a final Closing one, so I guess I can't really ask the
question that I was asking which is what if the other people which is
what are you working on at the moment because I think everyone kind of
knows so just say how are you doing?
How are you holding up?
You get you doing okay?
Because it must be a very stressful time.
I'm actually pretty happy right now.
I mean it's one of those things where the worst that could happen is
we miss our ship date by a little bit which is not great but
All that means is a lot of Gamers on the internet.
Feeling entitled to tell me.
I'm a terrible developer because I obviously you know, I don't think
we will.
I think we'll be on time, but it depends but it's a very on a small
team, right?
You have to make everything happen.
Yeah.
And there's a bell curve of how much you think has to happen and it's
heavily weighted toward the right.
So the to do list get longer and longer and longer and longer and
longer and longer and longer term, really.
Time.
Yeah.
Again because all these problems are fractal and you keep getting new
things.
And at some point like you remember, like maybe two years ago two and
a half years ago, I was in a really bad mood all the time.
Yes.
Because it was near the top of that curve and there was like no end in
sight, right?
It's like I can't even see.
I mean obviously the games more done than ever before but like the
there's just too much to do and my brain can't understand all the
things there are to do.
And now it's like okay, there's a
A lot of things to do in a short period of time and I wish we had more
time and but that's a very finite tractable, kind of continuing to do
just that just, you know, I just like like we just work.
Casey came down to San Francisco.
Actually, he worked on the Collision system for the witness and he
flew down for about a week and we just cranked I don't know how many
our did we pulled 14 hour days or something.
Approximately remember yeah for a week and like you just do that and
problems go away.
Way right.
And no.
But I mean that sounds funny but that doesn't work in the middle of
development.
No because that adds problems in the middle, right.
You work a 14-hour day and now your to-do list is 10 percent longer
than it was at the end of the day and that's the demoralizing part.
So now I'm actually a good job.
Well thank you very much for talking with us and soon pleasure.