The recording here.
Alright, hello everyone and welcome to day 10 of handmade.
Here.
We have made it through ten days already.
If you are following along at home with the the source code, from the
pre-order.
You will want to unzip Source 9 sources.
009 from that zip file because we are starting with Source 9 here on
day 10 and you could follow along.
All right, welcome to handmade hero.
The only show currently in
Distance that I know of, in the whole universe, where we code an
entire game from scratch using nothing, but our own, our bare hands,
our bear myths.
I know it sounds improbable but we are going to do it and we have been
doing it and everyone following at home has been doing it and it has
been fabulous so far.
I see no reason to stop.
Now.
Hopefully during the sort of warm up to the stream when the little
countdown timer was on there.
For those of you who joined a little early,
you notice that?
I left.
I conspicuously left a particular page here up for you to read.
I don't know.
If you did.
It's a little like summer reading assignment kind of thing only by
summer.
I mean, the 20 minutes before the stream started.
But what you can see here is a, the first time I've actually pulled
this up.
It's a great reference to be aware of now.
It's it's a little opaque.
It's true.
But I love having it around.
I keep a copy on my machine at all times.
It is called the Intel architecture reference manual and you can find
it online just by searching on the Google.
If you go in here and you put Intel architecture reference.
Annual into the search box.
You will get a link that basically has a, you know, some kind of long
winded way that you got to fill some stuff out.
But I don't even remember how this all works, but you can eventually
get to download.
I think that's this thing right here.
That's a PDF or something.
And then when you open it you get this nice thing.
And what this is is basically a manual that Intel puts out that really
meticulously goes over all of the details of their processor and you
can look over here kind of
Of in the in the table of contents.
Basically, this Volume 2 one is the one that we're mostly concerned
about but the volume 1 and volume 3 are actually interesting to look
through as well.
They've got all kinds of stuff about like how the virtual memory works
and how the various virtualization features work and how systems
programming works, all of this stuff.
There's all kinds of good stuff in here that you can read to
familiarize yourself with x86 and x64 processor technology, and how it
works.
But, in here volume to the most important,
Part for any programmer.
Who's just, you know, curious about how the CPU works.
There's basically these two chapters chapter 3 and chapter 4, which
have an alphabetical list of all of the
Actual instructions that you can execute on an x 64 processor.
Absolutely.
Every every last one of them, I think is in here and so you can go
through and if you want to know something, when you're looking at an
assembly code, or just you're just curious about what the processor
going to do.
You want to know something you can go in here and say, oh we saw that
mob and structured on the stream.
Well, what's that?
And they'll list every possible way that it can work.
Right?
It'll have comments that kind of tell you what goes on.
On when it actually occurs and it'll have, like, sort of some
pseudocode that says, what the processors actually doing internally.
So it's, it's pretty darn cool and it's something that you should
probably be familiar with.
If you're just trying to educate yourself a little bit about the
specifics of how the computer works, which is one of the things that
we try to focus on here.
So, the instruction that I had up was called our dtsc.
Some of you may be familiar with it.
What our dtsc is is it's basically a way of getting at a register or I
mean, it's really a performance counter, but it's basically getting at
a thing inside the CPU that increments by 1 every time the CPU
effectively like retires a clock cycle.
So, you know when you say that this is a 3.2 GHz processor.
Well, that means 3.2, you know, billion cycles per second.
That the processor is executing each one of those Cycles, this magical
counter goes up by one and the our dtsc instruction, lets you actually
access the value of that counter at any given time.
And the reason that I wanted to introduce this today was basically,
because we are going to look at some ways of figuring out what time it
is in our code today.
That's the thing that we're going to be working on.
And this is a pretty important way that you can get that information
because our dtsc basically tells you the cycle count at any point in
your program.
So by asking for the cycle count before you do something and asking
for the cycle count after it gives you a pretty good idea of how many
processor Cycles have elapsed during the thing that you did.
So if you want to know how many cycles it took to do to execute a
particular piece of code, read time stamp counter can give you a
Good idea.
Now.
It's not always perfect.
Because there's a number of factors that come into play.
The first factor is that not all operating systems, save and restore
the time stamp counter across basically like across tasks which has so
if your process is running and you're trying to time it so you do in
our dtsc at the beginning in our dtsc, at the end you're going to
compare them.
You won't necessarily know if the operating system woke up in the
middle of that, swapped out your code, Ransom, other code, and then on
the same processor,
Sir, and then swapped in.
It again for the ending, our dtsc.
So when you do those are dtsc's, you have to be aware that your timing
everything that the processor did in between those two points.
Not just the thing, your code may have done.
Now.
This is, like I said, depending on the operating system, some
operating systems actually try to save and restore the are dtsc
depending on how you access.
It will kind of look at that a little bit later.
There's basically like a query cycle that there's actually a call in
Windows, you can use, I think it's supported on Windows 7.
Pretty sure there's a call, you can use in Windows that basically
says, I want to know, just for my threat, like, just for this
particular stream of execution, and that will prevent that particular
problem for happening.
But point being things like that can happen.
Other things that can happen is, you don't actually necessarily know
where those Cycles are coming from.
They don't mean instructions.
They mean cycle.
So depending on how warm the cash was, how much time it took to get
memory, all these sorts of things that are dtsc numbers are not going
to be the same.
All the time, they're going to be widely varied.
So you time a particular piece of code.
Once you're getting at one value, you time it again, even immediately
thereafter, you're going to get different values because maybe things
were in the cash that weren't before, all these all other sorts of
things.
So it's not foolproof.
It's not a thing that magically tells you exactly what the performance
of a piece of code is but it is a thing that gets you some pretty raw
statistics on exactly how many cycles elapsed between two points and
that is quite useful.
So, we will be
Showing how to use it.
I just want to caveat if they're at the beginning.
So the people wouldn't think it was.
It was too perfect.
So that's the first thing I'm going to talk about today and in terms
of timing and we're also well, I don't know if that's the first one
going to talk about two things today.
The other one were going to talk about is query performance counter.
This is another way of figuring out what time it is.
Essentially again.
This is all about clocking basically what this is, is a way of asking
windows and saying, Hey to the
Of your knowledge.
What is an actual wall clock time?
So this is the processor cycle.
And it's in terms of the processors view of time.
And what that means is that, if we're counting Cycles on the
processor.
We have no idea how that actually corresponds to wall clock time at
all when I say.
Well, clock time.
I literally mean like time out in the real world.
The real time that you and I experienced processor time does not work
that way processors these days depending on the processor.
Desktop processors less so, but still, but in Mobile processors by,
you know, definitely, they do a lot of clocking changes in the clock
speed to work around battery life and also to put perfect to manage
heat signatures even sometimes.
So like, for example, if only one core is running, they may boost the
frequency of that core, but if multiple cars are running, they might
drop it things like this, they'll drop the, the clock speed of a core
when not much is going on to save battery life.
Finn laptop, all of these sorts of things happen.
Now, on main stream processors, which means that when you look at the
cycle count, there is no constant meaning for how long that cycle may
have taken in the real world.
Because for some number of Cycles when you are using this, our dtsc,
you know, you take your or DTS, Indiana, you take it, at the end of an
area.
You don't even know if the processor was executing at the same clock
rate that entire time.
Time.
It may be that somewhere in the middle of their the processor down
clock itself or up clocked itself.
And so the first set of cycles, each cycle took a certain amount of
time and then the second half of the thing.
Each cycle took you no longer or shorter than the ones in the
beginning.
So Cycles, really.
Just tells you something about how much work the processor did in some
sense, but it doesn't really tell you about the wall clock time.
Read query performance counter is the opposite of that.
Query performance counter ask the operating system to please give you
a high resolution meaning so it isn't cycle accurate perhaps but it is
fairly accurate, you know, it's not in seconds and it's not in
milliseconds.
It's something more granular than Ms.
Hopefully, excuse me, because you have to remember for running at 30
frames a second or 60 frames a second.
You're talking about things on.
Order of 16 milliseconds per frame or something like this for a 60
frames a second, right?
Because, you know, if you, if you think about it, if you're in, you
know, a handy Loops by to couldn't I, there we go.
Need my little handy calculator.
So, if you think about it, if you have 1,000, you know, Ms.
There's 1,000 milliseconds per second.
Right?
So if we're running at 60 frames a second, that's only going to be
sixteen point six six six six six six six, six repeating milliseconds
that we have to come to do.
Do the work for any given frame.
Each frame will be on the screen for, you know, rounded up to 16 17.
I suppose somewhere between 16 to 17 milliseconds.
Each frame will only be on the screen for that amount of time.
And so that's the amount of time we have to do the work for the next
frame.
So if we're trying to figure out how much performance, how a
particular piece of code that gets improved or pesum Eyes by a
particular code change and we're trying to time it we in general need
things that are going to be a lot more.
Accurate than say a millisecond because we only have 16 total of those
roughly per frame anyway, so if it was on the order of Ms.
Even if we sped up a particular function by 20%, we would still get
the same time back.
Potentially.
It'll be like, well, it took two milliseconds, then we speed it up by
20% and it's like it still took two milliseconds.
Like no.
Okay.
We need, we need much more granular than that.
So, hopefully, all these timers that we use are, you know, more than
that.
Certainly Cycles is way more granular than that, because there's 3.2
billion of
As per second, when the processor is running at full speed.
Let's say,
the query performance counter is also going to be more granular than
that.
It's just not perhaps going to be quite as granular as a cycle count,
but it is basically an attempt by the operating system to use some
aspects of the system.
I think it used to use some kind of bus clock in your so I don't even
know what it uses these days.
I'm sorry.
I just, I have absolutely no idea.
I've never even looked into it and on a modern computer, but it
basically uses some aspects of the system, whatever it can to give you
back some wall clock time.
You can see here that it's suggesting that it's resolution is actually
better than one microsecond, right?
So that's much better than a millisecond.
Right?
And just to give you something Ms.
/, oops.
Sorry, microseconds per millisecond there so you can see that
basically you've essentially got something greater than 1000 of those
per millisecond.
We don't actually know because it just says greater than.
So, it's something in this box.
Ballpark, so that's in theory going to be pretty high resolution for
us to time things with.
But the important part about this as opposed to the cycle count is
query.
Performance counter actually corresponds to wall clock time.
Meaning, when we look at to query, performance, counter times and we
look at the difference between them.
We will be able to actually correlate that out to a real-world time.
And that's important because it helps with your intuition.
If we know that we have 16 milliseconds per frame to do something.
It helps us to kind of know how much actual time is.
This particular piece of code taking?
And we think about it.
We're like, okay, takes point five milliseconds.
So I roughly know, I could do, you know, 30, some odd of them, you
know, thirtysomething of them per frame.
I kind of get sort of this idea of that, right?
Where again, with the
Since they vary so much, it's harder for us to tie that back to a
time.
We always can write.
We always could, actually we always could actually try to time the
artist tses with the query performance counter.
So we know how many roughly the CPU is executing every frame and then
back out those times and stuff like that.
But really without create performance counter.
We'd never have a way on a running machine of really even knowing how
those are dtsc eskom map back to wall clock time because we never
would have any idea how
How fast the processor was actually running.
We always at least need something that can tell us when a second went
by, let's say so that we could see using our dtsc, how many cycles,
the processor had actually executed in that s, right.
And so that's that's really where this comes in.
So those are the two things that we're going to be talking about today
and I'm just going to show you a little bit about how you use them.
And this will give us a little more insight as well into how our code
that we've already written is even working.
Because right now, we don't even know.
For example,
Or how fast our program is running.
We have no idea.
How many frames per second were even getting right?
And this will finally let us sign and get that information.
Okay, so I'm going to go ahead here and open up our Command Prompt.
I'm going to get into emacs, everyone's favorite editor.
Excuse me.
Still getting over the cold feeling feeling better today, but still
throat's a little scratchy.
Alright.
So basically, what I want to do here is I want to just start by doing
something extremely, extremely simple.
I want to start by saying, well, we have a loop, right here is our
We're going to we're going to have a while loop where we just run and
our game is sitting in this loop.
I just want to start by going.
Let's print out some number that we can use to sort of see how long it
took us to generate a frame.
Right?
And in order to do that.
I'm going to use this query performance counter thing because I want
to know the actual wall clock time.
I want to know how many actual seconds.
It's going to be fractional.
It took to generate this or, you know, maybe we'll do how many
milliseconds to make it.
Easier to understand print out wide so it's not .00, whatever.
Who knows but point out world, when we get to our actual output debug
string.
We will actually shoot me.
Print this out.
Okay.
So we have query performance counter.
We're going to go ahead and get that and we're going to call that.
Now, the way that it works is, it's another one of these windows
functions.
You've seen them a lot here.
We're basically they take something to fill out.
In this case, a large integer.
So basically we need a large integer and we're going to call this
begin counter and we're going to take the address of that.
And basically we pass an address and it fills it out.
Now a large integer.
I don't know where there's no way too quick jump to it.
I was
To show you the structure of it here.
So I'll just cut and paste it into the search box.
I want to actually show you the layout.
There it is.
So basically a large integer uses something called a union, which we
really have not covered in this at all.
It's a very simple concept.
Basically, what a union is, is it's just a number of things that are
overlaid on top of each other in memory.
So it's basically telling you that you can access the same piece of
memory in multiple ways.
So when you say Union in Syria,
C++ the then list things and each thing listed in the union occupies
the same space in memory.
So basically, this struct this struct and this long long, which is
long long as 60 is, is Windows way of saying you in 64, basically or
N64.
I should say, since it's not you long loan and in a 64-bit integer,
each one of these right is actually 64 bits, right?
That's 32 bits 32 bits.
That's 32 bits.
32 bits.
And this is stage.
64-bits, basically, this this Union is just 64 bits long.
But you can access it using any of these methods you can say, dot quad
part to access it as 64 bits.
You can say, Dot Low part to access it as the low 32 or high part
taxes.
It is the high 32.
You can also use dot U Dot Low part and Dot U dot High part.
Now, why they wanted to do it this way.
I don't know.
This is called an anonymous structure, which means that these are
directly accessible off of the things.
So basically, Anonymous lets
You access them directly.
So you like, you know, I can just say Dot Low part, right?
Like that just with one dot that directly accesses this.
That's why it's called an anonymous.
There is no actual.
It's not actually in here as a separate member this.
You right here means that there's basically a, you know, a field
called you inside here that is this, the type is this structure.
So, if I wanted to access it through that, I would do, dot U Dot Low,
part like that.
Now, I have no idea why they have both of these in there.
Doesn't seem like you would need them.
There.
Like I said, they're occupying the exact same memory.
So it's basically just to allow you to do that or that.
So, I have to assume that that's just for backwards compatibility
purposes.
Like they made this one originally and then we're like, wow, we should
probably do it this way as well or something.
I don't really know.
But point being, you don't even have to worry about that.
It's completely, it's some kind of weird anachronism.
I would suspect since we are on a 64-bit architecture.
We're just going to go straight for the quad part.
The quad part is basically the part we want.
So we're going to look at that.
The quad part tells us basically, the whatever this value is, and we
don't really know how to interpret this value.
It's some 64-bit value.
That is a clock value.
We that we know somehow corresponds to wall clock time.
And now we know that begin counter dot quad Park.
Quad part, is that timestamp that value at the time that we start the
loop.
So as soon as we asked for this, we basically now have
That start time is in begin counter quad park, right?
So then we're going to do is we're going to jump down.
Well, actually guess we don't.
We can just we don't even need to do that.
We're going to do it right here, basically.
Right.
So we're also going to say last counter, right?
And we're going to ask for that up here.
Excuse me.
I figured this was a better way to structure this.
I'll tell you why in one second, why I felt like that was a good idea.
So basically what we're going to do is we're going to say all right at
the beginning, we're going to snap whatever the value is then we're
going to go through the loop and every time through the loop when we
get to the end we're going to look at what this is and we'll call this
and counter.
Right encounter will give us another time stamp and that time stamp
will be how you know, after after we've done everything essentially
right?
And then we'll go back down through the loop.
Oop, and we'll get to encounter, we'll get it again.
So, all we're going to do is every time after we actually print out
here, right?
We're going to actually display the value here.
We're just going to say that the last counter, whatever that is equals
the end.
Her right?
So we're going to actually store whatever the value was here.
Back in the last counter that will let us essentially compute the
difference.
Every time whatever n counter dot quad, part - last counter dot quad
part, right?
I do this.
And I'm going to put this in, in 64, and this was the difference time
difference, right?
Could say, this was the time elapsed basically, maybe I should say,
counter elapsed.
Excuse me.
If you look at this, man, it isn't me so good to do this dream.
I'm not sick.
I've done almost the entire handmade hero sick.
And its really annoying.
All right.
Interrupts me anyway, so basically all we're doing here is we're
saying well we have this clock.
We're going to look at the clock before we enter our Loop, right?
Right before we enter it.
Let's say we're going to do everything in the loop.
We're going to look at the clock again.
So we've looked at the clock twice and just like in the real world.
We can now take those two times.
The beginning in the end that we looked at the clock subtract, the X
and we will get, how much time elapsed right by that.
Fuck.
So, then in order to make sure that works again for the next frame.
We will pretend that.
Now, that original clock.
We took, that's just the new clock value that we got back.
So that the next time we get back down here, will be differencing.
It from itself will be different.
Sing it from the last time it passed this point.
And the reason that I wanted to do that instead of putting a big
encounter at the top of the while loop and an encounter at the end is
because well technically that doesn't quite capture all the time,
right?
If the actual Act of getting back
Ooh, the top of this Loop, maybe the process got switched out or
something happened.
That took a lot more time than just doing one comp, and a jump to get
back to the top.
We'd miss that time.
So I want something that's guaranteed to never miss any time.
So by always using a single stable place, where we check the clock and
differencing, it from that every time, we know that we've never had
anything Escape our time, window.
Our time, window is all-inclusive.
There's nothing that could have happened that isn't accounted for,
within our clock window.
So, once we do that, we have a counter last value.
That basically tells us how much time has elapsed.
Unfortunately.
We still don't know how to interpret this clock value.
So if we want to print out how many seconds something took, how many
milliseconds something took we don't know what we'd like to do is we'd
like to be able to translate this back to human readable wall clock
time instead of machine-readable clock time, which we don't even know
what it is because we don't know how Windows is even arriving at these
clock values, but fortunately, they give us something that does
exactly.
Actly that it's called query performance frequency.
Now, what Corey performance frequency does is, it basically tells us
how many increments this clock goes through in one second, right?
So, basically, if we just ask for this,
Up here, right?
If we say, hey Corey performance frequency.
Now the question I think I'm going to double check this.
I think we can just ask for this once because I don't think great
performance frequencies allowed to change but let me see if they
actually say that for certain somewhere.
Let's take a look.
Yes, the frequency of the performance counter is fixed at system.
Boot time.
As is consistent across all processors.
Therefore, the frequency need only be queried upon application
initialization and the result can be cached.
So at least, according to the documentation, which granted is
sometimes wrong.
We only actually have to ask once so, we can just say the performance
frequency, or maybe I'll say the proof counter frequency, right is
going to be something.
We can just ask for we then know.
Many of them happened for second, right?
And and we are good to go.
So, there we go.
We now have that value and we can use it.
So if we actually go ahead and get that, right, I'm going to put this
up here on the unit area, if we do that.
We can then come down here and say, well, we have a counter value that
elapsed.
And we also know how many of those per second, we're actually doing.
Right?
We know that basically up here.
In fact, I could even stuff this into a more useful variable.
I could say in 64 per count frequency like this and say that that was
perfect Camp, frequency dot quad part like we did before and this will
be
Just a thing that uses to hold that value coming back.
There we go.
So now we have the perfect count frequency.
We know that is how many counts per second that thing is doing.
So, in here, when we have the counter elapsed, we can actually say
well, however, many elapsed right /, how many per second there were?
That's how many Hoops.
That's how many seconds actually elapsed.
I just spilled my coffee, ladies and gentlemen, it was bound to
happen.
Eventually, of course Frank.
Thankfully, it kind of limits.
Did on my Mitten.
So it did not actually do not actually spill anywhere but almost did
and it almost wasted valuable coffee, which is really a crime.
So doing this divide saying the counter counts that we saw divided by
the frequency of that counter gives us the S.
And of course, one thing I should mention for the benefit of those of
you who are maybe not math Stars.
I know I'm certainly not a mass star.
So I just want to point this out for people who don't think about
things.
This way to maybe get you thinking about things in this way and doing
a little more reading in this area.
Perhaps one thing I wanted to point out is
Channel analysis is particularly useful.
When you're doing these sorts of things, you know, in your head, when
you're writing the sort of code just
Think about if you have something like a counter and you say, well, I
have a counter value and I know it came back.
It was like X number of counts, right?
Which is what we have.
Like we got this back and we know that this is the number of counts
that were that transpire, the number of like clocks that transpired
right?
Number of counts nerve counter increments.
And then we also know that this performance frequency thing when we
read the documentation, right?
It says counts per second, right?
So we also have a value that is counts right per second.
So if you have two values one that is counts and one that is counts
per second.
And you want to know how many seconds something took which is this,
right?
But you have a value.
That's how many counts it took the question becomes.
How do you get that value?
Right?
And the answer is you can always just look at how the unit's cancel on
the Divide.
So let's say we were to multiply
Apply these two things together, right?
What would we get?
Well, just look at what happens with the unit's counts.
This is essentially over 1, right.
This is X counts and counts per second.
Right?
If I multiply these together I would get counts squared right counts,
times counts over s.
Right.
That is completely useless who I mean that is not count squared over
s.
Is.
We don't even know what that is, right.
So what you want to do is look at how do you
Actually cancel the counts right out like this so that you're just
left with s.
Okay.
And the way that you do that is you say, well X counts.
I just need this to be inverted if s was on the top and counters on
the bottom, the counts would cancel.
And that's what a divide is, right.
It divide flips, the two things in a ratio.
So if I do counts /, right?
Counts per second, that is the same as multiplying by seconds per
count, right?
So the counts.
And we're just left with x s, which is what I wanted.
So looking at things in terms of flipping, you know, basically
flipping your ratios by either dividing or multiplying.
You could line up a whole string of these things.
If you've got them and cancel all the things that you actually need,
right?
It's a standard kind of thing.
In dimensional analysis to do where you've got some number, like
you've got x s and you want to know how many days x s is, right?
And you can kind of just line things up.
You can say, okay.
Well, x s.
I would need to multiply by how many seconds I need to cancel s.
So there s, and I can translate S.
I know how to translate s in two minutes, right?
Because it's basically 60 seconds per, you know, one minute, right?
And I know how to translate minutes right in two hours because I know
there's 60 of those.
Right.
So, I can just say one hour is 60 Minutes.
I know how to translate hours into days because there's 24 hours in
one day, right?
And just by literally, going well, whatever.
This thing was, I got to put it on the bottom to translate into
something on the top, put it on the bottom translate something the
top.
I made the math, exactly what it needs to be.
It's just multiply it out.
X times 1 times 1 times, 1 is X 60 times, 60 times 24, 60 times, 60
times 24, these all
All cancel minutes hours hours day, right?
And we get this.
And that is the answer.
So, you would just divide X by 60 times, 60 times 24, and that is how
many days it is.
Again.
If you're a math minded fellow, this is Trivial, but if you aren't,
it's worth starting to think about things like this.
There you go.
Okay.
Let's go back to the actual code, which I have not really been doing
anything.
Okay, so there's an encounter here and there's a last counter.
We got the frequency here.
I got to put that in there.
Let's see, gotta take the semicolon there.
Alright.
So basically this is going to give us back that value, but the
question is, what are we going to do with that value?
Well, what we can do with that value certainly is we can say, well
we've got the counter Last Ride, the performance frequency.
The problem is, if this is an integer divided, right?
We know that the
Of count frequency is how many counts per second there are and we know
that we probably didn't take a whole second to draw this Frame.
So this is just going to come out 20, the integer divide.
There's no fractional part.
So something that's a large number divided by something.
That's a smaller number is just going to give us 0.
So s is not particularly useful.
So what we might want to do is say well if we multiply this by 1000
right first that would actually give us Ms.
Now.
So if we multiply this by 1000, then we've got some room to do our
divide that
That would give us how many milliseconds it took to do this Frame.
Right?
So this is milliseconds per frame, right?
That is the actual value.
So now we actually know how many milliseconds per frame, we're
actually taking and we can just take a look at how many that actually
was now, of course, it's going to vary preferring because like the
first frame, we may do a lot X of extra work in the first frame.
We may have a lot of Windows messages that come in that are like about
initializing the window or something, right?
So the
This time, we do it.
We're not necessarily going to know.
So we want to actually look possibly later frames.
Okay.
So basically, what we want to do is print this value out.
Obviously, we have output debug string which we can, we can use, but
we don't actually know.
We've never actually seen how to print out a value.
Well, we're going to look at that in a little more detail.
When we do the platform independent code.
We're going to look at how to Output our do our own output of values.
So what we're going to do first is we're going to use Windows is code
much.
We used Windows is sine function to just test our stuff.
We're going to use Windows code to Output the variable as well.
But later on, I want to show you how that works.
So it's not a mystery to you how you output a number because obviously
someone knows how to do it and it works.
There is a thing called WS printf which you can use in Windows code,
to quickly generate strings.
And basically, all you have to do to use it, is you create some buffer
that it could write into, right?
You can create some buffer like this.
You can basically pass this buffer to,
W sprintf, you can then give it some thing that you want to print out
and give it the value that you want, and it will do it.
Now, the way that it does, this is a little wonky, and it's just the
way sees standard Library actually did it.
So it's the way Windows does it.
Now?
Basically, what happens is it takes a format string so it can actually
be something like milliseconds per frame.
You know:.
That's going to actually appear in the buffer.
It's going to
Copy those characters to our buffer, right?
That we've, that we've made here.
That's 256, bytes long.
It's going to put those in there, but then it's also excuse me.
It's also going to go ahead and look inside the string.
It's going to process the string as it goes and look for anything with
a percent in it.
If it sees a percent, it will use the next thing that comes after it
to determine what to print out.
Okay, and then the parameters that come after it, right after the
comma, it will then use to fill in whatever the percent told it was
coming.
So if I say something,
Want to have, I've got like a thing here.
Once this is we don't actually need 64 bits to store this so we can
actually do something like 32 and I'll tell you why in a second.
Why do that % D?
For example, is the code that says, hey, this is a, this is a 32-bit
integer.
Basically, that's what that does.
So, this says, we're going to pass a 32-bit integer.
Please replace the percent D, in the string, with the 32-bit integer
that I point you, right?
And we can actually put a little Ms.
After that four milliseconds.
Let's
Say so in here, we can now just pass buffer and that will actually do
the print out for us.
Now.
There's a bunch of other things.
I want to talk about here, but I'm just going to see if we got this
working.
First.
I got to actually launch the debugger, of course, before we do
anything else.
Let's go ahead and do that.
Here we go.
So I'll close the app.
We can kind of see what happened here.
Right?
And and much, like I said, it's not particularly predictable.
If you look through here, the first frame was long.
Like I said, it was going to be not surprising, then each particular
frame.
You look at, took us something on the order of six milliseconds, which
occasional spikes up to 10 milliseconds.
Now, normally those spikes, you know, is that typical eye on this type
of machine?
I don't think it probably.
Is but you have to remember, we are on this machine.
All of our timings are highly suspect, because we have this fine
fellow the open broadcasting software.
That is allowing me to talk to you on Twitch.
You have to remember that.
It is doing a bunch of work to capture and compress this framing
everything.
And even though this this machine has an ungodly number of processors.
I think I showed this in the intro to see stream.
It just has an ungodly number of of course.
So it's two processor machine.
Each one has six cores or something like this.
I don't or four cores and to hypothetical.
I don't even know.
I think it's for a course to epithets fork or two processors.
Something like this.
I don't even know.
We'll have to look it up at some point when we start talking about
multi, you know, when we talked about optimization in terms of
processors, will start getting into stuff like, what a hyper thread is
and why you care.
But for right now, just say it's tons of horsepower in this machine.
It shouldn't be a problem.
But the point is that
That is not necessarily the case when multiple people are contending
for the same resources, since we are bleeding to the screen.
We are, we are copying our image up to the screen and our runtime
includes that effort that ability to display things.
On the screen, OBS is trying to capture the screen from Windows.
We may run into circumstances for all I know, where there's like a
lockup where we have to wait for it to do something and all.
You know, I don't know.
I've never done any profiling of code that runs on a machine where
video capture is running.
Concurrently, but suffice to say, as we're doing the stream, and doing
timings before we start doing any serious performance work.
I will probably try to do some kind of outboard capture to get that
out of the equation because all of the timings that I take on this
machine are going to be highly suspect until we get OBS out of there.
So that we know we're doing direct throughing.
Basically, but point being
What's interesting about this and what I hope is pretty interesting to
you.
Just from looking at this, is this 6 milliseconds here?
You remember, 16 milliseconds and I can print out this value as well.
I don't particularly love frames per second as a value that's useful
but it helps because people quote it in the news all the time and that
sort of stuff.
But we can certainly put out that number how many frames per second
there are so frames per second, right?
Is going to be the milliseconds per frame computation.
Basically, it's going to be the same as that FPS here.
All right.
Well, you know what you
Be able to do this.
Now.
You should not need me to do this because I told you how to do
Dimension analysis, dimensional analysis.
So let's see.
I'm going to, I'm going to do this real slow.
So that hopefully, those of you at home, who are going ahead.
We'll get it.
I want you to get it before I do.
Okay.
So what did I say about dimensional analysis?
I said that we want to look at what's on top and
Bottom of the ratios.
So our Target right is frames per second.
Okay, and what do we now have, right, what do we actually have?
Well, we've got two values, we could work with.
We have counts, right?
We have X counts.
We also knew how to translate that to S, right.
So, how do we get from here to here?
I want X counts in in frames per second, right?
Now, there's a little bit.
There's a little bit that I'm not saying yet.
To see if you got it.
Okay.
Hit number one.
Is that this isn't just X counts.
This is X counts per frame.
Right.
Because that is what we did.
We timed one frame.
So we know that X counts go by per frame.
So counts on the top frame, on the bottom, right?
Make sense.
Does everyone have it yet?
I don't know if everyone has it.
See, the thing is, you can see me through the webcam, but I can't see
you through the webcam and that's really the problem.
So I can't see if you've got it or not, but it's okay.
So let's, let's go ahead and take a look at this here.
So, the first thing that I would say right is I want to be able to
invert this, right?
I need frames to be on the top, right because frames is on the bottom
at the moment and that's no good.
Right?
I also know that I want seconds.
So really what I could do is I could say.
Well first of all, we know counts per second that
Our query performance frequency.
So if I multiply this right.
Oops, what's going on?
Oh, I accidentally did I hit some button there?
That was interesting and kind of It kind of froze me out.
Right?
So what I want to do is I want to multiply this by something that's
got like counts on the bottom right and S on the top like this.
How many seconds per count, right?
And we know that that is basically the inverse of our of our
performance thing that would give me because our performance frequency
was counts.
Right counts per second.
So the inverse of that which is obviously.
And I guess the one thing that I didn't say in that thing was, which
is again mathy.
So I suppose I should have said it is that if I have some ratio 1 over
that ratio, like if I do one over counts per second, that gives me S 4
count, right?
So I can always invert a ratio.
I can flip it around by doing one divided by the value gives me the
inverse of that value flips the to, right.
So basically the most straightforward way to do this, right?
Is to say, all right.
The first thing I want to do is I want to flip this around.
Okay, so
Going to do 1 over this value.
I'm going to take 1 divided by our counts per frame.
Right?
And if I do that, then that will give me.
I can't figure out how to actually erase this.
I'm trying to, but I can't do it, right.
Okay, there we go.
So, if I take 1 over this value, that will flip it around and that
will give me 1 frame per X counts.
Right, then I multiply that by how many counts?
Right per second.
There are, which we know this is our frequency counts per second.
This was the performance frequency, right?
And so, I cross out my accounts and I'm just left with frames per
second, which is what I wanted.
So, we need to do one over our counter, right?
We need to do one over our counter.
That's this step.
And then we need to multiply by the frequency.
And that should give us our frames per second.
Does that make sense?
Hopefully, that makes some sense.
I don't know if it does, but if it does, there you go.
So if we have 1 over the counter times the frequency.
Well, we can just multiply that out.
That's just the frequency divided by the counter right now.
If you think about that, that makes them pretty good sense.
That's basically saying we have, you know, we have our frequency
counts.
/ s RF counts per second, right over our accounts, right?
And that just drops out the count values, which is sort of what we
wanted and S, of course, moves to the bottom, because it's on the
bottom.
All right?
Okay.
So basically, you know, dimensional analysis play around with it.
I realize it's hard.
If you've only seen it for the first time, that's probably not the
best explanation anyone's ever given in the world.
I can tell you that right now.
Like I said, I'm not the math guy, so maybe take a look.
Excuse me online for something like that, or maybe we can find some
links to it.
But basically that's that's all we're trying to do here.
So four frames per second.
We basically just need to do our seconds per frame.
I'm sorry.
What's our performance?
We can see there.
It is.
Our counts per second.
Basically, right /.
How many counts we actually had?
Oh, there we go.
Counter elapsed, right like that.
And that
It should give it to us.
I'm not sure again like talking on the stream kind of makes.
There we go.
Okay, and then we close it and then you can sorta see.
Now this number translated into something.
That's more like what you would see reported in the Press.
So six milliseconds per frame is 143 frames per second.
Right?
And we can sort of double verify that because if we already computed
the milliseconds that it took, we know there is 1000 milliseconds in
one second.
So dividing by 6.
There's
That 166 value, of course, this is going to be more accurate than that
because it's actually a decimal here.
16 points something, something something.
And then there's the seven, which is a little bit lower value.
So that is 1000 divided by 7.
And that's up in the 142 which is which is right accurate.
So that was probably almost exactly seven.
So that's that's basically, you know, I mean, that's, that's really
all there is to it.
This is how you get a counter.
There's pretty much.
I mean, yeah, I think I've said just about everything.
There is dimensional analysis can come in to help you a little bit.
If you get start getting confused about how to compute a particular
thing.
You can look, you want to look at those units.
Try to let the
The unit's help you and that's the way that goes.
Now this this sort of thing.
Is is highly problematic?
There's a number of reasons why this sort of thing is highly
problematic.
The printout I'm talking about here.
There are so many ways that this sort of style of printout can go
wrong.
The first one is you can pass a buffer that's too small.
There's ways of getting around that.
Basically, this this, if you go look up in msdn here, obviously WS
printf is documented here.
There it is.
Basically, there's versions of these sorts of things where you can
pass in the size of the buffer, to prevent it from possibly going
over.
Basically, I don't know, I guess they'd have these strings.
CB printf here.
Yeah.
So basically, they have newer versions, which do that, which, which do
it.
Here's a, here's an easier one, understand.
So here's wns printf, wns printf is the same as W is printf.
But instead of just taking a pointer to a buffer, it takes how long
the buffer is as well, right?
So instead you could
So Point here, you could say size of buffer like that.
And now you know that if you pass it above this too small, you won't
overwrite memory basically because you have to remember, basically it
all it sees all the original one sees, let's go ahead and
What wns print death there, right?
Not found?
Why are you not found?
It's right there.
What's the problem?
What is the problem though?
It's in some special H file.
All right?
And wonder if this will call this may happen cause it's linked with
something special as well which case I'm not going to use it.
Let's take a look.
Yeah, so I'm not actually I'm not actually going to use that.
I'm just going to show this old one and say the fact there is one that
takes the size of the buffer.
So basically one of the problems with this thing is you pass it a
buffer but it has no idea how big that buffer is.
So if you were to pass it, a string that doesn't fit in the buffer.
Now, we know this will always fit in the buffer because the number of
the size of these two things can never actually be enough characters
to make this get out to 256.
So this is perfectly safe, but you could imagine if you made a mistake
and you pass a buffer here.
That isn't big.
Enough to hold the fingerprinting.
You just overwrite the end of memory because it has no idea how big
the buffer is.
It assumes?
You gave it a buffer that was big enough, and if you didn't off, you
go, that's definitely a source of bugs, right there.
S sorts of bugs and sometimes can some compilers, like llvm will try
to catch these by parsing, the string print out time, basically.
These percentage things are sort of just like assumed to line up with
whatever you pass it.
And this is basically a thing that does what's called Vera args, which
says it just the compiler, just sticks, whatever you put after the
after the thing after the format string here.
It just starts sticking these things on the stack and then this
function will just pull things off the stack, based on what it sees
here, but you could just, you could say that there was a ton of stuff
that was never.
Actually, they're right and the
Has no idea that that happened.
So it starts reading shit off.
The sorry.
I stopped to use.
Colorful language.
It starts reading stuff in off the stack that it was never supposed to
look at.
That isn't even a variable potentially.
The who knows what it is.
It can do all sorts of things like that.
If I told it that a pointer was coming %.
S says that there's going to be a pointer to a string but I didn't
ever pass a part of string then you get into a sex thing.
Well, you'll do an access violation, when it goes to try and read
that.
So it's fraught with Peril.
It's
be fraught with Peril.
So typically I don't use this sort of code in anything.
I'm going to ship like this is not code that I like to see hanging
around in like something.
I'm sending you an end-user.
I like to write my own versions of these things and know that there's
some degree of accuracy to them if possible and so on.
But basically, if there is a, if there is debug code or profiling code
like this, that we know is only going to
Ever really be run on our machines, when we're developing it.
Then you can go to town because a bug in there doesn't cost you
anything.
It's like, yeah, you crashed on your machine or yeah, you had some
security exploit on your profiled version.
That's not that big of a deal.
But if you're going to ship this, to an end user, this sort of stuff
becomes becomes dicey, doesn't mean you can't do it.
It just means that when you do it, you gotta know.
You really got understand what you're doing.
You can't just throw it in there and be like, I saw it on handmade
hero and I just typed it.
It's like, no, that's
At this, this can go wrong real quick.
So you want to leave this kind of thing, basically, as debug code for
the most part until you let you really know what's going on.
All right.
So the next thing we're going to do is basically all we're doing to do
is augment that with that are dtsc thing that I talked about.
Right?
So we're basically going to say, alright, when we do this query
performance counter.
I'm also going to go ahead and snap the our dtsc value.
Now.
Thankfully, we can actually do that right from the compiler.
There's usually a intrinsic for it, which I wanted to show you the
documentation for by.
Don't see it's usually like underscore our dtsc or something like this
that I don't see right now.
Why am I not seeing it underscore our
ETS.
See what's going on here?
People.
There should be in our dtsc on llvm.
It's that that's why I use.
Recently, but see so there it is.
Yeah, why didn't find that underscore underscore our dtsc.
Oh, I'm so sorry.
I forgot that s underscore makes all the difference there.
Okay, so it looks like that's all there is to it.
You just get ya.
All right, so generates the are dtsc instruction, which returns a
processor time stamp.
That's exactly what we wanted.
We just want to call that function of the processor and get that value
back.
So basically, we're going to insert another thing here.
We're going to say that.
There's an
64, which is the last time stamp counter from the processor, right?
Or we can also say, last cycle count, right?
And basically, that would just be equal to whatever our dtsc was, and
that just full-on should output.
That instruction later.
When we get down here, we're going to do exactly the same thing as we
did before.
So, now we go to end cycle count and we get it again, then when we do
our thing and you know, what, I'm going to do that, since this is
cheaper, are dtsc is cheaper than query performance.
Armand, do that one first because that's going to be the more accurate
time there.
I guess.
Well, it doesn't actually matter because we're doing round-trips time.
So it doesn't matter.
You can put them in either order because we're going to it's going to
have to then go through this, to do the rest of it as well.
But point being.
So then we're going to actually do here as well.
We're going to do Cycles elapsed, right?
And we do exactly the same thing we did before we do the End Cycle
count - the last cycle.
Count, that gives us that.
And we do last cycle count - I'm sorry, right equals N Cycle cap, too.
Set it.
So that next time through the loop will be using the most recent clock
value.
And then we know how many cycles of left.
It was.
So we know that milliseconds per frame and we also now know and we can
we can actually get rid of this because we actually said milliseconds
per frame and frames per second, right?
We're actually pointing out those values not doing a very good job
separating these this do comma comma and then we want something here
that we're going to print out which is basically our
Our cycles per frame right from the processor.
And so the cycle is elapsed is going to be a lot, right?
So, maybe what we'd rather do is say like megacycles, right?
So maybe we'd rather do something like MHz, right, like this.
So we're going to say basically, this is how many megacycles per
frame, we're actually taking because otherwise, oops, sorry that's
divided there.
So we're actually going to divide that out so that we're not actually
looking at such a huge, such a huge.
Value.
So we're going to say this is megacycles per frame.
And we're going to grab this value out here like that.
And then we are going to say that this is also passed it down to 32.
And the reason I'm casting these down to in 32s is because percent D
is kind of a uniform way to print things out.
Whereas printing out a 64-bit integer, using a printf style thing is
only very recent so % D actually always works.
Every see that you'll ever have, whereas printing out 64-bit can be a
little bit dicey depending on the circumstances.
So I'm trying to convert these two 32-bit values before I print them
out.
So hopefully that'll give us what we wanted.
We can then go ahead and run this and see if that makes any sense.
We'll stop it and we can basically see here that you know in a given
frame we took 6 milliseconds and we executed somewhere around 20
million instructions to do that frame in the six milliseconds.
So, let's see if
That holds water.
Basically what we're saying there?
Again, if we take a look at the divider divisor, we're basically
saying, okay, if we had a hundred and fifty two frames per second,
right?
So that's how many frames per second we have.
So, 152 frames a second times, the number of instruction megahertz,
which is, which megacycles, which was twenty there.
That should come out to roughly the processor speed.
Right?
And it sort of does basically, and we don't know what this values
fractional is because we're not printing it out, right?
So there we go.
We've got that.
And if I look at the actual, I don't actually know how to get to this
anymore.
I always forget.
Where is it?
If you look at the clock, so we should see, it's like, yeah, okay, so
it's roughly around there, right?
3.19 gigahertz.
And so that's, that's roughly in the ballpark of where it should be.
And I think if we, if we have, if we did a little more Precision
there, it should come out.
In fact, we could actually do the math with the actual original values
and see what it actually was.
We could say, for example,
We could do the milliseconds per frame times the the cycle, so
laughter something like that.
So basically, that there tells us all the clocking information that we
want to know, just not to very high Precision.
So the next question is, could we do fractional?
And the answer is, yes, we can do fractional.
We just have to learn a little more about how you do printf.
Now, if you want to do fractional, you have to use the C runtime
library because if I remember correctly, WS, printf, the thing that's
built into into Windows.
Cannot
Print out floating Point values.
It just doesn't have the ability to do so, that's my understanding.
Yes, it does not because this is basically a listing in here of all
the things that ws printf can take with that percent thing.
This percent thing here and you can see all the stuff that you can
say, right?
There's like sign character is sign, decimal, integer sign shorts
unsigned, short blah, blah, blah blah, but floating point.
Value like we learned about yesterday.
Nowhere to be found.
So if you want to print out a floating point value, you're kind of out
of luck.
And if so, if we want some kind of fractional value that says that the
fractional milliseconds we can't actually do that.
Now, obviously one thing you could do is just not use the numbers that
you have C 4 axis for but if we want to see a nice fraction, like a
fractional milliseconds, so, you know, 6.23 milliseconds per frame.
We actually need to use the C runtime libraries version of the same
function which is which is just sprintf.
So you can see here.
There's w.
Is Windows version of the sprintf?
If you want to, you can use a see runtime libraries version, which is
sprintf.
Again.
I don't really want to start relying on libraries too much.
So for debug code, this is fine.
I'm just telling you that it's there, if you want to use it.
So you can if you want to do want to do that, you can use sprintf
instead of print, F WS printf, but you have to go add up here.
A reference to standard IO dot h, that's the C runtime.
Libraries function.
We're already linking with the c runtime Library.
So all those
Functions are technically in there and you can all call them.
That will do exactly the same thing.
So if you run it, now, there's no difference.
Right?
Basically, we take a look, and there is the, there is the same as I
printed that we saw before, but we can go in here and actually use
percent F, which means print out a floating point value if we want to,
and we can also use some things called format specifiers.
So if I just do % F and and change these all 2% apps, then what I can
do here is do all of this in basically in float.
I can do all of these values in floating point and I can just instead
of, instead of a doing them, an integer arithmetic.
I can do it in floating Point arithmetic and get all of that stuff
that we wanted here.
I can just go ahead and say that all of these things are floating
Point values and then, we will essentially have everything computed in
floating Point like that.
So there you go.
If you can see that, basically, if we do it this way, there's a little
bit of a caveat here.
That is that
I'll tell you about in one second, but when we actually print these
out so many things to talk about here when we actually print these out
now, we will actually be able to print out floating Point values.
So now when we see it, you will basically get something that looks
like that same exact print out.
But now you notice we've got a lot of fractional Precision there and
presumably like I sang before.
Now if we actually look at the math, it'll come out a little bit
better if we do 147 frames per second, right.
And
Do that times the number of cycles megacycles per frame X?
You see, we get almost exactly that CPU number, right?
Which is what we were expecting to see, 3.19, which is exactly what we
wanted.
All right.
So anyway, hopefully you can sort of see how that works out.
I don't want to belabor this too much, because like I said, these are
just some of these are just some standard Library functions that exist
and we're not really going to be using libraries much.
At all in this in this stream as we build the game, since we're trying
to build everything from scratch.
So I don't really want you to get hung up on how to use the C runtime
library.
But again, it is all in there for getting your debugging code running.
I mean, when I go to write a platform layer, even when I am writing
everything from scratch, I will often use something in the standard
library of that platform or the or the operating system to get my
stuff going.
So I basically know, you know, that that it it's some reliable code
that I didn't just write myself from
Ouch.
Now, the other thing you can do in here too is you can add format
specifiers?
Again.
If you want to in here, if you look up the definition of sprintf and
stuff.
There's a thing.
Usually somewhere, that okay, here it is.
There's a link to say format specifications and you click on that.
And they'll be a whole big document that says, here is the thing that
you use for those percent things.
Here's all the stuff that you can put in there.
You can, you can look at all these things like flag to refuse, and so
on, and basically what they all are, as their ways of encoding in.
That percent notation how you want the value printed.
So, for example, if I say .02, right, I can control the degree of
precision and how the floating-point number is printed out.
Remember, it was printing it out at this Precision before six decimal
places and that's maybe a little too verbose for me.
So, if I specify .02, it says, I want you to go ahead and actually
print out the the number to two decimal places, right?
You can see there.
You can see that.
So, you know, if you want to learn how to do this, it's not a waste of
time.
You can call these when you're on a platform trying to get things
working.
They exist everywhere anywhere that you have a c compiler.
You have this function to call with the c runtime Library.
Kind of like we were able to call sign, that'll work everywhere
because the C runtime libraries built in.
You know, that a compiler has to ship with it in order to be like a
standard compliant compiler.
So, you know that you have access to these when you're getting your
debug code working, even if you're doing everything from scratch.
We will be, you always have those to fall back on if you're trying to
test our you have bugs and you're like, what's wrong with my code.
You can call their sine function and find out why your sign function
doesn't agree with it stuff like that is very useful.
So again, I don't want to try to tell people never touch a library and
you're like a bad program or something.
If you use libraries, libraries are totally fine.
We're just, we just want to go through and show you how to build
everything.
So later we're going to actually look at how to do our own, kind of
print us and stuff, which are actually kind of complicated.
We're going to look,
Look at some things like that as well, just because I want to show you
how that does.
So it's not a mystery to you, how it's doing stuff like this.
So that's basically everything about timing and what you can do now.
And this is something that will do a bit later when we get to
profiling is in the in the platform independent layer of the code.
We can also build a little bit of a superstructure that calls into the
platform layer, the puffer independent layer, to get timing
information at various points in our code.
So we'll be able to see who is taking that time.
So we basically, we time
The whole thing, right?
But you could imagine us doing something a little bit different.
Where, for example, we could put query the performance counter right
here as well.
Right?
We could say, let's take another performance sample right here, called
mid counter, right?
Like this.
And we could take a look at how long it took us to do everything, but
that stretch divots, right?
This is where the stretch stretch.
TI B happens.
How long does it take to do everything up to that point?
No.
Right, you could do that.
And you could come in here and say, well, the amount of counter
elapsed, we could do the exact same thing and see how long that takes.
That is the kind of thing that will be doing when we get into
profiling.
We'll have some nice utility function.
We can call to just drop stuff into our code and see how long every
individual thing takes.
How long is stretched debates?
How long does it take us to build our gradient?
How long it take to fill the sound buffer?
Those are all the sorts of things.
We look at when we Act start, look at profiling but that's really all
there was to it.
Now that you have those tools you can
Build any kind of profile you want.
We'll see, you know, some interesting tricks for doing that, but
that's it.
So anyway, we've come to the end of the stream and it is time for Q&A.
Thank you so much.
Everyone for joining me for another handmade hero.
I hope that that was all relatively clear.
I know, it can be kind of confusing with all these sort of things.
Hopefully, the clocking stuff was clear, this guy.
Like I said, this is a whole topic onto itself these printf.
So if you're a little hazy on that, I don't blame you.
Like I said, I don't really want to harp on it.
It's basically just
A simple way you can use to print stuff out any tutorial you read,
online about how to use printf.
And basically there's a bunch of variance.
There's like printf which prints them in the console.
There's s printf which print something to a buffer, you know, there's
a v vs printf which allows you to pass through printf things.
There's a whole bunch of different things like that.
There's fprintf which prints things to a file.
There's the whole Suite of those in the C runtime library that
basically are provided courtesy of the compiler for you to call if you
want to
to.
So, there you go.
So yes with that.
I'd like to go to the Q&A.
Please remember to prefix, anything that you want to ask with at see
me oratory so that I will see it.
Somebody saying our dtsc return an unsigned integer.
That's what I would have thought too.
But I thought maybe I was just, maybe I just quickly reading.
I would have thought it returned an unsigned integer as well.
But for some reason, it looked like it didn't.
I don't know why.
Oh, it did.
Okay.
I just, I was asleep at the switch.
Yes.
Thank you for catching that.
That was odd to me as well.
I was like, gosh, that's weird because I don't, I have always in the
past started in a, you N64.
But I was like, well, maybe I just want to follow think.
Okay.
Good.
That's good cycle.
Count.
There we go.
You and six?
Were, there we go.
Cycles of the elapsed?
Yeah, are you?
Okay, so that's that's really all we needed there.
Oh, so one thing I should talk about really quickly to well.
We're in the Q&A.
You'll notice I went in here and I had to cast these things to
floating Point values.
The reason for that and we kind of glossed over it.
We didn't really talk about this in detail and I should just mention
it for people who are not as familiar with.
See, maybe you're coming from this to the
I'm from a different language and you may not understand all the
implicit rules that c does.
So, one of the things is, if I have two integers, right?
I have in X and Y and I say x divided by y, right.
It's going to use the types of those integers to determine what kind
of divide to do.
So even if I was trying to store it in a floating point value.
It doesn't really look yet.
When it does the /, it doesn't look at like, what the what it needs to
generate.
At the end of the equals.
It doesn't use that to determine what kind of divide to do.
So these are integers and memory, and their integer types and see,
right.
So C is going to do this as an integer divide and an integer divide.
Another integer and of course, an integer has no fractional part.
So, the fraction is gets thrown away.
It's gone.
So if we did float Z equals x divided by y, we will get no fraction,
even though this value is capable of storing a fraction.
So what you have to do first is tell C using the casting, notation
that we learned.
Basically, we have to tell see cast this prick, you know, convert it
first to a floating Point number.
Then do the divide and then see understands.
Oh,
Okay, I see what you're doing.
We're trying to move these into floating-point registers do a divide
in the floating Point registers and then store the result of that
floating-point divide out to the float.
Oh, yes, you know what?
I still need to figure out.
How to put a window up there.
I was using an index card.
I'm sorry.
I was drawing behind my window and paint.
There's a little.
I gotta, I gotta make a thing that blocks my screen just out.
I've been so good and I forgot.
So someone is asking, let's see where we going here.
Someone was asking if we can compile with optimizations on and see how
this changes.
So that's true.
If we were profiling our code, obviously we are not, we are not
turning.
Optimizer here.
So basically the compiler is producing the slowest possible version of
our code right now.
It's not trying to do any thinking about how to make the code fast and
that could matter because again, we've got some, we've got some large
loop things happening here.
Like in our thing where we render weird gradient, there is a lot.
This is going to be, you know, 1280 by 720 or whatever.
We set our window height was we're going to be operating on a lot of
memory here in our little Loop.
If the compiler were to optimize this or not.
Is it that could make a difference?
You know, that's definitely true.
So basically, if we take a look here, I don't really want to get into
performance analysis yet.
So I'm not really going to harp on this.
But since someone asked the question, we could look here and say,
well, here is just a poor man's quick version.
We could look here and say, well, alright.
So here's the here's the thing unoptimized, right?
That's the sort of typical thing that we were seeing optimized and
then we go into our build script.
Can say we wanted optimize that would be in build up bats.
We can pass - 02 to it and it will do some optimization for us and
then we'll hit the five and see what it actually is.
We close it and now we can see.
What we actually get for our frames per second and see how they
compare right, our milliseconds per frame and so on.
So this is optimized, right?
And as you can see, the unoptimized version is pretty consistently
about twice as slow as the optimized version, right?
And that's not perhaps a typical in a circumstance where we have not
optimized our code at all.
So it's entirely up to the optimizer to do everything.
That's that's totally reasonable.
Right.
If it's code that we've optimized we would probably not.
Be getting a 2X like that, because we've already done a bunch of work
to make the code sort of more optimal as it is.
But yeah, so hopefully you can see that's that's basically this is
with with - O2 and this is without, so this is that's how that works.
Let's take a look here.
Okay, do do do do.
Do the divide in doubles?
Oh, yeah, I should mention that.
Thank you for saying that.
Someone was talking about the Divide here.
So I wanted to mention this as well.
I kind of set it as we went through the screen by never actually
showed it.
So one of the things that's true here is if you really cared about the
last little bit of accuracy, so you like at this level of accuracy,
you don't care about this at all.
But if you were printing out a more fine if you wanted more decimal
places here and you actually care what the value was, it's your, you
know, there's you're actually trying to be more accurate and not just
a rough idea.
It the thing to remember, is basically a real, a floating, a 32-bit
floating point value, as we covered, has 24 bits of accuracy in it.
Right?
We said it was 24 and Tessa and then, you know, 7 B exponent or
something like this.
I don't know what we, what we actually kept that with it was.
But basically that so it's 24 bits of accuracy, but we've got 64 bits
of accuracy coming in now, technically, after this subtract.
There's actually not going to be that many.
So the person who said do the divide and 64-bit.
I know where you were going with that, it probably won't change the
result at all because you don't have 64 bits of accuracy after you do
the subtraction, but let's say that you time something really long,
right?
So instead of 20 million coming back, like this is 10 million coming
back, 10 million.
You're not going to really lose any accuracy.
Doing a floating.
A point divide, a 10 million, but let's say you would time something
that was like 50 billion cycles.
It was several frames long or something like this, right?
Then doing the divide in a 32-bit float.
It'll still work just fine, but you'll have a lot less Precision
because 50 billion is much higher than the number of decimal places
that you can have the number of bits that you have in your 24-bit
flow, 50 billion would be like, you know, 35
five bits to represent all the things.
They're right, and we only have 24, bits of mantissa in our floating
point value.
So in order to actually do the Divide out all the way, so that it was
actually as accurate, as the numbers that we're going in.
You would want to cast these two real 64's.
You'd want to use 64-bit floating-point values.
For what we're doing.
We're never going to have a big enough thing that we ever actually
really care about that.
But if you want to, you totally can and one of the things that's a
weird total anachronism Quark, weird thing about printf is they always
act?
We do the printf in double anyway, basically, they always use 64-bit
floats.
So these actually get past as 64-bit floats.
Anyway, they get up converted when they get passed at the end.
So you're actually if you want to it's more or less free to do it with
the actual person with the additional Precision because you're only
doing this once.
And so it's not like it's some big thing and it's only for performance
tuning so you're not even shipping this code.
So it's not really a big deal.
You're not doing it that often you.
And for free, if you want to just do it with higher Precision, now,
you're not going to see any difference there.
The going to exactly the same in this particular thing.
But if you were doing stuff, it might count.
So it's free.
If you want to do it with the higher Precision, that's just something
bad.
Let's see.
It would be nice to have a road map, so we can read ahead.
When you deal with string formats threading, opengl DirectX cross
platforms, have etcetera.
And what I consider doing a 24-hour shifts a day roadmap, probably
won't happen.
And the reason for that is that I don't think they're a good idea, not
because I don't want you to know what's happening, but more because
programming with a schedule never works.
You have to be able to sort of feel, you have to be able to build up a
good intuition about
But the thing is that needs to happen next, after you do each
individual thing.
And if you have a road map, then you're sort of saying that you're
going to do whatever the thing is, that was on the road map next, but
that may turn out to be inappropriate.
So there will not be a roadmap.
That's not going to happen at best.
I will start to tell you, as we go into the later parts of the code
and I have done this already.
What we're doing the next day.
So if you want to read up on something in during the day for the next
night stream or something that might happen.
24 hour stream.
Probably won't happen.
Will we be able to use a PlayStation 2 controller?
Yes, I mean, at the end, we'll make sure we work with all sorts of
things.
I don't know about PlayStation 2 controller specifically, but at least
a PlayStation, like, for controller or something, some PlayStation
controller that plugs into a PC.
We will test with and make sure that we get it working with that.
Let's see.
Can we expect for Jess and Casey shows in the future?
There's one every Monday.
There was one just this past Monday.
They'll be one this Monday as well.
You can always
Get more, just subscribe to the podcast stream and you get one every
Monday.
Is it safe to use Thrifty for but variables and functions on a 32-bit
PC?
Yes.
It's just not safe to assume that they are performant.
So basically, if you do some kind of 64-bit operation on a 32-bit PC,
you may end up in a situation where your emulated.
So, basically, the processor generates a bunch of things to do a
64-bit multiply or divide.
It may be very inefficient as long as you're doing them only in in
places where you don't do them a lot.
So this is
One per frame.
You could afford 10,000 Cycles to do this, subtraction.
If you wanted to write and were immediately up converting them to
floating Point values to do the rest of the map.
So, we're only really literally doing some traction of 64 bit here.
That's attraction, will never hurt you, no matter what processor,
you're on pretty much.
So that's okay.
If on the other hand, you were in some tight Loop that Opera like,
let's say, in our pixel Loop that we're actually filling our gradient
out.
If you started doing 64-bit math in there, that would be real bad if
you
Then tried to run it on a processor that couldn't do 64-bit math
natively.
That would be a bad scene.
Let's see.
It feels like, even though we are doing low-level programming.
Sometimes we have to pass things to Windows and makes difficult to
follow.
Exactly what the computer is doing.
Well, this change, we moved on to other platforms, but we also run
into the same problems.
Occasionally, I would say, basically that is just an endemic problem
with modern programming.
Basically, one of the reasons that I did this Windows platform layer
first is because now that we're basically done with it.
There's one of the things we'll do which before we go a little
further, but we'll do that next week.
Integrated with other things, which is file IO.
Basically, the reason I want to get this out the way first, it's so
from now on, we'll always be able to know exactly what's going on.
But there's always this bottom substrate that you don't know what's
going on.
And it's unfortunate when we do the Raspberry Pi Port will be able to
have a lot less of that.
But even then we'll still have like a little bit of firmware you
never, unless you actually built the firmware for the machine, that's
actually in the wrong.
There's always some call you eventually make which
Triggers some code, someone else wrote even in the dust days, you
like, would trigger an interrupt to do.
I owe or something like this.
You didn't actually write that exactly, you didn't burn the eeprom in
there, which, which talks to the, you know, the IDE controller or
something.
So, there you, you do have to, unfortunately, even though we're going
pretty low level in the Stream.
You do have to always be used to the fact that at some point, someone
else does take control of things.
Even if you were to burn the firmware yourself.
It's still being a circumstance where there's microcode executing on
the CPU and you didn't write that.
So there's always someone below you and you have to be comfortable
with that.
What we try to do on this stream is going.
As low as reasonably possible.
So you can see everything you might want to control and that you could
control.
But in terms of actually getting all the way down to some pure level,
there really isn't one.
So you're always going to have to draw that line somewhere.
We are basically trying to draw it as low as feasible, so that you
understand everything you might ever care about basically, but we're
not going to try and go down to a level of absurdity.
Where we're like, let's try and
A code, our own.
Let's burnt, let's make our own CPU and have it fabbed and then
program on that, right?
You could go that far.
We're not trying to do that.
Let's see.
Do you ever use a profiler or mostly use hand coded timer calls?
I mostly use hand-coded timer calls, but sometimes the profiler can be
useful.
Why do I use Pascal case for everything?
I just that's just how I tend to program.
I don't have a why?
I like how you name things?
Not really a why it's whatever is most comfortable to you.
Is it a violation to set one member of a union, then read from
another?
No, that's, that's totally legal, or at least it works on every
compiler I've ever used.
I was playing around the input code yesterday with a Dualshock 4.
And so I started thinking about when we would get around to
implementing raw input so we can handle those controllers natively.
Probably not for a long time actually because I don't really want to
spend a lot of your time looking at platform code especially because I
just I'm showing you how everything works, but I'm not like telling
you you have to do everything yourself.
Like if people want to use this simple directmedia layer, something
sdl.
Or whatever.
That's a totally fine decision and tons of people ship games on those
things.
So the goal here is not to teach you that you should Implement an
entire platform layer yourself.
The goal is to show you how to do that if you so that you understand
how everything is working, when you choose to use someone else's
library, and, you know that stuff or so that you can write a better
version of sdl yourself, if you chose to do so, right?
So that you have the ability to write all that stuff.
So I really want to focus on the game code and all that stuff more
because that stuff is important, no matter what you're doing.
Something you need to know no matter regardless of whether you how far
down the stack you choose to go.
So we won't do like raw input or something like that.
To wait at the end.
When we do the shipping version of our Windows platform layer, which
will have raw input and overlapped IO and all these are the sorts of
things.
But we're not going to focus on those.
Now, we're just doing the minimal Windows code now and we'll do the
hardcore Windows code way later way later.
Like, when the game is done.
Modern CPUs are DSC returns nominal clocks, not real clocks.
So that's Tom Forsythe.
Who, by the way, if people don't know, actually is someone who worked
on for example,
Larrabee project with Intel CPU team, he was at Intel for a while.
So he is more of a processor expert than I am certainly,
unfortunately, Tom.
I'm not the guy to try and explain how clocks get returned because I
have no idea.
Like basically, I don't know.
What a real clock is in the in the CPU vs.
A cycle in terms of what it's going to tell you.
So,
If you Tom want to point to post a good article about this because I
know you have a Blog, I would be delighted to point people towards it
tomorrow.
Well, not tomorrow on the next stream, on Monday, not saying you have
to, but if that's something you would like to clarify for people, I
would be happy to point to a, but I'm not the guy for that.
I don't know CPU architecture very well.
So if I tried to explain exactly what a cycle in the CPU was versus a
cycle in our dtsc.
I die.
I'm just going to get it wrong.
Plus also, the modern CPU thing.
I don't know where that modern change happened.
Like, I know the Pentium introduced the our dtsc, but I don't know
where the changeover happened from Rio clocks.
And nominal clocks, and so on.
Why are you avoiding doubles in your code?
Well, I never use doubles really, because they're much slower than,
than reals.
So, sometimes in timing I would use them.
But again, here, they're not necessary at all.
They're completely, they would be completely unnecessary for the
computer computation we were doing.
So I only use doubles if they're absolutely necessary.
And this case, they weren't and that's because they're half as fast,
usually?
Right.
You can do twice as many float operations, as you can double.
In the same amount of time.
That's just how that works.
Are you opposed to every using high-level languages and making games?
Mmm, so I'm not opposed to using high-level languages.
I'm not opposed to programming at a high level.
I'm opposed to high level languages because all the ones I've seen are
lousy.
If there was a high level language that work the way I want to
high-level language to work.
Then I would be super in favor of it.
But all the high-level languages I ever see are awful.
And I would never program in them.
Let's see if you want to lock the FPS at a particular number.
Would you just sleep or do something more complex?
Well, the easiest thing to do there is, if you can wait on the
vertical.
Retrace, that's the easiest way to do that.
And you can do that with direct with with direct.
Not direct2d directdraw still, you can still I think I got a handle
director.
Aw, and wait for the vertical blank when you are using direct3d or
opengl.
You can usually tell the
Swap command to wait for the V blank.
So the easiest way to lock to the monitor refresh frequency, which is
what you presumably were asking that question.
About, that's the easiest way to do it because then, you know, it's
actually locked to the monitor, which is what you would rather do than
try to fake that.
But if you want to lock to a particular frequency on your own, then
yes, you would sleep.
But before you can sleep, since sleep is 50, millisecond granular on a
lot of operating systems by default on a lot of Windows versions by
default.
You have to do a thing called setting, the you have to set the thread
frequent, the swed thread, the scheduler, wake up frequency, and
Stuff.
So you have to call time begin period, there's other stuff you have to
do.
So we'll look at that a little later, but it's not as easy as just
calling sleep.
I guess is what I would say, you got to do sleep and a spin lock, and
you got to tell windows that your sleep is most likely granular.
Let's see.
Isn't already TSE affected by variable speed Technologies in modern
processors like speed step.
So it depends what you mean by affected.
It's sort of is and sort of isn't like.
It depends what the what you were trying to get out of it.
So yes, the answer is definitely affected but and I think I talked
about that when I was talking about the fact that there was like all
sorts of things where like, it could change the in the middle of when
you retire me something could change the CPU frequency and stuff like
that.
That's what I was talking about.
Unfortunately again, I'm the wrong person to really say how that all
works out.
So like for example for all I know in a in in the latest CPUs, they
may do stuff like pretend the R&D team.
SC is always at 3.2, GHz, even if the processor down flat.
Like, I don't know what they do.
Now.
I have no idea.
All I know is what it says in the Intel architecture manual.
So, all I know is what it says here.
I don't know anything that's not in here.
So if you really want that answer and this is maybe we'll be lucky and
Tom Forsythe, since he piped up in the twitch chat.
Maybe on the hook.
Now you want to ask a processor expert?
To tell you exactly what happens there because I don't know.
And I don't pretend to know, I use our dtsc as a high, a high
frequency profiler tool because I know that I can use differences in
it to know if my code was getting faster.
I don't try to use it.
Most of the time for doing the kind of really precise optimization
work where I actually want to know how many actual Cycles really
happened.
I don't do that.
So I'm
I've never had to really go figure out on a modern like on a core i7.
Let's say what that actually means.
Have I done lu?
Damned ra no, I have not.
It's
And no, I probably would not be doing that.
Let's see.
Let's see here.
Can we do a bonus stream on azzam?
We will actually be doing Assembly Language in the Stream.
As far as intrinsics are concerned will be optimizing our code with
intrinsics.
And as I'm stream again much.
Like I'm the wrong person to tell you about exactly how CPU Cycles.
Get retired and reported.
I'm also the wrong person to tell you how to program Assembly
Language.
I like
I understood Xbox 360 Assembly Language extremely well because I wrote
an assembler Optimizer for it.
That is like the only Assembly Language.
I really know how to program at all.
Like I know how to read x86 and x64 Assembly Language because I need
it for debugging and I need it for like looking at what the compiler
did.
So I can sort of read it.
Okay, but I just I don't have the kind of experience that I would want
to have before I would sit up here and try to tell you how to program.
Exit for Assembly Language, so I would love it.
If someone like Jeff Roberts did a Assembly Language, programming
extreme.
I don't know if he would, probably won't, but like, I would love it if
someone who is a Assembly Language, programmer, who did a lot of
civilians.
Programming programming would do one, that would be fantastic and I
would watch that stream, probably learn a lot from it, but I'm just
the wrong for assembly from scratch is just not, I don't have the
experience for that and I it would just be
Be, it would not be a good quality education for anyone.
Let's see.
If you read the latency tables for sse2, float versus double, you'll
see that.
Double isn't that much slower than float on the CB it's half as fast,
dude.
You can do twice as many floats in a register, as you can doubles.
What, what are you talking about?
I'm not sure what he's talking about.
I'll look at the agner fog tables.
You're talking about that these tables, right?
We're let's see here.
This is ogner.
The, this is ogner fog.
He's a guy who posts a lot of good optimization stuff.
He does like performance analysis, on x86 64 processors any basically
post a bunch of these things here, you can see like for example,
there's instruction tables list of instruction latency through puts
and stuff and Mike.
Prop break down.
So you can jump in here and see, you know, basically, a bunch of
information that's not in the architecture reference manual.
So, you know, if you go through here, you can find, I guess those
would be in the P.
I don't remember what the double instructions are that these would be
in down in the pee, pee Moe.
So, there you go.
So yeah, I mean, basically, let's see here.
So is it actually reciprocal throughput?
Let's see here.
What are the instructions we want?
So that was what was that?
That was a divide?
So you're saying that the floating-point Divide should be the same
speed as you think it's it's the same speed as the floating or not the
same speed but roughly the same speed as the double with divided.
So let's take a look.
Look here.
Where is our P reciprocal?
Well, I guess we can look at multiply first.
So, where is our multiply?
It's like p-muls something soapy mall.
Where are you?
Let's move.
I can't.
There we go.
So, where are we here?
That's not.
That's, that's the integer.
You can tell the last thing I did was Bink.
I immediately go.
Look at the
Jury instructions, which are totally not what you actually wanted.
Let's see here.
Sorry, we're kind of the stream is technically over at this point, but
it's interesting question.
You might as well.
Look it up here and see what the actual what the actual stuff is
instruction set for SSE.
What are the actual things here?
Those are packed integer?
What is do?
You know what the instruction is?
Tell me what the
Reduction is for double.
If someone on the stream, knows what the multiply instruction is for
double.
So I can, I can look it up more quickly instead of having to look it
up on the stream here because I don't know.
I don't think I've ever actually admitted that I've never asked for
that intrinsic in my in my whole life.
So I have no idea what the what the where it actually is.
Do do, do do.
Yeah, what is it?
Tell me who on the stream.
Someone must know what the intrinsic is, what the actual instruction
is for doing a double multiply a CMD + S es e double multiply here.
Oh, here we go.
Well, PD.
There we go.
I don't know why.
So, I'm used to using all the pssc ones because I have to do a bunch
of integer work when I was working on pink and that was the most
recent SEC thing that I did.
So, here we go.
So,
PS Mo PD, that's what we want.
So packed, single Precision floating Point values.
Pack double-precision floating-point values from 0, PS and mole PD.
So now, if we look those up in the table, presumably, these are still
at alphabetical order.
No, they are not in alphabetical order.
They are by type.
So let's see.
Arithmetic instructions, other floating point.
There we go.
Floating-point xmm instructions.
Where is our Mall?
Where you know what?
Maybe I'll just search for it.
Well PS, there we go.
So mopey.
S, this is on an AMD.
So that's probably not so good.
Where is whereas x64 ck8 K10.
Bulldozer Steamroller Bobcat Jaguar.
Pentium 2 & 3 are on God.
Ivy Bridge, there we go.
Let's look at look at like has well, for example, that's a good one.
So these are just basically all the cores.
Sorry.
This is, this is probably not that interesting to most of the people
on the stream.
But basically all we're doing here is we're looking up in the
instruction tables which takes a while.
We're looking up, how long it takes the CPU to do operation on a
double versus operation on a single floating point.
So basically like 32 bit floating Point versus 64-bit floating-point,
so,
These are broken down by core because obviously Intel ships a lot of
different versions of their CPUs.
So there's basically, if you think about it, there's basically lots of
different potential throughput values.
How fast the processor can do something, depending on which processor,
it actually is.
So what we want to do here is we want to take a particular core, a
relatively recent court like Ivy Bridge, right?
Which is a, you know, relatively recent Intel Core and take a look at
how it does a mul PS.
Which is a single Precision floating Point X versus a mole PD.
So basically what I want to do is I want to search down through here.
So presumably it's somewhere right here.
That's has well, why can't we see Mo PS MLPs mole?
PS mul p.s.
I don't know why I can't see it because I'm searching for mul PS.
And this is where it is.
For some reason.
It says it's there.
I can't actually see a mole PS there, right?
It's supposed to be showing on the page right now, but where I don't
seem oh PS anywhere on here.
So let's take a look more PS.
MLPs Mi PS.
Mopey.
S.
Okay.
Ivy Bridge.
Mul PS.
So it's one it's single cycle.
Is that correct?
Single cycle and mole PD and what's this single?
Wait?
What's this?
What's this column here?
Where it's our home?
S, what's, what are our columns?
Here?
The latency?
So if you want to do one in reciprocal, throughput is here.
Okay, so that's what we want to see.
So basically the latency is from when we issue the instruction to,
when we get it back.
How many cycles will it be?
So if we issue one, when do we get the result back and reciprocal?
Throughput is basically how long it takes to get them.
If how
How should I say it?
It's basically if we issue them every clock.
So if we just kept issuing them one right after the other, then sort
of how long would it take to do each incremental one.
So,
Like, if we, if we took, if it takes a latency of 5 to do it, but we
can issue one.
Every clock will start getting them back every clock that we issue.
So we could still have a, it's essentially an effective throughput of
one.
Even though we technically have to wait five for any given results
come back.
We haven't talked about that that has to do with CPU pipelining and so
that's a kind of a thing that we haven't gotten to yet.
But anyway, it looks like mul PS here, takes its a five Cycles.
Latency that looks like and a one cycle, throughput and mull.
PD is exactly the same.
Right?
So, basically, it's exactly what I said.
It's half as fast, right?
So I said it was half as fast and it's half as fast.
So I don't know, whatever the person who run the twitch chat is, I'm
not sure why you were saying that, it wasn't massively slower.
It's half as fast to do doubles as it is to do to do singles.
So, if half is fast, doesn't bother you.
I don't know.
What does that's like the difference between 60 frames a second and 30
frames a second, right?
That's, that's massive, but I don't know.
Alright.
Alright, so there we go.
Let's see.
We're still, you know what, it's kind of a lazy day and we kind of had
a
I'm going to keep going on the questions.
Why not?
Let's take a look.
What are your thoughts on Swift?
I've never seen it.
I mean, I know what it is, but I've never seen it, but I think of drop
them flows, programming language.
I think it's awesome so far.
I really like just to see when he actually gets something that that
he's willing to release.
I will be playing around with it.
Let's see what I think I should you do to try to be linked up.
Org.
I don't know what dealing dot or is but I can certainly look at it.
Do you have any discussions with Jonathan bonus compiler?
And what sort of features you'd like to see?
Yes, we discussed it all the time, but he and I don't have similar
programming Styles in some ways.
So
You know, I tell him we talked about sort of things and I you know,
sort of tell him what the tortoise, I would like.
And we also go over sort of stuff that he would like.
And so we definitely talked about it a lot but he has different goals
for language necessarily in mind.
Then sort of where I would necessarily go if I was doing a language,
so I try not to push him.
I don't I don't want to make his language into something.
That is what I would want, see necessary to language because you can't
make one language that does everything thing and he's going for a very
specific thing and I think
He's doing a really good job at that.
And so usually when we talk about it, it's less about me saying what I
would like to see in his language and more about brainstorming stuff
about how to accomplish, what he's trying to accomplish in the
language.
Because I would like to see that language be the best at that because
we do definitely need that as well.
And so I'm interested in seeing his language, go, where he wants it to
go, not where I want to go, if that makes sense.
Let's see.
Do I ever write functions like printf to take very large it sometimes
but usually only they're usually debugging functions.
Would you consider using a templated type safe version of printf?
Even though you hate templates?
No, templates are never worth the pain in my opinion.
So no matter what they do.
I wouldn't probably use them.
Let's see.
Let's take a look here.
If there is one book, you would, if it's half as fast, only, if you do
millions of operations.
Now, it's half as fast.
As long as you do 5 or more, right?
Well, it's half as fast, no matter how many you do, because it's
exactly the same timing.
So if you do any, it's half as fast, right?
Whatever, the piece of code was, it's half as fast in in.
In in float, as long as you're doing for operations or more.
If you're long as you're doing it on four or more floats, it happens
fast.
Okay, what low-level language would you suggest to someone new to
low-level programming?
Well, I think C is usually the one that's why I'm using it in for this
stream.
Are we using the win32 API?
But compiling for 64 bits.
Do we need to compile for 32 bits for when XP support.
And it looks like we have in 64 and real 64 in the CBP.
So, yes, we do need to compile for 32 bits for the next 50 support,
and we will be doing that.
But no, you don't have to worry about in 64 is in real 64's.
Those both work on 32-bit Windows as well.
They're just slower.
So as long as we don't use hardly any of those, we will be fine.
As long as we don't use in 64, is in real, 64 is being super critical
code, then we'll be fine.
In game development.
Do you follow Enterprise design patterns or do you have some different
design patterns?
No, we do not follow Enterprise design patterns, may be some people
game developers do.
I certainly don't follow any Enterprise design patterns?
Definitely not.
Sorry.
What do you use for collections?
If you do not use templates, I usually use just something hand coded
for whatever the situation is.
I didn't get the outcome of the mall PS.
Mopey dick a the latency packing was the same.
How does that end up being double time?
Okay, that's a good question.
I didn't really go into detail on this because it wasn't really, I
didn't really super wanna talk about it much because I was just trying
to make sure that the person who's writing in the twitch chat was, was
not correct about it, but basically because I want to correct what I
said if it was, but basically what I'm saying here is there's two
commands.
That you can issue.
Well, PS and multi D.
Okay.
Both of these commands take five Cycles to return, right?
So five Cycles to complete and they have one cycle throughput so you
can basically
Issue them every clock and get them back, five clocks later.
And so you can essentially do one per cycle.
If you get up to speed.
But we don't actually care about that at the moment.
And we're not going to talk about that much for purposes of what
you're asking.
All we need to know is both mul PS and mold PD have exactly the same
specified timings in the timing tables.
So, if you execute them all PS or you execute them all PD.
It's basically the same, right?
The
Timing.
So, the reason I said, it's half as fast to use doubles, which is this
one.
This is real 64.
And this is real 32.
The reason it's half as fast is these instructions are the same with
both instructions, operate on 128, bits worth of data, basically, and
128 bits /, 32 bits, right for a real 32 means you can pack for real
32s into
And register, right?
So basically mole PS operates on for real 32s.
At the same time.
If you call Mal PS, you can do for floating Point operation for two
floating Point multiplies.
At the same time, real 64's on the other hand.
It's still operating on 128 bits, but now you're dividing by 64 bit.
So you only have two real 64's that can fit into one register.
So, what I was saying is that if you're doing anything at all, like,
basically, if you're doing
Any more than three operations?
Then doubles are half as fast because basically, as long as you can do
for four of them at once, you will get twice the speed because this
instruction takes the same amount of time as this instruction, but
does twice as many multiplies, so hopefully that makes some sense.
Let's see.
Due to do.
So you say someone says was saying in the Stream, if you're ready some
because then you care.
Otherwise, you don't and what you're writing is not same D.
So no, that's not true.
So yes, this particular very specific example, may not be Cindy.
But literally the thing we will use it for is totally Cindy.
You will have a bunch of cycle counts from all the different places in
your program that you sample the performance counter, you will then
need to do a bunch of subtracts on them.
You will then need to do a bunch of divides on them.
You will are multiplied as on them or in stripper clothes on them and
you can do all of those completely Cindy because they're exactly the
same operations.
So no, this will be totally symbolized and it will be totally slower
if you decide to use doubles.
Now if I'm totally fine with someone saying that you won't have enough
of these to care about the fact that it's slower, but it is half as
fast.
That's just
That's just the truth.
So whenever you write code like this, unless it's literally, the only
time you think you will ever do it, which for performance profiling,
we know it won't be, will be taking hundreds of samples of our dtsc
and not maybe hundreds of the query performance counter, but will at
least be taking hundreds of our dtsc samples per frame.
So, if you're going to then do operations on them, if you can move it
down to 32-bit, those operations will be twice as fast period, but if
you don't care if you're like, I don't care how fast that is.
I just want to do it in 64-bit and I know since that we're only doing
like a hundred operations.
Maybe that doesn't matter because 100 isn't that many in processor
terms.
That's fine.
But understand the difference between saying you don't care and saying
it's not faster because those are different statements.
Let's see.
Yes, msv.
See, will often not pack things without intrinsics for you
potentially.
No, actually, I missed VC does have a way of doing that automatically
for if you want to, but yes, we will do all of our own intrinsics for
all of our own floating Point operations because it's just usually
easier to explicitly.
Tell the compiler, how you would like to do packed instructions, but
no both llvm.
Well, I should say, I have experience with lvm doing this.
I don't know about msec, but I believe it also does this.
You can Auto vectorize a loop just fine.
You don't have to msec, will totally output it for you.
At least.
That was my assumption.
I know llvm will llvm.
Will trivially output it for you.
You can just say that this thing is vectorized and it'll tow.
It has Loop vectorization built-in.
So, it just totally does that.
So I'm not sure what you're saying that it won't output that it
totally does that, but that maybe I'm SVC is like behind the times on
that, but llvm is not.
And and saying that the compiler won't up output vectorized code for
this is also not true.
You just have to do more of them.
And it totally could.
It totally could do that.
It could totally vectorize this.
If we were, if we had say, 20 performance counters, and we wanted to
vectorize them.
You could totally have llvm Auto vectorize the loop for you.
That's not, that's not hot at all or IPC.
If you were using that.
I don't know about msec because I don't use them as we see a whole lot
these days.
So whether msec will output it, I'm not sure.
I thought they had Auto V.
Relation msec, but maybe they don't because mstc does kind of tend to
lag behind but llvm will totally Auto vectorize that for you.
Let's take a look here.
And also Tom Forsythe, and Forsythe says, he has a rant on double
Precision.
So let's take a look at that since it's right in the Stream here.
Let's take a look.
He says it is at HTTP.
See here.
I'm going to try to decode this URL, 5T bah.
He posted this in the Stream.
This webpage is not available, Tom.
What's going on here?
Okay, there we go.
It's got to.
Okay.
So here is the link.
You can read it off here.
And here is his rant on double Precision.
So I don't know what it is.
Basically.
I don't know exactly what he's ranting about.
But Tom usually has interesting things to say, so if you want to read
about it all but certain I will go read it later.
Here it is.
I'll leave that up on the screen for people who want it.
Will we take msv?
See all the way to shipping or will you use llvm even on Windows?
I would already just be using llvm for everything.
If you could actually use it on Windows, but right now they haven't
gotten to the point where you really can.
Basically, if you want to use llvm on Windows right now.
You have to switch to using a GDB base to bugger, like a dwarf base to
bugger and the like QT Creator or something like that.
And those are worse than M sbc's debugger and stuff.
And
Basically, like what I would say is.
If llvm was at the point where I could ship Windows stuff with it, I
already would be doing that.
There would be no msv.
See in the picture, but it's not quite there yet.
Believe me, the day that it is.
There.
I am off M, SV C so fast because I don't like em SVC at all.
I have no interest in using it, but it's tool chain is more mature on
Windows.
And so I have to sort of stay on that on windows, for a number of
reasons, but when they get to the point, when you can have a totally
good experience using elevators,
On Windows, I am totally switching.
So yeah, if they did that in the middle of handmade hero, we just
read.
Go ahead and switch for sure, but I don't think they're going to have
that ready in the next year or so.
Maybe, you know, if we're lucky.
I know there's people working on it.
So
and you can, I mean, you can't actually do it.
You can't compile Windows code with llvm.
There's just a bunch of caveats, basically.
What's an intrinsic?
So an intrinsic such a thing that we will be looking at later that
basically is.
So we kind of again.
This is jumping the gun a bit.
But since we're kind of at we're way past time.
Now, we're just kind of having fun on the stream and I like having fun
on the stream.
Basically, an intrinsic is just something that tells the compiler.
It's it's something that looks like a function call.
And in fact, we've already used one this one.
It's something that looks like you're calling a function, but actually
what it is.
It's a hint to the compiler that what you want it to do is apply a
specific Assembly Language instruction.
And so we can sort of see how that works.
Like this looks like a function call, right?
It looks like we're calling a function called our dtsc and that
function is returning and cycle count.
But if you actually step into the call, right?
Right here and take a look at the Assembly Language.
That was generated.
You will notice that.
No, actual function call has been generated instead.
What's generated is a straight-up are TTC.
Pretty awesome.
Right.
So basically, an intrinsic is a thing that allows you to direct the
compiler to do a certain thing in Assembly Language that it can emit
directly in line that it doesn't have to think about a function called
or C programming or any of that stuff.
It can just know, okay, wants me to get the time stamp counter here.
I know how to do that directly on the CPU.
I'm just going to do it.
Right and that's what that is.
So the reason we were talking about them for Cindy is because see
Unfortunately was designed a long time before this concept of Cindy.
Cindy is for people who don't know, and we'll talk about this more
later.
But Cindy is basically an acronym simd.
It stands for single instruction comma.
If you will multiple data, and what it basically means is normally,
when CPUs were first created, they typically did.
Nations on one thing.
So if I say something like this and I then go Z equals x times y,
write this kind of a thing makes sense.
I expect to see some code outputted.
That is just going to do a multiply that says multiply X by y, right.
So there's one piece of data in Acts 1 piece of data in why I multiply
the two together and I get Z.
So it's single instruction single data, instant.
But modern processors have found that.
It's much more efficient because of the way instructions are encoded.
And so that it can, it can know basically because you tend to do
expensive things, you know, the expensive parts of your code, tend to
work on big batches of stuff.
Lots of pixels, lots of vertices that sort of thing.
It tends to be that you want to do the same instruction to a lot of
things at once, you want to multiply a lot of values, by a lot of
other values.
In a batch.
So you don't have to actually issue as many instructions.
If the processor gives you way to say.
Hey, look, I'm going to say one instruction, and I want you to
multiply these 16 things by these other 16 things just do them all
with one multiply.
So I can just basically load 16 things into register, 16 things to
another register.
That's really wide.
They're very wide registers, 128 bits, 26 bits, 512 bits, right?
Pack a bunch of different values into those registers for floating
Point values.
8 floating Point values.
16 floating Point values in one register.
So that when I say multiply this register, by this other register,
it's not just doing one multiply it's effectively doing.
For multiplies a multiplies 60 multiplies at a time.
So it saves on the instruction encoding and it saves on the
understanding of the logic that the processor has to do, but it could
do a lot more multiplier.
You're basically the arithmetic unit.
The thing that's doing the actual multiplies in the processor can be
this huge wide giant multiplier.
That does, you know, tons of multiplies in parallel and the the logic
that's actually driving can be very simple, just goes.
Okay, we're doing a x 60 multipliers go instead of having to go.
Okay, grab the two things.
Do a multiply grab the two things to multiply 16 times, right?
So what Cindy is is Cindy is that that concept that there's a single
instruction that operates on multiple data.
Multiple things at once and does a symmetric the same operation to
each of those pieces of data.
And so typically what it corresponds to is wide registers, registers
that you have one name for.
So I call this register, something XM, M, 0, or something.
I have one name to the register, but actually that register is
separated into buckets that contain multiple discrete 32-bit
floating-point values.
Now, the reason this up impacts are floating point in double situation
is because obviously, you can fit twice as many floats into the same
space as
I have doubles.
I'm gonna fit for doubles in something.
I can fit eight floats in there.
So if you're doing Cindy and assembly instructions, all took the same
amount of time, which as we saw, they did in the case of multiply,
then doing it in doubles, is half as fast as doing it in singles,
because you can only do half as many doubles you going to fit, have
some a doubles in the register.
Hopefully, that makes some sense.
Yeah, that's a good point.
So somebody was reminding us.
We stucco to in here to ask for optimized build and what we should
probably do is switch back to that because we're not, we're not doing
optimization yet.
So, we'd rather have a debug build because debug builds are easier to
understand and read.
Basically, they're easier to look at because the compiler hasn't
rearranged everything and smushed instructions and optimize things
out.
So when we're trying to learn, it's much better to work in debug mode
where the processor doesn't.
Actually, doing a better job the optimizer off so that we can see
everything explicitly.
All right, we're running up into the end of the stream here.
So last couple questions, isn't it?
A pain to work in Windows?
Specially the programmer?
No more so than anywhere else.
I like working in Windows, actually, the best of any platform because
the debugger is the best.
It's the best of Bugger.
I like working on Linux because I don't have to fuss a lot with.
Like, I don't have to every time I install a machine.
I don't have to call.
All Microsoft for permission and you know have it authorized my
machine and all this other nonsense.
Like I don't have to deal with all of that stuff.
I don't have to do, all the weird installation process, the package,
managers and stuff online, explain X are really good, that sort of
stuff.
So there are things I like about Linux better.
But the debug the debuggers are awful on the next they're just they're
just awful.
And so I do like programming on Windows, probably the best because the
debugger is the best if and when people come out with a really good
debugger for Linux, then I think there's probably nothing really that
I like better.
Better on Windows anymore, but it's so it's not really a pain on
Windows.
No, it's fine.
Let's see here.
Didn't we want to start adding wordings?
Yes, probably Monday.
I think we'll turn on a higher warning, level, and, and talk about
what that means.
And and why we care.
Let's see.
I think that's about it for questions on the Stream.
Yeah, so it looks like that's it for questions on the stream.
So, thank you so much for joining us, for a nice lazy, handmade hero,
and Ice to our handmade hero.
Sometimes, it's fun to go.
A little bit long, when we have the time for it.
Thank you so much.
Everyone for joining me.
I know that we're at not the normal time.
So I feel like probably it's anyone.
Who's on the stream is a rather dedicated handmade here.
We're not at our normal 8 p.m.
Timeslot, this hopefully this weekend.
Again.
I keep saying hopefully.
But I haven't quite had time to really fully wrestle.
All the CSS web programming is so slow, in my opinion because of all
the, the wrangling try and get things to look.
Okay, when you're using other people's code and stuff.
So we're still on the email.
So if you want to email question, got an email in here that will be
changing to forums at just as soon as I could finish up the CSS
nonsense.
Again, if you would like to follow a home at the source code and the
art assets, as we, as we start to have them, if you'd like to
pre-order the game, you can pre-order it here and that gives you a
link where you can always download the latest source code and latest
art assets.
As we start to work with art assets coming next week and so on.
So handmade here a.org is your source for anything that you actually
need.
You.
Don't get the video archive and the Twitter where we where we post
times and stuff like that.
So check that out and otherwise, thank you very much address.
I hope to see you here for the next ring, which will be Monday at 8
p.m.
Pacific Standard Time, hope that you have enjoyed this dream and we
will see you then.
Thanks everyone for joining us.