And there we go.
Alright.
Hello everyone.
And welcome to breakfast edition of handmade hero.
The show where we eat a nutritious breakfast.
I was actually just eating chocolate chip cookies, which I agree.
Is not the most nutritious breakfast.
Don't try that at home.
I'm a professional.
And I'm at, I'm trained to eat chocolate chip cookies.
So that's not a good idea in general, but I happen to be instructive
cookies for breakfast.
That's just the way it went.
And we don't need to harp on that.
Okay, we don't need to focus on the unhealthy diet.
What we need to focus on instead is handmade hero.
The only show where we code a complete game from scratch.
No engine.
No libraries, powered, entirely by chocolate chip cookies, apparently
at this point, but you know, whatever works, right?
You gotta, You Gotta Eat what's around?
I'm not letting it go to waste.
Let's put it that way, right?
It's being it's being conscientious about the food supply, eating
chocolate chip cookies.
Someone's got to do it.
You wouldn't want to have that food.
Go to waste anyway.
Today we are going to finally do something that's been on our to-do
list for a long time, which is to make our storage of the world
actually, sparse.
Even if it means it won't be particularly efficient because we're not
really at that point yet, but we need to actually take the step and
make it actually sparse.
So we're going to need a bunch of time to do that, and to talk about
the concepts involved there.
So what I would like to do
Is, I would like to jump straight into that, so quickly.
I will just say that anyone who has pre-ordered the game from handmade
hero dot-org.
You should have gotten a link in your email and that link should have
had the ability to download a zip file.
That zip file has a bunch of smaller Zips in it.
We are on day 55 today.
So, you want to unzip day, 54 is zip file, that would put you at the
same place that I am, so that you can code along with me.
And what's more fun than coding, along with me, really?
You know, it's like those old when Bill Cosby used to do picture
pages.
I don't know if
Also remembers that he used to do picture pages that was before he was
embroiled in Scandal.
Of course, it would be a very different picture pages, what he would
draw today, might be very different.
Anyway, let's go ahead and get back to where we were.
I also wanted to someone was saying we had a typo in our code.
Of course, it's code that doesn't work anyway, because we haven't done
the first thing yet, but we should fix the typo because then once we
do get The Spar stuff in wonder why it's not working.
The typos, will be it inside our set camera call.
We essentially had a greater than or we have our greater than or less
than Z.
And we actually had one of them flips.
You can see, I've got the X greater than tile X less than equal to Max
tile, but the Y is in the wrong.
Wrong order there, right?
So that's no good.
But that is, again this, this actually won't work because of the
sparseness problem, which we talked about earlier.
Basically, what we decided to do is to not support wrapping anymore,
but we don't support sparseness.
So let me quickly go to the white board and explain what that is for
people who aren't quite sure, or who are just joining us.
This will kind of just clarify where we're at, and why we need to do
what we're doing.
So what we decided to do early on this was just a design requirement
of that.
I decided to impose.
Again, you don't necessarily have to do this, but the desired
requirement.
I decided to impose just to show how we would handle it and it does
have some nice benefits.
I decided that we wanted our worlds coordinates to basically allow for
four billion tiles by four billion tiles.
Essentially.
If you thought of the world of the tile map, for example, which is
obviously very very large and what we
We're doing before, is we just kind of started creating the world at 0
0, which kind of makes some sense, but what we would like to do, we
decided that we didn't want to support the concept of wrapping around,
which is to say what happens when you go past the 00 tile this
direction and you come back on over here.
And the reason that this is important is because if you think about
what happens to numbers when they wrap, so if we have zero, right?
If we have zero and we start going below it, if it's a signed number,
it starts going to -1 -2 and so on.
But if it's an unsigned number, right then in and that's what its
meaning is.
If it's an unsigned number, it's slips 24 billion, right?
When you go, when you subtract 1 from 0, you actually go straight up
to 2 to the 32nd minus 1, which is this the you know, the number way
up here.
And so that poses a lot of problems for things that want to use
boundaries.
So if I want to look at a bounds like a rectangle in this space, what
will happen is if I see if I'm past if I'm if I'm somewhere near the
edge here, somewhere near the zero Edge and I do a subtraction to sort
of see what's over here.
I'm actually going to start looking over here.
Now, that's fine for some things where you're just direct indexing, it
will work.
But if you're trying to do greater than or less than it won't work,
because this is a very high number.
So, if you tried to think that this is the men, and this is the max,
right?
This is the man and this is the max of your bounds index.
And I'm going to do a like, is something in between them.
So is it greater than the man?
Is it less than the max kind of a thing that will only work?
When this is inside this region when it straddles, the - lock the zero
line there, or when it straddles, the four billion, the, to 230, s
minus one line, right?
2 to the 32nd, minus 1, which is the highest 32-bit number.
So it's like, for billions and change.
If we're looking at that, it won't work anymore because the men
actually becomes very high.
Iteration would still work, but we'd have to make sure that all of our
iterations were super careful to not use greater than or less than,
and always just used careful math, to make sure that they check for
not equals to, and do other things like this.
And never try to take the length of something like, never try to look
at how long something is that way and all these are the sorts of
things, right?
So, we've got a bunch of stuff that we would have to constantly be
aware of.
Now if we can do it, but it just didn't seem necessary because if we
start the world growing here,
And we imagine growing out the world.
We can make a totally huge world that just fits in the middle.
Not have to worry about these potential wrapping bug.
So we basically don't gain anything from handling, the rapping bugs
because we'd never actually need to make a world.
That's quite that big right?
We could make a world.
Let's just three billion by three billion and fits in that Center and
we'd be fine.
Right?
So what we want to be able to do is start somewhere here.
We want to be able to start somewhere at 2 to the 32nd over to or
something, right?
We want to be able to start it kind of up there.
And so what we need to figure out is we need
To figure out how to actually make that happen.
Now.
The reason that we can't do that directly at the moment is because we
haven't actually written the storage system for the world yet.
Really.
We just kind of put a little hacky thing in there while we were
working on it.
And so what we did was we basically direct access to the world.
By saying we have an array right of tile chunks, which are basically
groupings.
I think we said they were 16 by 16 at the moment of sort of sections
of the world that are 16 tiles by 16 tiles roughly and we just made an
actual dense array of them that centered right here.
So if we wanted to start at a point that was in the center of the
world and we actually still use the same system.
It would cost too much memory even just to store these tile chunks,
right?
Because that would be too.
The 32nd over to right?
Which is just, you know, 2231, right.
So it would be that far in.
If I'm not mistaken, excuse me.
Sometimes you just got to get one chocolate chip cookie in just to
keep you going.
You know what, I'm like, a little hit.
There, there, baby, Taco chip cookies.
I mean, this is what I'm talking about.
Right.
I mean that's not even.
That's a breakfast food at that size.
As far as I'm concerned.
Right?
Right.
I mean, that's look at that.
That's not.
How could that be?
Unhealthy?
It's hardly.
I mean, it's like a 1/16 of a cookie or something, right?
But no matter.
Don't worry about that for now.
We can talk about cookies later point being.
What we need to do is figure out a way to not have to store tile maps.
All the way up to that Center Point, right now, if we wanted to just
cheese it for now.
Which we totally could do if we wanted to.
Because again, we're just trying to figure out how the system works.
We could just re-center our coordinate system so that 00 was like here
or something like that.
Whatever.
But what I'd rather do is get things working with arbitrary
coordinates just so we can see if we have any problems with actually
having Tiles at coordinates.
There it is there any like unforeseen problems that we would be having
blah blah blah, right?
So if I wanted to do that, what I would like to be able to do is I'd
like a system where I can just store tile chunks wherever they
actually happen to occur and not have to have a whole giant array for
indexing them.
That's going to have that that sort of problematic penalty that I was
talking about, in terms of basically, you know, having to store a
continuous dense, set of them.
So that way we could be truly sparse and actually just fill in tile
chunks where we need them.
So we can have kind of sinewy.
Brawling World paths that don't pay a cost for their entire rectangle
footprint.
In terms of memory that only store sort of right along where the paths
actually go and where the player can actually go rather than doing
this kind of weird sort of forced or a thing.
So I'm not sure yet what the best way to do this would be, I don't
know.
So I'm going to pick one method and try it and we'll see how it goes.
And it'll probably be the method that we use here when we're just sort
of working stuff through.
But later on when we do the final world system, you know, we may think
harder about exactly how we should make it work.
I don't know.
But the point is what I've decided to do is I decided to just try
using a hash table because that's an easy thing.
We can implement, it gets us sparseness, and it's relatively
performant in terms of the stuff that we might need it to do.
I think we'll see.
So, what's a hash table for people who don't necessarily know what a
hash table is.
Well, a hash table is usually a linear array, right?
So we basically have a zero slot and we've got some number of slots up
to, you know,
N minus 1, slots 0 and N length hash table, but it has n elements in
it.
It's got, you know, zero through n, minus 1 just like a standard
linear array.
And each one of these things is an entry in the slot, right?
What a hash table is.
It's a way of taking something that you would like to have addressed
as one giant array and collapsing it down to a much smaller array for
storage.
Knowing that it is sparse.
Right?
So, what we actually have is we have x y&z coordinates for our tile
chunks, right?
We can have a three, we basically have a three-dimensional world, and
we can have X Y & Z entries for our child chunks.
If we wanted to store these in memory, we would have to do basically
each one of these can be for a billion wide, right?
So we'd have to do for a billion by four billion, by four billion,
would have to be the size of the array that we stored which is
obviously impossible.
Like, there's not enough memory in the world for that.
Right.
There's probably enough memory in the world for this much, but not
that much right for billion computers times.
GB of memory, you know, whatever.
Anyway, point being, this is too much.
And so what we need to do is say well, okay, but we know that this is
just the addressing scheme.
This is just the giant cube in which the world exists, but we're only
going to make a very small were only going to populate a very small
fraction of it.
We just don't know what fraction we're going to populate.
We want the world generator to be able to be freely.
Make very long skinny, things, it wants to or dense regions.
And we want the storage system to just cope and be able to fit this in
a
Nothing, but such that we can still access it via these coordinates,
right?
So, the way we would do this in with a hash table is, if you imagine
taking these as your actual Index, right?
How would we do this?
We have 32 bits of this, 32 bits of this, 32 bits of this, right?
If we were to pack those together, we would get numb one number which
basically looks like this, right?
It's 32 bits 32 bits, 32 bits, and we could pack it.
However, we wanted zyx or something like that.
Right?
And we'd have one number.
That would be the index into a
Giant array.
That was this big.
And when we looked in there, we would find our tiles.
Now granted.
We said that our tiles are 16 by 16.
So technically these are actually, you know, 16 is 2 to the fourth,
right?
So technically it's really more like the 28, right?
So we actually have 28 bits each here, right?
If we wanted to really talk about how many we have for tile chunks,
right?
Chunks, not tiles.
So, if we're talking about that, and we don't know what this number
because we could expand it to 32 by 32 as well.
And then it was reduced to 27, B, but point being, it's gonna be
something like that.
It's gonna be in the ballpark 24:28, something like that.
If we made a large number out of it, we could just do that by
concatenating the bits together, right?
And just have one really big number.
That's just a very long number, right?
It's something like a 90 bit number or something like this, right?
And then, we would use that 90 bit number to index into a giant array.
And that's the thing that we can't do.
So, the question is,
Can we do that similar to this process that takes advantage of the
sparseness of the array that we know that most of the entries are not
filled, right?
In order to give us something that has similar characteristics to a
nice fast array, look up, but which allows us to collapse the array
down to something quite small that does fit in memory, and that works.
Okay.
And so, a hash table is a pretty obvious choice for something like
this.
What it does is is you make some kind of a mapping some kind of a
function that takes this imaginary number that you've created with the
with the three with the impossibly large number and the mapping just
flat-out.
Reduces the B, A lossy mapping.
So let's say that we wanted to store this in, you know, a 16-bit
array, a 16 bits worth of array space.
So we had
Six entries in it, right?
Maybe that's even a little bit large.
Let's say is 4096 entries, right?
So we have
As a 96, entries in our array, let's say right?
That makes sense.
That's to the 12th.
If I'm not mistaken right to the 850.
68 is 256.
Ninth is 512, 1024 1112.
Yeah, so 2 to the 12.
So let's say we want to to the 12.
So we've got a 2 to the 90 or something thereabouts and we want to map
it to a 2 to the 12, right?
And you could imagine ways that we could do this without thinking it
through to carefully.
The, the most obvious way we could you guys just throw away some of
the bits, right?
We could just flat-out throw away some of the bits.
So we can take just a few bits from each one of these right 2 to the
12th.
Let's say we could take four bits from each of these just randomly,
whichever for a b, we decide take for a bit from each of these instead
of taking all 28 bits or all 30 bits or however many bits there
actually were and we could produce another number, so we could
basically produce this other number that we know is only 2 to the 12th
big, right?
And it's only got four bits of x.
It's got four bits of y, + 4 B of Z.
Right?
And now we know we could use this to address into an array, right?
And that is called the hash function.
The thing that takes basically the this big number and turns it into
the smaller number is the hash function.
Now it when when you're really trying to make a hash work well.
Typically, you do not just throw a b away like that.
You actually think about the patterns of the bits and what they're
likely to take.
And you try to make a function that will minimize what are called
collisions, which we'll talk about in a second, but regardless of how
you think about it.
So I guess what I'm saying is, I'm simplifying here by suggesting you
just concatenate.
The B.
Oftentimes hash functions will do something more fancy than that.
Like they'll mix the bits together.
They'll multiply numbers together, shift them, add them.
They'll do more complex operations, such that.
It's not like, it's just for a bit from each.
It's more like a mixture of them.
Also.
It's really usually to completely new number here.
That isn't identifiable by B that came directly from the previous, but
this would still be a totally valid hash function is just not typical.
So I just wanted to clarify that.
But point being, that's what the hash function is.
So essentially what you've got,
In fact, I guess I don't really need to delete that.
I forget that Creek I can just kind of scroll over.
So what you've got is something which takes you know, a is that
working.
There we go, that takes sort of a to, to the large amount and Maps it
to to a to, to the small amount, right?
So that this becomes feasible to store in the array and then inside
the array.
We now know that we can just look up in there and get the tile trunk
that we wanted.
So we do that map.
Calm down.
So let's say we wanted to get some random number that we wanted to get
the XYZ a thing, right?
We map it down from the large space that that's into a small space.
We can look it up in the array.
We grab the thing that's in there and that gives us our top junk.
Right.
That would literally work almost exactly the same way that we have
things.
Now, only instead of forcing us to store stuff in this, in this sort
of giant dense array.
If we want to do the whole world, now, we can store any any number we
want it.
We don't even have to initialize the bounce to be anything other than
just that initial small amount the, for however, many tile chunks
maximum.
We wanted was all we have to do in there.
Okay.
So what's obviously, it's not magic.
That can't be the only thing because if that was true, you'd just
always do that.
And then,
Magically, you just have smaller memory for everything.
Right?
Well, of course, there obviously is a problem with that, which is
that, since this right here was sparse, right?
You're taking advantage of some of that sparseness.
And so, that's one of the things, right?
But the big thing is, you can have what are called collisions, right?
So, if we're only using some bits of X, some bits of Y, and some bits
of z or r, whatever our hash function, miss, it mixes them up in ways
that Matt from a large coordinate space to a small one.
Right, then obviously you can get to things that were different sets
of numbers that both map to the same slot.
So, you know, I have another set here ABC and ABC and XYZ when they go
through this hash function, right?
Both map to this slot, right?
So both XYZ and ABC both compute through the hash function into some
small number.
And it turns out they both come up with 27.
So we
Look in here and we go.
Oh crud.
We don't have any room to store the second thing because we already
have someone there and it's not this guy, right?
So hash tables need to have in order to function an additional sort of
conceptual thing that regular arrays don't have which is they need to
have Collision handling, right?
So that's called a collision when two things they Collide essentially,
right to things which have different coordinates in the
Space both map to the same coordinates in the small space in that 1D
array space, that we're trying to use for storage.
That's called a collision.
And so we need a way of handling those collisions and there's two
typical ways of handling them and I'll talk about them both.
So, one way.
There's actually lots of different things here.
It's a whole field, but I'm going to talk about two specific ones.
Okay.
Let's expand, its expand our Horizons.
Oh, I keep forgetting any time.
I expand it clears with the wrong color Frita.
Alright, ever mined got a ride to drawing app.
So many things that have to get done.
What you going to do?
All right.
So let's say we've got this situation.
Right, and I'm just going to talk about two elements, A and B.
Now we can forget about the coordinates.
But they both map to the same slot in the hash space.
They both mad to slot 3 or something, right?
And we need to store them.
So the first thing we need to do is recognize that we need to know
when collisions happen.
An array.
Usually just stores something in it.
Right, but we can't do that anymore.
We have to store both the thing and the coordinates, right?
The original coordinates of the thing in the hash lot, because when
something goes into the hash or when someone looks up something in the
hash, we have to be able to look at what's in that hash Le and say is
it actually the thing you wanted?
Because again, if this guy had some coordinates x y z and this other
guy had, you know X2 Y2 Z2, right?
Or whatever in here.
When we go to look up X, Y X2, Y2, Z2.
We have to be able to see that the if like be was currently in hash
lot 3, we have to be able to see that b is not a and if we just
stored, whatever the data is, you know, I don't know what these things
are carrying data.
This carries a 5 and this carries a for if all we see, is the data
five or the data.
For when one of these guys goes in there, when the next guy comes and
looks up there.
It may think.
Oh, the thing that's in there must be the
That's it.
X2 Y2, Z2, but surprised it wasn't.
It was the thing that was at XYZ and you'll get back a for instead of
a five when you asked for.
What was it X2, Y2 Z2, right.
So the first thing you need to do is store the actual coordinates
inside so that you can compare them and know whether you've got the
right one or not, right?
So that's the first thing that has to happen.
And the second thing that has to happen is when you see that, you
don't have the right one.
You have to do something about it, right?
Okay.
And there's two ways you can do something about it.
Usually these are called, I shouldn't say there's two ways.
There's probably a lot more than two ways.
But there's two common ways one is called internal chaining and one is
called external chaining.
Right.
And sometimes this is also called probing.
And so on, there's there's a there's a bunch of terminology here and
it's been a long time since I've ever read any formal literature on
this.
So I apologize if I'm not using the terms 100% precisely, but I'll
explain what they are.
And you can go to like, try to read the Wikipedia page or something.
And and if you want the precise terminology for anything.
All right.
So what ends up happening is there's two sort of basic strategies that
I see people use and that I use one is just to essentially turn the
entries in
To a linked list, right?
So you have an array and that array is some fixed size.
Right?
Like we've got, you know, 256 entries in the array or something.
We mapped to the 286 entries.
We take the thing that's in the entry is just a pointer, right?
Or it may be the first element in a linked list.
Let's say so that would store like the, you know, if be went in there
first, it's sort of XYZ and for and then it's got a little slot for a
pointer.
That's just set to 0.
Then when we want to store a as well, it goes in there.
It looks to see that x y z is not equal to XYZ to write and it creates
in puts in this pointer, instead of it, overwrites the zero.
With a pointer out to another storage field, right?
Which is X2, Y2, Z2, and it stores the five in there.
And so basically, any time you have a collision you just over occupy
the space by having a linked list of the things that all map to that
coordinate, right?
And and that's external chaining, right?
Because basically, if this is the hash table, the chain exists outside
of the hash table.
It's like separate memory.
Basically, that's your pointing out to when you need to handle
Collision, right?
And that's the totally fine way to go.
Obviously.
It's a little wonky in that you end up having to chase these pointers,
but the idea is you hope that you don't have a lot of collisions.
So the depth of these lists is supposed to be quite short one to, you
know, that sort of thing.
The other way you can do it is within
Internal training and what internal training does is the exact same
procedure only instead of looking at a pointer.
So, instead of having a pointer in a slot that kind of goes out to
something else, when there is a collision, what you do is you just
start looking through the hash table to see if you can find it after
doing basically some some, some, some addition, right?
So, if I come in here, and I'm Onslaught one, right?
And here's two, three, four five.
I find a collision on
Not one.
So, I've got, I'm trying to do x to the x 2, Y 2, Z 2, but and it maps
to slot 1, right?
So, it Maps here, but in slot 1 is this x y z, which is not what I
wanted.
Instead of creating a chain.
That's external.
I create essentially A Train.
That's internal, I go.
Okay.
Let's look at like let's say if I was going to Chain by one.
So I'm going to do like plus one was my chaining method.
I would look at the next slot down and say, how about this one?
If this one's empty then I know okay.
Well, if this is empty, Then I then
Just must not have ever been stored.
So I'll just store it there, right?
X2.
Y2 Z2.
I just store it in the next the first available slot that I find,
right?
Then when someone comes to do the lookup, it does the exact same
procedure if it looks up.
X2, Y2, Z2, it goes, it should be in slot 1.
It's not.
All right, look at slot to it.
Sit there.
Yes, it is.
I found it.
Right.
So essentially you just populate slots.
That shouldn't hold the thing that you want.
With the thing that you want and you know that since everyone who does
the lookup follows the same procedure as the person who did the store,
you know, that they'll always find it if it's there and they just stop
when they get to a null, a something that's not filled, right?
Now, that has some.
Add behaviors, which is that?
Like, as the, you know, you can imagine that the linked list version,
right?
The link twist version kind of has a better worst-case performance in
some sense.
In the, when we're by worst case.
I'm talking about specific worst case.
It has a better worst-case performance when the hash table gets close
to full in the entry array, right?
Because for the same size array, like if you say, you know, I've got
I'm going to, I'm going to use
12 pieces of storage.
Let's say and I have 256 of them for my hash table, normally, and each
slot was occupied x 2, that would be full, right?
You can imagine that when you're actually in the case, where you're
doing the probing, you will have a lot of things filled.
So when you go and you try to find something that's not in the hash
table yet or something.
You are see.
You're skipping a lot.
You're going through a lot of thing bins to find an empty space.
Whereas with the linked list case, right?
You would
He's just check two things, you check one slot.
And then the the pointer on that slot, right?
So, as the hash table gets close to filled in the entry in terms of
how many pieces of storage you have for it.
This tends to perform a little bit better than the in terms of like
how much probing gets done.
How many checks get done the linked list case has a flatter
performance curve, right?
It's better in that case.
But you have to look at, there's, there's a flip side to it, which is
that, in the case of, in the, in the case of the, the internal
chaining case, right?
Which is this
Okay.
So the one I just described it has a nicer thing which is that all of
your storage is used for the hashing.
So the likelihood of collisions in the non full case goes down, right.
Because if I'm going to use 512, lots of storage, the linked list
case, right?
Can't use all of them for the hash table because some of them are used
for the linked list, right?
So if I wanted to use a constant the same amount of space for both of
them, I have to say, oh, well, the linked list is partitioned like
it's got
Twenty Eight slots, and then 512 - 128 is reserved for like the
chains, right?
Or something like that.
If I wanted to keep a constant amount of memory, then basically, you
have this problem where you're constantly using a lot less for the
hashing.
So collisions become more likely because you're trying to fit into a
smaller low coordinate system.
Whereas the internal training case, just always uses all of the memory
for the actual hash table, which reduces the number of collisions,
right?
Right.
so something to think about,
Sorry, little stuff you today.
Not sure if I'm getting cold.
Maybe I'm too much Chopper traffic chip cookies, I guess so.
That's the that's the skinny on hash tables.
Right?
So what I want to do for now is I'll probably just Implement a very
simple one and we won't try to do anything fancy like pacifically.
One thing that we won't quite do.
Yet is try to concentrate on the hash function, especially because we
want to be able to introduce something that appears in almost every
code base.
Even after it ships, which is to do: better hash function.
Because everyone always says they should make a better hash function
and then never actually does.
So this to do is in like every code based somewhere, right?
Because Hashem is even with a really lousy hash function.
Still work pretty well.
So a lot of times they're just good enough and no one ever ends up
going to do the math and figuring out what the best way would be.
But you know, maybe at least since this is an educational stream at
some point during development.
We will try to actually not leave that to do in there and do a better
hash function.
No.
Alright, so there you go.
There's a number.
Like I said, if you want to go read about hash tables, there's,
there's tons of topics involved in hash tables.
Lots of things to think about how big they should be size.
Should they be prime number sizes for wrapping?
Because you have to the way you map in the coordinate space.
There's there's all these sort of like number-theoretic issues that in
are involved here.
Some of which I'm not even that good at understanding because I don't
spend a lot of time studying hash tables.
So I'm even the wrong person to explain them.
Point being you should be aware.
Anyways, that there's a whole like big thing.
There's things while perfect hash functions which are guaranteed to
always fill the hash table correctly and just a lot of stuff to learn
there.
If you really wanted to kind of really, no hash tables inside and out
and we probably won't quite get all the way down that rabbit hole, but
I wanted to make sure people understand that it's there.
So all I really want to do is I just want to be able to start saying,
okay.
Let's, let's go to our handmade tile system here.
Right?
And let's stop doing this Kyle chunk count stuff and let's start doing
it so that we're just storing them in a hash table essentially.
So, in our tile chunk, we're going to say what it's it style, chunk X
tile chunk.
Why?
And tile chunk Z actually were right.
So, essentially, these right, we're going to say the coordinates of
the tile chunk.
Down here, and the coordinates.
Why?
Why is that?
My emacs is very slow right now.
What's going on?
Do I have some weird?
What's, who's who is responsible for this?
What's going on here?
Nothing weird going on, really?
No.
Yeah.
I wonder if krita's being a little hog, and I don't think so.
I don't know what's going on.
But I guess that's just the way it goes sometimes.
All right, so we've got these tile chunks, right, and I'm just going
to store with the tile chunk now, which coordinate it was so that it
can be in a hash table, right?
And maybe for now we'll just use external chaining.
So we'll just say that.
Any time that we have a tile chunk that we need to sort of extend to
have more tile chunks after it that map to the same coordinate in our
hash table.
We'll just have a next.
So, we'll say next in hash, just to be clear.
About what next means in this case, right?
And then we can say in this situation when we're going to go store
them.
Then we're actually going to call this our tile chunk hash and we'll
have our tile chunk.
Hash can be of a known size.
I'm going to use a power of two at the moment.
So that that it'll be not too bad to look up in, and I'll show you why
that we do that in a second, but it's worth noting that
That this is not necessarily the smartest thing to do.
because it's a little hard to explain exactly why, but
when we do the mapping,
There's number theoretic reasons why you may not want to have a power
of two because that powers of two directly truncate.
The bits that come out of the hash function and I'll kind of show you
why.
There's, there's some issues there when we get to it.
A bit of a little bit, but I'm going to do that right now just because
I think that'll be a little more efficient at the moment, especially
since we aren't going to be doing a particularly good hash function,
and aren't really thinking that stuff through, I don't think it's
worth it.
So, what I want to do is say we've got this tile chunk hash, and the
tile chunk cash.
We'll just be a bunch of pointers to top chunks, right?
So we'll have 4096 pointers off the top chunks.
That'll basically just store whether or not there's there's a topic
there.
Now.
What I could do is is have some notion of I could just flat-out store
it like this.
So we actually just have tile chunks there or I could throw them as
pointers and I think maybe it's better to just store the top chunks
exactly.
Because I don't want to have to chase a pointer right at the first
look up.
So we'll just say that.
The first tile chunk is stored directly in the hash table entry and
then the slots over.
Just like I drew it on the diagram.
The slot is just is stored there.
And the other thing that I could do is, instead of this being a
pointer to tiles again, we could actually make that as well be the 16
by 16.
I don't know if we really want to do that yet though, that's hard to
say because the reason we were making that pointer be a pointer to
tiles is because some of them weren't filled.
And so what we could do is say that those are actually there.
I don't know.
Yeah.
Right?
Because this was something like this, right?
But I don't think we want to do that yet.
So let's just do it this way.
Let's say that we have
Our touch on cash like so and we've got our tile Chung.
And so now we're basically just going to implement a very simple hash
table that looks up inside the touch on cash.
Right?
And in order to do that.
I need to actually change the functions that look up that towel, but
look up in that top junk array, which is compiler will helpfully, tell
me about.
So when we go to get a tile chunk, and we're passing it in x y and a z
instead of this stuff.
Now, we're never actually going to do these checks, right?
Because we no longer have any bounds on where our chunks could be.
That can be
Beware, what I'm going to do instead is create a hash index and I'm
going to do the stupidest possible thing at the moment that you could
ever possibly do.
I'm literally just pulling this completely out of nowhere.
There's really nothing intelligent about it whatsoever.
Literally, you know, don't do this at home.
It's just stupid.
I'm literally just going to create a function that just does some
arbitrary completely arbitrary, mapping of these things.
Together, right?
So it's just, it's just flat out doing some kind of weird manipulation
of the numbers and it's basically just doing a standard array kind of
thing where we're manipulating them and then smashing them together,
right?
And then I'm just going to take whatever that number is and we'll call
this look like to call this a hash value.
And then I'm going to make a hash slot which is to say whatever random
number, this thing pulled out by Smashing these guys together into one
number.
I now need to just put it into the table.
And so the way I'm going to do that is I'm going to take the array
count.
However, big my tile chunk.
Hashed was right.
However, many slots.
I had.
I'm just going to take that.
And I'm going to subtract 1 from it because we know it's a power of 2,
right.
I'm just put this in here at the moment.
This must be a power of 2.
Right.
So what I want to do here is say okay.
Take me Rake out with it for the top, for the touch on cash, subtract
1 from it, which will basically give me a mask that will that I can.
And my hash value against, right?
Because, remember, it was the power of 2.
It means, it's if it's a power of two, it means that it's something
that looks like this in binary, right?
It's a one, followed by a bunch of zeros.
If it's a power of 2, If I subtract 1 from it, it will borrow all the
way across until they're in the make a 0, which is exactly the mask.
I want to mask out.
Out the part of this value, that would not fit in the array.
So this basically just makes it into sort of a rapping number, if you
will that fits inside the array size that we've defined.
So, that we know is that the, the hash lat
That this thing would fit into and I think I said I wanted to do it
that way, right?
I think I said I didn't want to store pointers.
So we're going to do that.
So, the chunk that we actually want is just a child chunk.
Hash now plus, that hash lat.
So now, we've just indexed that that value, right?
And we can assert here as well that the hash lot is less than that
array count.
Because we never, we always want this trunk, this truncation.
Basically here should have made it, so that it always will be.
So after we compute the hash lot, we can get out the chunk.
Oh, and I forgot to do this is the to do.
I said that every code base has in it.
Right, so that'll be in there will probably shift the game with it.
That's just how it works.
What can you say?
But if we remember someday, we'll have to go back study UPS on our
hash tables and do a better job, okay.
So we've got our Tau chunk now and then what we need to do is say is
this chunk by Chunk we wanted, right.
So essentially what we have to do is make a for Loop now which goes
over the chunks in order.
Like so on and tries to find whichever chunk is the one that that has
that is the values that we were looking for, right?
Because we have to again, we can have Collision.
So we need to start comparing the value stored in the tile chunk to
see whether it's the chunk that we wanted.
Right.
This might actually have to be a while loop Jimmy.
In fact, I think I will make it a while loop.
Okay.
So what we need to do is we kind of know in fact that that's going to
be that.
So really, it's a do while loop at the end of the day.
So what we need to do now is we need to say, okay.
We have a certain tile chunk xed out require that we were looking for.
We're starting to look through our our chain.
Remember, we're trying to look through basically, you know, this guy
right here.
We're going to look through and see which one of these guys has.
Our thing has the
The chunk that we were looking for.
So you want to look to see whether we get a match on all three of the
coordinates, exactly, right?
So, we look to see whether we've got an X Y or Z match and it's Ari
and Uzi match.
And if we have all three of them, then we know we've found the Tau
chunk.
So if we found all three, then we say, yes, good.
That's exactly what we wanted.
Although we need one more thing, which is, we need to see whether the
slot is filled at all, because it could be that the child Chuck XYZ
are all zero, which I don't know if we want to, you know, we, I guess
we could also just say that all zero is considered an invalid.
We're so you can never get down 2000 so we could do something like
this.
A certain child chunk X not equal to 0 kind of thing or not.
I should say Tau chunk x equals 0.
And Kyle, junk y equals zero and tell chunk Z equals zero.
So we could just say that 0 0 since we're not allowing rapping,
basically the whole border of our world.
The very outer, most tile all the way around is not really allowed to
be occupied.
So 000 would be totally fine.
We could also assert that we're never asking for one of those ones on
the border.
So in some sense, we could also say assert that you never actually
asked for a border tile.
In fact, that might be a good idea because if we're not allowing
wrapping you should never ever ever.
Doing that.
So we kind of want to do something like this anyway.
And we could even say, you know.
Assert, maybe I'll do it this way.
We could say that there's a safe margin, right?
And we could say, you know, pound to find safe margin tile chunk,
safe.
Margin, we could just say never let the person get within the world
should never get within 16 of the border, right?
We start at the middle.
There's no way you should ever get out there.
So if something happens, that's like that.
That's just full on banana cakes and some there was some heinous bug
in the code.
So let's just say that we have to
Rather than the safe margin here.
And then we have to be, you know, less than the safe margin on the
outside as well, right?
On all the coordinates and that seems pretty reasonable to me, right.
That seems pretty good.
So we start by going through.
We grab the first Chunk in the hash lat, right?
And we then say, all right.
Let's go ahead and start looking through these guys.
Oops.
Compiled to good compelled to well.
Start looking through these guys assuming that we don't find it.
We need to go to the next one, the hash, right?
And so what we need to do is say well first, let's check does.
Is there a next one in the hash if there isn't a next one?
In the hash, then we're sort of, we're done right with the with the
situation.
Certainly, although I guess what I should do here is say, when we do
get to a chunk.
We can also pass a Bool to it, which says, create if doesn't exist or
something, create, if missing, and that will just assume to be
Else but if someone wants to actually make the tile chunk put it in
place.
We're at the right position in the code to do that.
So I might just go ahead and say all right, if you know
Like so I might just say if there isn't a next one in the hash and we
didn't match, right?
Then if create if missing is true, then I want to actually make one.
So I want to make next in half be equal to a new tile chunk.
Right?
And so what that's going to have to do is that
Going to have to.
And in fact, you know what, I can even do it in a slightly more
interesting way to what I could do is, if you pass the memory
allocator to it, then it will it will do the creation and if you
don't, you don't.
So, I don't know if you remember this, if you basically pass the
memory Arena.
Here, we'll just say, if you pass a memory Arena to it, then it will
go ahead and create one for you.
And if you don't then it won't.
So if there's an arena then it will create a new, a new one.
So I may have to return a little bit more than that.
But let's let's find out.
So yeah, so what we would do here is we'd also have to clear it
potentially if we always wanted to clear it, but we may want to not
clear at some time.
So we'll have to think about how we want to handle that.
Exactly.
But essentially what will happen here is this will do that fill,
right?
So
In the case where we don't find one.
We we do our push here.
So we would do to push, has essentially right one to push the array,
right?
New chunk.
New chunk, like so.
I'll chunk new chunk equals push.
I'll jump.
So we push a new one on to our Arena.
We push a new array for the tiles.
We initialize the tiles and we set the chain are in our hash chain.
We set that chain to point to the new chunk.
And now we are done.
You can just flat-out break out of the thing and we're done, right?
Same thing is true here.
If we happen to find it.
We have found the chunk.
So that's fine and everything's good.
And we can also do this so that when we break we can just return chunk
and that's the chunk that we found and that's, yeah, that's pretty
much it.
Don't need that either.
So you hope that you can see what happens here.
Let's walk through it once and this is mostly what we need.
so,
We assert that we're not asking for a chunk that's in an illegal
boundary, that we don't ever want to have something in because our
code is now not.
We're saying by Design can never wrap, and so we want to make sure no
one's near that apron, because then calculations that are based on
regions will go outside it, right?
We don't want that.
So we make sure that we're not in that region by checking to see
whether we're greater than and less than basically the two boundaries
on the low side and the high side which is set to 16 right now, but we
could set it higher.
Well, we could set it to 56 and just make a real big margin for
safety.
No one.
Should the world would be massive if you ever got out that far.
Anyway, there's never the player couldn't even walk that far in like
weeks, right?
So that's fine.
If we go to our hashtag computation.
We just are doing something random and crappy right now.
That's just going to compute some number.
That mixes together.
All three to give us a place to look in our hash table.
We then get rid of the bottom.
Sorry of the top bits of that and just use, however, many bits will
actually fit into the array.
That's the size that we made for our hash.
We assert that that's a valid thing to look up.
We then actually go and grab it out of the hash table.
And we start walking.
If we find a match by comparing the child chunks that we're looking
for, with the junk that's in, there we go.
Then we go and check to see if the person passes an
before allocation, and there isn't another new chunk to check.
Oh, I guess there's two things.
We should do.
They're actually now that I think about it because there's a second
case, the second case is, if there's a Rena and not chunk not Chum
hash, right?
Or, you know, tile chunk x equals 0, right?
Which is to say that, it was an uninitialized.
If it's an uninitialized slot, right?
Because we that first slot would,
Uninitialized?
Right, because we actually stored it directly in there.
So in either case, if it doesn't have the next one, or this one is not
it.
And I guess that we really owe.
This is a little ugly.
This makes the code a little more complicated storing it directly in
their that.
Whereas, if we just had a pointer, it wouldn't be.
Because then you have to kind of go like, okay.
Well, which one actually is it?
Do we need a new child chunk or not?
Right.
So I guess the way we would actually do it again to make the code work
properly, is if Arena and
Tile chunk count, right?
Equals zero.
So if the slot was uninitialized that first slop, it's there.
Then what we do is we'd say, okay, if that's the case, then chunk
equals push on the on the arena.
And I'm just going to go ahead and say that tile chunk x equals 0,
right.
So we're going to push a new one on there.
And then we're going to go ahead and set its x equal to 0.
Yeah.
Sorry, that's not what I meant to do.
That's not what I meant to do.
I did it backwards.
Sorry.
This is a little complicated to talk through.
I'm trying to make it so that these cases are relatively simple.
This is what I meant to do.
So if we have an arena, so we're supposed to make Nutella chunks when
we don't find them.
If we don't.
If there isn't another one next in the hash, then we need to make one
that's next in the hash right now.
So this is the case where we actually do new chunk, right?
So I'll make a new chunk because we know that this chunk was occupied,
right?
So,
there we go.
If this chunk was occupied and it doesn't have another one in the
chain, but we needed to make a new one, right?
Then I will go ahead and make the new one.
And in fact, I can just do it directly this way.
I'll just say that the the next in hash for this guy equals a new
chunk and is tile chunk x equals 0.
So we've marked then now we have moved on to the next guy, right?
So we can say chunk equals chunk next in hash, like so, and then I can
do, okay?
If we're supposed to allocate.
And end, we know that.
That the chunk tile chunk x, equals zero.
And again, we now know that this this has to be valid now because
there is no way we could have gotten past this case and have an arena.
If we didn't actually make a new one.
So we look to see if it's equal to zero, which means either it was an
empty slot to begin with which meant that this case didn't execute.
Can't really do that.
There.
Can I I have to actually do it here.
Gosh.
All right.
This is, this is, this is way more complicated than doing it with just
the pointers gah.
Maybe just climb talking through it.
Maybe it's not complicated.
Okay, one more time.
We check for the match, if we find the match, we're done.
That's the easy case.
We just return chunk, and we're good.
If the chunks lot was filled, so it is actually valid, which were
using chunk X e0 to tell us, right?
If the chunks lot was filled and the next in hash.
Is not filled.
Then that's a, that's a problem because that basically means they've
given us an arena, so they want new chunks and we're about to run off
the end of the list.
So what we do is we stick a new one on to the end of the list, we set
it style chunk X to be 0 so that we know that it's empty and then we
move to it.
The next thing we do is we say okay if we were supposed to make some
and we're on an empty slot, which we either were already or we just
made an empty slot for ourselves.
Then it is time.
To allocate that chunk, right?
Like so push our tiles on there.
The tile count, we actually need where is the total count?
What is the toe cap?
It's just this.
We go.
So we don't actually need this case anymore at all.
This just passes the arena done.
So,
We get the tile count.
We allocate space for the tiles.
We initialize a tiles all to one for now and we'll put it to do there
that says, you know, something like do we want to always initialize?
I don't know.
See, and there we go.
So we actually initialize all them.
And now we've got our
And we're done.
So we break out.
If none of those things happened, then we just go ahead and go to the
next in hash as we normally would and we continue probing.
I think that's roughly correct, but that's pretty darn complicated.
So yeah, what what did I do?
Incorrectly here?
I forget, I haven't used we hardly ever have done much in the way of
actually having to use our Arena.
I don't remember where we actually
made that.
Where is our push push strut?
Okay, there's chunk.
So and now we don't need to do this anymore at all.
Essentially, all we have to do is initialize that tile map to 0.
So we do need to do is we need to do a clear where we basically say
all of the things.
All of the things in that tilemap struct in handmade tile, dot h at
the beginning have to have their exes cleared, if that makes sense.
So we could do something, you know, like have an initialization
procedure or something like that, which maybe would be a good idea
here.
So what I'll do is I will make a, you know, initialize tile, map
function, the base.
We just takes that town map and does that in it in here.
So, that is something like this void initialise tile map, that takes
the tile map to initialize, and the tile side in meters that you
wanted for your tile map.
And then it goes ahead and does this stuff.
It'll
Initialize the chunk shift to whatever it wants to be utilized to tell
side M, like so, and then it'll Loop through all the top trunks.
So now chunk index less than a red count, touch on cash.
So tell Chuck index and then it will do child chunk, hash table chunk
index.
And again, the reason I'm doing this the first time through it would
always work because we're guaranteed all zero memory, but that's not
true.
If we wanted to do these in place, which we're going to make world's
multiple times throughout a game because the player May restart, that
sort of stuff.
So I just want to make sure we clear it.
So top chunk x equals zero.
That's how we have been marking, empty slots.
And we also want to go ahead and I guess we don't really need to clear
the next pointer.
The zero is sufficient because the zero will tell it to fill right
away.
So what we really all, we really need to do is go make sure that the
next pointer is always equal to 0, so I'll go do that a second.
All right, so I want to make sure I always clear that out, which is
good.
That and then this is just going to do initial as town map with that.
Point for value.
And if we go ahead and clean that out and we'll go ahead and move this
into the C file.
So that'll be that that's good.
And then up here.
We just have to make sure that our initialization does something sane.
So we want to do here is say that whenever we go to initialize one of
these guys, so we want to actually make sure that we initialize all
the values in that struct.
So we want to do the tile chunk x equals cosine X.
Y z.
So we store what the coordinates were of this guy.
We want to make sure that the next in hash is set to nothing so that
we know there's nothing after it and then I think we're good.
So that seems reasonable.
Oops combat.
So and that actually, I think does do what we wanted.
I think borrowing bugs.
So I think we've managed to get
Cells into a position where we're storing things parsley.
So now what we have to do and this assert fired, which it should fire.
Because remember, we haven't actually tried to move the world, pass
the origin yet.
So it's zero.
So now, what we have to do to start using it is actually start
building the world from the center, right?
And so to build the world from the center.
What we need to do is start us ourselves off at the actual center of
the world.
So let's go ahead and do that.
We have our this waiting for full sparseness that starts us off at the
middle, right?
You went 32 Max divided by 2.
That'd be the middle of where we would be starting and we then need to
also use that for our camera because we want to start the camera off
at that location as well.
So instead of starting it off at zero zero, we should do that screen
Center.
So, whatever, I don't remember, what we call, those just then let's go
find out what were those called.
Let's see.
Screen, x 4 and Y course we're okay.
So we actually need to save those screen base X and Screen base y so,
we'll just go ahead and store those there.
And Screen base X.
There.
Screen-based.
Okay.
And so then these guys can just use that.
Green Bay sex.
Screen baseball.
And now we've got the beginnings of our hash system working.
Aha and Z also have to be the same.
So, let's see here, what do we have for Z on our ABS tile?
Z should also be the same.
So that will be screen-based Z
so, and in here,
We need to now do screen Z or sorry, AB style Z.
Know why we're going.
Well AB style Z.
So if AB style Z equal screen-based Z.
Let's see here, AB style, Z AB style, Z apps Halsey
Equals screen basis Z.
Then it equals screen-based, z, plus 1.
Otherwise, it equals screen-based see.
Right.
Just gotta make that work out.
Here we go.
And so now, unfortunately, we have to actually figure out if we have
any bugs here, which we very melt very well may.
So, first of all, this should be showing our entities, and it's not.
So, the first bug we have to start to work with.
Now is figuring out
Why?
We're not why we're set camera.
Call is not working.
And I think we're just about out of time.
So I'll briefly step through it just going interested, but we'll have
to pick this up on on Monday.
All right, so when we come through our set camera call, let's see what
happens here, when we're actually doing this stuff.
We are stepping through our entities.
These mins and Max's now, correct.
Right, so that's all good.
And I guess.
New camera P AB style C.
So there's our first problem.
Our camera needs to be at screen-based Z because our camera was
previously all the way down to the bottom of the world, which is no
good.
So that's that.
Let's try that again.
Okay.
So now we have one.
I don't even have an idea of how we had that bug.
That's going to be interesting to see what's happening there.
I have.
Absolutely no idea.
What's happening there.
That's pretty funny.
You know, I guess I don't know.
What, how are we doing our screen?
Our screen Basie.
Screen face Z.
What are we actually doing here to compute these?
I don't know.
Three.
Next times tiles per width.
Oh, duh.
So this is not quite correct.
So, these are actually divided by a lot more than two because they're
actually divided by our chunk size.
Right?
So these are actually there's actually the notion of the max number of
chunks, right?
So this is actually divided by 16 here.
So we're going to want a better way of encapsulating that, right?
Because the screen base yet week that would
Ali overflow, the tile amount because we want however many tiles,
Harper tiles to say, where the center is.
I think we should have a better way of doing that.
Let's take a look.
Yeah, so that's a good point.
We should have a better way of doing that.
But okay, so when we actually create dudes here and we have our app
style, except I'll why we're making that by figuring out how many
tiles over we go?
And so the same should be true of our tiles e, but that will be now
and so that's fine.
That seems, although I guess for, for Z, we don't actually have chunks
in that form.
So Z actually does work this way.
Z is actually still just divide by 2.
But okay.
So now let's see where we're at.
Let's go ahead and step into the thing that creates them again.
I'll try to stop in a second and go back to questions by just, it's
frustrating to do something and I want to go see what our bugs are in
it.
I, you know, it's that obsessive, programming kind of thing where it's
hard to just stop when you're just about to finish something.
It's kind of difficult sometimes.
So, let's see.
What happens here.
AB style.
X, AB style, y, AB, style Z.
So why is ABS tile?
Why so much different than ABS tiles e?
That doesn't make a whole lot of sense to me.
What happened there?
That's a bit odd, right?
You would agree.
Oh.
It's because they're x 0, right?
So we're actually not doing it by chunks, even though
We're not doing it by chunks at all.
These screens are not in chunks.
These screens are in in our canonical.
Are in this.
That's so we actually want.
That.
Yeah.
All right.
That was weird.
Now, let's see.
Yeah, so those should now be close to Center and they are.
That's what I would have expected to see last time.
So we come in.
Here we go.
To get our tile Chunk.
We should see some random hash value here.
And the hash lot is some something that maps in there, which it does.
We go ahead and grab it.
It should not be filled and it isn't filled.
So we go ahead and grab the tile count.
That's supposed to be there.
We fill out.
Where is we push into our array?
We initialize everything, we set the chunk index, we break out.
So now we've got the valid chunk.
That chunk is the Chunk we asked for which is good, and then we set
the tile value in that chunk.
So that works exactly like
I would have thought when we go ahead and add our Walt, that works
just fine.
So that seems correct as well.
But for some reason we don't actually ever see any there and then when
we come in here we are finding that our tile map.
Relative positions are wrong.
So, let's take a look at what's going on there.
Is that just, because we're wrapping around, in terms of, in 32s.
I guess would be the problem there.
That's a little annoying, right?
Because you can see that that's, we actually, we are offset, has to be
signed there.
But the thing that we're doing is a little too much, so we could fix
that by again, reducing our range, a little, but I'm not sure if I
love that idea, but that would be fixed if we did this.
Right?
Because that just means that our range is a little too wide.
I think why is that?
Let me, let me see what happens if I just reduce this relatively
drastically, right?
So I do like something like this, right?
I just want to see what happens if we're just having bugs at the
Overflow, or not.
Yeah, so it looks like it looks like there's bugs in terms of the
Overflow there.
So let's take a look at it.
When we have it at a slightly more reasonable thing.
Yeah, let's let's see if we do it this way.
We'll see what it looks like when we debug it this way.
So inside here, I step in and I'm adding these guys, right and I add
their entities and so on, and off we go.
So now I looked like that was working properly.
In fact, when I go do this a second time or third time, we should see
that it finds the tachanka again, right?
Which yeah, which it does.
So storing it in the towel.
Seems fine at the moment.
So I think it just it's in our entity sort of situation that things
are going wonky.
So, let's see what happens when we map something from low to high,
since that seems to be our problem.
Now, let's see what happens there.
So, we want to do a make high entity.
So, the first problem was that none of the things past our inclusion.
Check, right?
Because we should have made High entities just right off the bat for
all of the walls, and that didn't happen.
Open.
So, let's see why that wasn't happening.
I don't know if that's because our cameras in the wrong place or what.
Let's take a look actually what's going on with our camera.
So this is our screen base X, so we're probably still setting the
camera wrong, right?
Yes.
That's our screen base X.
So that needs to be equal to tiles tiles per width and that needs to
be tiles.
Right?
So we were just basically had the camera in the wrong place, right?
There we go.
So, there we go.
And and so then when I create my dude, I need to actually create the
dude, wherever the camera is as
So let's go ahead and see if what add player does.
So add player.
We need to fix that as well.
So we want to add a player for now.
Since we don't have any other real idea about how we're going to add a
player.
We want to add a player wherever the camera is.
So we'll say that entity.
Lo P equals, whatever the camera p is, we'll just flat-out.
Put it where the camera is like, so,
Alright, so now we are properly sparse and our query seems to be
working at least to some degree.
So we're in better shape here.
We're not out of the woods yet, but we're definitely in better shape,
right?
Okay.
All right.
So that's an okay stopping point to leave it at again.
We still have plenty of work to do but now we're a little we're about
10 minutes over but we still have time for about 20 minutes of Q&A.
So let's go ahead and go to the Q&A.
Please prefix, your questions.
With Q: so I can see them and try to keep them to stuff that we did on
today's stream or on previous dreams while he ate my cookies.
How do I do it q a like that?
I don't know how to do it.
I think it's exclamation point q a
Why not center of the world at 0, 0, 0, and you signed into the
tablet?
Yeah, I would like to do that.
Unfortunately.
I think we met.
I can't remember if we baked in some stuff here.
That doesn't do that.
I didn't want to do that right off the bat.
I want to do that as a separate as a separate change, but I would like
to do that as well, because the reason that that would be nicer.
They just are the values are smaller so we can see them.
But yeah.
So what we're doing here is we take the tile side in meters and then
we divide by the relative tile.
So that just gives we should be.
That should work, right?
Because this just gives us an offset.
And so we're moving, whatever we move the offset by could be signed or
unsigned and it shouldn't matter, right?
So it seems like
It seems like that would work.
You want to try it?
Because I would like to.
As well, just to the numbers are smaller and easier to spot identify.
So, let's try it.
I mean, you know, if it doesn't work, it doesn't work.
Right.
So if we, if we did that we would just change all of these guys to in
32s, right?
Something like this.
And then we have to kind of clean up everywhere that it was doing
something.
That was at a chunk extell chunk.
Why sort of a situation.
So the chunk dim.
Tilak, so let's just, let's just do all these within 32s and that's
fine.
Andre canonicalize cord would work like that.
And ab style X greater than equal to.
So these are all done this way.
So so in theory, let's see if that causes any immediate problems.
No, it doesn't.
So in theory that would allow us to go ahead and do that.
And now so what we want to do to, I guess in our handmade tile here,
our tile chunk safe.
Margin.
We basically want to stay.
Away from the edge in any way that might cause us to rap.
So,
Oops.
What would really be doing here?
Is something like this, where this is like?
You know, it 32 Max.
/.
Some kind of safe number, right?
That's the chunk size that we're using currently.
So, that would be one chunk away.
And so what we maybe want to do is go a few more chunks than that
away.
Something like this.
I don't know.
And just say that, okay, we'll keep it to within their, I don't know
what the safe margin is, will have to think about that.
Think about what the real safe margin is.
Okay, so in theory that's fine still and that way we can now go back
to here and set our screen X screen y, right?
Screen-based ice cream base y to be 0 0 and 0 again and then
everything should still work out just fine, hopefully.
Yeah, so yeah, so no, I did want to do that.
That's a good idea.
Just really for legibility.
Right?
So I just wasn't sure if we could do it.
I didn't want to do it first.
I want to get it working first with the UN just in case there's any
baked in there, but looks like we're okay.
And so now I again, the reason I want to do that with just because now
if we look at those numbers, they're just easier to quickly identify
what they are.
You know, like if I look at this guy, when I first start up and we're
creating the world before they were these huge numbers.
As and now they're like 000 which is a much easier thing.
To internalize second time through there like, you know, 10 is right,
and that's just easier to read really.
And so that'll be a little handier, I think.
Is the Hat hashmap essentially, just a creatively shaped tile chunk.
If that's the case.
Could you preempt the hash function by contributing more bits from the
Z coordinate as opposed to the X + Y 4?
At our emap, for example, am I thinking about this, right?
I don't think you are necessarily.
But it's hard to say, let me give you an example and we'll see if this
clarifies, right?
So let's say, I wanted to store all the words.
In the dictionary.
Right.
Such that I could quickly given a word, tell whether that word was in
the dictionary or not.
Okay, so they could be arbitrary length.
Like you've got short words like it and you've got long words like
antidisestablishmentarianism.
Right.
And what I want to do is I want to quickly be able to say, are these
in the dictionary or are they not?
And what you can see from this is that like a hash table is
essentially just a function, right?
That takes B in some number of bits in, and that could be an arbitrary
number of bits and spits out a fixed number of bits.
Right?
So, it takes arbitrary, arbitrary, bits in and speak Stout Fitbit
fixed B.
Those fixed B can then be used to look up into a table of a specific
of a known length proportional to the bits.
Right?
So if I say that it's going to spit out, you know, a number between 0
and 27, then I've got a table whose n equals 27 and there's 27 slots
in it.
I look up in there and I do my chaining or whatever else I need to do
to store multiple things.
Right?
And that allows me to look up any word.
So it's not really shaped per se.
say, it's not confined to a shape or
Like that, it's a way of mapping anything that comes in into a fixed
number of slots, a raid linearly to do to accelerate the testing.
Because you could imagine just having an array and testing each
individual one, right?
We could have written the tile chunk thing.
So we just had an array of the tile jumps up there were and we just
Loop through them all.
Testing them one after the other, right?
But that be really slow.
Wom Pro.
Look up.
We have to look through all end tile Maps.
Every time we want to find one of them and that's real bad.
So the hashmap turns it much closer to 0 1, which is to say, we just
look up one slot.
We just go directly there and say is it there?
And most of the time we're right.
Sometimes we have to chase a chain one or two steps or something, but
mostly it's just a very fixed number of operations and it works for
anything.
We could just sum up all the characters in a string X, some numbers
going to kind of produce.
Some fixed set of bits that we can use look up on the table and this
will work for that.
Just like I work for our child chunk, just for it work for anything
else because that make more sense.
What do you think about and do you ever do free optimizations in early
or late stage of development?
Such as is in rectangle, equals true if greater than or equal to left
and less than right, and greater than equal to the top and less than
bottom in.
And instead trying to fail as early as possible.
Best case scenario, you only did one comparison rather than four.
So two things about that that I would comment on.
And we'll talk about both of them.
The first one is that is exactly how this is already written.
So, in see, the rule for treating, binary logical, operators and an
orange, so on is that you only evaluate as many of them as you need to
to produce the result.
So when you have an and operator, it'll compute this first.
And if it's value, is already 0, it knows that none of the rest of the
things need to be computed.
So the compiler is already free.
To generate exactly what you just said.
There'd be no difference to the compiler between running it this way
and writing it as a cascading series of ifs that return.
So the first answer to your question is those optimization look like
the kind you're talking about are already in the code in the places
where you see that, that's just how see works.
But the second part of your question, if we extend it out to something
that wasn't that way.
So, maybe like, you look at something like this, that's actually doing
a bunch of logic in multiple steps.
And do we think about, you know, how we're going to arrange those?
The answer is, no, I never think about that.
Before I get to a point where I'm actually profiling something,
because one of the things that you have to understand is performance
surrounding.
If statements is incredibly, incredibly complicated.
It is not sufficient to think about it.
The way that you are suggesting where you're just like, oh well early
out.
Some pieces of code are made Faster by always doing all the operations
instead of having any F's.
Some code is made Faster by doing the ifs.
Some code is made Faster by picking exactly which ifs you do when
because of Branch prediction and so trying to before you have time
things optimize, if statements, I would almost say never do it because
the chances that you will actually guess properly as to, which is the
optimal way to do them.
Are like zero?
So yeah, I would say when you're writing code in this stage.
Never think about that.
And only start to think about it when you get to a stage where you're
actually timing your performance.
And once you're actually timing your performance, then you can start
to think about how you should arrange your, if statements, for
performance purposes.
So I definitely wouldn't say don't think about it.
There is a very specific time in a place where you absolutely want to.
Think about it.
That time is just
Once you are actually timing, the cycle counts of your routine if you
haven't gotten to that stage, no.
What sort of cookie is best for programming?
Probably chocolate chip.
Sometimes new Munoz?
What do you think about splitting the hashmap code from the tile codes
that you can use hash map for other stuff later on.
So I realize that's a tempting thing for people.
People like to do that sort of stuff.
And I don't really want to be too critical of it because like I said,
programming Styles vary.
So I don't want to say don't ever do X or whatever because it's over.
It's more dramatic than I probably should sound.
But I think I can illustrate at least in this case, a very good
example, why I don't think it's useful to pull out hash code.
So here is the hashcode that's common among hash tables right here.
That much.
So if you tried to make this a common function, you would be saving
two lines of code at the expense of trying to shoehorn all the rest of
this into some common thing because the comparison function is
different.
So you're going to have to write that every time, one way or the other
because you don't know the comparison could be something pretty crazy.
Right?
It's going to check multiple values.
It can be checking vitals and different styles are coming.
So you're going to no matter what you did.
Like, let's say you made a template or something.
You're going to have to supply this.
Right.
This is completely custom and often doesn't exist at all.
So that's going to have to go outside the hash.
This way of doing things right where we're sort of doing like we want
the internal versus external chaining or things like that is a
decision / hash table, but you could have one for each like an
internal and external Cheney version or something.
So you could maybe save a little bit of that.
But this code that actually initializes the hash and the way that we
said, which value was whether things were filled or not.
Those are also totally specific to the structure.
So really almost none of this code can be reused because it's
All based entirely on how the chunks themselves work and how we want
them to function.
So really, it's just much more efficient to just write it this way.
Because I mean that's all the code that it takes to write a hash
table.
There it is.
So I would not pull that out from traction because it's much better.
All being in line and we can do very custom stuff here that can be
much better than what we would do, if we had to force it through some
kind of procrustean system.
So that's what I would say about that.
You're not passing the arena to the hash lookup function.
What do you mean?
I'm not passing it to the hash lookup function.
Get Tau chunk, right?
And so in get tile value, we don't call it which is what we want
because we shouldn't an inset tile value.
We do.
Right.
So what?
I'm not sure.
I follow you.
What do you mean that?
We're not passing the arena to the hash book up function, MTS mocks.
Could you clarify that question?
So that I know what you were referring to?
Is the world going to be generated on the fly or at game startup?
Probably?
Well.
I don't know about game startup, but game start anyway, at startup
that I mean, the player might generate multiple worlds when they like,
restart their game, whatever.
But yeah.
At the restart time, I think it'll be generated at the restart time
because I want to do a lot more complicated things.
And if you generate the world on the Fly Like, You know, I want to
have stuff where, oh, there's like a messenger.
Who's going between two places.
That's like really far from where you are like your way down here.
And he's going here and he tell somebody something, who tells another
guy to go do something.
Like, I want to be able to have very complicated stuff going on in the
world and that can't be simulated.
If the world only exists right around where you are.
So I want the world to exist everywhere at high frequency around where
you are, but at low frequency everywhere is the goal.
So it kind of all has to be generated before you start playing.
Instead of chunks.
Have you thought about spatial hashing?
I'm considering it for my game to allow an open General but not
confined to gridline tiles for fixed sized objects.
So, yes, we are not a lot.
We are not going to be confined to those either.
This is a spatial hash.
So the what?
What I'm planning to do next because we already did the step of it,
which is this step right here.
What I'm planning to do.
Next is entities will just be sorted out chunks and there will no
longer be tile store to tell chunks.
So that's our next step.
So we are actually already doing exactly what you're saying.
We just haven't quite gotten there yet.
What about using an octree for sparse?
Tell storage rather than a hashmap?
So I don't know what the benefit, like, what would the benefit of an
octree be right?
There's only one thing I can think of.
And I don't love it.
So, let's think about that.
Shall we?
So first, let's talk about the point of an octree, right?
The point of an octree.
Is usually that you want to store things at multiple levels of detail.
Audrey is really a large scheme.
Like I don't really think of octree is a spatial partition because
it's not a very good spatial partition if you're not talking about
this in my opinion, right?
Because if we have the ability to access like with the hashmap, we can
basically jump right into a table and do some small number of
comparisons to find out exactly the tile chunk that we're on, right?
And that number of comparisons will probably be quite small.
We can make the hashmap Fairly large and I think that number curves
will be like one or two.
Typically, an octree is guaranteed to every time you do a lookup have
to do as many steps as there are levels.
In the octree.
So how many levels would there be in Iraq?
Tree?
Well, we have four billion.
Possible coordinates.
Right?
We're saying there's an apron there.
So let's say conservatively maybe there's two billion or 1 billion,
right?
So that'd be like to let's say we have two to the 28th or something of
that nature tiles, and we're doing them by 16.
So we have something like 2 to the 24th, right?
If we have 2 to the 24th, that means the number of splits in the
octree, right?
The octree splits things in half.
Right.
Because any Dimension is split in half.
It.
Splits it into eight, cubes half on each Dimension.
So the first split would take us from 2224 to to the 23rd right on
either side.
So each one of these would be a two to the 23rd side Cube.
The next one would do is 22nd.
Then 21st.
We would need to test 24.
We need to do twenty four iterations down the octree to get to a
single one of our tile Maps, right?
There's just no way hash tables.
Not going to beat that in my opinion.
I just don't see it.
So I feel like an octree would be a real waste of computing resources
because usually the reason you do an octree is because
You start storing things at lower levels of detail.
So the only things that take 2 to the 24th things that aren't very
high level detail and other things are stored earlier up.
So you're talking about a non fully populated tree, but we actually
have a fully populated tree in the sense that all of our information
is at the very leaves.
We don't have any way of doing anything at at higher up levels, really
nor do I think we want any.
So this is just really, I think not very useful, unless I'm missing
something.
Since you are using a memory arena for all allocations, how will you
handle Dynamic amount of objects?
Like enemies, particles, Etc.
Well, you will have to see when we get there.
I mean, the short answer is, I just usually use circular buffers for
this.
Shouldn't the safe margin be in 32 Max minus margin.
So is that enough?
That's what I'm wondering.
I don't really know.
So the first thing is it's the the these are in tile chunks, right?
So it's at the very least, the it 32 Max over 16, which is the size
that we're using right now for tile chunks, right?
And so it's definitely going to be more than just in 32.
Max minus margin because that would be in tiles, not in touch honks
and I decided to just make it smaller than that, just to be extra safe
because I don't think we should ever get out there.
So that's why I used.
That as the margin?
When will this little guy have feet?
He's, he doesn't get feet.
He's limbless.
He does not have hands or feet.
Isn't the explanation where one letter points to the next letter until
the end of the word, but that's sorry.
I didn't I didn't mean to imply.
That was what was happening.
Are you talking about?
When I said we had the words in the dictionary and we had, like, ABC
or ABCDEFG QRS.
A,b,c Etc.
The letters, don't point to the next letters.
There's no pointing in here.
I'm talking about just a string and the hash function for this string
would just add all the letters together.
It would take all of the the ASCII values and produce one, say 32-bit
number, right, that it then truncates down.
To, you know, 8 Bits, right, like we did and then those eight bits
look up into a 256 entry table and the table has the each string that
was stored there.
And if so, this this string might be the word Foo, right?
And then if there was another thing that collided with Foo, it would
have a pointer off to the next word, which is bar or whatever.
Right, so there's no pointers to letters or anything like that.
So it's not a, it's not a tree in that sense.
I think you said that a hash table was just one of many ways to start
this First Data.
Could you briefly mention one or a couple of the other methods?
Sure.
So there's lots of other ways we could imagine storing them ranging
from common, to, to bizarre.
And so essentially, they're all exactly the same in principle.
They all take an XYZ.
Like I said, which is very large when you concatenated together,
right?
So in this case, if they were all
For a b, let's say like we were saying before.
Then when you add those together, you're going to get something like
72 bits worth of data.
Right?
So they're all something that tries to take 72 bits and smush it into
some smaller number, right?
Because we know that in memory, you're only going to have chance to
allocate say 24 bits worth of data, right, 24, bits, worth of space
for indexing or something.
That'd be 16 million entries, for example, or something like that.
That's a reasonable.
Number of entries, probably to have a something this is not
So they're all trying to do this same process.
So somebody already mentioned one of them which was like an octree.
Right?
And octree is a way of storing things such that you essentially have
A data structure that splits the world recursively into smaller and
smaller cubes, right?
So you have a head node, which is the world and it has eight.
It's like an octopus.
It has eight child nodes, right?
One, two, three, four, five, six, seven, eight.
It has eight child nodes and each of those nodes is a world that is
18.
Besides.
So it's one of these right?
And each one of those could be split into eight, right?
And basically, that's for storing things, at different levels of
sparseness.
So that you only kind of go down to a certain level.
Usually they're like, five deep or 60, right?
For the world.
And so, you know, that's one way of storing things parsley because you
don't have to subdivide every node.
You only subdivide down to where there's actually data.
There are similar ones in that family, the octave family.
There's quadtrees which are the 2 to D equivalent of an octree.
There's KD trees which are the same.
Idea, but instead of splitting along multiple access.
They only put on one axis at once.
So they'll start like, you know, like a quadtree, for example, splits
the world into quarters every time, right?
So as you go down, the tree, you keep splitting, quarters, quarters
quarters a KD tree splits, the World by one dimension each time.
So it splits the world in half exactly each time and that it can be a
variable place where it split and so that's how it works trying to
think of
Like some other sparseness ones, there's rle, right or run.
Encoding.
And basically that's just a straightforward sparse encoding.
What that basically says is.
All right.
I've got the world and I've got like contiguous regions where there is
stuff stored in the world.
Right?
So the way I'm going to store, it is just by storing counts.
Of what is filled in, what is not.
So, maybe there's like 200 million entries that are empty.
So, the first entry in my table is 200 million, right?
Empty, so, just the number 200 million in the note that it's empty.
Then the next entry in my table is like, okay.
There's 12 screens in a row that are filled twelve tile chunks in a
rather filled.
So then I put in twelve filled and I put like, you know, that I store
the data for the 12.
Then the next thing is how many empty there are.
And you go empty, filled empty field, empty field and you basically
put break it up into bands, right?
And you can imagine more complicated ways of doing that for 2D stuff
and whatever.
Trying to think of what other things are good for doing that.
I don't know.
I have to think about it.
There's surely more ways of storing Spar stuff.
But those are the ones that come to mind.
Yeah.
Yes, thank you for catching that.
Someone just caught a stupid thing that we just did in setting.
They were saying, does starting at zero cause a problem with the tile
chunks because now we're using that as our uninitialized variable and
you're totally right, it does.
So what we should actually do is Define tile, chunk uninitialized.
And and we should Define that to be, you know, something outside the
safe margin basically, right?
So we want to do is say that we've got an initialized value and that
initialized value goes everywhere that we were checking 40, right?
Like so
And and that should should do that.
So we have our initializer here as well.
So I think that is what we should do.
Thank you for catching that.
We would have had to debug that later.
It would have been a huge pain.
Yeah, so yeah, that's definitely true because that was something that
we did assuming that we weren't going to have assuming that we were
never going to have any at 000.
But now we since someone suggested to switch to the in three twos.
We kind of did it hurriedly and I forgot about that.
So that's pretty good.
Thanks for catching that.
That would have been really annoying.
Shouldn't chunk touching x equals 0 B, touch.
Tom next and chunk, hash touch on T equals 0.
Yes, you are.
Correct about that as well.
Well, I'm glad this is great.
This is like having this is very good.
So chunk next in hash.
Yes.
It should be.
I mean, or we can just do it this way.
I suppose move it one down.
So we move to the next one.
Set at uninitialized and go.
Thank you for catching.
Thank you for catching the bugs.
This is pretty handy.
I need people to watch me program regularly during, you know, during
the day.
Maybe they would find on my bugs before I made them.
Will you write an analog function to Malik?
Probably not normally in the in the normal execution of a game.
You never really need to call malloc.
I know lots of people think for some reason that they need a
general-purpose allocator.
But I mean I find in general, you don't really ever need to call a
So I doubt we will maybe but I doubt we will.
Start your pancakes.
I see, I guess what I was thinking about is what the full four billion
by four billion map would look like if you passed each index in the
hashmap, the opposite way through the hash function.
It seems like it doesn't matter in the case, because no matter what,
it's always going to be better than 0 n and in most of the time it's
01 with a tiny bit of performance cost to throw the coordinates
through the function.
Yes, I think.
But yeah.
Most of your comments are notes.
And to do is, do you ever add section title comments to separate long
blocks of code sometime, but I still use note, I use note to denote
those things.
Even, I always still put a note in there.
Do you see any value in adding unit tests for certain bits of this
functionality?
Yes, that has been asked many times before and I've answered it the
same many times before which is that some things are good for unit
testing and some things aren't definitely.
I don't want to do any unit testing tool.
We actually have final code that we're actually talking about.
This is what we want to ship because otherwise you're just wasting
your time.
So yeah, unit testing will happen for certain Small Things.
Most of the things in a game are not unit testable in any real way.
Least not.
Things that are hard to debug.
So unit testing is kind of limited utility in game development, but
there are some things that we probably will unit tests, especially
probably in the renderer.
Can you visualize the shape of the map?
So I can understand why a hash table is better than an array sure.
So let's say,
We'll take two simple examples.
Let's start.
With, you know, the Tower of Doom.
Or something.
So let's say, we make a map and we actually make the map fully dense,
right?
So, here's our map, and these are the tile chunks, right?
So clearly, you know, we've got something that's like, you know, it's
like five tile chunks by five tile chunks and you're asking me, why
wouldn't we store this as an array?
And you're totally right, but why wouldn't we it's way easier to
destroy this as a dense array.
5 by 5, the lookups would be slightly faster than in the hash table.
Certainly and there what was the point of having that whole hash table
just figure out?
Bounds of the world and make it so that you offset your coordinates by
that.
Right?
But now we make the Tower of Doom which has several tiles high on this
one square because there's a tower that the player can climb up and
then there's like, you know, similarly there's the Dungeon of Doom
dunes and it's got several tiles underneath, right?
So now our array has to be
Be five by five by however, many of these are here.
Let's say by ten.
So now it's five by five by ten.
Right?
But how many and what is that number?
That's 250 entries.
Well, how many of those do we actually need?
Will we only needed 25 for this?
And we only needed like 10 for these two like 5 here, and five down or
whatever, right?
So, we only needed 30.
I'm sorry.
We only needed 35.
So, we over-allocated by a tremendous amount, right?
This is, this is like nine times over allocated or eight times over
delicate or something.
Right?
So the reason we want to store things, sparse Tree in a hash map is to
avoid that over-allocation.
So, now, apply this to a whole world.
Now, imagine that our world is fairly sprawling, right?
So, we have towers of Doom and dungeons of Doom, and we've got little
areas of our map, but then we also have
Long winding passages.
Let's say that kind of come out right?
Like this sort of thing.
And then there's like long tall towers here and like Dungeons e here
and maybe these things connect underground like that, but there's
whole areas that are empty and all this stuff storing this in a giant
Cube would just be massively over allocating.
And so what we do with the sparseness is just make sure that we don't
over allocate and we only store where stuff actually is.
The randomize map only goes up into the end to the right at the
moment.
Is it good enough to catch bugs?
No, not really.
But like I said, at this point, we're not really trying to catch bugs.
We're just trying to make things work so that we can see what the API
needs to be.
That's it.
So, there's gonna be tons of bugs in here, and we don't really care.
We only care about the bugs so far as they slow down our development.
And so far, we haven't
Too much problem with that.
Will the renderer be a separate piece of code as like the platform
player, so that can be substitute with something like opengl.
Yes, it will be.
And I think that's it.
We have come to the end of the questions.
Very good.
I'm glad we have come to the end of the questions because that means
it is now time.
Well, to transition from breakfast to lunch.
I guess maybe we'll have to have chocolate cookies for choc chip
cookies, for lunch as well.
Who knows document on named?
Why is carita?
That was weird, right?
Don't know why that just happened.
Well, ladies and gentlemen, thank you very much for joining me for
another episode of handmade here.
It's been a pleasure coding with you.
As always, we have finally gotten the point.
We're doing sparse storage.
So we don't have that much left to go.
This is pretty good on Monday.
We will get to go and and start doing our like entity stuff.
Maybe we'll try to start to do a little bit of World building at that
time, so we can actually make some some maps with entities and
In-store the enemies and pull them in and out of our storage.
That's would be where I'd like to get to, so hopefully, we'll do that
on Monday.
8:00 p.m.
Pacific Standard time, on Monday again.
Hope to see you all there.
And I think that'll be kind of cool.
It'd be nice to actually have some real maps to walk around and so
we'll make something with maybe with with trees or something like that
where we can kind of walk around them in preparation for moving on to
animation and stuff.
So I'd like to get to that point and I think we're almost there.
So that's going to be pretty good and that's going to be a lot of fun
to do as well.
We do have some more things.
We'd like to deal with like we have to
Go ahead and figure out how we want to do walking up and down, and
that sort of stuff.
So we got a lot of stuff to think about but we're in a good place, I
think.
And I think we're still making pretty good progress.
So I'm happy about that.
Anyway, if you would like to follow along at home with a source code,
you can always pre-order the game on handmade hero dot-org using the
handy pre-order button.
If you do that, you will get a link in your email that allows you to
download the source code and the test assets update them.
So they're always totally current with whatever I'm working with
anything on the Stream.
So, I had around checking that out.
If you want to follow along at home.
We also have a patreon.
If you want to just support the video series.
You can always go there.
Check that out.
And then finally, we've got a news and Forum site.
That's really cool.
You should go ahead and check that out.
It's got the schedule on it.
It's got the coding resources, where we basically have people have
ported the game already to Mac and Linux and stuff.
So I've been trying to follow along another platform.
I highly recommend looking in there that could save you.
A lot of time, see what people have already done.
There's a Code discussion where you can post, you know, if
And bugs, or if you have questions or anything like that, we got a
nice discussion board going there, people are pretty helpful on it.
And finally there's an episode guide which I highly recommend checking
out, it lets you catch up on old episodes and stuff like that and also
people have been annotating them so that you can go in here you can
jump directly to certain things in the time code, but there's they
could use your help to it's entirely a
Effort.
So, if you're someone who watches the videos very carefully, and
wouldn't mind writing down the times at which we talked about various
things.
Definitely try to get in concrete cells.
Either post on the code discussion board, or you can tweet it.
One of them.
They would love to have some more help.
I know that it's a lot of work for them.
And obviously, they're just totally volunteering it.
So anyway, something to think about.
So, thank you everyone for joining me and I hope to see you again
here.
Monday night, 8:00 p.m.
Pacific Standard Time, have a fabulous.
This weekend and I will see you all then.
Take it easy, everyone.