Start recording.
Hello everyone and welcome to handmade hero.
The show we could a complete game live on stream.
We are back after having moved.
We have relocated the handmade hero machine and hopefully in that
process have not destroyed anything.
I sort of tested the streaming setup like just a little bit.
It seems to be working.
Okay, the set up is a little weird here but I think we're pretty good
to go.
We will see.
So hopefully today.
It's stream will not be lost and everything will recorded properly and
stream properly.
If it doesn't, well, that is just the way it goes.
When you first trying out a new streaming location, certainly
So on break, since we were off for a week, I was thinking about much
about what we have on hand made hero and we don't have a lot of engine
things left to do.
It's, you know, it's pretty full functional at this point in terms of
the sort of things that we need.
And so I was kind of going through things in my head of like, what,
you know, what are the last sorts of any big things that I want to
tackle before, officially saying we're done with this, and we're going
to move on.
Ends, I'm leaning towards, we'll see what happens at the end of this
week, if I change my mind, but I'm leaning towards switching over to
actually using a regular 3D pipeline.
It's not really a lot of work to do, we've already done all the hard
work of like, rasterization and all that stuff in our software
renderer.
So you're talking about only it's a little bit of stuff for like the
transforming clipping part of the pipeline.
And the reason that I was thinking about that is because I really
He just didn't like the way things were going with all of the sort of,
with all of the sort of sacrifices that I had to make in terms of what
I wanted to do, in order to get things to to work with Straight, 2D
with no mapping at all.
And so, what I was thinking about is I was like, I think I would just
be more comfortable in the long run.
If we pretty much left, everything the same in terms of all the
character sprites.
So they really wouldn't do anything different.
Right wise, but all of the environment would just be mapped onto
little blocks, you know.
So that basically like ground tiles were just little blocks and walls
would be little raised blocks with just just image a Sprite image on
each side of them.
I'm not sure, but I just feel like I might be more comfortable that
way because looking at sort of the way in which things are working on
the back end of the rendering.
Now, I just feel like we have a lot, just there's a tremendous amount
of work.
Work being done back there for the sorting and all of these sorts of
things.
And I really just don't think it's an efficient way to do things, you
know?
I mean yes we made it work and it can work in 2D.
But I think at some point just where I wanted to be in terms of our
capabilities,
Doesn't mesh very well with keeping the environments entirely 2D so I
don't know.
I feel like I just don't really want to leave the renderer in that
state.
I could change my mind but that's just kind of what I was thinking.
And so I kind of feel like I may want to just go ahead and set up an
actual 3D camera and have a way of mapping sending down a map Cube for
the environment blocks, and then they are those environment blocks
would actually be
Formed in perspective, right?
They would go through the z-buffer, they be transferred in
perspective, I would just see if that is workable with the art,
because if it is, I think I would feel a lot more comfortable at that
because then I don't have so many concerns.
We have like all of the special purpose code in there for doing a lot
of stuff that I really just wish we didn't have to do.
And I feel like it's going to create a lot of bottlenecks, you know.
Yes, we don't have to worry too much about our performance because we
are 2D games so you
We have a lot more horsepower than we need but the same time I don't
really like taking up that horsepower for no real purpose, right.
Like it doesn't really seem like a good trade off there and I don't
feel like I'm getting very much out of it like I don't feel like
there's very much we can do with the sort algorithm that we couldn't
have done with the Z buffer as well.
And so even though like
you know, even though it does seem like a little bit of Overkill at
first just as I was reflecting I'm just like, I don't know.
It seems like especially if we want to push the particle system stuff
a little bit, we're going to run into a situation where trying to
force lots of particles through a sorting backend just isn't going to
work.
They would have to be aggregated anyways and then you're into these
kind of nasty problems of like, well how are the particles getting
grouped for sorting and that sort of stuff?
And, you know, does that make it hard for them to flow around things
properly?
And so I feel like we
Just would end up in this really nasty situation and I don't want to
put us in that situation and have us not be able to do certain special
effects that we want to do for no reason other than we have to go
through a sorting back end so that we can't take advantage of the
z-buffer hardware.
So I don't know that's just my feeling on it.
That's kind of what I was feeling.
I pretty much only ever use 3D stuff normally so I'm not very used to
2D programming.
So that may just be, you know,
Sort of the fact that I'm more comfortable with 3D than with 2D and so
maybe like it's really, not as bad as I think it is and it's just a
question of well, you know, your first time through doing 3D to 2D
render engine, if, you know, you're very used to doing 3D render
edges, you expect all of these certain things to work certain ways and
you're going to have to work around them in 2D.
And it's not that big a deal, you know, it might be something more
like that but on the other hand it may just be that in general.
There really isn't a way to do high volume.
Some special effects in that sort of stuff without, you know, relying
on a z-buffer, other sorts things.
That's why we
Z buffer is right, so I don't know.
It's a really interesting question and I'm not sure exactly what the
right answer is.
But just based on kind of my feelings about it.
I was like, I didn't like the level of code complexity that we had to
achieve in order to do what we wanted to do.
And I fully respect the fact that that's because I was trying to do
some things that 2D games, don't normally do, like the floor, like
prospective floor shifting for like going up and down.
Down and, you know, maybe and doing lots of like particle effects that
may be work between floors and stuff like that.
I realize that's not something that pretty much happens in 2D games
really very much.
But at the same time, you know, we know that because nowadays, we have
3D Hardware that we can do all those things if we just put things into
3D.
And so I don't know.
It seems like something that we should probably do.
I also don't really like the idea of having to force people to
understand all the 3D stuff in order to follow it.
But at the end of
Day.
I think it's not too much more stuff, because since we already have a
transform, we already have, you know, the concept of a transform, the
concept of filling rectangles with, you know, sort of doing the
standard stuff, we would do the 3D full triangles.
You know, we could even choose not to implement a perspective.
Correct rasterizer in the software path if we want to write.
So we don't have to take on some of that complexity.
If we don't want to, we just need to do the transform.
Art.
We could even not do clipping properly, right?
We could do kind of like hacky clipping or something like this but
even if we did those things, they wouldn't be too big of a deal at the
end of the day, it's not like a huge amount of extra code to do the
front end for it.
So that's just where I'm leaning towards that's, that's my, my feeling
on it.
So I don't know how other people will feel about that.
I don't know if it's a good idea or a bad idea.
Usually, with stuff like this you only really know once you've done it
and then you can see whether or not it really did simplify things or
make things nicer or whether it was just a waste of time.
But it does seem like the kind of thing that I think when I look at
what we've got right now, it's the big thing that makes me kind of
upset because I feel like it just adds a ton of complexity for no
real.
And if it and I'm not liking how much I have to fight the various
concepts of Z values and things like this in the code base all the
time for.
No, again for no real benefit.
Like the only real benefit is we say, views of the Z buffer and that's
a good thing, in some sense, because it is nice to not have to use a
z-buffer because there are advantages that come with that and
certainly when you sort you get easier Edge anti-aliasing and stuff
like that better transparency, things like this.
So you know there are some benefits to it but those benefits
If it's are pretty minor and the drawbacks are pretty severe.
If we want to start pushing higher counts of things through the
scenes, right?
If we want to start having more Sprites,
You know, thousands tens of thousands of Sprites and up which is not a
huge number of Sprites right by today's standards, pushing all those
through a sorting system.
It's just not a good idea.
Like I really just don't think we want to do that and I just feel like
that's going to really come back to bite us.
So that's my current feeling on it.
Hopefully that all makes some sense.
I'm going to go ahead and ignore it for this week because we have some
stuff we can be doing, but since we're pretty much at the end,
Of engine things.
I do not know why this is pinging, that's all good.
Since we have a bunch of engine things, we can be doing for this week.
We're we will probably run out some point relatively soon, and then we
will have to make that decision.
So I'm going to go ahead and there we go.
All right, I'm going to go ahead here and bring up our to-do list for
a moment.
And if I take a look at it here, really like like I said there's not a
whole lot of stuff here that I really want to tackle.
That's still left on the list, the graphics upgrade would pretty much
be we would switch to the 3D stuff and we probably do that along with
the real artwork.
That would be what we would do and that would get rid of these two
things.
If that makes sense.
That would, that would also clean up sort of this stuff lighting is
something that we still have to kind of talk about.
And if we move things to 3D, I don't know that it would be that big of
a change in how we might may or may not do lighting.
But it would certainly be something we could look at during that
period.
So I feel like this could just be the 3D Graphics update if we wanted
to do it that way.
So let's go ahead and do the arena upgrade, for sure.
I just want to take a quick look here and yeah I would like to
potentially save the arena upgrade for a day where we just start out
and do the start doing the arena upgrades like right at the beginning
at.
So it might do that tomorrow today.
What I think I might want to do is work a little
It with this stuff, right?
We also by the way, have a simple zoomed out view for testing.
So we did that to do already.
What I would like to do here is just say, okay, for I want to take a
look at this stuff, one thing that I want to do is I want to let
combine Sim region and world, and I'll talk about that in a second and
then we could take a look at some of these things when we're doing
that.
Okay.
So here's
Is the situation as it stands at the moment, right?
Right now.
We kind of have this situation.
What day are we on here day 340?
Yeah.
so right now, we kind of have this situation where we have two pieces
of code,
Is the same region and there's the world, right?
And I like part, there's there's things I like about this system.
I like it quite a bit so far the way that it's working.
And the idea here is that this is, you know, potentially compressed
storage, its compressive.
It's potentially out of core, right?
We could Implement a thing.
If we wanted to where we paged out two pieces of the world and then
page them back in.
So this is almost, this is almost like a database
Style thing where it's like this external sort of thing that we talked
to when we need to kind of pull in what entities are wear and it's
like, a spatial query and kind of thing where we can unpack them and
pull them in, right?
And then we have the same region, which is, you know, the sort of the
the runtime right bit where we unpack everything it's uncompressed,
right.
So the entities are actually fully occupying.
The space.
They were it's in core.
It can't be you know it's going to have to fit entirely in memory,
right?
Obviously, which is
Big deal because it's only a little thing.
It's local, right?
This is global.
And right now we kind of have this sort of thing.
It's a little bit janky.
The reason it's a little bit janky is because when you create like
when we're creating things, we really want to be creating things with
a Sim region.
But right now a Sim region is kind of a little confusing in terms of
what it does or how it works.
It's in a separate file from world world in some regions, split things
in a weird way.
For example, the there's
The world file has the thing that does like packing entities.
So like packing entities happens in the in the world but unpacking
them right happens over here and it's a little bit strange it's not
that symmetric the way that it looks and that sort of stuff.
So I don't necessarily know that we've really solidified this stuff to
the degree that I would have preferred.
And so what I want to do right now is I just want to kind of go look
at these two things now
That we pretty much know how they're working and do kind of a couple
just basically do some code inspection.
Just make sure I know kind of what's going on there and see if there's
things that should be moved around or straightened out a little bit.
Now, given the current state of everything where we pretty much know
where everything goes and how it's working.
So, I want to do that and while I'm in there, I would also like to
look at the creation side of things.
So the like the world creation part of things.
Is currently a problem for us in that when we create things in the
world, we have this issue at the moment where we don't actually have
the ability to like, when we unpack things, I'm sorry.
When we create things, they get created in sort of an unpacked State,
and then they get packed into the world and that's how entities are
created right now.
Never a concept of entities getting created inside the Sim region.
But that's really how we want things to go when we're actually going
about creating rooms and stuff the way that we want to do.
Eventually, we definitely have an issue where we want to be able to
say, let's work on this room and all the entities in this room are all
uncompressed at the moment, right?
And will work with all of them and we'll figure out how to make sure
that they're all set to what they need to be set.
And then we'll say like packed this room away and that's
Exactly what we want in terms of how the Sim region worked because
then creating entities and packing entities and all that sort of
stuff, works the same during the gameplay and during World creation,
which I think we want to do because we don't really like we want to be
able to do the same operations in both places, right?
We want to be able to create entities, dynamically at runtime as we
see fit for gameplay, reasons or any other reasons.
And we also want to be able to do that.
Obviously, when we're creating,
The world initially.
And so you know I feel like those things really want to be collapsed
and they don't want to be different.
So that's the kind of thing that I would like to get straightened
away.
That makes sense.
All right, so let's see.
Let us see.
I'm going to go over here to sim region.
And I'm going to see how much code is actually in here.
So you know we've got some queries and stuff in here like get closest
reversible get close entity with brain, get closest, reversible along,
Rea blah blah blah.
We've got move entity transactional, occupy, you know, blah, blah,
blah.
All of these things are simulation oriented.
I don't know that they necessarily belong in Sim, region.
It's hard to say, but some of them certainly do and you can see then
here we have
The begin Sim step, right?
Where we do the packing and unpacking of the entities.
So here, I'm sorry.
The unpacking of the entities, not the packing.
So here is the part where entities are like unpacked.
And we're not really doing much in the way of unpacking and he's right
now.
Really all we do is pointer fix-ups eventually.
That'll do actual compressing of like to put an.
Only the data that we actually care about for a particular entity.
And then here it RN Sim is the place where we call out to the world to
pack our entity stuff in.
And you can see right here here is where we call pack entity into
world.
And now if I understand correctly, you know, from my own memory
basically,
How that sort of thing came about.
I suspect that the reason that we had to do that is when we're doing
these packing, it would make more sense for the packing to exist in
the same region.
Presumably because the same region is the thing that
Accident packs things, you know, to operate on them during the
existence of the same time step.
But you'll notice we don't do that, right?
We have pack entity stuff out here in the handmade world.
I believe the reason that we did that was strictly because we had this
problem with the same regions where we didn't have one at World
creation time.
So when you wanted to create entities, over in the game, you had to do
it calling this code directly.
Ali.
I think the more correct way to do this, probably would be to use the
Sim region itself.
To create stuff.
So that that way we don't have to worry about.
We don't have to deal with the fact that these packet of these stuff
have to be called cold called from somewhere else.
And that way, we can inline all of it and make it like nice and
efficient.
As we sort of figure out more what we need in terms of packing and
unpacking, right?
And so you can kind of imagine what this looks like.
If I was to move this stuff in, let me see what has room for does at
the moment so we do pack it into chunk, right?
That's the thing that that
Actually like sort of checks to see if there's room in the chunk and
grabs one out.
So you know, probably the the has room for a stuff that seems like
stuff that would stay in here.
But this stuff where we do like pack entity reference and packed a
versatile reference.
I feel like that would kind of go in here, right?
And then when we do pack entity into chunk, I think Pat Kennedy into
chunk this code here.
That actually happens to do the packing as opposed to the getting the
room.
I feel like that would just go in here to the end Sim, right?
So when we call n Sim and we're going to call pack entity in Two
Worlds.
I think what we want to do there is we just go ahead and do
That packing.
So I don't really know.
We're going to have to figure out ahead of time how much room we need,
which may be easier said than done.
We'll see when we get to that point in the code.
But assuming that we have it, we know that this is the code that we're
actually using right now.
So this, right, if we actually did, it would be the code that we would
have to use to do the packing, right?
So if we were to say, pack entity, into World, actually,
Turned to us.
I don't know why.
I cut that part out but we could basically say, alright, this like,
reserve some space in the chunk, and we're just going to return that
death pointer.
So then when we call pack entity into world or whatever, what that's
going to do is that's going to return all the way out, the void star.
Like so.
And then I'm just going to do exactly what it was already doing again.
Like just one step at a time.
I'm just going to go ahead and say when we call Pat Kennedy into
world, I'm going to say that I have a specific size that I want.
You can see the pack size getting passed in here.
It's just a it's just getting created by whatever the size of an end
of the actually is so instead of passing in that Source entity because
it doesn't actually need that, I'm just going to have it pass in what
the pack size actually.
I was, right?
So that means this guy here will just pass in.
Hey, you know what, I want to size this, to be the size of my source,
entity The Source entity itself, right?
Was just this.
So that means I should be able to say, like, okay, whatever the size
of the entity structure is, that's what I want you to give me packing
size for then.
When we get that back, I'm going to go ahead.
Ed and copy it over, you know.
So I'll take the end of the pointer that I had and copy it.
Then I'll do my packing and then I'll be done, right?
So that's all I wanted to do there here.
I think all we really need to do is say well, whenever you're going to
do the packing, just give us an actual pack size.
That's how we're going to know how much space to reserve.
I'll have to pass that through as well here, like so, and then this
pack entity into World bit.
When we do end entity, and begin entity for the for the stuff in the
game, that is the stuff I'm talking about.
That's going to have to change, right?
We're going to need a SIM region for that, and we're going to have to
make the world creation code work.
A little bit more senior there, right?
But that's not too bad.
Okay, so let's see.
So now I feel like these need to be named more properly.
So instead of pack entity into chunk, this is just like, you know,
Reserve or or, you know, acquire chunks face or something like this.
Right?
For like, use chunk space.
Sighs just called the size.
So that's how much we want to actually use.
So we call use chunk space, that's all we're going to do.
And this would also do it.
We could just have these be overloaded functions.
They do exact same thing.
It's just whether or not you need it to find out where you're going to
pack it or not, right?
So now we just have
have used chunk space.
Like so.
And now it's pretty clear what that does, right?
It just kind of like keeps
Grabbing space from the chunk and getting more if it needs to and off
you go.
So, now we have the ability to sort of like, treat that as a separate
thing.
And like I said, the only problem that we run into now is we don't
have the ability to call the packing externally, which is the only
reason.
Like I said that, that ever would have been happening before is
specifically during World creation time.
And I assume that we just kind of put this in without thinking about
it too much because we were just trying to keep the Old World
Generation code working for a while while we were doing other things.
Things, right?
So we probably weren't thinking particularly much about how we wanted
that stuff to work anyway.
So,
What we need to do now.
Is when we are creating things so you can kind of see like we do add
familiar and that sort of stuff.
What we need to do when we're doing this code now is we're going to
have to do stuff where we can know that.
We're putting things into a particular Sim region, right?
We need a tan opensim region so that we can do the operations that we
want to do on the same region and then pack it down when we're done.
Now, one of the interesting things about this is
That we kind of have an odd situation when it comes to non simulation
stuff.
When we're doing World Generation, we can actually cheat as much as we
want because although the Sim region is conceptually a collection of
entities that are all in the same place.
There's actually no need for them to all be in the same place.
If you don't want to do Collision detection other things on them so we
can easily take a SIM region that's been opened up in one part of the
world and we can stuff in entity in there that's actually on the other
side of the world and it would not actually affect the functioning of
the same region at least not as we've currently written it.
Because as far as the same region is concerned, there's just a set of
entities in an array and where those entities are is strictly a
Out how those entities came into the Sim region, that is the only
thing that actually groups them together.
And when they get saved back out of the same region, they are saved
back out of the same region based on whatever their current location
is.
And if that location was somewhere else in the world entirely doesn't
matter, right?
So that's really the thing that that I think I'm going to do first
because why not is instead of trying to do something fancy, where we
actually start doing some of the world gencode, which I don't really
want to do right now because I'd really like to finish up some of this
engine stuff because we're kind of close to having that, you know,
having sings that I can, sort of say, I'm happy with their, how, our
stuff is.
And we're ready to move forward.
So I don't really want to move on to World gen yet, but I would like
to keep
keep our current world Jen working since it's what we use for testing,
And so, I think the easiest way to do that is just to open a Sim
region at the beginning, plow all of the entities that were creating
into our Sim region and thus, in region and that will pack back,
right?
So we really can just abuse the Sim region here temporarily.
You know, there may be reasons down the road, why we wouldn't want to
keep doing that when we were actually doing creation but certainly
right now we can totally do that.
It's not an issue at all.
And so, all I really need to do here is, is sort of take this this
system where we do beginning to the end end entity, I can just go
ahead and first of all, eliminate the need to do and entity at all.
Right.
That's not necessary anymore.
In fact, I'm not and I think that will kind of be nice because we can
just do begin entity anytime we want, and then I'll add it to the same
region.
And then we know in the same region gets closed, all of those entities
will get packed up automatically for us, right?
Okay.
So for right now, what we're going to do is I guess we just, you know,
we don't even need to call like that or anything.
You don't need to call this anymore.
We don't need to do that, right?
We don't need to do any of these things.
And so really all we're going to have is just these two things to do
and then later I'll collapse these.
So that the world position P stuff is just happening automatically up
in here so that you don't have to do and entity with the world
position.
We then we can get rid of the entity call altogether, right?
Okay, so when you call begin entity, what we actually want to do, is
we actually want that to be a create entity call, and we want that
create entity call to happen on the same region, right?
Now, I don't know if we've ever created a v before we probably haven't
because we probably had no reason to do that during Gameplay at the
moment.
We don't have any projectiles that we create at the moment.
So I don't really know that there's ever been a case where this has
happened.
So, what we want to do here is just say, like, okay let's make a call
that'll happen in here because we have a delete entity call.
Right?
Let's make a call this.
Just like an ad and
Right.
Something that since we can delete one, we can also create one.
When you pass the region, it will pass you an entity back and I think
all we really need to do there is say, well, we've got the entity hash
here.
And we've got the max entity count.
So all we really have to do is just add you know the this entity in
and make sure that it gets hashed into the appropriate location for
its ID value.
So when we do create entity, I assume what we want to do is pass the
entity ID, right?
We want to pass a one of these
and that's the The Entity that the idea that it will get and we'll
want to make sure
We inserted into the hash but that's about all we would need to do.
So let's go ahead and do that.
I've got to do something here, which is kind of just a random thing.
Obviously we don't at the moment, expand the same region if we have
too many entities, right?
If we exceed the max entity count number of entities in the same
region, we don't expand it to be able to hold more.
Now we might want to do that in the future but I don't want to do that
right now and I don't actually know if I'm going to ever do that in
the future.
I might require that you always have a hard limit because I just don't
want to deal with the possibilities of what happens when you overflow
there.
And whether that's getting tested well enough and blah blah blah.
So what I'm going to do instead is I'm going to make a thing called
the null entity.
And what the nullity is going to be is just a thing that if you try to
create identity and for some reason, you have hit the hard cap in
debug mode.
We would certainly assert so that we know that we've hit the hard cap
but rather than just having that crash the game or something at that
point.
Just in case we ever hit it an actual release mode.
I'm just going to have it returned the nullity instead and that way
there's at least a chance that the game will keep running properly.
The Entity that was going to get created will not get created, but at
least the game doesn't count.
Obviously fail right now.
You might argue that that's not particularly good idea because hey,
now you've just got this kind of like quiet bug in the game.
I wouldn't necessarily disagree with you.
What can I say?
It's my code that just happens to be the flavor that I want at the
moment and we are always free to revisit that decision in the future.
If it turns out to create problems for us,
So here is another entity in the the same region, right?
And what I'm going to do is I'm going to start off by assuming that
like that's the result, right?
So if something bad happened and we couldn't get an entity, the way
that we wanted to, we would just return that one.
Okay, so the next thing I'm going to do is say, all right, I know that
we've got a Max entity count and I know that we have an entity count.
And so, I'm going to say, if the entity count is less than the maximum
of the count.
Then I know I can actually add one.
And at that point, I know that I've got the entities array, whatever
that entities array is, plus the entity count that we currently have.
That's like the next empty slot, right?
And then if I increment it there, I'm going to move the pointer Pat.
I'm going to move the count past so that the next time through we dad
in the next slot.
And so on.
If we don't have the ability to add one here, I'm going to insert a
cert rather so that we
Know that we've hit a code path that we really don't ever want to be
kidding and probably something's wrong.
That needs to get fixed that way.
It won't happen silently and debug mode.
As I said, it's really not a good situation for us to be in.
Okay, after I create an entity, I'm going to return it.
I don't know whether I want to do this here.
I'm going to like keep this in mind, right?
Because I do believe that that was a valid thing to say.
And so I want to go ahead and make sure that we think about that a
little bit in the future potentially.
So that's how we create an entity there, when we create it will Zero
stretch the struct as we you know, create a new one.
And then we'll just return it.
So that's really all we need to do to create an entity now, because
they passed in an ID.
We also, now want to put it into the hash properly, so that other
people who are looking for this entity, can find this entity while
we're doing creation stuff, or things like that.
So after we 0 everything, we want to set the ID to the idea that we've
had passed and we want to insert the entity entity into the hash
table.
Now, if that's been already pulled out, then we'll just call it.
If it hasn't, then we will go ahead and ensure that it actually gets
pulled out into a separate function that we can then use.
So let's see here.
Entry.
So it looks like right now we I'm not sure why exactly were doing this
the way we're doing it.
So the question is, why are we adding to the hash outside of the
bounds?
Check right like why are we bothering calling?
Get hash from ID.
Because we don't even switch on that at all.
It doesn't make a whole lot of sense If we're honest about it.
You know.
Like, it feels like that should be inside.
In fact, it feels like this should just be a condition of the loop,
right?
It feels like, it's just like, hey, don't even bother coming in here.
If you can't add, you know, any more entities right?
Because it wouldn't even make sense.
So I feel like, unless there's something, let me see what's going on.
Get hash for my ID.
Yeah, so if we're calling get Hashem ID here, it just doesn't seem to
make a whole lot of sense.
It just doesn't seem to make a whole lot of sense.
So when we call get Hashem ID, we're going to get back in entity, hash
function entity, hash pointer that stores information about The
Entity.
You can see that this kind of goes through all of the possible
colliders here and looks for one place where I can stick it and it
looks like this is kind of almost a silent bug.
In a way because if you look The Entity hash has 4096 entries in it?
And if we look at begin Sim when we actually push on the number of
entities that's also 4096 and so you know that just doesn't make any
sense because it means that we would start overflowing the hash bound.
So we really just don't.
This is just not right like
This should look like this because until such time as we can verify
that we could actually add the thing in.
And I mean, we might as well just go full pull and say, hey, right?
And furthermore, we could look, I said just make it in here.
So while there's something to add in the block and you could actually
bother adding anything keep going, right?
Although I guess now, I think about it if I do it that way, I can't
have the invalid code.
I would like an assertion there.
Right, so I guess I'll just leave it inside for that reason.
Just just to make sure that this if path is still there, I'm going to
switch windows so I'm not I don't have my head obscuring things.
So yeah.
So when that happens you can kind of see that we actually do.
Do this in two steps here.
When we call get Hashem ID, assert The Entity pointer is 0 and then we
will set these up.
You can kind of see that if I wanted to I could reorganize this piece
of code.
To work very clearly in a fashion that would have this idea stuff get
set up properly.
So what I want to do is collapse this down into one function that gets
called regardless of how you create the entity, right?
So what I want here is a thing that's like inline void, add entity to
hash, and I want to take this and put it in here and it, you know,
I got a pass my sim region in and I got a pass my entity ID.
But then after that, all I need to know.
Is what am I actually storing here for the entity pointer.
Right?
So what I do additive the hash that should work.
Now what I could do here as well, is just say a Dandy to Hash actually
demands that you use the the entities ID field that's inside it.
That would probably make sense as well so I'll just leave it like that
for now and then we'll just change this to be.
Hey, okay.
So when we grab out this desk guy, you know, I will
I guess I'm not sure when we do the decompression step.
I guess I would want to do it here and say, okay,
a Dandy to hash,
And pass the Sim region and the entity which is desk.
And I have to set that first, right?
Like so I suppose that would be something actually that we get set up
here and then this could get deleted.
Presumably.
So yeah.
So then we come down here and we're doing create entity, what we would
need to do, is after we set that, we'd have to say, identity to hash
and so, that way, we could actually put the entity into the hash table
and it would now be capable of being looked up.
In this case, I just have some typos.
So nothing to worry about there.
All right, so now we just have to actually get this entity stuff.
You know, we have to
Have a SIM reagent, actually get it from.
So what I'd like to do here is just say, well, let's take a quick
look.
Maybe we can just store that in the world.
No temporarily.
Because like I said, this is only for getting our kind of current like
hacky sort of world Jen that we're just using, for testing, working
properly.
So if I wanted to do that, all I need to be able to do is say, okay,
give me back an entity.
Using the world mode like creation region or something like that,
right?
If there isn't one of those, we will just crash because this is just a
test code, we don't care.
So we should never, you should never be calling this without it, if
that makes sense.
Okay, so when we do a create entity and we pass one of those, all we
need to know is what the entity ID is going to be.
We know what that is here, so I can essentially have a thing that's
just internal entity ID.
That's like allocate or you know, allocate entity ID and that would be
something that takes the game-mode world like so it comes in here and
says there you go right going to be ID result equals whatever the next
unique ID was for these entities that were going to look them up on
when we choose to do so and then I will can just call that allocate
entity ID.
And be done, right?
okay, so now what we need to do is actually have that region exists,
that's not particularly hard to do.
And so now we've kind of, I feel like we might be a good shape here
because really, that was a pretty simple piece of surgery to do even
though we kind of drastically changed the way that work because it's
just, I guess we're just, you know, we're doing a reasonable job,
keeping architecture out of control.
Even though it's doing some fairly complicated stuff.
So, hey, it turns out we can just make that change.
And all we really need to do here is just say Well when we're going to
create this stuff where we go to start creating entities.
So and you know, here is the first time
Where are we here?
I guess it would be as bad.
Wall probably.
Yeah.
So I'm guessing like the first thing we do when we come down here,
right?
We haven't added anything yet when we create the world, all we just
make some Collision stuff.
So the first things we do, when we come into your and we start to try
and make stuff is we're going to call AD standard room which is going
to call like add wall and stuff like that.
So really, we just have to, before we try to do any of that, we just
have to do a thing where we'll say, like, okay creation,
Jen.
Equals, you know a new sim, we got to go through here.
Until we're all done, right?
And we've created everything blah blah blah, blah blah and I guess at
that point even know something to add walls there.
I don't even know what that's supposed to be and then we just do an
end region.
Here.
If that makes sense.
So that's really all I want to do again.
Not
Not too fancy there.
But like everything else we need someplace for this thing to actually
operate.
Right.
We need some way for it to actually something for the begin Sim and
simp are to actually work with.
And so inside the Sim region, I believe, when we do begin Sam, right?
We pushed one of these guys on and, you know, we don't have any way at
the moment of cleaning that up, we just use the temporary ban.
Sounds like we use the begin attempt memory and temp memory to make
that work, right?
And so we would need to do the same thing for that here and so if we
want to do that, all we would have to do is say take a look at the the
same way that we were doing this in the other parts of the code,
right?
where we say, alright, the intemperate memory
Pass in the Train Arena and then later we just do the end temporary
memory.
Alexa.
And that's basically it.
So now what we would have to do is just add a place for that to be
stored.
So, in here, you know, when we're talking about
Last use storage index instead of this stuff, we would have a SIM
region pointer that's like the creation region.
And when we do that, n Sim that begins him in that end Sim on the N
Sim.
As soon as we do that, I'm going to set the world mode, creation
Region 20 just in case anyone tries to use it.
It'll crash immediately because I don't want anyone touching it
anymore.
And then when we do begin Sim,
I need to pass the loading bounds, which I don't really care about,
but I can pass basically anything I want here, right?
So when we call begin Sim here, we've got the simmer Reena.
I got a pass the world mode, which we obviously have and the worlds
And then I've got the origin and the bounds, the DT and the particle
cash.
I don't have to pass the particle cash.
It can be zero right?
Which is good.
I don't have a DT.
I don't really want a rectangle 3.
Because I don't want it to load any entities anyway and I don't really
want an origin either.
So really, I'm just kind of calling this as a dummy.
One, that doesn't have anything to do with anything because I just
want one, that's going to temporarily store some stuff for me.
So oops.
So yeah, there we go.
Are we building?
I thought so I was like that build looks slow somehow.
We're still building in in
Optimized mode.
I don't know why.
All right.
So let's see how much damage we've done here.
Now, if we try to run the game what we have destroyed that makes
sense.
So let's take a look.
So problem that we're probably you know, we could easily run into here
is that these regions get oh,
Well, that doesn't look right at all.
Where's my call stack?
You can entity add player.
Update and render worlds?
Yes.
So I guess we do have sort of another situation here which is that
When we do add other things, we sort of add players out of bound to
that world creation process which again is fine.
We just need to make sure that when we actually do something like
that, we
Have some way of actually making that go into the mode.
It needs to go into when you're adding a player, right?
In other words, this would have to be sort of encapsulated.
And use a SIM region.
Now the interesting thing is the same region we actually know about
it.
So if we actually were passing some regions here, we would actually be
fine because we just passed the same region in that we already have
because we know when we add a player that we already have a SIM
region.
So I'll cheese this for now but then maybe we'll just go ahead and
start to unwind that code as well because why not?
We might as well make it a little bit cleaner.
We're going to have to refine this code eventually at least this
Like ads entities and stuff.
So that doesn't seem like a waste of time to me.
You know, it's not the actual world gencode, right?
It's just something that adds entities.
So yeah, the cheese version of this right, is this
The cheese version just sets, an done sets.
The creation region to whatever the Sim region is that we're currently
using, but pretty cheesy because it's pretty easy to mess up, right?
Okay, so let's take a look at now where we're at, we're at game update
and render up to and render worlds were updating brains here.
I guess it does appear so, and we're calling execute brain.
We're try to do a transactional occupy of an occupying segment.
We do the transactional,
Pi, it looks like
It gets back, annul for whatever we're passing now.
That actually looks like
that actually looks like the kind of thing we probably would want to
keep relatively safe anyway, like I'm not sure that this should really
be unguarded, the way that it is like.
It seems like crew returning.
0 here, would be a valid thing.
Like if desired,
And not desired occupier.
So I'm going to change that but we almost certainly still have a bug
because the fact that that wasn't happening before, but I just don't
want to kind of leave that in the code base because that's probably a
bad idea as well.
If you ask me because I feel like that's kind of thing that should be
able to fail if someone just passes like hey can I transaction occupy
this invalid location that I got back from some query that said like
you couldn't go anywhere that's the
Kind of thing that we don't really want to have to guard Upstream all
the time.
And so,
It seems like.
That is just a much better way to do it.
That makes sense.
Max entity velocity.
Yeah, so that's just probably.
I wonder if I can just skip that.
That's just probably.
Again like I said, we probably have a bug here with how we're packing
things down, but since we can't see, we don't really know how bad it
actually is.
However, yeah.
So I'm not going to do.
I'm not going to touch the max velocity thing.
I'm just going to step through.
Now when we actually do some down packs and make sure that they
actually look correct to me.
I'm also going to take a quick look here.
So,
We'll take a quick look at ensign.
Where is my n sin?
I just want to take a quick look at how we're packing down these guys.
Hmm.
All right, so what I want to do is I want to set a breakpoint here so
I can see what's going on when we've created the world.
I want to then go through and set a break point when we're about to
end our world Sims stuff.
Right.
So when we kind of go through here and we do an end Sim, and I'm kind
of grabbing these entities out here.
I want to see what these entities look like that.
I've added.
And also, I'd like to see
Many we added right?
This is the whole world Jenna as it.
Currently stands.
So we added 407 entities, which seems like a reasonable number because
remember all of our ground chunks, all of our ground like things you
can stand on and the trees and the Sprites like everything is a entity
at this point.
So, we would expect that number to be relatively high for the little
rooms that were making, so, alright, that seems like a reasonable
number to have created.
And now I would like to take a look at the entities themselves.
So here is like an entity that's going to get packed down.
It's got an ID of 7 which you know, seems reasonable.
I think that probably was because we reserve some from it space for
other things we've got
No particular brain ID.
No real values here to speak of of anything in particular.
It has the X and y-axis set properly which is good.
That's is what we want.
It's got one traversable on it.
It is not occupied.
Anything.
So that's good.
You can kind of see it's traversable is here.
It is true that that traversable doesn't seem to be set to any
particular.
I'm going to look to make sure that that's just not where it happens
to be.
So that I guess that would make sense to because presumably its
position in the world is just where it's at.
I don't know why it has a hit point array.
That's filled.
Oh, probably just cause the address has changed.
There's this position and they're all at different positions.
Those positions seem reasonable
So, that all actually seems pretty reasonable.
I'm interested to know maybe.
Did I introduce a problem here?
We'll find out in a second.
So, here I am, setting up the entity stuff, you know, placing the
entity where it needs to go.
And a DP plus equals chunk Delta well, which is just where it's going
to be moved to.
Is that right?
What a sec.
What is going on there?
Jump.
He goes entity be chunk P offset.
0 chunk, Delta offset - entity pee.
FTP plus equals chunk Delta
That coat looks a little weird.
Don't you think?
not to mention the fact that
so,
Was all we were doing.
They're trying to do stuff where we removed somebody from the correct
because we don't actually have to remove people anymore.
I feel like that was probably code, that's left over from having to
remove people, right?
Because nowadays, the chunk Delta stuff.
I feel like that is really not that necessary for anything anymore.
Right.
I mean, do we really even need that?
Hold on a second before I get any further into that.
Now that we're in this area,
I just am curious.
So chunk Delta.
What do we do with it?
All we do is do entity P plus equals chunk, Delta, okay.
And we don't really modify any of this code.
Any of these positions do we?
No, we don't.
So really all this is doing is doing that and renormalization step
that we already have in the other code.
It does seem that just seems like kind of a waste to me, right?
That just really seems like kind of a waste.
And it looks like in general like when we're looking at this here,
It just doesn't seem like any of this is necessary.
So if we take a look at What entity P does,
We're basically just seeing whether or not.
We need to do the little apron scrolling thing.
Yeah, I don't love this code.
I feel like this could be really simplified now because we've gotten
things down too much cleaner, in terms of what it needs to do in the
code.
And so I feel like this stuff is not as necessary as it as it perhaps
once was
But anyway, that's neither here, nor there at the moment.
I just want to fix that.
So when we do use chunk space and we pass that chunk P down which is
the place where we want the space to get used.
I don't feel like anything here should have changed appreciably,
right?
We're just passing the size.
We know, we wanted to pet to store one end of these worth.
When we come in here, we check to see if we can get it assuming that
we can get it.
We take up the use, you know, we take up the space that we had wanted
to take up and then we, yeah, we just return the pointer to the data,
which I store here and, you know, Rob with the entity and
Nation.
And, of course, I also then update the pieces that need to kind of get
packed down, but that seems like pretty straightforward, right?
That's not particularly, that's not particularly tricky.
So, I'm not sure why that would cause anyone.
Any problems added under need to Hash.
On the other hand, we did add, we haven't really looked at too much,
but it looks, I mean, you know, it was not a particularly complicated
code change.
I feel like it would be pretty straightforward.
And we do set the IDS.
Beforehand.
So that should all be nice and clean.
When we do the get hash, we set the pointer and the ID
Which is exactly what we want.
Now, granted, I don't really know why we bother storing the idea
because we could just store just the pointer, but I guess maybe we
want to avoid the double look up.
Anyway, back to our show.
So we come in here, we've got one of these entities and we're going to
pack it down here is our destiny.
Here's our regular entity, right?
And these things to should be roughly equivalent, they do appear to be
for the most part.
Looks pretty good.
Oh, there's the p.
There's that p-value.
Looks the same.
Yeah, so the only real question is here, do we mess something up in
terms of how to receivables get packed down or something like this?
I wouldn't assume.
So I also just realize too that, now that we've done this, we may have
to postpone the debugging till tomorrow but now that we've done this,
I've got my sim region that's gets past here.
I think we now no longer need the Sim region because now we've removed
that dependency which is really nice actually.
Because that you can see how this code would definitely got nicer
because now it's separated along the correct boundary.
But before we sort of had mixed up, the chunk, based World storage
with the need to pack entities.
And we got this kind of like hybrid that wasn't particularly good.
Now we just know we're packing some things into this.
We don't really care what they are or what they're doing because
someone else is going to take care of that and that's much nicer now
and you can see how that kind of made things get cleaner for us.
We still
About somewhere.
So we'll have to do something about that, but at least we're pretty
good to go.
I will probably go to the Q&A now.
Just to make sense just to make sure that people have chance to ask
questions, but while I'm waiting for questions, so we'll go to the Q&A
while I'm waiting for questions.
I will continue to kind of just peruse until I see a question on there
because as you know, I don't like leaving
Bugs in the code if I can avoid it.
So yeah, yeah.
What do we when we do entity star?
Here.
I could also comment this out and see if there's any visual clue as to
what the problem was with that.
So let's see here, Max velocity.
That's actually pretty handy because that's sort of like if we can get
more information about what we're doing wrong, we might be able to
pinpoint the bug more quickly.
So we call update and render entities are came from here is null, so
it wasn't on anything to begin with.
Looks like get some space traversable, therefore fails.
I would say again, that's the kind of thing.
I kind of want to guard against.
I feel like will want to harden these routines.
Probably, I'll take some time at some point to actually, Harden them,
specifically, just go through to do that.
Because these are the kind of things that are going to be getting
called from like very spaghetti, like random gameplay code.
That's just going to be kind of weird, and wild, you know.
And so I do kind of want these to be more crash-proof.
That is pretty cool.
Can I just say I've no idea what it's doing.
That's pretty great.
Let me take a look here.
Snoring tortoise, did you resolve the kerning horizontal advance for
kanji characters?
I found when employing myself on OS X at the font table level that
Ariel doesn't actually have kanji in it.
It seems Windows and Mac.
The higher level apis that cortex load multiple font files for you.
If it detects that you are trying to load a code point, that is
outside the range of particular font file.
I don't really recall you'd have to go back and look at those the font
episodes to my recollection.
I didn't super care too much about getting the
Turning loaded properly on those because I'm assuming that the actual
fonts we would use for the game would be coming in as bitmaps that we
would set the kerning on.
But yeah, I don't know.
I don't even if that was the case.
I don't know why that would affect the kerning because I should be.
It should be able to.
I thought the problem we were having with the kerning was that it
wasn't matching.
What would happen if we went into a Windows, like a normal, text
editor, and windows, and did it.
And so,
So I would have expected to get the same results out since we were
using their API if I remember correctly to extract the glyphs.
So, you know, I don't necessarily expect it to be good kerning because
most operating system fonts that I see most fonts in general have
lousy kerning anyway.
So I don't think I would have been upset about the kerning being
lousy, but I would have expected to match and I thought it wasn't
matching Windows, right?
And so that was kind of just weird because even if they are loading,
multiple fonts
Behind your back, it should still report.
The same thing to you know notepad is it reports to me and it didn't
seem like that was what was happening.
so, that's the kind of
You know.
That's the kind of thing that I was talking about back then.
So, what happens?
Here we get the entity p and the chunk P we zero out the offset.
We take the chunk Delta, and that's the sat there that gets added back
in.
That's all fine.
We say, use whatever the chunk P was the chunk P, was the thing we use
for the entities position when we begin semi soon.
That's all set correctly.
We add the entity to the hash, we set its trunk Delta, and we said
it's p by moving the trunk.
Delta.
When we pack the P down.
I see we're removing the Delta because whatever the chunk is that it
gets stored in that is the chunk offset that we use, so that's
reasonable.
That all seems reasonable.
What?
I don't know is what we were saying.
Cyberpunk hobo can you explain what the idea is behind?
Using a zero sized Sim region bound.
Yeah.
So basically when we first create the world, there are no entities in
it anyway so there's no need to discuss like what the region, what the
boundaries are of the same region because the boundaries of the same
region are only actually used for streaming in the entities in the
first place and setting their Flags.
But we don't have to do that at the outset of hours of the creation
pass because there are no entities this to stream in, right?
And so basically I was just setting the balance to know and the and
all that because there really wasn't
there really wasn't any need.
That's all, that's all it was really.
Because the symbols don't really do anything else later on, we might
want to set them because that we may actually be using up more
elements of it.
But yeah, so it looks like the problem we have is when I went and did
the pack unpack thing, it looks like I accidentally introduced some
kind of a of a packing error with p with the, with the position of the
entities.
And so, I'm interested to take a look at that because you could sort
of see like, saying just getting a clue from what's Happening Here.
When I commented that out, you can kind of see how everything is sort
of grass, you know, moving and gravitating in this weird way that
doesn't.
Take a whole lot of sense.
It sort of seems, you know, like like maybe the camera and all the
entities
Are zooming through space diagonally down, right?
Or something to this effect.
So it feels to me, like we've got a problem with the way that P is
being packed and unpacked, but that's just my initial assumption.
And so, if we take a look at how p is being packed and unpacked, we
may see something that I messed up in when I was working when I made
the changes.
So, you know, when we get the death P, were assuming that whatever we
get here, whatever?
We whenever we unpack an entity,
We're assuming that we're going to get.
I think I okay.
I think I see what we did wrong there.
Or at least one of the things.
so, if we go back here,
To World mood, where we were actually creating the stuff.
So when we call end entity, we're setting this entity P offset here,
right?
And
we're not actually setting the world location properly in that in that
case, right?
The world position is actually going to be some actual position that
we need to set properly in empty p in order for it to get packed down,
right?
So what we need to do here instead is when we actually pass this world
position.
So like you know we say and then a tea here these are all taking those
World positions.
Whenever we say, end entity
We have to actually use that position when we get it, right?
So we would have to do say you know, inside World mode.
I'm sorry inside world, when we actually get one of these roll
positions back, we would want to do the subtraction to take a look at
where that actually was relative to.
Relative to the Sim region that it's going to get packed.
Let me next to, right?
So we would want to do a thing here.
We say like okay, the actual entity p is going to be the subtraction
of
This guy.
And whatever the Sim region bounds are.
Right.
Worlds and Undeclared identifier.
Hey guess what?
It's because it's not supposed to be world supposed to be World mode
and element 2 to World position star that help.
So now we're actually setting that position correctly.
Which is, at least a little better.
So now we've actually, at least restored some some working
functionality here, but we still got some issues.
Like, you can see that we're not really working, quite right?
People are going through trees and such and other sorts of things like
this.
So we're not quite there yet.
But at least we sort of fixed one obvious, major issue and we're
mostly back to good, right?
So that's good.
Get in there.
Still no questions, huh?
So I'm relatively pleased with that, I think that's a good thing.
It means that we can now be a little more confident in how we're doing
that process.
It don't go off the edge of the world.
So that's getting better.
Although we still there still some bugginess there.
Like, people are getting stuck in, are able to walk into a
traversable, is where there should not be traversable.
So we still have some unusual
Some unusual thing where they're able to find those traversable 's
even though they shouldn't right.
Like those traversable should be occupied by the trees or something
like this and so I'm not sure exactly why they're not.
I think that maybe because we might have done some weird hacking us
there because we didn't have the clean way of creating things before.
I'll have to take a look.
For example, when we add a wall, when we do occupying will standing on
and then we do end entity that will do the pack down.
I feel like that should be fine.
I feel like that should work.
At least feels like it should work.
Yeah, I'm not sure.
Ma'am.
so,
I guess, one thing I can do right now though is I can get rid of end
entity which I wanted to do.
Oh I'm supposed to be not really programming right now, though, I'm
supposed to have ended if this if that makes sense.
but I believe what's happening there is
If you look at what's happening, I obviously can't go into these
trees, right?
And the reason for that is because my head still runs through the
Collision detector, right?
We are still running the head through the cones detector, but the
reason that other people can't go through the trees is just because
remember your have to hop onto a legitimate square, that was the rules
of the game.
And so the the AI is are just required.
Got to find something to hop on, right?
That's all there.
That's all
Actually need to be able to do is to find something to hop on and so
they don't have to go through the Collision detector, right?
And that's sort of by Design at the moment, like we probably will want
to push them through the Collision Vector eventually, depending on how
we feel about it, and we'll see.
But at the moment, they're not supposed to go includes doctor, but
they should never hop into the trees and we're not hopping issues of
or because those trees are supposed to be occupying, the squares that
they're on her go.
You should.
Never be able to hop on them.
So either the tree would occupy it or we could just not create a
walkable there, but we were doing before is creating a walkable point
and putting the tree on it and then you should not be able to get at
that point, right?
But what we're seeing instead is that that's not happening, right?
So,
Probably who's at fault there is that the trees when they're packing
down are not correctly, saving their reference to the thing that they
were on but I don't know, I haven't looked at it yet.
Invincible Chas.
I've just started watching the stream.
How often have you needed to refactor?
Major parts of your code?
Well, I think that kind of
So, I guess what I would say is, I tend not to like the word
refactoring, only because it's really nonspecific.
So, you know, it's a good term to use when you're just kind of
throwing stuff around there.
Like, oh, I'm doing some refactoring right now or something because
it's always true, but it makes it kind of hard to be specific about
what you're actually doing.
What I would say is that I don't generally unless I'm trying to figure
out like an algorithm or something, I don't generally consider my
time.
Be divided in into refactoring and not refactoring.
If that makes sense.
I am always refactoring to some extent, right?
Like most of what I'm doing when i'm programming is trying to refine
the code into a better State than what it's in right now because I
don't believe in the methodology of trying to design things up front
before you actually have written them and then like writing them out
from there and hoping that you got it, right?
Right?
Because that's where you really see stuff like a question.
Like you said, where you said, like how often have to do a major
refactoring, that's really the only time that you have quote unquote,
major refactoring as an event is because you were like, oh whoops, I
got it wrong but the design was so now I have to do my major factoring
but otherwise I'm not really refactoring or something, but I don't
really like that.
Mental approach to programming.
In my opinion, you should always be refactoring, right?
You should always be looking for ways.
to improve the architecture of your system, and that can be in very
small ways such as
A function to make it more clear.
What it does something that simple or as complicated as I'm changing
the way that this entire renderer get skewed or something, that's all
in a day's work.
And I don't tend to think of it as I have to go to a major factoring
now.
And furthermore, I also try to and you've seen me do this many times
on stream if you're someone who's watched a long time, but you said
you're new to the stream.
So, obviously, you wouldn't have seen this yet, but the other thing is
that I always try to take.
Take any big change, whether it's refactoring or just creating
something new, it doesn't have to necessarily be refactoring.
Could just be the initial walkthrough of something.
I always try to break it into smaller steps.
And the reason that I do, that is for two reasons.
One, it keeps the debugging, more simple than it was before, right?
Because now, if you're only making small changes at a time, you can
more easily identify what code may have broken, right?
It doesn't always work because you still can get very tricky bugs, but
it definitely cuts down on the amount.
Mount of tricky bugs you get because you haven't just changed the
whole thing at once, right?
And the other reason I do that is because it gives me a good metric
along the way.
As I'm programming to know whether the change that I'm doing is
actually good.
If you have a mentality where you're like, it's refactoring week and I
refactored all the code or whatever then you can very easily get into
a state where the refactoring you did actually puts you in a worse
State than when you started, right?
Because
Is one of the things that's very true about code architecture is
nobody and I mean, literally nobody can keep it all in their head at
the level of detail.
They need to, to make the exact right decisions without doing actual
programming, it just doesn't work.
I'm actually one of the people who I would count highest on the list,
in terms of size of system, they can keep in their heads.
And I can tell you for a fact that I am nowhere, close right to being
able to do that sort of stuff.
And so I feel like the same way to do that kind of architecture.
Work is to always break it into parts and always do it incrementally
so that you can see very clearly whether you've made a good decision
or not and so that you can abort that attempt at changing the code.
If you see very quickly, you know, in those steps that it's not going
to come out the way that you wanted to write.
So you're trying to also maximize the chances that you'll be getting
the information.
Should you need to change to either change or just completely abort
the chains that you were going to make, you know, modify or cancel the
change that you thought you were going to make based on that
information that you're getting as you sort of go through the process?
And so I think one of the biggest mistakes you can make as an
architect early on before you've had enough experience with it is
definitely trying to do two biggest changes that once assuming that
At the picture in your head.
Of why the change is good, is correct.
Because a lot of times, the devil really is in the details and
programming and you forgotten maybe it might just be one little thing
you've forgotten, but you did forget it.
And it means that that change will actually leave you in a worse
position than you were when you started or perhaps just a wash.
So you do all this work and you end up with no really benefit for it
or even a detriment and I've seen that happen lots of times.
So, you know, I would just say
That's a very important thing to be aware of.
So that's that's the approach we took on handmade hero.
We try never to have a like a time when we say that you know the thing
we're doing is just doing a big rewrite of all this code.
I try to keep it as incremental as possible and I tried to even when
we know that we're going to like replace some system or do a new
version of a system that works quite differently.
We take that in as granular a pieces
Possible both to keep the debugging down and also to make sure that we
can check ourselves.
As we go, the other Fringe benefit, you get by keeping things
manageable in that way to that, I would point out.
Is it also helps keep your morale up as a programmer over time.
Depending on your proclivities, you can definitely get to the point
where you can do very large swaths of code without your mind
Meandering, right?
But certainly
When you're first starting out, I think this is true.
A lot of times is that if you, if you bite off something really big
and you're like, I got to do this whole thing.
If you can't break it into smaller more achievable pieces, you will
take way longer to do it because you're not getting that sort of
feedback loop of like compile run.
See something happen, get some information.
It's a really much easier.
Way to keep your brain going forwards at a reasonable rate.
Whereas if you're like typing in miles and miles of code before
anything works or even compiles, that's just a really bad place to be
in generally speaking you know on handmade hero.
It's a little more aggressive than maybe I would want because I only
do an hour so that people can follow it.
And yeah that's not the size of a coding session.
I want I usually want to H bring a short break and then another two
hours or something.
If I'm going to do any kind of major, we're kind of code base.
That's probably what I'm looking for but that is what I'm looking for
at the end of that for
H, I generally want to be in a place where I'm at least compiling, I
at least know what's going on with a code and can see how it's lining
up and all that sort of stuff and that's after years of practice,
right?
And even then, I still just don't like to go that long without having
some kind of verification there and so I think that's a really
important thing to remember, especially when you're first starting
out, try to break things into achievable pieces, the first question
you should ask yourself anytime you're trying to consider a major
change or a major new system,
from, you know, from when you're just starting it,
Can I break this into more achievable pieces because that will really
help you on a number of fronts and it's just good practice in general,
for a number of reasons, even if you are already very experienced, I
find it's the right approach.
The vast majority of the time.
The noble one is the millisecond counter in the corner of the render
time for the frame.
No.
It's the amount of time we are currently counting between frames being
displayed.
So basically it doesn't like if you take a look in here,
You can you can actually see this information on the profiler, so if I
pause the profiler for a second.
So we won't take any more profile snapshots and we go over here and
take a look at what's going on.
You can see, you know, we've got the game update here, which is a
very, very small fraction of the total frame time.
So that's actually the amount of time we're spending, then we've got
our debug stuff which is just debug collation, which takes a ton of
time because we collate a bunch of debug information.
So that's actually
Not including the game time.
If we turn the debug system off, that would all go away.
And then up here is just us, waiting, for the graphics card which is
we have vsync turned on.
So some portion of this could be rendering time.
We if we turn to vsync off, we would know.
We haven't done that.
We don't have a button for that at the moment.
I don't think probably should add one, but so, so a lot of time is
also like a third of the time or so.
Here is spent just waiting around for the the graphics card to
display.
Also, this time is not actually accurate in terms of how long we would
take in an actual gameplay situation because it's were compiled in
debug bone right now.
So if you take a look at like how the clocks are aligned here, you can
kind of see.
This is our top list.
So 26 percent of our time is spent in
Work.
Twenty four percent of our time is spent sending stuff to opengl 15
percent is spent processing the debug information.
Not just you know, drawing it
And then, then we get down to actual code, right?
So, 75% of our time is not actually spent in us actually doing
anything.
It's all in other systems that are, you know, either the graphics side
of things or, or our
Debug system, we can turn all of this off, but unfortunately, as soon
as we start to turn off everything, like if we turn off the whole
debug system and stuff, we then can't get very much profiling
information so we can't, you know, at some point we might want to make
some that turns off everything except just the profile zones or
something like this.
But if we compile an optimization mode, a lot of that stuff gets a lot
faster because the compiler actually does a much better job of
producing real code.
And so, if you take a look at that, now you can kind of see a more
accurate.
Turret picture of what's going on here.
When these kind of get taken out of the equation, a little bit more,
you can start to see that.
Yeah.
So 56 percent of the time when we actually compiled an optimized
build.
So well over half that frame time which is six at 60 frames a second,
right?
16.6, a Mills at 60 frames a second.
We spend most of our time just waiting for the graphics card to, to
flip the page.
And again, I think most of that's vsync because, you know, if you take
a look at what we're passing down here,
It's just not very much in terms of Graphics load, we haven't really
done anything to try and optimize our opengl usage at all.
It's very, very simple, but even so, I suspect that it's pretty much
all vsync.
I mean, even this card, which is old, it's 10.
It's a 10 year, old card is, probably not having any trouble pushing
this at 1080p.
So probably most of that's vsync, but some of its made might be
graphed rendering and then we just get down to like feeding the
graphics card which
Probably just because we're not doing it efficiently and have to see
why we're getting so much there.
It could be.
No I don't think the sort is baked in there, so I'm not sure why I
opened.
It already has taken that time.
That's probably something we should look at.
Why to verify that?
It isn't something stupid we're doing.
But then, yeah, we get down to just our actual code here.
Only takes about four percent of the frame time as our actual code.
And Neil I agree that we should put in some opengl query timers when
we decide to do some work with opengl for reals like because we only
use very simple, we don't really do much with it at the moment when
that's expanded out more, maybe towards, you know, the back half of
the game after the games, you know, the game part of the game is more
implemented, and we just want to mess around with some graphics sort
of Glitz on it.
We would totally like
Some some query timers.
Fort 99.
I was about to ask, what would happen?
If one of the sneaky guys got themselves stuck in a corner but I see
one already did.
Yeah, it's interesting.
I don't really know what to do with the snakey guys.
In the future.
I kind of like the fact that they can get stuck.
I mean we haven't really tried to do any real monsters.
You know, I just kind of implemented some stuff so we could see
whether or not it was convenient to implement them in our system.
And as we go forward, you know, will continue to improve on those
sorts of things.
But basically, like, this game is not supposed to have super smart
enemies.
You know, it's kind of supposed to have very predictable and fairly
dumb enemies.
But, you know, a fair number of them on the screen.
You know?
It, like I said, it's a Zelda Binding of Isaac, e, feeling kind of
thing.
I was kind of shooting for, so I don't really want, you know like the
sort of military shooter the enemy knows to like
Throw a grenade to flush you out.
And then, you know, shoots you from the side kind of thing or
whatever.
That's not really what I'm looking for.
So, at the end of the day, if we do end up using snakes, if we do end
up having some monsters that are snake-like, which I suspect, we will,
because it's kind of cool.
I would probably say let's just let them get stuck.
If they get stuck, I feel like that's just serendipitous and you know,
maybe we add something to their code to try and prefer not to go into
Coils or whatever might cause that to happen but like I'm fine with
the player just having a good time and you know if a snake gets stuck
or better yet the player like pushes a block into a way in such a way
that makes it likely that the state gets stuck and then it does that
seems to me like pretty and keeping with the spirit of this kind of
game.
So I wouldn't be inclined to do too much work.
To prevent something like that.
Starting tortoise off topic since there wasn't any sound to the pre
stream or there any sneak peeks regarding handmade con you can give us
well with handmade.
Can I tend to try and release the information about speakers as soon
as I can?
Unfortunately this year it's been really hard to get final
confirmations from a lot of people.
So it's always like, well, you know, I'm still trying to get total
confirmation from all the people who I need to get
Complete confirmation from and, you know, it's mostly there but I just
haven't been able to get people to give the total confirmation that I
need to be able to continue and so that's just an ongoing effort.
It's been a real pain in the butt this year.
If I don't mind saying so just trying to get everything nailed down.
I was much luckier last year in terms of
Of how simple it was to.
Change to get everyone sort of to, to be able to commit and say, yeah.
And part of that is just this year, you know, I feel like the people
who I asked or at least a cross-section of people, I asked definitely
had to do more work potentially to say yes, either because, you know,
they had to get clearance from a legal department or public relations
department.
Pants or whatever.
And so, you know, that sort of thing, especially when you're asking
high-level people, you know, and handmade con.
I try to get people who really know what they're doing and typically
occupy, a fairly important place in their organization.
You know, they've got a ton of stuff to do every day and it's hard to
Wrangle all of those cats that you need to Wrangle.
And, you know, you have to remember, oh, right.
I got to do a thing for hammock on.
See if I can get the
Lawyers to sign off on me speaking there, whatever.
So, I think it's tough for sometimes, for some speakers depending on
what companies do work for, to be able to agree to stuff in a timely
fashion.
And that just does mean that in general like, you know, stuff takes
longer than then, possibly I would like to be able to announce the
speakers.
So there's that at the moment I think there's really only one.
I think that I'm that I'm that I'm having trouble getting confirmation
from.
Ironically, some of the people who have had to do a bunch of stuff,
like getting stuff, cleared, actually did a very good job, getting it
done in time.
And so, I think right now, the only people I'm waiting on are actually
people who don't have to do that.
So I'm hoping that they can can can make definitive plan sometime
soon.
All right, I think I'm going to close it down soon.
Let's see here.
So I'm before I do, I'm just going to say
That here, we've got bug in.
We call them.
What do you call these things traversable?
Where trees aren't occupying their spots?
I mean it'll be pretty obvious I suppose when we boot up tomorrow I
unlikely that I won't notice the fact that people are hopping through
the trees which they
Very used to do before.
So probably not a huge necessity to put in that to do but it can't
hurt just so we don't forget it in case I would have forgotten it.
All right, thank you, everyone for joining me for this episode of
handmade hero.
It's been a pleasure coding with you.
As always, if you would like to follow along with the source at home,
you can always do so by pre-ordering the game on handmade hero
dot-org.
It comes with a source code every night.
I update it so that you can do experiments at home with the code base
and learn along with the series.
We also have a forum, you can go to ask questions if you have
questions about what's happening on the show or how the code works.
We also have a patreon page.
You can go to if you want to support the video series and we have a
schedule bot that you can use that, you can subscribe to if you want
to know when we're going to be live.
There's also an episode guide maintained by The Fabulous, mid low and
it tells you what all of the episodes have been in the past, it allows
you to look at like time coded information on them so you can jump
right to when we've talked about certain things.
So it's pretty handy way to catch up on.
To the series that you may have missed if you want to, that's about it
for this week, I will be back tomorrow.
I'm on an alternating schedule.
Now I'm going to try that for a while 8 p.m.
and 5 p.m.
Stream.
So I do 8:00 p.m.
5:00 p.m.
8:00 p.m.
That's just an experiment for now because there are some people who
kind of like the five PM some people kind of like the apm's and I did
have an opportunity now, to kind of like arrange my schedule to have
that happen.
We'll see it.
Could be a complete disaster.
Could be good, we'll see.
But so tomorrow, I will be back here, but I'll be back here.
At 5 p.m.
for the Stream.
That's about it.
I hope everyone has a good evening of coding and I will see you all
tomorrow.
Take it easy.
Everyone.