Recording.
Start recording.
Minimize.
Hello everyone and welcome to a very sleepy Edition handmade hero.
I did try to go to bed early last night, it did not work.
I was able to have a midnight snack of cheese and almonds which is
tasty.
But that means that I am bleary-eyed.
I did have some coffee and we've been chatting for about 20 minutes
that we should have been programming for here, as I attempt to wake
up.
And hopefully, now we are at the point where we could actually do some
reasonable coding, but there's really only one way to find out and
that is to try to do some reasonable coating.
So, welcome to handmade hero.
The show where we code a complete game from scratch live on Twitch
with no engine and no Library, even
And when we are falling asleep, ladies and gentlemen, that is our
commitment as the handmade hero team.
That is our commitment to you.
So if you want to follow along today and you are not as sleepy today
is day 83.
So unpack the source code for day 82 and that is what I am starting
with.
And if you want to follow along, that's when you should start with
two.
Now, we left off yesterday with a little to do that.
I said, I didn't have time to go over and so, you know what, we kind
of need to go over that right?
Don't know if you guys remember also, it is high allergy season here.
So the amount of times I'll blow my nose in the Stream is going to
Staggering, that's just something you should be aware of.
So that is going to be like continual currents.
I know it's delicious.
Anyway, so, what I was talking about yesterday, we, well, you know,
for those of you who might have missed it, what we did is we made it
so that we could cash bitmaps and then use them, I realized we have a
ton of little heads.
I don't know why I left all those heads in there they're just kind of
little familiar sort of floating around, hi their familiars but anyway
that bitmap in the background there what we basically did is we made
it so that we could do caching of bitmaps
On the, you know, on the fly.
So we could basically anything that we could have drawn to the screen
we can now draw into a bitmap and so that's like a bunch of stamps
that we put together to make a ground texture and it was really slow
to do that because we don't have fast rendering routines yet.
We haven't written any.
We just have a really simple bitmap copied routine which is not
optimized at all and so that was really slow and tanked.
Our favorite songs like well, we could just cast the results of it and
then draw and that's what we did.
And there it is, right.
But
Haven't talked about what to do with the alpha yet, right?
And so I kind of wanted to take a second to just talk about what that
means, so that we can kind of see you know, what's going on here.
So let's do that.
Let's see.
If I can for some reason and I don't know, the reason my pain does not
seem to be working.
Why does my pain not seem to be working?
See here, pain, there it goes.
You know, USB just unplug it and plug it back in.
Alright, so day 83, there we go.
So
You know what?
It's not really working, it's actually going through Mouse emulation,
isn't it?
Seriously people, is that where we're at?
All right.
Well, you know what?
Let's close mischief and we'll see.
You've got that little weird thing showing up.
You gotta love Microsoft Windows people.
You gotta love that, that sort of stability.
It's getting more Linux see every day.
Yeah, this is totally untrackable.
Why have you ruined the handmade here?
A Blackboard.
Why can we ask that question?
Why would you do that to us?
I don't know.
Well, we're not off to a good start and I'm sleepy already.
You'd think they could, you know, cut me some slack here.
Yeah, so it's totally messed up.
Well, I don't know what to do about that.
I guess we'll have to take a second to actually try to figure out
what's going on.
I have no idea why it would just suddenly stopped working other than
that's the sort of thing that happens with computers these days, even
though nothing has changed.
You know, shouldn't we have?
Like a Wacom driver thing in here?
Yeah.
So the tablet driver was not.
So let's take a quick, a brief moment and just point out, this is what
I talked about, you know, we've said this multiple times on the stream
where I'm just, like, what is going on with Computing these days
nothing has happened on this computer.
It is exactly the same as when we left it yesterday, like nothing
happened.
So how do people manage to engineer software so bad that when nothing
has changed?
All of a sudden you just a driver is gone, right?
It's just, it's, it's ridiculous.
And the quality level just keeps going down and down and down, it's
awful.
So yeah.
All right, this is going to be the worst drawing ever.
I'll try to do it as well as I can, but it's super hard to control
because it's not actually reading the
Tablets, treating you like a mouse.
So it's all ugly.
I'll do the best I can and then I guess, will someone please remind me
at the end or send an email maybe to remind me to try and get this
machine to re recognize the tablet that it was recognizing just just
the other day.
so,
If we take a look at what was happening before, right, we wrote some
code where we basically, you know, we have our drawbitmap, this is
drawbitmap here, right?
We have drawbitmap call.
And what that does is it takes a bitmap that has sort of.
It has an alpha channel in it, right?
Which is like a mask or were using it like a mask to tell us where the
bitmap has data.
We actually care about in
It doesn't.
And the reason for that is because we don't want everything to be
square, right?
We want to have things that have shapes in them and when we draw them
to the screen, right, if there was stuff underneath, you know, if
there was some stuff here on the screen already, we only want to put
this image right where it actually should go.
We don't want to overwrite like we don't want to see, you know, you
can imagine
If we were to add not use the alpha Channel, there'd be like a square
of emptiness.
That would follow this thing that we put in there, right?
And we don't want that, we want it to cleanly.
Come to composite those edges, right?
And that's why we need that Alpha.
So, that was working fine.
We got that working and the way that we did that again, is using our
linear interpolation, right again.
Like I said, most important equation in game development basically
using linear interpolation.
What we did is we said all right, we have an alpha channel, right?
The alpha channel is encoded as a bite.
It goes from 0 to 255 and that 0 to 255.
Number tells us how mask the area is
Zero means don't show what's here at all.
So that's like this area 255 means full show.
Like, that's the, the complete opaqueness.
And then in between are like gradations of blending and that allows to
have anti-aliased edges or like sort of transparent like, partially
transparent things, right?
So we can, we can do some transparent effects are to.
We haven't really taken advantage of that but we could use it, right?
And so that all works, just fine because we basically export things in
out of out of GIMP that have that or out of Photoshop or whatever.
And, you know, we, we use those bitmaps a composite to the screen.
But what we wanted to do yesterday, was basically have a two-step
process, right?
Instead of drawing that maps to the screen, and just drawing bitmaps,
the screen drawing them, drawing and drawing them.
What we wanted to do was take a bunch of bitmaps, so, same scenario,
right?
Like so we want to take a bunch of bitmaps and instead of drawing to
the screen we wanted to do it to like an intermediate buffer, right?
So we want to draw this to some other buffer here and then eventually
later draw it to the screen and the reason we did that is
We could save the work.
So if we did like, you know, let's say there's a hundred X of these
sort of Blitzen to here.
We wanted to save that work and then use it again later, right?
But what that means is, we have to be able to produce an alpha channel
for this intermediate buffer, right?
So this had Alpha that came from Photoshop or some other place, right?
This doesn't need Alpha, right?
This doesn't have to have Alpha at all because it's just getting
displayed on the
Screen.
It's not getting compositing outs and the alpha doesn't need the alpha
is, wouldn't isn't used by Windows to do anything.
We don't need Windows, doesn't need to know our Alpha Channel just
needs to know the color channels, right?
But this right here, where does this come from, right?
How do we get Alpha here?
And so, we just want to take a quick second to think about what we
need that Alpha to be.
So we can make sure that we fill it in, right?
And that's kind of where we left it yesterday, right?
Because we got everything working but we hadn't really figured out
what we want to do with the alpha Channel.
And so I'm just going to say a few things about it and then we're
going to see what it should end up being based on that and try it
right.
So I guess what I would say is we can have
Um, pretty straightforward things that we would want to have happen.
The example would be I'm going to use the numbers 0 to 1 since that's
how we actually translated the alpha in there before because basically
we had, you know, the real value of this is 0 to 1 and we're just
encoding that in b as 0 to 255, right.
So this isn't this is in, you know, this is this is an integers and
this isn't floats basically or reels, right?
So if we're talking about the zero to one thing where zero is
completely transparent and one is completely opaque, and everything in
between, is some, some gradation thereof and were encoding at 0 to
255.
If we need to think about that, whatever comes in and whatever is
already in the buffer, is what we're working with right for any given
pixel.
When something is getting drawn in here, we've got two things.
We've got the source Alpha, right?
Which I guess we could call Source Alpha and we've got the destination
Alpha, right?
That's the thing that's already in the buffer, right?
So the destination Alpha
Now we know that when we start out, we want all of the destination
Alpha to start at 0, right?
Because if we have this buffer and nobody do anything into it, we
would want it to be completely transparent everywhere because that
means there's nothing in the buffer.
So if we were to bleed it to the screen later, we would want to see
nothing should not affect anything at all right.
So we know that the destination Alpha defaults to zero so what we can
say then is on that first blind that comes in the first thing that
comes in if you just did one bitmap and pleaded that to the buffer,
then Blended the buffer to the screen.
You
I want it to be exactly the same as bleeding.
What, what was in that initial bitmap directly to the screen?
Right?
We don't want it to modify at all when it comes through here.
So, basically, like the first time, we could easily say that we just
want the destination Alpha to be equal to the source Alpha, right?
So that's kind of a requirement that we would have for this is that if
you just bladed, one thing you want them to be equal.
Okay, so then what we really need to talk about is what happens the
second time, you know, and subsequently after that man it's hard to
draw with this with no pain driver.
So if we want to talk about what happens the second time then, really
what we're talking about is what happens.
When destination Alpha has some nonzero value in it.
Right?
Because we know here destination Alpha is always zero at the
beginning.
So it's just basically a copy through there, right?
So the second time through
And maybe I should write this slightly differently.
Like maybe I should say that.
Actually this is you know that
assigned destination Alpha from Source Alpha.
So the second time through what we want to have happen is if they're
obviously was a zero in there.
So you know we could say if there was a zero in there then we want it
to do exactly what it was doing before.
So anywhere that hasn't been touched it should still operate exactly
as the first time right because the pixels shouldn't, you know, each
individual pixels, kind of like its own buffer in some sense.
So if there's a zero in there it should be operating the same as it
was.
First time now if there is a 1.
So if Source Alpha equaled one, right then we also know no matter what
happens.
The destination Alpha should also equal 1, right?
Because if I'm taking something totally opaque and putting it over the
top of things I want to have that result be totally opaque as well,
right?
Similarly, if sauce Alpha was Zero, we would want destination Alpha to
be whatever it was before, right?
If the source Alpha is not, if there's nothing in the source image at
that point, we don't want to modify whatever was in the destination
at.
All right?
So at the source Alpha is totally opaque.
It should just overwrite it.
If it's totally transparent, it should ignore it.
So now all we really need to think about is, what happens.
You know, that's pretty clear when we really need to think about is
what would happen when there's other values in here, right?
And so, you know, it's kind of hard to
it's kind of hard to conceptualize because it's not clear.
Really what the operation equates to if that makes sense.
So let's say we had two things.
So let's say we had sa equals 0.5 and destination.
Alpha equals 0.5
Right.
So this is a half transparent thing that we do.
In there.
And now we've got a half transparent thing that were drawing on top of
it, right?
What should the destination Alpha be there, right?
Should the destination Alpha be half again, right?
Should it be?
Oops, man, groans.
His pain is hard.
In other words, should the destination Alpha be point five because
that's you know what was drawn on here?
Should this kind of work at whatever the remainder is of here.
So if we had point five and we drew point five on it, should that
actually give us another half again.
So should destination Alpha become .75, right.
Meaning that like
Let's say here is 1 and 0 and we're saying that this is the level
that's currently in there, right?
.5.
Should the remaining range be what's used with the, you know, with
what's coming in so that we're going .5 of the way up to up to Transit
transparent, right?
And so, you know, would we would we want this to basically produce
that value right?
Going halfway there.
It's almost impossible to draw with this thing.
This is awful.
Windows, I hate you.
You make my life miserable.
All right, so
Windows is like the allergies of computing.
But you can live with it, but it makes you unhappy every day.
Alright, so
Let's see.
So you know which of those to do we want to do and unfortunately like
you know even thinking about it.
Now I can't think of a really important motivating case here, to
really even know what we would do.
So I'm going to look at it from the standpoint of the things that we
actually have working now, which is, you know, what we're actually
using the alpha 4 and that is for edges, right?
We're trying to Alpha blend our edges,
The edges smooth.
And so the way that we're really looking at Alpha is essentially as if
it was coverage in some sense, right?
We're really kind of looking at it mostly a saying if there was a
pixel and an edge was passing through that pixel, we are setting the
alpha value to be, you know, whatever that
Whatever that portion is there, right?
So, like if it covered .5 of the pixel, the alpha should be point
five, that's sort of how we were looking at it because we're not
actually using it for transparency anywhere, we're just using it for
edges.
So, when Photoshop, when the, you know, you paint as a, you know,
paint brush through there, that's what it's doing.
So you get into this, this kind of problem where you say, well, okay,
if it's coverage, what we really would like to know is what part of
Pixel was covered, right?
Because you can imagine two scenarios.
Let's say I had one bitmap that covered that part of the pixel and
another bitmap that covered that part of the pixel, right?
And if this is point 3 and this is point three coverage then clearly
when those two things do on top of each other, you would want that
pixel to become .6 because they're both covering different parts of
the pixel.
So you want to produce essentially that amount of coverage right?
But you could imagine another scenario where one thing was covering
this much, and that's point three.
And another thing was covered,
During almost exactly the same part, right?
.3.
And in this case, the coverage, when you composite them you know, is
going to be actually redundant and so it's actually going to be
something like more like .5 or 0.3 still you know because maybe this
covered everything that this covered and so on, right?
So this is this problem is why you end up with things like multi
sampling, right?
In Hardware that tries to do stuff like okay we actually take many
samples per pixel so that we
Kind of tell where the coverage actually was instead of reducing it
down to a single number, but we're not going to go that far because
that has a lot of extra implications.
So that's in terms of performance memory footprint, all these sorts of
things that we can't afford.
So what we're going to do is say all right, let's just pretend for
sake of our compositor.
That what we want to do is let's just assume that the coverage is
non-overlapping.
So let's just say that the two coverage is were the same, we're the
same
And or rather, let's let's how should I put this?
Chinese activate.
Let's assume that we are not trying to compute some absolute coverage,
actual real coverage result that would require us to do multi
sampling.
And let's just do something that will allow us to produce reasonable
coverage in some other way, right?
So the first problem we might have is if we just add them together,
right?
We would end up in a situation where we would overflow
Right.
So let's say we have two things that each cover the whole pixel,
right?
We add those two together and this is one, this is one, we would end
up with two right now, that's not necessarily a problem because we
could just clamp the value from 0 to 1.
So we could allow it to overflow and that would be like this model,
right?
That would just be saying all of the coverage is assumed to be
separate and so we're just going to go ahead.
And add them in clamp, right?
So we could try that and we can maybe try that, and see what happens,
right?
So that's add and clamp
Right for Destination output.
The other thing we could do is this method right here, which sort of
is the same.
It's saying, let's assume that the coverage value is talking about
covering the part that hasn't been covered yet, right?
And so if we wanted to do that, what we would do?
Is say, well, alright, we've got one - we want to know what's the
leftover, right?
We want to produce this region, right?
So you want to do one - the destination Alpha, right?
Which is saying how much do we have left?
And then we want to multiply that by the source output, to figure out
how much of it we're going to use.
That's the part that the source Alpha contributes.
And then, we add that to whatever the existing destination Alpha is.
Right.
That's exactly this case here.
This was the destination Alpha.
So this is one minus the destination Alpha this region up here.
And then, we're just taking however, far, we should go in that region
and adding it back to the, to the bottom, right?
And that seems maybe a little better to me because, I mean, I have to
do the clamping.
So it's kind of like a more consistent thing, so I'd like to try that
one as well.
If you multiply that out right, what you get is.
- right, I'm just doing the distribution here sa da plus d a.
So the other way we could have raised this is sa + 1 - excuse me.
Sorry.
Do you hear?
I'm just pulling this D @d.
A out, 1 minus s a DA, right?
So there's two ways we can actually phrase.
It, we can phrase it in terms of collapsing, the da term and using one
- The Source Alpha and we could phrase it in the other way which is
doing 1 - d a on the source author, right?
So we can we can sort of pick who is the one who's being inverted.
Make sure I do that, right?
I'm pretty sleepy this morning.
Sa - sa da plus d.
A, that's good essay.
And so we're pulling this out here and that's, yeah, that's one - sh
that's fine.
And so, yeah, so that's what we've got.
And the only reason I was showing that is because we may already have
this value pre inverted.
So, if we wanted to fuss with that, right?
I'm going to go ahead and, and kind of lean on the loop Live code
editing.
A bit here.
I'm going to go ahead and
This so that we can kind of see what's going on.
So if like, if I come in here to our drawbitmap routine, it seems you
know if we take a look we already have that one - sa term, right?
We've already got that on there and so if you think of that term as as
in vessei, I'm just going to call that in vessei for now in sa inverse
is probably the not the best term but you know, sometimes you
Not too sure what the one- would really be called, right?
So, if I change that to invest a right, nothing, nothing will change.
We're doing exact same blending equation, there.
Of course, I guess.
That I think about it.
We need to rerun the the blind every time.
So you know what we could do to is let me
Draw test round.
Let me actually call that every frame.
So we'll tank our frame rate again, but that way it'll update
continuously for us, right?
So, if I just put this in here, right there we go.
Now we're drawing it every time so,
If we.
Does draw test ground but draw test down.
Doesn't clear the image.
Hmm.
Yeah, so that's I can't keep doing that because otherwise, yeah,
you'll get that sort of hmm.
Well, so I guess what, I'll have to do is actually put in a drawer
rectangle, called to clear it.
Right draw test ground that we can then remove later.
So it would be this, right?
We're drawing to the buffer and and clearing it right?
And we'd want to clear it.
Oh, and you know what I could do to, I could use
A size for that but yeah.
So let's let's just see what happens if I do that.
There we go.
There we got our black Fringe back.
Okay, so now it's going and you can see it's going much slower because
we it's not actually caching the bitmap.
So let's go ahead and and play with that drawbitmap now
Alright, so in my drawbitmap call.
Now what I want to know is what should happen with this Alpha channel,
right?
And if we take a look at what we wrote out here, I said it was sa plus
1.
Minus s Ada, right?
And if you look that's exactly what we were doing with everything
else.
We're just doing the inverse S A times the the destination right plus
that that sa right.
That's that's exactly.
We're doing so.
All right, so if I just, let's see what happens if I just go ahead and
use that as our compositor.
That's not quite right.
That's right.
We've got these into different spaces.
I forgot about that.
So unfortunately, these are still all 0 to 255, aren't they?
So da is in a different space than essay in this case, which is not
what we wanted.
So what we kind of need to do here is we need to actually we need to
actually save essay in that case.
So I guess we'll have to sort of introduce maybe this for example,
right?
If we were to load them all out and then I grab
out of
Looks like so.
So if I were to keep them in the right space and then I just make a
real-valued version of The Source Alpha where we still have, what the
source Alpha is in the, in 255 land, right?
That would allow me to do what I need to do here to allow the blending
to work properly, right?
So now everything's in the same space if you don't have one, that's
been normalized and one that's in the range of 0 to 55, which isn't
going to work.
So I believe that would give us back to all right.
I'm not exactly it.
I believe that would give us what we wanted.
So that stuff is now you know in that in that correct space.
So when we load out the essay now that's a number from 0 to 25.
We divide that by 2 T5 to give us a number between 1 and 0.
We make the inverse of that by subtracting it from one.
But obviously I made a bit of a faux pas there because now we have an
amazing rainbow pixel screen which
Which honestly is kind of a little bit mesmerizing, but yeah, so what
did I mess up there?
I took out the source Alpha I did, in fact, divide it by 255, which is
what we wanted.
So that turns it from 0 to 1.
The C Alpha is just that coefficient so that we can like dim things,
right?
So that's fine.
The destination Alpha is getting, read out as a number between 0 to 25
there.
And I think, oh, there it is.
Right there are I forgot to put, you know, I forgot to replace that
with the new value that we computed.
Okay, so there we go.
So our least our Blitz is working that properly.
So now we just need to get our other destination Alpha stuff to be
correct.
So if I composite these things together that right?
Okay, there we go.
And that one still needs to be the source Alpha because this is that's
actually the blend.
So it would be, you know, that way.
All right, so, given that, that is that first method that we were
talking about, right?
That is, that is the method that we, that we wrote here, write the
essay plus 1 minus s Ada.
Right, that's exactly this.
And so the question is, did that produce, does that produce the result
that we expect
and the first question is well,
You know, is there anything objectionable about the way that composite
is working?
And, you know, if we take a look at what happens in these sort of edge
regions here, what I'd like to do is, maybe take a look at what they
look like in Gimp to see sort of, you know, what would be a reasonable
thing to have occur.
Now, if I, if I go
And open up.
Let's see, start made beta if I go and open up one of these that we're
using.
In Gimp so I can actually do what its edges look like.
I'm going to go ahead and here and make a, an actual thing that is
essentially the same as what we have screen.
So we've got a half bright thing, 128, 128 128, right?
So, I'm going to take a layer here and just fill it with that.
So we've got that essentially, right?
And so you know that that is what what one of these looks like.
When we composite it, just one of those sort of
Flats onto the screen.
And similarly, if I go in here and I open as layers, some more of
these, right?
I'm trying to think of which just trying to make sure we get a bunch
of them in here.
Right, so you can see some of them do have like darker regions Ground.
Zero doesn't write that one doesn't as much that one does have some
Darkness to it.
And so on what I'd like to do is say okay, let's take a look at at one
of these ones that doesn't have any any darkening fringes around it
and let's just use that one for the compositing and let's make sure
that our Alpha equation that we were picking their doesn't produce a
bad sort of fringing effect.
Let's make sure
That that when you composite layer these on top of each other, it
looks okay, right?
So in order to do that, this is Ground Zero Zero dot bitmap is the one
that I had.
So I'm going to do is in that draw test ground function.
I'm just going to go ahead and see what I'm going to go ahead here and
see what
what selection we were using.
So this is grass.
I'll turn off the grass entirely.
So we don't have that, right?
Let me bring that back up here.
So grass is gone entirely.
Oh whoops.
Sorry that that actually also draws the stone.
So what we want to do is turn off the grass entirely here, like that.
And then we also want to.
Well, in fact, you know what I could do is just say, all right, you
know what, here's our else clause.
There we go.
So we're just going to take that first stone bitmap and we're going to
use that, right?
So what you can kind of see here,
Is if you look at, if you look at what happens this didn't have any of
that darkness in it, right?
There was no when you can positive, this on this doesn't have any of
that Darkness on there, but if you look at what happens with the
actual bitmap you
You all of that darkness in there, right?
And so the question is, you know, what happened?
There is our Alpha equation wrong, why are we getting that?
Why are we getting that?
That Darkness, right?
And the other thing, we might try just to see right?
Is what would happen.
If we turned off that?
What would happen if we turned that off basically?
Right?
What would happen if we said?
We don't actually want
Let's see here, it map.
Sorry getting very sleepy today so it's a little sluggish.
What would happen if we just said?
Alright, the alpha is always just going to be 1, right?
So what does it look like if we just if we just always put in that 255
value there?
Right?
So, if I, if I restart it here, right?
And you can kind of see, you can kind of start to understand what's
happening there.
What we're getting is, we're getting the black of
The cleared buffer.
So the buffer that you know, when we cleared it initially to just have
nothing in it, what we're getting is that black color of the buffer is
bleeding through to our result?
Does that make sense?
And so that can kind of guide us towards fixing, what's wrong with our
compositing so far so that we won't introduce that black at the edges.
So again I picked a real bad episode.
Had to be talking about the math of alpha compositing, because we are
still, you know, because this pen doesn't work at all.
Oh and you know what I should also do.
Let's double-check that ad and clamp doesn't work either, right?
The other thing that we were thinking of so add and clamp if we were
to do that again here is oops.
There we go.
Add and clamp.
If we're to do that, that's what we're currently at.
And if we were to do ad and clamp instead of this, that would just be
a equals D.
Ay + sa.
And then we just say, if a is greater than 255 a equals 235, right?
Just we just pull on clamp it and you can see that we still get the
same problem, right?
So it doesn't actually matter which of those two we did.
It still doesn't work, right?
So what can we do here?
What's the problem?
What's going on?
Well, I don't know.
Let's go back to the.
Let's go back to the the Blackboard and see if we can figure it out.
So
what's happening is we're getting color bleeding through so we don't
necessarily know if it may not be our Alpha.
That's at fault here, right?
It could be that we're dealing with the.
It could be that we're dealing with with the colors and correctly,
right?
So let's think about what was happening there.
What was happening there was we had a color that was in the buffer,
right?
So so here's the source color, Source color is 0, right?
And then we had a destination and and I'll put the source Alpha here,
right?
So we had a source color and let's just say, we're looking at one
channel, right?
Like the red Channel or something.
So in fact, I could make
That more explicit.
So let's say we have the source, read Source, read was zero, right?
Then we have the source Alpha and the source Alpha was some, you know,
percentage was .5, it was on those edges.
Right.
And so we have the source of the source color being this, we have the
thesaurus Alpha being that and then we're compositing against
Oh, I'm sorry again to Sleepy today.
This is the source.
So the source red is some color.
It's point seven or something like that, right?
And the source Alpha was some, you know, portion that was .5 or
whatever it was.
Right.
And so then we have the Des tread and the desperate is cleared because
the buffer doesn't have anything in it.
So it's just clear.
20 and the destination Alpha has nothing in it as well, right?
So what's going to happen when we do this composite, right?
When we do this blend, what we're going to get is we're going to blend
The Source red and the dust read together, right?
And maybe I'll make this point eight just to make the math a little
easier on us, right?
When we blend that dashed red in there with the source red, we're
going to end up with point for, right.
We're going to go halfway in between these two because it's a halfway
Blends according to the source Alpha, right?
So the resulting color, right?
the new destination read in the buffer is going to be point for
The alpha channel is going to be something else, right?
Whatever we compute, it's going to be something else because we were
just talking about whatever that we don't know what it is.
We're obviously Doing It Wrong maybe and so it's going to be something
else.
So they'll be something else in here right now, when we go to do our
final thing because now we've got the screen read and the screen has
no Alpha right but we're this is our screen buffer that were actually
going to draw when
Go to composite these two together, right?
We wanted it to be the same as if we were compositing, these two
things, right?
This and this and I guess I shouldn't use screen because we're using
source for that.
So, we'll call this be
For buffer, I don't know.
Back buffer, let's say so whatever this this happened to be, you know,
if this was point five, right?
What we want to do is this is point five for that gray and this was
originally .8, if
We're to blend these two together.
Right?
What we would have expected is to get halfway between .5 + .8, right?
If we were doing the blind just directly like we're doing before,
right?
So what we wanted to get was something like, you know, Point 65 or
something like this, right?
We want to get halfway, we want to get point eight plus 0.5 over to
write if that makes sense.
So that's a point, three difference of .15.
So yeah, it's like you know, it's like point six five.
We want it.
We wanted that.
So what we wanted to see for our red Channel.
Well, nothing I'm ever going to do is going to produce a point, 65
once this has become point for this is now way too low, right?
For that to actually occur.
So what can we do right?
What there's there's no it looks to me.
Like we've we've backed ourselves into a very problematic situation
and essentially what's going on here, right?
Is, this is kind of like, I mean, I guess I don't know if it's the
best motivating case for it but this gets back to
This to do right here, which is someday we need to talk about
premultiplied Alpha.
This is not premultiplied Alpha, right?
Well what you can see here is that if we if we really want to try and
Tackle this problem it looks like we knew and we need a new way of
encoding the color, right?
So that when we encode the color, we don't have this problem.
Where we back ourselves into a situation where it doesn't look like we
can possibly produce the result that we actually wanted from the
inputs to the system, right?
And that's where premultiplied Alpha comes in.
So, if you take a look at what's going on in these equations,
premultiplied Alpha originally came sort of as an optimization, it was
an optimization idea.
And what it was looking at was the fact that like, hey, wait a minute
when I do these computations.
When I do the blending, you'll notice that I'm always multiplying the
colors of the source by their Alpha channel, right?
They never we never use S RS, G or SB we only
Who's them X their original values, right?
So it's like, okay, why don't I just store the bitmap pre multiplied
so that I don't have to do these anymore, right?
Why couldn't I just, why would I just do that?
And so that I don't have to do those multiplies, right?
It's more efficient and that's where premultiplication really kind of
came from her initially, but it turns out if we take a look at that
pre multiplication,
We can actually get, we can actually potentially fix this problem as
well.
So, let's let's quickly take a look at what would happen if we were to
change that encoding, right?
So let's say we have the
Same thing again.
So we have a source read that was supposed to be .8, right?
And we have a source Alpha That was supposed to be point five.
Right, like so.
And then again, we have that background, we're going to do eventually.
So will do, will do exactly the same setup.
So we've got Dr.
And and da here Dr.
Da and we got those has zero and zero.
So let's suppose instead of storing, this is point eight, we store it
premultiplied, right?
So it's already going to be multiplied by its source, Alpha value,
right?
So this is already going to be 0.45.
I'm sorry point for right, so it's already going to be what it would
have been when it's when it's going into this buffer, right?
So now what will happen when we do our Alpha blending equation.
Is when I composite.
So let's let's say we were going to do that screen composite will just
say so our final thing.
So we're going to skip this step here for a second and we're going to
do this green composite.
So we've got our screen.
Our buffer that's in there.
It's got the point five in it and we're going to do this composite
right now with premultiplied Alpha, right?
So you already saw me do what that is?
Even was, we're just saying we're getting rid of that multiplication
term.
So instead of doing the equation down here that we were doing before
where we were saying, okay, so it's going to be 1, minus the source
Alpha, right times, the buffer, plus the source Alpha times, the
source color, right?
That's what we were doing before we're saying this is going to be P
multiplied.
So the actual thing that we're going to compute is 1 minus the source
of a time's the buffer plus whatever that premultiplied.
Al you already was.
This is the new equation, right?
So we don't X that Source Alpha.
So let's say right,
That we're going to do that.
We now get exactly what we had wanted to use me.
What we had wanted to get before, so what?
Because Watch What Happens, right?
I plug these in.
And I get 1 minus sa, which is still point five because one minus
Point 5 is 0.5 times.
B r, which is 0.5.
So, .5 x .5 is 0.25, right?
And then I want to take the The Source color, which is point for right
and add them together and I get exactly the value that I wanted,
right?
It's exactly the right value .65.
This is exactly what we said we wanted now.
How did it do that?
It does that?
Because now we're encoding that value that we add directly.
So we don't have this problem of over of having to get a number over
one, to do to ever produce this actual blend to occur, right?
We've pre encoded that multiplication and so we can just produce the
value directly, right?
So that works just fine.
Just like in the old case and that would have worked up here, right?
And so now when we do this, when we do an intermediate stage
It will flow through properly.
So Watch What Happens, right?
I do the blend here and I get the exact same equation that we're doing
down here, right?
Is going to happen.
So I take the source red of point for, I take the destination red of 0
and obviously doesn't matter what I multiply by zero.
So the one - Source Alpha times, 0 is just going to be 0 again.
So and then I add the source red.
And so the source red persists as point for
Right.
Let's just put in directly.
I don't know what we're calling this.
We're calling this Dr.
So Dr.
Is .4.
And then the destination Alpha, right?
The destination Alpha.
We know we now can in a position to directly, see what, that should be
the destination Alpha.
Well, I guess maybe not.
Well - we might to work through.
We'll have to work through another case where this has some
destination outfit in it to see exactly what the equation should be
for that.
So, sorry, I misspoke
So, in order for this to still work, obviously, the destination Alpha,
if we wanted this to come out, exactly the same, which we do the
destination Alpha is going to have to be the same as the source off of
there, right?
It's going to have to be point five in order for that in order for
that to work, right?
And then we go and go ahead and and and then we go ahead and finish
the blend, right?
Does that make sense?
Because we know that we wanted it, we know that it needs to pass
through exactly.
In this case, in order for this to still produce the .65 that we
wanted.
So that we know that in the case, where the destination outfit 0, we
want the source Alpha to be Point 5 and now we've corrected this
problem that we have here but we still don't know.
We need to work through one more case to figure out what we want to
have happen if the destination alpha or Eddie had
Nothing in it, right?
So if we go ahead and do one more, so let's say we do the exact same
thing again.
And we think through what we want that to be, let's say that we had
Source our source, Alpha death star dust Alpha and let's say that the
dest alpha in this particular case was going to be.
I don't know.
Let's say it's .5.
Let's say let's say the destination Alpha is is actually
Maybe.
Let's seems that seems like probably the best thing to try next.
I'm going to go with that.
I haven't worked out this sort of stuff in a long time so I'm sorry if
I'm not picking the exact right set of cases to kind of show it as
easily as possible.
That's that's interrupt you.
So if we had our destination read of zero and we had our source red,
let's say the source red again.
Is the point eight, so it's multiplied, pretty multiplied.
Right?
So what we would want to have happen here, remember this was
originally a source Alpha of .8 before it got P multiplied by its
source.
Alpha channel of point five, right?
So if I had a background that was fully opaque already and there was a
zero in there, right?
I would want to produce
A result that was a halfway blend between these two color values,
right?
I would want to say that I want to go point five of the way 2 .8.
So I want to have point for in the resulting destination read/write
point for and certainly I still want to have a destination Alpha of 1
as well, right?
Because if it was already opaque, it should continue to be opaque at
the end.
Right.
So we come through there and then at the end of that, we would, we
would lend against the screen.
So the ad will still work here.
No matter what we do, the in Source, Alpha will work exactly
correctly.
So that that blend equation that we're using before works, and the
destination Alpha in that case, we would want to pass through exactly
because it should produce an opaque blend of point for.
All right, so now what happens again if this was .5 let's let's keep I
don't want to keep having to draw this tree, right?
So you know that.
Pass through in that case if we were going to say that it was .5.
Now what should the destination Alpha be right in the actual result?
Because in this case we're saying all right, we had something that
comes in its half so that we know that the color that we produce
should be halfway in between these two colors, right?
The original color here, we know was also 0.
Because, obviously, if the destination Alpha minus point five, it had
to be point five times.
The original color to produce the destination, which would be 0.
And similarly, here we know it's the
Point eight.
So we're still want to produce point for here again.
Same equation.
Nothing particularly confusing going on there.
But again we get into that destination Alpha situation.
What do we want to produce as the final destination Alpha here?
Right?
And so if we had that screen buffers read write and that screen
buffers read was .5 as it was before, right?
What would happen if we had done two, subsequent blends?
On this right?
What we're saying is if we had just done these two in series, first
this one, and then this one right?
What would the resulting color be and that will tell us what the
destination Alpha should be to make sure that that gets reproduced,
right?
And again that's a little complicated but but thankfully we've got
we've got a little more time here, right?
We've got we've got about 9 more minutes.
It's well, this was almost an entirely Blackboard episode.
The exact wrong day for that because the Blackboard thing was the
Blackboard pen is broken.
Some days you just don't have any luck.
That's okay, I was sleepy today.
So what do you do?
All right, so back to where we were at.
So if we were to do these two things separately, right?
Well we know what we wanted to have happen.
Sorry, so if we were to produce these two things separately, when we
do the drd, a blend here with against the screen, right?
So if we were to do this one against a br of point, five, right?
Then the color that we would expect to end up with would be point two
five, right?
You expect to get that after doing, after drawing this, to the screen
because we're doing a halfway blend between 0, the original color 0
and the original color point five, right?
So we'd expect you to cover .25 and then we would come along and we
would blend this guy in there, right?
We would say, all right, the SR, the essay, we would expect to blend
this in there and say point four point five.
So now we want
Halfway blend again, between whatever is in there and .8, right?
So I'll do the Emax quick calc there.
We basically want halfway blend between 0.25 and 2.8, right?
We want to average those two guys together so it's point five, two
five.
So after that next we want point five, two five.
So our goal is obviously
Maybe we can just tell from working it through.
We want to produce that as the actual eventual result in this, in this
color channel, that is what we need.
So given that we know that we're going to come out with a point for
here.
The question is, what is the alpha value, right?
That when we when we do that equation to be, are there, what is the
alpha value?
That would that would actually produce that, right?
Does that make sense?
So, we need some equation of sa and da, that's going to produce the
proper result there.
And so, to produce the actual color value, again, we're doing, we're
just doing one - the alpha Channel times, whatever was in the, ER,
Plus whatever the, the incoming color is, right?
So when we look at that, we're saying that that result has to be Point
5 to 5.
We know that
The incoming be are there is point five, right?
We know that the incoming red channel is going to be point four.
So what we need is something where one minus a x .5, oops times 0.5
plus point for
Is going to equal point five two five, right?
And it's pretty easy to see what that would be.
If we just actually go through this, we end up with Point 5 minus
Point 5 a right distributive equals point one, two five, right?
So, if I subtract from both sides, I get Negative point five a equals.
Well, - because it's .125 - boy
Five, right?
I never am good with math like this, so, I always do some point 5,
minus point one, two, five, we go .375 - .375 and divide both sides by
the point five.
So, if you could do last result in quick calc, I bet you can .375
divided by 0.5.
There we go and we get 0.75.
Right?
So let's just double check that that works properly.
So basically one minus Point 1, minus 0.25 that would be point.
I'm sorry 1 minus 0.75 that would be point two five, right?
So point two five times 0.5 plus point for its double check
Point two, five times 0.5 plus point for give this our value, right?
So now we got another piece of the puzzle.
We know that the the alpha value here.
Is going to have to be point two five, right?
So it's starting to look like, okay, well that's you know, that's the
source Alpha times, the destination Alpha, right?
That's just sa x d a.
So it kind of looks like s Ada is what goes in here right now.
We can click test that, but we haven't really mathematically worked
out.
That's actually true, but we kind of see.
We can kind of see where that starting to go.
So if we were to pre multiply things,
That is what would happen.
Let's quickly go ahead and change if we were to do this, right?
If we wanted to
Switch to that.
Premultiplied Alpha.
You can kind of see where is my load groups, where's my loaded bitmap?
There is debugger bitmap call.
So if you want to change to premultiplied Alpha to start to get this
working right, what we would have to do is when we're doing when were
you know, writing out our destination stuff here, we have to do.
So we have to be able to pre multiply whatever it is.
That's coming in.
To put it into this format, where where, instead of storing the colors
themselves we started them premultiplied, right?
So if I wanted to do that, what I need to do is say all right.
Well the alpha is going to have to be pulled out here, right?
First of all, so so that we can get it.
So we've got to get that Alpha value out like so so that that like
that, we've got to get that Alpha value out.
And then when we actually do,
I,
It's not exactly the way it should do that because we don't want that
rotate Alpha shift part.
So when we actually get the alpha Max mask out,
This is a little bit weird, so Superman's redshift.
Okay so basically this was the place we were kind of getting
overzealous with our bit scanning and all that sort of stuff.
So this is actually not quite what we want because what we want to do
here is actually multiply is actually get out those channels, do the
multiplications and then put them into position.
So really we don't want what we're doing here because this puts them
directly into position as they get loaded, but we want to actually get
them out first, right?
So, let's go ahead and take that one step at a time.
I'm going to go ahead and kill this guy, so if we take a look at what
happens now, when we load, that's what we get.
Let's go ahead and add that pre multiplication step here in.
Well, let's even just take it one step further once.
Step slower.
Let's actually grab out each individual channel so that we can get
what we want out of it.
All right, so if I was to do an RGB pull here, right?
So I'm going to get, there are G, the B.
And the, a, what I want to do is I want to to shift them down first,
which is how we had this code set up originally, but then people were
like, you should just shift it directly into place, which is true for
what we were doing, but it's not exactly what we wanted.
I should have resisted the urge.
When people said that you should do that, I should have said no, but
it was good to show.
I guess how we do it, so that's fine.
All right, so we found the least significant bits of these guys, so we
know actually what the shifts are for them.
We know that, you know, in fact, I guess we could say that we've got
two shifts here, we've got, we've got a red shift up in a red shift
down, kind of a thing.
So, we know that when we when we rev, when we read, when we shift the
red down, it's going to be there.
And when we put it back into position, it's going to be there, right?
This is green shift up.
This is blue shift up.
And this is Alpha shift up.
All right, so these scans that we did our, what we want to do for
shifting down, so really, what all we need to do is, is take our masks
stuff here and we can just do the shift directly.
We don't need that rotate anymore.
So when we rotate it down, this is our refuge redshift down where
we're going to grab it out there.
We can just go ahead and do that for all the different colors, right?
Green mask.
Blue mask.
Alpha mask.
I'll shift
Blue shift down range it down.
So we grab those out.
And then we just need to put them back, right?
So then we just need to say, all right?
We've got the, our redshift up like so.
Pudgy, green shift up.
4B.
You shut up.
And they.
I'll shift up, right down down down so that Loops that should produce
exactly the same thing that we had before, right?
No worries there everything's fine.
So you know
We've done the exact same letting me before.
So now all we have to do is do that pre multiplication.
I don't want to have to talk about exactly how to do the fixed point.
A fixed Point multiplied here.
So I'm going to do exactly the same thing that we did in our Alpha
blender which is just do the conversion in and out.
So I'm just going to say alright let's just say that we got these out
as reels for now, right?
And so I'm going to convert them after we do that.
In two floating Point values.
So we can let the floating Point multiplier do it.
For us, right?
So there we go.
So, we can convert those into reals.
Like so.
And then we're going to do that that same exact procedure we did
before, where we kind of take a normalized version of a, if you will.
So, we say that we get, we take it, and we divide it by 255, so we can
produce a number between 0 and 1, right?
Now what we actually want to do is just in you know, do that
multiplication.
So we want our to be equal to R times n.
So that now we're pre multiplying by that Alpha channel.
Right?
And and we want to round it after that.
So I believe what were we doing?
We already did sort of that in our drawbitmap call.
We already sort of we're doing that rounding here and we were just
doing it directly this way so we can continue to do it that way.
In fact, we can just copy this exact thing.
Right.
That's exactly what we wanted to do.
Like, so, right.
So for our source desk and then that gets us out of that.
The shifts are already baked in there.
There we go.
So we can get rid of that.
You can also get rid of this.
Right, so once we actually do this, all we really need to do now.
Is multiply each of these guys, by that Alpha to get that
premultiplied thing?
Right.
And I can leave that out for a second just so we can see if that are
that are function still works when we run it.
That we haven't broken anything.
And so now if I pre multiply by that Alpha now I've got premultiplied
Alpha coming in.
We haven't changed our blend equation.
So things are going to look wrong, as you can see, everything's got a
little bit of a black outline around it.
With some people may prefer, but that should be in the source art.
If we want it, not something that's, that's coming out the alphabet as
artifact of the creation.
So if we change that, that premultiplied Alpha there.
Now, in our drawbitmap call, we can actually say let's assume that we
have that pre multiply
Alpha.
So, that means we just get rid of these are sa terms, right?
Those are sa terms, go away.
And now, we're back to where we started looking at these guys, right,
you can kind of see exactly what what's happening there.
Everything looks fine, right?
And what's interesting too is you'll notice we've already even though
we haven't even looked at what that term should be.
We've already gotten rid of that black fringing, right?
So premultiplied Alpha is already working for us even though we
haven't even finished.
Out what exactly we should set the destination Alpha to we're already
just accidentally because premultiplied, Alpha is just easier to work
with.
In that way, we've already actually gotten better than what we kind of
had had before, right?
All right.
So what we were saying, what we were saying back here?
Is that well okay, we know that this is sa X da, that's what that is.
But of course, it was .5 and .5 so at some level you know it's it's a
little bit odd to do the calculation because we don't know this could
have been one - it could have been you know the equation that we wrote
here accidentally just from from before could actually be right
because in our essay 1 minus Point 5 would also be point five so this
would end up being
Really sa X ta + SA or whatever.
So, this may actually be the right equation that we had ended up with
here.
We need some way of actually figuring out what that should be.
And so what I'd like to do is just do exactly what we did with the
examples here.
But do it with algebra so that we kind of can see what the we actually
want the result to be.
Now this is going to get really messy and this is why I said I picked
exactly the wrong day to do this because the Blackboard pain is not.
Working properly.
And what can you do?
But
I mean, you got to do what you got to do.
Let's we want to finish what we started.
So you saw me work through these examples to kind of show you how
things are going to work.
All we really need to do, if we want to figure out what these things
should be.
Is just not use numeric values like passed through the actual terms
and then we should be able to solve for what that composited version
is.
We should be able to see what the the math works out to be right.
I'd like to do here and it's going to be ugly.
But what you going to do?
Nothing.
I guess.
So let's set up the motivating situation.
I'm not going to use color and Alpha and that sort of things, I'm just
going to maybe use.
Well, you know what I will use, I'll use C4 color and I'll use a for
Alpha, right?
And so we have several of these things coming in.
So we've got two of them.
Let's say we've got C, 0,
A 0, right?
And then I've got that's going to be like bitmap one.
Right then I've got C 0 c 1 a 1 and that's going to be bitmap too.
Right.
I guess I should say bitmap zero didn't have one, right?
And then I've got sort of the screen.
What was on the screen?
I've got see screen.
A well, we don't have an a screen, so that's just what's on the
screen, the screen buffer.
And then I've got the intermediate buffer, right?
So I've got see, whatever the intimate, we'll just call that b for.
Now, write Alpha buffer and this is that, that buffer intermediate,
So, if we look at what happens for the screen blend, right?
That we know exactly what that value should be.
And that's the motivation we're going to use.
So if I was to draw a bitmap 0, on top of bitmap, I'm sorry, bitmap,
one on top of bitmap zero, right?
Then I know what we want to have on the screen, so the first step of
that, right?
The see screen, the first step of that I'll call that maybe see screen
Prime for now, because we're going to do two steps compute it.
The first thing for see screen, the screen won't have anything in it,
so it's just going to be that blending remember.
The blending equation is 1, minus Alpha times, dest plus Source,
right?
That's the premultiplied equation that we worked out before.
So, that's what we're doing in here, right?
So the color we know is going to be 1, minus Alpha times desk, but
there's nothing in the destination yet, it's empty, right?
So we want myself a times dest plus, whatever the source color
actually is right.
Whatever that that Source color actually is okay.
And so that's going to just be, that's just going to be color 0,
that's going to go straight in there.
Because remember these are pre multiplied.
So these are, these are
These guys are already pre multiplied, right?
As is this guy?
So that's what's supposed to happen there.
The next step to get CS, right?
Is this is what's in the destination, that's this, right?
So we're going to have one minus, whatever bitmap.
Alpha is we're going to have one minus Alpha One.
Gosh, darn it.
Man, the pain is killing me today.
We're going to have one minus, whatever that Alpha is times, what was
in the destination, right?
Which is C 0.
And then we want to add to it, whatever our source was stream has
ended.
No it hasn't I beg to differ.
We're going to add to it, whatever our source was and that source is
C1, right?
Like so
So that's what's in the screen at the end of this process.
When we look at what that is, we can actually kind of see this is is
what we wanted that Alpha to be right, I believe.
Yeah, it's 1.
Minus alpha 1 is what we would expect to see do everything right here.
CS C 0.
Yeah, looks to me like, yeah, coz Alpha 0 is not involved because what
was in this room is not.
I wonder if you have to do one more stage of this, to get it.
That's unfortunate because now that, I think, yeah, well, okay, we'll
see.
So, we want that to equal this, right?
This is the, this is the end goal, right?
If I haven't made a mistake there.
So that's the end goal.
Now, what happens when we build that, that, that free buffer.
So we go through and we do this in two stages, this would actually be
the color that's in the buffer at the end of things, right?
If that makes sense.
So this is CB as well, right?
CB, if we did two steps of alpha, blending would also be this.
So when we then go to draw to the screen, right?
We're going to go through another another pass, so RC screen when
we're using the buffer, right?
RC screen, if we're using the buffer fact I could basically do that
this is going to be in there.
So RC screen we want to be equal to this, right?
This is the Target that we want it to be equal to
at the end but what it's going to actually it's going to go through
the equation 1 - the buffers Alpha whatever is in that what?
Oops, sorry 1 minus the buffers Alpha, right, times whatever was in
the screen to begin with, right?
Which we know in this case,
All right, man.
I'm too sleepy today.
So in order to actually do this correctly, right?
I've got to actually have something in that screen to begin with is
the problem because as I got down there I'm like okay that term goes
out to 0 and then I can't show anything.
So, alright, let's try that one more time, right?
These are pre multiplied.
Okay, and this has got to be multiplied as well.
One more time.
So we have to assume that there's something in the screen to begin
with and so yeah.
Like we're going to have to change the nomenclature.
So we want a result screen, right?
This is the this is the result, let's say or I should say color
result, we're doing that.
So this is the result we actually want
Okay.
Alright, one more time.
So, the result we want.
Is going to be the process of doing those Blends, right?
So it's a French, it's going to basically be if we if we imagined our
lerp here, right?
Our blend equation or whatever.
It's going to be a blend of whatever.
The, the thing that is, that's in the screen right now, right?
We'll do dest, will do.
Well, let's do Source test.
So it's going to be a blend of c0.
Percy one on top of a blend of c0 on the screen, right?
So, whatever is on the screen at the moment, right?
So expanding that out.
And again, our blend, right?
Our blend for source, and desk equals.
That one - The Source, the alpha for the source times, the
The destination color because we're doing color destination, and that
is plus, whatever the color of the source is right.
So that's that blind equation that we're using.
So if we expand that out, we get C.
R equals the blend equation for color one.
And man, it's hard to draw with this pen and then we're going to do
this equation for that back part.
So we get 1, minus the alpha of the source and again this is source
dest.
So that's going to be
Alpha 0.
And that's going to then be times the color of the screen, the color
of the destination plus that Source color so C 0, right?
So that's the blend.
So the result we want out one more step.
We've got the Blends now.
So out one more step.
The blend is going to be again, same equation.
It's going to be 1, minus the source Alpha, and again, this is the
source, right?
So Alpha 1 times that destination color and that's the destination
color there, right?
So, we've got 1, minus a 0,
CS + C 0.
Right.
And then that's going to be plus, whatever that sorts color was,
right.
So that's going to be plus that that color one.
Right.
Do that, right?
See my say, think that's right.
Yeah, put the link, okay?
So that's what we're looking at, right?
And you can see that the result here, right?
If we were to multiply this out a little bit more, let's just, let's
just group the terms, right?
So 1 minus a 1.
We if we do the distribution inside here we would get CS minus a 0 C,
s+ C 0.
Write plus C1 like, so, and so, if we were again to multiply out
again, it's going to get super ugly.
I might even check the stream for catching my math are as because I'm
very bad at multiplying out things like this.
I think I've said that many times on stream.
It's true.
CS minus a 0 C.
S+ C 0, right?
And then we've got - at the - a one version of that, right?
So we've got minus A 1 C S Plus a 0 A 1 C s+ oops sorry minus A 1 C 0
multiplied out plus C1 right?
So now if we group the terms
If we group the terms together, we can kind of, see, I guess what?
You know.
We can see this a little more clearly if we group the terms by their
Alphas, which is what I was kind of hoping do you can see, there's two
bear colors.
Here are sorry three bear colors here, right?
So all of the colors themselves get added in eventually, right?
You've got you've got a CS well, you know what, maybe we should group
them by maybe I should just group them by color.
Now that I think about it, that seems like a smarter way to analyze
this, right?
So if I group them by bye,
Yes, right.
My CS term would be 1 minus Alpha 0, right?
That's the Cs term here.
CS term here.
Minus out a one myself, a one.
Plus.
A 0, a 1, right?
Those are the terms that are on there.
One minus a0 A1, minus a0, minus A1, Plus that right?
Then if I group for my C, 0 term is a 0 term is just is just 1, minus
a 1, right?
And then my see, one term is just see one.
There's nothing happened to because it was the last guy on top, right.
And so I can pull that up a little bit further as well.
I can say CS, if I look at this, this thing here, you've got the sort
of
Well, I guess, I don't know if there's any real reason to pull that
out but you can kind of see if I was to pull out.
The I could I could do sort of an in a 01 pull out or thing here.
I don't know, it doesn't look like there's anything, actually all that
you sort of pull out here but this is what the result should be,
right?
This is what the result, I actually want to get, right?
So, let's take a look at what happens when I actually am.
Going to make you produce this buffer.
So,
I want to get this out.
This kind of super gnarly Ridiculousness that I've got here, right?
I want to get this out and I have this equation to work with, right?
So, what we're going to do at some point at the end of the pipeline is
we're going to apply this equation, right?
Blend source.
Dest and the source and desk is going to be my pre composite buffer,
right?
So this is going to be the source.
I want to blend that Source color.
That buffer color with the screen right with cs.
And somehow using that right?
Which is is going to be equal to that blind equation.
Which is you know one - whatever that that Alpha is for the buffer.
This is the thing that we don't know, right?
One - A B times the color that's on the screen I want to to have that
plus that that input color from the buffer.
I want to have this magically equal this.
Right somehow.
Now, we know that the color from the buffer basically has to
encapsulate these terms.
Right?
Because the color, the zip, the color from the first bitmap and from
the 0th bitmap in the first bitmap, that's not represented anywhere in
the screens thing so that has to be come through entirely here.
Now that's the trivial part because we already knew that that's what
the buffer is color was going to be right.
We or a disk just a blend that all that is that the blend equation for
c 1 + 4 c 1 over C 0.
So we already have that, right?
That's just
This right here we already knew that that was what that was.
We didn't really have to do anything there.
We already knew that's what that was right.
So RC B term is exactly what we thought it was.
It's just one - whatever the incoming Source Alpha is, right?
So the source Alpha times, the depth color plus the source color,
right?
That's exactly what that is.
There's the source color.
There's the source Alpha, there's the desk color, right?
So,
It's exactly right.
So we know CB, we did it correctly.
It's exactly what we want.
The question is, what do we do with this nonsense up here, right?
For our, for our source.
This is what that says, so this suggests that the equation for
producing RAB, right?
Is we're saying this term cscs.
We need this to reproduce that.
We need one - a bee
To somehow reproduce this Ridiculousness right here.
We that to produce 1 minus a 0 minus a 1 plus a 0, a 1 right solving
for that.
What we would get is 1, minus a b equals 1 minus a0, minus A1 Plus a
0, a 1, right?
We want to solve for a b.
So we got - a b equals
Of course, the one is subtracted now so that removes that one, right?
So we just end up, we get rid of those two, we get a 0, minus a 1,
sorry minus a 0, minus a 1 plus a 0, a 1
and we want to negate both sides, so we get a bee right equals a0 plus
A1, minus a0 A1
and yes after an hour of math, ladies and gentlemen we come to the
equation for the premultiplied alpha that will give us the result that
we want which is a 0 plus a 1, minus a 0, a 1 star,
If Casey.
Didn't make a typo, didn't make a, don't know what you call that math.
oh,
which I almost always do.
But that would be assuming that we worked out the math properly,
that's what that was.
And you saw how I did that there, right?
It was a ton of writing but there was nothing complicated.
All I did was just say, if we were to do this procedure that we'd
worked out by hand a couple of times, and we just let the math flow
through it, what comes out the other end, right?
And the answer is that, and if we were to type that in, right,
All that saying is all right, the result for the alpha and we have
that sort of space issue here where we're going to multiply these two
things together.
So we actually need to be able to do.
We actually need to be able to do some slightly more complicated stuff
here.
So,
Excuse me, this C Alpha complicates our life a little bit.
If you know what I mean, because we haven't thought about what happens
if we need to sort of introduce this additional blend in there because
what we really would need to do is since this is premultiplied Alpha,
now that see Alpha is going to have to be accounted for.
But let's let's let's ignore that for one second.
So let's do to do Casey put C Alpha back in
Right.
Okay.
So because we were only using that to modulate our shadows.
But anyway, so let's say we're going to actually try to implement this
now.
So now if we if we imagine ourselves having both of the alphas being
the 10 space, you can actually work with them, as simple, floating
Point values, right?
Then we have this equation, it's a zero.
So that's sa right plus d a
I did this rock fat right already?
A, there we go.
So it's our essay.
Plus our da, plus the two of them times each other or I sorry - the
two of them times each other.
That's the actual Alpha in 0 to 1 space.
And then, so, if we need that to go back up into 55 space, it would
look like that, right?
So again, the thesaurus, the dest, and then subtract the two of them
multiply together, right?
I don't know if that makes some sense and so that is the
Two equation that we would want for our destination Alpha and as you
can see also it produces those nice non darkened edges now and
everything works correctly everywhere, it would appear right?
Although we do have now the issue of C Alpha, which we need to to fix.
All right.
So let's go ahead and and re-enable or Draw test ground stuff.
Just so we can see what's going on there.
So let's go ahead and turn that back on like so, and I guess our grass
Tufts, we're still always in there.
So now we're compositing with premultiplied Alpha properly which means
our edges are all handled correctly and you can kind of see that, you
know, looking nice in there.
Of course, we do still have hard edges here, but that's to be
expected.
That's just clipping, right?
Our bitmap.
That's this is the whole size of our bitmap.
So,
There's nothing we can really do about that when we're actually
reducing these should we're going to let them keep going on the sea,
right?
So that's proper and we can also go back to doing our draw test ground
only that one time, right?
So now we're back to full speed as well and everything is good.
So that was an extremely long Meander.
But we needed to talk about premultiplied Alpha at some point.
And now we have and, you know, the pre
At Alpha is now working properly for us.
And we don't have those dark fringes on our bitmaps, which is what we
want too bad.
The pain didn't work the whole time, but what you going to do,
sometimes the worst things happen at the worst times and that
I guess the motto of Microsoft Windows when might say, okay, so that
means we can go ahead and get rid of our someday.
Talk about premultiplied Alpha because we just did.
And now we are also at least as far as we know, if I didn't make a
math, are doing the alpha correctly there, but we want to put in this
C Alpha.
Now to put in that c Alpha remember all of our Alpha now has to be
premultiplied, right?
And what that means is that this C Alpha is an actual is a new
premultiplication term.
We have to put in there, right?
And so when we compute the alpha here and we do if we multiply that c
Alpha in like we were doing to sort of add an additional modulation so
that we can make things be less trans you can be more transparent than
they would ordinarily be.
What we have to do, is we have to take these colors and also multiply
them, right?
We see Alpha has to multiply everything because everything needs to be
pre multiplied.
So that is, you know, necessary.
If we want our pre multiplication to come to work, and you can kind of
see now, our shadows are back to sort of modulating based on height,
like they were doing before, right?
All right, so that was not the way I would have liked to have done
that.
I would have liked to have had a working pen that whole time.
But there you go and that is literally like I didn't know that
equation ahead of time.
I mean, I think I probably knew it one.
I mean I probably have used it once or twice when I've been writing
some bitmap code, right?
But I literally figured that out on the stream, totally honest.
I did not look it up beforehand.
So that is what it looks like literally when I need to figure out an
equation, right?
And so if you go back and think about the steps that I went through,
It's kind of good to internalize them work through some examples
first, like, see what the process is and make kind of a little Tableau
if you will of here's the process that we go through, right then go,
okay I see what's happening in the process.
And again I shouldn't say it's not like figuring out that
premultiplied Alpha is the thing.
I knew that was a thing, right?
And figuring out, premultiplied Alpha is like hey you're a rocket
scientist or something, right.
The people who figure out premultiplied Alpha and that it was
important.
That took a lot of people, a lot of time and looking at things to do,
right?
So not that but I'm just talking about, you know, there's a thing that
you want.
How do you get, how do you get the math out for it, right?
And so, working through the examples, that's the first thing.
Seeing how they should go.
It gets you warmed up and it kind of gives you something, you know,
that you have to match and then just seeing, can you write the
equations so that things just flow through the equations.
So you
Solve for the value that you want and then you know that is obviously
the most rate for a path in the easiest one to do.
Sometimes, you can't do that and then things, get more complicated but
assuming you can.
That's what you go and then you end up with hopefully the right
answer.
What we really probably should do here.
Is is actually check the math, right?
Go back and plug some things in, and make sure that it works out the
way that we wanted if we didn't have any way of checking it.
Otherwise, that's what we should do.
What we could do is like destination Alpha equation for premultiplied
Alpha and just check ours versus someone else's.
But I don't know if there's really any way to find that out.
If that makes sense, what we really want.
Is like Sean Barrett's article on premultiplied Alpha.
So yeah, maybe I won't do that now because we're kind of, we've
already been quite long.
So, yeah.
So what we need to do like the last step is we need to go like check
this for math errors, because like I said, often times when I work
through math like that, I can't just assume the result that I got was
correct because oftentimes, I will make a mistake.
And so, what you want to do is you want to go through and like, retest
the equation,
Using the examples that you work through before and make sure they get
the right answers that you think you should have gotten and also
obviously, if other people have worked it out beforehand, go check
against there's etc.
Etc.
And you might ask the question well why would you re work out an
equation that someone else already worked out?
And the answer is because if you don't practice working out equations
that other people have already worked out, you're never going to be
able to work out equations that other people haven't worked out.
And so especially on simple cases like that where it's not.
Hard to work them through.
You should work them through and until you start getting the point
where you can do them reasonably well, right.
And if you're lucky, you're better at with math than I am and you
don't make as many careless errors when you're working through the
equations, right?
Because some people are much better at math than I am and they, that,
you know, that's a big help to.
You can also use a computer algebra system to do it, you know, like,
you could plug it into Wolfram Alpha or Mathematica if you have that
or Matlab sometimes those have symbolic solvers in,
Them.
And that can help you check or actually just do the the math all
through.
So, once you've set up the problem properly, you can have it chug
through it for you and produce the result.
So that's pretty good.
All right, let's go ahead and do the Q&A Q&A.
So if anyone has any questions quickly, we've got about, let's let's
we can do some quick questions before ending the Stream.
And let's see if there's any questions out there.
It's too bad.
In him 73 isn't here today.
Because I'm I'm kind of I think he's the resident math expert and so
he could tell me if I had he would have caught any any errors.
According to a link, they posted to fix the Wacom driver without
restarting stop and start Wacom, professional tablet service.
Okay.
Wacom.
Professional tablet service.
Stop the service.
Start the service.
Okay, I have done so and maybe I will plug in the tablet again.
Just to give it a fair shot there.
And let's see.
That did absolutely nothing.
You can try reloading, mischief.
Now that that did not help.
Unfortunately.
I'm assuming that if I reboot the machine, it'll help.
Of course, that'll kill the stream.
Oh, now, there we go.
So it did help it.
Just Mischief had to be rebooted because maybe Mischief, didn't think.
Oh, no.
It worked for a second there and then it seems like Windows like
overrode it.
Oh no, it's working.
I don't know.
Okay yeah, okay.
It is definitely working.
Cool.
Thank you very much for that.
That was very helpful.
Being happy sleepy and Sneezy.
Do you realize you do realize you're just for dwarf?
Sort of a cult crew?
Well actually, I would say I'm grumpy sleepy and Sneezy.
Because honestly that tablet thing like I had to do all this math with
a nonworking tablet was pretty annoying.
I mean, that's a lot of drawing, it was a Blackboard episode today so
like on days when we do a Blackboard episode, I kind of wanted to have
the Blackboard working that seems like a pretty reasonable thing to
ask for but you know
Nowadays.
Nothing works.
Reliably.
Anymore.
Mr.
Fourth dimension.
So if I understand correctly, sorry if my interpretation just confuse
anyone, but the reason off-screen rendering was incorrect before,
premultiplied Alpha.
Was that after blending things in the texture, the colors there were
pre multiplied because they were multiplied when they were put in the
texture.
If, for some reason, you didn't want to optimize your code, you could
also divide the color Channel by the alpha to get it back to unfree
multiplied.
Is this a reasonable understanding of the issue?
So it's more that you can't really make the math, work out properly
without the multiplication being in being pre multiplied, right?
the problem is actually a little bit deeper, it's that
trying to think of what the right way to say it would be
It's the way that Sean Barrett typically says it and really like if
you want the full technical explanation, he's the guy the way he
pretty usually says it is something like, you know, non premultiplied
Alpha.
Wish we had a better term for it, we multiply it Alpha.
Does not distribute.
Over linear interpolation.
I think that's the way he normally says it.
And basically, what he's talking about is that if you want to Stack
linear interpolations on top of each other, right?
So I'm going to do you know that linear that blend equation, right?
So I'm going to do a blend of a blend, right?
or blends of Blends and so on, you know,
right, I guess I probably shouldn't you whose
Those x y z.
He W.
There we go.
So if I'm going to do blends of Blends, right?
You can't actually make the math work out properly because if you
don't pre multiply the alpha, then the blend doesn't distribute,
right?
Meaning you can't actually compose Blends in arbitrary ways like this,
unless the alpha is pre multiplied.
So I believe that's how he usually phrases it.
I've never really worked out.
In fact, that's the first time.
This right here is the first time I ever even solved this equation
Right?
The first time I've ever done it so I've never really thought about it
too much Beyond just knowing that it was the right.
Eek but I don't do that much work with it.
In fact, recently was the first time, I think I ever even really
actually used this knowledge in an actual blending thing.
Not maybe I've done it once before but usually preserving destination
Alpha.
I don't do.
So this is the first time I've ever really done that preserving
destination Alpha.
I think I've done it maybe one time before, but I've never actually
worked it out all the way through like that.
And so, there you go.
But so I haven't really thought too deeply about the meaning of that,
but that is what he was sort of talking about in.
He's been advocating premultiplied Alpha for, you know, decades now.
He's the person, he's the reason I originally even knew about
premultiplied Alpha because actually for a long time game industry
people didn't know about premultiplied Alpha and you get those black
fringes on everything.
There are old games where you actually get black fringes on the
Sprites because they didn't do premultiplied alpha.
And once mipmapping like, you know, mipmapping on graphics cards,
mipmapping is a blend mipmapping.
Well, it's not a blend, but
I shouldn't say that.
Bilinear filtering.
You don't even need mipmapping, right?
Bilateral.
Bilinear filtering of textures like when you have textures and your
sampling like there so that you get a blend of the four colors of the
for texels.
That's two of these, right?
It's a, it's a blend between these two colors, these two colors.
Then you blend the the two results together, you know, conceptually
speaking.
So it's a bunch of Blends and then that gets Blended to the
Buffer.
Right.
So you have this series of Blends that goes on with texture filtering
and then that and you would get these black fringes on your Sprites
and the reason is because you need in order to have this work out
properly, if you're doing that lerp, if you're just using that linear
interpolation over and over again you need it to distribute properly
right now like you you like you kind of hint to that with your
question.
You could always probably make the math work out by like really, like
you said like re dividing every time
So you try to reconstruct what the color was, it seems like that
should work out and probably the reason that you never actually do it
that way in practice is because like you're working with Hardware that
does this sort of stuff and you don't have the opportunity to go in
there and tell the hardware you want to do this redivide.
Not only that, but like you said, the efficiency would be a problem.
So I suspect that yes
What you were saying is correct, you could just work out the math, the
other way and constantly be doing more work to your colors to put them
back into a space where they could blend properly.
So like you said do a divide out, do the thing, put it back in.
but,
Runs into problems because eventually you're going to have to be
working with Hardware.
That has some fixed notion of what those blend equations are.
So even if you didn't care about performance, you're probably in
trouble because you wouldn't kill do it now, maybe you could just turn
off if you really didn't care about performance.
Maybe you could still do it that way and just turn off the texture
filtering Hardware entirely and you just, you know, take samples
yourself and do the Divide out and whatever.
So it become tireli you just program it all.
Do it all in shaders, right?
Maybe that would work, but
Typically you want to take advantage of that fast stuff as much as
possible, so I don't know.
See any other on-topic questions?
Let's see, let's see.
Can you give a small example of what the decompression step between
Sim entity and stored entity will look like probably not because I
don't know what it will look like yet.
We're going to have to we're going to have to actually get there first
and then see what we want it to look like based on based on the
situation.
Drive 137.
Maybe we should set a way for you to see things like that.
Kind of help if someone finds a good possible solution.
No, I don't know how sorry.
I drive 137.
I'm not sure what that was in reference to
Looks like we don't have any other.
Questions here, math didn't screw math, dense streams tend to not have
very many questions I feel like that means probably people don't pay
very much attention to when I do the math workouts maybe I don't know
or maybe everyone's much better at math than I am so they're just like
yeah till they get it so we fine, we're done.
So yeah, that's fine.
Yeah, a lot of equation in today.
We could all that, man.
I wish to said been with the good pain.
Now I know though, thank you for pointing out to me how to fix it so
that's good.
So
So, you know, at least, at least now I know to start and stop the sir
to start Andre stop and restart the service and then that fixes it.
All right, so let's go ahead and wrap up the stream for today.
We've got our premultiplied Alpha in there.
We want to check this math for errors at some point to make sure that
we've got it properly, but now we are doing pretty much everything
that we needed to do.
So we pretty much got
Free compositing working.
Now again, we don't really have much of a use for that.
Pre compositing at the moment because we this was kind of just an
aside that we decided to go down because well because someone got ran
over by a train if you want to be completely honest.
That's that's basically the history of it.
Someone got ran over by a train and so we decided to
Go ahead and take a little diversion into some background compositing,
and I think I'm pretty happy with how it came out.
We learned about premultiplied Alpha and we fixed our pipeline to use
it.
So that's a good step when you actually need to do that.
There's still a little bit more left in there that we got to talk
about, like, gamma and stuff.
But we'll deal with that when we get to the renderer.
But yeah, so our compositing works and honestly it looks pretty good
already even though there's no logic in here, so it's kind of random
it actually, you know, like I've seen Game ground, textures that look
worse.
The mat, to be completely honest with you.
So I think that's that's pretty good that validates my assumption that
basically, when we start to do Logic for how we want the ground to be
laid out, I think it's going to work, just fine and composite
properly, so that's that's pretty good.
So hey, that was a good unknown that we got cleared up.
I'm pretty happy about that.
So, starting next week.
We should go clean up finish cleaning up our closing detector.
I suppose I may be maybe prematurely close to this.
I should probably grab up our to do list here.
So next week, I think will be the week that we finish out Z so what
I'd like to do next week is kind of get our Z worked out again where
we kind of have grounds and stuff properly done and just kind of have
a relatively stable idea of what's going on there.
So that we don't have any more confusion about that.
So next week, I think let's go ahead and finish up the Z.
And then the week after that, I think we should go ahead and tackle
the clintus.
I think we want to do this exactly as we kind of were doing it before
and then multiple SIM regions per frame.
Yeah, I mean, I would basically say that this is the hard stuff right
here.
So I'd say we want to probably go ahead and try to just bear down for
a couple more weeks and finish up all that.
And then I think we're in pretty good shape to just go ahead and
cruise through all of these things here which are much more
straightforward.
These are
A pretty wrote.
They don't involve a lot of experimentation.
They're pretty straightforward.
There's, there's really not a lot to them.
This is mainly just a lot of code typing in, right?
Because they're very, very straight forward thing.
So I think we'll kind of sail through those pretty pretty cleanly.
Yeah, and that should be about that.
Now, looking at how we do this, you know, I'm just kind of seeing how
we're probably want to go through things.
Animation AI, this is definitely.
So I would say we probably have, you know, we probably have
Something.
Yeah, I mean looking at it, this way, this this probably looks roughly
like how will tackle them in order to?
I don't know.
I mean like I said I don't really make schedules too much so we'll
tackle them in whatever order they come up but just looking at the
things that we want to do.
It looks like this probably isn't you know isn't isn't really too far
off.
I think this looks basically what we'll go ahead and what we'll be
doing to get to production.
It looks looks pretty reasonable.
Well and so you know, we'll go ahead and we'll we'll push through some
of this hard stuff.
We'll get our debug code working so that everything from then on we'll
kind of have a nice set to it.
This probably needs we haven't talked about fonts here.
So we're going to need fonts
Because otherwise we're not going to do any debug code.
So yeah.
So I think this looks relatively you know I think this looks
relatively good, I'm pretty happy with it.
So next week we'll probably go and try the new time slot like I was
talking about I'd like to I'd like to maybe try doing some 5 p.m.
eastern Daylight Time stream.
So I think we'll do five p.m.
slot next week and see how that goes.
See how much of a problem it creates for people who are on the west
coast?
I think everyone else is probably pretty.
Okay with it.
But West Coast.
It's a little more problematic because it's close to work time.
But we're going to we're going to go ahead and see how that goes as a
little bit of a test I think.
And we'll make a call from an after that.
Anyway, as always, if you would like to pre-order the game and follow
along with the source code at home because it comes with all the
source code, you can do that at handmade hero dot-org and use the pre
order button to do that.
It again comes to the link, you can use to Everyday, download the
source code that I've been working on so you can play around with it
yourself.
At home and that's a good way to learn from it.
Obviously you have a patreon page if you want to support the video
series, we have a news and Forum site that you can go to for asking
questions or getting ports to other platforms things like that.
There's an episode guide on there.
There's also the tweetbot which sends out the schedule which is Handy.
If you want to know what the schedule is going to be check that tweet
that out and we should be back here at 5:00 p.m.
eastern Daylight time, sorry, pacific daylight time on Monday.
So I
See you all there to try out the new timeslot.
We'll see how it goes or if it's a giant Panic, we will see.
So I hope to see you there have a great weekend and enjoy the pre
multiplication of it all.
Enjoy your premultiplied weekend brought to you courtesy of hanneman
hero.
Thanks, everyone.