Start recording.
Hello everyone and welcome to handmade hero.
The show we coded complete game live on stream.
We are doing a profiling View today and really, I don't know that
there's that much work to do to actually display the profile or
Graphics, because I think that's pretty straightforward and mostly was
implemented yesterday.
The problem that we need to solve today is about querying, what the
data is that we have, because we have two problems that we will need
to address the
First problem is that we don't have any fast way to get out the
profiling information for the just the previous frame or a specific
frame.
We have to do like a search through like a linear linked list and
that's just I mean that's not gonna hold up especially because we
track a ton of profiling data right now.
Right?
So we just have a buffers that you can just stream out to forever and
you keep piling up, more and more frames.
So searching through them will get slower and slower and slower and
the longer the program runs.
The slower.
It will run, right?
And so that's not okay.
Obviously and similarly we have another problem that we would like to
address which is that in order to print out this profile view, we need
to have some concept of the nesting of calls inside each other.
And the reason that we need that is first of all for the drawing to
work correctly because if we have calls, inside other calls, we need
to know that.
The, the calls that are inside.
Another call has to be drawn on top of the previous call.
Otherwise, the previous call, we'll
Completely overlap it and we won't see any.
So when we draw like a rectangle, we need to make sure that that
rectangle is drawn on top if it's a sub call.
If we're trying to do some kind of like a nice stack view their right
and so that's like part of it.
The other part of it is there could be hundreds of thousands of calls
in a frame if we wanted to abuse the system.
If we wanted to have a lot of timed blocks for some reason, or just
who knows why we're doing it?
Just if we did it, we would end up in a
stance where it would be prohibitively expensive to sort of draw all
that all the time.
So it might also be nice to have some sort of a notion of only
drawing, the immediate sort of top level or or one or two levels down
or something like that, right?
So that we could do something like saying, oh, okay, you know, we
right now we only want to draw, you know, the top call level and one
below that or two down or something, right?
As opposed to drawing all the way down, every time which
Might just be too messy, and everything's would be little tiny
slivers.
And who knows?
What else?
Right.
So you know essentially what we want to do today is just put our data.
When we're doing our collation pass figure out some way to put our
data into a structure that would allow us to do a little bit more in
terms of the profile view.
And we could do this in one of any number of ways.
We could try to just pre-baked down the data into like a view.
Like we were sort of doing originally where we just produced these
region Concepts.
Originally we could instead just just expand the size of the things
we're storing to be some kind of weird sort of thready like like tree
structure that we could walk and I don't know which of these is the
right thing to do.
It seems like since we kind of went hog-wild in the debug system and
its not.
So in there already, maybe we just build the tree and like say hey we
built the tree, happy birthday and and that's just how it goes
because, you know, I don't know that there's a lot of reason not to do
it and if we build the tree, then we just during the profile, we just
walk that tree and it has literally everything in it.
You know, who knows?
I don't know, we could do that.
So let's just talk about that really quickly on the Whiteboard so that
there's some understanding of what supposed to go on here.
Here's de 0xff.
So, what we're talking about here is like profile queries.
And so, what we want to do, right, is we want to be able to do
something like have these Lanes, right?
So we have a, first of all, we need to know threads and we need to
know thread ordinals like the first thread, the second thread, the
third thread.
So we know what Lane to put something in, right?
Because we want to be able to say, like, here's our threads, and here
is each lane.
Like, here's the zeroth.
One second.
Like, how many 012 lane or whatever?
So, that's one thing I think we talked about that yesterday.
We got to have some way of getting thread ordinals.
So we need thread ordinals
We know, that's true.
And then we need some way of saying.
Alright, so for a given frame, we want to or we want to be able to
say, like, for a particular scope and a given frame, we need to know
what all the times were that this thing was called.
So we want something that's going to give us like, you know, this sort
of a thing back and we don't care if we can't reverse it in
bi-directionally.
As long as we can get, just the part that happened in like a
particular frame, right?
So we need something that says, like, okay, there is from here to
here.
And then, from here to here is, when this particular thing was called,
so if we have some function Foo, we want to know that like Oak, your
was a call to Foo and here was also a call to Foo, you know.
So that's fine.
Then what we'd want to do is for any one of these Foods, we want to be
able to say give me what the sub calls were, right.
So we want to be able to say what the sub calls were.
So really, it's just a complete hierarchy, right?
That we could store.
And so, my first thought is, let's just store it, right?
Because who cares memory is cheap and this is the debug system.
So we can have arbitrarily large amounts of memory in our debug
machines.
If we want to, we don't have to care about whether the user.
The end user has extra memory for this sort of thing, because they are
never going to run this code.
And so
If we just went ahead and during collation, actually created
essentially that tree structure.
That would be a way to do it.
So let's just pretend that that's what we're going to do.
And then let's see what happens if we do it.
And then we can just walk it directly as we draw.
So, if I came into the debug system,
See here.
I need to actually open up and editor.
By the way, I don't know if you guys saw but there's a new version of
for coder that's been posted.
So tomorrow on stream will be able to use a new version of for coder.
Which I'm pretty excited about because I think it's got a lot of
things in it that I needed.
So I think it's going to be pretty pretty darn good.
I'm also thinking I might be able to switch to it, work as well,
because I think the things there is a couple things that made it.
So I couldn't use it at work and I think those things may be fixed.
So this may be
Good time for maybe a very good thing.
Alright, so here is our build.
And if I go to Ms, Dev and run the build, here we go.
Here is here, is what we had, and what, hopefully you can see is over
time, or did we?
It's okay.
We have sorted out, never mind.
Let's go to forehead here.
I want be debugged dot CPP and I want if 0.
So if I was to let this thing run it would do bad things, right?
So now it's drawing all the time and as this sort of continues to run,
you can see that this is a linked list situation going on here.
And
You probably saw this as a sort of turns you into the stream
essentially as we chew through enough memory because as we're chewing
through that memory, we're building up bigger and bigger lists.
This number is going to go down and you can see that if we go into the
game which uses does a lot more, it ends up being a does.
In fact, this was so there were so many things to draw in that when we
walk through there, that we overflowed the push buffer
For the renderer just drawing them right?
So that can give you just that's like what that break point is there,
right?
So that just gives you an idea of exactly how bad the situation is.
So we really don't want them to case now, granted probably what we
should do as well is take out some of those
Those time blocks because we're timing blocks at this point that are
way too frequently called to make sense.
So technically I mean, you know, let me see here, if I if I do like a
grep, let's see here.
I want to find like all the places that we do time, but I guess it
would just be in the renderer
where are those?
I suppose one thing about it they'll be nice.
McKenna profile working is I will now know what we're even profiling
because I don't really remember what we're profiling at this point.
Is there one in opengl?
Where are they?
I'm not sure where they all are.
I don't have a good way to search at the moment.
It's been on my list of things to do to add a search in all files to
for a coder, which would be pretty simple to do, but I just haven't
had time to actually do it.
So let's take a, let's do it in Dev Studio here, find and replace find
and files.
I just well well I don't know what an okay, can we
How is this even?
I don't even know what this is.
I don't know what any of this is.
And I don't really want to know.
I just want you to go to w: handmade code like so and I want to
Add that here and I really want these to all go away.
I like how this this is removed.
That means move from here to there and this means remove
Okay.
Whatever man.
So let's see if I go to timed and search, what are we actually timing?
So we're timing calls to the main guy.
We're timing loading, which should be fine, that shouldn't be too
much.
So we're timing get best matched ass.
Like, we're calling that thousands of times a frame, possibly, because
every time we use like
Fonts and stuff.
That's probably going to happen.
Oh maybe not, that might not know.
I think about it.
That might be okay.
Play sound is not a heavy path thing.
Neither any of these, I don't think.
Let's see.
so, ignored time function is this
This shouldn't be getting called the right because this were not
running this path.
We're running opengl at the moment.
So in theory we shouldn't see any of these coming through.
Let's see in seemed similarity, a Danity, raw begin soon and Sim
speculative Collide.
So probably calling a lot of that and these overlap or calling, a lot
of that.
I not too many move into these.
Get World chunk.
Change it look at.
Yeah, so we're calling a ton of these things.
I think that's it.
Pre-process dot temp?
Really does not need to be there to say the least.
Let's go ahead and get rid of that.
That was just something I was doing to check out in a macro.
All right.
So I think oh you know what?
So when people ask me to do the clock count, we left stb true type in
here even though we don't really use it, I feel like we should get rid
of that because that's probably messing up our our clock count.
the people sometimes ask me for this,
So it's much lower.
Well, I don't know if it's much lower but it's significantly lower.
I mean, it's like 8,000 lines lower, which is a lot.
So I think we're much better on the line count than it was making it
seem because we forgot that SUV to prison because I showed you guys
how to use it that time.
And then it never got deleted that make sense.
So, so yeah.
So there you go.
Alright.
So we're lower on the clock, which is good.
I don't really like to have a lot of lines of code like, having a lot
of
The code is not great.
So you know I don't really want handmade hero to be like 100,000 line
program.
That's probably not great.
I want it to be a 30,000 line program or something, you know, if we're
lucky so that it's, you know, manageable
all right, so anyway
It was, I can say.
Okay.
So anyway, we don't really know yet how many things were calling or
whatever.
And these are some stats.
These are the kinds of things that I would like to start printing out.
So one example to that we could do is like we could print out some
summaries.
So we could see if these things make any sense and that I think would
be nice as well.
So I'm going to F0 this out so we're not trying to draw anything here
until we get things sorted.
And I'm going to go ahead and say that the frame itself.
I want to just keep
But summary on the frame that tells us some stuff like how many events
were in it or things like that.
So you know like how many stored events occurred in that frame and how
many like blocks there were open and close.
You know, that kind of stuff.
So, inside the debug frame in here, if I had, if I wanted to, I could
say, like, okay, here's the debug frame, this is the total stored
event count or maybe I'll just call it sort event count.
This is the open block count or or I should say the this is the
profile block count and this is the data block out.
And so each time that we collate, I'm going to say that we want to
I'll see her quite a bit because I'm going to say that we want to have
those updated.
So when we set like the frame index, for example.
So in, you know, in here where we do this stuff,
Where do we set the frame index?
There should be an ad frame.
Right.
No.
Not that.
New friend.
There we go.
That was on it before I wasn't paying attention I guess.
So in here I want to do a thing.
Well, it looks like we 0 the structure anyway, so I guess I didn't
really have to initialize it.
It's just going to get initialized to 0 anyway.
So then anytime we store an event, whatever event frame, we store it
on, right?
I'm going to add to it.
So I know that we're in this collation frame here.
So I'm just going to go ahead and say that the collation frame, we add
Two, it's stored.
Event count.
Like so.
And similarly, I think we could also do a thing.
We're inside the collation.
So we're calling the debug records.
When we see something like an open data block and we take a look at
what frame.
It's on.
We could hear just say like Okay, so this open data blocks gonna get
stored in this Frame so we'll just say that that's in the, the data
block count.
And we'll say that when we get a profile block that that's an up in
here.
So, let's go ahead and run this.
Well you know what?
I should print those out first and so when we print out like last
frame time down here, I'm going to just add some stuff to this
concept.
Like, I'm just going to just keep this going here and say like, oh,
okay, when we print out, the rest of this stuff we could say like, oh
okay, fact, I guess I could put it
Could just put it up here.
So that's the frame time.
Like, that's how many events there are.
This is how many like profile blocks there are.
This is how many data blocks.
There are something like that, you know, I'm saying.
So then I can just say like, okay, the debug state,
Most recent frame store, an event count.
And then I'll just duplicate that a couple times and say that I want
to also print out.
The profile block count.
And the data block out.
So that's all of the group's, that's all of the information.
I was curious about there and I just want to see what those numbers
look like, because I don't know if that makes sense.
so that seems like okay so that seems busted to me if that's if it's
actually that low like are there really only 55 events getting stored
if so
Something's amiss.
23 profile blocks for frame.
Also seems extremely low right.
It just seems odd.
Oh duh we're in the cutscene.
That's more like it.
So we've basically, we're basically starting for 1,000 events per
frame and we're storing 9 data, blocks and 2000 profile blocks, right?
And so yeah like you can see why obviously we don't really want to,
you know, we would rather not have those be completely arbitrary and
try to draw them in the profile view.
We certainly could but if we were going to like if we were going to
make an industrial strength profiling system here or I guess it's not
the system, but the view, then what we would have to do is make a
render path specifically for a profiling.
Because like right now we're set up for just doing like little sprite
Blitz, right?
Which is about very little vertex, throughput.
A lot of textures, but a profile views exact opposite.
There's no textures.
It's all about lots.
And lots of vertex, throughput and so we just don't have any way of
doing anything like that, right?
That's just not something that we currently have.
So we could totally solve this problem and it would not be a hard
thing to do.
It's just not something we're probably going to want to do because you
know again it's just a bunch of time to make.
If what we were shipping wasn't primarily a profiling app, we would
definitely do that.
That but we don't really need to do that for our own purposes.
Okay?
so,
Also, by the way, it's nice that this is working relatively.
Well with, you know, like right now, all of that stuff we're storing.
We're processing 4,000 events per frame here and organizing it in all
the others things that we need to do with it without ever using any
more memory, right?
We're now just at recycle, you know, we're just recycling old memory,
and it'll just go on forever.
And it's just always keeping as much debug backlog as it can in 256
Meg's
Which is kind of cool like, that's kind of neat, right?
And we don't have to worry about like, oh, how long can we run before
we run out of memory?
It's just like, now it's never going to use more than that sign.
So let's go ahead back here to where we were at, on the
The event organizing and let's see if we can figure out some way of
processing this data.
Right now.
There's two things we can do.
One is the there's the tree and I think we want to do the tree and the
other thing we can do is to try to attack situations where there's a
lot of stored where there's a lot of calls to a function, right?
And so because what I'm concerned about is when there's a lot of calls
to a function, I don't know what we're going to
To do to really display that because like I said, we don't have
rendering capability for that now maybe we should add it, I don't
know.
But, you know, let's pretend that we won't.
Let's pretend we can't add it, we don't have time to add it or we just
there's billions of them so we couldn't possibly render it.
We need some way of coalescing.
Those into something that we can sort of show.
Hey, this thing gets called too often so we're not going to show it in
that way, right?
So we need to detect that case happening when we're making art.
Tree.
Maybe we need to detect.
This element has just has too many calls.
We can't do anything about it, I don't know.
So that's something to think about.
All right, so let's take a look.
Now, what we can do here.
So I'm going to pop back to the stored event, right?
And let's see how mad you were gonna face.
So, in handmade debug interface, we have the internet sort of meant
debug event.
Debug event is essentially
You know, the clock value, which is when it happened, which we need
for the profiler and then a grid pointer, which lets us know what's
going on.
Now, the kwid pointer, we don't need right, we only need the clock
value, the thread ID, the core index, probably, right?
So we could, we could easily and we don't need any of this, right?
None of this stuff is relevant for the profiler.
So what we could probably do is change up how the stored element thing
is working a little bit.
So in here, where we have
Those stored elements, I'm sorry, story events, write debug stored
event.
Could be quite a bit different than it is in terms of unions, right?
So we could have a way that we store the event as one of the things
that we store.
But maybe a different thing that we store is like the the pointer
struts.
Right.
Another thing we could even say is like, well okay inside here we're
actually storing.
You know, for floats, right?
For floats is enough for two pointers, right?
But I still think we want to go a little further and just say,
That is not restore.
So in here we could say, debug like,
What we would call this debug profile node something like this.
And in here we would just say like okay you know a debug profile node
just has the the clock value.
Of whatever it was here.
Trying to think we want to basically make this that we don't add very
much or if any storage to the debug event, we could have the, the
profile node
I don't know if we need to store the grid, we would have the thread
ordinal instead of the thread ID, right?
So here we would have like a
Fred ordinal.
I'm not sure what we would stick that in probably, you know, we can
probably do thread, ordinal core index, kind of a thing like this and
then we still have some more things here.
I'm not sure what we would necessarily want and we could even have it
so that maybe like we can aggregate calls.
So maybe we've got like, you know, aggregate count.
By the way, I started like a half hour late today so we're totally.
We got a ways to go.
So here I can store some things like this is maybe what I want to
store as part of this and I don't know if I want the glitter not but
either way, let's ignore that for now.
Maybe I store a pointer back to the element, I'm not sure.
But anyway, in the debug profile node then what we would have is just
like underneath that we would have liked the first child.
So the first thing that was called so child seems reasonable enough.
Can't think of a better word.
Inside a profile.
No, we'd like here's the first child.
And then we would have the, the next sibling.
So we could just link these guys up and when we're in here, we've got
the clock values.
What we would want to do is say, well, we've got the begin clock in
the end clock, right?
So we can just record at the beginning, clock in the end clock as
As the Span.
In fact, we could even do one better.
And in fact, we could say something more like duration so that we
don't have to take as much time, right?
We could even probably do since we know we wouldn't have four billion
cycles.
We could even probably do one better.
And say, frame relative clock.
So we take the frame relative clock, the duration, how many of them
there were the ordinal and the core index in case we care and then the
siblings and that should be.
So mean, that's 16 bytes.
And and well it's basically like a pair of pair of d words.
Another parody words parody with parody words, right?
So it's a cash, it's a cache line long.
Is that right?
So it's a it's, it's for things of, for know, it's going to be less
than
Never mind, it's only 16 bytes.
So, yeah, so that seems reasonable to me right, 8 B, 8 B, no sorry, 32
bytes half a cache line, so that seems reasonable to me and when you
stick it in here, then you would be still like under a cache line long
and that's all fine.
So I think that probably what I'd say is.
Let's just say that when we're in our storage, we can
Can also have one of these.
If we want to.
And so now when we store events, we can choose to store profile nodes
in addition to other information other event information.
So sometimes we're just during the event information directly, which
is what we store if we want to store data values and then we have the
profile information.
If we want to start profile values and then we just need to actually
build these profile nodes as we go.
And then once we actually do drawing of them, presumably, we can do a
thing where we do this sensibly.
So that we can walk those in a convenient way.
And what we could do is try to think of like how we might want to do
this aggregate, but what I'm thinking about is like, okay, so this is
called attribution for the other calls that are in there.
We could even be a little bit more feisty and say that, in addition,
we also have the next of the same call, right?
So we could have like, you know, sort of threading, two ways if we
wanted to.
So next for the same call.
And next for the same parent, we could, if we wanted to build those up
and those would be pretty easy things for us to to thread through,
right?
So yeah, I don't know if that's exactly what we want yet, but like,
that's just an example of one thing we could do.
And so let's say that we did that, let's take a look at what the
render routine would be like if that was the day that we built,
because that's something that we have now that we could actually use
right and like that, that would use this structure, we could see if it
makes any sense.
So if I go to the profile drawing code which is in
Let's take a look at what it would look like if I wanted to draw a
profile view here.
And so, if I want to draw a profile view, what I would do is say,
okay, give me the profile node.
So in here, we'd say, you know, what am I going to draw the profile
of?
Well, let's say that I passed that in.
So I'd say here's a profile mode.
And this is the root node.
So it's this is the node that I'm going to start from when I'm
drawing.
So if that was the case, inside this profile node,
I'm assuming these should be perform basically well.
So let me think about that for a second.
It seems to me that they should be per frame.
So that I basically look into a particular frame and say, tell me what
the profile node was for these.
Tell me what the profile nodes were for this Frame.
I think that's what I would want, right?
So I think we could just say, okay you pass in the debug frame and you
pass in that you're trying to look at and you pass in the route the
the call node that you want and we go from there.
I think least that seems relevant to me.
Yeah.
so,
I guess the other thing too is do, we might not even need the frame
for all.
I really know.
We'll see if we could even start to get away without the frame.
In fact, we might not need the frame at all.
So let's think about this.
Suppose we decided started saying that the profile nodes were just
kind of their own thing so in the profile node in addition to the
duration and instead of saying the frame relative clock, maybe what we
do is we say if the parents relative clock, right?
So, it's inside the parent here.
Is how many clocks in we were?
And so then you would just say we wouldn't even talk about a frame.
We're just saying you've got a profile note, I want to view the
profile mode.
The profile node is something that tells me this information here.
So instead of the frame span being based on some kind of a begin end
clock situation instead.
I would just say well what is the duration of this thing?
That's my
An right.
Then we come through and we draw these things, instead of debug
variable link, I'm going to iterate over the profile nodes.
So I'm going to say all right I've got profile nodes.
So we come through here, and I say, whatever this thing is that, I'm
looking at this debug profile node, right?
And this is kind of nice too, because if the profile nodes are
entirely on a frame, then when we free them, we can freed the whole
set of profile nodes with the frame.
Pretty easily, right?
And that seems pretty good to me too.
So we'll take a look at what happens with that in a minute.
But anyway, so we'd come through here and we'd say, all right for this
root node, I think is what we called it right for the root node.
We just want to start by asking about the the children.
So, we would go to the first child.
We would run through all of the children that there are
And since we're doing one by parent, here we would just step to the
parent each time.
Then in here, we don't really need this stuff.
I don't think oh, well I guess yeah this is the last thing we would
have to have we don't really have any way of getting back to
information about what this was so we would finally I think need a
debug element pointer right?
So yeah it's a little bit bigger than I would like
But not the end of the world, still not quite a cache line.
Write cache line is like eight pointers and we're still too shy of
that.
So not too bad and when paired with this when paired with this guy it
would basically be a cache line.
Yeah and the debug profile node I guess it's got its inside a store at
event.
This Frame index.
I guess we would possibly still want it's a little weird because the
profile node probably should be the thing that stores, the frame and X
in there.
And this debug event should probably actually have been smuggled in.
So at some level I that this it's probably the fact that this, debug
stored event should itself just have been a union but we won't worry
about that quite yet.
Anyway.
So in here we come through we say we've got the debug element, we can
get that from asking what the nodes element is.
We can then go through and do the drawing.
We know that we're actually going to draw every element so that's not
really a big deal.
And for now I'll just draw the top level elements, but then in the
future, we can draw Sub elements like of that top level element of
each element.
We could make it recursively.
Or we could do, who knows what could do, all sorts of things?
Anyway, so
Here we've got open event and this oldest event thing.
We don't care about that anymore, right?
We don't care about any of this stuff.
We don't care about the framing nice as we know.
We're always in the same frame that we're asking about.
And we don't care about Annie any of this at all.
None of this matters.
So we're just down to drawing the rectangle.
That's all we need to do now.
Okay, and what we want to say here is that the stuff that we were
doing like with the grids and all that, we have the debug element now.
So we can use that as any time we were actually looking for the grid
that doesn't even matter.
But point being so in here, we've got open Event, clock closed event
clock.
These are no longer what we actually need to worry about.
Now we just need to know what the like, what the duration is and and
start with the Minix and go, however, far, we need to go based on the
duration, right?
So, all we need to do is say whatever this node is, its duration is
how far we would go from, its starting point and to find the starting
point, we just need to know what its parent relative clock is because
whatever its parent relative clock is, is where it would be in the
graph.
We don't longer need to
act out the begin clock because that's already happened.
So those are our begin and end our you know, right?
Pretty straightforward.
And I think that's all we would really need.
So now if I were to compile this, I think we could get it compiling,
even though we're not building any of this.
Let's see here.
This profile.
Nude probably needs it.
Yeah.
So here in this course, if I type this correctly here, in this code,
we don't actually have any of these.
We haven't built any of them, but it's just a way what I'm basically
doing right now is saying, I want to know
The code that this is like me writing the use of code first, like, I
always say to do.
I want to know that the thing that I'm sort of envisioning here is
actually going to work to do the thing that I want.
And so while I sort of had an idea of how it probably should be
stored, I didn't want to commit to Computing.
Something that I don't even know if it's going to work with the code,
the way that we want.
And so I just wanted to verify that was the case and so that like
convinces me, that that's relatively clean.
And furthermore, now I know approach file node, I can go ahead and say
This is like the particular node that we're looking for, I have an
element pointer and I can say like we're looking for this particular
element or whatever, right?
Okay.
See here.
Still a little stuffy.
I take allergy medication now.
And it sort of works.
I think it's better than without it but it's not still not perfect
during allergy season, it's a bit rough.
So if we were to do that,
Then when I do draw a profile in here, what I could say is, all right,
when we're going to draw the thread interval graph for now, let's just
say that whatever the most recent frame is so the debug State most
recent frame, whatever that is.
And I guess I should probably verify here that I actually have one.
Because if there's no frames yet, that wouldn't work.
So assuming we've got a frame, then like the most recent frame I want
to know what it's route profile node is.
So that would be a thing that we would have on
on each frame.
So let's see.
Here's a debug frame.
So in here I would have a thing that was like Hey we're what's the
debug profile node?
That's like the whole time of this Frame.
Okay, so in the thread interval graph it will just do that call and
that's all I would need it to do now we're compiling but of course
we're not actually generating any of those things so that wouldn't
really help us at all.
And I suppose I can also guarantee that we have a route profile mode.
So here, if we ran, I don't even think we would crash.
We just won't see anything, right?
So our profile is garbage, right?
There's no nothing in it.
So yeah, so ignoring that part of it, what we now need to do is is
figure out how we're going to sort of build those those things up.
And the first thing I want to just look at is when we store an event,
oops, store event, when we store an event, I want to see if there's
something we can do to make sure that things get freed properly, right
and you can see how we're doing that here.
We call free.
Oldest frame.
And so if I go to free oldest frame and I look at what's happening in
there, you can see that what happens is we doing?
Well, we call free frame.
We Loop through all of the elements and we look to see if they have
events that are on that frame and we get rid of them.
I believe that we'll just work with our profile nodes.
Like, I think, at least I think it should.
There is one caveat that I think we would have to worry about, and
we'll see when we get there, and it has to do with when we actually do
element attribution for these profile nodes.
So,
Yeah, we'll take a look at that a little bit later.
Okay, so assuming that, that that would just work all we really need
to do now is actually build these as we go.
And so when we're coming through with our collate, debug oops, that's
not going to help.
As we're coming through, with our collate, debug records, we already
know.
We already know exactly what where we need to do this in begin block
and end.
Block is specifically where the information is is known and where we
want to record this.
And what we don't want to do at this point is actually like in fact we
may not even want to do this, get element from event.
We don't necessarily even want to store these in the profile group for
now.
I guess we can but we could even consider doing something where we
don't even use
Thursday by governments for it, but I'm not sure.
So, we'll leave those for now.
The point being what we want to do here is say, okay, any time there's
one of these, these open debug blocks.
What we want to do is we want to instead of calling store event, we
want to call sort of a, we want to make a call that's going to add one
of these profile nodes into the right place, right?
That's what we're actually looking to do here and so
I have to think for a second.
Let me take a look here.
so,
are you all right, so if we have this
If we have this, this concept of the debug profile nodes, it occurs to
me that these next pointers actually would still work.
So really stored event can still do almost exactly what it was going
to do.
And so probably what we would say is next for same call is the same
information that next to a storing.
So we don't actually need to store that instead.
What we could say is instead of doing profile nodes here, let's just
do debug stored event for all of these.
So that we can always just
Reverse the stored event itself.
That reduces the size as well as essentially making all of this work
properly with the next pointers, which is kind of great.
Because that means, it will automatically clean itself up as we move
through that part.
So we know that first child and next same parent will automatically be
irrelevant because the whole frame, it's flushed at the same time.
So all those events will go away at the same time and then we also
know that the debug stored event
URS the next chain, which allows us to walk to
People who are the same call site trivially as well so that's kind of
nice.
I really like this kind of thing.
In case you couldn't tell anyway.
Hmm.
That's kind of how you know, if you're an engine program and if you
like really weird, tricky stuff like this.
Pretty much pretty much what that means.
If you're sitting around.
Like, if you're sitting around going, I really want to get to
programming the actual game, you're probably are more of a game
designer programmer, right?
If you're sitting around going, like I much rather be figuring out how
to do like the inline profiling and have that running at the same time
and have it work across threads and bottle of, then you're probably an
engine programmer, right?
That's just that's just how that goes, neither good nor bad, it's just
a litmus test.
I guess.
So anyway inside here, if I am going to start building these up, then
what I need to know is when I do begin block, I need some way of
adding these to whatever the open block is.
And if there's no open block, then I'm going to need to essentially
have that sort of Route group be the thing that we add to.
And so, I don't actually know what we're doing right now for that.
I think it means that
This first open code block thing here.
I'm assuming, when we do allocate open, debug block,
I'm assuming when we do this here, it's entirely possible.
That the open d block is not valid.
I have no idea why this is passed as an address like that.
Because it gets replaced with this one.
It's just a shorthand.
So yeah.
So this might be zero right there might not be an open block and so
when we're actually doing that operation
When were actually doing that operation, if that thing was going to be
0, then we would know that we would have to create essentially the
root one of these.
But either way we're going to create one right?
Either way we're going to do a store event.
You know I'm saying?
And so what we could do and this is kind of being mr.
Cheesy mr.
Cheese?
Pants cheese, man, but you know, I mean, sometimes, mr.
Cheese mayonnaise, cheese, cheese, pants, E cheese, man is want is the
person who
Need to create the cheese plate that for the wine tasting of game
development.
It's a very good metaphor.
Don't just just let it be, let it be what it is.
Don't try to force it to conform to your, you know, stereotype.
What a metaphor has to be.
So when we do the store event, what we could do is just leave, our
current store event code and just be cheese, man.
And say yeah it stores the event happy birthday, I don't care.
It's going to return one of these and I'm immediately going to
overwrite it instead of the event code that's in there with the actual
profile no code.
Because that's just the kind of person that I am.
So here is the bookstore at event.
And here's the the the node this is actually now the profile node that
I'm getting back.
And now I'm just going to straight up like romp right over that and
say like hey thanks for filling that part out that I cared about.
I'm about to now go rewrite all of it.
So the element I know that's the element.
The first child I know is going to be 0, right?
The next with same parent is also going to be 0, and because I'm the
first one, I'm sorry.
I'm the last one in that.
Killer case.
And I think we're probably going to need a first and last child would
be my assumption.
Oh no, we don't because we don't add after this.
This is going to be, this is going to be good.
This is going to be good.
You ready for this anyway?
So our parent relative clock, we have to compute our duration, we
don't know yet, right?
Our duration will get computed later.
That's going to be an end, block.
Our aggregate count is not something we're actually going to talk
about today, probably our thread ordinal.
We need to compute somehow, and I don't know if we're actually have
this.
Now, do we have this in the debug block?
I suspect that we do.
Open debug block, parent free opening events.
Elements, starting from index.
How do we not have
Oh, we've got the thread.
There's it is right there.
There's Arlene index, that's what we wanted.
Bam,
See, I'm talking about man, it's right there, right there.
Beautiful core index, we still don't know, we'll save it as if we got
it because on other on some other hardware and print these not this
one you would be able to call the arditi SCP and get the core index.
Maybe I still not clear on whether it gives you back that or not, but
that's beside the point.
Anyway Palin railroad apparent relative.
Clock is just going to be whatever our clock was.
- whatever that.
So, the in the, debug, the open debug block, the opening event, is all
we need to know, right?
Because whatever the opening event was in our parent block, that's
going to be what our relative clock actually is.
And so, there's two, there's two cases where this could be happening
when we call this begin block, if well, I guess there's no, there's
not two cases.
We always need to have an open debug block, that's the root block for,
you know, the the the frame, not an open debugging, shouldn't say that
we always need to have a notion of that parent node.
And so, whatever it is, we're going to have one of those but we just
need to eat.
Either get it out of the open debug block, or it's the one for the
frame, one of the other, right?
So when we go, look at the parent relative clock,
What we're going to be doing, is taking whatever that parent was.
So whatever, our parent profile node is, which will compute in a
second, whatever, its clock was.
We that's the one that we need.
And I guess, like I said, we kind of need.
We need an open, debug block for it.
We need there to always be one of those.
So I think what we need to do is just make sure that they're always
isn't open debug block.
Or.
We always need to know what the frames clock is so.
So I guess we just need a clock basis.
We need to basically say, here's our clock, and we need our clock
bases.
And I guess the way that we do that is we say, well, did we have one
of the open code blocks or not?
Right?
Because that's going to determine who our parent was.
If that makes sense.
You're organized this way.
So mmm.
What we need to know, here is whatever that clock basis is.
So we have a clock basis value and that clock basis.
We know what framework in, right?
We have a collation frame, so our debug State collation frame.
Whatever that begin clock was, that's our clock basis.
If we don't have it open group because that's the beginning, right?
But if we do have an open group, so if thread first, open code block,
Is valid, then whatever that first open code block is stores the event
that started the block, which is our apparent, right?
So the first open code Block, it's got a shoot me.
First open call block, has an opening event.
That opening events.
Clock is exactly the thing that we want for our clock basis because we
want to base it off of that.
So that gives us essentially this computation exactly what we wanted,
right?
So then in here, you know, do we have a child?
Not at the outset we would add one later if we actually.
We're going to have one, we need to store something else in the open,
debug block for sure.
And that is, of course, if there was going to be debug start event the
the
First child, last child that we're sort of building up here.
I guess they're always going to be the case because for opened email
box, you always have them.
So we don't need to store anything here for this one and four.
Next with same parent, we will need to store something.
Once we actually added in, right?
We're going to need, it's going to happen when we when we come through
here.
So I think this is all fine.
The only thing that we don't have here is the duration so we'll set
the duration 20 for now.
And then what we do is in sight and block when we come through and
we're going to end the block, then we can say ok now is the time when
we will
When will close it up, right?
So in here, we'd say, with the matching block assuming that the events
match, then we now know that we had this, we don't need to store
another event for the end.
That's not necessary.
We only need to store an event for the, the initial one, right?
So, then what we can do is say, well, okay, we've got the node.
You know what, I just realized this is actually stored event, and this
is debug profile node node equals stored event.
What time?
You got five minutes.
Not quite there yet.
That's too bad, but I'm pretty confident that this is all what we
want.
Anyway, so that's good.
All right, so, all that stuff is good, I think we're all happy about
this, but then when we get down here, what we do is, we need to again
figure out where that note is, right?
The one that we opened before, and then in the node duration, what we
need to do is take whatever.
This event is and this event this tells us the duration, right?
Because whatever event we're on, that's the ending clock whatever
event.
We started on that was the starting clock, right?
That tells us how long it is, which could have been longer than a
frame by the way.
This end block might happen in another frame, but that's okay, because
as we're just classifying things by what frame they started in, and
that's fine, you know, that's a totally reasonable thing for us to do.
There's no reason we can't do it, so, you know, off we go.
So I think that's all good.
We've got the matching blocks, we've got the opening event, got the
events match.
That's all good.
So I think all of that looks reasonable to me.
So all we need to do now is have the debug profile node.
Come back to us here.
The one that we're going to edit.
I think that's pretty easy.
We just store that in here.
We'd say sort event in the open debug block, we'd say what it's a node
was, right?
and so, we
Just say, okay in the matching block that profile mode.
We just want to again access the profile node of it, just call this a
node.
So then here, when we actually do this, we call the allocate debug
lock function, when we get it back, we want to store into that, debug
block the profile know that we had, right?
So we want to do this.
Okay.
So I think that's all good, pretty sure.
Anyway.
Debug stored event is not there yet.
So this has to be a struct go.
And let's see.
What is this talking about?
Debug profile node root?
Ah yes.
So these are actually stored event, right?
and then in here we can just say, oh yeah, when we are in the you
know, the spirit event
We just grabbed just that part for basically convenience of typing
groups.
Yeah.
What are you complaining about?
Okay.
So again we know that this is probably going to be less than 4 billion
because that would be a whole second that this thing took.
So we're hoping that that is not
We hope we never have a frame time.
That's that long.
That would be bad and if you know if it overflows it overflows that's
not the end of the world.
That's good.
Keep going here, Thread Lane index, head and Loops, that's not good.
There we go.
And event.
And to the profanity bookstore at event.
Oh right.
So this is actually going store.
Do that.
There we go.
Which is there a new object file?
Generated cannot convert.
Yeah, well, you know what?
Yes, you can because I'm telling you to so convert.
There we go.
So now we're all stored in you 32s.
All right.
So technically, I think we should not
Of any bugs at the moment because we're never adding anything to that
group group, right?
So, we're still kind of like, you know, in a place where we haven't
quite hooked up the route, so nothing's going to versed.
So we may have any, we may have plenty of bugs in there but they're
just we're not going to have any when we run the program because it's
not visiting it.
So hey, let me take, I'm going to take an extra five minutes because
I'm kind of really into this right now and I just want to
See what happens if we do and then we'll leave it for tomorrow to
finish up.
So this could be, this is really a debug stored event.
and,
See, and this is.
Short event.
Okay.
So all I need now is I need to actually make it so that when you
create a frame there actually is somebody there to hold this
particular piece of information, right?
So when I do a new frame, what I want to do is I want to be able to
sort of create and I guess I don't even really need to do it then I
can just do it when we as necessary.
So basically when we do an open
Block call, or where are we?
There it is.
When we do a begin block, when we come through here, if there is no
open, if there if there is no open code block, then we would know that
that was the situation that we had, right?
So assuming there is like
You bugs stored event parent event.
Assuming that we had an open code block already, then we would know
who our parent was right.
Our parent event is just going to be whatever that codeblocks event
was, right?
So the open code blocks profile node is our parent event and we're
done, but if there is no open code block, then our parent event has to
be a separate event that we store, right?
And I don't know what we would pass here for event.
Probably just a null event.
Honestly.
I don't know if we should fill it with a name, a fake name or
something but, you know, probably just another man.
So we would store an event that was bogus and that would be what our
parent event actually.
He was and then we would make sure that that the well and I guess to
be fair, that's actually not even quite yet.
What we would do here is say if we have one in the frame,
right?
So if we have a root event, meaning there is already one of these, we
would just use it.
So we only actually need, it's not rude events called root profile
node.
Right profile node.
We would just use it.
In fact.
Could even do this.
Weird Echo.
Debug State, relation frame.
Profile node equals current event.
So now we know we have a parent event and the only thing left to do is
actually to thread these guys through, right?
So we need first child in the next with next.
Same parent to actually work, if that makes sense.
That's what we have to do here.
And so we need, we need two things for this and I don't know, I guess,
at this point I think we ended up with enough with
do you want to pointers in there that we don't actually care, but
When we have this route profile node, we would also need one other
piece of information here, which would be whatever the last thing was
that was stored under it so that we can chain them together in order,
if that makes sense.
Although I guess
we don't care if they're in order.
We don't care if they're in order.
At all.
Get rid of that.
So I think we're done, I think all we have to do is say that the first
in here, when we're actually threading through, we just say, all
right, the parent event, its first child is us, right?
And if there was and our next, the same parent is whatever was there.
So we can literally just thread them in reverse order because who
cares?
Right.
I think that just works.
I think that's all she wrote.
What are we complaining about?
Can I grieve 3 from diigo event start?
Right?
You are sir.
That's totally true.
None of our debug start event parent, event first child, what are we
talking about?
You know what?
That's true, too.
I agree with you.
I agree.
Oops.
How's that parent event profile node?
First child equals started it?
All right, so let's just see if we crash mightily here.
Or what happens.
All right.
So let's take a look and then I'll call it a call it a day.
I just want to see where we're at.
So we're we're that's this naughty.
We're not in the right file.
We're not even the right file people.
Like what's going on?
We got to be in the right file.
If you're not in the right file, you're not going to find the code.
So, here we go.
So, let's see what happens here.
We've got a root event.
And what's in it.
So inside the root event is a profile node and that profile node has a
child.
So, we actually did fill this out.
Here's the first child, we've got a profile note of it, which is what
it's Clocks Were.
That is apparent relative clock.
I don't know if it's accurate, that is pretty long, but for a top
level function,
It could be plausible.
Maybe we don't actually know which one was it.
Frame display.
Who knows?
Let's take a look here.
Duration.
Ah, our durations not going to have anything in it though because we
didn't update the, the frames information.
So we do have one more thing to do, which is here.
When we do our route profile node.
When we, when we detect that we need the one for the collation frame.
This one here needs to oops.
Needs to actually be filled out for reals, which I didn't do.
So this element,
Needs to be zero.
Actually, I guess I need to do this.
So this element needs to be zero.
This first child needs to be zero, the parent relative clock.
Probably should be zero because I'm not sure what else we would store
there.
The duration has to be what the duration actually is.
So, whatever.
The collation frame was.
It's an clock - it's it's begin.
Clock is what we actually need.
Oops.
So that's all good.
And then we need, we should might as well clear this stuff I guess.
Although, it doesn't matter.
In fact, it would already be cleared because everything in there is
already cleared so we don't need to clear anything because the event
the null event would clear would have cleared it all.
Right.
So actually, all of this doesn't matter.
We only need to set the part that we didn't want to clear because this
is a block of zeros that will clear this out, right?
Cheesy.
I know.
Yeah.
You know what?
And you probably don't want to rely on that because the size is good
change.
Look, we don't want to be we don't want to be lame about it so you
know, I'll do it for you.
I'll do it.
All right.
Are you happy now, fine?
All right, Stuart event, it's actually parent event.
And so now we've set the duration properly and that was probably
preventing us from getting anything useful.
We need to cast you 32, because that's by default going to be you 60
for computation, which obviously is not what we want, and then I think
we're good.
Okay.
Now whether we get anything useful out of this, I don't know.
But, you know off again.
Thank you.
Want to see the results first.
That is bizarre, never would have guessed that.
Have no idea what that is none at all.
But yeah.
Anyway, we're pretty close.
I'm going to call it there because I'm already over time, I'll take
the briefest, briefest of qas.
But really we should probably hold them tomorrow because we'll finish
this up tomorrow.
I think we've pretty much done.
Almost everything that I want to do there.
It's like in sohbat.
Is is getting it done.
Cream cheese is will the day counter overload tomorrow or will the
variable provide more bits for us?
Well since you're grumpy giant 256.
I think if you were expecting an overflow at the byte boundary
You would have been grumpy, giant zero.
Jesse used.
How are you going to celebrate handmade hip handmade here episode?
0xff programming is its own celebration.
Like, when I am able to actually program and make code without like,
Microsoft crapping up my stuff or, you know, having to install some
stupid update with something, you know, when I can just actually
program
I'm happy.
So just being able to program like we got to program all code today.
It was all our code and it was cool and I'm pretty happy about that.
So like, you know, I think that's as good as celebration as any
Soon enough, we will need 10 bits to store the day counter.
So we'll need
how many bits will the day counter need.
So,
We know we're going to need.
At least 10 bits.
Yeah, because an 8-bit day counter only gets us to 255.
So Burl be passed that tomorrow, right?
9 b day counter, gets us to 512 but I was saying that that we do at
least six hundred episodes, right?
So if we do six hundred episodes, we will need 10 bits because even if
somehow we finished everything before day of 5,
twelve, I would, you know,
I mean, I guess I would, I would just do extra strictly just go clean
up code me.
There's always plenty of code to clean up, right?
So since I already said, we're going past a 512, we will need 10 B.
We know, we will need 10 bits for sure.
I don't know that we'll need 11 B.
11 B, probably not.
I don't think I've got 2048 or well, or 1024 days.
So
How long will it take me to get your flow of coding, 40 years?
Well, definitely not 40 years because I haven't been programming for
40 years.
I haven't even been alive for 40 years.
For Tarson elk.
What kind of data is profile intend to display?
So I think based on the data structure just created will have a nice
will be able to do a nice thread overlap view, which is what we'll
have in a moment when we finish.
So tomorrow, we'll have that with drill down.
The drill down.
We'll take one more day to implement because there's another thing we
have to do, right?
And but the profile view will have a nice thread overlap with drill
down in Lanes.
So we can get all that info.
And we'll also I think be able to draw a nice we can sort functions by
how much they cost.
We should be able to do that as well.
So we can do a sorted list view so we should be able to have like the
best of both worlds.
Joe, the toe like I was yeah, it was like 12,000 or no 14,000.
All right.
Your help.
Will you be able to turn on and off profiling for certain functions
with the debug?
You, I well you could turn on and off recording the profile.
But the whether or not there's a profile point at a particular
function, what we're not going to write something that lets you type
in the name of a function and then turn like goes and like, obviously
we're not gonna do any of that.
So you have to have put them in ahead of you have to put in which
functions you want to profile ahead of time, right?
A big part of the slow startup for me is that the motor arena is clear
to default at the moment.
That's about two.
Nurses Meg's the motor remote Arena.
Oh, I know what you're talking about.
Handmade 3p.
Yeah.
So, you talking about which party you talking about?
Well anyway, you know what either way, so there's the startup right.
And so let's just do a simple test.
We don't really need any instrumentation or anything for this.
What we can do is just in win32, handmade.
We can just say, if we were not, if we were to not initialize opengl,
right?
so, in here, when we do win32 in it opengl
That's this code.
If we were to just not initialize opengl, right?
So that if that just wasn't going to happen,
And we were instead to tet to set the render mode.
Software.
Can see what the time.
What?
Well
So that is very slow fade.
I'm not really sure.
I guess it's still calling the game code there.
Not really sure when 32 in it with the gel.
So now in theory, if we don't call this, we should only be rendering
with, with no open gel, although I guess we're linking with it, still,
So, there is that.
I guess.
I don't itch that shouldn't matter.
I don't actually know if it does.
So let me take a quick look here.
all right, so in here, if we were to get rid of this,
Now, when we run, we should have no opengl at all.
So I think that does seem like there's still a bit of time that can be
saved there, right?
Just arbitrarily sort of judging how long it takes to start up.
I would say.
Find out hand.
May 22.
so, if I switch back to open gel,
now that it's, I mean,
I-it's that feels significantly longer to me when we initialize
opengl.
So I mean we probably should get rid of the other, you know, the clear
time we could get rid of all that time and maybe that's something we
should do sooner rather than later.
It's not particularly hard so we could do that.
But the opengl still still a problem.
As far as I can tell.
Anyway,
all right, I'm going to go.
I'm going to wind down.
I'm going to wrap it up.
Let's go ahead and close.
All right, thank you everyone for joining, for an episode of handmade
here.
It's been a pleasure coding with you.
As always, if you would like to follow along at home, you can always
pure to the game on handmade here at org and it comes with the source
code.
So you can play around at home.
We also form site.
If you want to ask questions, go there.
We have a patreon page, you can use to support the video series, and
we also have a tweet bot that tweets the schedule.
If you want to catch the stream live so you can subscribe to that and
find out when we're going to be on the air.
And speaking of that, will be back for the I think the tomorrow's
Friday, right?
So back for the last few of the week tomorrow, 5:00 p.m.
Pacific Daylight time.
Hope to see you here for that until then, well, there's the tweetbot
right there.
Until then have fun programming and I will see you guys on the
internet.
Take it.
Easy, everyone.
Oh, and by the way,
Tomorrow new for coder.
So I'm going to go download new for coder right now.
In fact, if you don't have four coder yet you should get it's what we
use on stream.
And there's a new version that just
Came out a new Alpha.
So if you want to go over here, if you if you pledge to this patreon,
you can download the editor that we use on the stream.
It's by someone who's actually on the stream.
Mr.
Fourth dimension on the stream.
So check that out tonight because that's gonna be exciting.
I'm pretty excited to go.
Look at it.
In fact that's what I'll be doing this evening.
So see you guys tomorrow and we'll chat about for coder on Twitter
before.
Then take it easy, everyone.