Hello, everyone, and welcome to handmade hero.
The show, we could a complete game live on stream.
I yesterday stream, I did the math for our projection Matrix is
handling of the near and far clipping planes, but I forgot about the /
Z when I did it.
And then we had to really quickly redo it.
When somebody asks a question actually, charlock asked a question and
it was like, so it's nonlinear, then I was like, no, no, it's just
Lydia and I was like no it's actually it's not like oh wait I forgot
about the divided by Z.
That's bad.
And then we resolve it really quickly but we didn't have a chance to
get it working.
So I gotta go in there and I got to actually finish.
Making it work with the correct way of understanding the correct
expectation of what open jails going to do with that Matrix.
Once it gets its hands on it whereas right now.
Yeah, well I guess or before we did this we had
sort of forgotten.
The fact that open Joe was going to want to divide
All right, I guess now that I look at it, this is probably Kim
Jorgensen, right in the chat with saying, hey, the new clip place up
to a negative number.
Is that a bug?
It is, I don't know when that happened.
It may be that.
That's our only bug, I don't know.
Actually, that certainly could be.
The fact we may have other bugs, we kind of have to take a look at the
at the routines.
Here to see what's going on.
So let's go ahead and and do that.
Yeah, let's go ahead and just see what happens with that.
It may be that we're working.
Okay, but we got to test our.
We also have to test this routine.
I feel like I would feel more comfortable.
In fact, you know what, I can do that right now.
I'd like to be able to push some points through it and just see how
they come out.
So for example, you know, just make a test result here where I can
multiply a vector times The Matrix and see what the result is that
comes out.
So for example, Maybe,
I can put in the near clipping plane and then I can put in the far
clipping plane and verify.
That those two things come out to be what we want them to be, which is
to say they should come out with the w component and the W component
and the and the Z components being equal to, you know, the Z
component.
Equal to negative W component and positive the W component
respectively and
I guess the only question is we can't see in that multiplication.
What happens to the W coordinate in any real way?
Because we don't have we don't actually return the W coordinate.
So it's a little hard to say.
but, you know,
We can assume that the W, coordinate is pretty clear what it would
because it's only a negative one there that's going to be affecting
it.
So we can assume that it's just the input Z.
It's just, you know, it's just - and I'm sorry it's just N - n and - F
right because it's the only thing that comes in.
So we kind of want to see if when we put these things in.
We get those those values.
Let's find out.
And thinking it through, too.
Yeah, well I won't say anything further.
Let's just take a look.
so in our math routines, where our math routines,
I guess they're not loaded for some reason.
That's all right.
We'll just set a breakpoint.
There manually
By the function name.
So going in here.
Here's us creating the Matrix and let's take a look at we get when we
do these tests multiplications.
So here's test 0, here's test one and let's see what's coming out of
those.
So in this case, it test 0 is coming out to be negative 1 and test.
One is coming out to be negative 3.
Those are not useful values at all.
So it looks like that does not seem correct to me at all, because
we're passing in a an n and an F there where it feels like those
should be those should be coming out much more sanely, right?
Because first of all, one of them should be positive and one of them
should be - as just a
Start, right?
Because we know that the, the near clipping plane and the far, cut
painter supposed to map to opposite sides right there.
So it's math, the negative 1 and 1.
And so, the fact that these two values are coming out
You know.
Are coming out with the same sign is not good because the sign of the
W coordinate in both cases, is - what that means is.
Then when this when this divides, right, when we get Z and W dividing
each other here, we're going to get correctly.
In this case, we're going to get one, I'm sorry, the incorrectly, in
this case, we're going to get one.
So we've got the right magnitude but the wrong sign, so this Z value
should have been positive.
When we do this one negative 3 over negative 3, that one will give us
the right result, which is 1.
So
Possible that we got a correct equation for r z for the far clipping
plane, but it doesn't look like we got the correct equation here for
the near clipping plane because you know, something about the way that
we did it.
We missed a sign somewhere as I'm often want to do when I'm working
through math.
This is in fact why I've always wanted a good computer algebra system
because most of the time, the reason I don't do,
Do more math all the time.
It's just because it's so frustrating to try and make sure you don't
make a mistake somewhere.
And these are mistakes that a computer, wouldn't make.
But anyway, so here we go.
Let's take a look at what's going on here and just make sure we've got
things relatively sane.
What I did was I said that here is the value that were looking at,
right?
AZ plus b, and we know that it's going to get / - Z at the end of it.
Because that's what we're putting into the W coordinate.
So we know that we want f of negative n to equal negative 1 and f of
negative.
F 2 equal 1, when whatever, we set these two things too.
And so then we tried to do sort of a solve for what F of Z would be
assuming that we're going to pre divide through by negative Z.
Right?
So if we pre divide through by negative Z, the Z's cancel, and here,
we're just left with a negative a.
And then here, we're left with a negative B over Z.
So that does look like the correct equation to me as far as I can
tell.
That that seems like a reasonable simplification of this.
I don't see any error in that.
Unless I'm missing something about the way this is working, but I'm
pretty sure that that is how opengl will do.
It will divide by Z.
I don't think it will divide by negative Z, so it's going to /, but
I'm sorry it will divide by negative Z.
I don't think it's going to divide by Z because it will / W not - w.
And we're putting negative Z into the W coordinate.
So then we came down here to solve it.
We said f of negative n equals negative 1 and so the negative one is
the result.
That's what the function evaluates to the negative.
N is the parameter which goes in the place of the Z.
We end up with negative 8 because that term is on touch.
We end up with positive B Over N because the negative n cancels the
negative here.
Right.
So then we solve for a we essentially move - A to this side which
becomes a and negative one to the other side which becomes one and we
have a equals 1 plus BN and that is the term that we use to substitute
back in to the existing equation.
Again, did not see a bug there, doesn't mean there isn't one.
I just didn't see.
It.
So then we come over here and we get the same kind of thing but for B.
So we have a negative f, I'm sorry, not for be, I shouldn't say, but
for were using this equation, we have the same equation.
We have a one, that's what it equals.
We have the negative 8 because that term is untouched from here.
And then we have a positive B over F because the negative B over Z
when we plug in negative f, the negatives cancel.
We just get the
A / f solving that equation.
We have to go ahead and substitute in the - a term here for what we
actually solve for.
We sell for a equals 1 plus b Over N.
So, we have negative 1 plus b over n and we retain the plus b over F
term, we then distributed the negative to get negative 1, negative B
Over N plus b over F.
Like so and then we transferred the negative one to the other side.
Giving us a to we
And had negative B over n and B over F.
Right, we it so be over F.
Comes here B Over, N comes here.
So it's 1 - the other, and then we multiplied, we cross multiplied to
make the denominator be the same to make the denominator B and F
right?
Or f.
N.
So the B term,
Here picks up a pen.
The B term here, picks up an f and that is correct.
It is it is the bn.trek because BF is the negative term and BN is the
positive term.
So that leaves us with a b and minus F over F times, n equals 2
Right at that point we need to divide through to solve for b.
We end up with 2 FN because that comes out to the numerator and minus
F goes to the denominator and we end up with b equals to f n Over.
N minus F again, that looks pretty solid to me.
I don't see the bug there.
And if I don't see the bug there, I'm not going to see the any bugs
here, probably because this is this and this work together, so it
would probably be very difficult.
To have a sign bug only in this one but I guess you never know.
So we'll keep going.
So there's our, you know, our to f n Over.
N minus F, we then have to plug that in right to the be to solve for
a.
And we come through here, we know that a equals 1 plus b Over N.
So in this case, we have 1 plus b Over N.
That means that n is going to
multiply the denominator of this expression when we plug it in.
So we will have to FN
- NF, right?
So it's 1 plus 2 FN and yeah.
That's what we would expect.
So that all looks reasonable to me.
But now that I'm looking over here, why do we have
These Look Backwards.
Did we label these incorrectly?
These are the non perspective corrected terms.
It says for orthographic and we've got
these two terms in here, but these are the perspective terms.
And the ones that say these are the perfect of correct.
Terms are not the perspective.
Correct terms at all.
I must have done a cut and paste error there because that actually
should be this.
So This is actually what we should have been doing for our Matrix,
let's just check that again because that's that's what's supposed to
be there.
And we'll see what we get when we multiply through now.
Because this is what we actually would expect.
So let's take a look at these.
We have n and we have F.
So test 0 is are near clipping plane.
Z is negative, three W is negative 3, so that divides out to one and
we've got again exactly the same problem, which is pretty weird.
Like we're so we've got two totally different equations and they both
end up producing the exact same result.
In terms of, in terms of the final divided value which makes like very
little sense to me to say the least.
Like I am correct in thinking that that actually
did what it was supposed to do, right?
Yeah.
So these are basically functionally equivalent in terms of the
mapping, even with the / Z which makes no sense to me whatsoever.
I mean that is just strange, right?
Because that sort of is we derived these two equations right thinking
that the / Z wouldn't occur.
And so when we did The Matrix math for those, we were assuming that
the Z value itself should come out to when we plug in the near and far
clipping plane, we were assuming that the Z value itself.
Would come out to be negative 1 and 1.
Here it comes out to negative 1 and negative 3 right, which is totally
wrong.
And so I'm kind of at a loss to figure out what exactly where we just
doing absolutely horrible math.
Like, did we just make absolutely awful mistakes yesterday or am I
like am I totally losing my brain here?
When we look at this, right, let's see what these terms are.
Just figure this out here.
So here's D and here's e.
That's what they that's what they equal the moment, right.
And with with that d and e, we would expect like it to be evaluating
this equation.
We would expect D times n, plus e and we would expect d x f + e and
there you go.
And so our Matrix is Computing, what we would expect given those two
terms but they're nothing like what
We want them to be right.
So that's pretty bizarre and I would also like to know why.
So let's see what's going on there.
If there's I'm going to start because I'd like to know completely
what's going on here, not just what's wrong with the perspective?
Correct ones.
I would like to know the perspective, the non perspective corrected
ones, I'd like to know why those aren't working either.
So here's what we typed in, right?
And let's just verify that it's what we were expected because we did
this math outright.
We said, yeah, here we go.
So we did all this this math here, based on those equations.
And we came up with what we typed in here, which is that the D value
is 2.
Over N minus f.
Right.
And the E value.
Is n + f.
And - F.
And looking at those two, we can, we should be able to also verify
that.
That's actually what we said.
Should be here.
There's the two of her, n+ F, right?
And there's the the B value.
Ah, - 1 - 2 F / n + f.
So did we simplify that down?
Oh, we did.
This was an erroneous calculation, right?
Because I remember that being erroneous so here, okay?
So here we go to around myself and plus F Over.
N minus F.
So when we solve the, we celebrate here and plus F Over N.
Minus F, there we go.
So, that solution was up here.
This is where we worked it out to Over.
N, minus FN plus F Over N, minus F, right?
And that is, that is what we've got there.
Yeah.
Okay.
So, here are the two values that were actually using.
And in this case, we know we've got d.
Z + e is the equation.
That we're trying to compute and now, we've taken opengl out of this.
We're just looking at our own Matrix multiply and we did it here as
well.
So even if we've got a misconception about what opengl does and we
could write
Like these could just be the totally wrong equations to even be
writing and that's fine but that's a separate part of the debugging.
Right now our math is not even doing what we expected it to do even
just in our own code.
So that's an easier thing to debug and we I'm just going to go ahead
and look at that first just to clarify about what I'm thinking about
incorrectly here, right?
Which is to help partition the problem into pieces.
I can break down.
So here's my FZ.
DZ plus e and here are those terms so that means that F of Z should
equal 2 over n.
Minus F times Z, right?
Plus
N + f.
And minus F.
That's what I should be Computing.
I can simplify that Z down.
Because in this case, these two numerators denominators are the same,
so that's just 2 Z + n+ f.
Oops.
And plus f.
Over n- f.
Right?
And that's the entirety of the equation that we're looking at.
We're just saying,
2z.
+ + + f / and - F, oops.
And myself.
That's it.
So now, if I plug in the two values that I'm interested in, if I say f
of negative n, what does it equal, right?
I would get its -2 n plus n plus F Over N.
Minus f
Yes, and if I look at what that equals, that's f of negative n equals.
- n + f / n minus f.
which,
If I pull out the negative here is, n minus F, right?
Because that is f minus n.
So the negative of that is n minus F Over N, minus f.
F of negative, n should have equal negative 1.
Ah,
that is what I did erroneously.
I was going to say I'm clearly missing something here because we can't
be wrong about all of this all the time.
All right.
So now let's see if these come out correctly.
So here's my test 0.
So Z over W in this case would equal 1.
Which again not is not right though because the near clipping plane
should be mapped to negative 1.
If I remember correctly, that's what we said we wanted and then our f
is also 1.
So then - n
Didn't help.
I'm sorry.
The - n- F didn't help.
In this case, which I guess makes sense.
Because hey, if you pass in the - in this case I suppose if we negate
both of them we wouldn't necessarily expect the sign to do what it
did.
Anyway.
So yeah, Z / dub and I guess I should say in this case.
Oh nope, I'm wrong.
We're testing the non perspective corrected case so we don't divide.
So this is correct.
Z is negative.
One, we ignore the W because we're testing this Branch the negative 1
to 1 is the mapping we wanted.
Okay, shoot good?
Good, good.
So those equations I think are right there just not the equations we
needed because we need the perspective version of them.
Now, let's take a look at these equations, when using the - properly
and see what they produce, whether we get what we want there.
So if I take a look at test 0, I have - - so this divides out to be
one again, that
I wanted.
And then test one.
Also, divides out to be one as well.
So we don't this equation, seems busted this equation seems to be
working properly.
So it looks like we're going to have to figure out where we've gone
wrong.
In our understanding of this, I will go ahead and re substitute those
back in there.
But at least now we're actually we verified that this is correct and
working.
We just don't actually want to do an orthographic projection here.
So that makes it less useful.
All right,
So let's go ahead and work the other one through.
What did I write down here?
so, in this case, we've got
A d and e.
We're looking at the top branch.
So in this case, our D value equals 1 plus 2 f n over.
N n- f.
Well, I'll be honest, is there a reason that we didn't cross the ends
out of this?
Like that's actually that's weird that we didn't do that because this
is just n.
Minus F Over.
N minus f plus 2 F Over N minus F, right?
Which is actually a much simpler term that's n- F + 2.
F Over N.
Minus f.
Right?
I mean, did I did I was a hasty there, but that's that's a, that's a
crap value.
Look at what that turns out to be right?
That's n- F Over N.
Minus f.
Which is just 1.
I mean, there's no way.
That's right because it doesn't do anything.
Right.
There's no point to that.
It doesn't correct for anything.
So we know we must have a signed bug in that term.
Like, that's gotta be wrong.
So I just checked our derivation.
Obviously, I'm just as bad at math, as I say that I am because we
looked at this and decided that it was still working correctly, but
that can't be right.
That just can't be right.
Because yeah, look I mean there it is and that's just totally
That's just totally nuts.
It even looks like we started to simplify it and then like we must it
must have been because I was doing this in a hurry like look at this,
we started to simplify it and then must have concluded.
We couldn't even though it's obviously simplify able, I mean, the ends
cross even right there, you can see that even if you didn't pick it up
here, that's just dumb.
So this is like yeah this is, this is some questionable Mass
situations Happening Here If we're honest, just not real good.
Yeah, Highly Questionable.
So let's take a look at what's going on.
They're not sure exactly what's happening with that.
So let's let's just take one more.
Look, real real close there.
We've got the - a - b / Z thing happening.
Here, we we solved for a and again that looks pretty solid.
Because that would be negative one.
Plus it would be, it would be be over, I'm sorry.
It would be -1 + a on this side.
If we moved it over, which would mean that we move the negative, or we
have B Over N plus 1, which is what we have.
And so that's just what we would plug into the other side which we
did.
And yeah.
So if we look here and we say that in this case, be equals to f n
Over.
N minus f
Curious, let's take one more.
Look at this.
So, if we look at this, we've got one equals negative one, So that
obviously becomes to.
That's right.
- BN + BF, that's going to be negative b.
F, plus BN on the top.
So that's what we have here as well.
Which
let me just go ahead and do that out.
So one equals negative 1 negative B Over N plus BF.
That's two equals negative B n + BF, right?
That's 2 equals negative B.
F and f plus BN.
Oops.
And F or two equals.
Bien.
- BF over NF.
Pulling out the b, you get B and minus F over NF.
Oops,
Which does appear to solve for 2nf Over N minus F.
So that b does.
I don't know.
That looks pretty solid.
Just not sure where we're making the bug here.
We know we must be because we're getting it wrong.
So let's substitute, well, I guess we can't even suspecting because
this we know this term is garbage.
We know the a term is is garbage, right?
so, when we substitute that back in,
B over n.
We got the to f n and minus f.
And that's divided by n on this side.
Make sure I'm doing that right.
OnePlus 2 FN.
And minus F that's crust ends.
And - F.
Over N minus f plus 2 F Over N minus f.
Okay so wait did I get overzealous?
There we may be at least slightly, okay?
And - F + 2 F Over N minus F.
That's actually just
And plus f.
Can't find enough of the math here.
Here we go.
So that may just been me being overzealous, maybe my checking of the
math was bad.
So what did I do?
I said,
So here's where we were doing that before 1 plus 2 FN NN minus F.
I said it was n- f n- f + 2.
F over M.
SF.
That's right.
Then I said that was n- F + 2 F and then somehow I said that was this,
but this was just wrong.
So okay, I'm less nervous about that now.
Good.
All right, so that does mean that we can treat these like this.
Now, it looks like we already knew that in some weird way, right.
So this value on the top here is actually not.
We do not need to do it this complicated at all, right?
It's not.
It's just n + f Over N.
Minus f.
According to us, which makes that quite a bit simpler, unfortunately.
Like I saying that's still wrong.
As far as we know, because the math when we tested, it didn't work
properly.
So now, let's actually see what we get.
That's actually the E term for the other equation.
You look at these.
These are basically the same now except for the fact that we've got
the two in this, in the E term is now times, F times n, which was not
the case before.
That's pretty weird and the term swapped so I don't know, again, kind
of just in math, math, nasty land at this point.
But let's go ahead and, and take a look at those
So, here's the D term.
And plus f.
And minus F.
And here's the E term.
2fn.
N- F.
So our function, in this case.
Is going to be the D term times, the incoming Z value.
So if you're Scott Z
And plus f.
Over N minus F and we're adding the E term, so we can just go ahead
and add in the 2fn.
They're both on the same.
They both have the same divisor, right?
So, let's take a look at our F of Z term here.
We're going to plug in f of negative n that's are near clipping plane.
So if we take a look at here, we get Negative n n+ f + 2 FN
Over n- f f of negative, n.
- N squared - NF.
+2 f, n Over.
N minus F.
Looking at what happens when we keep going with that.
We end up with a these two terms are both f n terms.
Whereas, this is not that makes things a little ugly for us.
I'm not sure there's much, we can do about that.
In fact, I can pretty much tell that this is wrong.
Oh no.
No, but we also know that we will be dividing by negative Z, right to
get our final answer.
So we also know that we will be dividing here, whatever this comes out
to, we will be dividing by negative Z as well.
So we do have an extra
An extra end that will appear in the numerator.
So that's fine.
It's not as like fine.
But, you know, no need to panic quite yet.
Right?
Because this is our equation for the output Z value, but the Z value
gets / - Z
So then we end up with this equation.
If I write this part out, I get Negative squared, minus F, FN, rather
and sorry N squared minus f n.
So then I've got an N squared and in the top, if I combine these two
terms, I end up with just the positive f n.
So I get Negative.
N squared, positive FN down at the bottom.
I get N squared minus FN, right?
That's the the
The same there.
And so if I actually look at what this poor or what this should pull
out to be,
Pulling out a negative from this.
I end up getting negative N squared.
Minus f.
N Over N squared minus FN, which should be negative 1.
Right.
So when I plug in negative end to this, I expect I would expect to
have seen - one coming out of that.
Right.
That's what I would expect after the Divide.
But if you look at what happens here, I'm not getting that at.
All right?
I'm getting positive one after the Divide unless I'm misunderstanding
something because W is getting set to negative Z, right?
Although no, it isn't.
This is my Z value.
- 0 .1.
But it's not.
Getting X that, ah, right?
That's awesome.
So I guess we see a reason, why not to call this uvw because this is
x, y, z w here.
If you had a formal structure, this is only three to ensure this W is
just this value.
So we never actually look at the W coordinate because it doesn't
actually come back from this thing that's bad.
Yeah, I'm going to go ahead and say that that's just not going to be.
Oh man, I have never had that bug before.
I think, as I never named that W like that before, I don't know why we
did that.
That's hilarious.
Well, that explains why we were having so much trouble with it.
Yeah, we're just going to call that like something that is that's not
there, right?
Because that's just, that's just real bad.
That's a really easy mistake for my brain to make.
I do not want that happening at all.
So basically like yeah, you don't.
You don't get that one.
Oh wait.
That's this.
One's actually.
Okay, this one.
It actually is a V4, so that's fine.
So it's only the V3 that that's just real bad.
That's just really, really bad.
Let's try that one more time.
So now when we look at this thankfully I'm not seeing that as a w
anymore so that way, I'll remember that.
That's just the UV coordinates at.
This is a separate way to look at this Union.
It's unfortunate that there's no way.
Like this is one of those things where, like, I wish I could just hint
to the debugger in like comments that don't show it to me that way,
right?
I just want to see three values and I want to see them like x /, you
know, U /r or something, right?
I don't want to see it as if there's more because my brain will do
something stupid.
Like, it just did.
All right, so that's actually fine that's actually just fine.
That's going to be the correct value.
That's going to be negative 1, which is exactly what I wanted.
Let's see what this one's going to be.
This one's going to be 100 divided by negative 100, right?
This one's going to be negative.
1 divided by a negative 0.1, divided by a positive point one, which is
going to be negative.
One.
This one's going to be positive one.
Okay.
We're okay.
That actually looks reasonable, right?
So off we go the only thing I don't know right now.
And yeah, I guess this is something that that we don't necessarily
have to worry about at the immediate moment.
But the only thing I don't know right now.
And and this all looks correct now.
So we're back.
We're back in business.
The only thing I'm not sure about is the the direction.
These go.
We mapped the near clipping plane to negative 1 and the far clipping
plane to 1.
We're assuming that's correct through opengl because that's what we
could could glean from the spec.
But again, since we can't step into the open GL code, we don't really
know what they're doing.
And like, it could be that they want them the other way around.
So for now we're just going to have to assume that we got that
correct.
And that that's the direction they go.
And I would suspect that we did because we're using a the the Z
comparison function that we set up was assuming that that was the
correct mapping and it appears to be working
Although, I guess we should just to double check again that, that's
true.
I should do something in like render group to make up right stuff,
kind of tilt up like we were doing before, because if I if I do that
then we can actually see if the Z is properly doing occlusion, which
we don't necessarily know that it is at the moment.
So if I take a look at the push pop call here, I'm just going to go
ahead and say, you know, if entry or sorry if object transform
Upright, I just want to go ahead and say, okay, let's let's put the
y-axis sort of standing up and, and verify that that works.
So that that does again look like the Z buffer is working properly
there, and is sorting in the correct order and that's all I really
wanted to verify, right?
You can see if I'm looking from below, I can't see anything, that's up
higher.
If I'm looking from the top, I can see those slanted.
Is appearing in front of the ground.
So all of that is much happier now and that's good.
Okay.
Alright.
So that was basically a case where we actually ironically did the
math, right?
In both cases and thought we had it wrong because first, we had set
the near clipping plane to the wrong value which I don't know how that
happened.
That's just been a typo and then
And because I forgot about the fact that w, we had named W to not be
for the fourth dimensional.
Element of a V4 that case that was just a real bad idea.
Now I know definitively don't ever do that.
I've never done it before.
I'm not sure why we did it here.
But we did and oops, we could also call it s, I believe s.
And t are sometimes used for those values.
But for now we'll just leave it unnamed if we want to name it later,
we always can write.
We can always choose to come in here and name it something else.
That's not W.
I think up until might name them, S, and T for example, but yeah.
Anyway, now that we've got that under control, quote, on quote, we
need to go and take a look at how we are doing our Sprites, right?
So if we take a look at render group here, when we are doing our push
bitmap, call for a Sprite, I'd like to have some idea here about how
we're going to
To make this a line with the camera or other things of that nature.
So what I want to do is I want to know where the camera is, obviously
that's important.
And then I want to be able to align things to the camera in a sensible
way and we got to have some kind of technique for doing this, right?
We got to have
Some kind of an idea about how this is going to work.
And so we need to take a look, let me go ahead over here and make a
new entry on the Blackboard for it.
Oops,
So here's day 365, and I feel like my pain for some reason lost its
its Mojo there.
Yeah, it did.
so,
We have to think about Sprite cards now.
And what I, what I mean by this, we kind of talked about the end of
the stream yesterday is I want to be able to have my Sprites do what
it appears to be an orthographic projection, right?
So I want my Sprites if I want to be able to stand my Sprites so that
when they're looked at on the screen, you know, even if they're in the
corner of the screen,
And they look like they're standing up rectilinear with respect to the
screen, you know?
But I want them to do that.
Even inside a perspective projection, we're giving them coordinates
that looked like that would actually have them look more like that.
Right.
And so what I'm trying to do here is say let's feed coordinates in
which make it appear to be at that sort of angle without it actually
being at that angle right?
So even though it's actually going through perspective transform that
does this two things we put in coordinates that are fake so that it
ends up doing that.
That's kind of what I would like to do.
So if you think about what that implies, if we look at it from the
side, what I'm trying to do is say, okay, here's what I've got.
Right?
And I'm looking down at the camp.
I'm looking down this way and so for the from the cameras perspective,
it's doing a transform, that's kind of making things on these slices.
They're looking correct.
If we were to make something at a particular width at this distance,
it would look correct if it was in this plane but we are actually
making something that's at this other plane right?
We want it to be this way for other reasons.
We want it to be this way because we're trying to make it so that it
can stand up in z.
And so, what that means is whatever I want that angle to be, and
that's something that obviously I can.
Prescribe essentially, you can imagine that I have a vector, right?
And that Vector is the direction along, which I am free to move this
point.
So, essentially, I once I fix the ground point, you know, so I say
that the Sprite starts at wherever it is in Z here.
What I then have to do is say well, okay, it's going to stretch
upwards and it's going to stretch upwards at this along this point for
some distance D and along that distance, I need it to go far enough
such that the projected area into this other plane.
Right?
If I was to look at it this way and I could imagine that that camera
playing just being a line going through.
Ground Point as well and projecting this point on to it right in that
plane.
I need it to be some other height, I need it to be H, which I am
specifying to be based on the bitmap, right?
So the bitmap is going to prescribe this.
I know this vector and this Vector right
And I just want to go as far up, as I need to to produce this age.
Okay.
And that's the first step, that's only the first step because that
won't correct this year.
It will produce the correct height, but it won't correct this year.
So if we take a look here and you look at what's happening, well
So this is the naive approach obviously, right?
It's just doing nothing particular.
So if you look at what happens here, you can see that I'm getting this
sort of, it's making my trees more squat.
It's like smashing them and so I need them to come out to the same
size and as you can as you if you don't know, if you remember from
last time, oops
For any given tree, right?
I can manually sort of fiddle with this value and get the I think
that's probably about what it is, right?
I don't remember exactly what the trees aspect ratio should be.
But we can fiddle with the value ourselves for any given Tree.
In this case, I'm looking at this tree right here, we can make that
look like the tree should look.
Right.
But the question is, how do we solve that for all trees, no matter how
far away they are, or anything else, right?
Or no matter where they are on the screen, we should be able to
produce that value for any tree, okay?
And in this case, you can kind of see to we're getting that part of
the problem there too.
Is that that, that Z value, whatever it is, I suppose, as we get
Further.
I have to think about this.
For a camera that's tilted.
Or I guess even for a camera that's not tilted where that point is is
going to matter in terms of the projection down, right?
Because when this gets projected, it's going to get projected out from
the camera point.
So wherever the camera point is, it's going to get projected out onto
onto this Vector, right?
It's projecting this onto this
Right?
So, I believe and I could be mistaken but I believe what we
essentially have is we have the cameras up Vector which is the y axis
of the camera in this case, right?
So here's the camera.
We have some.
Us of the camera.
So that's the cameras, y-axis.
And then somewhere out in the world, you know, we have a point, here
is our ground point, right?
This is RPG ground.
We are looking at this thing.
We know that the cameras y-axis is the thing.
We're interested in down here again, so that's the cameras y-axis,
right?
And we know that we have another axis, which is whatever the card
accesses, whatever.
The like,
Upright accesses will call that you and we know that that upright
access can have as much of a distance along as we want.
So we can go as far along that as we want, right?
So that's our devalue.
And what we want to do is we want to pick our D value such that when
the camera looks at the D value.
And projected onto the Cy Vector, right?
We get H.
Does that make sense?
Hopefully, that makes some sense.
Now, we can produce a number of these things relatively easily, what's
this point, right?
Let's let's think about what these are.
So this point here, which is the actually the target point that we
want, right?
This is the place we actually want.
So we'll call that point actually P because that's just the point of
interest there.
So for that point P, we know that what we've got
In this case is p equals p g.
Oops,
Plus this D value X you.
So we're starting here, right?
We're going along you until we hit this P value.
If we want to, we can Center everything.
This entire thing because both of these are going to be + PG.
We can Center everything about PG and just get rid of the term if you
want to write.
And we probably should do that.
So let's take a look at this and we'll take a look at this point here.
In fact, maybe I'll give these all different P names.
So this will be
The result piece, this will be P result and this will be the p y.
This will be the thing that's on, CY, write the p y term.
That's probably bad actually, because I don't really want the Y in
there.
So let's say this is the P ground term.
Oh wait.
No, I already used that.
P projected.
So my projected term is going to be my pee ground term plus height.
Right.
Times that Cy vector.
And this is entirely known.
Write this whole thing, this, this value is known completely, right?
Because we know the height value, we know the Cy and we know the PG.
Those are all inputs.
So, at the moment d, right?
Is the only unknown right d and PR are the unknowns.
So we know what we're solving for, we're solving for D, in this case,
and we need to work out the equation of terms of that.
Okay?
So how do we work out the equations in terms of that we known as the
Anything that we know and this is where we're going to get our thing
to solve from, is that the camera point, right?
So, this is PC, in this case camera,
We know we have a vector that goes from the camera through this point
and down towards the place that we're trying to hit.
Right, we know that we've got that point and we don't know the length
of this.
At the moment, I suppose.
We don't know the length of that because that's a solve, right?
We've got to figure out where this, these two things, hit in some
sense, right?
We've got to figure out where PP would hit.
Now, the interesting thing about that, if we look at it is, we don't
really need to know this yet because we can solve these.
Also, in reverse order, we could figure out where this Vector hits
this Vector, right, or this plane, if you will.
So we could do a simple
Ray intersects plane and we could get this point right here.
And once we have this point, then we know
This line as well.
However, since that's a projection, I don't think that really helps
us.
It seems like solving for this is just as good, right?
Yeah, so here's the way I think we want to approach this looking at
the diagram, some more.
I think we want to approach this as the intersection of these two
lines.
To get this point we know this line, because it's entirely prescribed,
right?
We know this point p p and we know this point PC, so PP minus PC,
And we can even normalize that.
This is like the camera ray.
Right.
So we can actually simplify this problem down quite a bit.
We can just say that from the camera point.
we have a ray let's say let's just call that are we have a re going
from the camera point
We have another array in this case.
Starting from the ground Point going up.
We know both of these, that gives us two lines and we just want to
know the intersection.
Right, that's all we want to know.
So, we just want to know.
If we have PC.
If we've got PC Plus T times are we just want to know?
And that's so it's saying somewhere, we got PC, we're going to, in
fact, we've done this on a maid here before.
This is just two lines intersecting we've got PC, + t r, which is
saying I can go.
As far along, this is I want, T is my free parameter of where I go on
the line, I want PC Plus TR and I want that to equal, you know, PG
plus something times you right?
So T called
Like say is time 0.
Right.
And so I want to know where these two are going to equal each other.
This is actually quite straightforward because this equation is in y
and z.
Right?
Because I've got, why is this direction?
I'm sorry, I've got Z.
Is this direction?
And why is this direction?
So this even though it looks like only one equation in two unknowns
here in here is actually two equations and two unknowns because we
have X.
I'm sorry, we have y and z.
So all we have to do here is solve for one of them and plug it into
the other, and that gives us the solution that we're looking for.
so, I believe
I don't know that we ever generalized this.
I don't think we did sadly but we should.
Let's take a look.
Oh well maybe we never really did Ray versus Ray.
Maybe we just did the special case of it being a wall.
Yeah, where the walls were rectilinear.
All right, so that's okay.
That means we didn't waste any work there.
So let's solve this for real.
So what we want here is Ray intersects Ray
Right, that's what we're looking for here.
Now, you'll notice that in this case, these don't actually need to be
normalized.
There's nothing in this equation that suggests that these are
normalized values which means we don't even have to normalize our and
you first, we can just solve this and we will get something that no
matter what these lengths of these are it will still produce the
correct solution in terms of those raised, right?
Which is also kind of nice.
So let's go ahead and do that if we go ahead and solve this and I'm
going to change these terms around here since we're going to do a
generic Ray intersection, let's just call them A and B.
Now let's make our diagram much, much more straightforward.
So let's call this like PA
and ra and we'll call this PB.
And our B.
Right.
And what we're looking for is this point right here.
And so what we're looking to do here is do ray intersection.
Kind of a thing.
We would be taking PA ra and a PBR be
And we want to Output a couple things like probably a pair of values.
That's the the tea, you know, the whatever the T value.
So we would want this to Output like ta and TB.
Let's say.
Which are those multiplier values.
So assuming that we have the equation PA plus T-ara equals P B+, T
BRB.
Oops.
Assuming that, that's what we're looking for.
Assuming that, that's what we're talking about.
Then we should be able to
We should be able to produce the TA in the TV, that tells you how far
to go along each rate.
To hit the point where they intersect
So in this case, when we're looking at these values, if we take this
and start to solve it for SATA, what we would get in this case is,
let's go ahead and, and we'll split this in half.
so let's say we solve it for ta, we would get ta
Oops, I did that way.
We would get T-ara equals PB minus PA
Right.
Plus T BRB
And then so we want to solve again 40 a member are a is as array is
actually known.
So we would get ta equals p.
B, minus PA plus, t b are be over.
Our a, and again, you can't really unless you're doing geometric
algebra, which probably we should, but whatever,
You can't really divide by a vector, but that's okay because we're
just pretending, these are scalar like I said, we're going to.
We have two equations, one in oops, one in y and one in Z.
So let's just say that we're going to do this one in y.
So now we have done all of this in terms of Y.
So all of these implicitly have a why right in them.
So this is actually p bypa yra yrb.
I TB is still just a scalar, right?
So we have solved, TA in terms of T be, there it is.
Pretty straightforward, right?
So then we come over here and we just do the X version.
Okay, we've got the same equation, but now we want to plug in this
ridiculous.
Monstrosity, 40 a.
So we end up with PA plus PB y minus p.
A, why write plus t?
B?
R Loops be y over R.
A why?
That's our T value?
And all of that is times are a that in this case is going to be the
X's.
So everybody outside of that is going to be exes because we're going
to treat this equation as a PA x + 2 ax.
Sorry Pa X Plus ta plus r times R ax P B+, T PB x + TB R BX, right?
So these are X's these were all solved in terms of Y so then we're
equal over here.
We've got our PBX, we've got
Rtb and we've got our RBX now again, this we know now to be just in
terms of TB so we only have one more variable.
We only have one variable solve for, so we should be able to solve
this.
Even though it's a big nasty ridiculous equation with a bunch of terms
and it doesn't matter because we know, we can solve it.
We've only got one term left to solve for.
So in this case, we again would say
Right, let's simplify this down P.
Ax.
Up top here.
We're going to have again.
We're trying to get the kind of this out of there.
In fact, I guess what we would do first is probably multiply through
by ra y, so we get p ax.
Our a y plus this term now comes out directly so it's PB y minus p, a
y x, r ax.
Right, that's doing that term here.
Plus t b.
RB y RX.
Right, so you can see where that's happening.
Right there are a wide is Multiplied.
Through the ra y, comes out on this side as well.
So that's PBX are a y + TB R BX.
Ra y, right?
And hey, now we're basically done.
Right?
There's not a whole lot more to it, we've got rtb terms and they're
isolated.
So in this case, we can combine them.
And so we just move all the
Constant values over to the other side and off we go.
So we would have PA X ra.
Y plus PB y.
Minus P AE y.
RX - PBX are a y equals TB R BX ra y.
Minus RB y RX.
Oops.
There we go.
And that's the solution to the equation, right?
This just divides out and you end up with these terms being exactly
what they look like and there might be something we can simplify in
there.
We've got a px P BX r iy r iy.
So the riy term.
In this case, look at you can see that it produces is sort of a
simplified version on this side as well.
So if we were to simplify these terms a little bit on the top of the
numerator,
You can see what we would get here.
It's p.
Ax, minus P BX.
Times are a y plus PB y minus p.
A why?
Times are ax, right?
That whole thing is divided by RB X ra y minus RB y RX.
And you can kind of see to what this is.
This is just the subtraction of the two points.
So really you know, if we wanted to simplify this even further we
could talk about this in terms of the Delta between these two because
if you look at this it's a x minus BX B.
Y- A, why?
It's sort of like a flipped version of the negation in both cases.
So you could even write it more in terms of this variable.
After as well, if you wanted to but there's not any particular
overriding reason to.
So you can see it's somewhat nasty just because there's so many
there's so much namik later in there but it's really pretty
straightforward.
When you look at it it's just two subtractions with to multiplies, you
add those together and then to multiplies with the subtraction on the
bottom, that's it.
We also get interesting information about the structure of the problem
here so you can see if R BX ra y, minus RB y RX.
If that's 0
Then we can't solve this equation because you can't divide something
by 0, right?
That's a not, it's not just an infinity or something like that.
It's actually undefined what that is, in terms of math, we're trying
to solve in this case and that actually corresponds to a pretty
straightforward case it corresponds to the case where like these two
vectors are parallel or something,
Right.
Because if these two vectors are parallel, they'll never hit each
other.
You know I'm saying and you can kind of see how that sort of thing
would happen.
In this case, you need there to be as far as a DOT product is
concerned, right?
If these two vectors are parallel.
So let's say, I've got, I've got to two dimensional vectors and their
parallel, right?
So any two two dimensional vectors that are parallel, doesn't matter
what direction they're pointing as long as they're pointing in.
Exactly this.
It doesn't matter where they're like where they are in this case
because we're just talking about the vectors.
If two vectors are parallel, then we know that their dot product is
just going to be
Equal to their length.
right, it's just going to be
Right.
We know that this is the fundamental equation for our job product.
We've been over at tons and tons of times a dot b equals length of a
length of B cosine Theta, right?
So we know in this case, the cosine Theta term is going to be one,
right?
So we know that a transpose B is just going to be equal to length of a
length of B.
In this case, in the
Cynthia Timbers away, which is to say that ax
X BX plus.
Ay, y times.
B y is going to be equal to ax minus BX squared.
Plus ay, y minus b y squared.
Sorry that's not at all.
What?
I meant one type of time.
Ax squared plus ay, y squared square rooted times.
The x squared, let's be y squared square rooted, right?
That's the length of a and the length of B.
In this case,
Right.
And we know that there's no cosine term because the cosine Theta term
will have to be one in the case where they are parallel.
In this case, another way to write that would be that.
Just showing some different equations.
We could use here to look at the parallel thing.
Another way to write that too would be to say alright I know that if
two things are parallel
You know, I've got a vector and it's, you know, you V or whatever.
I think the right way to say this, I've got some Vector U, let's say
right and it goes in Direction, I know that anything that is parallel
to you as a vector has to be equal to some value.
I'll use the Lambda for that value.
Anything that's parallel to it, has to be in the form of this
equation, right?
It has to be the U, Vector times some value,
Right, it can't be anything else because I can't change the Direction.
All I can do is change the length.
So in order for a and b to be parallel, another way to write that
would be that a has to be equal to some multiplier times B.
Right.
I know that that has to be true so that means in this case that a x
has to be equal to
Lambda X BX, right?
And a y, has to be equal to Lambda times.
Be why?
Right.
If that makes sense.
So that's another thing that we would know about these two things.
If they were parallel
That makes sense.
So looking at that through here you can also see that I could
substitute these guys in, don't ask me why I'm going down this.
I just felt like kind of
Having a mathematical aside.
I don't know.
Maybe we've just been doing.
Too much math.
And now I'm in a math Zone.
But anyway, so you can write you can imagine that this equation is
something that would be true about any two vectors that are going to
be parallel because it means that the cosine term for the dot product
has to be 1.
And then, similarly, we would expect this to be true as well, right?
We would expect the the lambdas to be true.
So, if I took a look at that, a little more closely that would mean,
that this would be ax.
BX, would just be Lambda x squared, right?
Because we could substitute in Lambda Lambda x 4, BX, or vice versa,
right?
In any case, it's also the case that Lambda I look either way, we said
that
One way to go, I suppose.
That since I wrote it this way, I'll keep going that way.
So it's Lambda b.
X squared plus Lambda b y squared equals.
Lambda x squared plus Lambda actually.
Sorry.
It's a little that Lambda is squared Lambda.
Squared times because there's a Lambda squared now in each of these
Lambda squared x squared plus Lambda squared.
A y squared x squared plus y squared.
Times.
I'm sorry, that's Abby.
Be x squared, plus b, y squared.
And if you look at what happens here,
we get that situations that same situation, we pull out the Lambda
squared, we'd end up with the Lambda here, right?
And that would go away and those who had multiplied together and we
would end up with Lambda be x squared, plus py squared, which is
exactly we have on the other side.
So this equation just becomes
On both sides, Lambda be x squared.
Plus 3y squared.
Right, which is what we would expect for for parallel vectors.
So, down here, we want to know, you know, what are the conditions for
which this, for which this will end up being 0, right?
And if we imagine what we would get, how would we get a situation
where this could be 0?
Well, think about exactly this constraint.
If I was to say that, I've got my to raise here, because remember
these are our two rays.
We've got one Ray that's our ax or a y1r.
A, that's RBX rby.
If I was to say the exact same thing about these,
Right.
So I'm going to say exactly this and a plug it in.
What this term becomes is Lambda R BX squared, right?
Because I would plug in Lambda R, B, I'm sorry.
Lambda.
R BX.
Ra Y is Lambda rby, right?
So it would be Lambda R BX, rby in this side.
I would get rby.
This ra X becomes a Lambda R BX of the Lambda comes out.
There are be X and now you can see that Lambda R BX, r b--, y minus
Lambda R BX rby it's the same.
Term.
So they cancel and you get a 0, right?
So you can see right here that the math without us even ever knowing
it, when we wrote it down, has found figured out
The fact that this problem we asked it to solve is unsolvable in one
case, and that case is when these are parallel.
And it's pretty cool.
I always liked how that works out where it's like we didn't write any
of this ahead of time, right?
We didn't tell the math anywhere about any of that, but just the fact
that we constructed the problem.
As we wanted it automatically produce a mathematical operation
necessary for its solving
That tells us that we have a case, we can't solve.
So if I didn't know that ahead of time.
When I See This come out of the equation, I'm like, oh oops, like now
I know better not feed this anything, where this term can be 0.
And once you start investigating that term, like I did here, you can
understand what it means, geometrically, and it becomes nice and
interesting, right?
You're like, oh,
I got it now.
All right, so that's a little bit of a, an excessive aside there.
I admit that.
I'll go ahead and get that out of there so we can see it more clearly.
So here's rtb term.
And so what remains here is in the TA case, we would have to solve by
plugging into this for TB, we can do that very simply, we've already
got ta solved in terms of T be here so we can just plug, whatever the
result is that we get we can just plug it in here and go.
So let's go ahead and type that in.
Was the game running this whole time, okay?
So what we'd like to do here?
Is just make a math function for this.
And this math function is just
Ray intersect to.
We've got a PA and an RA that we've got a PB.
We're like that being capitalized for what.
I don't know.
Math layout in code.
So he's so unsatisfying.
And now we've got our Ranger set.
Call I need to solve for these two things, so I would like to solve
for my TA first and you can see it's PA x minus PB X.
Right?
I want to multiply that by our a, at why.
Then I want to add PB y minus PA, y x, r ax like so.
and what I want to do here is I want to do a divide
I want to divide by RB x times ra Y and I want to subtract our be y
times.
R ax right?
So That's mighty, oops.
Sorry, it's Mighty B value.
Mighty a value is just
Up here, you can see it.
Pby nice.
PA Why?
Plus t, b.
X.
RB y.
And that whole thing is over.
All right, bye.
So that's what we think our equation is in this case.
Now you can see we've got a problem here.
This is, I believe correct.
Although, you know, we obviously could have a math bug there, but the
reason we don't want to leave it in this form, although this is
correct as, because you can see we've produced another divide here
that could
Zero, right?
So anytime that are a is y, component is 0.
This would fail.
And we know that we've got this condition here of them being parallel.
Being a failure case.
We don't want to introduce another failure case, just because we
didn't plug in the math and follow it through, right?
So what we'd like to do is produce a TA that has this work through
that goes with the same denominator of possible, right?
So you know, we've got this over here.
I suppose this would help here.
I'm using a feature now of Milton that I've never used for this
purpose before I want to write these equations here.
So we've got ta
Was pby - PA Why?
Plus t, b.
Rby wonder why that drawing doesn't work super well.
Like that plus didn't come out at all.
Ta equals pby - PA y + TB.
Rby, right?
Over are a why?
And then we got this one over here.
2B equals p.
X- PBX.
R iy plus PB y 1 is p a y r ax.
R BX R.
Ey.
R.
B-- y RX.
Right.
So if you look at what's going to happen here, if we wanted to plug T
be as an actual equation back into ta, right?
So we want to put this entire term back into here, then we can
actually will see what Lucy what's going to happen.
Rby is just going to multiply all of these terms.
Right.
So if you take a look at what that's going to mean, in terms of how
this equation is working, you can let's see.
You can imagine sort of what's going to happen here.
I've got my ta term.
Equaling.
Let's see, what's the best way to work this through.
So, if I isolate this term first, I would get pby - PA Why
over are a y plus and then here's this gigantic nasty term
He ax PBX.
all right, y+
B, y- p.
A why?
RX.
Those two terms on the top, are going to be X.
RB y.
So we get an rby in here.
Maybe I'll just
Cleaner than rby in here.
+ p.
B.
Y- p.
A why?
RX.
Oops, rby.
So we have again, this term RX X RB Y and that case
So, we get that whole thing times TB.
And it's going to be over.
This this situation right here, times that so it's an RA y x, r BX.
Ra y, minus RB y r ax.
And lovely.
And by lovely, I mean, not at all, lovely for obvious reasons.
So yeah, that's not fabulous to say the least.
Looking at the amusement that's going to happen here.
Assuming I haven't already made a math error, which I probably have is
that I guess the p b.
Y- p.
Ay, y term exists in both places.
So here is a pby PA why?
Right?
And here's the pby PA, Why?
And that might be the thing that allows us to do something useful here
in terms of canceling because what we want to do is simplify our
denominator so that it looks like this again hopefully, right.
Or something close to it.
So multiplying these three.
What we would get is TA equals this term up here.
So P be y, minus p a y x.
RB X ra y.
Minus RB y RX.
Right.
And then that we're going to add PA X PB why I believe.
You know, this is really.
Problematic.
I really need something that's more accurate for drawing because I
can't it's hard for me to see what my terms end up being, and it's
easy to make a careless error between the Xs and the Y's here, because
I can't tell the difference between them a lot, like when I write
them,
The lag kind of hurts me.
Like it wouldn't probably on paper I suppose.
So it's a x minus BX.
Y minus y.
So, all of the P values.
Are always equivalent 'add row.
So, it's pby - PA Why?
Yeah, and I'm really nervous about that.
I am almost certain, we won't get this math, right?
Because of that, I suppose we can go do it on a computer algebra
system after this.
Tap check what it comes out to be.
But yeah, like I had just it's like when I draw this a lot of lag in
in the switch between those and so like sometimes it doesn't even pick
up the.
Yeah, the thing that's just the nature of it at the moment.
So anyway, all right.
But I'll just kind of finish it through nominally.
And then we're going to have to probably go and use something where I
can definitely know what the terms are.
So I've got PB y, minus PA, Why cure I'm adding and multiplying
through by, by this term we got to have that we got to have the ra Y
in there.
So that's also our a y at the head end of it right off by itself.
It's got.
All right.
Why?
That whole situation?
Then we've got PA xpbex.
Terms are a yrb.
Why?
Oh no, that's not true.
Only this part is multiply that because it already has an r i y in the
denominator.
Alright yrb why
+ PB y minus PA.
Y r ax rby.
That whole thing is over our a y r BX ra y.
Minus RB y RX T.
Be
Right.
So looking through this again, I'm pretty sure we can't actually do
this math.
I'm pretty sure there's been at least one transition.
Nation by at this point of an X to Y and probably, I guess, what we
could have done is just use totally different terms for all of these
to make it easier on ourselves like an, A B C D, E kind of thing.
I don't know, it becomes hard when you've got this many things to keep
track of them, if they're not named in some way that you can actually
relate back, but, you know,
What do you do?
So if you take a look at these as they are, we can at least try to do
what we would do and have some semblance of that here.
So if we take a look at what happens in terms of pulling out terms,
we've got P bypa.
Why subtraction term here?
So that actually groups together and we would end up with a single
term here that was R BX r iy.
R BX, R ax, plus the ra X RB y term and so we can go ahead and do that
one.
BP b y- p.
A why is this term?
And we've got, that's just an addition in there.
So we know we've got our BX.
R iy minus r b y or X plus r, ax rby and these two terms therefore
would cancel.
You can see, this is an RX rby in both cases, right?
So, we end up with only that we, then add this term, which is PA
xpbex.
Are Ayr, be why?
What we're looking to do is cancel the Rai.
And now we found ourselves in a good position.
There's an RA Y, and an RA Y in both terms.
So those all cancel and we are left only with our be why.
I'm sorry PB y, minus PA.
Why write x r BX.
And P ax P BX X RB y.
But that's a - that should have been - they're, right?
That should have been -.
Right.
It's this term.
I had the recommend if you're doing math, folks, do it on actual
Brr.
Because it's real hard doing it this way.
Let me tell you.
So, that's the actual term now.
How do we still get it up with a t be in there?
That was that was dumb.
That's incorrect.
Right.
There's no TV.
We substituted T be in.
So that's what that actually looks like.
So, looking at that, right?
If we take a look at it, they're pretty much exactly symmetric so,
rather than solving it that way, which introduces a synthetic / 0, we
don't need to worry about.
We can instead solve it this way with the math work through, which is
PB y, minus PA y x, RB X Plus PA x, minus PB,
X times, r b.
Why
Right.
And these are in terms of the same new denominator exactly wanted.
So I'm going to call this denominator D for denominator.
And now we get to the actual equation.
And you can kind of see here.
What we can do is say, all right, let's compute that denominator.
If the denominator is 0 then they don't have a solution so we're not
going to be able to return anything to you, but if it's nonzero then
we can go ahead and do it.
Now this is not super numerically stable because as this approaches 0
we will get really huge values.
So in general this Ray intersection routine is not meant for people
doing anything wild, right?
Only really meant for people, doing something saying, and that's fine
because we know when we're using it, and that's okay.
If we ever need to use something wild, we need to think through the
math in a different way and take into account, whatever the special
things are, in the case of that, whatever that thing is that we're
doing.
So we look here, we can see sort of, our two values for TB and ta and
I'll go ahead and get rid of that.
Are you can see here our value for t.
A is the, the be y
Miss the a y and the ax, minus the BX X, the to our bxr be wise, and
it's almost a symmetric equation in the other case, the PA x minus B.
BX X.
RI y, PB, y, minus PA.
Why I must be our X and both /.
This product here, which again, talks about the parallel nature of the
two.
Raise.
In this case, like I said, that was pretty hard to read, writing it on
the, on the Blackboard.
And so I don't really know that we were able to get that math, right?
I don't have a Cas installed on this machine, but we could, if we want
to try to get Wolfram Alpha to check our stuff for us.
I don't really remember the Syntax for Wolfram Alpha.
I think it's similar to Mathematica, but I don't really remember.
So, here's an example.
Apparently we can just do the two equations separated by a comma.
In this case, we know what those two equations are, right?
We use my pen.
This is what we want.
So in this case, we have PA X Plus ta.
Oh, does it know?
It's not going to think those are all different variables does is it
does it?
Well, we'll try.
So if PA X Plus ta X re x equals PA PB X Plus t b times R BX.
and then I have the exact same thing, but in y,
But mu.
Okay, well ladies and gentlemen, the knowledge engine.
Can I get it to know that it's a solve somehow?
Okay, that's fine.
I don't know how to get it to solve these things for us.
I would, I would like it to say,
Of a system of equation.
It did here.
I don't know how it knew that that was a system of equations and that
my other one wasn't.
How do I tell it what to solve for?
Because I'm not telling you what to solve for.
For, there we go.
For the a
I give up.
Solve system of equations.
Stephen Wolfram.
What is the deal?
This is pretty simple, folks.
I just want to check my math.
And this is like the most simple thing.
This is like the most basic thing I could possibly ask you to do.
I just want a computer to check my math for two equations and two
unknowns.
I mean, right?
I mean, those are the equations, but again, I don't know how to
I don't know how to make any of these.
These things know what's a constant and what's not a constant, right?
Because this is symbolic solve.
I'm asking it to do, I don't want it to solve for numbers.
Look, I'm not asking it to solve a numerical equation.
but,
I give up, who knows?
Maybe we'll never know.
Anyway, that is the math as we worked it out.
There's our two dimensional array intersection case you provide the to
raise and it does the intersection call that it produces the
intersection back.
Which I'm just going to say for now is Right.
Someday, we'll find something that can check our math for us.
How this isn't just built into an editor these days?
I have no idea.
Computer programming is so ridiculous.
It's like it hasn't changed in in 40 years and
somehow we still are up in a situation where
Can't even check basic math without buying a fifteen hundred dollar
piece of software apparently.
Anyway, grumpiness aside here's our Ray intersect to let's just assume
it's right for now because we can fix it later when we can actually
check the mass somehow and we'll just look at how will we use it if we
knew it was correct.
So assuming that we have an upright transform, we have exactly the
situation that I was talking about before we
Know exactly what our construction is, because I described it
previously.
And so we've got our basic point that were passing down, that basic
point that we're passing down, is this entity P right here?
We know the camera transform because that's something that's set in
the render group.
So we can extract the axis of that transform if we want to and use
that as that other value, we were talking about.
But
Now we just need one of the thing that we have not specified and that
is the card, whatever that card access is.
And I don't know what that card access should necessarily be yet.
Let's say for sake of argument that card.
You know that standing up angle.
I don't know what that's what that is exactly.
But you know this is this is the card.
The card is going to be something in y z, right?
Right, we'll call this card y, z going up.
And that Vector is just going to be something like
I don't know.
Probably going.
Maybe 25 + y + 75.
+ z.
Like a, the cards probably should be fairly upright.
They shouldn't go too far and why?
I don't know, but maybe not could be point five point five.
Something like that.
This is not normalized at the moment, but we don't need it to be
normalized.
Like I said, we solved for the intersection not expecting anything to
be normalized, so that should be fine.
So, we have the card X Y, that's what that Vector is.
One of our vectors.
The other Vector that we
To know is the one along the ground.
So we need a another piece of information, which is the camera Y is e
Vector.
We don't know what that is yet.
So will we have to extract that out of the of the other transform?
But now we know everything else.
I guess we also need to know the campy.
So this is the camp eyz, I guess we'll do it this way.
This is the card Ray.
Gamma ray.
And the car pyz is just going to be entry P YZ.
And that's everything that we would need to solve this equation.
So we just need to extract these two out, right?
But otherwise, when we call the ray intersect code,
This would give us the intersect point.
That we were looking for.
Between the two rays.
So the camp eyz, cam ryz?
This is the card ryz.
Sorry card pyz
or ryz.
This would give us the intersection point.
So if we take a look,
At what that's giving us on the diagram, that intersection point is
the distance along the ray.
We would go to find the point that we're talking about.
And so, in this case,
in this case, we already know the y axis is going to be this axis.
So we actually already kind of know what this is going to be, right?
We sort of are getting an input from the user which is trying to
rotate that and we're going to have to take that into account
separately.
In terms of when we want to start allowing that that Shear to occur,
which I guess I hadn't thought of
Out too much in this case.
So we may have to kind of go back that in a little bit more later.
But for now what we're trying to do when we get this, this Ray
information out is the distance from the along, the camera to get to.
It is going to be here the distance from the point along card.
Our y z is going to be rtb value, right?
So, the thing that comes out in in y, right?
That is actually going to be the value that we need to go along.
That's how long our y-axis.
Needs to be basically.
So you know, in this case we've got the size, why?
Yet, we've got our size Y, and that's going to come into play when we
compute these two things.
And we've got our y-axis computation, which now is going to be down
here, and that's going to be
This unfortunately this we need to sort of put it to do in here.
Because right now we're sort of just going to be doing this, right?
We're going to be assuming we're going to get the size right.
But we wouldn't handle the rotation right yet.
In terms of correcting, this card.
So, when we get the camera pyz and the camera ryz here, then we'll be
good to go.
So let's see how we would get those out in terms of our
Render group.
We know that we have our projection Matrix which is the one that we're
using at the moment and that projection Matrix actually has the
information that we want.
So if we want the Y and Z locations of the camera, we could back them
out from here.
But what I would prefer to do is actually not have to do that every
time we want to look at them.
So I would rather have something which basically just stores this
This info for us because when we want to do computations with them,
it's nice to be able to grab that out and we can do that very easily
because we know when they're set.
So what I'd like to do is say all right if we want to get the camera p
y z we should be able to get that directly out of the group.
So the camera p y and the camera pz is exactly that and I guess I can
just do it this way.
So the only confusing thing is, how do we get camera?
Ryz.
And in order to get that rate, we need to figure out that kind of
offset along the cameras, y-axis, right?
Remember we way back.
When we started the math, we drew this and we said well, wherever the
entities point is, there's the cameras y-axis, it needs to go out that
much height.
Right along that axis.
So we need to say that the cameras are y, z is going to be whatever
the cameras position is, right?
We're going to subtract that away, and we're going to have the
Entities placement wherever it is.
Plus the height, which is that size y times, whatever that camera
y-axis is because that's what we're moving along, right?
And this will give us that camera Vector, that's pointing down.
So, that's actually all the code right that actually does everything.
We want it to do.
In this case, there's nothing more to it.
And then, you know, we obviously want to
critic ate this.
Because we don't actually want to do this operation if we're not
talking about one of those Sprites, it's supposed to kind of be
standing upright.
So if we take a look at what's supposed to be happening here, we just
look at this, we're like okay, this is the math that we're talking
about that we worked out again, we probably have a bunch of bugs in
there.
We don't even know if this routine is correct yet because we can't
check it at the moment and we need to check it.
But
What we can do is finish off this before the end of the day, we can go
down here to when we actually set our camera transforms.
When we set our camera transforms, we can
We can take those camera X and y's and actually use those to get to
set up what we actually want to do.
So in here when we do our set camera transform, I want to take a look
at who is calling that the moment.
That's all fine.
And that's all fine.
So if we want to I think the way I'd like to do this because we this
is already known I think I'd like to do something like this.
Which I think is how we had it before but I feel like we maybe want to
do that because I want to store this information and I'd rather not
have people have to back it out.
So it kind of feels to me like, maybe that would be the best way to do
it.
So, you know, in here, when we got World mode, instead of calling the
camera, transform code, maybe we just, oh, we force you to pass this
in here.
Instead because we want them to be stored because there are things.
We're going to need to do computation on.
We could back them out from here.
But then we're doing a bunch of math for no reason because we already
have that information if that makes sense.
So that kind of feels like probably a good idea there.
So maybe I'll do this.
And then inside render group.
I'll do something like this.
and that's the way we had it before and I figured well, it was easier
to pass in a matrix but in this case, I do kind of feel like it is
It's a little more interesting to do it this way because then I can
save those values which is what I want.
and in this case, that makes this a little bit more of a pain, but
only a little
And in fact, now that I think about it, we could just do something
like this.
and for you,
That is not nearly as messed up as I was expecting it to be given how
little we had testing wise there, but you can see we've still got some
nastiness here, right?
Right.
You can kind of see, we've got a little bit wrong in our, in our, it's
not completely wrong, but it's pretty close.
So yeah, so you know, we're not too far off, I'm going to stop there
because we're going to have to go dig into that math.
And like I said, it should be pretty easy to check the work but that's
okay.
And like I said, it's really hard.
I did not do it on paper, they're those terms all, look the same, the
drawing is just not High Fidelity enough.
It's kind of laggy and it has a lot of noise in it and it's really
hard to do my handwriting.
Isn't that great to begin with?
So it can't really handle that extra suffering but
But we will check it out.
So if there any cute questions for now, I can take them.
If not, we will deal with it next weekend.
Finishing the debugging there and then we should be good to go.
The games there was a lot of chat about Wolfram expecting one letter
variable names and interpreting RBX as R times B times x.
Yeah, I was wondering if it would do that, I don't know.
Building strong.
Didn't we do this math when doing the screen projection?
We might have.
I don't remember.
We didn't pull it out into a function if we did though.
Nympho asked to think we did an epilepsy warning there, I don't know.
I don't know what doesn't doesn't trigger epilepsy.
Pepe fell.
Hello yesterday.
I was asking about shaders and the z-buffer.
Could I rephrase the question?
It will be the last time.
Sure.
Messy all that maybe if you swap the order of the some on TB, you get
an equation more similar to TA.
They're already pretty similar.
You just talking about getting the wise lined up.
Something like that.
Can we show again the equation?
Yes.
So the equation is
In these terms, right?
It is that we want PA X, Plus
ta X are a x to equal PB x + TB X, RB X and
At the same time.
Why?
So we're saying a base Point.
PA plus some scalar times.
The raid erection a equals some base point B, plus some scalar times
the rate erection be, right?
And that's all we want.
Is just it's literally just a plus BC equals D plus EF in X and Y.
Right?
Is the stream Weekends Only now?
Yes, the stream is Weekends.
Only now,
1935 is Molly Rockets upcoming volitional fiction game.
Oh, it's about actually knows that that's cool.
Pepe Valdez had meteor is a 2-D game.
My idea would be to treat the Z variable, not as the Z coordinate, but
as a variable that the pixel Shader will use to kill hidden pixels and
do alpha blending with the GPU power.
Well, so the first part is like, well, the Z value is that is what the
Z value is.
So
Are doing exactly that but if the Z coordinate is, we want it to be
where the thing is in 3D.
That's what gives us the depth sorting that we want.
Alpha blending.
On the other hand, you would have to say, how do you think the alpha
blending will work, right?
Because the only way to do alpha blending is to have sorted, a sorted
order of combinations of the things that you're passing down.
And so there really is no way to use the z-buffer for that.
Unless you do like I talked about a while back something which
actually uses frame buffer atomics to keep a list of all the things
you do.
And then resolve them at the end, right?
Let's see.
Either questions about what we're doing.
Doesn't look like there are any other questions about the code?
Just to ask the person who wanted to know about seeing the equations
again, did this do that?
Was this what you wanted to know in terms of what the equations are?
Master Yoda.
Are you doing this?
So you can mix perspective, projection in orthographic projection for
game objects.
Yes, basically.
It's so that I don't have to.
It said that if I want to I can just always think of everything in the
same world space and not have to think about everything is maybe going
through two different matrices paths and having the lineup and stuff
like that.
So I was kind of hoping I could figure out a good way here to just
output Sprite cards that do whatever we want and we can keep them all
in the same space.
Brooke tag.
Now we have the alpha issue with the 3D stuff is that easier to fix
than the 2D sort because you already know how to fix that.
It's not necessarily easier to fix.
It's just that going through the z-buffer path.
We are guaranteed that we can scale properly because we know that we,
you know, we can basically treat the edge Alpha as something that can
be solved via.
For example, Alpha to coverage in a multi sample buffer.
Want to or maybe there's other good techniques we can employ for that
just just a little Edge Alpha and then for shadows and stuff like
that, we probably won't have to sort those.
We can probably just break them into two groups things that are Shadow
like and things that aren't
And draw them into passes.
So I think we should be able to get away with not having to do.
Enter object sorting pretty much at all for the most part.
And that's really what I wanted to get away from so it's not like it's
still completely trivial, it's just
You know, it's it's something that will scale better because I want to
be able to have lots of Sprites on the screen.
And I don't want to have to constantly worry.
if that makes sense, I don't want to constantly worry about
The, the sort being a bottleneck because there's lots of things we can
do per pixel to try stuff on the GPU.
And there's not a lot, we can do to speed up the Sorting when lots of
Sprites are overlapping.
It's just sort and sort is bad sorts and squared, worst case.
It'll in a lot of these algorithms.
It's n log n, even if you do it, most optimally,
Somebody ran the equation through Matlab, which is what I want to
check.
It says, this could be the solution at least for Matlab - PA XR B.
Y- P Ayr bx- PB X.
RB y, plus PB y x RB X over.
So the denominator is the same.
the numerator is at least slightly different
Let's take a look.
I'd like to take a look while we're here just to see
Good.
So people plug this into some math software which is what I want to
do.
So I would like to check this work.
Let's take a look here.
So we have P ax, I'm looking at the one from derive 6 here, we have PA
X RB Y, which is what we expect - PA y, x, r BX.
So, it looks like it.
Multiply this out.
Let me go ahead and multiply this out just so we can see a little bit
easier.
What we have here.
So we have p a XR B.
Y- P BX rby.
Plus pby.
R BX, minus PA, y, RB X over D and the equation here at.
They're both of our i yr, b, x, minus r, XR, B, RB Y, which is what we
had, right?
Although, they've got it the other way around, so, they have, we have
ra y times, R, BX o, no x minus RX Ry.
So, they've got the same denominator in both cases, which is what
we've got, right.
The denominators match up.
So, that's good.
And then in the TA case P.
XR.
B, y.
That's what we've got here - PA y, RB x py r BX, what we got here - PB
X?
RB y plus PB y r BX?
So that looks like the same thing.
TB is pxr, a why?
PBX are a y pa, why are exp a yre x and it's a negative, then a - P
BX.
R.
Ey.
+ A+ pby times re X+ pby.
So it looks like we got it right?
So it looks like that's correct shockingly.
So that's good.
All right, so our Ranger section math might be good and that's good
because that would mean that all we have to do is just take a look at
our usage of it.
A little more closely and make sure that we're doing everything
correctly.
This this part right here, obviously is
Kind of hastily thrown together that I was just putting in there.
But, you know, this thing about grabbing out the camera position and
taking the, the ryz which is the entries sort of ground point, plus
the cameras y-axis, how far we wanted it to go, how far we wanted it
to appear along that y-axis.
And then we took from there and subtract it away the cameras location
to get the vector.
Kind of going towards that Grand Point and and then we kind of made up
the card, poking access there, that makes sense.
Well, this is just totally bogus is why we never really finished this
out.
Did we?
So we were supposed to use this as the card y'see
first of all,
That's what we actually are supposed to put their.
So technically, we weren't doing that at all.
That's pretty weird.
so actually,
We're surprisingly good.
So far, our lower set of trees is not correct but our upper set is
basically exactly, right?
Looks like that's exactly what I wanted there.
You can see it's keeping this guy quite, right?
So we're not correcting, you know?
We haven't tried correcting the sheer yet but that's
That's quite good, actually.
Yeah.
I'm very happy with that.
All right, but we still have some issues here.
The
in terms of,
Getting these guys to line up, which might we, you know, we also do
sort of have the issue.
I don't think this is that that issue though.
But we do also have the issue of the parallel lines as well.
Obviously.
So there is that issue but that's, that's actually pretty good.
So we're in pretty good shape there.
So, that's good.
And Master Yoda said, it seems that valve has two solutions in the
Gated in relation to yours.
Negated in in the whole meaning of the whole thing is negated like
that.
miss you at Val buses is
Yeah, it does look like yours are negated, but, why, so why the other
one is not negated?
How did we get to computer algebra programs to produce two different
results?
Because did you guys look at the one that
I had that peppy Val posted there from Drive,
I'm do we know which one of those is correct?
Because it doesn't look like, I mean, you shouldn't be able to negate
them both?
Or not negate them.
Both right?
You should have to do one or the other is the correct answer.
And so,
I'm wondering since I haven't done it through the computer algebra
system, I'm wondering why derive, 6, did someone enter it in a weird
way, like, why or did I check it wrong?
You know what I'm saying?
Because I don't think it can't be both and I'm pretty sure that that I
checked it correctly versus yeah.
So I'm pretty sure it's not negated in that sense.
But we'll have to see and I think ours I think that looks pretty right
to me too.
I feel like we're correct here but I could be wrong about that.
And also that's very stable like this is looking quite good.
It's just at
As we flip around through one part of the projection, we get a bogus
answer through there but like, look at how stable that is everywhere
else, right?
We just have a singularity there which may be the parallel projection.
Part of things will have to take a look at it, but you can see that
it's very stable for everywhere else, right?
Like it's getting it's doing exactly the correct Sprite thing,
everywhere else.
It's worth noting too that we can always do sort of a separate thing
which is that one easiest right thing to do and it's not necessarily
the right thing that I want to do.
But in addition to this, we also have
another option here, which is that, you know, the entry x axis equal
size x, x group camera.
X.
Hammer wine.
And so, if you want just regular Sprite cards, you
That as well, right?
So you can see it's very easy to just produce a standards right card,
but that's not necessarily what we want to do here, right?
The reason for that is standard Sprite cards, don't
Don't stand up properly.
If you're looking down at a steep angle right there they're tilted in
kind of a bat in a not sufficient way potentially it might be that
that's still fine and we'll have to play with it but I wanted to have
the ability to do something a little fancier they're potentially.
So we'll play with it a little more, but you can see that if we wanted
to do something like this, we could just leave it like that.
And that would be fine, right?
These, you can see that.
What we're getting here is now really.
Our only problem is with shadows, right?
That the alpha R Alpha stuff is is bad, right?
If we were to clip out.
Everything that had Alpha in it.
By setting the alpha Funk to get rid of it.
Then you can kind of see, we pretty much have no problems in it at
all, at that point, right?
But unfortunately, that you know what?
That's I've never done that test before you can see that are our
Sprites don't have perfect Alpha everywhere, right?
Those must have like 250, 4253, Alphas or whatever, but you can see
that we don't have any of those problems anymore.
And really, the only thing we
I have to fix this with a cup-like are rectangles are drawing right on
top of each other, so you get the Z fighting.
But other than that, we don't have any problems, right?
Are sorting is all now perfect.
And everything's good, right?
So really we just need to again, figure out sort of roughly what our
solution other problems going to be and how we're going to handle that
Alpha.
Because at the moment, we don't have a, we don't have anything any
solution at all for the alpha.
I wonder if it would be sufficient to just the game just works like
that.
I wonder.
Without doing anything else.
You just do it that way.
I wonder if the Sorting works properly because it works pretty well,
right.
If we went ahead and solve the alpha problem, which we have to do
either way, maybe that's just sufficient.
I don't know, it's an interesting question because it, I guess you
really don't need.
You just need to only the tiniest amount of Z overlap.
So if you just tilt the camera, just a little bit
You know, I don't know.
Maybe that's efficient.
It's an interesting question.
All right, anyway, we'll take a look at this next week and basically
what we're trying to do now is just again kind of converge on a good
solution for how we're going to do the Sprites and then we can move on
to dealing with our Alpha.
Because that's really the only visual artifact problem that will have
once we get the Sprites have lined up.
However we want them to be, we just had to figure out what a good
solution would be for our Alpha compositing.
And that might involve doing like something like Alpha to coverage.
It might involve doing something else.
I don't know.
So we'll have to think a little bit about that.
And think about how we want to solve that problem because, again, that
is the one trans like translucent or transparent objects.
Are the things that rasterize our pipelines have the very hardest time
with because of that Reliance on the Z buffer.
That's just how it goes.
So that's the thing, we get, everything else for free, we don't have
to the sword anymore.
Everything else is nice and clean through the entire pipeline, but you
still run into that that nasty bit of how you're going to deal with
with transparency and translucency.
So that's the one thing we're going to have to address.
All right?
I'm gonna go ahead and close down.
Thank you everyone for joining me, for another episode of handmade
hero.
It's been a pleasure coding with you.
As always, if you would like to follow along at home, you can always
pre-order the game on handmade hero dot-org and it comes with the
source code, so you can play around with it.
We also have the forums, you can go to ask questions a patreon page.
You can go to, to support the video series, schedule, bot the tweets,
the schedule, it you.
And at episode guide, where you can go to catch up on old episodes,
that's about it for this week.
I will be back next week, same time probably but check the
Tweetbot.
If you want to know for sure, until then have fun programming and I'll
see you on the internet.
Take it easy, buddy.