Start recording.
Hello everyone, and welcome to handmade hero in a tree today.
We are going to be finishing up a little bit of our debug edit code.
We got it working actually yesterday, but we are still using like old
guids.
We're using some old style stuff in our debug system from when we were
still exploring options.
And so we got some cleaning up to do to make sure like highlighting
works properly and then we probably want to also try to re-enable some
editing for other kinds of values.
Like we had anything in there for me.
Any twos and stuff, but I don't know if that's still enabled, so we
want to just kind of go through clean out the old debug ID system,
which we don't need any more.
We can just use the quiz now.
I believe and that should just be, that should be about it.
So,
Today is day, 253 and day.
253 comes after day 252.
So if you are following along at home with the source code, you want
to unpack day to 52s Source here because that's what I'm starting with
and you will be in a weird place if you start with different code than
that.
So yeah, if if I remember correctly coming through here with if we run
things,
Everything is now working properly.
We can edit our values in that sort of stuff.
I don't remember too much about what these deeper values are actually
supposed to do, but I think they just only move when somebody
actually, yeah, like we had like this, so you could set it to whether
you were the cameras following or whether it would only update when
when the hero kind of moved into a new area, this was not actually
code be overusing, but we use it for other tests debug value.
So that's all good.
And we also have this
Mode from the from a while.
Back that's just used for testing.
So we have a bunch of stuff in here and it looks like that's working.
Okay.
Now, so we should probably go ahead and and just sort of clean this
stuff up.
Get highlighting working for these again and also now, because we
decided to leave those squids as full strings.
What we probably want to do is clip so that when we print them out,
we're actually printing them out in some kind of a reasonable fashion.
Like, we
We want to actually cut it down to some, you know, some reasonable
amount of of some reasonable.
Like, we don't need all of this stuff on here, right?
We can just parse to the end of that.
So we want to do just a couple things like that and I think that's
basically it.
So we've got oh right?
I forgot.
We even did this little thing here where you can view and of these.
So we don't really know at the moment.
We actually I don't think ever went back and re-enable, the ability to
view bitmaps either.
I could be wrong about that.
I don't really know if we select an entity.
We don't see the bitmaps here anymore.
So that's also something that probably should be working.
And the fact that it's not working, suggest that maybe we introduced a
bug there somewhere.
At least I would assume we did.
Like I said, don't really know, but just assume so yeah.
So I think we're pretty good and
Don't really know why I'm still talking.
I think I'm still sort of hung up about the fact that there was guy in
a tree.
Anyway, here we go.
Let's go ahead and launch the editor and again like I said, I think
I'm just going to try to focus on cleaning up this code because I want
to sort of get it down to a nice place where we can sort of say that
the debug code is you know, reasonable and we're okay with it.
Looks like we're still building in release mode there which we don't
really need at the moment.
So I'm going to turn that off and just continue to build in debug
mode.
Just about bills.
Tend to be a little bit faster.
Usually that tends to be the case.
As you can kind of see there at, sped it up a bit after it's used to
building and everything's in the cache.
So let's go ahead and take a look here at
And handmade debug.
So we've already got this thing here.
That was start last /.
And start at, lash lash is just going to be like started last pipe,
really?
And then we could use that to clean up those names because we already
word sort of doing that before.
And then we decided we didn't really need to do it.
But it turns out we really probably should because we sort of want to
get rid of that bit.
So I now need to pass that when we're printing things, I think
possibly this maybe should be the default to be honest.
So
I think this should probably be like, you know, don't start at last
play for like, use entire Grid or something like this or print show
entire grid, something like that.
I don't know.
Let's, let's just say that.
That was the case.
And that way, just by default, we just assume that nobody wants to
print out that grid information.
Because why would they it doesn't seem to make any sense.
And so we'll see if we can make that work.
Why is that not working?
I know why it's because this is supposed to be a not we're trying to
say if it's not set to show entire grid then we scan for the end of
our little grid thing there.
And then we hopefully
There we go.
So now our names are what the actual variables are, which seems like a
good idea and now we just have to go through and make sure that when
we sort of mouse over these things, they actually highlight the reason
that they're not having right now, I believe it's just because we have
this extraneous.
Debug ID stuff.
There's potentially interesting reasons for having it.
so, I mean, I don't want to pretend that it was useless because the
idea behind the debug IDs is if we wanted to sort of have ways of
identifying sort of more
Are sort of more stuff.
And I think, the key thing that I that I kind of want to to consider
here is really the only part that I think we need to care about for
having debug IDs that are not just the grid, is really just when we do
those open, debug block, close, debug block things.
If that's supposed to refer to, like a particular entity or something,
then, you know, maybe that's important in some way, but
But even then, I don't know that it is because the, debug IDs for
editing purposes are really only important on that particular frame.
So, I don't even know if that makes any sense.
So, I'm not sure that we care really about these debug IDs at all.
So, I'm going to just exercise them for now.
And just assumed that, that was an experiment.
We just don't need to really keep anything from and wherever we were
using debug IDs before we can just use the grid right.
Which is or rather even not even the grid.
We can just use the debug element pointer because those debug element
pointers never go away.
We always keep a debug element for everything so we should be able to
do something more like that.
I think, let's give it a shot.
We'll see what happens.
So if I am to delete debug IDs entirely from the system, you can see
them here.
I'll go ahead and just ice that out.
So we don't care about this.
I don't also know.
I'm not sure what this is actually used for.
Completely honest with you.
So I may also just get rid of that temporarily just to see so it
because I don't really know why it's there and I'm not sure it should
be there.
So I'm going to get rid of this as well.
Like so and I don't know, debug you, I enabled.
Not sure what that's about.
We'll take a look at that as well at some point.
So let's recompile debug ID, so the debug hit stuff.
So I think for this again,
with, with, with this debug ID thing, what we can do there is probably
just
Well, honestly, you know, we could even save the debug ID only for
debug hit me if we wanted to, if we want to just keep that path
working the same way.
It was, we could just have debug IDs or strictly for that purpose.
They don't do anything else, I'm not sure if that's necessary or not.
It feels like the answer is probably not.
So I think what we could probably do is sadiebug IDs.
Maybe just aren't important and maybe we just always use
Well now you know what?
I'm just going to leave it.
I'm just gonna leave it because why not?
So I think all I really need to do is just get like I'll leave debug
ID in here and it can be used for people who external And all I'll do
the only place.
I'll actually
It is inside the debug system itself because those don't need to do
anything anymore other than use other than be used by the hit system.
So something like this, where we have a debug view, for example with a
debug ID that says what it's actually tracking we can just get rid of
that concept and use the debug element directly.
Now, the other thing we can do is everywhere, we would have generated
a debug ID for something, we can just generate a debug element.
Instead are we can just
Wrap the debug element in a debug ID and still use it, but I'm not
sure that there's any reason to do that.
it seems like just unnecessary complexity, so,
Maybe we'll just do that.
And of course at that point I am also not sure.
Yeah, you know what?
I keep saying we'll get rid of it and then I'm like, well do I really
need to get rid of it?
It seems like, after all that really, I can just leave it in there and
all I have to do is just use the debug element as the pointer from now
on.
I think that's it.
Because it seems like that just works.
I think that would just be fine.
So like for example, when we're tracking all this stuff with, you
know, what's selected and and taught values and all that stuff, I feel
like we can just I feel like the debug I systems probably fine maybe I
was overreacting, maybe it's actually reasonable, like all this stuff
would just work and when we do debug ID from grid, it would just you
know, do it like this and it would be fine.
So I think the only problem probably is when we're doing this, we
should just make sure which, which grid we're looking at here.
Looks like we never actually generate that value though.
So, let's just take a look.
I guess I'll be really need to see.
Is why look, what are we using for the debug IDs right now?
And why, you know, why isn't that sufficient?
So here's like, looks like we're never really building them.
Hmm.
All right.
Well, so maybe this will be a lot easier than I thought, to maybe that
whole system could stay in place.
Maybe it's totally reasonable.
And all we need to do is just go fix this one part where we're
printing it out.
Okay, so that's fine.
I'm down.
That I apologize.
Debug IDs are saying your extraneous but really you seem pretty sanely
designed and I don't think there's any reason to get rid of you
because it looks like you're doing a useful thing.
So let's see.
We need to track back to wherever we would actually be using this.
We've got the debug event to text thing here, so that's where we're
actually printing out our stuff.
And when we're doing our default interactions,
When we?
When we do this, we need, I assume the default interaction stuff does
wrap up.
Well, wouldn't it?
It would have to wrap up what the debug ID was.
So here, is that what we call debug draw that we passed the debug ID
in.
And so the question is, why is that debug event not matching up with
anything?
Because interaction is hot, should be returning to
True.
If we're actually, if this actually worked so there's debug draw
element again with the debug ID.
Let's take one more look here.
So here is a sort of accessing all the elements as we go down and get
looks like
The debug ID is just made from the link, so it's made from this.
Variable link here.
The thing that's inside the variable group, that's what it's actually
made from.
I don't see why that's a problem, though.
I mean that should be fine, right?
We made like,
We made the debug idea from that.
And when we actually come through here, it does work to toggle.
So we know the debug ID can't be completely wrong.
So the question is just Why aren't we getting any highlighting, right?
And I would assume that since debugged element is getting past this
debug ID here.
I don't understand why the why we're not seeing a difference in color
when we come through because here's like our is hot call for debug
draw event and
Can see here is that it's just testing to see whether that interaction
is hot or not, and I'm not sure why it wouldn't be.
Let's take a look to see if there's a reason why maybe the
interactions not getting set to hot properly.
Maybe there's something we're not doing in here that we should be
doing because you can see we do begin element, rectangle, default,
interaction and element.
So in here in theory that should be setting the hot interaction as
necessary, right?
At least I believe so.
So let's take a look.
So element interaction.
Yeah, on and element, here we go with end element, right?
This does whatever it does here.
Yeah.
So this if it's in the rectangle the next hot interaction equal-sized
interaction.
Right?
That's for scalable things.
We've got next time.
Interaction equals element interaction, which is the the default one.
If we're inside the bounds of the element
And that all just seems like it should work because I can't see why it
wouldn't.
If we are able to click, you would think that it would be able to
highlight properly and it doesn't.
But that doesn't really make sense.
So, let me just check interaction is hot and make sure that there
isn't something about that.
That I don't understand.
So, let's go ahead and go to interaction is hot and just see
So interaction is hot goes to see whether to interactions are equal,
the one in the debug State and the one that we're testing which is
what you would expect it.
Test to see if the to debug IDs are equal, the types of interactions
are equal.
And whether A and B are generically the same is that just like, is the
generic.
I think that just is is a different type.
That's just the test.
That one value part of it, right?
Let's verify that.
That's just generic is just a way of comparing two things for
equivalence when we don't really know which one we're talking about,
right?
So all that is is, is let's see here.
Where is it?
Where is it interaction?
It's just testing like, basically all of these, right?
So yeah, I don't know why that would be busted.
So I'm going to have to step through that.
I think I can't think of any way not to to be honest because it just
seems like that always actually pretty reasonable.
So if I go here, that'd be the first one.
That I would come across.
And so I'm just going to set a breakpoint now live as it's running to
sort of figure out when it does interaction is hot.
I just want to take a look at to see why it's not considering itself
hot, right?
So let's see here, and let's see if this is the correct one.
First of all, this is
Stored event Loop stored event.
There's the event.
It is global rendering type.
That does sound like a reasonable one.
That would have been first, right?
So let's take a look and see what we ended up with here in interaction
is hot.
So we test interactions are equal, we get 0, which is
We expect because it's obviously not drawing as hot.
Let's took a look at A and B and C.
What we see here, a is the hot interaction.
So this is the hot interaction and the values of these.
I look basically the same up here, right?
Those are the same pointers both of these totally the same pointer.
So, the ID should compare the same.
They are both Auto modified variable requests.
So the only difference is the generic is different and I'm not sure
why the generic is different.
So I'm going to go ahead and take a look.
It's probably because the story event is perhaps getting used rather
than the element.
So it's the hot, I think, probably what's happening, right?
Is we record the values over time and we're probably
Bleep.
Talking about the only the latest value instead of talking about all
values because we only care about the element being hot.
Not a particular instance of a record.
Now, I particularly like frames value for that.
So I think that must be the only problem that we have.
So that's my suspicion.
I'm going to see if I'm correct about that.
So let's take a look.
So that's going to be in debug bra.
Element actually over here.
So in debug draw element, we passed the debug ID in.
So it's going to be created right here and if it's created from the
link, it feels like the link should be correct though, right?
Because that should be stable the entire time there.
Should, it should not be recreating the link over and over and over
again because it was we'd be seeing the tree change.
No.
So that seems not quite logical to me.
I can't say I have any idea.
Why that would be true.
Hmm.
Let's check this one more time.
Oops, didn't quite need to go there yet.
So, Global rendering type is, in fact, the one we were talking about.
And what I would like to do here is, I'd like to just go ahead and
stop on this multiple times to see if the debug ID itself changes,
right?
And so, what I'm going to do here is I'm just going to
Going to oops not that.
I'm going to open up stored event, I'm sorry not start event.
I'm gonna open up.
Debug State hot interaction.
And I just want to see if this value.
In fact, I guess I can just even just look at one specific value
because I only care about generic.
So I'm just going to look at that value and I want to see if over time
that value is changing for some reason.
So if I come in here and I'm now clearly over this one, I want to see
what I get in here.
So it is changing every time.
So now I'm going to walk back up the chain a little bit and I want to
see why that's happening.
So in draw main menu, where I make the debug ID to begin with, I would
like to know.
I want to see what I want to verify.
That that's happening here as well, right?
So yeah, let's stop in here.
Let's take a look at debug ID.
So what we should here, see here.
Is that a deal?
I d.
Oh wait.
Wait wait, wait.
Wait.
Debug ideas, not where generic comes from, right, right?
so, when we actually go through here,
And draw the value.
Where's that at?
I scrolled right by you, didn't I?
Sorry man in the tree right, there we go.
So when we come through here, when we make the item interaction, this
is actually the problem.
So that is the problem.
I for some reason, forgot, I was like, oh, right the debug idea was
wrong.
No, no.
The debug idea was right.
It was the generic that was wrong.
So it's this.
And so this has to be, we don't actually want this to be the event
value because that's changed over time.
We want this to be the
And value, right?
And so what has to happen is the element that we're talking about.
When we call debug draw event, we want to know what that one actually
is, so that we can use it and talk about it.
So that was really all that that had to happen.
So it was exactly what I thought it was.
I just tricked myself into not seeing it.
So, this is like, the element that we're in, and so, then when we come
here, we can just say, like, oh, it's in element, right?
Like that.
So now we have to take a look at anywhere that we might do a draw
event.
And yeah, that's true.
We would have to change event interaction.
We need this to be like element interaction.
Oops.
And then when this person calls, we need to pass what?
That element actually was.
So then event interaction, we could still leave a round, although it's
unclear that we ever actually want to have that happen.
I guess I should check to see if anyone else is calling it.
Somebody is calling it.
Just to tear off a bitmap for some reason.
All right, fine.
I'm going to still change that to an element interaction.
Cuz I think that's usually what we actually want, that makes sense.
So event interaction.
I think we're just going to say that that is not a thing.
Actually and it's only element interactions at the moment.
And maybe that's like something we would that I'm missing why we might
want something else, but for the moment I think we only want to talk
about interactions that happen for an element and then which one of
those you're operating on is going to be picked out for you based on
the situation because otherwise you could never edit element.
You're always like targeting an element that's older or something.
Right?
So yeah.
So
And interactions.
That's all fine.
So now, this is just going to be like, you know, element
Element like that and and that should be fine.
All right.
So in here, when we're checking the hot interaction for the type, this
would have to be an element.
And I don't really remember the Ridiculousness.
It's in here for storing these guys, it's pretty crazy if I remember
correctly because we've got a store all kinds of things.
So yeah, in here we have like most recent event that that is a pointer
chain for you, right there.
Sorry, there we go.
Cross cannot access the file because it would be all right event.
And so to get the when we do a toggle value, presumably we're talking
about the most recent one, right?
I mean, I guess, I don't know that we always want the most recent one,
but it seems like what we would normally do.
And same here.
Okay, so I think that is all we really needed in theory, anyway.
Of course, it looks like maybe event doesn't always have to be that.
Like this debug interaction might not actually have one of these, I
don't really know.
So it assumes up front that we
Yeah, we would need to say, you know, if this thing was actually
there, then do it.
Otherwise, you know, we don't actually want to try and grab that out
because we don't know if we even have that kind of an interaction, I
guess.
All right.
So that's good.
Now at least that's working properly and I don't know if there was
also this thing and I don't know if we can drag, it looks like that
Dragon is not working either.
So I would like to I thought we had some stuff for that.
Yeah like this thing right here.
So what we should probably do here is just to stem it Systema.
Sighs systematized we
Already like fixed this thing and you can see how it works here,
right?
You do this edit event, edit event grid nonsense, right?
So we probably don't want to have that all over the place, so we
probably just want to do something like, you know, debug edit Event
Event.
So we just, you know, we know that thing is going to get edited and
then it creates that that edit operation for it and we could do that.
You know, we could even do that sort of like that, you know, at the
after we do the toggle value for the event.
So that anyone else who's in here, we don't have to write it the same
way or maybe we'll call this like debug Mark edited event.
Like that.
So yeah.
Let's go ahead and put this in here.
Debug Mark, edited event, you know what edited only has like one t,
pretty sure about that.
So if I'm going to mark one of these, I just need to have the event
itself.
It looks like that's actually it, right?
Oh.
And the debug state.
And I think I know why.
The indentations not working there.
Nobody knows, but nobody cares.
So that's all good and then if we drag a value we probably want to
edit the value and we could actually make this a little safer by
saying like oh if you pass it annul we just won't do anything which is
also good.
Yeah.
And what are you complaining about?
Left of original grid.
Must Point get them at a venture far not found.
Yeah.
Well you know why?
That's because the pre deck needs to be right there.
Mark, edited Valley events, rather, you stick a debug state.
And that's it.
So now I think this probably work, if I turn on the debug camera, I
should be able to like
Zoom around.
Right so that's pretty good.
So that's all fine.
So now we can edit those values live and that's like suppose good.
I mean, who knows.
So all of that stuff works good now and I guess technically to we
could take a look to see whether we can re-enable some of the other.
Oh my God, I always forget that that's going to happen when I click on
that.
But that's exactly what happens when I click on that.
all right, so yeah, turns out
This dude is like got a lot of heads coming up all over the place that
was not my intention so I sorry about the heads that they're just
they're just kind of doing their thing.
Okay, so I think that is all I really want to do with that.
What we should probably focus on now is actually getting some of these
other things working properly.
So, let's I, I want to see where we're at with that are values the
tear off values.
I don't really care too much about them, but I just want to see where
where they why they are currently disabled and just see if there's
anything in particular.
So here's here's an example of where the tear value stuff happens.
I don't know if this actually works.
I don't even remember how terrible he was working.
The first place.
Is it right Mouse button?
I think possibly
I've no idea none whatsoever but I'm going to go ahead and re-enable
it and just see what happens because I mean I don't have anything
better to do so there we go.
So if I want to do at are value, it looks like
it looks like what happened here was.
There's a hot
And that happens.
Well you know what, I should probably look to see what we're storing
for tear values.
Let's see.
Debug interaction tear value and tear value.
It's an element interaction.
So that the value parameter is is a debug element.
And that I don't know if that helps us or not.
Probably not, let's find out.
yeah, so if we tear off a debug element,
That doesn't really help because tearing off a debug element.
Doesn't tell us what the tree looked like, at that point.
So really what we want to tear off at that point, if we're going to
process, something that was torn off.
It would have to be one of those links.
Right.
We need to be a link interaction and I don't know if we get the link
down here, we don't really I guess.
But that's where that would have to happen.
Looks like that's the only place that that happens.
Yeah, so I don't think we want this here on the bitmap anyway, that
doesn't seem like a particularly useful thing to do anyway so I don't
know what it should be.
I have no idea what the default interaction should be.
So I'm just going to leave that blank for now.
And then I'm going to go ahead and well, you know what, you can just
pass the item interaction, which I mean, it's automatically variable,
which is whatever it's going to do, right?
And then in here,
This chair interaction.
I'm going to actually grab that and I'm going to move that down for
when we're doing the main menu.
And so in the main menu, what I would say is that when we do this item
interaction here,
that I am interaction is built off the
off the link.
Right?
So it's a toggle expansion, it's built off the link.
And so I think what I would want to do is say, okay, if
If you do at are expansion, that are Terror.
Yeah.
if you do a toggle expansion,
Then it's always doing this thing but the view, right?
But if we try to do a tear off, what I want to do is I want to make
sure that the parameter to that or what we would tear off, what we
would tear off.
I want to be to me.
What we would tear off.
I want to be a link and so the hot interaction variable there.
I need to figure out some way.
That that could be set to the tree.
So let's take a look see here.
I want debug state so you can see here.
We've got debug interactions stacked up.
These would have they would never have a debug link.
So how what is actually getting passed for that when we're going down
here?
So we've got the toggle expansion and we pass the ID.
So it's just an idea, it doesn't take any additional information.
I feel like we would want that to be a link interaction because that's
what we're actually hovering over at that time is a link, right?
So and in either case, you sort of, there is a link to be had
If that makes sense.
So it seems like we want some way of having that that link get pushed
on there.
And perhaps I'm going to go ahead and see where that alt interaction.
Thing happens.
How do we set up?
We set that up.
Alt you.
I
so I think what I want to do is I think I want to just actually change
the way this is being handled so that alt UI is just set and then we
we don't handle the change in interaction.
Here we handle the change in interaction up top, right?
So we would say like where we're actually doing the processing so we
would do something like all you.
I would come in here and then when we do debug
When we actually do our debug processing before we start we set all UI
to that value.
So you know debug interact in here, right before we actually do
anything else.
We like set that stuff up so we just say like oh yeah all you I
Is set based on whatever happened with the right Mouse button, that
makes sense and and then we don't have that happening anywhere else,
right?
So
See.
Where is that actually used.
Begin interact if alt you I set the only place.
Yeah so I'm just going to get rid of that.
Entirely.
And I think I can get rid of it here, too.
so all you, I input Mouse buttons ended down
Don't care about that.
I don't care about this.
Alright, so now, I think we're sort of where we need to be.
So if we do a terror value then, what we need to do is create one of
those variable groups, right?
So, we've got handmade debug dots groupie, we've got ad or something
like, debug ad group.
I remember.
What it's called.
Add tree.
So we need to do both of these.
So, we've got a dead tree, add tree.
Looks like it would still work.
So we just need to do.
See here.
We just need to do.
However, you add things to a group or create a new group, rather.
No, where is it?
It should not be this hard.
There it is.
Create variable group is what I actually wanted.
So create variable group.
Like so returns a debug variable Group, which is, you know, pretty
sensical if you ask me, and then we've got the debug state, which is
fine.
We have what we're going to name it and I don't really know what we're
gonna name it.
So I'll just call it for the moment, I guess, you know?
Name.
Equals something.
So if I was to do that, then I can just pass the name temporarily and
I can say that whatever the size of the name is is what we pass.
And we'll figure out what to name it in a second I guess because I'm
not sure.
So then we will add an element to the group, right?
Add element to group and we need to, well, actually, I guess what.
We need to do here is let's just do that.
What we really want to do here is actually clone, right?
So what I really want to do is I want to do like cologne
Variable group.
You know what I'm saying?
So that's probably going to be something that I write right now.
Then we would add the tree using the route group that we made and then
I don't really know if there's anything else that we actually need to
do.
I don't know why we wouldn't be passing, why would we pass?
Like why wouldn't we just pass the mouse key right here?
I don't know why.
So I'm just going to do that.
That seems like the most logical thing to do and then
We're going to create a move operation.
So let's see where we're at with this create variable group,
identifier, not found because these are all below here.
I suppose create variable group.
There we go.
So if that's true.
I probably need to sort of copy these in here.
So create variable group.
Go.
We'll have our clone variable group.
and yeah, so that would take
first thing to clone from,
Seems like it.
And that's, that's about it.
Pig.
All right, so we don't really care about this just yet.
So I'm going to go ahead and pause that whole situation.
I'm going to run this and see because I don't actually know.
We're going to have to figure out a way to actually test the fact that
we even can clone.
So the idea is we're going to right-click on this thing and move it
over, right?
And so to do that, what I want to do is say, oh okay, when we're doing
debug draw event,
if we wanted to have or actually I guess it's actually in here when
we're doing this interaction here where we do toggle expansion, what
we can do is say like oh actually you know what if
We're using the alternate UI for this thing.
Then what we actually want to do is instead of item.
Interaction being what this one is.
We'll do a different one.
That's actually going to be.
Tear value.
It really should be called territory or something like that, but
that's beside the point.
So then we just overwrite the item interaction and then we still use
it right?
And so debug ID interaction it's actually going to be a debug link
interaction and we're going to pass the link that we are and that is
what I actually was trying to set us up for to do here.
So in here this would be like oh we're passing, you know?
One of those.
And so when we have like debug ID, interaction or whatever,
We can just make one of these.
Oops.
And that's all I was trying to do.
Is it what is it called?
Its debug like variable link.
Debug variable link.
and so if we do one of those, then when we do the tear value now, are
the actual value that we get,
So when we do this, the actual value that we get in here, as the
parameter is the the group that we would want to clone now, we don't
actually have to do that just quite yet because we should be able to
get this working without actually cloning the tree first.
But I want to, I got to get that part to work.
So, let me take a look at Tara value here, and let me set a break
point, so I can do to me.
Am I set a breakpoint so I can see if we ever successfully do it.
And you can see, we're not actually getting any tearing there.
So now I'm going to check to see whether we actually ever go through
this path, so they all uipath and we do.
So, you can see a setting this thing to tear value here.
And then we go through and set that as the default interaction
potentially.
Let's find out if that actually happens.
So it looks like the problem is actually not that there's anything
wrong here.
It's that we're not.
Oh, you know what?
I forgot.
We never really implemented.
It any kind of alternate, any kind, of course, clicking for it.
So it's actually you hold down the right button and then click the
left button.
So it does work.
That was so weird.
You I think so it is working the way.
To work, so that's good.
So yeah, so now I can drag out new ones of these which is good.
And so now if I just clone that tree I should be able to do what I
wanted to do before with the tree cloning right now.
What I don't know is whether that should be drawing a name or not.
I would have thought that it would but it might be that we never draw
the initial name because you know, like this guy doesn't have an
official name for example.
And so we'll have to just go double-check how that's supposed to work
as we're cleaning this out.
All right.
So what we actually want to do here is say okay, well there's actually
a thing called clone variable group as well.
And clone variable group, we'll just do whatever create variable
group, where is that?
Actually create variable group.
There we go.
So if we have internal,
Debug variable group.
And we say clone variable
Group.
What I do not know.
Is that any of this stuff works?
So let's just go take a look because we got a page it back into the
brain, right?
So let's see.
We've got debug
variable link.
So debug variable group is literally just a title and a linked list
and a debug variable link is like one Link in that chain.
so we might even say that we always clone groups as opposed to
individual values, but I don't know,
Let's just let's just see what we want to do.
So, excuse me, so what we would do, if we pass the variable link here,
if we pass instead of a group,
I guess we would need to know whether we were supposed to Cologne.
Yeah, I'm just not I'm not totally sure.
Whether we would always be cloning a group, whether it's clone
individual value.
So if we pass like I guess if we just passed a value which is be
about.
So I guess, you know, this is just the source, right?
And we would do something like,
Well.
Probably want to do this for cursive like debug variable link.
Dest equals add element to group.
And we do like, whatever the desk group is.
And then we'd add the source.
So, we'd add an element.
and then we would say if the source itself was a group
Then what we would want to do, is create a new group.
To hold those.
And we would just have it point to the exact same stuff, right?
So whatever the source is information was and right, so it's literally
just
Whatever the source has children, dot name length is and the sources
children dot name are.
That's the subgroup.
And then we would just do a for I Loop here through all of the
children that it actually has and adding them to the subgroup.
So I guess it's actually clone variable link is this function it would
take what the group is.
And then we are clone variable group call would actually create a
group and then call this for that it into that group.
So we would just say all right we got the subgroup here.
We're going to say Source children.
Hmm.
Was it first?
Whereas it should be like a first next kind of thing.
Sentinel
Sentinel next.
So we would just say, Okay, debug variable link child equals the
Sentinels.
Next pointer, know why I have not put arrows on this.
Okay, we would say as long as the child is not equal to the Sentinel
we're good.
And then we just chase the next pointer the whole time.
We clone.
Because we care.
That child and off we go.
So then
We return, the link, I guess there is no real reason to have this
thing.
Well, I guess because, yeah, we can't just create this freestanding.
All right, so that's fine.
It's not exactly.
Probably, if not probably how I would
Preferred it precisely but it's not really any real reason to change
it.
So I'll leave it like this for now.
So that would clone one of these variable links and return it.
And then we could also do the same thing.
For clone variable group.
And in that case we would just say like okay for cloning from one of
these then we need to create a variable group.
We don't know what the name is.
Maybe we'll just call it cloned.
So there's a name, it's cloned.
We probably want to push that string on so that if we go across
reloads it doesn't pose a problem.
So I would probably want to do a push string.
For this actually.
Right where we would say like okay, debug State debugger Arena.
You know, go ahead and save that name.
So that we don't have a constant string that would get unloaded with
the dll or anything like that.
Again, that's just a support the hot code reloading.
And after I create that variable group, then I will close call clone
variable link and I'll just clone the link that were passed into that
group.
It is true that does not take 0 parameters.
So we would need to pass the debug State and then the link that we
actually want is the is the actual parameter to our hot interaction.
So it'd be hot interaction, dot link.
Oh, not hot interaction, actually just regular interaction, right?
Yeah.
I don't want to group connector for three from dear a link to debug
element that seems fair.
So basically what that's saying is that when we clone a variable link,
we need to pass the element, which is fine because I believe it just
has an element in it, right?
Yeah.
All right, so I don't know if this works so that did not work at all.
What did that?
Just say, hold on a second.
Show me your tube.
Show me that message again.
Access violation.
Reading location element.
Okay.
So, that did not work well at all to say, the
Next.
Oh I know why because we do all these, add two groups but we never
actually copied the data for the variable.
So that's kind of stupid, right?
So we probably want to do that.
That was a mistake, right?
So we get back that variable link but it doesn't actually have
Well, no, that's not true.
It should have had some stuff in it, right?
It should have copied because all that debug like, does is just it
only contains a pointer to the element, so that actually should have
been fine.
I would think, let's find out debug, it's variable link.
So, it just has the point to the elements.
So I feel like that should just work, right?
That should just work.
We clone the element, everything's fine.
So it would only be if the element pointer was bogus which I suppose
it could be.
I guess I should verify that.
When we do our Terror value that it's actually the correct pointer
here.
We also don't care about that string anymore.
So let's see if we do a clone very group on the hot interaction link.
So does that actually what gets set timer action, tear value?
It does we pass an actual debug link, right?
And that is a debug variable.
Link.
Yeah, so I don't know.
All right, so let's take a little bit closer.
Look here.
Excuse me, by the way, I can still hear helicopters outside.
So I'm assuming the guy in the tree is still in the tree.
And I guess I'm almost up time because we started at 20.
So I'm just going to see if I can quick, do this, and then and then
we'll stop.
All right, so let's do clone variable group.
And I wanted to see what ends up happening here.
So, if we do this I want to see what we ended up with four result.
So here is the variable group.
It's got the name, we gave it.
Here's the Sentinel and you know, it's got some stuff in it.
And it looks like element is always zero.
So why is that?
Because I don't think those are all.
They don't have children or Elements which doesn't make a lot of
sense.
So the source has a children pointer there and then the children
Oh, whoops, because that's the Sentinel.
No, it's not.
Never mind.
So there's essential there.
Look at the next pointer.
So that's got an element pointer.
So, why is our elements?
So I just messed up the copy, that's the only problem.
So let's take a look.
We jump in here.
Push the string we call create variable group that does what it does?
We clone our variable link.
So we come in here and we want to add this element.
Huh.
Oh wait, but that's fine.
That part's actually fine.
So this is
this is totally fine because when we add an element and there is no
element, that's actually fine.
It just creates a thing.
That has two nulls.
It looks at their Source children.
There are secretes the subgroup it just never sets the subgroup,
that's the problem.
So when we do clone variable link,
I'm sorry clone variable yeah but variable link then in here that
subgroup it should actually be deaf children.
Is where that subgroup gets assigned, right?
And so
that is actually what we should have been doing this whole time.
I think that's at least problem, eh.
We'll see about problem, B's C's and D's.
So now if we grab simulation out here, now we've got the ability to
sort of like grab out parts of this.
I assume we can grab out individual pieces.
Yeah.
And so now we're pretty close.
I mean that's pretty great actually because if you think about how
many things this is now handling, it's actually storing UI state for
all of these as well.
Totally separately which is kind of cool and without ever actually
Using any more space than it would need to.
Because if you never actually touch one, it never stores any UI for
it.
So that's kind of nice as well.
And it looks like everything is working properly.
So for example, if I wanted, you know, I could drag out this entity
and leave this entity getting viewed here, right?
Don't know why.
It doesn't have a little.
I'm not sure I understand when it gets like these guys.
Don't have there with those little.
I guess they do have them.
You can't see them, we got to, we got to work on our rendering here, a
little bit, right?
So, yeah, we can, like, drag out something and all of this stuff works
properly.
So we really just need to clean up.
Rendering and I don't know why bitmaps networks.
We should look at that as well.
I think we're in good shape because now we can make these things
happen to where we like, you know,
Where are we?
You know, we can like pin things and places.
If we want like a particular heads-up thing to be happening so that we
don't need to like always go down.
Like if we always know that we're working on something in particular,
you know, we just want a particular value like,
You know like this or whatever to be available to us, we can always
get it right?
And that's kind of nice and look the Highlight works properly, right?
It doesn't highlight this guy instead of this guy even though you know
soon as its source of this is pretty good.
I'd say we're I say we're pretty good shape.
I say we're handling most of our things properly so now we just got to
work on a rendering.
We got a drawer, our profile in here.
We've got to draw this stuff a little bit better.
Make it not look so janky
And I think we're in good.
We're good shape here.
You happy about that.
All right, we will go to the most briefest of brief qas here.
Since we only have a few minutes left started pretty late today.
Thank you diabetics 17 for telling me.
I figured the dubis up in the tree gets, I can hear the helicopters,
but as I see the guy, I actually thought it was a binary tree and that
he would be on the ground if he gets to the leaves.
I see.
No questions.
We can we can turn in
Dude, in basement one.
What is the debug code to other code ratio?
Now, you know, it's probably not since we since we the amount of time
spent on the debug code is pretty high.
And that's because I decided to do the debug code as the thing to
like, go through a bunch of Explorations and pick one, right?
so it took a lot of time compared to the other code and that was sort
of on purpose but as to how much coded actually is
I don't know if it's that much code total compared to everything else.
I don't really know how to make this thing do that.
So if that's
I don't know what that's telling us but that's telling us something.
And then if I say handmade like debug dot star,
Does that work?
and there's interface as well, so maybe can I do
Okay that all right so it's 2,200 lines of a 1600.
I mean 16 16 thousand line program
So, it's an eight, an eighth of the code.
I think it took significantly more than eighth of the time if that
makes sense.
Let's see.
What happens if you try to modify a dynamic variable, like the player
position?
So the problem with that right now is, I don't think we have any
editors for V, 2 variables for vectors.
Otherwise, I think it would just move the player because it's just
over writing the value.
I don't actually know if there are any values in here.
Well, we could see, I don't know, let me find out.
So, if I go into the game and I look at the simulation in a day, if I
was to take facing direction and change it,
Could see what happens there.
Oh wait.
I have to select them first.
Yeah, so I think you can just edit any values now at this point,
right?
Like that just works.
So I don't know what else we would do here necessarily but
I don't think walkable height does anything.
So, the problem is mostly we haven't written any editors for these
like we need a little Vector editor or something, but otherwise it's
fine.
so,
in Clone variable group, size of name - one, should this be the string
length?
Not the size of pointer minus one.
So, let me see what?
You're talking about.
Oh, whoops.
Yeah, you are correct.
We didn't fix this code from before.
I guess there's no, it'd be nice.
If there was a way to get back, how much it pushed on, but
unfortunately, unfortunately, we didn't do that, right?
Because it's kind of wasteful to call this again, because we don't, we
already would have known that.
Right?
Because it had to push the string on in the first place.
Every so often we get that texture.
Download problem.
I'm hoping that we can fix that like that when the textures don't want
to don't download when we do a run, I'm hoping that if we change to
doing just a single thread, since it turns out Nvidia doesn't actually
optimize the multiple threads.
More on that later, Juan's been doing some research on this.
So yeah, doesn't we can't actually see any results of that obviously
because at the moment we're not actually doing anything that would
show that name but you are correct.
You are correct.
You just can't tell because at the moment we're not using it, but if
we were to use it it would have happened.
All right.
All right, folks, I'm going to wrap it up.
Dude.
and,
Close.
All right.
Thank you everyone for joining me, for another episode of handmade
here.
It's been a pleasure coding with you.
As always, if you want to follow along with the source code at home,
you can always pre-order the game and it comes with a source code.
So you can do just that if you want to ask questions, we have a forum
site, you can go to to ask those questions.
We also have patreon page, you can subscribe to if you want for 30
series and a tweet bot, which treats the schedule at you if you want
to catch a stream live, and if you do want to,
If the stream live will be back here at 5:00 p.m.
tomorrow pacific daylight time, assuming there is no man in the tree
again tomorrow.
Otherwise maybe we'll just have to call it a day because we all want
to watch The Man in the tree.
But tomorrow, I think we will probably want to start cleaning up our
drawing of stuff so maybe we will go fix sort of the the drawing of
those things.
So they look a little nicer and are a little more interactable and
then the other thing we can do is start working on that profile.
L've you?
I'd like to get that working so now that we sort of have the debug
infrastructure I think settled down to the point where it's like, this
is what it should be.
We can start to go through that code and just clean up the actual
implementation parts.
Are, you know, sort of very zico dish.
You know like that little nub that used for moving is super crappy,
right?
So so we'll just think of think about that a little bit and just clean
that stuff up and then we can finally have some nice debug code and be
done with it.
I think don't know if there's really anything else we need their maybe
diagramming, we could add a little diagramming support but I don't
know.
That's that's probably it.
Thanks very much for joining me.
I'll see you guys tomorrow.
5:00 p.m.
Pacific Daylight time until then.
Then have fun programming and I will see you guys on the internet.
I'm going to go watch the guy in the tree.
Take it easy, everyone.