Okay, hello everyone, and welcome to handmade hero.
The show we go to complete game live on stream.
We are in the middle of doing some, debug code stuff and I think we
kind of got to a pretty good place with the debug code last week.
And so now we kind of just need to start doing a little work on making
the interface stuff play well with the fact that the data like all of
the data is buffered.
So there's a bunch of stuff that we kind of like you know left to the
I'd as we sort of move things around to make it nice and concise.
So that you could put stuff in sort of the debug buffers and have that
display as data.
That's all nice now.
Well certainly nicer but we don't really have any way of interacting
with that stuff.
The way that we used to because we kind of broke that code as we were
doing the changes.
And so what I'd like to look at today as I'd like to look how look at
like how to like now go through and clean up our interface path.
Like we clean up there are data path so that we can start to get all
of those features, kind of unified and playing nicely with each other.
Now that we sort of have an idea of what that looks like.
Again today is day 2 12, so if you would like to follow along with the
code, we do today at home, and you preorder the game on handmade her
dot-org, you can go ahead and unpack that into a directory because
that is the code that I am going to start with today.
So, if you start with the same code, we will be in sync.
Like the band, like the Backstreet, Boys.
But different.
All right.
So, here's where we left things on Friday.
You can see that actually the stuff that we wanted to do is working.
You can highlight entities and print out information.
That information goes into the debug buffers and then kind of gets
picked up later by the collation code.
So it doesn't actually have to exist for a long period of time.
It doesn't have to exist.
Even at the end of the frame, it's something that can just kind of be
captured and played with, but things that are interactable such as
like, expandable things or like in this case, you know, we got this
sort of concept here.
But sort of a thing that gets like, dragged out, right?
You can see that.
There's there's a lot of kind of janky Enos there and we also have
some things like, you know, while it's highlighting its there and as I
move away, it's not, which might be kind of understandable, but we
sort of have this, you know, just a number of problems there were
like, okay, so maybe we need to be able to click on something and we
need to be able to store the information about that thing a little bit
better.
There's all sorts of things that we kind of need to start doing it and
having a more coherent plan for, so that's what I'd like to start out
doing.
Maybe we'll just start out with.
Something very simple like starting to get just debug you, I
interactions in in general like we had that sort of radial menu and we
have you know sort of these ideas interactions maybe we'll try to sort
of get those unified so that we can use them in the game as well.
And then from there, I think we have a little bit of work to do.
looking at how we actually,
Talk about what a debug element is in terms of its ID and that's
important for storing.
The information about how it's being viewed and that stuff like, you
know, like this kind of thing where I'm doing this sort of pull out
and those sorts of things, right?
Okay, so the first thing that I'm going to just take a look at here
or, you know, bring to your attention, right?
Is the extreme Jank Enos of that selection process, that was going on
there, right?
So if you imagine like, you know, we've kind of got this working in
we, you know, some of it is pretty good but you can kind of see that
this stuff is really pretty random and janky at this point because in
a real scenario if you imagine when we actually go to try and use
this, the obvious thing that I'm going to want to do is I'm going to
want to select one of these
He's or something.
And then I'm going to want to go over here and interact with it.
But just by the nature of how it works, right?
I've kind of got the situation where I suffer over it and it shows the
thing.
And then when I, if I was to go over here, to try and react with
whatever it was, it would go away because I'm no longer hovering over
it, right?
So at the very least we need to start having things like the ability
to like click and select something, you know, so that's, you know,
something we definitely would want to do.
But if you think about what happens, there we have a few more problems
even deeper than that.
And even deeper than that,
That is just that action, that activity, even of itself, right now, it
conflicts, with any selection, that I might do for the actual system,
right?
So, in here, like that, little nub is a selectable nub.
You'll notice that when I select the nub, now, technically I'm
highlighting both the tree and the nub, right?
So there's no Concept in the system of what.
Like, you know, the fact that both the debug system and the game, now
have things that might want to be part of a, debug UI interaction and
that's not going to fly, right?
What's going to happen if we let that stand?
Is that as I try to interact with things in here, I will be silently
selecting like entities underneath and ruining whatever it was that I
was trying to work on.
So we need the debug system in the game to have a unified
understanding of what a debug interaction is and who is actually doing
stuff with it.
And in addition to that, we need to do a thing where we can have that
be as unintrusive.
Like, we need that to be as transparent to the game as possible
because we don't want all the code, you know, all of the
The code in the game to get complexified by like, inserting code into
it.
That's just for dealing with the debug system.
So we, you know, ideally we want as much complexity as we can in that
system to live inside the debug system itself and as little of the
complexity as possible to live on the side of the game.
So that it's easy for the game to sort of expose new things that might
get clicked on, or that might get selected for debugging purposes
without having to like complexify the code.
That's being debugged because the last thing we want to do is
Is export complexity from the debug system out into the game, because
the debug system is only supposed to be for debugging.
It should be easy as easy as possible to use.
so, if we take a look,
It where this is actually happening.
Right in handmade hero dot CPP.
We have this thing here where we sort of have, like begin data block
hot entity.
We can see that this code right here is the code that like, does the
picking, you know, we Loop over the volumes for the, you know, we Loop
over the, the Collision volumes for a given entity.
And then we look at, you know, whether the mouse is over them or
whatever.
Now, what we want to do here, ideally is have some way that this would
interact with our debug system and
we can see like when we look at this code, right?
Is that it probably wouldn't be very difficult for us to just do
something that said like okay when we're going to begin this data
block, or when we're going to push this data block, you could imagine
something probably pretty straightforward which was just some way of
asking the debug system.
You know, like, hey should I push this data block or not right?
Or maybe it's a speculative push or something like that.
You know, you could imagine ways in which this would work.
All of this stuff goes into this data, block right?
You can see it happening there.
and one thing that I could do,
Is just make that data block somehow magically predicated itself on
one of these interaction things, right?
So that's the first thing that I'm going to look at as an option
because ideally since we know that like, this is the minimum that we
have to do either, you know, and this, you know, maybe in the future,
we can get this down to something even swankier where, we're just like
debug Auto data block.
And we say something, you know, like this.
Right.
We might be able to do something like that.
Using the meta programming stuff that we wrote if we wanted to because
all of this stuff, right?
Could be automatically determined from there.
So we know that we might be able to get it down to a much simpler
thing in terms of us not having to specify all the values.
But the only thing that really would be different there is that the
you know, the sort of meta program knows where all the values are and
that's why we don't have to do it but it would still get sort of
pushed in the exact same way.
So just be this code automatically generated.
So basically we know that this code is what's going to run for sure.
And we could simplify it down quite nice with the meta program if you
wanted to.
So, that's good.
So all we need to think about now, is, how do we simplify the fact
that it is an interaction that might involve like the concept of
selecting something or something like this, right?
So the other thing that I want to point out to you is this occurs this
exporting of the data right now does exporting the data occurs inside
the thing that selects The Entity, right?
And the fact that it occurs inside the thing, that selects The Entity
means that if the entity were not being hovered,
This data would not be exported now, that's not necessarily a problem
because the debug system could keep us a copy of it.
If it wanted to keep displaying it, we could do that.
It wouldn't be particularly difficult.
But the problem with that is it means that once you're no longer
hovering over the entity, the data would no longer update, right?
Because this is what actually sends the data to the debug system and
so if we don't have this getting called every frame, then the debug
system will not know of you know if these things change like let's say
the entities moving this p-value will change every frame.
umm, but if we only
When we were hovering then if you like clicked on it, select it as an
entity that you want to view for a while.
And it shows up in a window on the side when you then stop hovering
over that entity the P would no longer update, right?
And neither would anything else because it's not getting updated at
all.
It's not getting sent.
So, more likely the thing that I suspect we would want to do is
something like this, right?
And this is just me conceptualizing.
How I suspect this would have to work in order to do what I wanted to
do, which is that as we Loop through these entities here, right?
And you can see us dealing with
These entities, we do our updates and all that stuff.
We have a thing here that does the Collision detection.
What I probably want to do is say, you know what, at the end of all
this stuff, after we do the Collision detection, right?
Which is all this stuff and we don't need this anymore.
Excuse me, right?
There we go.
So after we do all of this stuff, we do the Collision detection, which
is only really necessary for for debug mode.
So, you might say this should be something where we do handmade
internal, we could also have sort of add another thing for this, which
is like, if, you know, debug you I enabled or something like this,
right?
You could imagine it being something like this.
But basically what we have is a section where we do our hit testing
for that debug stuff, right?
And then we have an output for the debug stuff and what I'd like to do
is decouple these.
So I'd like to do is
okay, they hit testing happens and if we have a situation where we hit
test somebody and it turns out that that somebody is the guy who was
was outlined
Then I'd like to have something in here where we can sort of announce
that to the big system like if debug, you know, hit hit data, I don't
know.
Something like this hit thing, you know.
I don't know if debug hit and we want to sort of announce this thing
and we kind of know what this thing is.
Right.
It's this this is its ID, right?
That we decided it had that was a pointer that had there.
So if you know you hit this thing then what we
Like to do is we'd like to display it or whatever and otherwise you
know maybe we don't and then same with here, we like, if debug, you
know system, anybody say if the debug system wants whatever this thing
is, you know, then we would we'd sort of open this data block and
stream out the values to it, right?
And that would be something more like this, if maybe we would call it
even something like this, we just have the data Block in there.
It maybe it opens it automatically and we just say, if debug begin
like optional data block or something and hear it that is
so in that case, now we have a situation where the debug system itself
can sort of ask for which entities it wants to have updated and some,
you know,
Some logic.
Can occur behind the scenes to make sure all of this stuff gets
integrated with the debug UI system itself.
And so in here we would say hey we have a hit do you want us to
highlight it basically do you want us to like do a highlight of that
or something like this?
You know, yes or no.
And I suppose the other thing we could sort of do here, we could sort
of have a thing where, you know, this could sort of have a double
meaning as well.
Maybe it could have a, something a little more,
Cancel associated with it.
So for example, when we do this operation,
We could do something more like this where instead of the operation,
let's do it.
Something like this.
We could we could do a two-part thing where we say okay.
If you know the thing is true, then we have a debug hit and then we
could also have a thing here.
Remember we said, okay there was a debug kit and there is a debug or
like highlighted, right?
And the other thing that you can see about this is we have a lot of
sort of the same thing going on here with this nonsense.
And so I also feel like we would want to have a way of encapsulating
that debug ID, you know.
So if we took a look at the way, the debug ID thing was working there,
debug ID,
That's in platform.
Oh sorry.
That's we move that out recently.
It's actually in debug interface.
So in here where we have this notion of like the debug ID, which is, I
guess not in here.
It's actually in here as it turns out.
So if we have this notion of a debug ID you know we can make that a
more sort of first class citizen sort of thing.
We could say that the debug idea
Self is actually a thing that is understood outside the debug system.
And so that way, when we're in code like this, we can do something
like, say, like entity debug ID, right?
And we can have like, you know, a pointer ID or something like this
sort of thing.
So we can make one of these out of whatever we want and when we make a
pointer ID out of this thing, it then knows that like okay, that's
what we're going to use for everything.
So instead of having something where this could get like out of phase
and we or we decide to change the way we're Computing it and it gets
to be a pain.
We could do something more like this.
Where we just sort of have
Hey, it was probably more properly, a simulation simulation ND.
So if we do something more like this, right now, we sort of have that
entity debug ideas kind of unify through the system and it's much
better, right?
So if you look at what we would need to add the system to do this.
Again, I'm following sort of the write the code in the place that we
know the most about first.
So, and then back it out,
You can kind of see the way that I'm envisioning it.
It's like.
Okay, we've got some switch that can turn this stuff off entirely
because if we don't want any of this happening, we don't so we could
make that be a pound to find that just turns off or who knows what we
do there.
We then have you know this code like what the debug ID and stuff like
that.
We have this code where we can do
Announcements of stuff in our system that we want to track and we can
give it some kind of a universal identifier that hopefully, the debug
system can use to know which one we're talking about from frame to
frame.
And, again, that's a common trick.
I use often.
I kind of originally started doing that back in the immediate mode,
graphical user, interface days, where I was sort of working out how to
do those sorts of systems.
It's this notion of a identifier that is generated from things that,
you know, will be unique, right?
And so in this case, I know that
Are Pointers that would uniquely identify this entity.
I know that we have that constant system, so I want to communicate to
the debug system that I'm talking about the same thing that I might
talk about later on, right, in multiple ways.
And so, this is just a way of sort of creating that unique ID.
It's a lot of times in C and C++ programmers, get confused about the
difference conceptually of a pointer.
Being a location in memory and a pointer being a name for something,
right?
And so, retain mode systems, traditionally have not understood the
concept that the pointer to something and the name of something are
different.
So like it's a really empowering thing to understand that a pointer
can both be a pointer can be serving as a name and storage but you
could also
Associate those two and just say as long as you do, have a way of
generating, some kind of name for this thing, that is unique, then you
can talk about it in multiple places without ever having to track its
storage, across that boundary.
And that's exactly what we're talking about here.
This debug system, we're writing to a buffer that's just streaming out
data.
We don't want to round trip to the debug system and get back the
storage that this will.
Eventually occupy because we don't even know if it will be stored.
And furthermore, we don't even know if the demon systems operational.
We might just be sending this stuff out and it may just be ignoring
them, right?
Not only that.
We don't want this code that were writing here to be complexified by
having to insert pointers into it.
So for example, I don't want to take my sim entity and have to attach
a debug entity pointer to it, right?
I don't want to do any of those things.
So what we can recognize right is just the fact that the pointer to
the storage on our side.
What we're using as a unique pointer which is this low entity thing.
We can just use that as a pointer
The name that the debug system can use to associate with storage on
the other side, right?
And it's a very common technique.
It's anytime you see someone using a map in code, right?
Like a key value pair, that's what that is, right?
The key is this thing that doesn't necessarily Point directly to the
storage.
It's just a name that we know will give us the storage or the it, or
the value back, right?
And it's very important because C and C++ programmers, aren't used to
destroy you.
Thinking that way as much other programmers are used to thinking
exclusively, that way there are used to thinking exclusively as
they're being names for things and they have no idea where they're
stored or even what storage is there.
Just like, I don't know, I put the name like a MySQL partner was like,
I don't know, I put in the key and I got the record, right?
The key is not a pointer to the record.
I have no idea where the record is record, could be anywhere.
I don't even know if it's in memory, or on disc or whatever.
Right?
I just know that, right?
So it's kind of important sometimes receive C and C++ or
They're new to C and C++ to remember that.
Just because pointers are often used as both the name and the storage.
They can also be used by just a simple map or a hash table or anything
else.
They can also be used as the name, right?
And the storage could be somewhere else and so on and so forth, right?
So anyway, that's just a little like brief diversion to the concept
here and that's just a common thing again, first for newer, see,
Best regards to forget because the language is because it allows such
explicit manipulation of storage.
Most a lot of the time you don't need separate names for things.
You don't need a name for something and a storage because the pointer
is both but in sort of certain circumstances where you want to
partition things more cleanly.
You can reintroduce that naming difference.
And basically, you know, again, you sort of have the best of both
worlds.
It's one of the nice things about C++, right?
Is that you are really seized single just really have anything to do
with it, but it's one of the nice things about see is you have the
option of choosing when you introduce a name as a name versus a name
as the storage and you can every time that they are the same collapse,
all of that intermediary code which is something that's a JavaScript
can't do right because it's always
Going through an intermediary in a number of ways and so on.
And only if a just-in-time compiler can like figure out just the right
things, can it ever like, you know, get past that limitation that
names are just names.
So anyway, if we go ahead and proceed a little bit forward with this,
we can sort of see how this is going to play out.
So we're going to generate some debug ID and it's going to have to be
some way that we can sort of tell the debug system.
This is the name I'm going to use every time I refer to this thing, in
this case it's going to be an entity and we know that the low entity
ID is unique in our system.
So we can
Can just use that pointer.
Then we go ahead and do the hit testing.
And whenever we find a hit we can just go ahead and say OK.
Whenever we find that hit, we know that the entity debug ID needs to
be announced as
Thumping, the mouse is hovering over right now.
We could also try to announce the Z value here so that there could be
some sorting involved.
I don't know how useful that would be but we do know what the Sorting
is to some degree, right?
We do know that the Sorting is like whatever that back project we did,
right?
So
We know that whatever we do this, look at most P Uhn project thing.
This local Mouse pz is sort of the z-depth right?
And so we can throw that in there.
Maybe the debug system will want to sort the hits or who knows in a 3D
game.
We'd obviously definitely want that in a 2-D game.
You know how useful is that going to be probably not.
There's not like so many things stacked on top of each other all the
time but in a 3D game you know, you definitely want that.
And then what we want to do is we want to check this debug highwomen.
Like to say, hey okay, you know, is this thing supposed to be
highlighted if so that I might do a little bit of work to render it
and that's just generally the code that we would need to expose this
stuff to the debug system, right?
And then later we say, all right, if this thing was something that was
supposed to be output, then we will output it and notice I've
decoupled that from the Collision detection now.
So the Collision detection happens in here or since they kill
injections, like it is conjunction, but it's hit detection.
Really?
What I'm saying?
Cause we're colliding with the mouse cursor, right?
It's not just to not be confused because Nick normally.
So, if you look at this code, this debug optional data block is
basically saying, okay, every entity is going to ask the debug system
whether or not it should be output here, right?
So, even if the thing is not being hovered over, you'll see the debug
system could still suck up that data, which is exactly what I wanted
to be able to have happen before, or right.
Like I was saying, now, it is true that this will only happen for
entities that are within the simulation region.
So you could imagine wanting to do something even a little bit more
fancy later.
On right, we could do something even fancier where we asked the debug
system to tell us all the entities that it wants us to display and
then we unpack them all but that starts to get a little more heavy
weight and that becomes less of less debug annotation and more full on
debug inspection system that we're writing custom.
And so I'd like to stay away from that for now because until I
actually see if we ever need something that advanced I'd rather stick
with something that's more general-purpose where that it just kind of
has like debug stuff that gets streamed out, right.
And there's
No, there's no reverse sort of announcement where the debug system
never announces IDs back to the game and says, could you give me the
data on these please right?
Okay.
So that's what I'd like to do and you can see if we compile it,
basically all of these new things that we've introduced of course,
they are not going to be found.
So I need to open up the debug interface code again and just add in
these values that we no longer have, right?
So here I go.
I'm just putting these in here.
I'm going.
To go ahead and first declare them as being compiled out we haven't
really done much testing of the compiling out.
So we're probably going to have
Test out again, sometime soon to let clean up all the stuff that would
not compile.
Now that we have made changes, but nominally we know we're going to
want these things here like so.
And then I'm going to need to actually Implement these things and and
those are going to have to go up here and I suppose when we do like
debug you and I enabled that's actually going to evaluate to 0.
So that that actually evaluates to something this as well.
Like debug pointer ID, that's actually also going to presumably
initialize to something.
It would probably be something.
You know, this just zeros.
It would be this if we knew we were always
Is, I don't know if you can do this and see now, see those first.
You didn't used to be able to do this sort of thing.
I don't know if you are allowed to do that now like you know I'm
talking about this sort of thing, I don't know if you're actually
allowed to do that yet I feel like you should have been able to do
that for a long time but you can't.
So we may have to do something like this where we have just an inline
that's like okay.
There's a debug ID and it's actually this sort of a thing, right?
And it takes whatever it takes, I guess it would take it just takes a
pointer, right?
And it Returns the null ID.
And actually I suppose we could even just do that where we just say
that this is a global variable, right.
There's just this until ID that's just there and you know it always
just returns just whatever that value of that variable is, you know,
but I don't know.
I'm going to leave it like this for now so there we go.
And the rest of this stuff, debug kit is also zero.
Debug highlighted.
Those are just assuming that you're never going to hit or highlight
everything and begin optional people datablock.
None of that stuff will do anything, right?
So they all just evaluate 20's.
I could also test to make sure that that works here, I guess.
So, here we go.
Debug you.
I enabled.
Wait, it's right there.
Debug you I enabled Undeclared.
Identifier, what are you talking about?
Oh, I see it's because it's not actually a function, so that has to be
removed.
There we go, in debug pointer ID.
Not found, that's true because we have not done that one yet.
Okay, and so here are debug pointer ID actually would do the thing,
right?
And in some sense I suppose, we could still use that.
I don't know.
We probably don't want to do, but this is this is what we would do
here.
Yeah.
And so that's all good and now we're compiling.
All right, so now I have to actually Implement these guys.
Debug you.
I enabled I suppose would be one here, right?
Because we do want the debug you.
I enable the least for the moment, it would always be enabled.
And so, then what we would have is we'd have these, like, debug kit,
debug highlighted and debug begin optional data block stuff.
And with those need to do, is those need to actually probably call
into the debug system to find out what's actually going on.
So, these might actually be functions, they might not actually be
macros at the moment anyway.
They're definitely macros when you compile out but they would not be
macros when you're compiled in.
So, this is more of a, you know, probably something like this.
It's going to return a Bool in both cases.
Oh, well, the debug kit doesn't.
It's that.
Is that right?
Sorry.
So I kind of messed that one up.
Debug kit actually doesn't do anything at all.
That's not true.
So what happens actually here in debug kit, it'll take a debug ID.
And it would take a z value, right?
And that's actually a function.
That's some function that we would have to you know actually described
somewhere.
It's obviously going to be internal and then debug highlighted again
going to be the exact same thing.
It's going to take one of these IDs here and return it right whether
or not that thing should be highlighted, debug begin optional data
block.
That actually is going to be a macro.
And the reason that's going to be a macro is because it has to call
debug begin data Block in the correct place.
Because we want the file line and um, and number directives to be
correct in case we ever want to print those out.
We may get decide to get rid of those because we don't really need
them in the future, who knows?
But, at least for the moment we want this to be expanded in line so
that that'll work but we just want to put an if around it essentially,
which I guess.
Now that I think about it, it's going to be a little bit easier said
than done.
This is kind of one of those card macros to write and I'm going to
have to think about whether or not we can really do it this way.
We may have to do it as a
As a series of two, as much as I wish that we didn't have to.
It might be really gnarly to write it without that because you can't
like open a brackets inside an.
If right, you can't open that, that it wouldn't work because of sees
bust expression syntax kind of the bane of existence of see that C++.
Of course, inherited is the fact that expressions and statements are
different for no reason that anyone has ever been able to articulate.
To me, it means it can't.
Code inside an if statement because doesn't evaluate anything.
So Kate Open, brackets.
Oh, well, anyway, ignoring that downside, I would say that probably
means that, you know, just to save ourselves the aggravation of trying
to do something ridiculous.
We could do something like this here, we just do debugging data block
and then we say, like, you know, debug like kind of we have
highlighted here, we could do debug
requested, something like this, you know, like if you wanted this
thing,
Then I'll tell you about it, right?
That seems like a pretty reasonable thing to do.
Not as nice as the other way, not the end of the world.
All right, so this is actually now going to be debug requested.
And this is also debug requested.
So what debug requested is again, same exact thing.
Here we have a debug question, it would take a debug ID and you know
off you go
Something like this.
And so I think that's mostly all we really need here.
In fact, if we compile this, I think, at least very soon, now we
should be able to get to a place where we don't have any compile
error.
So it looks like just in there.
Okay.
So when we do debug begin data, block, obviously, I kind of change
that to taking when we do debugging day about we're taking Porter
0.01, what I'd like to do is sort of change it to.
Thing like this.
Right where you do that sort of thing?
Right?
Or like something like this.
And that way, you know, the event itself now has the concept like a
formal concept that there are debug IDs in those debug ideas, kind of
come through here, right?
Like that.
That seems like a good idea to me, and now you can see, right?
We're getting to that point where now, the only problem that we've got
now, is that we have these debug functions?
Everything's working every compiling, we just have to get it now to
the point where those things are actually understood by the debug
system in some meaningful way, right?
We have to
Make them.
Like actual valid Concepts because when it gets to the end of the
compilation, it's like, hey, by the way, you never implemented any of
this.
It's true.
We haven't.
So, if I start implementing these again, I'm looking basically.
Now at the code, I'm the code we're talking about here is that, that
sort of interface code, where we've got the sort of debug interaction
stuff happening.
And if we kind of look through the code here, we have this, this code
here, right?
Is working with this sort of block of stuff here.
Where we have these debug interactions, we have like hot.
Traction, next hot interaction, all that sort of stuff, right?
And the debug interaction code you can see it can actually you know,
interact with very specific stuff and every interaction does have a
debug ID with it.
So we could very clearly know whether we were interacting with a
particular thing or not and that sort of stuff.
Now what we don't have at the moment in the debug system though is any
concept of selection so there's really no way to like add or remove
things from a selection but that's not something to be particularly
difficult for us to add certainly right.
It'd be pretty easy for us to kind of add a
Thing where we just allow you to select something and then you click
on something else and you select that something else, you know, if
that's not particularly hard and you know, we can sort of as we work
with the debug UI stuff.
We can make that happen pretty easily as well.
Alright, so if we're going to go ahead and Implement these guys here,
we've kind of
All of this interaction stuff happening.
What we want to do is sort of start to implement these things here,
where we can handle these things that are coming in in, through us,
right?
So if we have this code, it's going to need to store some state.
So you know, the debug State stuff.
Obviously, the game is never going to pass that stuff.
So, if you take a look at all of the things here, when we're doing
debug State, we're going to need the one.
And I don't remember exactly where we put that guy it.
It's up here somewhere, where we actually access the deep web site.
Here it is, where we access the debug State, using the game memory.
And if I remember correctly, the way that we did that.
Yeah, okay.
So here it is.
We actually already have the helper function.
We need, we just use that sort of global and then we start going from
there, right?
So what I want to do and, you know, actually the other thing that's
interesting answer, this doesn't seem to work properly if this was
null, if debug Global memory hadn't been set yet, so I feel like we
probably want
Up to look like this where we do that, you know, that seems like sort
of a little bit more of what we would want.
I don't know.
Maybe it's just stupid because that's never going to happen.
I don't really know, but I feel like, yeah, I feel like getting case
you accurately called something.
Before the system was initializer, something you just want to pass
through?
I don't know.
Maybe not.
But anyway, there we go.
So if I want to, I can just in these
These functions when I need the debug state, right?
I should be able to
Oops, just get it directly by dereferencing that pointer.
And so again, the reason that we're doing that, instead of passing it
in here, is because we really don't want to introduce any complexity
on the side of the using Code, the code that's using this stuff.
We don't want it to have to like track that debug State pointer and
pass it around stuff.
We want people to feel the cold, call the debug system from wherever
they are with, even no matter if they have no idea what's going on,
right?
So we want to be able to do this inside these guys, so that they
Just get to the debug State immediately and not have to do anything
else, right?
So at the moment there's a number of things we could do to test this.
Right?
So for example, one thing we could do is just do a return true in here
and a return true in here.
Actually, we could just, let's do that one.
Let's do a return false here.
Right.
And now in theory, everything should draw like an outline around
itself.
I would think, right?
So yeah, here, even that suggests to me that this is definitely the
case.
So here we go in game update and render, we're getting at the debug
system and it looks like it has not been initialized yet, right?
So I'm not sure why that actually is.
I have to look at the call order here, but that was exactly what I was
thinking.
As like, sometimes this thing they know.
Is it started up yet?
All right, so let's see where that.
Happens.
Initialized equals true happens here.
It's in debug start and so it looks like something maybe gets called
before debug Stark, it's called.
In fact, I'm gonna go ahead and run back in there and see where we are
on the call stack.
Yeah, so so essentially that debug says that debug start, right?
That's not going to happen until after the end of the frame because I
believe the way we left it was that debug start actually happens for
the first time all the way down here, right?
Like, it's like after everything else is about to happen.
Debug frame.
And so I'm guessing it probably happens in here.
Oops.
Where is my debug frame end?
There it is.
So I'm guessing that it happens in here.
Yeah, debug start debugging.
So basically you know this is just going to happen at the end when
everything else happens.
And so we really need some way of making sure that the debug system.
Either a gets initialized before we start, right?
Or that we ignore any any attempts to use it before them.
And again, I don't really know which one we want to do.
I kind of
Like maybe we just want to ignore those things.
I'm not sure.
Maybe that's a little dangerous and we should force it to kind of get
initialized, but I'm going to, I'm going to lean towards that one.
I'm going to lean towards saying that we really don't want to do this,
right?
And so what we'd want to do is say something more like this.
So that we just don't return anything.
In the case that that we don't, that we don't have one, you know what
I mean?
And so that seems a little bit more reasonable to me.
So these guys always just kind of do this thing.
I'm not sure.
Again, that may be a bad decision.
We'll find out as we go, whether it is or isn't
So there we go.
Now the debug system, right?
Like I said is telling everyone that they should highlight and we can
see that that's working.
Just fine.
And so now what we want to do is maybe let's try to make it.
So that only the thing that actually the mouse is over gets
highlighted, right?
So we know that when the mouse is over something, we're going to get a
debug hip call.
So we want to do is we want to track that, right?
We want to say that if the mouse is over something with remember what
it's over and then maybe, you know, we can just do the simplest
possible version here where we just kind of like return.
And whether or not you were that highlighted one.
So obviously the simplest possible way to do that without doing
anything more fancy here.
we've got hot interaction, you know I'm saying, we could just set the
hot interaction to have that ID and the type
Right where we have here, the type could just be a no op or something
or it could be a select, right?
We could have like debug interaction like select or something like
this.
And so in order to do that, what we do is any time that we got this
debug hit, maybe we do something where we say, like okay, when we get
a debug hit, I feel like we've got that sort of like hot interaction
concept going here.
You can see that we have this this concept of like next hot
interaction.
Getting
At two things.
So I feel like we could use maybe next hot interaction, just the way
that it was being used, right?
Just just straight up.
And so if we wanted to do that, what we could do is Hoops, that's not
good.
We could just go to debug kit and we could do something like make that
interaction, right?
So you can say, like, debug interaction interaction,
And when we're making those interactions.
There we go, debug interaction.
You can see that we've kind of got these different helper functions
here.
So tears, VAR, link interaction, we could do something like, you know,
like debug hit interaction where we make one of these, from a debug
idea, of course.
Now, I think about that might be kind of stupid and redundant because
we already have on there but I don't know.
I'm going to do it anyway, something like that.
You bug ID interaction, something like that, where we just pass a
debug ID and that's all it has.
There's no tree and
Moved.
And so when we make one of those, we've just passed the ID here, the
type.
And then obviously, this, this interaction stuff here doesn't have
anything presumably other than the ID.
So, like in here, there really wouldn't be anything other than that
debug ID.
I think because it doesn't have any anything else I suppose, we could.
If there was any other information here, we could store it but I don't
think there really is.
So I'm just going to go ahead and say that, that's all that we're
actually going to get for now.
Okay.
So
So let's let's just go ahead and leave it that way.
like so, and we could actually set generic
20 just to clear that out if we want to oh well it's already cleared.
You know what, that already clears it.
So okay we set this stuff up.
That's all good.
So here we're just saying, debug ID interaction, the type again, like
I said is going to be that select type.
So we're going to go ahead and pass the Select, Plus the ID and then
the next type interactions going to be that interaction.
You can even just do it like this.
And so in that case, if someone doesn't Mouse down now it will do,
it'll start the select process on that guy and then we could also sort
of test that tests for now.
Let's pretend we've got, you know, some kind of a selection thing for
now.
We don't really have one but let's pretend we did.
That's so maybe we just got something here, which is like you by God.
Selected or something, right?
And so in here we could say, all right, the result for this guy, the
result is going to be if the ID
Equals.
I don't know if we have like a way to check if debug IDs or equal yet
but it equals whatever the selected debug ID is.
I could just call it's like that ID.
We know it's in the debug system.
It's probably that.
So OK I now just need some way of testing whether or not they're
equal.
Looks like we do have a way of doing that at least for now.
So I could say debug is IDs are equal and I can check to see if these
two ones are.
So when we check to see if to debug IDs are equal, if the selected one
is equal to the one that we're being asked about then that means that
it's highlighted.
And similarly what we could do is just for.
Now we could do the exact same thing for the debug requested, even
though that's probably not exactly what we would want to do for that.
And I suppose, another thing we could do here is actually just say be
through to is selected.
You know, and is selected might be this.
Which is exactly what these guys are doing.
But it means that in a little while if we wanted to have like
multi-select or something, these routines wouldn't really have to do
anything different.
Right.
They could just
they could just go ahead and keep calling that function and that
function with them become smarter.
It would be able to look through a list of people who are selected or
anything else that it might need to do to figure that out.
It could do.
So at that point, we could have something much more, you know,
interesting happening in there and these routines don't really have to
care, they just know that they're going to operate off of that, right?
So now, what will happen in theory at least?
Is that well, actually, I guess technically absolutely nothing.
I would think.
Although now that I think about it to debug highlighted should
probably also look at hot interaction because if the hot interaction,
we probably would want to highlight that as well.
So we'd want to do like is Select selected or like if that hot
interaction.
So, hot interaction, debug ID.
If those debug IDs were equal, then I'd want to, I want to do that as
well.
Okay.
So, it is not a member not a member, huh?
Yes, that's true.
It does not a member
Okay, so yeah.
So well, you know what?
We should probably instead of returning true actually return the
results from these functions because that would be a lot easier to
test to say, the very least, okay?
So, if I take a look at this now,
Well, that's doesn't look very exciting to me.
That doesn't look great and the reason presumably and I guess I should
have thought of this before hand, but I only thought of it.
Just now when that didn't work is we always clear out the hot
interaction when we start, but really what we want to do is clear it
out when we end, because now hot interactions might be happening kind
of in the middle of the frame, right?
So if you see like we're sort of clearing the stuff out,
Before stuff happens.
But really, what we want to do I believe is clear stuff out at the
end.
So after everything's over like, you know, note Casey clear the UI
State for the next frame, you know, that's something that we want to
do kind of over here.
And that now we're now we're in much better shape, right?
So now that that process, right is all going through, sort of our
that's all going through our debug system, which is great because now
all of that code is you know any complexity that we're going to
introduce until like selecting objects or doing that stuff is hidden
in the debug code and doesn't have to expose itself in the game in any
way, right?
Which is exactly what we want.
We've kind of got like, you know, a minimum amount of complexity that
gets exposed
And that's good.
However what's not good is you can kind of see what's happening here
where once we get to the space entity, that's the only thing that gets
highlighted ever.
Right?
So these entities and it's because we're just checking out of the
order.
So this is a place again where we may want to start to think about
using that.
That's Z value, for sorting might be a good idea.
There's also some other things we could do there, but using that Z
value for sorting seems like a good idea.
I'm not sure what the best thing to sort on would be.
Like I said, I'm passing in sort of that value, but I'm not sure what
the best Z value to pass in would be when we do this sort of the
unprojected, right?
It's hard to say because their volumes and some of them are Hollow and
some of them aren't so.
It would depend on which kind of volume, it was probably
It's a hollow volume.
You'd pass.
One it one way and if it was not a hollow volume, you pass it the
other.
So it's a little bit tricky.
Just about how those work.
But anyway, that's that's the basics of it.
We've gotten to the end of the stream.
So I'll go ahead and switch over to the Q&A for now.
But you can see kind of how we'd start extending that tomorrow.
All right, q a Time.
If you have questions about what we were doing, please post them with
a Q:.
Oh wait.
You know what?
That's not actually true because I started with like 10 minutes on the
clock.
So forget that I can do the selection.
I'm going to go ahead and do this election because I was about to do
that.
We might as well do this election part as well, right?
That seems like a good idea.
It to me.
And furthermore, I feel like we could do something like this.
Potentially.
You know, I'm saying to you.
I don't know that.
That's a good idea.
But I'm going to do it anyway because why not?
I've got two minutes left on the clock.
So I'm going to use them.
I'm going to use them to nefarious ends as what I'm going to do.
I'm just going to go ahead and straight up, do weird stuff with that.
So, yeah, so debug highlighted, the four color, and what I'll do is
I'll just go ahead and write to that.
You know, another thing that I should point out, I don't know if I
ever explicitly mention this, you'll notice on the stream whenever I
compiled something out, I always just use dot dot dot.
As the parameter is because now that that C++ supports variadic
macros,
it just means that you don't have to change the compiled out version
every time you change the parameter.
So, like right there, I did by Khalid.
I added a V4 color to it.
It means that now when it compiles out, I don't have to go change that
place as well, right?
And that's just kind of nice.
So yeah.
So here's what we'll do.
We'll say something like this.
If is selected
Result equals true.
If debug IDs are equal,
Result, equals true.
But in this case, we will use one color, and in this case, we lose
another color.
So in this case, we know that if something is selected, for example,
maybe that's cyan.
Who knows why it just is.
And then another case, it's yellow, right?
And so now, if we run this, we should see no change from before,
right?
So everything is yellow.
Like for highlight.
And then now, what I'll do is I'll go ahead and Implement some
selection in here.
Hopefully,
so when we're interacting with things, I don't actually remember if we
have anything in particular that I have to do for selection because
it's kind of a straightforward thing to have happen.
So I think the only real thing that I would need to do is like when
you begin or when the interaction is kind of going, right?
You can kind of see how this works here, right?
Where we're doing the interaction type, you can see this red thing.
When the interaction is going, I feel like I could just sort of say
well if you're inside if you're with
If you're within the bounds or if the thing had been hit recently,
then it's still selected.
If not, then not, I'm guessing so it would be something like, I don't
know.
It probably be something like debug interaction.
Selected or select rather.
And I you know, if we wanted the cheesiest possible version of it
which maybe we do now.
I think about it.
Just when we begin we just say, okay?
Like whatever the interaction is when we go in here whenever we begin,
we'll just say like okay, whatever.
The debug State selected ideas is going to be whatever the hot
interaction.
Whatever its ID was.
So now you can kind of see we can pick like what our thing is that we
want, and it will stay available there in theory.
You know what I mean?
And at the moment there it is.
A little weird.
I'm not actually seeing so this it all seems to work.
Ok, but you'll notice, I don't seem to be seeing the highlighted one.
Ever, and I thought that, I thought, well, I thought I did something
with that.
Maybe I didn't hard to say, let's take a look.
So, in here, when we to debug requested, oh, nope.
That's exactly how it was supposed to work as it turns out.
All right.
Never mind.
So we could.
If we wanted to, though, you know, we could do something like this.
We could make it operate here as well.
So, you know,
if I do this,
that would make it so that I saw both of them.
So, you know, I can hover over something and it shows me the hovered
one that can also click.
And now it would show me both of them.
If I only, if I hover over the selected one, it would just show me
that just the one, but here you can see.
Okay, I've got 43 and 42, both entities are being viewed right by the
beach, the, by the system, right?
So again, that's also something where if we wanted to, you know, we
could sort of
Have again more more of those in the system we could have some kind of
a selection thing.
I don't actually know that we care about this all that much, but just
to again, since I've got like, four minutes or something, you can
throw in something pretty stupid here where we just did like, you
know, the selected ID or, you know,
Something really stupid.
I don't know what, but that would just be
When you do is selected, it actually just checks to see, you know, for
any given ID looks at all of those.
so this would just say like select in, you know, or, you know, just
just some index that were checking against
Here we would just do selected ID of that and so we check all of these
and then we just have some a couple things which is like you know
clear selection and clear selection would just again take a debug
State and all that's going to do is say hey you know what?
Now there's no selection anymore there's nothing is selected right
into setting the count 0 and then select.
When we actually select something.
Then technically, you know, we'd probably still want to do this.
And we just want to say like well, we could actually do this.
If is selected
Just say is not selected, then we doubt it.
Right.
And we probably also say, well you only get a certain number of these.
All right.
And the only reason I'm checking their is just because I don't
actually want to add something multiple times to the selected set.
So that's all that really is, I guess I don't remember.
So this is just yes, this is probably.
I should probably say add to selection or something like that.
So this is add to selection when we do this select and you know,
here's where, you know, we would want some modifier Keys, certainly.
So we'd
Like, I'm going to add to the selection, here's the debug State.
Here's the thing to add to it.
And normally, what we would do here is we'd say, like, you know, if
The shift keys.
Not down.
We do clear selection or whatever.
Right.
So basically, if if the shift key is down, we just keep adding the
selection like this typical thing that you do with selection, where
you hold down shift and you can select multiple objects.
If the shift Keys up, we would just clear the selection.
Two shift Keys down, then we would not clear the selection we just
append to it.
Right?
Right now.
I don't think we have modifier keys at the moment.
I don't think so.
It doesn't ring a bell.
Right?
So we have like the Mouse stuff, right?
We've got buttons and things, but we don't have
Any modifier keys there.
And you know, part of the reason that we don't have any modifier Keys.
Is that the game itself?
She's me.
Is being played with the keyboard.
And so like I don't know whether you know, like shift would maybe be a
bad modifier key to be using it because, you know, maybe the person is
like, trying to play the game and you can't tell the difference
between the two of those you'd have to be in.
Like are you in debug mode or are you not in debug mode or something
like that?
So I don't know exactly how would you want to do that but point being,
you know, we'll have to figure that out so
For now.
We just won't clear the selection and now we should be able to like
select as many things as we want.
Right?
And you can kind of see that that works.
Exactly has how we would expect
All right, so we're getting there.
Starting to look pretty good.
I guess I'll put it to do in here to, to do
Modifier keys for some way of doing.
Multi-select.
All right.
Okay, so now let's actually go to the Q&A.
So we've got about 19 minutes so yeah.
Anyone who has questions can hit me with a Q:.
Is the in sohbat smart enough to know that it should use Q: during the
Q&A?
Disused symmetry.
You can emulate expression blocks with lambdas.
If you don't mind the craziness of C++ 11, I do mind the craziness of
C++ 11.
Of course.
Chronodragon insta, but checks for your cue a thing I believe.
Yes, so that in sohbat, at what point can we replace the chat with
just in sohbats and then, at what point can we replace me with just
some programming bot and then
Select Bots.
Showing Bots.
Some programming.
Elvin, would you think it's better to start at a junior position at a
company than working my way up?
Or try to apply for hydrogen dude?
I have no idea.
I know nothing about modern hiring practices.
Mr.
Fourth dimension about Universal IDs.
What if some things want to be identified in the same system?
But don't have fixed storage location or conflicts in some other way
with the universal uniqueness.
So what I generally do, you'll notice very specifically this was even
like sort of predictive of me because we didn't actually have a need
for it.
But you'll notice skin cure.
The way that I did it is there's two pointers.
It's like why are there two pointers right?
And the reason is specifically because you can almost always generate
a unique ID with enough space and like, you know, I've seen it in my
system sometimes as high as four.
But basically what it is, is like, okay, let's say that I've got
something that only exists as some sequence of things that get
executed in a for loop from 1 to whatever.
And then, you know, I will typically like pile that stuff
Gather where I'll just be like, okay, I know that this point are
uniquely identifies this set of things that I'm doing and the integer
of the for Loop would uniquely identify like, which one of those, it
was right.
And so, I typically find that if you in systems where you want to use
an ID, you can usually find a way to generate them.
Usually.
Now, will it always work necessarily but for certainly, for debug
system, I think we'll be fine.
Adam and 12:17.
Do you know yet if the hammock on talks are going to be streamed and
recorded, I do not know.
I suspect, we won't know.
Probably up until pretty close to the event.
Since that's like, still kind of an active issue that I'm trying to
get resolved.
It's a lot harder than you might think to get people to actually reply
to emails.
Sometimes for whatever reasons,
Flamed Parts on Bart's, imagine of all the often winners.
Well, I make off-by-one errors, myself and I'm not a bot.
So Kira, Caleb wouldn't possibly teaching Bots how to program be the
beginning of the singularity, or the end of The Singularity, depending
how good at teaching they were doing League of?
Wow, scape, you've recommended C.
Programming language book after watching your directory series, are
there any other books you would suggest such as proper programming
practices or reference books?
Not really there probably are some out there, but I'm not
Up on them enough if that makes sense.
So I don't really know what probably the right books to read these
days would be that's not to say that there aren't
Good books.
Are you these days are probably our?
I just don't I don't know what they are.
Elvin you mentioned that the pointer could be used as the key and the
thing is pointing to is the value.
So do you mean something like this pair of X star X?
I just mean, as any way, anything that implements a map like a hash
table or anything like that, you know.
VZ trees e, what else you working on outside of this project?
So my main project you can go to Mali rocket.com and this is our Dev
blog here.
You know you can use the little buttons to like scroll through it.
We have not announced the project yet but this is the page for for all
of our announcements, every Monday gets posted and you can also go to
the follow page and there's a mailing list.
So if you do want to know what we're working on, is soon as we
announced, it would go out on that.
B.b.
King twitch.
If you're just starting out to watch these videos and you don't have
time to watch them all which ones are most important.
I wouldn't really say that there's a moster important or not.
It's because the the different thing about handmade hero is this is
not trying to teach you any specific programming techniques.
It's just trying to teach you one useful way of programming so it's
more just the mentality and how that goes you know it, how you just
generally approach problems
So I wouldn't say that there's a particularly important or not
important videos, I'd say just like, you know, as long as you're
understanding, what I'm doing in the video, then they're all roughly
equivalent.
There are certain times when, if really, what you cared about was
learning a very specific technique.
Maybe it's like, oh, I really wanted to learn how to rasterize a
Sprite and then I watch the rasterizing, the Sprite episode, you know,
then obviously, that's true.
But, you know, on the whole it's not really supposed to sort of be
that if that
makes sense.
How do you pick a part code of other programs?
Websites, Etc.
Sorry for the newest spam.
I just want to get started in the morning.
You know, I don't really pick apart other programs that much.
I mean, you know, sometimes I do like, when I was working on the
witness and even I guess sometimes still today, if I have to work on
the witness, I mean I have to go read the code of the other people who
worked on the project or whatever but you know I mean it's not like I
have to it's not like a reverse engineering job or anything like that.
If that's what you mean, you know, I
And most of the time I'm working on code that I wrote.
So I, you know, I'm really reading my own code most of the time.
So I'm not sure, I really understand the question.
If maybe you mean something a little bit more different than sort of
what I'm imagining that to be.
But
yeah.
I'm not, I'm not sure.
I understand really the question, Maybe.
Any other questions?
K trying to work with others.
In Reading their code, do try to understand everything they wrote or
just understand enough to solve your problems.
Um,
well, I mean, you know, it depends on the situation.
I try to understand a fair bit about stuff, but I find that generally
like it's if you know, at least like with the witness, for example,
it's a large enough code base that I'm not really going to understand
it all, unless I do work in it, like, typically I have to do some work
and break some stuff.
And then go, oh, I see like this system over here, actually depends on
this other system and I didn't know that and then like, fix it.
And we're like okay and so you know, as I worked with certain parts of
it, I certainly you know got better at understanding those parts.
But rarely is it the case that I like read the code and like totally
understood like all the code before trying to make some changes to it
because oftentimes you can't really fully understand the code.
At least I find I can't just by reading it, it would have to be like
super, it has to be like very, very small code for me to be able to do
that most of the time I have to kind of push.
On it a little and go.
Okay, I see what's going on here.
Like, I can't change this value because this other thing blows up or
whatever.
So, I see how that gets picked up here or whatever, you know,
Z z 3 Z, is there a programming pattern?
You see all the time that you can't stand or hate?
Um,
I don't, I don't think so.
I mean, usually the thing that I don't like well Getters and Setters
is one
I hate Getters and Setters there.
Like the silliest thing, I don't get why they were ever a thing.
So, Getters and Setters are pretty dumb.
And and that's and the whole Getters and Setters thing is just because
the people who made C++ didn't know what they were doing, they never
should have been that concept of a getter and Setter never should have
existed in the first place but due to the way that they'd efficiently
did the design of C++, it's a natural thing that somebody might do if
they weren't thinking it through all the way.
So it's like it's really that
That one's on screw strip.
That was a really, really bad his design for the way member functions
worked is like, is like exceptionally bad.
So, yeah.
So, I'd say, Getters and Setters, might be one.
But in general, I just don't like things that are overly complicated
like things where there's a lot of code that doesn't actually end up.
Really doing very much tends to be.
The only thing that I really don't like and I try to fight that as
much as possible, my code as well, like already in handmade here.
There's definitely some things that need to be simplified.
But, you know, in general, I think it him, a hero most the stuff isn't
It to ridiculous.
Like there aren't like giant systems that end up like setting one
integer or whatever but that's actually a pretty common thing to see
and some game code bases or other code bases, where it's like, oh my
God.
K.
How do you deal with Roman columns that use Loop?
Get her centers, Etc.
Do you try to give them advice or stay away from them as possible?
Yeah, I probably wouldn't work in that environment.
If I could avoid it like that, I like I would try to not work in a
company that I had to do stuff like that.
Ash Mario, I only know, C++ really.
But what's the alternative to get her sisters?
The alternative is just exposed the variable.
Right.
It's just to put the variable out in the thing and so the real so
basically like a brief whole story got like seven minutes left.
so, the first time someone told me about C++,
It was pretty funny because I thought they were describing something
sensible.
The first time someone told me about C++, they were like, you can make
a class, right?
You can say, you can make this class and they're like, and what you
can do is, you can make it so that there's functions so that if you
access stuff in the class, the functions get called, right?
And what I thought they were talking about
Was this?
I thought they were talking about.
Something that would have looked like this.
Right here is the thing that I would make, and then someone in code
right would do this.
Oops.
So many code would do this.
Right, this makes sense.
What I thought they were talking about is that you could write this.
Make sense.
Without anyone having to change any of the code, it would just
silently insert a call to this every time the value got set and
silently insert a call to this every time the variable was accessed.
Make sense.
Anyone with even like a small, like, a teaspoon of functioning, brain
matter which rules out strew strip would, that's what you would do.
Because this way anyone who wrote code in the natural way, you would
write, the code can just leave it and the person who's implementing
this class can override your access of that thing.
When, when and only when he needs to
Right.
It's really really obvious that that's how an object-oriented
programming language would work.
It's just, it's just, it's as clear and tons of programming languages.
Do this, like, like inform does this.
If you were programming the infocom game, you would have this, right?
But instead, what this idiot does is he puts this thing down here,
right?
And he puts this thing up here.
Any forces you to call it yourself?
How is that even possible?
Like it boggles my mind that the dude was so dumb that he couldn't
figure that out.
That that's ridiculous.
It forces, the dependency between, what whether the person who
initially created the thing thought, they were going to over it, need
to override it or you know or did it right.
It's just absolutely ridiculous.
So as a result by being so dumb key created this like epidemic of what
people do now
Which is for every value whether they need a getter or Setter or not,
they just create one, right?
And the reason that they're creating one is because they don't know
whether they're going to need to do it or not, and they don't want
everyone to have to change their usage code, which is totally
reasonable in some abstract sense.
Right?
I suppose.
But just forget about that, man.
Just do this instead and then if you ever need to do it, just go ahead
the one the time when you actually the rare.
I was on you actually then need to do.
It just put like an underscore at the end of it or drop it into the
private section at that point, right?
And change the like 50 places where it's actually accessed, it's way
less work and saves everyone.
All of this ridiculous typing and nonsensical function calls and all
this other stuff, right?
Yeah, I mean it's just like, like I said, I have no respect for these
people.
They were there complete idiots.
And I don't even know it.
Bothers me even to talk about this stuff because it's so dumb.
Insofar as what about a getter that?
Does some calculation on private variables, like a get day function in
a class that stores, an integer representation of time and date, you
can still do that, right?
That's totally still works.
It's just a simple, we're just talking about syntax Manic, the nobody.
John should be should do that for ji.
He already did.
I think?
I think it already does that.
The good version.
Not the bad version.
Easy size, C sharp does what you described?
Yes, C sharp does.
And so, do a bunch of other languages.
Like I said, it's obvious.
It's like, it's very obvious, like the much, like everything else in
C++, the only people who didn't get it are the people who design C++,
like, everyone else.
It's just painfully obvious but like C++ and like it's, you know, it's
a little, you know, malformed brother Java.
They just always manage to look miss, these super obvious things that
you would just
These are trees to Getters and Setters are less performant to, right?
Probably not, if the compiler knows what it's doing at all.
Qbert.
Caleb.
I know you mostly work on code in smaller groups of people of the what
is it like to program in teams and how does the work get split?
The work gets split usually by what people are just implementing at
the time, right?
You know it's like usually like okay I'm going to work on this
Collision detection thing.
So I'm doing the clothes injection code and typically whoever went and
did something.
First is typically the person who like ends up doing it later, as well
on small teams.
But a bigger companies and stuff like that.
You know, you'll typically have stuff, maybe where people are doing
more.
You know, sort of sort of more top-down management where you actually
like the side.
Look, I'm going to feel, you know, give this a to this person or give
this to the other person and so on, right?
This Isaac.
What about the downside that you don't know whether a value, you're
accessing, does a function call or not?
Well, that'd be a real difficult one for the C++ people to defend
since everything else they did doesn't tell you, operator overloading
does not tell you if you call a function construction, does not tell
you, whether you call a function like nothing in C++, does your cost
function, except that one, and that's the one where you really don't
want to have to know if you're calling a function, right?
So it's kind of ridiculous.
Yeah, it just frustrates me.
I have no sister.
Just such bad language.
Design, epically bad.
Anyway.
Let's go ahead and wrap this up.
I think I can only take so much griping about that particular topic.
Thank you, everyone for joining me for having me here.
It's been a pleasure coding with you.
As always, if you would like to follow along at home, you can always
pre-order the game and it comes to the source code.
So, if you want to play around with it, you can do that on, handmade
hero, dot-org.
You can also go to our forums and ask questions or viewer anti-deficit
guide.
You can go to the patreon page just for 3 or surgeon, go to the Tweet
bot to find out the schedule.
And if you are in the mood to join,
Us for our convention on December 5th.
Just this morning, the speaker list was announced and it is pretty
epic.
You can actually type handmade conduct or if I actually registered a
domain name that just goes directly there and you can read about it.
This is all the information about the like the location and all that
stuff.
And you can also buy the tickets here.
And then we also had just today as our blog post for the day.
We introduce the speaker is it's going to be pretty awesome.
Like it's kind of a crazy.
Awesome.
Line up Tommy reference is like obviously this is me play Mike act in
the head of development at Insomniac for like wisely all the games
ration, Clank resistance Etc blah blah blah blah.
Like every everything is here, Pat Wyatt like one of the original
programmers on Warcraft and and like all the early blizzard games and
then left and did a re Nanette where he did like the Guild Wars and
that code and stuff.
And then John Blow obviously talking about his language braid in the
witness and then
At the end, Ron Gilbert, who obviously guy, who did like secret of
Monkey Island and the, you know, event to the point-and-click
adventure game.
He's going to be talking and yeah, it's gonna be pretty awesome.
I'm pretty excited about it.
So it's going to be a pretty awesome programming Khan.
And obviously, all tried trying to figure out how to get it streamed.
It's been a real uphill battle, trying to get someone to agree to
stream it, but I'm looking to see if maybe now that the speakers are
announced and people.
We'll take a little more seriously, I don't know.
Anyway, if you do want to go to that though and you can make it to
Seattle on December 5th.
You can always buy tickets on the site and then they're pretty cheap
the price goes up to $45 November 5th.
So you still got still got a week or two to grab tickets at the
discount price.
All right, that's about it.
I'll see you guys tomorrow.
Back here, 5 p.m.
Pacific Daylight time, until then have fun programming and I will see
you guys on the internet.
Take it easy, everyone.