Okay, that was a mistake.
I admit that I was not supposed to stop the streaming.
I was supposed to stop the recording, but sometimes, when I get too
excited, I stopped the streaming instead of the recording, which
admittedly does stop the recording as well sometimes.
So it, you know, it does sort of accomplish the goal but then everyone
gets like a little off line thing and then it's a complete disaster
and you know how it goes.
So I was mistake admit that that's not
That we wanted to push and we will, you know, try to avoid pushing it.
But push it, we did.
And so now we're just going to have to live with that.
So anyway, you know, that mistake behind us going to minimize the
window and say welcome to handmade hero.
The show where we code a complete game live on Twitch know, libraries.
No engine just our own sagacious, Ingenuity with the help of the
twitch chat stream, to catch the mistakes that I will invariably.
Make we are going to absolutely every part of a video game from the
lowest little tiniest little detail all the way up to the big picture
in an attempt to answer the age-old question.
Which is, how does a hero with no arms and legs fight their way
through a magical forest, right?
It's a question that has plagued philosophers for Generations.
and honestly,
I feel like it's time.
We laid that question to rest once and for all, and that is exactly
what we're doing here on handmade hero.
But before we can do that, we have to take care of a lot of technical
requirements, first, that we have.
And that's what we're in the middle of doing right now.
What we're doing is we're creating a procedurally generated, ground
texture that will be unique everywhere in the game and that never
repeats.
And so, we've done a bunch of the work that we need to do that.
And we've discussed how we're going to do that, but we still have a
few implementations.
And things that we need to do today and so we will probably do those
today.
However, depending on how much explanation I do, we may not get to the
whole thing.
So it may be a two-day job.
Well, we're not sure.
We'll see.
But I like to get started because we know what we're doing.
We discussed it all yesterday in the day before.
So it's not it's not a mystery.
What needs to be done today.
So we might as well just roll up the proverbial sleeves.
Even though my sleeves are rolled down, that's why I said they were
proverbial and not literal in this case.
And get to
Work.
So if you have, if you want to follow along at home and you've ordered
the game on handmade hero dot-org, you should have gotten a link with
the source code download.
You want to download the source code ZIP and unpack date.
85 from inside that zip, that will put you exactly where I am today.
So if you want to follow along at home, that is the thing to do.
And if you don't do that, you know, don't come back to me and say,
Casey, I couldn't follow along.
Because if you unzip the wrong day, you know, anything goes at that
point, right?
You can't just go unzipping any day and then expect it to be the same
as today.
Because today is today and no, other day is ever today.
Of course, if you're watching this stream on a YouTube video that
means today is not today, today is someday in the past but you know
what I mean?
And that's a very important thing, you know, we're on the same
wavelength, we've got to maintain that same wavelength.
All right, so stick with me here, let's not go off on these
ridiculous.
Tangents that you seem to be encouraging me to do right now.
Again not necessarily directly but in spirit I know no one's actually
talking right now but I can I can sense it.
I can tell that that is what you were thinking and I need you to stop
thinking that entirely.
All right?
So let's go ahead and get back to what we were doing.
So what we did yesterday is we had our tile scheme, sort of working,
but we need to actually start generating more tiles.
And so we need a system that will go
Through and actually request to the tiles that we need so that we
don't just have this one sitting in the center.
We need tiles.
That cover everything.
So let's start by just doing that and we'll work up from there.
And so what I'm going to propose that we do is we start by making
tiles that we what I'd like to propose this is a proposal
Not in the awkward wedding.
Proposal sense where the guy like proposes to his girlfriend in the
middle of a basketball game, and she says, no, and he's really
embarrassed and all these ridiculous things, which it, honestly are
fantastic to watch on YouTube.
I don't know if you've ever done it, but it's there's this, it's one
of those really bad schadenfreude things.
If you get on.
If you get, if you go down that route, you will watch a bunch of them
but it's a lot of fun.
So I recommend it but that's not what I'm talking about.
What I'm actually talking about here is I'm talking about saying,
let's take this one step at a time.
So first, what we'll do is just produce tiles that cover things and
we'll try to make it so that as we move around those tiles adapt to
where we need them to be right.
That's something we obviously need to do but they won't be seamless.
So the tiles will just look totally wrong.
They'll look like a like a tile map game where you have like these
tiles that don't quite fit together right necessarily and you see
seems between them right?
So we'll do that first.
And then once we have that working properly, we will go to, you know,
Defcon 4 or 3, depending on what you want to call the previous Defcon
level that I just described and that new level will be making the tile
so that their seamless because they're two separate tasks.
Really one is about determining what tiles to fill and making sure we
evict tiles properly.
And the other one is totally different.
It's about filling tiles.
The actual tile contents in ways that you know, naturally flow with
each other.
All right, so you got that good.
I'm glad you do.
All right, so let's start.
Thinking we've got some stuff.
We have things to think about here.
Okay, we have we have stuff that needs thinking about stuff that needs
addressing and the first thing that needs to be addressed, is the fact
that these ground buffers that we have right?
We need some way of saying, what the ones we need?
Are we just have a big array of them and we can fill it up with stuff
but we need to know what the world positions are of the things that we
should actually fill.
Right.
And more specifically, we should we should we need to try and we need
to kind of place those things properly.
And furthermore the size of one of these ground buffers, we kind of
want that to line up with World positions.
So we want to make sure that the world position that we give it lines
up properly, you know, with whatever, you know.
So that the pixels the world units and the pixels line up properly for
however, big the ground buffer actually is right.
So let's think about this for a second and exactly how we're going to
do that.
Because there's definitely some issues involved there.
Alright, so in our ground, buffer situation here, when we actually
made our first one, we do this thing.
That's the test feel.
This is the one that fills that one that we've got, so we want to do
is stop doing that test, fill entirely.
So I'm going to, I'm going to take that out of there.
And what we want to do is I'm just going to make a function here, so I
have someplace to to work in for this.
I'm not exactly sure where I want to call it or anything like that.
I just know what needs to happen.
So I'm gonna stick it in here and then we'll figure it out.
What I need to do is I need to go through and essentially I need to
basically say, for every place, the camera could see, I need a ground
chunk there, and that will produce the list of ground chunks for me,
right?
The, the produce the this will produce the ground chunks that I
actually want to have.
Right, that's basically what I want to do, but there's a little bit of
an issue there with that, which is that our ground chunks, obviously
are stored in a way that makes it kind of tough for me to look up
whether we have them or not, right?
And so that's, that's kind of an interesting piece of it as well,
right?
So we'll think about this in a second.
But let's suppose that I was going to take that camera, right?
So, and you know what?
We kind of have some guidance here because in handmade Sim region,
we've got a thing that's like, begin Sim.
Write it.
We passed this bounds thing into into this begin Sim which is like a
region that we use for simulating the world in an area and its got
like an apron around it and so on.
And what I was thinking is well we kind of that's exactly the same
sort of thing that we need to do here.
Right.
That's exactly.
The same thing that we need to do here.
And so if you think about preparing these ground chunks, we could
think about them as being roughly the same as the same region that
we're talking about here.
So, like 17 times three times, nine times, three,
That's how many actual tiles there are, but I think there's not that
many in an actual in a 256 by.
256, there wouldn't be that many tiles.
So I don't know.
There's that's, that's probably something where it's going to be
reduced by a fairly considerable Factor.
So let me just see, what would I?
So that was about 1:00 to 3:30, it's about three per screen.
So if we did, if we did a three by three screens, and each one was a 3
by 3, maybe something like eighty one of them, so we could actually
Request something like the Sim region in terms of how many things we
actually need.
We could actually use something like the same reason.
Maybe that's a little too large so maybe we want to shrink that a
little bit but we could actually request something of that size.
But either way you can see exactly what we're doing.
Here is exactly the same thing that we want to do with the tile
chunks.
So we're just picking a region that's around the camera and we're
saying let's go ahead and fill in tile chunks in that region.
So I'm going to assume that we can do that and I'm going to
That we have basically request ground buffer is something like this
and I just want to be able to pass that.
I want to be able to pass it.
Something where again I've got sort of these these bounds if you will.
So something like a bounce and a world position that's you know, the
center or whatever like that.
And I want to be able to kind of iterate through there and say how
many chunks do I need to pull out for that, right?
And I'm not really sure what the best way to do this is I assume that
the best way to do this would say, all right, from that Center P, I
would want to basically snap to whatever the closest thing is on that
which is really easy.
It, you know, in ABS tile X AB style, while EPS tells e, that's
actually pretty easy to do, because that Center p, is already set up
in that space, right?
If I take a look at what happens in handmade World here, I've got in
that world position.
I've got the chunk X chunk by chunk Z.
So if I just ignore, whatever the offset is, right?
And say, I'm just going to use that chunk X chunk by chunk Z that kind
of, gives me that basis and I know that I could just go some number of
chunks over.
However many it would take to fill that bitmap that to Pieces by 26
bitmap that we have.
I know that I could just step by that until I hit the actual bounds.
So I know this sounds a little confusing.
But basically, what I want to do is say all right, I've got these
bounds, the bounce that got passed in.
I want to offset them by whatever the offset of the world position
thing is, so that my world Position will now be just a chunk X chunk
why chunk Z perfectly aligned.
Does that make sense?
So basically I'm saying, all right.
I've got bounds here, excuse me.
And I believe, I hope.
Anyway, we already have code for this, it's just adds to the Min and
the max.
I don't know if we actually have that or not.
We'll take a look and see.
We have ad radius to recommend me.
X, we have offset to be have, we don't have our set want y so we don't
actually have that but it's really trivial, right?
If we have a rectangle with a minute Max, we're just talking about
adding something to it.
And so much, like we have ad radius to.
We can just do a thing where it's like, okay, if I have a rectangle
three, I can do an offset right?
And the offset just takes whatever the rectangle is and it takes
whatever the offset is and it's just going to its, you know, literally
just going to do.
An operation to move the Min and the max by whatever they offset was,
right?
So, it's just that very, very simple, right?
And so I want to be able to do that.
I want to be able to offset the bounds by whatever the center P was
right.
And so the center p,
When I take that in, that's going to have that offset and I want to
basically get rid of that.
So, what I want to do is say all right, the boundary, and I'll just
draw this out for you real quick.
What day are we on here day 86?
Right.
So, here's day 86.
So, if you think about the, what's going on, right?
I've got some bounds and I've got, you know, basically a look a
location for their Center and it's based off of
AB style, except style, y, AB style, Z, some some Universal
coordinate, right?
That's an integer space.
And it's got an offset.
So what I want to do is I want to produce whatever this rectangle
should be.
But now around here, instead of around here, right?
So I want to essentially, I want to get rid.
I want to subtract that so that I move the rectangle back as if it
were around this thing.
I don't know if that makes sense.
But basically you can think of it like right now, right?
I've got the Min and the max like, you know, the Min is down here.
The max like is up here, right?
And so, what I want to do is I want to take this Vector for the for
the
I want to take this Vector for the for the maximum and I want to be
able to produce that as if I was as if I was here.
And so in order to do that I need to take whatever that offset is and
I need to include the offset in the max computation.
So if previously the maxim would have been you know offset plus Max,
right?
And previously it would have been offset plus Min, right?
This is where they actually would have been.
What?
Need to do now is just roll that into the maximum in.
So I'm just going to I'm just going to pass that offset indirectly and
that way it'll now be based around this this point instead, right?
Hopefully, that makes some sense.
I don't know if it does or not, but hopefully it does.
So I believe I should have to do is just this code right here so that
I'm going to essentially have whatever the bounds were there, now off
of that, and then, I can subtract that since I've added it.
I can subtract that away and basically say, okay, that the center p is
now just an AB style except I'll why it has no offset anymore, right?
Okay, so if I do that, then what I need to do is just say, all right,
let me step in X and Y because we're not really considering Z yet.
And again, that's something that's our next big task that we have to
do, but let me take that ABS tile X, AB style.
Why ABS taozi that we had there before?
Oops?
Where is my?
There it is.
I want to take these to these chunks, right X y&z, I want to take
those chunks.
Ah, you know what?
Only thing I failed to consider though is how big is a chunk, is
actually very large.
So even though we'd be aligned here,
We wouldn't really be, you know, a chunk is something is what like 16
by 16 tiles.
I wonder if that's just too large because I could do it per chunk.
Mmm, I was thinking in terms of tiles but these World positions are in
terms of actual real Choice, we'd only have tiles anymore right there.
Just kind of a thing that's like a was a thing for doing some World
creation.
That still sort of in there is residual, but we don't really have
those anymore.
So, if I'm producing one of these, 16 by 16 tiles, that's, that's a
little dicey, isn't it?
Because that may be too large for the granularity of our our ground
buffer?
Right.
That might be too too big.
It's kind of hard to say, for sure, right.
But if you just think about it, that that might be a bit much.
Now, I don't actually know if that's true or not, but I'm just that's
just what I'm thinking.
Now it would be nice if they aligned because if they aligned, that
would mean that we could just use, you know, we could, we could have
everything stored symmetrically.
So this is a really, really tough call.
This is a really, really tough call.
so,
let's think about this for a second.
If we were just, we don't really think about tiles per chunk much
anymore, right?
They're kind of not really, super much of a thing.
They're just a thing that we use to set that chunked in that's like
the only thing we do.
But the chunk, Tim could be whatever it is and the chunk Tim is in
meters obviously.
And so, you know, that's, you know, that's just how that false out.
And so if we were to say, for example, that one of these chunks was
the
size of one of our ground buffers.
Think about how much easier that would make things for us.
Right, it means we could essentially just sort of cash these ground
buffers directly with the world in a more direct sense, right?
We could we could do something.
It was really really easy.
We could even maybe store them in here.
We could store.
It seems a little wasteful, but you could imagine having the world
chunk say in here, like have an index into the ground buffers array,
that says what ground before it currently has, if it has one.
Right?
So, man, it's, it's really tempting to go that route and I'm kind of
thinking, that, that would be nice.
The only thing I don't love is, you know, storing it in here.
Seems a little bit unnecessary that seems possibly a little bit,
excessive.
Civ.
But you know, who knows?
It's hard to say, hmm.
Hmm.
I think I'm going to try that.
I think I might try that.
Let's, let's see what would happen if I were to do that.
Let's take a brief interlude from this, right?
And see how big those tile chunks actually are.
So what would happen if I were to draw the tile chunks, basically,
right?
So let's let's do that.
If we go in here to where we actually, where we actually draw stuff,
right?
If I were to actually draw the tile chunks that are involved in the
same.
I said, like, what would that look like, right?
Because if you remember inside, Sim region, I'm sorry knots image that
were visible on screen.
If you remember, we've got this, this code right here that basically
does exactly that iterates over the chunks that are involved in a
particular bounded region, right?
And so, if I were to do that, I could, you know, make a thing here,
that just, that just does that rendering, right?
So let's let's just do that.
Let's see what that does.
So when we make that same region right here,
Here it does.
That begin Sim, right?
I'm actually going to do a thing where we write, you know, right in
here, I do a little rendering where we, where we render the chunks
that are in whatever the same region Asim region size.
Sort of thing is, and it won't actually be the same region, it'll be,
just more, some kind of a screen size thing, right?
So if I did it this way, right, like this,
I'm going to go ahead and make a little piece of code for us to do
this here.
So if I, if I do this camera, bounce thing and I say, all right, how
big is the the actual cameras region going to be?
I can do that pretty simply by saying, you know, I've got M to pixels,
right?
And so if I have M to pixels, I can easily get from pixels to M.
So, if I want to know how big the cameras bounce are, right?
I know that the width or the the screen
In M, right is going to be whatever the screen riff was in pixels,
right?
Which is which is this
/ that m 2 pixels, right picks?
Which is, I don't know if we store restore m, 2 pixels.
I don't know if we start pixels to me.
As we probably should pixels to M, right?
So I'll just multiply it by pixels to M, which is just the inverse of
meals, m, 2 pixels, right?
So we've got M to pixels.
So let's go ahead and say pixels to M, I guess I don't need to store
it in the game State.
Oops.
I can just do it here.
1.0 F over m 2 pixels, like so.
So let's go ahead and just do it that way.
So the screen within m is just going to be whatever it is and pixels x
pixels to M, right, that converts for us, and similarly, whatever the
screen height is in meters.
I'm going to do that as well.
Once I know that I can trivially make a Rec Center half, Tim out of
that and just pass that in, right?
It's just going to be
A V3 of screen width in meters screen height in meters and we don't
really care how thick it is at the moment because we're not really
handling Z4, ground generation quite yet.
So once I do that, I can get those chunks out there and the origin.
In this case is just going to be that camera P.
It's going to be wherever the camera actually is right.
And then I can get it, these, the camera bounds again.
So this will basically give me the region that reviewing
Okay, and then what I can do inside here is when we go through to draw
these chunks chunks Z chunk by chunk X were looping over all the
chunks.
When I grab a world chunk out, I can go ahead and say, if there was a
chunk in that location, I'm going to draw a rectangle that sort of
encapsulates, the region where that was, right?
And in order to do that again I just do the reverse the reverse
mapping, pretty pretty straightforward, right?
All I need to do is figure out how big a chunk is.
Is by half draw that at the location where the world chunk is in terms
of, you know, it's exact placement, if that makes sense.
And so, if I take a look here at one of those chunks gives me, I have
the chunk X chunk why in chunk Z, right?
So it's pretty free for me to create a world position that has that
and ask for the difference between that and the camera just like,
we've been doing a million times before, right?
So I have a world position.
This is the chunk center, right?
And that's just going to be equal to excuse me.
The chunk Center is chunk x equals, whatever the chunks chunk exes.
And you know what, I probably should do do I already have a function
for getting the chunk Center because that's what I would really like
Center chunk Point.
That's what I want.
So what I really want to do is have one of these that just gets me at
for a chunk and that's pretty trivial to do as well.
So, centered chunk point that just takes a child chunk.
Exactly.
That's why I wrote chunk like that and actually does this for it.
That's that's exactly what I want.
So I'm going to grab one of those.
And I'm going to say that that's just equal to whatever this chunk had
in it, and so that's going to get me the location.
Oops.
That's going to get me a location of that result.
There we go.
So I'm going to do that and so I can just say centered chunk point,
right?
And that's going to be the central point of this junk.
So then I could do my subtraction and find out where it actually is
relative to the camera.
So this is the relative Center P, right?
And all I have to do, there is say I want to know how to get from the
camera, right?
To that chunk Center.
That gives me the relative P.
So then I'm good and I can now draw the rectangle to whatever the
draw.
Buffer actually, is now I think we just need the rail P, XY here.
And this scan has to be in meters to pixels right?
As we always know, and it also has to be plus the screen Center.
Press it, plus the sorry, the screen Center.
Do we have?
Here's our screen center.
Do we actually compute that as a
We never actually, we need to make this an actual X.
This actually needs.
It's been too long coming.
This actually needs to be just a vector, right?
That has the things in it, that we need something like this, right?
There we go.
And again, so this is again, just kind of compensating for our lack of
render anise.
It's considered plus, m, 2 pixels on that, on that relative one and
yeah, that should basically draw it.
We just need to know how big it is now and to know how big it is all.
We would really need to do.
I've got to give the color too, I suppose.
Let's make it a lovely yellow for now.
In order to draw that we would need to know how big it is, how big?
A
Chunk is, I'm not sure.
Do we have something that gets chunk sizes out, or do we have to
access directly?
I mean, it's in there, right?
It's a, it's chunk, Tim and M, right?
So just be half of that.
I guess what I could do is just say, half of whatever the world is
chunk gym and M, right?
Tim in m, j and m dot XY.
That's the half of that and so that would draw it.
So I can do that.
I got to fix the the stuff that
I did.
What is where is the buffer to find here?
There we go.
Let's go ahead and move that up.
So, probably should lose the surrender.
Comment up to
And this is all for the draw buffer.
So,
so pixels to meters is not off the gamestate, it's just a variable and
subtract needs to take
Dresses of these guys.
And of course, it needs to take a world as well screen center X screen
center.
Why that?
I just made into a vector and this is actually I could have just done
if the bitmap with was actually a D2 here.
This would be a nice vector equation.
Probably should clean that up at some point one more time, do that.
All right, so let's take a look at what that does.
I wanted to see if that would do some and it does absolutely nothing.
Oh wait you know what?
That's because I put that you can't clear the screen after drawing
stuff.
Yeah to say the least, this right here clears, the screen so that kind
of needs to be happening at the very outset of rendering to say the
least.
All right?
Let's try that one more time.
So do I actually see any boundaries, I do?
Not see any boundaries.
Why do I not see any boundaries?
Let's let's double-check what's going on in there?
Let's take a look.
Okay, so we come in here and we clear the screen which is good.
We grab that screen center.
And so then we come in here and we grab the screen with in M.
It's 22 by 12.
We never knew that for this first time.
We know how big our Playfield is 22.
Metres by 12 meters.
Then we're going to make that camera bands.
Let's take a look at what that looks like.
Can't wear bounds - 11:40 11:40 that's wrong.
I should have said wreck.
I don't know why I said half Tim.
That was that was a mistake.
Not has nothing to do with our problem, but that was that was not
true.
That's supposed to be rectangle centered dim because these are
actually the whole the size of the whole thing.
So, yeah, slight mistake there, you know, it happens.
Let's go back through.
And so, then we map these into chunks Pace.
Let's take a look at what happens, their main chunk P Max chunk p.
And so we're going between chunk, 0 and 1.
That seems fairly reasonable.
And there should be chunks there because we have some World stuff
there.
Let's take a look at what the trunk Center P returns for that and that
is what we would have expected.
Let's see what the relative P comes back as for that P.
I forgot the camera again, totally reasonable M for that as a
particular point.
And so I wonder what oh, again.
Yeah, we need to, I can't wait till we get to the render.
So we don't have to keep dealing with all of this.
Obviously, this is in meters which is no good.
We need this to actually be in pixels, right?
And that's really just something you want to set all that up on your
render, then forget about it.
Oh right.
Well two things about this one is I have to remember to actually draw
a rectangle.
I need to remember to actually draw the rectangle as a border but also
I'm doing something weird there, where it seems to be snapping to the
cameras location and that sure why that is.
So let's see, screen centers plus whatever.
The relative position of the camera thing is relative to the camera
that seems right to me.
And then
And the dimension not sure why that was doing what that was doing.
That seems kind of odd to me, but that's okay.
For let's, let's build a bug that a second but I want to do is draw a
rectangle outline, which I believe we actually did here, right?
Didn't we do some kind of an outline outline push wrecked outline.
Of course, we didn't actually.
Looks like, we never actually gave ourselves one of these, that, that
draws it directly mmm-hmm.
Well, sort of all just make one
Let's see.
Draw a rectangle.
And draw a tangle outline.
So let's do draw a rectangle outline and we'll have that take exactly
the same stuff as our draw.
Rectangle function did.
And this will basically do exactly the same things that we were doing
before except it'll do things in pixels instead of doing them in.
Yeah, in M like it was doing before so we'll do a thickness here will
say that it's going to be, you know, I don't know, two pixels thick I
guess that seems fair.
And so then we'll just call draw a rectangle.
With each of the pieces just the same way that we did them before.
So, there's that buffer.
And then we just need to look at none of this stuff matters.
We don't have offsets these, we just have mins and Max's, let's get
rid of that and get rid of that and get rid of that.
And the RG bees will be the same or Judy.
RGB.
Oops.
Of course, this is a little bit nasty, what I'm doing here because
usually when you're debugging something, you don't want to introduce a
new function.
So yeah, we'll probably have to test this and make sure that it works
properly before we actually use it for anything.
But that said, when we do this, let's see, we should be able to do
this by inspection relatively easily.
We have a Min and Max and then we just need to know what the thickness
stuff is.
So for producing new mins, and Maxes, from this, it's going to be
pretty straightforward, right?
Basically, all we need to do here is say for the top and the bottom.
In fact, I don't even know why I bother copying pasting.
This code, this is so simple, but for the top and the bottom to
produce the new minimum, right?
We just want the actual minimum,
in fact, I can do this in terms of what's going to do this this way,
right?
Fill it in exactly.
Okay, so, same exact drill, as before, if I want to draw this
rectangle.
I'm going to start, you know, in the, the bottom left corner, and
obviously, I want to start on the left and and draw to the right.
So, the, the Min and the max are exactly the same for the x coordinate
here, right?
That makes sense.
So they're just going to draw from the, in the same would be true for
this one because we're just drawing the same rectangle from left to
right here.
Nothing particularly odd happening.
There is one thing we might want to do where we we probably want to
back up by the thickness.
So we could say this is - lets just call that t, right?
So we'll back up by the tea and then we'll go out, you know, on the T
right?
And and you know what, I'm going to call this R for radius because
really we're going in and out by it, that makes sense, right?
So we're going to do that.
And then our X at our our y minimum is going to
Be just the, the Min y minus, the are to the Min y, plus the are right
or the V-Max.
Why - the are and the V-Max y plus Z are.
So again, I'm just drawing from the left to the right, and then using,
either the minimum a little bit around the minimum, or a little bit
around the maximum to produce that thick line for my rectangle outline
there, and then the exact same thing in, you know, Swizzle to
Around for the left and right sides.
Right.
I'm going to say, OK, I want to draw from the top to the bottom,
right?
So in this case, it's my, it's my ex that's going to go.
If that it's my ex that's going to go just within a narrow band of
itself like so and it's going to be the the left side is going to be 2
Min.
This side is going to be the max the right side.
Not having good typing day.
There we go.
And same thing here.
Okay.
And
The why will range between it's full, you know, range from the Min to
the max as you might expect and that'll happen.
The same in both cases.
Right.
So nothing particularly out there, okay?
So let's just spot.
Check this.
Again, for top and the bottom.
So first, we're going to draw the top and really this is this is not
actually true in all cases, so we probably should say Min and Max X,
because if we flipped our coordinate system, it wouldn't be top and
bottom in that order would be bottom and top but either way.
So we start off with that Min and we subtract our from it, because
we're trying to be a little bit further to the left when we start and
we go to the right again, start on the left.
Go to
The right and for the top and the bottom ones, we do first.
The Min minus r 1 plus r.
So we're just doing a radius of our around that Min and then the same
with the max, right?
Very very straightforward there.
Then doing it the other time, we're doing exactly the opposite, so
we're going to start at the at the top.
Start at the top, go to the bottom, go to the bottom, right?
And if that top one, we want the left side, - are the left side.
Plus are the left side, right?
Side?
The right side - are on the right side.
Are so that seems pretty reasonable and we could also pass this in so
if we wanted to because we could just make the thickness of parameter
so we can draw the things as thick as we want them to be which seems
pretty reasonable.
Oh oops, forgot we have in our hmm, so I can't do radius.
All right back to T that could see it is.
So sad.
We really need is for that to be color.
In fact, you know what,
I'm going for it.
People.
Are you seeing this happen?
It happened right there.
You saw it.
Didn't you?
I know you guys saw it.
So, there we go.
Lovely.
Okay.
Oops, and that's car.
Now, this is going to be draw a rectangle outline now.
And it does not take 6 arguments.
That's true because oh snap I just added the color vector.
And so now it is, all right?
So now we just have to figure out what I totally totally computed this
wrong and I don't know why.
And so, we're going to have to go figure out what on Earth is
happening there, because that's just totally wrong.
Can see, it's almost right, right?
It's almost getting to the part where it seems reasonable, but it's
still kind of just kind of messed up.
So, let's try and figure out what's going on there because I have no
idea.
And if I don't have any idea,
Then we can't move forward.
Okay, so drawing a rectangle outline that looks like.
It was doing exactly the same thing as the filled rectangle is doing.
But so I don't know, there might be some bugs in it still, but at the
moment I want to go back here and just take a quick look at this and
see what I was doing.
Oddly
so,
When I was 25, when I was Finding, I guess.
Let's see.
We did.
The rec center, Doom happened to chunk space.
We mapped into the chunk space.
So now we've got chunks iterating over the chunks, we get the chunks
enters out, we subtract them from wherever the camera is, which gives
them something relative to the screen center, which is what we'd
expect, right?
So, this should be drawing a rectangle.
I don't I don't really understand why that is failing to draw the
rectangle that we would expect screen center X Plus m, 2 pixels Rel
p-x, why?
Because that is whatever the distance is between that chunk Center
that we just got and the camera P.
So what's the problem?
M, 2, pixels, we are scaling properly and we're offsetting properly.
I'm confused.
I do sort of wonder.
I do sort of wonder if there's something weird going on here but I
suspect it probably isn't.
oh,
Duh.
Draw a rectangle to does not take a width and a height.
I just, instead of looking at it, I just was like, oh yeah, the width
and the height it's taking within height there because I looked at
that function, but that just happens to be based off of 0.
So that's just stupid.
That was just me being dumb.
I don't know if that's a love shame worthy, but it just me being
stupid.
So really if this is direct rectangular outline, what we need to do is
say there's the screen key of it, right?
Is this and
And we need the screen dimension.
Is this and we need to actually do compute the Min and the max, right?
So it's - screen dim so screen.
P+ screen dim
Simple.
Alright, so that was just a bunch of stupidity.
Oh and of course again we have our, we have our, why flipping problem.
That is always super annoying.
I feel like that's one of those things where you just like, at this
point, I probably should have just introduced some render stuff at the
beginning, because I said it so many times, but it's always really
hard to know, right?
I mean, you never, you never really know.
What's going to save you time versus cost you time.
Sometimes it's really clear and other times it's just not and like
maybe it's still the case that this was a smarter thing.
You to just handle it all the time.
You know, it's just, it's just really tough and so I don't know what
the answer is to that.
I really don't.
All right, so we're getting there, although we still have a problem
which is are chunks are drawn to Tiny, right?
Because obviously that can't be what the chunks actually are.
Because if that was how big the chunks actually were, then we would
they would not actually be able to cover everything.
So I'm off by a half bear, let's see what, that's why that actually is
the case.
So oh, because I already did the half dim here, that's why
All right.
All right, so now we've got our chunks and we can see how big they
are.
You kind of see that, they're like way too large.
I think for storing, if we were to use those as our ground buffer
points, I think they're just they're much too big and so I do Wonder a
little bit if maybe we should make them smaller and try to go with
that as our tiling size.
So that everything's kind of uniform.
So I don't know if that's a good or a bad idea.
Let's take a look at what would happen real quick.
If I was to change that size down,
So that it was a porter of its size, right?
I don't know what would happen there.
Exactly.
But you can kind of take a look at this and see, that's a more
manageable size of a chunk in terms of something that we would use
right to store Graphics.
I feel like that's, you know, that's not, it's possibly a little
larger than maybe I would want, but it's workable, right?
It's a workable size.
And we could even go potentially a little bit smaller than that.
It depends.
You know, there's obviously costs involved in doing each of these
things but you can kind of see now where we're at and so maybe we just
maybe we just do, maybe we just try doing the the ground chunks at
that resolution and we see how that goes.
So, the other thing we could do now is actually set that chunk size,
based on what we want, you know,
How big a 256 by 256 block is actually.
So for example, we could say instead of setting this house, instead of
this having anything to do with tiles per chunk at all in fact,
because we don't really care about that anymore, right tiles for chunk
is literally not a thing if you take a look it just doesn't matter.
So what we could do is instead back figure out how big 256 by 256 is
and just say that, that's the size of the thing that we want to put
there.
Right?
And make sure that chunks are exactly that size in float space, so
that it all kind of just works out relatively nicely.
This would also be a good.
If if we were being super conscientious, we would probably also want
to make our m 2 pixels something integral right because right now our
m 2 pixels you know we're setting that as some kind of particularly
odd value and so if we were going to set it let's see what it actually
is maybe we can set it to something that's going to be a little more
amenable to making the renderer and the world kind of get along nicer
in that sense, right.
Let's take a look there.
So, when we set our m, 2 pixels right here,
What's a coming out to be gamestate m, 2 pixels.
So you know that's not a particularly friendly number.
Similarly, the inverse of this
Not a particularly friendly number.
So it would be kind of nice, if there was a way for us to make these
things.
Be relatively, well, behaved, right, like a power of 2.
So if we were to change it to say, 32 it's in between 32 and 64,
right?
But like if we were to do that, I wonder how hard that would be for us
to get by if we were just say.
M 2 pixels, you know is going to be 32.
That's just what it's going to be.
Right, that obviously changes the scale of our world, right?
But it's kind of arbitrary where we place those things, but that looks
kind of nice as a tiling size and we can just make our, you know, our
our tile side and M are tile side in meters.
Could I mean I've tried all side in pixels.
We could we could change.
We could we could make that kind of fungible to make it a little bit
larger, right?
Or something like this because they don't we don't really care.
Outside of pixels is just something that we're using as a purely
synthetic Concept.
In fact, let me get rid of this, we can just get rid of this for now.
So let's say we were going to do that right?
When we were actually doing that.
In our world.
Let's see here, when we were doing this in our world, we initialized
things, where was it right here tile side in meters.
So where do we actually pass that in?
Where do we, where do we set that?
First of all.
So I don't actually know, initialize, where we set it right here.
So you pass the tile side in meters and we put the tile depth in
meters, right?
And
Like I said, I don't know that we really care about that.
Particularly much that tile side m is really just something that we're
using as a totally synthetic concept.
So I'm thinking that that we could probably just we could probably do
without it right because really what we're doing is we're just using
it.
For this world creation stuff, the chunk position from towel position.
That's really the only place we're using it at all.
So I think we could I think we could get away with this, I think we
could and if we did I think there'd be some bonuses for us in that.
So I think maybe that's something we want to think.
That's maybe something we want to try so if we were to initialize the
world let's say not with that tile sided M let's just see what would
happen if I start to pull that concept out.
So tile sided m is no longer going to be in there.
I guess tile depth in meters.
Let's see what happens.
If neither of those are in there, who's all the people that need it,
right?
So the people that need it, our other than our initialization, there's
this function, which tries to do things in tile space, which we use
only for World building at this point.
There's, that's the same thing.
It's all the same thing.
Alright, so here this is basically just to do how big we want things
to be for.
Section purposes.
Which again we could just our is purely arbitrary values that we just
sighs to our home taste.
Same thing with this, this is just camera bounds picked randomly
these.
In fact, this could now be driven off the screen size, which would be
even better.
So it looks like really, there's just not that much to this, so let's
try it.
Let's try going without it.
Right?
And and instead, making that chunk demand M be something that's
derived off of a screen size off of
something that will be easy for us to work with in a more exact way.
Right.
So when we do this initialization, what I want to do is I want to just
pass the chunk Tim in M directly in here.
So so we're going to pass that chunk Tim.
In meters and we'll just assign it right jump given M like so.
That's all we need to do there.
We're going to go ahead and move this guy.
This this function out because now this is going to be something
that's really only used just temporarily with our world building
stuff, and we'll get rid of it entirely once we move to a more
freeform world-building.
So right here, we don't even need to know this stuff.
So we just have to have whatever that tile side m, whatever we want it
to be, we can say that.
It is what it is for now.
Now, telecommuters just 3.0 just to use the old values, but again,
because this is totally throw away and not important at all.
So that'll be in there, which is fine.
Let's see position from top position, got to put that up a bit higher.
okay, and then we just need to fix these values because this is
something that people that
People were using for, you know, figuring out how high things weren't.
So, these are sort of game, speccy, kind of things.
So maybe I'll take this opportunity.
This is turning into much more of a clean up day than I expected.
I was going to work on the ground stuff, but I always like to take the
opportunity to do things more, right when I can, because you always
try to move things toward a good State and that's just, you know,
something that we kind of need to do.
So I don't know.
This kind of feels like we want sort of a game, a set of gain metric
things in here, and I guess I could stick them off of the game state
for now, that's
Seems totally fine, but this will basically be something like, you
know, our floor height kind of a thing like typical floor height and
that'll actually be, you know, what these people would use for tile
depth at M, if that makes sense, and and that'll be set to that 3.0
value.
Let's see here tile depth in meters.
This will be typical floor height.
Let's keep going here to other people's stuff initialise world.
So that's going to be that chunk Tim right?
M and sort of what I was saying there was.
Okay.
So if m 2 pixels is 32, then a chump chump, dimming M.
I kind of want that to be based off of this value, so,
If I initialize some of these here, if m, 2 pixels was 32 and the
ground buffer height, right?
So ground, buffer, width and height these guys, if I move them up here
and think about these a little bit, if I just leave those up there for
now, if I want these guys to play nicely with this, right?
What was to try to think a how I could work out these values.
So 256 divided by 32 is 8, right?
So that will divide perfect.
If I want to say the chunk dim is the same number of meters as a
ground buffer, right?
So all I would have to do there is say alright and you know what, I'm
going to go ahead and do my meters since since I'm using here, I'm
going to say pixels to meters.
So if I want to make this come out exactly, which I kind of do, right,
just because I want to make it so that we're not having to do a bunch
of fractional things when we're actually talking about pixel stuff.
So
I have both of these and then I want to know how big that chunk
Dimension should be right?
So this is the world chunk dim in meters.
Really all I have to do is derive that from these two values.
So if I make this this here what I would do is I take the pixels to M
value and just take whatever that ground buffer with is that I want
and say, okay that's going to be how that's going to be how big
The chunks are right.
Now we just know they're 256 by 256.
Right?
And similarly I can do the ground before height here.
Same way.
And then this, the world Chunk.
We were just kind of saying that they were.
I think we were saying they were three high but, you know, I don't
know what we're going to do with that eventually.
Again, that's, that's more Z, handling stuff.
We've got to sort of work out over time, but once we've got that,
What's that typical floor height?
This guy right here.
All right, we'll do game State, typical floor height and that'll be
set to there.
Okay, so that's fine tile side and meters.
Again, this is kind of just like how big those stairwells are so tile
side and M.
I don't really know what we want to do there.
I mean, we can sort of leave that in here.
We could we could do that for just for these guys tile size of M, we
could just say that it's still what it was before even though we have
there's no such thing as a tile anymore, but that's fine and similar
the tile.
Hm.
With the typical floor height.
And then we just get rid of all these.
So we kind of are just using those in the World Builder now which is
really where they should have only probably existed in the past
because the other stuff doesn't care about this at.
All right?
Side m.
Yeah.
Depth in meters.
Decided m.
And so this is the camera bound stuff.
So I think the camera band stuff actually should be done a little
differently, right?
Because now, we're actually producing proper camera bounds.
Because I went ahead and did that, right?
This is actually the camera bounds screen with the meter screen,
height and beater, and M, right scammer Bound in M.
Anyway, should say
And so if we do that I feel like the best thing to do would be to use
that for our Sim region as well, right?
Because instead of this nonsense with tile spans which we don't care
about the don't have anything to do with anything.
What we really want to do is say look the camera bounds for the same
region, right?
So we can call this Sim bounds or something, right?
This imbalance should just be the same as the camera bounds with an
apron added with some amount of apron added, right?
So really all I want to do is like add radius to whatever the camera
Bound in m is.
And then just say, however, much Sim Space we want to add beyond that,
right?
And so that's, you know, I don't know what amount that actually is
going to be, but if we were to say, okay, you know, we want to go, I
don't know.
D m in each direction or something like this, right?
Then that's that's how much we would do.
I could actually say sim bounds expansion is.
Is this right?
Like, so let's do how big do we actually want to expand here?
And there we go.
So, yeah.
So that's a bunch of Randomness that I just did and let's find out how
bad the, I broke everything.
So, it seems like we're still in exactly the same situation that we
were in before so that's good and yeah, it looks like we might be.
The only thing about it is that does seem kind of tight in terms of
our in terms of our our zoom level.
They're like our m 2 pixels in this case,
You know, being off.
So I guess we do.
We maybe want to let it be a little bit different than that, you know.
We might want to say alright.
Let's do something where it's a little closer to what it, what it was,
previously, something like something like 48, right?
M pixels.
That was very close to what it used to be, right?
So this is more more are our speed, right?
That puts a little bit closer and or I could do it as exactly 42.
I wonder what that actually ends up being
Oh F, over 42.
Point 238 is still.
It would be really nice.
It was a power to but I don't know how sensible that actually is and
since the renderer scales things, I don't know but we'll go with this
for now.
All right.
So at that point we're almost out of time.
Unfortunately, I spent too much time.
Well, I kind of spent the time that I think we need to spend going
through that stuff and working it out properly.
But what I need to do now, right.
Is once I have that going, we're in a position to actually do the
stuff that I wanted to do at the outset, which is when we're doing
these rectangle, outlines, we are now in the position to request a
particular World chunk, right?
So, if I wanted to draw World chunk here, what I could do is I could
say, all right,
When we draw those World chunks because we were drawing the them
before, right?
So ground buffer, we're drawing these ground buffers here, right, when
we're drawing these ground buffers.
What I could do is say, all right, I'm going to request, I'm going to
make sure that we have whatever the ground buffer is that we would
have needed here, right?
Don't know if that makes sense, and the ground box that we would have
needed.
Here is whatever this chunk Center P says we needed, right?
So we would look through and we'd say, okay, for that chunk Center p
and this
has not the code be actually want to use but we'd say Okay, ground
buffer, index,
Right.
Equal zero, g buffer.
Index is less than the trance, State ground, buffer count.
Right.
+ G, buffer index.
And we basically say, if, you know, we, we could find this one, right?
If we could find one, the one that we actually want.
Then we would not have to do anything, but if we can't find it, then
we have to actually produce one, right?
So, we doing a loop there where we basically saying all right?
For each of the ground buffers if the ground buffer in question
equals, the one that we want, then we can we can forget about it and
we found it, right?
So found false and true.
So if a particular ground buffer that we're looking at around buffer,
Number four, index.
If that one's location is the location that we actually want.
Right, so if it's p, is equal to choose me?
Is equal to whatever that that chunk Center p is right.
And we have a comparison function to these, I believe.
Let's take a look here.
Is canonical are in same chunk.
That would do it, right?
so we could say are in same chunk these two
If that's the case, right?
If two things are, if these two things were in the same chunk, then
that means we already have a ground buffer for that else.
I'll say you know if this one is not valid, if this particular ground
buffer is not valid, I should probably actually get the ground buffer
out here, huh?
Buffer.
Ground pepper.
So grab the ground before out, I'll say, OK, if this ground buffers
position is the one that we want, then we know we have that ground
buffer already and if on the other hand, its position is not valid.
So there was nothing in this ground buffer then that's actually a
ground buffer we could use to fill with the one that we actually
wanted, right?
So we could say, oh, okay,
Excuse me, we want to actually fill this ground buffer.
So I'm going to store empty buffer here and say if it wasn't valid
we'll just we'll just grab it now.
Like I said, this won't actually ever evict anything so this is not
the code.
We actually want to use and it's also extremely inefficient there's
that.
But for now this will actually just sort of do a little bit of it.
So at the end of this, if if
Haven't found it and we found an empty buffer.
Then we just want to make, you know, we want to fill that buffer and
we've got that filled ground chunk that we already did.
So we can just call that with all the stuff that we needed right past
that empty buffer.
And we know which position we're trying to fill, its the chunk Center
P, right?
And that will fill the chunk, excuse me.
Right.
Really pretty straightforward.
Nothing.
Particularly odd going on.
Their function does not take two parameters.
Really?
How many does it take?
Oh, cuz we have an assertion there.
All right, well, I can pass you the world.
I'm fine with that.
And this needs to be an address.
So, let's take a look at what that does.
So for some reason, well we're almost correct, but for some reason
we're not quite enumerating all of the chunks but it can see we're
almost there.
We just don't quite have it.
Now we're run out of chunks eventually, but you can see we're almost
there in terms of what we need to do for the basics.
But for some reason we're missing one chunk, and it's like when we
iterate, what if we're on it directly, it works, but otherwise, it
doesn't that's kind of a bizarre bug.
When you say
Pretty unusual.
And then eventually here we should run out of these.
Hmm.
In fact I'm kind of surprised we haven't run out of them already.
I guess we made a lot more of them but you can kind of see how it's
working here.
All we'll need eventually is an eviction scheme which we should be
able to do tomorrow and then we'll be in good shape but we have a bug
here and I don't know.
We could probably leave that bug till tomorrow I'm not too terribly
concerned about it but
Well, you can go for a long time.
This is kind of weird.
How many did we say?
We had there we go.
Finally got to the end.
I'm like we're not evicting anything.
So we should be able to get to the end, but it took a long time.
I guess that's when you have a pretty pretty big cash there, it's all
good.
All right.
So what I was saying though is
I'd like to take a look and find out it's a little bit weird.
I'm not sure why we're getting that that bug where we're not ever
producing one of those chunks there.
That's a little bit odd, and I'm not sure why.
That is, we're doing our Loops properly from why from the main chunk
to the max chunk, and we're actually including that Max chunk as well.
We're doing that on X and Y and so it would seem, it would seem like
that, should we?
Work.
But it's not and so something that we've done here is is off.
It's not actually filling the chunks that we think they're feeling or
I guess there could be a problem with the way we're rendering them,
but that seems a little less likely.
So I'm assuming that it's
Do with the way that we're actually filling them in here and I'm going
to push do here.
Also to do this is super inefficient, fix it tomorrow.
Also, it doesn't affect anything.
So I'm just going to take a little bit.
How much time we got.
I'm only six minutes over.
I'm just going to take a little bit of liquor to see if I can just
spot what I did wrong because I would like you know me I don't like to
leave bugs like that.
So I'm just going to take a quick look to make sure I can't just see
what it was.
That that was done stupidly here, right?
All right, so if we have the camera Bound in meters, we know that
that's the whole screens worth.
We're then going and mapping that into chunks Pace to get, you know,
the Min and the max.
They're the two corners of it which seems like it should be pretty
straightforward.
We're looping through those getting to see if there's chunks that.
Uh-oh.
Right, it's just ha ha.
This was working totally perfectly.
It's just, I was only drawing since this was a drawing loot.
Before I only drew it if there was a chunk if there's actually data in
the chunk.
Whoops.
So that's that's it.
Yeah, that's that's all there was to it.
Um, so that was kind of funny.
So what was happening is
Renault entities in those chunks so it just skipped them.
But then, when I would move into it, my entity was in the chunk.
So then it became active.
That's kind of cute.
You gotta admit that's kind of cute but problem solved.
And so, there you go.
It's so now really all we need to do tomorrow.
We have some issues, we probably will have to address when we want to
get things.
Totally right?
Like, how these things line up.
Exactly.
Whether they have but properly and how it scales up and down there,
there's some stuff.
We're going to have to address.
It's not all unicorns and rainbows at this point, but all we really
need to do tomorrow.
Now is generate them seamlessly, which is not really that hard.
And then we'll be good to go.
Now, of course, like I said, we still want to put this on a separate
thread and make it more efficient and stuff like that, so that we
don't get hiccups like we're getting right now but on the whole, this
schemes working quite nicely already and we haven't really even done
anything fancy with it.
So I think that's pretty cool or at least I think it's pretty cool and
hopefully you think it's pretty cool as well.
So yeah with that with that I think we can go ahead and go to the Q&A.
Please prefix your questions with Q:, so I
I can see them and yeah and I'll answer them.
so you can see here, where we still had
Alpha.
That wasn't quite all the way in.
Right?
And so you get some that showing through there, I guess I'm not
exactly sure if that's what that's from or not.
That's an interesting.
It's an interesting artifact.
It's that it's the chunk boundary.
Hmm.
What is Meera Tori syntax?
I'm not sure what you're referring to, but you could be referring to
Miura Tori for syntax, which is this.
Right.
I don't know if you can see that but basically what that is is get
double brackets, everything.
And the reason for that was because in the old days there was no
possible way.
You could have a compiler, there's no way you could write code without
doing it this way.
That would ensure that the compilers would always do the right thing
with respect to scoping for because M SV C.
Would put it in the outer scope and GCC.
We put it in the Interscope so this was a way of putting it.
Extra scope in there so that msec would behave the same way as GCC.
It's not necessary anymore, but in the old days it was the only way to
do it.
Well, the random graphs possibly based on some seeds so that the
ground buffer can be regenerated the same as it was after it gets
evicted.
Well, not only will it be?
It is see.
It's already based on whatever chunk it came from and so that's kind
of cool in that.
It will always be able to regenerate itself and that's going to be
pretty handy to being based off that because we'll use that to make it
seamless tomorrow as well.
Will be nice.
I'm sure it's been asked a bunch but any tips for what language to
start with and how to start?
Not really.
It's been so long since I started, I don't know.
So I've said many times in the Stream all it really the answer is
Whatever Gets you into programming it, whatever you can find, that
seems like you're having fun with it.
If you've literally never programmed before because what we're doing
here with, see is too hard for someone who's never programmed before.
It's, you know, right, like C and C++ or kind of the advanced language
right there.
They're, they're definitely when you have your, your adult pants on
and, you know, your little baby pants should probably not be the same
pants, right?
so,
When I was little and I started programming, I started programming in
basic and you know, and then I went I think to Pascal after that but
that was the same as see, more or less.
And then I went to see after Pascal kind of faded out of popularity.
And so I would recommend probably a similar two-stage process.
I'd recommend some language that's easy to use and forgiving.
And has a good standard library and like isn't for writing efficient
code or doing a lot of the stuff that we do on the stream.
But that lets you play around with it and be happy with coding and
then once you're ready to like level up and start taking more control
over things than you can come, you know, to see
Huh.
Someone said they actually found a Miura Tori for statement in the
wild.
No way.
That's crazy.
I had no idea.
I didn't know anyone used it, but me.
That's pretty interesting.
I wonder.
I wonder what that is.
Yeah, you're right.
It's there it is.
Re-find obstacle.
Very interesting.
That's very, very interesting.
It's only in that one routine.
I direction-- hit distance hit index.
Location, hit normal.
You know, it doesn't really look like my code, otherwise.
So I don't know.
That's kind of weird.
I wonder if someone like, yeah, I don't know.
That's very interesting.
I wonder who wrote that code for why?
That's bizarre.
Thanks for the reference.
Why are you not passing world as an address when calling functions?
I'm pretty sure we are.
Where are you seeing us?
Not do that.
Like here's a world pointer and I'm pretty sure pretty much everyone.
It gets passed as a pointer, right?
It's almost always fast as a pointer.
Where do you see it?
Not being passed as a pointer.
My question.
Are you going to prevent Z buffers and texture scaling Z buffer is no
because we don't need them.
And so they're going to Baby way they.
They would be both inefficient and lower quality so we will just be
doing sorting because then we can do proper Alpha compositing and not
have to do any z-buffer stuff.
But I don't know.
I mean, I suppose we could use an early out kind of people.
We don't really, we're not going to have.
Yeah, I don't think.
If we did anything that was like a z-buffer, it'd be more like an
occupation buffer, like an occupancy buffer, that was just designed to
early out chunks of the screen.
Texture scaling though.
Yeah, we will be doing and rotation.
Any other questions?
Does not look like it.
Is there any other possibility for a z-buffer?
Not not sure what that means.
What do you mean by?
Is there any other possibility for a z-buffer z buffers for 2D games?
It's really it's unclear.
Why you would ever use one?
I mean, one reason is, if you, if you were doing a very expensive
Shader calculations,
right?
And you were trying to use the Z buffer, you're trying to draw front
to back and use the Z buffer to early out so that you wouldn't do
Shader computations.
For something like this, right?
Instead of drawing back to front, you draw front to back with
destination Alpha and and save those Shader calculations, right?
And, you know, we could do that.
But you still don't really need a z-buffer.
Even in that case, right?
You don't need a z-buffer, you just need a binary buffer at that
point, right?
Like something that says, yes or no, and you still end up with the
problem that it's like, I mean you can't you can't actually early out
on the outfit edges so I don't know.
It sounds dicey to me.
But I'm not a rendering expert, you know.
I'm not I'm not one of those guys who spends all their time, think
about rendering and so maybe there's a good reason why you would do
it.
But I'm imagining that that for us, you know, some kind of a course,
occupancy thing and then just
Render, you know?
Front to back with destination alpha or, and, and if Alpha is 1, then
you early out would be the smartest thing to do because I can't see
the z-buffer ever really coming in and especially, yes, especially if
you do front to back with Associated front to back with destination
Alpha, I feel like, wouldn't you done?
Just use Alpha to determine whether you kill or not?
Yeah, I'm sorry.
You'd have to ask somebody who was more of a hardcore, rendering guy,
whether there'd be any reason easy.
But it doesn't, it seems like if you the only thing you would ever do
is use destination Alpha, probably, and you'd early out in the
destination Alpha, but why you would want to waste all the bandwidth
and the testing on a z-buffer when I just don't see what it gets you.
So I'm not I'm not feeling it.
I'm not feeling it.
You're right, I did miss your question.
I will, I will be below.
I will go back to that.
I just now that you said it, I can see it, but I must have gotten.
I must have missed it when I was scanning.
Couldn't you set the Sim bounds expansion from the screen dimensions
or camera bounds in meters or something?
Hope I'm understanding correctly.
Yes we could.
I just don't know what to set it to because basically like the Sim
bounds are just what we want to hear like acoustic bounds or
simulation related stuff bounds.
I mean, basically what the sin bounds does is it simulates the stuff
that's on screen and some amount of distance around the screen that we
say, is what we want.
Fidelity for.
And so it's stuff that might make noise that we could hear or is
people who might walk onto the screen or just walked off the screen
and might walk back on and we don't want them to go fall into some
slow update Loop.
We want them to be like integral to the gameplay or something that
point, right?
So, I don't know, right?
Like I really don't know.
What it should be set to.
I don't know that it, you know, should it be an extra screens worth?
Should it be some fixed distance worth?
I have no idea.
And that's why I was put to do there because until we have some more
idea of like what should be happening?
I really don't know what to set it to but you could certainly set it
based off the things you were.
Suggesting I just even based off of those things.
I don't know what it would be, right.
So we'll see.
We be implementing Dynamic lighting or any deferred rendering.
For lots of real lights.
Etc.
So the problem with deferred lighting is that transparency, doesn't
really work very well.
You got to do a lot of random stuff to make transparency work.
If you do deferred lighting, I'm sorry, deferred shading.
Really?
so, you know, I mean it probably not because you got so much
Horsepower with the, with modern gpus for a 2-D game.
It might just be a waste of time to deferred rendering and you give up
that translucency and a bunch of other things.
So I don't know that it's a good trade-off.
Deferred rendering tends to be more about managing depth complexity.
And so I feel like we'll probably able to manage depth complexity in
other ways red because the only thing deferred rent, like literally
the only thing deferred rendering does, is it cuts down on the number
of computations that you have to do?
If you tend to overdraw parts of the screen a lot, right?
That's it.
That's all it does.
It doesn't change anything other than that.
And so, if you have a lot of depth complexity, where you're saying,
like all right, you know, I'm looking at, you know, things through
other things.
Like I've got kind of this this layered approach
We're I don't know, like there's kind of a mountain in the way of a
thing in a railing in this that nothing in.
So I want to like kind of cut that down to just what's actually
visible and not do computations for things that are stacked on top of
each other.
It makes you know a fair bit of sense but how much of that stocking
will we actually have versus the cost of doing the Deferred rendering
right?
And so I don't know if it turns out that we're in a situation where we
have tons and tons of overdraw
Then you know maybe it makes sense but if it turns out that we don't
then deferred rendering just a waste of time and it's worse because
you don't have translucency and other things like that you might want
or you have to do crazy stuff to get them.
She is there anyone.
You can suggest for a hardcore render guy.
Mmm, well, they're few and far between these days.
But, you know, you'd want to ask like someone on, maybe like an
Nvidia.
One of those guys who does the Nvidia, like, sort of research and
Nvidia research guy, or maybe someone on the one of the engine teams.
Like, you know, like a frostbite rendering guy, or one of the guys
from the Unreal Engine rendering guys.
I mean, like I said, they're few and far between these days.
So I don't know.
But but yeah, I suspect they're going to tell you that a 2-D game.
Usually doesn't need a z-buffer.
But you know.
Could be wrong.
All right, I think I'm going to go ahead and wrap things up.
I think we're at the end of the questions about what we were doing.
Programming last, I'm pretty happy with how that came out.
I am pretty happy with that.
So I think basically all we do tomorrow is turn these into seamless
and then we will have our sort of infinite ground texture that
Wanted, which is pretty great.
All we got, and we an eviction scheme, so got two more things to do.
And so that's what we'll do tomorrow first.
We'll get rid of the seams because that seems to be that that's the
most ugly part of it, right?
First, we'll get rid of those seams and then we can go ahead and yeah,
we can go ahead and do the other part.
That's pretty cool.
I'm happy with that.
All right.
Anyway, I'll go ahead and shut things down here.
Save our mischief.
Okay, thank you, everyone for joining me, for another episode of
handmade hero.
It's been a pleasure working with you.
As always, if you would like to follow along the source code at home,
you can always pre-order the game on handmade here at dot org.
Basically, you can pre-order it and it comes with a link to the source
code so you can download it every night after I finish programming and
play around with the stuff we do on the stream that day.
We also have a patreon if you want to support our video series that's
just purely optional subscription thing.
If you're interested in it, it's always much appreciated.
You could check that out.
We also have a tweak bought, the tweets, the schedule, so if you're
trying to catch the scream stream and want to know when it's going to
be, that's that's the place to go.
And finally we have a news inform site and the news and firm site has
a bunch of great stuff on us, a place to ask questions, it has ports
to Linux and Mac.
If you want to follow along on other platforms, that kind of thing.
And it's got an antidepressant guide done by members of the community,
which is pretty great for following along catching up with old
episodes.
So definitely check that out.
If you're interested.
Otherwise I will see you back here tomorrow.
When we
We'll finish up our infinite ground texture, same time, same place, 5
p.m.
Pacific Daylight Time right here on Twitch.
So thanks for joining us and I will see you tomorrow.