Hello everyone and welcome to handmade hero.
The show recode a complete game live on Twitch.
No engines, no libraries.
It's just us coding here doing everything by hand and we are in the
middle of optimizing so code.
So I want to kind of get back to that if you want to follow along at
home today is day 120.
So if you would like to follow from where I am today, you can open up
a day, 170.
Sorry, day, 119 zip file and that is the source code that is
Starting with today.
So we had sort of two more things optimization why's that it wanted to
talk about where we did it.
You know, sort of rudimentary optimization work on this routine and we
got it down to 48 cycles and I tried to make a little thing that would
count cycles and it's fine.
You know, I mean we did a thing that counts sarnax, not cycles, that
counts instructions.
And we did a little thing that does exactly that.
So you can actually see
See here.
Mmm, you can see how we kind of did that.
We made a little thing which goes through and pound defines all of the
intrinsics that we were using to sort of count.
How many of them there were.
But but this, this got Fabien, this bothered Fabien at like a deep
emotional level and not because of that he was fine with that but he
did not like the way that we were attributing.
Our accounts here and the reason he did not like them.
Was because he felt like it was just not a useful number by putting
the throughput directly in here, right?
He didn't think that was a good idea.
The reason he didn't think that was a good idea is because well, the
throughput number or tea includes the parallelism of the CPU, right?
So basically the three put number, if it says like this one right here
that says, one-third.
If it says one-third, what that means is that the processor could do
three of those in a cycle, effectively.
If everything was going probably
up early and it was pipeline properly and whatever else has to happen,
it's going to be able to do three of those in a cycle, right?
So it's counting in that the way that it's actually doing that is
because it has multiple units that can do.
And and so what it can do is when it sees an and it could issue up to
three of them.
At the same time, hence, you get only a third of a cycle to do any
given one of them because you can do three of them in effectively one
cycle or a third of a cycle per, and right, but for something like an
Her multiply, right?
And you look at it, it says one cycle.
That's the throughput for that because there's only one unit that can
do and add or multiply.
We actually went and verified that
But an ad in a multiply could be issued together.
We talked about this a little bit at the end of last stream.
The fact that you could overlap ads and multiplies, which is why I
said things were running so much faster than the total cycle count,
even with the throughput,
Factored in there, you know, it was a situation where it was clear
that like, ads and multiplies were happening at the same time, and so
on.
And so what Fabien objected to was, it's kind of a meaningless number
to add it up this way, because we are capturing the fact that the, and
can be issued three times in one cycle, but we're not capturing the
fact that the ad in the multiply can be issued in, in the same cycle.
So really like either he's arguing and it's a perfectly reasonable.
Double argument, you should change like, the ad in the multiply to be
like half a cycle or some.
I mean, you should you should try to like, incorporate that Crossing
parallelism, but, you know, that's going to be an accurate for obvious
reasons or you should knock out the and, and say, like, okay, you
know, just try to count the total number instructions, like either do
a proper over estimate or a proper underestimate, but like mixing
them, it really bothered him.
So I was like, well, we'll see what we can do.
And I said to him but, you know, I mean, the only way to do this,
right is the way I did it on the 360 which is, I wrote a little
program that tries to simulate the CPU.
And what it would do is it would take all the assembly that you had
and the actual Assembly, not the intrinsics and it would actually go.
And it would figure out exactly what the chip would do to the degree
to, which it was documented.
And that would tell you when there were stalls, like, because
something couldn't get issued in the same cycle as something else or
all these other things you can see, here's how many cycles.
This thing should take best case.
And Fabian was like well yeah they you can do that.
Intel actually shifts a tool for you to do that.
If you want a said it's it's the Intel architecture code analyzer and
I'm like what?
So he pointed me to this and I feel like we should at least try it out
because this would be some way I could show on the stream.
Exactly.
What's happening in the processor will not exactly.
But to the degree that Intel nose and right.
Like Intel
You know, they're the ones who know how it was made and so presumably
and I don't know if maybe they sandbag a little bit to try and prevent
some kind of reverse engineering or something.
But presumably that would mean that all of the things that we don't
know about what will happen with the processor.
They have actually captured in here somewhere, so I don't know.
I've never used this tool before but Fabien said you could just use it
and it would show you that information.
So, let's see, I'll brought it on our code and we can see if we can
get a dump of that.
So,
Here's the windows 64-bit version.
This is supposedly a free piece of software.
Do not know what this license agreement says, does it say anything
about not using this on handmade hero stream?
Let's see.
We are not trying to reverse engineer.
It, we are not trying to distribute it.
We are not expecting them to be liable for when this blows up the
machine.
So, I think we're okay.
Here, I think this is okay.
So let's take a look.
So there is our wind 64.
And like I said, I've never used this before so you'll have to bear
with me.
I don't really know anything about this tool much like visual studio
2013, which we tried on the stream for the first time, this is
development tool.
I have no experience with so I make no promises, but we'll go ahead
and we'll open up.
Where is this W?
Will open up W and we'll dump it in here and if it works, it works.
So there we go.
Alright.
So I don't know why did that, why did that default to to
Compressed air are encrypted.
I don't know why that.
All right, well, we don't really need to encrypt it, that's weird.
All right, how do I decrypt that?
Oh, I guess I've got to go through it this way because it can't handle
the fact that the drive is substituted.
I don't even want to know what that just was people.
And, of course, now, Windows is thinking about it.
So, maybe in classic Windows fashion that the hardest part about
actually using this tool will be getting Windows to stop thinking
about letting me use the tool, which apparently is like this really
long involved process.
I can't actually imagine why that is, but apparently that is okay.
Can you please?
What is the problem?
This is absurd.
So is there something?
I don't understand here about what's going on?
Well, I can use it while we're waiting for that to happen.
I suppose I don't know what's going on.
I can look at it after.
So anyway what Fabien said is that basically what you're supposed to
do is you're supposed to include this h-file temporarily right, you
don't.
This is not actually something you don't build with this normally but
when you want it to give you when you want it, to run it through this
little code analysis tool.
What you do is you include this iaca marks
File, which will go ahead and include in here, right?
So let's go ahead and do that include I see a marks dot h, like so and
then you can use that to Mark the section that you want it to give you
a sort of an analysis of if that makes sense.
So you can see it here and basically all this is is just it's
literally just the markers that you're
opposed to use, right?
And so all I think it really does is emit code that then they're in
out analyzing tool can use to look at your binary and see what's in
it, right?
So what we want to do is say alright, let's do a start and an end
around this block that we were trying to analyze before, right?
So like right here, we could just do a start and then let it, you
know, let it count all that stuff and then we can go down and at the
end of it, just
Do do the end, right?
So oops, is that
That's actually here, I guess, right?
Is that correct?
Start?
Yeah, and end.
Okay, there we go.
So that should be that I think so.
We're going to have to modify the build briefly just to include that
directory, right?
Because it's not going to know where that actually is.
So I need to have some way of telling it to how to find that.
So when we actually compile our stuff, I'll just throw in and include
directory here, right?
I'll go back one, two, directories to this is a CA wind 64 /.
Well no / just I think that's just just it, right?
So let's compile that and see is that not correct?
Backslash backslash I-64 that should be it right?
Oh no we're in the build directory.
Never mind.
So we're building into W build so it's really just one backslash to
get back to the root.
That should be it right.
I see a marks dot h.
Feel like that should have worked although you know what I should do
now?
That I notice that as well for people on other platforms.
It's got a capital letter in the name there.
So for people who are building on Linux that would cause them to into
the consternation.
So let's go ahead and put that in there.
So, why is this giving me grief if I do a w:, would it work?
No, it's still can't find.
I see a marks dot h but I don't.
Oh,
How about I don't edit the removed 32-bit version that's that's good.
Nicely done Casey.
Yeah that could be it.
All right, let's see here.
Well.
That is a problem because it looks like that's not going to work on
this.
Do we need to do VC 64.
Is this what we need to do here?
Trying to figure out which one we would use if we need to use this
one.
Since it's the 64-bit to Burger can't do as mm.
Mm.
It's which kind of makes me wonder.
What are they doing?
I don't know what's.
Right?
GS B, that's pretty interesting.
I don't even know what that is.
That's some food.
Be right there.
That's pretty cool.
All right, so now in theory, we are supposed to be able to.
Let me make sure that we're building an O2.
We are.
So now, in theory, what you're supposed to be able to do is run this
little eye, a see a thing, right?
And you can tell it is a 64-bit thing, you can say that it's a, our
got, an architecture, and nhm is the Nehalem thing that we've got?
Right?
And now we're supposed to be able, I guess it.
Just give it our build, and it's supposed to know,
Like, it's supposed to be able to tell us what the actual cycle counts
are.
And lo and behold, that's exactly what it did.
Check it out.
People look at this.
All right.
So this is pretty great.
Let's go through this and see if we can understand it.
I've never seen one of these before but
Pretty great.
All right, so Port binding in cycles per iteration.
So here is all we've got.
I don't actually know what.
This readout is supposed to tell us though, because, looking at it
here.
That well actually, I guess that could sort of be well let's just
let's just move through it.
But anyway so here's what it says this chart is going to tell us here.
I'm going to hold off on this for a second because I don't necessarily
know exactly what that's trying to tell me in terms of like DV and d
and so on here so I'm not sure oh divider pipe and but D I don't know.
D is data, fetch pipe, okay?
So we're just going to take a look here and see
What's going on, right?
So we've got to move.
And so, I guess what it's telling us is, right?
Is this struction?
This is 1 micro op, right?
Which is the thing that the processor fundamentally operates on
remember, when I said things can have my coop.
So we basically a single instruction might take multiple Micro Ops
because it might be that that instruction itself is actually sort of
broken into multiple instructions inside the processor, basically.
So the things we see are not exactly what the processor executes.
All time, sometimes they are and when something is 1 micro up, then it
sort of is, right?
It's like one, it's one to one, but doesn't have to be so that went
into Port 1.
This went into the these two moles both went into this port.
Now something that I don't actually know what this is trying to say
here, right?
Is, I don't know if that implies that since these went into either
poor it that they would be that they wouldn't conflict.
Like since this is important 5 and this is important 0.
Presumably, they could issue at the same time but I don't see against.
I've never used this tool before.
I've never I don't actually know.
What the, you know, what is actually what it's actually trying to tell
me as far as simultaneous execution is so CP.
Like, I wonder if the CP, what is CP is CP like one clock tick or
something?
Potentially because that would make some sense, right?
Like if you look at this, I don't know if CP means, like maybe that's
when it had to click over and that would make some sense, right?
Because well,
Of course, you've got to multiplies in here so I don't know.
So I'm not sure.
So this may take actually some actually, you know, some study to try
and figure out what all this stuff is.
I mean, I'm sure there's a manual that comes with it and I don't know
that we need.
That right now.
But this is kind of cool because I did not know that they had actually
shipped a tool that you were allowed to use.
Externally that did this sort of stuff that's really great.
That's what we would have had to build ourselves.
When I kind of alluded to, if we wanted to do something that really
looked at the ports.
This will basically tell us on the Nehalem exactly what the those sort
of Port issues actually are right.
And so this is much better than the little janky macros that I was
using and this would be a great thing for us to use.
So I again, wish ICP was listed as what that was going to do a lot of
these other things here.
It's actually says, like, microfusion happened, which I assume is sort
of saying that Micro Ops could be done together in some way.
I'm not sure.
But you can see that this happened a couple times in here, right?
But a lot of those other ones.
0f, what else do we got in here?
Mac, refuse.
With the previous instruction occurred.
So what was that?
Let's see here Jas test.
Okay so basically saying could do these together so it didn't actually
have to count, I guess the jump a test is something that sets the
condition B in the jump jumps on that.
So this is like, you know, a conditional being executed here, right?
And so I guess it was able to fuse those operations together so that
they didn't take a cycle each or anything like this, right?
So some of that.
What else we got here?
Anything else.
Interesting looks like mostly just the carrot and the f.
I don't see anything else.
So, yeah, this is pretty great.
I mean, this is also great because it tells us exactly what
instructions are being executed.
You can look at the assembly, pretty easily in this format and see
what's going on, which is pretty great.
So yeah, this is, this is pretty awesome.
I'm glad you sent this to us.
I also don't know.
It looks like there's some other
Of fun things to like, I don't know.
There's just there's just some fun stuff in here.
Like you can output a graph.
I guess if you install graphviz I don't know.
That's kind of cool, right?
So there's just, I don't know, just pretty cool.
So what this tells us if this is correct, it says that this block of
code should take eighty six Cycles to execute right?
And what's kind of interesting about that is that that is actually
lower than
than what we were observing, right?
Because if you think about it, we were calculating four pixels at a
time, right?
So, 86 divided by 4 is like 21, 22, cycles per pixel.
And so we are clearly half the speed we would be if this were just
executing straight through.
Right based on what this tool is saying.
It says the block, throughput is 86 Cycles.
So I don't know.
Um, that would suggest that we might be waiting on some memory.
That would suggest that maybe we can do some interesting things in
terms of maybe doing some prefetching, I don't know, right?
So I'm not sure it seems like maybe there's some room for improvement
there.
It's something to think about.
So I don't know that we necessarily want to go into that right now,
but I really wanted to kind of see if that work and it kind of looks
like it does.
So that's pretty awesome.
That means we can get rid of all this craft and just have a nice way
of
Really using a tool.
Like I said, it would be nice if I can power to this for you.
Well, this is the next best thing, right?
It's not built into the compiler, so it's a little inconvenient.
You got to do some kind of little janky, a few janky, Little Steps
there, but not on the whole, that was pretty unoffensive, right?
That was not very difficult to do.
And so I'll take that any day over having to write, you know, sort of
like a simulator that I run myself for a processor where I don't
actually have that.
Surly all the documentation about how it's supposed to work.
Right?
If I trust Intel is actually doing a reasonable job on that thing,
then, presumably it should be authoritative and we can run it through
that tool and figure out what they think it actually will take to run.
So that's pretty cool.
All right, so we don't really need to do that at the moment.
So what I'm going to do is I'm going to get rid of that for a minute,
right?
And I can do that pretty trivially this way.
We don't need need that include because most of the time, we don't
really want to be building with that.
It's not it's not part of the program, right?
That's not something that we're really.
Using directly, but we want to kind of be able to perhaps turn it back
on again a little bit in the future.
So that's that's pretty great.
Again, another big thanks to Fabien for that.
He is like I said, kind of on Twitter.
He is our sort of our optimization, our patron, saint of optimization
at the moment and he mentioned something else that we should take a
look at today.
Today's kind of maybe a Fabien clean-up day in that sense.
He mentioned something else that I think it would be nice to take a
look at.
He was
Hang out as well that we didn't take as much advantage of some math
rearrangement as we could and this kind of gets more into actual
optimization optimization, right?
Because all we really did, you know, you saw me do it.
But all I really did write when we were working on this routine is I
wasn't really optimizing, your team.
I would just translating the routine, right?
I was translating the routine from scalar to Cindy, and that's mostly
what we did.
And then I did a little bit yesterday of, like, finding some things
that were easy to pull out into things that could be done in the loop.
We save some cycles that way, but that, that was really it right?
But what he was pointing out is well, first of all, he was saying, you
know, bilinear and squaring, right?
They don't actually have to be done in floating point if we didn't
want to do them floating point, right?
And furthermore, they don't have to be done.
0 to 1, if we don't want to do them 0 to 1.
So what he pointed out is we're doing all these multiplies right.
Mul PS to do the in 5255 4X right word.
These are these are in 0 to 255 space and we're turning into 01 space.
He was saying, you know, at you know, very simply you could just start
with doing that after you did the bilinear, right?
Because you could square numbers just fine.
In 0 to 255 space and you can bilinear, things just fine in 021 space.
So I'm sorry in certain should be five space.
So why are you multiplying all these values?
When, if you just move that after the fact, right?
You would only have to do the multiply on the result.
So let's take a look at that, right?
If we got rid of all of these multiplies, we're just doing the
simplest first step, if I just got rid of all of these multiplies.
So basically,
Everything here was doing that mull.
PS.
We got rid of so I'm just, you know, I'm just killing it right.
Kill rectangle.
I'm just getting rid of it there.
So basically all of these things that we're doing a multiply we just
get rid of all those multiplies and we were doing a lot of multiplies
and multiplies.
We only have one unit, we learned that yesterday, the end of the
stream we only have one unit so those multiplies don't overlap with
each other, you can only get one per cycle at maximum, right?
That was the throughput on those.
I think, and there's only one unit, so they don't duel issue.
So, you know, if you get too many multipliers, you could clog.
Things up.
So we get rid of those multiplies and we just have the square.
So basically what it does is it squares the value in the 0 to 25
range.
So what that's going to mean is that the maximum value and sorry I
guess I can get rid of this as well which is basically to say that
Texel A text will be a textile CA and so on just don't even get
processed at.
All right.
There?
What that means is after we do the bilinear, right?
Hmm.
After we do the bilinear now we could do the conversion, right?
So now when we do the multiplication by what we did, the location, we
can do that.
And I guess I just spotted this, we could do it by pre multiplying
that term into the color term, right?
Because we're already doing a multiplication here, right?
We're already multiplying this by the color, which is a constant.
So what if we just took that divisor and baked it right into the
color, then we wouldn't have to add a new multi, do we just use the
same multiply that we were already doing, right?
So, let's just do that right in color.
I think that's the only place that's ever used.
Right, we've got color are 4X here, right?
That's the only place that's ever used.
So instead, let's go.
Go ahead and do an M&M set 1.
PS of of the info, you know, of
Like, I guess are normalized coefficient will just call that, right?
Of are normalized, coefficient, will bake that in there.
And what's that?
Normalized coefficient going to be right, well, before it was one over
255, right?
It was this
But if you think about it that's not really correct for everybody.
It's going to be correct for Alpha because there was a Rosario 2255
but the rest of these guys got squared, right?
So it really means that the the normalize if they were going from 0 to
255, if they got squared, they're now going from 0 to 255 squared,
right?
So, their Reigns expanded, the range doesn't expand when your 0 to 1 U
Square.
It you stay 0 to 1, that's the magical.
Property of zero to one, right?
But if you actually have a value above one is your 0 to 55 when you
square it, your total value goes up.
So you widen that range.
So we actually need to do here.
Right is have a normalized squared c as well, right?
Which is just to 55 squared, right?
And so that is what we would multiply these guys by right to normalize
them out.
So I believe that if we just do that, think that should work but
famous last words, right?
And hey, guess what it does, right?
Pretty spiffy.
So we got rid of a bunch of work we could do there.
Unfortunately, we didn't save too many cycles.
We're down to forty five Cycles roughly now, but the other thing
that's important to remember at this point, we also don't really know
whether we're starting to be Memory bound here, right?
So, it's hard to say this store that change saved as many cycles, or
who knows what's happening, right?
So, we don't really know necessarily all of that stuff.
We, you know, it's hard to say,
Some of these things.
How much have benefit?
They actually are Because unless we take memory out of the equation,
it's hard to know.
So one thing we could do, right?
Is we could try to again like do something where we sort of fudge the
sample values for example,
To try and take these texture fetches out of the equation.
For example, right?
We could do something where we did something like this before.
Where we sort of said,
Excuse me, where we said, okay, you know what, if we were to, what if
we were to, just stuff those sample values with actual, you know, u
and v values or something like this, right?
So we were to say, you know, this is you, oops.
Sorry.
This is, let's say, fetch X for x and this is fetch y4y or something
like that, you know, we could try to stuff those values.
I don't know.
It's tough to say.
I'm not sure.
Best way to analyze that would be right, but at the very least,
removing all those multiplies certainly can't hurt us.
So I think that was a pretty cool thing, right?
And it turns out that we actually had this kind of nice, this nice
sort of lined up where we could do that factoring right in there and
not have to actually introduce a multiply at the end at all, so that's
pretty cool.
The other thing that Fabien was suggesting to and let me just double
check to make sure that that isn't something that
at all.
So we could do elsewhere, right?
I don't think so, but I could be wrong about that.
So let's see, we are doing.
We after that, we do sort of the what we do the blend.
I mean, technically
I want to say,
I mean, if you look at this routine,
It kind of looks like we don't have to really undo the blend there.
If we don't want to either, right?
We could just keep it all in the 0 to 255 space.
I mean correct me if I'm wrong but that seems like that could happen,
right?
Because if we change this, instead of being 0 to 1, if we change the
clamp between 0 and 65535 or old 2 to 5 squared, so if I 534 whatever
it is right, if we change the clamping it in 2022,
Two x squared space.
Then we could leave dest in that space as well.
And the only thing we'd actually have to normalize would be the alpha
value, right?
And we wouldn't really even after our minds that, but we do it, would
we have to do an extra normalization later potentially for it.
But
So I mean even that we might be little, but we could leave that for
now.
So if we got rid of that
then when we came in here and did the blend right in theory, we could
just use just this one multiplied at the end to put things back into
the proper range.
I think
Does that make sense?
I feel like it makes some sense, right?
So you do the square root.
You'd actually do the square root not in the zero to one range.
Now, maybe that's dumb, I don't know.
Because reciprocal square root might want to be.
I don't know.
Let's try it.
I think it's worth trying, right?
We got that far with it.
We might as well keep going.
That's what I think.
So, let's give it a shot.
So let's back out.
And we'll leave these guys as just whatever the color was.
Right.
So, let's see here.
So if these color values are all in that range, I'm trying to think.
I feel like if the color values, if we were
Do everything in the to 55 range.
We'd have to, we're gonna have a little bit honestly of a problem
here.
It would seem with Precision.
I'm a little nervous here about this because if we keep going there,
when we multiply the color that's going to introduce,
Well, it's a multiply, right?
So in theory, I guess we could just leave the color in the zero to one
space.
Should work.
I mean, it's a ratio so I don't know.
It should work, I think.
Let's just, let's do it.
So we multiply by the incoming colors in the zero to one space.
So these numbers are all to 0 to 255.
Sorry, 0 to 65535 or whatever, right?
Or it's not 653 for its 255 squared.
I want to stop saying the wrong thing.
It's that 6502 five, right?
So we go through here we multiply by the colors.
We would change this to like zero still, right?
But this is Max color value or something.
So we need we need to Define that, right?
And then when we go from srgb to linear brightness space, here we
would just do the squaring like we did before.
We wouldn't do the multiply, we just leave the desk exactly as it was,
and the only person that would get inverted is the alpha for now,
which maybe we don't even have to do that.
I'm not sure if that's a savings or not but you know, we'll leave it
that way for now.
Then we do the blend as normal everybody's in that space.
And then when we do, when we do this Final Fix up, instead here this
is just like the renormalize value, right re 255.
I guess we'll call it or something, which put stuff back in 2255 space
Reese, 255 of Fire.
That is a horrible name for a variable so it puts it back into the
0225 space and then off we go.
Does that seem right?
Feel like it is.
So, you know, here we just have, we have Max color value, which is the
mmm.
Again, just just, it's just a replicated value that's that's going to
be that, that 255 255 value, right?
So that we can do the clamping.
And then, you know, after that, we just need this guy, right?
And that's just going to be after you do that square root.
Well, I mean actually it just works right because the square roots
going to bring it back to the zero to 25 range, right?
I mean, I feel like we don't even have to do that.
I feel like
You just do the square root, right?
I mean, maybe I'm wrong about that.
But if it's already there and you square root that number, then that
should be it, right?
I mean that's what we're looking at.
so really it's just the alpha that would need to be fixed up there and
If we again didn't actually do that Alpha so that we essentially, you
know, the way this works is you multiply in textile?
A, we only care about infects Olay.
So if I just, if I just left the desde the same,
You know didn't Square it and and to be honest why was the alpha
getting square rooted in the first place?
Was that a typo that I just introduced?
We don't want that.
It's not supposed to be squared.
It's because the alpha never gets squared, right?
Right.
We should be able to just do it with Texel a here where the only time
we actually do it is to do this, this inversion, right?
So I feel like as strange as it seems, that's actually correct.
I mean it's kind of crazy, but I think it's right.
Which is wild.
Yeah, I mean, I think that's, I think that's correct.
So that gets rid of a bunch of operations actually quite a few in
fact.
So let's take a look at what's going on there.
So it looks like really we're having trouble getting anywhere below
the that boundary, it looks like right.
So I feel like if this point unless I'm I'm, you know, doing unless I
did something very stupid that I'm not thinking of it sort of seems
like we're running up against
we're kind of running up against a bit of a boundary here, right?
I feel like you know, let's take a look but if we take a look at what
this said before, our block throughput was eighty, six point, six
Cycles at maximum.
If you know, that's not counting any kind of memory stuff, so if I go
ahead and turn this back on again,
And do the compile right?
If I ask it what our cycle count is now, what does it have to say?
Oops,
86.2 5 Cycles.
Wow.
How is that possible?
so,
Of those things.
We got rid of the compiler was already getting rid of, or something to
that effect.
I mean that's basically the same, right?
I mean that's that's almost exactly the same.
So, that's kind of crazy because I feel like that should not be the
case.
I mean, removing all of those multiplies they, I guess the compiler
was smart enough to get rid of all of those.
I don't even know how that would be possible.
That seems kind of crazy but that, that would
Seemed to suggest that, that was true.
Right?
Because when we recompiled there, it seems like the analysis is still
the same.
I probably should dip these two to see what the differences between
them, right?
Yeah.
I mean, there's definitely
I feel like there's definitely more MLPs in there, but it's hard to
really say.
So, that's kind of frustrating.
I guess I would not have expected that but I'm not sure.
It does look like that.
Really just has no effect, right?
I mean, this is, this is kind of peculiar.
I kind of want to go back and look at the difference between those
two.
So I don't know if wind, if is on this machine, that's the thing that
comes with.
Let's see.
Do I have a diff of any kind diff?
There we go.
And maybe Beyond is beyond compare to on here as well.
I don't know what's on here.
So wind, if I feel like it's used to come with like developer Studio,
there was a little different tool that you could use but I don't
actually know if it's on their software development kit wind, if there
it is.
So when diff is installed on this machine, this is this comes with the
Microsoft sdks or at least it used to.
I assume it still does is a little tool for doing.
And ifs.
But you could use any, there's lots of public domain tools for dips.
You could use anything for it.
I think what I'd like to do is go ahead and capture these just so I
can look at it because I've never used this tool before and I kind of
want to see just for my own sort of Education, right?
I kind of want to see what's going on.
So I want to make dirt a
And I'm going to capture this output.
So I'm going to go to Temp.
Let's see.
This is our no moles run dot out, right?
Oops, capture that.
So we got the the one with
Moles.
And then, what I'm going to do is I'm going to copy the code, so I'll
copy everything in this section, right?
Like so but then I'm going to go ahead and I'm going to like back up
to where we were, right?
So here we go.
Just undo backwards and do backwards and do backwards.
All the way.
To the initial run of things.
Do do do.
Okay.
There we go.
Okay, so let's double-check it now.
You know, maybe I did something else.
Stupid, I'm not sure.
But here's the here's the new code we wrote, right?
Just so we can keep it in there.
And switch back to it later but here we go.
Let's turn this back on.
Compile it and then we'll capture.
This is the mold run right so that's the one that's doing all those
extra multiplications that we didn't really need to do.
And so now I'm going to go ahead and compare the two files that are
that are in that directory, right?
The moles run in the no malls, run.
Somos round.
No malls room.
Obviously, they're different.
And I mean, they take exactly the same number of cycles and what's
even more surprising about.
It is the, you know, it's saying throughput Port through public is
Port 1 and Port.
One is the multiply Port.
So you would think us removing a bunch of multiplies would actually
have helped things out but I guess in reality the compiler was
removing
Or something.
I don't really know and so you know, somehow that was not the case.
So looking through here, I wish this counted it's not actually
counting the total number of multiplies which is unfortunate.
I don't know if there's a way to do it and you can even see the total
number of Micro Ops is 349 in the original case and
And 306.
We actually got rid of 43 instructions, but getting rid of 43.
Instructions did not change, the total Block throughput in any way.
It's exactly the same basically, right?
And so, let's take a look.
So, here is the block here, you've got two moles in the red block to
Moses in the, in the nominee.
Block.
This one.
We actually have two moles at the head end, but only one mole here.
Over.
Here's the other Mall, presumably.
So we've got two and two.
There we go.
No moles in anybody.
Nobody's doing any malls for a while here.
That's probably fetching this textures and so on or something like
this, come down here, we get to know malls in here although we got p.
And so these guys are creating a little bit of pressure here on that
Port, right?
But still no moles still.
No most nobody is multiplying.
Apparently.
So here's mul PS.
Here's the mall PS here.
So we're doing two they're doing 1 then 3.
Then here's the other two it's it's it's really looking eerily.
Like it's doing exactly the same number of multiplies, doesn't it?
I mean it's doing them in a different way but man.
It just looks like it's doing.
Almost exact same number of these guys.
That's crazy.
So somehow the compiler was actually and we'd have to go through to do
the forensics, but the compiler was actually smart enough to do that
transformation or something, close to it itself.
Right.
I mean it was actually figuring out.
How to collapse all of that stuff that we were too dumb to do.
So basically all of that strength reduction, all of those term
cancellations.
Well, strength reduction is not the right word all of those sort of
those cancellations.
It found
As far as I can tell, I did that.
Which is kind of awesome.
I guess that's the kind of thing that compiler tree.
Analysis is probably not that bad at doing like looking for sort of
ways.
You can restructure things and collapse constants but still a little
bit surprising, right?
I mean, you know, I often don't think of the compiler has really
excelling at a lot of these things.
So I'm reasonably impressed by that.
I give the I give the compiler.
People some props on that you know that's that's a lot better than I
would have expected the compiler to be doing in that circumstance.
That's just my opinion.
Feel free to disagree but that's just my opinion.
So yeah, that's kind of crazy but I guess that's just how it goes.
So let's keep looking at this and now we feel like we should at least
try to beat the compiler, right?
It feels kind of stupid at this point, if we can, but oh well, right?
So let's see here.
okay, so if we run this guy, we still haven't really made any
Answered if Improvement there and we kind of now know why it doesn't
really matter which one of those we do, the compiler was kind of
outsmarting us.
So the question here, let's see, is what else can we do?
So if we're doing these in 0 to 255 space, one thing we could do is
square them before we convert, right?
That would certainly be an option.
Let's see how we're actually.
So we're masking these guys out here.
Let me think about this for a second.
So this would be actually fairly complicated if we wanted to do it.
But it is something that we could do, right?
And it would take pressure off, Port one
Because actually it would involve doing integer multiplied.
So let's take a look.
Let's talk about this for a second and take a look at what would be
involved in doing this?
I think it's probably too much of a change to do, just here at the end
of the stream, but you know, what do you do?
Let's take a look at the Intel intrinsics guide.
I want to know about mmm mole epi32 on the hail, mmm, so same.
Throughput on the, the epi32 --mm mul, which is the integer
multiplied.
Right?
Instead of, you know, instead of wait, that's the wrong one.
Sorry, I actually want epi16, I suppose, huh.
I'm all epr we don't have any PI 30.
We don't, is it only?
Multiply the low 32 inches from each pack 64-bit element in a, and b,
and store the sign to.
All right, well,
Well, I guess that's kind of dead in the water unless I'm missing
something.
Because if mmm oh oh duh.
Right I forgot their split up into mole low and go high never mind.
I was going to say, that'd be very, very strange.
All right.
I was like I could have sworn, I've done this before.
That's just how it goes in the Stream sometimes.
Alright, so basically what we've got here, you know, we've got
multiplies, the throughput on them is, is one
Which is, I believe comparable to what we were seeing before, right?
Latency 5 to put one latency 3, throughput one's late exacts a little
bit better.
In the three puts the same.
So we could, if we want to write, take a look at what we're doing here
and try to do more of this wide wider than we were.
Because when we converted to float, right?
Like right here, we converted to float that meant from there on, we
could only be four wide.
And technically some of these operations.
We could be doing in 16-bit integer, we mentioned that on a previous
stream on staying, at that, on converting it to do in that with, we
could choose to do that.
If it turns out that some of these operations could be done, quickly
in that space and we wouldn't have to worry because since we're
already now allowing it to be in the zero to sixty six, sixty 5025
space instead of 0 to 1, we wouldn't have to keep multiplying by a
fix-up, which is what really kills.
Fixed Point operations so we could.
We could in theory do that and looking through here I feel like we
could certainly do the square.
And then I feel like we could do the square and then convert here,
right?
And that could, you know, that seems reasonable and similarly, at the
end, I feel like we could in theory.
Well, we're not going to be able to probably do a square root in fixed
point, right?
Like that's not probably going to happen, so I feel like probably,
yeah, probably.
We just have to we, you know, we just have to leave that the way it is
although maybe I don't know, maybe there's something else we could do
there.
I don't think so though.
So
All right, so let's just take a quick look at what would what it would
take to do that.
Right right now what's happening is we're doing these shifts and masks
to put these things into their proper places and so, you know, I guess
what I would say is could we just instead of masking everything out
just mask out two things at once.
Right.
This is this is, I guess what I would think you know just just off the
top of my head about
How to do this, right?
So we've got a situation where we've got our values and, you know,
they look like this.
Right, this is what we've got coming in.
You know, and if this is what we've got coming in, then I wonder if
perhaps what we could do is instead of doing each one individually,
what if we just knocked out the A and the G and right like so and left
like the are in the be in there.
Okay.
Then these guys would be lined up exactly on the 16-bit lanes.
So in theory,
We could just multiply them in by six, you know, 16.
We could Square them, right in place, right?
Then we go ahead and up convert those to float by doing the
The additional mask, right?
Or doing an unpacked with zero doing something like that, that seems
kind of compelling.
So, let's see if we can do that, I'll just do it for one of our
textiles texture samples.
So I'm going to need something other than mask FF.
I'm going to need something that's like, you know, that it's going to.
It's going to mask out both the the bottom eight and the, and then the
eight, that's 16 up from there, right?
So, I want to do that, and we're going to call that I probably don't
want to get rid of the actual mask FF just yet, though, because we're
still using that for the other guys.
So, I'm going to make this called mask foof mask foof.
Sounds good to me.
So we'll go in here and we will do it twice, right?
We'll do a mask foof here, I will do a mask move here.
And so all we need to do is do a mask foof of of these guys and
instead of that being Texel a b, and I started Texel be and Texel G
there.
This is actually going to be Texel, R&B and Texel AG, right?
So we're getting both of them.
Okay so we're going to do that and I don't actually want to do this
part yet.
I don't want to do the convert.
I want to just leave them the way that they are, right?
I want to just leave them in place and then what I want to do is I
want to square them.
So what I need to do is I need to produce an A Squared version of this
guy and a squared version of this guy which means I need to do an M&M.
Mall of the of the 16-bit values, but we now have to talk about what
the difference is between molo and mull.
Hi.
Okay, so this is going to be a square like so I don't know, maybe
there's a smarter way to do the square as well, but just thinking it
through at the moment.
So what happens here is if you imagine having 16-bit values, right?
So I've got 16 bits and I'm going to multiply it by another 16 bits.
Technically the result
That is actually 32 bits, right?
Because you're gonna, you know, it's kind of like if you multiply 10
by 10, write the result?
Oops, the result doesn't fit intestine into things, right?
It overflows to a higher.
Number of digits, right?
So if we're multiplying, two 16-bit values by each other, we're
technically going, get a 32-bit result, but the result since this is
operating in 16-bit Lanes, the result has to fit in 16 bits.
So,
So the multiply unit allows us to pick which of the resulting 16-bit
Lanes.
We actually want right now.
Fortunately, for us, we don't have to care about that too much because
we're only actually using the bottom 8 Bits.
So, when we multiply the bottom eight by the bottom eight, we're only
going to get a 16 bit results.
So the high portion, the Overflow that would have flowed into the rest
of it.
We don't actually care about
So we can just use milou, which is the thing that takes that produces,
the low 16 bits of the multiplied result and we don't have to care
about Maja at all.
We don't care about that, really?
I don't think there's any reason we need to worry about that.
So we can just do that and that will Square R values for us, right?
So that means we can get rid of this here.
so,
These, by the way, around 128 eyes.
And so, then we come down here to produce these M 128.
Of course I just realized we do have one problem which is that this
one square R Alpha as well.
Hmm.
That's kind of annoying.
That introduces a wrinkled because that means we can't quite get a
perfect, half reduction there.
You know at it would be nice if we could but I don't think we can.
So that's
That's less cool.
So we'd have to blow another instruction to or two of our Alphas
together.
In order to save the square, which doesn't sound necessarily like,
such a great idea.
I don't know, but it does mean for the time being that we would just
need to look at that.
Leave that the way it is.
So we'll think about that.
Not sure.
I mean, I guess I guess we don't have to go that far, right?
I mean we could just knock out the multiplier, right?
I mean, we could do something where we've got the alpha, you know, we
could do this, right?
We could, and with masks FF and that would knock out that Alpha in the
multiply, which would leave the alpha N squared.
But again, you know, it sucks because we thought we were going to get
a bigger reduction there than we were.
But we're having to do is like that additional
In which is, which is too bad but all right, you know, that's that's
just the way it is.
So once we've got that
You know, now we should be able to in theory, go ahead and lock these
up into the actual.
Sorry.
We could convert these up from from fixed point there to floating
point, right from zero, from the integers to floats and that's what
this will do.
But now we have a problem which is we actually have our and be mixed
together, right?
And Ang mixed together.
Okay, so we need to do is we need to introduce the concept.
In a way that will actually will actually grab out the ones we want,
right?
And so I think probably the most efficient way to do that is still
just with masking, I would think, I don't know.
That's a pipelines.
There's other ways we could do it on unpack, might do it.
So we might have to look and see which of the you know which of them
would be the most overlap above the things we have.
But the
Just looking at these values.
You know if we if we went on and introduced another and here where we
just and with with that mask FF that would give us just the, I guess
that would give us just the B channel, right?
That would knock out the a I'm sorry that we knock out the are and
then to get if we did the the shift to the right to bring the the
R-value down that would just be that that shift down by 16 right?
So we
You that to grab out that our value, similarly, for the G value,
that's already in that correct position.
So that would again also just be another mask put C of Of Texel a Ag
and then finally the the end here would just be grabbing out that
Alpha value from from the AG.
So I think I did that right kind of confusing mentally to think about.
But let's see if that looks right at all.
All right, I'm going to go ahead and say that that's probably
incorrect.
Now I'm just I just have a hunch looking at it.
I just have a hunch that that is probably not correct.
So let's go ahead, it's Q&A but let's go ahead and just try to try to
take a quick look and see what I did wrong there.
All right, so we've got our tekzilla AR are be and our Texel AG here.
The way I get them is by doing the shift.
And masking out values, right?
So that puts everyone in the 16-bit lanes or at least I think it does,
that's what I'm arguing that it does.
And and so I hope that's the case because yeah, that seems very
straightforward.
We could check it in the debugger.
We're then going to do a multiplication of with itself which will just
do that multiply and I'm arguing that would basically give us eight
bit tiny bit.
So it's giving us that 16-bit value that we wanted the multiplication
value that we wanted.
And in this case with the Texel AG I had to do an additional mask here
to mask out so that the multiply would only multiply just the green
value.
So I'm a stout that Alpha value from one side of the term, so it would
only multiply the G, right?
So I did that, I then tried to produce the Texel.
On them, by Shifting, the our B value down 16 in each of the 32-bit
wide Lanes, which I felt like should give me just the are sitting in
the bottom and of course since it's shifting in zeros that should just
clear.
It should just be clear with just the are sitting there.
The G is already in the bottom.
So I just had to take the a Ag and mask out that
Mask out, the the alpha, the, our B value right already.
Had the be sitting in the bottom.
So all I had to do is mask that out and then the a ag again, I can
just shift that down by 16 to get the alpha out of the, a, a g.
So I feel like that should have been correct.
You can then convert those directly to float and I felt like that
should have done it but
You know, as we can see it definitely didn't do it right.
That is a good example of what we might call not doing it.
What's sort of clear?
I think about well, you know what, I'm not sure.
I can read very much out of that, that's a little confusing.
So I'm not sure what's going on there, but yeah.
Let's go ahead and and just step through it the debugger and see what
happens.
All right, so I want to stuff something in here that I can actually
perceive, right?
I want to stuff something in here that I can see.
So what I'm going to do is I'm going to take sample a and I'm going to
do an M&M set epi32 on that guy.
So I can actually set the values of this guy there, ice in, there is a
set epi32.
Yeah.
So what I'm going to do there is I'm going to set the values of it to
look like kind of those values that we were talking about before,
right?
So I can see the little bit better.
So the first thing I'm going to do is I'm just going to set it so that
the red Channel I'm sorry, the blue channel is FF so I can see where
it goes, right and what happens to it.
Okay, so let's see.
And I, guess what I'll do here is I'll you know, what else I'll do?
I'll set these to something, that I'll be able to recognize, maybe
he's more easily when they get squared.
So let's see, that'll be squared to 2, then we'll do that and that,
right?
Yeah, that seems reasonable.
Oh, and this obviously goes there.
Okay, so let's see, let's see what that's doing.
here we come in to sample a
and if I take a look, I want to look at the the I-16 probably of it
since that's the sort of what we're what we're working with at this
point.
Well, it's actually you 16, I guess is what we're working with, right?
And so if I take a look at it, you can see that.
I sort of stuffed some things in here.
Rather specifically.
So well, I don't really love the order.
This is showing it to me and but that's okay.
So this is still roughly, what I would have expected 02.
Yeah, okay.
So now let's take a look at Texel a are B.
So after it does that masking, what are the actual values here?
And so, after doing the masking which is designed to remove the middle
values, we have nothing in there.
So we should just see the exact same stuff that we have here, which
is, which is good.
Let's see.
Texas, laaaaaag.
Now this one should have nothing in it, but zeros because this one is
supposed to shift and mask out.
So we should have all zeros which we do.
We're then going to do the squaring into Texel AR
All right, so these numbers should all square.
They do.
Oops, but that one is what that's fine, right?
We're supposed to square out in out of the to 55 range.
That's, that's what's supposed to happen.
That's fine.
And so now we have those values multiplied, low, and sitting in there,
waiting to be up converted, okay?
So here are the values.
Right.
And that is what we would expect them to be, right?
So, let's see when we actually go to do our, our upconversion Texel.
Hey are, which is the only thing that should have anything in it.
I believe.
Let's see what it actually.
It actually is m120.
Groups.
Mmm, the actual model for that, it's m 128.
F32.
All right, so we do it.
And we get all zeros for the red channel.
Oh that's okay.
I was the blue Channel.
Sorry that we were doing so that's actually correct.
The green channel, the blue channel so green channel, should have
Does and the blue channel should have those values in it.
And there is obviously my mistake.
Yes.
Well, that would do it.
That would do it folks.
So, you know, you got to think it all the way through.
You don't get any points for just thinking part of the way through, if
I'm a scout just the 8 Bits.
Well, that's not going to do us very much good.
If these are 16-bit values so we got a mask out, 16s, not eight.
Kind of a no-brainer there.
But what you going to do?
Okay, let's try that again, shall we?
Well, of course, I gotta take out my mmm set.
PS there.
If I want to see what it's actually looking like.
So there we go.
All right.
Not feeling great about that either, but it's better.
I'd lie enough.
It's actually partially correct, which doesn't make a whole lot of
sense to me to completely honest with you.
So that's a bit odd.
But you know, what are you gonna do?
Oh duh, I forgot.
To change both our masks.
That's probably the only problem.
Oops, spoke a little too soon.
Not quite just the only problem.
Oh, changed it in the wrong place?
No, no.
So I did, I did change in both places.
I take it back.
I'm not I'm not totally out to lunch.
It's totally fine.
So that's, I think all fine that makes reasonable sense.
Ah,
But forgot, one more thing I can't just mask this out, right?
Because I need the mullet Sam multiply right.
It would need to be one's there.
Hmm, so yeah, I mean I would need, I need to Miss Lee, make sure that
the alpha comes through.
So that's the lat.
That's yeah, I mean I can do it but it
It just cost more instructions out there.
I wonder, is there some clever way that I can make this work so that
the alpha comes through, you know, Uhn squared, which is what I want
to have happen, right?
I want that Alpha to remain unsquare the entire time because the alpha
never gets square rooted at the end and we want it linear.
Right.
That's the only thing we need as a trick.
We need a simple way to make this vector.
Not have the alpha B squared.
Well,
Actually do we need to do that?
I guess now that I think about it is that just stupid could we just
Square them?
Both right but but actually pull out the alpha ahead of time.
How hard would that be right?
Not very
So am I just making a mountain out of a molehill there?
Right.
Am I just was that just just a lot of Ado About Nothing and it turns
out that it was
All right, so that's pretty good.
That's a pretty good thing.
And now we can do that now, we can actually do those wide.
So let's take a look and see how that's doing there that totally runs
just fine, still nice and Zippy.
And so, let's take a look at what happens if we just go ahead and, you
know, and convert them.
All right?
So let's see if I was to convert them.
All right.
We just have.
That would be Texel a
Replace with text will be.
Yeah.
Then we do Texel be replaced with Texas C and then we do text will see
replaced with Texel D, probably should make a macro for these, huh?
And that would be that.
And then when we do the conversions again it would just be the same
here for everybody.
So Texel a it comes text, the be Texel, be becomes text to see and
text will see becomes
Text will be.
Right.
Off we go and hey that definitely did make a difference, right?
Although I feel like I introduced a bug there, it doesn't.
I feel like it's not quite by Lynn earring like it's supposed to could
be wrong about that.
I want to make sure, let's make sure I didn't do something stupid.
There, we probably should have some kind of compliance test at this
point since we're doing so many wacky things.
With the rendering spot-checking by, I is not exactly the best thing
to do there.
But what, what did I do?
Anything.
Totally done there.
We're doing the milou.
Ah, we're reading from only sample.
A, that's the problem.
So, there we go.
It's got a read only reading 411 sample.
So there we go.
Back to our proper by linear.
It does look like the we're getting still a little bit of Aditi.
Like if you look at our hero, he's got some green fringing, it looks
like it.
Just it looks like the Alphas.
Not quite right.
It looks like it's I feel like we're still a little bit buggy there
and so that's also we kind of eaten up most of the Q&A here.
Sorry about that but you know what do you do?
So I feel like oh there we go.
Still got one more.
Just as I'm saying, we need to make a macro for something.
There's cut and paste book.
Think that's pretty good evidence for it.
So there we go.
All right, and so that, let's see how that goes when we run it.
So that is actually way worse than we were doing before, right?
That's actually super.
So the only reason we would got that Phantom speed up there was
because I had have it the typo there.
So that's actually way worse than we were before doing those
operations in the doing those operations like so.
So I wonder if we run that through the little analyzer, I wonder
I right, so if I do this and do our compiled there,
And then go back to our little capture here.
This is 16-bit square, right?
Let's take a look at what it outputs.
Right.
So 16-bit square is way worse on the Cycles, right?
And it says the throughput bottleneck is inter iteration.
I don't even know what that means.
That would definitely be a question for Fabien, certainly not for me,
but the total number of Micro Ops is much smaller than it was before,
right?
Much much smaller.
So because if you remember, if you look back at our previous run here,
the no malls run.
If you look back it was 306.
And now it's 283, right?
And the moles run, furthermore?
Right?
Whatever it was, what was it called?
Moles?
Run that out?
The moles run, was more still.
So we went from 350.
Down to 283, actual operations, but because of which operations they
were it's actually worse for us.
In terms of the total block, throughput, right?
Which sucks can't catch a break.
You know what I'm saying?
So I don't know, I don't know if that sometimes I feel like that's
probably a good place to end because sometimes that means you should
backtrack other times.
That means you should push forward and try to find a better way to do
whatever it is that you were doing.
So I'm not 100% sure which one of these we should do and so it might
be good to just let it sit for a little bit and think about what we
want to pursue going forward, right?
Just something to think about now loading the destination.
We could do exactly the same thing, right?
So,
I mean, loading the destination.
We could do the exact same stuff for but if that made us slower, I'm
not sure that this is going to make us Faster by converting that in
theory, you would want some things in the in the floating-point pipe
while they're things were in the in the integer pipe anyway and stuff
like that.
So I don't really know.
This is kind of tough.
I feel like kind of staring at this disassembly and coming to some
conclusions about what needed to happen to take the pressure off in
the places where it's currently bottlenecking either.
In the pure floating-point version or here in the wide version would
be required before taking any next steps that don't have an immediate
idea of what we would do to do better.
We could change this to be wide but you know what wouldn't actually
help.
Yeah.
I mean it wouldn't and I don't think that would actually help.
All right, well I'm gonna do the Q&A because we should have some Q&A
so I'm going to go ahead and do that and we will you know maybe come
back and revisit this this this may not be the end of it because we
may want to take another look at these as we go.
So okay.
CPS answer critical path.
Okay, thanks guys.
I'm assuming people can read the manual for this as well.
So in theory you guys on stream should probably or probably already
know a bunch more about this tool than I do, but so, yes.
So critical path I guess is, is bad.
So we don't want to be seeing a lot of CP, but yeah.
Alright, let's take a look here.
I see was showing Port 1 as the bottleneck not ports.
Ah typical programmer non-programmer mistake, I made there.
So if Port one was the bottleneck then yeah reducing pressure on the
multiplies wouldn't help at all.
But wait.
So here is the part that was confusing me.
Why does the 1.0 go in that car in the zero?
Column for the mall PS?
That's why I was reading it that way.
So I don't know.
What are you?
How did you know that the mole PS was in the one?
I don't think that's true.
I feel like the mole PS is in the zero.
Are you sure Fletcher rated?
I don't think that's true.
Enter iteration means that run that run X of a loop depends on the x
minus one run.
Well, why would that be true?
Because these Loops are independent
You could run them totally separately if you wanted to their you
shouldn't be dependent in any way, actually.
So are you sure about that?
You should try pulling out the texture pointer dereferencing from the
inner loop to local variables.
The compiler is probably doing a read every time because of aliasing
doing a read
Everytime of what exactly.
Oh, are you talking about like texture?
Arrow pitch and so on?
Yes, I could totally pull those out because like texture pointer
obviously, is is going to be different.
Yes, I can certainly hoist.
Those, if you think that's something where the compiler thinks there's
aliasing and doesn't want to do it.
So the texture pitch I can put out here.
Right.
Text your pitch.
Let's see.
Texture pitch.
Looks like just texture pitch.
Texture memory.
Is it, right?
Those are the only things that are used.
And I'll see anything else.
Wow.
So that was a pretty good call as well.
Because this is the, the routine that was actually slow.
Right?
This was actually the routine that was much slower because we're still
using the old version there.
So, let's let's let me take a quick look at that.
Texture locals.
We go.
Yeah, that's that definitely did make an improvement so you were
correct the compiler did not know that.
It could save those because since they were accessing off a pointer it
thought I guess that it thought that maybe they could change so it had
to read them every time and that helped it out quite a bit possibly
because it can do you know, optimizations with them now and possibly
just because it doesn't have to do the read which, you know, maybe
that was problem.
That read would have always been in the cash so I
I doubt it but I guess it would have just at least help the compiler
in terms of all the other operators to know, right?
That that's not what's actually happening there.
So yeah, that was pretty cool.
Very good idea.
I guess.
So I guess the question.
Now, let me take a look at that runs.
With texture locals here.
279 my crops and so the previous 16-bit 1.
So we reduced the number of operations down just a little bit as well.
Block throughput though.
Still the same so that was purely just memory stuff that's causing
that.
That's a little weird.
Not sure.
I have full faith in what this is telling me.
But
All right.
so,
Yeah.
How does one support new instructions?
Which are not ubiquitous like a VX.
Do you just checks?
You but setup function pointers to appropriate, implementations.
Yes, that is exactly what you do.
What about register saving for things?
Like context switches would one have to worry about such things with
the same D registers, no.
Because in general, well,
Actually guess that's not true.
I don't actually know because I've never tried it.
What happens on a VX on older operating systems, if they're smart
enough to mask it from you or whether you still see the AV exes being
there.
And then if you use it, you would just get totally hosed because
they're not saved.
So I actually don't know, you may have to check for a combination of
operating system and cpuid.
I'm not sure.
So you would have to
At the very least go double-check that so I'm not sure I'm sorry you
have to at least check to see and then set the function pointers but
I'm just I'm just not sure.
How about try to play replace squirt with mul are squirt?
Yeah, we could definitely replace squirt with Mall r squared.
We're still using the slower throughput version here though so I'm a
little hesitant to try any of these things but we can do that.
What he's basically saying is instead of issuing, the actual square
root, you know, we could, instead of doing that use, there's a faster
reciprocal square root which gives you an approximated 1 over the
square root.
Um, it's this, right?
And so, you know, the idea which is is basically to
To use the reciprocal square root instead of the square root command.
And so a square root operation.
So I don't actually know what r squared throughput is but I think it's
very high right through put one or two on this processor.
And so if you take a look at
At the squirt PS that we were using right.
The throughput is much slower, right?
It's only 16.
So, yeah.
So basically the idea here would be, we have a number.
We have X and we know that we want to compute the square root of x.
But the only thing we actually can compute is one over the square root
of x, right?
Is that what we want to compute?
What are we competing in total here?
We're just taking Blended.
We're taking blind know that.
Yeah so that's that's what we want.
So we have one over the square root of x.
And what we want to do is we want to we want
Vert that right?
So yeah, if we take that and multiply it.
So if we take that, we've got, you know why, whatever, whatever it's
going to do, it's going to give us y equals.
You know, 1 over 1 over X, we need to be able to do something to that
that will produce just square root of x for us.
So if we do multiply both sides, right, multiply both sides by
We would get X over the square root of x, right?
And, of course, we know that x equals, we could replace this x right?
With square root of x times, square root of x, because squared of x
times, square, root of x or, you know, square root of x squared.
Right is X.
So that would cancel the square root.
Then just leave us with one square root X.
So, x times the value that we get back from that should give us the
value that we actually want, right?
So MLPs,
Our times reciprocal square root, right, Loops Spotify in the wrong
one here.
Mul PS mul PS.
And so on.
And there we go.
So getting those out of there, also does look like a good thing.
Let's take a look at the no square root version.
But again, since we don't we're kind of in flux a little bit here.
It's hard to tell sometimes because you know, we don't actually know
We're still using that wide squaring, which which didn't help us,
right?
No squirt or we just call this our squirt.
So let's go ahead and take a look at what that gives us.
And para Square it.
so that
did also.
Wait to that actually should have gone up.
Yeah so that added a few Cycles because I added a few instructions
because of the are squirt but it did reduce the total throughput down
from what it was previously.
So that is good, definitely good but so I don't know.
So maybe we should actually not do the wide thing or maybe we should
try doing the Wild Thing further.
Or maybe what we need to do is just do these in a slightly different
way.
So
oh, that they would be able to assign better out here and to be
I again since it's the first time I've ever used this thing, I don't
have a really good feel for the right way to interpret what I'm seeing
right?
It's not a tool I have experience with so on stream when I'm trying to
talk and go out something I can't you know I would have to be an
expert on this to be able to do anything real with it in the middle of
the stream.
So I suspect
T', I mean, looking at this, with all of these looking at this through
here, and you can see that.
So many things are going into Port one there.
Yeah.
So oh Fabien is actually watching.
See what we really need is him to just be in the chair that would help
things out a lot, but unfortunately, haven't quite gotten that
happening yet but yeah, he's just commenting on the thing before which
is multiplier important 0.
Ad in Port 1, it looks like also so things that happen in Port 1,
right?
We've got the ads.
The comps both happen in that port and it doesn't look like they can
ever happen on any other Port.
Right?
So the ads the Max's, the mins all that stuff kind of stuffs up in
that Port, which
And the sub.
Yeah.
so, the multiplies that are actually doing
The 16-bit multiplies.
I assume that those also went into Port 1, so that was yeah, pretty
much all bad.
so, I guess
I feel like that just sort of suggests that we don't want to try and
do this.
Why?
Because it just adds to all of that Port one pressure and if we did do
the multiplies in floating point.
It's kind of like they're free because they're going into Port 0 where
we didn't have the pressure
in theory but I guess you know, on top of that.
I also I don't know how to balance the fact that you can do more of
them at once, right?
So it is true that you can, you know, if this were clever or perhaps,
No, it is doing able to do more of the multipliers with one actual
issue of a multiplied.
So it's, it's, you know, I don't necessarily know how to balance that
out.
So I'm just, I'm just not sure about that.
So I probably, I think I just want to let this sit for a bit.
We'll come back to tomorrow since this is kind of interesting and I
get to learn about how to use this thing and how to read it, which is
yet again like on stream.
It's kind of be
Hard to be hit with a new thing and it's hard.
I apologize for not knowing all the stuff I should and looking at
because going to take me a little while to go into speed on it.
But looks pretty cool.
And yeah.
I mean, it looks like for the most part.
That would kind of indicate that because of that Port pressure going
wide would actually be very going wider would actually be very hard
for us to do because since we're already using that unit even in the
floating-point path to do the mins and Max's, we'd have to come up
with like some other creative way, not to do that.
So yeah.
How can removing the square root help performance?
If the square root is done on the multiplied Port, not the adder port.
So, I guess the thing that I would say about it was that normally that
would be the right way to think about it.
But I suspect in this case, it's not simply because it's so the
throughput so long, right?
It's 60 and cycle throughput, which means that it's like
Even if we were perfectly pipelined, we have to do three square roots,
which means, 3 times, 16 Cycles just to get those square roots done.
So, that amount of overhang is pretty hard to fill with stuff,
especially because it comes at the end of the loop.
So you're basically talking about going up into the next Loop,
probably to grab more stuff to do.
Right?
Is length, is going to come from.
So I feel like it probably has something to do with the fact that the
total distance between the last square root and you know, and when it
would have to issue a mole PS before it could do anything else just
isn't wide enough to be 3 times.
16 cycles Long, right.
It just isn't far enough.
So even though it's not on a high pressure port that it's so big.
It's footprint is so big.
I suspect the processor.
Just can't deal with having the port gone for that long.
It can't it can't move all the other malls you know?
I mean keep in mind there's dependencies
This whole code, the processor can't just execute any instruction.
It wants whenever it wants, it still has to execute dependent or
instructions in series so I suspect that that probably has a lot to do
with it, but I don't know that be my suspicions.
All right, I'm going to go ahead and end the stream.
This has been very interesting for me, because I never have seen this
tool before.
It's cool.
I'm gonna have to learn this, and I'm going to probably run this on my
own code now, because I did not know, it was available, it's pretty
great.
So, thank you for being for that and for your optimization help in
general.
I think that people are probably getting a much better view of
optimization in general already, and I think that will obviously go
double.
When you put up a stream or come on this stream.
One of the other which I hope we can make happen because.
Yeah, I mean, basically, like I said before,
If you have an expert on something, they're going to know a lot of
stuff that you don't know.
And you know, one of the things that's really nice about having been
in the game industry.
A long time is that you know people who you can ask when you know you
don't know stuff.
Right.
And optimization is one of those things that definitely an especially
on sse2.
I just haven't done very much of and so all of the things that you
should know if you really do it on a day-to-day basis and want to be
very good at it or not things that I can.
Teach.
So again, thank you very much for that and I think everyone on the
stream really appreciates you taking the time to give us the pointers
because otherwise you know we would have done just the translation of
the routine and that probably would have been it, right?
So that's pretty awesome.
And and we will come back to it tomorrow and maybe just try to think
about a little bit.
What our strategy is here is there anything interesting that we could
do or should we just go ahead and move it back to doing it in float
and say that that's the way?
It should probably work.
So that's what we'll do tomorrow.
As always, if you would like to follow along at home with handmade
hero, you can do so by
Go into the handmade hero website and you can pre-order The Source,
pre-order the game, it comes to the source code.
So if you want to follow along with what we're doing and play around
the optimization yourself and maybe find some faster ways to do the
things that we're doing.
Now, that you've seen how do it, anyone could read that diagram and in
fact, probably better than I can because it's the first time I've ever
seen it.
I will be going to read the the docks on it for sure.
So, you know, you can play around with it.
You could take a look and see if you could figure out different ways
to structure the same stuff that
we're doing so that it ends up filling those ports better getting rid
of some of those stalls doing whatever needs to happen.
Because I believe, unless I'm very much an error, those printouts that
we're seeing there are showing us what our maximum block.
Throughput would be if there were no memory cells.
And so in some sense, we're kind of for free getting a pretty,
presumably pretty good estimate of what the code speed actually is
when you discount anything that has to do with memory, which is kind
of nice.
Because it means we can sort of play around a little, with the how
fast the routine is capable of going intrinsically, pun intended.
Before actually looking at the memory part of it which kind of might
help us get through it because then we can kind of break those into
pieces and you know work on them separately until they converge,
right?
So that's kind of cool too.
Which is harder to do if you don't have a tool that can tell you what
that throughput would be separate from the memory.
All right.
So anyway thank you very much for joining me for another episode of
handmade hero.
As always, check out how many here at or if you need anything.
If you want to preorder the game, if you want to go to the forums and
ask questions or get poorest to Mac or Linux or a CD annotated episode
guide, all kinda stuff like that.
If you want to scrub the patreon page and support the video series, we
would very much love it if you did that.
And there's also the tweetbot which has the schedule.
So if you want to catch the live stream, that is what it will be.
And and it also has a schedule post on the weekend for the whole week
so hopefully you can always catch a slide if you want to see us lat
and until the next time that you do, thanks so much for tuning in.
We will be off tomorrow actually now that I think about it, it's
Saturday will be the next stream so definitely check the Tweet, but if
you want to catch that, I think it's Saturday at 8:00 p.m.
All right.
Thanks everyone, and I will catch you later.