Hello everyone and welcome to handmade hero.
The show we could a complete game live on stream.
We just got done with a little fur, coat or Friday, so we're starting
a little late today.
We're starting it like, 422 we instead of starting at 5:00, I'm sorry.
522 instead of starting at 5:00.
So, you know, sometimes you're late in software development.
Things start late.
They end even later, it's always a disaster.
That's just how things go.
But we have some code to do today that we need to do.
Um, basically we played around yesterday and smushed our debug you I
systems together.
Because we had some like hockey stuff.
We were doing the profile before we kind of put it in there and so
today I'm not sure exactly what we're going to do.
I think what I'd like to do is I'd like to clean up a few things in it
since it's Friday.
I don't really want to go too far down getting the profile interface
working because I think what tomorrow?
I mean what next week should be about is getting some clean interfaces
for like the profiling, for switching things and stuff like that.
So what I'd like to do today is clean up a few things.
I'd like to clean up the way that we're doing our, debug trees a
little bit.
And there are the where interface
He's done a little bit so that we can have a few more advanced
features in there.
And so that things are running a little bit more smoothly.
So we're going to like, do some Cleanup in some feature addition
today, rather than focusing on, you know, sort of what I think is more
of an almost, a design problem, because honestly, I don't really know.
And I mean, like a ux is a problem, I don't really know.
I've never built a super capable profiler before.
I've only just had like, little readouts of like times.
And now that we have like, all this data about, like, when threads are
doing what and all this stuff, I haven't really ever given a thought
to like,
What should I actually, how do I make that something that's usable and
so next week, I think, you know, will be us, figuring that sort of
stuff out like, like, how can we make that a really nice little thing
to, we can view and use.
All right, I'm going to just go ahead and Jump Right In Here.
Today is day.
1 98 day, 197 source.
Code is what I'm starting with today.
So if you pre-order the game at hand be here at dot org, you need to
start with de 197 source.
Code don't start with some other day source code because you'll be
like, what's going on, start with 197.
Because that's when I'm starting with right now and you can see where
we were at is pretty cool.
You can go in here and you can edit these things where we just have
like all these kind of weird, you know, test things that we put in
there and
whatever they were, you know, could edit them.
And you could do stuff like this, where you could like change values
by like dragging and all that sort of stuff.
And you could also do things where, if you wanted to, you could open
up like a the profiler and it would show things like the, you know,
the whole profile or data inside here and you could even, like, change
the size of the profiler, right?
So, we had like the ability to like, you know, kind of drag things
around and you can kind of see it there.
And you can see us taking too long because our debug collation kind of
shoots right over the edge there.
Oops.
You know what?
Can you say?
Yeah, so we took a little too long.
We took a little too long, you know, are bad anyway, so you know,
we've got that sort of stuff here and you can see that you can have
multiple of them and all that other good stuff, right?
And everything kind of response dynamically and it's all nice and
easy.
And again you know we're not trying to make a professional.
You I hear anything like that but I am trying to show how easy it is.
It's only been a few hours on the actual UI stuff, right?
I'm just trying to show how easy it is that you can make some
interactable things.
You don't have to link some
gigantic UI Library into your game or anything.
You can trivially have some perfectly usable.
Debug you I in in only just a few lines of code really and so that's
kind of a nice thing.
All right, so what I'd like to do now, the first thing I like to do is
I want to make it so we can just tear off pieces of this thing.
So for example, if I'm in the debugging thing and I have this, this by
thread thing here, I want to be able to like grab it, you know.
And you can see like, right now, the only thing that'll do is it'll
just like turn on and off.
What I want to be able to do is like grab this thing and drag it out
here and have like that that profiler or whatever it is.
I want to have that thing through like sort of like throw up a little,
you know, separate debug list or whatever, you know.
So, you know, just just something that allows me to do.
That kind of operation.
And again it's really not that hard to do something like that.
So I just kind of wanted to show how easy it is to make some things
that are that can have that kind of capability.
Alright, so here we go.
So here we are in handmade debug, you can see it here.
And the way that we've got our stuff structured is we have these debug
variable groups and then we have these debug variables and what you
can see here is that a debug variable itself, actually stores.
The data that it's trying to edit, right?
It's the, it is the actual debug variable.
And the problem with that is it means that it's hard for us to put a
debug variable in more than one place.
Ace, right?
What we would much rather do is have this be in directed in some way
because we'd like to be able to have every debug variable be
referenceable from multiple places at once.
So the only thing I really need to do to have that is just to have an
in directed list.
Now we've talked about these before but we don't really ever use them
in my recollection in handmade hero because Dudley and directed list,
just aren't that common in games, we probably will see some little bit
later it when we're talking about things that are more like you know,
maybe like this guy.
Is like, chasing some people and their double, you know, who knows
there's going to be some things for doing the heaven but just we just
have not really had much use for them and they're a lot less common in
things like games than they are in something like an editor where
you're going to have more of that happening.
But either way, they're extremely easy, right?
All we have to do is introduce some secondary structure that instead
will keep what, you know will capture.
The linkage part of things and that linkage part will be separate from
the variable itself, right?
so now,
Whatever this thing actually is right.
We won't have to actually worry about about how many people want to
use it.
They will always just sort of be able to keep creating these new debug
variable references inside their hierarchies.
And you know, well they'll just be able to yeah they'll just be able
to keep on referencing and referencing and referencing and referencing
as much as they want.
And because the rest of this stuff
All just, you know, what you would expect.
Then all we really have to do is change anyone who is actually going
to be using one of these things, right?
To actually point to a reference instead of of an actual variable,
right?
So, for example, here, where we've got a group that's holding a bunch
of things, what we want.
Now, want to do, is, instead of making that group actually hold debug
variable chains.
We just want to hold reference chains, right?
And similarly, when we have a debug variable hierarchy,
Excuse me.
What we'd want to do, there is have that hierarchy basically take some
kind of a reference as well.
Now, I don't know.
when I think I'm kind of thinking about it here,
I feel like probably the debug variable hierarchy thing should
probably do something slightly different.
So I want to hold off on modifying that because I think we might want
to do something slightly different there.
So, for now, let me just, I'm just going to do the work necessary to
Port this, over to having, debug variable references, be things that
are kind of process dynamically in that way, right?
Alright, so here we go.
We've got our debug variable reference stuff.
I should probably make this defined up there so it can refer
Here we go.
And then you here when we do debug, add variable, what we want to do
now is essentially just make both things here because this is still
used generally to create, you know, sort of a referencing sort of a
scheme.
So what I'm going to do is I'm going to make
A debug variable thing here which is, which is like debug add, you
know, fun reference variable in case we want to ever do that
specifically.
And that will do just the part of this that does not involve the the
grouping, right?
So basically this part and then what we'll do is we'll say, okay,
we'll create the variable.
There we go.
And then we will also Jimmy once we create the variable, we will also
create a debug variable.
So do you add variable reference context type?
Well, we don't need type all I think we really need is context and
probably the variable, right?
And then in here, we'll just do debug variable reference
and the debug variable reference will just do this part.
You know that we saw before, right?
And this presumably will return a debug variable reference.
Well actually, I guess, I don't know which one it would have to
return.
I think you probably want it to return the variable reference because
the variable reference could get to the variable, but the variable
can't get to the reference, right?
So do it that way.
All right.
Yeah so in here what we would need for our debug variable reference,
we just need something that actually points the debug variable and
there it is.
And so when we create this debug variable reference, let's go ahead
and put that in there.
Again, really nothing.
Particularly interesting going on here.
Debug variable.
VAR.
And so when you know we're just going to do the exact same thing we
did before we're going to get another one of these guys.
Do you like variable reference we're going to push the debug variable
reference on to the arena.
We're going to go ahead and set the reference so that it's a variable
points to the variable that we were given and then all the rest of
these things that we used to do groupwise, they're all going to be
talking about the reference now instead of talking about the variable,
but that's about it, right?
Not a lot else going on there.
So, that's all we need to do there.
Now, on the parent front, again I think the parent front wants to be
doing references as well.
So so basically like when you look at this thing, we want to we want
our trees are cut the trees.
We construct.
I think always want to be references so we can have arbitrary trees in
the variables underneath will just be you know specific things or
whatever.
Right?
And so if we have that we need this to be a variable reference like
so.
And this right here would need to be
Of a reference like so.
And then if we move down, when we're talking about like the group cure
or whatever, we're actually going to talk about the group VAR, right?
Because now the group like is always sort of an indirect pointer
there.
And, you know, if we want to I suppose we could also do it this way
where we just say you know, we've got context group and you know, if
the group itself
We could also do something like this group ref.
In fact, I could do it like this.
Right, ref parent.
And then I can do something like, you know, here's the group.
And if the ref parent is not zero,
Oops, then we'll go ahead and grab that ref parent variable out.
Right.
So there we go.
All right in here in here.
It thinks it cannot convert something to a variable reference.
Now, why would that be?
Oh, that's because I forgot a pointer there.
That's no good.
Oops, let's try that again.
Debug add variable cannot convert from variable reference.
Okay.
So that's fine.
Where we begin variable group that will just do this.
Excuse me.
That's all really simple.
Nothing really to do there.
When we return groups, right?
This should return a reference as well and debug add variable same
thing here.
This is going to be reference.
This is going to be VAR this election year FR.
These are all rest now and I assume diesel are going to be something
like this, right?
Yeah, and again, all I'm really doing nothing.
Particularly unusual here, just really basic stuff.
I'm just changing it to that.
These things are kind of doubly directed and that just allows me to
have the superstructure stored in something other than the data is
stored in.
And it's just a really, really basic transformation.
It's a little bit of typing, but it doesn't really, you know, nothing.
Nothing momentous is happening.
It's really just pretty boring, pretty milquetoast, pretty
milquetoast.
And so yes.
That's about it.
These guys obviously are returning references now and so they kind of
have to go through that VAR and direction.
And again, this is debug code.
So we don't care about the in directions, either, we don't really care
at all about this stuff.
If it's performance was bad, we just buy a faster dead machine.
No users ever.
Have to run it.
So it only matters if it works, and it's convenient for us to
implement and hopefully it will be both of those things, although
sometimes you never do.
No.
All right.
Let's keep going.
So now, we want to go ahead and propagate this change out.
One level up, which is to say that the route group structure that
these people are working.
With, we really want to have a debug variable reference there.
And so, the hierarchy group, I guess I said I wasn't going to do it
yet, but I guess I will actually do it because, hey, we might as well
propagate it out and then I'll fix it in a second.
So then we have when we're writing our stuff out, when we do our route
groups.
Now we're going to want to look at vars here, right?
Like so, and these are not vars.
Really, these are refs.
And so we'll have debug variable bar equals ref.
Bar then all this stuff should work.
Basically the same, the only difference now is that the end
We do stuff.
Yeah.
The we're going to set the ref, not the VAR, right?
So we're really just working off of refs here because we're iterating
over the rest of the bars are.
Just this kind of like thing that we're looking into underneath that
make sense.
Okay.
Yeah.
And so we're going to have to do like I said, we're going to do
another round of lofting a second, but that's okay.
So, let's just go ahead and finish this up.
So in here again, we've got that hark a group thing so that's going to
have to access inside.
What are you complaining about, mr.
Right, we go and let's see.
Do we say hot equals far?
So this is actually a good guy said again, ref.
And then we have a debug variable VAR which is going to be the ref bar
and then we just have to fix our iterators.
Like I said before, we're iterating on ref now.
So this stuff just works like this.
Right.
Okay.
So I think that's it.
And in theory, this should still work relatively similarly to the way
it does before modulo any errors.
That we may have made, but it looks like it's pretty good, right?
We're still able to iterate over our things and all that stuff is
fine, right?
So that all seems pretty good.
So let's go ahead and check now.
Now that we have those variable references.
Let's see if we can do something where we take, you know, a
particular, debug variable and we add it into two different groups,
right?
Just to test that ability to make sure that we've actually done it.
Right.
So now, you know, let's say we've got something that we have here,
like, debug camera distance.
I want to go ahead and add that outside.
I'm going to say that.
I have a debug variable reference here.
That's the debug cam.
Use debug camera for something like that.
That use debug camera F.
When I do my debug variable listing, I'm going to grab it.
I don't know if I can actually do that with the macro.
I think I can.
Yeah, I can.
And so, when I come out here, what I want to do is I want to go ahead
and add a variable at the very end.
It's going to shadow that variable, they're going to be the same
variable, right?
So what I would do there is I'd say, use debug, cam ref.
I want to add like a few.
Oops, let me do that and made debug variables.
I want to go ahead and add that guy in.
So, what I want to do here is just debug add vertical reference like
so and debug, add variable reference will take the context and then I
can add this variable again.
So I'm just going to take that variable that I added before.
I'm going to add it again, right there, right.
Oops, and got it.
Get rid of that parent, add, that's there.
So now when I run, you know, if I open this up, you can see that I've
got used the about camera here which didn't used to be here, and it's
the same use debug camera.
That's right here.
And in fact, you can even see that when I Mouse over them now, they
both highlight because they're the same variable, and I'm testing for
highlighting.
I'm testing variable Miss and when I change them, they both change and
I can change them in either place, right?
And again, that's all I really wanted to do there.
I wanted to make it.
So there was no penalty for having things in more than one place
because I'm a
To have things in more than one place.
And now I do, right?
So, that's good.
Okay.
Alright, so now we're going to need some more memory gonna need some
more memory.
So one of the things that we do here is we take like all the memory
that we have are allowed to use for our debug system.
Which means that if I wanted to make more stuff, I wouldn't be able to
do.
So right there would be no way for me to actually make a new menu.
If I was going to tear one off, there would be no way to actually do
that, which is kind of, which is a villa bit, it's bad.
So that poop sauce, right?
And so, you can see where that's actually happening, right?
We have the, the debug start thing.
And up here, you can see me initialize this Arena like this.
You can see me, sort of like getting the, the size that do big arena.
And then I come down through here, we do like allocate render group,
we do all these sorts of things.
When we do the restart collation from not very much an error, we then
go ahead and take that collation Arena.
And yeah, that's the thing that we actually use to do all of our debug
scratch work.
And so,
Let's take a look at that, so when we do that sub Arena, oh, I'm a
liar.
We don't use all the memory.
Okay, so we still did leave some memory for use in stuff like this so
that's good.
All right, so when we want to we should be able to just go ahead and
make more of these anytime we want.
And that's pretty sweet.
I like that that makes me happy camper.
So if I want to do
All of this stuff.
All I really need to do now is make some way for me to have more, you
know, more than one of these debug variable hierarchies, right?
Because the debug variable, hierarchy is the thing that controls what
is drawn.
And right now, I can only have one of them when we called Drake draw,
debug menu, you can see that I can only draw one debug hierarchy.
It's like hard-coded to be that one.
So what I'd rather do is make it so that I can draw like as many debug
car keys as I want, right?
I'd rather have something that's just a for Loop here that
Draws debug hierarchies, like you know, and just keep stirring them in
drawing the drawing, the drawing them.
You know I'm saying?
Something like that.
And this debug State at why thing.
That's a bit of a janky thing as well.
Because, you know, that's just it means, it'll depend, we need like a
cut more of a, you know, a concept of where that stuff is going to go.
We have those sort of things are just like the little command line
compiling thing and that kind of stuff.
We need a better sense of where those goes because we these are now
these floating menu things and there's no such there's no real sense
of like, where things would get appended.
So, there's a bunch of things we need to do for that.
So just ignore that for now.
Forget about that stuff.
We don't care about that at all.
We're going.
Back around to it and just pluck it out, just give it a little pluck
with some Zircon.
Encrusted tweezers.
We're just going to reach in there and just grab it.
All right.
So we need to do here, we need to Loop over some of these things.
So I want something like, you know, hierarchy equals, you know debug
stayed first hierarchy or something.
Ridiculous.
Like that, I don't even know like this, or maybe there's a hierarchy
Sentinel, I don't even know hierarchies Sentinel or something like
this.
And I just want to go until hierarchy Sentinel next or something like
that.
Yeah so there's you know debug variable Harkey next or previous
something like that and so when the hierarchy is not equal to the
central anymore I'm just going to Loop through it.
And that would allow me to just have like some arbitrary number of
those.
And then when we actually talked about the hierarchy itself, we would
actually just grab whatever Harkey we want.
And that means we can have as many of those things, you know, floating
around, as we want to have floating around, they can just float float,
and float and Float all day long and no one will care.
No, I'm saying to you.
Getting be allergy season, man.
There's gonna be some stuffy noses.
So buckle up
Alright so here's here's that list, you know, iteration that I want to
have happen.
So all I have to do if I want that literally serration to happen, is I
have to actually just go implement it.
So now, our hierarchy is actually going to become the hierarchy
Sentinel
Like this.
And when I recompile everything will break and then I can fix it
because, you know, I'm just gonna do some fixing of it.
Never mind.
So when I go ahead and add that hierarchy function here, which is the
thinks we're gonna want, we're going to want to add our route group.
So we just want to do something that's going to like put the hierarchy
we already had in, is the only hierarchy, right?
So we're going to want something called add hierarchy, that's going to
do that for us because that's, you know, pretty obvious.
And we just tell it, where are we?
To go and then we tell it, you know like what the route group was
presumably, it would return to us with the hierarchy was you know
that's it.
Nothing fancy and then let's see what else it would complain about.
Yeah I know you don't have ad hierarchy so in here cannot convert ok
so I don't even take an address there I don't know why I thought I did
that was just kind of stupid.
Alright and so this is just going to be pointers because it wasn't a
pointer before.
Now it is pointers and yeah I think that's it.
So as long as we have a function called add a hierarchy that would
give us what we want.
Ain't nothing particularly weird about that, it's just we've seen me
do it a million times again.
This is the thing about not having metaprogramming.
I hate templates and I refuse to use them.
So I am happy to like code my own linked lists by hand when I need
them.
Normally work, I just met a code them.
But if I don't have them, I just type them in because I find that that
like actually works and trying to use templates, never does.
It's always a disaster and then you just have the iso C++ committee
squatting on you the whole time and it's awful.
So anyway, let's go ahead and go ahead and get a debug variable
reference in here.
Debug variable reference
and,
P the location where it's going to be.
So that's what I want.
I just need to get one of these so I can push struct into the debugger
Arena pretty easily.
Right?
So I can make a new one of these.
Where I just say like, okay, here's my debug variable hierarchy, my
new one, right?
like so and when I grabbed this hierarchy out debug variable
hierarchy,
I just need to initialize the stuff that's in it, so the UI p is going
to be at P.
The group is going to be the route group or I shouldn't even say root
group anymore because it's just group, it happens through the roof
group.
The first time I call it but that's it.
The next and the previous are just going to be again, standard doubly
linked list here.
It takes 10 seconds, Implement right?
You've got the hierarchy Sentinel.
Like so, so the previous pointer going to insert this at the head end
to the previous guy is going to be the sensible itself but whoever the
Sentinels next pointer was is going to be our next pointer and then we
just need to fix up the other pointers, right?
So at that point, we know that whoever is next.
Whoever is the person that comes after us their previous pointer
should point to us and whoever came before us their next pointer,
should point to us, right?
And that's about all there is to it, so then we finally probably want
to make sure that we actually returned this so that anyone who's
trying to do something with it.
After it's been added.
Excuse me, have barbecue for lunch, man.
It was crazy.
It's too much food.
All right.
So let's see.
Here we go.
Ahead and we do our push struct.
That seems like it's corrupt.
That's should be an address for
Way.
Huh.
Let's see.
Do not have an overloaded operator.
That is correct.
It does not have an overloaded operator.
I agree with you and that should be a pointer.
Okay, so that adds something our Sentinel to the list there.
And I think I don't remember if I wrote The Loop code there, I don't
think that I did.
So that's probably a little bit of an issue.
I also don't know if I have to clear out those pointers to point to
each other at the outset and so I just have to make sure that all that
stuff is kosher at
Start up and then I think we should be fine.
So when we create our context here, here it is, right?
We get our debug state.
I can just make that hierarchy, let's see where it is.
So we've got the next equals.
The hierarchy itself.
Again, I'm just standard doubly linked list, making the list start out
pointing The Sentinel point to itself.
So it's an empty list.
And I'm also going to go ahead and make that group pointer point to
zero, just to make sure that everyone knows that.
If you try to iterate over it, you would be very unhappy and things
would go horribly wrong for you.
So don't do that.
And let's see.
So I think that's the only thing I had left to implement on the linked
list but I can't quite remember.
Let's see.
Looks like we are drawing that multiple times that if I'm not
mistaken.
So I feel like we are not exiting out of our Loop.
Quite right?
Let me double-check that my for Loop.
There it is.
Right?
Okay, so in the debug car key, we go through the next one.
We Loop over it until we are.
Done with that.
And let me check my Harkey ad ad Harkey.
That looks correct and the previous points back to the hockey Sentinel
itself, that all looks good and the hierarchy, the next previous
points back to me and the previous/next for expect to me.
Okay, so that's good.
But it does look like we're doing multiple times.
So I'm going to grab the stuff in there to the draw main menu or what
is it?
Debug grub main menu.
Debug, where is that draw?
Main menu thing?
There it is, draw debug menu, that's what it's called.
Somehow we, you know what?
You know what the fudge man?
What the fudge?
Alright, debug draw menu.
Names.
At least a little bit more consistent.
Okay.
So my step into debug Drummond you they're actually going to do at
hierarchy.
Okay, and so let's just make sure everything is kosher here.
And yeah.
Actually wanted to look at that Sentinel RQ.
Sentinel next, there is my next guy.
So here's me which is no and here's my next guy and then the next one
points back to the Sentinel.
So that's good.
That's exactly what I wanted that all looks nice and then let's go
ahead and continue on.
Or try to continue on, where is my drug debug menu?
Oops, that's handmaids.
That's not actually where I don't want to be in handmade.
I'll see the PO me, he made debug, there we go.
And so here I should have my drum and you function.
And of course, there it is debug menu.
And so if I come through here, I should be drawing the hierarchy
hierarchy.
There we go.
So that's good.
And there's our debug variable group as well.
So I come through here and this thing does all of its drawing fun and
that's all good.
And then it should just kind of blessed bust out of there.
And then when I come through here, well, I exit it out.
So that seems totally correct.
Actually and I'm not really sure what the problem is.
You know what the problem is?
I bet add hierarchy, I bet I'm calling that in the yeah.
Nice, that's pretty stupid.
You got to admit.
It's pretty stupid.
I was calling that once a frame, that's going to be a lot of
hierarchies and a lot of drawing.
So let's not do that.
Question though, how will we know where to put this hierarchy?
When we do not actually know how big things are.
I guess we probably do actually know how big they are because we could
calculate this stuff ahead of time I suppose, right?
Like we would know what these things are, I suppose?
So if we want to, we could probably do, we can probably do that stuff,
right?
So, we could probably start out putting it at like that and
We could start out with this guy being, you know, at 0.5 times height.
Okay.
So now I think we're in better shape, right?
Everything seems pretty good there, everything is happy and smiling.
And so let's go ahead and make it so that we can tear things off of
here.
Which again is something that I said I wanted to do.
So if I want to be able to tear things off of here, what I'm going to
do for that is we have that sort of interaction concept here.
what I'm going to do is
Had a new interaction concept.
And that interaction concept is going to allow you to Terror groups
off and put them in other places.
So okay, if I was going to do that, what I'd like to do is go ahead
and introduce some kind of a little thing here into my interactions
type.
And so, what I'm going to do is I guess I've got this tear value
thing, right.
And
So I feel like probably the easiest thing to do would just be to put a
little thing that I could tear that I could use to tear stuff off of.
We'll try that first, we'll see.
But what I'm going to do before anything else is I'm going to make it
so that the toggle value thing, I'm just gonna make it.
So it always tears and then we'll have a way to do the tearing
separately.
So I'm going to go into toggle value here.
And say, when we do debug begin about, you know what, why am I just
what I do?
It just like, stop, like blabber.
At it and just go just do it, it take you longer to do it.
Then it would, it's like, say all this stuff.
So, anyway, when I do the push wrecked, you saw me before do this
where I put a size box in here.
Right.
And so what I could do instead like with other stuff is I could go
ahead and make it so that everything has like a little tear off thingy
like thing and so I'm just going to do that because why not right and
so to do that I would just do the exact same thing I did here, right?
I just do this.
Oops.
You know I'm saying where I basically just have like okay so there's a
tear box or something like this and the terror box would just be
something that we put that allows you to like grab the thing and like
put it somewhere else, you know.
Or something like that, right?
And you know, you could even do something fancier than that.
If you wanted to you could make it the like if you if you if you you
know had a modifier key held down or something like that, I don't
know.
But for right now I'm just going to do it this way or you know what?
No, I'm not gonna do it that way.
Let's just do it this way.
Let's say we have debug interaction none, but if we are in some
situation,
Where we actually do have some kind of extra input thing happening.
Some kind of, you know, something else happening.
Then we will do, do the chair right.
You know, something like this, like, you know, be 32 all you I right?
And so in here, there's like some kind of all you I think where we
just say like okay if you had whatever the all UI thing is down, then
it's going to be at are operation otherwise it's going to be an
operation, right?
Something like that.
Does that seem fair?
And maybe these guys work the same way as well.
I don't know, maybe will formalize that later.
I'm not sure.
But something like this and then when we isn't anything tear value,
Okay.
And then, you know, in here, what we'll do is, we'll just say, I don't
know, like, whatever is supposed to be happening, is happening.
If you have the something ALT key down to these, do the modifiers.
Do we have modifiers on here?
I don't even remember Mouse button Mouse buttons.
So we don't seem to have any modifiers, but we could actually add
those pretty easily, right?
We could add a modifier key and they're pretty trivially for right
now.
What I'll do is I'll just say like,
Okay, you know, the mouse P, the old UI thing, maybe the old UI and
you know what?
I could even do that, that doesn't even have to happen in here.
Now, I think about it, I could do that in a totally different way.
I could do that, where we just have, where we had the left Mouse
button thing and this thing doesn't even have to know about it.
What I could do is I could say, all right, when we do the the
interaction, begin stuff, right?
Debugged again, interaction and hear what I could do is say like, if
we were about to do an interaction with the right Mouse button, then,
let's do something a little bit different, you know what I'm saying?
Something like that.
Or if the right Mouse button was down at the time or something like
that and then
Will later make that be an ALT key thing?
So we could do something like, you know, input.
Like you I hear I could do this.
so, if the right Mouse button is down,
We're in all UI mode or I guess I should say ended down.
There we go.
So if the right Mouse button is down at the time there were in all UI
mode and we'll just go ahead and make the begin interact up here to
get interact.
Well, how about you I hear
Like so.
And then what we'll do there is what just say like if there was a hot
thing, right?
Then if there's a hot interaction, will do it.
If there's not a hot interaction.
What we'll do instead here is will say, well, if the old UI is
happening, we always want to tear the value, right?
So if the all UI is happening, then we're just going to force the
value to be a tear
Otherwise.
We won't.
Something like that.
And I guess now I think about it.
This could, this could happen up here as well.
Let's see.
There we go.
So that's all good but we didn't actually ever Implement Terror value.
So now I actually do have to implement Terror value.
You know what I'm saying?
And so we've got dragged value right?
And we implemented that but we never implemented tear value.
So let's go ahead and do that.
Here's tear value.
Like so and when we want to do at are value, all we want to do for
Terror value is just, we just want to create right.
Another, you know, some other sort of
Some other one of these, add hierarchy things, right?
And then we just want that to sort of persist.
So we want to do something like you know, we have a debug variable
hierarchy, right?
Which is like the the dragging hierarchy this sort of thing.
you know I'm saying and that is just a variable that we would set here
where we'd say like okay, you know if you had not actually done
That yet if you had not created the debug State Dragon hierarchy, then
go ahead and create that reading hierarchy equals add Harkey,
interacting with whatever the thing is that we're interacting with.
That's the variable that we want their, right?
Trying to think if we also need a new group to hold this variable, I
think we do.
So we actually want to do to hear as we want to.
To add a group, a new group.
I'm going to hold off on that for one second.
Just one little second, right?
And then we're going to do is we're just going to say like wherever
the mouse is like, I don't look wherever it is.
The debug State dragging Harkey.
You IP is going to be equal to that location.
Right?
And then debug hierarchy whenever we end our interaction, like when
were clearing out our state will just clear out that state and will be
done.
You know.
Okay, so if we do an ad hierarchy here, what we need to know at this
point like I said is we need to have some way of adding a group
because you can see that this is supposed to take a debug variable
reference.
and at the moment,
We aren't giving it that, and I'm pretty sure it needs a reference to
an actual group as well.
So, we, what we want to do here is, have some way of adding a debug
variable group directly, write a reference to a group.
So, we want a thing that's like, you know, like our debug begin
variable group thing, right?
We want to be able to do that but we want to be able to do that
outside of having a context, right?
So we want to be able to do something that does like debug
Add route group, something like that, which just takes the debug
content, the debug state.
By itself.
And can go from there so it can add the group it'll set its expansion
I guess in this case would be expanded would be set to true if the
route group it initialize its children stuff to not have anything in
it or anything like that.
And it'll set, you know, it'll set us up to actually use that thing.
As a root group.
Now we need a context of do, debug, add variable.
But what I'm going to do here is just
You know what?
I'm just thinking this through.
If we always have a group for every one of these floaty things,
Then really, these don't need to be referenced variables, do they?
So really they'd be these things that makes sense?
So really what we're looking at is something more like this, right?
or you might even say debug state state,
State feedback Arena.
You know, I'm saying.
And then these guys, when they actually call debug add-on reference
variable, it would just, you know, call it like that or whatever.
This is what we actually, I think probably want because there's no
reason to create a variable reference for that as far as I can think
of.
So when we do add route group, what we actually be doing is, is adding
on a reference variable, right?
And we do it, it would look like this, right?
So we do debug add-on reference variable.
We passed the state.
and it would be nice if we can get these two things to play together
and I think that we can write probably, what we would do is we just do
this where we say like okay,
You know, add a route group or something like that.
Like like this, you know, add a route group and then add the reference
for the route group immediately thereafter.
You know what I'm saying?
So be like this sort of thing.
Where we just do.
That.
And then, we could set it so that it's this, these guys don't expand
by default or something like that, right?
That seems that seems pretty same to me.
I know how you guys feel about it, but that seems reasonable, right?
Or at least somewhat reasonable.
okay, so I'm going to just make this
Go away for a second.
So and then I'm going to double check that.
That worked to add the stuff normally, it does.
Okay so now to finish our caring implementation, what we do here is
say okay when were dragging these things, what I want to be able to do
is I want to be able to add a route group here like so and then oops,
it's not right.
What I want to be I'll do is add a route group here.
Look at Route group.
And then, what I want to do is I want to add the variable to the
group, right?
I want to add a reference of the variable to that particular group.
And again, that's going to force me to kind of make this be a
two-level thing.
That's not going to use the context anymore, but that's okay.
Right.
Totally fine with that.
So if we do debug ad route group here, this will give me back a debug
variable.
That's my route group.
The route group itself will be the thing that the hierarchy sees.
Like that.
And again, they'll just take the debug State and the route group will
just take a name and I guess it doesn't really need a name because
it's never displayed.
It's just going to be like a user group, I guess or something like
that.
I don't know.
It never actually show that name.
I don't think, I don't actually know, we'll have to verify that that's
true.
But yes, I'm pretty sure that's true.
And so now all I really have to do is just go through here and
presumably make it so that that ad hierarchy actually,
Make sure that that takes a debug variable for the group, and the
hierarchies themselves are always taking debug variables, right?
So, something like this,
Okay, so
The context group.
In this case, we'll just grab the variable out.
Same thing here.
So in this case we don't have to dereference it by VAR and so we're
just doing this and now this should work I think properly and you can
kind of see there that it does.
Right?
And so now I just need to make it so that we can tear the values off.
We've already implemented the code for it essentially but what we have
not done is made it so that it actually adds anything now.
And interaction.
I guess the terror value doesn't actually need to do anything.
I don't think.
I'm pretty sure it only needs to do it here.
And so what we really need now is just a way of taking whatever the
thing was that, you were interacting with and adding it to that group.
So we want to do something like, you know,
Add variable to group.
Or debug add reference, I guess would be the thing.
So inside the variables thing where we have the add variable
reference.
Dear God variable reference we want to do is make it so that context
thing isn't actually required anymore.
So when you add a variable,
Friends what we'd say is like okay then you're going to need the debug
State because we need to be able to allocate it.
You're going to need the variable.
But then now we'll just say, OK, say there is a group, so you pass it,
the group and the variable and it just does that it just adds it to
that group, right?
And so, if I wanted to do that, all I would do is say the debug arena
is the arena are coming from so, you know, that's fine.
We have the debug variable reference, we allocate that we do all the
stuff that we need to do here, but now, instead of getting that group
out of context instead,
We get it like this, right?
And I don't think we need anything else there.
Well, I lied that's very sad.
Since people use their parents as a reference
Although in this case I do they even need to do that.
They don't.
So I guess they don't need a parent.
So I guess that's actually all fine too.
No.
I mean since you want to have the rest of so I guess I do.
You know I was hoping I get away with that.
If it doesn't look like it, it doesn't look like it.
It looks like this is going to have to be that way.
So that's the way it has to go fine by me.
Don't really care one way or the other.
So anyway,
Moving on, we do the exact same thing.
We were doing here.
Everything's the same.
The only difference is we don't sort of Loft it out of the context.
We just get it directly.
So it's the exact same function.
And so, all this is going to do.
Now is just, do you know, it's just literally going to do a pass
through, right?
So, when you're calling it from the sort of Builder context, like we
were using before, where your career instructing, these lists, you
would call it this way.
And here, what it does is it says, like, okay, when I'm going to pass,
What I'm going to pass this in, what I'm going to do is I'm going to
grab that group out of the context.
Like this.
And then it's going to be called the exact same code that anyone else
could call when they don't have a context, right?
So, this way, again, turning the context, just into like a helper for
that code below and since you don't ever actually need one.
So if we do, if we do it that way, we should be able to Now call debug
add variable reference directly this.
Unfortunately, again, I'm going to have to say that we do have to do
it the way that I was going to do it before.
I didn't really want to do it that way.
But turns out, we have to because the fact that our tree uses that as
a parent pointer kind,
If there's really no way of getting around it but then we just say,
okay, whatever the thing was we were interacting with now we're going
to tear it off, right?
And so we're going to add that in and we're going to go from they're
going to make that BR Harkey.
And that's pretty much all we would need to do.
But that just means that I have to make it so that we could do to me.
I think we're going to do before so let me just go ahead and make that
work.
There we go.
Do you look at variable none of the overloads, convert all the
argument types?
Debug add variable reference
Context State, there we go.
And then debug add route group, like I said before, debug at Route
group just now does have to be a thing that actually adds a variable
reference which is not particularly tough.
It just means that now the debug variable reference it will have, it
will have to actually call to make one of those four are stinking that
we would not actually have to make one of those, but it turns out that
we do.
So when we
Add the route group here.
In fact really, it's sort of almost exact same as this thing, too.
It just means that when we add the route group,
We're going to have to do something like this where we add the
variable reference.
We're going to pass zero cure because it's the route group and then
we'd pass the VAR here like this and then we'd pass that state, right?
So I think all of that stuff is going to be basically the same.
I don't think there would be anything else that we'd have to do with
it.
But again, it does mean that when we call debug add route group here,
we would be able to do that.
So, what we do is we say debug variable reference, right?
This would be debug variable there.
And this would be like, debug.
Ad group group, debug state state are surname, right?
Let's go ahead and return that.
Okay.
So now this is basically our debug a drupe internal, right?
Look, nobody else is going to ever call that.
It's just a utility and now we have two ways that's called, right?
We have one way that calls it here.
Right.
You can see that and I guess I could do it this way will be easier to
read.
So you've won way the calls it there.
That's the guy who actually has to add it using the context and it's a
little bit tortured.
I would unwind this if we weren't on stream it's not so you know
they're just some fussing I could do to make that a little online but
I want to finish this up and we only have about five minutes left so
I'm not going to do it right now or ever potentially.
But anyway, so we go ahead and do debug a drupe internal.
We can call that now from here, as well.
Here's debug a blueprint route, group internal.
Mmm.
Being called a second time.
When I call that here, what I'm going to do now is I'm going to add a
reference as well, but I'm not going to use the context call, right?
So instead what I'm going to do is called debug, add variable
reference with the one that takes the state and the group to add 2,
which is nobody in this case.
So that'll add that variable reference and allow me to return the
group ref like so,
So that's really all I need to do there.
I think
And then I'll just fix picks up whatever else there is.
There we go.
Yeah.
Now, add Harkey goes back to the way that it was before.
Jen nothing, particularly special there and just have to fix the
compiler.
Has that that introduced?
Which is that the debug Road group is now back to exactly.
And this is just basically reverting that change, right?
That's all I'm doing here.
Nothing else.
And that's about it for that.
Okay, so let's take a look what happens here.
I don't know where we're at.
When I hold down the right Mouse button, I think that was the cue for
doing the tear off.
So let's see what happens.
Let's see.
Oops, that's supposed to be a, not dragging hierarchy.
So off we go, let's see what happens.
So, if I drag this now, I've got another group out there.
Perfect.
Yeah.
There we go.
And so, you can see kind of what happens here.
I can now have multiple ones of these and the only problem that we
have now is, you know, things like the expansion, state of these guys
is mirrored because they're going to be in the same, like, sort of
situation right now I could so it's pretty easy.
If I build a new group out here, you know, I can put
Guys, I can leave them out here and those all work pretty nicely.
But yeah, again, what I might want to do is have it so that the expand
and collapse state for groups is going to be something that actually
gets sort of.
It gets its own state for that and there's multiple ways that we could
do that.
There's actually two different ways.
To do that.
What I'd like to do instead of focusing on that at all at the moment
as I'd like to do one more thing first and then we could maybe talk
about that next week since we don't have a whole lot of time here.
I'd like to be able to move these guys around.
You know I'd like to be able to move.
Once I put them somewhere, I'd like to be able to do something other
than pulling them off like I am at the moment.
You know, I'd like to be able to sort of move them once they've been
pushed and so what
Going to do there to is just again, introduced a little UI element,
something pretty simple.
Which is something, you know, that's going to be, I don't know,
something like this which is really, you know, move hierarchy or
something like that.
Something like this and that would just do something where it would
go.
Like, okay, if you're going to move,
If you're going to move a hierarchy, it will take whatever the
dragging hierarchy, uip is, and it will do the sort of same thing that
was doing with the with the Mouse stuff, right?
So I'd like to have a way to do that.
So I'm going to go ahead and add that.
A priority.
And the only problem with that is we don't currently have any way of
actually making that do anything, right?
We don't have a way of getting, you know, saying that we want that to
be what happens.
But I should be able to do something relatively quickly that allows us
to make it so that you can do that.
Juvie.
Not sure what the easiest way would be.
But one way might be, I could take, you know, one of these, one of
these sorts of things here, right?
And when I first draw the hierarchy, maybe.
What I do is I do some kind of a thing where I create a box which is
like the movement box for the thing.
Yeah.
Or something like this.
And I say that that's going to be whatever the uip of this thing is,
you know, there's like a little kind of, there's a little hot.
Hot guy there and maybe we'll do them at the end.
So he always has Primacy as well, you know?
So we'll do that.
You know, will render the thing?
Do a push wrecked, we'll call this.
The move box will do some kind of, you know,
We'll do some kind of a test on it.
Like, if you know what, I don't really care about this.
The moment I'll leave this as just a thing we're gonna do is we don't
have much time left.
And so now what I want to do is when I drag one of these out, right?
I get a little box there, I guess there's a little box in the corner
and what I might do is I might move it back a little bit from the uip,
right?
I might move it like, you know, so that it's off a little bit from the
UI p.
And so, if we are inside that rectangle, then what I'm going to say
is, you know, we've got something like, if it's inside the rectangle,
whatever the move box is to me.
Then what I'm going to do is say the next tide interaction, right?
Is going to be to move the hierarchy and the next hot thing where we
do this next hot hierarchy or whatever is going to be me.
Right, and you'll notice the next hierarchy thing.
This is kind of going to motivate the next change that I would want to
do here and I kind of alluded to it on the previous dream.
How these things start to proliferate?
I'll sort of probably want to start out Monday by doing this one, but
we're going to leave it that way for now.
So if we do that that's what we'll do.
It's all good.
And then here we'll have a thing where we're like, okay, debug
hierarchy
Next hot hierarchy.
That.
So then what I want to do and, you know, thinking about it too.
I feel like we probably could avoid that if we want to buy just having
tea, but to having Harkins themselves, we debug variables that
probably would have been a smart thing to do.
It's very tempting.
That's very, very tempting actually.
Mmm.
That would have been really smart.
I'm going to say that to do.
Car keys should be debug variables.
So I'm going to I'm going to say that that should happen.
But anyway, for a moment I'll just implement it in this kind of very
sloppy fashion.
And what I will do is say, okay, the next Harkey is going to be that
thing.
And so then what I'll say is, you know, when we do this thing when we
do the next hot thing there, right?
When when we do debug State, hot interaction that stuff, I'm going to
say that dragging hierarchy, equals next hierarchy.
That's it.
So okay.
So yeah, there's a couple ways we could do that.
Actually.
Now, I think about it that are pretty easy to.
So, we'll see.
So yeah.
So let's see if we can make this work at all.
So I should also do a thing where we can see whether we're inside
that.
So we know whether we're actually able to drag it or not, let me see
what happens with next hot Harkey here.
When I do dragging hierarchy, debug.
Interact, hot interaction, interaction goes hot interaction ragging,
hierarchy equals zero at the end of the end attract.
Okay so move box if is inside rectangle, move box you books 8?
Next hunt, interaction equals move hierarchy next.
Hierarchy equals hierarchy.
I feel like that should have worked but it did not work.
Why not?
Why did it not work?
Someone needs to tell me why it didn't work.
And I'm not sure.
Yeah.
All right.
Well,
What's the bucket?
Drop that guy.
Yeah, so never it never even gets in there.
Next Harkey.
You better state next Harkey.
Let's see.
Oh Next, Top hierarchy also, I wouldn't be having clearing it although
that doesn't actually matter.
Next hot.
There we go.
But doesn't really actually matter at all.
And in fact, technically next hot and next hard, umm it's really just
debug interaction.
None is the only thing that actually ever has to be cleared, but I
just like to do that so I can see it, right?
So what I'm going to do here is I'm just going to say that like okay
when we do this stuff I'm going to debug text line hierarchy.
I'm going to do that.
If the debug state.
Next hot hierarchy was nonzero.
right, so when we do debug interact and we come through
The debug drum anything at the end of it, I'm just going to say let's
add a text line if we if it thought we were interacting with the
hierarchy at that time.
Right.
So there we go.
So it does think we're interacting with it.
But for some reason we never set the we never set the thing, right?
So I'm going to go ahead and set a breakpoint at begin interact, just
to see what happens.
Yes, so it's never allowed to actually push the left Mouse button for
reasons unknown.
Oops,
So, let's see.
So it's just because it requires hot, that's dumb hot.
Interaction is supposed to be the thing that we check.
So that's just dumb, because that never should have been that way,
right?
It's only ever supposed to look like this.
It's only supposed to say like okay if there's a hot interaction we
always set the hot interaction if there isn't a hot interaction then
we would actually go into to this situation, right?
Because if there's a hot interaction, you always do it.
You just assume that the person knew what they were doing, maybe a bad
assumption but you assume it anyway, right?
Yeah, that's how that should actually work and then if they don't
click on anything, right?
If there was nothing, that was hot.
Fact, this this thing should be in here as well.
If there's nothing that was hot.
Then we just have this else case which is the to do the no op.
Alright, so let's try that again.
That was just an oversight in the way, I originally wrote that code.
That was not what I had ever intended.
That's just how it ended up in the series of steps we did to make it
so now we're all good here.
Looks like pretty good and this stuff all still works.
It looks like so that's good.
And now we can do are tearing off which I wanted to do.
So there we tear that off.
And in theory there we go.
Now we can drag as well.
Although
whoa.
looks like debug and interact assumes, we're always interacting with
something, which is not
What I ever actually wanted that to do and in fact should no longer be
an assertion because that's not something that I even care about that.
Looks like just some sort of vestigial remain, so that's fine.
All right so maybe that should go here because toggle value obviously
should always have one but all right,
All right.
Yay.
So that's pretty nice.
We're slowly, but surely getting there.
Building a reasonable UI system, it takes a few hours, but a few hours
is not very long.
And there's we're starting to get to the point where most of the
fundamental things are there and we just would want to polish them
maybe a little, you know, so they're not quite so ugly or janky.
But at this point, you know, you can do some pretty crazy stuff and it
all kind of works which is nice.
So I'll go ahead and go to a brief Q&A now now that we've got all that
working and we'll see what's going down.
So if you have any questions about we we did we will answer them.
Now, if you could please put 2: in front of it.
That would be pretty sweet so that I could see them.
Oh dear.
I should also probably get rid of that little debug print out.
Connor, Brent says no questions.
Well, if you don't have any questions.
Then that's it.
You just be like, all right, we're done.
Nothing to see here.
K you mentioned, that encapsulation is good but not in the loop way.
Could you elaborate then in which way you mean?
I just mean that it's fine to calve off sections of your project and
say that they are you know not supposed to be used by the outside
world, right?
Meaning once you're certain that something is like totally set the way
it should go.
You know, if you want to go ahead and move that out of like you know
the public interface for that thing.
Then that's fine, you know?
And I'll do that sometimes just mentally where I'm like, okay, you
know, I'll put a bunch of stuff in an h-file.
And these are the functions, you should call to use this system and
I'll take a bunch of the structs and a bunch of the functions out of
the HVAC.
I'm just put them in the CPP.
So it's kind of clear like these are the things you should call and
you shouldn't worry about anything else, right?
Because this, you know, sort of Library thing, or whatever it is that
I made doesn't, you know, there are certain things that I want you.
Sounds certain things that you don't and that's fine.
If that makes sense.
Insofar as our, the menu items spaced evenly vertically, it looks a
bit odd to me.
No, they're not at the moment.
The reason for that is because we don't actually use the font spacing
what we use is the rectangle spacing, which means that if something
has no descenders, it takes up less size and we can change that if you
want to, it's pretty simple, right?
Basically, all that's doing is in here where we do the this thing
where we do like the the first child, whatever debug text out.
Sighs thing.
What we would do instead is, when we do debug, get text size.
What we do is we force the bounds,
To actually be different.
So what we do is say, in fact, I guess what we do here is say that the
backgrounds of the text size should be made to ensure that they are
exactly the line size, right?
So whatever the line size is get line advance for this thing, right?
So what we want to do there and I think that's supposed to be
multiplied by the font scale, right?
Aunt, scale times.
Yeah.
So line advance for line advance.
Yeah, so basically that's what the line Advance should be.
So what we'd want to do there is just say, like, okay, in the case
that we're drawing a text element if you want to make sure they're all
spaced evenly instead of using the actual bounds here, you just say,
well, instead of that.
Let's actually just use whatever the whatever the line Advance is,
right?
So, what we'd say, is the bounds min
Should equal the bounds.
Max minus the line advance.
You know I'm saying and I suppose that's the band Min y, right?
And that would just be if you wanted to force them all, to be always
the same size, and now you can kind of see that happening there,
right?
Hopefully that didn't disconnect me.
Don't think it did.
So yeah, so now these these should be more reasonable sizes, least, I
think so.
Let me double-check that I did that right down.
Okay, Tim bounce.
Yeah.
And I think, you know what you do is you get rid of the spacing?
Why thing as well?
That would just be baked in there and we'd probably say that whatever
when this thing did its thing.
Well no, you probably put the spacing in there, you would probably put
the spacing in there.
So there's some room between them that maybe you wouldn't have, you
wouldn't?
I don't know.
It's hard to say.
It's hard to say, you know, the other way to do it is you put it in
here.
so, you would say something like,
Bounds.
Batman.
Why - equal spacing?
Why?
So things that aren't text, they get spaced.
They get that spacing.
Since they don't have a font line Advance telling them how they should
be spaced.
I feel like that would maybe make that work, you know what I mean?
But yeah.
So I think that's where it roughly.
What we would want to do.
So that makes sure that the band's minhwan
Max YY.
Yeah and so really all.
So I suppose the other thing you have to do is this stuff.
We really, if you want it all to be that way, after we get the text
size, we would want to Center, we would want to just just use the Min
and Max basically, right?
So we'd really do this, we'd really do rectangle, text bounds, like
that.
And then we do rectangle bounds, equal some, you know, something like
this.
We'd say rectangle min-max and we'd say we want it to be here, right?
We'd want it to do - whatever the Baseline thing was.
Right?
That's where we would want it to.
Or I guess.
Yeah, I guess we'd want to do the left side, we'd want to do the
bottom, which would just be the total, you know, however, much the the
line advanced was that's where the bottom is, right?
and,
The top is the top.
And the right is just going to be the left PX plus, whatever the width
of the, of the original one was, right?
Whatever the text bands were, in fact, this one you could kind of do
like, okay, the text bounds Min EX
Whatever that left PX is, it's just going to be the left, the X plus
the Min, right?
And the left PX
the max.
So that constructs the actual box, that is not sensitive to where the
text act, to what the text actual size is that just ignores the fact
that different texts are different sizes, because they may, or may not
have descenders or ascenders, right?
I think that would actually be what you would want to do, right?
And I don't remember exactly what this is.
Maybe recommend Max.
Yeah, so that's I think what you would want to do if you want to
eliminate any variability in the spacing and just space things
directly.
Oops.
That PX top view.
I did I do wrong there left the X Plus text bounds Min X.
And text bounds, Max dot X.
I feel like that should have been right Top py- Line advance and top
py.
What happened?
Bad there.
Oh, gotta love that variable shadowing.
There we go.
So that uses the actual line advance and so that should always be the
same now and it does look like it is so that's probably fine.
I don't know if that's what you wanted but that's how you would do
that.
Yeah.
Why is there so much lag latency when dragging the hierarchy is
around?
Or is that just Twitch streaming artifacts?
Well, me, see ya on my machine.
It's pretty much instantaneous.
The only the, the lag there is one bit of lag and that just happens
whenever the debug system resets, right?
Because we've never finished doing that part of the process, where the
debug collation thing happens, remember,
So, debug collation is still expensive there.
Because we never we've never made a cheap.
If you turned debug collation off, you would never have any hiccups.
You can see, it's, there's no lag at all.
And then when it does the debug collation, you get that hiccup, right?
And that's not a hiccup in the debug system, or in the game room.
That's literally just the collator, just the collator.
And so, if you just turned off player, that wouldn't be there, that is
something.
What we want to, we should probably fix eventually because it actually
we don't really care about that hiccup necessarily.
But we do care about the fact that it wipes, the debug
Every time and so it would be nice to have something that just doesn't
incremental rolling buffer.
So that we don't have to, so it doesn't have to ever do that wipe,
right?
That just be better.
Are the two different tariffs intended to have identical hierarchies,
or as the intention that you drill down into different things without
all the tariffs being affected.
So I think what we want to do is make it so that you
Can expand ones differently and also you can add ones like it'd be
nice to make it.
So, you could just, when you're doing a tear-off, you can have ones
that like ad.
So, you know, if I have this, I can then go ahead and like, add just
one thing to it or, or maybe like, you know, a better example would be
like if I have just that and now I want to add debug camera to it.
You know, I take the camera, I want to be able to make
So that it comes in here and could be dropped into that group.
So I can make my own groups right, which would be really pretty easy
to do and so that's just one.
One thing I would like
I notice you use the internal keyword.
I haven't seen it before.
What is this purpose?
It's just pound to find to static.
The geek pirate.
I apologize since I came in late, but of course, see what was the
tolerance and pixels you use for dragging out a subsection.
We did not do that.
Ours right now, just tell it, you just use the right Mouse button to
do it.
You mentioned that for link this at work?
Used men approaching.
What do you mean?
I mean we have a thing that generates stuff, super structural stuff.
So like things like this, it just makes for you.
Outcasted bird.
I miss tiny percent of the Stream, So I missed a ton.
I just want to ask what are some tips for people who want to get into
designing games?
Do's, and don'ts, and simple things that are worthwhile.
My only real tip is to try a different stream because this is a
programming stream, there is no design here.
Does anyone know if there is plans in the future to add other
platforms work to this project?
Yes.
We will be supporting many platforms with this project.
Have you written anything for the PS1?
No, I have not.
Blah 238.
Have you ever played any of the space Quest games?
Yes, I have music for the space, for the video of the hammer.
He recite reminds me of it a lot.
I can't say, I remember the music to space Quest well enough off to
go.
Listen to it sometime.
I don't really remember what it sounds like.
Martin Cohen.
Do you plan.
Do you plan on doing something with the character spacing in the text
renderer?
No, I do not split a do what?
Of something.
Do you mean angry?
Crow is Sentinel a design pattern that will help with making the
tortoises of the UI independent?
Or is that terminology that you've gained in years of tool
development?
Not understand what you mean by tearing the interface that seems
really useful for isolating a series of hierarchies.
Sentinel is just a word that's used to describe the fact that when you
you when you make a doubly linked list, you often use an element of
the list.
As the head and tail pointer.
We've talked about this on hand meteor before, there's actually an
episode where I draw it out and show how the link we're links.
Work long, will you not a huge deal with the labels?
No longer show of, clicking on them will expand or minimize them.
Also to glances not clear whether the category.
What is a ver?
Yes.
I mean like I said we haven't done any rendering stuff so this is just
a complete you know.
Which games console had the worst SDK.
That's always Nintendo.
Always, if I remember correctly, I'm pretty sure Nintendo.
Always delivers the worst SDK every time and has never has never been
beat, but I could be wrong about that.
That's just my recollection.
All right.
Looks like we're good.
Let's go ahead and wrap it up.
Wrap it up.
Here we go.
All right, thank you, everyone for joining me for this episode of
handmade here.
It's my pleasure coding with you.
As always, our debugging system is coming along quite nicely next
week.
What I'd like to do is start to sort of solidify some of those debug
interface elements, maybe draw them a little bit better.
In a bunch of cases and start to figure out exactly how to interface
with our profile code since we don't really have a handle on that
right now it's do still can't use it very effectively so I'd like to
spend some time just working out how we're going to actually have a
good interface so that we can see our profiler at a glance and stuff
like that.
But like I said we're getting there.
We've got some good features in there and I think we'll be able to,
you know, over the next few days sort of solidify, the debug UI stuff
into something.
That's pretty usable.
We do have one more major feature to add.
Add besides the cleanup, which is that?
I'd like to add some diagramming support.
That's not too difficult really to do, but there are some subtleties
to it.
So that's the one thing that we don't have in there right now.
So that's a feature addition, not just to clean up situation but other
than that like I said, mostly at this point.
Now we're at the point where we need to just start focusing on
finishing up, everything and cleaning it up.
Polishing it up so that it's nice and usable and get rid of some of
the roughness and the ugliness there.
All right, so that's it for today.
If you would like to follow along with handmade hero, especially since
there's a nice, big old weekend coming up here and you want to play
around the source code.
You can always figure to the game on handmade here at dot org comes
with source code so you can play around with it.
You can do that right here.
But this little pre-order button, we also have a patreon page.
If you want Sports video series, you can subscribe.
There, we have a tweet, bought the treat the schedule at you.
If you want to catch serious live, we have a forum site.
You can go to ask questions or check out past episodes.
If you're interested in something specific that you've seen that I
said hey we did it that on a previous, handmade hero.
That's the thing that place you want to go for that.
We also have a conference coming up if you go to handmade con dot org
and made con dot-org, you can see the first post about it.
We just announced it.
We have not announced the speaker list yet.
We will be announcing the speaker list yet in the next couple of weeks
and it is a pretty awesome speaker list.
I will say it is probably my favorite speaker list of all time so far.
And I still have one more slot to go.
So that's going to be pretty awesome.
And yeah, if you
To get tickets to that.
That is the place to do it.
That is it for today.
If if you would like to see some more handmade here, I'll be back here
on Monday.
Don't forget to check the tweetbot for the schedule.
You'll probably be 5 p.m.
but you never know.
I post schedule on the weekend for the rest of the week.
So the Tweet box, the place to check it out until then have a good
weekend programming and I will see you guys on the internet.
Take these everyone