Start and then we'll go ahead and close that.
Alright, everyone, hello and welcome back to handmade hero we have
been on break for a week, but it is now time to get back to coding.
A complete game from scratch live here on Twitch.
And we stopped before break at a point, that was kind of someone
interesting.
Actually, we were starting to do the work that we need to do to make
sure that we handled three-dimensional stuff correctly in our engine
all the time.
So we're a 2-D game.
Meaning we're supposed to be
a game that's, you know, similar to, you know, Binding of Isaac or
Legend of Zelda, these sorts of games where you kind of walk around
and it's very much supposed to be a 2d experience or something.
I guess like Don't Starve but we actually are trying to allow sort of
full 3d stuff in the world in so much as we care to have it.
So we want to make sure that there's nothing inherent in the way that
we've made the engine work that would, you know, cause sort of Jank
Enos to happen when you want to actually do stuff like
Multiple levels on top of each other or things like that.
And we'd also like to be able to do stuff like have multi-level rooms
where you can see perhaps the room below where you're standing in the
case, where there is, you know, a whole sort of, in the, in the floor
down to where that is, that sort of stuff.
So we want to make sure all that stuff is handled cleanly and not
really in a hacky way.
A lot of times there is kind of a key ways to do it where there's, you
know, exactly two levels that there can be your something like this
and you know, or it's kind of just a hack in the way that the graphics
are drawn, but it's not.
Really handling, it 3D.
We're trying to do it a little bit more robust than that, so we can do
more interesting stuff if we so choose.
Anyway, that's where we're going on right now.
So I'm going to go ahead and get back into it because I think we're
going to need some time today to just kind of get warmed up again.
It's been a full week since we last programmed been more actually
because it's been, it's been two weekends in between.
So it's been more like, you know, 9 days or something since we
program.
So, what I'd like to do is jump right back into it again, if you
already pre-ordered the game,
Handmade here a.org.
You can download the source code.
So if you want to follow along with today's stream, today's stream is
stream 76.
At least, I think I set that correctly.
Let's double-check and make sure that I haven't lost count.
Yes, 75 was the last one.
So what you want to do is you want to unpack day 75s source code from
the source code ZIP file that comes with the, with the pre-order.
You want to unzip the day 75 so that you'll be at the right place
today if you're trying to follow, along with me at home because I
We'll be starting with day, 75 source code for this episode.
All right, we can kind of put Mischief down into the minimize that
into the background for a second here.
And I've restarted this computer since then, so I hopefully everything
is still working properly.
I guess I don't know that it is, I guess let's let's just open up our
programs and actually make sure that nothing has gone terribly wrong
since we have left things.
You never know.
You restart windows and anything can happen.
It doesn't gentleman.
You really don't know what you're going to get.
When you restart a Windows machine, really?
Anything is possible.
So it looks like things are roughly the same as when we left them.
That's a good sign and our stairwell looks like it's working as well.
So that's good.
So it looks like nothing.
Nothing particularly bad happened, we're still able to run.
Okay, everything looks good.
And so if I remember correctly, what we wanted to do, what we had been
planning.
Nothing to do with the end of this was, first of all, we wanted to
maybe do a little bit of cleanup on how we were doing our Collision
detection for the stairwell, just kind of clean up some stuff.
We had only just finished getting it working.
Kind of the way that we had wanted it to work.
And the other thing that we wanted to do is get our
Our Collision detection properly working with Heights of things.
So that if entities are brought into the simulation set like in this
case, we've got sort of to play Fields going here, we got like a lower
one and a higher one.
You can kind of see these two rings of trees.
That's sort of the downstairs and this is the upstairs one that we
kind of had put in there.
If you've got situations where you've got multiple entities in the
working set like this and some of them are below you right now we're
just doing that close your section in 2D and that's not going to work
because it means that we can't ever
Or get through, what should be an opening here because we're going to
collide with the trees on the bottom level.
As if they were trees, that we would have to worry about on the top
level.
And so, we need to make sure that we're actually taking into account
where things are in three dimensions when we process collisions with
them.
So, that's something that currently we do for inclusion.
Testing, for example, when you're working with the stairwell, we are
actually testing where you are in three dimensions there.
But when we're testing against,
A movement like to see whether you can pass through something to see.
If you've collided something collided with something in that movement
step, we're not actually using the height of things that all there to
see what whether or not you should Collide.
So that's, you know, another thing we got to do.
Finally, the big feature that we need to work on and attacked in there
in a minute.
Sorry at the moment and that will have to sort of do possibly at the
end of this stream and probably tomorrow will be most of what we do is
we need to start coming up with a definition for.
What it means to have a particular ground height.
Right now, we're sort of just doing a really cheesy thing where we
just assume that the ground height is wherever the camera is.
So when the camera moves up and down, we set the ground height to be
wherever it's you know, sort of camera Center Point is and that's not
really going to necessarily work.
We you know, I suppose we could be could decide to do something like
that as the permanent solution but it seems to me like, you know, kind
of a little janky and it would also fight
Fight our ability to move the camera independently of where the ground
is.
It also makes it harder for us to Define things that say where there
isn't isn't round or stuff like this, I don't know.
There's there's just
I haven't thought it through too much and we need to go think it
through so we can kind of Define exactly how all that stuff's going to
work so we can get a nice stable way of understanding where the ground
is.
So right now, that's totally hacked, if I remember correctly.
So that's what we've got.
And that's pretty much.
That's pretty much.
We've got our work cut out for us there to get all that stuff going.
So let's go ahead and start working on that.
The first thing I'm going to tackle because it's the easiest one to
do.
It's very straightforward is just to get our Collision detection
working so that things are only colliding with you if they're in the
same.
Of Z neighborhood as you are.
So if you know, some things above or below you, that it won't Collide.
So, what I'd like to do is I'd like to go ahead and go in here, to our
handmade to our handmaids Sim region.
And when we do our move entity call, right?
This is where that that was happening.
When we did our move entity called, we have this iteration Loop where
we would go through and we would try to move the entity and we would
do a check against other
Serenity's to see whether it's any of them were hit, right?
And since we haven't really done General Collision detection, yet we
only did it just for a little square things.
We still have this call is still called test wall.
And basically, all it does, is it just tests against a single
basically line segment that is, you know, on one of the axes like X or
Y, or something like that, right?
And if you'll notice Z is not taken into account there at all, right?
There's absolutely no.
Z included here whatsoever.
And now what we could do is go expand the test, well, function to
actually handle Z, but it's unclear.
Why, you know, that's not really probably a good idea because when we
do the final Collision detector, we're not going to use test wall and
the things are not going to be rectilinear and they're not going to be
access the line.
And so really there's no point in updating the test wall.
Call the test, well, calls, probably fine for our purposes.
What we'd rather do is just say at the outset maybe let's just say
we're going to look to see whether these
Entities overlap in Z.
And if they don't overlap in Z, we're not going to do any testing on
them.
So basically, we'll just in here, right?
When we're actually doing this, we'll just we'll just full-on.
Say when we look at the can Collide the first thing that we do after
we do the testing maybe we'll still leave that Mankowski, diameter and
the min max Corner thing in there but right after we do that we will
do some check to see whether the entities
overlapped in Z.
And if they don't overlap in Z, then we simply aren't going to test
them at all.
Now, we've already constructed stuff that will help us test whether
things are in Z.
We've got this Mankowski diameter here and the McCaskey diameter is
the size of the entities added together.
So basically we've got the size of the entity in Z.
We've got both of those sort of concatenated together which means that
we also now we then use that to compute the Min and Max Corner which
is basically
The value of.
Excuse me.
If you assumed that the entity itself that we're testing against the
colliding entity, if you will, you know what I'm saying, too many
things here?
I should probably just draw this out.
That's probably the easiest way to to explain, what's already going on
in the code, rather than me constantly trying to to say stuff there.
So let's go ahead and thank you windows for that.
Wonderful helpful.
There we go.
What I want to do is I'm going to, I'm going to, you know, go ahead
and find a place here where you can
Anything.
There we go.
So we'll say day 76.
And what I was trying to say before is we have two entities, right
before?
We had basically like, you know, the wall entity, or the entity we're
testing against, which doesn't this.
I have to be a wall but that's the most of the things that impede our
progress at the moment and we have the hero, right?
And each of these had a dimension.
So it had a measurement that said how wide or how high or anything it
was right and so if you imagine we have the heroes Dimension here.
Here and we had the walls Dimension here, so HD and WD.
Let's say then what we decided to do.
Because if you remember the discussion of how Mankowski algebra works
and stuff like that, what we want to do is just treat the hero as a
point, that moves in a long lines.
And in order to do that, we need to shrink the hero down to a point
and expand the things against, which he is colliding against by his
size, right?
So what we did is we said all right, let's see.
Spanned the wall by however big.
The hero actually is half on this side, half on that side, right?
Expand that out and treat the new size of the wall, to be the size of
the here, plus the wall, which effectively shrinks the hero down to a
point for testing, right?
And then we said, well, we'll do this relative to the wall, right?
And so the way that we did that was we said let's subtract that hero
location, right?
If this is the point that the heroes at, let's subtract that from
wherever the wall is and we'll just get a relative point.
So what that means is now if we wanted to do Z, if you imagine a side
view here, what we've already done is we've already constructed
something where we basically have the heroes point, right?
We've got that relative to here and then we've got a Min and a Max Z,
right?
We've got a maxi level and a minzy level that already.
Tell us sort of whether the PE the, if we took peasy, right?
It would just be this.
It would just be where we are on the z-axis.
We can just see whether that's in between,
That men are the mat and Max, right?
And that will tell us whether we can hit this entity or not, if we're
outside of those bounds, that there's no way we're going to overlap
with it.
So we want to just ignore it that point.
So really, all we have to do here, very straightforward, we can just
take that Rel, we can take that rail Z, and we can say if the relative
Z is greater than or equal to
Ever are many corners he is and the real Z is less than or equal to
whatever our Max Corners he is now and again this is a little iffy
here because we don't really have, you know I'm going to I'm going to
put it to do here when we finally do the focus rejection do we want an
open inclusion at the max Corner because you notice I'm doing less
than or equal.
To in both cases there may be you know, if you remember when we did
our rectangle code and maybe I'll even maybe I'll just do this because
it seems like it's little
Are consistent, but if you remember when we did it here we were saying
that the max typically is not included, so it may be a little more
collect correct here to just say that for now.
I don't know, we don't have a robust after so we don't know why we
might care.
And so I'm going to put that off till when we do the Collision Tech
detection, full pass.
Because at this point, I really just don't know if that makes sense.
I really just don't know what it is that we would want to do there.
We'll have to think about it.
All right, so if I do that and I
Do that test.
Now we should have again, I'm not totally sure, but I believe we
should pass through things that are not on our level and stop and ones
that aren't okay.
That looks like we're just passing through everything.
Which is not what we want to do at all.
It's always funny.
So I wonder why I got to see here what I'm doing.
Ugly here, also to break point there and we'll see, but I believe am I
doing anything obviously stupid before I test that if R LZ is greater
than equal to Min Corners e and r LZ know that looks looks basic
right.
So I'm going to step in there and see what's going on again.
Hmm, it's been a while since we program.
So to chances of me forgetting something about how our code is working
is pretty high.
But what you going to do?
All right, so let's go ahead and step in here.
We should what's going on.
There we go.
We should be able to do some some hoops.
Let's see here.
I guess we should be able to step in at any time and we should be able
to see these triggering.
Right?
So let's see.
What is our Min corner and our Max Corner that we're testing against
here?
Let's just find out what those are.
So let's see, men corner and Max Corner.
They should straddle 0, right?
And they should be roughly the size.
What is this entity that we're testing against it's a wall?
So it should basically straddle either side of zero and does which is
good and the Z's in here.
All right.
Well so it looks like probably the
Problem that we're facing is just that we didn't actually give any
height to our walls.
So this is probably just a data definition problem because we didn't
really add 3D to a lot of things.
So when we add a wall, what we're going to have to do is actually add
some depth to it.
So if we go
Here we could say.
All right I don't know how high a wall is you know what's?
Let's say that it's half the the tile depth in meters or something
like this.
Will have to think about that a little bit.
When we they'll probably be walls of differing Heights.
I'm guessing in the game when we're actually done with it because
they'll probably walls that are low enough for flying things to fly
over and walls that are tall enough to block flying things or, you
know, stuff of this nature and so for now we kind of got a you know
leave it
Leave it at that.
So anyway we got to add that there and then I suppose other things
should also have a size as well.
Probably the player should have a size, he currently does not appear
to have a size, which is also odd and the monstars don't have a size.
So, so most people don't have a size.
Not sure what to really do about that.
I guess we'll just give them some size for now, and I guess,
So we've got a y and x.
Yeah, I don't know.
This is a little bit odd.
1.4 f is probably what his height should be.
I wonder if we should go through and actually think about these a
little bit.
Maybe that's something that should be on our to-do list.
Feels like something that probably should be.
So maybe go through and Define how tall everything should be.
And, and then, you know, just have some opinion about this because at
the moment,
We really don't know how tall things should be and it's a little bit
wonky.
All right, and also for things that are flying at The Familiar, we
should probably do a little bit of work on that.
Make sure flying things can go over low walls and so that'll be
that'll be some good stuff to work out.
Alright so we'll have to restart here because of course we change the
definition and so we'd have to you know the in it code is where all
that stuff was set.
So let's see.
We should find that we stop now and we do, we do seem to stop
correctly, although it seems like, are we stopping.
Yeah.
Now we're stopping correctly on the bottom stuff, which means I should
not be able to go through the exit here because we're on the bottom
right now.
And now let's walk up to the top.
We can walk up to the top and we cannot walk through the top ring, but
we should be able to go through.
We can so that looks like that's working properly now.
So that's good.
And yeah, that seems about right and I still can't, I can't walk
through the familiar, which is good.
I can't walk through the monster.
That's also good.
I'm not sure what's happening with this but that looking good too.
So our Collision detection is working stably enough at the moment for
the 3D stuff.
Well, that's oddly jerky, I'm not sure why that's being odd like that.
Is that
Yeah.
One thing that I did notice, you'll have to forgive me for a second
here.
I meant to check this out, but I totally forgot to I meant to look to
see when we did create wind oex.
Okay, I was noticing.
I was programming some stuff earlier last week, actually, and I
noticed that if you pass WX layered to a window, your frame rate gets
really, really bad, at least in opengl.
I don't know if it
It happens with with dip section, like we're using here, so I just
want to make sure that we weren't still passing that.
It's just a quick thing that I had thought of.
And I wanted to remember that not to do if we were doing it, but we
are it's not something I knew about but it kind of makes sense I
guess, because if it's a layered window it's got to go through the
compositor.
First to do the layering stuff and maybe, you know, can't flip as
fast.
I don't know.
But anyway, all right, so that's you know that
Our Collision detection is good enough right now in NZ.
So we can kind of say that this is this is done for now.
And then we can also go ahead and say let's let's take a look at the
at the other two that we added here.
I think because that seems like that seems like something.
Maybe we should we should go through and think about a little bit.
And in fact, it kind of sets us up for doing the ground stuff as well
because in order to do the ground stuff properly, we should have an
Idea of how everything lines up in 3D and how things are stacked on
top of each other, how that concept kind of works where tile chunks
are in terms of how things are staggered and all sorts of stuff like
that.
We probably want to get a handle on that.
So, yeah.
So let's take a look and and see what all this stuff is hammers out
too.
So, if I remember correctly, we set up a thing in here that said how
big tiles were sort of height Wise.
It's, let's see, tile side and M and tile depth and M is sort of
thing.
And what we said is that the tile side in meters is essentially what
the the depth I guess I should say of a tile.
So if we imagine a tile as a thing, you know, sort of a unit that we
think about typically as being this sort of element of space we don't
actually require things to be tiled at all but was sort of something
we were had been thinking about in terms of a unit of space.
For example, if we were going to do walls that you stamp out we'd
probably do them in this proportion.
So if we did something like this what we're saying is that we've got a
certain tile side and M here, right?
Whatever that.
Is whatever the world is initialized to.
We're setting up the tile side in M such that the it's a cube, right?
We're saying that.
These are all exactly the same.
This this and this are all congruent, they're all the same length and
what's kind of weird about that is?
I don't think we actually care about height the same way that we do
about sort of the, the two or I guess we should say depth as we do
about the other two Dimensions, because if you think about it, when
we're looking at the world top down, we typically want fairly fine
gradations this way right into
Terms of entities, you know we know the entities are moving around, we
typically want pretty fine gradations there but in terms of height I
don't know that we really do typically will probably represent very
tall things, you know, just sort of standing in a particular cell and
we don't really need the ability to have lots of things stacked on top
of each other.
Very often, that's not the common case for a game like this.
It doesn't really happen hardly at all and really, I don't know, it
seems like we probably want to say that.
However, High, you know, a floor would be of a building.
That's really the size of the cell that we care about.
So you know, probably it's something that looks more like this you
know where you've got kind of something that's very sort of tall
compared to its footprint.
That's actually the cell and maybe that's you know a good three or
four times.
However big that that tile Dimension would be right.
So if that's
The tile Dimension there.
So, you know, that's kind of what I'm thinking.
If you look at how high a building normally would be a building floor,
might be like 10 feet high.
Let's say right.
You know how tall tall is a typical Building Story and let's see what
this is.
Cutting the height of a building.
No, we just want to know.
How tall is the story of though?
10 feet is a common estimate.
So, yeah, let's say 10 feet was a common estimate.
What is 10 feet and meters?
Well, it's 3.04 so close to three, so we could say that three meters
high would be a, probably a pretty good, you know.
A pretty good estimate for how big we might want our cells to be in
terms of how we Chunk Up the world, right?
And so, when we build this, I'm thinking that basically what we want
to do is for tile chunks, we want to kind of do the opposite of what
we did here in some sense, right?
For a tile chunk.
We're often only looking at one slice of the work.
Well,
You know, the thing I was about to say is probably wrong.
So I'm going to, I'm going to stop there for a second.
Let's think about this.
So we have one more thing to think about.
So if we're thinking about a typical element,
Something like this.
When we start to think about tile chunks, I think maybe what I was
going to say, doesn't really apply but let's let's talk it through for
a second.
So what a tile chunk is, is an aggregate basically, and we don't call
them townships anymore.
Guess we call the world chunks.
It's basically a region of space where stuff lives, right?
It's like, it's sort of a storage unit for stuff in the world for
entities in the world.
And so if we're thinking about how big that should be, what we were
saying before is, you know, maybe if this was what
Our common sort of construction element looked like, I think what we
were saying is, like, maybe 16 by 16 across, right?
Was the thing.
Yeah.
So whatever that unit is of construction that we tend to think in,
even though, again, we're not explicitly representing this anywhere.
It's just kind of a size guide at this point because we allow any of
these to be any shape and positioned anywhere.
So we don't have to it's not like a tile map where it's locked to it
if we're saying that we're going to be 16 across, right?
And 16 this way the question
How tall should this chunk be in terms of units, right?
So we're basically saying that this is, you know, something like this,
right?
This is if this was our sort of construction grid, right?
Wow, I did a bad job, this is not even Square.
The construction grid, I drew, but you get the idea our construction
grid basically says, we store in chunks of this size, in terms of
construction,
When elements and again, things can be placed wherever you want in
here.
But this was sort of, you know, if you think of a typical wall piece
that might be made by an artist, that should be about that big or
something, you know, blah blah blah.
We're thinking about it in terms of stuff that would go like this in
the world, right?
So the question is, if that's what we're doing for how we're storing
the world, 16 by 16, which seems pretty reasonable, but we haven't
really thought to thought too hard about it.
How high should it be?
Right?
And so if we're saying that, you know, there's there's three meters.
So this is a distance of three meters here, right?
If are saying that there's three meters per floor.
One question is for tile chunks, how many floors do we want to store?
And it seems to me like probably the answer.
Alright, so I'm going to go back to things.
We're doing is a thinking it through a little bit.
I'll I'll say probably what I was going to say is okay.
Anyway, but
How many floors do we want to include in chunk?
And I think that probably, we only really want to include one floor,
right?
Because typically speaking, there's not going to be a lot of
visibility.
Florida floor, like typically floors are going to be opaque and when
they're not opaque they'll probably only show through to one thing
below it or whatever, right?
And so, what I'm thinking is in general, we probably don't want to be
pulling in lots of entities that are not
Involved in the computation, we probably want to just pull in the
floor, that's active.
And then if you can see down to the floor below, it will pull that in
as well or something like that, right?
But in general we won't be pulling in lots of floors like that and if
it turns out that we don't ever allow this case like we don't actually
allow things that show through to the bottom then we could restrict it
just to the one floor.
But I think we probably do for visual interest will probably want to
do that once in a while.
And so for looking down,
Down what we'll have to do, is basically do a query where we say.
Alright, let's look at everything that's inside the current camera.
Bounds that we want to use.
And then we'll expand that by when we detect that we have entities,
that would allow us to see through to the ground, will sort of detect
that and, and add layers going downward.
So what kind of will drill down or something like that, right?
That's kind of the way that I'm thinking we'll probably want to do it
that way.
We've got some inclusion in there and we won't grab more layers than
we need.
And so, what I think is we probably want to just leave it to one layer
at a time in those.
Chunks.
So that we don't have a situation where we are constantly to me
constantly, pulling in all sorts of entities, that we really just
didn't need to simulate at a high frequency because they're not even
visible at all right?
So, that's what I think we should probably do for now.
Now, in order to do that, what I want to do is say okay, we'll leave
all the same tiles per chunk stuff the way we were doing it before.
And then instead of making this tile side,
And M will just pass in another thing here, which will be the tile
depth in meters tile depth in meters and you can see that I've already
sort of done it this way.
This is already sort of what, I guess for lack of better term.
What I was expecting when we first typed in this code, you'll notice
that I had already just set it to one tile.
Hi instead of setting it to 16 tiles High when we're doing it before.
But we're saying now is we're going to do higher than that because
really the tile side and M is a lot smaller than what we
The average Florida up to be, so we're going to set it to that and
then we'll store it in here as well.
And so then when we call initialize World in here, when we actually,
oops, initialize world, will pass that tile side and then we'll also
pass whatever we want the depth to be right, which is going to be 3.0
for now and that'll be that that distance.
Now when we go to grab a floor,
now we kind of have this thing where that we got two competing things
that sort of fight against each other a little bit and I'm not sure
how we want to handle it.
Again, if you take a look at the side view.
So let's do a side view here.
If you take a look at the side view of what happens when we have a
multi-story thing like this, right?
Let's let's go ahead and do that.
So let's say here's story zero of our building and one two and three
Right.
And, you know, we've got a stairwell that kind of comes up in here
something like this and and you know, maybe we've got holes in here
and in a wall or something, you know, whatever you know.
So what what we have to consider is previously what I saying is to
avoid numerical nastiness, where we kind of have things that are
standing on the floor, that might drop a little bit below the floor or
things like, you know, who knows?
I was worried about that and I was saying, well, we probably want to
make it so that the tiles are like straddling like this, that that
world chunks are straddling so that they capture everything that's
near the floor.
Boundary.
But the thing that's nasty about that is that would bring in right in
a tile chunk.
You would, you would easily potentially say that like things like this
that were overlapping.
This might go into this chunk.
Instead of going into this chunk, right?
Depending on where this was placed a floating thing, that was floating
up.
Here, should clearly be in, in actually, this tile jump down here
related to this floor.
But instead, it's going to be placed in this chunk and our gather
would find that
that because our gather is going to gather everything, you know, you
know, in a region that looks like that.
But what that means is, we're always Gathering to child Sho tile
chunks.
Even if we could only see one floor, right?
Even if this is all we could see here is my little, that's my little
eyeball.
It's pretty great, huh?
If this is all we could see is just this floor, you know.
We can't see any of the rest of this.
We're still pulling in all of these entities.
We might still be pulling in and he's up here and that's just not a
good idea.
So it does seem like maybe even though it's a, you know, kind of a
nice thing to do it this way.
It does seem that maybe we want to do is do a nice inclusion thing
where we actually do and this would this would be our Max thing would
come into play here, where we actually do something where we say.
Okay, let's actually
We make it so that a tile chunk actually just encompasses the floor
itself and it doesn't extend below or above the floor boundary.
Now maybe we can stagger it a little bit, you know.
Maybe we can say that it's like a little bit like this.
So it, you know, it has a little bit of give to it.
So things are staggered a tiny bit but on the whole, you know, maybe
let's actually keep it fairly well aligned in that sense.
And so if we want to do that, I
Yes let's see here when we actually do are economically as coordinates
here I'm not sure exactly what we're doing already in terms of how we
re canonicalize them, let's take a look.
Actually, guess it's not really cannot size.
It's chunk position from tile position where were actually placing
these guys and so offsets, let's see what we're doing.
We're saying the world tells us
M, times the ABS tile in any direction.
So this is kind of a little bit wrong now because again tile side and
M is not how actually, how deep things are going to be and so we
really don't actually want that to be the case for these guys.
What we actually want to do here is is take just the the X and Y and
multiply it by it.
But you know what I could do, we could just say this is the you know,
tile size dimension or something like
This where we go ahead and say, OK, it's a tile sided M and then it's
the tile depth in meters.
And then, this is just a hadamard product, right?
Hadamard product of our tile Dimension, X.
That ABS tile XYZ.
That'll give us what we actually wanted for the position, right?
And that should work, good.
But now we got to say.
All right, so how are these things being sort of placed?
And it may
If it were already placing them in the way that I just said that we
should, it looks to me like, nobody here is doing an offset.
Which means,
Correct me if I'm wrong but that, that would seem to suggest that you
that we were actually already doing exactly what I just said, right?
In other words, we don't have to do any work, that was just what was
happening already.
And it's only if we wanted to do the staggered version that we would
have had to, actually do something about it because if we set the ABS
tiles E20, then obviously we would end up with zero.
If you set it to 1, we would end up with it being one more over.
It's over.
Really, if anything, I would say that all we really have to do here is
we want to do an offset for we'd want to do an offset for the X&Y.
We'd probably want the X and Y to be half a tile over.
So I'm trying to think of what the best thing to do is I think
probably what we'd want to do here is actually start drawing in a
little bit, how these things are layered.
This would be a good thing to have debug info for
Or and so maybe what I'll do is I'll postpone this until when we
actually have the debug code.
We might say something like draw tile chunks so we can verify that
things are aligned in the chunks.
We want them to be in ETC because that'll be a really that if we had
some debug rendering stuff, it'd be really easy to verify what I just
said, but
We don't it's a little bit harder, so I'm just going to go ahead and
double-check that that what I just said is working properly, it is
looks like that's fine.
Now you can see that that that that floor is much higher up than it
was before, which is because we changed the floor height to 3 meters,
which is exactly what
We would expect to happen and let's see here.
When we go upstairs, we also go up at a much faster rate, because
we've got to go all the way up to that top part there.
So, there we go, and that all works good.
So that seems pretty consistent and reasonable, so that's fine.
Okay, so let's leave that at that.
So now we have to do is start to say, all right, how, how tall should
everything be right?
How big should everything be?
And let's start to take a look at that.
So let's go into handmade World dot CPP here, I'm sorry, handmade dot
CPP, where we add our entity sizes, and let's just think about this a
little bit if we're going to add an NZ, how big should be?
Well, a wall.
Should probably be the tile depth in meters, right?
It should be the full height of the floor is what I would think.
And since we don't do since we don't do inclusion on the max, I feel
like, even though it goes all the way up to the top, we wouldn't even
need to leave an Epsilon, it would just work.
Now, I'm not sure about that.
Let's see.
So here, I'm going to walk around to test that Collision detection
there that all works fine.
Go to the top, Clint
Section works there, and it works here.
Yeah.
So so we can actually do it at the full height and that's fine.
So that's all good, no worries there.
So that's, that's nice.
So let's take a look at what things should be other Heights.
Let's say that we've got the stairwell
That well we already did that correctly because we said that that's
going to be the depth in meters.
Which is that height.
Now you know what I'm thinking though?
If this were only the depth in meters
We shouldn't be colliding.
So did we not use that as the inclusion rule?
I'm guessing we didn't use that as the inclusion rule.
I don't know if you see what I'm seeing there, but if the stairwells
only that big, then why are we able to walk down it?
Maybe we can't walk down it.
Let's find out.
Let's take a look here.
So, when we do inclusion, when we were doing our inclusion testing,
which is this stuff here?
When we did rectangles intersect, what exactly does that called do,
right?
Let's take a look and make
Math.h.
Let's take a look at rectangles intersect.
So, yeah, so you can see what's happening here, right?
Basically, rectangles intersect, which is our call for doing
intersection testing.
Here doesn't obey that Max rule, which is kind of janky, right?
That's not probably what we wanted it to do.
that that's just not like all of our testing is basically predicated
on the fact that, you know, if I've got a rectangle and in, let's say,
oops,
My men corner here is my Max corner, right?
All of it was predicated on the fact that that very last row or
column, that very last infinitely thin Edge, is not included in the
rectangle and the reason that we're going with a rule like that is so
that you can stack two rectangles perfectly together, right?
Like let's say I got a second rectangle here.
Like so and you know definitively what the people at this coordinate
are on you know that they're on this guy, right?
Not this guy.
If the max were included then there'd be no way to perfectly stack.
Two rectangles next to each other without trying to figure out what
the minimum floating-point Epsilon value.
Was at that scale that you could use to put you one floating Point
Unit over.
From the other guy which would be a huge pain and definitely not
something we want to do.
But for our rectangle intersection testing, we're not doing that,
right?
Our rectangle intersection testing says that you have to be less than
in order to be considered intersecting.
I'm sorry to in order to be considered not intersecting.
Which means that anything that was on and if the two rectangles a but
in any way then they are are considered, you know, they're they're
considered intersecting.
Which I don't think we want to do.
So even though that happens to help us in this particular case because
it means that when I woke up, this thing I can walk down it again
because I happen to be exactly on it both at the bottom level.
And the top level, what I think that we would rather do is fix that in
by having stairwells hit regions, extend above the floor a bit, which
I think we want to do anyway, right?
I think that's something that we would want to do.
Anyway, but I don't know.
So anyway, we could take a look at that and that's something that we
should play around with a little bit.
Just so we can kind of see what's going on there.
Now that that said I don't actually know that's what saving us.
It could be that I'm not quite thinking about it because, you know,
like what I'm also noticing is that if I walk into this guy, it stops
me and I feel like it shouldn't actually stop me because I feel like
our Collision that should not actually have been the case.
Let me
We think about that a little bit, but if you if you know what I mean,
right?
It should be that if you try to walk into it, the thing that would
have stopped it.
You was this test walk.
All right, because we're not stopping you down here in the overlap
testing.
So it seems to me like we're actually still intersecting
The stairwell even so, so that's actually not the thing that's
stopping us, but it doesn't change the fact that it's wrong.
And so first, I want to fix that and then we'll take a
And see what to do with the, with the other part of it.
So what we're doing here is we're basically doing an inversion test.
So what we're doing is we're saying, let's test first to see whether
they're not intersecting and then we'll just return the opposite of
that, right?
So to test, whether two things are not intersecting, what we want to
do here is we're saying okay, if the Min of this thing, right is less
than the maximum of the other one.
So let me, let me draw out what this is actually doing.
We talked about this before.
In fact, I don't know.
Can I actually find the drawing?
Probably not.
That's one thing we don't really have is how to search our drawings
effectively because like, what do you know, what do you do?
How can you see what, where we may have drawn?
That who has any idea?
Well, does anyone see it side?
I don't really see it.
On here.
Well, maybe overlap test.
At least one play.
Here we go.
This was the drawing, right.
So basically what we were saying before is, you know, we have a min
max and we have be min max.
And so what we're doing is we're checking for things like, okay, if
the minimum of B is greater than the maximum of a, then we know that
they can't be overlapping, right?
Because there's space in between,
Where this one ends and where this one begins.
So, what we want to say is, let's suppose the maximum minimum were
exactly equivalent, right?
So B's minimum was right on the maximum, right?
In that case, we would not consider them intersecting.
So what we actually want to do is we want to change these tests here,
for example.
So when we do Min vs.
Max, like the one I just said so if bees Min is
Greater than a is Max.
What you want to do is set that actually to be if it's greater than or
equal to, right?
Because if it's greater than or equal to we want to consider them not
intersecting because that Max is not included, right?
And so that's true of all of those dimensions.
And so now, the question is, what about the other side of that?
What about where we're testing the max against the Min.
And so what we're saying here in this case is we're looking for if
bees Max
was over here, right?
And so what about the case, where they're exactly coincident.
Again, I get we don't want that to be the case.
We don't want to include that maximum overlap.
So I believe what we want to do here is again, say the same thing.
We want to say that these max if it's less than or equal to a is men,
right?
That it's not going to trigger the intersection.
So that seems to me to be more in keeping with the
All that we set up and avoid this from getting into a situation where
we have different tests, returning different things.
Now, we still are working properly in terms of going up and down which
again, I think is a little odd.
So I'm just wondering what I'm forgetting because in theory.
Now, if we were right on the top, when we go here, we shouldn't
actually you know we shouldn't be actually going through like that
that that's that's not that's not correct.
So my question is what's
Actually happening there and I don't know.
So let's try and figure out what is actually happening there.
So, first off, let's make sure we know how big this thing actually is.
So if I go in here and I take a look at the stairwell, where are we
placing it, right?
So here, so, here is the first thing that I guess is affecting it,
right?
Is we're actually placing these at an offset in the world, right?
And oh well, you know what?
That, that explains it right there.
These placements are placing us.
So basically what our dimensions are interpreted as being around where
we are, right?
So basically when we, when we say what the dimension is, I guess I got
a zoom back to where we were day.
No, no.
Let's see here.
J76.
Where is des 76?
There it is.
This is such a funny drawing at this point.
All right.
So here's day.
76 again.
There we go.
Am I the right size?
It's heart.
That's the other thing that I don't know how to get this to do is to
to zoom to a known sighs.
I really wish Mischief could just do that.
I don't know, maybe it can and I don't know how to do it but yeah it
would be nice.
So does this look about right?
I think that looks about right.
That's how big things were.
So let's just say that that's how big they were and keep going.
So I guess what's happening here is just that are entities are
actually this size right are entities.
I'm snack, size are actually placed like so if this is the ground,
right?
Then essentially our entities are doing that and so that explains why
they can go and they're considered intersecting.
These stairwells that are even at the stairwell is only set up to be
that way.
So we want to actually do is Place entities such that they're, you
know, a base and their Dimension kind of goes up from the base like
that.
so, I wonder
I'm just thinking how we want to do this.
I wonder if that implies that our rule for where entities are should
actually be that the position, you know, you go out from the position
but you go up in z.
I don't know.
You know what I'm saying?
Like in terms of how you align the bounding box of the entity, I
wonder if we want to make it so that
Your alignment is, you know, from for the standpoint of a
three-dimensional drawing here.
Right.
I wonder if we want to make it so that essentially the, the point is
in the exact middle of the bottom face of your bounds.
And so the height is is measured that way.
Whereas the other dimensions are not the other dimensions are
measured, you know, as as being equally spread out from where you are,
mmm.
I mean, the other thing we could do is that everything is a minimum
corner.
So you're always specifying your minimum corner and then everything is
out from there.
Hmm.
I don't know.
I don't know how I feel about that.
So let's take a look at where it's actually used for starters.
That'll give us a little bit of an understanding of it, I suppose.
So if we were to, to go into SIM region and take a look at basically,
the places where I actually do something with it.
Well, so here's an example right here.
And then we've got another example.
Let's see.
So we actually
so we do do a fair bit of stuff that wants to be symmetric like
entities overlapping rectangles and sizing them so it looks it really
looks like we're we want to just keep treating it that way.
So it seems like what we want to do is we want to do, do we want to do
that placement where we're going to place things so that they're
adjusted properly.
Yeah, I feel like it just the center.
Plus the dimension is just a better thing to do there.
Yeah, so I mean, you know, that's what it is, that's what it is.
So I guess what we want to do here is say alright, let's go ahead and
and just account for that.
Maybe what I'll do is make a call in addition to add low entity,
something that takes a dimension, I'm not sure.
Let's take a look here, Adler and of the Adler entity everything.
Has one.
So maybe I'll just add that to the call and it will automatically
maybe do that adjustment for you.
Let's say,
Yeah, yeah, so I guess what I'm going to do here and I guess we should
give the sword dimension in Z as well.
Maybe just a very small dimension in Z.
I guess what we should probably do here is say, alright, let's add a
new function and there's going to be a function here.
That basically does the same thing as ADD low entity, but it's going
to be a, let's say a ground identity, right?
And a ground identity is going to have, you know, a dimension and a
position and you know, will will say that when you pass in, whatever
that position is, we're going to offset it.
We're going to go ahead and offset that.
Mission by whatever the dimension is.
So when you pass that dim in, you won't have to set that anymore,
it'll kind of do that for you.
And so what this will do is it'll call AD low entity with the position
and the type that you specify and then it'll go ahead.
Well, and set the dimension for you as well, but it'll also do before
it does that, it will do that.
That mapping for you, we're essentially it, it offsets the way.
The Entity was.
So if I take a look at handmade World, aah, whoops, there should be
that offset call.
Where is that offset map into chunks space.
So this right, so if I do that map in a chunk space World position
offset p.
And so what we'll do is we'll say we're going to map into chunks pace.
The original P that we got and then we'll take the dimension, will say
that we're going to, we're going to offset it by half the dimension in
Z downward.
So, to sort of I'm sorry upward, right?
So that will move it up to account for that.
So that it will be based on the ground properly, but that it's sought
its actual placement in the world will leave.
Its bottom, the bottom of this bounding box on the ground.
All right, so we'll go ahead and return that.
And that looks good.
So we've got now some work to do here, where I basically say that
Dimension is going to be something like this.
And this so there is a wall and then I can say a drowned identity dim
and delete that
That right?
That makes sense.
None of the overloads course you would make me do this.
Thank you.
See.
Right, maybe it wasn't as bad as I thought.
Let me let me give it another chance.
Okay.
Now see was not being mean to me.
There.
Who is just me forgetting to select the Z coordinate.
All right, so and I guess I have to pass the world there to probably
right.
This guy seems so it knows how to do that mapping.
So that should allow us now to place things.
Let's double-check that that actually worked at all.
That should allow us to place things properly in Z and, and we'll see
if it actually did.
And of course, our guy is now lower than the walls, right?
So he's
Like down a bit in Z and so now that should stop happening once we
actually Place him properly as well.
So let's go ahead, we got ad wall, we've got our ads stare.
So if we want our Dimension again, let's go ahead and set that up.
So we've got there's the X.
We've got our y here.
Is that in there and our Z, so that in there and that
Will automatically do its thing.
So a drowned identity.
Oops.
See
There we go.
So now what we would do is we would just get rid of this so we don't
actually need that offset anymore because it should just offset
itself.
There we go.
And what else we got?
We got we got RS, word, RS.
Word isn't a problem because we're, it doesn't actually have a
position at the moment so we can leave that be for.
Now, our player, he should be grounded.
So let's take his dimension.
Here and actually set him up properly and he should be about 1.4
meters high, right?
That was what we said.
The height of the hero should be, I think no, that can't be right.
He's not 1.4 meters.
He's a little kid.
We did this before, but I forget what it was, how tall is, let's say a
velociraptor.
How did that?
How is that?
The most common, what is going on here?
All right, well, whatever, how tall is, I don't know, maybe he's,
let's say, I don't know how old he is.
Let's say seven year old.
63 cm, right?
So point 6, 3 meters, so that makes sense, right?
You know, I'm saying, point 6, 3 meters is how big our kids will be.
There we go, seems reasonable.
And that's just, that's all yes.
So, if I go ahead and move these out, we've got he's he's won by 0.5
by 0.6 3F.
Delete that and we'll add him as grounded.
And we will add his Dimension there.
And that looks about it up.
We're almost out of time.
So let me just finish this guy up for the monstar.
The monstar is 1.0 0.5 0.5 with a minute and I know why our monstar is
so much taller than our guy, but I guess that's just because monsters
or bigger and scarier, so we'll add ground identity there.
Dimension and again, Jim equals 0.5 0.8, whoops, no 11.0.
F 5, F 0 .5 F.
Well, that's good .x.
Well, good that we caught that accidentally, there's the familiar, and
we'll have to do some more work on the familiar later because we
actually want the familiar to float and we haven't done anything about
that yet.
So I've got an entity.
There we go.
So what's the
Here, no semicolon.
Nobody likes the missing semicolon.
So let's go ahead and run that see where we're at.
Let's see if we can actually stop our guy.
That looks a bit wrong to me.
It looks like we're still lower than the trees are which which isn't
my intention.
So I've got a little bit of bogus and it's happening in my code more.
Importantly, we're still getting that, so that's
A little bit odd as well.
So some things a little something, as a little odd.
Let's just take a couple more seconds to take a look at that.
Where is my ad grounded?
Any code?
There it is.
So let's see.
Let me just make sure I did this reasonably so map into chunks space,
we're taking the initial p, and then we're doing that mapping.
We're adding it at the offset P so that seems right or change saving
the dimension.
That works roughly correct.
Let me go ahead and step into that but otherwise, I guess we'll have
to leave it here tomorrow and we'll do bucket tomorrow.
Ground identity.
Let's see what it says here.
So,
Map into chunks space.
Oh, you know what though?
Now that I think about it though really are drawing code is slightly
wrong.
In fact, I should fix the drawing code first before I look at this our
drawing code uses, the Z placement to to determine where to draw the
guy, but it really should use the minimum of the Z bounds, right?
It shouldn't be doing this as the entities
Right.
Instead it should be using
It should actually be using that, that point offset by it should be
using that base point because we're drawing up from the base.
Point.
That's how we were actually doing all of the other rendering, right?
Look, when we draw the rectangles we're actually doing I assume we're
actually doing that I don't actually know if that's true.
How are we doing it?
Let's see.
Draw a rectangle.
Play Love Tapas named entity with height 1.0.
Let's see here.
Clear, left top, layer left top.
Where is put out?
Okay.
There it is.
So player left top, we're not using that code at all.
That code is just bogus gravity, ground point, and it easy.
so, when we do this computation,
When do we actually offset the point by entities e right there.
So what we're doing is we're saying that the center
is the offset.
Yeah, you know what?
This is going to take a little bit because this I think is just wrong.
I think our drawing code is just bogus to begin with.
So that is actually it's not a fair test to say that it would look
like I was in the wrong place because this code is just kind of bogus.
So we should probably do is fix this so that it's actually drawing it.
So that the Z is actually starting at the lowest point in going up
from there because that's actually how we're thinking about the
drawing, in terms of how far it should be offset.
So that that does seem
It does seem a little bit bogus, which is how we're doing it, but
either way, we've got some bug's to deal with.
So I'll leave that for tomorrow.
I'll put that on the top of the to-do list, so we already went through
and went, how tall things are.
So let's say, debug drawing of Z levels and inclusion of Z to make
sure that there are no bugs.
because there are some now,
All right, so let's go ahead and go to the Q&A.
If you could, please please fix your question with Q: so that I can
see it and try to keep it to things that we've done on today's stream
or on a previous stream if you want to ask off-topic questions or
things about what we're going to do in the future or any other thing
like that, please do it in the pre stream.
Come about 15 minutes before a scheduled stream start time and we do
off-topic questions then.
We didn't do any today because we wanted to give everyone the
opportunity to watch John's programming lecture so that's why there
wasn't much today.
But on days when Jonathan doing compiler demos we always do
pre-screening questions.
So that's the time to answer those
I'm sorry to ask those.
That kid you just created is around 2 ft tall.
Yeah, isn't that that same?
Does that not seem right?
That's right.
Is there anything wrong with with that?
Oh you think that basically that thing that we got was just bogus?
So people are saying that that's too short for a seven-year-old.
So better data is that growth chart boys?
Girls height weight at Hall's dot MD.
Wait.
So just just just curious.
What is the actual height for a seven-year-old?
In that case?
Has somebody looked it up?
So as for someone asks, I was wondering, why do you have two windows
open?
And not just one, the answer is because I find that it's most
effective to work in a manner where I can have two files open at once.
Typically so I can do things.
Like you know, if I'm working on some region dot CPP, I often want to
see some region to H at the same time, so I just have hot keys to
allow me to view those and then I break my files up, such that I can
see, like my data types.
All together that make sense of things that I want to look at two.
There.
And then so that I have my CPP files when I'm working on them I can
quickly see a bunch of the types that are involved in that CPP file.
Over four feet seems right for a seven-year-old okay.
Well
I wonder if we can find.
Here we go.
Let's see, male children.
7 height in inches is 48.
so,
Oops, 48 inches in meters.
1.2.
Oh, so we were actually pretty close before.
That's huh.
Alright, so let's go ahead and
Let's go ahead and update that ad.
Player, that's what it's called.
So he is about that tall.
Let's say.
Let's see.
Any other questions about stuff that we were doing?
Doesn't look like it looks like mostly non programming related
questions.
As for the apps that we are using for the dev environment.
Yes, it is good.
New Emax is the editor Dev studio is the debugger and the, we use this
Mischief app for drawing, but that's not really a development tool.
It's just what we use for illustrating things on the string.
If you wanted to, you could get by with just if Studio because it's
got editing built in as well.
I don't like it's editor very much so I don't use
But there's nothing wrong with that.
Like people people do it.
People definitely follow handmade here on using just the visual studio
editor.
I think there are some trickiness and doing some of the live
co-editing stuff that we do getting that to work properly with its
build is a little janky sometimes but you know they've pretty sure
people have worked it out by now.
How to do that properly and visual studio so you don't really need the
Emax part of it.
That's just the editor that I prefer but you could, you could do it
just with, basically everything that we're doing, you could do just
with Visual Studio which is
You can use the Community Edition which Microsoft makes available for
free.
Let's see.
Any recommendations for tracking down Heap, corruption bugs.
Hmm.
so what I typically do,
for Heap, corruption bugs is
Let me see if I have any other questions that are, like, on topic to
stuff, we've been working on because it's a good question but it's not
really related to what we're doing at the moment.
Let's see.
Yes.
Oh, well, let me just answer this question because it's a good
question.
So typically, here's what I do to debug keep corruption errors.
So, you know, we've got this memory nothing.
Right.
And the way that the memory Arena thing works is I go ahead and I just
allocate out of a, you know, a memory block, right?
And so every time we do an allocation, we don't actually
Allocate.
Any memory really?
We just increment an integer.
So I mean our allocator, you know, it's still allocate, it's still an
allocation, right?
But our allocation is boiled down to just like plus equals the size.
That's that's the entire work of the allocation and that's intentional
because I want allocation to be completely free.
Like I don't want any time spent like program games should spend no
time allocating and deallocating memory.
If your game spends any time whatsoever allocating and deallocating
memory in my opinion, that is a poorer.
Architecture because there's no reason for it.
It's not necessary.
And so, all you're doing is wasting CPU time.
That could be better, spent Computing, something else or doing
something that would make the game better rather than allocating
ordeal nltk memory, which is not making the game better, it's just
bookkeeping.
So that's the way I tend to do it and that's intentional.
But what that means is, it's very, very difficult to track down.
Keep errors in this case because anytime you overwrite some of the
memory that you may have allocated here, right?
You will never know.
You'll just
Some other values that are, you know, somewhere else.
In that it we're being your something else and you'll get a bug.
But it's a hard to find bug.
So, typically what I do and we haven't had a chance.
We haven't had a reason to do this because we haven't had any
corruption bugs in the program so far.
Typically, what I do when we wanted to box, like that, is this class
this, the sort of shouldn't really say class this tool, this whatever
you want to call it.
I know I say class in my head sometimes I think of things as classes
and they're not what everyone else thinks those classes.
So I try to avoid using that term so that people won't think about
virtual functions like that.
Because that's not what I mean.
I kind of mean this utility, this thing that does stuff.
Right.
So basically this this combination this this initialized and push.
So these two functions here.
Well, I'll do is, I'll extend them to basically have two versions, one
version that I use for actually shipping the game, which looks pretty
much exactly like what you see here, modulo few things, it will
probably add later as well, but then the other version I have is a
debug version which wait does, is instead of actually doing the
allocation this nice clean way that I've set up here, it actually does
do an allocation, every time you do a push and what it does is it
calls through to the OS layer and ask for a block
lack of memory.
With a special debug allocation routine, and what that debug
allocation routine is is it does a virtual a lock or a mem map,
depending on which platform you're on, right?
But it does one of these and the way that it works is it asks for the
memory
If you imagine the allocation, right, let's say that this is the
virtual page size.
So let's say that this is a 4K page, right?
Because that's how big page boundaries are in in small in regular page
size operation.
They can go up to 64 K and 2 megabytes and other things like that.
But
Let's say that the page size was for okay for now.
So, normally what happens is when you do a virtual a lock right, you
allocate some memory and you start using it right from here, right?
From from the first byte offset of the page, and you just use however
much you're going to use.
And you know, there's these 4K Pages, they're mapped in your process
face and everything's fine and whatever.
But if what that means is that if I was to do a virtual Alec and ask
for the amount of memory that I actually wanted, let's say I wanted 6K
right.
I would get back this region here.
And it would map these two pages for me and I could write stuff into
here and it would just right in here, right?
And if I wrote over this, nothing would happen.
Until I actually wrote off to hear like I'd have to right past the end
of the page here, right?
If I did a virtual Alec and maybe this would actually be mapped for
all I know.
So it might be that nothing would even happen.
Then I just get silent bugs because you know, this thing's over
writing its bounds.
If I were to overwrite this way, I'd be more likely to fault but again
even that could be mapped.
But usually people very rarely underflow buffers, usually you overflow
buffers, that's just tends to be the way things go.
So what I do is I virtual Alec basically, a bigger range that I need.
What I do is I allocate an additional page, right?
So that basically I've got, you know, something that looks, you know,
that's too big to even draw.
So let's do this this way.
Let's draw the pages a little bit smaller.
We go so 4K, 4K.
A 4K.
What I'll do is I'll allocate it such that I place allocate one extra
page that I need.
So 6K needs 8K worth, you know, two pages to fit, I'll allocate
actually three pages.
So one more than the amount I need and then I'll essentially align the
6K the other way so that the 6K boundary starts here and ends here,
right, it ends right on the page boundary.
What I then do is I take this extra page that I've allocated and I'm M
protect it.
I do virtual protect
On that page and I set it to not be allowed to be accessed, read or
write.
What that allows me to do is even if anybody ever in the code ever
over rights by even one bite the end of the buffer, you get an
immediate page fault.
And that is a really easy way to track down memory errors.
What you can do is you could run your program twice in two different
modes to you can do it this way and then you can do the same thing,
but do it in reverse?
Line up the page.
So that um, men protect the first page.
And you align it like that.
So now that one bite over run in the other direction will fault.
And if you run the program once
This allocation scheme and once with this allocation scheme, you will
have guarantee that you will have hard faulted on any type of overrun
by 1 B, in any direction.
Now, this gets a little more complicated if you have alignment issues.
So if you are aligning, your your allocations to say 16 B boundaries,
which is common in Cindy operation.
If you're doing that, then you can't ever really do anything.
About the fact that you're going to be always 16 B aligned, which
means that someone could overwrite a boundary by up to 15 B if the
allocation wasn't actually allocating the full amount.
But since it's unusual to allocate less than a 16 byte granularity for
a 16 byte aligned thing.
Usually this isn't a problem but that's typically what I do and then I
run the program once in this way and once in that way and that should
get you just about
I hope that makes some sense.
Let's see.
If you're not allocating memory as the game goes, are you allocating a
bunch of the start?
How does that work?
Yes, we allocate all the memory at the outset.
At the moment, we allocate a lot more than we probably actually need
because we're just in development right now.
But later, we'll, we'll probably have a little bit more to say about
exactly how much we should do.
But if you want more information about that, obviously, you can you
can come here to the video archive and if you if you look at the video
archive, we've got
Every single day of coatings on here, you can go look up exactly what
that was.
So I believe, let's take a look here.
Platform-independent game memory is probably the one to look at Star
Trek but I'm not entirely sure.
I think that's probably it.
So I would probably take a look at that and just, you know,
watch the video to tell you.
What are the Linux equivalencies functions?
I think M mapped and M protect our the Linux equivalents to the
functions.
So let's see.
Do we have any topic questions still?
No.
So I guess I'll try to do the closest.
I'll try to sort questions by the closest to on topic.
That seem fair.
Let's see.
How far along are we in?
Developing the game.
We are so
Only do an hour a night and so the number of days is the number of
hours roughly.
So we're 76 hours in which is like, we're almost UND 880.
That'll mean we're at our second week of programming.
If it was a work week, right, 40 hours a week of programming is the
typical amount.
I kind of figure.
So we're about two weeks in and so we don't really have an engine yet,
we're working towards the engine.
So basically we are, you know, we're at the point where we're, we're
getting pretty close to having all the stuff specced out that we
actually want in our engine.
We've got a little to-do list here that
It's not that we want to still sort of figure out mostly.
This is the, the kind of this.
This first part here is mostly the tricky part, and I guess a little
bit down here, which is this stuff.
But yeah.
So we've got, you know, I'd say we've got at least two full weeks of
programming more to do to get through a lot of these things and kind
of have a better sense of it.
And then once we're done with that, we'll start on game production
proper and that's like writing the real renderer and then
Kind of like working through all the systems and making sure they're
all like full you know, full quality and stuff like that.
But yeah, so we're not very far into it.
I would say I mean two weeks is not very long to be programming on a
game especially when you're programming from scratch.
So, you know, I would expect, you know, you wouldn't it's pretty
unlikely to make any kind of game from scratch in in that kind of
time.
If you're, if you're, you know, not using an engine or something like
that.
Someone suggesting Emin map is another Linux equivalent call.
Is this insane?
Is this in C++?
Yes.
Well it's it's sort of C++.
We do use a little bit of C++ things.
So if you look here, you can see in our math Library.
This stuff is C++, right?
Operator overloading.
We also use some function overloading and that's mostly it.
We also 0, and we use the fact that we don't have to use, type deaths
to Define struck names and Union names the like that but that's mostly
it.
So really, we're sort of programming in c but technically it is C,
plus plus
Cuz we use a few C plus plus features here.
And there that we, or I should say that I think are useful.
I stay away from most of the other seat post.
Features that I don't think are so useful.
Does C++ compiler?
Generate hidden code like Constructors copy Constructors and Cetera in
the way that you structuring the game.
So I'm not really sure how to answer that question.
I mean, every compiler,
Like even a straight C generates hidden code, right?
Like if you were to assign a struct to another struck that does
essentially like a mem copyright and you didn't write that code and so
you're not controlling how that stuff got copied.
And similarly like you know in terms of
Various ways that things could be happening.
I mean there's just their stuff that happens.
That's that's hidden code.
In that sense, like C is not one-to-one readable in a way that like
directly implies what the Assembly Language is doing modulo, you know,
assignment of registers or something.
So in some sense I would say that hidden code is getting his getting
done.
Yes.
But in another sense I would say most of the time we're staying away
from any
Like weird hidden code generation.
We don't use templates.
We don't use Constructors and destructors.
We don't use stuff.
That's going to proliferate a lot of code that we don't explicitly,
right?
We do use operator overloading so that's some hidden code.
And that's four Vector, use, and so pretty much.
If that's what you mean by hidden code, I would say, operator,
overloading is the primary place for met for our math for our Vector
operators.
That's the place that you would see the compiler generating code.
That's not obviously there when you look at it.
Do you use the STL at all in your code?
No, I do not.
I don't think the STL is very good and I wouldn't recommend using it.
It it's the things that are provided in the STL are very rudimentary
and simple.
They are not complicated pieces of code and they are done in the sdl
in a way that's very complicated cumbersome.
And I find problematic when used in real code bases.
And so, I would never recommend using the STL
If you need something like that, you should write it yourself.
I think it's, well worth the effort to make sure that you don't
rely on it because it's not, it's not well designed and it's not,
well, executed in general as a piece of software.
So, and in general, you want to try to avoid having your basic
operations, like data types like that being done in something that's,
you know,
kind of janky.
Okay, I think we met maybe are coming to the end.
Coming to the end here.
Let's see.
Yeah.
Looks good.
I'd say that's pretty much all for today, in terms of questions.
So I am going to
Yeah, I am going to go ahead and call it, don't see any more
questions.
So I'm going to go ahead and close things down here.
We've got we know what we're doing tomorrow, so that's good.
And yeah, so let's let's, let's go ahead and end for the night.
Thank you very much, everyone for joining me for another another
episode of handmade here.
It's been a pleasure coding with you, as always, if you would like to
get your
And copy of the source code.
You can always pre-order the game on handmade hero dot-org.
And it comes with the source code.
I upload every night after I'm done programming so that you can play
around with it at home if you want and use it as a thing that for, you
know, for Learning and stuff, you can kind of tweak things and that's
a good way to learn.
I find is to be able to play with stuff Break Stuff and and kind of
figure out how it's working in a more Hands-On way.
So if you want to do that, you can do that at home made here at
orbital period of button.
If you want support the video series, we also have a patreon page if
Go to the patreon page, you can subscribe there and that's a way to
support the video series and it's always very much appreciated.
We also have a tweetbot so you can follow the series.
We're here.
Every weeknight basically, sometimes we're in the mornings on Fridays,
for example, so we will move the times around.
So if you want to know the schedule, you can always click on the Tweet
pot or you can some you know if you are on Twitter you can follow the
tweetbot and that way you'll get the tweets delivered to you and it
tweets about twice a day.
Once in the morning to say, when the stream will be and once
An hour before the stream starts.
It also has a like a weekend thing.
It does, we're at tweets out the schedule for the whole week, so you
can always take a look at that way.
So that's kind of Handy to got a video archived on YouTube with all
the old videos.
And we also have a news and Forum site, which also has an annotated
version of the video archive, which is pretty awesome.
I highly recommend checking it out.
It's also got some great coding resources up there like ports to Linux
and Mac if you're trying to follow along on a platform, it's not
windows.
It's got a place we can ask questions.
It's just got
lots of good stuff.
So if you're trying to learn from the series, I really recommend
checking it out.
Some people in the community have done some really helpful things up
there and it's just a good place to go.
So again, thanks everyone for joining me tomorrow.
We'll be back here at 8:00 p.m.
Pacific Standard Time are normal slot.
We were 30 minutes late today, because we moved the stream up to give
John stream a chance to finish.
We always try to move the stream to accommodate the compiler demos of
John does, because I'm pretty excited about the language he's working
on and
I want everyone to watch it and and be excited.
Because I know I am.
So that's why we were 30 minutes.
You know, that's why our scheduled time was, 30 minutes, it was 8:30
tonight, but tomorrow will be back at 8 p.m.
and it should be 8 p.m.
for the rest of the week until Friday when it will be at.
It's 9:00 a.m.
slot as usual so, pretty much other than today, every day is a its
normal schedule for this week.
So I hope to see you back here.
Tomorrow night, have a wonderful Tuesday and yeah, enjoy coding till I
see you again.
Take it easy everyone.