Anyway, welcome to handmade hero everyone.
This is, of course, the show where we make an entire game from scratch
using nothing, but our bare hands.
No libraries, no engine.
And we are basically doing this because I really think there's
something valuable to everyone who's a serious game, programmer going
through the entire pipeline of a game from start to finish sometime,
just so they can see.
Every last little thing that goes on in a sort of a full stack of a
game and just understanding every last little thing that
And I think it's great for educational purposes.
I think it makes you more powerful when you do professional
programming.
I think it allows you to be the kind of guy who works on an engine
team.
It allows you to be someone who can overcome limitations of the stools
that they work with.
It's just it's very empowering to know how everything works and that
is exactly what we are doing.
We are taking it slow and investigating every last little aspect of
game programming as it comes up.
We are at the point where we have made our win32 prototyping layer.
And we are building our game on top of it.
Right.
Now.
What we are doing this week is we have sort of been sort of trying to
imagine roughly.
What are the sorts of things our game is going to have to do so that
we can start building our engine.
And one of the things that I said early on is in order to build a game
engine, you need a game in order to build a game.
You need a game engine, right?
It's kind of a, its kind of this sort of thing.
Because if you've never built a game before, you won't know what to
put in your game engine, you won't know how to
Sure, an architect it correctly so that it's not just a pain in the
butt to use and similarly.
If you don't have a game engine you can't really make a game because
the game engines, the thing that provides all the services.
It's the thing that puts Graphics up on the screen is the thing that
loads the art is the thing that plays the sounds and the music's and
everything.
So how do you make a game of it?
And so, basically, we're in a chicken and egg scenario if you will
when you're making everything from scratch.
And so, what you want to do is you want to use sort of what I call
exploration programming, right?
You want to kind of start to just
Just play around with making the game in the engine together.
You just want to kind of play around with test code so that you can
start to see what things should look like.
And then once you kind of get a sense of what a certain part looks
like, then you can sort of go.
Oh, let me go make some code here that will start to be the basis of
the engine in this part and so on.
And so that's what we're really doing.
Today.
We're kind of continuing on our exploration.
Just trying to get stuff on the screen.
Make stuff work.
We're not caring about code quality.
We're not talking about cleanliness or any other abstract Concepts
were just talking about, let's just write some code.
That does some gave me stuff and let's see what it looks like so that
we can start to pull the sort of the common pieces out of it and pull
the structure out of it that we're going to need in order to make a
game engine that will allow us to do nice fast game development and do
all the things that we want to do.
If we were to license an engine or do something like that.
We want to make the that component right there.
So this will start to educate us to make that design look really good.
So if you are following along at home and you have
Pre-ordered the source code on handmade hero.
Org with a little pre order button here.
You should have gotten an email, that email has a link that allows you
to download the zip file inside the zip file.
There is ipps of every day.
We are on day 30.
So you want to unzip day, 29, yesterday's work, because that is what
I'm starting with today.
And so if you unzip, they 29 into a directory and start working with
that, you will be exactly where I am right now.
And where am I right now?
Is a good question.
I am going to run the game so you can see what we
Were doing.
So what we were doing was we were playing with the tile map.
We were basically saying, okay, we've got this little tile map here.
You can see we be putting some walls, you put in some doors and we
have a little dude who moves around?
We have it.
So he cannot move through these various pieces, right?
And so again, and what we decided to do was just use rectangles for
everything because we didn't want to deal with bitmaps yet until we
saw how we wanted to use them.
So pretty straightforward stuff, nothing really particularly strange,
but we've got it all going.
And so what we were trying to do yesterday and what we want to finish
Up today is we'd like to be able to walk out of the tie of the tile
map and onto another tile map.
Right?
We want to be able to walk from one screen to another and have the map
update properly.
So that is what we are doing.
And if I remember correctly, we had gotten partway through it, but we
ran out of time on the stream to finish it up.
So let's go ahead and take a look at where we actually.
We're going to go ahead and move it over here.
Here.
Okay.
So what we had done is we had sort of, we wrote inside our game update
and render call, right?
We're basically just spamming all of our code straight on.
In here.
We actually just made some little arrays that represent the tile maps
that we wanted to Traverse.
We made an array, a two-by-two array of those tile maps and we
assigned various tile maps to them.
Of course, you notice we didn't, it's got some nice typos in there.
These are supposed to be actually assigned to each of these things
individually.
Really, I believe which wasn't.
Oh wait.
No, that never mind.
That's not a typo.
That's correct.
That was basically cloning this initial stuff here.
So basically what we had is we these were the, these were the
variables that we found.
We needed to compute where the guy was, and the tile map and to draw
the tile map.
So we pulled those out into Tom app structure.
Then we realized we had multiple tile Maps.
So we made a world structure.
We made a tile map count X, in the tilemap count.
Why with a pointer to the tile Maps, right?
We have it made its parts yet.
So actually dense, we're going to talk about that a little bit later,
but basically what happens
Is we assigned everything to our world?
We have our world pointer sort of worked out here, but we never
actually did anything with it.
We're still doing all of our work.
We just kind of grabbed tilemap.
In fact, right here.
You can kind of see if I can pile.
We grab tilemap 00, the the base tilemap.
It's in the first position of that array and we do all of our work
with it, right?
You can system.
We do tile map tile map tile map, tile map.
Tile map.
All that sort of stuff, right?
Nothing particularly interesting going on there.
So,
What I want to do here is the player with the height that actually
should be moved kind of up here.
And this should kind of be referencing off this thing because we have
some constant variables here.
Again.
Just taking it one step at a time.
There's a lot of stuff.
We're going to want to do to clean all of this up.
I mean, this is literally just spamming the code out here, but I'm
just making little baby steps to kind of put things into the right
place slowly and over time.
It will creat.
And again a lot of this is not I'm not even saying so a lot of this
stuff I wouldn't be doing because I just know the right answers to
some of this stuff.
So I could just sort of type it in, but if I didn't already know what
some of the right answers are, this is not like messy code.
I'm just doing for the stream.
This is actually how I recommend you do it.
I recommend you type in awful code first.
That's whatever the first thing you think of to get stuff up on the
screen is and then afterwards when you're satisfied, does the basic
operations that it needs to do only them go through and clean it up
because otherwise you're spending a lot of time thinking
Think about how to make the code clean, but you haven't actually
figured out which code you actually need to make clean yet.
And so you end up going through all of these Cascades of writing, some
clean code and spending a bunch of time, fussing with that, only to
realize that it doesn't do some of the operations, you actually need
to do.
And so I can't stress enough how I really do, not think it's a good
practice to write clean code when you are just exploring things,
right?
Messy code and then write the clean code only once so that you save
that effort of writing clean.
Code only to when it actually is going to pay off.
Because code like this that's just transient and just like that were
playing around with isn't going to stay around.
So any time you spent making it clean was full-on wasted.
You basically just took your if you believe time is money, you just
held up a bunch of Benjamin's.
If you will, as they say in the states as the kids today, say and then
you light them on fire and that's no good.
All right.
So what I'd like to do is start to get us working so that we start to
think about
Where we are in this in this tile map space.
So you'll notice that we had sort of a concept of where the player was
and this notion of where the player was a sort of inside one tile map.
This is where they are inside the tile map.
But what I need to do and we wrote this function already yesterday.
There was a function that says, get a tile map from a tile Map X in
the town map, Y, and that tilemap X and Y, are basically sort of
indices into an array of tile maps to say which tilemap were in.
And then the player X and Y tells us where we are inside that Tom app.
So what I need to do
Do is I basically need to do a player.
Tilemap X and a player, tilemap why?
Right?
To sort of say here is the tile map that players in and then here's
where they are inside the tile map.
Right?
So, that's something that I need to do.
And then what I can do is when we are actually operating on the tile
Maps here, I could start to say, alright, which tilemap are we going
to operate on?
In the game Loop.
Well, we're going to operate on whichever one player.
Player tilemap X, right?
Game State player.
Tilemap why we're gonna operate on?
Whichever one.
We were actually looking at what the player that we actually remember
the player to be in.
Now, if I remember correctly, like I said, we wrote that function that
will actually retrieve it for us and actually does bounds checking
right?
Which is get tile map and you pass it.
The Tom FX in the time.
That's why.
So what I can do here
Is I can actually use that query function, right?
I can actually use that query function to do the query for us, which
is good because I type that in wrong.
I typed it in backwards there the Y comes first in the X comes second.
I don't know if you noticed that that as I was just doing a stream.
So this is actually much better because X usually we think of X is
coming first and why it's coming second but in C, because we tend to
store things in order of X is first and then why's it ends up being
backwards.
Looks like that when you access an array, so I kind of like to have
accessors because then I can always pass my ex first when my
Second and then I can throw bounds checking in there if I want to.
So this is just strictly better in my opinion.
So I'm going to stick with that.
All right, so I got to get the tile map out there and then if I guess
what we want to do here is also assert that he's always on a towel map
for now, because he should never actually, we should never allow the
player to be in some location.
That doesn't actually have a town map associated with it.
So for now, let's just say that that's true.
Okay.
So we need to do that.
We've got that game state that has to go after.
Initialization because we have initialized the game state yet at that
point.
So there we go.
And now we should still be on the same screen which we are.
So really all we need to do now is start thinking about moving the
player, when they would go off of here.
And we also have to do some other things, which is that right now,
when it looks off that tile map, we're not actually looking onto
another tilemap.
What?
Because if you remember, we wrote the code to do sort of are stopping
us.
When we hit a wall, what that's basically doing is it's looking where
the player would be on the next frame.
And it's saying is the location where the player would be on the next
frame in the tile map, empty or not.
Well, when we get to here and it reads and it looks over to sort of
no-man's-land, we assume that if you were accessing off the tile map,
the the timeout that are currently on, if you were to look outside of
it, either on the left the right, the top or the bottom.
We just assumed it to be filled but we need to do now is start
assuming that it's not filled assuming that it's actually could be
another Tom app that we have to look look at and see what the
The actual value is right.
And so if we if we go through here and take a look at that is Tom at
Point empty thing, right?
That is tilemap point empty.
What we want to do here is allow that function right to start looking
across multiple tile Maps.
Okay.
And so what we want to do is start saying, well, there's probably the
equivalent here of something like, you know this sort of thing where
it's like,
There's an is tilemap.
Point and empty which is the function that we had before and then
there's maybe something like a is World Point empty, which is actually
going to take a world location.
Right?
I'm sorry a world struck so that it can access multiple tile maps and
maybe that thing will actually take something more like this.
So it's going to take the tile Map X and the tile map Y.
And then it's going to take the test.
And or so I should say test Tom FX test tile map.
Why?
And then it's going to take that test X text.
Why.
Right now?
I'm just again, just doing the speculative lie because we don't
actually know what this function wants to do.
We probably want to preserve this guy here, who's actually doing our
testing inside one tile map, but let's just take a look at what we
might want to do here.
So the test tile Map X in the test tile map, why?
Well this test X test why is essentially what can happen is if those
were going to be outside the boundary, right?
If you think about what happens here, if the player tile X in the
player tile tile, why?
If they were outside the boundary?
What we were doing is we were just using this if statement to prevent
us from ever doing anything, in the cases where they were, but what we
could do instead is just start looking at what happens, right?
We could say if the player tile X was less than zero, instead of like
preventing it from looking.
If the player tile X was less than 0, what we could say is we could
say, okay, let's actually change what we were looking at.
Let's assume that if it's less.
Than 0, we're going to map it into the next tile Maps space.
The next tile map over, right?
So, you can picture what this is doing right here.
Is our lovely diagram from yesterday.
It's my art is always unpair unrivaled as you know, so if I have a
tile map here, right?
And I have some tile map next to it.
Right?
Previously.
What we were doing is we are figuring out where in this town map you
were and maybe you know, you walked off the left Edge, so
So it's negative 1 or something, right?
And so if it was negative one, we just assumed.
It's blocked.
That's what we're assuming.
What we'd like to do, instead is ask the next tile map before us what
he had in his right, most column, right?
So if a tile map was N, Things wide, right?
And they're numbered 0 through n minus 1.
As we do in see, when we look at the negative 1 of this guy, if it,
when we look at negative 1,
We sort of want to do is say, Okay - one is going to map to n minus 1
on the previous tile map and negative 2 is going to map to n minus 2
on the previous, tilemap, right?
So, it's basically, it's n.
However, Big N is - right whatever our actual x value is that we
computed here.
Right?
Right.
It's this value minus, whatever.
The width of a tile map is in tiles is the actual
That we'd want to look into, right?
So you can imagine it's basically the new tile X is just whatever that
with is - the player tile X, right?
If that makes sense.
I don't know if that makes sense.
But like we said, it's going to be negative.
So it just becomes.
I'm not explaining this very well and I apologize that hopefully this
made some sense.
Basically, what I'm saying is we know this number is already negative.
We know that we support, we got a negative number because this is the
zero with tile of our map and we got a negative number here.
So the player Ty
X is already negative, so I don't need to do n.
Minus X.
I'm really doing n plus the X because the x is negative, right?
I don't know if that makes sense.
Hopefully, that makes some sense.
So, what I want to do here is I want to just take whatever the tile
map was beforehand.
I want to take that tile map with this this context, right?
However, many tiles there are in a tile map and I want to go ahead
and, and, and add the player talks to it.
That is the actual player Telex.
I would look into up into in the previous time at.
But of course I have to actually, get whatever that tilemap actually
was because it's a different tile map now.
So the tile map that I'm actually going to be looking at again is test
tile Map X.
So what I want to do is say all right that test tile Map X is now one
before where it was.
So I'm moving to the previous tilemap.
I'm correcting.
What the player Telex is and off we go.
The exact same thing would work.
For y right?
If we were, we were one off the bottom.
We'd move to the previous tilemap in y, and we'd query this tile on it
right now.
One thing you may notice is this tile map here.
We don't actually know what tilemap we're looking at yet.
And so, what we would have to do if we wanted to do this, where each
tile map was a different size, we'd have to do a ton of different math
here, because we have to also have other information.
Like let's say the tile Maps,
Were different sizes, right?
So here's the one, we're on and here's a different one.
Well, now, the math is more complicated because if we move over here,
and we'd also have a different y offset than we used to have, because
the top is up here.
So the Y offset for this may be 0, but the Y offset for this maybe
like 7:00 or something, right?
But since all of our tile maps are supposed to be the same size and
their tiled like this, we don't actually have to do that which brings
up the thing we talked about yesterday.
And again I said don't do things until you actually have to do them.
You actually see, and that's exactly what I want to talk about.
Now, these values that are accessed off, the tile map are actually
constant for all the tile Maps.
We don't allow tile maps to be multiple sizes yet.
And I don't ever anticipate allowing you to do that because since we
allow you to have as many tile Maps as you want.
The only thing that that would do is we would have it so that
basically the you would zoom in or out.
So there would be times when we would be seeing your guy a lot smaller
because there'd be a lot more tiles on like one screen or something
and that
Not something that I plan on enabling in this game at all.
So what I want to do is say these values are actually constant, right?
All of this stuff is actually not a property of the tile map at all.
It's a property of the world.
Right?
And we could actually have you go between multiple worlds.
Let's say we could make this something else, which is like a series of
time-lapse of the same size or something like that we could do.
We could rename this.
But like I said, I want a fairly consistent space.
So I want the player to always be seeing a screen.
That's a certain number of tiles with what width and height and then
they walk around and it's always
He's consistent.
So I think that's fairly safe to say.
So what I want to do is move that out to the world.
So that what you're really doing all the time is you're really looking
at the world to know these things that you were previously looking
basically at the tile map to know, right?
So be should all be world based stuff, right?
World world world world world.
So when we do this, when we walk off the end like that we're going to
take a look and we're going to say okay if we moved off the end we
readjust which tile we're looking at in here.
Same has to go the exact same thing has to go for if we were going to
walk sort of past the right Edge as well.
So this thing right here that we were checking before that also has to
happen.
Excuse me.
So, if we were to walk off that right, Edge?
Same basic idea, what we need to do is say all right, let's go to the
next tile map over, right?
And when we go to the next aisle over, we're looking at this
situation.
We were here, we step to hear if this is, n, minus 1, right, which is
that count that count?
Number.
It's count X.
If this is Count x -1, we're then going to be on count X.
We're going to be on n.
And what we really want to be on is we want to be on 0, right?
We want to basically subtract out the count.
Just get how far we are away from that that boundary which will tell
us where we are on the next tile map.
Right?
So all we want to really do here is just say, okay, whatever that
player Telex was, you know, that we had was, we want to just subtract
out the world count X right.
There you go.
And the same is true for y again, there we go.
Let's see, X and Y.
So all I'm doing here is saying if we, if we step out the bounds,
let's let's
Reduce it and go to the next one over and this is basically the
equivalent of this clipping that we used to be doing.
But instead of actually just clipping in assuming we're actually going
to just look at the next tile map if we have to.
So once we do that work, we can then say let's get the tile map.
Whatever.
The actual tile map is here.
Using get Tau map.
We've now computed, which tilemap we actually want, right?
So this is the tile map that we actually want.
So let's go ahead and query it.
We say ask the the
That function, that looks up tile Maps.
We know that the player has moved, you know, or where the position
we're looking up.
I guess this is instead of player tile X.
This is really this is really testing.
Tilak's right?
So the test the tile that we're testing here, we're going to ask for
the tile map that corresponds to the place that we were asked to look
right adjusted by.
If we were out of bounds adjusted one in any one of the four
directions.
We're then going to say we get that tilemap back and we go ahead and
say let's let's ask if that point is empty.
Now.
What I'd like to do is since this function can fail like we could be
asking for a child.
It's out of bounds since that function go.
Know what I'd also like to do is, I'd like to go ahead and make this
function guarded.
I'd like to say that when you call this function, it's going to go
ahead and check the tile map to see if that tile map is 0 or not.
If it is zero, it's just going to assume that the tile was not empty.
It's going to assume that there was something there and that it's
blocking, right?
And so that way we can call this function, even if we fetched out of
bounds, it doesn't actually matter.
Right.
And then
Okay, we are going to ask our test X and Test.
Why?
So what we need to do now is oh wait, but we already have the tile
value.
So what we actually need here, right?
Yeah.
Okay, so we don't actually need this code anymore.
What we actually need to do is just pass this straight up the test.
I sent texts.
Test why that?
We've already computed, right?
We've already computed the index into the tile into the tile map
itself.
So we're going to go ahead and just pass that directly.
Test tile style, there we go.
And so this is Tom, a point.
Empty will actually just take the X and the Y, and it will not have to
do that.
So, this is, this is a, this is a test tile X and Test tile.
There we go.
So Claire test doo-doo-doo-doo to.
Okay.
So, where did that go?
Jump back to where the search started.
There we go.
So what we want to do here is we basically want to also probably
assert these sorts of things.
I would probably say.
Let's go ahead and assert basically the same things that are happening
in our unchanging are checked path.
Let's go ahead and assert those.
This should probably be 8X style.
Why?
Okay.
All right, getting closer.
So
Has to happen.
Now, is inside these functions where previously a tile map was
sufficient.
We are going now going to need that world pointer because the world
pointer has all of the dimensional information in it.
So basically, everything previously that we were using the tile map
pointer for now has to have the world pointer.
And so that's a little bit of work.
We got to do but not too big of a deal, right?
Not too big of a deal at all.
Let's see, what takes here, that goes there.
Nothing.
Just cleaning not doing.
Anything special here just cleaning up cleaning up things and then
we're going to step through this insert a start to look at.
Clean it up and fix any bugs that?
I, no doubt have.
Like I said, many times on the stream.
It's hard for me to talk and program at the same time people, it is, I
make a lot of mistakes.
Fortunately, the stream, oftentimes catches them for me.
So if we end the day with bugs, that I haven't found a lot of times,
the stream is right there to pick me up and I appreciate that
immensely.
I can tell you that.
So okay, is World Point empty.
What did I do here?
Oh, what did I?
I totally just this is, this was
Me not paying attention to what I was to what I was editing their.
Why do we have a another function?
That is the same?
I like got multiple.
How did I get multiple copies?
I don't even know how that happened.
Do not know.
Probably going to find out in a second when I go to compile and find I
accidentally edited like the wrong function and now I have no
functions left.
So now we're in a much better position to clean this code up.
Even, right?
Because now that we have the world set up as well.
The world can can take all of these.
Values that were very much more properly stored in the world, which
means that this cloning stuff doesn't have to happen anymore, right?
That cloning of the values that were in the tile Maps.
Which again, I said, when we did, it is sort of indicative that
something is, it's not quite right yet.
That is, is gone.
So that's a good again, a good cleanup.
It means that we can now start to talk about sort of maps 00 with
World.
There we go.
It means we can start to talk about the world properly and assign
things there that
At our constant and we don't have to worry anymore about sort of using
a tile map to get that stuff, which is inappropriate because again, we
don't know which time that would be talking about and those values
didn't actually vary across them.
So what we have here now is, we don't want to query is town that point
empty anymore.
We just don't even want that at all.
What we want is, is World, Point empty, right?
We want to do is World Point empty for our testing and now we pass the
world for that.
Not a child.
We want to pass our world pointer.
So we're going to ask it about the world, and we're going to go ahead
and say that our test tile map, x y, and x, and why.
We're only passing the actual X and Y inside the town map.
What we want to do now is also passed which tile map, we believe the
player to be on which, again, we have.
It's called player tile X and player tile.
Why?
Player.
Tau y like that.
Okay.
So yeah, there we go.
And about what did I do player time?
Oh boy.
So this is going to be something that is going to be really nice to
clean up.
I think probably based on how many we have in here already.
I think next week is a good time to do it.
So that's going to be good.
But yes, all right.
So anyway, let's see inside here.
We need to pass the world's pointer.
In eye, looks like that's all that is.
Looks like we're still using, we want to use the word.
For all of these references like this.
There we go.
We've got the tile map here, which is also not, right.
We just go all of these things.
I'll move over to the world.
So that's good tile with tile height also in the world.
Okay.
So, let's see what we're doing here.
So are we still running?
Let's let's see.
Let's stop.
Okay.
So let's see.
So we're still running and that's good.
But I think we've got some bugs here.
So let's go ahead and and, and see what's going on.
All right, so let's step in and see what we're dealing with here.
So is World Point empty?
We've got test tile Map, X test tile map.
Why?
Oh,
That is that because I hadn't stepped in the function yet, Wrightwood
on function entry.
The stack, isn't I guess?
Correct yet for viewing.
Those variables.
That's fine.
I was like, what's going on there?
That's not good.
But yeah, I hadn't stepped in to the function yet.
That's fine.
All right, so stepping through the function.
We're at zero zero in our tile map.
And that's fine.
We are at Test X test.
Why here's where our this is where our guy is, right?
Hmm, okis, I guess I was trying to move.
That's interesting.
That that's where I'm going to actually look up.
What I wasn't was.
I actually moving was actually trying to move.
What's my deep layer XD player y x?
I didn't think I was trying to move.
So I'm interested to know why it's looking at a non.
Even boundary.
Duplex.
Deep layer.
Why?
So
Game state.
Did my guy already move.
He's at 150 150.
So oh, right, that's because it's checking either side of the guy.
So it's using half the player with to check on either side of the guy.
That's why it's that.
Yeah, that makes sense.
Do you see what happened there?
I was wondering why the test X was a fractional value and it's because
the player with is an even even number.
So when you divide it, I'm sorry.
It's an odd number, I guess.
So when you divide it by 2 you get a fractional value, is that
correct?
Is it actually an odd value?
Yeah, probably is because it's
Bubbly added by 2.
So let's take a look actually at what the player with the knife is
just make sure that's true.
So the player with back here gotta jump back out to the enclosing
function player with
Yeah, it's 45.
So your name?
So the the reason is because the tile the tile with is 60 and the way
that we initialized, when I wrote the game just randomly, as I said
that a guy was going to be 3/4 the width of a tile, right?
And if a guy is 3/4, the width of a tile, then it's dividing.
You know, it's multiplying with 3 / 4 kind of a thing.
It's multiplying by 0.75.
What have that tile with is?
Which gives us 45 which then when we divide by half,
Look on either side of the guy to test the two points on his left and
right side, that ends up being a 45 divided by to offset.
Right.
Which is of course a fractional value.
If you don't if you don't clamp it there, there we go.
A fractional value and so that is why when we look in here this is not
an even value.
So I just want to make sure that was right, and it is, that's all
fine.
So now we figure out which tile we're looking at test tile, X, test
tile, why?
Oops.
Why we're looking at tile 2 comma 2?
We go in here and we see that none of our cases trigger, which is
correct.
We are not out of bounds.
We then need to get the tile map that corresponds to our test tile Map
X and our test tile map.
Why so we step in here and we go ahead and check to see if we are in
bounds.
We are in bounds, which is good.
We then retrieve the tile map itself.
So here is the tile map.
Itself, that is good and you know, it's got the tiles in it.
Nothing particularly interesting to see there.
We've got the tile map.
We then want to ask whether our hour.
Using the tile map that we know the guys in whether our location in
that, Tom app is empty or not.
Oh well, and then we don't assign it to anything.
So we've got one bug, which is basically that this empty, which is
what we return, we never actually assigned to empty.
So that's, that's a bug will fix that in a second.
We check to see if the time that points empty.
Let's see what happens in there.
We look to see if we have a towel map.
We do because we fetched one properly.
We look to see whether we're in bounds.
We are we then ask our accessor to look inside.
I'm the tiles.
It uses the sort of that sort of to d1d packing thing.
I talked about yesterday to go, pull out the value for the particular
tile using the X and Y.
We return that out.
We look to see whether or not is equal to 0 which is, which would mean
empty in our case.
We return it.
And then, of course, we throw the value away.
That all looks like it works.
The only thing that's wrong with it is we don't actually use the
return value.
So we definitely have a bug, but other than that, it looked pretty.
Okay.
Let's go ahead and fix that, and then we'll play with it and see if
that works.
You.
All right.
Where was that guy?
There was that guy right here.
Empty equals.
There we go.
Okay, so let's try that again.
All right.
So now we are walking around, just fine looks pretty good.
And now we should in theory be able to walk off this Edge.
I don't know if we can or not.
Nope.
So that doesn't quite work correctly at the moment.
So we are.
I thought it looked correct but it probably maybe we've got a bug
still in are other cases where we handle walking.
Well, that one does so that one actually did work a little bit.
Bit because we can't walk off one side there.
So it's starting to work a little bit, but we're still a little bit
buggy.
All right, so let's fix that.
And then once we fixed that, we actually only have one other thing to
do before, we can actually walk between Tom apps and because all we
have to do to walk between Tom after that is actually look to see when
we've
When our test Point, our new player location moves off of the screen
and switch to a new tile map.
All right, so what's our bug?
What have we got there?
What's going on?
So what we want to do now is, we'd like to go ahead and say when the
we'd like to see what happens in these cases, of course, I also should
make sure that our town maps are actually set up so that there
actually is an empty spot there that you can actually walk to.
So let's double check and make sure that's true.
So we essentially have a tiles are tilemap.
Excuse me a setup.
So they've got 0 0 and 0 1.
So this is, you know what?
I think I set them up backwards.
I did.
This is this is yet another reason why, you know, all these crazy that
the C Syntax for this and not being X Y, is is really annoying.
And at least a lot of Errors.
That's why I don't I pretty much always pack stuff myself as you've
been seeing.
I constantly move to packing things myself because this, this syntax
drives me nuts.
I always want to put the X first and then y s, because X and Y go in
that order.
And
And you've been drilled into it.
It's been drilling.
You so much.
That's hard, just like switch around and I believe that this is
actually wrong.
So let's double check.
So I wrote These as if it was X and why I believe, right?
Because that's x x, that's x y 0, 0, and this was X Y.
This was supposed to be below this one, right?
And you can see it was.
And so that's not what happened here.
What happened here is?
We did it the other way around.
So it's actually, it's actually, that is actually the way that I wrote
them.
So that was just me being pretty dumb actually.
So now we can go ahead and walk off of it as we would expect to.
And we can also walk off of this one.
I don't know though.
What happens?
I don't know.
Why exactly we stop.
We don't stop.
So there we go.
So now that we've corrected it.
It looks like we can walk off properly.
And so that's good.
So now all we have to do is allow our guy to actually change screens.
And so, we've already what we want to do here again, is we want to
reuse some work because as you can see, we do this Israel Point, empty
the Israel.
Empty thing actually does the work we need to figure out that we have
wrapped on a tile but we never get that information back.
We never find out that it looked at a different tile.
So when we accept the move, what we'd like to be able to do is then
accept the fact that it moved to a new tile as well.
And so what we want to do here is pull out this work in some kind of
convenient way.
Now, you'll notice this is again leading into exactly what I want to
get into next.
So hey that that worked out pretty well.
It turns out if you just write the code kind of guides you towards all
of
The right answers.
That's sort of the thing that I again.
I've been harping on over and over and it's true.
Again.
The next thing that we want to do to clean up this code is exactly
what it looks like we want to do, right?
So we're passing all this stuff around.
Test text, Sy time.
I'm Tom Apple abla.
Essentially, all of this is talking about a player's location, right?
And they're all interrelated.
You can't really talk about the test X in the test.
Why very effectively without talking.
Which test tile, the player is in.
And that's going to be true of everyone who has a location that can be
freely roaming right at some level.
So what we want to do is we want to probably have a way of bundling
these things together so that we could return them, right.
We want to be able to do something.
We'd like to be able to say like this, something like
You know, I'm going to call it.
I'm going to call it.
I don't know canonicalize maybe, I don't know, we're going to call.
I'm not sure what the name of this should be.
But basically what I want to do is I want to pull this code out so
that I can use it again where I'm going to go ahead and take a tile
map exit, AA map, Y and a real offset inside that.
And if this real offset is outside of the tile map.
It will realign the test.
I'll Map X and Y to correctly.
Put this this inside.
We could call it normalizes.
Well, I don't know.
I'm not called canonicalize for now.
But basically what I wanted to do is exactly what this function did,
right.
I wanted to take these things and I want it to sort of return these
things as well.
So I need it to have basically a struct that has them in it.
Right?
I need a struct that's got this stuff so I can return it.
Does that make sense?
So maybe so maybe get canonical location or something like that?
Right?
And I go ahead and I pass it in.
I say this is a tile map position or something or a tile map location
or maybe just a world location.
Let's say, World position.
I don't know.
I'm not sure what to name it yet, but I want to be able to say, I want
to be able to say something.
Like, let's pass one of these in.
I want it to do the same math that it was.
Being.
So I'm going to pass in a world position and I can probably pass this
in my value, right?
And then it's going to return 1 by value.
So this is just a simple inline function.
Let's say that can be inlined anywhere that all it does is it does the
truncation and then it does the check, right?
So it's basically going to do this exact math that I wanted this,
right?
And it's going to wreak, it's going to take sort of something that
could have been a bogus position that's been you know, sort of that's
wrapped outside of this tile.
It's going to take it and realign it into what we would consider
canonical.
Form, which means that it's always the the real part is always going
to be sort of with within one tile map boundary.
Okay, so I'm going to go ahead and do that.
Hope you can all see what I'm doing here.
I'm just sort of canonicalize.
I'm sort of wrapping these up into something that we can that we can
reason with cleanly.
So basically, I've got this guy here.
It's got the, the tile Map X and the tile map lie, and it's got his X
and Y inside that, right, so, it's like a pixel X and a pixel, why?
That makes
Sense, so hopefully that yet hopefully that makes some reasonable
sense.
So, and in theory, we could also even do this.
We could even do this down to the tile level.
I'm not sure if we want to, but we could, we could even do this, down
to the tile level.
Even more explicitly.
I'm not sure if you want to do that.
We'll have to see how we decide to actually play with these.
All right.
So we're going to get the canonical position.
We're going to pass that in there.
What we're going to do here is basically turn Test X test why into
pose expose, why write like this.
And then essentially all of the stuff that we do for the tile map, is
now going to be being done on pose like that.
There we go, right.
So basically that just
It does that canonicalization for us.
And so we can do the get canonical position like that.
Now that we have get canonical position, R is world map.
Quite empty function is sort of useless, but we're going to keep it
around.
Anyway, just because hey why not?
So basically what all we need to do here is we need to say, you know,
get canonical position for whatever the pose is that we were looking
at.
So I can pose test pose something like this and we will go ahead.
And use the values out of that, so test tile map.
The other.
So yeah, you know what?
Now that I think about it.
We already are Computing.
We're since for computing this value as well.
I guess we would probably want to keep that right as a fully world
world qualified position, right?
There's also this is this kind of interesting now that I think about
it, there's different ways we could use this, right?
Because we don't probably want to store this value.
Right, but it's kind of the thing that gets produced.
The fully computed position is sort of this thing, which means we
could start thinking of these floating Point offsets as being within a
tile itself as well.
I don't, this is kind of interesting.
I, this is not as wrote as I thought it was going to be.
There's some, there's some interesting things here.
I'm going to.
I'm going to have some fun.
I think playing with this stuff.
In some sense.
You might think of it as as there being two of these and I wonder even
if I want to represent that where there's
Essentially a, there's there's sort of a canonical position and like a
and like a, like a raw position, right?
I don't know if this makes sense, but basically, you could think of
their as being, I'm not sure.
I actually want to keep this abstraction, but I'm just going to since
we've got only about 15 minutes left.
I'm going to, I'm going to show what it would look like to do it
because I mean, I'm just I'm interested.
I'm interested to say you could think of it this way.
There's a raw position.
Which is just, I was on some tile map and I had some random X and Y
value that I wanted to test, right?
And then when I was once I do some work on it.
I also now know which tile that we're in, right?
And so in some sense you can think of this as the canonical position
takes in a raw position, right?
And then the the result of that right canonical position like this,
the result of that is going to be
Something that gets computed entirely out of this, right?
Let's see.
Tom at and this would have been a bug.
That's good that I didn't finish doing that because I don't really
want to edit the one in place.
So that's not, that's not actually correct.
So, anyway, okay, result, fixes, the bug that we didn't have to deal
with yet.
Okay.
So we've got to get kind of position, we pass in a position, we get
one back, we get that result back.
So what we want to do here is say that result Kyle map x equals pose
tilemap.
Right result.
Tilemap y equals pose town, map.
Why you copy those guys in?
And then we have to figure out what our X and Y is going to be.
And this is something that we haven't actually dealt with either yet.
Right?
When we do this, tilemap advancing.
We're going to have to deal with the X&Y floating Point values as
well.
Right?
So another reason we might want to do this.
In fact, this is all looking a little bit better now that I think
about it.
When we go to the canonical position this
And Y value could actually be inside a tile as well.
If we wanted to, which gets us out of the business of dealing with
wrapping the X and the Y.
Because remember, the X and the, Y, were wrong before we never
finished actually dealing with the X and the Y, because the X and the
Y are offsets in the tile in the space of an entire tilemap.
So when we wrap those to the next thing they would have been wrong.
If we do them inside the tile we're already dealing with wrapping the
tile X and Y.
If this is relative to a tile it would just work.
So I'm starting to like this.
This, I'm interested in this, I'm going to just, you know, and like I
said, this is what exploratory programming is all about.
I've never done a tilemap game before.
So I'm just kind of finding out what I like about how these things
work.
So I'm going to pursue this because it feels kind of good to have it
be relative to a tile, that seems kind of like it saves a little bit
of work.
Maybe.
So I'm going to go ahead and write this function that way and say,
alright, we come in.
We've got to tell my bexon why.
We know that that's not going to change unless we wrapped and that's
fine.
We compute what the tile X and tile?
Why are from the from this sort of offset in?
Tom app, right?
That makes sense.
So we go ahead and do that to me.
We might even just store it this way and then we could get rid of
this.
Yeah, this is, this is looking good.
We're not going to get to do all of this today.
So you have to blow my nose.
It is that time of year.
When occasionally get the sniffles, I'm not sick at the moment.
Thankfully.
All right.
Anyway, yeah, I like where this is going.
So we're going to keep going this direction because then we can get
rid of this story.
It relative, the tile seems like a really good idea now that I think
about it.
I just didn't think about it before.
So this is going to be good.
All of this is just coming out kind of naturally in the course of
seeing what the code had to do.
And again, I can't emphasize that enough.
It didn't require any forethought.
It just requires trying it.
Seeing what happens and we going?
Oh, duh, and that's a much easier way to program them.
Trying to guess everything up front, especially when you've never done
it before because you're likely to guess wrong, okay.
Okay.
So we're going to go ahead and say we're taking this proposition in.
We're take the pose X, we subtract it out.
We then come up with our tile X.
And so what I'd like to do now is re figure out what the X & Y would
be inside the tile, right?
So what I want to do is I want to say, all right, that pose expose,
why?
So let's do something like this.
Let's first subtract out the relative to the tile map for the X and
the Y, right?
Let's let's do
Let's do this because we need this value, right?
So that's the X and the Y relative to the tile map.
We then go ahead and truncate real 32 in 32.
We've got that but we like to do now is compute the offset as well.
So the result X right is going to be that tile x times that I'll Whip.
That is where the upper corner, right?
This is where the upper corner of the tile would be, right.
This is the upper.
This is the left part and this is the top part of that tile.
So what I'd like to do now,
Now is, I'd like to go ahead and subtract out.
Sorry.
Oops.
I'd like to subtract out that upper left corner of the tile from,
where my pose from, where I was in the pose for when we, when whatever
we got passed in.
So now, this is a tile relative X and Y, right?
No, Casey.
This is tile relative X and Y and this at the moment and I think we're
going to rid of this eventually.
That's what my Spidey.
The saying tilemap relative X and Y.
So, basically, these X and Y tells us how far we are away from the
upper left corner of the tile map.
This says, how far away we are from the upper left corner of a tile,
right?
And so, all I'm doing is saying, okay.
Let's make this, let's make that relative right now.
We don't have to care about these X of Y is anymore.
They're always going to be right as we adjust, which tile we were
looking at this test tile X test tile why stuff.
That's now that is just going to be
Totally correct.
When we do the adjustment, the X&Y won't have to be adjusted because
relative to Tau.
So we just the tile, we get the positional adjustment for free.
So I think they see if I've got this.
All right.
Now, let's go go.
All right, so I need to return.
This here is the result.
So I don't know.
That was a bunch of typing and like I said, hard to pay attention on
the stream sometimes, so we're going to step into that and make sure
that we didn't.
Introduce a bunch of random stupid stuff that shouldn't actually
happen, but now we can call get canonical position.
So basically get canonical position this thing.
If it takes in a raw position for example, and then wants to go ahead
and get that canonical position out it can do so, so this will take in
a raw position and say, okay, that's the pose.
We're going to test.
So we go ahead and get the test pose in we.
Then take the canonical position that came out.
We asked if the tile map point is
Point is empty by saying, alright.
The tile Map X and the tile map.
Why tell us which town map we're looking at?
And then the tile X and the tile y of that tile map.
Tell them, tell us, where, in the towel we are.
So we go ahead and do that.
And of course, we need that group.
We need a world pointer here because otherwise, we can't canonicalize.
We've got a use salt here again.
Just kind of dealing with the cleanup of changing.
How all these things are accessed.
It's okay.
And then here we are.
So this is our canonical position.
Get that out.
Function is not take.
What is true.
It doesn't it needs the world to do its work.
So we pass it, the world's typo there.
And then here, this is now going to take raw positions entirely.
So, okay, we've got raw positions and those raw positions are the
player pose, right?
And
And we can go ahead and do the player pose.
And then we've got some different poses that come out, that sort of
got tile Map X and tilemap why there.
And we've got the X and the Y, which is these, right?
So basically I'm just go ahead and building one of these quickly
course.
There's we're going to want to do a bunch of stuff with this.
Now, since this is starting to actually come together here.
So that's going to be player pose right there.
So, we're going to build the player.
Bo's.
Then we're going to do our opposition left player left.
That's going to be equal to the player pose.
And the only difference there for the player left and the player right
is that we're going to subtract that width from the X, right.
So, we've got that player left, and then the player, right?
Okay.
So now we are just doing
Israel Point, empty player pose that player left and player.
Right?
There we go.
Now we should be
In a place where we are working a little more cleanly or ready.
You can start to see this stuff is getting a little cleaner.
We now no longer have giant strings of variables that were passing.
So we could, you know, which we could have gotten the order wrong of
or get confused about what is what at least.
Now, we're passing sort of some bundles and those bundles, look a
little more intelligible and we know what they mean on the inside.
So that's a little handier.
We're pretty far from where we would want to be.
But we're getting, we're certainly making some progress.
And so, let's go ahead and take a look in here and see where we are.
Our at, we've got our player pose.
Let's see what that is.
It's on, 00, 150 150.
That is exactly where it should be.
Our player left our player, right?
Where are those?
We can
Get rid of all of this stuff now, goodbye.
So, let's take a look at those when 27:51 up.
Nope.
Got a bug, got a typo.
I did the player, right?
I still a need to add.
It's not.
There we go.
Oh, I keep forgetting.
I don't have to close because we've got our nice little.
Yeah.
Well, anyway, okay.
So that's our player left our player, right?
That is good.
So, let's go into Israel Point empty and look at our debt canonical
position, call our get canonical position.
Call is
Working between two things.
It's working between a canonical position that is trying to produce
and oppose that it gets in which is not necessarily.
It's mapped relative, the tile map.
So, okay.
So here we go.
I go into my result and I say, all right.
Let's copy the top.
Excellent time I buy for starters and those are both 0, obviously
already.
I'm going to compute the X and the Y, which is basically the X and the
Y relative to the tile map itself.
There you go that computes that which is f what we expected.
Because there's an offset of negative 30
On the X4 things.
So, that's exactly what we expect.
Let's go ahead and grab those tile Maps out and see what the toxin.
Why is it style map?
It's 3 and 2.
Is that correct?
I don't know if that's correct or not.
Is that where we're supposed to be 32?
I'm not sure if that's where we're supposed to be.
That's a good question.
I guess.
I don't know where the guy starts.
Let's assume.
It's correct for now, but maybe that's something we'll have to look at
later if it's not.
So yeah, so three.
Well if it's what
150.
150 180, 150.
Yeah, I think that is right because it's a little further over in X
and Y and the tiles were something like, what would they 90 apiece, or
60, a piece?
I don't know.
What are they, what?
Have a good.
Our tiles people.
60 a piece.
So, yeah, if it's an additional 30 over then it would be than 60.
Let's see.
150 0 divided by the tile with 2.5.
Yep.
So it would be it would be just over.
So that's fine.
All right, totally fine.
Make sense.
We then recompute and say what where?
We relative to our tile.
So, okay, result X and Y know that is okay.
So that is totally not correct at all.
That's just just totally totally bogus.
So so we've got, we've got an issue.
We have an issue here.
So our result tile x what has happened here.
What has happened?
Are posed.
X0.
Awesome.
Yeah.
I did all.
Work is very common on the stream people.
I did all the work and then didn't use it.
So we intentionally made things relative to the tile map so that I
could compute with that because I didn't want to deal with things that
were in the offset space that you know, with the shift on the screen
again, a lot of stuff will go away.
Once we get even further down the coordinate line of things.
But all right, so I'm going to, I'm going to remove the X and what do
the pose expose Y and use the actual values that
Relative the tile map because that is what I needed to use that.
The reason I did that is because I need to use that in order to do
this sort of computation.
I can't subtract out the position that I ended up Computing for the
upper left of the tile.
If I don't also take into account the upper left X, so that's why I
wanted to get rid of that ahead of time.
So that's just a bug.
That's just it was it just a stupid stupid mistake.
Alright, so let's come back in here and you know what we could do to
since
We have a certain now since we added in assert, what we could also do
is assert that our results that are results of mapping into the tile
space, right?
That those are always within the bounds, that would be allowed.
Right?
We could, we can just say that once we put something in tile space, It
should never be allowed to be too far off of the tub, you know,
outside of the size of a tile, right?
Okay.
Oops, so I actually didn't mean to stop there.
There we go.
So now our results should always be.
Yep.
In that that's more respected.
We should never be able to get a negative there because relative the
upper left corner of a tile.
So that's good.
We go through and we check of course we can't really do bug that those
cases yet because we're not hitting them at all.
So we go in here, we get our canonical pose.
Let's make sure that that canonical pose is sensical and it is 0, 0
times, we up all looks good.
We
Into getting the tile map.
That's just a straight up.
Look up.
So that didn't change at all.
Nothing, particularly.
Where there are?
We coming here?
We look at the test.
How we see what that value is.
We see.
Yep, nothing particularly odd.
So off we go and now we can drive around in the theory all our stuff
should still work.
It does seem to work.
So that's pretty good.
Nothing particularly out of the ordinary there and that is a good
thing.
We actually don't want to be out of the ordinary.
In this case.
We can walk off the screen and that is good as well.
So we are all happy.
So the only thing we have left to do now, I suppose is to actually
move where the player is on the tile map afterwards.
So we've set ourselves up to do that.
Presumably, it should be pretty straightforward.
Basically.
We have that player pose thing down here.
When we do player pose, if we accept a new state for the player, a new
X and Y for the player, what we should basically do is say, let's go
ahead and actually move the player.
New tile map where warranted and so we can do that pretty easily
because now we've got the canonical thing.
Although there is one thing that we still haven't quite done yet.
That makes it a little bit uglier than it should be.
But what we can do now, just call the function that we used.
We have our ability to get a canonical position out of for the players
position.
So his new position, right, which is this one here, the new player X,
right, that new position, we can just ask to get canonicalized, and
that will tell us sort of the new state of the dude.
Now.
The problem is the do.
Is still in tilemap relative coordinates not in.
Yeah, the the player is still in town that builds coordinates and what
we've done basically, as we've converted things over to being tile
relative for locations.
And so this is still going to be a little, uh, who needs to be.
And so, the first thing we could probably do on Monday is fix that,
but I'm going to go ahead and type it in any way just using what we've
got.
Just so we can see if it worked.
So we're going to go and get the canonical position.
Once we have the canonical position that has a tile Map X and the tile
map Y in it, so we're going to
Go ahead and and put that in here, right?
Just grab out where the player is now.
And then all we need to do is Rectify this stuff and that's pretty
easy to do.
Right?
We've got the canonical pose.
It's got an X and Y in it.
And all we have to do is add in the upper sort of how far they were in
tile X and tile.
Why space?
So Campos tile x times the tile with right?
Campos tile.
Why?
This and then, of course, we need the offset X.
And there.
What is it called?
It's oh, sorry.
It's upper left X and upper left y.
So, do you see what I have to do here?
Like in order to get the player location, the new location, these
locations are in our in World space, that the player is, it's just I
mean, I starting screen space.
It's just a cordon on the screen.
And so I have to take our coordinate system and we figure out where he
is on the screen.
I have to say, all right, the upper left corner and this of the tile
map space.
Plus the tile with times.
How many tiles any is place?
Where are you?
Out at the tile, got to do that stuff.
I think I typed it in, right?
I'm not sure, but as we're getting to the end of the stream here,
let's see Campos be canonical position.
Gotta pass the world location, their hoops.
And, oh, and these are all going to be dots because we're that.
Yeah.
Okay.
So player tile map.
Is that what it is?
It's player.
Town map.
Yeah.
Player town.
Map we go.
And let's see.
Now if we can omit.
Wow.
All right.
Well, that was not a good that was not an auspicious beginning.
Their people.
Not an auspicious beginning at all.
Why did we crash there though?
I'm going to see.
I'm going to, I just want to restart the app because we still have
some pdb problems that we need to chase down terms of it not reloading
our pdb.
So let's, let's get that crash again.
There we go.
All right, so we're getting close to working.
I don't think anyone will mind.
No, will you if I just go ahead and debug this, we were so close to
being done?
Might as well take a five more minutes.
And just finished a bug.
Thanks.
Alright, so we've got an assertion here, which is that our result Y is
less than or equal to 0?
What is the problem there?
Oh.
I don't know if we're having a truncation issue.
Let's find out here.
All right, so what we had and this could be good too.
If this is this could be if it's what I was expecting it to be, but
might not be.
All right.
So we take in a position and we say, all right, the tile Map, X,
tilemap?
Why?
That's fine.
We take in our X and our X is going to be 482.
That seems fine as well, around the tile map and our why we've stepped
off the
Top of the screen, so it's negative.
So that's fine as well.
What that ends up doing, is that ends up producing a negative tile
value, or it should right.
So, let's see, when we computed our tile X, in our tell, why we ended
up with the tile y of 0.
So, okay, so
It is what I thought it was, which means we will have to actually
dress this.
Now.
Unfortunately, we can towards the end of this, of the stream, which is
not exactly what I was hoping to see happen here.
But let's let's go ahead and try to think of how I can best step into
this here.
Well, you know what I can do.
This is what I can do.
Because now we actually have to face this issue a little more cleanly,
so, okay.
So what I could do here is let me just call this.
Function synthetically, and and show you what I'm going to.
What I'm saying is basically the problem here, right?
Okay.
So let's say I want to call truncate real 32 in 32 and I pass it 0.5
right or let's let's say I pass it through .75.
Okay.
So in 32 equals truncated and there we go, and I could say what
something here.
I'm just going to set up a call to this so I can show you what I want
to show you without having to deal with, getting to the point in the
debugger where it actually
Would be.
So let's go ahead here, and let's just step into that.
You can see Happening Here.
There we go.
And so you can see what I did right eye.
I passed in -0.75.
And I ask it to truncate.
Now, all of our trunk Asians have been working properly.
And the reason that they've been working properly for our purposes is
because we were always working with positive numbers.
And what happens in the sea, when I do this truncation, is you
remember?
And I UPS,
There we go.
If you remember, I basically was saying, okay, you know, I've got this
sort of thing here and I want to find out where we are on the tile
map.
So 0, 1, 2 3 4.
I want to find out where we are on the tile map.
So like we're here or something.
We want to truncate it down to zero.
So we just do the truncation and we just get what's left.
But if you think about what will happen, right?
When we are here, does that make sense?
This is negative 1.
We want it to truncate down to negative one because what we wanted to
do is we wanted to see where we still were in a tile map.
That imaginarily keeps going below zero.
Unfortunately, what see will actually do and you know, I don't pretend
to remember why it does these things, but this is I believe how it's
specified to work.
I'm not I think is basically it will truncate.
10.
So if you're if you're lower on the number line than 0, I believe what
happens is instead of truncating down to the next lower value.
It truncates to the next value closer to zero.
So basically around zero as you go out in either direction, if this is
0, the truncation direction is actually sort of combed towards zero,
right?
Like this.
And so, that's not what we wanted at all for our purposes.
That's like, totally not what we want.
What we want is something that truncates towards- towards negative
Infinity, right?
Negative Infinity, is off here.
Often Infinity.
We want something that always goes downward truncate towards negative
Infinity right now.
We can do a simple hack for this if we wanted to enforce that, right?
So if we have the truncate real 322 in 32, we can have basically a
floor function, right?
Like
Or something.
We can we can call this truncate.
Real 32 1032 toward negative infinity or something, but I believe
typically that floor has that definition.
Let me, let me, let me look up exactly.
If floor is, I don't want to use.
That's not what we want.
That's funny.
I just want to make sure I'm not going to use a wrong term here for
the name.
I want I want to know that floor is.
Yeah, so you can see floor and ceiling typically have the definition
of always doing the the thing that we want which is no matter what
side of
Oh, they're on, they always go sort of off towards negative infinity
or positive Infinity ceiling.
Like we'll go this way.
I'm sorry, stealing will go this way.
And floor will go this way.
And that's what we actually want.
So what I really wanted instead of truncation is actually flooring if
that makes sense.
And so for most of the places that we use truncate.
I actually want to use floor if that makes sense, right?
I don't know.
I hopefully, hopefully, that was pretty clear.
Why that's actually the case.
So if I look at this, when we're doing these, I really want floor in
these two things, not truncate because truncate has a particular
meaning that in see that we don't actually want to have
So, if I do floor here, I mean, obviously I can do this a little bit
uglier myself.
I could say, all right, you know, doing this or, you know, I could do
something ridiculous.
That would work for our purposes.
For example, which would be something, you know, like that, right
where I basically just force the value for the ranges that we care
about to be positive.
Right?
But usually the processor has a way of us being able to do this
directly and you can
Floor F.
Usually although I don't actually know I think we would have to
include math.h for that.
So I don't actually know if we want to do it that way, but I'm just
going to I'm just going to show you what the what the the difference
here ends up being.
So, where's my deleted?
My test case I was not very smart.
But anyway, if we actually do that that in theory, when we run this
particular thing, we will no longer have that problem of having the
negative value, which will cert.
So if I walk off the edge here and then walk back on, you can see that
we're back to working properly there, right?
So that's all good.
No worries there, but that is not a particularly useful thing to do
because we don't really want to use math that H.
So maybe what we'll do the first thing on, Monday is start to talk
about how to implement these math functions.
Right, so, we don't want to leave that in there.
So let's go ahead and say that that's going to be a priority for us
to.
So we can start talking about how to implement these sorts of things
directly.
And then the other thing I want to do real quickly because we're ten
minutes over here.
Well, I guess we started a little late but we're, you know, we're a
good five minutes over.
I also want to take a look at the thing that I was trying to look at
originally, which was our crashing case, which we had, but I didn't
get a chance to look at that.
So when we walked off the side of the screen here, we were supposed to
crash, we didn't
So I wonder if that was maybe the same bug that could be, but it would
have been nice to have that crash Repro.
That's a little unfortunate.
But anyway, our dude.
Now is super happy.
Weird guy.
He's walking around.
Look at how happy he is.
I don't know if you realize how happy is because he's yellow, so he
can't express himself to you in the same ways that he would, if he
were say a fully grown Sprite, but it looks to me like we have
successfully done what we wanted to do.
It's just we have a little bit of an issue which is that we need to be
able to implement our floor function ourselves and
So that is what we'll have to do next week, but ladies and gentlemen,
there's really no stopping us.
Now.
I feel like at some level you have to admit that were kind of getting
Unstoppable here.
We actually have a dude who can walk around through a tile map and,
you know, how far could it really be to the game 30 hours in and
there's already a dude walking around.
I don't know.
Slap a couple of bitmaps on here.
I think this could be on Steam Greenlight any day now.
Any day now.
Just got to have some kind.
Of a catchy name for it.
I don't know what we should call it.
And we can also make references to some some games and say, we'll get
mostly positive reviews.
I think.
All right.
Well, we have our work cut out for us because we got to deal with
this.
I don't like including math.h here.
So next week is going to be a pretty serious week.
I think we got a lot of things that we want to do, which I'm going to
stick another to do in here, which is convert to, or I should say.
Is this ever necessary?
Do we really need these propositions ever again?
Similarly, down in here, player, State should be canonical position
now.
Oops, going under my head there.
Listen.
Now, basically, hopefully you could see from the work that we did
today.
It's starting to get to the point where we really should start
thinking about coordinate systems because now we actually have an idea
of what our coordinate system is.
We've got a tile Map X and Y.
Got a tile X and Y and we've got a floating-point offside inside
there.
This is kind of an interesting thing that gives us all the information
we needed to actually make things work.
Is this a good coordinate system?
What our coordinate systems mean in general, that sort of stuff.
Maybe that's what we need to start working on.
Next week is sort of start to clean these things up.
We also haven't talked about vectors yet.
Maybe we should start representing these X and y's as bundles because
we're always XY.
XY XY.
Should we start to think about that?
We've got a lot of stuff thing about next week and we're really
starting to come together here.
So I think that's that's very promising, but we have a lot of
Work to do.
And, of course, we have to implement a floor function.
So so
Good shape, ladies and gentlemen.
This was a good week.
I'm feeling positive about this week.
But before I feel any more positive about this week, I think we need
to go to the Q and A.
So I'm going to start the Q&A now, please put Q: before your questions
and keep them to code.
We have done today or in a previous day.
Save questions about what we're going to do in the future or how to
get into the game industry, all that sort of stuff for of a
Scream, if you want to ask those questions, you can ask those
questions, but just not.
Now you have to come back to a future handmade hero, come before the
stream begins and ask those questions.
Basically I start the stream, when I whatever the time is.
It's announced the stream, the stream starts at 10 a.m.
Or whatever, come 15 minutes before that.
I'm usually on the stream.
That is a good time to ask those questions today.
We answered a bunch of very important questions about Japanese food,
for example, and we could do similar for your questions tomorrow.
Okay, running out.
Running on Empty, our people.
All right, let's put that down there.
Can you talk about the inline keyword?
Do you apply any strategies to make sure the compiler doesn't ignore
their Quest?
So not really, I mean, typically we're not really at the stage where
we're doing any kind of performance work.
So when I put in line on these things, honestly that in line is more
for me than it is for the compiler at this point, when I'm putting in
line in these things.
That's me telling my future self that probably these things might be
in lines, but it really has nothing to do with the performance.
It may be that this function is not really shouldn't be inlined.
It should be out.
Out of line.
So it's I'm not really at all trying to suggest that these are
functions that should or should not be inlined when we actually go to
do Performance Tuning.
Those are actually me saying, hey Casey, this might be something that
might need to be in line when we when we're way down the road.
It's just a habit of me, marking it.
So yeah, so at this point, no, there's no in line is really just a
marker for me.
It has nothing to do with the performance when we get to Performance
doing, we'll talk more about that.
And looking at inline function, so so don't, don't worry too much
about that at this point in the game.
Let's see.
Are we using C or C++.
I mean, like I said, please keep questions that are generally pretty
soon, but that is technically a question about code that we have done
today or other days.
We are using C++, but I typically say that we're programming in c so
that people don't get too confused.
I guess I should be more explicit because they get confused.
Anyway, we are basically not using any C++ features.
There's one or two features in C++ that we use, operator overloading
and function overloading are really the two things.
So we are technically program.
C++, but we won't really be using 90% of the new features that are in
C++ that aren't in C.
So, I feel I do, I try not to say that we are.
I try not to say that we're using C++ too often, because really anyone
who's a serious C++ programmer would not call the things that we're
doing a C++.
We're not making inheritance hierarchies.
We're not making a bunch of templates.
So we're not using a bunch of the things that you typically see in C++
code.
So, this is mostly
C code, and you could almost compile it in C C, 99 or something, but
there's a couple features, we're using that aren't supported in c99.
So technically, it's C++, but it's only barely.
And at the end of the show, at the end of the entire game, when it's
all done.
If we wanted to Port it from C++ to see, it would be pretty trivial.
Basically, it would just be us going in and undoing our operator
overloading.
That's it and function are willing, that'd be it.
So because we're really not going to use almost anything from C++.
How did we start the code for the game?
It's all there.
So if you go to, if you want to go to handmade here at or you can go
to the video archive and basically 100% of the coding.
Been archived.
So anything.
You want to see.
You can get
Let's see.
What's so bad about including math.h.
Nothing is bad about including math.h.
So sorry, don't don't get and get the wrong idea.
You are welcome to include math.h., No problem there but I don't want
to use any of the C runtime library that we don't have to use.
So I'd like to go ahead and talk a little bit about how to get the
processor to do the floor function directly.
By telling the compiler to use intrinsics here or something similar.
So I want to go ahead and just explore that topic a little bit right
off the bat so that we don't keep dropping math.h things around.
So that's why I don't want to that's why this is a temporary thing and
I want to get rid of it.
Why not subtract 1 if input is under 0 instead of using floor.
Well, so, you know, there's other we could definitely do a bunch of
Tricks here to avoid doing the truncation, right?
We don't we don't have to do it.
The way that we're doing.
Certainly we could we could use we could check first to see if they're
in bands.
But what I'd like to do eventually is make this get canonical
position, call actually work just right with math with math so that
you can actually have very large.
It offsets or things like this and not have to do if so, I'm thinking
we can probably get it to the point where it's where it might even
just be completely branchless.
Meaning.
There's no need to test anything.
It just kind of does the canonicalization directly and that may be
faster and more efficient depending on the circumstances.
So we'll see.
So the answer is you could do, you could do this, you could implement
this, in many different ways and which way you want it to implement.
It would entirely depend on the circumstances and the requirements for
it.
So don't take this as some kind of golden standard of how
you should do it.
I was just again, this is the exploratory part of things.
So right now we're kind of not focusing on.
What is the absolute right thing to do.
Always it's more about getting things working so we can look at them
and decide what we want.
A few days ago.
You said floating Point.
Math is the most CPU, efficient.
I thought integers are faster.
Even if the CPU as a floating Point Unit.
No, generally, that is not true.
So basically floating Point math is usually, the fastest thing you can
do currently.
And the reason for that is that doing the same operation in a fixed
Point, integer requires a bunch of operations to do, whereas usually
that same set of operations could be done in one floating Point
instruction.
And typically the processor is, as fast as floating Point instructions
now, is it is
Integer instructions.
So for example, if you would like to go look at the ogner fog tables
that we mentioned before, you can go ahead and do that.
If you go ahead and look through here, SSE intrinsic Stomp.
And again, this is kind of getting way ahead of where we are.
But just to answer the question, you will notice that, that if you
look at these tables and you look at the functions for doing
operations, on packed for integer, or packed for float, you'll notice
that the instructions typically take the same amount of time.
So there is no penalty.
For using floating point, floating-point tends to be as fast in terms
of Cycles taken, but you do less operations.
So, if you want to do a floating-point multiply its one operation, to
do, the multiply, if you want to do a fixed Point multiplier.
Usually at least two operations like multiplying a shift or something.
So in general floating point is almost always faster for everything,
we're going to do and so you really don't want to use integer unless
you need the properties of an integer.
Yeah, but can I say, let me push this pretty much always faster
nowadays.
Yes, and so whoever was asking about the video on demand for this
game.
The entire thing is there.
If you click on video archive every day, every every single piece of
every line of code has been described in detail and written on the
stream.
So literally, you can watch the entire game getting made when this is
over.
1000 hours into it or how, no two years from now.
Who only knows when we'll actually have a game.
And that we've decided is done, you will be able to go watch every
single line being typed in and me explaining why we typed it in so,
which I'm pretty happy about.
That's like what I wanted.
That's why the whole reason I'm doing this is to have that complete
document.
So,
Let's see.
You've mentioned before that you want to avoid forcing the color of a
function to pack our minutes into a struct.
I'm guessing that sometimes it makes things cleaner and sometimes it
does not.
But how do you decide what way to go in any particular case?
Yes.
So basically what I would say is,
There are there are two cases for packing things into a structure.
One is because both the caller and the thing being called 10, 20.
He's operate on everything together and that is the case that I'm
trying to get to here with our exploratory coding.
The other is when only the caller wants those things.
And in the former case, it is good in the latter case.
It is bad.
So let me give you a very explicit demonstration of that.
So let's say we have something like this.
Actually, this is this is a better example.
And I'm going to change these room hints to floats.
Let's say, I have a draw, a line function.
Okay.
So, the draw line function is kind of the canonical example that I can
use to show you exactly what you do and don't want for structure
packing of our
If I'm going to call the draw function, let's say we are here in Maine
or something like this, and I'm going to call the draw a line
function, and I'm going to pass it.
Some parameters 3.0 3.5, 10.000 10.5, something like that.
I don't know what we're passing here.
It's apparently making these up if I'm going to pass that in, let's
take a look at a good structure, structure structure?
Packing, sort of compression, and a bad one.
Okay, here's
A good one.
A good one would be to say that there is something called a point and
that point has an X and Y.
Okay.
So that's going to look like this and I'm going to change the draw
line function to basically be a point p 0 and a point P1.
So now you just pass those two and essentially that all that does is
that's going to go ahead and say that whatever whatever it was is just
going to get unpacked and and we're still going to do the same.
Drock.
Also that right there.
This is a totally reasonable way to start compressing this API because
it is very likely, Almost 100% likely that whatever is going on in
Maine.
It's actually thinking about those locations on the screen as X and
y's.
That is the, actually the common case, right?
So we basically would typically have something, you know, where we'd
have something.
That looks a lot like this, and we're actually trying to
Draw lines between them.
This is actually what you probably the caller will probably be happy
to have those things bundled because that is probably what they
actually have already.
Okay.
And so when you are doing your Explorations here, that's a good thing
to explore because it will compress the code on both sides.
Main probably is doing stuff like having a list of these p-values,
right?
And they're kind of getting initialized here and maybe it's got a for
Loop, right?
Right over the index has to pee that sort of stuff.
Right blah blah blah blah blah.
Just typing in random code here, you know, and it's trying to do
something like draw a line Loop or whatever, right?
So it's trying to draw and it wants to do this sort of stuff and there
you go, right?
So this actually makes things much more efficient because previously,
the code on the other side will also would have looked kind of really
annoying.
For for the caller as well, right?
So the caller has code in there that looks like this, right?
And now they have code that looks like this and that's better for
them, better for them better for you.
That is a good compression.
Right?
And that is what I'm driving towards in the code that we were working
today.
Better for them, better for me a bad example of how to do the
compression would have been to do.
Like this and you do see stuff like this all the time, but this was be
a bad idea.
I could have done this, right?
And again, it might look like, oh no one would ever be that dumb.
They are that dumb sometimes.
But a lot of times I'm using this as the most simple example, you can
imagine a more complicated cases where it's not so obvious.
As a line people often will still make the bad decision.
So I'm just trying to use this as sort of an illustration.
So basically, if I said this right, well, I'll leave in fact.
Oh, I should leave the
that's their.
Let me leave them all there so you can see them.
This is an example of the wrong thing to do.
Now.
It's almost in like impossible to conceive of a case where it would be
better for anyone other than than the person implementing the draw
line function, right?
If this is what you do instead, because now what you've got is pretty
much everyone who draws a line probably got the points from some
separate place, right?
It's very unlikely that they actually defined things.
And in fact, in this case, it would not work at all.
Right?
Because you have this
Two points are trying to draw in a loop.
So what they basically have to do is you're forcing them to constantly
do that first.
Then assign all the crap to it that they actually need, right?
And so they basically you're forcing them into something even worse
than the worst case they had before, where they were calling it in,
passing the things individually, right?
Does that make sense?
So, basically you've turned this call into this.
Which is a disaster and your only hope of recovering from that
disaster is to basically make some kind of constructing thing here
like this.
Which which saves you from being awful.
Right?
And the best case is the thing that saves you from being awful, looks
like the other API that we already have, right, you know, you've got
something like this.
Right.
Hopefully, hopefully all this is pretty obvious.
Now that I'm saying it.
I don't know if it is or not.
A hopefully I'm hoping that it is but you can imagine us trying to
save trying to bail this API out by basically making something that
does take, the things that we want, right?
It does that does take the things in here, that we actually wanted it
to take like this, right?
And now all we've done is basically make it into the function that we
had before, right?
This was the function.
We actually had.
Originally, right?
And so that's a lot of times that's things that people do in C++ that
is just bad API design.
They'll oftentimes force you to end up doing this in a lot of
circumstances.
When really all you wanted to do was that and that's just it just
makes it hard to use.
So that is what I would say is the crucial thing to think about is
structure, packing of parameters, should make it easier for both sides
to do.
Job, if most of the time it's actually only making it easier for one
side and maybe it's making it more difficult for the other side than
that is a bad bad decision.
So, hopefully that hopefully, that clarifies that for you guys.
Let's see.
Why would we care about screen coordinates?
Isn't it just platform code?
And yes, that is a very good question and it is a very important thing
to deal with basically.
That's where I'm trying to get to.
I didn't want to just sort of, I didn't want to just plop down and go.
Well, I kind of already know how to write this.
So let me write it.
Right.
What I want to do is kind of show you how we get there.
So I wanted to start with screen coordinates because they're what you
draw in but
Actually, what we're going to get to buy, probably by the end of next
week.
Is everything operating and sort of abstract coordinate space.
That's about our game world, but we haven't quite gotten there yet,
but you can see, we're getting closer.
We're already at the point where now we're sort of not talking about
screen coordinates in a bunch of the code.
We're talking about Tyrell, of course, but these are still in pixels,
right?
Right.
These are still in pixels there, pixel offsets from the tile.
And that means that if we were to change the size of the tile, in
terms of rendering, we actually also have to change the gameplay code
and that's not very good.
And so, like I said, we will be getting to.
We're sort of, we're Levering our way up through the various stages.
Some of which you would just skip if you are an experienced game
program because, you know, but I don't want to skip those things.
I want to show you how we discover them, because a lot of times and
like,
Said I'm actually discovering new things too, about how I probably
want to do this because I never done a tile map game before I'm
actually discovering how I want structure it.
But yeah, a lot of times you'll be going in and you'll writing game
code in stuff that isn't in.
That isn't exactly the way that you've done things before.
And it's important to learn these attack skills and the strategies
that you use to discover how to write things properly because
otherwise, you'll only ever be able to write the things that I show
you how to write, right?
And that's no good.
I want you to be able to write anything you want after you done with
this.
And so what we're doing,
As we're slowly building towards that.
Are you going to make it so that the walls below the player block, the
view of the character?
The same way the character blocks, the view of the wall above the
player, possibly I guess.
So what I'm going to do is we're going to start loading bitmaps pretty
soon so we can start to see once we kind of have ourselves moving
around and and kind of working a little bit more cleaner.
What I'm going to do is I'm going to start we're going to load some
bitmaps in here and put them in to see what they look like.
And then we can sort of start to see how far behind stuff we want the
player to be.
What I want to do is make sure the player doesn't get like fully.
Skewered, like I wouldn't want to be that far because you can't see
for gameplay purposes.
But like that much, for example, should be fine.
So what we can sort of do is maybe start to think about that sort of
stuff once we have bitmaps in and we can see because that's going to
be a gameplay, decision and we want to make sure we make it correctly.
Can you explain that raw position in the other one and what they do?
Yeah, we can we can we can do a recap there.
So essentially what I what I found when I was writing the code and you
could watch, hopefully, if you watch all today's stream, you can see
how I got to each step.
Basically.
I found that in order to do a bunch of the computations that we wanted
to do.
We had to have sort of a three tiered structure.
We wanted to know what, tilemap we were on because we have a bunch of
Tau Maps.
Now, we've got four of them.
So we need to know which time a prawn.
So this is like, you know, Tom app, 0 0 or 0 1 or whatever.
And that corresponds to these tile maps, that we defined, right?
So we need to know which tile map are on.
We need to know which tile we're on in the tile map, right?
So we need to know which one of these were on, you know, are we over
here whatever?
And then, inside that tile, we need to know what our X and Y.
Offset, is in pixels, right?
Because the guy moves, he moves continuously doesn't move from tile to
tile like a turn-based game.
He moves continuously, right?
So that's the composition is raw position.
Is something that I think will go away, but temporarily all it is, is
just something.
We
Sin, that says we're on the tile map, we are.
So which tilemap Iran?
So this these are the same but then this is actually relative to the
tile map itself.
So that that is relative to this whole screen, right?
It's relative to like sort of the invisible corner of the time at the
can't see her because only half of towels visible.
So it's like it does relative to right here.
And that is basically what the outer code was using.
It was just using where it was relative, the time that it was
basically because we wrote it from just moving a rectangle around on
the screen.
And so what we're kind of seeing is we're sort of pushing away from
this and minimizing it down to the point where I think on the next
dream will just be able to do is canonical positions in here for the
player.
And we'll just get rid of rope additionals.
Go away entirely, but that's we haven't quite made that step yet.
We are currently checking the players left and right for moving into a
non empty tile, wouldn't it be better to only check the side of the
player that it is moving to?
Yes.
That is well.
Okay, so it depends what you mean by better.
I would prefer it if you said more efficient, okay, because at the
moment with the way, our code is structured, it would be more
efficient to do so.
Meaning it set of checking this three times.
We could just check twice, right?
We check player pose and left or player pose and right.
But I don't think it would be better and that's why I didn't do it.
The reason that I don't think it would be better is because the it
doesn't change the behavior of the code at all.
right, it'll
Exactly the same thing.
It just doesn't call one function.
It doesn't need to call in certain cases and, you know, for and
obviously it would only call just it.
We could call none of these.
If the player isn't moving at all.
If D player X and D player.
Why were both 0?
We would have to kill any of them.
But it wouldn't be better.
And the reason that it wouldn't be better, is because right now we're
doing exploration code to figure out how our game should be
architected anything you do.
That's efficiency based that involves complicating the code, right?
Because now there's a bunch of ifs and more paths through here.
Anything you do that, complicates the code just introduce the
possibility of bugs without actually giving us any benefit because we
don't care how fast this code runs.
We're never going to ship any of this code to the, to the, to the
user.
So the only time
I'm you would want to do that stuff.
Is if we think that it's going to be structurally interesting and that
we need to know about it so that when we architect things we can
architect them around that.
Now I know that I'm never going to have an architecture concern with
that.
I can always stick and if in there and it's not going to be an issue,
so I actually don't think it would be better to do it.
I just think of you more efficient.
And right now we don't care about efficiency.
We only care about efficiency insofar as we think it will affect our
architecture.
And so if we thought that was going to be an architecture concern,
then we might want to explore it but even so we probably
We wouldn't want explore it.
Now, exploring the efficiency of the architecture is probably
something we should do.
Once we know that the architecture is at the point where it can
express the game and then we can start thinking about how to express
the game efficiently, but it's probably very premature.
Now to be thinking about efficiency.
Why not have a single set of coordinates for the player that map's the
player to a world position.
You could identify the correct time app easily and the correct tile in
the tile map and you won't have to deal with two sets of coordinates.
So I'm not sure exactly what you mean by that, but I can tell you
actually why I don't want to do one of the things that you might be
referring to.
So one thing you might ask is why not just have an X and A Y just a
floating Point X and Y and that's everything we need.
The reason for that is for float is because of floating-point
precision, so
What do I, what do I?
This is jumping the gun a little bit but just for the sake of
answering the question, I'll do a cursory explanation of it now and we
can talk a little bit more about it later.
All right, what did I tell you about floating point when we talked
about floating Point briefly earlier, on in the Stream.
I said that it's got a bunch of stuff in terms of exponent, right?
It's got an exponent and a sign bit, right?
It's got a up in the top of it.
Right?
But then it basically has 24 bits of precision.
Okay, it's got
24 bits to represent the number now, what do we know about 24 bits of
precision?
Right.
Well, one thing I know is that colors, right?
I'm just going through the whole thing.
Your of my how I think about these things colors on the display are
8-bit at least, right?
We are always going to be targeting at least an 8-bit display in terms
of the number of colors that we, at the number of Shades, we have
right of Any Given gun, any given channel.
So, if we have the red Channel, there's eight bits of red, right?
That means that for a given pixel value, right?
For if these are pixels.
So these are two pixels next to each other.
This is the pixel, right?
And this is a pixel.
Wow.
I can't seem to draw with this mouse today.
Here we go.
Oh, yeah.
So if I have two pixels, right?
And my guy is moving between them, is moving in this direction.
And one of these pixels is full on.
So, this value is 255, and this is 0.
So, the guy is here.
He's fully, he's, you know, he's, he's white.
Let's say he's a white rectangle for some reason.
He's here, I have to
Hundred and fifty six steps that I can do to show him.
Move from here to here, right?
I can slowly.
If he was slowly if he's moving infinitely slowly, if it's well, not
really, but very, very slowly.
This would go up to 1.
This would go to 254, right?
This would go to to this would go to 253, right?
And I'm just, if you imagine him sort of slowly occupying the new
pixel, right?
So he's moving across and this new pixels getting brighter with the
guys color and this one is dimming out to whatever.
Ever it is.
He's a one pixel guy and he's occupied here.
Right?
Because we haven't talked about this yet.
So I say jumping the gun, but you could imagine that the guy is one
pixel wide, right?
And he's, he's occupying a space in between the two pixels.
Right?
And I want to draw that.
Well, what I can do is just see how much of of this pixel he occupies
and set it to the number between 0 and 255.
That's what percentage of it.
So, he's occupying half of it.
It's 127 or whatever, right?
Because occupying quarter of it.
It's 63 that sort of thing, right?
And then the other one is the inverse of that.
The other one is however much cheese is on that side.
So it was 127 this side be 128, right?
That sort of thing.
Whatever you want to do.
Well over 127, depending how you want to do.
You're rounding, blah, blah blah.
You get the point anyway, so that tells me that I have 8 Bits of
fractional, pixel Precision that I need to represent in the position
of this guy.
At least, I need at least eight bits of fractional, Precision of where
the guy is.
He has to have 1 over.
256, right of a pixels worth of motion in order to get this thing
accurate, right?
So now we're down to 16 bits to represent where the guy is in pixels
because I've got fractional 8 Bits of precision to represent where he
is in between the pixels just as a bare minimum.
Will 16 bits is only 65536.
Right.
That's the most.
Can store.
That's how fast that.
That's, that's the limit.
It can store that many discrete values, right?
It's negative 32 768.
232 767, right?
Or whatever.
The I don't even know.
That's what that right.
That's the range.
Then it can store.
In pixels.
Okay, so if that's the range in pixels of the guy, I've got 1920 by
1080, is my screen resolution at minimum.
What do when we run on 4K displays in the future.
Maybe we want less worth that.
It's going to be more.
Okay, 1920 divided into that, right?
Divided into seven, five, five, three six.
Let's do that math, right?
Let's do that at 755 36 divided by 19, 20, 30, 40 K.
That means the maximum width.
In tile maps that fit on a screen of our game.
If we used one floating Point, coordinate, as is being suggested
potentially, don't know what the guy was suggesting.
We could only have 34 screens across before we run out a floating
Point accuracy to properly.
Represent a sub pixel guys location.
That's it.
Not acceptable.
What I want to be able to do is I want to be able to have essentially
for all intents and purposes.
It infinite size world.
I want to be able to have 50,000 screens in any direction.
If I want to do, I want to be able to make a game so big that there's
no player who can ever even walk from one in the end of it, from one
end to the other.
And I want to know that I can do that.
So, that way, if you want to make giant game worlds we can write.
So this is unacceptable, one coordinate is totally unacceptable.
So you have two decisions, right?
You could either go to doubles, right?
You go to 64-bit, right?
So that you'd have more bits of precision in your floating point
value.
And then you could use still just a single X and Y, so you could use
doubles and have a single X & Y.
That's one solution, the solution.
I am choosing instead is to have an integer that says where you are in
the world, at least one of them.
And then a floating point x and a y that says where you are relatively
in that part of the world, right?
So I think eventually we're going to use something very close to this,
but
What we may do.
And I'm not saying we will, we're going to have to decide what we may
do, is get rid of one of these.
So we'll have one integer coordinate that says, what tile were on and
which tile we're on is, you know, that will allow us to have four
billion tiles by four billion tiles as the as the size of the world,
right?
That we may do and then the tile map that you're in, we'll just be
looked up on that thing and then the X
In the Y will be where you are inside the tile.
That's probably what we'll end up doing, just because it's easy and
allows a world to be big enough that we for this game.
We will never have a player who could ever walk between them anyway,
right?
so,
That will do.
Hopefully that answered that question.
Let's see.
Following about in line.
Are there any consequences of using it in early development?
IE making it harder to debug?
No, there are no downsides to using and development, because almost
every compiler that I'm aware of has a compile switch that turns off
in lining.
So kind of convenient, right?
That's, that's, that's really why you don't have to worry about it.
If for some reason, it was causing a problem.
Basically, /.
You can see it right here, /o.
Zero means don't do any inline expansions.
I believe that's what that would actually do for us is to turn it off
entirely.
And so if for some reason we find the compiler doing things that's
making it hard for us to debug our inline functions, because it's in
lining them.
We just hit that switch.
And I don't even, we may even have that switch in there already.
I don't know if we do or not.
No, we don't but that, that would be all you have to do.
So most compilers do not.
You don't have to worry about the inlining stuff because it's just,
it's totally
You can turn off completely.
Wouldn't it be better to call the X and Y variables and canonical?
Start our relative accent?
I relative why?
Yeah.
Oh, that's Daniel Ben macdui.
I don't know.
Okay, that's cool.
Daniel.
Ben.
Macdui is asking question.
He if you don't actually know, he's the guy who does this game, which
is pretty darn awesome.
This Ernesto RPG.
This game is really, really cool.
And you should check it out if you haven't, and I'm very delighted to
see him on this stream music.
Of mine.
So this.
Yeah, he's doing this game right now, which I highly recommend, I
would recommend that you buy it except you can't, it's not out yet.
But when it is, it'll be very good.
Anyway, he's asking whether we should use a better name for these.
And I would agree with that sort of basically, like, I would agree
with calling these tile relative X and tile relative.
Why most of the time, my only concern is in the verbose - of them.
Because of the of the amount of time they're going to get used.
But, you know, I'm not averse to just throwing it in there for now and
seeing how that goes because I totally agree that it is better.
Oops.
It is a, it is a much better and clearer thing for people who are
reading the code.
So, yeah, I definitely agree with that.
Most of the time I do like for both names but once in a while, I
shorten them and so I'm not sure if that's one.
to a certain but I'm totally down with starting with them over votes
name and then, shortening, it only if I decide that it
To reverse.
The other thing I could do is change it just to Rel, you know, like
that.
I could also end.
We could even do R LX R LLY in the future instead of tile Rolex and
then it would at least, you know, it was relative and you'd look up to
see what it was relative to.
So that's good, too.
So, yes, thank you for that suggestion.
I actually that is probably what I should have done because normally I
like to start from a more descriptive name and reduce it.
If I find that it's not
You know, that it.
I like to start with more verbose things than if either.
Annoying me.
I get rid of the robustness rather than going the other way around.
So yeah.
Okay, so the game will happen on whole screens without any scrolling
or camera movement.
Um,
So, for the most part, yes, I don't necessarily know that there won't
be any scrolling or camera movement.
But I would like the game to basically be screens that the player
looks at and understands, as a screen, that's kind of a requirement of
the game design.
Now, whether we want to move the camera a little in there, for flavor.
I don't know.
So I'm not going to promise that we won't have scrolling or camera
movement, but we're not going to have
But we are going to have single individual screen for the player
thinks about, and that's a core tenet of the game.
Let's see.
Doesn't plus plus I create a stall on the CPU.
I do not know what you're referring to.
Sorry.
Hmm.
Yeah, I don't know.
I don't know what that means.
Well, there are a lot of questions and we're over time.
I think, folks, we're going to have to probably do more questions
tomorrow because we're way over time already.
Yeah, let me see if there's any other ones here.
Let's see.
Okay, I think so.
There probably is one or two other questions in here.
Looking at all the questions just I trying to brief the scan them,
that probably should I should try to answer.
So let's do five more minutes of these questions that are already out
there.
Let's see.
Okay, so I guess, let's let's take, let's take this one, which is,
excuse me.
I will say, could you explain how pointers references are working or
what you use them for and why I will simply take a minute to say these
are explained in quite a bit of detail earlier in the Stream.
So if you want to answer, if you have questions about stuff like that,
what?
I, well actually, if you go to handmade hero dot org, there's this
And forms link, I would highly recommend going to the episode guide
that's under there.
And going through these intro to see on Windows.
Courses, I'd go through those.
They show you what pointers do.
And why you care about them references, are just a different word for
pointer.
There.
There, a semantic thing.
They don't have any there no difference in terms of what they actually
do.
So I wouldn't really think of those different.
A reference is just a different syntactic way of talking about a
pointer.
Was there ever a point your career where you use these unfortunate
structure packing practices, or was it always a thing where you just
saw other people doing it and wondered who did this to you?
So I don't know.
I think mostly probably what I was more guilty of earlier on in time
was not ever packing.
Things that should have been packed and having them be able to
sprawling.
That makes sense.
Enemy maps.
That disaster code.
Looks like win32 API code.
Now, what, which code looks like with.
To API code.
Are you talking about, you talking about this code right here, or I
don't know, tell me which code you're talking about.
We can take a look at it.
Although, again, most of the stuff.
We're already getting a lot cleaner.
So things are actually looking much better than they were but, you
know, obviously this sort of stuff is kind of crazy and we gotta work
on that a little bit.
But if you had a particular objection to the code, let me know.
And let's see.
So what else have I got here?
Can I scroll up words?
I need to be able to scroll up words here on my thing.
And I can't actually
Ali.
Do that, of course because because well, who knows why?
Because how do I scroll up words?
There we go.
Do I have any other questions?
I think we're mostly done with the questions.
Yeah.
Alright, so I think that's about it.
Let me just know which the
Let me just no enemy Mouse which, which code you think is win32 API
code looking like and I can address that and say whether it's
something that we would be.
So,
Let's see, enemy Mouse.
Enemy Mouse.
Oh, the example of bad packet.
Okay.
Got it.
So enemy Mouse.
We was talking about that was talking about the example.
I did with the line where you had to pack them.
Okay, that makes much more sense.
Yes, exactly.
It does look like
22, code, win32 makes you pack things into structures.
A lot of times for no reason, that is very, very, very common.
So yeah.
Yeah, it's a problem.
So, okay.
Just want to make sure there wasn't a question about code cleanliness
and the other part of things.
So, I could say, either, yes, it should be cleaner.
No, it shouldn't be.
So it was saying handmade here at www.fairwork.gov.au.?
Actually.
No, so I should have to check.
I'll check, I'll go check that.
I didn't realize that www.h, a maid here at Edinburgh wasn't working.
So I have to go find out why it's not working because you
Are right.
It does not appear to be working.
I will check it out.
All right, make a note on my list here.
Www doesn't work.
Ugh, okay.
There we go.
Okay.
Thank you, everyone for joining me for another week of handmade hero.
I think that we are in excellent shape.
Now.
We are starting to see some game architecture stuff.
Take shape.
I think next week will sort of be in that place where I starting to
really kind of Leverage things and start to see kind of cool things
start to happen.
Again.
This week was, I don't know what it was five hours of programming
total, something like that and that's five hours of programming with.
Explanation because it's only been five days.
And we already got to see sort of all this cool stuff starts to happen
with with how, you know, we can sort of see exactly how to structure
stuff and have a tile map that we move around on that sort of thing.
So again doing stuff from scratch, even when you're explaining, it is
really not that long.
I mean, it does seem longer because we wait a day to do each hour of
programming, but it's really just doesn't take that long making things
from scratch is actually very quick if it's the thing that you've
practiced in your life, right?
If all you ever do is practice using other
As libraries other people's engines and obviously you will be faster
at that, but that's because that's what you practice doing.
But if you practice making things from scratch, actually just really
doesn't take that long.
It's a lot more fun.
It's a lot more rewarding.
It's not more interesting and you're liable to find things that other
people never did.
You're liable to go.
Oh, what about these cool things that I could do?
Now that I'm writing this stuff myself, that no one's tried before in
Amazon before, it's very interesting.
So, you know, yeah, engines and libraries are good.
They save you time a certain sense in certain cases certainly and and
that's always a good thing.
But
It's also interesting to sort of look at just how fun and and
efficient making things from scratch.
Can be because it really doesn't take that long to make things
shortly.
And again, this that keeps sort of being true from what I've seen on
the stream is like it.
Just take, you know, we'll do one week is five hours or something in
that five hours will do just so much stuff.
And if you stack those up and think about the fact, there's 40
programming hours in a normal week or something.
You just get you get many weeks of handmade here all packed in this
one single working week.
There's just a lot you can accomplish
In making your own engine or making your own, whatever it is that you
may want to make make your own component to something.
Make your own Unity extension, make your own whatever.
So, thank you so much for joining me.
It has been a pleasure as it always is, if you would like to get x to
the source code, you can pre-order the game on handmade hero.
Dot-org, just put handmade here at organ there, and click on the
pre-order button.
That will give you a download link.
You can follow along every day and get the source code or just play
around with it.
Do whatever you want want to do to sort of test out your own ideas.
If you want to support the video series, we do have a patreon that you
can contribute to over there.
And if you would like more resources for studying handmade hero, you
can click on this news and forums link and it's got all kinds of
stuff.
If you want to know about porting.
If you go to the code resources page, lot of ports on there.
If you want to ask questions, go to the code discussions, page, got
the episode guide, if you want to catch up on past serious, all kinds
of good stuff.
And of course, the schedule for the week.
Is always posted here on the main page.
So I hope to see you next Monday.
When we were back in our normal time slot, 8 p.m.
Pacific Standard time, and we will be working on sort of continuing.
That game, our children getting ourselves up into an actual game.
Maybe we'll be trying to do some getting some enemies in there that we
can fight and that sort of stuff.
Just sort of started building out again, an exploratory version of the
game so that we can start to figure out what we need in our game
engine for architecture.
So please join me for that.
I would love to see you here next week, and thank you for joining me
today.
It has been a pleasure.
See you later everybody.