Okay, everyone, welcome to handmade hero.
J-31.
This of course, is the show where we program an entire game from
scratch live on the air.
And of course, the reason that we're doing this is because I think
it's just a good idea for everyone to have the experience, at least,
once of ready a game from start to finish.
So they know how absolutely everything works in the entire pipeline of
a game.
It's very empowering to do this because it means that you never have
to be restricted Again by something that someone else wrote you can
always
Choose to go write some portion of an engine or some portion of a
library, or self, or even the whole thing yourself, if you were so
inclined.
But it also means that even if you're just using things, that other
people wrote to build your games, you will be able to know how those
things themselves work.
And so, that actually makes you a much bigger programmer, better
programmers.
Well, because you can do things like understand the performance
implications of the things that you're doing and that can help you
even when you're using like an engine that somebody else wrote.
So I think it's a great thing to do and I think people have been
enjoying it.
I have certainly been enjoying it.
So with that in mind, I think it's a good time to go ahead and get
started here.
Let's see.
If you are following along with the source code at home, which you can
do on handy here at Orange.
If you go to the pre-order button, if you pre-ordered it, there should
be a link that came to your email that you can click on and download
the source code.
I update it every night after we finish coding and you can open up
that link and you can download a zip file inside that zip file.
There's a zip like a sub zip for every day since we're on day 31.
You want to start with day 30, you always start at the previous day.
So if you unzip day 30 into a directory and start coding in that
directory, you will be exactly where I am today when I am started
because that is a source code that I am starting with, as well.
Now, where we were when we stopped last week is, we were actually at
the point where we had our little yellow rectangle that we were
basically using as a test for the player, moving around a little gray
and white.
Angle sort of Blobby tilemap placeholder and we were just verifying
that we could do some very basic things like move from around the tile
map.
We could have doors that he could walk out of that sort of thing and
you know, nothing nothing particularly fancy.
But again, what we're trying to do here is explore the code a little
bit and basically figure out what sorts of things were going to want
from our engine so that it supports the game that we're trying to make
cleanly and doesn't involve doesn't basically we want to basically
avoid going in writing an
And without any knowledge of what we want it to do because we'll
probably liable to make a lot of bad decisions.
So what we're basically doing here is trying to get down to what are
the exact things that we need the engine to do and how we want them to
how we want it to do them so that we can then go implement the engine
and do it in a nice clean concise way that does exactly what we want.
And that will be very convenient for us to use.
So, what we've gotten ourselves to at this point is a very basic thing
where we can sort of do what we want to do.
Tell map and we can sort of check for collisions and do that sort of
stuff in a very basic way, but there's a bunch of things that we
should probably talk about here.
And there's also a bunch of things that I want to sort of bring to
your attention about it before I do that.
I do want to talk about one thing briefly because it had come up a
little bit on the forums over the weekend.
And I just wanted to sort of clarify, some stuff for people just in
case they were concerned about this.
So, obviously I've said before that, like the design is not really
part of the
Stream.
So we're going to be making a design that I designed, and that's just
the way it goes.
I'm not a game designer.
So I'm not going to teach game design on stream.
I couldn't even if I wanted to.
So, basically, the design is just the design that I have and that's
what we're going to do.
But some people were concerned about the fact that I was saying that
my design calls for the game to basically be a lock screen.
And you walk off just like the old Legend of Zelda now, I could defend
my design decision to do that.
I think very well, I think about design things a lot.
I'm
I'm not just an arbitrary person.
And for people who think that that is not a good idea.
I have plenty of things.
I would say to challenge the notion that you want to have a scrolling
backdrop.
But like I said, the design is not up for discussion.
So I don't really want to get into that.
But what I do want to do is say, if you are concerned because you
would like to see how to implement scrolling because maybe you have a
game idea that would involve a scrolling backdrop that is totally
valid.
And so, what I would like to do as well while we're doing this.
Just show how there really is.
No difference between these two things.
And that I'm just making basically a game design decision to keep this
locked, but I will, I will be able to show you.
I think in just a couple days after we sort of finish our town map
exploration here.
I'll be able to show you how to basically just turn on scrolling in a
sense, because scrolling, if you do, the things that I want to do with
the tile map, if you support all the things that I want to support,
you get scrolling for free.
I just won't be turning it on because I don't want it.
Like, in the
Game, but it's actually for free.
And the reason that I say that is because I don't want them to ever be
any loading screens or hiccups when you're playing this game.
And what that means is that when you move, you know, when the little
yellow rectangle moves off the side of the screen, so if he comes down
here to the bottom and he moves off the bottom of the screen onto the
next screen, I, there's not allowed to be like a pause there.
Anything it has to immediately show, whatever that bottom screen is,
right?
And so I'm assuming that our engine will always be able to draw.
Basically, the screens that are all, you know, the eight, the the
eight screens that surround the one screen there were on it, would
always be able to draw those at a moment's notice.
Write it like instantaneously on the next frame.
So if you wanted scrolling, it wouldn't really be a problem because
all you would have to do is actually just go ahead and move the camera
over and ask it to draw, you know, part of that one tile map in part
of the other tile map.
You could have a smooth smooth, scrolling game with no problem.
So, I don't want anyone to think that our engine will be any cheesier
because of the fact that's not supporting scrolling.
We will be doing.
No cheese is achieves, free zone.
But, but yeah, I just don't want scrolling because there's a number of
things in the game is on that.
I want that are specifically prohibited.
If you have scrolling, they won't work as well.
And so I'm not going to do scrolling, but I will show you basically
how to turn that on, because if
if if for some reason you're concerned about the technology, we are
totally writing an engine that would have been able to scroll if it
wanted to.
I just don't want it to.
So with that out of the way.
Let's talk about the next thing that I wanted to sort of get into
here.
So what I want to talk about now is I want to start talking about, you
notice.
We've got this to do in our code which was math functions.
I used a floor, F function.
And previously I used another function, I use sign to make the sine
wave that we output.
It, I don't know if you remember that, but basically up here at the
top of handmade dot CPP, when we were using our test sine wave.
I was calling sign F to compute the sine of a value and that sort of
thing as well.
So really I would like to finish up doing the tile map stuff right
now, you know, Monday Tuesday Wednesday, but really I think these
things are sort of going to go hand-in-hand a little bit.
And so what I would sort of like to do is just pause for a minute and
talk about kind of all of the stuff that we're going to have to deal
with and sort of the the sort of the math function stuff as well.
And how we're going to deal with that stuff because we're kind of
getting into a part here, where we're going to have to have
Math functions are we're going to have to have a bunch of different
things we want to do.
So.
Here's the status.
First of all, math.h is the C runtime, libraries include file.
So this is saying that ships with any version of C, right?
It is the C runtime Library include file.
That has a bunch of functions that you would need.
If you're going to be doing basic floating-point, mathematics
operations.
So, I don't know if I can find a simple.
I don't know if I can find a simple reference right here.
Yeah.
So this is an example of the functions that are in there.
Right?
And they look like, the kind of things that you had in high school
trigonometry class.
Assuming that you have had high school trigonometry class.
I don't know if there's some youngsters on the stream then they may
not have, but
These are the things that you would expect, from their cosine, sine
tangent Arc, cosine of arcsine arctangent, an arc tangent to now,
arctangent, to is a better way of computing arctangent.
And we'll talk about that, a little later in the Stream.
But basically, you, this is the inverse of the cosine, inverse of the
sine inverse of the tangent inverse of the tangent, a different way.
These are basically two things that you recognize from trig, and we
don't care about the hyperbolic ones.
But again, they're just there.
Same as what you would find in Mathematica textbooks.
Similarly, coming in here, same sort of stuff you're used to, in your
high school math.
You can exponentiate things.
You can take the log base 2, you know, log based.
I don't know what these other ones are here.
Log base plus 1.
Okay.
So there's a shorthand for other ways of putting the logarithms for,
you know, for convenience.
There's the mod which is basically the way of breaking a fractional
number into its hole part and it's fractional part, you know, raising
something to a power, taking the square.
Route, all of these things should be pretty familiar to you.
Now things that won't necessarily be familiar to you.
Are these guys here and these are some discrete math kinds of
functions.
These are the ceiling and the floor functions like there is talking
about before the one that we use that floor.
F, that I was using to sort of like move things to the next lower.
Whole number on a number line.
Those functions are discrete math functions, to some degree and are
not the kinds of things that you often talk about in high school math.
Now, maybe some good good high school.
In good high school math.
Talk about them.
But certainly, I don't think mine did.
So these are some that you may not be familiar with, but a lot of them
are very straightforward.
Guy said, ceiling and floor are two that we were interested in.
And we talked about on the previous dreams.
But basically those are all sort of implemented in there as well.
Now the interesting thing about this math.h.
This method H file is, these are all functions that would actually be
implemented actually in the C runtime Library, calling a function.
So, for example, if we actually step in here, I guess I can because I
already had it running.
If I actually step in here, 20,
Is that function not getting called it off?
That's odd, don't you think that's a little odd.
Why is that getting what?
How is that possible?
What am I missing folks?
Did not hook, just probably didn't reload the pdb.
As always, we're gonna have to fix that.
I have a, I have a plan for fixing that, by the way, we'll talk about
that separate msv.
See Visual Studio.
Oh, he's always The Thorn, The Perennial thorn in our side.
Unfortunately.
All right.
So basically this floor function, if we go ahead and right-click and
go to disassembly, right?
We can see what it's actually doing here.
It's going to go ahead and it's going to actually call this floor.
F function, right, which is in the C runtime library, and I don't
actually know if I have that in.
It doesn't look like this is in this stall.
The machine.
It can't seem to find it.
So I'm not exactly sure if we've even got it on here.
But point being, this is actually the see runtimes function in here
that does the floor.
And you can see that it does, a bunch of stuff, right?
It's doing things doing, things doing things, doing things doing
things.
So on, right?
And that's to do this floor function, which you know, is pretty
expensive.
You look at, look at all this stuff.
It's doing tons and tons and tons and tons of stuff, and then it gets
out here to actually get the result.
So that's, that's just a lot of work for this floor function.
And remember, the only thing that we needed this floor function to do.
The only thing that we wanted to do was basically produce the next
lower whole number on the number line, right?
The only thing that we actually wanted it to do on here, right?
Was if we were looking at the the number
line like this, right?
All he wanted to do, we wanted that floor function to just drop us
down to the next one, right?
That's all we wanted to do.
And so what what's kind of curious about this is if he interesting to
know, right?
Is there some way that we can go ahead and do that in a more efficient
way that's just like simpler and doesn't involve using the C runtime
library and you know, who knows what it's doing in there, right?
Doing a bunch of stuff to comply with the c standard essentially, but
we don't actually know if we need to comply with the sea.
Enter because there may be ways that we can do stuff entirely without
that.
Right?
And so, one of the things that I kind of want to point out here is
actually, I don't know if I need to open the Intel architecture,
reference mail, just yet.
What are these?
I want to point out here.
Is that the Intel chips, nowadays, anything, that's going to be in a
machine that we are going to be shipping on is going to have sse2,
right?
That's basically an instruction set that, you know, for those of you
who don't know, basically,
The the processors on the the Intel processors that are in all of the
machines, like the one that I'm working on now or anything that runs
Windows pretty much and anything that runs Mac OS, X, and actually, I
guess for that matter, the things that are in that are in the
PlayStation 4 and the Xbox One, for example, they are all running
Intel based architectures and those Intel architectures, get revised
over time to have new instruction sets in them.
So the instruction set that were on right now is called.
64 and x64 is basically a 64-bit version of the old x86 instruction
set.
It was made, I Believe by AMD, and that's why it's sometimes called
amd64.
And basically it's just the basic set of instructions that we use to
run code.
That that is what our code gets compiled down to its what when we
actually run this stuff and I drop in here and I go to disassembly.
These are x64 instructions.
That's what they are.
Right?
So like move.
SS and call and CB teacher and a buh bah, blah, blah blah.
Those are all x, 64 instructions, but not every processor has the same
set of x64 instructions because as the processors, get revised over
time, they add new instructions, right?
And so they come up with names for these like there's SSE, which is
one set of instructions that all the chips will have nowadays sse2,
right?
There's even SS
You know, for there's a v x.
So they keep, oops, they keep adding new and new newer and newer
instructions which basically add to the set of instructions that you
can call and oftentimes also add registers.
So they add more registers of the processor that you can access.
Right?
And so basically any CPU that we're going to Target is going to have
sse2 like pretty much everything that we could possibly hope to run on
is going to have sse2 at least.
I don't remember exactly when it was introduced but it's been around a
long, long time.
And so really all of the sse2 instructions.
I don't know if we've got a good list of them here.
We want to.
I want to get a better list of these.
Let me take a look sse2 msdn.
There we go.
So if you take a look here at these at msdn there, if you search for
msdn in S SE and se2, they've got a little overview here where you can
kind of
Pop down by various types of instructions.
As the cmx was another one, a very old one, by the way of instruction
addition, that was on x86 as well.
So these are the different instruction sets and, and sort of the
instructions that we have available.
And for sse2, if I remember correctly.
There's a bunch of instructions that actually allow you to do things.
There's a number of things that you are able to do with these
instructions.
They will probably let us
Just go ahead and do our own floor in a much simpler way.
Now.
Like I said, I promised I would do everything from scratch on the
Stream, So that includes me having to dig through documentation, 's
because I never remember what the intrinsics are for stuff.
I don't do some deprogramming often enough.
I always have to go look them up.
Whereas if you're a super Cindy, if you do somebody every day, you
just kind of know what they all are.
So SSE instructions.
I always have to look up but
I believe this is where I typically go first, right?
I go to the msdn page because I've got them kind of listed by what
type of instruction, they are.
It's a little janky.
I don't love these Docks, but I don't know of a better set of docks
where they're listed by type.
Unfortunately.
Sometimes I look at the Intel architecture reference manual which also
has some sections like that but it's yeah, it's a it's a little ugly,
it's true.
But anyway, if you go in here, you can click on things that talk about
sort of What kinds of operations there are.
And you can see, like I'm going to click on arithmetic operations,
right?
And I'm going to make this a little bigger, so we can actually see it
in its entirety.
So you can kind of see what all the instructions are that the
processor has.
It's got, you know, add subtract multiply square root reciprocal, the
reciprocal square root min-max, right?
So it's got all these sorts of things.
And so if you know that you have these then obviously you can
right things that use them.
So the question is, is there.
Thing in here that we could use centrally to floor, you know, to floor
are our number.
And the thing that I can't quite remember is whether or not?
I don't remember if you have to go to sse4 first, which I don't know
if we want to necessarily be using, if you have to go to sse4 before,
you can reliably do a floor in one instruction or not.
I think maybe you have to or not.
I'm not entirely certain
Anyway, point being what we want to do is we want to look up in here,
how we would do, say the floor instruction by using these intrinsics
and if we and similarly like figure out how we would do sign and the
other sort of things we need to do using these intrinsics.
And then what we'd want to do is we want to come back in here and
instead of using math.h., What we'd want to do is sort of introduce
our own math.h.
If that makes sense.
We'd want to introduce our own sort of
Utility layer that for every platform that we care about, which is
basically.
It's basically just going to be armed neon, which is the instruction
set for like mobile devices and and sse2 for the most part or maybe
out if we decide to do something higher than that SSE for some like
that, some version of x64 will basically make a thing.
That for each of the operations that we care about like floor and like
sign, we will go ahead and make our own implementation where we know
what it does and we know that it does only as much as we need it to
do, right?
And that it uses the most efficient processor operations to do that.
And so that is where I would like to get to on that.
I don't know that we want to necessarily do that right now, but that
is what we have to sort of drive towards.
So that's one thing to think about and by the way, I should also point
out that sometimes
And I don't actually know if we can make this happen.
Sometimes, you can also get the compiler to do some of this work for
you.
If you don't want to do all the stuff that I just said, if you
basically turn on optimizations, so, you know, for example, we are
doing something where we have all of our optimizations turned off.
We have minus OD on our bill blind.
So basically, we've turned off optimizations entirely.
There's no optimizations that are allowed to happen.
And so, one thing that we could do is if we turn on optimizations,
right?
If
If I say - 02 I think is I'm not sure I actually remember what the
with the highest level as we can double check.
But if I turn that on then it'll actually compile it with
optimizations and one of the things.
Well, so the first thing you notice is that I can't even set a
breakpoint here because this function is almost certainly gotten in
lined.
So what I have to do is I have to actually go find where that floor
real.
32, 232 actually happens.
And I need to actually look there to see what the actual code does.
So,
Going into the disassembly and see if it does anything smarter.
Now.
I see it's still does floor and there's nothing useful.
We can do about that.
So I
And I don't sometimes you can set optimization levels where it says,
don't worry about floating-point, consistency and stuff like this.
I don't know.
I'm not sure if there's a way to do it.
Let's let's just double check to see if there's a way msv.
See, because I want to just point this out for people.
If they can some on the stream will probably know fast for f.
That's why I know if there's any way to tell it, tell it to do a
better better version of that.
Why did it?
Link me here.
I'm not sure.
Yeah.
Yeah, well, I don't know.
We'll take a look.
If someone on the street knows we can talk about in the qfa, in the
answer, in the Q&A.
But basically, like sometimes for certain intrinsics, there are
compiler switches.
You can pass or ways that you can tell it that you want to use that
function.
Like, sometimes there's like a way to do it like a built-in floor, F,
you'd call like a separate function, and, and it would know that it
could do something that wasn't quite as direct or quite as
comprehensive.
For example.
Yeah, so, okay.
So this is perfect.
This is what I was looking looking at here.
Flora has an implication that uses streaming Cindy extensions to which
is what we're talking about, right for information restrictions about
using the SEC to complacency set SSE to enable, right?
Okay.
So basically enables or disables use Distributing sentence in the CRT
math, routines.
Grocery want to actually do this in lined.
If you use.
Oh, I generate in terms of function compiler option to compile the
project.
It may appear that has an effect.
It's
Audit the authorities of trees to replace CRT calls.
That's good.
That's what we wanted.
So let's go ahead and try doing that.
/.
Oh, I as well, just to see whether we can get it.
I just want to see if I can show you this.
I apologize.
It takes a while but I really kind of wanted people to see the
compiler doing two different things here because they're there usually
is a way to make it do it.
Oh,
No, why are you still doing in that?
Well, I don't know how to make the compiler suddenly do it.
Anyway point being sometimes, maybe I'll you know what?
I could try calling something else.
I suppose.
I don't know.
Sometimes you can get the compiler to do smart things.
We can basically say, hey look.
I know that maybe it's not completely compliant with the see spec or
something, but I would like you to go ahead and do it.
Maybe I have to enable sse2 but we're in x64 mode.
So it knows that I don't know.
I do not know anyway.
We'll have to ignore that for now.
But please if someone on the stream happens to know how to get the
compiler to do some clever stuff.
Please mention the Q and A so I can show it basically.
Sometimes you can get that, you can convince the compiler to start
doing some of that stuff for you.
I tend to not rely on that too much only because, like, you just saw I
never remember compile switches or even if I do, I don't necessarily
know that the compiler can be trusted to do them and so on.
So I tend to just like to take that out of the equation and actually
have my own file where those will actually be called.
So, you know, essentially what I want to do is start to think about
these things like floor, real 32 and round real 32.
These sorts of things.
What I want to do is I want these functions to
Ventually kind of migrate out into a math file, where we can sort of,
you know, make the platform specific versions that will do the right
thing.
And so I'm not sure exactly what I want to call that maybe I'll call
that handmade intrinsics dot h for example, and we will just move
those into there for now.
And really what we want to be able to do here is we want to be able to
do more efficient stuff, using whatever is available.
On the platform for each of these particular instructions.
So that's something that we have to deal with.
And we're going to have to deal with.
In a number of places.
We're going to have to deal with it because we're going to need a sine
function as well.
We're going to need a cosine function, right?
We're going to need a bunch of these things that you'll see over time.
We're going to need an atan to
Cancers usually y over X, isn't it though?
Sorry, just wanted to sorry to talk out loud here.
Sometimes I get in the middle of something and I'm like wait a minute.
8 + 2 is usually not the way that I just typed it in.
But you know, you know how it is.
Hello.
It's usually written y y over X.
Yeah, that's what I thought.
Keep that same.
Anyway, so point being if you if you look at what the sort of stuff
that we're going to have to do here is we're probably going to have to
spend a fair bit of time going through.
Here and in talking about how this stuff works at a lower level and
implementing them based on the each and each particular processor and
so on.
But for now, what we're essentially going to do is we're going to say,
you know, what, and I can, eliminate these two dues for now by
basically making just a giant to do, which says convert all of these
to platform, efficient versions and remove math.h.
So basically, what we're going to want to do is kind of come through
here and do all of those that way.
But that's going to take us a little bit of time because we're going
to have to go through and look at how to implement things like sign
because processors don't always have sign and you have to implement it
yourself and so on.
So, for now we're just going to call these guys here, but I do, I just
essentially, what I want to do is make sure that our code isn't
littered with calls to math.h.
I want it to be calling into here so that we kind of can see all the
stuff that we're using and off we go.
All right.
So the reason that I bring that up now is
The floor F certainly which we want to get rid of but also there's
another reason 18 to fyx.
Yeah, there's another reason I bring it up which is that I wanted to
start talking about trig and vectors because there's a bunch of things
that we actually do need to talk about as well related to other stuff
with our tile map.
He'd been sick, study H we go.
Okay, so we need to do those math functions.
But the other thing that I wanted to point out, is well, okay, there's
a bunch of stuff that we're going to have to start talking about like
vectors in these sorts of things.
And I got to introduce those Concepts, sort of over time.
And that time is probably going to be pretty close.
Pretty soon.
If it's not going to be, it's not this week.
That's probably going to be next week.
What I want to introduce though.
Just right off the bat is
When we're thinking about this, tilemap, there's a bunch of things
that we want to do to it.
But one of them is one that may not be sort of clear to anyone, if
they haven't actually gone through this process before themselves.
And so, rather than get all the way to the end of it and then show you
that it's kind of unfortunate and have to sort of switch it all around
and do it again.
I'm going to kind of jump to a part in the implementation and show you
what will happen so that you can kind of understand one reason why we
need to think about it and so on.
Yeah, basically, as much as possible, I will discover things on the
screen on the stream for you in the natural way that they will would
get discovered.
But sometimes I kind of have to head things off at the pass to prevent
us from doing, like a whole engine, the wrong way, and then coming
back to it later and going well.
See that's why you wouldn't do it this way.
So sometimes I have to use experience and kind of talked about it
earlier than it would normally come up.
And so this is one of those cases.
What I want to talk about now is I want to talk about basically the
coordinate.
The things are in now, what we've been doing so far.
We made this tile map, right?
When we made this actual tile map.
I sort of showed you how to come at it from first principles and we
did a reasonable job of that.
We've got it working right now.
We could walk to multiple tile Maps.
It's fairly clean on the inside.
There's nothing particularly odd going on.
There's some stuff, I said, I wanted to kind of continue to push on
but for the moment it's looking.
Okay, but we've baked into here a very specific assumption.
And one of those assumptions is that we are just dealing with pixels
on the screen, right?
Because basically everything that we did, you know, our tiles have a
known pixel size.
When we move things around, removing them in pixels.
And and this sort of thing, what that means is, if we were to change
the resolution, right?
Of our screen, we would have to rewrite all of that code essentially,
right?
I mean, let's say, for example, I mean
Just for the sake of argument because we could do this actually pretty
easily here and I'll show you what I mean.
Let's say, for example, we came in here and we had we wanted to change
that the size of the tile map.
So we
We were going to change it from being 60 pixels across to being 30
pixels across.
Let's say right, we just decided to change it.
And so here we go.
Oh Christen my guys already stuck in the geometry there.
I got to have to move him a little bit over from where he is because
he started off in the middle of the world hazards, but he's in
gentleman his name.
So essentially this is, you know an example of what would happen.
If I go ahead and change that value.
So that now the tiles are not as large as they used to be instead of
being 60 right there.
Now, 30, but, oh, and you'll notice the offset is wrong as well.
Right?
Because that the offset is as much to is one entire tile to that
direction.
So, this should we should actually probably set these relative to the
tile with, right.
We should probably set them that way.
Anyway, so here's our map again, right?
And it
Roughly the same with a, you know, with a smaller thing.
But what you'll notice is the guy now moves twice as fast right
relative to the size of the, you know, of the stuff, right?
Because his speed is in pixels.
So if we change the resolution of the tiles, just the resolution of
the imagery, right?
It's as if the whole world has gotten smaller because everything that
we're doing, is effectively in some units and those units are pixels
right now.
That's a perfectly normal thing to do.
Do and like, I showed you.
It's what you would do.
As if you move up each step and sort of as you go condensed, things
down.
Now, the problem is, you will never figure out that this is going to
break something.
Unless you try to run your game at multiple resolutions and it's
entirely possible that we would not really be trying to do that for
quite some time.
And so, like I said, what I'm doing today is what I'm doing right now
is essentially, it's kind of forcing that issue and pointing out to
you like, okay, let's start to think about the ability to change.
Lucian's way easier than it may ever naturally come up or naturally
occur to you because that's a very real problem.
And we don't want to bake that assumption into our game or will could
create all kinds of headaches for ourselves by assuming that our units
are pixels when pixels are just something that we use to display on
the screen and don't really have any meaning in the game World
necessarily, we should be able to double the resolution or have the
resolution of our tiles in terms of Graphics without the game changing
at all, right?
The game itself should
Play exactly the way that it plays.
And so that's the first thing we need to think about is the concept
that units.
There's something there's such a thing as the units of our game and
those units may not be pixels and probably shouldn't be pixels.
Okay, so that's one thing to think about.
So that's Thing 1 and Thing 2 that we need to think about is how our
court.
So I'm basically trying to set us up to talk about the sort of the
coordinate system of our game are the other thing that we need to sort
of think about here.
Is well, we know that pixels are one unit that we could be in and
there's reasons why I probably wouldn't do that.
So that's one thing but also, what direction do things go, right?
If you think about it, this guy here, when he moves left to right,
right, he's moving positive.
We add numbers to him to move this way.
Right?
So essentially, if you wanted to draw what our coordinate system looks
like, right, you would say that that ex, you know, the X
Access it gets positive in that direction, right on the screen.
But but what happens with why right now?
I don't know if you remember, but if we go down here and we take a
look at what happens when the player presses the up button, right?
If move up is is down then then it's actually a subtraction that we do
from the guys, why position?
So really when we're going upwards or subtracting, we're going
downwards, were added, right?
And so, if you think about it, that means that
at y, if this is the y axis, Y is positive that way and - this way,
right?
So if this is the origin of our coordinate system, right?
That's, that's that's what it would look like.
So again.
There's an issue here.
The issue may not be obvious.
But it's one that I would like to demonstrate earlier rather than
later.
And that is that this is backwards from how all math is done.
Right?
We are essentially doing something that is is written in a coordinate
system where it looks like this.
And this is this is positive X and this is positive y, but every math
test book that's ever been written in the history.
Time that I'm aware of anyway, does have X+ going that way but y+ goes
up, right?
This is how how math looks always pretty much universally.
And so if you're someone who's used to working with math, which you
will be, if you ever took high school math or anything like that, you
will expect why to be going up and all of the stuff that you do.
When you look at math textbooks and physics and everything else will
be drawn this way.
So, you know,
It's y, goes up and angles are measured, sort of starting going
counterclockwise.
They do not go clockwise, which is what they would do on this.
Right, you know, circles are drawn this way and so on, so really we
have another problem, you know, we have we have our first problem is
the pixels versus World units problem.
Right now, but we have another problem, which is the upside down
problem, which is the fact that our coordinate system currently is
upside down.
From what math would want it to be.
And there's no real reason in practice why you have to have your
coordinate system agree with maths coordinate system.
Okay.
There's if you don't want to, you don't have to there's no compelling
reason.
There's no objective truth to what direction y has to go, right, but I
can simply say,
Say from experience that you will save yourself a lot of headaches.
If you are constantly looking at your math, textbook and seeing this
and then you can go type something in and it is that over in your game
world as well.
Because otherwise you're constantly having to deal with this inversion
that occurs between what you see in a math textbook.
When you're trying to do something or looking up, something advanced
math wise and what you actually, go ahead and do on the screen, for
example, if we wanted to shoot a projectile.
Tactile at a particular angle.
Let's say, you know, we've got a particular Theta and we want to shoot
a projectile off at that angle, right?
We would know and we'll be talking about this a lot more.
So if you don't know that's fine too.
There's cosine and a sine of that angle will give us the X and Y of
the vector that we need to sort of shoot it off in that direction.
Well, if you're thinking about it in this way and you're looking at
your math, textbook and trying to learn from it this way and then you
go and implement it and your dude is always shooting debt, you know,
the other way.
It's like, oh, it's he's shooting down instead of up.
What's going on.
I'm totally confused.
Right?
And then you're like, oh, right.
My quarter system is backwards and the more complex, your equations
get the easier.
It is to forget in there somewhere that there's an upside down this
and wonder why stuff isn't working and we write subtly wrong.
So I would say that we have two problems that we probably want to fix.
We want to pick fix the pixels versus World units and we want to fix
the upside down and I wanted to just kind of introduce those now that
we're sort of a little ways.
Into it because those are things that just from experience, I can say,
we probably don't want to bake into our engine because we're probably
going to be sad if we do so.
And there is no, real obvious compelling reason why you have to do
either these two things, but just like I said, if you want to make
your game support multiple resolutions and you want to have an easier
time going from math textbooks to your game and vice versa.
It's just their good things to do, and so I'm going to do them.
M in our code base, for those two reasons, but your game would work
just fine without them.
If you didn't ever care about changing the resolution, or you want to
do some hacks to change the resolution and so on.
And if you didn't ever care about going back and forth, match that's
books, then you would never have to worry about that.
Okay.
So where does that leave us?
Where indeed it leaves us with 15 minutes.
I've been talking a lot tonight.
It's been a lot of blabbing.
I've been a blabbermouth.
It's true.
But where does that leave us?
It leaves us at the point where we kind of have to start to think
about this tile map thing, a little more robustly, like, trying to
just make this, a little cleaner, you know, got to do a little
stretching today.
I got to go stretch after the streams over.
We're stretching.
It's going to be stretching time.
Maybe we could do one of those group calisthenic things for like I do
the stretch and all of you guys do the stretch as well.
And then it's like, you know, it's like group calisthenics.
Yeah.
Anyway.
Anyway, so
We gotta start thinking about all these things.
We gotta start thinking about Tom apps.
So there's a couple things that I still want to do that will naturally
fall out of the things that we're doing.
But those two that I introduced today, are things that wouldn't, I
don't think have naturally followed at fallen out.
They would have been things that we would have to get to later, and
then realize we're busted and then be upset.
Right?
And so, I'm just trying to kind of save us, that, that sort of grief
by pointing them out ahead of time.
Because I've been there already and know that these things.
Gotta go poorly.
So now we've got that out of the way.
What I would like to propose.
First of all is having some notion just to start off with having some
notion.
Therefore of what the units are in the world.
Right?
I'd like to have some notion, some, I'd like to be able to tie this
back basically to a actual notion of how big things are.
Are in the real world.
And the reason I want to use real world units essentially.
Is because I feel like, if I use real world units, it's easier for me
to conceptualize how big things should be, and I can play with that if
I want to.
But like, for example, if we want to implement something that has
gravity, we know how fast gravity is in the real world.
So if we already have real world units everywhere for stuff, then it's
easier to just type in the value for gravity and be starting at
something that's realistic and then you can tune it from there rather
than having no idea.
What would be realistic and having to guess, and then tuning for
there.
So, given that what I'm thinking about here is basically like, okay?
So we know our guy, right?
We know that are that are, are person is basically going to be about
one, you know, kind of looking at this.
I'm imagining how big is going to be?
So I'm imagining that.
We want the player to be, you know, something like that size,
something like that.
Rectangular sighs.
I don't know.
Exactly.
But something like it.
And so if we think about, you know, I don't know how wide a
Human is across right?
But, you know, I mean, I feel like one of these tiles for example is
probably not a full meter across.
Maybe it's a meter across.
I don't know.
It's hard to say, but I would basically think that, you know, if we
were to Ballpark the size of the guy, you know, what, we could say,
here's what we could say.
Here's here's one way, I could ballpark.
Of roughly.
What we might want those units to be.
Let's say I open up Google here and I say let's say our dude, you
know, he's a little kid so I don't know let's say what's the average
height of let's say, you know a ten year old.
The average height of ten year old boy was fifty, five point two
inches.
So let's just say randomly 55.2 inches times.
Excuse me.
Sorry and M.
How big would that be 50?
2.2 inches in meters?
So that's 1.4 meters right?
There.
You go, 1.4 meters.
So how big?
A my it's actually see six feet and meters.
I'm 1.8.
So 1.4 would roughly be, you know, sort of the height of one of the,
you know, what?
One side of these let's say would be 1.4 meters.
Not like that.
So if a tile on aside was 1.4 meters, we could actually use that value
as sort of a calibration value to say roughly how big these things
actually are supposed to be in real world units, right?
We could come in here and say our world definition.
We actually have a thing, which is going to be one point for right.
Which is M, you know, tile side in meters.
Or something like this, right?
And so when we create the world we're just going to say that the tile
side what, you know, one side of a tile measured in meters.
I'm just going to say for now that that's about 1.4.
Right?
That's about its 1.4 meters on the side of a tile.
So if we wanted to measure now in the world how long something was we
could actually do it in real world, you know in M something like that.
Now I'm not sure if that's exactly right.
You know, we're going to sort of say that that's roughly it for now.
Okay.
So what that essentially means is if a tile is that big in meters,
right?
And then we also have right over here and, you know, I guess we could
also say, I think.
Let's let's go ahead and say definitively that our tile side is going
to be square as well because I know that I want square tiles.
So let's go ahead and say a tile side in pixels, right?
Which we also have, which kind of formal for us this tile side in
pixels.
And I guess that's that should actually be a un 32 since we can't.
We're not going to allow there to be a fractional pixels there.
So a tile side in pixels on the screen is going to be 64.
Now.
Now you may want to let it be fractional.
You know, you might think okay.
Why not let it be a fractional number of pixels on the screen for a
particular tile.
And the reason that I don't really want to do that is because if you
think about it, we would like the art for the game to line.
Line up properly.
With the pixels on the screen.
When we get to the renderer, you'll see why we may want to do that to
avoid.
Basically, having more blurriness introduced than necessary and more
filtering, introduce the necessary.
So, you may wonder why I'm actually doing this as an integer for now,
but I think I want to do that for now.
We'll see if we could always decide later that we don't want to do
that later on.
But for now, I think I'm going to stick with that.
So basically the tile the tile side and pixels is going to replace
this width and height here.
And this will now give
Us an idea of the real-world size of things and how big they should be
on the screen.
And with those two, we can now do a mapping that will allow us to
write things like the player position, right?
We can write something like the player position in a way that will
actually tell us something more interesting than just how many pixels
he's moved.
We can say how many meters per second, he's going for example, or
things like that.
And then we can always map him back into where he should be in the
world afterwards.
Okay, so I'm going to go ahead and fix the stuff here.
I'm Gonna Change tile with to because we change we got rid of that
tile with the tile height.
So we have to change tile with to tile side in pixels.
Go ahead and change that everywhere that it was being used.
And similarly.
We have to change tile height to tile side in pixels as well.
So that okay.
Let's see here.
What did I do incorrectly?
Unary minus applied to unsigned type up?
Sorry, certainly, make that a sign type.
No need to be overzealous.
There.
Weren't user aversion from inch to real 32.
Is the upper left X gives a real.
So I will go ahead and make that a real as well.
And it looks like that is
Yes, there we go.
Okay.
All right.
So I think that's basically everything and it looks like everything is
still working properly.
There.
No, no.
Oddities.
Everything still seems correct.
So, that's fine.
And now, what I want to do is go ahead and start to put start to make
well, I don't know if I'll quite start this yet.
Maybe we'll do it tomorrow.
But what I want to do is continue down the road of kind of cleaning up
this time.
I've stuff now that we have a notion of what those two things are.
I don't quite necessarily.
To use them yet because there's something that I think maybe we'll do
one step of the time that compression first that we haven't quite
finished yet and then we will come back to it.
So I think I got time to do this in seven minutes left.
Well, actually we started five minutes late.
So technically we've got about 12 minutes left.
So we're going to do these and I'll actually put it to do here to to
do begin using tile side in meters.
Okay.
So what I'd like to do here is basically
You know, looking at these two things and thinking about the bit.
I think I mentioned on the previous stream because we were right in
the middle of working with them.
I mentioned that I didn't really love, you know, and I have this to do
here.
These are still in pixels.
This kind of was the foreshadowing of the thing that we were kind of
introduced here.
So, I know that these things I kind of don't want to be in pixels
anymore for chemical positions.
I already kind of said that so I want to start moving to real world
units for our offsets, but you notice we have these two numbers here.
We've got the
The tile Map X, the tile map, Y, and the tile X, and the tile, why?
Right?
So, what can we say about these values?
I was saying before that, like, I've got this raw position.
The raw position was basically a tile Map X and Y, which is some index
into which of the tilemap portions were having remember just to give
you a refresher just for folks who you know, maybe forgot from last
dream.
We've got this is the setup that we've got here, right?
We have a game board.
Oops a game board that
It looks like this, right?
You saw me walking around it earlier on the stream.
All right, doo-doo-doo-doo-doo doo-doo-doo-doo doo-doo-doo-doo.
There we go.
So basically you saw us walking around this, right?
This is a tile map.
This is a tile map and so on and we had court made coordinates for
these.
We'd said like this was 0 0.
This was 10.
This was 0 1 and this was 11 right?
For the tile, map that we were on.
And then inside there, we had additional things.
Where each tile was the num numerated as well with with the, you know,
with the coordinate system, right?
We kind of kept doing all these numberings.
And so, what I wanted to do is I wanted to say because this is
something that I saw as we were working on it, but we didn't have time
to do it.
Last time.
What I want to do here is I want to say, why do we need two separate
sets of indices, right?
Why do I need the tile Map X and Y and the tile X tile why?
Right?
Since I know already right that we're going to have a fixed number per
tile map there since I and even if we weren't, let's late.
Let's put that aside for a second.
Why can't I just have an integer for all the tiles in the world?
Right?
Just, you know, one integer for all the tiles in the world.
So one integer for x 1 integer for y and then whichever tilemap you're
in is basically just looking at that value and taking off say the High
bits of it, right?
It just looking at whatever the higher order part of it is.
Right?
Does that make sense?
So, you know, to map a tile X or a tile Y into a particular tile map.
Basically, all we're doing is we're sort of saying, okay, let's go
ahead and and page.
I mean, really what I'm saying is, Let's Make a virtual memory system
for our Tom apps.
Let's just have a single 32-bit value for the X and a single 32-bit.
Value for the Y that is the the individual tile and all the tiles in
the world.
So we have four billion by four billion is the maximum size we could
support which seems like a pretty reasonable size to support at
maximum.
Right.
That's what did we say?
Our size was 1.4 meters.
So 1.4 meters times 4 billion, right?
Is that many meters so that many meters.
I guess I'll copy that circumference of the Earth.
In meters, so that's the circumference of the earth.
Well actually see here.
Can I get that in kilometers?
So six-figure, 40 million, 40 million meters if you to walk all the
way around the earth.
And this is how many meters we could support, which is more than that.
So we can basically support an entire Earth's worth of geometry, which
seems like plenty for our purposes.
So if we do a 32 bit of X and a 32-bit, why?
Right?
What I'm basically saying is, let's go ahead and imagine that 32 bits
is broken up into, you know, pieces of some kind like chunks
basically, right where we basically say.
Okay?
The bottom.
Let's say the bottom four bits, right?
So that's 16 or something.
The bottom four bits in the top, twenty eight bits or something like
that are going to be separated in these numbers and the
Bottom 4 bits Will Tell Us Where in a chunk we are right.
And the top Ones Will Tell Us Where in the tile map where when the
indices of the tile map, we are.
So this part tells us the tilemap index and this part will tell us
which tile we are in a particular tile map.
Right?
Basically, what I'm doing is I'm packing the two numbers that we had
before into one number and just segregating it by the bit amount.
Right now.
You're going to say
When you first see it, you're gonna like, wait a minute, Casey though.
How is that going to work?
Because if you remember what we did before, when we were drawing a
tile map, right on the screen, we basically had time upcoming textile
map count.
Why that said how big these Thomas?
I was 17 by 9 and there's ain't no way.
You're going to get some number of bits down here to be 17, right
there.
You going to be 16 or 32 and there ain't gonna be no 9 was going to be
either 8 or 16.
So what gives right?
And that's a totally valid question to ask me.
I'm very glad you did.
How did I scroll like that?
I don't know what happened there.
I'm very glad you did.
What I'm basically proposing is that we no longer think about the
screen that is being displayed.
As the tilemap.
The tile map is just going to be a chunk that we can reference and
store.
What a screen will just be a view that could be viewing multiple tile
maps at once.
Right?
So for example, if our tile maps are 16 by 16, right?
Then basically we will have one tile map that covers essentially this
much, you know, of are displayed area.
And then another one that covers that much or whatever.
And when we look at a screen will just reference to tile Maps, right?
No, big deal.
Very, very straightforward.
So that's essentially what I would like to do is make it so that we
can
Can go ahead and do do that sort of.
Do that sort of packing, if that makes sense.
So, alright, if they, if we've run out of time for today.
Then this may be the time when I've done the least of know, I guess
one other time, I talked basically, if the entire stream was gonna
say, this may be the stream where we got the least actual programming
done, but I've tried explain to you what we were actually going to do.
So, okay.
I'm just going to fight.
I'm just gonna say that one more time, so that tomorrow, we can
basically start directly on it.
So, what we want to do now that we've talked all about all of this
stuff quite a bit.
Is I want to basically take these values and I want to collapse them
into one.
Right?
So what I want to do tomorrow is I want to say, take the tile Map X
and Y and the tile X and Y and pack them into single 32-bit values for
X and Y, where there is some low bits for the tile index.
The High bits are the tile page, right?
And basically what we're doing here is we're constructing essentially
a virtual memory system, exactly, like the kind that you would see for
just regular memory.
Only instead of it being a 1D thing, like memory is its 2D.
We're basically just making a 2d virtual memory system.
Right?
All we're doing is we're saying we have some gigantic world, right?
That's four billion by four billion across, right?
And we
Want to break that up into chunks, right?
And I'm thinking those chunks.
Maybe you'll be 16 by 16.
Maybe they'll be 64 by 64.
Who knows?
We'll talk about the reasons to make different sizes.
But basically will break those into chunks.
And those chunks will be something like 16 by 16 and then whatever we
want our games display to be however, big we want it to be in tiles,
will just grab out that portion of it and display that as the tile
map.
So instead of the screen and the and the storage,
In the same.
We're just going to split those up into two pages.
And again, you may ask, why do I just store a giant for a billion by 4
billion array for my tiles?
Well, that would never that's too much.
It's too large for a billion times 4 billion would never fit in
memory, not even close.
It would be absolutely massive.
So what we're going to do instead is we're only going to will show how
to do this later.
You know, as soon as we get this stuff working, we can actually go
ahead and do the stuff the stories.
But basically what we're going to do is we're only going to store the
places where the world actually exists.
So as the world kind of snakes, its way through various pieces.
We're only going to store Pages where there's actually data and that
way it'll be nice and sparse and we won't have to store a 4 billion by
4 billion worlds, which of course, you could never actually store.
Okay, so I want to do that and turn it into a paging thing.
So that's one thing.
I think we'll be able to do that tomorrow.
They'll probably take the whole day tomorrow, but we can probably do
it tomorrow.
And then the next step, because the things that I've talked about
earlier today is to be got to fix these tile relative things.
So we're going to compress those two guys down, but then these tile
relative things.
What I want these guys to be.
Bright is, I want these guys to be convert these to math friendly
resolution independent representations of world units, relative to a
tile.
Right?
And so basically these are going to be now they're going to be in
those units that we talked about before, which is the the tile side in
pixels.
So
See, what we're going to do is we're going to convert these canonical
positions over to something.
That's nice and clean.
It can be used as a virtual index into a giant tile store that stores
as much space.
As we want for Tau Maps, we're going to be able to do a nice sort of,
you know, math friendly resolution independent movement of things
relative to the tiles.
So that will organize.
And then we can also get rid of this raw position because again, we
won't ever have to think again about things in terms of those pixels
the way that we were.
So we'll just
or everything as the kanak positions and we'll get rid of these and
that will make our town map that will start to get our Tom up into
really good shape.
Something that we can really start to think about being sort of a
quality system that we're going to be able to use.
And again, what we will do to down here again, instead of this thing,
looping over a tile map.
This thing will actually just Loop over towels and pull the tiles out
of of that sort of virtual store once we build it.
So, so that is what we'll do tomorrow, but
With with, without taking up too much, more time from the Q&A.
I will close this and I will say, let us go to the Q&A here.
If you could, please prefix your questions with q: and keep them to
things that we've done today or in previous day's.
Because if you want to ask questions about sort of off topic stuff,
you could always do that by coming to earlier in the
Dream basically, before the before, the scheduled start time, like
8:00 p.m.
If you come at like 7:45, I am usually on the stream early and I
filled questions about whatever you want, but during the official q
and A's, I like to keep it on topic as much as possible.
Let's see.
We'll be making a map editor.
Not really because this is a procedurally generated game.
So you can't really have a map editor if you have to generate
everything procedurally.
Let's see.
Too fast floor.
Where you talking about?
I equals n TF P.
If I greater than FBI - - well, so not really like
Well, so let me show you first of all.
Sort of this is not necessarily what I'm thinking about for fast
floor, but let me see if I can show you.
There's a store instruction that I was thinking of in sse4 as well.
That would be sort of the one-step way to do it.
So Jimmy,
let's see.
Oops.
I wanted floor.
Not ceiling.
So in sse4, which I don't know if we should use or not because I'm not
sure how many machines have sse4.
I don't know what kind of coverage we get.
But basically if you, if you there's this round PS function that
actually can do all four different types of rounding.
Let me see if it's got the documentation for that here.
Kind of slow, kind of Pokey.
Flog them hamsters flog them all the hamsters on the Azure Cloud right
now.
Run, run faster.
Okay.
There we go.
So if you take a look at this instruction, that's an S SE for.
This is one if we had us as before I just use it.
But so I, when I was saying about sse2, I was thinking more like,
okay.
What are we going to Cobble together to make it work?
Relatively well in Assisi to but, you know, point being
Because we could do like fraction extraction or their stuff I can do
anyway, ignoring that for a second.
This is like the Uber example of what I wanted.
You can do an M&M round PS and that will basically take a floating
Point values and it will round them using whatever mode you want.
Right?
And so you can do all sorts of nice rounding with that.
You can do a floor, right?
You can do a seal, you can do truncation, you can do rounding, and you
can say whether
You want to go towards negative infinity or positive Infinity?
Right?
So you can, you can construct the round that you actually wanted to be
a floor to be a ceiling or to be whatever.
So that's like the perfect instruction.
That's the one you wish that they would have just had to begin with,
but unfortunately, never did.
So, what I wanted to know is basically what is the shortest set of
sse2 instructions that I could do to emulate that for our purposes.
Now,
It turns out that actually we can do something a little bit more
clever that I was going to get that will eliminate the need for floor
in this particular case and I'll add a thing here.
We can actually just use truncate for our purposes because once we
have this stuff packed, we won't need - offsets anymore.
So it's a little anticlimactic either way, but we probably will need
floor for other things as well.
So point being, I'd like to go through and get a good feel for, what's
the easiest way to do an sse2, you know, into bucket thing.
And, you know, I might have to ask some folks who are better at SSC
stuff, because I forget it.
Hey Jude in when I do have to see and then I paid it out immediately
and I forget what they are about the rant to study up.
Recursive anomaly, have you considered only storing the changes made
and then just regenerating everything else from seed instead of
storing it all.
So, that's an interesting.
So what you're talking about is
so let me talk a little about that because actually interesting
question.
So what he's basically asking or she I suppose I guess I don't know
the gender of anyone.
What do the the questioner is asking is, you know, do we have to
actually store everything or can we generate stuff from seed values?
Right?
And so when we go into a new page, when we go into a new part of the
world, can we just generate it from seed and then we can press it.
And I believe Minecraft works that way.
And then just re compresses and stores the world that after you change
it.
It only stores blocks.
If you change them.
I don't know.
There's games that work that way and there's two reasons why I don't
like that solution.
The first reason I don't like that solution as I feel like it
generates worlds that are kind of boring like worlds that can be
generated per page by a seed look like they were generated per page by
a seed.
And so I am more interested in creating worlds that are a lot more
creative than that.
And in
All things that would be much too expensive to create in a way that
will allow you to create them from a seed on a page basis, without an
extraordinary amount of work.
So I don't think I want it for that reason, but there's another reason
I don't like that idea.
And the reason that I don't like that idea is because I don't actually
think that it's a good up.
It doesn't have performance.
Levering, leveling characteristics, which is to say that, let's say
that you're like, oh, well, I can be more efficient.
By just not ever storing this.
And then when someone comes in here and does, if the world gets
modified in some way, then I'll write it back out.
Only if that happens, right?
The thing that I don't like very much about that is, what?
What?
That really doing assuming that the user does go through and do lots
of changes to the world.
Then you end up back in the state that you would have been if you were
just storing it.
Right?
And so I'm not sure where the benefit comes if it's just to sort of
save to spread computation time out, then maybe that's something.
But in general, it doesn't really save you any space.
If you assume the case where the user goes around doing as much stuff
as they can to the world, right?
So I don't see it being really that big of a win or even a win at all,
really.
It's sort of
thing that only saves space.
In the case of a world that the user isn't touching a lot of which
again, you know, isn't isn't perhaps quite so interesting.
So Sean McGrath suggest doing FP: fast, which is let's let's take a
look here.
Remember I was asking earlier on the stream.
I was like, can we get this guy to start outputting for that floor and
instruction.
I kind of wanted him to Output a better thing for floor.
Then it was outputting and I felt like the compiler.
Could have been doing a better job, but when we actually went and
looked, as you can see, it's it.
Still calling floor.
There's the call to floor right there.
So what I was hoping to do is basically to make it so that we could
have a compiler output, something a little more sensible.
Than this stuff that it is outputting at the moment.
And so the the commenter is suggesting to do FP fast.
First of all, let's see if that works.
See, if that has any effect there.
Go to disassembly, okay.
See, there it is.
Yes.
This is what we wanted.
This is much better now, you notice, we are not getting any more
floors.
Yes, thank you.
FP fast.
Remember are saying there's a way to like tell it not to do not to
have floating-point consistency.
So let's take a look at that as that.
That is the thing that we wanted right there.
P fast.
Thank you stream.
It's so nice having a stream.
You could just ask question.
You don't have to, you don't have to go digging through the
documentation.
So on msnbc's compiler, here is the way that you tell it not to worry
about adhering to the
Plus plus standard as much, okay?
Improves.
It gets to see a floating Point test for equality inequality by
disabling optimizations, that could change the Precision of floating
Point calculations.
That's the precise one and that's what it was on before, right?
Fast allows it to relax the rules for computations so that it can do
like things that might be less correct or less accurate.
The case of certain exceptional circumstance, except some
circumstances, it will just ignore those sorts of things.
Right?
And that's what we wanted, because I knew that I only needed to do the
floor, basically, the standard usage of Florida, just the basic
concept before.
I didn't need it to handle, you know, all sorts of special things.
Like, I don't know.
Do you normal numbers or who knows?
I didn't need to handle all things.
That the C++ spec may say that need to handle.
And so I was hoping that I could get it to go ahead and and generate a
fast floor.
Or because I know that I don't have any weird special requirements.
I don't have to adhere this.
He's back.
I just need a basic floor function.
And so that, that FP, fast is exactly what we needed to have that
happen.
And so, that's pretty awesome.
In fact, I wonder if that also will do the right thing for some of the
other functions.
Like, if I said something like here, if I say y equals sign.
You know, something like X, I don't know.
Let's take a look at what it does there.
I just want to see if I can what it would generate for other sorts of
stuff.
Let's take a look.
So no, so it'll still generate the call the sign.
So yeah, so that may not help us much.
Let's take a look.
Yeah.
Yeah, so, you know six of one half dozen of the other, you know, we
still got we it's it's better than nothing.
We're going to have to do some work still but but it's good to know
that we can get it to to do some of that stuff for us.
So that's pretty good.
I'm going to I'm going to leave that in a rem, their optimizations,
which has just so we can can remember that and don't have to look it
up again.
Thank you.
Sean McGrath.
I noticed the math Library.
All of the placeholder functions are in the for mint result, equals
Foo, return result.
What's the reason for making it that way instead of just return Foo.
So I believe what the person is asking is when I went and made the
intrinsics here.
Why am I doing it?
Why does it look like result equal something return result instead of
just making it be returned, the thing directly write.
Why isn't it just returned 8 and 2 FY X like why is it?
It, why isn't it that the reason is very mundane, but I think it's
still useful.
It's for the buggy is basically it.
So let me show you what I mean.
Let's say, for example, that I was to do it the other way, like I do
it like this.
Yes.
Right.
So there we have our floor function.
It is now operating kind of in the way that you were asking about.
And when I come in here, I'm in this function and I want to see what
it actually.
Computed.
What was the result?
That it computed and I hit F10 and you'll notice I can't see it
anywhere.
I can't see the actual value now, sometimes depending on the
circumstances you can use.
Whereas it here locals you can use this locals thing to basically say,
what is, you know, what is the result if that makes sense?
No, it's not locals.
Sorry, it's Auto.
Sorry.
I never, I almost never use these.
So, I'm a little behind on whether it's Autos.
Sorry.
So, sometimes you can use.
It depends on the debugger.
Sometimes you can use this Autos thing.
It will show you what the return value is here.
Right?
And so sometimes you can do that.
But sometimes the developer gets confused.
It doesn't show you that.
And also there's some developers that don't have that depending on
what platform you're on, right?
And so if you don't have that,
A debugger that has that capability then, basically, what I do is, I
just always write it to look like this, so that if you were to end up
on the, the final line of your of that function, you always have a
convenient variable.
You can just type into a Watchman do and it's always result as well.
So, I owe usually always named things results that I can just leave
result in the watch window.
And it's essentially always shows me the return value of everything
that is just a convenient way to make.
Sure that no matter what the bugger you're on.
If it can do anything at all.
You should still be able to see what the return what the actual
computed value is.
So that is why I do that.
It doesn't cost you anything because as soon as optimizations on at
all, any compiler will trivially optimize this out.
So you're not wasting any computing power here at all.
It's free.
It's one of the few things that really is truly free.
And so, you know, it's just a good thing to do for convenience.
Is it a little pre-emptive to be drilling down on intrinsics this
early and development?
Doesn't that kind of go against your rationing process?
Not really because we can't we're not supposed to be using any
Library.
So as soon as we start using something, it's time to sort of take a
look at it.
So again, I didn't do it before we started taking a look at it, but we
are using them.
And so the time to look at things on the stream is when we start using
them.
And so this is kind of a thing that shouldn't really be allowed this
math.h.
And so it's time for us to start taking a look at those.
Those at this point.
Now, we'll be able to
Of skirt it a little bit because we can actually get rid of the
flooring function.
Like I said, using some, because of the way that we're going to
refactor stuff.
But we're going to be wanting sine and cosine real soon.
And so the time for us to actually have to deal with this stuff is
actually fairly soon.
So, it doesn't go against my ratcheting process if I could push them
out to later, I would.
But the bottom line is, we have to call them and so floor, if we could
actually get rid of, but but sine X and cosine F, we're going to need
and we're going to need him soon.
So.
Is tile relative for the real 32 coordinates better than tile page
relative.
Hmm, so I am thinking, I mean, my assumption.
I mean, I guess the answer is sort of, I'm not sure.
I guess what I would say is I don't really know that it matters, which
one we pick.
I think they both might both roughly be the same but I suspect that
it's just easier to do it tile relative to the tile because relative
to the tile is always uniform everywhere.
Whereas relative to the tile map would not be like
I mean, well, I don't know.
I guess what I would say that is, I don't know.
I don't know which one of those would be better.
I can't think of a reason offhand.
Why why you couldn't do either one.
I can't think of a reason why you couldn't just use either of the two.
Yeah, so tile page Mount relative may be better or tile relative maybe
better tell map page there.
Okay.
So one reason we maybe would want to think about using it being
relative to the page would be because if we do things on page,
boundaries likes a sort of collision e things, maybe that invite.
Well, I don't, I don't know.
I really don't know.
Like I said, I haven't written tilemap games before most of
The stuff that I write is like, full 3d or whatever.
So, you know, it's a little bit of an exploratory process for me.
This time around.
I'm not qualified to say definitively.
Yes.
You should do it this way or you just know you should do it the other
way.
So I don't know, that's a very good question and I don't know which
answer is better.
If we're lucky.
We'll see as we start to do one.
That it either is nice or
Is it nice and is it nice in a way?
That would be better if we switched and then we could switch.
But but I don't know offhand.
Why not just store the player, XY coordinates in World coordinates and
determine which tile map until he's in by dividing modding.
So the reason for that is just float Precision.
I covered this actually on a previous dream.
So you might want to go check it out.
Basically, you can't a single floating point value.
32, bit floating point value is not enough Precision to actually store
256, bits of fractional per pixel.
Plus the amount of size of the world that we wanted.
We wanted to potentially have like, hundreds if not thousands of tile
maps of screens across in the longest case.
I mean, probably realistically will never get up to thousands, but we
least wanted hundreds thousands.
Maybe too long for the player to ever get from one side to the other,
right, but we definitely wanted to be able to do a thing where there
might be 100 tall set of rooms that you might go through or whatever
and floating Point, Precision isn't isn't sufficient and I showed that
on a previous stream.
So,
So we definitely don't want to do that.
So we need to have basically a two-tiered system so that we can have
more than 32 bits worth of addressing for the guy in terms of where he
is.
See.
You mentioned in your picture that the last four bits could represent
the tile in the map and the top 28 would be the Tom application.
But since we plan on making the tile map sparse, we won't need that
many bits to represent that why not use the B 4 tiles.
So I think maybe you are thinking I'm saying something different than
what I'm saying.
So here is what I'm saying.
Let's draw this out.
A little more explicitly.
I should really learn to just make a grid.
Wow.
This is a very War P grid.
So, let's say that each of these things, right?
1 2 3 4 5 6 7 8.
One, two, three, four, five, six, seven, eight.
Let's say that each of these is eight by eight, right?
So each of these little things here is 8 by 8 and we want to store
it's parsley.
So our world occupies, you know this region, right?
So it occupies this area, okay.
That's where there actually is world.
But the use that like it's there's Collision everywhere.
So the player can't get outside of this area.
That's this is the only map so you could ever get to.
So, what we want to do is we want to store this stuff, you know, into
our interests, our magical machine that we're going to make here for
storing the tile set of the world for my scoring the tile map.
So we know that it's trivial to store.
Just a regular old tile map.
We've done it already, right?
We have all the code in here for storing a tile map.
That's just one screens worth of tiles or whatever.
So we know, we could store an 8x8 tileset.
Trivially.
We already saw how to do that.
It's not very hard.
Right, but the question is, what do we
Then due to store the rest of these guys, right?
We need to be able to have a bigger sort of addressing scheme to talk
about where this guy is such that a specific tile in here.
Has an address that is, you know, whatever.
He is in his eight by eight, you know, inside this 8x8.
He may be the tile 3 comma 2.
Right.
But we also want to talk about the fact that on the world.
He's you know, whatever he is, here is 0-1.
So he's 3, comma 1, right?
And so all I'm talking about is the address for this guy for this tile
right here, X and Y.
Right, if, if it's eight by eight, we need three bits for the tile
address, right?
So one, two, three, right?
So, this right here is the divider and we have 3 bits right into those
three bits for the X.
We would put the three, right?
And for the why we would put the to into here and here, right?
That's the location of the tile inside the tile map.
And then for the location of the tile map itself.
We use the top bits, right?
Which is 32.
- three right, which is the 29 B here, right?
20, 9 B, 23 9, B.
We would put three and one, we put three in here and one in here,
right now.
We have a universal way of addressing this tile such that, we know
what part of it is the tile map inside, which is inside a particular
8x8.
Tilemap that store densely and then another one that's for storing,
which time appease in sparsely and then what we need to do and we
haven't done this yet, but
We need to do is have a way of taking this top part here, this 31 and
looking that up in some kind of sparse way, so that we don't store
absolutely everything in the entire map, right?
So, but that's all I'm saying.
Do you know of the Intel intrinsics guide its interactive which makes
for easy filtering for instruction set and categories?
No, I didn't.
That sounds pretty awesome.
Intel intrinsic guide.
Oh wow.
That is spiffy.
Of course, it seems to be little.
So okay.
There it goes.
Wow.
Okay, that's pretty cool.
Thank you very much.
Flying sand.
That is great.
Okay.
So this is something we should totally bookmark.
I will and I will add that to the Forum site as well.
That's great.
That's really nice.
So that's pretty cool.
You can just go ahead and say, what's the instruction sets that you
are going to Target and then it only shows you.
Wow, that's awesome.
That's just great.
Wow, that makes life a lot easier and then you can just see all the
instructions that are there.
That's great.
Thank you very much.
Is there a reason we have a majority of the code.
We've been working on in handy, dot CPP, and not something like World
wpr.
Tilemap dot.
CPP, and player dot CPP.
Yes.
The reason is because that's premature.
So we will have more files but only once we determine what the
architecture correctly actually is.
So, for example, right now we're starting to get the tile map stuff
straightened out, as soon as the tile map stuff API wise, I'm
satisfied with it, which I'm not yet because the the I talked
Three things today that I want to do to it as soon as that's ready.
Then we will be pulling it out into its own file where we can consider
it kind of done for a while or at least where it'll just kind of
reside.
But I don't like to pull things out until we're sure that they're
correctly Consolidated because otherwise you're just presupposing.
You know, what the API boundary is between things, and that's a bad
idea.
You never want to presuppose.
You know what, the API boundary is, so you always want to start by
just writing.
And whatever comes to mind in the place that it's most easy to write
it.
And then once you are satisfied, that it's correct, then you pull it
out.
That's almost always the best way to go.
So we'll start masks.
Are we going to move the origin to the bottom left?
Yes, we will.
Probably move the origin to the bottom left to get.
This is what I was talking about getting rid of the floor.
So I'll talk about that a little bit once we do it because that's a
Easy way to get rid of the floor problem.
Shift drag four straight lines.
Okay, is that a tip for these?
Get for this because that is that work?
Let's see.
That does not work that just draws a circle.
That doesn't look at what you've done.
Oh, how do I get that?
Just changes the size of the brush that does not work.
I think you have to be in line drawing mode.
Probably.
Yeah.
Yeah, you have to be in line drawing mode, which I'm too lazy to
switch to line drawing mode.
I got to have my quick, my quick dashing.
They should have some kind of function that lets you draw a straight
line out even in freestyle mode.
Will you be able to find arm assembly?
Instructions to match.
The Intel ones you are specifying if, when you want to port to arm.
Yeah, so arm neon is pretty good.
It won't probably be one-to-one the instruction set on on oops.
Army on the instruction set on arm has this thing called neon, which
is basically like the equivalent of SSE.
So it's like that, but forearm for the arm processors and
I don't know.
I have docs for it on my other machine and I'm sure there are you can
download them usually here.
I don't know if they have them on here.
I don't know if there's what the right place to look them up is but
basically there's a bunch of the equivalent things to S2.
All the SSE instructions, neon typically has something suitable for
for you know, doing whatever you were doing in SSE on the arm
architecture as well.
Well, I don't know if it has it probably doesn't necessarily have that
rounding.
Well, it might you know, I don't remember.
I did some neon programming a while back and I remember it being very
good.
So, you know, I would basically say that most of the time you can
probably find something as good or better sometimes than you have an S
SE with neon.
So that's that's what will be porting to on our if we choose to port
to arm.
How are we going to deal with different types of tiles?
So, basically, right now, this is just a placeholder.
So, on our tile map, we just have an you at 32.
That's a tile type.
But what we will do in the future is once we actually decide what once
we're actually working on the game mechanics, part of the game.
It should be
Free essentially, for us to change, whatever this is into some more
elaborate structure that has all the stuff that we might want for a
tile, but it's very premature and think about that now, so all we
really need to do now is know that we can store something, and then we
can assume later that we can change in destroying, whatever it is that
we actually wanted.
But right now I just picked you and 32 because that allows us to store
some type field base for that, we can use to draw something so that we
can actually see what we're doing until we actually know what we want
for our tiles.
All right.
Looks like we are done with questions.
Thank you very much for joining me for another episode of handmade
hero.
I'm sorry.
I talked so much today.
There was kind of just a bunch of stuff.
I think, maybe from thinking, over the weekend.
Sometimes the brain is going.
So I had some stuff that I wanted to talk about.
So anyway, but I think we are in good track.
Anyway, by the end of this week.
I think we should have all of our tile stuff straightened out.
I think all the things that I wanted to do will probably be well and
truly done.
So,
It is a good thing.
And basically, what I would guess what I'd like to do is I'd like to
get to that point by the end of the week where we can say that our
town map stuff is is sort of where we want it to be.
And also maybe throw a monster in there.
Throw it throw another thing in the world.
So we can have two things in the world, moving around the player and
some other thing just to set us up for next week.
When we start to work on some of the other stuff like, you know, how
we're going to treat entities and animation and stuff like that,
because obviously that's another big part of the engine.
In architecture, so we want to kind of get some zygote stuff in there.
We want to try to get some stuff in there were playing around that.
So we have some idea of how we want this to work and what we want the
engine to do, as far as animations concerned and those sorts of things
because those are the sorts of things that can be kind of tricky.
So thank you very much for joining me.
If you would like to follow along at home with the source code.
You can go to handmade hero dot-org and go hit the little pre-order
button.
If you preorder the game, you will get access to the source code and
Night, you can give send you a link.
Basically that every night you can download the source code.
I uploaded immediately after we finish coding.
So if you want to do that, you do that.
If you'd like to support the video series.
We have a patreon.
You subscribe to that's on this little patch on button.
And we also have a news and Forum site that you can go to.
If you are trying to learn along with handmade hero, it's got the
schedule for the week on here.
It's got an episode guide for catching up on past, ish episodes with
time-coded access to the videos and stuff that helps a ton.
There's coding resources page that has ports and things like this as
well as reference materials.
So if you're trying to follow along on a Mac and you need some help,
getting the platform stuff up and running, that's a great place to go,
same with a Linux.
And then once we have forums, we can ask questions, code discussion
forum that you can ask questions about the code that we are doing and
get help for people to community.
And I also read them all.
So I'll come in there and answer stuff.
When I see something that I can answer.
Definitely check it out.
If you're learning along with the series.
It's a great place to go.
And it has a lot of really helpful information on it.
So, again, thank you everyone for joining me for another episode of
handmade here and has been a pleasure.
And I hope to see you all here tomorrow at 8 p.m.
Pacific Standard time again, where, and I'll go through and do that
virtualization of the town map stuff that we talked about tonight and
maybe if it goes, well, I don't know if it does, but if it goes well,
then I can also do the relative sort of world unit stuff that I want
to do.
If not, we'll
Do it on Wednesday.
So, thank you, everybody for joining me, and I hope to see you
tomorrow.
Thanks, everyone.