Start recording.
Hello, everyone, and welcome to handmade hero.
The show where we code a complete game live on stream on Twitch.
No engines.
No libraries, although I say that every day and in truth, I did also
say that our asset processor, since it is not part of the game.
Could use libraries.
I said I do not have a problem having that use libraries.
And the reason that I mentioned that
Is because we do actually have a choice today of using a library and
because people wrote in on Twitter and sort of said this, they were
saying, since the asset processor is allowed to use libraries and I
said that, could we use a library there for opening the fonts?
And I am considering that.
So basically, there's two ways that we can really do it in the asset
processor 1.
Is that we just get the fonts from Windows, right?
And the other is that we use some kind of library.
Now, you know, originally my assumption was I just show you how to get
them from Windows because well, you know, it's very direct and you
know, when you're running the asset processor on Windows, you can just
distract the fonts and whatever other platform you would use Linux or
something has a similar API, you could use to extract the fonts and
and off you go, right?
But
I don't know, I thought about it when people were saying maybe you
should use a library here, I thought about it.
And the thing that I thought of was people always ask me on the stream
all the time.
If you were going to use a library, what libraries would you use,
right?
And I only say the stb, libraries and so, I don't know.
My thinking was, I could decide to use a library here to show you
what, how to use an STD library.
Because, as I have said over,
Over again on the stream.
If I was going to use the library, the libraries that I would use
would be the stb.
Libraries, their libraries written by Sean Barrett.
They're designed with a game programmer in mind.
They're written in a very convenient way to integrate into your
product and so, I don't know.
So I don't know if people have strong feelings on that one way or the
other.
So, I thought, maybe what I do today, we'll show you how to get the
fonts with s with an SD B Library, show you how to use one of those
libraries because they are libraries that I recommend using and this
would pretty much be our only time when we could do this.
Us.
Because, like I said, before in the actual game code, I don't want to
use any libraries, right?
That's just kind of a rule for the game itself.
It's just an arbitrary rule, it's true, but it's just part of the
thing that I want to do with the series was we write everything in the
game from scratch.
So the entire code for the game is completely there and written by us.
Right?
So I don't know.
So probably what I'll do is we'll do that today because it seems like
a reasonable request from people and then if it ends up bothering
people we can
Just show also how to do it.
Click through windows or something like that, but we'll see.
So that's what I would say.
So maybe that's what we'll do today.
That seems like a reasonable request and it seemed like something we
could do.
And it has The Fringe benefit of if somebody wanted to use this
library in their actual game.
Now, they would know how to do it and they would know how to probably
would know how to use all the stb of libraries really because they all
kind of work the same way and they're a great set of libraries that,
you know, is really easy for you to use.
Even if you are very
Oculus about low-level things.
Like I am their libraries, that won't cause you pain and suffering,
like a lot of them.
Well, so if you're going to do that, how would you do that?
If you're going to use SUV libraries, you would search like this,
right?
You search for stb libraries and you get them here and you can go to
this stb page, right?
It's nothing.
/St be and he's got all these libraries in here.
Now, several
Libraries are pretty darn useful.
Like, stb image is like a great way to let quickly, add image loading
to your code.
Right?
So, if you take a look at it here, you know, it's like this one file,
right?
And it reads like a bunch of stuff, right?
It reads like jpeg paying being that PSD TG, right?
And it doesn't read like the complete Speck of all of them.
Usually, it just reads the part that game developers.
Usually care about, right?
So this is just like, when people ask me, if you were going to lose
libraries, which ones would you use?
As these would be, the ones that I would recommend using, or at least
they'd be it.
Be the place that I would recommend looking first because if it does
the thing that you want, these are probably the libraries that will
cause you the least pain and suffering.
They are also public domain.
So there is no restrictions on using them, you can redistribute them,
you don't have to do anything in particular under credit screen for
them.
It's purely like, you know, it's code.
That's free for you to use in every possible way.
And, you know, it would be nice to probably to thank Sean Barrett, if
you ship.
Have them but you know you're not even obligated to do that.
And so you can see a little description here that talks about all the
different ones and the ones that you the one that you would be
interested in particular if you wanted to do, the font stuff is stb.
Truetype, Right?
Which is this one here and SUV.
Truetype is a library that it literally does exactly the thing that we
want.
Which is it is a true type font rasterizer, right?
It literally does exactly the thing that I said,
Our asset processor would want.
Okay, so the structure of one of these libraries is very
straightforward, there is one file.
He ships it as an h-file, right?
So you can see all of these are H files and the way that they work,
you can look inside one, right?
Estimate re-type.
The way that they work is inside the H file, there's actually a pound
I'm that you pound to find to say whether you want the implementation
or just the header.
So you actually like it's actually two files in one.
It's sort of like the H and the CPP file or in this case C file
wrapped up into one file.
So you don't need an h and a CBP, you just need the one file and then
what you do is if you want the actual implementation, the part that's
the that's the C file, the dot C file.
Then you pound if I'm typically something like this and if you don't
want that you just don't Define it and then it's acts like a normal
age Val because all of the actual implementation, like all of this
stuff won't get compiled in, right?
You can kind of see if I come back to it here.
Where would that be?
Where is the if death almost there?
Where are we?
Here it is.
This ifdef right kills everything after it if you don't Define stb,
truetype implementation.
So if you don't Define us to be true type of implantation, it kills
the entire C code.
And it just acts like an h-file whereas if you do Define that, then it
acts as a C file so that you can build it into the game.
Mmmmm, right?
So that's it.
That's like all you have to do if you want to use it and I can kind of
show you, you know, roughly how that would work, right?
So let's say we want to use this thing.
You would just download it from here, right?
You can I think you can just actually right from the test to be true
type page.
I think there's usually like a little download button somewhere,
right?
Isn't there somewhere?
Maybe?
No.
Yeah, I don't use GitHub.
in case you were wondering, so I have no idea how you download a file
pulse issues, truetype quickly, jump, copy, file,
Seriously guys.
Like reserve download button.
Okay.
Well.
I don't know.
How about that?
That's no good.
Well.
I have no idea so I would tell you how to download this.
I have no idea.
Download it.
So.
Yeah.
I feel like this should be really obvious.
I don't really know why it's not, maybe I'm missing something.
Maybe if you were logged in it would be easier to do but that's kind
of weird.
So let's click on Raw okay, there we go.
So raw is just actually just link to it.
So I don't know if that's what they intended.
But that it work, right?
Because there's the raw file
So yeah, so I guess you have to do is Click.
On Raw click on save as sorry to those of you who are GitHub experts
that is probably not the recommended way but you know those of us who
are GitHub impaired.
So if you're going to download this guy and save it in here, right?
Now, we've got s to be true type.
And like I said, the big difference between us to be true type
libraries.
And the reason why I feel like they are, you know, something that I
can that I consider for my own coding.
Unlike a lot of libraries is because they're just really sensibly made
and they're really easy to maintain and keep using your search because
there's just one file and it integrates really cleanly.
So for example, right if we wanted to in handmade dot CPP, right?
We could go ahead here and actually just do some rendering with Seb
truetype.
Let's say we wanted to kind of put it in here and I'm just going to
like Drop it right in the middle of some code here as an example.
And then we'll go into the asset processor and I'll show you how we
would integrate it.
So if you want to do it, you would literally we could just do truetype
Dot h.
And like I said, if you take a look at how that works, there's an stbb
truetype implementation, right?
In here, you would pound to find that first and you would set that to
one or something.
You would like just have to pound Define it, right?
So if you're going to do that, that basically says, I want the
implementation as well, and then you just compiled and like you can
see like that.
Is it, right?
And I really want to underscore this like this is why this is a big
deal.
Okay, we didn't have to download fifty thousand files.
We didn't have to deal with someone to make system.
We didn't have to figure out how they all link together.
There are what compile times which is they need or anything.
It's like I just included.
Sean Barrett's truetype font rasterizer in my game.
With two lines of code.
Right?
And it just worked, that's a really big deal and nobody else pretty
much does this.
There are few rare exceptions of people who have followed his lead,
but that is a pretty big deal and it goes a long way towards giving me
the confidence.
That if I use this thing, I can maintain an easily.
I don't have to worry about all of these problems that I'm going to
inherit.
Because of the way this Library works and is sprawled.
And God knows what and depends on 50 million things and all this other
stuff, right?
Download one file, put two lines of code in and now you have a
truetype, rasterizing library built into your game, okay?
So that's really important.
It's like I said, I'm just going to write a little something here to
show you how the rasterization from the library works.
And then we're going to move over to the will move over to the asset
processor where it's just where this actually belongs.
And we'll go through the actual work of actually building.
building out the thing that will,
A demonstration version of asset of fonts processing into the into the
asset file.
All right, so if I go into stb truetype and take a look at it, one of
the great things about it.
Again, you know, to extol the virtues further is that if you take a
look at what happens in here, the H file itself includes the
documentation.
So here are some sample programs included, right in the H file for you
to use.
So I don't remember how to use Shawn Barrett's, truetype rasterizer,
it does not matter that I don't remember that, right?
Because it's
The case that, you know, the H file itself, tells me how to use it,
right?
And you can kind of see some examples here, this is a text in 3D API
example and you can kind of see that it actually has the information
that we want.
Exactly.
So here is stb, Big Font bitmap, right?
Which is actually a thing that if you get it, a size rectangle, it
will actually pack all of the fonts into that rectangle.
Exactly.
Like what we
We might want in a game, right?
So he even had built in the thing that we probably want to do.
Now, we don't have to do that, we could instead do something a little
bit more straightforward and do something where we just get the code
point bitmap, where we're basically saying, let's just get one bitmap
of one letter, and since I want to kind of show a little bit more of
this process, I'm not going to use this, but if you were using this
library, and again, one of the reasons I'm doing this is to kind of
give you an example of how to use a library.
What makes a good Library?
Since it is something that's asked very often.
You can see that he's sort of almost done, some of the work for you
here.
It's like there's a utility function that actually does a bunch of
stuff that you might want to do, right?
All right, so if we take a look here at this is more what I'm
interested in.
This is a function that basically generates a bitmap for a given code
point, a given Unicode code point, right?
And so, what I'm going to do is, I'm just going to make a little
function here, right?
Internal Loops avoid.
I'm just gonna make a little function here that does this exact thing,
right?
So here is the function that I want to call.
It's called STP in it font.
We need to give it a place to store the font information which is just
got to declare It On The Stack.
This is St.
B TT font info, you pass an address to that.
And then I need some kind of a buffer right into which it will dump
that font information, right?
I'm sorry that dump of it into which, or I should say, from, which it
will read that font information, right?
So, this would be the font file itself.
Now, we already have a way to do this in hand.
A hero, right?
We have the stuff in ham a platform that's like debug read entire
file, right?
We've got this thing right here.
So we actually have a way of pretty quickly doing exactly what s.
He wants us to do.
And again, you know, just
Not to extol Sean's virtues to extensively here but again it's set up
exactly the way I want.
He's not forcing me to pass them a file handle.
He's not forcing me to pass him a file name.
He's assuming that I already have ways to read files and then I'm
going to want to read files the way I read files.
So he just takes a memory buffer of the file.
That's exactly what I want, right, it's exactly what I want.
It, minimizes dependencies, it makes it so that
Don't have to work around him, he's working around me, right?
And that's really great again, another sign of an intelligently made
Library, it doesn't Force its file I/O on you, right?
So I can do this, right?
I can read the file.
So, here's our ttf file.
I can say, I want to take platform a debug read entire file, and then
I can just pass it some truetype font name, right?
So I don't know what true type font we want to read.
Read.
But I can, for example, pick one out of Windows and here you can see a
giant set of fonts and Ariel dot.
T TF is almost always there.
So I can perhaps just say we will use aerial for the time being,
right?
So I will go ahead and do debug read entire file to read out this font
file
And then after that font files, read I will just pass the entire thing
to Shawn, right?
So I'll say, hey Sean.
Here is the contents of that file work your magic and and that is is
it now get thought offset for index?
I believe is just a thing.
You know what?
To be honest with you, I don't really know what that does.
I don't remember, I don't remember so let's see what that does in it
font.
Let's see.
Here.
And it font takes an offset into the data.
Given an offset into the file.
That defines a font.
This function builds the necessary cash info for the rest of the
system.
You must allocate this.
We find yourself.
Okay, so, so probably, this is just if there's multiple fonts in a
file, I would say so St.
B, TT get font offset or index.
I believe that is what that does each FL TTC file may have more than
one font.
Each one has a sequential index number starting from zero call this
function to get the font.
For a given Index, right?
And so real slow, the first font out of there, but that's so that does
exactly what we guessed.
It would do, if you're trying to load a ttf file that had more than
one font in it, this would be your jam.
So that wouldnít the font then if we want to get a bitmap out of the
font, we call SUV get code plate, bitmap.
Remember like I said on the previous stream a code Point, that's the
name in Unicode, for a particular sort of identifier for a glyph.
It's a numerical identifier that uniquely identifies.
Sighs a particular glyph, like the letter T, the Chinese symbol for
meat, whatever you want that.
So if I come in here and say, okay, we got fonts, we're passing it.
The font that we just sort of initialized and then what we would like
to do is we would like to give it some information about what we want
to do for getting that bitmap and we want to get back some information
from it.
Okay.
So, what is that information?
Well, first of all, you can see here that, this sort of this, see, I
happen to just kind of know how this works.
But again, if you didn't know how it works, you'd go in here.
To the documentation.
It would tell you what it is, scale X scale, why?
The code point.
The width, the height, the X offset the White House said, it's Etc,
right?
And so what that does is that allows me to basically get back
information about what the code point bitmap was that was generated.
And the return value is actually the bitmap and it's literally the
bitmap exactly, the way that we've been thinking about bitmaps.
The only difference here is it's a monochrome bitmap like I was
talking about yesterday.
There's really no need to store colors and fonts because
Fonts don't have color information, they're just black and white.
So really all you're getting a 0 to 255, which is about the
anti-aliasing of the font.
And that's it, right?
So we'll start start with that right?
We'll do a little thing here where we go ahead and get the bitmap so
this is the mono bitmap right?
Get code point bitmap.
This is the font that we want, right?
And then we've got scale X scale, y, if the zero, I believe, if you
pass in the scalex just means whatever the scale would nor would be
because my assumption given the Y scale, right?
Now the Y scale is a little tricky and the reason for that is because
the Y scale is not actually given in units that you would care about
in a true type font file.
I think it's given in points or something like this and typically we
want pixels.
And so again being a pretty cool Library, Sean already knew that.
And so what he did is he provided a utility function for us, right?
Which is s EV T, scale for Pixel height.
And what that does is it says given the pixels
And a particular font.
Produce the value.
I should ask you for if I were to want this many pixels tall for the
total font height, right?
So that's a pretty great thing right there, right?
We can just say look you know what?
We want to 20 pixels tall thing maybe since this is a you know a test
one, we want something higher like 128, right?
So it's a big old tall letter
And that's fine.
So we do SUV code Point bitmap that's going to get that for us at 128
pixels tall.
We then pass the actual Unicode code point that we want now since the
Unicode code points on the an C code points happen, to correspond for
the letters that we would care about in ASCII, we could just say that
the letter that we want is an S4 Sean or perhaps you would prefer an
end for nothing's.
I don't know.
Did ask him ahead of time, but presumably one of those two.
We will ask for an n and then when we get back, our width and height.
Again, if we go back to the documentation for get code Point metrics,
oops, get code Point bitmap, rather you can see that at the end here
we get back a bunch of information, right?
So, we can get a width, we can get a height, we can get an X offset,
and we can get a y offset.
And what are
Oh, those values, right?
Well, the width and height are just how big that bitmap is, that comes
back just like we've been working with this whole time and the X
offset and the Y offset.
Our this sort of, if you, you know, he's getting us back a bit map
that, I believe that.
Well, actually, you know what?
I don't know.
I think it gives us back a bit map, that's the tightest bound bitmap.
So it's basically a bitmap that that has no empty space around it.
I believe we'll see you in a second and the
Offset in the Y offset our how you would displace that bitmap to align
it with the rest of the font.
I believe meaning that you know if you have the letter A well it's
kind of a tiny bit map.
And so, it has to be adjusted relative to an H, which is much taller
in order to line them up potentially, right?
So the Y offset might be a thing that's all so but we'll play around
that in a second.
I also pretty sure that Sean does top-down bitmaps.
So we're going to have a little upside down fun happening here and I
don't know if he supports, yeah, top to bottom, right?
So I don't think there's any way to do bottom up in his system, so
we're going to have to do, do a flip of the result of this.
But that's basically it, I think there's a free in here probably for
code Point bitmap.
Hopefully because
You have allocate some memory for it.
Am I missed remembering this free STD free.
Do not know.
Do not know feel like it does need to be freed, don't remember.
But I feel like we should know.
So get code Point bitmap, does it say in the documentation?
so, I guess
Oh it's right above it.
The one place I did not look.
So yeah.
So after we do that
we'll get rid of it, right?
So this is really all there is to it.
There's some more stuff that we're going to do here, but we'll call
this like make nothings.
Test or something, right?
And, and we'll deal with that in a second.
But okay, so if we take a look here, cannot convert from void.
Start outside care.
So, so, he wants these is as you eight stars for whatever reason.
So we'll go ahead and pass this, probably because we're compiling and
C++ mod P compiles.
The sea.
So you probably never even knows about those sorts of things.
Free bitmap does not take one at.
That's true, doesn't takes a user data.
In case you wanted to pass like an arena thing or something.
It.
So that's really it.
That's the entirety of of how we would have to actually interface with
Library again, really?
Really good.
Work here, right.
If all libraries were written this way, handmade hero would probably
be called.
Let's use a ton of libraries to make our game right, but they never
are and so, there you go.
But anyway, so really, really nice.
I tried to point out a number of things that it does, right?
But you can kind of you can just into it, you can see
This was an arbitrary code base.
Handmade hero shots never seen before, right?
It just drops in, right?
It just drops right on in and the amount of work you had to do to get
out.
The thing you wanted was minimal, right was minimal.
Compare this to any say, modern, Microsoft API, or any of the sorts of
things that you see these days.
And it's just laughable, how huge they are and how many lines of code,
it takes to do basic things.
And this right here is
Exactly what you actually want out of a library, you just want,
whatever it was that you were going to do, you want to just call that
thing.
And that's it, right?
And he's really, you know, again just kind of showing how it's done,
you know, that is how it's done.
So let's actually see that this worked, let's actually do something
here.
Let's translate his bitmap into one of the bitmaps that we could use,
for example like a like a loaded bitmap, right?
So I believe we have a make empty bitmap call here.
You know like this.
Let's go ahead and do make, empty bitmap and and we'll just, you know,
we'll just call this that, at start up to, to make ourselves a bit map
of the letter N, right?
So let's do that.
So okay, we'll put the memory read in here, that we need it to use.
I think that's about it.
So we'll just say, okay, make make a
An empty bitmap, we know what the width and height would be because
Sean told us what they were and we don't need to clear to zero because
we're about to actually do all of that work ourselves, right?
So we can then step through every sort of pixel here.
Oops, every sort of pixel that's in this bitmap and we can do our own
translation to our style of bitmap, which happens to be 32 bits per
pixel, not I'm sorry.
Four bytes per pixel size probably it rather than one bite.
Bristly, Sean is 8 bits per pixel, right?
For mono.
So all we would have to do to do that again.
Not particularly tricky.
All we have to do that is we take our loaded bitmap that we get here.
So loaded bitmap result and we'd probably just return that as well.
There's are loaded bitmap, let's go ahead and return that here.
All you would have to do is be able to access our loaded bitmap.
That's again pretty easy.
It's just a the the address is obviously just going to be that result
memory the the
That we could actually do this with the skirt of the standard row,
pointer thing that we normally do.
We could just say, okay, we've got, we've got sort of a destination
and here we've got sort of our row.
This is our Destro, that's going to be our result memory.
And this is going to be despero.
And we just do part Des plus plus.
So writing into this a nation and what we want to do here is we just
want to write in essentially white with Sean's value as the alpha,
right?
So we kind of want something where it's going to be premultiplied,
Alpha bitmap, I guess would be the way to say it, right?
And so if you think about what a premultiplied alpha bitmap would be,
it's just the alpha value replicated, right?
Because if we're going to have 1, 1, 1 as the color and we're
multiplying by the alpha value, it's just going to be the alpha value.
All four channels, right?
So really all we're talking about here is doing that pack again,
right?
So, whatever the alpha is, it's just the alpha goes there.
The alpha goes here, the alpha goes here and the alpha goes here.
Right is all that we would be talking about, right?
So that Alpha value is just going to be the mono bitmap pointer and
we're just going to call that Source since we read The Source in order
and Shawn.
I believe packs them densely.
It's literally just reading it.
It out one by one.
And then at the end here, we just Advanced by our pitch.
Now, we started a half-hour late.
So we've got a whole half-hour to go here.
We're nowhere near Q&A so nobody get too excited about that.
But yeah, so there we go.
So that's roughly what we're looking at here.
Got to do a little bit of cleanup, but I think that's about it.
So it looks like these are actually in stare, right?
So those RS, 32, oops, that
Rather that and I think that is basically it.
So, let's see, we've got our Alpha that's missing in or sign.
Other than that.
We are good to go.
So that just Alpha replicates out there and produces, you know, the
color bitmap for a mono bitmap, right?
Nothing particularly weird going on there.
So that would create us a bitmap assuming that I haven't horribly
ruined everything.
By some kind of mistake in the code.
And so I'll just go ahead and add in here to where we kind of store,
random stuff like this.
I think we tend to have a few of these sitting around test font or
something and I will just make it so that game state test font, right?
Is going to be made like that, right?
So down in here when we first start up the game after we initialize
the World Arena let's say sure why not?
We'll just go ahead and make the test font like so and I'll just
Sure, use the World Arena does not matter.
Do not care, right?
So there we go.
So in theory, you know, if I haven't done anything horrible, that will
at least run, we won't see anything on the screen because we never
drawn anything at that bitmap but we can Rectify that very quickly
certainly.
So let's go ahead and there we go.
So that's actually creating the bitmap or just not running it.
So let's go ahead now and run it and I feel like the right place to
put this would be in our heads viewing code.
That seems like kind of the obvious place for it.
So instead of spewing
As we could, instead just spew a ton of.
Yeah, I mean a ton of ends, why not, right.
So we've got the particle being rendered.
Here, I'll go ahead and say let's not do that.
Instead of doing that, lets go ahead and do our test fonts which I
assume would work.
Fine.
Push bitmap, what is the problem?
Loaded bitmap needs to be an address that's fine and so let's run it
and see how we did.
Did.
Oh, so disappointing.
Where are they?
That's just cruel, really right when you think about it.
So let's go back up here.
Let's step into this and see what what I did wrong there.
What would I would I call that function?
I never remember make nothing's test so let's see here.
What did we do wrong?
Let's let's step in.
Let's step into this guy.
Destro particles result pitch.
It goes.
Destro that's Parts.
Correct.
Thesaurus steps through for every pixel, which is also correct.
That looks roughly right to me.
That looks roughly, right?
I would say so I'm going to go ahead, I'll see anything obviously
wrong.
So I'm going to continue with what I just said and step into it.
I think that's the only sane thing to do.
So let's go ahead and go here.
I assume we actually load this file correctly let's find out if that's
true.
We do you can see that that actually has some contents there will
initialize the font will take a look.
Num glyphs 3,400
That's a lot of cliffs, must have a lot of Unicode in there in aerial.
So it looks, you know, I mean, I feel like that's a reasonable set of
things.
They're certainly let's see how mono bitmap Works amount.
A bitmap comes back, just fine, the width and the height 66 and 83
totally seem reasonable to me.
Nothing particularly we're going on there.
So let's see here, source and desktop
So we come through here, let's take a look or Alpha value.
Here is one
Set a breakpoint there.
So we so we should have been seeing something.
I mean, an alpha value of 4 is certainly very faint, but we should
have been seeing something, right?
I'm going to step to the next row.
I mean there's an alpha value of 70 so clearly I mess something up.
You know?
Unsurprisingly Sean did not make a mistake, I made a mistake and you
know that's that's just how it goes sometimes.
Now it could be that these aren't getting extended to 32-bit that is a
very possible thing.
Let's see if that's true.
So I'm going to take a look at one previous.
From the test.
I want to see what its hexadecimal value is.
That doesn't make a whole lot of sense to me.
What was the alpha value?
Last time around, of course you won't tell me.
So let's see what the alpha value is now it's F.
So my destination is f.
So I don't know what's that looks like I'm doing it properly, right?
At least the trip, seems like it to me.
Yeah.
So that would be full Alpha full white, right?
So that seems pretty good to me.
With height pitch.
So I don't know what's going on there.
That's a little odd to me.
To be honest, that seems a little odd.
So let's hop down to our particle system and see if I did something
separately stupid because that looks like it's a reasonable thing to
want to do.
Hop over here.
Alright, so let's take a look at gamestate Testament.
Hoops state test, aunt.
And let's take a look at that memory.
In fact, I could probably just do this and look at that location.
So you know, pretty clearly there is data there, this should be
drawing.
So I don't really super understand why I'm not seeing
Thing there that is, that feels kind of odd to me.
So, I must be missing some obvious thing, right?
That is the problem right there.
We've never updated our make empty bitmap function to obey the new
rules of bitmaps.
Right?
You remember this tell me you remember this sort of using old Tesco
that we don't really use for anything anymore.
So we need to initialize some other things that are based on the
inputs to this function, right.
We need to actually do with over-height, right?
And I could do a safe ratio one of width over height, right?
For example.
And the Align percentage.
Again, we don't care about weakness Center the end about itself and
that's all fine.
So that's better.
So yeah.
Just some old sale code, they're not really a big deal, again really
easy to track down.
So there's our ends as lovely as they are.
And so, you can see something about our ends.
I suppose, we are ends are a little bit large, so maybe we should.
You know, that that's pretty big, maybe we should go in here and to
turn those down a little bit, you know.
Say that small.
There we go.
So there's our ends for, of course, standing for nothing's.
And if you take a look at what's going on there, you can see that the
ends are.
Well, I guess you, you might not know, right?
If you looked at the ends, you might not know whether the ends are
upside down or, or left to right flipped, right?
You can't really tell, but you do know that,
Something's wrong with the ends right there, not the correct way
around.
And so I happen to know, just because I've used to be Library far, but
we also, I pointed out in the comments just a minute ago.
Is that the STP Library assumes that bitmaps are top-down, right?
And so top-down bitmaps are the opposite of our convention.
Our convention for maps is bottom up.
So what we want to do for this is we want to flip his bitmaps around
when we load them, so ends will be right ways round, right?
so, if we were to do that, if we were to go into the code here,
We've already got something that's converting it from mono to color,
right?
So really all we need to do here is just do this, you know, make this
bitmap right.
The other way is round which would be really easy for us to do, right?
If we could just step the pitch backwards and and start out on the
last row, right?
We'd just start at, you know, Advanced pre Advance the pointer to be
starting at that last row.
Then we just write the rose in reverse order.
That's a pretty trivial way to flip it around and then, hey, guess
what our answer?
Right side up, but it's going to be aware of right now.
The stb library has that convention?
And so when we do our asset processing, we need that to to work.
Now, that's it.
That's all right.
Like I said, this is why when people ask me, if you're going to use
libraries, which would you use?
And I always say the sdp libraries because without fail, they go in
clean, they're easy to use their thought through.
You know, it's just it's very a very, very good set of architectural,
libraries, that can really quickly give you access to a bunch of
really great stuff without all the headache and problematic aspects
that are that plague almost all libraries, which
Is honestly why I don't use any libraries at work, other than
occasionally, the stb libraries, but like I said, I don't want to have
any Library usage in the actual game proper.
So, now that I've kind of shown you how that works in a way that you
can immediately see really where this belongs is in the asset Builder,
where I said that libraries were, okay.
And so if I were to go ahead and drop that back in, here we can sort
of conclude this true type Library Chauncy.
Beautiful library in our asset Builder.
And then when we're doing our astral, our loads and stuff to loading
and processing are like bitmaps and waves.
And that stuff we can do something here where we will process the
actual fonts.
Right.
I'm at that out right now because it's kind of made to be working in.
How should I say?
It's
it's we wrote it with like the arena and the load Tire found, whatever
the gets.
It's not the right type of code, but we're going to want to use basic
that same code.
So I don't want delete it, right?
We're going to be able to use that, so I can go ahead and get rid of
all the tests that stuff.
Now, you know, that can go away and we can go ahead and do that.
And so now we're back to the way we're building before.
But I have moved the stb library out of the game where I said no
libraries allowed into the asset processor where I said libraries are
fine.
So
If it were in here, we now have to have a way of sort of processing
these fonts into usable format by the game, right?
And we have a couple different ways we can do that, but as you can
see, you know, in our game asset system, you know, the most basic way
we could do that is we could just literally shove them into the asset
arrays directly, right?
That's something we could do.
And maybe that's the first thing we should do, that's what we'll do
today.
But then the next thing we're going to have to do is actually extend.
Our asset formats to account for fonts because like I said there's
things like kerning tables and stuff like that, we want to have in
there and so we'd like to have that information stored in the file so
that it can be loaded out, right.
Let's go ahead and take a look at how we might do that.
We have, you know, the asset I kind of want to merge these two things.
I kind of want to merge the asset tag ID stuff, and the file format
stuff and you know, it's, you know, who's to stop me, right?
It's kind of hard to stop me.
You have to admit.
So what I might do, what I might do
is do that.
Right.
Bam, there it is.
Don't see why not can't think of a reason why not?
Delete file, handmade asset type ID.
Goodbye!
So that's it for that.
It was fun, while it lasted, and it didn't last.
And now it's gone and, you know, not really that sentimental about
death.
So that's it.
That's all she wrote.
So, now in here, if we wanted to, we could do something absolutely
ridiculous.
I don't know that this is really what we want to do.
It seems like it might be a little conceived.
I'm gonna do it anyway.
Because why not, what I'm going to do is say all right, there's an
asset here that's just like asset font, right?
This is a really crazy abuse of our asset system.
I don't really want to Advocate doing this.
I'm just going to do it because we can
Yeah.
I mean we just can there's really no other way to say it than that so
I'm just going to say asset font and then I'm going to go into the
test asset Builder and I'm going to have it actually operate on these
on these guys.
All right.
Kidding.
So yeah, so if I come in here for asset font, I'm going to now do sort
of the nonsense that we were doing before this sort of thing, right?
I'm going to do that but I'm going to do it for a font and I'm going
to do it probably in a pretty weird way.
I'm going to just generate like when it does these things I'll just
have a thing that's like right font I guess I don't know.
Where do we want to put this?
We'd kind of broken this up into multiple files just for kind of
laughs I guess for lack of a better term.
But you know we could do a thing in here where we're just like okay
it's definitely a non hero.
So right in here, I guess I'll do begin asset, type assets asset font
and then I'll do end asset type assets.
And yeah, then we'll just do it for I leave here.
Right?
Where we go over a bunch of characters.
So like you know what character we going to do, I don't know.
Let's go ahead and do for care character.
I could even do a you 30.
character equals a
character is less than or equal to z may be able to capitals because
let's just do capitals, right?
And we'll just have it, create all of the letters from A to Z and
shove them straight into the asset system.
Now if you remember the way that we did this, right?
We could do a thing like this where we added tags.
And so, all I'm going to do is introduce a test
I'd called code Point, UT F code point, something like this, or
Unicode code point.
And I'm just going to go ahead and straight up tag the asset with the
Unicode code point, right?
There it is.
I will talk in a while, but why this is a really fantastic?
A bad idea what I'm doing, although maybe, you know, it's something we
want to think a little bit harder about in the future.
But anyway, what I want to do here is say, add a character asset,
right?
And I'm going to do that by using the stb library, right?
So I'm going to do add character s.
Am going to do this in a crazy crazily.
Inefficient way.
Absolutely 100%.
Responsible just horrific lie, irresponsible way, but I'm going to do
it anyway because this is an asset processor and at the moment we
literally just don't care about it.
Speed later on and it's trivial to optimize this but later on we could
do that.
I am literally going to do that.
I am going to reload the entire font file and make Shawn parse at
every darn time.
I know that's rude.
Like I said, no one will be timing us, so it's fine.
So then we're going to have a pure, we're going to have
That font code, it's going to actually be called add character asset
right now.
We're going to take the gloves off here and we're going to go ahead
and and get that working.
And what that's going to take, is this going to take that asset
structure.
I think, is that what it takes?
Think.
That's what it takes.
And it's going to take the font file and then it's going to take the
code point, right?
And so in here we're going to load, I think we have already have a
thing that reads an entire file, right here?
Right.
Again we just kind of emulated that because we wanted to be able to
cut and paste the code essentially.
So we know that we can just call read entire file.
We know that we can pass the font file in like so and then I assume
that we've got a way to free the entire file, right?
So, I
Then we can do something here, where we just do three entire file,
free file, I don't know what might just be free.
I really know what do we do.
Read the entire file.
Read results.
Results dot free.
I have no idea what we did with this code, maybe we didn't even bother
for you then.
I have no idea.
Are you as perplexed about this?
As I am?
I literally don't even remember what we did with this code.
Like it's so far out of my brain at this point.
Yeah, it looks that way.
Oh,
Wow.
No, you know what?
We were kind of clever here.
Interesting.
We did it down here.
So, it's all deferred free.
Hmm.
All right.
That's crazy.
That is really kind of crazy.
All right, well, I don't even know what to say about that other than,
that's crazy town, but I guess that's where we're at.
So we were kind of Sly.
We we actually I was thinking that the asset processor was just kind
of you know, stupid example thing but I guess we actually even cared
about our memory usage.
Yeah.
Well, all right, good job, handmade hero.
Nice work on.
One.
All right.
So anyway, if we read the entire file in here, I just kind of want to
free it because we don't need it.
This is not like the other things where we needed to keep them around.
We don't need to keep anything around.
That's not necessary at.
All right?
So, I'm just gonna get rid of it after it, some of it.
And I assumed that I didn't actually look before, but I assume that
also.
Similarly, inside the, the STP Library I could after in it font, I
could free font, right?
I'm assuming that that
after admit font there is a way to free the font.
Don't know that for sure.
Maybe that's not true, maybe he doesn't actually allocate anything
given us in the file, a defensive fonts function bills.
That's right.
Answer the question.
Yes, allocate.
So you find out for yourself and see you in the front.
Will fill it out.
You don't need to do anything special to free up because the cops are
pure value data.
So I don't that's it.
It's not even doesn't even require any memory.
It just kind of does this magic and leave this alone so yeah.
So I guess that's it.
It, that's the entirety of the cleanup.
So all we really have to do now, is deal with this, right?
We just have to deal with the with this stuff, right?
So yeah, I mean really what we're talking about is
Is his doing this stuff, the loaded loaded bitmap free stuff.
That's crazy.
Totally crazy, but fine by me.
Fine by me.
It makes it easier.
So anyway, when we do the font stuff we do, add character asset.
Come through here.
We get our code point, bitmap out.
And so now we need to do is make a little bit map that we can actually
use as our asset.
So I start by making one.
I guess we should also do a thing here that actually takes a look at
the ttf file stuff, right.
And doesn't actually try to do that unless it gets this back.
Not really necessary because this is again offline, but might as well
do that.
So if I go in here,
Where did it go though?
I deleted what I needed.
There it is.
So I'm going to Define one of these loaded bitmaps.
I am going to do a result free on that.
Like so to do read results, that'll be ttf file, contents.
We've got none of this is necessary.
None of this is necessary at all.
So the memory here is what we would actually have to allocate, right?
So, this is actually not true, we're not going to read the contents.
Remember, here's what we have to allocate, we know the width and the
height.
So what we would do here is we basically say you know the thing that
we free is the memory, right?
And we would moloch sighs enough for our bitmap which is just you know
you 32 width x height like so and that's really about it.
Now I feel like we want this to potentially be padded as well, so we
should probably deal with the pitch.
I'm guessing as a separate thing about know, if we actually
We ever did that.
Yeah, so there we go.
We've got code our pitch equals result, with times bitmap, B, 4 pixel.
So we do actually still have the pitch stuff in there, right?
So I'll go ahead and add that in as well.
Fault.
There we go.
Okay.
so if I were to do it this way, I can then say, all right, what I want
to Malik is basically whatever the pitch is times the width,
That gives me enough space.
I assume this is a void star that comes out so I'll grab that memory
and then that's what we actually want to free.
When this thing is done.
We don't care about any of this stuff.
We don't care about this.
This now operates exactly the same way, right?
It's just exactly the same code that we already did.
After it's done, we free everything and then we're left with a little
bit map that we need now.
I don't actually know, I don't remember at all how we actually deal
with that stuff.
So if you look at load BMP right it returns a little bit map.
So what I might do is just mirror that
That and say that.
Is also a loaded bitmap one that's like get font or get glyph bitmap.
Right.
That kind of just does exactly the same thing as the loaded bitmap one
so we do get glyph bitmap and we say Karis our file name and that just
kind of lets me lean on that a little bit so I can say these both work
in the exact same way.
So now if you wanted to if you want to load a bitmap from file, you
call this if you want to get a glyph, you call this.
And I guess I just need the code Point here, you 32 code point.
And so then the only difference is then I'm going to pass the code
point in here, right?
Instead of just picking n now we probably also want to do a size, but
I'm going to hold off on that for a second.
Again, will kind of come back through probably tomorrow, or maybe next
week and putting the stuff about, like, character alignment stuff,
because we have a bunch of stuff we need to do there.
But okay, so we do add character asset.
What add character s is going to do is to do the exact same code as a
bitmap asset, right?
Because it's the exact same thing.
The only difference is where it gets its loaded bitmap from, right?
So when you do, when you see the load BMP call there, right?
I guess, when we do add bitmap asset,
It's delayed, right?
It's a delayed.
Kind of add, right?
Yeah, so basically it comes down here and it does when it goes to
actually write them out.
It does the load right on sort of the the right, right?
When the right would happen.
So what I can do is I can just make another path here.
If I want to for my fonts, I can say asset type font or something
here, right?
And and then I can just do exactly this path, right?
I can say all right what I'm going to do that, I do exactly the same
thing.
But now I do, you know, load
Fit map.
Like so I pass it the file name and like the code point or something.
We'll figure out how to get that in a second.
It does the same exact stuff that it did here before and then it just
F rights that out exactly the same way, right?
I mean, really, I almost want this path, this code path to be shared.
In fact, I could, I could do that, what I could do is do it like this,
right?
So that don't have to have two of these, I could do like something
more.
Like, yeah, I could do something more like loaded bitmap, you know,
bitmap
And then do this.
If?
Source type equals asset type font else, right?
And now they share it the path and that seems much nicer to me, right?
Okay, so let's keep looking here.
So this we need an asset type font up here, and now we need a way to
store the code Point as well.
And of course, first sample index.
I guess we could just do it this way, right?
Go Point.
X0 make sense again, really, really basic stuff.
I'd literally just I'm doing nothing other than like, pure autopilot.
Right now pure autopilot on just what I'm looking at, what our source
code before.
I even remember how we wrote this thing, my brain been so out of it
lately, I have no idea so I'm just on pure out.
Tap a keg.
Well, we had a system in place.
I'm just following that system right, and that's totally fine.
So there's our local if it map.
So all we need now is just a way to record the fact that we wanted to
do one of these.
And so when we look at one of these things here for add bitmap asset,
right?
We can do the exact same code.
It seems like there's a lot of it is the only thing and so I do worry
a little bit about that and I wonder if these need to be compressed
together.
I'm not sure, right?
It's something.
I would look at since this is the asset processor and this is kind of
more just example.
I don't know that.
I cared that much, but it is something that just like, makes me a
little bit like, maybe right?
But yeah, so there's the code Point like so,
The rest of this stuff is pretty much exactly the way that it appears,
right?
And the aligned percentages again or not really particularly relevant
here.
We can use those the same at the moment because we're going to have to
do some other stuff for font alignment, either way.
Okay, so there we go.
Let's go ahead and what did I do wrong here, read file results, it's
called entire file.
Entire file.
Font file.
Wow name.
Free is contents.
That's totally wrong.
That's just what contents?
Results is the result.
Which is this?
And I think we're almost done, right?
Add character asset, should be returning, a bitmap ID, I guess would
be with that.
Would return.
And then we have a warning.
Actually look a bitmap used that is true because these need to be
trimmed.
Thank you, compiler.
That was a good catch.
So there you go that is that is the the test asset generator so if I
go into the data directory so handmade data right?
And I want to I assume these don't have full paths in them, right?
I assumed they just write things out.
So go into the data directory and I go ahead and run our generator.
It's kind of a Hail Mary.
Pass at this point because all we did was just saying a bunch of code
in there.
We have no idea what's going to do but we might, as well.
Try it anyway.
And we're at the end of the stream, what could possibly go wrong.
Well, I guess a lot of things.
But test asset Builder.
Let's go ahead and run it.
That does not look good.
Actually, I guess we can just click debug the program in Visual
Studio.
Oh my God.
No, oh no.
I picked the old version.
Alright, this is bad news, I don't know what's going on here.
Oh no.
Oh my goodness.
I don't know what's going on here.
That's that's that's some bad news right there.
Okay well let's try that.
Let's try that again.
That was that was very dangerous.
Please, please exit.
Mister, mister developer Studio.
I didn't mean, I think I clicked the wrong version there.
That was that was bad.
Let's try that again.
First of all, I think that was just say that might be a very thing.
We could just catch my inspection but that's that's hilarious.
Don't ever accidentally, click the wrong version of Visual Studio I
guess.
So you end up with your crazy old white color scheme or whatever that
was Visual Studio, 2005 or so.
I don't even know what that was loading.
I have no idea.
This machine is very old and probably has some things on it, which
should be removed.
But how much have not been removed yet by any stretch of the
imagination?
So let me double check that just real quickly.
After he called get code point bitmap, we are going to Fremont a
bitmap that seems reasonable when we met lock.
The memory here for result pitch, this is wrong.
That's probably pretty much the entirety of that error, right?
We weren't Computing.
The size of bitmap is obviously gonna be the height times the pitch,
not the with time, since we've done that many times on handmade here.
So that was just,
Kind of dumb.
So there we go.
So now we have our, you know, our our test to that ha got bigger, but
we don't actually know if any of that worked.
We don't know what any of that did write.
That was just pure conjecture.
So before I go to the Q&A, which is now time for, let's just go ahead
and straight up.
Try it, right?
We're doing our particle B Rd things here.
So right like we got the head
Let's try to change the heads to be fonts, right?
So in there,
When we set that bitmap ID will get a random bitmap from asset font
instead, and we'll see what happens.
Awesome.
So there's a lot of letters.
Going through the asset pack file and you know, I suppose if we wanted
to do something a little bit, fancier, you know, we wanted to to maybe
stick with the nothing's theme.
We could restrict our fonts to only the letters and O thi NGS.
For example, what we could do there is we could use our asset tag
matching system to pick out the correct.
Tag, right?
And so if you remember, we have some code and it's not going to be
very efficient like this could be pretty slow.
We probably would want to build this table at a time because we're
sort of forcing we have not ever app optimize anything in the asset
tag matching system.
So this is this is, you know, this is pushing it.
But if I go ahead and say, get best match asset, right?
What I could do here is I could pass the trance State assets, right?
I could give it the asset Finance as the type ID and then give it an
asset vector.
That was the match vector.
And an asset Vector, that was the weight vector.
And both of these would have absolutely nothing in them, other than
the Unicode code point.
Right.
So we basically say the Unicode code point that we want, let's say is
n.
Did we say capital?
I think we said capital letters.
And then we just do.
Okay, we've got a match vector and a weight vector, and we're just
pulling it out by the tag and the tag is n, right?
Go.
Go for it.
Oh, but you know what?
You actually got to use that.
You can't just call that you got to actually use it.
There we go.
So this will get that, that best match asset note.
No operator takes a right hand of what are you complaining about
right-hand operand February 32 could be bitmap IG.
Operator equals will try to my shower, unless bitmap ID, you and 32
Not sure I follow that.
What does get the best match asset?
Oh because it's getting matched.
Get best match bitmap from so what we actually want
Right, there we go.
So there's the end and so we want it to basically say nothing's,
right?
We want it to say nothing's.
So what we would do there is we would pick a random one from here.
So I guess what I'll do is I'll literally just do just the dumbest
possible.
Thing here's that affects entropy.
So we'll say, you know, switch random.
You know, we've got our random Choice stuff in here, right?
We'll just do random choice.
Random Choice array.
Count nothing's right?
All right.
You know what?
Even simpler.
Just say random Choice from a rake out.
Nothing's.
Use that affects entropy to get us a random letter from Sean's handle.
Right.
Just say nothing's bracket and then we will just put in that string.
Cara, nothing's equals nothing's.
Right.
Seems reasonable.
There it is a little bit big, little bit, big still, I think we're
basically done here.
I think our work here is done people.
I think our work here is done, right?
So there you go.
That's how you use the library, 99% of your success in using a
library, is using a library that Sean made pretty much full stop
occasionally.
There's other people who have made libraries into the Sean style and
they can be good as well.
So, you know, those are the criteria look for one file.
Very good sign API that literally does what you want.
Like word for word.
Like, I want to get a code Point bitmap.
There's a function called get code point Batman.
It gives me back the bitmap right directly
Trivial to integrate with no build options, no nothing, two lines of
code to integrate, you know, you look at all these things, that's what
makes a great library, right?
That was trivial to do trivial to use, you will not have that
experience with basically anything else.
You would still have been fussing with like apt-get if you were trying
to use something else right?
But here we were able to like get it working immediately and then
integrated our asset Pipeline trivially and
That's just fabulous.
So that is basically an episode of handmade hero that pretty much
concretely shows you why?
I always answer the question, what libraries would you use if you are
using libraries on him?
A hero with, I would use the SUV libraries because they're just that
good.
And with that, I will go to the Q&A.
so, if you have questions,
What about what we did?
I would be happy to answer them.
Please prefix your questions with Q Cullen, so I can see them.
And off we go.
Hey, is the best match for the null Terminator?
Ha.
That's right.
So, I didn't quite do that.
We should have, I should not have said a re-cap, should be a recount
minus 1 because it does have the null Terminator in there, right?
Because array count will count the null Terminator.
That's at the end of this.
So really, we just want a recount, nothing's minus 1.
That would be fabulous better, right?
James Woodman until tonight.
I thought there was a use case for see make, which is that if the user
compiles, the program at finds libraries that you don't need to know
where they're installed.
But now it seems the SUV ways.
The only reasonable default.
I think I'm done with cmake for this your future.
I would agree with everything.
You just said my experience is that build programs are only useful
because libraries and programs are constructed poorly and that if you
just construct them properly you can usually build.
Even a very large code Base by just using a one file built now.
That doesn't necessarily mean that.
That's always what you want to do.
It just means that build build tools are extraneous now
You have to make a trade.
You have to make a decision there, but whether you're going to go that
path or not, you know, but it definitely is true that if you do things
in a certain way, it forces you into this whole, make Nightmare where
everything has to be a make file and you're debugging your builds all
the time and there's all this kind of other nonsense and oh, you had
the wrong version of seen occur OC, make passes the wrong switches,
where the switches are there baked into cmake.
And oh, my I've had horrible thing, things happen on projects with
cmake that I've had to work on.
I'll spare you the Gory details of trying to build clang one time.
Oh my Lord.
That's a nightmare.
If you want to build clang statically linked I actually had to send a
document to John Blow to tell him how to do it because he was trying
to do it.
And like I had already gone through the pain and suffering of doing it
so you can make decisions that make you not have to deal with any of
that.
And I highly recommend considering it because for a lot of projects
its way.
Seen or not to go that route.
External libraries Malik free.
What's next?
A Java Java virtual machine.
So yeah for the asset processor.
You want a Java virtual machine?
Go nuts.
Right.
Because it's just a thing that I just don't it's not really part of
him a hero to me it's just there to show you some stuff about how, you
know, you would need to do some things.
So if you want a Java virtual machine and your asset processor, go
nuts have at it.
Can you cause you have used a library and there are riots raging in
the streets.
I see Shadows with pitchforks cast by torch Lights of the Rabid crowd,
run Casey.
I'll do my best to slow them down.
Tips his hat with a with the last, farewell gays.
So I feel like, also, what I might do tomorrow is show you how to do
the exact same thing without a library.
If only to emphasize just how bad, another API can be, because we can
call windows and have it.
Do the exact same thing, but it's really annoying, right?
How would you write debug info?
Now, debug info of what.
Also, if you make the heroes few out letters of my nickname at random,
at least till the end of the Q&A.
Holy hell, I will be so happy.
Well, if you wanted that to happen, why didn't you write a true type?
Rasterizing font Library, man.
You know, you got to earn it.
I noticed, Molly rocket in one of the comments of the stb file.
Did you make contributions?
Not to this library?
That is because I think it was crediting someone from the forums.
Right?
So he's crediting someone from the Molly rocket forums from the old
days.
He looks like this episode was brought to you by the letter N.
Yes, that is totes true, man.
Totes true.
This episode is brought to you by the letter n.
And so, by the way, like also you can kind of see that, that's pretty
easy.
So, if you wanted to rasterize stuff at runtime, I don't know how
efficient stb truetype is, but I assume it's probably pretty
efficient.
So it might even be a good choice for people who wanted to not pre
rasterizer fonts, you know,
now, you know, now you know,
Looks like there are no further questions.
It's a correct.
Rephrase, how would you output sentences to see debug strings like FPS
or error codes?
Well, we haven't quite gotten there yet.
So, so hold on to that question because that is what, you know, that's
what like next week is about, right?
So so hold on.
Is the debug text going to be spewing forth out of the handmade Heroes
head.
Let's hope not.
It would be really hard to read.
No more questions canoe cools, I'm curious.
What do you look at when hiring an artist?
I have no idea how you apply for that.
After watching a few episodes of double fine Adventure.
I'm in awe at how good artists double flying seem to be.
And what kind of richness is you have to have to be one of those.
You also seem to practice more intelligent and Humane approaches to
hiring.
So I guess here's what I'd say, I don't feel super qualified to speak
on that topic at the moment until Molly rocket ship, some successful
games with good art.
I think it's premature for me to talk about artist hiring, right?
It's a new thing for me, doing a real game project at my rocket where
there's like actual people working on it and stuff is a new thing for
me and I feel like
Advice that I have to give it.
This point is largely speculative, it would mostly be saying what my
approach to hiring has been so far but I have no data.
On whether it's good.
And so I feel like that's really a question, ask me in two years after
some of this stuff has had more time to play out and I'll be able to
answer that question, a little more intelligently.
That's about all I can say about that.
Kira.
Caleb.
It's almost 1:00 a.m.
please tell me this won't be a normal thing.
Well, you used to be the standard time was a p.m.
and then we switched it to 5 p.m.
because better for my schedule.
And so, no, it won't be a normal thing because my schedule doesn't
really permit, the APM streams for the most part.
So now it won't be normal, but that used to be normal
all good.
All good.
No more questions, questions and answers.
No more questions and or answers.
I feel like the answer is that there are no more questions and
answers.
All right.
Can you input a tilde sign in emacs with your config?
Because I can't.
Yeah, sure.
I do it all the time on.
Handmade hero, even
that, that's what you're looking for.
I don't look for a practical advice.
Just interested how you do it.
Now.
Off in my friends, tell me I can't give you objective answer data.
Screw it.
I want your opinion.
Yeah.
I mean I'm not I wasn't saying that.
Like I'm trying to tell you that that you know,
That I thought you were asking me for concrete advice or anything that
I was saying like I would rather not talk about it yet because I don't
feel like I have the background to really speak on it intelligently
yet.
So I would prefer to wait for a year or two and have a more informed
opinion about it before I start saying anything about that.
Like I feel like me giving advice on how to build a studio right now
is really pretty dumb because it's just
I don't have a well enough for him to pinion, I just have things.
I'm trying.
And once I have enough of them, sort of tried and see how they go,
then I will have to be able to speak more intelligent Channel gently
on it.
Ever thought of special episodes with guests bonus episodes done on
specific Topics by someone else, being a rad to burger with Jeff or
being as blender digital programmer with Fabien.
I already asked Bobby and to do a stream on optimization for us.
He said he was interested in that so my hope is that yes, that will be
coming.
But that is more for a little later on the project.
I was I was thinking that, you know, later on when the game is
Or full-fledged we would, maybe see if you wanted to kind of go
through some stuff and go, you know, how would you take a look at
optimizing this, you know, what would you focus on?
How would you test it?
What's your approach?
You know.
So yes, I'm very interested in that.
It's maybe something for a little bit further down the road but I am
very interested in that.
Gaston 5 is formatting coming tomorrow.
Formatting might not be tomorrow.
I'm because like I said, I might show how to do what we did today
without a library tomorrow.
Just for completeness sake, in case anyone cares.
But, you know, formatting would probably start next week, at least
would be my guess.
Did you see 2002?
I assume that the bot has already answered you.
Probably but the new language you're probably referring to as Jay I
developed by John Blow.
The guy who did braids and is now doing the witness that he is
developing which is like specifically made with like the pragmatic
programmer in mind and it's been it's been kind of going along really
well, even though it's only a spare time thing for him.
We good.
Looks like it.
Alright, I'm gonna go.
Probably to bed.
All right guys, we're going to wrap it up here.
Go ahead and close this down.
Thank you for joining me for another episode of handmade hero.
I hope you have enjoyed this episode.
This is the one and only time that I'll probably ever show you how to
use a library.
But I am proud to show how to use an STD library to, as like I said,
it's one of the only kinds that I can wholeheartedly endorse.
And so, if you've never used an STD Library, I hope I've done a good
job on the stream and showing you the reasons why it's really so much.
More useful and more satisfying than a lot of other libraries, you
might choose.
And I highly recommend.
Checking out the ones that Sean has made available.
They are all really very useful.
And like I said on handmade hero, we won't be using any libraries in
the game.
So it is library free and the asset processor.
I'd be fine with leaving the stb thing in there.
I have no problem with leaving Libras in the asset processor, but in
general, we won't be using any libraries in handmade here, a proper.
So, I am not using
STP libraries there, but like I've said many times before people asked
me, I would have no qualms about doing, so I simply don't use the stb
libraries on handmade hero because I want to show everyone how to
write the game from scratch.
It's for educational purposes.
It's not because there's anything wrong with UCB libraries.
The SUV libraries are a great service to humanity and if you are
working on a game and feel like you might want to use a library for
something, they are the ones to look at first for sure.
So, I hope I've given you a good production to that, and I hope that
you find them to be useful and I hope that you take some time to thank
Sean Barrett for them.
If you would like to find him, you can find him
Right here, this is his Twitter and not only can you follow him on
Twitter, if you would like to do that, you can also check out his his
twitch page because like me, he's streams, programming streams.
Actually, I guess it's not nothing is what is it?
It's nothing's too or something like this.
He's got it in here somewhere.
There it is.
Nothing's too.
If you want to check out his twitch Channel, you can also watch him
programming his, like, Minecraft engine that he was, he was working
on.
You can, you can subscribe to his twitch channel.
It's twitch.tv slash nothing's too.
So that's the guy who made that library and the other great libraries
that go along with it.
I highly recommend, checking them out and saying hi to Sean when you
get a chance and checking out his twitch Channel, if you want to see
in programming, that is it for today's episode.
Dude, if you want to follow along at home with the code you can always
go to handmade hero dot org and pre-order the source code.
I pulled a pre-order the game and it comes with all the source code.
Even now as we're building it, you can get it every night after I'm
done coding.
You can also if you just want to support this video series because you
like it, you can support our patreon page.
We also have a forums site that you can go to and ask questions and
we've got a tweet bot that you can go to to find out the schedule so
check those out.
I'm too sleepy to talk more about them right now, maybe on the next
string.
So until tomorrow which will be the normal time 5 p.m.
Pacific Daylight time until then everyone have fun coding and I will
see you guys on the internet.