This Isaac asks, do you have any favorite insects?
I don't really like insects, so I don't think I could have a favorite
one.
Good evening.
Casey had a bit of a Nutter moment today while annotating as you went
to the episode guide to double-check what day it was, but the expected
previous day was not there.
But I mean, that's okay, it's not it's not always completely
up-to-date, right?
Because I mean, you know, it's got to be annotated so, but we're on
the right day, right?
So this is 280, 281 282 283, so that's right.
And this one's all up-to-date.
So I mean, yeah, it's at most ever just one behind it seems because
you keep it really up to date.
So
Andrew JDR, if there are multiple GL context and use of the same time
in both have workload simultaneously, how does the GPU GPU driver,
decide to schedule.
Those workloads.
I noticed that window seems to prioritize the active Windows opengl
context, if you happen to have multiple opengl context, the same time,
so that's kind of interesting.
I guess what I would say there is I have absolutely no idea.
There's obviously a fair bit of
Rot in the opengl windows binding layer because again, Microsoft wants
to push their standards so they tend not to support opengl really at
all.
But the driver vendors do want to support it and so they typically
have sort of their own Solutions and stuff like this.
So I would point out for example, on Nvidia, it would depend on what
kind of cards are using the drivers for their high-end cards.
Will actually allow you to Target different.
Gpus separately and other things like this for opengl context.
And so I could imagine that on some of those drivers they might do
things like actually balance across multiple gpus if you have them and
all that sort of stuff.
I don't know.
But what happens in terms of balancing it otherwise I really couldn't
tell you.
I don't know that's a good question for like an Nvidia driver Dev or
something and be like what you know?
Let's say I've got three applications open that are all using opengl.
What do you know?
How are you?
Deciding how that gets sliced up and is it you know bay just based on
the same priorities you know if if an application at a higher priority
than other application would it get higher opengl priority to or you
know and I don't I have no idea.
It's not something I've ever really looked at.
What are your thoughts on flowchart, based programming?
And do you think they are effective in game programming?
I don't think I really know what the term flow chart based programming
would mean.
Obviously I know what a flowchart is, but I don't know that.
I know what it would mean to say that you were doing flow chart.
Based programming, if you're talking about something like a uml
diagram, oh my God, no.
I don't think they're useful for any kind of programming, but that may
not be really what you mean by flow chart based programming.
So I don't know.
You're paying on the Vulcan Epi.
I do not like it.
Okay, so flow chart based programming you meant
Like a visual programming language, for lack of a better term, like
sort of the kind that you use to make Shader graphs in Maya or those
sorts of things.
My opinions on those is, I don't really see the value in them from
everything I've ever seen, all they do is help.
You make very simple things.
Without having to, you know, by dragging and dropping some nodes
around, right?
But making simple things is never interesting to me, like I don't need
a programming language to help me make simple things.
I can make simple things and see really easy, right?
The hard part about anything that you're trying to make programming
wise is making complex things.
And that's where those systems always seem to completely fall over,
right?
It's like, as soon as you start to make complex things, you've got
this huge rats nest of like nodes with, like all the stuff between
And someone comes looks like I have no idea what I'm looking at,
right?
So I've never really seen an interesting thing done with graphical
programming languages.
I, which is not to say, I don't think there's a value to be had
potentially in them.
I just don't think people have made anything interesting with them
yet.
Like they haven't made one that actually leverages the graphical
aspect to do anything other than make it harder to create complex
from, which is the opposite.
It of what you would want to do, right?
You'd want to leverage the graphics to make it easier.
Which I think about structured editors.
I like the idea of structured editors but I've never really used one,
so I don't have like a.
I like the idea that editing should be more about what your editing
and not just about generic text.
So I think it's a prep like it's a, it's a good direction, the
probable direction to go in but I don't really know like
Much about it in practice because I've never used one.
And I don't know whether anyone's made one, that's like actually
usable and good, you know?
Susan, Kim 73.
That's a great quote.
I think that the main use case of boxes and arrows type programming is
to convince non-programmers that they're not programming.
It's a very good way to say that.
Where are we on the handmade hero to do?
I don't know.
Like the to do is just there if I run out of things to do that, I'm
actively doing right?
The to do is like, wait, what should we do now?
I don't know, and then I can go look at the do, but if I have stuff
that I want to do, I like to do list or just in that, for that case.
If I'm afraid that I might forget about some things, I might do.
And so then later, when I'm, like, I need something to do.
But right now, I know what I want to do.
You know, I know when I
Wind, we're working on so it hasn't been a problem.
Alright stream begins now.
Skip this go and stop recording.
Start recording.
Hello everyone and welcome to handmade hero.
The show we could a complete game live on stream.
We are well essentially what we've got to do is crack open a new
aspect of our simulation and get it a little bit more up to speed.
We fixed a bunch of things with it as we're sort of on our march to
doing more final Style game code and we kind of need to start
addressing physics and other things like that.
We, you know have had sort of a makeshift
Poor little thing for physics and movement in there for a very, very
long time, but we need to now start getting into a more realistic.
Not realistic in the, in the sense of behaves like real physics, but I
mean, a more professional, more complete, a more shippable state for
that parts of the code.
So we've got a couple different things we need to do.
And there's also a little bit of renderer thing in there as well.
So we've got essentially, two things.
One is that we have to go.
Figure out how we're going to make the physical side of things work.
And the other part is we got to figure out how we want to deal with
the multi-plane Z and I said yesterday, how I wanted that to shake
out?
We've got to actually do the work of making it clean and efficient
through the renderer.
So let's go ahead and dive in here.
Today is day 283.
So if you would like to follow along at home, you're going to want to
start with de 282 source code because that's what I'm starting with.
At the moment.
So let's actually, I should probably try to load something.
First before I build building, nothing does not help us much.
And let's go ahead and run this here.
Right, so here's where we left things.
We sort of were playing around with multiple Heights here and you can
already see to.
We have like our makeshift sorting, we kind of broke our mixture,
sorting on the guy as well because we have, you know, he doesn't quite
sort correctly because we used a bias there.
So, when his his head doesn't we got, we got tons of stuff.
We want to fix in, in all of that stuff, right?
And so now is a good time to kind of start cracking, open all of these
things.
How the, how the simulation Works physically and how the
He gets handled so we can start to take these elements that are not
quite right and make them into something that we're confident in so
that we don't have to constantly deal with them as we sort of go to
ship other parts of the game.
So anyway, in terms of what we should do first, I think probably the
easiest thing to do would be to focus on the world representation
first and get that down to where I'm happy with how the Z is handled
there.
And say, this is done, this is how he works because we're I don't
think we're that far.
Are from being able to do that.
And then what I'd like to do is shift over to the renderer and make it
so that representation flows into the renderer nicely and so that we
can get rid of our sorting bugs and that sort of stuff at that point,
right?
Because the renderer sorts quite nicely, but we don't feed it.
Very good information right now.
So it ends up doing, you know, it ends up not knowing what we want in
front of other.
It doesn't know for example that the heads always puts up here on top
of the body, so it can't ever do that sort correctly and so there's a
bunch of things like that that we just
To start treating more seriously.
Okay?
So what I'm going to do, first of all, like, you can already kind of
see that I have problems.
For example, I can't go, I can't always go nor like if I'm trying to
go north.
I and the reason for that is my head actually runs into it collides
with the ground tiles because right now, these ground tiles that I'm
hopping on these little those little Center dots that I'm hopping on.
They actually have a collision volume.
We're not drawing The Collection volume, but and that means my head
could run into it and stop and not go any further, right?
So that's not necessarily a bad thing.
We do want the cops to occlusion volumes but again, we haven't really
taken the time to go in and now say, now that we know exactly how this
stuff works, let's make the Collision volumes actually be reasonable
and how they're going to be structured and all that sort of stuff.
And then furthermore, we've never really fully done how we want our
Collision detection of work.
So now that we have a little bit more of a solid understanding of how
the game behaves.
I want to go in there and kind of make that a little bit more real and
I should probably
only take a minute to sort of talk about the fact that since this
game's design is kind of peculiar in the sense that there's this
concept of the, the head is a separate piece from the body, right?
And I move the head, you know what I actually control is, I control
the head as I move back and forth.
What's interesting about that is the body always moves to a discrete
point, right?
And we talked about how that's kind,
An important part of the game design.
What that means is that I have to start thinking about how Collision
detection is going to work in a very game, specific way, right?
We are so far from wanting to simulate realistic physics here because
if we were going to simulate realistic physics, we did.
We would lose sort of the binary nature of.
Can I hop to this next Square or can't?
I right, because what happens if maybe there's some kind of and I'll
jump to the pun intended, I'll jump
Over to the Blackboard here for a second.
Let me go ahead and scroll up here, so there's my day 283.
So what you know I am wanted to get across here was just if I imagine
two points that I can hop between and the hero doing the Hop, like so
while the hero is jumping, okay?
So the hero is like here and jumping up and it comes to here, right?
You know what word would happen if there was someone else who was in
transit to this square at the same time, okay?
There's a couple of different things that could happen here and we
would have to decide how we wanted to treat them one way.
Is that they both bounce off each other.
So the fact that two people try to enter the square if they Collide
before landing on the Square then they bounce back to their previous
square.
Right.
Another is to to take whoever was getting in first and use that,
right?
And another is that they I don't know.
Some other thing where they both
Probably the square somehow.
I'm not sure.
Right?
But no matter what I'd pick, you can see why this is a tricky problem
because I can always add another layer of problem.
To it to make the solution, not make sense.
So for example,
Let's say I was doing the exact same thing, right?
So two people inbound here, and whatever the rule is that I pick.
It's going to involve this one getting bounced back.
But while that's happening, someone else is inbound on this square,
right?
So, now, if this person reaches disc, where first, and this person
reaches disc, where first, this person who was caught here, has
nowhere to land.
Right there is effectively caught in limbo in between two squares and
there's no where they can go, right?
And so one of the things about this game that's kind of tricky and I'm
not sure how we want to deal with it, is there has to be a solid set
of rules that have nothing to do with physics, that are about how to
resolve who gets to stand on what squares win because the game is very
much about the concept that people have to be standing on a particular
Square.
That's a requirement of the way, the game is designed.
So there has to be a set of consistent rules as to how this is going
to work, if that makes sense.
So there's a couple different things we can do.
One is we can do some kind of a halfway requirement, right?
So what we could do and this is, I guess what I'm kind of leaning
towards doing is we could say, all right, when you hop on a square,
essentially, if you are ever inside this boundary of the square, that
means you are occupying this place.
And no one else is allowed to hop into it, right?
When you get to this boundary, there is then a transactional
operation, which occurs, which says am I allowed to occupy the square
that I was hopping into.
And if the answer is yes, then you will now relinquish the square
atomically and take this one, right?
And you will be allowed to continue down and land here.
Okay?
If not if you get to this boundary and you are not allowed to take
that square, then you will be
I sort of reflected back and you'll land back on the Square that you
took because you will never release the square unless you can take a
new square and my thinking is that's probably what I want the physics
system to be based around.
Okay.
So, I think we're going to effectively have two types of things in the
physics system.
All right ones that operate like this and we'll call this Atomic cop.
Right?
And you can see nothing to do with physics physics, really.
It's just I cross over the the halfway boundary between two points.
I try to take that point.
If I can't take that point, I'd go back to my other point, right?
And I think that's how we would have to do it.
So something like this.
And the other one is basically projectile.
Or like, you know, floating, right?
So something that's actually kind of not occupying a square.
It just kind of floats around and so it's just it can started be doing
more standard physics where it just it can bump and move and it
doesn't it doesn't necessarily have a concept of occupying anything,
right?
And this would be Primal.
So this is the most important thing because all of the heroes
gameplay, obviously requires that.
But then this is obviously secondary.
And, you know, this the head is this and the body is this and enemies
would be, you know, a combination of these as well.
Like, some enemies would have both, some enemies would have only one
or the other.
Obviously, like things like, you know, projectiles that are that are
sort of thrown or whatever would be.
If you talk how I feel right now this is not as easy as it sounds
unfortunately as well because it means that we sort of have to do a
hybrid physics e.
Well,
Maybe didn't send me the you know that I shouldn't say it's not as
easy as it sounds.
I guess.
What I'm where I mean is there are some subtleties involved here even
with the well-articulated rule that I was sort of suggesting and that
is that you can imagine.
We still might want situations where let's say there's a line of
points like so
And someone's going to be knocked back.
We still want the concept of them sort of flying back through here,
right?
Oh, dear.
I drew behind my head.
I was wondering why it wasn't showing up.
And it's like, I forgot there's a, there's a me down there.
So let's suppose that the hero is standing here, you know, and they
get knocked back.
Well, they may want to slide backwards across many squares, right?
And so, you know, the concept of hopping, it's really not hopping,
it's just the concept of physical movement, but that has to be
transactional in the points that it's occupying, right?
And so, you know, we're not going to do it as a specific hopping up.
Peter kind of thing.
We're going to have to do it as a movement operator, that just happens
to be transactional.
As far as points are concerned and we'll just have to make sure that
that's okay.
Whereas anything that's a projectile doesn't have to have that it can
projectiles, could be allowed to do whatever they want.
And you know so long as they don't collide with something that's fine.
And presumably they would have to have the rule that they are sort of
secondary in the sense that this is a hard constraint and so,
So this constraint means that no matter what happens, if a projectile
would be occupying the location where somebody needs to return to in
order to continue owning their square.
That projectiles going to have to move out of the way or you know even
to sort of a difficult difficult situation.
For example, where let's say we have
Four Points here and there's people standing on each of the four
points, right?
It could trap a large projectile in here in in between and stuff like
that is just going to have to be allowed, right?
Because the but the the concept of the square occupation is going to
have to be Primal and going to have to be the most important thing and
you're never going to be allowed to evict somebody from Square without
having a new square for them to go to.
Now, there's some tricky Parts about this and the tricky Parts about
this, I will, I will sort of illustrate to you now.
All right, so let's suppose we have a scenario where an enemy creature
is moving in this direction and the hero is up here and wants to move
in this direction, right?
Well, the problem with this scenario is that if the hero reaches the
halfway point here, before this enemy reaches, the halfway point here,
then the hero would get rebuffed right.
It would get the ear will get stopped there essentially.
Like, I can't move through it.
I don't know if that's a problem, but you can see why, you know why?
It might be because as this enemy is moving off of this Square, it
will appear to the player as if they could occupy it.
Because, you know, the enemy's gotten to there, by the time you get to
hear it seems like I should be able to hop in there, right?
And so, I don't really know what we want to do.
To do about that problematic scenario, but you can see why it's
problematic.
Hopefully, right, very tired.
So yeah, I don't really know what we want to do about that, but that's
an example of something that, you know, I think is going to cause US
problems.
It's a challenging aspect of the game design, that's just the way it
goes.
But hey, you know, the point is to do some real programming on the
stream.
Not to just do a little simple crappy things.
So we've got a complex thing to worry about and so we'll worry about
it and that's fine.
I don't have any other bright ideas about a how to handle this any
more smoothly than
Then a transactional taking of the squares and the reason for that is
if you if you don't do transactional taking of the squares, then you
could easily end up in a situation where somebody who needs to stand
on a square cannot stand on a square, right?
If you don't require it to be transactional, that could happen.
Very very, very, very easily.
So I don't really know.
I don't really know how we could do something all that much different
than this scheme.
Obviously, we could push this scheme a little further and say things
like, well, if I'm trying to move into a square and there's already
someone in that square who is also trying to move to another Square.
See if they can take their next Square early, right?
And then I can take, you know, my Square early.
That's one way to do it another way to do.
It would be to say that as soon as someone starts trying to take a
square they can take it if it's available, right?
And that way you would you would get in a situation where this person
is technically already a vacated the square and so I can move in
anytime I want you know, maybe that turns out to be a better policy
but again at the fundamental level, it's still basically all the same.
It's still basically just about how quickly I'm sorry that
Need to transactionally.
Take release my current square and take a new one.
And so if we build the system around that, unless I'm missing
something, I think we need that.
And so if we build the system around that, then whatever our most,
whatever our favorite rule ends up, being at the end of the day, no
matter how hacky that rule turned out to be.
Maybe it's this crazy heinous thing that we've tuned for all sorts of
weird game, play scenarios, as long as it's all built on a solid,
underlying concept of
A transactional switch from one squared or another.
Then presumably we can make that other part as happy as we want and
we'll never have any bugs of the form.
This person can't find a place to stand because the transactional
underpinning would always ensure that that wouldn't be a problem.
Alright, so now that once we sort of have that in mind, let's talk
about a couple of the things that are a little bit tricky here and
might be problematic.
So you could imagine once we have the concept that you're trans
actually on a particular Square, then we would probably also want to
entertain the following notion and it may be such that.
We would rather not entertain this notion for reasons of undeserved.
For reasons of undefined ability or something.
But let's say I introduced the concept that I've got sort of a
merry-go-round here and here are the points that I can stand on the
Merry-Go-Round or well actually let's make it simple.
Will just say that I could stand on these points here.
Okay.
And this thing can rotate in space.
Let's say,
so this thing can spin around and here is, you know, it's sort of
Center Point as it rotates around.
If the hero was standing on one of these, we would probably expect the
hero to rotate with it.
Right now that wouldn't be particularly difficult to do because we
know that the hero was embedded at this particular point, we could
remember the offset of that particular point.
In fact, we could just store that as his location.
So when he comes back again, we could say, oh he was supposed to be on
this particular point of this entity.
Where is that point put him there?
Right?
So it's pretty easy for us to allow you to rotate things like this to
rotate.
And have you stand on them?
Here's the problem with something like the heroes head.
Again, if that happens to be a projectile, right?
If it's one of these then what could happen is imagine I somewhere
have sort of a beam let's say or something that sticks in here and
this beam is hovering like over the top of the merry-go-round.
Well, when I rotated into it, my head is going to hit it, right?
And my head cannot pass through the beam.
My body will pass under the beam and my head and my body will become
separated, right?
This would be like decapitating the hero right now.
Probably, we don't really want that to happen.
So, what we would normally do is, we normally say, well, okay, you
know, if the hero is getting separated, it would behoove, you know,
the head would have to
pushed our side of the body would have to get pushed to move to
another nearby point where it could stand that wasn't getting
Underneath right.
And maybe we could devise some kind of an algorithm to make that
happen.
The problem I'm worried about is what if there aren't any other
squares.
So, first of all, you could imagine the simple case where, what if we
created and maybe the answer is you know, you just don't do this, but
I'm just going to give you the simple example.
First, what if I created a thing with?
Only one stand above point, right?
So it's effectively, just a beam like this that you're standing on and
there's another beam here that you can't that your head can't go
through.
So as I rotate through here,
Head and my body separate and there is no point.
There's nothing out here for me to push the body back onto.
Right.
What do I do in that scenario?
Similarly, let's say I never construct anything like that.
Let's say I construct something just fine.
So here is the, you know, the situation again and here is the blocking
beam.
And the heroes standing here.
We're going to come through here.
Let's say there's all these other points over here that he could stand
on.
Well great when he hits their will try to figure out to push them back
to him but what if there's just monsters on all of them?
Right.
So it wasn't that we created a situation that made it impossible for
the hero to do the right thing and knock adopted.
Its that, there is no way for them to actually hop off because well,
the series have look, here's means of egress right.
So that's Troublesome, right?
And there's a couple different ways we can address it.
One way, we can address, it is just say we never make this in the
game.
Right.
There is no such thing as head level obstacles.
And thinking that through,
I feel like for the most part, I can't think of a lot of reasons why,
it wouldn't be totally acceptable to say.
There's no such thing as optic obstacles, which prevent the head from
going somewhere, but not the body, right?
We could say that we could just say that, you know, whenever the head
runs into something, it pushes it out of the way.
So there's no such thing as soon as it exists at the head level, that
stops the head and furthermore, we would
Really care about anything like decapitation.
If it happened to a monster because we could just kill the monster and
that would be fun for the player.
What we don't want is to suddenly have the hero get killed just
because he can't seem to move off of the thing he's standing on,
right?
That that is not really a great feel for the game because we don't
want to, you know, we don't want to create a bunch of circumstances
where the element of the gameplay, which is you have to stand on these
points, becomes a nuisance for the player, the idea, is that supposed
to be interesting for the player to do that and there's a bunch of
mechanical
Annex that revolve around it.
So what we don't want to do is make it so that it's oh it's this thing
where you weirdly get decapitated.
Because we can't find a place to jump off of this swinging thing or
whatever.
Right?
So one you know, one thing is we say no have of obstacles.
The other thing we say is no, you know, no writable 's
Right?
If there isn't a thing that's, that's inexorably moving.
Then it's not a problem.
The other thing we could say is writable Czar halted.
Right.
So, if the, if the, if the hero is on something, he runs into
something like that, then it will stop the thing that's spinning
It just and you just, you know, it would not ever be allowed to
continue decapitating the player in that way, right?
So there's some options.
I don't know, which one's the right one, but, there you go.
Now, what's interesting to me is, I don't know if I actually have any
cases, where I care about head level obstacles, I haven't really
thought of anything, particularly important gameplay-wise where that
would be useful.
The only time you would care is if the head and the body got separated
by some kind of a, you know, you had some kind of magical ability that
allows you to do that.
You wanted there to be different things that the head, you know, the
head still had to navigate a certain path instead of just being able
to float over things.
So there were like these head level obstacles, but even so I don't see
why those obstacles.
Couldn't be all the way up and down.
Like it would have to be a reason why you wanted the body to be able
to go places that the head couldn't go right.
And furthermore, I don't know how important that right, that would
really be anyway.
Because it's much, you know, I can certainly make it so that the head
can go places.
The body can't go, I just can't make it to the body.
Can go places the head can't go.
So, I don't know.
I don't know.
I guess I don't really have a strong opinion of that one way or the
other.
But like I said, you kind of see the basics of what has to happen so
we can ruminate on that a little bit more but for now, hopefully you
can see the first sort of stuff that we would have to build physics.
Wise is we just have to know that transactional movement element.
And so right now that's happening entirely in sort of our hacked
gameplay code for the hero and only the hero is thinking about this,
right?
But we need to have happen very shortly.
Here is we want everyone to be going through that system.
So what I want to do is I want to change over to having that notion of
what square, you know, I'm occupied.
I want to start making that.
I think be inside the same region as a first class thing.
All right.
So, let's see.
I'm going to go ahead and open up some region.
And entity.
And right now, the way that we're doing this is every time.
Like, and for example, in these situations, all this stuff, every time
we are talking about those movement points in the hero, we actually
make that we do that operation every time through the loop, like every
frame, we do a search again to figure out what, like point the head is
over and what point the body is over and so on, right?
So what we could do is start by making this a little more formal,
okay?
And have it so that we actually track what point the the hero is on.
So go into the Sim region at a formal concept of the query for where,
you know, what's the closest one or whatever, at a formal concert of
that, where we can then record that in the entity struck and say, here
is where I'm actually, here's what I'm actually standing on this
particular point.
Okay.
Insu movement, from and movement to would be good examples of of what
that would be right?
Because movement, from, and movement to right now are always two
points.
I'm going from this point to this other point and so we would want
these and now be semantics in the sense that these are now entity
traversable 's, right?
So we would have something like, you know, entity traversable or maybe
just a traversable
Reference.
You know, in a traversable reference would be a lot like an entity
reference.
Right?
Here's the end of the reference, but in addition to the entity
reference would have another piece of information.
Like, so where we said, what's the the index of of the that
reversible?
So we can go grab that other entity and pull the traversable out, the
one that we care about specifically.
And so here, when we have movement to, and movement from, I could
start by saying, well, alright movement to movement, from are now
going to actually be traversals, right?
So I've got reversible here.
And traversable here.
Like so, so what would happen?
If all I did was just change the code to this, right?
And if I was so inclined, you can imagine me actually pulling the V3
out of here as well.
Where we just, when we unpack, we do it.
I don't know that we want to do that because entities could move
during Sim and we probably don't want to worry about that.
So I'm probably going to keep it.
This.
All right.
So let's take a look at what's going on here.
So here is the identity calls, right?
This is interesting, this is still called a damn, they probably want
to name it, something better but this is this is essentially what
brings it into the into the simulation.
And what you can see here is we're taking the movement from and we're
applying that chunk Delta to it, which is how we produce the offset.
But now that's not what these are going to be.
So now what we want to do is these are going to be again delayed by
one.
Since we want to look up specific traversable, 's we
Want to process these until after when we do our Loop through, right?
So these are going to become things where we do load traversable
reference, like so.
So we're going to connect this up in here where we do Sim region desk
movement, from, right?
That's going to be a thing here where we do
are loading.
So movement from a movement to are both going to get loaded this
reversal references.
So in load entity reference
Oops.
Where we hit the hash table here.
This is actually going to be exactly the same thing.
It's just going to, it's just going to sort of think through, right?
So here's load reversible reference, we've got our traversable
reference
And what we're going to do there is say, alright first, let's try to
get the the try to get the entity.
So let's load the entity reference
for the traversal reference.
then if we got the remedy,
well then I guess that's it.
Now that I think about it, since we're not going to pull the V3 out of
there.
We're good.
So that's load reversible, F reference and we're going to need the
reverse as well.
So we're going to need a storage reversible reference and again it's
really just a thunk at this point because we don't have anything else
that we need to do in particular about it.
So all it's going to do is call store entity reference on its
traversable on the entity part of its reversal reference.
Okay, let's compile that here.
Sim Regan is not a thing.
So now we come down to here where we're doing.
Our story entity reference.
We're going to do the same thing here where we store the traversable
reference.
Again, it's exactly analogous.
It's just a translation in and out part of the process.
And now we just have to go work on the actual code that we had from
before.
Where
In our movement, from, in our movement to now, this shouldn't be too
hard because our get closest.
Reversible already knows this piece of information.
So, presumably it shouldn't be too difficult for us.
All right.
So let's keep going through here.
I just want to take a quick look to see if there's anything.
Any other any other gotchas in here?
I don't think there are.
Yeah, so that's really it.
So now we just have to write that code.
So the first thing I'm going to do is say well this get closest
reversible.
I don't know that's sitting up here somewhere.
This get closest reversible is really going to be something that
happens in the same region.
I think at this point it's probably going to have to be accelerated
and a lot of other stuff blah blah blah blah blah right now.
So I'm just going to put that
In here.
And then we're going to take a look at it.
So here is a are streaming stuff.
Let me go ahead, I know where it should be, probably down at the
bottom for now.
So when we call get close to traversable, now, what we're going to do
instead of providing the V3 is we're actually going to want to provide
one of these references.
So we're going to want to provide a traversable reference.
So when we come through here will know whether or not it was found
right?
We still have want that.
But now when we have like test entity in that stuff, we're going to
want to say.
OK, the result here and I'll clear the result first, right?
I guess.
Well actually know what I can do.
I can look at the found if it was not found, right?
I can take the result entity and set it to 0, basically, just clear it
out.
So in here, if I'm going to search through the volume group for which
traversable it is, then all I need to do is when we find the closest
one, instead of storing the position of that thing, which is not what
I actually want.
Instead, I'm going to go ahead and store.
So yeah, there's probably one of the thing I want to do but it will
get that saying I'm not going to store the position of it, instead of
at the moment.
I'm just going to store The Entity pointer.
So here is our, what is it?
Test entity.
So I'm going to start a test entity and then I'm going to store the
traversable index that we used to find it.
And that's the p and X, right?
So now we're basically recording.
This is what the entity was standing on semantically.
This is what it is and we're passing that back.
Right?
So instead of a position in space for saying, this was the thing that
you were standing on.
Okay?
So now when we call that function, we're going to have to fix that.
What did I do?
Test entity.
Oh, that's right, that pointer and you as well, there we go.
So now in here when we have get closest reversible, we're not going to
anymore be getting a point.
Instead, we're going to be getting a thing that we should be standing.
On.
And so what I want to do is have a way of making that be be able to
generate a point.
So this closest P I'm still going to actually say is a thing that we
actually want but instead I'm going to have a traversable reference
here.
Like so and I'm going to pass that.
And then assuming that we get into, we get to a point where we
actually found it.
Then I'm going to say closest P equals like get traversable in World
space kind of a thing, right?
Let me go ahead and see.
I don't quite remember how we how we were phrasing that get SIM spaced
reversible, right?
I think that's what we wanted.
I'm not.
Why is it?
Why is that a
Double.
What?
What is what is that?
Let's just be honest, what is that?
I don't even understand what that is.
I want to know, oops.
So there's an image out, so I guess I guess it was just me providing
that there might be in the future, some more stuff there.
I guess.
So get some space traversable is all we really want.
I'm going to go ahead and say that it's this traversable index.
And you know what, I can probably get rid of the traversable index.
It seems like, I'm just gonna end up typing that all the time.
Let's see here.
Where's the reference?
There it is.
I should probably also stack that up here.
So yeah, so we're going to say, get some space.
We're going to ask for that reversible.
But first, I got to clean this up because I decided I didn't want to
keep typing traversable again and again and again because it's a hard
word, you type.
Well, it's not that hard but you get the idea.
So it gets into space.
We need to pass it.
Watch the stem region.
The V3 of what
Go away.
Oh wait.
No that's that's not right.
It's just the entity, the index.
So I literally just say exactly what's here.
In fact, what I can do is just make it so that there's a thunk which
would do exactly what I want because it's literally just a call to
this, right?
So if I say gets in space traversable and just pass it a traversable
reference,
Then we would just do.
The thunk.
Manuel currying.
Well, not really but you get the idea.
All right, so any traversable point results,
And so that is now allowing us to basically translate this code
without really changing anything.
Right so okay so off we go, we gotta pass the address of that although
I suppose we don't really actually know what I think about that's
going to be an inline function.
There's no point in really passing the address, we might as well just
pass it directly give the optimizer less work to do.
Alright so here we are getting our sins face
First of all, we only want the P value out of it because right now is
nothing else in it and future maybe we do something else.
In this case we're still going to do exactly the same thing
traversable reference, reversible.
I'm going to go ahead and grab that.
Out.
And then I'm going to say, if found I'll grab the closest to pee,
And there's the traversable.
As we come through here, eventually then we're going to get to the
part where we oops pee in there.
We're gonna get to the part where we need to start storing it.
So now when we do editing move from and then they move to in this
case, now we just have to take whatever thing we were standing on and
and write that down as are from.
And then our move to is now just a traversable that we found before.
Right, so that's pretty easy.
So this is our only fellow who is somewhat problematic here.
So we're going to have to deal with that one in a second.
Now, when we get to movement from and movement to, you can see that
here.
And here, we're using them as actual positions.
So what we're going to have to do is essentially ask right movement
from is going to have to be a get some space traversable for my entity
movement from
Right, and I'm going to have to do.
This operation.
So I'm going to do any movement from when I get this in space
traversable and then I will now be able to use it as a position,
right?
And the same thing is going to be true.
Here course, I gotta do the psoas.
Same thing is going to be true here when we're about to, like, lock
the movement to the movement too well, and I guess I should also do
movement.
When I do movement to, I want the exact same thing.
And what I can do here is I can just make these be things, we grab
when we're in the hopping mode because we know that we need them,
right?
And then
Where that we were using them.
We just use them that way, bear now.
So really, our only problem now is we're not actually tracking the
traversable, we're actually on.
That's not really a huge problem, obviously, because we're saying that
now things need to know that if you're a Hopping kind of a guy, you
would need to know where you were, so that should be down to our only
error at this point.
I think, right?
So that's the only thing that we have to do.
So let's take a look at how we're going to do that for the entity.
Right.
Here's our kind of our movement code, starting to shake shape for
people who do hopping sorts of stuff.
I'm going to do at revert traversable reference the movement from
movement to, I guess to some degree.
We don't we can maybe talk about this in a different way.
So instead of movement from movement to what we could say now is
instead of that will just say, you know,
Standing on and moving to.
Let's say, right?
So in here will change these two standing on.
And moving to.
And standing might be a bit of a stretch but we'll know what we mean.
Because now we don't ever need to think about this other than just
thinking of it as we always have a value there.
So when we jump from one place to another, all we're setting is our
movement to we're not actually ever setting are standing on because
that's always going to be tracked and then when we set our entity P
here the entity P, yes, it was set to move into but we'll also set our
standing on right to be movement to as well.
The wrong movement to
Right.
And this is again, we're taking steps to set the stage for that
transactional process because you can see the transaction happening,
right here, right?
We're already starting to say, okay, we're taking our movement to it
making, it are standing on, right?
We can't do it this way because this is, there's no guarantee that
that thing is always available.
So this is the part that will slowly start to come out into a system
that allows us to do that transactionally, right?
So you can kind of see where I'm trying to go.
That where I'm trying to get it down to a thing where we do exactly.
The kind of transaction that I was talking about, but just not in a
centralized way, and then will centralize it.
So, here we go with our movement to movement from.
That's got to be standing on and moving to
Oops, and I forgot that they're moving to, right?
And now we have no errors but we have no errors.
We do have a problem and our problem is that when we initialize our
entity, we don't actually put it in.
Particular position.
And that's a problem.
Now, if we're saying the enemies always have to occupy a particular
Square, what that means is we're going to have to actually remember
when we create points and put the hero on.
Say, a particular point, when they are created, we can't just
willy-nilly, you know, throw the hero down somewhere, inspect that, to
be useful because it's not going to be.
So what we need to do now is say, well, when we create this, you know,
there's two ways, we could do it one is, we could just say, oh, if
he's not on one,
A close one.
I want to make sure it's we're going to go transaction with this.
I want to make sure that when people are created, they had to be
created.
If there's somebody who moves around in that fashion, they have to be
created in a way that allows them to start out valid.
I don't want them to start invalid that make sense, although they are
invalid in the sense that they have no arms and legs.
What can I say?
Alright, so here we are in add player when we call add player.
I guess what I'm saying here is that I want you to have to give it a
traversable reference, which is the location.
And so there's yeah there's a couple things here.
One is that again that P the world position of the thing.
I don't know if we want to start making that be an offset from
whatever traversable it's located on I'm not sure.
Hard to say.
That's something, we'll have to start thinking about.
But anyway, so in here, where we create these, these fellows, the
body.
Who's the one that has to hop around, we're going to have to say, hey,
the body, its location has to be, I'm sorry.
I guess I could call the standing on.
It's standing on is going to be whatever we say it is, right?
And so then you here when we do an ad player and you know if the
button is pressed and we have to add a player, we need to find a place
where we can actually put this player and so we need to do that when
we actually have a SIM region open now I'll be honest.
I don't know why we process the controllers before we open the same
region.
I do not have any
Dear.
I suppose we probably had a reason for that.
I don't know what it was but it's not great.
What I'd rather do is move it right below there.
So that bright before we do anything else, we go ahead and process the
controller input.
I don't see why we couldn't do that.
So I'm going to do that.
All right, so what I'm going to do here and this is kind of janky,
we're going to have to do something a little smarter than this
eventually is I'm just going to say, okay, let's scan for the closest
reversible to wear.
Wherever the camera is and stick the player on that.
Right, like I said, not perfect.
Reason that this would not work in the game per se is we will probably
have to have some kind of additional information about whether or not
you could ever get to where you're going.
And so probably what will happen is when you first start the game will
put that player to known location and then from then on whenever
players join we will search for traversable that are connected to
where the current player is.
So that we don't like, stick somebody off in a wall are off area, they
can't get out of right, that's not a very fun gameplay experience.
It's you know, unless you're like Assassin's Creed or something and
you just want people to be like inside walls and stuff.
So at this point what we do when we do add player is we just sort of
drop him down instead, what we're going to do is I'm going to call get
closest reversible and if assuming that it succeeds, then I'll put the
thing down.
If not, then we'll probably do like, you know, to do here.
That's like game UI that tells you there's no.
No safe place, maybe keep trying on subsequent frames you know like
okay we acknowledge you hit the start button and we're just looking
for a place to put you you know maybe that's a thing that happens.
I don't know.
That's sort of a late-stage game thing that we can worry about later.
If we ever decide to actually let multiple people play in the shipping
version of the game.
Anyway, I don't know that we want that, but
So anyway, if I called get closest reversible, I'm just going to say
wherever the camera is.
So here's the camera, right?
That's the camera location.
So just give me the closest, reversible, the camera, drop it there.
So, it does not take two arguments, right?
You are sir, I actually need traversable.
Better.
And so now, let's see what we have wrought, who knows, right?
So we've added a player at this point.
Interesting.
I have a question.
Is that the only yet is okay.
So in theory,
In theory, we have placed the hero at a reasonable traversable for
this start, I guess.
But not, when we must not set it when we do our hop because it looks
like it's working up till that point, but I'm not sure we'll see.
So, anyway, is this working or is it not?
Well, if it didn't find it reversible.
So it must be setting it because it didn't
Reversible didn't hear it.
Then it wouldn't.
It would never have created The Entity, right?
We would never add the player.
So we should be in a situation where only are hopping is problematic.
We're setting our movement to to the traversable that we found up
here.
Presumably, we found one.
I guess it's possible that we didn't find one, but, you know, this
this Boolean should have prevented that case.
So we should always be talking about a very valid traversable that
we're setting with moving to and standing on was already set.
So when we get into hopping, I
You like both standing on and moving to should have been valid and
should have worked.
But obviously they didn't because we're getting an assertion that it's
trying to look up at verse 12, it doesn't exist.
So I guess the first thing we have to do is just figure out how did
that happen?
And I don't know, let's find out.
First things first, which one is it?
So it's are moving.
Its our movement to oh wait these are reversed.
All right, so this has nothing to do with the bug.
But before we go any further, let's not forget to put these in the
right order.
Right.
Moving to this is moving to this is standing on.
So let's there we go.
Got to fix that texture stuff.
It's just never a good time for it.
All right, so the one that we are having a problem with
is apparently standing on because it's not set to anything.
Right.
So at some point are standing on, didn't get set to anything.
I don't know when that is, it may be that the standing on was not
actually initialized properly, but that just seems kind of weird.
I don't know if that's true or not, but we should verify that.
Let me go back and see, maybe it's just a question of add player being
broken.
You can see body standing on getting set here right here.
And so I'm not sure why we would be having trouble with that.
But I'm going to go ahead and step in there and see what happened.
So here's where we add the player.
I'm coming through here and I'm setting standing on.
So what is standing on set to?
It's obviously valid right and and so in here where we where we set
it, the bodies standing on
There it is and moving to as well but that's what we would expect,
right?
So now if that's what it's set to, if that's what it's up to you in
the head I'm going to jump down to 08 rather the body.
When I come in here, I'm going to want to see and verify that that's
actually still true.
So, here's the head.
Here is the standing on here is the moving to and they are both know
that is not reassuring.
Not reassuring.
I am not reassured by that.
I feel not reassured.
So what happened there?
Let's go ahead and step back into a player and see is our packing
messed up, because it could very well be
There's the head.
Here comes the body.
Okay?
So what we're going to do here obviously, doing our little dance to
pack into the world.
We set the P.
That doesn't matter back any into into World.
Here we go.
And now we're copying it into the chunk.
oh,
Wait.
So this is busted, I guess, I forgot to finish this code.
This is that's a massive oversight.
Obviously, so yeah, that's just garbage.
This stuff is supposed to be done in pack entity into world, right?
All of these things have to be done when we do the packing that's
obvious, all like packing has to Encompass all of the things and we
weren't doing that.
So we were never actually converting that to a valid value, so that's
just complete nonsense.
Hopefully, you saw what was happening there.
I'll describe in a second just in case you missed it but let's go
ahead.
And fix that first.
So when we do pack em in the world, I'm sorry packing in chunk.
That's when we have to do all of our edits to it.
Right.
So here where we do our are Stardust equals Source.
This is where we have to actually do the storage, right?
So it's really that starting to be desk here.
I'm going to actually do any of these star desti or something like
that, which I will.
Set up that way.
But yeah, this this packing has to happen at store time.
That's you can't not pack when you create because all the same logic
has to occur.
So that was just dumb.
I don't know why that worked.
Yeah, I don't know why that worked at all.
That's just really weird.
In fact, if you think about it, our AB player stuff is actually kind
of a little bit busted in that case, too.
Because we should always be creating in the ungh in, you know, in the
in the expanded space and packing down.
And so when we do add player,
Add anything really?
Oops.
I mean we'll do when we do add player.
Obviously in here really, we should not be setting, indices right?
These should just be set to pointers and then they get packed.
Two IDs during the storage process, right?
So these are really pack, and those are going to be pulled.
Out of the same region and into the world code because that's how the
packing works.
Right.
Really, I should merge the Sim region and The Sims storage eventually.
Probably, because they're so tightly coupled.
I don't think there's any point in keeping them separate, but for now,
it doesn't really matter.
All right, so that should be a lot better now that's actually going
through the correct code path.
And hey, now I can hop around right.
So that's good and again so now we can also sort of say well, you
know, if that's the information about where the person is 2 then
during standing I could also say that he always recovers whatever his
position would have been, right?
And I don't know exactly how we want this to work eventually but I'm
just sort of giving you what the idea is here.
If we go down to the hero head code or sorry, Hiro body code,
Then when you are planted, what we will actually do is we will still
assign you to your location, right?
So we'll still say, oh, your entity P, we're always going to move you
to wherever you were supposed to be standing.
Right?
And so that doesn't do anything at the moment, obviously?
That doesn't do anything in particular here, but if we had something
here,
You could ride on right?
Like a, you know, some kind of an object you could move around on.
So for example, let's say we go up to one of these things where we do
you know, as standard room or whatever.
If we have this as standard room thing and we're like well, okay, you
know, we want a thing that's going to be basically the same as
something that you stand on here, but instead of any type floor or
whatever this is going to be entity type, well actually I don't even
know this is entity type.
Entity type.
Lodi.
Thing for now.
So we're going to have an ad floaty thing call because like you do,
and then we're going to add the floaty thing.
Yeah, and it's got the floor Collision will say it.
Doesn't do any special colliding and that's just how it goes.
Okay, so now we can add floaty things and the only reason I wanted to
do that was because now, when we look at any type floor and what it
does, right, we've got this rendering here, I'm going to say that also
will do that for a type floaty thing.
And by the way, these are not
Types are going away.
Why can't I complete that?
What did I do wrong?
There we go.
I think I may have accidentally
I deleted that line.
Yeah, I did.
All right, so if I have one of these floaty things for now, you know
and I do as standard room over here.
What I could do is say all right, let's also add a floaty thing.
Oops.
We'll add a floaty thing.
World mode and I'll just say, like whatever this would have been.
So you know, like oops.
Where we'll do it is we'll just say like if tile I don't know why
we're still doing this this way instead of just passing the thing.
It's don't even ask me.
I don't know if tile x equals what like seven and tile.
Y equals 7 equals 4.
I don't know.
We'll add a floaty thing.
So now in theory, there is a floating thing, right?
Can't see it.
But in theory, there is what and so now in fact, you can see it there,
there that's stacked up right there.
And so now, if we were to take that floaty thing and make the floaty
thing move, right?
So in floor, we don't have any logic for floor, but we can now make
some logic in here for floaty thing.
If it was to sort of, you know, move itself around what I could do, is
say,
You know, the air.
It's edit epz is going to be equal to, you know, I don't know.
Who knows the sign of something?
The sign of the frame time.
Howdy Bob
It's T-Bob, right?
So we just we say like, okay.
So, we just say entity T-Bob.
Plus equals V T, something like that.
And we make it, you know, go up and down by by quite a bit.
Right.
So now with that going up and down right in theory I can I can get oh
dear
I guess he doesn't ever think he gets to it.
I'm not sure why he's hopping like that.
Like, why does he keep popping?
That was quite dramatic.
What's our code for stopping hopping?
I thought it was just time based.
Oh, it's because the head picks a different closest point.
Yeah, that'll be kind of interesting.
Let's, let's make that a little less dramatic.
Okay, so in a standard room, what I'm going to do is I'm just going to
say in here instead of adding the ground identity floor Collision, I'm
going to actually do an if and switch which one of them I'm doing.
So I'm going to say oh okay if my you know if the offset x equals 0 or
rather equals, let's say 2 and the offset y equals 2 then I'll make a
floaty thing instead of the ground.
So it should be relatively unambiguous now so are broken.
You know, controller code won't have a cow about that, right?
Although where is our floaty thing floaty thing.
Where did you go?
Oops.
Tell you what?
Forget the floaty thing.
Just add it this way.
There we go.
Okay.
Okay, that is just weird.
This is going to have to be tomorrow's bug to search for.
I don't understand why we would be getting that.
Because why is he thinking needs to hop?
The Hop code is not based on the distance, right?
I just maybe you shouldn't ever hop to the same point, right?
I guess we kind of need to say that this happens prior to the search
that's I guess all we really need.
We would just say if entity movement mode
Equals movement mode planted then we need to update it before we
search, right?
So that that that's my bad.
So, there we go.
And you can see now we still have problems because we're still looking
for whatever the closest thing to the head is so we still need to now
rewrite our controller code with that knowledge of.
We only jump when we move the head further away from the body, and
then we pick because otherwise, every time we get nearer, there's one
that's like closer to the head.
It's going to like constantly try to jump back and forth between them,
right?
And that's like, definitely not what we want.
So that's bad news.
All right.
I'll take a couple quick questions, but I got to go soon.
Nibbler.
That sounds like a job for hysteresis, photo.
Shoot it, right?
I guess.
Sort of, in this case, really, it's more about the controller logic
that we programmed was before.
We had any concept of that, we were standing on traversable, so we
were just saying whatever the closest thing is and so you're right.
It is hysteresis is like we want to take into account what we meant,
right?
And so,
As it's going to actually very easy to make that happen, and it's
going to mean that the code for the head gets better too.
The implemented a structured editor for greenfoot.
I don't think I know what greenfoot is.
Sure does look ugly but I don't know what greenfoot is.
Kind of rents.
So we are planning to have the head detached forever.
What does that mean?
The head always moves separately from the body.
And the body follows the head.
graphically we will draw them as best we can to make it always appear
like they're connected physically in the artistic sense but
Abner where are the gloves?
You'll programming custom glove movement, right?
The glove is is actually like what you attack with.
So that's going to not, you don't really move it so much as you just
say when you're attacking with it.
Colonel Dragon.
Any idea when you plan on adding in the correct perspective, Arts with
the hero looks less strange.
No, because that's actually kind of held up as far as art as far as
getting the artist concerned.
Let's see.
So in theory, you could test this by adding a second Hero Test.
What?
With the X, I can try making sure they don't sound the same tile, but
we haven't implemented.
Transactional tile stuff yet so they could easily stand in the same
tile if they want to do.
We're not preventing them.
All right.
I have to head out.
So if there are questions that you want to know about on this holding
for tomorrow and I will get to them then.
All right, let's close this down.
Okay, thank you very much for joining me for this episode of handmade
hero.
It's been a pleasure coding with you.
As always, if you would like to follow along at home, you can always
pray to the game.
My Hand be here at our org and it comes with the source code so you
can follow along and experiment with it.
We also have a forum site, you can go to.
If you want to ask questions, we have a patreon page from a sports
video.
Is we have a schedule bot?
If you would like to know what time the videos are going to be live,
and we also have episode guide for try, catch up on old stuff, that's
about it for today.
I'll be back here for the last dream of this week tomorrow.
5:00 p.m.
Pacific Daylight time until then I will.
Well I'll see you guys in the unit.
Take it easy everyone.
Yeah.
Wait, this isn't good.
Why does that say start recording?
Did it not actually record.
Hmm.
Well that's a bummer.
Looks like we're gonna have to get this one from twitch because it
doesn't look like it restarted recording.
Oh well.
I heard us with such a passion.
Well, Alex were different witch.