Hello, everyone, and welcome to handmade hero.
The show, where we go to complete game live on Twitch using no
engines, no libraries.
It's really designed to be a complete project from start to finish,
where we show, how absolutely everything that is involved in the
execution of a game, including the engine, and the low-level rendering
and everything work at a very specific and fine grain level.
And right now, we are in the middle of doing something, which is kind
of cool.
We are sort of exploring how we
To handle the notion of three dimensions, inside a game, that is, you
know, using 2D art assets.
And so we're kind of working out exactly how we treat that third
dimension.
And what's interesting about this is basically that
If you make a game that's full 3d.
Then everything has to be represented fully in three dimensions,
obviously, and it kind of it solves some things for you.
It creates a lot of problems for you and new things that you have to
deal with, certainly, but it also solves a couple problems for you.
Such as how you deal with height and things like this.
Because since everything is represented in 3D, you can just do full
simulation on it and you get what you expect to happen out, right?
And that's kind of nice but you know, too?
Game where things are not modeled into, you said bitmaps.
That represent things, you need to have some kind of semantic
understanding of what should happen in terms of height because, you
know, to a certain extent, your game will probably have some limited
interaction with that third dimension, even though it's technically a
2-D game.
And so for example, thing that we're looking at now is what happens if
we want to put like a stairwell in the game.
What happens if we want to levels of something where you can see down
to the level below it, right?
There are things you may want to do that involve a third dimension
even though the game itself is not three-dimensional.
And what we're doing right now is kind of exploring what our options
are there and what it means for the code to do certain things there.
So that we have a solid view at solid perspective, pun intended,
perhaps on that third dimension when we move into, developing the
engine shipping engine code because I
I don't want to get into a situation where Z is always sort of
haphazardly, handled and like sort of lumber towards the finish line
of shipping the game with.
Oh he's kind of fighting how we're representing Z and hacking things
here.
And there, I'd rather have a very solid conception of it if we can
manage it.
So that it's always handled, very cleanly and logically in the game
and allows us to do all the things that we might want to do with it.
So that's what we're doing today, we're continuing that we started
that
Sort of earlier in the week and we've sort of been slowly going
through and going through a piece.
Code and seeing what Z means to them.
And so let's go ahead and do that.
Let's go ahead and continue doing that today.
Now, before I begin, obviously, if you pre-ordered the game on
handmade hero dot-org, you should have gotten a link in your email and
that link allows you to download the source code every day.
So if you'd like to follow along today is day 75.
So you're going to want to unpack day.
74 is source code and you're going to want to start with that because
that's what I'm starting with a 74 yesterday source code here on day
75.
All right, so let's, let's, let's sort of recap a little bit and let's
think about where we were.
We had just finished doing some stuff where we were working on going
up and down, stairwells and how we decided we wanted to implement that
yesterday, was we, you know, I should make a new one for our day.
75.
J 75.
So, what we had decided to do basically is, if you imagine looking, so
we'll do a top and side view since this is three dimensions.
We got to kind of think about it, in terms of a full three dimensions.
If we have something like a stairwell and our stairwell is, I believe
it goes up this way.
So, basically, you'd imagine like, this is the bottom stair.
And this is the top stair of our stairwell.
Can also think of, as a ramp the way we
Chosen to implement it, and if you're into perspective, you could
probably imagine it looking a little more like this.
Right.
It gets bigger as it goes up.
Something like that.
So if we're going to go up the stairwell, that we decided to do is,
well, when the player comes here, and they hit the stairwell, what we
want to do is say that the players Y location relative to the
stairwell.
Remember, this is the y-axis here, there Y location relative, the
stairwell as they move from here, to here as they move.
Sort of in between these two, we're going to adjust their z-height
where we believe them to be in Z, so that they travel smoothly.
The, until when they get to the end there at the like they're at a
particular Z height, which would be the next floor, right?
And same thing happens when you travel down the stairwell, you'd start
at the maximum height and go down to the lowest, right?
So, if we took at this as a side view, you would imagine it looking
like this.
Right.
And when the player comes in here,
when the player enters into this region, we then say, okay, they're
entering into the stairwell region.
So, now, as they move from here to here, what we're going to do is
adjust that ground height to be proportional so that it kind of the
ground kind of goes like that in between here.
Now, what we haven't done yet is actually move them down to the
stairwell.
What we actually did was Lie,
Gravity, which we actually always apply.
Just pull them down eventually.
But what that means is, that if you come very quickly off of the
stairwell, you actually don't go down.
You kind of curve like this, right?
You kind of do that, which means technically, you could actually jump
the stairwell or other things like this, if you're running it speed, I
don't know.
So it's a little bit janky there.
So that's
It's probably not the way we want to do that especially the speed of
the player right now and their size and so on are not calibrated quite
to human scale.
So they actually get a lot more momentum than they should and the
stairwells not very large at the moment although maybe we need to
change that.
So there's a couple things we want to do here.
There's one other problem that we had was basically our movement
scheme was a little bit janky to the way that it worked.
Is it constantly moved you underneath the ground and then projected
you back up to the ground, right?
That was our less than
Nothing.
And what that meant was that when you are approaching the stairwell
from the other side, you constantly were below it and then get pushed
up below it.
And then pushed up below it and pushed up that, which meant the
technically, if the stairwell wasn't larger, if the sterile doesn't
extend down this far, it we wouldn't actually ever be placed inside it
and that was a bug as well.
And so we need to start thinking about how we want to handle those
things.
A little more cleanly.
Just some things we need to think about in terms of actually getting
this handling into some better shape.
The other thing that we need to think about in order to get this
working properly is we need to think about entity Z bounds for two
reasons, we've got Collision detection.
So right now our Collision detection operates, only in 2D which means
that as you move if something is below you you will still hit it or
above you, right?
And so what we need to kind of do is we need to do something where
we're actually excluding things that are above or below you from
hitting you so that you can pass under them or on top over the top of
them.
And we also have to do something where we put in doing.
in addition to Collision detection, we would like to be able to put in
something where we, you know, draw more reasonably
Because right now, what happens?
Well, you can see what happens.
Basically, we have two floors.
Stacked on top of each other at the moment.
And
wait a minute.
We didn't recompile.
We didn't recompile yesterday.
We had turned off the two floors, because someone had asked a
question.
So let's do that.
There we go.
You can see what happens when we have two floors.
Basically you just got them stacked on top of each other.
It doesn't really make any sense.
It's hard to parse visually and so we need to we haven't written the
renderer for this game yet.
So it's true that we you know, in our in our placeholder renderer we
probably won't be doing very much with respect to making this look
pretty but we should at least play around a little bit and just figure
out what the plan is right.
We want to have some idea of what we're going to do when we actually
Have that real renderer, we need some clue here, right as to what's
going on.
And so we need to think about that a little bit as well.
Okay, so that's really what's going on here?
We've got a lot of stuff to deal with, so, you know, let's, let's
start taking these one at a time.
So the first thing I would say is, let's, let's go back up to the
stairwell situation and let's think about that that ground aspect of
it, right?
Let's
To think about getting this stuff.
Worked out a little more solid.
Let's let's think about not having the player go into the ground and
pop back up and stuff like that.
Let's let's try to do something a little bit better here.
So the first thing that I might suggest and you know it's again I
don't know because I'm sort of exploring this on my own here.
I don't generally right?
2D games, I don't know that much about how I prefer to handle things
yet because I
I haven't ever really tried it.
So I'm actually doing that experimentation and showing how we work
through stuff like that in the real world.
When I'm coming in here to my move entity call.
What I'm thinking is that in general, we want to sort of do what you
would, what you would actually have happen in reality, choose me, it's
allergy season now, I'm not sick anymore.
But my nose keeps running.
I know it's gross anyway.
So, what I'd like to do is have it so that perhaps when you are
standing on the ground, you do not accelerate into the ground, right?
So that basically that normal force when you're standing on the
ground, keeps you from accelerating into the ground.
So you don't get that dip down problem.
You just go straight across and it's only when the ground is below you
that you actually get acceleration from things like gravity that would
be nice.
And so in order to do that, I think what I'd like to do is really use
a little bit of energy storage.
Like a flag that says, whether you're standing on the ground at the
moment.
In other words, at the end of the last time, step were you standing on
the ground?
And if you were, then I'm not going to apply, right?
I'm not going to apply that gravity here.
Does that make sense?
Just something really simple?
And we could do the check.
We could do an overlap check again, but I want to not do lots of
overlap checks.
If we don't have to
Because you know it seems wasteful necessarily to do them at the
beginning and end of the frame.
And so, you know, it probably is good enough.
I think since we're not a game that's heavy on using Z, I think it
should be fine to basically, do some kind of a quick check that looks
something like this.
So let's say,
That we were to introduce a flag here which is like only flag on
ground or something like that.
And that on ground flag is just saying, or like supported by will just
say supported maybe, or, you know, vertically supported something like
that.
I don't know Z supported, how about that.
So, if it is supported in Z, then we'll just say the gravity is not
applying
Right.
So we'll say, you know, we'll do that that as a flag check which is
just R is set call.
So on this particular entity, if it's Z supported, we would not add
gravity.
And if it's not see supported then we do bad gravity, right?
And
I don't know.
We could make the flag since be the other way around.
I'm not sure how we want to do that but doesn't really matter for now,
we can always flip it later, it's not a big deal.
So then when we come in here, what we want to do is say, all right,
any time that this triggers, right?
This pretty much tells us whether or not we want that flag set.
If you are, if you've hit the ground, if you're going into the ground,
that means you're a z supported, right?
So what we want to do is we want to clear those flags, right?
So we want to clear.
That Z supported flag any time you've hit the ground because that
means you're standing on the ground.
Now and anytime that poops have that the other way around, sorry what
I meant to say is you want to set the flag when your Z squared, when
you hit the ground and anytime that you're not when you're in free
fall, you want to clear that flag?
That says that yours you supported, right?
And so that basically be a quick way to sort of say, yeah,
You know what?
We are going to we're just going to sort of remember that and we won't
let you like kind of keep dipping into the ground will Coast you along
the ground properly this time, right?
And let's let's take a look and see if that fixes one problem that we
had, which is right here.
You remember I did a to do, when we add the stairwell, we had to make
the stairwell larger than it than it should have been.
In order to make that work.
So let's take a look at that briefly.
So of course, here, we've got thing where we can go up the stairwell,
like so, but let's go ahead and see what happens if we take this out.
Temporarily
Let's see here.
Still no dice.
So, let's take a look at why that isn't working now because I think
that should work for the most part.
Let's take a look.
Of course, we still have a it's still not quite what we would want in
terms of collision technique, but I believe we should be able to get
this to work properly.
And I'd like to make sure that it actually does.
Let's take a look at the hero specifically.
Well, I guess I can.
I guess I can do that this way.
perhaps, can I
No, I guess I would have to step.
Yeah.
So I'm going to have to set a breakpoint on the hero specifically and
I guess, you know what, what I probably should do is give myself an
easy way to do that.
Now, that I think about it, so that I can always set a breakpoint in
in here.
So I can basically say okay, if entity type equals and any type hero,
Yeah.
So basically, that's a trick I like to do debugging wise where I just
set all kinds of weird conditions or whatever I want.
You know, stuff that would get compiled out certainly.
So it doesn't really cost you anything because it's the compiler will
eliminate.
This is dead code in an optimized build, but it gives me in a debug
build a way to stop on a certain thing.
So when the heroes moving I can just say, okay, let me go ahead and
see what happens to the heroes movement.
So when we come through here, now I can take a look at that overlap
test.
Right?
First of all, what I would like to do too, is, I'd like to see if that
flag is actually set.
So let's take a look at.
Well, I guess what I can do is just look at it here.
Yeah.
So it skips gravity as it should, and if we look at the DDP, it's Z is
0, so that's good.
And if I look at its entity position, it's
that's odd.
Why is it X Y and Z all 0?
Does that seem odd to you?
Why are the X and wives equal to 0?
Have I not moved the guy yet?
He's like, way up here.
Oh, because we always move the camera.
I forgot about that.
We're not, we're still we weave, we're not in room locked mode.
We're actually always move the camera.
So the player is by definition, always at 0-0, that's where he
supposed to because that the center camera Point.
Okay, so that's fine.
oh, that's interesting but now it's not
Huh.
I see what our problem is.
So we clear that flag when when we're not under the ground so that's
not quite what we wanted.
If you're still on the ground,
I do want you to actually consider yourself Z supported so really
it's, it's yeah, it's less than or equal to the ground.
Yeah.
That's that's a bit of a mistake admittedly.
So, okay.
So yeah, let's try that again.
So let's see.
Now we should be here and now we can actually go in and find out
what's going on there.
So we don't add in the gravity, which is what we expect we come down
here.
We don't really need to look at the Collision routine.
We need to look at the overlap routine and we need to take a look at
what happens during that can overlap now in can overlap.
I'm wondering.
I thought I set a breakpoint here before.
And yet it didn't ever hit.
So I'm wondering why that was the case.
Okay, there we go.
I guess that must have been just a trick of the eye.
So when we're actually going to look at what happens when we have a
hero and a stairwell, right?
There's the hero there's the stairwell.
When we actually do those tests, I want to know why, we're not
actually getting that overlap to occur here.
So let's take a look.
First of all, let's take a look at our two rectangles, so here's our
entity wrecked.
Right?
And well, you know, our entity it doesn't help that our entity has no
height to him.
We should probably fix that.
That's one of the things that we want to do today probably to where
we're talking where we were talking about, you know, having Collision
detection, be properly.
Three-dimensional.
So the tests entity wrecked.
So okay.
So basically the problem is, just our entity.
Our stairwell actually doesn't extend down to the floor, which I'm not
exactly sure.
Why, that is, it looks like it doesn't have any Z at all.
It has no z-depth whatsoever.
Why is that?
that's,
That's real odd.
What am I what am I missing here?
People do you know what?
What's going on there?
Do we not?
We didn't ever give him a z depth.
The stairwell really
What?
I'm so confused.
Now, I thought for sure we had done that.
Did we accidentally delete a line here?
Did I like errantly delete a line?
That's just crazy.
I thought for sure that we had typed this in there and I guess we
didn't.
All right.
Well, that's the problem.
Obviously, you can't run into the stairwell.
If it doesn't actually contain the region, it's supposed to contain.
Oh, so I must have just done it.
This is how tired I am when I came in here and deleted the to do.
And and we have that.
Did I just delete the whole line?
What?
Unbelievable.
This is why we need to always have almond milk, people, that's just
totally unacceptable.
Anyway,
Let's take a look.
Now, that that whole thing where I can keep going upwards by jumping
is kind of bizarre and since our win32 platform layer is you know kind
of a stand-in it also does this thing where it'll lock down if you.
Yeah.
It's kind of, its kind of amusing.
We should probably fix that at least temporarily.
Anyway, when I go on here, now it should work, it does.
So that's what we were expecting.
And and so now we want to take
Look at that part where we kind of float down it as well.
And instead make it so that we rise up it more correctly, right?
So we want to make it so that going up and down is instantaneous and
you can see how I kind of float down going up works properly because
we're always sort of forcing ourselves to do that properly, by having
the ground be a hard constraint, but we're not putting ourselves back
onto the ground in the case where we were touching it before.
And so what I'd like to do,
I think here is say, okay, you know, if the entity was on the ground,
I'm going to say that we've got another criteria for when we want to
stay Peg to the ground.
What I want to say is if you're underneath the ground or you, you have
that flag set, right?
The The Entity Z supported flag is set, right?
And so you were on the ground again with and you were not trying to go
upward, right?
So you know, and the entity your entity d z is equal to 0.
So you were not trying to accelerate yourself.
Then I'm just going to say that that we're going to place you flat on
the ground.
So if you're on the ground you stay on the ground.
Right?
Because I think that's mostly how we want the.
We don't really want the player jumping the jump, the fact we have a
jump in there is purely sort of arbitrary so yeah if I walk up it
should work now.
And if I walk down, it should work now as well.
It does appear to, unfortunately, we this familiar I might have are
Take a chill, he's making me kind of annoyed by following me around
quite so much.
Let's take a look at
At his update call there, so that I can.
Stop running into him all the time.
I'm trying to test other stuff familiar.
Let's just say that the familiar doesn't actually find hero ever.
There we go.
It's just not something he does and he can just stay there.
Thank you.
There we go.
So I walk up the stairs and walk down the stairs, up the stairs, down
the stairs, up the stairs, down the stairs.
So that seems fine.
I think that's working properly now, right?
And again, we don't really have any rendering for us there, so that's
a bit of a problem, but you know, what do you do?
I think we're in good shape there.
Yeah, yeah.
So, what's going on?
That's a little.
Oh, right.
So now we also have one more problem to deal with, which is we have to
start thinking about the other part of the stairwell that I talked
about yesterday, which is basically, you know, if you enter the
stairwell, if right now wherever you are on the stairwell Z wise,
right?
Is determines your height.
So if you enter the stairwell at the very top you just slam, right?
Right.
Z up right, you know, when you tuck the
All the top, you immediately go up to the top and I assume what we
want to do is make it so that that isn't allowed that you just bump
into the stairwell.
At that point.
I don't know.
I'm not sure what we really want to do.
Maybe you do want to just slam up to the top.
Maybe that's better for gameplay that, you don't have to think about
stuff like that.
I'm not sure one thing I would like to do is I'd like to make the
stairwell a little bit longer so we can kind of you know, think about
it a little more easily by looking at what sort of happens.
Is when you touch it.
So I'm going to, I'm going to go ahead and say that maybe it has a
little more.
A little more height to it since.
So this is going to be like two tiles long or something like this and
I'm going to try and place it a little bit lower as well, so we'll say
tile.
Why is seven or eight something like that?
Or not what happened there.
Tile.
Why is that something weird that I've done by saying?
Oh,
Tile X tile.
Why is there some reason why?
That was unhappy
let me find out now feel like it should have been
But it was, why is it unhappy about that?
I'm not totally sure I get it.
Tile x equals 10 and tile y equals 7 because it should be okay to do
that.
Oh because well, no.
So I'm I'd like to know what's going on there.
So shouldn't I be able to move this?
Oh, I guess that would move it up.
So, I actually wanted it move down, I guess to be clear and maybe even
a little bit more down than that.
Yeah.
All right.
That was because it was because of the should door part it was because
it was actually trying to put it on top of the door which we were not
allowing at the time.
So I guess I also want to when I add the stair I don't need it to be
so fat, either it can be you know, just one tile wide like so
Alright, so now that we have a longer stairwell, right?
We can kind of see, you can kind of see the guy walk up it, and when
you get to the middle of it, it's which is z levels, right?
Basically, this this yellow blob just represents where our stair is
and that works.
Pretty reliably.
Actually.
That's, that's pretty nice.
And so the thing that I was talking about is the fact that, okay?
I'm on the bottom level right now.
I touch the top and I just teleport right to the top right?
Which is exactly how we've defined it to.
And, you know, I feel like conceptually it's weird but yeah, I don't
know gameplay-wise.
What we want to do.
Do you want to just have, you hit it?
I suppose, we just want you to be able to use, want to stop there and
not go.
And so I'm trying to think, probably the easiest way to do that is to
actually have stairwells be built out of multiple things that like do
that block you basically like what I'm thinking
Probably the easiest thing to do is to say, all right, the
construction for a stairwell, right is an entity that's the stairwell,
and then two other entities, that are like, you know, something like
this.
Where it's like, there's an entity here that blocks you from passing
under the stairwell,
Right.
And there's an entity here that blocks you from passing over it.
Something like that.
That would still allow you to enter in the middle of the stairwell.
And I'm worried that if you were all the way, if you did something
like that, that the player would hit its head on it.
So really you'd have to also make them so that they were kind of, you
know, that they were like this.
I don't know, but we could do that, you know, we could basically make
an invisible walls, right?
That are just right on the sides of the stairwell.
And to be honest, I don't really know if there's any real reason not
to do that.
I don't know.
I'm a little conflicted.
It's hard to say, I don't know what the easiest thing is to do because
it seems weird to overload the stairwell handling and make it so that
they have special kind of consideration for that, but we could do that
as well.
So let's let's let's think about how we would do that.
So let's say we wanted to make it so that when you moved on to the
stairwell, you just couldn't change your z-height too much.
Right?
Like like let's say that we did it.
So that inside move entity right inside move entity.
What if this were actually something that we're done?
That can deny the move from actually occurring or something like this,
right?
Like we could decide that this is actually done say every Collision
iteration.
I know that seems a little
Weird.
But we could do it, right?
We could do essentially, you know, this sort of thing.
We're inside the loop.
Every time we actually go ahead and take this as an advisory P like we
say, you know, this is actually a like a like a test P that we're not
sure if we're going to do yet and we use that instead or something or
basically like
Well no, you know what?
No, I take it back.
We can't do that because we would still have to check for collision
with the stairwell and stop you when you, when you hit it, right?
Hmm.
So yeah I'm just really not sure.
I guess one way we could do, it would be to say that when you were
going to collide with the stairwell, we look at what your height would
have.
Been and allow you to pass on to the stairwell if the height
difference was small.
And not, if the height difference was large, and the way that would
have to look is basically the can Collide when after you do the
Collision here, right?
After you do this, these tests wall.
These results here would basically have to actually do the ground
computation for the stairwell, sort of write right in the actual
Collision routine.
And I don't know it's not hard to do.
I'm just wondering whether it's the right thing to do, but that would
solve the problem.
Them right.
Hmm.
Nice.
Eh.
And so just to give an example of what that would look like, let's
just go ahead and type it out.
So to give an example of what that would look like.
Essentially, this stuff here would have to be sort of speculative.
So if you like test will normal write and test it, MV
Like so, and these would actually be done like this.
Right.
And so in
Case where we actually find one.
So if we do hit something then what we would do is we'd create that
speculative P.
So basically be like test P this is where you would end up for this
hit and it's the test.
We need to do it on the team in as well.
So test and test those team in.
This is team in test.
So
so there we go.
So now we're doing the Collision entirely spectively with speculative
variables.
We then say, if we would hit the entity then we create that sort of
speculative point that we would have ended up at troops equals kind of
DP.
That's the point we would end up at during this collision and then we
can do after we do that.
That test is we can actually have logic here, right?
So we can say, basically if that's okay, you know then then go ahead
and actually do it.
So if that's okay, we will then do an assignment that takes these guys
and actually makes them the permanent ones, right?
So hit entity.
Test entity will normal becomes test.
Well normal and team in becomes team in test.
So right?
And so that allows us to do some kind of a thing that's like you know,
speculative Collide or something like this and that passes The Entity
and the test entity like so and that would allow us to actually figure
out whether you were allowed to move on to the stairwell there.
It's a little janky certainly, you know.
But but what do you do?
Some things are janky and we can sort of think about.
It as we go a little bit more carefully.
So if we did this yes we've got essentially this going on due to do.
That.
Yeah, so we would really just do exactly this.
And we would, sort of say, all right, this is the ground level on the
stairwell.
And we would then say, for the ground level, if the, the player, you
know, would not be trying to go up too much when it hit this, when it
hit the stairwell then you know that's
That's fine, right?
So we'd say if the if the entity see
Is.
Yeah, if the entity z-, whatever that ground level is is not, you
know, is not owners.
a, so we basically say,
If the absolute value of the difference between them, let's say is
less than whatever.
Our step height is, right.
So, whatever our we want our maximum step height to be, and, you know,
the step height is some random value.
I don't know what we want it to be, but, you know, a tenth of a meter
or something like this, who knows?
If that's okay, then you can go up it, if it's not, then you know,
it's not.
So then we would say, all right, here's the result.
We assume that it's fine and I guess we would say, if it's over the
step, I bet it's not fine because in general, you're allowed to move.
But in the case of stairwell, it rejects the move, if it would be too
high.
So that puts us, if we want to do that, that would allow us to jump
into their that puts a squarely in the camp again, of sort of
You know, wanting to be able to handle those pairwise Collision rules.
Because if I remember correctly, our stairwells are set to not
Collide, they're only an overlapping operation and we could get rid of
the overlapping operation on stairwells entirely at this point by
adjusting, the player pee in here, which is probably what we would
want to do.
So that inside the Collision, the duration, it would adjust your
position as you moved up the stairwell
yeah, so Jimmy
although we still need the overlap testing, never mind because you
need to overlap as you go.
We just want to handle that in and out case.
Yeah.
Yeah, and so the stops on collision we wouldn't ever actually stop you
on collision either.
We would let you just pass on through.
So the stops on collision.
Let's go ahead and take a look there.
I guess there's another kind of weirdness.
There's one other thing that we don't handle here.
This is man, this stuff is tricky if you actually want to do somewhat
fancy 3D handling.
There's so many things to think about.
Out.
But it's interesting.
I'm kind of enjoying trying to figure out exactly how I want to do
some of these things anyway.
So if we want to do our stops on collision bit here, then when we do
our handle Collision, we would also want to say, oh, we don't stop
you.
If it's a, you know if it's a stairwell, right?
And if you type stairwell.
So basically any time, it's stairwell you're allowed to pass right
through it.
So stops on collision equals.
False.
But we would then need to change our stairwells to be things that you
actually can collide with which right now.
They aren't, they don't have a colliding flag set on them, so we would
need to add that to the
Well, and then there we go.
So let's do it this way.
So on
Test.
Undeclared identifier test.
Well, that's true.
It certainly is it's supposed to be teaming test times player, Delta
change the wrong thing there.
If test hit entity, potentially undersized, local variable, that is
true.
It should be zero.
Thank you mr.
Compiler speculative.
Collide must return a value that is also true.
All right.
Let's see what's going on here.
So we can still walk up and down the stairs, which is good.
But the question is, now can we walk into them at the top and we can?
So that's not what we wanted.
So why is that?
Oh, because I don't restart the game so it didn't have that flag set
on the stairwell.
All right, let's try that again.
So I can walk up and down it, but can I walk into the top I can?
So we're still bogus.
They're right.
Because that shouldn't we don't want that to happen.
We don't want to be able to do that.
So
Go ahead and see what's going on there.
First of all, let's see if we ever actually trigger this, which
hopefully we do.
So let's go ahead and walk to the top part.
All right, so we never actually doing that hit.
We're never actually hitting the stairwell so that is the problem.
Obviously, let's find out what's going on.
So,
Is there something?
Okay, so there's our problem.
We still have check in there.
That said basically, we don't want to actually collide with
stairwells.
Let's remove that.
Alright, so now we are colliding with stairwells but it looks like
we're checking in the wrong.
It looks like I put the check in the wrong way.
What did I do?
Let me we almost implemented that correctly.
Well it is a, this is why you don't program when you're sleepy.
Okay, so yeah, I just had it backwards.
So basically, what we want to do is the result is, did you Collide?
And the answer is you collided when the step B was too high.
So that's what we actually wanted.
Right.
So now we should be able to walk up it.
Walk down it but we can't walk into the to the top of it, right?
That's not that's not allowed.
So that's good.
That's all very nice.
And presumably we can only.
Yeah we can only walk in at the very bottom
Ottoman top.
So that actually works quite nicely actually, the only thing that is
we're not gliding along it.
So we still have some weirdness there that I'm not sure.
I'm not sure exactly what's going on with that.
Why?
We not gliding, so speculative, collide.
Why can't we Glide along this entity?
Like shouldn't shouldn't this be taken care of that, for us?
What am I missing here?
What am I missing?
Did we break, you know, did we break the lighting entirely?
Well, it looks like we don't collide with walls now, so that's a bug.
Oh, right, so I guess speculative, Collide actually is generally true,
and this is more of a only for stairwells, kind of thing.
Sorry about that.
Like I said, sleepy programming, not the best idea.
Are speculative Collision thing was making it so that all collisions
don't work.
So we're gliding properly still along other surfaces.
So, I wonder why we can't Glide.
What's special about the stairwell.
I guess it's the thing where speculative Collide is because now in all
cases, they're still going through here.
So what's the problem?
Is it something with our handle Collision call?
I guess stops on collision equals false.
That's probably
That's probably what our problem is there.
Let me think about this, so once you are on it, it would pass up.
So I guess we don't want to have you hit return stops on collision?
We want it to actually get.
There we go.
So there's that gliding.
Yeah, so I feel like these Collision routines, they just have too many
weird predicates and stuff in them right that it's hard to like you
see how hard it is for me to keep track of all of the predicates and
where stuff happens?
I feel like it'd be nice if we could kind of unify those and make them
into some really nice orthogonal unified set.
What I will say though is I kind of like this way of handing the
stairwells because man it feels perfect like just playing with it
here.
It feels
Exactly.
Like you want it to feel?
In fact, despite the fact that our Graphics are awful because we're
not rendering anything, this is the best feeling stairwell.
I think I've ever felt in a game.
I mean that just feels great instead of like triggering some can
animation or just flashing that you really like go up it it just feels
awesome.
That's all I can say.
Yeah, I feel like when we combine that with some good rendering for,
you know, when there's actually a stairwell there and it's, you know,
a floating properly in whatever.
That's, that's going to be pretty awesome.
Yeah.
I I'm I'm a fan of how we did this as I guess what I would say.
That's, that's pretty cool.
So the next thing I think we need to tackle here.
Is we need
Yeah, I'm sorry.
I'm really enjoying this.
It's really nice.
When you actually spend some time to do something and then it comes
out good that that's really good.
That's that feels fantastic.
Yeah.
Okay.
Anyway, excuse me, we have some other stuff we got to do here.
We got to do the 3D entity Collision stuff.
Obviously, that's that's relatively simple actually.
But what I what I wanted to say was first of all, we're going to put a
thing on here.
Oops.
that H, what we do want to do is for Collision detection, I would like
to say
Can we do something about?
Clean up, predicate proliferation.
Can we make a nice clean set of flags rules so that it's easy to
understand how things work in terms of special handling.
This may involve making the iteration handle everything instead of
handling.
Overlap outside and so on.
So yeah, like I said, I don't really know.
But that's something that we kind of, it's just not, it's just not
perfect.
So we figured out how we would go up and down.
That's true.
But we still have our, how is this rendered?
Let's keep that on there.
And then we'll also to maybe do try to the question section in the
last 10 minutes here.
The one thing I did want to say was Z equals zero for the ground.
This is not right.
You know I'm saying, the reason this is not right is
As that's totally dependent on where the camera was Z equals.
Zero is just a camera location, right?
And so, what we'd rather do, is have a notion that the ground is at a
specific Z plane all the time.
You know, and those Z planes are like stacked, you know, one on top of
each other.
So I'm not sure exactly how we would want to do that.
Like I'm not sure how we want to know.
Know exactly where the ground should be.
But what I do think we want to do is say that for the same region that
ground is actually parameter.
Right, there's a ground-level parameter and what we're going to do
here, like default ground level, right?
And our Sim region.
We grab that out there and so when we
We do the begin Sim when we take that world position origin in.
We should compute the ground level, the default ground level based on.
That, that information, right?
So, yeah, so, we would want to basically do the movement based on
that.
Now, there's a bit of a nastiness here, I guess.
So I guess it's not really default ground level that we want as well
because this is bear with me here because I think this is actually
relatively tricky and I want to make sure we do it right.
so let's say we have a SIM region like we do,
And we have some scenario where we've got, you know, from, from a side
view.
We've got a hero who's up here and this is, you know, what?
He's standing on.
But then there's also another layer down here and there's a monstar,
right?
And the monstar
Monstar.
Hero and the monster is on here for simulating, these two people.
Their ground levels are different, right?
This guy standing on this ground of this guy standing on this ground.
And so we want to be able to handle those both in the same sim region
because the gather may have grabbed them both.
So we really don't want we it's not that we need to know anything
about the it's not that we need to know what a default ground level
is.
We need to know is just how these are aligned so that we can look at
where the hero is and say, okay?
What's his Z level that he's on and look at the monster and say what Z
level is, he on?
So we really need is is some kind of a like a z base that tells us
where, you know, these slices are and you are at some tile height, you
know?
Increment off of the Z base at any given time, right?
That's what I think we actually want and so I think that is is really
what we should be doing.
We kind of need something that's like like a basically like a ground Z
base, something like that.
And what you would do is to find out what your ground level is, right,
you would take wherever you are, and you'd sort of truncate it down to
whatever that.
That new Z is right, so your ground level.
When we're trying to figure out what your the place that would be
supporting you underneath your ground level is going to be about that,
right?
You're a ground level is going to be telling you that information so
there's still one more thing about this.
So let's say we have a stairwell truncation isn't going to work
because when you walk off the stairwell, you want to snap to the
closest one, right?
You want to snap and truncation will work for this guy but it wouldn't
work for this guy.
Hmm.
So it would seem like stairwell handling would have to be a little
smarter.
Essentially what we would want to do for the stairwells is say when
you exit a stairwell, we snap you to the ground level that you would
be on.
You walk off it because otherwise it's never going to work properly.
If we walked off here, let's imagine Heroes can fall off Ledges, which
I don't think we want them to do but just imagine that they could.
So for Hero, Walks off here, what's its its new ground level?
Well, we don't want it to snap to well.
Okay that's that's that's dumb anyway because if we were going to do
that we just probably put an entity here that was like empty space
since we're not representing ground explicitly, we would have to
represent empty space explicitly to.
So that's kind of dumb.
Yeah.
Forget I said that.
So if we wanted to snap, I guess the thing that we would want to do is
let's say, let's say Heroes here.
And it jumps right or the familiar and he's floating up here, we don't
want him to snap his ground level to cure.
We want them to snap his ground level to there, right?
So we definitely need to do truncation.
When we walk off of a stairwell, on the other hand, we wouldn't we
want to sort of snap up to the closer one at the top, which would
fight
The two, like these two can't coexist, we have a problem there, right?
And so,
I'm just not sure exactly how to handle that cleanly, right?
Without saying the stairwell has to be in charge of that Special Rule,
right?
Which is that if you're walking up the top of sterile, you snap to the
next ground level.
So yeah, it's pretty complicated.
I don't know, I don't know what a good solution to that is we don't
have a whole lot of time left so I'm not sure what I want to do there
but I guess I'll back that.
For now.
And we'll say that is another to do that.
We have to do.
So in here will say
You know, something like need to make a solid concept of ground
levels.
So the camera can be freely placed in Z and have multiple ground
levels in one sim region, right?
So that's, that's basically what we have to fix their and I suspect
the already sort of have a bug related to that, right?
Yeah.
So if you note the familiar and the monstar move up with us, which is
exactly what we would expect because they get snapped up to Z equals
0, right?
Because they are standing on the ground.
And so we already have that bug and and so we will know when we fix it
because they, those guys should stay in the same Z level.
Right?
That makes sense.
So yeah, so I think that's, I think that's important is I guess what I
would say,
All right, so that's all good.
I think nothing particularly weird there.
I do Wonder, one thing I'm kind of curious about.
I just want to try.
This is what would happen.
If when we rendered since we have a little bit of time left in the
Stream here, what would happen if when we render we just reduced by
yours is we took your Z depth and we use that to reduce your
And why a little bit, right?
So what would happen if we said, okay, I'm just playing around here
when we go to draw stuff, right?
So we do.
We do our, I'm going to go a little, I'm going to go just a little
bit, I just want to try this.
If we were in here and we just said, all right, we've got our piece
drawing function, right?
Our piece group and when we draw our peace, our pieces, right?
Let's see where we draw those.
Here's, here's our piece drawing code.
We do this computation to figure out where we should draw them.
And then we draw them.
Right?
So we do like our ground point plus the offset.
And so on.
So if we were going to take that entity ground point this thing, I'm
wondering what would happen if we took the X and Y and kind of made it
be proportional to Z a little bit, right?
So if he basically said,
Add something, something.
like you know, Z fudge equals, you know, 1.0 plus entity
P dot Z times.
Some constant, which is however much we want it to affect things,
right?
And then we multiplied, we multiplied that entity PX by that.
Fudge Factor, right?
I'm just, just purely wanted to see what would happen if I did that.
I'm just curious.
So you can kind of see now that we have multiple
planes of Z motion, right?
You see how, like, what's underneath me looks like it's underneath me
now or I guess, you know what?
Now, I think about it.
I am on the bottom one.
So yes, I have to walk up to the top one.
Right?
And and I can't walk through this yet because we haven't done 3D
Collision detection, but you can see.
So since we wanted to look at that 3D rendering thing, I was I was
curious.
What would happen if we did that and we really need to add that 3D
Collision detection so we can see it better.
But that's a good example, right?
Of something we could do rendering, why's that would make it so that
it was easier to tell what was above and below you in cases where you
See through things.
Yeah.
So we'll talk about that a little bit more.
I was just curious.
What would happen there?
So I'm going to say that's a that's a that's a good thing to play
with.
Anyway it's time for the Q&A.
All right.
Please prefix your questions with Q: so I can see them and we will go
ahead with the Q&A.
Let me put Q&A on there but yeah, I'm going to I'm going to add that
to our list here and say that under how is this rendered?
Z fudge.
I was just I was curious about that the other day and I've kept
forgetting throw it in there, but I think it's good.
I think we're probably going to do something like that.
Yeah, makes it feel really pretty nice, actually.
I'm guessing the engine will manage arbitrarily High Ground levels.
Would you really want that gameplay, such as projecting a tax to a
monster below?
Does sound fun?
So, I don't know.
What we'll want to do gameplay wise but I mean basically the idea is
just that I want to be able to support whatever we want to do in the
game with the engine just to show how to program it.
And so mostly that's what I was trying to make sure we did was like
Always, make sure that whatever we wanted to do.
With with grounds and stairwells and Holes in the Floor and stuff
would be cleanly represented in the engine.
And so since this is our architecture past I'm trying to get that
stuff worked out and mostly it has to do with Collision detection,
right?
Because mostly the Collision detection and response, like how things
move, and how they hit each other because drawing wise, it's pretty
simple.
There's there, I do.
We're going to have to do that, much work for drawing it.
Like I like, you know, that c fudge was pretty straightforward, right?
So yeah.
Why not use the X and Y positions as they appear on the screen for
detecting Sim regions?
I'm sorry, I'm not sure what you mean by detecting Sim regions.
Yeah.
Could you be more specific about?
What what the question is?
I'm not sure I understand it.
Should you also check the stair?
Step at the top of the, top of the stairs?
It seems like you can exit earlier than at the bottom.
Yeah.
So what we, what we actually need to do too is you can exit the stairs
at any time, which is not good, right?
You're right.
I should I should put that in there.
The reason for that is because in this call, which is not in this
file.
Where is that?
Yeah, in speculative.
Collide.
The problem here.
Is that what we're doing is?
We are only checking to see what happens when you are stepping onto
the stairs, right?
We're only checking the different.
The difference between your height and the stair height, if you're
already on the stairs we're not doing a check at all, right?
And we would want to so what we'd want to do is see what your Z would
be when you step off and checking that
And that would have been way better, right?
So, you know, I can put a to do in here as well.
So basically say we need a concept of stepping onto versus stepping
off of here so that we can prevent you from leaving stairs instead of
just preventing you from getting onto them.
Yeah, so I agree with that.
Could you please do an overview on blackboard maybe of the entities
position system, World screen, the cetera.
Now that it's done, I'm having trouble understanding it.
Hopefully, you'll understand my question.
It's actually pretty simple.
Now, there's not a whole lot to it.
So basically we didn't do.
We actually, you know, what do we have this already?
I'm trying to remember if this was before or after the
Craziness got started or because I explain this once, someone asked
that exact same question.
Here it is.
Is this?
It?
Yeah.
Think so.
So, I believe this is the diagram could be wrong.
But basically, what happens is we have a sparse World storage thing
and that sparse World storage things.
Stored stores, the world's in chunks that are non-overlapping.
So they're just little little basically, like chunks of the world
where there we know there's some data and that basically is just a way
of allowing us to store as large a world as we want in terms of
dimensions.
Well, still only paying for paying the storage cost of places that the
world actually exist.
Instead of having to, if we were allocated as a giant array, it would
be too big, right?
So this allows us to have like, long thin, you know, sort of spirally,
whatever crazy path through the world and not have to worry about
anything when we do that.
So anyway, we store it that way.
And then what we do is we gather any time we want to do a simulation
We pick us at some point in that world to gather around and we
essentially construct a box, a three-dimensional box of the all the
entities that we, you know, all the geometry, the entire region we
think wants to be simulated in drawn together.
So we grab that out.
And there's some part of it is what the camera is seeing at any given
time that be like this here.
But there's a larger region that's actually being simulated.
And what we do is these entity, the entities in here are stored
position Ali as wherever they are in terms of their tile chunk.
So we're whatever chunk there in plus an offset in that chunk.
So it basically says like I'm in this chunk and I'm this far from the
center of the chunk when they're brought into the Sim region.
We translate that into
You up position that centered around whatever that Center Point is of
the Sim region, which would be right in the middle of the screen in
the terms of a scripts image.
And we're drawing, if it's Imaging that we weren't drawing, we're just
using simulate, it's in the middle of the box, right?
That's being
So all of their positions are then just stored as simple.
Floating-point, three-dimensional offsets from the center, we do all
the simulation work there and then at the end we write them back into
the World by updating their particular chunk position if they're
chunk.
If they've moved to a new Chunk, we remove them from the old chunk of
put them on the new chunk.
And either way, we restore their offset to represent their new
location relative to whatever chunk there in and that's about it.
That's really all that, that happens.
Why is the order of stuff drawn on the screen, janky?
It's because we aren't sorting anything yet.
Isn't it?
Easy to draw them in order?
Each player?
Draws any of these left to right top to bottom.
So not, it's not.
You're missing one thing, which is the Z sorting as well.
So, it's not just left to right and top to bottom, it's actually, it's
actually
Z+ y.
It's a little more complicated than that but yes.
And the reason is because we haven't sorted them yet.
So until we write a sort, we can't do that if that makes sense.
So I don't want to bother doing that till we get to the renderer
because otherwise we have to start doing the renderer to put the sort
into something because we need to, we need to actually buffer all the
end of these first before we can sort them.
And so obviously I don't really want to do that until
We actually start the render.
Otherwise I have to do half the renderer to put the sword in and then
stop doing the rendering.
Go back to what we're doing so since there's absolutely no reason why
okay?
I don't care whether things are sorted.
It's not preventing me from doing any other work.
It's doesn't seem like a good use of time at the moment.
Is the reason why things in different levels seem shifted up due to
the Z offset, when rendering?
Yes, it is, it is and we can get rid of that too.
Like if you know, we could make it so that the entities Z was only
used as an offset.
So this shifted up B is in here.
It's this
Right?
So, if you didn't want that, you could just do this, right?
That's that's where the shifting up comes from.
I think that what you're talking about.
So, if you didn't want that, you would it would look like this, right?
And, and that may be preferable.
I don't know, like I said, we haven't quite looked at that yet.
But that's where that comes from and then when you come up you're, you
know, you're still in the same shifting.
So that's where that comes from.
If that makes any sense.
Will this cause for the wall, on the top to be drawn above the screen
when the camera is locked.
Instead of following the character,
Possibly.
But I mean, we can adjust all that stuff and don't forget our wall
stuff.
I mean, we haven't really figured out exactly how we want to position
those.
When we do more world-building will kind of have a better idea of
that.
When you are allocating everything with custom memory alligators, do
you only use the stack for pointers?
I'm not sure.
I know what that means.
You can still use pointers.
With custom memory allocator.
So I'm not not sure, I'm sorry, I'm not sure I understand that
question.
Exactly.
Are you not worried that three dimensions might complicate entity AI
to the point where impacts performance?
Not really no.
AI is pretty easily tunable, usually like, you know, certainly it
won't will be have plenty of power to simulate.
I think the a eyes that are interacting with you directly.
And so, the only question is, what we need to do in terms of
simulating other things like large, large worlds, where other things
are going on.
And so if that's the case, then I would probably say we just simplify
it.
We'd make a few concessions and do simpler a eyes when you're not
there, right?
When you're not interacting with them, they do more, they do much more
coarse-grained behaviors that aren't as complicated or something.
Oh so for people asking about the form registration process, I have no
idea what to do about that.
Apparently we've get listed at spamhaus for some reason, I don't know
why.
And then the registration emails don't go out, it's kind of an epic
disaster.
It's the standard thing.
I absolutely hate the web and web development.
This is a very basic simple concept, but since, of course, the, the
the Brilliance that is the architecture of the web can't
and handle spam without ruining people's forums apparently and so I
have nothing but negative things to say about that and it's been a
huge pain in the butt so I definitely
Apologize to everyone who can't register and there's absolutely
nothing I can do about it apparently, because that is how awesome the
internet is at everything.
We really need to do is just create our own application, that allows
us to talk about handmade hero separately and just cut all these lousy
programmers out of the mix.
When will you switch back to centered camera?
We don't know.
That's like that.
We've already demonstrated that both work.
So I'm pretty confident.
We don't really need to test anything on there.
That'll just be when we're making a game we'll play around with how we
want the camera to be aligned.
Any particular reason behind making the chunk origin the center of the
chunk rather than one of the corners not particularly, we had both at
one point we were using the corner.
and,
Yeah, I can't can't really think of any particular reason to use one
of the other, I guess, one reason is because it makes it easier to
allow chunks to hold things that are bigger.
Like if you wanted to, you could allow things to be
A little bit over the chunk boundary or a little bit in set.
You it's easy to think about where something is relative the chunk
Center in that way where it's a little harder to do that if it's a
corner because then it's asymmetric.
So centers might be a little bit more convenient for certain things
but on the whole I think it's probably arbitrary.
I would guess.
Sorry for being unclear.
Do you store anything else than pointers on the stack?
on the stack, meaning the
Like the thread stack like the stack.
I mean, the stack stores, all the local variables and stuff.
I still don't understand tons of stuff is stored on the stack.
That's not pointers for example.
Everything you see on the screen Z fudge would be stored on the stack,
right?
Piece index would be stored on the stack.
All of these are on the stack, right?
So I'm not sure, still don't quite understand the question.
If the camera were far enough away from the player with a player, go
into a simpler routine like the rest of the entities.
Well
The cameras defined to follow the player so I don't know.
That's really case that could never happen.
Should the possible Collision test.
Use the test 2nd and
Of test any of the or are they the same?
Can you briefly, go over the flow of the hit entity changes.
They are the same so I can show you what's going on there.
So testing entity and test entity are the same.
In this case, always the only reason that we have.
It being set to test.
Hit entity is because there's another thing called Hit entity which
basically in fact, here's one way to think of it, this could just be a
Bool.
This is just a Bool as to whether or not we hit.
So for example, we could just make this kit
Like this entity, right?
That kind of thing.
And then in here we would just say get this equals true, right?
We're just trying to see whether we hit the thing and then what we do
is we say, okay if we did hit this thing, then before we were doing is
we were just setting the entity that we hit.
Which is this is this what tracks, whether we hit something or not
it's setting hit entity.
Before we resetting hit entity in here because it meant that we had a
hit and we would process it.
But now what we're doing is saying okay, if we hit this guy, the tests
entity
Then let's do.
Speculative, Collide first, and see what happens.
And then only, if it if speculative collides says, we should actually
press it then we record the hit as we were recording it before.
So that's all that's doing is just putting a layer in between the
detection of a hit and the acceptance of that as an actual hit.
And so these are just temporary variables to let us do that processing
without actually recording it into the
The loop itself.
Hopefully, that makes some sense.
I'll compile that it's
Just verify that that actually works.
so, there's
There's that version working, right.
And so again, all that is, is just before we were directly, setting
the entity that we hit.
And so, every time we got an earlier Collision, in RT testing, we
would just accept whatever the earliest one is.
Now we provisionally, say okay, we found an earlier hit but we don't
actually want to take except that as our new closest hit, until we
check speculative, Collide and find out that.
It's okay.
Because maybe it's something we should just pass through like a
Well, when we're not trying to step onto it from too, great, a
distance.
Yeah, so yeah.
So what we, what we do need to do is we need to handle the stepping
off case.
Right.
And so that would also require us in here to kind.
Do a little more work trying to think.
I haven't really thought through exactly how we want to do that.
because it does seem a little bit, does seem a little bit difficult,
but, you know,
That's that's just the way it is.
I suppose what we would want.
You know what?
I suppose there is a way we could do this a little more easily.
If you're stepping off the stairwell, we could just see where you were
barycentric lie on the stairwell.
In fact.
I guess.
Technically what you could do is actually do it a different way
instead of figuring out what the ground or the step height and stuff
is because we know this is only semantics handling of Z.
You could do this.
Instead, you could say
that the result is whether you're you're only allowed to step on the
stairwell at the ends, right?
So we could say our barycentric, why, which is where you are on the
stairwell, in terms of where you were trying to step on to it or off
of it, we could just say that that Bary Centric y, has to be between,
you know, the first part of the stairwell and the last part of the
stairwell, right?
If it's, if it's in there, you're not allowed to step on or off of it.
Right.
Think that would work.
Yeah, and that does work.
You can see I can't get off of the stairwell, right?
Of course, we have that problem of the stairwells, actual Collision
region needs to be smaller than the width that you draw the stairwell
at because technically we're only checking that internal part of you,
right?
So I don't know how we want to do that handle that rendering bit but
that does that does.
Problem right now, you can't get onto the stairwell in the middle, you
can only get on to it at the end and whatever.
So oh I guess that but I guess that doesn't, that also doesn't fix the
stepping on at the end.
So I suppose you still do need to know whether.
Yeah.
So you still do need this basically, you would need to say if that
happens or this happens.
It's either case is disallowed, right?
And that would that would then allow us to
To do both.
So now you can't step on to it anywhere there and if you're at the top
you can't step on to it anywhere here.
But now you also can't step off of the stairs.
Unless you're at one of the ends.
That's a pretty easy way to do it as well, I guess.
So yeah, I don't know this, this needs this needs.
Needs work.
Right.
You could now cancel out the first hit this equals true and not do
other checks.
Oh you're talking about you're just talking about you, this kind of
thing.
Right.
So I was I think that's we're talking about if that is what you're
talking about, that's not actually true.
Because if you look at what happening here, we need to find the
earliest Collision so it may be that one of these is going to be
earlier.
And so this test well, normal and team in will be set to different
values.
So you actually cannot do what you were suggesting you can't early out
on this variable.
You need to do all the tests you find out, which while you actually
hit first, right?
So yeah, just to be clear.
You can't.
It's not that's not a valid optimization.
That would actually change the result.
All right.
Looks like we are coming to the end of question time.
Question time.
Yeah.
Yep, looks good.
We have come to the end of, not only another week of programming on
handmade hero, but we have done something that we have never done
before.
Ladies and gentlemen, and that is agreed to go on break for a week.
Now, normally, I don't like going on break for a week.
From coding.
I don't think I've ever had a week in which I didn't program
something.
That is absolutely crazy.
I'm okay with it because I program every day for work anyway, so
that's fine.
But going on break for a week.
Just just philosophically from programming.
I don't love, but people were asking for time to catch up.
With the series and so I can totally relate to that and I will be
traveling next week so it would be hard for me to stream the live
stream anyway.
So we decided to do is we will do a little break here.
Where next week we will not be doing handmade hero and then we'll come
back the week after.
So, basically this whole week here, the 2nd, through the 6th we won't,
and then on the 9th on Monday, the 9th will be back with him in here.
So enjoy the vacation.
I hope you get some good programming done and whatever else catching
up on the series or doing whatever it is that you'd like to do.
And I hope to see you back here when we resume until then, if you'd
like, to follow along with the coding, of course, you can pre-order
the game on handmade here at dot org and download the source code.
It comes to the source code, every night I upload it.
After we finished programming.
If you'd like to support the video series, we do have a patreon.
You subscribe to and
Flicked off here, media.org as well.
We have a news and Forum site which the wonderful architecture of the
World Wide Web is doing its best to make.
Sure never works properly.
Thank you very much to spamhaus for listing us as a spammer.
Even though we have never sent out a single email, that wasn't for the
forums, literally, we don't even have a mailing list and we all
listened to the spammer so that's awesome.
Again, really solid web architecture.
If you're wondering why I absolutely hate the internet and it's code,
it's
Because of stuff like that, every time we try to do something, it's a
disaster and that is often completely out of our control.
Anyway that said we do have some other good stuff on there.
Besides the fact that they are breaking our forums and that is that
people have done Community modifications to the engine stuff to make
it, run on Linux, and mac and stuff already.
Even that's not something that we've done.
You can find those ports on there and that's a cool place to check
those out.
There's also other resources.
They're like a annotated episode guide, which is pretty cool.
And when the when spamhaus is not blocking your registration emails,
you can also go to the forums and chat with other developers about the
code base.
And so on, we also have tweetbot the tweets, the schedule.
So if you want to know when things are happening, it obviously won't
be tweeting anything next week because the series will be on vacation,
but the week after it will resume tweeting the schedule.
And that's I think everything I've said, we also have a video archive
on YouTube so you can watch all the older episodes there as well.
So thanks everyone for joining me and I hope you have a good week.
I will see you guys back here, not next Monday, but the Monday after.
And yeah, it'll give us some time to think about other stuff.
We might want to do with RC handling.
So thanks everyone and have a good week.