All right.
Hello, everyone, and welcome to handmade hero.
The show Rico to complete game live on stream.
We are in the middle of implementing a Sprite graph, sorting system.
And really, we typed in the code for the Sprite cast, sorting, it
wasn't very complicated.
We haven't really optimize some of it yet.
So, you know, it's going to get a little more complicated, but it's
actually pretty straightforward what we needed to do.
So we did it.
But in order to actually get it going, we kind of have
Bunch of infrastructure stuff that needs to sort of get upgraded a
little bit in order for that to happen.
So that's kind of what we need to talk about today.
And it occurred to me too.
That, you know, one of the things I was sort of at the end yesterday,
I was kind of saying like, oh we got some stuff.
We got to do here, blah, blah, blah.
And I want this stuff to live in the platform code and all this other
stuff.
I was saying.
And one thing that occurred to me is I realized that if we wanted to
we might also take
Take this opportunity to move most of the rendering code back into the
platform there, if we want to because it looks like we really don't
have much in the way of calls that go through.
And I think we kept a lot of it pretty isolated.
So, if we want to and we kind of mentioned this at the time, if we
want to, we could probably Explorer putting some of those things back.
On the other side of the wall,
Which would also get us reloading on them as well, which you know,
seems like a pretty worthwhile thing.
So I'm just going to take a look a little bit at some of that stuff,
not saying in advance, what we're going to do, because I'm not sure
it'll depend when I get in there and actually sort of have an opinion
about it today is day, 30 5.
So if you're trying to follow along at home with this day, 304 is the
money day.
So, here we go.
So yeah, I guess what I'm thinking is just that well, you know, if we
take a look at what happens, say in opengl dot CPP, you know, if you
take a look at what goes on in here, there's really not a whole lot in
terms of stuff that gets called back, right.
We've got platform delicate texture and platform allocate texture
which are actually coming through the other way.
And so those would no longer have to be callbacks if we put these up
into
Main part of the code.
So that's what actually be a win.
We get rid of a boundary transition there, which, you know, the less
boundary transitions.
You have the better in my opinion.
So that's always good.
And if you take a look at what we've got, in terms of other things, we
just have a bunch of in lines here.
Really they're pretty straightforward.
I think we have an init call, which is this situation right here and
then we just have the open G.
Enter commands call.
So you know what?
It occurs to me that we can get rid of this which it requested us to
do.
What do you know a to do down?
We didn't even start coding it, we already got rid of it to do.
All right, call it there.
There you go.
Works done for the day.
Let's go to the break room.
Let's go to the fancy Silicon Valley, break room and get Eminem's.
Okay, so it does seem like if we wanted to since opengl.
Obviously is a cross platform API that we certainly could do some
stuff there.
Now of course you can see that we've got our wiggle stuff in here, but
I believe the wiggle stuff actually is only happening in the win32
platform layer stuff.
So we could move this piece.
The Wiggles specific piece over and leave all the
Windows stuff inside the opengl part here, and put it actually into
the game code.
Because the only thing we would need to do is exposed from the game
code, just that one call for probably, I'll be honest.
Opengl renderer commands,
Is probably the only thing we really need to maybe in it as well.
I guess we would need an it because you only want to call it once.
Probably.
I'm not sure.
So anyway and opengl display bitmap is again something that we have
only if we want to do our software rendering but same same it's
exactly analogous in the sense that we can just have those two calls
if we want to still support both modes of displaying, you know,
because remember we had one that goes through up in jail and one that
goes to set the i b or stretched a bit.
So I don't remember what and wind up calling but
GDI path through to the graphics card instead of a opengl path through
the graphic card.
So let's take a look at doing that.
I feel like that's a pretty same thing to do and yeah, I don't really
know a lot of reason why we wouldn't do that.
So I'm just going to take a look at it and if it turns out that it
ends up being something, that's not such a smooth move, right?
If it turns out that we get a little bit further in and I'm like, that
doesn't look right.
We can always pull back.
So yeah, so I'll take it trepidatious lie.
I'll take it like
One step at a time and if I feel if there's anything that's sort of
feels to me, like it's a little bit.
If it just doesn't have that flavor than I can, I can always pull
back.
So if we take a look at our platform API here at some point, we should
probably go through here and and simplify this a little bit, but
again, we'd already, you know, it'd be an even trade.
This platform API doesn't get any more complicated because really all
we're talking about here is like platform, you know, opengl
Old display.
Sorry, opengl display bitmap.
And platform.
Opengl where's that render commands?
Right?
So we could do that and we would end up with an even trade in terms of
complex trust about boundary.
Now, one thing that is kind of nasty, right?
Oh and I guess you know what?
That is is not exactly.
That is that is not.
What I actually wanted to do, what I actually would need to do because
those are past the other way.
So I actually need to do them down here.
Like, so we have got game update and render, for example, we would
need one more call.
That's, like, does the a call for doing the actual Graphics work?
So, I take it back, we would do something slightly different.
We wouldn't be having it there because that's the platform API.
So we get rid of to, but we would add a different kind.
So if you did that, I'd be fine with that.
However, once we move these guys in there, we're going to have all of
these GL calls, right?
And having, those GL calls isn't necessarily a problem because we can
include those bindings and we can link the dll with opengl, right?
If we want to sew on every platform, we would link,
With the whatever the opengl platform Library stuff was and go from
there.
However, you can see.
Also why that maybe isn't the nicest thing to do, right?
So, you know, I'm a little hesitant to go that direction because as
I'm thinking about it, I'm like, well, you know, all of these GL calls
are actually platform calls and at the moment, when we compile the
game code, we don't actually ever
We don't ever actually do anything where we would require platform
calls to be inside that compilation boundary.
So that actually as I'm looking at, it gives me a little bit of pause.
I I don't really like that idea.
And the reason that I don't like that idea is because I mean if we if
we took this kind of to ridiculous, sort of level of
Sort of what sort of look for.
If we push this really far, you could imagine something like, oh,
well, maybe we want the game code to actually be shared on all the
platforms, right.
You could imagine a sharing the game code on Linux and Windows and
Mac, where and I don't mean sharing the source code.
I mean sharing the actual dll because we could easily write it so that
our Mac and Linux versions just load the windows dll and jump into it,
right?
Because at the moment.
That code doesn't link with anything and so I think that may be enough
to put me off it.
I feel like that's enough to put me off because I feel like it's maybe
just a little bit too valuable to preserve that.
And so if we wanted to, I would almost say we could move the loading
code into a separate dll that we load if we wanted to have hot
reloading after the rendering code, we could do that.
I just don't.
I just don't think it's worth it to go that far because I'm looking at
it.
I'm just thinking about how many of these calls are were and we're not
going to virtualize, all those calls probably the way we did here.
I mean we could but I think that's just a lot more trouble than it's
worth.
It's okay.
All right, I've convinced myself that I don't want to go that route.
So I'm going to stick with the route that I was talking about before
where we're going to do something.
Not quite so not quite so aggressive.
Now we have two ways we can do this and I guess I haven't quite
decided on which
One of those I'm going to do, but one of the things we did before is
we kind of took out where did that go?
Where is our sort here?
So we had like our sort entries and I believe we didn't call it before
because it doesn't take two arguments, right?
And if you take a look at the actual call to that, you can see that
the problem was that it's expecting a memory Arena and stuff like that
because we want to be able to use that sort of thing too.
Make the code easier to use.
So when we're calling something like sword entries, what we want to be
able to do is we want to be able to use those memory reinsert.
So there's two things I have sort of suggesting one was moving, the
Sorting into the platform Civic layer of the other that I sort of was
thinking about was, well, the other thing we could do is just move
memory Arena as a thing out into the platform, so it can be shared in
either case and I do think there's something to be said for that
because memory Arena.
Bringing more things out into the platform code and allowing them to
be called.
Always seems like a good idea to me because like for example, right
now, we're already kind of in a situation, where inside this win32
code here, there's plenty of stuff.
We probably could have used the memory Arena stuff for that.
We aren't using in a marina stuffs for because we're not including it.
And so I feel like maybe that's a good sort of, just, it's a good time
to sort of take that move it out.
And then, we wouldn't really have to worry about that anyway.
So let's take a look at doing.
I'm going to go in here to handmade code.
Here is handmade code and I'm going to, I guess.
I'm going to copy handmade .h to handmade memory dot h, and I'm a copy
handmade.
Well, I guess I'll copy handmade at H2, handmade memory, Dusty p as
well.
I don't have a thing.
I haven't programmed for a code, to get to stick my
Weird like notice thing at the top yet.
So I tend to just copy a file that I have that its existing I need to
actually write that should have written that the other day but I
forgot to oops.
That's a spelling error move and odd May memory to handmade memory dot
CPP.
Alrighty then
So anyway, let's see here, memory dot CPP and H.
There we go.
So, okay, so in the H file, we've got sort of the memory Arena stuff.
Here, we have the temporary Arena.
We've got some of these zero size zero', struck, kind of things.
And all of that stuff, I think alignment, no, clear, sighs worry, all
that stuff, pushing this stuff kind of already.
As you can see, just it already, it basically makes
Its own.
You know, this is the sort of thing that I talk about all the time but
you can see it's example like
It's always easier to just make what works first and then pull it out,
right?
I don't, and I never had to decide like what should all go in there.
It's just like, oh, now I know here is a very nice class, basically,
write, instead of creating like objects and thinking about the objects
or whatever.
Instead, I just made the stuff that I need and now when it comes time
to make it into some nice little component, well, it already is one
and all I have to do is like, pull it out to a file and then trim off
any things where it may be had.
Like latches into something that it really shouldn't have, you know,
because it wasn't conceived As A Separate Peace.
And now I know that it just works correctly for everything, right?
So right now there is nothing to be done in the CPP file.
I don't think we don't really have any fancy stuff with memory that
we're doing.
Everything is very simple like one shot things.
But in the future, if we do have some stuff that wouldn't potentially
be inlined, we could we could go ahead and do that.
Okay, so let's take a look at what I need to do to make this.
Now be included in both places, obviously, handmade dot h.
That's one of the very first thing that's
Burning.
So I think I don't know what's in handmade shared.
This is just some stuff that we were using handmade shared, was that,
that's just some stuff that we were using for.
The parser.
when we did our little,
That even in hairstyle.
Yeah, simple preprocessor dots groupie.
I think that was grabbing this stuff anyway, so handmade shared.
I don't know if anyone actually is that really shared at this point.
Like, for example, it does that actually get good included, is that
only shared between the preprocessor and us, or is that shared between
know?
It is.
So it's here.
So I guess we could just go in handmade shared and say, all right, in
addition to that,
Handmade memory in here because handmade memories also going to be
shared, right?
And then I don't know if there's a shared Dusty BP.
Apparently, there isn't and so, maybe since we don't have one, I can
just go ahead and delete it, right?
So handmade, every dot CPP can go away.
Okay, so let's take a look.
All this stuff I suppose, like doubly linked list inserts and free
lists allocate and stuff.
We could probably move those over eventually as well.
I don't really want to look at that right now because I'm not sure.
So I'm going to go ahead and just delete, just do the very simple
thing of deleting the stuff that we had before.
Because all this stuff now exists in another place.
There.
And so now I think we're good and that means that now memory Arena can
just be something that's actually works just fine in here and we can
create one and use one and all that other good stuff, right?
So if I want to make sure I can use a memory Arena here, then I can,
you know, I can literally just say, well, let's, let's verify what the
actual parameter order is here because I don't remember.
So we've got a memory Arena and the out index array.
So yes, the passing the memory Arena here will be relatively easy.
We just need to make sure that we have some memory for this thing to
use, but we also have the problem now of the out index, array.
We want to kind of move towards using the out index array, for
rendering, which we don't currently do, right?
So that's that's another thing that we have to do completely
separately.
So yeah, so let's take a look at how I want to do this here.
First of all there's a couple things I feel like now also might be a
good time to sort of play with that memory stuff.
If I pulled it out, it might be a good time to have the concept of an
overflow memories State.
Like one of the things that we don't do at the moment.
But that we very easily could do is right now.
We are always forced to allocate everything up front, right?
Which is fine.
And, you know, not really a problem, but there's a couple reasons why
sometimes that's problematic, right.
If you happen to be on a platform where it's, you know, everything is
known and everything is, you know, like it's like, it's like
old-school console or something like this, where, you know, you just
have however, much memory you have.
Then it works really nicely however, on Modern systems like Windows or
whatever especially if you're in third.
To bit Windows.
You don't necessarily know how much contiguous memory you can get.
So sometimes for example, let's say we wanted to use three gigabytes
or.
Well, that way too much.
Let's say we want to use a gigabyte of memory for our game because I'm
32 bit Windows.
Probably, that's the most you get away with.
Maybe you can get away with two gigs but probably not continuous.
So if you try to locate one, get continuous, sometimes it'll work.
Sometimes it won't because there just isn't a contiguous memory range
available to give you, right.
And so, even though there might be one gigabyte of memory available,
you it has to come out in chunks.
And now, the way that we happen to allocate, our memory would allow us
to have our memory come in chunks.
And so one thing, we probably should do before the end of the project
is make our memory Arena so you can run them in multiple modes, one
mode is, you just gave it a block and then gets you into the Block.
It's done, right?
So if you want to do it that way on a platform where, you know,
exactly how much memory you have, you can just lock it and go and then
on other platforms where you might be worried or you just want to
support.
Like infinite memory.
Like you just want to be like keep allocating memory until the system
tells you to stop.
We're not going to set a limit.
So if the player tries to just create an infinite Network, like who
knows?
I mean, it's probably doesn't really necessarily apply to him a hero,
but imagine you were running some other game, you know, like a
Minecraft kind of a game or something where the players are supposed
to be able to go off into infinity.
And you want to use as much memory as possible to store that without
dumping to disk or who'd.
I mean, I don't even know making stuff up now, but you
And easily use the memory Arenas that way as well, where you just keep
allocating more and more and more and more.
Until the operating system tells you to stop, right?
So the way we've written our code, we really don't have to change much
to support that.
And so that's another thing that we could play around with here for
example.
And I could show you how that might work.
In fact, maybe that's maybe that's interesting thing to do after this
as well.
So anyway, so for example, when we do went through to display buffer
and window here, you'll notice or passing two different types of
memory in.
But my suspicion is we don't really need to do that, right?
What we could do instead is say that we have a memory Arena here and
this is just a temporary NE.
And what we could do is just pass that temper Arena into these guys
and they could allocate the memory on at themselves and then we just
have to make sure that that temporary NE has access to enough memory
to make this work, right?
Okay, so here's our sword entries calls to.
If we pass this, the temporary NE off, we would go and in the
linearize, crip clip.
Rex thing, we could pass the temporary new there as well.
And what we could say is, well, all right.
Whatever is going to happen here.
We could also say that the sword entries for example, Returns the
32 array that we're going to actually use for sorted entries.
If we wanted to write, we could do that too.
So in other words, this part right here, the the out index array
thing.
We could actually have that be something that this thing actually
allocates from the arena once once we allow that.
So then what we could do is we could say, oh okay, you know, begin
temp memory here.
And then n tent memory eventually.
Actually don't remember how this works.
Well, I remember how it works.
I just don't remember what the call looks like.
Yeah,
temporary memory.
So I can start the temporary memory and then I can end the temporary
memory and basically just put this.
So we do all of our rendering, whatever needs to happen.
Can happen with a temporary Arenas, have a party whatever, doesn't
matter, nobody cares.
And then at the end, it's just all wiped away, right?
And so that way, these guys can do, whatever they want to do, we can
return the draw into some sort of draw indices.
From sword indices and we can linearize the clip Rex like so and I
don't actually know where that like you'd think that would actually
return something here as well.
So we're going to skip breakfast and then we would like pass them
through or something.
But doesn't look like that's what actually happens.
So I'm not sure and maybe these wouldn't have to get rid done here
either.
Maybe they would just go into the render queue and that's fine.
I'm not sure.
So
We'll look at that in a second point, being these guys can now both
allocate the memory that they want to and then it was get flushed when
we get to the end.
So, you know, it's all nice and clean and tidy.
And in these cases when we call opengl renderer commands, or when we
call software vendor commands, we can pass those linear lives things
through.
So, I'm going to take a look quickly to see, just what these people
are expecting to do, because I don't remember it.
Kind of what the policy was when we went through here.
Where these guys
Are getting their stuff from so you can see.
Okay, so we're calling like get sort entries here.
So, basically what we're doing is, we're looking at that render game
render commands bit and we're sort of grabbing off of that.
And I'll be honest, that doesn't necessarily seem to me to be the most
efficacious, or were the most sane way to do that, to be completely
honest with you.
I like, I mean, we could do it that way.
I don't know.
Maybe.
All right.
I mean, I'll leave it that way.
That seems to be what we did here.
Maybe that's a sensible, I don't know.
It seems reasonable to just keep it bundled in there, I guess, because
that way, there's just one thing which is the game render command
structure which flows through things and we add things, we don't have
to go changing a bunch of people's code so I feel like that's not you
know that okay.
You know I could buy that that doesn't really bother me.
I'm okay with that.
So anyway yeah if we imagine in here we were going to do the sort of
drawing so then it makes it kind of clear how this would happen.
So essentially what would happen here is instead of this person ever
getting sort entries, it would never actually get that, right?
It's just going to call sort of draw indices and
And that's going to come this way, right?
And once you have the sort of draw indices, we're just going to go
through the count and we're never going to have this, this entry thing
here, work that way, right?
We're just going to have it be a, you 32 for the entry and we're going
to have sort of drawing to cease.
In fact, we don't even need swords throwing to cease to be a thing
anymore.
Can just be like that and then the entry just gets plus plus as we go,
right?
And as we March through there, we can get the entry by just looking at
what the entry actually.
It is a value.
We know if look at the index, the index is not relevant, right?
Okay.
And then everything else operates as normal?
So we can go back over to render.
And do the exact same thing, right?
Because there's really no difference between these two Loops there,
just the front ends and they work, they have to work a dummy because
the whole point is they read essentially off of an identical, they're
doing identical things just in completely different ways.
So the first little part of them, he's always going to be pretty much
exactly the same.
It's just what happens inside the loop.
That's completely different.
So anyway again, same thing here instead we can just do this and get
rid of that.
It's exactly the same.
and then we kind of come in here and we do our entry work, we just
have to dereference
So at that point, we have to ask ourselves though, get sorted into
C's.
That's actually a new thing that we're talking about adding here
though, right?
And so, when we take a look at where the game render command stuff is,
you can see how all this stuff works here, and we kind of have our
clip for x and we got the sorted, indices and Mama Mama Mama Mama.
And so, what we need to do at some point is we need to go ahead and
have in there something where we, where we actually have storage for
those sorted, indices.
And you can kind of see here.
Why I'm not why I was a little bit like you know it wasn't it wasn't
my favorite and and thing.
And the reason for that is just because there's two fundamental stages
of operation being represented here.
One of them is, when I am building these render commands in the game
to sort of handoff to the platform layer to say, here you go.
Now, render, all this stuff, right?
And that's the game render command structure, and it's, you know, it's
working, okay, to have a lot of complaints with it.
But then we clearly shoehorn in, and I seem to remember, I did this
kind,
And we're kind of debug system, so we weren't even working on the
read-a-thon.
We clearly shoehorned in this clip rect thing and we
The clip Rex in here.
But the clip Rex, don't actually exist as this linearized piece until
after and we're actually staging the render.
And now we've got a second thing which is these sorted indices, right?
And so I kind of feel like I would be more comfortable with it.
If we had another structure here, that was representative of that
second stage, right?
And that second stage is like game render prep for
Thing, right?
And that game render prep would just be a thing that, you know, you've
got this first wreck last trick that's actually real.
Then this cliprect clip Rex is stuff, that's only made as a linearized
thing.
As part of that post you know that post amble.
I would kind of like to see that here potentially, right?
And then stimuli, I would like to see, you know, the, the sorted
indices here as well because these are like part of that.
A memory, they don't actually work the way.
Any of the other stuff works because they're not actually built by the
game.
The game never even sees these and they don't exist after the end of
that call.
So I kind of, you know, like I said, I was okay with it.
I just really wasn't so, you know, looking at, I'm pretty sure that
that's just a thing.
I'm going to be happier seeing in real life in the world.
And then inside here you would always pass both of those.
So you'd pass the prep and you'd pass the commands and then inside
here,
Are you would say like, all right, I want to get the sorted indices,
well, okay.
Now we just know they're right off the prep.
We don't have to grab them out with a function call or any of that
thing.
I don't even.
We're even was that, is that what is get?
We're was get sorted into C's?
Well, we'll get an error on it anyway.
I'm not get started as the clip wreck stuff.
It doesn't matter.
So point.
So point being
That's that's how I would I think I would like it to go.
And that means that anywhere before where we were talking about,
grabbing the clip, Rex from the clip Rex array, it's not going to be
in, it's going to be in the prep stuff, right?
It's going to be in the prep stuff.
So same thing just pounce back over to the opengl version.
Exact same thing here.
So, instead of this, oops, I lied, we were in the opengl version.
Same thing here.
I just want to say like let's go get the prep sorted.
Indices.
and,
There we go.
And the same thing here for the clip Rex, right?
Those are coming out of here now and that's all
So that just makes me feel more comfortable.
And then back here in win32 then we just have this concept that.
All right.
Everything we're going to do here for prep, right?
We can now do.
In the context of this game render prep thing, right?
And so I can go ahead and take the prep and I can make that.
In fact, I could actually just do it this way where I pass it in to
each of these guys and they like, fill it out properly.
I could even take it one step further.
And I kind of like the idea of taking it one step further, where I
don't actually know where the linearize clip, Rex thing even is.
Where is it?
I do not know.
Hello.
Where are you?
There you are so linearize, clip.
Rex, I could sort of have that, and the Sorting stuff kind of work
together.
And at this point we sort of have the idea that the sort is not really
going to be a specific sort anymore.
It's actually a sort that's entirely based on.
Like it's a graph traversal, right?
So it doesn't really even want to be in that file anymore either.
So I'm going to, I'm going to kind of say, oops, I'm going to kind of
say that we could if we want to kind of pull those out and make those
be something that's not in sort anymore.
Because we kind of have this sort key nonsense here where we have our
merge sorts and already sorts and whatever.
But none of that stuff is actually going to use in.
All that stuff is actually going to be in here and then we wouldn't
have a thing in here that produces one of these game render Preps.
Right because this this sort is now and this sort is so simple.
Now to we could just move this out, we don't really need a handmade
sore anymore.
We could move this into shared or something.
I'm just be like, here's the sort have fun party time.
Everyone loves it, you know, you love it.
Okay.
So anyway, if we win and cure for preferential order, then we could
just say, well, this stuff is actually just goes in the platform
nonspecific code.
Anyway, that way any platform is trying to do.
Just calls prepper Ender doesn't have to worry about, you know how
that's, you know what that even means.
And then they just passed the prep on to whoever whether they were
trying to suffer render or
Or Hardware render or whatever.
And we don't care, right?
You just passed the prep and off, you go, and that's it.
So that seems to me like a lot better and that prep for render is
only.
It's really just needs these two things.
It just needs the commands and the
Arena.
And then we can it can do its thing.
Let me get out from behind my own head here.
At some point Alan Webster should make a mode in for a coder that just
understands that you're streaming and it like automatically like has a
boundary here that makes it so that you scroll when you go over into
that area or something, I don't know.
Since so many of us stream now anyway, so yeah, we would call prep for
render.
It would do its little happy dance here and then we could.
Yeah, do the rest of this stuff.
Pretty trivially, right?
So let's go ahead and Implement those assuming that we pass a memory
Arena.
Where is my linear rise?
Or it is, I'm going to move that down a little closer since the Sprite
sort stuff is so fussy.
Alright, so in linearize clip Rex, obviously we need to know the first
wreck last wrecked nonsense, right?
And then this clip memory memory garbage, what was that was kind of
all.
We just kind of slung it in there, right?
But we can make that a lot cleaner now, and we don't need to do.
We don't need the platform layer to be doing all this stuff recall
like get
Working memory and blah, blah, blah.
Like that's all kind of annoying, right?
We don't really want, we don't really want that.
Like, we don't really want that this leakage into the platform layer.
Understanding your like, how many of these things the renderer was
going to have or anything else.
So this needed clip memory size stuff and the collapse with above we
can do all that stuff, right?
We can just get rid of this entirely and instead before we go to
linearize, the clip Rex we can just say well, how many are there?
Well according to us it's going to be the push buffer element.
Count times, however, many of these clip Rex.
We actually have.
And so, that's a pretty trivial thing that we could do with our our
push array, right?
So if we want to, we could just say, well, alright, this thing rigged.
This thing Returns the render entity that the linearized version of
the render entry clip, Rex, and we're going to just say that that is
going to be, you know, the clip, you know, result I guess.
And we can just say, well, push an array of this mini.
Of those.
and again, you can kind of see here, like this should be kind of
obvious, but, you know, in case it's, you know, too distracting with
all the rest of the stuff going on around it, the importance of good
utility classes, like the memory Arena,
Right, and I guess I shouldn't call it a class.
As a class, you know, means something to C++ people.
But utility functionality, whatever you want to call it.
The importance of having.
Those is that, if you can figure out a set of operations that that
clean up the kinds of codes, you tend to write into much more simpler
forms, it just makes all the code, much more robust less likely to
fail and much easier to read and write the same time, right?
So instead of all this fussing this here, where we were trying to
maintain that stuff,
we already had good solutions for using temp memory and getting more
of it as we needed and all that sort of stuff.
And just by allowing the platform layer to use that, right?
We're leveraging the concept that we already built something that
works well and that we know does what we needed to do.
And so we just want to be able to like you can sort of see as the code
gets much more simpler here and put more importantly in the right
place so that people don't have to know about things that they really
shouldn't know about.
And
You know, it makes it when you keep things in their correct, places
like that, where you have sort of the code that's about the rendering,
does the rendering stuff?
It means that when someone needs to go replace the platform layer,
they don't have to know as much about the renderer, which is good.
Right?
And that's kind of important because the platform layer is probably
saying that often will get replaced like other things in the game are
probably not going to get replaced very much with the platform there
is going to replace like 10 times or something, right?
We're going to
Robbie, replace it, three or four times ourselves if we want to do pie
and Linux and mac.
And who knows what else, right?
So, we'll probably replace it a few times on stream but then who
knows?
Who else will want to point things.
People already poured it to all sorts of things and so, as you know,
in the final version of the game, we definitely want to keep that
platform part as anemic as possible because we don't really want
people having to rewrite or really understand a bunch of code.
They didn't really want to understand when all they were trying to do
was get handmade here are running on whatever platform, right?
And so by moving the understanding of how much memory is necessary
outside of the platform layer and into the renderer where it belongs
to the render.
That's actually using the memory.
That's obviously a good thing even separate from the cleanup part
because it means that the people who now Port the platform layer don't
see any of that and that's better.
It's just easier for them.
It means that they don't have to worry about what that means or how
they have to interact with it.
So same thing is here.
The sort memory write that stuff.
Just comes out and I'll leave it here for now.
But sorry, I'll leave it here for now but really I think we don't need
any of it.
In fact, we don't we don't pass sort memory around anywhere.
We just use the arena directly, we wrote it that way to begin with, so
we're fine there.
So yeah, so here I can just return this result and you can see that, I
sort of did my push array.
So I got that many clip.
Rex back.
I don't really care about any of this stuff at all.
I take my out and that's just going to be my result.
Now, I don't have to do any casting because we already have the the
sort of memory arena is capable of doing that for us.
And then we just go ahead and do our linearization and we're done.
Right?
So much cleaner much nicer.
Everything's a lot more, you know, sort of easy to understand as well.
So here comes the render prep.
Here is the sorted entries.
I don't remember what we called that.
Sort of indices.
Oops.
We've got sorted indices and we've got clip, Rex.
And both of those are going to allocate the memory inside the
temporary NE and then give it to us.
So then we'll just go ahead and return that back and we're done,
right?
So that's our prep for render.
Everything is copacetic and the memory Arena that we're given.
We assume we can use when we consume that, the color will clean it up
when they are done with whatever it is, we did.
Okay, so what are you complaining about rendering tree clip?
Rect right that's going to need a struct.
That's fine.
And I didn't first Sprite bound is not here when we do a push render
element.
Well, why isn't it?
I don't actually know, I'll be honest, I forgot what we were sort of
doing it.
Oh, because we don't probably include render inside render group,
that's the problem.
So that's sort key business is a little bit of a problem for us.
You got to love sea and they're ridiculous forward, decoration
nonsense anyway.
Certainly forward declaration is just ordered declaration whatever you
want to call that.
All right?
So
Here's all the stuff we've got.
We've got Sprite bounce, right Edge, Sprite Flags, right?
All these things.
So this seems like a reasonable time to say, okay?
Let's go ahead and get a handmade rendered out of H.
And we'll just stick those up in there, right?
Yeah.
Wait a minute.
How did that work?
We deleted that
we deleted that right there.
I guess we must have saved it.
Oh, you know what?
It probably exists in here.
Yeah, that's what it was.
All right, kill that.
Handy though.
Anyway, so we've got our handmade rendered at H.
So in the render group stuff in here, where we actually need it, we
can go ahead and say well we're as render group, there's handmade
vendor group.
So you know in here we could just say like okay before we do this
let's just include the handmade render.
That's got that stuff in it.
Okay cliprect count obviously.
Is I guess something that we need to.
I guess that's something we can put in the commands because it's
always the same.
Right.
It doesn't actually it's not transient so I can keep that.
I'm okay with that staying in here.
And then we would we will have to say that's this part still in the
commands because that's not a transient key.
So that's actually, I probably should have thought of that.
That's not, that's not really appropriate to be in there anyway, okay.
So render commands to bitmap for do tiled work.
I guess the deal.
Year is that taking the prep stuff now.
So when we actually call software render commands, and here, we need
to have the ability to plan to pass that prep.
Because, well, because it's important, right?
So
that pointer is got to be there.
And so whenever we actually call that guy,
Can I put this up here now that we have an H file?
Handy writer dots because in Winter to we don't include it.
We're do we do that.
Okay, here it is.
All right.
So we need now, this thing to have our game Bender crap.
Snip.
And out index.
A okay.
So now we're sort of back to where we were, and I think everything is
now a little bit cleaner and we still have a little bit of work to do
with our memory Arenas, actually prepping them because right now we're
not passing the memory Arena too.
Like will they'll be a compiler will get to in a second that we just?
Haven't looked at yet which says like hey you didn't pass memory does
thing, so that actually obviously has to happen as well.
Anyway, for our sword entries here, we need to do an allocation on the
count so we need to do a push array.
Into the temple Rena.
And that temporary know.
We need to tell it.
We need this many you 32s for our indices, because we're going to have
one for every entry, right?
Because the sort doesn't change the number of them that there are so
That's about that.
And then at the end here, we're just going to return that
I guess I could call that result so that it's clear to everyone.
This is the thing we're actually producing, right?
So let's see.
What is the problem here?
Not enough framers for macro push array.
You know what?
I agree with you because I didn't tell you what a ring to use.
That's the arena to use render commands Undeclared identifier.
That's true too.
How's that?
Is that better?
Opengl renderer commands.
So we got it passed the address of prep since we're not actually
passing the it by value.
And so, there we go.
So now we're down to just the memory Arena part of things and so now
we can kind of get rid of.
I think I just a lot of garbage like this is just all.
This is just junk, right?
I mean, there's really nothing else to say about it, it's just
garbage.
So what we want to do now is we want to say, okay, get rid of all of
this, and let's actually have a memory Arena.
Now, what we can do obviously is we can cheese it out to start with by
just giving it a memory.
Now, that has some amount of memory and we just know we won't go over
it, right?
So let's we'll do that first.
And then we'll kind of say okay?
What if we were to change the way this stuff works a little bit.
Moving forwards.
And so if we want to actually make one of these things inside,
handmade memory, we've got initialize Arena, right?
And so I can just say that this is the, you know, render Arena or
something and I don't even really need, I could just call this the
frame Arena.
Because it's really just I mean I could use it for anything, right?
I could use it for absolutely anything that wants to allocate memory.
That's in the
That's just getting dumped at the end, right?
So so if I want to initialize the arena, I can say, okay there's a
frame temporary NE let's say we've got a memory index to size.
That's that's what this going to be framed chimp.
Arena size.
We'll just make one of those and we'll win through to allocate memory
that much memory.
So let's just say we gave it 64, MB of memory, its massive.
We're never going to use that much, whatever, so that would be fine.
But I'm going to say to do here.
Let's make this, our first Global Arena, so I can show how to do that.
All right, so sword memory and clip memory are no longer necessary.
Now we just have a frame temporary NE and that's it.
Okay.
And yeah, so we've made so many changes.
Now we're probably going to be in for some debugging certainly because
I just went through and, you know, went crazy town and everything.
So let's take it one step at a time and see where we're at, okay?
So this is let me disable that for a moment because I want to actually
test a few things here.
I don't actually want to check our sort order.
Okay.
I actually don't even, I don't want to check any of this.
I don't want any checking, no, stop it.
Okay.
all right, so let's start with our
Let you know, I got to be honest with you, I was not expecting that to
be an assertion that we hit wasn't expecting it.
I have no idea why we asserted their cliprect index is less than
commands clip account.
What tell me what the
Oh, never mind.
It's actually just the assertions triggering.
I thought it was like saying the commands with
Little after lunch there.
It's true.
I'm out of water.
That's part of the problem.
Yeah, so, like first things first year, so let's think about this.
We're getting a commands cliprect count out of bounds error, which
means that we're just getting garbage in here, right?
And so the header we're probably reading we're probably reading crap,
right?
Type 560 is probably not a legal type, right?
Like, you know what?
Have four render types.
So except like five render types.
So, you know, 560 clearly this was not a valid header, I don't
actually remember what the, what the actual number of them was.
But
Let's take a look.
Here, here's the types.
There it is.
So you know, we've got what 0, 1, 2 3 4.
So anything over 5 is completely invalid and we've got 560, right?
So this is clearly not pointing to real memory.
Like this is this is a garbage situation here, certainly.
So let's take a look at what the entry was, the entry was Zero.
and there's plenty of them, so I'm not sure why that would have
created a problem for us, because if we're just looking at entries 0,
that doesn't really seem
like it would have been a problem.
Oh, although there's probably nothing at entry zero.
Now, that I think about it, we never actually wrote we.
When we do our shortages, we've never actually written anything in
here.
Have we like, did we actually ever do that?
I'm not sure that we did.
Walk Sprite graph walk out index.
Where is that index array?
So did we do?
We actually do
And how many of these do we actually produce?
So let's, let's figure out here.
How many of these we've actually produced?
Let's do an assertion.
And figure out whether this is producing anything that can actually,
that could even relatively be real.
And you know, what I could do first to let me assert, let me put the
assertion in there because I want the assertion in there but then I
want to check something else too.
So when we do the walks paragraph, I want to verify, I guess right
here I want to say that the input node count.
I'd like to say that the walkout index that we end up with
- the out index array.
So, the number of things we wrote, we're looking at like our output
pointer and are where we started.
I want the number of things, we wrote to equal, however, many things
we had total, and if it's not, then we missed like, our graph.
Walk is not actually outputting valid values for everything, right?
So we need to make sure that that's correct, but the other thing I was
going to say, is since we did so much work here, I'm going to put an
if 0
Around these guys.
And I'm just going to write a much simpler Loop.
That just goes through all of the nodes.
and,
Grabs out.
Whatever the index is of that node and just writes that, right?
So it's basically saying like, Okay, straight copy the indices over
because that should work.
That way we're not looking at the graph sort routine stuff, which is
stuff we did before.
Okay, so all of our stuff is now flowing without crashing, which is
what I wanted to just verify was true because we made a bunch of
changes there and if I look at Arkham its eyes, it looks sane, right?
I don't see.
I wanted to make sure there was no grounding of sorry, no, grounding
that's good.
I want to make sure there's no growing unbounded growing or anything
weird happening there.
There shouldn't because
We're not doing a dynamic allocation yet, but just want to make sure
everything was still stable.
Okay, so
Now, we got to go back to here.
We know, we're not doing some things correctly.
I'm assuming that we will find quickly that we either blow the
assertion or we're just writing the wrong value out.
And in fact, that may be the case in fact that is the case.
This is not the actual index we want obviously, we want that that's a
little misleading and probably, we should change that.
Indexes kind of the wrong term for that, but yeah.
There you go.
What can you do anyway?
In this case we are asserting.
The flags is zero.
So that looks like it's not getting cleared up stream our flags
anyway.
So we should probably go ahead and and make sure that it actually is
cleared up stream.
Let me go ahead and take a.
Look at where that's happening.
By the way?
Did you guys follow what was happening here?
You might not have.
So I'm just going to say sometimes
You know, I'm really really old, right?
And so I'm so used to certain kinds of programming things that I did.
I just didn't like, oh, right, that's whatever right, but I realize
that, depending on your level of a experience, some things maybe like,
wait, what?
And it's not helped by the fact that sometimes, you know, I don't pick
the best names for things or, you know, I've done something.
It's not quite done yet so it's a little janky and it's hard to follow
or whatever.
But in case you can follow what happened there.
We've got two concepts of an
X happening in this particular case and really one of them is more
like a pointer but it's not quite a pointer, it's more like an offset.
So really what would help is if we probably name
More correctly offset because there's two things.
There's the index, which is, you know, we have n Sprites that are
coming in, so you could think of them as each having an index.
The first one is 0.
The second one is one, two, three, four, five.
All the way to Index, right?
So we have that and that's sort of disarray that we're using for
sorting, we kind of know that.
All that stuff is there, right?
But in addition to that, we also have the notion that each one of
those things has data that exists at some point in the push buffer.
Well, that point in the push, buffer is the offset, right?
It's this thing here.
And so when I said at index what I was doing was writing the ordinal
essentially like which number Sprite this was into the thing that the
renderer uses to go grab the data but it can't use that to get the
data.
It needs the offset into the push buffer where that thing is in order
to draw it.
And so that's why we were getting an invalid chunk of memory.
They're really very basic but you know, like I said if it's getting
mixed up in your head, I don't blame you.
It's you know programming is just there's a lot of stuff happening and
just kind of kind of keep track of it all.
So anyway,
So what I could do there, right?
Is?
I could go ahead and say, look, let's you know, let's make this a
little clearer here.
This is, this is an offset, it's not an index, it's an offset into the
push buffer, right?
And by the way, while we're here, when I'm writing in these entries,
you know, if we, if we flip back there, we know that.
That's where the we wanted those flags to, right?
We're saying, we want those flags to be set to 0.
We weren't selling the 0, so we might as well do that now so that
that's clear our screen area is not getting
That at the moment.
So we also need to set that which is kind of going to be a bit of a
chore since that's the thing.
We don't actually know at the moment, you know.
That's that's definitely a little, a little dicey first edge with me
as front.
Also don't know if we need to clear it.
Probably do though.
I would assume.
And that's another thing we probably should be asserting.
So inside the render sort, as we're going through there.
And we're checking that each of the flags is clear.
We probably also want to check that each of the first edge with me as
front is clear as well because presumably.
Well, although I guess we can't really, because that may not be the
case anymore at that point.
I mean we could do a pre-check right, but that's about it.
So anyway, our problem now is, I think we've done most of the stuff
that we need to do.
The problem is our sorts, not going to work, it's not going to do
anything yet.
And the reason for that is because we haven't set the screen area.
So even if we had no bugs, even if we just happen to implement
everything perfectly for
The reason we made no mistakes, then this actually still won't do
anything because this rectangles intersect fit call will either always
fail or be random or whatever because these two screen areas actually
have nothing in them.
They're just garbage.
Right?
And so what we need to do, if we want this sort to actually work, is
we need to actually fill those up with some information about where
these things are on the screen and ideally we want to actually get a
fairly accurate.
Accurate boundary, for whatever it is that we're putting in here
because in theory, if that boundary is more accurate than our sort
will be more accurate.
If it's inaccurate, we may get sorting bugs, that are not due to
sorting are going there.
Due to the fact of the boundaries that were feeding, the Sorting
algorithm are wrong.
And so, that's, you know, something we need to be aware of.
so, when we do a push render element,
You can see there's a couple places where we're doing it, right?
Coordinates system is not actually called.
So we really just have the clear the rectangle and the bitmap right.
Those are the places that this actually gets called and each of those
places needs to be able to produce that screen area, whatever the area
actually is nice to be able to produce that screen area so that it
knows how to sort.
And, you know, one of the things that's probably true is to be honest.
The fact that we clear the screen to a color like, you know, do we
really want that in all of our sort graphs, like why is that a thing?
It doesn't matter, right?
And so I feel like that could even be pulled out.
It's just wasted work.
We know this clear comes first and at the moment, we're never really
going to do anything.
More stuff with that.
But who knows?
You know, I guess for now we'll leave it.
So we need to produce a full screen rectangle.
The clear.
We need to produce the rectangle for the record, that's going to be
easy because it is a rectangle for the bitmap.
It's not as easy as it seems.
The reason for that is, we're kind of, allowing like shearing and
stuff at this point.
And so it's actually relatively, you know, it's not difficult, but
it's a relatively involved procedure to produce what the actual screen
space bounding area is we will have to check all
Points.
Now, I'm over time.
So I think what we'll do is we'll just leave it at this today you can
see exactly what we need to do for tomorrow.
We'll do it tomorrow.
Get the screen area is working and that'll be it.
But for now I'll go to the Q&A in case anyone has any questions about
what we did.
And I'd also like to go to the global Arena stuff.
So we'll do the screen areas will do the global Arenas and then we'll
start cranking on
Our graph stuff work well.
Do you have questions?
Do you?
Have.
Questions.
Introvert has a question line, 31.
Well
Line.
31 Is An Open Bracket.
Is that what you wanted to know in sofa?
So I'm guessing that nobody has any questions.
So, if nobody has any questions.
All the gern.
Room since not on top, where the final game be orthographic?
Yes, the the game is orthographic.
The game's perspective is more top-down and basically as soon as we're
done with this and has got a great art pack for us.
So as soon as we get all of our Sprite nonsense under control, I will
I will look forward to that.
Brian wag when you're calculating pre-allocated buffer locations with
offsets, do you find the pointer bugs that pop up sometimes difficult
to track down or is that kind of a non-issue when you do it often
enough?
Yeah.
I guess what I would say is it's a little hard for me.
Like I suspect that some of my like surprised at people when they like
are like scared of using pointers or
I feel like they're really difficult or who like Felix think they
really need garbage collection, whatever, I do suspect that some of
that is failure of me to remember, probably how hard it was to get
used to doing all that stuff, when I first got used to doing all that
stuff, right?
Part of the problem with programming for a long time, is you don't
necessarily remember what was hard and what was easy to make your
brain do.
And so there probably is a little bit of the like
There probably is a little bit of, like, I just do this all the time,
so I just don't tend to have bugs that are hard for me to find or
something, right?
There's probably a little bit of that, but I would say in general
that, you know, even having programmed for 30 years or whatever and
how long I've been programming 32 years.
I think power of 2 number of years.
Even having programmed 32 years occasionally, I will still get a
really hard bug, right?
That takes me like a day or two to find or something right in.
And I've talked to other programmers, who I hold in very high regard
and they say the same thing, right?
So sometimes you just get a crazy bug and in my experience
It's pretty rare that it has to do with that.
Like,
I just don't find, that's the kind of thing that I spent, you know,
it.
They're usually like
usually they have more to do with, like,
Trying to think of what a good example would be.
Like usually the really really hard bugs have to do with stuff, we're
like youth.
I think that you did a math thing in one way and you don't have
visualization of it or something but it turns out actually it was this
other thing that just happens to work most of the time and it doesn't
work in this case or something and they're like eventually you have to
dig in there and draw it all out and you're like oh that's what's
happening, right?
Like it's usually and I guess I just putting that aside.
It's usually just bugs that are hard are problems with your mental
model.
Usually
yeah, it's like you thought X was happening but why was happening.
And so you never considered that.
The bug could have been a, why bug?
Because in your mind you were doing X, right?
And so I find that usually it doesn't super matter.
What X and Y are like, it doesn't matter if if that was pointer
arithmetic or mathematics or string concatenation or parsing or
whatever else.
It's just if you have a complex piece of code, for whatever reason,
and you think it's doing, why?
But it's actually doing X or vice versa.
That's the part where the bugs, take a long time because an
experienced, programmer can find a bug.
They're looking for is basically what it comes down to, right?
But even an experienced programmer has trouble finding a bug they're
not looking for.
If you're looking for some other bug because you believe can't be in
this other part of the system, or
It can't be because of these assumptions.
You will never do the tests necessary to find this one and there is
the problem, right?
Because even in a credibly Insidious kind of pointer bug like
corrupting some memory silently like way back when or whatever.
If that's often times, very easy to suspect like you get some crashed
somewhere in.
Like what the hell is like?
How did that?
That could never happen if it turns out to really be something because
of pointer arithmetic, you'll find that very
Lee because you're just set a breakpoint on that data and you'll wait
for it to happen.
You'll see who wrote it and you'll be like, okay was yeah, Point
arithmetic bug, right?
The problem comes when that happens but it's not a point arithmetic
bug, right?
And now you're like, how is that?
And then you realize oh in this one circumstance in like it was this
got set and then it cut through a series of valid things.
It's slowly arrives at this thing or whatever.
I don't know.
You know and so that that tends to be my experience at the programming
is is really like I don't find that.
Because Point arithmetic is with another thing you can do.
You can take a language that has no pointers and you can still make it
just as heinous and complicated as the most complicated pointer thing
you might do by just using other constructs of the language, right?
I mean, you could imagine taking a language like JavaScript, which is
designed, you know, to not really have anything like that.
And I mean, you can add members to classes run time and all this other
stuff.
Fright, you can easily create some super spaghetti crazy.
Nasty thing that's super hard to tease out.
So the pointer part is just because maybe if you grew up only
programming in languages that didn't have them, maybe taking the jump
two pointers can be a little daunting, but once you're there, they're
really, they're not really any harder than other programming
constructs that you don't have that same fear of and I don't feel like
the complexity fear is really that warranted.
There's super
Crazy ridiculous stuff you could do in JavaScript.
That's so much more hard to debug than a pointer problem, right?
And yet people don't seem to approach that with the same level of
trepidation.
And, you know, I would I would also underscore the point that a bug is
a bug, right?
A crashbug isn't really any worse than another kind of bug, right?
You could have a craft, that might be more severe because hey, the
little dialog box pops up and it's scary.
But if your program deletes the users data or it,
The file or it, you know, doesn't do a thing or it's really slow or
whatever.
All those are are similarly bad sometimes worse, right?
And so the fact that pointers are things that might crash you, maybe
leads you to believe that somehow, they're really hard to work with,
but no, it's like they're really just another thing.
A lots of things in programmer complicated.
They're one of the things that can be a little complicated, but at the
end of the day, there's plenty of other stuff that should be equally
scary to you.
If you were scared of pointers to scared of a lot of things and you
know at the end of the day, I think people perhaps overstate the
degree to which you should be scared of them, right?
Which system did you start programming on way back in the previous
Millennium?
I started programming on a deck rainbow
In fact, it looked much like that.
That is a very good that is.
That is how I remember it, in fact.
And so I was I was seven at the time and so it was a year I guess if
it came out in 1982 than it was a year after
It came out that I that I learned to program on it.
So I suppose the kid, I knew there is debug code for how long
functions take is there any debug code for how
Remembering is being used.
Unfortunately, not yet, we should write that.
Like we have not written that, and we probably shouldn't some point.
It's just the debug code.
We spent a lot of time fussing on.
So I, you know, I didn't go do all the things we could have done in
there because we'd already spent a long time, but it would be nice.
But the moment we didn't write that now.
All right, I think I think I'm all done.
I think there ain't no more questions.
Ain't no more questions.
This was a pretty fun computer I programmed in like base.
There was like a, some kind of basic on it or something, but I don't,
I don't know what the model like, I don't know what the basic was
probably came at that, huh?
so,
So it probably was this if this was bundled with it so it's probably
Microsoft basic.
But I'm not sure.
I can't remember.
But yeah.
So
I think that it was the M basic on there, that I learned to program
in.
And I don't think I learned to program in anything else on that
computer.
I'm pretty sure that I started programming in Pascal after basic and
that the Pascal was on a different computer because the, the
computers, my dad had computers from
From work.
That's why we had one of these.
We didn't own.
It was like, it was like, you know what, he bought, the computer.
It was just took take home from my dad's work.
He worked at digital Equipment Corporation and so
The rainbow like when away at some point shortly thereafter and, and I
think the vaccinate was what I learned, it was like a 286 fish thing
or something.
What was the processor in this thing?
Yeah, 286 surprised.
I remember that this thing.
I think was the thing that I learned Pascal on
And you.
I'll be honest, I cannot remember which Pascal it was.
I mean, the obvious answer would be that, it was turbo Pascal, but for
some reason I feel like it wasn't turbo.
Pascal.
Yeah, I don't I don't really know.
Yeah.
And I wish, you know, I always wish my one of my biggest regrets is
that I never had any reference material for Assembly Language.
Like, I always wish I had had I never knew how to make anything in
Assembly Language.
I never had any documentation on how to make anything Assembly
Language.
I just never knew.
So I always had to use like Pascal or something.
And the problem was you couldn't do anything in the on these computers
in Pascal.
So like I always had to make like slow,
Crappy things.
Because you couldn't like make high performance Graphics in Pascal.
Really like that is not a thing.
And so, I wish that I had had more at that time because like, a 286 is
a pretty good in 8.
MHz 286 is a pretty good CPU in Assembly Language.
You could have done some interesting stuff on that and certainly
people did but I didn't know any of that and I couldn't do any of it.
So,
Anyway, so yeah.
When was turbo, Pascal?
Can see the thing is it didn't look like this?
It did not look like this and maybe that's because it used to look
different than that.
What did turbo Pascal look like in monochrome.
That might at that, that looks more familiar.
That that does look more familiar.
All right.
Anyway, I'm going to close down.
Did you program on the Amiga?
Yes, much later.
I don't think I got an Amiga till 1987.
Or ate something like that.
Remember the year?
but,
Did have words to our key bindings.
I don't remember.
Yeah, I do not remember sorry.
All right, thank you, everyone for joining me for handmade here.
It's for pleasure coding with you.
As always, if you would like to follow along at home, you can always
pre-order the game on handmade here at Oregon.
It comes to the source code, which you can follow along with every
night after I am done.
Also for him site, you can use to ask questions a patreon page.
You can use to support the video series.
If you like what you see, we also have a schedule about the tweets.
The schedule at you if you want to stay up to date with the live
stream and we have a past episodes guide that you can go to to follow
up on stuff that maybe I've mentioned.
If you haven't been watching the series the whole time, you might want
to jump back and see a couple places where we did stuff that interests
you.
That's it for today.
I will be back here.
5 p.m.
Pacific Daylight time tomorrow.
Hopefully, we can finish up our sorting stuff.
I mean, probably won't finish it up but like, get it all working, at
least a cursory first pass so that we can focus next week on actually
getting the graph algorithm working nicely.
So we have our Sprite sorted, which is what we wanted.
Anyway, until then have fun programming, and I'll see you guys on the
internet.
Take it easy, everyone.