So it's about time to get started again.
So one of the things that people who watch the series on Twitch know
that oftentimes in the twitch chat or even on the stream data oriented
programming or other.
Other terms like this, come up and pretty much universally, what
everyone mentions and what I mention on the stream is go watch, the
CPP con keynote by Mike, actin, go check it out.
Like it's a fantastic lecture.
And it's like, it's just the perfect thing to point people to, as an
introduction to sort of the same sorts of stuff that we always talk
about and given by somebody, with, with a lot of credibility industry
as well as is pretty great.
And so when I was putting together who I wanted to come talk to you
today.
I was like well I don't I don't know.
Mike actin and never met him but I was like I just can send him an
email and see if he wants to come because I know that everyone would
love to hear what he had to say and and he was able to make it.
So thank you very much for coming and we're going to
Talk to him.
I guess he was making notes during Tommy's talk, so he actually has
some stuff that he wants to talk about separate from my list.
So, so this should be pretty good.
So, please join me welcoming Mike actin.
So Mike, I do have to say, this is an entirely different reaction that
I got from the C++ program.
What?
You do, we're gonna so before, you know, will we, I'm interested to
know what's on the list.
But before I ask about that, I just wanted to say quickly for people
who don't know very much, like for people who aren't in the game
industry.
For example, obviously, you do the technical Direction at Insomniac,
tell them just a little bit about what that actually is because
there's probably people have never worked at a game company before
those people would not even know what that necessarily means.
So okay so we have an engine team and you know,
The in the AAA space, I'd say we're about, we're at the low end of
size and the AAA space.
So our engine teams about 20 people and people and that includes the
our engine support people, which we have two people who are not
programmers on the team.
Okay, Steve Lee doing testing and other organization stuff, okay?
And so yeah it's a engine team and we do not just the engine run time
at all.
So the tools and supporting all the current games that were working
on, which tends to be somewhere between three and six Active games in
the studio.
That's a lot for 22 people.
Sure.
I mean so so yeah, I mean, we do all that engine in tools support and
Chase around the studio.
I mean, in the rest of production, which is another roughly 190
people.
Yeah, are divided into their various Productions and shared, you know,
groups and things.
And so yeah, we're
Running around supporting all the, all the games in development and
working on the engine and active forward features and whatever.
You know, the current fire and problem is and whatever.
The current demo is and whatever.
The current thing that publisher wants and that we want you not to
show off in terms of our vision of the game and Tech.
So yeah, it's a lot of stuff and I think you know there's that you
know we are like I said, sort of the small end
Dove AAA but you know, that means that it's very rapidly.
Yeah, from really have to be moving fast and there's no room for slaw
at our scale, right?
When you have a bunch of games in development and a team, you know, of
the size and you have to support everybody and you stuff to make
forward progress on an engine.
And you have to make all the details and everything.
Everybody is moving all the time and so what's your role in that?
So my role is the director of the team which is, you know, largely to
work.
You know, work with the team and work with the leads on the team and
organizing and make sure that we, you know, it's well, I like to tell
the team that your job is what you make it and I think that's true of
just about anybody, right?
You find you figure out what your your best way to contribute is.
And for me, you know, as the Director that's really sort of sitting
down with everybody sometimes, it's Architectural Review and saying
you know what, it is that you are doing and how do we approach it?
And is there a better way or is there?
You know, can I just ask the right questions to
Sort of cut off this you know a path that's going to waste a bunch of
time.
Okay.
Or is it sort of low level review?
I'm just looking at some code and doing that, or is it I, you know,
it's actually valuable for me to sit down and write something here,
right?
Okay, so sometimes you'll actually jump in and do something if that's
like really critical at that point.
Yeah, I mean it happens sometimes.
You know, usually though the that's not the highest value thing I can
be doing, right?
I, you know, I want my job as much as possible to be X.
You know what everybody is doing?
So as much as possible.
I need to be making everybody else better and spending time figuring
out how to help them become better programmers and that's really where
or better leads or whatever it is, right?
And that's really where the value comes in for what I do.
So, like, you know, obviously, I think, most people are probably seen
this EP pecan lecture, and the sort of stuff you talked about about
focusing on, you know what the actual problem is and the data and
transformation in the hardware, all of these things.
Do you find that, you know, at your scale which is, you know, 2020 or
so programmers who are working on, you know, engine console engine
stuff you've get a lot of our, most of the people on that team of the
same opinion as you about those things or is, is that, like, is there
some degree of tension about among people that, like, a lot of people
want a lot of object-oriented stuff is starting to look like, how does
that?
How does that look on your team?
Because I don't really know.
Because you're essentially a person with a very specific opinion about
that.
And what is the rest of the
Look like I would say, well, I mean to be fair most you would be
everybody.
Looks moderate by comparison to me.
Okay?
Okay, so that's true as well.
I think on on our engine team, right?
And the further away a think you get from from the engine team, the
more, that's true, okay?
Now, when you get to the sort of the gameplay team, they're going to
be less in that spot.
Okay.
But I think even among I think even among the the engine
Even though I mean I think we're all you know about the same kind of
fundamental principles, right?
We're all about understanding what it is that we're doing and and it's
really the small things that are different and it's about, you know,
it's how much we compromise that it's okay difference.
So there's no fundamental argue, there's certainly no one, no one on
the team that's saying.
You know what?
We really need here is more abstraction.
Okay?
What we really need here is to spend some time making uml diagram,
okay?
Okay, is no one, that is not said that that painting.
All right, so yeah, it's a matter of scale, right?
It's a matter of, you know, I you know how much is too much and you
know how much is it you know, where they wear something else really
more valuable to spend time on so I think maybe as a team we look
Extreme as a whole compared to other teams so your extreme in an
extreme team.
So in some sense yeah it's just some degree but I think yeah I mean I
think everybody is, you know, really wants to understand what you
know, not just their database.
What it is that they're doing and and fundamentally solve be rational
about how they solve problems.
So, within that space, if you're working with smart people who want to
be rational, it's hard to go wrong.
Okay really.
So, so like one of the questions I wanted to ask because it's
something that I get asked a lot of time and I'm not really in a
position to answer on the show is a lot of people worried or have the
understanding that a lot of the things that have to do with maybe like
object-oriented.
I mean, or other the kinds of programming that you were explicitly
saying aren't very helpful.
Like, in the CPP, con thing, that those are necessary for larger
scale.
Look they have this opinion that.
Yeah.
Okay.
If they start to believe that focused problem-solving kinds of
programming works for one person, they don't believe it would work for
20 people and somehow the like object-oriented this is necessary or it
comes as part of this attempt to make the programming scale.
Up to larger teams.
And so, as someone who is actually, you know, in charge of making sure
that such a team runs smoothly, would you say that's accurate
inaccurate?
Would, you know, what are your thoughts on that?
Kind of a comment or question, right?
So, here's the problem with the question, perfect, which is that, you
can't defend the question, okay?
Right.
You're giving me secondhand question, certainly.
Yes, right?
So, you know what?
I would be asking the whoever was asking the question was, you know,
from where do you get this?
Joint.
Right?
You know it because somebody told you yeah.
Is it because this is your actual experience that, you know, you've
been working in the space for this long.
But, you know, I mean, basically, the answer is no, that's complete
bullshit.
It's, it makes no sense like, that's why you would want to get to the
heart of the question.
Because the question doesn't make any sense.
Okay, there's no evidence to support none zero evidence to support
that.
In fact, I think, you know, if you looked at, we look if we just did a
Search.
So the most successful you know, you know the libraries for instance
that a survive, the longest have been the most successful.
You probably wouldn't find a deep object hierarchy in them, okay?
You would find sort of simple you know interfaces?
You know you might they might have their own problems.
But you know this you know the simple, you know, input output
interfaces are going to certainly last the test of time and be
complicated and support.
I mean, how many how many projects have used say
Lib C or leave em.
Right?
Right.
You know, that that's a large fairly large-scale, right?
And then lots of projects have used them and, you know, and to be
honest, I think that the real, the real answer to that is, it's
actually counterproductive.
Okay.
So scaling to a large project, you know, if we look at Deep object
hierarchies and that kind of design, you know, I'm gonna sort of
imagining in my head, what that design looks like what happens is
you're hiding.
So much valuable information and you're creating so much not valuable
if we serve adding.
Yeah, problem, right?
That you're making the problem more complicated than it is.
And when you have a bunch of people, 100 people, you know, a thousand
people all making the problem more complicated than actually is, its
orders of magnitude.
Ultimately of just bullshit that you have to get through to get to the
what you actually need to do.
Yes.
A more bullshit, right?
And that I think is problematic like it.
Actually going to be more brittle and harder to understand and more
difficult to change and more difficult to test and pretty much any
measure that you would want.
It's going to be it's going to be poor performing then the equivalent,
you know, and you don't even know that it's equivalent sort of data
oriented model, which is the equivalent simpler model, right?
Just reduce the level of abstraction as much as you could have.
Instead of thinking that you were adding some benefit by making things
more removed, right.
I think
Adding, I mean, this is the thing that I disagree with a lot of people
on is that adding stuff to the problem.
Does not make the problem simpler.
It never makes the problem.
Simpler do adding something.
Always makes it more complicated.
So you want to find the absolute minimum amount that describes, the
solution that you're dealing with, or even the problem, right?
This is the minimum set.
This is the minimum thing and that's what your, what Your solution is,
right?
That's what you're dealing with.
As soon as you start adding even just adding small,
Those that are in your head like I'm thinking of the problem in this
way, that's something that you're not adding to the problem space and
now somebody else is going to come and read it and that they have to
reinterpret this model that you had in your head on top of what the
actual problem is.
And that's going to cause confusion and it's going to, you know, and
this is why, you know, this is why they say one of the difficult
problems in programming is naming because by naming something, you are
introducing preconceived notion.
Yeah, you're introducing
In problem space, so you're introducing your mental mental model to
the space that just doesn't exist there.
To that point, I did have one of my notes from go right ahead and
Tommy's talk where he Tommy.
Yeah.
Sorry.
I you were first sorry.
So you're just gonna have to live with it.
You said that, you know, you had you're talking about the physics
stuff that you're doing are the controls.
So your tummy what controls and you're saying, you know, you have this
sort of garbage formula, this is what your word right garbage from the
garbage data and that they didn't make any physical sense, right?
That was also your foot.
So here's the problem I have with that language of that is that I
think that you know the the preconceived idea that the physical model
that take trying to apply sort of a real world models of this that if
that's better, is a problem.
That's not it's not better.
In fact, you've demonstrated through your game that that's not better.
Write that you've picked a model that is better for your game based on
You're testing based on it, three months of hard work based on, you
know, the having a very clear input and output, right?
The input is the can this you know the controls, right?
The, your physical input, the output is Tommy Smiles, right?
That's it, is very clear, right?
And the answer to that is the the stuff that you came up with right is
that that it's not garbage, it is the right answer, it works, right?
It's
It's the appropriate response the way you did it.
Sort of testing it and iterating on it, and, and it doesn't matter
that there's not an eight, you know, you had to create a name for, you
know, twisting, physical, whatever in the air, you know, doesn't it?
But it doesn't matter that it's not real, right?
It doesn't matter, that doesn't fit the model.
I think you probably lost time by thinking, that it should have fit
the model and I think coming back and now even reflecting on it and
still using the word save garbage when you're when you're referring
to, it sets the wrong message.
So there is in fact, the
Opposite.
It's exactly the right thing.
Garbage would have been trying to make it real, right?
Because it wouldn't have been fun that kind of gets a sort of a, I
suppose an interesting mentality there.
That's true for a lot of stuff which is just there's a notion of
There is some like, you know, proper programming Elegance, something
blah, blah, blah.
And then if you're not doing that, you kind of have to couch your
statement about what you did.
Like if you're not using a real physics, engine simulating, all of
this stuff, or whatever you have to call it garbage formula.
So that people don't say, oh, you don't know how to program.
You're just doing these like hockey formula, something, but kind of
sounds like what you're saying is like, no, no.
Like the problem is to make this thing.
Do what it's supposed to do and whatever is the correct solution to
that is is the best programming.
You could have done basically.
Luckily, yes.
If it's the it's the it's a simple solution that solves.
Exactly.
The problem that I had.
Yeah, that's the right answer.
Anything else is fucked up.
Like, why would I do anything else?
And so, yeah, there's that whole idea that there's that you can take.
There's a solution in The Ether without context without understanding
the problem that must be the right solution to this problem is such
complete nonsense.
Like there is no other, like there's no other space.
I can think of, that's like that.
That's just complete and utter nonsense.
I so why we think that there's there's that's even a thing is
unfathomable to me.
But it is and we know it is and people do.
I'll bring that kind of stuff all the time.
Okay, so did you wanted so, I don't know what's on the, see, kind of
some kind of, like, leaning over my list here.
Let me just tell you some of the, let's see what's on your list first?
Because if you had something you wanted to talk about, I should not.
I should I should not interrupt.
So hey, you
You tell me okay, my list is totally random, just stuff that you're
talking Tommy just sort of like a girls night.
I just what I need to do is get you and Tommy up here to talk and then
and then I can go, you know, the lunch.
So you mentioned that you could lock down controls early, which sort
of lock down the level design now, you're design the levels around it
and I think this is a really super important takeaway for everybody.
This is not a lesson to ignore another nice, or I'll bring an
alternate.
Another example of a similar kind of thing, which is you to working on
a say, an open world game, which is much more common nowadays, right?
And we work on Sunset and Sons of seven World game.
And one of the things that people many people don't realize that a
sort of a fundamental function.
Everything is a fundamental function of like this.
One piece of information is critical to design everything in the game
and that's movement speed especially in an open world game.
Because when you know, when we're talking about an open world game,
we're talking about physics.
I mean real world physics.
Like we're streaming off of a disc.
Ultimately it's not.
Everything is not a memory.
It's got to come from disk.
And that disk has real speed.
Yes, actually moving around right now, is it?
So we say real-world physics, you don't mean simulated physics.
You mean the actual physics is of the world?
Spinning the Des?
Yes.
Okay.
So there's physical re, you know, and everything will ultimately comes
down to physics, right?
I mean, there's ultimately this the reason why memory is the way it is
and yet speed, but
This is a more human relatable, physical problem, like there's a
spinning thing.
And so you know, getting the data off that Des is a real issue, right?
And even Under The best scenario, the best circumstances where like
the best circumstance is really, it's a, a console space where, you
know, the console manufacturers, just bought the shittiest Hardware.
Okay, I'm kind of right, but at least it's at least, you know, that
right there is a baseline that you can work with unlike the PC.
See where there's probably an whole bottom whole Barrel that they
missed.
That's blow that but somebody who buying PC can find, right?
So you know as so you have to work with that, right?
You have to know that this is, you know, this is basically the
expected seek speed that you can potentially get off this drive and
this is the absolute, you know what, you could, what you could
statistically guess you can get off of these you know these drives in
terms of bandwidth.
So those are sort of Baseline information that you absolutely have to
have to make any decisions.
All and then you have movement speed, right?
So you're moving around and that's determining sort of what you're
loading in.
We just determining how it, how fast can you get from here to here is,
how much time I have to stream in whatever?
Is there right?
Yeah, so which will ultimately determine your budgets right?
If I'm moving faster, my budgets, get smaller because I can only, I
can very good flesh intrigued, you know, assuming you have your world
divided up in some kind of tile, right?
And so
You know, you say your movement speed to say it's like 50 meters a
second.
That's a completely different game than if it's a 10 meters is because
now your worlds, you know, you're sort of tile, budget is
significantly different between those two things, right?
Radically different how you design the world, how much you can load
and you know, all that is just as radical differences between those
two choices based on this one variable, that's pretty interesting too.
Because that sort of is especially if you're talking about a large
team that basically affects
Almost everybody who's working.
Yes, the artists have to know this because they need to know how
detailed to make their stuff.
What it will look like, you know, how you know, especially if there's
lotting that happens or something like this, you know, what can I
really expect to have seen?
It affects the programming team because they have to think about like
it, what are we?
You know, how are we going to design this for balancing thing and
everything?
So that that really that one number, I guess, could could pretty much
change.
Literally everyone's job in the company, depending on where you said
it.
Sure.
So let's say you started.
I mean, we can go one of two ways is how you started out slow, right?
Say we're just making up numbers here.
The thing started at 10 meters.
Second and you're going through, you do a year of development and all
of a sudden boom through iteration.
Everything programmers just know what you know what 50 meters seconds,
that's fun.
Okay.
Okay, so now you have to go back and basically toss all the love of
work that you've done redo everything and a year.
And if you have 50 people or 100, people are 200 people.
Or if you soft, you have like five thousand people all working on that
one levels, right?
You're potentially, you know, you're potentially throwing the millions
and millions of dollars.
Yeah, right to say start over.
And maybe that's worth it.
Yeah.
Probably.
It's not, you know, and, and that's just because, you know, if you're
moving that much faster, your budgets have to be that much smaller.
Right, right?
Or if it's the other way, right?
Let's take it.
The other way.
You started off 50 and you go your development.
You say, you know what, really we're not getting much punch out of
that.
We can slow this way down.
Yeah.
And we can we can comfortably just like maybe you have more detailed
environments but same time now you have the opposite problem right?
You've done all this work and hasn't taken advantage of now this extra
buffer
Right?
And it's not a game.
May look kind of lousy by comparison to somebody because you could
have put all this detail in there and instead it's very spare because
it had to fit some streaming budget for like, basically a racing game
at this point, whereas you're a walk around looking for this game.
So the I mean, the lesson isn't really about locking knob controls or
about the movement speed.
It's about if, you know, figuring out what these sort of Keystone
variables are in your game or in whatever, you know the problem space
that you're dealing with is
Because you know, if you ignore them if you don't understand what they
are and they're always there and if you don't know what these key
stones are, what's going to happen is, you're just going fuck yourself
to, okay?
Because if you didn't pay attention to that, right?
You're just going to assume that I can just load the level, you're
just going to assume that it's going to work out.
And then you're going to say well I can just optimized at the end
which is the word you know anytime I hear that you want to slap
somebody.
You know you're going to get to the end.
You want to slap that person or just is there just like a person?
You have who's paid to be like slapped?
My I think this is just, there is a chain of people, okay?
So by the time it gets to that when you know, that one person saying,
there must have been a change that needs to Slap.
Ya, big long, slap, wake up, like a running slap.
Yeah, I'm just imagining that right now.
So yeah, I mean understanding what this Keystone variables are is
critical to doing your job properly.
Otherwise, you're just going to end up with sort of garbage and you
may or may not be able to make it make it work and ship it.
But it's either going to be really poor or it's not going to take
advantage of what you know what it could have had and if it's not
taking advantage of it then you know it's doing a disservice to your
players ultimately and
It's, you know, that's unprofessional.
So is that something that you sort of do organically I guess or is
that something that's actually more a little more.
I don't want a formal but like do you actually sit down when like
you're working on a project at the early end and you know, come back
to the design team and go look these you know, looking at the way,
we're this, you know, we're sort of talking about this game.
These are the very critical factors that you guys need to nail down
like now because you can't beat, you know, changing this or that or is
it not like, you know, how does that actually play out for you?
You when you're actually doing something like Sunset Overdrive.
Let's say so.
Yes, I think there are some, you know, when we can identify them and
is, you know, basically as soon as we can identify them, and we say
this or there is a massive knock-on effect.
Making this decision then,
We absolutely bring that to everybody.
Who will listen.
Okay, everybody has to just shut me up about it.
Okay.
Because yes, this is absolutely critical in must be decided or you
have to understand the cost of changing your mother.
What's going to happen, which is sometimes happens, sometimes they
say, I understand the cost of changing my mind.
Except that cost but I still don't know the answer.
So we have to move forward.
Okay.
Okay, fine.
That's just the way it is, okay, but yeah, I mean, absolutely you want
to identify those and make it make it loud as possible and you know
what people sometimes, you know, people don't want to hear it.
People don't want to hear that.
Sure that I have to, I have to make this decision now and you just
have to do it anyway.
Sorry doesn't matter if you don't want to do it just weird, you know.
So so yeah.
Yes, that's the answer.
Makes perfect sense, was there.
Another thing on the list?
I know.
I have more things in the list.
You okay.
Well, so I have, I think I can fit the thing I was going to ask, we've
got to let see 1250 as an hour.
So we've got it got plenty of time left.
So I want to do a couple more on there because the other things I have
to ask I think will fit relatively easily have to ask.
I have to there's a couple things I'm like I gotta ask them.
All right, I got a so exporting, cinematics.
Right.
So Tommy mention exporting cinematix as a problem on Super Meat Boy
Inside time-consuming iteration thing, right?
So I would like to share the exporting cinematix as a problem.
Does not go away should any scale.
And in fact, I mean Ron, who is I guess the inventor of the Cinematic
for the most part
We could probably attest to this being true from the very beginning.
So you can ask him that I wrote was true, I'll add in very beginning.
So, you know, we were looking at sort of cinematics, in Sunset
Overdrive and all of our cinematics are real time.
So you'd expect that that would, in fact not be a problem but real
time or not.
There's the, you know, there is a large animation and a lot of
Hand done work and that the enemy is doing in in Maya and our days.
And when you're saying cut scene here, in this case, nowadays is it's
in engine, kind of attendant and it's all real time.
It's all real time.
So it's not pre-rendered but it is actually designed right?
And the campus here and this.
Yeah yeah, yeah.
I mean it's somebody by like we have a cinematix tool that lets them
lay out tracks and do all the things instead of per frame.
And you know as you have seen you have music track that everything has
to be synchronized to the music track.
In some cases and all you have like the the first, the opening
cinematic and Sunset Overdrive had 90 shots, okay?
So it's a very just very complicated
Yeah, cinematic, right?
And you have to still deal with all the the fact that it's the game
and it's all the real-time things and still have to deal with, you
know, texture streaming, and all the things that happen and 90 shots,
you know?
Because yeah, that's a lot of shots.
So, it's a time-consuming process to build, but it's also a time
consuming process to export which we have which was not a real limit.
We're not a real problem.
Until we got cinematics of the scope and when you realize this is when
you really see the limits of the the
The work that you're doing, we use colada as our export format.
Okay?
And you know you can say what you want about colada which is you know
you can you can start with saying it's not a great format.
Yeah I totally agree with you.
Is it like compressed?
Text compressed would be a stretch.
So is it like it's been like to text?
It is text.
Okay?
It's XML.
All right, all right.
It's yeah, that's about.
Don't we don't really have to get into.
Okay, fair enough, keep going.
You know, the point of the point of colada is it's an interchange
format, right?
It is supposed to be an interchange format of which, at the point, at
which it was designed, there wasn't very many.
There was no successful interchange format, other than obj, which is
not sufficient.
And you know, since then, since then, we now have unofficially anyway
fbx, right in that.
Yes, from one more compatible with more stuff, mostly because Autodesk
own
Is everybody, right?
Once you own everybody, you can just say we're not straight this file
format.
Yeah, so that's largely.
The reason why if PX is successful.
So anyway, we use colada and, you know, it turns out at least using
the export of that we had at the time, the exporting the shop, you
know, a cinematic of the scope for Maya and the the at least just the
animation stuff, not even including all are sort of real-time tracks.
This is just the straight out animation stuff but just just a source
input data for the cuts in exporting from Maya just like save.
This file was something like 30 minutes.
Wow.
Just save the file so you have an exported it or that is the X.
Are you talking about just saving them for the modified.
Okay.
Saving the cloud of all right through my would you dare defy like this
is not including all our stuff or building or setting up a cinematic
so exporting the colada files for 30 minutes.
Yeah.
Okay so that was brutal.
So you can afford to to export the the stuff from Maya like 16 times a
day tops or something like this the before it's impossible.
It actually runs out the word.
Yeah.
To make start making your next change before the previous one is even
exported.
You know, that was brutal and that's something, you know, that we've,
that we have since tried to work around and, and, you know, we have
looked into, you know, obviously writing a better exporter for for
colada and you're looking at alternatives to plot ultimately, but I,
you know, I think for now we'll probably see it.
So, it's kind of on your radar, but it has not been solved.
Like, it's still like a minute.
We have, we have enough, we have enough in terms of
Workarounds of the problem.
Okay, so that it's not, yeah, it's not on my radar immediately like,
we can work around it and we can make it so that it's not like the
animators can make it.
So it's not 30-minute export for instance, by just not having one
giant one, okay, ready?
They just break it up into pieces and they can pull them in because
you said you have.
So, we have full access to all the in real Indigo simple.
Its work around mobile, it's not ideal, but it's work around the wall
and so, yeah.
But it's cinematics remains a problem.
Will always remain a problem.
There's always something.
So, I just wanted to share that exporting.
Cinematics is from the beginning, we all share.
So let's see.
I can't read my own notes.
I'm guessing I probably won't be any better.
So okay, so I'll just skip to the next one and you were talking a lot
about swf reader importing importing, right?
I don't have any as I don't have any Swift stories but I reminded me
of two things.
One is in terms of, you know you said you just sort of sat down and
read it, you know, read the fuckin neck, like great, you know, and
everybody clapped.
Yeah, every read the manual.
So yes, first of all, read the manual, I mean, looking at your, you
know whatever.
If you using, you know, you know, most people here okay.
He was either not using and x64 base x86 64 base or armed a CPU in
this room.
That's going to be no.
Be all right.
Okay, there's one nanak 64 non-armed.
Okay, so that would be so to cover all of you, except that one guy
right there, you can read, you know, between amd's manuals Intel's
manuals and
And the our manuals, you know, every single one of you should have
already read these manuals, right?
And I suspect you don't let the Intel architecture guide.
Yeah, you know, or and he's documentation, but yeah, the the Intel
books for sure.
Yeah.
Or the arm manuals, right?
But here's the thing without putting it on the spot.
I'm pretty confident that 100% of you have not.
In fact, read those annuals and that's kind of shitty
That's your spending the most of your time on these architectures
spending most of your, you know, you're going to probably spend a long
time, right?
You certainly going to spend more than a few months and so it's worth
it if you're spending more than a few months on piece of architecture,
it's worth it.
And this is, you know, and I come from Consul background and you know
what a we you know, every few years or every five years or whatever,
they just throw away the shit that we've done and gives something
completely different.
It's still worth reading the manual, even though, we know they're
going to throw it away, right?
So just, you know, definitely do that mean take the lesson and the
fact you all clapped is indicative that you think it's a good idea.
Um so just go home and do that.
I also, you know, when do we basically you're equating reading the SWS
factor out, an importer with writing, you know, if you're going to
write code in this architecture, read the actual architecture.
You know what it is?
Yeah.
I mean, you should know.
I agree.
Obviously.
There's there's information there that you could find useful.
That is canonical.
Yeah, you start there, right basic, you know, don't don't assume.
Yeah.
I'd also there's other, you know, it also reminded me of the iff
format document, which I think is a classic.
You mean, like the iff document from Electronic Arts?
Yeah, the original one.
Yeah.
Okay.
So do just for people who aren't as old, as we are, tell them what
that is.
Most people probably don't know what iff is.
I have this format really, really simple format.
It breaks breaks things into blocks and has a basically, a header
definition that says, size and type, right?
Was it was yet for Electronic Arts back.
You in?
I don't know when they introduced it, probably maybe two or something
like that.
Yeah, so it's like a for B type, I think for bite size and they're
usually asking so 16-bit size, right?
No, I don't remember.
Anyway, so it's very straightforward.
I think it's 32 bit now, but I.
Yeah, anyway, doesn't matter, it's not matter.
The point is that we can look it up.
That's the point that it's well documented and it was well documented
in 1982, well before.
You know well before was you know when it would be what we thought was
a good idea to do it and I think it's the gold standard which we still
have yet to follow very well of sharing documentation and sharing
ideas and being very clear about these formats.
So are you saying that you don't feel like modern-day sort of the
modern-day way of doing file formats?
And that sort of stuff does not adhere to this, I guess are
Perhaps talking about something like PSD.
For example where you look at the speck and it's like, what is this?
Well okay history is a good example.
Okay.
Right.
It's not well documented, yeah great but I'm also talking about your
own formats, okay?
So you're talking about like on a game so you're making you know, a
Ratchet and Clank game or something this and you have some file
formats.
If you're doing you actually think for example that your team should
document those internal only file formats, for example.
Yes.
Okay, so why?
Okay, why?
Why should you document your involve internal?
Why would you document an internal only file for?
I mean, it describes the data write it, it's a, you know, and Source,
the in Source, inputs to your system.
And it's the putting, you know, probably the most important thing that
you're working, okay?
Now the most important set of things that you're working with
everything else can be derived from that.
If I can look at, if I can understand the source input data, then I
can pretty much figure out what the rest of the system is, do we must
do, okay, right.
So I'm pretty sure that if I took, you know, any any
Cherry game out there and I said this is a description of what the
source data looks like, and I just released it to the hacker
Community, they can go to town on this game and because that's the
most important information.
Okay?
And that's obvious, that is the most important information.
Like, that's the thing that you would want to start with.
And yet we don't do a great job about documenting.
What is, you know, probably the most important information that we're
working with.
Do you think that's something that needs to be done during the
The active development so that there's a document which actually
evolves with changes to that data.
Or are you saying more like, when the game ships, part of the process
of shipping should be to take the final state of the data and document
that?
Well, I think you should be accurate.
So however, that works whatever the way.
So at the day, that the thing ships, whatever the way is to make sure
that the that the data description is the most accurate.
That is the thing.
You would like to see happen.
Yeah, I mean, I think that some teams for instance, doing it,
Great ships would be a really bad idea because that's the most
stressful thriving for the team.
And they're already overwhelmed already working extra hard and to say,
you know what, I know you are working on this sort of like 500 bugs on
20 different species and some guys and stuff, you know, I know you're
working on that.
But can you write some documentation on this file?
Format ground?
The slap goes the other direction, right?
Right, it's like Wham.
So that's probably not going to fly for some teams, right?
Okay, so it may be much better to do it, you know, incrementally.
We as you go and as you change it, just make it part of the change
process.
But you know, I do think we're talking about, you know, multiple
different things.
I think we're all talking about the internal formats and we are, but
we're also talking about the external things.
When we share, right?
Making that interoperability more more possible, it does seem like
there's been, I don't want to say a loss of that but there's
definitely, I guess less of a external incentive for that now, to some
degree to, because I guess it's just the first time I've ever thought
about this, because I don't think anyone's ever said that to me
before.
So,
Kind of like going in my brain.
So, in the past, we saw things, like, for example, Doom had a very
well-documented file format, so that people could mod it and it led to
there's a complete understanding pretty much of everything that goes
into that game or something like this.
But as I suggest we get more towards the Steam Workshop style of like,
there's just these tools that people use and nobody's ever really
touching the data besides the programmers.
I guess there's no longer much external pressure on a developer
because they're, you know, maybe it's all integrated inside.
Oh, it wouldn't we maybe wouldn't see things like doing so much
anymore.
I mean, is that a fair characterization?
Perhaps of that?
Well, I think one of the things that we should consider is, you know,
the sort of the historical aspect, right?
And, you know, how easy it is to Archive and say, Yes things, right?
I mean, we can, certainly imagine it being much easier to save much
easier to save an older game, which is you're saving.
Certainly an old again.
That's well, documented much easier to
4:20 any sort of keep it alive?
Yes.
And the less information you have about it.
The less you know it's a harder it is to save and we're talking about,
you know if we're once we get into sort of a mulch much the last 10
years, basically it's already hard problem, right?
Yeah.
How to Archive a PS3 game that's all runs on a network on PSN.
Right.
Is already a really, really hard problem.
And to make that even harder is, you know, maybe pretty much assume
presumes that it's not important to to Archive the
Te and, you know, we're going to lose a lot of that data.
Are you know, I don't know if that's important everybody.
And I don't really, I don't I have I'm undecided of whether or not
it's important to me and the scope of thing.
But if it were important that if we're importantly, is the case that
we're not really.
Yeah, not set up for it.
I suppose.
I mean there's something else I think that comes up and practice
right?
When we you know at some point somebody's going to say, hey, can you
port this forward right?
Yeah.
You know can you take this?
You know, assuming like okay, super weak point taken.
That's right.
We're talking about signore speaking.
You know, you've, you know, it's not that long ago, right?
But he's, you know, would you guys consider a classic at this point?
Yes, more or less, right?
Which means that in 10 years somebody's probably going to think about
it, we remember it want to play it again, right?
Maybe all this architecture that we currently presume is different,
very, very different, right?
And someone's going to want to pour it and then somebody's going to
ask
not you, but the mountains of people that work for you to board it,
right?
And you're going to go what the fuck.
I don't even remember.
You know, that was 10 years ago, I'm going to have to watch videos of
me myself, talking about at even remember what I was doing.
And, you know, having the ability to go back and, you know, have that
well, be well documented at least in terms of what the formats were
and what the data looks like.
So you could in theory, you're in, you know, you know, at least break.
Down and figure out what the cost is of pulling forward would be
totally worthwhile and I suspect very strongly that that will in fact
happen that, you know, in some at some future point that this will
happen to on some architecture that's hard for us to imagine today and
that you will have completely forgotten what all the data looks like,
right?
So, yes, I don't know what the question.
Oh, yeah.
So another completely random Point great.
I'm as I have no no insight into the into the list, this is still the
same point and still we're still talking about swf, right?
So the one thing one document, I think everybody should read is the
Tim berners-lee.
World Wide, Web hitched document.
This is really, this is, you know, I want to make a world wide web.
This is the pitch.
This is, this is what I'm going to make.
It is very short.
It's like a few.
Just long everyone should read this.
Because what you will learn is pretty much
The he set out to accomplish all the problems that he set out to
accomplish.
Now imagine this world why you know this is before the web so this is
early 90s.
I was and everything that he sent out to call it all these problems
that we want to solve, he's literally solved, none of them all.
I like if you imagine how much the world has changed right?
How much the web has changed, everything everything that we do and I
how we interact with each other and
And on business and, you know, everything and yet fundamentally.
We saw none of these problems.
I'm very interested to see what they are now.
And, you know, which is really, you know, it's really about, you know,
you know, it starts with.
Like, I can't find these documents that are important to me, you know,
and this is so complicated, I can find the document.
Okay, who has a problem finding information that, you know, is
relevant to their work right today, right?
That's still true.
It's still true that it's
To find that document.
It's still true that.
You know, even if you have what he imagined was something you know,
very clearly.
Something like a Wiki, right?
Okay.
How many people have Wiki's that survived the test of time.
Like after five years you can find everything.
It's totally there.
It's totally documented.
Well, okay, to be fair though to them as soon as they finish figuring
out how to turn these important documents into Justin Bieber songs
with the rebel were perfectly, right?
Because you can always find them.
Those.
So I'm not down on Justin Bieber.
I fair enough buying, I'm a huge pop fan.
But yes, continue, it's a data transformation problem.
We just have to take the things we can find and turn the things.
We can't find into that.
I think this is, I think there is some legitimacy to that argument,
you know, I think,
You know, and it's in terms of what you can associate, you know,
formation with.
I think there's some legitimacy but in terms of taking the lesson of,
you know, you have and I don't know what to take away from this.
You've taken, you know, you taking a problem of insurmountable scope.
You know, I want to be able to get this, I wanna be able to track down
this information.
I want to be able to communicate with people, and I want to be able to
very specific things.
Like I can't find the document that I want.
I want such a, you know, Association that I want something.
That's all of this for me.
Me and which is sort of always been a problem in this room all of
human history.
Yes.
And say I have a solution for it and it changes the world and yet and
yet the and still can't find the document that you want.
I find that fascinating and I don't know what the lesson is but it's
super fascinating.
So yeah.
Like I guess so you're basically saying take a look at this pitch
document, see the things he said he wanted to solve.
Yeah he hasn't managed to solve any of them.
I guess, even though he created a whole bunch of solutions
Problems or whole new problems even because they support we've done
right?
We create more problem, created a lot more problems.
Super fascinating, interesting problems, huge hugely interests and
you're sitting over there.
Listening to Tom, you talked about importing, an swf file.
Yeah.
And that was what this is that was well yeah, there's a connection,
right?
There's swf format during document and something to do with that
document anyway, there you go.
Alright, so I have some questions for you.
I want to ask.
Is there anything?
Us in the on the list, for sure, but go ahead.
All right, because I wanted to ask the things that I can only ask you,
or at least out of the people that are at handmade Khan.
So going back to, you know, putting documents aside for one second
because as we already said, you can't find them anyway.
So you know there, it's largely academic where you can't read them or
you can't read them, you can't read them or we can't find them either
or one of the things that I wanted to ask you or to try to get some
perspective on because like, I opened this with
A question that I had for you that I didn't know the answer to that.
People often ask me, which was the, you know, sort of scaling you
know, scaling up does that change versus whatever that sort of stuff.
But then another question that I get asked also.
So let's go back to that question.
So scaling up very important.
Let's put your other one aside from there is a minute, so scaling up.
So, you know, I'd sometimes I talk to it like Indie groups, whose in
the considers themselves, Indian the room.
Fair number.
Okay, that's a pretty good number.
Sometimes, I talk to interview some down talking to you guys any
group.
And I'll talk to me about the engine that they're making or, you know,
that they want to make.
And I'll be asking questions and, and often what I'll see is that they
are doing it very similar to say, what we would do or they're looking
at unity and they're doing something similar to Unity or unreal or
whatever.
The sort of copy means make like looking at, you know,
Making sort of an editor thing that you put entities down.
Like, yeah, I already ordered the runtime or the the tools.
Okay, whatever.
And I have no problem with people making their own tools and, you
know, fundamentally I'm engine programmer and, you know, that's kind
of what I like to do.
So I get I get it and, you know, I don't have a problem with people
doing that and that's what you like to do.
But you know what, I think that people Miss is the context in which
they're working, you know, you're working with a Yorkie on a game,
right?
Right.
You know, you're in space, or working by yourself or with a group of
people or students, you're working with group of students or whatever
and you're missing the context in which you're working.
You're looking at what other people have done and you're sort of just
copying that model, okay?
Right.
And so you're looking at unreal, you're looking at unity and you're
saying okay, they have actors in enemies and things that I'm sort of,
copying them all because that's how you do it.
And I think that in the same way that, you know, taking a physical
model, mental model, and saying this is the, this must be right now.
Everything else is wrong.
This is also poor approached.
Okay.
You know because Insomniac did it because epic did it or because
whoever did it that must be the right approach.
I'm just going to sort of copy.
That is also wrong, okay?
Because it has nothing to do with your problem, okay?
It has to do with our problem.
Those are very, very different and to talk about, you know, to go back
to your point, which is sort of what's the difference of scale?
Yes.
Right the difference is huge, its its massive.
So when you talk about one game or at least one game at a time and
you're talkin,
Entertainment Group of small people who are small group.
We will communicate really on a deep level, right?
You have seven people or 10, people are five people or whatever.
Yes, they can just communicate together on a deep level that totally
changes the game.
I was talking to one team recently and you know, it was just sort of
breaking down.
They started out with the actors important thing.
Similar.
I'm just like, okay, why do you even have this?
Like conceptually like, these are the components I have.
I'm like, forget forget all this, okay.
What you know, what's your game?
What do you at?
What are the problems are actually trying to solve.
And they would say something like,
Like okay.
Well we have ladders and our game, all right?
Okay cool.
We can start with ladders like okay why do you have ladders and what
are they doing?
But let's start with ladders was saying.
The difference between what you're talking about.
Building you're talking are building sort of the general purpose
editor where you know I can you know, design is going to spend time
placing a ladder and setting and assigning it a ladder component and
doing all like.
Now imagine different scenario by comparison.
I know the context in which I'm making the game, you guys are like
seven people.
I'm going to make an editor that that understands that I like that.
I use ladder.
There's a lot.
Button right there is a literal ladder button and it shows me on the
screen.
All the, only the places that a ladder could have possibly appear,
right?
Right.
And understand the constraints, I've defined the constraints under,
which a lot of compared.
So, it's sort of ghosting in all the places that it could possibly
appear and I just click on one.
That's the one ladder goes there.
That's like three seconds to put a ladder.
I don't have to waste time, like dragging some object in and it's an
arbitrary model is attached to some arbitrary about it because I'm not
making an arbitrary game.
I'm making this game.
Yes, and I'm making tools for this game, and the fact that you have
that much more context means you can solve the problem that much
better ignoring the context, or alternatively, if you want to look at
a different way, is trying to make it too generic.
Yeah, is the call, you're causing problems, you're making it slower.
It's like you're intentionally making the problem Harder by ignoring
the context by the trying to make it to generic.
It's basically the analog of what you were talking about with code
before.
It's just like, don't introduce extra things in here.
If they were not actually relevant to solving the
And to say it has to be generic or has to follow this.
Other model is introducing this whole mental abstraction this whole
mental model into the problem that just didn't exist and also doesn't
make it an order of magnitude harder.
It also doesn't seem clear why you would really want to go that route
because if you just want to end up with unity or unreal again, you
could have just used them.
Well, first, you should be trying to do something that you want to do
this.
For sure.
That's your advantage, I think.
And that's that.
Just your advantage is an indie in the space, right?
Is that you have that deep understanding of your context, you can take
it.
Intimate, you can write things that are just the cannot be, they
cannot be used to make anything else.
Yes.
But they just kick ass at this one thing and that's awesome.
And even our scale, right?
We can do that better than say a team that has to support.
You know, you know, millions of people yeah or you know hundreds of
thousands of people like we can do it better than that, but we still
can't do it to the extent that a small one.
Or this one.
We do have multiple games and fly that all have slight differences.
And we do have to be more, you know, support a wider range of stuff so
we can't even be as good.
As those smaller teams, so that's their advantage anyway.
That that know, that was accent.
I love the list scaling.
So, anyway, back to your mom.
Yes.
So my question is, sort of a couple different questions that, but it's
sort of all the same basic idea.
Which is that, you know, when I got into the game industry, it was so
long ago that it didn't look anything like it looks now, for example.
So, a lot of times, you know,
Really cuz with the series it's you know, a lot of people who aren't
in the game industry but might want to get in the game show.
You are starting to, you know, watch it or try to practice or do the
stuff.
And I get asked the question like, what should I, you know, what
should I do?
If I actually want to pursue a career here like what does that look
like?
And I get all kinds of questions that I simply can't answer.
Should I go to college?
What should I be practicing?
What does my resume associative?
Like how do I apply all these sorts of things?
So I was wondering as someone who actually presumably has a little
more insight into.
A the process by which people come into the industry now and to as
someone who presumably has spots they need to fill on occasion and I
would imagine has a bunch of things.
They wish were true about the people who were coming through the door,
like, could you give me a little perspective on that?
So when I get asked that question, I can say well, I don't know, but
Mike said this right.
If it's too tough of a question that we do not have an opinion, I can
certainly share.
Have an opinion about everything.
But to start with, I mean I agree with your point that it's really
hard for me to relate to people who are getting into the games
industry.
Now as a concept, like I can't I simply can't I don't have that that
exact experience that you're dealing with right now.
I have nothing to relate to that.
You know, there's this mountain of schools you can choose from like
right?
I don't even know what that's like.
Yeah, dr.
Self out.
You know you have the internet and yes, documentation and examples and
so yeah, it's completely different.
It's playing field that I don't, you know that I don't know.
The best person to ask somebody who just did it like four years ago, I
guess so.
You know, that they're the best people to ask.
But in terms of hiring, I can certainly give you an insight into what
I look for, you know, I over time.
I've looked for things that correlates strongly with good hires, you
know, and whether that's, you know what school you're going to or your
test scores, we do have a test.
Give it programming, we do give apartment test-retest, you know, your
your response to them a test or your work history or whatever.
You know, I'm trying to look for things that correlates strongly with
with good.
What I would consider good hires and there's only there's literally
only one thing that I found that correlates and everything else
doesn't and really really really hard.
Because it just doesn't like I said whether or not whether or not you
pass our tests.
Well actually doesn't really correlate.
Strongly with how good of a programmer you're going to be for us.
Why do you still get it partially?
Because a, you know it there there are bits in there.
That do tell me something.
Okay.
So I do find it useful, or insightful.
Part of it is just for your like what do I do?
If I don't have it, I don't have an alternative answer here.
Fair enough.
Okay.
You know, I am human during the day, so yeah, I don't have, you know,
Motivator.
Yeah.
So yeah.
I mean, the one thing that I have found that correlates is curiosity,
curiosity.
That's literally the only thing and curiosity to a point where it's
insatiable where I cannot words undeniable like, you know, I'm if I'm
talking to somebody and they aren't they aren't, is they are very
curious.
Ultimately, it's obvious that they are very curious.
Interesting, you know, I'm going to ask questions and they're going to
say, I do not only do I not know, but I don't care.
Okay.
All right.
It's not important.
From you to know that it should do my job.
So I haven't thought about it right.
I see that's and just a level of non curiosity that I that just
doesn't do well for working with with the group that I work it right
with my team.
Now, on the flip side, somebody who's insatiably curious, right,
where, it's just like everything, they may not have enough.
You certainly don't have enough time to satisfy at all but you want to
know you're interested in knowing, right?
You dig in and that sort of thing.
It correlates strongly with being successful on our team.
How is that help people?
Who are, you know, trying find a job?
I don't know.
Well, it kind of does, he's curious me?
Curious certainly first unless but, but maybe demonstrate, you know,
demonstrable curiosity right.
Show me that you are soaked, you're curious about something deeply
from, you know, top to bottom.
You know, even it's just like one really great blog post where you
just dug into something deeply and you've just kept digging until you
hit sand, right?
And you
just like, this is everything that I could possibly learn about this
in a month.
Yeah, right.
All the little tangents all the little interesting bits, I just pulled
every thread until I ran out of time right over a month or whatever
that's interesting and that would be that would be striking to me and
that's something that I would want to see if it's just like oh here
are three projects that I did and you know very it's not in that not
even a little bit interesting to me really especially if the school
projects because it's like everybody today they had to do them right?
So it's whatever it's Anna.
Big deal.
You know, I think that I don't care about, you know, I don't really
care about what school you went to.
I don't really care about your grades.
I don't, we're certainly don't care about what, what projects you did.
I don't care about what classes you took.
I don't care anything at all to do with your school.
I don't actually even care if you passed or finished or interesting.
So, yeah.
I mean, I care about sort of what you've demonstrated most of what
you've demonstrated on your own will?
Yes, that's what, what,
Interested in that's a fantastic answer.
So thank you very much.
It's like all right so I guess I guess my secondary question maybe is
not as well in fact that was kind of perfect but I guess I'll just ask
it anyway which was so you know if there was something that I was
going to tell people, you should practice or know how to do is there
anything that you find lacking in terms of fundamentals, right?
Like it's like, hey, I wish that all the applicants we got like
Even the ones who were curious and like, you know, they have the right
mentality for being on the engine team at Insomniac that like, that's
all set.
But I just wish they had done more of X or known more about, why would
have been really helpful to us, right?
So separate from maybe the hiring question, just more like, what do
you want them to be prepped to do when they get there?
Lots of Java programming, right?
I'm guessing.
So again, the answer is not very, not a very technically, specific
answer, the answer is practice, okay?
Most people do not know how to practice, okay, and most people don't
take it very seriously and that I think is a massive problem for our
full as massive problem for them.
Really massive problem for you and your career.
If you don't know how to practice and you know not taking seriously as
a big
You assume that, you know, I'm learning, you know, I'm going what I
need to know based on what I'm doing in my my job.
Well you know, that's not enough, okay, it's your career right, you
need to take you know, you need to take that seriously as a your own
problem, you know.
And how do you learn and how do you practice and how do you advance
your skills for your own career?
This is your responsibility.
Yes, you have a job and you're going to do that work.
That's great.
But separately, you have to deal with your career and where you're
going and
And what you need to know and you have to know how to do that.
Well, and most people do not know how to practice.
Well, you know, I talked to somebody and I'll say, you know, what, you
practice every day and they'll say, well, I don't really have time
everyday, American really.
So aside from putting aside from your family.
Yeah, this is the most important.
Like, this is the thing.
You're gonna spend your entire life doing so you don't have time for
the thing.
Like, Jude forget to brush your teeth like, like you
manage to do other things every day.
Like you eat every day, you brush your teeth every day because it's
important to you.
You probably change your clothes every day.
He might show,
Are there things you do every day?
Because it's important because it's part of who you are and yet you
don't practice every day.
Write the thing that, you know, you don't do it for your career.
And so, this is.
So second thing I'll get is, you know, well I have a little bit of
time and I read as a programmer, I really need to be able to sit down
for hours in order to get into the mood to I'm like okay you're not a
child, you know, this is you know as a professional and as an adult
person I think you should be able to
To organize your time.
So that, you know, you can get something out of 30 minutes, if that's
all you have, you know, you can absolutely do that.
You can absolutely have a plan for how I'm going to use this 30
minutes and what I'm going to do and that's better than doing nothing.
Yes, and you know, this is, you know, it's just some sort of a series
of excuses of why I don't practice right and I don't know how to
practice and so not taking that seriously, I think is a huge problem
for people not not necessarily an in terms of their contribution to
18.
But for their own sake like as a programmer as an individual person
with the career that you have to curate for yourself, like this is the
investment that you need to put in.
Or you're just not going to be as good as you could possibly be.
And you know, that's a presumably what you want, right?
You want to be as good as you can because this is your chosen career.
So you need to spend that time you forgot to do it.
Well, so what's a good example of how someone might practice for 30
minutes?
If they like, take this advice to heart and go, you know what?
That is something.
Should be doing, what's a good starter Project?
A lot of times, I tell people who are starting out in games I'll be
like asteroids is the one to make first, when you're like learning,
you know, how to make games because it's the simplest possible thing
and blah blah blah, right?
So let's talk about practice, like you said it, what's the simplest
way to get started?
Practicing, what would you say would be somebody who have 30 minutes a
day.
You are going to start devoting to getting better at programming
games?
Well, I mean you could pick something like say, ah let's see we're
going to pick asteroids right?
Fine my biggest advice.
Ice would be for while, for at least into, if you're just starting to
learn how to practice, well is to throw away, throw away, everything
you do after every practice, do not have any kind of continuity.
Interesting.
So maybe you work on the same problem, but you are not allowed to keep
anything that you did before.
So, that you simply have to get better at it.
You have to be a fast.
You have to try a different way next time and see if it works better
and that sort of because if you if you keep it it doesn't become
practice, right?
It becomes a project.
I say and it becomes about in becomes a hobby.
Yes.
Absolutely.
And it's not about a hobby, it's about real practice.
So just throw it away and didn't get better at it, right?
So if it's about asteroids and then ultimately maybe your practices,
how can you make it in 30 minutes what is what are you doing first?
A 30 minute, you know, the first day you don't even close the second
day, you don't even close.
Yeah, 300th day, maybe your buddy close to be able to do it in 30
minutes so you've done it so many times.
That's practiced.
Okay.
That's valuable right.
Maybe you are not, maybe you're not practicing the right thing.
You've gotten really good at building, asteroids at 30 minutes, but
that's probably something valuable to be taken from that.
But, I mean, really, I think it's, you know, I would say pick and pick
pick pretty much anything right.
Pick a project open source project, your own project whatever and just
start picking it apart, right?
You have a plan.
What about how I'm going to spend?
Spend the first two minutes saying?
What am I to do for 30 minutes?
Have a plant, got it.
And if that's I'm going to analyze this so I can gather more
information
Or I'm going to make this bit faster or whatever.
Fine do that.
You know, you have a plan, spend your 30 minutes doing that and then
stop and then throw it all the way and then tomorrow I have a new plan
and that's you know it's a different it's a completely different kind
of thing than a hobby or project or a portfolio piece or your work.
Or it's just about the value of the practice is the practice of
practice.
So
Well, I think we're just about out of time.
So did you have any stuff you wanted to talk about?
Just like you and I don't want to go back - do I miss anything on the
list but also just as you wanted to say a few closing remarks just
about, you know, I guess I asked Tommy sort of if he had any stuff he
wanted to mention that he's working on or stuff that he wanted to talk
about just as sort of a closing remark.
So if you've got any, I don't know what you would.
Yeah.
What your days, look like these days, but what am I working on?
So there was a problem.
That I decided to dig into a little bit.
We have something called a spatial DB which is not really database
just spatial DB.
Yeah.
Just as we're very our it's a sort of our mechanism to query things
spatially in our engine, we call it special TV and I was interested in
it and sort of seeing where the edges were and seeing if there was
anything that we could do in terms of optimization and so my Approach
was,
I wanted to let you know, I wanted to look into this more deeply so
I'm just sort of sharing what my approach this was and so I thought
okay, well maybe, you know, as the game is playing, I can sort of just
serialize it at certain points and the next sort of sampling it right
serializing.
Then analyze it offline and say where was this at this point?
And, you know, so I can look deeply more deeply into the data.
So periodically, you would just sort of say at this, you know, every n
seconds or something.
I'm going to just same out.
What is the DB look like yeah?
Here ya later.
I'll go gather them back up in a separate thing and start to see that
was, that was my original plan right now, I'm looking at it.
And I'm like, okay, well, one, the D, you know, the it's not really DB
in any kind of it's in my, you know, it's just, it's interface.
And that format is fairly optimized in Fairly complicated and
changing, and I'm like, you know what, I'm not gonna do that.
I'm feeling a little lazy.
So instead I said, well, you know what, I'm actually going to do is
there's a very limited number of entry points into this, okay?
And so, this
This data are a very limited number of ways that you can even change
the data.
So those sort of like, add something to the database, our edit
something are, delete it really, that's pretty much the whole end
initially judgment.
So that's pretty much it.
I'm like fine.
I'm just going to stream out like a command buffer.
I'm going to stream out all the entry points, so case database.
So like recreated offline.
Yes, right now and whenever programmer and says, I'm going to do
something else because I'm feeling lazy.
Usually, it involves way more work.
Yes, the original thing which is the
True absolutely in this case.
So, you know, I streamed at all the entry point stuff, you know, and I
sort of now I have a system that, you know, I see the command but from
Reading system or of just read it all back and reconstruct the
databases at any point.
So I can have a complete timeline playing the game.
Complete timeline I can scrub or whatever of everything that happened
to the database at any point.
While I was playing that's awesome.
Right?
As I can do a lot of queries in here and see how it's going and just
sort of discovering sort of doing analysis and spent you're spinning
out a bunch of data and
Analyzing it, tons of information, that was super valuable.
And then I said, you know what, there's a bunch of queries that are
coming in, you know, people asking in the game, you know, I want to
get stuff out of.
That's the whole point of the did queer is especially if it's do
queries against it.
So I'm like I want to visualize the queries like visually like honesty
you know what they look like.
So I'm done.
I'm in our queries, all come in this sort of convex Hull / defined by
planes.
Okay so comes in as a series of plane equation yes that bound some 3.
Deep space like a polytope, right?
So I'm like, okay, that's fine.
You know, I want to visualize that someone to visualize it as the
whole I'm Grand.
Yeah, that's Polly's.
So we have a clipping function that will take, you know, to set of
plans include against a predefined whole.
So right triangle, you know, defined whole and so I'm like, okay,
that's cool.
I'll just take a big, basically a big Cube and Slice It Up by right.
Just make sure the cube is bigger than whatever the bounds on this.
Planes are and then I'll just let it carve everything.
That's not the elephant.
We remove that marble and the elephants left.
Right?
Yeah.
So it's fairly straightforward, which we use for various things and
I'm just going to use this to sort of visualize the space, okay?
Right.
And it doesn't work in some cases, okay?
So I'm looking at it, I'm like okay well you know there's this cases
where it's just, you know, I'm just basically getting garbage out.
Yes, right.
And you know, I am just where I want to visualize any comment, you do
it.
Turns out that the problem is in that clipping routine.
Yeah, which we use in various places but it only no problem showed up
it because, you know, I'm this huge set of data that I've got that all
these different parties.
You know, hundreds of thousands of queries over time and every
variation on it right now, I'm pretty much just have this massive test
database.
Now for a polygon Clipper, right?
I just just gigantic test and I can split it against like, you know,
because it's just like this, like, you know,
no, because I just
I have this sort of history of the date, I can just go back and forth
and see exactly what goes wrong and it's not, there's not actually a
slider, right.
That's mentally because like, but but I do know.
So I went down this Rabbit Hole of like fixed the Clipper.
Yeah, we've got to mix the Clipper from.
I'm going to take a look at the spatial database, right?
But I mean the thing, the thing about it is is just looking at the
data right there lesson for me here is you know I started out with
something else, right?
But it's just about
Realizing the data looking at it and analyze it.
And while I did find out a lot of interesting things about the spatial
database.
I did also discover things about a completely unrelated system that I
didn't expect.
Like, I found ya Liza's in just trying to visualize the data that also
needed some attention.
So just the sort of effort of visualizing and just to sort of effort
of digging into the data.
Not only end it's helpful to fix, like offline.
Now, I have this gigantic.
Yes, you can test again, perfect.
Test Suite.
Absolutely insured.
My turnaround time is like, you know, less than a second to just test
it.
This massive database of tests that are all real world scenarios,
right?
That I just recorded I can get as many as I want.
Certainly not re bloating the game, the iteration that kind of
iteration time is just this like and I can do it on my laptop or I can
do that.
Yeah, thanks.
Right.
I like Linux tools.
I can do it there.
So super easy to iterate on and I have a much better result, just
because I'm looking at Zeta, and that's for me, like, this is the
approach that I like to take to probably approach that.
I find to be useful.
And it's always surprising, you know, it's it's, there's always
something that I hit that I didn't expect to hit just because I
looked.
Yes.
I feel like capture like capture and visualize is kind of like the way
most hard problems end up getting solved.
And sometimes problems, you don't even know that you had because until
you actually see the visualization you don't actually realize you
know, I think finding different ways of looking at the problem.
Yeah.
Like in terms of your, you know, your eyes, your ears or whatever,
looking at it is an important part of what we do.
Like, that's
We should be spending most of our time and not in the code.
Like, programmers.
Think that their job is to write typing, like, writing code.
And that's really not it like, that should be less than 1% of your
effort, right?
Is that typing part?
Which is why I don't want to hear that.
It took to this, I don't want to do this because it takes too long to
type like really fucking nobody ever didn't ship again because it took
too long to type.
It will.
If you get enough monkey, is that enough typewriters, right?
Well, I think that's all the time we have.
Thank you so much for the conversation.
It's been awesome and that was
And that was an excellent list as well.