Following up the compression talk which is a sort of a theoretical and
thinking talk with a much more practical talk or I should say session,
I guess.
And essentially like one of the things that's really kind of hard to
get across on handmade hero in any way because of the nature of the of
the project and the fact that it's only me programming, it is that
there's all sorts of things that you will start to run into when
you're talking about doing things at a scale where you may have, you
know,
Tens, hundreds, you know, 500 people all working on a project and
these are sorts of things that don't necessarily imply that anything
that you might be doing in the code, like, you would be doing it for
one person product or necessarily wrong, but it does mean that there
may be whole new systems or whole new things problems.
You need to solve that just simply don't exist when your scale is much
smaller.
And so what I, what I wanted to do because I knew that that bungee
Had shipped Destiny and had a bunch of work.
They had to do with asset systems and stuff in order to support
something at that scale and it was kind of a new skill for them.
So they'd gone through all of the growing pains, you know in that
project was I invited Chris butcher to talk to us about what that
process was like what they learned and just kind of like allow me to
sort of be the outsider who comes in and like asks for that, that
whole sort of like series of steps, they went through their learning
process and what they sort of ended up with
Are still working on potentially even to keep that sort of scale
functioning.
So please give a warm, welcome to Chris butcher stand before.
You said before we start, you wanted to take a survey.
So, yeah, yes.
Well, actually, it's funny, like I was wondering about the
juxtaposition of those who talks, because we're going from
compression, which is the super pure abstract problem, right?
Where you can look at something,
And say, here is a problem, here is a way to solve it.
Like let's try that.
Okay, that was the right way.
Let's go right.
We're going to talk about now is the exact opposite of that is just
like a nasty gritty messy problem, right?
If the kind that you run into, when you're dealing with game
production on a large scale and we certainly like have a larger scale
than we probably realized at the time and probably a larger scale than
most people.
So yeah I want to do a show of hands I'm actually curious.
So
Hands up, if you are not a programmer, like maybe you're a student or
a teacher and you're a programmer, you're not professionally, employed
the program right now.
So students, teachers game designers you thought your go to the Opera
may be okay.
So hands up if you are currently professionally employed as a
programmer.
Wow.
Okay, and now keep your hand up if you work on a team of more than
five people
Okay, more than 10 people.
more than
20 people.
More than 50 people.
More than 100 people, more than 200 people more than 300 people.
Where does it end more than 400 people?
Okay, thank you.
Bungee people, you can put your hands down.
So you have a destiny development team right now.
If you count everybody at the company it's like 680 people, those
people are all working on Destiny in one form or another their company
support people RIT or test or something like that.
But
Or development staff, we have probably around 500 people.
So a really big problem and a much larger problem that I think we
really understood at the time for a lot of reasons that are
interesting.
And so, sort of giving people the perspective on where the story
starts, so when you said realize that the time, so take us back a
little bit to sort of, you know, where you know, Destiny was getting
started as a concept or whatever.
Where are we at?
And what does the sort of landscape look like if we
We rewind all the way back to before we even started really thinking
about the asset system and maybe we're using like, you know, sort of
older architecture of an asset system from previous bunch of games or
something like that.
Yeah.
So just just sticking to the technology, right?
And kind of melt talking about, like, the game design and game
concept.
Well, that's a whole other thing just itself.
Yeah.
So we had been working on Halo for about 10 years at that time, right?
From like, 1997 through 2007.
And I wasn't wrapped the first couple years of Halo development, I
joined in around about 2000.
And so the Halo engine had been in use for 10 years and the principles
of the Halo engine were, there was a structure that we call the tag
for reasons that I lost to history.
The tag file is a piece of content that is has a known structure to
it.
Like it's a, you know it's a it's an object or it's a model let's say
and it saved on disk and then it gets loaded directly by the game in
that same structure.
ER and so just to be clear on that.
When you say two parts of that I guess tag is some kind of an ID.
What does this ID look like textual integer?
Yeah in this case, it's a string for the path, right?
And then a type which is, you know, object or model or what have you
and that type is also a string or some kind of integer code.
It's a string.
Okay.
So we essentially have two strings that are saying this is the assets
sort of name and another string which is the assets type and then you
say
Say that type implies a known structure.
It sounded like you were not talking about abstract, so you mean,
literally, this is the binary format and when it comes into the game
it will be exactly in this binary form.
Yes, specifically, there's a C++ header file, right.
And then here as a see structure and then in the Halo engine, there
was a parallel set of declarations which were saying, you know, like
four bytes for integer and then a string goes here and then like
It's four packs Flags or what have you and so you had to like declare
your see structure, you also have to declare like the fields which
told the game house can be stored on disk and then will be B swapped
for a big-endian little-endian platforms.
So pretty simple pretty standard like not super modern reflection
format just like a very hand created and then that was how the game
loaded in the development build is you would go and load one tag which
was the thing that told you everything you had to load and then you
would go and recursively call that right?
And so they're basically these just to flesh that out.
Every time you load one of these, it could itself include other
references which were the first part of that tag the name, presumably
or the name and the type both.
So, the reference itself also gives you nothing.
That's like, hey, it's the type as well.
So, you know, what, kind of type you're looking at you up there.
Okay?
So then you crawl out words from there and you could be doing this
many, many times.
Yeah.
Right then.
So like a typical level in Halo would probably be on the order of
Maybe 5,000 to 10,000 tags.
Okay.
And by the end.
And so there are some characteristics about that.
They're interesting to talk about the first.
One is the the structure of the data on disk is the same as the
structure of the data in memory.
Yes.
And the implication then is that if you have an editor, which is
working directly with these tags, these structure of the data, the
editor is looking at is the same as the runtime structure of the data
in memory.
I see, so, so basically there is not
The concept of a separate editor, at this point, a separate editor
data structure at this point, which gets kind of baked down into that,
think they are all operating under the same set of of data.
Well, we're talking here about the generic pipeline, right?
And then of course, for things like a texture.
Let's say right.
You know, there's a Photoshop file for the texture and there's a
texture importer which is like a specific command you run on a texture
that turns it into a tag and so the tag is not really human readable.
It's just like here's some binary array of data and then there's a
texture and portal that takes the texture and turns into the tag.
So that's like, that's pretty straightforward.
Like, that's something you can do and you can build a whole Pipeline
on top of that.
And there's lots of, there's lots of lots of interesting things that
you can talk about there about, you know, building graphical editors
on top of structured data formats.
And the, the most important thing to talk about here probably is that
in the development version of the game, you doing this crawled, go and
find all those pieces of data and you load the main memory and then
there's a fix-up function you call that in place converts things like
For example, if the designer said this should be negative for a is in
this group thin, like you change, the clamp that 20 will make it 1 or
what-have-you, right?
So if it's a function of the run in place from the data, the time is
loaded and then that's pretty slow to do that, right?
Like that might, if you are running that on Xbox, maybe that takes
anywhere from 2 to 20 minutes to load a level because you're loading,
these files individually from the hard drive and you're doing fix up
on them in place.
And after you the fix-up, you and discover the new things used to load
and go in
Seriously.
So so basically you're just talking about a lot of seeking around on
the I guess the development hard drive to pull these things in and
that ends up being a fairly dominant part of the performance.
Because means, because 10,000 tags is not a high number of tags for a
graph walk to process.
So, presumably, there's a particular part of that process, that's
slow.
Yeah, it's cereal, right?
You're seeking the best in your loading.
It we're talking about the original Xbox here.
Also 2004, right?
We're like this all kinds of known problems.
With like it's directory enumeration of slow when you have lots of
files in a directory, okay?
So anyway, so through, say, non-problem you mean artificial problem?
I guess I got to think things that you don't think about today.
Got it.
Yeah, 15 years later and for context there, so that's like the
development build, where you can make changes to a tag or change to an
individual field and a tag and then seek that across and it can be
loaded really quickly, right?
So, you're very, very rapid iteration there because everything is
organized in these files.
There's no dependencies between
Owls other than at the fix-up time in some cases, you can let go and
like, dereference something and go and pull the field out of it and
put it in there.
But the dependencies are very, very constrained by the model.
And so, as a result, the model lends itself to super fast iteration of
super slow load times and then there's another variant adjust that we
use.
Sorry to keep jumping in by just want to make sure I get all the stuff
out there.
So when you say lends itself to fast iteration, so obviously if these
tags are stored as separate files or you know, fairly
Separate files in some way.
Then you know yes I can overwrite that file with a new file or
overwrite.
The memory version by saying, hey, there's here's a new pointer to 1
but the dependency fix up process.
Now every time you change that, anyone who was pointing it to the
previous one, has to point to the new one is that just kind of
systemically built into the system so it has a generic way of just hey
walk the metadata get rid of everything you had that was like down
from this or something and bring it back around.
Or can you can you
Say a little bit about that works, maybe never implanted when these
before fright, that systemic in our engine we call it a handle system
basically.
So in our engine we don't allow people to have pointers to pretty much
anything.
We don't use like a smart pointer of reference counting system if you
are.
You know, a logical unit of data and you have a reference to something
else anywhere else in the engine memory space that's always done
through a handle.
So it's a double dereference soda reference to a table and the table
contains the pointer and then you go and get that.
And so
you can swap out any piece of data at the structural level by
switching, the pointer in the handle table and know that everybody's
pointing to it is going to get.
I see.
So that's kind of a core principle of the Halo Mission or something is
carried forward.
So, if you talk about again, I talked about the Halo development
build, you can change things quickly so I can artists the scribbling
on a texture.
There's an automatic process that is looking to see when the Photoshop
file is saved.
And then like runs the texture, importer generates the one filed one
Falco's across the development machine gets reloaded, so that was
nice.
I just really like that and that works on the target Xbox, right?
So they can see it on the actual exactly.
Has it will be when the person plays it.
Yes.
But there's a significant problem with this version of the build and
what that is is this is pretty slow startup because you're to go and
seek to all these files.
And so if your game crashes or if you need to reload the level, for
some reason, you're waiting for to 20 minutes for the thing to start,
right?
And so this is all.
Well, I'm just grabbing here is for the original Halo game back in
2001.
So then there's a process.
Is that basically runs the tag, loading recursive procedure, but does
it through a command line application on the PC goes and loads?
All of those things.
So it has the full picture in memory and then it will serialize those
things out into a big contiguous array of data, so that you can just
load the contiguous array happens to be that we had loaded as a single
if read, for example.
So, for a particular level, you have like 15 megabytes of data, you do
an F32 15 megabytes and then it's all in memory.
You sit the pointers in the handle table, you're done.
I see.
So the
The table sort of assume is prime, so we do an F read, we have all the
data now, but now we sort of got this table, we need to fill out.
So presumably, there's large like a header to this that says here are
all the like offsets into the file that you're going to use to like
read, you know, to initialize the handle table to point into this
block.
So you take wherever I loaded in memory, add the, you know, that Base
address to all the addresses in this header and that's my handle table
off.
I go.
Exactly.
Okay.
And that's what I just described there.
Air is not taking any account of like, asynchronous, loading or later,
you know, caches, for various things, you don't want to be Memory
resident all the time, a lot of detail there, that's not super
important and Halo was was doing these things.
Yeah.
So like when you went from one section, the level to another, like
basically there's one pack, which is always loaded for the level.
And there's one that switches out when you move from one area to
another race in which we call to be SP because a binary space
partition.
Okay, so that's like different different.
Like sub Maps, essentially.
We use that structure from Halo one all the way through to Halo Reach.
So everything I described it was kind of the same.
So you have these two different asset formats, right?
You've got the individual tag format, which is super fast iterate on
that super slow to load and game and also doesn't have the final
performance at runtime because a lot of the asynchronous caching and a
lot of the like fitting into memory in the final way doesn't work
here.
Because remember, you're loading.
All of these individual files individual exploded memory allocations.
Yes.
This memory overhead for that.
And so, with the
Xbox development kit.
I mean, when your level gets big enough, you just simply can't load it
anymore, right, right?
Like you can look at me optimize form but you can't load at the
development Forum.
Yes, unless you do stuff like, turn up all the textures and crap with
them got it or you can build these were cold-case files, right?
And so, then the, the case File then can be built and that takes
anywhere from like 5 to 15 minutes for your level, I say.
And then that can run at the shipping performance and it can fit in
memory always because it's the shipping memory format.
But you can't
Hatcher.
So you can't change the texture, you can't like rebalance a vehicle or
anything like that.
So that's what we had sorry again Justice.
I'm going to be the person who's constantly asking for their course
with the decompression.
So, when you say, you can't patch it though, if you have a handle
table still in that optimized version, why couldn't you patch it?
Because since everyone still going through the handle table, couldn't
I just reload the textured patch, the handle table, just like, I
wouldn't even just all the other people are still in that one.
And, yes, eventually I'd run out of memory as I kept.
Adding these patches, but for a little while with that work or about
Miss Winters, you can press, you can do that.
We never built like a general-purpose system to them.
If we built a bunch of really special case systems, which allows you
to do, certain kinds of things like audio mixing or like somatic
control in this optimized version, got it.
But the other reason is because we didn't really have the staff to
maintain like three versions of the game, right?
So we had like the super development version and the kind of like,
shipping final version and we could have
And some time to have like, okay, this is like mostly the memory lay
odds, but then you could also load patches on top that are in the
development format and practice, we stripped all that code out for the
retail version.
As of that is something we could have done if somebody talked about a
various points along the way, but it never really kind of got to be a
trade-off where it was worthwhile from because you're always taking
the resources from somewhere else if you're going to do that.
So you have to kind of go, wait a minute, our level reload time is the
most important part B during development is the most important thing
here.
We're going to pull people off of some other thing they're doing,
which is probably important.
Ain't it never came to that.
So the the twenty second twenty minute turnaround for a full rebuild
was still okay because most of the time people weren't using it.
Yeah.
And generally speaking what would happen is that most of the people
who are working on the game would be using the development version of
the game and they'd be using either like a small shipping level, like
a test level to build their assets.
So, most people who are working like a weapon or a vehicle or like AI
or something, or working the development version, the game that got
fast.
Iteration and also
Pretty fast loading and then the designers and artists who are working
on the final levels of the game.
They're working in the editing tool all the time.
So they're seeing their changes in the editing tool and we had like
editor that actually ran the game within it.
So you could like make all your AI changes on the PC and like play
them in the editors.
He goes super fast iteration there.
Then when you want to see those for real, you would build a cache file
copied across the to your Xbox.
And then that was like fifteen minute process.
But you can still keep
Working on like a winter other things.
So it wasn't terrible.
Basically, everybody could get their jobs done.
Okay.
And one of the things that I think is worth pointing out about this is
like that's a super simple pipeline, right?
Like I can describe that pipeline to you as someone who's not worked
in it in like 14 minutes.
Yeah.
You understand like all the trade-offs about that, pretty much
completely and it's worth pointing out.
There's a lot of value in simple pipelines because now we're going to
talk about what happens when you trust.
So like the Halo
Optimized, for a small set of use cases, right?
Like there're use cases, that work really well.
And then within that use case, you have quite known performance
characteristics.
And there's not a lot of blurriness in between them, they're quite
precise, right?
And so, as a result, you can Target your engineering solution to those
fairly precise use cases.
So now that and that is something we didn't really appreciate.
So now, let's kind of weird.
Moving ahead from United, that's like the 2001 to 2010 timeframe
working in the Halo region, right?
This system kind of like shipped all of these games.
Basically with, you know, presumably additions and modifications on
the way.
But substantially speaking, every Halo game up to reach was shipped on
something that looked pretty much like that.
Yeah.
And I mean, I didn't work on Halo 4.
Halo 5 is my understanding that you have like variance of this.
So it's kind of just like this was a you know which to some extent you
know, proves the point of there's something to simple pipelines.
It keeps working to some degree and you can maybe work with it pretty
well.
If it looks like if it was had that much longevity.
Yeah and this this significant upgrades the you make along the way as
far as like a synchronous file I/O and like loading packs in smaller
forms.
And then, you know, lru cache has for texture and geometry and
animation, and things like that.
So you can like bolt things onto it, but the fundamental fundamentally
if you have a pipeline with good bones,
And you understand that you can do a lot with it.
So if you kind of look around, like, 2008 to 2009 is when we started
working on Destiny in parallel, with all the work that was going on
Halo Reach.
And if you care more about that timeline, you can look at the GDC
talk.
I gave last year about that.
Okay.
But we started working on Destiny.
We were kind of looking at one major problem, which is in Halo, like I
said, you've got these two places you can be and you can be in fast
iteration or you can be in fast.
Loading and really representative console look and performance, right?
But like that's very binary, you can't have both we're like, well, why
not have both, right?
Like, why not just have all of the good parts and none of the bad
parts and so, let's, I mean, it sounds good to me.
Yeah.
Right that's pretty good.
That sounds pretty good.
And so, there's a lot of, there's a lot of less than there are a lot
of different ways.
We talk about that more probably, but so the fundamental idea was
okay.
So why?
I don't we instead of loading these pack files which are really
monolithic.
Let's do some processing of the individual assets.
And then, because we have this handle table, we can just load the
assets individually, right?
And then put the Assets in the handle table individually and so you
could say, well we maybe we'll build a pack file.
The first time you build a level and then you make some changes and
then instead of like then basically you'll say okay, so based on
Those changes that you made while you touch these 20 things.
So, we're going to build another pack file that contains those 20
things.
And then we'll load the base 1 and
Load the second one, that contains those 20 things, those 20 things
will overwrite, and then you'll just have everything and memory.
And so, then you get in this position where you're like, let's build
this, essentially optimized format for the final game and then let's
build it over and over again.
And each time only output the things that changed and then the game
can just load like a series of patches and then you'll be in a
situation where the game can load almost the final shipping speed.
When everything is loaded, it is in 100%.
And the final shipping memory configuration.
And also, you can change individual assets.
Like that.
Sounds awesome.
So essentially what you're saying, people are reacting already just at
the tone of voice.
Yes.
What is that awesome?
Yeah.
So so essentially what you're doing here is sort of making, you know,
the the development time version of almost what you would do if you're
patching the game in reality, right?
It's like, hey
We shipped the end-user a version of Destiny later on.
We find we need to make some edits to some helmets or something that
people were wearing so we ship this new piece of information out, you
know, it goes out as a steam update or whoever but as I guess you
know, in the console world out of steam up there, it goes out as
whatever you would call the updates on consoles.
I don't know if they have the vehicle updates actually, okay.
It goes out as an update and these updates are, you know, you
you have no ability to go say, oh, I want to send you a different
huge, you know, 10 gigabyte file or something.
So, your by necessity sending these smaller ones, so you're just
saying, let's just do that during development and make that be the way
the system works.
That's exactly right.
And that's like another thing we should talk about different Halo and
Destiny here, right?
Is that in Halo is talked about how you build this essentially, a
memory image, right?
That has everything all flattened down of the memory image.
And so there's a lot of stuff in there that's like offset and the
memory image and so suppose you
Want to come along and say, hey, like the designers thought this
weapon like fired too fast and so they want to reduce the fire rate of
this weapon.
Okay, well, so maybe if that's just like poking, a few numbers in one
location, you can do that, right?
And then you can find a way and in practice, it turns out the best way
to do that in Halo was actually to write like a piece of code in the
executable that was like after you load the hold map like go find the
fire rate and change it from 20 to 15 or something about it.
And we shipped
Weapon rebalancing for Halo 2 like that, for example.
So you patch the executable not the actual data.
For those changes, for those kinds of changes.
That's how we did it in.
Like the in, almost all cases in Halo.
And when we most of our updates to Halo took the form of downloadable
content, which is like entirely new memory images for like multiplayer
maps and stuff like that, we didn't even really have the desire or
ability to go in and change the single player game or like, a random
stuff.
Right.
And so, hopefully you see like why?
That is
It's like if you want to change a weapon or like, actually I wanted to
add some effects of that.
So you're like, adding a reference to some other asset and then that
like reference is a string, which is variable length.
So gets packed in there.
And then that thing relatively 200 bytes is now 248 B.
And then how do you like do that?
And so the the way you do that is you like basically like have to add
support in the executable for like loading things on the end as it's a
pretty big mess if you don't build it in up front and so
So one of the big constraints but Destiny is we knew we wanted to have
this, you know, ability to update the world arbitrarily.
So again another thing that leads into that is saying let's build a
model that's around patching, an arbitrary updates.
So
And I think just the stuff I described there like this does not
anything really wrong with that.
But you have to think very carefully about some of these
Like philosophical.
Structural pipeline decisions, right?
And so one of the assumptions that I say them there, I don't have
anybody caught it.
Is this the Assumption there that is people are still fundamentally
doing the same thing.
They were doing in the Halo engine, which is they are wanting to view
their content on Xbox or Playstation and they're working on their PC.
And then they want to, like, see it synced across the Xbox or
PlayStation that assumption underlay all of the pipeline, it turned
out the completely wrong.
Okay, because what actually happens between you know,
2005 and 2012 is that the development PC, workstations, converged a
lot more to the capabilities of the console's, right?
Like think about back in 1999, right?
You have the original Xbox and you have like your PC or Mac that
you're doing a development on if you want to see what it's really
going to look like in the final game rendering, you really have to
render that on the PlayStation because it's a sorry on the Xbox
because you know you've got your Envy to a chip
and like all the custom blend units and I'd like your programming it
with a graphics API.
That doesn't exist anywhere on the PC at all and so you have to see
everything on the target platform.
You know, today almost every game team everywhere in the world does
almost all of their work on PC and then sees it in an almost
representative format on the PC because there's been such
commoditization of the platforms that you know, maybe you're not on a
single platform.
Like Halo, maybe you're on like five platforms and you like even if
you're doing a mobile game, your maybe simulating your iPhone and like
Window on the screen that you're clicking on, right?
So,
That totally changes everything, because the performance
characteristics of data loading on the PC or totally different
performance characteristics data, loading on, you know, the original
Xbox, right?
And so there's much less reason for you to try and build these packed
files.
The other thing to consider is that on a console?
You are trying to squeeze every single byte of memory, right?
So think about Xbox 360, or for us the long pole is really hit
PlayStation 3, right?
So the you
To squeeze every byte of memory out of the PlayStation 3, then you
have to do a really large amount of data transformation to get from
your Source assets into what the most optimal thing is, is the most
optimal thing room in the Halo engine, like the source format and the
engine format, we're constrained to be the same thing.
Correct?
Because there's a header file that is like, here's what the data is
going to be in the engine.
And then also that's what's on disk.
So one of the things we identified as hey, like we're looking at
PlayStation 3, like
We're going to have to do crazy things, like transform your model into
spu programs, that like patch two constants for the shaders.
Because that's the only way you can ship like a really detailed game
on this like crazy architecture about how crazy the sellers.
Well, I'm actually the not a particularly cell knowledgeable person
but I can understand like, essentially, if you're talking about PS3
that's kind of before the break-in,
And sort of how consoles looked in terms of their similarity PC and
then just after, so if you have to reach back down in there, it does
seem like the kind of thing where you're talking about a very
radically different data format probably than anything you would ship
normally.
I assume that that is you know something that you I guess knew going
into it or did you not like was it was just something that was sort of
like visible to you like oh we're going to have to have different PS3
data packs for versus are other things or this
Something that like kind of, you know, in the back of your head but
weren't really focused on as like, oh man we got to pay attention.
This this is something we knew up front and so we thought we were
being extremely smart here.
Okay.
So you tell me, okay, yes, fact that we said like all right so if you
look at other engines, like for example, you know, look at Unreal
Engine 3 in this timeframe, right?
Like Unreal Engine 3, people are working on the PC like they're their
asset film.
At the source format is pretty close to what they're editing and what
they're seeing in the editor and they can't really see.
Like necessarily something that's super representative of the console.
And also there's a really long cook stage where they go from, like
what they can see in the editor down to, what's on the console right
there.
Like we want to avoid having a really long cook stage because we want
to be really incremental on the target platform.
So, we built the whole Destiny asset pipeline around the problem of
how can an artist be working on the PlayStation 3 and like, see a
totally final totally performant version of their content as quickly
as possible from what they're doing on the
EC got it.
And that turned out to be exactly the wrong problem.
To solve got it because the, because there's such a lot of data
transformation going on in that pipeline from like your Source,
formats have to be organized for editing and your engine formats on
like the console have to be completely squished down for memory.
And so there's a really big data transformation that has to happen
there.
And we said, let's put that data transformation in the critical path
through what we call the edit to view pipe.
Okay?
Brecht.
And
if we put that in the critical path,
That means we have to make it fast and then we'll only have one
pipeline to maintain and that'll be good, but it does.
I guess, you know, I guess the corollary to that is just that well.
Okay.
That will, if that always has to be fast, there will eventually be
things.
We maybe can't even do for data Transformations because they simply
can't be done fast enough for this iteration, but that be a fair
characterization or that is a fair characterization and this is where
you get into like launch.
Team problems is really interesting.
Like if you have got a team and you've divided up your team kind of
based on
Realization.
Let's know which is something that you do in any team over about 15
people.
Like there's always specialization.
So what happens is that you have like here, the people working on
like, say graphics features and here are the people working on, let's
say like asset pipeline, right?
Your incentives are not aligned across those engineering teams.
I see if you are working on graphics features.
You the natural way to think about that is I'm going to make the best
looking Graphics, right?
And the most performant Graphics, I'm gonna get the most things on
screen and
I'm going to make it look as beautiful as possible because that's what
my artists will tell me.
They valued my artists will always say, like I want it to be
beautiful.
I want all these features you'll never stop asking for more features
and so you just want to like Ramen the most graphics features as
possible.
And that means the most tightly optimized platform Target format and
then very often the time you're building these features, you're not
working hand in hand with a huge art team.
Like maybe you're working with one artist.
All right thing and there, Larry or prototyping artist is sort of
there to help.
Up guide that process contest content or something.
And so, you make these decisions very early about, like here's the
data format, here's how it's coupled together.
And you're like, I'm going to optimize for artists ease of use in the
editing program, and like a really natural way for the sources be
coupled together where they don't have to, like, type.
The same thing thing in three places and that I really like, beautiful
visual editor for shaders.
Maybe.
And then also like it breaks down to this hyper optimized format on
the PlayStation.
You can like, squeeze out stuff and make like a really beautiful
PlayStation game.
So what I just described there is a source format that is intuitive
and expressive meaning that changes in one place have to affect
Behavior, other places.
And like a lot of really intense runtime optimization.
So to give you a specific example there,
I'm going to get the details of this wrong but hopefully now you guys
will call me on that.
Think about the problem of having a crate that's glowing.
Okay.
And the glowing - of the crate it depends on its Health like maybe if
you shoot it's going to explode.
Okay.
Okay and so it glows more and close more and then it explodes.
This sounds like a perfect thing for Old Men Marie.
We have a large number of Science Fiction alien crates in there stood
out so
Okay, so we're saying it's all right, I have in game data.
This Dynamic so this crate has some hitpoint or something that's you
know, decreasing or whatever.
And then I have some artist-driven effect that they have created or
are going to author or want to tie into a Shader or something that
needs to wire that up essentially.
So that the dynamic piece of State goes into a system that allows them
to say the glow is based on the, you know, the hit points or something
this effect, exactly.
Okay.
And the destiny and the destiny model, the information that is exposed
by objects.
That can be looked at by other objects, or looked at by shaders.
What have you is called a channel, okay?
So an object will expose some number of named channels of information
and complicated object, like the player might have, you know, 120
channels on it or a simple object, like a crate.
Maybe only has like five channels, like it's velocity and it's health
or something like that.
And so, in the source data, what you are doing is here, like, in the
Shader editor, your like wire up, this Shader input to the channel,
which is health
That's cool.
Yeah, so you've created a dependency bear between that shaders Source
data and in practice, like in the object system, we have a component
based object system, so like one of the components is exposing like a
health Channel and that's great.
Like you could in some sense of where you're saying there is though
you have a data to code dependency in a sense, write it.
In other words that we say the optic system.
Are you talking about the fact that the actual C++ code expose this?
Or is it more like know?
There's
There's another data piece over here that said like, add an integer
here that's like hit points.
So yes, they're C++ code but it's actually cos code.
That's doing a generic thing for properties of objects and things like
this.
I'm sorry if I praise that poorly but I do know what I'm mostly
talking about is data to data dependency, okay?
Because so now let me rewind like you know, 20 minutes or something.
I was talking about about the tax system, right?
Like one of the properties the tax system had in Halo is if you have a
Allure piece of data and then it can be edited and then it can be
reloaded, just that one piece of data, right?
And so that's a constraint that you place on the overall pipeline is
any individual piece of data can be edited.
And then that one thing can be reloaded and it's a bug.
If you have a crash the artist right?
You kind of across the are displayed as one piece of data.
So what that means is as a programmer, you can't introduce structural
dependencies between pieces of data.
Okay.
Because so, for example, you couldn't in the Halo engine, you can't
write some code that's like in the object.
I know in the code that reads the object tag that shaders are looking
at the health Channel while they're not looking at the health Channel
because you don't know because that's not a different piece of data
and that could be loaded or reload independently, right?
And so you can't write code.
That says, look at all the channels.
On the object and then decide which ones are going to get output.
You can't write that code at like asset load time, right?
You can write that at runtime, right?
Can like, analyze all the data that's been loaded and then you can do
that.
And so I see what you're saying.
So basically, we're talking about here is, there's a certain number of
things which, for whatever reason, it could be for optimization
purposes.
It could be for, you know, because we need to Output the correct,
shaders stuff, or whatever.
I'm going to need to look across a graph of data.
Rather than add a particular piece of data.
And because the graph is changing over time.
Because every time we reload, we pull out a piece of it.
We end up in this situation where we kind of have a nasty Problem,
whatever thinking I was doing about this thing that needs to look
over.
The graph is now dependent on the graph, not on a piece of data.
Is that a fair characterization or yes?
Okay, and, and the right way to the right way to think about, this is
to look at the difference between Halo and Destiny is like in Halo.
You really don't have any graph analysis, right?
The only the only graph based thinking is what happens at run time.
Like, after you've loaded everything, you can do some like runtime
query to say, like on the object, look at the five channels, and if
two of them are being used by shaders and update those two, and then
don't update the other ones in Destiny.
So here we get into like kind of the heart of the problem which is you
have this Source data and I've described like a simple form of source
data coupling.
But in practice there's many many more complex kinds of
where,
If you want to run on the PlayStation 3 and you want to have a really
large number of objects and you want to be able to like render all
those objects on spu's.
You are basically trying to avoid like a lot of branchy graph analysis
type work at runtime, right?
Because it can only finesse for you can only focus on the little chunk
that it's given.
So you've got to have everything in that chunk when it winds up for
those of you have not programmed on the PlayStation 3, raise your
hands.
If you have ever written a spu code,
Okay, so like 95% of people have not written as few code on the
PlayStation 3, the spu has got a small area of memory that contains
both its code and data and it's basically running like a little micro
program.
Okay?
And so the only code you can access on the spu as whatever was in that
micro program.
And so if you are running your micro program and you encounter a
situation where you're just like, I would like to run some AI code in
line here or something like that.
You cannot do that.
Like that is not possible unless you
Unlike a virtual memory system on your SP with some people do.
But so what that means is, if you're optimizing for that kind of
processor, you are trying to push as much of your asset analysis into
assets like dependency and building time as possible.
And this is what really fucked us, okay?
Like that's the technical term for it, but there's the technical specs
and we will talk about the slow and gradual.
This is fun fucking okay in a second.
But so you have the situation where you're trying to build the best
and most polished graphics features in the PlayStation 3.
Meaning you're trying to build the most optimized spu programs and
most optimized data formats.
Meaning that you're trying to do a very large amount of asset analysis
at asset import time, okay?
And so as an example, so remember I said like, you have objects, they
have channels some channels might or might not be read by the Shader
croquet.
And so you're going to write an SP you bytecode.
Not like not like the program.
So your spu thing that's running the renderer is like a VM, okay?
Similar to the like what Jeff and Fabiana talking about.
So your sbu bytecode for render as like a VM and some of the
instructions that you can omit in your Shader processing language are
like here's how this channel should be exported to this.
Kind of Shader constant guy.
So part of the process of building your
Act is now building spu bytecode for all of the shaders and all the
channels that are being used.
Correct.
So to build that bytecode program, you have to look at the object data
and also the Shader data for any shaders that are used by that object.
So that there's now like a dependency between all that data and if any
of that data changes you have to rerun that processing.
And that processing is essentially a compiler.
I mean it's trying to produce output Shader, which
Means it, you know, if you want to do optimization, if I do the things
you are talking about trying to make a compiler that you know, does
all the standard things I assume.
Yeah, yeah, exactly.
Although we'll talk about how it's different to a compiler, a little
bit later, the and then there's another level of dependency on there
which is well, you can't just render all the objects and level as
individual objects because you know they you get a huge number of draw
calls and you can't do that.
And so you actually have to bake together.
All the objects that are in like a
Your location together, you have to write some kind of spatial
subdivision program, that's like here all the objects in this chunk of
the level and then I'm going to turn them into like one vertex buffer
and index buffer in one set of shared constants.
And so if you have this like glowing crate on the wall, then the data
optimization problem is not just that one object, it's maybe like
these 500 objects and then all of the shaders used by those 500
objects.
Okay, right.
And then that optimization problem, then is what you have to
Run, anytime the oddest changes.
Any field?
On any one of those shaders or any one of those objects got it?
Yes.
All right.
Do not do not blame Chris, so the nice enough to walk us through it.
So let's so here like everything I'm describing here is all of the
abstract theoretical level, okay?
And so
Just to be really specific about that the abstract theoretical
failure.
We're talking about here is
if you allow,
Some people in the pursuit of Awesomeness to add data dependencies,
without a clear, understanding of the cost of those data dependencies,
you can end up in a situation where all of your data is coupled
together, right?
And transformations to the source data produce.
Essentially unbounded transformations in the output data.
This makes a lot of sense.
So essentially what we're talking about here is, you know, in the
compiler analogy, you are talking about.
If you have a compiler that is trying to optimize for something that
is global to the whole program.
Then that simply means that whatever you change.
It could affect every last piece of code that you compiled.
Like it's like changing a pound to find at that point where it could
Cascades through the entire program and caused everything to have to
be rebuilt and
We have no idea what this could be, because as you start, adding more
of these things that aggregate pieces together for optimization, we
don't even really know what artist could build that could create huge
dependency chains in any particular level for unforeseen reasons.
Yes.
And the other reason that it's bad is because these dependencies they
may seem kind of benign to the individual quite smart engineer who's
working on it, right?
So you have like a
Dependency between this one field in this file and this one field in
this file and that's quite a small dependency.
But the level at which dependencies are tract is often at like file or
asset granularity.
I see.
And so even if it's a tiny dependency like you've just coupled
together two rather large things.
And then as a result of that like it doesn't take very many small
dependencies for everything to become like one Tangled Mass, right?
Because all you need is for any to, we're sort of talking about,
right.
Here's here's a
Raph and we've got some partition of this thing into like disjoint
subsets, right?
These things aren't connected there, you know, things we could pull
out as a chunk that can get processed and updated together.
All I need to do is add one little Edge between one of those two
subsets and now they're, you know, their own connected piece.
That's right.
So it doesn't matter how big that connection is in terms of its
meaning, it just has to be there, right?
And so this is something.
That we didn't really appreciate and we kind of just like walked into
this.
And so I'll just say one thing about that which is like in general.
If you can identify these dependencies, it is possible to remove them.
And the way that you remove them is that you identify where you're
going to cut your graph and then you prevent like, literally prevent
anybody from like, walking from
Going across asset to asset boundaries because you have to prevent
people because remember, your engineering team is probably 65 people
and there's maybe one and a half people on that team, who understand
how bad dependencies are.
Okay.
And so that's very clear.
Like you hope your team is full of smart people and in fact, our team
is full of smart people.
But like everybody is trying to solve their problem, right?
And the, the easy way to get it done, has to be the right way to get
it done.
Yes.
Otherwise you'll never be able to make progress if
If like only 2% of your stuff dedicated to fixing problems, the other
98% of your staff is narrated to dedicated to just getting a job done.
And in some sense you could just say, well, look, if you know, if an
aspect of our the way this asset system is working, is that all of our
Engineers have to be an expert in the asset system to do their job.
That's a huge like burden that that's placing on them.
Essentially like they have to have domain knowledge in this thing that
really shouldn't have that much to do with their job and now that's
taking up.
So even if you
Make sure everyone knew this, it's a cognitive load, that's costing
you all the time.
Anyway, even at that point, what's up stop time for this?
We are 46 minutes in and we have 90.
So you have quite use, we have until 1:00.
Yes, so you don't have any no need to rush although maybe I don't know
how long the know I think you called it the the the unfuckin process
will take us.
So we haven't actually finished going through all the fuckery.
I think so like unless you have more questions about the theory we
should probably talk about the practice because the practice is
actually more interesting than Theory.
I think the theory sounds fairly straightforward.
I mean, you could almost describe this separate from anything.
It's just like, you know, hey if if you need to consider things as
collections, then you now are, you know, beholden to the number of,
you know, that the number of sub graphs as that reduces you, you get
worse, right?
You just if that goes down to one now,
Rebuilding the whole game, every change, right?
Would be one way to say it.
Whereas what you had in Halo was something very close to every little
node in the graph is its own rebuildable piece and it will never
propagate outwards or connect in that way.
Yep, that's the next thing.
The next, the last thing to say, on this topic, by the way, is that
dependencies are pretty straightforward from a theoretical point of
view to eliminate once you understand what's going on.
Alright I said that's what.
Yeah, so like the theory is fine there in practice.
Once you start having people creating content in these systems, you
get into situations where it's like, Okay, so we've identified that
like, the way that shaders and objects relate to each other was just
like, theoretically wrong, okay?
To solve that, you have to rebuild every Shader and object in the
entire game.
While you also have like, a team of people working on shadows and
objects, right?
That's essentially impossible.
Right.
It is similar to a city transit project.
We cannot shut the whole city down.
Order to put the tunnel through here.
So we've got to come up with all kinds of crazy things that we're
going to do drilling under it and having crazy, you know, rerouting
people and all this sort of thing because there's no other option I
guess.
Yeah.
That's actually like, there's a, some fun analogies there.
Okay.
All right.
So now let's talk about like the practice.
Okay, alright so we've identified that we started out and this is in
like 2009 2010, right?
So you know three or four years before we were planning on shipping
the game.
And so we've identified that we, we wanted to have a system where the
source data can be customized for Autos the in genetic be customized
for consoles and then there's a process of transforming from Source
data and the engine data.
And we've also understood that we did not grasp how important it was
to establish graph Cuts, right?
Yes.
And so we started out by saying, okay, so we
In Halo had like a large number of different programs.
Each was transformed one piece of data, right?
So there was here at the model, compiler, the PSG, here's the Shader
compiler.
Here's the triangle stripper, here's the little bsp Butler, okay?
Every one of those programs had to have its own code for, like, doing
I/O and, like, paralyzation if there was any, and none of them had any
dependency tracking, right?
So, if you are working on a level, you change one tiny, part of the
level, the DSP Builder wasn't incremental.
And so you have
Fill the entire level.
Any time you moved a rock or something like that.
Not very good.
And so we said, okay, so we want parallelism, we want asynchronous I/O
and we want incremental ISM because we're talking about patching
everything.
So we said, let's let's instead of building like a large number of
small isolated programs, let's build one framework for describing work
for transformation.
Okay?
Okay so essentially this is like almost to some other countries like a
job system.
Yeah.
In multi-threaded game or something like this where we're just saying
Hey, look, we know we have a number of things we have to do.
We know these things are dependent on each other.
We know there's an underlying graph potentially that we have that
describes the relationships between the data.
Can we make something systemic here?
That just allows people to throw something into the system with that
description, and it will make the right things happen when you do a
change.
Exactly, right?
And so the approach here is to say, let's build a general purpose.
Work scheduler.
Which the way that the way that it works is that you have defined some
number of data formats, right?
Like some of your data formats are Source formats and they each have a
particular like structure associated with them.
Like here's the header file for a model, what have you?
And some of them are your engine data formats, okay?
And the granularity that we chose was to say what is a function of
work that can be performed in a single threaded fashion without doing.
Nei.
Oh okay.
So okay.
Functional.
Mission which is idempotent is noguchi like to call it idempotent
here.
Means give it the same inputs.
It'll give you the same outputs every time.
So basically what you're talking about is this thing you know we're
going to break it down into pieces where the data has been put into
memory.
That this thing will operate on and it will not get self cause new
data to be pulled in for any reason.
That's right.
And so it works on some number of chunks of data and it produces some
number other chunks of data.
And it can also produce specifications for other.
Tasks that need to be rung.
This is almost exactly like a multi-threaded job system.
So same basic principles.
Apply.
Yeah.
And so given that you're going to build like some awesome
multi-threaded like fully asynchronous.
I/O schedules, like completely deterministic like with caching on this
granularity system.
We basically said well since we're going to build this system.
Let's just make this system, really good, and then make it, do
everything.
This is the second time.
We're, let's make it do everything, it has come up.
Yeah.
And so here's like, here's the, here's the second observation here,
right?
Which is that
If you have data that, follows a particular model, okay?
And you are an engineer and you're trying to write something to
operate on that data.
If you are tempted to build a general system that can handle like
changes to the data model automatically, you're probably doing the
wrong thing, that sounds very reasonable.
So specifically, in this case, right?
Like, you can say, well, like in Halo we had like these whatever,
like, 120 different kinds of data, each with their own processor.
Some of those processes were very simple, lot of them.
Some of them are like the model compiler, the level Builder.
We said well liked,
Instead of trying to like have a lot of different asset processors
still, let's just have one general purpose, asset processor and then
let's have the structure of the data be encoded in, like, however, how
it was produced.
Hell is provided to the graph processor.
And what I'm talking about here is like, there's basically two
choices, right?
The first choice you can say is hey, our data tends to be organized in
the form of what you might call assets, right?
Like, an
Might be a Shader or a texture or an object, a thing that a human
might think of as a unit for some purpose, right?
And so, if you think about the process of like processing an object,
let's say that's not going to be a single like one of these C function
tasks that I'm talking about, right?
Because if that was true, then you basically the input would be like
all of the data loaded off disk that you're going to need to know
about when you process your object but you likely aren't going to know
that.
because,
Sometimes when you're processing an object, you'll be like, oh this
object has a component on it, and it references like this thing over
here that was like the damage that it can do.
Right?
And so instead of just having a reference to the damage, I'm going to
like take that damage and code it in line and my things so that I can
be more optimized right now.
And so a very common thing that you do when you're writing like these
see functions you're like I'm doing some work.
I discovered that actually I can't like I need to load a file off disk
and so I'm going to create another task that goes and lows that file.
That does the actual work.
Exactly?
Okay.
And so in some sense I mean this is sort of a general aspect of these
systems.
I suppose, you know, if you write something that's designed to be hey
we made we sort of defined, the unit of work as something which cannot
do I owe.
Then typically, what you end up doing, is your program really
operates?
One level up from that it's we have all these chunks.
I know that I'm going to need to do conditional IO, but now instead of
that living in the program, in the form,
Of some kind of read call, which will block it.
Now has to live up in a graph portion, which is sort of coded
simultaneously with the system that is like, instead of blocking on
the read here, I'm going to create sort of little programs that can be
run later, right?
This is, I mean, I've seen these kind of systems before they tend to
bifurcate in that way.
So I assume this is what you're talking about.
We now there's like a two-level coding process if you will.
Right.
So it's the only thing to say there is just like something a human
When things have been as an asset, is not going to be a single task,
like these functions, we call or tasks, right?
And so assets are going to have graphs of tasks with them.
And there are also going to be asset to asset dependencies.
Right?
Like the thing I talked about with the object name, to load the
shooter.
So we said, well like, because it's going to be asset asset
dependencies.
Like, let's just throw it onto the graph Optimizer and then it will
sort it out, right problem.
There is, like I said, there is now zero cost for a Crossing asset.
He's as a programmer.
Like and so, as a programmer your now like, working in this way,
you're probably not used to working in, which is rather than writing
like command line batch process.
The so that's like do some synchronous I/O, and read some file, you're
like actually create an asynchronous job graph, and then execute those
jobs and then like depend on the futures from that job graph by
creating another task to go and do it.
So you're already programming in this way that you're not used to
thinking about and you're quite
white detached from the actual performance of how that's going to
work.
Yes.
Because you're specifying your job graph.
It's going to go into the Magic Machine.
The Magic Machine is going to make it fast and you might be calling
some thing in that job rappers.
Like, oh, somebody already wrote the job graph that converts a PSD.
So I'll just call that one because I need it.
Now, that one of course, is this whole other job graph, which make all
other job graphs.
So you kind of have like a little bit of a Sorcerer's Apprentice job
graph.
Where who knows, how many brooms we end up with at the end of the day,
right?
And the classic like this super class
Example for something like that is maybe I'm I'm writing some code to
do visibility let's say so like we're going to have some middleware
program that's going to do visibility on a portion of the level.
And so I need the bounding boxes for the object.
So I'm going to call the graph for the object and that I'm going to
get back the object that I'm going to extract the bounding box from
It.
Go, Do you see the Trap?
I do, right?
Because when you get back the object, you have just depended on like
We bite and everything that was anywhere in that object because it
doesn't know, you only want the bounding box.
So it can't really even say oh hey by the way don't worry about the
sound effects that were in this thing right?
Because they matter as far as it knows.
Yeah right.
And so now you're in a situation where like someone is working on
audio and they're like I'm going to change the looping sound effect.
I'm not going to change the fact.
There is a looping sound effect.
I'm just going to change the b in the aiff file, okay?
And they press the Go Button there.
Why did it rebuild visibility for my level?
And take two hours?
It all makes such a logical sense.
When we've just gone through it, though.
I see exactly what right?
I don't understand his frustration or whoever the audio.
So yeah.
And so that that I just described again.
Now there's a theoretical problem, right?
Like that, still assumes that you wrote like a perfect bug, free super
optimized multi-threaded.
Processor.
Yes.
So now let's talk about what actually happened.
So we've already established that there are all of these like
theoretical problems that mean that there's Rocky Waters ahead of us
in the period, from like 2009 to 2014.
Okay.
Right.
And that those problems are like, theoretically intractable is that
the case of we wrote it bad X.
It's like we just the problem definition is such that
That there's really not going to be much we can do here, right?
The problem director definition is such that like is it's
theoretically impossible for us to produce a solution.
People will be happy for because we did not identify the importance of
graph Cuts.
Got it.
Okay.
And then a couple things happened one was there was some like stuffing
on the project where like the person who was writing the reflection
system was doing and they got pulled off to something else and then
someone else came in like six months later and so there's this
scheduling issue.
Ooh, we're so you're going to build this graph processor.
That's about dealing with like arbitrary data, right?
And so what you need is a reflection system that allows you to talk
about data.
So reflection system here is like we call it the schema system.
It's a system that allows you to specify the structure of data in such
a way that you can work with the data even if your code, didn't know
what the structure was.
So, what I mean by that is like your graph processing.
Doesn't need to have a C++ hitter for like the sound effect at some
point.
There was a sound effect that was declared in code, or have it was
declared and that got process down into a piece of data that piece of
data, describe the structure layout of what a sound effect looks like
and what is memory layout could be right.
So then your graph processor deals with like arbitrary structures with
arbitrary memory layouts, it just knows any time, I had a reference,
I've got an edge between those two things, I don't really care what
necessarily, you know, where that was and the thing.
Thing.
I just know.
That's how I get it and go.
Yeah.
So you're obviously super dependent on the details of your Affliction
system.
Yeah.
And for whatever scheduling reasons, the reflection system was like a
year late.
Okay.
Because like, it started late and the design was like, elegant in some
ways that are kind of cool, but maybe not actually necessary for the
problem.
We were very nice because if you're building a reflection system, you
intend to last 20 years, it better be a good reflection system, right?
Fair enough.
Yeah.
So anyway not things.
I would fault anybody for necessarily at the time, like, I probably
should have redirected that, but whatever, it doesn't matter.
So reflection system is late and then we're building the graph
processor.
Not, I wouldn't say under the gun, but like you're prototyping, team
has like built their own like data loader, because the reflection
system in the graph process are on available yet, right?
So effectively, it wasn't even so much that these problems to start to
manifest itself, we haven't even gotten to the point where
we're, we're noticing the problems because we're sort of using a
makeshift system.
While this is being the magical graph processor is coming online.
Yeah, so there's like a visible.
There's a prototyping environment that stood up this just like, here's
a text file reference, some other text file, just load it all into
memory, right?
And so people are going and they're defining their data definitions
and they're like by implication they're processing steps without like
any knowledge of what the process is going to be able to do right?
And how are they running this?
They saw
Just have a.
Okay, I just manually run the thing because I don't have a graph
processor.
They don't have like tasks that do anything or if they do, they like
jamming at run time.
It's kind of like a key portion and it because the data is not very
big yet it's that'll work.
Okay.
That's totally fine.
But you have like a couple scripted objects and like if you scroll
through got a problem and then we go and build the graph processor and
we decided we were going to use C++ 11 because it sounded pretty cool,
okay?
And if you're going to build
Build a graph processor that works on abstract data.
You should use.
This is a reasonable assumption, you should use like high-powered
abstract, algorithmic data processing tools, right?
Like, if you're going to build something that works with abstract
data, then why wouldn't you like use a lot of maps and Anonymous
Lambda functions and things like that.
All right, all right.
I see what you're saying.
It's really a case of like, if you're if you're if you're building
something, you're like, this is going.
Like work on, you know, algorithmic Comfort, complex problems.
We had to have like algorithms available to us and like why would you
write your own mapreduce?
When you continues ones off the shelf, okay?
And so like it's also just like hey this is new technology like it's
interesting to experiment with.
Yeah, we went down that path for a while and where we got to was a
graph processor that you could like run your point it at something,
okay?
Sweet.
We haven't built any caching layers yet.
Okay.
Okay, so when you pointed it at like a task graph, it would construct,
the whole task graph and memory than execute all the tasks, right?
See really, which is sort of a test for the overlap version it just
like, hey, let's make sure that if we execute these things to really
in some walk of the graph graph, that is like depth-first or
something.
However, we chose to do it verify that we get the right assets out the
other end and then we're sort of on our way to having our graph
processor magic.
Magic hasn't come yet, but we can sort of see it.
And from from one side, you can I think defend that decision which is
hey people really want to write their task graph, they really need to
write the task graphs in a way that they can like start because the
process of building an entire asset pipeline from nothing takes years.
Yes.
Right.
And so you want to get as quickly as possible to point.
People can write the task function.
That's presumably.
This is also a feature, you would want of an eventual system anyway,
because when something goes wrong with the grass scheduling, the first
thing you typically do is you regress back to the serial version to
go.
Let me make sure
Sure.
It's not a problem with my schedule, it, right?
I mean, like when I typically write these things, if I'm trying to
debug them, I need this, the sequential path to know what the correct
output is.
You know.
So that I know that I'm not just processing the graph wrong because,
you know, it helps with bug isolation, basically said that is a
reasonable supposition that I believe that is incorrect In this case.
And the reason is because we haven't talked about the data sizes yet.
Okay.
These like these graphs at Peak are like 15 million tasks.
And remember what I just said about like the coupling, can we see 15,
Mega tasks, 15 megatons is because I don't know that I'm ever gonna
get to say that again.
So if you're like, 1.5 E2, the seven tasks.
Okay?
Yeah, perfect.
So, let's just think about that for a second, you've got a graph
processor.
That is going to build a task graph in some way, right?
And it has to, like, for these tasks load know what?
The type they are no other inputs.
Their outputs, like how many bytes do you think per task?
You might need for your tracking structure.
Is this before or after C++?
11 comes picture.
Let's suppose we're using C++ 11.
I can't imagine.
I don't want to know.
I actually can't estimated, okay, I think it's probably on the order
of about 20, kb per task.
Okay, so basically, you're already
At extremely expensive, memory size card.
Just to say, let's do this like 30 gigabytes in only your task,
metadata structure.
And I should also point out this the 32-bit application.
This is the kind of thing that I would have nightmares about.
I think this is a, this is wow.
Okay, so this is a very difficult task, right?
This pun intended, I guess, this is very different charge and to be
fair, like 15 million tasks is like the maximal size of the task grass
for the shipping version of Destiny in 2014.
Okay?
Like at the time that this became like a really serious problem.
The task sought the task graphs was probably about
200,000 tasks.
Okay and doubling every three weeks.
Okay, so you look at this and you're like if we actually put this into
Excel and look at the shape of this thing, we are very scared right
now.
Yeah.
Because like around about like March of 2011 or something like that is
when like we had the single-threaded task processor and
It had like a caching system, but the way that the caching system
worked is that you ran it on a particular graph, okay?
And the second time you ran it on the graph, it like deserialized the
graph that was output of the end of the previous execution from disk,
okay?
And, and then like, did the incremental analysis to figure out what I
need to get knocked out and then like, okay, right?
Because it has to dip the two graphs.
Because it
It's to know what it actually has to run, right?
Because this the problem that's already intractable that was
terrifying.
Me is just the problem of rebuilding the game from scratch.
We haven't even talked about actually trying to make a change to one
floating point value.
That's right?
Okay, and also remember that like the structure of the graphs is not
the same.
Like you like, okay, your task functions are defined in some metadata.
That's in the executable, okay.
Just like this task has got five inputs of the following kinds and now
between runs, like, you might have changed executable versions.
And so, you have a graph that had to encode all the tasks metadata not
just for what the task was, but also like the schemas of the task
functions and the schemas of the data that was there.
Yes.
Because all the day that all the functions can
It's been fun to run.
And remember, this is where we start getting into fire drill
territory.
Okay.
Because we are still talking here about the like, the first version of
the graph processor.
You can stand up that allows you to in single-threaded fashion like,
build a little of the game because
Once you have that up and stable, then you can write all your tasks
functions, right?
And then you can work on what at the time we can.
I don't think we're thinking, too, clearly about, we're thinking maybe
it's like a different task processor that is like optimized for rather
than being like a single-threaded batch processor that you just point
at something.
It's like more like an on-demand asynchronous multi-threaded thing,
right?
Because it could run on a server somewhere and leave the, you know,
the graph in memory and some 64 GB server.
So that doesn't have to read from disk
Or things like this.
Am I making this up?
You don't generally want to run stuff like that on a server because
you want to be local.
Because if it's on a server you have really hard problems around
versioning like when individual people treat them more from one
executable version of so like it kind of has to run the local
workstation not necessarily, but there's a lot of really interesting
complexity there.
That will totally not get time to talk about but so we're in the
situation where this graph processor is a 32-bit application, you
know?
Tens of kilobytes of metadata per task instance and we're barreling
towards Milestones.
We're like hey like we actually can't build this level.
We're not only does it take 5 hours to build the level around the task
functions.
Serially but like it runs out of memory.
And so you can use that like Windows 3, GB like extension and that
buys you maybe like 12 days, okay?
Because remember the task graph is doubling every three weeks because
your art team is increasing and people are throwing more content in
the system and they're ready to go because they've been waiting for
this and they want to get levels and right, okay.
And so we crash like this is where I come on to the project and so we
crashed up.
We crashdot?
I'm so sorry.
Nuts?
Okay okay we crash start to programs simultaneously.
Okay, the first is to Port our entire engine from 32-bit to 64-bit
correctness, okay?
And just to just to do that as rapidly as possible, right?
Because then at least, we're going to open up more memory for buying
this time.
The second is, remember I said the graph processor like serializes its
output when it finishes.
Ok.
But like
Serializing to disk takes memory.
Yes.
So like you can even be in situations where it finished but wasn't
able to save out at state so you have to run it from scratch the next
time.
So what we did, okay, so what you're saying is essentially like it's
tried to write out the graph, it couldn't write out of the graph.
So now we can't even defend him or because we don't even know what to
difficult just right.
Okay, but what you?
But see, here's the thing.
This is like, so the process of building the graph
Turns out and running tasks takes more memory than DC realising that
same graph, okay?
Okay, so what you can do is when you detect you're getting close to
your 32-bit application limit,
Can stop processing tasks, save out to disk quit your application,
launch, the application, again, deserialize the graph and keep going.
That is pretty beautiful, actually, I feel like that's finding a bit
of awesome in a dismal situation, like X, I really like that it gets
better.
Okay, because so you made some amount of progress there.
Okay.
Yes.
And
Then you like deserialize the graph and then you you keep going again,
right?
So you make some progress, but you're going to make less progress than
the first time before you hit your memory limit because you have that
graphic memory.
Yes, that's okay because you can do it again, right?
So it's kind of this this curve.
It looks like that of how much I can process each time.
Yeah, exactly.
Okay.
All right.
And so like that buys you maybe another two weeks worth of production
and then you're like this level was previously crashing in like
Hours with the build time on the farm but now it can complete and I
had to restart 12 times but now it takes 14 hours because the restart
process takes a long time.
Got it.
And then you get to the point where an infinite number of restarts
will not actually help you complete because just deserialize in the
graph doing one atom of work and then serializing again, exhaust your
memory, the process, got it.
So it really is like a, it's not even asymptotic, it's kind of just
got a hard stop.
Where it's like, okay, we've hit we've laid out and now we just can't
go any further but that, fortunately, it around about this time, we
complete the 64-bit Port.
Okay.
So now we can use as much memory as we need to up until a physical
capacity of the machine gun and this isn't like 2011.
So typically, you know, we have like between 8 and 16 GB of memory on
our desktop PCS and we have some Farm machines that have as much as 32
or 64 gigs of memory.
So we keep going, okay?
At this point, we identify that, like, the cereal graph processor.
Like, we've already known that, like, it wasn't really going to work
out, but just the, the fact that it has like this requirement to have
the whole graph in memory at once, and also, that it's overhead is
Tans of kilobytes of metadata per task.
Like that's just not compatible, right?
This guy, like, remember, the task graph is still doubling every three
weeks.
Yeah, and we at this,
Point in the project.
I mean, you know, now, but at this point, the product, you have no
idea what that bound will be.
You don't know the 15, Mega task number at this stage, could be
anything, right?
We're in an unknown, number of killer tasks.
At this point.
Yes, we're hoping the answer is between 700 and 800, kilo, tasks and
practice.
We are off by a factor of like 25.
Yes.
Okay.
and so again, like now that we actually are in a situation where like
these levels can build
Although they're like overnight builds that will like the process will
be single-threaded and it will just like tap out at like between 8 and
14 gigabytes of memory before it completes.
Okay.
And oh by the way because it's like a graph Discovery process.
Yes.
You can't put the progress bar on that, right?
Because every time you execute a task it could generate more tasks.
So technically speaking.
The only way that you could possibly
Know what?
The progress bar was is to already have finished?
Yes.
Okay so you can tell it's like monotonically doing work, right right?
You really don't have any idea.
Maybe we know it didn't crash.
It was certainly not that.
Yeah.
Okay.
Pretty good about that.
I think we got that right.
But I mean home, I mean time.
Yes, obviously Crush.
I mean like, you know, we we assume it's not an infinite Loop because
we've seen it retire a task.
Right?
What we wouldn't necessarily know is if it's an infinite task
generating Loop.
That's true.
Did that ever happen?
Yo, yes, that that happens actually, that happens all the time as
still happens actually, and it's as simple as an artist like
referencing, a particle effect and then that particle effect, like
referencing the object that was created on, or something like that.
And so artists do it all the time.
Okay?
And when that happens, you have now like a 40 GB memory dump that came
off of
Machine and somewhere in that 40 gigabyte memory dump is the
information that tells you there's a Content reference that was for
the cycle.
And we do actually in practice, right?
Cycle detection logic.
And that doesn't take very long but like still like, it's like an
indication of the kind of problems with dealing with yes.
And this is all like in total fire drill mode, right, right?
Because this is not something you expected to deal with.
So all of your engineering resources at this point have been
reallocated to other things.
No one's job description was supposed to be emergency for the thing.
The 64-bit emergency figure out how to fix the test system, right?
And also remember, it's and C++ 11, which like very few people
I'm gonna have experience with and also like the kind of like super
gnarly, like algorithm problems here like that.
Like we have a high proportion of those people at bungee but still
it's not a very high proportion of game developers in general like
right because there's a lot of very pragmatic game developers who
might not be well, versed in the theory or it's just not going to
experience with it.
Just breaks your brain.
It really does.
Like when you start dealing with
You know, any any any graph algorithm anything that has to operate on
more than 10,000 nodes?
You're in a totally different place anyway, so we designed a system
that was going to like, which was going to be basically the second
system which was preserving the same task interface, right?
But like a
Lately different execution, and so you can reuse some of the code,
like the code that sets up around the task and like, does a bit of the
I/O.
But so you basically build a multi-threaded system and maybe I'll draw
that.
Actually, that might be interesting time to check.
We have 35 minutes.
So this is the system that we designed, we do even 21.
You said I had until we will, we should have till this.
This is the time.
Mer.
Okay, I should have 12 12 minutes.
Okay, I believe timer is we after this is lunch so we can certainly go
a little long.
Is your is your phone in the?
Oh no service, right?
Maybe I want all this anyway, so you build a system that has like the
following components, right?
It has a component that is responsible for storing task metadata and
only task metadata.
And it does that in a format which is not.
Like, as we're doing previously, like, it was kind of like the
exploded like in memory graph.
It's like it's somewhat somewhat compressed the format we're like
queries to it.
Maybe you're a bit slower from CPU standpoints like but it's more
packed into memory.
So we built like a version of that that was all in memory thing and we
built a version of that was kind of like a virtual memory thing where
it stores its data and pages.
And then like you load the pages from disk if you get a cache Miss.
And so that allows you to store a infinite amount of metadata and a
finite amount of memory.
So you kind of just move this out of core and said all right we'll
just do the paging ourselves.
That way we don't have to worry about this anymore.
It could get as large as possible.
It will still be sloped actually but it won't stop.
Yeah, exactly.
Right?
So that's one component.
The next component.
We built was the task dispatch engine and so we really like separate
the task dispatching from the graph processing, okay?
And so, the task dispatch engine takes like an abstract, specification
of a task and what the data should be.
And then it can either dispatch that locally or it can dispatch or it
can reuse data from a remote cash, right?
Because you can hash together all the inputs to your tasks, including
like, older versions of the structures and stuff like that.
And then you can go look up that hash and see if
System server, whole other interesting set of problems around that.
I guess the biggest problem to note there is remember like we don't
have any acid granularity.
We only have like this task granularity.
So if you're going to do like server look up, you want it to be on a
granularity that is as large as possible, and matches, like the actual
scope of your and validation, right?
Right.
So like if I'm like, if I haven't local modifications to an object and
I build the object, if I don't as get the whole object, right?
Yes, and so,
The nice thing about like, getting the whole object would be, you
don't have to take on the metadata cost of all the tasks within that
object.
Yeah.
Right.
Because its own self-contained graph.
Yes, we didn't have that, right?
And so if there was an object right, then the graph processor only
knows like oh hey,
is this like set of tasks of which there might be, you know, like
In some cases, like 50,000 tasks or an object, okay?
And that seems crazy.
And the reason that's crazy is because like the way that some of these
like graphs for various different features get built is that, for
example, in the Shader system, it does things.
Like if there are eight different variant inputs to the Shader, then
execute a task for every combinatorial combinatorial and just see
which one and see, which one's give you the same byte code and
Collapse them.
Yes, which is perfectly reasonable from the standpoint like you said
before if someone who's just looking at their into the problem isn't
particularly well, versed in, whatever the asset systems issues, maybe
our sorry, the graph systems issues may be perfectly reasonable way to
solve it.
If you're just thinking about, hey, I'm just running this thing.
Well and also if you've been telling people like the the way that the
graph processing system works as like hey the graph processing system
is smart and so if you run the same task 20 times, it'll actually only
run it once and then it will hash the results, right?
That's pretty
Reasonable, right?
So if you pass the same inputs, the shadow compiler 20 times, run a
show compiled, 24.
Only once problem is that doesn't mean it exists only once in your
graph, right?
So you can have a situation where like your engineers thought they
were being smart by having these like nodes in the graph that collapse
down and they do collapse down terms of execution, but I don't
collapse down in terms of metadata, right?
So you're still exploding out that that number even though you weren't
the engineer didn't know that.
That was, this an ancillary costs on top of the runtime, right?
Got it.
Yeah, if you're focused on like number of tasks executions as your
primary metric, then you'll totally do that, right?
You wouldn't even notice you just be like it's why is it so yeah?
Okay, right.
Because if you then profile about you just like all damn graph process
is so slow.
I see it.
Only read my show compiled for one second.
What is it doing the other five minutes?
Exactly.
Well, it was collapsing.
The other fifty thousand instances of your Shader compiler to give.
Yes.
Right.
Like,
Okay.
Yeah, anyway, so then we have like this multi threaded execution
engine, the dispatches to like multiple work processes locally and
then it can go and retrieve data from the service.
But remember, I was saying, like the data granularity retrieved from
the service is very small.
It's like one task, and remember, it's this graph processor is doing
this Discovery Pass, right?
That's right.
So you get a result back and you're like, okay, so I got that result
back and it said that it created, eight new tasks.
I'm gonna go get results with
Jose tasks, right?
So like many, many transactions to the service.
Yes, with like very little work happening locally because if you're an
artist and you're like, I just want to get the state of the level as
it is in the depot.
You expect to run.
No tasks locally, right?
Yes.
And so your machine is just going to sit there and do well like 15
million transactions to the service, right?
Yes.
Just even your local machine, even your local machine, if you didn't
have anything.
But then if you had to rebuild the whole thing.
Yeah, if you had to rebuild the metadata and then like once the
metadata
Is on your machine, then you're in better shape.
But remember there's no concept of a sub graph, right?
So, if you're working on this level, like, you built that metadata.
If you go switch to another level, all that metadata has to be rebuilt
because one of the things about the coupling is that you're often
passing data all the way down the tree.
So, for example, the tree the tree of graph, the cryptographic tasks,
okay?
So for example, we have a feature in Destiny which is pretty cool,
which is that
A Shader on a crate.
If that creates on Mars, it might be Dusty.
If that creates on Venus, it might be masih, I see.
So basically, there's a parametric aspect to these tasks where you're
sort of saying, like, hey, this is essentially the same graph that I'm
going to execute, but I'm passing information down.
So essentially, it's a totally different graph than the other graph
that would have looked exactly like it, otherwise, right, even if none
a piece of the tossed actually, don't look at any of those parameters.
If something does.
Yeah.
Got it.
Yep, so that was pretty cool.
And so actually we built that I'm pretty happy about that.
So we built that leg second system.
And we built that in about nine months, okay?
And then we rolled it out and mostly it worked.
But there are some significant problems that were associated with that
system, which is like the 2012 version.
Okay, that's basically and the
Them's.
Our even though you have this now, like multi-threaded like less
metadata overheads like has a server cache and all that sort of thing,
it's still building this metadata for everything, right?
And so as you said the theoretical problems are not going anywhere.
So far they are still 100% there and you're just working at a more
efficient solution to a theoretically very bad situation, right?
Right.
And so that like the tool chain we end up shipping Destiny on and
actually every distant really since then still fundamentally is like
in this
A state where it's kind of, its kind of a batch processor, although,
it keeps like The Meta data cache and memory and like a lot of the
caches or Hong.
And then you point it at like a really big graph of stuff to go and
do.
And then it analyzes the like 9 to 15 million 9 to 15 Megaton.
Ask grafts, yes.
And then like knocks out maybe the two tasks in there that did it to
rerun.
Yes.
And then reruns those.
And so
Like your time like when you're actually executing the tasks, it's
very very good at scheduling CPU and I oh right.
But like you're paying anywhere from like 1 to 7 Minutes worth of
overhead for a graph processing which is doing nothing other than
processing, 15 Mega tasks because that's what it has to do.
Right in a single-threaded fashion because like if you have got some
like algorithm that's doing like essentially a graft if on 15 Megaton,
Oscar.
Paralyzed very hot paralyzed.
I see.
So that is up to the actual shipping Destiny then.
Yeah, that is what been so I assume now this is probably something
that's very high on your Hit List.
Well.
So for going forward.
Yes, so we have actually already built and rolled out a version 2 and
I'm currently like people are currently working on a version 3 and
just like to talk about the version 2 of the graph processor like it.
Introduces graph Cuts, right?
Okay, simple simple.
Simple thing to say, like a lot of complexity there,
They're behind the scenes, but essentially rather than having one
graph of 15 Mega tasks.
It's now 1.2 million graphs,
Okay, the Each of which has something like 12 no stream Lee had
erogenous, right?
Because some of them are like, here's this one file that is catch to
get loaded.
And then, B swap to then output to a platform specific state, right?
And some of them are, here's an entire map.
And so, I guess the thing about the graph cuts that I don't super
understand, is how do you?
I mean, are the graph Cuts something that you can do separate from
reducing the function?
Woody of the system.
So I don't think I really understand.
I mean, I understand what a graph could is in the abstract, certainly.
But in terms of the practical, definition of what it means in your
system, I'm not sure I really have a handle on it.
Yeah, I mean, the way to think about it, the way that we chose to
think about it, was you have an asset, right?
And the asset is identified by a name, okay?
And the name is often a file on disk, but sometimes not because
sometimes it's like a logical or abstract thing.
Yes.
And
sometimes it's like a file on disk with in, with some parameters.
So it's like this Shader, but also the Shader on Mars and then for
PlayStation 4 and then with the following like 12 vertex types, for
example, entry, right?
So, like you can have one file on disk, they didn't still turns into,
like, you know, 900 individual graphs got at each with different set
of input parameters.
And then, the way it works, is, you go through an extremely laborious
process of like where you had this previous like,
In a soup of just like I'm a task, I've referenced some other task
which could be somewhere over like way in the graph.
Like I'm going to go and get this object so I can get its bounding
box, right?
Like example, instead, what you do is you say, I know that the object
is a graph time, okay, I know that, that graph type declares a
specific output, which is bounding box output.
So you say, give me the bounding box, bounding box, output of the
following named graph, okay?
And so, you can still have all those dependencies but then you
You force yourself to go through this hoop of saying, I'm going to
tell you exactly what I depend upon and that thing I depend upon us
going to be a named output, but that thing created, when it ran as
opposed to just give me everything it did.
Then I'll let go through to find the one thing I need.
And so that allows you to separate the process of dirtying the graphs
versus dirtying, their individual outputs,
This is dirty and which of their dependencies have to rerun.
So I guess the way I would describe the graph cut then is, it's not so
much a graph cut as it is a more explicit version of The Links.
That's right there, by reducing the chances that two subgraphs get
merged with that.
Be a correct statement the never merge subgraphs what it does is it
reduces the cases in which there is unintentional dirtying, right,
right.
We have like graph, a and graph B.
The and graph be like the programmer who wrote, that didn't really
intend to depend on all the details of graph a but they accidentally
did.
Right.
So now be runs all the time, you can break it down to where be only
runs if like The Ballot Box of a changed, right?
So that's what you can do.
So it's almost like you're like creating explicit tunnels between
graphs rather than cutting them?
Yeah.
Or I mean, but there still is a graph.
We could produce that would represent this, would it?
Not?
Yeah.
So in theory, it's just a different graph.
But the other thing that's really important is that all of your
Graph operations.
Now can operate on those sub graphs as independent problems, okay?
Which means you can paralyze them.
So in practice, we have 64 threads that are all running graph
operations on each individual asset.
Okay.
So, all right, and then and so that's like version 2, which we have
deployed to all of our people and it does both task level and asset
level.
Caching got it and it's got significantly better performance in terms
of
incremental computation.
But the big problem that it has, which we still haven't fixed.
Is that the, the contract between the game and the Importer is still
the same.
I see the contract between the game of the Importer is you're going to
give me this thing, which is this like totally hyper optimized, like
everything connected together, all these dependencies, all figured out
thing that I could run in a retail form.
Yes, and so, that's what we're looking at for version.
3 is basically saying, like, where can we literally cut the graph like
you're not allowed
To Tunnel data from here to here at import time anymore.
And if you want to do that, you now have to do that at runtime once
those things are loaded.
So in some sense, it's kind of going back to the old Halo model for
that part of it.
We're just saying, look, there's going to be resolution that happens
load time.
We're going to pick those strategically so that they're in the places
that are least likely to affect say, the performance or the quality
level that we think is important here.
And then that will give us kind of a hybrid that we can use to sort
of, you know, find the happy medium, if you will.
Exactly.
Right.
And also like part of that is like, developing the institutional
understanding that actually like asset.
Dependencies are a big deal.
So think about that.
So think about them and like the two places you can push them safely
are you can push them safely the runtime or you can push them safely
to edit time.
If you have like a GUI tool that has like the object and the shaders
all loaded at once.
Then you can at that time, say whatever you want really?
I know the object depends on only these shaders.
So even if the artist didn't have
I put in manually like you still like have that cross asset knowledge
at a time.
Anyway, so the moral of the story which case like think like think
really hard about if you have an existing solution like what are the
choices and the trade-offs that you made?
Because if you have some good properties, you almost certainly
accepted some bad properties to get there.
And
You don't just get to pick only the good stuff, right?
Like, you are either explicitly or implicitly.
Going to create situations where your solution does not handle it.
Right?
And so, the most important thing you can do is to make sure that your
game Falls entirely in the good place and stuff.
That's not your game as elsewhere.
That's fine.
You can't build everything but like build only systems whose complex
the you can completely understand before you start.
Is of course impossible.
Well Chris, thank you so much.
That was amazing.
So almost nothing of what I talked about was actually my work.
So, a big shout-out to like Chris Hargrove, Brian Sharp, Drew card,
noguchi, Brandon Morrow.
Mike Nicola Drew Solomon.
And everybody, I forgot along the way.
Thank you guys, thank you so much.