Start recording.
All right.
Thank you very much for joining me.
Welcome to handmade hero.
Sure, we could complete game live on stream.
We are going to do a little bit, a little, a little bit of
prefetching.
Today is what we're going to be doing.
You just this past week, we put all the cutscenes in for the
introduction sequence, for our game.
And one of the things that you'll notice, if you pay really close,
attention them, which admittedly is pretty tough to do because video
stream in there and that's kind of low quality even then.
in the video on demand like the YouTube videos are pretty low quality,
so unless you actually ran it yourself at home cuz you follow along
with the source code or if you watched like, the videos that are
shipped on the handmade hero,
We have a handmade hero BitTorrent, you can access on the Forum site
where you can get like high-quality recordings if you saw those you
definitely would have seen this if you haven't then it may have been
hard to notice because it's so janky.
It looks so sort of crappy with the video compression.
Anyway, you can't maybe pick up on some of these problems but there
definitely was a problem and it was a problem that I want to leave
till the end.
So you can kind of see, I could explain a little bit and see how to
fix it.
That's what we're going to be doing today, today's day to 24.
So, if you're following along at home and you pre-ordered the game,
M, 2 or you can download the source code and follow along by using day
223 source code, that's the source code that I'm starting with here.
So let me just try and see if I can point out what the bug actually is
and I mean bug is a tough term user because it suggests that
something's not working properly when actually everything is working
properly.
So, I guess what I really mean is objectionable artifact, something
that we would like to get rid of if we can write.
So it's not really that the code is broken, but it's that the code
isn't as good as it should be, right.
And so here's what happens when we switch from this scene to the next
scene.
What I'd like you to do is pay close attention to what happens right
at the transition point.
And I talked about this on yesterday's Q&A, but just for those of you
who didn't see that, what you'll see is, there's a brief kind of
flash, right?
It doesn't just like cut cleanly from one to the other.
And so the question is like what's going on there, right?
And what's going on there is we again, use an on-demand paged assets?
Them.
So what happens is we dynamically load everything in the background
off the hard drive and especially on this with you.
This is a 7200 RPM hard drive that's going to be kind of slow.
Although it's probably mostly in the cache at this point.
But either way point being it's kind of slow to page those things in
it.
Sees it's at least going to take a frame or two of latency for the
asset systems threads to go.
Grab those other images off of the hard drive and put them into memory
where we can draw from them.
Right?
And so what we want to do is
We want to try and solve that sort of glitchy problem so that we don't
get any errors in there.
And you know, one way to solve this obviously is just to have a big
old loading screen you slap in front of everything and you just do
this whole loading thing and you waste a bunch of memory.
And blah, blah, blah.
But we don't want to do that.
No loading screens on handmade hero.
Preferably, we want everything to be instant soon as the user clicks.
It's good to go, right?
That's our preference.
And so what I'd like to do is I'd like to have an alternative to that,
okay.
So let's start by start by talking about like what that problem
actually is.
In practice here, right?
So here we go.
I'm going to try and sort of show you.
In fact you're not the best place to do.
This is probably in the debugger, right?
So let's just take a look as this will happen.
Even the very first time we do render cut seam and so here's the
problem, right?
We come into the first time we do rendered, cutscene and we have
rendered layered seen there so you can see it.
And if I step into render layered scene, we're going to go through
each layer index.
We're going to pull them out, and then we're going to see in each one
of these, we're going to see
You know what, what that bitmap actually is and you can see that we
get back the bitmap ID here and that's all working properly because
that's all stuff that happens.
Just using sort of the, if you want to enough directories right turn.
But basically the database, the table, the data table for our asset
system, which can instantly answer these queries.
So we asked me initially get back.
Oh, that's asset 251.
That you were looking for, so then we go to render with asset 251,
right?
Of course, we got to pack up some, some floats, some factors there.
And so we come in here and we call get bitmap with that ID.
Now get bitmap.
Of course, is just going to ask the asset loader for that thing.
It comes in here and as you can see, it immediately fails to actually
get it because it's not there, right?
It hasn't been loaded yet that asset state is not is not set, right?
And you can see, if you look at the state here, the state set to 0.
So it's like, okay, that's not good.
Because we can't actually get it now.
It'll go ahead and say, oh, you know, that's okay, I'll issue a
command to load that bitmap, so the bitmap will get loaded, right?
But what that means is now when this Frame goes off to render, it's
just missing that bitmap and that's the entirety of the problem right
there.
It's just that when we ask for the bitmap oak, it's like, okay, thanks
for telling me.
I got to go load that, that frame, even if we're able to have like a
really short turnaround from the drive.
That frame is going to finish rendering before the drive ever, gets
back to us with that data, right?
That's just an even.
If it got back sooner, we've already made the decision that it's not
there and we're already not going to render it, right?
So we basically have to solve that problem.
So what I want to do to solve that problem is very simple.
It's called a prefetch.
What I want to do is I want to give the assets system, a little bit of
extra time because especially in a cutscene there's really no excuse
for not doing so because you know, we know exactly what assets are
going to get used in the cutscene +.
We know exactly when they're going to get used so there's really no
excuse for us.
Not
You know, sort of like, announcing if you will to the asset system.
Hey, man, here's what you're going to need very shortly.
Get those loads in flight for me, please.
Right.
And that's really, I think all will probably have to do.
The first thing that I want to do, though is, I'd like to get this
playing back at an artificially fast rate, just so we can see it
happen a little more clearly.
Okay, so here is US advancing the cutscene at a much more rapid rate
than we would have otherwise, right?
So here is a zipping through the cutscene, right?
And you can see that blinking happening at various times, they're
right?
So that's all nice and good and you know, you can see that kind of
little Flicker and so we want to do is get rid of that little flicker.
Okay?
So to get rid of that little flicker, what am I going to do?
How am I going to do this prefetch?
Well if you'll notice, we kind of have a nice thing here where we can
just go through and say oh he render this cutscene and we give it a
cut scene time and it does some stuff, right?
And the entirety of this routine is actually very simple.
There's not a lot to it, it's all pretty easy.
There's not, you know, there really isn't a whole lot that needs to
happen there.
And so what I could do right is I could just render the cutscene twice
if I wanted to and and basically the first one that, you know, the one
that we're actually going to render can be at the current time, but
then it's pretty free for me to just render another cutscene at a
future time.
And instead of ever actually asking it to commit, those bitmaps, I
could just throw it away after that, right?
It's because basically, you know, remember we do the render group
stuff, we build up a render list and then we ask it to render it
during that build-up process is when all those load cues happen.
If at the end instead I just said, throw it away, then we would get a
pre-caching for free, right?
So that's exactly what I'm going to do.
I'm just going to create a thing here.
That's like sort of a subset of this function.
Maybe I won't call this pretty stupid anymore, but I'll say like
cupcake seeing complete, for example, like so.
Right.
And so, what I'm going to do is just say, alright, let's move this
part out here.
And there we go.
Maybe I'll return that.
And I'm going to do like render cutscene you know at time or something
like this.
I don't know what I'm going to call it.
It's basically just an internal function to the cutscene system.
That doesn't that?
No one else really needs to call?
So the name of it's not too sensitive is not going to leak out in
anything.
Hopefully and so then we'll just have exactly this function
essentially the exact same function, right?
That's just render cutscene.
Oops,
At time, okay.
And that's, you know, that's it.
So once we've got that set and I'm going to go ahead and return that
from here, cutscene complete.
Now, we're just going to take it so that it just takes an R32 there.
It doesn't take a pointer in Marquez, this one's not supposed to
modify that value.
So, now, we just have a way of rendering cutscenes at times.
We could do that multiple times if we want to, we can do as many as we
want.
And so if we do something like that, now we have the option just gotta
do reference that
Now we have the option of potentially doing it twice, right?
So this is the one that actually renders the cutscene it's free for me
to do another one here.
Where I just say oh let's go ahead and look maybe like a half second
into the future or maybe a whole second into the future, right?
And then we can render to whole cutscenes.
Now, the problem with this, if I were to just do it this would solve
our problem.
But the problem with this right here is it would actually save all of
those drawing commands, right?
And we don't actually want it to do that.
At so we have two choices.
We can either call the prefetch directly if we wanted to meaning in
rendered layered scene right here, where we do this push bitmap, we
could choose to actually have that actually switch to calling prefetch
right.
That's totally valid thing to do.
We could do that or the other thing we can do like I said is just have
a stream and throw it away and so I'm not sure which one of those
would be the easier one to do.
Here is a trick.
I'm going to try right now.
I don't know if this is a particularly good idea but let's try it.
So what I'm going to do is I'm going to pass
With my render group.
Right.
And what I'm going to do here is anywhere that the rendered group gets
used, which is just like inside the perspective statement there, I'm
going to try just saying, oh, okay.
Well let's just only say, you know, if we were going to do you know,
sort of this render group stuff, right?
So I just do if render group, then we do this stuff.
Otherwise, we will only ever.
And in fact, I can do this up here as well, right?
If we didn't have a render group will,
To a prefetch.
Now I don't know if I love this idea, but it does mean that we don't
waste any memory.
Like, you know, building up the list that we're going to throw away.
So again, like I said, I don't really know if I like that or not but
I'm just going to try that at first because it seems like the easiest
thing to do.
So I'm going to try that first and see if I like that.
So there we go, that's really it.
That's the entirety of it.
And so now all we're doing is we're calling the exact same function
twice one with a
Right.
Look ahead.
Write about a second of look ahead.
And when we do that render cutscene at time, it's going to check to
see if the render group was set to 0.
And if the render group is set to 0, it knows that it's not really
rendering.
It's actually just prefetching, right?
And so now, let's see how that works and see, if that gets rid of our
glitchy, right?
And it does, you'll notice there's no glitching anymore on.
Have you seen transitions, right?
They're all just totally set and that's because now we've given the
streaming system enough time to catch up, although I did see one
there, right at the beginning one.
And there's a very good reason for that one as well.
And we should talk about that because we do want to fix that one
although we don't care about looping.
Since we're never going to Loop the cutscene we do, we do care about
it for a slightly separate reason.
So first let me ask, do you guys know why there's one on the
beginning?
One.
Right.
And you know, if you think about it, you should be able to figure out
why we have none on anywhere except that beginning one.
So, think about that for a second, one, two three.
Okay.
Times up, the reason is because when we are looking ahead, we don't
rap.
So when we get to the end of the cutscene, it's not going to go back
to the first one because remember the code that makes it loop around
is right here and that doesn't ever happen inside render cutscene it
time, right?
So it never asks for that you know when surrendering the last cutscene
it never looks ahead into the the first cutscene, but that's actually
okay because normally we would not be looping it so we really don't
have to fix that problem.
But the problem that we do want to fix is this right here that first
time it comes up we would rather not have that happen, right?
And so I think what we want to do there is because if this is the very
first thing you see in the game there's nothing we can look ahead from
We're
Starting up, we got to start rendering.
So typically what I do because the, you know, the streaming systems
always trying to run a little ahead of everything else, but at the
very start of the program, there's no way it could be a head.
So what I usually do is basically like the loading screen that I have
if you will, he's just to give it maybe just like 100 milliseconds or
200 milliseconds of black, right.
Just like a quick little black screen on boot so that it has enough
time to be loading ahead, right?
And so, what I would say here is just say, okay, you know, we would
just do something like this where a just be like there's nothing in
this scene at all.
Like at all, at all.
I think there's a nun.
Is there a nun?
Yeah.
So there's absolutely nothing in it and there's no actual like
anything, right?
There is no, it's just a bunch of 0, right?
Something like that.
And so now we could have this thing have a duration.
So we could say, oh, when we do, you know, when we do our asset none
and all this sort of thing.
So it's 0, 0 0, and then we would put a duration here, right?
If we wanted to, we could have like a big old
In their summer, right?
Wait, a minute is that the right one for it asset opening?
Cutscene is asset none.
Then we have index, then we have a red count through intro layers.
Yeah, so I think
I think that would be correct.
Let me see if I can put a big old delay in there too, so I can make
sure it's actually there.
Oh,
right.
We're never using that one.
There we go.
So now there should be a delay in there, right?
So perfect.
We now have a delay in there and so now all we need to do is make sure
that we have enough of a delay so that it can load things, which it
should be reasonably good with I think, but we don't really know like
how long that load, how long the loading time actually is for our
assets, if that makes sense.
So let's take a look at what that would actually have to be.
I'm going to turn it back now so that it doesn't do sort of the blitz
thing that makes sense.
Let's see here.
Let us see here.
If I can manage to search for it, here we go.
So we're back to our normal time.
Then this would, of course be what 20 seconds would course be too
long.
So, you know, we'll see, I don't know, Force lowered.
It was, you know, even just one second just seems like a long time,
right?
That didn't seem like one second to me.
But I guess it was.
So now we don't get that blink at the start up because we get in the
streaming system enough time to load everything in which is what we
wanted.
And yeah, that might take some tuning.
We could also do something where we wait intentionally to make sure
that everything's loaded.
But again, that's not necessarily, you know, we don't really probably
have to do that.
We could wait a little bit longer because I don't know why it seems so
fast.
It might be that.
It's just because it takes a while to get everything started up.
But it's like, before I can even maximize the darn thing off it goes.
Under do we have a way to start up in full screen mode?
I don't remember if we do or not, I might enjoy that for the moment.
Let's see here.
Toggle full screen.
Let's see.
All right, so if I wanted to do that, I suppose after we did our
create window, I could toggle full screen on it, right?
If I wanted to.
So I could do it, like, right here.
There we go.
So, yeah.
So there's still, there's a little craftiness in that, there's that,
that white sort of annoying thing there that we see when we boot up.
And that's probably something, it would be nice to get rid of, as
well, maybe we could do that today.
But now, we've got it.
So that now, you know, once.
Explain the cutscenes.
There's none of those little glitches, right and especially when it's
playing it sort of a nice leisurely Pace here.
Then you know that you're not going to get any you know the streaming
setup systems.
Got a full second or whatever.
I look ahead, time is right, to take care of that and maybe a second
isn't as much as we should give it because it could, we could give it
a lot more than that, right?
We could give it a significantly more than that.
We could say something like.
Oh, you know,
Cutscene warmup time, right?
And we could say that that's or warm-up seconds or something like that
and then we could just use that in both places.
We could say well will show nothing for a certain amount of that and
then will, you know, will look ahead by that amount as well.
So now we know we're always have like sort of a prefetch cursor in a
regular cursor kind of running through it, right?
And hey, you know, that's going to bug me.
So I'm going to go ahead and say, let's just get rid of that.
Annoying thing to.
So there's two things that we have to do.
The first one is for our render group.
I don't know that our render group ever gets actually cleared.
I don't know that there's a clear in our in our thing.
There might be, I'm not sure, but if we do begin render.
Yeah, I don't think there is.
So what we want to do is we're going to need a thing where we clear
the render group.
Now, normally we won't have to clear it because normally
When we're rendering the scene, we don't the layers of cells like
clear it right?
You know, which we draw the whole screen so we don't have to worry.
But what would happen is if there are no layers, if it's a layer count
of zero then we have a problem, right?
So what we would want to do is say like if the scene layer count
equals zero, then we would want to make sure we issue a clear and I'm
going to go ahead and see just a leave it gray.
So we can see that it's actually
Dang it.
So there we go right?
And so that's nice because then we can make sure that we're actually
clearing to Black during our sort of blackout startup period and that
way everything is nice and nice and clean.
So there we go.
And you know it kind of starts the thing and it'll go from there,
okay?
And so now, what I want to do is I want to get rid of those that
little.
I don't like that, flicker that white Flickr.
So I need to drop back to the win32 platform layer and figure out why
that's happening right now in our wa.
I'm paint.
We do this.
Win 32 display buffer in window thing.
But you can kind of see what happens here that does.
This kind of stretch GI B thing and I've worried that we'd never
initialize that buffer.
I don't know if that's the case but I suspect we don't.
In fact you can kind of see Ho Hey look at that probably clear this to
Black.
Yeah, probably.
Right.
And so what we want to do there is when we call that win32 or size dip
section, we want to make sure that we get rid of all of it so that
it's all cleared to 0, right?
And so you
you know, I think there's
Zero memory.
Call in Windows.
I want to say there is, I don't really remember, but I think so.
Might be it might use a c runtime library though I'm not sure yeah
runtime libraries zero memory macro.
What's Phil memory?
Wait.
When we virtual Alec though, can't we ask it to give us back
something, that's cleared.
20, isn't there just a way to automatically say, hey, zero, that for
me?
I thought there was
Let's find out.
Occasion type.
Physical.
No.
Zero.
Let's see.
Reserve commits or change the memory allocated.
By this function is automatically initialized to zero, so that all
should have been 0 apparently, right?
So, in theory,
We should never actually have to clear it to Black.
It should already be black, right?
so, I'm just going to say
Note, Casey virtual Alec should only have given us back zeroed memory.
Which is all black.
So we don't need to clear it, right?
And then I'm just going to check.
I'm going to check to see if that's actually the case because I don't
know that I necessarily trust msdn all the time, it can be wrong.
It's definitely been wrong before.
Oops.
All right, so I'm going to come in through here and make sure that
buffer memory looks like what we expected to look like.
Here is a memory window.
I'm going to probably move that up here for now.
So let's take a look at what buffer memory is first of all.
So there it is.
And I'm going to paste it in here to see that looks pretty 0 to me.
I'll give it.
I'll give you that, that looks very 0.
I don't see a lot of nonzero values in there so I'll give you that.
That's pretty easy Road.
So, the question now is, why are we getting that white that sort of
white nastiness in there, right?
So we got to figure out why that's actually happening.
So when we do toggle full screen, there's a couple things that could
be happening.
First of all, I want to look at our window class because sometimes
Window class, you might end up with an H brush, that does something
that you don't expect it to do.
It looks like we're setting.
Our H brush, like H, redraw CSH redraw CSV redraw.
I wonder if we really want those as well.
I don't really know exactly what we want here because we don't really
want our we want our window to just draw black when it does anything
like that.
So I guess the other thing we could do is initialize it with a black
Brush.
So that it always did that for us whenever it repainted the window.
I really don't know.
This is one of those ones where you kind of want Raymond Chen, just
say what's the simplest set of things we can do to make sure it stays
black and never draws anything else, right?
And it's hard to know because we can't step through it.
We can step through their code in C, so, hbr background, right is one
example, and this is a handle to the class background brush.
So we could, for example, make a brush that was just all black right
and set that and see if that helped at all.
So, let's see if that helps at all, if we do hbr.
Background.
Let's see if we do hbr background, we would need.
Like I don't know how I do an RGB brush RGB brush.
I forget all this stuff.
It's been a long time but if I want to handle to a brush, that's just
that's just RGB.
Well, how do I do this again?
Let's see, here create pen.
Set PK color, so wrecked
CPK color is not really what I wanted.
I wanted an actual brush, I think get stock objects, should give one
to me now that I think about it.
This is just my memory of Windows kind of coming back kind of slowly.
There it is.
So that's what I actually just want.
It's get stock object black brush, so we should be able to say, okay
here's a black brush to use, have fun with that.
Trust me, it's an inch brush, you know.
Windows, don't worry about it.
Let's see if that helps.
Hey, look, perfect.
So now we got rid of that kind of annoying white thing there that was
kind of, I assume that was just Windows, either, not clearing anything
or clearing us to White because it thought that's what it should do.
For some reason, I'm not sure.
But now we have a really nice startup experience the user pushes run,
and it's pretty good.
There they're still occasionally.
I'll see a little bit of a window wipe their which is doesn't Thrill
Me.
And I'm not sure.
I'm going to do something more like this.
I might create the window without it being visible first, so that you
can't see it.
And then we'll create it, visible will make it visible later.
And so, I don't know if any of these set WS visible.
I don't think they do.
So when we do it,
Go full screen will then cure do show window SW show, think that's the
right command for it to like instead of having it come up as visible
with the use, default stuff.
I'm gonna first, Let It Go full screen, then show it so that you don't
see any flashing.
So that's
that's way better than it was.
All right, so that feels pretty good to me.
I think that's that's doable.
So I'm pretty happy with that.
All right.
So it's 5:30 now.
We still have another half an hour.
So we've got our cutscene playing pretty nicely here.
I think the next thing that we want to do there's kind of this kind of
you know, two directions here.
So one thing that we want to do to finish this cutscene is we'd want
to sync it to an intro soundtrack, but we don't have an interest on
track yet so that's why we're not going to go do that.
that be, you know, we could go, we fix the win32 timing code to be
nice and
Consistent.
And then we would go ahead and sink it to some kind of a time, you
know, sort of go line it up to where in the sound we wanted each sort
of cut to occur and how long we wanted each sort of Zoom thing to
take, right?
But we can't do that.
So the other thing that I think we should probably do is just pop back
to the game code now and start to sort of structure our game code in
order to have an intro cutscene, right?
Because really, we're going to need some way of having the intro
cutscene play in the gameplay and that sort of stuff.
So we need some kind of a piece of code, you know, something that sits
there and can be logical about what it is.
We're doing, are we playing the cutscene are we playing the game?
Are we doing, you know, are we in some kind of a selection screen, you
know?
Who knows what's happening, right?
So let's let's go ahead and look at that and that seems like the most
productive use of the half hour since we can't really sink to a
timeline.
We don't really have one yet.
Now, there's not much to that.
Like I said, it's pretty straightforward because we set up everything
in our handmade cutscenes thing to work that way.
So you know, if we if just to give you an idea of what we would do,
it's really simple.
All we be doing is tuning these durations.
So that instead of each thing taking 20 seconds, it takes however long
we actually wanted to take right, you know, if we once we sort of take
a look at how long the intro track is, and where we think the brakes
would?
Naturally go.
We would just literally set these values and then we could play the
cutscene and the music at the same time and we would probably be good
to go right from there.
Because again, we don't have anything here that has to be like, super
sample.
Accurate, this isn't like a beat matching game or anything, so we only
care and there isn't lip-syncing either, right?
It's just still images.
So we don't even really have a whole lot of precision concerns.
So even anywhere.
Close is actually fine.
So it's pretty easy for us to just tune those values and that's
probably all we really need to do, right.
Okay, so let's take a look back at handmade dot CPP.
And so what I want to do here I guess is I want to just start sort of
thinking about how we deal with the game itself and the fact that this
is going to be an attract mode thing.
And then somebody at some point starts playing the game, right?
And we already sort of have that concept because if you remember, if I
switch this around, right, if I switch this back so that instead of
these instead of the cutscene, we're actually doing the game itself.
We already sort of had this concept right here is our, like, here's
our screen.
Here's our hero screen.
You know, our first, you know, dummy screen or whatever and the heroes
not on it yet, right?
And the hero, in fact, doesn't show up until I actually push a key to
sort of say that, hey, I'm playing a hero now, right?
And the reason we did that, I don't have a controller right here, but
way back when it's, because you can have multiple heroes in the game,
right?
And that's not, you know, the game's not really supposed to be me.
Player.
But we want to make sure the code supports multiplayer.
Just so I can show how you make sure you can do that relatively clean
lie.
Right.
And so what we, you know what we have there is we have already the
concept that such that the game gets started right on that.
When you push that spacebar, the game gets started.
And so, what I want to do is I want to sort of turn from having it
show this empty screen to perhaps showing that, like, let that
cutscene until you start the game.
That seems like a way better.
That seems like a way better idea to me, right?
Yeah, that seems like a good thing and that will also inform how we
want to do our sort of what's the word I'm looking for.
That can also inform how we might want to do our pinging like our
prefetch from the outside because we made that may have ramifications
for like how we say oh hey start prefetching assets or whatever,
right?
So let's see.
Hmm, you're enjoying on.
That is true.
It's a bit Jani.
so what I want to do here is I want to be able to switch between these
two and so what I think I might do is say okay,
This needs to be a dynamic variable for start, right?
So it's playing the cutscene or doing whatever, but we need some way
of testing it.
Now, what I could do is say, are there any heroes in the game?
You know what I mean?
And we have a thing that's like controlled Heroes, right?
And we Loop over it too.
And we say, like, for each controlled hero, we actually see, you know,
is there an entity index for this thing or whatever?
So we could even do a thing that's like Heroes exist or
Right?
And we could say that if we find one of these ones, then the hero does
in fact exist, right?
So, we could say something like, oh, here exist equals true, if that
happens, right?
And so, if we did that,
Then we could just say o Heroes exists is the thing that we switch on.
And so then we'd start off or or not because actually you have to make
sure that your cases are going the right order.
That's good, let's try again.
Then we start off playing the cutscene right and it'll just keep
playing the cutscene until eventually We join the game and then once
we join the game, we're in the game right now.
You can see that we've got sort of another like
Like issue that we probably have to address.
This is probably not the right time to address it because the game
itself you'd want to do this.
A little later on when the game itself is kind of more of a complete
game.
Like more, when you're more like walking around, fighting some
enemies, doing a few more things where you actually have that
structure, kind of more in place rather than just a little test thing.
But the idea there is just that, hey, you need to prefetch the assets
for the game as well, because, as you can see, you know, we're in
here.
And we're kind of doing our thing and then as soon as I hit the key,
it switches and you're playing.
But the assets may not have book we loaded yet you see like a partial
screen or whatever.
So that's another thing that we would want to do but I don't really
want to mess with that yet.
I wanted to make sure it was done for the cutscenes because there's no
reason not to if the cutscenes but I don't want to do it for the game.
This early.
Okay.
So now that we've got the cutscene working and we can start enjoying
now.
We've kind of got a start, we've got to sort of think about a few more
things like how we want to deal.
Other aspects of what's going on, right?
And the reason for that is once I'm in a game, I can't necessarily get
out of a game.
Like I can't hit Escape or something and go back.
Like I can't quit right, I can't exit or anything.
So we may want to actually have a way to like exit handmade hero.
Start to think about that a little bit and I don't know.
How we want to do that.
Exactly.
But one example would be like, we have the concept of a back button.
I don't know if the back button, let me see where that was back
button.
What do we set that to keyboard wise?
I don't know.
Arrow back.
So it is a to escape.
So what we could do is when you hit the back button, you just go back,
you can just exit out of the game that way.
Right.
Let's let's see about something like that.
So, if we want to do that, what we would do is we would I guess our
entity system.
You can kind of see when we do our add player here, right?
We have no real way of undoing, any of that.
It'd be nice to maybe start to, to fix that a little bit.
So let's, let's see what we can do.
Let's see what we can do there.
So if I'm going through my controllers here,
and I,
Hit the Escape key.
I'm going to make it so that that just straight-up gets rid of the
player entirely, right?
So, if the controller
Back-ended down.
I'm going to say that the con hero
Entity and x equals 0.
And I'd like to be able to delete this entity, right?
I'd like to be able to like delete low entity.
Do we have such a thing?
I don't even know.
Because we haven't really worked very much on that part of the game.
So we've got Get Low entity.
We have like a bad player.
I don't know what that actually does is, it says it does add ground
identity, right?
And so, do we have delete entity?
Anywhere.
We have delete low entity anywhere, so we don't have any way to remove
entities but that be a fair assessment.
It appears that that would be a fair assessment.
So we would want to have a way to delete any of these to be sure.
Right.
I mean, at least I assume we do one way of doing it would be to not
ever really
Do that and to just like kind of cycle them, but so how does that
actually work here?
So we just add any of these to the state incrementally over time.
So really just a simple free list, like we've been using everywhere,
else will be totally fine here.
So instead of at, you know, allocating a new one every time, it could
just go ahead and yeah and and and and keep it free list, that seems
pretty reasonable to me.
Yeah, so let's go ahead and do that.
For the time being and we'll just say, okay, there's an index right of
that thing.
And in there we will do a little like to do, you know, actually delete
or something like this and we'll be fine.
Okay, so in theory, we're calling it and I gotta pass the game state
to that.
As well.
Okay, so now in theory, if I create one of these guys and I walk them
around, I should be able to kill him and go back to the cutscene right
and I should be able to let create them again and go and you can see
these not actually deleted right there.
He is.
And yeah so you know proof that he's still in the world and so I can
keep doing this as much as I want and make more and more Heroes.
Course, they're all like stuck in each other's Collision boxes right
now because they're spawning right on top of each other which is not a
very good thing but you get the idea.
So we're all good there.
I think so.
Now I should probably just Implement that.
Although the thing that I want to do before I Implement that is Maybe
maybe say something like if you were to try and
Exit the game.
So if you were to save this where this thing ended down,
then maybe we exit the game.
Right.
So you know, like quit requested.
Like this and then if no Heroes exist and the quit was requested then
we would say like hey that's it for the game's over.
Right stop.
And so I don't really know how we want a signal quitting.
I assume that what we'd want to do is have that be in something that
we pass back to the game to the platform code because it's the thing
that needs to do shut down, right?
And so in order for that to work, we would need to do a thing where
like
Yeah, we would need to do a thing.
We're inside the code here, there was something it could look at,
right?
So in the weren't 32 platform section.
When we're doing sort of our thing, we've got Global running.
And you can kind of see that Global running is set by some platform
stuff so we can hit alt f4 to let kill the game or whatever and that's
all good.
But
We don't really have any way of sort of having the game.
Do the quit, you know what I mean?
So, what we want to do, I think is we want to go ahead and grab that
from the game itself.
So we want to do something we're in here, as we're sort of going
through, whatever is happening at the end or rather.
After we do update and render, let's go ahead and get updates and
render groups after we call game update and render.
I
Do you want to do is say that Global running you know is going to get
set to false if you know the game indicates to us that that should
happen.
So maybe we do something like this where we say oh if if there was a
quit requested you know then we'll go ahead and do that.
Now I would probably do that here and I'd say like okay if Heroes if
the heroes exist
If no Heroes exist.
Then if equipped was requested, then I'll just say, like memory quit
requested equals true and that'll end the game, right?
I could do it like, right here, even
Something like that.
And so that's just a way of exiting out.
That means we will need some Jimmy.
In the platform layer will need some way that it can that it can sort
of signal that back.
And this is like note Casey signals back to the platform layer and so
that would be be through to quit requested and that should be fine.
I think right now I'm going to take a look and went through two,
handmade.
I just want to make sure that we when we initialize game memory that
we initialize the whole thing, 20.
And I don't know if we do, we do.
So, there we go.
So now I should be able to if I'm watching the cutscene I should be
able to quit the game.
I can I should be able to go in here.
I should be able to go back.
Boo that quit the game even though Heroes existed.
Why is that?
Why?
Oh, I see why we never give it a chance to reset the Escape key.
So it's kind of like on the first frame, it goes.
Oh I should kill this hero on the second frame.
Right it exits out of the menu entirely.
So that's a key that's going to have to be D bounced, right?
Meaning.
Like or that we have to check for it.
Going down in up again, right?
And so yeah, I feel like we would need to do more of a
I guess we could do it was pressed, that would probably be fine.
Let's take a look here.
Oops.
So, we could probably just do this, right?
We could say was pressed that
Like so.
And was pressed.
And that may be it.
So, there's regular exit.
There's two step exit and then we're good.
So at least now we can like get into the game we can get out of the
game and that gives us a little bit more of a sort of solid thing
happening there.
But of course we also don't really have any logic for our cutscene.
So, what we want to do now is I think probably have a little bit more
of a formal idea of what's happening with the cutscenes, they probably
shouldn't have, you know, something where it's just this random thing
in the middle of game State.
That's like, oh,
The cut T, cutscene right.
So I think we want to try and make the cut scene a little bit more of
a thing so that we kind of have a little bit more of an idea of what
it's doing and how and whatever, right?
So I'm going to do a thing here where I just say okay there's such a
thing as a playing cutscene
And that's going to have to Encompass, all of the information that
needs to come to be encompassed by playing cutscene.
And, of course, that's for right now.
Not going to be particularly interesting.
but, you know,
That at least gives us a place to put other things.
Should we decide that we need to do that, right?
It's true that we probably will want a little bit more information in
there because right now, actually, this stuff is hard coded as
well-meaning the shot index and all that stuff.
So we could also do another thing where we said, okay, there's also,
you know, which one of these it is so, you know, a playing cutscene
could also have something like this.
What are the scenes, right?
And, and how many are there?
then here's the tea in it so far, so that
That seems a little bit more, little bit more reasonable.
Yeah, so what I'd like to do is then say, okay, you know, we've got
playing cutscene and playing cutscene, maybe is a thing that can be
returned.
So maybe we'll do something like play Intro, cutscene
a rather get intro in Mitchell eyes.
I don't know.
What do I want to call this baby?
Just begin intro cutscene or that suggests.
There's going to be an end.
Make intro.
Cutscene not sure.
Right?
So if I do make intro cutscene, then what I can do is just say like
all this information that was there.
I'm going to bake into it.
So I say here's a playing cutscene
That's the result and I'm going to go ahead and initialize it.
So we say okay the scene count is this this count
Seems.
Come here.
The tea.
Is just zero point zero that we don't need their size that because
that will happen automatically with this, and then I'm going to return
that.
So, there you go.
So that'll make the intro cutscene.
I don't need to pass anything to it.
Really there's nothing to pass.
And so now I could actually, when we start up the game, have a little
bit more of a concrete thing that says, which is, you know, which one
of these things were playing at the moment.
Yeah.
All right so if I do that let's go ahead and now change render
cutscene instead of taking T.
Cutscene I'm going to pass in which cutscene we're talking about and
now this will be like cutscene T, right?
And
It'll look more like that.
It'll do actually.
No that's not true.
It'll just pass that straight on in, won't it?
So we'll do render cutting that time will actually take.
Yeah, well actually take both of those.
And so anyway this will actually need to be past the actual cut scene
itself.
So let's go ahead and do that.
Don't know how.
I don't know where I want that past.
That I wanted at the end.
I don't know.
Let's put it there.
It's fine.
Don't worry about it.
All right, so yeah.
Playing cutscene comes in here.
We get it passed in.
We're going to go ahead and use the things that are in that.
and,
Yeah.
And now we should be good to go.
We just have to do a little bit of cleanup work surpassing the
cutscene of course.
I always spell it differently because that's just the way I am so
render cutscene that time.
Needs to take that sin T.
Cutscene not at the beginning like so and then this of course would be
cutscene oops cut seam tea.
And there we go.
All right, so you're right.
It doesn't have
There we go.
So that seems good that all seems good.
And T, cutscene is not a member of game State.
That's correct.
Now.
So now what I want to do is where we used to have to cut scene.
I'm just going to have playing cutscene and the current cutscene
like so.
So now what I'll do is when we do render cutscene, I'm just going to
say oh hey this is the current cutscene.
And what I want to do now is just to initialize that right?
When we are have not been initialized yet.
Then what I'm going to do is say, oh hey, yeah, when we initialize the
game and I need you to make that be an intro cutscene right?
Alexa.
Before.
And if I current cutscene missing type specifier into Sumo C++ does
not support default.
And
Yes.
Well, you know, I mean what do you want from me?
I didn't Define it because it was in here and, you know, it just
didn't have the chance.
So, there you go.
You know, no need to worry, no, need to freak out compiler.
All right, so we're going to do a render cutscene here.
This is just game State current.
Cutscene
XO T, cutscene, not a member of game State.
That's unfortunate of course, but not really a problem because we can
just do like, Advanced cutscene I guess with something like this.
Now, there is a nastiness here, there is a thing that's kind of
annoying.
And that is by doing it this way.
We do kind of make it a little harder on ourselves because these are
not going to be hot loadable anymore because they might move if that
makes sense.
So, that's kind of annoying, and I don't know if we want to do
anything to try and fix that.
We don't really have to because we could always make them be in the
function themselves.
So there's there's ways we can get around that, but it's worth noting
that, that may cause us a bit of a problem future.
And we'll have to see
About it.
Just in terms of the hot loading of the code since, you know, we baked
it.
It's not clear that that's going to matter too much because we're not
going to be probably fussing with as much, but it's worth noting.
That that is a little bit of a problem.
And so, you know, that's just a limitation of the fact that we don't
get much support from C4 our heart loading.
So we can't have stuff like the, the data, you know, get munched
properly.
It's it's just a bummer but that's the, you know, the reality of it.
So anyway so then we just need a way to like Advanced cutscenes and
time right?
Again just I had hard coded this but now just making it a little more
formal so that we kind of can have multiple cutscenes.
Want to and they're not all kind of baked in.
So here's cutscene, here's DT.
So cutscene t plus equals DT is all that's going to do nothing this
point and now we should be back to normal, right?
So now again we can we can go in, we can come back out and of course,
what's going to be problematic here is
When we go into the game like that and come back out, the cutscene
won't restart and presumably we probably wanted it to.
We probably will want like a little title screen at some point and
we'll probably want to restart the cutscene like.
So we show the title screen for a couple seconds and then we start the
cutscene or something like that.
I don't know exactly what we want to do but it'd be something like
that.
But right now what will happen is instead you know, if we let this go
right, like I wait for a little while you can kind of see the the
welcome sign right?
Kind
Flowing off to the right there.
It you know, it's now almost entirely gone as it kind of comes around.
So if I go into the game and now come back, you can see that's where
we start again, right?
So we don't really want that, you know, we want the ability to restart
instead of it sort of saving that state because presumably, that's
what we would want to have happen.
And so, in order to do that, what we'll need to do
Wait, you know, I should do.
We break that we did this one.
Make sure all the forest still worked.
We verify
So what we want to do is we want to be able to restart the cutscene
whenever we you know kind of come back.
You know, whenever we start the game we want to we want to make sure
we reset that cutscene right.
And so in order to do that we need some notion of like when we
transition.
And so that's the problem.
Like this is a very clean way to do it because it means that there's
never really going to be any kind of conflict about.
There's never really going to be any issue with accidentally you know
game getting thinking that it's in the game and it's not or thinking
that there's Heroes when they're not but we don't really have any way
of of knowing
That we transitioned from a state of playing cutscenes to state of not
played cutscenes.
And so that's the next thing we should do.
But at this point right?
The five-minute warning so don't want to start it on that yet.
Since I got to go a little early tonight.
Anyway I feel like what I rather do is just go to the Q&A now so that
we can get any questions that there might be and then we can start on
some of that stuff tomorrow.
So let me go ahead and move it to Q&A.
There we go.
Insofar as with adding a block until loaded style function, be a good
idea to make sure even lower computers have all the layers loaded
before the scene starts.
Yeah.
Potentially it depends what you want to optimize for, right.
And we already have one.
So if we want to do that, there actually is one of those.
It's it is
Where is it?
Handmade render group.
It's this.
Right here.
So, if you wanted to, for example, like what we could do, in fact, we
could do this right now is, let's let me just just to show you how
that's done, and we could do it.
We could leave it this way.
It's not a bad idea to just do.
So if we do it like this, right?
And we don't have a glitches because we're doing our prefetches
prefetches.
Yay!
For us.
Right.
Well, if we were to turn off the prefetches to simulate like a
superstar,
Computer or something, right?
So if we turned off the prefetch, which is here,
we'd be back to glitch land, right?
So now we see those glitches happening.
You know, if we wanted to turn this glitches into pauses,
What we could do instead is just not render.
Any time, we sense that there aren't any of those that there aren't
any assets that there are any assets missing, I guess what I'm trying
to say.
And the way that we would do that, right as we just say like oh okay.
You know, in here when we do tiled render group to Output we could
instead do like, okay, just take a look and say if all assets present
right then do the render otherwise don't.
And so now what it would do is it go like, okay, well, you know, now
there's a little like hiccup each time but it's really brief, right?
And so, that's totally, you know, a fine thing to leave in there and
maybe that's
We want, right?
And then you can also see like when I do, for example, if I do
spacebar you can kind of see that with the exception of our ground
tiles which page in as a separate thing.
And that's kind of a different issue when we hit that spacebar.
That thing also, we'll just wait until it's ready as well, so we can
totally do that.
That's a, that's an easy thing to do and probably it can't hurt.
Right, probably.
So we could just leave that in there and then once we put, you know,
our our prefetch
Back in then there's no hiccups and if you should have fall if you
know, for some reason it did fall behind it.
Be okay, you know, that'd be okay.
So yeah.
I'm going to go ahead and take out that times 10.
Isn't there a way to clear the back buffer using Cindy?
Yes, although it is not necessarily faster.
You have to test it to see.
Rep, rep instructions are often quite fast and so I don't know what
we're using at the moment, but Cindy's not always the fastest way to
clear, if I remember correctly but sometimes it is since, in that
case, we really don't have to worry because clearing we only do it in
the case where we don't render anything.
We don't really have to care how slow the clear.
Is that the moment I'm probably we never will have to.
Would be my guess.
Will there be any animated?
Cutscenes are just zooming shots.
Just doing shots, unless you count the, the like to frame for the
Santa putting the hat on.
Can you do a clock?
Sure.
15350 for
Would it be possible to fade from the desktop to the game's initial
black screen?
Yeah, you can, if you want to I'm not a fan of Fade to Black.
I don't really like Fades so much unless you are trying to do them for
a very specific reason.
You know, if you watch a movie there are very few Fades they're only
employed in very specific like Fades and wipes are used very sparing
in any modern cinematography, right?
You know, you think you think wipe you start to think of like 1970,
right?
And so Fades, you know, are definitely still employed wipes, very,
very wipes less.
So, but Fades are still employed for certain emotional effects, but in
this case, it's not necessarily one.
It, it's not probably what I would expect.
A fade in.
Maybe I don't know if I would want to fade it or not.
But but in terms of, can you do it?
If you do want that effect, you could.
And the way that you do that is, you would try to get the contents of
the desktop background or you'd put up a layered window first and Let
It Fade Out.
And, you know,
Yeah, I don't really know.
I mean, let me, let me try and sketch the idea out for you, I guess,
because it's not super easy to explain but I can try to kind of give
you what the idea is and and don't do it.
Exactly the way I'm doing it here.
But, you know, so if I were to do a fade out right here and make a
thing here, that's just like internal void Fade Out.
Then, what you would do, right?
Is you take one of these windows.
And you do exactly what we did to the main window.
So you'd say, okay, you know, I'm going to make this window on to make
it the size of the whole screen.
And off we go.
Now, I probably also need to.
I need that window class to be something else, so I'm going to have to
make one of these here as well.
Although I might
I might.
I might be able to do it without one.
Well, they'll do it anyway, right?
All right.
So if we have here, you know, here is our thing of this.
And this.
And that.
So I'm going to say like, you know, we're going to fade this thing
out.
I'm going to pass my instance in.
We don't really speak to need to, but we might as well.
You can get it by calling, get module handle zero.
Pro tip.
So anyway, if we do this we create a window Joe fullscreen.
What we would do is say oh you know what, give us something that's on
you know over the whole screen might be the easiest way to do it.
I'm just trying to think of the one that's the most likely to work
most of the time because there's a lot of different ways.
You could do this, you could try to capture the thing and drawn in
your window.
But this might be the one that's works the best because it doesn't
require you to try and capture which could be unreliable, depending on
the operating system, where
This would probably work from XP forward, I don't know.
So I'm going to sketching it out here.
Your mileage may vary.
It's not something I would really recommend shipping in a game for a
particular reason.
But you know, if you really want to do it you know, here's a way to
try, guess is what I'm saying?
So then, you know, we could just do a thing where we said, like, okay,
we want to do an update layered window on this thing.
So, here we go.
Are we going out like so, and you can see this update layered window
function is, you know, it's something that allows us to, you know,
call the operating system and tell it to update this sort of window
that's going to be translucent.
In fact, it's the thing that we do for this and I covered it on stream
before when we did the thing where we made our window translucent so
you could see behind it.
I don't know if you remember, we did that as a long long time ago like
it
Episode 30, or something.
We did it.
And so, if we want to do that here, right?
We could do something where we do you know what else we might be able
to do.
Well, okay, and I'm gonna I'm gonna stop.
Stop talking about, I don't know.
Maybe we even still have update layered window in here.
Do we know we know.
So again, I would just need to call this.
You can see what we've got here for docs.
So we want to pass the window handle that we're trying to update,
right?
Which is this guy
We want to pass a DC here for the screen and I think I don't actually
know.
So if HTC does handle to a DC for the screen, this handle is obtained
by something.
No man calling the function.
Calling what function it is used for pal.
Color matching when the window, contents are updated.
If HCC is null, the default palette will be used, which is this is
probably all fine.
We probably don't need, either of those HTC's.
I'm guessing I handle to a DC for the surface that defines layer
window, create pedal DC.
So we could, we could do both of those at zero potentially the new
size of their window size, not change, we could do null.
So, all of these we can probably do, you can probably do with no, I
think.
Ink.
I think.
Let's see, ya.
So I think we can do these with no.
So let's try that first and we'll see.
So I'm just going to pass zero for this.
HDC I'm going to pass zero for both of these, right?
And this and that.
And then I need to do the color key, the P blend and the DW Flags.
So the color key
I don't think we care about this.
So, the code recent compositing.
Larry, I don't think we care about that because we're not actually
going to use it because our the blend function is got to tell it not
to use that basically.
So I'll just
Put in some random thing here.
So there's the color key.
Now we need to blend function.
Will it blend?
And then we need to flags.
And so the way we're going to do it is we're going to do U LW Alpha,
which is telling it to do an alpha composite operation.
And I'm sorry, I'm kind of flying through this.
It's just cuz it's the certainly not really part of handmade here,
obviously.
But I'm going to do alpha level 0, Alpha levels less than 255 like
Alpha level plus plus or something.
So we go through all the ranges of it or whatever.
And so then we just need to specify the how we want to blend our
window on top of stuff.
You know, I'm saying?
So if we do that, we just have to say, okay?
Lend Upland flag stress concept of alpha format, right?
So let's start with the blend up.
And then we got to specify the blind Flags.
Then we got specify, the source constant Alpha.
Then we got do the out format.
Okay, so the blend up.
Let's say the only source cessation of an operation that has been
defined is AC Source over so hey not like a lot of options.
There blend Flags, can't be set.
So hey that's great specifies.
An outrageous use for the entire source bitmap so this is just going
to be our Alpha level, right?
That work incrementally over time.
Then we have an alpha format, which is showing the way it's our
sisters are interpreted.
Al format has a value AC Source Alpha by setting the alpha Channel.
Okay, so we don't actually have enough a channel.
I wonder if we can just set this to zero which means the red green
blue channels.
Must be multiplied for example, if your chance so is that the only one
they do?
When the alpha format member is AC Source Alpha, The Source, it must
be 32 bits as if it is not the official fail.
So I'm going to set that to zero.
I hope so because we don't actually want it to have any Alpha.
I don't know if we can or not though.
So this makes fails spectacularly.
Well, I got about five minutes left before I got to go so we'll see if
we can get it working.
Yep.
Oh, that's going to Loop forever, isn't it?
Area.
Okay.
yes, so Fade Out
Let's see, so Fade Out.
I'm going to do a sleep.
I'm going to do a one second sleep here.
So we'll start out with 50 and go to 255, and it'll just sleep for one
second in between Cycles.
So we'll see if that does anything.
So you can see I'm not getting anywhere with that.
So, I'm not actually seeing my window.
So I think I may have to pass more stuff to this.
I may not be allowed to do what I did here unfortunately which is
really too bad because I would have liked it to work but presumably it
didn't.
So let's take a quick look just here get last error.
See what it didn't like.
Okay, so error is 0.
Hmm.
That's kind of odd.
We should have gotten an error.
Presumably right.
Because we're not seeing our window show up at all.
Which is kind of odd because we know it's there.
And we know it's on top.
I wonder if we have our spy plus plus installed.
We do, right?
It's here.
Here's our Fade Out window class and highlight.
Guess let's take a look at it.
Yeah, it's the whole screen so that's all correct.
See, I don't know what's wrong with that.
Like I said, it may be that you can't pass that many zeros to update,
layered window, and expected, actually do anything.
I was hoping to abuse it.
So we wouldn't actually have to draw anything, but maybe we do have
to.
Let's take a look because the HDC
Porter service by the new screams earlier, window of the conversation,
not changing, it can be null, this can be.
Now that can be, no, this can be known as well.
So how does the color the CR key get used ever?
I was wondering.
Yeah because we're not using that so it shouldn't matter what we set
that to so that should all be good.
Yeah.
So I don't know, we may have to take a look at this sometimes when I
have a little more time because like I said you should be able to do
this, it's how this thing works.
But you may have to actually update the contents of the window is the
problem.
And yeah, and I don't actually know how to do that, part of it.
Now it could be that we just need would need to clear it to Black.
I guess I could get stock object that
But I don't think that's that's not how these tend to work.
The this is the thing that gives it the data.
And so I'm I suspect that this that this is not a sufficient if that
makes sense.
So yeah, so what I could do, maybe
yeah, let me just let me take one more.
Look at this to see if there's anything I can quickly.
Do that would give us one of those that would work.
That's not useful.
Table of coops, that's not good.
Table of contents.
That I can look at.
Let's just go update, weird window.
Yeah, I don't know if I want to look at any of these.
They might not be what I want, but
Yeah, so see, you can see here this is doing like our stuff to create
like our DC.
Look the same way that we were doing it and then they pass the full
thing in.
And I know that works.
That's how the other thing works.
So well.
I mean I guess it's not, it wouldn't be too hard to Surly do that.
I mean, we could if we wanted to use our resize dip section thing,
right?
Maybe we could make that work.
So, something like this.
And this would do that for us.
I think, right?
So we'd say like, oh, okay, create a dip section that we could use.
We have to do a creek credible, compatible DC, as well, which I guess,
I don't know.
So, that'd be like a client rekt, get client wrecked.
So here's our width and height.
There we go.
So then we'd have a dip section which we could draw two if we wanted
to.
And we could also do a thing where we then created all of our DC s.
So the screen DC would just be, like, get DC 0 I assume.
And our d.c.
Our DC is just going to have to be compatible d.c., right?
Yeah, this is going to take too long, there's no way I'm gonna be able
to finish this in time because I'm already one minute over.
All right, here's the deal.
We will do this on Monday because it's not that hard to do.
And we will just do it on Monday and I'll try to think over the
weekend, what, the easiest way to would be to just get to do black
because I feel like we shouldn't have to create an actual whole DC set
up to just put the black window over there and make it fade in.
So I'll think about if maybe there's a better way to do that and if
there is, we'll go with it, all right?
I'm going to shut it down.
I said I got to go.
So yeah.
Thank you very much for joining me for another episode of how many
here.
It's a recording with you, as always, if you want to follow along the
series at home, you can always well, you can always go to handmade
here a.org and pre-order the game because come to the source code.
So you can follow along at home.
There's also Forum site.
You can go to if you want to ask questions.
There's a patreon page wants worth of video series and a tweet Baht
which went down when they shut down our server.
But I restarted it.
And so in theory, it should be tweeting again starting next week.
So sorry about that, but I'll check that yeah, one of these days.
I'm going to go bother to find where the actual startup script is on
that particular server, so that when it reboots, it will actually
start my tweet.
But again, what can you do?
All right, so I'll be back here Monday and you can check that
tweetbot, which I will make sure it's working in a weekend if you want
to know the schedule.
Probably five, again, I'll be back here, Monday until then, everyone
have fun programming and I'll see you on the internet.
Take it easy, everyone.