Start recording.
Okay.
Hello everyone and welcome to handmade hero.
The show where we Kodak entire game from scratch using nothing, but
our bare fingers never toes.
No engines.
No libraries.
No nothing.
It's from scratch here on handmade here.
That's the way we do it and that is the way we have done it since day
one.
No reason to stop.
Now.
If you are one of those fine individuals who have pre-ordered the game
on handmade hero dot-org, you can go to the link that you got in your
email and download the source code.
I'm you want that link keeps on working.
It's the gift that keeps on giving frankly.
And so if you want to follow along with today's stream and you do not
know how to do that, and you're just like, what's going on here.
It's really simple.
All you got to do is extract the day.
47 zip, this one.
We're on 48, run, j48, right now, so extract that day, 47 zip into a
directory and then also unzip.
The if you want to use our assets that come with it, that's a
separate.
So if I could download and unzip into the data directory,
And that allow you to be like exactly where we are right now.
So you can follow along with everything I do at home.
It's kind of like one of those shows on PBS where, you know, the guy
paints and you're supposed to paint along with them and you have no
idea like, why he's, you know what he's doing exactly.
But then it turns out to be some kind of weird cherry tree at the end
or something, right?
And it's fine.
All right.
So without further Ado, let's get back to where we were yesterday,
which was very deflating because I was just
Out to finish some code and we had to end the stream because the
stream is over.
So let's take a look at what was going on there.
If you remember we had our little dude here, right?
And we were about to do some Collision work with him.
And we wanted to be able to have him run into the walls properly.
You can see he sticks on the walls right now.
And so what we need to do is we need to fix that.
We wanted to make a good Collision thing, so that we'd be kind of all
set to go.
All right.
So, how do we do that?
Well, we started writing something.
I was sort of teaching.
Collision detection in baby steps and so we were going down each
individual baby step and we got to the baby step of how to test
against just simple walls.
So just as a point like a moving point versus one horizontal or
vertical wall, and we wrote the equations for that and we solve them
and then we didn't quite get a chance to actually ever write the loop.
So that's what we're doing today.
All's we got to do is write that Loop and then at least we can have
some decent Collision.
Now, we've got other
Stuff that we want to do after that to make our Collision detection, a
lot better, but that's the first thing that we need to do.
Just as our baby step before, we can really talk about what to do to
make it better.
So let's do that.
Because right now, frankly, the Collision in this engine is awful.
Well, we don't really have an engine, but the Collision in this app is
awful and it shouldn't be off.
What should be good.
So, here we go.
What we have decided to do is take the place where the player was.
And the place where the player will be if he is unobstructed.
So the two points where he's going from, where is going to?
We have figured out all of the tiles that would be involved if we just
made a rectangle using that that span basically we're going to walk
through each of those tiles.
And if any of those tiles has a wall like if it's if it's marked as
solid then we are going to test against all four of the walls.
We're then going to take whatever the soonest Collision would be with
one of those walls and keep that as the earliest
And point that will tell us where our player will stop if he's going
stop.
Now.
We've pre initialized the minimum intersection time 1.0 which is
basically all the way to the new position.
Zero would be standing where we are.
1.0 would be all the way to the new location.
Right?
We've pre initialize it to 1 point 0.
So that every time through the loop, when we check to see, whether
we've gotten a better Collision than what we had before, if it's ever
above 1.0, meaning it would be past where we would actually want to
end.
If the guy
I could move all the way to where you want to be.
We just won't even consider it so that kind of or any pre takes care
of all the Collision stuff that would be past the place where we would
end because obviously we don't care about collisions that happen after
we get to where we were already going.
And again, we'll fill our solution.
When we ever when we do ourselves, will still get those things that
are off there because we're figuring out the time.
We're doing a salute solve for the time at which you would Collide,
and that time is not bounded by anything, so it could say, oh, in 10
minutes, you'll end up down and hitting this wall and it's like, well,
great.
Thanks, but we're not gonna, you know, we're not trying to take a
10-minute time step.
So that's how that those things get eliminated is by setting this team
into 1.0, which is the full motion that can happen.
All right.
So what we do here is we first start out by saying, we going to do
each individual individual Collision detection, from the perspective
of the tile that we are checking.
So we take the tile that we're checking and we subtract away the the
the player position, right?
From that tile.
So we can actually do it in one of two ways.
We can do it, where we have the player is the we can have the vector
going from where the player is.
How should I say this?
We can have the where the player is be relative to the tile or we can
have the tile be relative to the player.
And I think what we want to do here in this case is just make it so
that the player is relative to the tile.
So we're taking the Tile Center and we're talking about the position
of the player relative to The Tile Center.
So, basically, the relative thing for that is going to be, we'd want
to do it this way.
We'd want to subtract the tile position, right?
We'd want to
Subtract the tile position from the player position which would give
us a vector from the center of the tile out to where the player is.
Okay.
We then also have this, the player Delta Vector, which is pointing in
the direction of travel and that, that player, Delta Vector is exactly
as long as the total distance.
We want to travel to check basically the entire move, we would do this
time step if we were an obstructed.
So we go ahead and say, okay, we get that relative.
New player P, that's relative the center of the tile and now we have
the locations of the walls relative to the center of the tower as
well.
I mean Corner Max corner, right?
So now we need to do is test all four walls and take whatever the
minimum Z is.
So let's just test one wall for starters, right?
And I guess I've already kind of started with that here.
Right?
I said, test wall and I was going to pass the various parameters for
it.
So what I need to do is I need to write a function that will basically
update this for each wall, so that we can test the four different
walls of a tile.
So I'm going to write it in place, first for one wall and then I'll
pull it out into a function.
We can call once for each wall, so that we don't have to type the same
code four times, right.
Assuming that I can, we'll see, you know, maybe it's too hard to pull
out and I'm like a macro who knows.
We'll see.
Okay, this should be minimum T.
I don't know where Z came from there.
Okay.
So here was our equation, Artie results.
Meaning the, the T along that the percentage along the player, Delta
Vector, that we would have to go to intersect a particular walls x
coordinate at an x coordinate.
So, while an x-coordinate remember is a vertical wall, right?
So at the x coordinate of the wall, we care about, right?
We want to subtract whatever the players x-coordinate is, and then we
want to divide by whatever the Delta x coordinate is.
So the X offset that will give us the tee, at which we would arrive
there.
We then want to check the bounds of that thing.
And in order to check the bounds of that thing.
We then have to figure out where the other component would be.
Right.
So, where would the, why be right?
Well, we know where the Y would be, the Y is just going to be that.
Result whatever that t result is.
However, far, the T result was, right.
It's just going to be that times that player, Delta Vector is why,
right?
Because remember, I can do an entire Vector, T result times, the
vector equals how far along that Vector, I've gone.
And in this case, I only care about the Y.
So I'm just going to use the Y component of it and save myself the
trouble, right?
It's going to be that.
That's how far he would move along that tea, and we've got the new
players x-coordinate here.
So you players.
Y coordinate here, right?
So we can go ahead and do that so we can go ahead and add that.
And this is how far he would have gotten total.
Right?
The new y-coordinate is going to be his old y-coordinate and what, you
know, what, why is this new player P.
That's not right at all.
That should be old.
We want to where you started from.
Its old player P.
I don't know why.
This is, why is why is that knew?
Who did that?
Who snuck in here?
I'm sure obviously it could not have been me.
Somebody has.
Been into the code base and and put in the wrong variable.
How dare they?
Those people will be will be found and severely
Alright, so here we go.
We solve for that.
T result.
We find out what the new Y is and now we just need to see whether that
Y is within the bounds.
That would be valid for this wall because the wall is not infinite.
It's between, you know, two things.
So we want to say basically that if that new Y is greater than or
equal to them in Corners.
Why?
Right?
Then it's definitely above the minimum bound and if the Y is less than
Or equal to the max Corners.
Why?
Then it's within that maximum bound of the tile, know what this test
walls doing there.
So if it's in there, then this is actually valid.
And if it's valid, then what you want to do is check that team in.
So we want to say if T Min is greater than T result.
Then that means this is a closer Collision than we've had before
right?
Excuse me.
And you know, we could check this first since it's a simpler test.
If that team in is greater than T result, then that means
Then the T result is a closer collision.
And so, we should accept it.
Right?
So we should accept it.
And well, I certainly accept it assuming that the, the wall exists at
that point, right?
So that's really all we need to do.
But there's a catch and I talked about it on the last dream.
Don't know if you remember.
What's missing here.
Does anyone remember what's missing?
Remember.
Remember, what's missing remember?
Okay, I'm just gonna assume that you remembered in the Stream is right
now, filled with people saying, the thing that you are all remembering
when we do this computation 40 result, right?
We are going to get the intersection of essentially, the whole line
that the player is traveling along with that wall, which means he
could go backwards and hit the wall which we don't care about.
So, what we want to do is also say, well T result has to be greater
than 0 to begin with, right?
If T result is not greater than zero to begin with.
Then we're not going to we're not going to count this as a cliche
because that means the guy had to go backwards in order to hit it and
we don't we're not going backwards.
So that doesn't count.
So were strictly interested in collisions between 0 and 1, that's
where we want to be.
And so, so that's what we're checking for.
So, assuming that we got that we will then stop.
So, which wall did we Collide against here?
Right?
Well, so if we took wall X to be, oops, it's not, it's not
accidentally hit page up.
If we're assuming that we were going to test against, let's say our
Max Corner X, right?
So max Corner X testing would basically give us
Excuse me.
Got an itch.
Would basically mean that we can test against the right wall of
anything, right?
So that's going to be, could go test that after it.
All right.
So now we have one more thing and I don't know if when I said what's
missing, you guys remember this as well, so I'm just going to come.
With it.
We again harped on it yesterday.
This guy right here.
What's going on with this guy?
Right?
What is the deal here?
People?
This might be small.
It might be so small.
In fact, it could be zero and what would happen if we were to divide
by a very small number or zero, we would get a disastrous results.
Zero, of course would cause the FPU to actually put like an invalid
value in there.
Or if we divide by a very, very, very small number of this will end up
being huge.
That's not such a big deal because it will immediately get thrashed by
this.
The basically we got to make sure this guy isn't zero at the very
least, right?
So we got a check to make sure that player X is not equal to 0 because
if it's equal to zero, it's Bad News Bears now.
Fortunately if I were the sort of person who ever remembered
All the weird rules for, like, what happens in the SSE registers Nu
divided by zero, it's possible that this is one of those routines
where it would just work, right?
Because if you could guarantee that t, result would always be greater
than 1.
In the case, where this was Zero, we'd actually be fine, right?
Because this check would nullify it, but I don't know, right?
So, I'm just, I'm not going to leave that to chance at the moment.
And if we really care about it down the road, when we're doing
optimizations, we
Go read the manual, and figure out, whether this is a safe divided by
zero Zone where we could like, turn off / 0, exception and just let
stuff rock out.
You know what I'm saying?
Like one of those concerts where everyone gets backstage, you know the
ones I'm talking about anyway, so basically that is all we really need
to do to test against one wall.
Modulo bugs that I may have coded in there while I was gagging.
So in theory, we should be able to test against one wall.
Now.
While we are moving around, so I guess we're only testing its this
wall.
And so you know what?
I just realized though.
We're going to have to actually enable this case which we didn't yet.
That's that's what we actually want to do.
There we go.
Okay, so we got some compiler errors.
X is not a member of tilemap difference.
That is actually true.
This is so that's its Rel.
That's what I wanted.
Rel already made that into a V2.
There we go.
So no, who knows what'll happen now?
Okay, so we're not in good shape.
It's true.
Oh, well, that's just because I forgot to actually move the dude.
Sorry, dude, I forgot to actually move them.
In the case where, you know, because basically what happens here,
right is we set these sorts of things like whether you Collide it and
that sort of stuff, right?
And then we did some updating stuff here depending on the situation
and all that sort of stuff.
So what we got to do here, I don't even, I don't even know what what
was this even supposed to be?
Abs, if called P absolute X is less than entity P.
AB style x r equals.
And so then what do we do with the our we just, okay.
So this was basically, this was our wall, this, this reset the
velocity.
So we're going to have to do something similar to that with the
But for right now, we don't really care too much about that.
So we'll do that in a second.
But this is basically the problem that we need to solve right here.
We need entity P equals new player P and we haven't done that yet.
So, basically, what we need to do is we need to actually make our new
player P.
Dot offset code.
We want that too.
Actually.
Yeah, we don't even want that to be happening the way that it's
happening up here.
Really?
This is all this is all kind of not not good.
We're going to, we're just going to, you know, we're going to do.
This is what we're going to do.
We're gonna move all this craft into here and then we're going to say,
all right.
This is the actual stuff that we actually want.
So we've got our player Delta that can be computed stably.
And then what we want to do is say okay when we actually have the
player, Delta we need to recompute the velocity still, which is this
guy here, but we don't really know what's going to happen to that.
Exactly.
I guess we kind of do.
We could do that?
So it depends we have to talk about the order of operations there.
Later, when were finessing this but that's mostly right.
And so what we want to do now is actually move this stuff down there.
So we've got our player Delta and we've got that stuff.
Computed.
But now in this case, what we're going to do is we're actually going
to go ahead and do that update in a slightly different way.
Instead of doing it the way we're doing it before we're now going to
multiply that Delta vector by whatever our minimum intersection was.
And so that way if we hit something, we will only go as far as the
thing we hit because that team in will have been set to whatever that
closest thing we hit was in here.
And if
Nothing gets hit, then we'll just use 1.0, which will step us all the
way there.
Right?
Which is what we wanted.
So basically that's that's that's it.
And then I can do the actual update move which is here and we'll just
have to deal with velocity in a second once we're ready for that.
Okay.
So we've got a new player P AB style X.
Being a complaint here.
That's because this should, this is all just this is, this is all.
Oh, okay.
That's all right.
So, never mind.
I guess.
I did meet a new player P.
Guess, I did need new player pee.
Because I need to actually test against that AB style X.
I apologize, new player P.
I guess, I thought I had more than I thought.
I was.
Well, maybe I didn't, I could just on that by accident.
I don't actually know that past Casey, was smarter than future Casey,
in this particular case.
All right, so we've got a new player P and, and it's actually
There we go.
It's actually being computed there.
And now down here.
I just have to basically we do this a different way, right?
I just have to redo it to be the new the new way.
Alright, so at least you can still move.
So we know that our team in equals 1 when we don't hit anything as
working.
So let's see what happens when we go here.
Perfect.
That's actually exactly.
Right?
And we should be able to walk straight on through this wall, right?
Yeah, that's hilarious.
I can't get back in because there's walls on that side.
Oh, no, my guy is trapped in the wilderness.
Help him.
Oh awful.
Alright.
Well.
That was a mistake.
I admit that I admit that.
So that's exactly what supposed to do.
Let me rerun it again because I want to show you one thing first.
Just so we're all clear on it.
So you'll notice that that he is able to enter penetrate the wall now
and that's because we're only checking his one base point, right?
This is a point versus.
Well, it's a line but it's the motion of a point versus a wool.
So we're only checking that one point.
That's his sort of Base point, right?
So you can see that so interpenetrates.
So one of the things that we're going to do is expand him to a area
shape.
In a bit so that we can, we can Collide against that.
But, for now, I just want to point out that that's why that's happened
to so everyone understood what's going on there.
And like, don't go don't do this, don't ever do that.
Do not walk out of there until we implement.
The other one are we're in trouble.
We can do this with impunity.
Probably.
Can we know we didn't.
That didn't work very well.
Either that just got I'm totally stuck now.
Yeah, so we got to go ahead and fix all the rest of this stuff because
we're bad news here.
If we don't put the rest of these walls and we're going to have guys
ending up, stuck in things all over the
All right.
So all we really need to do now is turn this into something that tests
all the walls.
So I'm going to pull this out into a function and see if I can just
functionalize functionalize it, right.
So I'm just going to go ahead and say, all right.
I've got this this guy here.
It's going to be test wall.
I'm going to call it.
It's going to do this stuff and we're going to see what we can do in
terms of making this usable.
So, let's assume that I pass, did, I leave I left.
It all in there, right?
Yeah, good.
So basically, we want to pass this the wall X, right?
And this case, it could be an ex or oh, I we want to plas the, the
player Delta X, right?
And these are actually just going to be like, wall.
I guess.
Well, expired out the Xposed.
Even like that.
Third out to X.
This will be the relex.
So we got to pass the relex as well.
And then we got that and then we need the
Or Delta y as well, there we go.
And notice we're not passing this as a vector.
There's a very good reason for that.
I don't put real here first.
The reason for that, of course is because we don't actually know if
these are x's and y's.
They could be inverted because well, you'll see in a second because we
want to call it for both ways.
We want to call it for y, intersections and X intersections, right?
Okay.
And so then I've got my rail why as well?
Right?
Well why again, I don't know which sense those are that I got
Mighty results my team in.
So then we got a team in is the thing we're updating and then we got
our Min Y and our Max y, right?
So we got our Min Y and our Max, why?
Okay, and that'll do the wall test.
So, what is the problem here?
Team in needs?
There we go, so they can be updated.
And so now I just need to call this, right.
I just need to call this with the same things I was.
Calling it with before.
So, in this case, I call it with wall X and and that's going to be Max
Corner X.
There we go.
I've got my relex, and my rail, why.
And then I've got the player, Delta X and the player Delta y, right?
And then I've got my team in.
And I've got my Min Corner.
Why?
And my Max Corner why, right?
And that is my test.
There it is.
Now.
What I can do is I can just Spam this, right?
I can spam this out and say, alright, let's test the other ones.
So now let's test them in corner X as well, right?
And to do that.
All, I have to do really is change this because it's exact same test.
It just gets a different coordinate.
And then if I want to test the Y, right all I have to do is
That and flip, the things that I was passing, right?
I just flip them because it can just basically do them in the opposite
way.
That it was doing before and that should test against all the walls of
the thing.
If I'm not mistaken, could be mistaken.
Who knows?
We'll find out in a second, won't we?
So there we go.
That hit that wall, hit that well that hit that Willow.
I spoke too soon.
We are missing a wall which wall are we missing people?
So we're missing the WiMAX wall.
So there is a typo somewhere there.
That would be Max Corner .y, real X.
Ro why?
Delta X where Delta right Min Corner x, max Corner, X team in.
What?
What did I type in wrong there?
I made a mistake of some kind, but I don't know what it actually was.
Well, you know, actually don't necessarily know that I made a mistake
yet.
Because, technically, there's something that we haven't quite done.
It's a separate issue.
You about?
I guess I don't know for sure.
Let's put it that way.
So let me double check and make sure that that's not the case.
What I'm going to do right here is just check to make sure that I
don't have a thing where I'm just stepping through the wall because
we're not actually doing anything to prevent that at the moment.
Yeah, so that's what I thought.
All right, so that's fine.
So let's talk about that.
All right.
So we've gotten to the place where successfully testing all the walls.
But now we have to deal with problem number 2 for this kind of test,
which is that when we actually do this computation, right?
So here's the problem that we have when we actually do this.
We are finding the point where he exactly hits the wall where this
guy, exactly hits the wall, right?
And we have a problem, which is that when we, then if we then allow
him to actually be there on the next time, step.
He won't actually necessarily, you know, due to Precision issues.
And so on.
He won't necessarily ever hit this wall because he might be just a
little bit to the other side of it.
Right?
Because we're counting on that equation.
Producing a tea that is greater than or equal to 0, right.
But if we move him right up to the wall and stick them right on it.
If we stick him, even even the smallest fraction of a floating point
value to the other side of it, right?
Then he would not actually that test would no longer succeed.
So we don't have a very big margin for error there and that's not a
good thing, right?
Right.
that's not a good thing at all, because we that's not
At that's just not how you want to roll.
Right?
So there's a number of ways that we could deal with this.
And it's unclear.
Exactly necessarily what we want them to be.
I'd have to think about this a little bit more to think about what I
ultimately want to do for right now, since we're only doing very
simple thing.
I would say that the easiest thing to do is just for us to make sure
that we put in a little bit back from the wall.
Always, if he hits the wall, right, just make sure that you're a
little bit back from it.
That's probably the easiest thing to do and wouldn't really cause any
problems.
But basically this is something that we probably want to handle more
robustly.
Once we get forward enough, that we've actually written Collision
detection.
The way that we want to do it with area shapes and so on, then we'll
talk a little bit more about this case again and see if we can't do a
cleaner job for right now, I'm going to do is make sure that he's back
a little bit from it.
Right?
So what I want to do, there is say that
Whenever he hits a wall, right?
Whenever he actually hits a wall there.
I would like him essentially to be just a bit back from it.
So when he does that, I'm going to say that that we're going to have
this little like we're going to have some kind of an Epsilon on the T.
It be nice if that that was in World space and not motion space,
though is the only thing because if I do it in the terms of the T
value, then the problem with that is that's going to be proportional
to how far removed.
I'll see if this works.
Now, like I said, I don't want to necessarily do it quite this way
when we get to the end.
So I'm not going to sweat it too much making this quite right because
I'm not sure that we really care but, you know, we'll see.
So I'm going to make a little Epsilon here, right?
That Epsilon is just typically a term we use for like a very small
value that we're using to make a tolerance to work around floating
Point things.
I'm just going to say that the T Epsilon is going to be something
like, you know, 0.01 or something like that.
I don't know yet.
Yet.
But we'll just have some arbitrary value that we stick in there and
will basically say, okay in the case, where we actually hit the team
in what we're going to do is say we'll give it the minimum of that and
T that t result - that Epsilon distance, right?
And again, this is not a particularly good way to handle this.
I don't think, but I just want to see if this if this will fit.
Start situation, right?
Let's see here.
Yeah.
So you can see it's not really great.
But, you know, it is a little further away than I would.
Like.
You can see it's pretty far actually from where the guy is if that
makes sense.
Yeah, so, all right, so we want that to be much smaller, maybe
something like this.
I don't know why I keep closing the application.
So now we can go right up to the wall and hit it.
I don't know why.
That that was a little weird.
Don't know why he's hitting it that way.
That's very strange.
I got to take a look at why that's happening.
Feels like his velocity is much larger than I would think.
Or is Delta is much larger than I would think it would be.
Hmm.
That is very strange.
Yes, that's fine.
Continue.
Oh, that's right.
We don't actually have a way to continue beyond that.
So anyway, yeah, I don't love that.
Let's go ahead and take a look at this more because that's not quite
as good as I would have liked it to be just in, in general.
But anyway, that's what happens when he hits the wall.
He's now, we now at least know when he hits the wall and we just have
our, we don't have a very robust algorithm right now, in terms of
dealing with what happens when we actually want.
The, the floating-point stuff to work out properly.
Oh, you know what?
We forgot to do, though.
I know we forgot to do.
We need to do our re canonicalize.
That's something that we need to actually go look at as well pretty
soon here because that's going to get annoying real fast since we
haven't gotten to that point yet.
Yeah.
So, I believe we won't hit that assertion.
Now that we don't do that.
We're doing our economic lives, but we still just have that nasty.
I feel like that should stop right at the edge and it isn't.
So I wonder if I have another bug.
I feel like I must have another bug there.
That just feels really wrong to me.
So I think there's a bug.
I don't know.
Why.
Why do I keep closing the app I'm used to today.
I was working on stuff all day that did not have Dynamic reloading
because I'm working on some lower level stuff.
And so I'm used to having to close the app every time I'm going to
rerun it.
So I feel like there's something incorrect In what I'm doing, that's
causing me to get that stoppage in a way that I don't like.
And so I'm going to take another look again here at this and say what
exactly is going on.
Oh, okay.
That's fine.
I typed a minimum instead of Maximum, not the brightest movement.
But yeah, so I was trying to clamp against zero because I didn't want
it to make a move backwards and I typed a minimum, which meant it was
always going to pick zero.
Oh, that's awful.
Not that Salish, same awful, but it's pretty dumb.
There we go.
Much better.
Yeah, so now we're back to where I thought we should be, which is
being able to hit exactly.
I don't know why we're getting that.
I wonder if I'm if I'm still not doing the re canonicalize properly.
Let's take a look here.
So tile I might still not be doing that right?
But let me let me look at what tile rail is here.
So tile relative is really large.
So that seems wrong.
So I think we're not doing that properly.
New player P.
We cannot.
Last position.
So why are we getting?
Why are we getting that?
What's the tile side and M Tile map tile side and M, so 1.3.?
Well, no, that's that's about, even though that's, that's pretty darn
close, right?
That's, that's a that's about, right.
I would say.
So yeah, that's probably close enough these guys.
Yeah, these guys are
Are just going to have to.
That's just the way that's going to go basically.
Yeah, I don't think there's much of a way around that necessarily.
Let's see here.
I wonder if those should be loosened.
Tile.
So remember we put these in, just to check when we were doing recon,
as we know that they're not going to be exact at the moment.
So, I'm wondering what's happening here when we do this offset and we
subtract after we do the Divide.
I'm wondering if it's if it's why it's unable to get us to have
properly like that.
Let's see here.
You know, should it be?
Should I allow some slop there?
Yeah, yeah.
Yeah.
We'll see.
All right, because yeah, I don't I don't know exactly what we want to
do about that.
I but I don't love having those kind of I don't like any kind of
Epsilon things, really?
So usually once we have an Epsilon in the code, I usually kind of
think of it as something that I want to go back and fix.
But only once I actually know that I'm going to use the code.
So like that looked like he went a little bit too far into their which
didn't what's also looked a little bit chunky.
I want to see if I can reproduce that.
I don't know if I can though.
Yeah, so how did he get in there?
I'm assuming that, that is us not checking something the way that we
should be checking, right?
Because he shouldn't ever be able to move.
In like that, right?
Like like you can see you can get through there, right?
So how did he manage to do that?
How did he sneak through that hole?
I would like to know.
So yeah, you can see that.
All right.
So I think basically the probably the easiest thing to do is just be
to step up to the next level of collision detection, rather than
trying to get this to work more seamlessly.
Because most of the things that we're seeing here that are janky or
things that will go away.
If we go move to the next sort of level of goodness at that make
sense.
So let's just call that done for now, but observe the problems, right.
The problems are we have to have an Epsilon in order to not go through
the wall and even with that Epsilon I believe and I can't say for sure
because if you know, you know, what we could do we could we could
actually do something to visualize this.
To make it a little easier to see what I think is happening there.
And I just want to make sure everyone can see all the problems with
it.
Before we go up to the next thing.
Let's see here.
I want to render these guys a little smaller than they would otherwise
be so like that.
I think so.
There we go.
So did you see that?
Basically what happened there?
That that is exactly what I'm talking about.
So,
I can't get through here.
But if I could hit it directly at the edge, right?
Where is it?
Come on, there we go.
Right?
You see that if I hit it directly at the edge, I can get in between
where I was hitting this wall.
And this wall, right?
These two neighboring walls, the two verticals.
I can, I can just manage to get between it, right.
And I think someone on the street, the other day was asking about how
you can glitch through walls, and I sort of Drew that case where the
things, we're just a little
Off.
So that's an example, right?
Because it's the numeric numerically.
It's just not stable enough.
So there's a gap essentially that you can sort of fit through there if
you really kind of work at it, right?
So, that's a good example.
So, all right, so we've got a bunch of things that we would like to do
now.
and basically, what they boil down to
There's really two, there's two two.
Totally separate things that we want that both come from the same.
That will both be solved by the same solution, if that makes sense.
So what are they?
All right.
Oops, that's no good.
okay, so the first thing,
Is that we are testing against an infinitely thin wall, right?
We're testing.
I think that's like this little tiny thin wall and all we know about
is that pin point in space that the wall is, and what that means is
that if the guy is on this side of the wall.
He can hit it going this way.
And the guys, on this side of the wall.
He can hit it going that way.
But, if he's right here, or right here, right?
Remember imagine, this was very, very microscopic.
So he's just a hair on either side, right?
He would still be able to move in what freely?
In that direction or freely in that direction, right?
So if we're ever off by even the slightest bit numerically, and we
thought we were stopping him right here, but we actually put them just
on the other side.
Right.
It will it allow them to the player to tell me right through the wall.
And that's a symptom of the fact that we're treating it, as just this
thin, right?
This very infinitely thin.
Well, you know I'm saying?
So that's not very good.
We don't like that.
What we would rather be the case is, we'd rather it be the case that
this were a solid thing.
Right?
Something that didn't have a very tiny little miniscule, sort of thing
to it.
Where numerical imprecision could ever happen.
We would want this to be as thick, you know, some thickness that
allowed it to knock it through and of course if we think about it, the
tile itself, right?
Is very much a solid thing.
So like the fact that we were testing against each wall individually
and treating it as infinitely.
Thin isn't really necessary because the thing that we're trying to
simulate is not even an infinitely thin border around something,
right?
We're actually okay with just saying, hey, you know, you can't walk
anywhere within this entire block, right?
So what we'd like to do is solve this problem.
First of all,
Then we have another problem that we also have right.
And that problem is that our guy is, is too tiny in his Coalition
sense, right now, right?
He can interpenetrate here because we're only doing Collision
detection with that point.
Right?
And the reason that we're only doing context of the point is because
we all we know how to do at this point is do Collision detection along
array, right?
So we have a ray that is moving along and we're testing that against
the
A wall but really he should be some shape here.
You know, he should be like a circle or something so that when he
moves against, when these collisions act against other things, it's
actually whenever any part of the circle would touch, the thing that
he's colliding against that would stop him and that would allow us to
give him some volume, right?
So that he stops away from the wall, like, you know, they're properly,
but also if he's going in the other direction, stops away from the
wall, you know,
Like they're whatever.
Right?
So something that gives them that volume back and I think that's
obviously something that we want as well.
And so both of those things are.
Basically sort of asking us to move up a level in complexity of how
we're doing our Collision detection and say instead of talking just
about lines, right?
Because all we were talking about is lines.
Basically, what we wrote before was something that intersects the line
of the player, right?
With the line of the world, some kind of line in the world.
So, what we're talking about now is, we're saying, let's move from
lines to testing actual areas, right?
Or volumes if they were in 3D, right?
So let's go from lines to areas and figure out how to do area versus
area.
So that we can actually have Collision detection that is both
numerically more robust, because it's not talking about these
infinitely, thin things that are very easy to have Epsilon issues
around A and B.
So that we can make the player, have some volume as well.
And so he will not be just a pinpoint.
This moving around for the purposes of his Collision detection.
And so that's what we want to do.
And ideally we'd like to do that in a way that gives us a fair bit of
flexibility with what these volumes actually are.
You know, I would like to basically say, maybe at the very least, I'd
probably say we might want to allow ellipses in there.
R-right because I feel like the guy is probably wants to be a lips.
I don't know.
He might maybe he wants to be a circle.
It's kind of hard to say.
It depends on what's going to feel good to move around, really right,
but I don't know if a circle makes some sense for him or if an ellipse
makes more sense.
The problem is, you know, the perspective of the game is a little
tilted, in that sense.
And so maybe it needs to be more of an ellipse to properly feel right?
In terms of when you're moving through stuff.
But at the same time,
And that means that your motion is going to feel different depending
on whether you're grinding against a vertical or horizontal wall, when
you turn the edge and stuff.
So, so no means a circle.
So, at the very least, a circle, the very least we need circles
because he's at least going to be probably a circle because you wanted
to kind of be smooth and to be able to roll around things.
So that, when you're pushing into things, you don't want them to have.
Like you don't want its Collision shape to have hard edges, because
they'll get like caught in stuff and be kind of janky new around.
So, a circle is kind of nice because it rolls off things, and it just
feels nice and smooth to move.
Around.
So we definitely want circles.
And then we probably also want rectangles, because there's probably
rectangle stuff in the game, but we might also want polygons, right?
We might want to be able to say let's be able to draw just arbitrary
kind of little fancy sorts of things perhaps, right?
So that's another thing that we might want to have.
And so we're going to want to basically think about when we as we're
sort of, when we upgrade our Collision here.
Now, we're going to want to think about how we can do something more
along these lines.
So what we might do, what we might do is just do Circle and square so
that we can do tile map.
Well, you know, we could even just do circles and circles.
Yeah, let's do Circle and square.
Let's say let's shoot for doing Circle and square now, but to think
about also polygons going forwards, because when we actually go to do
the real shipping Collision, Vector code, whatever we decide to do
that, it'd be nice to potentially have those.
Not sure.
I'm not sure if we'll want them, but we might.
So we want to basically set our engine up since that's why, you know,
we're still in the phase where we wanted to find all the things we
needed to do and get
You know, placeholder versions of all of them.
I think that's basically what we're looking at.
We're looking at circles squares and and these and maybe I don't know
if we want rounded rectangles as well.
I don't know.
We might, like rounded things that are kind of rounded as well.
I'm not sure.
I'm not sure we will see, but circles and squares will probably be our
Target for now.
So we'll try to do a circles and squares one, and then we'll go from
there.
I think that pretty much brings us to the end of the stream.
It's a short stream of
Bit today because we were chatting a little too much at the beginning.
Everyone was gabbing but that's a good place to stop anyway, because
tomorrow we can write the new College of detector.
And, and so that'll be kind of nice to have the explanation and the
implementation in one day, or at least the start of the implementation
in one day.
Okay.
So let's go to the the questions.
Now, I will start the little thing here.
So please, if you have questions put
A q: in front of them and try to keep them things we've done today
stream, or on previous streams.
If you want to ask off-topic questions, come about 15 minutes before
the scheduled start time, and I'll take off topic questions.
Then I don't take off topic questions now.
Can you change the Whiteboard color to Black and use a light colored
pencil color switching from emacs to the Whiteboard is jarring.
It's true, that that's not really the same color scheme, as it's
definitely different.
I don't know.
How that would look exactly.
I guess we would do something.
How do I does this have a universal eyedropper?
Well, we could do something like this.
Where is my color cop?
There's my color cop.
We could do something like this, where we grab out.
You know, whatever this color.
Is he there?
Here we go.
So, we grabbed out that color and we could say, okay, the color here.
Do you have, how do I just imput a color people?
Where is that at?
I don't want an advanced color selector.
I just want, I just want to color selector.
How do I just type in a color value?
Seriously, is this where we're at here?
You won't let me type in a color, will you?
Alright, nevermind.
Then I have no idea.
Like, where are the colors?
Is these, the colors?
There they are.
Okay.
So if I want to add this in its 2051 7125 and we'll make that be our
foreground color.
And then our background color is that.
So that's 22, 22, 22.
So, there we go.
And so that would look something like this.
We could do that.
Well, what you guys think about that and think it over?
Would you give it tutorial for emacs?
There already is one.
Take a look at the episode guide on.
If you go to him a hero hero dot-org, if you click on the news and
forums link, there's an episode guide on there and they're already has
a tutorial for you Max.
Do you plan on getting into using calculus to get better, Collision
detection?
Or is that too?
You don't really need calculus to get better.
Collision detection will be doing better Solutions.
Action will be doing basically perfect Collision detection.
I mean, perfect is a tough word to use but will be doing Collision
detection.
That is
As shippable as any Collision detection, that ships in a game, but
without really doing any calculus at all.
So you do need Cactus for some things are just not that.
Do you ever feel it necessary to prototype different aspects of your
game?
Like, ocean protection with different methods in other languages?
Would you always do everything in the language that you're writing the
game in?
I always do it in the language.
I'm running the game in.
Wow, everyone is in favor of the colors, unanimously.
That's crazy.
Wow.
Zoinks.
If we change the resolution on with your handmade, well the tiles, in
the bitmap, still draw the same but smaller bigger versions of them
with the same settings.
So right now we don't have any bitmap scaling code.
So the bitmaps always draw a pixel to pixel.
So if you change the resolution, they'll change size.
And that is one good reason, for example why we would want our or
potentially at least want our render to be able to handle things like
that.
At least in the final stages where it could blow the bitmap out to a
bigger size.
So it always.
So it's not dependent on the resolution and so on.
Can you do Collision detection based on if a pixel in a bitmap has
Alpha?
Yeah, you can.
But you can't do it continuously.
I mean you sort of could do it continuously, but you can't really do
it.
Very efficiently with a non tunneling based stuff.
So you try not to do that.
If you can avoid it, like basically the problem is and let's will use
the new colors.
So what the problem is.
Is analytically like we already did this even just in our simple one,
right?
We were able to take a Time step from here to here and figure out
whether we hit the wall at any time during that time step, right?
There's no way to do that.
If we have to check the pixels of the bitmap.
And the reason for that is because that creates some kind of a of a
that would basically create tons of little moving, rectangles, right?
That are all the rectangles that are set in the bitmap and we'd have
to check it that way to really do that full thing.
And so what you would do if you were going to do that, right?
Is you wouldn't want to do it that way.
That right.
What you'd want to do is take a look at the bitmap and let's say that
this is the bitmap that we're talking about.
So, for some reason, don't ask me why.
It looks like this.
Right.
What you wouldn't want to do is actually take all of the things that
have Alpha set and actually test all of those swept things versus
every other.
Swept, the Emmy be a nightmare.
Right?
What you would want to do.
First of all is you'd want to say, well, this guy for the motion that
direction we're going is always going to be behind this guy, right?
And this guy is always going to be behind these guys, right?
So I don't need to sweep anything, but the exterior of the thing, and
I only need to sweep the exterior in the direction that we're going.
And quickly what you would find when you started to work on this is
that well, it would really just be way more efficient that no matter
what, you know, crazy thing.
My guy looks like, right?
Like, he's some snowman, weird thing, or whatever.
What I'd really rather do is just put some polygons in here that very
closely approximate the dude, right?
And then just use the edges of the polygons instead of using each
individual pixel.
Because otherwise you're just going to drown in computation.
And this is basically as good because it can be pretty close.
And you can always.
Make the polygon pretty detailed if you need to be.
But at least then you're only checking like you're checking some
version of it.
That's not literally looking at every little pixel because that's just
going to be way too slow.
If you actually don't want a tunnel.
It's interesting to have a tutorial on floating-point peculiarities.
Probably it would be but I'm not the guy to give it.
Like basically, I'm not super knowledgeable about floating-point
computation.
Like I'm Oka passable at it, but I'm just not.
I wouldn't give a very good tutorial.
Like basically, the way you see me working around it on the stream
will be, basically, the all that I know is really how to do, you know,
so we'll cover it when I do workarounds for stuff, but I don't really
know.
I'm not very good at that.
So,
I'm the wrong guy to give that tutorial.
I missed parts of the stream.
But in the last episode, you added the new Collision system and remove
the old one.
Why not use the old one.
And just use the new ft thing to get the new point.
If and only, if the old system director Collision because I want to
move to a system that's actually not using the tile map anymore.
Eventually, right?
I want to basically do an object-based Collision system.
So we're going to have stuff like, you know, I think our tilemap will
basically have a bunch of stuff in it.
Like, you know, trees with little Collision volumes at the basis of
them or whatever.
And I want to collide against those potentially, like, I don't know
what I'm going.
I want to do but I don't I don't want to actually do tile map.
Basically Asian.
I want to just do like polygonal and circular base Collision so that I
have more flexibility with with what the maps look like.
And so I'm not really interested in using the old version.
so I think, wow, not many questions today looks like
Oh, and what about the tiles?
Will they still draw the same across the screen with a different
resolution?
For example, we have nine by 17 tiles across and if we switch the
resolution that would be like 17 by nine tile-based.
We have any bugs and how to fix that.
So I'm not sure exactly what you're asking.
But basically, the idea is the game screen will always be the same.
And so, the right now we don't have the ability to
So, okay, we'll talk about two things.
So first of all, we're a bitmap game.
So we probably want to run in our native resolution most of the time
so we probably want to run in 1920 by 1080 all the time, right?
That's probably what we will do.
And so what we'll probably do is we'll draw in 1920 by 1080 and we
might also support downscaling by 2.
So we might also support running.
In a half mode where we're running half of that and where we actually
have our bitmaps pre-processed so that they're all half size and that
would be to support like Raspberry Pi and stuff.
If it's too slow or actually more to the point for the Raspberry Pi to
little memory potentially as well.
So basically what we will do is we will have a 1920 by 1080 buffer
where our tiles are lined up the way that we want them, right?
We will draw to it and then no.
Matter what the ending resolution is, we will blit that up to that
resolution, right?
Because we don't want to resize every individual thing because that
just waste a lot of time.
And we'll look worse than if we just actually do the whole composite
and then scale it up at the end and or down depending on the
circumstance, right?
What is dynamic loading?
I thought see was compiled a need to be recompiled to update the code.
No, that's I mean c does have is a compiled language, but that doesn't
mean that you have to not have Dynamic loading.
So we just implemented.
Dynamic loading.
You can go back and watch it, the episode where I implemented that we
basically just embedded system where you can recompile without exiting
the game.
So yeah.
Any more on topic questions.
Does anyone have any more on topic questions?
I'm guessing the answer is no.
I'm guessing that the answer is no.
And it looks like it's true.
There are no more questions.
Although I always I don't know how long the lag is when I said, say,
are there any more questions?
I don't know.
When you guys actually hear the fact that I just said, I don't know if
there are any more questions like, it could be 30 seconds.
It could be a minute.
I have no idea.
But yeah.
All right.
Well, then I guess we all get to get to go home early today.
That's some, that's some seriously, you know, I'm gonna go make some
more tea, That's what I'm gonna do.
So, I certainly hope that all of you will think about Collision
detection and dream about closures action while you're, you know,
sleeping tonight and what we're going to do tomorrow.
And so we'll come back tomorrow and we will right away to don't want
to actually delete this.
I'm going to leave it here.
Can I save, can I now that we've made our settings here?
Can I save that?
Setting it all.
I don't know if we can save like our foreground and background color.
Let's do it.
Vaz and I'll just make a desktop thing.
That's like handmade here.
O.K.
Are a, let's find out.
You ready for this?
You guys ready?
I don't know if you are not but doing it anyway.
Wait for it.
wait for it, and
Nope, the answer is no.
So that's a little bit below that down.
Yeah, it was exciting for a minute.
It's true, but then it all went to Pieces.
So I guess we're going to have to do apparently is we're going to have
to do that.
And then we're going to have to do, where is my color cop?
We're going to have to do the old.
Let's see.
Color swatch up in the corner.
Trick.
All right, and then we'll save it and then I'll grab it from there.
When we reload.
Thanks carita for not saving anything, with the file.
You certainly wouldn't want your foreground and background colors
possessed.
All right, everyone.
Thank you very much for joining me for another episode of handmade
hero.
We have gotten to the end of our crappy Collision detection.
And so tomorrow, it's ready.
It's time to start on some good Collision detection.
I certainly hope to join me, same time.
Same place 8:00 p.m.
Pacific Standard Time.
Are on Twitch, and we will be talking among among other things about
our friend, Mankowski, and why you should get to know him because he
makes your Collision detection life, much, much easier than it would.
Otherwise be if you want to follow along at home and you have not
already pre-ordered, the game.
You can pre-order the game on him, a here at Oregon, get all the
source code.
That is a good thing to have.
If you want to play around at home.
You can do that right here.
If you want Sports video series, you can go to our patreon page, which
is like to hear.
If you want to learn about the series, you can go to our Resource page
news in forums, all kinds of good stuff schedule, episode guide catch
up on past episodes coding resources, which has ports to Mac and Linux
and stuff like that and code discussion where you can ask questions.
Like nice little Forum, you can go to and check it out.
So okay, that is about it.
I highly recommend checking out all that fun stuff.
In the meantime, have an excellent Thursday, and I will see you
tomorrow night.
Thanks, everyone.