Start recording.
Hello everyone and welcome to handmade hero.
The show we could a complete game live on stream today.
We are going to look a little bit more closely at our particle system
code, which we sort of put in and actually it's all working.
Now it didn't take us very long, I guess to put that in there so
that's good and all.
But we've got a bunch more work to do.
There's the vegetables he's there and there's something I'm really
afraid about and we'll have to kind of talk about it a little bit and
figure out what we're going to do about it.
It's
Sort of, just another aspect of the 2D nests of the way we do things.
So there's a little bit of the of the particle system stuff.
I'm not 100% sure what we're going to do about.
But, you know, we've certainly, we have options.
So it's not, it's not the end of the world, but we'll talk about that
a little bit, a little bit as well.
So, let's just get right into it here.
Today is day, three thirty-nine.
So, if you want to follow along at home, you want to use day, 338
source code.
That's what I'm using today.
So let me go ahead and open up.
Our prayer.
Okay, that's not what I wanted at all.
I've pushed the wrong file, there it is.
So if
We go ahead.
And run.
You can see that we sort of made this little thing that like, kicks
these little particles off when we when we sort of hit the ground
there and that's all fine.
But we have sort of a little bit of a bug.
We haven't quite finished, getting this stuff working because we need
to make sure that when we move these particles, move properly with
changes in the camera.
I like how this map still includes a boost square but I don't know
where it goes.
We have this problem of like I guess we have sort of this the thing
that creates the world like still puts the blue square and even if
there is no way to boost to, I've no idea where it was trying to boost
to but that's not great you know not a good thing anyway.
So if we go over to the other screen here, when we moved,
Across from screen to screen our particles now like appear to do the
right thing.
So that's good right?
I mean they're not, they're not obviously wrong, you know?
They they, they're somewhat correct, but what we found yesterday, when
we sort of slowed things down just to see, whether they were being
placed correctly, it did look like if you really pay close attention
to what happens to the particles during the transition, they are not
displaced the
way that we would expect, right?
So as I kind of
To the side here.
You'll notice that, as I move, you can pretty clearly see the
particles are getting a lot of slide to them.
That is not what we would expect.
And so, I'm not really sure where that slide is coming from.
It would be a more understandable slide if it wasn't sinusoidal in
nature.
That's the part that really weirds me out about it.
You can kind of see here as I move.
That the particles will shift first shift left in their cell and then
shift right in their cell, which does not make a whole lot of sense.
If this were strictly a perspective, like they were getting
transformed at the wrong perspective, kind of a problem, I would have
expected to see a more straightforward displacement problem.
Like either they're being displaced more slowly than the ground or
more quickly than the ground but not in a parent.
Like sort of quicker and then slower, you know, inconsistent, if you
will.
Change.
That is not what I would have expected to see.
Now, the first thing I'm going to point out here is that in theory,
this should have nothing to do with our displacement, because the
displacement only happens with a camera actually moves.
It does not happen when the camera is simply just shifting.
Because if you remember the way we implanted this as we shift the
camera first, then we actually move the Sim region in the center of
the camera over then we shift it.
So it's kind of like it's almost like a glorified screen shake the way
we do that so that we can sort of keep this notion
Of which room were centered on.
And then we just do this kind of displacement for moving the camera
there.
So, what I'm wondering is, I would just like to know if we didn't do
the frame displacement at all.
So let's say I did frame displacement and I just nullified it.
So now we're not adding that frame displacement at all I want to see
what actually happens when I go ahead and and shift, right?
so, as I move across,
So you can see that brake line there.
You see how like as I come across it, shifts back, right?
But you can see that that.
Yeah.
It's it really does not require the frame displacement.
The frame displacement is strictly accounting, re realigning for that
camera shift.
You can see that the particles are shifting separate from that.
So it really is something to do with the way that they're getting
transformed separate from everything else.
So we
know that it's not our frame displacement, that's to blame there.
It's some other
Element.
And the frame displacement seems to be working properly.
So I'd like to go ahead and see if I could figure it out.
Figure out what is causing the other problem.
With the Z there.
Now one thing that's true is we're not setting the Z level properly
for our particles and again I'm not really sure exactly how we're
going to handle that.
One thing we could do is just make sure that we actually do sort our
particles into Z levels.
I'm nervous about doing these extra thing to particles because there's
a lot of them.
So it makes me a little worried but you know, if we were going through
that, it's not particularly hard.
All we would do is say, well from the transform, we've kind of got the
notion of the Z floor, right.
And we've got the notion of the Z level.
So in theory we could record those for our particles as well and if we
want to do that you know it's not that big of a deal.
So if we want to do something like that, then when we were to would
On the particles, we would track that information.
So you know, we do for each protocol for X.
We would say, you know, what is and this would basically just mirror
the render group
Yeah, meow, meow, meow.
Where is my pencil up?
There it is.
So we've got the floors in the chunk see their right.
And so if we were to store both of those, we wouldn't need to actually
store them.
A particle per se because we spawn these particles as a batch
currently.
So, in theory, you know, we've got these four X's here for X is 4.
X is 4X, has we want this particle structure to be aligned?
Slowly.
So the these two being sort of orphaned isn't a great idea.
So we'd probably sick at at the end of here so that to make sure
everything lines up on a 4X boundary other than that.
We're fine.
So, if you take a look at what's going on here,
you can see that all we would need to do.
Is when someone says spawn fire, we just need the floor.
Z and the chunks d.
And so you know it's like I said it's theoretically possible to get
this information in here so let's just go ahead and try it.
I don't love it.
We're but you know I don't want to prematurely say that we're not
going to do it all.
So let's just try it first and we'll see where we land at that point.
So then we could say all right in our object transforms.
As we go, we can set the chunk Z and the floor Z to a particular
particles.
Things, we can set those here, because they'll be the same for each
batch of four particles that will obviously come from the a particle
there.
There we go.
And if we're gonna overwrite that then probably what we would want to
do is we wouldn't want to we probably want to have our own version
here.
So I'd probably say like okay since we're going to modify it, let's
say that we have a transform that equals our Transformer in it, so
that we don't break the transform for the people who come after us,
which we might do otherwise, that's mostly that
Let's go take the address there.
So spawn fire is going to have to get that information.
Hopefully, we have that information.
That would be over here somewhere when we want to spawn.
These guys, let's take a look.
We sort of do sort of don't write, like we only compute these 44 ones.
We actually know about.
So, while the chunk Z is quite easy to compute, the floor, Z is not so
easy to compute.
It should be much easier to compute because it should just be a
straight value that you can just look up.
And so we could probably get it pretty easily by just doing a multiply
based on the chunk.
See which, of course at that point, one might wonder why we don't just
pass one value down in the answer is because we haven't gotten to that
level of cleanliness yet.
But
Um, when we do stuff on fire point being, where is there it is.
We have one of these pretty easily which is just the Z layer, but we
have to figure out how to get the other one because we haven't
actually we only compute that for the levels.
We can see and we want to spawn fire probably on any level.
Although maybe that night, I think we do though any level regardless
of, whether we can see it.
So anyway, when we do this bonfire, we get the Z layer, we then need
That that floor is he this guy right here and I'm going to maybe put
these in the opposite order, okay?
So, that floor is e.
I have to figure out a way to compute and you can kind of see the way
that's been computed up here already.
It's, it's called camera relative Ramsey and it's getting computed
this way, right?
You can, you can kind of see, it's like, okay, whatever the relative
layer index is, you know, I mean this this is the computation so if we
bake out that computation, we should be able to just do it wherever we
want to.
So, I'll put it one in there temporarily and then maybe we can
systematically
Sighs out a little bit.
So it's not such a, you know, hacky sort of cut and paste these sort
of thing.
So in terms of whatever the relative layer index is, I assume that
it's get the relative layer index.
All we would really have to do is take the Untied easy layer.
Right, and subtract it from the cameras e layer.
And I don't know what the camera is.
You layer is, but I'm assuming we must have had to figure out what
that was before at some point, right?
Somewhere.
Here, we must have that information.
What is the cameras?
Level value.
Anybody know.
Well, I don't know.
It's probably zero in.
Ah, I know what this is, never mind.
So these are just, these are Computing.
The relative ones, which means it's always just assuming that its
relative, 20 being where the camera is.
So presumably, when we do the entity layer Z stuff, when we compute
its relative one, we must have a way of figuring that out, right?
So we must do it right in here.
So relatively as alert here, it is.
So it's Tim region, origin chunk.
See, that's what I'm like.
I knew it's in here somewhere.
There's got to be a way to compute that that layer.
All right, so let's take a look.
At how this stuff is working here?
Doodoo meow, meow.
So if I want to know what it is, I just look it up from the Sim region
and off we go.
So now we're spawning these in theory at the correct floor height, you
know, and I would highlight the in theory there because we are not
actually dying to verify that that was true, but now we can sort of
check to see whether that had any effect whatsoever on, you know, go
to the other go.
Haha, there you go.
I don't know why we're now stopping in that space.
I guess that's just the way the alignment was so weird.
Anyway,
So, here we go.
So it doesn't look like that has any effect on it, right?
Like it looks like it still, it still gives that really weird like
sinusoidal pattern
As we go.
You know, from left to right?
All of those particles, still shift and they don't shift in a very
predictable way far as I can see.
I do.
No.
So yeah.
It bugs me a little that I don't have a good idea about why that would
be happening.
I am interested to know about whether the Z value of these things.
I mean, my feeling is that since the Z values are not gonna
Since the Z values of the particles are not really related because
it's always doing the perspective based on the chunk.
I don't understand why, you know, I don't understand why I'm not
getting a consistent movement and why there's that sort of slippage
back and forth.
And so I wish I had more of an inkling as to why that would be why
there would be that kind of slippage there.
And
One thing I can think of is if it was an off by one frame error, but
if it was, I would see Jitter.
It wouldn't be a smooth, it wouldn't be smooth like it is, right?
Because when we change the simulation time step, we're still rendering
at 60 frames a second.
So, in off by one frame error would not manifest itself as a sort of
weird displacement like that, that was really consistent, it would be
like a single framed
Are still always at 60 frames, a second of Jitter.
So I really don't know.
I'm at a loss for why?
That would be transforming the way that it is.
So we'll have to start playing around with something and and seeing
how it goes because you can see it really clearly, right?
And what's interesting about it is, so I guess here's one pretty big
clue.
At least.
I think it's a clue.
It looks to me.
like, if we watch,
These particles more carefully.
that they do, they do kind of look like
they are separating.
In parts, right?
Like it does look like different parts of them gets get moved
differently right?
Which does sort of still suggests that there's some kind of weirdness
to the prospective there or something odd going on.
And again I'm not
Really sure what that is.
But not all of the particles move the same amount.
So do you see here these particles are moving this way.
And these are saying stationery.
Right.
And see.
Here's the weird part 2.
Where now they start to move back.
So I guess I don't have any real strong ideas about that other than it
does, it sure does.
Look like, there's some perspective motion going on there of some
kind, which I'm not sure why there would be.
I'll double-check our perspective transform because I would like to
see what's going on there, but I guess one thing I could try as well
is let's just zero out the Z component of our particles to see whether
it makes a difference, right?
Because if I was to set the Z component,
Are always.
So for example, here is the p-value if I'm just to eliminate the
p-value entirely and then run the code.
Again, in theory, I should now have one where there's no Z component
to the particles at.
All right?
There's there.
Just why, I guess, right?
And I don't even know.
Did they even have a z-value in the first place?
I'm not sure.
Because I thought we, we didn't actually you
Use the so there's e values.
Actually should always be zero anyway, right 000.
So yeah, even though probably they should be using Z, these, this is
copied from a particle system.
Remember, when we were just doing tests, there are only moving in.
Why
Right?
So there is no.
To even have them transform at all.
You know what I mean?
Woohoo, so I really not sure.
How we can get such a weird slip-and-slide there.
And let's take a look at what we're feeding in for the transform.
Then I wonder if there's something odd about the transform that I
should be aware of here.
so,
Some care.
So, if I were to take a look at that transform, that is in World mode
update, and render particles.
So that's using the world transform.
And that seems pretty reasonable.
I would like to see for the entities.
What are they using for a transform?
So, if we take a look here, when we build this stuff,
hmm.
so, interestingly enough
This is not actually what the entities are using for drawing because
this code is kind of a little, too stringy at this point.
In this case, we passed the camera P.
So it's actually,
It's actually subtracting away the camera p as part of for the world
offset and then we're passing that in and you know, we're redoing that
calculation, right?
So the entity transform also has that it sort of separated out there
which should yield the same result.
Like there's nothing particularly unusual about that.
Certainly
I don't know.
So that's a tough one.
That's a pretty tough one, and I guess we're going to have to get a
little bit more serious here.
So the first thing I want to do is I want to take an entity and the
particles it spawned.
And I want to start a start to correlate.
What is actually getting sent down for their transforms because since
I I'm like, literally have no idea, right?
Like I'm looking at this problem and just going okay I from the motion
nothing is jumping out at me as like, oh well it's obviously X, right?
And so I don't have anywhere in particular to investigate.
So what I want to try and do is say well, if I know that two things
are wrong, if I know that like the position and of the end of the,
like, the, the ground chunks and the particles that are on top of
them.
If I know that those two things are moving relative to each other, and
I don't think they should be.
Then what I want to do is try to take a look at what are they sending
down to the renderer?
Right?
Because if I look at what they're posting out of the render, I should
be able to find a
Somewhere and hopefully by look you know sort of hunting down that
difference, I would be able to go.
Okay here now I can see what the problem is between these two.
Right.
And so here's the, you know, and here's the code, get render into G
basis P.
That is the thing that's actually doing the transform for the camera.
And when you look at what happens here, right?
You can kind of see the projected, the projection stuff.
It's based off a few things that floors, he's setting the the the Z
value of the Z value of the
Component itself is not actually used for that.
It's just used for the Computing, the Y displacement, right?
The projection is actually coming entirely from just the floor Z.
That's where the distance 2pz competition comes in.
So I don't really know why we would be getting
Why we would be getting that problem?
So what I'm going to do is I just want to take a look at these two
things and see what I can see.
So what I'm going to try doing is I'm just going to step in.
I'm going to kill this.
I'm going to step in to see the first time that I spawn a particle.
What I want to do is I just want to back up quickly and well I guess I
don't need to back up too quickly here.
But Flora Z is 0, chunk Z is 0, so that's easy to remember.
And all I want to do is I want to look at where this entity that,
that, you know, did this morning, where is the entity getting rendered
itself?
Like what does it sanity transform?
Actually look like, by the time we get down to when it actually gets
used, right?
So,
We've got all this stuff here.
We're coming down to it here.
And here we are with our transform, finally, getting put into use
right here.
So here is the entity transform.
Here's getting sent down.
I'm just gonna like select this and cut and paste it.
So I'm going to go into for coder here, going to scratch buffer.
Here is my data and scratch buffer.
And then what I'm going to do is I'm going to set a breakpoint.
So when we actually go to render those particles, I'm going to go
ahead and set a breakpoint.
When we go to render the first particle and see what its transform is
because they should be.
Same right?
What I'd like to see is them having the same transform if that makes
sense.
So let's go ahead and do that.
I lost my place because I accidentally hit the F10 key.
All right, so what I want to do is just come over here and take a look
at that transform.
And now we'll cut and paste it and put it in here.
Oops, it's not wanted.
So let's take a look.
They're both set to Upright.
The offset p is just a different X Y, but otherwise the Z is the same.
The scale is the same manual, sort all of the stuff.
So again, it sure looks like it's ending the same data down to me,
right?
I mean that that's looking basically the same.
Yeah, so I don't really see.
I don't see where the difference comes in there.
Now, one thing that I guess, I don't know is when these things get
rendered.
What if they set up for a clip region?
I guess that, I don't know, because I don't know if the clip region
ever, specifies anything more complicated.
I don't think it does.
At least not for our purposes, and it should be always using the same
one for the entirety of the the game.
The actual game graphs at the moment.
Who.
So yeah.
That looks the same to me.
Unless I'm missing something.
Now, I guess, one thing that's slightly, odd is the X and the Y, are
not in the transform in this case.
So, you know,
I don't know how much that would matter.
I don't expect that it would but you know we could imagine temporarily
that it did for some reason.
And if that was the case, then
We would be able to eliminate the bug in the following way.
And so, I guess I'm going to do that and we'll see instead of having
the p-values come in this way.
What I would do is set these 20
or I guess X.
That's not what I would do.
I would set the transforms, offset P equal to p and then I'd set P 20.
So now all of the information is coming through in the offset itself
if that makes sense.
And, you know, we can see whether that has any effect.
I should make sure to that actually, yeah, that's okay.
And so we'll see if that has any bearing on it whatsoever.
I don't know if it will or it won't.
What happened there?
Why did that not do anything?
Why am I not getting any displacement by offset P?
Somebody.
No on.
Tell me.
Because the P value should be the P that we get past plus the offset
piece.
So if I pass in the transforms, offset P there I should, it should
transform by that.
By that offset value, right?
I mean, that should be what?
What happens there.
So I'm not sure why we wouldn't.
Why we wouldn't see essentially the same results, right?
Not sure why we still have a w in here.
So that's a little odd.
Because I'm not crazy right?
It says right here that we're doing the two-piece plus each other.
So let me take a look at the office at P here and yeah.
So if we do the two-piece plus each other in theory, we should still
be getting that displacement.
Oh yeah.
Except of course we have to always remember to still keep that
displacement, right?
S because we've got an incoming displacement for the camera off set.
Set.
So obviously we need.
Yeah that's good.
Nice work.
Nice work case it.
Good job.
Great job.
so yeah, the transforming it comes in with the cameras offset and then
we've got our particles
We want to add those together shove that in the offset P.
That's actually what I should have been doing and now I am so this
should be more correct let's see.
And we got a course slow it down here.
Let's slow it down and take a look.
Same thing.
So now we like we know we're passing the same information but we're
getting for some reason.
This weird sinusoidal and behavior.
I do not understand why that is happening.
That is a real stumper.
Mmm.
So I guess one other thing to do here would be to not have the
particles, go anywhere and see if that does anything.
That would basically be something of the form, you know?
Don't update the position or the velocity ever.
Under any circumstances, you can update the color if you want to.
And so now when I go through and do these, they'll should just they'll
just stay where they are, right.
Eventually they'll fade out, but they'll just they'll just stay in one
place.
And so when I slide to the side, all I'm going to see is just where
they move because they're not moving of their own accord at all.
And they've only been at their initial locations, right?
So that is just fascinating, right?
Look at how those are moving.
Did you see that?
These are particles that are not moving in any way as far as We Know.
And they sort of crank downward.
I'll put back in the the frame to frame displacement because obviously
it's a little hard to watch when the thing is kind of Jitter like
that.
So I'll leave that in there but man is that crazy.
Right.
I mean, tell me that wasn't crazy.
There we go.
Like, look at that.
They like they go in a circle.
So there's basically like a cosine, they are going in like a
360-degree like cosine sine Circle.
Right.
So, the camera off set.
And the camera offset alone is causing them to rotate around
something.
I don't know what.
And that is just just absolutely fascinating.
so, I guess
Working backwards from that.
I would say that, you know,
we must be looking at something that has to do with the moment arm
like the rotational construction of these guys, you know what else I
should do?
I would like to verify that I think about it that this happens on both
render paths.
So what's what happens if I go over here?
And I set the frame rate all the way.
I'm at the frame rate, the update rate very, very low.
And then I switch to software rendering.
So now we're software rendering.
And now I like slide my dude slowly to the side.
And of course I would probably should have built-in release.
In fact, you know what, I will build in release mode.
You don't want R to take forever.
Okay.
So let's build an oops, hold release mode and will spill batti, man.
but,
What just happened there?
I missed that.
Do we have a release mode bug here?
Oh, are we unaligned?
What's going on there?
Give me something to work with your friend.
What was my crash type?
Access violation reading.
No.
All.
Okay.
Who is telling you to read?
No, obviously it's a dash.
So that means system particles, plus particle.
Index is somehow equal to null, is system known.
Can I inspect system at all?
My particles is definitely not null.
So what what are you talking about there?
Big guy.
Show me the disassembly.
So what are we looking at here are 15 so that must be an actually, I'm
as guessing this is just an unaligned move or something because
there's no way that that's actually a zero access because if this is
the address that it's trying to read, right?
Well, that memory address is clearly not zero.
Right.
So assuming we're trying to go from there, what is that, that memory
address, by the way?
Let's see here.
R15 - oh bah.
Oh well.
Okay, so it actually is zero though.
This is quite peculiar.
So what are you trying to do here mister?
Mister compiler.
So your rerouting.
Okay.
So you take frame displacement and you replicated it out.
I assume
yeah, and
Unsurprisingly AR-15 is the register that's holding the pointer to
system.
Oh not quite.
It's holding the pointer to what exactly maybe stack frame of some
kind?
I'm not sure.
So let's take a look.
Here are 15 is 10.
See what are my main variables?
Here, entropy DT.
Okay, so that's a register.
Finished basement in its surrender group.
Cb8.
All right, so we're look at the memory here.
I'm not just a giant wash of nothing.
So it looks to me like if it's trying to load out of there, I feel
like it's probably trying to load.
That that would be the system particles array.
You would think.
it's just
Gene 18, let's find out.
So let's take that and subtract it from this and see where it can't
quit load that can I
Come on.
I want I want to be able to get that part there.
It is, can I ask?
No, I can't.
I want to get that value, please.
Oh, Visual Studio.
You make debugging such a joy.
I just wanted to see where we were in here.
I want to see where we were.
So they're both 1017.
This one's 18 this with C8.
So I guess I'll just do it in my head.
It does it's not particularly hard, right?
It's just C8 -18 Actually, I don't even need to do in my head, I can
see how to keep up the expression going to do it for me.
So we're that far in.
And that far in seems like something you should be able to load.
So I'm guessing I don't know what we've got here.
I don't know why it can't load that.
It doesn't really make any sense to me.
I'm not sure what I'm looking at here and I don't understand why this
would be an unaligned load because if you were loading at oh well, but
yes, I do.
So I think this is just unaligned load, I think that's what the
problem is.
So what I've got to do, yeah, that's all it is.
All right, so I don't know if you guys follow that Ridiculousness but
basically I'll just go over it again.
I'm pretty sure it's what I said it was originally, but I just wanted
to make sure and I'm not the best at assembly.
So you know, takes me a little while to like make sure I only read it.
In these exact circumstances.
What I'm like, I got to figure out what's actually happening.
So you can see that it gave me an Access violation reading location,
zero error here.
And so that would imply that I was like accessing memory that I wasn't
supposed to access, right?
Like I was reading off of a null pointer or something, but inspecting
the assembly.
It was pretty clear that that was not really what was going on as far
as I could tell.
And so what I actually thought was happening is that because this is
Um, Cindy code here that probably what was going on is that it was a
non-aligned load and what happens is if you have a 70 instruction that
expects to be aligned to a 16 byte boundary and it's not aligned to a
16 byte boundary and we've talked about all this stuff on here before.
So if you don't know, I'm talking about, I would encourage you to go
back, go back and start earlier because that is all covered.
We need our Sim delos to be aligned.
And what happens is, you can see that we've got our particles for our
particle system are aligned here, potentially, but when we allocate
this particle cash, it's not necessarily going to be aligned unless we
force it to be aligned.
And what you'll notice is we get the particle cash from in handmade,
World group, weird mode, rather.
I would, you can see, here, is, I tell it to do.
No clear, but I don't give it an alignment, which means that it's not
necessarily going to be aligned to sixteen, byte boundary our default
alignment in handmade hero.
When we allocate things, we only try to pass them out to a 4 byte
boundary in our, in our, in our allocator, right?
And our memory Arena.
And I think what's that in here?
Yeah.
So if you take a look at what's going to happen, they're aligned no.
Clear is probably more what we want.
So we can say, hey
We need to align this to a 16 byte boundary because there's stuff in
here that needs to be loaded at alignment so you can't go fussing with
it.
I think that would probably fix it and I'm right.
All right.
So, let's go over here.
Let's let the simulation down again.
Will switch to the software renderer.
And again, I just wanted to make sure that this was the same in both
renderers because then that also tells me that it's not something
about like how we're interfacing to say open trailer, something like
this.
So here is our software renderer, we've switched to.
So now not using the graphics card at all and let's see what happens
when I move.
Okay.
So you can see them, they're still undergoing that Corkscrew motion.
So this is good because this basically tells us exactly what we need
to know, it has nothing to do with the render layer and Below.
It's at
The sort of upper level of the renderer when we're actually specifying
these particles.
Things are going bonkers, right?
Okay, so if I now go into handmade render group, what I want to do
here is I would like to sort of get some reacquaintance because we
don't have looked at this in a while at what happens when we actually
send down one of these bitmaps, right?
When I do a push bitmap call, I just want to see what I what I get
here, so you can see that.
I'm I've got an x-axis and a y-axis, the x-axis, the y-axis get sent
down here as part of the push-fit map.
All.
So presumably, they're just getting set to like one and zero and
they're getting multiplied by the scale values that come out here.
Which is the whatever size we've given the thing plus, plus the scale
value, right?
So
Since we don't see the bitmap rotating it all.
I figure that can't really be part of it.
I mean if the X and Y axes were moving it all there we would see that
and I can't really see like you know when we are passing
I guess.
Let's see what get bitmap Tim does.
So, in this case, we are passing through this dimpy so, yeah, you can
see.
There's a little bit of funny business going on here, right?
We use the alignment Point, like the hotspot, basically, of whatever
the thing is that we're passing down.
And that's actually the thing that gets transformed, right?
So, the alignment itself.
Sort of says, where the point is that the bitmap would be
Round.
I don't know immediately, why that would be anything to be concerned
about at the moment but it's just something to keep in mind there.
And you can kind of see, we pass this, the C line value down, that's
what controls these.
So, you know, if it was the alignment that was doing it.
Well, that kind of gives us though, one way to take that out of the
equation as well, which might be good, which is to say when we go
ahead and render one of these bitmaps if we call Push, but map,
Strip map.
I and we pass like the offset in the color, I could then pass 00 for
the alignment.
And hopefully, that would give me.
Oops, what did I do?
Accidentally edited that I did not mean to I should be able to take
that out and I should be able to see if the alignment has anything to
do with it either.
I'm assuming it doesn't, but again, obviously my assumptions, don't
mean anything.
Because any time you're fry in a situation like this, which, you know,
doesn't happen very often where you're finding looking for a bug, you
have no idea what it is, your assumptions are obviously wrong or you
would know where the bug was right.
So that to me, looks like that really doesn't change matters at all.
So I don't think that's it.
So I don't think that's implicated.
So I'm not sure what that leaves us with changing the camera offset.
Causes a corkscrew motion.
I mean, if we had rotation matrices or anything like that in cure, I
could see it being related but I really just don't know where that
would be.
So I'm going to look to see where we do any trig at all.
So this is all code, that's not even used, right?
This was when we were playing around with some lighting stuff and
weird things like that are M2 is there
But that's about it, that's not used.
So if I do look for arm to arm to is used pretty much only in angle
offset movement mode, which these are particles.
They're not going through that.
So I don't even know where we could generate motion of that form
because if we're not in putting any kind of circular operation, I'm
not sure.
Are we even get?
Anything like that to happen.
This is a Brain Buster.
This may be the weirdest bug.
I think we've ever seen on handmade hero.
I have absolutely no idea because if you asked me generate a circular
motion without using sine and cosine
I think I'd be at a loss.
I mean, I suppose I could try to I mean I don't know like pretty much
everything.
I know how to do that.
Involves rotation is going to have to take a sine, the cosine at some
point.
So I guess, I mean the answer is that must not be really a circular
motion, it's got to be some other motion that just kind of looks
vaguely.
Circular
Which I guess is fine.
But yeah, that's that's pretty confusing.
So it's definitely not circular guess.
That's what I'd say.
I guess I will open it up.
To the Q and A for now.
Because well I'm just thinking of random things to do.
If anyone wants to ask a question,
Neal says, look at the screen border, while you're doing it yet is the
screen border, do a similar thing.
Oh yeah, you're totally right.
So basically everything transformed by that world transform has this
happen to it but for some reason, the entities don't
Hmm.
And he's got this place by the modified camera P during room
transitions.
I think.
Yeah.
But aren't we also do not.
I guess we must not be doing that correctly.
And yeah, so if it's just that, then that would make sense because it
is a little like Parabola thing.
Which is sort of wrote, looks a little rotation e, someone suggested
and I think this is a very good suggestion.
Who suggested it?
This Isaac said, what if you try no, not sorry.
Cyberpunk hobo said, what if you disable the parabolic camera?
Transition terms, I think that is a good idea because assuming that
that is what's, if that is what sort of instigating it then we can at
least guarantee that that it is that Z motion.
That's it's a getting it by turning it off.
Because if we turn it off and it stops happening, then we know that's
the case if it's still happening.
Then we know that it's not that which is a good clue, right?
Doesn't quite tell us what's wrong, but it is a good clue.
So, here we have the world mode camera offset thing with the room,
Delta stuff.
I think, what we could probably do is just say like, okay, you know,
World mode camera offset, does equal, 0 0, and then, from there, we
know that we've zeroed out that particular piece of information.
So now when I go across the rooms, it should just be a straight, you
know, straight pan.
So hopefully now we will see
That behavior stop.
So we can know at least that it is based on the Z movement of the
camera.
Yeah, and that looks nice and solid, okay?
So at least we know it's based on the Z movement of the camera.
And so the question is, just if the Z Move Motion of the camera is
what's causing that to occur?
Why is it that we're a seemingly not applying that camera rotation.
The same for the entities as we are for everything else and I don't
know why, I guess it's just a slip of the finger.
There's but yeah, you can kind of see that happening there.
So when we look at the entities, we pass the camera P down into the
entities, right?
and,
I don't think we really do much else with it.
So I mean, get into the ground point - camera P.
Should be the same as sticking that into the transform.
Are we putting it in backwards or something?
Let's find out.
so,
Yeah, I mean this looks like the same transform.
Right?
It's just subtracting camera P.
That's all it does.
So, it should be the same as it is in here, unless there's anything
happened to Canberra P along the way.
Doesn't look like it does anything happen to World transform?
No.
So, I mean it it seems like it's the same.
Exact operation.
Right.
I mean, that is.
That is exactly it.
If the camera offset Z.
I mean, so I guess similarly
Right.
If I were to take camera P here and set the z20, I would also expect
none of that behavior to occur, right?
What?
So, what's interesting about that is the camera pee.
even if I zero out the Z motion,
So is it actually why motion?
That's really related here.
This is quite creepy.
So camera.
Mode, world made camera offset is that used elsewhere.
There's the places where we set it.
Cutscene doesn't matter.
I see.
I see said the blind, man.
We are using that.
in here, to set the floor height,
And we shouldn't be.
Presumably, we should be using this.
Oh boy.
Well yeah, I guess we kind of deserve that with how much tinkering
we've been doing with like sort of weird 2D rendering of 3D stuff in a
kind of ad hoc way that's, you know,
It's to be expected, I suppose.
So yeah, that's kind of really nasty.
I mean basically what that implies to me
Yeah, is again, we really have to be more rigorous about these sorts
of things, which, of course, is very difficult because we don't really
know what the right answer is for a lot of them.
But yeah.
So first thing is first, you should use camera P for the entities
because that's what we actually get we're passing in there.
Right?
So, we want to do that first.
And now what we have to do is for the particles, we would have to do
the same operation.
So basically, when
Compute the floor height.
We've got to take that world mode, camera offset into account.
So yeah.
So you know if we want to do the particles the same way, then what
we'd have to do is say, okay we're not going to we're going to pass in
the camera P here.
Instead of the transform, the camera P comes in this way when we
create our transform, we actually create a default transform.
and,
We taken here the camera pee.
Then what happens is when we come through this piece of code here,
then what we need to do is, when we are Computing, the, the floor
height there, right?
We need to say like, okay, so, first of all, the, you know, the
transform,
Offset p.
Equals negative camera p.
And then also like the floor.
Z has to have this entity baked into it.
There's that.
Here it is.
Right, which is kind of absurd and definitely not going to last.
We're going to have to fix that but I believe that is more like what
we would need to do to make sure these things.
Render the saying because hey they've got actually ready to the same.
Hold on a second.
Slow down.
Get back over here.
Okay.
Two.
Hey, look.
Sort of work.
Still got some movement there though.
I think probably because those guys are actually at different Z's,
that looks like actual motion.
I would expect at higher Z values
Potentially, so that may be a little more understandable, but we'll
see.
We're definitely not getting any more of the parabola displacement
though which is what I would expect to see now so that's good.
All right.
So a little closer and what was the other thing that I?
What was the thing that I had turned off there?
I think I did I think I turned it back on, right?
And Sim.
Region.
I don't have that turned off anymore.
Yeah, I don't.
And what about world mode?
I don't zero anything out anymore.
Do I?
All right, so a little bit better, not fantastic still, but a little
bit better.
and yet, I believe that that
I basically think that for 2D you know, you there's a lot of things
that are a lot simpler in 2D right but there's a few that are vastly
more complex you know and
A lot of it is this way it's basically like because you don't have a
uniform idea of where everything is.
You end up with all of these kind of hacks and you know we'll get them
more under control.
As we go further down handmade here we can crank this down a little
tighter and get these hacks to be more straightforward.
So you know, it's not as bad as it seems right now because we're still
in the process of hammering out some of these fire details and we're
trying to do you know more stuff than we should, you know, I mean
we're we don't have to do a lot of these things that we're doing.
We can just ignore these problems and not have some of these features,
right?
But but yet, when you do 3D, the nice part about that is, you know,
ahead of time because you're sort of already have a systemic.
Mised way of representing everything, you don't have to come up with
that stuff yourself.
So you don't have to go through the hacky phase of, like,
Doing things out because just like oh if I just actually do the 3D
math, everything gets placed properly and we're all good, right?
But, you know, you will quickly get into all those hacks in 3D as
well.
Because as soon as you know, yes it takes care of all your
spatialization for you.
But then transparency, doesn't work properly anymore and you can't do
lighting at all.
So, all your lighting stuff Nash to be crazy, hacked, weird stuff.
And now you've got a whole asset pipeline thing of.
How do you get like mesh data in and texturing and all these sorts of
things?
So there's
Tons of work apoplexy that does come in.
So I wouldn't necessarily say that 3D games.
Are ever going to be less complicated, but there are definitely parts
of the pipeline that just get a lot simpler in 3D, not because there's
something magically simpler about it.
But rather, because we've worked it out.
So, well at this point that you just don't have to do the work, right?
It's like, if I want to set up a 3D scene, I just know how to do it
now because we've had so much experience doing that and we've got it
down to a science, right?
Whereas 2D games is not quite that way.
There is no science of 2D games because since it's an approximation,
there isn't one uniform way that's just re can just teach.
That's like, oh, yeah.
And no matter what the 2-D game is, here's how you would architect the
spatialization of it.
You can't do that because it's always sort of a hack and which hack
you need to pick is going to be specific to the game.
And so that's really the problem with the to dienes of it is, is that,
but again, we'll be able to systematize this stuff as we push a little
bit harder on it.
We'll get it down to something.
Cleaner.
It won't be as ugly as it is now.
So the only reason the 3D kind of appears cleaner in that sense is
because we've already determined a set of stuff that works and you
don't have to guess what?
It's going to be.
So it's kind of clean from the start in that fundamental way.
What is the difference between handmade hero and 1935?
There.
Different in pretty much every way you could imagine.
I don't know if they're completely different, I guess, I would say
So just now the fix only applied to the particles because the borders
are still moving.
Yes, that's correct.
The borders are using that transform and that transform doesn't do the
floor thing.
It's basically, because of that floor hack, we did where we want to
transform floors at different heights,
Neil in the code.
I think they mean, oh,
Well I guess I would say the handmade hero code sort of has to I guess
I would say to Maine.
Well, let's say three main deficiencies compared to say, the 1935
codebase.
So, number one is, I have to program handmade hero in a way.
That's one hour a night, and it makes it very difficult for me to keep
the code as clean as I would like it to be from my perspective.
Because one of the things that often will happen is I'll go through
these periods of reorganization and a lot of stuff that I can't do
very effectively in an hour because I kind of have to keep everything
in
Brain and and play around with how it's Lots out and stuff like that.
So things in 1935,
Tend to achieve much higher levels of quality because of the time I
can devote to it and the blocks of time, right?
So it's both the duration of coding at a time but also just handmade
Heroes never going to be a game.
I mean, the number of hours spent on the 1935 codebase is so far
above, however, how many will ever be able to spend on handmade here?
All right.
There's really nothing you can do about that.
So, you know, it's necessarily less.
Refined, because there is no way to achieve that level of refinement
with the constraints of handmade hero.
So that's just how that is right.
Number two, is that I can't be too advanced on handmade hero, right?
Like I have to keep things in a relatively comfortable Zone both in
terms of people's ability to
Understand what I'm doing and why I'm doing it on stream and also my
ability to code it while talking, right?
And so the very most sophisticated stuff is just not going to be
happening on handmade hero because it's not like possible to do that
and then third is there's no tooling or or environment stuff on
handmade Heroes.
So I don't for example, have a meta programming.
Lair.
I don't have like a virtualized platform layer and stuff like this.
So certain things I have on 935 that I've written that we're sort of
separate projects that reinforce and are used to develop the main
project.
Those do not exist on handmade Heroes.
So the code cannot
Advantage of any of that.
Whereas, a 1935, it can.
So I say that there's probably like, you know,
those those three main differences in terms of the code, make it so
that there's, there's quite a bit of difference between the two code
bases.
My approach to the programming though is pretty much always the same.
Like, I approached the codon handmade here.
The same way I approach a 9:35, the only difference is I'm able to do
a better job on 1935, then I am on handmade hero.
So the quality of the code differ is fairly drastically, perhaps but
the approach doesn't.
And so you just have to imagine kind of okay, you've see how much
G.
Imagine if I had, you know, ten 10x the hours.
Where would this code have been in this time period?
Right.
You know, going over the same code and you know hopefully you can
imagine that it would be much much better because there would just be
all of this additional engineering that could go into it and it, you
know, it would get proportionally better.
Are we able to change the projection in this game?
Yes.
To a certain extent.
I mean it's a 2d game that the art assets are 2D so you can only
change like the way they're scaled really.
You can't rotate them in the third dimension because there isn't any
like data there to see.
In a painter.
Entities is the movement mode angle attack, slipcase missing a break
or is the fall through intentional falters intentional, if I remember
correctly,
How far would you say, you are developing this game?
How many episodes can we still expect?
I was ballparking 600 so we're like halfway there, but I mean, I don't
know.
That was just a very random ballpark.
I'd say it's not too out of the question because, you know, we're sort
of getting the point where the engines pretty good.
There's still some pretty rough parts to it.
So we're cut.
We're kind of trying to work those out now but you know, I would say
maybe you
Silver off.
700 800 episodes.
If we're off by a bit, but I don't know.
It depends on how much gameplay we put in.
Certainly, it's a little bit scalable because we don't have, you know,
I had goals of wine to cover like all the basic game engine stuff
showing some of that in all the cases.
And so you know, I that I want to have in there but it terms of what
we put in for gameplay, I don't care as much because you know,
gameplay is more of a game design thing.
And it doesn't.
You know, it that that's not what this stream was about.
So I don't really care what we do as long as the
I've shown enough gameplay programming so that everyone understands
what, how it, how that sort of code works and how to architect it, or
how to like play around with architectures for it?
That's really the only part that I care about there.
Do you find it difficult to connect?
Such a few 935 and handmade hero.
And if so has it gotten easier with time?
so, I would say like,
I do, I do find that I wish I could control more when I switch in when
I don't, there's sometimes on 1935 that I would have liked to just
been thinking about it for several days at a time, and not have had to
code, do a, handmade hero.
So there will probably be a time at some point.
I don't know when where I'll probably take handmade hero off the air
for three or four months when we are
Finally 1935, because I, you know, handmade hero as nice as it is,
doesn't pay the bills, right?
So I have to make sure 1935 ships, and ships.
Well, so, at some point, I'll probably have to put him a hero on delay
for little bit and then when I come back from that, you know, will
finish handmade hero up, I made even do an accelerated schedule at
that point, because I'm a like, then switch to handmade hero full-time
for a while maybe do like a couple episodes.
It was a day or something like that.
To finish it up.
I don't know.
But basically like it definitely is the case that being able to
concentrate on a single code base for a while is better and certainly
in the future, I wouldn't do another handmade hero.
Probably.
I really want to do it and so I'm glad I did, but it definitely is
taxing in terms of the mental shift and it's not like, it's not
Not possible to program to Cabeza once, but you do take a little bit
of a hit and I don't really want to always take a little bit of a hit,
you know?
I would rather
You know, I would rather concentrate on one or the other and
furthermore, you know, if I did do it where I like switch to the
program, handmade hero more full-time me for a little while.
That would also allow me to maybe make a little bit better codon
stream because I could do back to back a few episodes, doing something
that would take longer than an hour.
And they would kind of my mental state would be the same throughout
them.
So I could kind of, like, make sure that I kept everything in my brain
properly.
Early and didn't forget anything.
All right, I have a lot of work to do so I am going to go back.
An end, the stream.
All right.
Thank you, everyone for joining me for this episode of handmade here.
It's a pleasure coding with you.
As always, if you would like to follow along at home, you can always
pre-order the game on handmade hero dot-org.
We have a handy and appeared above that.
We also form site.
You can go too fast, questions.
A patreon page, can go to sports video series, a schedule bot.
You can use to know when we're going to be live and an episode guide,
if you would like to catch up on old,
Stuff that's about it for today.
I'll be back here tomorrow.
Same time.
Same place last year of the week, is a Friday.
It is for the last few of the week.
And until then have fun program, everyone, and I'll see you on the
internet.
Take it easy, everybody.